<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074754eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
DECEMBER 1981 - 4.50 French francs
Caribbean encounter
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
©
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^^
Haiti
Seat of honour
Carved in the form of a fearsome beast from the trunk of a guaiac tree, this duho, or
ceremonial chair, is a fine example of the wood-carving skills of the Taino Indians, one of
the indigenous peoples who inhabited the Caribbean before the arrival of the Europeans.
When Christopher Columbus landed in Santo Domingo in 1492, the Indians who greeted
him invited him to sit on a duho, an honour reserved for people of high rank. This rare
specimen, now in the Musée de l'Homme, Paris, is thought to be one of the many duho
that Columbus brought back with him to Europe.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
DECEMBRER 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox). .
, Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head. Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Sai'd (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille - Edition: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 CARIBBEAN ENCOUNTER
A journey through the history, peoples and places of the Antilles
by Alejo Carpentier
10 SLAVERY AND SUGAR...
THE BITTER AFTERTASTE
by Manuel Moreno Fraginals
14 TOUSSAINT LOUVERTURE
HAITI'S TRAGIC HERO
by René Depestre
14 THE PROPHETIC VISION OF SIMON BOLIVAR
by Manuel Maldonado-Denis
16 CRUCIBLE OF CHANGE
by René Depestre
29 'OURS'
The West Indies from within
by Marion Patrick Jones
31 «CALENDRIER LAGUNAIRE»
by Aimé Césaire
31 FERNANDO ORTIZ
'The father of Caribbean studies'
by Lisandro Otero
32 CREATIVE CONTRADICTIONS
The Caribbean genius has given birth to a new civilization
by Edouard Glissant
38 CALIBAN'S REVENGE
by Roberto Fernandez Retamar
40 UNESCO AND THE CARIBBEAN
41 JOSE MARTI :
'Citizen of the Americas'
42 MARCUS GARVEY AND THE AFRICAN DREAM
by Kenneth Ramchand
43 REGGAE: A JAMAICAN MUSICAL PHENOMENON
by Sebastian Clarke
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
HAÏTI : Seat of honour
Cover
The arrival of Christopher Columbus and the
Spaniards in 1492 marked the start of an
intermingling of cultures in the Caribbean
which continued amid the tragic events of
colonialism and the slave trade. Out of this
process involving Europeans, Indians, and
above all black African peoples came a
unique historical amalgam, rich in diversity
yet united by certain underlying patterns of
living and thinking. The cultural fusion of the
Caribbean, one of the most original and fruit¬
ful episodes in history. Is the theme of this
issue of the Unesco Courier. For reasons of
space the present number deals only with
the Caribbean archipelago, and not those
parts of the American continent which form
part of the history and geography of the
Caribbean. Cover shows Umbral (1949-1950),
a canvas by the Cuban painter Wifredo Lam.
Photo © Luc Joubert. Musée National d'Art Moderne, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Caribbean encounter
A journey through the history, peoples
and places of the Antilles
by Alejo Carpentier
Photo Goursat © Rapho, Paris
THE Caribbean has played a unique
and privileged role in the history of
the American continent. Here in the
Caribbean was the reality of the new
horizons, new forms of vegetation and new
lands first described by Christopher Colum¬
bus in his log-book. Indeed, it was through
that log-book and the letters Columbus
wrote to the Catholic Monarchs narrating
his successive voyages that the idea of
America was instilled in people's minds,
giving them, for the first time, a complete
picture of the world in which they lived.
They learnt that their planet was round and
they could set about exploring it in full
knowledge of where they were going. For
the first time in history they knew in what
world they were living.
So important and so far-reaching in its
consequences was this event that it could
be said to have been the most significant
historical event ever, forming a watershed in
the history of the world dividing humanity
into two categories: those who lived before
the discovery of America, and those who
came after.
America, then, had been discovered,
when suddenly, through a combination of
circumstances, these lands, and especially
those of the Caribbean, became the setting
of the first symbiosis, the first recorded
meeting between three races which, as
such, had never met before: the whites of
Europe, the hitherto unknown Indians of
America, and the Africans who, although
familiar to Europeans, were completely
unknown on the other side of the Atlantic. It
was a monumental symbiosis of extra¬
ordinary significance in its scope and the
potential cultural contributions it offered, a
symbiosis that was to give rise to a com¬
pletely original civilization.
Yet hardly had the discovery been made
and no sooner had the New World, as it
came to be called, begun to be known than
a negative factor emerged which was sub-
ALEJO CARPENTIER of Cuba, who died last
year, ranks among the most distinguished
novelists in the Spanish language. His books have
been translated into many languages and include,
in English editions, The Kingdom of this World
(1957), The Lost Steps (1957), published by
Knopf, New York, Explosion in a Cathedral
(Gollancz, London, 1963) and Reasons of State
(Partridge, London, 1976). A musicologist, he
also wrote A History of Cuban Music and many
articles and essays on Latin American literature
and music. The text published here has been
adapted from a talk broadcast on Cuban TV dur¬
ing the third Caribbean Festival of Arts
("Carifesta"), held in Cuba in 1979.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The curving arc of the Caribbean islands, as shown in a map published in Amsterdam in 1662.
THE CARIBBEAN ARCHIPELAGO POPULATION
ANTIGUA 74,000 JAMAICA
BAHAMAS 225,000 MARTINIQUE
BARBADOS 265,000 MONTSERRAT
BERMUDA 58,000 NETHERLANDS ANTILLES
BRITISH VIRGIN ISLANDS 12,000 PUERTO RICO
CAYMAN ISLANDS
CUBA
12,000
9,728,000
ST. KITTS-NEVIS
AND ANGUILLA
DOMINICA 81,000
ST. LUCIA
ST. VINCENT
AND GRENADINESDOMINICAN REP. 5,124,000
GRENADA 97,000 TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO
GUADELOUPE 330,000 TURKS AND CA/COS ISLANDS
HAITI 4,833,000 U.S. VIRGIN ISLANDS
POPULATION
2, 133,000
325,000
13,000
246,000
3,317,000
67,000
113,000
96,000
1, 133,000
6,000
104,000
sequently to be offset by a more positive
development.
To start with the negative factor. The idea
of colonialism was born with the discovery
of America. Before the Spanish came to
America, the Portuguese, those extraor¬
dinary navigators, had reached the limits of
Asia, had explored what they called the "the
spice islands" and, with some English and
French rivals, had voyaged on as far as India
and sailed down the coasts of Africa. But
they never thought of establishing colonies
in the strict sense of the term. They set up
trading posts, went in search of merchan¬
dise and offered merchandise in exchange.
They negotiated and bartered and, although
there may have been places where ten,
twelve or fifteen families settled, they were
the families of traders with no thought in
their heads of colonization.
The Spaniards, on the other hand, went
to America with colonization in mind. The
first great colonizer to land in America after
the discovery was the eldest son of Colum¬
bus, Diego, who arrived with his wife Maria
Toledo, the niece of the Duke of Alba. He
founded a small Renaissance-style court at
Santo Domingo where universities and
theatres were soon established and through
the streets of which once strolled Gonzalo
Fernandez de Oviedo, who was to become
the first chronicler of the West Indies.
The concept of colonization already seem¬
ed firmly established. But history has its sur¬
prises and people had not reckoned with an
unforeseen factor the African Slaves.
Transported from the continent of Africa,
the negroes, who arrived in America in fet¬
ters and chains, crammed into the bowels of
pest-ridden vessels, were to be sold like
merchandise and to be subjected to the
most degrading conditions to which it is
possible to reduce human beings. Yet with
them they brought the germ of the idea of
independence. With the passage of time it
was to be these pariahs, these outcasts of
the human race, who were to give us no less
a gift than the concept of independence.
Were we to have a map on which a small
red bulb lit up to indicate every uprising of
negro slaves on the American continent, we
should see that, from the sixteenth century i
onwards, a bulb has always been flickering I
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Panoramic view of the lies
des Saintes, above, is a
composite of three photos
taken one balmy day in
1899. "What marvels!"
Christopher Columbus had
exclaimed when he made
landfall in the Caribbean
four centuries before.
Sketch-map (right) was
drawn by the great
navigator in 1493. It shows
the north-western coast of
Esparíola ("the Spanish
island", now Haiti and the
Dominican Republic). The
north is indicated by a cross. y¿* *{f*ot*\ c«* * »
y somewhere. The first great uprising took
place in the sixteenth century in the mines of
Buria in Venezuela, led by the negro Miguel,
who succeeded in creating an independent
kingdom with a court and even a dissident
church with its own bishop.
Very shortly afterwards, the uprising of
the Cariada de los Negros occurred in Mex¬
ico and so frightened the colonial powers
that the Viceroy, Martin Enriquez, felt com¬
pelled to mete out such terrible punishments
as castration, with no consideration of mer¬
cy or justice, on any negro who fled into the
mountains. Shortly afterwards there was an
uprising in the stockade of Palmares, where
the runaway slaves of Brazil created an in¬
dependent kingdom that resisted the
numerous expeditions which the Por¬
tuguese colonists sent against it and main-
6
tained its independence for more than sixty
years.
In Surinam, at the end of the seventeenth
century, there was a rebellion led by three
black leaders: Sant Sam, Boston and Arabi,
who succeeded in holding out against four
Dutch expeditions sent to quell them. There
was the rebellion of the "tailors" in Bahia,
and that in Cuba led by Aponte. But special
mention must be made of the Oath of Bois
Caiman on account of its far-reaching
historical importance.
In a place known as Bois Caiman, or the
Forest of the Alligators, contingents of
slaves from the French colony of Saint
Domingue, now Haiti, met on a stormy
night and swore to proclaim the in¬
dependence of their country, an oath that
was to be fulfilled and made reality by the
great leader Toussaint Louverture (see
page 14). The true concept of independence
was born with the Oath of Bois Caiman. To
the concept of colonization which the
Spanish had brought to Hispaniola was op¬
posed, in the same country, the concept of
decolonization. This was the beginning of
the wars of independence and of the anti-
colonial wars that were to continue right up
to the present day.
When we study the celebrated mid-
eighteenth century Encyclopédie of
Voltaire, Diderot, Rousseau and
d'Alembert, men whose ideas had such an
influence on the leaders of our wars of in¬
dependence, we find that the concept of in¬
dependence in that great work was still
purely philosophical and was concerned
with the independence of man before God
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Cruel facts contradict any attempt
to portray the Antilles as an idyllic
paradise, for the history of the
Caribbean has been punctuated by
volcanic eruptions, earthquakes and
cyclones. One of the world's most
terrible natural disasters occurred
at two minutes past eight on the
morning of 8 May 1902, when
Martinique's highest volcanic
mountain. Mont Pelée, suddenly
erupted. In less than a minute the
town of Saint-Pierre and all its
population (some 28,000) had
perished in the holocaust (left).
Cyclones, which in Caribbean
mythology are hurricanes fed by
the wrath of Hu-Ra-Khan the wind-
god, have also brought great
suffering to the peoples of the
Antilles. Thirteen of them were
recorded in the 17th century, 33 in
the 18th, 28 in the 19th, and in this
century their number is higher still.
The havoc wreaked by some
particularly devastating cyclone has
left a gaping wound in the
collective memory of every
Caribbean island.
and the monarchy. It speaks of freedom of
the will and of man's individual freedom, but
it does not speak of political independence.
By contrast, what the Negroes of Haiti were
demanding and in that respect they were
the precursors of all our wars of inde¬
pendence political independence and
total emancipation.
Many people may object that the Oath of
Bois Caiman was only taken in 1791,
whereas the United States had achieved in¬
dependence years before. Nobody would
deny this. It should not be forgotten,
however, that when the thirteen North
American colonies were freed from the
tutelage of the King of England and became
an independent nation no longer subject to
the British throne, there was no change in
the pattern of life in those colonies. The land
owners were the same and the great
property-owners and merchants continued
to live as they had before. It did not occur to
anybody that the slaves might be eman¬
cipated. Before that stage was reached,
they had to wait for the American Civil War.
In other words, it was business as usual in
the United States after the Declaration of
Independence.
This was not the case in Latin America,
however, since, after the revolts in Haiti,
which were followed shortly afterwards by
the wars of independence, culminating in
the final victory at the battle of Ayacucho in
1824, the structure of the social order and
social life changed completely with the
emergence of the créole, a figure who
already existed but had not been considered
of any political account.
Who was the creóle? The word creóle first
appeared in old American documents from
the 1570's or thereabouts. Broadly speaking
the Creoles were people born on the new
continent of America, either of mixed
Spanish-Indian or Spanish-Negro blood, or
else were Indians or Negroes born in
America but living alongside the colonizers.
The creóles, however, felt that they were
overlooked and neglected. In his Letter from
Jamaica, one of the most important
documents we possess concerning the
history of America, Simón Bolívar the
Liberator spoke in these words of the status
of the Creoles, including the more affluent
among them, in the times prior to the wars
of independence which he was instrumental
in promoting: "We were never Viceroys or |
Governors save for very exceptional I
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
treasons; we were seldom archbishops or
bishops, and never diplomats; we were
soldiers but no more than subalterns; nobles
without any real privileges. Lastly, we were
neither judges nor bankers, and we were
almost never merchants".
The history of America as a whole
displays one very important feature, namely
that it only developed in terms of the class
struggle. We have had no dynastic wars
over succession to the throne, as in the case
of Europe; there have been no internecine
wars like the Hundred Years' War (which
was a feudal struggle); we have had no
religious wars in the strict sense of the term.
Our constant struggle over several centuries
was first of all between the conquistadors
and the subjugated and oppressed in¬
digenous class. This was followed by the
struggle of the colonizers against the con¬
quistadors.
The colonizers, who arrived later, set out
to create an oligarchy and impose their
authority, and succeeded in destroying the
conquistador class, almost all of whose
members ended up in poverty or destitution
or were murdered or dispossessed of their
The machete, or long Antillean cutlass, is a
familiar object both in the workaday world
and in the landscape of the Caribbean
imagination. It is widely used for cutting
sugar-cane, for clearing paths, for pruning in
the banana plantation (left) and for topping
freshly-picked coconuts. It has also served as
a weapon in liberation struggles and is
wielded symbolically in certain dances (below).
»
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
lands. Very few of them lived out their lives
to a happy end.
The colonizers, become the aristocracy or
oligarchy, then turned against the creóles.
Eventually, with the coming of the wars of
independence, the native inhabitants of
America rose up against the Spanish. But
the conquering creóles in their turn created
a new oligarchy against which the slaves,
the underprivileged and the growing middle
class had to fight. This class included almost
all the intelligentsia intellectuals, writers,
professors and teachers, in short, that ad¬
mirable middle class that was to continue
growing throughout the nineteenth century
right up to the start of the present century.
In this phase of the struggle, which was to
continue until the middle of this century,
and is still going on, the sense of nationhood
of the American countries had begun to af¬
firm itself. In other words, after prevailing all
over the continent, the creóles began to
seek their own special identity and, at a later
stage, with the growing independence
movements in the Antilles, there arose an
awareness of being Jamaican, Martiniquais
or Curaçaoan, in short of being nationals of
the separate islands forming the vast Carib¬
bean world and of having characteristics of
their own and being conscious of them.
When we contemplate the entire span of
the Caribbean, we stand amazed at the
gallery of great men it has offered us over
the centuries men who have forged our
history. They show that there exists what
might be termed a "Caribbean humanism".
Our great men never confined their action or
thinking, or the example they set, to their
own orbit but projected themselves on to
the neighbouring peoples. There was both
an exchange of people and an ¡nterpenetra-
, tion of ideas. There has always been
amongst us a strong urge for mutual
understanding in the context of our com¬
mon aspirations.
Admiral Brion, who was from Curaçao,
supported Bolivar in the independence
struggles of Venezuela, Colombia, Ecuador,
Peru and Bolivia. Petion, the President of
Haiti asked Bolivar to abolish slavery in
Venezuela in exchange for his moral and
material support in the war. Máximo
Gómez, who won independence for Cuba,
was a Dominican. The parents of the Maceo
brothers, who fought in the Cuban in¬
dependence struggles, had taken part in the
war of independence of Venezuela. And a
Cuban, Francisco Javier Yanes, signed
Venezuela's act of independence. The great
José Marti, the apostle of Cuba's in¬
dependence, whose eventful political and
historical career took place against the
backdrop of the entire Caribbean, bequeath¬
ed us many moving pages, imbued with a
sense of truth and profound love, on
Venezuela, Guatemala, Mexico, and the
countries of the Caribbean in general.
Through this exchange of people and
community of ideas, the mainland areas of
Mexico, Venezuela and Colombia, which
were peopled by African slaves in the same
colonizing process, as were Peru, Guayaquil
and Brazil, ultimately came to form part of
the Caribbean conglomeration which we are
now beginning to perceive and understand
in its entirety, as we compare what unites us
and what makes each of us unique, our
similarities and our differences, the birth¬
right of the individual and the common
heritage of us all.
B Alejo Carpentier
fitt
Perched almost a thousand metres above the Caribbean on a
rugged headland in northern Haiti, the citadel of Laferrière,
above, was built as a bastion to defend the newly independent
country against possible invasion by returning colonialist
forces. General Henri Christophe, one of the leaders of the
victorious national uprising, initiated the construction of the
imposing fortress in the early 19th century. Twenty thousand
men are said to have worked for nine years on the project,
depicted in naive painting below. This symbol of the liberation
of Haiti, already seriously damaged by an earthquake in 1842, is
today threatened by adverse climatic conditions, humidity and
encroaching tropical vegetation. At the request of the
Government of Haiti, the Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, launched an appeal on 10 March 1980
for the safeguard of the cultural heritage of Haiti, calling on the
international community to express "the brotherhood of men
through the dialogue of their cultures".
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Slavery and sugar.,
the bitter aftertaste
by Manuel Moreno Fraginals
10
IS there such a thing as a Caribbean iden¬
tity? The question has often been raised,
and the fact that it continues to be asked
demonstrates either that there is no
awareness or certainty about this identity or
that there are forces that stand to gain by
denying its existence. In our view, "cultural
identity" is the historic result of the common
evolution of common socio-economic
factors.
The wide arc of the Antilles forms an
island ecosystem with common climatic and
geological characteristics and, in early
times, with similar flora and fauna. From the
moment when the Europeans burst on to
the South American scene, the islands'
geographical location made them the natural
meeting-place of seaways to the Spanish
Empire and, in a sense, the "imperial fron¬
tier". As a frontier, the Antilles were to be
the site of the battles of the plundering col¬
onial wars. Thus, there was an early stage at
which these islands had to play a part in the
Empire. But they also had exploitable
resources, which, in addition to the role they
played in support of the empire, were impor¬
tant for their own economic potential. Dur¬
ing the eighteenth century, Cuba, for exam¬
ple, was the centre of defence of the
Spanish Empire and an outstanding pro¬
ducer of tobacco and sugar; Jamaica was an
island of sugar plantations and a key base
for the English navy.
The islands' shared climate, their
geographical situation in the arc of the An¬
tilles and their similar physical characteristics
made possible, in most of them, the
development of the slave sugar plantation
system. For this type of plantation required
terrain with specific physical features; it had
to be near the sea, have a particular
temperature and degree of rainfall, have
forest resources available, be near cattle
supplies, and have excellent maritime com¬
munications between the buyer's market
(Europe) and the labour supply market
(Africa).
MANUEL MORENO FRAGINALS, Cuban
historian and university teacher, is adviser to the
Centre of Caribbean Studies of the Casa de las
Americas, in Havana. His most recent published
work is Distintegration/Abolition of Slavery in the
Caribbean.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The islands of the Antilles were peopled
by a common indigenous stock which was
eliminated through a common historical pro¬
cess. The aboriginal cultures of the Carib¬
bean appear to go back as far as 2500 BC.
The colonizing process which befell these
peoples sparked off systernatic annihilation
in which the barbarous exploitation to which
they were subjected was accompanied by
epidemics, the breakdown of their
economy, the psychological shock of the
conquest and even premeditated extermina¬
tion. The extinction of the Indians in the
islands colonized by Spain was widely
publicized by the English, the French and
the Dutch; but what was not made common
knowledge was how the English, French
and Dutch themselves systematically exter¬
minated the indigenous populations of the
islands they conquered.
On these systematically depopulated
islands, a common economic structure was
established: the slave plantation, a typical
creation of European capitalism. Rather
than being the invention of any particular
European colonizing power, it was the result
of accumulated colonial experience. The
plantation system of the type adopted by
the Portuguese at Sao Tomé was transfer¬
red to America by the Spaniards. The
Hispano-Portuguese model was developed
by the English and French (Jamaica and
Santo Domingo are tragic examples of this
development), and was later taken up again
by Spanish colonialism, making the ex¬
ploitation in Cuba even more complex.
This point is emphasized because
historians tend to speak of different
categories of "slavery" according to
whether it was imposed by the English,
French, Portuguese, Spaniards or others.
There is only one type of slavery and its sole
aim is the exploitation of labour; the ex¬
ploiter's nationality is of little importance.
We reject the idea that there are different
types of slavery depending on the religion of
the exploiter as well as the notion that there
are "benign" and "malignant" forms of
slavery. For the enslaved mass, slavery was
always the same; the differences in the
degree of exploitation were due to economic
factors rather than to superstructure.
Nor do we accept any type of racial con¬
notation that might suggest a preference on
the part of the slave-masters for Africans.
Africans were enslaved because Africa was
the labour market that was available, cheap
and near; when conditions changed in the
nineteenth century Chinese and East Indians
were brought in.
The same system of enslavement and
commercialization was attempted with the
West Indian indigenous populations. As ear¬
ly as 1494, Admiral Christopher Columbus
himself selected fifty native inhabitants of
Hispaniola (Santo Domingo), who were sent
to Spain to be sold as slaves. And, accor¬
ding to Bartolomé de Las Casas, Columbus
reckoned that by selling all the Indians of
that island along with other merchandise he
would realize profits to the tune of forty
million maravedíes. As early as 1508 hunts
for natives to be sold into slavery were
legalized in the Caribbean. And if the
statistics provided by Pedro Mártir de
Anglería are correct, between 1508 and 1513
some forty thousand Caribbean slaves were
hunted down and sold to work in the gold
mines. Colonial barbarism resulted in the li¬
quidation of the indigenous population; the t
small aggressive groups which remained )
Few traces have survived of the
indigenous peoples, notably the
Carib and the Arawak, which
inhabited the Caribbean islands
before they were discovered by the
Spaniards. Within a few decades of
European colonial rule these
peoples had been virtually
annihilated, and today only a
handful of their descendants exist,
scattered throughout the region. A
few small but skilfully crafted
examples of their culture have been
preserved. Above, skeletal head
carved in black basalt (22 cm high)
was a religious or ceremonial object
used by an Arawak-speaking people
of the Taino culture of Puerto Rico.
Below, anthropomorphic stone
head (12 cm high, 17 cm long) from
the Dominican Republic. It is one of
the prized "three-pointed stones"
discovered in the Antilles which
may have been an animist symbol
of the Taino civilization.
Photo © Museo del Hombre Dominicano, Santo Domingo
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
From the 15th century on, various European powers used the island
of Gorée, less than 4 kilometres off Dakar (Senegal) as a port of
call or an entrepôt for the Atlantic slave trade. It was there,
packed in dank cellars or the torture chambers set aside for those
who resisted, that young Africans waited to be shipped to the
plantations and manufactories of the New World, especially those
of the West Indies. One of the great tragedies of history, the slave
trade played a crucial part in shaping the cultural and political
destiny of many parts of the Americas. In December 1980, in
recognition of the cultural and historical importance of the island's
architectural heritage, the Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, launched an international appeal for the
safeguard and restoration of Gorée. Above, map of the island as
shown on an engraving of 1779.
^were a hindrance to production and they
were exterminated in a systematic genocide
whose most typical expression was that
indulged in by the English and by the French
in Martinique.
From the sixteenth century onwards plan¬
tation complexes began to be established in
the Spanish Caribbean islands: Santo Dom¬
ingo, Puerto Rico and Cuba. In the seven¬
teenth century the system spread to the
Lesser Antilles, and later to Jamaica. The
plantation economy began to be dominant
in the islands. The Lesser Antilles were
covered with plantations and there was no
land left for other forms of economic
development, or even for the slaves to
escape to from the plantations. In the
Greater Antilles plantation areas alternated
with other exploitations and the possibilities
of social development were greater. These
differences of scale resulted in differences in
the socio-economic levels of the planta¬
tions, but otherwise most of the common
characteristics remained.
Each plantation, when it was established,
was simply a collection of human beings and
in no sense constituted a society. At this in¬
itial stage the plantation could be compared
to a prison nearly all of whose members
were of African origin, although they came
from different ethnic groups, and were bet¬
ween 18 and 30 years old. There was a
marked imbalance in the sexes; women only
formed between 10 and 30 per cent of the
population and it was not rare to find planta¬
tions comprising men alone.
Under this repressive system, working
time was strictly regulated and leisure time
was eliminated; diet was determined accor¬
ding to the economic considerations of the
masters; housing was planned for economy
and security, and clothing followed mass in¬
dustrial production patterns; sexual life was
subject to reproductive requirements; family
relations were paralyzed by the imbalance
between the sexes.
This set-up, typical of virtually all the plan¬
tations at the time of their foundation,
changed with the passage of time.
Clandestine hierarchical relationships were
established among the slaves, bonds of in¬
terests and brotherhood were created, and
the birth of children led to the formation of
family nuclei, generally of a matriarchal
type, since within the repressive system of
the plantation a father could not take
responsibility for his offspring. There was a
process of social integration, but it was
hindered by the decline of the group since
the mortality rate was higher than the birth
rate (a logical result of the imbalance bet¬
ween the sexes, and the prison regime) and
new influxes of slaves became necessary to
maintain the level of the work force. Never¬
theless, a process of socialization was oc¬
curring as a result of one unifying factor all
were slaves and free men were excluded.
The plantation required an import-export
centre which, moreover, provided a whole
series of services that formed the infrastruc¬
ture of the business. Thus there developed a
kind of urban centre, in which both slaves
and free men were to be found, but without
the prison ethos of the plantation and con¬
sequently with different social relationships.
Thus, the city-country distinction which is
typical of all societies assumed a more
definite connotation in plantation societies.
Furthermore, under pressure from external
factors (price of slaves, price of plantation
products, etc.) and internal factors
(economic viability of the enterprise, ap¬
plication of technological advances, im¬
poverishment of the land, etc.), the planta¬
tions gradually developed until they ac¬
quired specific social characteristics that
were common to all the islands.
Regardless of the social level they had
achieved, the plantation slaves of the Carib¬
bean were subjected to a common process
of deculturation. By deculturation is meant
the conscious process whereby, for pur¬
poses of economic exploitation, the culture
of a human group was uprooted so as to
facilitate the expropriation of the natural
wealth of the territory in which it was
located and/or to use the group for cheap
unskilled slave or semi-slave labour. In
American plantation societies deculturation
can be seen as a technological expedient for
obtaining maximum labour efficiency.
Deculturation was a conscious process
used on slaves in order to deprive them of all
identity. Their very names were wrested
from them. Out of thousands and thousands
of documents about slaves in the Caribbean
we only found twenty in which the original
African names of the slaves appeared. Their
eating, living and dress patterns were
destroyed, their music and their religion
were banned, and their masters' language
was imposed upon them. The slaves could
only resist this process of deculturation by
maintaining their original cultural values in
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
clandestinity. Thus began a struggle bet¬
ween the dominant culture which strove to
be a factor of integration and subjugation,
and the dominated culture as an integrating
factor of resistance. This dialectical conflict
was to be one of the basic sources of Carib¬
bean culture.
This process cannot be understood,
however, if we start from the classic tradi¬
tional anthropological schema which con¬
siders that in such cases a process of
"transculturation" or "integration" occurred
whereby African cultural values were in¬
serted into European moulds. The reality of
the Caribbean islands was quite different.
From the beginning it was a question of new
societies to which Africans and Europeans
came at the same time, the former as a sub¬
jugated people in a war of capitalist plunder,
and the latter as the exploiting group. There
was no pre-existing society imbued with
African contributions. There was basically a
system of economic exploitation in which
the dominant class created a culture for
itself which was also destined to be imposed
on the dominated class.
Naturally, this culture was based on
Eurocentric values and patterns which were
reworked, re-created and updated in relation
to the economic, political and social situa¬
tion on the plantations. Confronting the
dominant culture was a culture of resistance
which stemmed originally from African
values and patterns that disappeared, were
re-elaborated or transmuted into the class
struggle process, when they came up
against both imposed deculturation and a
repressive system.
And thus, at a given moment, the slave
plantation system disintegrated. The pro¬
cess of disintegration occurred at different
times and with different characteristics in
the various islands. In some the plantations
disappeared, in others they were transform¬
ed into modern plantations where the traffic
in human beings continued. There were far-
reaching migratory movements between the
West Indian islands and new peoples were
brought out to work in the canefields. To
change the origin of the people exploited is
not, however, to change the essential
nature of the exploitation.
For these historic reasons, the descen¬
dants of the former slaves, mainly Negroes
and mulattoes, constituted the poorest,
most unprotected and exploitable stratum of
society. Culturally, they were profoundly af¬
fected by different forms of prejudice and
social discrimination. They were deliberately
isolated and excluded, and attempts were
made to stir up conflicts among them which
would make it difficult for them to constitute
themselves into a cohesive class. The
cultural forms contributed, created and re¬
created by these groups were closely linked
to the situation of social exclusion,
economic exploitation and cultural rejection
imposed upon them by the dominant class.
Seen from this angle, the essence of a
study on cultural identity ought to lie in the
analysis of the forms in which this culture of
resistance endured or was used or re¬
created. Studies that analyse the symp¬
tomatic characteristics of this culture, but
not its real structures, speak of "dual"
societies or "plural" societies. These
theories are supported by extremely in¬
teresting observations from outside, but
they overlook the fact that cultural dif¬
ferences are not merely the opposition oik
Photo Bibliothèque Nationale © Société de Géographie, Paris
The basis of Caribbean colonial society was the plantation, a closed world in which
confrontation between white master and black slave shaped many aspects of the
region's culture. This divided world revolved around two poles. In close physical
proximity but alien in spirit: the "great house" of the master and the cabins of the
slaves. The master lived in his mansion with his family and household slaves. The huts
of the slaves formed a world apart ¡n which the black labourers lived in conditions
which were often inhuman. Photo above was taken in Martinique in 1882. Below, a
group of huts in a Curaçao plantation.
Photo © Luc Joubert, Paris. Nelly and René Depestre Collection 	
1
J t
UN
«U.ll vlffB " >j^
W KjL
Ll j±AÍ
pi W".
<r^nnr .nw"-'i	 ^1
Sugar, slavery and single-
crop agriculture are the
leitmotif of Caribbean
history. But if sugar headed
the list of crops it was
closely followed by tobacco
and some Caribbean
countries, notably Cuba,
have won a world-wide
reputation as tobacco-
producers. The manufacture
of the famous Havana cigars
requires a high degree of
craftsmanship, while artistry
and imagination are also
lavished on their packaging
and presentation. Left,
a striking design for
a cigar-box label.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
. European and African values whose cultures
interact in the abstract; on the contrary they
relate to very real class confrontations.
Other more idealist studies tend to seek
African graftings on a European stem. And
there are those who have dedicated
themselves to listing Africanisms in order to
determine how many of them, and with
what degree of success, have penetrated in¬
to pre-established moulds. Then again there
are those who, with a certain an¬
thropological complexity, have elaborated
the theory of social exclusion. But, as it has
been rightly pointed out, "although many of
these people have been barred from access
to total participation in society, or even the
most minor benefits of citizenship, they
have never been excluded from contributing
to the economic order". Indeed, their
marginality as citizens is a result of the
capitalist regime.
The role of the Afro-Latin-American
peoples of the Caribbean as suppliers of
notoriously cheap labour, and especially the
movement of Haitians, Jamaicans,
Dominicans, Puerto Ricans and others to
the United States and to the capitals of
Europe, has reduced the average total cost
of labour at the less skilled levels.
Marginalization has not meant taking away
from these men their status as exploited
people or creators of wealth.
Just as negative is the quest for identity
based on colour ("Négritude") or remote
African cultural roots, even though it
originated within the exploited peoples
themselves. These theories forget or
overlook the fact that exploitation of slave or
semi-slave labour was not a problem of col¬
our, since whites and Indians and later
Chinese, East Indians and Polynesians were
also exploited and enslaved. "Négritude",
which was early in its history a powerful and
beautiful rebel cry of a group standing out
against prejudice, has run the risk of being
transformed into an ideology. The return to
Africa, the recognition of roots, bring
something of undeniable value to the Carib¬
bean peoples the identification of one of
its sources and a sense of solidarity towards
peoples who for centuries have been ex¬
ploited and impoverished. But beyond these
limits it loses its validity, for Caribbean
culture is not African but a culture created
and re-created, under specific conditions, in
the crucible of the Caribbean.
Colonial or neo-colonial interests have
tried to perpetuate the sense of Caribbean
cultural diversity. To the real barrier of dif¬
ferent languages has been added the
isolating or distorting claim that each island
feels and acts as an independent cultural,
and hence political, world. In some cases,
the effort has even been made to persuade
certain islands to seek their identity in the
metropolis or in foreign lands, and hot in
themselves. The real identity of the Carib¬
bean is questioned and even denied. But the
history and the reality expressed in their ar¬
tistic manifestations show quite the op¬
posite. Caribbean artists and social scien¬
tists today have a much more important task
than a simplistic quest for African elements
in their culture or comparative analysis with
present-day African cultures. This task is the
study of specific phenomena of integration
and of common symbolic forms that have
developed in the Caribbean during the pro¬
cess of consolidation of the new societies
born there.
B Manual Moreno Fraginals
14
Toussaint Louverture
Haiti's tragic hero
Toussaint Louverture (1743-1803)
The prophetic vision
of Simón Bolívar
Simón Bolívar (1783-1830)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
BROTHERS and friends, I am Toussaint
Louverture; my name is perhaps
already known to you. I am intent on
vengeance. I want liberty and equality to be
respected in Santo Domingo, and I shall
work until this goal is achieved. Join us,
brothers, and fight alongside us for the same
cause.
The man who, in 1793, at the age of fifty,
was addressing himself in these terms to his
unfortunate companions, had reached a
point in his life when he felt ready to give
himself completely to a task which
transcended that of his own destiny.
Toussaint Breda was born on 20 May 1743
in the residence of the same name, at the
place called Haut-du-Cap. He was a descen¬
dant of Gaou-Guinou, an African prince of
the Aradas group. His godfather Pierre Bap¬
tiste taught him how to read and write. The
French he learnt opened the way to such
works as the Commentaries of Julius
Caesar, the Reveries of Marshal Saxe, the
History of the Wars by Herodotus and above
all the famous Histoire Philosophique des
Indes by the Abbé Raynal. The latter work
represented an exceptional "opening"
(ouverture) for his imaginative genius and for
the name under which the slave of Breda
was to distinguish himself.
In addition, his familiarity with his
country's medicinal plants, and the
rudiments of veterinary science, which he
had acquired while working in the stables of
his master Bayon Libertat, enabled him to
exercise unquestionable influence over the
Maroon negroes of the mountains once he
had joined them. His small stature, taciturn
and fragile air, and ugly features cloaked a
great strength of character, combined with
outstanding powers of physical and mental
endurance which brought him phenomenal
success when directing the operations
which took place in Santo Domingo (Haiti)
from 1791 to 1803.
The principal historical claim to fame of
Toussaint Louverture is that he transformed
groups of Maroon negroes into a seasoned
and disciplined army of liberation. His con¬
summate skill in guerilla tactics, plus a
shrewd appreciation of when to com¬
promise, enabled him to exploit to the max¬
imum the colonial rivalries between the dif¬
ferent empires represented oh the political
and military stage of the Caribbean.
The closing years of the 18th century
brought eventful times to the colony of San¬
to Domingo where Toussaint Louverture had
set in motion the irreversible process of
emancipation. Toussaint was aware that the
new power directing France since the coup
d'état of the 18th Brumaire would put in
question the fragile conquests of the Haitian
Revolution. His fears were justified, for
Bonaparte lost no time in introducing a
decree which made it obligatory to place on
all the flags of Santo Domingo the following
inscription: "Gallant black people,
remember that the French people and only
the French people recognize your liberty and
the equality of your rights". Toussaint
Louverture reacted sharply to this measure:
"It is not", he said, "a circumstantial liberty
conceded to us alone that we wish, but the
unequivocal adoption of the principle that no
man, whether he be born red, black or white,
can become the property of his fellow-men."
"When Toussaint Louverture appeared on
the scene", Aimé Césaire has written, "it
was to take the declaration of the rights of
man literally, to demonstrate that a pariah
race does not exist, that there are no
marginal countries, and no people meriting
exceptional status. It was to embody and
particularize a principle."
Such a universal extension of the law was
quite unthinkable for Napoleon Bonaparte
who dispatched an expedition to Santo
Domingo under his brother-in-law General
Leclerc in order to re-establish slavery. Dur¬
ing the night of the 7th and 8th of June 1802
Toussaint Louverture fell into a trap set for
him by General Brunet. Conducted on board
the vessel Le Héros, he was taken to France
and captivity in the Fort de Joux in the Jura
mountains where, on 7 April 1803, he died of
hunger, cold and nostalgia. At the moment
of his capture he made the following declara¬
tion : "My overthrow means only that the
trunk of the tree of Black liberty has been cut
down. But that tree will grow upward once
more from its myriad and profound roots."
A few months after these prophetic
words, on 28 November 1803, Toussaint
Louverture's right hand man. General Jean-
Jacquès Dessalines, proclaimed the in¬
dependence of Haiti at Fort Dauphin. Such
was the combat of Toussaint Louverture, "a
combat for the transformation of formal law
into real law, a combat for the recognition of
man, and a combat, in short, which explains
why the revolt of the black slaves of Santo
Domingo found, and continues to find, a just
place in the history of universal civilization".
H René Depestre
by Manuel Maldonado-Denis
SIMON Bolivar, the "Liberator", always be¬
lieved that the freedom of the peoples of
America would never be fully achieved if
it did not include Cuba and Puerto Rico in its
liberating embrace. Without the liberation of
Cuba and Puerto Rico, those last "two jewels
of the Spanish crown", efforts to rid the conti¬
nent of the colonialist scourge would remain
incomplete, in addition to which the in¬
dependence of the Latin American peoples
would be everlastingly threatened by what
Marti, years later, was to describe as the tiger
perpetually stalking the peoples of what, with
his acute historical vision, he called "Our
America".
Bolivar was by no means unaware of the
hopes and aspirations of the peoples of the
Caribbean. On the contrary, his wide-ranging
revolutionary action was largely shaped by his
Caribbean experience. For example, we know
of his exile in Jamaica and of his celebrated
"Letter from Jamaica" of 1815, in which he
outlined his historical plan for the continent
and included Cuba and Puerto Rico in his il¬
lustrious scheme of things. We also know of
his representations to the Haitian revolutionary
Petion and of his pledge to free the black slaves
on Venezuelan soil. The Liberator was utterly
committed to seeing the whole of Latin
America freed from Spanish colonialism.
In this context, the famous "Letter from
Jamaica", which he wrote in Kingston on
6 September 1815, should be highlighted. In it,
he wrote: "The islands of Cuba and Puerto Rico
whose populations, taken together, must
amount to some seven to eight hundred thou¬
sand people, are the most peaceful posses¬
sions of the Spanish because they are out of
touch with the independent nations. But surely
those islanders are American too? Are they
not humiliated? Do they not seek well-
being?" In fact, what Bolivar was doing here
was to call for the liberation of Cuba and
Puerto Rico since their inhabitants were peo¬
ple belonging to the concert of Latin
American nations, and at that early stage in
the liberation struggle, when it was difficult
even to start to see the triumph of the in¬
surrectionist forces, Bolivar's vision was
inspired.
Reliable historical evidence exists to show
that Bolivar never abandoned his commit¬
ment to seeing Cuba and Puerto Rico
become free and sovereign nations. The
Liberator even visualized the setting-up of a
military expedition to liberate the two
islands, but the domestic and international
situation prevented him from carrying out
his plan.
It should not be forgotten that at the time
Bolivar's revolution was in its infancy, pro¬
duction throughout the Caribbean was bas¬
ed on the enslavement of the negroes. The
only exception was that of the Republic of
Haiti, whose glorious epic of emancipation
from slavery culminated in the achievement
of independence. A significant consequence
of this was that, as one of the conditions
agreed with Haitian president Petion, in
return for Haitian support for the Latin
American independence struggle Simón
Bolívar undertook to free all negro slaves in
the liberated continental territories.
Bolivar also conceived the idea of the
Great Congress which was to take place in
Panama in 1826. The aim of this Congress
was to unite all the Latin American peoples
in a great federation of free and sovereign
peoples. But the United States was opposed
to the independence of Cuba and Puerto
Rico and accordingly frustrated Bolivar's
historic plan.'
Bolivar was a Venezuelan aristocrat who
was prepared to abandon all he possessed in
the cause of the freedom of what he called
"Southern America", a Southern America
that had ethnic and cultural features of its
own which distinguished it from the other
America, that of the North. The Liberator ex¬
tended his internationalist and Latin
Americanist view of things over the Carib¬
bean, a racial and cultural kaleidoscope on
which all the great empires of the period had
converged. The liberation of Cuba and Puer¬
to Rico was part of Bolivar's grand design,
but forces that were too strong even for his
extraordinary capacity for revolutionary ac¬
tion prevented him from seeing this part of
his vision fulfilled.
As the enemy of slavery and servitude,
Bolivar laid the groundwork for the eradica¬
tion of slave labour and slavery on the conti¬
nent. The great revolutionary example he set
paved the way for the future both of the
countries which he had liberated and of
those that were still fighting for their
freedom.
The history of the Caribbean would not be
the same without the thought and action of
Simón Bolívar. But, even today, there are
Caribbean peoples which have not yet suc¬
ceeded in transforming Bolivar's ideals into
reality. This is why, two hundred years later,
Bolivar's ideology is still relevant. Marti was
not mistaken when he said that "there is still
work for Bolivar in America".
MANUEL MALDONADO-DENIS, Puerto Rican
essayist, is professor of political science at the
social sciences faculty of the University of Puerto
Rico. He is the author of many essays about his
country, notably Puerto Rico, Mito y Realidad
(Puerto Rico, Myth and Reality).
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
w
Photo Charles Harbutt © Parimage, Paris
Crucible of change
by René Depestre
THE map of the Caribbean is the stuff
that dreams are made of. At this
cross-roads of the planet, history has
given rise to especially complex centres of
civilization, with the baroque, the picar¬
esque, the magical, the epic and the
marvellous intermingling and criss-crossing
one another with equal exuberance at the
political, social, religious and cultural levels.
Their five centuries of existence afford suffi¬
cient perspective for us to be fully aware of
and to identify, within the West Indian ar¬
chipelago, a family of peoples and cultures
formed in the mould of history. These
RENÉ DEPESTRE, Haitian author, has published
several volumes of poems, essays and fiction in¬
cluding Un Arc-en-ciel pour l'Occident Chrétien
(published in English as A Rainbow for the Chris¬
tian West, University of Massachusetts Press,
1977) and Poète à Cuba, (Poet in Cuba). He has
collaborated on two collective works produced by
Unesco, Africa en América Latina ("Africa in
Latin America") and América Latina en sus Ideas
("Latin America through its Ideas"), and is cur¬
rently a member of the Unesco secretariat.
peoples and cultures were moulded, on the
one hand, by the diversity and concordance
of the material and spiritual conditions of life
under colonization and, on the other, by the
ardently pursued fight for freedom and
liberation from those conditions.
For a long time our islands, the frontiers
of five distinct empires, were defined, not in
terms of their own intrinsic realities, but in
relation to Europe, Africa and the other
Americas. Today, however, it is possible to
study, interpret and understand from within
the internal system of values proper to our
societies. The Caribbean is intensely present
on the world scene in all its problematic
singularity, its music, its arts and letters, its
identity crises, and its dynamic thrust
towards change.
Prior to their encounter in the western
hemisphere, those peoples involved in the
colonizing experience knew nothing of one
another. This ignorance of their spiritual and
physical characteristics facilitated the pro¬
cess of ontological misrepresentation which
typifies the course of their history. The
natives of the islands knew nothing of the
Europeans or the Africans; conscious of be¬
ing Arawaks, Siboneys, Tainos, Caribs,
their surprise was, therefore, all the greater
when they heard themselves suddenly refer¬
red to generically as Indians!
It was not too long before a similar
semantic anomaly affected the self-image of
the Yorubas, Bambaras, Ibos, Mandingos
from Africa south of the Sahara as a result
of their deportation under the existential
travesty of being blacks', negroes or col¬
oured people. Moreover, this tendency to
identify members of the species "racially"
had disguised as whites peoples who had
their own ethnic specificity as Spaniards,
French, English, Dutch, Portuguese etc. In
the context of the American colonies,
necessity wore a white mask. The ignominy
and violence of this racial antagonism com¬
pounded the universal conflict of master and
slave, settler and native. Prospero and
Caliban.
From this time on, the somatic features
and physical appearance of Africans, Euro¬
peans, and natives of the Caribbean con¬
stituted so many social signs which served
to identify the relationship of domination
and dependence between conquerors and
their victims. It became standard practice to
argue for a cause and effect relationship bet¬
ween skin colour, the facial structure of dif¬
ferent human groups and the particular i
forms of insertion into nature and society. I
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
I M
<^c
Dancing is so much a part of voodoo, the folk religion of the
people of Haiti, that the Swiss ethnologist Alfred Métraux
classified the cult among the "danced religions". In voodoo
ceremonies (above) an active part is played by initiates known as
hounsis (a word from the Fon language of West Africa meaning
"wife of the god") who constitute with the male priests (houngan)
and the priestesses (mambo) a fellowship devoted to the cult of
the loa or spirits. Each loa has its own distinctive pattern of
drumbeats and its own dances of African origin such as the
boumba, the gabienne, the calenda and the nago grand-coup.
During the dance the women often seize the hem of their dress
with both hands and raise and lower it slightly in time to the
rhythm. The attributes of the loa are depicted in symbolic designs.
the vévé, whose outlines are traced on the ground by sprinkling
flour, ashes, coffee grounds or brick dust. Shown below are three
metal vévés. The heart without dagger (left) is the magic attribute
of the goddess Erzulie-Dantor, queen of beauty and love, protector
of homes and fresh-water ponds. The goddess Ayizan la-Grande
(centre) must be invoked at the beginning of every voodoo
ceremony. Like her husband Atibon Legba, the Haitian lord of the
crossroads and the meeting of the ways, she watches over doors,
houses, public places and markets. Vévé at right is that of the
marassa or twins, which have an honoured place in voodoo and
are connected with the rain. Like the other loas they belong to
various African peoples.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
k Because of this reduction of the social and
"cultural conflicts of colonization. to racial
factors, the human essence of workers
belonging to the different ethnic groups of
Africa was itself reduced to the absurd
notion of the natural-inferiority-of-the-
negro, while the human essence of the set¬
tlers from the different nations of Europe
was elevated to the no less extravagant no¬
tion of the natural-superiority-of-the-whites.
In short, it amounted to a mythological and
semiotic reductionism which supplied a
basis for the ease of conscience of the set¬
tlers who had freely left Europe, at the same
time that it debased and weakened the
states of mind of slaves brought by force to
the Caribbean.
This mental and physical "blocking out"
was preceded by that of geography.
Cheated of the fabulous East which he had
set out to find, Columbus gave the name
West Indies to the islands he took over. But
when the totality of "the lands discovered
on the other side of the Oceanic sea" were
being named, the star of Amerigo Vespucci
shone with a more brilliant light than that of
the Spanish Admiral, and these lands were,
therefore, called America. Everything took
place as if Europe, in order to carry through
its fantastic plans in the western
hemisphere, felt obliged to disguise at one
and the same time the field of operation of
its colonial activity and the realities of the
diverse protagonists engaged in it.
Thus, in common with the other countries
of the continent, the Caribbean's entry into
modern history took place under a false
identity. Disguised under a multiplicity of
masks, humanity in our regions acquired a
fresh consciousness of the forms, contours
and horizons of the planet. Europe's audaci¬
ty permitted it to reap the benefit of rich ex¬
perience in various agricultural, alimentary,
astronomical, naval and military fields. It
achieved a new mastery over land and sea;
and navigation, map-making, and evaluation
of distances, currents and winds advanced
accordingly.
The plantation system represented the
economic axis of this progress. The Por¬
tuguese had already tested this system on a
modest scale on the island of Sao Tomé.
Within the West Indian archipelago it under¬
went a spectacular expansion as a result of
the slave-trade and the boost this gave to
the production of sugar, tobacco, coffee,
cotton, cocoa, indigo and spices. Moreover,
the African biological fuel enabled interna¬
tional commerce and mechanized industry
to profit to the fullest extent from the
technological innovation of the first in¬
dustrial revolution as applied in the planta¬
tion economy, namely, the steam engine,
energy transmission, original lubrication
methods, improvement of windmills, etc.
For three centuries during which it function¬
ed as the energizing force of the world
market, the production of the West Indian
plantation was one of the essential
mechanisms for the accumulation of capital
and one of the historical causes of the scien¬
tific and cultural success of the West.
To expedite this success, Europe tried
first of all to "deculturate" the Indian and
African manpower. Itself a territory of cross¬
bred peoples produced by the Graeco-Latin
and Judaeo-Christian symbiosis, Europe
feared, nonetheless, the consequences of
cultural cross-breeding in the Americas.
But, in order to advance its commerce and
industry, it required an army of strong-
18
armed servants rather than an orchestra of
coloured Graeco-Latins interpreting the
spirit of their ancestors on the hills of the
new world.
Representatives of what they considered
to be a divinely-sanctioned political, social
and cultural order, the Europeans had no in¬
tention of assimilating exotic models to their
cultural heritage. They assumed that the
Yoruba, Fon, Fanti-Ashanti and Congolese
gods would efface themselves before the
Catholic saints because all that was not
white was barbaric or savage. Consequent¬
ly, the descendants of Africans were invited
to forget all about their past, to take leave of
their own imaginations and identity, and to
acquiesce in the dulling of their own con¬
sciousness and sensibility.
Fortunately, the socio-cultural process
reserved for the Caribbean took another
route. The new peoples formed in the Carib¬
bean melting-pot did not entrust themselves
to the providence of empires in order to
forge the essential elements of a new identi¬
ty. Caught up in their own problems and
trapped in the "racial" myth, they did not
believe that all that they had to do to pass
from "barbarism" to "civilization" was pure¬
ly and simply to imitate the behaviour, arts
and customs of Europe.
Cultural anthropology has made much of
the acculturation of the descendants of
Africans to European models and symbols.
Above all, it has advanced the idea of
"reinterpretation" according to which the
"African mentality" is seen as having re
mained unchanging in its relationship to
work, law, religion, the family, and liberty
throughout the long Caribbean process of
r cultural cross-fertilization.
This phenomenon required the historical
inputs and creative energies of the descen¬
dants of both Africa and Europe. The
cultural contribution of the slave africanized
the consciousness and the se the
mind and the body of the colonizer. In the
same way, the innovations of the latter
europeanized the African imagination. This
gave rise to a dynamic mutation of identities
which is perfectly summed up in the con¬
cept of creolization found in West -Indian
societies.
This notion of Creolism is fundamental in
all that has to do with the knowledge, inter¬
pretation and understanding of historical
phenomena in the Caribbean. The African
and European heritage, transformed by the
social metabolism of the plantation regime,
culminated in original ways of thinking, feel¬
ing, acting and dreaming. As a result of the
mixing of cultural elements inherited from
the two continents, along with the pre-
Columbian contribution, the Caribbean
became that New World imagined too soon
by Columbus, at the moment when his
Europe was feverishly engaged in applying
its masks to the history of other continents.
The originality of the Caribbean and Latin-
American world in general is the result of a
sustained cross-breeding which enabled the
oppressed peoples of the region to discover
themselves by tearing away little by little all k
the masks of colonization. r
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
In Haitian voodoo, the Ogou
(known as Ogun in the
candomblé religious ceremony
of Brazil and the santería of
Cuba) are a family of spirits or
divinities (loas) whose members
are blacksmith-gods. The name
of Ogou is often found
associated with others, (such as
the names of saints), reflecting
the syncretism of African beliefs
with those of Europe and of the
pre-Columbian world. Opposite
page, at the festival of Ogun at
Undo (Nigeria) a priest has
draped around his neck a snake,
one of the god's favourite
animals. Chango (the Shango of
Brazil and Trinité) is another loa
of Haiti and one of the most
popular gods of Caribbean
mythology. The god of storms
and hurler of thunderbolts, he
also protects the fertility of
women and passes through
cyclones and flooded rivers
unscathed. Left, a fire-bearer
joins in the festival of Shango at
Ede (Nigeria).
Left, a painting from Haiti
depicting the festival of Agoué-
Taroyo, lord of the sea and the
isles, fresh water, rivers, lakes,
ponds and springs. He often
appears to the faithful in the
form of a fish. Among his
symbols is a small sailing ship
which can be seen on the altars
of voodoo temples (houmfors)
and which is carried amid great
ceremony during the festival in
his honour.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
k Who, then, are these Caribbeans who
never allowed themselves to be Graeco-
Latinized? What is it that characterizes them
by contrast with Europe, Africa, the other
Americas, and the rest of the world?
Today it is easier to describe the condition
of our societies than in 1815 when, in the
eyes of Simón Bolívar, such an undertaking
appeared "at one and the same time extraor¬
dinary and terribly complicated." Since that
time the peoples concerned have
themselves decided to put an end to the car¬
ving up of their history effected by suc¬
cessive interventions of the colonial sword.
They have looked for, and some have even
found, adequate responses to the identity
conflicts which the natives of the Caribbean
have had to face since the struggles for
liberation sustained by such men as Tous¬
saint Louverture, Simón Bolívar, José Martí,
Marcus Garvey and Peralte.
Today in the Caribbean, new
methodological tools exist which permit the
re-evaluation of the history of our societies.
New conceptual frameworks enable us -to
avoid the ethnocentricity which consisted in
bringing all reflection back to the a priori
judgements contained in the ideologies of
colonialization. The tenacious "racial"
preconceptions which weighed so heavily
on the concepts of anthropology and
historiography are in the process of losing
their appeal thanks to interdisciplinary
research which has made possible an ex¬
haustive knowledge of the extremely com¬
plex historico-cultural processes which ex¬
plain both the astonishing diversity and the
unquestionable unity of cultures in the
Caribbean new world.
Much more is now known of the history
of the movements of resistance to coloniza¬
tion which many generations of Maroon
negroes inspired from 1519 up to the end of
the nineteenth century. The works devoted
to the Republics of the Maroons have
destroyed the myth of the supposed spirit of
resignation which, it was assumed,
characterized the African slaves. It has been
found, in fact, that the presence of the
Maroons not only represented a social and
political phenomenon, but also signified a
spiritual activity which permitted workers on
the American plantations to create for
themselves a new set of values in religion,
magic, music, dance, popular medicine,
creóle languages, cooking, oral literature,
sexual life, the family and many other areas
of social life.
In quest of a new existential basis for their
identity, the slaves of the Caribbean took
over and redirected the dynamism implicit in
the anguish of the "negro condition" which
had been invented for them, and thereby
cultivated in themselves the universal sense
of liberty. They discovered in the process re¬
joinders to the crises which threatened to
dull or to efface their social consciousness
and their sensibility. Like their predecessors
in the Roman Empire, they imagined native
religions of defence endowed with symbolic
and mythological structures corresponding
to their unfulfilled desires as terribly
humiliated and oppressed men.
This cultural influence of the Maroons did
not make- itself felt with equal force in all of
the areas of life and culture. The languages
of the masters were not pervaded
everywhere by Maroon influence, even if the
very real impact of African languages has
been noted in the case of the Spanish and
the Portuguese of the Americas. With the
20
exception of the creóle languages of Haiti,
Martinique and Guadeloupe, the papiamen¬
to of Curaçao and Aruba, and the West In¬
dian and Guyanese "Pidgin" jargons, the
Maroon influence on European idioms did
not become general.
Similarly, the juridical traditions of West
Africa, along with the political and
economic modes of thought proper to the
pre-colonial societies of the African conti¬
nent were stifled. Techniques and arts such
as iron-working, weaving, and statuary,
sculpture in wood and ivory, and other ex¬
pressions of the African genius, were lost
sight of because of the "purely socio¬
economic sensibility" of colonial America.
The historical effects of the Maroon ac¬
tivities were not enough, either, to exorcize
"Uncle Tom" attitudes, the fear and the
shame of being "negro", the inferiority com¬
plex, imitative behaviour, and the forms of
social ambivalence characteristic at times of
the way in which Caribbeans behave.
To be sure, the slave-traders of the
economic traffic have disappeared from the
scene, but even in this period of active
decolonization certain "elites" are, alas,
engaged in imitating with tragic results the
institutional models of empires old and new,
as well as parodying mental processes com¬
pletely opposed to the specific outlook and
attitudes of those who live in our islands.
Nevertheless, the facts are there: a
general renewal of mind and sensibility is
winning out over the phenomena of colonial
recurrence. Memory and imagination are
busy finding new functions for the cultural
heritages which our peoples have patiently
incorporated into their everyday life, their
work, and their most secret dreams.
The Caribbean basin which a
Manichean vision of history presents as
lands in flames surrounded by a boiling
sea is in the process of living a new
chapter in its historic adventure. At last free
to assume its own identity, the archipelago
in its totality has something of its own to ex¬
press and is doing it with vigour in every
field of thought and action. Indeed, the data
of history, ecology, society, play, politics
and religion frequently take on an epic
dimension in the life, as well as in the
cultures of the region.
As to the literary and artistic activity of the
Caribbean, it is characterized by a sensibility
which is Dionysian, solar and dream-like all
at once, and which brings together within
the same compass picaresque realism and
popular surrealism. A dazzling gulf exists
between the human being and his Caribbean
environment: the elemental joie de vivre (in
spite of atrocious social misfortunes) is
found side by side with the almost erotic
pleasure produced by a harmony of sounds,
colours and forms. In this respect, and
without underestimating the role of
literature and the plastic arts, music oc¬
cupies in the Caribbean the first place in the
aesthetic apprehension of lived experience.
The Caribbean bow will one day break the
last side of the triangle within which colonial
commerce has hitherto enclosed its destiny
and release, in every direction where
fellowship beckons, its arrows of music, art,
fiction and poetry. On that day the world will
learn that the disorders of history and
geography can be transformed into a state
of health reflecting both the imaginative life
and real experience of societies.
H René Depestre
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite page
The farmer-god Zaka, seated astride his
horse in the midst of a fantastic
landscape, is depicted in this painting
by the Haitian artist Edouard Duval.
Both Zaka, whose family plays a major
role in voodoo mythology, and his
steed have the same dreamy air of
mockery, self-confidence and, almost,
defiance. Embodied in the rider and his
mount are some of the hopes, truths
and mysteries which sustain Haitian
culture, quickened by the country's
historical roots and expressed in works
of painting and literature in which
dream and reality are one.
Photo © Alexis Stroukoff, Vogue, France
Pages 22 and 23
La Jungla (1943) by the Cuban painter
Wifredo Lam (right hand page). This
famous painting is rightly considered to
be a model expression of the Antillean
sensibility in the visual arts. Lam, who
was closely connected with Picasso
and the Surrealist movement, here
transmits the vision and experience of
Caribbean man. Clearly discernible in
the teeming mass of plant forms is a
landscape with which Lam was familiar
during his childhood in Cuba: the sugar
plantation. The bond which unites the
painting to tropical nature in the
Antilles appears in colours and forms
recalling the plant life found in so many
Caribbean islands (left hand page). But
more important than what the painting
tells us about nature is the light it
sheds on the intermingling which is the
characteristic feature of the culture of
Cuba and of the Antilles in general. La
Jungla, above all in the four mysterious
figures, conjures up the mythical world
of syncretic Cuban religions. In this
animistic frenzy, in the rust-coloured
leaves and flowers, is the vibrant
presence of the god Shango. But its
specifically Antillean content apart, this
work has been seen as the first
expression in the visual arts of a Third
World which had already understood
the urgent need to bring together all
world cultures to be shared as a
common heritage.
Photo © Yvette Vincent Alleaume, Paris
Photo © Museum of Modern Art, New York
Centre pages
The riot of colours, the exuberance and
the bustle of this market scene in the
port of Miragoane (Haiti) could be
matched many times over on other
Caribbean islands. The sailing ships are
a reminder of the omnipresent sea, the
very essence of Caribbean history.
Photo Michael Friedel © Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
i"
V
í^'
f
V
.#
y
5»ft
mm
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
J.
A
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
COLOUR PAGES
Page 26
Salt-pans form a geometric pattern on
the island of Bonaire. With Aruba and
Curaçao, Bonaire is one of the largest
islands of the Netherlands Antilles,
where Papiamento, a language which
evolved during colonial times, is spoken.
Photo Michael Friede! © Rapho, Paris
Page 27
Sugar and tobacco, the chief products
of the old plantation system, are still a
mainstay of the modern Caribbean
economy. Above, the abandoned ruins
of an old sugar factory in Tobago
symbolize the collapse of the old world
of the plantation. The mill, imported
from Glasgow in 1857, has been
overgrown by vegetation. Refineries
today use' ultra-modern techniques.
Below, a tobacco field in Cuba, home
of, the famous Havana cigars.
Photo Michael Friedet © Rapho, Paris
Opposite page
In the Caribbean the exuberant
festivities of the carnival have inspired
the creation of colourful masks, images
and other imaginative art-forms which
draw heavily on the African heritage
and are unrivalled examples of their
kind. Above left and below, two
images of the world-famous carnival of
Trinidad. Above right, Diablito, a work
by the Cuban painter René
Portocarrero. Diablitos are masked
figures who dance in groups during
certain ceremonies of Cuba's santería
folk religion. They display a striking
affinity with the figures of the carnival,
products of the same world of the
imagination.
Photo M. Moisnard © Explorer, Paris
Photo Michael Friedel © Rapho, Paris
Photo © Miguel Rojas Mix, Paris
Private collection, Havana
'Ours'
The West Indies from within
by Marion Patrick Jones
THE sea lashes against the edge of the
cliff as it has done for hundreds of
years. Sauters it is called, Sauters,
Grenada. Sauters the place from which the
Indians jumped when cornered by invading
European forces.
The desperate battles of Caribs, Arawaks
rebaptized Indians remain unsung. Their
rock carvings have crumbled into the sea,
their pottery is only fitfully collected. Names
remain: Jamaica, Chacachare, Naparima.
True, in Trinidad that mixture of Carib or
Arawak and poor Spaniard has maintained
for us corn, cassava dishes, the guitars, the
dancing and the songs of Parang (1), the
whirling of the Cascianne (2). There is little
that marks the mass refusal to be enslaved at
Sauters or the revolt against conquest in
Trinidad. Indeed most Trinidadians still see
the revolt in terms of "martyred" priests and
therefore part of native savagery.
This is not by chance. Historical recording
is always a selection of facts, not necessarily
according to their actual historical weight
but because of the preoccupations of the
present. The difference in the case of the
English-speaking Caribbean is that even
after Independence, this selection is not
made internally but largely externally. Nor is
this simply colonial or neo-colonial selectivi¬
ty. The Caribbean is seen by Left or Right
mainly as the appendage of external black-
white racial politics and ambitions.
The known heroes are those who prin¬
cipally influenced blacks abroad. The only
way to be known culturally is to be published
abroad, reviewed abroad, exhibited abroad.
Yet, for Trinidadians, it is Beryl MacBurnie
and her Little Carib that matters in dance and
Ellie Manette and Spree Simons in music.
Few Jamaicans can escape the influence in
sculpture of an Edna Manley or of Louise
Bennett in song. Bahamians remember Meta
Cumberbatch in music. These stubbornly
fought internally helping to create the Carib¬
bean that is. They were among those who
kept faith with countries that seemed to
have no future in themselves or for
themselves.
The beautiful island houses with their iced
fringed wooden carved work, their tiny
paned windows, their slotted jalousies, fall
in disrepair, replaced by yellow modern con¬
crete, except for the Great Houses of
Jamaica and Guyana. For what does this
patient art of the poor matter next to a black
aristocratic tradition, priestess to chief, that
(1) Parang: Christmas festivities. Parang songs have a
special rhythm and are sung in Spanish to a guitar.
(2) Cascianne: An old Spanish waltz still kept alive in
Trinidad and Venezuela.
must be established for external consump¬
tion in another age plantation owners
built their own mythology of a white
aristocratic past? Nor is this black or white.
Part of "East" Indian tradition in the Carib¬
bean sought for Brahminical princely roots.
Ah, the two Naipaul novelist brothers! It was
the peasant Orinhi that was ours.
Few people know of the existence of J.J.
Thomas although, as early as 1869, he had
established a creóle grammar for a "patois"
already under the pressure of English. His
Froudacity (1889) laid the basis for much of
the slant of Caribbean History, whether that
of Eric Williams, C.L.R. James, E. Brathwaite
or Walter Rodney. J.J. Thomas was born
around 1840two years after the final aboli¬
tion of slavery in the British West Indies.
Froudacity: West Indian Fables Explained
was a reply to an Englishman, James An¬
thony Froude's The English in the West In¬
dies (1888). If Nanny of the Maroons is now
recalled in Jamaica as the woman who led
slaves against British settlers and whom
bullets could not kill, she is yet to be given
the kind of recognition abroad that her
military skills would earn her if she were a
French Joan of Arc.
This preoccupation with abroad permeates
the entire society. Caribbean history is yet to
be given equality with European history, let
alone allowed to play its part in the ac¬
cumulation of knowledge. Part of this stems
from the fragility of countries whose history
is in part that of the myth of the naturalness
of European domination. Opposition to this
was often couched in a co-option but rever¬
sal of the dominant ideology. If the real
centre of superiority was In the high culture
of Europe, then the reply to this was seen as
the equality of high culture in India and
Africa and these continents as the source of
the real opposition to Europe.
This idealization of "abroad", the real and
complex problems of small countries, the
high percentage of emigrants to "white" in¬
dustrialized countries, the fear of the emerg¬
ing middle class that they would be swallow¬
ed by the unrespectable were factors that
continually prevented knowledge of the
past, with few exceptions, from rising above
the level of oral history and folk knowledge.
This history, this cultureours has been
patiently created in a struggle that, for the
most part, took place inside and which was W
principally a popular struggle with its f
MARION PATRICK JONES, of Trinidad and
Tobago, is a writer, novelist and anthropologist.
Among her published works are Pan Beat and
J'ouvert Morning, Columbus Press, Port of
Spain, Trinidad.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
backbone in slums and barrack yards, plan-
' tations and small farms. It was, as every¬
where else, a struggle complicated not only
by race but by freed or unfreed, by class, by
status. If the maroons emerge, because of
the wars they waged from 1655 to 1880, as
able to impose a treaty with Britain ensuring
their freedom from slavery, they were also
used by Governor Edward Eyre to put down,
in the name of Britain, the revolt of 1865,
associated with George William Gordon and
Paul Bogle, for better parliamentary
representation in Jamaica. Both were ex¬
ecuted by the colonial authorities for
"subversion".
The struggle in the late nineteenth century
was part of the effervescence which was
marked by J.J. Thomas culturally in
Trinidad. It was in popular culture that
history was kept, grievances given political
commentary. It was out of this that what
there was of élite culture emerged. Both
were part of a political battle for autonomy,
for trade union rights, eventually for in¬
dependence. It was never simply a struggle
against racial supremacy or for integration,
although racism was an important part of
the pattern of colonial domination. To forget
the association between popular culture and
politics or the dimensions of the political is
to misunderstand the nature of society in the
English-speaking Caribbean.
The 1920s and 1930s were marked by the
paintings of Alf Cadallo, peopled with myth
as by ordinary people, with the flambeaux,
the crowded old barrack yards. The poverty
that marked colonial rule became the ground
from which beauty emerged. But, at the
same time, Cipriani (3) was resisting colonial
encroachment on the few areas of autonomy
left. Alfred Richards (4) was organizing
dockers into a union, there were yearly peti¬
tions to keep carnival going or to keep the
paper carved temples of the Muslim festival
of Hosea on the St. James street.
(3) Cipriani: Captain Cipriani was a Trinidadian of Cor-
sican descent who fought in the 1914-1918 war and
returned to Trinidad to fight for autonomy and against
white privilege. Many times Mayor of Port of Spain,
he is one of the most important heroes of Trinidad.
(4) Alfred Richards: Closely associated with Cipriani, he
fought to improve the conditions of indentured labour
and for the establishment of trade unions.
None of these were as simple as they now
sound. First of all, they built on a past that
had seen the Central Administrative Building
burned down by the people of Port of Spain
in a revolt against water taxes the famous
Red House riots. They mobilized workers,
unemployed, the property-less against
British rule and they underlined an important
problem: trade union rights.
By the late 1930s working class dissatisfac¬
tion had spilled over in a series of revolts: a
sugar strike in St. Kitts in 1935, a revolt
against customs duties in St. Vincent in the
same year, a coal strike in St. Lucia in 1935, a
sympathy strike in Barbados in 1937 which
became a full-fledged conflict led by Payne,
revolt in the sugar plantations in Guyana in
1937, the dockers' strike in Jamaica in 1938.
Uriah Buzz Butler emerged in Trinidad as the
leader of a labour movement, a woman
single-handed stopped the feared policeman
Charlie King literally dead, while in Jamaica
the strike had thrown up two major leaders:
Norman Manley and Alexander Bustamante
(each later prime minister of his country),
and, let us not forget it, a number of deter¬
mined courageous women who fed the
strikers and without whom the strike would
have failed.
None of these local leaders became heroes
to the outside world. Bourgeois traditions of
revolution have not accepted Gordon,
although his arguments were along the lines
of George Washington and of Jefferson. Left
traditions have not included the attempt at a
socialist group and a First of May labour
parade associated in Trinidad with Richards,
Achong and Jones.
This period also saw the blossoming of
culture. It is parallel to this that emerges dur¬
ing the war years, in the slums "behind the
bridge" in Port of Spain, the steel band.
Created by the poor, steel band music,
beaten at first on stolen dustbin covers to
the horror of middle-class Trinidad
accompanied the pitched gang warfare
that had in the past marked stick fighting,
and was to become in post-war years the
national music.
This process is also part of the history of
"culture" in the English-speaking Caribbean.
The national cultural elements elaborated by
the poor are first fought against, then are
adopted by the élites, whether this is dance,
song, music or food. It is reggae that is
"Jamaican", Rex Nettleford adapts popular
dance, Sylvia Winter writes her finest plays
on the miming of John Cannoe, and who can
forget the sensitive jewel of Errol John's
Moon on a Rainbow Shawl?
Nor is it simply song, music, dance.
Pawan's rabies discovery coincides with the
1920s and 1930s. W. Arthur Lewis in
economics, M.G. Smith in social an¬
thropology cannot be understood outside of
popular problems or the fight to guide our
own future. Both belong to the In¬
dependence struggle of the 1940s and 1950s.
Their greatness and limitations stem from
this.
But what of the men that led us to In¬
dependence? For they too fought against
enormous odds. Take Eric Williams (5).
Author of a seminal work in history
Capitalism and Slavery, Eric Williams filled
the Trinidad Public Library to hear his history
lectures in 1949 and 1950. Fired from the then
Caribbean Commission because of his "bias¬
ed" views on the "Negro in the Caribbean",
Eric "let his bucket down" in a series of lec¬
tures in Woodford Square. It is out of this
that the people of Trinidad and Tobago
argued that the only solution for the prob¬
lems and conflicts that marked every institu¬
tion was Independence. True, we had a
bankrupt treasury, true we were at the time
many fewer than today's million people, yet
most of us had had enough.
This movement for Independence as well
as the question of American bases which ac¬
companied it was in itself complex. Certain
well-defined segments of the population op¬
posed Independence which they saw as like¬
ly to end certain privileges. This push to In¬
dependence was true in Jamaica under the
leadership of Manley and Bustamante where
it grew more directly out of the trade union
movement and out of the strikes in 1930, in
Guyana with Forbes Burnham and Cheddi
Jagan, Grantley Adams in Barbados. It was
the push that collapsed the "Bay Street
Boys" (6) in the Bahamas.
It would be optimistic to see the fight for
Independence as finished. Rather the strug¬
gle to make our own history according to our
own realities and to have this recognized as
having a right of existence goes on. The ac¬
clamation of Independence, which began in
the 1960s and which continues to sweep the
region, is neither the beginning of a process
nor the end of it.
We would make our own history. For we
are Caribbeans. The golden poul flowers for
one dayours. We have saved with our su-
sus, danced the limbo, drunk black coffee at
a wake, munched pattiesou«. We have
created a language, hill Jamaican, Bajan
Burr (7), West Indian standard ours. This is,
as one calypsonian put it, "our land and our
grandfathers' land and our children to come
land too"ours.
Bury us, bury those to come unto the end
of time, under the blue hills, the still stars of
Caribbean night. For the hills, the stars, the
sea hold the souls of ancestors who
fought ours.
H Marion Patrick Jones
(5) Eric Williams : Dr. Eric Eustace Williams was an
economic historian who analysed the relationship bet¬
ween free trade and the abolition of slavery. The
youngest professor at Howard University in
Washington, D.C, he joined the then Caribbean
Commission whose headquarters were in Port of
Spain. After losing his job there he founded the Peo¬
ple's National Movement and led Trinidad and
Tobago to independence. He died in 1981.
(6) Bay Street Boys: Of British descent, the Bay Street
Boys, so called because they controlled the com¬
merce located in Bay Street, for a long time
dominated politics in the Bahamas to the exclusion of
most blacks.
(7) Bajan Burr: Bajan is a local appellation of a Barbadian.
Barbadians speak with a distinctive accent, or burr.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Calendrier lagunaire
by Aimé Césaire
I dwell in a sacred wound
I dwell in imaginary ancestors
I dwell in an obscure desire
I dwell in a long silence
I dwell in an unquenchable thirst
I dwell in a thousand-year journey
I dwell in a three hundred years war
I dwell in a disaffected cult
between bulb and bud I dwell in the unused space
I dwell in basalt not a flow
but the billow of lava
which sweeps up the gu/ley
and burns all the mosques
I adapt as best I can to this avatar
of a version of paradise absurdly come to naught
far worse than hell
Sometimes I dwell in one of my wounds
Every minute I change my apartment
and all respite terrifies me
whir/wind of fire
. ascidia like no other for dust
of worlds gone astray
having spat out, a volcano, my entrails of spring vw.
/ remain with my words of bread and my secret ores
So I dwell in a vast mind
but I usually prefer to confine myself
in the smallest of my ideas
or else I dwell in a magic formula
the first words only
all the rest forgotten
I dwell in the icepack
I dwell in its débâcle
I dwell in the front of a great disaster
I dwell more often in the driest pap
of the gauntest pinnacle the she-wolf of these clouds
I dwell in the halo of the cacti
I dwell in a herd of she-goats drawing
on the teat of the most desolate sideroxylon
Truly I no longer know my true address
Bathyal or abyssal
I dwell in the holes of octopuses
I struggle with an octopus for an octopus hole
Brother lay off
Heap of kelp
Clinging like cuscuta
or unfurling myself like porana
It's all the same
and let the waves swell
and let the sun blister
and let the wind lash
round hump of my nothingness
The pressure, atmospheric or rather
historic is mounting my pain beyond measure
even if it makes some of my words magnificence.
Sideroxylon: a genus of tropical trees noted for their hard wood. Cuscuta: a genus of
twining, leafless parasitic plants. Porana: a climbing herb of the convulvulus family.
AIMÉ CÉSAIRE, poet and playwright of Martinique, is the mayor of Fort-
de-France (Martinique) and a deputy in the French NationalAssembly. He
is among the most brilliant modern lyric poets writing in French. The above
poem is hitherto unpublished.
Fernando Ortiz "The father of Caribbean studies' by Lisandro Otero
THE hundredth anniversary of the birth
of Fernando Ortiz was celebrated on
16 July this year. Ortiz-has rightly been
called the third discoverer of Cuba (after Col¬
umbus and Alexander Humboldt), for his
writings, so scholarly and rigorously scien¬
tific, have been one of the principal factors in
shaping Cuba's national identity.
Ortiz was among the very first people to
observe the mestizo (intermixed) character
of our culture and to point to our fragmented
and dissimilar origins and to the syncretic
nature of some of our popular beliefs.
He confessed in 1942 that, some forty
years earlier, he had become interested in
sociological questions, then a comparatively
new branch of studies, and had started look¬
ing into Cuban problems. "Immediately, the
figure of the Negro loomed large before me.
And this was only natural, for without the
Negro Cuba would not be Cuba." He began
to study the Negro as an integral factor in the
national identity and immediately came up
against a host of obstacles and prejudices.
There were very few studies and even less in¬
terest. For some people, it amounted to rak¬
ing up consciousness of or laying bare the
guilt of the past. Furthermore, it was
something that was not worth the trouble
and was not profitable.
In one of his lectures, Fernando Ortiz once
said: "It was dangerous to talk of the Negro
and it could only be done by adopting a
devious approach. Even the Negroes, and
especially the mulattos, seemed to want to
forget about themselves and to deny their
race so that they would not have to recall
their martyrdom and frustrations, just as
lepers sometimes try to conceal the shame
of their sores...".
At that time, at the beginning of the cen¬
tury, when the Cuban Republic had just
come into being, there existed a middle class
which was dedicated to producing an idealiz¬
ed image of itself and to aping foreign think¬
ing and behaviour patterns. Ortiz was the
first person to display the rigorous scientific
attitude needed to seek out the true roots of
this phenomenon, and to have the audacity
to proclaim their nature. His main contribu¬
tion to Cuban culture was his understanding
of the hybrid nature of our national origins.
In his researches, he left his mark on a very
wide variety of cultural fields. After embark¬
ing on a legal and criminological career, he
switched to sociology and then went on to
archaeology, history, philology and an¬
thropology, musicology and ethnography.
Ortiz showed us the dynamic interrelation¬
ships existing between the different
elements of the social life of Cuba. For seven
decades, he explored, analysed and
classified the new flowering of Negro
cultures in Cuba, after their former African
spendours.
One of the first problems with which Ortiz
had to contend was the lack of suitable tools
for his new task: there were no precedents
and there was not even an adequate scien¬
tific vocabulary to describe the phenomena
he was investigating. Ortiz coined such new
terms as Afro-Cuban, which has now
become so familiar, and transculturation,
which is used to designate the symbiosis of
cultures. The work he did in delving into the
specific features of things Cuban led him in¬
to the field of linguistics. In 1923, he publish¬
ed his Catauro de cubanismos (Dictionary of
Cubanisms), in which he listed 1,500 typical¬
ly Cuban words and expressions.
His best-known work is perhaps his Con¬
trapunto Cubano del Tabaco y el Azúcar
(Tobacco and Sugar: a Cuban Counterpoint),
in which he not only formulated a
penetrating analysis of economic history but
also wrote some of the finest pages in our
literature, subjecting the spirit of sugar and
of tobacco, as abstract entities, to a dialec¬
tical confrontation, contrasting white sugar
and brown tobacco, the sweet and the sour,
food and poison, energy and dreaming, the
flesh and the spirit, rain and earth, the sun
and the moon, day and night, water and fire.
The combination in this work of a wealth of
imagination and a mass of scientific
documentation makes it one of the land¬
marks of Cuban culture.
Ortiz the ethnographer wrote El Engaño de
las Razas (The Fraud of Races), which was
published in 1946, when the world had only
just emerged from the Fascist nightmare and
its pseudo-theories regarding the purported
superiority of the Aryan race and the in¬
feriority of the Semitic races: the former
destined to dominate and the latter to be
enslaved. The work of Ortiz constitutes a
fundamental refutation of those theses.
Yet Fernando Ortiz was more than a
scholar; he was an organizer and promoter
of culture. He created several institutions,
reviews and publishing houses even though
the times were not propitious for such
ventures.
His interest in the African influence on
Latin America led Ortiz to undertake a pro¬
found analysis of the main area in which
cultural elements of African origin were to
be found in a concentrated grouping the
Caribbean. In this Fernando Ortiz was a
precursor of Caribbean studies, and not only
in Cuba.
Throughout this centenary year Cubans
have been paying tribute to the vast, lucid
and penetrating work of Fernando Ortiz. For
Latin America, and in particular for that part
of Latin America that was subject to in¬
fluences from Africa, his work is essential
for the light it sheds and the profound
understanding it affords of the patterns and
process of transculturation.
LISANDRO OTERO, Cuban novelist and
essayist, is director of the Centre of Caribbean
Studies of the Casa de las Americas, Havana.
Among his novels, which have been translated in¬
to several languages, are La Situación (The Situa¬
tion) and General a Caballo (General on
Horseback).
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Creative contradictions
The Caribbean genius has given
birth to a new civilization
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
by Edouard Glissant
IT seems at first impossible to draw the
boundaries and define the internal
composition of the cultural and geo¬
graphic area known as the "Caribbean".
Does it consist purely and simply of the
Islands? Or should it be conceived of as a
broader expanse, including the three
Guyanas, which are continental, and
Panama, whose population is in part An¬
tillean? Venezuela looks out to the Carib¬
bean. Mexico has regularly joined in the now
traditional festivities of Carifesta, held in
Guyana in 1972, Jamaica in 1976, Cuba in
1979, and Barbados in 1981. The Creole
tradition still sets off many nostalgic echoes
in Louisiana. On the other hand, some of the
islands, such as the Dominican Republic and
Cuba, have until now appeared to show pro¬
pensities for an exclusively Latin-American
dimension. Four European languages
(English, Spanish, French and Dutch) are
officially used in the region, and at least five
varieties of Creole are spoken there. What
then is this reality which mushrooms out
over the Americas, North and South, and
which fits into no specific linguistic,
political, or ethnic framework?
The answer which gradually emerges is
that this element of indeterminacy is the
very hallmark of the profound richness of
the Caribbean. Or rather, that the indeter¬
minacy lies in the minds of those who still
envisage the Caribbean in terms of models
that have had their day, in terms of outmod¬
ed patterns which made sense of the
emergence of nations during earlier cen¬
turies in the West and elsewhere. The entire
region has been agitated by fruitful con¬
tradictions, the work and results of which
are worth pondering.
For example, it is naive to proclaim
without qualification that here everything
began with Christopher Columbus. The so-
called "discovery" left a substratum in
which Arawaks and Caribs, the original in¬
habitants of the region, exterminated by the
colonizers, implanted in Antilleans modes of
being of which they are often unaware.
It would be just as absurd to misap¬
prehend the historical conditions of the new
cultural area' thus constituted from the
period of colonization onwards, inherent in
which are the intermingling of cultural
elements and of peoples, tension leading
toward a shared dimension of human ex¬
perience. This intermingling, however, was w
not passive assent to the values imposed. F
EDOUARD GLISSANT, of Martinique, is the
author of many volumes of poems, novels and
essays, including Le Sel Noir, La Lézarde, La
Case du Commandeur, L'Intention Poétique and
Le Discours Antillais. He has also published a
play: Monsieur Toussaint. In 1967 he founded the
Institut Martiniquais d'Etudes af Fort-de-France.
He is currently a member of the Unesco
secretariat.
I awake, musing on the black fruit of the Aniba in
its warty and truncated husk... Ah! The crabs have
devoured a whole tree of soft fruit. Another is full
of scars; its flowers were growing, succulent, on
its trunk. And another one cannot touch with the
hand, as when calling someone to witness,
without a sudden shower of those flies, and colours!
Saint-John Perse
Éloges IV
<
o
<
Animal life and the plant world are virtually
indistinguishable in the French painter André
Masson's vision of the Antilles. In the mysterious
beyond of the imagination, dense curtains of plunging
lianas luxuriate in an impenetrable forest teeming
with wonderful creatures. "The Crab and Its Fortress"
drawn by Masson, above, seem to have emerged
from the primordial mud, girded with a wooden
cuirasse. Woody yet members of the mineral world,
they are nailed down by dry roots which climb to the
horizon where they suddenly become waving coconut
palms. For the people of the Antilles, however,
fortress crab can be, literally, shelled: at feasts on the
banks of remote streams it makes a succulent sacrifice.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
It is equally mistaken either to under¬
estimate the overriding impact of the
peopling of the Antilles with Africans (star¬
ting with the Slave-Trade) or to harbour the
illusion that the Antilles became a faithful
copy of Africa. Not only because of the in¬
flux of Indians to work the land abandoned
by the emancipated' African slaves; not only
because of the imprint left by the West; but
because the ferment born of the component
peoples has produced something else
new cultures, a new civilization.
Finally, it is not valid to conclude from the
variety of languages imposed upon the
region in the past or born of its ferment that
the people who live there are
heterogeneous. The Antilles today provide
an example of a civilization in full flood of
creativity, developing on a high tide of
multilingualism; the languages are national
(such as Spanish in Cuba or English in
Trinidad), but their use, and soon their shar¬
ing, is Antillean.
These "elemental" contradictions feed
many conflicts just as they have given birth
to many illusions and ideological assump¬
tions. The needs of nation-building in each
country on the one hand and virulent op¬
position among social classes on the other
seem to open up conflicting prospects in a
situation rendered more complex by the
necessity to affirm or defend cultural values
which are often inseparable from their
ethnic origins, and the elaboration of
generalized theories (indigenism in Haiti in
the 1930s, Négritude, Antillean outbreaks of
Black Power, Rastafari).
Yet it is contradiction itself which con¬
stitutes the value of this civilization. It can¬
not be appreciated by sticking to hard-and-
fast categories which make no allowances
for the unusual. Perhaps the lesson to be
drawn from the converging histories of the
Antillean peoples is that nation-building can
take place today without sterile confronta¬
tions, just as cultural values do not perish by
being shared. The Antillean countries,
which have known slavery and sometimes
"local" tyrannies, have paid a heavy price
for this privilege of cultural discovery and
contact.
The Caribbean Sea is the setting for such
a communion. The Saint Lucian playwright
Derek Walcott has encapsulated this in a
phrase, "History is Sea," and this is the
meaning of Barbadian historian Edward
Kamau Brathwaite's assertion that "The uni¬
ty is submarine." Both these writers are
poets intent on feeling and expressing the
long ordeal of the Caribbean's emergence.
The sea of the Antilles is an open sea. The
Arawaks and the Caribs roamed over it:
nomads of the sea, they periodically return¬
ed to places they had previously settled dur¬
ing their wanderings. It was colonization
which attempted, sometimes successfully,
to "balkanize" the region, to fragment it into
isolated lands locked in the conflicts which,
here as elsewhere, broke out among the
Western Great Powers. However, in 1794,
alarmed by rumours, the origin of which are
disputed, the slaves of the Lesser Antilles
tried to reach the country of Toussaint
Louverture, the future Republic of Haiti.
Many examples could be cited to
demonstrate that the histories of the Carib¬
bean peoples have always been intertwined
despite the barriers erected by colonization.
The Caribbean Sea, however, is not ringed
by lands and peoples which would seek to
34
concentrate in a constricting unit. It is not,
as the Mediterranean once was, an "inland
sea." Its propensity is to burst outwards,
whence the difficulty in charting the outlines
of such a socio-cultural phenomenon. The
offshoots of this civilization, from Louisiana
to Tobago and the Guyanas, overlie realities
which otherwise belong to other spheres of
influence.
But the cultural foundations of Antillean
reality were by no means indeterminate.
Wherever the slaves landed, on every island
and at various points up and down the
American coast, from northern Brazil and to
the south of the United States, the same
system was established for the exploitation
of various exotic products: spices, tobacco,
indigo, cotton, sugar cane. This was the
Plantation system. It was not only an
economic system based on slavery, but also
a way of life, a cultural framework, which in¬
spired many Antillean tales, as well as the
dance known as the calinda, and the blues.
The Plantation was an enclosure which
the slave or labourer did not leave. These
enclosures were ubiquitous. Casa Grande e
Senzalam. With the establishment of the
Plantation, two political and cultural institu¬
tions for escaping from the enclosure
emerged: running away and the carnival,
both widely practiced in the region.
Escape is not merely an episode in the
struggle of the oppressed against the op¬
pressors. It may have determined in large
part the attitudes and the reflexes of the
peoples of the Antilles: it meant escaping to
another enclosure, that of the intellectual
and cultural compartments within which
each people of the region was kept. The
historical consequence of this phenomenon
was the impassioned search for Caribbean
solidarity.
The carnival was not merely the overflow¬
ing of liberated instincts beyond the limits of
the Plantation. Little by little it reinforced the
tendency to make every cultural manifesta¬
tion simultaneously an act of consciousness
and a festival (Carifesta), an act of sharing
one's reasons for giving voice to the world
and one's conception of it.
From the Plantation came the tale, the
ballad, and the cadence of the drum, soon
to be replaced by the fulguration of poets
such as Nicolas Guillen or Aimé Césaire, the
fullness of folk artists (Haitian painting), the
exuberance and the syntheses of modern
arts (Wifredo Lam or Cardenas), and the
analyses and profundities of novelists
(Carpentier and Naipaul).
It is, perhaps, the memory of the Planta¬
tion that pushes so many Antillean intellec¬
tuals to expose themselves to the world of
les damnés de la terre, and to identify with
their cause: the Jamaican Marcus Garvey
with the blacks in the United States, the
Trinidadian George Padmore in Ghana, and
the Martiniquais Frantz Fanon in Algeria.
This kind of exile or noble expatriation is so
widespread that one wonders about its fun¬
damental causes an urge to understand
the Other which lies at the basis of the An¬
tillean experience, and a desire to break
bounds which still causes men to flee far
from the Plantation.
Thus, if the Antillean countries whose
cultural variety is so profuse, united and lux¬
uriant, still appear to be seeking their identi
ty, it is because of this very abundance
which is often not given its due. And also
because the collapse of the Plantation
system has left behind it, here and there, ex¬
treme varieties of political and economic
systems, the distortions of which explain
why the reality of the Antilles is so hard to
understand or accept. There is no indeter¬
minacy in life as it is lived, but it paralyses
those who analyse the cultures of the
Antilles.
In the present state of affairs, no possibili¬
ty of a federation or a confederation of the
Caribbean countries exists, however em¬
bryonic. CARICOM (The Common Market
of the Caribbean) mainly concerns the
English-speaking Antilles. In political terms.
111 Title of a work by the Brazilian writer Gilberto Freyre.
It means "The big house and the slave's cabin. "
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Striding barefoot on the
bare earth, this woman of
Martinique instinctively
adjusts her movements to
maintain the poise of her
head. On the cloth pad
above her brow, for all the
world to see, is the daily
fare; her baskets are laden
with modest treasures of
poverty and dignity. Women
have borne many things
across the Caribbean:
stones for the roads, coal
from mysterious cargo
boats, fruit and vegetables,
the trials of everyday life, and
the future of their children.
This work in ebony by the
great Cuban sculptor
Agustín Cárdenas is entitled
El Quarto Famba 1 (1973),
the name of the secluded
place where new members,
chosen for their fidelity to
the traditions of the
continent from which they
had been taken, were
initiated into a secret
society for Cubans of
African origin. Cárdenas has
produced such tall wooden
totems, like black flames
leaping from the African fire
which glows in the Antillean
consciousness, since his
early days as a sculptor.
Their form, expressive of
both serenity and torment,
marks the eruption into
modern art of sensibilities
which have not found
artistic expression since the
heyday of African sculpture.
These airy, smoothly-
finished works typify the
contact between cultures
that has inspired Cardenas'
work in wood and marble,
and show how an artist can
draw profound inspiration
from his roots yet also
practise the boldest
experimentation, in an art
that is both affirmation and
discovery.
the structures of the Caribbean countries
cover the whole spectrum. And yet Antillean
cultures have never gone so far in pooling
their specific features nor communicated so
much in terms of a single diversified concr p-
tion of man.
This conception has culminated in
Creolization, which is, as its etymology at¬
tests, an ambiguous phenomenon. Is the
Creole a White who lives in the Antilles, a
White born in the Antilles, or the descen¬
dant of an African? A long history of hesita¬
tion surrounds this question. Creolization is
not a simple process of acculturation: it in¬
volves original features, in some cases the
product of barely reconcilable contradic¬
tions, the chief of which, apart from ways of
life and cultural syncretism, may lie in
variants of language.
This phenomenon affects the languages
which have been imported into the region,
and which, as I have said, are sometimes us¬
ed in very special way. But its most extreme
expression lies in the diversity of pidgins and
especially in the existence of the Creole
language, a language of compromise, a
language forged within the Plantation,
which the Antillean people adopted in Haiti,
in Martinique and Guadeloupe, in Cayenne,
Saint Lucia, and Dominica.
Today this folk language is disappearing
in Trinidad and Jamaica, and it has never
been spoken in the Spanish-speaking An¬
tilles. Nonetheless, the world's tens of
millions of Creole speakers (including, as the
result of a strange and significant socio-
historical phenomenon, the inhabitants of
Réunion and Mauritius in the Indian Ocean)
can now envisage a renaissance for their
mother tongue, a renaissance admittedly
threatened by the technological weight of
the world's dominant languages.
The fact that the same Creole language is
spoken by the English-speaking peoples of
the Lesser Antilles is sufficient proof that it
has nothing to do with the patois formed
from the major languages, to which there
have often been attempts to reduce the
compromise languages which emerged in
the context of colonization. Creole is not a
deformation of French, from which its syn¬
tax, reputedly of African origin, is totally
alien.
Thus, in the present world configuration,
the Caribbean stands forth as a special set¬
ting in which nations and communities inter¬
relate, each with its own originality, sharing
nevertheless a common future. This area of
civilization opens onto the Americas; it is
gradually surmounting the barriers of a
paralyzing monolingualism and becoming
conscious of its singular talent for symbiosis
and for embracing, in all their overwhelming
exuberance, the often contradictory
elements which meet in the converging
histories of the Caribbean basin. In today's
threatened world this is a noble calling, at
once fragile and ineradicable.
M Edouard Glissant
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Carifesta
1 2
Photos above are stills from a Unesco film made during the
fourth Caribbean Festival of Arts ("CARIFESTA"), held at
Bridgetown, Barbados from 19 July to 3 August 1981. Now a
regular event in the region's cultural calendar, CARIFESTA offers
the Caribbean artistic community an opportunity to present their
work to a wide audience, and its success reflects the growing
consciousness of cultural potential that has spread through the
Caribbean in recent years. If the Caribbean arts in general are the
product of a fruitful synthesis of what has come to the region
from Africa, India and Europe, this intermingling is perhaps seen
most strikingly of all in dance, an art form which transcends
language barriers and national boundaries. There is above all a
rich African heritage of ritual dancing which has survived as each
generation made an effort to preserve the beliefs of their
ancestors. Photos 1 and 2 show the ganga dance from Trinidad
and Tobago. It is a tribute to Ogun, the mythological god of iron
in the pantheon of the Yoruba people of West Africa. During
36
such dances orishas or spiritual powers descend among the
mortals, "possessing" and transforming them for a period which
may last from a few minutes to several hours. Another thread in
the rich skein of influences (photo 4, dancers from Trinidad and
Tobago) was brought by the East Indians who came to the
Caribbean as indentured labourers in the 19th and early 20th
century. European dance movements also made their
contribution to this process of cross-fertilization. During the 18th
and 19th centuries planters kept abreast of European social
conventions and at glittering soirées in their great mansions
glided to the rhythm of the polka, the mazurka, the quadrille, the
minuet and other popular dances of the period. The influence of
these dances, observed, adapted and interpreted by African
slaves and servants. Is still strong today. (3) Dancers from the
Netherlands Antilles, where African rhythms and European
movements have combined in an original form of expression.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Legacy
of the past
A corner of historic Cap-Haitien
Haiti's second city
St. Mary's Roman Catholic church at Kingstown, capital of St. Vincent
The town of Trinidad, Cuba, was
founded by the Spaniards in 1514
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Caliban's revenge
by Roberto Fernández Retamar
AT the beginning of the nineteenth cen¬
tury, one of the first actions of the
victorious revolutionaries of Saint-
Domingue, the French part of the island of
Hispaniola, was to re-baptize their fledgling
nation Haiti, the name by which it had been
known by its original inhabitants.
More than a century and a half later, the
victorious revolutionaries of Cuba (which
had kept its original name) were to change
the names of the suburbs round the capital,
Havana. Country and Biltmore, the residen¬
tial areas of those who had benefited from
the social order that had been swept away,
resumed their ancient names of Cubancan
and Siboney.
This sanctioning of liberation struggles by
the elimination of place-names of European
origin (or, in the case of Cuba, of both Euro¬
pean and North American origin) and the
reinstatement of names connected with the
true discoverers of the region has been a
repeated practice in the Antilles. Yet,
curiously enough, neither the inhabitants of
Cuba nor those of Haiti had any ethnic links
with those peoples whose words and names
they brandished to proclaim their determina¬
tion to achieve complete independence.
The landing of the Europeans in the An¬
tilles misnamed "discovery" had
heralded the arrival of what the Cuban José
Martí, writing in 1877, described as a
"devastating civilization, two words which
a contradiction in terms and therefore, in
themselves, an indictment of a historical
process". And indeed, subjected as they
were to forced labour, hunted down like
wild animals, defending themselves in vain
against vastly superior arms, driven to mass
suicide or succumbing to contagious
diseases previously unknown to them, the
indigenous peoples (mistakenly called "In¬
dians" by the Westerners) had been virtually
annihilated within a few decades of the ar¬
rival of the Europeans. Yet they left behind
them words (many of which have entered
the European languages), the cultivation of
a variety of plants, some artefacts, and
habits such as smoking.
Neither the Haitians nor the Cubans
could, then, have been intent merely on
renewing a tradition that had been cut short
centuries earlier with the extermination of
the peoples who had given birth to it and
kept it alive. But the reintroduction of an¬
cient words and names harks back to the old
controversy about the "noble savage"
which is inextricably bound up with all our
part of America and especially with the
Caribbean. It was sparked off by the sudden
arrival in Europe, at a time when capitalist
development was in its infancy, of news of a
"New World".
The first peoples of this "New World"
whom the Europeans came to know were
the inhabitants of the Antilles. There is a
reference to them in the letter, dated
15 February 1493, in which Christopher Col¬
umbus, writing from his ship off the Canary
Islands, announced his "discovery" to
Europe.
These peoples formed two main com¬
munities which had spread out into the An¬
tilles from the northern part of South
America the Arahuacos (Arawaks), who
also included the Siboneyes (or Ciboneyes)
and the Tainos, and the Caribs, who were
eventually to give their name to the
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
"Mediterranean of the Americas". The first
of these peoples were of a peaceful disposi¬
tion, whereas the second were warlike. They
were to form the basis of the two main
images of the peoples of America which
fuelled the discussions of European thinkers
for centuries.
The first stirrings of this controversy arose
among the Spanish in the sixteenth century
and centred on the conquest and rights of
the misnamed "Indians". Among those who
spoke out on behalf of the Indians were men
like Bartolomé de Las Casas, the most
dynamic and celebrated among them, Fran-
' cisco de Vitoria, and Antonio Montesino,
who in a sermon delivered in 151 1 convinced
Las Casas of the rightness of his cause.
Among those who were against the Indians,
and hence in favour of enslaving them, were
men like Gonzalo Fernandez de Oviedo and
Ginés de Sepúlveda. The fiercest polemic
was that between Sepúlveda and Las Casas,
the man whom Simón Bolívar called the
"Apostle of the Americas", for his brave
defence of our indigenous peoples.
The repercussions of the reports on these
peoples of another world were not confined
to Spain alone. As early as 1516, the
Englishman Thomas More conjured up his
vision of an ideal country, Utopia, whose
resemblance to the island of Cuba was
pointed out in 1963 by the Argentine writer
Ezequiel Martinez Estrada. Moreover, in
1580, the French humanist Michel de Mon¬
taigne published his essay Des Cannibales,
in which he wrote that "there is nothing bar¬
baric or savage about those nations, from
what has been said about them; what hap¬
pens is that people brand as barbaric
everything alien to their own customs".
This assessment, with variations, was
kept alive as a sort of working hypothesis by
what we would now call the left wing of the
Western bourgeoisie in its revolutionary ad¬
vance and appears to have reached its
culmination in 1754, when Jean-Jacques
Rousseau wrote for the Academy of Dijon
an essay answering the questions: What is
the origin of the inequality between men? Is
it sanctioned by natural law?
Rousseau has been saddled with the
reputation of having lapsed into inane and
ingenuous thinking about the purported ex¬
cellence of the "noble savage". Yet when
we read what he wrote, he cannot be taxed
<
©
Caribbean countries and peoples
today are grappling with a legacy of
economic dependency created in
the past by the single-crop
plantation economy and their status
as mere appendages of their
colonial masters. Left, a modern
sugar factory in Barbados.
with having held such ideas. Perhaps more
than anybody else, he stressed the
hypothetical nature of such a creature. In his
view, "it is not a simple matter to distinguish
what is original from what is artificial in the
existing nature of man or to be perfectly ac¬
quainted with a state that does not exist,
has perhaps not existed, andprobably never
will..." (author's italics).
There can be no doubt, however, that in
developing his hypothesis, Rousseau often
had in mind the American peoples en¬
countered by the Europeans, especially the
inhabitants of the Caribbean, although
this is very revealing he would also
make reference to the Black African. The ex¬
amples he adduced for his "noble savage"
are sometimes "black" and sometimes (or at
the same time) the "Caribs of Venezuela",
the "Hottentots of the Cape of Good Hope"
and, on yet other occasions, the "savages of
America", the latter being the most fre¬
quently cited. He was to refer repeatedly to
these peoples, and especially to the Caribs
who, in his view, were "of existing peoples,
those who are least remote from their
natural state".
Rousseau's thesis is well known: "those
who were responsible for civilizing man...
were responsible for losing humankind". His
work is a condemnation of what, until then,
had been regarded as civilization and the
heralding of a fresh start which would
preserve the goodness of the natural man in
a new stage of development. The course of
history being what it was, this new start was
to be nothing other than the great bourgeois
revolution of 1789.
The Europeans' rather hazy perception of
the peoples they encountered on their arrival
in the Caribbean was to be used from
More (in whose Utopia slavery still exists)
right through to Rousseau to defend the
notion of the original goodness of the
human being, which had been corrupted by
society as Europeans knew it, and to form
the theoretical basis of a new society. At the
same time another very different view of the
indigenous peoples of the Caribbean was
evolving, at first in parallel with the
Rousseauist view, but then diverging from it
and transcending the context of the Carib¬
bean and even the Americas as a whole.
This view, like the first, originated with Col¬
umbus who, when translating into a Euro¬
pean language what he heard the in¬
digenous people say in a language (Taino)
he did not know, mentioned the existence of
Caribs, whom he also called Cambas "the
people of the Great Can" (The Great
Khan it should not be forgotten that, on
his first voyage, Columbus thought that he
had arrived in Asia) and cannibals, very
fierce peoples who were said to eat human
flesh.
Whereas the other inhabitant of the An¬
tilles was the conjectural "noble savage",
this one was the no less conjectural "ignoble
savage", regarding whom the most deter¬
mined opponent of Las Casas, Ginés de
Sepúlveda, resuscitating Artistotle's thesis
of the natural-born slave, wrote: "The
Spanish are perfectly right to exercise their
dominion over these barbarians... who are
so inferior to the Spanish in moderation, in¬
telligence and all manner of virtue and
human sentiments that they are as children
to adults, women to men, the cruel and in¬
humane to the exceedingly meek, the exag¬
geratedly intemperate to the continent and
moderate, in short, I was about to say as
monkeys to men".
This "ignoble savage" was to be given a
literary incarnation as Caliban in
Shakespeare's play The Tempest.
Shakespeare's Caliban/Carib/cannibal is a
misshapen monster imitating man, a
creature whom the European enchanter.
Prospero, has robbed of his island home and
has taught to speak his (Prospero's)
language and who owes his survival to the
fact that his labours are essential to his
master. Perhaps never before or since has a
major literary work shown the frightening
reality of colonialism in so clear a light.
The cannibal/Caliban is the hypothetical
creation of the right wing of the nascent
Western bourgeoisie which spread its ex¬
ploiting Prósperos and exploited Calibans all
over the earth. And here it must be recalled
that while the basis for Rousseau's
hypothesis of the "noble savage" was
sought in the examples of the aborigines of
the Antilles and Black Africans, the sub¬
stantive cannibal, in the sense of a bestial
man-eater, was to be applied not only to the
Caribs whatever the etymology is
worth but above all to the caricatures of
Africans with which people throughout the
world became familiar through the seeming¬
ly innocuous Tarzan films.
It was the sad destiny of the first in¬
habitants of our region to have inspired ad¬
mirably evocative verses and celebrated
works of art for the burgeoning European
bourgeoisie and yet to have failed to survive
the brutal impact of its "devastating civiliza¬
tion". Since they had been decimated and
since fresh Calibans were needed as labour,
millions of Africans were uprooted from
their great continent and were set down as
slaves in our region, and not a few Asians
subsequently suffered the same fate. The
Caribbean peoples of today were bom of the
still-continuing mix of the descendants of
European oppressors and African and Asian
oppressed. Only in this harsh light is it possi¬
ble to understand why the first country of
the Antilles to gain its independence and the
first to introduce a new social order have
both reclaimed their pre-Western heritage,
the painful heritage of the exterminated
Caliban who discovered and enriched the
places where we now live.
However, that heritage alone cannot ac¬
count for the cultural identity of the Carib¬
bean following the arrival of the Europeans.
The new Caribbean is one of the three main
areas forming what we call "our America".
These areas have been termed Indo-
America, Afro-America and Euro-America
and correspond on our sub-continent to
what the Brazilian anthropologist Darcy
Ribeiro has called pilot peoples, new
peoples and transplanted peoples.
What these peoples have in common is
that they were first colonized and then neo-
colonized, and were yoked, as exploited ter¬
ritory, to the world capitalist system. What
they also have in common are a large
number of features of widely differing
character, and this is why they form a
ï v
unit, r
ROBERTO FERNANDEZ RETAMAR, Cuban
poet and essayist, is a professor at Havana univer¬
sity and director of the magazine Casa de las
Americas. His essays and anthologies of his
poems have been translated into a number of
languages.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The logo of CANA, the independent news agency launched by the
English-speaking Caribbean countries in 1975, with Unesco support.
Unesco
and the Caribbean
Ranging from the introduction of educational innovations in
the Dominican Republic and co-operation with the Caribbean
News Agency (CANA) to support for scientific institutes for
biological research and the study and monitoring of marine oil
pollution in the region, Unesco's activities touch on almost all
aspects of life in the Caribbean.
In the field of education, Unesco, in co-operation with the
countries concerned, has launched a major regional project
whose main objectives are: the provision of eight to ten years'
schooling for all children in the region; the eradication of il¬
literacy and the development of adult education; the reform
and improvement in the general quality and efficiency of
educational systems. Adopted at an intergovernmental
regional meeting, held in Quito, Ecuador, in April 1981, these
objectives emphasize the political will of Member States
of the Caribbean region to initiate a process of economic
and social development centred on man and his all-round
education.
In the natural sciences, within the framework of its Man
and the Biosphere Programme, Unesco is involved in a major
project of research, training and demonstration aimed at in¬
tegrated management of humid tropical zones. Pilot projects
in Latin America and the Caribbean region are concerned with
land-use problems in humid tropical zones such as selective
land clearing, reafforestation and shifting cultivation, as well
as migration of mountain populations to the tropical
lowlands. In marine science the emphasis is on strengthening
scientific infrastructures in accordance with Member States'
requirements.
In the social sciences, studies are being carried out on en¬
dogenous socio-cultural factors in order to identify original
forms of development which would respond to regional re¬
quirements while respecting each country's cultural identity.
Unesco is also collaborating closely with a number of
organizations concerned with the development of the social
sciences in the region, particularly in the fields of research
and training.
Unesco is also undertaking a major research project on
cultural contacts in the Caribbean and their evolution.
Translations from and into Creole are being encouraged and
plans are in hand for production of a General History of the
Caribbean. In addition, the International Simón Bolívar Prize,
which honours persons or institutions that have made a
meritorious contribution to the freedom, independence and
dignity of peoples and to the strengthening of solidarity
among nations, is to be awarded for the first time on 24 July
1983, the bicentenary of the birth of the "Liberator".
But that unit does not imply uniformity or
monotony, nor does it absolve us from sing¬
ling out the characteristic specific to each
area.
Our area, which is sometimes called Afro-
America, is that situated around the Carib¬
bean forming the society based on the plan¬
tation system, whose rich human inputs of
African origin have had a decisive impact
on our culture and on our lives and were
later supplemented by a variety of Asian
contributions.
The history of the immediate past of the
modern Caribbean is therefore the history of
the sea which, at the dawn of capitalism,
witnessed the arrival of the European con¬
querors and saw them engage in quarrelling
and pillage. It was this sea that saw the
emergence, at the beginning of the nine¬
teenth century, of our first victorious revolu¬
tion, the formidable Haitian Revolution
which (before Spain and Russia) succeeded
in defeating Napoleon's troops, abolished
slavery and paved the way for the in¬
dependence of Latin America. At the end of
the century, that same sea was to witness
the first tangible movement, organized by
Marti, to stem modern imperialism, then in
its infancy, and, in this century, the triumph
of the Cuban revolution.
Our cultural identity must perforce refer
back to that turbulent historical environ¬
ment. It does this with a growing awareness
of how much we have in common, in spite
of having been (and in some cases still be¬
ing) subordinated to different metropolitan
powers and consequently speaking different
languages. We have experienced col¬
onialism, neo-colonialism, imperialism,
under-development and racism; feudal
estates, plantations ar.d one-crop
economies; slavery, Atlantic crossings and
the slave trade; landowners, overseers,
slaves and maroons; sugar cane, coffee and
bananas; the sugar mill, the plantation
house and the humble cabin.
Although the fruits of syncretism are not
always the same, they are at times very
similar to each other, as in the case of Hai¬
tian voodoo, Jamaican pocomania and
Cuban santería. And nothing, perhaps,
demonstrates more clearly our shared identi¬
ty than our wond-renowned music. That
"riotous innovation out of the Indies", as
Alejo Carpentier has fittingly put it, could be
heard from the very first years of the Con¬
quest and continues to live on today in
guarachas, rumbas, congas, sones, boleros,
mambos, cha-cha-chas, calypsos, reggae,
merengues, tamboritos, sambas, bossa
novas and salsas. Nor should we forget that
the slave culture of the plantations which
developed over the centuries also embraced
the south of what is today the United
States, where the meeting of Africa and
Europe gave birth to negro spirituals, the
blues and the powerful jazz that are the first
cousins of our own music.
We have, however, yet to assume our full
identity and we shall not do so until the last
traces of colonialism and neo-colonialism
have disappeared from the region. Only then
shall we be in a position to assert, through
the multiple roots that have contributed to
making us a world people, our role as an
essential meeting-place in the history of
mankind, a history in the making of which
we shall no longe'r be passive onlookers but
active protagonists. That process is already
under way.
H Roberto Fernández Retamar
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
José Martí
'Citizen of the Americas'
Self-portrait of José Marti (1853-1895).
ONE of the noblest, purest and most
profound figures of Latin American
history, José Julian Marti holds a
place of honour in the heroic avant-garde
alongside Bolivar and San Martin, Hidalgo
and Morelos, Sucre and Toussaint Louver¬
ture, fathers of the independence of their
peoples and illustrious and tireless com¬
batants in the struggle against colonial
domination.
Marti was born in Havana on 28 January
1853. The son of an honest junior official of
the Spanish government in Cuba, his life as a
child was burdened by necessity and a round
of wearying tasks. The daily spectacle of ar¬
bitrary actions and corruption turned him in¬
to a non-conformist and a rebel before he
had reached adolescence, and on the
publication of his dramatic work Abdala,
which is filled with patriotic fervour and
desire for liberty, the Spanish authorities of
the island brought him to trial for
"disloyalty", and condemned him to hard
labour at the early age of sixteen. In view of
the poor state of his health, his prison
sentence was commuted to confinement on
the island of Pinos, and, in 1871, to exile in
Spain.
From this time on, his life became an
anguished, impulsive pilgrimage in Europe
and America, and although this wandering
existence meant enduring the sufferings of
the expatriate, it enabled him to develop
solid, comprehensive political criteria and a
broad culture. In Spain, Marti was able to ac¬
quire, at first hand, an insight into the cor¬
rupt regime governing Cuba, but he never
theless came to appreciate (and this is a
tribute to his breadth of spirit) the very real
virtues of the people of the peninsula, and he
seized this opportunity to re-examine his
language at its source. From Spain, he went
to Mexico where he plunged into a life of in¬
tense activity as a lecturer and journalist. His
contact with the Mexico of this period led to
a lasting commitment to the problems of
Latin America problems to which he subse¬
quently devoted the major part of his
political and cultural activity.
Marti returned to Cuba in time for the sign¬
ing of the Peace of Zanjón, in 1879, after the
first war of independence, and, while there,
expressed in articles and brilliant speeches
his conviction that the freedom of Cuba
could only be obtained through armed ac¬
tion. Condemned once more to exile, he left
for Spain, moved on to Paris, and then, in
1880, he arrived in New York where he was to
spend the next fourteen years of his life.
Upon his arrival in the United States, Marti
resolved to devote himself body and soul to
the liberation of Cuba. In the process he was
obliged to smooth over the differences and
disputes between the surviving leaders,
determine the ways in which the groups of
Cuban emigrants could best contribute,
outline the character, and the short- and
long-term consequences of the armed strug¬
gle which was being prepared, and convince
everyone concerned that a war of liberation
was both opportune and worthwhile. As a
result he gained the total trust of his com¬
patriots and became the unquestioned
leader of the fight for the emancipation of
his country.
In 1891 Marti founded the Cuban Revolu¬
tionary Party, the fundamental instrument of
the armed movement then beir.j prepared.
From this moment up to the outbreak of the
revolution in 1895 his life was one of con¬
tinuous, frenetic activity, an incessant round
of travel across North America, and also into
Latin America. In agreement with the Cuban
separatist leaders, the Dominican-born Máx¬
imo Gómez and Antonio Maceo, Martí decid¬
ed to begin operations. On the very eve of
the combat he wrote and signed with Gómez
the Manifesto of Montecristi a fundamen¬
tal document which laid down the nature
and the objectives of the revolution.
On 11 April 1895 Marti disembarked in
Cuba and joined the insurgent troops as a
simple soldier. On 19 May a Spanish bullet
put an end to his life in Dos Ríos, in eastern
Cuba.
When he set out for Cuba, knowing that he
was going to give his life for liberty, the
revolutionary leader left in New York a vast
and varied corpus of work which, once col¬
lated, filled twenty-seven large volumes.
These demonstrate clearly that the austere
duty of the revolutionary in no way in¬
terfered with his vocation as a writer.
Although his books of poems (Ismaelillo,
Versos Libres, Versos Sencillos and Flores de
Exilio), in which he expresses his preoccupa¬
tions and premonitions as a man and as a
revulutionary, are distinguished for their
contribution to modernism, it was un¬
doubtedly in journalism that he excelled. His
famous chronicles, published in many coun¬
tries of the continent, provided a universally
accepted source of information for the
peoples of Latin America.
The author of incomparable biographies
(Emerson, Whitman, Thoreau, Longfellow),
diaries, and a correspondence of outstan¬
ding merit, a literary and art critic noted for
his shrewd perceptiveness, he never allowed
his passion for Latin America to desert him
for a single instant. His preoccupation with
the present and the future of the Hispanic
peoples of the hemisphere absorbed him
completely, and it is totally appropriate that
the "Apostle" of the Cubans should also
have been dubbed the "Citizen of the
Americas".
His action was concentrated, to begin
with, in his own country and in the West In¬
dies, of which he wrote in 1894: "The Antilles
are at the focal point of the Americas;
enslaved, they will become no more than a
floating base in the war of an imperial
republic against a jealous and superior world
which is already preparing to negate its
power... if free, they will be a guarantee of
the equilibrium and of the independence,
still under threat, of Latin America, and of
the honour of the Great Republic of the
North, which in thé development of its ter¬
ritory... will find much surer greatness than
in the ignoble conquest of its smaller
neighbours."
But as the poet and essayist Roberto
Fernández Retamar has written: "What in¬
terested Marti in an immediate sense was
Cuba... and in a larger framework the
American continent south of the River
Bravo 'our mestizo America'. While there is
a constant allusion to this idea throughout
his work, it appears with greatest clarity in
his fundamental text Nuestra America, a
document which constitutes a veritable
Magna Carta. In it he affirms the full
originality of these lands. And this affirma¬
tion is of capital importance because it is the
foundation stone of Marti's vision of the
world. This affirmation, this confidence and
this challenge constitute the point of depar¬
ture for everything else in his thought.
77?/s sketch of José Marti is largely based on a
longer, more detailed study by the Cuban essayist
Juan Marinello.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Marcus Garvey
and the African
dream
by Kenneth Ramchand
IN the first half of the twentieth century there
sprang up in the Caribbean and in North
America a number of movements in which
people of African origin turned for support to that
heritage and root. Their labour had sustained
economies, and the right to belong had been
dearly bought, but New World Negroes were not
at ease in the Western societies to which their
ancestors had been shipped. Emancipation, they
were told, had come; but for the mass of Negroes
it seemed long gone. The conditions under which
they lived as supposedly free men were at least as
demoralizing, especially after the First World
War, as those their chained ancestors had
endured.
At no time in the history of the world, for the
last five hundred years, was there ever a serious
attempt made to free Negroes. We have been
camouflaged into believing that we were made
free by Abraham Lincoln, that we were made free
by Victoria of England, but up to now we are still
slaves, we are industrial slaves, we are social
slaves, we are politicalslaves, and the New Negro
desires a freedom that has no boundary, no
limit. "
(The Philosophy and Opinions
of Marcus Garvey)
Of the movements that arose to bring emo¬
tional sustainment and practical support to the
victims of this depressing scene, the most spec¬
tacular was that surrounding the Jamaican Mar¬
cus Mosiah Garvey, founder of the Universal
Negro Improvement Association. Born a colonial
on August 17, 1877 Garvey died an obscure exile
in the British metropolis in 1940. Between these
two dates, Garvey rose to fantastic eminence
among Negroes in America. He was the Black
Moses, the spiritual leader sent to lead his people
out of bondage; he was also the maker of the
political kingdom. His Excellency the Provisional
President of Africa.
"/ asked: 'Where is the black man's Govern¬
ment? Where is his King and his kingdom? Where
is his President, his country, and his ambassador,
his army, his navy, his men of big affairs?' I could
KENNETH RAMCHAND, of Trinidad and
Tobago, is Reader in West Indian Literature at the
University of the West Indies. Among his publish¬
ed works are West Indian Narrative, The West In¬
dian Novel and its Background, West Indian
Poetry and An Introduction to the Study of West
Indian Literature.
not find them, and then I declared: 7 will help to
make them. ..' I saw before me then, even as I do
now, a new world of black men, not peons, sen's,
dogs and slaves, but a nation ofsturdy men, mak¬
ing their impress upon civilization and causing a
new light to dawn upon the human race. "
(The Philosophy and Opinions
of Marcus Garvey)
At its height in the mid-1920s, Garvey's
Association is estimated to have numbered bet¬
ween four and six million, with branches,
members, or supporters in all the countries where
there were people of African origin.
Garvey envisaged a day in the future when all
Negroes would have returned to a united and in¬
dependent Africa. In the meantime, however.
New World Negroes could contribute to the cre¬
ation of a free Africa to which they could look for
protection as they journeyed in the world, and to
which they could return if necessary; "a nation of
our own, strong enough to lend protection to the
members of our race scattered all over the world,
and to compel the respect of the nations and
races of the earth". In their adopted countries, at
the same time, they could organize themselves
"for the absolute purpose of bettering our condi¬
tion, industrially, commercially, socially, religious¬
ly and politically."
However, as a result of mismanagement, in¬
competence, greed and corruption among his
lieutenants, most of Garvey's economic projects
foundered like the broken-down ships he was sold
by white owners at black market prices for his
Black Star Shipping Line which he intended to be
the foundation of Negro trade and the symbol of
repatriation.
His educational aims were more nearly suc¬
cessful, but not as he originally intended. After
founding the Universal Negro Improvement
Association in Jamaica in 1914, Garvey proposed
the establishment of colleges for Jamaican
Negroes on the model of Booker T. Washington's
Tuskagee Institute. It was in order to consult with
Washington himself on this project that Garvey
planned the 1 91 6 visit to America which led to the
shifting of the base of his operations to the United
States. His enduring educational enterprise,
however, was the founding of the weekly 777e
Negro World, which ran from 1918 to 1933. In its
pages, Garveyism was expounded in detail, and
readers were educated in the glories of African
history and the heroism of Negro revolts, and the
comparative savagery of European peoples.
"When Europe was inhabited by a race of can¬
nibals, a race of savages, hated men, heathens
and pagans, Africa was peopled with a race of
cultured black men, who were masters in art,
science and literature; men who were cultured
and refined; men who, it was said, were like the
gods. "
(The Philosophy and Opinions
of Marcus Garvey)
There were inconsistencies and confusions in
Garvey's thinking and in his actions, and it would
be easy to use these to condemn him as an ex¬
tremist and a crackpot, as many Negro intellec¬
tuals did at the time. His island antagonism
towards the brown and light-skinned class of
Jamaica was transferred to the Negro intelligent¬
sia, whom he invariably saw as lackeys of White
America.
He co-operated for a time with the Ku Klux
Klan because he shared with them the wish for
racial purity and the emigration of the Negro from
the United States. Always rash and undiplomatic,
Garvey skirmished with authority many times until
at last they did for him, convicting him on a flimsy
and put-up charge of using the U.S. mail to
defraud investors in the Black Star Shipping Line.
Garvey was deported from the U.S. in 1928 and
returned to Jamaica where his brown and light-
skinned antagonists were waiting. Humiliated at
home, the failing prophet went into exile in
England where he died a beaten and disillusioned
man.
In 1964 Garvey's body was disinterred from its
London tomb and returned to Jamaican soil.
Several years later he was officially proclaimed a
National Hero. Even before this, both his contem¬
poraries and those who never experienced his
movement had begun to separate the follies and
foibles of this vain, egotistical and insecure man
from his enduring achievements.
Those elements in his philosophy or opinions
that were sound were not new, many of them
having been put forward by Negro intellectuals or
men of letters of some of whom Garvey had
probably never heard. Yet this skilful orator,
showman and propagandist extraordinaire com¬
municated with ordinary Negroes and touched
their hurts as no one had done before. Nobody
before Garvey had been able to organize a mass
movement of such size and enthusiasm from the
vast Negro proletariat. Nobody had so stirred
their imagination. "I shall teach the black man to
see beauty in himself." Nobody had given them
such self-esteem.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Reggae music exploded into existence among the urban poor
of Jamaica in the early 1960s and rapidly won an international
following, especially among young people. The drums and
guitars of Reggae masters beat out pulsating sounds which are a
synthesis of African and Afro-American rhythms, accompanying
lyrics which draw not only on contemporary events and the
timeless themes of passion, but also on harrowing folk
memories :
When I remember the crack of the whip
My blood runs cold
I remember the slave ship
When they brutalized my very soul.
The roots of Reggae no one knows for certain where the word
comes from run deep into the past of Jamaica where, as
elsewhere in the Caribbean, slaves kept alive the rhythms, songs
and dances of Africa.
Reggae:
a Jamaican musical phenomenon
by Sebastian Clarke
Text © Copyright
Reproduction prohibited
THE first batch of Africans shipped by
the Europeans to the so-called "New
World" arrived in Jamaica in 1509.
Although the Spaniards reaped great
economic benefit from the island, they did
not fully exploit it. It was not until 1655
when invading forces sent by Oliver
Cromwell arrived to make a systematic at¬
tempt to wrest "all the vast territories held
by Spain in the Caribbean", that the
economic transformation of the island was
completely undertaken. The British found
the island underpopulated and under¬
developed. Jamaica was thus easily con¬
quered by the British from the Spanish with
the aid of Africans.
Although the Africans were indeed
enslaved, their will for resistance and
rebellion was not broken. Thus rebellions
characterized the history of Jamaica. Slaves
who escaped ran to the hills and established
the type of social, cultural, political and
religious systems that they were accustom¬
ed to in Africa. These runaway slaves were
known as Maroons.
They fought against the British and
created havoc and fear in the minds and on
the properties of the slave-masters. Thus
the British, failing to make meaningful in¬
roads in destroying the Maroons, despite
the presence of great numbers of British
military officers, finally pacified them, sign¬
ing peace treaties with them and granting
them the right to stay on their lands.
By the end of the eighteenth century the
Maroons were finally broken as a dissident
and united opposition force. The Africans,
however, in spite of the abject condition of
slavery, still retained large elements of their
SEBASTIAN CLARKE, Trinidad-born writer and
journalist, has written widely on the modern
Caribbean arts. He is the editor of New Planet, an
anthology of modern Caribbean writing (1979)
and the author of Jah Music, published by
Heinemann in 1980. He is currently working on a
biography of Bob Marley.
cultural history. They evolved means of
communication through the invention of
patois, a combination of English and African
languages but phpnetically spoken within
the context of African languages. They sang
songs about their conditions, played games
on special occasions such as Christmas,
beat their drums, dressed up in elaborate
African-derived costumes, and danced.
Many of their forms of religious worship
remained unchanged. This was due to the
fact that the orthodox religious denomina¬
tions had no real interest in converting
Africans. The priests conducted baptisms
en masse, and for money. However, the set¬
ting up of the Ethiopian Baptist Church
under George Liele, an Afro-American
preacher and a former slave, created a great
deal of interest for Africans because the
manner of worship was similar to their own
and the offer of redemption and salvation
was a way out of slavery after death.
In the 1860s there was a great religious
revival in Jamaica, and it was centered in the
parish of St. Thomas where George William
Gordon, a coloured Baptist preacher and a
member of the local council, along with Paul
and Moses Bogle, played a great role. Not
only did they help to rekindle the flame of
religion, but they^also stood for justice for
the poor. This led directly to what is now
known as the Morant Bay Rebellion of 1865.
To suppress this protest against the treat¬
ment of the poor, the might of the British
militia was invoked, and both Gordon and
Paul Bogle were killed. It is important to
recognize the significance of this event in
the lives of the people from this area,
because it was from this parish that
Rastafari, both as a religious and political
' phenomenon, later originated. The Rastafari
movement takes its name from Ras Tafari,
as the Emperor Haile Selassie of Ethiopia
was known before he was crowned in 1930.
The history of Rastafari is inseparable
from that of Marcus Garvey, who was born
in the parish of St. Ann's and very early
demonstrated an interest in bettering the
conditions of the poor (see opposite page).
After moving to the United States in 1916
Garvey built a formidable organizational
base from which he attempted to tackle the
problems of black people, not only in the
United States, but world-wide.
When the American government in an at¬
tempt to stem his influence engineered
jealousy and dissension in his movement
and had him jailed and then deported for
fraud, Garvey rebuilt his movement in
Jamaica and at one of his conventions was
supposed to have said to his followers,
"Look to Africa where a black king shall be
crowned, for the day of deliverance is near".
People consulted their Bibles for confir¬
mation and found it in relation to passages
mentioning Ethiopia and the breaking of the
seven seals, and especially to "the Lion of
Judàh, the Root of David...", etc. When
Ras Tafari (Selassie) was crowned in 1930
he revived the titles of old, "The Conquering
Lion from the tribe of Judah, King of Kings,
Lord of Lords", etc. But even before the
coronation of Haile Selassie, the concept of
Ethiopianism had contributed greatly to af¬
firming in the minds of black people that
although the European attempted
desperately to project that Africans were
savages before the coming of the European,
and that they had made no contribution to
world culture and civilization, this was a
falsification of history. This affirmation took
the form of rejecting the Bible as a weapon
devised by the European to keep blacks in
mental bondage and of insisting that blacks
ought to create new religious systems from
that, of ancestral Africa. Not surprisingly, a
great deal of literature was written, and peo¬
ple sought it out. This expanded the debate
on African culture and gave indications that
black people were prepared to govern their
own lives.
The coronation of Selassie set the seal on
the acceptance of a new religious faith. Early
pioneers of this faith were Leonard
CONTINUED ON PAGE 46 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
>fR
KaVI . -. "
El
^H
Photo Jacques Pavlovsky © Sygma, Paris
Reggae is a Jamaican musical phenomenon
whose emergence parallels that of other
popular musical forms such as Soul and
Rock and Roll. Reggae music was the
creation of the special genius of the urban
poor, the "sufferers" of Jamaica's capital,
Kingston. Drawing on the spiritual
resources of the sufferers, it has a
stridency and an incantative magic that has
captured the minds and bodies of people all
over the world, for Reggae has become a
truly international phenomenon. Above,
Reggae's most renowned exponent, the
late Bob Marley, accompanied by the
l-Threes group, during a concert given at Le
Bourget, France, in July 1980, which
attracted an audience of many thousands
of Reggae fans.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
^Jf J I - IB E
^ ^ > \ "
ft
&k A.
** r
i
- *\\ **B^b ' JH
" ^
A
K| b
l M m i <J
^ lafcÜL. TrtÉl
L *?
^m^^^
The music is an important force within the lives of the black community, whether living in Jamaica (above) the Americas or Europe.,
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 43
P. Howell, Joseph Nathaniel Hibbert and
H. Archibald Dunkley. In varying degrees
they felt the wrath of official society. They
were harassed, hounded down, locked up,
physically attacked, and their locks, the long
plait-like strands they sometimes wore,
shaved off their heads. In the early days of
Rastafari, the philosophical input was not
confined solely to Jamaica. Black church¬
men from Afro-America, South Africa, An¬
tigua and Jamaica itself, took the concept of
Ethiopianism and Garvey's philosophy, and
wrote important documents that con¬
tributed meaningfully to the articulation of
Rastafari.
In its philosophy Rastafari was in the main
anti-colonialism and an affirmation of
African cultural and social history. It offered
both religious and political alternatives and it
was based on the focal point of Africa, Haile
Selassie as a man of divinity because of his
ancestral connexion with the King Solomon-
Queen of Sheba union and the long un¬
broken line of kings since then. Whether or
not Selassie was a despot is insignificant to
the movement that his acceptance, has
created in the psyches of the people. It is
revolutionary because it overturns the no¬
tion of white kings and queens and the cen¬
tral focus on Europe.
In this quest for cultural authenticity, it
would have been contradictory for
Rastafarians to be singing European-created
songs in the context of European music.
They thus fashioned their own songs, adap¬
ting the psalms from the Bible, as well as
creating new religious songs out of their
own religious experience. The Burru people,
descendants of the Ashanti of Ghana, were
one such people in Jamaica who survived
with their drumming intact. Rastafarians
gave the Burru their new religion and ac¬
cepted the Burrus' African drumming in ex¬
change. All this occurred in the slums of
West Kingston which were a refuge for the
poor and outcast.
In the 1940s Afro-American music was
popular with Jamaicans. This phenomenon
continued in the 1950s with Rhythm and
Blues (R & B) and Boogie Woogie (an
outgrowth of musical styles born out of
similar deprivation to that known by
Jamaicans, and sharing a similar ancestral
base Africa). The music was played on
sound systems (modern-day discos) as well
as on the radio. People also had short-wave
radio that could pick up radio stations in the
American South (Jamaica is about 160
kilometres from Miami).
Young singers like Owen Grey, Winston
Jackie Edwards, Laurel Aitken and Alton
Ellis used to imitate the styles of the Afro-
American music. The dominant element in
Boogie Woogie was the rhythmic impres¬
sion of the piano. It played a specific
rhythmic style that Jamaican musicians lik¬
ed. And when, in the early 1960s, Afro-
American R & B was being superseded by
Rock and Roll, Jamaicans could not feel any
great emotional attachment.
Thus they retained the element of the
piano rhythm and began to devise new ideas
to blend with it. Firstly they continued in the
R & B idiom, then they moved gradually
towards creating their own music. This oc¬
curred around 1962, significantly, the year in
which Jamaica achieved its independence.
The musicians, because they came from
the urban poor from whom the philosophy
of Rastafari issued, were obviously political¬
ly and culturally aware. Thus compositions
were sometimes titled after events that were
occurring both in Jamaican society and in
the world. "Independence Ska", for exam¬
ple, was composed by the Skatalites, the
foremost Jamaican musical backing band.
As early as 1958, Rastafarian music, i.e.
drumming, was placed on a popular record
by the Folkes Brothers, "Oh Carolina" (an
old Afro-American tune). The record was
produced by the legendary Jamaican artist
Prince Buster who imitated the sound of a
saxophone with his mouth because he could
not have afforded the use of a real sax¬
ophone, and the drumming was immortaliz¬
ed by the late Count Ossie, the man most
responsible for the popularity of this sound.
After Jamaica received its independence,
opportunities for local Jamaicans to control
power and reap financial rewards were
greater than before. Political rivalry was
already part and parcel of the Jamaican
political scene. In the 1960s and 1970s, this
escalated, drawing in the urban poor whose
singer/sufferers expressed the nature of
their social environment in songs.
Popular Jamaican music has a genetic
connexion with other Caribbean music. In
the 1950s the most popular indigenous
music was Mento, which was a combination
of calypso and musical rhythm from the
Spanish-speaking Caribbean. In the late
1970s and the 1980s, Jamaican music has
shown proclivities for calypso. The latter
provides the rhythmic ingredient which is
expressed by the local Jamaican musicians
as a fusion with Reggae. But what is impor¬
tant is that the themes of calypso have
directly influenced the lyrics of the Jamaican
singer. The themes of Trinidadian calypsos
have in fact been reworked and transposed
into the Jamaican cultural context, in now-
popular Reggae songs.
Today therefore, as in the beginning,
Reggae music is not limited to one musical
concept or to one thematic preoccupation.
There are songs that speak of love, death,
destruction, war and other topical subjects.
The music is, though, inextricably linked
with the struggle for political liberation for
black people globally. And when the music
speaks of liberation it is not speaking simply
of colour limitations.
The music has been accepted by black
people living all over the world as their own
music. Thus black people in Europe, for ex¬
ample, are making significant contributions
to its development. They are adding new in¬
strumental ideas to give the music colour
and are welding their experience of other
music, particularly Afro-American Soul and
Jazz, to give a new dimension to Reggae.
The music is obviously an important force
within the lives of the black community,
whether living in Jamaica, the Americas or
Europe. In the latter situation it has given
strength and resolve to those experiencing
the harshness of European racism and pre¬
judice and has forced them to resist these
experiences.
Stylistically, Jamaican music is changing
every day. New styles of drum and bass
combinations (the foundation of the music)
are coming into play, and different ways of
communicating a song have become a
characteristic of the Jamaican or black
singer. Undoubtedly the late Bob Marley
contributed largely to the world acceptance
of Reggae, without compromising his
political vision, but the music itself
transcends Bob Marley and expresses the
deep spiritual resources, wishes and aspira¬
tions of the black world for eventual
freedom and justice. As long as suffering is
the norm of the black experience. Reggae
will be relevant to the human condition.
I Sebastian Clarke
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1981
January
THE HANDICAPPED TENTH OF HUMANITY (F. Mayor). International Year of Disabl¬
ed Persons (A.-M. M'Bow). U.N. Declaration of Rights of the Disabled. The courage to
take risks (E.V. Roberts). Seeing with my hands (O.I. Skorokhodova). The handicap of
prejudice (P.O. Mba). 'I am so afraid they will laugh at me' (B. Lundahl). Unesco Braille
Courier (F.H. Potter). 4 pages in Braille. Louis Braille (S. Guillemet). Unesco' and the
disabled (N.-l. Sundberg). Disability and the developing world (N. Acton). A future for
every blind child (P. Posmowski). Art treasures: Stricken doe (Bulgaria).
February
TOURISM AND CULTURAL TRADITIONS (A. Bouhdiba). Passport to development?
(E. de Kadt). The Water Decade (1981-1990). Emperor Qin's bronze chariots (Photos).
Brazil's Museum of the Unconscious (F. de Camargo e Almeida). High-speed language
learning (M. Vaisburd). Resurgence of sail (A. Gillette). Art treasures: Carved crucifixion
(Iceland).
March
SCIENCE IN THE SERVICE OF ART (M. Hours). Lascaux: Saving a sanctuary of
prehistoric art. Zapotee statue. X-ray microfluorescence and a Merovingian treasure. An¬
cient metallurgy. Anatomy of a harp. Nuclear dating techniques (B. Keisch). Gallery of
fakes (S.J. Fleming). Principles of conservation (B.M. Feilden). Holography (I.G. Yav-
tushenko and V.B. Markov). Art treasures: Baal the storm god (Lebanon).
April
MAN AND THE BIOSPHERE (A.-M. M'Bow). The genesis of ecology (F. di Castri).
Tropical forests (F. Golley^nd M. Hadley). Taming of a swamp. Nature's chemical fac¬
tory. The changing forest. Marginal lands (M. Ayyad and G. Glaser). Holding the desert at
bay. Mountain scenarios. Cities in crisis (V. Giacomini). The ecology of megalopolis (S.
Boyden and J. Celecia). Conservation for development (W. Lusigi and J. Robertson).
Biosphere reserves in the USSR (V. Sokolov and P. Gounin). Poachers turned
gamekeepers. Getting the message across (J. Damlamian). Perspectives and prospects
(R. Slatyer). Art treasures: The bird-man (Chile).
May
BULGARIA: A modern nation salutes its past (M. Stancheva): 1. 'It grows but does not
grow old'; 2. 5,000 years of town-planning; 3. A tale of three cities; 4. From St. Cyril to
the National Revival. The plight of Africa's 5 million refugees (M.-L. Zollner). Science,
pseudo-science and racism (A. Jacquard). The man who vanquished yellow fever (P.M.
Pruna and R.O. Pedraza). St. Benedict of Nursia (G. Penco). Art treasures: Shamanistic
idol (Dominican Republic).
June
NEW WAYS TO LEARNING. SOS parents ILF. Buscaglia). An African approach (G.-J.
Nlo). Their handicap is hunger. Childhood awakening (M. Thorburn). Unesco and special
education. Special schools or integrated education? 1. 'The integration of the handicap
ped can best be prepared in special schools' (V.l. Lubovski); 2. 'Our task is to bring the
retarded into the community' (M. Söder). The rights of mentally retarded persons. Com¬
munities that care (M. Boucebci). Sounds from silence (Li Hongtaiand Shen Jiayin). Self-
reliance and the right to work (E. Sackstein). Disabled characters in search of an author
(T. Orjasaeter). Art treasures: Pre-Aksumite portrait (Ethiopia).
July
ENERGY 2000. Meeting the energy challenge (A.-M. M'Bow). Transition to a new energy
mix (E.V. Iglesias). Profiles of change (W. Sassin). Implications of a sustainable energy
system. The developing world and solar energy (A.M. Dioffo). World energy file (Z. Zaric).
Training and information (J.F. McDivitt). Unifying the fundamental forms of energy (A.
Salam). Costs and constraints (B.M. Berkovsky). Solar power for the Sahel. Brazil's green
gasoline (B. Silva). Biogas in India (T.K. Moulik). Art treasures: Sun-worshipper (India).
A ugust- September
ISLAM: 15TH CENTURY OF THE HEGIRA. The message of Islam (A.M. M'Bow).
Messenger of God (M. Hamidullah). A universal mission (H. Chatty). Ibn Battuta. Muslims
of the Soviet Union (Z. Babakhan). Renewal and reform in Indonesia (S.B. Baried). The
impact on black Africa (S.S. Nyang). Ethics of learning (M.A. Sinaceur). The Hegira
(H.M. Said). The scientific achievement of early Islam (A.-R. Kaddoural. Ummat ul-llm,
towards a commonwealth of science (A. Salam). Dynamic of Islamic thought (A.M. Me¬
ziane). The eye of the heart (Rahmatullah). A new architecture rooted in tradition (D.
Kuban). Art treasures: Al-Azhar mosque (Egypt).
October
THE LEAST DEVELOPED COUNTRIES (H. Lopès and H.C. Tri). The poorest countries
in an oil-rich region (M.S. Al-Attar). Tropic islands in search of a future (J. Brito). Dossier
on the 31 least developed countries. African youth between tradition and modernity
(B. Ly). Art treasures: Rattle with a human face (Panama).
November
ATATÜRK: FATHER OF MODERN TURKEY. Mustafa Kemal Atatürk (B. Tanör). The
Sultan silenced by the people's voice (C. Altan). Women and avant-garde literature (G.
Dino). The warriors of Riace (V. Abella). Teilhard de Chardin, philosopher, palaeontologist
and theologian: 1. François Russo; 2. Yves Coppens. Art treasures: Terra-cotta twosome
(Turkey).
December
CARIBBEAN ENCOUNTER (A. Carpentier). Slavery and sugar... the bitter aftertaste
(M. Moreno Fraginals). Toussaint Louverture. Simón Bolivar. Crucible of change
(R. Depestre). The West Indies from within (M. Patrick Jones). Fernando Ortiz (L. Otero).
Creative contradictions (E. Glissant). Caliban's revenge (R. Fernandez Retamar). José
Martí. Marcus Garvey and the African dream (K. Ramchand). Reggae (S. Clarke). Art
treasures: Seat of honour (Haiti).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
- BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. - CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing - CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch¬
bishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. - Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. -
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1.
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaa-
rankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GER¬
MAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140,
710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier
(German, English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag.
Germering/München. For scientific maps only: Geo Center,
Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street.
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong-Kong Government Information Services, Publications
Centre, GPO Building, Connaught Place. - HUNGARY.
Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V.
Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkozíársaság utja 16, Budapest VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsäon & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcut¬
ta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali
Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub¬
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 51 1 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street,
Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rasjiid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL.
A. B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366. 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon
3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. -
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait -
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.,
P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. -
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop.
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. - MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V.,
Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS AN¬
TILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Of¬
fice, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. - NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
- PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac
Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przed-
miescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & An¬
drade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. -
SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box
131, Mahé. - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University
and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New In¬
dustrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir
Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. -
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hov-
bokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Fórbundet, Skolgränd 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11. CCP. 12-236. - TAN¬
ZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dares-Salaam.
- THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung
Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I.," and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovénie, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
West Indian
pageant
]]>
</page>
</document>
