<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074708eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
DECEMBER 1983-6 French francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
© LAO PEOPLE'S DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC River harvest
Wet-rice farming in the lowlands, where more than half the population is concentrated, and shifting dry-rice
cultivation in the hills, are the main sources of food for the Lao people. Almost every household also raises
livestock and poultry and hunting and fishing provide a supplement to the family diet. Above, a Lao fisher-
girl in the Ventiane region.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
DECEMBER 1983 36th YEAR
Published in 27 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs; 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 12-1 983 - OPI 83-1 - 495 A
pages
I. CIVILIZATIONS OF THE SEA
4 The Phoenicians, master mariners of antiquity
by Mhamed Fantar
8 How Arab sailors read the stars
by Régis Moretón
10 The Viking saga
by Magnus Magnusson
14 Coastal and island civilizations of Africa
by Ibrahima Baba Kaké
14 Songs of the pirogue
by Francis M'Boulé
17 Equatorial Guinea: a nation moulded by the sea
by Catherine Gillard
18 The islands of Cape Verde
	by Elisa Andrade	
II. SPANNING THE OCEANS
20 From myth to reality
The rise of scientific map-making
by Vitorino M. Godinho
30 The dhow: queen of the Indian Ocean
by Cliff Hawkins
33 Pacific adventure
by Peter Gathercole
36 The Eskimos of Greenland
The guidelines of tradition
by Jean Malaurie
'The sea is our life'
by Gaba Broberg
38 The peopling of the Americas
	by Wigberto Jiménez Moreno	
III. WORLD OCEAN 2000
40 The new Law of the Sea
by Maria Eduarda Gonçalves
41 The Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission
43 Ocean watch
45 Where land meets sea
46 UNESCO NEWSROOM
A time to live...
LAO PEOPLE'S DEM. REP.: River harvest
/UST as the latest scientific
discoveries tend to confirm
that all life originally came
from the sea, so some of the more
startling developments in modern
technology seem to suggest that
the sea 's resources may be the key
to the-future of the Earth.
Between these two observa¬
tions, between the abyss of the
past and the dizzying possibilities
of the future, lies the history of
humanity, which is inseparable
from the story of the oceans. How
manifold, therefore, are the com¬
plexities that beset any attempt to
encompass and quantify such a
reality, how inexhaustible the
prospects ofstudy which it offers!
From thousands of possible
themes and angles, we have been
obliged to select a mere handful to
illustrate this issue on Civiliza¬
tions of the Sea.
Our investigation of the marine
environment focuses on the sea as
the cradle of civilizations, the sea
as a vector of cultural transmis¬
sion and exchange, and the sea as
an issue facing the world of the
twenty-first century. Instead ofat¬
tempting to present a panoramic
picture, a task which would in any
case have been impossible, we
have endeavoured to heighten our
readers' interest in and concern
for this fundamental element of
life on earth in a coverage which
ranges from the invention of the
humblest techniques to theflower¬
ing of the richest myths, from
harsh sufferings endured in
history to the routine of everyday
life in the modern world, from the
Eskimos to the Melanesians. We
have not tried to sum up the extent
of human knowledge about the
oceans but to show somefruits of
the impact which they have had on
our imagination.
Not surprisingly, this approach
has led us to examine some of the
"problem areas" of the ocean to¬
day: marine pollution, shores and
islands, the international law of
the sea, the sea as common
heritage of mankind.
Some of Unesco's fundamental
preoccupations lie in this area in
which it is striving to promote
scientific research and action in
the modern world.
Cover: A boom, a kind of large dhow,
under construction in a boatyard at al-
Dawha, capital of Qatar. Characteristic
features of these vessels, which are
found throughout the Arabian penin¬
sula and Iran, are a long sloping stem-
post and pointed poop.
Photo © Carlos Saldi, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The Phoenicians,
master mariners
of antiquity
by Mhamed Fantar
THE Phoenicians were a people of
ancient times who belonged to the
north-west Semitic family and
whose exact origins are a matter of
controversy.
Phoenicia covered an area correspon¬
ding to modern Lebanon plus certain
parts of present-day Syria and Israel. The
Phoenicians seem to have settled there
about 3000 BC.
Archaeologists have linked the Phoeni¬
cian world to the civilization of Canaan
(the name given in the Bible to Palestine
before the arrival of the Hebrews). This
ethnic substratum seems to have been
enriched and transformed by both ethnic
and cultural contributions due to inva¬
sions in about 1200 BC by the so-called
"people of the sea".
The persistence amongst the Phoeni¬
cians of the feeling that they belonged to
the land of Canaan has been cited in sup¬
port of this hypothesis. Indeed it is hard
to see to what other cultural stream the
Canaan of the Torah can be attributed.
Moreover, the "Punies" of the fifth cen¬
tury AD, to which Saint Augustine of
Hippo refers, also claimed to be
Canaanites.
There is also the linguistic argument
according to which the Greek word
phoinikes, from which "Phoenician" is
derived, is merely a translation of
"Canaan", both names recalling the pur¬
ple dye which was a typical product of
Phoenicia.
At all events, a new dominant factor
emerged with the Phoenicians the
sea to which they deliberately turned.
Whether it was the Mediterranean, the
Red Sea or elsewhere, it was the sea that
determined the destiny of the
Phoenicians.
They lived on the coast between the
Gulf of Issus to the north and Mount
Carmel to the south. Sidon, Tyre, Byblos
and Arwad were amongst their
prestigious City-States, each with its own
institutions, religion, ways and customs.
Phoenician maritime supremacy ap¬
pears to have begun at the same time as
the Iron Age (about 1200 BC). This
hypothesis seems to be supported by
Graeco-Latin writings, Scripture, and
MHAMED FANTAR, of Tunisia, is director of
the Tunisian National Institute of Archaeology
and Art and professor of archaeology at the
University of Tunis. A specialist in Phoenician
archaeology and epigraphy, he has published
numerous books andstudies on Carthage and the
Phoenicians including Carthage, la Prestigieuse
Cité d'Elissa.
archaeological data. If ancient
historiography is to be believed, Utica,
Lixus in North Africa and Gadès in Spain
originated between the end of the second
millennium and the tenth century BC, in
other words, at a time when ancient
Greece was coming into existence, and
Phoenician sailors brought to the Greeks
of the islands much of what they may
have needed in the way of material
culture and new ideas.
It would be very useful to have an in
ventory of all the documentary evidence
regarding these contacts which the
Phoenicians maintained with the Greeks
from an early stage of their maritime
supremacy, but unfortunately, because
of the "phoenicophobia" which prevail¬
ed during the nineteenth and first half of
the present century, this evidence has
been played down. Nevertheless there is
nothing to prevent our having recourse to
these documents and objectively putting
them to good use in the interests of
historical accuracy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Numerous classical documents, dating
from various periods, testify to the
maritime greatness of the Phoenicians.
Apart from the allusions to them in
Homer's Odyssey, there is the account by
Herodotus of the voyage which the
Phoenician fleet made on the instructions
of the Pharaoh Nechao II of Egypt (who
died in 594 BC). It sailed along the east
coast of Africa, rounded the Cape of
Good Hope and passed northwards
through the Atlantic Ocean to reach the
Mediterranean and return to Egypt. This
outstanding exploit is considered to be
one of the best proofs of Phoenician
mastery of the seas.
Their ships braved Scylla and Charyb-
dis in the Straits of Messina, and plough¬
ed their way through the open sea to
reach the southern coast of the Iberian
peninsula, where contemporary
historians place the kingdom of Tarshish
or Tartessos (in present-day Andalusia).
Here is the lament that Ezekiel addressed
to Tyre:
O thou that art situate at the entry of
the sea, which art a merchant of the peo¬
ple for many isles... O Tyrus, thou hast
said, I am ofperfect beauty.
Thy borders are in the midst of the
seas, thy builders have perfected thy
beauty.
They have made all thy ship boards offir
of Senir; they have taken cedars from
Lebanon to make masts for thee.
Of the oaks of Bashan have they made
thine oars... thy benches of ivory,
brought out of the isles of Chittim.
Fine linen with broidered work from
Egypt was that which thou spreadest
forth to be thy sail; blue andpurple from
the isles of Elishah was that which
covered thee.
The inhabitants ofZidon andArvad were
thy mariners; thy wise men, O Tyrus,
that were in thee, were thy pilots.
... all the ships of the sea with their
mariners were in thee to occupy thy
merchandise.
... and thou wast replenished and made
very glorious in the midst of the seas.
(Ezekiel chapter 27)
Nothing could express more eloquently
than these beautiful verses the maritime
power of the Phoenicians at the time
when Tyre, a sovereign State, was foun¬
ding colonies on the faraway coasts of
unknown lands.
In addition to documentary evidence,
there are archaeological facts. The dag¬
ger of Byblos has often been mentioned
and reproduced in illustrations. The
engravings which it bears tell of a
memorable event the return from the
land of Ophir (no doubt a market in
Southern Arabia where payments were
made in gold), a region rich in precious
metals and exotic products, to which
Phoenician vessels travelled. The king of
Byblos himself went down to the harbour
to welcome back the fearless travellers.
A silver patera (a typically Phoenician
product) found at Prenesta (now
Palestrina) in Italy bears a series of im¬
ages, also engraved, depicting a princely
hunt in which the imaginary appears to
surpass historical fact. The prince is be¬
ing attacked by a gorilla or chimpanzee.
Possibly this recalls the journeys which
took the Phoenicians to the heart of
equatorial Africa.
To meet their commercial needs and
ensure good conditions for their trading
activities, these adventurers established
warehouses and, later, colonies, as far
away as the shores of the Atlantic, with
the very clear intention of occupying the
territory, appropriating it and settling on
it in short, of acquiring new
homelands, without however expelling
the aboriginal inhabitants. Amongst the
best known of these settlements were
Carthage (near present-day Tunis),
Hadrumetum (near Sousse), Leptis
Minor (present-day Lamtah) in Tunisia,
Lixus (near Larache) in Morocco, Gadès
(present-day Cadiz) in Spain, Nora in
Sardinia, Panorme (Palermo) and Motya
in Sicily. This expansion and these
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
These three specimens of Punic art illustrate some of
the extraneous influences on Phoenician culture.
Above left, head of a terracotta figurine which, like
others unearthed in the same 6th-century-BC tomb at
Carthage, was probably a talisman. The discovery of
these statuettes at Carthage brought further proof of
the close and enduring relations between Cyprus,
where they seem to have originated, and the Phoeni¬
cian world. Small perfume bottle (height 9 cm), left,
like other objects discovered in Punic cemeteries,
seems to indicate by virtue of its style that although
the Carthaginians adopted neither the religion nor the
customs of the Nile valley, they knew of and set store
by Egyptian magic and funerary practices. It is now in
the Bardo National Museum, Tunis. Above, 3-cm-high
ivory figurine reveals Italiote influence on Punic art
(Carthage Museum).
seafaring exploits would not have been
possible without elaborate technical sup¬
port, whether in the form of the advances
achieved in shipbuilding, especially in the
use of the keel, ribs and nails, or of the
ability to navigate by reading the stars.
Phoenician expansion also seems to
have been favoured by the situation
prevailing in the Mediterranean, in so far
6
as no capable adversary or rival power
existed there. The Greek presence did not
yet count on the eve of this expansion. It
was not until the end of the ninth century
and the first half of the eighth century BC
that Greece joined in the great Mediterra¬
nean adventure and Greek colonies were
established in the Western Mediterra¬
nean. The city of Carthage appears to
have been founded partly to control and
contain this increasingly troublesome
Greek presence.
Carthage was founded by the Phoeni¬
cians about 825-819 BC to serve both as
a military base and a great trading centre.
It gradually asserted itself as the capital
of the Phoenician cities in the western
Mediterranean, with responsibility for
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
their defence and the protection of their
interests. From that time onwards, the
Phoenicians were no longer spoken of in
this part of the ancient world. Thanks to
the presence of Carthage, to the spread of
its influence in every domain, to its open
approach to the native populations and
to the ethnic and cultural contacts which
this implied, there emerged what are
often vaguely referred to as the Punies
a new, predominantly indigenous, ethnic
group and a new, predominantly Phoeni¬
cian culture.
The apparent Punic unity often con¬
cealed specific peculiarities. However,
like the Phoenicians, the Punies of Africa
continued to be mainly turned towards
the sea, although this did not mean that
they gave up the benefits of the land and
the products of the large farms of the
African hinterland. The name of Car¬
thage is for ever linked with the seafaring
exploits of Himilco (who sailed as far as
the British Isles) and Hanno (who reach¬
ed the West African coast), as well as
with Mago's treatise on agronomy.
The establishment of the link between
the two Mediterranean basins must be
credited to Carthage and the Phoeni¬
cians. In this way the western Mediterra¬
nean was integrated into the political,
economic and cultural universe of the
historical East. Neolithic Africa learnt to
write by adopting the Phoenician
language and alphabet (from which the
Aramaic and Greek alphabets were deriv¬
ed) without omitting to create its own
system of writing (what we call Libyan).
Another result of this Phoenician and
Carthaginian expansion was the pro¬
found change which took place in the
political geography of the western
Mediterranean. Benefiting from the ex¬
periences of the Phoenicians, the Greeks
themselves also founded colonies in
southern Italy, Sicily, Gaul and even in
Spain. This competition became a danger
for the Phoenicians, who until then had
been undisputed masters of these distant
regions. From then on, they had to take
account of the Greek presence.
But they also had other indigenous
rivals. These were the Africans whose
kingdoms seem to have been largely the
product of their contact with the Phoeni¬
cians and with the culture which the latter
brought in the form of' goods and
dialogue. It was the Phoenicians who in¬
troduced the concept of State, Kingdom
or City-State to North Africa. The
western Mediterranean was then to
become the scene of many conflicts. One
has only to recall the wars between
Carthage and the Greeks in Sicily and
Corsica, or those between Rome and
Carthage, which are referred to by
Roman historians as "the Punic Wars".
But what is really important is the con¬
tribution of the Phoenicians and Car¬
thage in the economic and socio-cultural
domains.
Amongst the many gifts made by this
civilization to the Western Mediterra¬
nean and especially to Africa, special
mention must be made of the creation of
urban centres and town-planning. Most
of the so-called Punic or Roman towns
generally bear names of Libyan origin.
This supports the hypothesis of a Libyan
foundation subsequently enriched by
Phoenician and Carthaginian contribu¬
tions thanks to which many localities,
such as Kerkouane at Cape Bon in
Tunisia, were able to grow until they at¬
tained the city stage.
The Phoenicians and Carthage sowed
in the western Mediterranean the seed of
the Semitic East, whose saplings pros¬
pered especially well in the lands of the
Maghreb. Mediterranean civilization can
justly claim that "what I am I truly owe
to many hands, but also to Carthage and
the Phoenicians".
Mhamed Fantar
Tunisian farmers at Dougga tend their livestock in a setting dominated by Roman ruins. Dougga, known in
antiquity as Thugga, was founded by the Phoenicians and became an important city during Roman times.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
How Arab sailors
read the stars
by Régis Moretón
AS early as the beginning of the
eighth century, in the wake of
the great Islamic conquests, the
Arabs had direct access to many seas
the Red Sea, the Mediterranean, the
Gulf, the Indian Ocean, the Atlantic.
From end to end of this vast expanse,
trade and commerce were partly conduc¬
ted by sea, first of all in coastal waters
and later on the high seas.
At that time orientation was a major
problem. When we speak nowadays of
orientation at sea, we immediately think
of the compass, and we know that the
magnetic needle was, indeed, used for
navigation in the Gulf as early as the ele¬
venth century, but only when the stars
were not visible. All orientation at sea
depended on observation of the heavens.
Nautical instruction manuals in those
days were largely devoted to problems of
astronomical observations measuring
the height of the heavenly bodies above
the horizon and using the great cata¬
logues of the stars. The most famous of
these was the catalogue drawn up in the
tenth century by the Islamic astronomer
Al-Sufi in a manner that was both scienti¬
fic and practical, since it gave the co¬
ordinates of every star and contained two
drawings of each constellation one as it
appeared in the sky, and the other drawn
symmetrically, as it would be seen on a
copper globe reproducing the vault of
heaven. With this catalogue and the cop¬
per globe which was meant to accompany
it, the constellation by reference to which
one wished to take one's bearings could
easily be located in the sky.
At the turn of the fifteenth and six¬
teenth centuries, two great Arab naviga¬
tors of the Indian Ocean, Ahmed Ibn
Majid and Suleiman Mahri, revived this
traditional method, and it is to them that
we owe our knowledge of those features
of Arabian nautical astronomy which are
described below.
With the aid of a simple diagram (see
diagram 1), let us take a quick look at
some elementary facts concerning the
apparent movement of the stars on the
heavenly sphere and to which reference
will be made hereafter.
Let us consider the semi-vault of
heaven as it appears to an observer loca-
REGIS MORELON, of France, is a member of
the Dominican Institute of Oriental Studies,
Cairo. He is a specialist in the history of Arab
astronomy and his new study on Arab texts on
astronomy is to be published shortly.
8
ted at T, picked out with the aid of the
four cardinal points NSEW, the local
meridian being the circle NPZS. The
north heavenly pole is at P and its height
above the horizon the arc NP gives
the latitude of the observation point. The
heavenly equator is represented by the
circle EGW. A star situated north of the
by establishing that the particular stars F,
G, H, for example, on the diagram men¬
tioned above were at the same height on
the horizon, which corresponded to a
definite latitude.
In addition to latitude, observation of
the sky enabled them to determine the
direction in which they were sailing,
Diagram 1. Apparent movement of the stars on the heavenly
sphere (see article).
Diagram © Régis Morelon
equator rises at A, its apparent trajectory
on the heavenly sphere is the circle AFA'
parallel to the equator, and it sets at A',
symmetrical with A in relation to the
meridian. Likewise, a star situated south
of the equator will rise, for instance at B,
its apparent trajectory will be the circle
BHB', B' being symmetrical with B in
relation to the meridian. A star situated
at I, at a lower distance from the pole
than the latitude of the spot, will always
remain above the horizon in its daily
movement. If its distance from the pole is
known and its height as it passes below or
above the meridian is noted, this will
immediately give the height of the pole
above the horizon.
A point on the earth is determined by
its latitude and longitude. The longitude
is given in relation to a meridian of ori¬
gin, and involves the difference between
a local time and an origin-time. How¬
ever, movable chronometers which per¬
mit "time to be kept" precisely have exis¬
ted for little more than a century. Con¬
sequently, it was impossible for Arab sea¬
men to take a bearing in longitude. On
the other hand, they calculated their lati¬
tude by observing the stars, or by mea¬
suring directly the height of the pole, or
which was ascertained by what we now
call the compass-card.
The compass-card as it is represented
on present-day compasses and naviga¬
tional charts is a 32-point star which,
when related to the horizon, shows the
direction in which a vessel is heading.
This choice of 32 compass-points on the
horizon existed long before the compass
and it is very likely that this division,
established through observation of the
rise and setting of certain stars, origi¬
nated with the Arab seamen. Diagram 2
shows this card as it is described in the
nautical instruction manuals of the
Arabs, with the corresponding directions
related to the four cardinal points.
We can see at once the symmetry in
relation to the North-South line. On the
East side, each of the 15 divisions is en¬
titled "rise of such and such a star" and
on the west side "setting of such and such
a star". Thus we find repeated the sym¬
metry of the points A and A' or B and B'
in diagram 1. The names of the stars are
inscribed in the centre of the drawing.
Some of them still pose problems of iden¬
tification, but during the history of
navigation these names have become
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Diagram 2. Compass-card as described in Arab nautical instruc¬
tion manuals.
Diagram © Régis Morelon
A North pole
1 Ursa minor
2 Ursa major
3 Cassiopeia
4 Capella
5 Vega
6 Arcturus
7 Pleiades
8 Altair
9 Orion
10 Sirius
1 1 Scorpius
12 Antares
13 Argo navis
14 Canopus
1 5 Crux (Southern cross)
B South pole
^¿JE-Jfe
Two symmetric drawings of the Corvus (Raven) constellation,
drawn by the great Islamic astronomer Al-Sufi (903-986 AD).
purely conventional, just as what are call¬
ed "the signs of the zodiac" have long
since ceased to coincide with the con¬
stellations in which this description
originated. Consequently, nautical in¬
struction manuals show this "compass-
card" with the old descriptions and in¬
dicate according to latitude which stars,
by reference to their rising or setting,
really determine on the horizon the dif¬
ferent directions to be taken.
With the aid of the co-ordinates of
those stars on the "compass-card" which
it has been possible to identify, it can be
calculated that this division was original¬
ly made by seamen navigating on the In¬
dian Ocean at about 10° north latitude
and simply noting the position on the
horizon when the most typical stars rose
and set.
We now have, then, sufficient infor¬
mation to read the instruction given for a
particular maritime route.
At the end of the fifteenth century,
Suleiman Mahri gave the following
description of the route between Diu
(Pakistan) and southern Ceylon (Sri
Lanka):
"From Diu head for the 'rising of
Suhayl' (SSE) until the north pole is 5
fingers (1) above the horizon, then turn
landwards until thou art within 5 or 6
zam (2) of the land, then turn back in the
direction of the 'rising of Suhayl' until
the north pole is at a height of 3 fingers,
then gradually head south because as
thou drawest near to Ceylon the sea
becomes rough whereas out to sea it is
less rough. Thou shouldst turn towards
the right very slowly. As soon as the 'two
calves' (Beta and Gamma of the Little
Bear horizontal to the East) are at a
height of 7.75 fingers, head for the rising
of 'agrab' (SE) until thou seest the 'two
calves' at a height of 7.25 fingers. Then
head eastwards for 18 zam until thou
recognizest that thou art south of
Ceylonthou shalt know by the light¬
ning flashes above the island, with or
without rain...".
These few lines from Mahri comprise
practically all the means of navigating at
sea known in his time height of the
stars, compass-card, distance covered
and indications furnished by the ap¬
pearance of a coast.
It was with the aid of these that Arab
seamen became the experts on navigation
in the Indian Ocean and so in 1498, after
rounding Africa, Vasco da Gama took
Ibn Majid as his pilot from Malindi, on
the east coast of Africa, as far as Calicut,
in India. But after this initial voyage Por¬
tuguese ships arrived in strength in the
Indian Ocean and snatched maritime
supremacy from the Arab seamen
throughout the region.
Régis Morelon
(1) The "finger" is a unit ofangle read on instruments
used by sailors lo measure the height ofa heavenly body
above the horizon.
(2) The zam mentioned here is a unit ofdistance depen¬
ding on the average speed of a sailing vessel of the
period: about 12.6 sea-miles covered in three hours.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Carved out of elkbone, this
helmeted head of a warrior (c. 1 0th
century) was found at Sigtuna,
Sweden.
Photo Soren Hallgren © ATA, Stockholm
Viking expansion was made possi¬
ble by the development in 8th-
century Scandinavia of strong,
swift sailing ships whose construc¬
tion and shallow draught enabled
them to land on sloping beaches
and manwuvre in waters unsuitable
to most European vessels of that
time. Well-preserved Viking
longship, right, was found in a
burial mound at Gokstad on Oslo
Fjord in 1 880 and is now in the Vik¬
ing Ship Museum, Oslo. It is 23
metres long and 5.25 metres'wide
amidships, but even when fully
laden would only have drawn 1
metre of water. Its keel consists of
a single timber 17 metres long. A
replica of the Gokstad Ship crossed
the Atlantic in 1893.
Photo Tom Schneiders © Rapho, Paris
10
The Viking saga
by Magnus Magnusson
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Coins struck by the Vikings attest to their receptiveness to the cultures with
which they came into contact. Above, 1 0th-century silver pennies from the
Viking kingdom of York. Left, coin inscribed "Anlaf Cununc" (King Olaf) is
decorated with a raven, traditionally associated with Odin. Right, penny
with the name of St. Peter shows a sword and also Thor's hammer, a symbol
as potent to a Viking as a cross to a Christian.
THE term "Viking" has come to mean anyone who hap¬
pened to be a Scandinavian in the Middle Ages, whether
he was a seaman, a farmer, a merchant, a poet, an ex¬
plorer, a warrior, a craftsman, a settler or a pirate. And the
term "Viking Age" has been applied by historians somewhat
indiscriminately, it must be saidto cover three centuries of
dynamic Scandinavian expansion that took place from around
800 AD onwards.
It has become popularly associated with an age of terror and
unbridled piracy, when Norse freebooters came swarming out
of their northern homelands in their lean and predatory
longships, to burn and rape and pillage their way across civiliz¬
ed Europe. They have always been portrayed as merciless bar¬
barians, heedless of their own lives or of the lives of others, in¬
tent only on destruction. They were anti-Christ personified;
their emblems were Thor's terrible Hammer and Odin's sinister
Ravens, symbolizing the violence and black-hearted evil of their
pagan gods.
This deep-rooted popular prejudice about the Vikings can be
traced back directly to the lurid sensationalism of ecclesiastical
MAGNUS MAGNLSSON, Icelandic-born author and journalist, is well-
known in the UK as a TV and radio broadcaster specializing in archaeology
and history. He wrote and presented in 1980 a major TV series on the Vik¬
ings which has been shown in many countries and has appeared in book
form as Vikings! (BBC Publications with Bodley Head). Among his many
other published works are the award-winning Introducing Archaeology
(1972), Viking Expansion Westwards (1973), and Iceland (1979).
writers who were the occasional victims of smash-and-grab
Viking raids. In a turbulent age, when piracy and casual raiding
were a commonplace of everyday life all over Europe the Vik¬
ings happened to be more successful at it than most other peo¬
ple; and they paid the price for it by getting an extremely bad
reputation.
But, curiously enough, no one knows for certain what the
word "Viking" actually means! It may be related to the Old
Norse word vik, meaning "bay" or "creek", suggesting that a
Viking was someone who lurked with his ship in a hidden bay.
Some think it may come from the Old Norse verb vikja, meaning
"to turn aside", so that a Viking was someone who made
detours on his voyage presumably to go raiding. A third
school of scholarly opinion looks for a derivation in the Anglo-
Saxon word wie, itself borrowed from the Latin vicus, meaning
a fortified camp or trading-post, so that "Viking" might mean
a raider or a trader, or both!
But not every Scandinavian was a professional warrior or Vik¬
ing; and not every Viking was a pirate. Modern scholarship is
now beginning to highlight the constructive, rather than the
destructive, impact of the Viking Age. Spectacular ar¬
chaeological excavations like Coppergate in York, which un¬
earthed a whole street from the Viking Age, are revealing the
ordinary Viking man-in-the-street as a diligent and skilled
artisan the Viking as man, not the Viking as myth.
If the origin of the word "Viking" is obscure, so too are the
motive causes of the so-called Viking Age itself. There is no iv
To relieve the tedium of the long nor¬
thern winters, the Vikings played
various board games, including dice
games and a game similar to chess.
Pieces were made of bone, amber or
glass. Left, 10th-century wooden
Viking gaming board from Ireland.
Photo © National Museum of Ireland, Dublin
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
single, simple reason why the Scandinavians should suddenly
have burst upon the European scene late in the eighth century
(in the history books, at least it probably wasn't as sudden as
it has been made to appear). All major historical shifts have
complex roots. We know that in the seventh century, the Scan¬
dinavians began developing new sources of iron, which had
several consequences: improved iron production made for bet¬
ter weapons, and better farm implements; better farm im¬
plements led to agricultural improvements, which led in turn to
better nutrition and a correspondingly lower mortality rate
amongst infants. There is evidence about this time that land
that had formerly been thought unsuitable for farming was be¬
ing vigorously cleared of forest and scrub to make new farms
for new generations of vigorous, well-nourished younger sons
who wanted a place in the sun for themselves.
So an acute shortage of land was probably a major factor,
which led to considerable settlement overseas; there is
evidence of peaceful co-habitation between the Picts of nor¬
thern Scotland and Norwegian emigrant farmers long before
the outbreak of the Viking Age.
But there were other consequences, too. With its surplus iron
production, Scandinavia had a new and much-prized product to
sell to its neighbours; and the traders had sharp, well-tempered
weapons with which to defend themselves from pirates that
swarmed in the Baltic and along the shores of northern con¬
tinental Europe. But in order to trade effectively, the Scandina¬
vians needed good ships. They came in all shapes and sizes,
from small six-oared boats for coastal waters to the enormous
"dragon-ships" of royalty. In between came a versatile variety
of cutters, ferries, pinnaces, plump-bellied cargo-boats, ocean¬
going ships and galleys.
But the pride of the fleet, the ship that has become the univer¬
sal symbol of the Viking Age, was the lordly longship, un¬
disputed master of the northern seas. These ships were the out¬
come of centuries of technological innovation and evolution
which have been charted by chance archaeological discoveries,
from flat-bottomed punts to the splendour and sophistication of
the single-masted, square-sailed longships. Without the ships,
the Viking Age would never have happened at all.
The Viking Age was not a concerted effort at empire-
building. The Vikings were never a single, homogeneous people
imbued with the same aims and ambitions. The three countries
of the Scandinavian peninsula, as they are now defined by
political geography, were not really nations at all in the modern
sense of the term. Norway, for instance, was a scatter of in¬
habited areas under independent tribal chieftains along the
western seaboard; even the name Norway (Norvegur) simply
meant "North Way" not so much a nation as a trade-route.
And the three countries had distinct if sometimes overlapping
"spheres of influence" the Swedes in the Baltic and Russia,
the Danes on the Continent and in England, and the Norwegians
in Scotland and Ireland and the North Atlantic islands.
The first recorded Viking raid took place in the year 793, with
a seaborne assault by prowling Norwegian marauders on the
Holy Island of Lindisfarne, just off the north-eastern shoulder of
England. But long before that, the Swedes had been busy in the
Baltic, growing rich on trade. At the outset of the Viking Age,
Swedish entrepreneurs started to penetrate the hinterland of
Russia (they called it "Greater Sweden") in pursuit of the rich
fur trade and the exotic markets of Arabia and the Far East.
Swedish pioneers made their way through Russia by way of the
major rivers like the Volga and the Dnieper, dragging their ships
in exhausting overland portages on the way to the Caspian Sea
and the Black Sea.
By the ninth' century they had reached the capital of the
greatest power in the western world, the successor to Rome
the Byzantine Empire centred on Constantinople. There, Viking
mercenaries formed the elite bodyguard of the Byzantine
emperors, the feared and famous Varangian Guard, a kind of
Scandinavian Foreign Legion. But the Swedes never conquered
Russia, as such; they contented themselves with taking control
of existing trading posts and creating new ones to protect the
trade-routes, but within two or three generations they had
become totally assimilated and Slavicized.
12
While the Swedes looked east, the Danes looked south-west
along the northern coasts of Europe and towards England.
Danish warriors were soon hammering at the cities of the
crumbling Carolingian empire after the death of Charlemagne in
814 AD: Hamburg, Dorestad, Rouen, Paris, Nantes, Bordeaux
all river-cities, notice. The Viking longships, with their excep¬
tionally shallow draught, could go much further up-river than
<
t-
<
©
In the Viking age silver jewellery such as this
delicately worked pair of ear-rings found in
Sweden was imported into Scandinavia
from the territory of the western Slavs,
south of the Baltic.
had been thought possible before, and the effect was rathei like
that of dropping paratroops behind the enemy lines.
To start with, the Danish Vikings acted as pirates with official
or unofficial royal backing. Later on, Danish designs on Europe,
and especially England, became openly territorial; the flag
followed the trade, just as trade had followed the piracy. But
here, too, the Danes, just like the Swedes, became assimilated
whenever they settled. In the year 91 1, one marauding army
accepted by treaty huge tracts of land in Northern France in
what is now called Normandy "Northmandy", the land of the
Northmen; 1 50 years later, the descendants of these Norse-
Frenchmen would conquer all England under William the Con¬
queror. Before then, but only briefly, under King Knut (Canute)
in the eleventh century, there was a united Scandinavian em¬
pire of the North Sea, comprising England, Denmark and Nor¬
way; but it quickly fell apart.
Norwegian adventurers joined Danish Vikings in subjugating
the whole of northern England (the Danelaw, as it was called)
before settling there as farmers and traders, where they
developed great mercantile cities like York. They also took over
much of mainland Scotland, the Hebrides, and the Northern
Isles of Shetland and the Orkneys. In Ireland they played a lusty
part in the endless internecine squabbles of rival Irish clans, and
founded Ireland's first trading posts: Waterford, Wexford,
Wicklow, Limerick and, most especially, Dublin. They were in¬
satiable explorers in search of new trade opportunities to ex¬
ploit, new lands to settle, new horizons to cross. They
discovered Spitzbergen and Jan Mayen Island; they discovered
and colonized the Faroes, far out in the heaving Atlantic; they
discovered and colonized Iceland, where they established
Europe's first Parliamentary republic a new nation that is still
regarded as the oldest democracy in Europe, and which has left
us the most enduring cultural monument of the Viking Age, the
Icelandic Sagas.
From Iceland, they discovered and settled Greenland. And it
was from Greenland, round about the millennial year of 1000,
that the Vikings launched their last and most ambitious expedi¬
tions of all, the discovery and attempted settlement of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
Air view of the Viking cemetery at Lindholm Hoje, northern Jutland. Low boat-shaped mounds and
stone settings in different forms mark the graves.
eastern seaboard of North America: "Vinland", the land of wild
grapes, as it was called in the two Icelandic Sagas that record
the first undisputed European discovery of the New World.
The discovery of North America, and the abortive attempts
at colonization which were thwarted by the indigenous Red In¬
dians, used to be considered mere legend; but now archaeology
has unearthed authenticated evidence of a Viking settlement at
L'Anse aux Meadows, in northern Newfoundland. All other
alleged Viking "finds", like the runic Kensington Stone, have
long since been exposed as forgeries or hoaxes, or merely
wishful thinking.
The impact of the Vikings was ultimately less lasting than
might have been expected. Why was that? They had all the
necessary energy, they had their own administrative systems
of justice and royal authority, .they had become converted to
Christianity, they had their own coinage, they seemed to have
everything. They had criss-crossed half the world in their open
boats and vastly extended its known horizons. They had gone
everywhere there was to go, and beyond. They had dared
everything there was to dare. They had given Europe a new
trading vigour, vigorous new art-forms, vigorous new settlers.
But they had neither the manpower nor the staying-power,
neither the reserves of wealth nor the political experience,
neither the cohesion at home nor the confidence abroad, to
master effectively the older, richer, more stable States they
tried to overrun. Instead, being rootless men of the sea, they
put their roots down where they landed, and then blended into
the landscape. Somehow or other, the dynamic simply petered
out.
But they left in the annals of history, a heritage of heroic
endeavour and courage, a legacy of robust audacity, that has
won the grudging admiration even of those who would other¬
wise deplore their incidental depredations.
Magnus Magnusson
Left, timber richly carved with interlaced fighting animals is a struc¬
tural detail from the 12th-century Stave Church at Urnes in western
Norway. It was incorporated into the Church from an even earlier
building. A remarkable example of the art and architecture of northern
Europe at the end of the Viking period. Urnes Church is today inscrib¬
ed on Unesco's World Heritage List of cultural and natural properties
of outstanding universal value.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Coastal and island
civilizations
of Africa
by Ibrahima Baba Kaké
AS the German anthropologist Leo
Frobenius (1873-1936) wrote:
"When the first European navi¬
gators arrived in the Gulf of Guinea and
landed at Ouidah, the captains were
astonished to find well laid out streets, tree-
lined for several miles. Travelling from
dawn till dusk, they traversed a countryside
of magnificent fields and inhabited by men
dressed in silks and velvet. They saw great
States, well-ordered down to the smallest
detail, powerful sovereigns, rich industries,
and peoples civilized to their finger-tips.
IBRAHIMA BABA KAKE, of Guinea, teaches
history al a Lycée in Paris. A former lecturer at
the Centre ofAfrican Research at the Sorbonne,
he is the author of many articles and books in¬
cluding Histoire Générale d'Afrique (A General
History of Africa), in collaboration with Elikia
M'Bokolo.
And the countries on the eastern coast, such
as Mozambique, for example, were just the
same."
All the studies made of the history and ar¬
chaeology of the African coastal areas fully
bear out this report.
Let us first take a look at the west coast
of the continent. The area extending from
about longitude 15 degrees west to
longitude 10 degrees east, or from present-
day Guinea-Bissau to the United Cameroon
Republic, is known in geographical terms as
the Gulf of Guinea. The prevailing climate
is equatorial, very humid, and the region
owes its riotous vegetation to rain borne in
on the south-west trade winds and the
monsoon.
Generally speaking this coast is difficult
of access to snipping because of its coastal
bar and is not favourable to human settle-
: f
|
m * ï
' m*W
WPT, <* 1
m ti '
Kfr J 4HmJ
*£» '-'BT«'
Chinese plates of the late Ming period
are embedded in this 18th-century
pillar-tomb at Kunduchi, 25
kilometres north of Dar es Salaam
(United Republic of Tanzania). They
are one of many pieces of ar¬
chaeological evidence in this region
for the existence of trading connex¬
ions between the coast of east Africa
and China via the silk routes.
Songs
of
the
pirogue
by Francis M''Boulé
FRANCIS M'BOULE, of the Cameroon, is a
research worker at the University of Pans VI. A
sociologist and psychologist, he was formerly
associate professor of medical sociology at New
York State University and guest researcher at the
Artificial Intelligence Laboratory of the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
THE pirogue, or dugout canoe, is a
central element in the life of the
Duala people who live in the coas¬
tal region of Cameroon, on the banks of
the network of rivers that come together
in the Suelaba estuary before spilling out
into the Atlantic Ocean.
Indeed, the pirogue embodies every
aspect of Duala culture. It is a utilitarian
object, providing a means of transport
for people and for merchandise as well as
being the fishermen's tool. It is a sym¬
bolic object that engenders myths and
affirms the pre-eminence of the God of
Water. It is a link that binds men together
since, once they have settled in an area,
the pirogue on the water, far more than
any reference to some more or less
vaguely remembered common ancestor,
is the expression of the unity of all
fisherfolk.
The pirogue makes contact easier and
favours the extension of family links. It is
a means of settling any disputes that may
arise, it plays its part in ceremonies such
as the enthronement of the chief and is,
of course, central to such institutions as
pirogue racing. It is a means of artistic
expression (the finely carved figureheads
on the prow) and it confirms the cultural
unity of the society through the songs of
the crews (which celebrate the pirogue as
ancestor, as the mother of heroes, as the
mother's noble son, etc.).
Pirogue races are still held today. Nine
days before the event, all the men capable
of taking part gather together. The eve¬
nings are alive with song and the feats of
the great piroguemen of the past are
recounted.
The songs of the piroguemen cover
every aspect of the life of the
community economic, political and
personal. The song is improvised by the
soloist and is then taken up in turn by his
audience, reinforcing the unity of the
group.
The history of the group is also reflec¬
ted in the creation of the figureheads that
decorate the prows of the racing pi¬
rogues, the most powerful figure or ani¬
mal representing the kinship group.
The prow presents a challenge to rival
groups who take it up by creating in their
turn similar figures which, it is hoped,
will stand out by their originality.
Thus, for a Duala, the pirogue is
indeed an extension of himself.
Before the start of a pirogue race the
rival crews sing in an attempt to intimi¬
date their opponents. Here are two of
these songs:
Yo, Yo, Yo!
Nkondo (I) mightier
than all other "lands"!
(I) Name of the pirogue.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
ment; it has been called "The White man's
grave", and it is equally deadly for the
"Black man".
However, long before the Europeans ar¬
rived on the scene, very advanced civiliza¬
tions flourished on these inhospitable
shores. The finest example of such civiliza¬
tions is that of Benin.
The archaeological digs carried out by
Leo Frobenius at the beginning of this cen¬
tury, at Ifé, have shown that, before the six¬
teenth century, the Yoruba people had
already established an advanced civiliza¬
tion. There Frobenius unearthed finely
moulded terra-cotta busts of negroes. Near
them were found headdresses decorated
with owls and crocodiles, the ¡mages of
divinities and other, richly-dressed per¬
sonages, as well as stone vases with vitrified
interiors, beads which bore witness to the
existence of an ancient glassware industry,
crystal, and large sculpted statues.
All these objects are the artistic evidence
of an advanced civilization whose existence
had previously been unsuspected. The
bronzes found by Frobenius are master¬
pieces, the precursors of the famous Benin
bronzes. From this ancient culture dating
from the beginning of the Iron Age, and
from its counterparts in the west, sprang the
technical innovations that were to enable
later peoples to create the States and Em¬
pires of the tropical forest zone: those of
Oyo, Benin, Adansi, Denkyera, Ashanti,
and others. The principal States of Guinea
and the hinterland were firmly established
by the time the Europeans arrived, but they
were inward-looking and owed little to their
Fishermen from Cayar
north of Dakar (Senegal)
watch as fire consumes
the hut of another fisher¬
man, lost at sea. They
have set fire to the hut in
accordance with an an¬
cient rite of the Ewe peo¬
ple which prescribes that
since the fisherman's
death has been caused
by a "sea demon" which
entered his hut, the hut
must be burned to pre¬
vent the evil from
spreading to nearby
dwellings and to force
the demon to return to
the ocean depths from
whence it was conjured
by an evil spell.
Photo © Folco Quilici, Rome
proximity to the sea.
Meantime, what was the situation in the
east? On the African shores washed by the
tides of the Indian Ocean, the Bantu-
Islamic civilization of the Swahilis (literally,
people of the coast) had developed.
This was a people with close links with
the civilizations of the Orient, and in par¬
ticular with India. The Portuguese were
astonished to find there City-States and
Governments as rich and as complex as
those of Europe, powerful stone-built cities
and ports bustling with merchant shipping.
They encountered men accustomed to
voyaging in eastern seas and whose
knowledge of navigation was greater than
their own.
The greater part of this east coast civiliza¬
tion was destroyed. Except in the north,
little or nothing survived of its erstwhile
prosperity. Most of the towns whose re¬
mains are to be found on the western shores
of the Indian Ocean date from the seven¬
teenth or eighteenth centuries.
It is said that, in the thirteenth century,
the Swahilis transported by sea an elephant
which was presented to the Emperor of
China. Their ships (mtepe), some of them
Photo © Museum fur Volkerkunde, West Berlin
African birds and snakes mingle with European motifs in the design
of this finely crafted ornamental prow of a Duala pirogue. The bird
is associated with the gods of the air, the snake with water
divinities. The central figure, a woman with multicoloured breasts,
is a motif from a genealogical tree, and the animals she holds in her
hands may have a totemic significance.
Come and see
Nkondo, mightier
than all other "lands".
I love Nkondo,
the one pirogue which troubles
all the land of the Duala.
Nkondo the triumphant...
You, sons of Duala,
descendants of Bedi,
I .defy you
Nkondo! mightier
than all other "lands".
Be not dismayed,
Ours is the only pirogue
that fills the hearts of others
with hate and fear.
Ebenye, mun'ango
A ma pumwa wenge
Kana mbela na
A ma longo wenge
Kana ngoso (I) na...
Ebenye, your son
has flown today
like an eagle.
Today he has sung
like a nightingale (2)...
(1) Ngoso: (parrot); literary style which might be likened
to the epic style in Western literature.
(2) "Parrot" in the Duala version.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
seventy-tonners, were in use for centuries in
the Indian Ocean. The Swahilis had a wide
range of sailing ships for trade, for fishing
and for the transport of farmworkers along
the eastern seaboard of Africa. According
to some researchers, hundreds of Swahili
vessels (in addition to the Arab dhows from
the Gulf) plied between the ports of Tanga
and Kilwa (in the present-day United
Republic of Tanzania).
A great variety of influences and cultures
contributed here to the establishment of a
long-lasting east African civilization. The
wide and varied trading contacts with the
Orient are attested to by the oldest original
document, a "Travellers Log", dating
from 100 AD and probably written by a
Greek from Egypt; it takes the form of a
guide for the sailor or the merchant, and
lists the ports of east Africa and their
trading interests; it covers an area extending
as far as the southern port of Rhapta, which
was, apparently, located close to present-
day Pangani in the United Republic of Tan¬
zania. Thus, some fifteen hundred years
before the arrival of the Europeans, the east
coast of Africa was already involved in
regular, peaceful trade with the cities of the
Red Sea, southern Arabia, the Gulf, India,
Ceylon (Sri Lanka) and more distant
countries.
In the Europe of the colonial period, this
was generally considered to be an Arab
civilization. The Portuguese of the six¬
teenth century gave none of the credit for it
to the Africans and invariably referred to
the peoples of Kilwa, Mombasa, Malindi
and other east African towns as "Moors".
Today it is recognized that, relatively early
on, the City-States of the east African
coast, although subject to strong Arab and
Muslim influence, were predominantly of
African culture. Undoubtedly, the brilliant
Swahili or coastal civilization owed much to
the Indian Ocean, since it was built on
maritime trade.
Leaving the mainland coasts, let us ex¬
amine the situation of the offshore islands.
When the Portuguese arrived at the Cape
Verde Islands in the fifteenth century,
although they were already known to the
Arabs, they found them virtually
uninhabited. The Portuguese navigators
settled there and began a fruitful two-way
trade with Europe and Africa, and for a
time Cape Verde became the focal point of
the slave trade in the Atlantic.
Carved wooden figures of a man and
woman adorn a Vezo tomb near Moron-
dava on the west coast of Madagascar.
The Vezo are a group of fishing people
living in close communion with the sea,
which is a favourite theme of Malagasy
poets such as Jean Joseph Rabéarivelo
who has written of:
she whose feet are impacted in the sea
and whose sticky hands emerge from it
full of coral and of sparkling blocks of
salt.
Photo © Siegfried Sammer, West Berlin
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Further south, in the Gulf of Guinea, are
the volcanic islands of Fernando Poo (now
Bioko), Sao Tomé and Principe. They were
inhabited by Blacks, either the descendants
of shipwrecked sailors or of slaves who
went there with the first Portuguese
occupiers.
Throughout the sixteenth, seventeenth
and eighteenth centuries, the Cape Verde
Islands, Sao Tomé and Principe (together
with other parts of continental Africa
where the Portuguese presence was less
lasting), Brazil and Lisbon were elements in
a single trading system based on a
geographical fact then of importance to
navigation, the maritime currents, and
which fed on the trade in slaves destined for
the American continent.
The culture that evolved in these
"creóle" islands has remained alive. In the
south Atlantic islands, the word "creóle"
evokes the most successful bio-social
amalgam achieved by the Portuguese in the
Tropics. Here was developed a new type of
man, a new type of mentality and even a
new language, Creole, born of a har¬
monious fusion of Whites and of Black
slaves. On the route between southern
Europe and South America, these islands,
with their original, racially-mixed society,
represented a transitional link between
Africa and the Atlantic world.
Much the same scenario is to be found in
the Indian Ocean, in the Mascarene Islands
(Mauritius and Réunion) and Madagascar.
From the end of the eighteenth century,
the peopling of Mauritius was dependent on
French immigration. French is still spoken
there today, along with English and seven¬
teen other languagesa veritable Tower of
Babel. But the most widely used language is
Creole. On Mauritius are to be found In¬
dians, Chinese, and east Africans, many of
whom are involved in the growing of sugar
cane, in the exploitation of the salt marshes
and in the construction of giant furnaces
for the burning of coral.
The Island of Réunion, it has been said,
was born of an idea of Colbert put into
practice by the Compagnie des Indes. In
1644, the Isle Bourbon, as it was then call¬
ed, had a population of 1,200 made up of
shipwrecked Dutchmen, pirates and women
destined for the settlers at Fort Dauphin, in
Madagascar. The slave trade provided the
first labourers. With the rise in demand for
coffee in the eighteenth century population
growth accelerated, with Blacks being
brought in from Madagascar and Mozam¬
bique. Bearing in mind the elements con¬
tributed by the Chinese and the Muslims,
Réunion could also be said to be a cross¬
roads for the intermingling of civilizations.
The most fantastic hypotheses have been
put forward regarding the origins of the
Malagasies. However, in 1614, the Por¬
tuguese Jesuit Luis Mariano wrote: "The
first inhabitants came some from Malacca
and some from Kaffraria" (the generic
term applied by the Portuguese to all the
territories along the south-east coast of
Africa).
Most Malagasies are of mixed descent.
The eighteen tribes of the Island are not
monolithic racial blocs, and the language
shows remarkable unity. It is an Indonesian
language, but its pronunciation suggests an
African influence.
CONTINUED PAGE 18
Equatorial Guinea:
a nation moulded
by the sea
by Catherine Gillard
AN archetypal maritime country by
virtue of its configuration and
history. Equatorial Guinea is a
land of shores and islands which has
been prominent down the ages as a base
for observation and action.
There are three Guineas in Africa: the
Guinea whose capital is Conakry;
Guinea-Bissau; and Equatorial Guinea.
The latter is the least known. Located in
the Gulf of Guinea, it is known as "Equa¬
torial" Guinea because its territory
straddles the Equator. Relatively small
(28,051 sq. km.), it comprises continen¬
tal Guinea, known as Rio Muni, and a
group of islands. Rio Muni is bordered to
the north by Cameroon, to the east and
south by Gabon. It has a long coastline
(around 180 km.) in comparison to its
maximum east-west distance (220 km.)
and its area (26,000 sq. km.). The insular
part of Guinea comprises five islands of
varying size in the Gulf of Guinea: Bioko
(formerly Fernando Poo), 2,017 sq. km.;
Annobón, 17 sq. km.; Coriseo, 15 sq.
km.; Elobey Grande, 2.27 sq. km.; and
Elobey Chico, 0.19 sq. km.
From this brief description it can be
seen that Equatorial Guinea is divided
into a maritime entity and an area of
mainland. If the islands are much less
important than mainland Guinea in terms
of size, they take precedence strategi¬
cally. Bioko provides an anchorage in the
Gulf of Guinea off the coast of Came¬
roon, and Annobón offers a harbour off
the coast of Gabon. It is not surprising
that the great navigators should have
been interested in these islands during
the period of colonial conquest.
In their quest for a new and quicker
route to the Indies, Spaniards and Portu¬
guese discovered new lands. Pedro de
Escobar and Juan de Santerem were
among the Portuguese sailors who fol¬
lowed the coast of Africa. After setting
sail from Sao Tomé, they sighted a
hitherto unknown island on New Year's
Day 1471 and named it Annobón ("New
Year" in Portuguese). In 1472 a Portu¬
guese adventurer named Fernao do Poo
landed on an island which he called "Fer-
CATHERINE GILLARD, of France, is prepar¬
ing a doctoral thesis under the supervision of
Professor Georges Balandier at the School of
Higher Studies in the Social Sciences, Paris. She
specializes in the study of the social and
economic problems of Equatorial Guinea.
mosa" ("marvellous"). This island
would later be named for him by the
Spaniards. The search for a route to the
Indies caused rivalry between Spain and
Portugal. By the Treaties of San Ilde¬
fonso (1777) and El Prado (1778) Portu¬
gal ceded to Spain both Annobón and
Fernao do Poo (Fernando Poo) together
with trading rights in the ports and along
the coast adjacent to Fernando Poo.
Spain wanted to provide herself with
supplies of slaves and grow rich in gold
and ivory. But she found it difficult to
penetrate into the interior of her new
territories.
The Spaniards did not really begin to
settle in the island and on the coast of
Equatorial Guinea until 1858; exploration
of the hinterland got underway even
later. The voyages of the great naviga¬
tors, the slave trade and the search for
wealth, all the great dynamic forces
which triggered the conquest of the
oceans, came into play on the modest
island territory of Equatorial Guinea. Its
history is a crucible of all the desires
which impelled peoples to embark on
epic journeys of seaborne exploration.
This magical point on the Gulf of Guinea
has attracted Portuguese, Dutch, Span¬
iards, English, and French, all seeking to
conquer the world and its wealth by sea.
These islands have long been seen as a
prize or as a gateway to power.
New commercial considerations are
emerging today, at a time when the
world powers are trying to find a basis for
agreement on the exploitation of the sea.
These islands of Equatorial Guinea are
once again a prize. The country's territo¬
rial waters and the continental shelf hold
rich promise since neighbouring coun¬
tries have discovered offshore oil depo¬
sits. Oil and mineral exploration compa¬
nies have offered to co-operate with the
Governments of Equatorial Guinea.
These resources may become an unde¬
niable asset in the political and economic
life of Equatorial Guinea.
Equatorial Guinea has an existence as
a nation moulded by the sea, different
from and complementary to its life as
part of the continent. From the time of
the great explorers to the most recent
negotiations on the law of the sea, this
small and unfortunately all too little-
known country has been constantly
marked by its island destiny.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
These children live on the Indian
Ocean island of Mauritius, where
European, African, Chinese and In¬
dian peoples and cultures have
met and intermixed. English,
French, Creole, Indian and Chinese
dialects are spoken on the island
which is dotted with Hindu
temples, Muslim mosques, Bud¬
dhist pagodas and Christian
churches.
Photo © Pierre Argo, Paris
Cultural features reveal a similarly pro¬
portionate balance of influences. Thus the
shape of the houses, the smith's bellows,
the megaliths, the ancestor cult, the polite
forms of address and ¿he oral literature,
among other characteristics, owe much to
Indonesia.
Other aspects, however, such as the im¬
portance of cattle, evoke eastern Africa.
Dance and musical instruments have been
borrowed from both areas, and these dou¬
ble roots are everywhere to be seen, with,
however, a certain Indonesian cultural
preponderance, which can perhaps be ex¬
plained on the basis of the supposition that
the Indonesians arrived via the northern In¬
dian Ocean and the African coast by taking
advantage of the monsoon winds.
It would seem, therefore, that, except for
the inhabitants of the islands, the African
coastal civilizations of the continent's
Atlantic flank drew little advantage from
the sea, whereas those of the eastern coastal
regions knew how to exploit the oppor¬
tunities offered them by the Indian Ocean.
The Swahili City-States were maritime
powers, thalassocracies. The absence of
maritime States on the west flank of the
continent was not due solely to
geographical considerations but also to the
lack of a merchant class anxious to grow
rich on maritime trade. Furthermore, the
peoples of the western coastal regions do
not appear to have mastered navigational
techniques.
Nevertheless, the sea played an important
role in the expansion of these coastal
civilizations, especially at the time of the
slave trade between Africa and the New
World. If Brazil is the country in which the
presence of African civilizations is most
clearly evident, it must not be forgotten that
they left a strong imprint on the southern
United States, the Caribbean and the whole
of South America.
Ibrahima Baba Kake
The islands
of Cape Verde
by Elisa Andrade
18
SPREAD out like a crescent in the
Atlantic Ocean some 600 kilo¬
metres off the coasts of Mauri¬
tania and Senegal, the Cape Verde
Islands form two clusters named from
their position relative to the prevalent
north-east wind: the Windward
Islands, comprising Santa Antäo, Säo
Vicente, Santa Luzia, Säo Nicolau,
Sal and Boa Vista and the islets of
Branco and Razo, and the Leeward
Islands, consisting of Maio, Säo
Tiago, Fogo and Brava, and the three
Rombo islets.
The history of Cape Verde is rooted
in the history of Portuguese colonial
expansion. Many Portuguese
historians and chroniclers maintain
that the Islands were discovered bet¬
ween 1460<and 1462 in the course of
two successive voyages. Oral tradi¬
tion, supported by certain Portuguese
sources, has it that the Island of Säo
Tiago was inhabited by Wolofs, who
ended up there after civil wars on the
mainland, and the Island of Sal (Salt
Island) by Lebu, Serer and Felup
peoples, attracted there by its salt¬
pans. However, these settlers were
too few in number to resist the Por¬
tuguese penetration.
The difficulty of growing the cereals
to which the Portuguese were ac¬
customed on the poor soil and in the in¬
hospitable climate of the Islands,
coupled with Portugal's low population
level, acted as a brake on European
settlement of Cape Verde. In June
1466 therefore, to provide a further in¬
centive to settlement. King Alfonso of
Portugal (1432-1481) granted the set¬
tlers a Charter of Privileges. His brother
Fernando, to whom he had made a gift
of the Islands, was also granted
jurisdiction in civil and criminal affairs
over all the "Moors, Blacks and
Whites", whether freemen or slaves,
provided that they were Christians. At
the same time, the settlers were
granted, in perpetuity, the right to
trade and to deal in slaves throughout
the entire region from the River
Senegal to Sierra Leone, with the ex¬
ception of the Arguin Bay area, which
was a Crown monopoly.
ELISA ANDRADE, of Cape Verde, specializes
in socio-economics and planning for develop¬
ment. She completed herpost-graduate studies at
the University of Algiers and the African In¬
stitute ofEconomic Development and Planning,
Dakar. The author of a number of articles on
socio-economic problems, she is at present
preparing a doctorate in History and Civilization
at the University of Paris VII.
The Charter enabled the settlers to
organize the slave trade which was to
provide manpower both for the col¬
onial development of the Islands and
for export to the slave markets of Brazil
and the West Indies.
The distance from metropolitan Por¬
tugal, the difficulty of communication
between the Islands, and the virtually
complete absence of European women
immigrants, favoured a process of
racial intermingling which is now evi¬
dent in about ninety per cent of the
population.
Throughout its history, right up to
the eve of independence in 1 975, Cape
Verde was the hub of Portuguese ex¬
pansion in ail its varied forms. Thus,
after the abolition of slavery in 1876,
the export of contract labourers replac¬
ed that of slaves. And after the Con¬
ference of Berlin in 1885, which con¬
firmed the division of the African conti¬
nent between the Western European
colonial powers, officials of the col¬
onial administrative corps gradually
replaced the pioneer settlers, the slave
traders and the merchants.
Before the days of the steamship
and radio communications, islands
scattered along the continental coasts
played an essential role in the develop¬
ment of long-distance navigation and
trade. Owing to its geographical posi¬
tion, halfway between the African con¬
tinent, Europe and the Americas, and
on the route to the East, Cape Verde
was destined, from the beginning, to
become a cross-roads of commerce
and the slave trade and to be a water¬
ing and supply point for shipping. The
colonial development policy of Cape
Verde was, therefore, based on its
geo-political and strategic position.
By introducing slave labour into the
Islands, the settlers were able to create
a dual agricultural system, one produc¬
ing cereals, vegetables and fruit for in¬
ternal consumption, and the other pro¬
ducing cash crops for export, such as
cotton, sugar cane and wine.
Towards the middle of the sixteenth
century, slaves expert in the weaving
of pagnes (African loin-cloths) were
imported and their output, much in de¬
mand by slave traders, was used prin-
rVoa"y 'n barter for the acquisition of
slaves from the continent.
Horses, donkeys, goats, pigs, and
cows were introduced into the Islands
to provide fresh and salted meat and
hides for sale to visiting ships and,
later, for export.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
ROUTES OF SLAVERY
Map shows routes of slave
ships which transported
their cargoes from the
west coast of Africa to the
Americas via the Island of
Säo Tiago, in the Cape
Verde archipelago.
Map © All Rights Reserved
The boundaries on this map do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by
Unesco or the United Nations.
c?
Antilles
O
MAURITANIA
Santiago (Sâo Tiago)
LIBERIA
Säo Tiago was the main slave depot
from whence slaves were exported to
the Canaries, Portugal and Spain, and
later to the West Indies and Brazil.
Ships sailing the rivers of Guinea in
search of slaves were obliged to call in
at the Islands to pay the royal tax.
Cape Verde was also a virtually
obligatory port of call at which all long¬
distance shipping had to stop to take
on water and other provisions. In
1 497, Vasco de Gama's "armada", en
route for the East, dropped anchor at
Ribeira Grande (today Cidade Velha) to
take on supplies of water and food.
Three years later came Pedro Alvares
Cabrai, on his way to Brazil. And in
1 522, the Islands were visited by the
ships of Fernäo de Magalhäes
(Magellan) on their historic circum¬
navigation of the world.
From the middle of the sixteenth
century, French ships from Senegal,
Gorée and Benin called in to buy provi-
sions and slaves which they later sold
in their American colonies; English,
Dutch and Spanish ships, on their way
to India, also called in for supplies.
This was a period in which, with the
development of commerce, shipping
and the slave trade, the property-
owning classes of Cape Verde flourish¬
ed and grew rich. But this was soon to
be followed by the decline of slave-
based societies.
During the period of the enforced
union of Portugal with Spain
(1 580-1 640), the Spanish took advan¬
tage of the Portuguese colonial policy.
By deviating the slave trade towards
the West Indies they freed the slave
ships from the obligation to call in at
Säo Tiago to pay the royal tax, and the
Islands thus lost one of their main
sources of revenue.
Other measures and other historical
events had a crippling effect on the in¬
terests of the Cape Verde elite: they
were forbidden to deal in certain pro¬
ducts essential for the acquisition of
slaves, the slave-trading areas con¬
tracted, there were frequent attacks
by French and English pirates, the Por¬
tuguese empire was reduced, to the
area which today is Guinea-Bissau,
and trade was monopolized by the
great trading companies established
from 1 664 onwards; the total abolition
of slavery was to be the final blow.
Elisa Andrade
Left, salt is an important product on
the island of Sal, Cape Verde Islands.
19
_*	-3
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
From myth
to reality
The
rise of scientific
map-making
by Vitorino M. Godinho
i
The Portuguese "Cantino Map", dating
from 1 502, is a landmark in cartographic
history. For the first time a map depicts
the African continent in its true profile,
India as a triangular peninsula, a
somewhat deformed Indochina and the
immensity of both the Indian and the
Atlantic Oceans.
Photo (c) Roncaglia, Modena. Biblioteca Estense, Modena
- ^w "ttQF; j£gsa
The "Catalan Atlas" (1375) is thought to be the work of a
celebrated Jewish cartographer of Majorca, Abraham Cres-
ques. Consisting of six panels of parchment-covered wood, it
depicts the world from western Europe to the Far East as ¡t
was known from tradition and the writings of travellers.
Astrological, astronomical and cosmographical diagrams are
featured on the first two panels. Fragment shown here is se¬
cond half of the sixth panel. Text at bottom left corner, above
the picture of a mermaid, reads: "Sea of the isles of the Indies
where there are spices, in this sea sail a number of ships of
various peoples and there are several kinds of fish called mer-
ids, one species is half woman and half fish and another
woman and half bird."
Photo t Urs Graf, Dietikon-Zürich
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
DURING the Middle Ages geo¬
graphy was based on myth rath¬
er than on fact. The changes
that occurred in and around the thir¬
teenth century made possible the first
timid intrusion of reality. Before then
there had been no system for visualizing
the globe. Planispheres and maps of the
world, as they were known, merely jux¬
taposed land masses separated by seas
and criss-crossed by rivers which were
given imaginary courses (in keeping with
the logic of the myth) in disregard of any
scientific law of correspondence between
their forms, their dimensions or even
their relative positions; they were no
more than symbolic configurations.
The years 1270-1320 witnessed the
resurgence of Euclidean geometry (giving
science the means with which to define
space) as well as the astronomy of
Ptolemy (passed down through Islam),
the optics of Apollonius and Ptolemy,
Based on this new-found knowledge,
the first cartographic system was
established using rhumb lines and the
estimation of distances. At that time, the
"Sea between lands" (the Mediterra¬
nean) was plotted correctly (except for
elongation in the longitude) and became
the centre of the scientific representation
of the oikumene (the inhabited world)
which, on the basis of information
brought back by caravaneers on the
Asian routes, then extended as far as
Cathay.
Those who would like a view of the
world as it appeared in the years
1375-1381 need only examine the Catalan
Atlas of the Cresques, a father and son
team of cartographers from Majorca.
The splendour of its illumination reveals
the camel trails of Africa and the Orient,
kingdoms of gold, the opulent cities of
Asia, fleets of the Indian Ocean and the
galleys of the coasts of Madeira and the
Portugal and Bordeaux, wool from Old
Castile, Wales and the Midlands, linen
from Ireland and Minho, and fish from
all regions. Shipbuilding remained active
thanks to the timber from the Sierra de
Cantabria, the Landes and other areas.
It is often held that this maritime ac¬
tivity was due to the introduction of
Mediterranean shipbuilding methods
(galleys) from Genoa. But galleys were in
fact only useful for naval warfare, and
the vessels used in the Atlantic were of
Atlantic design and construction. From
Biscay there came the cog, a broad-
beamed vessel which was to serve as a
model for Italian and Catalan merchant
sailing ships, and it was doubtless in the
ports along the northern coast of Spain
that the hinged rudder was invented to
replace the two rear oars that were used
to steer ships. The triangular lateen sail
most certainly came from the Mediterra¬
nean, whilst improvements in hulls and
L cCiraiuiejitioiB-
m
©eonuê
1)01*31»
rouai iSrp»|B»Wu,ilí
ni« añüi S5I RcvääBo:
BdbnkifiHl «Sircraisonnitihi
fflwbAjaas
©fains vnSinii. iiKiiiuialB.
m \ Ma i
anppF¡>::r-»Vi)íB§
/
,i.
(Jimibripncii;!
%
É
è
j>wt!ii8#jnÄ.
the medicine of Hippocrates, Galen and
Avicenna. Indo-Islamic arithmetic and
algebra were introduced at the same time
as the Chinese "South Pole indicator",
which was used in the Mediterranean as a
veritable compass. Missionaries and mer¬
chants discovered the vast Asian conti¬
nent and the existence of the caravan
routes across the Sahara became known.
VITORINO MAGALHAES GODINHO, of
Portugal, is professor at the Faculty of Human
and Social Sciences of the University of Lisbon.
A corresponding member ofthe British Academy
and of the Royal Academy of History, Madrid,
he is the author of many articles and studies in¬
cluding a report on Cultural Identity and the
Universalizing aspects of Humanism, prepared
for the Council of Europe.
Canaries. The British Isles, however, are
sketched very approximately and, as one
moves away from the hub of scientific
knowledge and measurement, the detail
becomes blurred, as, for example, in
south-east Asia. Nevertheless, in this
same atlas, as in all maps of the thir¬
teenth and fourteenth centuries, mythical
elements still remain.
As early as the eleventh or possibly the
mid-twelfth century, from Guadalquivir
to the shores of the English Channel and
on up to Northern Ireland, people began
to settle on the sea coasts, building ports
which, by the fourteenth century, had
developed from simple centres of fishing
and other activities or small Muslim
trading posts into a network of com¬
munication and trade routes for the
barter of iron from Biscay, tin from
Cornwall, salt from Andalusia, Setubal,
the Tagus, Aveiro, Brouages and the
Breton coast, wines from Andalusia,
other parts of the ship came from Scan¬
dinavia and the North Sea countries.
Nor was the arrival of- Italian and
Catalan merchants responsible for
stimulating Atlantic trade; on the con¬
trary, the endogenous evolution of the
Iberian peninsula was the more probable
cause of oceanic and mercantile expan¬
sion from the eleventh to the fifteenth
century.
Although the annexation of the
Canaries (in the fourteenth and fifteenth
centuries) resulted primarily from the ac¬
tion of groups from Catalonia, Valencia,
Andalusia and also Portugal anxious to
capture slaves for the sugar cane planta¬
tions and to obtain sealskins for leather-
working and other industries, and despite
the colonization of the archipelago by the
Normans at the beginning of the fifteenth
century, this period should not be con¬
sidered as the backcloth to the discovery
movement nor the point at which the cen-
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Landing at the Azores; fresco painted in 1 580 by the Italian artists
Fabricio Castello and Nicolas Granello, now in the Monastery of San
Lorenzo el Real del Escorial, near Madrid. The development of the
caravel during the 1 5th century as a replacement for the galley made
possible the great voyages of discovery of the 15th and 16th
centuries.
tre of activity shifted closer to the Atlan¬
tic. Decades passed before Castile allow¬
ed its ships to fit out in ports on the
Guadalquivir in search of gold from the
coast of Mina (in present-day Ghana) or
a western route to Zipango (Japan) and
Cathay. Moreover, the French and
English turned their eyes to the ocean on¬
ly towards the end of the sixteenth
century.
It was primarily the Portuguese who
advanced the great discoveries as a solu¬
tion to the long depression that afflicted
Christendom (among other spheres) dur¬
ing the thirteenth and fourteenth
centuries.
It was towards the middle of the fif¬
teenth century that this long downward
slide was reversed. About this time the
Portuguese began to take an interest in
African spices (not to mention the ivory
they had already been seeking), yet it was
under John II of Portugal during the
1480s that they began to covet Asian
spices and narcotics, and sought to link
the north-western African group of
countries and the Islands to the route for
22
the Cape of Good Hope. This occurred at
the same time as the voyages of Colum¬
bus and the Côrte-Real brothers (Por¬
tuguese navigators who discovered
Labrador, Newfoundland and
Greenland).
Three innovations were to open the
door to the oceans. The first, the caravel,
was launched by the Portuguese in
1440-1450. It replaced the galley which,
along with the heavy carracks and com¬
bined sail/oar boats, was poorly suited to
exploration. The caravel was an adapta¬
tion of earlier Muslim, Nordic and Atlan¬
tic vessels. It was longer for similar
width, had a hinged axial rudder and
triangular sails for bowline navigation
(hugging the wind), and was light, sturdy
and manoeuvrable.
Secondly, the caravel was an invention
that made the conquest of the oceans
possible because it was related to a new
style of navigation. This did not yet imp¬
ly the use of scientific experimentation;
the scientific aspect emerged gradually.
However, systematic exploration began,
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite page. Disporting fish
adorn a Roman ornamental pond at
Utica, Tunisia. A settlement
founded in the 8th or 7th century
BC by Phoenician seafarers, Utica
later became the administrative
centre of the Roman province of
Africa.
Photo Lawson © Rapho, Pans
Centre pages
Left hand page. Above, a
Greenland eskimo in his light
canoe or kayak. Traditionally built
by shrinking seal or other animal
skins over a wooden frame,
kayaks are valued because they
enable hunters to approach their
prey silently. Below, fishermen's
boats drawn up on one of
Senegal's Atlantic beaches.
Photo Lenars © Atlas Photo, Pans
Photo Dominique Roger, Unesco
Right hand page. Above, Sa-
moans race in speedy longboats
built with the skills which enabled
the Pacific peoples to explore the
earth's largest ocean in ancient
times. Below, in the Antilles, tradi¬
tional races between the crews of
rival fishing boats are today in¬
creasingly held under commercial
sponsorship.
Photo Jack Fields © Rapho, Pans
Photo Rivera © Atlas Photo, Pans
and myths were tested against observa¬
tion. Winds and currents were noted
down, landmarks and depths were
recorded and an effort was made to
determine the position of a ship and its
course when it was on the high seas,
perhaps hundreds of miles from shore.
Regular observations of the height of the
polar star during the night watches com¬
bined with the use of other instruments
and observations made it possible to plot
courses on the open sea, especially for
return voyages or to reach difficult to
find islands in the ocean. During the
1480s, this systematic nautical practice,
coupled with important borrowings from
Judaic and Muslim sources, evolved into
navigation by the stars. Concurrently,
the works of Ptolemy and other ancient
scholars were rediscovered and type¬
setting made their dissemination possible
at the end of the fifteenth century.
Latitude, calculated according to the
midday height of the sun on land and at
sea, became a basis for scientific
cartography.
Thirdly, progress in artillery made it
CONTINUED PAGE 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
6$
'í » * 9
jg ' ,
#^c
"h*
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Ä
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
'^^^^^^em
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
COLOUR PAGE
Opposite page above
Australian aborigine fishing with a
harpoon on the Gove Peninsula, on
the Gulf of Carpentaria. He seeks
his prey at low tide and hurls his
harpoon with extraordinary
precision.
Photo © Folco Quilici, Rome
Opposite page below
Fishermen on Lake Pátzcuaro in
Mexico with butterfly nets across
the bows of their canoes.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Pans
La Malinche, between the Aztec emperor Montezuma and the
Spanish conquistador Hernando Cortes. Of Aztec origin, and sold to
the Mayas as a slave. La Malinche was offered to the Spaniards as a
"gift". She became Cortes' interpreter, adviser and mistress and bore
him a son. She was long regarded by Mexicans as exemplifying the
betrayal of indigenous values and submission to European power and
culture, but today she is seen by some as the symbol of the intermingl¬
ing of cultures and the herald of the destiny of her country which was
to be neither Spanish nor Aztec but Mexican. More than this declares
the Bulgarian writer Tzvetan Todorov, she represents "the present
condition of all men, since, though we may not all be bilingual, we are
inevitably bi-cultural or even tri-cultural."
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 22
possible to instal weapons aboard ships.
Caravels and other vessels, heavily arm¬
ed, ruled the seas, forcing contact with
other civilizations.
The first resolve to explore grew from
an economic situation that followed the
great depression and a reversal in the
trend related to the "cluster of inven¬
tions" of the middle of the fifteenth cen¬
tury. Other series of inventions sprang up
at the end of the fifteenth century,
throughout the sixteenth century and at
the dawn of the seventeenth century. The
uncovering of things hidden and the
gathering together of dispersed informa¬
tion, required new patterns of reasoning
and a new procedure, the "experiment",
a word in common usage by then that
henceforth took on new meaning.
Of course, the importance of previous
intellectual revolutions should not be
underestimated. The Arabs, for instance,
who dominated the entire Indian Ocean
and communication with the Far East
possessed a chart indicating the actual
shapes of land masses and the true loca¬
tions of their coastlines, as Ibn Khaldun
explained in 1374-1378. This chart was
called al Kunbas (compass) because the
drawing was based on the use of the
magnetic needle. It indicated the places
where the winds blew, as well as their
direction, affording mariners a means to
take bearings during voyages. However,
the following remark was added concern¬
ing the ocean: "This is not at all validfor
the neighbouring sea, and that is why
boats do not sail in those waters if they
were to lose sight ofthe coasts they would
not know how to return, all the more so
since the vapours floating in the at¬
mosphere hinder navigation. "
To measure the progress achieved over
a span of 125 years thanks to the caravel
and the great discoveries, one need only
compare the Catalan atlas to the Por¬
tuguese map known as the Cantino map
of 1502. For the first time the entire
African continent appears in its actual
profile (only slightly elongated in
longitude). India has grown into the
shape of a triangular peninsula, shorten¬
ed and simplified. Although an inor¬
dinately swelled Indochina descends too
far in latitude and Sumatra is incorrectly
placed (the Portuguese still had not sailed
beyond the Malabar coast), the immensi¬
ty of the Indian and Atlantic Oceans is
here depicted, the Atlantic being
separated in part by the Caribbean
Islands in the centre, king of Portugal's
Land (Labrador-Newfoundland) to the
north, and Brazil, whose coastline is still
incompletely drawn, to the south.
Similarly, in the north, Asia is still shown
extending as far as Scandinavia. The
Americas came very slowly to be
distinguished as a single entity, separated
from the Asian and southern continents
by the immensity of the Pacific Ocean.
De Ruysch's planisphere of 1508,
Schöner's globe of 1513, Apianus' map
of the world of 1520 and Francesco
Roselli's map of the world of 1530 still
show Greenland and Newfoundland con¬
nected to Asia, while the Atlantic joins
the ocean that washes the Asian shore,
whether between Newfoundland and the
Caribbean or between the Caribbean and
Brazil a Brazil which is the southern
continent of traditional mythical iv
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Detail from a 16th-century tapestry showing the arrival of the Portuguese navigator
Vasco da Gama at Calicut (Kozhikode) in India in 1498.
geography, at times rendered as an
island. The Globo Dourado, or golden
globe of 1528 shows the Americas to be
one solid land mass, undivided from
north to south, in which only the
southern part is detached from the
southern continent, whilst the whole is
still integrated into the enormous Asiatic
mass. New Spain was placed in Mangi
(southern China), Cathay bordered on
the Gulf of Mexico and Florida. Never¬
theless, the sea already separated
Greenland from the Land of Cod (New¬
foundland) and, in Portugal, as early as
1 50 1 , the concept of the Americas as con¬
tinents, apparent in the modified version
of Cantino's maps, had become the ac¬
cepted standard.
Another major revolution in the man¬
ner of thinking (after that of the thir¬
teenth century) manifested itself in the
drawing of the universal map of the globe
using the new scientifically-determined
latitudes, weaving the web of the world's
routes, placing mankind throughout the
entire planet. Thus was created an
organized system of researched informa¬
tion in which the observations of the
caravaneer combined with those of the
pilot against a background of expansion
and commerce.
For the first time, rather than acting on
the basis of symbols and myths, men
built physically upon the basis of
something they had defined space,
spaces and could base their actions on
rational thought. For thousands of years
the earth had been no more than a sort of
strip whose ends did not meet; the'
Americas and the Pacific were unknown,
and traffic existed only between Europe,
Eurasia and Africa north of the equator,
and between eastern Africa and the Far
East. The world was a mosaic of cultures
and civilizations, many of which were
unaware of the others' existence, and bet¬
ween which there was little or no com¬
munication. The intellectual and
Arrival of the Por¬
tuguese in Japan. This
detail from a 16th-
century Japanese
painted screen, by ar¬
tists of the Kanô
school, bears witness
to the influence which,
despite only brief con¬
tacts, Europe had on
Japanese art. After the
arrival of the Por¬
tuguese in Japan and
the two-year mission of
St. Francis-Xavier, the
Japanese made several
experimental attempts
to assimilate certain
aspects of Western art.
This example of Euro-
Asian art is purely
Japanese in technique,
but deals with scenes
and events directly
relating to Europeans.
Photo © Giraudon, Pans.
Musée Guimet, Pans.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
technical resources of the time were in¬
capable of providing a conception of the
entire globe in all its diversity, divisions
and unities; there was no means of
guaranteeing that the traveller would be
able to return to his home port. There
were but shreds of reality in a world of
mythical geography and fabulous beings.
Henceforth, man possessed a system of
representation that was both verifiable
and effective for movement and com¬
munication. Barriers that compartmen¬
talized nations disappeared, and along
with them vanished the earthly paradises,
the Eldorados, fabulous islands of eter¬
nal youth, opulent kingdoms built entire¬
ly of gold and precious stones, lost
Christendoms, impassable deserts that
were hot as furnaces, boiling seas, giants
too fearful to meet, pygmies hidden deep
inside impenetrable forests.
The spherical conception of the world
predominated, although in certain circles
of bookish tradition, it remained related
to legend and myth. The Sphaera Mundi
of the thirteenth-century English mathe¬
matician and astronomer John
Holywood (known also as Sacro Bosco)
continued to be the foundation for a
great deal of educational and even prac¬
tical training. Thirty editions appeared
from 1472 to 1500, and forty more had
come out by 1647. The Mandeville book
was also widely published, the Imago
Mundi remained influential, and an
equally large number of copies of the
widely-read Auto das Sete Partidas
(which included the fabulous letter from
Préster John describing his kingdom to
the monarchs of the Western world) were
printed.
Men reasoned in terms of navigation
and relegated all fantastic geography to
literary circles, far from mercantile and
maritime practices. The idea of the
sphericity of the planet, recognized and
analysed, was proven scientifically by
means of the shadow of the eclipse, the
way in which boats disappeared beyond
the horizon, the circumnavigation of the
earth by Magellan and his lieutenant El
Cano. Discussions concerning the length
of degrees of latitude and longitude
(from 16 2/3 to 17, 17 1/2 and 18 leagues)
prepared the way for the establishment of
uniform measurements by the Academies
(especially the French) in the seventeenth
Henry the Navigator (1394-1460) is shown bottom right in this detail from the famous
St. Vincent polyptych, by the 1 5th-century Portuguese artist IMuno Gonçalves, now in
the Museum of Ancient Art, Lisbon. Henry was the third son of king John I of Portugal.
After having "evangelized" Morocco, Henry, who at the age of 26 was named Grand
Master of the Order of Christ, decided "to extend the arms of the Cross to the ends of
the earth". To his castle at Sagres, Cape St. Vincent, he summoned freebooters, Arab
merchants, Jewish cartographers, Venetian and Genoese sea captains, Ethiopian
monks and German astronomers. In his shipyards at Cape St. Vincent he built a new
type of vessel, the caravel, which combined the best elements of naval design of the
period. He ordered his seamen to turn their backs on the Mediterranean and head south
across the Atlantic. His ships explored the west coast of Africa as far as Senegal and,
before he died, had reached the Gulf of Guinea.
century. The installation of the maritime
clock mounted on a Cardan bearing
aboard ships for calculating longitude
meant that maps were drawn in an in¬
creasingly scientific manner. The ex¬
istence of the Antipodes was proven by
experience and solid reasoning and the
notion that the torrid and Polar regions
were uninhabitable was shown to be
false. This new way of thinking, based on
experience and rational demonstration,
is quite clear in the Tradado da Esfera
(1536?) by the Portuguese navigator
Joäo de Castro, the man who first con¬
ceived the scientific expedition.
Thus, the voyages of the navigators
and caravaneers, and the search for mer¬
chandise led to knowledge (using car¬
tographic representations based on scien¬
tific systems) about States, nations, pro¬
ducts, landscapes, and people of diverse
customs on the European, African,
Asian and American continents. Between
1560 and 1570 there already existed
literature covering a large part of the
earth, from China and Japan to Brazil
and Guinea, from Canada to the Cape of
Good Hope. Travel logs, books of
weights and measures, geographies, and
chronicles of all sorts provided a fairly
accurate body of knowledge about the
entire planet, lands and seas, peoples and
landscapes.
The Lusiads (1572) by the Portuguese
author Camoes summed up this new¬
found knowledge: The marvellous no
longer depends on wondrous deeds and
fables which are but a poetic way of por¬
traying reality and building a bridge over
to Utopia, the island of love. Even before
1516, Diego Velho had already sung:
The new things before us
Are now so evident to our eyes
That never did another soul
See a world like unto it.
Vitorino M. Godinho
Elephants, palm-trees
and exotic scenes of
African inspiration adorn
this 16th-century en¬
graved silver plate. In the
centre are displayed the
royal arms of Portugal of
that period.
Photo ©Council of Europe,
Strasbourg
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Cliff Hawkins, New Zealand
Under full sail, the thoni "Maria Antoraj" leaves Bombay for the port of Veraval, Gujarat State.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
PATTAMAR BATEL
The dhow: queen of the
Indian Ocean
by Cliff Hawkins
A thousand years before the birth ofMuhammad (570 AD),
Arab seamen were sailing the waters ofthe Gulf in a new type
of vessel, a broad-beamed shallow-draught, lateen-rigged
craft known to us today under the generic name of the dhow.
Taking advantage of the monsoon winds, the dhow, in all its
local variants, soon became the queen of the Indian Ocean.
THE dhow can justly claim to be the traditional craft of
the Indian Ocean. Precursors of the dhow are believ¬
ed to have plied their trade from the Gujarat ports of
Cambay and Ghogha to Persia (Iran) and Iraq between 2500
and 1500 BC. Long before the Portuguese arrived in the In¬
dian Ocean Arab dhows were trading through the Malabar
ports of Calicut, Cochin and Quilon with Malacca, China and
the Indies. Two great religions spread to present-day In¬
donesia and beyond as a result of Arab and Indian trade with
the East, the Muslims introducing the Islamic faith about the
twelfth century and the Hindus their religion even earlier.
During the twelfth century the Omanis settled in Zanzibar,
so that when Alfonso de Albuquerque sailed into the Indian
Ocean in 1 507 it was the Omani empire that the Portuguese
had to conquer. In the meantime the speedy dhow was play¬
ing its part in the thriving Arab slave trade, and the Gulf har¬
boured fleets of Omani dhows equipped for warfare.
India's Malabar Coast is the last stronghold of the old
style sailing dhows. Owing to the vagaries of the weather
their trade is seasonal, as it always has been; but between
the months of November and April the sea becomes alive
with white cotton sails dotting the horizon as though a
regatta were in progress.
CLIFFORD W. HAWKINS, ofNew Zealand, is an authority on dhows and
has written widely on maritime history and seafaring. In addition to The
Dhow (1980), his published works include Argosy of Sail: a Photographic
History (1981) and Praus of Indonesia (1982).
Only in recent times, with the introduction of diesel
power, have dhows become less reliant on the seasonal
monsoon changes for their voyaging, but even with engines
they are still compelled to cease operations during periods
when storms of great severity are liable to strike with little
or no warning. Indeed practically all the west coast ports of
India are closed to shipping during the south-west monsoon.
But no matter what the season the dhow world continues to
embrace, like a crescent moon, the Arabian Sea from the
Comoro Isles to East Africa, the Red Sea, South Arabia and
the Gulf, right down the Indian sub-continent, taking in
Lakshadweep (formely the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amin-
divi Islands), the Maldive and Andaman Islands.
In time one learns the difference between a pattamar and
a padao or batel, or whether a dhow comes from Kutch to
the north of Bombay or from Mangalore to the south. No
longer, unfortunately, does one have occasion to
distinguish between an Indian kotia and an Arabian baghla
since the last of the baghlas with their intricately carved
transoms disappeared from service some forty or more
years ago. Sadly too, very few of the older type of kotia with
carved transom remain. Replacing them is a strikingly smart
craft, very différent in character, but still called a kotia and,
in common with the earlier craft, carrying at its stemhead a
parrot-head image, looking inboard. This motif, looking out
ahead instead of inboard, is also carried by the padaos that
frequent the Bombay area, especially Mahim Bay where
they discharge gravel for the building industry under the
shadow of an old Mogul fort.
Sambuks and zarooks are the predominant types of dhow
in the Red Sea area, booms, jalbauts and shewès in the Gulf
and batels, battelas, as well as thonis, on India's west
coast. There are numerous motor dhows too, particularly of
the boom and dhangi type. And one must not forget all the
various individual local craft that appear like a page from the iv
SAMBUK ZAROOK
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
. past such as the East African jehazis and the odams of
Lakshadweep.
Until a few years ago the Maldives owned their own fleet
of lovely kotias as did Colombo. The seamen of
Lakshadweep continue to sail their odams, vessels that
have their planking fastened together with coconut fibre or
coir in the traditional manner. The only dhows seen in Sri
Lanka these days are the thonis from Tuticorin across the
Palk Strait and, of course, the numerous fishing
catamarans.
The hulls of craft built throughout the Indian Ocean area
traditionally had their timbers dowelled and sewn together
as iron fastenings were unknown until their introduction
from Europe in the tenth century. The method of sewing the
planks of a hull together with coconut fibre can still be
observed in the few remaining Omani bedans and in a
number of Indian batels and pattamars are well as the
Lakshadweep odams. The pattamars are remarkably com¬
modious craft and, being undecked, are capable of carrying
enormous loads of timber from the Malabar coast to Bom¬
bay. They rank among the largest dhows trading under sail
alone at the present time.
Dhows have long ceased to operate on India's eastern
seaboard where road transport has completely taken over.
The configuration of much of the west coast, though, dif¬
fers greatly from that of the east and the more difficult
Malabar country will no doubt help to preserve the dhow
trade there for many more years despite the bridging of
rivers. Bulk cargoes are more conveniently carried by dhow,
particularly silica sand, sent to Bombay for the manufacture
of glass, tiles and timber. Other cargoes vary from cement
to mangoes and coconuts.
Among the largest of all the Indian dhows that make long
coastal voyages are the thonis from Tuticorin. They evolved
from a barge that was introduced into the southern port
many years ago to convey cargo between ship and shore,
there being no deep-water berth at the time, ocean-going
vessels having to remain anchored out in the roadstead.
The hull is sharp at both ends with straight stem and
stern-posts only slightly angled. It is painted all over black
with a white ribband a little below the deckline and large
registration numbers at the bow and stern. An unusual
feature is that the yards and sails are arranged so that the
vessel can go about when changing from one tack to
another instead of "wearing ship" as other dhows do. A
number are three-masted and the mizzen always carries a
small European-type gaff sail.
A unique characteristic of the crew of a thoni is that its
members, almost without exception, are of the Roman
Catholic faith, and in the forecastle where they sleep, right
in the bows below deck, you will find a wick lamp always
burning before a Madonna. Here is visible evidence of a
religion introduced to India by the Portuguese in the seven¬
teenth century. The crews of most other Indian dhows are,
however, either Hindus or Muslims. A Hindu dhow master
is known as a tindel and his crewmen are khalasis. The
Muslim master is a nakhoda, by which name he is known in
all Arabian vessels. His crew go by various names according
to the area from which they come.
How different is the Arabian scene where it is rarely possi¬
ble to observe a dhow carrying a sail much larger than a
pocket handkerchief. Even so, the hull design of the Arabian
craft closely resembles that of the dhows that sailed over a
century ago, indicating that in Arabian waters modern
technology has gone hand in hand with traditional crafts¬
manship instead of altogether opposing it.
One comes across some fine examples of mariners' art in
the dhows. At one time it was seen in the intricate transom
carving of the Indian kotias and Arabian baghtas, but, with
the demise of both types of dhow, paintwork has become
more popular. The upper hull strakes of the newer kotias are
often brightly hued and the transom stern turned into a pic¬
ture gallery or ornamented with floral design work of excep¬
tional beauty. In Arabia, particularly with the zarooks and
sambuks, ornamentation is more of a geometric nature. It is
by such decor that a dhow's origin or ownership can be
determined that, the shape of the hull, and the crew who
man her.
Because a dhow as a sailing ship was, and still is, a thing
of great beauty, all the hard work associated with it is rarely
thought of. As a diversion from their lot the Arab dhowmen
resorted to music and when entering or leaving port they ex¬
pressed their pleasure in a noisy orchestration of drums and
conch shells the like of which is not to be heard today. But
crews still chant away whenever there is a tedious task at
hand, perhaps applying shahamu (a grease and lime mix¬
ture) to a hull to protect it from the teredo shipworm or call¬
ing for strength when some heavy hauling is required.
Maybe one day we shall see dhow regattas or perhaps
some nautical festival in an effort to preserve a maritime
past. This could be an extension to existing museum ac¬
tivities. What about it Mombasa, Kuwait or Doha?
Cliff Hawkins
DHANCI
32
Drawings *- Hawkins, Edita, Lausanne
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Pacific adventure
by Peter Gathercole
OUTSIDERS often see the Pacific
world as little more than images
of tropical beauty; cloudy peaks,
sea, sunsets, palm trees and endless
beaches. The reality is otherwise.
First, consider the size. The Pacific
Ocean covers one third of our planet, and
inevitably it is a world of islands aside,
that is, from Australia, the world's
smallest continent, which lies somewhat
apart in the southwest. There are perhaps
25,000 islandsranging from New
Guinea, the world's largest, to the merest
speck of an atoll of which about 1,500
are inhabited.
PETER GATHERCOLE, British an¬
thropologist, is Dean of Darwin College, Cam¬
bridge. He has taught at Otago University,
Dunedin, New Zealand, as well as at the Univer¬
sities of Oxford and Cambridge, and is the
author ofsome 50 studies on the archaeology and
anthropology of the Pacific region.
Second, it is a world of people, five
million of whom live between the
Tropics. They inhabit a surprisingly
diverse range of environments. Both
atolls and high volcanic islands festoon
the Central Basin, although they are
fewer and more isolated towards its
eastern edge. Arcs of mountain chains,
geologically and environmentally more
varied, lie to the west, fronting Asia, and
extending as far south as New Zealand.
So the Pacific consists of more than
"desert islands" or volcanic outcrops. It
is also lofty mountains, bleak extinct
craters, dense and humid rain forests,
and in New Zealand majestic stands
of kauri pine and totara. Indeed, in that
more temperate land is every variety of
landscape.
The people themselves are equally
varied and diverse in origin. When, after
the Ice Age, Australia and New Guinea
were still joined, hunters came from
southeast Asia, about 40,000 years ago,
some of whom probably reached even the
smaller islands immediately east of New
Guinea. Among their descendants are to¬
day's Australian aborigines, whose
culture is the most continuous in human
history. The rest of the south Pacific was
settled much later, however, by people
whom anthropologists call Austrone-
sians, because they spoke related
languages from which most of the
present-day languages of the area are
derived. The Austronesians were the
world's greatest colonizers, spreading
eventually as far westward as
Madagascar, eastward to Easter Island,
northward to Hawaii, and as far south as
New Zealand.
They peopled the Pacific, including the
islands east of New Guinea, today called
Melanesia, the scatter of islands (mostly
atolls) to the north, known as
Micronesia, and the entire central Pacific
Above, sketch of a Tongan, double hulled, ocean-going tongiaki, with in the rigth foreground a small fishing canoe and in the
background visiting European ships lying at anchor in the harbour of Amsterdam Island, now Tongatapu, Tonga, as seen by the Dutch
explorer Abel Tasman in 1643. Later, the English explorer Captain Cook (1728-1779) described and encounter with a huge tongiaki
carrying 150 warriors and sailors "sailing three knots to our two and sailing us out of sight to windward before nightfall".
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
triangle of Polynesia, including Samoa,
Tonga, Tahiti, Hawaii, Easter Island and
New Zealand. Of this remarkable pro¬
gression of discovery, archaeology is to¬
day the main witness. Settlement was well
under way by 2000 BC, and was com¬
pleted before the end of the first millen¬
nium of our era.
Polynesians were skilled ocean-going
navigators, as the extent of their voyages
across the empty reaches of the Pacific
shows. Their sixty-foot, double canoes
were built essentially of wooden planks
lashed to frames with coconut fibre and
caulked with breadfruit gum. Under mat
sails they could cover 1 00 to 1 50 miles per
day. They were also masters of the art of
preserving food and could travel up to
5,000 miles on a single voyage. Naviga¬
tion techniques were probably similar to
those found in Micronesia, and these
must have been used to settle the far-
flung islands of the "Polynesian
Triangle".
It is remarkable that Micronesian
canoe captains still navigate over hun¬
dreds of miles of ocean by traditional
means. They use stars, especially when in
zenith, as destination guides ("Star com¬
passes"), also bird flight-paths, changing
water colours (green betrays the presence
of a reef) and swell patterns which give an
island's bearings.
The Tongan ocean-going double canoe
(tongiaki) was probably typical of the
large canoes of Western Polynesia.
Remarkably seaworthy, it attracted the
admiration of such European explorers
as Tasman (1643) and Cook (1773, 1774,
1777). One canoe seen by Tasman had a
hearth in use on its deck.
The sea is many things; a highway and
a source of danger, but above all a source
of food. The Pacific has the richest range
of marine fauna in the world and, not
surprisingly, Pacific islanders are fine
fishermen, using line, net or trap for a
catch that can extend to shark, turtle and
occasionally whale. Atoll inhabitants
often take at least half their food needs
from the sea: from lagoons, reefs or the
open ocean.
Building a canoe on Satawal Island (one of the Caroline Islands), Micronesia.
A SWELL WAY TO NAVIGATE.
When main ocean swells en¬
counter an obstacle, such as an
island, they rebound creating new
swell patterns which indicate the
bearings of the obstacle. With
years of training and experience
behing them, Polynesian sailors
can detect these changing swell
patterns from the slap of waves on
the hulls of their craft. Meeting the
reflected swell from an island at an
angle, they have only to steer into
the swell to head straight for the
unseen landfall.
Diagram © Courtesy of the National Geographic
Society, Washington, D. C
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Polynesian ceremonial canoe paddle
(61.5 cm) representing the human face
reduced to its essentials; used to beat
time during ceremonial singing or danc¬
ing or twirled by the dancers in rapid, in¬
tricate movements.
Guide the handle of my steering paddle,
My paddle Kautu-ki-te-rangi.
The handle heaves high Into the sky.
The endlessly receding sky.
The endlessly approaching sky.
The sky wherein resides the heavenly force.
Maori Sea Chant
Photo © Musée de l'Homme, Pans
The naturalist Joseph Banks, a
member of the British explorer Captain
Cook's first expedition to the Pacific
Ocean, which reached Tahiti in 1769,
gave the following description of Tahi-
tian fishing methods:
"In every expedient for taking fish they
are vastly ingenious. Their Seines, netts
for fish to mesh themselves in etc are ex¬
actly like ours: they strike fish with har¬
poons made of Cane and pointed with
hard wood in a more dextrous manner
than we can do with ours that are headed
with iron, for we who fasten lines to ours
need only lodge them in the fish to secure
it, while they... throwing theirs quite
from them must either mortaly wound
the fish or loose him. Their hooks... [are]
of two sorts, first that... which is used for
towing. . . The shank is made of mother of
Pearl the most glossy that can be got...
for making all manner of woven objects,
quite apart from the food value of the
fruit.
The ancestors brought a number of
plants vital for existence, including
breadfruit, cassava, taro and yam.
Ultimately these plants were joined by
the sweet potato, arriving from the
Americas by a means still not known.
Cooked in the earth oven, often with pig
meat, they form the basis even of feasts,
for the people have always associated
eating with some forms of ceremonial.
Techniques for preserving taro, bread¬
fruit, fish and meat for some time have
always existed. Indeed, it was the ex¬
istence of these techniques that enabled
the Austronesians to survive voyages
lasting as long as two months and provid¬
ed the key to the great Pacific adventure.
Peter Gathercole
Polynesian fish hooks drawn by
Joseph Banks, a member of Cap¬
tain Cook's first expedition to the
Pacific.
[there] is a tuft of white dogs or hogs hair
which serves may be to imitate the tail of
a fish. These hooks require no bait... the
people who go out with them having
found by the flights of birds which con¬
stantly attend shoals of Bonitos where
they are, Paddle their Canoes as swift as
they can across them and seldom fail to
take some. This Indian invention seems
far to exceed any thing of the kind which
I have seen among Europeans...
"The other sort of hooks which they
have are made likewise of mother of
Pearl or some hard shell, and as they can
not make them bearded as our hooks they
supply that fault by making the points
turn much inwards... they have them of
all sizes and catch with them all kinds of
fish very sucessfully I beleive".
But for many islanders the land is a far
greater resource. Even the attenuated
flora of atolls includes the ubiquitous
coconut palm and pandanus, whose
leaves, as well as those of the sugar cane
and of the sago palm are invaluable for
house thatching. The leaves are also used
Vessels of the Island of Otaha:
unsigned wash-drawing, made
in 1769 during Captain Cook's
first voyage to the Pacific,
shows Society Islanders fishing
from rafts and double-hulled
and outrigger canoes.
Photo © All rights reserved
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE ESKIMOS OF GREENLAND
The guidelines
of tradition
by Jean Malaurie
LIKE the entire Arctic region, Greenland has been thrown
open to rapid development. All the modern means
available to industrialized countries giant excavators,
ice-breakers, nuclear submarines, cargo planes, mushroom
towns, television networks are being mobilized for the ex¬
ploitation of its vast spaces.
The uranium deposits in south-west Greenland are said to be
the most extensive available to the European Economic Com¬
munity to which Greenland still belongs, although the precise
form of its membership remains to be negotiated. Substantial
oil resources are also being explored. Moreover, the future
Canadian Arctic gas route (the Arctic Pilot Project) could
become one of the West's main energy routes, traversed day
and night by giant methane-carriers, if it is established in spite
of Greenland's opposition because of the pollution risks.
Although modern Greenland is resolutely turned towards the
world of tomorrow, its attitude to these futuristic projects is
one of prudent reserve. In the midst of the frozen and particular¬
ly fragile waters which surround it, it has elected to be the pro-
JEAN MALAURIE, French geographer and explorer, is Director of
Research at the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique and at the
Ecole des Hautes Etudes des Sciences Sociales, Paris and Director of the
Centre for Arctic Studies, Paris. He is the author ofmany scientific studies
and books, including a best-selling book on the life and problems of the
Green/and Eskimos, The Last Kings of Thule, (Crowell, New York, 1956).
This miniature ivory
mask, 3.5 cm. in
height, is one of the
oldest known
specimens of Dorset
culture Inuit (Eskimo)
art. It dates from about
700 BC and comes
from the Island of
Sugluk in Hudson
Strait, Canada.
Photo © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
tector of an ecological balance, thus maintaining its people's
age-old alliance with the sea. Less than thirty years ago, people
still gathered around the oil lamp in the igloos to hear the oral
traditions from the mouths of the older generation. The younger
people are still, consciously or unconsciously, imbued with this
tradition which for them is not mere "folklore". It is this tradi¬
tion which prompts Greenland's representatives at in¬
tergovernmental conferences to insist in the first place upon
their country's inalienable historic rights, and then on the need
for the greatest care in developing these spaces.
'The sea
is our life'
by Gaba Broberg
Gaba Broberg is a Greenland Eskimo.
When questioned about his future, this is
what he said:
Greenland is our world, the world
where the Inuits live. Inuit means the
people of the Far North or, simply, men.
Ourpeople 's history is lost in the mists of
time. We probably came from Mongolia
because we look very like Asians. Our
ancestors crossed Mongolia, Siberia,
Alaska and Arctic Canada by sledge as
far as Greenland. Later, in the tenth cen¬
tury, the Vikings arrived in the fjords of
southern Greenland, probably on a sum¬
mer's day since they named our country
"Groenland", which means "green
country".
Our history does not go very far back,
but we are a bigfamily. Our language has
the same roots as the other languages of
the Arctic. We have the same traditions,
the same kind offaces and the word "In¬
uit", by which we are all known, bears
witness to our original unity.
For Inuits, the sea is life. The land is a
place apart the elsewhere. The sea (im-
okh) with its whales, seals and fish,
brings us food, clothing, material to
build our boats and to make our artefacts
sculpted from walrus teeth and stones
polished by the sea. The sea is our daily
bread. Even the children know this. To
live as a fisherman means to live together
and, above all, to share. It means to live
with one'sfamily, with thefamilies ofthe
village. The sea means living as a com¬
munity. Our lives are conditioned by the
sea. We all live along the coasts. The sea
has developed in us a culture that is in
harmony with nature.
The sea is the surface on which we
move and travel. There are fishing and
hunting expeditions, andjourneys to col¬
lect supplies whenever the fishing and
hunting have been good and we go to
fetch the meat we have stocked up. There
are also journeys to visit relations. There
are no roads between the towns.
Nowadays there are planes, but we still
use boats. In the past, we used kayaks.
Nowadays the kayak is used only for
hunting. It is operated by a single man. It
is and symbolizes the man 'sjob. Another
boat, called the umiak, is reserved for
women. The umiak is like a house which
carries the women, the children and the
old folk. All the women from the village
gather together on the boat.
Building a boat is a community task.
Everyone joins in. This is still the case in
northern and eastern Greenland.
Although the climate is harsh, it
mustn't be thought that the country is
uninhabitable, even if we cannot get
away every year for a holiday in the
Canaries or Mexico. The sun is not
everything. Ours is a land ofcold, ice and
a special kind of light. The dark season
lasts from the end of November until the
10th of January. During that period, we
never see the sun, but there are four or
five hours of light. In the past, we fished
even during this period. Nowadays, dur¬
ing the sunless season, many of the men,
especially the young ones, go to town in
search of work. But the people in the
villages are happier than the townsfolk.
In the villages, the people are always
together, like a big family, sharing
everything, meat and everything else.
Nobody abandons anybody. But this
balance is in danger of disappearing, of
being replaced by "everyone for
himself". In the past, everyone bore the
darkness of the long winter months
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Greenland's leaders never tire of repeating, both in speech
and print, that "a natural order cannot be overturned with
impunity the ice restrains paroxysmal forces". Since time im¬
memorial, they have feared these hostile forces which their
high priests, the shamans or angakogs, had learned to appease.
In spite of their limited finances and although only 10 per cent
of their resources are still derived from hunting, they refuse to
agree to the exploitation, against their people's interest, of the
vast industrial wealth lying beneath their soil.
In this young nation, there are three distinct but connected
systems of thought: shamanism, Christianity and autonomism.
The Greenlanders want time for reflection, they want to follow
their own historical sense of time, to consider their history as
it is taught by their new élite while mobilizing all their spiritual
and intellectual forces hidden under two and a half centuries of
Christian mental colonialism which, though enlightened and
positive in many ways, was nevertheless extremely
dominating. It fought and destroyed the ancestral religion
which formed the backbone of the traditional group.
Thanks to a mental revolution which will enable it more fully
to assume its identity, the Greenland of the 1980's wants to
belong to the world of today. And after all, is not the Eskimo's
profound attachment to nature and its balances a direct expres¬
sion of his ancestral religion?
The beautiful words (below) of my friend Gaba Broberg, a
young Greenlander of insatiable curiosity, reflect the proverbial
prudence of Greenland's hunters and fishermen: Imera!
Perhaps!
He, too, reminds us that a country may be developed only in
the long-term interest of its inhabitants and with due respect for
their myths.
"Much of the progress that is being superimposed on socie¬
ty, although necessary, is too new or too rapid to be always
beneficial. We must reconsider it ourselves in the light of our
history which is being rewritten by us. Time, we need time..."
Such are the comments one reads in the press and literature of
Greenland, and how can one fail to approve of such prudence?
GODDESS OF THE SEA
"We are born of the sea", say the Inuits (Eskimos), and these
hunters and fisherfolk have traditionally been dependent on the
sea for their livelihood. The goddess of the sea, nourisher and
protectress of animals, is one of the major figures of Inuit
mythology. There are several versions of the myth about her,
but they have a common ending in which a young woman, her
fingers chopped off, sinks to the bottom of the sea where she
reigns as queen. The story of the goddess is frequently por¬
trayed in Inuit sculpture, engraving and drawing. This stone
engraving. Woman of the Sea (1976) by the Inuit artist
Soroseelutu, from Cape Dorset, Canada, recalls the theme of
the chopped off fingers, from which sea creatures are born.
Drawing 'ci National Museum of Man, Ottawa
because he knew that there were others
too. Now destruction is setting in. People
still share in the small towns and villages,
but this has become impossible in the big
towns. Those who work in the towns,
who don 'tfish or hunt and are obliged to
buy their meat, those people no longer
share.
Nevertheless, the Inuits have a kindly
vision of thefuture, for the group feeling
is part of the cultural and biological
history of the Inuits and of their percep¬
tion of the world. The Inuit will always
keep his roots, his language and its
dialects because of the affective links that
bind him to his family.
My father, for instance, when he
returnedfrom hunting with a lot ofmeat,
distributed it first of all to those families
where there was no man in the house,
then to the old and then to his own fami¬
ly, always keeping a good piece for his
friends. This custom is common to all In¬
uits, whether they come from Siberia,
Alaska, Greenland or Canada.
When you speak ofpoverty, you near¬
ly always mention money. In this sense, it
is true that we are poor, but we are very
rich in human kindness.
We have been ecologists since time
began. It is nature that counts and we
reckon with nature. We are not afraid of
civilization, it can bring good and bad.
For instance, pollution was unknown
here a few years ago. Now it comes by sea
with the enormous freighters carrying
minerals which are constantly passing up
and down our coasts. Our hunters and
fishermen have had to change their
habits. Animals are abandoning our
region, the fish are moving away, our
food is disappearing. But there is still not
too much pollution. The problems are of
another kind.
The people from outside the
whites are both good and bad. Former¬
ly, it was they who decided everything,
but that is finished now. The time has
come when equality has become a right.
This equality has always been part of the
daily life of the Inuits, but nowadays
political activities in favour of equality
are modelled on European habits. The
young people have adopted a revolu¬
tionary, sometimes very aggressive
outlook and this is bad. One cannot act in
that way with a brother, be he good or
bad, who has grown up amongst the Inuit
people. One cannot suddenly say to him
"clear out, it's finished". That's not the
Inuit way ofdoing things. On the 1st May
1979, Denmark granted semi-autonomy
to Greenland, but our country is still
under Danish protection.
If I were to express a wish, I would say
first of all that I would like to remain
myself, to continue to be an Inuit with
my own language and traditions.
Without these, I am no longer anything,
I am just anybody. I don 't want anyone
to come and destroy me, as has happened
in some other countries. I fear those who
want to devour my culture. There are on
ly 45,000 Inuits in the world, perhaps
that is why I don 't want to be eaten up
and why I must survive both in body and
spirit.
In the past, Inuits had time to create.
They sculpted, and it was very well done.
Now, as in other countries, it is less well
done. Formerly, the objects we made had
a religious significance, now that is lost.
For instance, there were sculptures of
Tupilak, a protective spirit of the Inuits.
Now Tupilaks are mass-produced. He is
still there, but he no longer has any in¬
fluence. However, it's better than
nothing. In any case, we must absolutely
continue to make Tupilaks.
Formerly the Inuits sang to the rhythm
of a drum. Now, except in the North and
East of Greenland, young people use the
electric guitar, but the older people still
write poems which the young set to
music. Progress must be accepted like the
daylight.
As yet there is no tourism. When it
comes, it will certainly change the coun¬
try, but for the worse. The Inuits will
have no thought but for making money.
If we want to remain Inuit, we must re¬
main men. Humanity is not to be
bartered for money. Our vocation is to
live as a group and to share. Ofcourse we
cannot go back to our traditional life of
hunting and fishing for shrimps in a
kayak, but I hope our children will con¬
tinue to have affection, a certain human
kindness, and the feeling that we are still
a big family.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The peopling
of the Americas
by Wigberto Jiménez Moreno
WHILE it is accepted that the
earliest inhabitants of Ame¬
rica came across the Bering
Straits, controversy surrounds the
hypotheses advanced by the French
ethnologist Paul Rivet (1876-1958) who
postulated that peoples from Australia
crossed Antarctica and reached southern
Chile and Patagonia 6,000 years before
the Christian era, and that Melanesians
and Polynesians reached the Pacific
coast of north and south America.
It has been suggested that transatlantic
as well as transpacific contacts existed in
pre-Columbian times. There are those
who maintain that Phoenicians or Car¬
thaginians, or other groups from the
Near East, the Mediterranean and even
Africa reached the coasts of the Gulf of
Mexico, the Caribbean, or the Atlantic
coast of Brazil.
WIGBERTO JIMENEZ MORENO, ofMexico,
is a professor at the Mexican National School of
Anthropology and History. A member of the
Mexican Academy ofHistory, he is the author of
a number ofarticles studies and books on history
and anthropology, including A History of Mex¬
ico, written in collaboration with José Mirande
and M. T. Fernandez.
Doubt has been cast on the existence of
many of these supposed pre-Columbian
transoceanic voyages. As for Paul
Rivet's hypotheses on Australian and
Melano-Polynesian migrations, they
were initially greeted with scepticism,
especially the former, but the existence of
a limited and late Polynesian influence
has finally come to be accepted.
It also seems that a "counter-
equatorial" maritime influence was exer¬
cised from Mindanao, the Moluccas and
New Guinea, through Micronesia and
Melanesia, then via the Marshall and
Gilbert Islands, as far as Nicaragua and
the Gulf of Fonseca. In 1952, after the
Kon Tiki expedition, Thor Heyerdahl
championed the opposing thesis accor¬
ding to which influences were transmit¬
ted from the Ecuadorian and Peruvian
coasts to Polynesia, principally Easter
Island. Perhaps it would be possible to
find a Polynesian origin for American
man (from Malaysia, the Philippines, In¬
donesia and Melanesia) in the later ar¬
rival of a pre-Inca élite, for there are un¬
doubted cultural analogies between
Panama, Colombia, Ecuador and Peru
on the one hand, and Easter Island on the
other.
There is also the hypothesis of a
Japanese incursion, which supposedly
explains the appearance on the coast of
Ecuador, 5,000 years ago, of the pottery
of the Valdivia culture. However, the
alleged arrival of ship-wrecked sailors or
of an organized expedition from Japan
comes up against many objections,
notably because the Japanese Jomon
ware, comparable to that of Valdivia,
does not appear until half a millennium
later. All the same, the most cautious and
authoritative archaeologists declare that
this still remains the most plausible
hypothesis.
It is possible that some 3,000 years ago
cultural influences were propagated by
land along the Pacific and Caribbean lit¬
toral of Colombia from Valdivia to Puer¬
to Hormiga (see map). The same in¬
fluences could then have spread by sea,
first from east to west off the northern
coast of Panama, then from south to
north along the east coast of Costa Rica,
Nicaragua and part of Honduras,
perhaps continuing through the Yucatan
Channel and the Straits of Florida. In
this way they might have reached the
Atlantic coast of what is now Florida,
where at a place called Orange a form of
pottery appeared 2,000 years before the
Christian era which was extraordinarily
Map of the peopling
of the Americas ac¬
cording to the most
widely accepted
theories. It shows the
arrival of Asian
peoples from across
the Bering Strait in
North America, of
Melanesians and
Polynesians on the
coasts of North and
South America from
across the Pacific,
and of peoples from
Australia in southern
Chile and Patagonia
after having crossed
the Antarctic.
Map © J. A. Busto
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
similar to that of Machalilla on the
Ecuadorian coast which dates from the
same period and which followed the pot¬
tery of Valdivia.
In his comparative study on the earliest
cultures of the Americas, Dr. J. A. Ford
distinguishes several waves of peoples
which came by sea and settled on the
Pacific coast between Acapulco (Mexico)
and the Gulf of Paita-Sechura (northern
Peru). He also points out the existence of
coastal settlements between Puerto Hor¬
miga and Orange, and on Stallings Island
at the mouth of the Savannah river.
The US anthropologist Michael Coe
has pointed out the similarities between
the pottery of Las Conchas I and II (800
to 200 BC) from La Victoria, near the
Guatemalan port of Ocos, and that of
Chorrera (1800 to 1500 BC) in Ecuador's
Rio Guayas basin. Similarly, it is during
the first half of the last millennium of the
pre-Christian era (1000 to 500 BC) with
the flowering of Tlatilco in the valley of
Mexico, that important analogies appear
between the Tlatilco culture and that of
Chavin. Coe points to the existence of
contacts between Peru and La Victoria
during this period and even during the
preceding 500 years, suggesting that La
Victoria might have been a port of call
between a Mexican port and another port
in Ecuador or Peru (not forgetting
Tumaco in southern Colombia). Thus
the cultural influences of central and An-
dine America which are perceptible in the
pottery may have been transmitted by sea
in both directions.
How were these Pacific voyages under¬
taken? Several writers have insisted that
sail-powered rafts were the most com¬
mon means of transport throughout the
Pacific, as they were along the coasts of
Ecuador and northern Peru, that they
were still being used during the colonial
period and in the Gulf of Guayaquil at
the beginning of the nineteenth century.
Rafts were used all over the Pacific, and
the ones which bore the greatest
resemblance to the rafts which sailed
along the American coast and which
usually had a triangular sail, were the
rafts used in Polynesia and the Fiji
Islands. After the Kon-Tiki expedition it
became clear that pre-Columbian craft
were capable of making long voyages,
and Thor Heyerdahl himself showed that
pre-Columbian indigenous peoples, set¬
ting sail from the coast of Ecuador, had
landed on the Galapagos Islands. But
long boats, sometimes known as
piraguas, were also used in America,
principally for coastal navigation; they
were speedy and could carry up to seven¬
ty persons. They are already mentioned
in a document of 1525 which says that in
pre-Hispanic times such canoes, prob¬
ably from the coast of southern Colom¬
bia, Ecuador and northern Peru, sailed
as far as the mouth of the Rio Balsas to
the ancient Toltec city of Zacatula.
The maritime links between these
regions, as well as links with Nicaragua,
Costa Rica and Azuero in Panama, have
been pointed out. It is because of such
Sailing rafts at Puerto Viejo
(present-day Portoviejo),
Manabi Province, Ecuador,
from Storia dil Mondo
Nuevo (History of the New
World), by Benzoni, which
dates from 1572.
Drawing © All rights reserved
Map of the oldest Andean and Meso-American cultures according to an
"historical reconstruction" in J.A. Ford's study Formative Cultures in the
Americas (1969).
links between Andine and central
America that the art of copper
metallurgy must have been brought from
Peru to Zacatula, although not directly,
around 750-800 AD.
It should also be remembered that the
Spaniards who embarked on voyages
across the Pacific soon began to use the
Mexican ports of Navidad (near
Chihuatlan, on the borders of
Chihuatlan State and Jalisco State) and
Zihuatanejo, perhaps because these ports
had already enjoyed a certain importance
in pre-Columbian times. The importance
of Acapulco, further south, may go back
even further, and it is in the nearby town
of Puerto Marqués that Mexico's most
ancient pottery (2000 BC) has been
discovered, which must have been
brought by sea. Ancient pottery dating
from 1700 BC must also have reached
Ocos and La Victoria by sea; it has strong
affinities with the pottery of Ecuador's
Guayas basin. Finally, between Ocos and
La Victoria is Salina Cruz, the ancient
port where Cortes built ships and from
which exploration of the Gulf of Mexico
began. Near Salina Cruz live the Huave
Indians who claim that they came from
the south by sea, giving rise to the
possibility that there may be an affinity
between their language and that of the
Yungas of the northern coast of Peru,
where the Chimu empire and culture
flourished. Finally, certain decorative
motifs found on polychrome Mixtee
ceramics are similar to motifs of Andine
origin, from which it can be conjectured
that influences from across the sea
penetrated into Mexico up the Atoyac
river which rises in the Oaxaca valley.
We have deliberately refrained from
mentioning the theses regarding Chinese
influences, some very old, others dating
from the Han period, on the pottery and
decorative motifs of Teotihuacan and El
Tajin, or of Hindu and Buddhist in¬
fluences in Maya art; these theses have
been definitively refuted.
Wigberto Jiménez Moreno
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The
new Law
of the Sea
by Maria Eduarda Gonçalves
ONE of the key events on the international scene in 1982
was the adoption of the United Nations Convention on
the Law of the Sea. It is no coincidence that this should
have taken place at a time of mounting interest in the oceans,
when the rarity of raw materials on land and the search for new
resources have pushed individual States and the international
community at large to turn their attention to the sea.
The Conference at which the Convention was drawn up was
held in response to this preoccupation. It was the outcome of
a combination of factors, such as technological progress (which
today makes it possible to explore marine resources which were
unknown a few decades ago) and political changes (the achieve¬
ment of independence by many countries) which have been
reflected in the desire of the developing countries to dispose of
a legal framework that would encourage a more equitable
distribution of opportunities for the exploration and use of the
oceans and their resources, and of access to the inherent
economic and social benefits.
The new legal framework replaces the traditional principle of
the freedom of the seas. Theoretically, the seas were open to use
by any State, but in practice only a small number of maritime
powers possessed the material, financial and human resources
to navigate, fish, and even make war on one another.
The freedom of the seas was based on a set of foundations
which were both political the international society emanating
from the maritime expansion which had followed the great geo¬
graphical discoveries and scientific it was thought that the
immensity of the oceans and the volume of their resources (held
to be inexhaustible) were such that all kinds of uses could be
made of them without seriously jeopardizing their conservation.
But when the basic facts of the situation were changed, the
developing countries began to call for greater justice in the shar¬
ing of maritime areas and greater equity in relations between
States. The Convention proposes to achieve these objectives
through the attribution of sovereignty rights over different
zones. This attribution has two main forms.
On the one hand, it is recognized that coastal States enjoy ter¬
ritorial sovereignty over "territorial seas" up to twelve nautical
miles in breadth, and functional and practical sovereignty in
200-mile "exclusive economic zones" and on the continental
shelf, the extent of which is dependent on the geological struc¬
ture of the area concerned. In addition to sovereign rights for
purposes of research, exploration, management and conserva¬
tion of renewable and non-renewable resources in these zones,
the coastal States will enjoy jurisdiction where marine scientific
research and protection of the marine environment against
pollution are concerned.
CONTINUED PAGE 42
MARIA EDUARDA GONCALVES, of Portugal, is a professor at the
Universidad Nueva, Lisbon, and a member of the Portuguese National
Council for Scientific and Technological Research. She was a member of
the Portuguese delegation to the third U.N. Conference on the Law of the
Sea, a subject on which she has published many articles and studies.
40
Sampling sea water for analysis during a marine
pollution monitoring workshop in Bermuda.
THE Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission (IOC)
was created by Unesco in 1960. It now has 140 Member
States. Its principal governing body is the Assembly,
supported by an Executive Council of 32 Member States in¬
cluding those of the Chairman and four Vice-Chairmen.
The functions of the Commission are, briefly:
to define those problems, the solution of which requires inter¬
national co-operation in the field of oceanic research; and to
develop, recommend and co-ordinate international oceanic pro¬
grammes for
scientific investigations of the oceans,
related services
strengthening education, training and assistance in marine
science and its technology which call for concerted action
by IOC Member States
with interested international organizations.
Ocean science
The Commission has five major ocean science programmes.
The programme on Ocean Science in Relation to Living
Resources (OSLR), which FAO was invited to co-sponsor, is
aimed at identifying fields of ocean science that could lead to
a better understanding of the relationship between fish stocks
and ocean environmental variability, to provide the scientific
basis for fishery development and management.
The programme of Ocean Science in Relation to Non-living
Resources (OSNLR), which the UN, through its Ocean
Economics and Technology Branch (OETB) co-sponsors, is aim¬
ed at the study of regional geology and geophysical problems
so as to provide the scientific basis for mineral exploration and
exploitation.
In the field of ocean mapping, the IOC and the International
Hydrographie Organization (IHO) jointly published in 1982, the
fifth edition of the General Bathymétrie Chart of the Oceans
(GEBCO). The International Bathymétrie Chart of the Mediterra¬
nean (IBCM) was completed and printed in 1981, andthelBCM
Group of Specialists on Overlay Sheets in Geology and
Geophysics is preparing six geophysical overlay sheets. The
Geological and Geophysical Atlases of the Pacific and Atlantic
are in preparation. The preparation of specialized ocean maps
for the Atlantic and Pacific coasts of Central America, eastern
and western Africa, and the South Pacific, is under study.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
>Q/ The Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission
The Global Investigation of Pollution in the Marine Environ¬
ment (GIPME) includes marine pollution research, baseline
studies and the development of a global marine pollution
monitoring system, with a view to providing a sound scientific
basis for regulatory action to protect the marine environment.
The IOC is responsible for co-ordinating the oceanic compo¬
nent of the World Climate Research Programme (WCRP), to im¬
prove our understanding of the ocean's role in climate change
and variability. The design of an ocean-monitoring system is be¬
ing undertaken in close collaboration with the IOC-WMO (World
Meteorological Organization) Working Committee for the In¬
tegrated Global Ocean Services System (IGOSS), the IOC
Working Committee for the International Océanographie Data
Exchange (IODE) and the ICSU Scientific Committee on
Oceanic Research (SCOR).
Ocean services
The IOC provides three major ocean services to its Member
States.
The Integrated Global Ocean Services System (IGOSS) is a
joint IOC-WMO, world-wide, operational service system pro¬
viding data and information on the state of the oceans for
various marine users. These users are concerned with explora¬
tion and exploitation of biological and mineral resources of the
ocean, shipping, weather and climate, recreation, search and
rescue operations, oceanic and offshore engineering, harbour
control and pollution abatement and control.
The major objective of the International Océanographie Data
Exchange (IODE) is to collect, process, archive, retrieve and ex¬
change océanographie data on a world-wide basis. These ser¬
vices are needed to be able to minimize the hazards of ocean
and atmosphere, protect and develop coastal areas, improve
weather forecasting and marine transport, safeguard the
marine environment and make proper use of oceanic living and
non-living resources.
A global network of National Océanographie Data Centres
(NODCs), co-ordinated by the Commission, has been establish¬
ed and is gradually expanding.
The IOC also co-ordinates the Marine Environmental Data In¬
formation Referral System (MEDI) and participates actively in
the Joint FAO/IOC/UN (OETB) Aquatic Sciences and Fisheries
Information System (ASFIS).
Within the coastal zones of the Pacific and the shores of the
Pacific Islands, twenty-two nations are now members of the
IOC International Co-ordination Group for the Tsunami Warning
System in the Pacific (ITSU). Educational and publicity material
has been published, and new and additional Tsunami Wave
Travel Time charts are being computed and drafted.
Training, education and mutual assistance (TEMA)
To support the Ocean Science and Ocean Service pro¬
grammes of the Commission, the IOC organizes specific train¬
ing, education and mutual assistance in the marine sciences. To
meet the aspirations of the developing countries, the Commis¬
sion has adopted a Comprehensive Plan for a Major Assistance
Programme to Enhance the Marine Science Capabilities of
Developing Countries.
Structures
The IOC also acts as a joint specialized mechanism of the UN
organizations members of the Inter-secretariat Committee on
Scientific Programmes Relating to Oceanography (ICSPRO):
UN, Unesco, FAO, WMO and IHO. IOC assists them in the
discharge of certain of their responsibilities in the field of ocean
science, ocean services and related training, education and
mutual assistance.
To execute its programmes, the IOC works, when ap¬
propriate, through regional subsidiary bodies; notably, the Sub-
Commission for the Caribbean and Adjacent Regions
(IOCARIBE), the Programme Groups for the Western Pacific
(WPAC), for the Co-operative Investigation in the North and
Central Western Indian Ocean (CINCWIO), for the Central In¬
dian Ocean (CINDIO) for the Southern Oceans (SOC), for the
South-east Pacific (through the Joint IOC/WMO/CPPS, (Perma¬
nent Commission for the South Pacific) Working Group on the
Scientific Investigations of El Nino; and efforts are under way
to form a regional subsidiary body for the Atlantic coast of
Africa.
For its global programmes it works through specialized in¬
tergovernmental Working Committees for GIPME, IGOSS,
IODE and TEMA, and other technical subsidiary bodies such as
the SCOR-IOC Committee on Climatic Changes and the Oceans
(CCCO).
The Integrated Global Ocean
Services System (IGOSS) in
operation.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
THE NEW LAW OF THE SEA
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 40
On the other hand, seabed mineral resources located outside
the limits of the national jurisdiction are declared to be "the
common heritage of mankind", to be managed by the "Inter¬
national Seabed Authority", an organization to be created
along new and innovative lines which will hold sovereign rights
over the ' 'Area' ' in the name of and in the interest of humanity.
The powers of the Authority include those of organizing, direc¬
ting and controlling exploration. The Authority will have a sub¬
sidiary, the "Enterprise", which will be directly concerned with
exploration for and exploitation of minerals. It will also be
responsible for distributing the fruits of such activities in accor¬
dance with equitable criteria, especially taking into considera¬
tion the interests and needs of developing countries.
Although the failings of the previous régime of almost total
freedom have been recognized, the international community is
not yet mentally prepared to accept a centralized system of in¬
ternational management for the oceans on a global scale.
However, the régime for the Area [the seabed and ocean floor
and subsoil thereof beyond the limits of national jurisdiction]
constitutes an important, even revolutionary, step in this direc¬
tion, in spite of the fact that exploration activities carried out
by States and by public and private enterprises are allowed,
under contract to the Authority, parallel to those carried out by
the Enterprise.
Hence the ocean appears to be compartmentalized, whereas
it could be claimed that a unitary juridical system would be bet¬
ter suited to the natural continuity of the marine environment.
In reply it might be argued that the obligations of the coastal
States towards other States and the international community
are written into the régime of zones under national jurisdiction
and that, in a sense, these obligations offset the exclusivist
tendencies of the system.
For example, the coastal State has a duty to respect freedom
of navigation in its exclusive economic zone and is obliged both
to co-operate with other States in whose waters the same species
migrate as those which enter its own zone of jurisdiction, and
to prevent, reduce, and control pollution which may have ef¬
fects beyond the limits of this zone. A coastal State also has the
obligation to concede the exploitation of those resources in its
exclusive economic zone which it cannot fully harvest itself, to
other, disadvantaged States which are either landlocked, or,
because of special geographical characteristics, lack important
coastal zones, or whose nationals have habitually fished in the
zone in question.
But the attribution of rights is not enough. Conditions must
also be created in which States, especially the least developed
States, can effectively exercise their rights and fulfil their
responsibilities. Accordingly, it is necessary for these countries
to have access to scientific knowledge and to possess
technologies for the rational administration and conservation
of resources. This in turn presupposes the endogenous scientific
and technological development that will enable them to par¬
ticipate in scientific research on equal terms. This preoccupa¬
tion is apparent in the Convention when it prescribes duties
relating to co-operation in the exchange of information and
data, to training of personnel, and to participation in scientific
programmes.
Thus international co-operation is presented as a necessary
complement to the new rights. Paradoxical though it may seem,
the division of the oceans strengthens the need for collaboration
between States. The importance attached to the role of the com¬
petent international organizations, notably the Specialized
Agencies of the United Nations, should be seen in this context,
as a framework for dialogue and rapprochement between
States, and for the promotion of action to improve the in¬
frastructures of developing countries, especially in the marine
sciences and their applications.
The international community today has at its disposal a con¬
vention for the oceans which is global in its range and universal
in its vocation. It should not be thought that achievement of
final agreement of the text was an easy matter. It took five years
non-stop work, prolonged debates, and the development of in¬
novative negotiating techniques in which the Conference broke
new ground.
The finalization of the Convention was only possible as a
result of compromises that often gave rise to vague and am¬
biguous formulations. Consequently, there was a strong feeling
that the régime which it established should be completed by a
system of organs and procedures by which it could be inter¬
preted and applied in the event of dispute. Provisions were
made to this effect.
The Convention provides for the creation of a Tribunal for
the Law of the Sea in which the representation of the principal
legal systems of the world and equitable geographical distribu¬
tion shall be assured. Members of the Tribunal will, of course,
be persons of recognized competence in matters relating to the
law of the sea.
As noted above, the Convention declared its vocation to be
universal. Nevertheless, a number of States (including the USA
and the Federal Republic of Germany, but also Turkey and
Venezuela) have not signed it and show little intention of ratify¬
ing it or of acceding to it in the near future.
The reason for this is that the industrialized States find it hard
to accept the obligations that would be incumbent on them if
they were to accede to the Convention, especially insofar as the
seabed régime is concerned, and specifically those relating to
production limits and the transfer of technology to the Authori¬
ty. Their greatest fear is that the solution that has been found,
based on the principle of "the common heritage of mankind",
constitutes a precedent which may be used in the future as a
source of inspiration for régimes applicable to other spheres of
international relations such as outer space and the Antarctic.
There are legitimate grounds for fearing that non-
participation in the Convention, especially on the part of in¬
dustrialized countries, may call into question the very effec¬
tiveness of the system whenever it appeals to those countries to
provide the Authority with the capital and technologies it needs
for the exploration of the mineral resources of the seabed.
Nevertheless, in spite of the compromises and the am¬
biguities, the Convention sets the objectives, defines the prin¬
ciples, and establishes the operating rules of a system of
distribution of power and relations between States on which a
new order of the oceans may be constructed. It differs from
previous trends in that it presents a model and programmes of
action that call into question values and principles rooted in
liberalism in favour of greater democracy and participation in
the international community.
Maria Eduarda Gonçalves
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Ocean watch
EVERY so often a tragic accident
occurs to remind the world that
inadvertently or deliberately man
is dumping significant quantities of
potentially harmful substances into the
oceans. The situation which probably
received the widest publicity was the
catastrophe which began in Minamata
Bay, Japan, in the 1950s when methyl
mercury chloride was released into the
scientists sponsored by Unesco and other
United Nations Specialized Agencies
drew a sharp distinction between what is
happening in the open ocean, on the one
hand, and in coastal areas and enclosed
seas, on the other.
"In the open sea", they noted, "we
have not detected significant effects on
the ecosystem. Trends have indeed been
observed of the concentrations of several
Map c IOC. Uñateo
During the four-year period 1975-1978, mariners and marine scientists made over
85,000 visual observations of oil slicks and other floating pollutants over much of the
world ocean, as part of a Pilot Project on Marine Pollution (Petroleum) Monitoring (MAP-
MOPP) sponsored by Unesco's Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission (IOC)
and the World Meteorological Organization (WMO). The map above shows the loca¬
tions at which visible oil slicks were present at the time of observation.
bay from a chemical plant. Consumed in
seafood by the local people, the mercury
caused a disease of the central nervous
system which claimed lives and left many
permanently afflicted. More recently, in
March 1978, the supertanker Amoco
Cadiz made headline news when it ran
aground off the French coast. Major pol¬
lution of beaches and coastal waters was
the result of this navigational error.
Although such incidents are localized
in their impact, they inevitably prompt
people to ask the wider question is man
polluting the oceans to a dangerous and
perhaps irrevocable degree, and thus des¬
troying one of his last great natural
resources?
In a recent attempt to assess the health
of the marine environment, a group of
contaminants, some up, some down, but
these are not reflected in environmental
deterioration.
"On the other hand, effects can be
seen in semi-enclosed seas, shelf seas and
coastal zones. Semi-enclosed seas, like
the Gulf of Mexico, the Mediterranean
Sea, the North Sea and the Baltic, receive
substantial contamination. . .Ina number
of local 'hot spots', the ecosystem
balance has been disturbed. In one area
of the North Sea (the Waddensee), and in
the Baltic, pollution has been implicated
in reducing the populations of some
marine mammals."
Coastal waters are under pressure
because of the continued growth of
human settlements along the coast, the
increase in coastal recreation, and the
concentration of industrial development
in coastal areas. They are vitally impor¬
tant to man because it is in them (and to
a much smaller extent in the upwelling
areas of the oceans) that the vast bulk of
marine fishery resources are located.
Today, since the highest concentrations
of metals, synthetic compounds such as
DDT, petroleum hydrocarbons, suspen¬
ded solids and litter are found in these
waters, coastal fisheries are particularly
exposed to the effects of pollution. In
some cases "fisheries have been stopped
in limited areas, sometimes leading to
suspicion among consumers that fish
caught elsewhere in adjacent areas may
be contaminated, thus causing problems
for the marketing of fish from whole
regions".
The scientists, whose report has appea¬
red as "The Review of the Health of the
Oceans" (GESAMP Reports and Stu¬
dies, N° 15), were members of a working
group set up by the Joint Group of
Experts on the Scientific Aspects of
Marine Pollution (GESAMP), an ad¬
visory body of specialists which provides
scientific advice to its sponsoring organi¬
zations (1), including Unesco, and to its
Intergovernmental Océanographie Com¬
mission (IOC).
Through the IOC, Unesco has for
some years played a leading role within
the United Nations system in focusing
attention on the scientific problems of
marine pollution, especially as it affects
the world ocean, and today the IOC
through its Marine Pollution Monitoring
(MARPOLMON) system, as part of its
"Global Investigation of Pollution in the
Marine Environment" (GIPME) is,
through a network of regional and global
activities, laying the basis for obtaining
the data required to keep the health of the
oceans under continuing review.
Defining pollution as "the introduc¬
tion by man, directly or indirectly, of
substances or energy into the marine
environment resulting in such deleterious
effects as harm to living resources,
hazards to human health, hindrance to
marine activities including fishing,
impairing of quality for use of sea-water,
and reduction of amenities", the
GESAMP specialists examined the
effects of five groups of potential con¬
taminants: sewage; certain synthetic
substances such as halogenated hydro¬
carbons (e.g., DDT and polychlorinated
biphenylsPCBs); petroleum; trace
metals which, though naturally present in »
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
sea-water in minute .quantities, have
significant adverse effects on organisms,
when they exceed their natural level of
concentration; and radionuclides or
nuclear wastes.
Suclrsubstances reach the oceans in a
variety of ways, ranging from dumping
and spillage to discharge from factories
or cities. They may be borne either direct¬
ly or indirectly via rivers, which have
been described as "the prime mover of
materials from the continents to the
oceans", or transported through the at¬
mosphere and washed in by rain. Many
materials enter the oceans through
natural processes; geological weathering
and volcanic activity, for instance, are
important natural sources of the trace
metals that are injected into the marine
environment. All the natural elements
are found in the ocean, and many of
them, such as copper, when they occur at
natural levels, are nutrients for marine
flora and fauna. The challenge facing en¬
vironmental scientists is to determine at
what level these concentrations become
toxic, in other words to establish when
the limits of the ocean's tolerance are be¬
ing reached.
Sewage. The GESAMP report
flashes a warning signal where sewage is
concerned, It notes that "the use of the
coastal zone for sewage disposal is
worldwide and the input is increasing",
but "problem areas are local rather than
global, and coastal rather than oceanic.
Sewage does present a direct risk of infec¬
tions to humans on some beaches,
especially during recreational seasons.
Discharge on or near shellfish beds
presents a greater risk to human health
through the consumption of con¬
taminated seafood."
The halogenated hydrocarbons, in¬
cluding polychlorinated biphenyls
(PCBs). Here the picture is somewhat
different. These compounds reach the
oceans primarily in the form of vapour
and, partly because of their world-wide
transport by wind and ocean systems, can
be detected at considerable distances
from their sources. DDT, which has
received wide attention because of the
ecological damage it has caused, such as
reproductive failure in birds due to egg
shell thinning, toxicity and reproductive
failure in fish and some marine mam¬
mals, is now virtually ubiquitous in the
marine environment; it is found in
plankton in every ocean from the Arctic
to the Antarctic. It has been used
primarily in agriculture as a biocide for
the protection of cotton crops and as an
anti-malarial agent. It is estimated that
between 1971 and 1981 over 500,000 tons
of DDT were used in anti-malaria pro¬
grammes. Today, several countries have
placed restrictions on its use because of
its adverse effects on non-target organ¬
isms. The PCBs have a wide variety of
uses ranging from dielectrics for trans¬
formers to the manufacture of paints and
printing inks.
On the subject of PCBs, the GESAMP
report notes that "There is no confirmed
record of human illness having been
caused by consumption of marine
organisms due to their content of PCBs,
although "PCBs residues in some marine
organisms exceed the level set by some
national authorities to safeguard human
health." As for DDT, "its residues are
not likely to place man at risk, but fear of
contamination from this and other
sources could damage the marketability
of seafood."
Petroleum. It has been estimated
that over six million metric tons of
petroleum hydrocarbons are injected an¬
nually into the world's oceans, and in the
last decade several spills and oil-well
blow-outs have occurred, discharging
large amounts of oil that have con¬
taminated the sea. Certain fractions of
crude oil are highly toxic to marine
organisms. All the same, there is an in¬
creasing body of knowledge to indicate
that not only is the open ocean not in
danger of becoming a wasteland because
of oil infections, it is actually
assimilating what is being injected
reasonably well. Once again, this is not
the case with coastal areas and semi-
enclosed seas, where spills from tankers
and offshore drilling represent only a
small part of the total input of fossil-fuel
hydrocarbons, and sewage, industrial ef¬
fluents, river and urban run-off and at¬
mospheric rainout and fallout have been
identified as the significant sources.
Discussing the effects of environmen¬
tal damage from oil, the GESAMP
report notes that "oil spill effects on
pelagic communities are rarely drastic,
and recovery is usually a question of
weeks or months. Impact on intertidal
and subtidal communities may be severe,
with recovery taking years or decades,
particularly in shoreline communities
where oil penetrates the sediments; and
oil on beaches can seriously affect their
amenity as recreational areas. Birds are
particularly at risk, but there is no
evidence that oil alone can threaten
species survival."
However, the situation may change in
the future, since "the extension of oil ex¬
ploration into extremely hostile areas
may give rise to major spills... and pro¬
duction is expected to increase in cold
areas where oil degrades more slowly".
Metals. Recent advance in analytical
techniques for monitoring metals have in
many cases resulted in a downward
reassessment of the levels of metals in
seawater in the open oceans. In inland
waters, on the other hand, pollution by
metals has been observed as a conse¬
quence of river, industrial and domestic
sewage discharge or of direct dumping.
The one exception to this pattern appears
to be lead which, like DDT, is carried to
the open oceans through the atmosphere
after being used as an anti-knock agent in
internal combustion engine fuel.
Increased concentrations of lead have
been observed in some open ocean areas.
Radionuclides. Since the very incep¬
tion of atomic energy exploitation, it has
been recognized that radionuclides, if
released indiscriminately into the en¬
vironment, can pose severe threats to
human health as well as have detrimental
effects on the environment. Man began
injecting nuclear material into the oceans
in the mid-1940s, a process which grew in
importance over the next two decades,
primarily as a result of the atmospheric
testing of nuclear devices. Since the
cessation of such testing by all but two
countries, concern has shifted to the
potentially adverse impact of effluents
from nuclear reactors on the coastal en¬
vironment. In addition, there is always
the possibility of a massive release of
nuclear material as the result of an acci¬
dent. Various international instruments
and guidelines for the disposal of
radioactive wastes into the oceans exist,
and in the opinion of the GESAMP
specialists no public health problem
should arise if these regulations are
followed.
The study of the ways in which man is
altering the chemistry of the oceans is still
in its infancy. The measurement of some
pollutants, such as radioactivity, is
relatively straightforward. Some other
potentially toxic substances occur in such
low concentrations that it is often dif¬
ficult to obtain reliable analyses. Only a
few years ago it was estimated that less
than a dozen laboratories throughout the
world were capable of measuring DDT or
petroleum components in seawater.
Surveillance of the health of the oceans
is clearly beyond the scope and resources
of a single nation or a single group of na¬
tions. In developing its Global Investiga¬
tion of Pollution in the Marine Environ¬
ment and the Marine Pollution Monitor¬
ing System (MARPOLMON), the IOC is
collaborating with the leading United
Nations Specialized Agencies and other
relevant regional and international orga¬
nizations. The overriding purpose of its
work is to see that the global monitoring
of the signals that foretell impending
damage to the marine environment will
be carried out using standardized meth¬
ods of analysis so that data produced by
scientists from the different world re¬
gions can be made comparable. This calls
for extensive training for analysts and
continual intercalibration exercises the
first steps in the global vigilance on which
the health of the oceans depends and
for an active programme of mutual assis¬
tance with a view to creating the required
marine research capabilities, particularly
in the developing countries.
(I) The International Maritime Organization, the
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations, Unesco, the United Nations, the World
Meteorological Organization, the World Health
Organization, the International Atomic Energy
Agency, and the United Nations Environment
Programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Where land
meets sea
TWO persons out of three today live in coastal regions, near the sea,
on the shores of continents or on islands. This situation, which is
the consequence of population growth and population movements
as well as of economic development, concerns regions with a delicate
balance, very often areas of ancient civilization whose prosperity was largely
based on shipping and maritime trade and also on the relatively high produc¬
tivity of the coastal environment.
The coastal environment is highly conducive to the establishment of human
settlements, both permanent and seasonal, urban and Industrial. Coastal
zones, In particular, are affected by the scale of seasonal tourism. One-third
of world tourism is thus concentrated on the coasts of the Mediterranean and
the result is that in some areas the whole coastline is a sort of continuous
built-up area.
The coastal environment is the product of the complementary effects of the
terrestrial and marine environments and constitutes a complex system mark¬
ed by the distinctive chemical properties of the waters and by a set of very
evolutive ecosystems and geomorphological entities such as beaches,
estuaries, lagoons, mangroves and coral reefs, environments which are all
vulnerable, and particularly exposed, to the effects of modern development.
Warnings are indeed being raised In one part of the world after another to
alert public opinion to the damage caused to these environments by degrada¬
tion and pollution.
It should be added that the Influence of the sea on the terrestrial environ¬
ment extends far beyond the coastline itself; the hinterland is, too, subjected
to strong economic and social pressures, often tending in contradictory
directions.
Only an interdisciplinary approach therefore makes It possible to under¬
stand the functioning of coastal environments. Coupled with data on the
physical, chemical and biological characteristics of those environments, the
social and human sciences provide a further basis for a more rational
management of coastal areas. No longer is it possible to disregard them or
simply consider them as being condemned to insalubrity and as a dump for
industrial waste; on the contrary, they have to be recognized as constituting
essential poles of development.
The countless islands of the world, especially those having an area of less
than 1 0,000 km2, are subject to the same pressures as continental coasts and
moreover are confronted by difficulties of a specific nature. Island
ecosystems are exceedingly vulnerable and the efforts made to increase pro¬
duction to meet development needs or respond to population pressure come
up against especially acute spatial limitations. In the light of the limited size
of islands and their isolation, the exploitation of local resources by the
islanders takes on particular Importance. In a large number of islands, ter¬
restrial resources, especially agricultural resources, are no longer adequate
to satisfy the needs of a growing population; the exploitation of coastal and
marine resources thereupon becomes an economic Imperative. This is a pro¬
blem of concern to all countries that are responsible for managing more or
less numerous groups of islands and of particular concern to island States.
Coastal wetlands and shallows, especially estuaries and
mangrove swamps, provide rich and abundant nutrients on
which an estimated two thirds of the world's fisheries depend.
Today, coastal wetlands in many parts of the world are being
degraded or destroyed by pollution and industrial development,
while some tropical regions mangroves are being cut down for
use as firewood. Below, mollusc-encrusted mangrove roots in a
mangrove swamp at Elinkine, Senegal. Research on mangroves
and other coastal marine ecosystems is promoted by Unesco's
Division of Marine Sciences through the Major Inter-Regional
Project on Research and Training leading to the Integrated
Management of Coastal Systems (COMAR). ,
Unesco's interdisciplinary research programme on the minor
islands of the Mediterranean is a research project on insular
ecosystems which offers a unique opportunity to study in
relatively controlled conditions the complete array of ecological,
economic and social factors which influence the relationship
between man and the biosphere. Launched by Unesco's Human
Settlements and Socio-cultural Environment Division, the pro¬
ject is being carried out in collaboration with the Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) National Committees of Greece, Italy, Malta
and Tunis. In its first phase the project concerns the islands of
Skiathos-Skopelos (Northern Sporades), Salina (Aeolian
Islands), Gozo (Malta) and the Kerkennah Islands (Tunisia),
above.
Furthermore, the island system and the conditions that define it lend
themselves to population/resources/environment/development interaction
studies with a view to obtaining precise information about the nature and ex¬
tent of the changes wrought by human activities in environmental manage¬
ment operations. It has thus been maintained that islands, where the incom¬
ings and outgoings of persons and products can be readily measured, con¬
stitute veritable laboratories for interdisciplinary studies. This distinctive
feature facilitates an integrated scientific approach to options concerning the
management and development of these ecosystems.
Unesco's Major Programme X (The Human Environment and Terrestrial
and Marine Resources) Includes a programme specifically devoted to the
Management of Coastal and Island Regions. The purpose of this programme
is to promote the integrated management of coastal zones and islands. It is
intended to foster international co-operation for the purpose of gaining a bet¬
ter understanding of the nature and functioning of coastal and island
systems; to further effective collaboration between specialists in terrestrial,
aquatic and marine environments and sociologists, economists and land-use
planners within the framework of concrete field projects; and to facilitate the
integration of scientific, socio-cultural and economic information for decision¬
making purposes.
In the various fields referred to, research programmes inevitably assume
an international dimension. In addition, in the field of the marine sciences,
particular requirements make themselves felt in respect of international co¬
operation, in view of the new order for the oceans as it emerges from the con¬
clusions of the United Nations Conference on the Law of the Sea.
Unesco's international scientific programmesthe International
Geological Correlation Programme (IGCP), the International Hydrological
Programme (IHP) and the Man and the Biosphere programme (MAB), and
those of the Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission (IOC)are thus
particularly well adapted to the nature of the tasks to be performed: these pro¬
grammes constitute a means of putting into effect a type of international co¬
operation which is shaped by the very nature of the fields of study and the pro¬
blems to be solved. They contribute to a better understanding of world or
regional phenomena, to the growth of knowledge about the natural resources
that are available at the national level, and to the strengthening of the
necessary scientific capabilities. They provide a means of exchanging
knowledge and encourage bilateral, subregional or regional co-operation,
with the result that the effort put into them undergoes a remarkable multiplier
effect. These programmes also require an interdisciplinary approach and
foster the establishment of working relations among research workers,
decision-makers and operational personnel with a view to the identification of
problems and the application of research findings.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
IB ra
lb IS al
Unesco's General Conference
The 22nd session of Unesco's General
Conference opened in Paris on 25 Oc¬
tober 1983. Mr. Said M. Tell of Jordan
was elected President of the Conference,
which is composed of the government
representatives of Unesco's Member
States, whose number rose to 1 61 when
St. Christopher-Nevis joined the
Organization on 26 October. As we go to
press, the Conference, which ends on 29
November, has not completed its work.
An account of its proceedings will appear
in a forthcoming issue of the Unesco
Courier.
Rainbow days
In 1979, on the occasion of the Interna¬
tional Year of the Child proclaimed by the
United Nations, L'Association des Amis
des Journées Arc en Ciel ("Association
of Friends of Rainbow Days") was
created in Toulouse, France. Its aim was
to organize periodic gatherings at which
children from different countries could
take part in sports and cultural activities,
and adults could meet to compare their
ideas and experiences as educators. A
first meeting was held in 1980. At the
second, held in Toulouse from 29 August
to 5 September 1982' with the support
of numerous organizations including
Unesco, 180 children from 18 countries
enjoyed a variety of sporting and manual
activities such as pottery-making, and
followed road safety and first aid
courses. They also discovered the ar¬
tistic treasures of the region and learned
more about the different cultures to
which they belonged. From 1 to 3
September, 200 persons from 16 coun¬
tries took part in an international sym¬
posium on the theme of "Games, Com¬
petition, Sport and the Child". The
Association is preparing a third meeting
which will be held in Toulouse in 1985.
World Poetry-Childhood Day
In 1976 a World Poetry-Childhood Day
was founded at the International Poetry
Biennale at Knokke, Belgium. It is
celebrated each year on 21 March, the
first day of spring, by children under the
age of 13. Held under the patronage of
Unesco (in 1979) and leading world
figures, the occasion has so far been
devoted to the following themes: Myself
and the others; Words to banish war;
Words to build peace; The world is our
home. The theme of World Poetry-
Childhood Day for 1984 will be: Let's
build a world without fear. Parents,
educators and children who would like to
know more about this event should write
to: World Poetry-Childhood Day, Avenue
des Ortolans 95, 1170 Brussels,
Belgium.
UNICEF greeting cards
Thanks to the proceeds from the sale of
its greeting cards, gifts and stationery,
the United Nations Children's Fund
(UNICEF) is today helping needy children
and mothers in over 100 countries of
Asia, Africa and Latin America by pro¬
viding basic health care, safe drinking
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the -authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street. New York. U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
water, improved nutrition and education.
This year's cards are now on sale at
UNICEF sales points throughout the
world. The collections of standard, air¬
mail and mini-format cards feature a
wide variety of designs donated by ar¬
tists and museums in many countries.
They include a 19th-century manuscript
from Kashmir, Indonesian batik designs,
and paintings from China, Japan and
Senegal. Also on sale are a 1984 wall
calendar for children and an engagement
diary with 54 colour illustrations on the
theme "/festivals and Celebrations".
Shown here, card featuring a work by the"
Spanish painter Joan Miró.
BOOKSHELF
Recent
Unesco publications
Racism, Science and Pseudo-
Science. Eminent international scien¬
tists critically examine pseudo-
scientific theories used to justify racial
discrimination in relation to their
respective fields: genetics, an¬
thropology, psychology, sociology,
and history. No. 8 in Unesco's "In¬
sights" series. 1983, 162 pp. (38 F).
Education in Latin America and the
Caribbean: Trends and Prospects,
1970-2000, by José Blat Gimeno,
1983, 190 pp. (45 F).
The Transition from Technical and
Vocational Schools to Work. Reports
from 17 countries. 1983, 100 pp.
(20 F).
Empirical Research in Education, by
G. De Landsheere. An overview of
research techniques and information
about research institutes world-wide.
1982, 113 pp. (30 F).
Quality of Life: Problems of Assess¬
ment and Measurement. 1983, 117
pp. (30 F).
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kim U-Yearn (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Alchis Angelou
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
S to
<U >
io
oo
, o
_z
o
o<
0.
¡<
OZ
oo
It
i<"
CE o_
o5
oo
ceo
<o
Oh
oo
ten
m a.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1983
January
A COURSE FOR THE FUTURE (Unesco's action plan for the next six years).
Where the future begins (A.-M. M'Bow). I. World problems. II. Education for all. III.
Communication in the service of man. IV. Education policies. V. Education, training
and society. VI. Science and development. VII. Information systems and access to
knowledge. VIM. Action for development. IX. Science, technology and society. X.
Human environment and land and sea resources. XI. Culture and the future. XII. Pre¬
judice, intolerance, racism and apartheid. XIII. Peace, international understanding,
human rights and the rights of peoples. XIV. The status of women.
February
BOROBUDUR. Indonesia's first Buddhist sanctuary (R. Soekmono). How
Borobudur was saved (R. Soekmono, C. Voûte). Bolívar the Liberator (A. Uslar-
Pietri). From Jacmel to Santa Marta (R. Depestre). Tashkent (E. Yussupov). A
treasury of manuscripts (M. Khayrullaev). The reindeer herdsmen of Lapland (P.
Aikio). A strategy for disarmament (C. Ene).
March
COMMUNICATIONS. In the service of man. World Communications Year (R. E. '
Butler). Doubts, fears, hopes (J. Ping). The challenge of the chip (A. F. Baryshev).
Anatomy of the computer. Japan hooks up for the 21st century. Computers and
literacy in traditional languages (R. W. Lawler, N. Niang, M. Gning). The computer
generation (O. Glissant, J.-C. Maillard, M. Vertes). Communications technology
and development (I. de Sola Pool). Satellites. Community radio for Kenya (J. Mills,
J. Kangwana).
April
THEATRE OF THE WORLD. Latin America (A. Boal). Europe (R. Hayman). Shared
disillusion (M. Cournot). Africa (A.-S. Malanda). Japan (M. Yamaguchi). Haiti (F.
Morisseau-Leroy). Egypt (M. Wassef). Soviet Union (N. Kornienko). Yugoslavia (J.
Cirilov). India (S. Awasthi). Spain (X. Fabregas). Finland (I. Niemi). China (Lu Tian).
United States (E. Oatman). Thailand (M. Chitakasem).
May
EDUCATION: The way ahead. Education for all (A.-M. M'Bow). Education in a
changing world (S. Tanguiane). Stemming the tide of illiteracy (Le Thánh Khôi).
Milestones to the learning society (T. Husén). Six pioneers of modern education (H.
Rohrs). The education gap (H. L. Maiga). The media in the classroom (M. Suchon).
June
THE WORLD OF THE PEASANT. The forgotten ones of Latin America IG.
Almeyra). What future for Africa's silent majority? (J. M. Ela). A village called Nan¬
pur (P. Mohanti). Changing pattern of Chinese agriculture (Ma Shiyu). The Kolkhoz
of Chtcherbani (Y. Novikov). Peasant values (E. Le Roy Ladurie). The world of the
mid-west farmer (D. Peasley). Bulgaria's post-war revolution in farming (M. Kazand-
jlev). The new nomads (J. Fauchon).
July
A TREASURY OF TONGUES. A talking animal (A. Burgess). National languages
and cultural identity (C. Fyle). Beyond Babel (E. Glissant). Black English (G. C.
Balmir). Indian languages of Latin America (R. Bareiro Saguier). Creole, language of
the Caribbean (L. F. Prudent). When Greek meets Greek (A. Kedros). The first one
(bilingual problems of Québec) (G. Mirón). India, a multilingual subcontinent (D. Pat-
tanayak). Story of an alphabet ( V. M. Sanghi). Spain's language mosaic (F. Vallver-
dú). The culture shock of language learning (P. Charaudeau). The translation explo¬
sion (A. Lilova). Bulgaria's first language laboratory (I. Pekhlivanov).
August
EDUCATION STRATEGIES. Learning for a lifetime (E. Gelpi). Unesco's
Associated Schools Project. World human rights congress in Costa Rica. What's
new in science teaching? (M. Malitza). Sowing the seeds of democracy in India (A.
N. Rai). Aesthetic education in Bulgaria (K. Goranov). Towards equality for women
in education (M. Eliou). Islam's Qur'anic schools (A. A. El Koussy). Ghana's univer¬
sity of science and technology (F. O. Kwami). A model school for blind children.
Some future prospects (B. Kluchnikov).
September
RIVERS. The moving highways of history (E. Turn). The Amazon (T. de Mello). The
Congo (H. Lopes). The Danube (F. Heer). The Ganga (L. Bhattacharya). The
Mississippi (J. Seelye). The Nile (L. Soliman). The Volga (L. Likhodeev). The Yangtze
(Bai Hua).
October
GREAT ANNIVERSARIES. Martin Luther (J.-N. Pérès). Leonhard Euler (E. A.
Fellmann). Stendhal (F. W. J. Hemmings). Richard Wagner (M. Watanabe). Karl
Marx (G. Labica). IN. I. Lapin). Gibran Khalil Gibran (G. Shukri). Franz Kafka (M.
Nadeau). The United Nations University (Soedjatmoko).
November
RACISM. Race, prejudice and myth (M. Leiris). The historical roots (M. V. Kriukov).
Ethnocide. Racism today: "Us" and "Them" (A. Memmi). Apartheid: the shameful
record (B. Davidson). Unesco, the United Nations and South Africa. Malice through
the looking-glass (T. Ben Jelloun). Myths under the microscope (A. Jacquard). The
cultural counter-attack (M. do Céu Carmo Reis). Mixed metamorphosis (R. F.
Retamar).
December
CIVILIZATIONS OF THE SEA. The Phoenicians (M. Fantar). How Arab sailors
read the stars (R. Morelon). The Vikings (M. Magnusson). Africa's coastal and island
civilizations (I. Kakél. Songs of the pirogue (F. M'Boulé). Equatorial Guinea (C.
Gillard). Cape Verde (E. Andrade). From myth to reality (V. Godinho). The dhow (C.
Hawkins). Pacific adventure (P. Gathercole). The Eskimos of Greenland (J.
Malaurie, G. Broberg). The peopling of the Americas (W. Jiménez Moreno). The new
law of the sea (M. Gonçalves). The Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission.
Ocean watch. Where land meets sea.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58AGipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066: Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals-
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW Sub- agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, P.O. Box 175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000 - AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq
Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco
publications agent Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060
Brussels, CCP000-0070823-1 3 - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co Ltd ,2182 St. Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que H3H 1 M7. - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O Box 88, Beijing
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0
Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N T L ,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display), Zahranicni
literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa
Verlag Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava
CSSR. - DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo - ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P 0 Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuia 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie
de I'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus
Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G. D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish
editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publica¬
tions- Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps
only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. -
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra, The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast, The University Bookshop of Legón,
PO. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HKI Ltd.,
5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 1 2 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen.
Swindon Book Co., 13-1 5, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong
Government Information Services, Publication Centre,
Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Konyvesbolt, Váci u 22, Budapest V, A K V Konyvturosok
Boltia, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh,
Hyderabad 500001 (API; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Banga-
lore-560001 ; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 1 7 Park Street, Calcut¬
ta 70016, Scindia House, New Delhi, Publication Unit,
Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex AFO Hutments, Dr. Ra-
jendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto Iskandardinata
til, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl Gadjah Mada 109, Jakar¬
ta, Indira P T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat.
IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co , 28, Vessal
Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran, Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 1 88 Enghelab Ave.
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158 P 0. Box 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd, Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin 1 2; Tycooly Inter¬
national Publ Ltd 6 Crofton Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co.,
Dublin. - ISRAEL. ABC. Bookstore Ltd , P.O. Box 1 283. 71
Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000. JAMAICA. Sangster's
Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc , 37-3 Hongo 3-chome
Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571 , Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean. National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait,
for the Unesco Courier, Farafalla Press Agency, P O. Box
SAFA 4541, Kuwait. - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre,
P.O. Mazenod Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Code
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribu¬
tion, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie
Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-11.- MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. -
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30. Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only: D&N
-Faxon B V , P O Box 197,1 000 AD Amsterdam; for publica¬
tions only KEESING BOEKEN B V , Postbus 1 1 1 8, 1 000 BC
Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-
Eddine N.V.. P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. -
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 1 30,
Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street,
P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P O. Box 1104,
Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P O 286, The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers). Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1 ; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A. S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6 - PAKISTAN. Mirza
Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729,
Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co , 926 Rizal
Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404 POLAND Orpan-
Import, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. POR¬
TUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé, New Service Ltd , Kmgsgate House, P.O Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (SI Pte Ltd Times
Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261. SOMALI
DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P O. Box 951 , Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri
Building, Church Street, P O. Box 924, Pretoria For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency,
P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O B
244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop. P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum - SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C E.
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan 1 2, Box 1 6356.
10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier Svenska FN
Forbundet. Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. All publications Europa Verlag. 5
Ramistrasse Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, POB 9030 Dar-es-Salaam THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company,
1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istambul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM. H M Stationery Office.
H.M.S.O , P.O. Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt.
Bookshops in London. Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birm¬
ingham, Bristol, for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd , 1 22
King's Cross Road, London WC IX 9 DS. - UNITED
STATES. Unipub, 1 1 80 Av. of the Americas New York -NY.
11036. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kmga, Moscow,
G-200 - YOUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11. Zagreb;
Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana, Nolit, Terazije
27/11, Belgrade. - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales IPVT) Ltd .
67 Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
i
*»-." . S
SH -^"8-
u
í§í*h«'
JflflHHH
fSSB
]]>
</page>
</document>
