<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074770eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window
open on the world
À
arms race
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
-£*
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Tunisia
Phoenician fertility symbols
In the ninth century BC Phoenicians from Tyre or Cyprus founded the city of Carthage on a site near to
that of modern Tunis. These terra-cotta figurines of mother-goddesses soon to give birth were unearthed
in a sixth-century-BC Carthage tomb where they had been placed as symbols of life and fertility. Another
figurine (25 cm high, 9 cm wide) so similar to that shown at right, that both may have been made in the
same mould, has been found In an eighth-century-BC tomb at a Phoenician site at El-Aksib, Lebanon.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco CoUFÍCF
APRIL 1979 32nd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
yearl. For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.: 13) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A. /
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Peter Mwombela (Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
Editors:
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
Dutch Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu Edition
Catalan Edition
Malaysian Edition
Korean Edition
Swahili Edition
page
10
15
17
18
20
26
29
31
34
THE WILL FOR PEACE
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
THE ARMS RACE
Military expenditure: the ever-rising tide
New technologies for overkill
The quality spiral
The deadliest weapon of them all?
Millions of victims before a shot is fired
Human want the spin-off from military waste
Three myths that die hard
The military establishment
Can the arms race be halted?
IN BRIEF
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
TUNISIA: Phoenician fertility symbols
Cover
Like a juggernaut defying all attempts to
control it, the arms race today continues with
mounting speed and Intensity. The nightmare
threat of nuclear war still haunts mankind,
and the world's arsenals grow in size and
sophistication, fuelling tensions and
engendering a mindless waste of resources
which could help to alleviate the plight of
millions whose basic needs are not met.
Cover shows Testigos (Witnesses) a vision of
this modern nightmare by the Spanish painter
Juan Genovés.
Photo © Marlborough Fine Arts, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The will
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
SINCE 1945 the disaster of a third world war has been
avoided; but at what price has this been achieved?
For how many days have the guns been silent
throughout the world? Although the field of conflict has
shifted towards the poor countries, children, whose lives
are no less precious than anyone else's are still dying as a
result of war.
Yet the nations, that in this twentieth century alone have
sacrificed more than 100 million human beings on the altars
of war, continue, as if caught up in the gears of a runaway
machine, to dissipate a vast proportion of their genius, of
their energy, of their resources, on the manufacture of
lethal weapons, ever more sophisticated and devastating.
To these nations, the question of disarmament represents
an unavoidable challenge.
If we take up this challenge, not only will mankind be
delivered from the menace of a hecatomb without prece¬
dent but it will also acquire the means to win the struggle
against poverty, sickness, ignorance and the other afflic¬
tions which beset so many peoples.
If only a proportion of the material and human resources
devoted to preparation for war were assigned to the cause
of development, it would suffice to change the face of the
earth, lessen the widening gulf between rich and poor coun¬
tries, and reduce the areas of poverty which continue to ex¬
ist in many industrialized countries. A great number of
essential activities, in the fields of nutrition, health, literacy,
the development of education, the training of scientific and
technological personnel, the establishment of research cen¬
tres, cultural development, and the safeguarding of the en¬
vironment, are curbed or even blocked, solely for lack of
material resources. This in turn aggravates inequalities, and
brings about new situations of tension.
And so in addition to the development of nuclear
weapons we have the armaments race in so-called conven-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
for peace
tional weapons, which extends to the smallest and poorest
States. Thriving on injustice, and representing a further
manifestation of selfishness in the world today, this race, in
turn, brings into being terrifying world-wide interests linked
to arms industries, multiplies the risk of a world conflagra¬
tion, and provides fuel for the flames of conflict.
The arms race is not only fraught with the most terrible
danger to human life; it also determines investment choices
and sets a premium on economic structures which, having
become essential to the life of nations, subsequently make
it all the more difficult to carry out the conversion of the
arms industry to non-military activities.
The countries whose high level of development enables
them to influence the crippling economic and social process
of the arms build-up have a special responsibility towards
the international community and to the small and medium
States which at present can do no more than submit to
decisions which have been taken elsewhere, even though
they involve their future.
For Unesco, the essential task is the creation of a growing
movement of world public opinion which is conducive to
disarmament and peaceful co-operation. One of our essen¬
tial objectives should be to work towards the inclusion of
education on disarmament in courses, not only at school
and university, but wherever knowledge or skills are ac¬
quired.
What has to be done, above all, is to ensure that the
burden implied by any war and the enormous benefits of
peace are better understood so that public opinion can
, throw its full weight into the balance and can support
governments in the movement towards disarmament.
We have to persuade and convince and appeal to reason
and common sense, but we also have to call on people's
generosity and a clearly realized sense of solidarity that
stands to benefit one and all. It is a long drawn-out, difficult
and at times unrewarding combat, for guns have to be
silenced by ideas, but it is a combat on which all the world's
hopes are staked.
X
>iN
%r
Photo Boubat © Top, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE ARMS RACE
Military
expenditure
the
ever-rising
tide
The Disarmament Decade solemnly declared by the
United Nations in 1969 is drawing to an end. A number
of international agreements and treaties on aspects of
disarmament have been signed in the last ten years, but
the fact remains that the arms race, far from slowing
down, is actually gathering momentum, swallowing up
vast material and human resources which are urgently
needed for development and constituting a grave danger
for world peace and security. The prospects for general
and complete disarmament under effective international
control seem as distant as ever.
To help alert world opinion to this problem of universal
concern, the Unesco Courier presents in this issue long
extracts from a United Nations report on "the economic
and social consequences of the arms race and of military
expenditures". The facts and figures revealed in this
important document, produced in 1976 and 1977 by a
group of experts from different world regions, draw
attention to the dangers inherent in the present situation
and stress the urgent need for resolute action to counter
them.
The following experts took part in the preparation of the
report:
Mr Gheorghe Dolgu, Chairman of the Group; Professor of Economics,
President of the Academy of Economic Studies, Bucharest; Mr. Simón
Alberto Consalvi, Permanent Representative of Venezuela to the United
Nations, New York; Mr. Hendrick de Haan, Professor of International
Economic Relations, University of Groningen, The Netherlands; Mr. Dragomir
Djokic, Counsellor, Permanent Mission of Yugoslavia to the United Nations
Office at Geneva; Mr. Vasily S. Emelyanov, Corresponding Member of the
Academy of Sciences of the USSR; Mr. Plácido García Reynoso, Former
Professor of Economics, National University of Mexico; Mr. Saad M. Hashmi,
Deputy Permanent Representative of India to the United Nations, New York;
Mr. Ronald H. Huisken, Visiting Fellow, Strategic and Defense Studies
Centre, Australian National University; Mr. Ladislav Matejka, Deputy
Minister, Presidium of the Government of the Czechoslovak Socialist Republic-
Mr. Akira Matsui, Adviser, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Japan; Mr. Isaac M.
Randolph, Former Commissioner for Customs, Liberia; Mr. Kurt W.
Rothschild, Professor of Economics, University of Linz, Austria; Mr. Yves
Ullmo, Directeur des Synthèses à l'I.N.S.E.E. (Institut National de la
Statistique et des Etudes Economiques), Paris.
FOR a number of years now the world
has been diverting annually about
$350 thousand million (1) to military
purposes. The six leading countries in
terms of military expenditure the USA,
the USSR, China, France, the U.K. and the
Federal Republic of Germany account for
three fourths of this total. Altogether bet¬
ween five and six per cent of the world's
total output of goods and services is
diverted to military ends. In most countries
the figure is between two and eight per
cent, although in some cases it exceeds 30
per cent.
The rapid rise in military expenditure dur¬
ing the 1960s followed by a levelling off
over the past eight years repeats a pattern
which has been encountered several times
before. Periods of massive military expan¬
sion, mostly in connexion with a war (the
Second World War, Korea, Viet Nam) have
alternated with plateaux lasting for some
years.
The resulting impression that there are
certain periods of relative stability is largely
an illusion. In fact, the underlying trend for
the great majority of countries is one of
long-term irregular rise in military budgets,
punctuated occasionally by modest and
temporary decline, it is merely the over¬
whelming weight of a few leading coun¬
tries in the total which gives the ap¬
pearance of stepwise growth.
National arms inventories are not
published, and for most types of arm¬
aments only highly tentative estimates of
world stocks can be made. Nevertheless,
some indications of a very general nature
can be given.
Current stocks of nuclear weapons are
sufficient to destroy the world many times
over. These weapons and the missiles, air¬
craft and artillery to deliver them are con¬
stantly being diversified and their perfor¬
mance improved. The number of nuclear
warheads in arsenals is not known, but the
number of carriers of different types is
known with a fair degree of accuracy.
From these figures it can be inferred that
in 1974 so-called "strategic" nuclear forces
in the United States and the Soviet Union
included between 10,000 and 11,000 ther¬
monuclear warheads deliverable from
missiles or bombers. This number has been
rising very fast. Nuclear arsenals are also
increasing in other States. Figures given by
the Stockholm International Peace
Research Institute (SIPRI) indicate that the
number of missile-deliverable warheads
possessed by the two major nuclear
Powers more than tripled between 1970
and 1976, rising from about 3,700 to nearly
12,000. Their combined explosive power is
believed to be equivalent to 1.3 million
Hiroshima-size bombs.
With regard to so-called "tactical"
nuclear weapons the situation is more
uncertain. Their number is believed to be k
about four times larger than the number of f
(1) Estimates of world military expenditure come
mainly from the United States Arms Control and
Disarmament Agency (ACDA) and the
Stockholm International Peace Research In¬
stitute (SIPRI). The figures supplied by these
two sources differ considerably in some cases,
but not enough to affect conclusions substan¬
tially. ACDA figures are generally higher. Figu¬
res quoted in extracts from the UN report are
those provided by SIPRI except where otherwise
stated.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
"strategic" nuclear warheads, but their
combined explosive power is but a fraction
of the latter. According to one source it is
equivalent to about 700 million tons of TNT
or to some 50,000 Hiroshima-type bombs.
As for the major types of conventional
weapons such as aircraft, fighting vessels
and tanks, estimates have been made
which provide a rough indication of trends.
They indicate that the value of the world
stock of fighting ships (in constant dollars)
doubled between 1960 and 1970 and rose
by a further 30 per cent between 1970 and
1976. This pattern appears to be valid for
several other types of armaments as well;
world stocks reckoned in numbers have re¬
mained fairly constant, but in terms of cost
and performance they are increasing very
rapidly, and, in the 1970s in particular, cur
rent models have been spreading very fast
to an increasing number of countries.
This is true of modern aircraft. Only 13
developing countries had supersonic air¬
craft in 1965. A decade later the number
had risen to 41. Over the past 30 years a
few major arms-producing countries
together developed and procured over 70
types of intercepters, fighter and attack air¬
craft and twice as many variants of these
types. Even after correction for inflation,
the unit price of fighter aircraft has been
doubling every four or five years, rising
from about $250,000 per aircraft (1975
prices) during the Second World War to
well over $10 million today, reflecting im¬
provements in performance and armament.
The six major military spenders not only
account for three-quarters of world military
States Arms Control and Disarmament
Agency, which gives the most comprehen¬
sive figures, estimates the total value of
goods actually delivered in 1975 at $9.7
thousand million in current prices. This
excludes training services and construction
which, if figures for the United States are a
valid guide, would add another 30 per cent
to the total, raising the figure for the value
of military goods and services transferred
world-wide in 1975 to an estimated $13
thousand million.
About one third of the total is traded
among industrialized countries; another
third, approximately, is made up of exports
to oil-exporting developing countries,
mainly in the Middle East, and the remain¬
ing third goes to all other developing coun¬
tries together. The total value of arms
The war-drums are sounded.
Men force their features into
frightfulness and gnash their teeth;
and before they rush out to gather
raw human flesh for death's larder,
they march to the temple of Buddha,
the compassionate,
to claim his blessings,
while loud beats the drum rat-a-tat
and earth trembles...
They will punctuate each thousand of
the maimed and killed
with the trumpeting of their triumph,
arouse demon's mirth at the sight
of the limbs torn bleeding from
women and children;
and they pray that they may befog
minds with untruths
and poison God's sweet air of breath,
and therefore they march to the
temple of Buddha, the
compassionate, to claim his
blessings, while loud beats the drum
rat-a-tat and earth trembles.
Rabindranath Tagore (1861-1941)
This poem by Tagore, the quotation from
Voltaire on the back cover, and all the other
quotations from poets and writers appearing in
this issue are taken from a forthcoming an¬
thology of writings on peace to be published by
Unesco. The preparation of the anthology,
which comprises texts from many lands and
periods, was made possible by the award of the
John XXIII Peace Prize to Unesco in November
1974.
WORLD MILITARY EXPENDITURE, 1908-1977 (constant 1973 prices) US $ thousand million
Already in this century 60 million persons have died in two world wars and since 1945 over
100 regional conflicts have also claimed millions of lives. Military expenditure has steadily
risen. Since the Second World War the direct costs of the arms race have exceeded $6,000
thousand million (In 1975 prices), almost as much as the aggregate GNP of the entire
world in 1975.
spending, but for practically all military
research and development (R and D) and
for practically all exports of weapons and
military _ equipment. All significant
developments in armaments originate in
these countries and spread from them to
the rest of the world.
The total value of transfers of military
goods and services cannot be determined
with accuracy, although several institutions
now publish counts and estimates of arms
transfers on a regular basis. The United
transfers has been growing steadily over
the years, increasing by a minimum of
three to four per cent over the past decade.
Despite this appearance of continuity,
very important changes in the pattern of
arms transfers have in fact taken place in
this period.
First there has been a rapid rise in the ex¬
port of major weapons to a number of
developing countries and in some cases
these are increasingly highly sophisticated
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
^L^L^L^L^L^L^L^L^L^L^L^-m-^m
WORLD MILITARY EXPENDITURE IN 1976
Drawing shows breakdown by groups of
countries of world military expenditure In
1976. The two major world powers
accounted for almost half (46.5 per cent)
of the total, the three other permanent
members of the United Nations Security
Council 16 per cent. A group of 33 countries
spending over $1,000 million each per
annum provided 31.5 per cent of the world
figure, while the remaining 6 per cent came
from the rest of the world. Half of what is
spent on military purposes every day
would be enough to fund the World
Health Organization's programme to
eradicate malaria, a disease which is
endemic in 66 developing countries whose
total population Is over one thousand
million. World military spending In a single
year would finance 25 years of economic
aid to developing countries (at 1978 rates).
weapons. According to SIPRI estimates,
exports of major weapons to developing
countries rose from $3 thousand million in
1970 to $6.3 thousand million in 1975 and
57.3 thousand million in 1976.
Second, there has been a major shift
towards transactions on commercial or
near-commercial terms. For most suppliers
commercial considerations have become
predominant to an unprecedented degree
and the only remaining constraint appears
to be the resources recipients are able and
willing to commit to the purchase of
armaments.
The arms trade affects the economies of
importing and exporting countries in
diametrically opposite ways. It is a highly
unequal exchange which is detrimental to
efforts to bridge the gap between poor and
rich countries. For the importer it is purely
and simply a waste of economic resources
which could have been used productively.
Even when weapons are provided as gifts,
operation and infrastructure costs must be
included on the debit side. In contrast to
the import of non-military goods these
outlays raise neither consumption nor pro¬
duction and generate no future output
from which to pay for them.
Not so for the exporting country. That
part of its arms production which is destin¬
ed for its own armed forces constitutes, at
first approximation, an economic loss. But
its production of weapons for export is no
different in economic terms from any other
export production. In some cases it may be
in fact more advantageous than other kinds
of export because the advanced-
technology component in arms exports is
particularly high.
These exports therefore tend to
stimulate important sectors of the
economy of the exporting country, such as
mechanical engineering, electronics and
the industries supplying these sectors.
Recent arms deals involving highly
sophisticated equipment have enhanced
these tendencies since the price of such
equipment often includes a large compo¬
nent to cover research and development
costs. In addition to orders for existing
weapons, some recent contracts have even
involved the development of new or im¬
proved weapons systems specially for ex¬
port to the contractor. In this way impor¬
ting countries are subsidizing military
research and development in the arms ex-
' porting countries. This also applies when,
instead of importing weapons, countries
produce them under licence.
In most cases this subsidy is of marginal
importance for the exporting country but in
some instances the viability of certain na-
. tional arms industries or of particular com¬
panies is significantly affected. In a very
real, although often marginal, way impor¬
ting countries are thus helping to
perpetuate the lead in military technology
of the main arms exporting countries and
to sustain the rate of innovation and ob¬
solescence in weaponry.
In addition to the growing volume of
arms transfers, various forms of interna¬
tional co-operation in arms production are
gaining importance. In the industrialized
countries the tendency is toward co-
production, , several countries pooling
facilities to produce different components
for a particularly costly and sophisticated
weapons system, and, less frequently, col¬
laboration (and cost-sharing) in design and
development.
In the developing countries the usual
pattern is to establish local maintenance
facilities and then gradually to take charge
of repairs, the assembly of imported com¬
ponents, local production of certain com¬
ponents, and so on. More recently, some
countries have been able to accelerate this
process by purchasing complete produc¬
tion facilities, with the foreign contractor,
whether it be a firm or a government, pro¬
viding the whole system design, plant,
.know-how and some of the parts of the
finished weapon.
Seen from a social and political angle,
something extremely important and
radically new is involved here. In some
cases, it could be the beginning of a pro¬
cess whereby the military-industrial com¬
plexes of the supplying countries expand
beyond their own borders, take root
abroad and reproduce the whole network
of relations between industry, producers
and sub-contractors, unions, government
and armed forces in the new environment.
With the transfer of complete and opera¬
tional weapons systems and the provision
of military advisers, as with other forms of
military co-operation, relations between
recipient and supplier tend to remain con¬
fined to the armed forces. But in the types
of multilateral production or dependent
domestic production considered here, a
whole set of mutually supportive relations
and of vested interests in the perpetuation
of the armaments process is built up and
spreads through society, far beyond the
military establishment proper.
While it is not likely, even in the long run,
to provide any genuine independence from
the main arms producing countries, the
multinational expansion of military-
industrial complexes could in time become
a significant impediment to effective arms
limitation and disarmament in the regions
where it is taking place. This underlines
once more the urgency of achieving pro¬
gress towards disarmament. The size and
complexity of the problems will only in¬
crease with the passage of time.B
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE ARMS RACE
New
technologies
for overkill
THE most important and spectacular
aspect of the arms race in the 1960s
was the development and the full-
scale deployment of intercontinental
ballistic missiles (ICBMs), of submarine-
launched missiles (SLBMs), and of the
associated satellite surveillance and com¬
munication systems.
By the end of that decade there was
widespread concern that a new arms-race
spiral might result from the development of
anti-ballistic missile systems (ABMs) and
measures taken to counter them. These in¬
volved increasing the number of launchers
and, with the development of multiple and
independently targetable re-entry vehicles
(MIRVs), increasing the number of
warheads per launcher with a view to
neutralizing the ABM systems by sat¬
urating them.
The first strategic arms limitation treaty
(SALT I) between the United States and
the Soviet Union which was signed in May
1972, set ceilings on the number of ABM
sites and ICBM and SLBM launchers and
succeeded in halting the deployment of
ABM systems. Since 1972 the number of
. launchers has been increasing and is ap¬
proaching the agreed ceilings. In 1976, in
round figures, 2,500 ICBMs and 1,400
SLBMs were held by these two Powers
together.
The SALT agreement has had positive
effects but it is important not to lose sight
of its serious inadequacies with regard to
the limitation of strategic arms. Thus in re¬
cent years the arms race in strategic
nuclear weapons has increasingly taken a
qualitative direction. Vigorous research and
development programmes on improved
ABM systems have been maintained.
The SALT agreement as a whole has had
no discernible impact on the extent of
MIRV deployment. As a result, the number
of ICBM and SLBM deliverable nuclear
warheads has been rising by about 1,000
every year.
Moreover, a major post-MIRV innova¬
tion is already at an advanced stage of
development. This is a maneuvrable re¬
entry vehicle (MARV) which can change
direction in the terminal stages of its trajec¬
tory. This could not only make defence
against ballistic missile attack more dif-
10
ficult, but also, if combined with
developments now taking place in terminal
guidance systems, could provide MARVed
missiles with pinpoint accuracy of a few
tens of metres instead of the current ac¬
curacy of somewhat less than one
kilometre. This means that the silos now
protecting land-based ICBMs can be
destroyed with near certainty with a single
warhead at the first attempt.
As a result it becomes possible to con¬
sider using "strategic" nuclear weapons in
new ways. In addition to being a means of
massive reprisals against centres of popula¬
tion and industry to serve as a basic deter¬
rent, it becomes possible to think of using
ballistic missiles in "counter-force" roles to
gain military advantage at the outset of a
war by striking at the weapons and military
installations of the opponent, or to use
them to conduct supposedly "limited"
nuclear war. The adoption of doctrines of
this kind could greatly enhance the pro¬
bability of nuclear war.
No less significant are the implications of
the deployment of long-range cruise
missiles. These weapons, now under
development, are best described as small,
highly manoeuvrable, low-flying pilotless
aircraft. They can be equipped with a
nuclear as well as a conventional warhead.
Current models have ranges of several
thousand kilometres and accurate
guidance systems, which readjust the tra¬
jectory at intervals by comparing. terrain
features with a map. Accuracy is therefore
independent of range. It will be impossible
to determine from its geometry alone
whether a cruise missile carries a nuclear or
a conventional warhead and, within wide
limits, what its range is. Moreover, it is a
small and easily concealed vehicle. Future
agreements on strategic weapons may thus
become very difficult to negotiate because
they will be difficult to verify.
The cost of the cruise missile will be at
least an order of magnitude less than that
of ICBMs, so that in the years to come it
will be well within the financial means of
the smaller nuclear powers and of many
other countries as well. For some time the
exorbitant cost of the latest types of
nuclear weapon carriers (ICBMs and
SLBMs) has helped maintain the two main
military Powers in a class by themselves. In
the foreseeable future the importance of
this factor may greatly diminish.
Developments in the technology of
nuclear weapons themselves are equally
ominous, particularly the development of
small, low-yield nuclear weapons and
enhanced radiation weapons and of tactical
concepts for their use in battle. Delivered
with higher accuracy and causing less col¬
lateral damage per warhead, their use on
the battlefield may seem more acceptable,
so that the step from non-nuclear to
nuclear war may be more readily taken.
Once they are used on the battlefield,
escalation towards full-scale nuclear war
becomes a dangerous possibility.
The aggregate effect of these
developments cannot be understood in
terms of the gradual improvements in per¬
formance which have been so common
since the 1960s that they are hardly news
any more. The importance of the changes
now underway in the field of nuclear ar¬
maments and their carriers is not that their
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Photo Henri Bureau © Gamma, Paris
performance in missions traditionally
assigned to them is improving year by year,
but that essentially new types of missions
are becoming possible. New technologies
open the way for new doctrines. These in
turn give an appearance of rationality to the
deployment of weaponry embodying these
technologies. At the same time they in¬
crease the dangers of war and alter the
terms of the disarmament equation,
rendering it more complex and more
intractable.
The proliferation of nuclear technologies
continues at an accelerating pace. France
and China acquired nuclear weapon
capability in the 1960s, and, in 1974, India,
which is not a party to the Non-
Proliferation Treaty [an agreement of 1 July
1968, signed by the U.K., the U.S.A., the
U.S.S.R. and a number of other States,
under which the three major signatories
agreed not to assist non-nuclear weapon
States in obtaining or producing nuclear
explosives], conducted a nuclear explosion
experiment underground. It was officially
termed a peaceful nuclear explosion experi
ment, but it demonstrated how readily and
cheaply a small nuclear weapon capability
could be derived from a major civilian
nuclear programme. In other cases nuclear
weapon capability could have been ac¬
quired without being demonstrated in a
nuclear explosion.
Civilian nuclear programmes, and with
them the technical expertise and the fissile
material required for military programmes
have spread all over the world during the
1970s. In 1975, nineteen countries had
nuclear power plants in operation and
another ten countries will have them by
1980. Experimental reactors are now in
operation in well over 50 countries. As far
as most industrialized and several develop¬
ing countries are concerned, there are no
longer serious technological or economic
barriers against initiating a nuclear
weapons programme. The only barriers to
proliferation are now political obligations
assumed under the Non-Proliferation Trea¬
ty, the good sense of governments and the
example to be set in the coming years by
the nuclear weapons Powers in agreeing to
reduce their own nuclear arsenals.
It is, of course, the continuation of the
nuclear arms race, not merely the spread of
peaceful uses of nuclear energy, which en¬
dangers peace. Stocks of nuclear weapons
and the continuation of the nuclear arms
race are factors which encourage nuclear
weapons proliferation. The danger of the
proliferation of nuclear weapons can be
removed by outlawing and halting the pro¬
duction of such weapons and by destroy¬
ing existing stocks.
The resolutions of the United Nations
General Assembly have repeatedly em¬
phasized that the Non-Proliferation Treaty
should become universal. It is consequent¬
ly important that the system of control en¬
visaged in article III of the Non-Proliferation
Treaty be adopted and that the parties to
the Treaty conclude the safeguards
agreements with the International Atomic
Energy Agency envisaged in article III of
the Treaty. »
Developments in the military use of I
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
space have been overshadowed in the
public mind by civilian space exploits. Yet
they have been of decisive importance. In
the Indo-China war satellites were used for
communication, for weather forecasting
prior to bombing raids and for navigation
for naval bombardment, but only now are
the full potentialities of these means
materializing.
Satellite technology is having a decisive
impact and conferring substantial
superiority on the major military Powers in
at least three fields target identification,
navigation and damage assessment in con¬
nexion with counter-force strategies in
nuclear warfare; surveillance, target iden¬
tification and navigation in "conventional
warfare"; and world-wide intelligence and
surveillance of the military programmes of
other countries and of wars in which the
major Powers are not directly involved.
The consequences of this latter capabili¬
ty could be both positive and negative
verification of agreements on arms limita¬
tions or disengagement, on the one hand,
and area policing and assistance in aggres¬
sion, on the other.
To cite an American example, because
these are the best known, the NAVSTAR
programme provides an indication of what
is becoming possible in just one field.
NAVSTAR is a 24-satellite system which
can provide three-dimensional positioning
throughout the world to within about ten
metres. Among its many possible uses is
the guidance of both nuclear and non-
nuclear forces in so-called "strategic" roles
and on the battlefield. It is to be established
over the period 1977-1984 at a cost in the
$3,000 million range. Not only will it allow
perfectly accurate guidance of ballistic
missiles against fixed targets, an essential
component of the counter-force strategy
already mentioned, it is also likely to
enhance greatly the effectiveness of sea,
ground and air forces in conventional war¬
fare and local wars.
Nevertheless, some progress has been
made and the installation of nuclear
weapons or any other kinds of weapons of
mass destruction in space is prohibited
under the Treaty on Principles Governing
the Activities of States in the Exploration
and Use of Outer Space, including the
Moon and other Celestial Bodies.
Throughout the 1960s conventional
weapons systems underwent continual and
rapid refinement in terms of size, speed,
propulsion, fire power, accuracy and so
forth. Unit costs for major weapons
systems typically doubled in real terms dur¬
ing this period. For aircraft they doubled
about twice as fast.
^Sophisticated weaponry, including
supersonic aircraft, became commonplace
in the armouries of industrialized as well as
less developed countries. And these
developments have continued unabated. In
addition, technological advances in several
areas have been combined to produce new
types of conventional weapons with poten¬
tially far-reaching military and political im¬
plications.
New precision-guided munitions
(PGMs), remotely-piloted vehicles (RPVs)
and other devices have been developed to
carry a conventional warhead to its target
with very great accuracy or, in the case of
RPVs, for reconnaissance and similar
missions.
This group of weapons uses the latest
developments in such fields as laser
technology, microelectronics, electro¬
magnetic sensors in the radar, infrared and
optical ranges, and wide-band data links
for a variety of remote or automatic
guidance and/or homing devices.
A first generation of PGMs made their
appearance in the Indo-China war. In the
Middle East in 1973, the enormous poten¬
tial of such weapons against tanks and air¬
craft was demonstrated. Both the type of
technology involved and their cost make
PGMs accessible to many countries and,
indeed, many already have them in their
inventories.
Such precision munitions are expected
to have battlefield implications as far-
reaching as anything that has happened
since the Second World War. The design
and mission assignment of the classical
weapons carriers, aircraft, ships and tanks,
and even the preponderant place they have
Since you set out for the south-east.
Who knows in what land you are
fighting now?
The fate of men who go away to war
Is no heavier than meadow-grass or
herbs.
Ghosts of dead men-at-arms, deep
sound of the great wind.
Warriors' masks, cold glimmering of
moons.
Soldiers and fighting men, laid out
now in silence.
Who will colour your features, or call
back your departed souls?
War leaves its traces, yet nature
remains unchanged.
The heart of the passer-by bleeds
with the pity of it all...
Man's destiny is to grow old on
battlefields:
Ban Siéu's hair was powdered with
hoar-frost before he returned.
Dang Tran Con and Phan Huy Ich
(18th century)
Song of the Soldier's Wife
ft
THE FIGHT OF THE
MONEYBAGS, a print by
Pieter Brueghel the Elder
(1525-1569?). Dating from
1564, the work Is now in
the British Museum,
London.
had hitherto in contemporary armouries
may be radically changed.
The new weapons, together with
developments in such areas as night vision
devices, battlefield surveillance and com¬
munications, are likely to accelerate the
pace of modern warfare and to place a still
higher premium on standing military
forces.
Last but not least, with dramatic im¬
provements in accuracy the yield of the ex¬
plosive charge becomes a less important
parameter in performance. There have
been suggestions, for example, that some
of the missions now assigned to "tactical"
nuclear weapons could be performed by
precision-delivered weapons with a con¬
ventional warhead. In principle this could
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
mean that the military planners would be
more willing to dispense with the use of
nuclear weapons in a limited conflict, but in
practice it could equally well have the ef¬
fect of blurring the distinction between the
use of nuclear and non-nuclear weapons,
thus enhancing the risk of any armed con¬
flict developing into nuclear war.
A range of new weapons and munitions
based on blast, fragmentation and incen¬
diary effects has been developed, and was
used, notably during the Indo-China war,
for saturation bombing over large areas.
Such carpet-bombing techniques approach
nuclear weapons as regards the blind, in¬
discriminate destruction they cause, the
long-term ecological effects to which they
give rise, and the high proportion of
wounded and maimed among casualties.
Other weapons of massive and in¬
discriminate destruction have not lagged
behind. The effectiveness of incendiary
weapons has been considerably increased,
and the development of binary nerve gases
and their munitions (which are relatively in¬
nocuous to handle as the nerve gas is only
assembled in flight) could seriously weaken
the remaining technical and operational
constraints on the development of
chemical weapons.
Significant developments have also
taken place in many other fields such as
radar technology, anti-submarine warfare
techniques, low-altitude intercepter aircraft
and laser-guided cannon.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Photo Alain Nogues © Sygma, Paris
Drawing shows four methods of delivering a nuclear warhead. Along
with other terms used to describe the apparatus of nuclear warfare
they are explained in this selective glossary.
Anti-Ballistic Missile (ABM) system: A system to counter strategic ballistic-
missiles or their elements in flight trajectory.
Ballistic missile: Any missile which does not rely upon aerodynamic surface
to produce lift and consequently follows a ballistic trajectory when thrust is
terminated.
Cruise Missile: a small, highly-manoeuvrable, low-flying, pilotless aircraft
equipped with accurate guidance systems which periodically readjust the
trajectory.
Intercontinental Ballistic Missile (ICBM): A land-based, rocket-propelled
vehicle capable of delivering a warhead to intercontinental ranges (ranges In
excess of about 3,000 nautical miles).
Kiloton: A measure of the yield of a nuclear weapon equivalent to 1,000 tons
of TNT (trinitrotoluene). The bomb detonated at Hiroshima in World War II
had an approximate yield of 14 kilotons.
Manoeuvrable Re-entry Vehicle (MARV): A ballistic missile re-entry vehicle
equipped with its own navigation and control systems capable of adjusting its
trajectory during re-entry into the atmosphere.
Re-entry Vehicle (RV): That portion of a ballistic missile designed to carry a
nuclear warhead and to re-enter the Earth's atmosphere in the terminal portion
of the missile trajectory.
Multiple Independently Targetable Re-entry Vehicle (MIRV): Two or
more re-entry vehicles carried by a single missile and capable of being in¬
dependently targeted.
Submarine-Launched Ballistic Missile (SLBM): A ballistic missile carried
in, and launched from, a submarine.
Strategic nuclear weapons: Long-range weapons carried on either ICBMs
or SLBMs or long-range bombers.
Tactical nuclear weapons: Short-range weapons carried on smaller missiles.
Warhead: That part of a missile, projectile, or torpedo that contains the ex¬
plosive intended to inflict damage.
Source SIPRI
*"£>' 'i i "i
CRUISE MISSILE A
ICBM/MIRV ICBM/MARV
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
THE ARMS RACE
The quality spiral
TIE competition in armaments be¬
tween the largest military Powers is
even more intense than is suggested
by the immense size and the rapid expan¬
sion of their arsenals, because it takes
place primarily in a qualitative rather than a
quantitative dimension, each new genera¬
tion of weapons being more complex and
more destructive than the systems it
replaces.
The strong qualitative momentum of the
current arms race influences both the way
it develops, the insecurity it generates and
the possibilities for disarmament. In an
arms race where the emphasis is on quanti¬
ty, where technological development is
slow and of little consequence, countries
may be expected to match their armament
efforts to the stocks or the growth rates of
the military forces of their opponents.
There is room for saturation levels or for
mutually agreed ceilings and reductions.
Under conditions of rapid military in¬
novation, on the other hand, the decisive
factor in the military procurement plans of
countries at the forefront of the
o.
technological arms race is not so much the
actual military strength of their opponents
but rather those technological advances
which opponents might be able to achieve
over the next decade or so. Inevitably, as
the apprehensions of military planners shift
from the force levels towards the research
and development efforts of their op¬
ponents, it is increasingly on the research
and development efforts of their own
country, which are known, that they will
have to base their plans.
In an arms race where the stress is on
technological advances the process of
weapon and counter-weapon development
therefore tends to become in some
measure an intra-national process, in some
cases only marginally related to the stages
actually reached by other countries. Each
country is actively seeking means of
defeating its own most advanced weapons
and of neutralizing its own most recent
defences, thus conferring on the develop¬
ment of military technology a momentum
and a rate of obsolescence much greater
than in comparable civilian applications.
A qualitative arms race with its long lead
time and its emphasis on future possibilities
rather than current realities tends to move
in one direction only: one country's ad¬
vances in weaponry will be emulated by
others, but its self-restraint heed not be.
Similarly an increase in international ten¬
sion may accelerate the arms race, but an
improvement of the international climate
will not necessarily suffice to slow it down.
In advanced military technology, the
achievement of exacting technical
specifications and early delivery schedules
tends to take precedence over cost con¬
siderations when new weapons are being
designed. The large cost-overruns which
have become an almost normal feature of
advanced military projects illustrate this
fact. The result is an increasing volume of
research and development with each new
generation of weapons.
For example it is estimated that the
amount of draughtsmanship required for
the design of a military aircraft today is
typically of the order of 4,000 man-years,
spread over a seven to ten-year period.
This may be compared with about 170
man-years spread over two to three years
required for the design of the Halifax
bomber on the eve of the Second World
War.
For many years now rising research and
development requirements have been met
by expanding staff rather than lengthening
the design cycle to prevent weapons from
becoming obsolete before they entered in¬
to service. This trend which is inherent in a
qualitative arms race cannot fail to create
problems of surplus capacity both in design
and in production unless military procure¬
ment expands for every new generation of
weapons.
Continuous employment is only com¬
patible with rapid development and design
if production cycles are short and military
stocks are replaced at a rapid rate. The
abandonment of many advanced weapons
programmes before production started but
after hundreds of millions of dollars had
been spent on development, again a recur¬
rent feature of the past decades, has of
course helped to alleviate somewhat this
problem of surplus capacity.
Even disregarding the inherently
wasteful character of weapons themselves,
arms production under the conditions of a
qualitative arms race appears as an excep¬
tionally wasteful process, whether the
waste takes the form of project cancella¬
tions half-way through, of intermittent i
underemployment or of military arsenals I
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE QUALITY SPIRAL
which are allowed to expand for industrial
rather than military reasons.
In an arms race so consistently bent on
qualitative improvements and the quest for
achieving or pre-empting technological
breakthroughs, a mere examination of
trends in military expenditure gives a wrong
impression of the true rise in destructive
potential.
In civilian production it is a well-known
proposition that under conditions of con¬
tinuous technical progress even a policy of
zero net-investment will lead to a constant¬
ly increasing output. Worn-out machines
are replaced by machines incorporating a
more advanced technology and this results
in higher productivity.
The same applies to military expenditure.
Even if it does not rise in real terms, the
devotion of a large proportion to research
and development and to qualitative im¬
provement means that the destructiveness
and the potential danger of the military ap¬
paratus continues to grow.
Thus it is necessary to distinguish bet¬
ween the economic and the military conse¬
quences of armaments expenditure. They
bear no necessary relationship to one
another: a rise in the (real) volume of
military expenditure will almost always imp¬
ly an increase in lethality and destructive
power. But when such expenditure is
reduced there may well be a divergent
movement: a certain relaxation of the over¬
all economic burden can be accompanied
by a further extension of destructive
power, as indeed we are witnessing today
in some countries.
However, since concentration on the
qualitative (i.e. technological) arms race re¬
quires a high input of specially scarce
qualified manpower (scientists, techni¬
cians, management, highly-skilled
workers), shifts towards greater emphasis
on rapid qualitative change can be
economically harmful, even when they are
accompanied by a reduction in total
military expenditure.
The facts about the qualitative character
of the arms race alarming and growing in
importance have to be kept in mind when
measures against a continuation of the
arms race are discussed. It will not suffice
to take cuts in total military expenditure as
the sole criterion of progress unless they
are very substantial indeed.
One form of progress consists in setting
limits on special weapons and weapon
systems. The ABM (Anti-Ballistic Missile)
Agreement between the United States and
the USSR or the Biological Disarmament
Convention are cases in point. Similar
steps covering wider ranges of weapons
and modes of warfare, nuclear and
chemical means of warfare in particular,
would help to erect important boundaries
for the arms race.
To be most effective these measures
should be directed at new developments,
that is before any significant research and
development work has been done and
before the projects acquire a political, in¬
stitutional and industrial momentum.
There is also a case for seeking prohibi¬
tion of the development and manufacture
of new types and systems of weapons of
mass destruction as called for in several
resolutions of the General Assembly of the
United Nations. Such action must be close¬
ly linked to firm measures to halt the pro¬
duction of nuclear weapons, the liquidation
of existing stockpiles and the complete and
definitive prohibition of nuclear weapons.
'A decisive attack on the qualitative arms
race would also be achieved if an agree¬
ment could be reached among the leading
military powers to cut down expenditure
on military research and development.
Such a measure could alsoafter redirec¬
ting the released resources lead to impor¬
tant economic and social benefits to both
the developed and developing nations.
The commitment to incessant qualitative
change is deeply embedded in the inner
logic of the arms race. Agreements on
qualitative and technological restrictions
are not easily reached, not least because of
difficult verification problems. But if the
difficulties of securing some measure of
control over this aspect of the arms race
are particularly great, so too is the urgency
of the need to take determined steps in this
direction. Each passing year sees the initia¬
tion of a spate of new weapons, and ex¬
isting programmes become more deeply
entrenched in the military and political
systems of countries.
UNDER the constant, brooding
menace of the nuclear bomb, the
ultimate weapon of mass destruc¬
tion, it is all too easy to discount the impor¬
tance of conventional anti-personnel
weapons intended primarily to kill or maim
individual human beings.
For some 250,000 years by the middle
of the Pleistocene Epoch our ancestors
were fashioning crude arms for use against
beasts and their fellow men the history of
these weapons has been the history of a
progression of invention, improvement and
refinement of such fertile evil genius as to
make one wonder whether the human
brain is not the deadliest weapon of them
all.
There is a stage in the life of almost every
weapon as it progresses from invention to
obsolescence at which refinements are
added to the weapon or its projectile which
ensure that the injuries inflicted are even
more horrible and "unnecessarily" in¬
jurious.
During the twentieth century, military
thinking has been concentrated less on
defeating particular groups of enemy
troops and more on denying terrain to the
enemy by covering large areas with con¬
centrations of missiles. This involves a
massive stepping-up of fire-power and the
use of indiscriminate weapons such as
delayed-action, multiple bombs, non-
directional fragmentation mines and booby
traps of all kinds.
This development has led the United Na¬
tions to call a conference, to be held in
Geneva in September 1979, with a view to
reaching agreements on "prohibitions or
restrictions of the use of specific conven¬
tional weapons, including those which may
be deemed to be excessively injurious or to
have indiscriminate effects, taking into ac¬
count humanitarian and military considera¬
tions, and on the question of a system of
periodic review of this matter and for con¬
sideration of further proposals".
Some of the weapons the conference is
likely to consider are described below :
777e cluster bomb is typical of the
modern indiscriminate anti-personnel
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The deadliest
weapon of
them all?
Photo © Spire, Paris. Reproduced with permission of Dausse Laboratories, Paris
weapon. To outward appearance a cluster
bomb is similar to a conventional 350 kg
bomb, but it is designed to open in mid-air
and scatter large numbers of grenades or
bomblets, with or without delay fuses, over
a wide area. Systems have also been
developed that are capable of dispensing
incendiary, chemical and biological agents.
The possibility of using these weapons far
behind the battle front adds greatly to the
danger of indiscriminate effects.
Fléchettes are small needle-like darts or
arrows, usually made of steel, that can be
fired from rifles or shot guns using car¬
tridges containing from four to twelve
fléchettes. Rocket warheads containing as
many as 6,000 fléchettes have also been
developed. Since fléchettes tend to buckle
into a hook shape on impact, the wound in¬
flicted is particularly big and nasty and
usually fatal.
Booby traps are concealed explosive
devices attached to apparently harmless
objects; they are activated, for example,
when the door of an abandoned house is
opened or a radio is switched on. There are
even reports of booby traps being attached
to the bodies of dead or wounded soldiers.
Fuel-air bombs have been developed that
spray out a cloud of gas or an aerosol of
particles of, for example, aluminium or
magnesium, which detonate when mixed
with a certain proportion of oxygen. The
cloud spreads out over a wide area and
may penetrate trenches and foxholes
before exploding.
Bounding fragmentation mines are anti¬
personnel mines which, when activated,
jump to about eye level before detonating.
Mines of all kinds present a particular dan¬
ger to civilian populations, sometimes for
many years after hostilities have ended.
This text, prepared by the editorial staff of the
Unesco Courier, is based on a recent study by
the Stockholm International Peace Research
Institute: Anti-Personnel Weapons, published
for SIPRI by Almqvist and Wikse/I International
(for Norway, Sweden, Finland and Denmark),
Crane Russak and Co., Inc. (for the United
States of America) and Taylor and Francis Ltd.
(for the rest of the world). 1978, 299 pp., £9.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Modern weapons take a
grim toll even in
"peacetime" for the arms
industry and the arms
trade engulf funds
desperately needed for
aid and development.
Right, in a drought-
stricken country a child
weak from the effects of
starvation gets a helping
hand from a doctor.
Photo Massa Diabate UNICEF
Millions of victims
before a shot is fired
RATE OF INCREASE
EXPENDITURE, 1957
The massive diversion of resources
to the arms race condemns countless
human beings to disease,
starvation and illiteracy
600
500
400 jma
'M
|^L
300%zZli^
¡Ok
iOO^J
<
k -J
\ -Ji
Î»
F* .-»
«*»-
^A
1957 60
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
VALUE OF MAJOR WEAPONS.TRANSFERRED TO THE THIRD
WORLD (constant 1975 prices) US $ thousand million
r"
OF THIRD WORLD MILITARY
1977 (constant 1973 prices) Index 1957= 100
Global spending on military
activities runs at not far off
$1 million a minute in a
world where some 500
million persons are
seriously undernourished,
800 million are illiterate,
1,500 million lack adequate
medical services, 750,000
die every month of
waterborne diseases, and
250 million children under
14 are without schooling.
An important feature of
world military spending in
recent years has been the
steadily rising proportion
spent by the countries of
the Third World. About 75
per cent of the current
trade in major
weapons armoured
vehicles, aircraft, ships and
missiles is with the Third
World. Figures in graph top
right exclude small arms,
ammunition and artillery
and are estimated to reflect
only about one half of the
total procurement of
military equipment by Third
World countries.
PROLIFERATION OF SOPHISTICATED WEAPONS TO THIRD
WORLD COUNTRIES
Number of countries
1955 1960
Supersonic aircraft
7965 7970 7975
O Long-range surface-to-air missiles
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE ARMS RACE
Human want
the spin-off
from military waste
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
n
WITH its economic costs and social
and political effects, the arms
race constitutes a serious obsta¬
cle to the establishment of a new interna¬
tional economic order. Exacerbated by the
population explosion, the food crisis and
the devastations of natural disasters and
war, the problems of eradicating poverty
and of improving standards "of health,
nutrition, education and housing have
become acute in many parts of the world.
No less important are the problems of in¬
dustrialization and growth in developing
countries, of combating the deterioration
of the environment, of halting the degrada¬
tion of cities,of developing new sources of
energy and raw materials while preserving
presently available sources. All of these
make claims on investment, research and
other resources, in direct competition with
military claims.
Meanwhile, the. massive diversion of
resources to military ends continues
unabated. The global waste of financial
resources, manpower, raw materials,
technical skills and research and develop¬
ment capability goes on year after year.
Every year military activities throughout the
world absorb a volume of resources
equivalent to about two-thirds of the ag¬
gregate gross national product of those
countries which together comprise the
poorer half of the world's population.
It is in the field- of scientific and
technological capability that the diversion
of resources to military ends is most
massive. It is estimated that at the present
time some 25 per cent of the world's scien¬
tific manpower is engaged in military-
related pursuits. It has been estimated that
of total cumulative research and develop¬
ment spending since the Second World
War some 40 per cent has been directed at
achieving military ends. By far the largest
part is spent on the development of equip¬
ment which has no conceivable civilian
use. Medical and biological research,
research related to the protection of the en¬
vironment or to the specific needs of
developing countries have consumed few
'
"
resources compared with military research.
The potential benefits over the years
from the redeployment of research and
development resources which effective
disarmament would permit are in¬
calculable. In the developing countries
enormous needs, unexplored in almost
every respect, are waiting to be dealt with
in the systematic, large-scale and purpose-
oriented fashion which has so far been the
almost exclusive prerogative of military
research.
In many other fields there is the same
urgent need for increased scientific and
technological resources. The effective ex¬
ploitation of the food and mineral
resources of the oceans, the development
of new sources of energy, the monitoring
of environmental health hazards,
meteorological research and forecasting,
natural disasters warning and natural
resource surveys are only a few examples
of areas where skills and facilities of the
types now wasted in military pursuits could
easily be used.
It is evident that in all these fields the
civilian spin-offs from military research, if
not in all cases negligible, have been trifling
in comparison with the resources with
which they were bought and with the
results that could have been achieved if the
efforts had been aimed directly at civilian
applications.
Manpower is another resource on which
the arms race makes heavy and wasteful
demands. The armed forces around the
world total approximately 22 million peo¬
ple. In the United States, for every three
persons in the armed forces another four
are engaged in military-related employ¬
ment. It is estimated that for the world as a
whole, 60 million people are engaged in
military-related occupations, uniformed or
civilian, public or private. Military and
military-related activities everywhere ab¬
sorb a proportion of the most qualified
categories of persons which is much higher
than the share of the military budget in the .
gross national product might lead one to f
expect.
Death from hunger
in the missile age,
Africa 1973.
Photo © Parimage, Paris
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
k Protection of the environment is an im¬
portant part of the resource problem and
the work of repairing the environmental
damage of the past and preventing or
minimizing further degradation is
hampered in many ways by military
activities.
Peacetime military activities, defence in¬
dustries, military installations, manruvres
and the like may be assumed to cause en¬
vironmental damage on top of that produc¬
ed by civilian activities, roughly in propor¬
tion to the share of military expenditure in
gross national product, but the supreme
mode of environmental destruction,
deliberate or merely incidental, is, of
course, war.
Military technology has acquired or
perfected means, including saturation
bombing, incendiaries, chemical and, of
course, nuclear explosives, of a nature to
cause extensive and in some cases persis¬
tent environmental damage. In South Viet
Nam more than 100 kilograms of dioxin,
the chemical of which 2.5 kilograms were
accidently released around the Italian town
of Seveso in 1976, were inadvertently
disseminated as an impurity in one of the
widely used chemical defoliants. Concen¬
trations in some areas reached 5 per cent of
the level which has rendered areas around
Seveso uninhabitable. This and a range of
other environmental and ecological conse¬
quences of the Indo-China war are such
that it is estimated that the recovery period,
at best, will have to be measured in
decades.
The world's armed forces are also major
consumers of a wide range of non¬
renewable resources, including both
energy and raw-material reserves. It is
clear that the consumption of raw materials
for military purposes is even more concen¬
trated in the main military powers than is
resource consumption generally. For such
metals as aluminium, copper, lead and
zinc, military demand in the United States
is 11 to 14 per cent of total demand. For
several other metals it approaches 10 per
cent. For titanium it exceeds 40 per cent.
Extrapolating from United States
figures, world military consumption of li¬
quid hydrocarbons (excluding petroleum
products used in the production of
weapons and equipment) has been
estimated to be about 700 to 750 million
barrels annually. This is twice the annual
consumption for the whole of Africa and
corresponds to approximately 3.5 per cent
of world consumption. For jet fuel on the
other hand, military consumption (in
peacetime) is reportedly one third of total
consumption for the United States. Even
though information is mostly lacking it is
evident that the military contribution to the
depletion of natural resources is substantial
in many cases.
The consequences of the arms race in
terms of natural resources may be il¬
lustrated by the situation as regards nuclear
fuel. The latest survey of uranium
resources, production and demand show
that, while there is a great expansion of
prospecting and development resulting in
major new discoveries, there will never¬
theless be formidable problems in ensuring
that there is enough uranium at com¬
petitive prices to meet demands for the
next twenty-five years. The report
estimates that during that period it will be
necessary to invest about $20,000 million in
exploration and a similar sum in mining and
milling.
The amount of fissile material in military
arsenals is not known, but if disarmament
released 2,000 tons it would be enough to
provide the initial and replacement fuel
over their useful life for an installed capaci¬
ty of about 100,000 electrical megawatts of
thermal reactors. For comparison with
these figures, current estimates of the total
installed capacity of nuclear power plants
are 200,000 electrical megawatts in 1980
and 700,000 to 800,000 in 1990.
In addition, complete nuclear disarma-
Now that current stocks of "strategic" nuclear weapons are sufficient to destroy the
world many times over (their combined explosive power is estimated to be well over a
million times that of the bomb that destroyed Hiroshima on 5 August 1945), attention has
turned to the "improvement" of "tactical" nuclear weapons. The latest project is the
enhanced-radiation neutron bomb with a "low yield" of about one kiloton (equivalent of
1,000 tons of TNT). This bomb is more destructive to life than to property. Diagram above
shows zones of destruction for a one-kiloton neutron bomb detonated 200 metres above
the target area. Zone 1: total annihilation and disruption of the site. Zone 2: All human
beings would be incapacitated within five minutes and would die within four to six days.
Zone 3: Fifty per cent of all people caught in the open would die, after much suffering,
within a period of several days to several weeks.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Diagram right shows
devastating environmental
effects of the detonation, of
a one kiloton neutron bomb.
In an area of 490 hectares
around the point of
detonation fifty per cent of
mammals and birds would
die. Closer to the centre of
detonation, the bomb would
also be lethal to many other
forms of life: within 350
hectares, to many trees and
higher plants; within 330
hectares, to many
amphibians and reptiles;
within 100 hectares, to many
insects; within 40 hectares,
to many microorganisms
such as bacteria, fungi, etc.
tprm*
\
vi*
ft
Although the use of chemical
weapons has been
condemned by a number of
international agreements, the
production and stockpiling of
such weapons have
continued. An alarming
development in recent years
has been the emergence of a
new generation of lethal
chemical warfare agents, the
binary nerve gases, which
are relativity innocuous to
handle and could thus
seriously weaken the
technical restraints on the
development of chemical
weapons.
490 ha 350 ha
Source SIPRI. Graphics Philippe Gentil studio © Unesco Courier
ment would release more than 20,000
nuclear scientists and engineers, now
working on military applications of nuclear
energy, some of whom could assist in the
peaceful nuclear programmes of developed
and of developing countries.
With world military expenditure remain¬
ing relatively stable in real terms since 1968
and world output continuing to grow, even
if only very slowly by the middle of the
1970s, there has been, of course, a
favourable trend in the ratio of military to
various non-military areas of expenditure.
Public expenditure oneducation, for exam¬
ple, overtook military expenditure in 1973.
But this is a world average and there are
very large differences between countries.
In the world as a whole there are almost as
many soldiers as there are teachers.
As with education, public expenditures
on health services have expanded rapidly in
recent years. Nevertheless, public health
expenditure (to which privately-financed
medical care should be added to complete
the picture) only amounts to about 60 per
cent of military expenditure on a world
basis. Again differences between coun¬
tries are very large. Even greater im¬
balances exist in the critical field of
research funding. The resources devoted
to medical research world-wide are only
one fifth of those devoted to military
research and development.
330 ha 100 ha 40 ha
In all cases the resources consumed in
the military sector are very large compared
with the social expenditures of govern¬
ments, even in such important fields as
education and health, indicating the unfor¬
tunate priorities that govern the allocation
of public funds throughout the world.
Yet if these priorities could be changed,
even a small proportion of the resources
now wasted on military pursuits could go a
long way towards alleviating some of these
problems, as a few examples will clearly
show.
The most alarming situation of all is in
the area of nutrition. Five hundred million
people throughout the world are severely
malnourished and millions more subsist on
diets that are far below minimal needs. The
physical and mental development of a large
proportion of young children in developing
countries is blocked because of diet defi¬
ciencies, and this entails incalculable con¬
sequences for the next generation.
In recent years famine has struck entire
regions of the world and on a per capita
basis food production in the developing
countries as a whole has been declining.
Yet the poorest countries, those with per
capita incomes below. $200, generally
countries whose military expenditures are
modest in relation to their gross national
product, nevertheless spend (on average)
about as much on military activities as they
spend on agricultural investment.
To complement national programmes,
there is a desperate need for international
assistance to finance increased food pro¬
duction and the establishment of emergen¬
cy reserves. At the World Food Con¬
ference, in 1974, it was estimated that
development assistance to agriculture
needed to be stepped up to five to six thou¬
sand million dollars annually for the re¬
mainder of this decade.
While fund-commitments for this pur¬
pose have risen substantially since then,
they are still two to three thousand million
dollars below the target. To close this gap,
funds equivalent to one per cent of the
military budgets of industrialized countries
would be sufficient.
The vast benefits which could result
from even trifling cuts in military expen¬
ditures and the reallocation of the funds
thus saved, are particularly obvious in the
field of health. The World Health Organiza¬
tion (WHO) spent around $83 million over
10 years to eradicate smallpox in the world.
That amount would not even buy a single i
modern strategic bomber. f
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Open-air classroom scene in
Lagos (Nigeria). It has been
reckoned that the numbers of
the world's armed forces,
supported by millions of
civilians in military-related
jobs, are today twice as large
as those of all the world's
teachers, doctors and nurses.
Photo Unesco/Almasy-Vauthey
k The WHO programme to eradicate
malaria, estimated at a cost of some $450
million, is dragging on owing to lack of
funds. Yet its total cost over the years is
only half of what is spent every day for
military purposes, and only a third of what
will be spent, strictly for procurement, for
each of the new "Trident" nuclear missile
submarines.
According to 1975 statistics, more than
one thousand million people in 66 develop¬
ing countries live in areas where malaria is
endemic, adding its effects to the other
privations of poverty, inadequate nutrition,
insanitary water supply, poor housing, and
multiple infections, causing high
prevalence of disease and high mortality,
especially in the young, and undermining
the capacity of the people in these com¬
munities to improve their lives materially
and socially.
The eradication of some of the major
communicable diseases would cost trifling
amounts compared to the cost of the arms
race. Moreover, the potential benefits of a
transfer of resources from the military to
the health sector reach far beyond the im¬
mediate humanitarian aspect. The im¬
plementation of such eradication program¬
mes would by itself release important
resources in the medical sector for new
tasks, and by improving the general stan¬
dard of health in affected areas, would
enhance the ability of people to improve
their social and economic conditions in
other respects.
Unless he is deaf, no one who lives
where millions of human creatures
are subjected to sub-human
conditions and reduced to virtual
slavery can fail to hear the clamour of
the oppressed. And the clamour of
the oppressed is the voice of God.
Unless he is quite without heart, no
one who has at last come to
recognize the injustice that results
from the unequal distribution of
wealth can fail to be aware of the
protest be it silent or violent of the
poor. And the protest of the poor is
the voice of God.
Dom Helder Cámara (1909-
God's Voice Today, from
The Desert is Fertile
)
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
t** *
%%* «n*^
^te ï
Photo Gott © Parimage, Paris
Photo © Léon Herschtritt, Paris
"They make a desert and call it peace". Since the Roman historian Tacitus wrote those words
almost 2,000 years ago science and technology have enhanced mankind's power over the
environment, for good or evil, to an almost incredible degree. Above, the crater-pitted landscape
that was left when the bombers had passed. Below, market scene at Fort-Lamy (Chad) in the
Sahel, the vast belt of semi-arid land bordering the southern Sahara. Stricken by disastrous
drought in recent years, the Sahel is only one of many regions whose peoples stand to reap
immense benefits from the harnessing of science and technology to peaceful uses.
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE ARMS RACE
Three myths
that die hard
MYTH I : Military
expenditure boosts
economic growth
THE international arms market has
grown in recent years at a rate
which contrasts sharply with other¬
wise sluggish trends in world markets, and
in many industrialized and some developing
countries the arms industry is now one of
the fastest growing sectors of the
economy.
High levels of military expenditure have
not been noticeably affected so far by the
economic recession which hit many coun¬
tries after 1973. Indeed, in some countries
there is a marked contrast between a still
buoyant military sector on the one hand
and, on the other, a depressed civilian
economy and a tightening of government
budgets, in some cases even to the point of
austerity. In certain limited areas the arms
race has even gathered a new momentum
directly related to the economic crisis,
since some countries have been able to im¬
prove their balance-of-payments positions
by increased arms exports.
But growing expenditure on armaments
is not an efficient way of combating reces¬
sion. Expenditures on such items as
education, health, housing and social
welfare are more effective for both
economic and social reasons.
First, the maintenance of high and rising
armaments expenditures in the face of
stagnating or falling government revenues
may lead countries to economize in such
areas as health, education and welfare with
all the negative social consequences this
entails.
Secondly, recession nowadays tends to
go hand in hand with high rates of inflation
("stagflation") and, in some cases, with
heavy balance-of-payments deficits, and
high arms expenditures have proved to be a
hindrance for economic policies leading out
of recession. High government expen¬
diture on armaments increases demand
without increasing the volume of saleable
or exportable goods. It thus intensifies the
problems of inflation and of the external
balance.
Military expenditures, therefore, reduce
the effectiveness of expansionary policies
or even lead to restrictive measures in other
fields which tend to prolong recession and
unemployment. To the direct waste con¬
tained in armaments production is added
the indirect wastage of unused resources.
In most countries, therefore, there is
MYTH II: the arms
industry offers
a panacea
for unemployment
A major factor in the growth equation,
manpower is today being diverted to
military ends on a massive scale. Labour
constitutes a real resource that could be
employed to useful ends if released from
occupations connected with the military
sector.
This is not contradicted by the fact that
in many countries a considerable fraction
of the work force is now either unemployed
or underemployed. For people are not
unemployed because there are no more
needs to satisfy. They are unemployed or
underemployed because of recession or
structural problems in the economy, and
these are themselves aggravated by high
military expenditures.
In most developed market economies the
use of demand stimulus to deal with
unemployment has been inhibited by fears
that it would enhance inflationary tenden¬
cies and adversely affect the balance of
scope for significant rises in investment if
military budgets are reduced. Even crude
calculations indicate that the potential ef¬
fects of this growth could be substantial. If
the greater part of world military expen¬
diture could, instead, be allocated to in¬
vestment, growth rates might be expected
to increase by one or two per cent. This is
in fact very large perhaps one third of the
growth rate achieved in the world as a
whole in the early 1970s, and probably
larger than the growth rate of world output
in the mid-1970s.
If such higher rates of investment are
sustained, the effects on growth cumulate
over the years. Thus, if half the funds
spent on armaments throughout the world
in the period from 1970 to 1975 had instead
been invested in the civilian sector, annual
output at the end of this period could have
been perhaps $200 thousand million larger
than it was. The sum of $'00 thousand
million is somewhat more than the ag¬
gregate gross national product of southern
Asia and the mid-African region, the two
large regions of acute poverty and slow
growth in the world, with a total population
of over one thousand million people. Over
a longer period the effects on world output
of the reallocation of part of world military
expenditures to investment purposes
would be even more spectacular.
Serigraph U.G. Satho, Mecanorama exhibition © J. CA., Tokyo
payments. But inflation and, in some
cases, balance of payments deficits have
probably been aggravated by high rates of
military spending sustained over a long
period.
In any case, under appropriate condi¬
tions funds released from military budgets
can be used to raise demand in the civilian
sector without stimulating inflation, and,
generally speaking, without affecting the
balance of trade either way. Indeed, to the
extent that military procurement is more in¬
flationary than most other forms of expen¬
diture a dollar for dollar reallocation of
monetary resources to civilian ends would
in the longer run ease inflationary pressures
and leave greater scope for policies to curb
unemployment.
Despite these obvious facts there is a
tenacious myth, dating back to the German
rearmament prior to the Second World
War, that high arms budgets protect
against unemployment or at least mitigate
it. This belief is seemingly self-evident and
is reinforced when, as has often happened,
governments have given publicity to the
supposed employment benefits of arms
procurement they were contemplating,
without adding that alternative uses of the
same funds would create jobs as well, and
normally many more.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
As a consequence it is still today a
widespread belief that disarmament, or
discontinuation of a specific weapons pro¬
gramme, would swell the ranks of the
jobless, particularly when unemployment is
already high. It should be stressed that
such conceptions are wrong. Military
' outlays are not unique in their ability to
generate employment. In fact, whereas
military expenditures obviously create jobs
in the industries supplying the armed
forces, the growing high-technology com¬
ponent in military expenditures has eroded
their direct and their overall potential for
creating jobs.
Today there is rapidly accumulating
evidence that high military budgets con¬
tribute substantially to overall unemploy¬
ment instead of alleviating it. According to
United States Government estimates (and
only for this country do figures seem to be
available) a thousand million dollars of
military expenditure creates 76,000 jobs.
But if the same amount is spent on civilian
programmes of the Federal Government it
creates an average of over 100,000 jobs,
and many more than this if channelled into
activities that are particularly labour-
intensive.
Calculations indicate that if the same
thousand million dollars were released for
private consumption by means of tax-cuts
112,000 new jobs would be created. In
other words, a 10 per cent cut in the
military budget, that is to say a cut of $8 to
9 thousand million and a corresponding tax
reduction, could diminish unemployment
by 300,000 and more than this if cuts and
alternative programmes were selected with
a view to maximizing the effect on
unemployment. Thus, the proposition that
military expenditure generates employment
at least as effectively as, if not more than,
non-military expenditure is demonstrably
false.
MYTH III: military
research is
the major spur
to technological
progress
In the case of technological innovation,
no less than in the case of manpower and
unemployment, the true impact of high
military expenditure has mostly been cloud¬
ed in myth. The basic fact of an enormous
diversion of resources has been disguised
by excessive claims about the importance
of civilian spin-offs from military research
and development.
The drive for continuous improvement in
weaponry and military equipment, so the
argument goes, has been an important
spur to technological progress, and, so it
continues, without the urgency of military
demands, funds on a sufficient scale would
not have been forthcoming.
A limited number of examples, always
the same, are cited to prove the
case nuclear power, air transportation,
radar, space technology and a few more.
Yet a sober assessment indicates that the
claims are grossly exaggerated and even
the standard examples are not all convinc¬
ing. In fact it is remarkable how many in
ventions of the greatest civilian importance
in production techniques, in materials, in
power generation, engines and appliances,
in all fields of surface transportation and in
communication owed absolutely nothing
of their origin and very little, if anything, of
their subsequent development to military
research and development,, even if they
were often adopted by the armed forces
and adapted to military requirements at a
later stage.
Military spin-offs from civilian research
have been incomparably larger than civilian
spin-offs from military research. The truly
remarkable fact is how little that is new, not
how much, has come to the civilian sector
from military research and development ef¬
forts. Product development in the sense of
incremental improvements in materials, in
miniaturization, in performance, in reliabili¬
ty, etc., has in some cases been made
under military auspices, simply because
this is where research and development
funds have been readily available.
The typical emphasis of military research
has been on devices which can perform the
same function as the old ones, only more
accurately, more effectively and more
reliably. The post-war association of the
military sector with advanced and dynamic
sectors of industry and research has
therefore been conducive to an emphasis
not on basic research and genuine innova¬
tion, but rather on product improvement
geared to details of specifically military
devices to such an extent that civilian spin¬
offs of importance have been few and far
between.
Military technology is moving further
and further away from any conceivable
civilian use, and is anyway focusing on
fields which are mostly irrelevant for the
solution of major world problems. There
can be no doubt that in the final analysis
technological innovation in the civilian sec¬
tor and, with it, growth are not furthered
by military research and development but
are greatly impaired by it.
They shall beat their swords into
plowshares, and their spears into
pruning hooks,: nation shall not lift up
sword against nation, nor shall they
learn war any more.
The Holy Bible
Isaiah 2 (4)
THE economic problems associated with disarmament and the reconversion
it would entail should not be underestimated. These problems, which
would be common to countries with different social and economic
systems, would arise, because, inevitably, the manpower and facilities released
by cuts in military expenditure would never exactly meet the requirements of the
new non-military programmes that the reallocation of funds would make
possible.
In the short run the skills required for expanded civilian research programmes
might not precisely match those released from military programmes. Similarly,
some firms now producing military equipment would need time and capital to
readjust to civilian production.
Adequate funds for compensation or conversion for these sectors and special
development programmes for regions or towns which would be particularly
affected would, however, absorb but a tiny part of the resources saved. None of
these problems are insurmountable from an economic or technical point of view.
Nevertheless, it would be of great importance if plans and legislation to facilitate
conversion from military to civilian production were drawn up and adopted as
soon as possible.
One useful approach of a general nature could be to require industries to rely on
military orders for less than a given percentage of their production. Industries for
which this is impossible for technical reasons might be required to seek location
in communities and regions likely to be able to absorb their work force if it is
made redundant. In some cases it might be desirable to disperse military
production around the country.
Another approach, not an alternative but a complement to this, would be to
require factories engaged in military production to draw up alternative plans for
using their equipment and employees In civilian occupations. Such measures
would not only be of assistance in disarmament, they would also help to break
some of the most powerful coalitions of political forces opposing disarmament by
rendering industry and workers less dependent on a steady flow of military
orders.
It must be recognized, however, that conversion Is primarily a question of
particular communities, particular plants and particular groups of workers and
scientists, and that it needs to be dealt with in concrete terms. When alternative
plans are not available there may be a temptation, and sometimes irresistible
pressures, to devise a new weapons project merely to keep the industry going.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE CORPORAL: It's obvious, it's too
long since there's been a war round
here. So what does it all add up to?
Peace means confusion and war
means order, that's what. In
peacetime people grow and prosper
here there and everywhere, without
any rhyme or reason. There's nothing
but waste of men and beasts. People
gorge themselves silly; they put a
rasher of bacon on a hunk of white
bread and then cheese on top of the
bacon. How many young lads and
how many sturdy horses are there in
that town down there? Nobody's got
a clue. They've just never been
counted. I've seen places where
there's been no war for nearly sixty
years. The people didn't even have
names; they didn't even know who
they were. It's only where you've got
a war that you'll find proper lists and
up-to-date registers, shoes in bags
and corn in sacks, animals and people
all listed and accounted for. Because
they say to themselves: "No order, no
war", and they're dead right.
Bertolt Brecht (1898-1956)
Mother Courage and Her Children
Always precipitate where warfare is
concerned, men rush headlong to
their ruin, unmindful that conflict
once begun becomes inevitable.
Where is the briefest skirmish that
has not led to longer engagement?
What peace-breaking war, after
however long or short a respite, has
not in its turn spawned other wars?
And finally, what clash of arms,
however harmless at its outset, has
not led in the end to monstrous
bloodshed, once the combatants'
anger is aroused?
Where the gravity of the situation is
concerned, the people themselves are
but poor judges; it is for the princes
and their counsellors to ponder the
matter. And it is for the clergy to
enlighten the people, impressing on
them by all manner of argument the
error into which they are led;
imposing themselves on all sides by
their attitude, on unwilling and on
willing ears alike, their reasoning
must needs at least be heard.
Erasmus (1469-1536)
The Lament of Peace Decried
on All Sides and by All Nations
Words
of
peace
To replace inhumanity by humanity in
their relations demands a tireless,
threefold struggle on the part of men.
In the first place, they mustto some
extentset promptings of passion
aside and, making allowance for their
common frailty, agree that it is
unseemly to heap hatred on each
other for vain reasons; they must, as
a general rule, place a seal of
forgiveness on ancient disputes,
wrongs and grievances. We may
describe this as effacing the past.
Secondly, no man should impose his
principles (whether they be
philosophical, theological or political
in nature) on another; rather, each
must permit his fellows to set forth
their opinions and to enjoy in peace
what belongs to them. We may
describe this as mutual tolerance.
Thirdly, all men must strive together
for the common good, uniting their
thoughts, their hopes and their
actions to this end. And this may be
described as conciliation.
Jan Amos Komensky (Comenius)
(1592-1670)
De rerum humanorum emendatione
consultado catholica
I Deganawidah
and the chiefs of the Five Nations of
the Great Peace
we now uproot the tallest pine
into the cavity thereby made
we cast all weapons of war.
Into the depths of the earth
into the deep underneath...
we cast all weapons of war.
We bury them from sight forever...
and we plant again the tree...
Thus shall the Great Peace be
established.
Iroquois poem
The Tree of the Great Peace
By a just or democratic peace, for
which the overwhelming majority of
the working class and other working
people of all the belligerent countries,
exhausted, tormented and racked by
the war, are craving a peace that
has been most definitely and
insistently demanded by the Russian
workers and peasants ever since the
overthrow of the tsarist
monarchy by such a peace the
government means an immediate
peace without annexations (i.e.,
without the seizure of foreign lands,
without the forcible incorporation of
foreign nations) and without
indemnities...
In accordance with the sense of
justice of democrats in general, and
of the working classes in particular,
the government conceives the
annexation or seizure of foreign lands
to mean every incorporation of a
small or weak nation into a large or
powerful state without the precisely,
clearly and voluntarily expressed
consent and wish of that nation,
irrespective also of the degree of
development or backwardness of the
nation forcibly annexed to the given
state, or forcibly retained within its
borders, and irrespective, finally, of
whether this nation is in Europe or in
distant, overseas countries.
Lenin (1870-1924)
Report on peace, October 26, 1917
Let me live in a world where no
exclusions are pronounced... in a
world where men's only title is their
humanity and where they are no
longer obsessed by rules, by words,
by labels.
Let churches and printing houses
everywhere be open. When people
visit their town hall, let there never
again be someone waiting to arrest or
deport them as they emerge; let them
enterand leavethe town hall with
a smile. Let no one, ever again, have
to flee in an open boat, or be chased
down by motor-cycles. Let the
immense majority, the only majority,
the whole of mankind be free to
speak, to read, to listen and to find
fulfilment...
Pablo Neruda (1904-1973)
/ Confess that I have Lived
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Louvre Museum, Paris
THE ARMS RACE
The military
establishment
On occasions of rejoicing precedence
is given to the left; On occasions of
mourning precedence is given to the
right. A lieutenant's place is on the
left; The general's place is on the
right.
This means that it is mourning rites
that are observed.
Lao Tzu (c. 570-490 B.C.)
Book of the Way and Its Power
CONTEMPORARY military institu¬
tions are often so powerful and
pervasive that they can have a con¬
siderable impact on political and social con¬
ditions and perceptions and can impose im¬
portant constraints on the evolution of
societies. In this sense they can represent a
major social force, influencing the social,
political and ideological development of a
country.
The extent to which military forces also
act as a social and political force, and the
form taken by their action, depends very
much on circumstances, on the social
framework, on economic conditions and
on the political context. It would be a crude
oversimplification to assume that the
military establishment has the same
characteristics everywhere or that its
specific political impact could be talked
about in general terms. Traditions, political
and social affiliations, historical ex¬
periences in connexion with former wars or
liberation struggles and the pattern of inter¬
relationships with other institutions in
society are too diverse.
There are cases in which the armed
forces have become, for one reason or
another, centres of attraction or incubation
of modernizing forces in society and have
played a role in social develoment going far
beyond their strictly military functions.
In other cases they have constituted a
major hindrance to social development and
have served to perpetuate privileges and to
repress popular aspirations. Nevertheless,
it should be recognized that the military in- W
stitution in the wide sense (including such '
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
institutions as paramilitary forces or secret
' services which may be formally indepen¬
dent of it) enjoys a unique position of
strength in many societies.
This is due to a variety of factors. First,
there is its sheer mass combined with its
highly centralized organization. Second,
the armed forces may enjoy privileged rela¬
tions with key sectors of industry, being at
once a customer and a link with govern¬
ment. Thirdly, they are in a privileged posi¬
tion vis-à-vis the State and many areas of
government policy (foreign, industrial, in¬
frastructure!, regional and others, depen- ,
ding on the circumstances). Fourthly, the
military institution can, to a varying degree,
protect its operations from public scrutiny,
and conduct a variety of activities under
the label of national security.
These may range from the establishment
of a full-fledged covert foreign service or
the covert conduct of military activities in
foreign countries to keeping- political op¬
ponents under more or less close
surveillance. Last, but of course not least,
the armed forces enjoy a monopoly of
physical force and appear as the ultimate
arbiter, both vis-à-vis other States and
internally.
Militarization often goes hand in hand
with social tension. As a means of
domestic repression it is characteristic of
countries where considerable social dif¬
ferences and extreme exploitation of large
sectors of the population prevail. South
Africa may serve as an extreme illustration,
but a similar pattern, minus the racial
dimension, can be found elsewhere. In
such countries it is not unusual to find, for
a period at least, a considerable rate of
economic growth together with heavy ex¬
penditure on armaments and on domestic
policing. To conclude from such instances
that high military expenditure is consonant
with economic growth is to disregard the
social ends for which growth is only a
means.
In most cases it may be assumed that the
military institution and the armed forces
have a double role. They are at once an
ultimate recourse in external affairs and an
ultimate arbiter in internal affairs. These
roles are not always unrelated. During con¬
frontation with an outside enemy the limits
of tolerated dissension become narrower,
and the real or supposed external threat
may become a pretext for increased
repression.
Conversely, when internal dissension
transgresses the accepted limits, and when
means for satisfying basic needs and
aspirations are scarce, there may be a
temptation to seek temporary, refuge in
domestic repression or in the escalation of
foreign confrontation. Here governments
may get trapped in an impossible situation
where an increasing burden of military ex¬
penditures further delays economic and
social progress, causes social structures to
ossify and exacerbates social tension, while
other policies seem to be precluded by a
confrontation and an arms race with
neighbouring countries. The conjunction
of external and domestic confrontation,
both of them temporarily stabilized through
a military build-up but ultimately exacer¬
bated by it, can give rise to a particularly
precarious situation.
In a country where the brotherhood
of man is an illegal doctrine,
outlawed, banned, censured,
proscribed and prohibited; where to
work, talk or campaign for the
realization in fact and deed of the
brotherhood of man is hazardous,
punished with banishment, or
confinement without trial, or
imprisonment; where effective
democratic channels to peaceful
settlement of the race problem have
never existed these three hundred
years; and where white minority
power rests on the most heavily
armed and equipped military machine
in Africa... But we are not deterred in
our quest for a new age in which we
shall live in peace and in brotherhood.
Albert J. Luthuli (1889-1967)
Nobel Peace Prize acceptance speech
Photo © Gamma, Paris
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
SS»*
al
©I
r
SECONDS
For over two decades the conclusion of a comprehensive nuclear test ban treaty has been
impeded by the difficulty of reaching agreement on effective methods of ensuring
compliance with such a ban. Verification would involve a variety of methods of
monitoring including satellite surveillance, on-site inspections and seismic detection and
identification of underground nuclear explosions. Above, seismograms obtained at the
Hagfors obervatory, Sweden, from, top, an underground explosion and, bottom, a
shallow earthquake. Although in this case the seismograms show clear differences
between the explosion and the earthquake, for complex technical reasons the distinction
is not always so clear-cut. Nevertheless, many experts now believe that, following
technical improvements in seismographic instruments over recent years, it would be
possible to establish an effective monitoring system consisting of a global network of
seismological stations, access to photographic satellite data and an international data
collection and evaluation centre. The United Nations is at present undertaking an
experimental exercise aimed at testing and evaluating various elements of such a
proposed global monitoring system.
Can the arms
race be halted?
WARFARE has been a permanent
feature of the period since the
Second World War. Weapons
have been in use on a significant scale vir¬
tually without interruption, more often
than not in several places simultaneously.
Casualties have been accumulating and
since the Second World War have totalled
many millions. To an overwhelming degree
these conflicts have taken place outside the
major industrialized regions of the world,
although in many instances some major
Powers have been directly involved and,
virtually without exception, the means of
warfare have been provided by these
Powers.
These, plus the ever-present possibility
of a nuclear conflagration, have been the
strictly military consequences of the arms
race.
But there are other important interna¬
tional consequences. First, there are the
economic effects. By diverting vastl
resources away from production and)
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CAN THE ARMS RACE BE HALTED?
, growth, and by contributing to inflation
and the economic crisis which have af¬
fected many countries, the arms race
directly and indirectly impedes the full
development of international exchanges.
In addition, the flow of trade and aid is
distorted, in some cases very markedly, by
interference from political and strategic
considerations,resulting in the misalloca-
tion of resources on a global scale. The
arms race thereby contributes to maintain¬
ing and widening the gap between and
within developed and developing countries
and impedes co-operation between States,
socio-economic progress generally and the
promotion of a new international economic
order.
Second, there is the impact of the arms
race on international political conditions.
In an environment characterized by high
military preparedness on all sides, conflicts,
even minor ones, tend to be exacerbated
and security considerations become salient
in the policies of countries.
This is an environment conducive to the
creation of spheres of influence, in which
local conflicts tend to become linked to
regional or global confrontations and in
which social and political developments are
likely to be resisted if they seem to call ex¬
isting alignments into question. The fric¬
tions arising from this rigidity at a time
when the relative economic, political and
military weight of countries is changing
more rapidly than ever are themselves
possible sources of conflict.
Finally, there is the destructive effect of
the arms race on the social fabric. The
fears engendered by having to live with
stockpiles of nuclear weapons sufficient to
destroy humanity altogether, kept in a state
of constant readiness and subject to
human or technical fault, have contributed
to disaffection and disillusion, particularly
among the young. There can be no doubt
that the continuing arms race and the
growth of violence in the world adds to the
disaffection of many people, to their sense
of futility and powerlessness, and turns
them away from socially constructive ends.
Thus the arms race not only entails
military conflict, heavy economic sacrifices
and political division at the international
level, it also threatens and perverts
democratic processes, and weakens those
processes of social evolution which provide
the only real hope for the future of
mankind.
There has been no lack of attempts to
deal with the dangers of the arms race,
even though successes have been relatively
modest so far. In the 1960s and continuing
into the 1970s, these efforts were
characterized by two main features; one
was the priority given to partial measures
aimed at preventing the arms race from
moving into certain new directions and the
other was the emphasis on détente, the
assumption being that relieving suspicion
and fear would not only diminish the risk of
war, but would also remove one of the
main factors fuelling the arms race.
The past decade and a half has produced
a considerable number of agreements on
arms limitation, including:
the Treaty Banning Nuclear Weapons
Tests in the Atmosphere, in Outer Space
and Under Water;
the Treaty on Principles Governing the
Activities of States in the Exploration and
Use of Outer Space, including the Moon
and Other Celestial Bodies;
the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of
Nuclear Weapons;
the Treaty on the Prohibition of the
Emplacement of Nuclear Weapons and
other Weapons of Mass Destruction on the
Sea-Bed and the Ocean Floor and in the
Subsoil Thereof;
the Convention on the Prohibition of the
Development, Production and Stockpiling
of Bacteriological (biological) and Toxin
Weapons and on Their Destruction;
the Convention on the Prohibition of
Military or any Other Hostile Use of En¬
vironmental Modification Techniques;
the Treaty for the Prohibition of Nuclear
Weapons in Latin America;
the Soviet-American agreements on the
limitation of strategic arms (SALT);
the Treaty between the United States of
America and the Union of Soviet Socialist
Republics on the Limitation of
Underground Nuclear Weapons Tests.
It has also produced agreements bet¬
ween the United States and the USSR and
between France and the USSR on the
prevention of nuclear war. Although these
treaties and conventions have contributed
to some extent to a new climate of
understanding, they have not proved equal
to the task of slowing down the arms race
or of significantly affecting the actual basis
of armaments.
Partial and collateral measures can play a
role in the cessation and subsequent rever¬
sal of the arms race, but it is becoming in¬
creasingly clear that they must be conceiv¬
ed as part of a broader programme, inscrib¬
ed in a whole set of measures aimed at
substantial disarmament in areas of
weaponry of central military significance.
If the partial measures are specially
designed just as measures to regulate an
ongoing competition in armaments, the
danger exists that they simply shift this
competition in other directions.
In the mid-1960s and the early 1970s, the
partial measures achieved contributed to a
climate of optimism, served to establish
useful channels of communication, and
demonstrated that agreements were possi¬
ble, within limits at least. These measures
thus undoubtedly contributed to pro¬
moting détente.
It is obvious that détente has had an im¬
portant effect in relaxing the international
climate, thereby diminishing the risk that
conflicts on the periphery of the arms race
or lesser conflicts involving the major
Powers will escalate into nuclear war. By
relieving the cold-war atmosphere between
and within the main military alliances and
helping to relax the rigid bipolarity of
former years, détente has also helped to
promote exchanges of all kinds. Indeed,
such exchanges are not only a result of
détente, they are part of the process of
détente itself, and continued relaxations of
set patterns of relations between the main
alliances, within them and within countries
individually, as recognized in the Helsinki
Declaration on Security and Co-operation
in Europe, are both aspects of, and pre¬
conditions for continuing détente.
By building international relations on a
sounder basis, détente has improved the
conditions for beneficial intercourse bet¬
ween States, for the development of
economic ties, and for increased scientific,
technological and cultural exchanges.
These are major, even . decisive
achievements, of the last decade or so,
which must be vigorously pursued and
strengthened.
While the overriding importance of
détente deserves constant emphasis, so do
the failures of this period. The fact that
political détente has not been accompanied
by corresponding measures of disarma¬
ment and military disengagement is its cen¬
tral weakness and a major cause of con¬
cern. Détente is being continuously assail¬
ed and undermined by the momentum of
technological developments in armaments.
It is essential that détente should not be
merely a process involving the main pro¬
tagonists, a process limited geographically
to certain areas and limited in substance by
an immense rivalry in the military field. For
a continuous build-up in armaments is
clearly incompatible with serious attempts
to eliminate the threat of war and to
strengthen beyond a very limited point the
confidence among States which must be
the foundation of genuine détente. If the
arms race is not reversed détente remains
without a real basis, always in danger of
sliding back into tension, suspicion, isola¬
tion and confrontation.
After more than a decade of attempts to
curb the arms race it can be seen that these
efforts have been inadequate. In every im¬
portant respect the arms race is continuing
apace, while much talent and energy has
been spent on what are now seen to be
issues of more marginal importance.
On several occasions it has been seen
how the public, when adequately inform¬
ed, can exercise a moderating influence on
developments in the field of armaments,
and fostering a genuine and widespread
public concern about the dangers of the
arms race may be one of the most impor¬
tant ways of giving a new momentum to ef¬
forts towards disarmament. This need for
an active and well-informed public opinion
capable of opposing all incitement to war
and of channelling its concern in construc¬
tive directions is of vital importance, for
where questions of armament and disarma¬
ment are concerned the very survival of
humanity is at stake.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
K
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Bookshelf
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
D Julian Huxley, Scientist and
World Citizen 1887-1975. A
biographical memoir by J.R. Baker,
F.R.S., with a bibliography by Jens-
Peter Green. Preface by Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow. 1978, 184 pp. (18 F)
D Urban Hydrological Modelling
and Catchment Research: Interna¬
tional Summary, by M.B. McPherson
and F.C. Zuidema. (No. 18 in Unesco's
"Technical Papers in Hydrology" series)
1978, 48 pp. (12 F)
The Peopling of Ancient Egypt
and the Deciphering of Meroitic
Script. Proceedings of a symposium
held in Cairo in 1974. The first volume in
a new series to be based on studies and
working papers of meetings held to
prepare the major Unesco project The
General History of Africa. 1978,
136 pp. (25 F)
D Developments in Technical and
Vocational Education, A Com¬
parative Study. The current situation
and possible future trends of technical
and vocational education in 23 countries.
1979, 143 pp. (22 F)
D Cultural Policy in Bolivia, by
Mariano Baptista Gumucio. 1979, 81 pp.
(16 F)
D Rural Radio: Programme Formats,
by Kiranmani A. Dikshit, Ian Boden, Clif¬
ford Donkor, Simeon Bonzon, Hernando
Bernai Alarcon, Jaroslav Kostál and
Glenn Powell. Describes .how seven rural
broadcasting programmes were created,
organized and produced in Nepal, Papua
New Guinea, Ghana, Colombia, Philip¬
pines, Czechoslovakia and Canada.
1979, 94 pp. (10 F)
D New Trends in Mathematics
Teaching, Vol. IV, prepared by the In¬
ternational Commission on Mathematical
Instruction. Describes worldwide trends
in maths teaching from the pre-
elementary to university level. 1979, 280
pp. (54 F)
D Lifelong Education: A Stocktak¬
ing. Edited by A.J. Cropley with con¬
tributions by A.J. Cropley, E. Gelpi, P.
Lengrand, A. Pflüger, K. Richmond,
A.K. Stock and B. Suchodolski. 1979,
115 pp. (8F)
D Cultural Policy in the Republic of
Panama, by the National Institute of
Culture 1978, 48 pp. (10 F)
D The Effects of Rural-Urban Migra¬
tion on Women's Role and Status in
Latin America, by Dora Orlansky and
Silvia Dubrovsky. 1978, 50 pp. (8 F)
D The Organization of Museums.
The fourth impression of Unesco's prac¬
tical handbook on the running of
museums. 1978, 188 pp. +44 pp. illus.
(40 F)
D Biogeochemistry of Estuarine
c 	... Proceedings of aSediments. r i t
Unesco/SCOR (Scientific Committee on
Oceanic Research) workshop held in
7a ion tax n
uc « n; K
1976. 1978, 293 pp. (45 F)
in brief... in bV
Forging a future
for Tanzania's
village blacksmiths
Rural blacksmiths will be among the first
beneficiaries of Tanzania's Small Industries
Development Organization (SIDO) set up in 1973
with U.N. help. Tanzania has an ancient tradi¬
tion of metal-working. A recent study in the
U.S. journal Science (Vol. 20, p. 1085) describes
how the country's Haya people produced high-
grade carbon steel over 1,500 years ago", using
technology not developed in Europe until the
mid-19th century.
Brazil's sugar crop
keeps traffic moving
Between 28 and 30 million bags of sugar will be
converted to alcohol for use as an additive to
petrol during the 1978-1979 sugar cane season,
as part of Brazil's National Alcohol Programme.
The goal of the programme is to produce 3,000
million litres of alcohol annually by 1980.
52 million
child workers
There are 52 million working children in the
world, according to the latest estimate of the In¬
ternational Labour Organisation. Some 42
million work without pay in family enterprises
and about 10 million are wage-earners in
workshops, factories and fields. The total of 52
million is probably only the tip of the iceberg
since children under 15 are not covered by
statistical surveys in many countries.
Inventory of
stolen art
An "Index of Stolen Art/ 1977" listing over 1,200
stolen works of art, has been issued by the Theft
Archive, a New York based non-profit pro¬
gramme. Containing entries from some 20
countries, the Index is the first instalment of an
annual publication, complemented by a monthly
newsletter. Further information may be obtain¬
ed from: The International Foundation for Art
Research Inc., 46 East 70th St., New York, N.Y.
10021.
The United Nations
and disaster relief
The United Nations Postal Administration has
issued a set of commemorative stamps on the
theme "UNDRO Against Disaster". UNDRO,
the Geneva-based Office of the United Nations
Disaster Relief Co-ordinator, co-ordinates and
supports international emergency relief aid in
disaster-stricken areas. Further information
about the stamps, issued in Swiss Franc and
U.S. Dollar denominations, may be obtained
from: U.N. Postal Administration, Palais des Na¬
tions, CH-1211 Geneva 10.
Unesco commemorates
Polish educator
Janusz Korczak
An international symposium, an exhibition and
film shows were among the events organized at
Unesco's Paris headquarters between 2 and 12
April to mark the centenary of the birth of the
Polish doctor, educator and writer Janusz Korc¬
zak, who devoted his life to writing for and
about children and to practical work in child
welfare, notably as director of a Warsaw or¬
phanage where he developed and practised
educational methods far ahead of his time. The
organization of the orphanage was based on
self-government by the pupils and included such
institutions as a children's parliament and a
children's court. Korczak died in the Treblinka
extermination camp in 1942 after refusing to
leave his children and rejecting all attempts to
persuade him to escape from the Warsaw ghet¬
to. Part of Unesco's activities within the context
of the International Year of the Child, the tribute
to Korczak was organized by the Permanent
Delegation of the People's Republic of Poland to
Unesco and the French Association "The
Friends of Janusz Korczak".
International Soil Museum
opens in Netherlands
An International Soil Museum, the first of its
kind, has been inaugurated at Wageningen, The
Netherlands. It presents samples of represen¬
tative soils from all over the world and by pro¬
moting research, training and information ex¬
change will play a vital role in developing a com¬
mon terminology for all soil scientists. Unesco
has actively supported the foundation of the
Museum, as part of its work in the soil sciences
which has included the preparation and publica¬
tion of the World Soil Map, a major joint venture
with FAO and the International Soil Science
Association. ^
WHO'S latest guide
to world diseases
The World Health Organization (WHO) has just
published the alphabetical index (1) to its 9th
revision of the international classification of
diseases. Vol. 1, a tabular list, appeared in 1977.
The second volume is in three sections: an index
of diseases containing the type of information
that would be recorded by a physician; an index
of external causes of injury, such as fires; and an
index of drugs and other chemical substances
giving rise to poisoning or other adverse effects.
It) Manual of the International Statistical Classification
of Diseases, Injuries and Causes of Death, vol. 2:
Alphabetical Index, WHO, Geneva, 30 Swiss francs.
The Ukraine at Unesco
An evening of Ukrainian songs and dancing was
held at Unesco headquarters in Paris on 28
March to mark the 25th anniversary of the Ukrai¬
nian Soviet Socialist Republic's membership of
Unesco. The evening, which featured works
performed by a trio of musicians on the bandura,
a popular Ukrainian stringed instrument, was
organized by the Permanent Delegation to
Unesco of the Ukrainian SSR.
The painting reproduced on the cover of our
February 1979 issue was erroneously attri¬
buted to Juan Ríos Martínez; it was, in fact,
the work of his fellow Huichol artist Guada¬
lupe González Ríos Edltor.
i
CO
S
O
g
<
Q
O
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
repertoire
international
des traductions
Just published
international
bibliography
of translations
Unesco's annual guide
IndeX to world translations
translationum
27
Index Translationum presents a detailed picture of world
translations, recording those published in a single year, and
including new editions of previously published books.
Compiled with the help of librarians in many countries, it
enables readers to follow, year by year, the flow of
translations from one country to another and to trace the
works of individual authors as they appear in translation.
The latest edition gives data on 46,384 titles published in
1974 in 61 countries.
lunasco
Multilingual, with trilingual (English / French / Spanish)
Introduction
846 p. Hardbound: 240 F
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors In countries not lis¬
ted, along wfth subscription rates In local cur¬
rency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria!, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch:
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K., Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2r18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking.
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L, Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI. National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Tahrir Square,
Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box
2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. FRANCE. Librairie de
¡'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach
140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Cotmantstrasse 22. For scientific
maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830.
Other publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung,
Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-'
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akademiai
Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok
Boltja, Nèpkôztérsasâg utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson 8- Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1;
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book a-
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House,
New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Social Welfare, 51 1 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001.
- INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286,
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication &
Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling
Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street,
Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco
Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat
71 -75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
¿L
L --
.
i
í
W
-
.Jt
s.
", - ^ t.^
Photo Philip Jon« Griffithi Magnum. Pirit
What has become of humanity, goodness,
modesty, temperance, tenderness, wisdom and
piety and what can all these mean to me... if the
last sight vouchsafed to my eyes is my city
reduced to rubble by fire and sword, and if the
last sounds to reach my ears are the cries of
women and children as they perish in the ruins?
Voltaire
Philosophical Dictionary
]]>
</page>
</document>
