<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074732eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Frenen francs
I
The changing face of China
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
0 Guinea
Photo © Dominique Darbois, Pans.
Dialogue and debate
In rural black Africa, the palaver is the time-honoured institution whereby communities or ethnic groups confer and
exchange views. While palavers are conducted according to strict rules (age confers precedence, interrupting a speaker
is forbidden) it is taken for granted that the participants will express themselves freely and frankly. Characteristic of
a civilization in which the spoken word is all-powerful, this method of using the power of words to settle disputes or
take the heat out of quarrels also gives force to the conscience of the community expressed in a fully democratic spirit.
Above, meeting of villagers at Dalaba (Revolutionary People's Republic of Guinea).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
DECEMBER 1982 35th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 26 LANGUAGES
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 48 French Francs
2 years: 84 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 36 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 11 - 1982 - OPI 82-1 -393 A
page	
4 FIFTY YEARS OF LITERARY LIFE
A leading Chinese writer looks back on tumultuous times
	by Ba Jin
10 CONTROVERSIAL CONFUCIUS
In China today, the ancient philosopher's works
are a source of lively debate
	by Pang Pu	
12 THREE IN ONE
The single complete art of calligraphy,
	by Huang Miaozhi
poetry and painting
18
19
WORKS AND DAYS IN ZHEJIANG PROVINCE
PEN OF PROTEST
The seminal work of Lu Xun
by Li Helin	
20
22~
3l~
NIGHT THOUGHTS, NOVEMBER 1926
by Lu Xun
CHINA THROUGH THE AGES
EIGHT PAGES IN COLOUR
A LITERATURE OF COMBAT
Self-portrait of a popular woman writer
by Ding Ling	
35 THE MODERNIZATION OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY
36 IMMORTAL CLAY
From neolithic times to today, a panorama of Chinese ceramics
	by Li Jixian
38 THE SPORT OF SAGES
	by Yan Naihua	
39
40
ON LAO SHE
THE CHANGING CHINESE FAMILY
by Fei Xiaotong	
42
46~
CHINESE CIVILIZATION AND THE WEST
by Zhang Kai
THE WHY OF THE NEEDLE
The story of acupuncture and moxa
by Joseph Needham	
A TIME TO LIVE...
GUINEA: Dialogue and debate
/Npreparing this issue of the Unesco
Courier, entirely devoted to Chinese
culture, the editors could not pre¬
tend to encompass within the limited
number ofpages at their disposal, still less
to analyse, one of the world's oldest
civilizations and one ofhumanity 's richest
cultures. There was no question of tracing
the path traversed by a society whose
origins may perhaps be said to go back to
Beijing Man half a million years ago, nor
offollowing the development of the arts
and sciences, which count among their
earliest inventions the compass and the
seismograph, paper manufacturing and
printing, the solar quadrant and gun¬
powder, and among their discoveries that
of the relationship between the cir¬
cumference and the diameter ofa circle, as
well as many other brilliant achievements.
As far as the ancient history of China is
concerned, we evoke in our pages only
China's cultural contacts and relations
with the West which always began along
the trade-routes, in this case the Silk Road
and the current which bore westward the
arts ofChinese ceramicists. On our central
colour pages we also present some of the
great landmarks of Chinese art from
prehistoric times until the fifteenth cen
tury;as well as scenesfrom everyday life in
China today.
It was decided to focus the articles on
contemporary China, born of the great
transformations which came about in the
middle of this century after several event¬
ful decades of struggle. These economic,
political and social changes have affected
every aspect of Chinese society: the tradi¬
tional family structure; the interpretation
of history and what was considered to be
the country's philosophy; the conception
ofartistic creation and scientific progress.
IfNew China still counts a rural popula¬
tion which constitutes 80 per cent of the
total, it is on this immense source of
human vitality, and on the manual and in¬
tellectual workers of the towns and cities,
that the country is basing its efforts to con¬
struct an original economy which will
enable it to go forward successfully with
bold scientific and technological pro¬
grammes for education and development,
many of which constitute an example for
other regions of the Third World.
The historical conditions which deter¬
mined these fundamental and definitive
changes in the organization ofsociety and
in the culture which derivesfrom it, appear
in ourpages through the testimony ofthree
of modern China's most famous writers:
Lu Xun, Ba Jin and Ding Ling, who were
eyewitnesses of and to a degree pro¬
tagonists in, a period of history whose
course they helped to change.
This radical transformation of society
was possible because the Chinese people,
scorned and oppressed during centuries of
feudalism, werefor thefirst time in history
taken into consideration. Some of the
oldest and most deeply rooted traditions
of the Chinese people, such as the martial
arts and acupuncture, have thus been
respected and encouraged and are today
not only practised in China but have won
adherents in other Asian countries as well
as in Europe and the Americas. Other
time-honoured forms of expression
discussed in this issue include ceramics and
calligraphy, an art which holds a special
place in China and for whose uniquely
close relationship to poetry andpainting it
is difficult to find a parallel elsewhere.
Finally we should like topoint out to our
readers that wherever possible we have
followed the Chinese Pinyin transcription
ofproper names.
Cover photo Andanson © Sygma, Pans
Calligraphy, by Hsiung Ping-Ming, reaäsZhong Guo (Middle
Country), the name by which the Chinese know their
country.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Fifty years
of literary life
A leading Chinese writer looks back
on tumultuous times
by Ba Jin
Ba Jin at his Shanghai home in 1982, aged 77.
I have been writing for fifty years,
and yet I don't consider myself
a man of letters. People come
to literature by different ways. I was
fond of reading novels when I was still
a boy, and would sometimes even forget
to eat or sleep. I did not read for the sake
of study but out of enjoyment. I never
dreamt that I would be a novelist
myself. I began to write novels simply in
order to make sense of things.
I was born into a large bureaucrat-
landlord family in Chengdu, the capital
of Sichuan province, and passed my
childhood among twenty or thirty "up¬
per class" people and the same number
of "lower-class" people. In this well-
off family, I learned about the wretched
lives of servants and sedan bearers. I
heard the complaints of the young
generation, tyrannized by the
BA JIN, born 1904, is a celebrated modern
Chinese novelist. He is currently Vice-
chairman of the China Federation of Literary
and Art Circles, Chairman of the Chinese
Writers'Association, and Director of the China
PEN Centre. His major works include: Trilogy
of Love (The Mist, The Rain, The Lightning),
Trilogy of the Torrent (The Family, Spring,
Autumn), A New Life, Garden of Repose and
Reminiscences of My Writing Life.
hypocritical, selfish older members of
the family. I felt that something was
wrong with our society, but I could not
work out what was wrong, nor did I
know how the sickness could be cured.
When I left home at the age of nine¬
teen, I felt as if I had escaped from a
dreadful nightmare. At twenty-three I
left Shanghai for a strange land Paris,
hoping to find a way to save humanity,
to save the world and myself.
In the spring of 1927 I took a small
room reeking with the smell of gas and
onions on the fourth floor of a small
apartment building in the Rue
Tournefort, in the Latin Quarter. I was
lonely and miserable. In that small
room, which was rarely visited by the
sun, I missed my homeland, my
relatives and friends. A struggle bet¬
ween revolution and counter-revolution
was going on in my country, and the
people were suffering.
In Paris there was a campaign to save
two Italian workers, Sacco and Vanzet-
ti, who had been charged with murder
and held in prison in Boston,
Massachusetts, for six years. Posters of
protest and notices of meetings were
everywhere in the streets. I read the
autobiography of Vanzetti and came
upon such lines as, "I hope every family
has its house, every mouth has bread,
everybody gets an education and
everyone is given the chance to develop
his gifts." I was greatly moved. How
well he had expressed it! Like a key, his
words opened the lock of my heart.
I lived near the Pantheon and passed
it every day. As dusk was falling one
rainy afternoon I stopped in front of the
bronze statue of Jean-Jacques
Rousseau and confided my frustration
and misery to this "citizen of Geneva"
who had dreamed of putting an end to
tyranny and inequality. Back in my
cold, lonely room I sat down to write a
letter in which I asked advice from the
prisoner in the condemned cell. In the
reply which eventually reached me
Vanzetti wrote, "Youth is the hope of
the world . " Several months later he was
executed in the electric chair. Fifty years
later Sacco and Vanzetti were
pardoned.
It was in such circumstances and in
such a mood that I wrote the outlines of
episodes for a novel, while the bells of
Notre-Dame tolled out the passing
hours. I would turn my misery,
loneliness and enthusiasm into lines of
characters on paper. My past loves and
hates, my joys, sorrows, sympathy and
suffering all rushed to my pen. I wrote
quickly. The flame burning in my heart
began to die down and I could close my
eyes in peace. The problem preying on
my mind was solved. I was saved.
After that, whenever I had time I
would pick up my pen and pour out my
feelings on paper so that my young,
lonely heart could find consolation. The
following year I completed my first
novel and posted it from the little
French town of Château-Thierry to a
friend of mine who worked at the Kai-
ming publishing house in Shanghai. I
wanted his opinion of my work which I
wanted to have printed. When I return¬
ed to Shanghai at the end of that year,
I learned from my friend that my novel
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
would be serialized in the magazine Fic¬
tion Monthly. He also told me that Ye
Shengtao, the magazine's acting editor-
in-chief, had read it and decided to
publish^it.
At that time Fiction Monthly had
great prestige. It opened the door to me
and let me, a young man ignorant of
literature, enter the arena of literature
in triumph.
I learned to write fiction in France. I
shan't forget my teachers: Rousseau,
Hugo, Zola and Romain Rolland. I
learned to integrate writing and life, the
author and his characters. I believe that
the highest achievement of a writer lies
in this fusion through which he devotes
himself to his readers. My novels are the
result of my exploration of life. Each
work is my harvest. It is for my readers
to judge them. I myself adhere to one
unchanging principle: always tell the
truth.
Apart from French writers I also
learned from Russian authors such as
Herzen, Turgenev's novels Fathers and
Sons and Virgin Soil, and Gorky's early
short stories. I am currently translating
Herzen' s memoirs. Among those who
have taught me is Charles Dickens and
the Japanese writers Natsume-Soseki
and Arishima Takeo. Lu Xun is my
Chinese master. My works have been in¬
fluenced to a greater or lesser degree by
these writers. However, my principal
teacher has been life, life in Chinese
society. My feelings and experiences
enabled me to be a writer.
Readers may detect the influence of
different writers in my work, but I did
not deliberately set out to learn from
any particular writer. "I must fight
against the old society," I once said,
"and I need weapons. I would take up
any weapon to fight against the old
order."
In 1928 I returned from France and
settled down in Shanghai. I began by
writing a short story and translated
some short pieces which I sent to
newspapers and magazines. Later the
editors asked for more. I stayed in the
same building as my friend who worked
at the Kaiming publishing house; he
lived upstairs while I lived downstairs. I
was shy of meeting people and speaking
in public, and I didn't want to have
anything to do with outsiders. So those
who wanted my writings always dealt
with my friend, and I could write in
peace. Sometimes I would work
through the night to write a short story,
leaving the manuscript on the desk for
my friend to pick up the next morning.
This was how I wrote The Dog, a short
story which was published in Fiction
Monthly. The more works I published,
the more people came to me for my
writings. Gradually I got to know more
and more people in the literary world.
In 1933 I noted that "I live on friend¬
ship, that's why I'm still alive."
In July 1982, the People's Republic of
China carried out the most massive
census operation in history. The full
results will not be known in detail until
1984, but overall totals were issued in
October 1 982. They show that China's
population at the time of the survey
stood at 1,008,175,288. The urban
population numbered 206,588,000,
while over 800 million persons (about
80 per cent of the total) live in rural far¬
ming areas. Left, his silhouette gleam¬
ing in the water beneath him, a rice-
farmer ploughs with a water-buffalo.
Above, family meal in a commune near
Shanghai.
Photo © Marc Riboud, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Photo René Burn © Magnum, Pans
Hewn into the face of steep cliffs overlooking the Qi
river near Luoyang in Hunan province, the Buddhist
cave-temples of Long-men are one of the artistic
wonders of the world. In the monumental Fang-hsien
temple, which dates from the 7th century AD, the
massive figures of Lokapala and Dvarapala (above)
flank an 1 1 -metre high seated Buddha.
During the first few years of this new
life I usually devoted eight or nine
months annually to writing and travel¬
led to see my friends during the rest of
the year. I lived on my royalties alone.
Because of my writing I did not marry
until I was forty. Until then my friends'
homes were my home; I travelled widely
to see my friends. I kept "travel notes".
Sometimes I shut myself up in my study
for a year at a time in order to write. I
once described myself in these words:
"Day and night an inner fire consumed
me. My hands trembled as I con¬
templated the suffering ofmany people,
including my own. I wrote constantly,
always in the same humdrum surroun¬
dings: a bare room with the sunlight
slanting in through the window; piles of
books and newspapers and writing
paper on the square table in front of me;
a worn-out armchair and two small
stools." The war reached Shanghai in
1932 and I had to move. However, I
didn't change my way of life nor did I
stop writing.
In 1934 1 visited Japan where I stayed
for a few months in Yokohama and
then spent several months in Tokyo. In
August of the following year some of
my friends in Shanghai founded the
Cultural Life Publishing House and in¬
vited me to do some editing work. I ac¬
cepted their offer and edited several
series of books. In the next twenty
years, I spent part of my time editing
literary works and translating, and
naturally there was less time for writing.
But the enthusiasm of my youth did not
wane, and my pen did not allow me to
rest.
In 1937, when the war of resistance
against Japan broke out, I left Shanghai
for the south. I returned and then
travelled to the southwest. My way of
life was changing, but I did not stop
writing. It was in these circumstances
that I finished writing the trilogy
entitled The Torrent. I had scarcely
made a simple home for myself in a city
before I was forced to leave, empty-
handed except for some paper. In those
wandering days I had to change my
writing habits. In some places it was
even difficult to buy a bottle of ink!
When I was writing The Garden of
Repose, I always had an ink-stick, a
Chinese brush and a stack of letter
paper with me. When I stopped at a
place I would borrow a small plate,
pour a little water on to it, grind the ink-
stick and then sit down to write.
When the Chinese people were
liberated and the People's Republic of
China was founded, I wanted to use my
pen, which had been used to writing
about darkness and misery, to write
about new people and new deeds, to
celebrate the people's victory and joy.
But I had not had the time to familiarize ,v
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Above, children in Shanghai's Tsao Yang Middle School take a short break to exercise their eyes. China is making massive efforts to
modernize and extend the benefits of its educational system. By 1 980, 93 per cent of children of elementary school age were in school,
as against 49 per cent in 1 952. Below, Shanghai shoppers take care not to put all their eggs in one basket. Shanghai is China's biggest
city (with a population of 1 1 ,859,000, according to the 1 982 census) as well as its greatest port and commercial and industrial centre.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
with these subjects. I also took
part in non-literary activities and
therefore at this period I wrote little.
In 1952 I went to Korea to see the
Chinese volunteers and stayed among
them for some time. This was the first
time that I had met ordinary soldiers
and lived with them. I was somewhat
anxious : a man who had shut himself up
in his study for so long and who had
landed up in a great family of revolu¬
tionary soldiers would surely be a target
of criticism. Not a bit of it! The soldiers
did not treat me as an outsider and
welcomed me as if I were one of them.
I had come from the homeland, and
they were extremely kind to me. Feel¬
ings like love and hatred are more
manifest in places where war is raging.
I became attached to these people and
their surroundings and became their
friend. I no longer thought about my
writing.
I often travelled abroad. I published
a number of articles and essays in praise
of friendship between peoples. I made
new friends and envisioned the shining
future of cultural exchanges between
different nations. I wrote widely in
praise of our new society and our new
life. These writings were used as
evidence of my "crime" and were con¬
demned as "poisonous weeds" during
the ten years of the "Great Cultural
Revolution". I myself was illegally de¬
tained and suffered from all kinds of
mental torture and humiliation. During
these ten years I was deprived of all my
civic rights and denied the freedom to
publish. I began translating Herzen's
memoirs, a project I had had in mind
for some forty years.
Each day I translated several hundred
words. As I worked, I felt as if I were
walking through the darkness with
Herzen. As he cursed the dictatorship of
Tsar Nicholas I, I cursed the fascist rule
exercised by the "gang of four". I firm¬
ly believed that their days were
numbered. I survived to witness their
fall. I was liberated a second time, and
once again I picked up my pen.
Excited and elated, I felt that a vast
new horizon stretched before me. I
wanted to write. There was so much I
wanted to say. But I don't have many
years left, I can't afford to waste a
second. I've set myself a five-year plan.
I intend to write two novels, a book en¬
titled Reminiscences of Literary Crea¬
tion, five volumes of "Random
Thoughts", and to complete my
translation of Herzen's memoirs. Of
these thirteen books, four have already
been published, including the first
volume of Herzen's memoirs. The
second, entitled True Words, is being
printed. I shall do all I can to complete
the other eight works. I must steer clear
of anything that may sidetrack me, and
save every minute for my writing. Some
8
people regard me as a "personality"
and arrange all kinds of social activities
for me. Others want to interview me and
note down whatever I say, hoping to get
some historic testimony before it is too
late. But all I want to do is to write until
I die. I want to write novels, not
necessarily true stories. But I must sum
up what I experienced during the ten
years of the "Cultural Revolution".
Those ten unforgettable years con¬
stitute an important episode in the
history of humanity. Few writers in the
world experienced such dreadful,
ridiculous, strange, painful events. We
were all involved, we all played a part,
and today when we look back at what
we did during those years we find our
behaviour ridiculous but it didn't
seem like that at the time. I often say to
myself that if I don't sum up those ten
hard years and analyse myself sincerely,
I may one day again regard cruelty,
savagery, and stupidity as part of the
normal order of things. The mental debt
can never be paid. I have decided to
write these two novels first to pay off
this debt and secondly to end my fifty
years of literary life.
I have never thought about writing
technique or ways of expression when
writing my stories. What I care about is
how to help people lead a better life, a
worthy life, and how to help my readers
contribute to society and to the people.
All my writings have this aim.
In 1935, two years after the publica¬
tion of my novel The Family, I said: "I
have never ceased to attack my enemies
ever since I picked up my pen to write.
But who are my enemies? All the old
feudal codes, all the irrational systems
that hamper social progress and human
fulfilment, all the forces that destroy
Photo © China, Beijing
China's great rivers, supplemented b.y a canal net¬
work begun as early as the 5th century BC, are
vast arteries of communication and transport, pro¬
vide precious irrigation water and, harnessed to
produce electric power, are an increasingly impor¬
tant renewable energy source. But in many parts
of the country they also pose the threat of serious
flooding. The dramatic photo at right shows a
rescue team helping stricken villagers to safety
through the foaming waters of the Changjiang
(Yangtse) during a flood which in 1981,
devastated parts of Sichuan province. The
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
love. I've never budged from this posi¬
tion and never compromised."
When I met a group of Sinologists in
Paris in September 1981 someone asked
how I had survived the "cultural revolu¬
tion". Their sincere desire to under¬
stand something which seemed quite
ordinary to us set my mind working.
Those ten dreadful years had taught me
something. At last I came to realize
what I have learned from those long
years of disaster.
Gradually things became clearer in
my mind. It must be love, fire, hope,
something positive. Many people had
survived because they had these
qualities. But many had been destroyed
and left to us their love, fire and hope to
be transmitted to posterity. No, I shall
never lay down my pen.
Ba Jin
catastrophe rendered over a million homeless and
claimed 1,350 lives. Air photo above shows the
great hydroelectric power station at Liujiaxia. It
has been estimated that by 1977 hydroelectric
power stations provided nearly 38 per cent of
China's total power generating capacity. Above
right, detail of an ancient wooden temple in honour
of a water divinity at Taiyuan. The projecting
eaves are supported by the ingenious system of
bracket sets found in some of the earliest surviving
Chinese buildings and which became a
characteristic feature of Chinese architecture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Controversial
Confucius
In China today, the ancient
philosopher's works
are a source of lively debate
by Pang Pu
The Master said, "When there is a preponderance of
native substance over acquired refinement, the result
will be churlishness. When there is a preponderance of
acquired refinement over native substance, the result
will be pedantry. Only a well-balanced admixture of
these two will result in gentlemanliness. "
The Master said : "That a man lives is because he is
straight. That a man who dupes others survives is
because he has been fortunate enough to be spared. "
Book 6
The Master said, "Inever enlighten anyone who has not
been driven to distraction by trying to understand a dif¬
ficulty or who has not got into afrenzy trying to put his
ideas into words. When I have pointed out one corner
ofa square to anyone and he does not come back with
the other three, I will not point it out to him a second
time. "
Book 7
There is little to choose between overshooting the mark
and falling short.
Book 11
The Master said, "To fail to speak to a man who is
capable of benefiting is to let a man go to waste. To
speak to a man who is incapable of benefiting is to let
one's words go to waste. "
Book 15
Extracts from Lun Yu (The Analects) by Confucius. Translated by
D.C. Lau. Penguin Books, 1979. © D.C. Lau
Confucius (c. 551 -c. 479 BC) is considered to be the
father of Chinese philosophy. He liked to say that he was
a direct descendant of the Song rulers of China, which in
his time was enmeshed in social and political strife. The
empire was divided into a large number of States govern¬
ed by nobles whose pastime was war and who oppressed
and exploited their subjects. Like Plato in later times, Con¬
fucius believed that he could preach to tyrants a certain
form of virtue, and travelled from court to court in an at¬
tempt to instil in local rulers his precepts of political morali¬
ty. His efforts met with little success, but after his death
his more lowly-born disciples, the most important of
whom was Mencius (Meng zi), set down his doctrines in
the Four Books and the Five Classics, and some of them
obtained prominent government positions. Gradually, a
body of high officials, the mandarinate, came into being,
notably during the Han dynasty and the Tang period.
These functionaries were recruited by competition in the
schools where the teaching was based on Confucian
texts, and found in the philosopher's work their perfect
ideological expression: the concept of the State which
they served allowed the political élite which they formed
to perpetuate itself. Although the privileges of the man¬
darins were based on learning, not hereditary right, the
Confucianism of the mandarinate bore the imprint of tradi¬
tionalism and conservatism. Its scholastic nature was an
obstacle to any reinvigoration of Chinese life, especially
during the nineteenth century. Consequently, Confucius
and his teachings were at first totally rejected in socialist
China. In recent years, however, deeper historical
analysis has set Confucius more firmly in his time and in¬
troduced different shades of emphasis into judgments
about him and his work. The article by Pang Pu on this
page outlines the main points at issue.
10
T
HE influence of Confucius during his lifetime and the
value of his teachings have been the centre of
vigorous controversy in China for several decades.
The philosopher lived towards the end of the so-called
Spring and Autumn period (722-480 BC) which was marked
by violent social upheavals. Some historians maintain that
this was the time when Chinese society based on slave-
ownership was transformed into a feudal society. If this was
so, then Confucius may have represented the interests of the
emerged landowner class in opposition to the entrenched
slaveholding class. His political role would in this case have
been positive and progressive.
However, many historians consider that this radical change
in Chinese society occurred somewhat later, during the Warr¬
ing States period (480-221 BC). In their opinion, Confucius
represented the interests of the declining slaveholding class
and consequently his political position was reactionary. As he
travelled from State to State, his principal objective was to
restore the old order based on slavery.
According to yet another school of thought, these pro¬
found social changes had taken place during the Western
Zhou dynasty, which ruled from the eleventh century to
722 BC. For those who hold this view, Confucius champion¬
ed the interests of the lower and middle strata of the
aristocracy and of the budding caste of high officials. What
Confucius wished to restore was not an order based on slavery
but the unity of an empire which, at the beginning of the Zhou
dynasty had broken up into powerful vassal States. The
unification advocated by Confucius would have speeded up
social development, so the argument runs.
Lastly, some Chinese historians believe that the feudal era
began at a much later date, during the period of the Wei
kingdom and the Jin dynasty (from 220 to 420 AD). Their
thesis is that until the time when the Wei, one of the States of
the Three Kingdoms, replaced the Han dynasty, productive
PANG PU is a journalist with the Chinese magazine Historical Studies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Photo <Z Lauros Giraudon, Pans. Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
Scene from the life of Confucius and his disciples as depicted in an early 19th-century Chinese painting.
work throughout China was largely carried out by slaves. The
age of Confucius was simply a transitional period; the old
slaveholding system still existed, but productive work was
beginning to be done by people reduced to slavery by debt.
Seen in this light, Confucius should not be accused of seeking
to restore the institution of slavery for the simple reason that
slavery still existed. In spite of the conservative caste of his
thinking, Confucius was thus not an out-and-out reactionary.
Confucius' political thinking was built on the two concepts
of ren and //. Although opinions differ on the subject, ren
(which literally means "benevolence" or "humanity") is
generally taken to denote the principles by virtue of which
people can live in society or love each other mutually.
Some scholars argue that ren was meant to impose rules of
conduct on slave-owners threatened by frequent revolts by
their slaves. In this way Confucius was seeking to attenuate
the contradictions between the dominators and the
dominated, as well as those which arose within the ruling class
itself, thereby serving incidentally the interests of the oppress¬
ed. And since, according to the same scholars, no previous
theory had taken account of humanity in its entirety, the
teachings of Confucius should be considered as revolutionary
and the man himself as the greatest thinker of his age.
Other historians reject this thesis, maintaining that Con¬
fucius did not intend that slaves and other labourers should
be treated with "benevolence" and that Confucius was in no
way progressive.
Most specialists seem to adopt a position somewhere bet¬
ween these two extremes. If they stress that Confucius' theory
was fallacious and that it strengthened the hand of the ex¬
ploiting class, they also admit that it took account, in an un¬
precedented way, of the common people.
For Confucius, //' (which may be translated literally as
"ritual", "ceremony" or "rules of propriety and
politeness") was the keystone of the established order but
also designated standards of individual conduct. Some
believe that some of Confucius' teachings on the subject of li
were useful not only for his own time but also for later genera¬
tions, and that // was thus in a sense positive. Others consider,
however, that since they were intended to shore up the mori¬
bund slaveholding system, the tenets of conduct laid down by
Confucius were fundamentally bad.
It is more generally believed, however, that although Con¬
fucius felt nostalgia for a bygone age, and especially for the
heyday of the Western Zhou, he succeeded in tailoring his
philosophy to the new relationships between human beings
which had become established in the society of his time.
Confucius preached ' 'the mandate of heaven", was oppos¬
ed to reform of any kind, and respected spirits and divinities.
His thought is sometimes seen as no more than a corpus of
idealistic metaphysics. On the other hand, it is pointed out
that in Confucianism "heaven' ' is identified with nature, that
the philosopher himself was extremely sceptical about the ex¬
istence of spirits and the soul and that such thinking was ex¬
tremely audacious in comparison with that of his contem¬
poraries. He attached great importance to moral principles
and to individual initiative; he formulated rational ideas
which enriched the theory of knowledge; he was
convinced that history is a continuous, ongoing process. To
qualify his thinking as "metaphysical" is to compress its
meaning to an exaggerated degree.
Most scholars recognize Confucius' importance as an
educator. While some historians claim that private schools
for the lower orders existed before his time, the majority ac¬
cord him the distinction of being the first teacher to dispense
learning outside the official schools attached to the court. In
so doing, he took culture and education outside the
aristocratic circle of which they had hitherto been the
monopoly.
Where pedagogical theory was concerned, Confucius was
ahead of his time. He advocated an education accessible to
all, irrespective of social origins. His approach took account
of the different aptitudes of each pupil and foreshadowed the
Socratic method of bringing out ideas latent in the mind.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Photo E. Erwitt © Magnum, Pans
Three in one
The single complete art of calligraphy,
poetry and painting
by Huang Miaozhi
IN China, poetry, painting and calligraphy are not
confined within the boundaries which usually separate
these arts. Whatever the specific characteristics of
each may be, all three are inspired and determined by the
nature of ideographic expression; all three aspire to grasp
with the same instrument, the brush, the profound nature of
existence, the "breath of inspiration" that quickens every
form and gives it its special rhythm; all three are the arts of
the brush-stroke. In the words of Han Yu, a great writer
who lived during the Tang dynasty. "It matters little
whether a speech be short or long... if the 'breath' be
powerful".
This notion of the "primordial breath" (the qi) is central.
The aim of Chinese aesthetics is to achieve the living essence
of the quickening breath, of rhythm, of life: art and the art
of living are one and the same. The brush-stroke, whether
in a painting or a poem, whether it transcribes the branch
HUANG MIAOZHI, Chinese art critic, is a member of the Chinese
Committee ofFine Arts and Literature. Among his published works are
How to Appreciate the Arts? and a number of biographies of modern
Chinese painters including Qi Baishi, Xu Baihong (Jupeon) and Fu
Baoshi.
of a tree or a character, must always be a living form. It is
this common effort to evoke the essential which is
characteristic of calligraphy, poetry and painting.
But painting alone englobes the other modes of expres¬
sion. The unity between painting and poetry appears early
in Chinese history. In a scroll painting attributed to Gu
Kaizhi (late fourth century AD), Admonitions of the In¬
structress to the Court Ladies, the elegantly calligraphed
text of a moralist may already be read.
During the Tang dynasty (7th to 10th century), the period
which marks the real beginning of scroll painting, painters
were inspired by the works of the great poets Du Fu and Li
Bai (8th century), and poets were closely interested in pic¬
torial creation. In a judgment which underscores the con¬
cern of the Chinese poet and painter to render life in all its
profundity, Du Fu explains why the renowned horse-painter
Han Gan is inferior to his master Cao Ba:
To paint his horses Han Gan has depicted the flesh but
not the skeleton
That is why his chargers have no stamina.
Already we find those who were both painters and poets.
Wang Wei (701-761), for example, was the inventor of the
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Calligraphy Ung No Lee © Ed. Ides et Calendes, Neuchâtel
Writing at one
with the universe
Opposite page, morning gymnastics in
Shanghai. Above, the Chinese character ren,
"man". The two ¡mages strikingly illustrate a
distinctive feature of the Chinese ideogram: its
link with the real world. In early Chinese
writing, many characters even consisted of
small drawings, or pictograms. By preserving a
form of continuity between signs and the vis¬
ible world, the Chinese express the desire
which has always been theirs, that man should
not be cut off and isolated from the universe.
The affinity between ideograms and the signs
drawn in ink by the poet and painter Henri
Michaux (left) reflects his fascination with
Chinese writing and his desire to create a
poetic language halfway between words and
forms in which the stirrings of life can be felt in
the sign itself.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Private collection. Pans
Photo © China, Beijing
Mountains
and water
In Chinese, landscape painting is called
"Mountain and Water" painting. For
the Chinese, mountains and water are
the two poles of nature and also, by a
typically Chinese assimilation, of
human sensibility. In the words of Con¬
fucius: "The mountain enchants the
man of heart; water rejoices the man of
spirit." Painting landscapes is thus a
way of painting man, not his physical
attributes, but his inner being, his
torments, his dreams. Traditional
Chinese painting employed water col¬
ours and inks, and the water-holder,
above, which contained the water used
to moisten the artist's ink-sticks, is
itself in the form of a drop of water. The
"painting", left, is in fact a highly
polished piece of marble whose natural
veining forms a mountain landscape, to
which a calligraph has been added. The
calligraph, below left, of the Chinese
ideogram for the word shan, or moun¬
tain, is echoed In the bronze ritual ob¬
ject (4th century BC), bottom right. The
theme of the mountain is still omnipre¬
sent in Chinese art, as witness the pain¬
ting, above right, by the artist Fu Baoshi
(1904-1965) and the photo-landscape
with added calligraph, above far right,
by the world-famous Hong Kong
photographer Cheng Fuli.
Calligraphy Ung No Lee © Ed. Ides et Calendes, Neuchâtel
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Chinese edition, Unesco Courier Photo Cheng Fuli © China, Beijing
Photo (9 China, beijing
technique of monochrome painting, an adept of chan (zen
in Japanese) spirituality, and a musician as well. The great
writer and calligrapher Su Shi would write of him:
You would say his landscapes are poems
And his poems landscapes.
Another painter-poet was Du Fu's friend Zheng Qian,
who presented the emperor with one of his paintings on
which he had calligraphed poems. In an extraordinary token
of esteem, the emperor himself noted on the painting:
"Zheng Qian, the genius with three talents."
This threefold mastery combined in a single person is that
of the "literary-man-painter' ' . Literary men's painting, which
developed under the Tang dynasty but blossomed above all
under the Song and the Yuan, the Ming and the Qing, is what
is usually meant when people discuss Chinese painting. It owes
its great freedom, directly or indirectly, to Taoist and Buddhist
influences.
One of the most subtle masters of this marriage of poetry,
calligraphy and painting was Su Shi (Su Dongpo,-
1035-1101), with whom the unity of the three arts was
established, to become the mainstream of Chinese painting.
One day, while intoxicated at the home of a friend, he
painted a bamboo tree on the wall and added this
comentary:
The alcohol vapours have expanded in my empty belly,
Rocks and bamboo grow there willy nilly,
My body cannot cope with them,
That's why I project them on your white wall.
And he went on, not without humour :
But you, you do not scold me, you seem content.
There are not many connoisseurs in the world like you,
my friend.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Drawing, below, of a young cowherd playing
the flute comes from a famous treatise on
Chinese painting. The Mustard-Seed Garden
(1 679-1 701 ) which contains over 400 illustra¬
tions. The caption to this drawing reads: "The
sound of a flute is heard among the flowers. A
young cowherd passes." Carved in stone, the
flautist, right, is one of 10,000 Buddhist
sculptures created over a period of a mere
70 years during the Song dynasty at
Baodingshan, near Dazu, Sichuan province.
The flute-player forms part of a series of reliefs
depicting the herdsman's life.
AC
tA
Drawing © Bollingen Foundation, New York Photo Ariane Bailey, Unesco
One of his contemporaries, Mi Fu, was a famous painter
and also a gifted calligrapher. The following story is told
about him, in accordance with a Chinese custom whereby the
distinctive styles of great painters are described in the form
of anecdotes:
"One day when he was at Wu-Wei, Mi Fu saw a giant rock
of extraordinary ugliness. Delighted, he donned his
ceremonial costume and prostrated himself before the rock,
which he addressed as 'dear elder brother'."
Under the Yuan dynasty (13th-14th century) this three-
point relationship became even stronger and deeper. Ni Zan
(or Yunlin, 1301-1374) was outstanding among the great
masters of the period. He was a peerless landscape painter
whose work was elegant, austere and imbued with poignant
nostalgia.
If painting in China is the complete art form in which poem
and calligraphy are an integral part of the painting, restoring
the harmony and mystery of the universe in all its dimensions,
poetry is considered to be the quintessence of art. It
transforms the written signs, enjoying an almost sacred
16
status, into song, and its supreme function is to link human
genius with the primary vital forces of the universe. Imbued
with Confucian and Taoist thought, Chinese poetry unites
reason and detachment. It aspires to penetrate reality and to
render, with the savour of life, "the impalpable rustling of
sound", helped by the innate musicality of the Chinese
language with its several tones.
In the painting, the poem is by no means an adjunct; it in¬
troduces a new dimension and opens the bounds of the picture
to life in time. Shi Dao, a celebrated painter of the early Qing
dynasty (18th- 19th century), was also the author of a famous
Treatise on Painting. His life was an unceasing investigation
both into technical problems and into the nature of artistic
creation and human destiny. In one of his landscapes he wrote
these lines:
This well-nigh deserted spot fills me with joy
The view of this mountain which hides clouds makes me
joyful.
Then he adds this piece of self-criticism, a reflection which
is Taoist in inspiration:
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
* * m
branch tip hibiscus blossom
Chinese poets have always made subtle use of the evocative
power of calligraphy. In a quatrain the first line of which is
reproduced above, the poet Wang Wei (701-761 ), describing an
hibiscus about to blossom, succeeds in conveying the idea of
what it would be like to live from within the tree the experience
of coming into bud and flowering. This is how François Cheng,
in his" book L 'Ecriture Poétique Chinoise (Chinese poetic writing),
comments on the first line of Wang Wei's quatrain.
"The line can be translated as: 'At the branch tips, hibiscus
blossoms'. Even a reader who knows nothing of Chinese can ap¬
preciate the concordance between the visual appearance of the
characters and the meaning of the words. Reading the characters
from left to right one has the impression of watching the process
of a tree coming into flower (Rrst character: a bare tree; second
character: something is visible at the end of the branches; third
character: a bud appears; fourth character: the bud opens; fifth
character: in full flower). But a reader who knows Chinese will
see even more. Subtly hidden in the ideograms is the notion of
man (X) entering into the tree in spirit and participating in its
metamorphosis.
Chinese poets have used a variety of methods to introduce the idea of
the Void into their works. Poem above is a veritable labyrinth of signs in
which, starting from any given point, the reader can choose to take
many different routes, full of surprises.
Naxi hieroglyphs
© Chinese edition, Unesco Courier
In addition to the characters used by the Han Chinese, certain of China's
minority nationalities have at one time or another created their own writ¬
ten language. The Naxi (230,000 persons who live mainly in the region
of Lijiang, Yunan province) developed a hieroglyphic language con¬
sisting of basic pictorial symbols and ideograms. The language was used
for the composition of canonical books of their religion (known as
Dongbaism), for recording events of everyday life, keeping accounts,
and the exchange of messages between mountain villages. It yields im¬
portant evidence on the origins of writing as well as throwing light on the
Naxi culture. In China today research is being carried out into the links
between Naxi hieroglyphs and the Chinese language. Table below
shows, Naxi hieroglyphs (left-hand column), Han hieroglyphs (right
hand column) and modern Chinese ideograms (central column). Above,
Naxi hieroglyphs from the Dongba scripture, "The Origin of the Human
Being".
My words are strange, my drawing is clumsy,
All is but illusion, even this work.
To look from the poem to the landscape, with its pines,
clouds and mountains, is to be filled with deeper emotion. Shi
Dao has heightened our perception of the uplifting of the
mountain and the Vacuity represented by the clouds. This no¬
tion of Vacuity, no less essential to Chinese philosophy than
the famous Yin-Yang principle, plays a central role in music
and poetry but is most fully and visibly expressed in painting.
Vacuity in a painting does not only mark the "unoccupied"
area in contrast to an "occupied" area; far from being an in¬
ert presence, Vacuity is a dynamic element. Linked to the idea
of the "breath of life", it is pre-eminently the location of
those transformations which lie at the heart of the conception
of man and the world in Chinese thought.
The favourite texts of Chinese calligraphers are doubtless
poetic texts (verses, poems, poetic prose). Calligraphy in
China exalts the visual beauty of ideograms . In practising this
major art, every Chinese rediscovers the profound rhythm of
his being and enters into communion with the elements. Not
confining himself to the simple act of the copyist, the
calligrapher reawakens the expressive movement and the im¬
aginary power of signs. Calligraphy must be the total projec¬
tion of the condition of a soul.
The writer Han Yu praised the famous Tang calligrapher
Zhang Xu in these words: "By the freedom of his script, in
the cursive style which he invariably practised, he expresses
his joy and his anger, his pain and his happiness, his jealousies
and hatreds, his affections and admirations, his intoxication,
his boredom, injustice, everything that thrills his heart." The
calligrapher should also exploit the pictorial possibilities, the
evocative power of characters, as Han Yu adds in his com¬
ments on Zhang Xu: "...he holds everything in his vision:
landscapes, animals, plants, stars, storms, fires, wars, feasts,
all the events of the universe, and expresses them through his
art."
Thus in China poetry, calligraphy and painting constitute
one complete art, a threefold pursuit in which all the spiritual
dimensions of its devoted practitioners are brought into play:
linear song and space, incantatory gestures and visualized
WOrdS. «Huang Miaozhi
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Works
and days
in
Zhejiang
Province
Photos © China, Beijing
Wisdom
of the ages
Laozi (Lao-Tzu)
The ten thousand things rise and fall
while the Self watches their return.
They grow andflourish and then return
to the source.
Returning to the source is stillness,
which is the way of nature.
The way ofnature is unchanging.
Knowing constancy is insight.
Not knowing constancy leads to
disaster.
Knowing constancy, the mind is open.
With an open mind, you will be
openhearted.
XVI
He who does not trust enough will not
be trusted.
XVII
Yield and overcome;
Bend and be straight;
Empty and be full;
Wear out and be new;
Have little and gain;
Have much and be confused.
XXII
Good weapons are instruments offear;
all creatures hate them.
XXXI
Keep your mouth closed.
Guard your senses.
Temper your sharpness.
Simplify your problems.
Mask your brightness.
Be at one with the dust of the earth.
This is primal union.
LVI
A journey of a thousand miles starts
under one's feet.
LXIV
Truthful words are not beautiful.
Beautiful words are not truthful.
LXXXI
From Tao Te Ching by Lao Tzu
translated by Gia-fu feng and Jane English
© Vintage Books, New York
Zhuangzi (Chuang Tzu)
Great wisdom observes both far and
near, and for that reason recognizes
small without considering it paltry,
recognizes large without considering it
unwieldy, for it knows that there is no
end to the weighing of things.
Autumn Floods
From The Complete Works ofChuang Tzu
translated by Burton Watson
© Columbia University Press, 1968
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Pen
of protest
The seminal work
of Lu Xun
by Li Helin
Lu Xun at the age of fifty.
B
ORN in 1881, at Shaoxing in the Zhejiang province of
China, Zhou Shu-ren, better known by his pen name.
Lu Xun, was a major figure of twentieth-century Chinese
literature. From his pen flowed a stream of short stories, prose-
poems, essays, translations and historical studies. Twenty-five of
his short stories on contemporary subjects were published in two
widely translated collections. Call to Arms and Hesitation. Among
them, the most famous is The True Story of Ah Q in which, with
a telling combination of pathos and humour, he highlighted the
shortcomings of the old social order. In another collection of short
stories. Old Tales Retold, this time with an historical setting, he
succeeded in satirizing contemporary life while scrupulously
respecting historical fact.
Lu Xun's inventive spirit revealed itself in Wild Grass, an an¬
thology of twenty-four beautifully concise and subtly allusive
prose-poems, the only anthology of this genre in modern Chinese
literature. Morning Flowers Plucked at Dawn recalled his life as a
youth, but at the same time was a critical exposure of the negative
aspects of the society of the past.
A master essayist. Lu Xun also penned some eight hundred
essays, most of which were political in character. In them he
assailed feudalism, the compradors, bureaucrats, the bourgeoisie,
opportunists of left and right and traitors.
Lu Xun's historical studies included a Brief History of Han
Literature and an Outline History of Chinese Fiction. Based
originally on the lecture notes he used when teaching at Beijing
University in 1 920, his Outline History of Chinese Fiction took ten
years to revise and complete in its definitive form. No one before
him had systematically studied the origins of Chinese fiction and
written, for a wide public, about how it evolved from ancient
myths and from the legends recounted by the public storytellers of
the Song (10th to 13th century) and Yuan (13th to 14th century)
dynasties, reaching a peak with the vernacular novels under the
Ming and the Manchu dynasties (14th to 20th century).
But Lu Xun was not only an accomplished writer, he was also
a great thinker and revolutionary. In 1903, in A Brief Study of
Chinese Geology, he voiced his indignation against the plunder of
the rich mineral resources of China by the imperialist powers. In an
article published in 1907, he criticized those theoreticians who
wanted "to save China through industrialization" and "laid stress
on material things at the expense of things spiritual." For Lu Xun,
only through the education of the people could their conscience be
aroused. He took a dialectical view of the relationship between
LI HELIN is a member of the China Federation of Literary and Art
Circles, and director of the Lu Xun Museum in Beijing. He is the author
of a number of studies on Lu Xun and on various aspects of contem-
potary Chinese literature.
material and spiritual things and called for a China in which man
would take pride of place.
In May 1918, six months after the October Revolution, Lu Xun
published a short story entitled A Madman's Diary in the magazine
New Youth. It is interesting to compare the difference of approach
to the problems of oppressed peoples as expressed in Lu Xun's A
Madman's Diary and in the nineteenth century Russian writer
Gogol's story of the same name. Gogol's hero isa poor devil who has
the audacity to fall in love with a government minister's daughter
and ends up in a lunatic asylum. Although Gogol's story brings out
the darker aspects of Tsarist society, he stops short of demanding
its overthrow. Lu Xun's story, however, shows that throughout its
centuries-long history Chinese society had been a "man-eating"
society which, despite its claim to be based on "virtue and morali¬
ty", ruthlessly exploited the weak and had to be overthrown. Lu
Xun's anti-feudal ideas were entirely different from those of the
bourgeois revolutionaries. He aimed not only to sweep away all
traces of feudal culture, but to destroy completely the "man-
eating" society which fostered this culture.
In 1 923, Lu Xun gave a lecture at the Beijing Women's College en¬
titled What happened after Nora left home? This was shortly after
the period of the reformist protest May Fourth Movement, which
emerged following the riots which broke out on 4 May 1919 and
which called for equality between the sexes and for a free choice of
marriage partners. This was also the time at which the Norwegian
writer Henrik Ibsen's A Doll's House was translated and published
in Chinese, achieving a wide popular success. Loth to remain her
husband's puppet, Nora, Ibsen's heroine, leaves home, an action of
which most Chinese readers approved. In his lecture, however, Lu
Xun examined a deeper and more practical question: "What hap¬
pened after Nora left home?" He pointed out that in the society of
the time only two possibilities were open to her to sink to the
depths or to return to her husband. So long as women were not
economically independent and could not work for their living, they
had either to beg or to remain dependent on men. In a cut-throat
society there was no other means of survival.
Lu Xun pointed out that: "The most important problem in today's
society seems to be the achievement of economic rights. First there
must be a fair sharing out between men and women in the family;
secondly, men and women must have equal rights in society. Unfor¬
tunately, I have no idea how we are to obtain these rights; all I know
is that we have to fight for them, and we may even have to fight
harder for them than for political rights. If you speak about the equal
distribution of wealth you will probably find yourselves faced with
enemies who will fight you bitterly. For in present-day society it is
not just women who are the puppets of men; men control other men
and women control women; and sometimes men are even the pup¬
pets of women. This problem will not be solved by the acquisition
by a handful of women of their economic rights. But people with^
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
empty stomachs cannot sit back and wait for the arrival of an ideal
world; so we need this relatively attainable goal until we can devise
other measures. Of course, if the economic system changes then all
this is empty talk".
Lu Xun returned to the theme expounded in What happened after
Nora left home? in his story Regret for the Past, written two years
later. In this story, in defiance of feudal ethical codes, the hero and
heroine come together in a marriage of love. However, since Zijun,
the heroine, is not economically independent, she becomes merely
a housewife, busy cooking, feeding the chickens and looking after
the dog.
When Juansheng, the hero, loses his job, he realizes that, blinded
by love, he has neglected all the other important things in life. "A
man must make a living before there can be any place for love..."
He begins to see his wife as a burden. "She never opens a book any
more and has forgotten that the most important thing in life is to
make a living. To do this a couple must go forward hand in hand, or
else struggle on alone." Finally, he tells her ruthlessly that he no
longer loves her. They part and Zijun returns to her parents, who had
opposed the idea of her choosing freely her own marriage partner.
In the cold and hostile atmosphere of her parents' home she falls into
a decline and finally departs a loveless world.
Lu Xun's activity as a writer and a social thinker cannot be divorc¬
ed from the practical role he played in the revolutionary struggle. In
1 904, when he was living in Japan, he joined the Liberation Society,
a revolutionary group opposed to the Manchu dynasty then in power
in China. From 1911 to 1 925, while he was teaching in his home
town of Shaoxing, and at the Women's College in Beijing he carried
on the patriotic struggle drawing his own students into it. His
political stance earned for him the hostility of a number of politicians
and bourgeois intellectuals. In 1 926, threatened with arrest, he took
refuge in a hospital.
In 1928, he joined the Revolutionary Mutual Aid Society, to
whose funds he was a regular contributor. In 1 930, in Shanghai, he
participated in the founding of the China League of Left-wing
Writers, but a warrant for his arrest was issued and once again he
was forced to go into hiding. In 1 933, together with Song Qinling,.
the widow of Sun Yat-sen, Cai Yuanpei and Yang Quan, he helped
to organize the China League for the Protection of Civil Rights in pro¬
test against the illegal imprisonment and assassination of revolu¬
tionaries and to provide a basis for the fight for democracy and liber¬
ty . In May of that year, accompanied by Song Qinling and Cai Yuan¬
pei, he went to the German consulate in Shanghai to hand in a pro¬
test against the persecution of writers and the burning of books on
the orders of Hitler. On June 1 8, Yang Quan, the deputy leader of
the China League for the Protection of Civil Rights, was
assassinated. On June 20, against the advice of his friends, and
braving the risk of being himself assassinated, Lu Xun attended
Yang Quan's funeraL
It would not be possible here to list all Lu Xun's activities aimed
at achieving the radical social transformation he so much wanted for
his country. One thing is certain, his works have stood the test of
time, and both in his writings and in his actions he was always to be
found on the side of the common people and the oppressed.
Li Helin
Illustration below shows an incident from one of
Lu Xun's most famous works. The True Story of
Ah Q, which evokes the humiliations of China's
rural poor early in this century. It was drawn by a
noted caricaturist. Ding Cong.
20
Night
thoughts,
November
1926
by Lu Xun
r T HIS evening (1), all around me, everything is perfectly
I calm. Behind my dwelling, at the foot of the moun-
M tain, a grass fire burns with little, flickering flames.
Now and then, the sound of drums and gongs reaches me
from the South Putuo Temple (2), where a marionette perfor¬
mance is taking place. When the distant noise ceases, the
silence returns with even greater insistence. My lamp shines
brightly, but a twinge of unhappiness creeps up on me from
goodness knows where, and I have the impression that I am
sorry to have had my essays printed. This sense of regret sur¬
prises me: it is out of keeping with my characters. But before
I can pin it down, it evaporates . Of course, I must press ahead ,
and nave the essays published; but if only to exorcize this
melancholy, I feel that I must add one or two words more.
As I have said before, these essays are no more than a few
traces left by my life, if my past can be called a life. I have
worked hard enough, but my thought is not a gushing spring,
my literary talent is without great brilliance and, since I have
no doctrine to advance, I have no intention of launching a
movement of any kind. But experience has taught me that
disappointment.-whether great or small, has a bitter taste.
This is why, whenever in recent years I have been asked to take
up my pen, I have never refused. Provided that their opinions
were not diametrically opposed to my own, and that I have
had the energy to do so, I have always tried to give a little
satisfaction to others.
Readers who claim me for their favourite writer often say
that I express the truth. This is excessive praise induced, no
doubt, by their very partiality. It is true that I do not seek to
deceive, but neither do I try to recount all that is within me.
What I express is merely a few odds and ends, just enough to
hand in to the printer. It is true that I often try to dissect other
people, but I apply the scalpel even more frequently to myself,
and with far less pity. When I lift only a corner of the veil , sen¬
sitive spirits quail . What if I were to reveal myself entirely, ex¬
actly as I am?
It occurs to me from time to time to use this method to drive
people away, so that those who even then did not abandon
me, "snakes and odious monsters" (3) though they might be,
would show themselves to be my friends, true friends after all.
And if even they left me in the lurch, then too bad, I'd walk
alone. But for the time being I refrain from putting this idea
into practice, partly because I lack the courage to do so, and
partly because I want to go on living in this society. But there
is another little reason, too, which I have mentioned several
times: it gives me a certain satisfaction to create for as long
as I can a feeling of unease among our "respectable and right-
thinking" fellow-citizens. This is why I shall continue to gird
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
myself with a few pieces of armour and stand before them,
disturbing their orderly world with my presence, until I
become tired of the whole business and take off this armour.
To serve as a guide to others is all the more difficult for me,
since I myself do not know which path to follow. There is cer¬
tainly no lack of "masters" and "guides" in China, but I am
not among them and they do not inspire my confidence. There
is only- one outcome of which I myself am certain, and that
is the tomb. But this is something everybody knows, without
having to consult a guide. The problem is that more than one
way leads to that ultimate destination, and up to now I have
been unable to determine which of them to take. I am still try¬
ing to find out, and I am very much afraid that my still-green
fruit should poison those who appreciate me, while those who
detest me the "respectable and right-thinking", for
example all live to a ripe old age. It is thus inevitable for me
to clothe my words in ambiguity, since it often occurs to me
that the best gift I can offer to readers who are fond of me
might well be "inconsistency."
The first edition of my translations and original works was
printed in a thousand copies; five hundred more were printed
later. My most recent works have appeared in editions of two
thousand and four thousand copies. Of course each increase
is welcome, if only because it means that I shall earn more
money, but I cannot help feeling unhappy that my writings
might be morally harmful to my readers. This is why I now
write with a great deal more circumspection and hesitation.
Some people imagine that I write spontaneously, that the
words pour out in total freedom. Nothing could be further
from the truth: I am inhibited by a host of scruples and uncer¬
tainties, I have known for a long time that I am not of the stuff
that warriors and pioneers are made of. Three or four years
ago, I remember, a student arrived to buy one of my books.
The money which he took out of his pocket and pressed into
my hand was warm with the heat of his body. And that
warmth penetrated me, so much so that ever since then,
whenever I take up my pen, I am afraid of poisoning people
like that student; I hesitate for a long time before putting a
single word on paper. I fear that the time will never come
again when I can speak without such reserve, and although I
sometimes think that in order to respond to the expectations
of the younger generation one should sweep every scruple
aside, I have not, as yet, managed to bring myself to do so.
That is all I intended to say today, and it may be taken as
relatively sincere. But I do wish to add a few final remarks.
I remember that when the idea first emerged of creating a
literature based on our spoken language, it was violently at¬
tacked from every side. Later, when it had gained ground to
the extent that a reversal of the tendency was impossible,
many of its former critics turned their coats and claimed
credit for the change, which they glorified as the "new
culture" (4) movement. Others proposed that the spoken
language be used as the popular language; while still others
recommended a return to the study of the classics as a means
of acquiring perfect mastery of the spoken language. It was
not long before the turncoats made yet another pirouette, and
began to vilify the "new culture". As for the other two
groups, they have reluctantly accepted the new language,
while conserving the hope that the old one will nevertheless be
kept alive as long as possible; there are plenty of such people
still about, and I have denounced them in my essays.
A few days ago, I came across a journal from Shanghai (5),
in which it is also maintained that a study of the classics is
obligatory if one wishes to write well in the spoken language;
the names of a number of writers are cited as examples in this
connexion, including my own. This makes me shudder. I can¬
not speak for the others, but in my own case, it is true that I
have read many classic works, and that I continue to do so for
my own enlightenment. As a result, my eyes and ears are full
of them, and this influences the vocabulary, construction and
style of my bai hua (6), which sometimes contains archaisms.
But it is also true that it is very painful and suffocating for me
to carry these old monsters around on my back, and not be
able to rid myself of them.
As far as the poverty of the present popular language is con¬
cerned, the question of ways and means of enriching it con¬
stitutes another important problem. Perhaps this might be
achieved by the injection of suitable material drawn from anr
cient literature, but this is a matter which lies outside the scope
of my present remarks, and I shall refrain from dealing with
it here.
I do believe, however, that with an effort, I might be able
to correct my own texts by introducing words and expressions
from the spoken language. If I have failed to do so up to now,
this is simply because I am lazy, and have not had the time.
Unfortunately, all this coincides with the publication of
this collection of essays, which are written partly in classical
and partly in spoken Chinese. They may, therefore, still be a
poison to certain readers. But I am unable, for the moment,
to bring myself to destroy them; I might even go further, and
say that I shall make use of them myself, for the glimpse that
they give of myself as I was when they were written. All that
I ask is that the readers who appreciate me consider this col¬
lection as no more than a simple memorial a grave-mound
covering a body from which life has fled. With the passage of
time, the body will turn to dust, and not even the memorial
will remain. And by then, I, too, will have laid down my arms.
This morning, as I was indeed reading a classic wotk, a few
lines from Lu Ji's (7) Lamentation on the Death ofCao Cao
came into my head. Let them serve as my own conclusion
here.
Refusing the ritual burden of the ancients,
You wanted a funeral with less circumstance and pomp.
Where are yourfur coats, then, your finery, your seals?
All that remains is the grumbling of the princes in the
procession.
Alas! Even a wise man like you was unable to resist
Excessive attachment to worldly goods.
Reading the document that betrays your weakness,
I dedicate these lines to you, with regrets.
Lu Xun
On the night of 11 November 1926
/. The postface to The Tomb, from which this text is extracted, was written
in November 1926, about a year after completion of the last of the essays of
which the work consists. Lu Xun had recently left Beijing, where hisfreedom
hadbeen threatened and had taken a teachingpost at the university ofXiamen
(Amoy).
2. The temple is situated near the university ofXiamen.
3. In the original: "Xiao, snakes, and revenants". Xiao was an unpleasant
mythical bird whose repellent attributes included devouring its o wn mother.
4. The movement for literary reform in favour of "spoken" language and
literature whichformedpart ofthe "Fourth ofMay"culturaldemonstrations
in 1919. Lu Xun's irony is particularly directed against Hu Shi, who joined
in the movement at the beginning, quickly changed sides to become one of
its most bitter adversaries, but later claimed to have been its originator and
main architect. The term ' 'new culture ' ' was used by Hu Shi in a number of
articles on the history of the "Fourth ofMay".
5. Vol. I, No. 3 of the monthly magazine Yiban (Just So) published by Kai-
ming anddated 11 November 1926 contains an article by Ming Shi (alias Zhu
Guangshuan), entitled'Yutiandeshu (The rainydays book) in which it isstated
that in order to write good bai hua, i.e. "spoken language" it is necessary
to read wen yan i. e. the classics. The article goes on to say that this is the case
ofHu Shi, Wu Zhihui, Zhou Zuoren and Lu Xun, "although they may not
admit this themselves".
6. Writing in the "spoken language. "
7. Lu Ji (261-303) was a famous writer. Cao Cao (155-220) was a general
renownedfor his military prowess, and a politician. In his testament, which
Lu Ji readjust before writing thispoem, Cao Cao calledfor a simplification
ofthefuneral ceremonies governed by ancient tradition, but at thesame time
refused any sharing out ofhis "clothes offur"andofthe' 'ribbons decorating
the seals"; his last wishes also included instructions to thefemale singers at
his funeral.
English basedon theFrench translation oftheThe Tomb, byLuXun, translated
from Chinese under the direction ofMichelle Loi and the Lu Xun Research
Centre of the People's Republic ofChina. La Tombe was published by Edi¬
tionsAcropole in 1981, and is included in the Unesco Collection ofRepresen¬
tative Works.
French translation © Unesco
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
China through the ages
The origins ofthe Chinese people go back at least
a million years to a hominid who appeared in
China at the end of the second glacial period.
With Beijing Man, who lived about 400, 000years
ago appeared the first signs of a communal
culture, and with the Xia kingdom the Chinese
people emerged from the mists ofprehistory to
embark on the adventure of modern times. On
the following eight colour pages we offer a brief
glimpse of eternal China through the ages.
Page 23 Page 24
Page 25
j^HMVV
Un J A
ÊJ8
^9
Page 26
¡ÎÈ j
w
f >
m 11
Page 27
1 ^ 12
i**
13
Page 28
Page 29 Page 30
Page 23
(1 ) One of the oldest prehistoric representations
of a human being to come down to us intact, this
painted terra-cotta head in the form of a mask
was found in north-west China and is probably a
representation of a Shaman, an ancient priest
and medicine-man. The snake slithering up the
back of the head of the mask (not visible in
photo) may well be a primitive precursor of the
Chinese dragon. (2) Marble bear from the Shang
dynasty. (3) Sophisticated carved jade pendant
depicting a tiger trampling a man dates from the
Zhou dynasty.
Page 24
(4) Green jade amulet depicting a dignified elder
dates from the Han dynasty. (5) For some two
thousand years these clay foot-soldiers, around
45 centimetres in height, stood guard undisturb¬
ed over the tomb of the Emperor Gaozu, the
founder of the Han dynasty. They formed one of
the seven phalanxes unearthed by Chinese ar¬
chaeologists during the 1970s near the city of
Xi'an, in the province of Shenxi. (6) Discovered
in the ruins of a palace built during the Qin dynas¬
ty, in the ancient city of Xi'an, this mural depic¬
ting a chariot drawn by four horses is the first
found from the Qin dynasty and the oldest
known fresco in China.
Page 25
(7) Jade and gold funerary vestments of prince
Liu Sheng, son of the fourth Han emperor Jingdi,
was one of the treasures found in two royal
tombs discovered in 1968 at Man-cheng in the
province of Hebei. These jade mailcoats were
believed to prevent the decomposition of the
body. (8) Fresco representing the Prince Sid-
dhartha (Buddha) dating from the Liang dynasty.
Buddhism came to China from India during the
first centuries AD. In Dunhuang, an oasis town in
Gansu province on the pilgrim road to India, are
the Mogao "caves of a thousand Buddhas",
grotto-temples hewn out between 366 AD and
the 10th century. With their 2,415 sculptures
and 45,000 square metres of frescoes, the
Mogao caves constitute one of the largest
treasuries of Buddhist art. (9) Detail from one of
the painted ceilings in the Mogao caves depic¬
ting an apsara. In Indian mythology apsaras were
feminine attendants who sang and danced for
the delight of gods and men. The fresco dates
from the Western Wei dynasty:
Page 26
(10) Detail from a Tang dynasty mural at
Dunhuang shows the great Chinese traveller
Zhang Qian dismounted and kneeling in front of
the emperor Wudi (not seen in photo) before his
departure on a mission to the Western Lands.
(11) Detail from a frieze in the Mogao caves,
dating from the Sui dynasty, recounts a Jataka
or tale of the Buddha's previous lives. Here he is
seen in his incarnation as Sudhana the young son
of a rich merchant noted for his generosity.
Page 27
(12) Birds and weeping-willow branch. Ink
painting on silk by the famous Song dynasty ar¬
tist Liang Kai. The circular format favoured by
Song dynasty artists, which derives from the
shape of the fan, symbolizes the world without
beginning and without end. (1 3) Lakeside in
moonlight. Ink painting on silk by an unknown
Song dynasty artist. The theme, a traditional
one, is the external world reduced to its simplest
expression; the observer is drawn into an
endless, dreamlike contemplation of the unseen.
Page 28
(1 4) Detail from one of the huge frescoes in the
main hall of the Yuan dynasty Taoist temple of
Yongle depicts heavenly and terrestrial divinities
attending an audience given by the three
supreme Taoist divinities. Formerly sited on the
bank of the Yellow River, the temple was moved
to the district of Ruicheng, Shenxi province, to
make way for the hydroelectric complex of
Sanmexia. The transfer, which began in 1959,
took seven years to complete. (15) The huge
Gate of Supreme Harmony, covering an area of
1 ,800 square metres, is the principal entrance to
the complex of buildings that constitute the Im¬
perial City, Beijing. It was here that the emperor
received his ministers in audience. Building of
the Imperial City was begun under the Yuan
dynasty, but was not completed until 200 years
later during the 1 5th century.
Page 29
(16) Detail of one of the many statues that line
the avenue leading to the tomb of Yongle, third
emperor of the Ming dynasty. (1 7) Scene from a
production at the Beijing Opera of the Legend of
the White Snake. The Beijing Opera offers a
popular form of theatre; plays draw their
material chiefly from traditional tales. The music
is provided mainly by percussion instruments
and two-string fiddles. A vigorous acrobatic
style of presentation was introduced during the
19th century and has remained a feature of the
Beijing Opera ever since.
Page 30
(18) Street scene in Beijing.
(19) Students at the university of Wuhan, the
fifth largest city in China. (20) Assembly worker
in a tractor factory.
(1 ) Photo © Museum of Antiquities of the Far East, Stockholm
(2) and (31 Photos © Bradley Smith, La Jolla. Seattle Art Museum
(4) Photo © Asian Art Museum of San Francisco. Avery Brun-
dage Collection
(5), (61 and (141 Photos © China, Beijing
(7) and (15) Photos © Marc Riboud, Pans
(8), (9), HOI and (11) Photos © Pierre Colombel, Paris
(12) and (13) Photos © Editions Cercle d'Art, Paris
(161,(1 7), (18) and 119) Photos Claude Sauvageot, Pans
(20) Photo Eve Arnold © Magnum, Pans
Table of Chinese dynasties
Xia kingdom
Shang kingdom
Zhou dynasty
Early Zhou period
Chunqiu period
Warring States period
Qin dynasty
Han dynasty
Western Han
Xin interregnum
Eastern Han
Three Kingdoms Period
Shu
Wei
Wu
Jin dynasty
Western
Eastern
(Liu) Song dynasty
c. 2000-c. 1 520 BC
c. 1520-c. 1030 BC
c. 1030-722 BC
722-480 BC
480-221 BC
221-207 BC
202 BC- 9 AD
9-23 AD
25-220 AD
221-265 AD
221-264 AD
220-265 AD
222-280 AD
265-31 7 AD
31 7-420 AD
420-479 AD
Northern and Southern dynasties
Qi
Liang
Chen
Northern Wei
Western Wei
Eastern Wei
Northern Qi
Northern Zhou
Sui dynasty
Tang dynasty
Five dynasties period
479-502 AD
502-557 AD
557-589 AD
386-535 AD
535-556 AD
534-550 AD
550-577 AD
557-581 AD
581-61 8 AD
61 8-906 AD
907-960 AD
(Later Liang, Later Tang, Later Jin, Later Han, Later Zhou)
Liao dynasty 907- 1 1 24 AD
West Liao dynasty 1 1 24-1 21 1 AD
Xi Xia State 986-1227 AD
Northern Song dynasty 960-1 126 AD
Southern Song dynasty 1 1 27- 1 279 AD
Jin (Tartar) dynasty 11 15- 1234 AD
Yuan (Mongoll dynasty 1 260-1 368 AD
Ming dynasty 1368-1 644 AD
Qing (Mandchu) dynasty 1644-191 1 AD
Republic 191 2 AD
Based on chronological table from Science in Traditional
China, by Joseph Needham
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
¡
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
A literature of combat
Self-portrait of a popular woman writer
by Ding Ling
Ding Ling, whose career spans more than half a century, is one of China's most popular authors. She is seen
here during a visit to a farm co-operative in 1955.
1am a Chinese writer, and for the first sixty years of my
life I lived, worked and wrote in the wake of the
Chinese people, by whose difficulties I have been
guided and inspired. In this way I came to know the world
and its contradictions, but at the cost of many trials and
tribulations. Today, at seventy-seven, one hope remainsto
be able to serve my fellow countrymen until I die.
I was born in 1904, at a time when the Manchu Empire
was in its death throes, into a family of notables, a breeding-
ground of mandarins such as described in those great classic
Chinese novels Dream of the Red Chamber, by Cao Xueqin,
and The Scholars, by Wu Jingzi.
My family was a replica in miniature of feudal society in
decline and its history was a chequered one. The branch of
the family to which my father belonged was impoverished
and going rapidly downhill, and when I was four years old
my father died completely ruined. My lonely childhood gave
me an insight into the miserable lot of the people in the
Chinese society of the beginning of the twentieth century
and opened my eyes to the selfish attitudes which governed
relationships between one man and another. I found com¬
fort in, and learned much from, reading the great Chinese
classic novels. European renaissance literature and foreign
literature of the nineteenth century was also grist to my mill.
And it was this reading that sowed in me the seed of my
vocation as a writer.
I had the good fortune to have an enlightened mother.
After my father's death she freed herself from the shackles
of the family, becoming a teacher to maintain her in¬
dependence. She had adopted Western democratic ideas and
nourished a vague hope of a socialist revolution. She often
told me stories of great historical figures, Chinese and
foreign, from both remote and recent times, who had
distinguished themselves by their heroism, generosity of
spirit and loyalty. These stories helped to dispel the melan¬
choly that had taken root in my young heart.
I was fourteen years old at the time of the events of May
1919 and my mother and I plunged into this current of
patriotic, reformist protest which was later to be known as
the May Fourth Movement. This experience was a revela¬
tion to me, shaking me out of the sheltered personal world
in which I had enclosed myself. Previously I had looked on
my studies as a means to earn a livelihood, to achieve per¬
sonal success and to restore my family to its former glories.
Suddenly I discovered new and nobler aims: to take part in
the struggle to lift the people out of their wretched state, to
break the centuries old feudal system and to free China
from its colonial status.
Leaving my provincial school at Changsa, in Hunan, I
went to Shanghai where I enrolled in the first school for girls
established by the Communist Party. There I met several
famous revolutionaries who taught me much and encourag-^
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CHRONICLE OF CHANGE
"///////Mfinn
Landscape Topography Architecture
me in the path I was taking. The Chinese Communist
Party had only recently been founded and was still feeling
its way forward, seeking to elaborate a doctrine in which
would merge the Chinese revolutionary tendency and the
Marxism-Leninism the Party was propagating in China. I
was too inexperienced to play a useful part in the Party's
work and action. With my petty bourgeois illusions I was
eager to soar directly towards the extremes of liberty. But
everywhere I came up against the harsh realities of the day
and I soon sank back into a mood of deep depression.
I felt isolated and demoralized, but I was still young and
vital enough to feel the urge to cry out, to express myself.
The only outlet available to me was to pour out on paper my
feelings of revolt against the society of which I was a
prisoner. It seemed natural, then, for me to follow the ex¬
ample of Lu Xun, Mao Dun and my communist mentor Qu
Qiubai, who was to die later in a Guomindang gaol. Like
them I became a writer, not out of personal vanity or out
of a love of art for art's sake, but to defend my fellow coun¬
trymen and help them to achieve liberty. The same objec¬
tives motivated other writers, both my contemporaries and
those of the following generation, to engage in a literature
of combat, even though there were at the time, as there are
also today in our vast country, authors who were only con¬
cerned with literature as an art form.
After the failure of the 1 927 revolution and the massacre of
militants by the Guomindang, I felt obliged to reflect more
32
deeply on political matters. I had already acquired a certain
reputation in literary circles and could have mixed with the
uppercrust, found a good job and then climbed gradually up
the social ladder. Indeed, this was what some of my friends
chose to do. But this option was not for me. I hated the vanity
of this coterie and its obsession with celebrity and material ad¬
vantage, so I continued along what seemed to me to be the
right path.
During the 1930s, while the Guomindang reactionaries
were stepping up their ' 'white terror' ' , I became a member of
the China League of Left-wing Writers, in Shanghai, which
was headed by Lu Xun and directed by the Communist Party.
Subsequently, I joined the Chinese Communist Party since I
wanted to give myself up totally to the cause of the people, to
share their destiny, their cares and their sufferings, to live and
die with them. During the 1920s my female characters had
been petty bourgeois intellectuals in revolt; from the 1930s
onwards they were based on working women and peasants.
This the Guomindang government could not tolerate and a'
single article of this nature published at that time could lead
to imprisonment.
Then, just half a century ago, five members of the League,
including my husband Hu Yepin, and ten revolutionaries
were assassinated by the Guomindang police in the sinister
Longhua prison in Shanghai. Although the world has
witnessed many other horrors since then, it is hard to imagine
how young writers could have thus been so cruelly gunned
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
A Chinese strip cartoon shows how the ancient village of Banpo became the model brigade of Fenghuo.
v« x
Implements Domestic utensils Energy
down. In fact, mere possession of a book with a red cover was
considered ground for arrest. Many writers were summarily
executed in prison or on pieces of waste ground, with no
pretence at atrial. They are counted among the martyrs of the
revolution.
In 1933, I myself was arrested and imprisoned and only
escaped death thanks to an appeal made by the China League
for the Protection of Civil Rights, founded by Song Qinling,
the widow of Sun Yat-sen, Cai Yuanbei, the former rector of
the University of Beijing, the writer Lu Xun and others, and
the protests of well-known foreign authors such as Henri Bar¬
busse, Romain Rolland, Maksim Gorki and Paul Vaillant-
Couturier. All my books were banned and I became the object
of scurrilous political and personal attacks in the press.
About three years later, with the help of Lu Xun and the Par¬
ty, I was able to flee Nanjing, then the official capital, and set¬
tle in the communist base in northern Shanxi.
During the Sino-Japanese War, I followed the communist
eighth army to the front, working as a propagandist.
Thereafter I continued my literary work in Yenan, the focal
point of the struggle against the occupying forces. After the
war against the Japanese imperialists was won, the struggle
for liberation went on against the Guomindang forces. I also
took part in the agrarian reform which abolished the feudal
land system and redistributed the land. In the new China that
had just been established I was given the task of helping in the
reorganization of literary life. So absorbed was I in this task
that I almost forgot that I too was a writer. It was only when
this practical work was completed that I began once again to
be haunted by the characters buried deep within my soul. I
became eager to reveal their existence by writing them into my
novels, stories and essays.
When I write, I do not allow myself to become entangled
in problems of style or form or to impose on myself the strait-
jacket of any literary school whatever. Nor do I take into ac¬
count what the critics will say. Once my work is published, the
only thing that matters to me is what my readers think. My
pen follows the thread of my imagination and I stick to my
first impulses, not trying to refashion the characters I have
known and loved in my life and who become the heroes and
heroines of my books.
Today I am more than ever convinced that we, the Chinese
people, one thousand million individuals, united in a com¬
mon inspiration and led by the Communist Party, will suc¬
ceed in enriching our lives, liberating our thinking, living
democratically and working and learning together. In this
way, and only in this way, will our country be able to
contribute largely to human progress and world peace. In this
way too, Chinese literature, with its own special attributes,
will play its part in enriching the universal artistic heritage of
mankind.
Ding Ling
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The
modernization
of science
and
technology
Old China is credited with the four
great inventions of the compass,
paper-making techniques, print¬
ing, and gunpowder. New China
has embarked on a far-reaching
programme for the modernization
ofscience and technology as a key
to development. Photos on these
pages e voke a very small selection
of scientific and technological ac¬
tivities and achievements in China
today.
A. Chinese archaeologists are
systematically and scientifically ex¬
cavating, restoring and preserving the
tomb of emperor Qin (d. 210 BC),
guarded by the army of life-size clay
soldiers whose discovery was one of
the most exciting events in ar¬
chaeology in recent years.
B. Chief engineer Zhi Bingyi (left) has
invented a new method for adapting
Chinese characters to the computer.
C. Farm kitchen equipped with
methane produced from fermented
organic wastes. This system is widely
used for cooking and lighting in the
countryside.
D. On 20 September 1981, for the
first time, China launched three space
research satellites from a single
rocket. China has launched 1 1
satellites since 1970.
1 . Plants are more sensitive to air
pollution than people. Following ex¬
periments which attracted interna¬
tional interest, Chinese scientists
have identified a number of species
which can be used as pollution-
detectors oras agents for purifying the
atmosphere of toxic gases. Here, staff
of the Botanical Institute of southern
China use smoke to select pollution-
sensitive plants.
2. Normal tissue of the rose-laurel leaf
3. Section of a rose-laurel leaf. Tissue
cells show signs of being affected by
toxic gases.
4. Ficus elástica is one of some 20
trees and bushes whose leaves are
resistant to chlorine and sulphur di¬
oxide and are capable of purifying the
atmosphere.
5. Hibiscus rose-sinensis is a detector
of chlorine.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Immortal clay
From neolithic times to today,
a panorama of Chinese ceramics
by Li Jixian
PERHAPS nowhere in the
world have pottery and por¬
celain assumed so much im¬
portance as in China. The influence of
Chinese ceramics in other world
regions has also been profound for in
the development of pottery glazes
and porcelain as in other fields China
can claim a long priority over the rest
of the world. Below, some of the key
stages and great achievements in the
history of Chinese ceramics, a tradi¬
tion which has surged back to life in
modern China.
Neolithic origins. The Yangshao
culture, so named after a site
discovered in 1 920, developed in the
Yellow River Valley during neolithic
times. Craftsmen of this culture pro¬
duced pottery painted with exquisite
geometric patterns and lively animal
motifs which, together with the black
pottery with etched designs of the
Hemudu culture of Zhejiang Pro¬
vince, reveal the outstanding
creativity of the ancient Chinese.
The earliest earthenware was
somewhat loose-textured and
porous, but. by late neolithic times the
Chinese had learned to use earth con¬
taining kaolin, or China clay, to make
wares which they fired at
temperatures as high as 1,000
degrees centigrade.
Next Chinese potters stumbled
upon the secret of glaze. When firing
pottery they may have noticed that
scattered alkaline ashes left glossy
LIJIXIAN is engaged on research in theArt In¬
stitute of the Academy of Chinese Arts. A
specialist in ancient Chinese ceramics, he has
written o ver a dozen s tudies on such themes as
the earthenware of the gijia culture and
porcelain in the reign of the emperor Kangxi.
36
specks on the wares, for they began
to leave ashes on the surface of semi¬
finished pottery before firing it. Glaze
smoothed the coarse surface of the
pottery, made it easier to wash, and
added greatly to its beauty. Thus
came into being the earliest kaolinic
porcelain, covered with a yellowish
lead glaze produced by high-
temperature firing. (Chemical
analysis has shown that the primitive
celadon wares of the Shang dynasty
of 3,000 years ago are basically iden¬
tical in composition to later
porcelain).
From the Eastern Han dynasty
(25-220 AD) to the Three Kingdoms
and the Southern and Northern
dynasties (221-581 AD). Potters
working during the Eastern Han
dynasty, especially those who pro¬
duced the celadon wares of the
southeast, further improved the firing
process, producing smoother sur¬
faces. Celadon ware is decorated
with glazes ranging from various
shades of green to blue and grey. The
colours are the result of a wash of li¬
quefied clay (slip) containing iron that
was put over the body before glazing.
The iron interacted with the glaze dur¬
ing firing and coloured it. The Three
Kingdoms Period and the Southern
and Northern dynasties witnessed
the rapid development of celadon
wares. Potters began to apply a thick
and even dark green wash to the body
before glazing.
The Tang dynasty (6 1 8-906) was a
great period in the development of
Chinese pottery. The two major pro¬
ducts were the white pottery of
Xingzhou (Hebei Province) and the
celadon wares of Yuezhou in Zhe¬
jiang Province. Famed for its refine-
Red pottery tripod jug dating from the 3rd or
early 2nd millennium BC.
Photo Erich Lessing © Magnum, Paris
Tang potters were unsurpassed at modelling
horses in a variety of spirited poses and pro¬
ducing highly expressive glazed or unglazed
figurines. Works shown here were unearthed
at Xi'an (Chang-an) China's ancient capital and
the starting point of the Silk Road.
Photos '5l China. Beijing
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
ment and whiteness, Xingzhou pot¬
tery was described by a contem¬
porary scholar, Lu Chu, as being "as
white as snow" or "as white as
silver". The transparent glaze of
Yuezhou ware won the admiration of
many poets, who praised its glossy
smoothness as "the emerald green of
a thousand peaks" and described its
transparency as "autumn water".
Finé clay and refined firing tech¬
niques gave the wares a mellifluous
sound when tapped, and ceramics
were in fact used as musical in¬
struments in ancient China, especial¬
ly during the Tang dynasty. The ex¬
cellent musician Guo Daoyuan pro¬
duced sweet sounds by tapping with
chopsticks on twelve teacups (six
from Xingzhou, six from Yuezhou)
filled with different volumes of water;
the sound was more pleasant than
that of musical instruments made of
bronze.
It was also during the Tang dynasty
that potters developed the world-
famous "three-colour" glazed pot¬
tery figurines. They created forms
and motifs that vividly illustrate the
life and culture of feudal society in
China.
The Song dynasty (960-1279)
marks a high point in the history of
Chinese pottery. Each of the five
famous wares for which this period is
This vase with two tubular handles is an
example of the exquisite guang ware
produced during the Song dynasty (height
10 cm).
Photo © Musée Cernuschi, Pans. Private collection, Paris
celebratedDing, Ru, Guang, Jun
and Ge was noted for its own
unique style. The exquisitely
beautiful Ding ware was noted for its
smooth, cream-coloured glaze, with
underglaze decorative designs made
by transfer printing, painting or
engraving in the paste. Ru ware was
covered with a thick glaze mixed with
powdered agate to produce a dark
green colour. The sturdy crystal
green Guang porcelain gave the im¬
pression of great age. The Jun pot¬
ters mixed a small quantity of copper
oxide into their glazes which after fir¬
ing became red or purple.
The origin of the unique crackled
surface of Ge ware is recorded in a
Chinese folk-tale which tells how
once upon a time two brothers of
Longquan county in Zhejiang pro¬
vince each opened a pottery
workshop. The goods produced by
the elder brother sold far and wide, to
the dismay of the younger brother
who could not sell his own wares.
One day when the elder brother was
about to open the door of his kiln, the
younger brother, spurred by envy and
hatred, splashed cold water on the
wares inside. The surface of the pot¬
tery cracked at once, and to his great
surprise the younger brother had
created a successful new product for
his elder whose kiln was from then on
known as the Ge (elder brother) kiln.
The Ming dynasty (1368-1644)
and the Qing dynasty (1644-1911)
were the golden age of painted white
pottery. Jingdezhen, perhaps the
Ming three-colour vase dating from the late
1 6th-century.
Photo Erich Lessing © Magnum, Paris
best-known factory in the history of
Chinese ceramics, became the
leading centre. Its basic product was
underglaze blue and white porcelain,
the emergence of which, together
with that of red porcelain, marked the
beginning of the painted pottery
period. Production of blue-and-white
underglaze porcelain became the
mainstay of the Chinese porcelain in¬
dustry and was exported all over the
world.
The development of famille rose
porcelain also opened up new
avenues of creativity. Famille rose is
the name given in nineteenth-century
France to enamelled porcelain in
which rose pink, made from gold
chloride, predominates. These pro¬
ducts brought great prosperity to
Jingdezhen.
Modern China. During the past thir¬
ty years several of the ancient kilns
have been restored and many new
porcelain factories established.
Jingdezhen now produces imita¬
tions of traditional colour-glazed
porcelain, among which jihong (crim¬
son) pottery is one of the most
precious. New glazes have also been
developed on the basis of traditional
wares. Kilns with a long tradition
such as the Longquan kiln of Zhe¬
jiang, the Cizhou kiln and Ding kilns of
Hebei, the Jun and Ru kilns of Henan
and the Jianyang kiln of Fujian have
succeeded in producing replicas of
the old wares which match the best
ancient porcelain.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The sport
of sages
by Yan Naihua
ON a vast green carpet, eighty-three-year-old Fu
Maokun is demonstrating how to wield a long
sword. A veteran practitioner of the Chinese
martial arts (wushu) who won fame in his youth when he
killed a buffalo with a blow from the side of his hand, he
twirls the weapon, over a metre long, with great force.
Fu Maokun's performance is followed attentively by a
young boy, Huang Mingjian, who in his turn manipulates
a three-metre-long rod, making it whizz noisily as it hurtles,
through the air.
Their brilliant display, loudly applauded by 5,000 spec¬
tators, was part of a national demonstration of wushu
recently held in the ancient city of Xian. No less than 232
adepts took part, showing their skill with sword, spear
and rod, as well as the various forms of Chinese boxing.
In addition to these exhibitions of the traditional martial
arts, some of the participants also displayed such rarely
seen exercises as the "devil's foot" and the "Buddhist
sword".
Wushu (often called gongfu outside China) is one of the
country's most popular sports. A unique phenomenon, it
has a long history for Chinese workers have always con¬
sidered wushu to be an excellent physical and moral exer¬
cise as well as a form of self-defence. There are four
categories of wushu: boxing with bare fists, contests in¬
volving the use of weapons, and contests between either
two or several adversaries.
There are several forms of wushu boxing, each adapted
to different conditions. Changquan boxing, which
demands astonishing rapidity and great suppleness, is
practised above all by children and adolescents. Taiji box¬
ing, with its gentle, relaxed movements, is particularly
suitable for elderly persons, the sick and those with a
weak constitution. Xingyi boxing calls for energy and
great self-control, and is practised both by young people
and adults. Nanquan (southern boxing) which is popular in
some of China's southern provinces, consists largely of
arm movements, precise leg movements, and shouts
through which the fighters express their force. Shaolin
boxing is very popular in northern China. Its neat figures
and brisk movements are extremely impressive. There are
also the "imitative" forms of boxing, so-called because
they imitate the movements of, for example, the praying
mantis or the drunkard, and are based on meticulous
observation of living creatures and human nature.
YAN NAIHUA is a journalist working with the Beijing sports magazine
Tiyu Bao.
38
Such ancient weapons as long spears, sticks and
longswords are used or so-called "short" weapons such
as swords and hooks, as well as flexible weapons such as
nine-knot whips, articulated sticks and chain hammers
known as "shooting stars".
Combat may take place between two or several per¬
sons who, according to the appropriate figures, with or
without weapons, execute the precise movements which
are required. Wushu consists of rhythmical sets of evolu¬
tions composed of basic movements such as dodging,
turning, leaping, sudden changes of position, and high
and long jumping. Execution of these movements calls for
harmony between manual gestures and movements of
the eyes and legs; the action should take place at
headlong speed, the fighter should be steadfast as a rock,
the movements as fluent as running water and as swift as
an attacking snake. When watching a contest it is always
astonishing to see the rapidity with which blow follows
blow.
Wushu is a sport which is suitable for young and old
alike. It can be practised at any time of the year, and no
complicated equipment is required. In China it has been
popular for centuries. Morning and evening wushu adepts
of all ages can be seen in the streets enjoying their
favourite sport. In the big cities such as Beijing and
Shanghai there are over 100,000 amateurs of wushu.
Some towns have created martial arts schools and clubs
for teenagers, as well as organizing training courses in
taiji.
Wushu is a deeply rooted tradition ¡n rural China. In cer¬
tain parts of Hebei, for example, the sport has long been
popular. The city of Cangzhou (population 200,000) has
a hundred-odd training establishments where over a hun¬
dred experienced boxers teach their art to more than
40,000 youngsters and teenagers. Of the 500 villages in
Yongfeng district, over 300 have a wushu organization. In
the village of Diquan in Boye district, two-thirds of the
families practise the sport, part of a tradition which goes
back hundreds of years. They apply themselves to wushu
before and after work and even during moments of relaxa¬
tion in the fields, where it is often possible to see two
young people taking part in an impromptu contest to
universal delight.
The massive popularity of wushu has led to the
emergence of many gifted young practitioners, and the
great enthusiasm for the sport has encouraged constant
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
refinements in movements and style.
From the time of the Western Zhou dynasty (11th
century-722 BC) wushu was considered, like shooting
and riding, as a military sport. The existence of xiangpu,
a kind of wrestling which is popular in modern Japan, is
already mentioned during the Han dynasty
(202 BC-220 AD). Towards the end of the Ming dynasty
(1368-1644) a boxer of the monastery of Shaolin named
Chen Yuanfu popularized his art in Japan.
Combined with Japanese jujitsu, it was eventually
transformed into judo, today an Olympic sport. Many
Japanese, Korean, Thai and Philippine schools of boxing
have also been influenced, to a greater or lesser degree,
by Chinese wushu.
In recent years wushu has attracted a wide following
outside China. In Japan, the first country to adopt the
Chinese martial arts, the Union of Shaolin Boxing, found¬
ed by Do Shin So, has 2,600 branches and over a million
members. In Malaysia the Jingwu Club is a national
sporting organization with activities throughout the coun¬
try. In Singapore, wushu comes under the auspices of the
National Federation of Martial Arts; in the Philippines it is
represented by the Guanghan Martial Arts Commission.
National competitions, tournaments and demonstrations
are regularly organized in these countries of southeast
Asia, and five regional competitions have been held since
1969.
Wushu has a growing number of followers in the United
States and Canada. There are some forty wushu clubs in
New York City alone, and other centres where wushu is
popular include San Francisco, Boston and Los Angeles.
Several demonstrations have been organized according to
the Chinese method, i.e. the participants are grouped in
three categories: boxing, weaponry and polyvalent.
A wave of enthusiasm for wushu has also swept
through Europe. In the United Kingdom, 200,000 people
practise the Chinese martial arts, and in France a Chinese
martial arts association groups forty clubs and 4,000
members. In March 1 982, for the first time, the European
gongfu federation meeting in the United Kingdom brought
together representatives from the UK, France, the
Netherlands, the Federal Republic of Germany, Spain and
Switzerland. Since then it appears that other countries
have expressed a wish to join the Federation. It seems
highly probable that wushu will soon be an Olympic sport.
On
Lao She
1899-1966
ONE of the major figures of twentieth-century
Chinese literature, Lao She (his real name
was Shu She-Yu) was born in humble cir¬
cumstances in Beijing in 1899.
When he was only two years old, his father, a soldier
in the Manchu army, was killed during the defence of
Beijing at the time of the Boxer uprising and from then
on his early life was one of great poverty. Despite this
handicap he worked his way up to become a teacher and
at the age of seventeen he was principal of an elemen¬
tary school.
In 1924, Lao She went to England where he earned
a living by teaching Mandarin Chinese and col¬
laborating in the translation of Chinese classics. He is
said to have been inspired to write his first novel by
reading the works of Charles Dickens to improve his
English.
By the time he returned to China, in 1930, his early
novels had established his reputation as a humorous
writer. He portrayed the comic side of the life of the
poor, a life he knew so well from personal experience;
but it was a humour that was always close to tears.
A prolific writer, he produced in rapid succession
three volumes of short stories and two novels: The Life
ofZhang Tian-Zi ( 1 934) and Xian-zi the Camel (1936),
better known under the title of its English translation as
Rickshaw Boy. These highly successful novels marked
a watershed in his writing; leaving his earlier in¬
dividualistic themes, he turned to a preoccupation with
the overall social environment.
During the Japanese war, Lao She turned to the
theatre and, as head of the National Writer's Anti-
Aggression Association, he wrote several patriotic pro¬
paganda plays of somewhat uneven quality. His best
known plays were written after the establishment of the
communist regime, including The Dragon Whisker
Drain (1951), which was about the construction of Bei¬
jing's new sewage system, and The Teahouse (1957)
which has been widely performed in Europe. During
the last twenty-seven years of his life Lao She wrote
some forty plays, operettas and musicals as well as a
number of historical and literary essays.
Lao She's death was as tragic as it was unexpected. In
August 1 966 he became one of the first victims of the long
period of disorders that ravaged China for some ten
years. He will be remembered as a man of the people who
made the people laugh, and through their laughter
understand the deeper meaning of the world around
them.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The changing
Chinese family
by Fei Xiaotong
THE family is the basic unit of
Chinese society. The changes
which are taking place in its
structure are an integral part of the far-
reaching social transformation that China
has experienced in the last thirty years.
When Western sociologists talk about
the family, they are usually referring to
what they call the nuclear family, con¬
sisting of husband, wife and children
the typical profile of the family in Western
societies. In China the notion of the family
is broader; it designates an extended
group which is based on the nuclear fami¬
ly and may include as a basic social unit
three or four generations living together
and even distant relations.
The small nuclear family of husband, wife and children is an increasingly common pattern
in China's cities.
Photo © Marc Riboud, Paris
In the past it was generally thought that
the great majority of Chinese families
were "big families" or "associated
families" grouping several generations.
This impression may have been due to the
influence of novels and plays, such as
Cao Xueqin's Dream of the Red Flag, Ba
Jin's Family and Cao Yu's The Storm,
which are set in this type of family.
It is true that in old China the rules of
"family piety and fraternal duty" acted as
a check on the disintegration of the family
and the independence of its members.
Feudal morality required that sons and
daughters should unconditionally obey
parents and brothers, and a family in
which five generations lived together
constituted a social ideal. But in reality
"big families" were far from being the
majority in China.
In my book Peasant Life in China,
published in 1938, I noted that the
average Chinese family then consisted of
from four to six members. The same fact
emerged from a study of a village near
Lake Tai, carried out at a forty-five-year
interval, in 1 936 and 1 981 . 1 also stress¬
ed in this study that the peasant
economy, then usually practised on a
small scale, was ill-adapted to the struc¬
ture of a big family. Although they were
influenced by traditional morality, the
peasants had to break up the family unit
for economic reasons such as the division
of the land into smallholdings, as well as
for internal family reasons. Thus a father
would often divide the family property
and live with his elder son. When the elder
son married and a new member joined the
family, a clash between mother-in-law
and daughter-in-law would often cause
the family to split up permanently.
Elderly peasants still remember the
times when many families were broken
up by poverty and discord. Before the
Liberation, even in the Suzhou-Hangzhou
region which was considered an "earthly
paradise", peasant families included
many widowers, widows, orphans, and
men and women abandoned by their
wives and sons, who lived in extreme
destitution.
Although the data are incomplete, it
seems clear that the number of
"associated families" was relatively
higher among the richer city-dwellers and
landed proprietors. This was because
financial resources were concentrated in
the hands of the head of the family, accor¬
ding to the customary practice of the
feudal and paternalistic landed proprietor
class. Among the working people of the
towns and cities, as among the peasants,
the proportion of nuclear families was
growing.
From a strictly sociological viewpoint,
four categories of family may be
distinguished:
1) Incomplete nuclear families from
which the husband or wife is absent, for
one reason or another or in which unmar¬
ried orphans live together. This type of
FEI XIAOTONG is president of the Chinese
Sociology Association and director of the In¬
stitute ofSociology of the Chinese A cademy of
Social Sciences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Although its structure is
changing, the family is still
the basic social unit in
modern China. Help from
elderly parents or parents-in-
law enables the couple to
work outside the home.
Right, three generations of
the Tscheng family on a
commune near Shanghai.
Photo René Burri © Magnum, Paris
family is unstable and is considered
abnormal.
2) Nuclear families, or small families,
consisting of husband, wife and their un¬
married children.
3) Extended families consisting of the
nuclear family and its satellites, usually
the widowed father or mother, but
sometimes including distant kinsfolk and
even persons unrelated to the family.
4) "Associated families" or big
families consisting of two orthree nuclear
families. In most cases the associated
family consists of two overlapping
generations, but a variant exists in the
form of nuclear families created by
brothers and sisters living under the same
roof.
On the basis of this kind of classifica¬
tion, the situation of the village we in¬
vestigated in 1936 and 1981 is as
follows:
1936 1981
Incomplete families
Nuclear families
Extended families
Associated families
27.6 % 18.1 %
23.7 % 39 %
38.4% 21.6%
10.3% 21.3%
During these forty-five years, the
village underwent profound changes cor¬
responding to the transformation of a
feudal or semi-feudal society into a
socialist regime. The table above shows
that in 1981 nuclear families
predominated, accounting for nearly 40
per cent of the total, whereas the number
of extended families had dropped to little
more than 20 per cent. The number of in¬
complete families had also dropped while
the number of associated families had
doubled.
Several factors have modified the fami¬
ly structure. In a society in which the
means of production have become the
property of the community, the head of
the family no longer has the power to con
trol the distribution of wealth by virtue of
his exclusive possession of land and other
means of production, as he did under the
old patriarchal system. Work in common
in the production brigades, the balancing
out of incomes, affinities, and the hous¬
ing problem are enough to explain the in¬
crease in the percentage of "associated
families", often to the detriment of the
extended family.
But one of the major reasons for this
change is the big increase in the number
of elderly people. In the village studied,
there were ninety-four persons over the
age of sixty in 1936. In 1981 there were
195. Thus the improvement in health care
and living conditions has produced a
situation in which the elderly are far more
numerous than before .but often just as
dependent on their children, and have
contributed to the enlargement of the
nuclear family, even transforming it into a
big associated family. Today children are
legally obliged to support their parents
who can no longer work.
The standard of living of the village has
risen distinctly since before the war, part¬
ly due to the establishment of factories. It
is thus not surprising that the number of
nuclear families has risen. Nevertheless,
housing problems have not yet been en¬
tirely solved, and they play a major role in
the rise in the percentage of "big
families", even if the latter are not the
same as the patriarchal clans of former
times. Thus, although the percentage of
incomplete families decreased by a third
between 1936 and 1981, 78 out of 950
men in 1981 were single. Young men
looking for a wife, widowers or divorcees,
these single men found it very difficult to
marry, notably because of the housing
shortage. Some of them have joined ex¬
tended families and helped to transform
them into associated families.
In extended families or large associated
families, there are tensions quite different
from those caused by the aggressive
authoritarianism of the head of the clan.
These too are largely due to housing pro¬
blems. Almost half the families in the
village studied have tried to cushion the
impact of these difficulties by the practice
of fen zao, cooking apart: mother-in-law
and daughter-in-law live together but
cook separately.
Other tensions may arise from certain
changes in the status of women. Women
who work in the production brigades or in
the factories which have been set up in
the village are paid their wages directly.
Although they usually hand over their ear¬
nings to the head of the family, these
women now have a certain freedom as to
how they spend their money. Many
young village women deduct the cost of a
permanent wave from their earnings
before handing them over to the head of
the family, even if this practice is frowned
on by their elders. These are the Chinese
peasant woman's first steps towards
economic independence.
When this independence is more
strongly asserted, it may exacerbate con¬
flicts between the generations and pro¬
voke clashes. It sometimes happens, for
example, that the mother-in-law prefers
to live alone, aided by her son who makes
her a monthly allowance.
On the other hand, especially in the
towns, when the two members of the
basic couple work, the presence of the
parents-in-law, or at least that of the
mother-in-law, in the home is often
warmly welcomed for although many
kindergartens and creches have been set
up near the factories, society's needs in
this sphere are still far from being fully
met. By looking after the small children,
the parents-in-law allow the couple to
work outside the home. In this respect the
extended family, far from breaking up,
tightens its links and becomes a solid
nucleus.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Over the centuries, the interplay of cultures between China and the West expressed itself in many, often surprising ways. Above, the
ruins of an extraordinary Sino-Rococo edifice in the Yuanmingyuan, a vast garden in the northwest suburbs of Beijing. It was designed
by the Italian Jesuit Giuseppe Castiglione (1 698-1 768) who was a painter and functionary at the Qing imperial court where he was known
as Lang Shi-ning. The white marble building is carved with European motifs but the tiled roof and other features were typically Chinese.
Chinese civilization
and the West
by Zhang Kai
IN the ancient world economic and
cultural contacts between Europe
and Asia reached their zenith during
the second century AD. At that time the
Silk Road and its western connexions, the
vital trade link between East and West,
stretched some 12,000 kilometres
across the known world from Xian to
Gades (modern Cadiz) on the Atlantic
Ocean. Along it, from East to West,
travelled Chinese silk, Arabian incense,
precious stones, muslin and spices from
India. In the other direction went glass,
copper, tin, lead, red coral, textiles, pot¬
tery and currency.
Caravans had been making the long
journey regularly from about 106 BC
following the epic explorations of Zhang
Qian, who had been sent by the Emperor
ZHANG KM is an assistant research fellow in
the Office of Relations between China and
Other Countries in the History Institute of the
Chinese Academy ofSocial Sciences. Heis the
author of a number of studies, notably on
themes connected with relations between
China and Latin America. He has translated
works of Latin American history into Chinese,
and is currently writing a history of Chinese
emigrants in America.
42
Wudi as ambassador to the ancient
Yuezhi people in Bactria. It was from
about this time that regular supplies of
silk began to flow to the West, and China
became known to Europeans as "Sérica"
(the land of silk). Virgil, the great Roman
epic poet, who was born in 70 BC, wrote
a poem in praise of silk which he imagined
as being combed from the leaves of trees.
While the camels were plodding heavy
laden along the Silk Road, a new marine
route was being developed. In about
100 BC a Greek ship's captain named
Hippalos discovered that use could be
made of the monsoon winds to make
rapid direct sea voyages from the Red Sea
to the Indian ports of Barbaricum,
Barygaza and Muziris, where Chinese
goods could be obtained from Indian
merchants.
The sea route was safer and more
economical and sea-borne trade between
East and West grew rapidly reaching un¬
precedented heights during the Tang
(61 8-906 AD), the Song (960-1 279 AD)
and the Yuan (1260-1368 AD)
dynasties. The seven missions to the
"Western Oceans" undertaken by the
famous admiral Zheng He, between
1405 and 1433 AD undoubtedly gave a
further fillip to Chinese sea-borne trade.
The period of the Tang dynasty also
saw the spectacular rise of Islam, the
great new power that was to affect
EastWest relations so profoundly. The
first Arab embassy to China took place in
651 BC and the conquest of Persia in
652 BC brought Arab domination to the
frontiers of Chinese influence. Arabs
began to play an extremely important role
as a medium of cultural and commercial
exchange between East and West. It was
through the Arabs that ancient Chinese
inventions such as the compass, paper-
making, printing and gunpowder were in¬
troduced to Europe.
Chinese porcelain predominated in
trade by the "Marine Silk Road." From
the Song dynasty onwards Chinese
porcelain was introduced throughout
south-east Asia, the Indian sub¬
continent, Arabia and the eastern coastal
regions of Africa, and from the sixteenth
century onwards it reached Europe and
even America.
Also during the sixteenth century
Chinese lacquerware began to reach
Europe in considerable quantity, its vivid
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
patterns and exquisite colourings arous¬
ing astonishment and admiration. By the
end of the seventeenth century French
craftsmen at the Gobelins factory in Paris
were producing imitations which were
known as ouvrage à la Chine which re¬
tained the characteristic elements of the
Chinese style.
Chinese painting, handicraft, sculpture
and architecture may all be said to have
made a decisive contribution to the
development of the eighteenth century
European style which came to be known
as rococo. The influence of Chinese ar¬
chitectural styles can be seen in a number
of imperial palaces and the
traditional Chinese arch-shaped roofs and
upturned eaves were often successfully
transferred.
Chinese-style garden layouts were also
highly popular in the West. With their ap¬
parently random arrangements of lakes,
mounds, artificial rocks, pavilions,
towers, winding paths, pagodas, they
broke away from the symmetrical,
stereotyped gardens of Europe. The
Chinese influence is still strongly evident
at Kew Gardens, near London, one of the
most famous gardens in England.
Another Chinese export which was to
have a profound influence on European,
especially English, social life was tea.
Originating in the China of antiquity, tea
cultivation and the tea-drinking habit
spread first to Japan and Korea and then
throughout Asia. By the seventeenth cen¬
tury tea, then considered a great luxury,
was being drunk in England and America.
Today in England tea is an indispensable
adjunct of daily life in all social classes and
the English now consume about a fifth of
the world's total tea production.
Material goods were not, however, the
only Chinese exports to travel the trade
routes. Unseen among the bales of silk,
crates of tea and porcelain came a wealth
of spiritual, philosophical, economic and
educational ideas whose impact on the
West was to be profound.
In the first half of the fourteenth cen¬
tury descriptions of their travels to China
by the merchant adventurer Marco Polo
(1254-1324) and the franciscan friar
Odoric of Pordenone (1 286-1 33 1 ) arous¬
ed European curiosity about the myste¬
rious "gigantic dragon of the East" of
which they spoke. But it was not until the
turn of the sixteenth century that a clear
picture of Chinese thought began to
emerge.
From the middle of the sixteenth cen¬
tury, missionaries were sent in suc¬
cessive groups to China from the Western
world. Some, like the Jesuit missionary
Matteo Ricci (1552-1610) adopted
Confucian-style clothes, learned the
Chinese language, studied the Chinese
classics and established close contact
with senior officials and the élite of socie-
ty, even gaining admittance to the im¬
perial court. Their deepening understan¬
ding of China and their admiration for its
highly developed civilization are reflected
in the reports they sent back to the
Vatican on politics, economy, culture and
art and daily life and customs in China.
In 1 585 the Historia de las Cosas más
Notables, Usos y Costumbres del gran
Reyno de la China (History of the Great
Empire of China), compiled by the
Spanish missionary Juan Gonzalez de
Mendoza (1540-1617), was published in
Rome. It was immediately translated in
several European languages and widely
circulated, arousing enormous interest in
things Chinese. During the eighteenth
century works concerning China pro¬
liferated. They included Edifying and
Curious Letters, published in thirty-four
volumes, a General History of China, in
thirteen volumes, and Memoirs on the
History, Sciences, Arts, etc. of the
Chinese, in sixteen volumes.
These publications raised European in¬
terest in China to fever pitch. Scholars im-
i0yr.«ir ksji
Completed in 1298, the
reminiscences of the great
Italian trader and traveler
Marco Polo brought to the
Western world unprece-
dentedly vivid and ac¬
curate first-hand descrip¬
tions of life in China. Marco
Polo's exciting travels are
the subject of a major new
TV film directed by
Giuliano Montaldo, of Ita¬
ly, with an international
team. In addition to many
Chinese actors, the star-
studded cast also includes
John Gielgud and Burt Lan¬
caster. Left Kublai Khan
leads the expeditionary
army in putting down
Nayan's armed rebellion.
Photo © China, Beijing
Uj j;
E ï
These ideograms (above, dong or east; below,
mlan or face) were inscribed on a Chinese stela
(a slab or pillar of stone used for com¬
memorative purposes) to indicate the direction
in which the monument faced. While travelling
in China on an archaeological mission, the
French poet and physician Victor Segalen
(1878-1919) was struck by these "monu¬
ments reduced to the form of a tall stone table
bearing an inscription". In his book Stèles
(1912), Segalen wrote: "This space riven by
points, penetrated by the nine firmaments,
who surrounds and contains it? Beyond the
confines is the Extreme, and then the Great
Void, and then what lies beyond?"
mersed themselves in the study of
Chinese philosophy, politics, economics,
pedagogics, state systems, military
ideology and strategy, literature, art,
garden landscaping and social customs.
In the field of philosophy, Confucianism
in particular captured the attention of Euro¬
pean philosophers. Confucius' teachings,
as contained in the Sishu (Four Books) and
the Wujing (Five Classics), had been
translated into Latin by Matteo Ricci and
the Jesuit missionary Niklaas Trigault.
Later, other works on Confucianism and
the Confucian school of idealist philosophy
of the Song dynasty were introduced to
Europe and Confucius came to be revered
as a learned prophet and a master of ethics
and political philosophy.
The principle of Li (propriety), con¬
sidered by the Confucian school of
idealist philosophy of the Song dynasty
as the supreme law, appealed greatly to
many European philosophers, especially
those with anti-religious tendencies.
Gottfried Leibniz, the eminent German
philosopher, was one of the first in Europe
to recognize the significance of Chinese
thought for Western culture. For some
time he devoted himself to the study of
Chinese philosophical ideology and he
had a wide interest in all things Chinese.
He maintained that if China could send
people to Europe to give guidance in "the p.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
aims and practice of natural theology", it
would revitalize the decadent and corrupt
ethics of Europe. He also gave much time
to the establishment of a scientific socie¬
ty in Berlin to promote cultural exchanges
between Europe and China.
The French writer Voltaire, a leading
figure of the Age of Enlightenment, also
had a high respect for Chinese
philosophy. He maintained that the
Chinese people had all the virtues and
were in advance in many branches of
learning.
The great Russian writer and thinker
Leo Tolstoy found that he had many ideas
in common with the philosophy of Laozi
and at one time he even planned to
translate the Daode jing (The Supreme
Way of Life) into Russian.
During the eighteenth century, Chinese
influence was also felt in the field of
economics. François Quesnay, the
French economist who founded the
physiocratic school of economic thought
and who proclaimed that laissez-faire in
economics followed natural law and ad¬
vocated an economy based on
agriculture, drew heavily on Chinese ex¬
perience. In his book On China's
Autocracy, he wrote that the "natural
law" was the "legislative foundation of
mankind" and the "supreme norm of
human behaviour." He pointed out sor¬
rowfully that this law was neglected
everywhere except in China and declared
that the Chinese system of government
should become an example to be
emulated by all European countries. His
advocacy of Confucianism and Chinese
thought earned for him the sobriquet of
"the Confucius of Europe."
A number of European scholars of the
Age of Enlightenment considered the
educational system of feudal China to be
a model to be followed. The eighteenth
century German professor of theology
Christian Wolff greatly admired the grad¬
ed educational system in China in which
there were separate schools for children
and adults. He maintained that this
system coincided with the natural law of
the human spirit.
Schools in China not only taught their
students reading and writing skills, they
also gave them lessons in ethics and in¬
structed them in methods of acquiring
knowledge.
In military affairs the Chinese classic
Bing-fa (The Art of War), written by Sunzi
in the fourth century BC and a book with
which Napoleon Bonaparte was familiar,
had a considerable effect on the forma
tion of military ideology in Europe and on
the application of military strategy and
tactics in war.
In the literature and art of the West the
influence of Chinese civilization can
similarly be seen. Some experts maintain
that the well-known Western fairy tale
Cinderella is a variation of a legendary
story in You Yang Za Zu, written by Duan
Chengshi in the time of the Tang dynasty.
A Chinese classic play An Orphan of
Zhaos, was translated into English, Italian
and French. It was re-written by Voltaire
as a five-act play called The Chinese Or¬
phan, in which Confucian ethics were
described. Some scholars maintain that
the great Goethe's unfinished play
Elpenor was inspired by An Orphan of
Zhaos.
It should not, however, be forgotten
that the interplay between China and the
West was a two-way affair. While the in¬
fluence of the rich heritage of ancient
China was pervading the West, the ad¬
vanced science and technology of the
West and its philosophical and artistic
ideas were in turn being absorbed in
China, thus cementing the bonds of
friendship and understanding between
two of the great civilizations of the world.
Zhang Kai
Venice
The
Silk Road
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The African encounter
CHINESE contact with Africa dates back to ancient times.
On his return to Chang-an, the capital of China under the
Han dynasty, after a mission to the "Western Regions"
(a term which designated the area west of Yumenguan, including
what us now Xinjiang and parts of central Asia) Zhang Qian men¬
tioned in his report to Emperor Wudi that he had heard of a place
in the West called Liqian. Contemporary scholars have confirmed
that Liqian was none other than Alexandria, in Egypt.
At that time Egypt was under the rule of the Roman Empire and
Alexandria was the communications centre for Asia, Africa and
Europe. The largest metropolis in the Western world, it enjoyed
great commercial prosperity. Legend has it that Cleopatra, Queen
of Egypt, wore robes made of Chinese silk brought to Egypt along
the Silk Road.
The reign of Emperor Wudi also saw the establishment of a
flourishing sea-borne trade between China and India and a sea
route was opened up between India and the Roman Empire. Ac¬
cording to Edward Gibbon's Decline and Fall of the Roman Em¬
pire about 120 trading ships left Egypt every year bound for India
and Sri Lanka. Chinese silk and other commodities were carried
via India to Alexandria and thence across the Mediterranean to
Rome.
The Tang, Song and Yuan dynasties saw an uprecedented
development of sea-borne trade between East and West. Under the
Tang dynasty, China's merchant ships, some reputed to have five-
storey forecastles, sailed as far as the Gulf. Under the Song dynas¬
ty, Chinese shipbuilding techniques further improved. Zhou
Qufei, a twelfth-century Chinese scholar, described the Chinese
ocean-going merchant ships of his day as "capable of carrying
several hundred people, with food supplies that could last a year
and even with pigs kept and wine made on board".
Exceptionally well rigged and navigated by compass, these ships
were particularly suitable for long, ocean-going voyages. In 1433,
on the last of his seven famous missions to the West during the
Ming dynasty, Admiral Zheng He led a huge fleet with as many as
27,000 men aboard, reaching as far as the mouth of the Red Sea
and the coast of East Africa.
The Admiral's voyages raised China's overseas trade to a new
high. Chinese porcelain became popular in East Africa. In his
book The Rediscovery ofAncient Africa Basil Davidson notes that
some princes and merchants in East Africa had Chinese porcelain
ornaments in their homes and drank tea from porcelain cups.
.Chinese porcelain fragments have been found in Tanzania and an¬
cient Chinese coins have been unearthed in Mogadishu, Brava,
Mafia Island and Kilwa Island.
In North Africa, Chinese cargoes were shipped to Egypt through
the Red Sea and then transported to Morocco for sale. Chinese
paper-making techniques were introduced to Egypt in 900 and to
Morocco in 1100. In the tenth century Chinese printing techniques
became known in Egypt and were used in printing the Qur'an.
Since Chinese gunpowder was introduced to Egypt in the latter
half of the thirteenth century nitre has been known to the Egyp¬
tians as "Chinese snow."
Thus Chinese products were introduced to Africa at about the
same time as they reached Europe and the contacts between China
and Africa were perhaps closer and more direct.
The great ancient trade
route linking China and the
West was a highway for
ideas and cultural contacts
as well as material goods.
Left, scene from 77»e Legend
of the Silk Road, a ballet in
six acts.
Map © China, Beijing
Photos © China, Beijing
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
The why of the needle
The story of acupuncture and moxa
Text © Copyright. Reproduction prohibited
by Joseph Needham
JOSEPH NEEDHAM, world-famous British
historian of Chinese science, is director of the
East Asian History of Science Library at Cam¬
bridge. For more than forty years he has been
engaged on a monumental, multi-volume
history of Science and Civilization in China of
which he is the director and principal con¬
tributor. The present article has been taken
from his latest work Science in Traditional
China, published by the Chinese University
Press, Hong Kong, in 1981.
ACUPUNCTURE and moxa, as
everybody knows, are two
of the most ancient and
characteristic therapeutic tech¬
niques of Chinese medicine.
Acupuncture can be defined broadly
as the implantation of thin needles to
different depths at a great variety of
points on the surface of the human
body points gathered in connected
arrays according to a highly
systematized pattern with a com¬
plex and sophisticated, if still essen¬
tially medieval, physiological theory
behind it. The classical theory was
based on conceptions, still of great
interest today, of a continuous cir¬
culation of qi (the "primordial
breath") and Xue (blood) around the
body.
Moxa consists of the burning of
Artemisia tinder, ai, either in the
form of incense-like cones, whether
or not laid directly on the skin, or a
cigar-shaped stick held just above it.
The points chosen for application are
in general identical with those of the
acupuncture system. Depending
upon the degree of heat there can be
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
either a mild thermal stimulus, like a
fomentation, or alternatively a
powerful counter-irritant cautery.
Very broadly speaking, the acupunc¬
ture technique was from ancient
times onward thought most valuable
in acute diseases, while the moxa
was considered more appropriate in
chronic ones, and even for pro¬
phylactic purposes too.
Now, acupuncture as a method of
therapy, including sedation and
analgesia, involving the implantation
of needles, first developed during
the Zhou period, in the 1st millen¬
nium. Today the needles are very
thin, much thinner than the familiar
hypodermic needles. Implantation
into the body was made at different
places at precisely specified points
according to a charted scheme,
based on ancient physiological
ideas. The theory and the practice
were, one finds, well established
already, well systematized, in fact,
in the 2nd century BC, though much
development followed. The tech
nique remains in universal use in
China and in all Chinese communities
at the present day.
The classical view of the circula¬
tion of the qi was that it passed
through a network of channels round
and round the body. This was the
jingluo system, an arrangement of
what we call acu-tracts and acujunc-
tions, twelve main tracts, and eight
auxiliary tracts, the famous qijing ba
mo. Each of these tracts contains
anything from ten to fifty acu-points
(as we call them), the shu xue, at
which the needles are implanted or
over which the moxa is burnt. But
besides the jingluo system of acu-
tracts there is also the jing mo
system, which we translate as the
"tract-and-channel network sys¬
tem," involving not only the circula¬
tion of qi in the tracts but also the
circulation of blood in the blood
vessels. It is extremely interesting to
know that the idea of circulation ex¬
isted so clearly and so long before
the demonstration of the blood cir¬
culation by Sir William Harvey in his
De Motu Cordis et Sanguinis in
Animalibus of 1628.
The cardinal importance of the
system of acupuncture in the history
of Chinese medicine is not denied by
anyone, but its actual value in objec¬
tive terms remained until recently,
and to some extent still does remain,
the subject of great differences of
opinion. For example, you can find in
various countries in East Asia
modern-trained physicians, both
Chinese and Occidental, who are
sceptical about its value, but on the
whole in China they are rather few,
and the vast majority of medical men
there, according to our experience,
both modern-trained and traditional,
do believe in its capacity to cure, or
at least to alleviate, many
pathological conditions.
The whole subject took a rather
dramatic turn during the past fifteen
years on account of the successes
achieved in China in the application of
acupuncture for analgesia in major
surgery. Here there is no long and tor¬
tuous medical history to be followed
up, no periods of remission or acute
relapse, no chronic conditions with
uncertain responses, no psycho
somatic guesswork. Either the pa¬
tient feels intolerable pain from the
surgical intervention, or he does not,
and the effectiveness can be known
within the hour, or even sooner. More
than any other development, this
acupuncture analgesia (or anaes¬
thesia, as it has often been called
with undeniable but infelicitous logic)
has had the effect of obliging physi¬
cians and neurophysiologists in other
parts of the world to take Chinese
medicine seriously.
One view commonly expressed
(mainly by Westerners) is that
acupuncture has acted primarily by
suggestion, like many other things in
what they often call "fringe
medicine," and some do not hesitate
to equate surgical acupuncture
analgesia with hypno-anaesthesia.
It is quite clear that in terms of
neurophysiology the acupuncture
needles stimulate various receptors
at different depths, which send their
afferent impulses up the spinal cord
and into the brain. Perhaps they trig¬
ger events in the hypothalamus
which activate the pituitary gland and
lead to an increase of cortisone pro¬
duction by the suprarenal cortex, or
perhaps they stimulate the automatic
nervous system in such a way as to
lead to an increased output of anti¬
bodies from the reticuloendothelial
system. Both these effects would be
of great importance from the
therapeutic point of view, and in fact
they are among the leading theories
used at the present day to explain the
therapeutic effects of acupuncture.
In a way, it is easier to explain the
analgesic effect than the therapeutic
effect, but of course if cortisone pro¬
duction and the things allied with it
are really stirred up by acupuncture or
if antibody output is increased by it, it
would be easy to see that acupunc¬
ture therapy cou|d have been of enor¬
mous value, even in diseases such as
typhoid and cholera where we know
perfectly well the causative invading
organism. On the other hand, in
another situation, the needles may
monopolize afferent input junctions
in the thalamus, medulla, or spinal
cord, in such a way as to prevent all
pain impulses getting through to the
cortex regions of the brain, thereby
successfully inducing analgesia. iv
Implanting thin needles in the body at points indicated on ancient charts,
modern Chinese surgeons use acupuncture, China's time-honoured
technique for relieving pain, as a form of anaesthesia. Left, anaesthesia
being carried out by acupuncture at a Nanjing hospital.
Photo © Marc Riboud, Pans
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
k Furthermore, there is no question
that acupuncture analgesia is con¬
nected in some way, we do not yet
know exactly how, with the opioid
peptides of the brain. It was one of
the most exciting and fascinating
discoveries of the last five years, that
our own brains manufacture
substances known as enkephalins
and endorphins. Enkephalins and en¬
dorphins are very powerful
analgesics, and they are made in our
own brains, so here is another way in
which you can see how the acupunc¬
ture needles at the periphery could
stimulate neurons to fire off and
release these highly powerful
enkephalins or endorphins.
Something remains to be said
about the theoretical setting of
acupuncture and other Chinese tradi¬
tional methods, such as the medical
gymnastics which are so important in
China. Here I am talking about the
relative value placed in Chinese and
Western medicine respectively on aid
to the healing and protective power
of the body, on the one hand, as
against direct attacks on invading in¬
fluences, on the other. In both
Western medicine and Chinese
medicine these two concepts are to
be found. In the West, besides the
seemingly dominant idea of direct at¬
tack on the pathogen, we also have
the idea of the vis medicatrix naturae,
the natural healing power of the body
and the strengthening of resistance
to disease which comes right down
from the time of Hippocrates and
Galen.
In China, where the holistic ap¬
proach might have been thought to
dominate, there was also the idea of
combating external disease agents,
whether these were malign or sinister
pneumata, thex/'e qi, from outside, of
unknown nature, or distinct venoms
ortoxins left behind when insects had
been crawling over food. That was a
very old conception in China. So the
attack on external agents was cer¬
tainly present in Chinese medical
thought too. The other one, the vis
medicatrix naturae was surely largely
what the Taoists meant in China by
yang sheng, the nourishment of life
and the strengthening of it against
disease.
It is fairly clear that whatever the
acupuncture procedure does, it must
be along the lines of strengthening
the patient's resistance and not
directly fighting invading organisms
that is, not the characteristic "an¬
tiseptic" technique which has
naturally dominated in the West since
the origin of modern bacteriology. In
this connexion, it is a significant fact
that while Westerners are often
prepared to grant value to acupunc¬
ture in things like sciatica or lumbago,
for which modern Western medicine
can do very little anyway, Chinese
physicians have never been prepared
to limit either acupuncture or moxa to
such conditions; on the contrary they
have recommended it and practised it
in treating many diseases for which
we all now believe we know the
organisms (like typhoid and cholera),
and they have claimed at least remis¬
sions if not radical cures.
In addition, there was a third idea,
which sprang from the idea of
balance or krasis. The idea was as
much Chinese as it was Greek. It
viewed disease as essentially a
malfunction or imbalance, one or the
other component entity in the body
having unnaturally gained the lead
over the others. Since the develop¬
ment of modern endocrinology, this
conception has taken a new lease on
life, but it was present from the begin¬
ning in both civilizations. European
bloodletting and purging was a direct
if crude result of it, because it was
thought that "peccant humours"
had to be got rid of; but in China a
defective balance between Yin and
Yang, or deviant relationships bet¬
ween the Five Elements, were
generally diagnosed and altered in a
more subtle way. Acupuncture was
the first court of appeal here again.
We have little doubt that many in¬
terventions of that kind did return the
living human body with its nerves and
hormones to a more even keel,
though exactly how the medieval
physicians visualized the interplay of
the two great forces always remains
rather difficult for us to understand in
our time.
The universal reproach directed
against therapeutic acupuncture by
modern scientific medicine is the lack
of statistical evidence. The absence
of adequate clinical control ex¬
periments, the existence of the
i"
Moxa, or moxibustion, is another tradi¬
tional Chinese pain-relieving practice
that has since spread to other coun¬
tries. Small cones of dried leaves are
burned on specific points of the body,
as shown in the 18th-century docu¬
ment at right. The term moxa is derived
from the name of the wormwood plant
most frequently used, Artemisia moxa.
Photo © Editions Tchou, Paris
48
llitoruùrrutri leterum-JiitciUiitrv.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
A doctor at Wuxi near
Nanjing applies a moxa
stick to a patient's
skin. Each stick burns
for four or five minutes.
Photo René Burn © Magnum,
Pans
placebo effect, and the relative pauci¬
ty of quantitative remission and
follow-up data in contemporary
China are hindrances, of course, but
let no one say that the Chinese were
unaware of the possibilities of spon¬
taneous recoveries and remissions.
There is a passage in the Zhou Li
which talks about the official physi¬
cians of the imperial government. The
Zhou Li is a treatise written in early
Han times about the kind of govern¬
ment bureaucratic organization
which ought to have existed in the
Zhou period, even if it never did. It
was a kind of system of the ideal
government organization. Speaking
of the YiShi, the chief medical officer
of the imperial government, it said:
"The Yi Shi is in charge of the whole
medical administration of the coun¬
try, and he collects all efficacious
drugs for the purpose of healing
diseases. All those suffering from ex¬
ternal maladies, whether of the head
or body, are treated separately by ap¬
propriate specialists. At the end of
the year he uses the records of each
physician to decide on his rank and
salary. Those who have cured 1 00 %
of their patients are graded in the first
class, those who have had 90 %
recoveries are in the second class,
those who have been 80 % suc¬
cessful are placed third, those who
have cured 70 % are considered
fourth class, and the lowest grade of
all contains those who could not cure
more than 60 %." Then the com¬
mentator in the 2nd century AD,
Zheng Kang-Cheng, has a fascinating
commentary in which he says that
"the reason why those who failed
with four out of ten patients were
placed in the lowest grade was
because half of the cases might well
have recovered anyway, even
without any treatment at all." This
text implies clearly the keeping of
clinical records, and the comment
seems to us an admirable example of
the scepticism and critical mentality
of the scholars of ancient China.
When one looks back, one sees
how great was the medical literature
concerning acupuncture and moxa
which grew up in China through the
centuries. Many matters of absorbing
interest arise as one looks through it.
For example, first of all there was the
deep conviction of Chinese scholars
and physicians about the circulation
of qi and blood in the body, determin¬
ing a rate of flow only sixty times
slower than that which modern
physiologists since Harvey have
recognized, and that with a priority of
about two thousand years. Then
there was the discovery of the
viscero-cutaneous reflexes, the con
nexions of many parts of the body's
surface with events occurring in the
internal organs. Then, too, there was
something I have not spoken of at all,
the appreciation of diurnal or circa-
dian rhythms, and longer biological
rhythms in man, and the develop¬
ment of an abstruse calculus on the
basis of this to determine when
acupuncture and moxa should best
be performed. Finally there was the
development of a very interesting
module system for locating acu¬
points in human bodies of different
sizes and proportions.
There have been a number of
misunderstandings in the West about
acupuncture and moxa. They have
nothing whatsoever to do with para¬
psychology, occult influences, or
psychic powers, and consequently
do not deserve the praises of those
who believe in such things. They do
not depend entirely on suggestion,
nor on hypnotic phenomena at all,
and they are not contradictory of
modern scientific medicine. Conse¬
quently they do not deserve the
odium theologicum of the medical
profession in the West. Acupuncture
with moxa is simply a system of
medical treatment which was already
two thousand years old when modern
science was born, and which has
developed in a civilization quite dif¬
ferent from that of Europe. Today the
explanations of its actions are being
sought in terms of modern physiology
and pathology. Great advances have
been made already in this direction
though the end is not yet in sight. It
looks as if the physiology and
biochemistry of the central and
automic nervous systems will be the
leading elements in our understand¬
ing, but many other systems,
biochemical, neurochemical, en¬
docrinological, and immunological
are sure to be involved.
Another problem of great interest is
the exact nature of the acu-points in
terms of histology and biophysics.
Since modern science did not spon¬
taneously grow up in Chinese culture,
acupuncture and moxa are tradi¬
tio Tally based upon a theoretical
system essentially medieval in
character, though very sophisticated
and subtle, indeed full of valuable in¬
sights and salutary lessons for
modern scientific medicine. Again,
the exact reinterpretation and refor¬
mulation of these theories, if such a
thing is possible, will be a difficult
matter for the future. However, we
think it likely that in the oecumenical
medicine of the coming years there
will be a definite place for acupunc¬
ture both in therapy and in analgesia.
Exactly how far this will be so, it is too
early tO Say. Neodham
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Unesco translations of Chinese literature
Unesco has for many years promoted the
translation and publication of major works of
Chinese literature. Notable titles that have ap¬
peared in English include:
Anthology of Chinese Literature from Early
Times to the Fourteenth Century. Comp, and
ed. by Cyril Birch. Associate editor Donald
Keene. New York, Grove Press, 1965.
XXXIV + 492 pp.; London, Penguin Classics,
1967.
Basic Writings of Mo Tzu, Hsün Tzu and Han
Fei Tzu. Extracts, trans, by Burton Watson.
New York and London, Columbia University
Press, 1 967. 1 40, 1 77, 1 35 pp. (in I volume).
CH'U TZ'U. Ch'u Tz'u: the Song of the South:
an Ancient Chinese Anthology. Trans, by
David Hawkes. Oxford, Clarendon Press,
1959; New York, Oxford University Press,
1962. VII + 229 pp.; Boston, Mass., Beacon
Press, 1962. 229 pp. (Paperback.)
CHUANG TZU. Chuang Tzu. Basic Writings.
Extracts trans, by Burton Watson. New York
and London, Columbia University Press, 1 964;
reprint., 1967. IX+148 pp. (Philosophy.)
The Complete Works of Chuang Tzu. Trans, by
Burton Watson. New York and London, Colum¬
bia University Press, 1968. 397 pp.
(Philosophy.)
Fifty Songs from the Yuan. Poetry of 1 3th Cen¬
tury China. Trans, with Introduction, appen¬
dixes and notes by R.F. Yang and Charles R.
Metzger. London, Allen & Unwin, 1967.
161 pp.; New York, Hillary, 1967. 161 pp.
HAN FEI TZU. The Complete Works of Han Fei
Tzu. Trans, with Introduction, notes and index
by W.K. Liao. London, Arthur Probsthain,
1959. 2 vols. Vol. I, XXXIII + 310 pp.; Vol. II,
338 pp. (A classic of Chinese political
('Legalist') science.)
Basic Writings. Extracts trans, by Burton Wat¬
son. New York and London, Columbia Univer¬
sity Press, 1 964; reprint., 1 967. IX + 1 34 pp.
HAN-SHAN. Cold Mountain: 100 Poems by
the T'ang Poet Han-shan. Trans, with In¬
troduction by . Burton Watson. London,
Jonathan Cape, 1970. 76 pp.; New York,
Columbia University Press, 1970, 76 pp.)
HSUN TZU. Hsün Tzu. Basic Writings. Trans,
by Burton Watson. New York and London,
Columbia University Press, 1963; reprint.,
1967. IX + 177 pp.
KUNG-SUN YANG. The Book of Lord Shang.
Trans, with Introduction and notes by J.J.L.
Duyvendak. London, Probsthain, 1963.
Chicago University Press, 1964.
XIV + 346 pp. (A classic of the Chinese
'Legalist' School of philosophy.)
LAO-TZU. The Way and its Power: a Study of
the Tao Tê Ching and its Place in Chinese
Thought. Trans, by Arthur Waley. New York,
Grove Press, 1958. 282 pp.; London, Allen &
Unwin, 1968. 262 pp.
LIEH-TZU. The Book of Lieh-tzu. Trans, by
A. C. Graham, London, John Murray, 1960.
XI + 183 pp.; New York, Grove Press, 1960.
XI + 183 pp.; New York, Paragon, 1970.
183 pp. (Philosophical parables).
LI JUCHEN. Flowers in the Mirror (Ching Hua
Yuan). Trans, and edited by Lin Tai-yi. London,
Peter Owen, 1965. 310 pp.; Berkeley, Calif.,
University of California Press, 1965.310 pp.;
New York, Anchorbooks, Doubleday, 1971.
MENCIUS. Mencius. A new translation arrang¬
ed and annotated for the general reader by
W.A. C.H. Dobson. London, Oxford University
Press, 1 963. XVIII + 21 5 pp. Toronto, Univer¬
sity of Toronto Press, 1966. (Philosophy).
One Hundred and One Chinese Poems. Trans,
and Preface by Shi Shun Liu. Introduction by
Edmund Blunden. Foreword by John Cairn-
cross with seven additional translations. Hong
Kong University Press, 1967. XXXIV
+ 173 pp.; London, Oxford University Press,
1967.XXXIX+173pp.
One Hundred and Seventy Chinese Poems.
Trans, by Arthur Waley. III. with drawings by
Madeleine Pearson. London, Constable, 1 962.
Poems of Solitude. (Juan Chi, Pao Chao, Wang
Wei, P'ei Ti, Li Ho and Li Yü). Trans, by Jerome
Ch'ên and Michael Bullock. London, New York
and Toronto, Abelard-Schuman, 1960,
1 1 9 pp., ill.; Rutland, Vt and Tokyo, Charles E.
Tuttle, 1 970; London, Lund Humphries, 1 970.
Poems of the Late T'ang. Trans, and Introduc¬
tion by A.C. Graham. Harmondsworth, Middx.
and Baltimore, Md, Penguin Books. 1965.
174 pp.; Tokyo, Charles E. Tuttle.
Reflections on Things at Hand. The Neo-
Confucian Anthology Compiled by Chu Hsi and
Lu Tsu-Ch'ien (Chin-ssu lu). Trans, with notes
by Wing-tsit Chan. New York and London, Col¬
umbia University Press, 1967. XLI + 441 pp.,
ill. tab.
The Romance of the Western Chamber (Hsi-
Hsiang Chi). Trans, by S.I. Hsiung. New York
and London, Columbia University Press, 1 968.
XLIV + 281 pp., ill. (Play.)
Sources of Chinese Tradition. Vol. I, compiled
by T. de Bäry, Wing-tsit Chan and Burton Wat
son. New York and London, Columbia Univer¬
sity Press, 1 966. XXIV + 578 pp. (Anthology).
SSU-MA CH'IEN. Records of the Grand
Historian of China (Shih Chi). Selected and
trans, by Burton Watson. New York and Lon¬
don, Columbia University Press, 1961. 2 vols.
Vol. I, 543 pp.; Vol. II, 563 pp. Reprint.,
1969, 2 vols., maps.
Records of the Historian; Chapters from the
Shih Chi of Ssu-ma Ch'ien. Extracts trans, by
Burton Watson. New York and London, Colum¬
bia University Press, 1969. 356 pp.; London,
Oxford University Press, 1969. 356 pp.
Stories from a Ming Collection (Translations of
Chinese short stories published in the 17th
century) (Ku chin hsiao shuo). Compiled by
Fêng Mêng-lung and trans, by Cyril Birch. Lon¬
don, The Bodley Head, 1958. 205 pp., illus.;
Bloomington, Indiana University Press, 1959;
New York, Grove Press, 1968.
ZUN TZU. The Art of War. Trans, with In¬
troduction by Samuel B. Griffith. Foreword by
B.H. Liddell Hart. London and New York, Ox¬
ford University Press, 963. XVII + 1 97 pp., ill.
(Essay).
SU TUNG-P'O (Su-shih). Selections from a
Sung Dynasty Poet. Trans, with Introduction
by Burton Watson. New York and London, Col¬
umbia University Press, 1965. X+139pp.
facs.
WANG YANG-MING. Instructions for Practical
Living and Other Neo-Confucian Writings.
Trans, with notes by Wing-tsit Chan. London,
Allen & Unwin, 1967. 161 pp. New York,
Hillary, 1967. 161 pp.
Please do not send orders to Unesco. Order
through your usual bookseller.
The General History of Africa
Coming after the History of Mankind: Cultural
and Scientific Development, the General
History of Africa is currently Unesco's most
important publishing project. Almost 240
distinguished writers from many countries are
collaborating in this exceptional work, which is
being produced under the intellectual and
scientific responsibility of a 39-member inter¬
national scientific committee, two-thirds of
whose members are African, and the remain¬
ing third specialists from other world cultural
regions. The work will provide a panoramic ap¬
proach to the African continent. It should make
it possible, through the vision it presents of the
past, to understand Africa as it is today.
The first two volumes are currently available in
English and French, and the first volume has
just been published in Spanish and Por¬
tuguese. Initially Unesco intended that the
eight-volume work should have been publish¬
ed in its entirety before the end of 1983.
However, as preparation of the History has
proceeded it has become apparent that an ex¬
tension is necessary in order to permit the pro¬
duction of a finished work of authoritative
scientific quality which would respond to the
hopes of the international community. Conse¬
quently it has been necessary to modify the
publication timetable of the different volumes
in such a way that the entire work will be
available to the public at the end of 1 985.
Unesco hopes that individuals and institu¬
tions interested in the General History ofAfrica
will understand its position and will excuse this
delay.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11
issues a year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head.
Inc., 111 West 40th Street; New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Lim Moun-Young (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1982
January
THE DRUG DILEMMA. Education and drugs (Unesco survey). New approach to drug
dependence (G. Edwards). Reports from 9 countries. The role of WHO. Lifelines. ABC of
drugs under international control. A pill for every ¡II (R. Cooperstock). No smoking, please
(M. Raw). A problem in constant evolution (G. Edwards and A. Arif) Art treasures: Mayan
mushroom stone (El Salvador).
February
ARE WE GETTING THE SCIENCE WE NEED? (A. Dañan and I. Prigogine). Mother tongue
and the brain (H. Brabyn). The world of Dostoievsky (E.D. Mikhailova). Dostoievsky, 'our
great contemporary' (O. Paz). Knots as numbers (G. Ifrah). An African cosmology (S.S.
Nyang). Art treasures: Mende helmet mask (Sierra Leone).
March
SWORDS INTO PLOWSHARES. 'A world of justice, peace and progress' (A.-M. M'Bow).
Disarmament and development. The sinews of war: 1 ) Manpower; 2) Military industrial pro¬
duction; 3) Raw materials; 4) Land; 5) Research and development; 6) Mirtary expenditures.
Statement of the consequences of the use of nuclear weapons, by an international group
of scientists. Art treasures: The angel of Nagasaki (Japan).
April
KIEV: 1,500 YEARS OF CULTURE (P. Zagrebelnyi). Science city of the Ukraine IB. Paton).
An International metropolis (D. Nalivaiko). Birth of a language (V. Russanovsky). The artistic
inheritance (G. Verves). Mummers and music of Kiev-Rus (S. Vissotsky). France's Ukrai¬
nian queen (S. Vissotsky). Centuries ¡n stone (Y. Asseev). A hundred years of James Joyce
(A. Burgess). Poets of Muslim Spain (E. García Gómez). A time to live...: Bajau bride
(Philippines).
May
DARWIN. The evolution of a genius (M. Pyke). The problem Darwin solved (I. Asimov). The
voyage of the Beagle. The Galapagos Islands: the origin of The Origin U.E. Adoum). Unesco
and the Charles Darwin Foundation. The evolution of evolution (P. Thuilher). Darwin and
racism. Computer confirms Darwin was right (B. Mednlkov). An astronomer reflects: Was
Darwin wrong? (C. Wickramasinghe). A time to live...: The water-bearers (Chad).
June
CHILDREN OF THE IMAGINATION. The landscape of the tale (F. Savater). All about Alice
(A. Burgess). Pinocchio (I. Calvino). Huckleberry Finn (M. Bradbury). The comic strip balloons
around the world (M. Pierre). Latin America: tall stories for small readers (J.E. Adoum). The
child-hero in African folktales |A. Sow Fall). Goha the simple (G. Makhlouf). The monkey
king Sun Wukong (Sun Youjun). Ivanushka, prince of simpletons (V. Berestov). Writing for
children (M. Tournier). A time to live...: The rhythm of the water drum (Niger).
July
PEOPLES AND CULTURES. Culture and development: the human dimension (A.-M. M'Bow).
Cultural pluralism ¡n a changing world (O. Klineberg). Unesco and the idea of cultural policy.
The writer between two worlds (T. Ben Jelloun). National identity and foreign domination
(Ngugi Wa Thiong'o). The machinery of cultural power (A. Roa Bastos). The woman revolu¬
tion (Han Suylnl. In praise of mother tongues (C. Aitmatov). The global village revisited (R.
Neuman). A time to live...: Music for mother earth (Chile).
August-September
QUESTIONS OF OUR TIME. Cultural identity: The building blocks of culture (Cheikh Anta
Diop); The emergent peoples of Latin America (D. Ribeiro). Education: Blackboard bungle?
(A.V. Petrovsky); Prepanng people for change; Hunger, Population, Environment: For an alter¬
native development (A. Agarwal); Environment and the global underclass (E. Eckholm); The
aftermath of the population explosion (R.M. Salas). Disarmament, Development: Develop¬
ment through demilitarization (R. Falk); The consequences of nuclear war. Human Rights:
A Third World view of human rights (R. Coomaraswamy); Human rights are universal (Y.
Sakamoto). Science, Technology, Communication: Barren soil (A. Mazru); Predicting the
unpredictable (CS. Holling); By word of mouth (M.H. Abdulaziz); Communication -facts
and figures. A time to live...: The joy of reading (France).
October
THE FULLNESS OF TIME. The splendid company of older men and women (P. Whitcomb).
The mystery of aging (A. Asian). The fires of winter (V. Kozlov). The eternal return (N. O'Khan
Kabwasa). How China cares for her aging millions (Yi Shui). Centenarians of the high valleys.
The aging world (facts and figures). How the family can help. Through youthful eyes: 1 ) What
young people think about the elderly and aging; 2) Bridging the generation gap. Education
and aging An International plan of action. A time to live...: Voting day (Soc. Rep. of Viet Nam).
November
WAR ON WAR (J.-J. Lebel). Poems (Adonis, Ai Qng, Breytenbach, Cardenal, Cortez, Faye,
Ginsberg, Labou Tan'sl, de Mello, Pritam, Kazuko Shiralshl, Voznesenskl). Poetry before and
after Hiroshima (S. Spender). Kupala and Kolas, poets of liberty (M. Tank). If St. Francis
came to call (C. Bo). Wifredo Lam (F. Fernández-Santos). Szymanowski rediscovered (J.
Waldorff). Bharati, poet and patriot (K. Swamlnathan). Hue, a city ¡n peril. A time to live...:
Woman of Valcamonica (Italy).
December
THE CHANGING FACE OF CHINA. Fifty years of literary life (Bai Jin). Confucius (Pang Pu).
Calligraphy, Poetry and painting (H. Miaozhi). Lu Xun (Li Helm). China through the ages (Colour
pages). A literature of combat (Ding Ling). The modernization of science and technology.
Immortal clay (Li Jixian). Martial arts (Yan Naihua). The Chinese family (Fel Xiaotong). Chinese
civilization and the West (Zhang Kai). Acupuncture and moxa (J. Needham). A time to live... :
Dialogue and debate (Guinea).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Coll-
ingwood Victoria 3066, Publications Educational Supplies
Pty. Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub- agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, P.O. Box 175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000. - AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq
Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen French edition and general Unesco
publications agent Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCP000-0070823-1 3 - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd , 2182 St. Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que H3H 1 M7. - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa
Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam 6,893 31 Bratislava
CSSR. - DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo - ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P 0. Box 2996, Addis Ababa
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10, Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuia 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie
de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, C.C P.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus
Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G D R - FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish
editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3 For other Unesco publica¬
tions: Karger Verlag, Germering/Munchen For scientific maps
only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra, Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra, The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University
8ookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon,
PO. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HKI Ltd., 5A
Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen
Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon Hong Kong
Government Information Services, Publication Centre, Basker-
ville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V, A.K.V. Konyvturosok
Bolt/a, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co , H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038, 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3, 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2, 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh,
Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Banga-
lore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta
70016, Scmdia House, New Delhi, Publication Unit, Ministry
of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr Rajendra
Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001 . - INDONESIA. Bhratara
Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakar¬
ta, Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta, Indira
P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat - IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi
Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran, Ira¬
nian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave IranchahrChomahNo 300,
B P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -
Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Com¬
pany of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin
12. - ISRAEL. ABC. Bookstore Ltd , P 0. Box 1283, 71
Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61 000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd , P 0. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon
3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Mmato-ku, Tokyo 105,
KENYA. East African Publishing House, PO Box 30571,
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P O Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco
Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P 0. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P 0 Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P 0 Box
34-35, Tripoli - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22,
Grande-Rue, Luxembourg MALAYSIA. University of
Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd , 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only: Dek-
ker and Nordemann NV, P O Box 197,1 000 AD Amsterddam;
for publications only: KEESING BOEKEN B V., Postbus 1118,
1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van
Dorp-Eddme N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad. Curaçao. N.A.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Govern¬
ment Bookshops at. Rutland Street, P O. Box 5344, Auckland,
130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch, Alma
Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P 0 Box 1104,
Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA The University Bookshop of Ife, The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O 286, The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana NORWAY. All publications-
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1 , Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3 For Unesco Courier only. A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza
Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O Box No. 729,
Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co , 926 Rizal
Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404 - POLAND Orpan-
Import, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No 7.00-068 WARSAW POR¬
TUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P O Box
48, Mahé, New Service Ltd , Kmgsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New In¬
dustrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop
and General, P 0 Box 951 , Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications- Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd , Libn
Building, Church Street, P.O Box 924, Pretoria. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only Central News agency,
P.O Box 1033, Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P O.B.
244 Colombo 2 - SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 1 2, Box 1 6356,
10327 Stockholm 16 For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-
Forbundet,- Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm
- SWITZERLAND. All publications- Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP 12-236 - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, P.O B 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P 0. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company,
1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E I , and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol, for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd , 122 King's Cross Road
London WC1X9 DS - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park
Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva
Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11,
Belgrade. - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd , 67
Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
The People's Republic of China is a multinational country. Some 94 per cent of the populatio
while the remaining 6 per cent are comprised of 55 national minorities and three ethnic groups. The subjects of
the above portraits belong to sixteen of these groups. From left to right, starting top row: Kucong (ethnic group),
Jingpo, Manchu, Lisu; Drung, Yi, Maonan, Lahu; Bai, Tujia, Mongolian, Jino; Benglong, Oroqen, Va, Uighur.
Photos Mongolian and Uighur women © Claude Sauvageot, Paris; others © China, Beijing.
]]>
</page>
</document>
