<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074765eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
OCTOBER 1980 - 3.50 FRENCH FRANCS
Avicenna
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
USSR
Ceramic art from Samarkand
A woman's features are traced In a few simple lines on this fragment of a glazed
ceramic dish, a product of the culture which flourished In Central Asia under the
Samanid dynasty in the late ninth and tenth centuries. Unearthed at Afrasiyab near
Samarkand, the piece is one of many discovered since the beginning of the century
which reveal the brilliant development of decorated earthenware art in this region
during the age of Avicenna.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
OCTOBER 1980 33rd year
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish . Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille i:> published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 35 French Francs - 2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue). For list of distributors see
inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
LáJ¿S&
TOT/?:
English
French
nish
isian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
*J$
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
.Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 AVICENNA- IBN SINA
A universal genius
by Muhamed S. Asimov
9 MY ODYSSEY
by Avicenna
12 MILESTONES IN A RESTLESS LIFE
13 THE CANON OF MEDICINE
A million-word thesaurus of medical knowledge
by Hakim Mohammed Said
18 NOTES AND NOSTRUMS
FROM DR. AVICENNA'S CASEBOOK
by Ahmed Aroua
20 AL-SHIFA
THE WORLD INA BOOK
by Ibrahim B. Madkur
23 FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
29 A PHILOSOPHER UNDER FIRE
Avicenna's doctrines stirred up controversy
in his own time and later
by Reza Davari
32 HOW IBN SINA BECAME AVICENNA
Transmitted to Europe, his writings
sparked off an intellectual revival
by Salvador Gómez Nogales
41 A FORERUNNER OF MODERN SCIENCE
by Abid S. Sadykov
45 THE SECRET OF THE STARS
by Ahmed Suheil Unver
46 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
USSR: Ceramic art from Samarkand
U>^vn;
"F'U^r.ri'C tt-.^o-tte^
Cover
Illustration from a 17th-century Persian
manuscript shows Avicenna (Ibn Sina) taking a
patient's pulse. The Arabic inscription beneath It
¡s a reproduction of a notation in Avicenna's own
hand on the cover page of an Arabic translation
of "The book of the excellent Galen On Medical
Sects for Students". The notation reads:
"[Came] into the possession of Husayn Ibn Abd-
Allah Ibn Sina the physician in the year 407". The
year 407 of the Hegira is the equivalent of the
year 1016-1017 in the Christian calendar.
Photo by courtesy of the Wellcome Trustees, London
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The year 370 of the Hegira, exactly one thousand years
ago according to the Christian calendar, marks the birth of
Ibn Sina, one of the most famous and most influential of
the philosopher-scientists of Islam.
Ibn Sina, or Avicenna as he is better known in the
Western world, was born near Bukhara, in Central Asia, in
a region which then formed part of the Abbasid caliphate.
But this immense community, stretching from present-day
Afghanistan in the east to southern Spain in the west
under the banner of Islam, was disintegrating politically.
Independent local dynasties were arising which admitted
only nominal allegiance to the Caliph in Baghdad.
Far from heralding a parallel cultural decline, however,
this break up was to usher in a golden age of
Islamic civilization. Each of the emergent new States
made their own scientific and cultural contributions and
their rulers vied with each other to attract to their courts
the greatest minds of the period. Spreading to the West,
the rich outpourings of this resurgence were to act as a
leaven of the later European Renaissance.
Avicenna was a key figure in this cultural ferment.
Permeating the whole of Islam, his influence penetrated
Europe through Muslim Spain where it remained a force
for centuries. Standing at a crossroad of history, where
different civilizations and epochs met, Avicenna was a
figure whose genius is the inheritance of all mankind. This
issue of the Unesco Courier is devoted to an examination
of the many facets of this remarkable man.
MM ttJE^NäS :>
y O
M. o
¡S
c
1 D
o
^^^^^^^
Avicenna - Ibn Sina
A universal genius
A
MM Mk L-SHAYK al-Ra'is" (prince
among scholars) was
the title bestowed in the
Orient on Abu Ali al-Husayn Ibn Abd-Allah
Ibn Hassan Ibn AN Ibn Sina, traditionally
known in the West as Avicenna.
He is one of the most extraordinary
figures in world history. A philosopher of en¬
cyclopaedic knowledge, scientist and ex¬
perimenter, eminent theorist of medicine as
well as clinician and healer, poet and musi¬
cian, he was also a Grand Vizier (prime
minister), then a chain-fettered prisoner, an
indefatigable traveller who visited many
regions of central Asia and Persia, and the
author of a vast corpus of writings covering
almost every branch of contemporary
knowledge.
This great thinker was also a man whose
human qualities of integrity and nobility of
character gave rise to a host of legends
some of which are still told today. Accor¬
ding to one of these stories, little Husayn's
mother was bathing him in a bowl when she
unwittingly, dropped a gold ring into the
bathwater and then threw it away. When
by Muhamed S. Asimov
she noticed that the ring had gone, she ac¬
cused a servant of responsibility for its
disappearance and severely punished her.
Thereupon, young Husayn, wishing to rec¬
tify this injustice, spoke up and said:
"Mother, beg the servant's pardon for it was
not she who lost the ring". These are said to
have been Avicenna's first words.
Born in 980 AD (370 of the Hegira) to
Abd-Allah, an official at Balkh (in the nor¬
thern part of present-day Afghanistan) and
to Sitora, the daughter of a farmer from the
village of Afshana near Bukhara, Avicenna
revealed his exceptional qualities very early
in life. By the age of ten he had already com¬
pleted the usual school curriculum and
could recite all the Koran by heart. At six¬
teen he was a physician whose renown was
such that he was summoned to treat the
Emir of Bukhara himself. By curing the Emir
the young doctor unlocked for himself the
doors of the Emir's celebrated library, the
"Sanctuary of Wisdom".
"By eighteen or nineteen," Avicenna later
told his disciple and biographer Juzjani, "I
had already made myself familiar with the
whole of philosophical knowledge logic,
physics, mathematics, geometry,
arithmetic, astronomy, music, medicine and
many other disciplines so that I met no one
who was my master".
This was no exaggeration. His memory,
and the range and depth of his knowledge
were stupendous. When the library of
Bukhara burned down, people consoled
themselves by saying: "The Sanctuary of
Wisdom has not perished. It has been
transferred into the brain of Al-Shayk
al-Ra'is!"
Avicenna's relatively brief life (he died
aged fifty-seven) could be epitomized as
one of titanic creation. He worked at all
times and in all conditions. He wrote or dic¬
tated his works day and night, in prison or
on his travels, even on horseback. The Ira¬
nian scholar Said Nafissi calculated that he
wrote (or had attributed to him) 456 works in
Arabic and 23 in Persian. At least 160 books
by Avicenna are listed in the catalogues of
the world's libraries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Shown here is a small selection from the imaginary portraits of Avicenna produced by
artists of many countries in the last ten centuries. Clockwise from top left: a study by
an anonymous artist which was reproduced many times in European editions of
Avicenna's work; fragment from a stained glass window; head discovered in 1950
beneath a layer of plaster on the wall of the Bodleian Library, Oxford; commemorative
stamp issued by Iran thirty years ago on the thousandth anniversary of Avicenna's birth
according to the lunar calendar; detail from title page of a 16th-century medical work
published in Strasbourg; portrait executed in the 1950s by an artist of the Tadzhik SSR.
Opposite page: a medal just issued by Unesco to mark the thousandth anniversary of
Avicenna's birth in the Christian calendar (for details see page 46).
A medieval engraving depicts Avicenna
seated on a throne, a laurel crown on his
head. Galen and Hippocrates are shown at
each side of him. If Galen and Hippocrates
were the fathers of medicine, the unknown
artist seems to be saying, Avicenna was its
prince and its hero.
This symbolic representation of
Avicenna's qualities is fully justified, for in
the Middle Ages the words Avicenna and
medicine were virtually synonymous. His
great work the Canon of Medicine is a
remarkable synthesis of medical knowledge,
which presents the achievements of the
most outstanding Greek, Indian, Iranian and
Arab physicians. The author's range, the
logical rigour of his thought, the con¬
ciseness and lucidity of his exposition, his
novel approach to the eternal problems of
medicine as well as to the formulation and
solution of new questions, the freshness
and originality of his thought all these fac¬
tors make the Canon a work without parallel
(see article page 13).
Translated into Latin in the twelfth cen¬
tury by Gerard of Cremona, it became for
centuries a veritable Bible of medicine. (In
fact, after the invention of printing with
movable type, it became the second most
widely printed book after the Bible.) In the
Canon Avicenna not only produced a
brilliant synthesis of his predecessors' work,
he greatly enriched medical science through k
his own observations and discoveries. *
MUHAMED S. ASIMOV, of the USSR, is Pre¬
sident of the International Association for the
Study of the Cultures of Central Asia, a corres¬
ponding member of the Academy of Sciences of
the USSR, and President of the Academy of
Sciences of the Tadzhik Soviet Socialist
Republic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
> He was the first person to describe cor¬
rectly the anatomy of human eye muscles,
and devised an explanation for the
mechanism of sight which is not far remov¬
ed from the modern conception of this
phenomenon. He explained with precision
the heart's system of ventricles and valves.
He described smallpox and measles,
illnesses unknown to the physicians of
Ancient Greece. His analysis of diabetes
does not differ greatly from that made eight
centuries later by the English specialist
Thomas Willis.
He put forward the hypothesis that cer¬
tain infectious diseases are transmitted by
"tiny organisms" in water and in the at¬
mosphere, and in the eighteenth century
this hypothesis was confirmed by the Dutch
scientist Antonie van Leeuwenhoek
(1632-1723) in research using microscopes
he had constructed himself (see Unesco
Courier, June 1977). His observations on the
pulse are of very great interest (he counted
sixty simple and thirty complex variants),
and modern science has added few
refinements to his work.
He invented a number of diagnostic pro¬
cedures. The percussion method, for exam¬
ple, whereby internal sicknesses are located
by tapping the patient's body with the
finger, is associated with Avicenna,
although it was later rediscovered by the
Viennese physician Leopold Auenbrugger
(1722-1809). However, the essential impor¬
tance of the Canon lies in the principle of
"natural causality" on which it is based and
from which Avicenna drew inspiration not
only in the field of medicine but in all his
scientific work.
Modern science came into being when
scholars began to see the physical world not
as the symbolic reflection of another,
spiritual world, but as a set of natural causes
and effects which could be studied through
observation, research and experiment
leading to the formulation of new
hypotheses. The works of Avicenna turned
Western thought in the direction which
would give birth to modern science.
The Ancient Greeks had made a synthesis
of the then-known cultural values, including
those of the Orient. The culture of the
Roman Empire assimilated many elements
of Hellenism and of the science of the Orien¬
tal peoples. Then, in the medieval Orient,
came a period which can be compared for
brilliance with the European Renaissance.
Avicenna was a luminary of this age, but he
lived and worked in a cultural and historical
setting which had produced other geniuses
such as the Persian poets Rudaki and Fer-
dowsi, the physician Abu Bakr Razi, the
astronomer Abu Mahmud Khodjendi, and
the encyclopaedists al-Farabi and al-Biruni.
Avicenna sparked off a new cultural
movement which, enriched by the in¬
vigorating sources of the past, swept
westwards from the Orient. First of all it
reached Spain; then it spread to the South
of France, where it made a contribution to
the development of freedom of thought in
Europe. This process reached its climax at
the time of the Crusades, when Arab and
Byzantine cultures once more began to
spread in Europe. The thought of Avicenna
was thus an essential link in the develop¬
ment and expansion of a unique human
civilization.
It would be hard to over-estimate the in- 1
fluence of Avicenna's scientific and I
S
During the age of Avicenna, the Islamic world was creatively developing the
mass of scientific knowledge inherited from the mosaic of cultural traditions it
had encountered during its rapid expansion. As well as developing
mathematical theories of remarkable accuracy, Muslim astronomers also served
the Islamic community's practical need to determine the times of daily prayers
at different latitudes and longitudes and to work out the direction of Mecca
from every locality where prayers were performed. Avicenna himself made
astronomical observations and devised a contrivance for increasing the
precision of instrumental readings. The copper astrolabe, above right, was made
in Iraq In the 9th century AD. It was used for measuring the height of celestial
bodies and hence determining the time of day or night. Above left, iron
compasses of the kind a scholar-scientist of Avicenna's time would have used.
This richly decorated ceramic
container was used in Central Asia
in Avicenna's time for transporting
and storing mercury, large
quantities of which were extracted
and widely used in everyday life.
Special metal recipients rubbed
with mercury, the only metal which
stays liquid at normal temperatures,
could be used as mirrors.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Avicenna's Canon of Medicine has been called "perhaps the most influential single work in
the history of medicine". Written in Arabic, it would later be translated into Persian,
Turkish, Urdu and other Islamic languages as well as into Hebrew.Catalan and Latin. But
although "the prince of physicians" was the period's most illustrious figure, he did not
stand alone, for numerous medical authorities of the highest rank emerged in the Islamic
world in the 10th and 11th centuries. One of them was the Arabo-Spanish physician al-
Zahrawi (d. c. 1013) known in the West as Albucasis, whose treatise on surgery, profusely
illustrated with drawings of surgical instruments designed by the author, became the
leading textbook on surgery in Europe for some 500 years. Above, a page from the treatise.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
, analytical concepts, set forth by one who
was both philosopher and man of science,
on the development of European thought.
He threw new light on Aristotle's logic by
considerably modifying the problems con¬
nected with the Aristotelian syllogism, en¬
visaging syllogisms based on categorical
judgements as well as syllogisms based on
hypothetical and conventional judgements.
But that is not all. Interesting though
Avicenna's judgements on induction, intui¬
tion and many other concepts may be, what
needs to be emphasized above all else is the
great store he set by logic. For him logic was
the very touchstone of knowledge which
makes it possible to realize "how what is not
known allows itself to be understood thanks
to what is known" and also "that all
knowledge which has not been weighed in
the balance [of reason] is not incontestable
and consequently is not authentic
knowledge".
Avicenna's contribution to logic was
stressed in the thirteenth century by the
English philosopher Roger Bacon
(1214-1294), one of the first champions of
experimental science. Bacon's appreciation
is particularly important since in Avicenna
the logician and the experimenter are
inseparable.
He formulated many original ideas which
heralded later discoveries, notably the prin¬
ciple of inertia set forth by the Italian
physicist and astronomer Galileo
(1564-1642) and Darwin's theory of evolu¬
tion. His methods of determining the
longitudinal differences between two points
on the earth's surface and the height and
azimuth of stars were reinvented five hun¬
dred years later.
It is known that on 24 May 1032, Avicenna
observed with the naked eye and described
a rare phenomenon: the passage of Venus
across the solar disc. This calls for a recti¬
fication in the history of science, for it was
long thought that this phenomenon had
been observed for the first time in 1639 by
the English astronomer Jeremiah Horrocks
(1617-1641).
If Avicenna was a pioneer in so many
fields, it is because he devoted all his life, in
medicine and philosophy, poetry and music,
education and sociology, to a single goal: in¬
creasing the sum of human happiness and
goodness. This he saw as the ultimate pur¬
pose of philosophy. Believing as he did that
there should be "understanding between
men, established standards of equity and
law", he expressed views which foreshadow
the idea of the Social Contract formulated in
the eighteenth century by Jean-Jacques
Rousseau (1712-1778).
The title of Avicenna's second en¬
cyclopaedic work, the Kitab al-Shifa (Book
of Healing) is particularly appropriate.
Whereas the Canon dealt with healing the
body, the Shifa dealt with healing the soul
so that men could become morally strong
and noble. (See article page 20).
The humanist ideas of Avicenna, who
saw in man an innate aspiration towards
beauty and harmony, and saw love as the
driving force in society, are expounded in his
Treatise on Love and in his philosophical
writings, Hayy ibn Yaqzan (The Living, Son
of the Dead), Salaman wa Absal and At-
Tayr (The Bird). They had an enriching in¬
fluence on the later development of the
literature of the peoples of the Orient and on
the work of the great poet Dante
(1265-1321).
Some specialists believe that through the
works of the philosopher and scholar Alber¬
tus Magnus (c. 1200-1280), Dante came
under a strong influence from Greco-Arab
philosophy and especially from Averroës
(Ibn Rushd, 1126-1198), who had himself
adopted many of Avicenna's ideas and also
made Avicenna known in Europe. Dante
himself remarked that he could not cite all
those of his predecessors who had influenc¬
ed him, but did include Avicenna among the
figures whose names he mentions in the
Divine Comedy.
The Persian astronomer and mathemati¬
cian Omar Khayyam (died around 1123) is
widely known as the author of the immortal
Rubaiyat (Quatrains). It is less well known
that he regarded Avicenna as his master, not
only in philosophy and the exact sciences
but in poetry, for it was Avicenna who
created the philosophical rubaiyat as a form
of expression. A number of these quatrains
have in fact survived, and they are
remarkable both for the perfection of their
poetic form and for the profundity of their
thought.
It is also recorded that Omar Khayyam,
shortly before his death, read with great
concentration the metaphysics of the Book
of Healing. As for Avicenna himself, when
he felt that he was about to die, he freed his
servants and distributed all his wealth to the
poor. On 18 June 1037 (Ramadan of the year
428 of the Hegira), he died in the desert near
the town of Hamadhan.
According to one story which has sur¬
vived, he wished to vanquish death and
achieve immortality. He is said to have
prepared forty different products which his
pupil was to administer to him in a predeter¬
mined order, immediately after his death.
The pupil faithfully accomplished this task,
and to his great astonishment the inert body
of his master became supple and youthful as
he injected the medicines. His face became
pink, he began to breathe again... and then
came the moment to administer the last cap¬
sule, which would bring about the Master's
resurrection. Unable to contain himself, the
pupil seized the capsule... but his hands
trembled, it slipped from his fingers, and the
mysterious liquid soaked away in the sand.
Fortunately, Avicenna has remained im¬
mortal in the minds of men.
Muhamed S. Asimov
Avicenna is
seated
symbolically
between two
great physicians
of Antiquity,
Galen and
Hippocrates, in
this engraving.
The doctrines of
Galen and
Hippocrates were
among the mass
of medical lore
codified and
interpreted by
Avicenna.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
{ß) Gurganj
/\
/ Bukhara^Äj
Kharmaithan
Hamadhan
X
	*i
"TEL
S* Samanqan-^^,
V
/
/
/
Nissa (Ä
®Afshana
Raiy
Chaqqa
Isfahan (§)
CD '
Above, map showing the travels of
Avicenna. Below, this mausoleum,
built by the Samanid Emir Ismail I
(892-907), is the only building from
the time of Avicenna still standing
at Bukhara, the city where
Avicenna spent his childhood and
adolescence and wrote his first
scientific and philosophical works.
Tus
>Baward
My Odyssey
by Avicenna
Our knowledge of the early life of Avicenna (Ibn Sina) is based on a book compiled by
Abu Ubaid al-Juzjani, his pupil and companion for twenty-five years. Although the
latter part of the book was written by al-Juzjani, the first part, which recounts the
great philosopher's life from his childhood until his return to Gorgan, was dictated by
Avicenna himself. It paints a vivid picture of a precocious intellect fully aware of his
own genius and of the incredible industriousness that brought that genius to fruition.
MY father was from Balkh. During
the reign of the Samanid ruler
Nuh Ibn Mansur (367-387 AH/
977-997 AD), he moved from Balkh to
Bukhara where he worked as a functionary.
He became the Governor of Kharmaithan,
the centre of a district in the region of
Bukhara, an ancient metropolis. In the
vicinity of Kharmaithan is a district called Af-
shana. He married my mother there and set¬
tled down. I, and later my brother, were
born there. Later we all went to Bukhara and
it was there that I began to study the Koran |
and belles-lettres. By the age of ten I had I
' . -SimT
¡r?***
i s
J
MOg
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
i reached the end of the Koran and had read
much belles-lettres, so that people were
surprised.
My father was one of those who had
responded to the invitation of the Egyptians
and was counted among the Isma'ilis. He
had accepted their opinions on the soul and
on the intellect. My brother likewise. They
often discussed these matters. I listened to
them, I grasped what they were saying, and
they tried to attract me to their rite. On occa¬
sion, too, they would discuss philosophy,
geometry and Indian arithmetic. Then my
father decided to have me learn Indian
arithmetic by sending me to a grocer who
was in the habit of using that form of
calculation.
Meanwhile, one Abu-Abdallah Nateli,
who professed a knowledge of philosophy,
came to Bukhara. My father invited him to
stay with us in the hope that he would teach
me. Before his arrival I had visited Ismail
Zahid, becoming an assiduous student of
Muslim jurisprudence and one of his best
pupils. I became familiar with the various
methods of argumentation used by the pro¬
fessionals. Later, under Nateli's guidance, I
began reading the Eisagoge [an introduction
to the Categoriae of Aristotle by the third-
century-AD philosopher Porphyry]. When
he explained to me the definition of genus, I
set about verifying the definition in a manner
whose like he had never heard before, so
deeply impressing him that he advised my
father that I should not engage in any other
occupation but learning. Whatever the
problem my Master set for me, I succeeded
in solving it better than he. I learned from
him the rudiments of logic, a science with
whose subtleties he had scant acquain¬
tance. From then on I began to read books
and study the commentaries on my own, so
that I achieved mastery of logic. I also read
Euclid's Geometry, under Nateli's guidance
from the beginning to the fifth or sixth
figure; as for the rest of the book, I managed
to solve all the difficulties on my own. Then I
moved on to [Ptolemy's] Almagest. When I
had finished the preliminary work and came
to the geometric figures, Nateli said to me,
"Read it yourself and solve the difficulties;
then' explain to me what you have read so
that I can distinguish for your benefit the
true from the false." (The book was beyond
the poor man's powers). And so I began to
elucidate it by myself, before expounding
the questions to my Master. How many
were the difficult problems Nateli had not
solved until then and which he understood
thanks to me!
Then Nateli left for Gorgan. As for me, I
applied myself to reading and studying al-
Farabi's Fusus al-Hikam and other commen¬
taries on physics and metaphysics. As each
day went by, the doors of knowledge open¬
ed before me. Then I took up medicine and
proceeded to read the works that had been
written on that subject. Since medicine is
not a difficult science, I soon excelled in it
and skilled doctors studied it under my
guidance. In addition, I cared for the sick
practically. Thus the doors of treatment bas¬
ed on experience opened before me, in a
way that cannot be described. At the same
time I kept up with my studies of religious
law and disputation. By then I was sixteen
years of age.
During the next year and a half I became
increasingly immersed in my studies. I went
over logic and all the problems of philosophy
10
once again. At that period I did not sleep
one night through, and worked all day, ac¬
quiring knowledge. I reduced every state¬
ment and proposition I came across into its
syllogistic premisses; then I examined the
possible results of the premisses and observ¬
ed their conditions until the moment when
the correct solution of the problem became
indubitable. Whenever I was baffled by a
problem, or could not work out the middle
term of a syllogism, I repaired to the
mosque. I begged and prayed the creator of
the universe to reveal to me what had been
locked in obscurity and to make difficulties
easy for me. Then, at night, I would return
home, set my lamp before me and begin
again to read and write. Whenever sleep
began to overcome me or I felt exhausted, I
drank a frugal glass of wine and waited for
my energy to return. Then I began to read
again, and when I dozed off I would see in a
dream the very same question that I was
pondering, so that the solutions to many
problems appeared to me in my sleep. I con¬
tinued unremittingly to follow this routine
until I possessed a solid mastery of the
sciences and held them in my grasp as far as
our human faculties allow. Everything I
learned at that time is not replaced by what I
have learned more recently, even until to¬
day. Thus I mastered logic, the natural
sciences and mathematics.
Then I returned to the study of the divine
science. I read [Aristotle's] Metaphysics, but
without understanding a word of it. The
author's intentions remained lost in obscuri¬
ty to me. Although I read the book forty
times from end to end until I knew it by
heart, I could grasp neither its meaning nor
its purpose. I despaired of understanding it
by my own efforts and said to myself: "This
book is incomprehensible". Then one day I
was walking through the book bazaar when
a bookseller proffered me a book whose
price he was shouting out. Discouraged as I
was, I rebuffed him, convinced that there
was nothing to be gained from this science.
The vendor stood his ground and said: "Buy
this book. It is cheap. I am selling it off for
three dirhams because its owner is in needy
circumstances." And so I bought it. The
book turned out to be Abu Nasr al-Farabi's
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Avicenna's pleasant life at Gurganj
came to an abrupt end when Sultan
Mahmud of Ghazna demanded that the
brilliant group of artists and
philosophers gathered under the
protection of Emir Ali Ibn Ma'mun be
sent to grace his own court. Avicenna
was unwilling to comply and, to avoid
the Sultan's clutches, was obliged to
flee Gurganj. Travelling farther and
farther westwards, he crossed the
Karakum desert eventually reaching
IMIssa. Not far from Nissa at the present-
day town of Meyhana, stands the
mausoleum (photo top left) of the sufi,
or Muslim mystic, Abu Said, whom
Avicenna is thought to have known and
from whom he may have acquired a
knowledge of Islamic mysticism.
Another of Avicenna's stopping-places
was Meshked-i-Misriana, then a
beautiful and populous town whose
ruined minarets (photo bottom left)
to.day rise like a mirage from the desert.
After many other vicissitudes Avicenna
at last reached Isfahan where he
became physician and adviser to the
Emir. Here, at the peak of his career, he
wrote in his native tongue, Persian, one
of his major works the Book of
Knowledge. Photo right, the
soaring arches of the Friday Mosque at
Isfahan. Worn out by his travels and the
hardships and alarums of an eventful
life, Avicenna died, in August 1037, on
the desert road between Isfahan and
Hamadhan, to which city his body was
taken. Today, his remains are at rest in
a new mausoleum (photo bottom right)
built during the 1950s by Iranian
architect Khusheng Saihun. The
mausoleum houses a huge library.
Twelve columns form a thirty-metre-
high tower supporting a cone-shaped
roof. They represent the twelve
branches of learning in which the
genius of Avicenna found expression.
Commentaries on the Metaphysics. I rushed
home and read it. The whole purport of
[Aristotle's treatise] straightaway became
clear to me because I already knew the work
by heart. In a transport of delight, I began
the following day to distribute abundant
alms to the poor as a thanksgiving.
At this time the Emir Nuh Ibn Mansur, the
ruler of Bukhara, was afflicted with a serious
illness which the doctors were unable to
cure. I was renowned among these physi¬
cians for the range of my studies. They sug¬
gested to the prince that he should summon
me. So off I went and joined the other physi¬
cians who were treating him. And I
distinguished myself in his service.
One day I asked him to grant me access to
his library, to examine the books there and
to read the medical works. He agreed to my
request. I made my way into a mansion with
many chambers, with chest upon chest of
books in each. Each room was devoted to a
single subject, one room containing works
of literature and poetry, another works of
jurisprudence. I perused the catalogue of
books of the Ancients and asked for all
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
those I needed. Among them I saw books
whose very names were unknown to
many works which I had never seen before
and have not seen since.
I read these books, profiting from them
and acquainting myself with each author's
rank in his own field of knowledge. At the
age of eighteen, I had finished studying all
these sciences. At that period my knowledge
was due above all to my memory; today I am
more mature, otherwise my knowledge is
exactly the same and nothing has changed.
A neighbour of mine called Abu'l Hassan
al-Aruzi asked me to write a scientific en¬
cyclopaedia for him. In answer to his re¬
quest I wrote the Majmu (Compendium)
which I signed in his name and in which I
covered all the sciences except
mathematics. I was then twenty-one years
old. Another neighbour of mine was a native
of Khorezm named Abu Bakr al-Baraqi. He
had no equal in jurisprudence, Koranic ex¬
egesis and asceticism and had a strong lean¬
ing for the speculative sciences. He asked
me to write a commentary on these scien¬
tific works and so I wrote al-Hasil wa al-
Mahsul (The Import and the Substance) in
about twenty volumes. I also wrote for him a
work on ethics which I called al-Birr wa al-
Ithm (Good Work and Evil), works which
can only be found at his dwelling and which
he never lent out for copying.
Then my father died and my cir¬
cumstances changed completely. I accepted
a post in the Sultan's employment and had
to move from Bukhara to Gurganj. The vizier
of the ruler of Khorezm, Ali Ibn Ma'mun,
was a learned man by the name of Abu-I Hu-
sain as-Soheili. I presented myself to this
ruler, wearing the clothing appropriate to
jurists, with scarf and chin-wrap. A monthly
salary, in keeping with my talents, was fix¬
ed. Some time afterwards, again constrain¬
ed by necessity, I moved from Khorezm to
the confines of Khorasan, passing through
Baward, then Tus then Shaqqan, then
Samanqan, then Jajarm and thence to
Gorgan. My entire purpose was to reach the
Emir Qabus; but it happened at that moment
that Qabus was taken and imprisoned in a
fortress, where he died. After this I went to
Dihistan where I fell very ill, then returned to
Jurjan where Abu Ubain al-Juzjani made
friends with me; and I composed a poem on
my condition in which there is a verse
saying:
And great once I became, no more would
city hold me,
And when my value rose, no one would care
to buy me.
Milestones in a restless life
980 AD (370 of the Hegira), birth of Avicenna (Abu Ali al-Husayn Ibn Abd-Allah Ibn Hassan
Ibn Ali Ibn Sina) near the city of Bukhara (in the present-day Soviet Socialist Republic of
Uzbekistan) in a village of which his father was governor. As a very young child, begins to learn
Arabic and the Koran.
The family soon moves to Bukhara. By the age of ten, Avicenna can recite the 114 chapters
of the Koran from memory.
Under the guidance of gifted teachers, Avicenna extends the range of his knowledge to a
prodigious degree. His last tutor, the philosopher Nateli, leaves because he has nothing more to
teach him.
At sixteen years of age Avicenna has won a reputation as a doctor and is beginning to attract
a growing stream of patients.
Around the age of eighteen he has already assimilated all the knowledge of his time in
theology, Arabic literature, geometry, mathematics, physics, logic and philosophy.
Succeeds, where all other physicians have failed, in curing the Samanid Sultan of Bukhara,
Nuh Ibn Mansur; wins the Sultan's favour and is rewarded with access to his library.
While at Bukhara writes his first works, notably al-Hasil wa al-Mahsul (The Import and the
Substance) and al-Birr wa al-lthm (Good Work and Evil).
In the year 1001 AD (392 of the Hegira) the Samanid State is threatened by the powerful
Sultan Mahmud of Ghazna (in present-day Afghanistan). Avicenna sets out for Gurganj, capital
of Khorezm (in what is now the Turkmen SSR) whose vizier Abu-I Husayn as-Soheili is a lover
of learning. The Emir of Gurganj, Ali Ibn Ma'mun, has gathered around him a galaxy of il¬
lustrious scholars including the renowned al-Biruni, Abu Nasr al-Arraq, the Christian Abu
Masihi, and Abul Kheir al-Khammar.
After a short stay, Avicenna is obliged to leave Gurganj when the Sultan of Ghazna demands
that all the Gurganj scientists be sent to his court. Prince Ma'mun is forced to yield to his
powerful neighbour, but Avicenna, accompanied by the Christian Masihi, who will not survive
the journey, leaves for Gorgan, southeast of the Caspian Sea.
While at Gorgan meets Abu Ubaid al-Juzjani who (until Avicenna's death a quarter of a cen¬
tury later) will be his most faithful disciple and his biographer.
For two years Avicenna devotes himself to study and writing. Finishes al-Mabda wa al-Ma'ad
(The Beginning and the Return) and embarks on one of his masterworks, the Canon of
Medicine.
Leaves Gorgan and journeys to the city of Raiy (whose ruins today stand southwest of
Teheran), the capital of prince Majd el-Dowleh. Avicenna treats the prince and cures him.
In 1014 AD (405 of the Hegira) leaves Raiy and settles near Hamadhan.
Avicenna, whose reputation has preceded him, is summoned to the bedside of prince Shams
el-Dowleh, who appoints him vizier (prime minister).
After being toppled by an army mutiny, Avicenna is reinvested as grand vizier, and for the
next six years lives a relatively stable life governed by a crushing work-timetable.
Begins his great encyclopaedic work on philosophy the Shifa (The Book of Healing). Rises
before dawn, teaches his pupils in the early morning, leads them to prayers as an Imam, writes
fifty pages a day of the Shifa.
In 1021 AD (412 of the Hegira) his protector, prince Shams el-Dowleh, dies, and his son
refuses to reinvest Avicenna as grand vizier. Goes into hiding where he virtually completes the
Shifa, without, as he would later point out, reference to written texts and relying entirely on his
prodigious memory.
A secret letter to the ruler of Isfahan, prince Ala el-Dowleh, is intercepted, Avicenna's hiding
place is revealed and he is cast into prison with his faithful disciple Juzjani. During four months
in prison writes the Risalat Haiy ibn Yaqzan (The Treatise of Living, the Son of the Vigilant), the
al-Hidaya (The Book of Guidance) and the al-Adwiyat al-Qa/biyya (The Cardiac Remedies).
After a war between princes Sama el-Dowleh and Ala el-Dowleh, in which the latter is vic¬
torious, Avicenna is released but is obliged to live at Hamadhan.
In 1023 AD (414 of the Hegira) flees to Isfahan accompanied by the faithful Juzjani.
At Isfahan, the final stage in Avicenna's tumultuous Odyssey, the philosopher spends the last
fourteen years of his life under the protection of prince Ala el-Dowleh.
Works on astronomy, and so the story goes, writes the Book of Know/edge at the prince's re¬
quest. Adds a chapter on music to the Shifa and writes a work on linguistics entitled The
Language of the Arabs.
During a campaign waged against Hamadhan by Ala el-Dowleh, Avicenna is seized by a
severe attack of colic which he tries to cure too quickly.
Dies on the first Friday of the month of Ramadan, 428 of the Hegira (August 1037 AD), aged
fifty-seven.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Canon of Medicine
A million-word thesaurus
of medical knowledge
by Hakim Mohammed Said
GREEK medicine reached the Muslim
world before philosophy, via the
medical school at Jundishapur.
During the Ummayyad age (41-132
AH/661-750 AD) a Persian Jew, Masar-
jawaih, translated the Pandects (treatises) of
Ahron into Arabic. Ahron was a Christian
monk who lived in Alexandria not long
before the Arab conquest.
This was followed by Mesue the Elder's
Jawahir al-Tibb al-mufrada (The Essential
Features of Drug Simples) and translations
during the Abbasid age (132-656
AH/750-1258 AD) by Hunayn, who, if his
claim is to be given credence, translated
some of Hippocrates' works (including his
Aphorisms), the whole of Galen's original
works and some of his commentaries on
Hippocrates.
The age of translation was followed by a
period which saw the production of some
original works of high order in medicine. Ali
Ibn-Sahl Rabban al-Tabari (833-923 AD)
produced his Firdaws al-Hikmah (Paradise
of Wisdom). It included some philosophy
and other disciplines like astronomy, but
broke new ground in that it included not
only Greek but also Hindu sources.
Tabari was followed by an even greater
figure, al-Razi (865-923 AD) who has been
called "the greatest and most original of
Muslim physicians, and one of the most pro¬
lific as an author". Unlike Avicenna's
Canon, his Kitab al-Hawi (Continens) is not
a theoretical work but a record of clinical ex¬
periences. Although he was interested in
philosophy, al-Razi mostly wrote treatises of
a practical nature, e.g.. Smallpox and
Measles; On the fact that even skilful physi¬
cians cannot heal all diseases; and On why
people prefer quacks and charlatans to skill¬
ed physicians.
Thus there existed a whole tradition of
medical writing when Avicenna's (Ibn
Sina's) Canon of Medicine appeared. The
literal meaning of Qanun (Canon) is codes of
laws and series of principles. Avicenna
therefore wrote the work not as an en¬
cyclopaedia of the knowledge of his own
time but as knowledge based upon reason¬
ing, logic, and principles. According to one
authority, "Numerous passages occur in the k
Canon which show that it is a series of notes t
HAKIM MOHAMMED SAID, of Pakistan, is
adviser on traditional Islamic medicine to the
Pakistan Ministry of Health, and President of the
Hamdard National Foundation (Karachi) which is
devoted to scientific and medical research. He is
editor-in-chief of the Foundation's periodical
Hamdard Medicine and Managing Editor of the
Urdu edition of the Unesco Courier.
EP*
-Z."-^ . "^*
C--
-
Above, first page of Part 10 of Book III of Avicenna's Canon of Medicine, in the form of a
richly ornamented manuscript in naskhi (cursive Arabic script) dating from 1601 AD. Each
part opens with a multicoloured unvan or illuminated heading and the text is framed with a
border of gold or coloured lines. The marginal notes suggest that the manuscript was once
in the possession of an industrious and attentive student.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Diagrams on this page, depicting
(below) the nervous system, (bottom
left) the human skeleton and
(left) the muscles, are from a
Persian manuscript of the Canon of
Medicine dating from 1632 AD. The
text accompanying the anatomical
drawing (right) by Leonardo da
Vinci, in the artist's famous
"mirror-writing", refers specifically
to Avicenna. "The elements of the
foot number sixty", he wrote, using
Avicenna's exact terms.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
,_« «t»* ^»tt»5» m»»!"'»'* ^****^11"
'-t'l-fi'~
F ' .
-W. ..».« »1^».
iJr,~y <- -"*»' * *"** "**"
. A.- .
-	 -
--
'	H
. .«»M »y»/.* -*¡WS TMy-J-Mf M*ft) -ï.
J-. -
rjr»i -~ -y- -«-
*4 V * ' 'a. ^*
-r -I
ii«>|«wwfqiMi«na
^ .1*.««»). fc.lf . Mf-'< « * «I i^ '
«««
ñ>» * - ^ " ' " «>/
-
-i .^. ,i ,.^- -,
-.»7
./. . ._..r
~» . «... *-,» *» * «
' or skeleton outlines, not too lengthy to be
memorized by his pupils".
The work comprises five volumes. The
first volume discusses the general principles.
It defines medicine and discusses the scope
of medicine, followed by discourses upon
temperament, temperament of organs,
temperament of age and sex, nature and
variety of humours, diseases of the organs,
muscles, nerves, a'rteries and veins, faculties
and functions, diseases and their aetiology,
signs and symptoms, pulse, urine, regimens
to be followed for different ages, preventive
medicine, management of temperamental
abnormalities, effect of climate, and
treatment.
The second volume consists of two parts.
The first part discusses the determination of
the temperament of drugs by experiment
and influence. Conditions for research into
drugs are laid down, e.g. the experiments to
be conducted on the human body, freedom
of the drug from extrinsic and intrinsic
alterations, trial to be on an allopathic basis
and made in simple diseases, and determina¬
tion as to whether the drug is qualitatively
and quantitatively appropriate to the nature
and severity of the disease, and so on.
General principles regarding drug action
and methods of collecting and pre¬
serving various drug products are described
as well. The second part lists 760 drugs
arranged alphabetically.
The third volume discusses the aetiology,
symptoms, diagnosis, prognosis and
systematic treatment of diseases. It
describes diseases of the head, e.g. abnor¬
mal temperaments of the brain, and
headache, epilepsy, paralysis, etc., diseases
of the eye, nose, ear, and throat; diseases of
the alimentary tract, genito-urinary system,
diseases of the muscles, joints, and feet.
The fourth volume treats of general
diseases. Part I deals with fevers and their
treatment, Part II with boils and swellings,
leprosy, minor surgery, wounds and their
general treatment, injuries, ulcers and glan¬
dular swellings, Part III with poisons, and
Part IV with "beauty culture".
Volume V is an aqrabadhin (the Arab
equivalent for formulary). A notable
predecessor to Avicenna's work is the for¬
mulary by the Arab philosopher al-Kindi
(800-873 AD). It comprises description of
special prescriptions and antidotes,
methods of preparing pills, pessaries, sup¬
positories, powders, syrups, decoctions,
confections, elixirs, etc., prescriptions for
different diseases; weights and measures.
The impact of the Canon has been im¬
mense. Translated into Latin a century after
its appearance by the famous Italian
translator Gerard of Cremona, it gained so
much popularity that in the last thirty years
of the fifteenth century it was issued sixteen
times and more than twenty times in the six¬
teenth century. It was still being printed and
read in the second half of the seventeenth
century, and was consulted by medical prac¬
titioners regularly. It continued as a text¬
book until 1650 in the Universities of Mont¬
pellier and Louvain. The medical cur¬
riculum in Vienna and Frankfurt-on-the-
Oder, in the sixteenth century, was largely
based on the Canon and the Ad Alman-
sorem of al-Razi. The noted Avicenna
scholar Soheil M. Afnan, speaking of its
popularity, remarks:
"The translation of the Canon by Andrea
Alpago (d. 1520) of Italy was followed by
even later versions which were taught in
various European universities, especially in
Italy and France. It was not until human
dissection came to be allowed that Euro¬
pean anatomists detected certain
anatomical and physiological errors of Galen
which had been transmitted to Europe
through the works of Avicenna."
A special feature of the Canon is" its
broadness and catholicity. It has now been
established beyond doubt that Ayurvedic*
works had become available in Arabrc in the
seventh 'century, and during the Abbasid i
period Salih Ibn Duhn and the Hindu |
* Ayurveda is the traditional Hindu system of
medicine based largely on homeopathy and
naturopathy.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
astronomer Mankah were the transmitters
of this tradition. Some descriptions in the
Canon, such as those of the pulse, are
reminiscent of the Chinese system.
A major contribution of Avicenna is to the
aetiology of disease. Taking his cue from
Aristotle, he believes that complete
knowledge of a thing is possible only if we
take into account the material of which a
thing is made, the "efficient cause" that
moulds it, the "formal cause" which deter¬
mines its shape and quality, and the "final
cause" or function for which a thing is
made. Avicenna introduces a theory in
which the concept of the elements sym¬
bolizes qualities of mass and energy at the
same time and interaction between the four
causes. He thus establishes not only the uni¬
ty between organs and functions in the body
but also brings the body and the outer world
in appropriate space-time relationship.
Now the human body is material but is
vivified by the vital force. The vital force is a
life-principle organized from the humours.
He defines psyche as expressing itself as
mind at the cognitive level and as emotions
in the heart and thus an integral part of the
body.
This concept of causation, then, implies
that the internal organs belong to each other
beyond the anatomical limits. Anatomy
regards the heart as a circumscribed organ
while for Avicenna it is the part of force oc¬
cupying the whole of the body.
If we combine the ancient with modern
knowledge, we might just as well say that
the arterial vessels with the blood contained
in them and the autonomic nervous system
including its hypothalamic centre are one
great composite of the functional heart
whose operation pervades the whole body.
The nafs in Avicenna is anima, which, in
accordance with the nature of an organism,
acts as the ultimate determinant or for¬
mative factor for its growth and activity. The
basic thesis with Avicenna is thus that the
whole is greater than the sum of its parts
and that man is a dynamic organism, with
each individual having his own unique
temperament. His dynamism cannot be ex¬
plained on the basis of analysis.
With the help of these concepts Avicenna
offers a constitutional approach according to
which disease is to be explained in terms of
the individual's genetic structure; the kind of
temperament, structure, and strength of
faculties possessed by him; environmental
factors; and Nature's own effort at the
restoration or maintenance of his life-
functions.
The concept of the elements in Avicenna,
in which heat and cold are two opposite
types of energy, and dryness and moisture
are two opposite qualities of mass, is to be
found in Aristotle. Avicenna's elaboration of
the Aristotelian thesis has been translated as
follows: The truth is that the first principles
behind all generable and corruptible
substances are primary, active or kinetic
energies and occur either simply in fire, air,
water and earth or linked to a composite
Illustrations from an edition of the Canon of Medicine, dating from about 1520 AD, show
methods of treatment for various spinal disorders. While Avicenna broadly followed
Hippocrates' methods for the extension of the vertebral column in the treatment of
displaced vertebrae, the use of a specially designed instrument (lower illustration) for
putting a displaced vertebra back in place was his own invention.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
I
»
s
.i
u
W
P
Avicenna's contribution to pharmacology was original and important and he is credited
with introducing many previously untried herbs into medical use. Book II of his Canon
of Medicine dealt with pharmacology, including the collection and preservation of
medicinal herbs, and formed the basis of many subsequent works on this subject.
Above, excerpt from a manuscript known as The Gift of the Believers, written by
Mohammad Dailani, physician at the court of Shah Ismaili (1686-1694). The illustration is
of Fasafis, a plant resembling the lentil, which was used to cure disorders of the throat
and liver and as an antidote to snake-bite.
temperament. The late Dr. Mazhar H. Shah
observed that, according to Avicenna, the
organization of various objects in nature is
the result of an interaction of the four
qualities of mass and energy and that the
four elements mentioned in the Canon are
merely symbols employed to understand the
various actions and reactions of the body
and its environment in qualitative terms.
Ayurveda has three temperaments: Vata,
Pitta, and Kapha as propounded by
Charak and Sushruta. Hippocrates has also
three temperaments apoplectic, phleg¬
matic, and melancholic.
Galen propounded four temperaments
sanguine, choleric, phlegmatic, and
melancholic. Avicenna formulated four
temperaments hot and moist, hot and dry,
cold and moist, and cold and dry.
Since then several temperaments have
been formulated, among those that are well-
known being those due to Eppinger and
Hess (1917 and 1931) and Pavlov. The
former formulated two temperaments, sym-
patheticotonia and vagotonia, while Pavlov
propounded four temperaments im¬
petuous, calm, and weak. These four types
correspond exactly to the Galenic classifica¬
tion of temperament into the sanguine,
choleric, phlegmatic, and melancholic
types.
The "heart" in Avicenna's system is not
just the structural heart described by the
anatomists but the "functional" heart
which, as the centre of emotions, thermo¬
regulation, sleep and water metabolism is
centred in the diencephalon, a portion of the
brain which in the phylogeny of the race was
the first to develop. The pituitary gland
which subserves as well as regulates the
functions of this region may also be included
in the concept of the "heart". In De Viribus
Cordis (paragraph 172) Avicenna says:
"The foundation or beginning of all these
faculties is traceable to the heart, as is
agreed upon even by those philosophers
who think that the source of visual, auditory
and gustatory power lies in the Brain."
The Canon abounds in original observa¬
tions made by Avicenna during the course
of medical practice, e.g. the distinction of
mediastinitis from pleurisy; the contagious
nature of phthisis; the diffusion of disease
by water and soil; sexual diseases and
perversions; nervous diseases; and careful
description of the diseases of the skin. The
materia medica describes about 760 drugs
and Avicenna has outlined pharmacological
Left, double-ended
instrument used by
pharmacists in
Avicenna's day in the
preparation of medicines;
one end consists of a
spoon and the other of a
small strainer. Below,
10th to 12th-century
bronze medicine phial
discovered in
Uzbekistan.
Photos Sergei A. Davydov
© Museum of the History of the
Peoples of Uzbekistan, Tashkent
methods. The book on materia medica and
pharmacology contains a passage upon ex¬
perimentation which according to the
French scholar A-M. Goichon, sets out the
three methods agreement, difference, and
concomitant variations which are usually
associated with the modern scientific
approach.
The Canon remained far more accessible
than the works of Hippocrates, even though
Arnold of Villanova (1235-1312) described
Avicenna as a "professional scribbler"
whose misinterpretation of Galen stupefied
European physicians. Ibn Zuhr (Avenzoar)
of Spain described the Canon as "waste-
paper". Such criticism belittles the critics
rather than the Shaykh al-Rais. If he
stupefied the European physicians, why
should be have been studied in Europe at all
and why did not European scholars come
out with their own interpretations of Galen?
Nor is the historian of science George Sar-
ton's contention that "His triumph was too
complete; it discouraged original investiga¬
tions and sterilized intellectual life", correct
for there were many notable physicians,
surgeons, and scientists after him among
the Muslims.
Hakim Mohammed Said
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Notes and nostrums
from Dr. Avicenna's casebook
by Ahmed Aroua
FROM examination of the character
and writings of Avicenna (Ibn Sina)
there emerges a picture of that
perpetual search for balance and unity that
is characteristic of Arabo-lslamic culture.
There is no contradiction, nor should there
be, between body and mind, between the
individual and society, between science and
faith, between nature and man.
The medical arts as propounded by
Avicenna are free of all those harmful and ir¬
rational explanations with which the
medicine of Antiquity was blemished and
which can still be found in certain practices
of modern fringe medicine. With Avicenna
medicine became a science.
He divided medicine into "theoretical"
and "practical" medicine, the latter being
sub-divided further into "curative" and
"preventive" medicine. Attaching as he did
great importance to preventive medicine,
Avicenna listed the following areas in which
it should be applied:
"The essential considerations ¡n the art of
preserving the health consist in maintaining
equilibrium between various concomitant
factors. But there are seven matters concer¬
ning which special care must be expended
to ensure just proportion: Equilibrium of the
temperament; Selection of the articles of
food and drink; Evacuation of effete mat¬
ters; Safeguarding the composite; Maintain¬
ing the purity of the air respired; Guarding
against extraneous contingencies; Modera¬
tion in regard to the movements of the body
and the motions of the mind, which include
sleep and wakefulness. "
With his view of health as a dynamic con¬
cept affecting the whole person, Avicenna
took into consideration questions of age,
temperament, constitution, climate, and the
psychosomatic duality of the individual.
He devoted many pages of the Canon to
the safeguarding of the health of the infant:
"Bathing the infant. In summer time it
should be bathed in suave, tepid water. In
winter the water should be on the warm
side. Whenever possible the mother's milk
should be given and by suckling. For that is
the aliment of all others most like in sub¬
stance to the nutrient material which the in¬
fant receives while in the womb. Experience
AHMED AROUA is an Algerian medical doctor
and poet. These extracts from Avicenna's Canon
of Medicine and the accompanying commentaries
appeared in his book Hygiène et Prévention Médi¬
cale chez Ibnou Sina (Avicenne) {Hygiene and
Preventive Medicine in Ibn Sina [Avicenna]),
1974.
shows that merely to place the mother's nip¬
ple into the infant's mouth is a great help
towards removing whatever is hurtful to the
infant. "
Ahead of his time in many areas of
medicine, Avicenna was especially con¬
scious of the importance of physical
exercise:
"Now'exercise is that agent which most
surely prevents the accumulation of these
matters and prevents plethora. It is this
exercise which renews and revives the in¬
nate heat and imparts the necessary
lightness to the body. For it causes the sub¬
tile heat to be increased and daily disperses
whatever effete substances have ac¬
cumulated. To forsake exercise would often
incur the risk of 'hectic', because the
faculties of the members are impaired in¬
asmuch as deprivation of movement
prevents the access to them of the innate
breath. And this last is the real instrument of
life for every one of the members. "
Avicenna also laid great stress on the ef¬
fect of sleep on mental activity:
"Sleep in moderation assists the
vegetative faculties in their functions and
brings the sensitive faculties into repose and
in so doing restores them and thereby ar¬
rests the dissipation of the breath. The good
qualities of sleeping by night are that it
should be continuous and deep. It is also
bad to go to sleep during the day. The best
sleep is that which is deep and that which
occurs after the food has passed on from
the upper part of the intestine. "
The Canon also offers much advice on the
effect on man of the air he breathes and of
his environment:
"As long as the air is attempered andpure
and has no substances admixed which
would be contrary to the temperament of
the breath, health will come and remain.
Otherwise the contrary occurs. The
substance of the air is good when it is not
contaminated with extraneous matter such
as the vapours from marshes and lakes or
canals and open sewers or the gaseous pro¬
ducts from chemical works or smoke or
soot. Air is good when it does not interfere
with one's breathing or cause the throat to
contract. "
Avicenna expressed in the Canon his
views on the effects of climate and the
seasons on human health:
"Spring. When the temperament of the
spring conforms to type, it is a very healthy
season. Diseases of the spring: Inflam¬
matory deposits, carbuncles, anginas, ab-
| scesses of various kinds. There may be
haemoptysis and troublesome coughs.
Puberty and the time of life thereabout are
benefited by the spring".
"Summer. In summer: the humours are
dispersed. The faculties and natural func¬
tions are impaired owing to the excessive
dispersion. The blood and serous humour
are diminished and the bilious humour in¬
creases. Diseases of the summer: if very
hot, tertian and burning fevers, emaciation,
pains on the ears, ophthalmia. Erysipelas is
common, also furunculosis; if spring-like,
mild benign fevers. Rheumatisms and catar¬
rhs also occur. Old people and those of
similar nature feel stronger in summer. "
"Autumn. The autumn season brings
many diseases for these reasons: there is ex¬
posure to sun by day and the nights are
cold. The blood is much less in amount
because this season is contrary in tempera¬
ment to the blood. Diseases of autumn:
fevers, rheumatisms and sciatica, oliguria
and dysuria, angina, worms.
"Winter. Winter is a help for digestion.
Diseases of winter: coryza, pleurisy,
pulmonary infection, hoarseness and sore
throat, pains in the chest, side, back and
loins, apoplexy and epileptic seizures.
Winter is inimical to old persons. "
The views expressed by Avicenna on mat¬
ters of housing and public health have an
astonishing topicality since today these
problems face urban authorities in ag¬
gravated form:
"Characters upon which the effect of
habitable regions on people depends:
whether high or low-lying; type of adjoining
country, whether open or sheltered; state of
soil; whether the water is plentiful or scarce,
stagnant or flowing; local factors, trees,
mines, cemeteries, putrescent pools, etc. "
Finally, it is perhaps somewhat surprising
to' find a physician of the year 1000 AD giv¬
ing careful instructions about the hygienic
precautions to be taken before operations, a
matter which was generally treated very
lightly as late as the 19th century:
"The greatest care must be taken during
surgical operations to prevent infection,
because a wound can only be treated in the
absence of infection. Should infection or
contusion occur, it will accumulate at the
wound which will suppurate, making
surgical intervention impossible until it has
been treated. If the blood in a wound
becomes infected it must be got rid of as
quickly as possible. "
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
AVICENNA AND THE LOVESICK YOUTH
In this 15th-century miniature, Avicenna is seen at the bedside of an
ailing young nobleman. It illustrates an incident in Avicenna's life
which reveals that he was no less aware than modern physicians of
the psychosomatic nature of certain illnesses.
For many months a young nobleman lay sick unto death of a
strange malady against which the potions and cures proposed by
the learned doctors called in to treat him were of no avail. In
despair, his relatives summoned to his bedside the most famous
doctor in the land. When Avicenna (for he it was) arrived, he
examined the ailing youth briefly and then asked to be left alone
with him. Holding the patient's pulse he said: "Tell me, my son,
about yourself, your life, your relations with your family, your plans
for the future." "I am very ill and like to die", was all the youth's
reply. "Do not upset yourself like this, you will surely live", replied
Avicenna. "Tell me, what think you of women?" And, feeling the
youth's pulse quicken, he went on: "Has your heart never been
captivated by a woman's beauty?" "No, no", exclaimed the youth
hotly. "Why do you say 'No' to me", said Avicenna, "When your
whole body cries out the answer 'Yes'? What is the maiden's
name?" Finally, after a long silence, the young man spluttered out
the name of his beloved. Avicenna summoned his parents and
announced solemnly: "The patient is suffering from an incurable
disease. He is lovesick and fears to tell you of the woman who has
won his heart. There is but one cure marriage". Some days later,
after the wedding festivities were over, Avicenna returned home,
leaving the young nobleman in the care of his new wife and fully
restored in mind and body.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Al-Shifa:
the world %\ in a book
o
2?
AVICENNA (Ibn Sina) is rightly
considered the most important repre¬
sentative of Muslim philosophy.
Al-Kindi and al-Farabi laid the groundwork
of this philosophy and established its prin¬
ciples, but it was thanks to Avicenna and his
clear expositions that it acquired its final
form and distinguished itself from other
philosophies.
Today no one can deny that a Muslim
philosophy exists. It is neither purely
Aristotelian nor purely Platonic. It is a
separate philosophy created by special cir¬
cumstances and by a specific environment.
It was influenced by ancient philosophies,
borrowing certain elements from them but
also incorporating others of its own. It has
thus become, in its own right, an inde¬
pendent phase in the development of
human thought.
It took up all the important philosophic
issues and dealt with them in an original
way. It laid great stress on the study of be¬
ing, analysing the one and the many and
20
by Ibrahim Madkur
defining their interrelations. It delved deeply
into the problem of knowledge,
distinguishing between soul and intellect,
the innate and the acquired, truth and
falsehood. It decisively established the
theory of virtue and happiness; it created a
hierarchy of values and then classified them,
thus arriving at the "virtue of virtues" per¬
manent contemplation attained by the
prophets and other exceptional people. It
made a careful study of all the various parts
of philosophy, whether speculative or prac¬
tical mathematics, metaphysics,
ethics, economics and politics adding to
these medicine, biology, chemistry, botany,
astronomy and music, all of which were
regarded as parts of philosophy in the
widest sense.
Assuming this to be the essence of
Muslim i.e. Avicenna's philosophy, the
Shifa, is, among all his works, the one
which expresses it best. In the Shifa, he ex¬
pounds philosophical problems in detail,
analysing them clearly and adding to therr>
certain branches of knowledge considered
at the time as an integral part of philosophy.
The work introduces ideas deriving from
Aristotle, Plato, Plotinus, Zeno and Chrysip-
pus, but presents them in such a way that
they form an organic whole. Therein lies
Avicenna's originality which appears even
more striking when he criticizes and either
refutes or defends the views of the
Ancients.
Avicenna himself described the object of
this great work: "My aim is to include in it all
the fruits of the sciences of the Ancients,
which I have checked and which are based
on outright deduction or induction as ac- I
IBRAHIM BAYUMI MADKUR, of Egypt is
president of the Academy of the Arabic Lan¬
guage, Cairo, and a distinguished scholar who
has specialized in Islamic philosophy, notably the
work of Avicenna. He is the author of several
studies on the age of A vicenna and has taken part
in many symposia devoted to the memory of the
great philosopher. This article is based on his
famous study Introduction to the Shifa.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
*S»^W/i^Ä
k V
/
«euras
y
' 'if - '"/M¡
v
Avicenna's Treatise on Terms
is a dictionary of the
principal philosophical
notions such as akl (reason),
nafs (the soul), jawhar
(substance), makan (space),
and haraka (movement). Left,
a page from a 14th-century
manuscript of the treatise,
which is an irreplaceable
source for understanding the
complex terminology of
Medieval Oriental philosophy.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
It is difficult to make anyone believe
that a person like me is an unbeliever.
My faith in God is unshakable. If I am
an infidel, then there is nota single true
Muslim on earth. Avicenna
cepted by thinkers who have long sought
'the truth. I have tried to incorporate as
much as possible of the entire field of
philosophy." He adds: "I have omitted
nothing that is of any value in the works of
the Ancients. If any element is not found in
its usual place or context, that is because I
have put it in a place which I considered
more appropriate."
In fact, the book contains such a wealth
of subject-matter that it is quite unique, and
unlike any other work of philosophy. It is
divided into four major "Summae" (juman:
Logic, Physics, Mathematics and
Metaphysics. Each "Summa" in turn is
divided into books (funun), each book into
sections (magala) and each section into
chapters (fusul). This is the general plan of
the work, but within each division and sub¬
division there are various subordinate
sciences and objects of study.
The Shifa is in fact an encyclopaedia in
which all the rational sciences have been
gathered together, predating our modern
encyclopaedias by six centuries. The
modern works, of course, deal with very
many more subjects, but the Shifa does
cover the whole range of the rational
sciences as they existed at the time. The
most surprising thing of all is that it is the
work of one man, whereas modern en¬
cyclopaedias, from Diderot onwards, have
been produced by large teams of
contributors.
Though its author lacked the peace and
quiet necessary for a work of such
God is the depth and the surface. He is
manifest everywhere and in all things.
Avicenna
magnitude, he succeeded in producing a
remarkably well-ordered and logically set-
out book. The work, begun in Hamadhan,
was completed in Isfahan within a span of
about ten years. Ibn Sina was forty and in
his intellectual prime when he started the
Shifa. By the time he finished it he was
already past fifty.
Thus the Shifa is not, as was long
thought, a commentary on Aristotle, like
those of Averroës or St. Thomas Aquinas.
Avicenna included in it the results of his own
wide-ranging research and theorizing; ac¬
cepting certain views and rejecting others.
Sometimes he borrows ideas from other
authors and discusses them, but without
mentioning their names or quoting his
sources.
The best description of the book is to be
found in the author's own introduction:
"This book," he writes, "ultimately presents
all the ideas unanimously accepted by prac¬
tically every thinker. Instead of indulging in
personal prejudice, I have done my best to
include in it the greater part of philosophy,
raising objections on each point, then at¬
tempting to disprove them, and showing the
truth as far as possible. I have taken care to
mention the main principles together with
their corollaries, leaving out, however,
anything that seemed to me to be clear from
22
what had gone before or anything that
happened to slip my memory."
This introduction does not seem to have
been available to the Christian thinkers of
the Middle Ages or, if it was, it escaped their
attention. In any case they did not study the
Shifa in sufficient detail to realize that it was
not a mere commentary or gloss on
Aristotle, but an original work in its own
right.
Avicenna made the best use of the wealth
of knowledge available in his time. If one
book can be said to reflect the period in
which it was written, the Shifa is un¬
doubtedly the best source of information on
the intellectual life of the fourth century of
the Hegira.
Scholars who have studied this period
rightly consider it to be the Golden Age of
rational studies in Islam. A school (the
Kalam) for interpreting the Koran was set up
under Ash'ari, and its activities were reg¬
arded as constituting a branch of science.
Mysticism was also following new paths: it
went beyond asceticism and hermitism and
embarked on the explanation of states of
the soul; it analysed minutely the stages of
"initiation"; it claimed to attain union
with God. Muslim philosophy was laying
down its foundations and establishing its
principles: al-Farabi, a profound and
penetrating thinker, organized its various
parts.
Islamic medicine reached its zenith with
the work of the great physician al-Razi
(Rhazes), and no longer confined itself to
repeating the dicta of Hippocrates and
Galen: al-Razi actually made use of his own
experience. And mathematics and
astronomy were making great strides: one
need only mention here the name of al-
Biruni from among a phalanx of renowned
scholars and scientists.
It is generally true to say that while in the
second and third centuries of the Hegira
Islamic scholars concentrated mainly on
translating and assimilating foreign
sciences, in the fourth century they launch¬
ed into research in their own right, moving
from assimilation to original creation.
Usually a book's influence is restricted to
that of its author and it belongs only within
the range of that author's work. But there
are some books which are special and have a
history and influence of their own. Avicen¬
na's philosophy was the philosophy of the
whole Arab world from the fifth century to
the beginning of the fourteenth century of
the Hegira: all authors, philosophers,
If I had made no impact on men's
hearts, they would have ignored me.
They would have been neither for me
nor against me. Avicenna
theologians and mystics, of all schools of
thought, drew upon it. During this time,
even scientific studies in medicine, biology,
astronomy and mathematics used it as a
base. Avicenna is the Philosopher of Islam,
par excellence.
It is true that al-Ghazali's attack on
philosophy and the "falasifa" [philosophers!
turned many scholars away from Avicenna.
But this did not put an end to his influence.
It can be said that such philosophy as sur¬
vived in Islamic culture certainly owes its ex¬
istence to him. The Spanish school of
philosophy which developed later never
CONTINUED PAGE 28
Tt
Colour pages
Page 23
The unifying perspective of Islamic
science, in which all forms of
knowledge are interdependent,
found brilliant expression in
Avicenna with his encyclopaedic
mind, voracious appetite for
learning, and determination to
organize his thought in a logical,
systematic way. One of his
accomplishments in the natural
sciences was in mineralogy where
his descriptions and classification
of metals and minerals and his
theories on their origins became a
major source of geological
knowledge in the Islamic world as
well as in Christian Europe until the
Renaissance. Above left, an
illustration from an 18th-century
Persian manuscript on mineralogy.
Muslim ophthalmologists in
Avicenna's time were leaders in
their field and their knowledge was
transmitted both westwards into
Europe and eastwards into India.
Avicenna's own highly influential
treatise on the subject not only
discusses the anatomy of the eye
and the principles of vision but
gives his readers practical, down-
to-earth tips on how to prevent
their sight from failing. Above
right, detail from a sixteenth-
century ophthalmologics! treatise
now in the library of Istanbul
University. Below, decorative
brickwork in the Friday mosque at
Kerman, Iran, shows how geometry
can be used in Islamic art and
architecture to express the
cherished idea which presides over
Avicenna's towering achievements
as a thinker: the emanation of
Multiplicity from Unity and the
return of Multiplicity to Unity the
Presence of the One in the Many.
Photos Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris
Photo © Roland Michaud, Paris
Page 24
Above, twelfth-century map
showing North Africa and Europe
as envisioned by the great
Moroccan cartographer al-ldrisi at a
time when the influence of
Avicenna's ideas was spreading
throughout the Islamic world and
Christendom. According to a
convention which is unique to
Arab-Islamic cartography, the south
is at the top of the map.
Below, fifteenth-century miniature
showing the French surgeon Guy de
Chauliac (1300-1368) receiving his
patients. One of the most learned
men of his time, Chauliac studied
at Montpellier University, where
Avicenna's theories were the
cornerstone of the medical syllabus
from the 12th to the 16th century.
Chauliac was an ardent defender of
Avicenna's ideas and in his writings
cited the Master over 600 times.
Photo © Jean-Loup Charmet, Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
£) ¡Mb; fsJfj*£/*X
b
f
4 -
\
mê
©*"
tU
^$>
«r**'*
W
<gfccS£^
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
A-
> /*
V
,;'
\*
v+¿-
*>*m%Ji
- 1 *
^«
.* »SKä
:
<
' :
r. - -
i
.-
«v.¿
-*-"/*
¿
V.
rjrt
w ÄV&
*3
&
ry..:
^
f
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
sa*/4
kfelíJRi
'r^JJû^'t^f^
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Colour pages
Page 25
In the Shifa and other works
Avicenna went deeply into the
theory of music, which he
defined as "a mathematical
science in which there is
discussed the state of melody
insofar as it is in harmony or in
discord and the state of the
intervening periods". According
to a tradition going back to
Pythagorean times music was
considered as an integral part of
science, and as George Sarton
writes in his Introduction to the
History of Science, "music
could be more easily transmitted
by popular contact than almost
any other activity, and practical
music would be followed,
sooner or later, by theoretical
music. Thus did it come to pass
that Muslim science penetrated
Christendom at least partly upon
the wings of music." This very
rare illuminated manuscript was
produced in Spain or Morocco
in the early 13th century. It
shows a scene from the story of
Bayad and Riyad in which the
lover Bayad sings of his woes to
a noble lady and her attendants.
Photo © Biblioteca Apostólica Vaticana
Page 26
This detail from a 17th-century
Persian manuscript in the
Islamic Museum, Cairo, shows a
figure purported to be Avicenna
teaching a group of students. In
addition to the astonishing gifts
and scintillating mind which
fascinated his contemporaries
Avicenna also seems to have
possessed striking good looks
and an impressive figure. A
description of him attending
court at Isfahan in the closing
years of his life relates how,
wearing a long robe and a
turban of coarse cloth, "he used
to sit very close to the Amir,
whose face became radiant with
delight as he marvelled at his
good looks and accomplishment
and wit. And when he spoke all
those present listened
attentively, none uttering a
word."
SONG OF THE SOUL
It descended upon thee from out of the regions above,
That exalted, ineffable, glorious, heavenly Dove.
'Twas concealed from the eyes of all those who its nature
would ken, _
Yet it wears not a veil, and is ever apparent to men.
Unwilling it sought thee and joined thee, and yet, though it
grieve.
It is like to be still more unwilling thy body to feave^
It resisted and struggled, and would not be tamed in haste,
Yet it joined thee, and slowly grew used to this desolate
waste.
It weeps, when it thinks of its home and the peace it
possessed.
With tears welling forth from its eyes without pausing
or rest,
And with plaintive mourning it broodeth like one bereft
O'er such trace of its home as the fourfold winds have left.
Thick nets detain it, and strong is the cage whereby
It is held from seeking the lofty and spacious sky.
Until, when the hour of its homeward flight draws near,
And 'tis time for it to return to its ampler sphere.
It carols with joy, for the veil is raised, and it spies^
Such things as cannot be witnessed by waking eyes.
On a lofty height doth it warble its songs of praise.
(For even the lowliest being doth know/edge raise.)^
Now why from its perch on high was it cast like thls~
To the lowest Nadir's gloomy and drear abyss?
Was it God who cast it forth for some purpose wise,
Concealed from the keenest seeker's inquiring eyes?
Then is its descent a discipline wise but stern,
That the things that it hath not heard it thus may learn.
(Extract from one of Avicenna's most famous poems.
Translation Professor £ G. Browne)
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 22
lessened Avicenna's prestige in the East
despite the relatively large number and im¬
portance of its representatives, in particular
the prolific Averroës. The fate of this school
was linked to that of Spain itself and it is not
surprising that Averroës' influence should
have been stronger in the Latin West than in
the East.
Avicenna's books continued to be studied
after his death. The Najat and Isharat were
particularly popular, but the Shifa retained
its attraction: it contains many details not to
be found in the two other works, and
scholars wishing to go more deeply into
their subject found they needed to refer to
its lengthy explanations. When, for exam¬
ple, al-Ghazali, in the Tahafot al-Falasifa,
and Shahrastani, in the Nihayat al-lqdam,
discuss in some detail the creation of the
world and the impossibility of its eternity,
the ideas they attribute to Ibn Sina were bor¬
rowed mainly from the Shifa.
Ibn Rushd (Averroës) often quotes ex¬
tracts from the Shifa either to support his
own theories or to contradict Avicenna,
mentioning his name on each occasion.
Nasir al-Din al-Tusi was one of Avicenna's
faithful disciples in spite of the fact that he
lived two hundred years later: his attitude
towards Fakhr al-Din al-Razi and the fight he
waged against him are well known. Similarly
Ibn Khaldun recognized the importance of
the Shifa which he mentions several times in
his Prolegomena.
Three treatises have dominated Muslim
theological studies in the last few centuries:
al-Aqa'id by Nasafi, Iji's Mawaqif and the
Maqasid of Taftazani. If we examine their
content and the commentaries that have
been written on them, we can see that they
made extensive use of the Shifa.
In Logic, the general tendency of scholars
to be as succinct as possible led to works
such as Abhari's Isagoge, Qazwini's Sham-
siyya and Akhadari's Sullam which have
dominated the teaching of Logic in the
Islamic world for the last six hundred years.
One book, however, published during this
period, the Basa'ir al-nasiriyya, recalls the
breadth and clarity of the Shifa's logic. Its
author states that he has drawn some of his
ideas from Ibn Sina, whom he describes as
the "best of the moderns".
Few works, at any period, have exercised
a greater influence than the Shifa on human
thought. In this, Avicenna's masterwork,
the duality of his personality is revealed:
received influence and personal reaction,
assimilation and original contribution.
Ibrahim Madkur
A champion of the rationalist
and scientific spirit, Avicenna
relentlessly attacked the
obscurantist ideas of his time.
To support his rejection of
alchemy he used philosophical
as well as scientific arguments
to show that the then widely
held belief in the transmutation
of metals was untenable.
Illustration is taken from an
Arabic version, produced in
13th-century Baghdad, of the
Materia Medica written by the
Greek physician Dioscorides in
the Ist century AD.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A philosopher
under fire
Avicenna's doctrines stirred up controversy
in his own time and later
by Reza Davari
THE philosophical works of Avicenna
(Ibn Sina) were violently criticized
both during his own lifetime and after
his death. Two major accusations were
levelled against him: atheism and heresy on
the one hand and a lack of originality on the
other.
Some of his opponents stressed con¬
tradictions between his thought and the
teachings of the Koran, while others regard¬
ed him as a mere compiler. And one gathers
from Avicenna's own writings that at a cer¬
tain period of his life he was ostracized
because of his ideas.
Among his most disparaging critics were
the theologian and philosopher Fakhr al-Din
al-Razi (1149 or 1150-1209) and the
'philosopher al-Ghazali (1058-1111) also
known as Algazel. But the strongest attacks
came from contemporary theologians.
In modern times, a few scholars have
challenged the originality of Avicenna's
work. Some have compared it to that of
Ferdowsi (c. 930-1020) and al-Biruni
(973-1048) in astronomy and the natural
sciences, and of al-Razi (c. 865-923) in
medicine, concluding in each case that
Avicenna's contribution was inferior. Other
critics even maintained that as a philosopher
Avicenna had merely revived and expanded
on the ideas of his illustrious predecessor al-
Farabi without making any substantial con¬
tribution of his own.
The first question one may therefore ask
is whether Avicenna was an innovator in
philosophy or a mere compiler. Al-Farabi
(872-950) was undoubtedly the founder of
Islamic philosophy. But his general views
mainly reflect fundamental principles
prevailing during the first centuries of the
Islamic era. It is therefore likely that if al-
Farabi had not existed, Avicenna would
have reached the same conclusions. For
ideas are not generated spontaneously by
men; men are dependent upon the ways of
thinking of their time.
In fact, the originality of al-Farabi himself k
has been the subject of long controversies, f
REZA DAVARI, of Iran, is professor of philo¬
sophy and dean of the arts faculty at the Univer¬
sity of Teheran. He is also the secretary of the Ira¬
nian National Commission for Unesco and the
author of many studies on philosophical and cul¬
tural subjects.
Built at Gurganj by the ruler of Khorezm, the Khorezm-Shah Tekish, who came to power
towards the end of the 12th century AD, this mausoleum is one of the rare buildings to
have survived that troubled period. Avicenna's stay at Gurganj was short but pleasant. He
was befriended by the vizier Abu-I Husayn as-Soheili and joined the circle of brilliant
scholars, which included the famous al-Biruni. at the court of the Emir of Gurganj.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Avicenna and al-Farabi
(872-950) were not
only great
philosophers they
both made valuable
contributions to the
advancement of the
theory of music. Al-
Farabi's Grand Book
of Music has been the
subject of a modern
study and Avicenna
devoted the last
chapter of his Book
of Healing to music.
Both men gave
descriptions of the
tambura, a lute-like
musical instrument
popular in their day.
Left, a Tadzhik, four-
string tambura in
mulberry wood, made
at the beginning of
this century and
modelled on the
ancient instruments
of Khorasan.
Photo © Academy of Sciences
of the Tadzhik SSR, Dushanbe
Seven years Avicenna's senior, al-Biruni was one of the great figures
who mark a high point of Islamic culture. The two men had a famous
confrontation at which al-Biruni questioned Avicenna about Aristotle's
study De Cáelo (On the Heavens). The drawing above was made by al-
Biruni to illustrate the view expressed by Avicenna concerning the
disposition of the four elements (earth, air, fire and water) between the
earth and the moon.
Photo © Anderson - Giraudon, Paris
Left, detail from the
School of Athens,
one of four frescoes
painted by the great
Italian artist Raphael
in the Stanza della
Segnatura, in the
papal apartments of
the Vatican. In the
centre can be seen
Aristotle and Plato,
two towering figures
of the Athenian
school of philosophy,
by whom Avicenna
was profoundly
influenced.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Averroës (Ibn Rushd), Ibn Khaldun and their
contemporaries accused him, as they accus¬
ed Avicenna, of amalgamating philosophy
and religion. But here criticism comes from
two diametrically opposed camps. While al-
Ghazali and Fakhr al-Din al-Razi stigmatize
the philosophers for views which they con¬
sider incompatible with religious teaching,
and go as far as to label them heretics,
Averroës and Ibn Khaldun regard
philosophy and religion as two separate
paths both leading to the same goal.
Al-Farabi and Avicenna were convinced,
however, that their ideas were in line with
religious thought. They conceived true
religion as a philosophy and maintained that
philosophy was the heart of religion. Like al-
Farabi, Avicenna used philosophy to inter¬
pret certain verses of the Koran. He con¬
sidered philosophy central to Sufism, an
idea which he discusses at length in the final
chapter of his work Isharat wa Tanbihat.
During the nineteenth century, Shi'ite
thinkers and scholars in Iran revived the idea
of the separateness of religion and
philosophy, which Averroës had so pas¬
sionately defended. But, whereas Averroës
gave pride of place to philosophy, the
Iranian scholars' main concern was to
defend religion. "Greek philosophy... but
for how long?" they asked, echoing the
Bahai Sheikh. "Study also the philosophy of
the believers."
To sum up, what some consider a heresy
and others a mixture of Greek ideals and the
fundamentals of religion forms the very
essence of Islamic philosophy. But this
philosophy is far from being a mere copy of
Greek thought, though it has certainly
drawn inspiration from it. If Averroës, for
example, had confined himself to inter¬
preting Aristotle, his name would never
have been remembered in the history of
human thought.
An anecdote related by Avicenna himself
illustrates this point. Avicenna read Aristo¬
tle's Metaphysics forty times, but it was only
with the aid of al-Farabi's commentary on
the Metaphysics, the De Interpretatione,
that he finally succeeded in overcoming the
difficulties he found in the text. Al-Farabi's
true merit, according to Avicenna, was that
he started the process of incorporating
Greek philosophy into the Muslim view of
the world. Al-Farabi served as a link bet¬
ween Aristotle and Avicenna by drawing
together the ideas of the first and the value
system of the second.
We lack detailed information about the
subjects which made it hard for Avicenna to
understand the Metaphysics, and therefore
cannot give precise opinions on the matter.
It is very likely, however, that his main dif¬
ficulty lay in commenting on Aristotle's key
ideas, in the context of a philosophy fun¬
damentally based on the belief in the ex¬
istence of God.
This anecdote about Avicenna's dif¬
ficulties also illustrates the dual relationship
between Greek and Islamic philosophy: on
the one hand, the first exerted an influence
on the second, and on the other, there was
a contradiction between their respective
views of the universe. If Avicenna
distinguishes between the possibility of ex¬
istence and essence (entity), it is because he
attributes objects to the Supreme Being
who, for him, is the first cause of all being.
The existence of objects is not the same as
Aristotle's God seen as final cause and pure
thought. But it represents science, will,
power and life... The Supreme Being is the
vital force in all beings. Everything that ex¬
ists or will exist is part of His knowledge.
Since these differences in attitude on ex¬
istence and the meaning of causality led to
the creation of new schools of philosophy, it
is clear that Avicenna's philosophy and that
of the Ancient Greeks differed not merely in
detail, but rather on fundamental principles.
Before Avicenna, al-Farabi had rated
revelation and prophecy with wisdom. He
had come to the conclusion that a prophet
attains active wisdom through thought and
that revelation is to be found in the associa¬
tion of active wisdom and thought.
Avicenna more or less agrees with al-
Farabi except that, for him, prophecy and
the message rank above all else in the
perfection of man. When he finds himself
unable to expound a religious topic, he ad¬
mits his own imperfection and falls back on
interpretation of the Koran or the Prophet.
Since he is incapable of explaining the resur¬
rection of the body, he maintains that he
follows the Prophet in this matter. And, like
al-Farabi, he believes that the social order
should conform to the religious order, and
that the Prophet is the chief of the Medina.
In all his philosophical writings Avicenna
sought to achieve a synthesis between
philosophy and mysticism, rationalism and
spiritualism. After an encounter with the
mystic Abu Said Abu Khevi, he is said to
have stated: "All that Abu Said sees, I
know." And Abu Said answered: "All that
Abu Ali (Avicenna) knows, I see."
Reza Davari
if$&*(*$
The Persian poet
Ferdowsi (930-1020
AD) was another of
the great
contemporaries of
Avicenna, who was
an avid reader of
Ferdowsi's epic
masterpiece the
Shah-Nama or Book
of Kings. Left,
illustration dating
from 1556 AD by the
artist Mohammed
Murad Samarkand!
for an episode in the
Shah-Nama, the
"Marriage of the Son
of Feridun". Avicenna
was also an
accomplished poet,
but some of his
detractors, somewhat
unfairly, drew
unfavourable
comparisons between
his poetry and that of
Ferdowsi.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
How Ibn Sina became Avicenna
Transmitted to Europe, his writings sparked off an intellectual revival
by Salvador Gómez Nogales
IT would be inconceivable to celebrate
the thousandth anniversary of Avi¬
cenna's birth (in the Christian calendar)
without examining the debt Westerners owe
to this great Oriental genius.
The influence of Avicenna in the West was
immense, giving birth to an intellectual move¬
ment, "Latin Avicennism", which bore his
name. This influence made itself felt in three
major areas: philosophy, the sciences
(especially medicine), and literature.
In philosophy, Avicenna dealt with all the
branches of Aristotelian enquiry: logic,
physics and psychology, metaphysics,
ethics, economics and politics, philosophy
and religion. He was also one of the great
theorists of mysticism.
In the sciences he influenced posterity in
almost every field in which he worked. From
medicine, mathematics, astronomy, alchemy
and astrology, to geology and geography,
mineralogy, herbalism, zoology and the
natural sciences, there is hardly an area into
which he ventured without whetting the
curiosity of later scientists.
Avicenna's artistic sensitivity can be felt in
his scientific and philosophical works, above
all in his mystic treatises. He also authored
several didactic poems on logic and medicine
which found an echo in the work of later
thinkers, including men of such stature as the
Cordobán philosopher and scientist Averroës
(Ibn Rushd) (1126-1198).
Another accomplishment of Avicenna the
artist and humanist was in music, where his
writings would leave a mark on the work of
later theoreticians.
As for his influence in the Arab-speaking
West, that is Muslim Spain or al-Andalus
(Andalusia), it has to be admitted that An¬
dalusian thinkers, with very few exceptions
and for reasons that remain obscure, were in¬
itially extemely hostile to Avicenna.
We do not know exactly when Avicenna's
thought reached Muslim Andalusia, but the
first person to be acquainted with it there was
the great Spanish thinker Ibn Hazm, who
died in 1064 AD, and was more or less a con¬
temporary of Avicenna. Ibn Hazm never
travelled to the East, but according to the
modern Spanish historian Asin Palacios, he
studied the works of Oriental writers in the
libraries of Andalusia.
But convincing evidence- of Avicenna's
direct influence in Muslim Andalusia does not
appear until the twelfth century with Ibn
Tufayl (d. 1185) whose familiarity with the
SALVADOR GOMEZ NOGALES, of Spain, is
professor of Arabic metaphysics and philosophy
at the philosophy faculty of Alcalá de Henares
and at Madrid's "Comillas" University. He also
directs the seminar on Arab philosophy at Spain's
Institute of Hispano-Arab Culture. Vice-President
of the International Society for the Study of
Medieval Philosophy and a member of the Aristo¬
telian Society (UK), he is the author of over a
hundred scholarly publications.
great thinker's work suggests that Avicenna
was by then known to Andalusian scholars.
Ibn Tufayl knew that Avicenna's Shifa
(Book of Healing) was remarkable for its
commentary on the works of Aristotle, and
that Avicenna had written another original
work [The Philosophy of the Easterners) in
the tradition of the Neo-Platonists, in which
he parted company with Aristotle. He was
also aware that not everything in the Shifa
originated with Aristotle. This is an impor¬
tant detail, not only because of the familiari¬
ty with Avicenna's work which it presup¬
poses but because it explains why Averroës
would later show hostility to Avicenna.
Ibn Tufayl was also familiar with Avicen¬
na's treatises on mysticism, and it was in
furtherance of this non-Aristotelian, esoteric
aspect of the philosopher's work that Ibn
Tufayl wrote the philosophical novel on
which his reputation rests, The Self-Taught
Philosopher. Both the novel's Arabic title,
Hayy ibn Yaqzan, and its two main
characters, Absal and Salaman, are taken
from Avicenna.
And so the evidence tends to show that
Andalusians were familiar with Avicenna's
works by the middle of the twelfth century.
The relations between Avicenna and
Averroës fall into a category of their own.
Divergences between the two far out¬
number the points on which they agree, and
Averroës fiercely attacks Avicenna at every
possible opportunity.
There were two main reasons for
Averroës's aversion. The first of them,
Photo © Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Pans
then relatively common among Islamic
philosophers, was the hostility he felt
towards the Mutakallimun (theologians who
philosophized about the articles of the
Islamic faith) from whom, according to
Averroës, Avicenna derived some of the
proofs which made him break with Aristotle.
The second reason, which may have ir¬
ritated Averroës even more because it seem:
ed to be more fundamental, was that by
blending certain Neo-Platonist and
Aristotelian theses Avicenna had
adulterated Aristotelianism. Perhaps the
most flagrant example of this is Avicenna's
espousal of the Neo-Platonist principle that
the One can proceed only out of the One.
When Averroës, concurring with the
Islamic theologian and philosopher Al-
Ghazali (1058-1111), refutes Avicenna's
proofs, the arguments he uses to defend
philosophy are simple: Avicenna's proofs
are not those of Aristotle, nor do they derive
from any of the classical philosophers.
Hence it is Avicenna who is at fault and not
philosophy, as Al-Ghazali had argued. Thus
the thread running through Averroës's
philosophy, insofar as it constitutes a reply
to Avicenna, is a return to pure
Aristotelianism, eschewing the mystical
adulterations which had been introduced by
Al-Farabi (872-950) and by Avicenna
himself.
But in one field medicine Averroës
does accept Avicenna's superiority, and his
admiration is evident in his commentaries.
For just as Averroës is recognized as Avicen- k
na's equal or superior in philosophy, in f
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Between the 8th and the 15th
century an Arab civilization
took shape on the Iberian
peninsula which had a far-
reaching influence, above all in
the Christian West. At times
the confines of Muslim Spain
* (al-Andalus as it was known in
Arabic) stretched over the
greater part of the peninsula.
For much of the period
Córdoba was the main centre
of this blossoming culture: it
grew to be the biggest city in
the West, with a population of
250,000; it boasted a university,
a magnificent mosque (right,
the ceiling of the antechamber
to the mihrab, the room
indicating the direction of
Mecca); its cultural and
commercial life was intensely
active. It was the birthplace of
great writers and philosophers
such as Ibn Tufayl, Averroës
and Maimonides, who
transmitted to Europe the
learning which reached them
from the Orient, including the
scientific and philosophical
writings of Avicenna. Apart
from the Great Mosque of
Córdoba, al-Andalus produced
other famous monuments such
as the Alhambra of Granada,
the Giralda and Alcázar of
Seville, and the Aljaferia
palace at Saragossa. Their
influence on the Christian
architecture of the Iberian
peninsula and beyond was
striking, and can be seen (below)
in these arches in the cloister
of San Juan de Duero, at Soria.
Below left, 10th to 11th-century
Persian ceramic with Kufic inscription.
Photo © Mas, Barcelona
4
ÖIM»
Í ,
5?
w&
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
, medicine it is acknowledged that Avicenna
outranks him and that Avicenna's influence
on posterity was far greater.
By the second half of the twelfth century,
Avicenna's intellectual citizenship was so
well established in Muslim Andalusia that it
began to alarm the religious authorities. This
concern is reflected in the couplets of the
Valencian Ibn Yubayr (1145-1217), who
complained of the emergence of a sect
whose intellectual leaders were Al-Farabi
and Avicenna. Ibn Yubayr claimed that this
sect was exlusively concerned with inanities
and substituted the false wisdom of
philosophy for the true wisdom of religion.
As for Avicenna's mystic doctrines, they
reached Muslim Spain indirectly, through
the work of Oriental mystics such as al-
Ghazali and Suhrawardi, who were influenc¬
ed by him. But it has been established that
his mystical works were read also at first
hand by the Spanish Arabic-speaking
philosophers as well as by the mystics such
as Ibn Arabi of Murcia.
This is the point at which to trace the
spread of Avicenna's work through the Latin
West, noting especially how Spain acted as
a bridge in this process.
During the twelfth and thirteenth cen¬
turies, Spaniards produced many transla
tions from Arabic into Latin, and these were
republished on a large scale during the fif¬
teenth and sixteenth centuries. European
humanists and scientists formed such a high
opinion of the achievements of Arabic
science in Spain that many of- them
unhesitatingly classified as Spaniards cer¬
tain Oriental thinkers such as Avicenna, who
had never set foot on Spanish soil.
The modern historian of science George
Sarton considers Muslim Spain to be the
most important cultural centre of the Middle
Ages. Indeed, fifteenth century Europeans
were so dazzled by Andalusian culture that
many of them believed that the brilliance
came from Spain and not from the Orient.
This widespread error was not new: the
thirteenth-century Spanish bishop and
chronicler Lucas de Tuy, for example,
believed that Aristotle himself was Spanish.
Many thought that all the names in the Latin
translations were Spanish, and the Italians
of that time transformed Avicenna into a
Cordobán. It is interesting to note that the
great thinker's name, Ibn Sina in Arabic,
was immortalized in the West in the form
which it assumed in Muslim Andalusia.
The interest which the Arabs, and more
specifically Avicenna, aroused in the West
can be gauged from this flow of transla
tions. Specialists have underscored the ma¬
jor contribution of Spain to the translation
movement, often referring to the School of
Toledo. But important though it was,
Toledo was not alone in producing the
massive spate of translations. Translators
from all over the Iberian peninsula, working
alone or in groups, inundated the Western
world with Latin and Hebrew versions of
Arab texts.
Spain was thus the main conduit through
which Avicenna's work flowed into Europe,
at a moment, moreover, when his ideas
came as a windfall for medieval philosophy.
Scholasticism the system of Western
Christian philosophy that flourished from
the eleventh to the fifteenth century owed
its renewal to two movements in whose for¬
mation Avicenna was a key figure: the
transformation of Aristotelianism into a but¬
tress of religious thought, and the revival of
Augustinianism through direct contact with
Greek and Iranian Neo-Platonism.
All medieval European philosophers were
acquainted with Avicenna's work: they
either accepted his teachings or were engag¬
ed in refuting them. And even those who at¬
tempted to refute him assimilated at least
some of the values which imbued his
writings.
Detail from a 13th-century
engraving showing the great
Cordobán philosopher and
physician Averroës conversing
with Porphyry. Averroës
contested many of Avicenna's
philosophical ideas and took
issue with him on the respective
value of philosophy and religion.
Nonetheless his contribution to
the diffusion of Avicenna's work
in the West was considerable.
Right, cover of an Arabic edition of
Avicenna's Canon of Medicine
published in Rome in 1593. The
Canon was one of the first books to
be printed and published after
Gutenberg' s invention of movable type.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Medieval authors not only drew on him,
they made him one of the great authorities
for their doctrines, probably invoking his
name more often than that of any other
thinker except for St. Augustine, Aristotle,
Boethius and St. John of Damascus. So
preponderant did his influence become that
without him medieval philosophy would un¬
doubtedly have taken quite a different turn.
Very few of Aristotle's works were known
in the Latin West when the translations of
Avicenna began to pour into Europe. The
translations provided three things: a far
more complete understanding of Aristotle
than Christendom then possessed; a com¬
mentary on Aristotle's principal works; and
a philosophic codification of Aristotelian
problematics which offered a synthesis of
philosophy and religion.
The Arabs, and particularly Avicenna,
directly influenced Scholasticism not as a
variant of Greek Aristotelianism but by pro¬
viding original new perspectives. They exer¬
cised their influence not only on heterodox
philosophers but on the orthodox outlook of
the great Christian thinkers. So powerful
was their impact that the English theologian
and philosopher Roger Bacon (1214-1294)
could present Avicenna as one of the line of
the great prophets.
The Aristotelian aspects of Avicenna's in¬
fluence are felt most strongly in Thomism
(the philosophico-theological system of St.
Thomas Aquinas [1225-12741), in the
thought of the British theologian Duns
Scotus (1265-1308), and later in the work of
the sixteenth-century Spanish theologian
Francisco Suárez. This influence found its
way into the Dominican school through the
first original metaphysical synthesis of
Thomas of York (d. 1260). But Avicenna's
presence is most notable in the work of the
two main Dominican architects of Thomism,
St. Albertus Magnus (c. 1200-1280) and St.
Thomas Aquinas, and in that of their great
commentators, Tommaso de Vio, Cardinal
Cajetan (1468-1534) and John of St.
Thomas (1589-1644). In opposition to
Thomism is the Aristotelianism of the Fran¬
ciscan school, under the aegis of Duns
Scotus. It is interesting to note how both
Thomas Aquinas and Duns Scotus support
opposing doctrines by citing Avicenna.
But it is mainly in the Augustinian tradi¬
tion that a Latin Avicennism comes to light.
All of Avicenna's illuminative wisdom blends
perfectly with Augustinianism, giving it a
badly needed systematic framework.
Avicenna's influence on philosophy is by
no means confined to the Middle Ages. To
the extent that medieval Christian thought
has a place in modern philosophy and
theology, Avicennism still occupies the
place assigned to it by history.
There are two areas in which Avicenna's
thought still carries weight. First, his in¬
fluence is notable in modern subjectivism,
from Descartes to Kant. It is equally evident
in all the ontological proofs for the existence
of God, from Henry of Ghent to our own
times. Finally, in formal logic Avicenna was
eight centuries ahead of the West. It was
not until the Renaissance that arguments set
forth by Avicenna reappear.
This brings us to the second area in which
Avicenna influenced the West, namely that
of the sciences.
When Westerners look to Spain in search
of the splendours of Islamic culture, they are
actually looking for the "new science" of the
Arabs, which Avicenna undoubtedly per¬
sonifies. He was deeply interested in
mathematics, but as a philosopher rather
than as a technician, in the manner of a late
Neo-Platonist. He also produced many
works on astronomy and astronomical
observations. His astronomic teachings,
along with those of Averroës, were ex¬
pounded at the Universities of Bologna,
Padua and Ferrara.
CONTINUED PAGE 38
CMW8 *ti*An«* n«»*i.iti(.' ofußruhj
n .V««i nM
ROM AE,
In Typographia Mcdicea
M.D.XCIII.
fMm ly*yi>
1» I.T«»li/r 'tin' 75 '..
The "prince of physicians" is
seated in the professor's chair in
this engraving from a Latin
edition of the Canon dating
from 1520-1522.
	
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Five heirs of Avicenna
Avicenna occupies a central position in the history of
European thought. It was through his interpretations and
commentaries that the doctrines of the great thinkers of
Greco-Latin Antiquity such as Aristotle, Plato, and Plotinus
reached the thinkers of the medieval West. On this double
page we show portraits of five of the medieval "heirs" of the
great Islamic philosopher: 1) the Englishman Roger Bacon
(1214-1294), known to posterity as the doctor admirabais, is
depicted in this 19th-century engraving ; 2) his contemporary,
the Scottish theologian John Duns Scotus, one of the
founders of scholasticism; 4) the German Albertus Magnus
(13th century) in a miniature by Tommaso di Modena, and his
great pupil, the Italian theologian St. Thomas Aquinas (5) as
shown in a 15th-century painting by Benozzo Gozzoli; 6) the
English poet Geoffrey Chaucer (c. 1340-1400). Avicenna is
mentioned as essential reading for a physician in Chaucer's
Canterbury Tales. 3) Imaginary .portrait by Goya of the
Christian Father St. Augustine of Hippo (354-430).
St. Augustine's idea of "interior illumination" was to inspire a
current of medieval Christian thought which echoed some of
the mystic doctrines of Avicenna.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
fr» ,
I
B
» ß tractor -Ç(fc*fi&xr
T Sofmwnt -<jjuc uotwtmefrt am xxvmc ü'~2L%rg
I' -jpUvçw ÄCt* cd/*« Cfwfí <aT*9
^ftW^njMÍ« crvic f* Gen© « *t* f>n*U<F <p4f ffen *tm& -«/-en
<u|ucrvtf* <opre p tccfr«»t>m & ftrtnmif wyvn ftp ^W/Njuffr
jfie í¡»Whau** píj iutjce íof pnjM& ^tme outfe afto&i
X«6 j*M W TFwfkfna p* CTfttuf <JUc£ m*£iftr ÇW «UtoW
< * &»*« l^pm» o-Hc<w>nwF «£ maiaTr ípirûiui fcVrc&Mt-rtur
1ß JÍÍKP** ^^jtmf fe tvmp» -o Argon & ^^ho^ iKwÍfir
^Ermofrc«" ««cCC^<ow «$r«*:&»Mtf'ca><p<ccFettfte^,r»
ft* tM*a« ;(flX>*w $ot «ftnnc *>% <xmi -miíánunrMI
The famous school of translation at Toledo was one of the centres of
learning which brought Avicenna's work to a wider audience. At Toledo
the Canon was translated into Latin in the 12th century by the Italian
Gerard of Cremona, aided, as the Catalan scholar Joan Carreras i Martí
has pointed out, by Jewish and Muslim assistants. Parts of an early
translation of the Canon into Catalan have survived in a 14th-century
manuscript now in the Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Above, a page of
the manuscript, which consists of the section of Book Four dealing
with fevers and a fragment of Book one.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Left, the University of
Brussels, where
a course on Avicenna was
offered
as late as 1909.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 35
In Avicenna's time astronomy was related
to astrology, a subject for which the Arab
philosophers generally speaking showed lit¬
tle sympathy, and even less for the
alchemical elements derived from it. Never¬
theless, the introduction of Arabic alchemy
into the Latin world is an established
historical fact, and Avicenna played a crucial
role by imposing a more balanced attitude
among European thinkers faced with the
more fantastic and purportedly mystical
tendencies of other, less objective and less
responsible authors. He helped the West to
preserve a critical approach to the im¬
postures of alchemy. The second work on
alchemy to be translated from Arabic to
Latin was the relevant chapter of Avicenna's
Kitab, in the version produced by Alfred of
Sareshel around the middle of the twelfth
century.
In the Latin version of his authentic
treatise on alchemy and mineralogy, which
was often mistaken for the appendix to the
Fourth Book of Aristotle, he expounds a
theory which the more thoughtful Latin
authors would later take up. In this work,
Avicenna condemns alchemy, especially
where it concerns the transmutation of
minerals, thus flying in the face of the most
widely accepted notions of his time. He ad¬
mits only that skilled artisans working with
special tinctures can obtain from other
metals imitation gold and silver. But, in
Avicenna's view, the real transformation is
impossible and cannot be defended either
scientifically or philosophically. Avicenna's
views were cited in nearly all the treatises of
the thirteenth century, and later, in the Latin
world. The encyclopaedist Vincent de
Beauvais (d. 1264), while admitting the
possibility of transmutation, was sufficiently
influenced by Avicenna to express certain
reservations.
It is, on the other hand, generally forgot¬
ten that Avicenna was one of the main
sources of geological knowledge for the
Latin Middle Ages, the principal work 'of
reference being the Kitab al-Shifa in the
translation of Alfred of Sareshel. The
general principles of geology as understood
by the great encyclopaedists of the thir¬
teenth century, notably Vincent de Beauvais
and Albertus Magnus, are drawn principally
from Avicenna. When they explain the mo¬
tions of the sea, erosion, and the origins of
mountains, they are simply repeating
Avicenna's doctrines. Avicenna was prob¬
ably the Christian world's richest source in
herbalism and botany, as well.
Turning to zoology, wa are confronted
with this surprising statement by Sarton:
"The real fountainhead of Aristotelian
zoology. East and West, from the eleventh
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
century on was the Arabic summary of the
nineteen books by Ibn Sina. In a sense we
might even say that Ibn Sina was indirectly
the main fountainhead of medieval
zoology...".
To conclude this discussion of the
sciences, it should be pointed out that in its
Latin translation Avicenna's encyclopaedia
made many of the notions of Arab physics
familiar in the West. Avicenna was one of
those who transmitted to medieval physics
the Arabs' far-reaching studies of motion,
contact, force, vacuums, the infinite, light,
heat, the finite speed of light, and their in¬
vestigations of the specific gravity of bodies.
The theory of gravity and the tables of den¬
sities of both liquids and solids entered
Europe by way of the Arab world.
Avicenna's Canon was, for example, the
main source used by the Florentine physi¬
cian Dino del Garbo (d. 1327) for his work
On Weights and Measures, while Avicenna
was one of the new authorities cited by
Peter of Albano or Padua when he com¬
pleted his Liber compilations de
Physiognomia during his stay in Paris in
1295. Avicenna, like Averroës, also influenc¬
ed the medieval theory of colours.
But it is medicine that constitutes perhaps
the most brilliant chapter of Avicenna's life,
and one that made him until relatively
recently one of the great masters of Western
thought. His undisputed sway in this
discipline was based on two works, the
Canon and the Aryuza, a diadactic poem on
medicine (see article page 13). Still read to¬
day, the Canon was for seven centuries
regarded in the West as an authoritative
manual for instruction in and the practice of
medicine. Between 1150 and 1187 it was
translated in its entirety by Gerard of
Cremona. It was subsequently translated no
less than eighty-seven times, mostly into
Latin but often into Hebrew. All of these
translations were done in Spain, Italy (above
all Sicily), and the South of France.
It would be safe to say that Avicenna held
undisputed authority as long as medicine
was predominantly theoretical, and that his
influence waned with the coming of ex¬
perimental science.
The Canon gradually became the basis of
medical instruction in all universities. It was
part of the oldest recorded medical cur¬
riculum at the Faculty of Medicine in Mont¬
pellier, as established in a Bull of Clement V
dated 1309, and remained a part of the
Montpellier curriculum until 1557. True
enough, ten years later, preference shifted
to Galen, but Avicenna continued to be
taught there until the seventeenth century.
The fact that an Arabic edition of his work
was brought out in Rome in 1593 is some in¬
dication of the regard in which he was held.
At the outset, Arabic medicine was more
theoretical than practical, and it may be that
one of the shortcomings of Avicenna's in¬
fluence was that his theoretical brilliance
constituted an obstacle to practical research.
But this does not alter the fact that in ex¬
perimental surgery he served as guide to a
succession of brilliant practitioners.
Thus Guglielmo Saliceti (c. 1210-1277),
physician and surgeon of Piacenza, wrote a
general treatise on medicine whose title.
Summa conservation/s et curationis, is
reminiscent of Avicenna's great en¬
cyclopaedic work. Avicenna is among the
authors most frequently cited by him.
Medieval treatises on medicine often con¬
tained an introduction to anatomy. All of
them referred to and plagiarized the Cation
which was considered as the supreme
medical authority of the Christian world, just
as it was in the world of Islam.
In prophylaxis and pharmacology as well,
Avicenna was the Europeans' undisputed
master. Cardo of Milan, who practised in the
second half of the fourteenth century, wrote
a work entitled A Regimen for the Plague, in
which he summed up the prophylactic
techniques then in use. One of his principal
sources was Avicenna. At about the same
time, Franchischino de Collignano, a Floren¬
tine physician, wrote a treatise on the plague
in which he used Galen and Avicenna as his
main authorities. Another treatise. De
Venenis, is largely derived from Avicenna.
Traces of Avicenna's influence can also be
found in medieval European ophthal¬
mology. In an anonymous treatise on this
subject written in the second half of the thir¬
teenth century, Avicenna is the most fre¬
quently quoted author, and almost all the
ophthalmological works of fourteenth-
century Europe rely heavily on Arab sources,
and mainly on Avicenna.
In obstetrics and gynaecology too Avicen¬
na stands out as one of the great masters of
the Middle Ages. The highest praise that
could be bestowed on a doctor in medieval
times was to call him "another Avicenna". In
accordance with this practice, the Italian
physician Gentile da Foligno was styled "the
soul of Avicenna". Consulted by Cino da
Pistoia about the case of a seven-month
child, he wrote a treatise citing a number of
authoritative sources including Aristotle,
who had cited an instance of an eleven-
month baby, and Avicenna, who had
discussed that of a fourteen-month child. Da
Foligno also wrote a commentary on the
chapter of Avicenna's Canon relating to
fevers.
Avicenna's influence on Spanish authors
of this era and on earlier medieval writers
also extended to semiology or diagnosis
through external symptoms such as obser¬
vation of the pulse. Sarton believes that
Avicenna can be considered the founder of
semiology.
Finally, psychotherapy and para¬
psychology were another field in which
Avicenna was ahead of his time. When
medieval writers theorized about
psychological methods of healing they
illustrated their works with the most
spectacular cures which he achieved. The
Frenchman Nicole Oresme (c. 1323-1382),
one of the fourteenth century's greatest
scientists, .went along with Avicenna in
believing in thought transference, but re¬
jected his suggestion that human thought is
capable of moving objects without physical
contact.
But there inevitably came a moment when
Avicenna's influence as the great authority
in medicine went into decline. A reaction
against him set in during the Renaissance,
with the development of a tendency to go
directly to the Greek sources instead of us¬
ing Arabic intermediaries. Leonardo da Vinci
rejected Avicenna's notions of anatomy
(although the lack of an adequate
vocabulary forced him to continue using
Arabic terminology). The physician and
alchemist Paracelsus (c. 1490-1541) burned
the Canon in Basle in a public display of
repudiation. The Englishman William Harvey
dealt Avicenna's work a severe blow with
the publication in 1628 of what he con¬
sidered to be his great discovery, the circula¬
tion of the blood, which was unknown to
Avicenna.
What Harvey did not know was that this
discovery had been made four centuries
before, even preceding the Spanish
theologian Michael Servetus (15117-1553),
by the Arab Ibn al-Naphis (1210-1288), who
used Harvey's own argument concerning
the thickness of the wall separating the ven¬
tricles of the heart, in a critical commentary
on Avicenna's theory.
Little by little, philosophic and theoretical
medicine made way for the practical and ex¬
perimental medicine of modern times. Even
so, the University of Brussels continued to
offer a course on Avicenna's medicine until
1909.
Today it is possible to study medicine
without recourse to Avicenna's Arabic texts.
It is impossible, on the other hand, to ignore
the immense role of human thought,
Eastern as well as Western, over the cen¬
turies, and to forget the great debt that
European culture owes to Avicenna in
philosophy, mysticism, the natural sciences
and medicine.
Salvador Gómez Nogales
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
V
t'ív.''"f/
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
A forerunner
of modern science
by Abid S. Sadykov
BEYOND all question, Avicenna (Ibn
Sina), whose million-word encyclo¬
paedia the Canon of Medicine
remained the supreme medical reference
book for six centuries, can be considered
the greatest physician of all peoples, places
and times. Furthermore, his philosophical
encyclopaedia, the Book of Healing, and his
Book of Knowledge, a work written in Per¬
sian, place him among the world's foremost
thinkers. Indeed, so great is his renown as a
philosopher and a physician that it has tend¬
ed to overshadow his contribution to the
development of the natural sciences.
Yet Avicenna worked intensively on
physics, astronomy, mathematics and
mineralogy, and put forward a number of
productive ideas of great overall impact on
the natural sciences of his times, and which
remain topical even today. One such prob¬
lem, for instance, was that of movement
and the measurement of movement. In this
highly important branch of physics, he bas¬
ed his analysis on two concepts: the rapidity
and slowness of movement. He viewed
them quantitatively and qualitatively: "The
quantity between the start of that which
went before and the end of that which
follows is the measure of the rapidity or
slowness of movement".
"That which passes in a short time moves
quickly", he observed, and advanced the
theory that speed depends on what in
Left, this fearsome panther head
embellishes a bronze perfume phial
dating from the 11th century. Found at
Khulbuk in Tadzhikistan, the phial is
22.4 centimetres in height. On one side
is inscribed the name of the maker, Ali
Ibn Abu Nasr, and on the other an Arab
Ibn Abu Nasr, and on the other an Arab
maxim: "The occasion brings forth the man".
modern physics is termed "mass": "That
which is smaller should move more quickly,
and that which is larger more slowly; but in
reality, we see the reverse".
Avicenna distinguished between the
speed of light and of sound. "Thunder can
be seen and heard", he wrote. "Thunder
(lightning) is seen at one time, but heard at
another, after it (the sound) has moved in
the air and gradually reached the hearing".
In other words, he established the difference
in the speeds of the two forms of movement
of matter.
Avicenna was the first to formulate such
concepts as the "quantity of movement",
"motive force" and "impulse", which were
propounded in the mechanics of Western
Europe in the seventeenth and eighteenth
centuries. He heads the long list of scien¬
tists Huyghens, Leibnitz,
D'Alembert, Thomson, Kirchhoff and
others who worked on the problem of the
measurement of movement, although no-
one prior to Descartes, and subsequently
Leibnitz, treated it on a genuinely scientific
basis. Be that as it may, Avicenna's con¬
tribution should be noted in the recorded
history of physics.
To modern science, Avicenna's investiga¬
tion of the problem of the unity of space and
time is far from irrelevant. "Movement has
two quantities beside itself: one is the length
of its path..., the other quantity... is called
time". In other words, Avicenna sees space
and time as the quantities of movement.
Following Aristotle and a few later
thinkers, he denied the existence of a void,
advancing the theory that neither movement
nor repose can exist in a void. He adduced
that "in a void there can be neither natural
nor forced movement or repose. Any body
which is in a place either moves or is in a
state of repose. Thus by this argument and
by other proofs, it is established that bodies
do not exist in a void".
Such ideas on the part of Avicenna to
some extent laid the foundation for the law
of inertia: the body is "in its place", i.e. not
influenced by an external force. His refuta¬
tion of the void and the support it has lent
this fertile scientific tradition prepared the
ground for the future recognition of many
fields of physics, including gravity and
electromagnetics.
He made interesting conjectures about
the transmission of energy and light.
"Bodies act upon each other in two man¬
ners," he asserted, and defined those man¬
ners as: "by contact as when ice touches
something, it cools it, or when wind con¬
tacts something, it moves it; in another
manner, as when green grass leaves a green
light on an adjacent wall, or when human .
faces leave an imprint in the observer's eyes
or in the mirror".
Extrapolating his views to the field of
"cosmic" phenomena, he asserted as had
previously Aristotle and his disciples that
many empirically observed phenomena are
connected with, for instance, the influence
of the Moon. He wrote: "The light and
forces emanating from the Sun and other
luminaries influence our world. Among the
most obvious influences of the heaven and
the Moon is that the Moon... causes the sea
tides to flow".
In correspondence with al-Biruni, Avicen¬
na advanced his own version of the principle
of the conservation of movement,
postulating that both presently and poten¬
tially, a sphere was neither light nor heavy.
CONTINUED PAGE 44
ABID S. SADYKOV is a Soviet scientist speciali¬
zing in organic and bio-organic chemistry, about
which he has written some 600 works, including
five monographs. A member of the USSR Aca¬
demy of Sciences, he is President of the Aca¬
demy of Sciences of the Uzbek Soviet Socialist
Republic. His works include an article on the ori¬
gins of chemistry in Central Asia, and the
influence of Avicenna on its development.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
o ^
m o
IS
É©
HELLENISTIC
HELLENIC
SABAEAN
Alinari-Giraudon, Paris
EGYPTIAN BABYLONIAN
r^^gaiuiftS^^I'-*@ 7-v '¿I
? ^'IMIU
»JÍJSU . A. rJ i. ^v
r « t»>t
I M /
Photo Eileen Tweedy © Editions Bordas, Pari
* -|íw
Photo © Louvre Muséum, Paris
ISLAM - CRADLE OF
The findings in mathematics, astronomy and medicine of the two
great river civilizations of Egypt and Babylon were developed and
given a theoretical framework by such thinkers as Pythagoras,
Plato and Aristotle in the golden age of classical Greece. However,
it was from Alexandria, the centre of the later flowering of the
Hellenistic period, personified by such figures as Euclid and
Ptolemy, rather than from Athens that the heritage of the past was
to reach Islam. The transmission of this Greco-Hellenistic tradition
was not direct but passed through the Sabaeans of Haran and the
Sassanids of Persia. It was via the Sassanids and the centres they
established, such as the medical institute of Jundishapur, that
Persian and Indian sciences mingled with the Greek heritage to
reach the Islamic world. The contribution of the Far East to Islamic
science does not compare in any way with that of Greece, India,
Persia and Egypt, but the importance of such Chinese
technological innovations as paper-making should not be
under-estimated.
Above, schematic representation of the transmission of scientific
thought. EGYPTIAN. Fragment of the Rhind papyrus, the original
of which dates back to 1800 BC, is one of the main sources of our
knowledge of ancient Egyptian mathematics. BABYLONIAN.
Astrological tablet from Uruk in Lower Mesopotamia dates back to
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
"Islamic science came into being from a wedding between the
spirit that issued from the Koranic revelation and the existing
sciences of various civilizations which Islam inherited and which it
transmuted through its spiritual power into a new substance, at
once different from and continuous with what had existed before it.
The international and cosmopolitan nature of Islamic civilization,
derived from the universal character of the Islamic revelation and
reflected in the geographical spread of the Islamic world, enabled it
to create the first science of a truly international nature in human
history.
"Islam became heir to the intellectual heritage of all the major
civilizations before it save that of the Far East, and it became a
haven within which various intellectual traditions found a new lease
upon life, albeit transformed within a new spiritual universe. This
point must be repeated, particularly since so many people in the
West wrongly believe that Islam acted simply as a bridge over
which ideas of Antiquity passed to medieval Europe. As a matter of
fact nothing could be further from the truth, for no idea, theory or
doctrine entered the citadel of Islamic thought unless it first
became Muslimized and integrated into the total world view of
'am. "
Seyyed Hossein Nasr
From Islamic Science, An Illustrated Study
Photo Serge Koutchmy vÇ CNRS, Paris
INTERNATIONAL SCIENCE
the second century BC. INDIAN. Recent photo of an eclipse of the
sun. Indian astronomers are thought to have taught Muslim
scholars various methods of determining eclipses. CHINESE. Arab
tradition has it that a Chinese prisoner captured at the battle of
Talas (751 AD) revealed to the Arab world the secrets of paper-
making. HELLENIC. Pythagoras (580-500 BC), mathematician and
philosopher who deeply influenced classical Greek thought.
HELLENISTIC. Euclid's proof of the Pythagorean theory. Euclid
founded and taught at a school in Alexandria during the reign of
Ptolemy I Soter (323-283 BC). PERSIAN. The goddess Anahita as
depicted on a Sassanid bowl. Under the Sassanids Persia
transmitted to Islam Greek and Indian learning as well as its own
scientific tradition as exemplified by the Royal Astronomical
Tables. SABAEAN. The Sabaeans of Haran passed on to Islam
many aspects of Babylonian astronomy and mathematics that are
not reflected in Greek texts. ISLAMIC. The golden age of Islamic
science. Illustration of a scholar giving a lecture from a 13th-
century manuscript of the Maqamat, a collection of tales written
by al-Hariri (1054-1122 AD).
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 41
"The proof is," he wrote, "that either the
potentially light and potentially heavy are
such in their whole, as is seen in the case of
the particles of elements, which remain mo¬
tionless in their natural places... or (they) are
such in their parts and not in their whole, as
we may see in combinations of elements,
which are neither light nor heavy since, if
some combinations of the elements move
upwards, then the other half of them must
move downwards". This theory may be said
to approximate to a grasp of the principle of
the conservation of movement, which was
further developed by Galileo, and sub¬
sequently, by Descartes and Newton.
Avicenna's thinking on anthropogeny,
which encapsulates the most advanced
ideas of his time, is of unquestionable in¬
terest. For instance, he put forward the
theory that man's origins lie in an animal
species. He wrote that until a species "has
acquired all the senses that are capable of
apprehending the things perceptible to the
senses, neither can nature, of necessity,
transform it from an animal to a rational
species". Of course, this theory is still well
behind that of Darwin, but it may
nonetheless be viewed as a kind of
hypothesis which no one prior to Darwin
was able to turn into a genuinely scientific
theory.
Avicenna's creative approach to some
problems of physics and mechanics is
shown in the Kitab al-Shifa (Book of Heal¬
ing) and the Danish-Nameh (Book of
Knowledge), and also in separate treatises
and in correspondence with al-Biruni.
Defending the theory of the "motive force"
put forward by the sixth century Alexan¬
drian philosopher 'John Philoponus, and
considering the problem of the relationship
between "forced" and "natural" move¬
ment, Avicenna propounded his own theory
of the mechanics of movement. The gist of
it is that "a kind of incorporeal kinetic force"
or dimension to some extent the
equivalent either of impulse or of kinetic
energy is imparted to the moving body. In
Western European science, this incorporeal
dimension was later termed "impetus".
Avicenna's theory exerted considerable in¬
fluence on the views of many scientists.
Eastern and Western, and lies at the origin
of the theory of impetus finalized in the four¬
teenth century by the French philosopher
Jean Buridan.
In his treatise The Measure of Wisdom,
Avicenna described a number of simple
machines and mechanisms for lifting and
moving loads, and also several complex
mechanisms consisting of pulleys,
windlasses, levers and screws. Not content
with describing the mechanisms known in
his times, he suggested a few new combina¬
tions which we do not find in his
predecessors' works, even in those of the
ancient Greek scholar Heron of Alexandria,
who illustrated the main achievements of
antiquity in applied mechanics. The prin¬
ciples Avicenna described were the basis of
various devices used throughout Central
Asia for raising water or processing oil,
grains or cotton.
Neither can his contribution to the
development of geometry and pure
mathematics be overlooked. In his commen¬
tary on Euclid's Elements, for instance, he
attempted to improve the structure of the
latter's axioms in order to provide a
theoretical foundation for geometry. In
arithmetic, he introduced the Indian method
of testing the simplest functions by using
the number 9, and generalized its use for
finding the cubes of numbers. In this field as
in many others he helped to promote the
development of abstract thought in the
Islamic countries.
Avicenna also wrote works on astronomy.
His Message to Zarrin Gis, daughter of
Qabus Ibn Washmgir, the ruler of Gorgan, is
lost to us, but al-Biruni was acquainted with
the Message and analysed it in his Geodesy.
To us, the value of this work is that it con¬
tained Avicenna's radically new method of
determining the difference in the
geographical longitudes of two localities. Its
gist is as follows: the culmination of the
moon is observed at the meridian of a locali¬
ty of which the longitude is unknown. Then
the position of the moon is calculated using
tables compiled for a locality whose
longitude is known. The difference between
the calculated and observed positions of the
moon is translated into the difference in
local times at the two localities, and that will
be the difference in their geographical
longitudes. Avicenna formulated this
method in Gorgan between the years 1012
and 1014. Exactly five hundred years later, in
1514, the method was rediscovered in
Europe by the astronomer Johannes Werner
(1468-1528).
In Isfahan, where his fates took him,
Avicenna built an observatory and, using in¬
struments he himself invented, made con¬
tinuous observations of the luminaries over
a period of several years. The result was his
ephemerides, or tables showing the daily
positions of the planets in relation to the
ecliptic. His calculations have proved more
accurate than those of the ancients. He was
among the first medieval astronomers to
prove that the sun's apogee is not fixed. He
invented a special instrument combining
several large rulers set in elevation, which he
used to determine the altitude and azimuth
of the luminary. To refine his
measurements, he used an original method
which subsequently became known as
Nonius' method, after the Portuguese
scholar Pedro Nunhes, or Nonius, who
rediscovered this method in the sixteenth
century.
Avicenna had no special knowledge of
chemistry, although he undoubtedly knew
of some chemical reactions from mixing
compound medicines, for instance, where in
some cases the number of components was
as high as thirty or forty. However, he un¬
doubtedly sponsored the development of
that science by his uncompromising critique
of alchemy. Here is what he wrote in the
Book of Healing on that score: "Alchemy is
far behind nature, and cannot catch up with
it, although it endeavours to do so. As
regards the pretensions of alchemists, then
they can produce no genuine change of
species. They can perform good imitations,
painting red metal white so that it resembles
silver, or yellow so that it resembles
gold. ..But the substance of those metals re¬
mains unchanged thereby..."
In his pursuit of science, Avicenna attach¬
ed enormous importance to water omnific,
dissolvent, uniting and destructive. In some
cases, he saw the solution of substances in
water as transformation. He gave special
preference to mineral waters, because of the
metals dissolved in them: if mineral waters
contained salts, gold and silver, then they
were beneficent to the human organism! Of
all waters, he considered the best, because
of its solvent qualities, to be "purified"
water, which could be obtained from or¬
dinary water, and he proposed a very
original technique for obtaining a kind of
distilled water: a layer of wadding is placed
over a cauldron of boiling water, and from
time to time it is removed and wrung out...
On metals too, Avicenna's views were his
own, and he placed special emphasis on
mercury. From the ninth to eleventh cen¬
turies, this metal was extensively used in
Central Asia: according to available informa¬
tion, several hundreds of metric tons of mer¬
cury were then extracted there.
At the same time, the mining of other
metals was quite advanced. Like his
predecessors and contemporaries, Avicenna
viewed gold, for example, as the most
perfect of substances, the sovereign
mineral. He also recommended the salts of
some heavy metals for external use. The
techniques for making sublimates of mer¬
cury were known to Avicenna's contem¬
poraries. The physical and chemical proper¬
ties of sublimate were also known, and it
was recommended for treatment of external
complaints. Gold and silver were deemed
excellent medicaments for strengthening the
heart and cleansing the blood. In addition,
he described the use of finely-ground glass,
salts, antimony, iron, lead and blue vitriol for
treating diseases of the eye and some other
organs.
Avicenna postulated that various
substances interact together, forming a mix¬
ture in which one of the components
predominates. A simple substance, he
thought, could not produce other
substances. In these views, an embryo of in¬
organic chemistry is not hard to detect.
Where Avicenna's contribution to
mineralogy and geology is concerned, pride
of place must go to the classification of
minerals he proposed, with its very rational
division into four groups: stones, ores, fuels
and salts. That division was taken over in its
entirety by European mineralogy as of the
late Middle Ages; it was maintained in the
Renaissance, and virtually until the nine¬
teenth century. Even the first classification
of minerals by chemical composition, which
was proposed by Torbern Olaf Bergman of
Sweden in 1780, sub-divided all minerals in¬
to Sales (salts). Terrae (earth and stones),
Bitumine (hydrocarbons) and Metalla
(metals): an exact repetition of Avicenna's
system. To commemorate his services to
mineralogy, one of the thallic minerals
discovered in the Uzbek SSR has been nam¬
ed avicennite.
Finally, it may be mentioned that Avicen¬
na thought the erosive effects of wind and
water to be one of the factors in the forma¬
tion of valleys and ravines. Considering the
fossilized sea creatures known at the time,
he said that the lands where they had been
found had formerly been sea-beds. He ex¬
plained correctly that earthquakes were due
to deep-seated geological processes.
"If I see somewhat further than
Descartes, that is because I am standing on
his shoulders", declared Newton. And if
modern science has advanced so far since
Avicenna's day, then that is only because it
has "stood on the shoulders" of many
pioneers, including, of course, those of
Avicenna himself.
Abid S. Sadykov
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The secret of the stars
by Ahmed Siiheyl Unver
IN the 11th century a Turkish ruler who
was known only by the name of
Giyaseddin, wondered why stars are
visible at night and not during the day.
Some of the learned men of the time offered
him the explanation that during the daytime
the more intense sunlight overshadowed the
light cast by the stars, whereas at night,
after the setting of the sun, stars once more
became visible. This answer was then com¬
pared by the ruler with another explanation
given by a smaller group of learned men. Ac¬
cording to their answer to Giyaseddin's in¬
quiry, the intensity of starlight is diminished
during the daytime; because of this, light
cannot penetrate into the depths of heaven.
Giyaseddin, the ruler, who viewed these
answers critically, asked of Avicenna: "How
can sunlight vanish from the semi-spherical
heaven? That sunlight can be completely
screened from heaven at any time of the day
is not possible since it is known that the
world which comes in between the sun and
the semi-spherical heaven is not so large as
the sun itself. The world can prevent the
sun's rays from falling on a part of heaven
AHMED SUHEIL UNVER, of Turkey, is a mem¬
ber of the Turkish Historical Institute anda former
professor at the Faculty of Medicine and the Aca¬
demy of Fine Arts at Istanbul. The founder of the
Istanbul Institute of Medicine, he has published a
number of studies on Avicenna as well as works
on Turkish miniatures, calligraphy and painting.
that is equal only to its own size. But since
the sun is many times larger than the world,
the part of heaven that is screened from the
sun's rays at any time will be very small in
relation to the world and even much smaller
in relation to the sun."
Avicenna, too, was not convinced of the
validity of the explanation offered by his col¬
leagues. Indeed, no one ventured further in
solving this important problem than the ex¬
planations cited above.
Avicenna offered the following explana¬
tion: it is true that at night the sun's rays are
transmitted to this end of Space. Space, like
air is transparent. Transparent substances
possess two important properties: one is
that they are not luminous but transmit
light; they are not brightened themselves.
The second property is that they do not
obstruct the path of vision. During the day
the sun which is above the horizon brightens
the foreign components in air, such as dust
and vapour. These components, which of
themselves are not transparent appear
bright on account of light rays falling on
them from other sources. Thus during the
daytime our surroundings appear bright and
the stars become invisible. This is easily
proved when at night the visibility of stars in
the light of a flame becomes diminished.
By this explanation, it becomes evident
that Avicenna has satisfactorily attributed
the solution of the present problem to the
effect of the diffusion of light.
0 Vault of Heaven, 0 Firmament,
In the name of the Creator, tel me.
Do you spin above us by your own design?
Or are you by another's power constrained
To eternal movement?
For mortal man you are Infinity;
Perplexed we wonder within what frame
Your revolutions are set. Can it be
That for you a greater Infinite exists?
Are you the haven to which souls return?
Or do they perish with our mortal coil?
The Sun that you uphold
Shoots out its rays
As though from the feathers
Of a great bird's wing.
But the Milky Way!
Is it a billow in the ocean of the sky?
Or is it the image of a sword
Reflected in a burnished breastplate?
The crescent Moon? Is it a pendant
On the necklace of the Stars
Shining through the night obscure?
Or is it a bracelet on an unknown hand?
The Stars? Are they encrusted pearls?
Or foaming bubbles crowning mighty waves
Whose weaving patterns by the night revealed
Uke some great sail, when daylight comes.
Are folded carefully away?
¡Extract from a poem by Avicenna)
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO NEWSROOM
Soviet Union Presents
Painting to Unesco
The USSR has donated to Unesco a vast
modern painting (above) on the theme of
"The Contribution of the Peoples of the
USSR to World Culture and Civilization".
The painting, by Ilya Glazunov (born 1930),
depicts some of the outstanding per¬
sonalities from the different peoples, na¬
tionalities and ethnic groups of the Soviet
Union who have made major contributions
to the progress of world civilization. The
figures, set against a background of impor¬
tant cultural and natural sites and
monuments, include Pushkin, Dostoevsky,
Tolstoy, Tchaikovsky, Chaliapin as Boris
Godunov, Gorki, and Yuri Gagarin. The
panoramic work is now on permanent
display at Unesco's Paris headquarters.
Chinese Edition
of Unesco Courier
We are happy to announce to our readers
the launching of a Chinese language edition
of the Unesco Courier. The Chinese edition,
the first issue of which appeared in July
1980, is published in Pekin by the "China
Translation and Publishing Corporation". Its
Managing Editor is Mme Shen Guofen. This
brings the total number of language editions
of the Unesco Courier to twenty-five, not
counting the quarterly selection in Braille
which is published in English, French and
Spanish.
» « *
tm<p*am*tm»m
46
It
imadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Re-elected
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, of Senegal,
has been re-elected Director-General of
Unesco by the Organization's General Con¬
ference being held in Belgrade from 23
September to 28 October. Mr. M'Bow, who
was elected Director-General in 1974, was
unanimously re-elected by the General Con¬
ference and will serve for a seven-year term.
An Apostle
of Scientific Progress
Two years ago, Unesco's General Con¬
ference proposed that, on the thousandth
anniversary of the birth of Ibn Sina (Avicen¬
na) according to the Christian calendar,
Unesco should pay tribute to this great
thinker (980-1037 AD; 370-428 of the
Hegira) and to the immense influence his
work has had on the development of science.
The anniversary has been celebrated this
year at international conferences and sym¬
posia, including three in the USSR, (at
Moscow, Tashkent and Dushanbe) which
have focussed on Avicenna's major con¬
tributions to physics, logic, sociology and
literature, as well as to the exact and natural
sciences and to medicine. Speakers also
drew attention to Avicenna's distinguished
role in encouraging, through scientific
knowledge, the efforts of the human com¬
munity to build a better world in which
scientific development can flourish. At the
, Moscow meeting. Prof. Pyotr Feodosev,
Vice-President of the Soviet Academy of
Sciences, made the point that Avicenna saw
his work as pre-eminently the fruit of com¬
munication between peoples.
"Avicenna could only conceive of man as
part of a situation, as existing within the
framework of society," Prof. Feodosev said.
"Outside the human community, he felt, the
capacities of the individual could not achieve
fulfilment, since man is a social creature.
Happiness is impossible, Avicenna wrote, if
a man does not forge links with others."
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, the Director-
General of Unesco, returned to this idea in
his address:
"Avicenna, perhaps more than any other
thinker of the great age in which he lived,
proved a fundamental truth which is also, in
a sense, the reason why Unesco exists:
civilizations only have a. future insofar as
they communicate with each other, enrich
each other with their mutual contributions,
and recreate together, through their diver¬
sity, the unity of our destiny."
Unesco Medal
Avicenna
Unesco has issued a medal to commemorate
the thousandth anniversary of Avicenna's
birth. On the obverse side of the medal,
designed by sculptor-medallist Victor
Douek, is a scene inspired by a miniature in a
17th-century Turkish manuscript, and the
inscription "AVICENNAE 980-1037"
"UNESCO 1980" (see photo page 4).
Reproduced on the reverse side is a phrase
(in Arabic and Latin) by Avicenna which
means "Co-operate for the well-being of the
body and the survival of the human
species", as well as the autograph attributed
to Avicenna which appears on our cover.
The Avicenna medal forms part of the "An¬
niversaries of Great Men" series launched by
Unesco in 1975, which now includes medals
struck in honour of Michelangelo, Rubens,
Aristotle and Einstein. For further informa¬
tion about the medals, available in gold,
silver and bronze, please contact Unesco's
Philatelic and Numismatic Programme.
Avicenna and his time
Further reading in English
Avicenna, His Life and Works, by'Soheil
M. Afnan. Allen and Unwin Ltd., London, 1958.
Introduction to the History of Science,
Vol. I, From Homer to Omar Khayyam, by
George Sarton. Published for the Carnegie Insti¬
tution of Washington by the Williams and Wilkins
Company, Baltimore, 1927.
Avicenna and the Visionary Recital, by
Henry Corbin. (Translated from the French by
Willard R. Trask). Routledge and Kegan Paul
Ltd., London, 1961.
A Treatise on the Canon of Medicine of
Avicenna, incorporating a translation of the first
book, by O. Cameron Grüner. Luzac and Co.,
London, 1930.
Islamic Science: An Illustrated Study, by
Seyyed Hossein Nasr. Published by the World of
Islam Festival Publishing Co. Ltd and distributed
by Thorsons Publishers Ltd., Wellingborough,
Northants., U.K. 1976.
The World of Islam: Faith, People, Cul¬
ture, edited by Bernard Lewis. Thames and Hud¬
son, London, 1976.
Avicenna on Theology, by A.J. Arberry.
London, 1951.
Avicenna, Scientist and Philosopher: A
Millenary Symposium, edited by G.M. Wic¬
kens. London, 1952.
The Central Asian Art of Avicenna's
Epoch, published by the "Irfon" publishing
house, Dushanbe, Tadzhik SSR, 1980.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
NEW PRICES EFFECTIVE 1 JANUARY, 1981
one year: 44 FF.
two years: 75 FF.
single issue: 4.50 FF.
SPECIAL OFFER VALID UNTIL 31 DECEMBER 1980
For current subscribers: if your subscription expires before 31 December,
you can renew for 1 or 2 years at the 1980 rate:
one year: 35 FF.
two years: 58 FF.
For new subscribers: by subscribing now, you can also take advantage
of the current one-year or two-year rates.
For gift subscriptions: if you'd like to offer someone a gift subscription,
do it before 31 December and you can benefit from the current rates.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschapplj Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
- FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): Deutscher Unesco - Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57,
D-5300 Bonn 3. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stutt¬
gart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger GmbH,
Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034
Germering/München. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book
Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL. A.B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. 8ox 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. .Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddlne
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(ßooksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road; Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue,
Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir
Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rueGrenus6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM.
H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and
Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester, Birmingham, Bristol. -UNITED STATES. Unipub,
345 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA.
Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade;
Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
'Prince and chief of physicians'
Ibn Sina, known in the Western world as Avicenna, author of the Canon of Medicine, an encyclopaedic treatise
which remained the supreme medical reference source for six centuries, has rightly been dubbed "the prince
and chief of physicians". But more than this, he is one of the handful of universal geniuses who have taken all
knowledge for their province. Philosopher, scientist and poet as well as physician, Avicenna found time to
design his own surgical instruments, many of which are virtually the same as those used today. Below, four ins¬
truments made recently in Uzbekistan from descriptions and sketches drawn by Avicenna himself nearly a thou¬
sand years ago. From left to right: Surgical scissors with sharply pointed blade tips for use in eye surgery; twee¬
zers for removing foreign bodies; a lancet; and a scalpel for removing fragments of skull bone during trepanning
operations.
]]>
</page>
</document>
