<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074717eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
cíófioln^a o§ *Jkß> imwuqvYvodJu&ri
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
Q NIGER
"Man cannot remain in a village where there are no musicians",
says a proverb of the Dan people of west Africa. This saying serves
as a reminder that on every continent and in every age a people's
music and the instruments on which it is played have reflected the
deepest cultural values of their civilization. The preservation of
traditional instruments and forms of musical expression, which are
The rhythm of the water drum
today dying out in many parts of the world, is a problem with
which Unesco is increasingly concerned as part of its mission to
protect the cultural heritage of mankind. Photo shows a Tuareg
girl of the Republic of Niger with an asakhalabbo, a ritual water
drum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JUNE 1982 35th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 26 LANGUAGES
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 48 French Francs
2 years: 84 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 36 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 6 - 1982 - OPI - 82-1 - 388 A
page
4 THE LANDSCAPE OF THE TALE
by Fernando Savater
7 ALL ABOUT ALICE
by Anthony Burgess
11 PINOCCHIO, THE EVERGREEN CENTENARIAN
by halo Calvino
15 HUCKLEBERRY FINN
An epic of self-discovery
by Malcolm Bradbury
18 THE COMIC STRIP BALLOONS AROUND THE WORLD
by Michel Pierre
20 LATIN AMERICA: TALL STORIES FOR SMALL READERS
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
23 THE CHILD-HERO IN AFRICAN FOLKTALES
by Aminata Sow Fall
26 GOHA THE SIMPLE
or the wisdom of folly
by Georgia Makhlouf
28 THE MONKEY KING SUN WUKONG
by Sun Youjun
30 IVANUSHKA, PRINCE OF SIMPLETONS
by Valentin Berestov
32 BOOKS FOR EAGER FINGERS
33 WRITING FOR CHILDREN IS NO CHILD'S PLAY
by Michel Tournier
2 A TIME TO LIVE...
NIGER: The rhythm of the water-drum
JHE World Congress on Books,
the first international, interdisci¬
plinary gathering ofbook special¬
ists on a worldwide scale to be convened
by Unesco, is to be held in London from 7
to 11 June 1982. To coincide with this
major event, this issue of the Unesco
Courier is devoted to literature for chil¬
dren.
Despite the many obstacles to its spread
in the developing world (illiteracy being
the most serious), children 's literature is
more and more becoming part of the
common heritage of the young and serv¬
ing as a link between cultures and
peoples.
Literature conceived specificallyfor the
young and featuring youthful heroes and
heroines, only really developed in the
western world during the nineteenth cen¬
tury. Today, the production ofchildren's
books represents a rapidly expanding sec¬
tor of the publishing industry. Although
some critics have seen this expansion as
being motivated by the desire for profits
as much as by any educative spirit, in
both the industrialized and the developing
world it has some remarkable achieve¬
ments to its credit.
Nevertheless, the desire and need to
spin talesforyoung people, both for their
entertainment and as a means ofpassing
on to them the collective wisdom of the
group, are certainly as old as mankind's
earliest cultural experiences.
Thus, rather than attempt to determine
the limits, whether historical or ofform,
of a literary genre so difficult to define
that certain writers, like Michel Tournier,
deny that any such limits exist, seeing in it
the quintessence of all literature, in this
issue of the Unesco Courier we have
chosen to give a panoramic, though not
an exhaustive, picture of the heroes and
heroines of children's literature.
It is no accident that, almost every¬
where, the earliest major works written
for children have drawn their inspiration
from the oral tradition and, above all,
from tales with an initiatory content,
whetherfor children or adults, as witness
the central place held by such tales in the
African social life and ethic.
Clearly, we cannot restrict ourselves to
the adolescent or child hero, to Pinoc-
chio, Alice, Little Ivan or Huckleberry
Finn. Over the years young readers have
claimedfor themselves tales from a wider
literature or legendary figures not
primarily intendedfor them, but who are
imbued with a mixture of liberating
power and inspiredfantasy. Among these
must be counted Goha the Wise Fool
and, in another vein, Sandokan the
Malay pirate and a host of other
characters who belong to literature for
everyone.
In dominated societies, the young
reader identifies himself more readily
with the adventurer and the upholder of
justice who fights against tyranny and all
forms of oppression, the revolutionary
model whom he usually finds in adult
literature.
In some types of "oral literature",
however, particularly in Africa, the omni¬
present child hero is raised to the status of
a symbol. He embodies the spirit ofgood
or the forces of evil and is seen not as an
individual but as "The Child", an
anonymous, superior embodiment of the
hopes and fears of the social group.
Another hero figure who must not be
forgotten here is the prestigious animal
intermediary or intercessor, such as that
great favourite with Chinese children the
Monkey King Sun Wukong.
Finally, mention must be made of the
strip cartoon hero. Although the strip
cartoon still too often remains a mediocre
consumer product purveying a suspect
ideology, it has become a means of com¬
munication of worldwide importance
which, whether we like it or not, con¬
tributes equally with literature to the "in¬
ner growth " of the child.
Cover drawing © Jose! Palecek, Prague
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
"The fundamental element in tales is the journey... Any means from the simplest to the most
extraordinary can be used... wax wings that are likely to melt if they fly too close to the sun or
the claws of Roc, the bird that carried Sinbad." The drawing is by the Iranian artist Ali Akbar
Sadeghi, winner of the Grand Prix of the Noma Concours for Children's Picture Book Illustra¬
tions 78, a competition organized by the Asian Cultural Centre for Unesco, Tokyo.
Drawing © Asian Cultural Centre for Unesco, Tokyo
IF one had to sum up in a few words the
message of tales, the quintessence of
legends and the lesson of adventure
stories, these words might be: a longing for
independence, intrepidity and generosity.
Tales tell of man's perplexity and watch¬
fulness and, in the last analysis, of his faith
in himself; or of the faith of each man in
himself and of mankind in what is human in
all men. Such faith is deeper and stronger
than the pursuit at all costs of a "happy
ending".
I am referring here to tales, legends, epic
poems and adventure novels, to all forms of
fiction in which action takes precedence over
passion, the exceptional over the humdrum
of everyday life, travel over immobility, in¬
itiation over routine, ethics over psychology,
and invention over literalness in description.
After all, many literary classifications are
academic rather than really pertinent. As
Lope de Vega wrote in La Filomena: "At a
time less wise than ours, but when men knew
more than we do, novels were called tales".
And so in this article I too shall refer to fic¬
tion as "tales" tales which express all the
dreams of childhood and the aspirations of
adolescence and which accompany us
throughout our lives.
I mentioned independence and intrepidity
in other words, the wish to go out into the
world, to break with the warm, routine tor¬
por of the home where the spirit is shaped
but where it can also become atrophied and
stifled. In tales, the motive force is the con¬
stant temptation of the outdoors. A tempta¬
tion which both attracts and repels,
FERNANDO SAVATER, is a young Spanish
writer and philosopher who is professor of Ethics
at the País Vasco University, San Sebastián. He
is the author of some 15 works of philosophy,
essays and a novel.
THE LANDSCAPE
OF THE TALE
by Fernando Savater
'I
fir*
y
?
©
"Tales tell of man's
perplexity and watch¬
fulness and, in the last
analysis, of his faith in
himself." Drawing by the
Argentine artist Eduardo
Ruiz, for the Venezuelan
story The Legend of
Maichak, from Tales and
Legends of Latin America.
The first volume of this
publication conceived
and produced by Unesco's
Regional Centre for Book
Development in Latin
America and the Carib¬
bean (CERLAL) is a com¬
pilation of tales and tradi¬
tions from Argentina,
Brazil, Colombia, Mexico,
Peru, Uruguay and
Venezuela specially
prepared for young
readers and illustrated by
Latin American artists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
fascinates and frightens. The hero of the tale
is forever "roaming the world" in order to
find out what is happening beyond the
mountains; sometimes he tries to discover
the nature of fear, for he dimly perceives that
the realm of fear lies on the borders of space
and that the distant horizon is always over¬
shadowed by a somewhat frightening halo;
but he knows, too, that to achieve its true
stature the human spirit must face those
frightening, far-distant reaches at least once
in a lifetime.
The home is not enough: if the young
adventurer never leaves home he will not ex¬
perience fear and acquire the knowledge
essential to his development, he will not even
experience nostalgia which, in a sense, he
needs even more. If he has no conception of
fear or of nostalgia, he will know nothing of
the human way of living in a home, for this
implies above all that one has returned.
The child lives in a home that he has not
yet conquered, governed by rules and regula¬
tions which, for him, are as immutable as the
"The young hero's astuteness and the infor¬
mation he possesses... do not serve so much
to show how reality operates as to stress the
hero's qualities and efflcacity." Still from a
film by Alexander Korda depicts Mowgli, the
hero of Rudyard Kipling's The Jungle Book.
laws of nature. He must leave home before
returning to it fully aware and sitting by a
fire lit from the embers he has brought back
from some distant volcano. Roaming the
world means running risks, accepting the
possibility that one may get lost, and giving
oneself the opportunity to go astray. Anyone
who has not got completely lost at least once
in his lifetime will live in his dwelling like a
piece of furniture, oblivious of the feats and
conquests that are needed to underpin the
peaceful structure of everyday life. But the
child feels this instinctively, and it is because
he loves the home that will one day be his,
because he has faith in the man he will
become, that one fine day he silently leaves
the family home at daybreak, a bundle on
his shoulder, bound for the distant horizon
and the as yet unknown realm of fear.
Each home is the result of an adventure,
but for the child it is someone else's adven¬
ture. He must rise against routine which ap¬
pears mechanical and apathetic. For no one
"For readers (or those who listen to
the tale) of the adventures of Little Red
Riding Hood... the word 'wood' is
more mysterious and threatening than
the 'forest' itself." Engraving of Little
Red Riding Hood and the wolf, by
Gustave Doré.
"...the sea which unites and separates, offering per¬
manent promise of far-off adventures... whether the
action takes place on its unruly waves or in its
depths..." In this still from John Huston's film Moby
Dick, the great white whale turns furiously on the
crew of Captain Ahab's whaler the Pequod.
can permanently change his life and the lives
of his descendants as required by the power¬
ful dream of the founder-hero: the serene
splendour won by audacity and valiant ef¬
fort, and the order obtained through guile
which no monster or catastrophe can
discourage, redeem him who achieves them,
but the repetition of the same deeds merely
subjugates their offspring. The moral is that
it is not enough to be an heir: every legacy
must be reconquered it must be lost before
it can be won back triumphantly. It is
respect for the efforts of parents that
develops into revolt against them: to become
self-sufficient, and even to rebel is to under¬
stand the sum of human effort needed to
achieve order and to realize that order is not
merely suffered or tolerated and that the
form it takes implies a certain freedom of
choice. Some tales tell of young heroes (the
protagonist is nearly always a representative
of the archetype of puer aeternus, an adoles¬
cent who has the child's carefree curiosity
and playfulness along with the father's
educational and social proclivities) who suc¬
ceed in reinventing new ways of organizing
the world or of warding off threats to existing
forms of organization.
As always the lesson they offer is am¬
biguous and two-sided: only those who break
with daily routine deserve to have a house,
only rebels who refuse to submit to anything
can say they have roamed the world, and it is
only in the regained peacefulness of routine
that they can fully appreciate the revelation
of fear.
The child sets out to roam the world; the
morning is fresh and new, the countryside is
coming to life, the sun has started on its
ascending course... in the distance are great
trees and blue mountains; the traveller closes
the door of his house behind him and begins
his journey. Landscapes are the very fabric
of tales, in the same way that "we are such
stuff as dreams are made on", according to
Shakespeare. For the fundamental element
in tales is the journey which removes the
hero from the' closed, secure atmosphere of
the family, exposing him to the unforeseen,
to adventure. Any means from the simplest
to the most extraordinary can be used to^
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^achieve this goal. It is good and bracing to
walk, but even better to don Tom Thumb's
Seven-League Boots in order to escape the
Ogre who is pursuing him; a horse, a camel,
or even an elephant can be pressed into ser¬
vice, and the lucky children for whom Jules
Verne invented a two-year holiday did not
refuse to ride ostriches. And what about fly¬
ing? Here too, the possibilities are legion,
ranging from wax wings that are likely to
melt if they fly too close to the sun, or the
claws of Roc the bird that carried Sinbad, to
balloons, comets, magic broomsticks and
flying carpets, to the winged Pegasus on
which Perseus came to rescue Andromeda,
and the ultra-sophisticated spaceships of
contemporary science fiction. The same goes
for sea travel; anything that floats can serve
as a boat: the little princess's cockle-shell,
the little tin soldier's paper boat, or the cof¬
fin that enabled Ishmael to save his life after
the wreck of the Pequod brought about by
the anger of Moby Dick, not to mention the
possibility of crossing the sea on the back of
an obliging dolphin or clutching the shell of a
giant tortoise.
Even a simple fall is an acceptable means
of transport, as discovered by Alice when she
"The wood is the home of the
wolf and the Ogre's hunting
ground... a place of perdition
and destruction, of hostile
darkness and of brambles
whose thorns arrest the tired
traveller's progress." Engraving
by Gustave Doré for Tom
Thumb.
dashed into the rabbit-warren leading to
Wonderland, or by those characters frpm the
Thousand-and-One-Nights who walk where
they are not supposed to walk, or take a false
step and land in a cave full of treasure.
(Something similar happened to Kipling's
Mowgli when he landed inadvertently in a
cave full of amazing riches guarded over by a
big white cobra).
What is at stake here is to go far to achieve
as soon as possible the undomestic fulfilment
of the free-ranging landscape: this can apply
equally well to the relatively close but always
enigmatic Nature that I see in the distance
from my window, or to the fabulous land in¬
to which I am wafted by a tornado, or,
again, as in the Wizard of Oz, to a thirst for
exploration. As soon as the journey starts
nothing is as before, everything becomes ex- -
otic and anything can happen.
Each component of the landscape possess¬
es its own significance. This is no neutral or
"natural" setting in the positivist or anti-
magical sense given to the term by the
modern world; it is the most mysterious and
fantastic décor of all, for the scenery in
which the action is set is part and parcel of
that action. The protagonists find
themselves in either a hostile or a friendly
relationship with the elements of natural
spontaneity which surround them, and these
elements in turn behave towards them in a
specific way. The relationship between the
young hero and the landscape is not one of
indifference; on the contrary, it is a confron¬
tation at a high level as befits anyone who
has left home in search of distinction and
must prove himself capable of discerning the
forces that challenge his initiation and of ac¬
cepting their often dangerous scrutiny.
The hero must face the genius loci
wherever he goes, wrestle with him, defeat
him or convince him. A certain animistic
belief in Nature is essential if the tale is to be
successful; its impact is reduced when
organic chemistry or molecular biology are
substituted for the secret powers of the local
divinity. If only aspects of the physical and
chemical causality taught by modern science
come into play, then anyone can triumph in
any given situation, provided he possesses
the necessary knowledge; but what the tale
demands of its hero is action of a very dif¬
ferent kind which highlights every possible
victory to the utmost: only he who is in a
specific way, we are told, can know what
there is to know.
The young hero's astuteness and the infor¬
mation he possesses generally provided by
allies endowed with magical powers whose
support he has had to win do not serve so
much to show how reality operates as to
stress the hero's qualities and efficacity. Cer¬
tain contemporary writers tend to create
"natural", science-based values which run
counter to this typical nineteenth century ap¬
proach. It is no coincidence that the tremen¬
dous popularity of Tolkien's Lord of the
Rings the supreme example of a tale with
an entirely animistic and ethical landscape
should coincide with the rise of the ecology
movement and that it should be hippies and
other supporters of the protection of Nature
against industry who should have been the
first to enthuse over the Hobbits' extra¬
ordinary saga.
Each culture and each latitude attributes
a different value to the various elements that
make up the landscape according to whether
they represent for them routine or exoticism.
An anecdote told by Borges illustrates the
relativity of exoticism which is as
legitimate a way as any other of satisfying
our powers of imagination. A Japanese was
giving a rapturous description of a trip he
had made to Persia, and when Borges prais¬
ed the remarkable achievements of
Firdausi's and Omar Khayyam's homeland,
he said: "Yes, I finally realized what the
West is".
In the same way, our mythical perception
of the sea varies according to whether we live
in direct contact with it or in the hinterland.
Similarly, some people regard the lion as an
almost fabulous beast, while for others he is
simply a distinguished fellow-citizen. I
myself can only speak of the tales on which
my European childhood was nourished.
What stood out above all was the prestige of
the wood with its shadowy, ghostlike quali¬
ty. For readers (or those who listen to the
tale) of the adventures of Little Red Riding
Hood, Tom Thumb and Hansel and Gretel,
the word "wood" is more mysterious and
threatening than the "forest ' itself. The
wood is the home of the wolf and the Ogre's
hunting ground; there are no proper paths in
the wood or else they all lead to the man-
eating witch who is waiting in its midst; it is
a place of perdition and destruction, of
hostile darkness and of brambles whose
thorns arrest the tired traveller's progress;
salvation can only come from co-operation
with small animals (birds, squirrels, rabbits,
etc. ) who join in helping children lost in the
wood by guiding them to its edge and by
warning their parents. Apart from the wood,
which for the European represents the most
easily accessible form of exoticism and the
most credible type of adventure, other less
accessible wonders include: the desert
through which we roam with Beau Geste or
the little heroes of Sienkiewicz's tale; the
volcano which leads us to the centre of the
earth with Jules Verne's characters and
which is a source of destruction for the deca¬
dent Pompeii of Bulwer-Lytton; the cave
guarded by melancholy dragons or ingenious
goblins in which magicians and forgotten
kings hide their treasure; snow and ice, an
indispensable setting for polar adventures
that is so often present in Hans Christian
Andersen's incomparable tales (in particular
when the Snow Queen receives little Kay in
her ice palace); the island where Robinson
Crusoe finds a refuge, and its rivals, moun¬
tains, swamps and, above all, the sea. The
sea of Ulysses and Long John Silver, of the
little Mermaid and Moby Dick, Sinbad the
Sailor and Kipling's Captains Courageous, a
sea which unites and separates, offering a
permanent promise of far-off adventures
and of the greatest of all: adventure per se.
Whether the action takes place on its unruly
waves or in its depths into which the great
Alexander, known as Iskander by the Hin-
dustans he conquered, descended in a glass
bell, the sea remains the landscape par ex¬
cellence of adventure narrative.
Our spirit travels through tales and with
tales, it takes risks, makes commitments and
is born anew. Under the spell of the nar¬
rative the child and the adolescent feel that
the inevitable can be defied and everything is
possible. The strength of their character in
years to come and the choice which will
shape the course of their future lives either
towards passive submission or towards active
freedom depends to a large extent on the
training in generosity and courage that fan¬
tasy can provide.
H Fernando Savater
6
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
S ALL ABOUT ALICE
by Anthony Burgess
Text © Copyright. Reproduction prohibited
LEWIS Carroll, who wrote Alice in
Wonderland and Alice Through
the Looking-Glass, was, in pri¬
vate life, a professor of mathematics at
the University of Oxford named
Charles Lutwidge Dodgson. He
latinized Lutwidge to Ludovicus or
Lewis and Charles to Carolus or Car¬
roll, and, under this name, produced
the first Alice book in 1865 and, the
second in 1872.
He produced other books as
well mostly on difficult mathematical
subjects. Queen Victoria, enchanted by
the Alice books, asked for all of Mr
Carroll's publications and was^
ANTHONY BURGESS, internationally known
British novelist, critic and man of letters, is cur¬
rently at work on his 45th book. His works in¬
clude A Clockwork Orange (1962, filmed 1971),
Nothing Like the Sun 11964) a fictionalized ver¬
sion of Shakespeare's life, and Here Comes
Everybody 11965) an introduction to James
Joyce. His most recent novel. Earthly Powers,
was published in 1980.
Above, Alice Liddell, on whom the character of Alice
was based, photographed in the late 1850s by Lewis
Carroll himself. Alice, Lorina and Edith Liddell were the
daughters of Henry Liddell, dean of Christ Church, Ox¬
ford, where Charles Lutwidge Dodgson (Carroll's real
name) was a lecturer in mathematics. On July 4 1862,
Dodgson rowed the three children up the Thames from
Oxford to Godstow for a picnic and it was during this
outing that he recounted the story of Alice's Adven¬
tures Underground which, with some additions and
revision, was published in 1865 as A/ice's Adventures in
Wonderland. Top left, pen and ink sketch of Alice (the
character in his book) drawn by Dodgson in 1886. Left,
Alice Liddell (seated) and her sister Lorina, in Japanese
costume. The photograph is thought to have been
taken by Lewis Carroll.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THE WHITE RABBIT: ...when the rabbit ac¬
tually took a watch out of its waistcoat-
pocket, and looked at it, and then hurried
on, Alice started to her feet, for... she had
never before seen a rabbit with either a
waistcoat-pocket, or a watch to take out of
it... "Oh my ears and whiskers, how late it's
getting!"
by the delivery of treatises
on trigonometry and the binomial
theory. Lewis Carroll was also the first
of the great photographers, and his
studies of children especially of little
Alice Liddell, who was both the heroine
and the first reader of the two great
books have a charm and a mastery of
technique envied by the snappers of
today.
He also loved little girls and did not
like them to grow into big ones, though
he was vague about the moment of
change. He tried to kiss big seventeen-
year-old young ladies and was surprised
that their mothers should protest. His
love of girls, which he was too innocent
to interpret sexually, had perhaps
something to do with his desire to re¬
main a child himself. Although he prac¬
tised the adult art of mathematics,
THE CROQUET MATCH: ...the croquet balls
were live hedgehogs and the mallets live
flamingoes... The chiefdifficultyAlice found
at first was in managing her flamingo... Just
as she hadgot its neck straightened out, and
was going to give the hedgehog a blow with
its head, it would twist itself round and look
up in her face with such a puzzled expres¬
sion that she could not help bursting out
laughing...
8
aspects of the love of nonsense which
was prevalent in England in the Vic¬
torian age. There was no nonsense in
the rest of the world. When, in the early
years of the twentieth century, France
began to discover the delights of
nonsense, this was called surrealism,
and it was regretted that the British
were too old-fashioned to produce sur¬
realist writers or painters. But the
British had already produced their own
surrealists in the staid age of Victoria,
and of these perhaps Lewis Carroll was
the greatest.
Surrealism consists in destroying the
logic of ordinary life and substituting a
kind of logic of the unconscious mind.
Alice's adventures take the form of
dreams in which bizarre things happen,
but these things are based on a more
A MAD TEA-PARTY: There was a table set out under a tree in front of the house and
the March Hare and the Hatter were having tea at it; a Dormouse was sitting bet¬
ween them, fastasleep... "No room! No room!" they cried out when they saw Alice
coming. "There 's plenty ofroom!"saidAlice indignantly, end she sat down in a large
armchair at one end of the table.
which children hate because it is too
abstract, he did not really wish to have
the responsibilities of an adult.
He never married, he was deeply and
innocently religious, he liked to be cut
off from the dangerous outside world.
He was happy to be enclosed by the
walls of an Oxford college and to tell
stories to the little daughter of Dr Lid¬
dell, the great Greek scholar. But the
publication of the two Alice books
brought him fame. There was
something in them which touched
strings in the adult imagination and yet
pleased and continues to please
children. Carroll was a greater man
than he knew.
Both the Alice books are fantasies,
serious approach to language than we
can permit ourselves in waking life.
By language I mean, of course, the
English language in which Carroll
wrote; many of his dream-jokes are im¬
possible to render into other tongues. If
there is an insect called a butterfly, it
seems dreamily logical to have a bread-
and-butterfly, and Carroll's illustrator,
Tenniel, draws us one of these. The
flower known as a dandelion is a dandy
lion, hence it can roar. There is a school
in which the lessons get shorter every
day: the lessons "lessen." If your
watch stops, the dreamworld says that
time has stopped. The watch of the
Mad Hatter and his friends the March
Hare and the Dormouse has stopped at
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
teatime, so they must go on taking tea
for ever.
One of the characters who appears in
the looking-glass world is Humpty
Dumpty, who is a talking egg. His
name not merely describes him: it is
him (or he). An egg has a hump above
and a dump below. He is the most
dangerous, and yet the most persuasive,
philosopher of language imaginable.
He says "There's glory for you", and
he explains that "glory" means "a fine
knockdown argument." Alice protests,
but Humpty Dumpty says "It's a ques¬
tion of who is to be master, you or the
word." Words, in other words, can
mean what we want them to mean or
else what the logic of dreams wants
them to mean. Their normal everyday
meaning doesn't apply when we pass
through the looking-glass.
Alice's world is a world full of eccen¬
tric English Victorians disguised mostly
as animals. Like real grown-ups they
can be very rude or pompous to a child
like Alice, but in her dreams Alice can
answer back without being punished
for her effrontery. She is temporarily
living in a kind of Garden of Eden, in
which total liberty seems to be
possiblein Wonderland Alice can
change her shape and size merely by
drinking from a bottle that says
DRINK MEbut liberty is cir¬
cumscribed not by notions of right and
wrong but by mad logic. In the songs
she hears or sings herself this mad logic
seems to disappear, but there is
A PACK OF CARDS: "Off with her head!"
the Queen shouted at the top of her voice.
Nobody moved. "Who cares for you?" said
Alice (she had grown to her full size by this
time). "You're nothing but a pack of cards!"
At this the whole pack rose up into the air
and came flying down upon her...
tit say that, did you?
I In hni'i ho* promised
me iritli his urif own
mouth to to
"To send all lii^ horses
and all his men," Alice
interrupted, rather un¬
wisely.
THE LION AND THE UNICORN: "You don't know how to manage
Looking-glass cakes", the Unicorn remarked. "Hand it round first
and cut it afterwards. " This sounded nonsense, but Alice very obe¬
diently got up and carried the dish round, end the coke divided
itself up into three pieces as she did so. "Now cut it up", said the
fion as she returned to her piece with the empty dish.
substituted for it the spirit of parody,
which implies an existing logic in the
waking world. Alice knows very well a
song that goes:
Twinkle twinkle little star,
How I wonder what you are,
Up above the world so high
Like a diamond in the sky.
This becomes:
Twinkle twinkle little bat,
How I wonder what you're at,
Up above the world so high,
Like a teatray in the sky.
Why bat? Why teatray? For that
matter, why is a raven like a writing-
desk? We feel that if we dig deeply
enough we shall find our answers, but
there is no time for digging, except for
apples. If, in French, potatoes are
pommes de terre, they are apples in the
earth, and digging is quite in order.
It is the very English eccentricity of
the denizens of Wonderland and the^
HUMPTY DUMPTY: "Now
take a good look at me! I'm
one that has spoken to a
King, I am; mayhap you'll
never see such another; and
to show you I'm not proud,
you may shake hands with
me!"And he grinned almost
from ear to ear, as he leant
forward (and as nearly as
possible fell off the wall in
doing so) end offered Alice
his hand.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ALL ABOUT ALICE
world that endears them
to us. The White Rabbit, the Ugly
Duchess, the Queen of Hearts, the
White Knight, Tweedledum and
Tweedledee, marvellously drawn by
Tenniel, are also very fully characteriz¬
ed by Carroll. They speak as we would
expect them to speak, and they are full
of an appalling self-will and vigour. But
the men are less vigorous than the
women. It is a child's world of petticoat
government in which the women
mothers, sisters, governesses are near
and magisterial, as well as wantonly
cruel, while fathers are more distant,
nicer, and busied with their own eccen¬
tric affairs.
But finally the appeal of the Alice
books is to the creative imagination, by
which space and time can become
plastic and language itself diverted
from the everyday course of
straightforward communication. There
is a strange poem, which Humpty
Dumpty kindly explains to Alice, that
sums up the possibilities of the dream¬
ing world. It is called "Jabberwocky"
and it begins:
Twas brillig, and the slithy toves
Did gyre and gimble in the wabe.
All mimsy were the borogoves,
And the mome raths outgrabe.
"Slithy" is both slimy and lithe, to
gyre is to girate, to gimble is both to
gambol like a Iamb and to turn like a
gimlet or corkscrew. Humpty Dumpty
calls these "portmanteau words,"
because, like portmanteaux, several
things can be crammed into them.
James Joyce saw the possibilities of this
Jabberwocky language and, in his great
novel Finnegans Wake, which presents
an adult, not a child's, dream, he used
the technique. What, with Carroll,
began as a joke ends, in Joyce, as the
most serious attempt ever made to show
how the dreaming mind operates.
But we leave it to the psychologists
and literary critics to find in the Alice
books great profundities and profound
ambiguities. The Freudians have seen
sexual symbols in them, which Carroll's
innocent conscious mind could not be
aware of, and the Marxists have seen
images of social tyranny and revolt. We
are wisest if we become children again
and use the books to recapture a lost in¬
nocence. We must learn to identify
ourselves with a girl in a Victorian
frock whose hair is long and golden and
whose manner has the self-assurance of
a product of the Victorian ruling class.
To be honest, Alice is not a very nice
little girl. She is far too sharp and bossy
and proud. She lacks humility,
but and this is an aspect of the British
imperialist spirit she also lacks fear. It
requires great courage, at the trial of
the Knave of Hearts, with the Queen
shouting "Off with her head!", for her
to cry: "You're nothing but a pack of
cards!" and to see the chaos of the
mass of pasteboard that, a minute ago,
was an imperialist society whirling
about her head. She is transported to
mad colonial territories and retains
something of her sanity. She is very
British and very Victorian, but she is
also admirably and universally human.
H Anthony Burgess
LEWIS CARROLL (1832-1898)
Although a brilliant logician and the author
of a number of treatises on mathematics,
Charles Lutwidge Dodgson is remembered
today as Lewis Carroll, the author of two
outstanding books for children, Alice's
Adventures in Wonderland and Through the
Looking-Glass, which are among the most
quoted and most translated books in English
literature. Dodgson was also a fine photo¬
grapher and a fair artist. The original
manuscript of Alice was illustrated with his
own pen and ink sketches, but the first
published edition was illustrated by John
Tenniel, probably the greatest of the many il¬
lustrators of the two Alice books.
TWEEDLEDUM AND TWEEDLEDEE: They
were standing under a tree, each with an
arm around the other's neck... "If you think
we're wax-works", said Tweedledum, "you
ought to pay you know. Wax-works weren't
made to be looked at for nothing. Nohow!".
"Contrariwise", added Tweedledee, "if you
think we're alive you ought to speak".
DOWN THE RABBIT-HOLE: ...she went back
to the table... end this time she found a little
bottle on it ("which was certainly not here
before", said Alice), and round its neck a
paper label, with the words "DRINK ME"
beautifully printed on it in large letters.
Drawings by Sophie and David Brabyn (aged
11), of the U.K., after Sir John Tenniel.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
PINOCCHIO
THE EVERGREEN CENTENARIAN
by halo Calvino
STRANGE though it may seem, Pinocchio is a hundred years
old. Strange... for two reasons. On the one hand it is hard to
picture him as a centenarian, on the other it seems natural
that he should always have existed, and impossible to imagine a
world without him. However, bibliographical exactitude has it that
he was born on the same day as an Italian weekly entitled the Gior-
naleper i Bambini ("Children's Newspaper") edited by Fernando
Martini, the first issue of which appeared in Rome on 7 July 1881
and contained the opening episode of "The Story of a
Marionette", by Carlo Collodi.
Today, a hundred years later, Pinocchio is world famous. His
story has been told in many languages. He has displayed a talent
ITALO CALVINO, is a major 20th-century Italian novelist whose fiction
has been translated into many languages. His published works include: II
sentiero dei nidi di ragno (1947; Eng. trans. The Path to the Nest of
Spiders, 1957); Il barone rampante (1957; The Baron in the Trees, 1959);
and II visconte dimezzato (1952) and II caviliere inesistente (1959) which
both appeared in English in The Nonexistent Knight and the Cloven Vis¬
count (1962). He is also the author of a children's book, Historias de Mar-
cobaldo. His latest novel to be published in English is If on a Winter's Night
a Traveller.
for surviving intact changes of taste, fashion, linguistic expression
and habits. Never for a moment has he been forgotten or banished
to obscurity (and this in a field as subject to the wear-and-tear of
passing time as children's literature). He has won a vast and ever-
widening circle of unconditional admirers among authors and
critics of "adult" literature, and the number of works devoted to
"Pinocchiology" has swelled accordingly.
Is there anything in Pinocchio's progress to prevent us from hail¬
ing it as a triumphal one? Just this: although in the course of the
last century Pinocchio has achieved the status of a classic in our
literary history, it is that of a minor classic. Now the time has come
to affirm that Pinocchio should be considered as one of the great
books of Italian literature, which would without it be incomplete in
certain essential respects.
I shall cite three of these gaps. First of al], the picaresque novel is
a genre which does not exist in Italian literature (with the possible
exception of the Autobiography of Benvenuto Cellini and, of
course, a handful of tales from the Decameron). In Pinocchio, a
book of vagabondage and hunger, of seedy inns, hirelings and gib¬
bets, the atmosphere and rhythm of Italian picaresque are created
with such authority and vividness that one might think that it had
always existed and would continue to exist forever.
The fantastic, "black" strain of romanticism is also missing
from nineteenth-century Italian literature. Collodi is neither Hoff¬
mann nor Poe. But the little white house gleaming in the darkness,
with the girl at the window like a waxen image, crossing her arms
on her breast and saying: "Everyone is dead... I am waiting for the
Pinocchio the marionette, newly
fashioned from a piece of wood by Gep-
petto, starts to play its first pranks. Il¬
lustration by Attilio Mussino (see cap¬
tion p. 13).
Illustration from Le aventure dt Pinocchio © Bemporad Marzocco publishers, Florence
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
to carry me off" would certainly have appealed to Poe. And
Hoffmann would surely have relished the scene of the "Butter-
man" driving his carriage through the night, its wheels wrapped
with straw and rags, drawn by twelve pairs of young donkeys wear¬
ing tiny boots... Each scene is presented with such visual force that
it is unforgettable: black rabbits bearing a coffin, assassins hooded
in coal sacks, scuttling along on tiptoe...
We do not know what reading nourished Collodi's penchant for
such romantic imagery and the constant whirl of metamorphosis
(quite unlike that in the fairy tales of Perrault, which Collodi had
translated). I do not think he could have known the extraordinary
German story-tellers of the first half of the nineteenth century, but
it is not beyond the bounds of possibility that he may have read a
French writer of the same pedigree, the Charles Nodier of La Fée
aux Miettes.
This story of initiation, the hero of which is a young carpenter
protected by an omnipotent fairy who is at one and the same time a
down-at-heels dwarf and the stunningly beautiful Queen of Sheba,
has certain themes in common with Pinocchio, but it goes without
saying that Collodi's powers of invention are far richer, lighter and
more unpredictable.
Thirdly, Pinocchio is one of those rare prose works in which the
quality of the writing is so high that each word remains engraved
on the memory, as if it were poetry, a distinction which it shares in
nineteenth-century Italian literature only with Manzoni's / Pro-
messi Sposi and certain Dialogues of Leopardi. (This quality is
equally rare in other literatures, I believe; in France it does not ap¬
pear until Flaubert). In Pinocchio one might say that this effect is
due to a natural felicity of expression, to an instinctive refusal to let
through a dull, lifeless or abstract sentence, rather than any striv¬
ing for stylistic artifice. Above all, there is the dialogue: Pinocchio
marks the appearance in our literature of the novel entirely ar¬
ticulated around dialogue.
The secret of this book in which nothing seems contrived, in
which the plot unfolds by weekly instalments (with various inter¬
ruptions, one of which, the hanging of Pinocchio, is seemingly
definitive but how could the story possibly have ended there?)
lies in the inner needs of its rhythm, of its syntax of images and
metamorphoses which determine how the episodes follow each
other in a dynamic flow.
Hence the fertilizing power of Pinocchio, at least as I have ex¬
perienced it, for ever since I began to write I have looked on it as a
model for the narration of adventures. But I believe that its in¬
fluence, which all writers in Italian have felt, whether consciously
or (more often than not) unconsciously, ought to be studied, since
Pinocchio is the first book which they all come to after (if not
before) learning the alphabet.
Hence too, another characteristic of the book, the way in which
the reader is continually invited to participate by analysing and
commenting, by dismantling and reassemblingactivities which
are always useful as long as they are undertaken in a spirit of
respect for the text.
In 1980 a symposium was held in Pescia, Italy, on the symbolism
of Pinocchio. It provided a golden opportunity to confirm what
had long been common knowledgethat the little marionette takes
a mischievous delight in unchaining the demon of interpretation,
and that this demon has an irresistible propensity to take control of
those who wish to expound the text of Pinocchio.
The centrepiece of the symposium was Ecce Puer, an essay by
Gian Luca Pierotti on Christological symbolism in Pinocchio. The
idea of reading the story of this putative son of a carpenter as an
allegory on the life of Jesus is not new; it was put forward by Piero
Bargelini in a book which appeared in 1942. But Pierotti goes much
further than his predecessor. He refers not only to the canonical
Gospels but to the Apocrypha (in which the childhood of a tur¬
bulent or frankly delinquent Jesus plays a large part); to traditions
and legends (such as those relating to the symbolism of wood:
Joseph's staff, the rod of Jesse, the tree of Eden which becomes
the wood of the cross, the Christmas tree); to certain little-known
aspects of folklore (such as the sacred marionette performances
which were still held in Florence during Lent at the end of the last
century); to popular iconography (hand-painted images of the
Madonna, with the blue of her coat running over into her hair; the
slug as an emblem of virginity).
The inference is that each of the human and animal figures, like
each of the objects and situations in the story of Pinocchio, has a
pendant in the Gospels, and vice versa. There is even a circum¬
cision (when Pinocchio's nose is pecked by the woodpeckers), a
baptism (when the old man in the nightcap pours a bowl of water
12
over Pinocchio's head), and a Last Supper (at the Inn of the Red
Lobster). Herod is Fire-Eater the puppeteer; even Pinocchio's cap
made of bread has a eucharistie significance.
A more skilful display of prestidigitation it would be hard to im¬
agine. The profusion of unexpected correspondences which Pierot¬
ti plucks from his expositor's hat is astonishing, even if, in order to
construct a narrative scheme which corresponds to the story of
Christ, he is obliged to postulate that Pinocchio tells the Gospel
story three times over, different each time with various gaps and
unorthodox additionsand by continually modifying the rules of
the game. The main thing is that the whole operation is performed
with the humour and finesse (which Pierotti fortunately possesses)
necessary to resist the temptation to demonstrate that Collodi is
linked directly to the same vein of inspiration as the evangelists
(whether there were four of them or more), or that he is seeking to
tell an edifying story, or that he is the echo of a Gnostic tradition.
The only possible conclusion is that the imagination of a civiliza¬
tion is composed of a given number of characters which can be
organized in many ways but not in every way so that two suc¬
cessful stories are bound to have many points in common. This be¬
ing so, it is possible to try to make the same kind of rapprochement
with other figures, as other contributors to the symposium did with
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
varying degrees of success: between Pinocchio and Dante; between
Pinocchio and neo-Platonism; between Pinocchio and Tantrism;
and between the Lovely Maiden with Azure Hair and Isis. Natural¬
ly, psychoanalytical symbolism was also in evidence at the sym¬
posium, not only in the most obvious equivalences (the nose which
grows guiltily longer) but also in the conflict between nature and
culturethe opposition between maternal-vegetal nature and
culture as the super-ego embodied by the talking cricket, or as the
Jungian archetypes of the Senex-Puer conflict and the Great Con¬
ciliating Mother and the unconscious.
The great absentee in all this is Collodi himself. It is as if the
book had been born of itself, just as its hero was born of a piece of
wood, but without a Geppetto to hone it down. How did the idea
of writing Pinocchio come to him?... The rest of his output does^
In the illustrations which he produced for a 1911 edition of Carlo
Collodi's classic The Adventures of Pinocchio, Attilio Mussino
created a portrait of the famous wooden marionette which became
definitive. He was the first illustrator of Collodi's work to employ
colour, taking great care to use tones which reflected the spirit of
each chapter and illustrating each stage in the story according to a
technique which has affinities with that of the modern comic strip.
He also abandoned the more or less faithful realism of earlier il¬
lustrators and instead drew the characters in the story as
caricatures, archetypes of different social classes, professions and
offices. Whenever the Florence publishing house of Bemporad
published a new edition of The Adventures of Pinocchio, Mussino
was commissioned to do the illustrations, and over a period of
35 years he produced hundreds of Pinocchio drawings. To illustrate
Italo Calvino's article we have chosen 7 of Mussino's 1911 illustra¬
tions in a sequence which runs from page 11 to the top of page 14.
(1) "Pinocchio eats sugar, but refuses to take medicine. But when
he sees the undertakers coming for him, he drinks the medicine
and feels better. Afterwards he tells a lie and, in punishment, his
nose grows longer and longer." (2) Detail from "The Land of Toys."
(3) "After five months of play, Pinocchio wakes up one fine morn¬
ing and finds a great surprise awaiting him. Pinocchio's ears
become like those of a Donkey. In a little while he changes Into a
real Donkey and begins to bray." (4) "Pinocchio is thrown into the
sea, eaten by fishes, and becomes a Marionette once more. As he
swims to land, he is swallowed by the Terrible Shark." (5) "In the
Shark's body, Pinocchio began to walk toward the faint light which
glowed in the distance... He found a little table set for dinner and
lighted by a candle stuck in a glass bottle; and near the table sat a
little old man, white as snow, eating live fish."
Illustrations from Le aventure di Pinocchio © Bemporad Marzocco publishers, Florence
Texts from The Adventures of Pinocchio, translated by Carol Della Chiesa, Macmillan, New York 1963
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
not stand comparison with his masterpiece, not even the imitation
he produced in Pipi, la Scimiottino Color di Rosa (a kind of Pinoc¬
chio in reverse who refuses to become a man), although part of it
(that concerning the brigand Golasecca) is worthy of the best
passages of Pinocchio and deserves attention from all Pinocchio
fans.
But is it not the ultimate fate of all masterpieces, or many of
them at least, to transcend their author as if he were simply an in¬
termediary or an instrument, and to impose their own existence
and needs independently of him? Writing of Pinocchio, that most
paradoxical of Italian authors, Giorgio Manganelli, concludes that
its author did not exist (or at least that it is impossible to prove that
he existed) and affirms: "from a scientific viewpoint, the
hypothesis of the author's existence is superfluous".
And so it is quite right that we should have celebrated the
centenary of Pinocchio's birth in 198 1 , that we should be preparing
to celebrate next year his appearance in a book (1883), and that in
eight years time (the centenary of the death of Paolo Lorenzini* in
1890) we should return to the question of whether or not Carlo
Collodi ever actually existed.
* The real name of Carlo Collodi. Italo Calvino
In 1972 the French painter, cartoonist, novelist and film-maker
Roland Topor drew a series of highly symbolic, almost
nightmarish illustrations for Pinocchio in which he presented
a kind of psychoanalytical interpretation of the wooden
marionette. "I adore Pinocchio", Topor has said. "He is the on¬
ly literary figure who is of our time, modern, authentic."
"I wonder where the old Pinocchio of wood has hid¬
den himself?" "There he is", answered Geppetto.
And he pointed to a large marionette leaning against a
chair, head turned to one side, arms hanging limp and
legs twisted under him.
Pinocchio as drawn by an 11-year-old Italian boy,
Walter Pesaresi.
Drawing © Scuola Media Statale, Rome
14
Enrico Mazzanti, born in Florence in 1852,
was the first illustrator of The Adventures of
Pinocchio. Left, one of the 62 illustrations
Mazzanti drew when Collodi's work was
published in book form in 1883.
Illustration from Pinocchio e la sua immagine
© Bemporad Marzocco publishers, Florence
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
HUCKLEBERRY FENN
AN EPIC OF SELF-DISCOVERY
by Malcolm Bradbury
r
IT has often been said that many of the
greatest American novels are really, in
the end, boys' books: James Fenimore
Cooper's Leatherstocking Tales, Herman
Melville's great sea-tale Moby Dick,
Stephen Crane's story of a young man in
war, The Red Badge of Courage, even
Ernest Hemingway's battle stories or J.D.
Salinger's painful but comic exploration of
adolescent crisis, The Catcher in the Rye.
Many American novels have been stories of
adventure rather than explorations of socie¬
ty, and this no doubt helps to bring them
closer to young people; so, too, does that
famous spirit of innocence that runs
through so much American writing.
However, few of these books are really
about the experience and the mythology of
childhood, its real dreams and anxieties. But
there is one that is; there is little doubt that,
of all the great American novels, none
comes closer to being truly a children's book
than Mark Twain's The Adventures of
Huckleberry Finn.
Yet Twain's story of two people, a white
boy and an adult black slave, floating
adventurously on a raft down North
America's central river, the Mississippi, to
get away from the tangles of adult society in
which they have become trapped, has long
been seen not just as a classic story for
children but as a fundamental human myth.
T.S Eliot once called Huck Finn "one of the
great permanent symbolic figures of fiction,
not unworthy to take a place with Ulysses,
Faust, Don Quixote, Don Juan, Hamlet and
other discoveries which man has made about
himself." Ernest Hemingway identified the
book as the true starting place of modern
American literature, the place from which
all other books begin.
Whether Mark Twain consciously
understood the potential of the story he was
telling is very doubtful. He began the book
as a sequel to an earlier children's story, The
Adventures of Tom Sawyer, and, as Huck
tells us in his own voice at the beginning,
"You don't know about me without you
have read a book by the name of The
Adventures of Tom Sawyer; but that ain't
no matter." Tom Sawyer is a fine children's
book, and is still widely read today. But
MALCOLM BRADBURY is professor of
American Studies at the University of East
Anglia, Norwich (UK). He is the author of many
books of criticism, including forthcoming studies
of Saul Bellow and The Modern American Novel.
He is also a novelist whose most recentpublished
work. The History Man, appeared in 1975. His
latest novel. Rates of Exchange, will be published
shortly.
"I guessed I wouldn't stay in one place, but just tramp right across the country,
mostly night-times, and hunt and fish to keep alive."
Huckleberry Finn is a great one, a work
both of lasting human weight and genuine
originality.
Ask a child what it is that makes this such
a remarkable children's book, and you will
probably be told that it is the book's
celebration of Huck Finn's freedom and in¬
dependence. Huck does not have to go to
school, or accept the rules of daily life; he
seems able to determine where he wants to
go and he chooses to act by his own stan¬
dards. Bored with "living in a house all the
time," tired of being "sivilized" by the
Widow Douglas, threatened by the return of
his brutal father, he takes to the river to
secure his own fortunes.
His adventures on the floating raft and
off it, on the riverbank, are spectacular,
somewhere between play and serious living;
he travels through the middle of his country
and discovers its places and spaces. His life
on the raft protects him, and gives him a
continuous means of escape; he moves with
nature and in nature's world. The river as a
moving and powerful force bears him on,
initiates him into endless new experience; he
begins a quest that might go on for ever. He
comes to enjoy and learn from the simple
things which are nonetheless the essentials
of life. And above all he tells his own story,
speaks always in his own voice, and judges
things in his own way.
Many readers have celebrated Huck's
spirit of freedom and his role as the natural
boy who is growing into the natural man,
and found in it a fundamental western and
American myth. It is the myth of the self-
created person growing up beyond the limits
of society in innocence and wonder. Out of
the world of nature come conscience and
understanding, nowhere more so than when
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Huck realizes that his companion on the
raft, Nigger Jim, who will be returned to
slavery if he is recaptured, is entitled to
freedom too.
Yet Huck's story is not one of a total and
innocent freedom, rather of a painful grow¬
ing up: even his play moves into agonizing
discovery. Huck's adventures are often
flamboyant, but they involve not just comic
excitement but a struggle with the complex
society around him on the one hand, and his
own conscience and nature on the other. His
journey begins with the escape from the
brutality of his father, but also involves the
discovery of his father's mortality. And it
moves through dangers that are not just out¬
side Huck but within him, as he realizes the
complexity of his own conscience and also
realizes that, in wanting Nigger Jim's
freedom, he could go to Hell. If society is
often unkind, so is nature; and the river
itself is threat as well as promise.
Huckleberry Finn is a novel about the
river as a great but dangerous god, but it is
also a social river. It is America's main
artery, in the years when the book is set,
before the American Civil War. The very
direction of its flow is ironic, for the raft
floating downstream is drifting away from
the free states, where slavery was abolished,
to the slave states, where Nigger Jim is in
fact in greater danger.
Mark Twain realized this irony as he
wrote the book, and considered diverting his
raft up the Ohio River. But it is part of the
book's honesty, and its sense of growing
depth, that he did not. Bringing his story
closer to slavery, Twain took his theme of
freedom closer to complexity. The Adven¬
tures of Tom Sawyer was set in the lasting
playtime of childhood. This, its sequel, is a
book in which its simpler yet far deeper hero
begins to grow up. When Tom Sawyer ap¬
pears at the end of Huckleberry Finn, bring¬
ing childish adventures with him, we grow
Illustration of an episode
from The Adventures of
Tom Sawyer shows Tom
Sawyer, Huckleberry Finn
and Joe Harper during
their pirate expedition. "It
seemed glorious sport to
be feasting in that wild
free way in the virgin
forest of an unexplored
and uninhabited island, far
from the haunts of men,
and they said they never
would return to civiliza¬
tion. The climbing fire lit
up their faces and threw
its ruddy glare upon the
pillared tree trunks of their
forest temple, and upon
the varnished foliage and
festooning vines."
i^l*"
<É
\
^ ** * j ^k
pk . ^^^fc.
WEmák^
**** iWur
é*? ^p£-
"
Drawing Worth Brehm, from The Adventures of Tom Sawyer, Harper and Brothers, New York
The action of The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn centres on the river which Mark Twain described as the "great Mississippi, the
majestic, the magnificent Mississippi, rolling its mile-wide tide along, shining in the sun". This Currier and Ives print shows cotton being
loaded onto a steamboat of the kind Huck and the fugitive slave Jim might have seen as they floated downstream. Mark Twain's own
house in Hartford, Connecticut, was built to resemble a Mississippi steamboat.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
impatient; Huck is now not a child at play,
but a complex character.
One reason why we feel this is that Huck
does tell the story in his own voice, and
through his own vision. To take this simple
and uneducated child from the American
frontier, the boy who wants to get away
from the house to smoke, and believes in
ghosts and simple superstitions, and
transform him into a voice of real ex¬
perience was Mark Twain's greatest fic¬
tional triumph. His originality was to give a
language built on vernacular and dialect, on
instinct and childhood judgement, a total
literary authority. It is a language that sets
itself against that of those in authority, the
language of those who are "sivilized" or ut¬
ter stable moral truths; it is a voice of play
and discovery.
We can feel Twain relaxing into it, not
just because it is comic, though the novel is
a classic of comedy, but because it has moral
dignity. It was a release of the child in Twain
himself, with all its sense of discovery, and
all its openness and vulnerability. The rela¬
tion of the child to the adult, the child ex¬
pectant and enquiring, the adult fixed in
social practices and impostures, is central to
the book. But it is the child's voice, unable
to take as truth the "blather" and social
pretension and hostility, that counts. "If I
never learnt nothing else out of Pap, I learnt
that the best way to get along with his kind
of people is to let them have their own
way," Huck says. But he has his own way
too, the voice of his own self-reliant
wisdom.
At the end of the novel, with Huck Finn's
complicated adventures down the river over,
and Nigger Jim set free, Huck's ideal of
escape and freedom is expressed again: "...I
reckon I got to light out for the territory
ahead of the rest, because Aunt Sally, she's
going to adopt me and sivilize me, and I
can't stand it. I been there before."
The territory is the frontier to the West,
where Tom Sawyer wants to "go for howl¬
ing adventures amongst the Indians," but it
is also another open space of nature in
which Huck's dream of flight and escape
might be again fulfilled. It has been rightly
thought a very American ending, celebrating
the free-standing ideal of the American
frontier, the dream of a good world beyond
society, "sivilization," and, indeed,
women, a place of new brotherhood. But
the flight is a familiar one in children's
books everywhere: the idea of a new world,
a fresh island, where old responsibilities
derived from the world of adults can be set
aside and a new life of self-sufficient adven¬
ture begun in nature is one of the lasting
myths of children's fiction. Huck's raft, like
Jim Hawkins' island, in Robert Louis
Stevenson's Treasure Island, is a place as
much of danger as of escape. No doubt
Huck's territory, if not too much spoiled by
Tom Sawyer's "howling adventures,"
would be the same.
For Huckleberry Finn is not a novel of
pure escape. It is a novel in which Huck flees
in order to discover to discover new places
and spaces, the workings of nature and
society, to discover himself, but above all to
discover what he "can't stand." Like
Holden Caulfield, in J.D. Salinger's The
Catcher in the Rye (a book that clearly owes
much to Huckleberry Finn), Huck protects
enough of childhood to keep his innocence
and seeks enough of adulthood to acquire
judgement. Huck "lights out for the ter¬
ritory," and Holden Caulfield plunges into
the big city world of New York to escape
from his preparatory school and discover
himself. Huck creates a child's Mississippi
River, Holden an adolescent's New York.
Both leave fixed places to discover changing
ones, and both end up not only reinter¬
preting the adult world but by finding a
language, a morally vigorous speech that
makes the novels which tell their stories
works not only of children's literature, but
of serious literature everywhere.
I Malcolm Bradbury
Old Man Dnieper
Photos right were taken during
the filming of a Soviet TV produc¬
tion of The Adventures of Tom
Sawyer which is astonishingly
faithful to the spirit and detail of
Mark Twain's novel. The three-
hour film, directed by Stanislav
Govorukhin, was shot on loca¬
tion with the banks of the
Dnieper taking the place of the
Mississippi valley. Above, after a
meal of fish Tom and Huck
stretch out in front of the fire and
Huck lights up his pipe. Below,
Tom and Huck watching a
steamer on the "Mississippi".
>
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE COMIC STRIP
BALLOONS AROUND THE WORLD
'B
iASICALLY, you know," Gen¬
eral de Gaulle once remarked
to André Malraux, "Tintín is
my only rival on the international scene.
This joking admission by the French
President of the comic strip hero's
universal scope and appeal gave, as it
were, "political" consecration to Tintín,
the little newspaper reporter invented in
1929 by the Belgian artist Hergé (a
pseudonym made up of the initials of his
real name, Remi, Georges) and whose
adventures cover half a century of con¬
temporary history.
Today cartoon strip heroes continue
to fascinate tens of millions of readers
throughout the world. A product of the
mass communications era, they are the
modern counterparts of the heroes of
folktales and adventure stories.
Comics, a synthesis of writing and
drawings of the most diverse kind, on
by Michel Pierre
Though the comic strip owes its
development to modern printing and
distribution methods, it is rooted in an
old tradition. In Europe, its origins can
be traced back to the images d'Epinal in
France and to the picture stories of the
German Wilhelm Busch (1832-1908)
and the Swiss Rodolphe Topffer
(1799-1846).
In Japan, the comic's early ninth cen¬
tury ancestors, the Choju-Guiga
Emakimono (stories on scrolls of paper),
were a mixture of war reporting,
philosophical legends and scenes from
everyday life. Lian huan hua (little il¬
lustrated books) existed even in ancient
China. From the 1920s onwards they
developed considerably and, after 1939,
they began to report on aspects of con¬
temporary China, as well as adapting in
picture form the most famous Chinese
novels, such as The Monkey King Sun
Wukong (see page 28) and The Three
Kingdoms, using time-honoured draw¬
ing techniques. Africa also turned to its
sources in producing picture versions of
ancient legends such as The Adventures
of Leuk the Hare, after a text written by
Leopold Sédar Senghor.
But it was in the United States at the
end of the nineteenth century that the
strip cartoon was created in its modern
form, increasingly sophisticated tech¬
niques made it possible to integrate text
and images in which the various
characters expressed themselves in
"bubbles" or "balloons".
Early comic strips like The Katzenjam¬
mer Kids, which first appeared in 1897,
met with immediate success and were
the forerunners of dozens of popular
heroes including Mickey Mouse (1929)
and Peanuts (1950) to cite some of the
most universally known.
S KB
22 R&M%uim®Jte£i&±.-&, J!A^sm¡sma*o
Ä^SÄ-itf» SIESTA. -fc#, ft-M» Wfcëifc
the border between literature and film
where text and image interpenetrate,
have given rise to an art form that holds
great appeal for the younger generation.
But while the child's imagination has
little difficulty in penetrating into the
universe of comics, adults, unused to
this medium, find it difficult to decipher.
And this difference in approach often
gives rise to misunderstanding.
MICHEL PIERRE, of France, is a staff member
of the college of education of the Essonne
(France) and a book editor with Unesco and with
the French publishing house Études Vivantes. He
is the author of La Bande Dessinée (The Comic
Strip) and a regular contributor to the French
magazines A Suivre and Magazine Littéraire.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Europe has given birth to a specific
style of comics, thanks in particular to
the productions of the Belgian school
with its well-constructed plots, fearless
heroes and strikingly simple drawing
techniques. Latin America has also
developed an original style, especially
Argentina where such artists as Quino
(the creator o/Mafalda, in 1964), Oski,
Mordillo, Munoz and Sampayo all pro¬
duce comics.
One must also mention the work of
artists from Indonesia, Yugoslavia,
Finland, Algeria and Angola who testify
to the vitality of the medium in all parts
of the globe.
It often happens that a character in a
cartoon created in a specific culture and
1. Drawing from The Cry that Kills <Q Atoss
Takemoto, Matsuda, Japan
2. Waterside Yarns or The Marsh Outlaws
and the Lion Inn. Drawing © Publications
Orientalistes de France, Paris
3. Mafalda's Gang. Drawing © Quino
4. Corto Maltese, The Ethiopics.^ Drawing
Hugo Pratt © Casterman, Paris
5. Leuk the Hare. Illustration G. Lorofi © Les
Nouvelles Editions Africaines, 1975, Dakar and
Abidjan
6. Nasdine Hodja. Drawing © P. Leguen, R.
Lecureux.
7. Snoopy. Drawing Schulz © 1982 United Fea¬
tures Syndicate Inc.
8. Tintin et L'Ile Noire. Drawing Hergé © Cas¬
terman, Paris
9. Mickey and the Mysterious Island.
Drawing © Walt Disney Productions. By special
permission of Waif Disney Productions (France).
designed for a certain audience takes on
a new significance in another context.
For example, Corto Maltese, created by
the Italian Hugo Pratt for Italian and
French magazines, was adopted by the
Angolan freedom fighters who saw in
the thoughts and deeds of this left-wing
adventurer a reflection of their own
struggle and preoccupations.
Comics can also provide a means of
communication between civilizations
and cultures. This was the case when
Nasrudin Hodja, the legendary hero of
Muslim humour, became the hero of a
French strip cartoon published by the
children's weekly Vaillant, in 1955.
Thanks to the immense popularity it
has acquired with young readers, the
comic strip is gradually establishing its
position among the contemporary com¬
munication media. It is sometimes laud¬
ed excessively, but more often unjustly
criticized. It now remains for it to con¬
vince the last critics and win the final
battle.
Michel Pierre
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
LATIN AMERICA:
TALL STORIES FOR SMALL READERS
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
¿rpiilHEY took the gold and left us
the words," said the Nobel
Prizewinning Chilean poet
Pablo Neruda of the Iberian conquistadors.
Since, with the exception of Paraguay, we
have never been bilingual, and since our in¬
digenous languages have not been transcrib¬
ed, we in Latin America learn to read in the
languages of those "words" even the sacred
texts of the Quiche Maya: the Popol Vuh,
the Book of Chilam-Balam, and the Annals
of the Cakchiqueles.
The language of the conquistadors thus
became the only official language, the
language of administration and justice, of
education and writing. Even today our in¬
digenous populations live in a situation
which modern Latin American sociologists
have called "internal colonialism". In order
to exercise their rights as citizens they must
learn to read and write in "the language of
the whites": universal suffrage exists in few
countries, and even there it is a recent in¬
novation. Those of our compatriots who are
the victims of such discrimination must
speak or at least understand our Spanish (or
Portuguese in Brazil) when they need to
communicate with us, while we do not make
the slightest effort to understand Quechua,
Aymara and other indigenous languages, or
those African languages which have been
transplanted to America.
The cultural colonialization initiated by
colonialization pure and simple goes on. In
some countries a newly emergent national
conscience has begun to collect and preserve
in writing indigenous traditions and legends,
the mythology and signs which abound in
the dreams and languages of our Indians
and Blacks, but so far these works possess
more anthropological than literary interest.
And so, whatever our ethnic origin or
ideology, all those of us today who practice
the terrorism of an official language and
culture originating in Europe are "col¬
onizers". In a word, all those of us who
went to school.
But it was precisely at school long
before we realized that we were becoming
the willing or unwilling accomplices of this
vast discriminatory operation that we
became aware that we were ourselves endur¬
ing the "perpetual dictatorship" of the
hydra-headed adult: parents, teachers, con¬
fessors, traffic policemen, shopkeepers,
bystanders. They knew what was right for
JORGE ENRIQUE ADOUM, Ecuadorian poet
and writer, is the author of some ten books of
poetry, a novel, two plays and many essays. He is
currently a member of the editorial staff of the
Unesco Courier.
The Black Corsair (in background at right) attacks one of "the great Spanish
galleons which brought to Europe the treasures of central America, Mexico and
the equatorial region". This illustration by G. Gamba appeared in an Italian edition,
published in 1921, of Emilio Salgari's II Corsaro Nero.
us, what we ought to say and do; they knew
what we wanted better than we did
ourselves. And at home our parents, as well
as giving us the food they liked and ordain¬
ing the bedtime that suited them, imposed
on us their favourite stories which were pro¬
bably, we suspect, the only ones they knew.
When we reached a certain age we had
had our fill of these "children's stories"(l),
perhaps because we were tired of their
message and had had no desire to be inno¬
cent, diligent, or submissive; we had lost in¬
terest in stories in which, Tom Thumb ex¬
cepted, the heroine was always a girl who
had been or would be one day, a princess
(1) See "The Sting in the Fairy Tale", Unesco
Courier, January 1979.
("girls' things" we called them, even though
later on we should feel something akin to
love for Andersen's little mermaid), nor did
we want to be the prince whose appearance,
albeit decisive, comes only at the end of the
story. We boys wanted to escape from an
authoritarian, dictatorial, restrictive reality
which did not even leave us the right to
dream. Alice (in a book which we stupidly
refused to read at that time, for the same
reason) had only to open her eyes for all to
change to reality, but in our case closing our
eyes was not enough to provide escape from
reality, from the clutches of the ubiquitous,
omnipotent adult, whose omniscience
asphyxiated us. And our first rebellion
against this other form of colonialism lay in
reading: as soon as we could read for
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
In Jules Verne's novel The Children of Captain Grant,
Mary and Robert Grant embark on the Duncan in search
of their father whom they eventually find, after many
adventures on land and sea, on an island near New
Zealand. Left, an incident from the story which with
20,000 Leagues under the Sea and The Mysterious Island
belongs to Verne's series of novels with a nautical set¬
ting. This illustration, by the French artist Edouard Riou,
appeared in the first edition, published in 1867-8.
ourselves, we read those books "for grown¬
ups" which adults had never read to us(2).
To compensate for what appeared as a
kind of immanent injustice at home, at
school, in neighbourhood and town, what
we looked for in reading was getting away
from home, as Tom Sawyer did, bringing a
little order to life, and righting wrongs
(although we would never have dared to go
to a cemetery at night as he did) like some
junior Robin Hood defending the innocent
and denouncing the guilty. But we "iden¬
tified" more with Mark Twain's other hero,
Huckleberry Finn (in order to be like him we
even tried vainly to make a corncob pipe
from the husks of the cooked maize we ate
each day at home), because of his authorita¬
rian and unjust father, because of the socie¬
ty he abandoned and which rejected him,
because of his adventure in the treasure
cave (Ali Baba on the Mississippi) and his
voyage on the raft; we also suffered with^
(2) Books came from Spain, such as the Tales
published in Spanish by the house of Calleja in a
format no bigger than a cigarette packet and
which were easy to read surreptitiously, and the
books from the publishing house of Sopeña,
which were later also published in Argentina. In
1889 José Martí created in New York the
magazine La Edad de Oro ("The Golden Age")
"A monthly publication of recreation and in¬
struction for the children of America". Four
issues were actually published which Cuban
children have been able to read in many later edi¬
tions, but they contained more instruction than
recreation. The most important Latin American
author of children's books, Monteiro Lobato,
founded in 1918 Brazil's first publishing house
(before then books came from Portugal). He
created figures well-known to all Brazilian
readers, such as Emilia, a talking rag doll obsess¬
ed with correcting the errors of Nature, Doña
Benta who accepts that children's creative im¬
agination changes reality, and Tía Nastasia (Aunt
Anastasia) who sees sin and evil in everything she
does not know, and the Viscount of Sabugos, an
adult who only believes what is written in books.
© Ll%(StS
PRÉFAI L
_
The Three Musketeers, Athos, Porthos and Aramis, as
depicted with their inseparable companion D'Artagnan
on the opening page of the 1846 edition of Alexandre
Dumas' novel.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
"...I embraced [the little finger] in both my arms and put the tip of it with the ut¬
most respect to my lips." Drawing by the Cuban artist Daniel Garcia Rojas was
produced for a recent edition of Gulliver's Travels. It illustrates an episode in
Gulliver's second voyage, when he visits the island of Brobdingnag which is
peopled by giants.
the threat of an imminent and enforced
return to school routine after his adventures
on the great rivers of north America.
These exceptions apart, we hardly ever
found any child or adolescent figures in our
reading whose destiny we could share or ap¬
propriate for ourselves. Rudyard Kipling's
characters did not command our loyalty. As
far as Mowgli was concerned our opinions
tended to vacillate rather than diverge. On
the one hand we understood that men were
"the chosen race", and this did not fail to
reassure us when faced with the black pan¬
ther and the yellow-eyed tiger; but at the
same time we reproached him for a kind of
ingratitude towards the animals which had
saved him, fed him and welcomed him like
the real king of the jungle, a precursor of
Tarzan. And qualities which we detested
also reappeared in these books: hierarchy,
authority, the duty of obedience. Kim, on
the other hand, we judged summarily and
unconditionally as a traitor. It is not that we
were particularly precocious or perspica¬
cious; it was just that we had been studying
the independence period at school and we
knew that many descendants of Spaniards
born in America had instigated and fought
in the wars of independence, so that we
could not justify Kim's activities as a secret
agent in an army foreign to the country of
his birth, except by what our teacher called
"links of blood". As for Collodi's Pinoc¬
chio, a book we had been led to read after
seeing a film, we were already sufficiently
steeped in lying to know that your nose did
not grow if you told lies, and with the
aplomb of the guilty we were not unduly
disturbed by the "Talking Cricket" of the
22
conscience. On the other hand, we relished
the bravado with which Pinocchio lived the
life of a dissipated adult, even though this
was not our greatest ambition.
Perhaps we admired our adult "models"
adventurers, corsairs, pirates and
sailors because Adventure with a capital A
had to take place at sea. We had to put
distance oceans between us and injustice
which, because we had not travelled, seemed
to us purely local.
Our first heroes,, in both senses of the
word, were the characters of the Italian
Emilio Salgari: Sandokan (the name itself
rings like an epic) the Malay corsair who
fought against the British colonial
authorities, the Black Corsair and the Red
Corsair who braved the Spanish governors
of the Caribbean and who through a cruel
quirk of fate fell in love with the daughter or
niece of their worst enemy. From
Guatemala to Uruguay, from Puerto Rico
to Ecuador, we formed gangs not minding
which side we were on. (But we had no girls
to play Yolanda, the daughter of the Black
Corsair, who was Queen of the Caribbean).
The same thing happened when we played
The Three Musketeers only the first
episode, since we all wanted to be d'Ar-
tagnan with swords made for us by the
local carpenter from pointed pieces of wood
with cross-pieces for handles: there was
never anyone to play Milady or Constance.
For us boys, anyway, this was the least in¬
teresting side of the story.
Perhaps because of so much sea and so
many islands; because of the vision of boar¬
ding parties and hand-to-hand fighting with
pirates which kept us awake at nights;
because of our envy of Robinson Crusoe
who had managed to survive for twenty-
eight years, two months and nineteen days
on an island where no one could enforce
their wishes on him; because of Gulliver's
Travels (we did not venture further than the
first voyage which made us realize the im¬
becility of war, and thus missed the second
where the stupidities of the powerful are ex¬
posed, and the cornucopia of wonders in the
third, with its flying island where talking is
done with objects instead of words and
where food has geometric shapes); because
of the children of Captain Grant (at first
Verne had bored us, perhaps because the
journeys to the moon and to the centre of
the earth were too much for us, but later on
we came to love the enigmatic and con¬
tradictory Captain Nemo); because of the
adventures of the Count of Monte Cristo
with his hoard of treasure which would
allow him that just revenge which seemed
proportionately speaking similar to our
own... for all these reasons, some of us left
home and became, as destiny dictated,
waiters, travelling salesmen, proof-readers
and booksellers, until the day when each
one found the place earmarked for him in
society, as they say, through a kind
of fatalistic spirit rather than any social
determinism.
The thirst for justice and the great dream
of adventure had waned in most cases into a
"practical spirit", and although some still
wished to transform life and the world,
almost all became tradesmen, soldiers,
employees of one kind or another,
policemen, economists, informers, am¬
bassadors or notaries.
Nor was the fate of our sisters and girl
cousins more enviable: after dreaming of the
Prince Charming who would deliver them
from servitude, they now began to weep
with Louisa M. Alcott's Little Women and
then later for such books were forbidden
by the nuns at schoolthey thought they
had the right to the same destiny in love as
Madame Bovary or Eugénie Grandet
(without the same end, obviously)... and
ended up by making the best match their
parents had been able to find for them or by
yielding to the never very original declara¬
tions of the local Don Juan.
However, many of us had discovered, at
home or elsewhere, a fabulous and
boundless continent: that of literature. A
few made their home there and continued to
live there until today or until they died;
others made only a fleeting visit: they got to
know Walter Scott and James Fenimore
Cooper, Jack London and Paul Feval,
Eugène Sue, Charles Dickens and Victor
Hugo, and maybe Saroyan and Salinger.
And those who followed us discovered
other, recent treasures: Le Petit Prince, The
Diary of Ann Frank...
But I realize that I am writing in the past
tense. Not because of nostalgia for a distant
adolescence, nor because of the tenacious
dream of liberty and justice, but because
since then the boys have adopted an almost
exclusive diet of picture books and comic
strips and the girls read photo-novels the
kind of trivia churned out by a factory of
sub-literature, in praise of wealth and even
racism which today appear regularly in
magazines. And because, in other countries,
adolescents of both sexes, caught in a dif¬
ficult moment of their collective destiny, are
themselves heroes of history and have no
time to read stories with heroes, because,
turning up noses already used to the smell of
gunpowder, they rightly say to themselves
that literature can wait.
H Jorge Enrique Adoum
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
This illustration for an African folk-tale, "Children of the Forest", was drawn by the Sudanese artist Abdulahi Mohd Eltaieb. It won a prize in
the "Noma Concours for Children's Picture Book Illustrations '78", a competition organized by the Asian Cultural Centre for Unesco.
THE CHILD-HERO
IN AFRICAN FOLKTALES
by Aminata Sow Fall
AM I NATA SOW FALL, of Senegal, is director of the department of
literature and intellectual property in her country's ministry of culture. She
is the author of two published novels. Le Revenant and La Grève des Bat¬
tu, and of the forthcoming L'Appel des Armes. She is co-author of school
textbooks on grammar, French literature, and theatrical expression.
BEFORE describing the role of the child-hero in African folk¬
lore, it is well to recall briefly the place occupied by the
folktale in the African universe. Although traditionally
recounted by that multiple-part actor the story-teller, the folktale is
essentially a group production and it provides an unrivalled
medium for the transmission of African wisdom. It expresses the
deepest aspirations of the community and ensures its cohesion by
maintaining value systems and beliefs necessary for its equilibrium
and survival. Failings are exposed and the marginal members of
society are punished by man or by supernatural forces, according
to their misdeeds. The lesson that emerges from the African
One of the most popular
children's books in Tanzania tells
the story of a boy called Kiungan-
dua who fought successfully in
his tribe's war against European
invaders. Eventually he is cap¬
tured by the enemy but commits
suicide to avoid disclosing the
secrets of his group's successes.
The book written in Kiswahili by
H.A.K. Mwenegoha, is entitled
Shujaa wa Vijana ("The Youths'
Hero"). In this illustration
Kiungandua is shown in conver¬
sation with a veteran warrior of
his tribe.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
folktale is a warning to anyone who might be tempted to stray
away from the moral principles and religious concepts of the
community.
In addition to its entertainment value, the folktale is therefore
essentially didactic. With its capacity to reach beyond everyday
reality into the realms of fantasy and the fantastic it offers wide
scope for the child's imagination. It is also a means of developing
the child's belief in supernatural phenomena and of initiating him
into the metaphysics of myth and cosmogonie legend.
Concern for ethical teaching emerges particularly strongly in
tales in which the hero is a child. According to the circumstances,
the child-hero embodies either values that strengthen society or
destructive counter-values. But he can also assume metaphysical
dimensions which make him a saviour or the embodiment of the
spirit of evil in all its absurdity.
The child-hero is thus a symbol and for this reason the same
character can be given different names according to the geographic
region concerned and the adaptations which the tale undergoes to
suit ethnic particularities. The name is less important than the sym¬
bolism; often, in fact, the hero is simply called "the child".
There are three sorts of child-hero in African folklore: the model
child, the boisterous child and the child of evil.
There are numerous versions of the tale of the model child. The
child-hero is often an orphan girl, ill-treated by a wicked step¬
mother, who bullies and punishes her mercilessly and burdens her
with painful, back-breaking tasks. Without any help from her
weak, virtually non-existent father, the little orphan obeys all her
cruel stepmother's whims and orders until the day when, ex¬
asperated by the girl's patience and forbearance, the wicked
woman demands the impossible.
In Birago Diop's tale, La Cuiller Sale (The Dirty Spoon), little
Cumba is ordered to go and wash a spoon in the "Daayaan" sea,
which she can only reach by following paths used by wild animals
and crossing a strange kingdom peopled by supernatural creatures.
Thanks to her gentle good behaviour, she eludes all the traps and
snares and returns with the washed spoon and great riches.
The stepmother, who never expected the orphan to come back
alive, is surprised and very jealous. She decides to send her own
daughter on an expedition to the "Daayaan" sea and starts prepar¬
ing a magnificent reception for her return. But the girl dies, her
body is eaten by the wild beasts of the forest and all that remains is
her heart which a vulture drops in the calabash in which her mother
is preparing couscous for the feast. A double punishment has thus
been meted out to the heartless stepmother and her insolent
daughter.
All versions of the model child tales follow the same pattern.
They provide models of behaviour and a lesson in patience, obe¬
dience, respect and discretion which enable a child to overcome the
most difficult situations. So that the lesson should be properly
understood, the model child in these tales is often opposed to his
negative counterpart, the spoilt child. Thanks to this technique, all
problems related to the child's education can be treated globally.
The model child inspires tenderness and admiration, while the
spoilt child, who is rude and disrespectful, incurs only anger and
the audience's approval for the terrible punishment which always
overtakes him, sometimes along with innocent people. The spoilt
child is shown as a social scourge and parents and the whole com¬
munity are therefore advised to teach the basic moral virtues to
their children.
In Petit Mari, one of the tales recorded by Birago Diop, a little
girl's obstinacy drives her brother to suicide and her mother to
madness, and engulfs all the other members of the family in
catastrophe in the- depths of the sea. These tales are not intended
only for children; adults are also warned of the price to be paid for
wickedness and injustice.
Frequent manifestations of providence stress the intangibility of
the borderline between the real and unreal, the visible and invisible.
In several tales the dead mother comes to the aid of her maltreated
daughter. In Le Pagne Noir (The Black Loincloth), by Bernard
Dadié, little Aiwa finally triumphs over her wicked stepmother by
bringing back the shroud which her dead mother has given her in¬
stead of the black loincloth she has been told to wash white.
African folklore abounds in tales about unruly, mischievous and
naughty children. Jabu, Ndaw and Samba-of-the-night (in Les
Nouveaux Contes d'Amadou Koumba) and the "Little Terror" (in
Le Pagne Noir) are a few examples of such children. The extraor¬
dinary circumstances surrounding the hero's birth and his extreme
precociousness are characteristic features of these tales. In his
mother's womb the child already presses her to give birth to him
and from the very day he is born he speaks, gives himself a name
and starts on his exploits. On the day of his birth the Little Terror
traps a deer after having carried a meal to his father in the fields.
On the second day he dips a panther in boiling water and on the
third he puts to flight all the kings of the jungle.
Several versions of these tales recall episodes from Tom Thumb.
The child-hero foils the witch's evil designs and saves his brothers
or uncles by substituting the witch's own daughters for them. In
this way, the witch, not realizing what she is doing, cuts her
daughters' throats. All attempts at revenge fail for the child, who
has hidden powers, always manages to outwit the sorceress.
Beliefs play an important role in these tales and strangeness is
not considered out of place, as can be seen from this reply by a
mother to her son who has just commanded his own birth: "As
you have delivered yourself, you can also give yourself a name!"
Nor does this strangeness stem merely from a taste for the super¬
natural and for extraordinary adventures fired by an imagination
that transcends terrestrial limits. Here extraordinary phenomena
Taken from a book of popular
tales and legends from Guinea,
this drawing illustrates the story
of the combat between the spider
and the wasp. The spider often
plays an important role in west
African stories of the jungle,
while the hare, seen here among
the onlookers, figures largely in
tales of the savannah.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Left, the cover of an edition of the 7a/es of
Amadou Koumba, by the Senegalese writer
Birago Diop, shows an African village where
animals are endowed with human qualities.
The illustration was drawn by a boy from
Cameroun, Balbo Oussoumanou.
Photo Naud ki a A A , Paris
Leuk the Hare, a character in a story by
Leopold Sédar Senghor, as depicted by
Françoise N'Thépé, a nine-year-old
Camerounian girl.
are part and parcel of life, and the child, through the mystery of his
conception and birth and his lack of speech during the first months
of life, is held, in certain African societies, to be very close to in¬
visible forces. It is not surprising therefore that the child should be
' central to such tales.
By his deeds and by the very nature of his unusual personality
the unruly child disturbs the laws of nature, but he never deviates
from the social ethic or from the community's basic beliefs. He is a
saviour. He urges caution when warning his family of the evil
designs of the witch who has disguised herself as a jujube tree laden
with fruit or as a beautiful woman seeking a husband. And he
pokes fun at the mighty by exposing their worst faultsgreed,
selfishness, and so on.
The character of the child of evil is more difficult to understand.
All his actions are blameworthy. His parents often die when he is
born or shortly afterwards, which suggests that he is the bearer of
misfortune. He neglects the advice given by his father on his death¬
bed and he squanders the family fortune. Prompted by an unquen¬
chable thirst for destruction, he returns evil for good and kills all
those, whether men or animals, who have shown him kindness.
The existence of this type of hero in African folklore is no acci¬
dent. It can be explained partly by a belief in the reincarnation of
discontented ancestors who return to earth to wreak vengeance.
The child of evil therefore "existed" long before his parents. As
Samba-of-the-night declares:
"I am Samba, born last night
Older than my mother
Older than my father
The same age as
My younger brothers and sisters
Yet to be born."
The child of evil can also be perceived as an evil spirit, the son of
the devil. According to popular belief, such children were unmask¬
ed by soothsayers, and, to ensure that they would not bring misfor¬
tune on to their family, they were deposited in the jungle at the
foot of a tree so that they could return to their true realm.
Tales with child-heroes are not merely designed to satisfy the
child's need to escape into the world of dreams and fantasy. They
embody the hopes, fears and fantasies of the entire community.
Aminata Sow Fall
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
I GOHA
THE SIMPLE
OR
THE WISDOM
I OF FOLLY
by Georgia Makhlouf
The Syrian artist Nazir Nabah drew this illustration of
the story of the self-important Sultan who is convinc¬
ed that the moon follows him wherever he goes.
WHEN I first heard about Goha the
Wise Fool I was a little perplexed.
He was not the usual hero of
fairy-tales who saves nations or princesses in
distress, nor the flat, one-dimensional
character of stories that one laughs over but
soon forgets.
He was different, indefinable sometimes
the judge, sometimes the accused, the rob¬
ber or the robbed, the cheat or the cheated. I
couldn't make up my mind if one should
make fun at him or with him, sharing in his
bizarre wisdom.
He had been described to me as a
Lebanese peasant from a mountain village
who has to face the various tribulations of
country life. But I also met him in the guise
of a judge in a Cairo court-room, as a guest
of the sultan in the palaces of Baghdad, and
on a shopping expedition in the suqs of the
old city of Tunis.
But with all this, Goha remained true to
character, ageless and always accompanied
by his donkey who, whether friend or foe,
sticks to him like a shadow.
Goha is to be found everywhere in Arab
folklore. Unlike the typical characters in
most traditional literatures who are assigned
to a more or less set corpus of tales and
therefore occupy a clearly defined position
in the development of the plot, Goha is a
versatile, fluctuating character whose deeds
and words constantly change according to
the circumstances. He is part and parcel of
daily life and the comical adventures of
which he is the eternal hero are continually
updated to fit the socio-political conditions
of the day.
GEORGIA MAKHLOUF, of Lebanon, is cur¬
rently preparing a university thesis in Paris on
ideology in modern Lebanese children's
literature. She has worked on a number of
studies on the role of the mass media in Lebanon
and has written children's stories in Arabic.
This may explain why, despite his impor¬
tance and omnipresence in the collective
consciousness, few books have been written
about Goha. He is not a static character
automatically condemned to be eaten by the
wolf like Little Red Riding Hood. When he
meets the wolf there are always several alter¬
natives: Goha misleads him about his
destination, he leads him before the judge,
offers him sweets... and even eats him!
His multi-faceted character holds great
appeal for young audiences, probably
because of his "anti-heroic" behaviour.
Goha is often shown as a lazy, poor, ig¬
norant, dirty and dishonest individual living
on the fringe of society, outside the social
logic of work and productivity, but who
manages nevertheless to disentangle himself
from embarrassing situations through guile
or simple wisdom.
Though ignorant, Goha exposes the con¬
tradictions of official scholarship; establish¬
ed, sacrosanct standards do not impress
him. In an delightful scene in Jacques
Baratier's film Goha le Simple, the
scenario of which was written by the
Lebanese writer Georges Shéhadé, Goha
succeeds in setting at loggerheads two
ulemas of the famous Al Azhar university.
The first maintains that truth is straight, the
second that it is curved; the first that truth is
luminous, the second that it is obscure.
With his simple approach, akin to that of a
child who has not yet been warped by social
constraints, Goha appears wiser and more
knowledgeable than these learned scholars.
His relationship with his environment also
reveals several traits that are characteristic
of the child's universe. The way he falls
under the spell of things and the ease with
which he confronts Nature (very well
described in Adès and Josipovici's Goha), in
particular his relationship with his donkey,
recall certain aspects of the child's animistic
thought as identified by Piaget.
Goha has conversations with his donkey
who is all at once at faithful companion, an
enemy, a scapegoat and the mirror-image of
himself. To critics he often replies: "I have
lived so long with my donkey that I've
become like him."
Goha is also an eternal truant. In
Shéhadé's scenario he is sent to school by
his father who hopes that his son will
become a scholar at AI Azhar. But instead
of attending the madrassah (Koranic
school), Goha wiles away his days in the
shadow of an arcade and sends his donkey
to school in his place. Incidentally, the
donkey is completely at ease among the dull
and studious pupils.
When Goha himself becomes a
schoolmaster he practises avant-garde
teaching methods by getting his pupils to
teach one another.
In yet another tale, set this time in a draw¬
ing class, he becomes an adept of modern
art by depicting, instead of the bird the
teacher has told the class to draw, the
branch of a tree. When the time for the exer¬
cise is up, the teacher claps his hands for the
pupils to raise their slates exhibiting their
work. When he sees Goha's drawing he asks
angrily: "Where's the bird?"
"It flew away when you clapped your
hands", replies Goha.
This irreverent, non-conformist charac¬
ter, full of weaknesses and faults, who suc¬
ceeds in extricating himself from difficult
situations by inversing traditional values, is
very popular with children. By his example
Goha "shows that there are temporary solu¬
tions to the most pressing psychological dif¬
ficulties" (Bettelheim). Thus he is often
rewarded by the Kadi (judge) or the sultan
for his resourcefulness. His cunning and
shrewdness disarm his enemies and he
receives presents for getting out of tight
corners.
For a child there is something reassuring
in the sight of little, unimportant
Goha who is definitely on the side of the
poor and the weak defending himself sue-
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
cessfully and triumphing over people who
are stronger and much more powerful than
himself.
Nevertheless, Goha is unlike the usual
heroes of children's tales who are never am¬
bivalent but, on the contrary, strongly
polarized and form an opposition within the
story. Because of his versatility and the
variety of roles he plays, Goha cannot be
classed in the usual category of children's
characters.
In a historical study which attempts to
answer the question: "Did Goha ever
exist?", he is referred to as a Mukhadram.
This term was used originally to qualify
historical figures who lived both in pre-
Islamic times and during the period of
Islam's emergence, thus participating in two
different cultural universes; its meaning has
now been extended to describe someone
who is astride two worlds, but does not
belong completely to either, in other words,
an ambiguous and therefore very versatile
character.
In certain tribes the mukhadram is a
mediator in inter-tribal disputes: he does not
really belong to either tribe but is sufficient¬
ly familiar with both to serve as an in¬
termediary between them.
Without seeking to ascribe validity to this
historical theory (whether Goha ever existed
or not remains an open question) it points to
an important dimension of his personality:
fundamentally he is a "marginal"
character, who participates in different
social worlds but never identifies with any of
them completely. Both an adult and a child,
he is not anti-social, for he maintains a com¬
plex network of social relationships; rather,
he is an anarchist in spontaneous revolt
against the prevailing social order which im¬
poses its own vision of reality. In this respect
Goha is essentially ambivalent.
His subversive instincts expressed in the
struggle against oppression and brute force
sometimes lend themselves to political inter¬
pretations. The story of "Goha's nail", for
example, is so famous that it has become
proverbial. Goha is obliged to sell his house,
but he adds a clause to the contract under
which he remains the owner of a nail on the
wall of one of the rooms, and this clause is
accepted by the buyer. One fine day Goha
arrives at the house and hangs a decaying
carcass on the nail. The whole house soon
reeks with the smell. Goha is asked to
remove the carcass but refuses pointing out
that the nail is legally his property. The new
owner is appalled and finally has to aban¬
don the house to Goha.
When Goha's nail is mentioned today in
conversation it is taken to mean someone
who keeps the best for himself while appear-
Another inci¬
dent in the life
and times of the
inimitable Goha
as drawn by a
six-year-old
Egyptian girl,
Shainda Niazi
Lane.
ing to be disinterested, or it can allude to a
clause introduced into a contract in order to
thwart the beneficiary.
At the political level the story symbolizes
the people's struggle against occupation. In
a more recent tale about a water melon
Goha is shown as a dissident. The scene is
set during an election: red ballot papers have
been prepared for candidates of the ruling
party and green ones for those of the op¬
position. After the proclamation of the
results which have returned the ruling party
to power, Goha goes to the market and sees
a magnificent piece of fruit, a big green
water melon. He is delighted by its fine col¬
our and buys the fruit which is unfamiliar to
him. On returning home he discovers to his
surprise that the inside of the melon is red
and that he has been deceived.
Other aspects of Goha's personality make
him unlike the usual hero of children's tales,
as for example his disrespectful attitude
towards Arab social institutions such as
marriage, religious rites, the law.
By his pranks he pokes fun at religious
bigots, ridicules high-sounding phrases and
uses the Kadi as a cat's-paw.
In yet another story, Goha, who is about
to marry, has a house built and orders the
carpenter to "put the woodwork for the
roof on the floor and the woodwork for the
floor on the roof".
The carpenter expresses surprise at this
and asks Goha to explain: "Don't you know
that marriage makes everything topsy¬
turvy", he replies. "So if we turn things up¬
side down beforehand order will be re¬
established after marriage".
Goha is also a very poetic character, a sort
of Oriental Pierrot who sings while he runs,
for he likes to hear his own voice from afar,
and outwits two thieves who have challeng¬
ed him to climb a tree and pick fruit, by
unexpectedly taking his shoes with him:
"Perhaps I will find a path leading from the
tree-top," he explains "And if I do, I shall
need my shoes."
Goha forms an integral part of the collec¬
tive Arab imagination. Not only is he the
hero of folk tales, he is also to be found in
proverbs and popular expressions. When
business is bad it is customary to remark
that it is "like Goha's affairs". And when
people are faced with a situation that they
do not understand or with behaviour whose
motivations are unclear, they say: "Do you
know what tore Goha's tarbush?"
Goha has been updated in modern
literature, notably in the works of Moham¬
med Dib, Kateb Yacine and Rachid Boud-
jeba. In children's literature, too, there are
characters such as the dreamer, the
simpleton and the wise fool who recall dif¬
ferent aspects of his personality and Goha-
like situations. For example, the story of the
sultan who is convinced that the moon is
following him, since he sees it move when he
moves and stop when he stops.
The same kind of proble-n exercises
Goha: he is seen one day going down to the
bottom of a deep well, for he has seen the
fallen moon in the water. Once below he
looks up and is reassured when he sees that
the moon is back in its place.
Georgia Makhlouf
Goha and his donkey
pictured in a cartoon
from a Lebanese chil¬
dren's book.
Drawing © from Stories ofJeha by Rose Gorayeb. Dar al-Kitab al Lubnani, Tyre
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE MONKEY KING
SUN WUKONG
by Sun Youjun
WHEN I was a child I used to declare proudly, "I'm
Sun Wukong!" Now, without being taught, my nine-
year-old son does exactly the same. I've often heard
other children identify themselves in the same way, and in fact
it would be difficult to find a Chinese child who doesn't know
about Sun Wukong, the Monkey King.
Sun Wukong, also known as Monkey, is the hero of
Pilgrimage to the West, a classical novel written by the Ming-
dynasty scholar Wu Cheng'en (c. 1500 to 1582). Taking his in¬
spiration from popular folktales about a Tang-dynasty monk
(known as Tripitaka in the novel) who went to the West to seek
Buddhist scriptures, as well as from vernacular literature of the
Song and Yuan dynasties, Wu Cheng'en created a great
mythical novel.
According to historical records, a young monk named Xuan
Yang actually did go to India to fetch Buddhist sutras. But
because he went alone on a trip of several thousand kilometres
which took seventeen years, and encountered many dangers
and difficulties, this journey became invested with a strong
mythical flavour in the folk stories. Perhaps because the image
of Tripitaka was limited by the historical character, in the fan¬
tastic stories his place was gradually taken by a monkey monster
who helped him in his travels. In Pilgrimage to the West, this
monkey becomes Sun Wukong, the novel's principal character.
Children love fabulous stories, and it is through its rich and
wonderful fantasies that Pilgrimage to the West has satisfied
their curiosity and aroused their imagination, while the
'character of Monkey Sun Wukong has anchored itself firmly in
their hearts. Sun Wukong starts life as a little monkey born out
of a boulder on the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit, a special
boulder which contains the essence of Nature itself. At first, he
is carefree and plays with the other little monkeys on the moun¬
tain. Then he is elected the Monkey King because he is the first
to enter the Cave of the Waterfall. But later, aware that his life
is controlled by the King of Hell and that he will die someday,
he becomes distressed and is determined to find a way to con¬
quer death.
After crossing many mountains and seas, he at last finds an
immortal from whom he learns many magic arts. He is able to
jump 108,000 // in one somersault, visit Heaven at will and enter
the Dragon King's Palace at the bottom of the sea by chanting a
magic spell. He also learns how to pluck out hairs from his
body and transform them into hundreds of little monkeys to
help him defeat his enemies. He masters, "seventy-two transfor¬
mations" and can change into anyone at will, so convincingly
that if he turns himself into a certain demon, even the demon's
wife cannot see through his trick. He can also transform
himself into things such as a pine tree, or a temple, using his
eyes as windows, his mouth as the gate and his tongue as the
statue of a god. Unfortunately, however, he cannot find a pro¬
per place to put his tail so he changes it into a flagpole behind
the temple. But how can a flagpole be erected at the rear of a
temple? As a result, his opponent sees through this particular
transformation.
So children love this most marvellous of heroes who will
never submit to oppression and insult. No matter how strong
his enemies, he dares to fight back and defeat them with his
skills. When the court of the nether world decides that, accor¬
ding to the "Book of Life and Death", Monkey Sun Wukong's
life-span has ended and draws his soul to the nether regions, he
takes out his weapon, the "gold-hooped staff", from inside his
ear, and fights his way to the palace of the King of Hell.
SUN YOUJUN, of China, is a well-known author of books for
children.
Crossing out his name and date of death from the "Book of
Life and Death" as well as those of other monkeys, he declares,
"That settles it! We are no longer under your control!" But
when the Jade Emperor, supreme ruler of the heavens, hears of
this, he flies into a rage. After failing to cheat the Monkey King
into submission, the Jade Emperor tries to resort to force by
sending heavenly troops to the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit
on a punitive expedition against him. Monkey in turn rises in
resistance and vanquishes the heavenly generals and their troops.
In the end, the Jade Emperor has no alternative but to agree
to give him the title of Paragon of Heaven and put him in
charge of the Garden of Immortal Peaches. But one day the
Heavenly Queen plans a banquet at which the peaches of im¬
mortality will be served and all the gods and deities are invited
except the Paragon of Heaven. Unable to swallow such an in¬
sult, he changes into an immortal and arrives at the banquet
before the others, drinks the imperial wine, and eats the peach
and elixir, thus destroying the banquet and creating havoc in
Heaven.
Escorting Tripitaka to the Western Heaven to fetch Buddhist
sutras, Monkey Sun Wukong shows the true qualities of a hero.
He is accompanied by two other disciples, Pigsy and Sandy,
who protect their weak and incompetent master. Pigsy is also a
children's favourite. A rather lazy and gluttonous character, he
always wants to quit and go home whenever they meet with dif¬
ficulty and could hardly be considered a hero. Tripitaka en¬
counters "eighty-one perils" on the way, monsters of every
description representing natural calamities and evil forces, and
it is Monkey who always fights in the forefront and sweeps
away demons and ghosts.
On the way to the West, he displays not only a dauntless
spirit but also intelligence and wisdom. He is adept at discover¬
ing an enemy's weak points and reacts accordingly. When he
encounters a strong opponent, he transforms himself into a tiny
gnat. Hiding himself under the bubbles in some tea which the '
monster is going to drink, he works his way into the belly of his
foe, where he turns somersaults and handstands until the suf¬
ferer begs for mercy.
Before the Monkey escorts Tripitaka to the West,
Avalokitesvara plays a little trick on him by putting a cap with a
gold hoop on his head and teaching Tripitaka to recite the "In¬
cantation of the Gold Hoop" for fear the Monkey will disobey
his master. Monkey is deceived into putting on this headgear, so
that the hoop rests tightly on his head. All Tripitaka needs to do
then is to recite a spell and Monkey will roll on the ground
because of the pain in his head as the hoop tightens.
During their journey, Tripitaka always uses this method to
punish Monkey, sometimes for no reason whatsoever; but
though he is infinitely resourceful, Sun Wukong can find no
way to rid himself of this hoop. This punishment always evokes
immense sympathy from children who, perhaps, associate it
with the restraints forced on them by seemingly unreasonable
parents and teachers in their own lives.
Pilgrimage to the West has 100 chapters and is more than
800,000 Chinese characters in length. The original is too long
and the language too difficult for children, so in recent years
various adaptations of the novel have been published specially
for children, as well as a growing number of strip cartoons and
picture-books. Even many popular science books for children
make use of the Sun Wukong character. There can be no doubt
that the image of Monkey Sun Wukong will long continue to be
cherished by Chinese children.
H Sun Youjun
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
iffk
IIP^f \ VN^7I r< 2
,\
x\\ %.
A
Í L/^
W ^ J
s»
W
PILGRIMAGE TO THE WEST is a very long
Chinese novel of fantastic adventures
written in the 16th century under the Ming
dynasty by Wu Cheng'en. The main hero
of the story, which runs to a hundred
chapters and has over 800,000 ideograms,
is clever and unfailingly resourceful Sun
Wukong the Monkey King, who never
spurns an opportunity to outwit an
enemy. Here he is seen escorting the
feeble and clumsy pilgrim Tripitaka who
travels with two disciples one of whom,
the lazy and gluttonous Pigsy, is a
favourite children's character like the
Monkey King.
Drawing © Miao Zhen, Peking
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
IVANUSHKA
PRINCE OF SIMPLETONS
by Valentin Berestov
This horse which "gallops higher than the murmuring forest and lower than the moving cloud" and
"brushes the meadows and fields with its tail" is the steed of Ivanushka, one of the most popular figures
in Russian folklore. A hero who is by turns the son of the Tsar and a simpleton, Ivanushka was immor¬
talized in the 19th century by the Siberian writer Pyotr Ershov. The above drawing is by Tatiana
A. Mavrina, a noted Soviet illustrator of children's stories, especially those of Pushkin. Her outstanding
work has been recognized by the International Board on Books for Young People, which has awarded
her its Hans Christian Andersen medal.
EVERY nation has its own fund of amusing stories about
simple-minded and eccentric folk, and more mysterious
fairy-tales in which knights errant overcome monsters to
save members of their family, beautiful maidens or mankind in its
entirety from all manner of fates worse than death. The Russians
are no exception. But, as the saying goes, fools sometimes rush in
where angels fear to tread; and when they do the characters from
the former type of story become the heroes of the latter.
One well-known figure in Russian folklore is Tsarévitch Ivan,
the noble prince; but it is another hero, Foolish Ivanushka, the
unattractive, shabbily-dressed, soot-stained lad, who, to the great
delight of listeners and readers of the tale, captures the iridescent
firebird Zhar-ptitsa, wins the heart of the most beautiful girl in the
world, plunges into the nether regions, swims across the ocean and
flies up beyond the clouds to drink tea and converse amicably with
the Sun and the Moon sometimes as an honoured guest,
sometimes as a visiting relative.
I was still a very small child when I first heard the tale of
Ivanushka from my country-woman grandmother. I well
remember how his fabulous horse rose up before me, in the
darkness of the night, every time I listened to the story.
But even without a story-telling grandmother I would have
discovered and appreciated Ivanushka at an early age. Every Rus¬
sian child is familiar with the poem about Konyok-gorbunok, the
VALENTIN DIMITRIEVICH BERESTOV is a noted Soviet poet and
author of children's books. A specialist in literary detection, he has
discovered hitherto unidentified verses by Pushkin, on whom he has writ¬
ten a number of essays. He has published over 40 books of poems, some
written specially for children.
small, unsightly horse with long ears and a pair of humps, whose
odd appearance matches that of his master, who is none other than
Ivanushka.
How this poem came to be written is almost a fairy-tale in itself.
In 1834, at the age of nineteen, a young man called Pyotr Ershov
travelled to the Russian capital from the Siberian city of Tobolsk,
to "look and learn". Siberia was a land rich in story-tellers; in¬
deed, they formed a sort of rural aristocracy and were much in de¬
mand as companions on hunting trips and wood-cutting expedi¬
tions into the forests and on the fishing boats that ventured out in¬
to the northern seas. Listening to them during the long dark nights,
the weary peasants and fisherfolk forgot their burdens and were
mentally transported into a completely different world.
The young man from Tobolsk had listened to many of their tales
as a child; and he had just discovered the stories in rhyme written
by the great poet Pushkin. Suddenly, an astonishing thing hap¬
pened event that in its own way resembled one of Ivanushka's
adventures: Pyotr Ershov himself sat down and wrote a magnifi¬
cent tale in verse, as rich in language and imagery as the popular
stories he had heard and as poetic as anything written by his
recently-discovered master.
It was to be his only masterpiece. Throughout the rest of his life,
which was full of labour and misfortune, his writing never rose
above the commonplace. As director of the high school at
Tobolsk, he was cut off from his roots among the people and the
magic spark which had transformed him for a brief moment during
his youth died out.
Maxim Gorky, who greatly appreciated Ershov and regretted
that none of his subsequent writings matched his first youthful ef¬
fort, urged the critic Chukovsky to continue where Ershov had left
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
off. The book of tales in verse intended for the tiniest children aged
between two and five that Chukovsky produced in the 1920s was a
great and immediate success.
The first and most important collection of tales of this kind had
appeared in 1855 and 1863 in three volumes edited by A.N.
Afanasiev, with the title Russkie Narodnye Skazki (Russian
Popular Tales). "Particularly interesting in these tales", wrote
Afanasiev in the first edition, "is the role played by the youngest of
three brothers. Most of the tales begin with the time-honoured for¬
mula: "Once upon a time a man had three sons; two of them were
clever, but the third was stupid". The elder brothers are smart, in
the everyday, market-place sense of the term, and are only con¬
cerned with feathering their own nest. The third son is stupid in
that he lacks this practical wisdom; he is a simple, guileless soul
who shares in the troubles of others to the extent of neglecting his
own security and interest".
According to custom, the entire inheritance, including the right
to perform heroic deeds and miracles goes to the two elder
brothers. Ivanushka, the third son, is not even favoured with in¬
telligence or good looks. He is, as it were, kept on the sidelines, on¬
ly allowed to participate when his brothers have failed in some
enterprise. Only later does it become clear that the "smart"
brothers, playing the game according to their own selfish rules, are
of little account when compared with the "stupid" Ivan, and that
their role in the story is to reveal that his inferiority in comparison
with them is, in fact, the source of his strength.
Ivanushka is indeed a paradoxical character, equally capable of
lying lazily on top of the stove, letting his thoughts wander or
catching flies, and of leaping into action while his brothers are
snoring away, oblivious to all around them. In one tale, their dying
father begs the three of them to take turns watching over his tomb
at night. The two elder brothers think it far more sensible to sleep
comfortably in their beds when their father dies and send
Ivanushka to keep watch in their place. As a result he undergoes
the experiences originally intended for them.
Ivanushka's three nights of vigil resemble the sleeplessness of the
philosopher, the poet or the lovesick swain. In his trance-like state,
various things happen. His dead father appears and they talk
together. On the third night his father presents him with a fabulous
horse: "The horse gallops, the earth trembles, flames burst from
its ears and smoke from its nostrils".
Presenting his horse to Ivanushka, his father says: "May it serve
you as it has served me". But the horse in question is no ordinary,
stable-loving steed. Whistled up or called by an incantatory phrase,
it appears from nowhere, and just as suddenly disappears. Sivka-
burka, as it is called is, in fact, a magic horse, symbolizing the
spiritual testament of the father, the blessing which fathers at all
times have given their offspring, the message handed down from
generation to generation by all peoples, past, present and those to
come. The horse is in fact Pegasus, the symbol of poetry, the trav¬
eling-companion of inspiration. And the gift of inspiration is what
Ivanushka possesses in the highest degree.
In one of the tales, Ivanushka one day emerges from the horse's
mouth transformed into a smartly dressed, handsome young man.
Obviously he has now become one and the same person as
Tsarévitch Ivan. With other suitors, he attempts to leap, on
horseback, to the window of a high tower where the Tsar's
daughter is sitting, to kiss her and take from her hands the hand¬
kerchief which is the pledge of their forthcoming marriage. Three
attempts are allowed and on the first day Ivan almost reaches the
goal, winning even his brother's admiration.
Suddenly, the handsome knight disappears and in his place there
stands the stupid lad, who asks: "Wasn't that me?". Ivan's
remark, which provokes unrestrained mirth on the part of his
brothers, seems to be designed to test them, to find out whether
they indeed love him and whether, if only for a moment, they can
imagine him as a winner, as the object of general celebration.
The winner, like Cinderella, wishes to remain anonymous. All
the young people are invited into the palace, where they drink beer
and jealously watch to see whether someone wipes his lips with the
precious handkerchief. Nobody notices Ivanushka, who is sitting
behind the stove, black with soot, his hair tousled, watching the
proceedings with his mouth wide open. Only on the third day is he
offered a drink of beer, whereupon he wipes his mouth with the
princess's handkerchief. He has come to the palace in the form of a
simpleton rather than a prince, because it is important for him to
know whether the princess will be true and faithful to her promise.
And if the first kiss was given by a prince, the responding kiss is
received by the simpleton. Thus not only Ivanushka, but also his
bride, enter a new world, where fairytale justice is seen to be done.
The tales about Ivanushka have immense historical depth. If we
could travel in a time-machine back into the Russian past, one of
our first encounters would be with a feudal peasant who, to use the
Russian expression, pridurivaetsja, that is to say, deliberately
passes himself off as a fool in the eyes of the gentry and the
authorities, while at the same time preserving jealously the values
Carried away from the kingdom of the Kusmans by
his ally the grey wolf who has kidnapped queen Helen
for him, Ivanushka flees through the immense Rus¬
sian forest, holding his beloved in his arms. The above
painting, 77ie Tsarevich Ivan on his Grey Wolf, is by
Victor M. Vasnetsov (1848-1926) who painted many
themes from Russian folklore and popular fiction. It is
now in the Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow.
Borne skywards by a little horse with a pair of humps
and long ears, Ivanushka gallops in headlong pursuit
of the Firebird which he must take to the Tsar.
Vladimir A. Milashevski drew this illustration for
Ershov's book The Little Humpbacked Horse.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
In a story called The Frog Princess, Ivanushka must
marry whoever retrieves an arrow which he shoots in¬
to the distance. Poor Ivanushka! Left, he is seen at the
moment when he discovers that destiny has selected
a frog to be his spouse. However, the frog soon turns
into a beautiful girl, Vassilissa the Very Wise, and
although they experience many vicissitudes they
eventually live happily ever after. The illustration is by
Ivan Bilibin (1876-1942), a graphic artist and theatre
designer who was noted for his illustrations of Rus¬
sian folk-tales and songs. He created a style related to
Art Nouveau which influenced wood sculpture, em¬
broidery and popular imagery. Below, Ivanushka as
depicted by 8-year-old Liuda Rakitina of Syktyvkar, a
town in the north of the Soviet Union.
* *
and culture of the people. Further back in time we would briefly
meet the warrior on horseback and in armour, defending his land
from devastating invasion. Further back again, we would witness
the collapse of kinship-based society, where the youngest brother
was expected to remain with his parents until their death, as guar¬
dian of the hearth (the modern folklore specialist V. Anikin has
discussed this subject). Finally, we would find ourselves in the
heart of a society based on kinship, and the early days of homo sa¬
piens. If we are to believe V. Propp, the author of The Historical
Roots of Fairy-Tales, the initiatory experiences imposed by their
elders on adolescents were similar in nature to the training received
by modern cosmonauts and involved elements of hair-raising
adventure, the domination of fear and pain and the accomplish¬
ment of extremely difficult tasks. If fairy-tales indeed have their
roots in actually performed rituals, then we may discern a thread
which runs from our distant ancestors, who were virtually
powerless before the forces of nature and who created standards of
brotherhood and justice without which humanity would have been
unlikely to survive its infancy, far ahead into some splendid future
age, where men will no longer be powerless in the face of the
elements and where all people will live according to fairy-tale stan¬
dards of behaviour.
It is by no means a coincidence that the greatest secrets of nature
are repealed, as in a fairy-tale, only to the most exceptional in¬
dividuals, and often to those considered to be the most eccentric.
This is why the role of those who write for children is so impor¬
tant. For the sake of their people and of mankind in its entirety
they must present the child, at the earliest possible age, with the
"fabulous horse" of inspiration. B Vaientin Berestov
Books for eager fingers
When blind children learn to read. Braille is the magic key that
opens for them the door to the priceless treasures of world
literature. In the world of books they can hold their own with
anyone and they are soon immersed in the stirring adventures of
such heroes and heroines as Peter Pan, Alice, Pinocchio, San-
dokan. Gavroche, Sun Wukong, Leuk the Hare and Nasrudin Hodja.
La Llave Mágica (The Magic Key, see photo) is one of a series of
specially-shaped books in Braille, produced by the Braille Founda¬
tion of Uruguay, for young blind children aged from six to eight.
Just as colour and image motivate the sighted child to read, so
shape arouses the interest of the visually handicapped child. As he
begins to finger the book his curiosity is awakened and he feels the
urge to read the story.
For the deaf-blind child. Braille books are even more essential, pro¬
viding as they do virtually the only source of culture, entertainment
and information. Although using the manual alphabet by touch per¬
mits communication with relatives and friends, it is through the
embossed system of reading and writing that the intellectual
development of deaf-blind children is chiefly sustained and
nourished.
An interesting development which could help to further the in¬
tegration of blind children into the world of their sighted peer
groups is the production of texts in both Braille and ink-print, with
embossed illustrations in colours. A highly successful example of
this type of publication is Red Thread Riddles (see the Unesco
Courier, January 1981), a book which Unesco helped to produce
and which is now available in English, French and Spanish and will
shortly be published also in German and Italian.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
WRITING
FOR CHILDREN
IS NO
CHILD'S PLAY
by Michel Tournier
IN 1967 I published my first book, a
novel entitled Vendredi ou les Limbes
du Pacifique. It was a new version of
Daniel Defoe's famous Robinson Crusoe of
1719, countless "remakes" of which had
already been produced down the centuries.
For me the ground-rules were to remain as
faithful as I could to my model while, as it
were, discreetly and surreptitiously smuggl¬
ing into it all kinds of modern assumptions in
the realms of philosophy, psychoanalysis
and ethnography. I should add that I had
just taken the competitive exam for teachers
of philosophy, and was stuffed full of Jean-
Paul Sartre and Claude Lévi-Strauss.
A later re-reading of my novel made me
realize its inadequacies and how far short I
had fallen of my first ideal. The philosophy
stared me in the face from every page,
weighing on the story and holding it back. I
very quickly felt the need to rewrite the book
in a leaner, tauter form, adding purely nar¬
rative episodes and weaving the philosophy
more closely and deeply into the story; not
changing it, but concealing it. And so, using
Vendredi ou les Limbes du Pacifique as a
kind of draft, I wrote a new book not a line
of which was copied from the first called
Vendredi ou la Vie Sauvage, (Friday and
Robinson: Life on Esperanza Island).
And that was when the surprises began.
The first was to discover that I had written a
children's book. Yes indeed, the brevity and
clarity of the story, the pace of the plot
everything made of this little novel a
popular "classic" of the future in the proper
sense of the word: one that is read in class.
Meanwhile, and this was the second sur¬
prise, I couldn't find a publisher. For at the
same time, I discovered how "children's"
publishers or the corresponding departments
MICHEL TOURNIER is an internationally known
French writer. Notable among his published
works, which have been widely translated, are:
Vendredi ou les Limbes du Pacifique (1967;
published in the USA as Friday and in the UK as
Friday or the Other Island/, Le Roi des Aulnes
(1970; The Erl-King) which won the Goncourt
Prize, and Les Météores (1975; Gemini/ He has
also written books for children, including Pierrot
ou les Secrets de la Nuit (1979).
"Beside himself with excite¬
ment, Friday climbed to the
top of a tree. He had
brought a telescope with
him and he trained it on the
approaching ship which was
now clearly visible." In
Michel Tournier's book Ven¬
dredi ou la Vie Sauvage (Fri¬
day and Robinson: Life on
Esperanza Island), from
which these words are
taken, Robinson elects to
stay on the island whilst Fri¬
day leaves for Europe on the
ship. Not entirely satisfied
with his earlier book. Ven¬
dredi ou les Limbes du
Pacifique (Friday or the
Other Island, 1967), in which
he had taken up and examin¬
ed in depth the theme of
Daniel Defoe's Robinson
Crusoe (1719), Tournier set
out to write the story again
in a leaner, tauter form.
When the new version. Ven¬
dredi ou la Vie Sauvage, was
published in 1971, he
discovered, to his surprise,
that he had written a book
for children!
of the major publishers work. Vendredi ou
les Limbes du Pacifique had been published
by a dozen foreign firms. Those that had a
"junior" section unanimously rejected Ven¬
dredi ou la Vie Sauvage and the specialized
houses proved just as unwelcoming. Why?
Because the children's book trade operates
by laws that absolutely ban all genuine
literary creativity.
Those laws impose a ready-made idea of
children stemming directly from the nine¬
teenth century and a mythology that is a
compound of Victor Hugo and Queen Vic¬
toria. In the United States, the world of
children's books has long been dominated by
the Walt Disney factory. The specialized
publishing houses live in terror of the
watchful gaze of parents' or booksellers'
associations and a certain kind of press,
which together make up a vast network
where whispers play their part. The publica¬
tion of a children's book that fails to comply
with the requirements of this censorship not
only means that the press and booksellers
will boycott it, but discredits the entire out¬
put of the publishers, henceforth viewed as
"suspect". Hardly surprising, then, that any
original or creative work is automatically
refused by reading departments.
In most cases, standard moulds baptized
Drawing © Georges Lemoine, courtesy of Editions Gallimard-Jeunesse, Paris
"collections" are produced, each with its
own collection editor, in which pseudo-
writers unwearyingly cast their made-to-
measure, pre-programmed products. The
"audience" for each collection is described in
an "identikit" picture giving its age, sex and
social status. In many cases, the entire
operation is dominated by a political or
religious ideology. Should the unfortunate
author of a work that is original and hence,
unlike any other knock on the door of one
of these fortresses, his manuscript will for
politeness' sake be kept for a few days, but it
won't even be read.
All this was ten years ago. Thanks to the
success of my novels, some publishers have
finally accepted my Vendredi ou la Vie
Sauvage. But many of them were purely
literary or even avant-garde publishers, with
no previous experience in children's books.
This brought me to question seriously
whether there was any reason to speak of
children's books. Closely considered, the
idea of a "junior library" is fairly recent: it
dates to the very period of the Victorian
myths about children that I have just de¬
nounced. But what about Perrault's Fairy-
Tales, La Fontaine's Fables or Lewis Car¬
roll's A lice? And what about such classics as
the Grimm and Andersen stories, the Orien-
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
WRITING FOR CHILDREN IS NO CHILD'S PLAY
^tal legends, Selma Lagerlöf's Mis Holgerson
and Saint-Exupéry's Little Prince? Quite
simply, I feel we must unflinchingly recall
that except for Selma Lagerlöf, none of these
authors was writing specifically for children.
But being geniuses, they wrote so well, so
clearly and so concisely qualities that are
rare and hard to achieve that they could be
read by everyone, even children!
To me this "even children" has come to be
of major and even commanding importance.
It is a literary ideal that I strive, with infre¬
quent success, to attain. Frankly, at the risk
of scandalizing the reader, I maintain that
Shakespeare, Goethe and Balzac are marred
by a defect that I find quite unforgiva¬
ble children cannot read them. For my
part, I would gladly sharpen my pen and
recast my other novels, Le Roi des Aulnes
(The Erl-King), Les Météores, Gaspard,
Melchior et Balthazar, in purer, less clut¬
tered and more chiselled form: in a word, so
that even children could read them.
If I have not done so, the reason is not
natural laziness it would be a gigantic
undertaking but because it would achieve
nothing. Adults would not read these
"children's stories" and nor would children,
because no "children's publisher" would
agree to handle such "non-standard" books.
But on one occasion at least I have achiev¬
ed my ideal. For years I had tried to weave
into a perfect adventure-story, with a power¬
ful metaphysical foundation, the three prin¬
cipal characters of Italian comedy, Pierrot,
Colombine and Harlequin. I finally succeed¬
ed. The result is a short story some thirty
pages long entitled Pierrot ou les Secrets de
la Nuit. My chief publisher having opened a
"junior section", I managed to persuade him
to take on this "children's book", which he
published separately from his collections, in
a format that the house has never used
before, rather as some towns used to map out
a "red-light district" and surround it with a
kind of cordon sanitaire. It should be said
that two years later the book's popularity
was such that it was included in one of the
firm's regular collections, much as a son
previously cursed and driven out by his
father is welcomed back into the family
when he has made his fortune. Be that as it
may, these thirty pages for which I would
exchange all my other work cannot find a
publisher abroad.
Since the second version of Vendredi
became so popular, I am constantly asked to
speak about it to schools in France and the
French-speaking countries. I listen to the
children's questions and try to answer them.
They are no more "childish" than those that
adult readers ask: indeed, rather less so on
the whole. Their bluntness always strikes at
the heart of the matter: how long do you take
to write a book? How much do you earn? If
there are spelling mistakes in your
manuscript, what does your publisher say?
How much truth is there in your stories?
From these and a hundred other questions
I have learnt a good deal through the
answers I was forced to find, it being a prin¬
ciple of mine always to answer frankly and in
full. The last question in particular calls the
entire literary aesthetic into question. Need I
recall that Marthe Robert calls her last book
La Vérité littéraire? (Literary Truth?).
I begin my reply by writing on the black¬
board a quote from Jean Cocteau: / am a lie
that always tells the truth. Then I tell them
about the origins of Defoe's Robinson
Crusoe (often the children have read my
Vendredi). There was the true story of the
Scottish helmsman Alexander Selkirk, who
was cast away for four years and four
months on Mas a Tierra island in the
Pacific, and that is what inspired Defoe to
write his novel. Now we know Selkirk's story
from the report of Captain Woodes Rogers,
who found the castaway and brought him
back to civilization. But who has read it?
Nobody but a handful of specialists. Defoe's
Robinson Crusoe, on the other hand, enjoys
enormous international popularity to this
day.
Why is it that fiction has so much more
hold on the minds of men than the plain
truth? The question is momentous, and he
who found the answer would hold the key to
masterpieces. Without making any such
claims, let me none the less try to cast a little
light on the enigma.
What is really most remarkable about
Defoe's tale is that reading it alone is not
enough. Indeed, in my belief, very few
people read the full authentic version. The
strength and value of the book lie in the fact
that it prompts an irresistible urge to rewrite
it. And that is why, as I said earlier, there
are countless versions of the story, ranging
from Jules Verne's Mysterious Island and
Giraudoux 's Suzanne and the Pacific, to
Wyss's Swiss Family Robinson and Saint-
John Perse 's Images à Crusoe.
Some masterpieces and it is this that
places them at the summit of world litera¬
ture contain an incitement to create, a con¬
tagious spirit of creativity. Setting the
reader's inventiveness in motion is for me, I
admit, the pinnacle of art. Paul Valéry used
to say that inspiration is not the state in
which the poet writes, but the state into
which he hopes to bring his reader. I think
that saying should be made the banner and
foundation of a new aesthetic.
But does this not imply that the first
criterion of a work of literature is its educa¬
tional qualities? Montaigne said that
educating a child is not filling a vase but
lighting a fire. I don't believe it could be any
better put. And for me too, the sign of my
victory is the flame that I sometimes see in
the eyes of my young readers, a living source
of light and heat that my book has kindled in
a child. A rare reward, but priceless, and one
that redeems all the effort, all the loneliness
and all the misunderstandings.
H Michel Tournier E !
TIC
<D <
I0-
8 ¡S
< '
¿ (D
£(0
M
S3
:Si <
.a ce
Q I
1 U
05 LU
CC CC
UJZ>
1<5 rr
OO
Oo
ui^
00
It
3°
rr o_
"S
OO
CEO
<o
ÛH
OO
ce X
Cû û_
Tha UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a year
including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do
not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captionsand headlines
are written by the Unesco Courier staff
The Unesco Courier It produced In microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (11 University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head. Inc., 111 West 40th Street. New York,
U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road.
Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition:
French Edition:
Spanish Edition:
Russian Edition:
Arabic Edition:
German Edition:
Japanese Edition:
Italian Edition:
Hindi Edition:
Tamil Edition:
Hebrew Edition:
Persian Edition:
Dutch Edition:
Portuguese1 Edition:
Turkish Edition:
Urdu Edition:
Catalan Edition:
Howard Brabyn (Pans)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos
(Paris)
Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Sayed Osman (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Mohammed Reza Berenji
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-Young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille Edition: Frederick Poner (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian Edition: Dimitar Gradev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
The latest (1981) edition of Unesco's indispensable
reference book of statistics from some 200 countries
statistical yearbook
annuaire statistique on:
anuario estadístico
Population
tdwMwn ftfrnrlni fvdu.acton
fililí 1 M limal MpataUtU litpcmr. de ! 'cniciaiunirlll ('.«lot di li cduiiclón 'fmmÊmm
Scion« «mi lí.-hnolojí S.*n,r n ti;liiKili«i (.Vii.u ; icvnolojl»
lihraft» UblwtMwM »ihfcoltcu f^W*
Uuku.ii> and rtlaitd Mutt« i\ anUhUlom MjUlns 1 m. lit Nia»^W
aUtkWt« »riiLÜur. atnllWM
Thtiuc .»d nlKti nMmatalMCMdt T«lro mpwliculo /'""(V.
énmmk «m i dut« ,if wn Ldicion dt btro* V -À ^
Education
Science and technology
Stwipapcn *ml olho pfcM piibliiitKima ¡»tt.ojihi VaMMaaMI
ptrunlk-M* PspMi coltaral fipcl nulluni
Kj.li.i liroi.kailwi Itlnoion MnMta
Ttlf.mon
Libraries
Book production
Newspapers and periodicals
~f\ Paper consumption
jc\j Film and cinema
jXr
TV and radio
^ Prepared in co-operation with national statistical
services and National Commissions for Unesco and
with the help of the Statistical Office and the
Population Division of the United Nations
1152 pages 280 francs
Trilingual: English/ French/Spanish
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collmg-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty Ltd.
P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals. Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Divi¬
sion, Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne {Victoria!,
3000 - AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books Internatio¬
nal Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R K Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca
3. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only. N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P 0. Box 88, Beijing CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch- '
bishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0 Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S N.T.L , Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaa-
rankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP. 12598-48. - GER¬
MAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140,
710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier
(German, English, French and Spanish editions): Mr H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3 For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag,
Germenng/Munchen For scientific maps only Geo Center,
Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80 - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra, Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon, GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HKÍ Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong Kong Government Information Services, Publication Cen¬
tre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Kónyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V, A K.V. Konyvturosok
Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI ICELAND.
Snaebjórn Jonsson Er Co , H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2, B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1 ,
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016, Scindia House,
New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture,
Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi
110001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers,
29 Jl Oto Iskandardmata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl
Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie
47, Jakarta Pusat IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribu¬
tion Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O Box
314/1486, Teheran, Iranian Nat. Comm for Unesco, Ave. Iran-
chahr Chomali No. 300, B P 1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKen¬
zies Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road,
Walkmstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B C. Bookstore Ltd.,
P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA.
Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc , Shuhwa
Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-ku,
Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P O Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa
LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P O. Box 286,
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication &
Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
' MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11 - MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
, Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For
periodicals only: Dekker and Nordemann NV, P.O. Box 197,
1000 AD Amsterddam; for publications only KEESING BOEKEN
' B.V , Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS
i ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V., P 0. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Of¬
fice, Government Bookshops at- Rutland Street, P.O Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch,
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton, Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife, The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286, The University Bookshop of
Nsukka, The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1, Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
- PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND Orpan-lmport, Palac
Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przed-
miescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias 6 An¬
drade Ltda Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P O. Box 48, Mahé, New
Service Ltd., Kmgsgate House," P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd , No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications. Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty ) Ltd., Libn Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gar¬
diner Mawata P O B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publica¬
tions A/B C.E. Fntzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan
12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier:
Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65,
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications Europa
Verlag, 5 Rámistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair,
Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Cad-
desi. No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGAN¬
DA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. - UNITED
KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P O Box 569, London,
S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol. UNITED
STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South, New York, N Y.
10010. U.S S R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200.
- YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8,
Belgrade, Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25, P O B. 50-1,
'Ljubhana - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales IPVTI Ltd., 67
Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
ML
*
s
i
e
f
The Monkey King Sun Wukong is portrayed in
this watercolour painted in 1981 by a nine-year-
old Chinese boy, Gejie Ou. (See article page 28).
^
]]>
</page>
</document>
