<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074721eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
AUGUST SEPTEMBER 1982 - 10 French francs
eeUuûti^t Hüitet-pm-
ltt*l ¿¿tatito ád**au**\
J
QUESTIONS
OF OUR TIME
mm0Mà
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
FRANCE The joy of reading
The doors of the venerable library of world literature stand open to every seeker, none should be afraid of its size, for
mass is not relevant here. Somefind a dozen books enough for a lifetime andyet are true readers; others have swallowed
everything and can talk of anything, yet all their trouble was in vain. For education needs something on which to
worka character, a personality. If none is there, if educationformationstands empty-handed without a substance
to mould, then knowledge may come about, but not love or life.
Hermann Hesse
(1877-1962)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
august- SEPTEMBER 1982 35th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 26 LANGUAGES
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 48 French Francs
2 years: 84 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 36 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 8 - 1982 - OPI - 82-1 - 390 A
page
CULTURAL IDENTITY
The building blocks of culture
by Cheikh Anta Diop
The emergent peoples of Latin America
The cultural profile of a continent
by Darcy Ribeiro
EDUCATION
13 Blackboard bungle?
A defence of the school as the cornerstone of education
by Arthur V. Petrovsky
17 Preparing people for change
A testing time for modern education
HUNGER-POPULATION-ENVIRONMENT
23 For an alternative development
Balanced economic growth will be impossible without environmental protection
by Anil Agarwal
21 Environment and the global underclass
40,000 preventable child deaths each day
by Erik Eckholm
30 The aftermath of the population explosion
By the year 2000, a world population 40 per cent higher than today
by Rafael M. Salas
DISARMAMENT- DEVELOPMENT
41 Development through demilitarization
by Richard Falk
44 The consequences of nuclear war
HUMAN RIGHTS
49 A Third World view of Human Rights
by Radhika Coomaraswamy
52 Human rights are universal
The individuality and independence of a culture must start
with the equality of man
by Yoshikazu Sakamoto
SCIENCE-TECHNOLOGY-COMMUNICATION
57 Barren soil
For technology transplants to 'take' the ground must be carefully prepared
by Ali Mazrui
60 Predicting the unpredictable
Is it possible to identify the variables that trigger surprise and change?
by Crawford S. Ho/ling
63 By word of mouth
The spoken word is still the most widely used medium of communication
by Mohamed H. Abdulaziz
66 Communication facts and figures
69 Nobel laureates speak out
70 Letters to the Editor
A time to live... FRANCE: The joy of reading
OUR July issue was devoted to certain
problems relating to culture, in parti¬
cular those concerning the application
of State cultural policies. In this our annual
double issue ofAugust/September, the Unesco
Courier examines certain aspects of a number
of universally recognized world problems: the
development crisis, the arms threat, the
dangerous imbalances provoked by disparities
in the conditions of life of different peoples,
disregard of human rights, the problems of the
dissemination of knowledge.
These two issues thus evoke Unesco's most
fundamental concerns and essential functions
in the world spectrum of today.
In both issues, the conclusion reached by
our contributors, even when they appear to be
most divergent, all concur in one respect: these
grave world problems cannot be attacked
piecemeal. Culture is inherent in development,
in the long term education is the key to the
maintenance ofpeace, new technologies to be
viable must respect cultural identity, social
progress within a nation is inseparable from
consensus between nations.
This, then, is the reason for and the
justification of Unesco's contribution to the
attempt to achieve global understanding of the
problems we have to resolve. And it is this
"total" approach that is in our minds when we
speak of "the world problématique": the
urgent problems of our time are indissociable
and their solution calls for a united effort of
will.
It is to be hoped that such an approach to
world problems will gradually give rise to a
new mental attitude in international public
opinion which will in turn facilitate the prac¬
tical success of the most daring and ambitious
enterprises in the service of the human com¬
munity. Thefearfulperils ofcontemporary life
must not be allowed to deter us from under¬
taking the intellectual effort of reflection
that is the prerequisite of any action liable to
benefit the peoples and nations of the world.
Cover: The four words contained in the circles
on our cover evoke four of the great world
problems of our day. Clockwise from bottom,
Liberty, Arab calligraphy by Hassan
Massoudy; Peace, Chinese calligraphy by Rin-
nie Tang; Work and Education, in Cyrillic and
Latin script, by Slobodan Bijeljac.
Arab calligraphy from Calligraphie Arabe Vivante,
by Hassan Massoudy i£) Flammarion, 1981, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
To try to impose on men an alien way
of life is a serious error, which, far
from enriching the cultural heritage of
mankind, impoverishes it greatly.
Amadou Hampâté Bâ
Detail from The Large Studio, by the
* Spanish artist Aguayo (1926-1977).
Photo Luc Joubert © Galerie Jeanne
Bûcher, Paris.
¿. «
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
CULTURAL
IDENTITY
DEVELOPMENT as measured by an exclusively
economic yardstick tends to crush the specific
genius of peoples, which expresses itself
through their powers of creativity. This rule applies to
the industrialized countries but it is even more valid in
developing countries attracted by a Western model of
growth. The brutal transfer of Western technology and
patterns of consumption which scorns the cultural iden¬
tity of Third World peoples is bound to end in failure.
These peoples should draw from their cultural identity
the energy and drive to create original models for the
future even if in the process they incorporate the most
positive aspects of other cultures and other models.
For culture, a synthesis of all the creative activities of
a people, should be the ultimate measure of develop¬
ment. With its intellectuals, scientists and artists in the
forefront, each people should assume its own identity,
constantly enriching and reinventing it through acts,
words and works of art. Culture defined in this way
opens the door to what is modern through certain forms
of exchange, the grafting of knowledge and skills, pro¬
cesses which are no longer a threat nor a source of
harm.
To wish to be oneself is not to shut oneself off from
others, quite the reverse. Each culture needs all the
others, and when one culture is endangered, every man
is impoverished thereby. Both at the national and the
international level, cultural pluralism means open-
mindedness, and by remaining true to all that is most
authentic in his experience each individual contributes
to the strengthening and diversification of the wider
community. Initially conceived as a necessity in a
regional and national context, the affirmation of
cultural identity is now seen as a duty to the interna¬
tional community, in the sense that it affects the diversi¬
ty of cultures, the wealth of the common heritage of
mankind.
The building blocks
of culture
by Cheikh Anta Diop
CHEIKH ANTA DIOP, Senegalese anthro¬
pologist and physicist, is the founder-director of
the Radiocarbon Laboratory of the Institut Fon¬
damental d'Afrique Noire (IFAN), at the Universi¬
ty of Dakar. In the field of the human sciences, he
has published a number of works on African
questions including Nations Nègres et Culture,
L'Unité Culturelle de l'Afrique Noire, and L'Afri¬
que Noire Précoloniale.
A people's cultural identity is related
to three major factorshistorical,
linguistic and psychological (the
last of which may include the people's
specific forms of religious observance).
These factors vary in importance in dif¬
ferent historical and social situations; when
they are not fully present in a people or an
individual, the cultural identity is flawed.
The harmonious conjunction of these fac¬
tors is an ideal situation, and in practice all
kinds of combinations are possible. When
any one of the factors is influenced, the col¬
lective or individual cultural personality is
modified; these modifications may go so far
as to cause an "identity crisis."
Can these factors be classed in a hierarchy
of importance or does each one play an
equal part in the constitution of the cultural
personality? Any answer to this question
must begin with an analysis of all three.
The historical factor, first of all, is the
cement which gives a people its cohesion
and distinguishes it from a group whose
members may have nothing in common with
one another. Awareness of a common
history is the most solid rampart a people
can build against cultural or any other form
of aggression from outside. Thus in contacts
between civilizationsduring the coloniza¬
tion process, for examplethe colonizer
tries to weaken if not destroy the historical
consciousness of the colonized people.
The loss of national sovereignty and
historical awareness resulting from a pro¬
longed foreign occupation causes stagnation
or decline when it does not actually lead to
collapse or downfall into violence or anar¬
chy. The story of Egypt under the Romans
aptly illustrates this process. Egypt was a
centre of civilization in the Ancient World
but when its people were deprived of their
sovereignty, from the sixth centuiy BC until
the second century AD, they lapsed, into
savagery, according to the Latin poet
Juvenal who described the fierce fighting
between the people of Denderah and Hom-
bos in the second century AD.
The exercise of national sovereignty is
thus by far the best school for a people's
mind and soul, and the only way to keep
alive its greatest virtues. Colonization
always diminishes the colonized who are
treated as infants.
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
There is much glib talk of "peoples with no history",
sometimes with the added rider that these are the happiest
peoples. This elliptic formula merely means that their history is
and remains unknown, not that it does not exist. Among these
peoples too, over tens if not hundreds of thousands of years,
men have loved, hated, suffered, created, fought. In truth,
there is no such thing as an "infant" people; all peoples are
adult, even those who have kept no written record of their
childhood and adolescence.
Claude Lévi-Strauss
The ethnological view of the plurality of fundamentally
heterogeneous cultures seems to contradict the evolutionist view
of a process leading gradually towards a universal rationaliza¬
tion. This opposition seems to me to be undeniable, but it is
based, Ifeel, on judgements of value rather than on judgements
offacts.
Raymond Aron
Motif from a rock engraving in the valley of Valcamonica,
Italy. Photo © Centro Camuno di Studi Preistorici, Capo
di Ponte, Brescia.
It is hard to say. whether or not the
historical factor is more important than
language. For the French philosopher
Montesquieu language was the only com¬
mon denominator, the supreme mark of
cultural identity. "As long as a vanquished
people has not lost its language," he wrote,
"it still has hope."
How does cultural
domination influence
language?
But nowhere in the world does the
phenomenon of linguistic unity exist on a
continental scale. Languages follow the
migratory paths and fortunes of each
people. Fragmentation and diversity prevail
until an official effort is made or a political
decision is taken to extend the use of one
language, if necessary by force. This is what
happened in France where, in a straightfor¬
ward example of acculturation or linguistic
alienation, the form of speech used in the He
de France came to dominate the "dialects"
of Picardy, Provence and Brittany.
This process, nevertheless, at first only af¬
fects the vocabulary of a language, not its
grammar, i.e. its morphology and syntax. It
is surprising that in spite of four centuries of
cultural pressure, no European language
(English, French, Portuguese or Spanish)
has had the slightest impact on the grammar
of any African language, even the most
fragile or the most exposed to deformation.
Vocabulary, however, is a receptive, sen¬
sitive area in which acculturation (or
cultural exchange, depending on one's point
of view) takes place. But however intensive
it may be, the borrowing of words cannot
disintegrate a linguistic system, since the
newly introduced words are "tamed" and
adapted to the phonetics and the genius of
the borrower language.
The work of History is not yet complete,
'Tis a boulder pushed up hill by our hands.
The moment we desist, its weight presses
upon our breasts,
The moment we rest, it crushes our heads.
The work of History is not yet complete,
This globe has not yet been tempered in the
fire of the Spirit.
CK. Norwid
(1821-1883)
Spartan-style bowl on which the suf¬
ferings of Sisyphus (left) and Pro¬
metheus are depicted. Photo ©
Anderson-Viollet, Paris.
6
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The civilization with the most advanced
technology usually exercises a one-way in¬
fluence on the civilizations or societies with
which it comes into contact. This explains
the phenomenon of Franglais in France.
Such an ascendancy can only disappear
when the technological imbalance no longer
exists.
Creolisation is a linguistic process which
began in a specific historical situation.
Isolated individuals, deprived of their
freedom, were taken from their original en¬
vironment and cast brutally into another en¬
vironment to which they adapted as best
they could. The illiterate Africans thus
deported to the West Indies deformed the
European languages spoken there, creating
new forms of speech in which specialists
have found distant echoes of the syntactical
and morphological structures of African
languages. The same process occurred in the
French empire when Senegalese sharp¬
shooters in the French army virtually
created their own language. Similarly, in
Does cultural assimilation
spell cultural disintegration?
trading areas where different civilizations
meet, linguae francae always tend to form.
Such processes are without exception almost
totally onesided.
Admittedly there are other, more complex
acculturation processes which are reciprocal
and take place between civilizations on dif¬
ferent levels of technological development.
Thus at a Conference of Black Writers and
Artists the French novelist François Mauriac
once maintained that civilizations influence
each other via their negative aspects, and
that the West had taken from Africa and the
Black African world its most dubious pro¬
ducts (he was referring to jazz!) and vice
versa.
Finally, the psychological factor presup¬
poses a certain permanence within a diversi¬
ty of structures. A thorough analysis of this
factor would call for study of what might be
called cultural invariables, that is the un¬
changing psychological characteristics of the
African, the European, the Asian, etc. as
opposed to those characteristics that are
modified by changing conditions. Far from
defending the idea that human nature is im¬
mutable, the aim should be to perceive the
human profile which remains if not iden¬
tical, at least recognizable across centuries
of incessant change.
The cultural environment may be regard¬
ed as an assimilating structure which ab¬
sorbs material from outside and evolves
while remaining aware of its own identity.
Assimilation enriches it without affecting its
destiny. Only destruction by some external
agency, disintegration (whatever the
reason), or hardening of the arteries because
of excessive autarky can be fatal to it.
And so Mauriac's remark should be taken
as a witticism, for civilizations can influence
each other through their positive aspects.
It is accepted today that African art has
had a lasting influence on twentieth-century
Western art. The Western artist has borrow¬
ed from his anonymous African counterpart
not so much a canon of beauty as the right
to break away from such classical norms as
the Golden Number or anatomical realism,
which in various forms have dominated
Western art from Antiquity until modern
times. The creative freedom of plastic forms
and rhythms, a renewed liberty of inven¬
tion are the great lessons that
the wellspring, the heart of all living culture,
of all civilization. Jean-Paul Sartre defined
it well when he wrote that "the specific
characteristics of a society correspond
precisely to the untranslatable locutions of
its language." The second way or level is
concerned with the universal, with general
ideas that everyone can grasp, with the area
in which one civilization can influence
another.
I am not a man of the Diallo looking at a distinct Western world and judging
coolly what I can take from it and what I must give it in return. I have become
both. It is impossible to remain lucid on the horns of such a dilemma. One
becomes a strange being, distressed not to be two.
Cheikh Hamidou Kane
Anthropomorphic Head Sections, by British sculptor Roy Adzak. Photo
© Gérard Dufresne, Paris. Xavier Jeupitre Collection.
modern art has learned from African art.
This is an excellent example of a positive in¬
fluence arising from contact between two
civilizations pursuing a course which is both
parallel and autonomous.
Each civilization has two ways or levels of
handling concepts. The first is concerned
with all that is specific, with an area that is,
so to speak, protected by the people's uni¬
que psychological barrier, an area which can
only be understood from within. This is also
the level of poetic expression; it is the core,
When the core perishes, the life of
societies and civilizations comes to an end.
Hence the widespread efforts today to
safeguard this productive uniqueness which
is not isolation nor withdrawal but the fun¬
damental condition of universality.
Cheikh Anta Diop
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The emergent peoples
of Latin America
The cultural profile of a continent
by Darcy Ribeiro
WE anthropologists have been so
busily engaged in micro-studies of
acculturation that we have never
got around to elaborating a theory of ethnic
transfiguration that would enable us to
understand how modern peoples are form¬
ed. By concentrating our attention on the
supposedly reciprocal cultural influences at
work between peoples we have learned
something of how tribal cultures are
destroyed and rebuilt but remain almost
totally ignorant about the development of
modern peoples and nations.
This is one of the consequences of reduc¬
ing anthropology to "barbarology", a
science interested only in primitive peoples
seen as living fossils of the human species, a
vision, one might add, which is so narrow
DARCY RIBEIRO, Brazilian writer and an¬
thropologist, is a specialist on the Indian tribes of
Amazonia. He has been rector of the University
of Brasilia, has served as his country's Minister of
Education, and has taught in various Latin
American countries, notably in Peru. He is the
author of Civilization Process (Smithsonian In¬
stitution Press, 1969) and many other published
works including a novel, Maira, inspired by the
life of the Amazonian Indians.
that, even in terms of this limited objective,
little progress has been made. Rarely do any
of the numerous specialists of the question
ever mention, even less denounce, the brutal
character of the colonial relations of tribal
peoples with the frontier zones of civiliza¬
tion. Nor do they make clear the ways in
which those peoples, alienated from the
tribal condition, become victims of
deculturation and candidates for incorpora¬
tion into the mass of national societies.
From an ethnic-cultural point of view,
modern American peoples present certain
distinctive characteristics. The first of these
is the astonishing uniformity of the two
blocksthat of the neo-British in the north
and of the neo-Iberian in the south.
England, which never successfully absorbed
the Scots, the Irish or the Welsh, managed
nonetheless to construct a new and gigantic
Anglo-Saxon world in North America.
Spain, which was obliged to respect the
identity of the Basques, the Catalans and
the Galicians, built up a Hispanic America
ten times ar large and more homogeneous
than its own society. Portugal, finally, has
more variety of regional accent in its small
territory than Brazil with its continental im
mensity and its twenty million inhabitants.
This uniformity brings to light, however,
another characteristic of modern and, in the
largest sense of the word, American peoples,
a characteristic which is common to many
non-European peoples its diversification
in four distinct historical and cultural con¬
figurations:
(1) Witness Peoples, that is, those
resulting from the clash of the European in¬
vader with developed civilizations such as
the Aztecs, the Mayas and the Incas; no real
synthesis took place between a surviving
"Indianness" and the newcomers from
Spain.
(2) The New Peoples, produced by the
coming together of Indians from the tribes,
black slaves, and whites from the Iberian
peninsula, employed on the tropical planta¬
tions, in forest exploitations, or in the mines
from which precious metals were extracted.
They gave rise to a completely new ethnic
group, very different from its three com¬
ponents, which is still in search of its identi¬
ty. These are peoples in the process of
becoming and who, lacking a long past of
which they can be proud, depend on the
future for self-definition.
ÏÔÏÏ I -fct
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
(3) Transplanted Peoples, such as those
of North America and Canada, who are
simply European transplantations on
American soil (compare also Australia and
New Zealand). Argentina and Uruguay can
also be placed in this category; although
their populations consisted at first of "New
Peoples", they underwent a migratory flux
of such importance as to change them com¬
pletely.
(4) Emerging Peoples corresponding to
indigenous groups issuing from the
"Witness Peoples" and aspiring to national
autonomy.
Each of these groupings corresponds to a
different process in the formation of
population and nationality. We Brazilians,
for example, as a new people, along with the
Venezuelans, the Cubans, etc. came from
the cross-breeds, sons of white fathers and
Indian or black women, anxious to identify
with the father but rejected by him. We
grew up, all of us, as the spiritual killers of
our maternal lineage, wearing down
thousands of Indians and Blacks in the pro¬
cess of bringing ourselves into being. We
survive in the Tropics because we have
learned to live here with the Indians, making
a living from the small plots where we
cultivate the plants inherited from them. We
hunt, we fish, we build our huts exactly as
they did. We even use Indian words to name
the things of the earth and the sky.
For the black slaves coming from Africa,
civilization meant the loss of their
egalitarian tribal community, where each
man lived as an individual, and being chang¬
ed into an object or commodity. In the
quilombos (compounds) they were reduced
to the state of animals. There they learned
to carry out simple tasks of commercial pro¬
duction with the whip as teacher. They
worked from dawn till dusk, seven days a
week, on their small cultivated plots in order
to have something to eat. As the master
never put together Blacks speaking the same
language, in order to reduce the possibility
of mutiny, they were forced to communicate
between one another in the master's
language. Thus, little by little, they became
rehumanized, learning to be, to speak and
to understand; they became new beings,
ethnically transformed.
Due to the high mortality rate, this savage
system was only able to function thanks to
the constant introduction of fresh black
slaves. To assist this process English and
Spanish entrepreneurs raised the capital to
establish the first modern multinational
enterprises, prodigious organizations to pur¬
sue the Blacks in Africa and embark them
on slave-ships for shipment across the
Atlantic and resale in America.
There were always fewer black women
than men one woman for every four men
perhaps. They were impregnated by the old
boss and his young son, then by the
foreman, etc. Thus came to be born a
number of smiling mulattos who increased
the number of slaves in the service of the
master. Products of this land, they quickly
gained a bad reputation as runaways,
pretentious and suspect mulattos who did
not know their true place. Still very badly
regarded, these mestizos born of Indians
and mulattos form the major part of Latin
Americans today.
The process of formation of the "Witness
Peoples", such as the Mexicans,
Guatemalans, Peruvians, Bolivians and
Ecuadorians, was completely different.
Developed civilizations with cities and a
nobility, priests, armies and bureaucracies,
they were quickly subjugated by the Euro¬
peans who captured their cities, destroyed
their temples, beheaded their nobles,
defeated their armies and took over the
bureaucracy the better to dominate the
enslaved Indian people.
As a result, a prodigious mixing of a few
Europeans with a multitude of captured
Indian women took place. But the
mestizoscuriously much more wester¬
nized isolated themselves in the cities and
towns, still differentiated from the Indians
who continued to live in a universe of their
own, a peasantry cut off from contact with
the urban world. They apparently
represented above all else an inexhaustible
source of manpower for all kinds of work.
Until recently, these natives were seen by
researchers as simple peasants still holding
out against what seemed to be an inexorable
assimilation. The feeling was that sensible
agrarian reform and help in the form of
some elements of education, together with
cunning play on certain indigenous customs,
would encourage them to lose their mania to
be Indians and to become simply good Peru¬
vian, Bolivian, Guatemalan or Mexican
citizens.
Lately, however, the perception that they
are not atypical peasants has become more
generalized. They are, in fact, oppressed
people and as such they aspire legitimately
to be masters of their own destiny in throw- r
The press informs us that a bitter worldwide
struggle is on for leadership among the
major languages: English, French, Russian,
Chinese, Italian, Portuguese, Spanish, etc.
One of the most serious defeats human
culture could suffer would be for one of
these languages to triumph at the cost of the
others. The three or four thousand
languages spoken by man are one of our
most splendid natural resources, as in¬
dispensable to men as is (or was until recent¬
ly) the "green lung" of virgin forest in the
Amazon. These vernaculars are not just
local speech forms but cultural roots. If we
let them rot or be severed, we will be literally
uprooted ourselvesabandoned to suf¬
focate, to suffer a cultural death with far-
reaching consequences.
Marc Soriano
Pictograph "letter" from a Yukaghir girl
(north-east Siberia, beginning 20th cen¬
tury) to her absent lover: "I am all alone
at home. You have left me and gone far
away. You love a Russian girl (with full
skirt) and you have married her (under
one roof with her), but your marriage is
not happy (crossed lines between
them). You will have children and I shall
remain alone and sad (crossed lines). I
shall always love you, although there is
another man who loves me." Photo ©
Musée de l'Homme, Paris.
Racism is one of the most disturbing phenomena of the great revolution of the modern world. At the very
time when industrial civilization is penetrating to all points of the globe and is uprooting men of every col¬
our from their age-old traditions, a doctrine, treacherously scientific in appearance, is invoked in order to
rob these men of theirfull share in the advantages of the civilization forced upon them. There exists in the
structure of our civilization a fatal contradiction. On the one hand it wishes and insists that certain cultural
values, to which it attributes the highest virtues, be assimilated by other people. But conversely it will not
admit that two-thirds of humanity is capable of attaining this standard which it has set up.
Alfred Métraux
(1902-1963)
The Lanlate satellite ground station which handles Nigeria's international telephone, telex and
television communications. Photo Mike Wells © Parimage, Paris. .
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ing off the hegemony of the creóle
minorities, whites in fact, who fought for in¬
dependence, but only to serve their own in¬
terests. Indeed, wherever they took the reins
of government they oppressed the majority
native populations as much, if not more
then the old colonials from the metropolis.
The aggressivity of the Flemings and the
Basques, for example, in their self-affirming
movements, reveals how serious can be the
conflicts that can occur when peoples much
more exploited and oppressed, such as the
Latin American Indians, start to revolt.
Some of them have already begun to do so,
demanding self-determination and the
freedom to be themselves culturally as
"Emerging Peoples" rather than as custo¬
dians of a folklore which enriches the na¬
tional mosaic.
If the Spanish model of unitary States
dominating multi-ethnic societies persists in
the nations where these "Emerging
Peoples" live, violent conflicts will be in¬
evitable and could even degenerate into
ethnic wars. On the other hand, the adop-
white emigrant was generally offered the
possibility of becoming a free farmer, in the
subjected and enslaved zones the work-force
was treated, not in terms of people with
rights, but as animals. In fact, the original
population has always been treated as a
source of energy to be burnt up and used in
much the same way as coal was to be utilized
later on.
For their part, the Latin-American élites
offer a different explanation for this
backwardness. For decades and centuries
they have consoled themselves with the
"erudite" notion that the underdevelop¬
ment of their countries was due to natural,
unalterable factors. Thus the cause was seen
as the intolerable tropical climate and the
uncontrolled mixing of inferior races un-
suited to civilization.
At the same time, without even question¬
ing these explanations, which were both
causal and consolatory, they pointed to
other handicaps, such, for example, as the
live. Others showed that those who work
from sunrise to sunset in our countries
building whatever is constructed there,
cultivating whatever is cultivated and
manufacturing whatever is manufactured,
are, in fact, the Blacks, the mestizos and the
poor whites.
Today there is a growing awareness that,
as in the past, the old social classes run the
country for their own enrichment and pro¬
fit; it is they who supply the managers of the
multinationals and the technocracy that
organize us, ever more effectively, for the
greater benefit of their mother-companies
and the perpetuation of the same sterile
dominant classes.
Over and above the multiple alienations
which are specifically ours, others, still more
serious, come to us from Europe in the form
of ideological contraband. The first of these
was always, and still remains, our ignoble
cultural heritage of racism, the principal
arm of the European ideological arsenal of
A culture of fiesta and siesta?
tion of forms permitting a more active par¬
ticipation as in Switzerland, for ex¬
ample through the organization of
multinational States corresponding to multi¬
ethnic societies could do something to
reduce such conflicts, even if it cannot
eliminate them altogether.
What is unfortunate in this situation is a
tendency to complicate the already very
tense framework of social struggle with
ethnic-cultural factors. The ethnic energies
which are in the process of mobilization may
very well merge with class demands to create
a revolution permitting the building of a
new State, at once more open and
egalitarian at the ethnic level and more
fraternal at the social level. The contrary
could also occur, with the dominant classes
making use of these tensions to perpetuate
their own rule.
Different levels of civilization correspond
to these different historico-cultural con¬
figurations. It is a well known fact, for in¬
stance, that the "Transplanted Peoples"
achieve much higher levels of development
within industrial civilization that any of the
others, especially those transplanted to
North America who, even if they put down
roots a century later and were very much
poorer and had a less illustrious colonial
past, are still very much in advance.
There are good reasons for this. The
"Transplanted Peoples" simply continued
on the other side of the ocean the kind of
life they had led in Europe, fulfilling the
potentialities of the civilization to which
they already belonged within the vast spaces
which they succeeded in conquering. The
"Witness Peoples" and the "New
Peoples", however, developed from the sur¬
vivors of native populations who were vic¬
tims of the terrible massacres that followed
the European invasion. Moreover, they had
been torn from their original culture and in¬
serted in a second class version of the culture
of the colonizers.
Whereas in the settlement colonies the
Criticism of one's own society and culture is also one of the primary functions of culture
which, in our age, has been particularly accentuated. The poète maudit of the romantic era
has today become the committed or revolutionary writer or artist. Refusing injustice, he
demands and exercises his own freedom to further economic, social, moral or cultural revolu¬
tions. Such critical or dissident activity is necessary for the health of peoples, an essential
component of democratic pluralism and an indispensable motor of social progress and
change.
José Luis Martinez
Pen... itentiary! Drawing © André Paris, Fontenouille, France.
Catholic religion which was deemed inimical
to progress.
A still further Latin-American misfortune
was the Iberian heritage which accounts for
the indolence and intolerance of these exotic
peoples, more African than European, from
the confines of the Mediterranean. Many
still regret the expulsion of the French and
the Dutch.
In recent years this consolatory discourse
has been challenged. Some people came to
realize that the Tropics were a good place to
colonial domination.
In attributing to himself the role of civiliz¬
ing agent, the European began by represen¬
ting the outside world as inhabited by sub-
races which he was called upon to
regenerate. The strategem is so terrible and
subtle that .the Blacks, the Indians and the
mestizos acculturated by Europeans, having
profoundly integrated in their consciousness
the idea of their own ugliness and inborn in¬
feriority, suffer terribly for simply being as
they are.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Confronted with the overwhelming
evidence of the physical grace, vivacity and
vigour of the mulattos and mestizos, the
theorists who propound the superiority of
the white race have said for centuries that
the latter are nothing more than human
mules and as such not only sterile but in¬
capable of civilization. Despite their beauty
and incomparable grace, black and brown
women were to be despised not only because
of their ancestral servility, but above all
because they were indelibly marked with the
colour and sign of the inferior races.
Latin-American racism is, it can be seen,
an exported European fruit. Transported
here* it grew and prospered. As compared to
the Saxon variety, the only typical
characteristic of our racism is its
"assimilative" and mixing tendency. The
Indian and Black are no more than the raw
material for making more cross-breeds
whose "whitening" progresses each time a
little more until they become complete
whites.
The second form of ideological and
Eurocentric contraband has to do with the
so-called differential quality of Western
civilization, which is its singular creativity.
This vision claims all the latest material ad¬
vances of civilization as being intrinsically
European. In reality, they are cultural and
human creations achieved in the course of
evolution and as the result of the exploita¬
tion of the material world. However,
because they happen to have appeared in
Europe, they are characterized by "Euro-
peanness", which has led to the error of im¬
agining that sources of energy and
mechanical and technical processes are in¬
herent to a particular civilization.
What are the fruits of Latin
America's African connexion?
This misconception is as stupid as believ¬
ing that petrol is Christian or electricity
English, when in fact they are conquests of
human evolution which can be adopted by
any society which has reached a certain level
of civilization. They may even serve to re¬
inforce cultural autonomy and defend
ethnic identity. Such an eventuality is not
limited to the entry of goods as merchandise
into the imperialist system of unequal ex¬
changes organized to exploit and enslave
other peoples. The fact, for example, that
the Chinese productive system is becoming
more and more technical does not make it
more westernized. On the contrary, it brings
about the very conditions in which it can
free itself from European influences to
become more majestically Chinese.
One last comment on our supposed defi¬
ciencies. It is time we taught the rest of the
world to see us as we are and not as mere
stereotypes. The idea of a Latin America
which is all siesta and fiesta, machismo, of
ready-made dictators, frenetic rumbas and
an unhealthy indolence has exactly the same
function as racism: it completely overlooks
the reality of class and colonial domination.
I have noticed people taking longer lunch
breaks in Holland and Italy than in Brazil.
The long European round of summer
MAIS
.OMISTßOSMQ
il ^~, to yjtttuut*. JU K T*t7m»iVíw**¿
I' M
n*fc~J-
This culture considers itselfsuperior,
not wanting to assimilate others or
to allow itself to be assimilated. It is
ready to incorporate the men of the
discovered territories, but only on
condition that they abandon their
own culture. Thus the culture of the
conquistador and the colonizer was
superimposed on the "demonic" In¬
dian culture. Christian temples were
erected on the ancient Aztec teocallis
(mounds), in place of their ancient
idols were raised up a cross, a statue
of the Virgin Mary or of a saint.
Leopoldo Zea
Los Maestros de Coro y de
Escuela (Choirmasters and
Schoolmasters). Drawing by
Felipe Guarnan Poma de Avala
for his book Nueva Crónica y
Buen Gobierno, a lengthy ac¬
count of indigenous South
American cultures and the
Spanish conquest, probably writ¬
ten between 1578 and 1613.
^tlum m»yt K»
holidays does not, unfortunately have any
parallel here. It is not, however, as creative,
vital and beautiful as our festivals.
As for -the legendary Latin American
laziness, it is worth pointing out that a
worker in a car factory in Mexico or Sao
Paulo works just as hard as his German
counterpart, earning in the process five
times less. On the other hand, directors and
bosses in Brazil make ten times more than
their European counterparts. Exactly the
same point can be made with respect to the
boia-fria (day-worker) of Parana State or
the vaqueiro (cowboy) of Bahia who work
much more than a Texan cowboy or a
French peasant, slogging away without a
break under conditions much worse than
theirs, and for ten times less remuneration.
So much for our laziness.
For us, indolence, like affectation, never
characterized the Blacks, the Indians or the
mulattos, nor, for tlliat matter, the poor
Whites. Rather they were the lot of the rich
white man, the most delicious of his
privileges.
Even the few merits which it is grudgingly
agreed the Latin-American peoples may
^possess, are instantly qualified by the
depreciatory tone employed in speaking of
them. Such is the case, for example, with
our popular music, recognized and praised
as beautiful, rhythmic and vibrant thanks to
its African quality. Even this is held against
us when we are dismissed as insatiable
dancers of sambas, rumbas and boleros.
The "boom" currently enjoyed by Latin
American literature is even more irritating,
and here the prejudice is blatant. A boom,
no matter how surprising, does not need to
be explained as a phenomenon. The simple
truth is that the modern world has few bet¬
ter novelists than García Márquez, Borges,
Cortázar, Rulfo and Guimaraes Rosa, and
few better poets than Neruda, Cesar Vallejo
and Drummond.
Some deficiencies, it must be admitted,
have justly been laid at our door. Take
machismo for instance. It is true that we
have often been guilty of it, but our women
are actively engaged in re-educating us so
that, in addition to being warm and loving,
we can be co-operative, cordial and, why
not, faithful.
The Caudillo-style authoritarianism
which is often attributed to us is not, in fact,
ours. In any event, it is not a creation of the
Latin-American people who have suffered
and still suffer in the flesh from the stupidity
of the enslaving colonial or multinational
"petty kings" which European civilization
has imposed on us.
We are, it is clear, peoples who do not yet
exist; but we shall exist. A process of declin¬
ing civilization has destroyed our sources
and melted us into an immense block, of im¬
portance today if only because of the human
mass it represents: 400 million souls.
Another emerging process of civilization
will transfigure us so that tomorrow ours
will be a privileged place on earth, free, pro¬
sperous and fraternal.
H Darcy Ribeiro
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
1&»
*
te primary and indispensable duty of
'ulture is education.
Pope Jean-Paul II
(speaking at Unesco headquarters, 1980)
Willingly to school! Bali. Photo ©
Hilmar Pabel, Umratshausen am
Chiemsee, Fed. Rep. of Germany.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
EDUCATION
THE eradication of illiteracy is the most urgent
educational problem at the planetary level. In
1970 almost one-third of the world's adult popu¬
lation was illiterate: 32.4 per cent of persons aged 15 and
over, a total of 742 million people. By 1980 it was
estimated that the illiteracy rate had dropped by around
3.5 per cent during the preceding decade. However,
because of soaring population growth the number of il¬
literates had risen by 72 million since 1970 an increase
of 7 million a year and stood at 814 million.
These figures show that the struggle against illiteracy
and its attendant inequalities (for illiteracy affects
above all the countries of the Third World) is a race
against the clock. But the statistics also show that no
less flagrant inequalities exist at the other end of the
scale, in higher education. The total number of scien¬
tists and engineers involved in research and develop¬
ment throughout the world (with the exception of China
and certain other countries) was estimated to be almost
2.8 million in 1974, in the middle of the second develop¬
ment decade; 2.6 million of them, 94 per cent, were
working in the developed countries, which thus had
almost 2,600 scientists and research workers per million
population, as opposed to 100 per million in the
developing countries.
Harmonious cultural and economic development will
be beyond the reach of mankind until the imbalances in
basic and higher education are radically corrected. One
of the surest ways of achieving this goal is the
democratization of education. Access to education
should be open to all: rural populations, minorities,
workers and migrant workers, boys and girls, adult men
and women. By giving everyone the chance to pursue
their education as far as their gifts permit, this
democratization would reflect concern for quality as
well as quantity.
If it is to be more effective, education should also be
better adapted to the cultural environment. It yields its
best fruit when it is firmly rooted in the cultural identi¬
ty and traditions of each people.
Finally, education can be made more relevant to the
economic development of each country when it is more
closely geared to meeting its people's short- and
medium-term needs, and when it attaches a new value to
manual work thus healing the debilitating breach bet¬
ween manual and intellectual work.
Blackboard bungle?
A defence of the school
as the cornerstone of education
by Arthur V. Petrovsky
ACCORDING to Unesco statistics, almost one-sixth of the
world's population is still illiterate. The percentage of il¬
literacy is particularly high in Africa and Asia. The ap¬
parently unresolvable contradiction between the demand for
education and the material possibilities of satisfying this demand
have led to talk of a "world education crisis", although attempts
to extrapolate the real difficulties confronting education in the
developing world to the educational situation in other countries
seem to go a little too far.
Thus the USSR is today in the process of solving, with overall
success, the problem of teaching and educating its rising genera-
ARTHUR VLADIMIROVICH PETROVSKY, Soviet psychologist, is Pro¬
fessor of Education and Psychology at the State University ofMoscow and
a member of the Academy of Pedagogical Sciences of the USSR. In 1971
and 1972 he was a member of Unesco's International Commission on the
Development of Education. He is the author of several works on
psychological and educational questions, and of textbooks for use in
higher education.
tion. The country which sixty-five years ago had an illiteracy rate
of 73 per cent has in this short period eradicated illiteracy, whereas
forecasts made by the Education Ministry of Tsarist Russia shortly
before the October Revolution indicated that it would take at least
120 years to provide universal education in European Russia, and
4,600 to achieve the same goal in central Asia and the Caucasus.
The right to education, proclaimed by law, is exercised in a
whole network of educational establishments of different kinds. In
the USSR one person in every three is a student, and over
100 million persons are receiving some form of education. Some
44 million children attend schools providing a general education.
These observations should lead to the establishment of a sharp
distinction between the characteristics of educational development
in the developing countries and those in the industrially developed
countries.
In the developing countries the expansion of educational systems
and the increase in the number of pupils are sure to lead to the
characteristic distortions of a "growth crisis". The first of these, ^
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
We do not ask of the strong
that they should have a bad
conscience, merely (hat they
should have a conscience.
Paul Marc Henry
Ugandan boy. Photo A. de
Wildenberg © Gamma,
Paris.
^ breaking the link between the educational system and the needs of
society, will lead to the school being cut off from the outside
world, and to an increase in the ranks of the educated unemployed.
Secondly, distorsions will arise within the educational system itself,
stemming from a lack of co-ordination between its various stages
and constituent parts. Still poorly attended and beyond the reach
of the mass of pupils who complete primary schooling, the secon¬
dary school forms a bottleneck, especially since it does not prepare
its pupils for productive work but for entry to an institution of
higher education which in practice the majority of them will never
reach.
Languages are the pedigrees of
nations.
Samuel Johnson
(1709-1784)
St. Cyril (827-869) and St.
Methodius (825-884) who
translated the Bible into Old
Slavonic and invented the
Cyrillic alphabet. Photo ©
Missi, Paris.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Continents, major Public expenditure Public expenditure Public expenditure
areas and groups on education on education on education
of countries (in millions of dollars) as % of GNP per inhabitant ($)
1965 1970 1975 1978 1965 1970 1975 1978 1965 1970 1975 1978
World total* 96 026 159 898 333 079 474 014 4.8 5.4 5.7 5.6 38 57 109 146
Africa* 1 737 3 102 8 320 12 972 3.4 4.2 4.8 4.8 6 9 21 29
America 43 374 77 355 127 622 171 985 5.1 6.3 6.1 6.0 94 152 229 291
Asia* 7 221 12 910 44 368 80 039 3.5 3.5 4.9 5.0 7 11 33 55
Europe iincl. USSR) 42 624 64 546 145 816 200 240 5.0 5.2 5.8 5.7 63 92 200 271
Oceania 1 071 1 984 6 953 8 778 3.7 4.4 6.2 6.3 63 104 331 399
Developed countries* 88 173 147 302 295 520 418 907 5.1 5.7 6.0 5.9 86 137 263 366
Developing countries* 7 853 12 596 37 559 55 107 2.9 3.3 4.1 4.1 5 7 19 26
Africa
(excl. Arab States)* 1 106 1 860 6 954 7 257 3.2 3.6 4.3 4.1 5 7 16 21
Asia
(excl. Arab States)* 6 845 12 331 39 226 72 965 3.4 3.5 4.7 5.0 7 11 30 52
Arab States 1 007 1 822 8 508 12 789 4.0 4.9 6.8 5.6 10 16 63 87
Northern America 40 049 71 839 113 288 151 187 5.4 6.7 12.2 6.6 187 318 480 622
Latin America 3 324 5 516 14 334 20 798 3.0 3.3 3.7 4.0 13 20 45 60
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1981
General note Owing to the rounding of figures, the totals and sub-totals
shown in this table do not always correspond exactly to the sums of their
component items.
*World Total Not including South Africa, China, Democratic Kam¬
puchea, Democratic People's Republic of Korea, Lao People's Democratic
Republic and Viet-Nam.
*Africa Not including South Africa.
*Asia Not including China, Democratic Kampuchea, Democratic Peo¬
ple's Republic of Korea, Lao People's Democratic Republic and Viet-
Nam.
*Developed countries Not including South Africa.
'Developing countries Not including China, Democratic Kampuchea,
Democratic People's Republic of Korea, Lao People's Democratic
Republic and Viet-Nam.
*Africa (excluding Arab States) Not including South Africa.
*Asia (excluding Arab States) Not including China, Democratic Kam¬
puchea, Democratic People's Republic of Korea, Lao People's Democratic
Republic and Viet-Nam.
In almost two-thirds of African countries, the proportion of
young people who enter secondary education does not reach the
threshold of 10 per cent which, specialists believe, is indispensable
for autonomous development. The percentage of students in in¬
stitutions of higher education is no more than 1-2 per cent in the
developing countries (0.2-0.3 per cent in some parts of Africa).
Attention must also be drawn to the disharmony between the
acute need for qualified personnel and the speed and nature of
their training, and the disparity between limited material resources
and the magnitude of the tasks on hand.
The developing countries are just as keenly aware of the problem
of the content of education and of increasing its efficiency as the
industrially developed countries. How to bridge the gap between
an ever-rising tide of information and the amount of knowledge
that schools can actually provide? This problem is bound to worsen
in the developing countries since they have inherited from long
years of colonialism defective, second-rate educational facilities.
In recent decades, these countries have tried in several ways to
find a solution by maintaining the bases of pseudo-classical educa¬
tion with the addition of a few correctives inspired by the spirit of
the age; by recourse to practical training in primary schools (at the
expense of general subjects); by maintaining in secondary and
higher education institutions a high level of training similar to that
in the industrially developed countries; by radically overhauling
general education in order to gear it to a future occupation, usually
in farming; by splitting education into two systems, one
"practical", the other "academic".
The basic problem facing the developing countries is how to find
the most efficient methods of intensifying the teaching effort. This
is also a central preoccupation of educators in the developed coun¬
tries, and on its solution, to a large extent, hinges the future of
world education.
But may there not be a way of solving all these problems at once,
of cutting the Gordian knot? Some people believe that such a
course is possible, and that the answer is simply... the abolition of
schools.
As I discovered when I was a member of Unesco's international
commission on the development of education, there is no easier
way to win applause and make a reputation as an "innovator"
than to boldly attack the school. The accusations levelled against
schools (and against education in general) as well as the commen¬
dations they attract, always follow the same lines: education
institutionalized in the school is "reactionary", "conservative",
and "elitist"; the school is incapable of transmitting a corpus of
knowledge to the pupil; the pupil should enjoy the same rights as
the teacher, deciding what he or she wants to learn and how. For
these reasons schools should be abolished, perhaps not immediate¬
ly but in the not-too-distant future.
Does this old and faithful ally of humanity in the struggle to ac¬
quire knowledge, culture and education really deserve such op¬
probrium? Born several millennia before the Christian era, at the
time of the flowering of ancient Egypt, Babylon and India, the
school has satisfied human needs and all that constitutes the pride
and glory of humankind has emerged from its walls. So what has
happened on the eve of the twenty-first century? What arguments
are advanced by the proponents of a "radical criticism" of the
school?
Argument number one: the school acts as a brake on progress.
School education is essentially "conservative"; it reinforces in¬
equality between men. Its consequence is the transmission of
established, tested and thus notoriously out-of-date opinions. It is
in the interests of those who define the goals and content of educa¬
tion to make sure that others know no more than they do
themselves.
Such, roughly speaking, is the case made by the "radical critics"
who maintain that education is a force "that helps people to accept
society as it is and to resign themselves to it." Can this point of
view be upheld?
The fact that education involves the transmission from genera¬
tion to generation of tried and tested opinions and experiences is
no more a criterion of conservatism than the use of tried and tested
medicines by the medical profession. It would be a mistake to
regard as conservatism the relative stability of any kind of educa¬
tional system (educational systems often possess a dynamic of their
own). Admittedly, the facts and laws to be transmitted to the pupil
may change, today more rapidly than ever, as the scientific and
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
^ technological revolution progresses, but this dynamic of change
should not be pushed to the absurd.
The experience of a soundly based educational reform, as cur¬
rently being carried out by the Soviet Union, for example, shows
that the inevitable, well-founded modifications in the syllabus are
not an exact, point by point reflection of the scientific discoveries
of today and yesterday. The nucleus of knowledge transmitted to
the pupil undergoes relatively slight changes whereas modifications
occur more rapidly in the envelope of information which surrounds
this nucleus.
It is equally inaccurate to maintain that education is always reac¬
tionary, just as it would clearly be wrong to claim that it is always
progressive. The educational system as it has emerged historically is
reactionary if the social and economic principle underpinning the
Is school the enemy of creativity?
society in which it functions is reactionary. Everything depends on
the goals and content of education. A partial approach can only
lead to confusion.
Argument number two: it is just as easy to learn in a café as at
school. The theory of "incidental education", whose supporters
advocate deschooling, envisages the free exchange of opinions, en¬
counters with interesting people, freedom from interference by
teachers, from the spine-chilling fear of examinations and from
blinkered study programmes. "Studying" in a café and sweetening
with liqueurs the bitter root of knowledge undeniably holds more
appeal to some than attending school. There can be no doubt that
the cinema, the street and the mass media are sources of informa¬
tion; there is in any case no question of underestimating their im¬
portance.
However, scientific knowledge, that is to say the presentation of
what is general and essential in objects and phenomena and, afor¬
tiori, of systematic knowledge, can only be communicated by
means of structured teaching and above all by a soundly organized
school. The goal of a school is precisely to enable each individual
to learn how to learn, in other words to give him an opportunity to
acquire knowledge for himself, to develop his capacities for
assimilation and to stimulate the need to know and under¬
stand.
Argument number three: young people are always right. Bran¬
dishing this slightly modified version of the salesman's slogan that
the customer is always right, the "radicals" claim that they are put¬
ting young people on their guard against teachers who "attach too
much importance to the printed word" (i.e. books and textbooks),
against systematic education which may "paralyze" the free-
ranging creativity of young people, and against examinations
which are "an insult" to the free expression of their personality. In
practice, these "revolutionary" appeals are transformed into an ir¬
responsible attitude on the part of teachers towards their pupils
and into indifference on the part of the pupils towards their
teachers.
The affirmation that "the pupil should be able to choose where,
how and what subject he studies; thus education will be adapted to
each individual" has the same ring as those set forth above.
Undeniably each person is free to choose the general direction of
his studies. But the programmes, the methods, and the textbooks
imply a harmonization without which it would be impossible to
create equal conditions for all. Pupils are not equal in energy and
abilities, their level of education varies, and a certain individualiza¬
tion of education is indispensable; but this must not become, in the
educational system of the future, an end in itself. The in¬
dividualization of education is one of the most important aspects
of the universalization of education, but it is neither an absolute
nor a panacea.
Admittedly, certain types of school and certain forms of
teaching are open to criticism. Many aspects of schooling call for a
complete overhaul and invite reforms. However, rejection of the
school as a social institution, now or in the future, would be tanta¬
mount to capitulation in the struggle for education, and would
mean that we should enter the twenty-first century with the pro¬
blems and difficulties bequeathed to us by the twentieth.
Like a meridian and the horizon, the line we draw between cen¬
turies and even millennia is a convention. Only what we sow here
and now will bear fruit beyond that line. It is up to us to see that
the harvest is good, and that it satisfies humanity's ever-growing
need for universal knowledge and understanding.
Arthur V. Petrovsky
We want to construct an economy? Then look at our peoples. Who are they? They are many, they are poor,
malnourished, badly housed, sick, without education and reduced to unemployment. This must be our starting
point. There can be none other.
Han-Sheng Lin
These imposing terraces were built by a production brigade in the Shansi Province of China. Photo
© China Photo Service, Peking.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Preparing people for change
A testing time for modern education
Only the educated are free.
Epictetus (AD 55-135)
A school in Zambia. Photo © Abisag Tüllmann, Frankfurt, Fed. Rep. of Germany.
JOensure continuity in each society
and to promote its renewal with¬
out detriment to its inherent
genius would appear to be the essential
purpose ofeducation in its twofoldfunc¬
tions ofsocial reproduction and innova¬
tion: the school is the place above all
others where the cultural heritage ofeach
people can be transmitted and
perpetuated, while it simultaneously
paves the way for social renewal by in¬
culcating the attitudes and aptitudes that
people need in order to take part in
change and to master it.
But the very speed of contemporary
social and economic changes, the grow¬
ing pace of advances in knowledge, par¬
ticularly in science and technology, and
their application to increasingly varied
fields, the growing complexity of the dif¬
ferent societies, and the intensification
of intercultural exchanges and in¬
fluences, all mean that this twofold ob¬
jective presents something of a
challenge.
One of the major features of this se¬
cond half of the twentieth century is un¬
questionably the recognition that educa¬
tion is a fundamental right for in¬
dividuals and a prerequisite for social
progress. This universal recognition ex¬
plains the unprecedented expansion of
education throughout the world over the
last two decades. Between I960 and
1980, the numbers ofpupils and students
at the different levels of education
almost doubled, rising from 327,000,000
to 648,000,000, although admittedly
growth rates varied from region to
region, country to country and level to
level. Growth was particularly marked at
the secondary and higher levels. The
number of students in post-secondary
education almost quadrupled, going up
from under 12,500,000 to over
47,000,000. The number of secondary
pupils rose by a little more than 150 per
cent, from 69,000,000 in 1960 to
180,000,000 in 1980.
Despite the substantial advances
achieved, however, the democratization
of education is still, in many countries,
by no means a reality. In addition to the
persistence of illiteracy, which is among
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Education is an act of love and therefore an act of courage. If it does not
want to be considered a joke it must fearlessly accept debate, realistic
analysis and creative discussion.
Paulo Freiré
A young Canadian Eskimo girl at school.
Paris.
Photo © Paul Almasy,
To see our neighbour and everyone is now our neighbour does not
mean to know him. Just as the brain interprets the message receivedfrom
the optic nerve, we must, in the same way, equip ourselves to interpret the
messages received from other peoples. It has been said that racism is a
pathological state of mind, a form of irrationality, a kind of epidemic.
These terms imply the existence of a healthy state which can be attained
and maintained in a world where different nations coexist.
Jean-Paul Sartre
(1905-1980)
Intervention au Havre, by the French artist Ernest Pignon Ernest
who exhibits his work in public places associated with violent in¬
cidents. Photo © Ernest Pignon Ernest, Paris.
^ the gravest of the inequalities that afflict
the modern world, there are still con¬
siderable differences in the opportunities
available for access to education.
Inequalities weigh particularly hardly
on the rural areas, even though, sofar as
schooling is concerned, those who live
on the fringes of certain cities, the han¬
dicapped, certain minorities, migrant
workers and refugees are also at a disad¬
vantage. The same is true, in many cases,
of girls and women. Despite the con¬
siderable increase in the numbers ofgirls
and women enrolled which, in higher
education, increased fivefold between
1960 and 1980the percentage of girls
and women attending schools and
universities is still, in many countries,
below that of men. It drops as the level
of education rises, and is in general
markedly below that ofthe male students
following scientific and technological
courses.
By no means all levels and kinds of
education have as yet been made free of
IB
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The mother tongue the sine
qua non of education?
charge everywhere and, in some cases,
the expansion ofeducation has been par¬
ticularly advantageous to the most pro¬
sperous sections of the population. In
this respect, the limitations of the kind of
egalitarianism that merely offers equality
ofaccess to all, regardless of inequalities
or differences in background, are begin¬
ning to be more clearly appreciated: it is
now obvious that the democratization of
education cannot be interpreted in pure¬
ly quantitative terms, and that its pur¬
pose must in fact be to secure the best
opportunities for everyone.
This probably implies that special
measures need to be taken to assist those
who, because of their race, sex, origins
or socio-cultural antecedents, are unable
to take full advantage, on a footing of
equality, of the education offered them.
In the same connexion, efforts need to
be made to relax the technical pro¬
cedures for changing from one type of
course or kind of education to another,
thereby making it easier for students to
branch out in new directions as they pro¬
ceed and so ensuring that different
talents can be developed in the best
possible way.
It would also be well to endeavour to
adapt the content and methods ofeduca¬
tion more closely and at the same time
moreflexibly to the natural, cultural and
human environment in which it is pro¬
vided. In the developing countries that
have recently gained their independence,
under the lingering influence of systems
inherited from the colonial period,
education still often fails to some extent
to match the real situations and needs.
In many of those countries, the ques¬
tion of the language of instruction is still
unsettled, even in primary school, and
the use of curricula to maintain and re¬
inforce cultural identity is an acute
problem. But most industrialized or
developing societies find, in varying
degrees, the same difficulties in reconcil¬
ing the additional demands now placed
on education, which is required to open
people's minds to the international en¬
vironment through a better knowledge
of worldproblems and greater insight in¬
to the values of different civilizations,
while at the same time promoting deeper
ties with the fabric of local life, so as to
enable individuals and their communities
to master their own environment and
mobilize its resources.
Education is, in fact, by its very
nature, angled towards the future, i.e.
the uncertain, and the function of
preparing people for change has become
all the more difficult to discharge
because of the extremely rapid
developments taking place in modern
societies and the constantly increasing
complexity and diversification of their
forms of organization, while there are ,
still, for practical purposes, no effective
instruments for evaluating changes and
predicting developments. It is scarcely^
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
^surprising, then, that educational
systems have for several decades past
been severely criticized, partly on the
grounds that education prepares people
to live in an already outdated society.
This is borne out by the fact that con¬
tent and curricula often lag far behind
the advance of knowledge, particularly
as regards science and technology
teaching. In very many countries, greater
emphasis should be placed on general
science teaching, which should begin in
primary school and continue throughout
the various stages of education, so as to
give pupils a thorough grasp of the prin¬
ciples of scientific method and instil an
attitude conducive to active, critical in¬
vestigation of the world around them.
Technical and vocational education
should likewise be developed, since it is
in very many cases still inadequate, while
the branches ofspecialization and course
content offered do not always meet
development needs.
More generally, the way in which
education and vocational training are
matched to employment leaves much to
be desired. A case in point is higher
education, where students are often
distributed among the different course
options with no regard for the develop¬
ment of society and its consequent
employment needs, leading to an over¬
abundance of skilled manpower in cer¬
tain fields and a shortage in others, and
creating both difficulties in obtaining
work and frustrations for individuals.
Moreover, despite the efforts made to
link education more closely with the
world of work, as an essential require¬
ment for a sound training for life,
whether through better careers counsel¬
ling or through a growing interpénétra¬
tion of education and work, calculated
to acquaint pupils, students and teachers
with the realities of the productive sec¬
tor, this linkage has seldom been achiev¬
ed. Thepractical measures taken for this
purpose, such as the introduction ofpro¬
ductive work into the educational pro¬
cess, which is of indisputable educative
value and can make a real contribution
to ending the age-old dichotomy between
intellectual and manual work, are en¬
countering resistance in many countries.
The difficulty experienced in opening
up education to the world of work is
evidence of what some see as a split bet¬
ween schooling and life. It reflects the
fact that, in very many cases, educa¬
tional systems that are still too rigid to
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
respond appropriately to all the increas¬
ingly numerous, increasingly diversified
and constantly changing demands made
upon them by society are lagging behind
what has become an extremely complex
and unsettled social reality.
The need for freer adaptation of
education to social needs, andfor afiner
appreciation of their probable develop¬
ment, is therefore making itself felt in
most parts of the world.
This means developing the educational
sciences and research in that area. It is
still quite widely believed that teaching is
a craft for which there is no need to call
on the aid ofscience. It would seem that,
on the contrary, the linkages and inter¬
relations between education and society
cannot be improved without constant
progress in the educational sciences, as
integral parts of the social sciences, and
the devising ofappropriate arrangements
to enable their findings to be taken more
fully and more swiftly into account in
educational practice.
It further seems to be increasingly
clear that initial teacher training is not in
itself enough. Teachers' knowledge must
be regularly and systematically updated
in order to cope with the development of
knowledge and meet the needs of social
change. Hence lifelong education ap¬
pears to be an essential facet of the
teacher's profession.
From the standpoint oflifelong educa¬
tion itself, considered not as further
vocational training but rather as an
overall process of education, starting
with the earliest stage and continuing
throughout life, the development of in-
Is there a split between school
and society?
formal and non-formal types of educa¬
tion, and better co-ordination between
them and the formal systems, also seem
to meet the wish to bring about greater
interpénétration between education and
society as a whole. This would make for
that diversification of the content,
methods, structures and levels of educa¬
tion and training required by the modern
world.
Another point is that the efforts and
resources of every kind invested in
education are now on such a substantial
scale that it seems difficult to in¬
crease and for some countries, even to
maintain their present level; the finan¬
cial and human cost represented in many
countries by excessive repeating of
grades and dropping out, particularly in
higher education, is a source of keen
anxiety. It therefore appears more than
ever necessary not only to improve
school and university counselling but to
tap for the benefit of all the whole
educational potential of society, if it is
true that in view of the limitations on
natural resources and the slippages of
growth, the future of the nations will in
the coming years depend on how well
they can mobilize and make use of the
human resources at their disposal.
To that end, and having regard to the
uncertainties and difficulties inherent in
any attempt to peer into the future, it is
reasonable to think that the best
preparation for this as yet indeterminate
world to come is a kind ofeducation that
endeavours to marshal all capacities for
initiative and creativity, individual and
collective, so as to prepare the way for
communities themselves to take charge
of their own development. In this
respect, an especially apt approach is to
organize learning as a process whereby
the pupilfollowsfor himself the paths of
the historical and methodological
development ofscientific, technological,
philosophical or artistic creation. Seen
thus, the act of learning becomes an act
ofre-creation and as such the basis ofall
creativity.
But while education must aim for the
all-round development of the individual,
bestowing on him a fuller control over
his environment and helping him to
develop his specific talents and ap¬
titudes, it must alsofoster, from the very
earliest years, attitudes of tolerance,
justice and solidarity. At a time when
much of mankind is experiencing a
renewed and explosive upsurge of
violence in various forms, and while
flagrant violations of human rights con¬
tinue, there is a widely felt need to give
civic and moral education, or give them
back, their rightful place. But such
education poses a problem in a certain
number of countries where a gap has
opened up between morality as taught
and what is actually practised in the
family and in society. Education should
therefore endeavour, in the coming
years, to foster the emergence of at¬
titudes and values corresponding to the
realities, demands and aspirations of a
changing society.
To accomplish great things one must be with men, not above them.
Montesquieu
(1689-1755)
Moving a Dorze style house, Ethiopia. Photo Georg Gerster
© Rapho, Paris.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
i
2
Know this, sovereign and subject,
Prince and pauper,
None shall have the right to an excess
So long as a single man is lacking
The bare necessities.
Salvador Díaz Mirón
(1853-1928)
San Francisco 1933, at the soup
kitchen. Photo Dorothea Lange © The
Museum of Modern Art, New York.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
HUNGER, POPULATION
ENVIRONMENT
HUNGER and malnutrition claim millions of vic¬
tims in the Third World every year, exacting a
grim toll of deaths, disease and deficiencies.
Undernourishment (less than 2,000 calories a day) af¬
fects 28 per cent of the population in Asia, 25 per cent in
Africa, and 13 per cent in Latin America. According to
recent statistics, 17 million children under five die each
year, most of them in developing countries. Fifteen
million could be saved if they had access to food sup¬
plies and hygiene facilities available in the developed
countries. How can our all-conquering technological
civilization permit the existence of this scandalous
situation which Unesco Director-General Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow has denounced as "an intolerable situa¬
tion with which history confronts mankind"? Scandal is
the word if only because world cereal reserves are
enough to provide everyone with 3,000 calories and
65 grammes of protein per day, in other words more
than the minimum necessary for a normal life. Why
does this situation persist? For one thing because 43 per
cent of these reserves are used as animal food (mainly to
satisfy over-consumption of animal protein in the rich
countries). Meanwhile many countries with a hunger
problem are actually exporting large amounts of food to
feed animals and people in the rich countries where
overnutrition is a health problem.
What is the justification for a model of development
which leads to extremes of overconsumption by a rich
minority and drags Third World peoples deeper into a
morass of poverty and marginalization, at the cost of en¬
vironmental degradation? Is it not true that our planet
has enough resources to satisfy everyone's need but not
everyone's greed? What steps should be taken to meet
the needs of over 6 billion persons who according to
United Nations projections will populate the planet in
the year 2000? The immense majority of them will be in
the Third World which the current system of develop¬
ment and international relations already prevents from
feeding itself adequately.
For an alternative development
Balanced economic growth will be impossible
without environmental protection
by Anil Agarwal
IF there is anything that can be said with
certainty about environmental and
development problems it is that they
worsened considerably throughout the
Third World during the 1970s.
The United Nations estimates that nearly
half a billion people go to bed seriously
literally half-starved at the
end of every day. Many millions of these
people are children. Any disease that at¬
tacks them in this condition, and there are
many diseases going around, takes a heavy
toll. During the 1970s, for example, diar¬
rhoea caused by lack of clean drinking water
and sanitation continued to kill at least
16,000 children in the Third World every
ANIL AGARWAL, Indian author and journalist
specializing in development questions, is Director
of the Centre for Science and Environment, in
New Delhi. Among his published works are
Drugs and the Third World (1978) and Mud,
Mud: The Potential of Earth-based Building
Materials for Housing Programmes in the Third
World (1981)
day. Yet diarrhoea seldom kills unless the
child also happens to be a victim of inade¬
quate nutrition.
The changing environment is also
resulting in the increased incidence of many
diseases. The rapid spread of
schistosomiasis in several North African
countries is now very well known. Lesser
known is the spread of the killer disease
Japanese encephalitis from Japan to India.
Japanese encephalitis is a brain fever that
kills almost every second person who is un¬
fortunate enough to get it. The disease has
spread slowly with the growth of surface ir¬
rigation systems which provide an excellent
breeding ground for the disease-spreading
mosquito. Provision of drinking water and
various types of construction activities
without adequate drainage have led to a
dramatic surge in filariasis in several coun¬
tries. The increase in malaria cases with the
growth in vector resistance against
pesticides is also now well documented.
As if this were not enough, many
developing countries are now acquiring a
double burden of disease: the traditional
water- and mosquito-borne diseases
together with what are generally regarded
as diseases of affluence. With uncontrolled
industrialization and increasing use of
chemicals in both agriculture and industry,
cancer is becoming an important disease in
the Third World. The World Health
Organization estimates that, of the eight
million cancer cases in the world, five
million are in the developing countries. With
cigarette consumption growing in the Third
World, a commerciogenic epidemic of
cancer can be expected well before the end
of the century. At their current expenditure
of a few dollars per head on health services,
developing countries will have neither the
manpower nor the financial resources to
provide the necessary therapeutic facilities.
The environment, too, has been slowly
worsening. Every minute 20 hectares of
tropical forest cover is destroyed about
one per cent of the total forest cover in the
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
world every year. As much land is lost to
salinity and waterlogging as comes under ir¬
rigation every year. In most countries of the
Third World, air and water pollution are
becoming increasingly worse whereas in
many developed countries, governments
with greater access to financial resources
have initiated schemes and enforced stan¬
dards that have reversed the trend.
Across the Third World today, there is
growing disenchantment with the existing
development process. This is reflected in a
growing concern about the environment
too, in marked contrast to the fears that
developing countries exhibited at the mam¬
moth Stockholm conference on the human
environment which first raised environmen¬
tal consciousness on a worldwide scale.
Experts then argued that there would be
conflicts between environmental preserva¬
tion and the process of economic develop¬
ment and that concern for the environment
would retard the latter. Today many
recognize this debate to be an entirely
fallacious one. The demand for an alter¬
native development process is growing and
experience now clearly shows that rational,
balanced, equitable economic development
will be impossible without environmental
protection. Environmental degradation in¬
evitably leads to greater inequalities in
which the poorest sections of the society
suffer most.
The rationale for this line of argument is
pretty simple and straightforward. In a Third
World society with a high population densi¬
ty and high levels of poverty, virtually every
ecological niche is utilized by some cultural
or occupational group for its sustenance.
When the more powerful forces in the
society destroy that ecological niche or
allocate its resources for some other use,
the dispossessed group obviously suffers.
All over the Third World this process is
repeating itself ad nauseam. Take a few ex¬
amples. For years, traditional marine
fishermen have sustained themselves on the
fishery resources available near the coast.
With the introduction of mechanized
vessels and trawlers, these resources are
being overfished all over Asia. The losers in
the process are the small fishermen who
have lived for centuries in harmony with
their environment.
Environmental degradation
who are the culprits, the élite
or the poor?
Third World forests are being destroyed
in a big way to meet the demand for in¬
dustrial timber, both for local urban and in¬
ternational markets. In this process, the
forest-dependent indigenous peoples of the
world are being destroyed at the rate of one
tribe a year. The destruction of the forests
completely disrupts their age-old lifestyle.
Even where afforestation is taking place, it
is useless for them. Monocultures of com¬
mercial species do not provide them with
the fruits, roots and tubers that traditionally
met their needs.
A similar process is affecting the nomadic
people of the Third World. With cultivable
land in short supply, the more powerful
sedentary peoples, supported by their
governments, have moved in and occupied
the marginal lands that were formerly the
nomad's grazing lands. Pushed out of their
traditional territories, the nomads are being
forced on to even more marginal lands,
where these exist. Otherwise they simply
crowd together into the ever-diminishing
areas of grazing land that are left. In the pro¬
cess, both the nomads and the land are suf¬
fering immensely.
The world's rivers have been used for
centuries as sources of drinking water and
for sustaining substantial populations of
riverine fishermen. But with unregulated in¬
dustrialization and urbanization, these rivers
have become cheap dumping grounds for
chemical and microbiological filth. Inland
fisheries in many parts of the Third World
have disappeared totally and those who
continue to depend on the untreated waters
of these rivers for drinking purposes suffer
high mortality rates.
This process of marginalization and grow¬
ing poverty on the one hand and greater
control over resources associated with un¬
precedented levels of material affluence on
the other, is going on all over the world. A
high consumption culture, characterized by
Western life styles, is pervading even the
Third World. But because of its high cost
and heavy resource use it remains restricted
iflf*
o v
m
6
Y '
Í > -
V
.*->
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Product or process should
development be redefined?
to a small section of its population.
Almost all the Third World's environment
and development problems can be traced to
this cultural process. The current patterns
of economic development have initiated this
"multinationalization" of culture and now
that this culture has been set in motion, it
demands with increasing force the con¬
tinuation of the same pattern of economic
development. Even those who do not now
benefit from this culture keep hoping that
someday they will. Today there is no
freedom to choose. A kind of vicious circle
is operating. Multinational corporations sell
the kind of products that initiate a multi¬
national culture, and once this culture
begins to seep in and be enjoyed by the
powerful, they demand even more strongly
the products of multinational corporations.
To keep this vicious circle going everything
is attacked and degraded, nothing is ex¬
empt, from forests, rivers and whales to the
mass of human beings and human cultures.
Some naive experts and politicians have
argued that environmental problems can be
arrested if the basic needs of the poor can
somehow be met. Global environmental
problems can in almost every case be traced
to the overconsumption of the rich, not the
underconsumption of the poor. These ex¬
perts betray total lack of understanding of
the problem of poverty. Many of those who
Give me a lever long enough and a fulcrum
strong enough and single-handed I can
move the world.
Archimedes
(287-212 BC)
Gabra tribesmen building an access
road, Kenya. Photo Richard Saunders
© ICA, Washington, D.C.
Our blood must burn
We must catch fire
If we are to move the onlookers
If the world is at last to open its eyes
Not on our remains
But on the wounds of the survivors
Kateb Yacine
The breadlinewaiting for the daily
ration of bread at Dessie relief camp,
Ethiopia (1966). Photo Brian Aris ©
Parimage, Paris.
are poor today were not poor a century ago
and then lived in close harmony with nature.
Moreover, the very definition of
"development" has been completely
distorted. Instead of defining development
as a process which enables individuals,
communities and nations, in fact, all levels
of society, to become increasingly self-
reliant, with greater control over their
destinies, development is now defined
almost as if it were some kind of product
that can be obtained with economic
growth. Development cannot simply be
equated with increased consumption and
production of material goods in society, yet
this is the operational definition of develop¬
ment that prevails all over the world. It
clearly smacks of the very consumer culture
that it is creating.
If the definition of development as a
process towards greater self-reliance at
all levels of society, including individual
and community, is accepted, then the so-
called developed countries have
"underdeveloped" at a more rapid
pace their demands having far outgrown
the resources of their environment than
developing countries and they are now
spreading an economic process that is
underdeveloping the Third World too.
A remarkable facet of past cultures which
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
There are two types of poverty: that which, in certain societies affects only a minority, and that
which, in other societies, affects all but a:minority.
J.K. Galbraith
Child In the City, photo-portrait by Josef Pokorny, Czechoslovakia. International
photographic contest, UNO.
lived in harmony with their environment was
that they were totally dependent for their
daily needs on their immediate environ¬
ment. Today the so-called developed
human beings know less about their im¬
mediate environment and are more depen¬
dent on products from afar. This trend has
gone so far as to disrupt even such intimate
biological behaviour as breast-feeding and
to make the mother dependent on multi¬
national milk powder that is imported from
other nations.
As the driving force of the current culture
is a system that wants to extract the max¬
imum from the environment for a few, the
growing world crisis can only be controlled
if the current culture can be destroyed and
replaced by a new world economic environ¬
ment that allows a multiplicity of cultures to
coexist in a spirit of equality. Everything else
would be a façade, part of an effort to
postpone the real solution. Some would
even call it a deliberate trick. A culture that
does not care for human beings cannot care
for the environment or vice versa.
26
The 60-odd non-governmental groups
which met recently in Nairobi to attend the
Symposium on Environment and the Future
were remarkably unanimous in their agree¬
ment, despite their diversity of backgrounds
and experiences, that the major intellectual
challenge before the world today Is to
delineate an alternative development pro¬
cess. A new vision must emerge and with it
a way to turn it into reality.
Within the intellectual cloud that exists,
some elements of the new culture can
already be discerned. It will clearly be:
participatory and resource-sharing, frugal
when compared to the affluent sections of
the world but with a higher average stan¬
dard of living for the poor majority;
respectful of the multiplicity of lifestyles in
the world;
more self-reliant and independent;
respectful of feminist concerns; more and
more evidence now shows that women suf¬
fer more from ill health and malnutrition and
care more for the restoration of en¬
vironmental integrity than their cash-hungry
men.
As we approach the end of the twentieth
century, the urgency for finding the alter¬
native development process will increase. If
the world cannot find a better way to share
its resources, the fight between the poor
and the rich will inevitably increase, both
between and within nations. The current
crisis of the Third World is merely a symp¬
tom of the crisis in the entire world.
Nearly seven decades ago, the wise old
man of India, Mahatma Gandhi, put the
entire population, resources and develop¬
ment question into one succinct and simple
equation. When asked what he wanted
India to look like after it became in¬
dependent he wanted it to be like
Britain, the Mahatma replied with a ques¬
tion of his own. If Britain had to exploit half
the world to be what it is today, how many
worlds would India have to exploit ? This is
a question that every developed and
developing nation has to ask today. There is
enough for everybody's need in this world
but not enough for everybody's greed.
H Anil Aga rwal
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
HUNGER, POPULATION, ENVIRONMENT
Environment
and
the global underclass
40,000 preventable child deaths each day
by Erik Eckholm
The United Nations Conference
on the Human Environment, held in
Stockholm in 1972, provided a focal
point for the gathering environmen¬
tal concerns of the 1960s; it gave
birth to the United Nations Environ¬
ment Programme (UNEP) to act as
a catalyst and as "the environmen¬
tal conscience of the UN system".
Ten years later, in Nairobi, from 10
to 18 May, the Governing Council of
UNEP held a meeting to com¬
memorate Stockholm and to take
stock of the achievements of a
decade.
THE convergence of ideas about
environment and Third World
development over the last
decade must be reckoned a historic ad¬
vance for both fields. In the past those
concerned about the preservation of
nature and those concerned about
economic progress have often been at
loggerheads. Recently, many on both
sides have begun to realize that they
need the insights of each other if the
goals of either are to be met.
The world conservation movement
has for the most part focused on the
need to protect endangered animals
and to establish parks and preserves.
But an animal cannot be saved apart
from its habitat, and natural areas can¬
not last as fortress islands in seas of
hungry people. Where large numbers
lack a means to make a decent living,
some are sure to invade national parks
to grow food and cut wood. Desperate¬
ly poor people cannot afford to worry
much about what they see as useless
tigers.
Instead of dwelling on the threat to
the environment posed by develop¬
ment, many conservationists now
recognize the need for development as
a prerequisite of successful conserva¬
tion. But not just any sort of pell-mell,
lopsided development; the key is
economic progress that is ecologically
sustainable and satisfies the essential
needs of the underclass. Analysis of
Third World conservation problems
ERIK P. ECKHOLM is a specialist on environ¬
ment and development issues who has served as
a consultant to United Nations agencies, as a
U. S. government official and as a Senior Resear¬
cher with WorldWatch Institute in Washington,
D. C. This article is adapted from his new book
Down to Earth: Environment and Human Needs,
published by W.W. Norton in New York and
Pluto Press in London. His previous books.
Losing Ground and The Picture of Health, have
appeared in ten languages.
leads inescapably to concern for social
justice. Broader sharing of the fruits of
development is important not only
because it is morally right, but also
because it is crucial to the protection of
natural systems.
The deterioration of natural systems
in poor countries is at once a symptom
and a cause of the extreme misery in
which hundreds of millions live. The
struggle to preserve global environmen¬
tal quality is unavoidably intertwined
with the struggle to improve the lot of
the global underclass the landless
rural residents, the urban slum
dwellers, and the tribal minorities who
are the poorest of the world's poor.
Roughly half this underclass lives in the
three South Asian countries of India,
Bangladesh, and Pakistan. Large
numbers live elsewhere in Asia,
especially Indonesia, and in sub¬
sanaran Africa, with the remainder
scattered among countries in the
Middle East, Latin America, and the
Caribbean.
Struggling week by week to survive,
caught in endless cycles of hunger, il¬
literacy, exploitation, and disease, the
absolute poor have little time to worry
about global environmental trends. Yet
in many ways they are more deeply af¬
fected by environmental quality than
are the affluent. Most of the rural poor
live directly off the soils, forests,
waters, and wildlife whose deteriora¬
tion has become the object of so much
international concern. Many are forced
by circumstances beyond their control
to destroy the very resources from
which they must scrape their living. In
the cities, the poor live in filth and are
often the prime victims of industry's
pollution, too.
Undernutrition is chronic among the
underclass. In the mid-1970s, accor¬
ding to United Nations estimates, more
than 400 million people one-tenth of
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
^humanity consumed less than the
"minimum critical diet" below which
health may be endangered. The ill ef¬
fects of undernourishment are often
nearly invisible. Outside of famine
zones and refugee camps, overt starva¬
tion is uncommon. But chronic under¬
nutrition can mean chronic health pro¬
blems, a higher chance of death from
disease at any age, heightened odds of
mortality for mothers during childbirth
and for their babies, and a reduced
capacity for work. Routine diseases
such as diarrhoea and measles are,
among the undernourished, routine
killers.
Most of the world's absolute poor
live in rural areas, and most of them are
either landless labourers or people who
lack secure access to enough farmland
to support themselves at a decent level.
Landless labourers, sharecroppers,
and marginal farmers together con¬
stitute the majority of rural residents in
In preserving 'useless'
species, are conservationists
barking up the wrong tree?
most countries of Asia and Latin
America, and they are rising in number
in Africa, where land inadequacy has
only recently begun to emerge as a ma¬
jor problem. These people, the
dispossessed of the earth, have
generally been bypassed by economic
development and in some cases have
been harmed by it.
Lacking land or jobs in traditional far¬
ming areas, peasant farmers clear and
plant lands that should never be farm¬
ed. They move into rain forests,
destroying diverse ecosystems in what
often turn out to be futile attempts at
sustainable farming. Sometimes within
sight of huge, under-utilized
agricultural estates in valley floors,
desperate farmers in South and Central
America plough up mountain slopes so
steep that the topsoil washes away
within a year or two.
In semi-arid zones of Africa and Asia,
land-hungry farmers plant in low-
rainfall zones, which turn into dust
bowls when the inevitable drought
comes. Meanwhile, herders are squeez¬
ed into ever more restricted areas and
the problem of overgrazing is inten¬
sified. The emerging inadequacy of the
land base in relation to population and
technology is often partly concealed by
a steady decline in the soil-preserving
fallow period.
The rural landless have their counter¬
parts in the slums and shantytowns of
Third World cities. With the old slums
overflowing, huge numbers of people
become squatters on vacant land or
buy illegally subdivided plots and build
their own dwellingsanything from
tarpaper shanties to sturdy and livable
structures. The most disadvantaged
We, the people, are like a saucepan; all thefood is cooked in the saucepan, it suffers the torments of
the fire, but when thefood is ready, it is told: you cannot come to the table, you will make the cloth
dirty.
Jacques Roumain
(1907-1944)
Preparing the family meal, India. Photo © Claude Sauvageot, Paris.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
people tend to wind up on dangerously
steep hillsides or in flood zones, where
natural hazards join overcrowding and
lack of sanitation to endanger health.
Because they live in illegal areas, squat¬
ters are seldom served by convenient
water connexions, let alone sewage-
disposal facilities or garbage collection.
In many cities they pay exorbitant rates
for water that is carted in by private
vendors, and thus end up paying more
per unit for this basic need than do the
rich. They are often victimized by
severe air pollution and water-borne
toxic chemicals the effluents of
others' affluence.
More than half the population of the
developing countries (excluding China)
Are the poor doomed to
destroy the environment that
sustains them?
lacks ready access to safe water sup¬
plies and waste disposal facilities. The
resultant poor sanitation combines with
undernutrition to take an awesome toll,
especially among the babies of the
underclass.
Altogether, according to the World
Health Organization, about seventeen
million infants and children under age
five died each year in the late 1970s. If
the excellent health conditions of Nor¬
thern Europe had prevailed throughout
the world, only two million such deaths
would have occurred. Hence fifteen
million deaths of babies and small
children more than forty thousand a
daycan be regarded as preventable.
All other global health problems pale
before this one. Yet because they are
so commonplace these forty thousand
daily scandals do not provoke the
global outrage they should.
Some planners and aid agencies
have at last begun to incorporate an
ecological perspective into develop¬
ment activities. But solving the in¬
terlocking crises of poverty and en¬
vironmental degradation depends as
much on politically contentious socio¬
economic reforms as on improved
planning.
More than anything else, the stone
wall of inopportunity facing the poorest
fifth of humankind ensures the continu¬
ing degradation of natural resources in
large parts of the world. In the absence
of national and international economic
reforms, efforts to protect wildlife and
forests, to manage watersheds and arid
lands, to clean up shantytowns and
waterways, cannot be fully successful.
Nor is population growth apt to slow
down quickly among people whose
children so frequently die. The
worldwide struggle to preserve a livable
environment must be part of the
broader struggle to create a more just
global society.
H Erik Eckholm
He who declares that he has the courage to withstand hunger has never experienced it.
The Book of Negro Wisdom
A canteen at Bihar, India. Photo © Claude Sauvageot, Paris.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
HUNGER, POPULATION, ENVIRONMENT
The aftermath
of the
population explosion
By the year 2000, a world population
40per cent higher than today
On every contented, happy man 's doorstep there should be someone with a
hammer in his hand, who would keep reminding the happy man by his
knocking that there are unhappy people in the world, and that, however
happy he may be sooner or later life will show him its talons and misfortune
will befall him, in the form ofsickness, poverty or loss, and no one will see
him or hear him, just as today he neither hears nor sees others.
Anton Chekhov
(1860-1904)
La Cena (1941), by the Cuban artist René Portocarrero. Photo
© Almasy, Paris.
by Rafael M. Salas
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
i.' . r.1 --VW; ¡f",
A/en make a city, not its walls or its ships.
Thucydides
(460-399 BC)
City crowds. Photomontage © Richard Napier, Paris.
THE largest and most complete
memory bank on the past, pre¬
sent and future of the world's
population stands on the East River in
New York. Here the United Nations
Population Division stores and analyses
information on population size, growth
and movement from nearly every coun¬
try in the world. Year by year its records
show the way we have come and the
RAFAEL M. SALAS, of the Philippines, is an
Under-Secretary-General of the United Nations
and Executive Director of the United Nations
Fund for Population Activities, which he has
headed since it became operational in 1969. A
graduate of the universities of the Philippines and
Harvard, he has served as a Minister and oc¬
cupied other high-level posts in the Philippine
Government.
way we are likely to go. Out of the
figures of the past is constructed a pic¬
ture of the possible future.
If conditions had remained as they
were in the 1950s the picture of the
future would have shown birth rates
stable and death rates falling, as they
had been for some years. In these con¬
ditions the population of the world
would have increased very rapidly,
reaching 7,500 million by the year 2000
(it was 2,500 million in 1950). By far the
greatest part of the increase would
have come in the less developed coun¬
tries of the world.
As these possibilities, and others
even more daunting, became more
widely known during the 1950s, con
cern grew and the idea of the "popula¬
tion explosion" was born. It is at least
partly to this concern that the United
Nations Fund for Population Activities
owes its existence.
Death rates continued to fall in the
1960s that is to say as chances of sur¬
vival improved and expectation of life
became longer under the impact of bet¬
ter health care and understanding of
how the most common killer diseases
could be controlled. But birth rates also
began to fall in the 1960s, even though
conditions in most countries were ap¬
parently unfavourable. The pace of
decline was slow at first, but became
faster and faster until in the mid-1970s
it was twice what it had been a decade
before. ]
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Source: WHO
^. By the end of the 1970s it was clear
that the gigantic numbers and
cancerous rates of growth which seem¬
ed likely only a few years before would
not after all afflict the earth. This year,
the UNFPA's State of World Popula¬
tion Report was able to say that the
population at the end of the century
would most likely be of the order of
6,100 million people 1,400 million, or
twenty per cent fewer than would have
been expected in projections based on
1950s data.
This is good news; but as the dust of
the population explosion settles, our
perception of the true position
becomes clearer. It now seems likely
that by the end of the century the earth
will be called upon to support a popula¬
tion forty per cent bigger than it is now.
This alone should renew a sense of
urgency in meeting the needs of this
and future additions to the world's
people.
Growth has not stopped, nor will it
stop finally until well into the century
after next, by which time there may be
10,500 million people on our planet. We
must find ways of accommodating the
needs of these vastly increased
numbers; and it should be remembered
what difficulties are found in meeting
the needs of even the present popu¬
lation of the world. Whatever the
capabilities of technology or the
theoretical carrying capacity of the
global ecosystem, the fact remains that
even today many millions of people are
denied the bare necessities of life. The
prospect of additional billions, ninety
per cent of them in the less developed
countries of the world, should reinforce
determination to supply their needs,
but also, in all humanity, to limit the
size of the addition.
There is much to learn from the ex¬
perience of the last two decades, dur¬
ing which world growth rates have
slowed from 1 .99 per cent in 1960-65 to
1.72 per cent in 1975-80.
First, during that time many govern¬
ments have turned away from an at¬
titude which declared the growth and
By the year 2000 there will be at least 150 million
disabled children under 15 years of age living in
developing countries.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
spatial distribution of a country's
population to be irrelevant to develop¬
ment planning. About eighty per cent
of the population of the developing
world now live under governments
which consider the national level of fer¬
tility to be too high and would like to
reduce it; 110 out of 126 governments
in developing countries consider the
distribution of their populations to be
unacceptable to a greater or lesser
degree.
Second, the recognition by govern¬
ments that population growth and
movement have definite, sometimes
deleterious, effects on a country's
economy and social structure and con¬
versely that patterns of development
affect rates of growth and movement
has given rise to policies designed to
counter both causes and effects. In the
process of developing and implemen¬
ting these responses, the nature of the
linkages between population, natural
resources, the environment and
development has become clearer. Ex¬
perience and research have both shown
that population and, for example,
health care, education, the status cf
women and social development
generally are in a circular relationship.
Reinforcing one may have a positive ef¬
fect on the others, or perhaps it may be
necessary to strengthen several factors
before another will respond.
The World Fertility Survey is one of
the best examples of carefully struc¬
tured research work showing the com¬
plex interrelationships between one
aspect of population and other
variables. The Survey demonstrates the
truth of several assumptions that fer¬
tility goes down as status in society
goes up, for example and refines
some others. Employment for women
and low fertility have generally been
found to be linked, but the World Fer¬
tility Survey showed that women who
had worked at some time had fewer
children than those who had never
worked, and that the type of occupa¬
tion is important. Agricultural work ap¬
parently has little effect on fertility com¬
pared with blue-collar employment,
while white-collar and professional
women have the smallest families.
Literacy and level of education affect
not only the number of children a
woman has but their chances of sur¬
vival. Children of illiterate women in ^
Urban and rural population
Population in millions
500 1000 1500 2000 2500 3000
Source : WHO
Net additions to World Population at 25 year intervals
1900-2100
Source : UNFPA
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Latin America, for example, have a risk
factor 3.5 times that of children whose
mothers have had ten or more years of
education. The probability of death bet¬
ween birth and the age of two declines
steadily as the mothers' level of educa¬
tion rises.
Research and experience in the 1970s
seem to show that the aim of reducing
both birth and death rates in developing
countries is best served by paying at¬
tention to the education and employ¬
ment of women, to access to health
and family planning services and to
changes in attitudes to family forma¬
tion.
The third important lesson to be
learnt from the experience of the 1960s
and 1970s is the need for effective
delivery of services. Reducing the
number of infant deaths requires the
Can the world adapt to an
aging population?
eradication or at least control of the im¬
portant killer diseases, which are mainly
contracted through polluted food and
water and poor sanitation. Medical ser¬
vices to treat disease may be of less im¬
portance than effective communication
about the importance of clean food and
water, the need for adequate sanita¬
tion, and the provision of each. This ap¬
plies to family planning as to any other
service; the level of awareness of con¬
traception, the World Fertility Survey
found, is considerably higher than the
level of practice. One reason is the lack
of services.
The fourth point is the size of the
allocation a country is willing to make
for population programmes. The pro¬
portion of national budgets devoted to
population has dramatically increased
as interest has grown. In Kenya, for ex¬
ample, government expenditure during
the period 1976-80 was about twelve
times the amount spent from 1971-75.
Lastly, international assistance for
population has doubled in real terms
since 1970 and forms perhaps a third of
the total resources spent on population
programmes in developing countries. It
is still, however, less than two per cent
of total international assistance.
Between them, these five points
cover the main developments in plann¬
ed approaches to population problems
and between them help to account for
the accelerating fertility decline which
has been seen over the past decade.
But global figures conceal wide
regional and national diversity. Most of
the decline in fertility is accounted for
by a handful of countries, mostly in
Asia, which contain between them
some two-thirds of the population of
the developing world. In many other
countries, notably in Africa, population
growth remains high and life expectan¬
cy low. For these countries the strain of
attempting to balance already scarce
resources against the needs of a rapidly
growing population is becoming con¬
siderable. In many of them the pro¬
blems are compounded by the difficulty
and cost of providing services to a scat¬
tered and diverse population when
even the basic medical, educational
and transport services are lacking.
For the future, the answer must be,
at least in part, more of the same. An
increase in resources devoted to
population, both internally and interna-
When living standards go up,
does fertility go down?
tionally, is essential if the momentum
created in the 1970s is to be maintain¬
ed. As programmes develop, they will
throw up more information on the
linkages between population and
development, showing the way to new
kinds of approach, but they will also
show up areas of ignorance or uncer¬
tainty where research is needed before
progress can be made. Above all we
will need better techniques for reaching
out to the community and gaining ac¬
ceptance and co-operation. One thing
which experience has taught us is that
CONTINUED PAGE 39
Source: WHO
Infant mortality
(per 1000 live births)
Developed
countries
Developing
countries
1975 22 109
2000 10 50
olour pages
DISARMAMENT
We should try to
I establish the Uni-
I versal Declaration
lof Human Rights
j and the human
! rights pacts as the
basis of a new
world morality. I
couple the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights with the human rights
pacts because the latter cover economic
and social rights, which I think must be
included among the human rights that
should be supported by governments.
This is important not only in order to
prevent the rights of the individualfrom
being violated but also from the point
of view of credibility. How can you ex¬
pect the children of today and tomor¬
row to believe in the concepts we try to
teach them if in practice they are being
violated? If a government organizes the
torture of political prisoners, for in¬
stance, can you expect youngsters to
respect that government, or to think
that torturing people themselves is a
thing not to be done?
Sean MacBride
Angola. Photo Mingam © SIPA-
Press, Paris.
EDUCATION
/ believe that the
main object of
education should be
to encourage the
young to question
and to doubt those
things which have
been taken for
granted. What is
important is inde¬
pendence of mind.
Benin. Photo ©
Claude
Sauvageot, Paris.
Bertrand Russell
(1872-1970)
HUNGER
In truth, our system
offood security re¬
mains based on
neyt year's crop.
Edouard Saouma
Peru. Photo
' Silvester ©
Rapho, Paris.
DEVELOPMENT
Man is the best
remedy for man.
Wolof proverb
China. Photo
Eve Arnold ©
Magnum, Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Wfc»'' JÊ
1
1
pp
* 1
te* ^
j ' «a
' Ji^^l
I ^MW^ 1
i^L ^^H
^^ V V
J
V^Ly v ^
i^^SSb
/ 41
L
1
En E
¿jj
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
¿fi
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
HUNGER, HEALTH, ENVIRONMENT
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 34
population programmes cannot be suc¬
cessfully run without the active par¬
ticipation of the people. The communi¬
ty can provide physical resources,
leadership and communication to sup¬
port the government programme.
In addition, new approaches will be
called for to meet problems as they
develop. What should our response be,
for example, to the staggering in¬
creases in urban population now in pro¬
gress and foreseen for the future?
Some possible answers were sug-
The aftermath
of the
population explosion
gested by the Conference on the Urban
Future held in Rome in 1980. The ques¬
tion of international as well as internal
migration will call for urgent attention
as people increasingly seek work far
from their homes. Also, as the propor¬
tion of elderly people in the population
increases far beyond what most
developing countries have been ac¬
customed to, social structures adapted
to their needs and abilities will be re¬
quired.
These questions and others like them
will occupy the attention of the interna¬
tional conference on population plann¬
ed for 1984. Ten years after the World
Population Conference in Bucharest, it
will be possible for the nations of the
world to sit together to assess their pro¬
gress and their problems and agree on a
common response. The story of their
success will be told by the figures in the
memory bank on the East River and
on the faces of millions of men and
women throughout the developing
world. Rafael M. Salas
Sleep, hungry people, may the gods offood watch over you,
And if words do not satisfy your hunger, may dreams assuage it.
Sleep on the bed of broken promises and the flow of words,
And may the shadowy handmaidens of reverie
Delight you with round loaves of bread shining like the moon.
Mohammed Al-Jawahiri
Lullaby of the Hungry
Corbeille de Pain (The Breadbasket, 1945) by Salvador Dali.
Photo Éditions Draeger © SPADEM 1982, Paris
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The nuclear threat, as manifest in the
deterrent theory, implies an ever more
determined search for a more effective
second strike capability, and the nor¬
mal defence-of-the-territory effort is
becoming more and more concerned
with the permanent preparation of a
country for a preventive war.
Marek Thee
Soldier. Photo United Nations, Nagata.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
DISARMAMENT,
DEVELOPMENT
THE report of the independent committee on dis¬
armament and security under the chairmanship
of Olof Palme, extracts of which are published
on page 44, spells out with terrifying precision the conse¬
quences of a possible nuclear war between two super¬
powers: 200 million dead, 60 million more wounded by
explosions, fire and radiation. The report concludes that
a generalized atomic war would plunge humanity into
chaos and perhaps mean the annihilation of all human
life.
Can such a war be envisaged today? The constantly
escalating race to overarmament seems to be leading in
this direction, for it is impossible to see how it can con¬
tinue indefinitely. It is often justified in terms of the
need to establish a "balance of deterrence", but perhaps
such a balance is a fiction and, since it is unattainable,
logic insists that the absurd, abortive arms race should
give way to the only rational alternative solution: de-
escalation ending in general and complete disarmament
(see the Unesco Courier, April 1979, "The Arms Race").
But though both the motivations and the goals of
overarmament may be irrational, does it not buttress the
economies of some countries? Are arms industries
necessary to soften the effects of crisis? This point of
view is both short-sighted and fallacious. Overarmament
means colossal waste, it misuses human resources, it kills
by condemning to famine millions of people in the Third
World. It exacerbates imbalances and makes crisis more
acute. But with political determination and a full
awareness of all that is at stake, today's vast technological
potential could be turned to good use and the arms in¬
dustry could be converted to peaceful ends without too
many problems (see the Unesco Courier, March 1982,
"Swords into Plowshares").
Such a project is no longer Utopian. How could it be
carried out? Unesco's role in this field is clearly set forth
in its Constitution which formulates the objective of "ad¬
vancing, through the educational and scientific and
cultural relations of the peoples of the world, the objec¬
tives of international peace and of the common welfare of
mankind". Unesco has pursued this goal unfailingly by
striving to create a favourable climate for disarmament in
world opinion and above all among young people (see
the Unesco Courier, September 1980, "Disarmament
Education").
Development through
Demilitarization
by Richard Falk
WORLD economic, political, and cultural life in general is
entering a period of sustained crisis. Dominating the
current scene is a ferocious arms race between the
superpowers and an incredibly rapid process of military moderniza¬
tion that is global in scope, taking in countries of the most varied
backgrounds. An increasing militarization of political life, as well as
a growing popular revulsion against the danger of nuclear war are
among the immediate results. This preoccupation with the military
picture, including concern with the recurrence of actual warfare
throughout the Third World, makes it difficult in the 1980s to place
much creative emphasis at the international level on the develop¬
ment process.
RICHARD A. FALK, U.S. educator, has been Albert G. Milbank Pro¬
fessor of International Law and Practice at the University of Princeton
since 1965. Among his many published works are This Endangered Planet
(1971), A Study of Future Worlds (1975) and (as co-author) International
Law and World Order (1980).
This difficulty is reinforced by the general circumstance of
economic recession that has existed for the past several years and
is likely to persist at least until the mid-1980s. The impact of reces¬
sion has been felt in the West and its repercussions have been felt
in the East, North and South, in the form of reduced economic
growth, and for almost every country some form of monetary
disturbance, generally some combination of indebtedness and in¬
flation. The most painful burdens of this prolonged recession are
felt by the poor, the weakest economies in the South, and the
underclasses in the North. Even the richest market economies of
the North, with the exception of Japan, have been enduring high
levels of unemployment, totalling as of 1982, an incredible ag¬
gregate figure of almost 30,000,000.
How long the international and intranational poor will acquiesce
in bearing the brunt of cyclical adjustment costs is highly
uncertain.
What is not in doubt, however, is the impact of this economic^
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Peace is not merely the absence of war, it is a virtue which is rooted in the strength of the soul, for obe¬
dience is the constant desire to do what must be done according to the common law of the City. A City, it
must be repeated, in which peace reigns solely through the inertia of its citizens, led like aflock ofsheep and
accustomed only to servitude, should be called a wilderness rather than a City.
Spinoza
(1632-1677)
Photomontage Tsunehisa Kimura © Pacific Press Service, Tokyo. ANA, Paris
crunch on the development picture. The earlier liberal impulse to
negotiate co-ordinated global economic reforms that shift
resources and trade advantages from North to South has definitely
been blunted, mainly by domestic pressures toward selfishness
that flow from the overall recession, and partly from the related
disillusionment that is affecting foreign economic assistance and
the role of such international financial institutions as the World
Bank and the International Monetary Fund.
It is important to realize fully that this disillusionment generally
affects both donor countries of the North and recipient countries
of the South. Many donor countries, especially those under con¬
servative leadership, are becoming unconvinced that it is worth
"investing" their resources in the elimination of poverty or the pro¬
motion of international co-operation, alleging that corruption
among élites, unrestrained population growth, and political tur¬
bulence and radicalism in recipient countries nullifies any expected
benefits of capital transfer. The recipient governments, in con¬
trast, seem increasingly disturbed by the extent and character of
interference in their economic and political life that is demanded by
international financial institutions as part of the cost of receiving
either public or private capital assistance, and would generally
prefer trade concessions, including tariff relief, to further
dependency-creating infusions of capital.
In many cases, the debt trap facing Third World governments is
producing new forms of post-colonial dependency that interfere
with the full exercise of sovereign rights by precluding
autonomous modes of development at the national level. In addi¬
tion, externally conceived conditions of fiscal soundness are given
priority over the social and political goals of development, in¬
cluding the elemental well-being of the people. One major effect of
this externally imposed "austerity" is that wages and labour unions
are kept artificially repressed by the apparatus of State power,
which often requires interference with human rights and reliance
on organized terror to maintain order.
Furthermore, the modernizing side of the development process
has imposed on most Third World governments a heavy import
burden. To pay for these import costs, without producing even
worse situations of indebtedness and inflation, has led many Third
World governments to emphasize export-led growth.
This emphasis has been encouraged by the main centres of in-
42
ternational influence, including banks and multinational corpora¬
tions. But export-led growth has meant giving preferential treat¬
ment to investment and development projects in areas of produc¬
tion where export demand is strongest. In agriculture such
priorities have meant a push to replace traditional agriculture with
cash crops that bring a favourable price on the world market.
Often the local population suffers either by a reduction of domestic
food supplies or by the consolidation of land holdings in large-
scale agrobusiness ventures.
In industry, the adverse effects of export-led growth include an
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
additional incentive to keep wages repressed so as to enable lower
prices and higher profits for output and a receptivity to polluting
technologies as a means of attracting forms of foreign investment
that migrate overseas to escape burdensome regulation at home.
The net effects are to distort the development process in relation
to the satisfaction of basic human needs (that is, the elimination of
poverty) the attainment of rising living standards for the overall
population, and to make the domestic economy extremely
vulnerable to shifts in the pattern of international demand.
A further complicating factor in assessing the current develop¬
ment picture has been the unevenness of economic growth in the
Third World. The most obvious division has been between the oil-
surplus and oil-deficit countries, creating vastly different economic
circumstances from country to country. It should be noticed, of
course, that the apparently obvious advantage of being endowed
with abundant oil resources for export can work out as a mixed
blessing. The enormous capital placed at the disposal of the
government and the investing élite can induce mindless and
unstable modernization, including a top-heavy military establish¬
ment that is visibly dependent on foreign advisers and a pattern of
development that concentrates its material rewards on small sec¬
tors of the population.
Rapid growth may also induce disruptive patterns of rural-urban
migration that strain the facilities of the main cities while under¬
mining the self-sufficiency of the countryside. Inflation, pollution,
housing shortages, urban congestion, and the breakdown of
Where are the real
development decisions taken?
In a nuclear world, will the
poet's lamp ofclay sufficefor
his needs? Yes, ifman yet has
remembrance of clay. It is
enough for the poet to be the
conscience of his time.
Saint-John Perse
(1887-1975)
"The Poet Li Po Reciting a
Poem", by Leang Kai
(c.1140-c.1210). Executed in
less than 15 brushstrokes,
the work is typical of Zen
Buddhist art. Photo ©
Roger Viollet, Paris. Na¬
tional Museum of Japan,
Tokyo.
public transportation can make the life of ordinary people harder
while the country as a whole is experiencing high growth and un¬
precedented prosperity. Perhaps even worse, certain types of
rapid modernization cause cultural traumas of a severe sort,
displacing and threatening traditional values.
There are other basic forms of unevenness that produce greater
diversity of outlook on development issues. A few Third World
countries have managed to sustain economic growth over a suffi¬
cient period to be in a class by themselves, the so-called "new in-
dustrial countries". These "new Japans" are sufficiently modern
to make it no longer accurate, indeed, if it ever was, to think of the
Third World as a grouping of non-Western states that are generally
all at low levels of industrialization. Also, of course, there are im¬
portant distinctions between the developmental outlook of coun¬
tries integrated into the world capitalist economy and those largely
socialist societies that are neither havens for investment and
credit, nor participants in any major way in international trade. At
the same time, the uneven experience and capability of First World
economies in coping with the recession reflects a sharpening of
competition even among close allies, giving vent to protectionist
tendencies that threaten economic warfare that could be very
damaging to most countries in the Third World.
In short, there is no longer a consensus on development in either
North or South. Furthermore, the intensity of geopolitical rivalries
and the anguish of slow economic growth for most societies, has
moved the North-South dialogue to the margins of international
concern. The OPEC countries could still mount pressures, if so in¬
clined, but their interests seem generally so closely linked to the
main oil-importers and to anxieties about radical domestic
challenges, that their support for international economic reforms is
increasingly low-profile. .
Whether there is an enforcement authority or not, whether law is
statutory or not, peace will still only be secured if the International
Law is based on certain fundamental principles. Law which of¬
fends against basic human rights does not fulfil thepurpose of law
because it does not secure man's life in society.
Julius K. Nyerere
/...VA \\ví
>vV*r lv -4..É.
Wi
South African mine compounds enclosed by barbed wire
fences. Photo Abisag Tüllmann © International Defence
and Aid Fund for Southern Africa, London.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Such a global setting is obviously characterized by a growing
pluralism. Each government calculates its gains and benefits and
emphasizes sovereign rights. There is less confidence that interna¬
tional reforms are either feasible or important. The general neglect
of the Brandt Commission's generally enlightened recommenda¬
tions, the inconclusive and disappointing provisional outcome of
the law of the sea negotiations, the desultory spirit of the Cancun
Conference, and the heightening of East-West tensions among the
superpowers are all signs pointing in the same direction. The North
feels no pressures because the South fails to exert leverage, and is,
in any event, more ambivalent about what it has to gain.
All in all, the development picture has few bright spots. Growth
with equity requires an efficient national mobilization of capital and
a fairly large degree of autonomy in relation to the world economy.
International institutions can play supportive roles, offering selec¬
tive help by extending credits or loans. Yet, in essence, the self-
help character of the world political order, with its dynamic of
militarization, and the hierarchical character of the world economic
order, with its long phase of stagnancy, creates very little basis for
optimism. Instead, slow growth without equity is the near-term
prospect for the majority of peoples and countries of Asia, Africa,
and Latin America.
There are two positive paths open to restore hope in the
development process. First, popular movements might achieve
real control over their development choices, provided they can
prevail over the coalition of foreign and domestic élites that main¬
tain structures of privilege and exploitation. To prevail usually
Do cash crops grown for
export prevent poor countries
from feeding their poor?
means a struggle for democracy and human rights that amounts to
a national revolution. Secondly, significant political successes for
the grassroots, citizens anti-nuclear movement now surging in the
advanced industrial countries and beginning to challenge establish¬
ed leadership and economic priorities, and the demilitarization of
The consequences
of nuclear war
WHEN a nuclear weapon explodes
in thex atmosphere, the first
noticeable effect is a blinding
flash of intense white light strong enough
to blind observers many kilometres away.
The light does not kill, but the heat that
comes with it does. Both light and heat are
emitted by thefireball caused by the explo¬
sion, a mass of air containing the residues
of the weapon, heated to the order of 10
million degrees centigrade. Any un¬
protected person within two kilometres of
the fireball will be killed by the heat alone.
With a weapon of low yield, say 10 to 20
kilotons, roughly the size of the bombs
dropped on the Japanese cities, second-
degree burns will be suffered asfar as three
kilometres from the explosion.
Within seconds, the light and heat are
followed by a blast wave. It arrives like a
thunderclap, pursued by hurricane-force
winds strong enough to uproot telephone
poles and trees, overturn trucks, and sweep
human beings along at a tremendous speed.
The compression ofairpressure brought on
by the wind and the blast wave itself will
crush buildings, killing nearly everyone in¬
side, and loosen bricks and paving stones
which will hurtle in all directions, knocking
over everything in theirpath. Anyone in the
open or in ordinary buildings within 1.5
kilometres of the blast will have virtually no
chance of surviving.
As thefireball rises, it cools and becomes
a cloud, hovering high off the ground.
Beneath it, a column of dust and smoke is
sucked up from below. Looking like an
enormous mushroom, six kilometres high
and four across, the cloud is a mass of
radioactive atoms, some of which are lethal
enough to kill anyone who had managed to
survive the heat and blast effects.
If the explosion occurs close to the
ground, the immediate effects will be
Text © copyright. Reproduction prohibited.
greater, as thousands of tons ofradioactive
soil are sucked into the air in deadly con¬
centrations and deposited over a wide area.
Although its deadliness dissipates rapidly,
harmful radio-active materials from the
blast can be carried thousands of miles and
not reach the ground for weeks. Over the
decades to follow, the risk of cancer and,
possibly, genetic defects will be great.
Neither the unborn nor the unconceived
can escape the effects of nuclear war.
These are only the direct effects of a
nuclear explosion; secondary destruction
will be ubiquitous and intense. Fires will be
the worst hazard, caused both by the heat
of the explosion and by falling debris,
broken gas mains, rupturedfuel tanks, and
the like. Under certain circumstances, the
fires triggered by the blast will coalesce, .
forming a storm ofheat andflame that will
ravage huge areas and be virtually impos¬
sible to extinguish until there are no more
materials to feed on.
Other secondary effects will also be
devastating. The destruction of water
mains and sewers will result in the spread of
infectious diseases in epidemicproportions.
Communications and other electronic
systems will be disrupted severely by the
electromagnetic pulse emitted by the blast.
The damage from blown transformers and
overloaded computing and switching cir¬
cuits will be extensive and difficult to
repair. As a result, the allocation of
emergency equipment, even the identifica¬
tion of the location of injuries and damage,
will be difficult. Andfinally, the deaths of
doctors and other medical personnel, and
the destruction of health care facilities and
other municipal services, will mean that
even minor injuries and common diseases
will result in many more deaths than norm¬
ally would be expected.
The exact consequences of an exchange
ofnuclear weapons would depend on many
factors. Among the most important would
be the weather; winter would be a par¬
ticularly cruel time for those few who
managed to survive. But the overriding in¬
fluence would be the number of bombs
used and the extent of the attacks. A na¬
tion's ability to contain the effects of a
single explosion would depend greatly on
whether or not the central government
could shift people, water, food, and
medical supplies from other regions. If the
war were widespread, its effects could well
be synergistic; that is, the cumulative
results of burns, blast injuries, radiation
disease, and secondary consequences such
as the spread of infectious diseases could be
far greater than the sum of their individual
effects.
At some point, a nuclear exchange could
bring urban civilization to an end. It is dif¬
ficult to imagine the continuance ofsocial
discipline in theface ofthe devastation that
would accompany a war involving hun¬
dreds, much less thousands, of nuclear ex¬
plosions. Wouldpeople be willing to abide
by the authority of a government that had
just led its country to incredible disaster? If
not, the basic services upon which modern
society dependssuch as protection from .
criminal elements, the banking and
monetary system, the generation and
distribution of electric power, the distribu¬
tion of water and food to urban
areas could well come to a halt. Society
could regress to autonomous bands ofpeo¬
ple living largely in the rural areas that had
been spared the worst radiation, each sur¬
viving primitively on its own wits and
resources.
Jonathan Schell has put it well, in his re¬
cent book The Fate of the Earth:
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
internal and international political life could free resources and
talent for a renewed emphasis on development and the elimination
of mass poverty.
The reversal of the nuclear arms race is unlikely to occur without
a wider assault upon war and militarism, which in turn, will en¬
courage emphasis on the causes of war, including economic
distress and disparities within and among states, as well as on in¬
stitutional substitutes for war (peacekeeping, dispute-settlement
under the auspices of the United Nations, regional organizations).
Demilitarization implies new conceptions of security, especially
a substitution of security for the people in place of security for the
State. Such an altered context for security would create a new
progressive emphasis on world development policy and processes,
as well as a devaluing of armaments. Security will then be
understood more in terms of a governing process supported by the
citizenry than by the size and quality of the military establishment.
The fate of development, then, is tied closely to prospects for
demilitarization. In the interim, a particular country will do well to
free itself, to the extent possible, from crippling structures of
dependency. A national governing process is not truly indepen¬
dent if it is subject to policies set by distant centres of decision,
whether these be foreign capitals, multinational corporate head¬
quarters, or the guidelines of international financial institutions.
Demilitarization, self-determination, human rights, and develop¬
ment are increasingly part of a seamless web of progressive na¬
tional aspiration.
Richard Falk
/ Deganawidah
And the chiefs of the Five Nations
of the Great Peace
Weshall uproot the tallest pine
Into the cavity thereby made
We shall cast all weapons of war
Into the depths of the earth
Into the deep underneath...
We shall cast all weapons of war
We shall bury them from sight forever...
Then we shall plant again the tree...
Thus shall the Great Peace be established
The Tree of the Great Peace
Iroquois poem
Canadian Iroquois Indian of the
"Sang" tribe. Photo © Boyer-Viollet,
Paris.
[Although nuclear strategists] speak of a
period of "recovery" after a limited attack,
the likelier prospect is a long-term radical
deterioration in the conditions of life... To
restore [these] essentials of life takes time;
but there would be no time. Hunger, ill¬
ness, and possibly cold would press in on
the dazed, bewildered, disorganized, in¬
jured remnant of the population on the
very day of the attack. They would have to
start foraging immediately for their next
meal. Sitting among the debris of the Space
Age, they would find that the pieces of a
shattered modern economy around them...
were mismatched to their elemental needs.
Looking into the future, considering the
potential long-term effects ofmany nuclear
explosions on the human gene pool and the
incidence of cancer, to say nothing of its
likely effects on the ozone layer and result¬
ant destruction ofanimal andplant life and
eventual climatic changes, human life itself
could be in jeopardy. Thus, humanity
would face the ultimate riskits own ex¬
tinction. Within five years of the nuclear
explosion in Hiroshima two hundred thou¬
sand people had died from the effects of
the bomb. Within a similarperiod of time,
fatalities attributable to the nuclear blast in
Nagasaki, where the hilly topography of
the city tended to limit its effects, rose to
140,000. Even today, the death toll is still
rising in both cities, albeit slowly, as such
long-term effects as an increasing cancer
rate continue to manifest themselves.
Every year, the descendants ofthose who
died at Hiroshima light lanterns, each one
inscribed with the names of a deadfamily.
They push the lights off into the river that
runs through the city. For miles, the whole
river appears to be one mass offlame.
And what of the survivors? In De¬
cember 1981, the Commission visited
Hiroshima and spoke with survivors of the
atomic bomb. Consider the testimony of
Mr Yoshiaki Fukahori, a survivor of the
Nagasaki bomb:
Some people say that the survivors are
more fortunate than those who died, but is
that really so? Those of us who have surviv¬
ed these thirty-six years having to fight to
find food, to find clothes, to find a
livelihood... I rather think that we are suf¬
fering from a heavier cross... Because I was
young when I was exposed to radiation, I
have a tremendous uncertainty about the
future of my health. My wife is also a vic¬
tim and is suffering from disease... As
parents we are uncertain about the future
of our children, the second generation vic¬
tims... Would my children be able to father
and mother healthy children? Would the
third generation of my family survive?
Projecting the consequences ofa nuclear
explosion for a modern urban area on the
basis of the bombs exploded over Japanese
cities in 1945 is tricky. Nuclear weapons
have changed tremendously. The bombs
used against Japan are relatively small by
current standards, and the distribution of
the energy released by the explosions
among light, heat, blast, and radioactive
emissions is likely to be different in modern
bombs. The characteristics of cities also
have changed. The Japanese cities of the
1940s, constructed largely of wood, pro¬
bably suffered much more from fire than
would modern cities. On the other hand,
the Japanese cities had relatively small
populations by contemporary standards,
and thus suffered fewer casualties than
might occur today.
Still, fairly reliable estimates can and
have been made. The US Office of
Technology Assessment, for one, has
analysed several hypothetical examples of
single nuclear bombs dropped on modern
cities. Consider, for example, the effects of
a one-megaton weapon, the equivalent of
one million tons of conventional ex¬
plosives, roughly the size of the warhead of
a US Minuteman II or Soviet SS-11 ICBM,
on the cities ofDetroit and Leningrad, each
with populations of about four million.
If the weapon exploded in the air over
Detroit at night, without warning, approx¬
imately 470,000 people would be killed,
and another 630,000 injured. If the same
weapon were exploded during the daytime,
when the downtown part of the city was
crowded with commuters, an additional
130,000 would die. A one-megaton weapon
exploded over Leningrad would be even
more devastating, as thepopulation ofthat ^
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
/ have a dream that one day men will rise up and come to see that they are made to live together as brothers. Istill have a dream this morning
that one day every Negro in this country, every colouredperson in the world, will bejudged on the basis of the content ofhis character rather
than the colour ofhis skin, and every man will respect the dignity and worth ofhuman personality... I still have a dream today that one day
justice will roll down like water, and righteousness like a mighty stream. Istill have a dream today that in all ofour state houses and city halls
men will be elected to go there who will do justly and love mercy and walk humbly with their God. Istill have a dream today that one day war
will come to an end, that men will beat their swords into ploughshares and their spears into pruning hooks, that nations will no longer rise up
against nations, neither will they study war any more.
Martin Luther King
(1929-1968)
Civil rights march in the United States. Martin Luther King fifth from right. Photo Matt Herron © Rapho, Paris.
^ city is less suburban and more closely pack¬
ed. Under the same night-time conditions
specified for the Detroit estimate, 890,000
residents ofLeningrad would be killed, and
another 1,260,000 injured. More than one
half the city's totalpopulation would be the
victims of a single nuclear explosion.
Large warheads like the onejust describ¬
ed, however, are going out offashion. The
nuclear powers have been replacing their
existing weapons with yields in the megaton
range with greater numbers of weapons
with smaller explosive yields. These smaller
weapons are more efficient. Several
kiloton-range weapons can do greater
damage, even though their total yield may
be less than a single-megaton weapon. For
example, the detonation of ten 40-kiloton
weapons over Leningrad, in aggregate only
40 per cent the yield of a single one-
megaton weapon, would likely result in
130,000 additional fatalities.
The physical devastation in either city
would be incredible. Houses would be
demolished or made uninhabitable in an
area ofmore than 300 square kilometres. If
the bomb were exploded on the surface, an
area extending well beyond either city's
municipal boundaries (more than 1,000
square kilometres) would be contaminated
by radiation. Rescue workers and medical
personnel could enter this zone to help the
injured only at the peril of their own lives.
Radiation dangers aside, rescue work
would be extraordinarily difficult. Fires
would rage, water mains would flood,
power lines would be down, bridges,
freeways, and elevated railroads would
have collapsed. Once proud cities would be
reduced to debris.
The effects of a nuclear explosion on the
medical treatment system would be par
ticularly devastating. The Commission met
separately with Drs. Howard Hiatt and
Eugene Chazov, US and Soviet leaders,
respectively, of an international movement
of physicians concerned about the danger
of nuclear war. Their testimony makes
clear that it would be impossible to provide
modern medical assistance, even basic care,
to the victims of a nuclear attack.
John Hersey recorded the effects of the
1945 explosion on the Hiroshima health
care system:
Of 150 doctors in the city, 65 were
already dead and most of the rest were
wounded; of 1,780 nurses, 1,654 were dead
How would nuclear war affect
the earth's climate?
or too badly hurt to work. In .the biggest
hospital, that of the Red Cross, only 6 doc¬
tors out of 30 were able to function, and
only 10 nurses out of more than 200.
Yet numbers and statistical estimates
cannot begin to convey the horror of
nuclear war, nor the grisly consequences of
the destruction of the medical system. Con¬
sider the testimony before the Commission
of Dr. Tatsuichiro Akizuki, a physician
associated with the St. Franciscan Hospital
in Nagasaki:
Our hospital was at a point 1.5
kilometres from hypocentre, therefore the
patients and we suffered from only minor
injuries. But the building was burned down
several hours later. From the burning city,
grotesque looking naked people came in
droves and they moaned in agony and pain.
It took time for me to realize that they were
human beings suffering from severe burns
and bruises... All the major hospitals were
burned down or collapsed, and most of the
victims died without receiving any treat¬
ment. Several hundred people came to me.
They were turning black and purple,
vomiting blood and passing black stools
before they died. These were the symptoms
of acute radiation illness... There was a big
hospital thirty kilometres away, but there
was no means to go there. Tens of
thousands of people died without receiving
any treatment... Patients lay in holes dug in
the ground, and people died one after
another because of radiation illness... I felt
helpless as a doctor. I could not give any
treatment to the survivors... What would
happen if a nuclear war should occur now?
Even if you have doctors, even if you have
medicines, human beings are helpless. No
matter how much medicine has improved,
medicine is helpless in the face of atomic
war. It was a hell, an inferno.
// is clear that the number ofpeople who
might ultimately survive a nuclear attack,
to say nothing of the physical recovery of
the devastated area, would be crucially
dependent upon help from the outside. But
what if the attack were not an isolated one
against a single city? What if tens, or hun¬
dreds of major metropolitan areas were
devastated by nuclear weapons? Ifthis hap¬
pened the chances for rebuilding anything
resembling our present society would be
slim.
The chaos that would accompany such
an attack is almost inconceivable. Even if
only a handful of cities were struck initial¬
ly, it would cause an overwhelming panic.
Every urban dweller would assume that his
city would be the next target, turmoil
would come as people fled to the coun-
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
tryside. In some regions, like the American
West, many refugees could be accom¬
modated. In areas like the American Nor¬
theast, however, or most parts of the Soviet
Union, during winter, the evacuations of
cities would have terrible consequences.
Winds would spread the fall-out over crop
lands and river basins. What would be safe
to eat, or to drink? In some regions the ur¬
ban evacuees would be met by a hostile
rural population. Even the central political
authorities, to the extent that they survived,
would be uncertain about the status or well-
being of other parts of the country.
The reports from Hiroshima and
Nagasaki reveal that the instinctive reaction
of many of the victims was to protect
themselves by leaving the bombed areas as
quickly as possible. Children abandoned
parents, husbands left wives. Only one
bond remained intact mothers would not
be parted from their children. Undoubted-,
ly, amid this disturbance and upheaval,
some would find unknown sources of
Could mankind survive a
nuclear war?
strength and character. But would this be
enough to resist the general chaos, to
counter the terror of those whose lives and
minds had been torn asunder, first by the
explosions themselves, and later by the
after-effects of illness, disfigurement, in¬
security, and the destruction of family,
home, and everything familiar?
There is no satisfactory way to answer
this question. But official US estimates of
American fatalities in the event of a large-
scale nuclear attack, assuming no effective
measures of civil defence, range from 105
to 165 million. Comparable estimates of
Soviet fatalities range between 50 and 100
million. In both cases, it can be assumed
that virtually the entire economic in¬
frastructure would have been destroyed.
Under such conditions, those who op¬
timistically predict a return to ordinary life
within one generation are naïve. More
realistic is the conclusion by the US Office
of Technology Assessment that a nuclear
attack involving thousands of warheads,
"would place in question whether the
United States (or the Soviet Union) would
ever recover its position as an organized,
workable, and powerful country".
A meeting of distinguished doctors from
East and West was more pessimistic. They
concluded that an all-out nuclear exchange
between the United States and the Soviet
Union would immediately kill some 200
million men, women, and children. Sbcty
million more would be injured, of whom 30
million would suffer from radiation
sickness, 20 million would experience
trauma and burns, and another 10 million
would be affected by all three afflictions.
At the same time, 80 per cent of the doc¬
tors would have been killed and a similar
percentage of hospital beds destroyed.
Stores of blood plasma, morphine, anti¬
biotics, and intravenous fluids also would
have been destroyed. The report concluded:
The fabric of society would disintegrate
and the medical care system, deprived of
the facilities developed over the years,
would revert to the level of earlier cen¬
turies. The surviving walking wounded,
physicians and laymen alike, could only
provide what mutual comfort the remnants
of their individual humanity would permit.
The earth will be seared, the skies heavy
with lethal concentrations of radioactive
particles, and no response to medical needs
could be expected from medicine.
Not only would the US and USSR suffer.
For example, climatic changes would be
likely. The vast amount of polluting dust
drawn into the atmosphere would cool the
air by as much as one degree centigrade. A
large proportion of the world's wheat
stocks are kept at high latitudes. If these
stocks were destroyed and the American,
Canadian and Russian farmlands con¬
taminated, many countries would suffer
famine on a wide scale.
More than this, the supply ofagricultural
machinery, pesticides, and fertilizers that
now are exported by the industrialized
countries would cease. The fruits of
agricultural research would no longer be
available. For many Third World coun¬
tries, crop yields would fall dramatically,
turning even those countries that are
presently self-sufficient into nations with a
potential for famine.
The world in the 1980s is far more com¬
plex than it was even a generation ago.
Trade has grown rapidly, interdependence
is intimate and ubiquitous. Without the
ability to sell oil and other raw materials,
textiles and machinery, without being able
to import trucks, tractors, tools, fuel, and
pharmaceuticals, industry and agriculture
in the developing nations would grind to a
halt. In many areas, the developing world is
like Europe a generation ago, with large ur¬
ban populations and complex industrial
needs. Without trade it would sink.
Without the fabric of international finan¬
cial exchange, all nations, both rich and
poor, developed and developing, would
shrink to subsistence.
In a world undergoing such fast,
tumultuous and all-embracing destruction
it would be difficult for any society to
avoid its consequences. One cannot guess
at the degree ofsocial and political disrup¬
tion, and the breakdown of communica¬
tions would only add to rumour, feeding
the seeds of fear, breeding despair and
changing human life in a way and at a
speed that is almost unimaginable.
No past war can help us understand the
impact of a nuclear war. In the Second
World War, despite the astronomical
death-toll and appalling barbarism, there
was no massive breakdown of society or
morale. Air raids on cities and industries
rarely caused damage and disruption that
could not be bypassed in a few days. In¬
dividuals suffered, ofcourse, but for many
"life laughed and moved on unsubdued".
An all-out nuclear war would create a
degree of chaos and confusion for which
humanity is totally unprepared, and for
which it can never prepare. It could mean
the end of life itself.
This article has been extracted from "The Conse¬
quences of War", chapter 3 of The Report of the In¬
dependent Commission on Disarmament and Security
Issues under the Chairmanship of Olof Palme. The
members of the Commission were: Chairman: Olof
Palme (Sweden); Giorgi Arbatov (USSR!; Egon Bahr
(Federal Republic of Germany!; Gro Harlem Brundt/and
(Norway); Josef Cyrankiewicz (Poland); Jean-Marie
Dai/let (France); Robert A. D. Ford (Canada); Alfonso
Garcia-Robles (Mexico); Haruki Mori (Japan); C. B.
Muthamma (India); Olusegun Obasan/o (Nigeria); David
Owen (United Kingdom/; Shridath Ramphal (Guyana);
Salim Salim (Tanzania); Soedjatmoko (Indonesia);
Joop den Uyl (Netherlands); Cyrus Vance (USA). The
Report has been published, in English, under the title
Common Security: A Programme for Disarmament.
Text copyright © ICDSI, publishers Pan Books, Ltd.,
London.
O lord! War is evil and barbaric. War,
I Abhorred by mothers, fills men's hearts with fury.
I While war holds sway, who will sow the seed?
Who will harvest the ears of corn that June has ripened to gold?
Antonio Machado
(1875-1939)
3èr: ' " £S
Bitter harvest.
France.
Drawing © André Paris, Fontenouille,
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
PÖBliMiBOTlffirW
èêvWëft fM itâHô$ ft i\
11 HI1M Mil Mil/ h (l!|i|!ll| í 1 1 lt 1 II
ilMitKîliMil
fí» ft^ttâkât tiUé fc ft ii
Ht |j<MLig
1 | Il P1
*T* *- v *- s .r*
'I II
HP,
il» |'(-'/llt),1 r |V& tabú fc ft *\
Man IS Other men. Bantu proverb.
éiJKltô) r i& li^4 fr Ift f.
MiKIliJI JILLJL. M
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
MEN have always invoked the ideals of justice,
equality, and liberty when fighting against op¬
pression and discrimination, and prophets and
spiritual leaders of religions and philosophies have
preached the universal brotherhood of man. Gradually,
progressive societies incorporated into their constitu¬
tions, their legal systems and their political and social in¬
stitutions guarantees which went at least some way to
upholding certain rights. However, in the 20th century
this edifice of rights was threatened with destruction by
the Fascist powers. After the Second World War, in the
aftermath of a tragedy which had claimed so many vic¬
tims, the General Assembly of the United Nations pro¬
claimed on 10 December 1948 the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights as "a common standard of achievement
for all peoples and all nations".
The Declaration, a short text of 30 articles, is partly in¬
spired by earlier models such as the English and
American Bills of Rights, the American Declaration of
Independence, and the French Declaration of the Rights
of Man and the Citizen of 1789. It proclaims, notably, that
all human beings are born free and equal in dignity and
rights; that everyone has the right to life; that no one
shall be held in slavery nor subjected to torture; that all
are equal before the law and are entitled to its protection;
that everyone has the right to freedom of thought, con¬
science, religion, opinion, peaceful assembly and associ¬
ation; everyone has the right to work, to just and
favourable conditions of work, to social security; the
right to form and join trade unions; the right to rest and
leisure, to holidays with pay, to an adequate standard of
living, to medical care, to education; motherhood and
childhood are entitled to special care and assistance; that
everyone has duties to the community, etc.
The Universal Declaration of Human Rights has been
criticized on the grounds that it is too general. However
in 1966 the United Nations adopted two international
covenants, the International Covenant on Economic,
Social and Cultural Rights and the International Cove¬
nant on Civil and Political Rights. These have been
ratified by over 60 countries and came into effect in 1976.
Among the rights formulated by these texts are the
following: that all peoples have the right of self-
determination, to freely dispose of their natural wealth
and resources, to freely determine their political status
and freely pursue their economic, social and cultural
development; they also stress the equality of men's and
women's rights, the right to strike, provided that it is ex¬
ercised in conformity with the laws of the particular
country, the right to participate in cultural life, to enjoy
the benefits of scientific progress, etc.
But human rights must always come to terms with the
evolution of human societies. Today we are witnessing
the emergence of what the Director-General of Unesco
has termed "the third generation of human rights".
These include the right to development, to a healthy and
ecologically balanced environment, to peace, to the en¬
joyment of the common heritage of mankind. These
"rights of solidarity" can only be achieved by a common
effort from all individuals, States and other public and
private institutions.
A Third World view
of Human Rights
by Radhika Coomaraswamy
IN many ways, the human rights move¬
ment has reached a crossroads. The
success of its endeavours is closely
related to its ability to meet the challenge
posed by developments in the Third World.
Its growth and transformation will greatly
depend on its capacity to capture the im¬
agination of young people in these societies.
The texture and fabric of its development
will be affected by the manner in which it
handles the sensitive issue of women's rights
in diverse cultural settings.
RADHIKA COOMARASWAMY is a Sri Lankan
lawyer who has specialized in human rights
research and education.
To a great extent, the Third World has
not played a creative part in the formulation
and implementation of human rights.
Though human rights embody many tenets
found in all the world's cultures, the
theoretical origin of the human rights
movement are distinctively Western. The
pillar concepts of the movement liberty,
equality, material welfare and self-
determination are formulated in the man¬
ner envisioned by the modern movements of
nationalism, liberalism and socialism. These
movements originated in the West but have
influenced political values throughout the
world.
These historical origins alone have made
many cultural nationalists advocate the re
jection of the human rights movement as a
universal norm. Violations of human rights
are justified in terms of the illegitimacy of
certain human rights values in the Third
World context. This remains a major crisis
for the human rights movement in the latter
half of the twentieth century.
What approach should be adopted to
reconcile the tension between the inherited
tradition of human rights and major
developments in the non-Western world? It
is inevitable that any such reappraisal must
begin with a view of history as a collective
experience, a synthetic process of human
rights learning and growth. At present there
is a need for Third World insights into
human rights protection, but the process
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
^ must be a creative one and not a denial of
the very concept of human rights; a process
of supplementation and not of derogation.
The problem posed by this polemic bet¬
ween North and South has two aspects. The
first is the reconciliation of non-Western
cultural values with the basic concepts of
human rights. The second is the integration
of the "development" experience into the
norms and structures of human rights pro¬
tection. One method of moving towards
resolution of these problems would be to
regard human rights not as ends in
themselves but as a process which implies a
certain approach to law, politics and
economics. It should be seen as an approach
which accentuates the human dilemma
above other considerations.
The human rights movement cannot im¬
mediately be removed from the context of
Should human rights be part
of the school curriculum?
its own history and structures. To do so
would be to deny it content and increase am¬
biguity. Instead, the process of reconcilia¬
tion should be seen as being dialectical. On
the one hand, it should encourage Third
World societies to articulate their values at
this period in their history. This would force
them to come to terms with the norms of the
international tradition of human rights in
the light of their particular historical ex¬
periences. On the other hand, the process of
reconciliation should compel the human
rights movement to reach beyond the con¬
fines of past historical experience, both con¬
ceptually and factually, and to search for
alternative visions and institutions which
may better capture the imagination of all the
world's societies.
The success of the human rights move¬
ment in the future of developing societies is
greatly dependent on its ability to convince
the youth of these nations that human rights
must be an important, if not primary con¬
cern of any political ideology. This becomes
particularly important when we consider
that the world, whether North or South, is
currently experiencing a "crisis of
morality".
Conflicting values and dual systems of
life-style in developing societies have served
to liberate people from fixed stations and
hierarchies. And yet, the marketplace of
values and ideas may in fact have created a
moral vacuum which will inhibit youthful
interest in causes such as human rights. To
escape this moral dilemma created by
modernist impulses, youthful insight may
find realism and materialism superior to the
call for social action required by those
dedicated to human rights protection. Or,
The level of a people's civilization can be
measured by the social position occupied
by its women.
Domingo Faustino Sarmiento
(1811-1888)
India. Photo © Jacques Minassian,
Paris.
they may seek to avoid the moral dilemmas
of the future by clutching on to the struc¬
tures of the past which have been the basis
for their identity and security. Neither of
these reactions will dynamically serve to fur¬
ther the cause of human rights.
It is therefore imperative that teaching
human rights be considered a fundamental
aspect of the school curriculum. Without
such "consciousness-raising", the concerns
of human rights will be lost in the modern
marketplace of competing values and ideas.
And yet, care must be taken to ensure that
the idealistic impulses behind the human
rights movement do not remove the teaching
of its tenets to the level of religion or
metaphysics. The need to protect human
rights in a realistic political and cultural con
text must be the basic thrust of any such
teaching exercise.
Though women's rights have received
much attention in the Western world, it is a
more fundamental but complex dilemma in
developing societies. One the one hand, the
problem is political, legal and economic,
especially in relation to the so-called
"modern" sector. The human rights ap¬
proach to women's rights has most
relevance to this sector where the structure
and style of the industrial establishment are
based on those either in Western Europe or
the Communist countries of Eastern
Europe.
The "techno-rational" principles of
management and policy-making are
especially relevant to the structures of pro- ^
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Power is a multi-dimensional concept and consists of different components. These, we contend, are offive basic
types. Firstly, there is physical violence such as used by armies, police forces and informal groups or even individual
political extremists and terrorists. The second and third components are of an economic character: power deriving
from coalitions and monopoloid organizations; andpower derivingfrom the possession of scarce resources, whether
natural resources or human qualities (e.g. intelligence, leadership or personal attractiveness). A fourth component is
thepower ofcustom or law, sometimes recognized as a legal basisfor certain types ofbehaviour. Thefifth element we
propose to identify is the power of ideas, rational or ethical.
Jan Tinbergen
Man and his Imprint. Serigraph © Roman Cieslewicz, Paris.
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
tection formulated and implemented by the
human rights movement. As the organiza¬
tions in the modern sector are prototypes of
their European counterparts, the human
rights issues greatly resemble those which
are present in the developed societies. The
issues are, nevertheless, accentuated because
of a limited sharing of resources.
On another level, the problem of
women's rights in developing societies has
enormous social and psychological dimen¬
sions. In many ways, the issues of women's
rights have accentuated the constant tension
between tradition and modernity. Women
have been classically regarded as the bearers
of tradition from one generation to another.
The transformation of their role in society is
seen as an erosion of the foundations of
traditional cultures. When the alternative to
tradition is westernization, there is an in¬
built cultural prejudice which is often the
justification for the denial of equal rights
for women. There is an important and fun¬
damental need to extricate women's rights
from the constraint of traditional ideas and
institutions, while acknowledging the
creative role that such concepts may play in
other areas of social and political life.
These brief remarks cannot, of course,
convey the many dilemmas created by
human rights problems in the context of
Third World development. One cannot even
begin to address the concrete issues of
human rights protection in such areas as
criminal procedure, free speech, race-
relations, women's rights, political and
economic rights etc... In all these areas dif¬
ficult questions continue to persist, ques¬
tions which are qualitatively different from
the issues as they exist in the North Atlantic
States. The resolution of these problems
even within the normative framework of
human rights protection may differ in con¬
tent and procedure from those traditionally
accepted by advocates of human rights who
have been trained in the political-legal
culture of the West.
But the fundamental question is not
whether the resolution of human rights
problems is different in the Third World but
whether the process of resolution will play a
creative or derogative role in the growth and
development of human rights. The essential
quest is not only for the articulation of rele
vant ends but for the creation of means both
at the national and international level which
will ensure a positive and dynamic interac¬
tion between the past and the present, North
and . South, tradition and modernity,
idealism and realpolitik.
Such a dynamic may turn destructive,
disturbing the fragile network of human
rights protection which has been built up
over the years. But, if articulated and en¬
couraged in a rational, and deliberate man¬
ner, it may prove to be a creative and in¬
novative exercise. The first step in this pro¬
cess must be a call to "open-mindedness",
not only on the part of traditional, develop¬
ing societies but also on the part of the inter¬
national human rights movement.
Without evaluating the development ex¬
perience and without coming to terms with
varying cultural viewpoints, the movement
is likely to be delegitimized or
fragmentedneither of which will help for¬
ward the main purpose behind the human
rights movement, ie. the basic amelioration
of the fundamental human condition.
B Radhika Coomaraswamy
Human Rights
are universal
The individuality and independence ofa culture
must start uith the equality of man
by Yoshikazu Sakamoto
ALTHOUGH the universal dimension
of the concept of human rights is
today generally accepted without
question the declaration adopted in 1948
by an overwhelming majority of United Na¬
tions Member States was, after all, entitled
the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights it must be recognized that in certain
of its aspects this concept is the product of
Western civilization. When, towards the end
of the nineteenth century, Japan began to
"modernize" and a number of new political
and legislative notions were introduced to
the country, no word existed in Japanese for
"human rights" and a new term had to be
invented. This is just one example of a non-
Western cultural tradition in which no
equivalent of this concept existed.
This startling contrast points immediately
to the problem inherent in the universaliza-
tion of such a concept. Clearly, the penetra-
YOSHIKAZU SAKAMOTO, of Japan, is Pro¬
fessor of International Politics at the Faculty of
Law, University of Tokyo. He is the author of
many articles on problems of international rela¬
tions, disarmament and peace, and of several
books including Peace Its Realities and
Research IMainichi Press, Tokyo, 1976). Since
1979 he has been Secretary General of the Inter¬
national Peace Research Association.
tion of the non-Western world by this
Western concept was brought about under
the influence of Western colonialism. In
other words, the "right of equality", which
is one of the fundamental human rights, was
propagated throughout the non-Western
world within the context of a flagrantly un¬
equal, dominator/dominated relationship.
This paradoxical situation evoked two
kinds of reaction in the non-Western world.
The first of these was to take advantage of
this notion of the "right to equality" and,
using it as a lever, to criticize, indeed to rise
up against the reality of Western domina¬
tion. This was an effective way of showing
up the contradictions in the Western stand¬
point, but it also implied acceptance of
Western values, a situation that involved
other contradictions. Furthermore, even if
this kind of reasoning was more or less ac¬
ceptable to the often Western-educated
élites in the developing countries, it was not
necessarily effective in mobilizing the sup¬
port of the peoples of these countries.
The second form of reaction 'which
became apparent in a number of Third
World countries was more firmly rooted in
the general public. This was an out and out
nationalism which denied the universality of
Western values and, exalting traditional in¬
digenous values, attempted to strengthen
and preserve its own political and cultural
existence.
Although such an affirmation of popular
sentiment has its positive aspects, going
beyond mere rejection of Western cultural
domination, just like the affirmation of the
universality of Western values it also has its
dangers. An extreme example is the ex¬
istence in certain developing countries of
governmental policies that are repressive vis-
à-vis human rights. In face of pressure from
Western countries and from international
organizations anxious to defend the univer¬
sality of human rights, it is to be expected
that a reaction of rejection should set in
against a concept considered to be both
Western and ill-adapted to the realities of
national life. The notions of "in¬
dependence" and "non-interference in in¬
ternal affairs" are distorted and used to
counter outside pressures in defence of
human rights.
Thus, just as the Western notion of
universality was often used for political ends
to rationalize colonial domination, it is quite
common to find the notion of non-Western
specificity being used by those who hold the
reins of power to justify their domination of
the people. In other words, both Western
"universalism" and non-Western "speci¬
ficity" are capable of being distorted in such
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Three things sustain man in this world: sowing, harvesting, eating.
Wolof proverb
Preparing the ground in Tanzania. Photo International Labour Office, Geneva.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
^. a way as to prevent international application
of human rights.
Today this problem has become more
acute than ever. Never before has the princi¬
ple of the rights of man been so widely
disseminated. And never before have the
peoples of the non-Western world been so
eager in their search for their own identity or
so positive in their affirmation of their in¬
dependence and their cultural originality.
In stressing their diversity and their
cultural originality, even where human
rights are concerned, non-Western societies
are also underlining the difference that ex¬
ists between their way of thinking and that
of the West. Examination of the place of
women in society, for example, reveals that
many cultures attach great importance to
the distinctions between the social roles of
men and women. In some societies too, true
wisdom is held to be the adjunct of the
gerontocracy, and the young, even those
that show promise, can never attain the
status of decision-makers.
Relationships between the individual and
the group also vary. In many societies loyal¬
ty to the group or the organization takes
precedence over the rights of the individual,
in contrast to the idea prevalent in Western
societies that groups or organizations owe.
their existence to acts of free will on the parti
of the individuals who compose them and I
that they are therefore a means of expressing |
the rights of the individual.
Again, there are many societies with a sort
of dualistic structure in which the laws and
constitution uphold the Western-style no¬
tions of the universality of human rights
whereas social rules and customs keep alive
Does the logic of cultural
relativism imply denial of the
universality of human rights?
traditional indigenous standards of value.
This dualism merits deeper analysis. On the
one hand, many non-Western cultures un¬
doubtedly have specific values which can
neither be assessed nor explained in terms of
Western criteria; on the other hand, there is
the danger that, in the name of these speci¬
fic values, authoritarian oppression and
violation of human rights will become
entrenched.
One approach, which has come to be
known as cultural relativism, involves
recognition of the specific values of each
culture and rejection of the notion of a
hierarchical scale of values. This line of
thought has done much to undermine the
concept of a world centred on Europe, that
is to say the presupposition of the superiori¬
ty of European culture. But if the basic
reasoning of cultural relativism were to be
taken to its logical conclusion, it would, it
might be thought, lead to anarchy in world
value systems. If this were the case, a univer¬
sal system of values based on rejection of
the violation of human rights by the ar¬
bitrary exercise of power, would have no
raison d'être.
This might lead one to think that the logic
of cultural relativism leads inevitably to
denial of the universality of human rights.
But is this really the case? A deeper analysis
of the meaning of cultural relativism gives
quite another picture.
Underlying cultural relativism, with its re¬
jection of cultural imperialism, is the notion
that cultures should be classified not in a
hierarchy with Western culture at the head,
but as separate systems possessing equal
values. Why this affirmation of the equality
of different cultures? Is it not because every
culture is based on man and our starting
point is that all men have equal rights? If we
accept the argument that the equality of
cultures is based on the equality of men, we
can only accept this equality of cultures if it
is based on recognition by the different
cultures of the equality of men. In other
words, cultures, with all their relativity and
specificity, are fundamentally equal.
The subjects of earlier tyrannies recognized
their slavery in the overt controls which
restricted their physical movements, and by
the terror which the minions of authority
inspired in them, whereas the citizens ofthe
future, manipulated at the very sources of
their being, may love their servitude and
call it freedom.
William Leiss
Automatons. Drawing by Guillotin ©
Encre Libre, Paris.
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
When a culture denies the fundamental
equality of men, that is to say the equality of
the rights of men, it lays itself open to inter¬
national criticism. It is, of course, desirable
for this equality to find expression, to take
material shape in the most widely diverse
forms freely chosen by the members of each
society. But this diversity must always be
based on the first premiss of equal rights.
The individuality and independence of a
culture must take as its starting point the
equality of men. And this universal equality
of men, from which spring cultural in¬
dependence and diversity, is one and the
same thing as the universality of the rights
of man. B Yoshikazu Sakamoto
The ideal condition for mankind
is one in which no one is rich, no
one wants to become richer, and
no one is afraid of being left
behind by those who are striving
to advance.
John Stuart Mill
(1806-1873)
Stairway to the stars. Draw¬
ing © Gourmelin, Paris.
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY,
COMMUNICATION
"S'
CIENCE and technology are said to be the cause
of most of our ills today. By conquering di¬
sease and extending life they have been respon¬
sible for an explosion of the population. By increasing
productivity and raising living standards they have
been responsible for depleting resources and polluting
nature. By expanding knowledge and emphasizing effi¬
ciency they have been responsible for deflating myths
and diminishing man. And by placing enormous power
in the hands of man they have brought him to the brink
of destruction."
This was how nuclear chemist and Nobel laureate
Glenn Seaborg once summed up the current popular
case against science and technology. Yet though
valuable as an indication of public unease about what
scientists and technologists are doing, this kind of
criticism is based on a misunderstanding of the nature
of both science and technology. The corpus of scientific
knowledge is not, as the layman tends to think, a vast
compilation of coherent facts each neatly attached to the
next in a logical sequence. Instead, whenever new facts
are discovered, old ones have to be eliminated. The
scientist is always fundamentally in error. Science is
based on uncertainty; it is the pursuit of the apparently
unknowable and it is precisely for this reason that it is
so inextricably linked with other aspects of human
culture.
Technology, the handmaiden of science, is founded,
on the contrary, on what might be called hard
mechanical facts; it is at the moment of application that
it comes up against a host of uncontrollable variables
and uncertainty creeps in. And there is no warning
feedback, no means of telling early enough to alter
course when a new technology is being wrongly
applied.
Is there no way in which we can eliminate the uncer¬
tainty factor in the application of technology? Cannot
new indicators be devised that will give early warning of
possible misapplications?
Curiously enough, the problems of the impact of
science and technology on man and society are most
starkly revealed in the field in which, over the past
decade, the most astounding advances have been
achieved communications. Direct broadcast satellites,
videodiscs and vidéocassettes, cable television, teletext
and videotex, open up immense possibilities for good or
for ill. These new communication technologies offer
broadcasters direct access to the homes of millions of
people throughout the world. Will they be used to sub¬
ject the world to the cultural domination of a handful of
great powers? They can also offer the television viewer
or radio listener the possibility of a very wide range of
different programmes and of an instant and direct two-
way dialogue with the broadcasters. Will this mean that,
at last, the ordinary man will be able to monitor and in¬
fluence the men, the machines and the events on which
his destiny depends?
Barren soil
For technology transplants to ïake'
the ground must be carefully prepared
by Ali A. Mazrui
TECHNOLOGY transfer is a comprehensive term which
encompasses both short-term and longterm technolog¬
ical movements, from computers on lease to African
countries to the establishment of local institutes of tech¬
nology. What fits and what does not fit is subsumed under
"technology transfer".
In contrast, "technology transplant" borrows a metaphor
from biology to imply the need for receptivity in the host
body. Some compatibility is needed between the thing
"transplanted" (be it a heart or a seed) and the recipient.
Our first proposition in this assessment is that there has
ALI A. MAZRUI, of Kenya, is Research Professorat the University of Jos
in Nigeria, and Professor of Political Science and of Afro-American and
African Studies at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. He is the author
of A World Federation of Cultures: An African Perspective (1976), Africa's
International Relations (1977) and Political Values and the Educated Class
in Africa (1978).
been a considerable amount of technology transfer to the
Third World in the last thirty yearsbut very little
technology transplant. Especially in Africa very little of what
has been transferred has in fact been successfully
transplanted. Very little has taken roots. The question is:
Why?
We propose to argue (with special reference to Africa) that
while the normative climate is favourable to technology
transplant, the structural and sociological soil is still relative¬
ly barren. While indeed there is interest in, and enthusiasm
for, a technological culture, the actual sociological soil still
tends to reject what is being transplanted. Let us look at these
two parts of the argument more closely.
The climate of opinion in much of the Third World favours
moves towards "modernization", "industrialization", more
efficient "rural development" and faster modes of travel.
Apart from a few poets and philosophers, there are no major
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
movements opposed to industrialism and technology
change.
India loves and reveres the late Mahatma Gandhi, but even
those contemporary Indians who favour cottage industries
often tend to see them more as an additional developmental
strategy, rather than as an alternative to the big trusts like the
Tatas and the steel industries. The more militant economic
Gandhians (urging a return to economic simplicity) have so
far had little impact on policy or indeed on organized mass
opinion.
Africa and the West Indies have also produced from time
to time dedicated economic primitivists. The whole négritude
school in Africa and the West Indies has at times included
nostalgia for the economic simplicity of the African past. As
the poet and politician Aimé Césaire of Martinique once
brilliantly put it:
...Eia for those who invented nothing
For those who have never discovered...
For those who explored nothing...
Eia for joy
Eia for grief at the udders of reincarnated tears...
My Négritude is neither a tower nor a cathedral
It thrusts into. the red flesh of the soil...
(Return to my Native Land)
Césaire revelled in the non-technicalness of original
African cultures.
Africa's most distinguished champion of négritude is
Leopold Senghor. But although Senghor was President of
Senegal for more than twenty years, he did not embark on a
programme of revived simplicity. On the contrary, official
policy in Senegal under Senghor was in the direction of an ex¬
panding industrial and monetary sector.
What all this means is that the religion of industrialism is
not in danger in the* Third World. Even countries like Burma
and the People's Republic of China which turned their
backs for a while on the lure of Western technology have
more recently shown signs of renewed fascination with that
technology.
It is because of these considerations that the normative
climate for technology transplant appears, at least on first
estimate, favourable in most of the Third World. Parents are
eager to send their children to Western-type schools; govern¬
ments are eager to formulate five-year plans; there are
technical experts galore temporarily imported from outside.
With such a favourable climate, why is not the plant of
technology taking roots? Yes, why? This is what brings us
back to the metaphor of a barren soil. We see the soil in terms
No, we do not want to overtake anyone. We want to walk, day and
night, for all time, in the company of all men.
Frantz Fanon
(1925-1961)
Bringing in the rice harvest, Indonesia. Photo Georg Gerster
© Rapho, Paris.
of the sociology of the society in relation to its structural links
with the outside world. This soil is not congenial. A series of
contradictions are part of the explanation.
Firstly, are parts of the Third World experiencing cultural
Westernization without economic modernization? Is there a
transmission of Western consumption patterns without a
transmission of Western production techniques? Is there a
craze for Western technological gadgets without a pro¬
gramme of how to produce them locally?
Consumption patterns are a reflection of values, either new
or old. Production techniqifes would have been a reflection
of skills. The West has been more successful in popularizing
its values and tastes than in transplanting its skills. This im¬
balance has often been deliberate. Creating a taste for
Western goods without a local capability for producing them
was often more profitable for the West than exporting both
tastes and techniques.
Even in exporting capitalism as a system the West has been
more effective in exporting the profit motive than the en¬
trepreneurial skills. The profit motive is a desire for profit. It
is not necessarily to be skilled in securing it.
African businessmen may be eager enough to maximize
their returns. But many are more comfortable sitting on
Boards of Directors than trying out new trading techniques.
Risk-taking as an aspect of creative entrepreneurship is often
underdeveloped in the Third World. Easy money and safe in¬
vestment are preferred.
Is the West transmitting
its consumption patterns
rather than its production
techniques?
Even the Western puritanical principle of "make
money but do not spend it," is honoured in the breach.
Money is made but promptly spent ostentatiously. Re¬
investment in better equipment or more effective techniques
is seldom elevated to a priority. When new equipment is
bought it is the wrong equipment.
As for the Protestant principle of "industriousness" (or
the work ethic) as a moral principle, this is often more
characteristic of African peasants than of the African
bourgeoisie.
The latter have indeed been converted to the profit motive
in many parts of Africa, but even when they are Protestants
by religion they have not necessarily been converted to the
"Protestant ethic" in the classical economic sense that Max
Weber has reminded us about in his study, The Protestant
Ethic and the Spirit ofCapitalism. The profit motive is strong
in much of Africa, but entrepreneurship is still weak. This is
part of the barrenness of the sociological soil for effective
transplantation of relevant technology.
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Time is the field ofhuman development.
Karl Marx
(1818-1883)
Villagers of the Mekong delta. Socialist Republic of Viet-
Nam. Photo Raymond Depardon © Magnum, Paris.
For I remember stopping by the way
To watch a Potter thumbing his wet Clay:
And with its all-obliterated Tongue
It murmuredGently, Brother, gently, pray!
Omar Khayyam
(1048-1122)
Throwing a pot. Photo Leo Pelissier © Rapho, Paris.
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
Even the educational systems in Africa are better at
transmitting Western values and tastes than Western skills
and techniques. The schools bequeathed by colonialism are
instruments of cultural re-orientation and not instruments of
economic transformation. In the classroom there is ac¬
culturation of the arts of conversation rather than the
transfer of techniques of production.
African universities are on the whole designed to produce
communicators rather than creators, masters of verbal and
literary "skills", rather than practitioners of the craft of in¬
novation. Colonialism preferred imitative communicators
to innovative creators. Colonial schools were designed
accordingly.
Scientism rather than the scientific spirit emerged out of
colonial educational structures. The ideology of "modern
scientism" rather than the principle of genuine scientificity
held sway on graduation day and beyond. Africans were
trained to be awed by science rather than to master it, to be
impressed by Western scientific achievements rather than to
cultivate their own scientific self-confidence. The ideology of
scientism made Africans not only awed by Western science
but helplessly dependent upon it psychologically. The stage
was set for long-term African technological dependency as
well.
These are some of the contradictions which have gone
towards making the post-colonial soil so inhospitable for ef¬
fective technology transplantation. The climate of opinion is
still in favour of technological development, but fundamental
changes are needed sociologically and structurally.
To carry the metaphor of the soil a stage further, fertilizers
are needed to help enrich the soil and enable the plant of new
technology to take roots. It is not enough to complain about
North-South abuses and the genuine excesses of transnational
corporations. It is not enough to focus on limitations of
copyright and patent, or excesses of exploitation, real as these
problems are. Sooner or later we have to confront the defi¬
ciencies of the host soil those caused by colonial distortions
and those caused by indigenous cultural divergences. What
may be at stake are factors which range from motivation pat¬
terns to educational systems, from a distorted Protestant
ethic to the imbalances of the world economy.
The quest for a New International Technological Order
must begin with the issue of fertilizers technological fer¬
tilizers to enrich the host soil in the Third World and make it
more receptive to the genuine transplantation of the skills of
production and the craft of innovation.
I Ali A. Mazrui
Predicting the unpredictable
Is it possible to identify the variables
that trigger surprise and change?
by Crawford S. Holling
TODAY'S rate and scale of change is perceived by many to be
transcending the adaptive capacity of individuals, govern¬
ments, industry, and nature. Caught in the currents of
turbulence, man searches for a generic cause to give reason to the
unreasonable and hence a basis for action. Like Fourasti's
bewildered bee on a moving train, man appears to have forgotten
where he comes from and has lost the sense of where he is going.
Many in positions of influence and responsibility
share a concern for the world in structural transition,
but are frustrated in their efforts to decide and
govern wisely by the increasing inability of traditional
planning mechanisms to deliver the needed com¬
prehension and options. At the same time, fun¬
damental paradoxes are emerging to challenge tradi¬
tional concepts of science and scholarship. Those
traditions, which have sought typically to increase ef¬
ficiency, ensure constancy, maintain stability, and
improve prediction, have often shown that the very
effectiveness of the pursuit has generated paradoxes
that suggest the need for a deeper understanding of
structural change.
In increasing the efficiency of a system, for exam¬
ple, we have often increased its fragility and
vulnerability. In aiming to achieve constancy, we
have frequently eliminated the role of variability as a
way of testing, renewing, and maintaining a system's
flexibility. Similarly, in seeking stability we have
observed a constructive role for instability in main¬
taining the processes of self-enrichment, self-
monitoring, and self-regulation. And while working
to improve prediction techniques, we have en¬
countered the issues of limits to prediction and the
CRAWFORD S. HOLLING, of Canada, is Director of the
International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (HASA)
at Laxenburg (Austria). Since 1967 he has been professor at
the Institute ofAnimal Resource Ecology and in the Depart¬
ment ofZoology at the University of British Columbia. He is
also a consultant in the Office of Biological Services, U.S.
Fish and Wildlife Service, Washington, D. C, and was the
first leader of IIASA's Ecology and Environment Project
from 1973 to 1975.
60
need for adaptation that explicitly recognizes the inevitability of
failures and the unexpected.
My colleagues and I at the International Institute for Applied
Systems Analysis, Austria, in collaboration with a number of na¬
tional research institutes, have been exploring different concepts
and perceptions of surprise, crisis, and change, in order to identify
categories of surprise generated by the intersection of man,
technology, and nature, and to define the ingredients
for adaptive behaviour and management.
In each case the analysis focused on the links bet¬
ween the "natural" environmental system, the
management institution(s), their policies and
technological solutions, and society. Over twenty ex¬
amples of resource management have been examined.
Here I will emphasize five for illustrative purposes,
analysing those key features that seem important for
adaptive design.
For the cases that follow, we observed that all of
the management policies succeeded over the short
term; all failed over the longer term and produced a
crisis; all owed the failures to success in reducing
variability; some adapted successfully to failure while
others did not.
Suppression of spruce budworm populations in
eastern Canada using insecticides preserved the pulp
and paper industry and employment in the short term
by partially protecting the forest. But that policy has
left the forest and the economy more vulnerable to an
outbreak of an intensity never experienced before.
Effective protection and enhancement of salmon
spawning on the west coast of North America is
leading to more predictable success. But that has trig-
Development means putting man on his feet.
Dom Helder Cámara
Statuette of the Barriles culture, Panama,
Dating from 300-500 A.D. Photo © National In¬
stitute of Culture and Leisure, Panama City.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
That which we call modern is that perhaps
which will not endure.
Dante
(1265-1321)
Demolition of the Biltmore Hotel, Okla¬
homa City. Photo John Vowter ©
Rapho, Paris.
We have to overcome the complex of awe
and fear which derives from the idea that
"technology" is something beyond our
grasp. We should know that technological
development is not only that which has
taken man to the moon or made satellite
broadcasting possible; on the contrary,
technological creation does not mean only
making new things, but also finding new
ways of making things which have been
made already. We should realize that
technological creation, innovation and
adaptation can be developed not only by
large industries but also by the medium-
sized and small industries of our countries.
Roberto Salas Capriles
Wind-powered generator, Senegal.
Photo © Christophe Naigeon, Paris.
gered increased fishing and investment pressure, and less produc¬
tive stocks are becoming extinct, leaving the fishing industry
precariously dependent on a few enhanced stocks that are
vulnerable to collapse. . ;
Forest fire suppression has reduced the probability of fire in na¬
tional parks in the United States. But the consequence has been the
accumulation of fuel to produce fires of an unprecedented extent
and cost.
Semi-arid savannah ecosystems have been turned into productive
cattle grazing systems in the Sahel zone of Africa, southern and
east Africa, the southern United States, northern India, and
Australia. But because of changes in grass composition, an irrever¬
sible switch to woody vegetation is common and the systems have
become highly susceptible to collapse, often triggered by drought.
Malarial eradication programmes in Brazil, Egypt, Greece and
Italy are brilliant examples of sophisticated understanding, com¬
bined with a style of implementation that has all the character of a
military campaign. But elsewhere, where malaria was neither
marginal nor at low endemic levels, the transient success has led to
human populations with little immmunity, and mosquito vectors
resistant to DDT. As a consequence, some countries have recently
reported a thirty- to forty-fold increase in cases of malaria com¬
pared to 1969-70, endangering both public health and socio¬
economic development.
Two categories of "solution" appear when we compare our
studies. One class is unforgiving of error; one forgiving. The use of
insecticide to control insect populations in order to protect trees
from defoliation or people from malaria requires a level of
vigilance and efficiency of application that does not match well
with the fallibility of man and his technology. In contrast,
biological control, through the introduction of parasites, predators
or diseases of pests, represents an effort to work through natural
laws to generate dynamic responses to change that are self-
regulating, self-monitoring, and self-correcting. Failure can still
occur but it is typically localized and transient.
All the cases achieved their short-term objectivesmaintain
employment in the face of imminent destruction of the forest from
an insect outbreak; reduce the frequency of forest fires; increase
salmon populations; increase meat production; and decrease the
incidence of malaria. But as a consequence, each system evolved
into a qualitatively different one. That evolution took place in
three areas. The socio-economic environment changed. More pulp
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
mills were built to exploit the protected spruce-balsam forests;
more recreational demand was developed in the parks protected
from fire; more efficient and extensive fisheries were developed to
exploit salmon; more land was moved into cattle ranches on the
savannahs; and more development was possible in malaria pro¬
tected areas.
The management agencies also began to evolve. Operational
agencies were formed to spray insects, fight fires, operate fish
hatcheries, encourage cattle ranching, and reduce mosquito
populations. Their goals shifted from socio-economic ones to
those emphasizing operational efficiency; better and better air¬
craft, navigation and delivery systems to distribute insecticide; bet¬
ter and better ways to detect and control fires.
Evolution also occurred in the biophysical area, the consequence
of which was not generally perceived. Success was achieved by
reducing the variability of a target variablethe forest insect
populations, the fire frequency, the salmon numbers, the cattle
stock density, and the mosquito populations. The features of the
biophysical environment, viewed implicitly as constants, gradually
changed to produce a structurally different system.
Reduction of budworm populations to sustained moderate levels
led to the accumulation and persistence of foliage over larger and
larger areas. Any relaxation of vigilance could lead to an outbreak
sometime, in a place where it could spread over enormous areas.
Reduction of fire frequency led to accumulation of fuel and the
closing of forest crowns, so that what once were modest ground
fires affecting limited areas and causing minor tree mortality
became catastrophic fires covering large areas and causing massive
tree mortality.
Similarly, increased numbers of salmon led to an increase in the
size and efficiency of fishing fleets and the gradual elimination of
many natural stocks, thereby increasing vulnerability to unex¬
pected events; maintenance of moderate numbers of cattle led to
changes in grass composition toward species more vulnerable to
drought and management error; persistent reduction in mosquitoes
led to gradual increases in the number of people susceptible to the
diseases and to mosquitoes resistant to insecticide. In short, the
Can we design for change?
biophysical environment evolved into one that was more fragile, at
a time when greater dependencies had developed in the socio¬
economic and institutional environment for continued success.
I am not arguing in these examples against their original pur¬
poses to maintain employment or reduce the debilitating burden of
disease. Nor am I even arguing for a blanket indictment of solu¬
tions that are unforgiving of error. At times that is all that is
available. At times, they should be used but only to buy time for
developing alternatives. The difficulty is that technological man is
so good at making such techniques successful in the short term.
Consequently, the need and motivation for continued exploration
of alternatives succumbs to the simulacrum of success. When the
inevitable crisis begins to be perceived, there is often no obvious
direction to go except to continue as before, but more rigorously,
more efficiently, and with bigger budgets. Policy changes typically
occur in the face of crises but only when there are clearly
understood options available. Delays in developing those
alternatives shrink the domain of attainable alternatives.
What is true for policy change is true for technological develop¬
ment. Many policies are derived from available technology, as well
as from socio-economic incentives and penalties. If alternative
technologies are not available, policy change is difficult. As control
of budworm using insecticide seemed to be successful, programmes
to develop biological control agents, pheromones, or even dif¬
ferent harvesting methods withered. Currently there is no opera¬
tional alternative to insecticide. The phase of technological
development was frozen in the face of apparent success.
In his book Disturbing the Universe, the physicist Freeman
Dyson makes the same point for the development of nuclear
energy. He points out that effective technological developments
proceed through trial-and-error generation and exploration of
alternatives. He argues that this phase of exploration was foreclos¬
ed in nuclear energy development by a premature application of
the accountants' criterion of cost effectiveness. The very real
possibilities for designs that are more forgiving of error at a more
manageable scale were not realized as the present technology
became entrenched within government and industry. Rather than
have the environmentalist join the accountant in a further smother¬
ing of innovation, it would seem wise to dramatically increase sup¬
port for exploratory technology in critical areas of unforgiving
technology.
Our analysis revealed that ecological systems do not evolve
toward some climax or persistent equilibrium, but are dominated
by a pattern in time and space of growth, quiescence, collapse, and
renewal. Thus time and rates of change are central for understan¬
ding and developing adaptive, self-organizing designs.
The analysis of the biophysical part of our cases included three
sets of biological variables, each operating at different speeds. For
example, in the forest insect pest examples, they were the insect
and its associated natural enemies, the foliage and the trees. Their
speed is roughly related to their generation times one year for the
The evil application of scientific discoveries has
never been more rampant than at the present day. It
is common knowledge, indeed, that a scientist can
hardly make any new move in his research without
having the military attempt to make use of it. The
comparative psycho-physiology of dolphins, for ex¬
ample, is applied to naval warfare; anthropological
studies are appropriated for "counter-insurgency"
purposes; and special-sense physiologists see their
findings used for the intellectual cruelty of techni¬
ques of sensory deprivation.
Joseph Needham
Dolphins. Photo Helen Fischer © Rapho, Paris.
insect, eight years for the foliage, and over sixty years for the trees.
As management began to restrict the variability of the target
variable, parameters typically associated with slower variables
began to change. Foliage in the budworm system accumulated at
fairly high levels spread more homogeneously over space. These
represent changes in variables and supposed parameters that are in¬
termediate between the fastest and slowest. These changes are
mediated by competition or natural selective processes. It is these
changes that led to increased vulnerability of the systems to unex¬
pected events.
Present forest fire policy in the US National Parks has recently
changed radically, reverting to fire as the natural "manager" of
62
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
the forests. That dramatic adaptation was not made easily, and
rested on the availability of an alternative policy and technologies
to implement it, on a climate of understanding, and costs that were
relatively modest compared to our other examples. But it might be
equally important that the critical variable of fuel and forest tree
composition changed at the slowest rate of all examples. It was
some sixty years before the change became critical. I argue that
twenty to thirty years, the turnover rate of employees, is the rele¬
vant time unit of change for a management institution. By the time
the problem became critical, there was a new generation of experts
and policy advisers who were more willing to recognize the failures
of their predecessors. And of dominant importance, the slowness
of change allowed the accumulation of knowledge of the processes
involved and the communication of that understanding to a wide
range of actors;
In contrast, changes in the budworm forest system proceeded at
a faster rate. Insecticide spraying began on a large scale in the
mid-1950s, with conditions of vulnerability building to a critical
point by the early 1970s. That fifteen to twenty-year period was in¬
sufficient to accumulate and, most important, disseminate an
understanding of the problem. Alternative policies and
technologies were not developed, and the parents of the original
policies were still central actors and defenders of the past. Adaptive
change has been an agonizing process that is only now showing
signs of occurring.
Although there are insufficient examples to generalize with con¬
fidence, our analysis suggests that one can identify key parameters
and variables that trigger surprises. Unexpected events that occur
rapidly require an emphasis on predictive capability. Those in the
intermediate range require emphasis on adaptive capability
(development of alternative policies, exploratory technology, sear¬
ches for forgiving solutions). Those occurring slowly require an
emphasis on monitoring and regulation.
Times of turbulence can be times for creativity and renewal.
Man has always sailed on a sea of the unknown, encountering
waves of technological innovation and stagnation, hope and
despair, stasis and renaissance. Somehow, haltingly, he has thriv¬
ed. Indeed, the brilliant technological developments of this century
testify to man's inherent ability to adapt his tools to change. Since
neither mankind nor nature is predictable, inevitably we will con¬
tinue to be subject to unanticipated shocks from changes and the
conflicts they generate. If we can comprehend the patterns of these
changes, their causes and consequences, we will have the capability
and flexibility to respond adaptively to the unexpected in ways that
exploit the profound developments of science and technology for
man's survival and renewal.
I Crawford S. H oiling
By word of mouth
It is not often realized that the spoken word
is still the most widely used medium of communication
by Mohamed H. Abdulaziz
COMMUNICATION through language is one of the greatest gifts
bestowed on man. The civilizations of ancient times and of the
Middle Ages looked upon language as an object of great
mystery, even ofmagical power, able to create, cure or destroy. It provid¬
ed the basis for philosophical debate on right and wrong, truth and
falsehood, reality and deception, and was the source of the great debates
of the conventionalist and the rationalist schools of thought.
Language has also been the medium through which all human creative
talent has been expressed , preserved and transmitted throughout history.
All religious and ideological philosophies have relied heavily on the use of
language and its mystical power. There is also the issue of the relationship
between language and the cognitive process, language and culture and
language and the world view.
Again, throughout history, language has been used as a basis for
delimiting nation States and peoples and has been one of the main causes
of nationalism with its positive and negative aspects. In fact, without
language, it would be difficult to visualize the survival of human social
organization. '
Studies of oral communication, especially in the West, have until
recently usually been undertaken from an anthropological point ofview.
As late as the 1950s, oral traditions were viewed by scholars within the
framework of the concept of primitive pre-literate idealistic human
forms ofcommunication. The historical perspective ofsociety as open to
change was underplayed. A society such as that of the Masai of East
Africa was looked upon as having exotic social, economic, ideological
and religious organizations; it was indigenous and primitive. There was
no empirical approach that looked at the phenomena from the point of
view of the stimuli and responses of social change, affecting all human
societies, though perhaps differently, in different periods of history
based on observable and explainable conditions. It was not until the
late 1950s when the "modernization" approach came to the fore that
oral communication was viewed from a socio-psychological angle.
Among linguists oral language is now considered the basis of the data
for both theoretical thinking and descriptive methodology. The myth of
structurally superior and inferior languages, traditionally based on
literate tradition, has been completely exploded. In its place a new
outlook has come into being supported by linguists such as Noam Chom¬
sky and his followers. The view now prevalent among the linguists is that
' 'instead of the individual languages determining cognition, it is a univer-
MOHAMED HASSAN ABDULAZIZ, of Kenya, is Professor and Chair¬
man of the Department of Linguistics and African Languages at the
University of Nairobi.
There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and
none of them is without signification. Therefore if I know not the
meaning of the voice, I shall be unto him that speaketh a bar¬
barian, and he that speaketh shall be a barbarian unto me.
I Corinthians, XIV, 10-11
Experts differ on the number of languages spoken in
Nigeria, their estimates ranging from 368 to 513; Hausa, Ibo
and Yoruba are the country's three majority languages.
Photo Peter Larsen, Unesco.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
sal system of innate cognitive principles which, at the semantic level at
least, underlies and gives form to all human language"
This view ofmodern linguistics has sealed the supremacy of the spoken
language as a basis for all human communication. In fact, it is often not
realized that only a small proportion of communicated human inter¬
action, even in highly organized and industrialized societies, is in fact in
written form.
Among the pre-literate societies throughout history, oral communica¬
tion depended on social context. Oral behaviour was directly linked with
the reality of social situations. Such factors as the value of an individual
person's word, trust, reliability,,were heavily constrained by social sanc¬
tions. In oral civilizatons no written document was required to prove
ownership, to place responsibility, to define social obligation, or to ap¬
portion blame. The oral word was adequate since it was built, not on an
abstract system of non-verbal behaviour, but on communicational value
systems which could not be breached without far-reaching consequences
to the individual.
Of course, there have been abuses even in such oral cultures, but there
was no question of inadequacy ofcommunicative efficiencyor ofdivorc¬
ing communication from the contexts of human interaction. This is
shown by the use of oral communication with its heavy dependence on
personal references as opposed to the impersonal reference often
associated with modern documents.
The historical approach views oral tradition and folklore as universal
phenomena. In fact, the print medium itselfcame into being fairly recent¬
ly, in the fifteenth century, with the first printed materials in the form of
government gazettes. By the seventeenth century most of the printed
communication materials were of the "Advertiser" type, for example,
the Rotterdam and Manchester Advertisers. Of course, with the coming
ofcopying machines and printing the whole structure ofcommunication,
especially at the popular level, completely changed.
In Africa most communication is still oral, because over seventy-five
per cent of the people in most African countries live in traditional
societies as members of ethnic groups, clans or extended families, in
villages and homesteads. Most day to day transactions and interactions,
be they economic, social or inter-group are conducted orally. There is no
apparent inefficiency in such communication, unless interfered with by
written elements of modernization imposed from the urban areas where
centres of political power and administration are located. In fact,
throughout the continent of Africa, one sees a vast oral communication
network which is very efficient, in spite of the extensive and complex
multilingual reality in existence. Most information is still transmitted by
word of mouth.
Colonial rule in Africa has brought about a cultural and linguistic com¬
plexity with far-reaching psychological and sociological consequences.
In almostall African countries that have attained independence, there ex¬
ists unstable linguistic and cultural heterogeneity. In a small country like
Cameroon there are over a hundred ethnolinguistic communities. Tan¬
zania with twenty million people has over a hundred ethnolinguistic
groups or tribes. This should, on the face of it, raise an acute problem of
communication but, in fact, for centuries people from different ethno¬
linguistic backgrounds have been efficiently communicating using the
oral medium, the basis being a sharing of common understanding,
assumptions and presuppositions that are vital to an efficient com¬
munication system.
At another level, there is a diglossia situation in most countries where
the metropolitan European language, English, French, Portuguese,
Spanish or Afrikaans, fills the role of the official and national language.
The local indigenous languages then are often reduced to a purely conver¬
sational role, except, of course, in countries like Tanzania, Somalia and
Ethiopia where there are indigenous national/official languages, but
with a European language still playing an important role in higher educa¬
tion and other areas of communication. Nevertheless, in Africa, after
nearly a hundred years of westernization, most communication is still
oral in form, making a vital contribution to group solidarity and identity
and providing a basis for social, psychological and cultural life.
In some cases problems arise due to the existence of written codes of
law, often in a foreign language, and manifesting value systems alien to
the vast majority of the people. Injustices in the courts and the legal
system in general can and do easily occur, when a defendant is forced to
submit to a legal system he does not understand or appreciate. A situation
of privilege and discrimination with respect to social and economic rights
such as job opportunities and social mobility can also often arise, to the
detriment of the so-called illiterate people. Illiteracy then simply means
inability to express oneself in and understand the written word.
Oral communication in all societies, including the so-called developed
ones, is relatively more flexible since it is dependent on the human con¬
text. Many ugly situations leading to misunderstandings and even wars
could be defused if people met and exchanged views orally in a human
>
Our own monuments are oral traditions which
die along with the old men, conveyed by a
multitude of languages which often do not inter¬
communicate. Our traditional authorities no
longer have any responsibility or any means of
expression. Our institutions are undergoing the
aggressive irruption of modernity. We are in the
world a fragile people.
Alioune Diop
The late Wa Kamissoko, a famous Malian
griot (story-teller, musician, entertainer).
Photo © SCOA, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
/ can still clearly remember the day
when a car was first driven on to my
father's estate. The labourers asked that
the hood should be opened and that the
hidden horse be taken out. This was not
all that long ago. Yet no one today con¬
siders an interplanetary rocket to be
that much ofa sensation any more. Men
sit at home, in slippers and dressing-
gowns, to watch the astronauts walking
about the moon and listen to their small
talk. The world was replaced by worlds,
and our small globe by the universe. We
have to change and revalue our view of
the world in accordance with this.
Albert Szent-Gyorgyi
The Orrery, painting by Joseph
Wright of Derby (an orrery is a
mechanical model of the solar
system). Photo © Derby Art
Gallery, UK.
context. Discrimination in education systems, even in the developed
countries, can often be traced back to linguistic barriers that recognize
only one variety ofwritten standard language, which often coincides with
the language of the educated élite of the middle and upper classes. High
failure rates among working-class schoolchildren have been found to be
due to a large extent to cultural and linguistic discontinuity between the
home and school. In Third World countries such discrimination,
especially where a foreign language is involved, can take on enormous
proportions.
In Third World countries, many people still rely on oral communica¬
tion as adult (and general) literacy campaigns have not had the impact
originally expected. Indeed, in many parts of the world people still
depend on oral tradition for day to day survival. Many family-
In an organization whose objectives relate to such matters as
education, science, and culture we must avoid systematic confron¬
tations... What we need most is a constant willingness to engage in
dialogue. ^
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Detail from Feeding the Hungry, from the series The Seven
Works of Mercy, by the Master of Alkmaar, 15th/16th cen¬
tury Dutch artist. Photo Dominique Roger, Unesco.
planning programmes have failed in Africa because this was not fully
understood by the authorities.
An example of this emerged from a door to door survey in a poor,
working-class section ofNairobi aimed at finding out the effectiveness of
a family-planning campaign. Free contraceptive pills and other aids had
been distributed. It was found that one lady continued to produce
children even though she and her husband had actually tried to practice
birth control. When interviewed, the lady said she normally took her pills
but when tired of doing so she would give them regularly to her husband
Can the oral tradition coexist
with the written word?
for a time, assuming that the result would be the same. On other occa¬
sions she would take a whole week's supply in two or three days. It was
then discovered that the packet containing the contraceptive pills had
been imported and that the instructions were in Swedish and English.
The 1960s and 1970s saw a great effort to promote functional literacy
as a tool for improving communication that was considered vital to
economic and social development. But the results have been disappoin¬
ting in many areas. The conflict seems to be one of culture and tradition
so far as the majority of the low income groups are concerned, and these,
ironically, happen to be the target population.
When the idea of functional literacy was introduced in Africa, it was
believed that it would serve as a panacea for underdevelopment in the
rural areas and would lead to higher productivity, especially higher food
production. Again, very little impact has been made. In some cases at¬
tempts to force people to join the world of Uterate society have been
deliberately frustrated.
It is a pity that only in this century have scholars and others realized the
importance of oral tradition as a source of knowledge of human history,
culture, belief systems and other facets of oral civilization. Even in the
Western world great artistic works must have been lost for ever because
the oral tradition was not considered worthy of preservation. In Africa
today, oral tradition forms an important source material for the inter¬
pretation ofhistory. Oral stories and folklore provide vital linguistic clues
to the state of the languages in a given area, their genetic classification and
the form of linguistic change they have undergone, thus enriching the
science of language.
Today, dances, rituals and other fruits of oral civilization are being
revived as objects of serious study and research, and for entertainment
purposes. Traditional medicine, for example, has been found to be of
great value and of intrinsic interest to modern medicine, both for physical
and for psychological and emotional therapy. There is now a worldwide
appreciation of the value of the oral civilization and its destruction can be
considered as nothing less than the deliberate spoliation of an ir¬
replaceable element of the great human heritage.
H Mohamed Abdulaziz
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
Communication
facts and figures
rHE changes now taking place and
the likelihood offuture upheaval in
the field of communication and in¬
formation are bringing new dimensions to
thinking about communication and infor¬
mation as essential determinants of change
in the lives of societies.
The means of storing data, sounds and
images are being extended and improved
with the aid of computer memories and
video discs; processing and computation
capacities are being very considerably in¬
creased with microprocessors; transmission
capacities are being extended in space by
way ofcommunication satellites, and at the
surface of the earth or under the sea with
the use ofmicrowaves or opticalfibres; and
data collecting is acquiring new dimensions
with the help of remote-sensing techniques.
The association of computer technologies
and communication technologies is giving
rise to the establishment and interconnex¬
ion ofcomplex networks enabling informa¬
tion to be processed and transmitted instan¬
taneously, in real time.
These technologies are playing a part in
transforming societies and causing them to
move towards ever greater complexity .'
Communication and information may in
fact be regarded as the nervous system of
contemporary societies: they are essential
to their activities, particularly in economic
matters, and play an essential part in finan¬
cial transactions and banking and in the
development of trade, of land, sea and air
transport, of health or public administra¬
tion systems, and of military systems.
Communication and information in¬
dustries are in some countries acquiring
such economic importance that they are
tending to become predominant and to
take over from heavy industry and
manufacturing as the chief component of
the national product. Some people conse¬
quently consider that tomorrow's economy
will be based mainly on information, and
that information is in the process ofbecom¬
ing the key resource marked out for a
major role still more decisive than that of
raw materials and energy.
The impact ofcommunication and infor¬
mation on education is also emerging more
clearly. As we know, it is quite commonfor
children in some countries to receive infor¬
mation put out by the audio-visual media
during periods as long as, if not longer
than, the time spent in the classroom. The
school, as a means of transmitting
knowledge, thus finds itself in a context
very different from that obtaining in the
past, for it is now faced with the need to
provide a kind of "neo-literacy" instruc¬
tion by instilling the ability to select
messages, to interpret them critically and to
classify discontinuous and heterogeneous
flows of information into organized and
coherent bodies of knowledge.
In addition, the new technologies have
given rise to the production ofa great many
educational materials designed to extend
the effects of instruction. Their use and the
possible benefits resulting therefrorñ in
terms of time and manpower savings and
increased effectiveness, together with the
role of the computer as a medium and a
subject of instruction, are central themes
for reflection on the future prospects of
educational methods and programmes.
Scientific and technological development
is also influenced to a great extent by the
existence ofmore and better means ofcom¬
munication and information. This may be a
matter of research and computing capacity
and the circulation and use ofscientific and
technical information intended for
specialists and passing on the store of ac¬
quired knowledge, or ofefforts to make the
general public more aware of science and
technology and the development ofa scien¬
tific and technological culture.
Resulting from the convergence of
various interrelated and interacting
technologies, the world of communication
and information can be seen as a shifting,
complex and as it were ubiquitous entity.
This makes the very great disparities in the
different countries' situations as regards
their communication and information
capacity all the more serious. The least well
equipped countries, especially the develop¬
ing countries, are deprived of some of the
most effective means of controlling the
various aspects of the development process.
The development of communication and
information in the developing countries,
which is generally recognized to be
necessary by the international community
today, is therefore a prime prerequisite for
the advent of a world ofgreater equity and
solidarity and for the free development of
democracy within the various societies. If
they were better able to communicate and
to acquire and impart information, the
developing countries could not only make
their voices heard more effectively in inter¬
national affairs but could also make more
progress in education particularly in the
struggle against illiteracyand could
develop their scientific and technological
potential, improve their health systems,
promote rural development, and be in a
better position to deal with natural
disasters. Communication and information
can also help those countries, and indeed
all others, to consolidate national unity,
preserve their cultural identity, and make
provision for greater participation by the
public in the changes currently taking
place.
With the continuous advancement of
knowledge, information is steadily growing
in volume and variety, and all societies anx¬
ious to make progress are faced with the
need to operate systems for the storing,
processing and dissemination ofspecialized
information, including scientific and
technical information. Information systems
and services are being developed mainly in
the industrialized countries, and some of
them hold a privileged position, in some
cases a monopoly, in regard both to con¬
tent, most often derived from studies and
research carried out in those countries, and
to technical facilities for storage and
distribution.
Many countries have to overcome a
variety of technical obstacles and financial
constraints in order to gain access to infor¬
mation. The compelling requirement is for
freer and more effective access to more
relevant information. Information should
be able to flow freely, and every country
should be able to avail itself ofdata helpful
for its development. It is therefore im¬
perative, on the one hand, to ensure the
compatibility and interconnexion of infor¬
mation systems throughout the world and,
on the other, to foster the development, in
all countries and at the regional level, of in¬
frastructures, networks and data banks
which will make it possible to handle all the
information needed for scientific,
technological, economic, social or cultural
activities, and lastly to create the necessary
conditions for freer access to the informa¬
tion needed for the progress of the various
peoples.
The new communication and informa¬
tion technologies represent a huge potential
and are opening up unsuspected
possibilities for all countries, and more
especially the developing countries. Any
countries that are unable to avail
themselves amply of these technologies are
in danger of finding themselves on the
fringe in relation to the rest of the world,
and their populations in danger of being
cut off from the mainstream of political,
economic and cultural life.
66
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
The second halfof the twentieth century^,
has been marked by the expansion of the
mass media and the audience available to
them.
Increase 1950-1975 Percentage
Press (Number of copies, daily newspapers)
Radio (Number of receivers) 	
Television (Number of receivers) 	
Books (Number of titles per year)
+ 77
+ 417
+ 3 235
+ 111
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1977.
Media audience increase 1960-1975 Percentage
Total world population	
Daily newspapers (circulation per thousand inhabitants)
Radio receivers (number per thousand inhabitants) 	
Television receivers (number per thousand inhabitants)
Book titles (published annually per million inhabitants)
+ 33
+ 5
+ 95
+ 185
+ 30
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1981.
Press agencies are the major source of in¬
formation to newspapers and to broadcast¬
ers, particularly for foreign news. More
than a hundred countries now have their
own national news agencies.
Among the news agencies there are
five Agence France-Presse (France), As¬
sociated Press (USA), Reuters (UK), Tass
(USSR) and United Press International
(USA) which have a particularly wide in¬
ternational role due to the size and techno¬
logical strength of their systems of collect¬
ing news and distributing it in many lan¬
guages all over the world. Each has offices
in more than a hundred countries, and
employs thousands of full-time staff and
part-time correspondents. They collect
hundreds of thousands of words a day and,
domestic distribution included, transmit
millions of words. Each issues news twenty-
four hours a day to thousands of national
agencies, subscribing newspapers, radio
and television organizations in over a
hundred countries. All have regular ser¬
vices, usually daily, in Arabic, English,
French, German, Portuguese, Russian and
Spanish; some also provide their service in
other languages.
Daily Newspapers. Although circulation
has grown constantly, the worldwide total
of daily newspapers has remained fairly
static for a number of years, due to
mergers, the disappearance of small local
newspapers and competition from radio
and television.
Books. This century has seen a great and
still accelerating increase in book product¬
ion, which can be ascribed to the growth in
the absolute number of literates, advances
in education, the arrival of paperbacks,
improvements in production and distribu¬
tion techniques, and the spread of libraries
and travelling libraries even to remote
places. Between 1955 and 1975, world book
production more than doubled, taking the
number of titles -published annually, and
tripled in the number of copies printed.
Distribution of national news agencies
Africa
Arab
World
Asia Europe
Latin
America
North
America
Oceania
26 18 19 28 11 3 2
Distribution of circulation daily general interest newspapers by continents and major areas: estimated
percentage 1960 and 1979.
Latin America
4.9%
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1981 "Excluding Arab States
Number of book titles published
Continents,
major areas, and 1955 1960 1965 1970 1975 1979
groups of countries -
World total 269 000 332 000 426 000 521 000 568 000 689 000
Africa 3 000 5 000 7 000 8 000 11 000 12 000
America 25 000 35 000 77 000 105 000 121 000 145 000
Asia1 54 000 51 000 61 000 75 000 88 000 139 000
Europe
(including USSR) 186 000 239 000 260 000 317 000 343 000 381 000
Oceania 1 000 2 000 5 000 7 000 5 000 12 000
Developed countries 225 000 285 000 366 000 451 000 480 000 558 000
Developing countries 44 000 47 000 60 000 70 000 88 000 131 000
Africa (excluding
Arab States) 1 600 2 400 4 300 4 600 8 300 9 200
Asia (excluding
Arab States) 53 200 49 900 59 700 73 700 85 800 135 500
Arab States 2 200 3 700 4 000 4 700 4 900 6 300
Northern America 14 000 18 000 58 000 83 000 92 000 112 000
Latin America 11 000 17 000 19 000 22 000 29 000 33 000
Unesco Slalislical Yearbook, 1981.
Distribution of book production by continents and major areas: estimated percentage 1960 and 1979.
1960
Africa
0 7%
Oceania \
0.6%\ /
^:::':::i\m
«::;«:/Pli
Arab States
_1 2%
i/ ÍÍÍK 15.0%
Wmî
wm
mm
(lui Northern
JA America
55Ä 5.4%
Latin America
5-1%
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1 98 1 "Excluding Arab States
67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
Radio. Radio is the most ubiquitous of the
mass media. Latest available estimates indi¬
cate that there are well over one thousand
million radio receivers in use around the
world, i.e. approximately one for every
four people on earth.
Number of radio receivers and receivers per 1,000 inhabitants
Continents,
Major areas and
Groups of countries
Number of radio receivers
Total (millions)
Per 1,000 inhabitants
1965 1970 1975 1979 1965 1970 1975 1979
World total
Africa
America
Asia
Europe
(including USSR)
Oceania
Developed countries
Developing countries
Africa (excluding
Arab States)
Asia (excluding
Arab States)
Arab States
Northern America
Latin America
524
10
285
42
184
3
460
64
6
40
6
251
34
672
16
357
58
233
8
572
100
8
56
10
306
51
931
28
505
108
277
13
770
161
17
102
17
424
81
1 140
35
581
169
335
19
924
216
22
161
22
476
105
207
33
619
39
273
189
449
42
24
39
59
1 173
138
241
45
701
48
341
428
533
58
31
48
83
1 353
180
303
70
900
80
380
606
687
83
55
77
120
1 793
249
336
77
964
108
450
863
801
97
63
106
144
1 951
252
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1981.
Data for: World total, Asia, Developing countries and Asia (excluding Arab States) do not Include China
Distribution of radio receivers by continents and major areas: estimated percentage 1960 and 1979.
Afnca*
0 5%
1960 l Arab States 1979
Oceania \ I n ?°'° # Oceania
0 8% \ I 1 6%
Africa
1 9%
A ab States
/ 1 9%
Asia*
14 1%
Unesco Siattsucal Yearbook, 1981 Arab States
Television. The age of television dawned in
1936 when France and the United Kingdom
began regular transmission ofprogrammes.
By 1950, five countries had a regular TV
service and by 1955 the number was 17.
This figure had increasedfourfold by 1960.
A decade later, more than J 00 countries
were transmitting television programmes.
Number of television receivers and receivers per 1,000 inhabitants
Continents,
Major areas and
groups of countries
Number of television receivers
Total (millions)
Per 1,000 inhabitants
1965 1970 1975 1979 1965 1970 1975 1979
World total 181 266 374 471 72 96 122 139
Africa 0.6 1.2 2.5 6.7 1.9 3.4 6.2 15
America 84 109 160 188 182 214 285 311
Asia 19 27 37 50 18 22 27 32
Europe
(including USSR) 75 125 169 219 132 196 241 294
Oceania 2.4 3.5 5.5 6.5 137 200 258 295
Developed countries 170 244 334 407 166 227 298 353
Developing countries 11 22 40 64 7.3 13 21 29
Africa (excluding
Arab States) 0.1 0.3 0.6 3.3 0.4 1.1 2.0 9.4
Asia (excluding
Arab States) 19 26 36 47 18 22 27 31
Arab States 0.9 1.9 3.4 6.4 8.4 15 24 42
Northern America 76 92 133 151 355 407 562 619
Latin America 8 17 27 37 32 60 83 103
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1981
Dala for: World total, Asia. Developing countries, and Asia (excluding Arab States) do not include China.
Distribution of television receivers by continents and major areas: estimated percentage 1960 and 1979.
Oceania
1,4%
Africa"
0 7%
Arab States
1 3%
Asia*
Latin America
3
Unesco Statistical Yearbook, 1 98 1 'Excluding Arab States
68
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
Nobel laureates speak out
Jean Dausset Pyotr Kapitsa
ERADICATION of contempt for others and the
teaching of the vital importance of the differences
that exist between men are unquestionably among
the great imperatives of our time, indeed of all time.
It so happened that the day on which I heard that I had
been awarded the Nobel Prize was Mutual Tolerance
Day. I was struck by this coincidence because at the
same time that I had been explaining to journalists the
advantages of biological diversity I had also been stress¬
ing the benefits of cultural diversity.
Variations between individuals are essential if a species
is to be able to adapt to modifications in its environment
and to perpetuate itself despite the various hazards to
which it is subject. Thanks to even a very subtle
biological difference, one individual will survive an
epidemic to which another will succumb. Now, with
the exception of identical twins, no two individuals are,
or ever will be, exactly the same. Each human being is
unique.
The future of our species, its ability to adapt and to
evolve biologically is dependent upon the careful preser¬
vation of this diversity. Uniformity would lead to decline,
degeneracy and death. The notion of a "pure race" is thus
biological nonsense. In the same way, the cultural evolu¬
tion of humanity depends upon jealous preservation of
the intellectual diversity of individuals and ethnic groups.
This diversity has enabled mankind to adapt to the most
varied and harshest conditions and it will enable humani¬
ty to adapt to new structures, especially to the new social
and economic structures imposed by modern technology.
Freedom of thought and opinion, freedom of religious
practice, are simply the expression of individual diversity.
They are the leaven of ferment of a humanity ever on the
march. Here too uniformity would be equivalent to death.
I am not too happy with the word "tolerance" because
it has the connotation of a kind of rejection only over¬
come with difficulty, with a rather grudging resignation.
The differences we see in others should not be simply
tolerated, they should be accepted, encouraged and
cultivated in full knowledge of the inestimable riches
they offer.
Professor Jean Dausset, of the University ofParis, was awarded the 1980
Nobel Prize for Physiology and Medicine for work on genetically determi¬
ned structures on the cell surface which regulate immunological reac¬
tion';
TODAY'S world problems con¬
front science with a set of
new challenges, the most im¬
portant of which are:
the study of "qualitative" changes
in the population and their relations
with the social structure;
the safe use of nuclear power as a
basic energy source and above all
the development of controlled ther¬
monuclear fusion;
the devising of closed cycles,
especially in the field of agro-
technology;
the study of the earth's heat
balance and of environmental pollu¬
tion.
We only have a limited time,
perhaps a century, to solve all these
problems which exist on a planetary
scale.
A State's participation in the solu¬
tion of world problems is dependent
on the nature of its society and on
the ideology which is the bedrock of
its political life. At the present time,
eminent economists believe that on¬
ly the socialist States will be in a
position to take action, for the
undertaking is one that calls for very
strict control of the country's
economy.
Thus appropriate scientific re¬
search is today urgently needed. It
must be carried out before the crisis
comes to a head. The best minds
must take part in this effort and ac¬
cordingly they must be organized on
an international scale and be provid¬
ed with the facilities they need.
It is well known that under the pre¬
sent organization of production
scarcely one third of the population
of the developed countries is involv¬
ed in activities of vital importance to
the country as a whole. The lion's
share of surplus productive forces is
essentially devoted to military spend¬
ing and to the maintenance of armed
forces which do not participate in
productive work. For all these coun¬
tries, in short, military spending is
much higher than the research
budget. It would seem reasonable to
channel a part of these resources,
however small, and above all the in¬
tellectual potential engaged in the
preparation of military programmes,
to the organization of scientific
research for the solution of world
problems. This would not have any
repercussions on the budget and
would not cause an increase in
unemployment since employment in
industry would be maintained, simp¬
ly being directed to different objec¬
tives.
At a time of growing international
co-operation it is to be hoped that
such measures will'be taken and that
reason will win the day. But for this
to come about, the problems must
be formulated clearly and convinc¬
ingly and be the object of wide
public debate. It is up to the scien¬
tists to shoulder this task for they
have an authority which enables
them to envisage the possibility of
solving major world problems in a
way that will benefit humanity as a
whole. Hence scientists should not
keep social problems at arm's
length; they must be aware of the
close connexion between these pro¬
blems and scientific activity.
Academician Pyotr Kapitsa, of the Institute for
Physical Problems of the USSR Academy of
Sciences, Moscow, was awarded the 1978
Nobel Prize for Physics for basic inventions and
discoveries in low-temperature physics.
Asian writers and cultural identity
An Asian Writers Forum, organised, by Unesco with the collaboration of the Asian Federation of
Unesco Clubs and Associations, was held in Tokyo and Kyoto from 11 to 18 April 1982. The theme of
the Forum, which was attended by eleven leading writers from nine countries, was "Cultural Identity:
an Asian Viewpoint and Perspective. " The work of the meeting, thefirst of its kind, concluded with the
unanimous adoption ofthefollowing Declaration, which reflects the consensus reached by these writers
from widely different backgrounds.
We, eleven writers from nine countries of Asia
assembled in Tokyo and Kyoto, Japan, from 12
to 16 April, 1982, in the Asian Writers Forum
sponsored by Unesco and the Asian Federation
of Unesco Clubs and Associations,
recognize that Cultural Identity is a dynamic
process, not "being" but "becoming"; that it is
in evolution, since everything is under constant
change. The traditional wisdom is re-discovered
and breathes new life into the process of cultural
evolution;
hold that the cultural identity of any nation or
community must be inclusive of the culture of
the silent and the voiceless and especially of the
minorities, which is expressed not only through
the verbal but also oral, visual and performing
manifestations;
agree that the authentic writer is essentially
revolutionary, not necessarily in the political
sense, but in the sense that he moves ahead of his
time;
are aware of the challenges of modernism and
recognize that technology is a component of
culture; the development of science and
technology, therefore, should be based on
respective indigenous cultures. Education,
whether formal or non-formal, in this context,
plays a crucial role. Education should be so
structured as to reconcile scientific attitudes with
cultural sensitivity:
believe that Asia could make a distinctive con¬
tribution to world culture through the widely-
shared concept of man ideally in harmony with
nature and the community, where all existence
assumes co-existence, where man is defined as
"we" rather than "I", where substance of being
is "relation" as manifested in various ways in
Asian languages; and through its original con¬
cepts of Time and Space;
confirm that every language has a right to digni¬
ty, for it is the articulation of the world view of a
people;
affirm that the world of today and tomorrow
should be enriched and made secure through ac
ceptance of cultural plurality and through con¬
stant dialogue between cultures emphasizing
their unity in diversity;
note that Japan, the host of this Forum, pro¬
vides an example of assimilation of various
cultural trends throughout its history while
preserving its identity which is simultaneously
permanent and dynamic;
appreciate that this kind of Forum has been
organized for the first time under the auspices of
Unesco; and
urge Unesco and all National Commissions for
Unesco of Asian Member States vigorously to
promote cultural exchange and to take special
and urgent steps to encourage, support and
sponsor direct translations from one Asian
language to another;
declare that, as writers, we shall do our best to
promote dialogue and mutual understanding
between all nations.
Kyoto, 17 April, 1982
Ai Qing, Mohammad Ajmal Makhdum, Ashok
Vajpeyi, Vasit Dejkunjorn, Faiz Ahmed Faiz,
Yasushi Inoue, Nick Joaquin, Takeo Kuwabara,
Phan Tu, Tide Said Sadikun, Harischandra Wi-
jetunga.
69
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
<^Z^ei/i/íetd &
EVOLUTION FROM SPACE
Sir,
For over twelve years I have been a
subscriber to your magazine which has
taught me many things about a wide variety
of subjects.
I thought your May 1982 issue on Darwin
was particularly interesting, especially the
article by Chandra Wickramasinghe, "An
Astronomer Reflects: Was Darwin Wrong?"
Could you tell me whether the two books
mentioned in his biographical note, Space
Travellers: the bringers of life and Evolution
from Space, have been translated into
French?
Odette Valle
Paris, France
Sir,
I found the article in the May 1982 issue of
the Unesco Courier by Chandra Wickrama¬
singhe extremely interesting. However, I
have tried everywhere without success to
find the books he has written: Space
Travellers: the bringers of life and Evolution
from Space. Can you please let me know
where I can obtain these books?
F. Robin
Fontenay-sous-Bois, France
Our May issue on Darwin, and Professor
Wickramasinghe's article in particular, seems to
have aroused great interest among many of our
readers. Unfortunately, none of Professor
Wickramasinghe's books ¡written in conjunction
with Sir Fred Hoyle) has yet been translated,
although a Japanese version of Space Travellers
is now in preparation. They are obtainable in
English as follows: Lifecloud: the origins of life in
the universe (1978), price £6.95, Diseases from
Space (1979) price £6.95, and Evolution from
Space 11981), price £7.95, available from
J.M. Dent and Sons Ltd., 33, Welbeck Street,
London, WIM 8LX; Space Travellers: the
bringers of life 11981) price £8.95, available from
University College of Cardiff Press, P.O. Box 78,
Cardiff, CF1 1XL. Money should be sent with
orders adding ten per cent forpostage Editor.
SACRED EFFIGY
OR POTTER'S MOULD?
Sir,
On page 2 of the January issue of the
Unesco Courier you published a very fine
photograph of a "Mayan mushroom-stone"
with a caption that implied that this type of
mushroom was known to be hallucinogenic.
I would just like to point out that it is
deplorable that an affirmation, unsupported
by a single serious archaeological finding,
should be very widely accepted whereas a
hypothesis which, as research stands at pre¬
sent, offers more solid guarantees of being
correct is almost totally ignored.
As far as I know, the only really scien¬
tifically thought out theory, based on solid
facts and without serious contradictions, is
that put forward by Ulrich Köhler in
American Antiquity, Volume 41, No. 2 of
April 1976, in which he states that the pre-
Columbian mushroom stones are potter's
moulds.
Without going deeply into Köhler's argu¬
ment, I should like to bring out one or two
salient points.
is there even the slightest proof that a
sacred mushroom cult ever existed? No. For
the Indians, hallucinogenic mushrooms
were (and still are) a means of divination;
there is nothing to indicate that the
mushrooms themselves were ever regarded
as divine. The absence of any form of
veneration of the mushrooms used in the
divination rituals clearly runs counter to any
attempt to class mushroom-stones as idols,
since the creation of effigies logically
presupposes that the effigies concerned
would be treated with at least a certain
minimum of veneration.
Henri Broch
University of Nice, France
In his latest book Aux Sources du
Futur Unesco's Director-General,
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, pro¬
vides a synthesis of today's major
worldproblems: the arms race, hunger
which afflicts millions of human be¬
ings, the impact of certain human ac¬
tivities on the natural environment.
While stressing that these are global
challenges which may threaten the
very existence of humanity, he does
not overlook the repeated breaches of
human rights and the liberty of
peoples, the persistent inequalities bet¬
ween individuals and between
societies, and the marked injustices
which characterize certain aspects of
international relations.
But as the title indicates,
Mr. M'Bow does more than simply
isolate these fundamental problems
and others such as those posed by new
developments in science and
technology, communication between
men and between cultures, education
and cultural identity. Turning to the
future, he also outlines solutions, sug¬
gests an order ofpriorities, and, final¬
ly, proposes for the Organization he
leads, in accordance with the goals set
out in its Constitution, a number of
tasks for the years 1985-1989. The
authorpoints out that, in keeping with
its mission, Unesco is at one and the
same time an "observatory" and a
"think tank". It should break new
ground in the eradication of illiteracy,
the democratization of education and
the media, the free flow of knowledge
and know-how, the advancement of
science, the storage of information,
and the renewal of values for the ad¬
vancement of the cause of peace and
human rights.
In a world in which selfish interests
too often obscure the general interest
of humanity and in which many
specialists cultivate their own garden
without concern for their neighbours,
this clear-sighted, panoramic and
timely work deserves to be read by all
who are anxious about the direction in
which humanity is moving today.
* To be published in English later this
year ; provisional title: Where the Future
Begins.
The UNESCO COURIER Is published monthly (11
issues a year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted
from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and
three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed ar¬
ticles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited
manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by
an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
(Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva
(Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Lim Moun-Young (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es- Salaam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
70
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
More than enough? is the first title to appear in Unesco's new
Sextant series, which is designed to present specialist thinking
on pressing human issues to a wide spectrum of readers.
183 pages - 48 French francs
Just published
Is the world exhausting its energy
supplies? Will there be enough to
go round as the planet's
population rises from 4,000
million to 6,000 million or more
during the next 20 years? In More
than enough? An optimistic
assessment of world energy, over
a dozen authoritative bodies and
experts set out to answer these
and other vital questions. An
easy-to-read, illustrated analysis
of world energy supplies, the
book discusses the different
options available to produce more
energy and outlines the strategies
required to formulate a new
world energy policy.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066, Publications Educational Supplies Pty Ltd
P O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals Dominie Pty
Subscriptions Dept , P O Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agenf United Nations Association of Australia, P 0 Box 175,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. - AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-101 I.Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books Internatio¬
nal Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca
3 - BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd , 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P 0 Box 88, Beijing - CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch¬
bishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S N T.L , Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR - DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10, Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaa-
rankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GER¬
MAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140,
710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G D R - FED REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier
(German, English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, ßasaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag,
Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps only: Geo Center,
Postfach 800830. Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd , P O Box 195, Accra: Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P.O Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra, The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom - HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co , 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong Kong Government Information Services, Publication Cen¬
tre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Konyvesbolt, Váci u 22, Budapest V, A K.V. Konyvturosok
Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co , H F , Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2, B-3/7 Asaf Ah Road, New Delhi 1 ,
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 Sub-Depots Oxford Book &
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016, Scindia House,
New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture,
Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi
110001 INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers,
29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta, Gramedia Bookshop, Jl.
Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta, Indira P T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie
37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribu¬
tion Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran, Iranian Nat Comm for Unesco, Ave Iran-
chahr Chomali No 300, B P. 1533, Teheran - IRAQ. McKen¬
zies Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad - IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd , Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12 - ISRAEL. ABC. Bookstore Ltd ,
P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA.
Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston. JAPAN Eastern Book Service Inc , Shuhwa
Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-ku,
Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier
Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P 0. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.,
P O Box 286, Monrovia LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P O Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg
MALAYSIA University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd , 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis - MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo - NETHERLANDS. For
periodicals only: Dekker and Nordemann NV, P.O. Box 197,
1000 AD Amsterddam, for publications only KEESING BOEKEN
B V., Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N V., P O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao N.A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Of¬
fice, Government Bookshops at. Rutland Street, P 0. Box 5344,
Auckland, 130, Oxford Terrace, P O Box 1721 Chnstchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton, Princes Street, P O Box
1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA The University Bookshop of Ife, The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P O. 286, The University Bookshop of
Nsukka, The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana NORWAY. All publications
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1, Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3 For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-l-azam, P 0 Box No 729, Lahore 3.
- PHILIPPINES The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P O Box 632, Manila D-404 - POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac
Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przed-
miescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW - PORTUGAL. Dias & An¬
drade Ltda Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES National Bookshop, P.O Box 48, Mahé, New
Service Ltd , Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé -
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S I Pte Ltd , No 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P 0. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications- Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty ) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only Central News agency, P O. Box 1033, Johannesburg
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gar¬
diner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.*- SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum, - SWEDEN. All publica¬
tions A/B CE Fntzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan
12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16 For the Unesco Courier
Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65,
Stockholm - SWITZERLAND. All publications Europa
Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1211, Geneva 11, C C P 12-236 - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, P.O B. 9030 Dares-Salaam. - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair,
Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A S , Istiklâl Cad-
desi. No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGAN¬
DA Uganda Bookshop, P O Box 7145, Kampala. - UNITED
KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P O Box 669, London,
SEI, and Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps
only McCarta Ltd , 122 King's Cross Road, London WC1X
9 DS. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
G-200 - YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11.
Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana, Nolit,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. - ZIMBABWE Textbook Sales
(PVTI Ltd , 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
POWER
OF THE WORD
]]>
</page>
</document>
