<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074776eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window
open on the world
-
%&
Medicine's ygreen revolution'
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Adrian Bodek, Mexico
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
©
Mexico
The swinging Totonacs
Apprehension rather than appreciation seems to be the expression caught by the sculptor
of these solemn-faced Totonac girls as they sit on a swing dressed in their best skirts and
rounded quechquemitl capes and adorned with disc earrings and necklaces. Dating from
between 500 and 750 AD, this hollow figurine, from Veracruz, Mexico, is a relic of the
Middle-American Totonac civilization. The Totonacs, an offshoot of the Huastecs, are
believed to have built the famous Pyramid of Niches at El Tajin.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco (~V)UFÍCF
JULY 1979 32nd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must :
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (31 Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Thé Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam).
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
Avicenna
HEARTS AND FLOWERS
by Hakim Mohammed Said
6 MEDICINAL PLANTS MAKE A COMEBACK
by Michel A. Attisso
8 MEDICINE'S 'GREEN REVOLUTION'
by Jean-Marie Pelt
17 AFRICAN MEDICINAL PLANTS
UNDER THE MICROSCOPE
by Donald £ U. Ekong
19 UNESCO AND THE BASIC CHEMISTRY
OF NATURAL PRODUCTS
20 A MEDICAL THESAURUS
FROM THE ROOF OF THE WORLD
by Lydia Khundanova
21 FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
25 CHINA : A NEW MEDICINE BORN OF TRADITION
by Wei Wen
29 NEPTUNE'S PHARMACOPOEIA
by Mario Piattelli
33 MEXICAN PLANTS AND HUMAN FERTILITY
by Pierre Crabbé
35 PLANT PROPHYLACTICS FROM TROPICAL BRAZIL
by Otto R. Gottlieb and Walter B. Mors
38 HERBAL THERAPY IN THE WAR ON DRUG ADDICTION
39 BULGARIA'S FOLK REMEDIES STAND THE TEST OF TIME
by Vesselin Petkov
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
MEXICO: The swinging Totonacs
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
»íM^M'^y^íív
Photo © V. Shumakov, Russian edition
of the Unesco Courier,
Moscow Buryat Department
Siberian section of the USSR
Academy of Sciences
Cover
The discovery in plants of active substances
which, in themselves or after further
chemical transformation, have powerful
therapeutic effects has led to what might be
termed a "green revolution" in medicine. In
many cases, chemists are finding scientific
confirmation of the healing properties of
plants traditionally used in popular medicine.
Taken from the Atlas of Indo-Tibetan
Medicine (see article page 20), our cover
photo, published here for the first time ever,
represents the "Tree of Therapy". The left
hand stem, the "stem of nutrition",
represents dietary treatments for various
illnesses; the second stem from the left, the
"stem of the way of life", recommends
appropriate life styles for patients; the third
stem, "the stem of medicines", demonstrates
the properties of various medicines; the
fourth stem, the "stem of corrigents",
illustrates acupuncture, massage and surgical
operations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Avicenna
Hearts and flowers
Type of plant: Rosa Damascena (red
damask rose)"Owing to its aromatic
volatile matter, it resembles the vital
spirit in temperament. Used to cure un¬
consciousness and fainting, especially
when these are due to hot abnormal
temperament."
Avicenna (980 to 1037 AD),
Treatise on Cardiac Drugs
"Flower buds are astringent and are us¬
ed in cardiac troubles, and as a tonic
and aperient. Rose water prepared
from the petals is said to have a cooling
effect."
The Wealth of India, Volume IX (1972)
DESPITE the tremendous scientific
advances that have been made in
the close on one thousand years
that separate the Treatise on Cardiac
Drugs, written by the great Islamic
physician-philosopher-scientist Avicenna,
from the late twentieth century inventory
of India's natural resources, The Wealth of
India, little has changed in the scientific
assessment of the medicinal properties of
the red damask rose. Indeed, Avicenna's
evaluation of many of the sixty-four cardiac
drugs mentioned in his Treatise closely
resemble the assessment made by modern
scientists.
Divided into seventeen sections, the
treatise explains the psychological and
physiological basis of the principles of
treatment of cardiac patients together with
the action of the relevant drugs. The left
human ventricle is mentioned as the place
of origin and repository of the cardiac soul
which is the vehicle of animal faculties of all .
organs of the body. Illustrating further he
says that when the cardiac soul reaches the
brain it acquires such a temperament there
that it becomes capable or receiving the
faculties of sensation and movement and
when it reaches the liver it acquires there
such a temperament as is capable of receiv-
HAKIM MOHAMMED SAID, of Pakistan, is
adviser on traditional Islamic medicine to the
Pakistan Ministry of Health, Social Welfare and
Population Planning. President of the Hamda: i
National Foundation, he is editor of the journal
Hamdard, the organ of the Institute of Health
and Tibbi Research. He is also editor of the Urdu
edition of the Unesco Courier.
ing the faculties of nourishment and
growth. Similarly on reaching the
reproductive organs it acquires such a
temperament as to befit it to accept the
faculties of procreation.
Proceeding further Avicenna mentions
that the cardiac soul is particularly affected
by and reacts to emotions such as
pleasure, sorrow, -fear, etc. This means
that the heart is the place where emotions
make themselves felt. But the organ which
reacts to them and the faculty of reacting
to stimuli is possessed by all individuals but
in different degrees.
Recording his findings about sensation
he says that it is dependent on the dif¬
ference or changes between, the perceiv¬
ing organ and the object of perception.
When this difference is lost, the perception
of it also disappears. This, according to
him, is illustrated by the feeling of discom¬
fort experienced in fever and the indif¬
ference of a tubercular patient to his raised
temperature. Discussing these points in
detail he holds that sick persons are not
capable of enjoyment because of the
temperamental imbalance of the soul.
Similarly old persons or those who have ex¬
cess of black bile, whose soul is thick,
coarse and dark are incapable of enjoying
themselves.
Later in the Treatise he discusses the
physiological causes of the capacity for en¬
joyment or grief and suggests measures for
creating this capacity. He distinguishes
between the weakness of the heart and dis¬
quietude which is felt as a pressure on the
chest. He discusses the relation between
qualities of blood and soul and analyses the
difference between anger or malice and the
mode of action by virtue of which cardiac
medicines produce exhilaration. He states
that the soul is instrinsically attracted
towards fragrant and sweet substances
and describes the meanings of the words
temperament, property and the action of
DORONICUM HOOKERI
Idoronicuml
"Its action as a cardiac tonic and
exhilarant is extraordinary. "
(Avicenna)
"Used as an aromatic tonic. Some
species are reported to prevent
giddiness during high-altitude
mountain ascents. The roots of the
European species are used as a
constituent of cardiac and nerve
tonics."
(The Wealth of India, Vol. Ill)
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
ROSA DAMASCENA (red damask rose)
Photos and drawings © H. Said, Karachi, Pakistan
by Hakim Mohammed Saïd
substances. He also explains the occasion
and the aim of using drugs and ends by giv¬
ing prescriptions which he himself found
useful.
Thus a careful and critical study of the
whole Treatise gives an insight into the
mode of treatment of cardiac patients with
drugs, diet and environmental adjustment.
It is therefore worth scientific study so that
humanity may reap the benefit from the
researches of the past in the curative
sciences.
OCIMUM BASILICUM (sweet basil)
"Contains volatile matter; acts as an astringent and an exhilarant; has a
warming effect. "
(Avicenna)
"Diuretic; useful in diseases of the heart and brain, chronic pain in the joints,
asthma and enlarged spleen."
(Indian Medicinal Plants, Vol. Ill, 1962)
MELISSA OFFICINALIS (lemon balm, sweet balm)
"Regarded as an extraordinary drug which exhilarates and strengthens the
heart. "
(Avicenna)
"A cardiac tonic also used as a gargle for sore throat."
	 (Indian Materia Medica. Vol.1. 1954)
See also next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
HEARTS AND FLOWERS (continued)
CROCUS SATIVUS (saffron)
"Tones the vital system and exhilarates;
produces a sense of luminosity, brilliance
and well-being; regarded as a cardiac tonic. "
(Avicenna)
"Stimulant, aphrodisiac and stomachic;
slightly anodyne and anti-spasmodic; in over¬
dose it is a narcotic poison; owing to its
essential oils it stimulates the central ner¬
vous system."
(Indian Materia Medica, Vol.1)
ONOSMA BRACTEATUM
"As a cardiac stimulant and exhilarant it is a drug of
choice. "
(Avicenna)
"Used as a tonic, alterative, demulcent, diuretic
aod refrigerant; also reported to be useful as a
spasmolytic."
(The Wealth of India, Vol. VII)
CITRUS MEDICA (limette)
"Citron is also a cardiac tonic and re¬
garded as a useful remedy for cardiac neurosis
and palpitation." ,A .
(Avicenna)
"Fruit is expellent of poisons; pulp is aromatic,
stomachic, bitter; rind is aromatic, stimulant,
tonic and anti-scorbutic; distilled water of the
fruit is sedative, refrigerant and digestive."
(Indian Materia Medica, Vol.1)
LAVANDULA STOECHAS (Roman lavender)
"An exhilarant and cardiac tonic; purifies the intel¬
lectual faculties of the mind. "
(Avicenna)
"In Eastern medicine it is known as the 'broom of
the brain'; strengthens the brain; it is a good
stimulant, aromatic, general carminative,
diaphoretic, expectorant and anti-spasmodic."
(Indian Materia Medica, Vol. I)
Photos and drawings © H. Saïd, Karachi, Pakistan
KOREAN SCHIZANDRA
Used in traditional medicine as a tonic and an ana¬
leptic, as a remedy for coughs and shortness of
breath, and to improve eyesight. In modern medi¬
cine: lessens fatigue and is used as a preventive
against senility and arteriosclerosis; contains active
vitamin F and vitamin E.
Photo © Permanent Delegation to Unesco of the
Democratic People's Republic of Korea
by Michel A. Attisso
MICHEL A. ATTISSO, of Togo, is director and
pharmacist of the University Hospital Cen¬
tre and professor at the Faculty of Pharmacy,
Montpellier University, France, where earlier he
had been a student. Before returning to Mont¬
pellier he taught for twelve years at the Faculty
of Medicine and Pharmacy of Dakar University,
Senegal. He is a consultant to the World Health
Organization and was formerly vice-chairman of
the International Narcotics Control Board of the
United Nations Economic and Social Council.
Right, mountain herbs and plants are
identified, cleaned and cut before being
sent to a drug processing factory at
Kanzikode, India. In collaboration with
the Indian Council of Medical Research,
the World Health Organization (WHO) has
initiated a four-year scientific study on the
therapeutic qualities of Ayurveda, the
traditional Indian healing system based on
homeopathy and naturopathy. In April
1979, as part of its programme on
traditional medicine, WHO held a meeting
in Rome on research and training in
traditional systems of medicine in
developing countries with particular
reference to medicinal plants and herbs
The meeting called for the creation of a
task force for the organization of
traditional medicine programmes in
Africa, including the establishment of
training facilities for young African
scientists, botanical gardens for medicinal
plants, and provisions for testing
traditional therapies.
Photo A. Kochar © WHO, Geneva
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Medicinal plants
make a comeback
PHYTOTHERAPY, the treatment of
illnesses by pharmaceutical prepa¬
rations based on vegetable drugs,
was the mainstay of the therapeutic arsenal
until the mid-nineteenth century. This prac¬
tice gradually gave way to the use of
medicines produced fror; pure molecules
of the active ingredients of medicinal plants
which had a more specific or precise phar¬
macological activity. Thus medicinal plants
to some extent faded away into oblivion
and were replaced by treatments using
wholly or partly synthesized chemical
substances.
In recent years, there have been un¬
mistakable signs that phytotherapy is mak¬
ing a come-back. Statistics from the Inter¬
national Centre: of Commerce show that
medicinal plants have lost none of their im¬
portance despite the constantly increasing
use of chemotherapy, the treatment of
disease by chemical substances. The pro¬
portions of medicinal plants used in the
preparation of pharmaceutical products in
the world today is about one-third that of
synthetic chemical substances.
The global value of imports of raw
materials of plant origin destined for the
pharmaceutical and cosmetic industries
soared from $52.9 million in 1967 to $71.2
million in 1971, with an annual progression
of some 7 per cent since then.
The annual quantities of some of the
drugs consumed world-wide since 1974 in
the form of pharmaceutical preparations
are as follows: 3,000 tonnes of aloes;
10,000 tonnes of fresh artichoke leaves;
5,000 tonnes of quinquina bark; 1,000 ton¬
nes of belladonna, henbane and datura
leaves ; 5,000 tonnes of senna pods ; 1 ,000
tonnes of digitalis leaves.
In addition, it has been estimated that in
1974 the industrialized countries consumed
in the form of infusions : 150 tonnes of lime
blossom; 250 tonnes of mint; 100 tonnes
of camomile; 200 tonnes of vervain; 30
tonnes of orange blossom; 30 tonnes of
Chinese anise; and 45 tonnes of eucalyp¬
tus.
These figures alone should be enough to
show that there is a renewed interest in
medicinal plants, inspired neither by
charlatanry nor by any modish desire to
return to nature. To understand the
underlying reasons for this phenomenon
we must look elsewhere.
An understanding of the distinction, ig¬
nored by many people, between medicinal
plants and vegetable drugs, may help to ex¬
plain why medicinal plants are today enjoy- k
ing a new lease of life. f
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
, A medicinal plant is one which contains
in one or several of its organs substances
that can be used directly for medicinal pur¬
poses or in chemical and pharmaceutical
semi-synthesis, while the term vegetable
drug refers to that part of the medicinal
plant used directly in the preparation of
medicines.
As raw materials, medicinal plants are
vital as a source of pure molecules which,
. though not medicines themselves, can be
used for the partial synthesis of phar¬
macologically active derivatives. This is
notably the case of various kinds of aloes,
agaves and dioscorea which contain
steroids that can be used in the partial syn¬
thesis of cortico-steroids (hormones
secreted by the outer region of the adrenal
glands) and their derivatives, of progesta¬
tional substances and oral contraceptives.
Through their active ingredients,
medicinal plants also constitute ideal
models for pharmaceutical research.
Substitutions and artificial mutations of
natural molecules have enabled new kinds
of medicines and more specific phar¬
maceutical products to be obtained. Ex¬
amples include the synthetic local pain¬
killers which have been derived from the
cocaine molecule, medicines used in the
treatment of high blood pressure, and
derivatives of the alkaloids found in the
roots of the Rauwolfia plant.
Finally, when medicinal plants have been
picked and checked for quality, parts of
them or their secretions can be used as
vegetable drugs in phytotherapeutic
preparations. In this form they are, either
prescribed in addition to specific
chemotherapy or as major medication for
certain ailments, especially psychosomatic
complaints, various cardio-vascular
diseases (including high blood pressure
and certain kinds of heart disease where
there are no organic lesions), digestive
troubles, disorders of the liver and gall¬
bladder, and as antiseptics for internal and
external use. "Aromatherapy", for exam¬
ple, (treatment using preparations with a
base of essential oils of medicinal plants)
has made great strides in the last five years.
It is likely that these trends will continue
to grow in the next few years. The scien¬
tific study of medicinal plants in developing
countries will provide new molecules that
will directly enrich the present range of
medicines or provide a basis for further
chemical and pharmacological research.
Michel A. Attisso
Medicine's
green
revolution'
by Jean-Marie Pelt
ALL over the world, a revival of interest in medicinal plants is
making itself keenly felt. Anxiety concerning the excesses
of industrial civilizations and the threats which they pose
to physical and mental health is leading more and more men and
women to seek herbal remedies for their suffering and illness, in a
movement of reconciliation with nature.
At the dawn of history, when the first glimmerings of knowledge
began to pierce the darkness of men's ignorance, both the
therapeutic and the toxic properties of plants were subjects of
In a factory at Kottakal, 'India,
medicines are prepared
according to the precepts of
Ayurveda, the classical system
of Indian medical science.
Traditional Ayurvedic remedies
use herbs carefully selected on
the basis of a highly elaborate
theory which takes into
account the taste of the plants
and their heat-giving
properties. Ayurveda, which
literally means the Science of
Life, was once widely
practised in Asia and is today
enjoying a revival. Faithful to
Indian traditions. Ayurvedic
healers look at the mind and
body as a whole before
prescribing the appropriate
remedy for a disease.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
equal interest. Sorcerers, "medicine men" and witch doctors were
as familiar with poisons as with cures, and this knowledge gave
them an aura of supernatural authority.
In its turn, modern medical science has been enriched by the in¬
vestigation of plants that were known to primitive societies. Thus
the poisonous seed of a West African climbing plant, the calabar
bean, once used in trial by ordeal, today yields the drug known as
eserine, which contracts the pupil of the eye.
Another modern drug, the powerful heart stimulant ouabain, is
obtained from the Strophantus plant of tropical Africa and Asia,
used to poison arrows for hunting and war. Curare, another arrow-
tip poison, used by the Indians of Amazonia, is applied in modern
surgeryand abdominal surgery in particular to produce
muscular relaxation.
But how were these plants persuaded to part with their secrets ?
Doubtless as the result of a lengthy process of trial and error, dur¬
ing which manwhose very existence was intimately bound up
with natural processes and whose survival depended on endless
stratagems had to learn to recognize and distinguish between
plants which were useful and plants which might do him harm,
plants which might be used as food and plants which might cure
his illnesses, and plants which were capable of killing him.
JEAN-MARIE PELT, of France, is professor of plant biology and the
science of drugs at the University of Metz. Chairman of the Administrative
Council of the European Institute of Ecology, Metz, he has undertaken a
number of research and teaching missions in Africa and Asia. He has
published several works, both scientific and of general interest, including:
Evolution et Sexualité des Plantes (Evolution and sexuality ofplants), 1970,
Drogues et Plantes Magiques (Magic drugs and plants), 1971, and
l'Homme Re-naturé (Man's links with nature renewed), 1977.
At a later stage in history, this accumulated knowledge found
expression in a number of theories which may give rise to smiles
today, the most widespread of which was certainly the so-called
"doctrine of signatures".
According to this doctrine, every medicinal plant Indicates by a
sign its healing properties. "Everything that Nature creates",
wrote the Swiss physician Paracelsus in the sixteenth century, "is
shaped in the image of the virtue she intends to conceal therein".
Thus, plants which secrete the milky substance known as latex will
serve to prepare medicines that stimulate lactation. If this latex is
yellowish in colour, as in the case of the celandine, the plant is
considered helpful in the treatment of jaundice.
Fleshy plants put flesh on human bones. The shape of the
walnut is a sign of its usefulness as a medicine for brain diseases,
while that of the bean predestines it as a treatment for kidney com¬
plaints. This "therapy by analogies", developed by Arab physi¬
cians and the medieval alchemists, was in direct opposition to the
theories of Hippocrates and of Galen, whose famous aphorism
Contraria contrariis curantur lay at the foundations of a "therapy
by opposites".
Beliefs of this kind, which are found among the traditional
healers of Africa, the physicians of China and the empiricists of
South America alike, would appear to reflect a characteristic, "pre-
scientific" stage in the development of knowledge.
At first sight, the doctrine of signatures may provoke amuse¬
ment. It is difficult to believe that the leaves of the lungwort are a
remedy for chest diseases, just because their vein structure
resembles that of the air-cells in the lung ; that saxifrage (from the
Latin saxum, a stone, and frángete, to break) splits gallstones as
effectively as the rocks in whose crevices it grows ; or that bamboo
stems help to strengthen the spine because their knotty excrescen- v
ces resemble vertebrae. Y
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
> On the other hand, the uncontested virtues of such present-day
drugs as colchicine and aspirin seem to confirm this doctrine,
which in reality constitutes a means of committing to memory, by
means of "signs" and in civilizations which do not keep written
records, the remedies which medical experience has shown to be
efficient.
If the corm of the Colchicum or meadow saffron is shaped like a
gout-swollen toe, the extract which it yields, colchicine, is in fact
the only effective treatment for this painful affliction. And as for
aspirin, its story is worth telling as an example of the evolving rela¬
tionship between traditional plant medicine and modern phar¬
macology.
The origins of this drug are to be found in the bark of the willow,
a tree of the genus Salix, which usually grows in watery places and
is only truly happy when its feet are wet. According to the doctrine
of signatures, this indicates that the willow does not catch cold,
and that it should thus be capable of curing feverish chills,
rheumatic pains and similar conditions. And since it is the bark of
the willow that keeps it well wrapped up and warm, it is here that
one may expect to find the active property in question.
In the eighteenth century, willow-bark was found to be com¬
parable in its bitterness to the bark of a tree found in Peru, the cin¬
chona, an extract from which, quinine, was known to be the
supreme remedy for the feverish disease malaria. Thus a decoction
from willow-bark came to be used for the treatment of fevers. In
1829 the Frenchman Leroux succeeded in extracting from willow-
bark a substance which he called salicine (from the Latin name of
the tree).
Not long afterwards, a Swiss pharmacist named Pagenstecher
distilled the flowers of meadowsweet, a plant of the genus
Spiraea, which also likes to have its feet in the water, and obtained
a substance very similar to salicine, methyl salicylate. And now the
story moves to Germany where, a few years later, yet another
similar substance, salicylic acid, was produced artificially for the
first time; this in turn yielded a derivative, acetylsalicylic acid,
which (with its echo of Salix, the original willow) is none other
than the official name for aspirin, our common remedy for aches
A variety of blackberry is depicted on this page from the sixth-
century Codex Aniciae Julianae, the oldest surviving herbal, or
illustrated manual of medicinal plants. The Codex is a version of
a famous herbal by the Greek physician and pharmacologist
Pedanius Dioscorides (1st century AD) who described with
remarkable accuracy the therapeutic properties of many plants
used in medical practice until modern times.
and pains, where the syllable "spir" reminds us of its other vegeta¬
ble ancestor, the meadowsweet Spiraea.
Similar processes have given birth to a great many modern
medicines, the origins of which are to be found in plants known to
man since time immemorial. Ephedrine, for example, which is used
in the treatment of asthma, is derived from the Ephedra herb,
employed in Chinese medicine for at least 5000 years. Sovereign
pain-killers like henbane, mandragora, opium and asafetida are
listed in the earliest pharmacopoeias of Babylon and Sumer.
In fact, the capacity to relieve pain was probably the first great
triumph of medicine, and came long before the ability to heal.
Sedatives were used in Ancient Egypt, and a medical treatise
drawn up in Thebes in about 1600 BC contains an inventory of
seven hundred plants, including purgatives like senna and the
castor oil plant, and plants such as those of the genus Scilla, used
in the treatment of heart conditions.
It was Greek medicine, under the influence of such physicians as
Hippocrates and Dioscorides, that established the therapeutic
value of herbal remedies, as distinct from their significance in ritual
and magic. But sorcery and occult science made a powerful
comeback after the fall of the Roman Empire, while knowledge of
medicinal plants took refuge in monasteries and convents, and
medical learning flourished in the work of Arab scholars.
We now know that certain pathological states described by
medieval authors, like the inflamed skin condition called "St. An- .
thony's fire", can be induced by a minute fungus that attacks grain
and grasses, and that collective poisoning can occur, accom¬
panied by the hallucinations in which medieval man detected
satanic influences at work, when large numbers of people eat
bread made from contaminated flour. But it was not until the eigh¬
teenth century that ergot, the fungus in question, was identified.
Curiously, ergot serves today to produce a large number of
medicines used in the treatment of high blood pressure and other
circulatory ailments.
The discovery of America by European explorers and the open¬
ing of the sea route to India added new plants and spices to the an¬
cient pharmacopoeias, and thus led to the enrichment of the vast i
inventory of herbs used in modern medicine. f
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
w
unste lift.
i â*3al~~
i £M~
Î&Ê3MA
>2Ï
Photo © University Museum, Philadelphia
Documentary milestones in the story of man's long quest for
mastery of the art of healing: (1) Illustration from the Arab
physician Ahmad al-Ghafiq's classic study on the cultivation and
use of medicinal plants (Cordoba, 12th century). Shown here, a
stylized representation of the myrtle plant, widely cultivated In
northern Africa and the Iberian peninsula. (3) Over 4,000 years
old, this tablet unearthed In the ruins of the Sumerian city of
Nippur has been proclaimed the world's oldest treatise on
medicine. Inscribed on it are recipes for plant medicines,
although their uses are not specified. (4) Fragment of the oldest
known Egyptian medical manual, the Ebers papyrus. Dating back
to the second millennium of the pre-Christian era, it was
acquired by the German Egyptologist Georg Ebers in 1873. (2)
Birch-bark, as well as the tree's leaves and sap possess blood-
cleansing, antiseptic, diuretic, stimulant and sweat-inducing
properties. In the 12th century birch flowers were extolled by St.
Hildegard as aiding the formation of scar tissue.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
"God has imprinted on
plants, herbs and flowers
hieroglyphics which are in
some wise the very
signature of their virtues",
wrote the 17th-century
English botanist Robert
Turner. According to this
"theory of signatures",
which held sway for
centuries, medicinal plants
possess some feature such
as the shape of their roots,
leaves or flowers which
relates them to the ailment
they can heal. According to
one variant of the theory
(right) propounded by the
Italian scientist
Giambattista della Porta
(1538 - 1615) a scorpion bite
can be countered by
heliotrope, cumin and
scorpiorus, plants whose
appearance has marked
affinities with that of the
deadly creature (pictured at
bottom of document).
All Rights Reserved
The nineteenth century marks a watershed in the manner in
which medicinal plants are used, and the transition from use of the
plants themselves or preparations ma.de from them for therapeutic
purposes, to use of the active molecules they contain. This is, in
fact, the period when the productivist ideologies of young in¬
dustrial societies begin to overthrow the traditional image of
nature, which is no longer regarded as anything but a vast source
of readily available raw materials. The resources are there to be ex¬
ploited, and modern man indeed exploits them, sometimes to an
excessive extent.
Where the plant world was once composed of individual "per¬
sonalities", it is now considered merely as a mine, whose sole pur¬
pose is to yield the substances it contains. In many cases, it must
be said, this new approach has its advantages: no one would
dream of sweetening their coffee with a lump of beetroot, when it
is much more convenient to extract the sugar from the beetroot
first!
When this process is carried further, and chemists succeed in
reproducing artificially a specific active substance, there is no fur¬
ther need for the plant from which it was originally obtained. And
the next stage, when one synthetic product is transformed into a
series of derivatives, which are tested first on animals and then ad¬
ded to the steadily lengthening list of "chemical" medicines, can
be carried so far that the fact that once upon a time there was a
plant which produced the same effects is all but forgotten. Who
today remembers that the amphetamines, prescribed as a
stimulant in cases of depression, are merely synthetic "descen¬
dants" of a natural extract of the Ephedra?
The shelves of modern pharmacies are stocked in this way with
artificial products, many of which originated in the active consti¬
tuents of medicinal plants. To an ever-increasing extent, man is
producing artificial molecules, which have no counterpart in the
natural world, and using them to concoct potions of his own
making.
Produced in greater and greater quantities and designed to serve
a huge variety of purposes, these synthetic compounds tend to
result in what we may call "medicinal pollution", with the grave at
tendant problem posed by the daily consumption, on a constantly
growing scale, of vast amounts of medicines by people who are
not really ill. Tonics, tranquillizers, all kinds of psychotropic treat¬
ment, contraceptive pills and so on, these are the "convenience
medicines", absorbed in huge quantities by masses of basically
healthy individuals in the belief that they will feel better as a result.
"In the belief" only, for there are no means of telling whether, in
the long run, the effect will be beneficial.
However, more and more people are asking themselves what
will happen if uncontrolled industrial development, based on the
production and consumption of ever-increasing quantities of new
commodities, is permitted to continue.
There is a powerful public demand for research into "softer",
less aggressive therapeutic techniques, which will subject the
human system to less strain, accompanied by a steep worldwide
increase in the production and consumption of medicinal plants.
But before breaking with the excesses of our chemistry-based
civilization, and inventing or re-inventing new therapies designed
to place man on better terms with his environment, it would be
wise to clarify, once and for all, the relationship between inductive
science and the empiricism of the ancient physicians and healers, a
relationship which resembles that of a couple in which the partners
are somewhat weary of living together, but at the same time in¬
capable of living alone ! A speedy reconciliation is called for. Here
lies the interest of the research carried out by the World Health
Organization, which is encouraging all its Member States to draw
up a completely fresh inventory of their therapeutic resources, in
which medicinal plants continue to occupy a prominent place.
There can be no doubt that such a research programme will lead
to the discovery of new medicines and the development of new at¬
titudes to the treatment of illness. It is hardly necessary to recall
that their wisdom and keen sense of observation frequently led our
ancestors on different continents to use the same natural
medicines for the treatment of the same afflictions. Thus, the con¬
tinents with tropical climates each produced popular remedies for
the same disease, leprosy, based on extracts from the same family
of plants, the Flacourtaceae. In other words, healers working
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
thousands of kilometres apart, unaware of each other's existence,
discovered the same medicines, based on very similar plants which
modern botany groups in the same family. Both the Incas and the
Chinese, for example, considered that the water lily had sedative
and anaphrodisiac properties I
Such convergences, when they occur, draw attention to the
usefulness of drugs discovered at different times by different
civilizations. Today a number of countries are devoting con¬
siderable resources to the reappraisal and scientific investigation of
their therapeutic traditions. Identical efforts in this connexion in
every continent would not only enrich the cultural heritage of each
people, society and civilization, but also place additional resources
at the disposal of modern medicine.
Progress of this kind, however, presupposes an entirely new ap¬
proach to medicinal plants. After decades of analytical research
aimed at the extraction of specific active substances, the accent
should now be placed on utilization of the entire plant. In this
respect, some of the radically new concepts of ecology may be of
help^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^
To the ecologist, a givien effect is never the product of a single
cause, but rather the oufcbme of interplay between a number of
simultaneously occurm^ phenomena. In a complex system,
therefore, the whole is more than the sum of its components; and
understanding of the former depends on more than familiarity with
the latter. The '%©rking" of. nature's machine is not the sum of the
actions carried 9 Hoeously and in juxtaposition by all its
parts, but the consequence of the many interactions between
them. Expressed more simply, it is as if, once a certain threshold
of complexity has been passed, matter and life acquire new
properties.
In application to medicinal plants, whose composition is in¬
variably complex, this theory confirms a posteriori the traditional
theories according to which a plant in its entirety has properties
which differ from those of its constituent parts. The overall proper¬
ties of ergot, opium or digitalis, which are clearly different from the
properties of the individual substances which they contain, are ex¬
amples most frequently cited in support of such notions, but they
are not particularly convincing, since a minimum of Cartesian logic
is enough to show that the properties of a mixture constitute an
algebraic summation of the properties of its ingredients.
Our experiments with the artichoke would appear to yield more
significant results in this connexion. According to the doctrine of
signatures, this bitter-tasting plant ought to assist the functioning
of the liver, and this is in fact the case. The property involved was
initially attributed to a single substance, and then it was discovered
that a number of other substances are also partially responsible.
When, however, these were tested separately on mice, it rapidly
became clear that the majority of them isolation were totally
inactive. On the other hand, the administration in equal doses of
mixtures of these substances revealed that the greater the number
of ingredients involved, the more pronounced was their activity. In
other words, this was a spectacular demonstration of how new
CONTINUED PAGE 16
An intriguing feature of this 16th-century sculpture of St.
George and the Dragon, which stands in the palace of
Prague (Czechoslovakia) is that the clash takes place in a
field of stylized artichokes (detail below right). Experiments
seem to show that the bitter leaves of the artichoke, a plant
of Mediterranean origin, assist the functioning of the liver,
as suggested by the "doctrine of signatures".
Photo Jaroslav Jerabek © Narodni Gallery, Prague
1
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Pine-tree therapy
for the vascular system
	 - 	_
1 i I ' 1
The Maritime Pine has a tendency to
inhibit the growth of other plant-life. Its
needles and bark contain a substance of
the pycnogenol group which is dissolved
by rain and impregnates the soil, thus
inhibiting grasses from germinating and
taking root.
Photo 1, a forest floor carpeted with pine-
needles. Photo 2, grasses cannot get a
foothold at the base of trees whose bark
has been stripped. This phenomenon can
be reproduced in the laboratory. Wheat
seeds placed on dampened paper, photo
3, germinate and grow very rapidly, but in
the presence of coarsely-ground pine-
needles, photo 4. germination is virtually
eliminated. Similarly, a poplar cutting
placed in water grows roots within a few
days, photo 5 bottom, whereas on a
cutting placed in an infusion of pine-
needles no roots appear, photo 5 top.
This is a question of hormonal activity.
The pycnogenol in the pine inhibits the
activity of the enzyme whose task is to
maintain the optimal level of the growth
hormone ; as a result the excess
accumulation of the hormone upsets the
growth mechanism. This effect can be
seen in photo 6; the dark spot in the first
frame (from left to right) indicates a high
hormonal level. The second frame, in
which the spot is almost invisible, shows
the regulatory effect of the enzyme. The
third, fourth and fifth frames show the
inhibition of the enzyme by the action of
the pycnogenol and the consequent high
hormonal level. In mammals, however,
pycnogenol from pines acts like a vitamin
and is used as a therapeutic for the vascular
system. The vitamin is extracted from the
bark of the pine, photo 7. It is a virtually
colourless substance which has to be
separated from the dark red tannin in which the
bark is rich, photo 8. The separation is
effected by an industrial process based on
the specific solubility of the vitamin in
certain organic solvents. Photo 9 shows the
substance accumulated in the upper layer
formed by one these solvents.
The action of this vitamin is studied by
means of carbon 14 labelling. This is
achieved by photosynthesis in an
atmosphere of radioactive carbonic gas.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
and, since it is difficult to cultivate a pine-
tree in a laboratory, the yellow pansy,
which contains a precursor of pycnogenol.
Is used instead, photo 10.
After oral administration to mice, the
vitamin, being radioactive, can easily be
detected in the animals' bodies. In photo
11, the white areas are due to radioactivity
and demonstrate that the vitamin has
spread throughout the entire organism,
even to the skin and the vertebral discs.
Photo 12 is a photographic enlargement of
the heart showing the walls of the large
blood vessels. The vitamin isolated from
the pine acts in conjunction with vitamin
C to maintain the vascular system in good
condition and for this reason is often
referred to as "vitamin C¿'.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 13
active properties can emerge through the addition of substances
which, in isolation, are ineffective.
Similar phenomena doubtless occur in the case of other plants,
such as hawthorn and valerian, although the exact nature of their
active components has not yet been accurately determined. Just
as the "common weal" is something different from the sum of all
the individual interests concerned, so the properties of a given
drug are different from the sum of the properties of all its consti¬
tuent substances. This means that an entirely new approach to the
study of medicinal plants is required, as well as development of
specific pharmacology so that the full range of their nature and
action may be more readily understood.
In this way, for example, observations of the floor of a pine
forest by Professor Masquelier of Bordeaux University, led him to
discover an important medicine used in the treatment of cir¬
culatory disorders. Noting that grass is virtually non-existent on
the floor of such forests, Masquelier wondered whether the cause
of its absence might not be found in a substance contained in the
dead pine-needles, which inhibited the germination of the grass
seeds. Tests made with a decoction of dead needles revealed that
such inhibition did in fact occur, and powerfully so (see photo
story pages 14 and 15).
Professor Masquelier succeeded in extracting the substance
responsible, which was found to exercise a profoundly disturbing
influence on the hormonal processes governing the division and
elongation of vegetal cells. It was also found that this substance in¬
hibited the growth of malignant cell cultures of human origin.
When attempts were made to reproduce it synthetically,
however, it was found that only the polymers possessed such a
property (polymers are substances composed of very large
molecules that are multiples of simpler chemical units called
monomers). However, when reduced to dimers (a dimer is a com¬
pound former by the union of two molecules), these substances
were found to strengthen the resistance of the capillary blood
vessels and thus to fortify the cardiovascular system. Observation
of woodland undergrowth, coupled with the quest for new
therapeutic compounds thus led to the discovery of a new treat¬
ment for circulatory diseases, based on an extract of pine-needles.
This shows how scientific research must sometimes follow
curiously original and tortuous paths in order to arrive at positive
results.
Of a simpler nature are the tests which are systematically carried
out on plants in order to determine their activity. Every year, such
tests are applied in industrial and university laboratories to
thousands of species used by purveyors of herbal remedies in all
corners of the world.
Of more than ten thousand species investigated in this manner,
in the quest for a cure for cancer, only 10 per cent have revealed
only to a minor extent such properties. Some fifty of
these have been examined in greater detail, and it may be hoped
that some at least may one day form the basis of a useful therapy.
Another fruitful line of research consists in the investigation of
genera, species and subspecies of plants which are rich in active
substances. Reasoning by analogy suggests that if a certain
substance is found in the members of one species, it is likely to be
present in the members of a closely similar species.
Despite appearances, there is order in nature's affairs, and the
chemistry of botanical species is by no means a haphazard pro¬
cess. There is a "family spirit" among plants, and each family is
specialized in its own type of chemical reactions, just as each pro¬
duces its own type of flower.
At all events, and irrespective of the chosen path of research,
the study of medicinal plants is enjoying a new lease of life
throughout the world, and there are encouraging signs in the keen
interest now shown by the developing countries in their own tradi¬
tional pharmacopoeias. With the encouragement of the World
Health Organization, they are endeavouring to meet public health
requirements from their own resources, drawing on all that is
richest in the age-old medical traditions of their own civilizations
and thus reducing to a minimum the import of costly foreign
drugs, whose superiority is not always evident. Today, as ¡ri the
past, the world of medicinal plants remains a vast one, offering its
horizons to research and medical progress.
Jean-Marie Pert
THE study of extractives of medicinal
plants is without doubt the most
commonly chosen field of research
among organic chemists in Africa. Many
people think that it is an obvious and
natural subject of study for an African
chemist.
This is not only because of the abun¬
dance of plants in our environment but also
because of the important role they have
played in our system of traditional
medicine. It has been virtually assumed
that if only one took the trouble to find out
what the African herbalist uses, and ex¬
tracted it, one would without fail come up
with something new to modern medical
science.
Indeed the study of African medicinal
plants is a field with many promising pro¬
spects and one which should be given high
priority in terms of research effort and fun¬
ding. But this is not because plant use in
traditional medicine is unique to Africa.
Most countries of the world at one time or
another have had a traditional system of
medicine similar to that of Africa which in¬
volved the use of plants.
In countries such as those of North
America, Europe, Australasia, Japan and
the Indian subcontinent in which scientific
investigation of plants has been intense
and of long standing, few of their medicinal
plants if any at all have survived as such in
present-day medical practice. However
these investigations have made tremen¬
dous contributions to scientific knowledge,
particularly organic chemistry, and inspired
the development of new synthetic
DONALD E.U. EKONG, of Nigeria, is professor
of chemistry at the University of Ibadan and first
Vice-Chancellor of the University of Port Har-
court, Nigeria. He is the author of a number of
papers on the chemistry of natural products in
which he has a special interest.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
African medicinal
plants under
the microscope
by Donald E.U. Ekong
Photo © CNRS, Paris
Plant extracts being separated by a process known as column chromatography at a
laboratory of the French Centre National de Recherches Scientifiques. Using this
technique, chemists can separate the components of a mixture without having detailed
prior knowledge of the type, number or relative amounts of the substances present.
medicines with far superior properties to
those of the traditional medicinal plants.
Not that African medicinal plants have
not been investigated before. Indeed there
is hardly any common African plant which
has not been studied, mostly in Europe and
North America, and the results of the in¬
vestigations recorded in the world scientific
literature.
Some of them have yielded active
substances which were already known
from other sources. An example is the bark
and latex of Antioris africana from which
cardiac glycosides (heart poisons) were
isolated, which were already known to oc¬
cur in Digitalis species, and are used in
modern medicine for the treatment of heart
diseases. Most of the plants already in¬
vestigated have yielded substances with
either no significant activity or with inferior
activity to those of other well-known pro¬
ducts used in modern medical practice.
A few new substances have, however,
been discovered and are now used in
modern medicine although such use is
often different from that to which the plant
was applied in traditional medicine. A well-
known example is physostigmine isolated
from the "esere bean" (Physostigma
venenosum) which is now used in oph¬
thalmology, but was traditionally used for
trial by ordeal.
Some of the importance of research on
extractives from African medicinal plants
derives from the fact that naturally occurr¬
ing substances which have biological ac¬
tivity often inspire chemists not only to
synthesize them, in order to obtain them
more easily than by extraction from plants,
but also to synthesize derivatives of the
parent drug which often have superior
medicinal properties to the natural
products.
Some of our research in Ibadan (Nigeria)
has been concerned with studies of this i
nature. For instance we have studied the
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
r
v\
<..
Photos © A.D. Pasquale, University of Messina, Italy
Photo Georges Viollon © Rapho, Paris
f
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
roots of the tree Fagara xanthoxy/oldes
commonly used in traditional medicine and
also as chewing sticks which are chewed to
a brush and used to clean the teeth.
Various natural products were isolated in¬
cluding a good yield of xanthoxylol which
had earlier been isolated from the wood of
the same tree and its structure elucidated.
It was reported that crude aqueous extracts
of the roots had antimicrobial and anti-
sickling activity. Sickling makes affected
red blood cells assume strange crescent
forms, deprives them of the ability to
transport oxygen, and causes their destruc¬
tion by dissolution of the cell. This' promp¬
ted us to have bioassays tests of the
strength of a substance by comparing its
effect with that of a standard prepara¬
tion out on the pure compounds
that we had earlier isolated from the roots.
In a preliminary bioassay carried out at
University College Hospital, Ibadan, xan¬
thoxylol seemed to possess some anti-
sickling activity. In an attempt to enhance
this activity, various modifications of the
structure of the compound were carried
out. This was facilitated particularly by the
fact that the substance could be obtained
in good yield from the roots of the plant. Of
the modified products, a compound called
DBA appeared the most interesting and
detailed bioassay studies carried out in the
Sickle Cell Centre, Harlem Hospital, New
York, showed it to be a very active anti-
sickling agent. DBA has many properties
such as lack of acute toxicity and non in¬
terference with oxygen delivery which
make it superior to most known anti-
sickling agents and suggest that it might be
a useful therapeutic agent for sickle cell
anaemia.
Another promising approach to the
study of extractives of African medicinal
plants arises from the possibility of
isolating in adequate yield certain com¬
pounds which, though themselves not ac¬
tive medicinally, might provide the raw
materials for the synthesis of already
known and accepted drugs. For instance
most of the steroids, which represent a
CONTINUED PAGE 42
The development of the scanning
electron microscope, which can
provide three-dimensional images
of the surface structure of plant
cells and tissue, has enabled
researchers to study in detail the
sites at which biochemical activities
take place within the plant. Far left,
a fine specimen of Digitalis
purpurea. Left, two photos of the
upper face of a leaf of the Digitalis
purpurea, as seen by a scanning
electron microscope, showing the
protective and glandular hairs of
the leaf magnified about a
thousand times. Digitalis purpurea,
the common, purple foxglove, is
cultivated commercially as the
source of the heart-stimulating drug
digitalis.
Unesco and the basic chemistry
of natural products
BEHIND a barrage of test tubes,
retorts and, to the layman, seem¬
ingly obscure symbols and for¬
mulae, scientists working in the field of the
basic chemistry of natural products are
quietly writing a new page in social and
economic as well as scientific history.
Research in one specific corner of this
field, the basic chemistry of medicinal
plants, is proving particularly exciting and
has already achieved notable successes.
Development of the compounds on which
the contraceptive pill is based, for example,
has sparked off a chemotherapeutic, social
and demographic revolution; development
of Pyrethrin pesticides, as powerful as DDT
but without the latter's harmful side-
effects, offers new hope of controlling
certain widespread human diseases and of
curbing crop depredation by pests.
A particularly interesting aspect of
research into the basic chemistry of
medicinal plants is that the lead time
between basic research and practical
application is now comparatively short.
Furthermore, it is a field which offers
virtually limitless possibilities for original
work with high economic returns and
which is accessible to workers over a wide
range of capability and sophistication
(rudimentary student projects of consi¬
derable educational value can be attempted
at high school and university level). It is
therefore an ideal growth area for many
developing countries.
With all these factors in mind, Unesco
has established the South-east Asian
Regional Network for the Chemistry of
Natural Products which links research
institutions in eleven Member States.
The network is founded on the principle
of self-help and mutual co-operation. It
concentrates on existing facilities and
resources and provides an organizational
structure which allows each institution to
contribute as best it can, and to seek
assistance directly from colleagues in other
countries.
This system allows for the realistic use of
the very limited funding available provided
in the main by the participating countries
themselves, most of whom are developing
countries, by a generous annual grant from
the government of Japan of US $50,000 and
from Unesco's regular programme budget.
It encourages the development of research
directly related to the needs of the region,
as determined locally by local chemists.
Directed by a co-ordinating board
consisting of one chemist from each
participating Member State, the network's
major activities include the organization, in
local universities, of training courses for
young chemists in techniques and
interpretation of data; the holding of
seminars at both national and regional
levels; exchange programmes which allow
institutions to invite eminent chemists to
assist in the development of their research
programmes and which enable individual
young research workers to obtain short
term research fellowships to travel to other
institutions in the region for further
training; collaborative research projects
which normally involve teams in three or
more institutions. The co-ordinating board
also publishes a regional newsletter,
"Chemistry", a triannual publication which
now has a reading public both inside and
outside the region in some twenty-one
countries.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
A medical thesaurus
from the roof
of the world
by Lydia Khundanova
Text and photos © copyright
Reproduction prohibited
WIDELY practised in many countries of south-east Asia
as far back as two to three thousand years ago, the
Tibetan system of medicine was a synthesis of the
traditional medicines of Tibet, India, China, Mongolia and other
countries.
The system was based on the notion of the integrity, the
wholeness of the organism, and treatment, by a combination of
natural medicines of animal, vegetable or mineral origin, was
aimed at the entire organism and not at curing any individual
part of it.
Among the many treatises and manuals on Tibetan medicine,
the main canonical work and the fullest manual is the four-
volume Rgyud-bzhi (literally, the four principles) which con¬
tains both theory and practice. According to tradition it was
written in Sanskrit in the fifth century BC and was translated
into Tibetan in about 820 AD. The original Sanskrit manuscript
has long been lost.
The four volumes which make up the Rgyud-bzhi consist of :
Volume I, Basic Principles, which presents a six-chapter outline
of the framework of the manual and an introduction to Tibetan
medicine; Volume II, Theoretical Foundations, in which the
general theory of Tibetan medicine is developed, in thirty-one
chapters; Volume III, Fundamentals of the Doctor's Art,
ninety-two chapters dealing with general pathology and practi¬
cal prescriptions for treatment; Volume IV, Supplementary
Principles, twenty-seven chapters giving additional information
on diagnostic methods and treatment.
Towards the end of the seventeenth century, a high-ranking
Tibetan physician wrote the Vaidouria-onbo, a 1,283-page
commentary on each of the 156 chapters of the Rgyud-bzhi.
The commentaries contained in the Vaidouria-onbo were illus¬
trated by the Atlas of Indo-Tibetan Medicine. This consisted of
seventy-seven stylized colour plates containing a total of over
ten thousand individual illustrations (see front cover and colour
pages 22, 23 and 24).
Compiled at the monastery of Serkog-Manba in north¬
eastern Tibet, the Atlas was acquired by a Buryat doctor who
had gone there to study medicine ; it is now preserved in the
Ethnographical Museum of Ulan Ude in the Autonomous
Soviet Socialist Republic of Buryat.
Only twelve of these plates, including that reproduced on
page 24, have been published before ; the plates shown on our
cover and central colour pages are here published for the first
time ever.
Tibetan physicians still use many of the methods and reme¬
dies handed down from ancient days and, today, in India and a
number of European countries, Tibetan medicines are being
scientifically investigated. In the USSR, the Siberian section of
the Academy of Sciences has established a special department
at which the biologically active components of Tibetan medic¬
ines are being tested under experimental laboratory conditions.
LYDIA KHUNDANOVA, of the USSR, is director of a unit of the Buryat
branch of the Siberian section of the USSR Academy of Sciences that is
studying the biologically active components of Indo-Tibetan medicine. A
physician, she is the author of some sixty works including an important
monograph on Tibetan medicine.
Colour page
In the Middle Ages, Islamic scholars made a great contribution to
the study of botany and in particular of medicinal plants.
Compiled in the 9th century al-Dinawari's six-volume Book of
Plants was of outstanding importance. It combined a
philological, historical and botanical approach to the study of
plants whose medicinal properties he listed in detail. Avicenna
dealt with. medicinal plants in his pharmacological studies and al-
Biruni listed in his Book of Drugs some 850 drugs of every
conceivable origin, giving their names in several languages. The
first Arabic work on drugs in their simple or natural state,
compiled by Masarjis, preceded by a century the translation into
Arabic of the famous Materia Medica of the Greek physician
Dioscorides. The first Arabic version of the Materia Medica was
compiled in the 9th century. Colour photo right Is of a page of a
15th-century Persian edition of this work, now preserved in the
Topkapi Museum, Istambul. It shows, top left, the formula for
the preparation of a remedy extracted from various aquatic
plants such as papyrus. The main text describes a powder
preparation used in the treatment of hepatic infections, disorders
of the spleen and menstruation problems.
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris.
Central colour pages
Coloured plates from the Atlas of Indo-Tibetan Medicine which
illustrates the Vaidouria-onbo, a commentary on the most
famous and most complete manual of Tibetan medicine, the
Rgyud-bzhi (see article this page). Colour page 22: plate 24 from
the Atlas, with illustrations referring to chapter 20 of the Rgyud-
bzhi on Medicines and Officinal Plants. Colour page 23: top left,
detail from plate 24 and, top right and bottom, details from plate
30 which illustrates some of the remedies given in the same
chapter. Although the first two volumes of the Rgyud-bzhi were
translated into Russian at the turn of the century, the complete
text has never been translated into any European language.
Today, at Ulan-Ude, in southern Siberia, orientalist, historians,
physicians, pharmacists and linguists are working together on a
new, more accurate translation of the Rgyud-bzhi, a task made
more difficult because the text contains many cryptic passages
inscribed in numbers or in the form of allegories.
Photos © V. Shumakov, Russian edition of the Unesco Courier, Moscow Buryat
Department, Siberian section of the USSR Academy of Sciences
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
cT
-r. J^~
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
SS
-^=ö£ 1
^"^¿~ l
»V*;^"4no
ft«yr»gtyy^
	
ID
rü.
7P.Ull / *r~i«.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
.-:. M¿
r\ *.** na
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
China:
a new medicine
born of tradition
by Wei Wen
Colour page
This plate, like those on our front
cover and central colour pages, is
taken from the Atlas of Indo-
Tibetan Medicine. It illustrates
various mineral and vegetable
medicinal substances mentioned in
chapter 20 of the famous Tibetan
medical manual, the Rgyud-bzhi,
including precious stones (after
pulverization), mineral salts, plants
and the fruit and leaves of trees.
The original of this illustration is
now preserved at the Institute of
Tibetan Medicine, Lhasa, People's
Republic of China.
Photo © China, Illustrated Review,
People's Republic of China
Anew, highly effective antimalarial
drug has been successfully extrac¬
ted in China from a medicinal herb.
This is a breakthrough comparable to the
development of chloroquine, which is ac¬
cepted throughout the world as the most
effective treatment for malaria.
The new drug, Ching Hao Su, is a
substance obtained from wormwood, a
plant which, according to ancient Chinese
medical records, was used in the treatment
of malaria more than 1,000 years ago.
Research began at the Institute of
Chinese Materia Medica, which is attached
to the Academy of Traditional Chinese
Medicine. Members of the Institute's staff
succeeded in extracting Ching Hao Su in
1972. Later dozens of other scientific
organizations joined in the work. Clinical
tests and experiments in chemical phar¬
macology, preparation and production pro¬
cesses were studied and herbal resources
were surveyed. The clinical effectiveness
and chemical structure of the drug were
ascertained. Its crystalline chemical struc¬
ture is entirely different from those of the
antimalarial drugs now being used
throughout the world, and in this respect
Ching Hao Su is entirely new.
WEN, of the People's Republic of China, is
a specialist in medical information who writes for
the New China Agency, Peking.
The new drug can be administered orally
or by intramuscular injection. Reliable
though it is, it has one shortcoming : it is
unable to prevent short-term relapses. Ef¬
forts are now being made to remedy this
defect.
Traditional medicine is part of China's
cultural heritage. As early as the Warring
States period (475-221 BC) herbal medicine
began to develop as an independent
branch of Chinese medical science. As time
went by, more and more medicinal herbs
were discovered and experience in using
them against disease grew richer.
China's health services are making great
efforts to develop and popularize both the
traditional and the western schools of
medicine, with the aim of creating a new
integrated medical science based on a syn¬
thesis of the two schools. To date, more
than 5,000 varieties of medicinal herbs have
been catalogued in China, as against some
2,000 before liberation. Many therapeutic
herbs and treatments have been collected
from the Chinese people, some more effec¬
tive than certain western drugs.
In this field, China is focussing on herbs
for the prevention and treatment of com¬
mon and recurrent diseases. One example
is chronic bronchitis, which affects from 3
to 5 per cent of the population in some
parts of northern China. Since 1971 the
government has sent 290,000 medical
workers to the countryside, factories and
mines to study the prevention and treat-
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
China's herbal
drugstores
Traditional Chinese medicine, known
throughout the world primarily for its
acupuncture, has used plants and herbs
since very ancient times. Today, in
conjunction with Western medical
techniques, the use of medicinal plants is
helping China to spend less on synthetic
drugs and its people to achieve better
health. Far right, boxes brimming with
herbs in a chemist's shop give a glimpse
of the variety of Chinese herbal reme¬
dies. Top right, medicinal herbs being
dried by growers and "barefoot doctors"
at Huangshan (Ankwei province). Bot¬
tom, right, at a Peking pharmacy, staff
prepare herbal prescriptions while the
customer waits.
Photo © WHO, Geneva
ment of this disease. Along with the village
"barefoot doctors", these medical workers
have investigated the impact of the disease
and collected some 100 effective drugs, in¬
cluding a plant named Muching which with
nine others is being introduced all over the
country. Dozens of compounds have been
produced.
Clinical reports made in the past few
years show that Muching (vitex negundo
var. cannabifolia) has been highly effective
in treating 60 per cent of the 2,000 chronic
bronchitis patients tested. Laboratory tests
show that this herbal medicine is effective
for clearing up phlegm. It stimulates the
body responses, promotes the functions of
the cortex of the adrenal glands, and acts
as an antihistamine (used to relieve the
symptoms of hay fever and other allergies)
or as a sedative.
The work done on Muching shows how
western techniques may be integrated into
traditional Chinese medicine. The use of
Muching dates back many centuries, but
ancient pharmacological works recorded
that only the fruit and the roots of the herb
were effective in treating chronic bron¬
chitis. No previous sources have been
found to indicate that the leaves are useful.
However, modern chemical analysis shows
that the medicinal quality of the fruit is due
to the volatile oil content of its calyx, the
outer circle of leaflike scales at the base of
the flower, and that the leaves contain four
to six times more volatile oil than the fruit.
This important discovery has opened wide
possibilities for the extraction of oil from
Muching. The case of Muching
demonstrates that there is much to be
learned from the experience of traditional
Chinese medicine and, on the other hand,
that traditional medicine must be made
more effective by applying modern scien¬
tific methods.
The Chinese herb medicine salvia mi/tior-
rhiza is now being used to treat diseases of
the coronary artery, another common ill¬
ness. This medicine was known in ancient
times for its efficacy in activating the cir¬
culation of the blood. The herb has been
made into injectable solutions for the treat¬
ment of angina pectoris and has proved ef
fective in 87 per cent of cases. Electrocar¬
diograms showed some improvement in 53
per cent of the patients thus treated.
Laboratory tests reveal that in patients
given injections of salvia miltiorrhiza there
is a noticeable increase in the volume of
blood circulated. Tests also show that
treatment with this drug causes a drop in
blood viscosity. It also hastens the flow of
red cells, in some cases bringing this flow
back to normal. These results show that
the medicine promotes blood circulation
and dissolves clots of red intercellular
bodies.
A large number of effective herbal
remedies have been found for treating
burns, hypertension and even cancer. They
are abundant and inexpensive, but they
work slowly. Since 1958 a hospital affiliated
to the Shansi Medical College has suc¬
cessfully treated more than 800 cases of
extra-uterine pregnancy with herbal
medicine. In 90 per cent of them no surgery
was used. Pharmacological studies showed
that the various decoctions of medicinal
herbs used checked bleeding, improved cir-
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Above, 19th-century miniature depicting
the great Chinese botanist Han Kang (2nd
century AD). "The nobles decked out in
their finery sought him out in vain", reads
the inscription. "He walked alone, happy
in the mountain of clouds". Indifferent to
worldly distractions Han Kang devoted his
life to the search for new plants..
Photo E. Reber-Lleras © WHO, Geneva
culation and hastened the disappearance of
blood clots.
Chinese specialists are also carrying out
research into the selection of safer, more
effective and more convenient contracep¬
tives both for men and women from among
herbal prescriptions (see article page 33).
In China, where many farm production
brigades grow medicinal herbs on their
own plots, a wide-ranging study of
medicinal herbs is under way as part of the
development of rural medical and health
services. This includes a further survey of
plant resources, the domestication of wild
herbs and the improvement of drug
preparations. One achievement resulting
from research carried out in the past dozen
years by the Institute of Medicine of the
Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and
other bodies, is the successful cultivation
of the rare and widely needed plant
gastrodia e/ata, used for 2,000 years for
treating dizziness, headaches and infantile
coma.
Wei Wen
Right, a tree of the
Cephalotaxus hainanensis
Li species and its seeds
(inset). From the bark of
this species, indigenous to
Hainan Island in southern
China, scientists have
isolated substances which
inhibit the formation of
tumours and have yielded
promising results In the
treatment of certain kinds
of leukaemia.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Himalayan
herbalists
and healers
Partly owing to its wide variety of natural conditions, Nepal Is
exceptionally rich in medicinal plants and herbs and can boast
one of the world's oldest traditions of herbal medicine. (In the
Rgveda, a collection of over 1,000 sacred hymns written between
4500 and 1600 BC, it is recorded that Himalayan plants were used
for healing.) Some parts of this country in the heart of the
Himalayas are a mere 50 metres above sea level, others rise to
over 8,000 metres, while the range of climatic conditions
(tropical, subtropical, temperate, Alpine) also contributes to the
profusion of different types of vegetation. The Nepalese
Government plays an active role in promoting the production,
processing and export of medicinal plants. More than 500
species grow in Nepal today, sales to other countries accounting
for 3 per cent of the country's export earnings. (1) Immediately
after being harvested, the roots of Picrorhiza Scrophulariaeflora,
used as a sedative and in the treatment of chronic bronchitis, are
laid out to dry. (2) 4,500 metres up in the Himalayas, a Picrorhiza
gatherer prepares his cargo before embarking on the journey to
the valleys of southern Nepal. (3) Vendors arrive at Kathmandu
market bearing loads of Acyranthes Áspera, a purgative and
diuretic plant. (4) Press for crushing mustard seeds which yield
an oil possessing curative properties. (5) A healer selling
medicinal plants at Kathmandu.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Corals, jelly-fish and sea anemones are among the 9,000 species that make up the group of aquatic
invertebrates known as Cnidaria. Many cnidarians live in very close relationship with certain forms of algae
and some substances apparently extracted from corals, for example, for possible medicinal use may be
derived from the algae living in symbiosis with them. Above, a soft coral of the Cnidaria alcyonaria family.
Neptune's
pharmacopoeia
by Mario Piattelli
MARIO PIATTELLI, of Italy, is professor of
organic chemistry at the University of Catania.
The author of some hundred scientific publica¬
tions, his research work has been concerned
mainly with the biochemistry of natural pro¬
ducts. In recent years he has concentrated on
the study of compounds of marine origin.
THE seas and the oceans, which cover
two-thirds of the earth's surface
and contain around five hundred
thousand species, including twenty thou¬
sand algae, represent an immense and
almost untapped reserve of natural,
biologically active and potentially useful
products.
Yet the abundance of medicines ex¬
tracted from land organisms, particularly
from higher plant forms and micro¬
organisms, is in striking contrast with the
scarcity of those obtained from marine
organisms.
The lack of interest that organic chemists
have until recently shown in marine pro¬
ducts is probably due to a combination of
several factors: the general perception of
the sea as a hostile milieu, the relative dif¬
ficulty of gathering material, and the par¬
ticular problem of identifying marine
species.
It is reasonable to assume that marine
organisms, being adapted to an entirely dif¬
ferent milieu than that of earth species,
have developed different secondary
elements not universally found in living i
species. A significant number of elements I
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
of rare composition have already been
' isolated. The most recent research has
been concerned primarily with products
derived from organisms which are seden¬
tary and relatively primitive from an evolu¬
tionary point of view, that is to say, in¬
vertebrates (particularly sponges, jelly-fish,
corals) and algae.
Because of the great interaction that ex¬
ists between plants and animals which in¬
habit the oceans, it is not always easy to
ascertain the true origin of a compound ex¬
tracted from a particular species. For exam¬
ple, many substances which have been ex¬
tracted from jelly-fish and corals and
therefore are usually considered animal are
probably derived from monocellular algae
which live in symbiosis with such in-
vertebrae.
Awareness of the possible biomedical
benefits to be had from algae is certainly
not new. Ancient Chinese pharmacology
suggested their use in the cure of many
diseases from cancer and dropsy to
menstrual disorders. Popular remedies in
fashion during past centuries and in certain
cases still employed today, used marine
algae for their therapeutic properties. For
instance, a red algae known as "Dulse"
was used in the 18th century in England to
stimulate sweating.
Other red algae, including one popularly
known as "Corsican moss", are employed
in many countries in the treatment of
worms. Varieties of the Sargasso weed are
used in India for bladder infections and in
South America as a remedy for kidney
disease and goitre (the rarity of this last
disease among the Chinese or Japanese is
certainly due to the high iodine content in
the algae which is part of their diet).
If the idea of using algae for therapeutic
purposes is old, however, scientists are
now exploring this form of marine life, us¬
ing new methods which are often extreme¬
ly refined (and expensive). Some thousand
marine species have been examined for the
purpose of establishing the presence of
potential anti-cancer agents. These studies
have revealed that algae cannot be con¬
sidered particularly suitable material in the
search for substances which could even¬
tually be used in cancer therapy.
The prospects look better with regard to
antibiotics, even if only one compound of
marine origin has up till now been adapted
for clinical use. Cefa/osporina C, the com¬
pound in question, extracted from a fungus
gathered in the vicinity of a sewage
The oceans of the world cover
some seventy per cent of the
surface of the globe. They
have been described as "inner
space" and "the last
unexplored frontier",
expressions which evoke their
vast resource potential. Fish
have long been an important
food source and today
scientists are examining
marine plants as a possible
source of new medicinal
extracts. Photo shows fish
traps off the coast of
Sjaelland, Denmark.
discharge along the coast of Sardinia, has a
similar composition to penicillin and is ef¬
fective against a wide spectrum of bacteria,
including penicillin-resistant ones, a
characteristic which it owes to its lack of
sensitivity to penicillinase, a bacteria en¬
zyme capable of destroying penicillin.
In addition to this example, which has
reached the stage of practical application,
there exists a lot of data concerning the an¬
tibiotic activities of marine flora, particular¬
ly with regard to species of red, brown and
green algae. The percentage of species,
which present these characteristics (anti¬
bacterial, antifungal) is rather high, pro¬
bably greater than 10 per cent.
Another potentially useful phar¬
macological activity is found in the sterols
of marine algae, which are known to
reduce the level of cholesterol in the blood,
or in the hypotensive properties of an
amino-acid isolated from brown algae.
Numerous more or less recent works
have been devoted to the pharmacological
study of complex carbohydrates known as
polysaccharides extracted from algae. The
most common compounds of this
category, whose composition is the result
of the union of many molecules of plain
sugar, are agar and carrageen, both ex¬
tracted from red algae, and laminarin and
alginates, both found in brown algae.
These compounds are used widely and
often in fields other than pharmacology
and present remarkable biomedical proper¬
tiesagar, for example, is extensively
used in bacteriology in the preparation of
cultures, and alginates are used in the
nutritional sector. Agar and carrageen, as
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ï
well as laminarin after the appropriate
chemical reaction has transformed it into a
sulfate, have anticoagulant properties.
These polysaccharides also have anti-
peptic and antiulcerous properties : in
many cases of ulcers the oral administra¬
tion of carrageen has proved to be an effec¬
tive remedy. Introduced intravenously, car¬
rageen and laminarin sulfate lower the fat
content in the blood serum and prevent the
development of arteriosclerosis. Alginates
and carrageen, administered orally, inhibit
the absorption of cholesterol by the in¬
testines. The polysaccharides of the algae
have also shown inhibiting action with
regard to numerous viruses.
The ability of alginic acid to form salts
with metal ions is at the origin of its use as
a protective agent against radio-strontium
contamination. The presence of alginic
acid in the intestinal tract effectively checks
one of the most harmful consequences of
radioactive fallout, the absorption and fixa¬
tion of strontium in human tissue. The acid
combined with the radioactive metal
creates an insoluble alginate which is
eliminated in the faeces.
The usefulness of alginic acid is not
restricted to the field of preventive
medicine but extends to therapeutic
medicine as well. Alginic acid is effective
not only in the prevention but in the treat¬
ment of radioactive strontium poisoning,
since the substance already deposited in
the bones is resecreted into the intestines
where in the presence of alginic acid it is
immobilized, to become an insoluble form.
The pharmacological study of algae
should not be limited to compounds which
may possibly be used in the treatment of
disease but should also include the toxins
which some algae produce. These toxins,
whose effects are known to be particularly
strong (a toxin derived from Gonyau/ax
catenella is one of the most lethal venoms
known today), sometimes accumulate in
edible organisms such as mussels and
other bi-valve molluscs, crustaceans and
fish, where they can cause serious food
poisoning if ingested. It is clear that food
poisoning due to such toxins can be
treated more effectively if we have greater
knowledge of their effects. Moreover, the
composition of these toxins can serve as
models for analogous synthetic chemical
compounds which would conserve their
medicinal properties.
This rapid and necessarily incomplete k
review of the present state of research con-
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
. cerning active substances which can be
found in marine flora may appear rather
discouraging, particularly since researchers
may sometimes present the results of tests
for biological activity in a far too optimistic
light in the hope of being granted further
funds to continue their studies. Further¬
more, the clinically useful results we
possess and these are far from substan¬
tial mostly been obtained by
sporadic and not very recent research.
Nevertheless, in order to evaluate the
question properly we must consider two
very important points: above all, con¬
siderable and continued efforts in this field
of scientific research have only begun in
the last few years and it is well known that
the development of a new medicine from
the time of its discovery to its use usually
takes from three to ten years, in some
cases longer. In the second place only one
biologically active compound out of
thousands succeeds in overcoming the
severe tests of its efficacity and reliability
before being put to practical clinical
application.
In the light of such considerations, it is
reasonable to believe that a systematic
study of substances produced by marine
algae (and by other marine organisms)
should be actively pursued in the hope of
obtaining useful results within the next
decade.
Mario Piattelli
Photo .£> Claude Carré, Station Marine, Villefranche-sur-Mer, France
32
The
jewels
of the sea
With their intricate shapes
and geometric designs,
diatoms, the microscopic,
single-celled algae to be
found in all the waters of
the earth, have been aptly
called "the jewels of the
sea" (photos left). Among
the most prolific sea
organisms one litre of
sea water Is said to contain
from a few thousand to a
few million diatoms they
serve as food for many
marine creatures. They are
divided into two orders on
the basis of their symmetry
and shape: the round
Centrales have radial
patterns and the elongated
Pennales have feather-like
markings. Diatoms are
believed to have
contributed to the
formation of oil deposits
and a substance composed
of fossil diatoms is used in
filters, abrasives and some
paints and varnishes. More
recently, certain diatoms
have been found to possess
antibacterial and antifungal
properties.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
*
.*s K
Photo © Ken Heyman, New York
The population question is one which
concerns the whole world, but the
nature of the problem varies widely
from country to country and from
continent to continent. Different
aspects of the problem call for
different solutions. Today, synthetic
steroids derived from extracts from
plants make it possible to increase or
inhibit human fertility and thus to
influence birth rates in either
direction. These steroids are
obtainable cheaply and in abundance
from sapogenins, substances
originating from plants of the
Dioscorea family.
Mexican plants
and human fertility
by Pierre Crabbé
PIERRE CRABBE, of Belgium, is chairman of
the Department of Chemistry of the University
of Missouri, Columbia, U.S.A. The author of a
number of scientific books and papers, he has
served as a consultant to Unesco's new pro¬
gramme on the chemistry of natural products.
Alittle under forty years ago, chemists
discovered in plants from the
Mexican jungle a raw material
which created a revolution in the phar¬
maceutical industry. These plants, which
belong to the Dioscorea family, contain
products whose chemical structure is
closely related to that of certain organic
chemical compounds known as steroids.
Steroids are a group of naturally occur¬
ring substances and their derivatives that
are of great importance in biology, i
medicine and chemistry. They occur I
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
naturally in the human body and include
the main categories of sex hormones (an¬
drogens, cestrogens and progestogens)
which control the human reproductive
system, and adrenocortical hormones.
These adrenocortical hormones or cor-
ticoids keep the individual alive from day to
day by regulating his metabolism, that is,
the chemical process in living cells by
which raw material is assimilated and
energy is released to the body. For in¬
stance, corticoids regulate mineral
metabolism by keeping sodium, potassium
and water in adequate balance. Corticoids
also promote the metabolism of car¬
bohydrates, fatsand proteins. Additional¬
ly, the corticoids somehow help to protect
the individual from the effects of stress and
shock.
Synthetic steroids prepared from ex¬
tracts from a wide range of vegetable
sources are today used in the treatment of
rheumatoid arthritis, allergies, inflam¬
matory diseases, sterility and various heart
conditions, and form the basis of modern
oral contraceptives.
But when, during the 1930s, the proper¬
ties and nature of steroid hormones were
becoming better known; the sources of
steroids were rare. They were obtained ex¬
clusively from animal sources such as the
adrenal glands of livestock.
It was at this point that the American
chemist Russell Marker appeared on the
scene. In 1935 Marker embarked on
research into steroids at Pennsylvania
State college. He became actively engaged
in the search for a cheap and abundant
source of steroids and concentrated his at¬
tention on certain substances of botanical
origin called sapogenins. By 1940 he had
developed an efficient process for the con¬
version of various sapogenins, including
diosgenin, into progesterone.
Interested in exploring sapogenins of
new types and hoping to discover a prac¬
tical source of diosgenin. Marker launched
a series of extensive botanical collection
trips in the south of the United States and
in Mexico. He worked in collaboration with
seventeen American and Mexican
botanists. Over four hundred species in the
amount of forty thousand kilograms of
plants were collected. About half of the
plant species yielded interesting
substances and a total of twelve new
sapogenins were discovered.
In the early 1940s, Marker transferred his
activities to Mexico. He found an abundant
source of diosgenin in a species of
Dioscorea, known in Mexico under the
name of cabeza de negro (Dioscorea
macrostachya), a vine growing wild in the
jungles of the States of Veracruz and
Chiapas.
On subsequent trips. Marker collected
different specimens of Dioscorea, mainly in
the state of Veracruz. During one of his ex¬
peditions, near Tierra Blanca, he found
Dioscorea composita, called barbasco by
the natives, and which contains nearly five
times as much diosgenin as cabeza de
negro. However, for many years barbasco
could not be exploited commercially, since
there was no road allowing an easy access
to this part of the Mexican jungle. Accor
ding to a saying in Mexico, local Indians
utilized these roots for fishing, as their
saponins are poisonous to fish.
With the help of Mexican collaborators.
Marker produced additional quantities of
progesterone, enough to have a sizable im¬
pact on the world market. This was the
birth of the steroid hormone industry using
plant products as starting materials.'
After developing methods for producing
progesterone from diosgenin, attention
was focused on more difficult undertak¬
ings, such as the production of
testosterone. Barbasco, found to be a bet¬
ter botanical source, richer in diosgenin
than the cabeza de negro, became the
favourite plant for extraction. Since that
time, related Dioscorea species have also
been found in Central and South America,
as well as in China, India and South Africa.
Today although more than eighty million
women are using oral contraceptives,
those in current use are still fairly costly and
women have to be educated in their use.
What is now urgently needed is a cheaper
contraceptive pill with a long-term effect.
Research is continuing and the World
Health Organization (WHO) is conducting a
research programme at ten centres
throughout the world where more than two
hundred new steroid compounds with
potential long-term contraceptive proper¬
ties are being synthesized.
Recently, scientists from the People's
Republic of China have reported significant
anti-fertility effects associated with two
substances, anordrin and dinordrin,
prepared with steroids derived from the
sisal plants Agave sisalana and Agave
americana. These agents, whose anti-
fertility properties have been confirmed by
Chemicals
from crops
In Latin America experiments
are being made in the
cultivation (photo right) of
plants of the Dioscorea
family. These plants yield a
substance called diosgenin, a
form of sapogenin, which
can be converted into the
steroid hormone
progesterone. Progesterone
is used to inhibit ovulation,
and therefore conception, in
women. Diosgenin is
obtainable in large quantities
from the roots of the
barbasco (Dioscorea
composita), a plant (lower
photo) found in the forests of
the State of Veracruz,
Mexico.
*tà
.
v.«3$
Further research carried out in the early
1950s by Carl Djerassi in Mexico (he is now
professor of chemistry at Stanford Univer¬
sity) and an Australian chemist, Arthur
Birch, at Oxford set the stage for Gregory
Pincus to propose an important practical
application for some of these new steroids,
to develop what has come to be known as
"the Pill" and to begin the initial clinical
tests. But the value of these developments
was not limited to the inhibition of the
reproductive process. Pincus concluded
one of his reports as follows : "If we are on
the brink of finding numerous methods for
the inhibition or disruption of various
stages in reproductive processes, it means
that we are also armed with means for the
repair of natural defects. Fertility and sterili¬
ty are two sides of the same coin."
scientists in Sweden and the United
States, constitute a new family of con¬
traceptives with the great advantage of
having to be taken orally only once or twice
instead of the twenty times per month
necessary with the ordinary pill.
Another recent publication from scien¬
tists from the People's Republic of China
has reported that gossypol is being tested
as an orally administered male contracep¬
tive. Gossypol, which is isolated from cot¬
tonseed oil and is not a steroid, begins to
take effect about four to five weeks after
daily oral doses are administered. Gossypol
is a leading candidate for a male contracep¬
tive and could very well be the first
molecule of another interesting chapter of
scientific discoveries.
Pierre Crabbé
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The latticework of lines that decorates the torso of this mother-to-be of an Amazonian Indian tribe, the Je,
was painted with an extract from the genipapo tree. The extract, which turns black in contact with human
skin, also has antibacterial properties.
Plant prophylactics
from tropical Brazil
by Otto Gottlieb and Waiter Mors
OTTO R. GOTTLIEB, a Brazilian of
Czechoslovak origin, is professor of chemistry at
the University of Sao Paulo, Brazil. A member of
the Brazilian Academy of Sciences, he is a
leading specialist in the chemistry of naturalpro'-
ducts and biochemical systematics.
WALTER B. MORS, of Brazil, is a member of
the Brazilian Academy of Sciences and an ex¬
pert at the Ministry of Agriculture. He is a
specialist in the chemistry of natural products
and the economics of botany.
BRAZIL is blessed with a wealth of
plant lifeone estimate suggests
some 120,000 different species
and plant extracts, so botanists and
ethnologists tell us, have played an impor¬
tant part in Brazilian life, being used
throughout the ages as medicines and as
arrow poisons in hunting.
While a great deal of research on these
plants has been carried out in recent years,
much still remains to be done. This is a
matter of urgency since, with the advance
of modern society and the deforestation
this entails, the natural habitat of many
plant species is being destroyed and several
of them are now on the verge of extinction.
The first methodical description of plants
used for medicinal purposes by the in¬
digenous people of Brazil was undertaken
by a scientific mission brought by Maurice
of Nassau to the north-eastern part of the
country during the Dutch occupation
(1630-1654). William Pies, physician to the
expedition, described the most important
medicinal plants, including ipecacuanha,
jaborandi and tobacco.
One hundred and seventy years later,
another mission, brought to the newly-
independent State by Leopoldina of
Austria, the bride of Pedro I, the country's
first emperor, was to play a decisive role in ^
the beginning of scientific activity in Brazil. Y
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
> Two of the mission's most famous
members, the zoologist Johann Baptist
von Spix and the botanist Karl Friedrich
Phillip von Martius, carefully documented
their thorough observation of the country's
natural wealth. Then, in 1847, at the in¬
stigation of Martius, Theodor Peckolt, a
little-known pharmacist from Silesia, arriv¬
ed in Brazil and with admirable drive and
enthusiasm analysed over 6,000 plants,
publishing his results in more than 150
papers.
Although his analyses were necessarily
crude by present-day standards, his
descriptions of a number of chemical en¬
tities have withstood the rigour of modern
scrutiny. Peckolt was probably the first, in
1870, to isolate and describe a new
substance which he extracted from the
bark of the agoniada shrub and which he
named agoniadin. Its structure was
elucidated eighty-eight years later.
Agoniadin and related compounds are an¬
timicrobial and sometimes have a purgative
effect. One related compound, genipin,
isolated in 1960 from the genipapo tree,
forms a black pigment in contact with skin,
a property exploited by Amazonian Indians
in their warpaint.
These and many other investigations on
naturally occurring compounds were spark¬
ed off by observation of the use made by
local populations of the plants from which
they were derived. Thus emetine is obtain¬
ed from ipecacuanha, pilocarpine from
jaborandi and curarizing alkaloids from
several Loganiaceae and Menisper-
maceae ; these are all classic drugs widely
used in modern medicine.
Ipecacuanha is a small herb encountered
in the undergrowth of the virgin forest of
the Mato Grosso. The plant requires special
ecological conditions and its cultivation is
therefore rather difficult. The roots, which
look rather like knotted rope, are the source
of the drug. This is taken in the form of a
powder or syrup as an emetic, or in smaller
doses as an expectorant. Its action is due
to emetine, an alkaloid present in a propor¬
tion of about 1 .5 per cent. Emetine is also a
most important remedy for amoebic
dysentery.
Although ethnobotanical sources con¬
tain many references to Pilocarpus jaboran¬
di and suggestions as to its use in the treat¬
ment of a variety of diseases, a recent
study failed to pin down the use of jaboran¬
di to any particular purpose among South
American Indians. The plant occurs in
north-eastern Brazil which includes Per-
nambuco, the native State of Symphronio
Coutinho who, in 1873, called the attention
of French physicians to the copious
sweating and salivation brought about by
jaborandi leaves. Soon these were used in
the treatment of many diseases. Their ac¬
tive constituent, pilocarpine, was
discovered in 1875 and was used in the
treatment of eye diseases ; it is still used to
alleviate pressure in the eyeball in
glaucoma.
The curares are the famous arrow
poisons of South America. Innocuous if
taken by mouth, a single drop in the blood
stream paralyzes the prey without killing it.
This particular muscle-relaxing action is
due to a blocking of the nervous impulses
at the nerve/muscle junction.
TT^if;,^,,/,.,,,,,,,,,; TU^auwfL/Ttxmùm**.*
^ eunxccti . jy> tiuryu* « Tee t tan* (utinqn* u UL .
The natural curares can be divided into
two classes: tube-curares, which were
kept in bamboo tubes, and calabash-
curares, which were stored in gourds or
clay vessels. They were in use in different
geographical areas, being of different
botanical origin and chemical nature and
being handled in different ways. Curare
and its derivatives, both natural and syn¬
thetic, are used to this day as local
anaesthetics or as pre-anaesthetic muscle
relaxants, as well as for the treatment of
the symptoms of various kinds of spastic
conditions.
Brazilian pharmacologists have only very
recently begun to make detailed studies of
the aetiotropic properties of plant pro¬
ducts, that is to say their action against
organisms which are the causative agents
of diseases such as schistosomiasis and
Chagas' disease which affect millions of
people throughout the world.
Although non-existent in Europe and
North America, schistosomiasis affects one
tenth of the population of Brazil and is
spreading. It is caused by a blood fluke, the
Schistosoma mansoni, which localizes
itself in the liver and the intestines. The
females produce hundreds of eggs which,
by clogging capillaries in the liver, spleen
and intestines, cause severe malfunction of
these organs and, consequently, physical
disability of the host.
In order to complete its larval cycle, the
parasite depends upon an aquatic snail as
an intermediate host. Eggs of the fluke are
carried from the faeces of affected humans
into the waterways in the vicinity of their
dwellings. From these eggs, the first larval
forms are hatched and these infect the
snails. Inside the snail the parasite
multiplies to emerge later as fork-tailed lar-
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
CTfnfn<rT\-oc,/'t/l
4L n*
fie i i'.í: r.tni
Ancient Mayan
medicines
Before the arrival of the Spaniards, the
peoples of Mexico, like those of other ancient
cultures, made use of certain plants for
medicinal purposes. These plants, and the
use to which they were put, were recorded in
the Codex Barberini. This document was
compiled in 1552 in the Náhuatl language by
Martín de la Cruz, "an Indian doctor... whose
sole qualification was his practical
experience", as an inscription on the title
page tells us. It was later translated into Latin
by another Indian, Juan Badiano. The Codex
found its way to Spain where it was acquired
by the papal nuncio Cardinal Francesco
Barberini (hence its name), later passing into
the possession of the Vatican Library. Colour
paintings of plants adorn most of its pages,
three of which are reproduced here. Left,
seven medicinal plants and their names:
temahuiztilli cuahuitl, tlapalcacahuatl,
texcalamacoztli, cohuaxocotl, iztac cuahuitl,
teoezcuahuitl and huitzcuahuitl. Their
therapeutic properties are not given. Above,
the tlatocnochtli, a plant used to treat burns.
Right, the cuauhtla xoxocoyolin, used to
encourage salivation and thus to assuage
thirst.
Photos Almasy, Unesco. © Mexican Institute,
for the Study of Medicinal Plants, Mexico
fttctatrfatti , a&Morsa. */.<*< ^*Utm acma >mu
/.iw ti*>no ?'> * y i r it i
d*£L fib»*- C«?* .u^jHfcrfvn/ifn *******
MA
¿ï mue"»" r>» v -V 4, ' .
cms ' hunntt >jcn btic iffi
vae known as cercariae which eventually
again invade humans by penetration of the
skin.
The problem is being attacked from
every angle : education, hygiene measures,
elimination of snails, etc., but progress in
combating the disease has been extremely
slow. The discovery of chemical agents
which inhibit skin penetration by the larvae
has, however, drawn attention to a possi¬
ble new approach. In practice, application
of these active compounds on to the skin
constitutes, at present, the only possible
prophylactic measure. It has been shown
experimentally in mice, however, that one
compound introduced internally appears to
have an inhibiting effect.
The first compound recognized as in¬
hibiting skin penetration by cercariae was
discovered in 1967 and was derived from
the leguminous species Pterodon
pubescens. Another compound, lapachol,
which occurs in the heartwood of a
number of tropical trees, and several of its
derivatives are among the most active
agents inhibiting skin penetration.
Although lapachol was originally isolated
about one hundred years ago, its phar¬
macological properties and those of many
derivatives and transformation products
have been extensively investigated only in
recent years. They have the effect of
preventing the abnormal division of cells
(and therefore may be of use in cancer
therapy) and they are antimicrobial, as well
as acting as a prophylactic against
schistosomiasis. Lapachol is now produced
in the State of Pernambuco for oral ad¬
ministration as an adjuvant to other drugs
in cancer therapy and; in view of its low
general toxicity, has been approved for w
human clinical trials. *
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
, Recent important studies place this class
of compounds in the foreground among
possible weapons against Chagas' disease,
which affects some ten million Brazilians.
Not only have some of these substances
been shown in laboratory tests to have an
inhibiting effect against Trypanosoma
cruzi, the protozoon which causes Chagas'
disease, one of them has been shown to be
most effective in treating blood intended
for transfusions, which is often the vehicle
by which the disease is transmitted. Hopes
of finding an actual cure for this form of
trypanosomiasis are growing with the pro¬
gress of this research.
With the increasing exploration of
Brazilian forest reserves many extracts
from wood, bark and leaves could be made
available in significant quantities. But use
of the natural substances themselves is not
necessarily to be advocated. In many in¬
stances the plants themselves are rare or
the active agents occur in low concentra¬
tion or are only minor . constituents.
Research, however, is well justified if these
natural substances are looked on as model
compounds whose effects warrant their
synthesis.
An extreme case is that of glaziovine, an
alkaloid from the bark of the very rare tree,
the Ocotea glaziovii (Lauraceae), only two
examples of which are known to the
authors. Glaziovine is a compound which
relieves anxiety states but has no depres¬
sant, muscle-relaxant or anticonvulsant ef¬
fects. It has been shown to counteract
experimentally-induced gastric ulcers in
rats.
This final example shows once more the
fruitful results that can be expected from
work on the chemistry of Brazilian plants
once it is taken up with vigour by
biologists, pharmacologists and the phar¬
maceutical industry. Those instances
where purposeful investigations have been
conducted show how an intensive inter¬
disciplinary approach can lead to a com¬
plete knowledge of the facts. Only in this
way can the immense legacy nature has
bestowed on us be put to good use.
Otto Gottlieb and Walter Mors
The harmful effects of certain plant
extracts can sometimes be
countered by treatment with
derivatives of other plants. The
medicinal properties of the fruit of
the Papaver somniferum or opium
poppy (right) have been known
since antiquity, but unfortunately
abuse of the narcotics derived from
it, such as opium, heroin and
codeine, can lead to addiction. The
traditional healers of Malaysia use
infusions of various plants in the
management of drug-addiction.
One such infusion, an extract of
buah mengkudu, the fruit of the
morinda tree (above) has been
shown to have a general sedative
effect and to alleviate withdrawal
pain in drug-addicts treated with it.
Herbal therapy in the
war on drug addiction
THE poppy may be considered one of the
first medicinal plants known to man.
Sumerian records from 5 000 BC refer
to the poppy and Assyrian tablets record its
medicinal properties ; Hippocrates made
extensive use of opium and its virtues were
extolled by Galen. Indeed the opiates from
the poppy opium, heroin, codeine,
etc.are still among the most powerful
pain-killing, sleep-inducing agents available
to man.
Unfortunately, this boon of nature has
another face ; abuse of these drugs can
lead to physical dependence upon them, or
drug-addiction. In the addict, the cells of
the central nervous system become ac¬
customed to the presence of an opiate and
eventually become unable to function in its
absence, the euphoric effects decline and
the addict requires ever higher doses. If the
supply of the drug ceases, the addict suf¬
fers severe withdrawal effects including
vomiting, convulsions, respiratory failure
and even death.
Drug abuse is a problem which affects, to
some degree, many countries of the world.
Various methods of treatment including the
use of substitute chemical drugs such as
methadone and psycho-social therapy have
been tried but, for a variety of reasons, have
only met with partial success.
In recent years, however, scientists in a
number of countries of the south-east
Asian region have begun to look again at
traditional approaches to the management
of drug addiction. Acupuncture is the most
often quoted example of this approach, but
yoga, meditation, bio-feedback and the use
of various medicinal plant remedies are also
commonly practised. Sometimes, two or
more of these methods are used in com¬
bination.
In Malaysia, as part of the national pro¬
gramme of research on drug addiction, the
National Drug Dependence Research Cen¬
tre, under its director. Dr. V. B. Navaratnam
is making a scientific evaluation of the effi-
cacity of traditional methods of drug-addic¬
tion management, especially those involv¬
ing the use of medicinal plants.
The traditional healers of Malaysia are
reluctant to reveal the exact ingredients of
their medicinal concoctions and each of
them has his own treatment methods. But
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
certain similarities can be observed. All
healers use one or more medicinal "teas"
during the detoxification phase and these
concoctions are given regularly for periods
varying from three days to one month. As
part of the treatment programme a spiritual
component is often included.
In general, the medicinal teas appear to
be made up from roots and tubers and from
the leaves of various herbs. One healer used
a tea consisting of a mixture of water and
the ground-up leaves of a creeping herb and
of turmeric. The same healer indicated that
he used another concoction to' be taken in
small amounts internally and to be applied
externally as an ointment during massage
of the patient. This concoction contained
black turmeric, white turmeric, leaves from
the white hibiscus tree and of the
macarange plant, the roots of the "stone
banana", of rough grass and of the "dragon
shrub", as well as ginger, the fruit of the
Acorus calamus and other ingredients.
The therapeutic value of these teas Is still
not clear. However interviews with pa¬
tients who have undergone treatment by
traditional healers indicate that the con¬
sumption of these concoctions does
alleviate somewhat the severity of
withdrawal pain.
Research Into the pharmacological pro¬
file of some of these concoctions is current¬
ly being carried out at the School of Phar¬
maceutical Sciences of the University of
Science, Penang. Studies have been made
of two teas supplied by traditional healers
and of an extract of buah mengkudu, the
fruit of the morinda tree.
Preliminary results show that the extract
of the pulp of the buah mengkudu sup¬
presses precipitated withdrawal jumping in
mice but has a spasmogenic effect on
guinea pig muscle. It was found that one of
the teas examined also suppressed
precipitated withdrawal jumping. Both teas
had a general depressant action on mice as
well as inducing hypothermia. Both teas
were found to have a marked pain-relieving
effect and to reduce motor activity in ex¬
perimental animals. Both samples were
found to be devoid of any opiate type
substance. Preliminary results therefore
seem to indicate that both teas and the
buah mengkudu extract have the ability to
suppress withdrawal symptoms in addicts
and to induce a general depressant effect.
It is very tempting to assume that other
traditional treatment procedures may have
similar effects. But until such time as ade¬
quate scientific data are made available on
these traditional treatment approaches
they must remain classified among the
many possibilities that have yet to be pro¬
ven or discredited on a scientific basis.
^ÙÊ£.*f¥i
f^jfmoisaiiH.li, Mi/ruM« M4XUII k-ri \*t?ui h'i . HflfrtV
JL »iMM-i ^nnmu jíín^m i-t imh» . hiijkmh iiénê mut
JL fin)i Minn mmiaIi», n4ii.+*nnAtnn u'l í otrtii mt4fu .
', ^L- '*«» 1111*11-11 M*H IVHtlWf, M4INMH ttA*ti.>M\OAI*VH.
NÄy.^rniit'l-fOiiiiiMv.'w itfUrii^i ii*r'i£nÍHfr«mt4
4i'' (<H ,1'otll-l-fl HMII i<r»A<HIIUt MM4tHltUI.«3|K»
' r
Ok-u-MrlfUMtiin. yîiv»»i«.ivi
^ 'fAtr* H«MM<jMMf4.lfl ifrllf¿if H4 Uff 11 {f'ïf
The first page of John the Exarch's Hexameron, a 9th-10th century
Bulgarian religious work with a glossary annex describing the
therapeutic properties of various plants and trees.
Bulgaria's folk remedies
stand the test of time
by Vessel in Petkov
Abasie characteristic of popular
medicine is that the information
it givesabout medicinal plants
and other healing substances, about
hygiene habits, principles and practices
which tend either to preserve good health
or to cure illness has always been handed
down by word of mouth from generation to
generation. Only a very small part of this in¬
formation was ever written down.
VESSELIN PETKOV, of Bulgaria, is a member
of the Bulgarian Academy of Sciences, director
of its Institute ofPhysiology andprofessor of ex¬
perimental and clinical medicine at the Universi¬
ty of Sofia. The author of some three hundred
scientific publications, including several
monographs on medicinal plants, he serves as a
consultant to the World Health Organization.
Folklore is a rich source of information
about the realm of popular medicine. Since
folklore is an art of the people, it often em¬
bodies subjects relating to popular
medicine, subjects which are widespread in
customs, legends, folktales, folksongs,
sayings and proverbs.
Certain elements of phytotherapy, or
plant therapy, reflected in Bulgarian
folklore seem at first sight to be the expres¬
sion of a certain superstition, or an attempt
to conceal man's inability, because of his
ignorance, to explain natural phenomena.
Folktales and folksongs tell us that the
miraculous power of such and such a sim¬
ple can be relied upon only if it is plucked i
"at dead of night", at dawn, as the first I
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
cock crows, or else in a place that is
"secret, shady and damp". Other simples
must be picked at a specified time of year,
for instance at the Feast of Enio, the an¬
niversary of Krastu or the birthday of the
Holy Virgin, or they must be gathered in
certain clearly defined areas.
Nowadays, we are in possession of an
abundance of scientific data which prove
that the sun, the temperature, the quality
of the soil, the time of day, and the stage of
development of the plant all have an impor¬
tant effect upon the plant's metabolism
and, more specifically, on the biosynthesis
(or natural formation) of active biological
components and on the changes in the
plant's cycle which take place as these
components are distributed to different
parts of the plant the roots, leaves,
flowers, or fruit.
In the early morning, the leaves of
stramohy or thorn-apple are much richer in
alkaloids than in the evening. Certain other
active substances react in the opposite
way. For instance foxglove or digitalis
leaves lack glycosides at night, because
glycosides decompose at night. Thus
leaves gathered in the afternoon have a far
higher glucose content than those
gathered in the morning. In general, plants
growing in shady areas contain far more
alkaloids.
Biochemical studies of the various stages
of a plant's development demand that the
exact timing of gathering any plant be
specified, so that the greatest quantity of
the active substances can be extracted.
These timings coincide in most cases with
the requirements specified in folklore.
In some areas of Bulgaria, the snowdrop
is completely lacking in its active
therapeutic alkaloid, known as galantine;
in some areas, camomile plants do not con¬
tain the substances which are the source of
camomile's healing properties. In some
places, wild rose-hips are very rich in
Vitamin C, while in other places this
vitamin is almost totally absent. In general,
the directions given in popular medicine,
though they may appear to spring from
superstitious mysticism, are in fact found¬
ed on wide popular experience, which has
been accumulated and passed on from
generation to generation.
The use of herbs as preventive and heal¬
ing agents in the treatment of a variety of
ailments in Bulgaria has its roots.far back in
the history of Bulgarian popular medicine.
In his nine-volume "History of Plants", the
Greek philosopher Theophrastus tells us
that Thrace was a region extremely rich in
healing herbs. And Dioscorides, a Roman
military doctor although Greek by birth,
describes in his work "On Medical
Matters", written in Greek, a great many
plants which were used by the Thracians in
medicine. Dioscorides' indications were
widely used by Avicenna and by Galen as
well as by almost all doctors in medieval
times. Thus early Thracian experience in
medicinal plants became part of the body
of European medicine.
The Slavs too were happy to combine
magic with the use of healing methods
originating from plants. They used fewer
herbal plants than other peoples and far
more leaves and fruits of forest trees elm.
pine, fir, juniper, willow, ash, sycamore
lime, hawthorn, cornel, and so on. The
Slavs also used poppy and hemp as
anaesthetics.
Information about the use of medicinal
plants in the first Bulgarian State, which
. was founded in the 7th century, has also
come down to us. The glossary, given as
an annex to John the Exarch's "Hex-
ameron" (now preserved in the British
Museum), describes pleurisy and a treat¬
ment for it consisting of the leaves and
fruits of willow, poplar and hellebore, the
first two of which both contain salicylates.
John of Rila (early 11th century to mid-
12th century), later canonized by the
Bulgarian church, was a famous healer
known for his ability to treat all sorts of
illnesses with medicinal plants.
recognized throughout the world as a
Bulgarian contribution to European
medicine, was also apparently practised by
the ancient Bulgarian healers. Long before
Ivan Raev, they had been using extracts of
belladonna for chronic sufferers from
locomotive troubles (quite probably various
types of Parkinson's Disease) in quantities
which provoked a temporary dementia in
the patients followed by a complete cure.
Today, after a long period during which
it was fashionable to attribute absolute
power to the efficacy of synthetic
medicine, to the point of excluding all the
possibilities of natural products, en¬
thusiasm for medicines of herbal origin is
increasing. Scientific institutes and phar¬
maceutical companies from all countries
are studying plants as potential sources of
new therapeutic products.
'In poison
there is physic'
Because of their often deadly effects,
poisonous plants and animals played an
important role in the life of early man.
Surrounded with an aura of mystery and
superstition, poisons were used in rituals
and ordeals, arrows were tipped with
poison extracts and venomous snakes
often figured in religious beliefs and
ceremonies. As medicine gradually
became dissociated from magic and
religion, poisons and their antidotes
were studied more intensively and
recorded In medical manuals. Among
ancient records that have survived are
two works in verse by the 2nd-century
BC Greek poet and physician Nicander
of Colophon: the Theriaca, on the nature
of venomous animals and the wounds
they inflict, and the Alexipharmaca, on
poisons and their antidotes. Right, 12th-
century Byzantine illustrations of the
Theriaca which retain the flavour of the
ancient Greek originals. But poisons can
heal as well as harm. Today curare
arrow poisons are used as muscle
relaxants and anaesthetics and the
poison of the cobra has pain-killing
properties.
. ...
.a
Vassily the Healer, a leader of the
Bogomil movement, who was burned as a
heretic in Constantinople in 1114, was also
a healer of great renown. The Bogomil
talent for healing is well portrayed by the
fact that the chroniclers describe them as
preachers travelling from village to village,
with two bags slung across their shoulders,
one containing bread, the other medicinal
herbs.
A more recen i example is that of the
Bulgarian method of treatment for Parkin¬
son's Disease. The inventor of this
therapeutic method, which was based on
an infusion in wine of the roots of belladon¬
na (Deadly Nightshade), was the healer
Ivan Raev. From 1928 to 1933, his method
was tested in a number of clinics, mainly in
Italy, but also in Germany and other
Western European countries, and became
known as the best method at the time for
the treatment of Parkinson's Disease.
It is interesting to note that this method.
It is now recognized that biogenesis,
which operates in plants by the assimilation
of simple molecules into infinitely com¬
plicated plant systems, has possibilities far
beyond those of any modern chemical fac¬
tory. The plant world provides an inex¬
haustible fund of medicines. The active
biological substances originating from
plants are capable of further chemical
transformations, and are excellent models
for new synthetic programmes. The fairly
recent discovery of a drug as effective as
Reserpine, which is of vegetable origin, as
well as the fact that certain alkaloids con¬
tained in plants have been found to be ef¬
fective remedies against cancer, have
together provoked a complete reversal of
attitude on the part of many experts
towards the importance of herbal
treatments in modern medicine. Scientists
and medical men alike have given up their
former disdain, which was the required at¬
titude in respectable scientific circles,
towards the therapeutic properties of
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
medicinal plants. A new era has begun, an
era of revolutionary discoveries in the plant
world which have greatly benefited
medicine, a new blossoming of "green
medicine".
This revived interest in the healing
powers of medicinal plants has given birth
to the question of which directions should
be taken to obtain the greatest success in
the experimental work now being under¬
taken. For it is unlikely that we shall ever
succeed in studying in depth every one of
the 500,000 different vegetable species
growing on our planet, even if the entire
human race were to join forces on the pro¬
ject. It therefore seemed logical to adopt
the policy of concentrating research on
plants traditionally used in popular
medicine, and therefore tried and tested by
many centuries of common experience.
other plants or simples which were used in
Bulgarian popular medicine, has proved
that forty of them have the effect of
decreasing blood pressure, ten can arrest
intestinal spasms, and approximately fifty
have a germicidal action more powerful
than that of the strongest chemical
medicines. The studies have also confirm¬
ed the healing properties of certain plants
described by popular medicine, which are
used against worms and disorders of the
bile system, and as tranquillizers.
But at the same time, certain medicinal
plants have not produced the effects which
popular medicine attributes to them, and
others have even proved dangerous. This is
why it is the doctor's duty to oppose the in¬
discriminate use of remedies and methods
advocated by popular medicine. Each
remedy must be subjected to a detailed ex-
alien to it. This explains the fact that plant
therapy is less harmful and causes fewer
side-effects than modern chemical drugs.
The use of medicinal plants In treatment
works on the organism by means of a com¬
pound of active or apparently inactive
biological substances. A great many of
these "apparently inactive" substances,
known in the past as "ballast substances",
retard or accelerate the reabsorption by the
tissues of the active substances, and also
their evacuation in the urine or the bile.
Their action also causes useful changes
in the effects of the main active biological
components in the medicinal plants. In re¬
cent years it has been discovered that a
great many medicinal plants contain,
alongside their primary active substance, a
series of other biological components.
Photos © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
A few examples will serve to illustrate the
wide horizons which this approach makes
possible.
Garlic is widely used by the Bulgarian
people as a remedy for a great many
diseases. Judging from popular descrip¬
tions of these diseases, one can infer that
they consist of infectious disorders of the
digestive and respiratory tracts, worms,
hypertension and arteriosclerosis. Modern
studies by Bulgarian specialists have prov¬
ed that garlic contains substances with a
very strong antimicrobial action and is in¬
deed an effective remedy against worms
and that it retards the development of
arteriosclerosis. Garlic is also an excellent
preventive against chronic lead poisoning,
and can also be a cure when the condition
has already developed. Another interesting
fact, and one which could have economic
importance, is the stimulating effect which
garlic can have on the growth of animals.
The study of a few hundred herbs and
amination, and no treatment should be ap¬
plied without a medical prescription.
It is not a question of choosing between
medicinal plants and chemical substances
isolated from natural products. Any direct
opposition of these two groups would be
misplaced, as they are not mutually ex¬
clusive but, on the contrary, if cleverly used
by the doctor, can be complementary.
At the present stage of development of
pharmacotherapy, it is quite out of the
question to try to substitute herbal
remedies for the efficient medicines we
have in our possession to fight against
most diseases. But we must recognize that
in a not inconsiderable number of cases,
plant therapy provides undeniable advan¬
tages as against modern drugs. Taking into
account the fact that the active biological
substances found in plants are the product
of the metabolism of a living organism, the
human body is able to assimilate a great
many of them more naturally than it can
assimilate synthetic medicines which are
some of which react on the biosynthesis of
proteins, stimulating the synthesis of
antibodies and reinforcing the system's
immunities.
This also explains why the effects of
numerous medicinal plants like belladonna,
garlic, tea, coffee, St. John's wort and
others are very different from the
therapeutic effects of chemical products
extracted from the plants such as atropine,
hypericin, polysulphides and caffeine.
There is every reason to suppose that
medicinal plants and the active biological
substances which are extracted from them,
will gain in importance every year. A very
powerful factor in this area would be a
multidisciplinary approach to the scientific
study of medicinal plants, and the number
of scientists using this approach is increas¬
ing every day. The successes already
achieved by plant chemistry have a decisive
part to play in widening the use of
medicinal plants in modern medicine.
Vesselin Petkov
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
African medicinal plants... continue* *om page 19
large and very important class of drugs and
have a wide range of therapeutic and other
uses (as oral contraceptives for example),
are generally manufactured by processes
that originate from the saponin diosgenin,
a substance available in large quantities
from a Mexican yam species. Unfortunate¬
ly African yam species contain very low
quantities of this saponin. But many
African plants are rich in steroidal saponins
and continued search might reveal new
sources of this or other steroids that might
serve as starting materials for the synthesis
of steroidal or other drugs.
Many interesting new compounds have
been discovered in the last decade or two
from African medicinal plants as a result of
the application of modern methods of
isolation and structural elucidation. While
hardly any of these compounds has found
clinical application in modern medicine,
some of them have shown activities which
give credibility' to the use of the plants in
traditional medicine.
An example from our own work in
Ibadan is our investigation of the fruit of
Xy/opia aethiopica. The dried fruits of this
plant are used in many parts of Africa as a
spice and in many folk medicinal prepara¬
tions. We investigated the dried fruits and
found, besides large quantities of an essen¬
tial oil, an acid component obtainable in
good yields of up to 1.5%. The new com¬
pound was named xylopic acid and its
structure determined by spectroscopic
analysis and chemical degradation.
Publication of our work eventually
prompted other researchers in Ghana to
study the antimicrobial properties of ex¬
tracts of the dried fruits and they found
xylopic acid very active against two
bacteria, Staphylococcus aureus and
Bacillus subtilis, and the yeast Candida
albicans. The demonstration of an¬
timicrobial activity by xylopic acid against
this yeast, a common agent of vaginal in¬
fections, is of interest because of the use of
the dried fruits in traditional obstetrics and
preparations of vaginal douches.
There has also been considerable interest
in alkaloids leading to the isolation of a
large number of either known or derivatives
of otherwise well-known classes of
alkaloids, such as the alkaloid funiferine
from the roots of Tiliacora funifera which
exhibits significant anti-leukaemia and
antibacterial activity.
Most of the work described above was
prompted either by a reputed use in folk
medicine or an interest in a particular class
of compounds or groups of plants. But the
studies were not directed at isolating com¬
pounds of any specific activity and were
therefore not monitored by bioassays.
They consisted usually of extraction with
solvent, separation of the fractions by a
chromatographic process and isolation of
the compounds that happened to be ac¬
cessible usually through crystallization. The
chances of this method of investigation
leading to any further results of interest are
now very small, one might almost say
negligible.
This is not because the vast resources of
the plant kingdom have been fully tap¬
ped is very far from being the case.
About the middle of this century there was
a fall in interest in plants as a source of new
drugs because of advances in the ability of
the chemist to synthesize new compounds.
However the success rate in finding new
drugs from such purely synthetic com¬
pounds has been very low and since the
1960s there has been a growing revival of
interest in plants as a source of new
biologically active substances.
The approach is however different from
the classical one. Extraction is carried out
with well defined objectives, as part of a
search for substances possessing
specifically selected activities. The extrac¬
tion and fractionation procedures are
therefore monitored and guided by con¬
tinual bioassays of the various fractions,
until the active substance is isolated.
By this method active compounds have
been discovered which would otherwise
have been overlooked because of their oc¬
curence in minute quantities. A well-known
example in the field of anti-cancer drugs is
the alkaloid vincristine which was isolated
from Catharanthus roseus.
Vincristine is now one of the drugs in
clinical use for treating certain forms of
leukaemia. Since the discovery Of vin¬
cristine there has been an intensive search
for anti-cancer drugs from plants, guided
by bioassays at every stage of the frac¬
tionation procedures. Many tens of
thousands of plants have been investigated
by this method including several thousands
of African plants. Most of the investiga¬
tions even of the African plants are taking
place in the U.S.A. and Europe and a large
number of active anti-cancer compounds
have already been discovered, which are
undergoing further studies to determine
Photo L. Allorge,
© National Museum of Natural History, Paris
When a German botanist landed on one of the
Molucca islands in the Malay Archipelago, in
1742, the inhabitants told him of the virtues of a
small tree with red fruit and yellowish wood
Ochrosia, the plant that cures. More than two
centuries later, extracts derived from Ochrosia
appear to offer hope of beneficial results in the
treatment of certain types of cancers. (See back
cover for details of the action of a compound
derived from a plant of the Ochrosia genera).
their suitability as potential therapeutic
agents.
At the same time these compounds have
provided incentives for the synthesis of
modified derivatives which might have
superior properties to the original natural
products. One of the most promising of
these new anti-cancer compounds is the
macrolide maytansine isolated from a
Kenyan medicinal plant Maytenus ovatus.
Maytansine occurs in such small quantities
that it might never have been found if the
investigation of the plant had not been
directed towards the isolation of an anti¬
cancer agent and the fractionation of the
extract guided by bioassay.
At present intensive work is going on to
develop an efficient synthesis to avoid the
tedious extraction procedure. This is to
say, if it does prove successful as a
therapeutic agent, there is not likely to be a
booming trade in the export of the plant or
its extracts, let alone the compound, from
Africa to the rest of the world. In other
words, if maytansine turns out to be effec¬
tive in therapy, a synthetic procedure
would probably have been developed in the
meantime for preparing the compound,
which would make it available more cheap¬
ly and in larger quantities than would other¬
wise be possible by extraction from the
plant.
The lesson for African scientists is clear.
They do not have a monopoly of the study
of African medicinal plants. The old screen¬
ing techniques as well as the blind frac¬
tionation of extractives without bioassay
are of little interest. The traditional use of a
plant in folk medicine serves only as an in¬
dication of the possible occurrence of ac¬
tive substances whose significance for
modern medicine may not necessarily be
related to the traditional use of the plant in
folk medicine.
Extraction and fractionation must be
directed towards a clearly defined objective
of isolating compounds possessing a
specific activity of interest. Consequently
the fractionation procedure must be
monitored by bioassays of each of the frac¬
tions. This implies close collaboration bet¬
ween chemists and scientists trained in the
life sciences. If close day-to-day collabora¬
tion between chemists and life scientists is
not practicable, an alternative is to develop
simple bioassay techniques that can be car¬
ried out in a chemical laboratory by a
chemist during fractionation of extracts.
Such simple bioassay techniques need
not meet all the requirements for full in¬
vestigation of the biological activity in
which the chemist is interested, but need
only be adequate to give an indication of
activity in a fraction, leaving detailed in¬
vestigation of the activity to be carried out
later by the appropriate life scientist after
isolation of the pure compound. It is only
by such an approach that African scientists
can expect to contribute to the worldwide
search for new substances of medicinal
and other economic value which African
medicinal plants have and without doubt
will continue to afford.
Donald E.U. Ekong
o
z
<
5
q
3
O
(3
Q
DC
<
Q
O
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
nature and
resources
J4.V.-J.I. ,t . r. ,..
For f/iose w/jo care about the environment...
Unesco's quarterly NATURE AND RESOURCES
offers :
D articles by leading natural and social scientists which
assess the impact of man on the biosphere, review the
latest research projects and findings on conservation
and environmental problems, and survey new
developments in resource management;
D a unique and comprehensive book-review section
covering environmental publications;
D news items and information about forthcoming inter¬
national symposia, conferences and training courses.
NATURE AND RESOURCES also incorporates the
bulletins of Unesco's three major intergovernmen¬
tal scientific co-operation programmes : the Man
and the Biosphere Programme, the International
Hydrological Programme and the International
Geological Correlation Programme.
Published quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Price, single issue : 6.50 French francs
Yearly subscription : 20 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors In countries not lis¬
ted, along with subscription rates in local cur¬
rency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria!, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine StEeet West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CHINA. China Nationaln. - CANADA. Renouf Publis¬
hing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Oue.
H3H 1M7. - CHINA. China National Publications Import Cor¬
poration, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking.
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra: Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok
Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1;
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book Et
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House,
New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedla Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL. A.B.C
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71, Allenby Road, Tel-Aviv
61000. - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box
366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo 100-91. - KENYA. East
African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942,
Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35,
Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-
Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot
8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas,
26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only:
Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007.
Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van
Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. -
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin:
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book 'Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Llvraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 121 1 , Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Scientific study of the chemistry of medicinal plants is opening up new horizons in chemotherapy.
Natural compounds isolated from these plants, or synthetic compounds modelled on them, can offer
powerful new weapons in the fight against disease. Scientists have, for example, recently isolated
compounds from plants that inhibit mitosis, or cell division. Cell division is part of the normal life
process, but these compounds offer hope for treatment of the abnormal division of cells in some forms
of cancer, which has been described as "mitosis gone mad". Photo shows root cells of a garlic plant
after short experimental treatment with a compound derived from a plant of the Apocynaceae family. In
the oblong, palm-tree-like cell, at centre, the process of splitting has been disturbed by the application
of the compound; extended treatment will further disturb and then block the cell division process.
Photo CP. Boumique, Laboratoire de Botanique. Faculté de Pharmacie. Paris
00^*
%
m
I
H
K
V*
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
July 1979
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
fromnews
unesco
Science Takes
Limelight
in Unesco
Conferences,
Ceremonies
May could have been designated
"science month" at Unesco,
embracing as it did a wide variety of
activities aimed at intensifying the
Organization's work in this field.
The month opened with the
Director-General, Mr. Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, reporting to the
Executive Board on Unesco's
preparations for the U.N. Conference
on Science and Technology for
Development (UNCSTD). It ended
with UNISIST II, the
Intergovernmental Conference on
Scientific and Technological
Information for Development, which
itself is a major Unesco contribution
to the work of UNCSTD. In between
there were such events as a public
ceremony at Unesco Headquarters to
mark the centenary of the birth of
Albert Einstein, a three-day meeting of
60 of the world's leading scientists to
discuss future prospects for
international scientific cooperation, a
session of the bureau of the
International Co-ordinating Council
for the Man and the Biosphere
Programme, and a visit by the
Director-General to the French Bureau
des Recherches Géologiques et
Minières (BRGM) where he presided a
panel discussion on the unification and
development of earth sciences at the
international level.
Quite apart from the events at
headquarters there were meetings
Photo Unesco/ Dominique Roger
Unesco Director-General Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow presents a medal to Prof. P. A.M.
Dirac, Nobel prize-winning physicist and former associate of Albert Einstein, at
Einstein ceremony 9 May at Unesco Headquarters.
concerned with Unesco's work in
science and technology policies,
hydrology and oceanography in such
cities as Dortmund (FRG), Ottawa
(Canada) and Dakar (Senegal).
In its discussion of the UNCSTD
conference, which is to take place in
Vienna in August, the Executive Board
endorsed the Director-General's view
that it would be undesirable to create
new structures to deal with science
which would be "ineffectual and
unnecessarily expensive", and declared
that it should be the responsibility of
the Specialized Agencies, particularly
Unesco, to translate the results of the
Conference into action.
At the ceremony marking the
Einstein centenary, Mr. M'Bow hailed
the late physicist as not only a great
scientist but "a man of peace and
freedom" who strongly supported
Unesco and who "defended the idea
of giving to the United Nations the
prerogatives of a supranational system,
the only one which he considered
capable of instituting and supervising a
just and lasting peace."
One of Einstein's disciples and
colleagues, Prof. P.A.M. Dirac,
winner of the Nobel Prize for physics
in 1933, recalled the controversy with
Niels Bohr over the interpretation of
the findings of quantum mechanics
that marked the latter period of
Einstein's life.
Einstein's love of beautiful
mathematical equations, said Dirac,
made it difficult for him to accept the
probability calculations of standard
quantum mechanics. "They lead to
infinities and are therefore illogical",
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
he added. "I agree with Einstein. I
think he will turn out to be right in
the end if a better quantum mechanics
is achieved."
Dirac, who retired from Cambridge
University and now is professor of
physics at Florida State University in
Tallahassee, demonstrated how
modern physics still follows the paths
that Einstein traced. This theme was
then taken up by Prof. Abdus Salam,
director of the International Centre
for Theoretical Physics at Trieste, who
spoke of "Einstein's last dream, the
space-time unification of fundamental
forces."
Salam, who is also associated with
Imperial College in London, ended his
talk with the reminder that Einstein
might have been lost if he had been
born in a developing country. He
recalled the genius's difficulties with
his teachers and in obtaining a Ph. D.
and said : "Every one of the
discouragements he suffered is a
norm for a scientist in a developing
country. And in a developed country
today, would an Einstein, with his
commitment to science for its own
sake, fare any better?"
The 60 leading scientists who took
advantage of the Einstein observance
for a three-day exchange of views on
enhancing international cooperation in
science, included three other Nobel
Prize winners besides Prof. Dirac.
They were Hannes Alfven of Sweden,
Alfred Kastler from France, and
Academician A.M. Prokhorov from
the USSR.
Chairman of the meeting was
M.G.K. Menon from India, who is
also chairman of the preparatory
commission for UNCSTD, and one
purpose of the meeting was to help
make known to UNCSTD the views of
the world scientific community.
These views, as expressed in a
series of recommendations, showed
how attitudes towards science and
technology as factors for development
have changed since the first UN
conference on this topic was held in
1963 in Geneva. At that time, the
Geneva conference's chairman, Carlos
Chagas of Brazil, told the Paris
meeting, it was generally believed that
developing nations had only to shop
around the "supermarket" of science
and technology for solutions to their
problems.
At the end of the Seventies, this
attitude is long dead. As J.F. Da
Costa, secretary-general of the
UNCSTD conference remarked, it now
seems clear that science and
technology cannot be separated from
their cultural and social context. In
other words, they cannot be imported,
they must be grown at home.
But how? Here, Prof. Salam, a
Pakistani, remarked that in a
developing country like his, there is
only one research physicist for every
million inhabitants, as compared with
one for 10,000 in the United States.
Without quantity, he felt, there is little
hope of getting quality in science.
The meeting recommended the
strengthening of international and
regional scientific centres and
expansion of this form of international
co-operation into other scientific
fields. Suggestions were also made for
ways to enable leading scientists from
developed countries to spend at least
part of the year in developing
countries and for "Einstein
fellowships" to allow young scientists
from those countries to work abroad.
There was an undercurrent of
criticism of indiscriminate introduction
of technology which, as was said,
tends further to enrich the rich and
impoverish the poor in the developing
countries. Instead, science should
work at local levels.
An example was mentioned by S.
Bhagavantam of India, president of
the Committee on Science and
Technology in Developing Countries
of the International Council of
Scientific Unions. He related how
research by Malaysian scientists has
quintupled the yield of rubber trees
and enabled natural rubber to hold its
own against competition by synthetics.
He regretted that similar research had
not done the same for jute, cotton and
the coconut palm.
This concern was reflected in the
meeting's recommendation that
scientific research in developing
countries be concentrated on
maximizing the return from indigenous
resources. Such needs, Menon stated,
explain why scientists in developing
countries may apparently show less
interest in pollution or
overconsumption of energy,when the
immediate demand is for basic food
and shelter.
Decisions concerning research
priorities must be made with the help
of scientists in the councils of
government, the meeting declared,
after several participants warned that
economists should not monopolize
planning for science and technology.
Winners Named in
Art Contest for
International Year
of the Child
A four-year old boy from Japan, a
nine-year old Austrian girl, and a
Peruvian boy, aged 1 1 , were among
the winners announced in May of a
children's art contest organized by
Unesco, Unicef and the United
Nations High Commission for
Refugees (UNHCR).
More than 600,000 pictures on the
theme "My life in the year 2000" were
submitted by children aged four to
twelve in 84 countries, including
children living in refugee camps.
The winners, selected by an
international jury at Unesco
headquarters, were : a group of nine-
year-old handicapped children in
Berlin (German Democratic Republic) ;
Claudia Chesi (Austria, 9) ; Panayota
Demetriou (Cyprus, 11); Nipa Sae
Lim (Thailand, 11); Torben Larsen
(Denmark, 8) ; Ito Tsuyoshi (Japan,
4) ; Hu Xiaozhou (China, 6) ; Park
Jeong Je (Republic of Korea, 6) ; Tang
Che Ye (Singapore, 7), and Marco
Antonio Acuna Picon (Peru, 11). An
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
IP**
EZHl
1 m *' ^1
MM i B B iiiiiimimm^M
i flit * "J «
"jffpl
lit '
^ r ** fcÄ
'^^Sh.^ j
111«
Photo Unesco/ Dominique Roger
11th prize was awarded by the
International Fund for the Promotion
of Culture to Koumidou Antri, a nine-
year-old in a refugee camp in Limasol,
Cyprus.
This autumn, the prize-winners will
fly to Paris on tickets provided by Air
France, for a week's stay during which
they will work together on a design to
decorate Unesco headquarters and
mark the International Year of the
Child. Their winning entries were on
display at Unesco from May 29 to
June 8.
Among the members of the jury
were Madame Amadou-Mahtar
M' Bow, wife of the Director-General
Members of the jury study a selection from the more than 600,000 entries in a
children's drawing contest sponsored by Unesco, Unicef and the U.N. High
Commission for Refugees.
of Unesco, Princess Caroline of
Monaco, Mr. J.J. Dubois,
representing the President of Air
France, H.E. F. N'Sougan
Agblemagnon, Togo Permanent
Delegate to Unesco and Madame Leda
Mileva, former Bulgarian Permanent
Delegate. Italian publisher, Mr. Gino
Nebiolo, Mr. Peter David of the
European Secretariat for International
Year of the Child, Mr. Baron-
Rebouard, France, Vice-President of
the International Association of Art,
and Mr. Dunbar Marshall Malagola,
its Secretary General, were also on the
jury, along with eight painters : Mr.
I.C. Glazounov (USSR), Mr. Oguiss
(Japan), Mr. Svend Otto (Denmark),
Mrs. Alicia Penalba (Argentina), Mr.
Adam Saulnier (France), Mrs. M.
Torres (Mexico), Mr. Hédi Turki
(Tunisia) and Mr. Zao Wu Ki (China).
UNISIST to be
Oriented Towards
Use for
Development
Planning
A shift in emphasis in the
UNISIST programme is slated to take
place as one result of the recent
intergovernmental conference on
scientific and technological
information for development
(UNISIST II). Whereas up to now the
programme has been concerned chiefly
with scientific and technological
information for the advancement of
science, it will now be concerned with
the use of this information as an
essential but increasingly complex tool
in the development process.
"Scientific and technological
information is a national and
international resource", declared one
recommendation of the conference.
"The progress of science and
technology depends to a large extent
upon access to and effective utilization
of this resource, and together with
economic, social and cultural
information, it constitutes a major
factor for accelerating the
development process. All countries
have the same right to full access to
the resources of scientific and
technological information and need
the necessary means to adapt, utilize
and absorb this information to serve
their development."
Some 300 delegates and observers
from 90 countries and about 40
international organizations attended
the week-long conference at Unesco
headquarters in Paris. They reviewed
the achievements of the UNISIST
programme to date and made
recommendations for future strategy
in this area.
They also recommended that the
forthcoming U.N. conference on
science and technology for
development (UNCSTD) "take full
advantage of the considerable
experience accumulated by Unesco
through UNISIST" and "avoid the
creation of new programmes and
structures within the United Nations
system which could duplicate the work
of existing agencies."
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Executive
Board Endorses
Aid to Yugoslavia
The 107th session of Unesco's
Executive Board, meeting in Paris,
unanimously supported a proposal by
the Director-General to launch a world
appeal for the protection and
conservation of cultural monuments
and the reconstruction of scientific
and educational institutions in
earthquake-ravaged Montenegro.
This followed Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M' Bow's account to the Board of a
visit to the devastated area of
Yugoslavia shortly after the April 15
earthquake. The Board also invited the
Director-General to examine the
possibility of creating a network of
seismic observation stations in the
Balkans and the Mediterranean and to
consult with Member States and UN
agencies to see whether a relief fund
for natural disasters might be
established to permit speedy aid in
Unesco's fields of competence.
In his appeal, launched on 28 May,
the Director-General called upon
governments, public and private
institutions and individuals the world
over to give their aid, and urged
experts working with Unesco on the
safeguard of humanity's cultural
heritage to mobilize public opinion on
behalf of Montenegro as well as
offering their expert services.
Museums, art galleries^ and libraries
could also give appropriate assistance,
he said.
Mr. M' Bow also appealed to
teachers, students and, in the current
International Year of the Child, to all
the children of the world to organize
collections to contribute to the
reconstruction of educational facilities
in Montenegro.
Another proposal of the Director-
General also received unanimous
support of the Executive Board. He
was authorized to devote to the least
developed countries some $3 million
earned as interest on loans granted. by
some Member States to the
Organization.
A new prize for meritorious work
in promoting literacy was established
following the Board's acceptance of an
offer from the International Reading
Association to provide $5,000 yearly
for such a prize.
On the agenda of the Board, which
met under the chairmanship of
Mr. Chams Eldine El Wakil of Egypt,
were questions ranging through
Unesco's fields of competence in
education, science, culture,
communication and the social sciences
to problems of human rights and
peace.
One resolution, recognizing the
"universal scope of Unesco's mission"
in the field of human rights, invited
the Director-General to consult the
UN Secretary-General to determine to
what extent Chilean exiles belonging to
Unesco's specific fields of competence
might receive assistance from the
United Nations Trust Fund.
"Speedy and continuing action"
taken by the Director-General at the
request of the Lebanese Government
in fields of priority assistance was
noted by the Board, which requested
the Director-General to provide
increased assistance. Another
resolution noted from the report of a
mission sent by the Director-General
to Jerusalem, that Israel had not
undertaken to refrain finally from
archaeological excavations in the Old
City and invited the Director-General
to continue his efforts with a view to
the implementation of the resolution
adopted by the last General
Conference on the preservation of the
city's cultural heritage.
Two new members were
unanimously elected to the 45-seat
Executive Board during the session :
Mrs. Josefa Maria Prado, replacing
Mr. Horacio Bustamante of Panama,
and Mr. Daoed Joesoef of Indonesia,
replacing Mr. Sjarif Thajeb. The 108th
session of the Executive Board will
begin on 19 September 1979.
Paris Meeting
Calls For Better
Protection of
Newsmen
Journalists exercise "the most
dangerous profession ih the world"
and must be protected in their
personal and professional integrity.
This was the principal conclusion
reached by representatives of 30
international press and broadcasting
organizations at a meeting in Paris, 17
and 18 May, convened by Mr. Sean
MacBride, chairman of the Unesco-
sponsored International Commission
for the Study of Communication
Problems. The aim of the seminar was
to obtain the views of professional
organizations on recommendations
regarding the protection of journalists
which might be included in the
Commission's final report. Mr.
MacBride emphasized that the
Commission had not yet adopted a
position on the subject and was
seeking advice from journalists
themselves in this connexion.
He was encouraged by the fact that
the meeting underlined the importance
of protecting journalists on dangerous
missions. Several participants had also
stressed the importance of investigative
journalism and the special need for
protection of investigative journalists.
While agreeing that the mass media
have a moral responsibility to inform
the public honestly and truthfully
about world events, the participants in
general did not share the view that the
protection of journalists should be tied
to their duties and responsibilities. In
addition, given the plurality and
diversity of legal, political and
ideological systems in the world, they
saw no possibility of an international
code of ethics for the journalistic
profession at the present time.
National voluntary codes of ethics,
established by professional
organizations, could be of value,
however, they said, and might possibly
be worked on later ih some regions.
IV
]]>
</page>
</document>
