<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074786eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Q)UrÍer A window
open on the world
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
^
«RS,,f
SS
TREASURES
O F
WORLD ART
Romania
Golden helmet of the Getae
This gold helmet, unearthed at Cotznofanechti in Romania, was fashioned in the 5th century
B.C. during the "Thraco-Getic" period of Romanian history. (The Getae, ancestors of the
modern Romanians, were a people of Thracian origin.) The magnificently worked repoussé
motifs, especially the sacrificial scenes on the cheekpieces, suggest that the helmet (25 cms
high) might have had a ritual religious use.
Photo r Bulloz. Paris, National Museum of Antiquities. Bucharest
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COUI*Íer
MARCH 19 7 8 3 1 S T YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 18 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian Turkish
Hindi Urdu
Tamil Catalan
Hebrew Bahasa-
Persian " Malaysia
Dutch
Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 Issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of Issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100, U.S.A. ; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
Managing
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Editors
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Édition
Edition
Edition
: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
: Werner Merkli (Berne)
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
: Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition :
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
8 7
page
\/rONE MAN'S LUXURY IS ANOTHER MAN'S NEED
/\ Bringing environmental issues into focus
' ' by Peter J. Fensham
V/lNFORMATION, PLEASE...
/\ Towards a world science information network
I by Yuri I. Litukhin
10 MANKIND'S MEMORY BANKS
Archives from the clay tablet to the computer
by Jean Favier
JB/'cATALAN MASTERS OF MODERN ART
by Alexandre Cirici
18 THE ANONYMOUS PAINTERS
OF MEDIEVAL CATALONIA
Four pages in colour
24 GAUDI'S 'CATHEDRAL OF THE POOR'
Photo story
28 THE WHYS AND WHEREFORES
OF EDUCATION TOMORROW
by Charles Hummelfc
31 JULES VERNE
Seer of the Space Age
,x by Alain Bombard
38 HUNDREDTH ISSUE OF 'DIOGENES'
by Jean d'Ormesson
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
ROMANIA: Golden helmet of the Getae
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
Cover
This month's cover was specially created for
the Unesco Courier by the Catalan painter
Joan Miró, one of the world's greatest living
artists. In this watercolour. Miró has
illustrated the theme of our articles devoted
to the originality and lasting influence.of
Catalonian art and culture. (See also back
cover.)
Watercolour © Miró Foundation, Barcelona
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Baby polecats scurry along after a little boy on an
experimental farm at Novosibirsk (U.S.S.R.), where
scientists are studying the behaviour patterns of a
variety of Siberian animals.
One man's luxury
is another
man's need
How education can sharpen
our awareness
of environmental issues
à
by Peter J. Fensham
PETER J. FENSHAM is professor of science
education at Monash University, Victoria (Aus¬
tralia). As a member of the Australian National
Commission for Unesco, he chaired an Austra¬
lian national seminar on environmental educa¬
tion in 1975. He led the Australian delegation at
the intergovernmental conference on environ¬
mental education organized by Unesco and the
U.N. Environment Programme (UNEP), and held
at Tbilisi (U. S. S. R. ) in October 1977.
HOW can education help us meet the
challenges of environmental prob¬
lems?". This was the question
facing the 330 participants and observers
who attended the world's first Intergovern¬
mental Conference on Environmental Edu¬
cation, held in Tbilisi, Georgia, (U.S.S.R.),
from 14 to 26 October, 1977.
This meeting was the culmination of the
first four-year phase of the international
programme for environmental education
launched by Unesco and the United
Nations Environment Programme (UNEP)
in response to a recommendation of the
U.N. Conference on the Human Environ¬
ment in Stockholm in 1972.
What emerged from the working ses¬
sions at Tbilisi were a number of insights
that go right to the heart of the problems
facing environmental education. These
might be summed up as follows. Environ¬
mental education must be seen, not as a
new "subject' to be taught in schools, but
as an added dimension to the educational
process. It should be a global, lifelong acti¬
vity involving society as a whole, a training
to distinguish "environmental luxuries"
from "environmental necessities", and an
aid to development.
As yet very little headway has been made
in many countries to reshape teaching pro¬
grammes so that this concept of environ¬
mental education becomes a real part of
formal learning.
Geography and biology seem to be the
subjects which have been most able to
incorporate environmental issues. And yet
in many ways, these subjects reflect the
symptoms of environmental problems
rather than their causes.
Environmental issues bring into play
social values, political organizations, eco¬
nomic policies and structures, technologi¬
cal control and development, and national
and international patterns of distributing
resources. All these are, in fact, more
naturally related to other subjects such as
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
literature, social studies, the physical scien¬
ces, and mathematics.
Much needs to be done to assist tea¬
chers in elementary and secondary educa¬
tion to present in simple form some of
these radical issues. For example, the way
in which resources are distributed and the
indicators (such as Gross National Product)
that we use to measure economic growth
are both fundamental to our perception of
environmental issues.
Yet these concepts are often taught only
in a formal, analytical way during the senior
years of secondary schooling. Teachers
might well be surprised how readily six- or
seven-year-olds can grasp these basic ideas
if they play a game in which they share out
differently, on successive days at school,
the same number of things like favourite
story books or coloured pencils.
Or, again, the younger children in a
family regularly have their desires overruled
by others.
Until now we have made very little use of
these real experiences to familiarize
youngsters with the processes of power,
control by groups, and decision-making in
society.
Environmental education must not only
involve all the disciplines normally taught in
schools, but must also force schools out of
their isolation from the community. Envi¬
ronmental education set wholly within the
confines of the classroom is a contradiction
in terms.
But this certainly does not mean that
field trips, camping, or museum visits auto¬
matically constitute environmental edu¬
cation. Unless these experiences "help
groups and individuals acquire the skills for
identifying and solving environmental
problems," they are not environmental
education as expressed in the Tbilisi recom¬
mendations.
Environmental education must be a life¬
long process. Not only should learning
continue beyond school; different age
groups should also learn together. The
roles of teacher, student, parent and citizen
become more flexible, as they join in a
learning situation that serves to en¬
hance awareness of their environment.
Learning by doing is one approach devel¬
oped in recent years. It may take the form
of a movement like "Make Cuba a
Garden", or a community or school effort
to eliminate litter in Singapore. Or it may
be a drive to reduce energy consumption in
home or factory.
There has been a tendency, particularly
in the industrially developed world, to
define the environment in terms of middle-
class values. There has been more empha¬
sis on the conservation and preservation of
aspects of the man-made and natural envi¬
ronments that are enjoyed by the middle
class than on the quality of life enjoyed by
the less privileged. As the preservation of,
certain of these resources clashes with the
provision of jobs, sustenance and shelter, |
there is likely to be a backlash against many I
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
aspects of today's environmental educa¬
tion programmes.
The concepts of "environmental luxu¬
ries" and "environmental necessities" may
prove useful since they provide criteria and
bases for choice. They may make it easier
to tackle such questions as the merits of a
building in New York whose energy con¬
sumption approaches that of a city the size
of Pittsburg. During a campaign for a new
national park, these concepts may also
help us see the viewpoint of workers who
would be obliged to leave the area, even
though they have no powerful lobby to
voice their claims for adequate compensa¬
tion and alternative job opportunities.
Again, it may turn out that the land
rights of the 800 or so aborigines living on
or near the uranium deposits in northern
Australia are the "environmental necessi¬
ties" in that situation, and that the econo¬
mic consequences of mining which may
shore up the "environmental luxuries"
other Australians enjoy are of lesser
merit. Similar problems for environmental
education crop up on the international
scene.
In the developing world there is a ten¬
dency to see environmental education and
education for development as one and the
same, and many environmental educators
in the industrially developed world would
also like this to be the case. However,
many of them fail to recognize the contra¬
dictions that exist between the conserva¬
tion of many things the developed world is
coming to appreciate as "quality of life,"
and the redistribution of the world's resour¬
ces in such a way that development also
takes "quality of life" into account.
Two examples come to mind. Environ¬
mental education in Japan developed ini¬
tially almost entirely in response to a com¬
pelling environmental issue rampant
The wood
and the trees
The problems posed by the conservation of
the environment and the exploitation of
natural resources are not always seen in the
same way. In the industrialized countries,
city-dwellers are taught at an early age
(above) to respect and care for trees and
greenery. Wood is often imported, even if
this sometimes leads to the deforestation of
tropical regions (right). The establishment
of a new international order means that
environmental problems, like those of
development, must be approached in a
spirit of solidarity, for there is still too much
injustice in the management of mankind's
common resources.
Straying off
the beaten track
The spread of cities, towns and villages
often disturbs the habits of animal life in
the natural environment. Left, a bear
beats a retreat from a village in the Ural
Mountains (U.S.S.R.). It is not unknown
for a bewildered animal to blunder its way
into a big city, like the moose (below) that
turned up one morning in a Moscow street.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
fe
^(^
'
% M
Photo Georg Gerster, © Rapho, Paris
industrial pollution. Although they have by
no means solved this problem, the Japa¬
nese have made some progress. Some
processes that produce effluent are now
controlled by local and national legislation.
Others have bsen "stopped" altogether by
exporting the problem to other less devel¬
oped countries in Southeast Asia. For
example, a particularly dirty phase in the
processing of iron ore imported from Aus¬
tralia now takes place in the Philippines, en
route to Japan.
Again, Australia's strict re-afforestation
rules now make some local timber very
expensive. Accordingly, Australia now
imports large quantities of cheap timber
from Southeast Asian countries which,
because of their urgent need for trade with
the developed world, cannot afford to lose
this revenue by enforcing the same expen¬
sive environmental controls as Australia.
Unesco and UNEP have a vital role to
play in promoting international co¬
operation in the development of teaching
programmes and materials that bring an
awareness of such global interactions,
both to students in formal education and to
the general public. If left to individual
national efforts, these issues are always
likely to be underplayed because of nation¬
al constraints and the natural myopia that
shrouds the consequences of one's own
actions.
Formal education has been a delusion for
many people in most countries. It promises
to be the key to social development, but
instead it serves to select a small eiïte, and
as a result most people experience a sense
of failure. The environmental education
movement suggests that at each stage of
education the question should be asked: Is
the programme enabling the maximum
number of learners to extend their mastery
over their environment?
An excellent example of what can be
done is the alternative approach to elemen¬
tary education formulated by the APEID
programme in the Asian Region of Unesco,
and its pilot projects in various countries
have shown that such a goal is not impos¬
sible. If children at school in Nepal can, in
fact, learn how to choose the right fuel,
then their families will indeed have a new
sense of mastery, since many families in
that deforested land spend hours each day
seeking firewood.
There is a pointlessness about so much
schooling in the industrially developed
world that this approach is just as urgently
needed there as it is in countries like Nepal.
Perhaps the "back to the basics" move¬
ment in a number of countries is really a call
for educational programmes that have the
same relevance as true environmental
education.
It is clear that the Unesco-UNEP Pro¬
gramme has served as a catalyst for nation¬
al developments in environmental educa¬
tion. What for many countries in 1975 was
simply an idea has now become a much
more concrete movement through the
development of teaching materials for
schools, national plans and programmes,
expanded non-formal environmental edu¬
cation, and new legislation establishing
environmental education.
The réponse to the Tbilisi recommenda¬
tions will vary according to the political and
educational structures in each country.
Nevertheless, in many countries educatio¬
nal innovators now have a chance to get
their contributions to environmental educa¬
tion recognized and established.
Peter J. Fensham
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Each year two million scientific articles written by
750,000 specialists appear in some 50 languages.
To help scientists keep up with this "information
explosion", Unesco and the International Council
on Scientific Unions decided 11 years ago to
launch a programme of international co-operation
in scientific information. Much progress has
already been made in some parts of the world
towards the ultimate goal of hooking up all the
world's regions in a single automatic scientific
information network.
Information
please...
Towards a world science
information network
by
Yuri I.
Litukhin
SCIENTISTS form an international
community whose common bond,
science itself, leads them to see
beyond national boundaries and sectarian
attitudes. When a scientist makes a dis¬
covery, he wants to tell, not just his fellow-
countrymen, but the world.
YURI IVANOVICH LITUKHIN, Soviet specia¬
list in computer science, is a staff member of
Unesco's division for the international develop¬
ment of social sciences. He is the author of
many studies on the application of information
systems to economic development.
Similarly, when he seeks information, he
wants to be provided with it as quickly as
possible, regardless of whether its source is
inside or outside his own country.
Today, no one scientist or engineer can
hope to keep up to date with the avalanche
of technical articles, books and abstracts
which threaten to engulf even the most
conscientious researcher.
At the beginning of the 19th century, a
solution to the increasing number of spe¬
cialized reviews was found in the form of
the abstract journal. But since then both
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
*""
abstract journals and periodicals have pro¬
liferated at an astounding rate so that each
year the scientist and technical expert must
confront some 50,000 scientific and techni¬
cal journals, publishing almost two million
articles written by some 750,000 authors in
as many as 50 languages.
This "information explosion" is both ex¬
citing and frustrating. On the one hand,
scientists are eager to share in the know¬
ledge and ideas of their colleagues. On the
other, they have neither the time nor the
resources to sift through a heap of publica
tions to unearth those items which fall
within their field of interest.
And when the scientist does gain access
to the material he wants, linguistic and
other barriers often prevent him from put¬
ting it to good use. The resultant wastage
and loss are staggering: for every thousand
new ideas in science, only three or four are
ever put to practical use.
To reduce these information gaps and
frustrations, an intergovernmental co¬
operative venture called UNISIST has been
set up under Unesco auspices. It is de
signed to stimulate the creation of national
and international information systems in
the social, natural and exact sciences. Its
beginnings go back to a January 1967
meeting between the International Council
on Scientific Unions (ICSU) and Unesco at
which it was decided to work towards a
world scientific information system.
Clearly, this goal is far from realization,
but much progress has been made towards
it. A preliminary step involved establishing
new relationships and better co-ordination
on a national and regional scale between
CONTINUED PAGE 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Mankind's
memory banks
Around the beginning of the 3rd
millennium of the pre-Christian era,
the Sumerians of southern
Mesopotamia invented cuneiform
writing as a means of recording
names, speech and actions. This
clay tablet, dating from around
2000 B.C., is inscribed with a text
concerning the income earned from
the sale of cattle by the ancient
Babylonian city of Isin. A gift from
the government of Iraq, it is today
exhibited at Unesco's H.Q. in Paris.
The story of archives
from the clay tablet
to the computer
by Jean Favier
LONG before they became the hunting-
ground of historians, archives were
the stuff of history itself.
From the very earliest times administra¬
tors have committed to public archives the
records of state business, just as indivi¬
duals have kept private records of their
own or their families' activities, noting
down today what might be of use to them
tomorrow.
The materials on which these documents
were recorded were as varied as their con¬
tent. Wax tablets and tablets of baked
clay, shells and potsherds, were all used at
one time or another. In this way material as
varied as the correspondence of ancient
kings of Asia Minor, surveys of the Roman
Empire, estate-books of the Roman Catho¬
lic Church, and William the Conqueror's
record of his estates, was preserved for
posterity by men who can hardly have been
aware that they were acting as the custo¬
dians of history.
But if these documents owed their exis¬
tence to matters of immediate concern,
and were in no way conceived with the
needs of future historians in mind, they
also had two other features in common.
In the first place they were relatively
durable. Constant reading could never
wear away a tablet or a marble plaque, nor
could it harm the fragile papyrus (although
the latter might suffer from rough handling
or excessive exposure to light). Secondly,
each of these documents, no matter how
many copies of it were made, was unique.
Although procedures for handling the»
documents were varied, a copy of the origi- 1
JEAN FAVIER, Director General of the French
National Archives, is a member of the Executive
Committee of the International Council on
Archives. He is a former professor of medieval
economic history at the Sorbonne, where he
also headed the Institute of History from 1971 to
1975. Among his many published works on
medieval history are volume 4 of Paris au 15"
Siècle ("Paris in the 15th century"). Hachette,
Paris 1975.
vAi1T¿
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
For centuries, archives have, been used to store and preserve historic documents and
books. Top, a reader consults the largest of the million volumes in the library at
Tambov (U.S.S.R.) Below, a fragment of a nation's memory is stored in this section of
the U.S. National Archives In Washington, D.C.
Photo © National Archives, Washington, D.C.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
This ancient inscription
on clay is another
document in cuneiform
(wedge-shaped) writing.
Unearthed in the Arab
Emirate of Bahrein, it
was produced around
1800 B.C. Cuneiform
was used for writing a
number of languages in
the ancient Near East.
> nal was generally made in the interests of
administrative efficiency, while the author
also kept a copy as a record of the deci¬
sions and information it contained. Thus,
there grew up the "registers" and "rolls"
which, from the Middle Ages onwards,
came to constitute a wealth of information
revealing how' rulers conducted their
affairs.
A glance at the Rolls kept by the medi¬
eval kings of England, the papal registers
and the documents conserved in the Trésor
des Chartes in France is sufficient for us to
realize the debt which history owes to the
systematic compilation of official docu¬
ments of all kinds.
Together with society's need to conserve
documentary evidence came the need to
organize this material. It is, after all, to the
archives that people turn when they seek
precedents for their decisions and the basis
for actions and judgements whose rules are
not prescribed by law.
For this purpose, the archivists of Anti¬
quity initiated, and those of the Middle
Ages particularly from the 13th century
onwards^ expanded and extended the pro¬
cess of listing and drawing up inventories,
classifying their material alphabetically,
chronologically and topographically, so
that it could be consulted with greater
speed and efficiency.
These traditional archives had their
drawbacks, foremost among which was
their extreme vulnerability above all to
fire, the nightmare of all ancient towns and
cities. When historians think of all the
documents that have, over the centuries,
gone up in flames, they are reduced to spe¬
culation and surmise about their contents,
if not to tears of frustration.
Another scourge of archives has always
been "borrowing", to use a euphemism.
Outright theft is relatively uncommon, but
many precious documents have disappear¬
ed because their users neglected to return
them. If archives were less useful, their
contents would be much richer!
From the 17th century onwards, West¬
ern historians increasingly felt a need to
base their work on documentary evidence,
and archivists began to take into account
the historical interest of the documents
they handled, in addition to their legal con¬
tent and their value as precedents. Collec¬
tions of historical documents were made,
composed of copies as well as originals.
Wealthy collectors enriched their libraries
with such miscellaneous acquisitions,
which often included documents
"diverted" from their original homes.
Scholars ranged far and wide across
Europe in quest of unpublished texts,
making copies for themselves and their
friends. In many cases, these copies are all
the evidence we have of important records,
since the originals were subsequently des¬
troyed by fire or tossed into the dustbin
during an epidemic of manic "sorting".
This preoccupation with History turned
the archivist's world upside down: the ser¬
vant of administrators became the servant
of the historian. During the 19th century,
this even led to a reversal of priorities: a
scholar himself, the archivist often gave the
needs of the historian priority over the
immediate demands of the bureaucracy.
Thus the century that saw the develop¬
ment of the positivist approach to history
was also the century whose history is in
many ways the most difficult to write,
because it paid scant regard to future gen¬
erations of historians. Preoccupied as they
were with the past, people forgot that the
present too would one day be the past.
At the same time, however, the 19th
century also made a major contribution to
the writing of history, through the great
collections of inventories, exhaustive cata¬
logues of publications and documents that
were compiled in many countries.
While archives were acquiring a new
scientific and cultural dimension, the right
of public access to their contents, as part
of a universal heritage, found clearer and
more forceful expression.
As a result, the management of archives
was subjected to fresh constraints, from
which emerged the modern concept of the
archivist as a public servant whose duty is
to communicate, to assist research and to
advise. The development of research in
universities would pack the reading-rooms
with an enthusiastic yet disinterested
public, for whom the right to consult ar¬
chives was part of the right to discover
the truth.
With the coming of the 20th century,
archivists began to be faced with a massive
increase in the output of official docu¬
ments, primarily due to the expansion of
the state's activities in most countries of
the world.
Only a century ago, countless transac¬
tions were handled purely on a private basis
by the individuals concerned. Today, the
state has a finger in every pie from house¬
building to symphony concerts with its
permits and prohibitions, its regulations,
aid, and taxes. Public records today thus
reflect virtually all the activities of the com¬
munity. At the same time archivists are
now more concerned than in the past with
preserving additional sources of informa¬
tion in the form of private archives, whe¬
ther compiled by the man-in-the-street or
the statesman, the shopkeeper or the
multinational corporation.
Technological progress has also brought
upheaval to the archivist's world. The last
century has seen the replacement of the
quill pen by the ball-point, and of the inky-
fingered copyist by the electric typewriter,
the duplicator and the Xerox machine.
Once, original documents were the rule;
now they are the exception.
"Papers, papers, everywhere..." is the
result, swamping the archivist, who can no
longer cope single-handed with a flood of
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Some archives are today a
tantalizing mystery. The
signs and symbols on the
seals produced between
2500 and 1500 B.C. by the
' ancient civilization of the
Indus, have defied all
attempts at decipherment.
This elephant seal was
discovered at the famous
site of Mohenjodaro
(Pakistan).
documents which may not be of immediate
or daily use, yet are not sufficiently unin¬
teresting to be destroyed. Highly speciali¬
zed new techniques must be used to
handle this mass of new material.
Whether the specialists concerned are
"archivists" or "documentalists", their
task is not merely to let the archives pile up
until there is time to attend to them, but to
"process" systematically documents which
are still useful for administrators and
already sought-after by research workers.
The sheer bulk of the material means
that closer attention must be paid than in
the past to sorting and selection. Some
weeding out is essential, but it must be
done with care. The solution is to use a
"sampling" procedure, thus avoiding the
total disappearance of documentary evi¬
dence concerning certain activities.
Thus, the archivist may keep archives
concerning one year in five, or one in 20.
He may take samples on a geographic
basis, taking care that the samples are suf¬
ficiently varied to reflect a whole range of
social and economic affairs. Or he may
take samples according to subject, so that
the historians of the future will be able to
Photo © Archives Nationales, Pans
The use of the stylus to
keep records on wax-
covered tablets was a
practice that persisted
from Antiquity into the
Middle Ages. Wax
tablets at left were used
by Jean Sarrazin,
Chamberlain of St.
Louis, king of France, in
the mid-13th century.
grasp the full complexity of events at any
given point in space and time.
The storage of vast quantities of archives
is also a costly process. Here, microfilm
may seem to be a solution not far short of
miraculous, when one compares the cost
of a metre of film with that of a metre of
shelving, and when one considers that
documents which would once have filled
whole buildings can now be stored in a few
small canisters.
And yet, when the cost of preparing
documents for microfilming is added to the
costs of the labour and the equipment
required, it turns out that it is twice as
expensive to microfilm a big collection of
archives for storage as it is to construct a
special building to house the full-sized
documents.
This may mean that the creation of ar¬
chives on microfilm will not become a
serious alternative until the end of this cen¬
tury. Another major drawback must also
be faced: in most countries microfilm,
which defies many forms of analysis and
expert examination, is not yet legally reco¬
gnized as documentary evidence.
Nevertheless, there can be no doubt that
microfilm offers the archivists of our cen¬
tury invaluable possibilities for storing .
material in limited space, and providing |
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
hAtt Jt fW ¿ft ó»4 «-Ä- Î, Sr v*-V. Uf ¿ , Ô* tuM
Among the treasures preserved in archives are
documents recording some of the great moments
of history. Left, a letter bearing the royal seal
written in January 1196 by Richard the Lion-Heart,
King of England and lord of much of France,
concerning a peace treaty with the French King
Philippe Auguste.
, access to documents whose originals are in
distant libraries.
This technological revolution brought
renewed awareness of a threat which archi¬
vists have, perhaps, tended to neglect
since the age when records were inscribed
on papyrus: the fragility of documents.
What will remain, a few centuries from
now, of our photographs which yellow
with time, of our photocopies, and of car¬
bon copies on flimsy paper? In 30 years
time, what will have become of our
recordings on tapes which deteriorate with
every playing and eventually become
demagnetized?
The widespread use of computers poses
an even more serious problem. Even if
ways are found of preserving from decay
the memories contained in today's data
banks, who can be sure that the machines
of the late 21st century will be able to use
them? What shall we do if the memories
are silent?
The methods used for storing archives
on paper may be inadequate when it comes
to preserving the records of the computer
age. A document committed to paper
bears traces of all the stages of its life; suc¬
cessive entries mark its pasage through dif¬
ferent hands. A register, an account book
or a file shows an unfolding pattern in the
work of a law court or the activity of a busi¬
ness, and enables us to follow the deve¬
lopment of a career and a life.
But as a computer absorbs new informa¬
tion, it cancels earlier entries as obsolete. If
no remedy is found, the historian who con¬
sults the memory of a computer may well
find the "final result", but not the full story
of the game.
The growth of scientific curiosity during
the past half-century has also modified the
nature of the demands made on archives.
The archivist of 1914 had a fair idea of the
requests that would be made in a few years
time: they would be the same as those
made a few years earlier. He would be
asked to produce "traditional" material for
political, institutional and local history, bio¬
graphies and genealogies.
Today, however, historians look to the
same archives, as well as records of other
kinds to which scant attention was paid in
the past, for a much broader range of infor¬
mation on economic and social history, the
history of collective attitudes and religious
beliefs. In the course of a single day, an
archivist may be asked to provide docu¬
mentation concerning the evolution of
prices, the development of technology,
matters of public health, and forms of reli¬
gious observance.
At a time when many historians are turn¬
ing their attention to the recent past, peo¬
ple are concerned with the right to privacy
in their own and their family affairs. For
archivists, this has created a problem
which was unknown to their predecessors
a century ago. How can they open their
most recent records to public scrutiny, so
that the history of our times may be scienti¬
fically studied and the workings of govern¬
ment may be clearly understood by the
governed, and at the same time protect the
individual and his private life from prying
eyes and pressures? The archivist's task is
indeed full of contradictions.
Domesday Book, compiled in 1086 on the orders of the King of England, William the Conqueror, is the first
official census of property owners in England. Its two volumes (760 pages and 900 pages) are the earliest
"public" archive preserved at the Public Record Office in London. Below left, part of a page of Domesday
describing in minute detail the land and possessions of Edward of Salisbury, an important landowner. Right, a
plough-team from an 11th-century calendar showing costume and implements at the time of Domesday Book,
which is considered by many scholars to be the greatest administrative achievement of the Middle Ages.
Üfm/7 jot- wtti 7 jwjwrr<£.<*. «r lb,. . nwUnt rOS
~tv(b- È- toi* H*»14*1* liut^TBti* i. I£ yyiHá¿UK, i>¿-
WfÁ- m- «^ lt* »wl"í r*¿fv- «íáy,7*.^^7DS(ut/
toJbwT- SiW-i^l^aWW 0(í<Á.l*.m*l>í<*-l*.
fcyr^.hJr'MpK.t. {.du» iam5-.1t -cupu-ap-
Photo © Public Record Office, London Photo © British Library, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photo © National Archives, Washington, D C.
Design (above) proposed by William Barton in 1782
for the Great Seal of the United States is now in
the National Archives, Washington, D.C. The
small design in the upper right-hand corner was
adopted as the reverse of the seal and also
appears on a dollar bill. The rest was rejected.
' :
r(t%
vjßaAfav makíÍy
,. %t\drj/,Yhi*.iaá)fal),#Í£IW^Íd^,j
û M/ratimnr « lajyr//sá- .
/hit.:, j¿ Cs¡Minuit «ràxrAi .kiàrit ¿bar ¿Mi Jàji exmnAt? m
!rt f*rê*rryrf.i.w*)pn¡M r/ipm m*pvwfjr*Hrlr¿lrr/í¿lrnlmM¿r /»m * *'/x j< s.w/m
H.Unlitfw. I ('.Î4i. IriXtt. Jtyrmi . ''ffyfiOiAaAt l%fíHm7fsl¿uj*foAiíinjf. moWlití
íKpmuíjáaifmwPulmm/ ir&tHliíJf
r, iumu .-ya»'» t^mÊitfÊÊMiWrtnmr:
. iatyxxikitiii! ft h. mpmr
¥i1/n_ ÎiW iJ/A'ïi . ¿w/*,;:
^¿u.^
Original document of the Lei Áurea, the Golden Law abolishing
slavery in Brazil, dated 13 May 1888. The first two articles read
as follows: "Article 1 Slavery in Brazil is herewith declared
illegal as from the date of this law.
Article 2All contrary provisions are hereby rescinded."
Human rights are one thing. The rights
people actually enjoy are another. The
break-up of great empires, which began as
long ago as the Middle Ages but which
acquired particular momentum in the past
two centuries, has obliged many peoples to
look outside their own countries for some
or all of the records of their history.
This has led to claims which are as com¬
prehensible as they are difficult to satisfy.
Photo © Photo Department, Archives Nationales, Paris
People often think of
archives as stacks of musty
papers stored in deserted
rooms. Today this image is
increasingly false. Archives
now contain a mass of
recent documents, which are
often recorded by modern
techniques such as microfilm
and are consulted by the
general public as well as
specialists. Left, microfilm
reference room at the
Archives Nationales, Paris.
The present distribution of archive material
does not necessarily reflect the territorial
changes which followed the fall of the
Ottoman or Austro-Hungarian Empires or
the end of colonial and military occupa¬
tions.
And although microfilm may offer a
scientifically acceptable solution, it is no
help in settling questions of principle.
Nor as we have seen is it an inexpensive
process. This is one of the problems which
are being examined today by Unesco, the
International Council on Archives and the
International Round Table on Archives.
The history of archives goes back 3,000
years. Throughout this period, they have
reflected human difficulties in every age.
Today, they are part of the national and
international policies of every country. A
thread of continuity runs through this
history the quest to improve the tools of
government and administration, pursued
by both medieval kings and the Heads of
State of developing countries today.
When modern states define the laws
which govern access to their own archives,
and negotiate with other states the right to
consult archives which are not in their own
keeping, they are turning a new page in the
history of human memory.
Jean Favier
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Catalan masters
of modern art
by Alexandre Cirici
c
ATALONIAN art can only be fully
understood when set in its geo¬
graphical and historical context.
The Catalan language is used in a broad
area on the western littoral of the Mediter¬
ranean. Catalonia, which was for many
centuries an independent state, is today
inhabited by some 10 million people and
divided between Spain and to a lesser
extent the Principality of Andorra and
France. In France, Catalonian territory
coincides almost exactly with the adminis¬
trative department of the Pyrénées Orienta¬
les (Eastern Pyrenees), and in Spain with
the provinces of Gerona, Barcelona,
Lérida, Tarragona, Castellón, Valencia, Ali¬
cante and the Balearic and Pitiusan Islands.
Catalonia first appeared in history in 801
as an outpost of the Carolingian empire
known as the Spanish March (Marca His¬
pánica). In the 10th century, during the
rule of Count Borrel II, it declared its inde¬
pendence of the Frankish empire. Thus
was born a sovereign state which would
last until the 18th century.
In the 12th century Catalonia began to
grow, with the conquest of Tarragona and
Lérida, and in the 13th, when expansion to
the north was blocked by the French, it
acquired fresh territory further south.
Mallorca was conquered in 1229, Ibiza and
Formentera in 1235, Valencia in 1238 and
Minorca in 1287. The resulting confedera¬
tion between Catalonia, Valencia and the
Balearic Islands marked the appearance of
national unity in the territory where the
Catalan language is still used today.
The construction of a vast Catalonian
Photo Jean
16
© Editions Carmen Martinez, Pans
ALEXANDRE CIRICI, Barcelona-born Spanish
art historian and art critic, is professor of the
sociology of art in the university of Barcelona.
The author of some 80 published works, includ¬
ing studies on Gaudi, Picasso, Miró and Tapies,
he is member of the Miro Foundation Jn Barce¬
lona. He is also a member of the Spanish senate
and of Spain's delegation to the European
Parliament in Strasbourg.
empire in the Mediterranean then got under
way with the annexation of Sicily in 1282,
Greece in 1311, Sardinia in 1323, and the
kingdom of Naples in 1443.
Pyrenean Catalonia, where people lived
mainly from farming and livestock rearing,
became a meeting-point of cultures. The
urban civilization of Islamic Cordoba, then
the greatest city in the West, spread from
the monasteries of Ripoll and Cuixa to the
rural areas of Europe. Monumental sculp¬
ture, instrumental music, secular poetry
and so-called "Arabic" numerals were
important features in this process of cul¬
tural transmission. Catalonia was also
among the birthplaces of troubadour
poetry.
At the beginning of the 16th century, the
last king of Catalonia and the queen of Cas¬
tile made the Fleming Charles V their sole
heir. Thus Catalonia and Valencia came to
figure among the states ruled by the House
of Austria.
In 1660 France annexed the northern part
of Catalonia (present-day Roussillon), and
in the 18th century Spain brought the
Catalans under its rule. Valencia lost its
independence in 1705, and in 1713 Minorca
became an English possession. Mallorca
and Ibiza lost their autonomy in 1715, as
did Catalonia in 1717. From that moment
on, France and Spain began to stamp their
imprint on their new acquisitions.
Even so, 19th-century Catalonia enjoyed
a remarkable economic, literary, scientific
and political renaissance, which trans¬
formed it into a modern industrial region
equipped with a major seaport. At the
same time, Catalan came to the forefront
of the world's "non-official" languages in
terms of published output.
Catalan is today the only official lan¬
guage of Andorra. It is also one of the two
official languages of Catalonia, a status;
which it is also expected to acquire in'
Valencia and the Balearic Islands during
1978. Since 1977, the area of Catalonia i
which forms part of the Spanish state has I
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Catalonia, which produced
a remarkable school of
Romanesque painters and
sculptors in the Middle
Ages (see following pages),
has also made a major
contribution to modern art.
Some of the boldest artistic
innovators of the century
were Catalonians, such as
Julio González (see page
23) and Pau Gargallo. A
pioneer of cubist sculpture,
Gargallo was one of the
first artists to experiment
with modern industrial
techniques for fashioning
metal. Shown here, two
typical examples of his
work: The Prophet (detail
left) and David with his
Harp (opposite page).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
> been moving towards the autonomous sta¬
tus it enjoyed between 1931 and 1939. It
now has a government of its own that
devotes special attention to Catalan lan¬
guage and culture.
The most remarkable contribution of the
Catalan people to world culture is without
doubt their art. Architects, sculptors and
painters from Catalonia have played a
major role in the revolution in visual idioms
that has taken place in this century.
The development of modern art in Cata¬
lonia can be broken down into three main
phases.
Between 1890 and 1910 the Symbolists
opened up new horizons, and their works
reflect the joy of life and the spontaneous,
instinctive manifestations of human nature.
The period from 1910 to the outbreak of
the Spanish Civil War in 1936 was marked
by bold experimentation, as artists sought
new directions, new methods and intellec¬
tual concepts, as well as a fresh sensibility.
A renewed spirit of adventure in the arts
appeared around 1950, when the fascist
régime ceased to be applied in all its
severity.
The first of these periods was that of
"Modernism", a revolutionary movement
in the arts that affected architecture in par¬
ticular, but also radically changed the
forms of objects such as ceramic ware and
curtains, stained-glass windows and metal
ornaments, jewellery, porcelain, clothes,
posters and books.
Everywhere the forms inherited from
classical art began to give way to sinuous
lines and a profusion of floral shapes, the
lyrical manifestation of a quest for an inten¬
sified sensuality which could only find
expression in the most mysterious art
which on the one hand sought its inspira¬
tion in grandiose concepts, and on the
other took delight in a close scrutiny of
details the meticulous observation of
twigs and insects.
Art of this kind existed in other European
countries as a form of decorative fantasy,
but in Catalonia it had a remarkable vitality
that expressed itself in hundreds of build¬
ings and in decorative ensembles and
objects of exceptional quality.
The most outstanding figure in this
movement was the architect Antoni Gaudi,
who broke with dull, colourless academic
traditions to create a highly original type of
architecture rich in colour, sometimes in¬
fused with Islamic or Japanese motifs, and
always looking to Nature for its inspiration.
Gaudi began with shapes borrowed from
exotic styles, but he was soon covering his
buildings with a coating of sculptural forms
taken from the landscape and from the
living world of Nature stars, constella¬
tions, clouds, rocks, icicles, plants, animals
and people.
Later he even went so far as to treat
architectural features as organic shapes.
Thus windows became gaping mouths,
cornices eyebrows, columns thighbones,
rooftops scaly skins, domes garlic bulbs,
vaults rib cages, and so forth.
Towards the end of his life Gaudi put this
imitation of natural forms behind him and
The anonymous
painters
of medieval
Catalonia
CATALONIA is a land steeped in an age-old civilization and hence in art. The Cata¬
lonian language and culture came into being around the same time as the other
great languages and cultures that grew out of the collapse of the Roman world:
French, Italian, Spanish, Provençal, Galician-Portuguese, Romanian and others.
Like them Catalan emerged around the year 1000 and gradually took shape in the later
Middle Ages down to the Renaissance and the great voyages of discovery in the 16th
century.
Catalonian culture reached a high level during these centuries, producing such great
figures as Raymond Lully in philosophy, Joannot Martorell in literature and Juan Luis
Vives in humanist thought.
But it was in art, and especially painting, that early Catalonian culture achieved its
finest splendours, as it would do again centuries later with its world-famous modern
architects and painters. (See article page 16).
With the exception of the mural paintings in the Pantheon of Kings which adorns the
basilica of San Isidoro in the city of Leon, most of the treasures of Spanish Romanesque
painting are concentrated in the churches and monasteries of Catalonia. These works,
many of them executed on wood panels, are examples of a humane, powerful, and
emotionally charged art that, until recent times, was known only to a few specialists.
Most of the artists who created these masterpieces were monks. Their names are
unknown, and they are identified by the names of the places where they worked. The
Master of Pedret, the Master of Tahull, the Master of Soriguerola, the Master of Osor-
mort and the Master of Espinelves were some of the most famous of these painters who
worked between the 11th and 13th centuries.
For hundreds of years the marvels of Catalonian Romanesque painting remained hid¬
den in small churches, convents and monasteries in the towns and villages of Catalonia.
It is only since the beginning of this century that specialists have been bringing them to
the attention of a wider public. Today most of these works are preserved in Catalonian
museums, notably Barcelona's Museum of Catalonian Art, which has an unrivalled col¬
lection of Romanesque painting.
Romanesque art in Catalonia and elsewhere in Spain bears traces of various out¬
side influences. The road that ran from Cordoba in the South to Toledo and Leon in the
North was the principal route along which Muslim art and culture spread from Cordoba,
until the fall of the caliphate early in the 11th century. There was, for example, an
important Mozarabic school of panel painting that left its mark on painting in the Chris¬
tian kingdoms of the Iberian peninsula.
Then, too, the pilgrims' road to St. James of Compostella crossed northern Spain
from east to west bringing artistic influences from elsewhere in Europe, starting with
that of the Benedictine abbey of Cluny in Burgundy which was the fountainhead of
Romanesque art.
The works of the anonymous painters of medieval Catalonia blazoned forth the great
themes of the Old, and even more often the New Testament, as well as the lives and
legends of the saints, in a style that is sometimes strikingly modern. On the following
pages we present a selection of these masterpieces. (See also back cover.)
Colour pages
Centre double page
Scenes from the life of St. Clement
are shown on this frontal from the
church dedicated to the Saint in
Tahull, a Pyrenean village in the
Spanish province of Lérida. The
painting, executed in the 12th century
by an anonymous painter known as
the Master of Tahull, is now in the
Art Museum of Catalonia, Barcelona.
Photo © Spanish Embassy, Paris
Opposite page
St. Margaret devoured by dragons: a
detail from a frontal in the ancient
monastery of St. Martin, in Sescorts
near Vich (Barcelona province). The
12th-century work is now preserved
in Vich Episcopal Museum.
Photo © Spanish Embassy, Pans
CONTINUED PAGE 23
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
&
OL * . '
I, » ,
o-
» If J
qV?
s\ t ¿ KA v íá \íV8? úDQ'LI
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
, concentrated on the inner logic of struc¬
tural design.
Another architect of the period, Lluis
Domènech ¡ Montaner, combined a search
for technical innovations with a lavish use
of decorative floral motifs, covering every
inch of his buildings with ceramic flowers
in high relief, mosaics, stained glass and
trees sculptured in stone.
Younger than both Gaudi and Montaner,
Josep Puig i Cadafalch carried on where
they left off. To the fantastic, polychrome
architectural style of "Modernism" he
added a whole range of structural and
decorative forms taken from the folk art of
Catalonian rural houses to which he gave a
rich ornamental character. He was also
instrumental in helping to revive the tradi¬
tional skills of blacksmithing, glassworking,
graffito decoration (1) and tile-making.
The most original figurative artist of the
period was Isldre Nonell, who broke with
academic theory by choosing to paint the
slums, the poor, the mentally retarded,
gypsies and outcasts. The most important
phase of his artistic career might be the
record of a descent into hell. During this
sombre period a bronze-green colour pre¬
dominates in canvases depicting the
melancholy faces of gypsies bowed down
by care and rapt in silent thought. Yet des-
Dite the gloomy subjects and the sombre
(1) Graffito is a method of decoration in which designs
are produced by scratching through a superficial layer
of plaster, etc., revealing a ground of a different colour.
Colour page opposite
Above left: the Nativity, detail of
an altar panel from the church of
St. Andrew, in Sagas, north of
Barcelona. This 12th-century
work is now in the Diocesan
Museum, Solsona. Above right,
Lazarus at the rich man's gate. A
detail of murals from the
12th-century church of St. Clement,
in Tahull, it is now in the Art
Museum of Catalonia, Barcelona.
Nativity (below) from a frontal of
the church of St. Mary, Avia, was
painted around 1200 by the Master
of Avia. It is also in the Art
Museum of Catalonia, Barcelona.
Photos Unesco
Photo © Spanish Embassy, Paris
tones of these paintings they are rich in
subtle colour gradations.
Nonell was a friend of Picasso during the
latter's famous "blue period" in Barcelona,
and his own development followed similar
lines. Only towards the end of his life did
he again come to terms with joy, beauty,
light and transparent hues.
Aristide Maillol, the sculptor from French
Catalonia, stands on the borderline bet¬
ween the dreams and visions of the turn of
the century and the new taste for simple,
concrete forms which was to characterize
art after 1910. He discarded the concept of
sculpture viewed as the interplay of light
and shadow, and introduced the new idea
that sculpture was the art of volumes set in
space.
Two other Catalonian sculptors took part
in the avant-garde movement in Paris and
went on to win international acclaim. One
of them, Pau Gargallo, was a key figure in
the creation of cubist sculpture. His great
contribution was to show that volume did
not necessarily imply a physical mass but
that it could also be represented by empty
space. Gargallo discovered that it was pos¬
sible to express volume by the use of inter¬
secting planes and the technique of per¬
foration.
The other sculptor, Juli González, after
working for many years as a jeweller,
invented an art form that would be widely
imitated sculpture made by welding metal
with an acetylene torch. This technique
often produced dramatic results because of
the effects of the molten iron dripping.
The most important contribution to the
avant-garde, however, came from the pain¬
ters associated with the surrealist move¬
ment.
The most brilliant was Joan Miró, who
has today become the national painter of
Catalonia and is still as active and produc¬
tive as ever.
Miró began to be known about 1918. In
1923, influenced by his friendship with the
surrealist poets in Paris, he made the great
discovery that was to lead to his distinctive
of painting.
As he himself said, he stopped looking
for Nature and let Nature come to him.
Thus he learned to look at landscape for a
long while, allowing it to impress itself on
his mind. Only then would he paint, giving
his hand free rein, guided only by the feel¬
ings that contemplation of the countryside
had aroused in him.
Since that time Miró has painted his own
highly personal world. It ¡s a world full of
mystery, strength and joy, but one which
also sends out cries of despair, a universe
peopled by creatures that hover between a
mythological earth and sky filled with
signs, where birds and star clusters exist
side by side with great red suns and blue
moons.
A few years later there appeared another
surrealistic vision, that of Salvador Dalí
who used a meticulous, academic manner
to paint his dreams and obsessions, reveal¬
ing in his work a whole new world of sub¬
conscious realities.
The Spanish Civil War (1936-1939) did
not.interrupt, but on the contrary stimula-
CONTINUED PAGE26
Julio González, a Catalonian who
settled in Paris as a young man and
became a friend of Picasso, is one of
the founders of modern sculpture. He
used the techniques he learned as a
welder in a car factory to create works
in sheet metal. Above, Don Quixote, a
cubist work by González.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Gaudi's
phantasmagoria
in stone
The best-known work of the celebrated Catalonian
architect Antoni Gaudi (1852-1926) is undoubtedly
the cathedral of the Sagrada Familia (Holy Family)
in Barcelona. The conception and construction of
this extravagant building (which was never
completed) show Gaudi at the height of his
creative powers. In 1891, he took over the project
from another architect who had built the crypt,
and worked on It for the rest of his life. Photo 2
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Clovis Prévost-Robert Décharnés, Paris
shows the building at the turn of the century.
Initially inspired by neo-Gothic and Arabic models,
Gaudi soon left behind all consideration of the
past, and began to cover the cathedral's façade of
the Nativity (photo 3) with a riot of complex forms
from Nature. The stone seems to flow In curves
like lava, solidified in a wild profusion of plant and
animal motifs, stalactites and stalagmites, clouds,
stars and constellations. Photo 1 shows in close-
up a detail of what Gaudi called his "Milky Way
coagulations". But the architect also moved away
from the use of natural imagery for its own sake
to a conception of architecture in which there is
often a logical structural reason behind the
apparently capricious forms. The many sculptures
adorning the cathedral illustrate a tireless quest
for realism. All the New Testament figures were
portrayed from life. Gaudi used his workmen and
their families as models, and the church became
known as "the cathedral of the poor". In photo 5,
a mason's sister poses with a baby in front of a
mirror for the Nativity scene. Photo 4, the Nativity
as finally depicted on the cathedral façade.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Surreal living quarters
Two multi-storied apartment buildings in Barcelona (above, the Casa Battlo; below
right, the Casa Mila) illustrate Gaudi's penchant for highly animated surfaces. Broad
wavy balconies enliven the façade of the Battlo house, which is covered with pieces
of coloured glass and enamelled ceramic tile. Building with stepped gable end, at
left of the Battlo house, is by another Catalonian architect, Josep Puig i Cadafalch,
who played a leading role in the modernist movement. The Mila house, and
especially the roof terrace shown here, is one of Gaudi's most astounding creations.
An undulating path without handrails runs round the void of two inner patios,
creating an atmosphere of insecurity heightened by the weirdly-shaped chimneys.
Another great Catalan artist, Salvador Dali, is a fervent admirer of Gaudi and drew
inspiration from the Mila terrace in architectural drawings (below).
kted, the artistic efforts of the Catalonians
who almost to a man defended their auto¬
nomous regional form of government and
the Republic against Falangist forces. An
example of the spirit of the time was the
opening of the pavilion of the Spanish
Republic at the Paris International Exhibi¬
tion in 1937 where Picasso's Guernica, Juli
Gonzalez's Montserrat and Joan Miro's
Segador were all displayed in a building
designed by Josep Lluis Sert.
Sert is an architect who took part from
the outset from 1929, to be exact in the
creation of the international movement in
favour of functionalist architecture. His
contribution consisted in broadening its
programme by incorporating features
drawn from Mediterranean folk art, as well
as the equally Mediterranean concept of
deep interior spaces where light filters in.
Sert was exiled at the end of the Civil War
and sought refuge in the United States,
where he became Dean of Architecture at
Harvard University.
For years the directives of the Falangist
State forbade any attempt to build in a
modern style, until finally the treaty con¬
cluded between Spain and the United
States in 1951 brought with it more free¬
dom in architecture.
From then on a style known as organic
architecture began to develop around J.A.
Coderch, an innovator with a fondness for
trapezoidal spaces and star-shaped ground
plans, though he later evolved towards
sophisticated experiments in the use of
materials and space.
The restless yearnings of Catalonian
architects ultimately crystallized in the Bar¬
celona School, in which Oriol Bohigas
played a leading role. Members of this
school followed the tenets of empiricism,
which was given the name of "realism",
and looked for a fresh kind of visual poetry,
while continuing to use traditional building
methods.
In the last 25 years Catalonian painting
has been dominated by the personality of
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Masters
of despair
Isidre Nonell (1873-1911) was a leading figure in the Catalan artistic revival of the early 20th
century. As a young man he broke away from prevailing trehds in academic painting, and turned
to portraits of gypsies, outcasts and the poor. In Barcelona around the turn of the century, he
was closely associated with the young Pablo Picasso, who made a careful study of Nonell's work.
Several of Picasso's paintings from this famous "Blue Period", such as the Absinthe Drinker (left)
display a strong affinity with such typical Nonell works as the Seated Gypsy (right).
Antoni Tapies. After a period in which he
painted magical, mysterious imagery, he
began to produce what has been called
"matter painting", in which terrifying graf¬
fiti are scraped or scratched on rough, sim¬
ple materials to express the anguish of life
and a protest against death and destruc¬
tion.
Since 1970 there has been a marked
trend towards the "dematerialization" of
art and the use of media such as video
tapes. Antoni Muntadas, In conjunction
with certain groups in the United States, is
carrying out highly original research in this
field, as well as experiments in tactile and
olfactory art.
Catalonia continues in the forefront of
world art developments.
Alexandre Ciricl
The Centre of
Contemporary Art Studies
in Barcelona (left) ¡s a
major work by José Luis
Sert, one of Catalonia's
most outstanding modern
architects. Also known as
the Miró Foundation after
its creator, the great
Catalan painter Joan Miró,
the Centre has just been
awarded a prize by the
Council of Europe for "its
contribution to the creation
of a new conception of the
art museum as a cultural
centre". The Centre
houses an Important
collection of works
donated by its founder.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The whys and
wherefores of
education tomorrow
by Charles Hummel
CHILDREN who enter school today
will be about thirty years old in the
year 2000 and will therefore still be
in the early stages of their professional
careers. Those already in school will shape
the beginning of the next millennium.
In education, reforms and innovations
conceived today will not come into force
until a few years from now and it will be
several decades before their effects are felt.
Whenever an attempt is made to reform
existing educational systems, planning is
automatically implied, and it is thus essen¬
tial to try to make forecasts. Planning
means making choices, taking out options
on the future. Educational planning also
presupposes the existence of a political
purpose, for its aim is to bring into being a
given type of society.
A few years ago, educational planning
was still primarily conceived in quantitative
terms. For example, planners set out to
forecast the «number of enrolments in
schools, colleges and other educational
institutions, as well as the number of gra¬
duates they would turn out, and tried to
furnish a "product" that corresponded to
manpower requirements drawn up in the
light of economic and other objectives.
To some extent, this type of quantitative
educational planning has proved a failure,
largely because manpower needs cannot
be predicted over a long period.
It is generally admitted today that educa¬
tional planning should form part of a com¬
prehensive social policy designed to pro¬
mote changes and innovations that will
last. Since any policy reflects a system of
values, it is clear that educational planning
should be concerned with quality as much
as with quantity.
Planning also means forecasting how the
present situation will evolve, and defining
goals which are both desirable and realistic.
But the future is never completely open,
CHARLES HUMMEL, Switzerland's perma¬
nent delegate to Unesco, is a member of
Unesco's Executive Board. He also represents
Switzerland on the Council of the International
Bureau of Education, and was rapporteur at the
International Conference on Education held in
Geneva in 1975. The text published here forms
the conclusion of a study prepared for the Inter¬
national Conference andpublished by Unesco in
1977 as Education Today for the World of
Tomorrow.
r «J i jj
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
and the possibilities it holds are to a large
extent determined by the present and by
the past.
The future of education will depend
more on external factors political, .econo¬
mic, social and cultural than on the intrin¬
sic characteristics of educational systems.
These factors, which vary from country to
country and from region to region, will
determine tomorrow's education just as
they determine today's. However, as cer¬
tain similarities exist between educational
problems in different parts of the world,
one might expect to find certain common
trends appearing as well.
Certain trends do undoubtedly exist
which are bound to influence the future of
education. But their impact will obviously
depend on more general factors such as
economic growth. Until 1973 no one hesi¬
tated to base forecasts on the assumption
of continuing economic growth. Today this
hypothesis is extremely dubious, to say the
least.
It is more than likely that a slowdown in
economic growth, not to mention econo¬
mic stagnation or even a prolonged reces¬
sion, would hamper any attempts to re¬
structure educational systems, as well as
putting a brake on educational expansion.
The first signs of this have already ap¬
peared. There is a danger that reforms may
lose their- impetus, especially in the indus¬
trialized countries.
If the world, or at least most countries,
should enter a period of widespread insta¬
bility and insecurity and this seems to be
happening far-reaching changes in hu¬
man relationships could be on the way. In
seeking greater stability, social systems
may well tend to become more rigid. For
education this would imply a return to
more authoritarian teaching methods and
more rigid structures.
On the world political scene there is a
growing awareness that the future destiny
of mankind hinges on the establishment of
a new international economic order.
The task that lies ahead is to strike an
acceptable balance between the devel¬
oping world and the industrially developed
countries, and to create a world-wide soli¬
darity among peoples. Without this solida¬
rity, we cannot hope to survive on our pla¬
net, that rudderless boat adrift on hostile
waters. This task must be accomplished in
the very near future and it is in the broadest
sense an educational one. Although we
may not realize it, the race is on between
education and catastrophe.
The new world order cannot be based
exclusively on economic .considerations. It
must be social and cultural as well. Insofar
as it does or does notcome into being,
it will determine the future development of
education throughout the world. If it does
not come about, world peace will be
gravely threatened. If, on the other
hand, there is a real determination to reduce
injustice in this world of ours, then the edu¬
cational systems of the developing coun¬
tries are bound to expand at an unprece¬
dented rate.
But even if we accept the most optimis¬
tic forecasts about the resources available
to the developing countries after successful
negotiations on the establishment of a new
world economic order, it seems highly un¬
likely that the educational problems of
these countries will be solved by traditional
European teaching methods, often dating
from the 19th century.
It seems more realistic to suppose that
the new forms of non-formal education
now being developed will gain ground.
One does not need to go so far as the
famous thinker Ivan lllich, who believes
that the school as an institution is on the
way out, to feel that education will increas¬
ingly be affected by a certain "despool¬
ing" process. Teaching methods being
developed outside the schools, especially
those such as group dynamics now being
used in adult education, will have a grow¬
ing influence on teaching in the schools.
Non-formal educational activities and
above all the mass media are bound to have
a stronger impact.
All these influences will force schools to
open their doors to the outside world.
Teaching will become more flexible and
more relevant. It will break out of the
straightjacket of tradition and become
more closely associated with "cultural
development" in the widest sense.
This flexibility will be reflected in the
classroom: instead of being grouped ac¬
cording to age, pupils will be grouped
according to the extent of their knowledge.
Wide areas of the curriculum will be taught
outside the school, especially in other cul¬
tural institutions.
The extent of "deschooling" will, how¬
ever, depend on future economic perfor¬
mance. It will take place at a faster rate if
there is economic growth, for it is bound to
slow down during a recession if only
because new schools (or educational and
cultural centres) will have to be built to free
education from the excessively rigid struc¬
tures of today.
The concept of lifelong education seems
certain to change the face of education
throughout the world, even though it is still
far from being generally understood and
has not yet been fully integrated into any
educational system. But wherever major
educational reforms are carried out, they
will be conceived with lifelong education in
mind. This means that education systems
will become more coherent, but at the
same time more complex and therefore k
more unwieldy. V
Between 1960 and 1972, enrolment in
secondary schools throughout the world
grew faster than in primary schools, and
enrolment in higher education increased
even more rapidly. The greatest
discrimination seems to occur when
children reach primary school age, but for
those who succeed in entering the
system, chances of gaining admission to
the higher levels are Improving.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
It also means that more and more people
will be engaged in learning. Pre-school
education will become universal, young
people will stay on longer at school, and
adults including the elderlywill enjoy
many more educational opportunities.
Education is already a mammoth undertak¬
ing: there are more than 50 million young
people in school in the U.S.A., and India
has over 100 million schoolchildren.
Tomorrow it may be absorbing an even big¬
ger share of national budgets, and so
cheaper, more efficient ways of teaching
will have to be found.
Expanded education systems will
become even more inert and resistant to
change than they already are. Far-reaching
reforms will need the most powerful back¬
ing if they are to succeed. There is a dan¬
ger that the "old democracies", where un¬
stable political situations seem to be gra¬
dually developing, may lose the necessary
strength to launch major reforms. The
most remarkable educational innovations in
the future may well appear in the "young"
developing countries.
The democratization of education is
already a major priority in many countries.
This trend will continue, and will probably
be reinforced by a growing decentraliza¬
tion, particularly in educational administra¬
tion.
It is likely that lessons will be learned
from certain failures to achieve equality of
opportunity, but one can assume that the
idea of equality will be further developed
and refined. This will be encouraged by the
strong trend towards individualized
teaching, for equality no longer means "the
same education for all", but "the best edu¬
cation for everyone".
The democratization of education will
put greater pressure on higher education,
and the resulting difficulties such as gra¬
duate unemployment, will become more
serious. The remedy for these problems
will not be found within educational
systems.
It may well be asked whether a different
division of labour may not solve the prob¬
lem. It is also possible that we may be
moving towards an increasingly strong
meritocracy.
As education becomes more democratic,
there will probably be an even greater tend¬
ency to standardize instruction up to the
end of the first stage of secondary school,
but adding an increasingly wide choice of
options to this common core. The same
trend will also be encouraged by the conti¬
nuing need of qualified people to keep
abreast of the latest developments in
science and technology. It will become
normal practice to change careers at least
once in a lifetime. The distinction between
general and vocational education will grad¬
ually disappear, since the ability to adapt to
change will become more important than
the possession of specific knowledge or
skills.
A few years ago, everyone expected that
such technological developments as class¬
room TV and computers would completely
revolutionize education. But although
some changes have occurred, they have
been far fewer than might have been fore
seen. Education systems have so far prov¬
ed surprisingly resistant to the impact of
new educational technology. It is thus
unlikely that they will bring about any major
changes in the future.
' International and regional organizations
will play an increasingly important role in
the development of education systems.
There have already been several instances
of new guidelines for education being
worked out in such organizations before
being taken up at the national level.
It is thanks to international organizations
that avant-garde thinking is crystallized and
disseminated. The international organiza¬
tions are the great catalysts of thought,
research and development in the service of
all nations.
It is also the international organizations,
and primarily Unesco in the field of educa¬
tion, which are creating networks for the
exchange of information and experience-
arteries which are vital to modern proces¬
ses of innovationas well as structures for
practical co-operation.
There is, however, a certain tendency to
establish international co-operation on a
regional basis. In some cases regional
bodies are tending to take the place of the
truly international organizations, which
have often become too unwieldy, too
ambitious and too "politicized" to provide
with maximum efficiency the "technical"
services that governments need.
Perhaps the promotion and co¬
ordination of regional activities will become
new tasks for the international organiza¬
tions, whose work will in turn become
more decentralized.
As the world becomes increasingly inter¬
dependent, international co-operation in
education will become more imperative
than ever. As a result the problems to be
solved will be increasingly similar, and
there will be an ever growing need for the
exchange of information, the comparison
of solutions adopted, and united action.
Charles Hummel
Portrait of Jules Verne (1828 - 1905)
by his friend Nadar. When this photo
was taken about a century ago, Jules
Verne already had a wide readership.
Today his popularity is still growing.
According to Unesco's Statistical
Yearbook 1976, he is one of the three
most translated authors in the world
(with 156 translations in 1976). Only
Lenin (348 translations) and Agatha
Christie (159) had a higher score. His
universal appeal is due not only to his
outstanding gifts as a storyteller but
also to his prophetic qualities. In
Autour de la Lune, 1870 (published in
English as From the Earth to the
Moon... anda Trip Around It, 1873)
he described the weightlessness that
modern astronauts would later
experience. Right, drawing from the
first edition showing the hero happily
and weightlessly afloat.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Jules Verne
Seer of the Space Age
by Alain Bombard
To mark the 150th anniversary of the birth
of Jules Verne the Unesco Courier has
asked Dr. Alain Bombard to evoke the life
and work of the great French writer who
was one of the founders of modern
science fiction. Dr. Bombard could
qualify as a Jules Verne hero in his own
right. In 1952, to test shipwreck survival
techniques, he sailed across the Atlantic
on a tiny rubber raft without either food
or fresh water, surviving the 65-day
crossing from the Canary Islands to the
West Indies by catching fish.
J
ULES Verne was born in the Breton
seaport of Nantes 150 years ago, on
8 February 1828.
ALAIN BOMBARD, French marine biologist
and doctor, is the author of numerous scientific
studies. His account of his trans-Atlantic cros¬
sing on a rubber raft has been translated into a
number of languages, and appeared in English
as Dr. Bombard Goes to Sea (Vanguard Press,
New York).
His stories have been part of my life ever
since my earliest childhood. My mother's
parents had known him at the height of his
fame, and their house near Paris, where we
used to spend our Sundays, was crammed
with his books.
We used to imagine we were the children
of Captain Grant, and pretend to be other
heroes of his novels, such as Dr. Liden-
broek and Captain Hatteras. We fought
tooth and nail for the honour of being Cap
tain Nemo of 20,000 Leagues under the
Sea.
Maybe that was how my destiny was
shaped. I would be a mariner like Nemo, a
discoverer like Cyrus Smith, a shipwrecked
sailor like Kazallon (in The Survivors of the
Chance/or), a castaway on a Mysterious
Island.
Jules Verne was the apostle of a con¬
structive, useful science, as opposed to the
kind that kills or threatens mankind. He
foresaw many later inventions (for Verne
invented nothing himself; he simply projec¬
ted his ideas of progress into the future) k
but he also perceived their potential for evil f
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Verne
prophesies
a Pacific
splashdown
The astronauts' splashdown in
Jules Verne's novel From the
Earth to the Moon (left, the
original illustration by Emile
Bayard) proved astonishingly
prophetic over a century later
when the U.S. Apollo 8 spacecraft
landed in the Pacific (right) a
mere two and a half miles from
the point mentioned in the novel.
In a letter to Jules Verne's
grandson, the commander of
Apollo 8, Frank Borman, paid
tribute to Verne's visionary genius
as "one of the great pioneers of
the space age". "Our space
vehicle was launched from
Florida, like Barbicane's," he
wrote, "and it had the same
weight and height." Would Verne
have been surprised by this
uncanny accuracy? Perhaps not,
for he once wrote: "For
Americans the Moon isn't much
further than Texas."
(as we can see in such works as The
Begum's Fortune, For the Flag and Master
of the World), and spoke out against their
use for destructive purposes.
Jules Verne was a prophet of progress,
not of violence. He may have had an over-
optimistic view of progress, but he believed
that it was bound to bring an improvement
in people's lives, take the backbreak out of
their labour, and ultimately bring them hap¬
piness.
Jules Verne first answered the call of the
sea in 1839 when at the age of 11 he
stowed away aboard the Cora/ie, a three-
master bound for the Indies. What an
adventure it would be to bring back a coral
necklace for his cousin Caroline, with
whom he had fallen madly and unhappily in
love!
As the anchors were weighed and the
vessel slipped out of Nantes into the Loire
estuary, a life of adventure stretched
before him. But the escapade lasted only a
day, for when the boat put into the nearby
port of Paimbceuf that evening, the would-
be sailor was recovered by his anxious
father.
His wings clipped, he decided to settle
for a legal career, and left Nantes to study
law in Paris in 1848, shortly after the dra¬
matic events that had drowned the fledg¬
ling Republic in blood and trampled the
demands of the workers. A reluctant law
student, he nevertheless managed to
obtain his degree in 1849.
He began to dabble in literature and tried
his hand as a playwright. Thanks to the
friendship and help of the elder Dumas,
one of his plays was performed, but it was
received with a chorus of boos and cat¬
calls, and the budding dramatist wondered
whether he might not be better off as a
lawver after all.
About this time, Verne developed a pas¬
sion for science. First of all he studied geo¬
graphy, and then took up mathematics
with the help of his cousin, a student at the
Polytechnique. He became fascinated by
the way the slightest miscalculation in
physics could have disastrous conse¬
quences.
Here lie the origins of the mathematician
J.T. Maston's astonishingly accurate cal¬
culations in From the Earth to the Moon, as
well as his monumental error in Sans Des¬
sus Dessous ("The Purchase of the North
Pole"), one of Verne's most remarkable
novels.
This is the tale of an attempt to shift the
Earth's axis to the perpendicular, as a result
Qf which the whole world will enjoy a tem¬
perate climate without extremes of heat
and cold. A tunnel is dug into Mount Kili¬
manjaro to house a gigantic cannon which
will fire a single shell whose recoil will be
powerful enough to "correct" the Earth's
axis. The experiment takes place, but fails
when Maston, who is responsible for the
calculations, loses his concentration at a
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
First inklings of the laser beam?
"... He added that by sending light rays concentrated in beams by parabolic
mirrors, it would be possible to establish direct communications. These rays
would be as visible on the surface of Venus or Mars as the planet Neptune is
from the Earth. He concluded by saying that bright spots already observed on
the nearest planets could well be signals being made to Earth."
Jules Verne
From the Earth to the Moon...
and a trip around It (1870)
crucial moment and makes a colossal error.
In the 1850s Verne tried his hand at two
travel stories, Un Voyage en Ballon ("Jour¬
ney in a Balloon") and A Winter amid the
Ice. They were only moderately success¬
ful, but they finally decided their author to
turn away from the theatre (where he had
had another ignominious flop).
In 1857, he married a young widow
named Honorine de Vignes, whom he had
met at a friend's wedding in Amiens. Two
years later, he was offered a free trip to
Scotland, and used his experiences there
as the basis for an exciting novel called
Black Diamonds in which he plunged his
readers into the depths of an abandoned
Scottish coal-mine.
For most of his life, however, Verne was
an armchair traveller, who took his often
limited daily experiences and transformed
them in his work. He always used a factual
starting-point for those flights of the imagi
nation which took him through time and
across distant continents.
On his return from Scotland, he met
Jules Hetzel, a young Paris publisher with a
particular interest in children's books.
Verne showed him the manuscript of
"Journey in a Balloon", which was rewor¬
ked and published by Hetzel as Five Weeks
in a Balloon, the account of an expedition
across then-uncharted regions of Africa.
At that time, geographers were involved in
heated controversy about the location of
the main source of the Nile, and in Five
Weeks in a Balloon Verne opted for the
hypothesis that it flows out of Lake Victor¬
ia. Fifteen years later he was proved right.
Author and publisher became firm
friends, and Verne signed a contract with
Hetzel, committing himself to writing three
volumes a year. Now he was well and truly
launched as a writer of fiction and his
genius could begin to express itself fully,
memory, he started work on 777e English at
the North Pole, the first part of a long novel
about polar exploration called "The Adven¬
tures of Captain Hatteras". (All his life
Verne was fascinated by the polar regions,
which appear in many of his stories such as
20,000 Leagues under the Sea, The Fur
Country, The Clipper of the Clouds and An
Antarctic Mystery.) Before completing his
polar novel, however, he published A Jour¬
ney to the Centre of the Earth in 1864.
This was the only occasion when Jules
Verne's extremely logical mind led him
astray, for this gripping and amusing tale is
packed with scientific howlers. The plot is
highly implausible, to say the least, and
generations of vulcanologists have tut-
tutted at the idea of being able to plunge
into the bowels of the Earth through Mount
Sneffels, the mysterious volcano in Ice¬
land, and then pop up in the Mediterranean
during a volcanic eruption of Stromboli
With his Scottish jaunt still fresh in his Captain Hatteras's search for the North
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Machines
for mastery
of air,
land
and sea
Jules Verne took immense care with the details of the ingenious locomotive machines
and contraptions that play such a memorable part in his work. Above, rivalling the
eagles: a scene from Master of the World (1904). To make the fantastic birdlike flying
machine sound as feasible as possible, Verne went over its description word by word
with an engineer. But of course, he was not propounding a device that actually
worked but drawing attention to the possibilities of heavier-than-air flight at a time
when most people believed only in the dirigible balloon. Steam-driven elephant (below
left) is a more far-fetched Verne vehicle. It pulled two wheeled edifices through India
in The Steam House 11880). Below right, one of Verne's most unforgettable
characters. Captain Nemo of 20,000 Leagues under the Sea (1870) gazes through a
porthole of submarine Nautilus at "a squid of colossal dimensions."
Photos © Editions Hachette, Pans
>Pole aboard the Forward, on the other
hand, turned out to be astonishingly accu¬
rate. The Forward sailed as far North as
latitude 83°35' before becoming ice-bound.
Further north the ice never melts, not even
in summer, and no one had ever ventured
to these desolate regions. Forty years
later, the American explorer Commodore
Peary chose a spot just 10 km. away from
this same latitude to establish the base
camp for his successful trek to the North
Pole.
In 1865 came a novel of space explora¬
tion, From the Earth to the Moon. Here
again, Verne was almost dead on target.
His Moon projectile was fired from a spot in
Florida not far from the present-day Cape
Kennedy. What is more, Verne's manned
projectile made a splashdown in mid-
ocean, just like Apollo 8 a century later. On
the whole Jules Verne made more accurate
predictions and fewer mistakes about the
future than any other "prophetic" writer.
By now Verne was producing novels at a
furious rate. Notable works from this
period are The Children of Captain Grant
and The Mysterious Island, two tales of
adventure on land and sea which have pro-
.bably influenced later generations of vulca-
nologists, submarine explorers and speleo¬
logists more than any of his other works.
In real life too, he became a seafarer and
a geographer. He bought a converted fish¬
ing boat, the Saint Michel, and in the sum¬
mer of 1866 wrote a remarkable geographi¬
cal dictionary of France. The follow¬
ing year he sailed for America aboard the
world's biggest passenger liner, the Great
Eastern, on its last Atlantic crossing. The
voyage provided Verne with material for
the novel A Floating City, and from his visit
to America, much too brief for his liking, he
drew the sharply-observed Will of an
Eccentric.
The characters in this amusing and little-
known novel play a game with dice and a
checkerboard covered with a map of the
United States. After throwing dice, the
players move their counters forward by a
corresponding number of squares and
must then visit the state shown in the
square before playing again.
A few years later, in 20,000 Leagues
under the Sea, Verne created the unforget¬
table Captain Nemo, perhaps the most fas¬
cinating figure in all his work. Nemo is a
greater man than even the mighty Robur, k
hero of The Clipper of the Clouds, although r
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Around the world in films
With their unique blend of adventure, dreamlike fantasy and
precise observation, Jules Verne's stories have been a gold-mine
for 20th-century film-makers in many countries. Some, such as
'The Children of Captain Grant and Around the World in Eighty
Days, have been filmed more than once, and no less than nine
screen versions have been made of Michel Strogoff. Shown
here, stills from three films based on Verne's works. (1) Le
Voyage dans la Lune by the pioneer French cineast Georges
Meliès (1902), freely adapted from the novel From the Earth to
the Moon; (2) and (3): scenes from The Invention of Destruction
(1957) by the Czech Karel Zeman, based on For the Flag (and
other Verne novels). Zeman skilfully recreated the period flavour-
in backdrops, props and costumes, so that the settings looked
exactly like the original illustrations. (4) David Niven as a
debonair Phileas Fogg is attended by his valet Passepartout
(played by the Mexican actor Cantinflas) in this airborne scene
from Mike Todd's Around the World in Eighty Days (1956)
directed by Michael Anderson.
Photos © Cinémathèque Française, Paris
f Tolstoy sketches
Phileas Fogg
Among Jules Verne's millions of fans all round the world was the
great Russian novelist Leo Tolstoy (1828 - 1910). Tolstoy often
read Verne's stories aloud to his children, and amused himself by
sketching a number of scenes from Around the World ¡n Eighty
Days in the margin of his copy of the novel, which was not an
illustrated edition. Left, Tolstoy's drawing of Phileas Fogg's
dramatic return to London after his round-the-world trip.
Photo© LN Tolstov Museum, Moscow
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
, Robur wields mastery of the air and the
oceans by inventing a fantastic heavier-
than-air flying machine which retracts its
wings and propellers to become a subma¬
rine and sprouts wheels for driving on land.
For Jules Verne, Nemo is a complete man:
he is the personification of genius,
altruism, goodness, generosity and learn¬
ing, in spite of his one great failing, his
thirst for vengeance.
In the person of Harry Killer, Verne also
created a character who used science for
evil purposes. In L'Etonnante Aventure de
la Mission Barsac (published in English in
two volumes as Into the Niger Bend and
City In the Sahara), Killer rules a town in
which he keeps a huge force of slaves and
a captive team of scientists and technicians
who spend their lives producing fabulous
inventionsweapons,- devices for fertili¬
zing the desert, ingenious flying
machines all used to serve the purposes
of crime, murder and tyranny. Verne's
message is that the scientist, who is capa¬
ble of providing humanity with inestimable
benefits, can also perpetrate the greatest
evil.
Although Jules Verne foretold the
machine age, he did not foresee the social
changes that the 20th century would bring.
In this respect he remained firmly rooted in
the 19th century; he never produced any
."politics fiction".
His genius lay first and foremost in his
extraordinary scientific rationalism and his
faith in humanity. He predicted the advent
of the submarine (in 20,000 Leagues Under
the Sea), the aeroplane (the "Mission Bar¬
sac"), the helicopter (in The Clipper of the
Clouds and Master of the World), and wea¬
pons of destruction ( The Begum's Fortune
and For the Flag) as well as prophesying
interplanetary and interstellar travel (in
From the Earth to the Moon... and a Trip
Around It, and Hector Servadac ), and des¬
cribing big city life (Propellor Island) and
life in natural surroundings (The Giant
Raft).
He foresaw the depletion of natural
resources, but he failed to predict pollution
and the rift beween man and his environ¬
ment. He was blind to the need to preserve
the balance of Nature and knew nothing of
ecology. No work of "biology fiction"
came from his pen. This is perhaps one's
sole cause for regret when confronted with
his otherwise monumental achievement.
Alain Bombard
To our readers
Unesco Courier
now in 18 languages
We are happy to announce the launching
of a new language edition of the
"Unesco Courier". The first issue of
"Kurier", the "Unesco Courier" in
Bahasa Malaysia, has just been pub¬
lished in Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia) by
Penerbit Universiti Malaya (University of
Malaysia Press). The publication of this
new edition, which began in February,
brings the total number of language edi¬
tions of the "Unesco Courier" to 18:
English, French, Spanish, Russian, Ger¬
man, Arabic, Japanese, Italian, Hindi,
Tamil, Hebrew, Persian, Dutch, Portu¬
guese, Turkish, Urdu, Catalan and
Bahasa-Malaysia. The launching of edi¬
tions in Korean and Kiswahili are schedu¬
led to take place later this year.
In the last few months there has been a
steep increase in the number of
subscribers to the UNESCO COURIER.
We now count tens of thousands of new
readers, to whom we should like to
extend a warm welcome.
However, we regret to say that because
of the sheer number of new
subscriptions, it has proved difficult to
respect our usual schedules for
processing them (between six and
eight weeks).
Furthermore, for reasons beyond our
control, the most recent issues of the
UNESCO COURIER have been published
with a certain delay. We ask our readers'
indulgence for this situation, which we
are doing all we can to remedy.
We sincerely hope that you will continue
to enjoy our magazine in spite of these
temporary difficulties.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Information
please...
Continued from page 9
the various information handling institu¬
tions such as libraries and documentation
centres. Internationally, the aim is to fur¬
ther develop transnational information
systems and ensure compatibility among
existing and prospective programmes,
especially those related to the storage and
retrieval of scientific information.
UNISIST Is also concerned with formu¬
lating national information policies, plann¬
ing information service networks, and pro¬
moting research on the acquisition, pro¬
cessing, and dissemination of data, as well
as setting international standards and gui¬
delines. In addition, it provides assistance
to countries in setting up information cen¬
tres, as well as in training and retraining
information specialists. The ultimate aim is
the progressive integration of national,
regional and international information ser¬
vices into a single world network.
, The most spectacular demand for a rapid
transfer of knowledge comes, of course,
from developing areas. Developing coun¬
tries, handicapped by a scarcity of accessi¬
ble information and expertise, can only
develop scientifically and technologically as
the result of enormous effort and sacrifice.
Moreover, a natural tendency to imitate
foreign models sometimes leads such
countries to turn their backs on more pro¬
ductive and original paths to economic
development.
Y endeavouring to make
scientific information
more easily available to
developing countries, Unesco hopes to
help them in technological and scientific
policy-making, as well as stimulating
industrial and economic growth. In other
words, there is an awareness of the close
connexion between a new world infor¬
mation network and a new international
economic order. Indeed, this is one
reason why Unesco has made assistance
to developing countries an important
feature of the UNISIST programme.
This assistance comprises field missions
by experts and consultants, practical
recommendations for improving national
information services, organization of semi¬
nars and refresher courses for local specia¬
lists, and provision of direct financial aid.
In 1977, help of this kind was extended to
Somalia, Senegal, Sudan, Morocco and
Ghana.
While assistance to developing countries
accounts for a significant part of UNISIST
programme activities, it is also imperative
to think in terms of larger regional units.
Consequently, in 1976 and 1977 Unesco
organized a number of regional meetings
in Delhi, for South and Central Asia; in
Tunis, for the Arab countries; in Bali, for
South- East Asia, to name but three to
draw up a blue-print for regional co¬
operation and to promote the access of
developing countries to world stocks of
scientific documentation, and to train
documentalists.
In Europe, the first regional conference
on the exchange of social science informa¬
tion took place under Unesco auspices in
Moscow in June 1977. This conference,
which brought together representatives of
information centres in Western Europe and
the Socialist countries, was jointly organi¬
zed by the European Centre for co¬
ordination of Social Science Research and
Documentation (Vienna) and the Institute
of Social Science Information of the
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences. It consti¬
tutes a positive step towards implementing
decisions reached during the Helsinki con¬
ference and may serve as a model for Euro¬
pean co-operation in this field. A second
European conference is due to be held in
Poland in October, 1978.
Unesco initiatives at the regional level
complement international efforts to build a
flexible network based on the voluntary co¬
operation of a number of information ser¬
vices, such as the International Nuclear
Information System UNIS).
INIS exchanges information among its
49 Member States through a world infor¬
mation centre located in Vienna (Austria).
Each Member State, together with a num¬
ber of international organizations, issues
monthly data on scientific research. ' This
data is fed into a computer, micro-copies of
scientific abstracts are made, and the resul¬
ting information is forwarded to each natio¬
nal centre. In this way, each Member State
processes its own data using a standard
system and receives data on scientific
research in the other Member States.
Countries can thus make use of available
information in an economical way. Each
month, for example, Vienna forwards to
Mexico's National Institute for Nuclear
Energy information on the latest scientific
publications together with reports from
France, the U.S.S.R., the U.S.A., Italy,
Poland and other countries all of it con¬
densed, ready to use, and in one language.
Some of these information systems also
play an important part in the regional deve¬
lopment of UNISIST. A case in point is the
Moscow International Centre for Scientific
and Technical Information. It has been
given a key role by the Council for Mutual
Economic Assistance (CMEA) within the
scientific and technological information
system currently being organized by Bul¬
garia, Hungary, the German Democratic
Republic, Mongolia, Cuba, Poland, Roma¬
nia, the U.S.S.R. and Czechoslovakia.
HE Moscow Centre's
activities cover virtually
every field of natural
science and technology, from industry and
transport to energy and medicine. In the
case of research reports, periodicals and
translations from little-used languages, it
receives information from different coun¬
tries. As a research institute, it provides
advice on standardization, technical plann¬
ing and electronic data-processing equip¬
ment.
As a regional agency within the frame¬
work of the UNISIST programme, the Cen¬
tre is compiling a world register of scientific
periodicals, and is helping Mongolia and
Cuba to develop their national information
systems.
In Western Europe, the Euronet system
represents an ambitious attempt on the
part of the Common Market countries to
store and exchange scientific and technical
information. The need for an improved
system of information-exchange made
itself felt as early as 1967 and in December
1975 representatives of the post-offices of
the nine member countries signed a con¬
tract to set up such a system.
The Common Market's Committee for
Research, Science and Technology
(CREST) plans to make the network opera¬
tional as quickly as possible. It is tackling
three major areas: extending and rationali¬
zing information services; providing access
to computerized data bases by means of a
telecommunications network; and training
professional staff and system users. An
idea of the overall scope may be gauged by
the projected figure of 700 terminals, each
asking three or four questions a day, giving
an estimated total traffic of some half a mil¬
lion questions per year by 1980.
The exchange of information across
national boundaries is a desirable develop¬
ment, but it also brings new problems in its |
wake. Sometimes, relevant information is I
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
.scattered in a wide range of documentation
'in scores of languages. Then too, informa¬
tion is becoming obsolete at an accelera¬
ting rate. As a result, governments often
lack the up-to-date, complete information
needed to take pressing decisions.
To meet this new demand, Unesco is
working on a project called SPINES, an
international science and technology poli¬
cies information exchange system. Ini¬
tially, it is envisaged as a voluntary co¬
operative arrangement between eight to
ten countries (the United States, the U.K.,
France, the Federal Republic of Germany,
the German Democratic Republic, Poland,
Spain, the U.S.S.R. and possibly also India
and Japan) but its potential users range
from governments and national scientific
bodies to academic institutions, industry
and international organizations.
What kind of problems would SPINES
help to solve? For developing countries the
possibilities are endless. Imagine that a
developing African country has discovered
vast deposits of uranium within its terri¬
tory. How should it exploit this newfound
source of wealth? Export the crude ura¬
nium ore, export pre-processed ore, or
establish a uranium enrichment plant and
then export enriched uranium?
Depending on circumstances, any one of
these solutions may be correct. But what¬
ever the choice, the information obtained
through SPINES should afford a wide
range of experience on which to base an
informed decision.
The worldwide preoccupation with infor¬
mation systems reflects something more
than a sudden surge of interest in data pro¬
cessing; it represents a marked social and
economic trend.
Whether we like it or not, information
theory and its applications have already
begun to bring about far-reaching changes
in the lives of millions of people, and we
must prepare ourselves for the consequen¬
ces. The next two or three decades may
well see the completion of a fully automatic
science information network serving the
majority of the countries taking part in the
UNISIST programme.
Yuri I. Litukhin
Hundredth
issue of
DIOGENES
WITH the publication of its 100th issue, the quarterly review
Diogenes celebrates its 25th anniversary. Published with
Unesco support by the International Council for Philosophy and
Humanistic Studies, it appears in three language editions
(English, French and Spanish). It also produces yearly
anthologies in Arabic, Hindi, Japanese and possibly Portuguese
in the near future. Its role is unique in contemporary culture.
The current issue, though not devoted to a single theme, is
nevertheless bigger than usual and its contents are extremely rich,
and varied. (The French edition is now available; the English
edition will be published early in the summer.)
Each article sheds new light on an unusual aspect of
contemporary life, ranging from the new "sign language", a
study of the signs, posters and billboards in modern cities, to
"articulturists", those who live from art without creating it; from
healing by radio as practised by certain Brazilian religious sects
to a study of the cultural level of illiterate peoples.
Arthur Koestler, Jean Starobinski and Jean Fourastié examine
the nature of imagination and discuss the relationship between
science and poetry. The sources and meaning of Pop Art are
also analyzed, while a mathematician looks into the conditions
which favour the birth of scientific hypotheses. Another article,
a study of America's "new economists", examines the latest of
those intellectual movements that sweep America before
reaching Europe and the rest of the world.
The aims of Diogenes have been defined on several occasions by
Its founder and editor-in-chief, Roger Caillois. First and
foremost, it is international in outlook and scope. Most literary,
artistic and scientific magazines and reviews, as well as those
originating in the universities, are linked to a specific culture.
Diogenes, as the organ of an international council and supported
by Unesco, knows no cultural boundaries. Obviously, it takes
Into account the decisive importance of cultural identity, but
since it does not originate from within a given culture. It
deliberately adopts an international and intercultural outlook.
It Is also interdisciplinary in approach. "Interdisclplinarity" has
come Into vogue in recent years, and the pages of Diogenes may
have had something to do with that. However, unlike many
publications, Diogenes is not content merely to present a
diversified, many-sided approach to problems. It also tries to
establish parallels between often remote fields and disciplines.
Such hitherto hidden affinities herald those "diagonal sciences"
with which the name of Roger Caillois is so closely linked.
Along with this, Diogenes has also helped to broaden the very
concept of human sciences. Though it is a cultural review, it
also covers such rapidly changing disciplines as those connected
with biology, physics and chemistry. The interests and curiosity
of Diogenes range from the study of poetry and art through
linguistics, anthropology, psychiatry and economics to the exact
sciences.
Diogenes is thus opposed to narrow specialization and an
excessive division of labour in the sciences. This does not mean,
however, that it questions the need for analysis or scholarship,
nor that it champions hastily-formulated synthesis. The
avowed aim of Diogenes is to forge much-needed links .
between the various branches of science today.
This already gives some indication of the public Diogenes wants
to reach. Steering between excessive detail and vague
generalization, it is designed for specialists who wish to keep up
with developments in disciplines other than their own. Useless
jargon and glib systematizing are equally banned, as the review
seeks to provide for its readers the fullest possible picture of the
way science is moving and the relationships between its various
branches.
Diogenes rejects both pedantry and simplistic explanations, and
in so doing meets a need felt in a broad range of scientific and
cultural circles. In the last 25 years it has earned a reputation
which can be measured not only by the fidelity of its readers but
by the number of scientific studies and university theses that
quote it.
Diogenes feels that it has remained faithful to its ambitions and
that in contemporary cultural life it is playing the role of a
pioneer, a catalyst and a vehicle for ideas. In this way It forms a
link between scientific innovation and the curiosity of a wide
public.
Jean d'Ormesson
of the Académie Française.
Secretary-general of the International
Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies
Editorial offices of Diogenes: 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15
Subscriptions for English edition:
Casalini Libri
50014 FIESOLE (Florence), Italy
Single issue: $3
Year's subscription: $10
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Just published
The development of solar energy systems is one of the
greatest challenges facing our fuel-hungry and
increasingly polluted world. In
Solar Electricity
Wolfang Palz surveys all the known ways in which the
sun's radiation can be converted into power. For the
non-scientific reader, the book provides a full and clear
introduction to the science and techniques of solar
energy. Specialists and prospective users of solar
devices will also be interested in the reviews of the
latest research and development.
Co-published with Butterworths, London, who have
exclusive sales rights in the United Kingdom.
292 pages 140 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division, Campbell House, 100
Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000. AUSTRIA. Dr.
Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandlung, Industrie*
hof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220 Wien. BEL¬
GIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Handel-
maatschappij Keesing Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation N% 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Qu' H3H
1M7. CYPRUS. "MAM", Archishop Makarios 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicnl literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1, For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, N% 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahnr Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskukatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH Karger Buchhandlung. Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/Múnchen. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legón, P O. Box 1, Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkoztârsasâg utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Cal¬
cutta 13, 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf All
Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-
560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016;
Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of
Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish
ing and Distribution Co., 139 Shah Reza Ave., opposite to Uni¬
versity of Teheran, P.O. Box 14/1480, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. MAURI¬
TIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
- MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition
only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V. Marti-
nus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.), N.V.,
Willemstad, Cura¿ao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O.
Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christ-
church; Alma street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street,
P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Welling¬
ton. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The Univer¬
sity Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturje-
neste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65
Sarah Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIP¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632,
Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I
Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.
7.00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Uda,
Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, MahV
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (SI Pte Ltd., No. 1 New
Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General. P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O, Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales
(PVTI Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata
P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.
Box 1118, Khartoun. - SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Fbrbundet,
Skolgránd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030
Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaegi Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402,
Bangkok: Suksapan Pamt, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Brimingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Sta¬
tion New York, N.Y. 10016. For "Unesco Courier" in Spanish:
Santillana Publishing Company, Inc., 575 Lexington Avenue,
New York, N.Y. 10022. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovénie, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
March 1978 from
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
news
unesco
Bogotá:
a 'turning-point'
in international
cultural
co-operation
The Mint at Potosi, Bolivia, a fine example
of the architectural heritage of Latin America.
Despite the ethnic variety and the
cultural diversity of their peoples, Latin
America and the Caribbean constitute a
single region with a common destiny
and a mission to serve mankind.
This conclusion, in the view of many
observers, was one of the chief
accomplishments of the
Intergovernmental Conference on
Cultural Policies in Latin America and
the Caribbean. Held in Bogotá from 10
to 20 January, the conference was
termed "a turning-point in the history
of international cultural co-operation"
by Unesco Director-General Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow.
"You have reached a very broad
consensus with regard to the general
questions on the conference's agenda,"
he told the delegates at the closing
session. "Such unity, as many of you
have stressed, is made up of many
diversities, but it is solidly founded on a
rich cultural heritage regarded very
much as a common one. Above all, it
is founded on solidarity and on respect
for others, which is not merely a
commitment or a tactic but is derived
from ethical values, from a feeling for
the human that is a characteristic of
your civilizations."
"A major theme of your debates has
been that of cultural pluralism, " he
continued. "Such pluralism is much
more than just a general openness to
others which even in itself would not
be so bad; it is the very essence of your
cultural identities. Openness to the
most diverse contributions and a
welcome for all immigrations, certainly;
but also, and above all, it is the
unceasing and often heroic struggle of
the humble, the oppressed and the
exiled from everywhere. Thus the revolt
of the African slave to achieve his
dignity finds its counterpart in the hopes
of the emigrant from Europe or Asia
seeking in your countries not only well-
being but also freedom and respect for
human rights."
The Bogotá meeting was the fourth such
conference to be convened by Unesco,
the others having been held in Helsinki
for the Organization's European
Member States, in 1972; in Jogjakarta
in 1973 for Asia, and in Accra in 1975,
for Africa. A similar conference is
planned for the Arab states in 1979, to
be followed by a world conference on
cultural policies in 1981 or 1982.
The Bogotá conference declared that
more economic growth, unless offset by
adequate and effective cultural policies,
leads to serious imbalances in the life
style of peoples, and called on Member
States to "incorporate the cultural
dimension in integral development plans
where this has not yet been done, and
increase and organize it properly where
it already exists."
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Cultural policies, the conference added,
should be founded on the basic concept
of personal freedom within the
framework of each community and
"with maximum respect for the
originality, authenticity and freedom of
cultural values."
The conference called upon the
Director-General of Unesco to take
concrete action to secure the restitution
of works of art which have been
claimed by countries of the region and
to study the possibility of international
action to safeguard the rich artistic and
historical heritage of Latin America,
particularly the town of Potosi in
Bolivia, which is threatened with
destruction.
Delegates also gave their approval to a
mechanism permitting continuous
implementation of the conference
decisions based on close co-operation
among Latin American countries
themselves and with international
organizations such as the United
Nations Development Programme and
the Inter-American Development Bank.
Calling for the stepping up of action
already undertaken to achieve a
"Common Market in Books" in the
region, the conference also stressed the
vital importance of the circulation of
books for the diffusion of ideas and the
working of intercultural influences. It
also demanded a programme to
facilitatefinancially, technically and
administratively the free circulation of
cultural property as well as theatrical
exchanges and exchanges of cultural
services among countries of the region.
The conference also proclaimed the
right of Latin American and Caribbean
states to produce their own information,
stressing the particularly critical
relationship which exists between culture
and communication in Latin America.
It favoured the harmonization of
cultural policies and communication
policies in the region on the lines of
resolutions adopted at the Costa Rica
Conference on Communication Policies
and those of the last Unesco General
Conference in Nairobi.
Unesco study
hits Namibia repression
"Africans are worse off in Namibia
than in either the Republic [of South
Africa] itself or Southern Rhodesia."
Such is Marion O'Callaghan's bleak
conclusion in a new Unesco study:
Namibia: The Effects ofApartheid on
Culture and Education. This situation
is not surprising, she writes, since
Namibia is one of the few remaining
colonies in the world and "we have here
a degree of colonial rule that has seldom
been surpassed."
"We have found racial discrimination at
every level of society," she adds, " in
land ownership, in administration and
education, in access to urbanization,
credit and technology and (although it
was not strictly within our brief) in
access to political power.
"We have found that human rights have
been infringed as regards the right to
education, the right to information, the
right to freedom of movement, the right
to culture, the right to freedom of
religion.
"However... it seemed to us that racial
discrimination and the denial of human .
rights were inadequate as concepts to
explain or analyze the situation in
Namibia... The denial of human rights
and the policy of racial discrimination,
repugnant as they both are, are not
problems. They are the inevitable result
of the social structure of Namibia, of its
history of conquest, of its present
occupation by the Republic of South
Africa, of the pattern of its economy
and of the method of capital
accumulation.
"Race is the factor used to provide the
cheap labour on which profits are built,
the justification for the allocation of
land, the ideology which consolidates
the white group, and the method by
which the State can limit its
expenditures. Tribalism is
complementary to this, as is the
deliberate construction of tribal
identities and tribal units."
The study is a companion volume to
other Unesco analyses of social structure
in the white-dominated territories of
southern Africa: Apartheid: its Effects
on Education, Science, Culture and
Information (Unesco, 2nd revised
edition, 1972); Portuguese Colonialism
in Africa: the End of an era (Unesco,
1974); and Southern Rhodesia: the
Effects of a Conquest Society on
Education, Culture and Information
(Unesco, 1977).
Mozart Concert
aids Musicians'
Fund
A record album, produced by Philips
for the benefit of the Unesco-sponsored
Musicians International Mutual Aid
Fund, sold more than 5,000 copies in
France alone in the first week of its
release.
Recorded during a gala concert
organized by the International Music
Council on 27 January in Strasbourg,
the album features soprano Jessye
Norman and pianist Alfred Brendel with
the orchestra of the Academy of St.
Martin-in-the-Fields under the direction
of Neville Marriner. The all-Mozart
programme includes concert arias, the
Idomeneo Overture, the Symphony No.
40 in G-minor and the Piano Concerto
No. 25 in C. All of the musicians
donated their services, and the concert
was broadcast by France Musique and
three German radio networks as well as
being filmed for future television
showing.
The Musicians International Mutual Aid
Fund was established by the
International Music Council and Unesco
in 1974 in order to contribute to the
quality of musical life and the well-being
of the musical profession in all cultures,
irrespective of nationality, race or creed.
It promotes young performers at the
outset of their careers, encourages
mutual appreciation of music and
musicians among different cultures and
helps to preserve authentic forms of
traditional music.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
African journalists
ask aid boost
for rural press
A seminar of African journalists has
urged Unesco to step up its assistance to
Member States for the development of
rural newspapers and rural radio
services and to make this a priority in its
communication programme.
Meeting in Libreville, Gabon, from 30
January to 2 February, the seminar
brought together directors and editors-
in-chief of newspapers and news
agencies from all parts of the continent
to discuss the theme "Unesco, the
information media and journalists in
Africa and their roles in the global
development of the continent." The
seminar was jointly organized by
Unesco and the Government of Gabon.
Pilot projects in several countries had
demonstrated the effectiveness of rural
newspapers in stimulating support for
literacy campaigns and rural
development, the journalists declared,
and assistance in this area should now
be increased. As for radio, it would
remain in most African countries and
for many years to come the chief means
of communication. Unesco was urged
to help Member States enlarge and
improve their radio services to rural
areas and to provide information
materials on rural development
problems which could be adapted to the
needs of each nation.
In other recommendations, the
journalists called on Unesco to intensify
its efforts in the training of journalists
and in mass communication research
and to diversify its production of public
information materials to make them
more suitable for different regions and
audiences. Finally they recommended
the establishment of effective unions or
associations of journalists in each
country.
'Save
the
Acropolis'
ceremony
Photo Unesco - Dominique Roger
During a recent ceremony in Paris, the
Director-General of Unesco,
Mr. Amadou Mahtar M'Bow, presented
Mr. George Plytas, the Greek Minister
of Culture, with a complete set of the
medals (gold, silver and bronze)
produced by Unesco for the benefit of
the International Campaign to Save the
Acropolis.
Spanish gains
ground as Unesco
language
This year Unesco's Statistical Yearbook
has been published for the first time in
a tri-lingual edition Spanish as well as
French and English, and beginning in
1979 all Unesco periodicals will appear
in Spanish editions as well.
Addressing a ceremony in honour of the
Thousandth Anniversary of the Spanish
language, Mrs Martha Hildebrandt,
Unesco's Assistant Director-General for
social sciences, cited this as evidence of
an increasing use of Spanish for official
purposes in Unesco. Spanish has, of
course, been a language for conferences
and other meetings since the beginning
of the Organization, she added, noting
that the Second General Conference of
Unesco was held in Mexico City in
1947. However, its use has been
intensified in recent years in conformity
with resolutions of the 18th and 19th
sessions of the General Conference.'^
The Spanish edition of the Unesco
Courier, Mrs. Hildebrandt said, has the
second highest circulation among the
magazine's 17 language editions and the
number of subscribers is growing
constantly. Furthermore Unesco
published some 47 books in Spanish last
year, not counting twelve volumes
produced by outside publishers. s \
Spanish is also one of the leading
languages for Unesco films and radio
and television programmes.
Japan gives $10
million more to
U.N. University
Japan has contributed another $10
million to the Endowment Fund of the
United Nations University which is
jointly sponsored by the United Nations
and Unesco and which became
operational in 1975. Japan pledged
$100 million to the Fund and the latest
contribution brings her total payments
to $70 million.
The Unesco Executive Board last year
called on all of the Organization's
Member States to make substantial
contributions to the U.N. University.
It has been estimated that $500 million
will be required to carry through the
planned programme of research into
such global problems as world hunger,
human and social development and
natural resources.
Of the 16 nations which have
contributed so far, Japan has made the
largest gift. Japan also supplies
facilities for the U.N.U.'s Programming
and Coordinating Centre in Tokyo.
The Endowment has also received
$4 million from Venezuela.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
World literacy:
theme of Unesco
exhibit in Montreal
The campaign for literacy in the world
will be one of the principal themes of
the Unesco pavilion at the Montreal
Man and his World exhibition this
summer.
Announcing Unesco's participation in
the exhibition, which opens on 22 June,
Montreal Mayor Jean Drapeau said that
the main aim of the annual event is to
bring people together. It is a successor
to the international exposition which
was held in Montreal in 1967, and uses
the pavilions which were constructed on
that occasion.
In addition to literacy, the Unesco
pavilion, which covers 20,000 square
feet, will feature other activities of the
Organization world-wide. One wall will
be given over to a world map illustrating
Unesco projects in various countries. A
selection of art works donated to
Unesco over the years will also be on
display. In a section devoted to the
restoration of monuments it is hoped to
include a scale model of the temple at
Borobudur, Indonesia.
Showings of some 20 Unesco films in a
wide variety of languages will be
organized, and there will also be four
different audio-visual shows with colour
slides and taped commentaries. From
time to time during the summer there
will be gala concerts performed by
musicians and performers of
international stature.
Arrangements are also being made with
the International Civil Aviation
Organization, the U.N. agency which
has its headquarters in Montreal, to
show some of its work, including an
exhibition of the history of flight over
the past 50 years.
Getting together
"East is East and West is West", wrote
Kipling, "and never the twain shall
meet."
But that was in the days before Unesco,
where not only East and- West but
North and South and every other
conceivable region meet virtually every
day and on a bewildering variety of
subjects.
A provisional calendar for 1978 lists no
fewer than 250 gatherings this year
ranging from major international
conferences and congresses through
advisory committees, meetings of
experts, seminars and symposia, to
training and refresher courses.
Furthermore this list does not include
the meetings of Unesco bodies such as
the Executive Board or the General
Conference, nor meetings organized on
behalf of Unesco by governments of
Member States, non-governmental
organizations, universities or other
outside institutions.
Participants in these affairs may number
as many as a thousand (Unesco General
Conference), or from 300 to 500
(Meeting of Government Representatives
to Prepare a Draft Declaration on Race
and Racial Prejudice or the
Intergovernmental Conference on
Strategies and Policies for Informatics)
or as few as five (Meeting of Experts bn
Application of Nuclear Techniques in
Hydrology). Many if not most of the
meetings will be held in Unesco
Headquarters in Paris, but even a
partial list of the others reads like a
travel agent's catalogue: Colombo,
Kathmandu, Santiago, Ouagadougou,
Dakar, Beirut, Bangkok, Geneva,
Amman, Turin, Penang, Bucharest,
Athens, Montreal, Mexico City,
Caracas, Rabat, Alexandria, Rio de
Janeiro, Munich, Quito, Abidjan,
Lagos, Leningrad, New York and
Vienna.
Major Unesco
meetings in 1978
13-20 March, Paris, Meeting of
Government Representatives to
Prepare a Draft Declaration on Race
and Racial Prejudice
28 March - 7 April, Nijmegen
(Netherlands)
International Conference on Integrated
Science Education
4-13 April, Lisbon, Special
Committee of Governmental Experts
to prepare a Draft Declaration and, if
possible, a Draft Convention
concerning the Prevention and
Coverage of Risks to Movable
Cultural Property
23-30 May, Paris, Interim
Intergovernmental Committee for
Physical Education and Sport
19-28 June, Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia)
Intergovernmental Conference on
Communication Policies in Asia and
Oceania
24 July - 1 Aug., Colombo (Sri Lanka)
4th Regional Conference of Ministers
of Education and those Responsible
for Economic Planning in Asia and
Oceania
28 Aug. - 6 Sept., Torremolinos
(Spain) Intergovernmental Conference
on Strategies and Policies for
Informatics
11-15 Sept., Belgrade, Conference of
Ministers responsible for Science and
Technology Policy in the European
and North American Region
12-16 Sept., Vienna, International
Congress on Teaching of Human
Rights
24 Oct. - 28 Nov., Paris, Unesco
General Conference, 20th Session
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
St. Michael
weighing the souls
This painting, a 13th-century altar panel from a Romanesque church in the Ribes
valley, Catalonia (Spain) shows the archangel Michael weighing the souls of the dead
while the devil waits expectantly to claim the damned. The work of an artist known
as the Master of Soriguerola, it is now preserved in the Episcopal Museum at Vich,
Catalonia. For Catalan Romanesque painting, seepage 18 and central colour pages.
-.
fel Hal
*
^
, .
r
\
A*'"
t»
*
\ V
M ..^'*
¿
jrt
]]>
</page>
</document>
