<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074739eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
MAY 1981 - 4.50 French francs
BULGARIA: 13 centuries of history and culture
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Dominican
Republic
Shamanistic idol
The Taino ¡ndians, a peaceful farming people whose culture flourished in
the Greater Antilles between the 10th and 15th century AD, created an art
which is today recognized as one of the richest and earliest forms of pre-
Columbian expression. This stone head (22 cm high) from Macorix, in
what is today the Dominican Republic, is a zemi, a representation of one
of the ancestral spirits or magical forces which, the Taino believed, con¬
trolled different aspects of nature. These spirits were invoked by the chief
or shaman to provide such benefits as health, rain, or fertility. Unable to
defend themselves and vulnerable to new diseases, the Taino soon
became extinct after the European conquest, but some vestiges of their
art still persist today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
I ho
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
MAY 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform ( microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A ; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc.. 111 West 40th Street.
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Frederick Potter (Paris)Edition:Braille
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
5
6
8
11
BULGARIA
A MODERN NATION SALUTES ITS PAST
by Magdalina Stancheva
I. 'It grows but does not grow old'
II. 5,000 years of town-planning
III. A tale of three cities
IV. From Saint Cyril to the National Revival
13 BUILDING THE FUTURE TODAY
14 THE BANNER OF PEACE
15 THE PLIGHT OF AFRICA'S FIVE MILLION REFUGEES
by Maxime-Leopold Zollner
19 FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
23 SCIENCE, PSEUDO-SCIENCE AND RACISM
by Albert Jacquard
28 THE DECLARATION OF ATHENS
Scientists speak out against racism
29 THE MAN WHO VANQUISHED YELLOW FEVER
by Pedro M. Pruna and Rafael O. Pedraza
31 SAINT BENEDICT OF NURSIA
A voice across the centuries
by Gregorio Penco
38 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC: Shamanistic idol
1 fjjSaV wT^flHflH^fl
» . JU» »
Cover
Two years ago a treasure including a diadem,
a necklace (see colour page 21), ear-rings,
rings and coins was found at Preslav, ancient
capital of Bulgaria. Cover shows a finely-
worked gold plaque from the diadem
representing the ascension into heaven, in a
chariot drawn by two griffins, of Alexander
the Great who, over the centuries, became
the quasi-mythical hero of all kinds of
legends and romances. This year Bulgaria is
celebrating the 1300th anniversary of its
foundation and this edition of the Unesco
Courier gives pride of place to the country's
eventful story. This year will also see the
launching, in June, of a Bulgarian edition of
the Unesco Courier, bringing the total
number of language editions to twenty-six.
Photo © Gérard Dufresne, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
BULGARIA
A MODERN NATION
SALUTES
ITS PAST
by Magdalina Stancheva
iny,i!
%
' .+«5.
: 0^
**xr
*> .
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
I. 'IT GROWS BUT DOES
NOT GROW OLD'
THE motto Inscribed in the coat of arms
of the city of Sofia, capital of
Bulgaria, "It grows but does not
grow old", seems an apt summary of the
history of a vigorous modern State which
this year celebrates the 1300th anniversary
of its foundation by khan Asparukh in the
year 681.
Between the 6th and 9th centuries of our
era, when the mix of populations brought
about by the great migrations from east to
west and north to south was reshaping
Europe (as well as Asia and North Africa),
giving it the ethnic, linguistic and cultural
features it has to this day, the fertile lands
between the Danube and the Aegean and
between the Black Sea and the Adriatic
were undergoing fundamental changes. The
former Roman provinces of Thrace and II-
lyria were breaking away from the Eastern
Roman or Byzantine empire, and thereafter
Byzantium's influence in these lands was to
be mainly cultural.
After successive waves of invasions, Slav
tribes settled in the region in increasing
numbers during the 6th and 7th centuries.
Then came warriors of Turanian origin the
Proto-Bulgarians from the plains of the
Dnieper and the Volga. Bulgaria's cha¬
racteristic personality and culture stem from
In modern Bulgaria the ancient past is
seldom more than a step away. In
Varna, formerly Odessos, a flourishing
port and holiday resort on the Black
Sea, many features of the ancient
Graeco-Roman city have been
integrated into the streets and squares
of the modern city, left. In Sofia,
above, children on their way to school
have living contact with history in this
small exhibition room arranged by the
City of Sofia History Museum in one of
the capital's pedestrian subways, which
is itself part of an old Roman road.
the fusion of these two peoples: the first
gave the country its language, the
second its name.
But though these events played a decisive
role in the history of the country and in the
development of its culture, the modern
Bulgarians do not forget their more distant
Thracian past to which they consider
themselves heirs. This past is so rich and
monuments from all periods are so
numerous more than 31,000 have been
listed and protected in the 110,911 square
kilometres of the national territory that at
the same time as the country builds for the
future it is in daily contact with the relics of
its earliest ancestors. History is part of con¬
temporary life and prehistory is more in
evidence here than in most other parts of
the world.
Cereal cultivation began in these ter¬
ritories more than eight thousand years ago
and the remains of early farming com¬
munities are numerous and conspicuous.
Mounds or tells formed by the remains of
successive building levels testify to the
lasting nature of the settlements. Most
Bulgarian towns are built on superimposed
layers of ruins and archaeological deposits.
One of the most famous of these tells,
discovered near the village of Karanovo in
the southern department of Nova Zagora,
has attracted considerable interest in scien¬
tific circles: it is twelve metres high and its
deepest layer dates from the early Neolithic
period in the sixth millennium before our
era, while the top layer belongs to the Iron
Age. An archaeological cross-section shows
that generation followed generation on this
site one above the other down the ages.
The Karanovo excavations have yielded a
rich crop of relics: tools, weapons and uten¬
sils of various kinds which today fill rooms in
several museums.
Another remarkable find is the Copper
Age or Chalcolithic necropolis of Varna on
the Black Sea coast. There archaeologists
have uncovered a series of tombs built at the
end of the fourth millennium and containing
hundreds of gold objects, from tiny beads to
bracelets weighing 200 to 300 grammes. A
particularly interesting feature is the
presence of gold sceptres in two of the
tombs. These symbols of established power
show that even in those far-off times this
corner of south-eastern Europe already had
a firmly-founded tradition of sovereignty
and a fairly complex social structure.
How this happened is still a mystery. One
possible explanation is that copper, which
was mined in the area at that time, probably
gave rise to extensive exchanges with the
countries of nearby Asia Minor. Trade,
therefore, may well have been a source of
progress and prosperity for these miners
who buried so much gold with their dead
and whom archaeologists today regard as
the ancestors of the Thracians.
The Thracians are the oldest people
whose name is known in south-eastern
Europe. Remnants of their language which
belonged to the same branch of Indo-
European as Greek and Latin are to be
found in inscriptions and the names of
towns, mountains and rivers. The Thracians
occupied an important place in the literature
of neighbouring peoples. During the
classical period, from the 6th century BC on¬
wards, the Greeks often referred to Thracian
influences on their mythology, religion and
arts, especially music. It is only recently,
however, that the general public has
become acquainted with the Thracians,
thanks to a fabulous exhibition of gold
jewels, vessels and weapons which has
toured several countries. Most of these ob¬
jects, some discovered by chance and some
during systematic excavations, were found
in the great tombs that testify to highly
developed beliefs: faith in after-life, and
perhaps the hope of union with the divine
rather than of material survival.
The dead were buried with their most
precious possessions and the funerary
chamber was covered with a mound of earth
the size of which varied according to the
rank and wealth of the deceased. Thus the
Thracian lands were dotted with tumuli,
most of which disappeared down the ages,
though more than ten thousand still remain
and are today protected against unauthoriz¬
ed excavations. They are the most
characteristic features of the landscape in
certain regions, as in the area of Plovdiv, for
example, along the international motorway
leading to Istanbul.
One of these tumuli, in the department of
Stara Zagora, contained the famous
Kazanlak tomb whose wall-paintings dating
from the 4th century before our era are of
paramount importance to the history of art.
The main mural depicts a funeral banquet
and is characterized by the extreme finesse
of the central figures, the prince and his
wife, and especially by the tenderness and
elegance of their parting gesture. No less
remarkable are the figures of the parents and
relatives of the deceased who are shown
leading horses or bearing offerings.
The Kazanlak tomb is among the
monuments of exceptional importance
which Unesco has included in its World
Heritage List (see Unesco Courier, August
1980). To avoid damage a replica of the
tomb has been built nearby for the benefit of
the thousands of tourists who visit the area
every year. For Kazanlak is in the famous
"Rose Valley" where field upon field of
flowers flourishes in an exceptionally
temperate climate, producing the attar or
essential oil used in the manufacture of
perfume.
MAG DALINA STANCH EVA, of Bulgaria, isa
leading research specialist in medieval ar¬
chaeology and head of the archaeological depart¬
ment of the Historical Museum of the City of
Sofia. She has published several scientific studies
on Sofia's archaeological problems and on
Bulgaria's medieval cultural heritage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Bulgaria
II. 5,000 YEARS
OF TOWN-PLANNING
IN coastal districts underwater research
has brought to light the remains of the
first sea-ports and relics of early naviga¬
tion on the Black Sea, including a number of
stone anchors used in the late Bronze Age
about twelve hundred years before our era.
On their outward journeys, the Thracian
ships carried cargoes of sheet copper; the
goods they brought back enabled the
coastal cities to become the country's
earliest centres of maritime .trade.
So when Greek colonists settled on the
Black Sea coast in the 6th century BC they
found a string of flourishing Thracian cities.
Before long they had imposed their own
language, built theatres and introduced their
own sculptors and potters; the towns in
which they worked long continued to bear
Greek names. The close relations the Greeks
maintained with the Thracians were not only
commercial. The two peoples exchanged
customs and divinities and shared common
festivals. Such cultural exchanges were
often repeated down the centuries and have
given Bulgaria its particular character.
But cultural interchange and the legacy of
antiquity were not limited to the coastal
cities. More than half the Bulgarian towns
are at least five thousand years old. Cities
like Sofia, Plovdiv, Varna, Nessebur and
Stara Zagora are in themselves monuments
to the history of town-planning, and in many
cases it has been possible to explore their ar¬
chaeological heritage deep down in the
earth beneath the modern cities.
In Sofia, for example, several acres of the
city centre are built over cultural layers that
are ten metres deep. This area was severely
damaged by air raids in the Second World
War and its replanning has brought to the
fore the controversial problem of preserving
archaeological remains in an urban setting.
In Bulgaria the question has been settled
once and for all. Every archaeological monu¬
ment that is brought to light is integrated in¬
to the modern environment in the most ap¬
propriate way. In Sofia, an underpass built
between the new headquarters of the State
Council and the Council of Ministers skirts
the ancient city wall before passing through
the eastern gate and following a 6th century
street with marble flagstones bearing
Roman inscriptions some four hundred
years older.
Further up the avenue, in the centre of
another underpass, one can enjoy a cup of
coffee opposite a tiny medieval church.
Elsewhere the tram-lines skirt the corner
tower of the city wall, and remains of
another tower can be seen in the basement
'of a department store. A new bank under
construction has had to relinquish half of its
basement to another section of the city wall,
part of two 4th-century streets and the foun¬
dations of a 14th-century church. Opposite
this bank, a big open space has been made
over to the archaeologists pending the time
when the architects draw up plans for
safeguarding the remains.
All these towns have found original ways
of preserving their archaeological heritage.
In Plovdiv (the Roman Trimontium) an am
phitheatre discovered in an excellent state of
preservation is to be used for dramatic per¬
formances; the ancient forum, naturally, is
reserved for pedestrians and the ramparts
circling the hills serve as supporting walls for
houses of the 19th-century districts. At
Stara Zagora (the ancient Augusta Trajana)
Neolithic dwellings have been enclosed
within the walls of a new museum; and a
section of a district, including an am¬
phitheatre, baths and ancient streets, is to
be preserved in its original state as an open-
air museum, while other parts will be
covered over or indicated by markings on
the floor in the new buildings. Varna
(Odessos) maintains "archaeological sec¬
tions" within its new districts, and many
features of the Graeco-Roman city plan are
to be integrated into the modern streets and
squares.
There is only one way Into Nessebur and
that is through the ancient gate in the ram¬
parts. This small town on the Black Sea
which still bears a Thracian name, Messem-
bria, deserves more than any other the
somewhat misused title of "living museum".
It is built on a tiny peninsula linked to the
coast by a narrow neck of land, and was one
of the main Thracian ports. A Dorian colony
was established there in the 6th century and
grew rich through maritime trade and farm¬
ing the fertile hinterland. Under, Roman
domination Nessebur remained prosperous
and subsequently became one of the Byzan¬
tine empire's chief ports.
For centuries Bulgaria and Byzantium
fought over this tiny strip of land surrounded
by sea on all sides, and every time the penin¬
sula changed hands it was endowed with
new monuments. The Italian republics,
especially Genoa, also asserted their in¬
fluence at Nessebur, even after the Ottoman
invasion. In spite of changing fortunes and
the slow decline of its trade the city main
tained its vitality with the passing centuries
and its inhabitants have kept the customs
and independent spirit of a seafaring people.
Today this ancient city in the heart of
Bulgaria's most famous resort areas draws
tens of thousands of tourists attracted by its
monuments and its picturesque site.
Among the masterpieces left here by
three thousand years of civilization, the
most impressive are the churches. The
dozen that remain represent almost every
stage of Christianity in this area, from the
oldest built in the 5th century to the most re¬
cent at the end of the last century. Most of
them, however, date from the 13th and 14th
centuries and these are also the most in¬
teresting, both for their style and for the
originality of the building techniques used in
their construction. Small blocks of tufa
alternate with rows of bricks to form an
unusual kind of decoration. Details such as
cornices, arches and niches are embellished
with inlaid ceramic circles and four-leaved
clover, so that the façades of the buildings
shine in the sun like so many pieces of
multicoloured embroidery. These vivid
patches of colour contrast with the
plain façades of the houses, whose wooden
facing is weathered by sun and salt.
In Nessebur as elsewhere in Bulgaria,
modern life goes hand in hand both with dis¬
tant antiquity and with the Middle Ages.
Workmen digging the foundations of a
youth centre some years ago discovered the
altar of a church which has long since disap¬
peared. It has been carefully preserved and
incorporated into the new building where it
is protected by a cement column and can be
seen through a glass panel. In summer
tourists attend concerts organized in the
great 6th-century basilica. But the most
persevering visitors are the archaeologists,
historians and restorers whose patient work
continues season after season.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Cities that span
the centuries
Washed over by successive tides of
history, the towns and cities of Bulgaria,
more than half of which are over 5,000
years old, constitute veritable chronicles in
stone. At Plovdiv, for example, the visitor
comes face to face with past Roman
glories, such as the fine amphitheatre and
the ancient stadium (right), as well as the
cobbled streets and 18th-century, timber-
framed houses of the National Revival
period (centre right) all carefully preserved
and displayed within the confines of a
bustling, modern city. Thracians, Greeks,
Romans, Byzantium, the Genoese all left
their mark on the Black Sea port of
Nessebur. Its churches, the earliest dating
from the 5th century, are representative of
almost every stage in the history of
Christianity in this region. Among the most
outstanding examples are the great 6th-
century Basilica and the remarkable 13th
and 14th-century churches built of brick
and tufa, their arches and cornices
decorated with inlaid ceramics (photo
opposite page).
Many Bulgarian towns and villages have
been protected and restored as part of a
nation-wide campaign to safeguard the
country's cultural heritage. One such town
is Koprivchtitza (right). Famed as the scene
of the start of the ill-fated insurrection of
April 1876 against the Ottoman Turks, it is
noted for its well-preserved 19th-century
houses with their richly ornamented fronts
and sculpted wood ceilings. The museum-
village of Etara (above), near Gabrovo, a
town renowned as Bulgaria's "capital of
humour", is now a centre for traditional
crafts where potters, leatherworkers and
wheelwrights can be seen at work in
carefully restored workshops.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Bulgaria
III. A TALE OF THREE CITIES
IN the history of Bulgaria three names of
towns have a special significance
because of their national and cultural
associations. They are those of the capitals
which the Bulgarian princes established dur¬
ing the Middle Ages: first Pliska, metropolis
of the first Bulgarian State from its founda¬
tion in 681, through the periods of its con¬
solidation, its conversion to Christianity and
the introduction of the Cyrillic alphabet.
Then comes Preslav which was the
country's capital during the "Golden Age"
of Bulgarian culture when the arts and let¬
ters flourished at the court of king Simeon.
Finally, Turnovo was the centre of Bulgarian
civilization in the 13th and 14th centuries up
to the time of the Ottoman invasion and
conquest.
Each city still seems imbued with the spirit
of the age in which it flourished. Pliska, con¬
ceived like a huge fortified camp with the
palace of the khan and the temple of his god
in the centre, is massive, austere and ma
jestic. The huge limestone blocks of its sur¬
rounding walls and palaces recall the power
and might of its founding princes. Their
determination to live and last is expressed in
the remains of the fortress and the palace,
and in the inscriptions engraved on columns
by order of the khans. That memory must
conquer death was the message left by khan
Omurtag (814-831): "Man, even if he lives
well, dies, and another sees the light. Let
him who has been born later remember...".
Very different is Preslav, built by young
king Simeon (893-927) among the softly
rounded hills bordering on the Ticha river.
Preslav was also an imposing city, but here,
instead of uncovering fortresses, ar¬
chaeologists are intent on bringing to light a
town of builders, stone-carvers and
sculptors, painters, potters, goldsmiths and
writers, for discoveries have shown that
these artists and craftsmen were extra¬
ordinarily creative and original. It has been
established, for example, that a kind of
Above, ruins of the 9th-century palace of the khan
at Pliska, the first capital of the Bulgarian State.
Founded in 681 by khan Asparukh, Pliska remained
the capital for a little over two centuries and
towards the end of this period two major events
occurred which were to have a profound influence
on the country's future its conversion to
Christianity and the introduction of the Cyrillic
alphabet. Left, ornamental key representing a lute
player and made at Pliska in the 9th or 10th
century. The key doubled as an implement of
some sort but the precise use of the.spike
emerging from the musician's hat is not known.
faience used chiefly in mural decoration but
also for making dishes was probably
manufactured for the first time in Europe at
Preslav in the 10th century. The painters
even made ikons in ceramic, and faience
served as a medium for writing. An earthen¬
ware spindle-whorl decorated with enamel
has been discovered, on which the crafts¬
man or donor has inscribed the name of the
young spinster for whom it was intended.
"Lola's spindle-whorl" indicates the ex¬
tent to which literacy was then developed in
Bulgaria. Preslav is famous in the history of
Slav culture for its literary school,
represented by a constellation of writers
such as Chernorizetz Khrabar, John the Ex¬
arch, Constantine of Preslav and king Si¬
meon himself, who is said to have filled his
palace with books. Most of the books com¬
piled or written in Preslav during this period
were religious works, in particular sermons
and commentaries on the Bible. But they
also contain interesting discourses on lay
subjects and sometimes inspired texts like
Constantine's "alphabetic prayer" extolling
the historical importance of the Bulgarians'
conversion to Christianity.
During the 12th century, after several
decades of Byzantine domination, Turnovo
became the capital of the Second Bulgarian
Kingdom, and so it remained until 1393,
when the city was burnt to the ground after
the Ottoman conquest. In a fantastic site of
steep hills separated by the deep gorges of
the Yantra river, a great city was built in a
highly complex style which was hierarchical
even in its architecture.
Religious and political conflicts were fre¬
quent at that time. But enlightened rulers
protected the arts and encouraged the
development of literature. Among the rare
manuscripts from Turnovo which have
escaped destruction is the Chronicle of Con¬
stantine Manassès now in the Vatican,
which contains 69 magnificent miniatures
including 21 on Bulgarian subjects. Other
masterpieces of illustrative painting are to be
found in a few 14th-century manu¬
scripts famous Tetraevangelicum of
king Ivan-Alexander now in the British
Museum, and the Moscow Psalter.
But hardly any examples of monumental
painting are still extant in Turnovo. For¬
tunately the frescoes of the little church of
Boyana (1259), near Sofia, said to be works
of the Turnovo school, are there to
demonstrate the splendour and refinement
of the art of the time. The unknown artist
who painted portraits full of charm and
dignity of the donors of Boyana, prince
Kaloyan and his wife Dessislava, showed by
the life he injected into the traditional im¬
ages of saints a dramatic sense and a
humanism unsurpassed in 13th century
Europe.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Above, ruins of Preslav, the city that became Bulgaria's second capital during the
reign of king Simeon (893-927) and which witnessed the "Golden Age" of medieval
Bulgarian culture. In 971 Preslav was captured and sacked by the Byzantine Emperor
John Tzimisces and Bulgaria languished for several decades under Byzantine
domination. Below, the ramparts of Turnovo, which at the end of the 12th century
became Bulgaria's third capital, a position it held until 1393 when it was destroyed
following the Ottoman conquest. The art of the illuminated book reached its apogee at
Turnovo during the reign of king Ivan Alexander (1331-1371). The king himself is
depicted with his family in this illumination, bottom right, from the magnificent
London Ivan Alexander Gospel which the king himself ordered in 1356.
Gold coin dating from the reign
of Tsar Ivan Asen II (1218-1241).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A national festival of culture
In the second half of the 9th century, Cyril and his brother Methodius
created an alphabet for translating the liturgical texts into Slavonic,
thus bringing learning "to all men through the medium of their native
tongue". For Bulgarians, this achievement by the "apostles of the
Slavs", as Cyril and Methodius are often called, became a symbol of
their cultural identity which wa,s preserved during five centuries of
foreign oppression and domination. The two saints are com¬
memorated each year on 24 May, the day of Bulgaria's national
festival of culture. This annual "festival of the alphabet and culture"
is an occasion for art exhibitions, musical performances, book fairs,
the presentation of literary and scientific prizes, and cultural events
organized by students. Past and present also meet in the ornamental
ceramic tiles which began to be manufactured in Bulgaria around the
time when the Cyrillic alphabet was being adopted in the Slav coun¬
tries. These tiles, so lavishly covered with inscriptions as to be virtual
books, were used to adorn the floors and walls of monasteries and
palaces which were thus transformed into "public libraries" the
ancestors of the book centres and libraries of modern Bulgaria.
CkNfcC
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Bulgaria
IV. FROM SAINT CYRIL
TO THE NATIONAL REVIVAL
IN Bulgaria the monastic tradition is as old
as the nation itself. The first monastery
was founded at Pliska by Boris I
(852-889), who retired there at the end of his
life. The disciples of Cyril and Methodius
came to work in this monastery, teaching
and spreading the Slav alphabet invented by
their masters.
Thus the monasteries early became
cultural centres, a tradition which continued
at Preslav and became widespread under Ot¬
toman domination when every monastery
became a centre and refuge for the national
spirit. On the feast days of the great
monasteries pilgrims came from far and
wide travelling across the country on foot or
horseback or by cart. The inhabitants of
towns and villages sent offerings of all kinds
to contribute to the decoration of the
building.
This is still the case at Rila monastery
where the monks celebrate divine service in
the church and chapels maintaining the
tradition of Bulgarian religious chant. This
monastery built in the mountains to the
south of Sofia is also a national museum
with exhibition rooms devoted to a variety
of subjects: history, economic activity,
ethnography and ikon collections.
Seen from the outside, the monastery is
like a powerful fortress. Inside, the huge
courtyard is bordered by façades rising up
for several storeys and ringed with carved
wooden balconies. In the centre stand a big
church and a tower dating from the 14th
century. On the floors above are small
chapels, set between the visitors' dor¬
mitories and the monks' cells, where mass is
celebrated on certain feast days.
After Rila, the most important monastery
is Bachkovo, which was founded in 1083 in
a valley of the Rhodope mountains by a
Opposite page
St. Cyril and St. Methodius as depicted in
a painting by Zahari Zograph, a celebrated
19th-century Bulgarian painter.
May 24 celebrations in Sofia.
The "palace of books" in the town of
Plevene. The mural symbolizes the history
of Bulgarian literature from Cyril and
Methodius until modern times.
Detail of a 10th-century ceramic tablet
(6x6 cm) inscribed with Cyrillic letters. It
is thought to be from Preslav.
high-ranking Georgian officer, Grigori
Bakuriani, who was governor of the area
during the period of Byzantine domination.
The monastery at Bachkovo has had an
eventful history. On several occasions it has
been destroyed, rebuilt, restored and
enlarged.
During one of these alterations, in the
17th century, an unusual masterpiece was
added to Bachkovo. The mural paintings
that decorate the walls and vault of the
refectory form an overall composition in
which Biblical scenes framed by garlands of
foliage stand out against a starlit sky
together with some of the great figures of
Antiquity. Socrates, Plato and Aristotle, for
example, are represented in medieval dress,
which in no way detracts from the solemnity
of their bearing and the nobility of their ex¬
pression.
In the centre of this magnificent hall
stands a long narrow marble table around
which the monks used to gather. The ar¬
chitect's remarkable use of space combines
with the power of the painter's brush to
achieve a remarkably persuasive effect:
under a vault studded with golden stars,
surrounded by the philosophers of antiqui¬
ty, the human spirit seems to soar above
terrestrial life.
Outside in the monastery courtyard one
of the walls is decorated with a much more
recent composition recalling the
monastery's main feast which is celebrated
in August on the name-day of the Virgin
Mary. It is a narrative scene that contains a
wealth of information: the monastery is
depicted surrounded by the foothills of the
mountain. On the hilltops all around are little
churches and chapels dedicated to various
saints. A solemn procession is advancing
through the main entrance headed by pro¬
minent citizens bearing the miraculous ikon
of the Virgin. The procession goes round
each church in turn. After the priests, led by
the bishop of Plovdiv, come the monks and,
finally, the laity, townsfolk and peasants.
The artist has depicted the geographical
details of the site with meticulous accuracy:
the river, the bridges and the path on which
laggards are still lingering. The ethno¬
graphical detail and social characteristics of
the figures, many of which are undoubt¬
edly portraits of real people, are typical of
the art of Zahari Zograph, self-taught author
of this composition and one of the most
gifted painters of the mid-19th century.
Zahari Zograph also decorated the two
monastery churches. All his compositions
show a concern for social criticism. Thus, in
the scene of the Last Judgement, he
painted the portraits of Plovdiv
moneylenders and their haughty wives
bound for the ovens of hell.
However, the art of the painters of this
period is rarely limited to social themes. The
artists delighted in covering the walls of
monasteries and churches with roses and
leafy branches. Their saints are clad in
bright colours and their open faces are lit
with a vitality and cheerful optimism
characteristic of the period which has been
called that of Bulgaria's National Revival.
After the Ottoman invasion at the end of
the 14th century the Bulgarians lost their in¬
dependence and, for more than five hun¬
dred years, experienced ordeals which few
peoples have had to endure. But they
preserved their national consciousness,
traditions, faith and life-styles and were to
show a fierce determination in the liberation
struggle of the 19th century.
But before the successful outcome of the
Russo-Turkish war of 1877-1878 which
brought about their liberation, the
Bulgarians were to live through a very dif¬
ficult period, particularly after the April 1876
uprising. The uprising failed despite the
heroism of the freedom fighters and the
revolt was crushed. The wave of indignation
and sympathy which this cruel repression
caused throughout Europe certainly hasten¬
ed the advent of freedom. But the founda¬
tions of Bulgaria's liberation had been laid
long before by the leaders of the Revival
movement, and the country's aspiration to
freedom was foreshadowed by the architec¬
ture of the same period.
For centuries the Bulgarians had only
been allowed to build humble churches, as
low and as dark as possible. But in the se¬
cond half of the 18th century, as the power
of the Ottoman empire gradually weakened,
spacious, well-lit churches began to be con¬
structed with beautiful decorated façades
and magnificently carved iconostases inside.
The figures of Adam and Eve are often
represented on these big wooden screens
surrounded by birds and acanthus leaves.
Clad in Bulgarian peasant costume, Adam is
tilling the land, while Eve is busy spinning.
And naturally, among the images of the
saints, Cyril and Methodius, inventors of the
Slavonic alphabet, take pride of place.
After the liberation of Bulgaria, for various
social, economic and political reasons, the
towns developed very slowly and without
major upheavals. This stability has made it
possible to preserve the architecture of the
Revival period which, today, is the object of
great attention. In Plovdiv, for example, one
of the hills on which this picturesque city is
built has kept whole districts of Revival
period architecture. Corbelled houses with
ingeniously articulated façades seem to vie
in exhibiting their brilliant colours, but the
general effect is one of harmony and propor¬
tion. The graceful lines, the many windows,
the arches over the doorways, the skilful
combination of wood and metal and the
flowers decorating every window-sill all
express the spirit of hope characteristic of
Bulgaria when they were built.
These ancient streets and dwellings are as
busy and as lively today as the new building
sites, towns and villages in other parts of the
country. The historic legacy is so full of
vitality and enterprise that it can easily be in¬
corporated into the most modern aspects of
the country's culture. The youthful spirit of
modern Bulgaria can draw upon knowledge
and respect for the past.
I Magdalina Stancheva
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
From the earliest days of the
Bulgarian State onwards, and
especially during the period of
Ottoman domination, the
monasteries of Bulgaria have at
times provided a refuge where
the national spirit could survive
by keeping its forms of cultural
expression alive. The monks
taught in the Bulgarian
language, translated Greek and
Oriental philosophers, and laid
the foundations of a national
literature. It was in the
monasteries, too, that the
heyday of Bulgarian
monumental painting began in
the 15th century. The frescoes
on the walls and vaulting of the
refectory in the monastery of
Bachkovo are an outstanding
example of this religious art.
Their wide range of themes
includes scenes from the Old
and New Testaments, portraits
of monotheist philosophers of
Antiquity, and pictures showing
councils of the church (a rare
subject in Bulgarian religious
painting). Left, parts of The Rod
of Jesse, painted on the
vaulting, and of The Last
Judgement, on the east wall of
the refectory at Bachkovo.
Above, detail of a fresco in St.
George's church, Sofia (10th or
11th century).
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
BUILDING THE FUTURE TODAY
In the classrooms and lecture halls of univer¬
sities and technical institutes throughout
Bulgaria today, young people, like these
students at the Institute of Electro-
Mechanics, Sofia (above), are preparing
themselves to guide their country into the
21st century. Transformed over the past
three and a half decades into a modern
industrial-agrarian nation, Bulgaria entered
the space age on 10 April 1979 when
cosmonaut Gueorgui Ivanov (below) step¬
ped aboard the spacecraft Soyuz 33 and,
with his Soviet partner Nikolai
Roukovischnikov flew off on a mission plan
ned within the framework of the Inter-
cosmos Space Programme. With a territory
of 110,911 square kilometres, Bulgaria ranks
in size among the smaller European nations,
yet its scientists and research workers have
at their disposal the latest scientific equip¬
ment, including this experimental nuclear
reactor (above right) at the Institute of
Nuclear Research, Sofia. The late Bulgarian
statesman George Dimitrov once said that
in the field of culture there are neither small
nor great nations, and the dynamism of
Bulgaria is firmly rooted in a cultural
heritage spanning 13 centuries.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The banner of peace
The children's "sun" bell
Just south of Sofia, Bulgaria's capital, rises
an imposing concrete edifice hung with
bells. Its name, the "Banner of Peace"
monument, commemorates an international
gathering with a difference an assembly at
which the youngsters of Bulgaria were hosts
to 1,300 children from 76 countries. The aim
of the meeting, one of the most memorable
events marking International Year of the
Child in 1979, was to bring together budding
writers, musicians and painters from all over
the world (below) under the flag of peace
and friendship between peoples. Patrons of
the Assembly, during which the youthful
delegates drew up an appeal for world peace
which was later presented to the Secretary-
General of the United Nations, were the
Chairman of the State Council of the
People's Republic of Bulgaria, Mr. Todor
Zhivkov, and the Director-General of
Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow. One
of the highlights of the assembly was the
inauguration of the Banner of Peace Monu¬
ment, which consists of a central tower sur¬
rounded by two semi-circular walls. At the
top of the 37-metre-high tower hang seven
bells representing the world continents
(below right). Hanging from stanchions in
the walls below are bells sent from many
countries, each accompanied by an appeal
for peace on earth. A symbolic "sun" bell
dedicated to the children's assembly is also
Bulgaria
Turkey
Japan
O Ghana
Switzerland
Indonesia
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
incorporated in the monument. The bells
vary widely in shape and size (see photos);
that of Bulgaria weighs 1,300 kilos, the num¬
ber of kilos corresponding to the age of the
Bulgarian State. Bottom right, commemora¬
tive plaque "To the children of the world"
was offered by Unesco to the Banner of
Peace monument. Another international
gathering of children, "Sofia 81", is schedu¬
led to take place this August, the second
anniversary of the Banner of Peace
Assembly. Its programme will be a prelude
to the Second International Assembly of
Children under the banner of peace, which
will take place in Sofia in 1982.
The
plight
of
Africa's
five million
refugees
THERE are currently some ten million
refugees in the world, the casualties
of wars and various forms of oppres¬
sion and persecution.
In the aftermath of the Second World
War, it was Europe which faced a massive
refugee problem, setting up transit camps to
house the hundreds of thousands of
uprooted and displaced persons who had
survived the holocaust. There were still
many European refugees in 1951, when the
United Nations established the Office of the
High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR),
with headquarters in Geneva. This year, the
thirtieth anniversary of UNHCR's creation
provides an unwelcome reminder that its
work is still as necessary as ever, for year in
year out events continue to swell the ranks
of the world's refugee multitude.
by Maxime-Leopold Zollner
'
AUX ENFÂÎ
. VE SCO
/
I
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Today the problem has moved away from
Europe and, as United Nations Secretary-
General Kurt Waldheim has urged, world
attention is being focussed on the plight of
refugees in Africa. What is more, the num¬
ber of Africa's uprooted has soared alarm¬
ingly in the last few years: in 1975 there were
a million; in 1977, 3,700,000. Last year the
figure reached a staggering five million.
In response to this crisis, the General
Assembly of the United Nations last Novem¬
ber called for an international conference to
be held in order to mobilize the community
of nations and to appeal for aid, and on 9
and 10 April, the "International Conference
on Assistance to Refugees in Africa", was
held in Geneva. Invited to it were Member
States of the Organization of African Unity
(OAU) and of the United Nations, as well as
national liberation movements recognized
by the two organizations. The main objec¬
tive of the Conference was to obtain additio¬
nal resources for programmes to aid those in
the greatest need and, perhaps even more
important, to provide assistance for the Afri¬
can host countries which would enable
them to shoulder the heavy burden which
the massive influx of refugees imposes on
their personnel and their economies.
International action in this field is not
new. UNHCR has a long record of efforts to
improve the conditions of African refugees,
and their plight is clearly a matter of the
highest priority for the Organization of Afri¬
can Unity. The Conference on the Legal,
Economic and Social Aspects of African
Refugee Problems, held at Addis Ababa in
1967, was one milestone in the co-operation
between the two institutions. This Confe¬
rence, the first occasion on which matters
exclusively concerning refugees in Africa
were considered in an international forum,
adopted a series of recommendations aimed
at alleviating the burden of asylum coun¬
tries. Another result of the Conference was
the OAU's creation of the Addis Ababa-
based Bureau for the Placement and Educa¬
tion of African Refugees, and the adoption
of the OAU Convention governing the Spe¬
cific Aspects of Refugee Problems in Africa.
The Convention incorporated the defini¬
tion of a refugee which has been adopted by
most governments, in line with the formula
established by the United Nations, as any
person who, "owing to well-founded fear of
being persecuted for reasons of race, reli¬
gion, nationality, membership of a particular
social group or political opinion, is outside
the country of his nationality..." But the
Convention goes further than this, in stating
that the word refugee also applies to "every
person who, owing to external aggression,
occupation, foreign domination or events
seriously disturbing public order in either
part or the whole of his country of origin or
nationality, is compelled to leave his place of
residence in order to seek refuge in another
place outside his country of origin or natio¬
nality". The African States, in line with
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
This sea of improvised tents stretching far into the distance is an
emergency refugee camp somewhere in Africa. Half the world's
refugees are today in Africa, and their total number exceeds the
population of many African countries. The Office of the United
Nations High Commissioner for Refugees is collaborating with
the Organization of African Unity and voluntary relief agencies
on a massive effort to help some of the world's poorest countries
provide food, shelter and medical aid for these millions of
refugees and displaced persons. Below, women and children wait
for food to be distributed at a refugee camp.
these provisions, had also recognized that
the granting of asylum to refugees is a
peaceful and humanitarian act and not an
unfriendly act committed by the country of
asylum against the country of origin.
Unfortunately, these texts, despite their
generosity and the efforts they encouraged,
proved inadequate to solve the refugee
problem at a time when there was an inten¬
sification of liberation struggles, especially
in southern Africa, internal conflicts, and
inter-territorial disputes. A single figure
highlights the dimensions of the problem: in
the mid-1970s about 2,000 Africans became
refugees or displaced persons each day.
This was well over twice the world average
of 800 new refugees per day.
Consequently, another conference was
held at Arusha (Tanzania) in 1979 in order to
define a strategy for the repatriation of
refugees to their countries of origin or for
their integration into the economic struc¬
tures of the host countries. The Arusha con
ference, organized by the OAU, the United
Nations Economic Commission for Africa
and the UNHCR, also reaffirmed the prin¬
ciples of solidarity and "burden-sharing",
and outlined a list of existing and forseeable
needs. These needs have been identified
and costed for each country by UNHCR.
African governments have shown extraor¬
dinary hospitality by accepting refugees by
hundreds of thousands. They have set an
example by scrupulously respecting the
principles of the right of asylum and the
non-refoulement of refugees. But it must
not be forgotten that these countries some
of them among the world's poorest are
facing very serious economic difficulties.
Not only are they hardest hit by international
market forces and mounting energy costs,
they are also a prey to natural catastrophes.
Somalia, for instance, is a country virtually
without resources, but in addition to its own
population of 3,600,000 it now has over a
million and a half refugees.
Ensuring the survival of the neediest
refugees in the poorest countries is the
prime target of the aid programmes for
which UNHCR is responsible and which it is
carrying out in co-operation with the World
Food Programme, the World Health
Organization, UNICEF, and other govern¬
mental and non-governmental voluntary
agencies, whose work is absolutely in¬
dispensable. But existing resources are
barely sufficient to prevent men, women
and above all children from dying of hunger
in their hundreds of thousands.
Providing for the future needs and lives of
the refugees, and bringing them into the
African economy, are scarcely less urgent
problems which may turn out to be more
lasting and more costly. Whether they stay
in asylum countries or whether after a few
years they wish and are able to return to
their own lands, displaced populations do
not ask to be helped indefinitely. On the
contrary, they want to work. But before
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A group of refugee children learn to read in a ruined classroom.
^ can play a full part in economic and
social life, the State which has accepted
them must provide them with land, tools,
seeds and fertilizer, create workshops, dig
wells, build villages, roads, bridges,
hospitals and schools. The cost of in¬
frastructures, materials, equipment and per¬
sonnel required by undertakinps of this kind
is beyond the capacities of the host coun¬
tries. If the remarkably limited welcome
which most rich countries accord to
refugees is anything to go by, it would seem
that these countries consider the cost of
such measures to be extremely high. And
yet no people would refuse to join in a
genuine collective effort.
It is to this spirit of international solidarity
that the United Nations' appeal has been ad¬
dressed. UNHCR announced to the ninety-
nine governments represented at the
Geneva Conference, which was chaired by
Mr. Waldheim, that the urgent measures
which need to be taken in the next eighteen
months will cost $450 million. In other cir¬
cumstances, such a figure might have
alarmed donor countries who are often at
the receiving end of requests for aid. On the
second day of the Geneva conference,
however, the participants pledged to pro¬
vide $560 million, perhaps more than had
been hoped for. Then, on the evening of
10 April, the Assistant Secretary-General of
the Organization of African Unity announc¬
ed that other promises, which it had been
impossible to make formally, had boosted
the sum by at least $100 million.
18
Thus the appeal has not fallen on deaf
ears. It would be hard to find a better note
on which to conclude than these words by
Mr. Poul Hartling, United Nations High
Commissioner for Refugees: "The suffering
of the refugees has been understood; inter¬
national solidarity exists".
I Maxime-Leopold Zollner
MAXIME-LEOPOLD ZOLLNER, of Benin, is
director of the Assistance Programmes Division
of the Office of the United Nations High Commis¬
sioner for Refugees, in Geneva. A former Vice-
President of the Economic and Social Council of
the United Nations and Secretary-General of the
Union Africaine et Malgache, he has served as his
country's ambassador to the United States and
Canada and as permanent delegate to the United
Nations in New York.
Colour pages
Opposite page
The mountain fastnesses of Bulgaria are dot¬
ted with medieval monasteries which con¬
tain a wealth of frescoes, painted icons and
wooden reliefs. Above this shady portal in
the monastery of Rozhen, near Melnik in
southwestern Bulgaria, is a majestic pain¬
ting of Christ Pantokrator (the all-powerful
lord of the universe) seated on his heavenly
throne. Around Him are twelve medallions
with images of the Apostles, above which is
a waist-length image of Christ. The monas-
terty dates back to the 12th or 13th century,
and the painting bears the date 1597.
Centre pages
Left, bone figurine (12 cm high) unearthed in
the Chalcolithic necropolis at Varna in Bul¬
garia. It dates from the 4th millennium of the
pre-Christian era and is thought to represent
a helmeted warrior. The discovery of the
Varna necropolis was one of the great
archaeological finds of the century. Its
tombs were filled with thousands of objects,
many of gold, as well as fragments of pain¬
ted pottery and other artefacts.
Right, miniature praying Virgin adorns the
gold and enamel central medallion of a 9th-
10th century necklace unearthed two years
ago at Preslav, the ancient capital of Bulga¬
ria. It formed part of a treasure which inclu¬
ded a diadem, ear-rings, rings and coins. The
Virgin's pink and white face is that of a
young woman; the features are expressive
and not conventionalized in the usual man¬
ner of ikon Virgins. The portrait is surroun¬
ded by fine pearls and rock crystal.
Photos © Gérard Dufresne, Pans
Colour page 22
St. Benedict gives the Rule to his
monks. Detail from a series of frescoes
painted by the Italian artist Sodoma in
the monastery of Monte Oliveto
Maggiore near Siena (Italy) between
1505, and 1508 (see also page 34).
Photo © Scala, Florence
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
"V.
w*
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
i i
< r
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
.¿L
>
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Organized by Unesco at the invitation of the Foundation for
Human Rights ofAthens, a symposium devoted to a critical
review of the pseudo-scientific theories invoked to justify
racism and racial discrimination was held in the Greek
capital from 30 March to 3 April 1981.
Since those who attempt to impose the notion that some
kind of "natural hierarchy" exists between different
populations or between different individuals often invoke
science in support of their theories, it was necessary for
Unesco to clarify the situation by making the true stand¬
point of scientists widely known. Twenty-three
distinguished personalities from eighteen countries,
representing the various disciplines involved geneticists,
biologists, anthropologists, sociologists, psychologists,
historians, etc.spent a week analysing the most up-to-
date findings of science and drawing from them the
arguments with which to counter the affirmations of the
neo-racists.
The collective statement of their conclusions drawn up by
the scientists gathered at Athens and addressed to all the
peoples of the world is published on page 28 of this issue of
the Unesco Courier. The article below, by French geneticist
Albert Jacquard, rapporteur at the Athens symposium,
highlights the main themes of the debate.
Science,
pseudo-science and racism
by Albert Jacquard
MAN'S spontaneous and apparently
natural reaction to a setback is to
find the culprit, who necessarily
has to be someone else, or "other" people.
In a similar situation a group will react by at¬
tributing its misfortunes to some other
group or, preferably, to a sub-group of its
own kind."
These instinctive, infantile, cowardly reac¬
tions bear no relation to a reasoned analysis
of events in the real world and their causes,
but they seem to be so widespread and so
persistent that there are few grounds to
hope that they can be made to disappear. If,
in spite of everything, we must keep this
hope alive, we can only to do so through
"science", a somewhat solemn name for the
efforts of the human mind to understand the
real world.
Strangely, it is in the name of science that
overtly racist attitudes are beginning to re-
emerge in certain Western societies. People
refer to "recent biological discoveries" or to
"the latest genetic research" as justification
for their attempts to classify men in certain
categories or "races", and above all to com¬
pare these races according to various criteria
and to rank them in hierarchies.
However, what scientists are actually say¬
ing, especially those working in genetics,
the discipline most directly concerned, runs
counter to any such claim. Any attempt to
make biology serve as a basis for elitist
theories is rooted in a fundamental
misconception, whether the "elite" consists
of certain individuals within each group, or
of certain groups in themselves.
It is essential, therefore, that scientists
should in the present circumstances speak
out, for it is their duty to describe clearly and
ALBERT JACQUARD, French geneticist,
teaches at the universities of Paris VI and Geneva,
and is head of the genetics department of
France's National Institute of Demographic
Studies (INED) in Paris. Among his published
works are Genetics of Human Populations,
Freeman Cooper and Co., San Francisco, 1978.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Arabic word for dice, az-zahr, gave its name to a once-popular
game called Hazard. As its name implies. Hazard is a game of
chance, like all dice-games, since it is impossible to know exactly
how the dice will fall. Or is it? If only we knew much more about the
phenomena involved in throwing a dice then perhaps if would be
possible to predict the result of each throw, thus removing the ele¬
ment of chance from the game. This may seem a far-fetched idea but
it serves to highlight the infinitely more complex processes involved
when we "dice with life". According to Albert Jacquard the number
of potential variations involved in the transmission of genes by
parents to their children is so immense that we may never know
enough to exclude the element of chance from our understanding of
the process, and must predict its outcome on the basis of probability.
Drawing from Le Second Souffle de la Créativité. Marthe Seguin/ Fontes. © Dessain and Tolra publishers. Pans
^ publicize the discoveries made in their
disciplines. Reasoned arguments, unswayed
by sentiment, are needed to combat the dif¬
ferent forms of racism. For this, clarity is
vitally important, so we must carefully
define the terms we use.
To be "racist" is to despise someone else
simply because he belongs to a group. This
group may be defined by many different
criteria: colour of skin, language, religion,
genetic inheritance or cultural heritage. And
so it is more realistic to talk of racisms rather
than racism. The first requisite of each form
of racism is a definition, firstly of how to
classify people into relatively homogeneous
and distinct categories, and secondly, of
how to establish a scale of values applicable
24
to these categories. In other words, the dif¬
ferent "races" must first be defined, and
then ranked in a hierarchy.
In the case of a species which has
gradually become differentiated into
definitively and strictly separate populations
as a result of a series of separations, the gap
between the genetic or cultural structures of
two populations widens as they move fur¬
ther in time from the initial split. It is thus
possible to attempt to reconstitute the
genealogy of these successive separations,
taking as a starting point the structures
which can be observed today.
On the other hand, when the history of a
species does not take the form of a tree
which has become progressively differen¬
tiated, resembling instead a network of
amalgamations and exchanges between
distinct populations (i.e. migrations), this at¬
tempted reconstitution is doomed to failure,
save in exceptional cases. Our knowledge of
the present state of the groups does not
allow the steps which have led to this state
to be retraced. In the case of the human
species, which is remarkable for its
nomadism, this difficulty is particularly
great.
To be sure, geographical distance has
prevented exchanges between populations
living on opposite sides of the globe; migra- .
tions have come up against sometimes in¬
superable natural obstacles; cultural dif-
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
ferences have raised barriers and isolated
certain groups genetically. But the history of
human populations is so intertwined that
none can be described without reference to
its exchanges with many others. Little by lit¬
tle, each has come to be related to the
others. At the same time, natural processes
(the foremost being that of sexual reproduc¬
tion) have given. rise to and sustained a
remarkable degree of diversity within each
population.
Mankind is an aggregate of persons,
families, ethnic groups, and nations, all of
them different. But these differences can
only be classified at the cost of an arbitrary
impoverishment of our view of individuals
and groups. The most rigorous form of
classification concerns genetic inheritances:
the degree of frequency with which various
genes occur in each of two populations be¬
ing seen as a token of the degree of
dissimilarity between these populations.
If confined to a small number of genes,
the attempt at classification will soon pro¬
duce results, but they will vary from one
group of genes to another. If, for example,
we take the genes responsible for the syn¬
thesis of melanin, a pigment which ac¬
cumulates in the skin and gives it a dark col¬
ouring, we find that, where these genes are
concerned, blacks differ very greatly from
yellow or white people.
As for the genes responsible for the activi¬
ty of lactase, the enzyme which makes it
possible to digest milk, they are very fre¬
quent among North European populations,
slightly less so in the Mediterranean region,
but very rare in Asia and Africa. The
classification of people into two groups,
based on the frequency of these genes,
would set the Europeans apart from people
from the other continents.
In the case of two biological charac¬
teristics whose genetic mechanism is well
known, the Rhesus blood system and the
HL-A immunological system, both result in a
classification of people into two groups,
with Asiatics and Eskimos on one side, and
Indo-Europeans and Black Africans on the
other.
Depending upon the criteria selected
skin colour, persistence of lactase, or im¬
munological "systems" our view of the
relations between the three major human
groups classically referred to alters com¬
pletely: it may arbitrarily be claimed that the
populations of Europe resemble those of
Africa more closely than those of Asia, or
the reverse.
This is because the history of humanity
cannot be expressed in the form of a pro¬
gressively ramified tree. Instead, it consists
in a network of exchanges, mergers and
separations. It is therefore a mistake to try to
devise a classification that can have no
global validity.
The impossibility of devising such a
classification is confirmed by research which
is not based on some arbitrarily selected
characteristics, but on a synthesis of infor¬
mation concerning all the different
characteristics studied.
Where many sets of genes are involved, it
is possible to express the various
resemblances and differences between the
genetic structures of two populations in
terms of "distance". The definition of race
here means attributing populations with
small distances between them to the same
group, and populations separated by a large
tmj
Biologists investigating the way in which characteristics are
transmitted from parents to children make a fundamental distinction
between what they call the genotype (the total of the genes that an
individual inherits from its parents) and the phenotype (what an in¬
dividual is: its appearance, bodily structures, etc.) Whatever happens
to an individual, its genotype does not change, whereas the
phenotype is the outcome of interaction with the environment during
the individual's growth and development. Drawing above is a
schematic representation of this process. Circles in lower part of
drawing (A) represent the genotypes of a father, mother and child. In
middle layer (B) the three are shown by silhouettes depicting their
"characters" (i.e., their phenotypes). Columns joining the circles to
the silhouettes (C) illustrate the way in which the changing
phenotype is "governed" by the unchanging genotype. Top layer (D)
symbolizes all the physical, cultural and other influences to which
the phenotype is subject from its external environment.
5 i
CO
< 5-
II
Z -
"Sil
5?
m
©I
oí
D_ 1^
^>
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
"The only value judgement
with any scientific backing
concerns the importance of
differences for their own
sake... The more different we
are the more I give to my
neighbour and the more I
receive from him in return".
A Neolithic artist carved a
human face in this sea-shell
from Tongsamtong (Republic
of Korea).
^ distance to two distinct groups. In the case
of human populations, this method cannot
be conclusive.
Basing his research on the best-known
blood systems, the Harvard geneticist R.
Lewoutin has shown that the distance bet¬
ween two populations belonging to different
"races" is, on average, not more than 7 or 8
per cent higher than the distance between
two populations of the same race.
In other words, if belonging to a given
race or a given nation is not without
significance as regards genetic structure, its
consequences are very limited; an Eskimo or
an African could well be closer to me
genetically than the policeman in my village.
This is not to deny the differences between
the various human groups. But the web of
similarities and dissimilarities is so intricate
that the picture becomes blurred as soon as
an attempt is made to incorporate all the
available data.
_ So the geneticist's answer, when asked
about the meaning of the word "race", is
categorical; insofar as the human species is
concerned, there can be no objective and
stable definition of this concept.
Experience shows that thé classifica¬
tion of humanity into more or less distinct
groups usually goes hand in hand with a
value judgement distinguishing the "good"
from the "bad". Thousands of examples
could be cited of writers who are convinced
that they are not racists and yet take it for
granted that their own group is the best. A
book read by several generations of French
children, Le Tour de la France par Deux En¬
fants, presents stereotyped portraits of
Whites, Blacks, Yellow people and redskins,
and affirms that "the white race is the most
perfect."
Current attempts to establish a hierarchy
of races seek to envelop themselves with an
aura of scientific respectability by making
reference to research in a variety of
disciplines, notably those concerned with
explaining the evolution of species and
those that study the various manifestations
of intellectual activity.
For over a century, explanations of evolu¬
tion have been dominated by Darwinism.
The key concept of this theory is that of the
survival of the fittest; those individuals best
26
fitted for the "struggle for life" have the best
chances of surviving and transmitting their
genetic inheritance to the next generation.
According to this theory, the biological
structure of the population undergoes
transformation as a result of this inequality
of individual capacities, desirable
characteristics spread, and undesirable ones
gradually die out.
When, thanks to the Austrian botanist
Gregor Mendel, it was understood that sex-
ed beings transmit not their characteristics
but the genes governing these charac¬
teristics, it became necessary to modify this
theory and to attribute a "selective value"
not to the individuals or to their
characteristics but to the genes they
possess. Darwinism was supplanted by neo-
Darwinism whose approach is basically the
same.
However, the attribution of a "value" to
people or to genes can be highly misleading.
By definition, this value corresponds ex¬
clusively to the gene's ability to transmit its
biological inheritance, i.e. to procreate
children. Individuals who die without off¬
spring are thus "of no selective value". To
classify them as "inferior beings" is to con¬
fuse their selective value and their value as
human beings.
This blunder has been made many times
by those who have extrapolated a social
Darwinism from the original biological Dar¬
winism, and have advocated a type of soci¬
ety in which the powerful must "naturally"
prevail over the weak. Contemporary
Western thought has been deeply influenc¬
ed by this kind of reasoning, which many
regard as dictated by "the laws of nature".
The fact is, however, that nature really
teaches us the exact opposite of this hierar¬
chical vision.
One of the consequences of natural selec¬
tion ought apparently to be the gradual stan¬
dardization of populations. Since the
"good" drive out the "bad", in due course
only the best genes remain, and there is less
diversity. Now, analysis of the genetic in¬
heritance of various species shows, on the
the contrary, that this diversity is maintain¬
ed. One unexpected discovery made by
biologists, which has gradually been con¬
firmed over the last ten or fifteen years, is
the extent of "polymorphism", the ex
istence of a wide field of variation within a
given population.
This discovery has led to a fundamental
revision of neo-Darwinism. This revision has
taken two directions: certain scientists are
developing a "neutralist" theory, from
which the concept of selective value has
been eliminated; others retain the concept
but give it a much more complex definition,
giving weight to the interaction of several
genes on a single characteristic. In either
case, this revision renders obsolete all
reasoning based on the existence of a scale
of values according to which individuals,
characteristics or genes may be set in a
hierarchy.
The mechanisms at work in nature do not
select the best and weed out the less good:
they preserve the sustained coexistence of a
wide variety of characteristics. If we are to
learn from nature, then we ought to rank ,
groups not according to the quality of their
characteristics, but according to the variety
of these characteristics. The "best" group is
the one that has managed to preserve the
greatest diversity, whatever the content of
this diversity.
Our judgements on our fellow men often
concern their psychological rather than their
physical characteristics. It is the role of the
psychologist to define with greater precision,
the various traits of the personality, and for
nearly a century now. Western
psychologists have sought to turn their
discipline, with all its nuances and subtle
distinctions, into a "scientific" discipline.
For this, they have introduced quan¬
titative criteria. In particular, they have
popularized the intelligence quotient, or I Q,
a parameter that supposedly measures the
activity of our intelligence. Admittedly,
psychologists themselves denounce the
abuses that have arisen in connexion with
the cult of I Q. Even so, this quotient figures
prominently in many misconceived
arguments; it serves to justify often harsh
decisions concerning children's school
careers, and it has been the crux of the con¬
troversy provoked in the United States by
the revival of a certain kind of racism.
This is not to deny the usefulness of the
concept of I Q. But it is necessary to define
the limits of its significance: I Q indicates the
position of an an individual on an arbitrarily
defined scale of reference within a given
population, at a specific moment in time.
This indicator is extremely imprecise, and its
stability is little-known and probably low.
Despite these limitations, certain scien¬
tists have used I Q to compare human
populations. The most famous study is the
one conducted by the American
psychologist Arthur Jensen, who in 1969
compared Blacks and Whites in the United
States and concluded that there was a
15-point differential in favour of the latter.
This conclusion depends upon the factors
to which the observed difference is at¬
tributed. This involves a delicate genetic
concept known as inheritability. Certain
psychologists have totally misunderstood
this concept: they have forgotten that the
inheritability of I Q merely measures a
resemblance and have used it to attribute
I Q differentials between populations to
genetic factors.
This is not to deny the influence of
genetic inheritance on a characteristic such
as intellectual activity. Clearly, the medium
for this activity, namely the central nervous
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
system, is produced from the genetic in¬
heritance, but its ontogenesis also requires
the intervention of the environment. The
outcome will depend upon the way they in¬
teract. But to try to measure the relative in¬
fluence of each is meaningless.
Thus it is impossible to base a classifica¬
tion of the "intellectual potential" of dif¬
ferent human groups on observable intellec¬
tual performance, or even to ascribe observ¬
ed variations, as certain doctrinaire thinkers
have tried to do, to genetic differences.
The very concept of intellectual potential
is indefinable. Attempts to establish a hierar¬
chy of races on the basis of this criterion are
not just mistaken: they are absurd. Ex¬
perience unfortunately shows that it is
harder to combat an absurdity than to clear
up a mistake.
The chief lesson to be learned from
genetics is that the groups to which we
belong do indeed differ from each other, but
that the individuals within each of these
groups are even more different still.
The only value judgement with any scien¬
tific backing concerns the importance of dif¬
ferences for their own sake, without at¬
taching a plus or a minus sign to these dif¬
ferences. I am neither superior nor inferior to
anybody else; I am different from
everybody; the more different we are, the
more I give to my neighbour and the more I
receive from him in return.
This is not an assertion dictated by a
moral system; it is the central lesson of
genetics. It is a serious matter that this
lesson should have been distorted to justify
racist doctrines. It would be easier to com¬
bat this kind of perversion of the truth if
communication between scientists and
public opinion were better organized. In this
field, the activities of Unesco could prove
decisive for the future of us all.
H Albert Jacquard
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Declaration
of Athens
Scientists speak out
against racism
THE scientists brought together by Unesco appeal to the
peoples of the world and to all individuals everywhere to
base their attitudes, behaviour and statements on the follow¬
ing conclusions, which represent the present state of scientific
knowledge on the racial question.
1. The latest anthropological discoveries
confirm the unity of the human species.
2. The geographical dispersion of the
human species has favoured its racial
differentiation but has not affected its
basic biological unity.
3. All attempts to classify the human
species so as to give objective content
to the concept of race have been based
on visible physical characteristics. In
fact, the concept of race can only be
based on transmissible characteristics,
that is to say, not on visible physical
features but on the genetic factors that
govern them.
4. Modern biological techniques have
made it possible to study these factors.
They reveal a far greater genetic diversi¬
ty than had been imagined.
5. It has been found that the difference
' between the genetic structures of two
individuals belonging to the same
population group can be far greater than
the differences between the average
genetic structures of two population
groups. This finding makes it impossible
to arrive at any objective and .stable
definition of the different races and con¬
sequently deprives the word "race" of
much of its biological meaning.
6. Whatever the differences observed,
biology can in no way serve as the basis
for a hierarchy between individuals or
population groups, since no human
group possesses a consistent genetic in¬
heritance. In any event, one is never
justified in proceeding from observation
of a difference to the affirmation of a
superiority-inferiority relationship.
7. In fact, each human being possesses a
genetic combination that is unique
among the countless possible combina¬
tions.
8. Man has developed culture, which has
enabled the human race to adapt itself
to different ecological environments and
to transform them according to its
needs.
28
9. The pre-eminence of culture makes the
human species unique and invalidates
any explanations of human behaviour
based solely on the study of animal
behaviour. There are no grounds for ex¬
plaining variations in group behaviour in
terms of genetic differences.
10. Intellectual activity constitutes one of
the most striking characteristics of man.
Certain disciplines have developed
techniques for measuring this activity.
11. These techniques are designed to com¬
pare individuals within a given popula¬
tion group and cannot, by definition, be
used for the purpose of comparing dif¬
ferent population groups.
12. It follows, a fortiori, that any value
judgement on the intellectual capacities
of a given group based on such
measurements is completely without
foundation.
13. Indeed, the complexity of the inter¬
action between biological and cultural
factors makes any attempts to establish
the relative importance of innate and
acquired characteristics completely
meaningless.
14. It is unacceptable and scientifically un-
. justifiable to use the results of
psychological tests and the intelligence
quotient in particular to promote social
ostracism and racial discrimination.
15. The social sciences provide no support
for the view that racism is a collective
form of behaviour that inevitably arises
when certain kinds of social relationship
predominate between different ethnic
groups. On the other hand, the plurality
and coexistence of cultures and races
that characterize many societies con¬
stitute the most felicitous form of
mutual enrichment between peoples.
16. Racism, which takes a number of forms,
is in reality a complex phenomenon in¬
volving a whole range of economic,
political, historical, cultural, social and
psychological factors. Effective action
to combat racism must necessarily ad¬
dress itself to all these factors.
17. Racism is generally a tool used by cer¬
tain groups to reinforce their political
and economic power, the most serious
cases being those involving apartheid
and genocide.
18. Racism also takes the form of denying
that certain peoples have a history and
of underrating their contribution to the
progress of mankind.
19. While the quantitative analysis of social
phenomena can help to elucidate
sociological and economic issues, it can
also be used to promote exclusion and
segregation. The application of quotas,
tolerance thresholds and numerical
stipulations for educational purposes
based on ethnic or racial criteria should
be denounced when it violates the basic
principles of human rights. However,
legitimate measures can be taken to
redress the wrongs inflicted on certain
underprivileged groups.
20. Those engaged in scientific activity bear
a major responsibility for the social
future of their contemporaries. Where
racism is concerned, this responsibility
involves political and ethical choices.
Scientific research, particularly in the
field of the human and social sciences,
should always be based on respect for
human dignity.
, 21. Recognition of the risks to mankind im¬
plicit in certain applications of science
should lead not to a rejection of science
but rather to the fostering among the
public at large of a genuinely scientific
attitude, that is, an attitude based not
on an accumulation of certainties but on
the cultivation of a critical spirit and the
continual challenging of accepted
views. The struggle against racism in all
its forms calls for the extensive involve¬
ment of scientists in the fostering of
these attitudes, making use in particular
of education systems and the media.
22. There is a need therefore for scientists,
whatever their differences or divergen¬
cies of viewpoint, to strive to maintain
the objectivity that will ensure that their
work and conclusions cannot be used as
the basis for falsifications and inter¬
pretations detrimental to mankind.
Signatories
A.C. Bayonas (Greece), historian and philosopher;
T. Ben Jelloun (Morocco), philosopher and writer;
J. Björnebye (Norway), philologist;
A. Bouhdiba (Tunisia), sociologist;
H. Condamine (France), geneticist;
E. Czeizel (Hungary), geneticist;
M. Diabate (Ivory Coast) ethno-sociologist;
CA. Diop (Senegal), anthropologist;
R. Droz (Switzerland), psychologist;
M. Fraginal (Cuba), ethnologist;
S. Genoves (Mexico), anthropologist;
A. Jacquard (France), geneticist and mathematician;
J. Ki-Zerbo (Upper Volta) historian;
C.B. Krimbas (Greece), geneticist;
E. Nevo (Israel), geneticist;
H. Tawa (Lebanon) historian and mathematician,
D. Trichopoulos (Greece), professor of medicine;
T. Tsunoda (Japan), professor of medicine;
P. Vegleris (Greece), lawyer and professor of law;
L.P. Vidyarthi (India), anthropologist;
G. Wald (U.S. A), Nobel Prize for medicine,
A. Yotopoulos Marangopoulos (Greece), President of
the Athens Human Rights Foundation;
I. M. Zolotareva (USSR), anthropologist.
Symposium on a Critical Review of the
Pseudo-scientific Theories Invoked to
Justify Racism and Racial Discrimination
Athens 30 March to 3 April, 1981
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
man
who
vanquished
yellow
fever
by Pedro M. Pruna
and Rafael O. Pedraza
A century ago relatively little was
known about the tropical diseases
which brought suffering and death
to the peoples living in the hottest regions of
the globe.
Today, although not all tropical diseases
have been eradicated, some of them are on
the way to being completely wiped out, or
else their incidence has dropped.
Yellow fever was the first tropical disease
to be eradicated from the regions where it
was considered to be endemic. Coastal
cities such as Havana, Veracruz, Rio de
Janeiro and other ports of Central and
South America were the front-line targets of
yellow fever epidemics, as well as relatively
large areas of West Africa. The disease
sometimes affected regions with a more
temperate climate such as the Mississippi
valley, where it caused over 13,000 deaths in
1878, and other parts of North America and
even Europe.
Two big questions emerged from analysis
of the causes of yellow fever. One had to do
with the nature of the pathogenic agent
which caused the disease; the other with the
specific way in which it was transmitted. It
was known that it could be propagated over
relatively large distances without there
necessarily being a carrier in the vicinity of
each new infected centre.
The Cuban physician Carlos Finlay
(1833-1915) knew that the pathogenic agent
responsible for yellow fever could be "an
amorphous virus", an animal or plant germ
or a bacteria, but he was more interested in
discovering how the disease was pro¬
pagated than in isolating the micro¬
organism which caused it. Between 1879
and 1880, Finlay concentrated all his efforts
on discovering in which organs of the
human body the first symptoms of the
disease appeared. His studies convinced him
that the germ which caused the disease was
first of all lodged in the walls of the blood
vessels. It could thus be supposed that it
was introduced into the blood by a medium
of transmission which was still unknown.
In the history of science it sometimes hap¬
pens that a fact which apparently has little
connexion with the matter being investi¬
gated provides the inspiration for a scientific
discovery. Finlay's discovery was one of
these occasions. The inspiration came from
an article describing wheat-rust, a disease
caused by a fungus part of whose life-cycle
is spent as a parasite on an intermediary
plant. Finlay immediately realized that the
epidemiological characteristics of yellow
fever could be explained by,the existence of
an active intermediary agent capable of in¬
oculating healthy persons with diseased
blood and thus with the germ causing the
disease.
In February 1881 Finlay expounded the
hypothesis of the existence of a transmitting
agent in an address to the International
Sanitary Conference at Washington, D.C.
By August of the same year he had made so
much progress that, in a lecture to the
Havana Academy of Medical, Physical and
Natural Sciences, he was able to describe
this agent with amazing precision. The vec¬
tor of yellow fever, Finlay declared, was a
mosquito whose description corresponded
to the species which is today known as
Aedes aegypti. For the first time it was
claimed that a pathogenic micro-organism
was transmitted from one person to another
by a biological vector.
Before Finlay's discovery, the theories put
forward to explain the transmission of
yellow fever from an infected to a healthy
subject had given rise to a confused debate
which brought into confrontation two main
schools: the contagionists, who claimed
that the disease was transmitted through
secretions, through clothing and direct con- 1
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
1965-1968 1969-1972 1973-1976 1977-1979
Maps from WHO Weekly Epidemic Record. No. 46, 1980
	1	
A century ago, when Carlos Finlay discovered that it was transmitted by a mosquito,
yellow fever was an endemic disease in much of tropical America and Africa. Today its
ravages have been greatly reduced. Shaded areas on maps (top) show the incidence of
jungle yellow fever in South America between 1965 and 1979. The four maps showing part
of Africa also illustrate the evolution of yellow fever during the same period. Localized out¬
breaks in three countries spread rapidly before becoming concentrated in two countries by
1979. Generalized vaccination is the main weapon used by national health authorities
against yellow fever.
30
tact, and the miasmatics, who maintained
that foul-smelling marsh gas was the culprit.
Seen from a historical perspective, the
major contribution of Finlay's work was not
only the identification of the transmitting
agent of yellow fever, but his realization that
certain diseases were transmitted not so
much through person-to-person contagion
as through a biological vector.
It is today widely recognized that the
theory of biological vectors has a double
paternity, since it was set forth and demons¬
trated almost simultaneously by Carlos J.
Finlay for yellow fever, and Patrick Manson
forfilariasis. However, Finlay was the first to
put forward the theory in the case of a
micro-organism.
Finlay also distinguished himself by
explaining why the indigenous population of
Cuba suffered less from yellow fever than
foreigners who had recently arrived in the
country. He supposed, correctly, that the
Cubans had developed a certain immunity to
the disease, and that for them the mosquito
acted as a kind of vaccine. This was an
explanation ahead of its time.
In 1898, Finlay put forward the method of
combatting yellow fever which four years
later would be applied to eradicate the
disease from Cuba. This was the destruction
of the larva of the mosquito in the water
where it lived, using chemicals.
Before the year 1900, Finlay carried out
over a hundred inoculations using the mos¬
quito as a vector, and although most of the
results obtained corroborated his theory, the
latter had been confirmed by no other scien¬
tist. An opportunity to carry out an impartial
test arose in 1900 when a commission of
physicians from the United States, led by
Walter Reed, arrived in Cuba. Their aim was
to investigate the causes of yellow fever, but
they were more interested in isolating the
pathogenic micro-organism which caused
the disease (through a process of elimina¬
tion they reached the conclusion that it was
a "filtrable virus") than in studying how the
disease was propagated.
It was only when Finlay took up the mat¬
ter strongly with the supervisory authorities
of the United States in Cuba that the Com-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
mission agreed, with considerable scepti¬
cism, to examine the theses he put forward
and to repeat, in controlled conditions, the
experiments he had performed. In so doing
they confirmed the fundamental results he
had obtained. It should be added that the
only member of the Commission who be¬
lieved in Finlay's theory, the young doctor
Jesse Lazear, died in the course of an expe¬
riment designed to test it and carried out on
his own initiative.
Years later, William Gorgas, who headed
the campaign to wipe out yellow fever in
Cuba and Panama, wrote to Finlay:
"If we had followed your advice during
our stay in Cuba, we should have obtained
in 1899 the results we obtained later, in
1901. For myself, I would even go so far as
to assert that it is thanks to your work and to
the way in which you defended your mos¬
quito theory that the American Commission
of which Reed was president was induced to
investigate the theory. Were it not for the
work you had already carried out in 1900,
the American Commission would never have
embarked on research into the mosquito
theory."
The first scientist of international reputa¬
tion to recognize the outstanding merits of
Finlay's work was the British bacteriologist
Sir Ronald Ross, who was noted for his
investigations of malaria and was awarded
the Nobel Prize for Medicine in 1902. Two
years later he proposed Finlay for the same
award. But although Finlay never received
this prize which he so richly deserved, he
was privileged to receive in person many
tokens of universal gratitude for his work.
He won the Breant Prize of the French Aca¬
demy of Medicine, of which he became a
member, and the Mary Kingsley Medal be¬
stowed on him by the University of Liver¬
pool. He was also awarded the French
Legion of Honour.
At the Panamerican Medical Congress of
1933 it was decided that Finlay's birthday, 3
December, should be celebrated each year
as American Medicine Day. Several interna¬
tional congresses on the history of medicine
have underlined the importance of Finlay's
discovery, and some years ago Unesco
created a prize bearing his name. But
perhaps the finest tribute that could be paid
to Finlay's work and to Finlay himself would
be for its significance never to be forgotten.
In Cuba there has not been a single case
of yellow fever since the first decade of this
century, and the disease has been wiped out
in many other Latin American countries, in
the United States, and wherever the princi¬
ples established by Finlay have been applied.
Pedro M. Pruna and Rafael O. Pedraza
PEDRO M. PRUNA, Cuban biologist, is scien¬
tific secretary of the Carlos J. Fin/ay Centre for
the Study of the History and Organization of
Science of the Cuban Academy of Sciences.
RAFAEL O. PEDRAZA, Cuban physician, is
president of Cuba's History of Medicine Society.
SAINT BENEDICT
OF NURSIA
The only authority for the facts of St. Benedict's life is book 2 of the
Dialogues of Pope Gregory the Great, which was written around 593-594,
almost fifty years after the saint's death. This medieval miniature from the
Miracles of St. Benedict by St. Gregory, Adrevaldus and Almoin (1437)
shows Gregory listening to testimony about the life of St. Benedict.
A voice across
the centuries
by Gregorio Penco
Jl J/ BEAR, my son, the precepts of
BiH the Master and lend him thine
I I heart's ear. Receive with
gladness the teaching of a good father, that
in its practice and in the exercise of obe¬
dience, thou shalt return again to him from
whom base contumacy hath led thee
away".
begins the "Rule of Saint
Benedict", a document written some 1500
years ago that was to become one of the
foundation stones of monasticism in
western Christendom.
All that we know about the life of Saint
Benedict, the author of this document, is
contained in Book II of the Dialogues of
Saint Gregory the Great (Pope Gregory I).
Benedict was born in the year 480, of good
family, at Nursia, Umbría, Italy. After a brief
period of schooling in Rome, impelled by a
desire for a closer union with God and by a
strong sense of vocation, he withdrew to
the solitude of a cave near Subiaco, while
still a young man, where he devoted his life
to prayer and penitence.
There he lived for three years, attracting
by his devoutness so many disciples that he
was obliged to found thirteen communities
in the region. Later, he left the area, moving
south to found the famous monastery (in its
chequered history it has been destroyed and
rebuilt four times) at Monte Cassino where,
in 547, he was to die. r
GREGORIO PENCO, of Italy, is a Benedictine
monk at the monastery of Agrano, near Novara,
Italy. A noted theologian, he is a specialist in
monastic history.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Works of art inspired by St. Benedict, many of them painted by great masters, would
have a prominent place in any portrait gallery of Christian saints. In the 15th-century
fresco, above, left, by the Italian painter Mariano di Matteo da Roma, St. Benedict is
shown deep in meditation. Fingers to his lips, he enjoins his monks to silence. Quite
different in spirit is the drawing of the "patriarch of Western monks" by the great
Flemish painter Peter Paul Rubens, above right. It was executed around 1605 after an
earlier portrait by Giovanni Bellini. St. Benedict, shown holding a crook in one hand
and an open Bible in the other, is accompanied by St. Mark. The authority of his gaze
and bearing reflects the decisive role played by St. Benedict in European history.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
This miniature from the Miracles of St. Benedict by the medieval Flemish chronicler
Jean de Stavelot shows a famous episode in the life of St. Benedict as recorded by
Gregory the Great. St. Benedict is admonishing the Gothic king Totila, who then
dominated much of Italy, with the words: "You commit acts of great evil, you have
done many wrongs. Put an end to your cruelty!" This appeal for peace and justice,
courageously addressed by the sequestered monk to one of the mighty figures of his
age, here appears as a symbol of the superiority of the word over the sword.
^ Saint Benedict was, above all, an ascetic,
a contemplative, a "man of God" as his
biographer called him. Yet he was also a
legislator who expressed and codified his ex¬
perience of monastic life in his famous Rule
which was destined primarily for application
in the monastery at Monte Cassino, but also
in other monasteries that little by little came
to adopt it.
The monastic movement had, indeed,
been in existence in the West for some two
centuries before Saint Benedict's time and
had already produced a number of notable
figures, such as Saint Martin of Tours, as
well as various monastic rules. What it lack¬
ed, however, was a balanced, reasonable,
harmonious code which would make the
monastic life accessible to people not en¬
dowed with exceptional physical and
spiritual qualities and which, above all,
would provide monastic communities with a
solid, wisely-conceived organizational
framework capable of withstanding the
vicissitudes of time.
Saint Benedict was inspired by a pro¬
found faith, and it was upon this faith that
he based his entire spiritual edifice. In this
respect, the Benedictine Rule has been
described as being "Christ-centred", since,
to the eye of the faithful, the presence of
Christ can be discerned in everyone,
whether abbot or monk, sick person or pass¬
ing guest.
Since the community for which it was
drawn up was formed and exists above all
for religious purposes (seeking after God),
the Rule gives pride of place to prayer,
which Saint Benedict called Opus Dei, the
supreme work of God. Periods of prayer are
allowed for at fixed times of the day, con¬
sisting of readings of psalms and lessons.
The Bible, accompanied by the commen¬
taries of the Church Fathers, is thus the
basic text of prayer. By means of prayer the
monk can express the renewed gift of
fellowship with God both in personal collo¬
quy and in a collective act of praise in which
all creation is united in celebration of the
greatness of God in the world and
throughout time. Linked in this manner to
the Bible and the liturgy, monastic prayer
has an essentially objective character quite
distinct from that of other spiritual schools
which tend rather towards the introspective,
contemplative approach.
Work is another fundamental component
of the Rule. Indeed, so essential was it con¬
sidered to be that later tradition coupled it
with prayer in the formula Ora et Labora
(pray and work), although these words do
not actually appear in the text of the Rule.
Previously left almost entirely to slaves,
work not only offered an escape from
idleness, so harmful to the spirit, it also pro¬
vided a means of subsistence and of helping
pilgrims and succouring the poor. The Rule
speaks explicitly of Arti, that is to say, of the
activities undertaken by the monks within
the monastery. Work in the fields was left to
the peasants, although the Rule provides for
the monks to take part in this work when
necessary. It also gives instructions on what
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
"Slave or free man, we are all one in Christ, and we are militant under
one Lord, bearing an equal yoke of servitude", wrote St. Benedict in his
Rule. The abbot, leader and father of the monks, takes no important
decision withour consulting the community or the council of seniors,
and some writers who have described the organization of the
Benedictine life have even spoken of "monastic democracy". This detail
from a fresco in the Benedictine monastery of Monte Oliveto Maggiore
near Siena in Italy shows the Benedictine community eating in silence
which is broken only by the monk reading aloud. It forms part of a
series of scenes from the life of St. Benedict painted by the Italian artist
Sodoma between 1505 and 1508.
constitutes a suitable ration of food and the
time to be allotted to sleep and rest, the
Abbot being allowed a wide margin of dis¬
cretion in these matters.
These apparently simple regulations, des¬
tined for the closed world of the monastery,
cut off from society, were to prove extre¬
mely fruitful during the succeeding centu¬
ries. Born just after the fall of the Western
Roman Empire, in 476, Saint Benedict lived
in a period of profound change, of crises
and upheavals whose effects were felt as
much by ecclesiastical as by other institu¬
tions.
It was a period marked by intensified
transmigrations of peoples which were to
give birth to the Europe of the Middle Ages.
And, although there are no grounds for sup¬
posing either that the Popes gave any expli¬
cit instructions concerning the formulation
of the Benedictine Rule, with a view to the
conversion of these people to Christianity,
or that this was in the mind of the Saint
himself he had no wish to deviate from his
¡deal of solitude and detachment from the
world the regulations he had drawn up
were to be decisive for the future.
With the foundation of the Holy Roman
Empire under Charlemagne, in the 9th cen¬
tury, and under his successors, the Benedic¬
tine Rule was more and more widely adop¬
ted until it became virtually the sole body of
monastic regulations of the period. This
meant that innumerable monasteries had the
good fortune to find themselves governed
on the basis of a wise and compassionate
Rule, while at the same time retaining vir¬
tually complete autonomy.
At the end of the 6th century, Pope Gre¬
gory the Great had sent some forty monks
under Saint Augustine to convert England
to Christianity. Later, from the 8th to the 9th
century, Anglo-Saxon monks, under the
leadership of Saint Boniface, were in their
turn to land on the continent, penetrating
into the heart ôf Europe to regions un¬
touched by Roman civilization, to convert
the Germanic peoples to Christianity. They
then took their message to the Scandina¬
vians and the Slavs, and in this way, over
the centuries, the spread of Christianity and
the expansion of monasticism went hand in
hand.
The time came, however, when the
monasteries felt the need to emerge from
their isolation and to band together into lar¬
ger associations to defend themselves from
external threats. The first of these associa¬
tions, the precursors of the great religious
orders, was centred on the famous monas¬
tery founded at Cluny, in Burgundy, France,
in 910. Many others followed suit, notable
among them being Citeaux, the monastery
which Saint Bernard and some thirty of his
relatives and friends were to enter two cen¬
turies later.
As it expanded, Benedictine monasticism
followed fairly closely the evolution of both
Church and society, associating itself with
the Church in the task of spiritual reform to
counter interference from the outside world,
but acting in concert with society in the
introduction of new craft techniques and in
the development of agricultural production
and trade.
Situated, in many cases, beside the main
communication routes, whose upkeep they
ensured, the monasteries provided hostels
for pilgrims and, later, full-scale hospitals for
the sick. But, above all, the Benedictine
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
1">V C ifIHptí' wi - -*t>} V
-<- .,T.r,r ..-»."/
ill*1 r.t?.^iwilwr»rr tir.r
c cir^fw? Ar î.aiif.t
By the end of the 12th century there were over 100,000 Benedictine
monasteries in Europe. Their impact on European culture and civilization
was far-reaching: their scribes and copyists helped to transmit the literature
and learning of Antiquity to the modern world, and their schools were the
leading educational institutions. Above, 15th-century miniature showing
Constant the African, an 11th-century monk in the great Benedictine
monastery of Monte Cassino in Italy, diagnosing an illness through
uroscopy. Constant was instrumental in transmitting elements of the Arab
pharmacopeia to Europe. Below, the scriptorium, or scribes' copying-room,
in the abbey of Echternach (Luxemburg) as depicted in an 11th-century
miniature.
'Pray and work"
An original feature of St. Benedict's Rule is
the stress it lays on the importance of
manual work in the spiritual life, the
monk's day being divided between prayer
and work, and governed by a strict
timetable. Bells were rung when it was
time to pass from one activity to another.
Top, the ringing of bells is depicted in the
initial "E" in an illuminated Bible (c. 1250)
from the abbey of Saint-Eloi in northern
France. Above, preaching monk carved on
a stall from the abbey of Saint-Lucien,
Beauvais (France). Carving on another stall
from the same abbey (below) shows a
monk working a butter churn. As a result
of their "work ethic" the Benedictines
made a decisive contribution to the
economic and social life of medieval
Europe. Manual work is still coupled with
prayer in the daily activities of the monk.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
While St. Benedict was living as a hermit, the fame of his sanctity
spread and disciples flocked to hear him preach. Tiny painting
(above) in the margin of a mid-15th-century breviary from the abbey
of Grammont (France), shows the monks of Vicovaro beseeching
him to become their abbot. Later his followers would preach the
length and breadth of Europe. In 529 Benedict founded the
monastery of Monte Cassino on the site of an ancient temple to
Apollo halfway between Rome and Naples. The monastery (below)
was an important cultural centre in the Middle Ages when its monks
produced outstanding manuscripts and paintings. It has been
destroyed and rebuilt several times, most recently after the Second
World War.
^ monasteries gave an extraordinary impetus
to the life of the mind at a time when there
existed very few other institutions in a posi¬
tion to do so.
Each monastery had a library and a writ-
ting room for the transcription of manu¬
scripts required both for the religious offices
and for the cultural education of the monks.
At a time when the outside world was ex¬
periencing a disturbing cultural decline, the
monastic libraries represented virtually the
sole repositories of knowledge. In tran¬
scribing and preserving not only sacred
Christian texts but also classical Greek and
Latin literature, the Benedictine copyists
rendered an invaluable service to civilization,
maintaining its continuity in face of the
threat of irreparable rupture.
Nevertheless, Saint Benedict and his suc¬
cessors will be remembered primarily for the
spiritual values which they kept alive and
spread throughout Western Europe up to
the start of the modern era. Then the chang¬
ing conditions of the times made necessary
the development of new religious orders
with more clearly defined aims and that were
better prepared for the apostolic mission. In
the organization of work, in the sense of
prayer and in the collective life of the
monastery were to be found the specific ac¬
tivities and conditions of life that together
constituted the values that Benedictine
monasticism sustained and propagated in ,
medieval society. The very soul of Europe
was moulded by Saint Benedict and his suc¬
cessors who created a culture which,
despite the diversity of its national and local
forms, was profoundly unitary because it
drew inspiration from a single source, hav¬
ing a single faith based on the Bible and the
tradition of the Church.
For centuries, the ideal of saintliness re¬
mained that formed by the monastic life,
and Benedictine saints, whether canonized
or not, can be counted in their thousands,
among whom were spiritual leaders, ad¬
visers to popes and emperors, founders of
monasteries and of cities, and evangelists
who carried the word to the people. They in¬
cluded many great thinkers, Doctors of the
Church such as the Venerable Bede, Saint
Damien, Saint Anselm and Saint Bernard,
who contributed to the emergence of a par¬
ticular kind of theology known as "monastic
theology" because it was appropriate to a
life of prayer and the quest for union with
God. Their writings, highly esteemed by the
student of today, are of lasting value
because they stress the unity of prayer and
life, of faith and charity, of religion and
culture. Thus the influence of Saint
Benedict's spiritual legacy still makes itself
felt across the centuries, and from the past
his voice still brings enlightenment to
modern man.
H Gregorio Penco
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
All over the world today there are men and women who live according to
the Rule of St. Benedict. Above, two Benedictines from the monastery of
Koubri (Upper Volta). Below, monks listening to their prior in the cloister of
a monastery near the village of Bédouin in the south of France.
Photo Gilles Mermet © Figaro Magazine, Pans
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
ffl El
r
ï
Soviet scientist and broadcaster
wins Kalinga Prize
The Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of
Science has been awarded to Sergei Kapit-
za, professor of physics at the Moscow
Physico-Technical Institute. Since 1973,
Prof. Kapitza has produced a peak-hour
popular science TV series which reaches an
audience of some 40 million. Programmes
conceived and presented by him have
covered such subjects as thermonuclear
power, gerontology, humour and jokes, the
origin of life, and creativity in art and
science. Created in 1951, the £1,000 Kalinga
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
& PERIODICALS
Book Today in Africa, by S.I. A.
Kotei. A broad-ranging enquiry into the cur¬
rent book situation in Africa. 210 pp., 1981
(30 F).
Made to Measure: Children's Books in
Developing Countries, by Anne Pellowski.
129 pp., 1980 (22 F).
Studies in Mathematics Education,
Volume 2, edited by Robert Morris. A con¬
tribution to the design of future mathematics
programmes. 179 pp., 1981 (24 F).
The Concept of International Organiza¬
tion, edited by Georges Abi-Saab. 245 pp.,
1981 (42 F).
Methods of Computation of the Water
Balance of Large Lakes and Reservoirs,
Vol. I, Methodology. A contribution to the In¬
ternational Hydrological Programme, edited
by H.L. Ferguson and V.A. Znamensky.
(No. 31 in Unesco's "Studies and Reports in
Hydrology" series). 120 pp., 1981 (32 F).
Community Communications. The Role
of Community Media in Development, by
Frances J. Berrigan. (No. 90 in Unesco's
"Reports and Papers on Mass Communica¬
tion" series). 50 pp., 1981 (10 F).
Alexander Pushkin, by Dmitrij Blagoj.
One of a number of monographs prepared in
the context of Unesco's project for. the study
of Slav cultures and being published, in col¬
laboration with the International Association
for the Study and Dissemination of Slav
Cultures, under the general title of "Promi¬
nent Figures of Slav Culture". 104 pp., 1981
(18 F).
Museums in China is the theme of
Museum, Unesco's quarterly on
museography (Vol. XXXII, no. 4, 1980).
Single issue: 24 F; annual subscription: 72 F.
Weapons from Science: Civilization's
Pitfall, theme of Unesco's quarterly Impact
of Science on Society (Vol. 31, No. 1, Jan-
March 1981). Single issue: 16 F; subscription
56 F (1 year); 90 F (2 years). See news item
this page.
Educational reform 1: Approaches,
theme of the special dossier in Unesco's
quarterly review of education Prospects
(Vol. XI, No. 1, 1981). Single issue: 16 F;
subscription 56 F (1 year); 90 F (2 years).
Prize is awarded annually by a Unesco-
appointed jury for work contributing to the
popularization of science. It bears the name
of the ancient Indian empire which flourish¬
ed under the reign of Ashoka, the enlighten¬
ed emperor who renounced war to devote
himself to study and religion.
World Food Day
World Food Day will be observed for the
first time on 16 October 1981, the 30th an¬
niversary of the foundation of the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United Na¬
tions (FAO), and will then become an annual
event. World Food Day will be an opportuni¬
ty to do something about world hunger
through renewed commitment and
resources for food and development pro¬
grammes, internationally co-ordinated ac¬
tion to tackle food problems, sponsorship of
activities such as seminars, debates, essay
competitions for schoolchildren, etc. Most
governments and many non-governmental
organizations are planning World Food Day
events. For further information write to: the
World Food Day Secretariat, FAO Head¬
quarters, Via délie Terme di Caracalla, 00100
Rome, Italy.
International effort
to save the panda
The World Wildlife Fund has lauched a ma¬
jor international fund-raising campaign on
5 continents in support of efforts by the
People's Republic of China to save one of
the world's best-loved animals, the giant
panda. This is the first joint conservation
project between the Chinese Government
and a non-governmental conservation
organization. Field work is already underway
on the save-the-panda operation, which was
inaugurated last year in Wolong Natural
Reserve, Sichuan Province. The initial
agreement which the World Wildlife Fund
and China signed in preparation for their
scientific collaboration acknowledged the
panda as "not only the precious property of
the Chinese people but also a precious
natural heritage of concern to people all over
the world."
The threat of military research
and development
Some 400,000 highly qualified scientists and
engineers around the world are engaged in
military research and development (R&D).
Their activities, which account for about
40% af all R&D, constitute the major ele¬
ment fuelling the arms race and thus
threaten the future existence of humanity.
These are two of the grim conclusions
reached by contributors to the latest issue of
Unesco's quarterly Impact of Science on
Society (vol. 31, No. 1, Jan. -March 1981).
Articles in the issue, which is entitled
"Weapons from science: civilization's
pitfall", include: "Arms control, disarma¬
ment and small nations", "What the arms
race means", and "The influence of arms
development on new research".
Satellite send-off
for Bulgarian anniversary
Two "Intercosmos Bulgaria-1300" space
satellites equipped with Bulgarian equip¬
ment will be launched from USSR territory
to commemorate the 1300th anniversary of
the foundation of the Bulgarian State. Their
mission will be to study the interaction of
the ionosphere and the magnetosphere.
Since the first Bulgarian satellite went into
orbit in December 1972, Bulgaria has
become a veteran of space exploration.
New creatures found
in Pacific geysers
A research ship off South America has
reported discovering sea creatures which
may never have been seen before, living at
the bottom of the Pacific Ocean. The sea
floor was known only as a pitch black ter¬
rain, nearly barren of life, until 1977 when
hot water geysers gushing up through small
"smokestacks" were discovered off the
Galapagos Islands and were found to sus¬
tain communities of species, genuses and
families unlike any evolved elsewhere on
earth. The latest discovery, by the U.S.
vessel Melville, may be the largest of these
"ocean vent communities". The vent sites
are on the crest of an underwater mountain
range called the East Pacific Ridge, where
two great plates of the Earth's crust are
slowly pulling apart. ' ,
Unesco group votes
to launch sports week
A Unesco-sponsored intergovernmental
committee has unanimously recommended
that all Member States support the
organization of a World Physical Education
and Sports Week. The 30-member Inter¬
governmental Committee for Physical
Education and Sport also appealed for in¬
creased contributions to the international
fund for the development of these activities,
stressed the need to democratize sport, and
called for large scale programmes to provide
sports opportunities for everyone.
Flashes...
The world total of blind people is now
estimated at 30 to 40 mi/lion, reports WHO,
80 per cent of them living in the Third
World.
In an average year tropical cyclones kill
about 20,000 people and diminish the
economic resources of the countries af¬
fected by $6,000-7,000 million, according to
the World Meteorological Organization.
The World Food Programme is sending
10,000 tons of grain to drought-stricken
populations of Mauritania.
An estimated $1 billion worth of technical
assistance to Third World countries is ex¬
pected to be delivered by the United Nations
Industrial Development Organization
(UNIDO) in the 5-year period 1982-1986.
The Serengeti National Park and the
Ngorongoro Conservation Area in Tanzania
celebrate their 60th anniversary this year.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
What is consensus? What role can it play in the search for and
the building of, a just, lasting and constructive peace? Such is
the twofold question examined by the contributors to this col¬
lective work, using an institutional, interdisciplinary and inter¬
cultural approach.
Contents include
CONSENSUS
AND
Consensus in international organizations (by the Director-
General of Unesco, Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow)
PEACE
Linguistic aspects of consensus (Gérald Antoine)
Philosophical, cultural and historical aspects of consensus
(Beseat Kiflé Selassie, editor of the work)
Consensus and international relations (Mario Amadeo)
The political aspects of consensus in a developing country
(Abdoulaye Wade)
Political and legal aspects of consensus in the Arab world and
in the Islamic world (Rachid Daker)
The technique of consensus in Spain's progress towards
democracy (Joaquin Ruiz Giménez)
wi \dou-m \m \r \i now
M \RIO WI \l)l O . OI.RU.l) \\TOI\L
Political aspects of consensus in a socialist country: the ex¬
ample of Yugoslavia (Mihajlo Javorski)
RU'iim n\K.t r \shjorn ni)h mih mi o j\\ orski
JO VQUIN RLI/-GTMI M / . UIDOLI U 1. U MIL
EU SI M KIM 1 SI 1 ASNII
231 pages 55 French francs
UNESCO
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications' Educational Supplies Pty Ltd P 0
Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals Dominie Pty Subs¬
criptions Dept , P 0 Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW Sub-agent
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St , Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
- AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31, A
1011, Vienna BANGLADESH Bangladesh Books International
Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3
- BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only NV Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing Keesinglaan 2 18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent. Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. - CANADA Renouf Publishing
Co Ltd , 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P O Box 88, Peking -
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos3rd Avenue, P 0 Box
1722, Nicosia - CZECHOSLOVAKIA - S N T L , Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display), Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only Alfa Verlag - Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo - ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P 0
Box 2996, Addis Ababa - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja¬
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10 - FRANCE
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G D R - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish editions)
Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse
57, D5300 Bonn 3 For other Unesco publications
Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps only
Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Pres¬
byterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P O. Box 195, Accra, Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd , P.O Box 7869, Accra, The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast, The University Bookshop of Legon, P O Box 1, Legon.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom - HONG
KONG Federal Publications (HK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12. Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen Swindon Book Co,
13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon Hong-Kong Government Informa¬
tion Services, Publications Centre, GPO Building, Connaught
Place - HUNGARY Akademiai Konyvesbolt, Vaci u 22,
Budapest V, A K V Konyvturosok Bolt|a, Nepkoztársaság utja
16, Budapest VI - ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson Et Co , H F ,
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd ,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2,
B-3/7 Asaf All Road, New Delhi 1, 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001, 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 Sub-
Depots Oxford Book & Stationery Co 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scmdia House, New Delhi, Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastn Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta, Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta, Indira P T , Jl Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat - IRAN Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi Street,
Enghélab Avenue, PO Box 314/1486, Teheran, Iranian Nat
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No 300, B P 1533,
Teheran - IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street,
Baghdad - IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd , Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin 12 - ISRAEL.
ABC. Bookstore Ltd , P O Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd , P O
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston -- JAPAN Eastern Book
Service Inc , Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon
3 Chôme, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P O Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P O Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait -
LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre, P O Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. - LIBERIA Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd ,
P 0 Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication b Distribution, P O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEM¬
BOURG Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg -
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11 - MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic
Street, Valletta - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd , 30.
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis - MONACO British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins. Monte-Carlo - NETHERLANDS For the
"Unesco Koener" Dutch edition only Systemen Keesing,
Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco
publications N V Martmus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The
Hague - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N V , P O Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. NA - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops af Rutland Street, P O Box 5344, Auckland, 130,
Oxford Terrace, P O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch, Alma Street, P O
Box 857 Hamilton, Princes Street, P O. Box 1104, Dunedm,
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington - NIGERIA The
University Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P O 286, The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University
Bookshop of Lagos, The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana - NORWAY. All publications Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers'), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1 For Unesco
Courier only. A S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6
- PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i azam,
P.O Box No. 729, Lahore 3 - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P 0 Box 632, Manila D-404 -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7 00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon - SEYCHELLES. New Ser¬
vice Ltd , Kmgsgate House. P 0 Box 131, Mahé - SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown - SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd , No 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19 - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O Box 951,
Mogadiscio - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications Van
Schaik's Bookstore (Pty ) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street,
P O Box 924, Pretoria For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only Central News agency. P 0 Box 1033, Johannesburg -
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gar¬
diner Mawata P O B 244 Colombo 2 - SUDAN Al Bashir
Bookshop, PO Box 1118, Khartoum - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B C E Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16 For the
Unesco Courier Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP 12-236. - TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, POB 9030 Dares-Salaam -
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P O Box 402, Bangkok Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok, Suksit Siam Com¬
pany, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A S , Istikläl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P O. Box 145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P O.
Box 569, London, S E.I , and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol - UNITED STATES Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N Y. 10010 - U S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade, Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P O B 50-1, L|ubliana - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd , 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
X
f/
The crisis of Africa's five million refugees (see article page 15)
]]>
</page>
</document>
