<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074805eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^r*% %
The Unesco COUfier A window
open on the world
" M
R r\
UP I
*$&
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
- a 1 1 * « ».
-^rtBL # Bà, »
mmmwmwÊh '^ÊÊÊÊÊÊT^- k>
fl bTbTbT*^^ bw Bbb*.
bb ^^¡S Eh» ]
'aàmm^mmlÊmx C^>.WA
j "* - " ^P
Buk. ^mBI ^JbI
m ' 'BF - ^1 IAvM>
^BB jji * Ffll
' :- * * BF
-r >A ^ J
1 &£*\ *üb> i
V~$ >^k ^^H^
»jP JBBJ ^BJ
Ipïfl
H jB
^B
*\ *Ä »
(A
C
t»
<
^^^^^MB ^^BBB^^
a
CO
0
a
>
to
r-
(A
O
>
a
©
o
o
OL
TREAS
OF
WORLD
Grée
URES Monarch in miniature
: This ivory head (height 2.5 centimetres) is thought to portray King Philip II of Macedonia (382
A OT 336 B.C.), who laid the foundations for his country's expansion under his son Alexander the
1 ART Great. Along with many other outstandingly important gold, silver and bronze examples of
Hellenistic art, it was unearthed a few months ago at the village of Vergina in northern
k Greece, during excavations conducted by Professor Manolls Andronicos of the University of
1 Salonika. The head was found beneath a huge tumulus in a barrel-vaulted tomb dating from
the third quarter of the fourth century B.C. It has been suggested that the tomb, which has a
magnificent wall-painting on its façade, may have been the burial place of Philip II.
ice
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco CY)UFÍCF
JULY 1978 31st YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 18 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese Dutch
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's Issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York. U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editors:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
«
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin ?
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum 0
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
So
page
AN APPEAL BY MR. AMADOU-MAHTAR M'BOW
DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF UNESCO
A plea for the return of an irreplaceable cultural heritage
to those who created it
RETURN TO THE HOMELAND
Entire regions have been deprived of their cultural past
by Georges Fradier
12 A WOMAN OF HIGH DEGREE
300 years ago, Elena Lucrezia Cornaro Piscopia
became the world's first woman Ph.D.
by Maria Remiddi
14 MY YEARS WITH TOLSTOY
Extracts from an unpublished diary
by Dushan Makovitsky
24 TOLSTOY: THE STRUGGLE TOWARDS THE LIGHT
by Victor B. Shklovsky
27 'THE MOTHER'
The spiritual heir of Sri Aurobindo
by Emmanuel Pouchpa Dass
30 TECHNICAL CO-OPERATION
AMONG DEVELOPING COUNTRIES
by Dragoljub Najman
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
GREECE: Monarch in miniature
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
Photo © Rljksmuseum Voor Volkenkunde,
Leyden, the Netherlands
Cover
Through the vicissitudes of history, countless
vyorks of art and artefacts of all kinds are now
in exile far from their homelands. As Unesco's
Director-General, Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, has
pointed out in a recent appeal (see page 4), art
is for the whole world, out peoples who have
been deprived of their cultural heritage have
the right to demand the return of those objects
that best represent their culture. Already some
items have made the long voyage home, like
this 13th century statue of the Buddhist god¬
dess Prajnaparamita from East Java which was
returned, in April 1978, to the Museum Pusat,
in Jakarta, Indonesia, by the Rijksmuseum
voor Volkenkunde, Leyden, the Netherlands.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
An appeal by
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General
of Unesco
ONE of the most noble incarnations of a people's
genius is its cultural heritage, built up over the
centuries by the work of its architects, sculptors,
painters, engravers, goldsmiths and all the creators of
forms, who have contrived to give tangible expression to
the many-sided beauty and uniqueness of that genius.
The vicissitudes of history have nevertheless robbed
many peoples of a priceless portion of this inheritance in
which their enduring identity finds its embodiment.
Architectural features, statues and friezes, monoliths,
mosaics, pottery, enamels, masks and objects of jade, ivory
and chased gold in fact everything which has been taken
away, from monuments to handicraftswere more than
decorations or ornamentation. They bore witness to a his¬
tory, the history of a culture and of a nation whose spirit
they perpetuated and renewed.
The peoples who were victims of this plunder, sometimes
for hundreds of years, have not only been despoiled of irre¬
placeable masterpieces but also robbed of a memory which
would doubtless have helped them to greater self-
knowledge and would certainly have enabled others to
understand them better.
Today, unbridled speculation, fanned by the prices pre¬
vailing in the art market, incites traffickers and plunderers to
exploit local ignorance and take advantage of any conni¬
vance they find. In Africa, Latin America, Asia, Oceania and
even in Europe, modern pirates with substantial resources,
using modern techniques to satisfy their greed, spoil and
rob archaeological sites almost before the scholars have
excavated them.
The men and women of these countries have the right to
recover these cultural assets which are part of their being.
They know, of course, that art is for the world and are
aware of the fact that this art, which tells the story of their
past and shows what they really are, does not speak to
them alone. They are happy that men and women else¬
where can study and admire the work of their ancestors.
They also realize that certain works of art have for too long
played too intimate a part in the history of the country to
which they were taken for the symbols linking them with
that country to be denied, and for the roots they have put
down to be severed.
These men and women who have been deprived of their
cultural heritage therefore ask for the return of at least the
art treasures which best represent their culture, which they
feel are the most vital and whose absence causes them the
greatest anguish.
This is a legitimate claim ; and Unesco, whose Constitu¬
tion makes it responsible for the preservation and protection
of the universal heritage of works of art and monuments of
historic or scientific interest, is actively encouraging all that
needs to be done to meet it.
The return of cultural assets to their countries of origin
nevertheless continues to pose particular problems which
cannot be solved simply by negotiated agreements and
spontaneous acts. It therefore seemed necessary to
approach these problems for their own sake, examining
both the principle underlying them and all their various
aspects.
This is why, on behalf of the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization which has empowered
me to launch this appeal,
I solemnly call upon the governments of the
Organization's Member States to conclude bilateral agree¬
ments for the return of cultural property to the countries
from which it has been taken ; to promote long-term loans,
deposits, sales and donations between institutions con¬
cerned in order to encourage a fairer international exchange
of cultural property, and, if they have not already done so,
to ratify and rigorously enforce the Convention giving them
effective means to prevent illicit trading in artistic and
archaeological objects.
I call on all those working for the information
mediajournalists of press and radio, producers and
authors of television programmes and filmsto arouse
worldwide a mighty and intense movement of public
opinion so that respect for works of art leads,
wherever necessary, to their return to their homeland.
I call on cultural organizations and specialized associa¬
tions in all continents to help formulate and promote a
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
A PLEA FOR THE RETURN
OF AN IRREPLACEABLE
CULTURAL HERITAGE TO THOSE
WHO CREATED IT
stricter code of ethics with regard to the acquisition and
conservation of cultural property, and to contribute to the
gradual revision of codes of professional practice in this
connexion, on the lines of the initiative taken by the Interna¬
tional Council of Museums.
I call on universities, libraries, public and private art gal¬
leries and museums that possess the most important col¬
lections, to share generously the objects in their keeping
with the countries which created them and which some¬
times no longer possess a single example.
I also call on institutions possessing several similar
objects or records to part with at least one and return it to
its country of origin, so that the young will not grow up
without ever having the chance to see, at close quarters, a
work of art or a well-made item of handicraft fashioned by
their ancestors.
I call on the authors of art books and on art critics to pro¬
claim how much a work of art gains in beauty and truth for
the uninitiated and for the scholar, when viewed in the
natural and social setting in which it took shape.
I call on those responsible for preserving and restoring
works of art to facilitate, by their advice and actions, the
return of such works to the countries where they were
created and to seek with imagination and perseverance for
new ways of preserving and displaying them once they
have been returned to their homeland.
I call on historians and educators to help others to
understand the affliction a nation can suffer at the spolia¬
tion of the works it has created. The power of the fait
accompli is a survival of barbaric times and a source of
resentment and discord which prejudices the establishment
of lasting peace and harmony between nations.
Finally, I appeal with special intensity and hope to artists
themselves and to writers, poets and singers, asking them
to testify that nations also need to be alive on an imagina¬
tive level.
Two thousand years ago, the Greek historian Polybius
urged us to refrain from turning other nations' misfortunes
into embellishments for our own countries. Today when all
peoples are acknowledged to be equal in dignity, I am con¬
vinced that international solidarity can, on the contrary,
contribute practically to the general happiness of mankind.
The return of a work of art or record to the country which
created it enables a people to recover part of its memory
and identity, and proves that the long dialogue between
civilizations which shapes the history of the world is still
continuing in an atmosphere of mutual respect between
nations.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Thanks to an agreement between the Royal
Museum of Central Africa at Tervuren (Belgium) and
the National Museums of Zaire (see also pages 8
and 9), this ivory pectoral amulet (67 millimetres
high) has been returned to its country of origin.
Produced by an artist of the Hungana people, noted
ivory carvers who live In the valley of the river
Kwilu, It has the folded arms, the chin resting on
the hands and the knees bent close together that
are typical features of Hungana carved figures.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
RETURN
TO THE
HOMELAND
The art of Oceania Is rich In masks designed for use at funerals or fertility rites. Made
from a variety of materials, usually including tapa, or bark-cloth, they are sometimes
elongated in shape and have richly decorated eyes, like this example from the Gulf of
Papua which now forms part of the collection of the Papua New Guinea Museum. It was
returned to Papua New Guinea in 1977 by the Australian Museum, Sydney, where it had
been since 1884.
Entire regions
have been deprived
of their
cultural past
by Georges Fradier
IMAGINE a country which has collec¬
tions of works of art of all kinds and
diverse origins. It makes careful provi¬
sions for storing these precious objects; it
exhibits them to an admiring public; it
makes them available for study by scholars.
But what if representatives of another
country should come along, point at a sta¬
tue, say, or some mosaics or a manuscript,
and declare: "Look here, these things don't
belong to you. They were removed from
our country. In all fairness, you ought to
return them to us"?
This situation has in fact occurred often
enough to arouse the concern of the Uni¬
ted Nations General Assembly, which since
1973 has been looking into the question of
"the restitution of works of art to countries
victims of expropriation", and of Unesco
which is now preparing to set up "an inter¬
governmental committee concerning the
restitution or return of cultural property to
countries having lost it as a result of colo¬
nial or foreign occupation." Last March, an
international group of experts meeting in
the capital of Senegal, Dakar, drafted the
committee's terms of reference.
In some cases cultural property is seized
by force of arms. Except for the nomadic
hordes of old, who chose to destroy what
they found, armies have on the whole had
GEORGES FRADIER, French novelist and
essayist, was for many years a member of
Unesco's staff, latterly as Acting Director of the
Division of Human Settlements and Socio-
Cultural Environment. Among his many pub¬
lished works are East and West, towards mutual
understanding (1959), Encounters and Celebra¬
tions, on the mutual appreciation of Eastern and
Western cultural values (1963) and About the
Quality of Life (1976) all published by Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
This wickerwork mask with a tapa face, possibly a fertility-symbol, was
found in a Papuan village. A characteristic specimen of a highly
original art, it was returned to Papüa New Guinea on 20 August 1974 by the
National Museum of New Zealand at Wellington as part of an informal
arrangement with the Papua New Guinea Museum, Port Moresby.
at their head, or in their ranks, shrewd col¬
lectors on the look-out for objects to take
back for the adornment of palaces and,"
later on, museums.
The law of nations has been quite explicit
on this point for almost 2,000 years: if a
country that has enriched itself in this way
loses a war, the victors enforce restitution.
The 1815 Treaty of Vienna, and the
Treaties of Versailles, Saint-Germain and
Sèvres at the end of the First World War,
resulted in the return of thousands of
works of art from all over Europe to their
country of origin.
Those treaties even blithely ignored any
notion of prescription, the principle of law
whereby the right to something may be
acquired through its continued use or pos¬
session over a long period: in 1920 one
country was requested to return objects
and documents which it had removed in
the 18th century from a region then under
its domination. They included a triptych
painted by Peter Paul Rubens that one of
the country's kings had purchased in 1777.
Naturally, any power which imposes
such treaties ought to feel bound by the
same obligations if it too possesses works
once removed from another country.
Examples of such elementary courtesy
have, however, proved rare and, in this
context, historians are fond of quoting
their precursor, the Greek chronicler Poly-
bius, who wrote, more than 2,000 years
ago: "It is my hope that the conquerors of
the future will learn not to despoil the
towns they take, and will refrain from
turning other nations' misfortunes into
embellishments for their own country."
It is quite frequent, today, for one
country to approach another with a formal
request for the restitution of works taken
from it in unhappy circumstances at a spe¬
cific time and place. The other country will
listen politely and then regret that it is not
in a position to take any action.
One African country, for instance, is cur¬
rently attempting to recover one of four
ivory masks removed in 1897 by certain
members of a "punitive expedition". The
whereabouts of the masks, which are of
enormous symbolic and historical value, is
known; one of them is in a museum, and
the three others are in the possession of
private individuals. These include a woman
descendant of an officer who took part in
the raid. Doubtless she considers thft the
item forms part of her family possessions;
what the holders of the other two masks
feel about the matter is not known. The
fact remains, however, that the official
delegation of the requesting country,!
which was empowered to buy one of the
masks (for a very high price), returned
home empty-handed.
It would be a mistake, however, to sup¬
pose that military operations alone have
been responsible for the large-scale re- k
moval of cultural property which is now f
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Wooden "ndop"
figurines depicting kings
played a major role In
the transmission of
authority among the
Kuba people of Zaire,
whose traditions of
kingship are centuries
old. The subject of each
statuette can be
identified by a symbolic
object attached to its
base. Example shown
here (height 55
centimetres) is a
representation of King
M'Bop, who ruled at the
turn of the century.
Photo © Royal Museum
of Central Africa,
Tervuren, Belgium
Thought to depict an Amazon, this
polychrome mosaic dating from the
5th century A.D. attests to the extent
of the Roman colonization of Asia
Minor. It was discovered at the
ancient city of Apamea In Syria and
belonged to the Newark Museum,
New Jersey (U.S.A.). Following a
request sent to the Museum on 25
June 1973 by the Syrian Department
of Antiquities and Museums, this
outstanding work returned to its
homeland on 6 April 1974.
causing concern to international organiza-
' tions like Unesco. Nearly all such transfers
have taken place in peacetime, and in the
most peaceful manner possible. A number
of renowned museums boast works which
came to them as a result of cold-blooded
plunder, carried out, under a cloak of
authority, either during a "foreign or colo¬
nial" occupation, or on occasions presen¬
ted by the occupation of a territory by a
third power; whatever the circumstances,
the essential common factor was the
defencelessness of those being plundered.
The most blatant example of such
dealings remains the case of the "Elgin
Marbles", sculptures from the Acropolis of
Athens which were hewn off the buildings,
dismantled and sent out of the country be¬
tween 1800 and 1803 by the British envoy
extraordinary in Constantinople, the
Seventh Earl of Elgin. How many visitors to
the British Museum realize, as they stand in
admiration before the frieze of the Parthe¬
non and a Caryatid from the Erechtheum,
that Lord Elgin's henchmen smashed
dozens of bas-reliefs as they took the tem¬
ples to pieces? Or that some of the met¬
opes, which might eventually have formed
part of the London, Paris or Copenhagen
collections, were shipwrecked and now lie
at the bottom of the sea, somewhere off
Cape Malea at the southern tip of the Pélo¬
ponnèse? Do they realize that all these
sculptures would now be standing on the
Acropolis, where their creator Phidias
intended them to stand, had it not been for
Lord Elgin's frantic efforts to "save" them,
with the dubious approval of the govern¬
ment in Constantinople?
This is but one typical case among hun¬
dreds. It would be absurd to level accusa¬
tions at one particular country rather than
another. Besides, at the time, nobody criti¬
cized Lord Elgin more vehemently than the
English poet Lord Byron. Most leading
museums of ethnography or ancient art
today possess important works obtained in
similar circumstances in Greece, Italy,
China, India, the Middle East, Africa or
Latin America. It is more instructive to exa¬
mine the clear conscience with which such
"rescue operations" were nearly always
carried out.
Around 1800 it was fashionable to bring
to Europe any work deemed beautiful; a
beautiful work of art was a reflection of
man's genius, and Europe assumed that it
held the monopoly of that attribute. Occa¬
sionally, a single European nation would go
it alone. When Napoleon's commissioners
walked off with statues, books, paintings
and gold objects from Flanders, Italy and
Spain, they seriously believed they were
striking a blow for Reason and Enlighten¬
ment.
Later on, other high-flown pretexts,
such as scientific progress, love of art, or
simply the needs of the collection, were
found for relieving weaker countries of
their heritage. Thus, most cultural property
removed from former colonies (or from
countries in a de facto situation of depen¬
dence because of political unrest or econo¬
mic stagnation) would seem to have been
legally acquired. Legislation protecting
such property and forbidding its export is
only recent, and has not yet been enforced
in all countries.
The problem is how to decide retrospec¬
tively whether acquisition was legal or not.
Travellers in search of exotic souvenirs or
experts carrying out research may well
have behaved with scrupulous honesty. A
local administrator, landowner, or village
chief would authorize them to take away
the fruits of their excavations, objects from
a sanctuary, or manuscripts from neglected
archives.
Many objects, ranging from the priceless
to the most utilitarian, were given away in
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Kuba people, who migrated in large numbers from the west
to central Zaire, have always felt a keen admiration for art and
beauty and hold the artist in high esteem. Of all the craftsmen at
the royal court, the sculptor held pride of place. Carved In minute
detail, this wooden hand (84 millimetres long) was a ritual object
which may have had a sacred meaning.
This pre-Columbian ceramic, produced sometime
between 800 and 1200 A.D., was discovered in a
tomb at Sitio Conte in Codé province, northern
Panama. The Peabody Museum at Harvard
University (U.S.A.) has returned it to Panama under
a ten-year renewable loan.
The Lega people of the Maniema
region of Zaire produce an art
whose simple, expressive style
appears to full effect in the
objects they create for the
Bwamé, a society of initiates. This
mask (137 millimetres high) is
made of ivory and probably
belonged to a high-ranking
initiate. Like the other two objects
from Zaire shown on these pages
it has been returned to its
homeland as part of an agreement
between the Royal Museum of
Central Africa at Tervuren
(Belgium) and the National
Museums of Zaire.
The Hungarian coronation
regalia have returned home
once more. The crown was
given to St. Stephen, the
first king of Hungary, in the
year 1001 by Pope Sylvester
II; the sceptre and the orb
date from the 12th and 14th
centuries respectively.
Several times lost and even
stolen during the centuries,
these precious objects were
stored at Fort Knox,
Kentucky, after the Second
World War. Following an
agreement between the
United States and
Hungarian Governments
the regalia were returned to
Budapest early in 1978.
accordance with the laws of hospitality.
Even more were simply bought or bartered
as the result of transactions which, how¬
ever odd they may seem today, probably
satisfied both parties. Later on, the use of
currency simplified matters, and dealers
began to flourish. What could be more
legal than such dealings when carried out
in good faith and in accordance with local
practice?
There is good reason today to look
askance at such practices and to take the
notion of good faith with a pinch of salt.
One may wonder, for instance, whether
the donors were always entitled to give.
Sometimes the degree of generosity was
unacceptably high, such as when a poten¬
tate gave away the property of "his" peo¬
ple, or when a priest kindly offered a visitor
the contents of "his" church.
It is equally legitimate to question the
validity of commercial transactions from
the time of the wandering pedlar down to
the tentacular business concerns of today.
Was the seller entitled to sell? Was he really
the owner, or at least a genuine representa¬
tive of the owner?
Works of art are stolen or disappear
every day. After a long and circuitous
route, they reappear in the shops of respec
table dealers, who then sell them to equally
respectable collectors. Sometimes it might
be more relevant to ask whether the seller
was really in a position to refuse to sell in
the first place, in other words whether or
not he was forced by social or economic
pressure to accept money for a piece of
property that he would have kept for him¬
self if he had had greater freedom of
action.
On the international art market paintings
pass from hand to hand, from strongroom
to museum, from continent to continent.
In general, this is the lot for which they
were intended and for a long time painters
have been putting their works up for sale
and dealers have been pushing their prices
upwards. On the art market there is a kind
of equality between buyer and seller.
This is not the case, however, when the
market handles items that were never
intended to be sold. Three-quarters of "lost"
cultural property consists of objects that
were carved, painted, modelled or woven
for religious and ceremonial purposes, or
else were purely utilitarian. The flow of
such property is almost always in one direc¬
tion only, from the poor to the rich coun¬
tries. A number of countries with out- 1
standing artistic gifts have been deprived in I
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Oakland Museum, Oakland, California
These two Chancay funeral figures,
formerly in the possession of the Oakland
Museum, Oakland, California, were
handed back to the Consul-General of
Peru in San Francisco in March 1977. The
Chancay people inhabited the central
Peruvian area from around 1000 AD up to
the arrival of the Spanish conquistadores.
They were famed for their weaving which
was technically highly advanced.
This chalk figure, from New Ireland in the
Bismarck Archipelago (Pacific Ocean) is
one of a number of items returned in 1977
to the Papua New Guinea National
Museum by the Australian Museum,
Sydney. It was originally acquired by the
Australian Museum by purchase.
this way of their entire cultural heritage.
The richer their traditions, the more their
artefacts tend to flow abroad.
This explains why many countries are
now feeling frustration and resent¬
ment are demanding the restitution
of their works of art. One African head of
state was leafing through a book on his
country's art when he realized that of the
hundreds of important and characteristic
works shown in the illustrations every sin¬
gle one was outside the country. An¬
other "African leader wanted to create a
national art .museum. His representatives
approached museum curators from Europe
and America during a congress telling
them: "We have nothing of our own left.
Would each of you agree to let us have one
work, just one, from all those in your col¬
lections?"
So far, none of the museums involved
has felt able to accede to that request. The
national museum has opened, but its ex-
^^^1
^1
mw
C W^^ .- -
^m
^m t ^^M
^B^ J
i J9^H
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Detail from a stele dating from the late
classical period (600-900 AD) of Mayan
culture. This stele, which stands 240 cm
high, was originally discovered at the
ancient ruins of Piedras Negras, in north¬
western Guatemala. The stele, which was
acquired by a United States Museum, was
returned to the Government of Guatemala
In 1970.
hibits are photographs and one or two
copies.
Yet such heartfelt appeals are being
increasingly heeded, and it now seems cer¬
tain that they will not remain completely
unanswered. Restitution is not being
requested on a scale too massive to be fea¬
sible. No country is claiming back more
than a portion of its lost cultural property,
even in cases where the losses have left
unpleasant memories. It is universally
accepted that the arts and sciences have
nothing to gain from being enclosed within
national boundaries and that, on the con¬
trary, admiration and love of a people's cul¬
ture can only increase when its works of art
are exhibited and studied abroad.
The experts brought together by
Unesco, all of them museologists, defined
a specific objective they felt should be
aimed for: the reconstitution, through bila¬
teral negotiations, of a country's dispersed
heritage. More precisely, they said, it is
advisable "to ensure the return to its
country of origin of cultural property which
is fundamentally important from the point
of view of its spiritual value and the cultural
heritage of the peoples concerned." No
one could refuse to subscribe to such a
reasonable objective.
It would seem, however, that manifesta¬
tions of justice and solidarity, the recogni¬
tion of cultural identities, or a spirit of
generosity are not enough alone to solve
this problem. There remain a number of
hurdles to be cleared; the most important
of these, according to the Unesco experts,
are "psychological difficulties" and legal
obstacles.
There are, they say, certain psychologi¬
cal difficulties which "are linked to the
incriminating aspects of the act of restitu¬
tion which implies that the possession of
the object was up till then illegitimate.
Many countries and private owners would
find it difficult to accept being placed as it
were in the dock when the objects in ques¬
tion were added to their collections by
means that were legal and legitimate at the
time, and when they could well, it seems,
invoke the principle of non-retroactivity."
More serious is the concern expressed by
institutions and private individuals about
the legal and physical protection, even the
conservation, of cultural property once it
has been returned to the country of origin.
The experts proclaimed what they called
"the primacy of the object"; and indeed it
would ill become a requesting country to
recover a given item unless it could
demonstrate that it could guarantee perfect
conservation.
In this sphere, however, there exist a
number of broad rules that could be fol¬
lowed anywhere in the world. But their
applicationa moral duty which no state
would wish to be seen to shirk may be
hindered by material difficulties and
administrative shortcomings, as happens in
areas where conservation methods are still
inadequate. In such cases, the following
solution was suggested by the experts:
countries "in possession" of the objects
could and should offer the technical aid
necessary for every aspect of conservation
to those countries which need it, and help
to train every echelon of the staff who will
be in charge of collections.
Their advice has already been put into
practice. For example, an agreement rea¬
ched in 1970 between the Royal Museum
of Central Africa, at Tervuren in Belgium,
and the National Museums of Zaire pro¬
vides for the collection of objects, the resti¬
tution of certain works, the services of Bel¬
gian experts and the training of Zairian
curators.
The legal obstacles to the return of cul¬
tural property arise in connexion with the
question of the legal status of the claimed
objects. When they form part of national
collections (which are in theory untransfer¬
able), they can be donated to another state
by government decision. This occurs only
rarely, and in a number of countries any
such decision would (again in theory) be
subject to prior parliamentary debate.
But even when this obstacle exists,
however formidable it may appear to be,
there are usually ways of getting round it.
Museums are perfectly free to arrange
loans and exchanges, and more particularly
to entrust works of art to foreign institu¬
tions on a long-term deposit basis. Such
deposits may be indefinitely renewable by
tacit agreement.
Objects that are in private hands, how¬
ever, seem difficult to recover. The right of
ownership is almost universally guaran¬
teed, and could be overridden only by
CONTINUED PAGE 33
H
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
300 years ago, Elena Lucrezia Cornaro Piscopia
became the world's first woman Ph.D.
A WOMAN
OF HIGH DEGREE
by Maria Remiddi
JUST three hundred years ago, on 25
June 1678, a young woman submit¬
ted a doctoral thesis at Padua in Italy
and was solemnly awarded the title of
"Master and Doctor of Philosophy" (Magis-
tra et Doctrix Philosophiae).
A large audience was expected, and so it
was decided not to hold the ceremony in a
lecture hall, as was the usual practice, but
in the cathedral itself. The decision was a
wise one, for thousands of people flocked
to witness the historic scene as 32-year-old
Elena Lucrezia Cornaro Piscopia (1646-1684),
the daughter of a Venetian dignitary, step¬
ped apprehensively into the cathedral.
Giovan Battista Cornaro, her father, was
of noble lineage. The Cornaros had prov¬
ided the Venetian Republic with four Doges
and had also produced a Queen of Cyprus.
Nothing if not proud of his family's glorious
achievements, Giovan Battista had done
everything in his power to overcome the
obstacles that then stood in the way of a
woman who sought academic honours.
Only one had proved insuperable : the
authorities had refused to allow his daugh¬
ter to be examined for a doctorate In theo¬
logy. When she resubmitted her application
specifying the discipline of philosophy
(then called "dialectics"), the college of
professors had relented.
On the day of the examination, Elena
Lucrezia would have been only too glad to
forego the doctorate and return to her life
of learned seclusion, but beside her stood a
priest who urged her to comply with her
father's wishes. Put on her mettle by the
examiners' questions, she soon began to
display her vast erudition with an authority
that impressed the jury. A laurel crown was
placed on her head, and a teacher's ermine
MARIA REMIDDI is editor in charge of the
Italian edition of the Unesco Courier.
cape was draped on her shoulders as the
college of professors conferred on her a
title which until then no woman in the
world had earned.
But Elena Lucrezia could not wait for the
moment when the congratulatory speeches
would be over and she could return home.
There she would continue her studies until
her death six years later.
Three centuries after this historic event,
interest is being rekindled in this noble and
learned Venetian woman. Research has
shown that she has been widely quoted by
other writers and the enumeration of her
works takes up over a page of a guide,
published in Padua in 1832, which lists
writings by women throughout history. The
earliest of her works to be cited is a trans¬
lation, executed in 1665 when she was six¬
teen years old, of a Spanish book entitled
"Conversation between Christ our Redeem¬
er and the Devout Soul".
Elena Lucrezia was still in her teens when
she felt her religious vocation and showed
her desire to turn her back on the things of
the world and devote herself to eternal
things. But her religious vocation went
hand in hand with a thirst for knowledge.
According to her biographers, she spoke
and wrote French, Spanish and Hebrew, as
well as Latin and ancient and modern
Greek. She played and composed music
and was a student of mathematics and
astronomy. A precocious and highly-
developed intellect, a prodigious memory
and an unremitting contempt for frivolity
and worldliness enabled her to amass her
vast store of erudition.
She was in no way misanthropic, in spite
of her refusal to marry and her fondness for
the monastic life. Elena Lucrezia was glad
to receive visits from scholars from Italy
and other countries and was ready to take
part in debates or, as we would say today,
give lectures. Her reputation spread
quickly. She became a member of seven
cultural academies ; her poems were
widely read.
Many stories are told to illustrate her sen¬
sitivity and modesty. Her father, who was
not only a rich man but vaunted his wealth,
was once talking to a group of painters and
craftsmen about a project for decorating
his palace on the Grand Canal.
"Why not give all this money to the
poor ?" Elena Lucrezia is said to have
asked. "If you did, you would be building a
far more resplendent and enduring palace
in Paradise."
Faced with his daughter's determination
to live a scholarly, ascetic life, Giovan Bat¬
tista sadly abandoned any idea of arranging
W--
B**H
3 ^1
(0
Q_
o
u
U
O ** M
m
W I
3
5
, JÍ¡M
< ! r^
c/i
D
.c
1 wB
*
£
2?
co
c
0}
c
0)
u
0) :
H :
O F <A
«j r *i
C
o
<-> 1
©
°
o
Q_ 1
Just three hundred years ago, Elena
Lucrezia Cornaro Piscopia, a young
Venetian, became the first woman in the
world to receive a university doctorate.
The historic award was made by the
College of Masters of the University of
Padua (Italy), renowned for its rigorous
standards of scholarship. In this work by
the 19th-century artist Michèle Fanoli she
wears the ermine cape symbolizing her
teacher's status.
Right, a stained glass window depicting
Elena Lucrezia Cornaro defending her
doctoral thesis before an immense
audience in Padua cathedral. It was
designed in 1906 for the library of Vassar
College, Poughkeepsie, New York, then a
leading university for women (it became
coeducational in 1969). Elena Lucrezia
Cornaro first became widely known in the
United States through a biography
published in 1896 by Lady Mathilde
Pynsent, the abbess of the English order
of St. Benedict in Rome.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
a marriage for her. He installed Elena Lucre¬
zia, along with four servants and a doctor,
in his palace at Padua, where for some
years she pursued her studies of theology
and philosophy at the ancient university.
In Padua she lived the simple life. The sil¬
ver plate was only brought out during her
father's visits. Usually she ate off the dishes
used by the poor. She served her servants
and ministered to them when they were
sick.
In earlier times, other Italian women had
distinguished themselves by their erudition.
In the 14th century Novella d'Andrea re¬
placed her father when he was ill and from
1355 to 1366 taught canon law at the Univer¬
sity of Bologna (founded 1088). But when
she lectured her face was modestly covered
with a veil.
Elena Lucrezia Cornaro's face, however,
is well known to us through a number of
portraits. The scene as she presented her
thesis is depicted on a stained glass
window in the library of Vassar College in
the United States, where the story of her
life and work is widely known. Reflecting
this interest, an Italian-American commit¬
tee has been formed in Pittsburgh to cele¬
brate the tercentenary and to support
research being carried out at Padua.
Founded in 1222, the University of Padua
enjoyed a high reputation as a centre for
scientific and medical studies. Above, the
vast 16th-century anatomy amphitheatre.
Photo © Cornaro Tercentenary, Pittsburgh-Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, U.S A.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Leo Tolstoy in the monastic simplicity of his
bedroom at Yasnaya Polyana. With him is
Dushan P. Makovitsky (right) the doctor who
tended Tolstoy and kept a record of his life and
sayings from 1904 until the great writer's death
in 1910. Dr. Makovitsky was the only person to
whom the 82-year-old Tolstoy divulged his
plans to leave his estate in search of a refuge
where he could live a simple life in closer
conformity with his convictions. When Tolstoy
left Yasnaya Polyana on the night of 10
November 1910, Makovitsky was with him. A
few days later Tolstoy's health broke down,
and he died at the tiny railway station at
Astapovo, attended until his final moments by
the faithful Makovitsky.
MY
YEARS
WITH
TOLSTOY
by Dushan Makovitsky
To mark the 150th anniversary of the birth
of Leo Tolstoy, the Unesco Courier presents
on the following pages specially selected
extracts from a hitherto unpublished diary
kept by Dushan Petrovich Makovitsky
(1866-1922), a Slovak physician who was
both Tolstoy's doctor and his close friend.
Throughout the last six years of Tolstoy's
life, Makovitsky lived at Yasnaya Polyana,
keeping a record of the great Russian
writer's comments on a wide variety of
subjects, including morality, religion,
philosophy, art, literature, history and
scienceand, more particularly, on the
most burning social and political issues of
the time.
The result was a voluminous diary
comprising more than 7,000 typed and
handwritten pages in the Russian and
Slovak languages, known today as The
Yasnaya Polyana Notebooks, although
Makovitsky himself called his record "With
Tolstoy, 1904-1910".
Makovitsky's diary owes its originality to
the manner in which it reflects what Lenin
called "the manifest contradictions" that
were so typical of Tolstoy's utterances and
thoughts. But the Notebooks are more than
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
just a day by day, at times even hour by
hour, chronicle of Tolstoy's life at Yasnaya
Polyana; they provide a memorable picture,
refracted through the prism of Tolstoy's
personality, of the period in which they
were written, of the critical years which
saw Russia's involvement in war with
Japan, the first Revolution of 1905, and the
reactionary backlash which followed its
repression.
The Yasnaya Polyana Notebooks are
invaluable source material for the study of
the life and work of one of the most
complex and spiritually fearless men of all
time, and of a writer who had a worldwide
influence on the development of modern
literature.
The first complete and annotated edition of
Makovitsky's diaries is at present being
prepared by Literaturnoe Nasledstvo
(Literary Heritage), at the A.M. Gorky
Institute of World Literature of the U.S.S.R.
Academy of Sciences, with the
collaboration of the L.N. Tolstoy State
Museum in Moscow, the Charles University
in Prague and the Institute of Literary
Studies of the Slovak Academy of Sciences
in Bratislava.
Photo Hermitage Museum © Aurora Publishers, Leningrad
This impressive bust of Tolstoy, the 150th
anniversary of whose birth is being
celebrated this year, is by the Russian
sculptor Anna Golubkina (1864-1927) who had
attended Auguste Rodin's studio in Paris.
Today in the Hermitage Museum,- Leningrad,
the sculpture conveys all the creative force of
the author of Anna Karenina, Resurrection,
The Power of Darkness, The Kreutzer Sonata,
Father Sergius, The Death of Ivan lllyich and
above all of War and Peace, one of the
greatest literary masterpieces of all time.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
MY YEARS WITH TOLSTOY
Tolstoy as a young man, at two key moments in his life as a
writer. Top, in 1856 at the age of 28. He had just returned to
St. Petersburg after serving as a volunteer in the Russian
army in the Caucasus and during the Crimean War. His
soldiering days left Tolstoy with a lifelong horror of war and
every form of violence, revealed in such early works as The
Cossacks and Sebastopol Stories which were based on his
experiences in battle. Above, Tolstoy at the age of 40 when
he was completing his masterpiece. War and Peace. This
vast novel, set against the background of the Napoleonic
Wars and above all the invasion of Russia in 1812, was
conceived and written between 1863 and 1869. With an array
of some 600 characters, it presents, through the story of a
group of families, Tolstoy's epic vision of Russian and
European life.
Text © Copyright. Reproduction prohibited
1905
20 January
Tolstoy : "In the past, literature functioned like chamber
music, as something designed to please a small circle of idle
rich. Now that it is within the reach of the workers, it should
be based on what ordinary people want. But literature of that
kind does not yet exist."
4 February
Tolstoy : "I'm being serious, why not visit the Slav countries?
Italy, the Riviera that's all familiar stuff. But new places,
peoples that haven't changed they're what is interesting.
That's where I should go if I were you. I'm grateful to Dushan
Petrovich tMakovitsky] for everything, but especially for what
he teaches us about the Slavs. Apart from the "Slavophils"
( 1 ) who make a point of finding out about them, we Russians
don't know much about the Slavs; we ought to be asking
how many of them there are, what they are like, where they
live, and so on."
25 April
Tolstoy : "We've been trailing along behind the rest of
Europe. Why don't we move up to the front and show what
needs to be done?"
27 April
Tolstoy : "I was fortunate, in that I began to love and revere
our people at a very early age. Spiritually, the Russians are
growing up. They are moving ahead, although at a slow pace.
The people know a lot; it's up to us to learn from them."
8 May
Tolstoy : "It was Radishchev, Novikov and the Decembrists,
(2) and not Alexander II, who liberated the peasants. The
Decembrists sacrificed themselves.
"At the moment, the question of freeing the land is where the
peasant question was at the time of the Decembrists."
17 May
Tolstoy : "Goethe says that he thinks better than he speaks,
that he speaks better than he writes, and that he writes better
for himself than for the public. I think it's the opposite with
me: I write more clearly and more comprehensively, and take
greater account of every point of view, when I'm writing for
publication, than when I'm writing for myself or speaking."
22 May
Asked whether the [Russo-Japanese] war could have any
kind of cultural influence, Tolstoy replied: "Enormous, but
anticultural. It takes no time at all to assimilate European
culture look at the Japanese. The nations with European
culture are out of their minds, struggling for colonies in order
to sell their goods. Arming themselves all the time. First it's a
metre of armour plating on their ships, then a metre and a
half, two metres, two and a half. One lot mobilizes its men,
(1) From the mid-nineteenth century onwards, Russian political thought was
divided, basically, between two schools: the "Westernizers", who wished the
Russia of the future to be modelled on Western civilization, and the "Slavo¬
phils", for whom the only hope lay through the development of specifically Slav
traditions.
(2) Alexander Radishchev (1749-1802) and Nikolai Novikov (1744-1818) were the
first Russian writers to raise the question of the abolition of serfdom. The
"Decembrists" were the instigators of the unsuccessful rising of December
1825 against the autocratic rule of Tsar Nikolas I. Five of the ringleaders were
hanged and 120 others were deported to Siberia.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
another calls up the women as well. All their thoughts and
energies are directed towards destruction. Isn't that mad¬
ness? Equality and brotherhood that's what true culture is
about."
27 May
Tolstoy : "It seems to me that the Russian people have lost
their moral sense. And yet I continue to venerate them. They
have their own religion, their own philosophy, their own art."
Vladimir Grigoryevich [Chertkov] (3): "What you have written
for the people is in a sense their property; but do they really
understand it?"
Tolstoy : "No, they only understand what I have borrowed
from themtheir tales and given back to them. What the
Russian intelligentsia is giving them is not what they need.
Dickens gave back to the English people the best of what the
people themselves possessed. In the West, the intelligentsia
laughs at the people, scorns the way they speak; in our
country it is the people who teach us how to speak, and who
reveal themselves through their speech. I come from the
people I like to believe that I really come from the
people and I try to write for them, in their own spirit."
1906
11 January
His voice choked with emotion, almost in tears, Tolstoy mut¬
tered: "How can I be a moral person when I am living off
others? The muzhiks [peasants] have taught me how to live.
Morality is possible only through physical labour and simple
living. When I learned that, it was my road to Damascus."
28 January -
Concerning the attachment of the lesser Slav peoples to their
national languages, and the enormous importance which they
accord to their mother tongue, Tolstoy said: "We Russians
are lucky, nobody else is oppressing us; we don't need to dis¬
cuss such matters. It's easy enough to talk about these things
when you're not under somebody else's yoke."
11 February
We were talking about music. Tolstoy said that music in¬
spired confidence and hope. It should be left on its own and
not be mixed up with drama and poetry. Music was the
highest form of art, the most mysterious and indefinable.
13 February
Tolstoy: "What a lot of barriers there are to prevent people
from leading reasonable lives! Racial distinctions, for in¬
stance, and governments, and religion."
28 March
Tolstoy: "At the moment, I'm making a thorough study of the
peasants. But what do the history books tell us? Almost
nothing that's of any use. I'm wading through the whole of
history, just to find a few scraps of the information I need.
Today we know at least that the people is made up of workers
on whose toil our food depends; in the old days, history
didn't even mention the people; it was all about tsars and
boyars [nobles] and fighting men and merchants.*'
1 May
"I have been thinking about the Duma (4)", Tolstoy told me,
"and wondering what it will all come to. More likely than not
the overthrow of the Romanovs and the declaration of the
Republic. A young worker from Tula was telling me a fort¬
night ago about a meeting in Zaseka forest. A state Duma is
not enough. What the people want is Socialism."
(3) Vladimir Chertkov (1854-1936) was one of Tolstoy's closest friends and the
publisher of his works.
(4) The elective national assembly created after the revolution of 1905.
"I reject the life of my class," wrote Leo Tolstoy in A
Confession, the account of his search for the purpose of
life. For many years his thinking was dominated by his
desire to share the life of the mass of the people, with
whom his sympathies lay. Photo above, taken in 1909,
shows Tolstoy with a group of local peasants who had come
to talk to him about their affairs and to seek his advice. He
held such gatherings almost every day of his life for he had
become, in his own words, "the advocate of a hundred
million peasants".
Tea-time outdoors for Tolstoy, his wife and seven of their
thirteen children on a day in 1892. A Count, Tolstoy
belonged to a noble family whose name has been traced
back to Ivan Tolstoy, a provincial governor during the reign
of Ivan the Terrible in the 16th century. It was at the Tolstoy
family estate, Yasnaya Polyana, just over 200 kilometres
south of Moscow, that the great writer produced most of
his works.
J\
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
MY YEARS WITH TOLSTOY
.
7 May
Tolstoy praised some of Schiller's work, and Goethe's shorter
poems and his Introduction to Faust. But he said that the
second part of Faust was nonsense, and that he didn't
understand a word of it, although he is as old as Goethe was
when he wrote it. In his own old age, he said, he appreciated
clarity and simplicity more and more and shied away from
mysticism.
18 May
Tolstoy: "The old order is on the way out, and with it, the
passivity and forbearance of the Russian people."
21 May
[A musical evening]... At about half-past-eleven, Tolstoy
took a glass of lemon water and went off to his room, smiling
at the singing and the dancing. Each time he heard a new
dance, he came out again to watch. Obviously delighted, he
joined in the singing. He once told me that if he had not been
a writer, he would have been a dancer.
13 August
Tolstoy told me about a talk he had this morning with a
couple of ragamuffin revolutionaries who were passing
through. "These young people «bave more to say than the
newspapers," he said. "It was useful to have a chat with
them. It's quite clear to me now that the government will have
to give in to all the revolutionaries' demands. A new Duma
should be convened without delay. Things can't get any
worse than they are at the moment. The people are in a state
of ferment, and the government is just trying to hold them in
check. A new government will soon emerge from amongst
the revolutionaries. The present government can survive
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
On the occasion of Tolstoy's eightieth birthday in 1908, the
Moscow Literacy Society decided to open a library for the
people of the village near to his estate. Tolstoy took a keen
interest In the project and supervised the choice of books.
On the day the library was opened the camera recorded
two informal glimpses of the great writer inold age. Left, he
is seen marching sturdily through the snow on his way to
the inaugural celebrations. Below, later in the day he stands
outside the newly-opened library surrounded by a group of
readers of all ages.
Photo A J. Saveliev © Tolstoy Museum, Moscow
Photo V.G. Chertkov © Tolstoy Museum, Moscow
(there's no knowing what the Revolution will lead to) only if it
purifies itself and cleanses itself from sin."
21 September
Tolstoy: "The Revolution has done a lot of good, as far as
education and the circulation of books are concerned."
17 October
Tolstoy: "Herzen (5) there's a writer who was hidden from
the Russians for a long time, but who has come to the sur¬
face. Herzen is an example of how a sincere, intelligent man
becomes a progressive. He went off to the West, thinking he
(5) Alexander Herzen (1812-1870) was a Russian writer, publicist and revolutio¬
nary who lived as a political exile in Western Europe from 1847 until his death,
witnessing the revolutionary events of 1848. His works were banned in Russia
before the Revolution of 1905-1907, but circulated clandestinely throughout the
country.
would find that things were ordered better there. But what he
saw during the revolutions disillusioned him with the Western
system, and he came to place all his love and hope in the Rus¬
sian people. Rightly or wrongly, that's where his hope lay. He
could serve as an example to Russian politicians, and save
them from making the same mistake of being attracted to
Western forms.
"People expect our own Revolution to give the same results
as the French one. But they should bear in mind that even if
that happened, nothing would come of it. What we must wait
for is a bigger, deeper upheaval in people's consciences, a
religious awakening. Perhaps all the horrible things that are
happening will bring people to their senses and make them
understand that they can't go on living this way; but the
Cadets'- (6) programmes won't do that. What is needed is
something completely new."
(6) The Constitutional Democrat Party.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
MY YEARS WITH TOLSTOY
1907
19 January
Tolstoy: "To portray things in their entirety, the bad side of
things as well as the good, that's where the artist's task is dif¬
ficult and art is hard."
14 February
Tolstoy: "The only time to speak up in public is when your
words are better than silence."
27 February
Tolstoy: "A good woman is better than the best of men; but a
bad woman is worse than the worst."
4 March
Tolstoy: "The Japanese have outstripped the English and the
Americans; in the space of a few years, they have acquired all
the trappings of Western civilization. In some ways they have
gone even further. That just shows how very easy Western
civilization is to assimilate."
21 March
Tolstoy: "Dostoevsky was not as refined as Turgenev, he was
serious. He went through a lot, and spent a lot of time
thinking things over. And he knew how to resist playing to
the gallery."
9 April
Tolstoy said that when he heard people say that his work was
productive, he was pleased, although he ought not to be.
"Moses did not reach Canaan that's the way things
happen."
15 April
Tolstoy once said that every thought had its own trajectory,
rising to a point of brilliance and then growing pale. The time
for writing it down was when it reached the zenith. And that
is what he does. He keeps his notebook handy at all times in
his pocket during the day and on his bedside table at night.
He doesn't mind getting up as many as a half a dozen times
during the same night to light the candle and jot down the
ideas that come into his head.
25 April
Tolstoy: "A wise man in China was once asked whether there
was a single word that contained the possibility of human
happiness. 'Yes,' he replied, 'the word Shu, which means: do
not do to others what you would not want done to yourself."
26 April
This morning G. and S. played one of Mozart's sonatas with
some marvellous variations, then Schubert, and finally Beet¬
hoven's Kreutzer Sonata. They played well, calmly and with
simplicity. G. and S. weren't performing tonight; they didn't
get excited, but just played, and better than they do when
they are on stage. Tolstoy smiled with delight; once or twice
he clapped his hands. He liked the Mozart variations very
much, and best of all, the Beethoven. Afterwards, he de¬
clared that he had never heard the Kreutzer Sonata played
so well. The first part, he said, was pure Beethoven, grandi¬
ose and with a tragic, passionate tone. The second part was
melodious and simple, more in the manner of Mozart.
Later, he said that he knew and admired the artistic detail in
Homer and The Arabian Nights, and in certain Russian folk¬
tales.
28 April
Tolstoy asked for the scene from Victor Hugo's Les Miséra¬
bles where Jean Valjean meets the Bishop to be read to the
schoolchildren (7).
(7) Many years earlier, Tolstoy had opened a school for peasant children at Yas¬
naya Polyana.
"I can't do it," he said. "It moves me too much. The story
tugs at my heart-strings I can't read it."
17 May
Tolstoy: "Here I am, 80 years old, learning from schoolboys
how to write short sentences..."
22 May
Tolstoy: "I place Christ in the same class of men as [the Stoic
philosopher] Epictetus."
10 June
Tolstoy said that it was better to be old than young. He was
80 years old, he said, and only just beginning to live peace¬
fully, and things grew better every year. Youth was a time of
excitement, self-accusation, envy, passion. All that disap¬
peared with age.
Pointing to the candle on the table, he said: "It shines quite
naturally, without trying. It's the same with men, when they
improve themselves they unwittingly cast light all around
them. Things are so arranged that whatever a man does to
himself, he does to others."
When he was asked if it was true that night-time was really
the best time for writing poetry, he replied: "No, poetic acti¬
vity is the most intense activity of all."
24 June
We drank tea on the terrace, and talked about Dostoevsky.
Tolstoy recalled Taine's statement that Dostoevsky was the
world's most outstanding writer. He himself regretted that
Dostoevsky had worked so hurriedly, without correcting what
he wrote. In his novels, the first chapter was always the best
and contained everything. The rest was watery stuff.
S. said that wasn't true in every case. It wasn't true, for
example, as far as his best novel. The Brothers Karamazov,
was concerned.
Tolstoy retorted that The Brothers Karamazov was one of
Dostoevsky's poorest novels. His best novel was Crime and
Punishment, and its first chapter was the best. Tolstoy went
on to say that he blamed Dostoevsky for opening the door to
the "decadent" school of writers. Dostoevsky was a pas¬
sionate man who wrote about passionate subjects, but the
decadent writers who came after him were insincere.
25 June
Talking about the school, Tolstoy said that yesterday he had
introduced the children to some difficult bits of philosophy,
explaining to them, for example, that just as a leaf stripped
from a twig was torn from the whole tree, so an angry man
alienated himself not only from the person with whom he was
angry, but from everybody.
26 June
At ten o'clock this morning, the workers' children from the
schools across the river at Tula arrived with their teachers
from Kozlovka. There were 850 of them in allwe had been
expecting 350...
Tolstoy took the boys down to the Voronka river to bathe,
and joined with them in games and gymnastics and wrestling-
matches.
27 June
Tolstoy talked about "Grandpa" Islenyev. How frankly he
speaks about his relatives! The Tolstoys have absolutely no
family secrets, and hide nothing from their friends, or even
from their house servants. Instead of seeking to justify their
shortcomings and failures, they talk about them so objec¬
tively and in such a way that they might be discussing other
people.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
1 él/-^A £?
II |
. T» i» . IBA
mw mM WF
mT VMm\\
P
Tolstoy was not only a great
writer for adults, but also a
noted educationist who loved
children. He was a captivating
teller of children's stories. Left,
he entertains two of his
grandchildren with his version
of an old popular fable. In 1859
he started a school at Yasnaya
Polyana where for some time
he taught his own children and
those of the local peasants. In
the 1870s he published two
spelling books and a Russian
reading course containing
fables and stories as well as
simple and attractively written
essays on physics and the
natural sciences.
Between 1889 and 1891, crop
failures caused widespread
food shortages and famine in
Russia. "The day before
yesterday," Tolstoy noted in a
letter, "I visited one village
where nine families owned
only a single cow; today I was
at another where everyone
lives on charity..." To alleviate
the widespread hardship
Tolstoy organized canteens,
donating large sums himself
and collecting contributions
from others. In two years he
collected over 140,000 roubles,
enough to feed 9,000 persons a
day. Left, Tolstoy and his
co-workers examine lists of
the needy.
Tolstoy's vigour was legendary
and even at the age of 80 he
would spend hours on end in
the saddle, riding through
fields and forest on Delir, his
favourite mount.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
MY YEARS WITH TOLSTOY
Y.
27 August
At tea-time we talked about the two summer vacationers over
in Kozlovka-Zaseka, who are going about in their motor-cars
(the first in the district), and frightening the. horses.
Tolstoy: "The way civilization is moving at present material
but not moral progress is not at all promising. If human well-
being was the real issue, there wouldn't be any motor-cars.
Bringing up horses from foals, breaking them in, that gives a
lot of pleasure. But when there is moral progress our way of
life motor-cars, horses and the restwill change. What is
most important at the moment is that moral and material
progress should go hand in hand; when that happens, the
material conditions of everything will change. In what way?
Impossible to say."
2 September
Tolstoy talked about the letter he received yesterday from the
peasant Novikov, and how it revealed an awareness of the
growing needs of the people. The meeting today at
Chertkov's had shown him that there was the same aware¬
ness throughout the peasantry.
"How could it be otherwise?" he went on. "Ermilin, a peasant
here at Yasnaya Polyana, had four grown-up sons who were
all married to fine girls. The farm had five three-horse teams.
Then the sons divided everything up between them. Their
wives had children, and in their turn the children divided up
the farm. The fields got smaller and smaller, and they got rid
of all the hired hands except one. The old foundations of
family life fell apart, and there was nothing to put in their
place. Who would have thought, thirty years ago, that we
should be beaten in a war with Japan, and that a peasant like
Novikov would one day be writing a letter without a single
grammatical mistake, quoting Marx (relevantly, by the way,
and not just to show off his learning), and writing so power¬
fully?"
7 September
Tolstoy: "Too much polishing, and you spoil things. There's a
limit to the expressibility of ideas. You have a new thought,
an interesting one. Then, as you try to perfect it, it ceases to
be new and interesting, and loses the freshness with which it
first occurred to you. You're spoiling it."
12 September
Tolstoy said that the time for loving is the present; but people
are so busy looking ahead that they forget the present.
18 September
Tolstoy: "It's a bad thing to seek to impress. A true artist
writes what he considers necessary, and doesn't bother
wit.h the effect. But the temptation exists. The idea that it is
possible to influence people should be avoided like the
plague."
25 September
"What is the most important thing in art?" Tolstoy asked.
"Sincerity? Truth?" He provided his own answer: "The most
important thing in art is a sense of measure."
8 October
Tolstoy said that revolutionaries were obviously superior to
conservatives of all kinds and to people who thought that one
could go on living as in the past. The old order cannot con¬
tinue, he said, peoples grow up, just like individuals. It's im¬
possible to turn back the clock.
20 December
Tolstoy: "In my Cycle of Reading for children, I've put some¬
thing about love for animals. It's natural for children to love
animals on the one hand, and yet on the other hand to tor¬
ment them. It is very important to lead them in the direction
of love.
1908
5 January
H.A. is scandalized that Tolstoy should fail to appreciate
Dante.
Tolstoy: "Raphael, Beethoven, Shakespeare, Dante,
Goethe none of them come up to what I expect of art. But
personally and I'm ashamed to admit this I'm very fond of
them."
25 April
Tolstoy: "Any peasant you talk to will speak of the same
thing: the injustice in the present distribution of land. There's
a big change among the people, I feel it. There's a general
feeling of discontent."
17 May
Talking about the revolutionaries, Tolstoy said that they had a
certain arrogance: "My Party will put things right", they say.
But one thing was certain, evil made them sincerely
indignant.
5 June
All yesterday was spent in reading Vivekananda. Tolstoy said:
"There is one chapter, written with great talent, which justi¬
fies non-resistance to evil". Tolstoy also said that he was
reading a biography of Pushkin and some of his poems.
"What bad luck that two extraordinarily talented men, the like
of whom are pot born every century, Pushkin and Lermontov,
should both be killed in duels." Later, he said that he prefer¬
red Pushkin's prose writing.
29 June
Tolstoy: "If one thing still frightens me, it's the idea of being
born in a palace, rather than a slum. Life is a process of
liberation liberation of the essential spiritual principle that
exists in the jailbird as in everybody. And that's where we
should be directing our energies, not to speculation about the
spheres, or what will happen to our souls. Spiritual liberation
is what is most important; you'll find that the same thing is
said everywhere."
1 July
Tolstoy expressed no definite view on the matter, but he did
not dismiss the possibility that, one day, there would be a lan¬
guage common to all men. His words conveyed the feeling
that this would be a step towards understanding and peace
among nations.
1909
14 June
Tolstoy: "Freedom of conscience... A conscience that is not
free is as unthinkable as a flame that does not burn."
27 June
Tolstoy: "I read this phrase in Prugavin [a Russian
journalist] : 'When the storm of revolution blew across Rus¬
sia...'. Oh, yes, the storm has blown over, at least as far as
outward appearances are concerned. The old order has been
strengthened, and for a long time to come, just as it was after
the French Revolution. But what seems most important to me
is that the events have left their mark on a hundred million
Russians; they have aroused the people. I still get letters from
peasants, asking 'Is there anything to hope for?' They are
waiting and hoping for something."
8 August
Tolstoy: "It is strange how little the past or the future matter,
as one grows old. One lives for the present."
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
21 August
Tolstoy: "If I had created human beings, I would have
arranged things so that they were born old, and grew
steadily younger, The appealing characteristics of children are
simplicity, naivete and truthfulness; and the greatest of
these is truthfulness."
25 October
Tolstoy: "I'm interested in Bernard Shaw. He's very witty and
original, one of the best modern writers."
1910
14 January
Tolstoy: "I have been thinking of those writers I know of
three, Pushkin, Gogol and Dostoevsky for whom moral
questions were important. Pushkin died young but he
thought about them seriously. Lermontov also died young
and was concerned about moral problems."
22 April
Tolstoy said that he had decided to write for the cinemato¬
graph.
29 July
Tolstoy: "Nowhere is the failure of Christianity as it is taught
by the Churches more evident than in the behaviour of the
Europeans in their colonies."
26 August
Tolstoy: "There's nothing like Robinson Crusoe for teaching
children the work involved in making the things they use. It's
a very fine story."
23 September
Tolstoy went for a ride. What steep slopes he gallops up and
down, what dangerous places he goes through, across half-
rotten bridges and along the edge of precipices! He rides
straight through a thicket of young trees, bending to pass
under the low branches. His horse suddenly shies, but on he
goes, galloping and trotting! I'm not very heavy, I enjoy riding
and I have taken plenty of exercise in my time. I'm 43 years
old, and Tolstoy is 82, but I'm hard-pressed to put on such a
show as he does, and I can't keep up with him. My horse and
I nearly break our necks. What a horseman!
6 October
Tolstoy: "Nourishment, torment and instruction-
one gets from work."
-that's what
11 October
Madame Tolstoy told me that when Vanechka (8) died in
1895, Tolstoy slumped down on the sofa and said: "It's a
hopeless situation. You see, I thought that of all my children
he was the only one who could continue my work after me."
25 October
Tolstoy was talking about the huge quantities of books being
printed; he said that it had been calculated that if children
continued to be born at the present rate and if fewer of them
died, men would before long be standing shoulder to shoul¬
der on the earth. In the same way books would soon form a
pile reaching up to the sky if so many continued to be pub¬
lished. It was important, therefore, to select the best.
(8) Tolstoy's youngest son, who died of scarlet fever at the age of seven.
Text © Copyright "Literaturnoe Nasledstvo"
A.M. Gorky Institute of World Literature of
the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences, Moscow, U.S.S.R.
Tolstoy died on 20 November 1910. Top: the
peasants who had been his friends bear his coffin
to Yasnaya Polyana, followed by an immense
crowd. He was laid to rest in a simple grave on
the edge of a ravine beneath the trees of the
dense forest of Stary Zakaz (above). As children,
Tolstoy and his brothers had roamed the forest in
search of a legendary "green stick" on which the
secret of happiness and goodness was carved.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
TOLSTOY
THE
STRUGGLE
TOWARDS
THE LIGHT
by Victor B. Shklovsky
T
time.
iHE greatness of a writer is not always
perceived at once. Familiarity, ab¬
sorption and assimilation all take
When Olenin, the young hero of
Tolstoy's early novel The Cossacks, first
sees the mountains of the Caucasus, after
his long journey across Russia from Mos¬
cow, their misty grandeur dawns upon him
slowly. His growing awareness is some¬
thing the reader shares:
"All 'he could make out was something
grey and white and fleecy: try as he would,
he could discover nothing beautiful about
these mountains of which he had read and
heard so much. Mountains and clouds
appeared alike to him, and he began to sus¬
pect that the special beauty of snowy
peaks, of which he had so often been told,
was as much a figment of the imagination
as the music of Bach, or love, in neither of
which did he believe and so he gave up
looking forward to the mountains. But
early next day, awakened in his post-chaise
by the freshness of the air, he glanced
casually to the right. The morning was
crystal clear. Suddenly he saw, at what
seemed to him at first glance to be about
VICTOR BORISOVICH SHKLOVSKY, Soviet
critic and historian of literature, is the author of
biographies of Tolstoy and Dostoevsky as well
as a number ofnovels including The Sentimental
Journey (1923).
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Above, Tolstoy and his friend the Russian historical painter llya
Efimovich Repin (1844-1930), whose work he greatly admired. Repin
illustrated several books by Tolstoy and executed several portraits of
him during visits to Yasnaya Polyana. Repin's reputation rests on
powerful, dramatic compositions such as his famous painting The
Volga Boatmen (below), today in the Russian Museum, Leningrad.
This work has been seen as a symbolic depiction of the fettered
Russian people under the Tsarist regime, dragging their chains
behind them.
twenty paces away, gigantic pure white
masses with gentle curves and fantastical
airy summits minutely outlined against the
distant sky. When he realized the distance
between himself and them and the sky, and
the whole immensity of those mountains,
and their infinite beauty, he feared lest it
prove to be a mirage or a dream. He gave
himself a shake, but the mountains were
still there."
The birth of mountains is a primitive
affair. The earth's crust splits and heaves ;
deep fires thrust layers of rock into the cold
sky. The mountains drink deeply from the
surrounding clouds. Snow falls. The sun
shines. Torrents burst from the deep blue
shadows on their flanks. They are part of
the earth, the mountains part of the old
earth that man has always known. And yet
their presence comes as a surprise.
A great man is a simple man, but one
who has assumed the contradictions of his
age and come to terms with them, sharp¬
ening rather than blunting their edge.
Working on Dead Souls, in 1844, Gogol
wrote to his close friend, the critic Annen-
kov: "Outstanding people are not those
who see something that others do not see,
and who are surprised that they alone
should see it; the only people who can be
called outstanding are those who see
everything that everybody else sees, but
who put two and two together so that they
see what nobody else sees, and are no lon¬
ger surprised that others should be so
blind."
In great men, mankind sees a reflection
of itself, but in an uplifted and enlightened
state. A great man is a product of the
people's suffering.
In Russia, the events of 1905-1907 had
sounded the death knell of the old order.
The country's contradictions had become
acute. But the gathering storm of protest
still did not break.
And yet, slowly, the mountains were
emerging. In 1910, Tolstoy wrote: "With
the Revolution, our Russian people sud¬
denly awoke to the injustice of their situa¬
tion. It was the story of the emperor's new
clothes; the Revolution was the child who
cried 'the emperor has no clothes!' It op¬
ened the people's eyes to an intolerable
untruth, and after that, the people under¬
stood. Their eyes can never be closed
again."
The emperor had no clothes... And with
the unmasking of the Tsar came awareness
of other injustices in the ownership of
land, in the army, in the red-tape of official¬
dom, in the marriage bond, and in spurious
"science" which profited only the rich.
This new understanding came as a revela¬
tion, and laid the foundations of a new art.
In an article on Tolstoy, Lenin wrote: "Illu¬
minated by Tolstoy's genius, this period
which paved the way to revolution, in a
country still under the yoke of serfdom,
was to stand out as a new landmark in the
artistic development of all mankind."
With Tolstoy, too, human psychology
came to be seen in a new light. Where ear¬
lier writers had explained men's actions as
a product of their thoughts and their envi¬
ronment, he dug deep into the thinking
process itself, revealing the conditions and
contradictions of what Chernyshevsky
called "the dialectic of the spirit".
Tolstoy did not believe that the world lay
beyond the grasp of the mind. On the con¬
trary, and whether he was writing about
the present or the past, he took events
which at first glance seemed common¬
place, fed them through the prism of his
consciousness and experience, and re¬
vealed them in their true colours. The result
was a world cleansed of all ordinariness,
refreshed, beautiful and like Olenin's
Caucasus crystal clear.
The mountains are high, and the paths
into them are wearisome. Familiarity with
them takes time. The ancients believed that
they were the footstools of the gods, and
built temples on their topmost peaks.
In his old age, the contradictions Tolstoy
had laid bare sometimes frightened him; it
was then that he turned towards God for
shelter. But at times Tolstoy's thought
went beyond the bounds of his faith in
God, which, indeed, he had put in question
on many occasions.
On 2 September 1909, he wrote in his
diary: "During the night, towards morning,
there came over me a sort of coldness, like
nothing I have ever felt before a feeling of
doubt about everything, especially about ,
God, and about whether my understanding |
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
k of the sense of life is right. I could hardly
credit that I had had this experience, nor
could I recover the faith by which I was
living and had always lived."
On 18 December, he wrote: "Life in its
madness becomes increasingly incompre¬
hensible, and to express the sense one
gives to it is quite impossible."
Six days later, he wrote: "I saw in a
dream the negation of God, and the objec¬
tions that could be raised to my idea of
non-violence as a precondition of a better
life."
In Gorky's reminiscences of Tolstoy,
compiled from notes of their conversations
together, there is the following entry:
"I was struck by a strange saying in the
diary he gave me to read: 'God is my
desire'. When I returned it to him today, I
asked him what he meant."
'An unfinished thought', he said, screw¬
ing up his eyes as he looked at the page. 'I
must have wanted to say God is my
desire to grasp what he is... No, not that...'
He laughed, rolled up the notebook and
thrust it into the pocket of his smock. His
relations with God are indefinite, some¬
times they remind me of 'two bears in one
lair'."
In his refusal of what had gone before,
and in his struggle towards the absolute
light, in his rejection of the past, and his
search for a new path that the entire people
would understand, Tolstoy achieved great¬
ness, and emerged in his grandeur as a
snow-covered mountain range emerges
from the plain.
He placed the human soul within men's
grasp, and, drawing on ancient sources,
discovered a new truth, and a new beauty.
Leaving the home of his ancestors,
leaving his friends and family and turning
his back on their faith, he acquired a new
understanding of the world a world he
could not change, because to do so re¬
quired a new struggle.
He stood on the frontier of a new land,
which he had seen, but could not enter.
Tolstoy's departure from Yasnaya
Polyana was not the flight of an old man
into the cold dampness of an alien world. It
was the conscious decision of an artist to
transcend feelings of compassion for those
close to him, and to make a clean break
with all that had gone before.
Victor B. Shklovsky
The quotation from The Cossacks is from Rosemary
Edmonds' translation, published in 1960 as a Penguin
Classic. © Penguin Books Ltd., Harmondsworth, U.K.
Photo © APN, Pans
In October 1900 Leo Tolstoy welcomed to Yasnaya Polyana the young writer Maxim Gorky
whose talent he admired and whose great literary future he foresaw. The visit left a
profound impression on Gorky. "I looked upon the old man," he wrote later, "and saw a
fantastic creative force. The immensity of his stature is quite unbelievable and the vigour
of his mind is stupendous. So remarkable is he that nothing like him would seem to exist
anywhere in the world." Gorky added that it was a gloomy autumn day and that as
Tolstoy led him to the riverside near to a clump of birches, the old man tenderly caressed
the trees with his hand.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE MOTHER I The spiritual heir
of Sri Aurobindo
by Emmanuel Pouchpa Dass
Photos © Sri Aurobindo Ashram, Pondicherry, India
Above, The Mother with her spiritual master, the great
Indian philosopher Sri Aurobindo. Right, as a young
woman during a visit to Algeria in the early years of this
century when she was starting to become aware of the
vocation that would take her to work with Sri Aurobindo
15 years later.
EMMANUEL POUCHPA DASS of India is
Director of Unesco's Division of Cultural
Studies.
THIS year, the centenary of the birth
of "the Mother" is being celebrated
in India. An outstanding and much
revered figure, she was the closest disciple
and direct spiritual heir to Sri Aurobindo,
the great Indian philosopher whose teach¬
ing has had a profound spiritual and moral
influence on modern India.
She was born Mirra Alfassa on 21
February 1878, in Paris, where her parents
had recently settled. Her father, Maurice,
who came from Adrianople in Turkey, was
a mathematician and banker. Her mother,
Mathilde Ismaloun, a native of Alexandria
in Egypt, was a strong-minded woman for
whom religion was nothing but superstition
and weakness and anything to do with ima¬
gination was a waste of time.
Mirra lived in Paris with her parents until
her marriage at the age of 19 and received a
rather strict and austere upbringing.
She enjoyed playing tennis (and con¬
tinued to do so until she was 80), but her
main loves were music, poetry and above
all painting. She practised the piano several
hours a day, yet still found time for painting
and poetry, to the dismay of her mother,
who had pinned great hopes on her daugh¬
ter and feared she would fritter away her
life. Ideas for poems would come to her in
her sleep, and she would get up in the
middle of the night to jot them down on
paper.
In 1897, when she was 19, she married
the painter Henri Morisset, and got to
know artists of the older generation such
as Claude Monet, Auguste Renoir, Edgar
Degas, Alfred Sisley and Paul Cézanne,
and the sculptor Auguste Rodin, as well as
younger painters like Paul Signac, Georges
Rouault, Maurice de Vlaminck, Georges
Braque, Henri Matisse and Pablo Picasso.
Mirra lived in the world of artists until
1908, when she and her husband sepa- >
rated. This was a period of great spiritual f
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
> intensity. Much later in life, she recalled a
visit to Fontainebleau:
"No one had ever told me about medita¬
tion, or how to meditate. I sat down under
the trees and felt a great sense of inner
calm and concentration ; I lost all sense of
the outside world and felt in harmony with
the trees: I was very happy."
Mirra's undoubted gifts enabled her to
discover unaided the wisdom of the ancient
philosophers. She possessed that quality
that Sri Aurobindo described in the fol¬
lowing terms: "Sense is fundamentally not
the action of the physical organs, but the
contact of consciousness with its objects."
By a curious coincidence, it was pre¬
cisely in 1904, at a time when Mirra, then
26, was beginning her systematic explora¬
tion of the various levels of consciousness,
that Sri Aurobindo began the serious study
of yoga. But it was not until 10 years later
that they actually met.
Through a process of experimentation.
Mirra soon discovered what the Vedic Ris¬
his (1) had found out thousands of years
before, secrets that Sri Aurobindo was
himself beginning to unravel through self-
mastery and a methodical exploration of
every level of consciousness. The Rishis
had discovered what they termed enigmati¬
cally, "a certain Fourth". This was a new
world that Sri Aurobindo called "the supra-
mental", a possible fourth state of Matter,
a future state where Matter does not die. A
different kind of Matter, perhaps, or a dif¬
ferent vision of the same Matter.
In the course of her spiritual experimen¬
tation, Mirra succeeded in analysing the
mechanisms of many religious, social and
political systems. It was almost as if she felt
the need to exhaust every possible alterna¬
tive. Later she would insist on the need to
escape from what she called "the prison of
age-old habits". But at that time she still
lacked any experience of speculative philo¬
sophy.
This she hoped to acquire when, in 1910,
she married Paul Richard, whom she had
met two years earlier. With her new hus¬
band she set off for India, a vast sub¬
continent as yet unknown to her.
On 19 March 1914, she walked up the
steps leading to the large white verandah of
the house in Pondicherry where Sri Auro¬
bindo and his first followers lived. He was
expecting her. Although they had never
met before, each of them felt a sense of
recognition.
"Though there may be thousands of
human beings plunged in deepest igno¬
rance". Mirra wrote next day, "the man we
saw yesterday is here on earth and his pre¬
sence alone is proof that the day will come
when darkness will be turned into light."
(1) Rishi: the term refers chiefly to the authors of the
hymns of the Rigveda (between 1500 and 800 B.C.),
which were thought to have been revealed by Brahma,
and which make up the most important of the sacred
Vedic texts.
Sri Aurobindo was born in Calcutta on
15 August 1872. His father, a surgeon,
gave him an English education. After
studying classics at Cambridge, Sri Auro-
b'ndo returned to India in 1893 and became
a teacher, first in Baroda, in western India,
then in Calcutta. At this time he
joined the revolutionary movement whose
purpose was to free India from British
domination. He became involved in a
secret organization that would be ready,
when the time was ripe, for an armed up¬
rising. Then in 1906, he began to preach
the nationalist cause with missionary fer¬
vour in the columns of the Calcutta daily
newspaper Bande Mataram.
Aurobindo's activities caused him to be
arrested and held in solitary confinement in
Alipur prison on a conspiracy charge. After
a long-drawn-out trial, he was finally
acquitted and released in May 1909. During
his spell in prison, he experienced a mysti¬
cal revelation of the divine omnipresence,
which made him decide to turn his back on
politics and retire to Pondicherry in south¬
ern India.
Aurobindo said at the time: "The advo¬
cates of action think that everything can be
put right by an ever renewed upsurge of
human intellect and energy. The present
state of the world, after a development of
the intellect and a stupendous output of
energy for which there is no parallel in his¬
tory, is signal proof of the emptiness of the
illusion under which they labour. Yoga
takes the stand that it is only by a change
of consciousness that the true basis of life
can be discovered; from within outward is
indeed the rule."
The first issue of the philosophical jour¬
nal Arya appeared on 15 April 1914. The
journal continued to appear until January
1921 and in its pages Sri Aurobindo was to
publish the greater part of his philosophical
work.
Meanwhile, Mirra was still reaching for
the key to transformation, a way of inven¬
ting new modes of consciousness and
perception in other words the path to the
súpramental. As her spiritual Odyssey pro¬
gressed. Mirra was gaining assurance as a
thinker. This can be seen in the vivid imag¬
ery and lively language she employed in her
Conversations and in her teaching at the
Ashram, the international community she
and Sri Aurobindo founded at Pondicherry.
She taught that our first step along the
road to self-perfection is to become con¬
scious of ourselves, of the various parts of
our being and of their respective activities,
in order to become aware of the origin of
the impulses we experience and of the
various reactions and urges that stir us to
action
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Dominique Darr, Pans
The Mother taking an evening class at the
Ashram, the international spiritual
community at Pondicherry which she
founded with Sri Aurobindo. Above, a
gathering of disciples at the Ashram,
which today has some 1,800 members.
Photo Vidyavrata Visharad © Sri Aurobindo Ashram, Pondicherry, India
View of Pondicherry showing (in foreground) the buildings
of the Ashram, where The Mother continued the work of
Sri Aurobindo after his death in 1950.
Right, a stamp issued
to commemorate the
centenary of the birth
of The Mother.
^21-278 «
«ft aTTfipit
SRI AUROBINDO
25 .
ASHRAM
This process, she said, "is a bit like
taking three or four different colours, put¬
ting them in water and mixing them to¬
gether. What you get is a greyish, indis¬
tinct and incomprehensible mixture. You
can't tell the red from the blue, or the
green, or the yellow. All these colours
mixed together come out as something of a
mess. So what you have to do first is sepa¬
rate the red, the blue, the yellow and the
green, and put each of them in its own
place."
"We are exposed to every conceivable
kind of influence good, bad, neutral,
dark, light it's all there, and in theory
each individual should act as a filter... In
the last resort, this is the reason for physi¬
cal existence.
"And it's a wonderful thing, people
don't realize what an infinite boon it is: the
universe is so arranged that there is a mass
of substances, ranging from the most
material to the highest form of
spiritualityall gathered together in what
we call an individual; yet still controlled by
a central will."
Thus it is only by subjecting all our inner
impulses to the strictest examination that
we can hope to create within ourselves an
unfailing power of discernment. At the
same time the external being must also
strive after perfection.
This process of inner discovery must also
be accompanied by mental development,
which the Mother defined in these terms:
"Mental development in its most complete
form involves the minutely detailed study
of all kinds of philosophies and ideas, get¬
ting inside systems of thought and fully
understanding them... Development, in the
sense of the realization that all ideas are
true, is followed by a realization that a
synthesis must be made... And that some¬
thing luminous and true lies beyond that
synthesis."
A group of followers had formed sponta¬
neously around Sri Aurobindo. But should
they first practise yoga and pursue their
own spiritual development and only then
turn their attention to other people?
Or should they immediately allow all those
with the same aspirations to join them, so
they could all march together towards the
same goal? Sri Aurobindo and Mirra chose
the second solution, for, as Aurobindo
said: "I am concerned with the earth, not
with worlds beyond for their own sake; it is
a terrestrial realization that I seek and not a
flight to distant summits."
From the founding of the Ashram on 24
November 1926, Sri Ai/robindo put the
Mother in charge and devoted himself to a
new enterprise. First of all, he sought the
transformation of consciousness, the tran
sition from mental man to spiritual man;
then physical transformation, the transition
from spiritual man to the gnostic being,
governed by the supramental.
Sri Aurobindo corresponded at length
with his followers but he appeared among
them only three times a year. The Mother,
however, saw them as often as possible:
she organized and took part in their various
activities, whether work or play, and
encouraged them to discover their inner
truth.
At one point in her life. Mirra noted that
she was putting such intense energy into
her inner activity that "sleep" became
impossible. "For more than a year, I jotted
everything down little things, a snatch of
conversation, an impressionand tried to
find a transition from one memory to an¬
other. At first, nothing much came out of
it, but after a time I was able, by starting
from the end, to trace all my "dreams"
back to the beginning of the night. It put
me in such a conscious, continuous state
that I ended up by not "sleeping" at all. My
reclining body was fast asleep, but my con¬
sciousness was not at all at rest."
The Ashram consisted at the start of only
a handful of disciples, but house after
house was gradually added, it grew larger,
and its inmates learned to be self-sufficient.
The community now numbers 1,800 people
CONTINUED PAGE 33
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
by Dragoljub Najman
Amajor international conference on
technical co-operation among de¬
veloping countries, to be held later
this year, promises to initiate a new phase
in the history of development policies. It is
being organized by the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP) and will
take place in Buenos Aires from 30 August
to 12 September.
Not that the idea of exchange of skills
and know-how between developing coun¬
tries is altogether new. For many years
experts from countries such as India or
Peru have participated in development pro¬
grammes elsewhere in the Third World,
and a number of Third World countries
have welcomed trainees from neighbouring
states. Experience has shown that such
exchanges are beneficial, and should be
promoted more systematically. It should
also be borne in mind that any change of
direction in the flow of technical assistance
will, necessarily have a bearing on the
establishment of the new international
economic order.
In recent years, recipient states, donor
states, and the secretariats of international
organizations have been increasingly criti¬
cal of the manner in which the technical
assistance necessary for their development
has been provided to the less privileged
countries.
For the most part, such assistance has
been provided by countries of the northern
hemisphere for those of the south and. has
taken the form of a package of grants,
scholarships, equipment and specialist
advice. The ingredients of the package
have been the same although the propor¬
tions may have varied. This package was
supposedly equally valid for a basically agri¬
cultural African country, for an already par¬
tially urbanized and industrialized country,
or for a country rich in mineral resources.
The first conclusion to emerge from the
current reappraisal of technical assistance
programmes is that the old procedures all
too often encouraged recipient states to
base their actions on concepts and approa¬
ches that were alien to their economic and
social situation and cultural traditions.
This led almost invariably to excessive
costs, both in financial terms and in terms
of effort. There would often be a difficult
period of adjustment, and sometimes the
"transplant" would be rejected and the
whole process would fail.
Consequently, strong efforts are now
being made to turn away from such pre-
Technical
co-operation
among developing
countries
Photos Patrick Waeles - Unesco
Television aids development
Photos on these pages show schoolchildren and trainee teachers taking part in an
educational television project organized by the Ivory Coast in collaboration with Unesco.
Right, student teachers learn TV production techniques; above, an audiovisual class; top
right, a practical exercise in modern maths. As part of a growing trend towards the
exchange of skills within the developing world, many developing countries have
expressed interest in this project as the possible foundation of a system of technical co¬
operation in educational television.
DRAGOLJUB NAJMAN, Unesco's Assistant
Director-General for Co-operation for Develop¬
ment and External Relations, is the author of
L'Enseignement Supérieur, Pour quoi faire ?
("What's the purpose of higher education ?")
published by Fayard, Paris, In 1974.
conceived models and to initiate and
encourage a form of development based
essentially on the natural, technical and
intellectual resources of the recipient coun¬
tries. This concept of development as an
"endogenous" process rooted in the histo¬
rical evolution of nations obviously pre¬
cludes any form of autarky. However,
everything imported from outside is
selected, reappraised and adapted to the
environment into which it has to fit.
Many developing countries and in
some cases developing regions as
well have a great deal in common as
regards their human resources, their clima¬
tic conditions and some aspects of their
social structure. This makes it easier for a
given country to adapt for its own use
ideas and methods which have proved suc
cessful in other parts of the world where
general conditions are comparable.
In addition to these technical factors,
whose importance is now recognized,
there are considerations of a more political
nature. These cannot be ignored, since
they reflect the evolution in the approach
of the United Nations system as a whole
resulting from the decisions of the 6th and
7th Extraordinary Sessions of the General
Assembly, which defined the role the
various states and organizations should
play in the establishment of a new inter¬
national economic order.
This new. order might be said to repre¬
sent a break from the existing type of
North-South economic relationship,
whieh, under conditions which still prevail.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
almost automatically favours countries
which possess capital, the most advanced
technology and the most highly developed
economic infrastructure and is detrimental
to those whose resources chiefly consist of
raw materials and cheap labour.
Although the most widely known aspect
of this break with the past remains a re¬
adjustment of the terms of trade aimed at
eliminating inequalities, it is also a fact that
increased trade can and must contribute to
the profound transformation of world eco¬
nomies which the notion of a new inter¬
national economic order implies.
Economic development can then be seen
more clearly in its twin role as both a bene¬
ficiary and an instigator of change : a bene¬
ficiary through the increasingly rapid accu¬
mulation of capital in the poorer countries,
which will be made possible by the intro¬
duction of more balanced North-South
trade; and an instigator through an
increase in the complexity and diversity of
trade-flows stemming from the rapid deve¬
lopment of many national economies, each
to buy and to sell on every
market.
Technical co-operation among deve¬
loping countries is thus seen as a corollary
of economic co-operation among these
same countries, which it carries over into
the field of technical and intellectual rela¬
tions. For some years now, this type of co¬
operation has formed part of the action of
Unesco, which, in all the spheres of its
competence, has sought to increase the
number of training, research, and cultural
centres at the regional level, and to
organize them into multidisciplinary and
interdependent networks. Such activities
are destined to play an even more impor¬
tant role in Unesco's work in the future.
The reason for emphasizing the multipli¬
city of flows is to bring out an important
aspect of technical co-operation seen in
this new light. This aspect is a natural
corollary of the tasks incumbent upon the
industrialized countries as part of the
establishment of a new international eco¬
nomic order, and underlines their conti¬
nuing importance. The fact is that the
development of co-operation among deve¬
loping countries will in no way relieve the
industrialized countries of the responsibili¬
ties entrusted to them by the international
community and which result from their
technological and economic predomi¬
nance.
The new international economic order
marks a step towards righting the scales of
justice, but it will remain meaningless
unless the industrialized countries make it
their duty to contribute as much, indeed
more, than they have done in the past to
this effort to restore a global equilibrium. It
is difficult to envisage the establishment of
co-operative relationships between devel¬
oping countries whilst at the same time
these countries remain in a position of eco¬
nomic, technological and intellectual
dependence upon those of the industrially
developed world. The internal contradic¬
tions arising from such a situation would
inevitably lead to extreme tension between
countries at different stages of develop
ment.
The evolution that the Conference pro- f
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
k poses to encourage will, then, tend to
replace the North-South bipolarity, which
is still very much the rule, by a North-
South-East-West multipolarity, of which
only the first signs can as yet be seen.
This multipolarity, based on a streng¬
thening of the autonomy of the developing
countries, will entail the pooling of the
increased capacities for production, and
research which make that autonomy pos¬
sible, in order to enable such countries to
take a more active part in the activities of
the international community.
For such changes to become feasible,
the institutional and technical foundations
of autonomous progress in developing
countries will have to be strengthened, just
as the regional bodies, whether inter¬
governmental or not, which deal with
financing, training, research and exchan¬
ges will also have to be developed and sti¬
mulated. As for the industrially developed
countries, they too should participate
fully it is in their own interest to do so in
the pooling of financial and technical
resources, and in the strengthening of
infrastructures^ which form the basis for
progress in developing countries.
Since the process of development inhe¬
rent in the notion of technical co-operation
among developing countries is first and
foremost an autonomous process, there is
reason to hope that this approach will have
a salutary effect on all the effortswhich
have hitherto been vain to reduce inequa¬
lities between nations. Furthermore, the
results of the increasing number of experi¬
ments and initiatives being carried out in
Third World countries will be more widely
known and more immediately comparable
with, and applicable to, situations else¬
where.
Thus there is reason to hope that this
increase in the number of exchanges will
not only speed up the processes of
research and development, but increase
the momentum of industrialization and
boost the growth of trade.
But other activities such as education,
communication and culture which are
equally important aspects of human pro¬
gress, have much to gain from the intro¬
duction of multipolar exchanges in place of
those favoured by historical circumstances
or by an interdependence based on
inequality. Up to now the door has, so to
speak, been only ajar; now it must be flung
wide open.
A number of examples of Unesco activi¬
ties in recent years illustrate the wide range
of possibilities opened up by technical co¬
operation among developing countries.
One of the most common characteristics
of these activities has been support for
training and research institutions, national
or otherwise, which play a major role and
have been able, through the assistance of
Unesco, to undertake operations on a
regional scale.
Here are two examples of technical co¬
operation in the world of communication.
In August 1977 the Asia Pacific Institute for
Broadcasting Development opened in
Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. Through the co¬
operation of Unesco and of the United
Nations Economic and Social Commission
for Asia and the Pacific (ESCAP), this
national institution has been given the
resources to serve the entire region, which
it now provides with general or specialized
training courses in every area of radio and
television news, as well as furnishing tech¬
nical advice and a consultancy service.
In Nairobi, Kenya, a centre for the
exchange of radio and television program¬
mes was opened in 1977 by the Union of
African National Radio and Television
Organizations, with the help of Unesco. It
helps not only to promote co-operation
among African radio and television organi¬
zations, but to reduce Africa's present
dependence on imported programmes.
Another example, this time from the
sphere of science, is the network of institu¬
tions in South-East Asia for co-operation in
the basic sciences, which has been active
since 1974 and is co-ordinating a pro¬
gramme of research and training for the
optimal use of natural products in develop¬
ment.
HE programme includes two
pilot schemes, one involving
the chemistry and the other the microbio¬
logy of natural products. They both com¬
prise training courses and practical work.
One of the industrialized countries, Japan,
is making an effective contribution to the
running of the network.
In Latin America, the Latin-American
Centre of Ph'ysics, a Unesco-backed inter¬
governmental organization, is contributing
to the regional development of physics
research; and other networks, some of
which enjoy the support of the United
Nations Development Programme (UNDP),
are in the process of being set up.
Of particular interest is the Intergovern¬
mental Océanographie Commission's Pro¬
gramme of Co-operative Investigations of
the Caribbean and Adjacent Regions,
which since 1976 has been not only co¬
ordinating scientific research in states bor¬
dering on the Gulf of Mexico, but endea¬
vouring to solve, through co-operation
among all participants, the problems of the
circulation of information and data, of the
education and training of specialists, and
of the pooling of facilities. It should be
noted that the participating states (1) are at
very different stages of development.
Another particularly significant example
is to be found in the field of education.
Unesco, UNDP, and a group of industrially
developed countries have, for the last ten
years, been helping the Ivory Coast govern¬
ment to develop a major pilot project for
educational television. This project forms
part of a broad range of activities involving
co-operation between Unesco and the
Ivory Coast, including educational planning
(1) Brazil, Colombia, Costa Rica, Cuba, the United
States, France, Guatemala, Guyana, Haiti, Jamaica,
Mexico, the Netherlands, Nicaragua, Panama, the
Dominican Republic, the United Kingdom, Surinam,
Trinidad and Tobago, the U.S.S.R., and Venezuela.
and the reform of junior secondary educa¬
tion, as well as educational television.
As many Member States showed inter¬
est in this project, the Ivory Coast govern¬
ment and Unesco decided to create the
conditions for a thorough and systematic
exchange of information about the situa¬
tion and evolution of educational television
in developing countries.
Preparations are already at an advanced
stage for an international seminar to be
held ,in December on technical co-
among developing countries, in
this field. It will provide people from the
developing world working in educational
television with an opportunity to exchange
ideas, to visit the Ivory Coast educational
television centre, and to lay the foun¬
dations of a system for the exchange of
information and experience.
Thus, whatever the levels of develop¬
ment of the countries concerned, there is
bound to be a transition from the notion of
technical assistance to the notion of techni¬
cal co-operation.
An increase in the number of co¬
operation centres, the consolidation of
their activities, a greater confidence felt by
each Third World country in its own élite
and in the élites of other countries with the
same experience all these factors should
enable these countries to carry greater
weight in the global volume of economic,
technical and intellectual exchanges.
What the Conference proposes to do is
work out a plan of action which will allow
the international community to reach
agreement on the kind of objectives to be
aimed at, on the tasks incumbent upon
states and organizations, on the various
phases of the undertaking, on the means to
be employed in order to set in motion or
accelerate the process destined to lend a
whole new dimension to international tech¬
nical co-operation.
The Conference will return to and dis¬
cuss in greater detail, at the level of the
whole United Nations family, arguments
which in some cases, like the notion of
endogenous development, already form
the basis of thinking in such essential docu¬
ments as Unesco's Medium-Term Plan;
and it is the hope of Unesco that the Con¬
ference will succeed in getting all United
Nations organizations to share its preoccu¬
pations. This of course implies that we
must be careful this time to avoid the pitfall
of "institutionalization", and never assume
that a problem has been solved just
because a new institution or body has seen
the light of day.
Moreover, the problem before us is one
not of sectoral development, but of a quali¬
tative change in our approach, in all the
areas of activity involving the United
Nations system.
It is up to each organization to draw the
necessary conclusions from the Con¬
ference, as regards both the content of its
programme and the way in which it pro¬
poses to implement it. This is a path that
Unesco, which can already point to several
instances of fruitful co-operation among
developing countries, will follow- with the
, greatest determination.
Drajoljub Najman
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
RETURN TO THE HOMELAND
(Continued from page 1 1)
exceptional expropriation measures, which
are scarcely ever resorted to except when
the public interest is at stake. Few coun¬
tries would feel able to justify the identifica¬
tion of the public interest (a notion which
would have to be redefined) with interna¬
tional cultural values.
But there is always the possibility that
privately owned works whose return is
desired by their country of origin may sur¬
face on the art market. Several states have
the right of pre-emption at public auctions
held on their territory which gives them by
law a prior claim over the rights of the
highest bidder, who receives compensa¬
tion. A system of bilateral agreements
could be envisaged, whereby the right of
pre-emption could be exercised to the
advantage of a state which has requested
the return of an invaluable part of its heri¬
tage. But in all other cases, if compulsion is
ruled out, there is no choice but to rely on
the good will of the owners.
When it comes down to it, the restitu¬
tion, loan or deposit of property, and the
technical co-operation that can facilitate
such action, will always depend on the
good will of owners, whether private or
public. It may be claimed that it is inge¬
nuous to bank on such qualities as intelli¬
gence or a sense of fairness, which do not
usually govern human relationships. But
such pessimism has already been belied on
numerous occasions.
The collaboration between Belgium and
Zaire is by no means an isolated case. In
1974, the National Museum of New Zea-
. land despatched, at its own expense, to the
National Museum and Art Gallery of Papua
New Guinea, a collection of valuable
ethnographic items it had acquired the
year before.
In the last few years, the Stockholm
Museum of Ethnography has established
working relationships with universities and
museums in Kenya, Tanzania and Sri
Lanka, in order to improve research and
conservation techniques and pave the way
for any necessary restitutions.
On two occasions, in 1959 and in 1976,
Harvard University in the United States
returned to the Mexican authorities hun¬
dreds of gold and jade objects discovered
during excavations on the Yucatan penin¬
sula at the turn of the century. Other price¬
less pre-Columbian items, acquired over 50
years ago by U.S. citizens, were also
recently returned to the national museums
of Panama and Guatemala by Harvard and
Pennsylvania Universities.
Lastly, there was the recent case of a
Japanese businessman who decided that
his prize possession, the 1,000-year-old
sword of a Sumatran king, complete with a
scabbard studded with gold, diamonds,
rubies and sapphires, should be returned to
Indonesiawhich only goes to show that
some private collectors at least are aware
of the need for restitution.
It is a pity that the many instances of pro¬
perty being returned in this way are given
very little publicity, because once an exam¬
ple is given the idea may catch on, with the
most fruitful results. However, the initia¬
tives of this kind that are known to have
been taken are already sufficiently nu¬
merous to suggest that the appeal made by
the Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, on 7 June 1978,
"for the return of an irreplaceable heritage
to those who created it" will be swiftly
heeded and will help to smooth out any
difficulties in negotiations which are still
only tentative. (See page 4).
His stirring appeal was addressed not
only to governments and public or private
institutions, but also to librarians, art gal¬
lery owners, journalists, critics, historians
and writers.
But it is to be hoped that the men and
women of today, and more particularly the
young people Mr. M'Bow had in mind
when he called on the help of educators,
are already aware that respect for works of
art should lead "wherever necessary to
^ their return to their homeland", and that
they understand "the affliction a nation can
suffer at the spoliation of the works it has
created." They may not themselves have
anything to return; but their support is
absolutely vital.
Georges Fradier
THE MOTHER' - SPIRITUAL HEIR OF SRI AUROBINDO
(Continued from page 29)
who wish to give their lives a spiritual
dimension. Its various activities, which are
organized by the members themselves,
range from weaving and spinning, to
farming, building, handicrafts and metal
work. A papermaking plant supplies the
needs of the community's printing presses
which publish works in thirteen languages.
Cultural activities include painting, sculp¬
ture, music and handicrafts.
The Ashram, then was, created just as
Sri Aurobindo wished, "with another
objective than that usually associated with
such institutions; not for the renunciation
of the world, but as a centre and a field of
practice for the evolution of another kind
and form of life, which would ultimately be
moved by a higher spiritual consciousness
and embody a greater life of the spirit."
Sri Aurobindo died in 1950, leaving the
Mother to carry on their common work
alone.
Two years later, the Sri Aurobindo Inter¬
national Centre of Education was founded:
it now provides education ranging from
kindergarten to university level based on
the so-called "free progress" method,
which was devised and defined by Sri
Aurobindo. Up until 1958, the Mother her¬
self took an active part in teaching there,
and gave pupils a grounding in French in
the course of her yoga lectures.
A tireless teacher, she continued to offer
guidance to the disciples, and to receive
visitors from all over the world. She used to
explain to her followers that whatever the
ideal they set themselves they would only
fully achieve it if they attained inner perfec¬
tion. She referred to what she called the
great "change of government", by which
she meant that mental government by the
intelligence should give way to spiritual
government by the consciousness a word
central to her and Aurobindo's thinking.
The Mother used to say that it was
impossible for any individual on earth as we
now know it, however great he might be,
to change the world single-handed, to
change creation as we know it, and to
achieve the superior truth of a new world.
She was convinced that only a group of
individuals (either in time, one after the
other, or in space, in the form of a commu¬
nity) could enable that truth to take shape
and to establish itself. Achievement obeys
all-embracing laws which reflect a certain
aspect of Eternity and the Infinite.
In 1968, at the age of 90, sensing that the
world was ready to experience and under¬
stand a new venture aimed at realizing the
unity of mankind, the Mother initiated
plans for a city in which men and women
would eventually be able to live according
to the ideals of Sri Aurobindo, and which
would be. called "Auroville" in his honour.
The Mother died on 17 November 1973, at
the age of 95.
E. Pouchpa Dass
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to
the editor
FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS
Sir,
One need not necessarily agree with Ms.
Thomson's objection to endorsement of
compulsory elementary education in the Uni¬
versal Declaration of Human Rights in order
to be in disagreement with Prof. Vasak's
analogy between compulsory primary edu¬
cation and the outlawing of slavery. ("Let¬
ters to the Editor", April 1978).
Certainly a libertarian argument can be
made against compulsory elementary educa¬
tion. An even stronger libertarian argument
exists in favour of voluntary slavery. Is it
seriously contended that the international
communities should outlaw voluntary sub¬
mission of priests, monks, nuns, and others
to the discipline of their Orders? Is it not a
human right for the individual freely to
decide to dedicate her or his labour freely
without hope of material reward to a cause
believed in? Just as the right to live does
include the right freely to choose to die, and
the right to marry does include the right
freely to choose celibacy, so does the right
not to be compelled to labour include the
right freely to donate one's labour.
Jeremiah S. Gutman
New York
Sir,
Prof. Vasak's reply to Sheila Thomson's
letter must not go unchallenged.
If a child needs medical attention it should
be provided, even though the child screams
"go away" and tries to spit out necessary
medicine. However, if an adult chooses to
let nature take its course then he or she is
entitled to do so.
In the same way a child is not mature
enough to understand how much it needs
education in the world and so its choice is
restricted until it becomes near-adult. Fur¬
thermore, compulsion is to ensure that a
child's own wish to attend school is not pre¬
vented by selfish guardians, or even by a
state's so neglecting its members that they
feel economically unable to leave the child at
school even if they wish. If it were simply a
case of "now or later" there would be less
justification for compulsion, but it is a fact
that once grown up without education it is
only rarely possible to "catch up", so that
those not able to follow traditional occupa¬
tions not requiring formal schooling will
become a permanently disadvantaged class.
However, it is important to acknowledge
that there is no requirement that it should be
"state" education; attempts to force chil
dren into state-run systems regardless of
their being able to obtain adequate educa¬
tion in other ways are a travesty of freedom,
and should at all times be condemned.
As for Prof. Vasak's statement, I deny that
anyone has the right to forbid me to be a
slave. They may say no one shall keep me as
a slavewhich will mean that, however I
may act vis-à-vis my master, the terms are
not recognized by the law where they con¬
flict with rights of free men. The result will
be virtually the same, but the difference is
significant.
Once we allow city, state, area or even
world government to define "freedom" in
terms unacceptable to the person suppo¬
sedly being "made free" then we are well on
the way to George Orwell's 1984. Unfortuna¬
tely, this trend of authority to "know best
what is good for us" is only too clear at pre¬
sent. One can only pray that it 'will get no
worse, as a tyrant convinced of his own vir¬
tue can be the worst sort of all.
E.R. Kermode
Bristol, U.K.
CLAIRVOYANCE?
OR A PUT-UP JOB?
Sir,
The Apollo 8 splashed down in the Pacific
merely two and a half miles from the point
where Jules Verne's imaginary space travel¬
lers came down more than a century earlier
(Unesco Courier, March 1978). The statisti¬
cal probability of such a near hit is about
1:7,000,000. (Approximately 140 million
square miles of the Earth are covered by
water.) The coincidence, therefore, cannot
be explained by chance and asks for an
explanation.
Your article interpreted it as a case of
"accurate prediction." Do you believe in
such clairvoyance? Or should we assume
that NASA thought it would be funny to
splash down exactly at Jules Verne's site?
Such a case of a self-fulfilling prophecy
would be even more fascinating.
Adriaan Kortlandt
Amsterdam,
The Netherlands
TURKISH DELIGHT
Sir,
At the secondary school at which I work, I
am responsible for a special language class
for non-French eleven-year-olds (Turkish,
Algerian, Moroccan and Portuguese chil¬
dren).
When, recently, I took copies of the Tur¬
kish and Arabic editions of the Unesco Cou¬
rier to the class, excitement was general.
Many of these children are literate in their
own language and each child attempted to
explain, in French, to his or her classmates
of different native tongue what your maga¬
zine has to say.
For me it was an unexpected and felicitous
use of the Unesco Courier.
Mademoiselle Renon
Saint-Claude, France
EDUCATION - A RE-THINK
Sir,
Thank you for the extremely interesting
articles on education for the under-sixes in
your May 1978 issue.
Although the colonial era is over, certain
consequences of it still remain, particularly in
the field of education. The developing coun¬
tries should not be copying European educa¬
tion systems and transmitting European
values. It is vital for these countries to be
given the means to resolve their develop¬
ment problems. It is essential, therefore, for
the role of education to be reappraised in this
context.
Children should be made aware of the pro¬
blem of development from the earliest age.
Many countries, in Africa especially, have
realized this and are developing new forms
of intensive technical instruction.
Michel Orliac
Viroflay, France
Sir,
Pre-school children certainly deserve the
attention they received in the May 1978 issue
of the Unesco Courier. In favourable sur¬
roundings they acquire the values associated
with Unesco before they begin school at five
or six. I know of a boy of four, living as one
of three children among four adults, who
must have thought about some of the con¬
versations he overheard. At various times,
without any prompting, he made such
remarks as:
"We have friends in other countries, don't
we? It would make a muddle of a war
wouldn't it!"
"When I grow up I'm going to collect all
the bombs and drop them in the middle of
the sea."
Although Unesco does not sponsor mar¬
riage bureaux it may be relevant to indicate
the width of his thinking and sympathy:
"When I grow up", he began on another
occasion, "I'm going to find all the lonely
mummies (women) and take them to the
lonely daddies (men) so they can get mar¬
ried."
The thinking, the formation of attitudes
which these remarks imply should be reco¬
gnized as being of even more importance
than early reading skills. If many children
made this start in life the world would be a
very different place, but parent education is
in its infancy or perhaps in its swaddling
clothes.
Nicholas Gillett
Bristol, U.K.
1776 AND 1917
Sir,
The July 1976 issue of the Unesco Courier
was entirely devoted to the bicentenary of
the United States. However, you did not see
fit to produce a special issue to mark the
anniversary of the most important event of
this century, the October Revolution of
1917.
Last year the sixtieth anniversary of this
event was celebrated by peoples everywhere
as well as by international organizations and
peace-loving states, at a time when the
action of the U.S.S.R. and its government is
of paramount importance for peace and the
development of harmonious relations in our
increasingly complex world.
Pedro J. Gutiérrez
Pinar del Río, Cuba
77?e Unesco Courier devoted its November
1967 issue to the U. S. S. R. on the occasion
of the 50th anniversary of the October Revo¬
lution.Editor.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Museums today..
...and tomorrow
This Unesco-sponsored study presents examples of the most
original, forward-looking and constructive ideas being applied in
the museum world today.
conservation of works of art
museum buildings
the museum and its visitors
selection and training of personnel
Prepared by Kenneth Hudson with assistance from an
international panel of museum directors and curators, with an
introduction by Georges Henri Rivière, Permanent Adviser to
the International Council of Museums (ICOM).
KENNETH HUDSON
MUSEUMS FOR THE 1980s
A SURVEY OF WORLD TRENDS
Foreword by Geofges Henri Riviere
Illustrated 190 pages 120 French francs
Co-published with Macmillan, London, who have
exclusive sales rights in the United States and the
United Kingdom
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch-
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Oue. H3H
1M7. CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade. DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahnr Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH Karger Buchhandlung. Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germermg/Munchen. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra, Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Václ u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvtùrosok Boltja, Nêpkoztarsasag utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson 8- Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7
Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub¬
Depots: Oxford Book Er Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish¬
ing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza
Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, At -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing tHouse, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, -
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martmus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned
Ant.), N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christ-church; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Sarah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mah'.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales IPVTI Ltd., 67-Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgránd 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rámistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 12-236.
TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen
Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sn, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok:
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Slam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S E.I., - and Government Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol.
- UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Station,
New York, N.Y. 10016. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
JULY 1978
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
Round Table sees
uncertain future for
world's children
What kind of world are we leaving to
our children?
A very uncertain one, concluded a
group of eminent personalities which
met in a round-table discussion on this
theme at Unesco headquarters in June.
Unesco Director-General Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow set the tone for the
discussion when he declared that the
world in which children are now born is
"not only a world in crisis but a world
undergoing a veritable mutation", a
mutation of a technical nature but
above all a mutation of values and
ethics which confronts all of humanity
with new and serious challenges.
This note was echoed by Mrs. Estefanía
Aldaba-Lim, Under-Secretary General
of the United Nations responsible for
the organization of the International
Year of the Child. Stressing the poverty
and misery in which millions of children
find themselves, she noted that half the
world's deaths in any given year involve
children under fifteen years of age.
At the close of three days of
discussions, the participants, who
included three Nobel Prize winners, a
former head of state (Daniel Oduber of
Costa Rica), a brain specialist, a worker
for the blind, Princess Caroline of
Monaco, as well as musicians,
educators, writers and economists,
agreed to the following report, drafted
by Peter Ustinov:
Philip Noel-Baker, Nobel Peace Prize¬
winner, and Princess Caroline of Monaco at
the Unesco Round Table
fromnews
unesco
"The future of children is our
responsibility, just as our own future is
our responsibility, and is indivisible
from the state of the world as we find
it. Clearly the state of the world is not
showing improvement, despite the high
hopes which are as ever invested in
science as a solution to our problems.
"The extent of armaments is
unprecedented in the history of the
world, and the contribution of the man
in the street in the form of taxation
going directly into armaments is, on an
average, two weeks of his yearly salary.
One quarter of all the scientific work
force are engaged in the manufacture of
weapons. The demographic explosion is
adding 70 to 80 million births per
annum in excess of recorded deaths.
World energy, based on fossil-fuels, is
being rapidly exhausted at a rate of ten
times its possibility of replacement per
annum, and thus many predominantly
agricultural countries are reduced to
importing foodstuffs owing to rising
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
costs, since to maintain the present rate
of vast expenditures, the great powers
are exporting inflation.
"The inequalities between the haves and
have nots are ever-increasing instead of
diminishing, and an economic
domination has succeeded what used to
be military and colonial.
"In such a world, the future of children
is under a dark cloud of confusion,
penury, malnutrition and the ever-
present menace of total annihilation.
"Cities are growing at a rate which
suggests that in the year 2000, half the
world's population will live in them. At
the same time, it is projected that by the
same year there will be one billion
unemployed, if present trends continue.
"It is understandable that with these
and other statistics at their disposal,
many speakers warned of the extreme
urgency of the present situation, in
which children, who represent a quarter
of the world's population, are already
deprived of schools, hospitals and food
by the extraordinary burden of the arms
race, to say nothing of increasing
instances of child-abuse and child
prostitution, and the alarming growth of
violence, for which the irresponsible use
of the entertainment media must bear
some blame.
"It was unanimously felt that the
enormous world resources made
available by nature and by science
should, with the shortest possible delay,
be deflected from negative ends to those
which would be of benefit to the
fundamental needs of all mankind. A
reappraisal of our priorities is a vital
necessity.
"A collapse of personal and public
morality was regretted by many
speakers, and some solutions were
tentatively offered, ranging from a
return to the ethical principles of
religion to the possibilities of
engineering the human brain to positive
and constructive ends, but the most
general of practical proposals was an
insistence on the need for a most urgent
appeal to the public consciousness.
Opinion must be informed if it is to be
a force, as it has already become a force
in defence of women's rights and of
nature.
"Now, at the dawn of the International
Year of the Child, it is the turn of the
children to capture the public
imagination. We all have 250,000,000
deprived children on our consciences,
and in the future, the joy at the arrival
of a new member of the family will be
tinged with gathering anxiety and fear
unless it is realized today, that,
whatever the race, religion and
nationality of the particular family, the
new baby is predominantly a member of
the human race, and is the moral and
physical responsibility of us all."
The participants, who were invited in
their personal capacity by an organizing
committee headed by Jean d'Ormesson
of the Académie Française included:
Estefanía Aldaba-Lim, Anatole Alexine,
Léon Boissier-Palun, William G.
Brohier, Schuyler Chapin, Samuel
Cookey, J.R. Delgado, Paolo Grassi,
Han Suyin, Paul-Marc Henry, Aziza
Hussein, Michiko Inukai, Alfred
Kastler, Prem Kirpal, Tchavdar
Kiuranov, Carmen Romano de Lopez
Portillo, Gertrud Lutz, Sean MacBride,
Mircea Malitza, Annette M'Baye
d'Erneville, M.L. Mehrotra, Hephzibah
Menuhin Hauser, Her Royal Highness
Princess Caroline of Monaco, Philip
Noel-Baker, Daniel Oduber, Jean
d'Ormesson, Bibiano Osorio-Tafall,
Aurelio Peccei, Marcel Roche, Léon
Schwarzenberg, Janez Stanovnik,
AJvin Toffler, Peter Ustinov and
Victor Vasarely.
Biosphere reserves
144 areas
in 35 countries
Barely two years after the first biosphere
reserves were approved by the
International Coordinating Council for
the Man and the Biosphere Programme,
the network of such reserves now
numbers 144 areas in 35 countries.
In his oral report to Unesco's Executive
Board recently, the Director General
said: "I hope that there will be reserves
of this kind in most countries one day,
and more especially that ways will be
found of establishing links between
reserves in different parts of the world.
In any case, this network, if it is
extended, can make an effective
contribution to the protection of the
environment."
It was in June, 1976 that the first list of
57 biosphere reserves was approved.
They included areas located in Iran,
Norway, Poland, Thailand, United
Kingdom, U.S.A., Uruguay, Yugoslavia
and Zaire.
Newspapers
surviving TV
competition,
survey shows
Are" newspapers on the way out as
readers turn increasingly to television
viewing?
Apparently not, according to Unesco's
Statistical Yearbook, the latest edition
of which (1976) has just been published.
True, the United States now has one
television set for every two inhabitants
(so has Monaco), and newspaper
readership has dropped sharply during
the past 10 years. On the other hand,
the number of dailies published in the
U.S. actually rose from 1,751 in 1965 to
1,812 in 1975.
Similar trends were observable in other
countries. During the same period the
number of papers in India, for example,
rose from 525 to 835. The Soviet Union
was also up (691 against 639), as were
Sweden (135 against 119) and the United
Kingdom (111 against 110).
Furthermore, both the Soviet Union and
Sweden also showed increases in
newspaper circulation, although in the
United Kingdom as in the U.S.A.
readership declined. In Switzerland,
readership increased although the
number of papers dropped, while
France recorded a drop both in the
number of dailies and in total
readership.
The Swedes are the world champion
newspaper readers, according to the
Yearbook, publishing 572 copies of
daily newspapers per thousand
population.
The Japanese probably come next.
They had 526 per thousand in 1974, but
their 1975 figures are not yet available.
Next come the German Democratic
Republic with 472, Iceland (431) and
Norway (estimated 412). The U.S.A. is
rather far down on the list with 287, a
decline from 310 in 1965.
On the other hand, the U.S.A. has 571
television receivers per thousand
population, topped only by Monaco
which has 640. Canada ranks third with
411 per thousand, followed by Sweden
(352), the United Kingdom (320),
Denmark (308), the German Democratic
Republic (307), and the Federal
Republic of Germany and
Finland (306 each).
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Unesco seen through its publications
A major exhibition, "Unesco through
its Publications", will be held at Unesco
headquarters, Paris, from 26 September
to 5 October, and readers of this
bulletin are cordially invited to visit it.
The exhibition will present a selection of
works published by the Organization
since its founding in 1946 and covering
all its fields of action: education,
science, social science, culture,
communication and human rights.
Three computer terminals will link the
exhibition -to Unesco's central computer,
enabling visitors to pose questions about
the entire range of Unesco publications
or to consult the computerized technical
lexicon which facilitates the translation
of complicated texts from one language
to another.
Unesco study
calls for more curbs on sea pollution
International controls over marine
pollution have multiplied rapidly in
recent years, largely because of public
concern generated by such disasters as
the Torrey Canyon and the Amoco
Cadiz.
But much more is needed, according to
. Michael Waldichuk, a leading Canadian
marine scientist. In a study just
published by the Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission, Waldichuk
lists some Í5 international conventions,
treaties, protocols, regulations and
standards which are already in force,
and 21 others which are in preparation
or which have been adopted but are not
yet in force.
However, he writes, most of these deal
with general marine pollution, oil
pollution and radioactive substances,
and international legislation is urgently
required in three other main areas:
shore-based pollution sources, including
river discharges; atmospheric emission
of pollutants, and pollution from
exploration and exploitation of the sea
bed and its subsoil.
The publication, "Global Marine
Pollution: an Overview", also looks at
research currently being carried out and
again concludes that much more is
needed: "Little is known about the
world-wide distribution and ocean
inventory of the critical pollutants... A
baseline survey of the present level,
accurately measured, of critical
pollutants in the water, biota and
sediments of the oceans and in the
principal entry routes (rivers, coastal
outfalls and atmosphere) is required
before trends can be recognized." (The
IOC Assembly last November instructed
the secretariat to prepare a plan of
operations for such a study.)
Another recent Unesco publication,
"Pollution in the Marine
Environment", describes the overall
problem in general terms and then
outlines the activities of each of the
United Nations agencies concerned as
well as those of several international
non-governmental organizations.
New Deputy
Director-General
Mr. Federico Mayor, a Spanish
biochemist, has been appointed Deputy
Director-General of Unesco.
Photo Unesco - Michel Claude
Mr. Federico Mayor
A doctor of pharmacy of Madrid
University, he was a senior fellow of
Trinity College, Oxford, before taking
the chair of biochemistry at Grenada
University in 1963. He then became
rector of the University and vice-
minister of education and science. Most
recently he was professor of
biochemistry and director of the
department of biochemistry and
molecular biology at the Autonomous
University of Madrid. He was also
director of the Molecular Biology
Centre of the Higher Council of
Scientific Research.
A member of several learned societies,
Mr. Mayor was elected to Parliament in
1977 where he served as chairman of the
commission for education and science of
the chamber of deputies.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
It's back to school
for curriculum experts
Primary school curriculum experts from
some 20 countries will become students
again this summer during a four-week
seminar at the United Nations, Geneva,
and Unesco, Paris.
In Geneva the participants will listen to
lectures by top U.N. officials, sit in on
sessions of the Economic and Social
Council (ECOSOC) and visit the
headquarters of various U.N.
Specialized Agencies and the
International Bureau of Education.
Most of the programme in Paris will be
devoted to technical discussions of new
teaching methods and materials. In
addition, the participants will be aided
in the preparation of curriculum
outlines, model lessons, teaching units
and other written or audio-visual aids.
The aim of the exercise, called the
Triangular Fellowship Programme, is to
increase the effectiveness of education
about the United Nations in schools and
teacher-training institutions. Particular
emphasis will be placed on the work of
the United Nations system in the fields
of peace, human rights, development,
environment and population.
Jointly organized by Unesco and the
U.N. Office of Public Information, the
Triangular Fellowship Programme was
established in 1961 to provide an
opportunity for young journalists and
writers from many geographical areas to
receive briefings and to study at first¬
hand the work of the United Nations
system. Later it was expanded to
include textbook writers and specialists
in educational broadcasting. The series
of seminars for curriculum experts
began in 1975.
Culture Fund aid
totals half million
dollars
During its initial period of operations,
the International Fund for the
Promotion of Culture has given more
than half a million dollars' worth of
financial assistance to 18 projects in
various parts of the world. They
include, among others, publication of a
series of children's books based on
Central American folk tales; training
and work on diffusing the traditional
performing arts of Asia; a prize for
young African film-makers, and a
programme of socio-cultural activities in
the French and Swiss Jura region.
Dedicated to the principle that
"everyone has the right freely to
participate in the cultural life of the
community", the Fund was established
in November 1974, by a resolution of
the Unesco General Conference.
Following a year or two of
organizational, promotional and fund-
raising activities, it began operational
assistance in 1977.
Unesco
send-off
for cycle-ecologists
Unesco Director-General Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow greeted a group of 60
members of the group "Sauvons la
Nature" as they set off on a two-month
bicycle tour of Europe which will take
them from Paris to Moscow. The object
of the tour, which includes men and
women aged 17 to 73, is to draw
attention to environmental problems in
Europe.
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
MY YEARS
WITH TOLSTOY
: Bfeh
'
& ¿&k
Extracts from
the unpublished diary
of Tolstoy's doctor
To mark the 150th anniversary of the birth of Leo Tolstoy (1828-1910) the
Unesco Courier presents in this issue specially chosen extracts from the
"Yasnaya Polyana Notebooks", the record kept by Dushan Petrovich
Makovitsky of his years (1904 1910) as Tolstoy's private physician. (See
page 14). The notebooks not only furnish a vivid picture of Tolstoy's daily
life but also, through his off-the-cuff comments on world events, provide a
unique evocation of the period in which they were written. This painting by
his friend Repin shows Tolstoy ploughing a field on his family estate,
Yasnaya Polyana. It is now in the Russian Museum at Leningrad.
]]>
</page>
</document>
