<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074801eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier A window
open on the world
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^^
Germany
(Fed. Rep.)
Musée Bonnet, Bayonne, France Photo © Bulloz, Pans
On the wing
The German painter Albrecht Dürer (born in Nuremberg in 1471) had already won International
renown by the beginning of the 16th century, when great Renaissance artists throughout Europe
acclaimed his originality and genius. A prolific engraver and draughtsman, Dürer was also a
passionate observer of the natural world. "Verily art is embedded in nature," he wrote, "and he who
can extract it is an artist." This watercolour of a jay's wing is one of many studies that reveal Dürer's
astonishing skill at turning nature into art.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COUTÍer
APRIL 1978 31ST YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 18 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Bahasa-
Malaysia
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A. : (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York. U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier Is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education. Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
Managing
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Editors
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Edition :
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
page
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition :
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
FLIGHT WITHOUT FRONTIERS
The 30th anniversary of
the International Civil Aviation Organization
by Yves Lambert
8 HIGH-FLYING WOMEN
Photos
9 DOWN WITH DECIBELS !
by Eugene Sochor
12 DESTINATION DEVELOPMENT
by Luis Cabrai
15 THE SKY'S THE LIMIT
The endless possibilities of special purpose flying
by Patrick Finn
20 SAFETY FIRST IN THE AIR
by Olof Fritsch
22 WORLD ALERT AGAINST HIJACKING
by John Marrett
24 FLYING FOR THRILLS
by Oleg K. Antonov
26 THE SHAPE OF THINGS TO COME
by Charles D. LaFond
33 IN BRIEF
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 SADRIDDIN AYNI
A great Central Asian poet of freedom
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
FED. REP. OF GERMANY: On the wing
*0kfe
Cover
This issue, which marks the 30th anniversary
of the International Civil Aviation
Organization, is devoted to the development
of aviation and highlights the shape of things
to .come. Tomorrow's aircraft are already
being designed and laboratory-tested. The
two brilliantly-coloured photos that comprise
the cover were taken at the hydraulic test
tunnel of France's aerospace research centre
(ONERA) at Châtillon near Paris. Below,
simulation of aerodynamic flow around an
experimental delta-wing plane. Above,
turbulence created by a thin obstacle.
Photos © ONERA, Châtillon, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Flight
without frontiers
75 years after the Wright brothers,
the International Civil Aviation Organization
celebrates its 30th anniversary
by Yves Lambert
Secretary-General of the
International Civil Aviation Organization
ON 17 December 1903 in North Caro¬
lina, U.S.A., a frail structure of
metal, wood and fabric struggled
into the air and precariously managed to
remain airborne for 260 metres. Thanks to
the Wright brothers, Wilbur and Orville,
man had succeeded for the first time in
flying a heavier-than-air, engine-powered
machine.
The date is generally considered Year I in
the history of aviation. From the beginning,
however, the conquest of the air was inter¬
national and exploits were scored simulta¬
neously all over the world.
YVES LAMBERT, French civil aviation engi¬
neer, has been Secretary-General of the Interna¬
tional Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) since
1976. He formerly represented France on the
ICAO Council.
The Frenchman Clément Ader and the
Brazilian Alberto Santos-Dumont were
experimenting with flying machines at the
same time as the Wright brothers. The first
international flights were by the Frenchman
Louis Blériot who crossed the Channel in
1909 and the Dutchman Wijnmalen who
managed a Paris-Brussels round trip in
1910.
Their single seater planes flying at less
than 100 km. per hour were the not-so-
distant ancestors of today's jets which are
so much a part of our daily life that they no
longer evoke interest, much less wonder,
on the part of the public.
During the last 30 years, the transatlantic
flight has been cut from 17 to 3 hours,
thanks to Concorde. The number of pas
sengers using scheduled carriers has
grown from 24,343,000 in 1947 to 620 mil¬
lion (including the U.S.S.R.) in 1977,
without counting the millions of holiday-
makers who travel all over the world on
chartered flights.
The ocean liners which in 1947 still car¬
ried two-thirds of the passengers across
the North Atlantic have virtually disappear¬
ed. Aviation has become one of the major
means for international exchange, shatter¬
ing man's concept of time and distance and
causing him not only to reassess his con¬
cept of geography but also to re-evaluate
his social traditions and cultural patterns.
No other achievement of our century has
made such a profound impact on the lives
of peoples everywhere as aviation.
Yet travellers see only one facet of avia- f
Historic photo (left) was taken
on 17 December 1903 at Kitty
Hawk, North Carolina (U.S.A.)
when the Wright brothers,
Wilbur and Orville, achieved the
first powered, sustained and
controlled flight of a heavier-
than-air machine. (In the 1890s,
the French engineer Clément
Ader succeeded in making a
short hop in a powered plane he
had built, but the machine was
not capable of sustained or
controlled flight.) Orville, lying
prone in the middle of the lower
wing beside the 12 HP engine, is
at the controls of the plane
which the Wrights designed and
built after experimenting with .
kites and gliders. Wilbur has
just released the wing. The first
flight lasted 12 seconds. On the
4th, the machine was airborne
for 59 sees. Today, 75 years
later, civil aviation is a vast
industry employing over 10
million persons. Right, bird's
eye view from a modern airliner
over South America.
Photo © Smithsonian Institution National Air Museum, Washington, D.C.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
3*
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
1906 On 12 November in Paris, the Brazilian Alberto Santos-Dumont became
the first holder of a world air speed record: 41 km. per hour. Three years
later, Santos-Dumont produced his famous series of "Demoiselle" or
"Grasshopper" monoplanes (above). These lightweight craft (wing span 5.10 m.;
length 8 m.) were among the first to be used for pleasure flying.
^ -
10 fi Q Above, children hail the first-ever oversea plane flight as Louis Blériot's
«U« tiny monoplane (wingspan and length 8 m.) crosses the English coast
near the end of its 37-minute Channel crossing on 25 July. A rival French aviator,
Hubert Latham, had attempted a crossing 6 days before but engine trouble forced
him down in mid-Channel. Below, two eras of travel and transport caught by a
photographer on 27 July 1909 as Latham made a second gallant but unsuccessful
attempt to fly the Channel.
Photo © Photothèque Hachette, Paris
, tion and hardly notice all those who work
behind the scenes to make their flight pos¬
sible. They can hardly imagine the complex
co-ordination required to make the interna¬
tional airline network operate efficiently.
An essential link in this chain is the Interna¬
tional Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO), a
United Nations specialized agency with
headquarters in Montreal (Canada), which
has just celebrated its 30th anniversary.
In spite of setbacks at the beginning of
the jet age and the changing economic
situation, remarkable progress has been
made, far exceeding the hopes of those
who more than 30 years ago drafted the
1944 Chicago Convention to ensure the
"safe and orderly" growth of international
civil aviation.
The Convention, the birth certificate of
ICAO, has now been ratified by 141
governments, and is the legal basis which
made possible the multilateral agreements
governing international air transport. The
rapid development of international air
transport, the opening of new routes, the
search for new structures by carriers,
charterers, airports and, of course, national
administrations are the living and con¬
stantly renewed embodiments of the Chi¬
cago Convention.
ICAO is also a technical organization.
Aviation requires international standardiza¬
tion, for international flights would be
unthinkable if flight procedures and equip¬
ment were not the same throughout the
world. ICAO acts as the international regu¬
latory agency which sets the Standards
and Recommended. Practices for the pre¬
cise and detailed characteristics and
performances of both airborne and ground
equipment.
To be effective, these Standards and
Recommended Practices must be imple¬
mented. This is why ICAO establishes
regional air navigation plans which define
all the essential international air navigation
facilities and services in the various regions
of the world.
Thus, when taking a plane, whether for
the longest scheduled non-stop flight
10,876 km. from Tokyo to New Yorkor
for one of the shortest hops27 km. bet¬
ween Copenhagen and Malmothe pas¬
senger boards an aircraft which has a certi¬
ficate of airworthiness issued in accor¬
dance with ICAO regulations.
During the flight the aircraft crew suc¬
cessively contacts various area control cen¬
tres, using ICAO radio procedures. Finally,
the aircraft will be guided by an ICAO ins¬
trument landing system, whether touching
down in London or Bujumbura in the heart
of Africa.
The aeroplane has overcome many natu¬
ral obstacles, such as mountains, oceans
and deserts. In recent years, however', air
passengers have become concerned about
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
a new threat. Faced with the rising number
of unlawful seizures of aircraft and with
acts of terrorism against passengers, air¬
craft and aviation facilities, the internatio¬
nal community has reacted in two ways. A
complete international legal system has
been worked out in the form of three con¬
ventions signed in Tokyo, The Hague and
Montreal. ICAO has strengthened these
legal instruments with technical measures
that have been circulated to all contracting
states. (See page 22).
ICAO is not only concerned with the
interests of air transport users. For some
years now, it has also been active in the
field of environment by introducing mea¬
sures to limit aircraft noise. In 1971, the
ICAO Council adopted a set of standards
on aircraft noise which were incorporated
in Annex 16 of the Chicago Convention.
These standards are becoming progres¬
sively more stringent for the latest aircraft.
(See page 9).
Today the world is also concerned with
pollution caused by exhaust fumes from
cars, trucks and aircraft. Although it is
generally agreed that aircraft are little to
blame, it is nevertheless essential to es¬
tablish the facts.
A first step in this direction involves
drawing up international specifications for
measuring polluting agents from all
sources, including aviation. For this pur¬
pose ICAO is co-operating with other inter¬
national organizations, such as the
World Health Organization and the World
Meteorological Organization.
Air law is a new branch of international
law compared with maritime law, which
enjoys a long tradition. ICAO's task is to
codify international air law, taking into
account different legal concepts and
systems of jurisprudence, to draft conven¬
tions on various aspects of international air
law, and to try to obtain their ratification.
So far, ICAO has prepared eight conven¬
tions covering such widely different areas
as international recognition of the right of
ownership of aircraft, damage caused to
third parties on the ground, the liability of
the air carrier towards passengers, offen¬
ces committed on board aircraft and acts of
unlawful interference with civil aviation.
While ICAO does not set fares and does
not apportion air routes to the different air¬
lines, its role is neverthless essential in the
development of air transport.
There has been much talk about disorder
in the air transport market and about
unbridled competition on certain air routes.
However, this market is governed by bilat¬
eral agreements and the price of tickets is
fixed by the airline tariff conferences, sub¬
ject to government approval. ICAO's role
with regard to the economic aspects of air
transport has so far been limited to collec¬
ting and publishing statistical information i
and economic studies which can be used I
1Q1Q ^n era °* pioneering long-distance flights began on 15 June
lulu when British aviators John Alcock and Arthur Whitten Brown
landed in Ireland (above) after the first nonstop transatlantic flight (16
hours 27 minutes from St. John's, Newfoundland). Later that year the
world community showed its concern to promote international co¬
operation in civil aviation: the International Air Traffic Association
(IATA) was founded at The Hague; the League of Nations took steps to
draw up regulations for air traffic; and on 19 October the first
international convention on air navigation met in Paris.
z&
? m
^mm^. - ^m\
m% *^ ***m^ Jrm
fer ^Kf pr
\
W
Urn* '" Ám\ - un
B^nVHifln^n^HAfl
|Q97 The president of Japan's Imperial Aviation Company, Gen.
I U¿# Nagaoka, welcomes French aviators Costes and Le Brix to Tokyo
during the round-the-world trip (10 October 1927-14 April 1928) on which
they made the first nonstop flight across the South Atlantic. In the
same year (1927) the American Charles Lindbergh made his epic solo
flight from New York to Paris (in a machine only a little larger than the
Wrights' first plane). Aviation continued to make rapid advances during
the next decade, which saw many pioneering exploits including (in June
1937) the first nonstop flight over the North Pole from the U.S.S.R. to
the United States. Soviet pilot Valeri Chkalov did the 9,130-km. trip in
63 hours aboard a single-engine Tupolev aircraft.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
High¬
flying
women , I
Photo © Keystone, Pans
Some of the most legendary figures of the "heroic age" of flight in the 1920s and 1930s were
women pilots who amazed the world with their flying skills and endurance. First great
performance by a woman aviator was due to Adrienne Bolland of France (1) shown here in
the single-engine craft in which she crossed the Andes on 1 April 1921 in spite of strong
adverse winds and bitter cold. Many men in more powerful machines had failed to perform
this feat. Amelia Earhart of the U.S.A. (2) was the first woman to fly the Atlantic, both as a
passenger (1928) and as a solo pilot (on 20-21 May 1932). She played an active part in efforts
to open aviation to women before disappearing in the Pacific in 1937 while attempt¬
ing a round-the-world flight. (3) 24-year-old New Zealander Jean Batten at Calcutta during
her record-breaking England-Australia flight (14 days 23 1/2 hours) in May 1934. (4) Soviet
aviator V. Grizodubova (centre) and her team beneath the ANT-37 in which they flew
almost 6,000 km. nonstop in 1938, breaking the long-distance record for an all-woman crew.
kby Member States for the preparation of
development plans.
These activities, as well as the role of
ICAO in co-ordinating air policies among its
Contracting States, are far from negligible.
They may have an even greater impact as
the result of a special Air Transport Con¬
ference held in April 1977, the first such
gathering in more than 30 years.' ICAO is
now entrusted with new tasks concerning
the application of rates and fares, policy on
chartered or non-scheduled flights, the
regulation of capacity on international
flights and the machinery for fixing interna¬
tional air tariffs. (1)
ICAO is active in many other fields, in¬
cluding aviation medicine, telecommunica¬
tions, search and rescue, training films and
manuals, and smoothing out cumbersome
customs, immigration and public health
formalities which impede the movement of
people and goods.
But among the many activities of ICAO,
technical assistance to developing coun¬
tries has a particularly important place.
(See page 12). A recent study carried out in
Africa by ICAO and the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP) has
shown how aviation can contribute to eco¬
nomic development in the Third World,
bringing an inflow of foreign currency,
creating new jobs and opening up export
markets.
In a world of increasingly rapid change,
aviation is destined to become the key form
of medium- and long-range transport. And
as aviation expands, its problems too are
bound to multiply. ICAO has already amply
proved its determination to solve them.
Yves Lambert
(1) As an intergovernmental organization, ICAO works
closely with a number of non-governmental bodies
representing various interests in international civil avia¬
tion. Among these is the International Air Transport
Association (IATA), with headquarters both in Montreal
and Geneva, which groups 109 scheduled airlines. Be¬
sides dealing with uniformity in fares, ticketing, hand¬
ling of baggage and freight, and with technical and legal
matters, IATA represents the scheduled airlines at ICAO
meetings. A major feature of lATA's work is its clearing
house which permits member airlines to settle pay¬
ments made all over the world in different currencies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Symbolic photo of a child jumping in the air as a plane roars by
overhead won second prize (amateur category) in the international
photo competition organized in 1974 by Photokina of Cologne,
Germany (Fed. Rep.). The theme of the competition, "A World for
AH", was chosen by the United Nations for World Population Year.
THERE is nothing like noise to make a
noise. While most people don't care
a decibel about aircraft nuisances as
long as they are not bothered themselves,
the roar of planes at many airports is real
enough for those living close by. Distant
echoes are also heard by airline executives
and international aviation bodies concern¬
ed with safe and efficient air transport.
Consider these facts :
Not long ago, stores, office buildings,
schools and homes around Los Angeles
International Airport occupied what is now
a large swathe of open space laid bare as if
by a giant lawn mower. These 2,800 build¬
ings have been destroyed in the most dras¬
tic step yet taken in the United States to ^
deal with the thunder and whine of jets, f
Down
with decibels!
by Eugene Sochor
EUGENE SOCHOR, head of the Office of
Public Information at the International CivilAvia¬
tion Organization (ICAO) in Montreal, was for 12
years a staff member of Unesco's press division.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Since it was impossible to move the air¬
port, city officials decided after more
than $4 billion in damage suits over aircraft
noise to move the people instead at a
cost of $300 million.
A survey of U.S. airports conducted
recently by the Airport Operators Council
International found $245 million in pending
noise-related lawsuits filed against airport
authorities in the U.S. In addition, over the
past five years, airports have spent some
$200 million in land acquisition program¬
mes because of noise.
In some schools, jets disrupt teaching.
One junior high school near Los Angeles
Airport had to be closed because of cons¬
tant interruption. The Airport agreed to
pay $21 million to five local school districts
for sound proofing.
Usual complaints of residents near air¬
ports are interrupted sleep, bad television
reception and houses that shudder every
few minutes. A survey indicates that peo¬
ple living close to airports suffer a higher
incidence of nervous breakdowns than
people living further away.
In response to public outcry, many air¬
ports have had to cut operations at night as
part of a growing pattern of resistance to
aircraft noise. Wellington Airport in New
Zealand is a good example. It is closed to
traffic from 11 P.M. to 6 A.M. except for
emergencies, delayed international flights
and meteorologicaí conditions.
A list of major cities with some sort of
night curfews includes: West Berlin, Bre¬
men, Cologne, Dusseldorf, Frankfurt,
Geneva, Hamburg, Hong Kong, London,
Manchester, Malmo, Montreal (Dorval),
Munich, Nice, Oslo, Paris (Orly), Sydney,
Stockholm, Tokyo, Toronto and Zurich.
Internationally, the growth of local shut¬
downs has caused air carriers to alter flight
plans and schedules, with resulting traffic
peaks and strain on air traffic control, and
on airport and customs facilities immedia¬
tely before or after curfews. Some interna¬
tional airports must handle as many as 500
flights and 70,000 or more travellers a day.
The chain reaction is also felt on stop¬
overs. Bombay International Airport, for
instance, is completely saturated with traf¬
fic at night and deserted during the day.
The reason is Bombay's strategic location
between Europe and Tokyo. Most interna¬
tional flights arrive at night since they take
off comparatively early to avoid the cur¬
fews on departure in Europe and at their
destination points. It has been pointed out
that if a night curfew were imposed at
John F. Kennedy International Airport in
New York and the summer night curfew at
London Airport were made year round, jets
would have only 3 hours a day to cross the
Atlantic.
The noise issue has also affected the
development of new airports. As an execu¬
tive of the Airport Operators Council Inter¬
national noted recently : "No new major
airport has been started in the U.S. since
1970/ Even relatively minor projects like
runway extensions are being delayed, often
for years, as citizens fight to ward off more
noise".
ICAO experts who have been working on
the problem of airport curfews in relation to
traffic peaks think that the most that may
be expected is some easing of the situation
through prudent, well considered and wor¬
kable measures. These measures should
be applied both nationally and internatio¬
nally and will require a co-ordinated inter¬
national approach.
Action taken at airports in one country
may affect operations half-way round the
world. A variety of differing and inconsis¬
tent restrictions applied at random at dif¬
ferent airports in the network may prove
disruptive to airlines and their passengers,
to air traffic control, and to airport opera¬
tions generally.
Responding to public concern, the last
ICAO Assembly clearly recognized its res¬
ponsibility and that of member govern¬
ments to achieve maximum compatibility
between the safe and orderly development
of civil aviation and the quality of the
human environment.
It noted that with most jets now in ser¬
vice exceeding the noise limits set by ICAO
for new aircraft, the noise problem in cer¬
tain areas, including many busy internatio¬
nal airports, had led to curfews and genera¬
ted strong opposition to the expansion of
existing airports or the construction of new
ones. The Assembly called on all states to
recognize the role of ICAO in "aggressively
pursuing a comprehensive programme" to
reduce aircraft noise at its source and to
develop effective noise abatement
strategies.
The whole question of aviation and envi¬
ronment is in fact one of ICAO's major con-
Reckoning with noise
102 decibels
98 decibels
107 decibels
102 decibels
91 decibels
86 decibels
long-haul jet, recent model,
on landing (1.500 m. from
runway end)
medium-haul jet, recent
model, on take-off, 1,500 m.
after leaving taxiway
car horn heard at 7.5 m.
express train travelling at 140
km./hr. heard at 25 m.
bus heard at 7.5 m.
motorcycle heard at 7.5 m.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
cerns. It is resulting in ever-tightening
noise limitations on aircraft, which, accor¬
ding to the ICAO Constitution,' are binding
on all contracting states. These standards
(which are part of Annex 16 of the Chicago
Convention on International Civil Aviation)
aim at reducing the noise at source through
certification of the aircraft, starting with
future subsonic jets through production of
current jets, propeller-driven planes, super¬
sonic transport planes and STOL (short
take-off and landing) aeroplanes.
. ICAO is also studying noise reduction
requirements for existing first generation
subsonic jets which do not meet the Annex
16 requirements. It must, however, be
recognized that the cost of "hushing" or
"retrofitting" such jets the noisiest in the
world's aircraft fleetwould be exorbitant
for most airlines.
Airline executives also question the use¬
fulness of modifying engines with sound
absorbing material when in fact these older
jets are due to be replaced by the newer
wide-body jets which do meet ICAO noise
standards. Also, the cost of "retrofitting"
the older planes would be passed on inevi¬
tably to the travelling public.
Airlines have readily co-operated in
working out procedures and route patterns
which generate the minimum noise distur¬
bance and meet the needs of a particular
airport. Some approach and landing pro¬
cedures to ease the noise over residential
areas are being steadfastly opposed by
pilot organizations as being too dangerous,
instead, the International Federation of Air
Line Pilots' Associations (IFALPA) has
always maintained that aircraft noise abate¬
ment should be achieved by control of
noise at its source, rather than by
modifying aircraft operating procedures
which may impinge on safety of opera¬
tions.
The ICAO Assembly is also concerned
with another aspect of the situation: better
airport planning and zoning. Land in many
countries has become a rare commodity
keenly disputed by people and planes. A
dramatic case in point is what a newspaper
called: "The carrot patch standing in the
way of Tokyo's shiny new airport". This
massive airport at Narita was built to ease
congestion at Haneda airport. Its opening
has been postponed 12 times since 1972 by
the violent opposition of squatters, inclu¬
ding a farmer who refused to move his car¬
rot patch from under the shadow of the
control tower.
Quite a different story is the new Naga¬
saki Airport on Kyushu Island, the first
"floating" airport in the world. It resembles
a huge aircraft carrier. Japanese officials
are so enthusiastic about this novel
approach that they are also planning to
locate the new Osaka Airport off the main¬
land in the bay of Osaka. Few countries,-
however, can be as fortunate in selecting a
site and financing its airports as the
sparsely-settled and oil-rich United Arab
Emirates, which boast four international
airports within short distances of one an¬
other. Even so, a new airport is under con¬
struction in Abu Dhabi.
Land requirements for older airports took
into account only the needs of the airline
operators to move people the fastest,
safest and most economical way. Few
people lived around the airports anyway.
People came to watch the new jets take off
in a roar of excitement. But as traffic
increased and housing developments
moved closer to the airports, the novelty
wore off and the problems piled up.
The land required for airport develop¬
ment has increased dramatically as a result
of increased numbers of flights and pas¬
sengers, volume of cargo and operating
requirements of aircraft. Whereas 1,600
hectares may have been adequate 20 years
ago for a major international airport, some
airports being constructed now require
areas as large as 6,000 hectares merely to
satisfy direct operational needs. Mirabel
Airport servicing Montreal occupies the lar¬
gest such area in the world7,000 hec¬
tares in its final phase and a protective
cocoon of 27,700 hectares. The price for
such seclusion is distance in this case 55
km. from the city.
The fartner away the airport from the city
centre, as common sense would dictate,
the louder the outcry of travellers who
stand to lose the time gained in air travel.
Hence the need for fast and improved city
to airport transportation, if necessary by
rail or even helicopter.
The^location, size and configuration of
the airport must be co-ordinated with the
patterns of residential development and
other major land uses in the area. An ICAO
Airport Master Planning Manual states that
in long-range planning of airports, inclu¬
ding the expansion of existing airports,
planners should assess the impact on the
airport's surrounding community. This
necessarily involves a close relationship
with the authorities that control the land
around the airport.
Like so many of man's other machines,
the aircraft is both a blessing and a curse.
Its nuisances cannot be wished away.
Perhaps the patient outlook of the writer
and flyer Antoine de Saint-Exupéry is to the
point. If, as he wrote, we feel that the
machine is destroying man, it is that we
lack the hindsight to assess all the sudden
changes which it has brought about.
Eugene Sochor
Photo © Jean J. Moreau, Paris
This presentation of the noise levels caused by various means of
transport was prepared on the basis of a diagram published by
the ICAO Bulletin, the technical monthly of the International Civil
Aviation Organization, In February 1975. Above, giant silencers
at Charles de Gaulle airport, Paris. The enormous tubes are
designed to muffle the noise of jets being tested after overhaul.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
.
Photo © Keystone, Pans
Destination
development
by Luis Cabrai
LUIS CABRAL is an Indian economist working
with the TechnicalAssistance Bureau of ICAO in
Montreal.
MODERN air transport can drama¬
tically improve the economic
development prospects of Third
World countries.
Investment in aviation is usually consid¬
ered a costly and risky business, but there
is now abundant evidence to show that a
well-organized national and international
air transport system can substantially boost
the foreign-exchange earnings of develo¬
ping countries, as well as creating thou¬
sands of new jobs and millions of dollars of
revenue.
These are the unexpected and welcome
conclusions of a two-year International
Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) study of
the contribution civil aviation can make to
the economic development of African
states. The study, funded by the United
Nations Development Programme (UNDP)
following a resolution of the African Civil
Aviation Commission (AFCAC) involved 37
countries south of the Sahara, from Mauri¬
tania in the north to Lesotho in the south.
These countries have a total population of
250 million people; twelve of them are land¬
locked.
While countless studies have been made
of African economies and many of civil
aviation, this was the first attempt to link
the two fields in a "cause and effect" rela¬
tionship. ICAO worked closely with other
U.N. agencies to cover a multitude of acti¬
vities, but attention was focussed primarily
on agriculture, industry, commerce and
civil aviation itself. At first project members
doubted whether aviation could make
much of a contribution to economic
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
growth in Africa and provide anything
more than luxury transport for the privi¬
leged few. After studying the question for
two years, the governments involved are
convinced that aviation is indeed a vital
force in Africa.
Its contribution to exports is already
significant: airlines carried over $30 million
worth of fresh horticultural products to
Europe in 1974 and could carry much more,
if production and marketing were better
organized. While only seven of the 37
countries visited contributed to these
exports, the study revealed that most of
the others could create employment and
earn valuable foreign exchange by growing
fruit and vegetables for overseas markets.
As a result, a recommendation was made
to 27 governments that they request assis¬
tance from the Food and Agriculture Orga¬
nization of the United Nations (FAO) so as
to get a larger slice of this lucrative market.
Project members were often amazed by
the opportunities civil aviation offers to
increase Africa's earnings. Most of them
were aware that cut flowers represent a
potential export, but hardly imagined that
the retail market for flowers in Western
Europe is worth $3 billion a year, and that
African countries are so well-placed to take
an increasing share of it. AN states were,
therefore, encouraged to become active in
this area and at the same time to
increase wherever appropriate their par-
Aviation can contribute to
the economic development
of Third World countries by
providing speedy transport
for perishable goods and by
opening up hitherto
inaccessible regions. Above
left, cattle flown over the
Andes frpm the Pacific coast
are unloaded at Tingo Maria
(Peru). As part of its
livestock improvement
programme, Peru has
airlifted thousands of cattle
to breeding centres in its
Amazon region. Right, 100-
tonne cargo of grapes was
flown from Nicosia (Cyprus)
to London, arriving 10 days
ahead of grapes sent by sea
and fetching premium prices
on the British market.
ticipation in the export market for fresh
fish.
Industry is still in an embryonic stage in
Africa. Most activity is in light manufactu¬
ring, designed to reduce imports by pro¬
viding local populations with foodstuffs,
beverages, textiles, bicycles and the like.
The study found, however, that better use
could be made of the plentiful supply of
low-cost labour to produce a wide range of
goods, from fashion garments to electronic
equipment. Many of these goods would
still be competitive even with the added
cost of air transport.
While tourism is highly developed in a
few African countries, many others would
like to enter the field. Tourism in Africa is
almost entirely dependent on aviation, but
here the experts expressed caution.
Though the continent as a whole is rich in
tourist attractions, few countries have
enough to offer individually to draw signifi¬
cant numbers of visitors.
The study warned that tourism can be a
risky venture, with no assurance that
returns will cover the large investments
required. In order to avoid costly errors,
governments were advised to seek expert
advice before launching tourist develop¬
ment programmes.
Though it can bring high financial
returns in a short period, tourism does little
to stabilize national economies, and there is
little doubt that in the long run air com
merce geared to the exporting of perishable
merchandise represents a sounder invest¬
ment for most African states.
A rapid survey of the actual and potential
markets for perishable goods reveals that
handsome profits could be made by Afri¬
can countries willing to make a modest
investment and to exploit the available
capacity of air-transport carriers to Europe.
During the winter. of 1975-76 Western
Europe imported 105,000 tonnes of fruit
and vegetables from Africa south of the
Sahara, but only 20,000 tonnes were car¬
ried by air. Given normal rates of expan¬
sion, the latter figure should double by
1980.
But if further efforts are made along the
lines suggested by the ICAO study, there is
no reason why air exports should not reach
60,000 tonnes, worth $90 million or more
by 1980.
The possibilities offered by the cut
flower market are even more impressive. In
1974, flower imports to Europe, worth $45
million in all, were dominated by Israel,
Colombia and South Africa. Only two Afri¬
can countries (Kenya and the Ivory Coast)
had a share in this market (to the tune of
$3.3 million), and yet the climate and soil
throughout most of Africa are ideal for
growing flowers and aircraft are available
to transport them.
'Experts predict that European flower
imports will treble by 1980 to $135 million,
and provided a sufficient number of states
respond to the challenge, Africa could well
capture half of this market.
Another export field where rewards are
high is that of fresh fish. Shipped by air,
fresh fish command very high prices and
bring exporters between 50 per cent and
100 per cent profit. But Africa has done
almost nothing to capitalize on this oppor¬
tunity. Only 1,300 tonnes of fish (worth
$4.5 million) were air-freighted to Europe
from Africa in 1975, yet Africa's exports
could easily total $25 million in two years'
time.
One tangible proof that the ICAO survey
results are being taken seriously is the
recent purchase by a group of West Afri¬
can states of ten turbo-prop cargo planes
from the U.K.'s Royal Air Force. The
planes, which can carry a maximum pay-
ioad of 35 tonnes, are designed for both
long- and short-haul. operations from the
most difficult terrain and do not need
sophisticated ground support equipment.
As this example shows, developing
countries are already making decisions in
the field of air transport which are bound to
affect their rate of economic growth. Not
all of these choices concern the develop¬
ment of exports; many have to do with
regional and internal problems and pros¬
pects.
Preliminary findings of ICAO studies in
five East Asian countries show that while
the level of aviation development is more
advanced there than in Africa, the potential
of air transport is not fully utilized and
should be better integrated into the social
and economic growth of the region. This
group of countries, which includes Indone¬
sia and the Philippines, consists of morei
than 10,000 island archipelagos. It would I
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
be a big and costly process to develop sur¬
face transport to link up the isolated com¬
munities living in this difficult terrain.
Another preliminary study indicates that
better air transport between the islands in
the South Pacific (including Fiji, Papua-
New-Guinea and Western Samoa) and
Australia, New Zealand, Japan and the
U.S.A. might benefit tourism, light
industry, agriculture and trade.
In Latin America, air transport is already
playing an important role in the develop¬
ment of several countries. It is not generally
known, for example, that Brazil has the
world's largest general aviation fleet, after
Canada and the U.S.A. The development
of Brazil's interior provinces in the last 20
years would have been much slower
without the intensive and intelligent use of
aircraft. The same goes for the rest of
South America.
Brazil uses aircraft in numerous develop¬
ment programmes, including construction
of the Trans-Amazon Highway, while
Venezuela has pressed them into service to
prospect for oil and mineral resources in
Amazonia. In Peru, the Ministry of Fishery
employs C-130 cargo-planes to airlift 20-
tonne loads of frozen fish from Lima to
Aycucho in the interior. The aircraft cross¬
es the Andes in one hour, while a truck
with only a 4-tonne load takes 22 hours to
circle the mountains.
Taking advantage of airfreight develop¬
ment, Peru is now building freezer plants in
the towns of the Andes to improve the
local diet. It has also flown in thousands of
pure-bred cattle from Brazil, Argentina,
Costa Rica, Guatemala and Panama.
Across the Andes, Argentina uses a
large cargo fleet to airlift machinery, vehi¬
cles, fruit, meat and other products to
various countries in Latin America and
even to Africa. Bolivia too is now using two
new C-13 Hercules to airlift farm produce
from its Amazon basin area to La Paz. The
aircraft will also be used to promote
exports and to prospect for oil and gas.
Mineral prospecting and oil and gas
exploration can be made easier and quicker
with the help of a well-organized air trans¬
port system. Inaccessibility is no longer the
obstacle it was, thanks to shuttle services
capable of airlifting personnel and equip
ment to a desired location in a matter of
hours.
In Alaska's North Slope, for example,
aircraft ranging from heavyweights to light
helicopters are used to prospect for oil,
moving men and supplies in a quick and
efficient manner.
Again, if a preliminary geological survey
shows that a region contains enough mine¬
rals and ore to justify exploitation, vehicles
and equipment can be airlifted to the site
either by conventional air-transport or by
specially adapted STOL (short take-off and
landing) aircraft. These aircraft can then
make the return journey with a cargo of ore
refined on the spot. This might prove a
solution, for instance, to Egypt's difficul¬
ties in exploiting the inaccessible, yet ore-
rich regions between the Nile and the Red
Sea.
These specialized uses of air transport
offer new hope to countries unable to
exploit their natural resources because of
the exorbitant cost of constructing related
road or rail networks. But the most imme¬
diately productive use of aircraft in Third
World countries, at least in Africa, is for
exporting perishable goods to overseas
markets.
Europe and the United States are the tra¬
ditional markets for such goods, but there
is also a growing demand for rare fruits and
exotic seafood in the oil-rich countries of
the Middle East, where shrimps from
Ghana, Brazilian limes, and Senegalese
beans are beginning to make their appear¬
ance.
The term "perishables", however,
covers a whole range of commodities other
than food and cut flowers, which develo¬
ping countries can export by air. Such
items include fashion garments, short-life
radioactive substances, gold, gems, bank¬
notes and valuables of all kinds, antiques,
newspapers and magazines.
In the highly competitive world of
modern business, developing countries can
reap enormous benefits from air-freighting
perishable goods. Contrary to general
belief, air freight is no longer a means of
transport to be used only in emergencies or
when cost is not a prime factor. In many
cases, air freight is the most economical
way of shipping and marketing goods.
According to an IATA (International Air
Transport Association) study, the compari¬
son between air and surface costs only
makes sense as part of an overall export
drive. In terms of packing and crating, insu¬
rance premiums, transport charges, transit
warehousing and wharfage and interest on
capital invested in shipments en route, air
freight comes out better. There are also the
invisible benefits such as speed, punctua¬
lity, dependability and flexibility in adapting
to changing market demand all of which
help to ensure the overall success of the
operation.
At .the national level, any developing
country must sooner or later face the ques¬
tion : what form of transport is the most
productive investment? Compared to road
transport, transport by air is relatively
cheap to develop, but somewhat expensive
to run.
This leads to the surprising conclusion
that in a majority of cases the least expen¬
sive and most satisfactory way of develo¬
ping a national transport system seems to
be to start with air transport, then cons¬
truct railways, and finally to build roads to
link outlying villages with the railway
stations.
Luis Cabrai
Aviation holds out great potential
for Africa's developing economies
by boosting exports and foreign
exchange earnings and by
creating new jobs. Right, coffee
being loaded on to a cargo plane
at Tlppi (Ethiopia).
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Top of the props In this remarkable photo, three giant Australian cargo planes flying nose to tail with only
a hazardous 8 metres between them look for all the world like a 12-engined airborne
monster with three sets of wings. Today's heavy-duty workhorses of the air transport a
wide range of bulk cargoes, from road-building machinery to life-saving supplies.
The sky's
the limit
The endless possibilities
of special purpose flying
by Patrick Finn
THE modern traveller usually thinks of
aviation in terms of airline transport,
and perhaps of military applications.
But the myriad uses of planes that come
under the heading "general aviation" are
often less known.
Yet they range from tasks that affect our
everyday life, such as cargo flights, to eso¬
teric scientific experiments such as flying a
set of clocks around the world to test Ein¬
stein's theory of relativity, or climbing ^
above the clouds to get a better look at anr
eclipse of the sun.
PATRICK FINN is a Canadian journalist specia¬
lizing in aviation and air transport news. He is a
former president of the Canadian Science Wri¬
ters' Association and a member of the Aviation
Space Writers' Association.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
POLSKA
Farmer...
Flying farmers in many
parts of the world use crop
dusters or spray planes to
spray fields with liquid
plant food or Insecticide.
Light aircraft are also used
for bombarding forests
with nitrogen pellets to
speed growth. Left, aerial
forest-spraying depicted on
a Polish stamp.
.Doctor...
Far from the nearest coast,
a doctor is winched down
on to a supertanker to
examine a casualty.
The aeroplane, along with other types of
aircraft such as the helicopter, the glider
and lighter-than-air craft, have become
tools of economic development, sources of
recreation, and special aids to communica¬
tion and humanitarian effort throughout
the world.
In the field of air cargo, for example, air¬
craft such as the L-100 Hercules now travel
the skies like the "tramp ships" of an earlier
era, picking up and dropping off loads of
cattle, drilling equipment, road-building
machinery and life-saving supplies.
Large cargo aircraft have played a vital
role in such major projects as the Trans-
Amazon highway in Brazil, the Trans-
Gabon railway in Africa, and the Alaskan
oil pipeline.
Other, "general aviation" aircraft of
various sizes and designs are used through¬
out the world in such tasks as hurricane
hunting, the location of dangerous ice¬
bergs, and forest fire fighting.
But these spectacular uses are only part
of the story. General aviation in all of its
forms now contributes thousands of inte¬
resting and highly skilled jobs to the econo¬
mies of the nations, with a growing num¬
ber of small airports providing new trade
and communication networks.
One of the major roles of general aviation
is in business and commuter-type flying. In
fact, business flying has become one of the
world's fastest growing industries in recent
years.
Forecasters say that business flying will
continue to grow despite the energy and
fuel shortages in many areas. On a seat-
mile basis, small aircraft use less fuel than
big airliners. And as airlines continue to
cut back on flights to smaller communities
because of light and uneconomic loads.
businessmen will continue to turn to com¬
pany planes to get them to the right place
at the right time.
In many countries, business planes are
no longer used only for top company offi¬
cials. They now transport managers, engi¬
neers, accountants and other specialists
who must be constantly on the move.
Busy people are also becoming used to
the idea of hiring planes or taking small
commuter aircraft to get them to their des¬
tination quickly. In fact, such services fre¬
quently connect with the major airlines.
The result is a complex network of air com¬
munications similar to that which develo¬
ped in earlier eras in land and sea transport.
Personal transportation is probably the
most high profile category of general avia¬
tion. It means flying for fun, learning new
skills, and perhaps the opportunity to move
into the professional side of the aviation
world.
In the broad category of special purpose
flying, there are so many uses of general
aviation that it would be impossible to list
them all. However, some of the more
diverse uses include:
Flying health services. In Australia,
there is a flying doctor service, which is
designed to provide quick aid to persons
living in lonely, isolated areas of the "out¬
back"
Forest and crop spraying. In Canada
and the U.S., aircraft are used regularly to
spray forests in the northeast where spruce
budworm is infesting thousands of acres of
conifers. For crops, special low-flying air¬
craft have been developed for spraying,
and farmers are now also seeding their
fields from the air.
Disease control. In the Volta River basin
in West Africa, the World Health Organiza¬
tion is involved in a major spray programme
to kill the larvae of the blackfly, which
transmit the blinding disease of onchocer¬
ciasis.
Livestock airlifts. In Peru, cargo aircraft
were used to transport 35,000 head of
purebred cattle over the Andes to Amazon
villages in the interior.
Forest fire fighting. Both planes and
helicopters have proved successful in keep¬
ing these outbreaks under control. So-
called "water-bombers" drop both -water
and special fire-fighting chemicals on hot
spots in the forests.
Plant airlifts. In the Philippine islands,
cargo aircraft were pressed into duty to
move seedlings and plants as part of the
government's green revolution pro¬
gramme.
Pipeline and utility line patrol. Heli¬
copters and light aircraft are used all over
the world to fly up and down pipeline
routes and remote power and telephone
lines to check for possible problems.
Aerial photography. Map makers use
aerial photos that can be employed with
special viewing equipment to produce
three-dimensional effects.
Aerial archaeology. Aerial photography
has become widely used by archaeologists
in recent years as a means of discovering
hidden or partly destroyed ancient sites
that could not be found on the ground.
Aerial photos also help archaeologists to
plan digs by providing an overall view of
sites and their topography.
Urban planning. Air photos can provide
developers and city officials with an up-to-
date look at urban growth or creeping
blight.
Environmental and wildlife protec¬
tion. Helicopters and light aircraft can be
particularly effective in tracking down the
sources of water and air pollution. Conser¬
vationists in many countries use aircraft to
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
...Fireman...
Aircraft have proved their worth many
times over as versatile fire-fighting
machines. Above, a helicopter alms a
hose during a fire in Chicago. Below, a
plane specially designed for fighting forest
fires drops Its load of water.
(see also photos pages 18-19)
take inventories and assess the state of
wildlife.
Aerial logging. Planes can be used to
identify patches of valuable types of wood.
In the western part of the U.S., helicopters
are used to fly deep into forest areas and
remove small logs for the roof shingle
market.
Search and Rescue. This is one of the
better known uses of general aviation.
Many a hiker, mountain climber or wilder¬
ness traveller owes his life to airborne res¬
cue teams and spotters.
Cargo drops. Cargo can sometimes be
dropped by parachute in areas where there
are no airfields. Non-fragile supplies can be
allowed to free fall from a low altitude, if
necessary. During severe winters or
drought, an aeroplane or helicopter can be
used to drop hay and other forage to keep
animals alive until the weather improves.
Mail delivery. This is no doubt the
oldest form of general aviation. Early airline
passenger routes were pioneered by the
pilots who flew the mail.
Prospecting for natural resources.
Mining firms use aircraft to carry special
detection instruments over land that has
good mining prospects. Water resources
can also be surveyed easily by aircraft.
Disaster relief. Following major floods
and earthquakes, the aircraft is usually the
quickest way to bring clothing, food, medi¬
cine and blood into a disaster area, as well
as to evacuate the injured.
Recreation. Perhaps the most fascina¬
ting development in sport aviation in recent
years is the increased interest in gliding,
manpowered flight and the most basic type
of flight of all hang gliding.
The recent development of the short
take-off and landing aircraft (STOL) has
been a boon to general aviation. It paves
the way to flights to many areas that have
only makeshift or short runways.
Another general aviation trend is the
renewed interest in lighter-than-air craft.
Experiments have already been conducted
in North America on the use of balloons for
logging; several firms have plans to build a
new generation of lighter-than-air craft.
But spectacular as these experiments
and sports may be, it is in the area of busi¬
ness and special purpose aviation that
general aviation will make its economic
impact during the next few decades.
The aircraft has joined the computer as
one of the great new tools of our time. And
both can be of benefit to developed and
developing countries.
The small community with an industrial
airport can now compete on a more equal
basis with big cities in bidding to attract
industries. In fact, some observers see the
growth of general aviation as a handmaid
of industrial decentralization.
Companies can be attracted to smaller
population centres by their proximity to
raw materials, by their lower land and ope¬
rating costs, and by better living conditions
for employees. General aviation makes
remote communities accessible to the
larger market centres.
If the past is any guide, men will con¬
tinue to find v new special uses for the
aeroplane.
Patrick Finn
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Art restorer...
Equestrian statue being carried
directly from the foundry to its
base in Cracow (Poland) in
1976. It now crowns the
reconstructed monument to
King Ladislas Jagello,
destroyed in World War II.
...Wildlife
protector...
Dancing on air, a young
elephant is airlifted to its
new home in Rwanda's
Akagera National Park as
part of a programme to
remove herds of elephants
that were roaming wild
across vitally needed
farmland.
Photo © Keystone, Pari Photo © Agence France-Presse, Pans
House mover... .Rescuer...
Metal hangar heads for an oil well
In an otherwise inaccessible spot in
Alaska. Drilling equipment was
also airlifted.
Passenger being hauled to safety in
1976 from a cable car that stalled
above the city of Grenoble in the
French Alps.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
...Archaeologist...
Many archaeological sites have
been spotted and identified
from the air. Outline of the
foundations of a Gallo-Roman
villa at Biarre (France) is
clearly visible on aerial photo
at right. Small white blob in
front of the main rectangular
building Indicates
the site of a fountain.
...Carrier...
Like some giant insect clasping its prey, a heavy-duty helicopter
takes a bus for a ride.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
*/
^cC
/"N
n «
^\ -».
.<
>»
/ .- ~
^ /..
sT*
*
i^
Safety^first
-i. m 4* .in
the air
Hs
Birds an<
same ain
damage <
impact w
maps foi
flvinn nn
irds and aircraft sometimes find themselves competing for the
sa e airspace. When they do the encounter often causes
and can be fatal. The cost of repairing planes after
ith birds runs into millions of dollars yearly. Special
r navigators show bird migration routes. Top photo:
flying ornithologists in the U.S. join a flock of Canadian geese to
study their migration habits.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
by Olof Fritsch
3
©
O
human race, born to fly upward,
wherefore at a little wind dost thou
so fall?".
Wind shear was not exactly what Dante
had in mind in his poetic outburst 600 years
ago. Yet he couldn't have been more to the
point about this weather hazard which,
along with birds and wake vortices, the
ICAO Council has called one of the three
major technical problems facing aviation
today.
Wind shear the sudden change in wind
with height and distance is not the worst
thing in an aviator's atmosphere, but it
rates high because of the element of sur¬
prise. Under certain circumstances it can
turn a smooth take-off or a final approach
into a sickening roll if not a dive at the end
of the runway.
For over 10 years, ICAO has been trying
to establish requirements for measuring
low-level wind shears and turbulence at
international airports, and to develop inter¬
national procedures for warning pilots
about them. It recently studied replies from
42 states and three international organiza¬
tions to three inquiries on the subject and
especially on the kind of information
needed to avoid these dangers.
These replies show that less than half of
the ICAO states are studying wind shear.
Several of them mentioned that studies
were difficult because of the complexity of
the problem and the need for sophisticated
equipment and facilities.
A few states, however, are carrying out
studies using instrument towers, experi¬
mental ground-based measuring devices
and data obtained by aircraft. Some of
these studies concentrate on wind data
provided by masts or towers in the vicinity
of aerodromes or, as in the United States,
on a variety of aspects, including manned
flight simulation, wind shear hazard defini¬
tions and digital simulation, wind shear
forecasts and the development of airborne
and ground-based detection and , mea¬
suring systems.
The United States reply noted that since
five of the last six air carrier wind shear
accidents in the U.S. were associated with
OLOF FRITSCH, Swedish pilot, is Chief of the
ICAO's Accident Investigation and Prevention
Section. He is also Vice-President of the Cana¬
dian Society of Air Safety Investigators.
thunderstorms, a major portion of their
research deals with measures to prevent
thunderstorm-related wind shear acci¬
dents.
ICAO is cautiously optimistic about the
progress of studies now under way. Some
useful results may be expected within one
to two years, mainly in respect of wind
shear effects on aircraft, aircraft instrumen¬
tation and pilot training. The development
of effective ground-based wind shear mea¬
suring equipment, however, is likely to take
longer.
The increasing use of wide-bodied jets
has highlighted a phenomenon which
exists to a certain extent with all aeroplanes
but which has now become a matter of
great importance. This is wake turbulence.
It is a simple enough phenomenon but
one with serious implications for aircraft
operations and airports. Every aeroplane in
flight generates wake vortices, pairs of
counter-rotating masses of air extending
backwards from the aircraft's wing tips and
flaps when extended.
The violent, fast-spinning but invisible air
masses trail for several kilometres behind
the aircraft. The greater the lift being pro¬
duced by the wing and the bigger the aero¬
plane, the more violent and long-lived the
vortices and the greater the danger for any
light aircraft which follow too closely
behind during take-off or landing.
The U.S. National Transportation Safety
Board has cited wake vortices as a contri¬
butory factor in 147 accidents in the United
States between 1963 and 1974. While most
involved light aircraft, one fatal accident
involved a DC-9 behind a DC-10. In the
United Kingdom, where the proportion of
light aircraft is small, especialiy at busy air¬
ports, there has so far been no accident
caused by wake vortices, but a number of
near accidents have been reported.
Vortex encounters occur most frequently
when aircraft are approaching an airport
since it is in this phase of flight that succes¬
sive aircraft are most likely to follow similar
flight paths. These types of encounters are
especially hazardous since the aircraft may
be close to the ground and the crew's
workload is high in this phase of flight.
At the time the B-747 entered service,
authorities in the U.K. imposed a distance
of 10 nautical miles or four minutes be
tween it and any following smaller aircraft
as a precaution during landing. This sepa¬
ration was later reduced to five nautical
miles or two minutes on the basis of results
of trials in the United Kingdom and the Uni¬
ted States. In the U.K., the five-minute
separation was maintained for small aircraft
following big planes, including Concorde.
In the U.S., the five-minute separation was
applied behind aircraft having a take-off
weight in excess of 135 tonnes. This inclu¬
des the heavier B-707's, DC-8's and
VC-10's.
Extensive theoretical and experimental
research on wake vortices has been carried
out in recent years by private industry and
government agencies in the U.S. and the
U.K. In May 1974, a joint agreement bet¬
ween the U.S. Department of Transporta¬
tion and the British Civil Aviation Authority
established a test site at Heathrow Interna¬
tional Airport in London which recorded
12,950 landings through June 1975.
A vortex test site is also in operation at
John F. Kennedy International Airport in
New York while a joint U.S. -Canadian pro¬
gramme to collect data on departing air¬
craft has been set up at Toronto Interna¬
tional Airport.
It is hoped that further developments in
ground sensors and comprehensive data
collection will enable experts to find ways
to reduce and dissipate the vortices.
Meanwhile, separation standards remain
the best possible way of coping with the
problem.
While man gets craftier, birds also
become smarter. Scaring them away from
aircraft is not an easy task even if modern
techniques are better than the farmer's
scarecrow.
There exists no "Convention on Air Traf¬
fic Control" to regulate whether birds or
aircraft have the right of way. Although
most people in aviation are aware of a "bird
problem", few realize its magnitude. As
reported in the ICAO Bulletin, eight aircraft
crashes have been attributed to birds since
1973. In 1976, two executive jets were
downed by birds. It is estimated that each
year there are 2,400 significant bird strikes
to civil aircraft, and repairs to damaged air¬
craft were said to run into millions of dol¬
lars.
Since civil jet aircraft spend most of their
flying time at altitudes not normally occu¬
pied by birds, the hazard exists mainly at,
and near, airports. It is during the critical
take-off and landing phases that aircraft
and birds occupy the same airspace.
Simply stated, the bird strike prevention
programme aims at keeping birds from
coming to the airport, driving away those
that do come, and reporting on those that
stay too long.
Birds may live at an airport, but, just as
often, they may only be visitors and, like k
any visitor, look for a place to eat, drink or r
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
r rest. The airport can be made unattractive
to them by draining wet areas and cutting
down trees. Other countermeasures, such
'as changing the ground cover or extermi¬
nating earthworms, are more complex.
Each airport requires its own study and
improvement plan.1"
However, these measures will not elimi¬
nate all birds from an airport. Like any tou¬
rist, different birds are looking for different
things. What may be unattractive to one
may be inviting to another. Airports offer
large areas which, except for aircraft, are
relatively undisturbed by man.
In one reported case birds had built a
nest in the engine intake of a turbo-prop
plane in only one and a half hours while the
aircraft was idle on the ground. An¬
other report noted that a group of jack¬
daws had hidden 72 pieces of metal in a
plane while it was in a hangar. The largest
piece was a wrench. With resourcefulness
¡ike this, the only solution is to remove all
birds to other nesting places far away from '
the airport.
The most common techniques currently
being used to drive birds away are loud noi¬
ses produced by shells or gas explosions, |
flashes of light, flares and recorded bird !
distress calls. These calls, played back
through sound systems, have been found
most effective.
Many airports now employ patrol teams
equipped with vehicles and dispersal equip¬
ment. The noise of guns usually keeps the
' birds away for a short while, but they may
soon come back or be replaced by new¬
comers. It doesn't take a bird long to figure
out that the noise below is produced by
man.
It is also important, therefore, to have a
reporting system that will inform pilots
when they may expect competition for the
same airspace. The control tower, assisted
by ground staff, can provide such informa¬
tion.
Radar is also used to detect flocks of
birds flying in the vicinity of airports. This is
particularly useful during bird migration
periods when extremely hazardous condi¬
tions may occur. Besides reporting on birds
near airports, charts have been published
that show the migration routes of birds.
Improvements in aircraft design have not
been ignored. Agreement has been
reached in ICAO that aircraft structures
should be designed so that aircraft can
continue to fly safely after impact with a
1.81-kilogramme bird.
Olof Fritsch
by John Marrett
ACTS of unlawful interference today
pose a serious threat to civil avia¬
tion. Like other major forms of
transportation in the past, aviation has in
recent years become a target for criminal
acts. The media usually describe this new
form of crime as "hijacking" or "air
piracy", using terms which evoke similar
offences on land and on the high seas.
All states must deal inexorably with
crime, and to protect their national inte¬
rests must take steps to combat these acts
of unlawful interference.
The President of the Council of ICAO, Dr
Assad Kotaite, drew attention to this issue
on 15 September 1977 during his address
to the 22nd session of the ICAO Assembly:
"Unfortunately, acts of unlawful inter¬
ference with international civil aviation and
its facilities continue to have a serious
adverse effect on the safety, regularity and
efficiency of international air transport. It is
imperative that all states take measures to
safeguard international civil air transport.
"The number of parties to the three
ConventionsTokyo (1963), The Hague
(1970) and Montreal (1971) is steadily
increasing. Our aim at ICAO is to achieve
universal acceptance of these instruments
and their full application to prevent the
occurrence of any acts endangering the
safety of international civil aviation."
The international community has expres¬
sed its concern about this form of crime
through a number of resolutions of the
United Nations, the most recent of which
,was adopted on 3 November 1977, and
through resolutions adopted by other inter¬
national organizations.
The Aviation Security Programme spon¬
sored by ICAO was drawn up in response
to this concern. It may be divided into two
complementary parts, legal and technical.
Three conventions dealing with the legal
aspects of the problem have been adopted
so far.
The Tokyo Convention, adopted as early
as 1963, was the first concrete action by
JOHN MARRETT of Jamaica joined the Inter¬
national Civil Aviation Organization in 1970 to
prepare its Security Manual and is now the
Organization's Aviation Security Officer.
World
against
the international community to draw up
legislation on the unlawful seizure of air¬
craft. It deals with offences, committed on
board aircraft registered in a Contracting
State while that aircraft is in flight.- At pre¬
sent, 88 states are parties to the Tokyo
Convention.
The Convention of The Hague, signed
on 16 December 1970, defines the act of
unlawful seizure of an aircraft. It contains
detailed provisions on states' jurisdiction
over an offence, on taking offenders into
custody, and on questions of prosecution
and extradition. The Convention has so far
been ratified by 79 states.
A year later, in September 1971, another
conference convened at Montreal under
the auspices of ICAO adopted a Conven¬
tion for the "suppression of unlawful acts
against the safety of civil aviation." The
Montreal Convention defines a wide spec¬
trum of unlawful acts and is concerned,
: broadly speaking, with acts of sabotage.
The Contracting States have undertaken to
make these offences punishable by severe
penalties. So far, 75 states have become
parties to this Convention.
On the technical side, the primary goal of
the ICAO aviation security programme is
the prevention of unlawful acts, but it also
deals extensively with measures to be
taken if preventive action fails. To help
states implement their own security pro¬
grammes, ICAO convenes informal regio¬
nal seminars, and in 1971 published a
manual on aviation security. The manual,
which provides detailed procedures and
guidance, is kept up to date by regularly
issued amendments.
Some states that have requested more
detailed technical assistance have been
provided with the services of an itinerant
aviation security expert. Funds have been
provided for this by the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP).
Other aviation security programmes have
been developed by such international orga¬
nizations as the International Criminal
Police Organization (IPCO-lnterpol); the
Universal Postal Union (UPU); the Interna¬
tional Air Transport Association (IATA);
the Airport Association Co-ordinating
Council (AACC); and the International
Federation of Air Line Pilots' Associations
(IFALPA).
The travelling public may therefore be
assured that the resources of the entire
world community have been and still are
being mobilized to promote the safe,
orderly and efficient development and use
of civil aviation in the interests of all the
peoples of the world.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
alert
hijacking
k ^ A decade
^^^^^ seizures: 483
k ^
of violence
J
^^^^ deaths: 1,137
i^^^^sabotage (threats): 18,411 j
injuries: 829
M persons detained: 31,84b ^j
^^^_îicts of sabotage: 145 ^
Record of almost ten years of violence (Jan. 1969 to Feb. 1978) to
passengers and crews of civil aircraft is shown here. The figures in this
diagram were compiled by the International Civil Aviation Organization
from news reports and other sources but they have no official status.
According to the same sources, such illegal acts affected no less than
41 airlines and 49 different countries in 1977 alone.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Flying
for thrills
by Oleg K. Antonov
In photo below the famous Soviet
engineer Oleg Antonov shows
models of aircraft he designed to
his son Andrei. Right, Antonov's
biggest cargo plane, an 80-tonne
AN-22, on a runway at Medvezji,
site of the richest natural gas
deposits in the Soviet Far North.
Several types of Soviet aircraft
flying with internal and
international airlines bear the
markings "A N", indicating that
they were designed by Oleg
Konstantinovich Antonov, the
noted Soviet aeronautical
engineer. The designer and
constructor of aircraft ranging
from small Red Cross planes to a
big 80-tonne transport, Antonov is
a Member of the Ukrainian
Academy of Sciences, a Hero of
Soviet Labour, and a Lenin Prize¬
winner. Since 1946 he has been
head of a major U.S.S.R.
Aeronautical Research and
Development Bureau. In the
following text, an extract from
his memoirs Ten Times Over
("Desiat' raz snachala"), he looks
back to the year 1932 when he
was beginning his career as a
glider constructor.
Photo © APN, Moscow
Text © Copyright
Reproduction prohibited
I am sitting in the cockpit at the controls
of my glider, my beloved brain-child,
as it lurches forward, throbbing and
humming under the quivering tension of
the shock-cord a rubber-stranded rope
stretched out by the ground crew to launch
the aircraft. Everything has been thought
through, everything calculated. Every pin,
every bolt has been driven in place to func¬
tion properly; every rivet locked in the hole
made for it; every lever stamped, bent,
welded, and there you have it that re¬
markable and yet simple apparatus
the glider.
So simple, in fact, that in medieval Rus¬
sia and in ancient Greece and even earlier,
in ancient India, craftsmen and materials
could have been found to build a glider
capable of flying hundreds of kilometres
and soaring for hours aloft. But there was
just one little thing missing the know-
how.
It would take man two or three thousand
years to solve an apparently simple prob¬
lem: fitting together pieces of wood, fabric
and a few metal elements to fashion what
goes nowadays by the unassuming name
of glider.
For a glider pilot there is no such thing as
an engine. He accustoms himself to the
discipline of gliding from the very first jerk
on the shock-cord.
The glider pilot has a golden rule which
he must never forget: "keep up speed."
There is no engine, no propeller thrust, so
forget about stepping on the gas and pull¬
ing the stick back to gain height. Keep
going, forward and down; forward and
down. If you lose concentration you lose
speed and down you go. A good glider will
go into a half-spin, or even a spin, and if
there's enough altitude, you'll come out of
it. But if there's not, say just 50 or 100
metres, you'd better not dawdle.
The minute you have an inkling you're
losing gliding speed, your hand automati¬
cally eases the stick. If you're flying in an
open cockpit, you feel the speed with your
whole being. With your face, with your
eyebrows, with your ears, from the slope
angle of the glider, from the pressure on
the stick, from the singing of the struts,
from the hissing of the air stream, from the
vibration of the cabin. Forward and down,
forward and down...
...But today the instructor is taking me
up in an engine-powered plane to do some
aerobatics in order to improve my skills.
The motor idles. The instructor and I
climb into the cabin. No parachutes. In
1932 parachute jumping was just getting
started as a popular sport. You flew
without a parachute in gliders, in small
aircraft, too. Why bother with a para¬
chute? Safety belts were also frowned
upon.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photo I. Sapojnikov © TASS, Moscow
We climb into the cockpit. A short run,
and we're airborne.
Emerald tufts of trees, pale yellow
specks of scorched grass, quadrangles and
rectangles of sunlit fields flash past the
green wings of our biplane.
I do some vertical turns. The cowling of
the plane swings along the horizon. I'm
pressed back in my seat. A bay looms up,
then a lilac chain of cliffs, the steppe,
mountains, sea, steppe, mountains,
seaeverything is spinning in a sparkling
iridescent whirlwind. The ailerons yaw,
increasing the pull on the stick. I am hold¬
ing it with both hands.
We come out of the turn...
The plane, as obedient as a good-
natured bumpkin, shifts into level flight.
Altitude: 800 metres.
"Well, how about a loop now!" shouts
the instructor. "Let's dive!"
I ease the stick away from me, the
plane's nose dips more, and still more,
we're accelerating... 120, 140, 160 km. an
hour.
"Pull the stick back."
I do. I'm pressed hard back against my
seat. The plane's nose rises, the horizon
tears by us, disappearing below.
"Stick full back!" the instructor yells.
As we climb, the speed slackens, and
there we are, flying wheels up, upside-
down. The noise of the engine subsides as
the instructor throttles back. We dive, we
come out of it... From behind, the horizon
below, bathed in the light of the sea, pas¬
ses us by.
My companion opens the throttle.
Great!
"Again!"
"I do another Nestérov loop." (*).
"Now for a wing-over!"
Once again we gather speed. I come out
on the horizon, stick full back, with my left
foot pushing the rudder bar to the limit. I'm
forced back against my seat as we bank to
the left. The plane, rolling over, is travelling
wheels up. But here the irrepressible condi¬
tioned reflex of the glider pilot takes over.
My hand, responding to an involuntary
impulse, shifts the stick into neutral. I feel
myself coming away from my seat, and...
At that instant, the only part of the plane
that I am conscious of, the only thing that
connects me with the plane, is the twine-
wrapped end of the control stick. And at
that very instant, the stick springs back
against me. I'm thrust against my seat.
The instructor has yanked back his stick,
changing the curved-line flight trajectory
that I had broken and restoring the centri¬
fugal force that retrieved us and kept us in
our seats.
And not a moment too soon. Had his
attention wandered for a fraction of a
second, our submissive little biplane would
have dumped us and left us floating
through space with no parachutes, just a
few hundred metres above a craggy slope,
alone with our thoughts about how useful
safety belts can be.
Oleg K. Antonov
(*) Piotr N. Nestérov, Russian engineer and aviator'
(1887-1914), significantly improved the manoeuvrability
of aircraft. One of the pioneers of aerobatics, he excu-
ted a loop in 1913 subsequently known as the "Nesté¬
rov loop"
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
WHAT shall we see in civil aviation
after the turn of the century?
Thousand-tonne flying wings
carrying 1,000 or more passengers? Hyper¬
sonic transports with unlimited range?
Spacecraft, regularly winging their way to
and from Earth orbital missions?
Some of these craft will be operational
early in the 21st century; others may not
reach fruition before the year 2025; yet
others may never see service at all. But
they all exist today, either as concepts in
the minds of aircraft designers and engi¬
neers or at some stage of development. A
few are already with us as experimental
vehicles.
The problem with crystal-balling in the
aviation field, as in others, is that major
technological advances do not always
occur when the world is ready for them.
During the period between the conception
of an experimental aircraft and its success¬
ful demonstration, non-technical obstacles
may crop up to prevent the normal progres¬
sion from testing and evaluation to opera¬
tional use. The opposite may also happen:
prototypes at an advanced stage of deve¬
lopment may become obsolete because of
a major technological breakthrough.
The consensus today in the civil aviation
industry is that between now and the year
2000 there will be no major design changes
in the world's commercial aircraft. Both the
airframe manufacturers and the airlines
26
The shape
of things
to come
by Charles D. LaFond
CHARLES D. LAFOIMD has been editor-in-
chief of the ICAO Bulletin, the monthly technical
journal of the International Civil Aviation Organi¬
zation, since 1971. Previously, he was for 20
years an aerospace-magazine writer in the
United States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Tomorrow's aircraft are already on
the drawing board and in some cases
models are being tested in wind or
hydraulic tunnels where various
flying conditions are simulated.
Special optical instruments are used
to record the movement of air or
water as they flow around the model,
sometimes producing surprising
visual effects. Turbulent flow round a
cylindrical fuselage (left) in hydraulic
test tunnel at Châtillon (France)
shows up as a haunting owl-eyed
mask. Below, model of a supersonic
commercial transport developed In
high-speed wind tunnels at a
research centre in Virginia (U.S.A.).
Multiple exposure photo shows
wings outsretched for take-off and
landing, folded halfway back for
medium speeds and almost flush with
fuselage during supersonic flight.
expect new aircraft during the next tew
decades to be derivatives of today's
designs. They will be shortened or"
stretched. They will have more or fewer
engines, and passenger craft will be modi¬
fied so that they can be more easily con¬
verted to carry freight. Engines will be
quieter and produce less pollutants. Range
may be extended, and take-off and landing
runs may be shortened. But for those of us
on the ground, the narrow-body transports
will look about the same as today's. So will
the large, wide-body aircraft, though they
may possibly be bigger.
The reasons for this are largely econo¬
mic. The cost of new aircraft continues to
escalate. The air transport industry is still
growing, but at a much slower rate than
anticipated. The cost of fuel is still moun¬
ting as available world supplies diminish.
In the longer term, however, the picture
may not be so bleak. In all the industrial¬
ized countries, intensive research has been
going on for years in key areas that would
permit radical changes in aircraft design.
Research into advanced materials alone
is already producing structures which com¬
bine enormously increased Strength with
significant reductions in weight. New
engine designs, backed up by sophisticated
research in acoustics, may prove so effec¬
tive in the not-too-distant future that the
next major step in reducing aircraft noise
will have to come from the airframe itself.
Fuel research is introducing an entirely
new factor into the equation. Synthetic
fossil fuels, liquid hydrogen and nuclear
power are all being studied today as poten¬
tial power alternatives. However, given
today's technology and the lack of interna¬
tional commitment, the practical use of
either liquid hydrogen or nuclear energy for
aircraft propulsion is a long way off.
Advanced wing configuration is another
area of research that is already paying off.
Some models, now in an advanced stage
of development, have been shown to com¬
bine enormous lift for heavy payloads with
short take-off and landing (STOL) capabili¬
ties. As a result, we may see vastly differ¬
ent wing structures coming into use in the i
next century, as well as the possibility of a |
Photo © USIS, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
New
silhouettes
in the air
There are two major
trends in aeronautical
research today. One Is
the result of a quest for'
higher speed; the other'
stems from a search for
greater economy.
Designs for future high¬
speed planes
incorporate wings that
are smaller and
increasingly tucked into
the fuselage. The
search for economy, on
the other hand,
produces wings that are
stretched, have less
sweep and are thicker.
The fuselage tends to
disappear. Drawings,
right, show these two
trends in aircraft design.
Increased
thickness
(giant cargo)
Increased
sweep,
slimmer fuselage
Today's
subsonic
Delta wing
(supersonic,
hypersonic)
Stretched thick fuselage
(hypersonic.
Space Shuttle)#-
Drawing J.M. Troillard © Science et Vie, Paris
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
transonic transport operating at slightly
over the speed of sound.
Let us look at some of the research now
in progress.
The use of composite materials for the
manufacture of aircraft structural parts is a
relatively recent field, although the devel¬
opment of bonded glass fibre began as far
back as 1940. This technology consists of
producing structures of virtually any shape
by stacking and moulding layers of diffe¬
rently oriented fibres contained in a plastic
base.
The so-called advanced reinforced com¬
posites which emerged in the mid-1960s
incorporate boron filaments whose
strength and high performance instantly
appealed to aeronautic engineers. Today
composites are replacing more and more
metal structures because of the weight and
cost savings and greater fuel economy that
can be achieved.
The really important thing about compo¬
sites is that the selection of fibre material
and the lamination of layers with fibres run¬
ning in different directions for each layer
permit an end product that fits specific
structural needs. For example, composites
can guarantee good bending strength for
one piece and keep costs down in another
which is only subjected to low stress. It
has been estimated that, compared with
metals, advanced composites can bring
energy savings of up to 33 per cent and
weight savings approaching 30 per cent.
A relatively new material has been pro¬
duced by what is called "whisker" techno¬
logy, in which nearly perfect crystalline
structures of carbon provide a specific
strength approximately 50 times that of
steel.
One major U.S. airframe manufacturer
estimates that up to 75 per cent of an air¬
craft could be made from composites, pri¬
marily graphite epoxy, and that the overall
cost would be 21 per cent less than that of
its metal counterpart. As the airframe
would be much lighter, fuel consumption
would be reduced by about 30 per cent.
With today's technology, such an aircraft
could be built by the 1980s or early 1990s,
and operational soon after.
What kind of fuel will be used in the early
2000s? Most experts believe that conven¬
tional kerosene jet fuel will be the basic civil
aviation source well into the next century.
As we approach the year 2000, however,
alternative fuels may have to be intro¬
duced.
Synthetic kerosene, obtained from coal
and shale, could be mixed directly with
petroleum-based fuels, giving an end-
product whose properties would be similar
to those of today's jet fuel. Coal and shale
supplies appear to be large, and such a fuel
would require few changes in storage and
ground handling and could readily be used
in conventional aircraft. However, some
specialists feel strongly that a major com¬
mitment should now be made to devel¬
oping the use of liquid methane or liquid
hydrogen as a fuel. In either case, a new
aircraft design would be required.
For the same weight of fuel, liquid
methane can provide 20 per cent more heat
than kerosene. Its density is about half and
its cost about the same as kerosene fuels.
But liquid methane only exists at very Ipw
temperatures ( 161 °C at atmospheric
pressure), like liquid hydrogen( °C),
and thus creates storage and handling pro¬
blems. Although its higher heating value
reduces the total fuel needed to carry a
load over a given distance,' the improve¬
ment is only modest. Because it is lighter,
bigger fuel tanks are required.
More interest has been shown in an air¬
craft fuelled by liquid hydrogen because of
its even higher heating value: 280 per cent
that of kerosene for the same weight of
fuel. The trouble is that its density is only
one-twelfth that of kerosene. Thus the
liquid hydrogen needed to produce the
same energy as kerosene fuel, while weigh¬
ing only 35 per cent as much, requires a
volume four times as great.
Obviously, then, an aircraft using liquid
hydrogen would require a larger, heavier
fuselage with greater aerodynamic drag
and consequently reduced efficiency. At
the same time it would have a lower gross k
weight at take-off, thus requiring lessf
i
Windmill
effect
Photo taken during experiment
in a hydraulic test tunnel shows
simulated airflow patterns
created by the rotor blades of a
helicopter.
Materials
under the
microscope
Research into advanced
materials which combine
increased strength with reduced
weight has led to the
development of new alloys.
Right, a nickel and niobium
carbonate alloy seen through a
microscope.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Fuel
of the future?
Liquid hydrogen is a possible fuel for
aircraft of the future. However, It
would require a new aircraft design
incorporating giant fuel tanks (right).
Space Shuttle
on piggyback
The U.S. Space Shuttle has already
made its first free flight after being
launched from a specially
adapted carrier (here shown taking
off). When fully operational it will
leave Earth powered by its twin
rockets, go into orbit, perform a
space mission and then return and
land like a glider. After refuelling it
will be ready for its next flight.
Swinging wings
One proposed design for tomorrow's
aircraft is the oblique-wing plane
which would fly at slightly over the
speed of sound. The wing, located
atop the fuselage. Is rotated as the
aircraft gathers speed. (In wind
tunnel testing it has already been
turned as much as 50°.) If maximum
speed is carefully controlled no sonic
boom is created.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
y energy per kilometre than conventional air¬
craft. On a long flight the energy economy
would be significant. Nevertheless, cost is
a serious hurdle.
Another problem that cannot be taken
lightly is the storage and handling of liquid
hydrogen. One expert estimates that the
complex required at a major international
airport for the storage and handling of
liquid hydrogen for wide-body jets would
be 30 times the size of the gigantic U.S.
Apollo Space Programme installations near
New Orleans.
The proponents of liquid hydrogen,
however, stress a number of advantages of
this fuel. There would be a dramatic reduc¬
tion in the noxious exhaust fumes from
commercial transport aircraft. The major
exhaust product of liquid hydrogen is water
vapour, with minute amounts of oxides of
hydrogen. With careful design, they
assert, the latter could be reduced far
below that of equivalent kerosene-fuelled
jet engines.
Furthermore, hydrogen-fuelled superso¬
nic transport aircraft of the future would
generate a lighter supersonic boom, and
these second- or third-generation superso¬
nic transports will require 40 per cent less
energy than if synthetic jet fuel is used.
As we near the end of the century, new
aircraft, particularly those operating in the
subsonic and transonic ranges, may benefit
from current developments in wing aerody¬
namics and even from entirely new con¬
cepts in the use of wing structures.
Some of these changes may not even be
noticed by the casual observer. For exam¬
ple, by increasing wing thickness or redu¬
cing sweep, we may significantly reduce
the weight of. wings and greatly improve
aerodynamic efficiency. The result would
be lower fuel consumption or much smaller
engine sizes to carry the same payload over
a given distance. Another by-product
could be reduced noise on the approach to
airports.
Other, even more sophisticated changes
in wing design involve controlling the air¬
flow around the wings in order to reduce
turbulent flow and thereby reduce drag.
This could result in fuel savings of as much
as 50 per cent.
An even stranger-looking design is the
proposed oblique-wing aircraft, which
would fly at speeds slightly over that of
sound. A relatively long, narrow, straight
wing is located atop the fuselage, forming
a shape which turns out to be ideal for both
low-speed and high-speed flight. As the
aircraft picks up speed, the wing is rotated.
In wind-tunnel testing it has been turned as
much as 50°. The remarkable thing is that
at low supersonic speeds (up to Mach 1.5)
in the wind tunnel such asymmetrical
models have been found to be more stable
than models of conventional aircraft. Also,
if the maximum speed is carefully control¬
led, no sonic boom is created.
Because of new developments in shield¬
ing nuclear reactors and successful tests
which have shown that there would be no
release of radioactive material in the event
of a crash, we may see nuclear power
coming to the fore for aircraft propulsion.
The temperatures generated are suffi¬
cient to drive a turbofan engine suitable for
powering subsonic transports. However,
because of the concentrated weight of the
reactor and its shielding, very large aircraft
would be required, probably weighing in at
500 tonnes or more. A nuclear-powered
transport aircraft could provide a range
equal to some 10,000 continuous flight
hours without refuelling.
In the same weight range or larger is the
"flying wing" that many designers have
dreamed of for years. Some feel that the
flying wing, unencumbered as it is with the.
long body structure of conventional air-^
Pedalling
on air
On 23 August 1977 the first successful man-powered flight took place in California (U.S.A.). At the
controls of the flimsy-looking Gossamer Condor was a young hang-glider pilot and bicycle racer,
Bryan Allen, who triumphantly walked off with an $86,000 prize awarded by British industrialist Henry
Kremer. Competitors had been trying to win it for 18 years. Propelling the craft with a bicycle-pedal
mechanism, he flew the figure-eight course around two pylons 800 metres apart in seven minutes. *
The craft, designed by aeronautical engineer Paul MacCready, was made of piano wires, aluminium
tubing and see-through plastic. With a wingspan of 28 metres, it weighed only 32 kilos.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
, craft, is the most efficient design obtain¬
able. Others believe it to be inherently
unstable.
The wing required for take-off and lan¬
ding would have to be deep enough to pro¬
vide lift, and would thus have enough room
for the payload- possibly 1,500 to 2,000
passengers and 300 tonnes of car¬
go could be distributed over the
entire span. A first-generation vehicle
could use conventional engines, while
second-generation flying wings might have
a fusion reactor. The later version would
have an unlimited range; its cruising speed
would be some 1,000 km. per hour.
Looking further ahead, we may even¬
tually see an even more revolutionary air¬
craft, capable of travelling at Mach 6 i.e.
six times the speed of sound. The fuel,
liquid hydrogen, would also be used to cool
the aircraft's skin, compensating for the
enormous heat generated at such a high
speed. Researchers look on the Mach 6
hypersonic transport as the logical succes¬
sor of the March 3-4 class supersonic trans¬
ports of the nearer future, which will pro¬
bably also be powered by liquid hydrogen.
Why Mach 6? The answer is that this
seems to be the upper speed limit that fits
the practical journey times for long-range
flights of from 8,000 to 10,000 km. Such a
hypersonic plane, carrying between 300
and 400 passengers and looking not much
different from today's Anglo-French delta-
wing Concorde, except in size, would make
the non-stop trip from Los Angeles to Paris
in less than three hours.
Although there seems little doubt in the
minds of many scientists today that such a
craft could be built some time early in the
21st century, there certainly is some doubt
as to its practicality. Nevertheless, experi¬
mental versions of ramjet engines neces¬
sary for powering the hypersonic transport
are already in research and development.
Much closer on the horizon, however, is
a vehicle that represents an equally radical
departure from the norm: the U.S. Space
Shuttle. It is the first offspring of the mar¬
riage between aerodynamics (it is a glider)
and space technology (it uses rocket con¬
trol when in space). This large aerospace
transport vehicle is now well ahead in deve¬
lopment.
The first re-usable space transport
system, the shuttle will leave Earth boosted
by immense twin solid propellant rockets,
go into orbit, manoeuvre in space as re¬
quired to perform its mission, then return
and land without powersomething like a
conventional jet transport aircraft, except
that the pilot will have to control it like a gli¬
der during a lengthy landing approach.
After refuelling, it should be ready for its
next flight and could be used for hundreds
of missions.
The first fully operational flight of the
Space Shuttle is expected in 1980,
and the life of the programme as pre¬
sently conceived could carry it up to the
turn of the century. And if these missions
are successful, one can expect that at
some point during the next 20 years a
follow-up programme for an even more
versatile Shuttle might evolve. For this is
just the beginning.
Charles D. LaFond
Landing
on laser beams
A new landing system using laser beams was perfected in late 1977 by Soviet
scientist Igor Berezhnol. Known as Glissada, the system reduces the pilot's
reliance on his instrument panel in conditions of poor visibility or at night. Five
powerful red beams (left), which présent no danger to vision, are visible 20 km.
away. Three of them indicate the edges and centre line of the runway; the other
two show the glide path. Schematic representations above show what the pilot
sees on his glide path as he comes in to land: 1.) plane is left of course; (2.) on
course; (3.) right of course. Shown below, plane touching down at night with the
aid of Glissada. The new system is already being patented in sixteen countries
including the U.S.A., the U.K., the Fed. Rep. of Germany and France.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Bookshelf
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
The Image of the Buddha, edited by
David L. Snellgrove. A major study of
the many forms in which the ¡deal of
Buddhahood has found artistic expres¬
sion over some 2,500 years. 58 colour
plates and 310 black and white illustra¬
tions. 1978, 482 pp., Co-published with
Kodansha International Ltd., Tokyo,
who are exclusive distributors for the
U.S.A. Other exclusive distributors:
Serindia Publications for the U.K. and
Vikas publishers for India. (220 F).
Maori Art of New Zealand, by
Terence Barrow. Co-published with A.H.
and W. Reed, Australia and New Zea¬
land. 1978, 108 pp. Illus. (28 F).
Population Education: a Contem¬
porary Concern. 1978, 120 pp. (No. 28
in Unesco's "Educational Studies and
Documents" series) (14 F).
Aspects of Algerian Cultural
Policy, by Sid-Ahmed Baghli. 1978, 57
pp. (10 F).
Communication Policies In Japan,
by Hidetoshi Kato. 1978, 57 pp. (12 F).
Growing up In Cities, edited by
Kevin Lynch. Studies of the environment
of adolescents in Cracow, Melbourne,
Mexico City, Salta (Argentina), Toluca
(Mexico) and Warsaw. 1977, 177 pp.
Illus. Co-published with the MIT Press,
Cambridge, Mass., U.S.A. and London,
U.K., who have exclusive sales rights in
U.S.A. and U.K. (48 F).
Namibia: the Effects of Apartheid
on Culture and Education, by Marion
O'Callaghan. 1977, 169 pp. (35 F).
Race and Class In Post-Colonial
Society. A study of ethnic group rela¬
tions in the English-speaking Caribbean,
Bolivia, Chile and Mexico. 1977, 458 pp.
(65 F).
Ecosocial Systems and Ecopolitics,
Edited by Karl W. Deutsch. A reader on
human and social implications of envi¬
ronmental management in developing
countries. 1977, 368 pp. (70 F).
Handbook on the International
Exchange of Publications, edited by
Frans Vanwijngarden. 1978, 165 pp.
(38 F).
Statistics of Educational Attain¬
ment and Illiteracy 1945-1974. A report
covering 202 countries and territories,
prepared with the co-operation of the
U.N. Statistical Office. (No. 22 in
Unesco's "Statistical Reports and Stu¬
dies" series) 1977, 233 pp. (26 F).
Directory of Documentation, Libra¬
ries and Archives Services in Africa,
by Dominique Zidouemba (revised and
enlarged by Eric de Grolier). 1977,
311 pp. (60 F).
Thai airport plan takes off
With the help of the United Nations Develop¬
ment Programme (UNDP) Thailand has laun¬
ched an airport development plan to bring its
domestic air services into the jet age. A master
plan will be drawn up incorporating the develop¬
ment needs of the country's 31 domestic air¬
ports, many of them in remote areas which can
only be reached by air.
Apartheid and sickness
On the occasion of the International Day for the
Elimination of Racial Discrimination (21 March
1978), which coincided with the launching of
International Anti-Apartheid Year, Dr. Halfdan
Mahler. Director-General of the World Health
Organization, reaffirmed WHO'S condemnation
of apartheid in these terms: "The destructive
invasion of apartheid into all spheres of human
existence has not spared one of the most cher¬
ished human values: health. There is an enor¬
mous gap between the state of health of the
white minority and that of the black majority.
The patterns and levels of nutrition, sickness
and mortality of whites and blacks are so diffe¬
rent that it would be difficult to believe that they
refer to populations which have been living
within the same country for centuries."
Cape Verde
Unesco's
144th Member State
The Republic of Cape Verde signed the constitu¬
tion of Unesco on 15 February 1978, bringing the
total number of Unesco Member States to 144.
The Cape Verde Islands (capital Praia on San¬
tiago island), a former Portuguese colony situa¬
ted in the Atlantic 500 km. from the African
coast, is a major stopping-off point for transat¬
lantic shipping.
Blind dolphins of the Indus
In 1974 only 50-odd fresh-water dolphins were
alive in the Indus river, and this rare species
faced extinction. Today numbers have risen
(198, including some 30 babies, were recently
counted) thanks to conservation measures taken
by the Pakistani authorities with the aid of the
World Wildlife Fund based in Morges (Switzer¬
land). The Indus dolphin, which lives in muddy
waters, has lost the use of its eyes and relies on
a highly developed sonar system to move about
and find food.
Clean air
for the Acropolis
For the first time since the World Health Organi¬
zation (WHO) began its environmental pollution
control project in Athens there has been a dra¬
matic drop (50% for the period mid-Nov. 1977 to
mid-Jan. 1978) in the level of sulphur dioxide
which causes much of the Greek capital's air
pollution. A regulation issued by the Greek
government, on the recommendation of WHO,
has prohibited the use of heavy high sulphur oils
for heating in the Athens area. This measure,
which has not only improved health conditions
in Athens but also removed a major cause of the
deterioration of the Acropolis monuments, fol¬
lows a series of studies carried out with the aid
of Unesco specialists.
New Unesco records
Two new titles have been released in the
Unesco-sponsored "Musical Atlas" record col¬
lection (Odeon/EMI): Music of the Baka
Pygmies of Cameroon (3C 064-18265) and Tradi¬
tional Arab Music from Morocco (3C
064-18264). Forthcoming recordings in the
Unesco-sponsored "Musical Sources" collec¬
tion (Philips) include Australian Aboriginal
Music, Religious Songs from Corsica, and
Osawa Daiko Japanese Drums. (The Unesco
record collections are edited for the International
Music Council by the International Institute for
Comparative Music Studies.) Please do not send
orders to Unesco. Order through your local
record dealer.
Drought and hunger
in the Sahel
The food situation in the African Sahel following
last year's drought is worse than at first expec¬
ted, reports Mr. Edouard Saouma, Director-
General of the Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion of the United Nations (FAO). Upper Volta,
Mali and Chad have joined Mauritania, Senegal
and Gambia on the list of stricken countries. Aid
operations, co-ordinated by the World Food
Programme, have been going on since the
beginning of the crisis in September 1977.
Cultural co-operation
in Europe
A new plan for cultural co-operation involving 22
European countries has been adopted by the
Council of Europe in Strasbourg. The plan inclu¬
des six major projects on the following themes:
secondary education and preparation for life;
innovations in higher education; the develop¬
ment of adult education; modern languages tea¬
ching; cultural development policies; and culture
and the media.
Human Rights:
signed but not yet ratified
In our November 1977 issue, we indica¬
ted in footnotes (pages 29 and 32) that
69 Member States had ratified or acce¬
ded to the International Covenant on
Economic, Social and Cultural Rights,
and that ¿8 States had ratified or acce¬
ded to the International Covenant on
Civil and Political Rights. We also listed
28 countries as having ratified or acce¬
ded to the Optional Protocol relating to
the Covenant on Civil and political
Rights. In point of fact, these figures did
not represent ratifications or accessions
to the Covenants and to the Protocol but
more broadly to tfie number of States
which had merely signed them. Not all
the States which have signed these ins¬
truments have formally ratified or acce¬
ded tothem. We ask readers to excuse
this confusion of terms which do not
have the same legal weight. As of April
1978 49 States had ratified or acceded to
the first of these Covenants, 47 the
second, and 18 the Protocol.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to the editor
A YOUTHFUL VOICE
ON WORLD PROBLEMS
Sir,
Several critical problems face the world
today and increasingly menace its future.
The main problem is overpopulation, mainly
in the poor countries where there is a need .
for education and information. Population is
increasing at an immense rate, and feeding
all these people is becoming a big problem.
For the moment, the U.S.A., the
U.S.S.R. and Europe have enough surplus
food to supply the poor countries. But in¬
stead of doing this we live on a mountain of
products that we can hardly consume. We
waste and eat far too much rich and fat
food, and in so doing we threaten our own
health.
Why is this waste and over-consumption
so dangerous? Consumption needs produc¬
tion, and production needs energy, lots of
energy, and energy comes mostly from oil,
which will be used up by 1995-2000. It is the
poor countries that need oil in order to deve¬
lop technologically advanced agriculture to '
supply their starving people.
Why is nuclear energy not a solution?
Nuclear energy needs uranium and
plutonium and they will be used up in
about 50 years.
The fact that $43 million are spent every
hour on military purposes throughout the
world, day and night, does not make the
situation easier. Isn't it ridiculous to spend so
much money on weapons that are only used
to kill? All the weapons in the world today
could kill the Earth's population about 20
times over.
Pollution in water, air and soil have ecolo¬
gical effects and bring about climatic
changes. These effects could destroy agri¬
culture and drastically cut down the produc¬
tion of food.
I could go on listing problems for ever, but
these are the most important. They are pro¬
bably too big for an individual to cope with
but they are certainly not insoluble if we all
work together. For many people who are not
young and do not have their whole lives in
front of them find it hard to see what they
could do.
Educating and informing your children and
grandchildren is very, very important, giving
them love and respect so that they will go
out into the world with high moral values
and a determination to solve problems.
For young people it is best to choose to
educate yourselves as much as possible and
choose a job that can help the world; for
example as doctors, engineers, agricultural
economists, politicians, missionaries, etc.
I hope that we can together make a decent
future for ourselves and for posterity,
although the future is full of big problems.
Hakan Björkman
16 years old
Brussels
SHOULD HUMAN RIGHTS
BE COMPULSORY?
Sir,
I should like to draw your attention to arti¬
cle 26 (1) of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights, the full text of which you
published in your November 1977 issue.
This article declares that everyone has the
right to education and that in the elementary
and fundamental stages it shall be free. No
one could quarrel with this. Why then does
the article continue by saying that "elemen¬
tary education shall be compulsory"? Is the
Declaration excluding the rights of children
(or their parents) not to be compelled if they
so choose?
I know the argument that where education
is not compulsory poor communities have no
choice but to put their children to work
rather than sending them to school, but who
is to say that they are wrong in so doing? I
think a clause insisting on compulsion has no
place in a document dealing with human
rights.
Sheila M.S. Thomson
London, U.K.
Editor's note. Prof. K. Vasak, Director of
Unesco's Division of Human Rights and
Peace, replies:
The problem of negative human rights is a
formidable one. If we have the right to live,
should we not also have the right to die? If
we have the right to marry, do we not also
have the right not to marry?
But if we all have the right to freedom and
personal security, we certainly do not have
the right to renounce this right and opt for
slavery.
What this boils down to is that the interna¬
tional community, rightly or wrongly, consi¬
ders that certain human rights involve not
only individuals but also the society at large.
Consequently, the international community
insists that such rights be exercised (or not
be exercised) in a certain way. The right to
education is one of these. The international
community is convinced that, to be a human
being worthy of the name, a person must
benefit from primary education: hence pri¬
mary education should be compulsory. The
problem is similar to that posed above with
respect to freedom and security of the per¬
son, and their negation slavery.
Obviously, one does not have to agree
with the international community. In disa¬
greeing. Miss Thomson is exercising her
human right to freedom of opinion and
expression.
Sadriddin Ayni
A great Central Asian poet of freedom
APRIL 1978 marks the centenary of the
birth of Sadriddin Ayni, a great and
original writer who wrote in two
languagesTadzhik and Uzbek both of
which are spoken in his native region of
Bukhara (in what is today Soviet Central
Asia). The works of Sadriddin Ayni, who
died in 1954, are widely read in the U.S.S.R.,
where they have been translated into 36 lan¬
guages. But even outside the U.S.S.R.,
there had been 300 publications of his
works by 1970.
The son of a craftsman, he was orphaned
at 11 years of age, and in order to continue
his studies in a madrasah (a, Muslim reli¬
gious school) he worked as a street swee¬
per and a porter, and took a number of
other jobs. When he was 18, he began to
write poems, many of which were inspired
by popular festivals and fairs.
An educator as well as a poet, Sadriddin
Ayni developed a critical attitude towards
the feudal regime in Bukhara which altered
the course of his life. In 1905 he headed a
pioneering school in Bukhara which prac¬
tised new teaching methods, and when the
school was closed down by the clergy, he
and his supporters organized clandestine
Sadriddin Ayni in 1925
lessons for illiterate adults. Ten years later
he was forced to flee from his native city
because of his opposition to the regime.
On his return to Bukhara in Spring 1917,
he was arrested, brutally beaten and
thrown into jail where he stayed until his
release by the soldiers of the Revolution.
But it was only after 1920 and the fall of the
Emir of Bukhara that Sadriddin began to
express himself fully and freely as a writer
and an educator, taking an active part in the
creation of the country's first Soviet
schools and writing a number of handbooks
for teachers.
But although Sadriddin Ayni was a poet,
he was above all a writer of prose. His rich
experience of life, his profound knowledge
of the customs and traditions of Tadzhikis-
tan and Uzbekistan and his constant stri¬
ving for freedom permeate all his work,
from the stories in The Hangman of Buk¬
hara (1922) to his epic novel Slaves (1934-
1935) and his four volumes of Memoirs
(1948-1954).
A humanist
Sadriddin Ayni
work as an edu
end of his life.
Tadzhikistan S.S
founded in 1951,
member of the
Sciences.
of encyclopaedic range
unflaggingly pursued his
cator and writer until the
The first President of the
R.'s Academy of Sciences,
he was also an honorary
Uzbekistan Academy of
Q
<
O
o
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Why not subscribe
to other Unesco periodicals?
CULTURES explores the world of art and culture, reviews recent developments in theatre, crafts and cinema, and
examines the role of cultural institutions in modern society.
Annual subscription: 75 French francs
IMPACT OF SCIENCE ON SOCIETY reports on science as a major force for social change, emphasizing the
interrelationship of science, technology and human development.
Annual subscription: 40 FF
PROSPECTS covers all aspects of education, especially innovations in school systems around the world.
Annual subscription: 42 FF
MUSEUM presents the latest developments in museum display, conservation, finance, security and management, for
layman and specialist alike. Illustrated.
Annual subscription: 72 FF
NATURE AND RESOURCES offers an interdisciplinary approach to news about scientific research on the
environment, natural resources and conservation of nature.
Annual subscription: 20 FF
INTERNATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE JOURNAL takes a broad look at what's happening in social science theory
and practice.
Annual subscription: 70 FF
All published quarterly
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Ham, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch-
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Qué H3H
1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed, only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH Karger Buchhandlung. Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034Germering/Munchen. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémial Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. SnaebjornJonssonErCo., H.F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranian Avenue, Cal¬
cutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf
Ah Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-
560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book 8- Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016;
Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of
Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish
ing and Distribution Co., 139 Shah Reza Ave., opposite to Uni¬
versity of Teheran, P.O. Box 14/1480, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication £r Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. MAURI¬
TIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition
only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-
1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTIL¬
LES. G CT. Van Dorp Et Co. (Ned Ant ), N.V., Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing
Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box
5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christ-
church; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street,
P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Welling¬
ton. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The Univer¬
sity Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A S. Narvesens Literaturje-
neste. Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65
Sarah Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIPPI¬
NES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632,
Manila D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I
Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.
7 00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias Er Andrade Ltda,
Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal Publi¬
cations (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New industrial Road, off Upper Paya
Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPU¬
BLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadis¬
cio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van Schaik's Book¬
store (Pty.) Ltd , Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 924,
Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SOUTHERN
RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue,
Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chit-
tampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo2. SUDAN.
AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN.
All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Freds-
gatan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier: Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65,
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Ver¬
lag, 5 Rámistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, C.C.P. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469
Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istambul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145. Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM.
H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and
Government Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol. UNITED STATES. Uni-
pub, Box 433 Murray Hill Station New York, N.Y. 10016. -
U.S.S R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazije, 27, Belgrade;
Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljublana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Fasten
your seat belts!
\
/
In 1911, when this group posed on a French Farman plane for a
souvenir photo, only eight years had elapsed since the first powered
plane flight, but aviation had already made great progress. In that
year, more than 1,350 planes were built around the world; pioneering
airmail services began in Europe, the United States and India; and the
Frenchman Louis Bréguet broke a record by piloting no less than 10
passengers! In 1911, 12,000 passengers took to the air (more than
twice as many as in 1910). In the last three decades (1947-1977) civil
aircraft have carried almost 6 billion passengers-one and a half
times the world's population.
]]>
</page>
</document>
