<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074814eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^~*\^ A window open on the world
«»Lourier
August - September 1977 (30th year) 5.60 French francs
LATIN AMERICA
composite profile of a continent
<w*
m
ff;'' " '?& '»"
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
v
w
V
1
k
,
v ft ¡F.'S^v BmF- . . ;tjh# ^H
m.
,tK£' jy. a > i, ¡* L* ^^H
;V,* * Hk 1 Bfet "'^
>á fei' 11 ''L?/ '* ^
1
1 1 ^ *»
x. '
V -, *,£%»* WH
' JWUifl
' ;-'*m
<9i »
'SB J
1 Ei-
V
' \flfl BT ^^ If '
« »«iflp5
v'"
V P. " JBB^^^
.
^1
Bat.
bk ^t^T^ v^hK
r . ^BW ^^"^Hp
HHB^HHBlV.
^h1
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
@
El Salvador
The man in the bird's beak
During its Classic period (4th to 9th centuries A.D.), Maya civilization stretched from its heartland in the Peten
lowlands of Guatemala to Palenque in southern Mexico and Copan in Honduras. The Mayas were outstanding
sculptors, fashioning works whose realism, elegance and minute detail contrast strongly with the simplicity and
abstract forms of the sculptures produced during the same period by the Olmec and Teotihuacán civilizations of
Mexico. Above, flattened head of a man set in a bird's beak. Carved by a Mayan sculptor from a block of granite
23.5 cm. high, it was discovered in El Salvador.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1977 30TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 16 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese Dutch
Italian Portuguese
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Turkish
Urdu
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 28 French Francs
2 years: 52 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier Is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A. ; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street. New York, U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
France
Managing Editors
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
Dutch Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu Edition
: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
: Werner Merkli (Berne) .
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
; Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
page -
4 LATIN AMERICA
The long journey to self-discovery
By Leopoldo Zea
8 THE BLACKS IN LATIN AMERICA
Africa's imprint on the art and life of another continent
By Alejo Carpentier
13 THE AFRO-BRAZILIAN EXPERIMENT
By Gilberto Freyre
18 WHERE GODS AND MEN HAVE MINGLED
By Jorge Amado
21 A MATTER OF LIFE AND DEATH
Aztec myths and Christian beliefs in Mexico
By Octavio Paz
23 THE PASSION ACCORDING TO THE YAQUIS
Photo story
28 FIESTA OF DEATH
Photo story
30 OUT OF THE TROPICS, AN AVANT-GARDE ART
By Arturo Uslar-Pietri
36 FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
39 THE LIVING LEGACY OF THE ANDES
By Pablo Macera
40 THREADING THROUGH THE CENTURIES
Photos
46 COMMUNITIES IN CRISIS
The modern world is bringing mixed blessings
to the Indians of the cordilleras
By Jorge Enrique Adoum
51 THE LAND-LOCKED ISLAND OF PARAGUAY
By Augusto Roa Bastos
54 DEBUNKING THE 'BLACK LEGEND'
Spain's historical role in Latin America reconsidered
By Roberto Fernandez Retamar
56 EXTRAVAGANZA OF BAROQUE
Photo story
60 THE TANGO TANGLE
By César Fernandez Moreno
62 SPANISH OVERSEAS
By Marcos A. Morinigo
64 VICTORIA OCAMPO'S GIFT FOR WORLD CULTURE
By Jacques Rigaud
67 UNESCO AND LATIN AMERICA'S CULTURAL HERITAGE
68 UNESCO BOOKSHELF ON LATIN AMERICA
70 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
EL SALVADOR: The man in the bird's beak
Photo Barbosa © Rapho, Paris
Photo montage. Studio Picto, Paris
Cover
The fusion of different cultures is one of the
most distinctive characteristics of the vast
Latin American continent. This far-reaching
creative process, which is still going on today,
began with the Spanish conquest. Iberian and
African cultures confronted and intermingled
with those of the great indigenous civilizations
to form a unique amalgam. This issue of the
Unesco Courier examines some major aspects
of Latin America's original cultural identity.
Cover shows a Brazilian mulatto girl against
the background of a brightly coloured
painting on bark, the product of an art of
which the Mexican Indians are past masters.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Is it possible to speak of a specifically Latin American culture? And if so,
how did it develop, in the vast Latin American melting pot of peoples and ways of
life? The Unesco Courier has invited some of Latin America's leading writers
and thinkers to try to answer these vital questions and to define the unique cultural
identity of their continent.
Unesco's interest in what Simon Bolivar once dubbed this "extraordinary ,
and complex" continent goes back many years. In 1967 it launched a wide-ranging
study programme on Latin American cultures, whose results have been
published in Spanish in a number of volumes under the general title América Latina
en su Cultura ("Latin America Within its Culture"; see page 70).
The Unesco Courier has already devoted two special issues to Latin America:
"Latin America: 150 Years of Independence" in June 1961, and "Latin America's
Cultural Explosion" in March 1972.
LATIN
AMERICA
The long journey
to self-discovery
by Leopoldo Zea
OUR position as Latin Americans is,
as the Liberator Simon Bolivar
(1783-1830) put it, a most extra¬
ordinary and complicated one: "We are
neither Europeans nor Indians, but a spe¬
cies midway between the native inhabi¬
tants and the Spaniards."
Such is the uniqueness and complexity
of Latin America and its culture. It is a
culture which arose from the coming
LEOPOLDO ZEA, Mexican philosopher and writer, is
professor of the philosophy of history and the history
of ideas in America at the Autonomous National Uni¬
versity, Mexico City. He also heads the Centre for
Latin American Studies at the university's faculty of
philosophy and letters. Among his works published
in English are: The Latin American Mind (1963) and
Latin America and the World (1969), both published
by the University of Oklahoma Press.
together, without mutual assimilation, of
separate cultures. Instead of merging,
they' opposed one another, and what was
supposedly superior was juxtaposed with
what was considered inferior. The relation¬
ship that was perpetuated between Euro¬
peans and Americans was that of lords
and serfs, conquerors and conquered,
colonizers and colonized.
For the mestizothe person of mixed
bloodthis cultural and racial relationship
was interiorized, and resulted in inner con¬
flict conflict of a man whose blood
and culture flowed from both the con¬
queror and the bastard offspring. He was
looked upon as a bastard not just because
of his blood but also because of his cul¬
ture, or simply because he was born in
America and not in Europe.
Indeed, for the Spaniard born in Spain,
there was no difference between the ere- ,
ole, the legitimate son of the colonizer,
and the mestizo born of European father '
and Indian mother. The person born in
Latin America knew that Europeans con¬
sidered him an inferior, while the Indians
saw him as an exploiter, a henchman of the
colonizer.
"Americans by birth and Europeans by
right", Bolivar added, "we find ourselves
caught up in a conflict: we contest the
natives' rights of possession and defend
our position in the country where we were
born against the invaders... Though we
were all born of the same Mother, our
fathers are foreigners, by blood and by
origin, and the colour of their skin is dif¬
ferent. This dissimilarity has very serious
consequences, for we are made to do j
continual penance for it." I
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
An intermingling of cultures or a juxtaposition of cultures? These
are the terms of the dilemma confronting Latin Americans as they
seek to define their cultural identity. Ever since the Spanish
conquest, different cultures those of the conquistador, the
defeated and exploited indigenous population, and the African
slave have met, juxtaposed and interpenetrated one another.
The result has been the gradual development of forms of
cultural expression which are complex and sometimes
contradictory, but authentic and vigorous, as can be seen in
countless works of art scattered throughout the length and
breadth of the continent. Yet even today the Indians are not
totally integrated into this culture which they have helped to
create. Below, Indian women wait patiently in front of San
Francisco de la Paz Cathedral (Bolivia). On the wall behind
them, Indian motifs blend harmoniously with the Spanish
colonial-style architecture.
m
C
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Plaza of Three Cultures
. Such was the position of the Latin
American: this perpetual inner conflict led
to a sense of uneasiness, which he felt just
as much towards his father's people as
towards his mother's. Rejected by the
one, he was ashamed to belong to the
other. He began by accepting the atti¬
tudes of the colonizer towards his maternal
American culture and looked on his own
mixed race as a mark of inferiority, which
prevented him from feeling that he legiti¬
mately belonged to the paternal culture.
His mixed heritage, instead of being a
positive factor, became the source of all
the ambiguity and ambivalence which
permeate the history of his culture. He
oscillated between what he was and what
he would like to belong to.
The attempt to impose a highly admired
but alien model on a past felt to be un¬
worthy gave rise to a philosophy of histo¬
ry which is the opposite of the European
philosophy of history. It is a philosophy
based on a juxtaposition and not an assi¬
milation of cultures.
But it was this very juxtaposition that
eventually made Latin Americans realize
the inevitability of the cultural fusion that
came to be the basis of Latin America's
cultural identity. In other words the men
who formed Latin American culture had
to assimilate different cultures, creating,
as Bolivar put it, a culture that is both
extraordinary and complex".
The source of this extraordinary cultural
complexity can thus be traced to a history
of colonial domination. Whether we like
it or not, this past must be taken into
account if the much-needed change we
desire is to be brought about.
For what we need is to change the
relation of dependency which has been
the root cause of all our problemsa pat¬
tern of colonial domination which, contra- .
ry to what happened in Europe, made
genuine cultural integration impossible.
For European culture grew out of a
process of exchange, as multifarious
peoples moved back and forth across the
various regions that came to be Europe.
Greco-Roman culture was one product of
this process, later being assimilated by
Christianity, which in turn culminated in
the European or Western culture which,
from the 16th century onwards, spread to
America and the rest of the world.
The European colonizers tried to prevent
any further transculturation (even though
their own culture was the result of this
process), for they felt themselves superior
to other peoples.
But European and Western imperialism
was very different from that of the Greeks
and Romans, who assimilated cultures
just as they annexed the gods of other
peoples to their pantheon.
When the Spanish conquistadors arrived
in the 16th century, they were prepared
to take over the inhabitants of the newly-
discovered lands provided they gave up
their own culture.
The evangelizers were willing to assimi¬
late these creaturesor homunculi (little
men), as Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda called
them in his polemic with Bartolomé de Las
Casas (see Unesco Courier, June 1975)
provided that they would relinquish for¬
ever a past which had more to do with the
devil than with God. They must let them¬
selves be cleansed of their sins, stripped
of a false history and culture and led to
the culture that God Himself had created.
In this way, the culture of the conquer¬
or and colonizer was superimposed on
the "devilish" indigenous cultures. Chris¬
tian churches were raised on the sites of
ancient temples, and the old idols were
replaced by the cross, statues of the Virgin
or of a Christian saint.
The same thing happened during the
second wave of conquest and colonization
in the 17th century, this time from all of
Western Europe. These men likewise
ruled out any form of assimilation, al¬
though their own culture was the result of
an extraordinary degree of assimilation.
Like their predecessors, their attitude was
one of domination: to assimilate without
being assimilated. Their mission was to
bring civilization to the barbarians.
But this time, the barbarians were not
only the original inhabitants and the mes¬
tizos but also the very same European
settlers who had made racial intermingling
possible and whose culture was consider¬
ed outdated in relation to the new Western
culture that was rapidly expanding.
The new representatives of Western
culture would have nothing to do with
racial intermingling, for to mix was to
debase, to contaminate. That is why the
so-called inferior cultures, such as those
found in North America, were simply
wiped off the map and their members
exterminated or rounded up. And what
could not be stamped out because of the
sheer size of the population, as in South
America, Asia and Africa, was belittled so
as to make any contamination or assimi¬
lation impossible.
And the "natives" were not incorpor¬
ated into civilization as human beings
but, as Arnold Toynbee pointed out, as
part of the flora and fauna of the land.
They were called naturales in Spanish,
because they were considered to be part
of a nature that had to be subdued and
utilized for the sake of civilization.
Bolivar clearly expressed the relation
between Latin America and Western Euro¬
pean culture when he said: "Let us be
aware that our people are not European,
nor North American, but a mixture of Afri¬
ca and America rather than a product of
Europe; for even Spain itselfwith its
African blood, its institutions and its cha¬
racter not European. It is impossible
to properly define to what human family
we belong."
And yet the particular character of Latin
America did begin to express itself despite
the pattern of imposed cultural norms and
the servile imitation of outside models.
In the Christian churches built on the
sites of native temples, the devil, who was
to be extirpated, popped up in forms
created by Indian artists following the
instructions of the conquistadors and
evangelizers. The Indians danced in front
of the crosses. Virgins and Christian saints
just as they had once danced for their
own gods.
In the baroque art that still adorns the
churches, one can see the faces of the
native artists and admire their feeling for
colour. Even though the pantheon of
Maya, Aztec, Inca and various other gods
had officially disappeared, their spirit is
nonetheless evident in the various cultural
forms of the colonial period.
The year 1810 marked the beginning of
the struggle for the liberation of Latin
America and it symbolizes the Latin Amer¬
icans' inability to keep faith with their
Iberian cultural and historical past. Though
they considered that past as their own,
the arrogance and intolerance of the Por¬
tuguese and Spanish, and especially the
latter, vetoed any pretension to political or
cultural equality between Americans and
Europeans.
As far as the metropolitan Spaniards
were concerned, everyone born in America
was racially and culturally inferior. The
people of America were seen not as the
children of the Spanish conquest but as
its bastards and, therefore, as men with¬
out rights.
The Americans could elude but not
change this distinction, which was rigor¬
ously enforced. And so they were forced
to draw away from Spain. They had no
option but to renounce a culture which
prepared men only for servitude.
Again, Simón Bolívar expressed the
feeling of rejection experienced by Latin
Americans: "Within the Spanish system,
the Americans have no place in society
other than as servants or at best as con¬
sumers." The only culture available to
these men was one designed to make
them into efficient servants.
When the Spaniards rejected their de¬
mands for equality, these men had to
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
History is telescoped in the "Square of Three Cultures"
in Mexico City: foreground, remains of an Aztec
pyramid; centre, a 17th-century Spanish church in the
Jesuit style; background, modern apartment blocks.
improvise as "legislators, magistrates,
treasury administrators, diplomats, gener¬
als and the whole gamut of authorities,
from the highest to the lowest, which
make up the hierarchy of a properly orga¬
nized state."
But there were two mutually exclusive
ways of improvising, and it was the con¬
flict between them that lay at the root of
the long struggle which ravaged the whole
of Spanish America after its emancipation
from colonialism.
One way was to preserve the same
political and cultural order that had allow¬
ed Spain to keep its control for three cen¬
turies, by simply placing it in the service
of those who considered themselves its
heirs: the creóles, the land barons. They
who had once governed in the name of
metropolitan Spain would now exercise
authority in their own name. This meant
perpetuating what the Chilean Diego Por¬
tales (1793-1827) called the long "weight
of the night": that is, the long colonial
night with all its customs, institutions and
culture.
For, culturally speaking, there was a
Spanish past as well as a colonial past to
be assimilated. Spanish culture, like
Spanish history, was also that of the
Spaniards in America. This was the view
of the Venezuelan writer and statesman
Andrés Bello (1781-1865) who showed
that the drive for emancipation on the part
of the Spanish-Americans was actually a
genuinely Spanish response. Those who
had confronted the French troops at Sara¬
gossa were the same men who had fought
against the metropolitan Spanish troops
at Cartagena, in Colombia. The metropol¬
itan Spanish troops had been defeated in
various places in Latin America by insur¬
gent armies who were equally Spanish.
To appropriate Hispanic culture and
keep it alive would be to keep alive. the
very being of Latin America. Spain, in
spite of itself, had left expressions of its
culture which the Latin Americans could
make their own. There was no need, in
that case, to improvise: it was merely a
question of assimilating, learning and put¬
ting into practice. These were the major
concerns of the conservative programme.
In opposition stood those who chose
the second way: they wanted nothing
more to do with a past and a culture that
had made them subservient either to
metropolitan Spain or to those who pre¬
sented themselves in America as its legi¬
timate heirs. If they had to improvise,
then they preferred to improvise some¬
thing different. If knowledge and expe¬
rience were required, then they could be
sought in other experiences and other
cultures. Bolivar himself demanded a total
break with a social, political and cultural
order within which the Americans could
only have the role of servants.
Since they had nothing to call their
own, the Latin Americans could turn to
more relevant cultural models and expe¬
riences and make them their own. And
what could be more relevant than the
experiences of the men who had created
the nations which were now showing the
way to the rest of the world. These were
the very nations which had relegated the
Iberian world and its culture to a back¬
water and disputed its conquests. And so
the long colonial past was false and had
to be got rid of.
There was nothing for it but to start
again from scratch, making up for lack
of experience by taking over foreign
models. The supporters of this project
saw the Indian, Spanish and mestizo past
as the expression of a barbarism which
civilization would have to tame.
And just as the Iberian conquistadors
and colonizers tried to bury the old Indian
cultures and replace them with their own,
so the Latin-American civilizers tried to
bury the colonial past, both Spanish and
Indian, as well as the racial intermixing of
the colonial period.
They decided to imitate the cultural
models of Western Europe: the political
institutions of Britain and the literary and
philosophical movements of France. The
democratic institutions of the United
States which had so surprised de Tocque¬
ville were also to be adopted.
The goal of the civilization programme
was to be like England, France and the
United States and to eradicate the Latin
American past because it was considered
to be alien. The political emancipation
achieved by the liberators was to be fol¬
lowed by what the civilizers called "mental
emancipation".
To stop being what one is in order to
become something differentsuch was
the major preoccupation of this new cul¬
tural movement in Latin America. "Let us
recognize the tree by its fruits", the Ar¬
gentinian writer Domingo F. Sarmiento
(1811-1888) declared: "South America will
be left behind and will lose its providen¬
tial mission as a branch of modern civili¬
zation. Let us not stand in the way of
the forward advance of the United
States... Let us catch up with the United
States. Let us be America as the sea is
the ocean. Let us be United States...
Call yourselves the United States of South
America, and a sense of human dignity
and a noble desire for emulation will make
you worthy of that great name."
How was this to be achieved? Through
education and through massive immigra¬
tion. Brainwashing and bloodwashing.
This was the aim of an education which
took its inspiration from French positi¬
vism, English utilitarianism and North
American pragmatism. Justo Sierra (1848-
1912) believed that the Mexicans should
become the yankees of South America.
Juan Bautista Alberdi (1810-1884) also
spoke of Spanish-American yankees. The
civilizers would have no truck with the
past, with boorish Spain, the servile negro
or the savage Indian. They had an even
CONTINUED PAGE 69
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THE BLACKS IN LATIN
Africa's imprint on the art
and life of another continent
by Alejo Carpentier
IN the year 1441, ten natives of north¬
ern Guinea were taken to Portugal
as a "present" for King Henry the
Navigator from Antam Gonçalves, a mer¬
chant-traveller who had brought them
with him simply as exotic curiosities, just
as he might have brought a few parrots
or some rare plants back from the tropics.
Soonall too soon Europeans realized
that these "tropical oddities" might make
a tremendous labour force, and within
three years 235 African men, women and
children had been forcibly taken to Por¬
tugal "in order", as a pious chronicler of
the time noted, "to save their souls, which
were hopelessly lost."
Thus it was that black slaves in ever
greater numbers came to do domestic
work in the palaces and farmwork on the
domains of wealthy landowners. This was
the start of the abominable slave-trade
which was to take on such staggering
proportions with the discovery of America.
It was Charles V, King of Spain and
Emperor of Austria, who in 1518 gave
official status, as it were, to this traffic by
ALEJO CARPENTIER of Cuba is one of Latin Ameri¬
ca's leading novelists. His many books have been
translated into 22 languages and include, in English
editions: The Kingdom of this World (1957), The Lost
Steps (1957) published by Knopf, New York, Explosion
in a Cathedral (Gol/ancz, London, 1963) and Reasons
of State (Partridge, London, 1976). A musicologist,
Carpentier is the author of A History of Cuban Music
(1949). He was for some years director of Cuba's
national publishing house, in Havana and professor of
the history of music at the National Conservatory,
Havana. He is currently Counsellor for Cultural Affairs
at the Cuban Embassy in Paris.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
AMERICA
African slaves and the caravels that transported them to the New World dominate a huge
mural, below left, in an office in Bahia (Brazil). Along with the Iberian conquistadors, the
blacks were to create a new form of culture in the Caribbean, Brazil and other parts of
Latin America. Black artists in the New World lost touch with purely African art forms, but
family resemblances to the African tradition have survived in the work of such artists as
the Cuban mestizo painter Wif redo Lam. His monumental canvas The Jungle, which
created a furore when shown in New York in 1943, has been seen as the first painting to
express the Third World's awareness of the need to pool all the world's cultures. Below, in '
his canvas Presencia Eterna (Eternal Presence) painted in 1944, Lam returned to some of the
major themes of The Jungle.
authorizing the transportation of 4,000
í African slaves to the islands of Hispaniola
(Santo Domingo), Cuba, Jamaica and
Puerto Rico.
Even before that time, the custom of
using black slaves had spread throughout
Spain in imitation of what was being done
in Portugal. (Cervantes alludes to the
^practice in his Exemplary Tales). In this
way, many blacks found their way to the
New World, and especially to the Antilles,
which were already being colonized long
before the slave-trade' actually became
established as a large-scale commercial
enterprise.
The Catálogo de Pasajeros a Indias, or
list of passengers embarking for the Indies,
in the Casa de la Contratación in Seville,
is an invaluable source of information
about population movements in 16th-
century Spain. In its pages are the names
of those who first sought passage to "the
recently discovered lands on the other side
of the Occeana Sea." Among its entries,
one finds:
"5 February, 1510.- Francisco, a black
man." (Francisco was the first one of his
race to apply and was assigned number
38.); "27 February, 1512. Rodrigo de
Ovando, a black freedman; April 1512.
Pedro and Jorge, slaves (travelling with
their masters); August 1512. Cristina, a
black woman, and her daughter Inès."
The list goes on and on, with the names
of many slaves, freedmen, loros (those
with particularly dark skin), mulattoes (with
skin "the colour of stewed pears") and
curious cases like that of one "Juan
Gallego, a black, born in Pontevedra,
Galicia," who embarked on 10 November,
1517, though the record does not specify
whether he was a slave or a free man.
With the slave-trade now firmly esta¬
blished by both the Spanish and the
Portuguese, the number of blacks shipped
to America began to grow in geometric
proportion till they gradually formed one
of the basic ethnic components of the
population.
The Europeans who had children by
Indian women, plus the new African
elements, soon gave rise to the criollo
(creóle) class, which is basic to the inter¬
pretation and general understanding of
the history of Latin America.
The word criollo first appeared in a
geographical study by Juan López de
Velazco, published in Mexico between
1571 and 1574. "Spaniards who go out to
those parts" (that is, America) "and stay
there any length of time, necessarily
undergo some colour and personality
changes as a result of differences in tem¬
perature and climate; but those who are
born there are called criollos, and although
they are considered and held to be Spa-
Photo © André Morain. Paris. Private Coll.. U.S.A.
niards, they are obviously different in
complexion and build."
Silvestre de Balboa^ in a poem written
in Cuba in 1608, refers to a ¿lack slave as
a creóle. Another poet, Garcilaso de la
Vega, known as "the Inca" because his
mother was a princess of the royal line of
the Incas, wrote in 1617: "The Spanish
call those born in the New World criollos,
whether their parents are Spaniards or
Africans."
Sensing the danger implicit in this
neologism, the Spanish Crown tried for a
while to prohibit its use in any document,
report or legal text, but the word continued
to be used to designate a type of human
being that had arisen in America and was
taking on characteristics of its own, with
variations according to the region and to
the ethnic components responsible for its
formation.
In the Antilles and along the coasts of
Mexico, Colombia, Venezuela and Brazil
with outposts as far north as the Missis¬
sippi basin these people were to be
strongly marked by their African origins,
and in some of the Caribbean islands the
black ' population eventually outnumbered
the Europeans.
Around 1920, Paris experienced what
Jean Cocteau, the French poet and paint¬
er, did not hesitate to describe in alarm
as the "negro crisis". Picasso had painted
Les Demoiselles d'Avignon in 1907,
obviously influenced by certain African
art objects which had aroused his- enthu¬
siasm, as they had that of Matisse and
Derain. They and others, like the poet
Apollinaire, started collecting what they
dubbed "negro art". Galleries were filled
with sculpture, carvings, masks and all
kinds of objects from the African continent
whose history and creations were quite
unknown.
To lump all this together and call it
"negro art" was as preposterous as putting
the label "white art" on a collection ofr/
say, Greek Venuses, Renaissance marbles,
medieval gargoyles and Calder mobiles. .
After these art objects, a whole oral Y
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Spontaneous art
and voodoo rites in Haiti
k tradition arrived in Europe. Spoken, recited
and sung, it was a literature in which
magic and religion alternated with more
or less epic tales, cosmogonie legend,
beast fables, proverbs and simple stories
meant to entertain or edify the listeners.
This literary corpus, gathered here and
there by explorers and missionaries, began
to be published in collections of "negro
literature". (Needless to say, the term
"negro", as usual, failed to make any
distinction between the various ethnic
groups or degrees of cultural develop¬
ment). The best known of these is Blaise
Cendrars' famous Anthology, translated
into 20 languages and still to be found in
bookshops the world over.
So now there was "negro art" and
"negro literature"; the only thing missing
was "negro music". It soon put in its
appearance.
Jazz made its spectacular entrance on
the scene shortly after World War I. Stra¬
vinsky was enchanted with this novelty,
just as Picasso had previously been enthu¬
siastic about masks from Dahomey, and
he composed a piece entitled Piano Rag
Music, followed by Ragtime for Eleven
Instruments.
A key work embodying the spirit of the
times was Darius Milhaud's ballet The
Creation of the World, composed in 1923.
The music uses the syncopated beat and
runs of jazz, and the. story, by Cendrars, is
based on an ancient African legend about
how the world began. Since the stage
sets and costumes had to match the rest
of the work, the painter Fernand Léger did
his best to convey the spirit of African
objects.
A serious misunderstanding arose,
however, and it was to become the source
of many later errors. The first two pieces
of jazz to become hits in Europe were
"Alexander's Ragtime Band" and "Saint
Louis Blues", but European fans did not
seem to realize that the latter had been
written by a black musician from New
Orleans named Christopher Handy, and
that the former was the work of a free¬
style white composer named Irving Berlin.
In other words, such elaborated jazz had
very little in common with African music.
It was an authentically creóle product that
had its source in a racial intermingling that
had been going on for a long time in the
New World.
As Deborah Morgan so aptly comment¬
ed in the review Musique en Jeu: "The
history of jazz began in 1619 when a Dutch
frigate landed in Jamestown, Virginia, with
the first blacks sent to work in North
America. For jazz is not a type of music
that sprang up somewhere around 1900
in New Orleans, as a die-hard legend
holds; it is the result of á three-hundred-
year confrontation between two commu¬
nities, one which came from Africa and
the other from Europe."
It is curious to note that Cuban popular
music acquired its own specific features
about the same time, that is, in the early
17th century, though they were of course
quite different. Cuban rhythms scarcely
resembled jazz, but they spread through
the world in the early 1930s, whereas
Brazilian music began to be known outside
Brazil only just before World War II.
If jazz is totally different from the African
musical forms with which we are now
familiar, so is the music of Cuba and
Brazil. Blacks have indeed contributed
greatly to the development of all these
musical forms, but any similarity to what
is heard in the African countries has
disappeared. The Cuban cha-cha-cha, the
Dominican plena, the beguine of Santa
Lucia and Martinique, the calypso and
steel bands of Barbados and Trinidad, the
samba and bossa nova of Brazil, like the
boogie-woogie and free jazz of North
America, have nothing in common with
the scholarly recordings of African folk
music or the careful notations made by
ethnographers.
What has happened is that the black
man, cut off from Africa, has changed.
As Franz Fanon, an expert on the subject,
pointed out: "There is as much difference
between a Haitian and someone from
Dakar as there is between a Brazilian and
an inhabitant of Madrid."
This leads us to an observation on the
creative activity of the displaced African
living in North or South America. When
he is forced from his homeland, he seems
to lose his feeling for the plastic arts.
But what he forfeits as a sculptor, carver
or painter, he gains as a musician. A
transfer of energy takes place within him.
And though we may admire some sta¬
tuettes or drawings he turns out today
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
In recent years, a group of black and mulatto artists has created an authentic school of
"spontaneous" or "primitive" painting in Haiti, in other islands of the Antilles and in
Venezuela. Below left, work by an artist from Haiti, where ancient African rites such as
voodoo (below) are still practised, especially in rural areas. Voodoo, which originated in
what is now Dahomey, was introduced to the island in the 18th and 19th centuries by
slaves brought by the French. Since then, local beliefs as well as elements of the Catholic
liturgy have been added.
Photo Eve Arnold © Magnum, Paris
such as the "signatures", or graphic sym¬
bols, of the Abakuá groups in Cuba, the
vevés drawn at the foot of the voodoo
altars in Haiti, or the small wrought-iron
figures used in candomblé rites in Brazil
none has the force, the originality or the
technical mastery of an art that was left
behind and slowly forgotten.
On the other hand, the greatest compo¬
sers of this century, in both Europe and
America, have drawn inspiration for major
works from the extraordinarily inventive
music written by blacks in the most widely
different regions of the New World.
This apparent loss of their original plastic
sense can be explained by the fact that
sculpture, carving -and decorative painting
required free time, which the slave-holder
was not prepared to grant.
He was not going to place workshops
and tools at the disposal of men who were
there to increase his wealth, simply so that
they could have the pleasure of carving
figures that he considered barbaric idols
and repositories of ancestral beliefs.
. On the contrary, any such recollections
had to be wiped from the black man's
memory with the help of the overseer's
lash. "Civilized man" in the West did not
yet have the slightest interest in what he
would later come to value as "folk art".
While the black man's paintings or
carvings were considered works of the
Devil, music, on the other hand, did not
cause much inconvenience. The planta¬
tion owners in Cuba, for example, allowed
their slaves to beat their drums and dance
every evening because this showed that
they were in good health and that their
"ebony flesh" was fit for hard labour.
Meanwhile, the slaves listened to what
they heard around them. During the 16th
century, when they were first taken to
America, they assimilated Spanish ballads,
songs from Portugal and even French
square dancing. They discovered musical
instruments unknown in their own lands
and learned to play them.
j ......
If one of them succeeded in being freed
by a master who was more benevolent
than othersfor slavery as an institution
was only abolished by degrees in . the
Americas he might well turn to music as
a way of earning his living, mingling with
white people in a kind of occupational
freemasonry. As the Cuban essayist José
Antonio Saco noted in 1831: "Music enjoys
the prerogative of bringing blacks and
whites together; in orchestras, no distinc¬
tion is made between whites, browns and
blacks."
Far removed from his African roots, the
black man in Latin America became a basic
constituent, together with the Indian, of
the creóle class that was to affect the
destiny of a whole continent with its
aspirations, its struggles and its protest.
As the centuries went by, the blacks were i
slowly incorporated into the society of I
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
, their new homelands and, little by little,
they recovered their poetic sense and the
feeling for the plastic arts which they
seemed to have lost.
Observing ancestral traditions that no
longer bore any relation to their surround¬
ings was now out of the question. The
black peoples had forgotten their African
dialects by this time and spoke only the
major languages of the New World. They
felt no need to revive old Yoruba tales, to
recall ancient legends or return to the
sources of an oral culture they were alie¬
nated from, but rather to "make poetry"
in the full sense of the term. (1)
The same thing happened in painting.
Black artists in the New World were
completely out of touch with art forms that
in Africa were related to religious cults
now left far behind (even though some
vestiges can still be found on altars osten¬
sibly consecrated to Christian saints).
On the contrary, they had to solve the
same technical problems that face artists
everywhere in any period. It is obvious
then that the work of the black and mes¬
tizo painters and sculptors active in Latin
America in the 19th century bore no
resemblance whatsoever to the forms and
stylizations of African art.
This was also true of poetry at that time.
And one may add that there were many
"white" writers the word "white" has
always been quite relative in Latin Ame¬
rica published novels with "negro"
settings, denouncing the loathsome
aspects of slavery in the Americas.
It is only in the last 50 years that a new
generation, of poets and painters has
appeared, whose works are marked by the
symbiosis of cultures fostered by the
New World.
There has been much talk, for example,
of "black poetry", referring to a resonant,
percussive, onomatopoeic type of poetry
which, despite a prevalent assumption,
has often been written by perfectly "white"
poets, like the Cuban Emilio Ballagas or
the Venezuelan Manuel Felipe Rugeles.
In point of fact, this is an exotic view
of "négritude". The truth is that if "black
poetry" as such ever existed, it would have
had to be a protest on behalf of the black
people oppressed by centuries of slavery
and racial discrimination.
First and foremost, it would have had to
be a revolutionary cry because, since the
16th century, the blacks have always been
in revolt against their overlords in some
part of the hemisphere, and even formed
small independent states in Brazil, the
(1) It may be argued that the Abakuá and Santería
groups in Cuba, the Obeah rite in Jamaica, and the
voodoo of Haiti are authentic African survivals. But
it could also be said that such vestiges, besides absorb¬
ing and being much influenced by small local cults, are
destined to disappear in a few years, or else to be given
a strong creóle character. Such is the case of the
voodoo sect, which has had a fresh crop of gods added
to it, such as Criminel Petra, Erzulie and Marinette
Bois-Cheche.
On other islands in the Antilles, African folklore has
become a tourist attraction; "magic ceremonies"' and
"ritual dances" are performed for money. When folk
art is for sale, it has long ceased to be authentic. Not
to mention the fact that in a country like Cuba, the
socialist system makes the old nanigo groups (secret
mutual aid societies) completely superfluous.
Guyanas and Jamaicastates that some¬
times survived for many years.
The blacks of Latin America never
resigned themselves to their status as
slaves: there were countless uprisings and
escapes. The rebellion organized in Vene¬
zuela in the 16th century by Black Miguel,
and the liberation movements in Haiti in
the 18th centuryadmirably led by Tous¬
saint Louverturewere forerunners of the
great wars of independence soon to be
fought in Latin America.
Never during their long history in the
New World did the blacks give up their
quest for freedom, a quest furthered by
the creóles of all classes and stations who,
after much struggling, finally threw off the
yoke of Spanish, Portuguese, French and
English colonialism.
'Never
did the blacks
give up
their quest
for freedom
in the
New World'
It was a typically creóle thought that
Montesquieu, in 1721, put in the mouth
of a black from the Antilles: "Why should
I work for a society that I don't wish to
belong to? Why should I abide by a cove¬
nant made without my being consulted?"
Because he is a creóle, and also educat¬
ed in the best classical traditions, the
Cuban poet Nicolás Guillen was able to
write poetry which took as its metrical
basis the rhythms of the Cuban son, a
musical form with strong creóle influence.
His verses plunge their roots not into
African soil but into well-cultivated ground
broken centuries before by Lope de Vega
and Luis de Góngora in Spain, and Sor
Juana Inés de la Cruz in Mexico in what
they chose to call "poems of blacks."
If there is a kind of poetry that can
properly be called creóle, it is that of
Guillen who, in any case, does not confine
himself within the narrow limits of any
particular style. Whether he is writing his
classical poems or the resounding first
verses of Motivos del Son or Songoro
Cosongo, he is Cuban through and
through.
Similarly in painting: Wifredo Lam's
monumental canvas The Jungle, a com¬
pendium of the plant life and forms pecu¬
liar to the magical environment of the
Caribbean, is the work of a mestizo painter
who has a truly creóle sensibility and
whose painting occupies a special place
in the panorama of modern art.
In Venezuela, Haiti and the small islands
of the Antilles, there is currently developing
an authentic school of "spontaneous" or
"primitive" painters who have been doing '
extraordinary things since the 1940s.
Their work constitutes another contri¬
bution to Latin American painting in gene¬
ral, without a trace of any ancestral African
tradition other than a common fondness
for bright, lively colours, which stems
more from individual temperament than
from a hereditary predisposition.
In short, there exist in the Antilles, where
Spanish, English and French are spoken,
literature and painting with a markedly
creóle character, and it would be difficult
to say just what can be attributed to their
various ethnic components.
The contribution of the blacks to the
world where they were taken by force
does not consist, therefore, in what has
mistakenly been called "négritude". (If
that were the case, we should also have
to speak of the contribution of "white-
itude") It is something much more impor¬
tant, namely, their creative sensibility.
The blacks brought with them a fresh
energy that added a new dimension to
both art and history in the New World.
The creóle class, formed of Indians and
Europeans, did not reach maturity in Ame¬
rica until it had the benefit of black sen¬
sibility.
From the blending of these three races
with greater Indian predominance in some
regions and a more pronounced black
strain in others there arose a type of
man who, with his music, art forms,
poetry and novels, has won a place in the
forefront of world culture.
Alejo Carpentier
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
For four centuries, black Africa has exercised a strong influence In Brazil, alongside the
Amerindians and the European colonizers. Black African cultures and peoples played a
major part in the development of a new type of civilization, which is neither European nor
African, but distinctively Brazilian. Below, an Afro-Brazilian family out for a stroll in
Salvador de Bahía. On the walls in the background, scenes from the conquest and
colonization of Brazil.
THE AFRO-BRAZILIAN
EXPERIMENT
GILBERTO FREYRE of Brazil is an internationally
known authority on sociology and social and cultural
anthropology.. He has served as a consultant with the
United Nations and Unesco on questions concerning
racism and social tensions, and has taught in a number
of American and European universities. His works
translated into English include: The Masters and the
Slaves (1956), New World in the Tropics (1959) and
The Mansions and the Shanties (1966), all published
by Alfred A. Knopf, New York.
by Gilberto Freyre IT is an irrefutable historical fact that
Brazil was initially a "pre-Brazil"
historical and human outpost of Eur¬
ope, and specifically of Portugal. But this
is not enough to explain either Brazil's
emergence as a new social and cultural
entity in the modern world and its evolu¬
tion as a cultural and social system based w
on coexistence. Y
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Rhythms of bondage
The cultural "consolidation" of Brazil
,was a complex and far-reaching process
brought about by an intermingling of both
European and non-European elements. Of
the latter, the Amerindian peoples and
cultures have played an important and
lasting part. But another non-European
element was subsquently to share in the
process: the black African.
From the 16th century on, black African
cultures and peoples played a part in the
formation of an ethnically mixed type of
human being and a pre-national type of
culture.
Their contribution was so dynamic, and
their Africanizing influence so vigorous,
that even though they had come as slaves
to Brazil, the black Africans became colo¬
nizers, as it were, of this part of America.
Alongside the European founders of the
new culture, they came to outweigh the
influence of the Brazilian Indians.
For four centuries now, the black Afri¬
can has made his presence felt from both
a biological and cultural point of view.
Intermingling has given rise to new types
of human beings and new kinds of femi¬
nine beauty. Cultural intermixing has
produced new cultural blends which
have left their mark not only on the Amer¬
indians, but also on the values which were
imported from certain regions of Africa
and from the Iberian Peninsula, the basic
source of Brazilian colonization, which
was itself already impregnated with black
African influences.
To these ethnic and cultural contribu¬
tions, one must add an ecological factor
tropics. Inevitably, the tropics in¬
fluenced the Brazilian, fostering a readi¬
ness to try bold experiments. This can be
seen today in certain distinctive economic
and governmental institutions, most of
which are still at an experimental stage of
development.
But when Brazil embarks on such ex¬
periments, this does not reflect anti-
European feelings; it shows, rather, that
Brazil is aware of the fact that in many
areas of its social and cultural behaviour
it must be non-European. This fact was
stressed more than 50 years ago by
Brazilian thinkers and social scientists who
laid down sociological and anthropological
guidelines which, while still universally
valid, . were nonetheless Brazilian and
"Euro-tropical" in scope and outlook.
Brazil's experience can be useful to new
nations in Africa, Asia and elsewhere for,
after four centuries of pre-national and
national development and more than a
century of independence, Brazil is now
emerging as a civilization in search of
forms of expression suited to a tropical
environment. This civilization does not,
however, repudiate the European values
which are so basic to Brazil's national
heritage.
Brazil now boasts its own types of
architecture, music, painting, cooking,
Christianity, social life, attitudes towards
health and hygiene, and footballa more
dionysiac Brazilian kind of football than
the apollonian English one. All of these
express a new type of civilization whose
novelty derives as much from : racial
intermingling as from an intermixing of
cultures.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Influence of African religions can still be felt in the rhythms and mythological
symbolism of Brazilian dances such as the maracatu (below left) and the macumba (see
colour photo page 35). Dancing was one of the rare forms of expression allowed to the
African slaves, from whose senzalas (slave houses) African cultures spread throughout
Brazil. Below, a senzala at Olinda, today transformed into an antique shop.
The black African has been integrated
not only biologically, but also sociologi¬
cally. A case in point is Brazilian Catholi¬
cism which is becoming a strongly Afri¬
canized religion: its officially Roman Ca¬
tholic, and originally European, rites and
symbolism are being transformed by the
admixture of pure African religious beliefs
and practices.
The cult of the Virgin Mary is an exam¬
ple of this: elements have been assimilated
from the Yemanja cult (the female counter¬
part of Orixa, a secondary divinity in the
African jeje-nago cult). Brazil has black
Virgins like the Virgin of Rosario and mes¬
tizo Virgins like Our Lady of Guadalupe,
whose devotees pledge themselves by
offering ex-votoswood and clay sculp¬
tures whose expression and colour sym¬
bolism are more African than European.
This African influence is also felt in the
maracatu, a dance whose deeper meaning
reveals a complex infiltration of African
elements into the Brazilian religious spirit.
Other examples of this infiltration are found
in the many saint cults common in Brazilian
Catholicism, such as those of St. George,
St. Barbara or St. Damián.
Brazilians do not consider themselves
less Catholic because elements of African
rites or beliefs have been incorporated
into their religious worship. Though their
Catholicism is more tropical and less Euro¬
pean, believers do not feel it has been
corrupted or de-Christianized.
The same holds true for Brazilian cook¬
ery, music, sculpture and painting of
European origin: African penetration re¬
presents not a corruption of values but an
enrichment.
It is of course true that European colo¬
nization gave this new type of society and
culture a means of communicationthe
Portuguese language, heir to the noble
and prestigious Latin of ancient Rome. But
it is also clear that none of the European
languages imported into America is be¬
coming so intensely "tropicalized" as
Brazilian Portuguese.
This process, due in part to de-Euro-
peanization, stems primarily from African
influence, and only secondarily from
Amerindian influence. As a literary lan¬
guage, it is no longer considered as inferior
to the academic language of Portuguese
purists.
Less and less academic, the Brazilian
language is daily acquiring new rhythms
and expressions whose musicality and
forcefulness are deeply marked by their
African origins. Not so long ago, how¬
ever, these expressions were restricted to
the vernacular and were considered ple¬
beian, vulgar, "blacks' talk" or "slaves'
talk".
What conclusions can be drawn from
these observations about the importance
of black or African elements in the society,
culture and language of Brazil? One result
seems to be that the people are becoming
increasingly but not exclusively brown-
skinned and that Brazil is witnessing the
formation of an increasingly extra-Euro¬
pean culture.
Segregationist attitudes such as exclu- 1
sive Aryanism or exclusive "négritude'' are I
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Gods, legends and figureheads
> countered in Brazil by a general move
towards synthesis, whether biologically
through intermingling or sociologically
through the intermixing of cultures, some
of which are more markedly non-European
than European.
Today Brazil tends to look on its own
independenceespecially its political and
economic independence, but also its so¬
cial and cultural independence as a result
not so much of a sudden decolonization
but rather of a rapid process of "self-
colonization" (another sociological neo¬
logism coined in Brazil).
This self-colonization no doubt develop¬
ed because Brazil found itself opposed
to Portugal, which was less tentacular
and less interventionist than other Euro¬
pean colonial powers, and thus less able
to impose its will. As a result Portugal
was more apt to compromise and to let
the people there practise self-colonization,
allowing the African to become a partner
in the process.
The Amerindian mestizo joined forces
with the Portuguese and even outstripped
them in this colonizing activity, as is
shown by the great part played in the
building of Brazil by the bandeirantes,
associations formed to capture Indian
slaves and to explore for mines. But most
important was the part played by the
black ladinos, slaves who spoke Portu¬
guese and had some notions of Christian
religion and domestic or agricultural prac¬
tices. They worked alongside the Portu¬
guese and even outdistanced them in
many fields thanks to the ease with which
they adapted to the Brazilian tropics. They
withstood the difficult working conditions
in the flooded or marshy Brazilian lands
better than the wholly European settlers.
The fact that Brazil could express its
creativity in a non-European way, even
when it was still officially a Portuguese
colony, explains some of the characteris¬
tics that distinguish Brazil from other
decolonized countries.
Consider, for example, the sculpture of
Antonio Francisco Lisboa, better known
as Aleijadhino (1730-1814): it seems to
come straight from the tropics. It is no
copy of a European style, but rather a
bold and original Brazilian creation.
It is clear that in the aesthetic field
Brazilians have special African connexions
which differentiate them from other Latin
Americans even from those tropical
American regions where the African
influence is strong.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
African religious beliefs and practices have been incorporated into Catholic ritual In Brazil,
where the cult of the Virgin Mary is strongly coloured by that of lemanjá, a female divinity
of Nigeria. Below left, the ceremony of the cult of lemanjá. An Afro-Brazilian legend of
the African divinity Oxosse is the theme of a ballet created by the choreographer Clyde
Morgan. Below, a scene from the ballet performed by the Contemporary Dance Group of
the Federal University of Bahia. Bottom left, a curious example of Brazilian folk art: one of
the famous figureheads which decorate canoes on the San Francisco river.
In Nigeria, for example, there is a Bra¬
zilian style in both architecture and in
interior design; it even makes use of
typically Brazilian animals and plants. A
special Brazilian flavour has also crept into
Nigerian cooking, dance, recreation,
worship and folklore.
Some art critics see links between the
works of the Spanish painter Joan Miró
and those of the young Nigerian sculptor
Jacob Afolabi. One good turn deserves
another: was it not another giant of Span¬
ish painting, Picasso, who developed
African art forms and transmitted them to
artists in Europe and elsewhere in the
world?
Jacob Afolabi and other African artists
have affinities not only with Picasso, but
with Brazilian artists too. It seems clear
that Nigerian artists today find something
familiar in much authentically Brazilian art,
something fraternally related to what they
themselves consider to be art.
The Brazilian heritage explains why
African artists like Afolabi are linked more
closely to such Brazilian artists as Ciceros
dos Santos Dias, Emiliano di Cavalcanti
and Lulas Cardoso Ayres, than to artists
like Miró. It also explains why the work
of Nigerian craftsmen like Adebisiwho
deliberately cultivates the so-called Brazi¬
lian-Nigerian style in his artshows simi¬
larities with the painted pottery of a Bra¬
zilian artist like Francisco Brennand.
Does Brazilian artists' sensitivity to their
African roots reflect an exclusive attach¬
ment to "négritude"? If so, then Brazilians
of African descent would tend to draw
away from Brazilians of different descent.
Would this make for a "black Brazilian"
like the black North American? Not at all,
for Brazilians are conscious of the fact
that they are brown-skinned people
"brown" here meaning every shade, up to
and including black. Hence the Brazilian
concept of "meta-race" or "going beyond
race", which makes Brazilians unconcerned
about ethnic origins: they do not affect
one's status as a citizen. .
Such concepts are of immense impor¬
tance for anthropologists and sociologists
because they prove that it is not colour or
race which makes a man what he is, but
rather his personal tastes, motives and
outlook including artistic ones.
In Brazilian folklore there is no lack of
idealized or romanticized African figures.
They have been incorporated into Brazil's
essentially . patriarchal society. Among
them are such figures as the mae prêta,
(black mother), the ba (nurse), the negro k
velho (old black man) and the negrinho do Y
Photo © Rivaldo C. Leite, from Cultura magazine. Ministry of Education and Culture, Brasilia
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
¿pastoreio (a kind of good angel of the
; pampas).
Brazilian authors have been inspired by
the figures of "Isaura the Slave" (Ber¬
nardo Guimaraes), the "mulatto" (Alui-
sio de Azevedo), the "good creóle"
(Isaias Caminha), "little black Ricardo"
(José Lins do Regio), "Balduino" (Jorge
Amado), "Falo the Black Girl" (Jorge de
Lima). Nor should one forget the mulat-
toes of the painter Emiliano di Cavalcanti,
who are sometimes of à pure black now
so rare in Brazil after years of intermingling.
More has been written about the African
influence on Brazilian music than on any
other Brazilian art form. It is apparent not
only in popular music but also in some of
the country's most serious music. The
composer Hector Villa Lobos (1887-1959)
was influenced both by African and even
more by Amerindian musical themes, which
he considered basically Brazilian.
The cultural affinities between Brazil
and Africa are, as we have seen, strong.
But we must not forget that another
factor, besides the historical one, has
contributed to these similarities: a common
tropical environment undergoing the
process of modernization. It is important,
though, that modernization must not turn
these peoples against their environment
and cut them off from the sources of
their national cultures. This would risk
reducing their national artistic and cultural
forms to parodies of the modern art
forms prevailing in economically and tech¬
nologically advanced regions that now
tend to dominate the cultures of the
developing countries.
There is no question of rejecting Euro¬
pean cultural elements, or even North
American ones, for they can be adapted
to non-European conditions. But there is
also no question of turning Brazilians into
sub-Europeans or sub-North Americans.
What Brazil is trying to do may well pro¬
vide valid examples for the young African
nations, who may find that they can apply
them to their new social and cultural
situations.
Gilberto Freyre
THE THREE RACES, a canvas by the Brazilian painter Emiliano di
Cavalcanti, symbolizes the harmony reigning between the ethnic
groups that went to form the population of Brazil.
WHERE
GODS
AND MEN
HAVE
MINGLED
by Jorge Amado
JORGE AMADO, Member of the Brazilian Academy,
is one of Latin America's most widely read novelists.
Since the appearance of his novel Mar Muerto ("Dead
Sea", 1961), which won him a reputation throughout
Latin America, he has published over 15 books that
have been translated into some 30 languages. Among
his more recent works published in English are Gabriela
(Chatto and Windus, London, 1963) and Doña Flor
and Her Two Husbands (Weidenfeld and Nicolson,
London, 1970).
BRAZIL is a country of racial mixture.
This is an obvious and incontro¬
vertible fact. The Brazilian experi¬
ment is of immense importance in the
search for a solution to the terrible racial
problem that afflicts the world. For in
Brazil the most diverse races have con¬
stantly been mingled.
What Brazilian could honestly claim to
be of "pure" descent in a country where
Iberians, Slavs, Anglo-Saxons, Magyars
and others have become inextricably mix¬
ed with black and Amerindian peoples
and with Arabs, Jews and Japanese?
This continuing process is the funda¬
mental reality of life in Brazil, and repre¬
sents our own special contribution to
world culture and the humanist tradition.
We are a racially mixed people, and
the mixture has depended as much on
the contribution of the black as on that of
the white. We owe to the black peoples
some of our most outstanding character¬
istics: our ability, for example, to endure
misery and oppression, to survive in the
toughest conditions, and to love life and
laughter.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
tN
K
Photo © Dominique Desjardins, Paris
It is to them that we owe the unfailing
joyfulness that inspires our efforts to fight
against and defeat backwardness, poverty
and the many obstacles on our path to
development. We owe this toughness
and fighting spirit to the black blood
which flows not only in our veins but also
in our music, dance and other forms of
artistic expression.
The culture of Brazil was formed in the
struggle against racism and was born of
the mingling of whites, blacks and Amer¬
indians. The black element in Brazilian
society is inextricably mingled with the
white, and Africa is a maternal presence
in our midst.
But it would be ridiculous to claim that
there are no racists in Brazil, for there are
many. On the other hand, we do not
have a racist philosophy of life: our out¬
look is fundamentally anti-racist, based
as it is on intermingling.
The vigorous "negro" art of the sculptor
Agnaldo da Silva, without equal in Brazil
today, is not exclusively black. It bears
traces of white and Iberian influences in
both form and subject: Agnaldo's Oxossl
is also St. George.
It is all the more unfortunate, then, that
a distorted image of our way of life is
sometimes presented abroad. The African
contribution, which is of fundamental im¬
portance to Brazilian culture, is glossed
over or pushed into the background.
This is a totally false approach. Through
a curious reversal of the colonial mentality,
there is a tendency to put the spotlight on
painters, writers and singers with the
blackest possible skins. This attempt to
prove the absence of racial prejudice in
Brazil actually indicates a preoccupation
which is totally alien to the Brazilian philo¬
sophy of life.
The blackest girls are chosen to sing,
but no attention is paid to the fact that
they sing songs more strongly marked
by Iberian than black influence, although
Brazilian music derives primarily from the
atablques of Africa.
The paintings shown tend to be typical
examples of the Paris School the
important thing is that the artists' skins
are black. Brazilian painters like Tarsila
and Di Cavalcanti are neglected, although
their work displays the black African in¬
fluences which, along with white, Amerin
dian and Japanese elements, have pro¬
duced an art which is uniquely Brazilian.
We must proclaim to the world at large
the tremendous importance of the African
presence in Brazil, in our life, culture and
in the faces of our people.
The black African has contributed to all
the great achievements of Brazil. The
presence of Africa with its sunlight and
shadow can be felt in the prophets, saints
and angels which the mestizo sculptor
Aleijadinho (1730-1814) carved in the
mining region of Minas Gerais.
Africa is present in the music of Villa
Lobos and Dorival Caymini, in the Orixas
and Madonnas of Agnaldo, in the poetry
of Gregorio de Matos, Castro Alves and
Vinicius de Moraes. It is present in the
dancing, and the singing, the gentleness,
the friendliness and the expansive imagi¬
nation of everything great in Brazil.
For here in Brazil gods and men have,
happily, become inextricably mingled.
Jorge Amado
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
'J
20
The strains of solitude
"All men are born disinherited and their true condition is orphanhood, but this is
particularly true of the Indians and the poor in Mexico", Octavio Paz has written.
The art of the Mexican Indians is imbued with this intense feeling of solitude, which
can be traced back to their Aztec past.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Aztec myths and Christian beliefs in Mexico
A MATTER OF LIFE
AND DEATH
by Octavio Paz
Text © Copyright. Reproduction prohibited
ANY contact with the Mexican peo¬
ple, however brief, reveals that
ancient beliefs and customs are
still in existence beneath Western forms.
These still-living remains testify to the
vitality of the cultures that existed before
the Spanish conquest.
And after the discoveries of archeolo-
gists and historians, it is no longer possi¬
ble to refer to those societies as savage or
primitive tribes. Over and above the fasci¬
nation or horror they inspire in us, we
must admit that when the Spaniards arriv¬
ed in Mexico they found complete and
refined civilizations.
Meso-America that is, the nucleus of
what was later to be New Spainwas a
territory that included the central and
southern parts of present-day Mexico and
a portion of Central America.
The last centuries of Meso-American
history can be summed up as the history
of repeated encounters between waves of
northern huntersalmost all of them be¬
longing to the Náhuatl familyand the
settled populations.
The Aztecs were the last to enter the
Valley of Mexico. The previous work of
erosion by their predecessors, and the
wasting away of the springs of the ancient
local cultures, made it possible for them
to accomplish the extraordinary task of
founding what Arnold Toynbee calls a
Universal Empire, based on the remains of
older societies.
According to Toynbee, the Spaniards
did nothing except act as substitutes, re¬
solving through political synthesis the ten¬
dency towards dispersal that threatened
the Meso-American world.
OCTAVIO PAZ, Mexican poet and essayist, is one of
the most outstanding writers in the Spanish language
today. He has been Mexico's ambassador to India
and has taught at several universities, including Cam¬
bridge (U.K. I where he was Simon Bolivar Professor
of Latin American studies. He has published several
volumes of poetry, including Libertad bajo Palabra
("Liberty on Parole"). English translations of his es¬
says include Claude Lévi-Strauss: An Introduction
( 1972) and Alternating Current (1973). The article pub¬
lished here is taken from his classic analysis of the
Mexican mind. The Labyrinth of Solitude, published
by Grove Press Inc., New York. 1961.
Meso-America has been described as a
uniform historical area characterized by
the constant presence of certain elements
common to all its cultures: an agriculture
based on maize, a ritual calendar, a ritual
ball-game, human sacrifices, solar and
vegetation myths, and so on. It is said
that all of these elements originated in the
south and were assimilated at various
times by the immigrants from the, north.
If this were true, Meso-American culture
would be the result of various southern
creations that were adopted, developed
and systematized by nomadic groups.
But, apart from the particular originality
of each culture, it is evident that all of
them, because of decadence or debilita¬
tion, were on the point of being absorbed
into the Aztec Empire, which was heir to
the civilizations of the Central Plateau.
Those societies were impregnated with
religion. The Aztec state was both mili¬
tary and theocratic. Therefore, political
unification was preceded or completed by
religious unification, or corresponded to it
in one way or another.
Before the Conquest, each city worship¬
ped gods who steadily became more alike:
their names were different but the cere¬
monies honouring them were similar.
The agrarian deities the gods of the
earth, of vegetation and fertility, like Tlá-
loc, and celestial warriors like Tezcatlipoca,
Huitzilopochtli and Mixcóatl belonged to
a single cult;
The most outstanding characteristic of
Aztec religion at the time of the Conquest
was the incessant theological speculation
that reformed, systematized and unified
diverse beliefs, both its own and others.
The systematizations, adaptations and
reforms undertaken by the priestly caste
show that the process was one of super-
imposition, which was also characteristic
of religious architecture. Just as an Aztec
pyramid often covers an older structuré,
so this theological unification affected only
the surface of the Aztec consciousness,
leaving the original beliefs intact.
The situation prefigured the introduction
of Catholicism, which is also a religion
superimposed upon an original and still-
living religious base. Everything was pre¬
pared for Spanish domination.
The conquest of Mexico would be inex¬
plicable without these antecedents. The
arrival of the Spaniards seemed a libera¬
tion to the people under Aztec rule. The
various city-states allied themselves with
the conquistadors or watched with indif¬
ference not with pleasure the fall of
each of their rivals, especially that of the
most powerful, Tenochtitlan.
But the political genius of the Spanish
conqueror Cortés, the superior techniques
of the Spaniards, and the defection of
vassals and allies, could not have brought
about the ruin of the Aztec Empire if it
had not suddenly felt a sense of weak¬
ness, a deep-rooted doubt that caused it
to vacillate and surrender.
When the Aztec emperor Montezuma
opened the gates of Tenochtitlan to the
Spaniards and welcomed Cortés with
gifts, the Aztecs lost the encounter. Their
final struggle was a form of suicide, as we
can gather from all tfie existing accounts
of that grandiose and astounding event.
Why did Montezuma give up? Why
was he so fascinated by the Spaniards
that he experienced a vertigo which it is
no exaggeration to call sacredthe lucid
vertigo of the suicide on the brink of the
abyss? The gods had abandoned him.
The great betrayal with which the his¬
tory of Mexico begins was not committed
by the Tlaxcalan Indians or by Montezuma
and his group: it was committed by the
gods. No other people has ever felt so
completely helpless as the Aztec nation
felt at the appearance of the omens, pro¬
phecies and warnings that announced its
fall.
We are unlikely to understand the mean¬
ing of these signs and predictions for the
Indians if we forget their cyclical concep¬
tion of time. As with many other peoples
and civilizations, time was not an empty,
abstract measurement to the Aztecs, but
rather something concrete, a force or sub¬
stance or fluid perpetually being used up.
Hence the necessity of rites and sacrifices
to reinvigorate the year or the century.
CONTINUED PAGE 24
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
In Mexico, Spanish Catholicism and
indigenous beliefs have become so
inextricably mixed that it is sometimes
difficult to distinguish pagan gods from
Christian saints, pre-Columbian rites
from Catholic ritual. Mexican
representations of Christ (photo 4) resemble
certain Aztec gods as well as the suffering
Christs of Spanish religious art. The same
intermixture of Christian and pagan
elements is found in religious festivals such
as those of the Yaqui Indians of northwest
Mexico, whose history can be traced back to
pre-Columbian times. During Holy Week
the Yaquis re-enact scenes from the Passion
and perform rites harking back to their
distant past. A curious feature of the
ceremonies is the worship of Judas by
masked Yaquis known as "Chapayecas" (the
long-nosed ones). On this double page are
shown scenes from Yaqui Holy Week: (1)
Christ's litter, decked with flowers, is borne
through the village; inside it are wooden
fetishes and stuffed animals; (2) Long-nosed
ritual masks of the Chapayecas, mounted on
wooden swords; (3) Two Yaqui archers
reverently guard the statue of.Christ; (5) The
"march of the warriors" outside the church
recalls the Yaquis' long and sometimes
fierce struggle to preserve their
independence.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Passion according
to the Yaquis
Photos © Marino Benzi-Editions du Chêne, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
k, But timeor, more precisely, each
period of timewas not only something
living that was born, grew up, decayed
and was reborn. It was also a succession
that returned: one period of time ended
and another came back.
The arrival of the Spaniards was inter¬
preted by Montezuma, at least at the be¬
ginning, not so much as a threat from
outside than as the internal conclusion of
one cosmic period and the commence¬
ment of another. The gods departed be¬
cause their period of time was at an end,
but another period returned and with it,
other gods and another era.
The conquest of Mexico is an historical
event made up of many very different
circumstances, but what seems to me the
most significant the suicide of the Aztec
people is often forgotten.
One part of the Aztec people lost heart
and sought out the invader. The other,
betrayed on all sides and without hope of
salvation, chose death. The mere pre¬
sence of the Spaniards caused a split in
Aztec society, a split corresponding to the
dualism of their gods, their religious sys¬
tem and their higher castes.
Aztec religion, like that of all conquer¬
ing people, was a solar religion. The Az¬
tecs concentrated all their aspirations and
warlike aims in the sun, the god who is
the source of life, the bird-god who breaks
through the mists and establishes himself
in the centre of the sky like a conquering
army in the centre of a battle-field.
But the gods were not mere represen¬
tations of nature. They also embodied
the will and desire of society, which made
itself divine in them.
The victory of the death-wish shows
that the Aztecs suddenly lost sight of their
destiny. Cuauhtemoc, the last Aztec em¬
peror, fought in the knowledge that he
would be defeated. The tragic nature of
his struggle lies in this bold and intimate
acceptance of defeat.
The drama of a consciousness that sees
everything around it destroyedeven the
gods appears to preside over Mexican
history. Cuauhtemoc and his people died
alone, abandoned by their friends, their
allies, their vassals and their gods. They
died as orphans.
The fall of Aztec society precipitated
that of the rest of the Indian world. All
the nations that composed it were over¬
whelmed by the same horror, which almost
always expressed itself as a fascinated
acceptance of death. Few documents are
as impressive as the remaining handful
that describe this catastrophe. Here is an
expression of the suffering of the Mayas,
as recorded in their holy book, Chi/am
Balam de Chumayel:
"II Akan Katun: the blond-bearded
strangers arrived, the sons of the sun, the
pale-coloured men. Ah, how sad we were
when they arrived!... The white man's
stick will fall, will descend from on high,
will strike everywhere... The words of
Hunab-Ku, our one god, will be words of
sorrow when the words of the God of
Heaven spread out over the earth... [And
later:] The hangings will begin, and light¬
ning will flash from the white man's
hands... The hardships of battle will fall
upon the Brothers, and tribute will be
demanded after the grand entrance of
Christianity, and the Seven Sacraments
will be established, and travail and misery
will rule this land."
The Mexican is a religious being and his
experience of the divine is completely
genuine. But who is his god? The ancient
earth-gods or Christ?
In many instances Catholicism only cov¬
ers over the ancient cosmogonie beliefs.
In the following passage, Juan Pérez Jolo¬
te, a Chamula Indian of southern Mexico,
describes the ¡mage of Christ in a church
in his village and explains what it means
to him and his people:
"This is Señor San Manuel here in this
The hero's
tomb is the
cradle of the
people'
coffin; he is also called Señor San Salva¬
dor or Señor San Mateo. He watches
over the people and the animals. We pray
to him to watch over us at home, on the
road, in the fields. This other figure on
the cross is also Señor San Mateo; he is
showing us how he died on the cross, to
teach us respect... Before San Manuel
was born, the sun was as cold as the
moon, and the pukujes, who ate people,
lived on the earth. The sun began to grow
warm after the birth of the Child-God,
Señor San Salvador, who is the son of
the Virgin."
In this account (recorded in Juan Pérez
Jo/ote, the Autobiography of a Chamula,
as told to the anthropologist Ricardo
Pozas) we can see both the superimposed
religion and the ineradicable presence of
the indigenous myths. Before the birth of
Christ,, the sunthe eye of Goddid not
give warmth. The sun is an attribute of
divinity.
The persistence of the pre-Cortesian
myth underlies the difference between the
Christian and indigenous conceptions.
Christ saved the world because He re¬
deemed the Mexicans and washed away
the stain of Original Sin, but the Aztec
god Quetzalcóatl was not so much a re¬
deemer as a re-creator.
Among the Indians the idea of sin is
still bound to the idea of health and sick¬
ness, personal, social and cosmic. The
Christian attempts to save the individual
soul, disconnected from the group and
the body. Christianity condemns the world,
while the Indian conceives of personal
salvation only as a part of the salvation of
society and the cosmos.
In modern Mexico, there is no especial
veneration for God the Father in the Trini¬
ty. He is a dim figure at best. On the
other hand, there is profound devotion to
Christ as the Son of God, as the youthful
God, above all as the victimized Redeemer.
The village churches have a great many
images of Jesuson the cross, or covered
with thorns and wounds in which the
insolent realism of the Spaniards is mingled
with the tragic symbolism of the Indians.
On the one hand, the wounds are flowers,
pledges of resurrection; on the other, they
are a reiteration that life is the sorrowful
mask of death.
The fervour of the cult of God the Son
would seem to be explained, at first
glance, as an inheritance from the pre-
Hispanic religions.
When the Spaniards arrived, almost all
of the great masculine divinitieswith the
exception of Tláloc, a child and an old man
at the same time, and a deity of greater
antiquity were sons of gods like Xipe, god
of the young corn, and Huitzilopochtli, the
"Warrior of the South".
Perhaps it is not idle to recall that the
birth of Huitzilopochtli offers more than
one analogy with that of Christ: he too
was conceived without carnal contact; the
divine messenger was likewise a bird (it
dropped a feather into the lap of the earth-
goddess Coatlicue); and finally, the infant
Huitzilopochtli also had to escape the per¬
secution of a mythical Herod.
Nevertheless, it would be a mistake to
use these analogies to explain the Mexi¬
can's devotion to Christ, just as it would
be to attribute that devotion to a mere
survival of the cult of the sons of gods.
The Mexican venerates a bleeding and
humiliated Christ, a Christ who has been
beaten by the soldiers and condemned by
the judges, because he sees in him a trans¬
figured image of his own identity., And
this brings to mind Cuauhtemoc, the young
Aztec emperor who was dethroned, tor¬
tured and murdered by Cortés.
Cuauhtemoc means "Falling Eagle".
The Mexican chieftain rose to power at
the beginning of the siege of México-
Tenochtitlán, when the Aztecs had been
abandoned by their gods, their vassals
and their allies.
Even his relationship with a woman fits
the archetype of the young hero, at one
and the same time the lover and the son
of the goddess. Thus López Velarde wrote
that Cuauhtemoc went out to meet Cortés
is, to the final sacrifice"separated
from the curved breast of the Empress".
He is a warrior but he is also a child.
The exception is that the heroic cycle does
not end with his death: the fallen hero
awaits resurrection. It is not surprising
that for the majority of Mexicans Cuauh¬
temoc should be the "young grandfather",
the origin of Mexico: the hero's tomb is
the cradle of the people. This is the dia¬
lectic of myth, and Cuauhtemoc is more i
a myth than an historical figure. I
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
- ->*
'V '
Photo © Gisèle Freund, Paris
The steps of time
Imposing pyramid at Teotihuacán, north of Mexico City, was
until recently covered by a mass of rubble, earth and vegetation.
A major religious centre of ancient Mexico, Teotihuacán went into
decline long before the conquistadors arrived.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Doña Malinche
Doña Malinche (or Doña Marina), the Indian woman who became the mistress of the
Spanish general Cortés, is often taken as a symbol of Mexico's violation by the
conquistadors. In the drawing below, from the Codex Azcatitlán, a manuscript dating
from the beginning of the Spanish conquest, she can be seen (far right) beside Cortés,
escorted by a group of Spanish soldiers and Indian porters.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
k Another element enters here, an analo¬
gy that makes this history a true poem in
search of fulfilment: the location of Cuauh-
témoc's tomb is not known. The mystery
of his burial place is one of our obsessions-
as Mexicans. To discover it would mean
nothing less than to return to our origins,
to reunite ourselves with our ancestry, to
break out of our solitude. It would be a
resurrection.
If we ask about the third figure of the
triad, the Mother, we hear a double ans¬
wer. It is no secret to anyone that Mexi¬
can Catholicism is centred on the cult of
the Virgin of Guadalupe. In the first place,
she is an Indian Virgin; in the second
place, the scene of her appearance to the
Indian Juan Diego was a hill that formerly
contained a sanctuary dedicated to To-
nantzin, "Our Mother", the Aztec god¬
dess of fertility.
We know that the Conquest coincided
with the apogee of the cult of two mascu¬
line divinities: Quetzalcóatl, the self-sacri¬
ficing god, and Huitzilopochtli, the young
warrior-god. The defeat of these gods
which is what the Conquest meant to the
Indian world, because it was the end of a
cosmic cycle and the inauguration of a
new divine kingdom caused the faithful
to return to the ancient feminine deities.
This phenomenon of a return to the
maternal womb, so well known to the
psychologist, is without doubt one of the
determining causes of the swift popularity,
of the cult of the Virgin. The Indian god¬
desses were goddesses of fecundity, link¬
ed to the cosmic rhythms, the vegetative
processes and agrarian rites. The Catholic
Virgin is also the Mother (some Indian
pilgrims still call her Guadalupe-Tonantzin),
but her principal attribute is not to watch
over the fertility of the earth but to provide
refuge for the unfortunate.
The situation has changed: the wor¬
shippers do not try to make sure of their
harvests but to find a mother's lap. The
Virgin is the consolation of the poor, the
shield of the weak, the help of the oppress¬
ed. In sum, she is the Mother of orphans.
All men are born disinherited and their true
condition is orphanhood, but this is parti
cularly true of the Indians and the poor in
Mexico.
The image of the Chingada, the violated
mother, may be used to evoke the Span¬
ish conquest, which was also a violation,
not only in the historical sense but also in
the very flesh of Indian women.
The symbol of this violation is Doña
Malinche, the mistress of Cortés. It is
true that she gave herself voluntarily to
the conquistador, but he forgot her as
soon as her usefulness was over. Doña
Marina, as she was called by the Span¬
iards, came to represent the Indian women
who were fascinated, violated or seduced
by the Spaniards. And as a small boy will
not forgive his mother if she abandons
him to search for his father, the Mexican
people have not forgiven "La Malinche"
for her betrayal. She embodies the open,
the chingado, to our closed, stoic, impas¬
sive Indians.
Cuauhtemoc and Doña Marina are thus
two antagonistic and complementary fig¬
ures. There is nothing surprising about our
cult of the young emperor, an image of
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
...and Our Lady of Guadalupe
The cult of Our Lady of Guadalupe, practised throughout Mexico, incorporates survivals from
pre-Hispanic times. The Virgin appeared to an Indian, Juan Diego, on a hill near Mexico City
where the Aztec fertility goddess Tonantzin was once worshipped, and some Indians still refer
to her as "Guadalupe-Tonantzin". Below, Mexican Indians pray at a portable shrine
dedicated to Our Lady of Guadalupe.
Photo © Marino Benzi-Editions du Chêne, Paris
the sacrificed sonand there is also no¬
thing surprising about the curse that
weighs on La Malinche. This explains the
success of the contemptuous adjective
ma/inchista to denounce all those who
have been corrupted by foreign influences.
When we shout "Viva México, hijos de
la chingada!" (Long live Mexico, children
of the chingada!), we express our desire
to live closed off from the outside world
and above all from the past. In this shout,
we condemn our origins and deny our
hybridism. The strange permanence of
Cortés and La Malinche in the Mexican's
imagination and sensibilities reveals that
they are something more than historical
figures: they are symbols of a secret con¬
flict that we have still not resolved.
When he repudiates La Malinchethe
Mexican Evethe Mexican breaks his ties
with the past, renounces his origins, and
lives in isolation and solitude.
The Mexican condemns all his tradi¬
tions at once, the whole set of gestures,
attitudes and tendencies in which it is
now difficult to distinguish the Spanish
from the Indian. For that reason the
Hispanic thesis, which would have us
descend from Cortés to the exclusion of
La Malinche, is the patrimony of a few
extremists.
The same can be said of indigenist pro¬
paganda, which is also supported by fana¬
tical creóles and mestizos, while the In¬
dians have never paid it the slightest
attention. The Mexican does not want to
be either an Indian or a Spaniard. Nor
does he want to be descended from them.
He denies them. And he does not affirm
himself as a mixture, but rather as an
abstraction: he is a man. He becomes the
son of Nothingness. His beginnings are
in his own self.
The opposition between life and death
was not so absolute to the ancient Mexi¬
cans as it is to us. Life extended into
death, and vice versa. Death was not the
natural end of life but one phase of an
infinite cycle. Life, death and resurrection
were stages of a cosmic process which
repeated itself continuously.
Life had no higher function than to flow
into death, its opposite and complement;
and death, in turn, was not an end in itself:
man fed the insatiable hunger of life with
his death. Sacrifices had a double pur¬
pose: on the one hand man participated
in the creative process, at the same time
paying back to the gods the debt con¬
tracted by his species; on the other hand
he nourished cosmic life and also social
life, which was nurtured by the former.
Perhaps the most characteristic aspect
of this conception is the impersonal nature
of the sacrifice. Since their lives did not
belong to them, their deaths lacked any
personal "meaning.
Our indigenous ancestors did not believe
that their deaths -belonged to them, just
as they never thought that their lives were
really theirs in the Christian sense. Every¬
thing was examined to determine, from
birth, the life and death of each man: his
social class, the year, the place, the day,
the hour. The Aztec was as little respon¬
sible for his actions as for his death.
Space and time were bound together
and formed an inseparable whole. There
was a particular "time" for each place,
each of the cardinal points and the centre
in which they were immobilized. Whereas
we dissociate space and time, mere stage
sets for the actions of our lives, there were
as many "space-times" for the Aztecs as
there were combinations in the priestly
calendar, each one endowed with a parti¬
cular qualitative significance, superior to
human will.
Religion and destiny ruled their lives, as
morality and freedom rule ours. We live
under the sign of liberty, and everything
Greek fatality and the grace of the
theologians involves choosing and
struggle, but for the Aztecs the problem
reduced itself to investigating the never-
clear will of the gods.
The advent of Catholicism radically
modified this situation. Sacrifice and the
idea of salvation, formerly collective, be¬
came personal. Freedom was humanized,
embodied in man. To the ancient Aztecs
the essential thing was to assure the con¬
tinuity of creation; sacrifice did not bring
about salvation in another world, but
cosmic health; the universe, and not the
individual, was given life by the blood and
death of human beings. For Christians it
is the individual who counts.
Both attitudes, opposed as they may
seem, have a common note: life, collec¬
tive or individual, looks forward to a death
that in its way is a new life. Life only
justifies and transcends itself when it is
realized in death, and death is also a
transcendence, in that it is a new life.
To Christians death is a transition, a
somersault between two lives, the tem¬
poral and the otherworldly; to the Aztecs
it was the profoundest way of participating
in the continuous regeneration of the
creative forces, which were always in dan¬
ger of being extinguished if they were not
provided with blood, the sacred food. In
both systems life and death lack auto¬
nomy; they are the two sides of a single
reality.
Octavio Paz
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Fiesta of death
Mexicans, perhaps more than any other people, regard death as a
close acquaintance to be mocked, serenaded and treated with
broad humour and slapstick burlesque. Shown here are some
expressions of this attitude, which may seem macabre to other
peoples but comes quite naturally to the Mexican. (2) Grinning
figures of death in the carnival at Tlaxcala; (1 and 4) two skeleton
bands; (3) A skull made of sugar, traditionally eaten on All Saints'
Day. Inscribed on the forehead is the name of the person who
gives or receives it. I5) Death is a major theme in the work of the
great Mexican artist José Guadalupe Posada (1851-19131. In this
engraving, a grinning skeletal Don Quixote mounted on a skeletal
steed routs the skeletons of his enemies.
fe.
Xë'
9
i . i
Í
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A
x/,
- ~^^^t
r\ \<í
i»Ü&.
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
OUT OF THE TROPICS,
AN AVANT-GARDE ART
by Arturo Uslar-Pietri
OVER the past 20 years, in a sur¬
prising and significant departure,
a group of Latin Americans has
taken the lead in one of the most novel
developments in contemporary art: kinetic
art (See Unesco Courier, September 1963).
In going beyond abstraction and in for¬
mulating what must be regarded as a new
plastic language rich in possibilities, these
artists have contributed to the creation
and definition of a new dimension in art.
Kinetic artists have discovered the ele¬
ments of a new language . and a new
relationship. They believe that works of
art, instead of simulating space and
movement, should create their own move¬
ment and a new spatial relationship with
the people looking at them. Instead of
contemplating a work of art from the
outside, people participate in it. In some
instances, they can actually install them¬
selves physically inside it, like being in a
forest or in a rainstorm.
The fact that artists from Latin America
have become some of the leading creators i
of the new kinetic language in the world's ?
ARTURO USLAR-PIETRI, Venezuela's ambassador
and permanent delegate to Unesco and member of
the Organization's Executive Board, is one of Latin
America's most famous writers. He is the author of
many novels, short stories and essays such as La Otra
América ("The Other America") and has been profes¬
sor of Latin American literature at Columbia University
(U.S.A.). His novel Las Lanzas Coloradas has been
published in English as The Red Lances (Knopf, New
York. 1962).
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Much of Latin America is situated in the tropics. The vast impenetrable forests,
rugged high plateaux, mighty rivers and endless beaches of the tropical landscape
constitute a hostile, menacing presence whose multifarious forms and colours are
constantly changing. This landscape has inspired a major development in modern
art, kinetic art, in which three Venezuelan artists, Jesús Soto, Carlos Cruz Diez and
Alejandro Otero play a leading role. For the close link between their work and
natural life in the tropics (below) see also page 33 and centre colour pages.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
, art centres has caused surprise and given
rise to controversy.
There are some who claim in rather
simplistic fashion that this type of art is
not suited to the development of Latin
America and its social and historical back¬
ground. Latin American artists, they feel,
should confine themselves to popular
realism or political expressionism instead
of forging ahead in search of new forms
and types of expression that are in the
forefront of Western artistic creation.
However, the fact is that these artists
have not broken with their past, nor have
they gone against their own sensibility.
Anybody who has been in contact with
them or has heard them speak soon dis¬
covers that there are solid ties between
what they are creating, what they them¬
selves are and what, as Latin Americans,
they are keeping alive.
I would go even further and suggest
that it is the very fact that they are Latin
Americans that has prompted them to
strike out in search of new spatial forms
and movement. Kinetic art is not merely
an offshoot of machines and big cities: it
reflects the changing relationship of man
with his natural environment and with
the movement in which he participates.
This could largely explain why Latin Amer¬
ican sensibility is suited to the creation of
kinetic art.
Latin Americans have always had a
special relationship with nature. They
have never seen it as a mere backcloth,
for nature has always conditioned their
way of life. Most of Latin America is
situated in the tropical or sub-tropical
regions, where the landscape assumes
proportions that are unknown in Europe.
Quite apart from the sheer mass of the
inaccessible snow-capped cordilleras, the
ocean-like expanses of the plains, the
incredible vastness of the impenetrable
forests and the majesty of the heaviest-
flowing and most fickle rivers in the world,
nature itself is particularly hostile and
aggressive. Its vastness and magnitude
are a threat to man. Vegetation prolif¬
erates and is all-devouring. From time to
time, floods turn the plains into inland
seas. In a matter of hours, one can move
from dense, humid forests to bleak and
barren uplands.
The people of Latin America have lived
for centuries in open conflict with nature.
Plants and animals have been their tradi¬
tional invaders. The landscape is always
on the move, lying in wait. To venture
into the realm of nature is to court danger.
Moreover, in the tropics, nature is con¬
tinually changing even in the course of a
single day. In the morning, it flares up
with life, at midday it is obliterated by the
dazzling whiteness of the sun and, as the
evening draws in, it breaks down into an
endless profusion of tints and hues before
turning at night into a frenzied theatre of
moving shadows and indistinct noises.
In Latin America, man's relationship with
space has a dynamic and dangerous qual¬
ity that is unfamiliar to Europeans. It is
space which man has still scarcely manag¬
ed to subjugate or penetrate.
'Kinetic art
reflects man's
changing
relationship
with his
environment'
Man has not succeeded in creating a
stable relationship with the shifting, trem¬
bling earth, the bursting torrents, the arid
or inundated plains, the volcanoes belch¬
ing fire into the sky, or the stealth of rav¬
enous and hostile animals.
In the Latin American cultural melting
pot, there is an all-pervasive impression
that the white and the black, the two pro¬
tagonists who came from outside the
continent, are still somewhat ill at ease in
their environment. Only the Indians have
succeeded in establishing a harmonious
and balanced relationship with nature in
Latin America.
We have no record as to how the blacks
reacted, but we have ample evidence of
the fear and anxiety which gripped the
Spaniards when they were confronted with
nature in Latin America. A work such as
that written by the Jesuit priest José de
Acosta at the end of the 16th century
echoes their apprehension at having to
contend with the landscape and the plant
and animal life. For Europeans, the Atlan¬
tic crossing alone represented a sudden
break with centuries-old norms, distances
and living patterns linking them with their
natural environment.
This break in continuity and the appear¬
ance of a new set of dimensions were
bound to affect the psychological make-up
of these people and their attitude to life.
Their whole frame of reference was sud¬
denly transformed.
Concepts of altitude and distance
changed, as did the significance of natural
phenomena, and the impact this had on
people's minds was far-reaching. It gave
rise to a sort of instability psychosis and
an agonizing break in man's day-to-day
relations with his world. Everything was
different, changing and unfamiliar. Rain
was a torrential downpour unleashed from
the sky and rivers were such vast expanses
of water that the other side did not exist.
Fear of warlike Indians was only one
thing: dread of the uncharted and menac¬
ing wilderness was another. We do not
knowbut it is easy for us to imagine
what enormous psychological pressures
the conquistadors must have been sub¬
jected to when they felt that all the spatial
relationships which had hitherto governed
and secured their lives were collapsing.
We cannot know what the companions
of Francisco d'Orellana must have felt
when, like dwarfs in an infinite fastness,
they sailed down the immense and unfa¬
thomable Amazon, or what Hernando de
Soto and his handful of men sensed when
they entered the Mississippi basin, which
could have contained the plateau of Cas¬
tile a hundred times over and the waters
of the Guadalquivir as many times again.
Or, for that matter, what Vasco Nunez de
Balboa felt when he first glimpsed the
Pacific; or what the straggling bands of
adventurers thought as the days went by
and they saw no end to the oceans of
grass of the Orinoco and La Plata plains;
or the feeling of awe which gripped Piz-
arros's comrades in arms when they first
set eyes on the wall of rock and snow
formed by the Andes.
Perhaps a good many of the psychotic
and criminal reactions engendered by the
conquest of Latin America stemmed from
the fact that man had taken so enormous
a step and had broken his normal, tradi¬
tional relations with space.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
This state of mind has survived in
various forms among the descendants of
the Spanish conquerors and the black
peoples; they are heirs to a disorder that
has never been completely overcome. For
thousands of years, Europeans, Africans
and Asians have adapted to the dimensions
and characteristics of their environment
and have assimilated them. But the
culture, language, historical vision and
sense of landscape which have prevailed
in Latin America are those of the European
transplant.
'Nature has
played a
decisive
role in man's
adventure on
this continent'
Cultural intermingling has not solved
the problem; in fact, it has kept some of
the contradictions alive. The image
which present-day Latin Americans have
of volcanoes, rivers, alligators, snakes, and
so on, is not that of the Indians. It is
closer to that of the Europeans who expe¬
rienced the initial shock of transplantation.
They still find nature threatening and
strange. They apprehend it as an immea¬
surably large being which is gravitating
around them and fighting them, and with
which they cannot live on confident and
stable terms.
Nature has been a dominant theme in
Latin American literature right up to the
present day because it was not only an
impressive new experience but also played
a decisive role in man's adventure on the
continent.
To my mind, this has also been a deci¬
sive factor in the part which Latin Amer¬
ican artists have played in the develop- j
ment of kinetic art. I
Photo © Alejandro Otero, Paris
The Venezuelan artist Alejandro Otero has created
giant metal structures with mobile sections, which
are remarkable examples of the integration of works
of art into the landscape. Pablo Neruda, the great
Chilean poet and Nobel Prize-winner, once wrote of
these outdoor structures: "Now they are shimmering
lights, now playing water. They are vibrant
structures, whose loftiness is both material and
spiritual." Below, one of a group of three works
entitled Delta Solar created by Otero in
Washington D.C.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
r Of many possible examples, I shall dis¬
cuss three leading Venezuelan artists I
know well, who came to Paris in the early
1950s at a time when abstract painting
seemed to have exhausted its possibilities
and who produced work whose originality
was instrumental in charting new directions
in art.
Jesus Soto came from the most tropical
and forested region of Venezuela. He was
brought up in Ciudad Bolivar on the
Orinoco on the edge of the Guyana forest,
in a geographical setting in which, per¬
haps unlike any other, human beings were
puny compared with the subjugating and
manifold presence of a natural environ¬
ment that was imbued with strength,
dynamism and myriad forms. Ciudad Boli¬
var was not a centre for training in the
arts but a long-established settlement on
the banks of a vast river and at the edge
of an impenetrable tropical forest. The
most striking presence that Soto witnessed
until he was in his teens was that of the
forest.
After studying at the School of Plastic
Arts in Caracas and spending some time
teaching in an art school in Maracaibo,
Soto came to Paris filled with youthful
enthusiasm. He arrived in postwar Paris,
where total anarchy reigned as all kinds of
abstract art were being taught. Soto was
captivated by all the possibilities which lay
before him and, after a short breathing-
space, he ventured boldly along a new
road: the art of movement and spectator
participation.
With amazing speed, he became an
innovator. He sensed that it was possible
to create a new space in which the work
of art and the spectator were merged and
in which movement would not be simu¬
lated or mechanically generated but would
be created by the spontaneous and delib¬
erate participation of the spectator.
He was to claim later that his aim was
to "integrate time into art", in other
words, to go much further than Mondrian,
Kandinsky and Malevich.
He began by assembling piles of super¬
imposed translucent or opaque elements
in varying patterns, which interacted with
one another as the spectator's eyes moved
across them. He created new visions and
optical illusions which, through their action
on the eye, set up endless vibrations of
lines and colours to give an impression of
fluid and ¡iving space endowed with a
fourth dimension.
These new spaces created by Soto,
where the spectator enters into, and forms
part of, a new relationship involving
movement and variations in colour, line
and perspective, are strongly reminiscent
of some of the features of his native tro¬
pical landscape. The movement of vertical
rods superimposed in differing thicknesses,
and the colours and forms which appear
to move and change, produce an effect
very similar to that of the palm fronds,
creepers and ferns in the dense tropical
forest, where the interplay of light and
distance seems to subject them to per¬
petual variation.
Between Soto's works and certain
aspects of nature in the tropics there is a
correlation whose existence has, in fact,
been demonstrated in a film.
Soto did not make a conscious and
deliberate effort to' produce this effect; it
simply emerged during his search for a
new art form because of the way in which
his responses had been conditioned.
In his constant endeavour to encourage,
the participation of spectators and actually
integrate them into works of art, he has
succeeded in creating new forms which
offer the most extraordinary possibilities.
In his "ambiguous spaces", for instance,
he uses large plexiglass compartments in
which the transparent surfaces and visitors'
movements create an effect of contin¬
uously vibrating shapes, colours and
perspectives.
One of his most recent experiments
along these lines are the "penetrables",
dense hanging columns of nylon rope
which visitors enter, in which they lose
their bearings and are swallowed up, as if
in dense jungle or a tropical cloudburst.
The visual sensation is enhanced by the
experience of being in physical contact
with a tentacular and amorphous material
which covers and envelops the participant
like the spray from a waterfall.
Soto has also created "audio-pene-
trables" made of resonating metal rods.
As the spectator passes by, these rods set
up a continuous metallic vibrating sound
which adds to the vibrations of light and
CONTINUED PAGE 66
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite page:
Indians dress up as their Aztec
forebears in a scene from the Dance
of the Conquest in Mexico City (above).
In this dance retracing the events of
the Spanish invasion, the performers
give free rein to their taste for rich
ornamentation and brilliant colours, a
distinctive feature of Mexican popular
art. In Brazil, many of today's popular
dances such as the macumba (below)
are of African origin.
Photo © Gisèle Freund, Paris
Photo Klaus Meyer © Rapho, Paris
Centre double page:
Impact of nature on art is strikingly
evident in these photos of a South
American forest scene (above right)
and of two contemporary works of
art. At left, a sculpture of metallic
rods by the Venezuelan Jesús Soto.
(A similar work by Soto stands In the
entrance of a building at Unesco's
headquarters in Paris.) Below, a
chromatic structure by his compatriot
Carlos Cruz Diez. Born in the tropics,
both artists succeed in transposing the
impression of a dense tropical jungle
in their works.
Photo © Jesús Soto, Paris
Photo Ktaus Meyer © Rapho, Paris
Photo © Cruz Diez, Paris
Above, four strolling players in the Andes, where
musical instruments of local origin like the Indian flute
are still played alongside those imported by the
Spanish settlers.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
- i
1
1
IM 'i ffl
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
.:¡P>
y-
>í
4
ki
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
by Pablo Macera
THE
LIVING LEGACY
OF
THE ANDES
Photos Hans Silvester ©Rapho, Paris
The conquistadors transformed Cuzco, ancient capital of the Inca
empire, into a Spanish city. Almost all the buildings in the centre of
modern Cuzco rest on Inca foundations. Opposite page, entrance of the
Inca Temple of the Moon at Ollantay Tambo near Cuzco. Andalusian
influence is strongly marked in the narrow Cuzco street above.
THREE South American countries,
Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia, consti¬
tute the heartland of the ancient
civilization of the Andes. Other countries
like Colombia and Chile also played some
part in this civilization, whose influence
can be felt even in the extreme north of
the Republic of Argentina.
Over an area of almost 3 million square
kilometres, millions of people thus live
often without realizing itaccording to
norms of conduct that evolved thousands
of years ago.
In speaking of "the civilization of the
Andes," we are not merely referring to the
famous Inca emperors of Cuzco. The
Incas were to Andean civilization what the
Romans were to classical Mediterranean
civilization or the Persians to Mesopo¬
tamia: an end rather than a beginning.
A simple date demonstrates this fact.
The Incas began their conquests in the
middle of the 15th century and their
empire was only 80 years old when it was
destroyed by the Spanish invaders. Andean
civilization, on the other hand, had begun
to take shape thousands of years before.
The most ancient inhabitants of what is
today Peru and Ecuador lived 20,000 years
ago alongside the giant sloth and the
sabre-toothed tiger.
Around 2000 or 3000 B.C., the popu¬
lation began to domesticate numerous
plants (Lima beans, kidney beans, cotton,
potatoes and maize) and such animals as
the llama, the guinea pig and the duck.
The invention of pottery, which also dates
from this period, allowed them to make
more efficient use of fire and water.
Some 3,000 to 4,000 years elapsed
between the formation of the first agrarian
societies in the Andes and the Spanish
conquest in the 16th century. Empires
rose and fell during this time, and many
highly complex and sophisticated cultures w
were implanted in various parts of the vast t
PABLO MACERA, Peruvian historian, is a professor
at the university of San Marcos in Lima (Peru). A
specialist on economic history and the history of art,
he is director of the Centre of Andean Rural History.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Threading through
the centuries
Andean region. Three of these cultures
Chavin, Tihuanaco and Inca (dating from
1000 B.C., 800 A.D. and 1400 A.D.
respectively) still constitute a unifying
link between Peruvians, Ecuadorians and
Bolivians. We can say that geographically
Chavin was an "Ecuadorian" culture,
Tihuanaco a "Bolivian culture" and that
of the Incas was a "Peruvian" one, al¬
though this is an approximation since Peru,
Bolivia and Ecuador are very recent cre¬
ations, barely 150 years old.
How much of these ancient Andean
civilizations disappeared when the Euro¬
peans arrived? How much still survives?
Even in the Andean countries, no-one
knows for certain, and the question
arouses vigorous controversy in which
scientific considerations take second place
to political passions.
Those who hold conservative political
views claim that they belong to a Western,
Christian society. For them, Andean
culture is only of marginal' importance
within the framework created by European
colonialism. Moderates say that theirs is
a mixed society a mestizo culture
whereby they try to mask the conflicts
that exist between Andean and European
culture.
The truth is quite different. A provincial,
Western-type culture does of course exist
in these South American countries, but it
is found primarily in certain urban areas,
where its future is in question.
The mestizos, members of a group
which is difficult to define from a scientific
standpoint, have never since colonial
times managed to emerge as an entity
independent of Andean or European
culture.
But for most of the population, Andean
culture is still the only frame of reference.
This is true not only of the Amerindians
belonging to different ethnic and linguistic
groups (Quechuas, Aymarás, Urochipayas
and Yas) but of all the other inhabitants of
Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia.
At least 90 per cent of the place names
in these countries come from the Andean
languages. But more important, Andean
and not European culture shapes economic
and social structures in the rural areas of
Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia, and this is
where the overwhelming majority of the
people live. South American farmers
were of course subject to the feudal system k
of the hacienda, or ranch, and the Spa- Y
An ancient civilization flourished in the Andes many centuries before the
arrival of the Spanish invaders. From its heartland in what is now Ecuador,
Peru and Bolivia, its Influence stretched as far as northwest Argentina. In
the rural areas of the Andes today, a popular tradition survives of hand-
woven objects whose patterns and vivid colours recall those of the Incas.
The works shown here display animal motifs a serpent, a two-headed
condor or eagleas well as stylized representations of the human form
and geometric designs.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
niards tried to introduce new crops and
^ farming techniques. But 400 years later,
the Amerindian ways still prevail.
The ancient crops such as the potato,
maize, and yucca still form the basis of
their diet, and the people of the Andes
practise many of the neolithic farming
techniques used by their ancestors before
the Spanish Conquest. Oxen, ploughs,
wheels and metals are practically un¬
known; farmers still use wood and stone
tools, without the help of animals.
But Andean civilization has not only sur¬
vived at the economic and technolog¬
ical level; it also shapes the people's ways
of thinking and their most sophisticated
art and religious forms. The peoples of
Peru, Ecuador and Bolivia do not perceive,
organize or represent Space or Time like
Westerners.
Europeans think of time in terms of
progress and are sure that the future is
bound to be better than the past. But in
Andean civilization, time is cyclical, with
an ascending and a descending phase
leading to a great Universal Crisis (Pacha¬
cutec) which may bring about the end of
the world.
This is a cosmic vision no doubt suited
to ancient agrarian societies subject to
seasonal cycles. It is also appropriate in
an environment in which natural disas¬
ters floods and droughts-
are so frequent.
This notion of Pachacutec explains the
importance of certain Catholic cults like
that of the Lima Lord of Miracles, who is
none other than an ancient god, Pacha-
camac, dressed up as a Christian. The
same could be said of the "Taitacha Tem¬
blores" (earthquakes) of Cuzco.
Nevertheless, Andean culture does not
express an attitude of pessimism and
resignation. Instead, it embodies the idea
that man's mission is to re-establish a
cosmic balance through such concepts as
Tinkuy and Paikiki. Tinkuy denotes the
idea of struggle but also of union. Paikiki
is the magic counterpart which compen¬
sates and counterbalances. The people
of the Andes still think of their lives in
terms of Pachacutec (crisis), Tinkuy (strife
and union) and Paikiki (parity and equU
librium).
When they are confronted with des¬
perate hardship and poverty which give
the lie to the Western idea of progress,
they do not lapse into pessimism, "fhey
know that their duty is to join with the
positive forces in the universe to overcome
The gods dance at Oruro
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Above, masked dancers parade
through the streets of Oruro,
capital of the mining region of
Bolivia, at carnival time. The
festivities closely resemble the
ancient rites of the Indians in the
region of Lake Titicaca, and
illustrate how pre-Columbian
myths and forms of expression
have survived in the high
plateaux of the Andes. Although
the devils' masks worn during
the carnival display Spanish and
Catholic influences, they are
inspired by religious images
such as that of the great Inca
god Viracocha. Left, one of the
oldest masks worn at Oruro;
right, a modern devil's mask.
Photo ©Dominiaue Desjardins, Paris
Pachacutec. This cosmic vision is reflected
in the way space is used and represented
in poetic symbolism.
Like all agrarian societies of the oriental-
despotic type, that could tap large man¬
power reserves, the Andean societies
erected buildings that required enormous
masses of material.
This practice survived into the Spanish
colonial period because the Spaniards had
the same abundance of workers as the
Inca emperors and the Chavin priests.
Egyptian and Babylonian architecture
also used enormous masses of material.
All these edifices are designed according
to a special order, or rule, which in the
case of Andean civilization may be des¬
cribed as the horizontal principle. On the
coasts and in the mountains, everything
was built on the horizontal: human cre¬
ations were parallel to the landscape, so
that the buildings seem designed to
express the hidden potential of natural
shapes.
We find this principle throughout the
region: in a temple of the pre-ceramic
period on the coast; in sanctuaries of the
Chavin and Tihuanaco cultures; and in the
ranch houses of the colonial and repub¬
lican periods. It has also survived in
mid-20th century buildings such as the
Lima Civic Centre, where a young Peruvian
architect made bold use of concrete to
create large masses which, far from clash¬
ing with the urban surroundings, actually
reflect them.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
But this use of parallel and horizontal
lines is nowhere more evident than in
Cuzco, where all is sad and grandiose.
Nothing is more Andean than Cuzco
cathedral, built nevertheless by a Spanish
architect. The massive cathedral stretches
along one side of the square like an
immense parapet defending the Sacsahua-
man fortress, unlike the Jesuit church of
La Compañía which rises vertically towards
the sky.
It is important to remember, however,
that the economic and social foundations
of Andean civilization were profoundly
altered by the European invasion of the
16th century. The conquerors demanded
recognition as conquerors, and to survive,
the conquered peoples had to dissimulate.
Dissimulation is the second principle of
Andean civilization under Spanish and
creóle domination. For the last 400 years
Andean civilization has worn camouflage.
In Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia, "yes"
can mean either "yes", or "no" but one
can never be sure unless one is an initiate.
Language not only enshrines the legitimate
and necessary hypocrisy of the underdog,
but it is also a tactical device for preserving
what is one's own and triumphing over a
dominant culture by taking over one of its
power bases.
It also presupposes a generalized use of
metaphor. Whites and creóles in South
America today contemptuously describe
the Indians as liars because they cannot
understand that metaphors have become
an underpinning of Andean culturea
structure reinforced by the colonial situa¬
tion. Let us examine some results of this
process in the vast area stretching from
Quito (Ecuador) to the frontiers of Bolivia
and Argentina.
Until the arrival of the Europeans,
Andean women fastened their cloaks with
a brooch shaped like a waxing moon
whose masculine counterpart was the
Tumi or sacrificial knife. This ambivalent
sexual shape (Moon-Tumi) did not dis¬
appear in colonial or republican days but
tended to oe replaced by the shape of the
soup spoon introduced by the Spaniards.
In Andean civilization there were two
basic ritual objects: the Conopa, a stone
figure shaped like a llama, and the Kero,
a wooden receptacle with straight sides.
The Conopa-llama symbol changed into a
pottery bull, and in Ecuador the Kero was
turned into a cup. The progression is
suggestive: from moon to spoon; from
reclining llama to bull; from Kero to cup.
In each case the utilitarian shapes of the
triumphant culture have been incorporated
by the defeated culture, which apparently
renounced its own sacred forms.
Among the Chinchero Indians of Peru
and the Urochipayas of Bolivia, the qui¬
pus, a form of writing that uses knotted
string, imitates a girl's tresses, since both
words and hair come out of the head. No
scribe was allowed to read the sacred
letters without first donning a female wig.
This special reading wig was kept in a fox-
skin bag, the fox being a female deity
symbolizing cunning and cleverness.
An even more famous example appears
in the Oruro carnival in Bolivia and the
Puño fiesta in Peru. They are basically the
same feast, which derives from ancient
pre-Spanish rituals practised between
lakes Titicaca and Poopo. The devils'
masks in these rituals are doubtless influ¬
enced by Catholic iconography, but they
are variations of religious images of much
earlier date: the heads of the god of
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
European soldiers; in the 18th century
they were dressed like provincial governors,
and in the 19th century they are shown
wearing the military uniforms of creóle
generals.
The St. James of Callapa had moved
even further into the future: stripped of
the silks he wore a mere ten years ago,
he was wearing green battle-dress.
The Callapa St. James also reflects
another historical experience: he has the
wig and glasses which, according to the
sacristan, were worn by the guerrilleros.
What is the future of Andean culture?
Many fear it will disappear in the process
of industrialization which is under way in
Latin America. For many, industrialization
and modernization mean adopting Western
cultural models.
This danger is compounded by the
social structure of the Andean countries.
A city-based white and mestizo minority
dominates a great majority of poor, rural
Indians and mestizos. To understand this
phenomenon one must remember that the
independence revolutions led by Washing¬
ton in North America and by Bolivar in
South America were basically oligarchic
revolutions.
In countries like Peru and Bolivia, the
Creoles have been in power for 150 years,
and of course think of themselves as
Europeans who happened to be born in
another continent.
The cultural uniformity which today's
world is heading for is a danger for the
whole1 human race. The survival and free
development of cultures like that of the
Andes broadens the scope of man's
heritage.
Pablo Macera
PANPIPES AND STORIES IN STRING. The Incas invented a remarkably efficient
substitute for writing known as quipus, knotted strings of various colours (see
drawing above left). A 16th-century Spanish chronicler noted that "It is incredible to
see what the Incas can record in this way. All that books can present in the way of
history, law, ceremonies and commercial accounts is expressed in Quipus with
astonishing precision". Quipus are still used in many Indian communities in the
Andes. Another survival from ancient times is the rondador, a kind of panpipe
played by the Indians of Peru (above).
Chavin and that of the great deity Viraco¬
cha which has survived at Tihuanaco.
The Andean gods worshipped more than
4,000 years ago are still dancing in the
20th century.
A few months ago, while visiting the
Callapa sanctuary in the Department of
Oruro (Bolivia), I was struck by the naive
mural paintings of Noah's Ark, and even
more fascinated by the figure of St. James
over the main altar. The St. James Mata
mores (the Moor-slayer) of the Spanish
reconquest of Spain from the Moors had
been transformed into St. James Matain-
dios (the Indian-slayer) of the Spanish
conquest of Latin America. The Amer¬
indians took over St. James and identified
him with lllapa, the thunder-god of their
own religion.
Indian depictions of St. James were
decked out with all the trappings of the
enemy. The oldest look like 16th-century
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
I
JTJTHN Latin America, anyone who
isn't descended from the Indians
or the blacks just came off the
ship." This saying, popularized despite
its non-popular origins, exactly describes
the state of ethnic and cultural intermixing
in the continent today. But a devil's ad¬
vocate looking back 400 years could argue
that the Indians, the only natives on Latin
American soil, saw both white and black
men descend from the shipsthe former
from the bridge and the latter out of the
bilges.
Intermingling began almost immedi¬
ately, since the conquistadors brought no
women with them. It has continued to
such a degree that it provokes astonish¬
ment, perhaps because it is unique to Latin
America (unlike the superimposition of
cultures produced by conquest or colonial¬
ism in other parts of the world) and also
because its ethnic components were more
strongly different than those which formed
the basis of racial intermingling in Europe
or North America.
But one must specify the regions in
which this racial and cultural fusion has
occurred and define the levels it has reach¬
ed. The situation in the Antilles, the Carib¬
bean, Brazil, Uruguay, Argentina and
Chile where the Amerindians have disap¬
peared or survive only as small minori¬
ties quite unlike that of countries with
large indigenous populations like Ecuador,
Peru, Bolivia and parts of Central America
and of Mexico.
Whatever the level of cultural or ethnic
intermingling in the latter regions, the
phenomenon of acculturation has also
occurred to some degree the word accul¬
turation being understood as "the transfer
of cultural elements from one social group
or people to another".
Cultural intermingling, like ethnic inter¬
mingling, presupposes equal participation
in the mixing process: an enriching exchan¬
ge produced by the addition of cultural and
other values. Acculturation, on the other
hand, entails a loss. Certain cultural ele¬
ments always necessarily valuable or
valid may be imposed, directly or indirect¬
ly, on the original culture, or be adopted by
it, to the detriment of its values.
When one hears talk of "incorporating
the Indians into civilization" or of "inte- k
grating them into the life of the nation" in Y
JORGE ENRIQUE ADOUM, Ecuadorian poet and
writer, has published several volumes of poetry,
including an anthology. Informe Personal Sobre La
Situación (Personal Report on the Situation, Madrid,
1973). His play about the Spanish conquest of the
Inca empire, published in English as The Sun Trampled
Beneath the Horses' Hooves (The Massachusetts
Review, Winter-Spring 1974) has also been translated
into French, Swedish and Polish and performed in
several countries of Europe and Latin America. He
has taken part in Unesco's programme of studies on
Latin American cultures, and is now a member of the
editorial staff of the Unesco Courier.
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
COMMUNITIES IN CRISIS
The modern world is bringing mixed blessings
to the Indians of the cordilleras
How can a people
preserve its cultural
identity when
confronted with ways of
life far different from its
own? This is a very real
problem in Latin
America today, where
increasing numbers of
persons from isolated
rural areas are coming
into contact with city
life for the first time.
Even in once
inaccessible villages like
this one in the High
Andes (right), improved
transport and
communications are
making many changes
in the traditional pattern
of life.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
, countries where Amerindians constitute
between 40 and 80 per cent of the popu¬
lation and are the major source of the
nation's wealth as miners or farm workers,
it is clear that "civilization" and "the
nation" are white and mestizo, and not
Amerindian.
But the curious fact is that in Latin Amer¬
ica this discrimination is not racial but
social and cultural. In nearly all Latin Amer¬
ican countries where they constitute a
large part of the population, the Amerin¬
dians have access, although sometimes
only exceptionally, to higher education, to
economic and even to political power.
Indeed, there are men and women in the
professions, landowners, civil servants and
politicians who are more Amerindian than
mestizo.
But in order to aspire to such high status,
these people have had to renounce their
culture, beliefs, customs, clothes and lan¬
guage. The official language, which peo¬
ple must learn in order to exercise their
civic rights, is Spanish, which is also the
language in which business is done.
It may be that Spanish has already
absorbed all the words that it needs from
the languages of the Quechua Indians; but
the assimilated Indian learning Spanish
renounces his own language, first for
reasons of prestige, and secondly because
it will be of no use to him in the new circles
he will move in and because he will no
longer need it to talk to his erstwhile fellow
Amerindians. It sometimes even happens
that Indian children in cities will not answer
when addressed in Quechua.
The assimilation of isolated Indian
groups goes hand in hand with a transition
from a subsistence economy to a market
economy. This determines intercultural
contacts, be they sporadic or permanent.
When Indians remain in a state of isola¬
tion, they can only conceive of themselves
in relation to their own community, which
has a system of authority but no social
classes. As the Peruvian writer José
Carlos Mariategui has noted, the Amerin¬
dian "is never less free than when he is
alone". He only acquires our notion of
individual liberty when he comes into
contact with the dominant culture...
perhaps because it is at that moment that
he loses his liberty.
This sense of community is traditionally
expressed in institutions like the prestama-
nos (or "helping hand": unpaid collective
help in roofing a neighbour's house) or the
minga (collective work in communal fields
or digging irrigation ditches). But the
other, official, culture exploits this tra¬
dition of community life and work to pro¬
vide unpaid labour, with fines for absen¬
teeism, for road and railway construction
and for building schools and churches.
And although the Indians thus come into
contact with new cultural forms new
tools, new architectural ideas it would be
a euphemism to speak of cultural inter¬
mingling.
Isolated groups of Indians in the High
Andes speak of "we" much more than of
"I", and are unlikely to use the words "I
have" except when answering a specific
question. This may be because they
possess little; but more important than this,
they have no notion of personal "posses¬
sion".
Members of the community acquire this
notion, together with the idea of individu
alism, when they come into contact with
the villages or cities of the whites and
mestizos. Here they also acquire such
hitherto unknown values as adultery, pros¬
titution, exploitation of women or the very
notion of exploitation.
In the cities, the man from the High
Andes can buy "modern" sandals, which
are reproductions of his traditional foot¬
wear except that the cord soles have been
replaced by ones cut from car tyres which
last longer. But if he buys a bicycle and
he will now utter the words "I have" he
will go back to the countryside much faster
but much more wearily than on his donkey,
with his wife in front and child behind and a
sheep slung across his shoulders. It is
interesting to ask at what point he begins
to feel different from his fellows, and who
benefits from the time he saves especially
if he is working for someone else.
When the Indians drift to the towns.
Three generations
of cordillerans
Photo Hans Silvester ©Rapho, Paris
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
which they are doing with increasing
frequency as mechanization reduces the
need for farm labourers, they generally
become part of a subproletariat of drop¬
outs.
When one of them succeeds in becoming
relatively well-off, he may command the
moderate amount of respect accorded to
mestizos. If he becomes more prosperous,
he may win the consideration reserved for
whites. His "rise" is reflected in a changed
legal status: he has more rights and influ¬
ence and, no matter how Amerindian his
facial features may be, he automatically
acquires a passport inscribed "White
Race" without even asking for it.
These are the extreme cases of isolation
and integration. But one can discern
between the two a series of stages which
for the moment appear to be irreversible.
Without falling back into the white-mestizo
paternalism which long predominated in
literature, anthropology and sociology, and
without wishing to idealize Amerindian
society, it seems necessary to examine
each individual case to see whether there
has been any mutual enrichment or real
intermingling of two or more cultures.
It was the haute couture fashion de¬
signers who introduced the vogue for pon¬
chos and Andean zoomorphic textile
designs to America and Europe. But when
the Indians themselves weave their carpets,
and replace these traditional designs by
floral or Persian patterns glimpsed in some
foreign catalogue, this is not a personal
decision but a result of imposed urban
tastes the effect of market demand.
Similarly, in Guatemala, the lovely highland
Indian pitchers of traditional shapes and
styles are nowadays made of plastic.
It is true that in the museums of Europe
hundreds of thousands of people enrich
their own culture by visiting exhibitions of
pre-Hispanic Indian art. But the inhabitants
of the High Andes have no inkling of such
events and sometimes know nothing of
such art forms. Far from continuing the
artistic traditions of even their recent
forebears, they are now producing pottery
adorned with Walt Disney figures.
It may be objected that the other side of
this cultural "enrichment" lies in tourist
consumption of work produced by authen¬
tic local craftsmen. But the basic and
immense difference is that the tourist
acquires a decorative object at no loss to
himself, whereas the Amerindians' acqui¬
sition of plastic articles reflects a confused
urge to be "modern" and "be like" some¬
one else the first stages of his incorpo¬
ration into a "superior" culture. The same
outlook is found in young villagers who
dress up in city clothes on Sundays or,
worse still, when they proudly don Batman i
or Tarzan T-shirts like some city youngsters. I
Once totally cut off from the outside world, the Indians living
in the Andes of Peru and Bolivia proudly keep up the cultural
traditions which colour so many aspects of their lives, from
everyday tasks to dress and jewellery. Their sense of belonging
to a community is so strong that the idea of loneliness is
totally alien to them. Shown here, three generations of
Indians of the High Andes.
Photo Hans Silvester ©Rapho, Paris
Photo © Gaillarde, Paris
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
, In a small Ecuadorian village on the
threshold of the Amazonian jungle, the
local schoolgirls recently took part in the
fiesta dressed in crêpe-paper costumes and
posing like ballerinas in Swan Lake, on a
float decorated like a gondola. This was
probably not a unique event. It would be
highly interesting to know by what myste¬
rious ways this Venetian art form had pene¬
trated into the jungle. It would be less
disturbing if one could be sure that these
girls had been taught something about
Italian culture and, more important, about
their own. (I have no idea whether they
parade canoes full of Amazonian "Indians"
in festivals in Nice or Venice, but I doubt
whether anyone would consider such
pathetic imitations of the "exotic" as a
cultural enrichment.)
Serious Latin American, and sometimes
European, music is often based on Indian
rhythms but does not use its instruments.
The Indians do, in fact, continue to play
their own music. But in addition to the
traditional flute and drum they play the
Spanish guitar now so popular that it has
become Latin American par excellence
as well as violins, harps, harmoniums and
accordions.
These are what they take to their fiestas,
which usually coincide with those of the
Catholic saints. But after the mass or the
procession (during which the Virgin has
been wearing a cloak encrusted with bank¬
notes, coins, dried corn ears and bits of
newspapers- and old mirrors) the Indians
celebrate their own ancient rite, of whose
profound mythological content the other,
official culture knows nothing.
During these fiestas, beer is drunk as
well as the traditional chicha, or corn liquor,
and although at fiesta-time the Indians get
their only opportunity to eat meat, they do
not drink milk (the word does not even
exist in Quechua) or eat eggs, because
these products must be sold on the "other
culture's" market. Thus, some Indians
have become so conditioned that they
would never dream of eating eggs, even if
they were given some as a present. In this
way, the inadequacies of a meagre diet
imposed by poverty, deficient in proteins
and excessive in carbohydrates are exacer¬
bated by taboos of economic origin.
Although the Indians do not know it,
their only compensation has been that two
of their indigenous products potatoes
and tobacco have conquered the world,
and that city fare including business
lunches and receptions for VIPs is often
graced by "typical native dishes" of the
sort which most Indians can never afford.
And often they are not typical at all.
It is becoming harder every day for
Amerindians to live in complete isolation.
The Cuna Indians of Panama, who inhabit
the San Bias archipelago (said. to have as
many islands as-there are days in the year)
have traditionally preserved their culture by
avoiding contact with the continent.
However, one of their nele-kantules or
medicine-men has complained that "Be¬
fore, it was easy to fight against this so-
called civilization because it was men.
Now it's worse, because it's machines".
He was talking about television. Because
of civilization, Indians do not have to go
anywhere to make cultural contact, since
concept-carrying machines come right into
their homes and stay there.
Transistor radios have invaded the whole
Andes region. But between the life of the
Indian communities and the idealized
image of urban life, there is such a brutal
contradiction that it must produce many
psychological tensions.
Indeed, radio and television may create a
feeling among the Indians that their 'life¬
style is old-fashioned and their houses ugly
and unhygienic. This is creating a depen¬
dence on luxury products which are alien to
their way of life, together with a depen¬
dence on the people who produce them. It
also produces a sense of frustration as they
realize that their own cultural values are
despised.
It now seems impossible to preserve
cultures intact. Each one must assimilate
the elements it considers most useful and
appropriate and not those imposed by any
kind of power structure.
In defining and preserving their cultural
identity, our peoples must first recognize
themselves in a mirror. But the mirror must
be neither convex nor concave, for if it is,
they will find a distorted image, of the face
they are trying to identify.
Jorge Enrique Adoum
ROVING CULTURE. Radio, television and cinema can be invaluable teaching aids but can
also be a vehicle for mediocrity. If children like these Indians (above) peering at "moving
pictures" on a square in La Paz (Bolivia) are fed a diet of poor-quality films, what opinion
will they form of "civilization" and "progress", not to mention their own cultures?
Moreover, when Indians leave their mountain villages to seek work in the towns (below),
the blandishments and benefits of urban life often lead them to turn their backs on their
own cultural traditions.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
by Augusto Roa Bastos
PARAGUAY has always been a vir¬
tually unknown quantity in Spanish-
American culture; in more ways
than one, it is "a land-locked island" in
the heart of the continent. What is more,
observers of Latin America have, for some
mysterious reason, rarely bothered to
pinpoint the reasons which have made
Paraguay a terra incognita, closed to
exploration and analysis.
Paraguay is actually one of the Latin
American nations and peoples that has
known the greatest vicissitudes. Para¬
guay's history reads like a melodrama, a
non-stop tragedy punctuated by moments
of great and sublime significance.
The basic stages in its history are as
follows:
It was from this land-locked island that
the conquistadors, obsessed with the myth
of Eldorado, set forth in search of treasure.
AUGUSTO ROA BASTOS, of Paraguay, won an in¬
ternational reputation with his book Hijo de Hombre,
published in English as Son of Man by Victor Goliancz,
London, 1965. His latest novel Yo el Supremo is re¬
quired reading for students of Latin American litera¬
ture in a number of European universities. He is cur¬
rently teaching Latin American literature at the univer¬
sity of Toulouse (France).
THE
LAND-LOCKED
ISLAND
OF PARAGUAY
Paraguay, like most Latin American countries, has a large rural population,
amounting to some 70 per cent of the total. Almost all of them are Indians
(above) who communicate among themselves in Guarani, a language which
is spoken in Paraguay's towns and cities as well as in the rural areas.
In its heyday, towards the end of the
16th century, it represented the largest
single colonial administrative unit. Para¬
guay was then the "Giant Province of the
Indies", and it stretched across almost half
the continent, from the torrid tropical
forests to the icy southern tip of Tierra del
Fuego.
When the mirage of gold disappeared,
the conquistadors were left only with the
vast resources represented by the indige¬
nous population, which eventually turned
out to be poor compensation for their loss.
They began to exploit "the gold of their
bodies", a dark, living metal which, instead
of running out, multiplied constantly. It
provided them with slave labour for the
subsistence economy of the encomiendas,
or slave holdings, and with slave women
for their harems. It also provided them
with children of mixed blood, the criollos.
who were later to outdo their parents in
exploiting their half-brothers, who had not
had the "privilege" of being the children
of Europeans.
In the early years of the 17th century,
the vast amorphous Giant Province began
to shrink and break up, losing access to
the sea in the process. Now land-locked,
it turned into a poor province which the
metropolitan administration abandoned to
its fate.
Meanwhile, the Jesuits had begun an
incredible experiment which combined
proselytizing with the exploitation of the
indigenous population. They founded the
Indian communities called Reducciones
which, under the name of the Guarani
Republic, came to form an empire within
the Spanish empire, with which it eventu¬
ally clashed. Based on a system that made i
full use of the division of labour, the enter- I
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
( prise yielded profits beyond the wildest
expectations of its founders.
The province also witnessed the first
mass insurrection against Spanish abso¬
lutism. This was the so-called revolt of the
communeros which lasted from 1717 to
1735, and in some ways resembled the
Revolt of the Communeros, or Common¬
ers, of Castile against the usurpation of
the Emperor Charles V in the 16th century.
Thirty years after these events, in 1767,
the Jesuits were expelled by Charles III
from all the territories of the Spanish
empire. The king saw the empire built by
the Jesuits not only as a virtually impreg¬
nable stronghold against his authority
but also as a dangerous example to his
corrupt and tyrannical colonial admini¬
stration.
For the Jesuit system Of temporal and
spiritual organization was more humane
than that of the encomiendas, as well as
being the first of its kind in America to
preserve the language and culture of the
indigenous population and their traditional
modes of production.
It is not surprising, then, that certain
chroniclers spoke of the "communist"
regime set up in the Reducciones: a kind
of communist republic-empire. Such
semantic confusion could not, however,
conceal the true nature of an experiment
which preceded the formation of an inde¬
pendent sovereign state in Paraguay by
over a century.
The independent state of Paraguay
began its existence under the dictatorship
of José Gaspar Rodriguez Francia (1816-
1840) and flourished under Carlos Antonio
López and his son Francisco Solano López.
But in 1865 Argentina and the Brazilian
Empire entered into a secret agreement.
Drawing Uruguay along with them, they
declared war on Paraguay with the blessing
of the British.
The war of the "Triple Alliance", which
lasted five years, was a bloodbath. The
male population was all but decimated,
and the countryside plundered. It marked
the end of the independent state, laid the
country open to extortion and led to
many years of dependence on the victo¬
rious countries.
The martyrdom of this freedom-loving
people constitutes a break in the continuity
of Paraguay's history: from one of Latin
America's most advanced nations, the
country was turned into one of its poorest
and most backward.
Paraguayan culture must be seen against
this background of historical events and
geographical isolation which provides clues
to its enigmatic fate as a nation.
But one cannot hope to understand
Paraguay without taking into account its
linguistic problem. For 400 years now,
two languages have coexisted in the
country: Spanish and Guarani the lan¬
guage of the conquerors and the language
of the conquered. These two languages
are used as parallel, though not comple¬
mentary, means of expression for a whole
society.
In this, Paraguay is unique in Latin
America. For a long time it was common¬
place to say that Paraguay was a bilingual
country and that this bilingualism was an
obstacle to its cultural development or, as
others would have it, a handicap to its
material progress.
According to the leading authority on
the subject, Father Bartomeu Meliá, "The
description of the Paraguayan linguistic
situation as 'typically' bilingual is very
widespread and is accepted even by some
linguists. But Paraguayan bilingualism is a
myth.
"Since the time of the conquest and the
formation of the colony, Paraguay has al¬
ways constituted a unique case of bilin¬
gualism. Two languages and two cultures
have existed side by side in apparent har¬
mony, each influencing and complement¬
ing the other. To this extent Paraguay
seems to represent the triumph of the
colonial ¡deal: antagonism between master
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
A living
tradition
at the loom
Handed down from generation to
generation, the art of weaving has always
been one of the most important
occupations of the Indian women of
Paraguay. Centre photo: two villagers
weaving ponchos with "typically Indian"
designs. Village weavers today
manufacture more of these ponchos,
much sought-after by tourists, than other
traditional garments such as embroidered
shirts. Left, Paraguayan men construct a -
"weft" of palings around their farm.
and slave has been overcome. Further¬
more, as Governor Lázaro de Ribera com¬
plained at the end of the 18th century, 'We
have reached such a point that the langua¬
ge of the conquered peoples has become
the dominant one.' "
But for the child with a European father
and an Indian mother, the natural mother
tongue was Guarani, and Spanish was a
language imposed as a symbol of author¬
ity. It was the language which the mestizo
would in turn use to impose his own au¬
thority on the Indians.
Under the harsh conditions of the enco¬
miendas, which were nevertheless more
liberal in Paraguay than in other parts of
conquered Latin America, mestizos and
Indians felt that the language of their
father or master, as the case happened to
be, was a more integral part of his domi¬
nance than the arms, tools, food, houses
and customs which were the trappings of
his power.
In the missionary settlements of the
Jesuits, however, sermons and prayers
were in Guarani. There, the Indian was
not forced to change his language. He did,
however, have to change his rituals, his
liturgy, his gods, and his conception
of nature, of the world and of the
universe although the embers of all these
still glow brightly today in. Indian myths
about the universe.
CONTINUED PAGE 69
Birthplace of a nation
Below, the Casa de la Independencia (Independence House) in Asunción,
capital of Paraguay, where a group of patriots gathered on the night of 14
May 1811 before deposing the Spanish governor, Bernardo de Velazco, in
a bloodless coup d'état. A month later, the independence of the
Paraguayan Republic was proclaimed. Of all the capitals of Latin-
American countries with a large Indian population, Asunción is the only
one in which bilingualism (Spanish-Guarani) is widespread, although here
and in the country's other major cities Guarani is increasingly losing
ground to Spanish.
Photo © Jesús Ruiz Nestosa. Paraauav
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
DEBUNKING
THE < BLACK LEGEND'
A hard look at the historical role
of Spain in Latin America
by Roberto
Fernandez Retamar
ROBERTO FERNANDEZ RETAMAR, Cuban poet
and essayist, is a professor at Havana university and
director of the magazine Casa de las Americas. His
essays and anthologies of his poems have been trans¬
lated into a number of languages.
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
IN recent years, the debate about Latin
American culture has become increas¬
ingly lively. Emphasis has been put
on the indigenous Amerindian and Afric¬
an heritage, while the differences or, as
some would have it, the affinitieswhich
characterize Latin America's relationship
with the West have been pointed up.
But there is another heritage, which one
might call "intermediate", neither indige¬
nous nor strictly speaking Western: the
Iberian heritage.
It is obvious that much of Latin American
culture comes from Spain. But although
this Spanish influence should not be exag¬
gerated, it should neither be minimized
nor dismissed.
Latin Americans received much more
than their language from Spain, but lan¬
guage indicates the special way in which
the Iberian heritage was transmitted.
Referring to the unity of the Spanish
language, the Spanish historian Ramón
Menéndez Pidal said, "One can say that
there are two types of educated Spanish,
just as there are American and British
versions of English, primarily distinguished
by peculiarities of pronunciation."
This obvious phonetic difference can be
considered a sign of richness, and fortu¬
nately it has not endangered the unity of
our language, since "the peoples who
emerged from the former Spanish Empire
communicate much more with one another
today than when they belonged to a single
state". The unity of the Spanish language
has thus been preserved, enriched by the
contributions of the various regions in
which it is spoken.
In other respects, the situation is much
more complex. We Spanish Americans
like to say that we descend not from those
who stayed behind in Spain but from those
who came to America and whose children
stopped being Spanish, becoming first
creóles, and later, intermingling with other
ethnic groups, Latin Americans.
Spanish America began breaking its ties
with the battered and decadent Spanish
Empire more than 150 years ago; and Spain
was to lose its last American possession,
Cuba, in 1898. Spanish America, mean¬
while, was trying to define its own identity
by making a sharp distinction between the
old and the new continent. It was a com¬
plex task to determine what differentiated
it from the mother country, but it proved
even more difficult to propose distinctively
Latin American solutions. As a result, many
were lured into the arms of other greedy
powers: as if, as the Cuban writer José
Marti (1853-1895) exclaimed, changing
masters amounted to being free.
A readiness to accept "Western" solu¬
tions was typical of certain Spanish-Amer¬
ican groups who were avid supporters of
CONTINUED PAGE 58
A particularly rich form of art and architecture developed in Latin America during the late
17th century and the 18th century (see following double page) with the intermingling of
Iberian and indigenous cultures. Left, an example of this "colonial style" art: a late 18th-
century rococo portrait of a Viceroy of New Spain (Mexico). Equally striking is the church*
at Ouro Preto (below) in the Province of Minas Gerais (Brazil) where the churches are
notable for their flamboyant motifs of garlands and scrolls and eloquent sculpture.
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
Extravaganza of baroque
Photo © Companhia Malhoramentos de S3o Paulo
Latin American art and architecture is marked
by a strong penchant for the baroque. As the
Cuban writer Alejo Carpentier has noted:
"Our art has always been baroque: from the
splendid pre-Columbian sculptures to the
drawings in Maya and Aztec manuscripts,
from the colonial cathedrals and monasteries
to the best of today's novels". The baroque
style is particularly evident in what is known
as "colonial art", which is strongly marked by
Spanish and Portuguese influence but has a .
lushness and liveliness that are specifically
Latin American. On this double page, we
present examples of the richness of this art.
(1) A prophet by the great 18th-century
Brazilian architect-sculptor O Aleijadhinho on
the terrace of the church of Buen Jesús de
Matosinhos at Congonhas do Campo (Brazil);
(2) the episcopal palace at Lima (Peru), one of
the gems of colonial architecture; (3) detail
inside a church at Bahia (Brazil); such
exuberant ornamentation is a characteristic
feature of many Latin American buildings;
(4) 17th-century portrait of an Inca princess
holding sacred floyvers; (5) vaulting in the
church of Santiago de Pomata (Peru), in
which the Indian artist depicted Andalusian
forms and motifs, themselves strongly
influenced by the Arab art of Spain.
56
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
INCA ARABESQUES. The dome of the church of Santiago de Pomata is
one of the most remarkable examples of the mestizo style of architectural-
decoration in the Andes. Between each ornamental "spoke" of the radial
design, which follows Andalusian tradition, whorls and arabesques form
Indian motifs (detail below).
; modernization. It was encouraged by the
pitiful state into which Spain had fallen and
its iniquitous exploitation of the new
nations. But it was also encouraged by the
fact that, since the 16th century, Spain and
all things Spanish had come under the
stigma of the "Black Legend", which made
the word "Spanish" synonymous with
purblind reactionary cruelty. Many Spanish
Americans rejected their Hispanic heritage
as a result.
The Black Legend was apparently the
product of an understandable revulsion
against the monstrous crimes committed
in the Americas by the Spanish conquis¬
tadors. But even a minimal respect for
historical truth shows that this is simply
false. Of course there were crimes, and
monstrous crimes at that. But when
compared with others committed in follow¬
ing centuries, they were no more mon¬
strous than those of the metropolitan
powers that followed the Spanish imperial
example, sowing death and destruction
throughout the world.
PLUMED PROFILE. Head topped
with a crest of feathers is carved on
the door of the church of
Paucarpata, near Arequipa (Peru).
This product of Spanish colonial art
recalls the forms on certain pieces
of pre-Columbian pottery.
58
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
The conquests carried out by the other
Western powers were not lacking in mur¬
ders and acts of destruction. What they
did lack, however, were scrupulous men
like Bartolomé de Las Casas, who cham¬
pioned Indian rights (see Unesco Courier,
June 1975), and such debates about the
legitimacy of the conquest as the one
launched by the Dominicans, which shook
the Spanish Empire.
This does not mean that dissenters, who
represented a small minority, managed to
make their views prevail; but they did
manage to defend them before the highest
authorities. They were heard and their
ideas were to some extent acted on.
According to the Chilean scholar Ale¬
jandro Lipschutz, "the Black Legend is
worse than simplistic: it is malicious pro¬
paganda. It is simplistic because all im¬
perialist conquests have taken an equally
traumatic form and continue to do so".
Laurette Séjourné, the Mexican archeo-
logist, admits that "It is now clear that
systematic condemnation of the Spaniards
has played a pernicious role in this vast
drama, because it takes the occupation of
Latin America out of its world context.
Colonialism is the mortal sin of the whole
of Europe... No other nation would have
behaved better... On the contrary, Spain
boasts one important distinction here: it is
the only country to date in which powerful
voices were raised against the act of im¬
perial conquest". -
The Black Legend was concocted with
one aim in view: to discredit Spain, the
leading European power in the 16th cen¬
tury. Other powers of the time were con¬
spiring to usurp its place, and eventually
they succeeded. Thus it was the bour¬
geoisie of the other colonial powers which
invented the Black Legend.
The Legend was a skilful ideological
weapon in the inter-colonial power struggle
which accompanied the rise of capitalism
and was to last several centuries (although
by the end of the 17th century the outcome
was virtually decided in favour of the new
colonial powers).
In any case, it is important to remember
that there were not one but two cultures in
Spain, as in any other country: a ruling-
class culture and a popular one; a culture of
the oppressors and of the oppressed. The
latter culture was the living and authentic
one, and it is this which we Spanish Amer¬
icans stand for.
Few countries, moreover, were so fully
conscious of this duality ás Spain. The
idea of an external duality (Europe/Spain)
was to become a constant theme of Span¬
ish thought and literature from the onset
of the country's decline. It ño doubt
sprang from the fact that Spain was first
in the forefront of capitalist development
and European expansion, and that it was to
be outdistanced and finally left behind by
the capitalist movement it had contributed
to.
The Spanish writer Mariona José de
Larra's famous epitaph is revealing. In
his All Souls' Day 1836 he noted: "Here
lies half of Spain, it was killed by the other
half".
It is no wonder then that the anti-
Spanish Black Legend reflects one of the
various and intolerable forms of racism.
One need only recall the classic remark
that "Africa begins at the Pyrenees",
which expresses the West's distaste for
everything different from itself, a difference
epitomized in this case by Africa. Here
again traditionalist Spain went hopelessly
wrong in being offended by this assess¬
ment.
There is a ridiculous notion that because
"Eternal Spain" was occupied for centuries
by Arab infidels whom it finally succeeded
in expelling, it consequently preserved
Catholic purity and eliminated the "Islam¬
ic barbarian threat" from Europe. This
can be countered by pointing to a far fnore
potent truth: Spanish Christians, Arabs
and Jews lived together in Spain for
centuries and influenced one another
fruitfully.
But Spain was not only to be a link
between Christianity and Islam. It also
served as a bridge between Europe and
the vast Islamic world, where Greek, Indian
and Persian influences had been assimilat¬
ed by the Arabs.
It is thus correct to state that not only
Africa but Asia as well begins at the Pyr¬
enees; among other factors, this helped
to resuscitate the languishing culture of
Europe.
Alejo Carpentier is fond of reflecting on
the sad fate of the Caribe Indians, a proud
and combative people who came from the
Orinoco Basin to the shores of the sea to
which they gave their name. Their battle
cry was "Only the Caribes are men", but
when they came into contact with the
proud and warlike Spaniards in their expan¬
sion across the seas, they met a people
with a similar battle cry.
But the sails, swords and crosses of
Spain were as puny as the Caribes' canoes,
arrowheads and war cries, and they went
down before the inexorable development
of capitalism. Spain and her history were
cast aside, with all the philosophical,
artistic, scientific, legal and technical
contributions she had made. Even Spain's
introduction of the Europeans into the
Americas was forgotten, together with the
gold and silver she had brought from the
New World, wealth which ended in the
greedy hands of German and Genoese
bankers who sarcastically referred to the
proud nobles of Spain as "our Indians".
"Despite all this", the French historian
Pierre Vilar says, "Velazquez's Spain was
still prestigious. It inspired the classical
French 17th century." Centuries were to
pass before the new European powers
would pardon Spain for this superiority.
The Black Legend was to be the form their
"pardon" took.
There is no need to insist on the close¬
ness we Spanish Americans feel to that
other, democratic Spain, the Spain of Las
Casas and the great Dominicans of the
16th century who defended the Amerin¬
dians: the Spain of thinkers like Vives and
the 16th-century Erasmians like Servet,
Suárez, Feijoo, Jovellanos and Blanco
White even if some of them had to do
their work in exile. The Spain of those
writers who began producing after most of
Latin America had achieved independence:
Larra, Pi y Margall, Costa Iglesias, Cajal
and, above all, Antonio Machado. The
Spain whose people gave birth to an off¬
spring of American rebels.
This Spain opens our eyes to a complex
and fascinating constellation of great men
and works: Hispa no-Arabic art, El Cid and
the picaresque novel, Garcilaso, St. Teresa,
Cervantes, St. John of the Cross, Gongo-
ra, Quevado, Calderón, El Greco, Velaz¬
quez, Goya, Unamuno, Valle-lnclán,
Machado, Picasso, De Falla, Lorca, Bunuel.
So what on earth is the point of the
defenders of the Black Legend telling us
that the horrors of Spanish reaction should
make us forget this other inheritance?
What point is there in rejecting a cultural
tradition because of the momentary aberra¬
tions of certain groups in that country?
Does colonialism stop us admiring Shake¬
speare or Virginia Woolf or Bernard Shaw?
Rabelais or Malraux? Pushkin, Tolstoy or
Dostoyevski? Goethe or Brecht? Dante or
Pavese?
The truth is that we feel proud that this
other Spain is also ours, and that we would
be impoverished if we rejected it.
Roberto Fernández Retamar
MYSTERIOUS STATUE carved on the
facade of the Casa de las Recogidas
(House of the Repentant) at Potosí in
Bolivia bears a surprising resemblance to
the high-relief sculptures in such Hindu
temples as those at Elephanta Island and
Konarak (India). It is not known how this
"exotic" figure came to adorn a baroque
building in the Andean highlands.
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
by César
Fernandez Moreno
THE TANGO
TANGLE
WHEN we Argentinians set out in
search of our identity, we usu¬
ally encounter a void.
The landscape of the pampa is not a
landscape at all; in the words of the Span¬
ish essayist Ortega y Gasset, it is no more
than a promise of one. In the northwest
there are a few lingering remnants of the
Inca culture and in the northeast something
of Guarani culture. But only "frontier"
forms of these cultures have survived.
Patagonia is an immense region, virtually
uninhabited, nothing but a road.
For the people of Buenos Aires, known
as Porteños to mark the capital's role as a
great seaport, the problem is even more
serious. Buenos Aires is such a cosmopo¬
litan city that it is almost impossible to
define its identity.
So we must start with the assumption
that the typical Porteño has no cultural
identity of his own or, put in another way,
his cultural identity lies in not having one.
This is a fair criticism, and one which
Argentinians from outside the capital
would level against the Porteños a criti¬
cism which is serious as well as just since
more than one-third of Argentina's popu¬
lation lives in the Buenos Aires conurbation.
Most Porteños are second- or third-gen¬
eration immigrants. They often tease each
other about the nationality of their fore¬
bears. The Gallego (the nickname given
the Spaniard) makes fun of the Ruso (the
Jew); the Ruso mocks the Tano (the
Italian) and the Tano derides the Gallego.
In short, everyone makes fun of everyone
else. Yet beneath it all runs a deep feeling
of brotherhood.
At what level of society is the typical
Porteño to be found? Certainly not among
CESAR FERNANDEZ MORENO, Argentinian essay¬
ist and poet, is director of Unesco's Regional Office
for Culture in Latin America and the Caribbean and
head of the Unesco programme of cultural studies on
Latin America. Among his published works on culture
are La Realidad y los Papeles ("Books and Reality",
1967) and Argentina (1972). He has founded and
directed various literary magazines and has written for
and about radio, television and the cinema in Latin
America. His principal work of poetry is Argentina
hasta la Muerte ¡"Argentina to the Death", 1963).
the landowners, for they have been "deper¬
sonalized" by their rural and nationalist
commitments; they resemble equivalent
élites in other countries. Not among the
executives, filled with admiration for "the
American way of life". Not among the
intellectuals, who are for the most part set
on behaving like Europeans. Nor among
the working class, whose life is suburban
rather than urban.
The typical Porteño is found primarily
in the heart of Buenos Aires, in a social
class consisting mainly of shopkeepers,
small manufacturers and office workers.
It is here that one finds all the traits
of the Porteño: a comfortable, reasonably
hedonistic life, a certain awareness of this
hedonism, an irreverent and flaccid political
involvement. As many of these character¬
istics are also found in the neighbouring
city of Montevideo, a friendly rivalry has
grown up between the Porteños and their
Uruguayan brothers.
A brief list of Porteño characteristics
would include:
A love of café life (no doubt imported
from Spain) and its activities: dice and
billiards. Café life tends to be identified
with friendship.
' A fondness for cabarets (a term obviously
taken from the French) and a dash of
machismo, accompanied by respect for
one's wife, the patrona.
' A taste for asado (beef grilled over a
slow fire) which these city people have
borrowed from the gauchos.
A healthy appetite, which is usually
considered a virtue in well-fed commu¬
nities. The Porteño has enriched his
traditional meat diet with Italian pastas
and pizzas (bound up with the mamma,
the mother figure).
A liking for mate, the Latin American
equivalent of tea. Originally a Paraguayan
brew, it is now the national drink of
Uruguay and Argentina as well. As the
French writer Raymond Queneau ironic¬
ally noted: "Drink mate and you turn into
an Argentinian."
1 A use of language swinging between
lunfardo, an Ítalo-Porteño dialect that
originally developed in the Buenos Aires
underworld, and the vernacular. Other
60
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
An Argentinian writer unravels
the mystery surrounding Buenos Aires'
favourite song and dance
The tango, according to the
Argentinian writer Ernesto Sàbato,
"is perhaps the most original
creation of the Rio de la Plata."
As such, it has inspired numerous
artists, three of whose drawings are
shown here.
Porteño linguistic peculiarities include the
use of reversed syllables "tango", for
example becomes "gotan"and of
borrowings from other immigrant dia¬
lects.
Last but not least, an inordinate love of
the tango, which the Porteño considers as
the purest form of music and philosophy.
But here we come up against a problem:
is the tango really Argentinian?
The origin of the tango is a hotly dis¬
puted point in the Rio de la Plata region:
did it begin in Argentina or Uruguay? To
solve this problem it is necessary to go
back to the musical folklore of Andalusia,
since the striking similarity between the
words "fandango" and "tango" is matched
by the closeness of their musical relation¬
ship. But let us move a little further south,
to Africa.
For if is very likely that the tango origi¬
nated in Africa and then developed in
Spain. Its original version was probably
brought to America by black slaves and
Andalusian settlers, whose music had
already been influenced by African rhythms.
The Cuban musicologist Argeliers León
has pointed out that the first blacks reached
America in the ships of Christopher Colum¬
bus, which, of course, sailed from Spain.
Once in America, they kept up their own
festivals, which, however, slowly blended
with those imposed on them by the Catho¬
lic Church. "In Uruguay," he notes, "these
processional celebrations bring together
such dance and musical forms as the
calenda, the tango, the candomblé, the
chicha, the bambula and the samba."
Latin-American Africanists and anthro¬
pologists have paid particular attention to
the origin of the word tango. Some say it
derives from the Congolese word iango (a
type of dance); others maintain that it is an
onomatopoeic rendering of the sound of a
drum-beat. The French specialist on Latin
America, Roger Bastide, believes that
tango comes from the Bantu word tamgu,
which means "to dance". For the Argen¬
tinian specialist on Africa, Ortiz Oderigo,
"the expression tango is purely and simply
a corruption of the name 'Shango', the god
of storms and thunder in the mythology of
the Yorubas of Nigeria.
So much for philology. Ortiz Oderigo
does not put forward an opinion about the
relationship between the earliest negro
tangos and the later Rio de la Plata ver¬
sions. He does, however, present a list of
antecedents which, starting in the 15th
century, indicate a direct continuity with
popular Latin American and even with
Andalusian music. And he states cate¬
gorically that the Andalusian tango "results
from a blend of Afro-Spanish music".
During the colonial period, the Spanish
Viceroy Vertiz allowed popular dances to
be held in the Ranchería theatre in Buenos
Aires. The favourite dance was the fan¬
dango, which already foreshadowed some
of the steps of the tango. This custom of
popular dancing reached the height of its
popularity in the mid-19th century, during
the dictatorship of Juan Manuel de Rosas.
It was to disappear a little later in the gen¬
eral vogue for Europeanization.
Around the turn of the century, as the
cities expanded and the less-favoured
classes became better-off, the tango again
emerged as the "typical" music of the Rio
de la Plata cities.
In 1870, the blacks of Buenos Aires
organized themselves into "nations",
according to their countries of origin, and
groups of carnival masqueraders appeared
in Montevideo. In Uruguay, the tango
appeared in a particularly authentic form,
since Montevideo had a bigger black popu¬
lation than Argentina, whose blacks had
begun to emigrate to the mines in the north.
The Porteño tango was born sometime
around 1880 in suburban bars, in bordellos
and among "women of ill repute". Some
specialists even claim to know the actual
place: the Corrales Viejos slaughterhouse.
The tango was also enriched by improvised
poems sung by the muleteers and gaucho
minstrels of the pampas.
Two currents, then, flowed together to
create the tango: a musical current of
negro-Andalusian origin and a literary one
of gaucho origin. The gaucho's mastery of
the guitar was passed on to city-dwelling
composers, and his gift for improvising
verse was taken up by poets writing ink
dialect. As any budding Argentinian poet f
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
can testify, these two great poetic achieve¬
ments gaucho lyrical poetry and the tan-
!go are not easy to live up to.
About the same time as the first tangos
with lyrics appeared, the first sencillismo
!( easy-to-read) and vanguardismo (avant-
garde) texts were published. They pointed
the way to all later developments in Argen¬
tinian poetry. Thus the incorporation of
verse into the music of the tango created a
common denominator between it and the
great literature of Argentina.
Argentinian literature and the tango
share another common feature: nostalgia.
The tangos express a longing for the
adventurous life of the gaucho or the
criminal, of the man whose luck has run
out or whose woman has deserted him.
In the same vein, serious Argentinian
poetry of the early 20th cefitury sprang
from the nostalgia of the uprooted immi¬
grant. The urban poetry of Jorge Luis
Borges in the next generation also express¬
ed nostalgia for the Buenos Aires under¬
world.
Such is the story of the tango's social
climb, if the conquest of the privileged
classes can be considered a climb. From
the slaves it passed to the poor, from them
to the middle class and the aristocracy.
Between the two World Wars, the tango
made its way to Europe, reaching the height
of sgccess with the triumph of its greatest
exponent, the singer Carlos Gardel.
Through personal appearances and films,
Gardel brought the tango to a wider
audience, first in France and the United
States and then throughout Latin America.
With Gardel, the tango reached its widest
public but not its highest musical develop¬
ment, which had already been achieved
before Gardel's "tango-song".
With his great gifts as a singer and his
personal charisma, Gardel projected the
¡mage of the masterful Argentinian male.
At that time, anything from Argentina was
assured of success. The country exported
commodities of all kinds: from its grain and
meat to its football and its tango. But to be
perfectly honest, one must admit that this
national Argentinian idol was... French. He
was born in Toulouse in 1890 and arrived in
Argentina at the age of three.
Although they may not know much
about him, Europeans identify the gaucho
with the tango, and in the 1920s and 1930s,
the European public considered that no
tango could be genuine unless danced and
sung by people dressed up like gauchos.
In fact they were not far wrong, consider¬
ing the gaucho's contribution to the tango.
When performed in films or plays today,
the tango generally brings a slightly ironic
smile to people's lips. Nevertheless, its
rhythms can still be heard in many a French
hit song, and in Japan it is so popular that
bands reproduce with oriental precision the
rhythms that have reached them from
Buenos Aires.
The tango has also been used to express
more deep-seated emotional tensions, as
in the play Tango by the Pole Slavomir
Mrozeck and in the film Last Tango in Paris
by the Italian director Bernardo Bertolucci.
In Argentina today, the tango is paradox
ically on its way in. ..and out. On the one
hand, it is looked on as a relic from the
past, since only the older generation still .
remembers how to dance it; the younger
generation has replaced Carlos Gardel with
more vociferous idols. On the other hand,
an "avant-garde tango" is making its mark,
backed by the composer Astor Piazzolo
and by the intellectuals.
The tango has been aptly defined by the
film director Simon Feldman as "the
sound of the life of Buenos Aires, a dis¬
tillation of the city". But there are times
when the city seems indifferent, if not
hostile or repressive, towards its own
sound. When Feldman finished his full-
length documentary on the tango in 1970,
he had great difficulty in getting it shown in
Buenos Aires, . whereas in Europe and
North America it was snapped up by
television.
A final pessimistic note: the great expo¬
nents of the tango have been short-lived.
There is even a tradition that tango singers
die in accidents, beginning with the great
Carlos Gardel, who was burnt to death in
a plane crash in 1935.
But sometimes the dead survive in myths
which make them larger than life. People
still say, metaphorically, of Gardel, 42 years
after his death: "Carlos is singing better
every day". There are even fans who
believe, or who wish to believe, that he is
still, alive somewhere in Latin America. In
some Latin American countries the anni¬
versary of his death is commemorated each
year.
In one way or another, the tango still
asserts its vitality in Argentina and else¬
where in the world. It is one of the most
universal products that the Porteños, and
Argentina itself, could present when wish¬
ing to affirm their cultural identity.
César Fernandez Moreno
SPANISH
OVERSEAS
Born 1,000 years ago,
the Spanish language
is today spoken by
200 million Latin
Americans
by Marcos A. Morinigo
MARCOS A. MORINIGO, Argentinian philologist,
is director of the Institute of Philology at the university
of Buenos Aires. He has taught at several universities
in North and South America and has published many
studies on Spanish literature and philology.
62
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
WHEN Castile recently celebrated
its 1,000th anniversary, no one
thought to have a special cere¬
mony for the 1,000th birthday of the Cas-
tilian language. This is most certainly an
oversight, for over the centuries it has
become a living bond between peoples and
continents.
The history of a language is closely linked
to that of the people who speak it. When
their fortunes run high, the language is
invested with vigour and prestige, but when
times are less fortunate, it begins to atrophy.
The first appearance of Castilian as a
written language dates back to- the 10th
century A.D., in the form of a scribe's gloss
on a manuscript written in low Latin. Even
at this date, Castilian possessed certain
forms of its own, which distinguished it
from neighbouring dialects. These inno¬
vations were to render the other dialects
archaic.
Castilian began to appear in literary form
to describe the exploits of great popular
heroes and to narrate local events. Else¬
where in Spain, Latin continued to be used
for these purposes, although the scribes no
longer had a sufficient grasp of the lan¬
guage and sprinkled their manuscripts with
the vernacular, with which they were more
familiar.
The oldest Castilian literature probably
consists of short poems about famous
court figures. These were followed by more
ambitious works on similar themes.
The form of Castilian spoken In the
capital of Castile, Burgos, became Spain's
literary language, in which lyric and epic
poetry, novels, and historical, religious and
scholarly works would be written. Writers
from parts of Spain speaking other dialects
would opt for Castilian when seeking to
reach a national audience.
In 1492, the Reconquista, the conquest
of Moorish Spain by the Spaniards, came to
an end with the fall of the Muslim Kingdom
of Granada. In the same year, Christopher
Columbus brought a "new world" to the
kings of Castile and Leon, an unhoped-for
gift which fate had laid in their hands.
The Spanish monarchs were eager to find
out the exact size of their vast new posses¬
sions, and were hungry for information
about the people, the natural life and pro¬
ducts of the New World. Countless expe¬
ditions set sail from the ports of Castile to
the Americas.
Mariners set out In search of gold and
spices. At one point Columbus and his
crew thought they had reached the coasts
of the fabulous Golden Peninsula orCipango
(Japan). The Spanish adventurer Lucas
Vasquez de Ayllon made landfall on the '
snow-bound coasts of Virginia, to the vast
disappointment of the gold-hunters. For,
according to a widespread belief which
Columbus shared, gold was the son of the
sun and only to be found in hot countries.
It was gold that determined the direction
of Columbus's voyages and took him to the
coasts of Venezuela and Colombia, to
Panama. Nicaragua and the Caribbean.
The lure of gold also drew the conquis¬
tadors Grijalva, Cortés and Panfilo de
Narvaez to the coasts of Mexico, Spaniards
and Portuguese to Brazil, Soils to the Rio
del Plata, and Pizarro to Peru.
The Spanish kings set themselves the
goal of snatching the souls of the infidels
from the jaws of Hell and converting them
to Christianity.
The Spanish- humanists, for their part,
saw the whole of America as .a vast region
where Spanish would be spoken.
Following in the footsteps of the Spanish
grammarian Debrija (1444-1522), the human¬
ists identified the glory of the Spanish
language with their nation's imperial des¬
tiny and were ready to see parallels between
Spanish and the Latin which had been prop¬
agated by the armies of the Roman empire.
"If Spain rules and has contacts with other
parts of the world, the old and the new, the
Spanish language must be taught in the
same way as Latin".
Within 20 years, the Indians of the Antilles
were speaking Spanish with Bartolomé de
n *y- J 7?
J^uJeaot-sa^fOfU^.^tArnoénáí
l*J . V-» ".-J-' I
/w^-ittf-. Qu*4m-fu£tun*.'naUwfu-
<t>*lk-£<«"3!rn orflb«fVMntYl«nfb.
fita': awmcn 'men «nfaf^iñiVvJ-ui».
I lmpvAtf»«ffí,¿M*^it«lmuír-T
î>>»* 1 MVu*«in« rifa Inúyoo ¿oí ¿
.CrfOt
Above, the earliest known text in the Castilian
language, written 1,000 years ago in 977 A.D.
It consists of 43 words penned by an
anonymous monk of the monastery of San
Millán de la Cogolla, in Logroño, northern
Spain. Today Castilian is spoken by almost
300 million persons, mainly in Latin America
and Spain.
Las Casas. Soon after, in Mexico, the
Tlaxcaltecas began to learn Spanish, fol¬
lowed by the Aztec nobles and their sons.
Further south, the household of the Inca
studied Spanish, and when the navigator
Alvaro Nuñez reached the forests of Para¬
guay in 1541, it was in Spanish that the
Guaranis greeted him.
Indeed, by the middle of the 16th century,
Spanish was the only language spoken in
the streets of Potosi (Bolivia), as well in
Cajamarca and Cuzco (Peru) and in Quito
(Ecuador).
The conquistadors felt that it was not for
them to learn the languages of the conquer¬
ed territories, but that their vassals should
speak the language of their victors. In La
Araucana, his great epic about the struggle
of the^Araucanian Indians against the
Spanish invaders, the poet Alonso de Ercilla
(1533-1594) noted with astonishment that
three of the conquistadors, including "the
valiant Ibarra", had learned the Indians'
language.
The cities of the Rio de la Plata region,
such as Asunción, Corrientes and Concep¬
ción, where a high percentage of the popu¬
lation was Indian, were bilingual. But Santa
Fé and Buenos Aires, which were founded
by bilingual mestizos with a large following
of Indian servants, became completely
Spanish cities.
Spanish has always been intensively
taught in Latin America. In May 1770,
Charles III signed the Real Cédula, royal
letters ordering the colonial authorities to
do everything within their power to promote
the teaching of Spanish to the Indians. In
most cases the king's instructions were not
carried out, but the future governments of
independent Latin America were to carry
out his wishes, and the use of Spanish
spread rapidly in the 19th century.
Local languages did not, of course,
disappear and, with the exception of Uru¬
guay, they are still spoken from Mexico to
Patagonia, though less so today than in the
past.
Literacy campaigns and the development
of public schooling obviously promote the
teaching of the official language of the
country Spanish. Whether admitted or
not, such programmes push indigenous
tongues into the background, where they
fall into oblivion.
In a world where standardization is
progressing by leaps and bounds, a stan¬
dard language is an excellent way of spread¬
ing culture.
In Latin America today, local languages
are little more than archeological relics and
Spanish is the only substitute for them, not
only because it is spoken by 200 million
people; not only because for five centuries
their most eloquent spokesmen have used
it; nor because Latin America's greatest
works of literature have been written in it:
but because the Spanish language has
given those who can speak it the concepts
and forms of Western culture.
Marcos A. Morinigo
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
VICTORIA OCAMPO' S GIFT
On 15 January 1973, Mme Victoria
Ocampo and her sister Mme Angelica
Ocampo, of Argentina, donated to
Unesco a group of estates including
the spacious Villa Ocampo (right) at
San Isidro, Buenos Aires. In accor¬
dance with the wishes of its donor,
Victoria Ocampo, the villa will be used
"for promotion, research, experimen¬
tation and development of activities
related to culture, literature, art and
social communication, which are
aimed at improving the quality of
human life...." The villa is particularly
appropriate as a setting for "perma¬
nent studios or for programmes of
research, experimentation or produc¬
tion related to the cinema, television,
theatre, music and literature, for trans¬
lation or new forms of expression and
communication, as well as new types
and techniques of cultural and artistic
creation and art education."
by Jacques Rigaud
IT would be easy enough to see Victoria
Ocampo's life and work as the intel¬
lectual adventures of a rich heiress in
love with literature. But to do this would
not only be committing a grave injustice
towards a woman who has fought many
battles and taken many risks, it would also
ignore her remarkable achievement as a
pioneer in promoting the meeting of
cultures.
Victoria Ocampo was born at the end of
the last century, into a family whose his¬
tory is closely interwoven with that of
the Argentinian Republic itself. She en¬
joyed the happy childhood and cosmopoli¬
tan education of the privileged classes of
that time, and like many of her kind mignt
have been satisfied with the cushioned
and glossy existence of the rich. However,
her life was to take a different course.
JACQUES RIGAUD is Unesco's Assistant Director-
General for programme support and administration.
A precocious intellect, a generosity of
heart and mind which spurred her to ac¬
tion, indefatigable energy, insatiable curio¬
sity, courage begging to be put to the
test, an unrivalled gift for rallying her
friends and leading them into the frayall
these qualities destined Victoria Ocampo
to a life of creativity and commitment.
It all began in 1924 when she invited
Radindranath Tagore, who had prolonged
a stay in Argentina for health reasons, to
her family home at San Isidro, near
Buenos Aires. Through this encounter,
Victoria not only discovered the work of
the great Indian writer and the fascination
of Indian culture, she also discovered her
own vocation in life, which was to enter¬
tain, encourage, help and introduce to one
another writers, artists and creators of all
kinds. Ever since then Victoria Ocampo
has been fulfilling her mission at a pace
which seems to have made her forget to
grow old.
She works in the two houses with
which she has become identified; her stone
house at San Isidro and a spiritual dwell¬
ing of her own creation, the review Sur
("South").
In the first, she has been hostess to
some of the great names of this century:
José Ortega y Gasset, Igor Stravinsky,
Walter Gropius, Le Corbusier, Pierre Drieu
la Rochelle, Pablo Neruda, Jacques Mari-
tain, Ernest Ansermet, Albert Camus,
André Malraux, Saint-John Perse, Jules
Supervielle, Graham Greene, Roger
Caillois, Indira Gandhi, Alain Robbe-Grillet
and Michel Butor. There is no end to the
list of distinguished visitors whose pres¬
ence can still be felt in this opulent home
which has become a temple of culture.
As for Sur, which Victoria Ocampo has
headed since its creation in 1931, there is
probably no other review which can rival
it for boldness, discernment and eclecti¬
cism. During my visit to the Ocampo villa
in 1976 in the nostalgic mellowness of an
Argentinian autumn, the scent of dead
leaves mingling with that of late-blooming
flowers, Victoria proudly showed me the
complete collection of her review. I picked
up the first volume and, while leafing
through it, came across the signature of
Alejo Carpentier in the first issue. It took
considerable perspicacity to publish the
work of this prodigious novelist (see arti¬
cle page 8) 46 years ago.
When a complete analytical index and
anthology are made of Sur, it will be
obvious from the contributors (1), the sub¬
jects treated and the intellectual curiosity
and tolerance it has always shown that it
is an institution of international intellectual
cooperation.
A recent issue, which appeared at the
end of 1976, deals with translating, a vital
but neglected aspect of the inter-relation-
(1) They include Lorca, Joyce, Kazantzaki, Faulkner,
Sartre, Toynbee, Heidegger, Pirandello, Gabriela Mis¬
tral and Thomas Mann.
64
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
FOR WORLD CULTURE
Far left, Victoria Ocampo in 1947 with
Unesco's first Director-General, Julian
Huxley. Left, Mme Ocampo a few years
later with the French writer André
Malraux.
ship of cultures. The problems posed by
translating were treated in the rigorous,
challenging and imaginative fashion for
which Victoria Ocampo is famous.
Despite all this, Victoria Ocampo's life
has not been confined to running a house
and a literary review. She is a writer her¬
self, as well as a citizen whose commit¬
ment has on occasion landed her in prison.
For several years she was president of
Argentina's National Arts Fund. An inde¬
fatigable traveller, she always keeps her¬
self informed about the latest intellectual
developments.
She has far too strong a personality to
steer clear of controversy. People of her
calibre demand respect but they also tend
to provoke strong reactions. Yet it is
almost worth airing criticism of her simply
to see how easily it can be refuted.
Though she has sometimes been criti¬
cized for being too cosmopolitan and
though it is true that she has done a lot to
introduce art and literature from other
countries to Argentina, no one is more
deeply Argentinian than she.
As the French writer Etiemble, who is
by no means given to flattery, wrote in
1962: "She who for 30 years has spent the
better part of her fortune in order to print
and distribute the works of writers whom
she valued, whether they sold or not, and
whether they were Yankee, Argentinian
or European; she who for 30 years, and
contrary to all business sense, has been
giving the world the best Spanish-language
literary review how could anyone think
that she has not served her country?"
Her efforts to promote the international
reputation of Borges, Sàbato and many
other Argentinian writers are proof of her
deep-seated attachment to a land whose
cultural identity she has done so much to
uphold.
She has also been criticized for prefer¬
ring European culture. But Tagore, Nehru
and a number of Japanese writers have
acknowledged their indebtedness to her,
and Octavio Paz has said how much the
whole of Latin America owes her. The
ethnologist Alfred Métraux once remarked
that Victoria Ocampo "also considers her¬
self American in the geographical sense of
the term: she likes to discover themes and
elements which are common to the litera¬
ture of the New World and which set it
apart from that of Europe".
Can she be dismissed as a mere woman
of letters? No, for she has done much for
architects like Le Corbusier and musicians
like Ansermet and Stravinsky, and Sur has
shown continuing interest in the social
sciences.
And, lest one should be tempted to
think that it was easy for a member of the
upper classes like her to lead such a
brilliant life, the fact is that it was by no
means easy for Victoria Ocampo to pro¬
mote the emancipation of women in
Argentina during the 1930s not just in
words but in action, and later to risk not
only her personal fortune but also her
freedom because of her commitment. In
short, she paid for her privileges by con¬
tinually taking risks and by laying herself
open to misunderstanding and even insults.
Lastly, some might be tempted to say
that Victoria Ocampo's honours list is
now slightly out of date, and that the
world has moved on to other things. Even
here the would-be critic must accept that
Victoria Ocampo not only extended a
warm welcome to the nouveau roman,
but she also helped, and still helps, young
writers.
Always receptive to new ideas from
wherever they come, she is quite defin¬
itely not one of those who, like the French
19th-century politician and philosopher
Royer-Collard, admit sadly that "at my
age one no longer reads, one re-reads."
Victoria has always been enthusiastic
about new talent and ideas and quick to
tire of anything that smacks of the estab¬
lishment. Like Borges, Sàbato and Cor¬
tázar, she is consumed by a desire to
penetrate beneath the surface of things,
a refusal to be taken in by shadow-play.
To be questioned by her is a far from
restful process: she challenges, defies and
harries her interlocutor until she has dis¬
covered the truth and then, as Octavio
Paz has written, she can be seen "with
outstretched hand, ready to grasp another
hand".
Victoria Ocampo's ties with Unesco date Y
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
, back a long way. It would have been
surprising indeed if a pioneer in interna¬
tional intellectual cooperation such as she
had not shown interest in an institution
whose purpose is to provide a permanent
basis for just such cooperation. When
Julian Huxley visited Buenos Aires, and
talked to Victoria Ocampo about Unesco,
his words must have made a deep impres¬
sion, for years later she bequeathed her
two houses at San Isidro and Mar del
Plata to the Organization so that her work
there may be continued.
To this end, Unesco is making plans for
the future in close collaboration with the
donor. As Victoria Ocampo's life has
clearly shown, progress in the field of cul¬
ture often depends on the personal initia¬
tive of a smail number of people, on the
visionary daring of a few possessors of
creative talent, and also on the actions of
people like herself who have a gift for
. making things happen, creating needs,
forging connexions and inducing the tal¬
ented to exceed their own limits.
Nonetheless, once bold initiatives of
this sort have been taken, it is up to the
community to take over from the indivi¬
dual and guarantee continuity without
destroying any of the initial vitality.
The noble concept of the meeting of
cultures, which forms the cornerstone of
Unesco's mission, is perfectly embodied in
the person of Victoria Ocampo. By carry¬
ing on her work and lauding her example
which can be transposed to any
time or place Unesco will remember the
most precious element of a personal, and
to that extent ephemeral, life's adventure,
namely the fervour praised by the poet
Saint-John Perse:
"There are 'real' people who by their
very nature make us believe in them.
Victoria Ocampo can be said to have con¬
ducted her life's work like a great tree of
her native land; or better yetsince trees
are bound by their roots like the impe¬
rious Rio de la Plata which dominated her
childhood, adolescence and years of
mature womanhood, and whose pulsing
rhythm still resounds through her being.
This river is as true to its mighty course
as to its wedding with the sea and to its
distant alliance with far-out ocean currents
that sweep it towards other shores.
"Dear Victoria, great force of strength
and candour, inalienable and possessive
just* like your own Rio de la Plata, there
are many of us in Europe, America and
Asia who consider you one of the finest
exponents of the Argentinian spirit, which
expresses itself so proudly in you, a com¬
plex soul of many facets, both prodigal
and fatalist, passionate in its enthusiasms
yet regardless of the consequences in
moments of action and indifferent to
continuity."
This fine tribute calls, however, for one
comment: "indifferent to continuity"
should now read as "determined to con¬
tinue"a task Unesco has taken upon
itself.
Jacques Rigaud
AVANT-GARDE ART FROM THE TROPICS
(continued from page 34)
form. Participants literally have to force
their way through the object, and the
conventional act of contemplating a work
of art is thus transformed into an ines¬
capable living experience.
Carlos Cruz Diez expresses himself in a
different way but his aims and his concep¬
tion of art are the same. He sets out to
make colour "speak" with all its creative
power. The main virtue of light is its
protean ability to keep on changing. This
is what the Impressionists tried to capture
when they painted series of pictures of
the same subject, but they only managed
to achieve their aim in a representational
and allusive manner.
Cruz Diez sets out to portray the contin¬
uous transformations occuring in light
and its independent creative power. In his
paintings, he attempts to achieve an
"open-ended" situation that is constantly
evolving. He believes that, in traditional
painting, time is constricted and space is
falsified or simulated. His aim is to replace
"the representation of space by real
space." He believes that a work of art is
a reality in itself "autonomous reality".
Cruz Diez has embarked on this voyage
of discovery and conquest through his
"Physiochromes" and "Chromosaturations"
and induced colour effects. One has only
to approach some of his colours for them
to start vibrating and moving. Not only
is it impossible to see them twice in the
same way, but the painting itself starts to
produce new colours which the artist did
not paint but which the existing colours
induce on the retina. In this way, the
painting embodies a time element, as well
as creating its own space dimension in
which the spectator plays an active role.
Although Cruz Diez's experimentation
follows quite different and original lines,
his aims coincide with those of Soto. They
are both intent on banishing simulated
space and time in art and on creating
autonomous space and time in which the
spectator can actively participate. There
are no moving elements in Cruz Diez's
work; instead, movement is created on
the surface through the dynamic effects
of colour. His paintings come alive, cons¬
tantly changing in appearance and nuance
depending on one's viewpoint and the
light penetrating them.
Carlos Cruz Diez acknowledges a debt
to his experience as a graphic artist. For a
long time, he was an advertising designer
and draughtsman. This can clearly be seen
in many aspects of his work, especially at
the outset of his career. However, some¬
thing must have conditioned him at an
earlier stage for his sense of space and its
independence to have developed as it did.
Cruz Diez is also a child of tropical Latin
America and this must have had a pro¬
found influence on his feeling for space
and colour.
A third Venezuelan who was also born
on the banks of the Orinoco arrived in
Paris with his two compatriots in the 1950s.
His name is Alejandro Otero. Though he
moved from Picasso-like works to abstract
and kinetic art, his aims were the same:
he set out to create a new form of space
in works of art that also embody time and
light.
He began by painting on canvas and
wood, evolving the highly expressive and
original manner to be seen in his Co/orit-
mos, in which lines of pure colour criss¬
cross each other and create new colour
and dimensional relationships. Then he
went on to create objects in space. Using
the vibration of metals ionized by light, he
erected giant structures which, under the
effect of the wind and the time of day,
change shape and colour as if they were
alive. The vibrations of the light on the
polished surfaces rise up like mirages or
unexpected patterns of reflection on clouds
and buildings. This is what he calls
"vibrating integrals" or "solar wings".
His structures are like endless perfor¬
mances which unfold before the spectators
in a continuous display of shapes and
colours. His works are designed for large
spaces, and merge into the landscape.
The artist has erected these dazzling and
fascinating "reflecting hills" in Washington,
D.C, Bogota, and Ciudad Guayana in
Venezuela.
The changing environment of tropical
Latin America and its ambiguous rela¬
tionship with man have molded the cre¬
ative sensibility of each of these three
outstanding Latin-American artists. It is
no mere coincidence that each of them,
in his own way, has played a leading role
in the development of kinetic art.
Arturo Uslar-Pietrl
66
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
AND
LATIN
AMERICA'S
CULTURAL
HERITAGE
IN the past few years, Unesco has stepped up its activities
relating to the preservation and restoration of monuments
and other cultural treasures in Latin America, whose coun¬
tries are increasingly aware of the importance of their cultural
heritage as a factor in their cultural identity as well as its place
in their overall development.
In 1974, a regional programme was launched in six Andean
countries (Bolivia, Chile, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru and Vene¬
zuela). Financed by the United Nations Development Pro¬
gramme (UNDP), it has been so successful that it has stimulat¬
ed a number of private initiatives as well. A wide variety of
activities has been initiated, in such fields as professional training,
the listing and preservation of monuments and other treasures,
and urban planning.
Since 1975, a training programme has been organized each
year at Cuzco (Peru), with courses on the preservation of archi¬
tectural monuments, archeological remains and other works of
art. Over a hundred students from the six countries in the region
have taken up scholarships to attend theoretical and practical
courses given by more than 40 international specialists.
Meanwhile, laboratory-workshops for the restoration of paint¬
ings and sculpture have been set up at La Paz (Peru) and Quito
(Ecuador), while the activities of existing laboratory-workshops
at Santiago de Chile, at Lima (Peru) and at Bogota (Colombia)
have been strengthened.
All the countries participating in this regional programme have
embarked on the urgent task of drawing up inventories of all'
their historic buildings and other art treasures, with the assistance I
of a large number of experts and consultants. . I
Restoration work on the church at
Checacupe, Peru, forms part of one
of the programmes for the
conservation of monuments and
other cultural treasures in Latin
America with which Unesco is
associated.
67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
y Specialists in a wide range of fields have, been called upon to
deal with the problems of preserving sun-dried brick, stone,
paper, wood, pottery and metal, as well as the restoration of
colonial style buildings and questions related to museology and
the preservation and planning of historic towns.
Seminars and symposia have also been held with the parti¬
cipation of internationally-known experts on such themes as
"The Preservation of Historic Towns" (Quito, Ecuador), "Museo¬
logy" (Bogota, Colombia), and "The Listing of Monuments"
(Santiago de Chile).
A key target of the regional programme is to make the Latin
American cultural heritage more widely known and to encourage
the active participation of the people who live near the historical
monuments. To achieve this goal, exhibitions, lectures, sym¬
posia and round-table discussions have been organized, bro¬
chures and articles have been published, and radio and television
broadcasts have been produced. A notable example of these
activities is an exhibition entitled "5,000 Years of Peruvian Cloth",
presented at Lima in 1977.
Unesco is also participating in another major programme in
Latin America, the COPESCO plan, in which Peru and Unesco
are collaborating on the cultural and economic development of
the area between Cuzco and Lake Titicaca. The plan's objectives
are, firstly, to preserve monuments of the pre-Columbian and
colonial periods, particularly numerous in this area which was
once the centre of the Inca empire, and secondly, to foster the
growth of tourism. For the tourism attracted by these historic
monuments may help to promote the region's economic develop¬
ment and improve living standards, which are low.
In the preliminary stages of the plan, Unesco is putting its
experience in restoration techniques at Peru's disposal. The
execution of the work will be financed by the Peruvian govern¬
ment and the Inter-American Development Bank.
In accordance with the wishes of the Peruvian government,
Unesco will continue to provide technical assistance on indi¬
vidual restoration problems. Many specialists and consultants
are working with Peruvian technicians in such fields as archeology,
the restoration of architecture, painting and sculpture, as well as
museology and urban planning. A workshop-laboratory in Cuzco
is also serving as a centre for regional training courses given by
international experts.
In addition to these two major projects, Unesco is participating
in a number of other specialized activities related to the preser¬
vation of the cultural heritage of Latin American countries. With
Honduras, Unesco is collaborating on the preservation of the
Maya site at Copan and is assisting Guatemala in repairing the
damage caused by last year's earthquakes. Unesco is also
cooperating with Panama in drawing up an inventory of the
country's historic monuments, and with Brazil in organizing
training courses for specialists in the restoration of monuments
and in the preservation of historic towns and villages.
Finally, Unesco is working closely with Argentina and Uruguay
on the preservation and restoration of the ruins of Jesuit mis¬
sions; with Uruguay on the exploration and excavation of the
prehistoric site at Salto Grande; with Bolivia on the conservation
of archeological sites and the restoration of old Jesuit villages in
the east of the country; and with the Churubusco training centre
in Mexico.
UNESCO
BOOKSHELF ON
LATIN AMERICA
Works in Unesco's
Literature Translations
Series
ANTONIO MANUEL DE ALMEIDA (Brazil). Memoirs
of a Militia Sergeant. Translated by Linton L. Barrett.
Washington, U.S.A. 1959, 244 pp.
Anthology of Mexican Poetry. Translated by Samuel
Beckett, compiled by Octavio Paz; preface CM. Bowra.
Bloomington, Indiana University Press. Thames &
Hudson, London, 1958, 213 pp.
CONCOLORCORVO (Peru). El Lazarillo; A Guide for
Inexperienced Travellers between Buenos Aires and
Lima, 1773. Translated by Walter D. Kline. Bloomington,
Indiana University Press, 1965, 315 pp.
MANUEL DE JESUS GALVAN (Dominican Republic).
The Cross and the Sword. Translated by Robert
Graves. Bloomington, Indiana University Press, 1954,
366 pp. Victor Gollancz, London, U.K., 1956, 366 pp.
BALDOMERO LILLO (Chile). The Devil's Pit and
other stories. Translated by Esther S. Dillon and
Angel Flores, Washington, 1959, 152 pp.
JOACHIM MARIA MACHADO DE ASSIS (Brazil).
Yaya Garcia. Translated by R.L. Scott-Buccleuch.
London, Peter Owen, 1976, 220 pp.
Modern Brazilian poetry. Translated by John Nist.
Bloomington, Ind., Indiana University Press, 1962, 175 pp.
TERESA DE LA PARRA (Venezuela). Mama Blanca's
Souvenirs. Translated by Harriet de Onís, Washington,
U.S.A. 1959, 129 pp.
OCTAVIO PAZ (Mexico). Selected Poems. Trans¬
lated by M. Rukeyser in collaboration with the author.
Bloomington, Ind., Indiana University Press, 1963.
171 pp; Jonathan Cape, London, 1970, under the title
Configurations.
FLORENCIO SANCHEZ (Uruguay). Representative
Plays. Translated by Willis Knapp Jones. Washington,
1961,326 pp.
DOMINGO F. SARMIENTO (Argentina). ' Travels. A
Selection. Translated by Inès Muñoz, Washington,
1963,297 pp.
JAIME TORRES BODET (Mexico). Selected Poems.
Translated by S.P. Karsen. Bloomington, Ind., Indiana
University Press, 1964, 155 pp.
JUAN ZORILLA DE SAN MARTÍN (Uruguay).
Tabaré: An Indian Legend of Uruguay. Translated by
Walter Owen. Washington, 1956, 366 pp.
Many of the above works are out of print, and are
listed for information purposes.
Please do not send orders to Unesco. '
Order through your local bookseller.
68
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
THE LAND-LOCKED ISLAND OF PARAGUAY (continued from page 53,
And so Governor Lázaro de Ribera was
mistaken. The language of the conquered
peoples was not, and could not be the
dominant language. Guarani retreated into
the depths of the collective memory,
settled there like a sediment, and came to
dominate from within the self-expression
of Paraguay, whether it be bilingual or not.
"Colonial society", Meliá explains, "was
officially Spanish-speaking from the start.
Guarani played no part in administration
or official policy. During the colonial
period, Guarani had no literary foundations
and was in contact with a major literary
language Spanish. Gradually, a Paragua¬
yan Guarani emerged which had all the
characteristics of^a vernacular language:
it became the mother tongue of a group
dominated socially and politically by ano¬
ther group speaking a different language."
Such a situation could perhaps be de¬
scribed as di-lingualism rather than bilin¬
gualism.
According to Meliá, "Paraguay is bilin¬
gual, but few Paraguayans are themselves
bilingual. Indeed, it may be that no one in
Paraguay is really bilingual. The situation
can best be described as rural-urban bilin¬
gualism". For although Guarani is even
spoken in the capital, Asunción, it is be¬
coming increasingly obvious that the towns
are moving towards Spanish monolingua-
lism while in the countryside the proportion
of monolingual Guarani speakers is very
high.
The use of Guarani or Spanish in Para¬
guay is governed by social and regional
factors. Even people who think of them¬
selves as bilingual will never discuss certain
topics in the indigenous language: it would
be simply impossible because social cir¬
cumstances do not allow it. The Guarani
speaker thus finds in fact that he is exclud¬
ed from a whole range of fields because he
cannot make himself heard in them. Worse
still, he cannot even conceptualize them
because he lacks adequate linguistic means
of self-expression.
If, for example, someone speaking
Guarani had access to the world of advanc¬
ed technology, he would find that he
would have to use so many neologisms
that his language would be practically
annihilated.
In Paraguay, then, the problem of bilin¬
gualism is rendered more acute by the fact
that Guarani, which is above all an oral
language, has become impoverished during
the centuries in which it was forced to
play a marginal role in Paraguayan society
and culture. It is, according to Meliá,
"like a country which has been deprived
of vast areas of territory and is losing its
capacity to express its cultural identity".
It is clear that the future of Guarani like
that of Spanish is closely linked to the
historical destiny of the country itself.
Although Guarani has been relegated to
the status of a vehicle for communicating
emotions, it will continue to modulate
the expression of a whole people's deepest
and most vital feelings. Herein lies its
strength.
Linked to the mysteries of blood, in¬
stinct and collective memory, the survival
of Guarani is guaranteed by the density of
the linguistic sediment that forms the
foundations of the bilingual island of
Paraguay.
Augusto Roa Bastos
LATIN AMERICA'S JOURNEY TO SELF-DISCOVERY
(continued from page 7)
lower opinion of the mestizo: "In America
everything which is not European is bar¬
baric", Alberdi wrote^
To "educate for civilization", as it were,
and to bring in men who would do for
Latin America what they had already done
in Europe and the United States amounted
to joining up with those who were already
far advanced along the path of progress
and civilization. Sarmiento warned that if
Latin America did not take this course, it
might lose its chance to become an out¬
post of modern civilization.
Without experience, the Latin Ameri¬
cans were obliged to ask for guidance
from those who were turther ahead along
the same pathWestern Europe and the
United States. If Latin America could not
be a centre of civilization, then let it at
least be an outpost. If it could not be the
locomotive, it could at least be the
caboose.
Europe, however, was engaged in
brutal imperialism at the time and the
United States was in an expansionist
phase that began with the 1847 war
against Mexico and continued in 1898
with its ouster of Iberian imperialism from
the Caribbean. These events made Latin
Americans conscious of their cultural con¬
flicts and of the need to surmount them.
They also became aware of their inferi¬
ority complex, which had facilitated the
shift from an imposed dependency to a
freely accepted one.
The Uruguayan essayist José Enrique
Rodé (1871-1917) was one of the first to
decry the errors of the civilization policy.
He exposed the tendency to "de-latinize"
and the mania for imitating all things
northern. In his book Ariel, he wrote;
"One imitates the people in whom one
sees superiority and prestige." And that
is why the United States, he added, is
"conquering us morally".
Imitate, yes, but invent as well, urged
the Mexican Antonio Caso (1883-1946).
Latin America, "our America", as it was
called by the Cuban writer and patriot
José Marti (1853-1895), is not a vacuum
which has to be filled over and over again.
Latin America is a reality: it has a culture
and a long history.
America is the Indians, and also their
conquerors, the liberators struggling to
put an end to the conquest as well as the
conservatives seeking to preserve the
established order and the civilizers trying
to jump ahead of their own experience.
Latin American culture has overcome the
supposed superiority of all the cultures
which different people had tried to impose
on it. Each of these cultures was absorbed
and mixed in the melting pot.
This attempt to produce an assimilated
culture also made Latin Americans aware
of the errors of previous generations.
These errors had been made at the very
moment when the continent achieved its
political emancipation.
It was a mistake to assume that Latin
Americans were incapable of acquiring
their own form of culture and civilization.
"Incapacity", José Marti wrote, "does not
lie with new-born nations which need
reforms tailored to their needs and a bene¬
ficial greatness, but in those who want to
rule genuinely original nations, whose de
velopment has been unusual and violent,
with laws that were forged over four cen¬
turies of freedom in the United States...
The spirit of government must be adjusted
to the particular constitution of the coun¬
try. Government is nothing more than the
equilibrium of the natural elements of a
country". The path of genius would have
been to bring together what had seemed
to be separate. "The problem of inde¬
pendence", Marti added, "was not to
change the form but to change the spirit".
This is what Latin Americans have
sought to achieve throughout this century:
a change of spirit in terms of their own
past and their own culture. One of the
leading proponents of this movement, the
Mexican political thinker José Vasconcelos
(1882-1959), spoke of a Cosmic Race. By
this he meant a Latin American melting
pot which would produce its own forms
of culture and its own specific identity.
It was a painfully earned identity, but
one which its heirs could be proud of.:
"What fatherland", wrote Marti, "can a
man have more pride in than these Amer¬
ican republics born of travail, raised up
among the silent masses of Indians, amid
the noise of battle and of the book and
candle held in the bloody hands of a hun¬
dred apostles? Never have such compact
and advanced nations been created in so
brief a historical time out of such disor¬
dered factors".
A complex cultural identity and by the
same token an original one. The expe¬
rience of men in extraordinary and complex
situations: this explains their original con¬
tribution to history and to human culture
in short, to mankind. Leopoldo Zea
69
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
0 b 0HS/: ï
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
The Caribbean Mathematics Pro¬
ject: Training the Teacher as the
Agent of Reform, by H. Martyn Cundy.
(Unesco: International Bureau of Edu¬
cation "Experiments and Innovations in
Education" series, no. 32) 1977, 72 pp.
(10 F).
Communication Policies in India,
by M.V. Desai. 1977, 88 pp. (18 F).
Communication Policies in Sri
Lanka, by M.A. de Silva and Reggie
Siriwardene. 1977, 59 pp. (12 F).
Readings on Population for Law
Students, edited by L.T. Lee and P.
Saney. 1977, 123 pp. (22 F).
Cultural Policy in the Union of
Soviet Socialist Republics, by A.A.
Zvorykin, with the assistance of N.I.
Golubtsova and E.I. Rabinovich. 2nd
impression 1977, 68 pp. (12 F); Cultural
Policy in the Federal Republic of
Germany. 2nd impression 1977. 53 pp.
(10 F); Cultural Rights as Human
Rights. 3rd impression 1977, 125 pp.
(20 F); Cultural Policy in Czechoslo¬
vakia, by Miroslav Marek with the co¬
operation of Milan Hromádka and Josef
Chroust. 2nd impression 1977, 77 pp.
(13 F); Cultural Policy in Tunisia, by
Rafik Said. 2nd impression 1977, 56 pp.
(10 F). (All in Unesco's "Studies and
Documents on Cultural Policies" series)
New Trends in Integrated Science
Teaching, Vol. II, edited by P.E.
Richmond. 2nd impression 1977, 239 pp.
(40 F).
New Trends in Mathematics
Teaching, Vol. Ill, 2nd impression
1977, 145 pp. (28 F).
9 Youth Institutions and Services:
Present State and Development.
1977, 51 pp. (8 F); Buildings for
School and , Community Use: Five
Case Studies. 1977, 122 pp. (12 F).
Nos. 23- and 26 in Unesco's "Educatio¬
nal Studies and Documents" series.
Education and Training of Users
of Scientific and Technical Infor¬
mation: UNISIST Guide for Teachers,
by A.J. Evans, R.G. Rhodes and S.
Keenan. 1977, 143 pp. (28 F).
Human Settlements is the theme
of Unesco's quarterly Impact of Science
on Society (Vol. 27. No. 2, 1977). Each
issues 9.50 F; annual subscription 32 F.
Ends and Means for Continuing
Education is the major theme of Pros¬
pects, Unesco's quarterly review of
education (Vol. 7, No. 2, 1977). Each
issue 9.50; annual subscription 32 F.
Unesco publications
on Latin American
cultures
Since 1967, Unesco has been carrying out
a broad programme of studies on Latin
American cultures. Some of these studies
have been published (in Spanish) under
the general title "América Latina en su
Cultura" (Latin America within its Culture)
in collaboration with Siglo XXI publishers,
Mexico City. The titles which have appear¬
ed so far are: América Latina en su Litera¬
tura, América Latina en sus Artes and
América Latina en su Arquitectura. A
study on Latin American music, América
Latina en su Música, will appear shortly.
Another series, "El Mundo en América
Latina" (The World in Latin America) has
also been created; the first volume, Africa
en América Latina (Africa in Latin Amer¬
ica) is currently in preparation. In addition
to these series, Unesco has published
other important studies on various aspects
of Latin American cultures, including a
bibliography of Latin American literature
(Bibliografía General de la Literatura Lati¬
no-Americana) and a work on architecture
(Panorámica de la Arquitectura Latino-
Americana).
Unesco travelling
exhibition
on Latin America
"The Arts of Latin America" ¡s the theme
of the 12th travelling exhibition organized
by Unesco in its programme for the inter¬
national circulation of cultural works. The
exhibition consists of hundreds of photos
providing an overall picture of Latin Amer¬
ican painting, sculpture, the decorative
arts and architecture from pre-Columbian
times to the present day.
At the request of Unesco's Member
States, the exhibition will be displayed in
different parts of the world from mid-
October 1977. An identical exhibition will
be presented at Bogota (Colombia) on the
occasion of the Intergovernmental Confer¬
ence on Cultural Policies in Latin America
and the Caribbean, which will be held
there from 10 to 20 January 1978.
The challenge
of the year 2000
A round-table discussion on "The Challen¬
ge of the Year 2000" was held at Unesco
headquarters in Paris from 28 to 30 June
1977. Thirty internationally-known politi¬
cians, artists, thinkers and scientists, in¬
cluding Nobel Peace Prize-winners Lord
Noel-Baker (U.K.) and Sean MacBride
(Ireland) and Nobel Physics Prize-winner
Alfred Kastler (France) expressed concern
about the triple danger that now faces
mankind: the nuclear threat, the environ¬
mental threat , and the growing , moral
threat. -
During the discussions, opened by
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-
General of Unesco, and Mr. Luis Eche¬
verría, former President of Mexico, alarm
was expressed at "the sluggishness of the
implementation of world nuclear disarma¬
ment as a first step to general and com¬
plete disarmament; the continued reckless
plundering of the irreplaceable resources
of the earth, arbitrary deforestation and
the pollution of nature; the perceptible
slackening of ethical standards and the
invasion of men's minds by the subliminal
influences of a press or mass media mani¬
pulated by economic interests, govern¬
ments or other agencies or individuals for
reasons of their own".
All the participants, irrespective of their
political beliefs and their countries of ori¬
gin, stressed "the need for the closest
international cooperation in the solution of
all these problems, including the contin¬
uing and urgent need for social justice,
for the equitable sharing of natural resour¬
ces and for a brake on unrestrained con¬
sumerism". All these questions, along
with those of youth and unemployment,
are factors in the new world economic
order "which is a prerequisite for that
peace so gravely threatened and so ar¬
dently desired by men, individually and
collectively".
Among the participants were the
Egyptian writer Tewfik Al-Hakim; Buck-
minster, Fuller, American architect and
writer; Jerzy . Grotowski, Polish theatre
director; Vladimir S. Kemenov, Vice-
President of the U.S.S.R. Academy of
Fine Arts; Prem Kirpal, Indian education¬
ist; Takeo Kuwabara, professor of French
literature at Tokyo; M.L. Mehrotra, Indian
pulmonary physician; Peter Ustinov, actor,
dramatist and film director; and Sir Ronald
Syme, formerly Camden Professor of An¬
cient History at Oxford University.
Fight against
child-killing diseases
The World Health Organization has set
itself the goal of providing immuniza¬
tion for all the world's children by 1990
through its Expanded Programme on
Immunization. Safe, effective vaccines
are available against such common child¬
hood killers as diphtheria, measles, polio
and tuberculosis. However, there is an
urgent need for programmes to bring
vaccines where they are most needed it
is estimated that less than 10 per cent of
the 80 million children born each year in
the developing countries are being immu¬
nized against these diseases.
Venezuela's gift to
Unesco cultural fund
Venezuela has paid 5666,000 to the Inter¬
national Fund for the Promotion of Culture
as a first instalment of $2 million it has
pledged to the Fund. The Fund, set up by
Unesco's General Conference in 1974,
aims to finance and promote cultural pro¬
jects in Unesco Member States with vo¬
luntary public and private help.
70
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
Unesco books
on Latin America
THE BASIC SECONDARY SCHOOL IN
THE COUNTRY
An educational innovation in Cuba
by Max Figueroa
1974 7 French francs
COMMUNICATION POLICIES IN
COSTA RICA
by Jaime M. Fonseca
1977
COMMUNICATION POLICIES IN PERU
by Carlos Ortega and Carlos Romero
1977
CULTURAL POLICY IN CUBA
by Lisandro Otero with the assistance of
Francisco Martinez Hinojosa
1972
16 FF
15 FF
8 FF
EDUCATIONAL
by Judith Bizot
1975
REFORM IN PERU
STATISTICS OF SCIENCE AND
TECHNOLOGY IN LATIN AMERICA
1976
YOUTH PARTICIPATION IN THE
DEVELOPMENT PROCESS
A case study in Panama
by Luis Z. Gomez de Souza and Lucia Ribeiro
1976
8 FF
10 FF
12 FF
FORTHCOMING
RACE AND CLASS IN
POST-COLONIAL SOCIETY:
A study of ethnic group relations in the English-speaking
Caribbean, Bolivia, Chile and Mexico
Expected publication date: late 1977 Approx. 60 FF
Where to renew you»' subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW; Periodicals;
Dominie Pty., Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division 5th floor, 134-136 Flinders St.,
Melbourne (Victoria), 3000. - AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain,
Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandlung, Industriehof Stadiau,
Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220 Wien. - BELGIUM: "Unesco
Courier" Dutch edition only; N.V. Handelmaatschappjj Keesing.
Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition
and general Unesco publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 112,
rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 000-0070823-13. - BURMA.
Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552 Merchant Street. Rangoon.
- CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
Street West, Montreal, Qué H3H 1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L, Spalena 51, Prague 1
(Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka,
Prague 1. For Slovakia only; Alfa Verlag Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR. DEN¬
MARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency
for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, SF 00100 Helsinki.
FRANCE, Librairie de l'Unesco. 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Interna¬
tionalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53
Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22, C.C.P. Hamburg 276650. For
scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach
800830. Other publications; Verlag Dokumentation, Pössen-
bacher Strasse 2, 8000 München 71 (Prinz Ludwigshöhe).
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRrTAIN. See United Kingdom. - GREECE.
International bookshops. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
Division, Far East Publications Ltd., 5 A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, Wong Chuk Hang Road, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co.. 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémial
Könyvesbolt, Vâci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvturosok
Boltia, Népkoztarsasâg utja 16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New
Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots; Oxford Book &
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House.
New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop. Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 139 Shah Reza Ave., opposite to University of Teheran,
P.O. Box 14/1486, Teheran. Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco,
Ave Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad. - IRELAND.
The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly
Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48, Nachtat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv; 9, Shlomzion Hamalka Street Je¬
rusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. - JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo 100-92. - KENYA. East
African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, P.O. Box
2942, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O.
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA.
Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O.
Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publi¬
cations Sdn. Bhd., Balai Berita, 31, Jalan Riong, Kuala Lumpur. -
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30, bd des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications; N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.). N.V.,
Willemstad, Curaçao. N. A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street,
P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721,
Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes
Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag,
Wellington. - NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife. The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. Box 286; The University
Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The
Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY.
All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl Johans-
gate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only; A.S. Narvesens
Literaturtjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore
3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. ORPAN-IMPORT,
Palac Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias 6
Andrade Ltda, Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New
Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop
and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Buil¬
ding, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier (single copies) only; Central News Agency P.O. Box
1033, Johannesburg. - SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook
Sales (PVTI Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata
P.O.B. 244 Columbo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.
Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications: A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier; Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030
Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London. Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill
Station, New. York, N.Y. 10016. For "Unesco Courier" in
Spanish: Santillana Publishing Company, Inc., 575 Lexington
Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Teraztje, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenlje,
Titova C 25, P.O.B. 60-1, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
»
-^\
- \%):
]]>
</page>
</document>
