<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074813eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The ^~~~\^ A window open on th« world
tLourier
JULY 1977 130th year) 2.80 French francs
A HALT
TO DESERT
ADVANCE
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Ú
aäVw»
p*m
&&
:&
'/'SOT.
}'. ,-K.
KB
JVrl
ffi
tfi
^>J
<£/#
Y^y?*-'
HH
ÄOW
Sc?"
MfflflffBH
y y .
Küfl í?r
S Y.
IP8SÍSü
Y:',..;-;--: ^;¿'
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Winged ram of Ribadeo
Recently discovered in the little town of Ribadeo in Galicia (north-west Spain), this hollow
statuette of a winged ram is over 2,000 years old. It is made of thin strips of gold beaten together
and covered with a variety of embossed motifs, including tiny spheres and pellets. On each side
side of the ram (6.5 cm high and wide), the artist has fashioned a crested bird and a four-footed
beast. Some scholars have suggested that the statuette may be Phoenician or Hellenistic, but
others believe that it is a product of the ancient culture of Tartessus in south-west Spain.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JUNE 1977 30TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 16 LANGUAGE!
English Japanese Dutch
French Italian Portuguese
Spanish Hindi Turkish
Russian Tamil Urdu
German Hebrew
Arabic Persian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 28 French Francs
2 years: 52 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (11 University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100. U.S.A. ; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
France
Managing Editors
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
Dutch Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu Edition
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
: Werner Merkli (Berne)
; Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
page
4 ARE DESERTS MAN-MADE?
by Mohammed El-Kassas
7 DESERTIFICATION: THE CLIMATE AS ACCOMPLICE
by F. Kenneth Hare
11 A PRECARIOUS BALANCE UPSET
by Victor A. Kovda
14 THE SANDS OF WRATH
America's Dust Bowl in retrospect
by Harold E. Dregne
18 A WINNING BATTLE AGAINST DESTRUCTION
Desert science in the steppes of Central Asia
by Agadjhan G. Babaev and Nikolai S. Orlovsky
23 ONSLAUGHT ON THE NILE
Shifting dunes threaten Egypt's breadbasket
by Farouk El-Baz
25 A CASE STUDY IN SURVIVAL
Animal life in desert conditions
by Claude Grenot and Roland Vernet
29 THE POOR MAN'S ENERGY CRISIS
by Erik P. Eckholm
32 THE GREAT GREEN WALLS OF CHINA
to S
m
SR
Oen
o"7
Zrs
!2z
34 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
SPAIN: Winged ram of Ribadeo
Cover
What causes deserts to advance? How
helpless is man faced with the ravages of
desertification? These are only two of the
disquieting questions raised in this issue.
Today we still know relatively little about
deserts how they are created, and the roles
that man and climate respectively play in their
spread. To have a global evaluation of the
problem and to initiate a programme of
action, the United Nations has decided to hold
the first Conference on Desertification this
year in Nairobi (Kenya), from 29 August to
9 September. Preparatory to the Conference,
a world map of deserts and desertification is
being drawn up in collaboration with Unesco
and other international organizations.
Photo Maximillen Bruggmann © Editions La Spirale, Switzerland -
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Should man be blamed for the expanding deserts? In many cases, the answer, is "yes". Because of his activities,
man often aggravates an already serious situation stemming from natural causes. In Africa, for example, the Sahara
is slowly expanding and now constitutes a threat to the economies of several countries. Shown below: the
Tibesti desert region that straddles the borders of Chad and Niger. At right: the Fezzan, in Libya.
Are deserts
man-made?
by
Mohammed El-Kassas
MOHAMMED EL-KASSAS, Egyptian botanist, pro¬
fessor of applied botany at the University of Cairo, is
director of the Egyptian National Committee for the
Unesco Man and Biosphere (MAB) programme. From
1970 to 1974, he was vice-president of the Interna¬
tional Coordinating Committee for this programme
and, from 1972 to 1976, assistant director general of
the Arab Organization for Education, Science and Cul¬
ture. A member of the Club of Rome, he is on the
board of several international scientific publications.
DESERTS are part of the arid and
semi-arid zones that cover one-
third of the earth's land area and
fall within the boundaries of some 60 coun¬
tries. They include:
rainless deserts, where it does not even
rain once a year (the Central Sahara in
North Africa, the Rub-al-Khali in Arabia,
the Takla Makam Desert in Central Asia
and the Atacama Desert in South
America);
run-off deserts, where annual rainfall is
less than 100 mm. and perennial plant
life is confined to run-off collecting ba¬
sins such as desert wadis, those rivers
that flow only after rain;
rainfall deserts, with between 100 and
200 mm. a year of rain. While there is
not enough rain to sustain crop produc¬
tion, perennial plants are found just
about everywhere.
These limits of 100 and 200 mm. a year
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
are only approximate. In the coastal
desert of Chile and Peru in South America
or Namibia in southern Africa, the lower
figure may drop to 50 mm. of rain a year
because the ocean keeps the atmosphere
humid at least part of the year. In tropical
deserts where rain is steamed off by sum¬
mer heat, the limit can be 150 mm. a year.
As for desertification, it may be defined
as retrogressive ecological changes in vege¬
tation, soil or water regime that reduce
productivity, lower the carrying capacity
of the land and make it more vulnerable/
to soil erosion. Temporary desertification
can occur during the rainless season, in a
year of below-average rainfall or in a spell
of a few years, such as the Sahel drought
from 1969 to 1973. However, the ecosys¬
tem, as we shall see, may eventually set
matters right again.
For plants, animals and man manage
to survive within deserts. Populations
may be sparse and only temporary (such
as nomads and ephemeral plants) or clus¬
tered around oases, but they are not
altogether absent.
Organisms strike a precarious balance
between their ability to survive and the
austere resources of their arid habitat.
Under such conditions, physical environ¬
ment and plant life are in a state of dyna¬
mic equilibrium on the razor's edge: a
small change in the former has a dramatic
effect on the latter.
Next to the arid zones are areas where
the rainfall runs between 200 and 400 mm.
a year. Man uses land in a variety of ways
here, but these are not divorced from land-
use practices in rainfall or even drier
deserts. Grazing extends over all three
categories of land.
Run-off horticulture dating back to
Greco-Roman days still thrives in central
and southern Tunisia around Sousse,
Matmata and Gafsa where 10 million olive
trees are cultivated and in southwestern
Libya at Beni Ulid where olive groves are
maintained though rainfall averages but
70 mm. a year.
Comparable run-off farming without
irrigation was formerly practised in Pales¬
tine during the Nabatean period from
600 B.C. to 200 A.D. Experiments in the
northern Negev, where rainfall is 80 mm.
a year, have shown it can still be done.
A principal characteristic shared by arid
and semi-arid areas is their fragile ecolo¬
gical situation. Rainfall or the lack of it-
is the crucial climatic element:
It is deficient throughout all or most of
the year. By this we mean that it is less
than potential évapotranspiration the
water lost by evaporation from the sur¬
face of the land and transpiration by
plants. Life, therefore, is under the
stress of a shortage of moisture.
It is seasonal. The year consists of a
rainy season and a rainless season.
During the often long dry period, the
ground may be totally or partially strip¬
ped of plant cover.
It is variable. Figures describing average
annual rainfall hardly correspond to
reality. At Agadès, in Niger, the mean
annual rainfall from 1922 to 1972 was
159 mm. but 288 mm. fell in 1958 and
only 40 mm. in 1970. Comparable year-
to-year differences are found everywhere
in arid and semi-arid zones. Plant
growth responds to these variations. It
may fail during dry years, with the result
that there are no crops, little or no pas¬
ture and not enough cover to protect
soil from erosion.
It falls in short cloudbursts concentrated
over small areas. If the ground is not
protected by plant cover, these torren¬
tial downpours may do serious damage
by washing away surface soil.
Under natural conditions and without
destructive interference by man and his
domestic animals, ecological systems may
keep their balance even under such con¬
ditions. Wet years enable plants to make
up growth lost during a dry spell. Peren¬
nial and woody plants survive during dry
seasons and dry years, thus maintaining
at least a skeletal plant cover on the earth.
True, cloudbursts are destructive but
they enable water to penetrate under¬
ground and provide the deep roots of arid
land shrubs with a year-round supply of
moisture. In other words, natural proces¬
ses can correct ecological imbalance in the
long run, and the land will regain its nor- k
mal appearance. f
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
But when the hazard of erratic rainfall
is coupled with pressure brought to bear
on the land by man, then the damage may
be irreversible: desertification.
Traditional land uses in arid and semi-
arid zones provided their inhabitants with
a life basis for generations. In low rain¬
fall areas, subsistence farming is carried
out whenever rainfall is above average.
Land is cleared and crops (barley in
winter rainfall areas and sorghum or millet
where the rain comes in summer) are cul¬
tured by hoe. If the rains come two years
in a row, an adjoining area is farmed.
Under this system, there are long fallow
periods before the same piece of land is
worked twice. Where rainfall amounts to
more than 400 mm., shifting cultivation of
larger tracts is carried out. Often, fire is
used to clear the ground and control
weeds.
The cycle of shifting cultivation in the
so-called Gum-Arabic belt of the Sudan,
which lies in an area where rainfall runs
from 250 to 450 mm. a year, is a fine
example of how integrated land use can
be maintained for centuries.
First, there is a cultivation period. Aca¬
cia scrub is cleared, then dukho (Penni-
seteum typhoideum) and dura (Sorghum
vulgare) are grown four to ten years run¬
ning, watered by rain. When the soil
becomes exhausted and parasite-infested,
it is allowed to lie fallow.
Next comes the colonization period.
Acacia Senegal, Acacia seyal and associate
grasses invade the abandoned field. In
about eight or ten years, the acacias are
ready for gum tapping.
During the orchard period, lasting from
six to ten years, the acacias are tapped for
a cash crop.
Finally, deterioration begins. The Aca¬
cia Senegal trees start do die, but their
fallen trunks are thorny and keep grazing
animals away. This allows tall dense grass
to flourish until the land is ready once
more to be cleared by burning so another
crop can be planted.
Such cycles prevailed throughout semi-
arid zones, though in some places char¬
coal-making may have replaced gum-
tapping as a cash source. These cycles
replaced the natural Acacia-grass cycle of
Africa or Prosopis-grass cycle of the
Americas that characterize the vegetation
of semi-arid zones.
However, the cycles have not been
maintained under the accelerated pace of
land use in recent decades. Acacia sene-
gal, the main gum-arabic producer, no
longer regenerates effectively. Nor do the
grasses, and crop failures are common.
Here we have an aspect of desertification.
Inhabitants with their traditional land-
use practices move south to areas of
higher rainfall between 500 and 800 mm.
a year. As a result, the savanna belt of
parkland is gradually replaced by the
plants and the land-use practices pre¬
viously found in the semi-arid belt. This
is part of the shift from forest-to-savanna-
to-steppe-to-desert that occurs in the
broad framework of desertification and
other forms of ecological degradation.
This form of desertification cannot,
therefore, be remedied by natural pro¬
cesses. It is primarily man-made, trigger¬
ed by the pressures of land use that are
beyond the carrying capacity of the eco¬
system and its ability to recover from
degradation.
Among these pressures are over-grazing,
over-cultivation, over-cutting of woody
plants for fuel, and uncontrolled use of
fire. When plants are destroyed or criti¬
cally thinned, the soil loses its protective
cover and is laid open to rapid erosion by
wind and water.
The causes of the over-exploitation of
the resources of these fragile nabitats are
mainly socio-political. They are related
to the increase in population and the
changes in society that have appeared in
recent years. As the human population
grows, so does the number of livestock
(there were 4 million cattle in Nigeria in
1925 and 10 million in 1970) while farming
must become more extensive or more
intensive to feed new mouths.
As national governments set their devel¬
opment plans, the subsistence livestock
economy gradually gives way to -a com¬
mercial livestock economy. Livestock
becomes a major export. The develop¬
ment of agriculture heightens the conflict
between the farmer and the herdsman
with one inevitable result: still more pres¬
sure on land.
The appearance of cities as political and
administrative centres gradually breaks
down the old mechanisms of social inter¬
dependence within networks of kinship
bonds. And this reduces the ability of
herdsman-farmer societies to respond
flexibly to environmental fluctuations.
Without a doubt, desertification is but
the end result of ecological, economic and
political pressures.
Mohammed El-Kassas
Too much or
too little
It sometimes happens that the desert
gets too much water. A case in
point is the Ouaar wadi, in southern
Morocco (above), where sudden
storms can produce flash floods.
The same situation, growing worse
in some areas, prevails in many arid
zones and poses the problem of
worldwide changes in climate.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The climate
as accomplice
DESERTIFICATION
T
by F. Kenneth Hare
F. KENNETH HARE, Canadian c/imatologist, is Direc¬
tor of the Institute for Environmental Studies at the
University of Toronto. A member of the Canadian
Environmental Advisory Committee, he is Director of
"Resources for the Future" in Washington, D.C. He
is also the principal author of the report "Climate
and Desertification" prepared for the United Nations
Conference on desertification to be held in Nairobi in
August and September, 1977.
have always been deserts on
earth. They are natural creations,
locked in place by endless subsi¬
dence of the overlying atmosphere. Rain-
making disturbances are weakened or
destroyed by large-scale downward settling
of airstreams. Subsidence is natural to
the sub-tropics of our rotating earth it
has been, and always will be.
Yet the desert margins have shifted, and
the aridity of the interior regions has waxed
and waned. Until about 2,700 B.C.,
cattle-herding nomads roamed over pro¬
ductive savannas in what is now the arid
eastern Sahara. The civilizations of the
Indus Valley flourished under moderate
rainfall in the margins of the present-day
Rajasthan and Thar deserts, created by
sudden desiccation nearly 4,000 years ago.
It is thus natural for societies that live
along the margin of the deserts to fear
that these encroachments will continue.
"Desertification" is a shocking and visible
reality for many of the peoples of North
and East Africa, as it is for many countries
in southern Asia and the tropical Americas.
A recent survey in the Sudan suggests
that the southern edge of the Sahara
moved southwards almost 200 kilometres
between 1958 and 1975 not by remorse¬
less expansion across fertile lands, but by
the patchy deterioration of the marginal
areas until, in effect, they joined the desert
to the north.
Are these changes due to a harshening
of world climate? Can we expect them to
continue? Is there something we can do
to stabilize matters? Or is the process too
powerful and overriding?
To the first question we can return a
reasonably confident "no". There is no
evidence of a lasting deterioration of cli¬
mate. The Sahelian drought of 1968-1973
has given way to moderate or generous k
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
í iT5TTTT
rainfall in the past three years, in most of
the affected areas.
The severe drought of 1972 in the Aus¬
tralian interior (which was the culmination
of a long phase of desiccation) has been
followed by several years of excessive
rainfall. We can point to no area of the
world where desiccation of the desert
margin has continued through the whole
period of record.
Variability is characteristic of rainfall in
such climates. In a given rainy season,
the distribution of rainstorms is patchy,
erratic and unpredictable, so that wide
differences of available moisture occur
within each year.
Differences of relief accentuate this
effect by concentrating run-off water into
basins, while the nearby slopes gain little
stored moisture. Large differences occur
between successive years. In many regions
several dry years follow in succession.
"Drought" in the semi-arid lands is often
taken to mean such prolonged rainfall
failures.
Natural ecosystems "remember" such
phenomena, and are well adapted to
them. Each plant and animal species has
a specific genetic specialization that per¬
mits it to tolerate the stress normal to
such climates.
Pastoral nomadism was and is (where
it survives) a reasonable adaptation to
such a climate, because it permitted flocks
and herds to be driven to where the rains
were most abundant, and grazing good.
In the Sahel, where such systems had
long historic experience to sustain them,
it was possible to avoid both the hazards
of drought-induced failures of forage and
exposure to tsetse flies in the moister
woodlands to the south. Fulani and Tua¬
reg alike survived countless droughts.
But today, with partial stabilization of
the herds, with an extension of temporary .
cultivation into semi-arid environments, f
Ancient
splendours
under
the sand
Great monuments of some of the world's most famous
civilizations are now half-covered by the sand. These remains
attest to the extraordinary prosperity of many regions that
have since been turned into deserts. As countless cave
paintings prove, the Sahara once boasted towns built near
immense lakes where crocodiles and hippopotami sported.
The civilization of the Indus flourished in part of what is now
the Thur desert in Pakistan, while other great cultures
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Michel Andrault. París
flW'fflUffl
«.
developed in those regions now invaded by the deserts of
Central Asia. In the Syrian desert, the Palmyra oasis (above)
was the seat of a prestigious kingdom dating back to the
3rd century A.D. In the arid mountains of Afghanistan, the
minaret of Jam (right) stands as a solitary memorial.
In the Sudan (below right) numerous remains recall the Meroe
kingdom some 2,000 years ago. Sand is destroying such
places as Al-Mukha (below), in the Arab Republic of Yemen.
__
Photo © Paul Almasy, Paris
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Nothing but
an illusion...
The mirage is a typical desert
phenomenon: an inverted
image of far-off objects, it
looks like a stretch of water
situated between the object
and the on-looker. Mirages
appear over uniform surfaces
without vegetation that have
been heated by the sun. itf
LÏ
, and with increasing human population, the
system has lost this resilience. Overpas-
turing or overcultivation has strained the
vegetation and soil to the point where
prolonged drought has brought disaster.
In the Sahel itself, regional rainfall had
been declining since 1955 or 1960. The
drought of 1968-1973 (see Unesco Courier,
April 1975) was the culmination of a pro¬
longed, gradual deterioration. It raised
the spectre of permanent destruction of
productive land, of almost mortal damage
to the economies of several countries.
It is quite possible, moreover, that the
intensity of this prolonged episode was
increased by human misuse of the land.
This works in two ways. The first, and
most obvious, is that the destruction of
perennial vegetation, or removal of fine
materials and humus from soils, them¬
selves contribute to a harsher microclimate.
As drought increases, these effects are
brought about by the treading, browsing
and grazing of desperate animals, espe¬
cially near watering places, or by the
abandonment of arable land. Such pack¬
ed, denuded surfaces become hotter,
more reflective and less water-retentive.
Sudden showers may flow rapidly off
them. Windstorms will remove fine mate¬
rials. These are effects that will outlive
the drought itself, and will hinder the re-
establishment of fertility and productivity.
The second effect is more insidious, and
is not obvious to the local inhabitants. It
arises from the increased reflectivity of the
denuded surfaces, their "albedo", as the
climatologists say. It has been established
by infrared photography from satellites
that the high albedo of the Sahara, the
Arabian peninsula and much of the arid
Middle East causes this area of the atmo¬
sphere to be cooled even in mid-summer.
The fear is that the rise in albedo caused
by the destruction of vegetation in desert
margin areas such as the Sahel will cause
an increase in subsidence over these
regions with a still further intensification
of droughta positive feedback whereby
drought leads to intensified drought.
It is also possible that the widespread
loss of organic litter that accompanies
such events lessens the opportunity for
rain showers to fall from cloud systems
(which need "seeding" particles to bring
the rain down). It is hence conceivable
that the prolonged and severe character
of the Sahelian drought owed much to
the destruction of vegetation and soils by
the desperate efforts at survival made by
those involved in the calamity.
There is no easy way out of these
problems, and no simple, palatable advice
that a climatologist can offer. All the evi¬
dence points towards a recurrence of
severe and prolonged drought along most
desert margins at some date that we can¬
not now predict.
In Sahelian Africa such events have typi¬
cally occurred every two or three decades,
though not with enough regularity to
allow prediction. The decreasing phase of
rainfall often lasts a decade or more, so
that the culminating drought, when it
comes, attacks already enfeebled eco¬
systems and human societies.
Moreover, the 1970s have brought un¬
usually large extremes to many regions of
the world, for reasons at present undis¬
covered. Hence it is prudent to assume,
for strategic purposes, that in the next
few years droughts of unusual severity
may occur in the semi-arid world, and that
the desertification hazard is hence likely
to be high. Strategies for such hazards
should be articulated by the world com¬
munity; they will certainly be needed.
Control of land useessentially stabili¬
zation of a continuing, perennial vegetation
cover by careful control of stocking and
rainfed cultivation is the only direct mea¬
sure that can be advocated. The planned
green belts along the northern and south¬
ern flanks of the Sahara may achieve these
gains, even though they have little appar¬
ent effect on the large-scale climate (which
is governed by worldwide processes).
Drought cannot be avoided; but its effects
can be mitigated by good land manage¬
ment.
Rainfall enhancement experiments, now
planned or in progress in several parts of
the arid zone, should certainly be pressed
forward, but they are unlikely to produce
major changes of drought incidence.
Indeed their main effects may be to in¬
crease rainfall in already rainy years.
Large-scale flooding of desert basins and
irrigation of large areas are also likely to
produce only minor local effects on
climate.
There is some hope, finally, of a measure
of prediction of rainfall anomalies in these
areas. Recent research has demonstra¬
ted the existence of numerous teleconnec-
tions between arid zone rainfall and events
in distant places, notably sea temperature
anomalies. Some of these teleconnec-
tions have time-lags of two or three
months, which makes some foreshadowing
possible if one monitors the control areas
adequately (as is now possible with satel¬
lite technology). "
But for the moment the climatologist
must warn that droughts are recurrent,
prolonged and unavoidable aspects of
desert margin climates. Only rational,
wise use of the land and its resources can
avoid the calamity of desertification in the
wake of such drought. This may be poli¬
tically and economically a herculean
challenge, confronting countries that are
for the most part poor and ill-equipped to
accept it. Yet there is no real alternative;
and the challenge is really addressed to
the entire world community.
F. Kenneth Hare
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Photo Emile Schultess, Bern © Rapho, París
WORLD TRENDS IN ARIDIFICATION
A precarious
balance upset
by Victor A. Kovda
VICTOR ABRAMOVITCH KOVDA, eminent Soviet
soil scientist directed Unesco's Department of Natural
Sciences from 1958 to 1965. Initiator and head of the
joint FAO-Unesco project for a soil map of the world
11960-1965), he has worked as an expert in a large
number of Asian, African and South American coun¬
tries. This specially written article is based on his
book "Aridity and the Fight Against Droughts", ori¬
ginally produced at the request of the United filetions
Environment Programme.
THE age of anarchic economic activity
which once characterized a portion
of the globe is drawing to a close.
The curtain is rising on an era of rational
and controlled use of the resources and
mechanisms of the biosphere.
Aridification probably begins as a result
of deforestation, increasing surface run¬
off, a deepening level of groundwater and
a deterioration of grassland, while tern- k
perature and rainfall remain normal. Y
Atlas of aridity
On this map, compiled for the United Nations Conference on
Desertification, to be held this year, the various regions of the
world are divided into 14 categories according to their degree of
aridity or humidity.
1) Stable humidity, droughts unlikely. 2) Droughts very rare
(incidence: 5%). 3) Droughts rare (incidence: 5 to 10%).
4) Relatively frequent droughts (incidence: 10 to 25%). 5) Frequent
droughts (25 to 30%). 6) Highly frequent droughts (30 to 50%).
7) Exceedingly frequent droughts (50 to 75%). 8) Continuous
droughts (75 to 95%). 9) Absolute droughts (incidence: about
100%). 10) Semi-bound drift desert, dune sand. 11) Surface
latérite crusts denuded by erosion with almost no vegetation.
12) Arctic deserts. 13) Mountain chains, thin forests, shrubland and
savannas with over 50% drought incidence. 14) Mountain deserts
and semi-deserts with almost absolute drought.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Human activity may accelerate this pro¬
cess. Drainage of groundwater, erosion,
dust storms, the destruction of vegetation,
dehumidification of the soil and drifting
sand all contribute to the desiccation and
degradation of land and intensify deserti¬
fication.
Today, as in the past, man can obtain
food from arid lands if he exploits them
cautiously and sensibly as grazing land or
by means of dry or irrigation farming. But
the present productivity of arid and sub-
arid lands quite obviously fails to meet
human requirements.
The natural tendency observed in recent
years towards aridification and cyclical
climatic changes, coupled with the conse¬
quences of human error, has aggravated
the generally unfavourable state of world
agriculture.
Several years of severe drought in Afri¬
ca (from Ethiopia to Upper Volta, Mauri¬
tania and Senegal), in Asia (notably India),
in a number of South American countries
and in the plains of Eastern Europe and
North America have been followed by
belated downpours, which were of little
benefit to agriculture and caused flooding
and erosion. Moreover, droughts seem
to return with identical or even greater
intensity in one- to three-year cycles, as
has been observed in Eastern Europe,
India and Africa.
In many countries, such unstable clima¬
tic conditions create highly acute food,
fodder, water and fuel problems. Pastures
and farmland suffer from overuse, exhaus¬
tion and erosion. Marginal arid and semi-
arid tracts acquire the appearance of
desertland, while the desert itself begins
its encroachment or quickens its rate of
advance.
Desertification is accompanied by a
rapid drop in the productivity of semi-arid
and sub-humid zones. Destruction of the
ecological balance leads to profound
changes in the vegetation cover and in
the variety and quantity of animal life and
particularly to destruction of the
soil. In the past, this happened as a result
of overgrazing of pastures and primitive
husbandry. Today, the process is aggra¬
vated by the extensive and disorderly
introduction of heavy vehicles and ma¬
chinery and by mining operations.
Primitive methods of farming, based on
fallowing and the one-crop system, cou¬
pled with the age-old practice of excessive
pasturing, is the main cause of declining
fertility and desertification.
This is especially true of Africa. Land
along the southern border of the Sahara
is turning into desert at an estimated rate
of over 100,000 hectares annually. Each
year the border of the Sahara shifts sever¬
al kilometres further south.
Many believe the deserts of the Middle
East and the Mediterranean region to be
man-made. Two or three thousand years
ago, the mountain-slopes and plains of
Lebanon, Syria, the Egyptian seaboard
and Tunisia were covered with rich vege¬
tation (including the celebrated cedars of
Lebanon), and provided ancient Rome
with ample supplies of timber, grain, ol¬
ives, wine and other produce. Tree-felling,
the destruction of forests and herbaceous
vegetation and the trampling of pastures,
together with erosion by wind and water,
have transformed these territories into
semi-deserts and deserts.
Arab scientists point out that the natu¬
ral environment of Arabia and North Africa
has been almost completely replaced by
man-made landscapesas a result of a
long history of uncontrolled nomadic pas¬
turing and the complete deforestation of
sandy land, loamy plains, hills and moun¬
tain-sides alike, intensified during the 19th
and 20th centuries with the arrival of colo¬
nialists, traders and industrialists.
Desertification has reached alarming
proportions in the Sudan, where the
savanna is advancing on the forest, the
steppe is advancing on the savanna and
the desert is advancing on the steppe.
The borderline between the zone of vege¬
tation and the desert south of Khartoum
has shifted between 90 and 180 kilometres
during the past 20 to 50 years, at an ave¬
rage rate of 5 kilometres each year.
The famous gum arabic acacia planta¬
tions are disappearing from areas where
they once flourished. In the space of a
dozen years, groundnut and sesame crops
have fallen to a half or a quarter of the
previous yield. The picture is the same in
the dry-farming areas and grazing lands
of Algeria, Tunisia and Morocco.
The governments of the independent
African states are endeavouring to draw
up and implement vast projects to check
the spread of desertland, involving the
binding of drift sand, protective afforesta¬
tion, plant improvement and the rotation
of pastures, irrigation and other measures.
In fact, it was the Arab countries and
those of the Sahel region which promoted
the special United Nations programme to
combat the desertification of the planet.
Most of the Sonora desert in Arizona
and virtually all the desert of New Mexico
owe their existence to several hundred
years of overgrazing. The vast arid fracts
of Central Asia were once covered not
only with grass, but also with trees and
shrubs.
Man destroyed the vegetation of arid
and semi-arid areas by using it not only
to feed his livestock but also to meet his
own requirements in fuel, shelter, medi¬
cine and food. The worst damage was
done in years of drought and famine.
When the rains came, they washed over
the denuded surface, carrying away the
humus, without penetrating into the
ground. The result was further desicca¬
tion and an aggravation of its consequen¬
ces. The deforestation of hills and moun¬
tain-sides led to the disappearance of
streams and brooks, with a corresponding
drop in the groundwater level in the plains.
The nomadic way of life and nomadic
livestock raising have existed for three or
four thousand years. The total popula¬
tion of domesticated animals has now L
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Oases under siege
Like islands floating in the desert,
these oases in the Souf, in the
Algerian Sahara, must be
constantly defended against the
invasion of sand drifts. Palisades
made of palm fronds hold back the
. drifts and protect the often very deep
craters where the date palms grow.
In the Sahara, oases are home to
two-thirds of the population.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
grown to some 3,000 million head, almost
half of which are found in the world's arid
zones. In North Africa alone, there are
almost 30 million head of cattle, and in
Australia nearly 50 million.
Yet ecologists point out that semi-
deserts and dry steppelands are highly
"fragile" and unstable. Sandy pasture-
land can be transformed into moving
dunes in the space of two or three years,
whereas the restoration of vegetation and
stabilization of the shifting sands require
as much as 15 or 20 years or longer.
The loss of vegetation cover and humus
intensifies the process of aridification.
Larger areas of soil are exposed to sunlight,
the surface temperature rises by 18-25°C,
soil humidity declines and the albedo (the
amount of radiation reflected by a surface)
is doubled or trebled, approaching that of
deserts (40-50 per cent).
All these considerations indicate that
the increasing frequency of drought con¬
ditions, and crop failures, the loss of
vegetation and the destruction of soil over
large areas are interrelated, that they are
linked with the general trend towards
aridification and that they are aggravated
by thoughtless and misguided human
activity.
The intensity and regularity of droughts
during recent years (albeit with some fluc¬
tuations) have turned the semi-arid and
sub-humid zones of Africa, Asia and
America into what look like semi-deserts
and deserts. The danger of desertification
has increased.
World food demand has rocketed, toge¬
ther with the price of foodstuffs. At the
same time, the known world reserves of
food and livestock fodder fell in 1973-1974
from their previous level of 40-80 million
tons to 30 million tons.
What makes matters worse, as noted
by the Soviet scientists A.V. Shnitnikov
in his study of the world's rhythmic chan¬
ges of climate, is that the 20th century
falls basically into a prolonged period of
desiccation. Hence the conclusion that
droughts are an increasing probability in
the immediate future, and that both crop
farming and livestock raising must be
organized to meet the possible conse¬
quences.
Specialists who have studied climate,
weather and yields of crop and animal
farming conclude that it is at present
impossible to predict how soon and in
what direction this unfavourable situation
will change. But the general opinion is
that it may be expected to continue for
some time, perhaps for 10 or 20 years,
and perhaps even for a century or two.
At all events, most climatic forecasts, at
least until 1985, are pessimistic.
Victor A. Kovda
Advancing deserts are a danger
that can also threaten
developed countries. In certain
regions of the United States,
desertification processes were
set in motion by man, that is,
by overgrazing and by
ploughing techniques
ill-adapted to fragile soils. In
these areas, droughts brought
on disastrous situations. One
of the most famous, that
struck the centre and south of
the country between 1934-1936,
created an exodus that was
immortalized in The Grapes of
Wrath. As this photo taken in
Texas in 1934 shows, erosion
and dust storms were such that
everything was half-buried in
the sand.
THE SANDS
OF WRATH
America's Dust Bowl
in retrospect
by Harold E. Dregne
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
OF all the lessons that have been
learned from desertification in the
United States, probably the most
significant is this: land productivity is easy
to destroy but difficult to restore.
Arid lands have fragile ecosystems with
low resilience after disturbance. Exploita¬
tion during a drought at the level accepta¬
ble during a wet spell can prove disastrous
to plants, soil and people. And overgraz¬
ing during good times weakens plants and
makes them more vulnerable when a
drought comes. Good land stewardship
must be practised continually.
This lack of resilience, this inability to
recover, in arid lands makes it essential
that signs of desertification be recognized
before it is too late. Now we can do this,
and so it is much easier to identify poten¬
tial problem areas while there is still time
to control them.
HAROLD ERNEST DREGNE, American soil special¬
ist, is an expert in arid zones, and particularly in plant-
water-soil relationships and the effects of salinity.
Chairman of the department of agronomy at Texas
Technological University since 1969, he was director
of the International Centre for Arid and Semi-aridLand
Studies in 1976. He is also the chairman of the Advi¬
sory Committee on Desertification of the American
Association for the Advancement of Science and edit¬
ed "Arid Lands in Transition".
In the United States, there have been
three instances of widespread desertifica¬
tion over the past century. The most
recent of all was wind erosion in the semi-
arid southern Great Plains during the long
drought of the 1930s. The situation was
worst of all in what came to be known as
the Dust Bowl.
The Dust Bowl covered parts of five
states: Colorado, Kansas, New Mexico,
Oklahoma and Texas. Wind erosion
damage was so great that a mass aban¬
donment of farms and an exodus of fami¬
lies resulted. This was the basis for John
Steinbeck's novel. The Grapes of Wrath,
which described the migration of the
"Okies" from Oklahoma to California.
Most of the scars of the Dust Bowl
have been healed during the intervening
years. However, the threat of a repetition
of the disaster is present again, now that
pressure is on to expand food production
into marginal areas to meet world needs.
The experience of the United States could
well be relevant elsewhere.
Dryland farming was introduced into
the western (and drier) Great Plains in the
late 1800s. Settlers had no previous expe¬
rience in coping with the vagaries of an
arid climate.
They often believed that the high rain¬
fall of the 1870s was either the normal
condition (despite the evidences of aridity
all around them) or that "rain followed
the plough", meaning that cultivation
induced increased rainfall. Yields during
the wet years encouraged an optimistic
view of the future.
But then the inevitable drought return¬
ed in the 1880s and a wholesale flight from-
the region occurred. A second major re¬
treat took place in the early 1920s, 12 years
before the Dust Bowl days began.
A stark picture of the Dust Bowl was
given in a report of the U.S. Soil Conser¬
vation Service set up in 1934. A year
later, a survey of the area was made and
Arthur H. Joel described what it found:
"The conditions around innumerable
farmsteads are pathetic. A common farm
scene is one with high drifts filling yards,
banked high against buildings, and partly
or wholly covering farm machinery, wood
piles, tanks and troughs.
"In the fields nearby may be seen the
stretches of hard, bare, unproductive sub¬
soil and sand drifts piled along fence rows,
across farm fields and around Russian
thistle and other plants. The effects of
the black blizzards are generally similar to k
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
( those of snow blizzards. The scenes are
dismal to the passerby; to the resident
they are demoralizing."
Black blizzards were the massive, dark
dust storms that blotted out the sun and
turned day into night. Livestock died
from starvation and from eating excessive
amounts of sand, a notable increase in
human illness was attributed to the dust-
laden air, machinery was ruined, cars
damaged and roads became impassable.
Erosion was so great that a dust pall
spread over the humid eastern United
States and out over the Atlantic Ocean
3,000 kilometres awayafter major wind
storms in the Great Plains.
Less than twenty years after the
terrible droughts of 1934-1936,
another hit the same regions of the
United States in 1952-1953. This
photo, taken in Texas in April 1953,
shows that damage was
considerable but soil conservation
measures taken after 1934 this time
prevented a major catastrophe.
The Soil Conservation Service report
prophesied what would happen if correc¬
tive steps were not taken before deserti¬
fication got out of hand. In a section on
adjustment measures, which meant return¬
ing cultivated land to grassland, it spoke
of personal sacrifices. Many people would
have to move away, some businesses
would fail, tax revenues would decrease
and there would be losses on land
investments.
Harsh though this adjustment would be
for some, delaying it would invite a more
complex and costly adjustment in the
future.
Despite predictions that much of the
land was ruined forever, crop yields gener¬
ally returned to normal when the rains
began again. Some areas, however, have
never recovered even though cultivation
ceased.
The second case of widespread deserti¬
fication in the United States began with
the settlement in earnest of the arid west
during the second half of the 19th centu¬
ry. A rapid increase in cattle and sheep
led to heavy grazing pressure on what
seemed to be endless grassland.
Within a few decades, undesirable
shrubs were replacing grass near watering
points where livestock were concentrated.
As overgrazing went on, much of the
remaining grassland went the same way.
By the beginning of the 20th century,
desertification had left its mark on virtually
all of the arid rangelands. Deterioration
of plant cover led to a speed-up of wind
and water erosion and the appearance of
man-made gullies and sand dunes.
Increases in shrub density, and shrub
expansion into grasslands following selec¬
tive grazing of grasses by livestock and
recurring drought, had their most marked
impact on the hot Southwest.
There, creosote bush (Larrea divaricata)
and mesquite (Prosopis spp.) were the
principal invaders. In the worst cases,
areas between the bushes have been
eroded by the wind down to hard, barren
subsoils and are referred to as "blow¬
outs".
Natural re-establishment of a grass
cover is very difficult under such circum¬
stances, even if further grazing is totally
excluded, simply because few plants and
seeds remain and much of the topsoil is
gone.
Awareness of the desertification problem
in desert grasslands became general in the
1910s and 1920s. Since then, research on
range management has developed tech¬
niques of rotational and deferred grazing,
reseeding, determining optimal stocking
rates, location of watering points, and
brush control that have, when properly
applied, improved livestock production.
However, progress has been slow,
especially in the hot desert regions. The
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
magnitude of the problem can be seen in
the lack of improvement of a creosote
bush-infested test plot in southern New
Mexico when little or no grazing was per¬
mitted. After 20 years, there was little
difference between the protected plot and
an adjoining unprotected one. Such re¬
sults point up the weakness of relying
upon total exclusion of livestock to bring
about rapid improvement of overgrazed
land.
The third instance of desertification is
associated with irrigation. Waterlogging
and salinization began to affect large areas
shortly after a rapid expansion of irrigation
began in the arid west at the end of the
19th century and in the first part of the
20th.
As a consequence of the lack of know¬
ledge of the hazards posed by irrigation,
salty and poorly drained soils were irri¬
gated because they occupied low-lying,
level areas that were easy to water. Water
tables rose when excessive irrigation water
was applied.
The most pervasive problem is the in¬
crease in soil salinity sometimes slowly,
sometimes more rapidly that threatens
many thousands of hectares of irrigated
land. The Imperial Valley of southern Cali¬
fornia is a case in point.
There, where over 250,000 hectares are
irrigated with water from the Colorado
River, increasing salinity of the river water
and difficulty in draining the fine-textured
soils has made it necessary to install ever
more costly drainage systems.
As more dams are built, evaporation
losses rise, and so does the salinity level.
Even the simple act of irrigating more land
serves to raise the salinity of the river in its
lower reaches, due to the reduced volume
of flow in the main channel and the great¬
er salinity of the drainage water when it
returns to the river.
The rise in the salinity level of the river
has aggravated the salt problem in the
Imperial Valley, and the problem will be¬
come steadily worse as more dams are
constructed and more water divertedfor
various purposes in the upper Colorado
River Basin.
As with overgrazing, salinization is a
greater problem in the hot deserts of the
West than in the cool deserts. Unlike
the grazing lands, there are no large areas
of irreversibly desertified salty lands at
present. However, the struggle to prevent
a disastrous buildup of salt in the soil is
never-ending where irrigation is practised.
With continued expansion of irrigation
from a limited number of rivers, water
potentially available tor any one hectare
declines at the same time that the need for
extra leaching water rises. The technol¬
ogy for controlling salinization is available;
it remains to be seen whether it will be
used effectively. Political decisions and
economics will decide.
H.E. Dregne
Imperial Valley in southern
California (below, an onion field in
flower) was reclaimed for farming
thanks to irrigation water from the
Colorado River. Excessive irrigation,
on the other hand, can raise the
salinity level, which harms crops and
which must in turn be combatted.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
a*;
A WINNING BATTLE
AGAINST
DESTRUCTION
Desert science is turning
the steppes
of Central Asia green
by Agadjhan G. Babaev
and Nikolai S. Orlovsky
»
4% V
Wir.
'&Mw
THE desert and semi-desert regions of
the Soviet Union cover some 2 1/2
million square kilometres, mainly in
Central Asia and southern Kazakhstan.
This broad swathe of inhospitable land,
which measures 1,200 kilometres from
north to south and 2,500 kilometres from
east to west, is subject to a great variety
of natural conditions and is, in fact, a
source of considerable wealth.
Although the surface under irrigation
(some 7 million hectares) accounts for
only 3 per cent of all the cultivated land of
the U.S.S.R., and 61 per cent of its irri¬
gated land, it nevertheless produces the
Soviet Union's entire crop of cottonseed
oil, one-third of its natural fibres (including
all its cotton and hemp), 76 per cent of its
raw silk and more than 23 per cent of its
vegetable oil. A further 20 million hec¬
tares set aside for irrigation constitute an
impressive reserve for future food produc¬
tion.
In addition, the grazing lands of the
desert nourish the karakul sheep which
provide the country's entire output of
astrakhan, as well as flocks which pro¬
duce one-third of its mutton and 16 per
cent of its wool.
AGADJHAN GELDIEVITCH BABAEV is a Soviet
specialist in desert studies. A corresponding member
of the U. S. S. R. Academy of Sciences and President
of the Turkmen S.S.R. Academy of Sciences, he
directed the Turkmen Desert Institute from 1960 to
1975. An editor of the review "Desert Reclamation",
he is also the author of numerous works, including
one on the reclamation of oasis sands in Turkmenistan.
NIKOLAI SERGEIVITCH ORLOVSKY, Soviet clima¬
tologist and agrometeorologist, is Deputy Director of
the Desert Institute of the Turkmen S.S.R. Academy
of Sciences.
Photo © Yuri Trankvilitzki, Moscow
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
i¿*4
rV
iBi «*-.
In the arid and semi-arid zones of Central Asia, man has pitted himself against ihe desert for centuries. Today,
thanks to sand-stabilizing techniques, irrigation, soil reclamation and the creation of natural reserves, it is
possible to protect and even to extend farm and grazing land. These are now major crop-growing areas in the
U.S.S.R.. where cotton is especially important. Shown here sitting in front of a huge pile of cotton, these
farmers from a kolkhoz in Tadjikistan discuss plans for the next harvest.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
And this is not all. The desert also
yields 34 per cent of the Soviet Union's
natural gas, 13 per cent of its coal, 50
per cent of its sodium sulphate and one-
third of its phosphates, together with
quantities of potassium and sodium chlo¬
ride, barium sulphate and other minerals.
The desert once served as natural graz¬
ing land. Until 50 or 60 years ago, live¬
stock raising in our country was based on
the nomadic way of life. According to the
season, the herdsmen led their animals
over huge areas in search of the best
pastures, counting on favourable years
and never doubting that the desert would
continue to yield food for their flocks, and
demand almost nothing in return.
Today, all that has changed. Settlement
has replaced nomadism, and the pastures
are used on a regular basis.
Land degraded as a result of over-stock¬
ing or deforestation is withdrawn from
service for a period of two or three years,
to permit plant improvement and the re-
establishment of vegetation.
The exploitation of grassland in desert
areas takes account of all the possible
social, economic and ecological conse¬
quences, and the creation of new pastures
makes use of the experience handed
down from generation to generation of
nomad herdsmen, especially as far as the
provision of water is concerned. The old
tradition of collecting rainwater in clay-
lined trenches has been refined by modern
engineering techniques, and reliable me¬
thods of freshening mineralized water are
being developed.
If the ancient desert bred herdsmen, it
also bred specialists in irrigated agriculture
in the vicinity of natural springs, where
oases created the most favourable condi¬
tions for human settlement. Tashkent,
Ferghans, Samarkand, Bukhara, Khorezm,
and other oases, are strung like huge
pearls along shallow rivers, and cover
immense areas.
During the past 30 or 40 years, irrigated
farming has undergone tremendous, care¬
fully-planned development, as may be seen
from the following two examples.
The Golodnaya step (literally, . "The
Barren Steppe") is an area of more than
one million hectares, situated on the
southern fringe of the Kyzylkum Desert.
Irrigation was begun as long ago as 1908,
but due to the limited natural permeabi¬
lity of the soil and the generally low level
of technology and agricultural know-how
at the time, the irrigated lands rapidly be¬
came salt-ridden. It took several decades
before the initial irrigation systems were
perfected and new systems introduced,
and before closed horizontal and vertical
drains offered protection against salting.
The Golodnaya project fully justified a
"comprehensive" approach to desert re¬
clamation, involving the creation of a
construction industry capable of produc¬
ing not only hydrotechnical installations
but also factories, housing and public
buildings.
Today, the steppe remains barren only
in name. Railways and highways, water-
and gas-pipelines and electric grids criss¬
cross the territory between scores of cot
ton farms, poultry stations, market gardens
and vineyards. Where their grandfathers
saw only a desert, today's children look
out on a rich and fertile land, the centre
of the country's most important cotton-
producing area, which annually yields as
much as 500,000 tons of raw cotton, toge¬
ther with a considerable amount of other
agricultural produce.
The Karakum Canal is the world's long¬
est man-made waterway. Already mea¬
suring a thousand kilometres from end to
end, it will be 1,400 kilometres long when
complete. Linking the Amu-Darya (the
ancient river Oxus), with the Caspian Sea,
the canal has a triple function.
Firstly, it is the key to the world's
largest desert irrigation project. Some
300,000 hectares on its banks already
produce almost half of the Turkmen
S.S.R.'s crop of high-quality cotton, and
its water will eventually irrigate more than
a million hectares. Secondly, the Kara¬
kum is a ship-carrying canal. And finally,
its waters contain a thriving population of
fish, which not only keep the canal
clear of weeds, but also delight Turkmen
gourmets!
Many other irrigation canals, driven into
the very heart of the desert and watering
what were hitherto sparsely vegetated and
arid grazing lands, have changed the face
of Central Asia.
Man himself is moving deeper into the
desert, attracted by its newly-discovered
industrial potential. Factories are spring¬
ing up in the vicinity of mineral deposits.
But man and industry alike require fresh
water. One of the U. S.S.R.'s first pipe¬
lines to carry water across the desert was
the Yaskhansky pipeline, serving Nebit-
Dag, Cheieken and other towns in west¬
ern Turkmenistan. The construction of a
complex network of pipelines on the
Mangyshlak Peninsula has made it possi¬
ble to build huge industrial centres in the
desert, including the copper works at
Dzhezkazgan (Kazakhstan), the oil ins¬
tallations at Nebit-Dag and Cheieken
(Turkmenistan) and the gold-mines at
Zeravshan (Uzbek S.S.R.), and to supply
the industrial chemists and electrical engi¬
neers of Navoi, in the same Republic, with
all the water they need.
Desalinated sea water is used to meet
industrial and human requirements in
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Combatting aridity in Central Asia
In desert reclamation, top priority is given to stopping sand drifts and
finding water. To do this, special instruments are brought in to study
the formation of sand hills (at left and below). Such major undertakings
as the Karakum Canal (above) in Turkmenistan are today bringing
water to Soviet Central Asia. When it is completed, the canal will
run from Amu-Darya to the Caspian Sea, covering a distance of
1,400 kilometres.
desert areas which have no access to
natural fresh water.
Shevchenko is the only Soviet city^and
one of the few cities in the worldto be
entirely served in this way. Here, the
world's first nuclear-powered desalination
plant produces 120,000 cubic metres of
water every 24 hours, distributed econom¬
ically through three pipelines.
The first carries drinking water, the
second partially purified water for indus¬
trial and domestic use and for watering
the city's parks and gardens, and the
third, sea water for use by the municipal
authorities for street-cleaning and other
similar purposes. The 80,000 inhabitants
of Shevchenko are allotted as much water
as those of any major Soviet city, such as
Moscow, Leningrad or Kiev, and each
citizen enjoys almost 10 square metres of
green space, planted with trees.
Only 40 years ago, Nebit-Dag, rn the
Turkmen S.S.R., was little more than a
halt on the Central Asian railway. Not a
blade of grass, and not a drop of water
(its supply came in tanks from Krasno-
vodsk). Today, Nebit-Dag is one of the
largest and most modern cities of the
Republic, and the capital of the Turkmen
oil industry. Walking in its tree-lined
streets, the visitor forgets that a barren
plain lies all around the city, while its in¬
habitants rightly claim that they drink the
best-tasting water of any desert brought
from an underground lake at Yaskhansky,
120 kilometres further east.
Among other examples of the transfor¬
mation of the desert when water is piped
in, we may mention Bekdash, where
sulphate is extracted, and Khauzkhan, a
settlement created at the same time as a
huge reservoir, which was the first stage
in the creation of a modern paradox, the
"desert fishing industry".
the carefully planned and comprehen¬
sive approach, which mobilizes the latest
achievements of science and technology,
makes it possible to predict the processes
which lead to desertification, and to trans¬
form harsh desert conditions into a more
stable and favourable environment. Man
no longer flees the desert, but goes there
to live and workand not merely to work,
but also to relax and restore his health at
such well-known resorts as Bairam-Ali (for
its climate), Archman (for its waters) and
Molla-Kara (for its mud baths). In the
past 10 years, the population of the desert
regions of the U.S.S.R. has grown from
20.4 million to 40.4 million.
The modern battle with drifting sands
is waged on the basis of a careful study of
the mechanics of dune movement and
accumulation, of the ecology of sand-
binding vegetation and of the conditions
under which trees grow in the desert, etc.
During the past 25 years, 720,000 hectares
in the Karakum and Kyzylkum deserts
have been planted with trees and shrubs.
The shifting sands have been checked,
pastures have been improved and forest
belts have been created to protect crop
farming and animal husbandry.
The drifting of sand into oasis areas
creates great problems for the cotton
growers of Central Asia. In the Turkmen
S.S.R. alone, more than 500,000 hectares
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
i are threatened. But the latest experiments
at the Desert Institute of the Turkmen
Academy of Sciences have produced an
optimum technology for agriculture in
sandy areas, making it possible to pro¬
duce up to 900 quintals of green sorghum
(the locally-developed "Turkmen-I" varie¬
ty), and up to 600 quintals of maize per
hectare.
Hitherto unexploited land in the vicinity
of water supplies is being brought under
cultivation, thus liberating improved land
for more profitable crops, market gardens
and vineyards. At the same time, irriga¬
tion water is being used more sparingly,
costly sand-binding measures are no long¬
er necessary and there is no further danger
of salting.
Protective measures are an essential
part of the exploitation of the natural
resources of the desert. Eleven reserves,
covering a total area of 62,500 hectares,
have been created in the Central Asian
deserts for the preservation and study of
their ecosystems.
In the U.S.S.R., the protection of the
environment, including deserts, is in trie
hands of the State. Special nature con¬
servancy laws have been adopted by all
the republics of the Soviet Union.
Leopard-hunting is absolutely forbidden.
The hemione, a uniquely Central Asian
animal and the pride of the fauna of Turk¬
menistan, has been saved; more than a
thousand now live in the shelter of the
Badkhyz reserve, and several hundred
have been transferred to the island of
Barsakelms in the Aral Sea. The saiga
(a rare species of antelope) has been
brought back from the frontiers of extinc-'
tion, and its population now numbers two
million.
The many birds which winter in the
southern Caspian region have been pro¬
tected for a considerable time, and the
area of the Krasnovodsk bird sanctuary
has recently been extended, while the
Karakum Canal offers an additional win¬
tering-place. During particularly hard win¬
ters, the birds are fed from motorboats
and helicopters. Even venomous snakes
are now protected.
Conservation by no means implies let¬
ting the desert have all its own way. As
the scientists at the Repetek reserve have
shown, there are many occasions when
an over-zealous approach to conservation
can endanger, rather than safeguard, its
already meagre biological resources.
A careful approach, based on the infant
discipline of desert science, can transform
this harsh environment into one in which
man can live and work, and result in the
creation of well-watered fields and grazing-
lands, mining and manufacturing indus¬
tries, health centres, resorts and all the
facilities for tourism. As the 18th-century
Turkmen poet Seidi observed, "All land is
wretched, compared to this desert."
I Agadjhan G. Babaev and
Nikolai S. Orlovsky
Balanced development
Once considered useless for agriculture, this clay soil is now productive. When troughs are
dug (at top), enough rainwater is caught to irrigate the soil, and tall-stalked plants can
grow (lower photo). Nonetheless, only 20 per cent of such land should be set aside for
cultivation in Central Asia, according to the Soviet specialist Andrei G. Bannikov.
Vice-President of the International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural
Resources, Mr. Bannikov believes that priority should be given to grazing land, which
protects the natural ecosystem. "If the norms for cattle-raising are observed, it is possible
to let domestic and wild ungulates graze simultaneously." This does, in fact, help wild
fauna to develop: "The irrigation of deserts, and particularly the Karakum Canal and
reservoir, bring a considerable increase in fauna, and especially water fowl. Today, there
are from 600,000 to 800,000 ducks, geese, and so forth, that winter on the water basins that
man has created in the desert."
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
ONSLAUGHT
ON THE NILE
Shifting dunes threaten
Egypt's breadbasket
by Farouk El-Baz
FAROUK EL-BAZ taught geology at the universities
of Assiut (Egypt), Missouri (U.S.A.) and Heidelberg
(Fed. Rep. of Germany). Since 1973, he has been Re¬
search Director of the Centre for Earth and Planetary
Studies at the Smithsonian Institution in Washington,
D. C His work there entails analysis of the scientific
results of the Apollo flights and their application to
earth and planetary sciences. Among his numerous
geological publications, he is co-author of Nasa 's 'The
Moon as Viewed by Lunar Orbiter".
A composite view of
Egypt, made up of 60
photographs taken and
transmitted from a
"Landsat" in orbit 920
kilometres above Earth,
clearly shows the dark
band of fertile soil
bordering the Nile, as
well as the triangle of
the delta and the
Fayoum oasis. Two-
thirds of the photo shows
desert to the west of the
Nile. In the lower part
of the photo can be seen
broad parallel curves of
sand dunes.
WHEN we consider the dramatic
contrast between farmland and
desert in Egypt, we realize that
Egypt is truly "the gift of the Nile". This
mighty river meanders through the waste¬
land and brings life to a narrow strip of
land bordering its course.
If viewed from hundreds of miles above
the Earth, the Nile would look like a fragile
tree stem, barely supporting the branches
of the triangular-shaped delta. The Faiyum
Oasis, farmland reclaimed from the desert
by the ancient Egyptians, would look like
a solitary, heart-shaped leaf.
To portray the Nile and its farmland as
such a frail entity is particularly suitable
because of the imminent threat of shifting
sands from the Western (Libyan) Desert.
This great- expanse of dr/ wilderness
covers over 686,000 square kilometres or
more than two-thirds the area of Egypt.
It includes several oases enclosed in de¬
pressions.
The flat surface of this rocky desert is
crossed in many places by parallel belts of
sand dunes. The largest concentration of
these is known as the Great Sand Sea,
whose area of 140,000 square kilometres
is more than the combined total area of
Belgium, Denmark and the Netherlands.
Dune sand in the Western Desert is
migrating in a south-southeast direction,
with the prevailing winds from the north
and northwest. The migration is constant k
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Advancing dunes that threaten the Valley of the Nile are clearly visible in the
upper right-hand part of this aerial view, taken to the northwest of Assiut, about
half-way between Cairo and Aswan. A few protective hedges made of palm
fronds can be seen on the edge of the dunes; they help to slow down the
encroaching sands but are not sufficient to stop them.
and relentless since the dunes can easily
overwhelm both natural and man-made
objects in their way. These dunes are
large enough to be easily detected on
space photographs. The last group of
photographs of Egypt were taken by the
American astronauts of the Apollo-Soyuz
mission.
In one colour photograph taken of the
area just west of the Nile Delta, I recogniz¬
ed three zones that did not correspond to
mapped geological formations. To study
these zones, I travelled to the Western
Desert in the company of five geologists
from Ain Shams University in Cairo. In
the field it was realized that the three
zones corresponded to arable soil com¬
posed of sand, calcium carbonate and
clay particles; a sheet of active sand with
sparse vegetation; and a rocky desert sur¬
face covered with pebbles. The youngest
sands are in the form' of southward-
migrating linear dunes.
These dunes are 5 to 40 kilometres in
length and a few kilometres wide. When
we visited the southern tips of the dunes,
we noticed that .the main sand mass
breaks up into crescent-shaped dunelets,
each attaining a height of 3 to 20 metres.
One can stand near the tip of one of
these dunes and watch it migrate. Grain
24
by grain and layer by layer, the dune shifts
in the direction of the prevailing wind.
The motion is steady and generates a soft
hissing sound.
The paved road from Cairo to the iron
mines of Baharia Oasis is in the path of
several of these dunes. One dune has
reached the road and has begun crossing
it, intermittently closing it to traffic. Pa¬
rallel to this road is a railroad used for
hauling iron ore from the mines to the
smelter at Helwan, near Cairo. At the
dune crossing, it is common to observe
labourers sweeping sand away as the train
inches its way forward.
In the Baharia Depression itself, there
are numerous villages. One of these, El-
Harra Oasis, is presently being inundated
by sand. The shifting dunes continue to
claim fertile land despite the efforts of
local farmers to block the way of advanc¬
ing sand. The sand grains keep moving
with the wind until they meet an obstacle
around which they accumulate. ' This
obstacle can be just a thin, scrawny bush.
With all this tangible evidence of dune
migration, we felt that aerial and space
photographs taken at different times should
record this phenomenon. Back in the
laboratory, we compared photographs
taken during the past three decades. The
photographs indicated that one of the
dunes had shifted 5.7 kilometres over a
period of 22 years. This is an average of
260 metres per year.
Continuing the investigation by air, I
noticed that further south and closer to
the Nile, there is an earlier generation of
sand dunes. These are no longer of the
linear type but form a complex network of
crescent-shaped dunes. Here the sands
are moving toward' the farmland, inunda¬
ting the western boundary of the fertile
Nile Valley.
Encroachment of sand on fertile land in
Egypt is a dangerous process. Less than
4 per cent of the area of Egypt is fertile
land, the rest is a desert wasteland. Egypt
cannot afford to lose any small part of this
fragile strip of land to the desert. On the
contrary, the irrigated area of land must
be constantly increased to supply food to
a population which is increasing by one
million each year.
Farther to the. southwest, the Apollo-
Soyuz astronauts photographed numer¬
ous dunes whose sands were derived
from the Great Sand Sea. In the Oweinat
Mountain region at the borders of Egypt,
Libya and Sudan, the dunes streak be¬
tween dark circular mountains. Dune
migration in this case can be a threat to
CONTINUED PAGE 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A CASE STUDY
IN SURVIVAL
How animal life has adapted
to impossible desert conditions
by Claude Grenot and Roland Vernet
CLAUDE GRENOT, French research
scientist. Ecole Normale Supérieure In
Paris, specializes In desert fauna and
is the author of numerous articles on
ecology and the physiology of repti¬
les. Ha is a consultant for the Addax
Oryx project at the International Union
for Conservation of Nature and Natu¬
ral Resources at Morges, Switzerland.
ROLAND VERNET, French biology re¬
searcher. University of Paris, is a
specialist on Saharan ecology. He has
published numerous articles on ecolo¬
gy and the physiology of reptiles.
THE Sahara has not always been a
desert. It became one gradually
over a long period, which seems to
have begun in earnest some 8,000 years
ago, during the late Stone Age.
In prehistoric times, the Sahara was a
very different place. Long before the
Libyan horsemen and camel drivers
ancestors of the modern Berber nomads
its inhabitants were farmers, herdsmen
and fisherman, living beside lakes whose
only trace today is found in fossilized
remains.
From their chipped stone tools and the
engravings and paintings of their cave wall
art, we know that their settlements were
numerous and widespread throughout the
Saharan region.
Contrary "to what one might imagine,
the number of species of mammals found
in the Sahara today is relatively high,
amounting to 65 (including 24 which are
native to the region) as compared with
115 in France. "Genuinely" Saharan mam¬
mals include the majority of its rodents,
the fennec fox, the white gazelle and the
addax antelope.
As far as birds are concerned, 90 spe¬
cies are found in the Sahara, 18 of which
are native to the region and actually nest
there (the white-rumped black wheatear,
the bifasciated and other larks, the crow,
the trumpeter bullfinch, the desert warbler,
the houbara bustard, the courser and vari¬
ous grouse).
Spendidly adapted, the reptiles have
colonized all desert wastes. The authors
of this article have identified 32 species in k
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
, the northwestern Sahara (23 lizards and
9 snakes), seven of which are found in the
shifting sands of the great dunes. Twenty-
five of these 32 species are authentically
Saharan. Lizards are the last vertebrates
to survive the intensification of drought
conditions.
The smaller animals burrow under the
surface or hide in the vegetation to escape
from high temperatures and to avoid
dehydration. Shrubs, crevices, rock slides
and the burrows of lizards or rodents
create "microclimates", where tempera¬
tures are cooler than in the surrounding
area. A mere 20 cm. beneath the surface,
the temperature is virtually constant, with
only two or three degrees of variation
during a 24-hour period.
The arachnids, which include spiders
and scorpions, dig long, sloping galleries
into the ground, but some spiders bore
perfectly cylindrical and vertical holes,
sometimes to a depth of 40 cm., which
they line with silk.
Unlike the surface mounds of more
humid regions, the termite colonies and
ants' nests of the Sahara are complex
networks of underground galleries, linked
to the surface by a single opening which
is often virtually invisible. The drier the
surrounding environment, the deeper the
nest, and some species even provide their
nests with water by digging down to the
damper sand.
Most rodents choose their homes where
there is most respite from desert condi¬
tions, and burrow beneath shrubs and
plants, taking care not to destroy the
roots, which are a precious source of
moisture. They drive numerous galleries
to a depth where the temperature remains
below 35°C, and where the humidity is
highoften near to saturation-point. In
this way, they surround themselves with
an environment very similar to that of the
temperate regions.
Of the reptiles, the so-called medicinal
skink, one of a large group of semi-
burrowing lizards, actually "swims" like a
fish through the sand, and rapidly dives
to a considerable depth, thus escaping
not only from the heat of the surface but
also from its enemies, the desert monitor
and the sand viper.
The sand-viper behaves differently; in¬
stead of diving head-first, it remains appar¬
ently motionless on the surface and then
means of lateral undulations from
the tail towards the headslowly sinks
under the sand, in the manner of a sub¬
merging submarine.
While some creatures go underground
in search of cooler temperatures, others
seek respite above the surface. Many
insects, reptiles and birds (larks and war¬
blers) which are diurnal (mainly active by
day) spend the hottest hours perching in
bushes. During these periods there may
be as much as 20°C of difference between
the surface and air temperatures.
Changes of routine are common among
the desert animals, and are basically sea¬
sonal in nature. Some species (snakes)
are diurnal in the spring, become noctur¬
nal as summer advances, and return to a
diurnal existence in autumn. Many spe¬
cies are, however, entirely nocturnal.
Most Saharan animals do not have
regular feeding habits or diets. Conditions
may vary considerably for the same spe¬
cies during the course of the year, and
nowhere more spectacularly than in the
case of the herbivorous, or plant-eating,
creatures. Thus, the whiptailed lizard,
whose intake of plant matter during the
spring accounts for 40 per cent of its
weight, can survive lean periods on a diet
of dry wood, insects and gazelle-droppings.
Many Saharan invertebrates (scorpions,
ticks, etc.) have an astonishing resistance
to famine, and can live for months, or
even years, without food. Among the
vertebrates, the herbivorous reptiles hold
the record for fasting. The whiptailed
lizard can survive for almost a year with¬
out eating, at a temperature not exceed¬
ing 30°C, and can then regain in just over
a month the 40 per cent of its body weight
lost during the process.
Some desert creatures have long legs
which raise their bodies well above the hot
surface of the ground. Their feet are
often provided with tufts of hair or bristle
which, in the manner of snowshoes, facil¬
itate movement over soft sand.
The feet of many Saharan mammals,
including the rodents and hoofed animals
(ungulates) are broad-soled and hairy. The
gundi, which is a diurnal rodent, has
thickly padded feet which absorb the
shock as it leaps from rock to rock and
which to some extent insulate it from the
heat of the ground.
The addax antelope and the drome¬
daries have broad hooves which are out¬
standingly useful on soft surfaces. The
skink lizard's slender body and flattened
toes help it to burrow deep into the sand.
Creatures of the Sahara
Three typical examples of Saharan fauna
are, from left to right; the lanner, a falcon
that lives in the North African desert; the
skink, or "sand fish," which is in fact a
lizard but which gets its name from its
capacity to wriggle like a fish into the
sand; and, lastly, a gundi, a short-tailed
rodent that lives by day rather than by
night, like most of the Saharan rodents.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Crocodiles from lost rivers
It is now known that crocodiles lived in streams and rivers .'
that flowed through the Sahara in very ancient times. Proof
of their existence is provided by, among other things, prehistoric
paintings; shown here, an etching in sandstone found in
Nabater, in southern Libya. It is part of a group of prehistoric
works, some of them portraying mammoths, that dates back
from 7,000 to 15,000 years. The crocodile skull shown here is
much older; paleontologists estimate it is about 100 million years
old. As it measures 1.10 metres long, the crocodile itself was
about 6 to 7 metres long. It was found on the edge of the
Tademait plateau, in the northwestern part of the Sahara, where
forests and the mouth of a great river existed at that time.
Its smooth scales, similar to those of a
fish, reduce friction with the sand.
The most remarkable adaptations of
desert animals are physiological, and relate
to temperature regulation and water
balance.
Reptiles are "ectothermal" and can only
warm or cool their bodies by moving to a
warmer or cooler spot of their environ¬
ment. Thus, when the outside tempera¬
ture is cool, diurnal lizards place them¬
selves at right-angles to the sunlight and
swell up their bodies so that the greatest
possible surface is exposed to its warming
rays.
When their body temperature reaches
"normal" (about 40°C), they resume their
activities. In the late afternoon, they flat¬
ten themselves against the hot sand and
absorb by conduction à further store of
heat, which enables them to lengthen
their "working day".
The desert monitor and the whiptailed
lizard can survive for long periods with a
body temperature which could kill most
other vertebrates (42°C to 46°C). Lizards
exposed to extremely high temperatures
are often observed to pant in an effort to
reduce their body temperature.
The skin coloration of reptiles can chan¬
ge according to their temperature and the
amount of sunlight to which they are
exposed. Light colours, which reflect a
large amount of solar radiation, act as a
protective screen against the heat.
Most Saharan reptiles do not drink. The
moisture contained in their food is suffi¬
cient to compensate for losses through
evaporation. Under humid conditions,
their skin, which is normally waterproof,
can become porous, to permit hydration.
The urine of desert reptiles, like that of
insects, is a sludge, containing a large
quantity of uric acid crystals, with very
little water. Certain speciesthe masti-
gures, or Uromastyx lizardssecrete their
salt wastes by means of special glands
situated in the nasal cavity.
Desert rodents hardly drink at all, and
must economize as much water as possi¬
ble. During the night, they coUect dry
seeds from the surface and stock them in
their burrows, where the relative humidity
is close to saturation point. The water
vapour contained in their breath con¬
denses on the seeds and most of it is thus
reabsorbed when the rodents eat.
Having only a limited number of sweat
glands, they lose very little water through
perspiration. Their urine is highly concen¬
trated, and may contain up to two or
three times as much salt as sea-water.
The urea content may be as high as 24 per
cent (five times as much as in human
urine).
Large herbivorous mammals such as the
gazelle, the oryx, the addax antelope, the
dromedary, the ass and the sheep, are
unable to escape from high temperatures
like the rodents, by hiding underground.
The adaptation of the dromedary, the
famous "ship of the desert", is directly
linked to a number of anatomical and
physiological peculiarities. The thick
fleece covering its back acts as a screen
against solar radiation: an outer surface
temperature of 70°C is matched by a skin
temperature of only 40°C. The dromedary
wastes very little water; its many sweat
glands only function at temperatures
above 41 °C.
In contrast with most mammals, the
dromedary's body temperature is not
constant and may, like that of reptiles,
rise by 6°C during the summer, rang¬
ing from 34.5°C to 40.5°C in the course
of a single day. As the outside tempera¬
ture rises, it accumulates a stock of calo¬
ries which it releases by radiation in the
cool of the evening, without sweating.
On a diet of dry fodder, it can survive
without drinking for 30 to 40 days in
winter, but only for ten days or so in
summer.
The dorcas gazelle cannot modify its
body temperature like the dromedary, but
it can survive without drinking for 9 toi
12 days in winter and for 3 to 4 days in f
Photos © Claude Grenot, Paris
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
summer, with a . corresponding loss of
some 14 per cent to 20 per cent of its
body weight. Under such conditions, the
gazelle reduces the amount of urine ex¬
creted to a third or a quarter of the normal
quantity and doubles its concentration, at
the same time economizing water loss by
limiting its activities to the cooler hours of
the day. .
The addax antelope of the Sahara lives
on desert vegetation and does not drink.
Its stomach is full of a liquid which the
nomads drink after passing it through a
rough filter. Its urine is of limited quantity,
and highly concentrated.
All these ungulates, and the addax
in particular, have survived in the Sahara
until a very recent date, thanks to their
astonishing adaptation to desert condi¬
tions. It is certain, however, that human
intervention has accelerated the reduction
of their habitat which increasing aridity
had already begun.
A vast project for the preservation of
the addax, the oryx and similar species in
the Sahara and the Sahel has been launch¬
ed by the International Union for Conser¬
vation of Nature and Natural Resources
(IUCN), and detailed prospections have
already been carried out in Mauritania,
Sudan and Chad.
The white gazelle and the dorcas gazelle
are two other species which are doomed
to extinction within a relatively short space
of time unless steps are rapidly taken to
protect them.
In a period in which truly "natural"
environments are obviously shrinking, the
methodical study of the deserts has be¬
come a necessity.
Claude Grenot and
Roland Verriet
Deserts of Central Asia abound in a variety of fauna that are, generally speaking, highly
specialized, like these outsized lizards called varans (below, right). Rodents are numerous
and are preyed on by small wildcats (below, left). A number of ungulates, like the kiang,
the djeiran antelope and desert sheep (above) provide food for large carnivorous animals
like the leopard and the cheetah. "Natural reserves," according to the Soviet zoologist
Andrei G. Bannikov, "play an important role in the preservation of species... Their total
area now covers over 500,000 hectares in the deserts of Central Asia, and is growing yearly.
Thanks to these reserves and to appropriate legislation, a number of rare species of desert
fauna in the U.S.S.R. are not only being protected but are increasing ."
Photo © A.G. Bannikov, Moscow
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
If more and more regions
are exposed to the danger
of desertification, one of
the major causes can be
traced to deforestation;
and one of the principal
causes of deforestation is
the need for firewood. In
Latin America, for
example, the lack of wood
and charcoal constitutes a
serious problem in
many parts of the Andes,
in Central America and
the Caribbean. The
shortage is so acute that
villagers are obliged to
search ever further afield
to satisfy their needs.
THE POOR MAN'S
ENERGY CRISIS
Firewood, the only fuel available
to over a billion people,
is becoming alarmingly scarce
by Erik P. Eckholm
ERIK P. ECKHOLM, specialist on environment problems at the "WorldWatch Institute" in
Washington, D.C, is the author of Losing Ground (published by W. W. Norton & Co. inc..
New York, 1976) as well as numerous articles on desertification. His research has been fi¬
nanced by the United Nations Environment Programme.
FOR more than a third of the world's
people, the energy crisis means a
daily scramble to find the wood
they need to cook dinner. Their search
for wood, once a simple chore and now,
as forests recede, a day's labour in some
places, has been strangely neglected by
governments, economists and the press.
At least half of all the timber cut in
the world still fulfills its original role for
manas fuel for cooking and, in colder
mountain regions, a source of heat.
Nine-tenths of the people in most poor
countries today depend on firewood as
their chief fuel, and all too often, the
growth in human population is outpacing
the growth of new trees.
The resulting firewood scarcity is prob¬
ably most acute today in the densely
populated Indian subcontinent, and in the
semi-arid stretches of central Africa fring¬
ing the Sahara Desert, though it plagues '
many other regions as well. In Latin
America, for example, the scarcity of
wood and charcoal is a problem through¬
out most of the Andean region, Central l
America, and the Caribbean. f
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
As firewood prices rise, so does the
economic burden on the urban poor. One
typical morning on the outskirts of Kat¬
mandu, Nepal's capital city, I watched a
steady flow of people men and women,
children and the very oldtrudge into the
city with heavy, neatly chopped and
stacked loads of wood on their backs.
I asked my taxi driver how much their
loads, for which they had walked several
hours into the surrounding hills, would sell
for. "Oh wood, a very expensive item!"
he exclaimed without hesitation. Wood
prices are a primary topic of conversation
in Katmandu these days. "That load
cost 20 rupees now. Two years ago it
sold for six or seven rupees." Firewood
prices have risen even faster than kero¬
sene prices.
Firewood and charcoal prices are climb¬
ing throughout most of Asia, Africa, and
Latin America. In Niamey, Niger, deep in
the drought-plagued Sahel in West Africa,
the average manual labourer's family is
now spending nearly one-fourth of its
income on firewood. In Ouagadougou,
Upper Volta, the portion approaches 30
per cent.
Those who can't pay so much may hike
out into the surrounding countryside to
forage if enough trees are within a rea¬
sonable walking distance. Otherwise,
they may scrounge about for twigs, gar¬
bage or anything that can be burned.
When I visited the Chief Conservator of
Forests in Pakistan's North West Frontier
Province, officed in the town of Pesha¬
war, he spoke in a somewhat resigned
tone of stopping his car the previous day
to prevent a woman from pulling bark off
a tree. "I told her that peeling the bark
off a tree is just like peeling the skin off a
man", he said.
Of course the woman stopped, intimi¬
dated by what may be the most personal
encounter with such a senior civil servant
she will have in her lifetime, but she
doubtless resumed her practice shortly,
for what else, as the Chief Conservator
himself asked, was she to do?
It is not in cities but in rural villages that
most people in the affected countries live,
and where most firewood is burned. The
rural, landless poor in parts of India and
Pakistan now face a new squeeze on their
meagre incomes.
In the past they have generally been
able to gather wood for free among the
trees scattered through farmlands, but as
wood prices in the towns rise, firewood is
being commercialized, and landlords nat¬
urally see an advantage in carting available
timber into the nearest town for sale
rather than giving it to the nearby
labourers.
With the farmland trees and the scrub¬
by woodlands of unfarmed areas depleted
by these pressures, both the needy and
the ever present entrepreneurs are forced
to poach for fuel wood in the legally pro¬
tected, ecologically and economically
essential national forest reserves.
The gravity of the poaching problem in
India has been reflected in the formation
of special mobile guard squads and mobile
courts to try captured offenders, but law
enforcement measures have little effec¬
tiveness in. such an untenable situation.
Trees are becoming scarce in the most
unlikely places. Nepalese foresters told me
that in some of the most remote villages
in the world, deep in the once heavily
forested foothills of Nepal, journeying out
to gather firewood and fodder is now an
entire day's task. Just one generation ago
the same expedition required no more
than an hour or two.
The firewood crisis has not provoked
much world attention. Fuel wood scar¬
city, unlike oil scarcity, is always localized
in its apparent dimensions.
Unfortunately, however, the conse¬
quences of firewood scarcity are seldom
limited to the economic burden placed on
the poor of a particular locality. The
accelerating' destruction of forests through¬
out Africa, Asia, and Latin America,
caused in part by fuel gathering, lies at
the heart of what will likely be the most
profound ecological challenge of the late
20th centurythe undermining of the
land's productivity through soil erosion,
increasingly severe flooding, creeping
deserts and declining soil fertility.
Oversized herds of cattle, goats and
sheep are the chief destroyer of grass¬
lands, but firewood gathering is the prin¬
cipal exterminator of trees in many regions.
Firewood is a scarce and expensive item
throughout the vast semi-arid zones of
Africa, Asia, and Latin America, but citi¬
zens in towns like Niamey are paying a
much higher price than they realize for
their cooking fuel.
The caravans that bring in this precious
resource are contributing to the south¬
ward encroachment of the Sahara itself
and, more important, to the creation of
desert-like conditions in a wide band
below the desert's edge. Virtually all trees
within 40 miles of Ouagadougou have been
consumed as fuel by the city's inhab¬
itants, and the circle of land "strip-
mined" for firewoodwithout reclamation
continually expanding.
In the Indian subcontinent, the most
pernicious single result of firewood scar¬
city is probably not the destruction of tree
cover itself, but the alternative burning
cow dungto which a good share of the
people in India, Pakistan and Bangladesh
have been forced. Between 300 and 400
million tons of dung is annually burned for
fuel in India alone, robbing farmland of
badly needed nutrients and organic matter.
The plant nutrients wasted annually in
this fashion in India equal more than a
third of the country's chemical fertilizer
use. Dung is also used for cooking rather
than fertilizer in the Sahelian zone of
Africa, Ethiopia, Iraq, and the nearly tree¬
less Andean valleys and slopes of Bolivia
and Peru.
Even more important than the loss of
agricultural nutrients is the incalculable
damage done to soil quality through the
failure to return manures to the fields.
Organic matter' preserves soil structure
and fertility, reduces erosion by wind or
water, and helps the soil withstand
droughts.
Progressive deforestation on steep
Himalayan slopes is bringing with it a
special set of problems. Nepal is best
known to outsiders as the home of Mount
Everest. Perhaps the chief distinction of
this land, however, is the world's most
acute national soil erosion problem.
Ground-holding trees are disappearing
fast as population growth forces farmers
onto slopes too steep for sustained farm¬
ing even with astonishingly elaborate
terracing, and as villagers roam far and
wide to collect fuel and animal fodder.
And once procuring wood takes too long
to be worth the trouble, some farmers
start to use cow dung, which was formerly
applied with great care to the fields, as
cooking fuel. As this departure from tra¬
dition spreads, the fertility of the hills, al¬
ready declining due to soil erosion, will
fall sharply.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Indian subcontinent is one of
the regions where the lack of
firewood is endangering the
environment. In Nepal, for example,
the shortage is so acute that the
price of firewood has tripled in the
last two years. At left, two
Nepalese have just spent a day
finding a load of precious wood and
are now making their way horns.
This same cluster of phenomena threat¬
ens the future habitability of the entire
stretch of Himalayan foothills, from
Afghanistan through northern Pakistan,
India, and Nepal to Burma.
The negative consequences by no means
stop at the base of the hills. When soil
washes away, it must relocate some¬
where, and the rising load of silt carried
by Asia's rivers is choking up expensive
reservoirs and irrigation works.
Also threatening the Indian subconti¬
nent's food production prospectsand
hence the world's, for nearly one in every
five human beings lives in the subconti¬
nent a rise in the frequency and se¬
verity of flooding in Pakistan, India, and
possibly Bangladesh, the result of denud¬
ed watersheds off which rainfall rushes
rather than seeps downward, and of the
excessive load of sediment from upstream
that builds up river beds, reducing their
capacity to channel water.
Firewood scarcity, then, is intimately
linked to the food problem facing many
countries in two ways. Deforestation and
the diversion of manures to use as fuel are
sabotaging the land's ability to produce
food.
The firewood crisis is in some ways
more, and in others less, intractable than
the energy crisis of the industrialized world.
The poor, like the rich, are faced with the
necessity of energy conservation. Millions
of families cook over wood or charcoal
stoves that are extremely inefficient in the
use of heat; many cook over open fires.
The dissemination of cheap, simple wood-
stoves that waste less heat could substan¬
tially reduce per capita firewood con¬
sumption.
Even if more efficient stoves are adopt¬
ed, however, future firewood needs in
developing countries will, in the absence
of alternative energy sources, be heavily
influenced by population growth. Fire¬
wood scarcity will undoubtedly influence
the urgency with which governments
address the population problem in the
years ahead.
The demand for basic resources like
firewood will still push many countries to
their limits. Fortunately trees, unlike oil,
are a renewable resource when properly
managed. The logical immediate response
to the firewood shortage is to plant more
trees in plantations, on farms, along
roads, in shelter belts, and on unused
land throughout the rural areas of the
poor countries. Often fast growing tree
varieties are available that can be culled
for firewood inside of a decade.
The concept is simple, but its imple¬
mentation is not. Governments in nearly
all the wood-short countries have had tree
planting programmes for some time, but
several problems have plagued these pro¬
grammes from the beginning.
One is the sheer magnitude of the need
for wood, and the scale of the growth in
demand. Population growth has swallow¬
ed the moderate tree-planting efforts of
several countries almost without any no¬
ticeable impact.
The problem of scale is closely linked
to a second major problem: the perennial
question of political priorities and decision¬
making time-frames. It is hard for any
politician to concentrate funds and atten¬
tion on a problem so diffuse and seemingly
long-term in nature.
Even when the political will is there and
the funds are allocated, implementing a
large-scale reforestation campaign is a
surprisingly complex and difficult process.
Planting millions of trees and successfully
nurturing them to maturity is not a tech¬
nical, clearly boundaried task like building
a dam or a nuclear power plant.
Tree planting projects almost always
become deeply enmeshed in the political,
cultural and administrative tangles of a
rural locality; they touch upon, and are
influenced by, the daily living habits of
many people, and they frequently end in
failure.
Most of the regions with too few trees
also have too many cattle, sheep and
goats. Marauding livestock are prime
destroyers of tree planting projects
throughout the less developed world.
Whatever the success of tree planting
projects, the wider substitution of alterna¬
tive energy sources would contribute
greatly to solving the firewood problem.
Even in the poor countries, the propor¬
tion of wood users is falling gradually, but
the hopes of foresters and ecologists for
a rapid reduction of pressures on retreat¬
ing woodlands through a faster shift to
kerosene usually the most feasible wood
substitute withered overnight in Decem¬
ber 1973, when OPEC (Organization of
Petroleum Exporting Countries) announced
its new oil prices.
Fossil fuels are not the only alternate
energy source being contemplated. Indian
scientists have experimented for decades
with an ideal-sounding device that breaks
down manures and other organic waste
into methane gas for cooking and a rich
compost for the farm. Tens of thousands
of these bio-gas plants, as they are called,
are now being used in India, and many
more than that are being used in China
and elsewhere.
But a substantial reduction in cost and
further technological simplification are
needed. Still, relatively simple, small-scale
devices like these will likely be the fuel
source of the future in the poor countries.
The firewood crisis, like many other
resource problems, is forcing governments
and analysts back to the basics of man's
relationship to the landback to concerns
lost sight of in an age of macro-economic
models and technological optimism.
The attitude of people toward trees is
being brought into sharp focus. In his
essay "Buddhist Economics", E. F. Schu¬
macher praises the practical as well as
esoteric wisdom in the Buddha's teaching
that his followers should plant and nurse a
tree every few years.
Unfortunately, this ethical heritage has
been largely lost, even in the predomi¬
nantly Buddhist societies of Southeast
Asia. In fact, most societies today lack an
ethic of environmental cooperation, an
ethic not of conservation for its own sake,
but of human survival amid ecological
systems heading toward collapse.
This will have to change, and fast. More
than anything else, the inexorable growing
demand for firewood calls for tree planting
efforts on a scale more massive than any
most bureaucrats have ever even contem¬
plated, much less planned for. The suici¬
dal deforestation of Africa, Asia, and Latin
America must somehow be slowed and
reversed.
Deteriorating ecological systems have a
logic of their own; the damage often
builds quietly and unseen for many years,
until one day the system collapses with
lethal vengeance. Ask anyone who lived
in Oklahoma in 1934, or Chad in 1975.
Erik P. Eckholm
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The
reat Green Walls
of China
The following article presents the
main points of a study prepared
by the Laboratory for Deserts,
Glaciers and Tundra of the
Lanchow Academy of Sciences
(People's Republic of China). The
study will be presented to the
United Nations Conference on
Desertification that will be held in
Nairobi (Kenya) this year.
IN China, deserts cover an area totalling
1,095,000 square .kilometres or 11.4
per cent of the country's entire area.
The largest, Takla Makan, is in Sinkiang
province.
These deserts are, however, very differ¬
ent. Some, such as Takla Makan, are
comprised of shifting dunes 100 to 150
metres high. Others, with semi-stabilized
furrows, stretch out over vast expanses.
Some have sharply delineated sand hills
from 200 to 300 metres high with swampy
stretches between. One also finds deserts
of drifting sand and swampy, grass-filled,
areas. Others have sand hills that alternate
with eroded areas. A typical example of
this last type of desert is the Chaidamu
basin which, with altitudes between 2,600
and 3,400 metres, is the highest desert in
China. Lastly, there are regions whçre
shifting sands juxtapose semi-stabilized
dunes, swampy basins, and sometimes
even rivers.
To contain these deserts, a number of
methods have been used. In the areas
near oases, where sandstorms can wreak
havoc, the inhabitants plant forests around
the oases to hold back the sand. Then,
inside the oases, they plant rows of trees
around the fields and, on the edge of the
desert, they plant grass to hold down the
sand. Water resources are used to the
maximum to irrigate the fields, to evacuate
the sand and to create new farmland in
problem areas.
In deserts where the sand hills are semi-
or fully stabilized and in deserts of shifting
sand, the inhabitants are trying to make
use of stabilized dunes, certain grass-lands
and the more humid zones to turn the
desert into a steppe. At the same time,
trees, shrubs and grass are used to hold
down the shifting sand and a forest belt
is established to protect the land under
cultivation.
In the great desert regions, reservoirs
are built to catch water from flash floods,
and underground water is tapped. The
terrain is levelled, protective forests are
set up, land is cleared and new oases
created.
Here are a few examples of the tech¬
niques used. If the dunes are less than
ten metres high, a chain of extended
forest belts is set up at their base. To hold
down the sand between the belts of trees,
two things can be done: sand barriers,
within which plants are grown, are set up
and a layer of clay is added to thicken the
sand to increase its wind resistance. Wind
speeds then decrease by from 28 to 33 per
cent.
Expanses of flat land, shifting sand and
semi-stabilized dunes are found in the
vicinity of certain oases situated near the
edge of the desert. Protective forests of
tall trees and bushes are planted which
decrease the velocity of the wind at ground
level. When, for example, tamarisks are
planted and when wind speed is average,
the amount of wind-borne sand drops by
nearly 80 per cent.
To protect the oases plagued by sand¬
storms, notably in the Gobi desert, a num¬
ber of protective forest belts are planted
every 50 to 100 metres.
Another method consists in planting
rows of trees in channels. This was the
technique used at "Five Stars", a people's
commune in the Turpan desert in Sinkiang.
Five tree belts were created. First, five
channels measuring 1.5 metres in width
were dug at intervals of four to five metres.
Then shrubs and small trees were planted
the length of the first channel, which is
exposed to the wind. The next two chan¬
nels were planted with poplars and mul¬
berry trees. The last two each got a row
of poplars and elms. As the trees are of
varying heights, the tops form a staggered
surface, which makes it much more wind-
resistant. Such a surface can reduce wind
velocity by two-thirds.
At the same time, the oasis is divided
up into a grid-like pattern; groves of trees
are planted in squares around each field to
form a wind screen. The size of each
square in the grid varies according to the
force of the wind it is exposed to. The
effectiveness of these tree barriers is
directly proportional to their height. At a
height of ten metres, wind velocity de¬
creases on the average by 33.2 per cent
up to 300 metres from the barrier. For a
height of six metres, the decrease is 20.9
per cent up to 240 metres.
On the land where hydraulic resources
permit it, trees, bushes and grass are used
jointly to hold down the shifting sand.
One method, called "protection from the
front and retaining at the rear", applies to
crescent-shaped dunes and to chains of
dunes. Planting is done in the spaces
between the dunes, under the wind, to
prevent the sand from sliding forward.
This creates a grid-like pattern that sur¬
rounds the dunes. Other planting is done
in the lower third of the slopes exposed
to the wind, which holds the sand down,
reduces the wind's force and retains the
dune from the rear. It takes from four to
five years to complete this process.
Results are already forthcoming. A
thick forest barrier now crosses the western
part of the regions of Liaoning, Jilin and
Heilongjiang, covering an area more than
800 kilometres long and 500 kilometres
wide. It is the largest forest barrier in
China and protects 2,800,000 hectares of
land. What was once sand dunes whipped
by wind is now rich farmland producing
high yields.
In the southern part of the Mu Us desert,
in Shansi province, the people have already
set up forest barriers that cover more than
200,000 hectares. This has enabled them
to reclaim as many as 20,000 hectares
of arable land. To the north, over half the
grazing land was in the process of deser¬
tification and was covered with shifting
sand dunes. Since the revolution, 15,000
hectares of these shifting dunes were
reclaimed, 6,000 hectares of which were
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Photo © China Press, Peking
In China, tremendous energy is
being expended in the fight against
desertification. Here, members of -
the commune of Wushenchow, in
Inner Mongolia, are planting a wind¬
screen of vegetation to hold down
the sand.
turned into grazing land. Livestock has
increased six-fold.
In Inner Mongolia, north of the Ulanbur
desert, a forest barrier more than 170 kilo¬
metres long was planted; this "Great
Green Wall" has stopped the encroach¬
ment of sand. More than 600,000 hecta¬
res of rich farmland have become available
for cultivation on the edges of two other
deserts, the Takla Makan and the Gur¬
bantünggüt. ' The southwestern part of
Gurbantünggüt was once a bleak and
barren desert. In the last fifteen years,
15,000 hectares of rich farmland have
been created, and the region has become
an oasis dotted with forests.
The Chinese people have expended
tremendous energy and ingenuity on these
projects; they have already succeeded in
accomplishing a great deal.
ONSLAUGHT ON THE NILE (continued from page 24)
the Sudan. Sand from these dunes can
claim arable soil in the northwest part of
that country. The Sudan is considered by
many people to be North Africa's future
food supplier.
The dunes do not stop at the Sudan;
the American astronauts of the Apollo-
Soyuz mission observed linear streaks of
sand dunes all the way to Lake Chad. In
this region and even farther south all along
the Sahel belt, lack of rain, uncontrolled
grazing and shifting sands from the north
are all active in the desertification of fertile
lands.
It is clear that what happens in the
Western Desert of Egypt affects other
parts of the Sahara. To study this expanse
of land, all of its parts have to be taken
into consideration and dealt with as one
continuous geographic unit.
The colour of dune sand can be indic¬
ative of its age. As it is transported far¬
ther from its sources, and as it is subject¬
ed to oxidation by air and moisture, sand
becomes coated with a thin film of iron
oxides. Therefore, sand from the same
origin will appear redder when it is far¬
thest from the source. This property can
be used in mapping relative age zones of
desert sands.
Consequently, colour photographs taken
from Earth orbit can assist in the study of
desert landforms and the process of deser¬
tification. These photographs help in
documenting regional variations in the
colour of desert sands; providing evidence
of regional sand transport directions; and
aiding in the location of areas for detailed
ground investigations. The next oppor7
tunity to take these space photographs
will be provided by Nasa's next program¬
me, the Space Shuttle, which is due to
start test flights in July 1979.
! Farouk El-Baz
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
Newsroom
Nature and resources
In its latest issue (April-June 1977), the Unesco quarterly
Nature and Resources devotes several articles to the
problems of desertification. Of particular interest are:
"Unesco and the United Nations Conference on Deser¬
tification"; "Climatic and Ecological Aspects of Deserti¬
fication"; and "Desertification in the United States".
Nature and Resources is the official bulletin of Unesco's
Man and the Biosphere Programme (MAB), of the Inter¬
national Hydrological Programme and of the Internatio¬
nal Geological Correlation Programme. One-year sub¬
scription: 20 FF; two-year subscription: 36 FF. Copy
price: 6 FF
Development in the desert
Experts from over 40 countries met from 31 May to
10 June in Sacramento, California, under the auspices
of the United Nations Institute for Training and Research
and the state of California, to study ways to develop and
manage desert regions. Called to prepare for the United
Nations Conference on Desertification that will take place
in August and September of this year, the experts took
stock of the resources of desert zones and proposed a
series of appropiate long-term development strategies.
International book award
The International Book Committee, which is comprised,
among others, of publishers, authors, librarians and
book-sellers, recently bestowed its 1977 International
Book Award on Julian Behrstock. Mr. Behrstock, an
American, directed Unesco's' Division of free Flow
of Information and Communications Policies from 1964
to 1967. He also directed a programme designed to
promote publishing in the developing countries and inter¬
national cooperation in the field of books.
China's use of water
Twenty experts sent by governments of developing
countries recently completed a one-month study trip to
China. Under the auspices of the United Nations and
the United Nations Development Programme, the trip
was designed to show experts how the Chinese make
maximum use of their water resources on the local level:
irrigation techniques, reservoirs, canals, and so forth.
Tuberculosis on the rampage
Although much has been done to combat it, tuberculosis
still remains a major killer: over 400,000 persons around
the world die each year from it. According to the World
Health Statistics Report, just published by the World
Health Organization, there are roughly 8 million cases of
tuberculosis in the world today.
Tribute to French poet
International homage was paid to the late Jacques Prévert
recently at Unesco headquarters under the auspices of
the International Theatre Institute. Leading French actors
participated in the ceremony.
TO OUR READERS
We are pleased to announce that, starting with this
issue, you will find improvements in your magazine.
In answer to frequent requests from readers of the
Unesco Courier, we have decided that the cover of each
issue will from now on be printed in four colours, replacing
the two-colour process we have often used before.
In order to be able to offer you a magazine of
ever-finer quality, we shall also shortly be introducing a
carefully prepared new typographical layout.
As you know, our magazine, like Unesco, is a
non-profit operation and it cannot count on the advertising
revenue that many periodicals on the market depend on
and without which they could not continue to operate.
The Unesco Courier's financial resources come entirely
from the budget of Unescothat is, from the
contributions of its Member Statesand, for a great part,
from the faithful support of hundred of thousands of
readers around the world.
During the last three years, we have kept the same
newsstand and subscription prices, which we believe to be
very modest compared with those of magazines of similar
style and quality. This has entailed considerable sacrifices
on our part. Today, given the improvements we are
initiating and the fact that production and distribution
costs have risen steadily over the last three years, we find
ourselves obliged to ask our readers to continue to help
us. We are sure you will understand our reasons and
accept the price increase we are asking of you, an increase
which is in any case small and nowhere near offsets the
increased expenditure Unesco is taking upon itself to
maintain your magazine on a level of quality worthy of the
high ideals that justify its existence.
You will find the new price list on the opposite page.
To end this appeal on a pleasant note, we would like
to make you a bargain offer: up until 31 December, 1977,
you can take out a one- or even two-year subscription to
the Unesco Courier at the present price. In this way,
those of you who so desire can receive your regular copies
at today's price until the end of 1979. Thanks to this offer,
we will have succeeded in maintaining the same price for
our faithful subscribers over a five-year period. This, as
you will appreciate, in view of the general increase in
prices the world over, has only been possible through a
great effort on our part.
UNESCO COURIER
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
NEW PRICES EFFECTIVE 1 JANUARY. 1978
one year: 35 FF.
two years: 58 FF.
single issue: 3.50 FF.
SPECIAL OFFER VALID UNTIL 31 DECEMBER, 1977
For current subscribers: if your subscription expires before 31 December,
you can renew for 1 or 2 years at the 1977 rate:
one year: 28 FF.
two years: 52 FF.
For new subscribers: by subscribing now, you can also take advantage
of the current 1 or 2year rates.
For gift subscriptions: if you'd like to offer someone a gift subscription,
do it before 31 December and you can benefit from the current rates.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country- (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription4 rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd.. P.O. Box 33. Brookvale. 2100, NSW: Periodicals:
Dominie Pty., Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association
of Australia, Victorian Division 5th floor, 134-136
Flinders St.. Melbourne (Victoria). 3000. - AUSTRIA.
Dr. -Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandlung
Industriehof Stadlan, Dr. Otto-Neurath-Gasse 5. 1220
Wien. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition
only: N.V. Handelmaatschappij Keesing, Keesinglaan
2-18, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition and
general Unesco publications agent: Jean de Lannoy,
1 12, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 000-0070823-13 -
BURMA. Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552 Merchant
Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal,
Qué. H3H 1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Maka-
rios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. -CZECHO¬
SLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L. Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1.
For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag - Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6, 893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK-1165,
Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat
Harb Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, SF 00100 Helsinki. - FRANCE, Librairie de
l'Unesco 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, C.C.P. Paris
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from
Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED.
REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse '22. C.C.P.
Hamburg 276650. For scientific maps only: GEO
CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80. Postfach 800830. Other
publications: Verlag Dokumentation, Pössenbacher
Strasse 2, 8000 München 71 (Prinz Ludwigshöhe).
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd.. P.O. Box
195, Accra: Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box
7869, Accra: The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra: The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The
University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - GREECE.
International bookshops. - HONG KONG. Federal
, Publications Division, Far East Publications Ltd., 5 A
Evergreen Industrial Mansion, Wong Chuk Hang Road,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road.
Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kónyvesbolt.
Váci.u. 22, Budapest V: A. K.V. Konyvtúrosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co.. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.. Kamani
Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chit-
taranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13: 36a, Anna Salai, Mount
Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf AN Road, New Delhi 1:
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001 ;
3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots;
Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House. New Delhi; Publications Section,
Ministry of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing,
Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop. Jl.
Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Or. Sam
Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. - IRAN. Kharazmie Publish¬
ing and Distribution Co., 229 Daneshgahe Street. Shah
Avenue, P.O. Box 14/1486, Teheran. Iranian National
Commission for Unesco, Avenue IranchahrChomali No300,
B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al-
Rashid Street, Baghdad. - IRELAND. The Edu¬
cational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown,
formely Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road '
and 48, Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv: 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's
Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O.
Box 1728, Tokyo 100-92. - KENYA. East African
Publishing House. P.O. Box 30571. Nairobi. - KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. -Box
Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop
Co., Ltd, P.O. Box 2942, Kuwait. - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole' and Yancy Book¬
shops Ltd.. P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA.
Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution.
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie
Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue. Luxembourg. - MALAY¬
SIA. Federal Publications Sdn. Bhd., Balai Berit«,
31, Jalan Riong, Kuala Lumpur, MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street. Valletta. - MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30. Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. - MONACO. British Library, 30. bd des Mou¬
lins, . Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing,
Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam- 1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout. 9. The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES.
G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.). N.V., Willemstad.
Curaçao. N. A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government Prin¬
ting Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street,
P.O. Box 5344, Auckland: 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box
1721, Christchurch: Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamil¬
ton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife. The University Bookshop
of Ibadan, P.O. Box 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos: The Ahmadu
8ello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All
publications: Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl
Johans-gate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only:
A.S. Narvesens Literaturtjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mir'za Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-
azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES.
The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue. P.O. Box 632.
Manila D-404. - POLAND. ORPAN-IMPORT. Palac
Kuitury i Nauki, Warsaw: Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon. - SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte
Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar
Road. Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O.
Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publi¬
cations: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Buil¬
ding, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News
Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. - SOUTHERN
RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Book¬
shop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop.
P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum, - SWEDEN. All publica¬
tions: A/B C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel. Fredsgatan 2,
Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2, Box
150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse. Zurich.
Librairie Payot. rue Grenus 6, 1211. Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop.
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh
and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri. P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit.
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. -TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H. M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London. S.E.I., and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast,.
Manchester. Birmingham, Bristol. UNITED STATES.
Unipub, Box 433, Murray Hill Station, New York, N.Y.
10016. For "Unesco Courier" in Spanish: Santillana
Publishing Company, Inc., 575 Lexington Avenue,
New York, N.Y. 10022. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga. Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzayna Zalozba Slovenije,
Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
KtÊÈak
. : : V:
Photo V Chidlovski, USSR
Tea for two in Turkmenistan (U.S.S.R.)
Far-reaching efforts are today being made to bring life to the deserts which cover much of Central Asia.
The Kara-Kum canal, a major feature of this vast programme, is at present 1,000 km long and links the
Amu-Darya river with the Caspian Sea (U.S.S.R.). It irrigates some 300,000 hectares, transforming harsh
desert conditions into a more stable and productive environment (see article page 18). Above, two
generations of desert-dwellers in Soviet Turkmenistan quench their thirst with a drink of tea.
]]>
</page>
</document>
