<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074823eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The f~*\ A window open on the world
Courier
April 1976 (29th year) 2.80 French franca
he world
humour
©
HE
PORTANCE
NO!
ING
RNEST
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OFWORLD ART•
Man with a skin of clay
The civilization of Tolita. which flourished between 500 B.C. and the fifth century A.D., owes
its name to the small island off the northern coast of present-day Ecuador where it originated.
The artists of the Tolita civilization. whose influence spread to the mainland, shaped remarkable
pottery figures such as the statuette shown here. Their works depict a wide variety of different
physical types. and may be portrayals of persons who visited the island of Tolita for important
religious ceremonies that took place there. Tolita artists also worked in gold and copper, and
were pioneer craftsmen in platinum, a material not used by artists in Europe until the 18th century.
Photo ,ti Vautier-De Nanxe, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Page
PUBLISHED IN 15 LANGUAGES
APRIL 1976 29TH YEAR
5 THE IMPORTANCE
OF NOT BEING EARNEST
Humour across frontiers: make laugh(ter) not war
By George Mikes
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
9 THE GIFT OF THE GABROVO
How Bulgaria became famous for good humour as well as yoghurt
By Bogomil Gerasimov
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational. Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris
Annual subscription rate 28 French francs
Binder for a year's issues: 24 French francs
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER," plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re-
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro-
film andlor microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head. Inc.. 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the
Readers' Guide to Periodical Literature. published by
H. W. Wilson Co.. New York, and in Current Con-
tents - Education, Philadelphia. U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editors-in-Chief
Rene Caloz
Olga Rodel
Managing Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition: Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: N. K. Sundaram (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Telci (Istanbul)
Assistant Editors
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Philippe Ouannes
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Illustrations: Anne-Marie MaiUard t
Research: Christiane Boucher
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-In-Chief in Paris
12 WORM-BREEDING WITH TONGUE IN CHEEK
Confessions of a scientist hoist hy his own petard
By James V. McConnell
16 NASRUDIN HODJA, THE MAN WHO RODE
HIS ASS BACKWARDS
Comic folk hero whose jokes delight the world
By Ivan Sop
22 THE WORLD WILL NEVER DIE
IF IT DIES LAUGHING
By Yuri B. Boryev
25 THE POLITICAL AND SATIRICAL CARTOON
Stepping in where angels dread to fear
By Ivan Tubau
28 THE CHINESE HAVE A WORD
FOR (W)IT
By Kristofer M. Schipper
33 UNESCO NEWSROOM
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Deadpan man with a skin of clay (Ecuador)
Cove,
This issue of the ·Unesco Courier" is devo-
ted to "World Humour - and the Importance of
NOT Being Earnest". The intriguing figure on
our cover, opening his patched robe to reveal
a decor of startling magnificence, is one of
history's great pranksters, Nasrudin Hodja,
comic folk hero of the Muslim world since
early medieval times. To the question very
often posed: Is humour international? Nasru-
din has supplied the answer. His anecdotes
have girdled the earth with people holding
their sides or rolling in the aisles all the way
from China to Europe and from America to
Africa and the Middle East.
Dr_lng by Richard Williams and Errol le Cain,
from "The Pleasantrlea of the Incredible Mulla Nasru-
din" by Idrles Shah © 1968 Mulla Nasrudln Enterprises
Ltd., published by Jonathan Cape Ltd., London.
Back cover: photo Maltete © Rapho, Paris
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Associated Press
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
THE IMPORTANCE
OF NOT BEING EARNEST
by George Mikes
I1 am. classified by most of my
enemies and even by some of
my friends as a humorist. Make no
mistake: to call a man a humorist is
no compliment. No one calls himself
a humorist because there is some¬
thing pejorative and dismissive in the
phrase. But I accept the classification
not with pride (I am not a very proud
man), not with resignation (I am not
given to melancholy) but with a shrug.
Very well, I am a humorist if you
insist on it. But here I must sound a
warning against myself. A humorist is
no more an expert on humour than
a man suffering from diabetes is an
"expert" on diabetes. The humorist
like the diabetic has got it but he
has no idea how he got it and still
less how to get rid of it.
\ Humour is a problem of philosophy
but philosophers do not fare much
better than humorists or diabetics.
- A philosopher with a sense of humour
will laugh at a joke instead of per¬
forming a post mortem on it; and a
philosopher will not be able however
competent he may be otherwise to
teach us a lot about the sense of
humour if he himself lacks one.
The issue is further plagued by
another complication unique to this
subject. A man reading an essay on
humour has no more right or reason
to expect to laugh or to be entertained
than someone reading an essay on
Nicomachean Ethics; yet he does
expect to be vastly amused. A woman
reading a cookery book does not
expect to have her hunger quenched
but a person reading an essay on
humour expects to be entertained.
And the fact that more dull books
have been written on humour than on
any other subject seems to make no
.difference.
GEORGE MIKES, author of How to be an
Alien (1946) and Switzerland for Beginners
(1962) has sent us the following biographical
note: "I was born in 1912 in Siklos (Hungary)
but moved to Budapest when I was ten. I
wanted to become a journalist and writer but
my family insisted on my becoming a gentleman,
i.e. a lawyer, following in my father's and grand¬
father's footsteps. So I studied law but got a job
for myself as a journalist too. By the time I got my
doctorate, I was too far gone in journalism and
my family had to give up all hopes of my becom¬
ing a gentleman. I was sent to London for a
fortnight and have stayed ever since. During the ]
war I worked In the BBC's Hungarian Section,
after that as a freelance writer. I have also
written more than 30 books and I am told
they have sold several mil/ion copies in 21
languages. "
humour
across frontiers
make laugh (ter)
not war!
Let us then have a very quick survey
of what other people said about
humour and how they tried to define it.
The Old Testament already noticed the
sadness of laughter: "Even in laughter
the heart is sorrowful"; and "the
end of mirth is heaviness." Accord¬
ing to Plato we laugh at the misfortune
of our friends and our feeling is mixed
pleasure and pain. Aristotle also
recognized the essentially cruel nature
of humour and said that to make a
joke of a man is to vilify him. Cicero,
too, thought that the ridiculous had its
grounds in baseness and deformity.
A very long jump takes us to John
Harington, Elizabethan courtier and
wit, who says that comedies "may
make men see the shame of their own
fault". The English philosopher Tho¬
mas Hobbes' definition is the most
famous of all: "Laughter is nothing
else but sudden glory arising from
a sudden conception of some emi-
nency in ourselves, by comparison
with the infirmity of others, or with our
own formerly."
I could go on for 24 volumes to
quote the great sages and philos¬
ophers through Hegel and Schopen¬
hauer but I shall quote only three:
Bergson, Koestler and myself.
Bergson knew that laughter was
always corrective. He was also fully
aware (and Freud later agreed with
him) of the aggressive and cruel-
nature of laughter. "In laughter we
always find an unavowed intention to
humiliate and consequently to correct
our neighbour."
Koestler wrote a great deal about
humour, including an essay for Encyc¬
lopaedia Britannica. His definition is
more pragmatic: the aim of humour
is to provoke laughter. He goes on,
explaining that laughter is the one
"luxury reflex" of humanity: a reflex
which unlike sneezing or closing our
eyes in fright serves no useful
purpose.
Finally myself. I quote an old Jewish
joke, one of those which, I find, are
often more illuminating than a bunch
of philosophers.
An old, blind Jew asked a young girl
what milk was like.
"Milk?" asked the girl, astonished.
"Yes, milk, You see, I'm blind and
I just cannot imagine what milk is
like."
"Well, milk is white."
"White..." said the old man. "I'm
old and blind. I just don't know what
white means."
"It's easy to explain," said the girl
brightly. "A swan is white."
"But I've never seen a swan."
"It has a curved neck."
"Curved?" sighed the old man.
"What is curved?"
The girl lifted her right arm, bent
her wrist forward like a swan's neck."
"Feel it," she said. "That's curved."
The old man felt the girl's arm,
touched the curved wrist several times
and then exclaimed with satisfaction:
"Thank God I Now at last I know
what milk is like."
Philosophers, like that helpful little
girl, keep telling us clever and true
. things about humour. She was right
and everything she said helped: milk
is white, and a swan is white and -
the swan has a curved neck. But in
the end, having read a whole library ^
about humour, we know as much about r
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
humour as the old man knew, in the
end, about milk. In other words: many
important and helpful details, except
one basic thing: what humour really is.
I should like to add just a few
observations to our knowledge of
important details before proceeding
to other subjects.
It is usually the grotesque, the
paradoxical, the funny which strikes
me in a situation where others per¬
haps see darkness and tragedy.
About 15 years ago I was writing my
first novel and Arthur Koestler whom
I have already mentioned asked me
what it was about. I told him it was
about a man who ate too much, whose
mortal passion was eating, who ate like
some others drink. "A good subject,"
he nodded. "A better one for Kafka
than for you but a good subject." He
only saw the tragic element in it.
I, while I hope I do not lack com¬
passion and understanding and while
I liked my hero and felt sympathy for
him, saw him as an essentially comic
character. After all, to eat yourself
to death is less tragic than dying, say,
a heroic death on the battlefield. Yes,
I often see the humour and fun where
others look at me quizzically and with
suspicion: what the hell is he laughing
about?
My sister had a bit of a great Slav
soul. I had a very happy childhood
and she had a tormented and unhappy
childhood but we both had the same
childhood. I had loving, devoted and
understanding parents while she had
harsh, strict and not devoted parents.
But we both had the same parents.
And this fact that humour is not
in the situation but in the beholder's
eye is the answer to the question
every humorous writer is often asked.
"How is it," people ask you, "that
all the funny things always happen to
you?" A humorist's life seems to be
an endless chain of hilarity while, they
add with dismay, nothing ever happens
to them.
Life is, of course, a long, happy Joke;
it is also a dark, horrible tragedy; or
endless boredom, ¡t depenas on you.
The only difference between the
humorist or rather between the man
with a strong sense of humour and
one utterly without it is that the former
notices the humour in all situations
while the other misses it.
It was G.K. Chesterton who gave
the perfect answer to this question
when he remarked, speaking to
humanity at large:
"You make the jokes; I see them."
Telling endless jokes without any
apropos can be an awful bore. Lis¬
tening to endless jokes is a pro¬
fessional hazard for a humorist.
Wherever I go, people keep telling me
jokes. It was Frederic Karinthy, the
great Hungarian humorist, who com¬
plained: "I cannot explain to people
that the humorist is the man who
is supposed to tell jokes and not the
man to whom you are supposed to
be telling jokes."
The joke is a minor art, with not
only literary but also with political
significance. A joke which has a point
not only the point of a joke but some
point of telling it in the circumstances
can be more revealing than many a
long lecture.
Jokes have special significance in
tyrannies. They are brief; they can be
whispered from ear to ear in a few
seconds; and by making fun of the
tyrant they bring him down to a human
level, showing that the great man is
nothing more than an erring, frightened
and stupid human being, like the rest
of us, and that's the one thing no
tyrant's reputation can bear for long.
The joke has never received its
proper due. It has been analysed by.
Freud and others as a psychological
phenomenon but never as a literary
one. It would deserve some attention
but it must, inevitably, remain a minor
art. Why minor? For three main
reasons.
1. Humour must always take second
place behind tragedy. This does not
mean that great humorous writers, like
Mark Twain, lag behind silly serious
writers. Of course not; they are much
greater. But if you take Shakespeare
himself, his great tragediesKing
Lear or Hamlet are greater, master¬
pieces than his excellent comedies,
Drawing © Saul Steinberg: Société Nouvelle
dea Editions du Chêne, Paris
Drawing © Danllo Aqulstl, Italy; from a cartoon 'collection published by
The House of Humour and Satire, Gabrovo, Bulgaria, 1975
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
M
m
<*&
¿ra
3
m
MMM*
3
,.ai
ri-
<u^
,«¿¿*á
From the days when the ancient Egyptians
used hieroglyphic typewriters to caption
their obelisks, words have always caused
problems. Some people just drop their
aitches instead of minding their p's and q's;
as for others whole words escape them.
The Merchant of Venice or the Taming
of the Shrew.
2. The joke. is one dimensional, while
life is complex and multifarious so it
just cannot cope.
3. There may be beauty in a short
piece of art say, in a Japanese poem
but there can be no development,
no construction.
It was Ferenc Molnár, the playwright,
who encouraged his friend, the Aus¬
trian, Alfred Polgar, to write longer
pieces and not to stick to his excellent
epigrams, paradoxes, very short obser¬
vations. Polgar thought this advice
over and rejected it. That's the form
which suited him, he would stick to
it. Molnár shrugged his shoulders.
"Very well", he said, "then you will
remain the world champion of the one-
yard sprint."
Yes, the joke as a form of art is
the one-yard sprint.
Is there such a thing as a national
humour? Of course there is. The
speciality of the English, for example,
is understatement. A man is swept
into the water from a Channel boat. A
tremendous gale is lashing moun- ;
tainous seas. The man's head emerges
just once from the water. He being
a proper Englishman shouts at the
people on the boat, not excitedly of
course, just loud enough to be heard:
"Rather windy, isn't it?" That's
understatement.
Or take this scrap of dialogue from
the pen of the English writer and
humorist, P.G. Wodehouse:
you seen Mr. Fink-Nottle,"Have
Jeeves?"
"No, sir."
"I am going to murder him."
"Very good, sir."
Understatement is not simply a
manner of making jokes; in England it
is also a way of life. When the
Englishman leaves his house in pouring
rain, all he will say, passing his neigh¬
bour, is: "It's not so nice, is it?" The
whole rhythm of life in England is
understatement. The underreaction to
everything, the polite word instead of
the rude outburst.
I could go on analysing such unlikely
national humours as the Greek or the
Swiss. I have given considerable time
trying to understand the Chinese, and
even more, the Japanese sense of
humour. I failed. In our European
arrogance we are inclined to believe
that they have no sense of humour
just because it is so different from
ours. Well, I am not sure.
All I can say now, in conclusion, is
this: yes, there is such a thing as
national sense of humour. As long
as there are national characteristics,
they will manifest themselves also in
national humour. How long this will
last in a world which is steadily
becoming duller and more uniform, no
one can tell.
Does then, national humour exist?
It does. There is a less frequently,
asked but perhaps more interesting p
il'h
Il p
fin 1 " t.l
II fWH i /
fa
mpwp'm
Drawing © Ronald Searle from "The Square Egg",
Weldenfeld and Nicolson, London, 1968
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
question to pose: is there such a thing
as international humour? Does hu¬
mour, cari * humour travel across
international boundaries?
Many people maintain that it does
not and cannot. This statement,
however, just is not true. People laugh
at the same jokes all over the world.
Having said it, I hasten to qualify, and
enlarge upon, this statement.
Educated people laugh at the same
things and uneducated or less edu¬
cated people also laugh at the same,
though different, things.
This does not mean that educated
people will not laugh at the man who
slips on a banana skin or has custard
pie thrown into his face. This banana-
skin or custard-pie humour releases
such atavistic feelings of fear and
aggression that all barriers of edu¬
cation fall to the ground like the walls
of Jericho. We may be thoroughly
ashamed of our low taste; but we shall
laugh.
There are certain other types of
jokes and certain types of humour
which are far below the level of some
people and far above the level of some
others. The education barrier is more
difficult to cross than the national
barrier.
Some jokes are not only international
but pretty ageless. Some crop up at
various places in different centuries.
Sometimes they are cleaned up,
modernized, dusted, put into a new
guise but they do come back. Jokes
born at the time of the post-World
War I German inflation reappeared
half a century later in Brazil or Italy;
jokes told against regimes in, say,
Greece or Chile, were already told
against Hitler, against Napoleon III or
even against Caligula.
So I can emphatically repeat that
humour does not respect national
frontiers. This, however, does not
mean that jokes and humour travel
more easily than, say, wine. Some
wines do not travel at all; many people
detest Retzina, others would not touch
anything else; others again do not
like wine at all, and so on. Similarly,
the popularity of jokes depends on
many factors:, the national .mood;
people's individual sense of humour;
education; momentary painful problems
or euphoria; taste, etc.
But the foundation is there: humour
can travel and in many cases does
travel. It is not easier to establish
true internationalism in humour than
in anything else. No, on second
thoughts, I think it Is easier: people,
after all, are more inclined to laugh
than to make political concessions.
So make laugh(ter) not war.
George Mikes
SAD TAIL OF
GABROVO'S CATS
Cats had no easy life in
the town of Gabrovo, Bulgaria's
Internationally famous capital of
humour. The Gabrovians have
given themselves a reputation
totally unjustified for
stinginess. The story goes that
they cut off their cats' tails so
that the animals took less time
to pass through the doorway,
thus saving heat In winter.
So It's not suprising that a
tailless cat (right) is the symbol
of the festival of humour and
satire held in Gabrovo every
year. Satirically smiling cat on
dish (left) still has a tail, but it
will soon lose it (below) to the
astonishment of Gabrovo's dogs.
Photo Unesco Courier
' \. '¿,\ f **f#rop
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Sofia Press
THE GIFT
OF THE GABROVO
how Bulgaria became famous
for good humour as well as yoghurt
by
Bogomil Gerasimov
ASK a Scot if he can tell you
where mini-skirts, tight trou¬
sers, gliders, the smallest coin in the
world or similar things were invented
and he knows immediately that a joke
about Aberdeen is coming up. Put the
question to a Bulgarian and he knows
that he can expect a quip about the
town of Gabrovo in central Bulgaria.
It was only a few years ago that_
"the British learned tö" their surprise that
Aberdeen's fame for stories of mean-
BOGOMIL GERASIMOV, Bulgarian humorist
and journalist, has published an anthology of
Scottish jokes and anecdotes: From Aberdeen
with Laughter (in Bulgarian). He is the author
of several novels, television plays and film
scenarios.
ness is shared by Bulgaria's Gabro¬
vo and that Aberdonian and Gabrovo
jokes are astonishingly alike. And not
only the jokes, but also the sense
of humour behind them is identical.
This whole revelation on a new type
of town-twinning came about by pure
accident in 1967, when I was an offi¬
cial of the Bulgarian Embassy in Lon¬
don. I was joking with a British jour¬
nalist friend of mine about the fact
that both Bulgarian yoghurt and Scotch
whisky have achieved world-wide re¬
nown, when he asked me to tell him
a typically Bulgarian joke. So I told
him about the inhabitants of Gabrovo,
who are said to be extremely mean,
and far from resenting this reputation,
do their best to feed it by inventing
their- own "jokes and "even publishing
collections of them.
To illustrate my point I told him that
Gabrovo people stop their clocks and
watches during the night, in order not
to wear out the cogs. "But what do
they do when they want to know the
time at night?", asked my friend, and
before I could reply he added: "An
Aberdonian always keeps a trumpet be¬
neath his bed. When he wants to
know the time during the night, he
opens the window and lets off a blast
on it. There is always a neighbour who
will bang up his own window and
shout: 'Who's the idiot making that
racket at twenty past two in the morn¬
ing?'" Incredible, but true; the ending
was identical with that of the joke from
Gabrovo.
My friend seemed fascinated by the
Gabrovo sense of humour, and so I
told him a few more typical Gabrovo
stories. The Gabrovians dance bare¬
foot, so they can hear the music from
the next village... They put green spec¬
tacles on their horses, so that they
take straw for fresh grass..JThey.throw-
their cats down their chimneys to avoid
paying chimney-sweeps... They heat
their knives before dinner, so that
guests can't use the butter... They join
wildlife protection societies so that
their wives won't ask them for fur
coats...
Out of this conversation was born ^
the idea of organizing a competition for r
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
All the cartoons on these pages are taken from the catalogue
Caricatural Sculptures published by the House of Humour and
of the 2nd Int. Biennial of Cartoons and Small
Satire, Gabrovo, Bulgaria, 1975
the best Gabrovo-type Scottish joke,
run in Glasgow, Scotland's largest city,
by the Da/7y Record newspaper. The
grand finale of the competition was, of
course, held in Aberdeen, where the
winners were awarded a free two-week
stay in Bulgarian holiday resorts, inclu¬
ding a special visit to Gabrovo.
The Daily Record headlined its report
of the final "The Night Aberdeen Dou¬
bled up with Laughter", and the Aber¬
deen Evening Express ran an article
headed "Humour links Aberdeen with
Bulgaria". As a result of the publicity,
I received an avalanche of letters, not
only from many places in Britain but
also from the U.S.A., Zambia, Australia
and New Zealand. All these letters,
together with those sent directly to the
Da/7y Record are now carefully pre¬
served in Gabrovo.
As I have said, a number of Scottish
anecdotes are virtually identical to
those found in Gabrovo. I have often
been asked who thought up these stor¬
ies, and whether one country could
have picked them up from the other.
In my opinion, there may well have
been some borrowing, but it is very
difficult to prove, and in any case the
question is not that important.
It is well known, in Bulgaria at least,
that Scottish bagpipes are of Bulgarian*^
origin, although this does not prevent
the Scots from claiming them as their
own invention and as their special
contribution to the world's musical cul¬
ture.
Some witty Gabrovo jokes may well'
have followed the bagpipes to Scotland
where they speedily took root in the
northern Scottish soil and flourished.
In the same way, no doubt, a number
of Scottish jokes took out Bulgarian
citizenship and settled down cheerfully
in the town of Gabrovo. These obvious
similarities are curious enough but the
most striking thing of all is the basic
resemblance of the sense of humour
in both places.
, In Bulgaria, Gabrovo has the same
reputation that Aberdeen enjoys in
Scotland. The inhabitants of both
towns are considered to be misers,
penny-pinching, deeply cunning and
always on the lookout for ways of
making easy money. The facts, as
often, are different from the fiction.
The inhabitants of Gabrovo are hard
working, honest, hospitable and gen¬
erous. And from my own experience
of the Scots, I can say the same thing
about the Aberdonians.
The town of Gabrovo lies on wooded
slopes of the foothills of the Balkan
range not far from the ancient capital
of Bulgaria, Veliko-Tirnivo, and ex¬
tends along both banks of the Yantra
river. Mountain towns generally are
short of arable land, and the people
who settled the area in the 16th cen¬
tury had to find other ways of existing
than farming; so they turned to crafts¬
manship.
There was no electricity then, but the
fast flow of the river was there to
work for them, harnessed by their
own ingenuity. They produced excel¬
lent quality goods, and then set out
to sell them, becoming tradesmen in
the process. But salesmanship is not
easy. It demands special qualities. The
people of Gabrovo had to fight off
competition, pull in the customers, flat¬
ter them and convince them that buying
Gabrovo goods was the hallmark of a
customer with an eye for a bargain.
With this in mind, the tradesmen
of Gabrovo exaggerated some of their
own defects, and passed themselves
off as simpletons. They constantly
polished this particular tactic and laugh¬
ed at themselves as hard as they
could, provided it was good for busi
ness. They made up jokes and anec¬
dotes about their own shortcomings
but never about the goods they
were selling. That is a fundamental
rule of Gabrovo humour.
As the years went by, the small
craftsmen were joined by larger enter¬
prises. The first factories went up.
The town was slowly changing. But
Gabrovo was only really transformed
after the Second World War. The old
workshops and small factories were
replaced by modern industrial plants
from which goods are today exported
to dozens of countries.
The people's lives too have chan¬
ged. Gabrovo is now a pleasant and
steadily growing town. It has wide
streets, parks, monuments, elegant
buildings and attractive suburbs.
Nothing is left of its former poverty,
hovels and narrow dusty streets. All
that is a thing of the past. Only the
Gabrovo flair for business, its inge¬
nuity and enterprise and its sense of
humour constantly replenished by
streams of new jokes carry on un¬
changed.
One striking example of this enter¬
prising spirit is the well-known
museum-village of Etara just outside
the town. The village recreates for
visitors the atmosphere and way of life
of 150 years ago. (See "Unesco Cou¬
rier" October 1975). Its narrow paved
streets are lined with fine examples
of the old architecture of Gabrovo, and
with small workshops where master
craftsmen and their apprentices prac¬
tise traditional skills using the old ma¬
chinery powered by the flow of the
river. The number of foreign tourists
visiting Etara is growing annually.
And, of course, Gabrovo remains a
town bubbling with humour. The peo¬
ple seem to be born with a sense of
fun which they keep for the rest of
their lives. In the centre of the town,
on a rock in the middle of the river,
is a statue of the town's founder,
Ratcho the Blacksmith. Another exam¬
ple of the citizens' parsimonious out- .
look: why not use the useless rock
as a pedestal and save the good
land on the riverbanks?
The unofficial symbol of Gabrovo
is a tailless cat. Gabrovians, it is
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
© Francis Georges, Belgium
©
i,i*ii!M,.i,íi.MI.,i»MiI,ii*1,i,|.,i.Ií' l 'i'
i1 li ll iM u'ii' »' ifi.iMi ill1
"' . A'li'i ¡'
'"III.1!1!, .ii
li'iVi/i' i
W'i'i'.i.'m
I'll'»
'l'll',"
I'll
Ii1!!.1!
'»Il '
'U
M
..'.{'
'S1
i«
'i S
iVil
.. >i,i
iiVii
'¡'.'M
said, cut their cats' tails, so that the
animals take less time to pass through
a doorway, thus saving heat in winter.
Each May, Gabrovo organizes a
great festival of humour and satire.
It starts off with a symbolic gesture:
the tail of an enormous dummy black
cat is cut off. Then comes the carni¬
val procession, with floats presenting
scenes from satirical shows, and illus¬
trating old jokes, with participants
dressed in fantastic costumes and
wearing masks, singing and dancing.
Nowadays a special place is reser¬
ved at the festival for Scottish humour,
and the links created between Gabro¬
vo and Aberdeen. The people of Ga¬
brovo, dressed in Scottish costume,
carry posters written in English and
act out Scottish sketches.
All this is treated as excellent fun
by participants and audience alike with
spectators packed on the pavements,
massed at the windows or even look¬
ing down from vantage points on the
roofs in order not to miss anything.
But the Gabrovo festival is not just
a carnival. During a whole week,
theatres and cinemas present all-com¬
edy programmes. At the same time,
conferences discuss the nature of hu¬
mour and satire. Exhibitions on hu¬
mour are staged, and the festival ends
with games and comic contests in the
town stadium.
In. May 1973 the first International
Biennial of Cartoons was launched
during the Gabrovo festival, under the
title "Gabrovo 73". Its display of over
1 ,300 works by 348 artists and car¬
toonists from 22 countries, gave a pro¬
mising start to this international cul¬
tural event. The second Biennial, held
during the 1975 festival, was even more
successful.
The Biennial of Cartoons was the
first important event organized by
Gabrovo's "House of Humour and
Satire". Now completed, this centre
has its own film projection room, a
theatre for staging satirical works, and
conference and exhibition halls. The
idea of setting it up was welcomed
internationally and received warm
support from well-known humorists
such as Charlie Chaplin, Jean Effel,
Herluf Bidstrup, Eric Lipinsky, among
many others.
The House of Humour gets a steady
flow of enthusiastic letters from all
over thé World and has received more
than 10,000 contributions for its collec¬
tion. Through its wide-ranging pro¬
gramme, this remarkable cultural cen¬
tre will contribute to the development
of humour, and will promote contacts
and exchanges between creative ar¬
tists in this field.
The humour of Gabrovo is thus part
of Bulgaria's national heritage and one
that is not kept in museums or guard¬
ed in safes. It lives in the hearts
of those who enjoy it and who are
proud to preserve and enrich the.
traditions of Bulgaria's "capital of
humour" f
Bogomll Geraslmov
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
mKÊKKKKKmmKKM
DD
g 0)
3 =
II
f:
8*
¿i
5|
Ihe
14O0V1 RUNNER'S
digest
FIFTEENTH ¿NNIVERS/lftY ISSUE
Vol. XVI. Ho. 2
December, 1974
12.50 per copy
Mo> Mi oS'lt
Á0OlOHO/8d
"îiioiora
p|DUjnoíai||
Shown above are two title pages belonging to the 15th anniversary Issue of one
periodical it all depends which half of it you're reading: The Worm Runner's
Digest or The Journal of Biological Psychology. The Worm Runner's Digest
was started by American biologist James V. McConnell and a small team of
colleagues as a scientific joke. It became an immediate success and was
even taken seriously in some scientific circles. Later serious articles were
mixed in with the spoofs and the magazine then split in two, one half upside
down. Photo right is a drawing of planaria by the Dutch artist M.C. Escher.
It is shown upside down in The Journal of Biological Psychology, above.
WORM - BREEDING
WITH TONGUE IN CHEEK
or the confessions of a scientist
hoist by his own petard
by
James V. McConnell
JAMES V. McCONNELL, founder-editor of
the satirical magazine The Worm Runner's
Digest and later The Journal of Biological
Psychology, is Professor of Psychology at the
Mental Health Research Institute, University of
Michigan, Ann Arbor (U.S.A.). The author of
numerous papers and articles on planarian
worms and the biochemistry of learning, he has
edited the volume The Worm Re-Turns: The
Best from the Worm Runner's Digest (1965).
A longer version of this article originally appeared
in Unesco's quarterly Impact of Science on
Society (July-September 1969). It has been
very slightly amended to bring it up to date.
FOR sixteen years now, I've pub¬
lished a somewhat humorous
semi-scientific journal called Worm
Runner's Digest. Herewith begins my
confession. . For the Digest started as
my own personal little joke on the
Scientific Establishment but has turned
out to be more of a joke on me.
I've lost grants because of the Di¬
gest, had my laboratory experiments
questioned not because of their content
but because of the Digest, had articles
I submitted to other journals turned
down because I dared to cite studies
published in the Digest. It would seem
that a little humour goes a very long
way towards excommunication!
This scurrilous journal will seem
humorous to you only if you happen
to know a great deal about flatworms.
On the off chance that some of the
finer planarian points are lacking from
your store-house of knowledge, 1 will
duly explain a bit about the psychology
of worms so that you will gain some
insight into the psychology of worm
runners. It's a strange tail, I assure you.
The planarian, or common flatworm,
is a small aquatic animal that seldom
grows to more than three centimetres
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
r
in length and is found in ponds, streams
and rivers throughout the world, I got
interested in the beast because it's
the simplest animal on the phylo-
genetic tree that has a true brain
and a human-type nervous system.
But the planarian is famous for many
reasons beyond its brain. For instance,
it is the simplest form of life to have
true bilateral symmetry which means
that you can cut it in half from head to
tail and the left half will be a mirror
image of the right. And it has about
the most mixed-up sex life of any
animal going.
Let's face it: the planarian is that
psychological anomaly, an anti-Freu¬
dian animal. To begin with, it is an
hermaphrodite, having a complete set
of both male and female sex organs.
The flatworm lacks a mouth; instead,
it has a pharynx in the middle of its
body that it extrudes when it comes in
contact with food. The pharynx latches
on to whatever is to be the meal and
the worm sucks the juices up through
it as through a drinking .straw.
As a graduate student at the Uni¬
versity of. Texas, I had undertaken a
project with another student, Robert
Thompson, to see if the planarian could
be trained. Presumably, since it is the
simplest animal to possess a true brain,
it should be the simplest animal capable
of showing true learning (or so the
psychological theories of the day
insisted).
So Thompson and I set up an exper¬
iment in which we demonstrated at
least to our own satisfaction that the
flatworm could be taught the type of
lesson that Professor Pavlov called the
conditioned response. Later, when I
went to the University of Michigan at
Ann Arbor as a struggling young
instructor, the head of the Psychology
Department called me into his office
for a friendly little chat.
"Jim", he told me, "you may have
heard a nasty rumour that to survive
in the academic world, you must
'publish or perish'. I just want you to
know that the rumour is true. I'm sure
you know what is expected of you, but
I have a favour to ask. If at all poss¬
ible, will you please try to do good
research. But if you can't, for God's
sake, publish a lot of bad research,
for the Dean won't know the difference
anyhow."
I got the message and right away
set up the first "worm lab." at the
University of Michigan.
I was given a tiny little basement
room and enough funds to purchase
a very modest amount of equipment
and a few worms. Like all eager
young instructors, I was wise enough
to talk two very bright young students
(Daniel Kimble and Allan Jacobson)
into doing all the actual work for me.
But I had a problem; we had
demonstrated that worms could learn,
so what were we to do next? For
a long time 1 puzzled over this problem,
then recalled that one day when
Thompson and I were working at the
University of Texas, we had had a
wild idea.
Planarians not only reproduce
sexually, but asexually as well (one
might say they have by far the best
of both worlds). When a worm is first
hatched from its egg, it is fully equipped
to do everything but reproduce. After
a few months of fattening up, it
reaches puberty and begins mating.
Sexual activity continues for three to
four years, after which the animal
seems to go into a senile decline,
becomes all lumpy and misshapen and
then a miracle often occurs.
One day as the animal is crawling
along the bottom of some pond, the
tail develops a will of its own and
grabs hold of a rock and refuses to be
budged. The head struggles to get
things going again, but no matter how
hard the head pulls, the tail remains
obstinately clinging to the rock.
Not able to convince the tail to get r
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
> on with it, the head does the next
best thing: it pulls so hard that the
whole animal comes apart at the
middle. The head then wanders off,
leaving the tail to manage as best
it can.
Now, if you cut a human being in
half across the waist, he has a
tendency not to survive the operation.
But if you do this to a flatworm, you
merely trigger off asexual reproduction
in the same way that the animal
occasionally does itself. For the head
will grow a new tail in a matter of five
or six days, and the tail, clinging
gallantly to its rock, will regenerate an
entire new head (complete with brain,
eyes and full sensory apparatus) in a
matter of a week or two.
Furthermore, each of the regenerated
portions of the beast will soon grow
up to the same size as the original
animal and, being rejuvenated as well
as regenerated, will begin sexual
mating again. (Now there's a topic
that needs further research if ever
I saw one!)
Thompson and I, knowing this odd
habit of the flatworm, thought it might
be clever if we trained a worm, then
cut it in half, let the head grow a new
tail and the tail grow a new head, and
then tested both halves to see which
half remembered the original training.
Thompson and I never had the time to
do that experiment at the University
of Texas, but at Michigan I had
students, worms and apparatus, so we
set out to see what would happen.
To our great surprise, we found that
the heads remembered (a month after
original training) just as much as did
worms that had been trained but not
cut in half at all. Apparently, if you
are a worm, losing your tail does not
affect your memory. To our greater
surprise, we found that the tails
remembered even better than did the
heads. Obviously, for worms, losing
your head actually improves your
memory!
These odd results suggested to us
that, in the planarian at least, memories
might not be stored just in the head
section. Our next experiment con¬
sisted of chopping a trained animal
in several pieces and letting all of them
regenerate. As we half expected,
each regenerate showed memory of
what the original animal had been
taught.
Slowly it began to dawn on us that
the usual theories of memory storage
just didn't hold, for these all insisted
that memories were stored neuro-
physiologically in the brain. Since our
regenerated worms had to re-grow an
entire new brain, it seemed to us that
they must be storing their lessons
chemically.
In other words, whenever the worm
learned something, there had to be
some corresponding change in the
molecules in their bodies Qust as there
must be an electrical or mechanical
change in a computer each time it
stores a bit of data). Our chemical
theory of memory was interesting, but
how to go about proving it?
People have personalities and, after
you've studied them a while, it becomes
apparent that planarians do, too. That
is, each organism reacts slightly dif¬
ferently from its cousins and brothers.
But chemical molecules are all sup¬
posed to be the same. So, when one
worm learned his lesson in our training
apparatus, we assumed that the chemi¬
cal changes inside his body were more
or less the same as those that would
take place in any other worm's body
when it learned the same lesson. Now,
that's a perfectly tenable hypothesis if
you don't "happen to know much about
zoology or biochemistry so, blessed
with a most enthusiastic ignorance of
such arcane topics, we ploughed
ahead.
Here was our reasoning. Worms
are rather special. Not only can you
cut them in half, and each piece will
regenerate into an intact organism,
but you can also play all sorts of
sadistic games with them.
If you slice the head in half, from
the tip of the snout down to where
the worm's Adam's apple would be
(if it had one, which it doesn't), and
then you keep the two sections of
the head separated for 24 hours, each
section will regenerate separately.
You'll end up with a two-headed worm.
Interestingly enough, a chap at Wash¬
ington University in St.Louis worked
with two-headed planarians later on
and found, to our delight, that these
animals learn significantly faster than
Photo of the common flatworm or planarian,
the origin of the humorous scientific
magazine The Worm Runner's Digest.
do normal beasts. So, as far as the
worm is concerned, two heads are
indeed better than one!
And if two heads aren't enough for
you, split each of them again, and
you'll have four heads on the same
body. You can get up to twelve heads
at once, if you and the worm are
interested in such things. More than
that, you can take the head from one
animal and graft it on to another
planarians don't reject tissue grafts
the way that most higher organisms do.
Well, if the memory molecules were
the same from one worm to another,
why couldn't we train one worm,
extract the chemicals from it, inject
them somehow into another, and thus
transfer the "memory" from one beast
to another?
itf A LANp of Trte WrtP,
lite ccoz-eyev arb K1M45.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
For several months we tried to do
just that, but we failed, simply because
we were rather stupid about it all.
Our hypodermic needles were far too
large and we tried to inject far too
much material. The poor little worms
swelled up like balloons; a few popped.
Eventually, though, a brainstorm hit us.
Hungry planarians are cannibalistic.
If we couldn't make the "transfer"
using our crude injection techniques,
perhaps we could induce the worms to
do the. work for us.
So, in our next experiment, we
trained a group of "victim" worms and
then chopped them in pieces and fed
them to an unsuspecting group of
hungry cannibals. After the cannibals
had had a chance to digest their meal,
we promptly gave them the same sort
of training we had given the victims.
To our delight, the cannibals that had
eaten educated victims did significantly
better (right from the very first trial)
than did cannibals that had eaten
untrained victims. We had achieved
the first inter-animal transfer of
information.
After we had repeated this exper¬
iment successfully several times, we
went on to show that the chemical
involved in the transfer was RNA
(ribonucleic acid), a giant molecule
found in almost all living cells. For
we showed that we could achieve this
type of "memory transfer" using a
crude extract of RNA taken from the
bodies of trained planarians and in¬
jected into untrained worms (using, I
may say, a very, very small needle).
In recent years, a considerable
controversy has cropped up concern¬
ing a whole series of similar exper¬
iments using rats and mice as subjects
rather than worms. And, despite the
outcries of the orthodox, it does now
seem as if chemicals extracted from
the brains of trained rats and injected
into their untrained brethren does
cause much the same sort of "memory
transfer" as we had originally dis¬
covered in flatworms.
But I stray from the point. We
published our original regeneration
results in 1959 and at once found our¬
selves mentioned in several national
publications. Of course, none of the
journalists . took our work at all
seriously but, unfortunately for us,
there were hundreds of high-school
students around the country who did.
Many of the brighter students in the
biological sciences saw immediately
that the worm could make an intriguing
and most inexpensive substitute for the
rat. So in 1959 we were inundated
with letters from these bright young¬
sters asking us to tell them all about
the care and training of worms. (A
few more aggressive souls wrote us
demanding that we send them a few
hundred trained animals "at once",
because they needed them instantly
and didn't have time to mess around
doing the work themselves.)
I answered the first few letters per¬
sonally at great length, but when
several hundred arrived, it became
clear that some more efficient means
of communication would have to be
arrived at. So my students and I sat
down and wrote what was really a
manual describing how to repeat the
sorts of experiments we had been
working on.
It took us all of fourteen pages to
pour out our complete knowledge of
planarianology. We typed the material
up and reproduced it on "ditto" paper
(using purple ink guaranteed to fade
rapidly so that years later we wouldn't
be embarrassed by residual displays
of our youthful ignorance).
Now, I had always been noted for
the oddness of my sense of humour,
and the planarian research greatly
enhanced this reputation. Thus none
of my students considered it strange
that we should try to make a joke out
of this little manual, so joke it became.
First of all, it had to have a name.
In psychological jargon, a person who
trains rats is called a "rat runner",
because, presumably, his task is to
get the rats to run through a maze or
some other piece of apparatus. A
man who trains insects is a "bug
runner", and someone who works
with humans is, quite seriously, called
a "people runner". Obviously we were
"worm runners", and so the title of
our manual simply had to be Worm
Runner's Digest.
One of the girls designed a crest that
appeared on the cover, with a rampant
two-headed worm, a coronet of con¬
nected nerve cells at the top, a Latin
motto (which Arthur Koestler translates
as "When I get through explaining this
to you, you will know even less -than
before I started"), an S and R for
"stimulus-response", a 4> for psycho¬
logy, and a pair of diagonal stripes
painted the maize-and-blue colours of
the University of Michigan. (It wasn't
until years later that we learned that
in the language of heraldry, diagonal
stripes across your escutcheon mean
that you're descended from a bastard;
as I like to say, there's been a good
deal of serendipity in pur research.)
To top the manual off, we called it
"Volume I, No. 1", the joke being that
we had no intention of continuing its
publication. Little did we appreciate
the strength of the publish-or-perish
syndrome. Academic scientists are so
desperate that they will publish any¬
where (for the Dean really doesn't
know the difference), so to our utter
amazement, we began getting contri¬
butions for the next issue. Hoist with
our own petard, there was nothing we
CONTINUED PAGE 32
i!
oi
à
DC «
.o e
S a>
« O)
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
NASRUDIN HODJA
THE MAN WHO RODE
HIS ASS BACKWARDS
mmffià y:':, y.. wÈËm H
the legendary hero
of Muslim humour
whose wit and jocular wisdom
have the world splitting its sides
with laughter
by Ivan Sop
EW comic folk heroes in world
literature rival Nasradin Hodja,
the author of innumerable pranks and
the subject of waggish stories which
amuse and delight people from Mor¬
occo to the frontiers of China and
from Siberia to the Arabian Peninsula.
Stories by Nasrudin or about him are
found in some forty languages.
For centuries the name of Nasrudin
Hodja (Hodja is a term of respect,
meaning teacher) has been associated
with tales that are amusing, somewhat
naive, ribald, and yet imbued with pro¬
found folk-wisdom. These stories also
exemplify the use of wit and irony as
weapons against brutal force and
oppression.
But who was Nasrudin?
Some think he never existed and
that he is part of the inexhaustible
IVAN SOP, Yugoslav writer and literary critic,
is an authority on the humour of the international
folk hero Nasrudin Hodja. He has written a
doctoral thesis on this subject lor the University
oí Belgrade and is the author oí "The Meta¬
morphoses of Nasrudin", a book published in
1973. He is currently working with the Belgrade
Institute oí Literature and Arts.
fund of popular legend. Others are
convinced that he was a man who
actually lived and was born in Turkey,
but many countries claim to be his
place of birth.
According to tradition Nasrudin
was born about eight centuries
ago in Turkey, in the little village
of Harto near the township of Bivrihisar
(to the west of Ankara). For over a
century scholars have been trying to
discover where he really came from. In
Akcheir, another town in Turkey which
claims him as a son, a festival is held
periodically in his honour. This is
where he is supposed to be buried
and an inscription on the wall of his
mausoleum suggests that he died
some time before 1392. But there
is no means of proving these assertions
and theories.
According to legend, his tomb
was surrounded by columns but was
without any railings and merely had
a massive door with a padlock and no
key. This was said to be an example
of the wisdom of Nasrudin who used
to say that the doors were "closed
for his friends and open for his ene¬
mies"
CONTINUED PAGE 20
SYMMETRY PRINCIPLES
AT HIGH ENERGY
JANLARV J»-H. IH4 / UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI
bwhram kurfurtr-flu * Arnold FarimuttM EftlTOU
THE GLOBE-TROTTER
Nasrudin Hodja Is often depicted sitting
backwards astride his donkey. He
explained to his students why he did this:
"If I rode facing ahead", he said, "you
would be behind me. If on the other hand
you were to walk in front, you would turn
your backs' on me. I think therefore that
to ride this way solves all these problems
and besides it's far more polite!" In
Turkey, Nasrudin has been represented
in many ways: right, 18th-century
miniature in the Topkapl Museum, Istanbul;
bejow, cover of an illustrated book of
200 tales of Nasrudin by Alfred Mdrer,
published in French, Istanbul 1975. This
picture has also been used as a postcard
in Turkey. Nasrudin and' his donkey have
even crossed the Atlantic. Above, they
figure on the cover of a collection of studies
presented at a conference on high energy
physics held at the University of Miami,
U.S.A. (Symmetry Principles at High
Energy, published by W.H. Freeman and
Co., San Francisco and London, 1965.)
Anecdotes and aphorisms of Nasrudin
are scattered throughout the texts.
ALFRED MÖRER
CONTES CHOISIS
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
WHERE THERE'S
LIGHT THERE'S HOPE
Someone saw Nasrudin searching for something
on the ground. "What have you lost, Mulla?"
he asked. "My key", said the Mulla.
So they both went down on their knees and
looked for it. After a time the other man
asked: "Where exactly did you drop it?"
"In my own house." "Then why are you looking
here?" "There is more light here than
inside my own house."
From "The Exploits of the Incomparable Mulla Nasrudin",
by Idries Shah, illustrations by Richard Williams © 1966,
Mulla Nasrudin Enterprises Ltd, published by Jonathan Cape
Ltd, London
A MAN OF HIS WORD
Nasrudin had some good news for the King, and after
a great deal of difficulty managed to gain an audience
although by tradition every subject theoretically had
the right of immediate access to the Court.
The King was pleased with what he had been told.
" Choose your own reward", he said. "Fifty lashes",
said Nasrudin. Puzzled, the King ordered that Nasrudin be
beaten. When twenty-five strokes had been administered,
Nasrudin called: "Stop!" "Now", he said, "bring in
my partner, and give him the other half of
the reward. The chamberlain, Your Majesty, would
not allow me to see you unless I would give him
exactly half of anything that I got for my good news."
From "The Pleasantries of the Incredible Mulla Nasrudin",
by Idries Shah, illustrations by Richard Williams and Errol le
Cain © 1968, Mulla Nasrudin Enterprises Ltd., published by
Jonathan Cape Ltd., London
ART OF IMPARTIAL JUDGEMENT
When the Mulla was a judge in his village, a dishevelled
figure ran into his court-room, demanding justice.
"I have been ambushed and robbed", he cried, "just
outside this village. Someone from here must have done
it. I demand that you find the culprit. He took my
robe, sword, even my boots."
"Let me see", said the Mulla, "did he not take your
undershirt, which I see you are still wearing?"
"No he did not."
"In that case, he was not from this village. Things are
done thoroughly here. I cannot investigate your case."
WHICH WAY ROUND ?
A man who had studied at many metaphysical
schools came to Nasrudin. In order to show
that he could be accepted for discipleship
he described in detail where he had been
and what he had studied. "I hope that you
will accept me, or at least tell me your ideas",
he said, "because I have spent so much of
my time in studying at these schools."
"Alas!" said Nasrudin, "you have studied the
teachers and their teachings. What should
have happened is that the teachers and the
teachings should have studied you. Then we
would have had something worthwhile."
THE
THOUSAND
AND ONE
PRANKS
OF .MULLA
NASRUDIN
Nasrudin Hodja, the great comic folk hero of the
Muslim world, whose origins go back to medieval
times, has become an international character of
universal appeal. The anecdotes of Nasrudin are
enjoyed for their exhilarating humour and admired for
their jocular wisdom.
"Good enough for Nasrudin" is the hallmark of a
rib-tickling story in Turkey. Egypt, Syria, Yugoslavia,
Bulgaria, Greece, Iran, Pakistan and India, and he is
increasingly read in many other countries ranging
from the U.S.S.R. and U.K. to the U.S.A. and China.
A Soviet film has also been made depicting Nasrudin
as a people's hero.
The stories and witty drawings on this double page and
our cover are from two collections of Nasrudin tales
told by Idries Shah, a writer born in India from an
Afghan family, and published by Jonathan Cape Ltd.,
London : "The Exploits of the Incomparable Mulla
Nasrudin" (1966) illustrated by Richard Williams and
"The Pleasantries of the Incredible Mulla Nasrudin"
(1968) illustrated by Richard Williams and Errol le Cain
(see also front cover). A third book, "The Subtleties
of the Inimitable Mulla Nasrudin ".illustrated by Richard
Williams and Richard Purdum was published by
Jonathan Cape in 1973.
LAST YEAR'S NESTS
"What are you doing in that tree, Mulla?" "Looking for eggs."
"But those are last year's nests!"
"Well, if you were a bird, and' wanted a safe place to lay, would you build a new
nest, with everyone watching?"
From "The Pleasantries of the Incredible Mulla Nasrudin", by Idries Shah, illustrations by Richard Wil¬
liams and Errol le Cain © 1968, Mulla Nasrudin Enterprises Ltd., published by Jonathan Cape Ltd., London
From "The Pleasantries of the Incredible Mulla Nasrudin",
by Idrles Shah, illustrations by Richard Williams and
Errol le Cain © 1968, Mulla Nasrudin Enterprises Ltd.,
published by Jonathan Cape Ltd., London
SEE WHAT I MEAN ?
Nasrudin's tomb was fronted by an
immense wooden door, barred and
padlocked. Nobody could get into
it, at least through the door. As his
last joke, the Mulla decreed that the
tomb should have no walls around it ...
The date inscribed on the tombstone
was 386. Translating this into letters
by substitution, a common device
on Sufi tombs, we find the word
SHWF. This is a form of the word
"seeing", especially for making a
person see. Perhaps It is for this
reason that for many years the
dust from the tomb was
considered to be effective in curing
eye troubles ...
From "The Pleasantries of the Incredible Mulla Nasrudin", by Idries Shah, illustrations by Richard Wil¬
liams and Errol le Cain © 1968, Mulla Nasrudin Enterprises Ltd., published by Jonathan Cape Ltd., London
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Nasrudin Hodja is known by the name of
Goha in Egypt where many anecdotes are
told about him. "I saw your wife at the
market!" a neighbour remarked to Goha.
"That's right," Goha replied. "As it's her
fortieth birthday today, I propose to barter
her for two twenty-year-olds!" Widely popu¬
lar, Goha figures in a series of Egyptian
children's books, "Stories of Goha" by
Kamel Kilani, published by Dar Maktabaf .
al-Atfal, Cairo.. Drawing below Is from one;
of them, "The Sack' of Dinars".
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 16
He is always popularly represented
as an old man with a white beard
wearing an outsize turban, simply
dressed and sitting backwards astride
his donkey so as to be sure that he
is always facing in the right direction
for, as he says: "whatever I tell my
donkey to do, he does the opposite."
The character of Nasrudin, an aston¬
ishing blend of wisdom and native wit,
has long since gone beyond the
frontiers of popular Turkish literature.
He is part of the folklore of the Balkan
peoples, the Serbians, the Croatians,
the Macedonians, the Bosnian Muslims,
the Bulgarians and the Albanians.
His stories are also current in Iran,
Armenia, Georgia, the Caucasus, Tur¬
kestan, and in many other countries.
Nasrudin exemplifies the humour
that is deeply rooted in oral folk tra¬
ditions, so it is hardly surprising that
so many of his "brothers" are to be
found all round the Mediterranean.
The Arabs know him as Djuha,
Djoha, Djuhi or Goha, the Berbers as
.Si Djeha or simply as Djeha,. the
Maltese as Djahan, the Sicilians as
Giufa, the Calabrlans as Hioha or
Jovani.
In reality, Nasrudia is something of
an anti-hero, a parody of the epic hero;
he is poor, dirty, shabbily dressed and
uses coarse language. He steals
without hesitation when he has the
opportunity.
One day when he was singing while
washing himself, Nasrudin decided that
he had a very pleasant voice. When
he emerged from the bath house he
rushed to the top of the minaret of
the mosque and, although it was noon,
he called the faithful to evening prayer.
Someone shouted up from below:
"Fool. With such a horrible voice
you should be ashamed to give
the call to evening prayer when It's
midday." Nasrudin leant over and
shouted back, "If some kind person
had built a bathhouse on top of the
minaret you would see what a fine
voice I have."
Innumerable stories Illustrate his
character and behaviour. When his
wife died Nasrudin did not seem very
upset. Shortly afterwards his donkey
died and he wept bitterly. Someone
said to him, "The death of your donkey
seems to have upset you more than
the death of your wife." Nasrudin
replied: "That's quite easy to explain.
When my wife died my friends told
me, "We'll find you an even more
beautiful wife." But when I lost my
donkey nobody said to me, 'Don't
worry, we'll buy you a stronger donkey.
Surely I've every reason to mourn my
donkey."
One day, Nasrudin was throwing
fermented milk into Lake Akshir. A
passerby called to him, "What on earth
are you doing? "I'm making yoghurt."
"Do you think it'll take?" asked the
man in astonishment. "I'm quite sure
it won't", answered Nasrudin, "but just
supposing it did!"
Since folklore is a valuable well-
spring of literature, anecdotes about
Nasrudin have served as an inspiration
for poets and authors of many national¬
ities, Russian, Ukrainian, Romanian,
German, Serbian and Turkish among
others. In some cases one adaptation
Influences another. The Yugoslav
writer Slovko Micanovlc used a book
about Nasrudin by the Soviet author
Leonid Golovyov as a model, in writing
his novel "Nasrudin Hodja in Istanbul".-
Nasrudin appears to have been
everywhere as we learn from ubiquitous
legends about his life. According to
one such story Nasrudin was a sage
living in Baghdad around the tenth
century, at the time of the Abbasid
Dynasty. Having been accused of
heresy during a period of religious
strife, he is said to have feigned mad¬
ness in order to save himself from
the scaffold.
Other accounts say he lived in Asia
Minor, in Anatolia, in the 13th or 14th
centuries. Tradition also has it that he
lived at the time of Sultan Bayezit and
his wars with Tamerlane in the late
14th and early 15 th centuries. And an
entire cycle of tales about him and
Tamerlane exists in Turkish folklore.
Some stories about Nasrudin and
Tamerlane, reflect the spontaneous
popular resistance to the Mongol con¬
queror. In the following stories, for
example, the dialogue between Nas¬
rudin and Tamerlane initially seems to
be merely an exchange of ideas but
then a sudden flash of Nasrudin's wit
makes Tamerlane seem ridiculous.
Tamerlane said to Nasrudin, "All
the Abbasid Caliphs are known by a
nickname. Al-Mustansir means 'dep¬
endent on God's help', al-Mu'taslm,
means "seeking protection in God'
and al-Mutawakkil means 'trusting in
God'. What would you have nick¬
named me if I had been one of
them?" Straight away Nasrudin repli¬
ed, "Tamerlane God-help-us."
One day Tamerlane Invited Nasrudin
to the bathhouse and asked him, "If
I had been a slave what do you think
I would be worth?" "Fifty pence"
replied Nasrudin. Tamerlane was
offended: "Don't you realize that the
loin cloth I am wearing is alone worth
that?" "Yes, of course", replied Nas¬
rudin smiling, "That's my offer for the
lot!" , .-r
One day when Nasrudin was with
Tamerlane in his palace, a platinum
mirror was brought to the conqueror
as a gift. Tamerlane looked at himself
in the mirror and a. few tears came
into his eyes. Noticing this, Nasrudin
in his turn began to weep. Soon
Tamerlane recovered his composure
whereas Nasrudin was still sobbing.
"Nasrudin" said Tamerlane, "when
I saw how ugly I was in the mirror,
I was a bit upset. Knowing how
fond you are of me I wasn't sur¬
prised to see that you shared my
sorrow, and I thank you. But, tell me,
why are you still crying now that I
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
have got over it?" "Sire", said Nas¬
rudin, drying his tears, "seeing your
face for a moment in the mirror upset
you for quite a time. I see you all
day long. It's only right that I should
weep a little longer.
Variants of these stories occur in '
which ordinary people get the better ,
of the powerful and in which the
"adversary" who is made a fool of ¡s
not Tamerlane but a bey or a pasha.
However Nasrudin's witticisms some¬
times have quite a different character,
as in the following story. A man
said to Nasrudin, "Look at that goose
running over there." "And what's that
to do with me?" Nasrudin replied.
"But it's just gone into your house",
the man said. "And what's that to do
with you?" retorted Nasrudin.
Nasrudin, one of the poorest of men,
also stands up for a certain stan¬
dard of human dignity and moral inte¬
grity although it is the comic vein
which prevails, as in the following tale.
One day Nasrudin was a guest at
dinner and turned up wearing thread¬
bare clothing. Everyone ignored him.
Feeling his pride hurt, he slipped out
of a side door, hurried home, changed
into suitable clothing, put on a beauti¬
ful fur-lined cloak and returned to the
palace. This time he was welcomed
at the door with great ceremony and
was ushered to a place at the prin¬
cipal table. He was offered the best
dishes and every attention was lavish¬
ed upon him. After enjoying all his
favourite foods, Nasrudin took hold of
the fur on the ample sleeve of his
cloak, leant towards it and pushed it
affectionately towards a well-filled
plate saying "Eat, eat, my furl"
The other guests were intrigued
by this prank. "Nasrudin, what are
you doing?" With his customary good
humour, he described what sort of
welcome he had been given on his
first arrival and the reception that had
been accorded him when he returned a
second time. "As it is my fur that has
received the honour", he concluded, "it
too should share in the feast".
The humour of Nasrudin is not only
social satire, it is also a way of looking
at life which was obviously not always
in agreement with the ideology and
ruling powers of the time.
The character of Nasrudin is a pro¬
duct of anonymous creators: crafts¬
men, peasants, shopkeepers, donkey
drivers, carters, beggars, shrewd
townsmen and countrymen, dreamers,
all those who felt social injustice more
clearly than they understood the
reason behind it, and who expressed
their human predicament in stories,
tales, jokes and quips.
Nasrudin's stories have a value
which is universal: always using the
same effect, that of comedy, they
approach and sometimes even rival
the great works of world literature.
Ivan Sop
STROKE OF LUCK
Nasrudin Hodja lost his donkey and began to look for it crying "Thanks be to
God, thanks be to God". "Why are you thanking God?" people asked him.
"I'm thanking him because I wasn't on the donkey when It got lost, otherwise I
should have got lost with iL"
ONION MYSTERY
One day when Nasrudin Hodja was stealing onions in a field he was caught by the
owner, who asked what he was up to. "I was blown here by the wind", replied
Nasrudin unabashed. "And who uprooted the onions?" "I caught hold of them
to stop myself being blown away." "And how did they get in the sack?" "That's
just what I was wondering when you interrupted me."
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
© Georgl Anastasov, Bulgaria; from the catalogue of the
2nd Int. Biennial of Cartoons and Small Caricatural Sculpture«,
published by the House of Humour and Satire,
Gabrovo, Bulgaria, 1975
Ahappy April Fools' Day to all
our readers! Even if this issue
didn't coincide with International
Laughter Day, I would still wish you
a happy April Fools' Day because for
people who like to laugh, the first
day of April lasts all year round. And
since one of the Specialized Agencies
of the United Nations and its magazine
are showing an interest in laughter,
this is just the moment to wish the
whole world a happy April Fools' Day.
What does the world have to do
with laughter and what is laughter
to the modern world? And what does
laughter have to do with Unesco?
I think it is all to do with the nature
of humour and its broad social rele¬
vance. As an organization dealing with
education, science and culture, Unesco
strives to express in its work the moral
awareness of mankind. Laughter, by
asserting the high ideals of goodness
and humanism, favours the develop¬
ment and heightening of this aware¬
ness and promotes the growth of the
ideals which guide it.
The dictionary tells us that to laugh
means "to give audible expression
to an emotion by the expulsion of air
from. the lungs..." This is true as far
as it goes, but if laughter were only
the expulsion of air, it would not be
much good for anything but blowing
down houses of cards.
Actually, as the great Russian satir¬
ist Mikhail Saltykos-Shchedrin has
pointed out, laughter is a very power¬
ful weapon, for nothing so discoura¬
ges a vice as the knowledge that it
will be perceived and ridiculed by
others. The- laughter of the great
French philosopher Voltaire strikes
and sears like a flash of lightning.
Laughter knocks down idols. Wit was
the favourite weapon of Vladimir
Mayakovsky, the greatest revolutio¬
nary poet of the 20th century. Char¬
les Chaplin holds that humour is to¬
day's antidote to hate and fear it
clears the fog of suspicion and anxie¬
ty that envelopes the world.
All panegyrics of laughter extol it
as a powerful weapon. But, unlike
other weapons, laughter is extremely
selective in its choice of targets. A
bullet does not care who stops it
but laughter always homes in on
scoundrels.
THE WORLD
WILL NEVER
DIE IF
IT DIES
LAUGHING
by Yuri B. Botyev
YURI B. BORYEV, Soviet writer and literary
critic, is a senior research associate at the
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences' Institute of
World Literature. He participated in the 1975
international symposium on humour and satire
in Gabrovo, Bulgaria (see article page 9).
He is the author of over 250 articles and 1 0 books.
His works have been published in 17 languages.
We are talking here, of course,
about satire, for humour is always
harmless, though not toothless. Satire
is Indignant laughter, aimed against
vices of mankind. Humour is
friendly laughter, aimed against the
defects that are the other side of our
better qualities, laughter aimed at
friends and at things that correspond
to our ideals.
\ In the nuclear age, laughter is the
only weapon that may be praised
without violating humanitarian princi¬
ples, for laughter ¡s a creative, not
a destructive weapon, in other words,
an anti-weapon. Incidentally, every¬
thing there is to say about creative
laughter was said long ago by the
ancient Egyptians, who envisaged the
creation of the world like this: God
laughed, and the seven gods who rule
the world were born. After the first
burst of laughter there was light, after
the second, water, and so on until,
finally, after the seventh and last peal
of laughter, the soul was born.
This notion .that laughter was the
source of the world's creation is in
keeping with. a saying popular in the
Bulgarian town of Gabrovo: "The
world has not perished because it has
always laughedl" (see article page 9).
Humour and satire by their very
nature are democratic. Laughter is
very much a collective phenomenon,
tied up with a sense of community.
Henri Bergson, the great French phi¬
losopher, quotes an interesting exam¬
ple ¡n his book, Le Rire. During an
exceptionally inspired sermon by. a
well-known local preacher, only one
man failed to react in any way, being
moved neither to tears nor laughter.'
When asked why, he replied, "I don't
belong to this parish." Laughter is
a social reaction, it has a collective
nature: "Laugh and the world laughs
with you, weep and you weep alone."
Satire ¡s a special kind of social
criticism designed to organize public
opinion and orientate it aesthetically.
By its nature, therefore, satire is
linked to democratic traditions.
I am not, of course, suggesting that
humour and satire do not exist in
undemocratic societies, but that laugh¬
ter is part of the richest fabric of a
people's life. Democracy provides
the most favourable conditions for the
art of comedy, showing tolerance to¬
wards even the most caustic satire.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
mnmmnnm
mmnmmn
© D. Koprlvchtenov, U.S.S.R.
The very fact that laughter ¡s addres¬
sed to public opinion and not to offi¬
cialdom shows its democratic nature.
Even the most ancient examples of
satire show its democratic origins and
character. Aristotle claimed that com¬
edy had its beginnings in ancient
Greece in the democratic period follow¬
ing the banishment of the tyrant
Theagenes. Only a democracy could
tolerate the frank personal nature of
the comedies of antiquity.
When the tyrant Dionysius wanted
to get to know Athens, Plato sent
him Aristophanes' comedies, saying,
"If he understands these comedies,
he will understand the Athenian
State." Born of and nurtured by demo¬
cracy, comedy has always been a
grateful child and repaid its mother's
kindness.
"If subordinates were allowed to
laugh in the presence of their supe¬
riors, then we could say farewell to
subservience," wrote the great 19th-
century Russian democrat and revo¬
lutionary Alexander Herzen. This cha¬
racteristic, the social function of laugh¬
ter, is what gives Andersen's mar¬
vellous tale "The Emperor's New
Clothes" its satirical point. The em¬
peror is an emperor only so long as
those around him maintain their ser¬
vile attitude towards him. But when
the people believed their eyes and
realized that the emperor had no
clothes on, it was indeed good-bye
to subservience the people began
to laugh.
As time goes by, the democratic
role of satire grows. . In the future,
it will no doubt be satire that will
replace the present agencies and me¬
thods for the prevention of anti-social
behaviour. The disturber of the estab¬
lished social order will be punished
by public ridicule, which will be a more
effective and perhaps an even more
severe kind of lesson and punishment
than the coercive measures hitherto
taken by society.
Powerful though the effect of laugh¬
ter in society may be, let us not over¬
estimate its possibilities. Ten years
after the publication of Gulliver's Trav¬
els, Jonathan Swift expressed his
amazement that toadying, stupidity in
high places, harebrained scheming,
vain ambitions and other human vices
could still exist after he had so harsh¬
ly and convincingly ridiculed them.
Laughter can be effective only ¡n
conjunction with other means, includ¬
ing action in the fields of politics,
economics and culture in general.
This is the right moment to recall
the Bulgarian town of Gabrovo I men¬
tioned earlier.
When, in the spring of 1975, I ar¬
rived from warm and sunny Moscow in
cloudy, rainy Gabrovo, and when the
next morning, wanting to shave, I spent
an hour searching for the shaver-plug
and finally found it, of all places,
under the table, I realized that I was
in the humour capital of the world and
that this was merely an example of
a Gabrovian practical joke.
Yet nowhere in the town did I find
a monument to Aristophanes, or a
street named after Gogol, or a Mark
Twain Square, or a Yelin Pelin Way,
or a Rabelais Avenue, or even a
dead-end named after the theoretician
of laughter, Yuri Boryev. However, I
did find the wonderful "House of
Laughter", where I saw a widely rep¬
resentative and well-presented inter¬
national exhibition of cartoons.
Some cities are built on oil, like
Abadan, or on coal, like Donetsk.
Gabrovo's mineral resource is the pure
gold of folk humour. What a good
thing it is that this resource is begin¬
ning to benefit the whole world. Fes¬
tivals of humour have become a tra¬
dition in Gabrovo. The Gabrovo car¬
nival is colourful, witty and full of
folk humour and the spectacle attracts
people from all over Bulgaria and
abroad.
And ¡t is good to know that the
idea has been taken up elsewhere.
The Soviet city of Odessa, famous
not only for its courage during the
Second World War, but also for the
quick wit of its inhabitants, has
started to hold an annual Spring Fes¬
tival of Humour. The main theme of a
recent Odessa carnival was: "What
have you done to bring the population
of'your city up to a million?"
But then there are also Tarascón
in France, birthplace of the famous
Tartarln, and Windsor in England, with
its merry wives, immortalized by ^
Shakespeare, and many other towns r
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
y throughout the world that are famous,
or worthy of being famous for their
wit.
It is worth recalling that even in the
darkest periods of the Middle Ages,
every European spent a quarter of his
life at carnivals, since the high days
and holidays of those times added up
to three months out of every year!
At one time, each of the seven
cities of ancient Greece contended for
the honour of being the birthplace of
Homer, incontestable proof that all
of Greece claimed the Iliad as its
own. For centuries, at least six cities
of the Middle East and Central Asia
have claimed and still claim to be the
burial-place of Nasrudin Hodja. If
the "disturber of complacency," as
Nasrudin Hodja is known, has six
different burial places in six different
cities, that means that he never died
and never will die. He, like all heroes
of folk humour, is immortal (see ar¬
ticle page 16).
Humour is national and internatio¬
nal national in its form but in its
content common to all mankind. Spring¬
ing from the depths of a people's
life, and drawing upon the incompara¬
ble wealth of experience, humour
in its highest classical forms of ex¬
pression always becomes international
property. Universality is of the very
essence of humour.
Every people has its own favou¬
rite quick-witted hero who embodies
all its joys and sorrows, all its skill,
cunning, common sense and resour¬
cefulness, in short, everything neces¬
sary to live in a hard world among
the strong and the all-powerful, whom
one must deceive and outwit if one is
to survive. Much can be said about
each of these heroes of folk humour.
IVANUSHKA - DURACHOKIvan
the Fool for instance, is a favour¬
ite of Russian folk stories. He en¬
joys neither wealth nor station, he
suffers many trials and tribulations, the
high and mighty of this world look
down upon him with disdain and take
him for a fool, and Ivan himself is not
averse to posing as a fool.
But he is always ready to come to
the aid of a friend or of any good,
deserving person in need of a helping
hand, and finally all the troubles that
he encounters end up bouncing off
him. He conquers the strong, outwits
the clever, surmounts misfortunes and
hardships, and copes successfully with
even the most hopeless and insolu¬
ble problems, usually with some gain
for himself.
Nesterko is a hero of Byelorussian
folk tales who is too lazy to work and
not bold enough to beg, and so lives
by his wits and the bold inventiveness
of his artful dodges.
The cheerful rogue Pácalá is a hero
of Moldavian tales who is charac
terized by the quality of "dor" a
mixture of hopefulness and nostalgia.
Arlecchino, (Harlequin) the hero of
Italian folk comedy, is a country lad
bright, naive and direct. He is not very
practical and does everything on im¬
pulse, for which he Is rewarded with
cuffs and blows. But this does not
diminish his gaiety or his open and
childishly naive view of the world.
The favourite character of the French
puppet theatre, Polichinelle, is a jolly
hunchback, a bully and a mocker.
Nasrudin, the hero of Eastern hu¬
mour, goes by many names: the Azer¬
baijanians call him Mulla Nasrudin, the
Tajiks Mulla Mushfiki, the Turkomans
Nasrudin Hodja, the Tatars Ahmed
Akai, the Kazakhs and Kirghiz Aldar-
Kose. He is a convivial fellow, a man
of wit and wisdom, a rebel and a pro¬
tector of the weak.
ALL these national heroes of folk
humour are basically similar in
that they stand up for the downtrodden
and abused, are optimistic and cheer¬
ful by nature, witty, cunning, resilient
and able to overcome any obstacle.
But they are as different as the
national characters of the peoples who
created them.
And how instructive, significant and
relevant for the modern world are the
heroes of the great classics of com¬
edy: Tom Sawyer and Huckleberry
Finn, Khlestakov and Chichikov, Fal-
staff and Monsieur Jourdain, Don
Quixote and Sancho Panzal
Cervantes' two heroes, for instance,
though opposites in many ways, share
a wonderful and rare human quality
unselfishness. Because of this quality
we are ready to forgive them their
eccentricities, follies, shortcomings
and foolishness. Sancho Panza, the
realist, is no less unselfish than Don
Quixote, the dreamer. He abandons
his position of power, of which he has
grown weary, taking only some oats
for his ass and half a loaf for himself
the only profit derived from his
governorship. Yet his "laws" stand
and are known as the "Decrees of the
Great Administrator, Sancho Panza".
Don Quixote and Sancho Panza are
not of this world, because they are
too good for it. We may measure the
world by their standards of humanity,
unselfishness and wisdom. In the crazy
world of these characters, there is
so much freedom and poetry lost by
people in their everyday lives that in
the final analysis the mad Don Quixote
turns out to be more sane than the
"normal" people, who are consumed
by greed and the lust for power.
We would like to believe that the
happy day will eventually come when
the wisdom embodied in the images of
these and other immortal comic heroes
will become popular not only among
the citizens but also among the leaders
of the countries represented in the
United Nations.
Humour and satire represent the.
two poles of laughter. In between is
a whole world of different tonalities:
Aesop's merry and bitter mockery, Ra¬
belais' rollicking fun, Swift's biting,
sardonic humour, Erasmus of Rotter¬
dam's refined irony, Voltaire's wise
ridicule, Béranger's alternatively care¬
free and satirical laughter, Beau¬
marchais' sparkling wit, Daumier's
caricatures, Goya's horrifically cruel
world of grotesques, the barbed ro¬
mantic irony of Heinrich Heine, Ana¬
tole France's scepticism, Mark Twain's
gaiety, Shaw's Ironic humour, Jaroslav
Hasek's mischievous wry comedy, Go¬
gol's laughter through tears, Saltykov-
Shchedrin's wrathful, scourging,
scalding, scathing sarcasm, Chekhov's
soulful, sad lyrical humour, Maya-
kovsky's triumphant laugh, Gorky's
optimistic satire, and the Irrepressible
humour of Tvardovsky's hero, Vasily
Terkin.
What riches! Aristophanes, Juve¬
nal, Shakespeare, Molière, Lope de
Vega, Goldoni, La Fontaine, Krylov,
Griboyedov, Dickens, Fredro, Chalup-
ka, Caragiale, and Delavrancea all
masters in using the multi-coloured
pallet of laughter.
True laughter is rich in different hues
and glows with the most diverse emo¬
tions. This was beautifully expressed
by Leonardo da Vinci in his Mona
Lisa. What an inspired smile on
her beautiful countenance, at once
mocking, mischievous, tender, pensive,
sceptical and melancholic and express¬
ing many other deep and contradic¬
tory emotions.
TO live aright, one must laugh, and
to laugh one must know what
laughter is and what laws govern it.
I therefore suggest to you, dear
readers, that you get hold of a copy of
my book, Comedy, or How Laughter
Castigates the World's Shortcomings,
Purifies and Reforms Man and Asserts
the Joy of Living (1) and keep it by your
bedside you will never suffer from
insomnia. But before you fall asleep
please think about whether or not your
town is worthy of staging a carnival;
of humour in its turn. And when. you
awake in the morning, don't forget to
smile and wish everyone a happy April
Fools' Day.
In the world of laughter and in the
laughter of the world lies one of the
hopes for peace on earth. The citizens
of Gabrovo are right: the world will
never perish so long as it can laugh!
In other words, the world will never
die, if it dies laughing.
Yuri Boryev
(1) It has been published In Russian, Bul¬
garian, and German, and I hope that
all the "Courier's" readers understand one
of these languages, at least in their dreams.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE POLITICAL
AND SATIRICAL CARTOON
stepping in where angels
dread to fear
by Ivan Tubau
û̂
B ARDLY anybody in this exciting and
I I contradictory century would deny the
importance of the cartoons that appear in
the press. The cartoon is Important as a
historical document, as an x-ray of society
and politics and as a form of artistic and
literary expression.
What essential differences are there
between cartoon humour and oral or literary
humour?
According to Freud, humour is a first
step to liberation. "It is a triumph of
gaiety, and represents the victory of the
pleasure principle". But this victory must be
considered as resulting from frustration:
"Dreams become ingenious and amusing
because more direct and comfortable chan¬
nels for the expression of our feelings are
blocked". In the same way, we crack
jokes when other, more directly aggressive
forms of activity are denied us.
In line with this reasoning, it is sometimes
argued that a joke involves at least three
persons: the author, the reader (or listener)
and the "victim". This proposition may be
more or less valid for oral or written jokes,
but does not seem to apply to cartoons
and humorous drawings. Some of the best
cartoons produced this century and here
one inevitably thinks of the brilliant Saul
Steinberg have no victim.
A much more acceptable definition of
most of today's cartoon humour is this
one of Kuno Fischer's describing humour
in general: "Humour Is an unbiased judge¬
ment". According to Fischer, "Aesthetic
freedom is the detached observation of
things". "It may be", he adds, "that
this aesthetic freedom gives rise to a dis¬
tinctive type of judgement., which because
of its origin we will call detached judge¬
ment". And he affirms: "Freedom pro¬
duces humour and humour is simply a game
with ideas".
One could apply this definition to the
cartoon and call It a game with ideas,
IVAN TU BAU, Spanish cartoonist well known
by the pseudonym oí "Pastecca ", is an authority
on the graphic techniques of the mass media.
A journalist and writer, he has published many
studies on popular art and culture. The present
article is adapted from his book De Tono a
Perich. El chiste gráfico en la prensa española
de la posguerra (From Tono to Perich. The
Cartoon in the post-war Spanish Press) published
In Madrid (1973).
Drawing by Vazquez de Sola Spain Taken from
"Caricatures", © Editions Albin Michel, Paris, 1975
expressed in a drawing with or without the
assistance of words. However, the con¬
cept of "detached judgement" does not
apply to the majority of cartoons appear¬
ing in the press. On the contrary, the
most effective of them imply a definite
and categorical judgement based on a
real situation.
I have already used the word "freedom"
several times, and with good reason.
Without a certain degree of freedom, the
political cartoon and the social caricature
could not exist at least not in a legally
authorized publication.
And yet the cartoon often emerges from
conditions of "relative freedom", as a subs¬
titute for more direct forms of expression
which cannot be used openly. On this score
the Spanish essayist Carlos Castilla del Pino
has written: "The distinctive characteristic
of a joke is that by laughing at a problem,
one avoids the opposite down-to-earth and
serious approach. Thus, for instance, the
political joke shows critical awareness, but
it cannot replace active, direct criticism,
which is ruled out by either external or
self-imposed censorship.
The cartoon requires of its creator a i
minimum of dexterity in drawing and a I
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
, minimum of aesthetic judgement, two cha¬
racteristics which can only exist when a
certain level of culture has been reached.
An illiterate person may be able to draw
because he has inherited a natural cultural
. sensibility.
However, the cartoon in the opinion
of the Spanish humorist Maximo, which
I share is a literary form. Although
expressed fundamentally through drawing,
it is much closer to the narrative form of
expression than the plastic arts. One might
say (even of work like Steinberg's which
would seem to suggest the contrary) that
in humorous drawings the aesthetic treat¬
ment always takes second place and the
idea is always of primary importance.
ONCE we accept the status of the car¬
toon as a literary form, it seems lo¬
gical to point out that the development of
the cartoon is closely linked to the develop¬
ment of printing techniques. Even if some
scholars claim to have found traces of gra¬
phic humour in the contexts of prehistoric
times, Ancient Egypt, Classical Greece and
the Middle Ages, the cartoon as such was
born when printing allowed it to be widely
circulated.
Vases have been found in Apulia, Cam¬
pania and Sicily which, like the paintings
of Cranach, Breughel, Bosch or Teniers,
provide examples of a caricaturist's outlook
on the world, bordering on the humorous.
Other artists, such as the English painter
Hogarth or the Spaniard Goya, can be
seen as genuine humorists.
But the development of the cartoon went
hand in hand with the rise of periodical
publications: in Germany and the Nether¬
lands during the religious wars; in England
with the growth of journals of opinion;
and in France under the Bourbon monar¬
chy and during the Revolution, until Napo¬
leon and his rigid censorship of the press
cut short its development.
The spread of lithography brought the
cartoon a wider audience during the 19th
century. This was particularly striking in
France in publications like La Caricature
(1825) and Le Journal pour Rire (1848) both
founded by Charles Philipon, and in Chari¬
vari (1832). This last magazine numbered
among its contributors the great caricatu¬
rist Honoré Daumier. Almost every great
French caricaturist of the age appeared in
Philipon's magazines: Paul Gavarni, Gus¬
tave Doré, Grandville, Bertall and André
Gill.
In Spain, however, few printed cartoons
were produced during the religious wars
in Europe. "Spain itself was a caricature",
commented the 19th-century thinker Jacinto
Octavio Picon. Then during the war of
independence the country found an effec¬
tive pioneer in Leonardo Alenza.
In the mid-1 9th century, satirical publi¬
cations began to proliferate in Spain: Gil
Bias (1864), El Fisgón (1865), Doña Ma¬
nuela (1865), El Saínete (1867), La Gorda
(1868), Jeremías (1869), La Flaca (1871).
In the majority of them we find the work
of the prolific Francisco Ortego, the most
important cartoonist of 19th-century Spain,
whose work was to some extent carried on
by José Luis Pellicer (El Cohete, 1872).
In Spain, as elsewhere in the world, the
history of graphic humour, which began
about 150 years ago, has been a check¬
ered one. But in general terms we can
follow the evolution of cartoon humour from
the viewpoints of aesthetics, expression,
content and diffusion.
From an aesthetic viewpoint, the general
tendency in cartoon-drawing has been
towards progressive economy of line. Even
though the immense amount of detail shown
by contemporary cartoonists such as Topor
rivals the work of Bertall, in the 19th
century, the majority of today's cartoonists
have opted for a simplification of forms, a
rigorous visual synthesis and an economy
of detail which in the last century already
characterized the work of French illustra¬
tors such as Doré and Caran d'Ache.
If attempts to separate content and
form are regarded today as arbitrary and
controversial, then to try to separate the
purely aesthetic aspect of a cartoon from
the idea it seeks to express would be the
very height of absurdity.
The aesthetic evolution of the cartoon has
therefore been accompanied by changes in
its form of expression, which have also be¬
come more simplified. Texts or captions,
where present, have become shorter and
more cryptic, the drawings less concerned
with detail except where necessary.
Most important of all, however, is the
fact that the drawing has thus gained
complete autonomy and its own power as a
means of expression. Even the best humor¬
ous drawings of the last century were
almost always illustrations often excellent,
but ultimately no more than illustrations
of a given text which was often a play
on words or a literary joke; a text, in short,
which could have stood alone without the
image.
But although cartoons of this type are
still published today, they are no longer
considered to qualify as genuine graphic
humour if the drawing can be suppressed
leaving the words on their own. Only when
the text, title or caption have no meaning
without the image are we looking at a
genuine cartoon. Purists go even further:
only the "mute" joke, the cartoon with
no words, is for them the genuine article.
However, even without making this sort
of demand for absolute purity almost im¬
possible in political or topical cartoons a
close interdependence between text and
image is today considered indispensable
in graphic humour. And if we are now
thoroughly aware of this new dimension of
humour, it is very largely due to the car¬
toonists and humorists of North America:
they "invented" modern cartoons, as they
"invented" the silent movie comedies. This
conclusion in no way detracts from the
merit of their European forerunners, such
as Méliès or Max Linder in the cinema,
and Caran d'Ache in cartoons.
It is almost axiomatic that in talking about
American influence, we tend to consider
as American both the Rumanian Saul Stein¬
berg the greatest cartoonist of all time
and Charles Chaplin, who is an English¬
man. But in addition to Steinberg other art¬
ists working in America have had a strong
influence at a number of different levels:
Peter Arno, James Thurber, Charles Ad-
dams, among others. The New Yorker and
Britain's Punch, with its extraordinary Ron¬
ald Searle, have incubated the best of
modern humour.
Yet Spain too has made its own very
important contribution to graphic humour in
the form of "gratuitous humour" or what
I have called "Codornicesco" (1). It has
sometimes been suggested erroneously
that this is an imitation of the humour that
in Italy under Mussolini appeared in publi¬
cations such as Bertoldo. The simple fact
is that Spaniards and Italians made similar
discoveries at about the same time. It is
inevitable that periods of censorship which
prohibit critical humour foster development
of cartoonists specializing in allusive hu¬
mour, particularly in the field of the verbally
absurd, where both the Spanish and the
Italians have reached standards that are
difficult to match.
When it comes to the problem of content,
evolution has been much more blurred and
contradictory. One widespread idea is that
humour (critical humour, since drawings
such as Steinberg's by their nature lie on
the periphery of this argument) has mainly
concentrated, during the last century and
a good part of the present one, on poking
fun at anything new, from new means of
transport to political theories.
This idea demands a closer look. In gen¬
eral terms, one can say that cartoons have
been moving from "right" to "left" nobody
would consider the French cartoonist Sine
as a conservative, for example though ft
is equally true that progressive tendencies
were also expressed1 during the last century.
Even if it is true that Cham, Bertall and
Doré were clearly reactionaries (Doré took
refuge in Versailles when the Commune
took over Paris during the Franco-Prussian
war), and that Forain and Caran d'Ache
were violently anti-semitic, it is no less true
that Daumier (who refused the Legion
of Honour offered him by the Second Em¬
pire) displayed a distinctly critical and pro¬
gressive attitude in his work.
AT an international level, the fact that
some critical humour seems to have
moved towards non-conservative and some¬
times even revolutionary standpoints is due
to its circulation among a much wider and
more varied public.
This brings us to consider the dissemi¬
nation of humour generally. It Is obvious
that the number and circulation of humorous
publications have continued to Increase,
even if their growth has been uneven.
Cartoons have also. moved successfully
into the general information field after a
long period of finding the door shut in their
face and have won a better-placed and
wider showing in the daily press.
Most significant of all, the importance of
the cartoon is now almost universally recog¬
nized. Today cartoons are not used sim¬
ply to fill up space. They occupy a privi¬
leged place ¡n the best pages, next to
the main editorial or the articles of leading
contributors.
Ivan Tubau
1) Codornicesco: form of humour found in the
Spanish satirical weekly La Codorniz.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
k_ ;,-" -
i»*
a^L." M'iMi<itTn3írilli'-?¿:.'<" ..7 ~
' x 1
W '*m
1 1 C1 3 3
CIBID«
suais
oip non
. : :
auras
G : : 3 :
r ; m c
hiDJKBC
ce m e me
DODII
IBDBfl
;: C G B Si
il man
in
c c :
í
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
the Chinese
have a word
for (w) it HSIAO-hua
by Kristofer M. Schipper
A seventy-year-old scholar
became the father of a
son, and he proudly decided to call
the child 'Age'. The following year,
another son was born and, since the
new-born baby looked intelligent, the
father decided to call him 'Study'. A
year passed, and yet a third son came
into the world. The old scholar laugh¬
ed and said, 'Three sons, at my agel,
This is getting to be funnyl" So he
called his last-born 'Humour' (Hsiao-
hua).
"The children grew up, and one day
they went up into the mountains to
gather wood for their father. On their
return, the old scholar. asked his wife,
'Which of my three sons has brought
back the most wood?' His wife re¬
plied, "Age gathered a handful; Study
nothing at all; but Humour has brought
home a whole pilel'"
This ancient tale is a good illustra¬
tion of popular Chinese wisdom, which
holds that a little humour in life can
be more profitable than either exper¬
ience or education. The philosophers
of ancient China were well aware of
this, for they often quoted witty stories
in support of their theories. Mencius,
the ancient sage-philosopher, writing
in the 4th century B.C., tells the story
of a villager who, distressed to see that
his crops were not growing, tugged on
the stalks with his hands so as to
coax them into growing more rapidly.
He returned home at the end of the
day sighing, "I'm worn out; I've spent
the whole day helping the crops to
KRISTOFER M. SCHIPPER, born in Sweden,
Is Professor of Chinese Studies at the Ecole
Pratique des Hautes Etudes (Sciences of
Religion Section), University of Paris. He is
also Secretary of the newly-founded European
Association of Chinese Studies. He is an
authority on Taoist traditions of China and the
author of L'Empereur Wou des Han dans la
Légende Taoiste (Emperor Wu of the Han
Dynasty in Taoist Legend) 1965, and Le Feng-
teng, Rituel Taoiste (Feng-teng, Taoist Ritual)
1975. both published by l'Ecole Française
d'Extrême-Orient, Paris. He has published many
reference works as research aids in the little
explored field of Chinese Taoist ritual on which
he is at present preparing a long monograph.
Professor Schipper is currently also at work on
a new French translation of the writings of the
Chinese Taoist philosopher, Chuang-tzu.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
>;>
KU*
The Chinese ideogram reproduced above says hsiao-hua,
meaning "joke" or "funny story". A literary genre in its
own right, the hsiao-hua has enjoyed wide popularity since
ancient times in China, where the God of Joy (Hsi-shen)
here depicted on a 19th-century engraving (left) was traditionally
revered. Right, watercolour by Li-Ts'an (17th century)
shows the Immortal, Chung-li Ch'iian, riding his donkey
backwards, like Nasrudin Hodja (see page 16). The other
figure is the famed Taoist philosopher Chuang-Tzu
floating (frontwards!) on a huge gourd.
growl" His sons ran to the field to
see what he had done, only to find
that the stalks had already dried up...
The moral of the story lent added point
to Mencius' belief that we should
cultivate ourselves with care and
patience.
The Chinese call this kind of anec¬
dote hsiao-hua which literally means
"Laugh-talk" or "stories to make you
laugh". The example just quoted is
one of. the oldest examples of this
kind of humour in the world.
Though laughter is as old as huma¬
nity, or perhaps even older, the rôle
of humour changes from one culture
to the next. What is characteristic of
China's own particular brand of hu¬
mour is that the hsiao-hua, whose
origins were undoubtedly popular, was
incorporated into the classical written
tradition at a very early date.
Another very ancient form of hu¬
mour in China is known as ku-chi
which literally means "a side-swipe,"
and is now used for sarcastic and
satirical humour. Significantly, the first
examples of this were handed down
by a Taoist author named Chuang-tzu
(who lived in the 4th century B.C.).
As opposed to Confucianism, Taoism
embodied the Individual's aspirations
to freedom and the throwing-off of
social, pojitical and ideological cons¬
traints.
Chuang-tzu uses humour to fight
prejudice and dogmatism. For ins¬
tance, he shows us Confucius acting
as a sort of Chinese Don Quixote,
attempting to teach his moral precepts
to a highwayman known as Ch'i-the-
bandit. But the brigand turns out to
be just as eloquent as the Master,
and even manages to tie the latter
up in knots with his own arguments,
concluding with the parting shot,
"Since people call me Ch'i-the-bandit,
why don't they call you (who are
only a hypocrite after all) Confucius-
the-bandit?" 	
We later come across specialists
in this kind of satirical repartee at
the court of the emperors, and they
were referred to by this same term,
ku-chi. Tung-fang Shuo was one cele¬
brated ku-chi ; he was a courtier of
the Emperor Wu, during the Han dy¬
nasty (141-187 A.D.). One day, Tung-
fang Shuo drank a magic potion in¬
tended for the Emperor, and which
was supposed to make the latter im¬
mortal. The emperor was furious when
he found out, and decided to execute
the impertinent courtier forthwith.
But the latter argued, "Your majesty,
if the elixir works, then I am immortal
and you cannot put me to death. If,
on the other hand, the potion does
not work, then what crime have I com¬
mitted?" The emperor had to laugh,
and he pardoned the ku-chi.
Tung-fang Shuo subsequently be¬
came one of the patron saints of
laughter in Chinese .folklore. Other
clowns later came to be canonized
in China, such as the two Buddhist
monks Han Shan and Shih Te (8th cen¬
tury), so frequently represented ¡n
popular art The figure of the laugh¬
ing sage, perfectly conscious of the
truth, meanwhile became a familiar one
in Taoism. It is thought that it was
this Taoist tradition that influenced Chi¬
nese sculptors when carving their
first representations of the Buddha.
In the Buddhist grottoes at Yun-k'ang
the late fifth-century Buddhas wear
a mystical smile to be found neither
in Indian nor in Central Asian art.
The fondness of the Chinese for
laughter meant that the hsiao-hua very
soon became a literary genre in their
own right, and more than 70 antho¬
logies of anecdotes of all kinds have
been compiled over the centuries. The
oldest of these is called the Hsiao-lin
(The Forest of Laughter). Written by
a scholar named Han-t'an Ch'un
(c. 132-222), the Hsiao-lin's amusing
tales are perfectly harmless. They
are Innocent jests told in a gently
mocking tone. Here is an example:
"In the course of a dispute, a man
bit off his adversary's nose. The
judge wanted to condemn the man,
despite the accused's claim that the
victim himself had bitten his nose
off. The judge tried to reason with
him, 'But the nose is placed higher
than the mouth, so how could he pos
sibly have got up there to bite ¡t
off?' 'He stood on his bed' came the
prompt retort."
As we said earlier, the hsiao-hua
were popular in origin, and yet they
were mostly written down in classical
language. This anomaly can be ac¬
counted for by the fact that the highly
concentrated style of classical Chi¬
nese is ideally suited to sketching
a situation with a few light touches
and to rendering swift repartee.
Where we possess two versions of
an anecdote in Chinese literature, one
written in classical Chinese, the other
in spoken Chinese, the latter often
turns out to be two or three times
as long as the former.
But the scholars did not confine
themselves merely to transcribing
popular anecdotes. They also made
up their own hsiao-hua. One of the
more noteworthy features of these last
is their "historical" character, in that
they refer to named people, usually
famous scholars, situated in their
appropriate historical period.
This genre first made its appearance
at about the same time as the Hsiao-
lin quoted above, among a group of
cultivated and eccentric aristocrats,
the best known of whom have gone
down in history as the "Seven Sages
of the Bamboo Forest". These sages
enjoyed thinking up fresh witticisms
to pin down a person or a situation.
Their behaviour was often eccentric
and openly defiant of etiquette. Their
witticisms and jests were written down
in a famous anthology entitled Shlh-
shuo Hsin-Yü (Contemporary Short
Stories).
But, as was to be expected, only
people of their own time and milieu
could hope to understand fully the
sense of humour of these eccentric
scholars. Their jokes have lost all
meaning for us, though some acade¬
mics are striving obstinately to fathom
them out an activity that might have
brought a smile to the lips of the sages
themselves I
A good many other anthologies in
a similar vein have made their appea- »
ranee since. Some of the anecdotes (T
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
FROM
MAGISTRATE
PAO'S
CASEBOOK
Nineteenth-century Chinese polychrome engraving of an episode from a 16th-century comic novel entitled
Five Rats up to No Good in the Eastern Capital. It depicts the marriage of a rat which is later eaten by the
watchful cat In the novel, Pao Kung, a character based on a famous 11th-century magistrate-detective of
the same name, unravels a tangled web of criminal intrigue. The detective story as a literary genre was
actually born in China. A collection of detection tales (The Strange Cases of Magistrate Pao) was pu¬
blished by Panther Books, London, in 1970.
, have retained their meaning, but they
are too deeply rooted in the rather
special milieu that gave birth to them
to be translatable without pages and
pages of explanatory footnotes.
Humour of this sort really cannot
be said to cross all frontiers. In this
respect, though, the frontiers were not
only national ones, for even inside
China a deep gulf came to divide-
scholars from the .ordinary people over
the centuries. The coming of the mod¬
ern era and the arrival of Western
civilization did little to attenuate this
lack of communication.
Around the 1920s and 1930s one
came across Chinese writers so igno¬
rant of their own popular traditions
they even claimed the Chinese had
never had a sense of humour. Eager
to introduce this wonderful Western
discovery into their own country, they
invented a new Chinese word for it,
"Yu-mou" , which is simply a transli¬
teration of the English word "humour",
using two monosyllabic Chinese cha¬
racters which, taken separately, mean
"dark" and "silent" !
Fortunately, scholarly culture not¬
withstanding, popular humour has
come down through the ages and
across frontiers unscathed. A great
popular story-teller and poet, long
unknown to scholars, Feng Meng-lung
(1574-1645) was also the author of an
anthology of genuine hsiao-hua enti¬
tled Hsiao-fu (Thesaurus of Laughter).
This collection of stories enjoyed
tremendous success not only in China,
but also in other Far-Eastern coun¬
tries, and especially in Japan. Some
of the anecdotes in Hsiao-fu directly
influenced seventeenth-century Japa¬
nese burlesque theatre (Kyôgen).
The original edition of Hsiao-fu
contained 722 anecdotes, classified
according to theme. The kind of sub¬
ject that amused the ordinary folk of
China three hundred years ago inclu¬
ded: "Ancient luxury" (the rich); "Dil¬
apidated elegance" (Confucian scho¬
lars); "Not to be mentioned" (the
poor); "Eccentrics and misers"; "The
height of vulgarity" (debauchees and
sharp-tongued women); "Inside the
women's quarters" (naughty stories).
As one can see from these themes,
the Chinese used humouras do
others as a critical means of expres¬
sion in a world of exploitation and op¬
pression. Rich persons and officials
were favourite targets. For example:
"A freshly qualified mandarin arri¬
ved to take up his first post. He asked
his subordinates how things were
done in the place. The answer came,
'In the first year, you're supposed
to stay honest; in the second, half
honest; but in the third year you can
really go to with a will I' 'Shall I ever
have the patience to wait three
years?' sighed the mandarin. "
"The mandarin's birthday was due
soon. On hearing that he was born
in the year of the mouse, one of his
subordinates made a gold collection
and offered him a model of the animal
made from this precious metal. The
mandarin was delighted with the pre¬
sent and added, 'Did you know it'll
soon be my wife's birthday? She was
born in the year of the cow...'"
The Japanese have a modified ver¬
sion of this last story: "A samurai,
accompanied by his servant, spied a
dead mouse lying in the road. 'Pick
it up for me!' 'But it's dead.' 'I can
see that, but you know perfectly well
I was born in the year of the mouse!'
'Yes, my lord, and I'm glad it wasn't
the year of the cow.'"
Professor André Levy, who transla¬
ted these three last stories, shows how
the Japanese adaptations of Chinese
hsiao-hua tended to bowdlerize the
sarcastic tone of the original Chinese.
According to R.H. Blyth, in his book
Oriental Humour, the difference bet¬
ween Chinese humour and Japanese
humour can be compared to the dif¬
ference between the music of Handel
and Mozart.
In traditional China, amusing stories
often served to enliven the atmosphere
at gatherings and especially banquets.
It was considered bad manners to em¬
bark upon long discussions at a ban¬
quet; the conversation was supposed
to be light-hearted and gay, and to
avoid distracting the guests from their
main occupation, namely eating. So,
to pass the time, guests would play
games, make up verses or tell hsiao-
hua.
Even today, on the occasion of
feasts, each person is expected to do
a little act, sing a song or tell a story.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Certain authors of anthologies made
allowance for this kind of usage and
included instructions as to how the
stories should be told so as to be
sure of making a successful impact.
Here is an example:
" A father was out walking with his
son. A stranger noticed the son
and asked, 'Who is he?' The father
answered, 'this is the son-in-law
of the granddaughter nine generations
removed of the direct grandson by
marriage of a president of the Chan¬
cellery, who was a great favourite of
'one of the emperors of the present
dynasty; in other words, my son!' Shih
Ch'eng-chün, the author of the collec¬
tion of stories entitled A Good Laugh
(Hsiao-ti-hao) published in 1739, in
which this story figures, adds, "One
. should assume the air of a man
obsessed with his own self-impor¬
tance, and the answer should be blurt¬
ed out in one breath."
But the author of this collection was
not merely concerned to make his
public laugh; he also regarded humour
as a means to educate the masses.
His attitude is summed up in a brief
poem published as a frontispiece to
his book:
"People want hsiao-hua so as to
[have a good laugh,
But I use hsiao-hua so as to wake
[them up...
One can jest about the mysteries of
[religion,
But laughter is still a sure road to
[salvation!"
Consequently, the stories contained
in the Hsiao-Ti-hao are less satirical
than those to be found in the Hsiao-
fu. Most of them, moreover, are drawn
from the everyday life of the people.
"A master of the ch'in (classical
Chinese lute) was playing in the mar¬
ket (in the hope of attracting a few
pupils). The people in the market¬
place at first thought he was playing
a p'i-pa or a samisen (instruments for
light music) and crowded round to lis¬
ten to him. But when they heard the
calm, pure sounds of the ch'in they
were disappointed and little by little
the crowd drifted away. Finally, only
one listener remained. The master of
the ch'in was delighted and exclaimed,
'Well, at least one connoisseur appre¬
ciates good ch'in playing.' The man
answered him, 'If the table your ch'in
¡s standing on didn't belong to
me, and if I didn't have to wait for you
to finish your performance to get it
back, I'd have been gone ages ago.'"
"Two brothers bought a pair of
shoes, saying they'd take turns to
wear them. But when they got home,
the younger brother wore them all
day long. The older brother was most
unhappy, as the only chance he got
to wear them was at night, when at
last he could go out for a walk. The
result was that he never got any sleep.
The shoes were soon worn out, and
the younger brother said to the older
brother, 'Let's go and buy a new pair.'
The older brother frowned and said,
'Let's not buy any more shoes; I'd
rather get some sleep at night.'"
"A half-witted constable was ord¬
ered to bring a monk who had com¬
mitted a crime to the court for trial.
Afraid of forgetting something, he drew
up a precise list before setting out,
'Baggage, umbrella, cangue [large
wooden collar worn by prisoners]
documents, monk and me.' All along
the road he kept on muttering these
two phrases. The monk rapidly gather¬
ed the constable was stupid. So one
night he got his gaoler drunk, shaved
his head, and locked the cangue about
his neck before making off. When
the constable awoke, he said to him¬
self, 'Let's see now: baggage, um¬
brella... yes, they're here.' Then he felt
about his neck and said, 'Here's the
cangue.' Then the documents, 'Ah,
here they are.' Then, all of a sudden,
he grew frightened, 'Ayeee! But
where's the monk got to?' He stroked
his skull with his hand, 'Thank heaven,
the monk's still here! But in that
case, where am I?'"
In this last example, in particular,
the naively amusing surface conceals
a much deeper meaning. It shows
us man caught in the tangle of obliga¬
tions and possessions to the point
where he loses his own identity. This
story is familiar beyond the confines
of China, though, for we come across
it in a slightly different form in Cen¬
tral Europe. Which just goes to
show that, cultural differences notwith¬
standing, man's condition is universal.
Kristofer M. Schipper
HENPECKED
BUT HAPPY
This 19th-century engraving presents ten scenes of husbands being tormented in various
ways by their cantankerous wives. According to Chinese tradition few men boasted
that they were not afraid of their wives. There is a Chinese saying that to succeed in life
and become rich, a man must fear his wife.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
WORM-BREEDING
WITH TONGUE IN CHEEK (Continued from page 15)
could do but put out a next issue, and
a next, and a next...
And now, here we are, a journal
with 16 years behind us, an inter¬
national circulation that today is
numbered in the thousands. One of
our crowning achievements, inciden¬
tally, was the receipt of a letter from
the Library of the Academy of Sciences
of the U.S.S.R. offering an official
exchange of journals. We wonder still
if they quite knew what they were
getting. -
Of course, even as our circulation
increased, we remained unique. We
decided that most scientific journals
are deadly dull, and ours would be
different. To pep things up a bit, we
included poems, joke's, satires, car¬
toons, spoofs and short stories
scattered more or less randomly
among the more serious articles.
People seemed to like this melange;
or at least, some of them did. A few
people complained that they didn't
have time to waste on the (admittedly)
sophomoric humour they wanted the
"truth" and nothing else. Their trouble
was that they often found themselves
getting halfway through a satire before
they realized (dimly) that their leg was
being pulled.
WE would have ignored such
complaints had they not come
from some of the most famous and
influential members of the scientific
community. (Any conclusions you wish
to draw about the qualities necessary
to gather fame in the scientific com¬
munity are made on your own time.)
To help these poor souls out, we
resorted to a propagation device much
like the worm's namely, we split in
two. We gathered all of the so-called
funny stuff and banished it to the back
of the journal, printing it upside down
to make sure that no one wouíd
confuse the fact with the fancy.
The Digest inched along this way for
several years, until we faced another
crisis. The authors of our serious
articles complained that they weren't
getting adequate coverage. When an
article is published in most scientific
journals, it is picked up by one of the
abstracting services for dissemination
in abstract form.
Despite the fact that the serious
side of the Digest contained some
pretty meaty stuff, .none of the ab¬
stracting services would touch anything
that came from a journal with such
an odd name as ours. Eventually, as
a kind of last-ditch compromise, we
changed the name of the front half of
the Digest, calling ¡t The Journal of
Biological Psychology.
Nothing else was changed but the
name, but what a difference it made!
Within two months we received letters
from Psychological Abstracts, Biologi¬
cal Abstracts and Chemical Abstracts
asking that we send them this "new"
journal for abstracting. Naturally, we
obliged.
AS I look back at the past 16
years or so, it becomes apparent
to me that life would have been a lot
easier had the Digest suffered a still¬
birth. Much of the controversy sur¬
rounding the work on "memory
transfer" stems in no small part from
the fact that it received its first publi¬
cation in what some of my colleagues
still refer to as "the Playboy of the
scientific world".
I can recall attending a meeting at
Cambridge (the one in England) in
1964 at which I presented what seemed
to me to be rather conclusive evidence
that memories could be transferred
chemically from one planarian to
another. Afterwards, over the inevi¬
table soggy cookies and warm, flavour¬
ed water (the British national drink
just isn't my cup of tea), I was taken
to task by a noted Scientist who
informed me flatly that he would
refuse to consider seriously anything
published in a "scientific cartoonbook".
When I asked him which of the British
journals he had reference to, he almost
dropped his cookie.
I can also remember when a good
friend of mine took me aside one day
to tell me how much damage I was
doing to my reputation by printing the
Digest. He was really quite worried
about the matter. "My God", he said,,
"if you keep publishing articles in that
thing, people may actually want to cite
them some time, and then where will
you be? You ought to change the
name, throw out all that so-called funny
stuff, and make it a respectable
journal."
I also treasure a letter I received
from a world-famous zoologist who
demanded that we remove her name
from our subscription list because
we were "misleading students" into
thinking that Science could be fiinl
Now, in all these cases, the person
doing the criticizing was a bona fide,
expert scientist as well as Scientist.
They were quite sincere ¡n their
comments, offered them up for my own
betterment. I respect their scientific
work, but I do feel rather sorry that
so much of what is great and glorious
and meaningful about science seems
to have slipped through their fingers.
The kind of intropunitive wit that is
the hallmark of the Digest can thrive
only when its author is fairly secure
emotionally and intellectually. People
who neither understand nor appreciate
humour are probably threatened by
those of us who do. We speak a
language they don't understand, we
react to the world around us in ways
that are foreign and disturbing to them.
Most of them have based their entire
approach to life on the premise that
seriousness is next to godliness.
Those of us who see the occasional
folly and ignorance of most of our (and
their) behaviour often react by cracking
a joke. Humour, particularly that
directed against ourselves, keeps us
humble in the face of our own too-well-
perceived incompetence. The totally
serious person fears this kind of
insightful perception into his own
behaviour patterns and fears humour
because he cannot afford to be humble.,
NOW perhaps you see the Digest
for what it really is: the house
organ of an anti-Scientific movement.
It is my firm conviction that.; most of
what is wrong with Science these days
can be traced to the fact that Scien¬
tists are willing to make objective and
dispassionate studies of any natural
phenomena at all except their own
scientific behaviour. We know consi¬
derably more about flatworms than we
do about people who study flatworms.
The Establishment never questions its
own motives; the true humorist always
does. '
It is my strong hope that if we can
get the younger generation to the point
of being able to laugh at itself, then
and only then can we hope to. turn
Science back Into science.
H James V. McConnell
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
UNESCO'S LITERATURE
TRANSLATIONS SERIES
IRAN
(The Persian Heritage Series)
The Rabai'yat of 'Umar Khayyam.
translated from the Persian, with an
introduction, by Parichehr Kasra.
Scholars' Facsimiles and Reprints.
Delmar, New York, 1975. 183 pp.
Manichaean Literature. An antho¬
logy edited and translated from
various Middle Eastern languages
by Jes P. Asmussen. Scholars' Fac¬
similes and Reprints, Delmar, New
York, 1975. 148 pp.
JAPAN
The Roof Tile of Tempyo, by
Yasushi Inoué. Translated by James
T. Araki. University of Tokyo Press,
1975. 140 pp.
The Broken Commandment, by
Shimazaki Toson. Translated and
with an introduction by Kenneth
Strong. University of Tokyo Press,
1974. 249 pp.
Wonderful Fool, by Shusaku
Endo. Translated and with an intro¬
duction by Francis Mathy. Peter
Owen Ltd., London, 1974.
Gfl
OTHER UNESCO BOOKS
The Book Hunger, edited by
Ronald E. Barker and Robert Escarpit.
Published as a "Sangam Book" by
Priya Adarkar, Orient Longman Ltd.,
Bombay (India 1974. 203 pp.
(Rs 7.00).
National Communication Systems.
Some Policy Issues and Options, by
E. i loyd Sommerlad, 1975. 35 pp.
Tiid Rural World: Education and
Development, by Louis Malassis.
1976, 128 pp. Co-published with
Croom Helm Ltd., London.
Open Learning: Systems and Pro¬
blems in Post-Secondary Education.
A report prepared with the support
of the Ford Foundation, by Norman
MacKenzis, Richmond Postgate and
John Scupham. 1975, 498 pp. (65 F
hardbound; 50 F softbound edition
for developing countries).
Producing for Educational Mass
Media, edited by Alan Hancock. 1976,
261 pp. Co-published with Longman
Ltd., London.
Cultural Trends in the 20th Cen¬
tury is the theme of Unesco's inter¬
national quarterly Cultures (Vol. II.
No. 4). Each issue 22 F; annual sub¬
scription 75 F.
Function and Organization of a
National Documentation Centre in
a Developing Country, by a working
group of the International Federation
for Documentation Committee for
Developing Countries under the
direction of Harald Schütz. ("Docu¬
mentation, libraries and archives:
studies and research" series, No 7)
1975. 218 pp.
Death of Mr. René Cassin
Mr. René Cassin, winner of the Nobel
Peace Prize In 1968, one of the great names
In the modern struggle for human rights
and an architect of Unesco, died in Paris on
20 February 1976. A distinguished French
jurist, Mr. Cassin was French representative
to the League of Nations (1924-1938) and
between 1942 and 1944 he took part In
meetings which led to Unesco's creation.
He served on the U.N. Human Rights Com¬
mission between 1946 and 1957, becoming
its President (1955-1957) and played a
major part in drafting the 1948 Universal
Declaration of Human Rights. Mr. Cassin
was French delegate to many sessions of
Unesco's General Conference and of the
U.N. General Assembly.
'Carthage must not
be destroyed'
Inspired by the December 1970 Issue
of the "Unesco Courier" devoted to the
preservation of Carthage, first-year pupils
at the high school in Mutuelleville (Tunisia)
carried out a programme of archaeological
research on this ancient city, near Tunis.
They set down the results of their project
in a roneoed book over 100 pages long,
illustrated with photos, drawings and dia¬
grams. The children sent a copy of this
remarkable example of collective work to
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-Gene¬
ral of Unesco. In his reply, Mr. M'Bow
told them: "I admire the way in which you
have drawn full benefit from the stimulating
teaching you have received, and congratu¬
late you on being able to deal with such
an advanced subject for children of your
age".
New life
for ancient stones
Experts from 43 countries who met re¬
cently in Warsaw have drawn up a Unesco
recommendation establishing international
standards for the preservation of historic
quarters, towns and sites and their Inte¬
gration In urban planning.
The text which now goes for approval to
the General Conference of Unesco In Oc¬
tober 1976, follows a series of International
agreements adopted by the Conference
since 1962 relating to the environment and
other aspects of the preservation of the
cultural and natural heritage.
Flashes...
A new chart of the oceans incorporating
findings of the past 20 years of oceanic
exploration is being published under the
auspices of Unesco's Intergovernment
Océanographie Commission in Paris and the
International Hydrographie Organization in
Monaco.
"Philae in the Saving", a new Unesco
16 mm. colour TV film shows the most
recent stages In the international rescue
operation of the- temples on the Nile island
of Philae and their reconstruction on nearby
Agilkia island.
M Unesco is to distribute a series of video-
cassette films recording ethnological events
in Asia, Africa, Latin America end Oceania
tor use by academic and cultural centres.
(For details write Division of Cultural De¬
velopment, Unesco, Paris).
unesco miró
'z*w »
human rights
Unesco's human
rights poster
This Unesco Human Rights poster, pro¬
duced in collaboration with the International
Association of Art (IAA) is designed by
the famous Catalan painter Joan Miró. It
is the second of a series of posters being
produced on Unesco and U.N. themes, as
a joint Unesco-IAA project called "Artists
for Unesco".
Unesco cultural
week in Venice
Unesco is sponsoring a series of cul¬
tural events in Venice from the 19 to 26
September 1976, to help the International
campaign for that city. These will include
concerts, an International contest of chil¬
dren's drawings and an auction sale of
works by well-known artists. The proceeds
will be used for one of the city's restora¬
tion projects.
Cultural tourism
in Jordan
A Unesco study on the development of
cultural tourism in Jordan suggests that
priority be given to the preservation and
development of touristic facilities at two
major sites: Jerash one of the best exam¬
ples of an Imperial Roman provincial town
and Petra, a famous ancient city with rock-
hewn monuments and temples.
APHIA
takes humour
seriously
May 1973 saw the creation of the
Association for the Promotion of
Humor in International Affairs. This
organization, known as APHIA,
"takes humour seriously so that it
has no officers or official meetings
and carries out its activities only on
social occasions." The Association
awards what is called its "Noble
Prize" for humour. In 1974 this
prize went to the American humor¬
ous columnist, Art Buchwald, who
received 100,000 American pennies
as his $1,000 award. The Association
plans to award another prize In
1976. Co-founders of APHIA are
Alfred E. Davidson, an international
lawyer, and Unesco's Deputy Direc¬
tor-General, John E. Fobes.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
DEFORESTATION
FOR AMAZONIA'S ROADS
Sir,
The caption to the photo illustrating
Paul W. Richards's article "Doomsday
for the World's Tropical Forests" (in
your October 1975 issue) states that
during the construction of the Trans-
Amazonian Highway a major pro¬
gramme in Brazil's development plan
"over 130,000 sq. km. of forest (an area
four times the size of Belgium) were
cut down and burned". However, even
a layman would find it hard to believe
that an area of forest four times the size
of Belgium would have to be felled in
order to build a road, even a road
5,400 kms. long especially as at least
a quarter of the road almost 1.400 km.
runs through semi-arid and dry trop¬
ical regions.
I should like to make it clear that the
Brazilian Government is currently build¬
ing not only the Trans-Amazonian High¬
way, but also other roads In Amazonia
(which has an area of almost 5 million
sq. km.) with the aim of connecting
vast areas of Brazil by land routes.
The most important of these roads are:
Brasilia-Caracas: 6,110 km. (about
5,000 km. on Brazilian territory);
Cuiabá-Santarém: 1,650 km ;
Northern peripheral road: 2,300 km;
Trans-Amazonian: 2,250 km. (first
stage, Estreito-Humaitá, already built).
The Trans-Amazonian road starts offi¬
cially at Joao Pessoa on the Atlantic
coast and ends on the Peruvian frontier;
its overall length being 5,400 km.).
The regions where deforestation has
taken place for the construction of
these roads are, respectively:
Brasilia-Caracas: 300 sq. km. (on
Brazilian territory) ;
Cuiabá-Santarém: 100 sq. km.;
Northern peripheral: 140 sq. km.;
Trans-Amazonian: 135 sq. km. (bet¬
ween Estreito and Humaitá). Total :
675 sq. km.
This figure is a far cry from the
130,000 sq. km. quoted in the "Unesco
Courier" for the Trans-Amazonian alonel
It is easy to calculate the precise figures
from the fact that the average strip of
deforestation needed to build roads in
Amazonia is about 60 metres wide
10 metres for the road itself (two
lanes and verges) and 25 metres of
"protective clearing" on either side of
the road. To justify the absurd figures
which were given, the deforested strip
would need to be over 24 km. wide
(even supposing that the strip ran along
all the 5,400 km. of road). In relation
to the 10 metres needed for the road
itself, it is clear that such deforestation
is not only useless but impracticable
and quite uneconomical. If the figure
quoted above were applied to the
2,250 km. stretch of road where defor¬
estation has already taken place, it
would Imply a strip over 57 km. wide.
These figures speak for themselves.
Finally, for your information, and since
the same "Unesco Courier" article
states (page 16) that "Brazil has
earmarked large areas of Amazonian
forest" as "biosphere reserves", I
should like to point out that there are
currently eight forest reserves in Brazi¬
lian Amazonia, with a total area of
150,000 sq. km. (which Is indeed an area
five times that of Belgium). The region
also contains two national parks with an
overall area of 14,600 sq. km. and two
national forests with an area of 8,000
sq. km. and two national forests with
an area of 8,000 sq. km. None of
these national reserves is a "biosphere
reserve" within the framework of
Unesco's Man and the Biosphere pro¬
gramme (MAB).
In February 1974 a symposium was
held in Rio de Janeiro as part of MAB'.s
Project number 1, "Ecological effects of
increasing human activities on tropical
and sub-tropical ecosystems". The
Unesco experts later visited Amazonia
and had an opportunity to see for them¬
selves the care with which the Brazilian
Government is endeavouring to recon¬
cile the maintenance of the ecological
balance with the region's development
needs.
Joao Frank da Costa
Assistant Permanent Delegate
of Brazil to Unesco
Paris, France
HELPING GYPSIES
TO HELP THEMSELVES
Sir,
In December 1975 you published a
letter from Dr. Rémi Durand who took
up some Issues raised in your article
"Gypsies: a Minority at the Cross¬
roads" (November 1974 issue). Show¬
ing a laudable desire to respect the
cultural Identity of the Gypsies, who
have preserved "their nomadic way of
life and independence during centuries
of contact with the sedentary peoples
of the Western world", Dr. Durand
protested against the "stubborn deter¬
mination tó urge them to settle down
and to teach them to read and write",
although he agreed that we should
"help them to learn to read and count,
if they wish to do so."
The problem is not as simple as that.
There can be no doubt that nomadic
Gypsies feel that the right to move
about is an integral part of their
freedom. At the same time they insist
on their children's right to education.
But how can schooling be provided for
children who are constantly on the move
and live in groups too small or too
rapidly changing to Justify an itinerant
school?
The Gypsies also claim the right to
park their caravans in temporary
encampments between spells of wan¬
dering. Such halts form an essential
part of their rights. They are in no way
an obligation for Gypsies to settle down
but offer them opportunities to look for
work and receive medical care. The
right of Gypsies to park their caravans
is also a factor in enabling their children
to benefit from attending the local
school.
But we should remember that some
Gypsies and travellers do wish to
settle down permanently. They should
be able to do so in decent conditions.
In France the Association des Etudes
Tsiganes (Association of Gypsy Studies)
collects information on Gypsies system¬
atically while the Comité National
d'Action et d'Information Sociales pour
les Nomades (National committee of
social action and information for no¬
mads) promotes and supports social
work for Gypsies and persons of
nomadic origin. The committee aims to
help Gypsies find their own place In the
world, choosing for themselves as
responsible persons which of their tra¬
ditions to preserve or abandon. These -
aims require from the public authorities
not only a welcoming attitude towards
Gypsies, but the assurance that their
rights and needs will be respected.
While the governments of most
countries today favour a wide-ranging
social policy for Gypsies and travellers
in difficulties, none seem as yet to have
worked out satisfactory means for
operating one. In any case, any
measures to benefit Gypsies are bound
to fail unless they have the full weight
of public opinion behind them.
Henriette David
Secretary-General
Les Etudes Tsiganes
Paris, France
MICROBIUS THE MICROBE
Sir,
Congratulations to Jean-Marie Clé¬
ment, the highly talented artist who .
drew the comic strips "The Adventures
of Microbius the Microbe", illustrating
your issue "To the Microbe, with Scien¬
ce's Eternal Thanks" (July 1975). These
lively drawings of microbes served as
a delightful guide to microbiology,
showing how each of these minute
creatures has its own distinctive charac¬
teristics.
André Gray
Richelieu, Quebec
Canada
WORLD HUNGER
Sir,
460 million persons are today afflict¬
ed by hunger. It is appalling and
senseless that babies should come Into
the world only to die prematurely or
suffer hardship, to be deprived of the
opportunity to live a normal life, or to
fulfil themselves and serve mankind.
The world community must act to
solve the hunger problem, or we shall
face the prospect of returning to jungle
law, the law of chance, obscurantism and
barbarism.
World hunger has many causes.
Since food must be paid for in currency
whose value is today depreciating, a
new social and economic situation has
arisen: the impoverishment of many
peoples who now suffer undernourish-1
ment along with peoples which have?
always been poor.
Furthermore, It is not* uncommon to
learn of food products being destroyed
simply to keep stocks down and to
maintain price levels, even when selling
them would not produce a big profit.
Arms spending is another cause of
hunger. The Immense sums spent on
weapons are a crushing burden on
world resources, leading to the arms
race and international tension. There;
is no easy solution to the world hunger
problem... and yet we have made so
much progress in other fields.
Suzanne Emery
Saint-Ouen, France
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Just published
by The Unesco Press
HOW 11 COUNTRIES TRAIN
FILM AND TV DIRECTORS
In the early days of cinema the training of film-makers was often a
matter of trial-and-error and apprenticeship. Today, training pro¬
grammes in many countries successfully integrate the theoretical
and practical aspects of film-making. The Education of the Film¬
maker surveys the current status of film and television education in
eleven countries, covering such topics as:
cultural impact of cinema and television
.cinema as a major art form
education of the film-maker as artist and craftsman
H ethical and legal problems
current trends and new concepts in cinema education
"Film education, like any other kind of education, is an act offaith in
the future" _ Satish Bahadur
Film and Television Institute of India
182 pages 30 French francs
Co-published with the American Film Institute, Washington, D.C.
Available through Unesco except in the U.S.A. where the American
Film Institute has exclusive sales rights.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National
Distributor in your country. (See list below; names of
distributors In countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates In local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW; Periodicals: Do¬
minie Pty., Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brookvale 2100,
NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia,
Victorian Division 5th floor, 134-136 Flinders St., Mel¬
bourne (Victoria), 3000. AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg
Fromme & C., Arbeitergasse 1-7, 1051, Vienna. BEL¬
GIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Handel-
maatschappij Keesing, Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publica¬
tions agent: Jean de Lannoy, 1 12, rue du Trône, Brussels 5.
CCP 708-23. BURMA. Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552
Marcha« Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Information Ca¬
nada, Ottawa (Ont.). CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Ma-
karios 3rd Avenue, P. 0. Box 1722, Nicosia. CZE- '
CHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L, Spalena 51, Prague 1 (perma¬
nent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka Prague
1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag - Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6, 893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK Munks-
gaards Boghandel, 6, Nörregade, DK-1165, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb Street, Tahrir
Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis-Ababa. FINLAND. Aka-
teeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy,
75700-Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC
REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 701 Leipzig or from
Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED.
REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed.
only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22, CCP. Hamburg
276650. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stut¬
tgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications; Verlag Do¬
kumentation, Pössenbacher Strasse 2, 8000 München 71
(Prinz Ludwigshöhe) GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of
Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast,
The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. In¬
ternational bookshops. HONG KONG. Federal Publica¬
tions Division, Far East Publications Ltd., 5 A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, Wong Chuk Hang Road, Aberdeen.
Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUN¬
GARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbold, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Könyvtarosok Boltja, Náopkoztársaság utja 16, Bu¬
dapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H.F.,
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400 038; 17 Chitta-
ranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road,
Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery
Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Wel¬
fare, 72 Theatre Communication Building, Connaught
Place, New Delhi 1. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers
and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta;
Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira
P.T., Jl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Tusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution C° 229 Danes-
hgahe Street, Shah Avenue, P.O. Box 141486, Teheran.
Iranian National Commission for Unesco, Avenue Iran-
chahr Chomali No 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad; Univer¬
sity Bookstore, University of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, '
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ire¬
land Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walklnstown, Dublin 12.
ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book¬
stores, 35 Allenby Road and 48, Nachlat Benjamin Street,
Tel-Aviv; 9, Shlomzion Hamalka Street Jerusalem. JA¬
MAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service
Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo 100-92.
KENYA. The E.S.A. Ltd., P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi. KO¬
REA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co.,
Ltd., P.O. Box 2942, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBE¬
RIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Mon¬
rovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication &
Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg. MA¬
LAYSIA. Federal Publications Sdn. Bhd., Balai Berita, 31,
Jalan Riong, Kuala Lumpur. MALTA. Sapienza's Li¬
brary, 26 Kingsway, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MO¬
NACO. British Library, 30, bd des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edi¬
tion only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned
Ant.). N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao.N. A. NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford
Terrace, P.O. Box 1721, Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1 1 04, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop of ife. The University Bookshop
of Ibadan, P.O. Box 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu
Bello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All pu¬
blications: Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl .
Johans-gate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only; A.S.
Narvesens Literaturtjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKIS¬
TAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404.
POLAND. All publications: ORPAN-IMPORT.PalacKultury
i Nauki, Warsaw. For the Unesco Courier only: RUCH, ul.
Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade
Ltda, Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SIN¬
GAPORE. Federal Publications (s) Pte Ltd., Times House,
River Valley Road, Singapore 9. SOMAU DEMOCRA¬
TIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box
951, Mogadiscio. SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook
Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. SRI
LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI
Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN.
All publications: A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2, Box
1 50 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publi¬
cations: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 12-236.
TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-
es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402,
Bangkok; Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave¬
nue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Cad-
desi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop,
P.O. Box 145, Kampala. SOUTH AFRICA. Ali publica¬
tions: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty). Ltd., Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only; Central News Agency P.O. Box
1033, Johannesburg. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Statio¬
nery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester, Birmingham, Bristol. UNITED STATES. Uni-
pub, Box 433, Murray Hill Station New York, N.Y. 10016.
For "Unesco Courier" in Spanish: Santularia Publishing
Company, Inc., 575 Lexington Avenue, New York, N.Y.
10022. U.S.S.R. Mezhdu- narodnaja Kniga, Moscow,
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazije,
27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenije, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
