<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074817eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier A window
open on the world
'¿^J&r *
'¿i'ï
¿
.
-
i'JVL
w¡
y.
.^
5p*
K
^&*
T
3=áJ
- . .''»*. »»». ».»I»-'
^</w
14
k P^P IV*w/*»
|.-» fl/ t^WA i\fy
jSEgS ^mwi m^WuV f f Ml Jt
^^EflPy J 1 ' ~^K9i ' La
Wrl^#\^^
Va 1 gjái
Mi \jT^ ' i
i| -
*
i
.'
. , tV «^
.^T/á>.
ï?i V.
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
m
-* m
M
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
People 's
Democratic
Republic
of Yemen
The man
from Derah'il
A rare example of pre
Islamic Arabian art, this
alabaster statuette (46
cms. high) depicts a mous-
tached and bearded man
at prayer. His name,
"Am m a lay from Derah'il"
is inscribed on the base of
the statuette, which was
fashioned in the 2nd cen¬
tury B.C. by a sculptor of
the Himyarite people of
southern Arabia.
Photo Réunion da* Muté**
Nationaux. Paria.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco ÇoUPlCF
DECEMBER 1977 30TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 16 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 28 French Francs
2 years: 52 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier Is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100. U.S.A. ; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York. U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
France
Managing Editors
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
Dutch Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu Edition
: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
: Werner Merkli (Berne)
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
: Fereydoun Ardatan (Teheran)
: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
: Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
4 CITIES THAT BLOSSOMED IN THE DESERT
by Mohammed Allai Sinaceur
11 PRESERVING THE MEDINA OF FEZ
12 BROTHERHOODS OF THE BAZAARS
The guild system in the Islamic city
by Yusuf Ibish
19 SCHOLARS WHOSE LEARNING KNEW NO BOUNDS
by Mohammed Arkoun
23 CLASSICAL ARAB MUSIC-THE MAKING OF A MODE
by Bernard Moussall
25 EIGHT PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
33 THE THREE R's IN THE MOSQUE
The pursuit of learning as a sacred duty
by Hisham Nashabi
35 THE MADRASAHS
The first universities in the Arab world
by Badr-Eddin Arodaky
37 SCHOOLDAYS IN CAIRO
A great Egyptian writer looks back on his childhood
by Taha Hussein
38 ISLAM'S WRITING ON THE WALL
The stylish marriage of Arabic calligraphy and architecture
by Mustapha El Habib
45 EMBROIDERY IN BRICK AND STONE
Photos
46 HOW ARABIC BECAME
THE INTERNATIONAL LANGUAGE OF SCIENCE
by Salah Gala/
53 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
54 UNESCO NEWSROOM
55 UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1977
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
PEOPLE'S DEM. REP. OF YEMEN: The man from Derah'il
Cover
This 18th-century ceramic tile is a
representation of Mecca, the goal of Islamic
pilgrimage and the city to which Muslims
turn in praying. In the heart of the city is
the Ka'ba (literally, "cubic edifice"), the
ancient shrine venerated by Muslims the
world over. This small stone building is
draped with black brocade which is changed
each year. Embedded in one of its corners
is the "Black Stone" which, according to
tradition, dates back to the time of Abraham.
It is the starting point for the ritual procession
around the Ka'ba.
Photo © Museum of Arabic Art, Cairo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Among the great civilizations of world history, Arab Islamic culture of
the classical age occupies a place of major importance. Between the
9th and the 13th centuries this brilliant and original civilization left a
distinctive mark on a vast territory stretching from Baghdad on the
Tigris, across the Near East, the Middle East and North Africa to the
Iberian peninsula. Its influence was felt in many other parts of the
world, and it served as an indispensable link between Antiquity and
the medieval Western world.
by
Mohammed
A. Sinaceur
A GOLDEN AGE OF ARAB CULTURE
Cities
that blossomed
in the desert
NO lapidary phrase, however brilliant,
can fully evoke the complexities
of a culture, and anyone who sets
out to describe the achievements of a
civilization should take care to avoid over¬
simplification. This warning has particular
force in the case of Arab civilization, whose
origins lay in a message of universal sig¬
nificance among a people which stormed
the ramparts of Eastern and Western
powers alike.
Time-honoured judgements of the type:
"Arab civilization is above all a reflection
of its nomad ancestry" are neither wholly
true nor wholly false. They should be
regarded as shortcuts across a dual reality:
the reality of facts and the reality of the
impressions that the facts provoke.
For although Islam was born in the
desert, its development was accompanied
by urbanization on a remarkable scale. The
builders of the Muslim empire were also
great founders of cities such as Kufa,
Basra, Baghdad (the largest city in the
world during the 9th century A.D.), Shiraz,
Damascus, Aleppo, Cairo, Kairouan,
Tunis, Mehdia, Algiers, Tlemcen, Cordoba,
Saragossa, Sijilmasa and Timbuktu.
It is undoubtedly a paradox that a people
born and raised in the desert wastes should
be inspired to create or revive so many
cities. Where did this impulse come from?
MOHAMMED ALLAL SINACEUR, head of Unesco's
Division of Philosophy, was formerly a department head
at the French National Centre for Scientific Research
and laterprofessor of sociology at Hassan II University
in Casablanca (Morocco). He has published a number
of articles, most of them on philosophical problems
and the history of mathematics.
Did it reflect a need to settle down, to
create "with the solidity of stone" a cradle
for the infant religion? Was it to provide
the body politic the statewith continuity
and stability?
This was certainly the case. But there
was also another factor: the crucial import¬
ance of trade (to which Mecca owed its
very existence) and its expansion on a scale
matching that of the then-known world.
The great economic and social revolution
that was Islam may explain how a desert
civilization also came to have the strongly
urban flavour whose importance has all
too often been neglected by the historians
of world urban movements.
Arabia was a thoroughfare, the cross¬
roads of trade routes linking the great
civilizations of East and West. At its hub,
halfway between the Yemen and Syria,
was Mecca, whose interests lay in secur¬
ing the highways along which its fortunes
flowed. To keep peace, it wove a fabric
of alliances between the desert nomads
and the city clans.
Islam brought into contact, and fre¬
quently supplanted, the earlier civilizations
along this thoroughfare, reviving the
embers of many an ancient settlement and
building new cities, either to control the
trade routes that stretched from China to
Spain, or to serve as staging posts on
them.
Muslim conquest opened vast territories
to the city-builders. Urbanization progress¬
ed by leaps and bounds, from Mesopota¬
mia, where it existed already, to Syria and
Egypt, where it was in decline, and to
Africa, where it had long been dead.
Ancient settlements enjoyed a new lease
of life, and their size, population and
social and economic importance increased
accordingly. Thus, 10th-century Baghdad
had more than a million inhabitants,
Damascus and Cordoba between 300,000
and 400,000, and Cairo half a million.
These figures are all the more impressive
when we remember that the flourishing
cities of medieval Europe had populations
of scarcely more than 30,000 or 40,000, and I
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
In this issue of the Unesco Courier writers and historians from the Arab
world examine some facets of this great cultural flowering.
Unesco is currently developing a comprehensive programme of studies
on Arab culture. It aims to bring out the "authenticity, cohesion, unity
and universality" of Arab culture, as well as throw light on the
contribution of Arab Islamic culture to other cultures, and their
interrelations. Finally, in 1979 Unesco will organize a major conference
on cultural policies in the Arab world.
The city is one of the most
outstanding achievements
of Arab civilization, often
representing a triumph of
ingenuity over
unfavourable natural
conditions. And at the
heart of the city is the
mosque. Left, the
precinct of the great
mosque at Samarra (Iraq),
capital of the caliphs of
the Abbasid dynasty
between 838 and 889 A.D.
Covering an area of some
38,000 sq. metres, it was
one of the largest
mosques in Islam. The
outer wall, with its 16
entrances, is still
dominated by.the 50-
metre-high Al-Malouiya
spiral minaret (right)
once linked to the
mosque by a bridge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
that Paris, for example, did not reach the
300,000 mark until the 14th century.
Such rapid growth established the city's
ascendancy over the surrounding country¬
side, which became a source of food and
manpower. It would be wrong, however,
to assume that the city lived entirely off
the land, for the latter was generally too
poor to provide all the commodities requir¬
ed by a sophisticated society. Indeed,
isolated and backward rural communities
were more of a threat than a help to the
cities, whose preoccupation with the need
for security along the caravan routes led
them to form alliances with nomadic
tribes and to leave the peasants in a com¬
mercial backwater, cut off from the tide of
orthodox Islam.
The 14th-century Arab historian Ibn
Khaldun noted the stubbornness of these
country-dwellers, frequently entrenched
in mountain fastnesses, and their meagre
contribution to the prosperity of the great
Muslim cities.
This dependence on trade explains the
importance of the merchants, not only
along the highways of Arabia but in far-off
Africa as well. It was they who fitted out
the caravans which made their way across
the sandy, stony wastes towards Tinduf,
Tripoli and Benghazi in the north, and
towards Timbuktu, Kano and Abech in the
south.
All these cities shared a common origin
as meeting-places for the enterprising
camel-drivers of the Sahara and a handful
of equally enterprising businessmen from
the towns of the Mediterranean coast.
Their creation was -a complex process,
sometimes involving the settlement of
previously nomadic tribes along the fringes i
of the desert. I
Mazy desert townscapes
In the midst of barren desert, tightly
packed settlements have formed and
clustered around wells and waterholes.
Left, three aerial views, each taken from
a different height and angle, show the
one-storey houses and labyrinthine alleys
of Souk El Oued (Algeria). Each dwelling
has a courtyard that is separated from
yet at the same time joined to its
neighbour by windowless walls.
One of the most delightful literary
portrayals of everyday life in Arab
countries during the Middle Ages is the
Maqamat (or "Assemblies"), a collection
of tales written bv Al-Hariri (1054-1122).
Opposite, a scene painted for an
illustrated edition of the Maqamat
produced in Baghdad (Iraq) in 1237. It
shows two travellers in conversation
with a passerby near a village. In
background are the mosque and its
minaret, and the arches of the bazaar,
thronged with merchants and their
customers.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
AVA«#^rAW/uu'#/'#
* ! » » t
M »MlZ». » m
«» J
W&
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Compass points
of Islam
Frontispiece of a 16th-century
atlas by Muhammad Sharfi
of Sfax (Tunisia). Round the edge
of the circle are the names of the
Islamic countries. They are
connected by lines to the Ka'ba
(at centre), the sacred shrine at
Mecca containing the Black
Stone, an object of veneration
dating back to pre-lslamic times.
The corner in which the Stone is
fixed is known as the black
corner, the others being named
the Yemen (south), Iraq (north)
and Syrian (west) corners, from
the lands to which they
approximately point. Note that
the north is shown at bottom
of "map", according to a practice
often followed by Arab
cartographers.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
k The prosperity of these trading centres
'and the wealth and prestige of the great
merchant adventurers were reflected in
their buildings in palaces, mosques and
colleges known as madrasahs. (See article
page 35).
The layout of the city reflected its eco¬
nomic and social role. At its heart lay the
suq, the market district, and at the heart
of the suq stood the principal mosque,
symbol of a discipline which transcended
the petty constraints of day-to-day affairs.
This marriage of the sacred and the secular,
of piety and profitwhich can still be
seen today in the suqs of such cities as
Fez and Tunis recalls the remark attribut¬
ed to the Caliph Omar, that "in all things,
the bazaar and the mosque are in
harmony".
Not far from the suqs were the funduqs,
warehouses and lodgings for the mer¬
chants, and the qaysarriyya, where pre¬
cious goods were kept under lock and key.
The same neighbourhood contained the
place of the money-changers and some¬
times a mint.
This was the core of the city. Around
it lay a veritable labyrinth of little streets
and lanes, each lined with the open-fronted
workshops of groups of craftsmen busily
weaving, carving, dyeing, beating out
copper and generally engaged in the
thousand-and-one activities of their trades.
To an outsider, fascinated by the
mystery of blind, trellis-shaded alleys,
streets that kept the secrets of houses
hidden behind high, windowless walls,
and thoroughfares noisy with the hubbub
of the market, this workaday world, in
which merchant and broker rubbed shoul¬
ders with journeyman and porter, must
have seemed like chaos.
But system was there, and nowhere
more so than in the person of the muhtasib,
who as the symbol of municipal authority
was responsible for the regularity of deal¬
ings and for the maintenance of Islamic
order, the overriding precept of which was
to do good and to prevent evil.
The muhtasib's specific functions varied
from city to city. In Fez, for example, he
was officially appointed by the central
authorities to supervise transactions, to
inspect weights and measures, to fix
prices and to oversee the functioning of
the ovens, the markets, the manufactories
and the public baths.
In Ottoman Cairo, this task was assumed
by a senior officer of the Odjaq (the militia
of the pasha's government), assisted by
a team of agents including a treasurer, a
secretary, a scalesman and a punishment
squad.
His writ ran over much of the Cairo
markets, and more particularly over activi¬
ties connected with the production of
edible and consumer goods. He was also
responsible for the collection of taxes levied
on imported foodstuffs. On his tours of
inspection he was preceded by a scales-
man, carrying a weighing instrument
fitted with standard weights, and followed
by a punishment squad, ready to administer
summary chastisement which was some¬
times severe.
But the tiresome business of quality
control was less appealing than pomp and
circumstance, and the "inspector of
weights and measures" tended to be seen
more frequently at the official ceremonies
of the trade guilds than among the stalls
of the market-place.
Like those of the muhtasib, the functions
of the guilds also varied in different times
and places, but the guilds were all related
in one way or another to the futuwwa, a
complex institution characteristic of the
Islamic city.
The futuwwa (a name derived from the
word "fata", meaning a young man, and
by extension a "gallant and generous
person") was a professional association of
craftsmen, membership of which was
subject to initiatory rites. According to
the great traveller Ibn Batuta, who en¬
countered such groups in the 14th-century
Muslim world, the creation of these
brotherhoods of young men pledged to
comradeship and mutual devotion probably
originated at an early date, before the
reign of the Abbasid dynasty (which began
in the mid-8th century).
These groups strengthened the structure
of the guild system, which imposed disci¬
pline and cohesion on the urban commu¬
nity in cities such as Fez, where the term
futuwwa appears to have been unknown.
Through the guilds everyone knew every¬
one else, everyone was linked by the same
grapevine of information and subject to
the same unwritten laws, transgression of
which was discouraged by the deterrent
of judgement by one's peers.
In some parts of the Muslim world,
particularly in Egypt, detailed and syste¬
matic treatises were written about the
futuwwa, describing such rites as the
initiation ceremony, in which new members
were invested with a knotted waist-cord.
(See also article page 12).
These texts ascribed to the futuwwa,
and to the different trades and crafts of
its members, a mystical or religious origin.
Thus, the ceremony of the waist-cord was
traced back to the investiture of Ali,
"Commander of the Faithful" and cousin
and son-in-law of Muhammad, around
whose waist the cord was placed by the
Prophet himself, who had been initiated in
the same manner by the angel Gabriel.
The whole question of initiation and the
transmission of skill and authority inevitably
brings to mind the religious fraternities,
the mystical equivalents of the guilds.
The religious order of the dervishes
recruited most of its members from among
the artisans and merchants, who also
provided the membership of most of the
guilds. The relationship between the two
types of association is a complex one,
reflecting the deep interpénétration of
spiritual and professional life. Moreover,
both types assumed a more or less defini¬
tive form at the same moment in history.
The moral code thus drew its strength
from the well-spring of religion.
From the 16th century onwards, the
guilds and religious fraternities seem to
share the same attachment to tradition
and the same principle of submission tok
authority. Thus apprenticeship of all*
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
y kinds, whether manual or intellectual, was
seen as a process of initiation involving
the transmission of knowledge through a
master-pupil relationship.
In cultural terms, this is significant. The
world of the corporations of craftsmen
and traders and the worlds of the mosque
and the university had many points of
contact. The "wise man", who was both
the caretaker of religion and the guarantor
that its laws were applied, became a
dominant figure in the intellectual and
moral life of the urban community.
Intellectual life was dominated by the
traditional Islamic sciences, inherited from
the Greeks and subsequently developed.
The new Islamic city, whose foundations
were set in the soil of more than one
ancient civilization, provided favourable
conditions for the development of medi¬
cine, astronomy and mathematics,
sciences which could be applied to satisfy
new needs.
Intellectual activity was intense, nurtur¬
ed sometimes by polemics, frequently by
research, and invariably by the spirit of
inquiry which underlies all human contact
and which served as the tap-root of an
urban culture that was cosmopolitan in its
diversity.
Among many controversies which illus¬
trate this intellectual ferment is one con¬
cerning the relationship between Arabic
grammar and Greek logic. In the course
of a debate on the subject, recorded by
Abu-Hayyan at-Tawhidi, the distinguished
philologist As-Sirafi confounded the logi¬
cian Matta by obliging him to admit that
linguistic precision took precedence over
logic, since imprecision was a source of
obscurity and nonsense, and was thus
totally illogical.
We may detect behind this spirited
defence of Arab culture the pride of men
whose empiricism and open-mindedness
led them to prefer the deciphering of
divinely inspired realities to the sterility of
deductive reasoning.
But if the outlook that was advocated,
taught and ordained was an essentially
pragmatic one, this urban cukure, imbued
with liberty and humanism, by no means
neglected its religious origins. Nor did it
neglect the diverse and powerful currents
of pre-lslamic Arab culture, whose value
was increasingly recognized, firstly as a
component of a specific cultural. identity
and later as an indication that a society
which had not lost its vitality was determin¬
ed to resist decline.
But there came a moment when the
tide of, innovation was checked by a
counter-current which carried it into trie
backwaters of traditionalism. The result
was that thought, creativity, teaching and
belief became increasingly hidebound. In
an atmosphere of rigidity, stratification
and introspection, the religious fraternities,
the guilds and the principle of authority in
education became the pillars of religious,
economic and intellectual life.
In spite of such setbacks, however,
Arab culture continued to evolve . under
the profound imprint of the city.. The
university, practising the "commerce" of
science, was in itself a guild par excellence.
It played an essential role in urban life as a
school for the city's administrators and
the source of its moral inspiration, while
its activities, like those of business and
trade, generated a culture that facilitated
communication.
And if, as we have seen, the rural world
was neglected in the alliance between the
cities and the nomad tribes, there can be
no doubt that urban prosperity, cultural
efflorescence and commercial prosperity
invariably went hand in hand.
Thus the cities were not merely dots on
the economic map. They were also focal
points of an intellectual network, centres
of religious life and stages on the pilgrims'
ways.
It was traffic, the coming and going of
persons and goods throughout the Muslim
world, that unified all aspects of Islamic
life. The journey to a centre of trade was
also a journey to a centre of study and of
culture. A pole of attraction for the
merchant . was also a magnet for the
scholar.
This explains why culture leap-frogged
over the peasantry from metropolis to
metropolis, uniting almost all the cities of
Islam in a single pattern. There was a
greater degree of mutual understanding
and communication between Cordoba,
Fez, Baghdad and Samarkand than be¬
tween these cities and their surrounding
rural areas.
Islamic culture thus served not only as
a highway for communication but also as
a bridge which facilitated the creation and
maintenance of a strong degree of unity
in urban life. It is significant that through¬
out the territories of Islam there was no
real system of hostelries or inns. It was
the funduq and the mosque that welcom¬
ed the traveller and found him lodging.
The urbanization of Islam spread far and
wide, bringing wealth and the civilization
of the city to the doorstep of the West,
whose own Renaissance developed out of
this flow of learning.
This phenomenon was unprecedented
in the history of cultures and civilizations.
Never before had there been a movement
as complex, as vast or as rich in potential
for unification on a world-wide scale. From
Baghdad in the East to Cordoba in the
West, from the West to Byzantium, and
from Christian Byzantium to the Muslim
Orient, new territories were opened up for
trade and new circuits established for the
transmission of religious, intellectual,
economic and political ideas.
Under the impact of the city-builders of
Islam, the pulse of universal history assum¬
ed a different rhythm, one that would be
felt right up to the present day. What
traveller could deny the truth of these
words: "You will discover no new coun¬
tries; you will discover no new shores. The
city will be with you everywhere". The
omnipresent city!
The cities of Islam were garden cities.
Jealously guarded behind walls whose
height discouraged curious eyes lay an
enchanting domain of water and domesti¬
cated greenery. Gardens brought life to
"a patch of desert", provided a setting for
"unworldly dreams" and offered an
invitation to "thoughtless yet thoughtful"
reveries.
Such silence and immobility were
luxuries, perhaps; they are even more so
in today's fast-moving industrial age. But
should we not endeavour to preserve and
restore something of this peaceful universe
of infinite horizons, where beings and
elements alike sing praise to human friend¬
ship in a world eternally young?
Mohammed A. Sinaceur
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Preserving
the historic Medina of Fez
One of the most prestigious centres of ancient Islam and once
the capital of Morocco, the labyrinthine Medina of Fez still
looks much as it did in medieval times. With its industrious
population of artisans and tradesmen leatherworkers,
saddlers, potters, tanners, tile-makers and enamellers,
woodcarvers and weavers the Medina is bursting at the
seams. The conservation of such a unique site, rich in historic
monuments, poses difficult problems. The Moroccan
government, in collaboration with Unesco, is drawing up a
master plan to preserve the historical character of the Medina
while adapting it to modern needs.
CONTINUED PAGE 12
Photo Lengyel-Unesco.
1. Monumental gateway was part of the ramparts
surrounding medieval Fez. Its elegance attests to the
city's reputation as a great artistic and intellectual centre.
2. Olive groves surround the jumbled rooftops and slender
minarets of Fez. In the foreground, the old city.
3. Stalls line the narrow, cobbled streets of the Medina.
On this "thoroughfare" sheltered by bamboo matting,
everything from herbs to jewellery is sold.
4. Muqarna, or "honeycomb" ceiling graces AI Qarawiyin
Mosque. The largest in north Africa, it can accommodate
some 22,000 worshippers.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
FEZ (continued)
Fez is known in Arabic as Fas or pick. According to one tradition, the city
is so named because its founder Moulay Idris buried a pick on the site of the new
settlement in 790 A.D. to symbolize its vocation as a centre for craftsmen.
Craftsmen belonged to a trade corporation, or guild, which supervised the
training of apprentices and carefully controlled the price and quality of
manufactured goods. At right, a tannery where workers dye leather in large,
round vats. Tanneries, like other trades involving pollution, tended to be located
on the edge of Islamic cities. Nearby, a vendor (far right) proudly displays his
woven baskets, another of Fez's traditional crafts. In the Middle Ages, raw
materials and finished goods were stored in lavishly decorated warehouses
. known as funduqs (below).
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris.
Photo Louis-Yves Loirat © Rapho, Paris.
BROTHER¬
HOODS
OF THE
BAZAARS
the guild system
united apprentices,
artisans and
master-craftsmen in
the service
of a common ideal
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo J.-N. Reichel © Top-Réalités, Paris.
by Yusuf Ibish
IN Islamic cities, everyone engaged in
economic production, distribution and
services belonged to the guild system.
With the exception of high government
officials, army officers and theologians,
the population was organized into guilds
according to their crafts and trades.
Not only artisans and merchants belong¬
ed to guilds, but also people such as
singers, brokers, auctioneers, musicians,
story-tellers, donkey drivers and boatmen.
The guild system embraced owners of
starch factories, tanneries, dye-works,
sulphur workshops and similar activities
which were located, not in the bazaars but
on the edge of the city, "because of the
bad smell".
There is ample evidence that other guilds
existed for those who had no shops but
worked outdoors or at home, such as
YUSUF IBISH is professor of political sciences at the ;
American University of Beirut (Lebanon) where he '
specializes in Islamic literature and thought. A fuller »
version of this article will appear in a forthcoming
study on the Islamic city, to be published by Unesco.
painters, pipe-cleaners, water carriers,
sherbet vendors, barbers, couriers, lamp-
bearers and midwives, as well as such
government employees as slaughterhouse
workers, employees at the mint and tax
collectors.
In fact, everyone belonged to the guild
system, whatever his status : rich and
poor, Christians, Muslims and Jews, native-
born citizens and resident aliens.
The social and conceptual basis of the
guild system was transmitted orally from
generation to generation. The members
of a guild in a traditional Islamic city con¬
sidered themselves first and foremost as
members of the community of believers
(Ummah). The bond that held them
together was neither nationality nor ties of
race or blood but a belief in the Oneness
of God and in the duty to bear witness to
Him not only through lip-service but
through all their daily endeavours.
Hence there wasand still is no sepa¬
ration between religious and secular acti¬
vities in Islam. Before God and under the
. revealed Law, a Muslim stands on an equal
footing with other Muslims.
The guilds were integrated in a social
and conceptual system closely connected
with the mystic Sufi orders. By joining a
Sufi Order, a Muslim attached himself to a '
master (shaykh) and, through him, to an
unbroken chain of masters going back to
the Prophet and through him to ail the
previous Prophets as far as Adam and his
Divine Creator.
Usefulness to the community consisted
of being truthful, helpful, generous and
kind to other men, and also of achieving
proficiency in a craft or trade and provid¬
ing services needed by others.
Such proficiency could only be acquir¬
ed through hard work under the skilful
guidance of a master-craftsman and
through being initiated in a guild. Like the
religious orders, each guild had a chain
leading from its master back to the patron
saints. The concept of the guilds was thus
perfectly harmonious : each guild was
linked to the others by a common origin.
As far as the links governing relations
between different guilds are concerned,
we know that the masters of guilds attend¬
ed the initiation ceremonies of guilds other
than their own and gave proficiency certi¬
ficates to craftsmen from other towns.
They corresponded with and occasionally
visited one another, to harmonize stan¬
dards of production, beauty and prices in
their respective cities.
The first connection between a young
apprentice and his craft came when a
master took him into his workshop. In the
presence of members of the guild the!
Fatihah (the opening chapter of the1
Quran) was recited and the apprentice was1
said to have entered the guild's first»
"gate". I
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
An apprentice received no wages for a
number of years, his family comforting
themselves with the thought that he was
learning a craft from his master and was
being integrated into the community
through his guild. Until he was initiated,
he was not allowed to open a shop of his
own.
When an apprentice had mastered the
craft which he had been learning since
boyhood, the members of the guild began
urging his master to initiate him. The
master would often delay the ceremony,
but without discouraging the apprentice.
"This man is doing well," he would say,
"but his time has not yet come." Or else:
"That fellow has the makings of a good
craftsman, but his syrup is still thin",
meaning that he should remain eager and
diligent in his work.
When the master felt that the time was
ripe, he ordered the shawish, an official
specially appointed to supervise the
markets, to give the candidate a green twig
of basil or some other fragrant plant. The
apprentice took the twig with a great show
of gratitude, kissed it and placed it on his
head.
The master registered his name with
those of other candidates, if there happen¬
ed to be any, so that they might be initiat¬
ed together, and the date of the ceremony
was fixed. The shawish then went off to
invite the elders of the guild, and anyone
else he wished to have at the initiation
ceremony.
Since guilds had no house of their own,
the ceremony took place in one of the city
gardens or in the house of a member of
the guild. The ceremony began when the
shawish led in the initiate, with his hands
folded respectfully on his breast, to a green
carpet in the middle of the assembly.
Thereupon the deputy master of the guild
ordered the shawish to recite the Fatihah
in a loud voice, while all present prostrat¬
ed themselves on their knees.
After everyone had recited the Fatihah,
the deputy proceeded to "the girding of
the belt" (either an ordinary sash or a
shawl). He raised the candidate's hands
from his breast to the top of his head,
stretched out the belt, and wound it round
the initiate from his waist to his ankles.
Drawing the edges of the sash from the
back to the front, he tied them in three
knots, in honour of the master of the
guild, the initiate's own master, and the
shawish.
Only the head of the guild was allowed
to untie the first of the three knots, so that
the initiate knew beyond any doubt that it
was to him that he owed obedience. The
second was untied by the master-crafts¬
man, so that the initiate should know that
it was to him that he owed his skill. The
shawish untied the third knot.
These knots also symbolized the pact
that bound the initiate to the other mem¬
bers of the guild, who henceforth consider¬
ed him as their brother. When the three
knots were untied, the deputy then ap¬
pointed one of the masters present to be
the initiate's "trade father". More often
than not, the initiate's own master became
his trade father, but he was allowed to
choose someone else if he wished. The
trade father had to guarantee the initiate's
conduct and be answerable for all his
offences.
Next the master of the guild gave the
initiate the following advice: "My son, all
the guilds are trades which hold a position
of trust as regards money, property and
lives. Your trade is like your property;
guard it with all your might. If you receive
people's money, do not abuse their trust
by squandering it. Beware of betraying
the members of your guild, for the traitor
shall surely be judged."
He then turned to those present, and
asked: "What say you, brethren and
artisans and masters; is this initiate worthy
of becoming an artisan?" To which they
replied: "Yes, he is worthy and deserving."
The trade father then approached the
initiate to administer the solemn pledges.
Facing one another, they both bent down
with their right knee touching the floor,
before approaching each other until their
right thumbs and their left knees were
touching.
Next, the trade father grasped the
initiate's right hand in his own, and each
held the thumb and forefinger of the other
with his own thumb and forefinger.
Meanwhile, the shawish covered their
hands with a handkerchief or towel, so that
outsiders could not see the sign they were
exchanging. The father then said to the
postulant: "Swear to me by the oath of
God and His Apostle that you will not
betray the members of the guild or play
false with the trade." To which the pos¬
tulant agreed.
Then the shawish led the initiate, with
the sash over his shoulder, round to the
guild elders to receive their recognition
and congratulations.
When the initiation was finished, every¬
one sat down to a simple meal called the
Tamlihah (Salting). Salt had great sym¬
bolic value for the guilds, because it
created a bond among men who shared it,
and because artisans were known as "the
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
salt of the bazaars", meaning that they
earned their living by sweat and patience.
An artisan could graduate to the rank
of master by passing an examination of
proficiency in his craft. If he qualified he
was brought before an assembly of the
guild which decided whether or not he was
worthy of promotion.
In some cases, the artisan was required
to produce a sample of his finest work
before his promotion was considered. This
"masterpiece" was put before the assem¬
bly, and if found to be defective, the
man's promotion was postponed, for the
guild was above all concerned to maintain
its reputation and high standards.
Masters who had attained an influential
position were called elders or notables.
They assisted the master of the guild in
his functions and helped the market in¬
spector (the muhtasib) to keep law and
order in the bazaars. They were known
for their conscientiousness, high moral
character and thorough knowledge of the
affairs of the guild.
The appointment of a new master of a
guild was not always easy and smooth,
because it was usually decided by con¬
sensus, although in some guilds the office
was handed down from father to son. . This
was not considered inconsistent with the
principle of selection, for the office could .
only be inherited with the approval of the
elders of the trade who took into consid¬
eration the candidate's past services and
reputation.
The master held office all his life, that is,
as long as he was physically and mentally
able to discharge his duties in a just and
upright manner.
It was also the duty of the master to
ensure that the regulations of the trade
were respected and to penalize those who
infringed the privileges of the craft. For
example, when a weaver produced a piece
of cloth that fell short of the customary
standards of length and breadth, the
master of the guild would cut it into pieces
and hang it up in the market as a warning
to all.
Similarly, when a member of a guild
was found guilty of sharp practice, the
master sent the shawish to shut his shop,
which could not be opened again without
his approval and that of the elders. If a
goldsmith was found guilty of adulterating
his metal, the master of the goldsmiths
overturned his anvil so that he was unable
to work until the master gave his permis¬
sion. Traitors and thieves were usually
expelled and "a war without quarter was
waged against them."
The master of a guild was also called
upon to find work for labourers, whom he
recommended to master-craftsmen. He
alone had the right to initiate skilled ap¬
prentices and to promote artisans to the
rank of master-craftsman.
It was also his privilege to grant permis¬
sion to a master to open a new shop in
the guild's bazaar or its section of the
bazaar. He negotiated with the govern¬
ment on matters concerning his guild,
especially those relating to taxation.
He settled disputes among the guild
members, mobilized them in emergencies
and led them in public ceremonies and
processions.
In short, the master of a guild was not
only its head but the symbol of its very
existence. Furthermore, his powers trans¬
cended the bazaar, for he was an important
figure in the residential areas where the
guild members lived.
The grand master of the guilds enjoyed
great authority in the Islamic city, for he
was the head not of only all the guilds but
also the Sufi orders. In some cases he
was also the doyen of the Ashraf, the
descendants of the Prophet. In this triple
capacity he ruled over the guilds and
through them the bazaars, which meant
that everything that was produced and
distributed in the city as well as all its
services were under his control.
As grand master of the Sufi orders, he
co-ordinated the affairs of the "Lodges"
and supervised their trust funds. High-
ranking civil servants and army officers
who were not organized in guilds generally
belonged to a Sufi order and so they too
fell under the authority of the grand
master.
His authority in the city was such that
he only nominally acknowledged the
suzerainty of the political rulers. In various
ways his spiritual authority counterbalanced
the temporal power of kings and sultans.
It should not be forgotten that many
rulers in Islamic history were also members
of the Sufi orders and submitted to their
inner hierarchy even if they were political
rulers. This of course does not mean that
the grand master was a "political" figure
in the modern, Western sense of the term;
it simply means that he was, in the ab¬
sence of a caliph, the symbol of stability
in Islamic society.
Under the influence of Sufism, Islamic
guilds emphasized the moral and spiritual
basis of manual skills. Craftsmanship had
to reflect the artisan's "inner state", regard¬
less of economic incentives or other
rewards. When an artisan seeking promo- \
tion presented a sample of his work to his t
^^^^\#AW VU ! Will
<mti
Dazzling patterns
The carpet weavers' corporation
(far left a Berber woman at her loom)
was always one of the major guilds
in Arab-Islamic cities. Not only did
Muslims need prayer mats but also,
reminiscent of their nomadic origins,
brightly coloured ornamental rugs
to decorate their walls. At left,
cloth-sellers in the sun-stippled
bazaar of Marrakesh, in Morocco.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
, guild his own spiritual evolution was
evaluated, as well as his handiwork.
Perfection of human nature and striving
in the path of God were seen as twin ideals
for every artisan, no matter how humble
his craft.
The 19th century saw the decline and
gradual disappearance of various guilds in
the Muslim world.
The influx of competitively priced Euro¬
pean manufactured goods in the wake of
colonial rule or under colonial pressures
put local artisans out of work. In many
instances, the colonialists were looking for
raw materials and markets and hence
their first victims were the local manufac¬
turers.
The reorganization of government under
colonial rule and the introduction of new
systems of taxation weakened thé powers
of the traditional authorities and hit the
crafts severely. For example, the authority
of the guild masters was undermined when
they lost their power to decide who could
open a shop in the bazaars. New, oppres¬
sive taxes and duties caused many trades
to be taken over by Europeans because
they were exempted from taxes.
Modern transportation systems changed
not only methods of carrying goods back
and forth, but also the traditional trade
routes. From 1880 onwards, the hajj
(pilgrimage) from North Africa no longer
passed through Cairo, a change which
had a devastating influence on local trade.
The building of the Hijaz railway linking
Damascus and Medina had similar
consequences.
The population explosion in the 19th
and 20th centuries accelerated the pace of
sedentarization and urbanization in the
Muslim world, and many cities became
overcrowded. This process was accom¬
panied by the erosion of traditional social
and economic ties.
It is not surprising, therefore, that the
guild system in the Islamic city is gradually
coming to an end, and with its disappear¬
ance more than an outward expression of
social and economic solidarity is being lost.
It is a direct spiritual threat. The Swiss
Orientalist Titus Burckhardt has summed
up the situation in a masterly way (1):
"I knew a comb-maker who worked in
the street of his guild. He was called
Abd al-Aziz (the salve of the Almighty)
and always wore a black /el/abathe
loose, hooded garment with sleevesand
a white turban with a litham, the face veil,
which surrounded his somewhat severe
features.
"He obtained the horn for his combs
from ox skulls, which he bought from
(1) Fès, Stadt des Islam (Fez, City of Islam), Fribourg,
Switzerland, 1960.
butchers. He dried the horned skulls at a
rented place, removed the horns, opened
them lengthwise, and straightened them
over a fire, a procedure that had to be
done with the greatest care, lest they
should break.
"From this raw material he cut combs
and turned boxes for antimony (used as
an eye decoration) on a simple lathe; this
he did by manipulating, with his left hand,
a bow which, wrapped round a spindle,
caused the apparatus to rotate. In his right
hand he held the knife, and with his foot
he pushed against the counterweight. As
he worked he would sing chapters of the
Quran in a humming tone.
"I learned that, as a result of an eye
disease which is common in Africa, he
was already half blind and that, in view of
long practice, he was able to 'feel' his
work, rather than see it.
"One day he complained to me that the
importation of plastic combs was diminish¬
ing his business: 'It is not only a pity that
today, solely on account of price, poor-
quality combs from a factory are being
preferred to much more durable horn
combs,' he said. 'It is also senseless that
people should stand by a machine and
mindlessly repeat the same movement,
while a craft like mine falls into oblivion.
" 'My work may seem crude to you, but
it harbours a subtle meaning which cannot
be explained in words. I myself acquired
it only after many long years, and even if I
wanted to, I could not automatically pass
it on to my son, if he himself did not wish
to acquire itand I think he would rather
take up another occupation.
" 'This craft can be traced back from
apprentice to master until one reaches our
Lord Seth, the son of Adam. It was he
who first taught it to men, and what a
Prophet brings for Seth was a Prophet-
must clearly have a special purpose, both
outwardly and inwardly.
" 'I gradually came to understand that
there is nothing fortuitous about this craft,
that each movement and each procedure
is the bearer of an element of wisdom.
Not everyone can understand this. But
even if one does not know this, it is still
stupid and reprehensible to rob men of the
inheritance of Prophets, and to put them
in front of a machine where, day in and
day out, they must perform a meaningless
task.' "
Yusuf Ibish
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
A thousand-and-one
trades and crafts
Everyone, from sherbet vendors and
midwives to donkey drivers, belonged to
a trade corporation in the old Arab cities.
At left, the bustling market at Gardaia,
Algeria.
God's gift of writing
Scribes enjoyed great prestige, as writing
was considered one of the major skills
God gave to man. A numerous and
powerful group in Islamic society, they
were employed in the civil administration
of the caliphs and were often very highly
paid. Much of classical Arab literature
is a product of the scribal profession.
Medieval
department stores
Retail selling in the Muslim world has
changed little since medieval times. The
suq, a large covered market with shops
grouped according to the goods sold, is
still, after a thousand years, one of the
most characteristic features of Islamic
towns. Below, a view of the vaulted
suq at Aleppo (Syria).
Photo Unesco.
Lessons for a lifetime
Apprenticeship to a master craftsman
was the only way to learn a trade and, as
such, was an integral part of the guild
system. Above, boys learn how to emboss
copper plates at a school of Islamic arts
and crafts in Tripoli (Libya).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Scholars
whose learning
In the silence of a
mosque at Mecca, a
pilgrim studies a
sacred text. The
mosque has always
been a centre of
learning as well as a
place of worship.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
knew no bounds
by MohammedArkoun
HISTORY offers no example of a
dynamic, innovative system of
thought that has emerged and
flourished in the absence of a number of
favourable conditions.
Territorial expansion is one such condi¬
tion. The possession of mineral, agricul¬
tural and industrial resources is another.
Other important factors include financial
power, the mastery of technical and trad¬
ing skills, a high quality of urban life and
the development of favourable relations
between cities and their surrounding
countryside.
Most of these conditions were met, to
varying degrees, in the Muslim empire
which extended from Iran to Spain bet¬
ween the 7th and 12th centuries A.D.
Discussing the position of "Islam confront¬
ed with barbarian Europe" in this classical
period of Arab-Islamic civilization, the
French historian Maurice Lombard lays
particular emphasis on the extraordinary
nature of developments and accomplish¬
ments in the years 800-1000.
"As the result of the territorial expansion
which followed the wave of conquests,
the Muslim world encompassed... those
countries whose soil was most' fertile:
Mesopotamia, which owed its wealth to
MOHAMMED ARKOUN, of Algerian origin, is I
Director of the Institute of Islamic Studies at the
, University of Paris. A noted authority on Arab intel¬
lectual history, he has lectured widely in American and
European universities. He is the author of many
studies on Arab civilization and thought, including La
Pensée Arabe ("The Arab Mind") published by Presses
Universitaires de France, Paris 1975.
its remarkable system of irrigation; Egypt,
the granary of the ancient world; and the
vast plains of North Africa and Andalusia,
which provided abundant supplies of
wheat and oil for the Roman world."
The Muslim empire also included the
"major mining areas in the Caucasus,
North Africa and Spain. More specifically,
it took in all of the world's known gold
minesthose of East Africa, the Urals,
the Siberian Altai, India and, above all,
those of the Sudan, whose outflow sup¬
plied the Mediterranean world until the era
of the great discoveries".
Within its confines fell "the main centres
of industrial production such as the cities
of Mesopotamia, of Syria and of Egypt, as
well as the world's great ports, with their
vessels, shipyards and mariners: the ports
of the Red Sea and the Gulf, the Syrian
halts, Alexandria, and the cities of the
Straits of Messina and Gibraltar."
As Lombard points out, the Muslim
world held "the monopoly of the rich
transit routes of the Far East, of Central
Asia, of the Indian Ocean and those runn¬
ing from the African hinterland to the
Mediterranean... In fact, it commanded
access to the entire network of interna¬
tional trade routes, whether continental,
spanning Asia, maritime (the Persian Gulf
and the Red Sea), the caravan routes
through the Sahara to the Sudan, or the
Russian rivers flowing into the Baltic from
the Caspian Sea.
"Finally, and perhaps most important of
all, within the frontiers of the Muslim
empire lived the world's most seasoned
traders, with their age-old techniques and
ancient commercial traditions." (1)
An awareness of the material conditions
in which a system of thought can develop
and flourish does not necessarily imply a
belief that intellectual life is subordinate to
and dependent on those conditions. The
extent to which cultural activity influences
and transforms the material aspects of
civilization, and vice versa, must be re¬
examined in each social and cultural con¬
text and in each historical setting.
Hence it is imperative to seek new
perspectives and to reinterpret classical
Arabic thought in the light of modern
knowledge. - -
The appearance of the Quran was an
historic event of supreme importance
because it signalled the advent of a religion
of universal dimensions. Taking this as a
"starting point, it is possible to trace several
major periods in the development of Arabic,
thought. - ' '
(1) Espace et Réseaux du Haut Moyen Age, Mouton
Publishers, Paris-The Hague, 1972.
The classical period, which lasted from
the early 10th century to around 1300,
may be seen as a kind of summit, and its
formative period, stretching from 632 to
900-950, as the road leading up to it. Then
came a period of relative decline (from
1300 to 1800): an era of innovation in
some parts of the Muslim world, but in
others an age of conservatism. This phase
was in turn followed by what has been
called the "Arab Renaissance", which
roughly covers the period from 1800 to the
present day.
Classical Arabic thought explored a
multitude of subjects. With varying
degrees of emphasis, it examined matters
of strictly religious concern, ethics, juris¬
prudence, politics, social and economic
questions, theology and philosophy.
Linguistics, aesthetics (literature, music,
painting and architecture), science and
technology, as well as history, geography
and cosmogony were other fields of
inquiry.
; This multiplicity of interests points to an
extraordinary degree of intellectual curiosi¬
ty. Specialization, however, never over¬
rode the desire to relate the various disci¬
plines to each other and to weld the dif¬
ferent branches of knowledge into a
coherent whole.
Motivated by a strong desire to resemble
God, Who "embraces all things in His
wisdom," as the Quran expresses it," the
intellectual of the classical period was a
humanist open to knowledge in all its
forms. The excessively rigid, modern
lines of demarcation between law, ethics,
aesthetics, history and the natural sciences
were virtually non-existent at this time!
: The word adab, which today signifies
"literature", in the classical age referred to
a general intellectual attitude towards the
world-at-large, knowledge, private and
public behaviour, a literate humanism, and
the special form of civilization which
developed in Islamic cities between the
7th and 13th centuries A.D. '
i The various branches of knowledge
explored during this period at first overlap¬
ped and ¡nterreacted. Little by little,
however, they , were to become distinct
entities, as social. and cultural conflicts
developed. ,
All types of knowledge and all disciplines
recognized by classical Arabic thought
were encompassed in the religious : per¬
spective opened up by the Quran. For the
Quran did more than talk about a unitary
God, Judge, and Creator, as revealed to
Muhammad." Not only did reestablish a
religious relationship between the believer w
and his Creator-Benefactor, it provoked Y
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Unesco translations
of Arabic literature
To make the great wealth of Arabic
literature more widely known,
Unesco has for many years promot¬
ed the translation and publication
of major works in Arabic. Notable
titles that have appeared in English
are:
IBN RUSHD (AVERROES). On
the Harmony of Religion and
Philcsophy (Kitab fas Al-Maqal).
Translated by George F. Hourani.
Luzac and Co., London, 1961.
126 pp.; The Incoherence of the
Incoherence (Tahafut at-Tahafut).
Translated with an introduction and
notes by Simon van den Bergh.
Luzac and Co., London, 1954.
2 vols. Vol. 1,373 pp.; vol 2, 219 pp.,
(Philosophy).
AL-GHAZALI. O Disciple! (Ayyu-
ha'l Walad). (Bilingual edition)
Translated by Georges H. Scherer.
Catholic Press, Beirut, 1951. 28 pp.;
30 pp.
AWWAD, Tawfiq Yusuf. Death in
Beirut. Translated by Leslie Mc-
Loughlin. Heinemann, London,
1976. 190 pp. (A novel).
HILAL, Al-Sabi'. Rusum Dar Al-
Khilafah (The Rules and Regula¬
tions of the Abbasid Court).
Translated with an introduction and
notes by Elie A. Salem. Lebanese
Commission for the Translation of
Major Works, Beirut, 1977. 134 pp.
FORTHCOMING
IDRIS, Yussef. Arkhas Layali
(The Cheapest Nights). Translated
by Wadida Wassef. Peter Owen,
London, 1978.
Major works that have been publish¬
ed in French include:
AVICENNA. (Ibn Sina). Livre des
Directives et Remarques (Kitab
Al-lsarat wa I'tanbihat). Translat¬
ed with an introduction and notes
by A.-M. Goichon. Commission for
the Translation of Major Works,
Beirut. Vrin, Paris, 1951. 553 pp.
(Philosophical treatise).
IBN KHALDUN. Discours sur
l'Histoire Universelle (Al-
Muqaddima). Translated with an
introduction and notes by Vincent
Monteil. Commission for the
Translation of Major Works, Beirut,
1967-68. 3 vols.
Please do not send orders to
Unesco. Order through your usual
bookseller.
, an unquenchable intellectual curiosity
which extended to all areas of knowledge.
Insofar as ethics and law were concern¬
ed, the development of a code of religious
law had to take account of social relations,
trade and production, property, and
personal status in public and private life.
However, the norms of religious law had to
be based on the precepts of God as record¬
ed in the Quran or on those of the Prophet
expressed in the hadith, and not on the
arbitrary judgement of the human law¬
maker.
Since men could not interpret these
divine precepts properly without reference
to the testimony of successive generations
of Muslims following the initial Revelation,
history, theology and the study of lan¬
guages came into the picture. Philosophy
too had a place in this scheme of things
to the extent that it provided methodolo¬
gical and conceptual tools.
. A striking illustration of the correlation
of all these intellectual disciplines was the
great Quranic commentary of Fakhr al-Din
al-Razi (d. 1209), in which the full range of
human knowledge was brought to bear on
the exegesis of the sacred text.
The same interdependence of intellectu¬
al disciplines was found in philosophy,
which was clearly distinct from the strictly
religious facet of classical Islam, even to
the point of apparent contradiction. This
is amply demonstrated in the running
controversies over the respective roles of
reason and faith, the dichotomy between
rational and religious knowledge, between
rational judgements and those of religious
Jaw.
But the fact remains that philosophy
and theology overlapped whenever ethics,
politics and metaphysics came into play,
just as religious law made use of logic,
mathematics, rhetoric and the natural
sciences branches of knowledge studied
by the philosophers.
The interpénétration of philosophy and
theology -can be seen in the work of the.
Mu'tazilites, advocates of rationalism
applied to all fields, not least to religion,
and in that of humanists such as Jahiz.
The tendency to synthesize became even
more marked in the 10th century, with the
grammarians, the juridical theologians,
men of letters, medical doctors, and the
encyclopaedists, such as the Brothers of
Purity. To put the matter in a nutshell, at
this stage, the intellectual climate was
exceedingly dynamic and open-minded.
History and geography, as they were
understood at the time, provide further
evidence of the tendency towards uni-
versalism and the empirical verification of
data. A spate of universal histories
appeared in which the chronological re¬
cording of events (especially after the
coming of Islam) superseded mythical
references to prophets, ancient Persian
kings, and the sages of Antiquity. Trav¬
ellers, missionaries and merchants, wander¬
ing the length and breadth of the Islamic
empire, added their own observations to a
geographical corpus already rich in informa¬
tion and descriptions of prevailing
conditions.
The tale of Ajib and Gharib in the
Thousand and One Nights (2) provides a
significant example of the intermingling of
history, geography and literature. In it,
specific historical events became the plot
of a splendid tale in which the collective
mind projected and rediscovered its desires,
beliefs and symbols.
This link between the humanities and
literature can be found in the work of
several writers, notably that of the great
scholar Al-Biruni (d. 1048), whose thinking
was in many respects astonishingly
"modern". (See Unesco. Courier, June
1974).	
(2) Un conte des Mille et Une Nuits, Ajib et Gharib,
translated into French with a commentary by André
Miguel, Editions Flammarion, Paris, 1977.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
In Seville, the Giralda ^^
(or "weathervane") was
built in 1171. Within, ramps
allowed two horsemen
abreast to reach the top
without dismounting.
Photo G. Martin © Rapho, Paris.
Trio of towers
Along a virtually straight line,
three holy places of Islam were
built in the 12th century by the
Almoravid dynasty, the rulers
of Morocco and Muslim Spain.
Their minarets were all fashioned
along the same lines.
/ RABAT
MARRAKESH
The Hassan Tower in
Rabat, begun in 1196, was
never completed.
Surrounding it are hundreds
of truncated columns, which
once supported the roof
of the mosque.
Photo Jean Mazenod, Paris.
The minaret of the
Kutubiyya in Marrakesh.
The original building, begun
in 1140, faced in the wrong
direction and was replaced
in 1195.
Photo © Almasy, Paris.
The intercontinental trade routes traced
by the Arabs were also the arteries along
which their culture spread through the
medieval world. Left, a bridge built
by Arab engineers across the Nahr
al-Kalb or "River of the Dog" in Syria.
Broadly speaking, the period was cha¬
racterized by a running confrontation bet¬
ween two basic approaches, the one
rationalist, following lines traced by the
Greeks, the other traditionalist, concerned
with the direct meaning and implications
of the sacred texts (the Quran and the
hadith).
Nonetheless, many thinkers chose to
ignore this distinction. They were often
men of great stature, such as Ibn Sina
(Avicenna, d. 1037), Ibn Rushd (Averroes,
d. 1198), and Ibn Khaldun (d. 1406).
Although there existed an intellectual
meeting ground for the various social
groups within the Islamic empire which
were gradually exposed to the life and
culture of the cities, rivalries arose between
different schools and "sects", sometimes
even leading to street brawls.
Dissident groups and movements arose
in reaction, to forms of. orthodoxy
supposedly accessible to everyone, but in
fact reserved to "official" Islam, whether
Sunnite, Shiite or Kharijite, depending on
time and place.
The tendency to see these scissions as
purely religious still prevails in the Muslim
world. But in the light of modern histori¬
cal sociology, it becomes clear that they
were closely linked to the social and cul¬
tural conflicts of the period. The demands
of newly-Arabicized converts for equality
and access to positions of responsibility
may be taken as a case in point. In the
political context of the Abbasid Caliphate,
for example, these demands could only be
formulated in religious terms.
The Kharijite movement is another
example: strictly religious by definition, it
arose out of the nomads' opposition to an
authoritarian, centralized state.
.In yet another setting, Shiite Islam's k
following expanded significantly with the Y
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The scholars of the order known as the Brothers of Purity (Ikhwan as-Safa)
held a distinguished place in 10th-century Arab cultural life because of their
vast scientific, philosophical and religious knowledge. Above, an illustration
from their encyclopaedic work "The Epistles of the Brothers of Purity."
Two of the authors are shown with a scribe and servants.
conversion of non-Arabs (mawali), who
were for the most part former client-
peoples'^ craftsmen and merchants in the
new urban centres which were created or
revitalized by the Arab conquest (Basra
and Kufa in particular, as well as Baghdad
and the Iranian cities).
By the same token, social and economic
changes in the 8th and 9th centuries gave
rise to new groups of dissidents: the urban
poor, the dispossessed Arab tribes, and
the peasants, among others. . Their
discontent found expression in the various
Shiite factions opposed to the existing
power structure.
It becomes clear, then, that these social
and economic conflicts were at the root of
the controversies among the various
schools of theorists, theologians, mystics
and jurists who were responsible for the
maintenance of doctrinal orthodoxy and
official Islam.
Islam is characterized by a long-standing
conflict between personal questioning, on
the one hand, and obedience to tradition,
on the other. This conflict evolved out of
the social divisions and tensions generated
by rival groups in the cities. It should be
noted that the return to tradition became
more pronounced as the rivalry between
Sunnites and Shiites abated, or as one or
the other acquired the status of official
religion.
It was in the 11th century that the edu¬
cational system and institutions which
would ensure continuity in religious life
and its expressions came into being.
Till then, adabculture understood in
the broadest sensedeveloped and was
passed on in "scientific circles", which
attracted large numbers of disciples, and
were maintained by thé viziers, princes,
rich merchants and humbler men devoted
to the pursuit of knowledge. Then too,
there were the bookshops, where men of
every rank and station met to exchange
ideas, a tradition which still lives on in the
Arab world today.
Theology was taught in the mosques,
which were the centres of intense social
and cultural activity, as well as being
houses of prayer.
In the 11th century, a succession of
events began to shake the power of the
Muslim world and to threaten its prosperity.
Surging out of Central Asia, the Seljuq
Turks settled in Mesopotamia and took
power in Baghdad, encouraging the resto¬
ration of Sunnite Islam and ending the
Shiite domination of the preceding century.
Even as Muslim Spain was in the throes of
political fragmentation, waves of Egyptian
nomads swept across North Africa and
destroyed the existing power structures.
Arab Islam stood at the threshold of a
period fraught with danger, under the
double threat of internal disintegration and
destruction by external forces the Cru¬
sades of the 12th and 13th centuries, the
Mongol invasion of the 1200s, and the
Spanish Reconquest, which was to last
until the 16th century.
Arab Islam withstood all these dangers,
developing a cultural heritage transmitted
through the madrasahs (see - article
page 35), and through educational institu¬
tions for mystics and (from the 13th
century onwards) for members of the
religious brotherhoods. Philosophy,
inseparable from medical science and
practice, was "dispensed" in the hospitals.
But the most salient factor was the
evolution of the madrasah, from the 11th
century on. Originally an intellectual
training ground where ideas were freely
discussed and exchanged, it gradually
became a centre of scholasticism. Once
it acquired official status, the madrasah
was transformed into an institution for
teaching the precepts of a given school or
brotherhood to the exclusion of all others.
Divergent views were presented, explicitly
or implicitly, as deviationist, if not plainly
heretical.
The madrasah was an institution of
learning with a single chair occupied by a
master recognized by a given school of
religious law. Sunnite Islam alone had four
such schools (Malikite, Hanbalite, Shafii
and Hanafite), each with its own madrasahs.
Specialized institutions modelled on the
madrasahs, known as Houses of the Quran
or the hadith also proliferated. Their
masters awarded diplomas only when the
student correctly repeated a number of
formulae, logical exercises, and solutions
which corresponded to the traditions of
his school.
Learning was transmitted by recitation
before the master and by the diligent
study of manuals, bibliographies and
anthologies.
The weight of this medieval scholasticism
increased as Western Europe tightened its
economic grip on Mediterranean Islam.
In this way an idealized and constricted
vision of an "orthodox" Islam gradually
emerged. This image, forged under the
defensive imperatives of a community
threatened from within and without, is
still very much alive today.
Thus, contemporary struggles for na¬
tional liberation and the Palestinian tragedy,
for example, have only served to consoli¬
date the ideological role of Islam and of
the Golden Age of Arabic thought.
The redefinition of philosophical and
historical perspectives is today a matter of
the utmost importance. It is common
knowledge that Arab intellectuals are
engaged in the urgent tasks of economic
and social development. Consequently,
such urgent and relatively simple tasks as
the preparation of new, critical versions of
the great classical texts are either postpon¬
ed or carried out imperfectly.
There is much talk about economic
development, much less about cultural
underdevelopment. One consequence of
this is the existence of vast gaps in our
knowledge of societies with particularly
impressive pasts. This is true of the entire
field of Arabic studies.
To my mind, we should be thinking in
terms of a new world cultural order closely
related to the new world economic order
towards which we are working for the first
time in history.
Mohammed Arkoun
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The delights of music ranked even
higher than the pleasures of the chase.
Below, musicians and hunting scenes on
an 11th-century ivory plaque, produced
under the Fatimid dynasty which rose
to power in northwest Africa in the .
10th century.
CLASSICAL ARAB MUSIC
The making
of a mode
by Bernard Moussali
THE study of music was an indispensable
part of every cultured man's education
in the Arab world between the 9th and
the 13th centuries. No fully educated
man could afford to be without at least a work-
ing knowledge of the subject nor without some
degree of mastery of its skills.
An epicurean love of life, eroticism and praise
of the Muslim city were among the favourite
themes of musicians of this period, who drew
their inspiration from pre-lslamic and classical
Arab poetry, especially from the qasida or ode.
A collection of their works, the famous "Book
of Songs" transcribed in the ,10th century by
Abu-I Faraj al-lsfahani, reveals a society that
was at once complex, highly cultivated and
open to all kinds of intellectual speculation. .
In the 9th century, the practice of classical
music reached a peak of accomplishment at the
court of the Abbasid caliphs of Baghdad. This
led, from the 9th century on, to far-reaching
advances in musical theory and the creation of
a musical terminology which formed the basis
for the subsequent development of Arab, Per¬
sian and Ottoman music from the 14th to the
19th centuries.
At the beginning of the 9th century, classical
Arab music was already a century and a half
old. It had evolved from its pre-lslamic origins
and had undergone Persian and Syrian influ¬
ences, to form a tradition that was essentially
vocal. It could be rhythmic or non-rhythmic,
and was probably based on a number of series,
or "scales", comprising five or in a more
refined formseven "sounds" of varying
importance.
BERNARD MOUSSALI, Lebanese musicologist, is
currently engaged in research on the development of
Arab music in Egypt, Syria and Iraq during the 19th
and early 20th centuries.
It was thus a modal system, involving notes
of indeterminate pitch, specific scales and
melodic improvisations.
This music was defined in terms of naghma,
or melody, which concerned its vocal com¬
ponents, and isba' (literally "finger"), whichas
the name suggests concerned the position of
the fingers on the accompanying stringed
instrument.
The performers of a given melody all obeyed
the same rhythm, singing in unison or at inter¬
vals of an octave. Polyphonythe combination
of two or more melodic lineswas only an
accidental or secondary feature used for pur¬
poses of momentary embellishment.
The instrumental accompaniment, which was
closely related to the text, was provided by
percussion or plucked string instruments. The
former consisted for the most part of small
drums of the tambourine family, such as the
duff, which was sometimes fitted with small
copper cymbals. The latter comprised instru¬
ments of the lute family, including the two-
stringed tunburs of Baghdad and Khorasan (prob¬
ably of Arab and Persian origin respectively)
which were similar in their narrow-bodied, long-
necked form but different in their tuning. Also
used were the '"ud" lutes, four-stringed instru¬
ments with wide bodies and short necks which
were invented by Mansur Zalzal at the end of
the 8th century in an attempt to combine in one
instrument the sounds produced by earlier
models.
This chamber music, although governed by
strict rules, left performers a large measure of
freedom to display their imagination through
improvisation. Pride of place went to soloists,
whose aim, whether as singers or instrumental¬
ists, was to provoke in the listener an emotional
response known as tarab, which was specific |
to music. I
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Arab music was created by three categories
of performers. First came the singers, some of
whom, like Ibrahim al-Mawsili (c. 743-806),
attained great celebrity. Next came their
accompanists, who were either native-born
Arabs or Arab by adoption and protégés of the
Abbasid caliphs. Finally there were the famous
female musicians and dancers who were
brought as slaves from many countries and
were generally trained in their art by the singers.
Each composition, jealously protected by its
creator against plagiarism, was transmitted by
ear, sometimes with the help of private systems
of notation, secret codes and, other aids to
memory. Transmission took place either from
father to son or from master to pupil on a fee-
paying basis, with the master repeating the song
until the pupil had learned it by heart. In the
case of pupils who were slaves, apprenticeship
was paid for by their owners.
Unlike the merchants and shopkeepers (see
article page 12), musicians were highly com¬
petitive and not interested in forming lasting
associations or guilds. Solidarity was con¬
spicuous for its absence. Ziriyab, who was
expelled from the court of the Abbasids as the
result of the schemes and threats of the il¬
lustrious Ishaq al-Mawsili, was only one musician
to undergo the bitter experience of being oust¬
ed by a rival.
Instrument-making was an equally individua¬
listic process, each musician manufacturing his
own from models handed down by his teacher.
The Caliph al-Ma'mun (786-833) created at
Baghdad a "House of Wisdom" where Greek,
Syrian and other manuscripts were translated
into Arabic. One result of this work was to make
known the musical theories of Aristotle, Aristo-
xenes, Nicomachus and Ptolemy. Ishaq al-
Mawsili was among the first to adopt the
Greek notion of music as "the science of
making melodies" and as the study, on the
basis of ancient principles,' of vocal and instru¬
mental sounds alike.
In the late 9th century, musicians, writers and
philosophers began to speculate on the nature
of their music, initiating a movement which
lasted until the 13th century. In Iraq and Iran,
the outstanding representatives of this wave of
speculation were the mathematician al-Kindi
(d. 874), one of the earliest musicologists; a
circle of anonymous Shiite philosophers known
as the "Brothers of Purity" (late 10th century);
and the physician and philosopher Ibn Sina,
also known as Avicenna (980-1037).
Another great theorist was Al-Farabi (d. 950),
a Syrian philosopher who wrote a famous
"Treatise on Music". (See "Unesco Courier",
June 1973). In Egypt, Ibn al-Haytham (c. 965-
1039) was a versatile writer who produced
numerous commentaries on the work of his
predecessors. Finally, the new musical theories
reached the Maghrib, through the work of the
Andalusian philosopher Ibn Baja (d. 1138).
The volume of these studies and exchanges
points to a musical life of great intensity. All
the authors and theorists considered music to
be a "scientific art" comparable to arithmetic, '
geometry and astronomy, and devoted their
attention to acoustics, composition and rhythm
as well as the study of musical instruments. Big .
gaps still remained in the study of the transmis¬
sion of sounds and the relationship between
acoustics and physiology, but instrument-making
took a step forward with the development of
the qanun, a form of cithar whose strings are
plucked.
None of the scholars working between the
10th and 13th centuries found a satisfactory
solution to the problem of recording Arab music
through a system of notation. Although some
attempts were made to introduce a form of
alphabetical notation, it was not widely adopt¬
ed because musicians were afraid of plagiarism.
Music also gave rise to a branch of the occult
sciences. This was the science of "correspon¬
dences", which was practised in such esoteric
circles as the Brothers of Purity and involved
investigation of the relationships between
music and the elements, the animal, vegetable
and mineral worlds, and colours.
The practical outcome of all this research was
the extension of the Abbasid mode throughout
the Arab-Islam world.
In the Maghrib ancient musical traditions
were renewed and the notion of related com¬
positions, or "suites", was developed. In
Andalusia, the late 9th century saw the creation
of the muwashshahah songs, poems set to
music and freed from the constraints of classical
Arabic metre. Under the influence of Ziriyab
and his followers, this new wave of exploration
in the field of rhythm sent out ripples to all the
corners of the Arab-Islam world.
Another major source of musical development
was created by the "whirling dervishes" {Maw-
lawiyya), a brotherhood founded by Jala! al-din
al-Rumi in the 13th century. The dervishes
devoted themselves to musical studies which
may have been based on Pythagorean theories
and systematized the processes of initiation to
music and sacred dance.
In the late 13th century, Safi al-Din al-Urmawi
established a musical terminology and solved
the problem of scales in Arab music in his
"Epistle to Sharaf al-Din" and above all in his
seminal "Book of Musical Modes". Even more
important was his methodical use of the term
maqam (position), a mode in classical Arab and
Turkish music which heralded their modern
forms.
The homogeneity of Arab music has thus
persisted until the present day. Notwithstand¬
ing differences of mode, rhythm and composi¬
tion, it remains firmly rooted in the "classical"
artistic and cultural heritage of the Arab world.
Bernard Moussali
Colour pages
1 »:
Page 25
An illustration from a
13th-century illuminated
manuscript of the
Maqamat (see captions
pages 6 and 48): a scholar
gives a lecture in front of
a well-filled bookcase.
Page 26
Ducks and a tortoise, a
lion and jackals are
depicted in two scenes
from Kalila and Dimna,
a celebrated book of
moralistic beast fables
translated into Arabic by
Ibn al Muqaffa (8th
century) from a Persian
version of the Indian
Fables of Bidpal.
Page 27
Another scene from
Kalila and Dimna
illustrating a dispute
between crows and owls.
Page 28
A sea-going boat from
the Maqamat. Arab
navigators established
new sea routes linking
Asia, Africa and Europe,
as well as devising a
new technique for
navigating by the stars.
Page 29
In this miniature from
Pseudo-Galen's Book
ofAntidotes (see caption
page 51), a pharmacist
supervises work in the
fields.
Page 30
Two more scenes from
Kalila and Dimna: the
tortoise and the monkey
and the cormorant and
the crayfish.
Page 31
Mosque scene from
the Maqamat: the ¡mam,
or prayer leader,
addresses the faithful
from the minbar, or
pulpit.
Photos © Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
i
jP i
-*«
».
;
¿P>^p\j,_ '..
ù^m ' '&&M¥*&
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
\ ¿J> ÁXXS» <-r> p!MfcPS%:
.¿&\$cvÂy$fo ^pp^f^ Ô o
\oX &&Ü. M o^buiAUI v¿Ai -y ÜTj^? ' r
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
^W^^^^i^y^o*
y
f
à MsfeteSr^
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
^ t s / ^^V^l^ii^l^KtóEi
> > ° , .
£\P^p\patpkjppp¿
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The madrasah (literally "the place for
lessons") was the university of the
medieval Arab world. The curriculum
was centred on the Quran, Islamic
theology and law, but a variety of other
subjects such as grammar, literature and
mathematics were also taught in some
madrasahs and are still taught today.
Students were well looked after. Not
only was tuition free, but food, lodging
and medical care were also provided.
Left, traditional scene of instruction in a
13th-century manuscript. One pupil
recites for the teacher while another pulls
the ceiling fan.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
The three R's
in the mosque
The pursuit of learning
as a sacred duty
by Hisham Nashabi
THE most outstanding characteristic
of Islam is its repeated insistence on
unity: the unity of God and the unity
of the spiritual and the worldly aspects of
life, of the religious and the secular.
Islamic education reflected this aspect
of Islam by considering the various
branches of knowledge as a cohesive unity.
Hence practically no subject was barred
from study in the mosque.
The acquisition of knowledge was also
considered a religious obligation. This
explains why the ulemas, scholars trained
in religion and law, have always occupied
a high position in Muslim society.
Seen from this viewpoint, education is
not only a means of achieving knowledge
for its own sake or for the sake of truth.
Nor is it simply a means of becoming a
good citizen nor of earning a living. It is
first and foremost a way to moral and
spiritual development.
Islamic society frowns on the scholar
who refrains from passing on his know¬
ledge to others. People are in duty bound
to transmit their learning, thus gua¬
ranteeing that the stock of human know¬
ledge will be preserved and, in the course
of time, enriched. This attitude may be
considered as the historical antecedent of
what is today referred to as the "democra¬
tization of education".
The mosque, äs an educational institu¬
tion, was the first and most effective
instrument to ease the transition of Arab
society from an early stage in which the
oral tradition was a dominant characteristic
to a more developed stage based on the
written tradition.
The Prophet Muhammad brought a
message which was essentially represented
HISHAM NASHABI is director of the Makased .
Institute of Islamic Education in Beirut (Lebanon). He
is professor of history at the American University of
Beirut and at Beirut University. A fuller treatment of
the subject of this article will appear in a forthcoming
study on the Islamic city, to be published by Unesco.
by a book, indeed The Book, the Quran.
The study of the Quran immediately
became the core of intensive educational
activity. Reading, writing and arithmetic
were primarily aimed at a better under¬
standing and appreciation of the Quranic
text and the application of what it taught.
And yet the oral tradition, deeply rooted
in the Arab mind since pre-lslamic times,
was not abandoned. On the contrary, it
was institutionalized and systematically
organized in the new Islamic society.
The story-tellers, poets and narrators
who were the repositories of this oral
tradition continued to perform their func¬
tions after the coming of Islam, side by
side with the educators of the new society.
All these educators unanimously believ-
' ed that a good memory was the most
valuable quality in a student, since the
highest aspiration of the first Muslim
scholars was to learn by heart both the
Quran and, if possible, the hadith (tradi¬
tions concerning the acts and sayings of
the Prophet).
During the reign of the first four caliphs
(the Prophet's successors as head of the
Muslim community), Muhammad's com¬
panions followed their leader's example in
expounding the different aspects of Islam
to their fellow citizens. Apart from the
emergence of the mosque as an educa¬
tional institution, there were no significant
developments in Islamic education during
the first century of the Hegira (1).
However, the Arabic language attracted
the attention of scholars at an early date.
It began to be studied in the mosques,
where it soon occupied a place of honour
in the curriculum.
The beginnings of theological debate in
the Muslim world also date , from this
period, when the first "circle" to discuss
(1) Hegira: the Muslim era, which began in 622 A.D.,
when the Prophet Muhammad left Mecca and setjled in
Medina.
theology met in the mosque of Basra
(Iraq).
The 9th and 10th centuries saw the
appearance of great Muslim jurists, theo¬
logians and linguists, as well as the cre¬
ation of the kuttab, which became the
most widespread institution of elementary
education in the Muslim world. The kuttab
developed in response to the needs of the
new Islamic city, where the ability to write
in Arabic was necessary for transcribing
the Quran, as well as being an essential
qualification for government posts. As a
rule each kuttab had a single teacher, but
in some cases there were two or more,
one of whom always specialized in Quranic
studies. The homes of the ulemas and the
shops of "paper merchants" were also
used for educational purposes.
Major developments in Muslim educa¬
tion occurred in the 10th and 11th centu¬
ries, when the mosque became a veritable
public university as well as a place of
worship and a community centre. The
"circles" formed in the mosques were of
high intellectual calibre and produced a
number of outstanding works.
Two new institutions of learning also
appeared during this period: the "Houses
of Wisdom" and the "Houses of Science."
Unlike the mosques, they were not places
of worship and their activities, which were
purely academic, were not strictly related
to the religious sciences. On the other
hand, some of the academic pursuits
which took place in the mosques may have
been of a secular nature: it should never
be forgotten that in Islamic society the
secular and the religious are inextricably
interlinked.
Translation was the principal activity of
the House of Wisdom founded in Baghdad
sometime during the reign of the Caliph
Al-Mansur (754-775) or that of Harun al-
Rashid (786-809). In its golden age during
the reign of Al-Ma'mun (813-833) this
great library became an academy where i
eminent scholars translated Greek and I
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The great Qarawiyin mosque in Fez is the
centre of one of the world's oldest
universities, founded in 850 A.D. and
still active today in the teaching of Muslim
law. Students sit around their lecturers
in a circle, following a tradition
dating back to the earliest days of Islam.
Indian works into Arabic and studied and
discussed a range of scientific subjects.
The first "House of Science" known to
history was created in 10th-century Egypt.
Houses of Science had more students and
teachers than Houses of Wisdom and
concentrated on mathematics and the
medical sciences rather than translation.
It should be noted that mathematics then
encompassed arithmetic, algebra, geo¬
metry, astronomy and music.
The 12th century saw the development
of the state-sponsored colleges known as
madrasahs (from the Arab word darasa,
"to learn"). These institutions are generally
associated with the vizier Nizam al-Mulk,
who established the famous Nizamiyah of
Baghdad between 1065 and 1067. (See
facing page.)
In medieval times medicine was consider¬
ed a branch of philosophy, and as such it
attracted the attention of several Muslim
philosophers, such as Äl-Farahbi and
Avicenna. Medicine was taught in the
mosques, but medical studies flourished
above all in an institution known as the
bimaristan, which was the equivalent of
the modern teaching hospital.
Although the mosques, kuttabs, houses
of wisdom and science, madrasahs and
34
hospitals were the main educational insti¬
tutions in Arab cities, the ulemas and the
apprenticeship system practised by the
guilds and the mystic orders also played
an important role in educational life.
The Muslim educational system had
only two levels: the elementary and the
advanced. Children between the ages of
five and ten had no option but to attend
the kuttab, where they were taught to
read the Quran and to memorize as much
of it as they could. They also picked up
writing from copying passages from the
Quran and learned a little arithmetic.
Sometimes poetry and "wise sayings"
were also taught at this level.
Kuttab education lasted roughly five
years. The educational system did not pro¬
vide an intermediate or pre-mosque stage,
and a pupil who wanted to continue his
education after leaving the kuttab had to
find a "circle" in a mosque or a madrasah
which would introduce him to advanced
studies.
In most cases, however, a pupil would
choose to take up a trade or craft when
he left the kuttab, becoming apprenticed
to a master craftsman who was often his
own father or another member of his
family. (See article page 12).
Muslim teachers made a sharp distinc¬
tion between the methods to be used for
educating children on the one hand and
adolescents and adults on the other. At
the kuttab level, reliance was placed
almost exclusively on learning by heart, on
the grounds that memory is usually most
active during childhood and must be
fully exploited.
In subjects other than the Quran it was
generally accepted that the teacher should
proceed "from the simple to the difficult"
and adapt his teaching to the pupil's
capacities. Avicenna insisted on the
importance of taking into account the
child's temperament and natural aptitudes
before preparing him for a particular career
or profession.
The most characteristic feature of Muslim
education in the mosque was the "circle",
a group of young scholars gathered around
a teacher who sat with his back against
the column of a mosque. This practice,
later followed in the madrasahs, dates
back to pre-lslamic times and is still follow¬
ed today.
At first teachers lectured from memory
without referring to a text. Soon, how- k
ever, they began to use notes, and in the*
CONTINUED PAGE 52
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
by Badr Eddin Arodaky
The Madrasahs
The first universities
in the Arab world
THE first school in the Arab world was the mosque built at
Medina in the 7th century by the Prophet and his Compa¬
nions. From then until the 10th century mosques were used
to bring the new faith to the people and to instruct them in their
religion. But, as social structures and the values and rules that
governed social life became more complex, the Islamic community
began to face new problems.
A century after the Prophet's death in 632 new forms of teaching
became necessary: study circles were held not only in the mosques
but also in the palaces, in the streets and even in the market
places. The teaching was no longer limited to the Quran but also
covered literature, poetry, grammar, and other subjects.
Groups of grammarians, students and onlookers gathered in
Baghdad's Mirbad Square, and classes in jurisprudence, poetry
and grammar were often held in one and the same mosque.
These classes and study groups constituted a kind of "free
university", for the teachers were not subject to any particular
restrictions or obligations and students were free to choose
among the available classes, discussion groups and study circles.
This ferment of activity shows a high degree of social and
cultural cohesion. The transmission of knowledge by men and
books and the contribution made by the various cultures which
came together in the melting-pot enabled Arab culture to achieve
unprecedented development and impetus in every field of learning.
During the reign of the Abbasid caliphs in Baghdad (from 750
A.D. to the end of the 13th century) religious education became a
branch of learning in its own right, with some teachers specializ¬
ing in the Quran, the hadith (acts and sayings traditionally attribut¬
ed to the Prophet) and jurisprudence, while others studied Arabic
language, literature and history. The study circles also grew in
number and quality during this period, forming the nuclei of what
were to become the madrasahs, colleges intended for adults who
had already received primary education in private schools or
mosques.
In the 10th century, the madrasah emerged as an independent
institution distinct from the mosque, although madrasahs at least
in the early days were set up either for a single jurist or for
teaching the tenets of a particular school of jurists
These establishments soon came under the control of the ruling
power and were subject to its "planning". The degree of control
and the type of planning were partly determined by the very nature
of the conflicts between the Abbasid caliphs and the Fatimid
dynasty.
The Fatimids, who controlled Syria and Egypt after 969 A.D.,
tried to wrest power from the Abbasid caliphs in Baghdad, whose
rule was based on the strength of the Seljuq Turks and who, from
1055 onwards, controlled the entire eastern flank of the Muslim
world.
This power struggle was paralleled by a religious struggle, a
frequent occurrence in Islam, where religious, political and tem¬
poral issues so often intermingled.
The Fatimids spread their doctrine of Shiism through intensive
preaching, chiefly in the mosques of areas outside their control.
These preachers, who were trained at the university of Al-Azhar in
Cairo, the chief seat of Shiite learning at that time, met with stiff
resistance from the Seljuqs.
Nizam al-Mulk (1018-1092), Grand Vizier of the Abbasids, drew
up an educational policy whose long-term aim was to contain and
BADR-EDDIN ARODAKY, Syrian sociologist and writer, is a staff member of the
university of Damascus. He has published many studies on the sociology of
culture..
subsequently smash the Fatimid advance. The implementation of
this policy began with the creation of the Nizamiyah Madrasah
(named after the Grand Vizier), the first "university" of the Arab
world. It was founded by the public authorities, who controlled,
financed and administered it.
Located in Baghdad, the political and intellectual centre of the
caliphate, the Nizamiyah was much more than the first public
college. Officially opened in 1065 under the patronage of the
caliph himself, it was to serve as a model for all the madrasahs of
the Muslim world during the next 200 years.
First of all, other madrasahs modelled their organization on that
of the Nizamiyah, whose status as a public institution was explicitly
set out in the foundation deed drawn up by its head, Nizam al-Mulk.
The establishment was managed by the Vizier himself or by his per¬
sonal representative. For the duration of their studies (from four to
six years), the students received a grant covering the cost of food,
accommodation and miscellaneous expenses. The madrasah also
contained a large number of masters' and students' lodgings, while
its library received gifts and legacies of books.
Its methods of recruiting staff were also imitated. The teachers,
who had to belong to the Shafii school, were appointed by the
head of the Nizamiyah or by his representative. Their salaries
were drawn on a special account, something like a modern endow¬
ment fund.
Its curriculum was also imitated by other madrasahs. Students
and teachers alike had to belong to the Shafii school, and while
teaching methods depended on the individual teachers (who were
chosen from among the great scholars of the age), the syllabus
had a purely religious purpose, being designed to equip students
to defend the principles of Shafiism against Fatimid and Shiite
propaganda.
The madrasah was thus an institution of higher education in
which religious disciplines such as the study of the Quran and
jurisprudence were complemented by Arabic language and litera¬
ture, poetry, arithmetic and other subjects. Students were only
admitted after attending schools or study circles in mosques.
Two centuries later, the Nizamiyah was overshadowed by ano¬
ther madrasah, Al-Mustansiriyah, created in 1227 and named after
its founder. Caliph al-Mustansir. The caliph wanted to make the
new madrasah into an intellectual centre capable of reviving the
cultural splendour of the golden age of such caliphs as Harun al-
Rashid or Al-Ma'mun.
Unlike the Nizamiyah, it did not limit its teaching to that of a
single school but taught the doctrines of the four schools of law
of orthodox Islam. This intellectual open-mindedness was reflect¬
ed in the madrasah's construction, which comprised four ¡wans
(porticoes or wings), one for each school. In addition to religious
knowledge, many other subjects, such as mathematics, medicine,
pharmacy and geometry, were taught there.
It also differed from the Nizamiyah in that the number of
students was fixed, being limited to 308: 62 in each of the four
schools, 10 for the study of the Quran, 10 for the hadith, 10 for
medicine, and so forth.
Thirty years after its foundation, the Mustansiriyah was des¬
troyed by the Mongols who captured and destroyed Baghdad in
1258. The madrasah's books were thrown into the river, and its
teachers were drowtlfcd. After this assult the conquerors rebuilt
the madrasah, and it continued to function as such until the com¬
ing of the Ottoman Turks, who turned it into a caravanserai.
The third great madrasah, Al-Azhar in Cairo, remained a
sanctuary of Shiism and a training centre for its new converts
right up until the fall of the Fatimids. With the advent of the I
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
, Ayyubite dynasty in Egypt in 1171, its influence waned, only to
revive some years later when it became the centre of Sunnite
teaching. Al-Azhar was modelled on the other two great
madrasahs.
During the 13th century all three served the same cause, but,
whereas Al-Azhar continued to develop and spread its influence
throughout the Islamic world, the other two madrasahs, weaken¬
ed by the ravages of the Mongols and torn by the conflicting
ambitions of local rulers, declined and eventually disappeared. Al-
Azhar, on the other hand, is still over 1,000 years after it was
founded in 970 the greatest religious university in the Arab world.
(See facing page).
Al-Nizamiyah, Al-Mustansiriyah and AI-AzKar, the three great
universities of the Muslim world between the 11th and 13th
centuries, were taken as models for educational institutions in
other Arab cities: the Zahiriyah in Damascus (1264), the Nasiriyah
in Cairo, the famous Zaytunah of 14th-century Tunis, and the
equally famous Qarawiyin at Fez in Morocco.
For four centuries all these madrasahs played a major role not
only in the political and religious spheres for which they had been
founded, but also in the expansion and enrichment of Arabo-
Islamic culture.
Badr Eddin Arodaky
Cupola and minaret dominate the courtyard of Al-Azhar ("the splendid"), the great Cairo mosque which has been a
teaching centre for the entire Muslim world for more than 1,000 years. When the great Egyptian writer Taha
Hussein was a student there at the turn of the century, education at Al-Azhar was still much as it had been in
medieval times. Today Al-Azhar has facilities for studying every discipline of the natural and social sciences, in
addition to its institutes for traditional Islamic and Arabic studies.
Photo © Almasv. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
by Taha Hussein
Schooldays in Cairo
A great Egyptian writer
looks back on his childhood
Taha Hussein, who died in 1973, was one of the
greatest Arab writers of modern times. Born in
Egypt in 1889, he became blind at the age of three
but nonetheless pursued his schooling in Cairo, first
at the famous Muslim university of Al-Azhar and
then at the newly-founded Egyptian university.
Later he continued his studies in Paris, where he
obtained his doctorate at the Sorbonne. In his
masterpiece. Stream of Days, Taha Hussein retraced
his childhood and adolescence through the
experience of a hero who is simply referred to as
"the child". His account of his student days in
Cairo in the early years of the 20th century is both
poetic and accurate.
The following extracts from Stream of Days show
that the teaching methods then used at Al-Azhar
were strikingly similar to those current in the Arab-
Islarr.ic world ten centuries earlier. However,
reforms carried out shortly after the period Taha
Hussein describes brought profound changes and a
degree of modernization to Al-Azhar.
Text © Copyright. Reproduction prohibited '
WALKING beside his companion, the child crossed the
courtyard. As his foot touched the low step marking
the entrance to Al-Azhar, the University, his heart grew
heavy with modesty and humility; his spirit soared with pride. Step
by step he advanced, across matting so worn that the floor appear¬
ed in places as if offering to the feet of the visitors the blessing of
its touch, of contact with holy ground.
The child loved Al-Azhar at this moment of dawn as the wor¬
shippers finished their morning prayers and gathered their eyes
still heavy with sleep in circles around the columns of the mos¬
que, to await the teacher who would give a lesson on the hadith,
or traditions, or on dogma or theology.
Here and there, a teacher was beginning his lecture in the weary
tones of one who has awakened early to say his prayers, who has
not yet breakfasted, and whose body is still drained of strength
and energy. The voice was tranquil, gentle, slightly wavering.
"In the name of Allah, the Merciful! Glory to Allah, the All-
Powerfull May His blessing and salvation lie upon our Lord
Muhammad, the noblest of the Prophets, on His family and His
Companions! This is what the author tells us, may Allah preserve
his soul and enlighten us with his wisdom, amen!"
...At dawn, the voices were supplicant, rising like an appeal to
the benevolence of the ancient authors. At midday, they were
militant, launched like an army against its enemies. This contrast
both amazed and amused the child. Staying close to his compan¬
ion, he negotiated the two steps leading to the ¡wan, the portico
surrounding the main courtyard of the mosque.
His companion settled him beside the teacher's stall, which was
linked by a heavy chain to one of the sacred columns.
"Sit here. You will hear a hadith lesson. When my own lecture
is over, I will come and fetch you."
The subject of the lesson was the basis of Law, and the teacher
was sheikh Radi, may Allah preserve his soul. The text was taken
from the Tahrir, by the 15th-century author Kamal ibn Humam.
The child listened in fascination to the words, with feelings in
which panic, ardour, respect and veneration were inextricably
intermingled. The basis of Law! What could that possibly mean?
Who was the sheikh Radi? Tahrir? What a strange word! Kamal
Ibn Humam! Could any names be more magnificent? Knowledge
was indeed like a boundless ocean, and an intelligent man could do
nothing better than plunge into its waves...
...For the moment, however, he must listen. Understanding
would come later. How many times did he turn the same phrase
over and over in his mind before it began to make sense! He had
learned little, but he had gained respect for knowledge, a profound
feeling of deference towards scholars, an awareness of his own
ignorance, and the determination to work as hard as he could!
Sitting there beside the column and playing with the chain, the
child listened as the sheikh went through the hadith lesson. Oh,
he understood the lesson perfectly. His only objection was to the
avalanche of names and prepositions which the teacher poured
over the heads of his pupils. "So-and-so said, according to so-
and-so, as it is related by so-and-so..."
What was the point of jumbling all those names together, of
piling up all those prepositions? The child waited impatiently for
the sheikh to get to the text of the hadith. The text was what mat¬
tered; the commentary could be set aside...
...The child wondered when he would become a full member of
the university. For the moment, he was just a child, listening
carefully and conscientiously to two lessons...
At last, the great day arrived. At the end of a Law lesson, the
child was told to present himself for the test in recitation from the
Quran which served as the entrance examination.
The news that he was to be examined in an hour's time dismay¬
ed him. Uncertain, anxious even, he hurried to the Chapel of the
Blind, where the examination was to take place. But as he ap¬
proached the examiners, his fear vanished. He sat down to wait
patiently until they had finished with the previous candidate, and
then, suddenly, one of the examiners called his name. He took his
place in front of the jury. They asked him to recite the Sura of
"the Cave", but he had scarcely begun when they asked him to
recite the Sura of "the Spider". After a few verses, they interrupt¬
ed him again.
"That's enough, blind boy," said one of the examiners. "You
have passed!"
The child was shocked. The examination had been meaningless,
and in no way a test of recitation. He had expected them to
demand a recitation at least as long as those his father asked of
him. He went away, delighted with his success but furious with
the examiners and scornful of their methods. Before they left the
Chapel of the Blind, his brother drew him aside, and one of the ser¬
vants circled his wrist with a string, sealing the ends with lead.
"It's all over," said the servant. "Congratulations!"
The child could not understand the meaning of the curious
bracelet. His brother explained that he must wear it for a week,
until the medical examination, when his health would be checked,
his age estimated, and he would be vaccinated against smallpox.
But he remained fascinated by the bracelet... It was the symbol
of his success in the examination. He had taken the first step...
I Taha Hussein
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
In the Arab Islamic world, calligraphy was widely used in architecture both for the message of
its text and as pure decoration. Architects and sculptors sometimes covered entire walls in
palaces or mosques with rich combinations of Arabic script, stylized plant motifs and geometric
forms. The walls of the Alhambra palace (below) in Granada (Spain) abound with Arabic
inscriptions exquisitely carved in stucco. Built in the 14th century, the Alhambra is one of the
oldest Arab palaces to have survived intact and one of the jewels of Arab architecture.
bpv
Photo Cart-Unesco
m mm¿m ^TZVfTT/TÇW
,\ rTF^r-,
SUSS cH
ifl
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
by Mustapha El Habib
THE Arab contribution to the histori¬
cal, religious and linguistic aspects
of Islamic civilization can be easily
identified and distinguished from the other
great creative forces that shaped the
world of Islam. It is much less easy how¬
ever, to disentangle the Arab thread from
the skein of influences that went to form
the art and architecture of the Muslim
world.
And yet the Arabs and the Arab genius
undeniably left a mark on the plastic arts
of Islam. There is, after all, a fundamental
difference between the art of such ancient
and homogeneous cultures as those of
Mesopotamia, Egypt and Persia, and the
art forms that were rapidly developed by
the earliest Islamic societies.
But let us first examine some key facts
about the culture and history of the world
that confronted the Arabs as they moved
up out of the Arabian Peninsula towards
the Middle East.
Modern studies tend to focus mainly on
the Greco-Latin and Persian cultures which
played a fundamental role in shaping the
profile of Islamic civilization. But other
forces were at work, too, and none more
so than the Yemen with its ancient
and distinguished Arab culture. According
to Arab authors, the Yemen contributed
to such important features of Islamic
civilization as civil engineering and the
organization of urban life.
We also known that in the north of the
Arabian peninsula, on the frontiers of
Byzantium and Persia, there were other
centres of Arab culture, influenced by
many years of contact with their powerful
neighbours, yet conserving a distinct
personality of their own.
Among the most important of these
centres were the principalities of the
Palmyrenes (in present-day Syria), the
Lakhmids (Iraq) and the Ghassanids (Syria).
Situated at an oasis in the Syrian desert,
on the caravan route from Damascus to
the Euphrates, the city of Palmyra is noted
for its economic, political and artistic
achievements. During the 3rd century
A.D., the Palmyrenes joined forces with
Rome in challenging the power of the
Sassanid dynasty, which ruled Persia from
226 to 651. The rapid conquest of Egypt
and Asia Minor by Zenobia, the celebrated
queen of Palmyra, foreshadowed Arab
expansion a few centuries later. Rome,
not yet in decline, was startled by this
lightning progress and turned against
Zenobia. Her troops were defeated and
Palmyra was sacked by the emperor
Aurelian in 272 A.D.
MUSTAPHA EL HABIB, Tunisian specialist in Arab
Islamic art, lectures at the Ecole du Louvre, Paris, on
Arabic epigraphy and paleography. Curator of the
Maghrib (North African) arts department at the
Museum of African and Oceanian Arts in Paris, he has
written widely on many aspects of Islamic art and
civilization.
The fall of Palmyra paved the way for
the arrival of another Arab people on the
Middle-Eastern stage. These were the
Lakhmids, who originated in the Yemen
and whose capital was the city of al-Hira
in Iraq. By faith Nestorian Christians (1),
the Lakhmids struck a delicate balance in
their relations with Rome and Sassanid
Persia.
Patrons of the arts, and of poetry in
particular, ' they enjoyed considerable
influence at the Sassanid court, while
their own capital, according to ancient
texts, was a place of exceptional beauty,
with numerous princely palaces.
Al-Hira was the meeting-point of three
different cultural streams: Persian, indig¬
enous and pagan Arabic, and Byzantine.'
It was here that Arabic writing was develop¬
ed, that an urban Arab culture flourished,
and that Christianity assumed the form in
which it would be carried into the deserts
of Arabia.
The Ghassanids, another Yemenite Arab
people which had settled in Syria, profess¬
ed a Monophysite form of Christianity (2).
In the early 6th century they joined forces
with . Byzantium against Persia and the
Lakhmids.
The Ghassanid rulers carried the develop¬
ment of Arab culture to a high pitch of
refinement. They played an active role in
the urbanization of Syria and were once
thought to have been the founders of
Damascus.
The defeat of the Ghassanids by the
Byzantines in 592 A.D. and of the Lakh¬
mids by the Persians in 613 A.D. left the
Arabs . of the Syrian and Mesopotamian
deserts in disarray.
But it was not long before they found
new allies. Doubtless remembering their
common origins in the southern part of the
(II Nestorianism: the doctrine imputed to Nestorius
(c. 380-451) according to which distinct divine and
human natures are to be attributed to Christ:
(2) Monophysitism: the doctrine that recognizes in the
person of Jesus Christ only one nature rather than
two, divine and human. It is today professed by the
Armenian and Syrian churches as well as the Coptic
Church of Egypt and Ethiopia.
Peninsula, and united in hatred of their
former overlords, they welcomed the new
wave of conquerors which, shortly before
the death ot the Prophet, swept up north¬
wards from the Hejaz region of the Red
Sea coast. They rallied to the banners of
their Islamic kinsmen, and eventually
adopted their religion.
The progression of the Arab converts
to Islam towards the Fertile Crescent the
semicircle of rich land that stretches from
Egypt to Mesopotamiawas thus more
than an isolated and unexpected event
which challenged the supremacy of the
Greco-Latin and Persian civilizations. It
was a chapter of history deeply rooted in
the Middle-Eastern past, and one which
marked revival as much as revolution.
The nomad of the Hejaz and his Arab
kinsmen drew their inspiration from a
historical, cultural and religious heritage
which had been steadily growing along
the banks of the mainstream of history
since the pre-Christian era.
Any assessment of Arab artistic creativi¬
ty should not be confined to a purely
quantitative analysis of the plastic arts of
the nomads. It should take into account
the whole of Arab society of that time,
whose common experience, shared by
nomadic and sedentary Arabs alike, rang¬
ed beyond the limits of the Hejaz region,
and even of the Arabian Peninsula. This
approach should help us to understand
the rapidity with which an original Islamic
art came into being.
When he built the house in which he
would spend his exile in Medina, the
Prophet Muhammad created a new type
of construction whose layout was to
inspire the so-called hypostyle Arab mos¬
que (whose ceiling is supported by pillars).
All forms of creativity involve borrowings
and outside influences, but one basic
feature that distinguishes the mosque
from the places of worship of other reli¬
gions, such as Christianity, is a direct
reflection of the ancient nomadic custom
of sitting side by side in a row during |
desert halts. As worshippers, they adopted I
"Eternal glory and everlasting renown", reads the Arabic inscription on this small ivory
plaque. Carved with the flowery, cursive script known as "thuluth", the plaque was
produced in Egypt or Syria in the 13th or 14th centuries.
Photo Luc Joubert © Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Paris
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
1 ï
\i \
>t jl. u.c.tillA-^K.
Il I
ft
fcU»§JU!fÍ¿V
The Holy City of Jerusalem
Jerusalem is one of the holiest places of Islam. In earliest Islamic
times, milestones were set along roads leading to the city for the
benefit of travellers and pilgrims. Above, a milestone inscribed with
its distance from Jerusalem and with the name of the Ommayad caliph
Abd al Malik, the builder of the famous Dome of the Rock (right).
Inside this sacred shrine, which was completed in 691, a circular
colonnade surrounds the Holy Rock (below). Also known as the
Mosque of Omar, the Dome of the Rock was built in the ornate
Byzantine tradition and was lavishly decorated with polychrome
mosaics. Together with the nearby Mosque of AI Aqsa, it is one of
the most important of all Islamic shrines.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
, the same alignment, and this explains why
their prayer halls were of greater width
than length.
This architectural innovation accompan¬
ied the Prophet's revelation of a new type
of religious institution: one in which every
political, religious, moral or social issue
concerning the community could be raised.
Additions to mosque architecture after
the death of the Prophet are all direct or
indirect consequences of his original initia¬
tives. Among the former are the minaret
the tower from which the faithful are
summoned to prayerwhich is a develop¬
ment of the custom practised during the
Prophet's lifetime, of issuing such sum¬
monses from the highest roof in the vicinity
of the mosque; and the columns and
capitals which are derived from the roof-
supporting palm-tree trunks of the original
prayer hall at Medina;
Indirect consequences are seen in the
mihrab, the prayer niche in the centre of
the wall closest to Mecca, the holy city of
Islam; and the epigraphic decoration which
replaced the figurative ornamentation of
pre-lslamic Arab monuments.
Islamic architecture was carried to
perfection as a result of constant technical
improvements under the first Arab dynas¬
ties. Thus, written sources state that a
kind of concrete was used during the first
centuries of the Hegira. It was made
of chalk, sand, clay and rubble which
hardened to a rock-like consistency.
This explains why Arab Islamic monu¬
ments are not merely graceful, but extra¬
ordinarily resistant to wear and tear. Some
9th-century mosques and castles in the
Iberian Peninsula have survived until today
in a perfect state of preservation.
The problem of roof supports was solv¬
ed in different ways. Sometimes, columns
from earlier monuments were used, but in
Eastern and Western Islam, the columns
of antiquity gave way to slender shafts
and expansive capitals reminiscent of the
world of plants and trees, and more parti¬
cularly of the palm groves among which
Muhammad and his companions lived.
The specific character of the Arab mos¬
que was finally established when the
architects revolted against the bare sur¬
faces and the angular and rectangular
forms favoured by their Greek prede¬
cessors. This refusal found expression in
two new lines of research, one concerning
the structure of the mosque, the other con¬
cerning its decoration.
In each case, the aim was to dispense
with angularity, and to revive the orna¬
mental tradition which, in Mesopotamia,
Persia and Byzantium alike, had been
brought to a peak of perfection after
thousands of years spent in repeating the j
same patterns. I
Built before 850 A.D., the
Great Mosque at Susah
(Tunisia) is one of the
oldest in the Arab Islamic
world. Right, a corner of
the main courtyard, lined
with arcades. A frieze
in ornamental Arabic
script runs along the
top of the wall, forming
part of the fabric of
the architecture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Places for worship
in desert and city
Left, in Southern Algeria, deep in the Sahara,
passing worshippers have used rows of
stones to mark out an enclosure for prayers.
A Muslim can pray to Allah wherever he
happens to beas long as he faces Mecca.
To designate the direction to be faced during
prayer, mosques have a niche or alcove
known as the mihrab in the wall facing
Mecca. In the great mosque of Cordoba
(Spain), the mihrab consists of an entire
room, resplendent with a forest of columns
and a cupola (right). Built by Abd ar Rahman
in 785, the mosque is an outstanding example
of Arab Islamic architecture in Andalusia,
complex in design and rich in decoration.
A more modest example of Islamic religious
architecture is the mosque of a Mauritanian
desert community at Chinguetti (below).
At the other end of the Arab Islamic world,
the muezzin (below . left) calls the faithful
prayer from leaning minaret of Mosul (Iraq).
to
Photos Naud © Afrique-Photo, Paris.
a»-* J<
- ,
i .
*,-. M
'y
1
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris.
, The first line of research led to the
development of the cupola, the dome, the
arch and the so-called muqarna work,
which had the ornate appearance of a
honeycomb or stalactite.
Research in decoration led to the inven¬
tion of the arabesque, a style of ornamenta¬
tion involving fancifully-twisted plant
motifs, capable of expressing rhythmic
movement and suitable to the Islamic
preference for completely filled surfaces.
The mathematical precision of the
arabesque would in the 16th century find,
an admirer in the Italian painter Raphael,
who introduced it into the art of the
Renaissance.
But no account of the quest for new
ways of decorating the mosque would be
complete without mention of Arab orna¬
mental epigraphic art, whose history is
closely related to that of the arabesque.
No civilization has made more use than
Islam of writing for ornamental purposes.
A written Arabic alphabet, composed of
somewhat rudimentary Semitic characters
inscribed from right to left, either separ¬
ately or linked in a cursive hand, was already
being used in the Arabian peninsula in the
5th and 6th centuries A.D., before the
appearance of Islam.
Early Arab authors mention the import
ance which the Prophet Muhammad
attached to writing as a means of propagat¬
ing the Muslim faith, pointing out that his
entourage included not only his compa¬
nions, whose task was to learn the revela¬
tions of the Quran by heart but also a
number of scribes entrusted with the task
of transcribing the revealed message.
As Islam spread throughout the Arabian
Peninsula, there was an increasing need
to instruct the faithful in the art of writing
the Quranic language, and we are told
that after the battle of Badr against the
pagan Meccans, the Prophet liberated
every literate captive who agreed to teach
the art to ten young Muslims.
With the extension of the faith, and in
the space of a few years, Arabic writing,
as the vehicle of the divine revelation,
was adopted by all the converted peoples.
Today the script is used not only in Arabic,
but also in languages as varied as Persian,
Hindustani and Malay, as well as a number
of languages of Black Africa. Until the
reforms of 1928, it was also used in
Turkey.
The aesthetic qualities of Arabic script,
which were clearly apparent early in the
Islamic era, stem from the individual
characters themselves and the symmetrical
manner in which they are related to each
other in composition.
These qualities, coupled with the reli¬
gious prestige of the Quranic language,
soon made Arabic writing the object of
embellishment, and led to the creation of
calligraphy, the earliest and the most
"Arabic" of all the plastic arts of Islam
whose invention is ascribed by modern
specialists to Ali ibn Abi Talib, cousin and
son-in-law of the Prophet.
Rapidly "democratized", because it was
an art which all literate Arabs could prac¬
tise without distinction of wealth or social
status, calligraphy was also considered to
be the noblest of occupations, since it was
through writing alone that the revealed
message of the Quran could be given a
tangible form.
After the initial, formative period con¬
sidered to cover more or less the first
century of the Hegira Arabic writing in
its two forms (angular and cursive) was
systematically developed. From a number
of possible alternatives, the angular form
which finally emerged as the basic model
is the script known as "Kufic", from the
city of Kufa in Iraq, which was one of the
greatest centres of classical Arab culture.
This script was used at an early date to
transcribe the text of the Quran, so that
it came to be used throughout the Islamic k
world. Y
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Yvette Vincent Alleaume, Paris.
Kufic writing employed characters
reduced to their simplest form, so that
decipherment depended as much on their
context as on their shape. It became the
subject of artistic experimentation which
reached a peak of perfection in the late
8th and early 9th centuries in a type of
ornamental inscription which determined
the whole art of Arabic calligraphy.
Angular Kufic served as the basis for
other styles of writing, which included
"foliate" Kufic (in which the spaces be¬
tween the strokes were filled with plant
motifs which at first sprang organically
from the letters themselves), "plaited"
Kufic (in which a procession of upright
letters stretched away towards infinity
against a floral background, and which
found particular favour in the Maghrib);
and "geometrical" or "quadrangular"
Kufic, generally used for decoration on
buildings, in which the letters of the in¬
scriptions were made from materials such as
baked or unbaked brick.
In the 10th century, a fluent cursive
script known as Nashki and used by scribes
and scholars for inscriptions on papyrus,
began to be employed for the transcription
of Quranic texts. The main difference
between Kufic and Nashki is that Kufic
letters are static, while Nashki characters
are linked together in an undulating,
uninterrupted line.
Guided for the most part by the rules of
angular writing, the famous calligrapher
and Abbasid minister Ibn Muqla (d. 939-
940) invented a mathematically proportion¬
ed cursive script. This writing was perfect¬
ed and amplified by another great Arab
calligrapher, Ibn al-Bawwab (d. 1022),
who laid down the rules of cursive script
which would enable subsequent genera¬
tions to practise the art of calligraphy in a
manner that was both free and rational.
In this brief survey of the Arab mosque
and Arabic calligraphy, we have tried to
throw light on a little-known aspect of the
Arab contribution to Islamic civilization
and to place the Arabs in their context
among the other great creative peoples of
the Arabian peninsula, with whom they
lived in close contact for so long.
However, until a comprehensive history
of pre-lslamic Arab civilization is written,
the nomad of the Hejaz and his kinsmen
in northern and southern Arabia will remain
shadowy figures, and their contribution to
the art of Islam will remain a matter of
conjecture.
Ancient Arab sources, which have up
to now been victims of neglect of misinter¬
pretation, contain a wealth of information
which might be used in the investigation
of monuments which the historians of
Antiquity described as magnificent, but
which have long since disappeared.
Only when these sources are tapped
will the history of Arabia cease to be
merely a field for speculation on a mun¬
dane sequence of battles, diplomatic
intrigues and genealogies, and will help us
to appreciate the true originality of Arab
art. Only then will it be possible to write
the history of an art that is truly Arab, and w
Mustapha El Habib
not merely Islamic.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Embroidery in brick and stone
The Yemen is one of the oldest centres of Arab civilization.
Throughout its history, this mountainous yet fertile country
(widely known in Antiquity as Arabia Felix fortunate Arabia)
has always preserved distinctive and original forms of
cultural expression. It today comprises two independent
states: the Arab Republic of Yemen and the People's
Democratic Republic of Yemen. Yemeni towns and cities
are renowned for the beauty of their architecture. Left,
townscape in Sanaa, capital of the Arab Republic of Yemen.
The façades of the tall terraced houses are resplendent with
white, brown and green ornamentation; the windowpanes
are of multicoloured stained glass. Right, a cascade of
domes and arches in the ancient town of Sadah. Below,
ablutions basin in one of the many mosques in Zabid.
*Aj!rt«rtÉH**vni
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
How Arabic became
the international
language of science
by Salah Galal
CLASSICAL Arabic science was a
vast and complex enterprise that
was effectively launched by the
early Abbasid caliphs at Baghdad shortly
after 750 A.D. For at least 600 years
thereafter it maintained a vigorous existen¬
ce, gradually spreading over a geographi¬
cal area that extended from Andalusia to
the lands beyond the Amu Darya River in
Central Asia.
Arabic rapidly became an international
language of science to, a greater extent
than any other language had ever been.
SALAH GALAL, science editor of the Egyptian daily
AI Ahram since 1959, is also editor of the Arabic
edition of the World Health Organization's monthly
World Health. The author or translator of many
scientific publications, he is correspondent of the
weekly science journal Nature.
Until the caliphs organized the translation
into Arabic of ancient Greek and Syriac
scientific texts, Arabic had been the lan¬
guage of poetry, of the Quran, and of the
recently developed disciplines concerned
with Islamic religion and with the Arabic
language itself.
By the 11th century the great scientist
Al-Biruni was describing Arabic as the
language most suited for scientific expres¬
sion. But he was speaking after the
event. The ninth-century decision to turn
Arabic into a vehicle for scientific tradition
that had previously been alien to it was an
act of great originality and imagination.
Islamic achievements in optics were
solidly based on the foundations laid by
the ancient Greeks. Ptolemy's treatise on
optics was translated into Arabic early on,
and a Latin version was made from Arabic
in Sicily in the 12th century. The treatise
now survives only in the Latin version,
both the Greek original and the Arabic
translation having been lost.
Some Arabic authors, as a result of the
translation of their works into Latin,
became widely known under Latinized
names: Al-Razi as Rhazes, Ibn Sina as
Avicenna, Ibn Rushd as Averroes, and so
on. Their books were widely read and
frequently cited and quoted by writers in
the West.
In the 10th century, Ibn al-Haytham
formulated a theory of vision quite distinct
from any other that existed then or had
existed earlier. He was a mathematician,
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
£.*<- <.< i
r
l'Aj
"> J»
^ 7 7 ^
1 è f
p
i
74"^
r
i^ac ''t <*^r*
^ <j
-A* t^vA|^/^jr*»
HT
'>
Lt
H* ^ _>«
\l
"^
f ,?
-rUl
A
á
y
^HHI
^
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris
Left, the great reservoir at Kairouan (which means
"encampment" in Arabic) in Tunisia, built in 862. A 48-sided
polygon (128 m. in diameter) it is the most impressive of a series
of hydraulic projects realized by the Emir Abu Ibrahim Ahmed of
the Aghlabid dynasty. Adjoining it is a smaller (17-sided)
polygonal reservoir with a diameter of 37 metres.
Above, map of Central Asia by the 10th-century geographer Ibn
Hawqal. The title, inscribed in Kufic script, reads "Picture of
what lies beyond the river" (the Amu Darya). In margin at right
are the words "the Maghrib" (where the sun sets). (See also
caption on page 9).
not a natural philosopher, but he combin¬
ed physical doctrines with mathematical
methods.
From natural philosophers Ibn al-Hay¬
tham derived the idea that vision occurs
when a "form" emanating from an object
enters the eye. As a mathematician, he
was impressed by the geometrical approach
taken in the works of Euclid and Ptolemy.
His own contribution can be characteriz¬
ed as an attempt to apply the geometrical
method to the physical doctrine of forms.
He tried to show how a form capable of
representing the visible features of an
object, whether large or small, can enter
through the pupil and make its way to the
brain, where the process of vision is
completed. To achieve the synthesis he
desired, Ibn al-Haytham was led to alter
important, sometimes essential, compo¬
nents of earlier theories. At the same time,
he formulated questions that had never
been conceived before.
Ibn al-Haytham's Optics is a large and
comprehensive work that includes, not
only a new theory of vision, but also
important discussions of the propagation,
reflection, and refraction of light and
colour. Its superiority to the treatises of
Euclid, Ptolemy, Al-Kindi, and Ibn Sina,
all of which were translated into Latin,
soon became clear to Latin medieval
writers. In the 13th century, Roger Bacon
frequently referred to Ibn al-Haytham as
"the author on optics".
Almost all branches of the healing arts
in Islam were indebted more to the indefat¬
igable efforts of Hunayn ibn Ishaq Al Ibadi
(809-873) and his team of translators than
to any other ninth-century author or
educator. Together with his students and
associates, Hunayn made the most impor¬
tant medical writings of the Greeks availa¬
ble in Arabic, and established a solid
foundation for the development of Arabic
medicine by devising a distinctive metho¬
dology, which was followed, modified,
and perfected during the following century.
The physician Ibn Butlan elaborated on
the six "non-natural principles" that had
been identified earlier by Hunayn: clean
air, moderate diet and drink, rest and
work, wakefulness and slumber, evacua¬
tion of superfluities, and emotional reac¬
tions and involvement.
If these six principles are kept in equili¬
brium, he maintained, health results; if
abused or imbalanced, sickness occurs.
Ibn Butlan also recommended the utiliza¬
tion of fine music to lift the morale of
patients and help speed their recovery.
The development of Arabic clinical
medicine and therapeutics reached its peak
in Andalusia, in the works of the physician-
statesman Ibn Wafid and in the medical
writing, teaching, and practice of Ibn
Zuhr (known in Latin as Avenzoar). In his
famous Book Facilitating the Study of
Therapy and Diet, he dealt with the
diagnosis and treatment of diseases,
describing, possibly for the first time in
medical history, certain chest abcesses and
pericardial diseases. He also emphasized
medical experimentation, as well as clinical
observation, treatment and pathology.
It was under the patronage of the Arab
caliphs that hospitals were first estab¬
lished and flourished in the Muslim world.
The early Arab concept of the hospital
became the prototype for the development
of the modern hospital an institution
operated by private owners or by govern¬
ment.
The great 10th-century philosopher and
physician Al-Razi considered hospitals of
primary importance in providing practical k
training in the medical profession and in Y
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Hercules the celestial dancer
In his Book of Fixed Stars, the 10th-century astronomer As-Sufi followed the ancient
practice of representing the constellations by animal or human figures or objects. Above,
representation of the northern constellation Hercules is from a 13th-century manuscript
version of As-Sufi's work. According to tradition, Hercules is depicted as a dancer, but
although he is elsewhere shown as a youth with a scimitar, here he is bearded and
weaponless. This version of The Book of Fixed Stars, produced in the North African city
of Ceuta, is the only known western Islamic manuscript to mention its place of origin.
An eye on the heavens
The illustrations produced in 1237 by the artist Al-Wasiti for Al-Hariri's classic tales known
as the Maqamat are an outstanding example of medieval Arabic art. (See also pages 6
and 25). These miniatures and their surrounding text, which describes the adventures
of a witty and resourceful figure named Abu Zaid, are today preserved in the Bibliothèque
Nationale, in Paris. Below, a scene with a scientific flavour: Abu Zaid measures the
height of the celestial bodies with an astrolabe.
> disseminating health information. The
Adudi hospital in Baghdad was a striking
example of an institution which performed
such a role. It had 24 doctors on its staff
and was equipped with lecture halls and
an ample library. In the late 10th century,
its fame spread far and wide.
Among Arabic authors who wrote on
ophthalmology and eye diseases, a branch
of medicine that received special attention
in the Muslim world, Hunayn ibn Ishaq
was perhaps the first to write a systematic
manual on ophthalmology, complete with
diagrams. His work was developed by ,
later authors and has survived until today.
In ten treatises written between 840 and
860 and completed by his student and
nephew, Hubaysh, Hunayn discussed the
anatomy of the eye, brain, and optical
nerves, as well as the physiology, diseases,
and treatment of the eye. Although he
copied extensively from Greek works, he
added many new, personal observations.
Al-Razi was possibly the first to describe
pupillary reflexes.
Arabic progress in ophthalmology reach¬
ed a peak around the year 1000 in the
work of Ali ibn Isa, an oculist of Baghdad.
His book A Treasury for Ophthalmologists
was a comprehensive summary of all the
achievements of the past. His contempo¬
rary Ammat ibn Ali Al-Mawsili was the first
to introduce the technique of suction
removal of cataracts. He devised and
used a hollow needle for the purpose, a
technique revived in 1846 by a French
doctor, Blanchet.
This high level of performance was
continued by Ibn al-Haytham (Alhazen)
and in a guide for oculists written by
Muhammad al-Ghafiqi of Andalusia.
Al-Ghafiqi illustrated his manual with
pictures of the surgical instruments he
used in performing eye operations.
The physician-philosopher Ibn Rushd k
once stated that "whosoever becomes fully Y
Stalactite fantasy
in a royal chapel
The royal chapel built in Palermo around
1140 by Roger II, ruler of the Norman
kingdom of Sicily, is famed for its richly
painted wooden ceiling (detail at right)
with "stalactite" vaults arranged in a
honeycomb design. The paintings,
depicting scenes from princely life, were
executed by Muslim artists and constitute
the largest surviving ensemble of Muslim
painting. Specialists believe that they
were probably produced by artists
following Mesopotamian traditions and
influenced by the pictorial art of Fatimid
Egypt (11th century) or of Tunis.
Photo Michel Desjardins © Top Réalités, Paris
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Y: f ¿}
%
^Z îtv l SÉX
è:
ÏCP
.r
P*
.g
\L
/? H
VvC*
>fl
\ * '
I A il^ jj^ja
'2$^jk&-
MSP,., *^n fV
IfV;
^
è£~U&' £S*
¿
'.*. ' le.**
-*M1vx
HÏÏL
È.^7
Al
*
nu* í$¡i
^^^
** 1*1
È
7
^
«à* LH| .-<?*--
¿$
feu
ffi
*V -i^'i- r¿3
¡tfi
tir A
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Anatomy of a thoroughbred
Knowledge of the animal world was highly valued in Islamic civilization, for
animals, along with plants and minerals, were regarded as essential to the
cosmic equilibrium. Animals such as the horse were frequently depicted in
works of art and literature, and were also studied scientifically. This
anatomical study is from a 15th-century Egyptian manuscript now
preserved in the university of Istambul.
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris. University of Istambul Library, Turkey
( familiar with human anatomy and physio¬
logy, his faith in God will increase". This
statement explains why surgery was
accepted by the Arabs from the early days
of Islam (1). It also explains why Muslim
surgeons were among the first to use
narcotic and sedative drugs in operations:
Islam teaches that God has provided man
with a great variety of natural remedies to
cure his ills. It is man's obligation to
identify them and to use them with skill
and compassion.
The greatest achievements in medieval
surgery, however, are attributed to Az-
Zahrawi of Moorish Spain. An important
part of his medical encyclopaedia, The
Book of Concessions, deals with obstetrics,
paediatrics, and midwifery, as well as with
general human anatomy. The surgical
part of the encyclopaedia contains a
discussion of cauterization, the treatment
of wounds, the extracting of arrows, oral
hygiene, and the setting of bones in simple
and compound fractures.
He used antiseptics in the treatment of
wounds and skin injuries; devised sutures
from animal intestines, silk, wool, and
other substances; and developed tech¬
niques to widen urinary passages and ex¬
plore body cavities surgically. His surgery
contained about 200 surgical instruments
that he himself designed and depicted in
his writings. Such instruments, with
modifications, were later used by many
surgeons in Christendom as well as in
Islam.
Donkey-driven
irrigator
Most Arab countries are arid,
and water management has
always been a major concern in
Arab civilization. One problem
faced by Arab engineers was
how to raise water from
streams and canals for irrigation
or domestic use. In his
celebrated Treatise on
Mechanical Devices; the great
13th-century inventor Al-Jazari
described in detail the
construction of an array of
mechanical devices, including
water-raising machines such
as the donkey-powered irrigation
system shown at right. The
donkey turns an upright pole
connected to a series of toothed
wheels. The wheels are linked
to four water scoops (here
submerged), which rise in
succession and empty their
contents into a canal.
(1) Editor's note: in some parts of the Western world,
the dissection of human bodies was prohibited for reli¬
gious reasons.
Herbs for healing
A Book of Antidotes attributed
to the Greek physician Galen
was translated into Arabic and
widely used in medicine. Detail
at right is from an illuminated
manuscript version produced
in 1199, probably in Iraq. It
shows two medicinal herbs
used for treating poisonous
bites. The name of each herb is
annotated in Arabic.
:>'-,1 :KP
New theories of vision
Ophthalmology was a branch of medicine
which received special attention
throughout the Islamic world. Scientists
such as Ali ibn Isa, author of a famous
Arabic Treasury for Ophthalmologists,
added new theories and experience to
the knowledge they inherited from the
Greeks. Left, diagram showing the
interconnection of the optic nerves is from
a treatise on ophthalmology in the
Egyptian National Library, Cairo.
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
, Az-Zahrawi's discussion of mother and
child health and the profession of midwifery
is of particular interest in the history of
nursing. His text imples the existence of
a flourishing profession of nurses and
midwives in general practice, which
explains the reluctance of many conserva¬
tive Muslim families to seek the assistance
of male doctors in normal childbirth. Skilled '
physicians and obstetricians such as Az-
Zahrawi instructed and trained midwives
so that they could carry out their duties
with competence.
Pharmacy, as a recognized profession,
is an Arab-Islamic institution. It became
an independent scienceseparate from,
yet co-operating with medicine, and it
was practised by skilled and trained spe¬
cialists. It achieved this status around the
year 800, under the patronage of the
Abbasid caliphs. The first privately owned
and managed pharmacies were opened in
the early 9th century in Baghdad, the
Abbasid capitl, where drugs and spices
from Asia and Africa were readily available.
Within a short time, pharmacies sprang
up in other large cities of the Islamic
world.
In Arab mechanical technology two main
categories of machines were produced:
firstly those designed for use, such as
mills, water-raising devices, and war
machines; and secondly, devices designed
to cause wonder and aesthetic pleasure
within courtly circles.
The inventors of ingenious devices, or
"automata", such as Ibn al-Razzaz al-
Jazari, also designed useful machines.
They were thoroughly familiar with the
work of carpenters and millwrights, from
whom they derived much of their vocabu¬
lary and many of their techniques, tools
and mechanisms.
The most impressive array of automata
were displayed in Al-Jazari's monumental
clocks. Circles representing the Zodiac,
the sun, and the moon rotated at constant
speed; birds discharged pellets from their
beaks onto cymbals to sound the hour; .
doors opened to reveal small figurines. At
regular intervals musicians such as drunv
mers, trumpeters and tambourine players
performed on their instruments.
These automata were usually actuated
by a float sinking at a constant rate in a
water reservoir. Their mechanism involv¬
ed the use of complex hydraulic systems
which later reappeared in Europe during
the Industrial Revolution, and incorporated
a type of conical valve which was first
mentioned in the West by Leonardo da
Vinci and which came into general use in
Europe during the 16th century. A great
deal of research still remains to be done
before the sources of Leonardo's ideas
can be fully established, but it seems
likely that he had access to some of the
translations from Arabic made in Toledo
in the 12th century.
Arab technology was essentially based
upon the use of the effects of water pres¬
sure and air pressure. Most of the mathe¬
matical relationships that underlie these
physical phenomena had not then been
identified, and so engineers had to draw
upon a large fund of practical experience.
Two types of mill have been known
since classical times, one with a vertical
waterwheel that drives the millstones
through a pair of gear wheels, the other
with a horizontal-vaned water-wheel with
direct drive to the millstones. It has been
computed that the second type could
reach an output of 10 horsepower with an
efficiency of 75 per cent. From the ac¬
counts of geographers and travellers, we
know that both types of mill were widely
used in the Islamic lands for grinding grain
and for industrial purposes.
The five full-scale machines described
by Al-Jazari were all designed to raise
water, and four of them incorporate
features that are of great significance in
the history of machine technology.
There is ample evidence that knowledge
of Arabic science, medicine, mathematics,
and philosophy was transmitted to Europe
in written form, but very little evidence
that engineering ideas were disseminated
in this way. Technological ideas have
frequently been carried from one culture
to another by travellers' reports, by the
observations of commercial agents, and
by direct contacts between craftsmen.
Until modern times, such cross-fertiliza¬
tion was probably more frequent and
more fruitful than written communications.
Arabic culture, including its contributions
to the life sciences, reached its highest
stage of development between the 9th
and the 11th centuries, and experienced
a number of major revivals during the 12th
and 13th centuries. During this period the
West was just beginning to awaken from
the Dark Ages.
From the 12th century to the Renais¬
sance, via translation and copying activities
in Spain, Sicily, and Syria, the bulk of
Arabic writings in all fields was made
available in Latin. Despite the poor quality
of translation and scholarship that prevail¬
ed in the West at that time, these Latin
versions revived the spirit of learning in
Western Europe during the late Middle
Ages.
In the life sciences, Arabic authors not
only preserved the classical achievements
of the ancients but also added new and
original data. to the fund of human know¬
ledge, thereby contributing to the well-
being of all men everywhere.
Salah Galal
THE 3 Rs
IN THE MOSQUE
(Continued from page 34)
course of time the writings produced by
the great early masters became textbooks
for their successors and their students. In
many cases teachers simply read out and
commented on these ancient texts,, a
method which led to the stagnation of
Muslim education for several centuries.
Discussion and questioning were two
other features of education in the mosques.
Students often engaged in heated debate
with their teachers and professed opinions
which were at odds with theirs. At the
same time they remained highly respectful
of their teachers' views. An art of dial¬
ogue and discussion regulated by clearly
defined rules thus developed in Muslim
academic life.
In the early days of Islam, Muslim
scholars travelled far and wide to collect
hadiths which certain elders had committ¬
ed to memory, but which had never been
written down. Later scholars journeyed in
search of unusual Arabic expressions and
syntax, and eventually the practice of
travelling "in search of knowledge" expand¬
ed to include all other fields of academic
life.
"All knowledge is ultimately religious
and is acquired in God's name". This prin¬
ciple underlies the transmission and acqui¬
sition of knowledge in the Muslim world.
Any secular calling must be placed in a
.divine setting, and in the last analysis the
purpose of education is to serve God.
Hisham Nashabi
A major contribution to scientific progress
The Arabs were not only responsible for major innovations in science and tech¬
nology. Through their translations of Greek and other scientific works of Antiquity
they also ensured the transmission of knowledge that contributed to the sub¬
sequent flowering of Western science.
Arab scholars played a key role in the development of such scientific disciplines
as astronomy and mathematics, as well as medicine, natural history, geography
and agronomy. One outstanding example is the 9th-century mathematician Al-
Khawarizmi, the creator of algebra (from the Arabic "al-jabp, who also gave his
name to the word "algorithm", today used in arithmetic. This great scholar,
who has been called "one of the greatest mathematicians of all times", also
elaborated a method of finding square roots and made important advances in
trigonometry.
The development of Arab scientific thought and its impact on medieval Europe
and world scientific progress have been discussed in several articles in the Unesco
Courier (especially the June 1974 issue). More recently, Unesco's international
scientific quarterly Impact of Science on Society also devoted a special issue to
"Science and the Islamic World" (May-September 1976).
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to
the editor
IMAGES OF AFRICA
Sir,
. Congratulations on your issue "The
Changing Face of Africa" (May 1977). Ola
Balogun's article on the significance of
African sculpture gives a clear exposition of
ideas which a European mind often finds
difficult to grasp.
However, I should like to make a few
comments on the illustrations and photo
captions. Firstly, the mask from Gabon
shown at the bottom of page 16 is probably
Pounou and not Fang, as indicated in the
caption, even though it may have come
from Fang country.
As for the Dan mask from Liberia shown
on page 16, to my mind it is not a "master¬
piece" worthy of inclusion in the 4 pages
you devote to illustrations of African masks.
The Dan have produced thousands of more
notable masks.
Finally, many different interpretations can
be given to the tiny ornamental "proverb
weights" shown on pages 24 and 25. For
example, the two crocodiles with the same
stomach suggest that even though a family
has several mouths, it feeds a common
stomach. The moral is that people should
subordinate their personal interests to those
of the group.
A.J. Safaris
St. Maur-des-Fossées
France
Sir,
Your issue on African culture (May 1977)
was fascinating. African art is a source of
constant enrichment and has a timeless
quality, like the art of Assur, Sumer, Oceania
and pre-Columbian America.
As far as the cinema is concerned,
however, it cannot be said that foreign
film companies use Africa as a place to get
rid of their duds. According to friends of
mine who live in Upper Volta good-quality
and relatively new (not more than a year
old) films are shown there.
Claude Lambert
Epinal
France
Sir,
As a teacher, ethno-historical researcher
and music columnist, I should like to con¬
gratulate you on your issue "The Changing
Face of Africa". It is a pity that the Unesco
Courier is not better known among South
African educationists and writers.
I hope one day that your magazine will be
printed in our language, Tsonga, which is
spoken in South Africa, Rhodesia and
Mozambique.
Risimati Mudunwazi Mathonsi
Ga-Rankuwa
South Africa
IN PRAISE OF RUBENS
Sir,
I should like to offer my sincere congratu¬
lations on the July 1977 issue of the Unesco
Courier, devoted to the 400th anniversary of
Rubens' birth and to the life and work of Spi¬
noza and Leewenhoek.
The quality of the articles and the visual
presentation, both in colour and black and
white, make this issue of the Unesco Courier
one of the best ever.
Alberto Wagner de Reyna
Ambassador of Peru to Unesco
Member of Unesco's Executive Board
Sir,
I congratulate you most warmly on the
issue of the Unesco Courier devoted to
Rubens. It really is a very interesting piece
of work and I would welcome another issue
of the same kind.
I am glad to take this opportunity to say
how much I appreciate the quality and
variety of the articles you publish.
J. Baugratz
Paris
ARISTOTLE UNDER FIRE
Sir,
I should like to take issue with Constantine
Despotopoulos's article on Aristotle in your
October 1977 issue. It is a great mistake to
praise so debatable a personality in a maga¬
zine read by young people. The great
English philosopher and statesman Francis
Bacon (1561-1626) roundly condemned
Aristotle, and so did Bertrand Russell, who
wrote that Aristotle's intellectual influence
made him "one of mankind's greatest
scourges."
Marx's reference to Aristotle as "the
greatest thinker of Antiquity" is superficial.
Aristotle was quite incapable of imagination
or prediction for he was completely prejudic¬
ed by the ideas of his time.
The following quotation from Aristotle's
Politics illustrates my point: "If the shuttle
could weave cloth all by itself, if a bow all
alone could bring forth the desired sounds
out of a cythar, then architects would no
longer need workers, nor masters slaves."
By this, Aristotle meant to show that such
possibilities were absurd. However, machi¬
nes had existed since the time of the
Pharaohs, although Aristptle did not seem
very familiar with this subject. He proved
himself to be an enemy of progress and a
supporter of slavery.
Jean Pilisi
Issy-les-Moulineaux
France
SPINOZA AND JUDAISM
Sir,
The article on the philosopher Benedict
de Spinoza in your May 1977 issue made
very interesting reading.
Our members celebrated the three hun¬
dredth anniversary of Spinoza's death, and
in Paris we held a ceremony of commemo¬
ration devoted to this great man, to his
universal thought and to his relations with
Judaism. Men of different creeds, as well
as atheists, put forward various views about
Spinoza, but none of their conclusions tallied
with those which the author of your article
seems to reach.
Spinoza was excluded from the synago¬
gue, but he never broke with Judaism and
in spite of powerful pressures and subtle
attempts to convert him, he never joined a
Christian church. He remained a student
of Hebrew, a Judaic scholar and the author
of the first Hebrew grammar. Many letters
reveal his courage and adroitness in answer¬
ing points made by his non-Jewish friends.
To avoid dependence on the church, he
turned down a chair at the university of
Heidelberg which was, like most univer¬
sities at that time, dominated by the clergy.
Finally, certain passages in your article
seem to me to attach too much importance
to the place of money in the Jewish commu¬
nity.
Spinoza's ideas have been criticized by
philosophers from many viewpoints, but the
opposition of certain Jewish thinkers to the
concepts he formulated are above all philo¬
sophical or theological. In the eyes of most
Jews, his condemnation was unjust and
would have been unthinkable a century
later. The most important thing is that his
philosophical system marked the starting
point for many developments in modern
religious, political, ethical and scientific
thought. S. Hoffenberg
Permanent Delegate to Unesco
B'nai Brith International Council
THE GERMANS
IN LATIN AMERICA
Sir, '
I greatly enjoy the Unesco Courier, and
especially liked the recent issues on Rubens
and the Acropolis. However, in your fasci¬
nating issue on Latin America (August-
September 1977), an important matter was
left out: the contribution of the Germanic
peoples (the Swiss, Alsatians, Austrians,
Bavarians, and peoples from the Rhine,
Hamburg, Berlin, and so forth) to Latin
America.
Though Germans emigrated in greater
numbers to North America, German geo¬
graphers and astronomers often served in
Portuguese and Spanish ships in the 16th
century. The King of Spain offered land to
German settlers, which they called Vene¬
zuela, or "Little Venice", even though they
came from Bremen and Hamburg.
In the 19th century, hundreds of thousands
of emigrants from Germanic countries
settled in southern Brazil, Argentina and
Chile. In southern Brazil, there are towns
with such names as Hamburgo, Germania,
and Oberlandia.
Today there are some 5 million South
Americans of Germanic origin. They have
played, and continue to play a leading role
in architecture, medicine, industry, the
economy and politics.
J.-L. Fronville
Hangest-en-Santerre
France
TOWARDS WORLD SOLIDARITY
Sir,
I have been an enthusiastic Courier reader
since I was at secondary school 10 years
ago. I particularly enjoy your articles on
history and archaeology, as well as those
on science, geophysics and ethnography.
For me, the magazine is a continuing source
of enrichment and awareness of world
problems, as well as a means of creating
solidarity and unity among peoples.
Mme. Thirion-Chiroux
Savigny-sur-Orge
France
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
121 (P
UD \SM m sa
Libya gives $1 1/4 million
to General History of Africa
Libya has agreed to contribute $1,220,000 to
Unesco's project for a general history of Africa.
The contribution will ensure publication of the
eight-volume work in Arabic, French, English
and several African languages.
Bookshelf on Arab
Islamic civilization
UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
Islam: the Perenniality of Values:
theme of Unesco's international
quarterly Cultures (Vol. IV, No. 1,
1977) 22 Francs.
Cultural Policy in Tunisia, by Rafik
Said. 1970, 56 pp. (8 F); Cultural
Policy in Egypt, by Magdi Wahba.
1972. 95 pp. (8 F). Both published
in Unesco's "Studies and Documents
on Cultural Policies" series.
Islam and the Race Question, by
Abd-al-Aziz Abd-al-Qadir Kamil.
1970. 65 pp. (6F).
Education in the Arab region view¬
ed from the 1970 Marrakesh
Conference, by Mohammed A. El-
Ghannam. 1971. 57 pp. (6 F).
National Science and Technology
Policies in the Arab States, present
situation and future outlook. 1976.
214 pp. (20 F).
SEE ALSO BOX PAGE 20
OTHER BOOKS
The World of Islam: Faith, People,
Culture, edited by Bernard Lewis.
Thames and Hudson, London. 1976.
360 pp. (£12.50).
The Arabs in History, by Bernard
Lewis. Hutchinson, London. 1966.
(£2.50).
Art of Islam: Language and Mean¬
ing, by Titus Burckhardt. 1976.
204 pp. (£12.50); Islamic Science:
an Illustrated Study, by Seyyed
Hossein Nasr. 1976. 273 pp.
(£12.50). Both published by the
World of Islam Festival Publishing
Company Ltd. and distributed by
Thorsons Publishers Ltd., Welling¬
borough, Northants. U.K.
Early Islam, by Desmond Stewart
and the editiors of Time-Life Books,
Time Inc., New York. 1967 (2nd
impression 1970). 192 pp.
The Genius of Arab Civilization:
Source of Renaissance, edited by
John R. Hayes. Phaidon Press,
Iver, Bucks., U.K. 1976 (£15).
PHILIPPE OUANNES
Shortly before this issue went to
press, on the morning of 23 Novem¬
ber, we learned of the sudden death
of our friend and colleague Philippe
Ouannès, editor of the French edi¬
tion of the Unesco Courier. He was
38 years old. He had spent the
previous day in our midst, putting
the finishing touches to this issue
on Arab culture, his own special
field (he had taught Islamic literature
at the University of Paris). Philippe
Ouannès contributed more than
anyone else on our editorial staff to
the conception of this issue. It is
thus a last tribute to his ability,
courage and generosity, as well as
a reminder of all that the Unesco
Courier owes to him and loses with
his death.
Arab states
adopt declaration
on education
and development
Ministers of Education and Ministers of Econo¬
mic Planning from the Acab states met in Abu
Dhabi (United Arab Emirates) between 7 and
14 November 1977 for a conference on educa¬
tional policies in the Arab world. Addressing
the conference, organized by Unesco in col¬
laboration with ALECSO (the Arab League
Educational, Cultural and Scientific Organiza¬
tion), Unesco's Director-General, Mr. Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, stressed that the Arab states
faced the challenge of moving from a traditional
to a modern society, while mastering their
technological development and the process of
urbanization. At the end of the Conference,
delegates unanimously adopted a declaration
reflecting their determination to accelerate the
process of development guided both by the
achievements of modern science and technology
and by their traditional values, which are the
vehicles of progress. The Declaration, which
shows that the Arab states have opted for the
democratization of education, also calls for a
strengthening of regional co-operation and
solidarity to benefit the region's financially less
privileged countries.
Atoms
for peace
On 18 November
1977, the U.N.
Postal Administra¬
tion issued a set
of commemora¬
tive stamps on the
theme "Peaceful
Uses of Atomic
Energy". As a .
member of the
U.N. system, the International Atomic Energy
Agency (IAEA), founded in Vienna in 1957,
"seeks to enlarge the contribution of atomic
energy to peace and health throughout the
world". For further information about this stamp
issue, please write to U.N. Postal
Administration, Palais des Nations, CH-1211
Geneva 10, Switzerland.
Sorbonne honours
Unesco's Director-General
The Sorbonne (University of Paris) bestowed
an honorary doctorate on the Director-General
of Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, on
18 November 1977. In an address given during
the ceremony, Mr. M'Bow stressed that one of
the university's most important missions today
is its commitment to the service of the national
and international community united in its aspira¬
tion for a new world order based on solidarity.
Milestone in
environmental education
At the first-ever Intergovernmental Conference
on Environmental Education, held in Tbilisi
(U.S.S.R.) from 4 to 26 October 1977, delegates
from 60 nations adopted a declaration defining
how education can help cope with environmental
problems at national and international levels.
The conference organized by Unesco and the
U.N. Environment Programme (UNEP) recom¬
mended that environmental education should
be part of teaching programmes at all levels.
Specialists in environmental teaching should
be trained and efforts should be made to
educate professional groups whose activities
affect the environment.
U.N. Development Forum
launches business edition
Development Forum, the United Nations monthly
publication on world economic and social
affairs, will launch a new fortnightly Business
Edition in January 1978. Undertaken on a
co-operative basis by the World Bank, the U.N.
Development Programme (UNDP) and the U.N.
Centre for Economic and Social Information,
which has published Development Forum's
general edition for the last five years, the new
edition will provide comprehensive information
on the goods and services required for develop¬
ment projects, thereby stimulating more com¬
petitive marketing. According to U.N. Secretary-
General Kurt Waldheim, the new edition will
help to "better acquaint the business world
with the broad conceptual framework on which
United Nations development policies are bas¬
ed." The subscription rate in the introductory
offer is $150. For further information, please
write for a prospectus to Development Forum,
Subscriptions Department, United Nations,
CH 1211 Geneva 10, Switzerland.
African arts on film
The 2nd World Black and African Festival of
Arts and Culture ("Festac '77") has been record¬
ed in a half-hour colour 16 mm film made by
Nigerian television and Unesco. The film,
written and directed by Philip Gaunt, features
music, dancing, drama and exhibitions at the
festival held in Lagos in January and February
1977. For further information please apply to
Press and Audiovisual Information Division,
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Flashes...
Each year 6 million tons of petroleum are
dumped into the world's oceans, according to
experts of the U.N. Environment Programme
(UNEP).
Mr. Michel Debeauvais of France has been
appointed director of Unesco's Paris-based
International Institute of Educational Planning.
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Index 1977
January
WHO OWNS THE OCEANS? (M.E. Gonçalves). The law of the sea (M. Ruivo).
Unesco and the Oceans. New wave in oceanography (D. Behrman). Last of
Leviathan (Photos). Hidden dynamos of Neptune's powerhouse (K.N. Fedorov).
Marine pollution (D. Behrman). Test tubes in the sea (T.R. Parsons). Expedition
FAMOUS (X. le Pichón). Art treasures: Mayan dignitary (Honduras).
February
EBLA:. Syrian metropolis of 4,000 years ago. (P. Matthiae). The Acropolis in danger
(A.M. M'Bow). Churches of Lake Tana (B. Abbebe). Henna for happiness (J. Saksena).
After literacy, what next? (S. Malya). Bolivar and the Congress of Panama (A. Uslar-
Pietri). Art treasures: Mask with half-moon eyes (Zaire).
March
UNESCO AND THE WORLD AHEAD. Unesco's Medium-Term Plan. Signposts
for 1982 (A.M. M'Bow). Birthright of Man. In search of a lasting peace. Science,
technology, man and society. Manthe centre of development. Education. An
equal chance for everyone. Man and the environment. Communication more than
a one-way street. Books for all. Art treasures: Blue idol (New Hebrides).
April
WORLD DEBATE ON INFORMATION. Unesco and communication (M. Makagiansar).
Unesco and news agency development. Caribbean news agency (H.N.J. Cholmondeley).
Cross-cultural communication (J.A. Willings). TV's one-way traffic (H. Topuz). Non-
aligned countries' news pool (P. Ivacic). A voice from the Third World (R. Najar). The
mass media and society: (1) A Soviet viewpoint (Y.N. Zasursky and Y.I. Kashlev);
(2) An American viewpoint (W.G. Harley). The 'Symphonie' experiment (E. LI.
Sommerlad). Art treasures: Rice-spoon fit for a queen (Ivory Coast).
May
THE CHANGING FACE OF AFRICA. Africa rediscovers its cultural roots. African
sculpture (0. Balogun). Masks from 20 countries (Photos). Art that explains the
universe (P. Ahyi). Africa's proverbial wit and wisdom (T. Aka etc.). A song for every
season (S. Mbabi-Katana). New African theatre (D. Nwoko). Awakening African
cinema (F. Bebey). Art treasures: Twin with open eyes (Canada).
June
RUBENS. 400th anniversary (M. Makagiansar). Portrait of the artist (R. Avermaete).
Mansion for a master; Vive la femme! (Photos). Stamps. Colour pages. Rubens the
diplomat (F. Baudouin). Spinoza (B. Rekers). Van Leeuwenhoek (J.W.M. La
Rivière). Art treasures: Childhood radiance (Belgium).
July
A HALT TO DESERT ADVANCE. Are deserts man-made? (M.- El-Kassas). The
climate as accomplice (F.K. Hare). A precarious balance upset (V.A. Kovda). Sands
of wrath (H.E. Dregne). Battle against destruction (A.G. Babaev and N.S. Orlovsky).
Onslaught on the Nile (F. El-Baz). Study in survival (C. Grenot and R. Vernet). The
poor man's energy crisis (E.P. Eckholm). Great green walls of China. Art treasures:
Winged ram (Spain).
August-September
LATIN AMERICA. (L. Zea). The blacks in Latin America (A. Carpentier). The Afro-
Brazilian experiment (G. Freyre). Where gods and men have mingled (J. Amado). A
matter of life and death (O. Paz). The Passion according to the Yaquis; Fiesta of death
(Photos). Avant-garde art (A. Uslar-Pietri). Colour pages. The Andes (P. Macera).
Communities in crisis (J.E. Adoum). Paraguay (A.R. Bastos). The 'Black Legend'
(R.F. Retamar). Extravaganza of baroque (Photos). The tango (CF. Moreno).
Spanish overseas (M.A. Morinigo). Victoria Ocampo (J. Rigaud). Unesco and Latin
America. Art treasures: The man in the bird's beak (El Salvador).
October
THE ACROPOLIS IN PERIL. (C. Bouras). Caryatids in need of care (Photos). The
Acropolis in Antiquity (J. Travlos). The Parthenon (Photos). Athenian democracy's
grand design (M. Andronicos). Citadel in praise of peace (A. Diamantopoulos).
Pericles and Plutarch. Acropolomania (Photos). Village life among the ruins (J.
Lacarrière). Aristotle (C. Despotopoulos). Art treasures: Athena (Italy).
November
RACISM IN SOUTHERN AFRICA. Apartheid (A.M. M'Bow). U.N. campaign
against apartheid (E.S. Reddy). South Africa: facts and fiction (L. Rubin). South
Africa's captive work-force. Namibia moves to independence (S. MacBride). Nami¬
bians train for tomorrow (H.G. Geingob). From Rhodesia to Zimbabwe (M. O'Callaghan).
Apartheid in sport (S.A. Ogouki). Unesco and apartheid. 30-year-struggle for human
rights (K. Vasak). Text of Universal Declaration of Human Rights. Art treasures:
Prehistoric bison (France).
December
A GOLDEN AGE OF ARAB CULTURE. (A. Sinaceur). Brotherhoods of the bazaars
(Y. Ibish). The Arab Mind (M. Arkoun). Music (B. Moussali). Colour pages. Education
(H. Nashabi). The Madrasah (B. Arodaky). Al-Azhar university (T. Hussein). Calli¬
graphy and architecture (M. El-Habib). Science (S. Galal). Art treasures: The man from
Derah'il (People's Dem. Rep. of Yemen).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division, Campbell House, 100
Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000. - AUSTRIA. Dr.
Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandlung, Industrie¬
hof Stadian, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220 Wien. - BEL¬
GIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Handel-
maatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 1 12, rue du Trône, Brussels 5, CCP 000-
0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552 Mer¬
chant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Qué H3H 1M7.
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spa-
lena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahrancni literatura, 11
Soukenicka, Prague L.For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag Publis¬
hers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR. DEN¬
MARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165,
Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OP). National
Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb Street, Tahrir
Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa, Keskukatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. FRANCE. Librai¬
rie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, C.C.P.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22,
C.C.P. Hamburg 276650. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER
D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH Karger Buchhandlung. Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/München. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications 4
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Vâci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjöm Jonsson Et Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Cal¬
cutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali
Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-
560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book Et Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016;
Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of
Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publis¬
hing and Distribution Co., 139 Shah Reza Ave., opposite to Uni¬
versity of Teheran, P.O. Box 14/1480, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. Mckenzie's Bookshop, Al-Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formely Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachtat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling. Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. MAURI¬
TIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
- NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition
only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V. Marti-
nus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. - NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.), N.V.,
Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O.
Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christ-
church; Alma street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street,
P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Welling¬
ton. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The Univer¬
sity Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Book-shop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturje-
neste. Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65
Sharah Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIP¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632,
Manila D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury ¡
Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.
7.00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias Er Andrade Ltda,
Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications ISI Pte Ltd., No. 1 New
Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schalk's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. - SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales
IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata
P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.
Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications: A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030
Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaegi Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402,
Bangkok:Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
- TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Sta¬
tion, New York, N.Y. 10016. For "Unesco Courier" in Spanish:
Santillana Publishing Company, Inc., 575 Lexington Avenue,
New York, N.Y. 10022. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenije, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
The city
of the Prophet
r**v
After preaching for 13 years in Mecca, Muhammad settled in Yathrib,
a town some 500 km away, where he remained until his death. Yathrib
became known as Madinat al-Nabi or "City of the Prophet", or simply Medina
(Al-Madinah) the city. This 17th-century Mamluk tile from Egypt shows a
schematic view of the Holy Places of Medina, notably the dwelling of
Muhammad, on which later Arab mosques were modelled.
t
H
» _
griii
áMÉtfMÉ
i,émt^irftum\mttÈûtâàtatfà
U-i. A.ijr, >'" ., -.,',-*lx:-:jl'í Î <l
;
aEssr
Photo © Werner Forman, U.K.
Museum of Islamic Art, Cairo
]]>
</page>
</document>
