<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078152eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
HC,5L. t, l°ï- fr
^- * WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
Courier
MAY
1956
(9th year)
Price : 9d. (U. K.)
40 francs (France)
Special Report
PRESS, FILM,
TELEVISION,
RADIO TODAY
The Educated
Man in 1984
London's
own language
*
'Waste paper'
finds reveal
life in Egypt
2,000 years ago
HEAR YE TV !
HEAR YE TV !
(See p. 4)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
jpv^fc» '*
' Private
papyri
from t h
lives' on
emerge
e sands
Fascinating facts about the lives of Greeks and Romans who lived in Egypt some 2,000 years
ago have been pieced together from thousands of fragments of papyri found buried in the
sands since the sites of ancient cities began to be exploited about a century ago for the
"fertile earth" (potash salts) they had accumulated. Their subject matter ranged from
shopping and laundry lists to literature, drama, and public affairs. Some of the richest finds
have been made under the ruins of Oxyrhynchus (above). Fragments shown below are from
a commentary on the works of the Greek lyric poet Alcaeus, c.6l 1-580 B.C. (See page 26)
British Museum
»jur-r ~~orr-<
y * . -J
riM&Si .T*^"' -»v-, fer
iâriJTT-
***** *&*M xt ^¡f
_^N Irr,'
r*j
¡
1
ff '3SES " JÄ* £/:|
i
/ I V
fÍAíC :
4* Kr A \l "*g# * '^¥! At
ff$*£gf B
si^-'V . ",1«'*
HA ^i'
-
S'fftfÖ
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Â WINDOW OHM ON THt WOâlO
ner
N°5
9th
MAY 1956
YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 WHAT'S WRONG ON FRENCH FARMS?
A unique TV experiment puts the question
7 TV LIKES AND DISLIKES
9 'STATE OF EMERGENCY'
In France's farming community
14 TV: GIANT IN SEVEN LEAGUE BOOTS
16 DAILY PRESS RUN: 255 MILLION COPIES
18 HALF THE WORLD
Lacks modern means of communication
20 BRITISH ARE MOST AVID CINEMA GOERS
22 THE EDUCATED MAN IN 1984
By Dr. J. Bronowski
24 UNESCO IN PICTURES
From Turkey to Ecuador
26 DESERT «WASTE PAPER BASKETS'
Reveal city life in Egypt 2,000 years ago
By Prof. E. G. Turner
29 LONDON'S OWN LANGUAGE
The growth of Cockney rhyming slang
By David Gunston
30 YUGOSLAV ART MASTERPIECES
In the palm of your hand
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9, Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual arcicles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 8/-; $2.50 or 400
French frs or equivalent.
(MC. 56.1.102 A)
The Unesco Courier
COVER PHOTO
"Television show at the village hall
tonight", cries this French village con¬
stable whose duties include making all
public announcements. (Letters "G.C."
on his kepi stand for Garde Champêtre).
See next page for the story of an impor¬
tant Unesco TV programme experiment
which was carried out in rural France.
T
I his issue presents the major findings of a series of surveys
I just completed by Unesco of the four great channels of
JL communication press, radio, films and television which
bring to us the news and information of events occurring every¬
where on the globe. The surveys show the phenomenal strides
made in the course of the past five years in all of these media,
and particularly in radio and television. But they also reveal that
millions of people in vast segments of the world still have little or
no modern means of communication.
Unesco is permanently committed to "promote the free flow of
information by word and image", and it has taken action to help
the less favoured nations of the world in developing their commu¬
nication services and thereby reduce the great gaps that separate
them from the more favoured countries.
But there is another important problem that goes hand-in-hand
with the rapid expansion of press, radio and television. It is the
growing need for more trained journalists. The opinions that
people have, the decisions they arrive at, are based not only on the
amount of information they get but also on its quality on how
accurately and completely the facts and events are made known to
them. Because the press (the word is here used to include all the
information media) is one of the most potent instruments for
influencing the minds of men towards peace or war, the compe¬
tence and sense of responsibility of those who write the news today,
of those who select it and present it to the public, are matters of
vital importance to everyone.
In all important countries today journalism is accorded a high
status among the professions, and it is now generally recognized
that for a journalist to be worthy of his calling he should be pro¬
fessional in the full sense of the word: professional in his training,
and professional in his ethics and in his social responsibility.
In April of this year, Unesco convened the first international
gathering devoted exclusively to journalism education. The
editors, broadcasters, newsreelmen and journalism school directors
who attended from 23 countries stressed that each country must
have full freedom to establish its own system of training, since
systems differ so widely. In the Americas, schools of journalism
in universities play an important role; in Britain there is on-the-job
training under the National Council for the Training of Journalists;
in other countries there are other methods. But, the experts'
meeting agreed, whatever the system chosen as best suited to local
circumstances, it should include both technical training in the craft
and general education so that the journalist has the necessary
background for accurate interpretation of news and events around
the world.
This conference also emphasized the need for regional and inter¬
national centres which would train journalism teachers, organize
refresher or "booster" courses for active journalists, undertake
special research into mass communication problems in their parti¬
cular areas, and suggest ways to improve present teaching methods.
A plan for action on a broad international scale was elaborated
which calls for the exchange of journalism teachers and journalists
between different countries, special attention to the needs of
technically under-developed countries, more emphasis in courses on
the culture and history of other peoples, and more foreign language
teaching. Unesco has been asked to pioneer the production of
prototype textbooks for prospective journalists and to increase its
aid to governments wishing to set up or develop their training
facilities for press, radio, film and TV staff. It is hoped that as a
result of the attention now drawn to the problem, and with the
co-operation of all the information media and the universities,
training for journalism will be extended and improved with result¬
ing benefits to those who gather, present and interpret the news,
and the general public they serve.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A unique TV experiment puts the question :
WHAT'S WRONG ON
FRENCH FARMS?
UNESCO-Cassirer
LIFE ON THE LAND was described most convincingly when the farmers themselves spoke from the
TV screen. This farmer advocated mechanization, described advantages of planting several crops.
A unique experiment carried out in
France through the co-operation of
Unesco, French Television and rural
tele-clubs has shown conclusively how
television can now be used to develop
popular culture and adult education cam¬
paigns on a vast scale.
It took the form of a series of 13 TV
programmes dealing with one of France's
most serious national problems the mo¬
dernization of agriculture and the raising
of rural living standards from which it
took its title: "State of Emergency".
Through the rural tele-clubs groups
which meet for collective TV viewing in
many villages it spoke directly to the
country people of their own problems
the drift to the towns, modernization diffi¬
culties of small farmers, land re-allocation
and lack of community enterprise and the
people who did the talking were the small
farmers, wine-growers and labourers them¬
selves, turned actors for a day.
Opinion polls and surveys showed that
its results were striking and positive. It
encouraged one local council to go ahead
with long-delayed community projects,
people pooled resources to buy equipment
for community use, parents decided to
send their children to agricultural and
domestic science schools (1). Thus it will
suggest ideas for similar projects to TV
producers and educators in countries where
TV is a growing force, infusing new blood
into TV and bringing new vitality to adult
education. On the following pages, the
Unesco Courier tells the story of "State of
Emergency" and how it changed the atti¬
tudes of many French farmers towards
problems of rural modernization.
(I) Full results of the study are published by
Unesco in " Television and Rural Adult Educa¬
tion", by J. Dumazedier, price $ 3.50; 2I\-;
1,000 francs.
TELE-CLUB TERRITORY covered by the Unesco experiment was in the rectangle shown on
this map, to the north east of Paris. It includes celebrated Champagne wine-producing region.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Some 60 miles to the north east of Paris lies the De¬
partment of the Aisne, a largely agricultural region
of woods, plateaux and valleys, whose fields of sugar
beet, potatoes and vines give it a prosperous air. Yet
most of the people live in conditions of extreme
discomfort.
In the villages around Chateau Thierry, the most
southerly county town, for example, 65% of the people
have no running water and 95% have no communal
draining system. (Of 21 1/2 million living in France's
rural areas nearly half the population only 9 million
have running water.) One rural housewife out of two has
a primitive wash-house with no real shelter. Seventy
percent of villages have no communal hall and 65% are
without a sports ground.
The houses look quaint. But, as J. Dumazedier points
out in the Unesco study, "Television and Rural Adult
Education," most of them are more than a century old,
and less than half have been renovated since they were
built. The women fetch their water from the public foun¬
tain or horse trough.
More than half the
people have no water
laid on at all. "A tap
above the sink?" That
is just a dream. One
house in five has an
electric cooker, one
person in two uses bu¬
tane gas for cooking
and central heating is
a luxury beyond the
reach of 90% of the
people. Nine out of ten
people have a radio but
less than two have
main drainage in their
homes or a washing
machine of their own.
Most of the small
farmers have all-metal
wheel ploughs, but
only 12% have tractors.
These are conditions
one might expect to
find in isolated De¬
partments of France
rather than 60 miles
from the French
capital. Yet the people
of these Aisne villages
have access to one of
the most modern of
inventions television
through the tele-
clubs which have
sprung up in many
places. .
A few years ago
television was just as remote from the everyday life of
these villages as an atomic pile or an electronic calculating
machine. What they did have were rural film clubs set
up after the war for educational purposes. By 1950 with
. rising costs, these were running into difficulties.
It was then that the treasurer of one of the clubs,
writing up his annual report, concluded with this wry
remark: "If we are to survive we shall have to give up the
cinema and turn to television." It was as though he had
said: "As we have no money left to buy bread, let's buy
cake instead."
Roger Louis, organizer of a group of cinema clubs took
the joke seriously. He began to investigate the technical
difficulties of turning from film shows to collective view¬
ing of television: Could telecasts be received in the Aisne?
Were there sets with screens large enough for 30 to 40
people to watch at a time? Would the images be clear
enough to be seen from the back of a large room? How
much did sets cost? Some of the answers he got were
discouraging. Just the same he went to Paris to have a
look at a television programme, and came back full of
enthusiasm.
His enthusiasm was contagious and soon a plan was
worked out for the collective purchase of sets, the
subscribers to be reimbursed from fees charged for ad¬
mission to the broadcasts. A manufacturer of TV sets
agreed to loan two sets for try-outs in two villages though
he was sure the experiment would not work.
FRIENDLY ATMOSPHERE of the
village people. Together they look out
screenand also begin to see local life
has done much to offset the loneliness
The first tests made in the villages of Nogental and
Etampes were highly successful. Luck was with the em¬
bryo tele-clubs. Reception turned out to be good con¬
founding the forecasts of experts and the village people
liked what they saw.
A friendly rivalry sprang up between Nogental and
Etampes to see which would be the first to raise the cost of
a receiver and thus launch its tele-club. Out of wood and
cardboard Nogental built a thermometer and Etampes a
clock dial marked out in thousands of francs. Each day
the villagers watched the totals mounting. In a week
sufficient money had been subscribed.
The movement spread rapidly. By the beginning of
1952, 43 clubs had been formed and were giving regular
programmes, while 43 receivers provided by the manu¬
facturer on "permanent loan" were used to help open new
clubs. In 1954, some 180 tele-clubs in about ten De¬
partments were giving regular programmes.
The telecasts attract audiences from every class of the
community. Creating
links between groups
with conflicting inter¬
ests is not always easy,
but at least people
from every group come,
whereas in the ' old-
established village as-
sociations, such as the
firemen's society or the
municipal band, social
taboos are much more
in evidence.
The tele-club is a
form of recreation
which is finding a
natural place in village
li'fe. It is not reserved
for any particular
social circle, nor is its
membership largely
confined to a handful
of T.V. fanatics. It
attracts a widely varied
audience, each member
fitting the club activi¬
ties into his personal
programme of recre¬
ation.
While some people
come only at very
irregular intervals to
celebrate some event of
personal, family or
general interest others
make the club their
favourite spare-time
haunt. Some come
regularly to a parti¬
cular programme, some make it the occasion for an
"evening out" and others use it to meet their friends or to
join in group activities. As a social Institution, therefore,
the tele-club is rich in possibilities and easily adaptable to
the varying needs of a small village.
The cinema and the theatre, it has been said, owe much
of their success to their well-padded seats and their
attractive decorations. The tele-clubs' appeal cannot be
explained in the same way. Most are housed in school
class-rooms, often half a century or more old, which are
neither comfortable nor beautiful. Furthermore, the old
school buildings were certainly not planned with a view
to radio or television reception. Acoustics are often bad,
and as all the seats are on the same level, the view from
the back rows of a packed house leaves much to be desired.
Despite these shortcomings, the audience squeezes on to
the cramped old benches which pinch their knees, usually
bunching into groups here a flock of children, there a
cluster of old ladies, several local wine-growers or young
men about to leave for their military service, exchanging
banter with the girls. They all have their favourite seats.
All talk, laugh, stamp their feet or let out catcalls, and
even during the telecast there is never complete silence,
except at particularly tense moments. Most of the time
the programme is accompanied by noisy
comment, whispering, exclamations, stifled
squeals and children's laughter. In other (Cont'd on
words, everyone feels at home. next page)
Copyright Bcizeaux
tele-clubs attracts diverse classes of
on different horizons through the TV
in new perspective. Group viewing
that often afflicts country people.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
TV TEST TUBE
(Cont'd)
Tele-club activities have
highlighted the social func¬
tions of the village school¬
master and especially his
role as a leader and organiz¬
er in rural communities.
Despite their uncomfortable
premises and the meagre
grants these teachers manage
by a display of competence,
energy and self-sacrifice, to
continue their educational
work outside school hours. Among young people and
adults they wage a struggle against the ignorance and
prejudice that impede individual development and hold
the villages back.
Educator and village leader, the schoolmaster has to be
something of a psychologist when it comes to choosing the
days and the hours of tele-club meetings. Amusement
and recreation must take second place to the long hours
and hard work of farming life. The Unesco inquiry show¬
ed how difficult it is to please everyone in the matter of
fixing evenings for collective viewing.
Some favour Saturday evening because they can bring
the children who have no school next day. The same
applies to Wednesday (in France primary schools are clos¬
ed on Thursdays). Some people find every day difficult
because, as they point out, "We have to get up every
morning at 6 a.m. to milk the cows."
But while they may differ on this question, most villag¬
ers are agreed that despite some present technical
shortcomings, the potentialities of TV are boundless,
compared with the cinema and other means hitherto
available for widening the horizon of village daily life.
After four years' experience, the village televiewers are
able to weigh the cultural and financial advantages of
group television against the technical advantages of the
cinema (most tele-clubs were previously film clubs). They
see their club as an information centre, a window on the
outside world, a source of knowledge on all kinds of prac¬
tical subjects, a theatre, concert hall or cinema.
How do the club members feel about the future of
collective viewing ? Do they regard it as something likely
to be replaced by T.V. in the home? They were asked:
"Would you like to have a TV set in your own home one
day?" Sixty-eight percent replied "Yes" and 34% said
"No." Most of the negative replies came from small
farmers burdened with work. Those who wanted a set at
home said: "It's a home entertainment which you can
switch on or off as you please." "It's a home variety
show," or "It's like having one's own cinema."
Asked, "If you found yourself with 150,000 francs in
hand next year, would you buy a television set?", 34%
replied "Yes," and 53% "No." Most of the 34% were not
employed directly in agriculture, while among the 53%
there was a large majority of agriculturists and small
farmers.
It's the club that counts
In reply to a complementary question: "If not, what
would you buy instead of or sooner than a television
set?" they gave these answers: a motor-cycle, a car or
a scooter (33%); modern household equipment washing-
machine, refrigerator, central heating, a shower bath, etc.
(27%); various projects farm equipment, "moving into a
house," paying off debts, "travelling in Europe," etc.
(17%).
These answers show clearly the sort of things that
televiewers feel they need more urgently than a television
set. There is therefore every chance that in France and
still more in countries with lower standards of living, the
tele-club will long continue to provide a majority of people
with their only chance to enjoy telecasts.
But tele-clubs do more than simply fill an economic
need. To the question "If you had a television set at
home would you still like going to the club?", 75% of the
replies were "Yes!"
The reasons given for continuing to visit the tele-club
were very diverse. Most people were interested in the
debates because they wished "to discuss interesting pro¬
grammes". Other reasons ranged from "so as to be with
other people" to "because its like going to a show."
There is no doubt that this new type of adult education
activity meets a social need and that people come to it not
only to enjoy the programmes but for the sake of other
group activities as well.
A FARMER-ACTOR AND
HIS INVISIBLE FRIEND
Professional actor or farmer-
actor? The Unesco experi¬
mental TV programmes gave
a clear answer to this question.
No one could present the life of
the farmer better than himself.
Even when it came to putting
forward other people's views, the
non-professional who knew his
subject inside out carried more
conviction than a professional
actor could ever have done.
As the films for the programmes
had been shot "'silent" in the
country they had not only to be
cut, but a sound track added.
For the first telecast of "State of
Emergency" the story was to be
presented by a countryman who
was both the author and the actor.
This is what happened when his
commentary was recorded.
The man in question, M. De-
marck, a wine-grower at Grouttes,
a little village in the south of the
Aisne, had been asked to write the
commentary for his own story, as
related in the film. But when this
had been written down and read
back by its author it somehow
struck a false note. Furthermore,
the recording sounded unpleasant.
The wine-grower's characteristic¬
ally gruff voice, which the product-
er was keen on using, seemed
artificial and the text flat and un¬
interesting.
After several unsuccessful at¬
tempts, the producer wrote a
different text; with no better luck.
On the point of giving up the
idea of using the "story told by its
author" approach, the producer
said to M. Demarck as a last hope:
"Try to imagine you are telling
your story to a friend... try to keep
pace with the picture, but if you
can't manage it, don't worry... just
carry on!"
"What about my paper?"
"Put it in your pocket and forget
it!"
"Ready?... Go ahead!"
Then from behind the glass par¬
tition of the control room, the pro¬
gramme team watched this unique
sight: a farmer alone in front of
a microphone, gesticulating and
grimacing as he told his story,
while it was being shown on the
screen, to an imaginary friend. It
went on for 20 minutes. When it
had finished, M. Demarck, without
a page of script, had recorded a
faultless commentary with no
over-running. The sound engineer
said he had never known anything
like it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Poll reveals likes and dislikes
WHAT does TV try to do?
It aims to bring relaxa*
tion to televiewers after
the fatigue of everyday
work; to provide entertainment
and to take their minds off work
for a short time ; and to help to
develop the personality, by
showing people how to cope
more satisfactorily with the prob¬
lems of th'eir daily lives. These
closely-linked functions meet
certain basic needs and a weekly
programme should allow scope
for them all. There should be
some measure of each in every
evening's telecast, otherwise the
audience will be fatigued or
bored. To see if these three
basic aims were being achieved,
tele-clubs in France were asked
during a UNESCO opinions
survey what they thought of the
various types of regular program¬
mes put out by French television:
variety, films, plays, literary
programmes, practical subjects,
news reporting, etc. The impor¬
tance of the survey lies in the
fact that the tele-club audiences
are largely representative of a
country such as France. Their
replies thus set a standard of
comparison for TV programme
planners who want to please a wide
public, by mixing entertainment
with the education which they
present through the TV screen.
REAWAKENED IN¬
TEREST in the theatre
now exists among rural
tele-club audiences. Not
all plays have been cho¬
sen with an eye to the
susceptibilities of coun¬
try folk some, either
too frivolous or too
subtle, have left bad
impressions. But more
and more villagers say:
"If it hadn't been for TV
I would never have got
to know the theatre."
Documentary program¬
mes (like the one shown
here taking the TV au¬
dience into a business
training school) are also
tremendously popular.
Radiodiffusion-Télévision
Française.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Likes and dislikes (Cont'd)
Variety gets
top rating
Top favourites of all French weekly
telecasts viewed by the rural
tele-clubs, are variety program¬
mes (circus, music-hall, sketches and
interviews with leading entertainers).
Unesco's survey of audience likes and
dislikes showed that between 78%
and 92% of televiewers were en¬
thusiastic about these programmes
and especially about Trente-six chan¬
delles (Thirty-six Candles) a fort¬
nightly variety telecast, and one of
the most popular in France. The
circus was much more of a favourite
with the small farmers and labourers
than with non-manual workers.
" Sunday feature films tied with
Trente-six chandelles (80% each) for
popularity, though many viewers
complained that the films released
were too old. Although extracts and
incomplete works are usually disliked
by unsophisticated audiences, se¬
quences from recent films rated 60%
of votes. Documentaries, though ge¬
nerally reputed to be tedious, were
also approved by 60% of televiewers.
Studio-produced plays were liked
by 60% of the audiences, while only
7% were against them. The theatre
seems to appeal to women slightly
more than to men, but all age groups
show much the same attitude.
Books are a bore
Least popular o'f all the program¬
mes was "Lecture pour tous"
(reading for all) chief literary
programme of French TV. Even the
non-manual workers were not keen
about this telecast and not one of the
small farmers or workmen liked it.
Thus, this feature, though winner of
the French Television Prize for 1954,
has certainly not solved the problem
of popularizing reading through TV.
Merits of Le Magazine Féminin, the
only one of the "practical" program¬
mes regularly seen by the tele-clubs,
seem to be strongly in dispute (48%
in favour; 36% against). It is na¬
turally most liked by women, yet the
cutting out lesson is equally popular
with men and with women. A
puzzling feature of audience reaction
is this tepid welcome given by women
to programmes dealing with house¬
hold problems.
Among the news and outside broad¬
casts, the Journal Télévisé rivals va¬
riety programmes in popularity.
Workmen are its staunchest support¬
ers, far more so than non-manual
workers, though they are less en¬
thusiastic about the Magazine du
temps passé, a review of past events.
Reports by explorers on distant
countries, deserts or polar regions
(Magazine des Explorateurs) are
not outstandingly popular, especially
among the "Over 40's." Docu¬
mentaries on social themes receive
more approval and this type of outside
telecast seems to be the one likely to
interest everybody.
COOKING LESSONS
given on " Women's
Magazine" programmes
were only welcomed by
5% of televiewers. But
this women's programme
as a whole is a favour¬
ite "practical" telecast.
Even men like lessons
on cutting out clothes.
WORKS VISIT: One of
highly popular telecasts
on social problems.
Geographical program¬
mes have even more
appeal. One farmer was
surprised to find that
"Finns look like us; 1
always thought they
resembled the Chinese."
INVENTORS' CLUB,
a programme on which
latest inventions are
presented, got 17 votes
compared with 60 given
to domestic features.
"Practical" programmes
explaining different jobs
and professions are also
very much in demand.
OLD CROCK shakes its
way down the Champs-
Elysées In Paris while
taking part in the "Pile
ou Face" (Heads or Tails)
programme for young
people. Age group of
21 to 25 gave most
votes to music-hall and
variety programmes.
Radiodif.-Télévision Française.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The U esco Courier
STATE OF EMERGENCY
AN EASIER LIFE for coun¬
trywomen was the subject
of one of the "State of
Emergency" programmes.
Yet a survey among tele-
clubs showed that more
women than men are oppos¬
ed to modernization. Left,
Roger Louis, tele-club orga¬
nizer turned producer who
arranged the programmes.
The evening of January 7, 1954, marks an important
date for a group of small French villages some
60 miles from Paris. On that evening farmers, rural
workers and local officials were crowded together in their
town halls and schools to "have a look at the television".
They were there for the opening of a new television series
called "State of Emergency" which had been prepared for
their tele-clubs by the Radiodiffusion-Télévision Fran-
. çaise and Unesco. The series was a unique experiment
which had as its goal the introduction of mechanization
on farms, and modernization of living conditions in
villages.
The joint project grew out of a Unesco decision to
produce a series of educational programmes aimed at
rural populations, to evaluate the results and to publicize
them for the benefit of governments, educators and tele¬
vision producers throughout the world who are trying to
find the best ways of using television for adult education
in rural areas.
Why did Unesco choose a group of French villages for
its experiment? Firstly because the conditions there
seemed to offer an ideal "testing bench". It is no mere
chance that tele-club associations had sprung up mainly
in the country where the need for new kinds of entertain¬
ment has become more pressing as countryfolk have
become more- aware of the greater amenities of town life.
Secondly because the economic and cultural conditions
of the little villages to the east of Paris reflect a way of
life that 'is roughly the same in many other countries.
Isolation, material handicaps and financial and social
problems, all too common in Europe and elsewhere, are
barriers to a badly needed modernization.
Thus the lessons and conclusions drawn from a pilot
project conducted in France through the tele-clubs would,
with some adjustments, very probably serve as a guide
for the introduction of television into the country areas
of many of Unesco's member states, and at the same
time would be of help to other countries embarking on
similar educational experiments.
The chief difficulty in planning the telecasts was to
find a subject that would interest both the wine-grower
and the farmer, the labourer and the engineer, the village
family and city television audiences, for there is only one
television network in France. Finally, it was decided that
the series should demonstrate the vital problems con¬
fronting French agriculture and the need to introduce
modern methods for their solution.
All the problems would be presented in a framework
of "true life stories" and in nearly all the programmes
their main lines would be explained through the experi¬
ences of living people. In many cases farmers came to
the studio. Viewers, for example, were introduced to
M. Lecomte whose son had joined the army and left him,
at an advanced age, to work his farm alone.
A small farmer and an industrialist discuss-
ing credit, revealed both sides of the question. (Com d on
Whether the subject was the re-allocation of next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
MASCULINE TASTES strongly fa¬
vour films and variety programmes.
EXPERTS PANEL presided over by TV producer Roger Louis, took part in some programmes. Panel
included manufacturers, big and small farmers, labourers and others interested in rural problems.
UNESCO-Cassirer UNESCO-Cassirer
land, co-operative activities,
the flow of young people to
the towns, or women's life
in the country, it was always
the tale of personal expe¬
rience which made the
greatest impression.
Roger Louis, who planned
the programmes, went out
to study rural problems on
the spot. In three districts
Tardenois, Brie and Cham¬
pagne^ he talked to the local people and asked them :
"What isn't going right in your part of the world?" The
men and women he questioned represented a wide range
of occupations, age-groups, financial and social positions
and cultural levels. He spoke to teachers and parish
priests, veterinary surgeons and doctors, shopkeepers and
managers of co-operatives. Taking to the big farmers,
farm labourers and small farmers, he tried to pin down
the main features o'f rural difficulties.
As the districts concerned were so poverty-stricken, it
was decided that the programmes should deal above all
with the problem of the poorest farms the most numer¬
ous and should be aimed particularly at the small
farmers, explaining to them the need for modernization
and showing how improvements could be made despite
difficulties such as the splitting up of land among many
owners.
The telecasts aimed to show that such efforts were
practicable, providing that modernization of equipment
went hand-in-hand with the use of agricultural credit,
the re-allocation of rural property, increased co-operation
and better conditions for women and young people. To
emphasize the gravity of the problem for small farmers
10
and for the nation as a whole, the series was called
"State of Emergency".
The success of "State of Emergency" was immediately
obvious from the tele-club discussions which followed each
transmission. At first, many teachers thought it unlikely
that the telecasts would stimulate such debates. "Coun¬
tryfolk will never dare to say what they think in front
of people from their own village," they said, "they are
inarticulate". But in all the tele-clubs, even in those
where it had previously been impossible to start any
discussions, the main themes of the 13 telecasts were
hotly debated. In some clubs, discussions went on until
two in the morning.
The debates and the information collected during an
opinion survey soon showed what the tele-club members
thought about the rural problems dealt with in the pro¬
grammes.
?bad for the land*
The ideas which the small farmers had about modern¬
ization of farm equipment, either on an individual
or a collective basis, varied considerably. Almost
everyone wanted' to buy if he did not already possess
them certain items of equipment now regarded as part
of the bare- minimum required for his work. Less than
10% of small farmers without such equipment were
against buying it.
The things which people considered as essentials varied
greatly: a farm building in a good state of repair, an
all-metal wheel plough, a reaper and binder, artificial
fertilizers, an electric motor or a diesel engine.
Then there was equipment which 10% to 30% of small
farmers did not wish to buy. Slightly over 10% of
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
OVER FORTIES are more interested in telecasts on social problems than are young people. But
both age groups find common ground in approving news, outside broadcasts and studio plays.
UNESCO-Le Fauconnier
A - 1- 4T
4 \ ^\\
CLASSROOM BENCHES are hard but
tele-clubs usually have a "full-house".
Ut lESCO-Cassirc,
farmers were not interested in selected seed; about the
same number wished to buy it. The small farmers were
suspicious of artificial insemination, about one in three
being against this scientific method of stock-improvement.
The natural way, they said, was good enough for them:
"I've got a bull", "My neighbour has a bull", and so on.
Only about 10% wanted to repair dilapidated buildings.
The others thought it "useless" or "too expensive". About
85% of those questioned had no modern machinery such
as milking and separating machines, and close on 30%
were definitely against them.
While 80% of farmers had a bank account, as against
some 15% who did net want one, things like a progress
table or an account book were considered utterly useless
on a small farm: "Pointless." "I keep the accounts in my
head."
Opinion was much the same on the subject of tractors :
about 80% had none and barely 20% would like to buy
one. More than 30% were openly against them. When
asked how they would like to spend an extra
500,000 francs, an even more minute percentage of small
farmers (0,3%) said they would buy a tractor, while
16% said they would buy a car. Spending money on
the home (6%) also got priority over a tractor. All in all,
these small cultivators had a strong aversion for the very
machine most likely to raise agricultural output: "There's
no money for it", "I get along all right with what I
have", "The holdings are too small", or "'They're bad for
the land".
Perhaps if they clubbed together the small 'farmers
could buy and make good use of a tractor. But how do
they feel about co-operative undertakings, leaving aside
silos, cellars and wine presses which are not of equal
interest to farmers and wine-growers alike? The inquiry
showed, in fact, that something like 40% of all categories
did not belong to any buyers' co-operative, and less than
15% were keen to enter any such co-operative association.
Eighty percent had never heard of a users' co-operative
which could give them the use of such large and costly
machines as tractors.
When it same to domestic aid appliances, opposition
towards co-operation was even more marked. The idea
of a collective washing machine was unknown to or
rejected by 90%. Reasons most often given against co¬
operation were : "There aren't enough of us", "It wouldn't
pay", "I don't believe in it", and (in the case of the
collective washing-machine), "It's unhygienic".
Against sewage and water mains
If rural workers are to adjust themselves to the pro¬
gress of techniques and ideas, they stand in increasing
need of information and education. Nearly all of them
have joined or wish to join school extension associations.
Tele-clubs come under this heading. Yet, roughly 85% of
viewers live in villages where there are no young farmers'
groups, and only 40% thought that it would be useful
to found such a group.
How did the small farmers feel about the modernization
of public and domestic equipment? Among large com¬
munal undertakings, road and bridge building was their
first choice (22%), followed closely by the laying down
of a mains water supply (only 65% of the televiewers had
water laid on).
About 50% of people without running water wanted
it and the same proportion were in favour of
public sewage, yet about one quarter of the (Cont'd on
villagers did not want either main drainage or next page)
main water supply. The most stubborn oppo-
1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
[TV TEST TUBE
1
J
FOUR MONTHS' RESULTS WERE
STRIKING-AND POSITIVE
sition came from small farmers: only 30% of them wanted
running water as against 65% of workers.
Though women are the first to suffer from lack of
domestic comfort, they were more hostile than men to
such schemes: 52% of men wanted running water as
against 36% of the women; 61% of men favoured public
sewage while only 36% of women wanted it. The argu¬
ments, whether justified or not, were always the same:
"The commune is too scattered", "The village is too
small", "We have no money for it", "'We get along all
right as we are", and so on.
Although 90% of the people have a wash-house, over
50% considered it quite inadequate. Nearly 95% have no
bath or shower, or are dissatisfied with what they have.
Yet barely 35% wanted to improve the wash-house and
only about 50% were anxious to install a bath or shower.
Here again, farmers are more strongly opposed than
workers, and women (37%) are less enthusiastic than men
(58%).
What reasons do they give for their objections? "The
village is too scattered", "There isn't any water", or, more
often, "That wouldn't work", "The brook isn't far off",
"I've lived in dirt and I'm not going to change now",
"Things are all right as they are".
In these, as in other rural areas, entertainments are
few and far between. For example, between 70% and
75% of the people questioned lived in localities with no
village hall or sports ground or said they considered
existing facilities inadequate. About 40% wanted "to do
something" about having a village hall and about 25%
wanted a sports ground. Both men and women equally
favoured a sports ground, but more men were in favour
of having a village hall. As could be expected, young
people under 25 years of age were the most enthusiastic
supporters of these projects 50% in favour of the sports
ground compared with 15% of persons over 40.
'Gas for cooking ? It might blow up'
Some expenditures aimed at modernizing the home met
with practically no opposition. This does not apply
to the coke cooking stove or the radio which
practically all homes (about 90%) already have, nor to
sewing machines owned by approximately 70% of viewers'
families. But 55% of those questioned have no water laid
on to the sink by means of a pump, or a tap feed from a
tank, and this was demanded by 50% of the people,
particularly the men.
About 40% are without butane gas, and only 20% of
those questioned, wanted to use it. Eighty percent have
no household sewage, and less than 50% wanted to install
it. As for washing machines of their own, 85% of viewers
had none and only 45% wanted one. Central heating is
practically non-existent and over half the people consider¬
ed it an unattainable ideal.
Generally speaking, workers were far keener on pur¬
chasing modernizing equipment than were the small
farmers. The lack of enthusiasm of the women for the
modernization of household equipment, though less mark¬
ed and consistent than for public equipment, still showed
them to be, more conservative than men.
Arguments against up-to-date household equipment
varied greatly : "Butane gas? It might blow up." As for
the electric cooker: "We have our wood for nothing", and
"There are breakdowns." Sewage: "What would I want
that for?" or "I've got a cess pit". Washing machines:
"They aren't perfect yet", "They're a luxury" or "They're
hard on the linen." Central heating: "That's all right
for the people of Paris", and so on.
12
The reasons behind these ideas and attitudes usually
fall into two categories: Either genuine, material obstacles,
and economic or geographical ones, or imaginary obsta¬
cles due to prejudices. Those in the second category
reflect indifference or conservatism towards technical
progress. ("We've been doing things like that for 20 years,
so why should we change now?") or asocial or anti-social
attitudes ("I have my own wash-house; the others can
look after themselves..."). In general, those based on real
obstacles only made up about 50% of the total.
Prejudice against building overcome
In any case, the title of the programme "State of
Emergency" was justified. Modernization is vital to
French agriculture and is an urgent national problem.
In every field mechanization or credit, the re-allocation
of the land and the situation of women in rural areas,
the community spirit, vocational training and the orga¬
nization of recreation for young people ignorance and
prejudice add their weight to genuine obstacles and slow
down the forces of progress.
How far did the series of telecasts succeed in uprooting
prejudice and in creating a constructive approach? As
the experiment lasted four months it would be unrea¬
sonable to suppose that centuries-old prejudices could be
broken down in this length of time. It would be still less
reasonable to expect education alone to create a new type
of mentality. This requires higher standards of living
and basic changes in the structure of rural life.
When the programme had ended, a second survey of
opinions was made, the same questions being put to the
same people. Comparisons between the two results
revealed the positive effects of "State of Emergency".
Reports, observations and statistical tables all agreed.
Most of the positive changes in attitude applied to the
repair of buildings or the building of new ones. Many
people, too, had changed their ideas about using artificial
fertilizer and about seed selection, and others, far fewer
in number, about the use of tractors.
But little change had been worked in the anti-co¬
operative ideas and there was still strong objection to
collective agricultural equipment. There was, however,
much more positive feeling among the small farmers, as
regards collectively owned cultural materials and resour¬
ces, as applied to after-school leisure activities.
Farmers wives stand to benefit
The most marked progress showed up in the small
farmers' attitudes towards domestic equipment
washing machines, housing repairs and the installa¬
tion of running water. It looks, therefore, as though
farmers' wives stand to benefit most from any improved
conditions stimulated by the TV programmes.
More positive ideas were to some extent noted among
persons in all age-groups, sexes and occupations. Most
striking was the change in attitude of those who had
previously been the most strongly opposed to or wary of
modernization. While they had certainly not all been
converted overnight, they had changed as a group more
than the other categories.
The experiments helped to give the lie to assertions
such as "country people take no interest in anything", or
"all they care about is making money". These village
people were shown to be keenly interested in the basic
problems of daily living. They are not loquacious but
their ideas, though often limited, are clear and consis¬
tent. Using this as a starting point, popular education,
popular culture and popular art should start their efforts
among such people to bring about a gradual im¬
provement in the level and scope of knowledge and skills.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Its the talk
of the village
The first practical effect of the "State of
Emergency" telecasts was to stimulate
discussions and arguments in the village
tele-clubs often for the first timeon
the rural problems dealt with in the I 3 pro¬
grammes. Here, taken at random, are
some of the ideas expressed by the small
farmers and wine-growers during the
debates that took place in schoolrooms and
village halls.
Re-allocation of land ? We'd be expected
to give good land in exchange for rubbish!
together to buy a tractor ? If one
man handles It badly everyone has to pay
for the repairs!
No! we need to be less individualistic
and have some confidence!
In a co-operative a man is not working
for himself, but for his children and for
everyone in general!
machine for outside work is all right,
but the inside of the house can wait!
Improve the house equipment! We'd
look fine with a grand farm and no modern
equipment to work it with!
Why do young people drift to the towns ?
When they see that town-folk can rest from
Saturday to Monday, it tempts them!
once took four families to get in the
Harvest, now one lad can do it by himself!
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TV : GIANT IN SEVEN LEAGUE BOOTS
Every day some 255 million
copies of daily news¬
papers, 257 million radio re¬
ceivers and 44 million television
sets bring news and informa¬
tion to the peoples of the
world. Over 130,000 permanent
cinemas and mobile units pro¬
vide them with entertainment.
These facts emerge from a
264-page UNESCO report,
"World Communications", (1)
which gives the latest informa¬
tion on press, radio, film and
television facilities throughout
the globe. The report also
highlights developments
in these media during the past
five years.
A striking development in
this period has been a sharp
increase in the world total of
radio receivers which for the
first time exceeded the num¬
ber of copies of daily news¬
papers. World press circulation
rose by 14% while radio receiv¬
ers increased by 41%.
Some other striking facts re¬
vealed: Europeans buy 38% of
world's daily papers, Americans
24%, while Africans, Asians and
South Americans together com¬
mand barely 24%; North Amer¬
ica possesses 50% of the world's
receiving sets while Africa, Asia
and South America together
own only 11%. Radio's most
significant advances, how¬
ever, have been made in Latin
America, China, various Afri¬
can territories and the Pacific
islands. TV is being operated
regularly in 34 countries and in
Latin America is expanding
more rapidly than either the
press or the radio.
The UNESCO report high¬
lights the fact that communi¬
cation facilities are unequally
shared by continents and coun¬
tries and points out that coun¬
tries wishing to develop their
news enterprises may now re¬
ceive technical aid from the
U.N. and its Specialized Agen¬
cies.
On the following pages, The
UNESCO COURIER presents
some of the more salient feat¬
ures of the developments in
press, radio, film and TV,
throughout the world during
the past five years. .
(I) Published May, I956. Price: $8; 42/-
2,000 Fr. frs.
According to Unesco's latest survey
of world television three con¬
tinents today remain relatively
untouched by the TV screen: Africa
with only two stations, both in Moroc¬
co; Asia where only Japan and the
Philippines o'ffer regular telecasts;
and Oceania where only Hawaii has
TV. But television is expanding so
fast nowadays, Unesco's report adds,
that it is extremely hard to keep track
of all changing developments.
The latest count obtained by the
Unesco Courier shows that TV is
operating on a regular basis in 34
countries, is being developed in 12
others and is in the planning stages
in some 19 more.
The "Big Four" of television were
listed six years ago by Unesco as the
U.S., U.K., U.S.S.R. and France. To¬
day Canada has jumped to third
place with two million receivers, a
good distance behind the United
States with 38 million or 80 % of the
world's sets, and the United Kingdom
with five and a half million. The So¬
viet Union, which was expected to
reach the million mark by the end of
1955 is now fourth. The "million¬
aires" are well ahead of France which
has been unable to keep the same
pace. With its 350,000 declared private
sets (plus a probable 80,000 unregister¬
ed) it is now fifth just one small
step ahead of the German Federal
Republic's 300,000 sets (plus another
probable 80,000 undeclared). French
TV, though, with its 40 hours a week
offers the most complete selection of
programmes on the Continent.
Surprising changes are being made
in the structure of television. Inter¬
national programme co-operation is
promising to become a regular feature
of the industry. The establishment
of an exchange relay network known
as "Eurovision" is breaking down na¬
tional barriers. It groups eight coun¬
tries Belgium, Denmark, France,
German Federal Republic, Nether¬
lands, Italy, Switzerland and the Uni¬
ted Kingdom and first went on the
air in 1954 to telecast the world foot¬
ball championship matches from
Switzerland.
I transmitter in regular operation
I transmitter in experimental operati
= 50,000 receivers
= 500.000 receivers
Countries with regular
television service
Pictographs published on pages 14 to 21 were produced by the Netherlands Statistical
Foundation and taken from Unesco's publication "World Communications". Pictograph
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Today each of the eight countries
can receive programmes broadcast by
the others.
International relays are not limit¬
ed to Europe. American pro¬
grammes are regularly linked with
Canadian stations, and in 1954 the
first public broadcast via "stratovi¬
sion" (a transmitter located in an
aircraft) successfully relayed the
American baseball world series from
Miami, Florida, to Cuba. The plane
flew in a 10-mile dameter circle about
9,000 feet above the sea some 50 miles
off the coast of Cuba, and reception
was reported excellent.
Direct TV links between Europe and
the U.S. by over-the-horizon micro¬
wave transmission have now been cal¬
led "feasible in a matter of a few
years". The international exchange
of kinescope or TV film programmes
is also being considered. The U.S. has
been offering kinescopes to stations in
Latin America for the past two years
and more recently to European and
Japanese stations.
TV's biggest boom is still going on
in the United States where it has
changed the daily life of the Ameri¬
can people. TV's growth there has
been unparalleled from 8 million sets
in 1950 to a phenomenal 38 million
early in 1956. Well over 565 stations
are on the air and in major cities
such as New York, viewers can choose
from seven different programmes at
almost any hour of the day or night.
A coast-to-coast network of colour
TV is now planned.
In the U.S., Canada, and the United
Kingdom, TV is rapidly encroaching
on the place' previously held by sound
radio. Moreover, the impact of edu¬
cational TV is only beginning to be
felt. Brazil, Colombia, France, Japan,
the U.S.S.R., the U.S. and certain
other countries are telecasting re¬
gular educational programmes for
schools and adults. "Teaching by
sound and image promises revolution¬
ary changes in the field of educa¬
tion", the Unesco report states.
Curiously, while in the United Sta¬
tes 19 non-commercial educational
stations have gone on the air with a
potential audience of 20 million peo¬
ple, and a "pay-as-you-view" system
replacing commercial sponsorships is
being discussed, commercial television
has come to Europe to the Saar, Mo¬
naco, Luxembourg and the United
Kingdom (in September 1955 under a
government-established Independent
Television Authority).
Television in the United States has
made its influence strongly felt on
the countries of Latin America. Cu¬
ba, with its nine transmitters, 200,000
receivers and 100 hours of programmes
above has been slightly modified by "The Unesco Courier" so as to include some
of the latest developments that have taken place in the world-wide growth of television.
The Unesco Courier
per week, heads the list. Brazil is the
number one TV country of South
America with 6 transmitters and
150,000 sets in 1954. Mexico has no
fewer than nine stations and over
100,000 receivers. A closed-circuit
colour TV service operates at the Uni¬
versity Medical School. In all Latin
America, TV is expanding now more
rapidly than either press or radio.
Japan's dramatic advance
Television has made one of its
most dramatic advances in
Japan where no regular broad¬
cast existed before 1953. Today five
stations are in operation and while
the number of receivers now total
some 250,000 there is a considerable
amount of public TV viewing for
which 200 large screen sets are used.
When 29 new stations now planned
are completed they will serve 65%
of Japan's households. Since the
end of 1955, Thailand has gone
beyond the experimental stage and is
giving regular programmes. Turkey
is transmitting closed-circuit experi¬
mental programmes. India and Iraq
are planning TV services.
The Soviet Union, one of the first
countries to telecast first-run films
regularly, has developed its TV
services rapidly during the past two
years. The U.S.S.R. already has ma¬
jor stations at Moscow, Leningrad and
Kiev, and six smaller ones at Gorki,
Kharkov, Odessa Stalingrad, Sver¬
dlovsk and Tomsk. Others are under
construction at Baku, Minsk, Mur¬
mansk and Riga. One Moscow trans¬
mitter regularly telecasts experimen¬
tal programmes in colour. Use of a
new natural colour process has been
announced in recent months. Soviet
programmes include many education¬
al and cultural telecasts, film shows
for schools and special children's
programmes. Many sets are located
in clubs, and social centres. Pro¬
grammes on film are exchanged
within the Soviet Union and with
other countries of Eastern Europe.
97% coverage for Britain
In Western Europe the number of
television stations has risen in the
past two years from 25 to 76.
Italy, which started from scratch in
1954, now has eleven transmitters cov¬
ering most of north and central Italy,
and about 225,000 receivers. Plans
call for complete coverage of Italy in¬
cluding Sicily and Sardinia by the end
of this year (66 new transmitters
planned). The United Kingdom now
has a national TV service of 14
transmitters available to 84% of the
population. When 77 medium and
low-power transmitters are added,
U.K. coverage will be 977o.
Of the 19 countries which are today
operating regular or experimental TV
services in Europe, almost all have
plans for the rapid extension of their
coverage. The German Federal Repub¬
lic has six broadcasting organiza¬
tions operating 24 transmitters, but 16
new transmitters are under construc¬
tion. The German Democratic Repub¬
lic plans to add four new stations to
the existing eight. France has 16
stations covering its northern, eastern,
central and southern areas ; 13
transmitters are operating and 18
more are planned.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
DAILY PRESS RUN:
255 MILLION COPIES
Despite growing competition from radio, newsreels and
TV, more people still turn to newspapers for their
daily news. Circulation has increased 14% in the
past five years, Unesco's latest survey of the world's press
shows. Every day some 255 million copies of newspapers
are sold. In the U.S.A. the regular daily press now has
a circulation exceeding 55 million as against 54 million in
1951; in Japan 34.5 million (28 million in 1951); while in
the U.S.S.R., the combined circulation of dailies and week¬
lies is estimated at 44 million as against 34 million in
1951. In some countries, rising production costs have led
to press mergers or forced weaker, papers out of existence.
France, for example, lost 32 dailies and Japan seven be¬
tween 1951 and 1954.
Europe, the Unesco report says, buys the most news¬
papers (38%) followed by North America (24%) while
Africa, Asia and South America together account for
barely 24%... The British are still the world's most avid
newspaper readers with Sweden, Luxembourg, Iceland,
Australia and Japan following in that order (see table
on next page).
One of the most rapid circulation growths in recent
years has been scored by Japan. In 1952 there were 186
dailies with a 30 million circulation. Today there are 179
dailies but circulation has jumped by four and a half
million. Circulation per 1,000 persons is more than dou¬
ble that of any other Asian country, and is now higher
than the United States level. Even the smaller newspapers
now have circulations exceeding 850,000.
Simplified script
starts a revolution
Perhaps the most significant increases in the past
five years have been made in the economically
under-developed countries, where greater oppor¬
tunities for education, the growth of new schools, adult
and fundamental education campaigns have .spurred the
demand for more newspapers. In Africa, newspapers
have spread into jungle villages where total illiteracy
prevailed only a few years ago. Air and radio communi¬
cation now enables papers published in towns which
previously had little or no contact with the outside world
to receive feature material and photographs regularly.
Some examples of African progress: Gold Coast now has
11 dailies (total circulation 75,000) plus nine weeklies and
a local news agency ; Madagascar has seven dailies and
27 weeklies, nearly all published in Malagasy ; little
Reunion Island in the Indian Ocean has eight dailies
and weeklies and circulation has doubled in the past
four years. Even Swaziland has two weeklies, while the
remote island of St. Helena can boast a roneoed news
bulletin.
Even more important has been the development of the
vernacular press in Africa. Many district newspapers
circulating in villages appear in local languages. Tangan¬
yika has dailies and Uganda weeklies in three vernacu¬
lars. The Bantus of the Union of South Africa now have
a chain of 23 publications.
In Latin America, Argentina remains the country where
daily newspapers are most readily available. Most Argen¬
tine towns of any size have their own daily and can draw
on three national agencies for local news. Brazil and
Venezuela are typical of the rapid growth of the press
in South America. In 1952 Brazil had 230 dailies, a year
later it had 254 and circulation was skyrocketing. In
Venezuela circulation rose as much as 20% between 1952
and 1954.
A similar trend is noted in Asia, particularly in Japan,
India, Indonesia and continental China. On the China
mainland 776 dailies appear in a multiplicity of editions;
many large national dailies publish provincial editions in
a simple vocabulary. Though newspaper reading has been
stimulated by efforts of the Chinese postal administration
to promote circulation, wall newspapers are stilt a major
source for news in rural areas. They are seen in every
street and hamlet, sometimes printed on paper but often
no more than chalked information on a blackboard pro¬
tected from the rain by a canopy.
The recent introduction of a new simplified script is
revolutionizing publishing in China and is expected to
I copy of a daily newspaper per I 00 people
have far-reaching effects in increased readership. The
official New China News Agency now has teletype equip¬
ment capable off transmitting news in this script. New
photo-composing equipment to replace laborious hand
type-setting is also foreseen.
India and Pakistan face problems similar to those of
many other Asian countries. Their press must combat
a low literacy rate and difficulties of distribution to large
rural areas. In India, although circulations remain small,
there has been a remarkable growth in numbers of papers,
particularly country weeklies and magazines in towns of
less than 100,000 persons, spurred by India's rural liter¬
acy drive. Burma is an exception to the general Asian
trend. Some 32 dailies are published but many sizeable
towns still lack a newspaper of any type. Burma's largest
daily in Rangoon has a circulation ox only 13,000 yet
Burma's population exceeds 19 million and has a rela¬
tively high literacy rate for Asia of 50%.
The press of the U.S.S.R. has several unusual charac¬
teristics. Each of the 16 republics has its own official
language, and newspapers are issued in 119 different ton¬
gues. There is only one truly national daily, the Commu-
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Urjsco Courier
nist Party organ Pravda, printed in Moscow and 12 other
cities with a-circulation of some four million. About 75%
of all dailies and weeklies are published outside Moscow.
The nation's dailies and weeklies now total 7,800 with a
combined circulation of 44 million, an increase of 11 mil¬
lion since 1951. Advertising is now allowed but is limited
mostly to. announcements of available consumer goods.
Although no newspapers are privately owned, periodicals
are not always government run. Trade unions, co-opera¬
tives, sports clubs, youth organizations, collective, farms
and factory groups all issue their own newspapers.
In Eastern Europe, newspaper publication and distri¬
bution follows a uniform pattern. Communist Party-
dailies in Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Poland
enjoy the greatest circulation, sometimes three or four
times higher than their nearest competitors.
In Western Europe only four tiny countries lack a daily
newspaper: Andorra, Liechtenstein, San Marino and
Monaco. With some exceptions expansion has been slow
in most European countries. Belgium and Sweden have
increased circulation by nearly a million since 1951. The
German Federal Republic now has 671 dailies with a total
circulation of about 16 million with the birth of 48 new
dailies and the addition of 3 million readers since 1952.
In France, both total circulation and number of dailies
have declined in the past five years. There are now
132 dailies as compared to 164 in 1951 a drop of 32.
Circulation has fallen only slightly10,280,000 compared
with 10,606,000. France's weekly and periodical press is
unique in that the turnover of new publications is as high
as 1,000 a year. In recent years births have exceeded
deaths and there are now 7,365 weeklies and periodicals
as against 4,075 in 1951. Part of this increase is accounted
for by the phenomenal rise of women's magazines and the
popularity of illustrated weeklies. As in the U.K. and
U.S.A. some of the women's magazines have individual
circulations of over one million.
The British people are the world's greatest newspaper
readers. Some 610 copies of dailies are sold for every
1,000 persons the highest recorded rate. The United
Kingdom also has the newspapers with the world's lar¬
gest circulations. Two dailies sell over four million copies
each and one Sunday newspaper over eight million. The
BBC's weekly "'Radio Times" also has an eight million
circulation. Britain's concentration of population and
highly developed distribution of "national" papers (all
but one are produced in London) largely accounts for
the high circulation. There are 137 dailies with a total
circulation amounting to 31 million, and 11 national
Sunday newspapers with 30 million circulation.
The United States has more newspapers, reviews, maga¬
zines and periodicals than any other country in the
world and no country can match its prolixity of news
distribution. Information through the printed word is'
always readily available to everyone throughout the
48 States of the Union, and the U.S. press has developed
into a unique instrument of mass communication. Its
1,786 daily newspapers had a total circulation of over
55 million in 1954; 95 foreign-language dailies appear;
and there are 545 Sunday papers with nearly 50 million
circulation, and 8,892 weeklies with over 25 million.
Sunday 'heavyweight' :
360 pages, 2 inches thick
Un papers are also physically the largest with
^ dailies running from 20 to 40 pages, Sunday
*-' editions to as many as 100. One Sunday paper
weighs almost four pounds, has 360 pages and is just under
two inches thick. With 7% of the world's population, the
U.S. in fact absorbs nearly 60% of the world's newsprint
output. In only one respect does the U.S. fall behind
other countries in the number of copies of daily news¬
papers per 1,000 inhabitants. The U.S. figure of 344 is
lower than that for the U.K., Sweden and eight other
countries.
Canada maintains its position as the world's largest
producer and exporter of newsprint. In Mexico, literacy
campaigns have had significant results for the press.
Over 160 dailies now exist and provincial papers exert
considerable influence. In Australia, where half of the
total population lives in Sydney and Melbourne, dailies
in these cities claim over half of, the country's circu¬
lation. Australia now has 20 foreign-language papers
reflecting the influx of European migrants.
The Pacific islands, Unescoís latest survey reveals,
depend for their news more on radio and cinema than on
the press. Many have only one weekly or monthly news
sheet. American Samoa has seven cinemas as against
one monthly newspaper ; the New Hebrides has three
cinemas and no newspaper. Only Hawaii, Guam, Fiji and
French Oceania have dailies of general interest.
CIRCULATION OF DAILY
NEWSPAPERS
(Copies per 1,000 Persons)
1950 (I)
1. United Kingdom. 596
2. Norway	 464
3. Australia 455
4. Luxembourg	 441
5. Sweden	 416
6. Denmark 399
7. New Zealand.... 365
8. U.S.A	 354
9. Switzerland 	 352
10. Bermudas 	 340
I I. Belgium 331
12. Netherlands 	 281
13. Finland	 271
14. France 259
15. Canada	 245
16. German Fed. Rep. 238
17. Israel	 235
18. Japan 224
1955 (2)
1. United Kingdom.
2. Sweden	
3. Luxembourg	
4. Iceland	
5. Australia
6. Japan	
7. Norway
8. Belgium	
9. Denmark
I 0. New Zealand. . . .
I I. U.S.A	
I 2. Finland
I 3. Bermudas.. ......
I 4. German Fed. Rep.
I 5. Switzerland 	
I 6. France	
I 7. Netherlands 	
I 8. Canada	
609
506
447
433
408
399
393
380
370
349
344
343
333
312
308
263
258
243
(1) "World Communications": Unesco, Paris, 19 50 (2nd. edition).
(2) » » » » 19 56 (3rd. edition).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
U
L
I
<Q
¿
LITEc
o
Oc
¿
O<
^
J
P
P
»S
«
ft
à?
c
o
oL
OC
j
:u
L
U
oZ
|
^<
oi
n
û
O
1
co"
<
OÔ
sL
U
U>0c
Z
L
HM(U
U
«
J
V
<
u
c
o
c
.0Z
oO<Q
¿
c
o
^U<
1
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
T
h
e
U
n
e
s
c
o
C
o
u
rie
r
O
L
Ü
S
"~
m
T
í
<u
c
C
re
~
X
c
£
o
r
U
)
<U
U
«-*
*£
t-
C
Q
.
a
-
ï
ü
o
S
í
«
o
;
u
iS
-
in
ro
o
¡S
E
-5.g
"o
G
o
O
iN
O
-
c<
=
>
tu
a
j
E
â
C
J
Q
m
i
o
i-
°
S
i^
t
^
S
5
c
»
a
jz
?
n
E
o
L
c
O
-
w
o
a
j
-
0
0
-
o
Z
£
8
<
s
-
~
.
E
â
.-
o
o
n
E
S
8
E
o
F
*
M
K
«
"
O
*R
U
°
O
Q
"5w
c
c
-C
£
*
- o
öa
-
w
-
«
i
O
E<
C
*>
0
)
O
U
S
0
Í
o
q
Z
"R
3
I
F
L
O
U
O
O
r
t
c
c
a
»
D
O
v
>
a
I
I
=1
D
U
W
(11
"
A
w
u
-5
a
*
o
a
i
v
i
«
ï
"
-o
ï
"
"
c
o
>oD
O
X
Jcr
t
ZD
0
U
V
I
X
JCt9
L
O
r-J
Z
C
J
Z
"rt
X
J
XC
J
Û
X
J
C
J
i
-C
O
D
O
C
C
J
z
z
e
t
L
.
X
J
O
>
u
'
c
r
t
z
z
C
l
c
O
U
r
j
D
x
:
r
t
L
.
n
r
j
X
J
m
u
O
i
/
i
V
I
H
0
)
i
nC
J
u
-1
co
cC
J
oucC
J
M
'o
CO
o
n
a
i
X
G
r
t
c0
C
J
c
c
i
Z
J
e
x
au
jC
t£
Z
4
-»
<
D
c
Í
4
)
X
J
r
t
>
^
c
C
r
t
E
J
Z
)
c
0o
"o
ur
t
U
0
0
u
X
0
)
r
t
r
t
1
ca
i
>
r
t
C
J
*
j
CC
J
L
.
3oX
J
X
Jar
t
a
i
J
Z
oa
i
uCz
¡
'c
<
-»
C
J
Û
GC
J
£
D
O
u
X
£
C
J
X
c
<
u
a
i
?
o
~
rt
u
L
»
2
j
a
i
<
ri
v
*
"
S
"
P,
o
<"
"S
4
J
ü
E «
rt
>
-
ÇD
rt
C
J
n
i
m
_
i
t-
a
C
cr
t
OC
l
J
Z
>
r
t
V
I
r
t
0
0
C
ur
t
a
i
X
3
c
V
I
r
t
1
a
i
c
7
;
X
J
32ur
t
0
1
J
C
C
J
J
Z
a
i
E
a
i
X4
-*
1
^
1
C
J
U
vTr
t
a
i
L
,
a
i
L
.
C0
X
JL
.
£
C
^O
'5C
T
C
J
ñ
"
O
O
r
t
c
0
"
~
x
zD
0
t_
X
J
0
1
w
!
O
i
n
0
?
>
v
W
o
ao
o
X
J
L
-
l
L
J
C
a
Z
J
'l-
X
D
C
Z
3
»
S
o
-5
o
S
o
g
>^
a»
o
o
U
c
0
r
t
01
r
t
O
L
.
0
aO
-
>
C
l
C
J
v
n
0X
a
.
C
l
O
r
t
0
a
i
Q
.
X
X
-
C
C
J
*
r
¡
*
j
w
J
Z
ï
a
C
ï
4
J
O
u
0
0
C
0
C
l
>
~
K
E
a
V
E
o
o
^
£
a
i
a
i
O
a
i
-F
E
->
2o
o
u
u
-
Q
.
c
u
O
«
u
-
u
u
o
»
_
0
1
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
BRITISH ARE WORLD'S MOST AVID CINEMA GOERS
U.S.A. 354 -Japan 302- India 25? - Hong Kong 200 - Italy 140 - U.K. 138- German Fed. Rep. 108- France 100 - Mexico 99 - Philippines 80 - Egypt 49 -
Pakistan 47 - Spain 44 - Turkey 40 - Argentina 39 - U.S.S.R. 38 - Sweden 33 - Austria 24 - Czechoslovakia 25 - Finland 24 - Singapore 23 - Greece 20.
MR RADIO LISTENER HAS 257 MILLION SETS
l Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha
ED a Isla 1SJ a ISJa
Isla |i?la IttI Isla
5?
Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha
T^ '^rX '^» ~^r\ ^r\
CsJ KJa BUja ED¿ IttIl
ËSIa tSJa lSMn EDa H¿ la »SI a ftlh ÜtJ Isla
Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha Ha
~^r\ "^^ -4n ^ft ^^ '^í "^» -^^ ^^ ^^
HaHiHaHaHa ^
"^^ ~^T\ ^rT ^^
Ha
I radio receiver per I 00 people
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
One person out of ten in the. world goes to the cinema on an
average of once a week, Unesco's most recent survey of
the film industry reveals. Anglo-Saxon countries seem to
be most bitten by the cinema "bug". The British are the
world's No. 1 cinema goers with 25 films per inhabitant
per year and a total annual attendance of 1,290 million in 1954.
New Zealand is second with 18 films per person each year.
Australia is third with 16. Americans now watch TV screens
instead and go to the '"movies" only 15 times a year (once in
3 weeks).
Since 1946 television has caused 6,000 cinemas to close down
in the U.S. There are now 19,000 cinemas of which 4,000 are
'where the spectator's motor car is his cinema seat.
(Britain has 4,500 cinemas with a seating capacity of over
4 million). Seating capacity in the United States is now
10 million. The annual attendance figure of over 2,000 million,
however, is still not equalled in any other country.
Cinemas have increased in number in many countries of the
Caribbean area. Panama now has 60, the Dominican Republic
70, and Mexico 2,062. Most South American countries also
report increases in the number of commercial cinemas and a
wider use of mobile units in rural areas. Mobile units are also
being increasingly used in Africa (no cinemas exist in British
Togoland or British Somaliland; only one in Bechuanaland, British
Cameroons, Sao Tome and Principe). The Union of South
Africa and Egypt have the most cinema houses. A few countries
of Africa have been producing newsreels and other information
films in recent years though Africa is still the continent most
dependent on the rest of the world for its newsreels.
The world's greatest producer and distributor of films continues
to be United States. It leads in newsreel production (800 a year)
and ' with the exception of certain European countries and con¬
tinental China, most countries depend on the U.S. for at least
70% of all feature films exhibited. Some 350 features are
produced in U.S. studios annually and enjoy world-wide
distribution and publicity. Mexico is the second largest producer
in the Americas with Argentina a good distance behind it.
Canada, Brazil, Guatemala, Jamaica and Puerto Rico have a
limited output.
In Asia, feature film production is booming. With 302 features
only some 50 less than U.S. output Japan has now jumped
to second place ahead of India. Japanese and Indian films are
now regularly exported to other Asian countries and to Europe.
The Far East has also witnessed the sudden rise of the Hong Kong
film industry, now the fourth largest in the world. It owes its
growth to the great demand for films in Chinese which seven
Hong Kong companies are now producing at amazing speeds.
Thailand, Pakistan, the Philippines, Turkey and continental China
also have a fair amount of feature production.
Alongside the rising production of films an increasing number
of new cinemas are now to be found in Asia. Japan now has
3,750 and India 2,000. In continental China the present total of
800 cinemas is increasing as a network of theatres is being built,
and cinema attendance is up at least 30%.
Like the New Zealanders and Australians, the Pacific islanders
are avid cinema goers especially in remote island groups where
up until a few years ago the cinema was a rarity. Fiji for
example now has 30 and Guam 16.
European film production now represents a large proportion of
the world total (see pictograph). Greece has doubled output in
the past two years. Norway now produces 10 features annually.
In the U.S.S.R. all features produced are automatically shown on
television. Numerous newsreels are made in Europe, most
countries either producing their own or making local editions of
world newsreel issues from France, U.S.S.R., United Kingdom and
the U.S.A.
Documentary, educational, scientific and instructional films have
spread throughout the globe and today most film-producing
countries contribute a quota of them. Increased production has
gone hand-in-hand with an increase in distribution and exhibition,
particularly in the non-commercial field. A good example is
Canada, where 150 to 200 documentaries are produced annually
by the National Film Board, dubbed in 5 languages and exported
all over the world. With the aid of mobile units, educational and
documentary films now reach millions previously untouched by
the cinema, especially in Africa, and in many parts of Asia and
Latin America.
The following are ä few of the highlights and sidelights of
radio in the world today as gleaned from Unesco's newest
survey, "World Communications".
Press Lags Behind. For the first time, there are now
more radio sets in the world (257 million) than copies of
daily newspapers sold (255 million). A good half are in 50 million
American homes where almost one out of every two families now
owns two sets or more. The U.S.S.R. has 20 million sets ; the
U.K.' 14 million; Japan over 11 million; and France nearly
nine million.
Atmospherics gone. Some 25 countries (mostly in Western
Europe) now broadcast by frequency modulation (FM) thus
eliminating atmospheric disturbances as well as assuring high
quality reception. Leaders are U.S.A. (652 transmitters), German
Federal Republic (118), Canada (34), Italy (20), Finland (17),
Austria (10). FM is a godsend to Finland and Austria, both
plagued by persistent interference on the medium-wave channels
assigned to them in recent years. Austria plans a network of FM
as well as more powerful standard transmitters to improve
reception since almost half its population cannot receive any
Austrian programme satisfactorily at night. South Africa is in
a high atmospheric radio noise area, disastrous for reception.
Authorities are considering switching to short wave.
Saucepan. A cheap, sturdy and simply-operated battery set
called '"saucepan" receiver is becoming increasingly popular in
most U.K. territories in Africa. Local authorities offer them to
village chiefs and bigwigs. One of the major developments in
recent years has been the expansion of radio in the economically
under-developed areas of Africa, South America and Asia.
Wire hookups. A system of providing programmes by wire
hookups with receivers or loudspeakers is widespread in the Soviet
Union, Eastern Europe, Continental China and other countries.
All Soviet towns of over 50,000 inhabitants now have a wired
system. A million wired receivers were installed in 1953 alone
in collective farms previously without radio facilities. Poland's
3,700 relay centres transmit to 1,300,000 wired receivers and
loudspeakers. In Rumania 38% of the 830,000 sets are wired.
Foreign languages. Some 500 stations broadcast in 30 lang¬
uages to listeners inside the United States. In the U.S.S.R.
programmes for Soviet listeners are broadcast in 70 languages.
Radio Pakistan offers 90 programme hours a day in 17 languages.
One of All India Radio's major headaches is serving listeners
speaking 16 major languages and 125 dialects. The BBC
broadcasts in 43 languages in addition to English, Gaelic and
Welsh. The Gold Coast transmits in vernaculars called Ewe, Ga,
Twi, Fanti, Hausi, and Dagbani. A Mexican station now
broadcasts in Náhuatl, the language of the Aztec Indians.
Broadcasts from Rhodesia in 6 local languages cover Central Africa.
Hucksters. Commercial advertising takes up 50% of total
broadcast time of private stations in Uruguay; 40% in the
Dominican Republic; 30% in Costa Rica; 28% in Cuba (limited
by decree, but only to stations with national coverage); 25% in
El Salvador (80% of programmes are recorded music). Per¬
centages are high for private stations in many countries.
In class & home. All the major European countries conduct
both school and general educational programmes. Non¬
commercial stations in Latin America and stations in Africa and
Asia feature educational programmes prominently. In the U.S.
a '"tape" network set up by the National Association of
Educational Broadcasters groups over half of the 150 non¬
commercial educational stations run by colleges, universities and
public institutions. Commercial networks also provide educational
programmes. About 75% of all Australian schools take school
broadcasts. In Czech schools 80% do. Canada has radio sets
in 10,000 schools, and its "National Farm Radio Forum" and
similar group listening and discussion programmes are popular.
Listening to school broadcasts at home is assigned as
"homework" by teachers in the Saar. Norway beams short wave
educational programmes specially to its vast merchant fleet plying
the Seven Seas. News and cultural programmes take up over
50% of total radio time in Japan. Over 45% of France's total
broadcast time is devoted to music. In Russia it is given 60%.
Outdoor listening reached a new high in the United States
with 37 million radios installed in automobiles. In 1953 the U.S.
manufactured 13,400,000 receivers, including 5 million motor
car sets, 2 million clock-radios and 1.5 million portable sets. A
religious mission in Ethiopia periodically hires Radio Adis Ababa
to transmit religious songs and stories.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Educated
Man in 1984
by Dr J. Bronowski
Director of Research, British National Coal Board
THE education of the man of 1956
was largely formed twenty or
thirty years ago. When we ask
what to-day's education should do,
the man we have in mind to inform
and to form is the man of twenty or
thirty years hence. Thus the year
1984, the year of George Orwell's
book, carries a symbolism which our
education ought particularly to keep
in mind.
Education in schools and universi¬
ties has many functions. I shall con¬
fine myself to two, both of them do¬
minated by the skills which we need
in order later to carry on adult life.
Education in this sense is learning to
do something quite precise.
Even so, there are different things
to be learned, or rather there are
different purposes for which we learn
things. The young man at night
school learns book-iteeping in order to
keep books. An engineering student
learns the calculus in order to become
an engineer. A historian learns
Medieval Latin in order to read
documents. These are examples of
education for a very specific purpose,
and since this purpose often helps us
to earn our living, I think of it as
vocational education.
But I knew a man once, a school¬
master who had just retired from
teaching mathematics, who then
learned Italian in order to read
Dante. What he learned was indeed
precise, and the purpose specific, yet
I cannot feel that this was vocational
education. The learner was fitting
himself to derive from the work of
Dante a larger, deeper sense of the
many-sidedness of human life than
had reached him in translation. At
sixty-five, he was fitting himself not
to make a living but to live.
Humanism doomed unless...
This is the purpose for which we
learn English and arithmetic
and history at school, for these
are subjects which do not stop at a
single need, at writing letters and
making out bills. They inform and
hold together the fragments of so¬
ciety, so that they form and, in a
sense, are its culture.
But my subject is science as part of
culture, and a scientific education as
a necessary part oí our cultural
education. Our society is divided
between the past and the future, and
it will not reach a balanced and
unified culture until the specialists
in one field learn to , share their
language with those in another. The
scientist has much to learn still, in
language and thought, from the
22
humane arts. But the scientist also
has a contribution to make to culture,
and humanism is doomed if it does
not learn the living language and the
springing thought of .science.
The syllabus of schools and univer¬
sities is always in movement from
vocation to culture. No doubt
reading was first taught as a strictly
useful skill ; certainly Latin and
Greek ;were first taught for clerical
use. Some subjects in the syllabus
remain vocational subjects: others
turn out to have a wider range of
uses. Men find that, whether they
are farmers or mechanics or bank
clerks, they, cannot do without them.
So in time these subjects cease to be
the prerogative of specialists and
become general needs.
From creches to reactors
Science was once the concern of
specialists, and now enters into
the life of everyone. The switch¬
board and the motorcar, the treat¬
ment of flour and of cigarette paper,
the building of a creche and of an
atomic pile are our daily concerns. We
simply cannot dissociate ourselves
from the hot-water system, the
airmail, frozen food and the linotype
machine. A nation where the
screwdriver and the fusebox are still
handled with suspicion is to-day a
backward nation.
When a society is penetrated by
technical skills and engines, the
decisions of State cannot be taken
out of the context of science. No
voter can advocate a policy on
myxomatosis without a general sense
both of the ecology and of the econo¬
mics of rabbits. And no Member of
Parliament or minister can make
intelligent judgments on such a
profound issue as the secrecy
which surrounds fundamental atomic
research until he is at home in the
tradition of science since Giordano
Bruno and Galileo. The fate of a
nation may hang on a error of
judgment here.
To - make science familiar as a
language, we must start in the
schools. General science courses
suffer from two handicaps: they
have to be planned as part of the
education of the scientist as well as
the non-scientist, and they are tied
to the rather dull resources of school
laboratories.
Fixing our minds more especially
on the non-scientist, I would propose
less mathematics than he does now
but more of a more practical kind.
The language of mathematics is still
taught as a dead language: there
should be more translation from
everyday facts into mathematics,
and back into the everyday. Statis¬
tical methods should be made part of
the education of everyone in schools
and universities, for only from sta¬
tistics can the non-scientist learn to
use averages and approximations.
My second proposal concerns the
teaching of physics and chemistry:
I think that the atomic picture
should be made central to both
subjects much earlier than at present.
The picture of the way atoms are
assembled can be made real and
exciting to the non-scientist because
it lends itself both to geometrical and
to statistical thinking.
My third plea is for more biological
teaching: there is a wealth of natural
material and natural interest in
plants and insects and in animal
processes which we allow to wither.
Biology offers us a path into scientific
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Photo Copyright A. Wassef
thinking by way of the pleasures of
collecting and of skill of hand.
Liking to collect, to observe, to draw,
to take apart and to put together
this is how many children and adults
of little other education find their
way into the arts, and could find it
into science.
Fourthly, I think we need to teach
science as an evolution of knowledge.
For the evolution of science goes to
the heart of the scientific method: it
shows at each step how the logical
deduction from what seems to lie
behind the known facts must be
confronted with experience. We
make an induction, we put the
deductions from it to test, and on the
results we base a new induction this
is the progress of science.
To these four general points I will
add a fifth: that every boy and girl,
every undergraduate, should do one
small piece of personal scientific
research. It can be as simple as the
pitch of an insect's wing beat, or the
composition of a rock, or growing a
crystal ; but I believe that this small
practical experience could change the
light in which non-scientists see the
long and unsung vigils of the solitary
research worker.
Science must become part of our
culture or we shall fail, not to train
scientists, but to preserve our culture.
It is certain that the educated man in
1984 will speak the language of
science. Will he be a specialist, a
scientist or technician with no other
interests, wno will run his feliowmen
by the mean and brutal processes of
efficiency of George Orwell's book?
Or will he be a humanist, who is at
home in the methods of science, but
who does not regard them as mere
tools to efficiency. The choice be¬
tween 1984 and an earthly paradise
does not depend on the scientists, but
on the people for whom they work.
And we are all the people for whom
science works.
H.G. Wells used to write stories in
which tall, elegant engineers admi¬
nistered With perfect justice a society
in which other people had nothing to
do except to be happy. But a world
run by specialists for the ignorant is,
and will be, a slave world. By
leaving science to be the vocation of
specialists, we are betraying demo¬
cracy, so that it must shrink to what
it became in the decline of Athens,
when a minority of educated men
(who had to be paid to make a quor¬
um) governed 300,000 slaves. There
is only one way to head off such
disaster, and that is to make the edu¬
cated man universal in 1984.'
This article is copyright and may not be
reproduced without prior permission.
. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN PICTURES
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
UNESCO
BLACK AND WHITE circle is formed by girls dancing and singing in school compound of village of Shewaki in Afghanistan. Village is centre of
important U.N.-Specialized Agencies community development project covering health, agriculture, crafts and literacy. UNESCO runs rural
education programme, trains boys in pottery and other manual work, has kindergarten section in village mosque, offers literacy classes for adults,
and at Women's Welfare Centre trains girls in knitting in morning, and in afternoon offers adult women classes in reading, writing and craft work.
UNATIONS
GRATIFYING RESULTS. A successful experiment in progres¬
sive education has been undertaken by a UNESCO mission in pri¬
mary schools of Quito, Ecuador. New teaching methods offer more
elasticity and initiative, are welcomed by teachers, and parents.
UNESCO
DON'T PUSH. Young recruits crowd into bookmobile near
barracks in a Colombian town. Bookmobile is part of extension
service of Medellin Public Library (set up in 1954 as a UNESCO
pilot project) which now has I 3,000 borrowers for 24,000 volumes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Papyri hunt ¡n Egypt
DESERT 'WASTE PAPER BASKETS'
REVEAL CITY LIFE 2,000 YEARS AGO
- . .. I¿=
~
t
Jr.
' s5
71 h tf
"N.
. ' - ¡r '
=>-{
;X( -"?:;; f^ riV^^j>Té-4
m-, -V¡TTfÍJU,7iB
\ ¿2%
.KV
in
TATTERED TEXT unearthed from the sands of Egypt is one of papyrus fragments from which the daily life of Greeks and Romans living in the
Valley of the Nile two thousand years ago can be reconstructed. This text, dating from the third century, contains illustrated verses on the Labours
of Hercules (Heracles). The only Labour illustrated on this fragment is the killing of the Nemean Lion and is from the beginning of a roll.
Photo from " The Oxyhrynchus Papyri " published by Egypt Exploration Society, London,
by E. G. Turner
Professor of Papyrology in the University of London
Supposing the contents of your waste paper basket
were by some miracle to be preserved for two
thousand years, generations of the future would have
the most exciting material from which to construct a
picture of your daily life.. Yet that is almost exactly
what has happened in some of the cities in which the
Greeks and Romans lived in Egypt two millenia ago.
The dry climate has preserved those everyday writings
and notices that are usually the first victims of time.
TRIUMPHAL ARCH erected by Romans in the city of Antinoe where
many ancient papyri have been discovered. Drawing, taken from
the book Description de l'Egypte, shows the state of the ruins in 1817.
British Museum
Turn over casually the pages of a catalogue of papers
from these cities and you find here an invitation "Theon,
Origens' son, invites you to his sister's wedding tomorrow,
9th Tybi, .2 o'clock," here a shopping reminder "to get
olive kernels," here again a duplicate of the form you put
in at the local town hall to register yourself and your
family in the census.
The material principally in use for writing two
thousand years ago was papyrus (it is the same actual
word as paper). It was manufactured by cutting the
stem of the papyrus plant into fine vertical sections with
a sharp knife, and laying these pithy ribbons across each
other in two layers placed at right angles. Skilful
ancient craftsmen turned out a smooth surface which
had the colour and expectation of life of good hand¬
made paper. For writing, a reed pen and carbon ink
(lamp-black and gum) were employed.
It is only in the last hundred years that these papyrus
texts have begun to re-emerge from the sands in -which
they have slept and to speak to us again. At first a few
were picked up by chance travellers and treated as
curiosities. Then the ancient sites began to be systemat¬
ically exploited for the "fertile earth" (potash salts)
they had accumulated, and papyri in their thousands
turned up. Finally came the idea of systematic explor¬
ation of some of the better preserved cities, especially
Oxyrhynchus, Antinoe, Hermopolis, by men such as Pétrie,
Borchardt, Breccia, Johnson, Boak, and above all, Grenfell
.and Hunt. The town to which the latter devoted the
greater part of their lives, where they excavated . and
published their finds in the handsome series known as
"The Oxyrhynchus Papyri" (the last few volumes of
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
which have been published with the support of Unesco),
is perhaps the best known of them all.
Its name Oxyrhynchus is derived from the sharp-nosed
fish held sacred by its inhabitants. Though four hundred
miles from the sea it was a place of importance. From
what can be seen on the ground today only a poor idea
of its appearance can be formed. "We can get some help
by inspecting the pictures of it and of Antinoe drawn by
Napoleon's team of surveyors a hundred and fifty years
ago, when the ruins were in better condition.
But we learn to know the place best of all from the
allusions contained in letters and papers found on the
spot. Its walls, pierced by five principal gates, were about
four miles round. The main streets were lined and
roofed with colonnades. In the centre of the town stood
an enormous temple of Sarapis; at its south-western side
stood the theatre, where 9,000 persons could be seated to
take part in public events as well as watch
dramatic performances.
One popular show of which we have what
appears to be the producer's script was the
mime of Charition. On the coast of some
barbarian country the pretty heroine is
about to be sacrificed to the moon by the
native king. In the very nick of time she
is rescued by her brother and a party of
Greeks who make her gaolers drunk. There
is a great deal of comic barbarian jabbering
and low gags by the clown, the whole punc¬
tuated by drums beating. At other times
the stage is given over to a Homeric reciter,
one of whom was paid a fee of 448 drachmas
(£20) for a recital. At other times again
The Unesco Courier
24, Thoth 4, 41bs of meat, 2 trotters, 1 tongue,
1 snout.
Thoth 6, tongue and chaps.
Thoth 11, 2 lbs of meat, 1 tongue, 2 kidneys."
Theophanes, a civil servant who went on an official
trip to Antioch has left us his laundry list: "Fine tunics 2,
self-colour 1, Dalmatics 2, self-colour 1, other wraps 2,
birruses 2, chlamys 1. Ditto linen: Tunics 4, Dalmatics 4,
mantles 3, face-cloth 1, -scarf 1, bath-towels 4, face towel
1, linen squares 4, 'Romans' 2, counterpane 1, dressing-
gown 1, bolsters 2, breeches 2, boots 1, felt slippers 1, rug-
cushion 1, small rug 1, carpet-bag, ground-sheet, small
pillow, etc." These were clothes intended to last for a
trip of some five months in summer time. Some of them
seem to have gone missing for there is a query mark
against them.
CHILDHOOD TREASURES of a
little boy named Theon were found
among ruins of houses at Oxyrhynchus.
They include a rag doll, a wooden
horse and spoon and a papyrus rosette.
British Museum.
the crowd is gathered for a religious festival
or to hear a new Roman emperor proclaimed.
Trades carried on and different classes of
inhabitants are reflected in the names given
to the various districts of the townthe
Shepherds' or Gooseherds' Quarter, the Cob¬
blers' Market Quarter, the Cretan or Jewish
Quarter. In the shade of the principal build¬
ings, the scribes and bankers set up their
booths and attended to customers in the
street, writing letters for the illiterate,
registering contracts, making out receipts
such as this one: "Quintus Zenas, son of
Quintus, greetings to Gaius Iulius Zosimus
I have received from you the ten drachmas
of Ptolemaic silver left to me by Gaius Mae¬
cenas Gratus, according to a will made in
Roman form. Year 1 of Tiberius Caesar Augustus."
The economic position of the inhabitants can be
measured by what they leave in their wills or what they
deposit with the pawnbroker. There is a very large class
of manual labourers who live in a single room only just
at subsistence level, and have a hard fight against hunger
and the tax gatherer. Above them come the educated
classes, some of them skilled craftsmen, but the majority
living on rents from their lands. They are Greek in
origins and sympathy, like the very few really rich per¬
sons in their midst who in fact come from Alexandria.
AÍ a however. sufficiency rather than ostentation
is the key-note of this community: a stone-built house
with an enclosed courtyard and a few rooms opening out
of it for entertaining, half a dozen slaves, a few books
an adequate but not sumptuous table. Here is a meat
bill for one such household:
Among his miscellaneous papers Theophanes kept a few
sheets that stimulated a father's pridethe letters sent to
him by his schoolboy sons. They are beautifully written
and spelled, and of impeccable sentiments, no doubt put
together under a tutor's eye. So other schoolboys write
formally to their parents, occasionally relaxing with a
postscript: "Please feed my pigeons."
Some fathers however failed to gain such respect from
their children. Here is how little Theon writes to his
father: "That was a fine thing not to take me with you to
town. If you won't take me with you to Alexandria, I
won't write you a letter, I won't speak to you, I won't
talk to you. And if you go to Alexandria, I won't ever
take your hand or ever greet you again. That's what
happens if you don't take me with you... In
future send for me, please do. If you don't
send I won't eat, I won't drink, so there." (Cont'd on
For all his childish tantrum, little Theon next page)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
L
ILArt^jííS^^^
LEGACY RECEIPT reads :
"Quintus Zenas, son of Quintus,
greetings to Gaius lulius Zosi-
mus. I have received from you
ten drachmas of Ptolemaic silver
left to me by Gaius Maecenas
Gratus, . according to a will
made in Roman form..."
British Museum
LAUNDRY LIST of Theo¬
phanes, a civil servant who
took with him on an official
mission to Antioch sufficient
clothes to last for five
months in summer time. Some
items, with query marks against
them, seem to have gone astray.
Courtesy of John Rylands Library,
Manchester
m f
r J'JÍ'ci
l_J* - - - -
writes a long letter. He has probably already put away
his toysthe rag-doll, the wooden horse, that were
found among the remains of the housesand gone to
school. And schooling is a serious business. First come
exercises in writing : the letters of the alphabet, then
maxims such as "Letters are the foundation of life" or
"Sea, fire and woman are evils three," then exercises in
grammar. Next follows reading of the poets, especially
of Homer the favourite. So many copies of Homer have
been found in Oxyrhynchus that there was certainly one
for each house.
Most often the lesson would have consisted in learning
by heart, but occasionally the homework had to be
prepared in writing and has survived. At a later stage,
when the modern undergraduate writes essays, the pupil
is asked to write speeches on imaginary situations. A list
of subjects includes such topics as this: "'Write a speech
accusing Euripides of impiety for representing Heracles
turning mad on the stage."
The great event in a young man's life is the time he
spends among the ephebes, the adolescents' section of the
gymnasium. The gymnasium itself was more than a
centre for physical exercise. It formed a kind of social
club for all the Greeks in town, and had its junior and
senior sections. The young were offered more than
physical instruction. Of course they developed their
bodies and ran races (in which a spectator might invoke
magical aid for a favoured competitor), but they compet¬
ed in cultural events as well. A list recently discovered
gives the names of the winners in the town games over a
period of thirty years in three events playing the
trumpet, acting as herald, and in poetry. They were well
worth winning, for the four top boys every year were
given exemption from taxes.
For the leaders of society their life's work is government
service and the conduct of municipal affairs in their own
town. It is a career that will require them to dip freely
into their pockets on behalf of their fellow citizens as well
as give freely of their time. There will be oil and fuel to
supply free for use in the gymnasium, the market to be
inspected, tax collection to-be supervised and any defi¬
ciencies made good, the sessions of the local council to be
attended. And very stormy some of these meetings
appear from their minutes, especially when it is a matter
of election to one of the more onerous offices.
Other young men are bound apprentices to learn a trade
such as weaving, or the craft of writing. A line of Virgil
written out again and again in a beautiful handwriting is
probably the work of one of the latter. Such trainees live
in their master's house, are fed and clothed by him, and
get 20 days holiday a year. Other persons find it ne¬
cessary to seek a livelihood away from home. To join
the army is one resource, and may offer a snug berth.
"I give thanks to Sarapis and Good Fortune that while
all are sweating breaking stones all day long, I swagger
about as a principalis and do nothing" is how one of
them writes home from the Arabian desert. Another has
reached Italy with the great convoy of grain ships that
leaves Egypt regularly for Rome and sends back word:
"We had a slow trip but not a bad one, and I felt none
of the ill-effects that often occur, especially on a first
crossing."
It is, however, not only in their joys but their sorrows
too that we can share. A friend writes to comfort one
whose son has died young: "The gods are my witness that
when I heard of my master, our son, I was as distressed
and mourned as if he were my own child yes, for he was
winsome. When I was eager to rush to you, Pinoution
held me back, saying that you, my lord Apollonianus, had
instructed him I was not to come up since you were gone
to the Arsinoite nome. But bear it nobly. This, too, is
what the gods have in store."
Two thousand years are annihilated by the poignancy
of this distress.
el
^ ¿¿ft*
WEDDING INVITATION
like other missives was written
on papyrus by the people of
ancient Oxyrhynchus using a
reed pen and carbon ink (lamp¬
black and gum) for ink. This
particular invitation was sent
by the bride-to-be's brother.
Courtesy Egypt Exploration Society
SHARP-NOSED FISH is the
Oxyrhynchus a member of the
mormyr family of fishes which
vary greatly in size and shape,
and are found in the fresh wa¬
ters of Africa. It was regarded
as a sacred fish and city of Oxy¬
rhynchus was named after it.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
London's own language
by David Gunstoft
Visitors to London cannot move about the capital for
long without hearing odd words spoken by the natives
that seem to have no apparent meaning. If they mix
to any degree with down-to-earth Cockneys, be they bus-
conductors, taxi-drivers, street tradesmen, porters or shoe-shine
boys, or, more especially, overhear these colourful types
talking among themselves, they will quickly realize that, quite
apart from his delicious accent, your true Londoner has a
special language of his own.
And so he has, for Cockney rhyming slang, always
respectable and currently spoken by upwards of two million
Londoners in the Metropolis, and known, at least in part, by
a great many Englishmen, is indeed London's own language.
Grasp the principle behind this initially incoherent slang it
is not a form of jargon, as we shall see later and you see the
comedy and the colour in it. As is well-known throughout
the world, the . typical Cockney has many sparrow-like
qualities; he is ever perky and chirpy, and whatever the
weather, whatever difficulties and hardships he may be
suffering, he manages to keep a cheerful outlook on life, an
outlook that is always apparent in his manner, his chuckle, his
bearing and his special slang.
The Cockney sense of hu¬
mour is strange but lively and
has a touch of philosophy
about it, too. A good deal of
it is based on simple word¬
play, or rather on sound-play,
which explains why rhyming
slang achieves its best effect
when spoken, not read, which
it rarely is anyway. The
Cockney takes an insensate
delight in talking and when
talking, in going the longest
possible way round to get to
his usually comic point.
That, in essence, is the
secret of rhyming slang. First
of all, any common word in
everyday use is replaced by
another word, or more usually
a phrase of two, three or four
words, which rhyme with it, not always accurately, perhaps,
but nearly always obviously, in speech. Thus the simple word
stairs becomes apples and pears. To say stairs does not appeal
to the Cockney; he must invent something similar and
recognizable (by means of the rhyme) and say that instead!
So, apples and pears, a smooth-flowing sequence of words, it
becomes.
But that is too easy, and not elaborate enough. Therefore
the first word of the substitute phrase is generally used,
just apples, as short for apples and pears. Thus to run up the
apples means to run up the stairs! True rhyming slang
consists of an endless series of these abbreviations, which tend
to make confusion doubly confused to the uninitiated. For
although the rhymes are sometimes guessable, the shortened
forms often bear no possible resemblance to their real
meanings. For instance, rats to a Cockney means dice, since
rats is the accepted abbreviation for the common, paired
phrase rats and mice, in which the key rhyme is obvious.
This means that much conversation where rhyming slang is
used freely is seemingly inane, and quite unintelligible to the
outsider. You hear people saying things like "'As it began to
Andy Cain and I had no Quaker, I took the baa lamb to the
Gates of Rome", or "'The trouble put our cherry in the
dolly", for the following simple statements: "'As it began to
rain and I had no coat (Quaker oat, a proprietary article long
known), I took the tram home", and "The wife (trouble and
strife) put our dog (cherry hog) in trie garden (Dolly Varden)."
At first sight, it seems that any rhyming word has been
picked at random, but actually they are all words or phrases
that come readily to the lips of a Londoner, not necessarily the
Londoner of today, for this slang goes back a century at least
Trouble and strife = wife
House to let = bet
Iron Duke = fluke
Gertie Gitana = banana
Brass tacks = facts
and at any rate in part probably much more. A watch is a
bottle of Scotch, and a shop a lollipop. Morning is Gipsy's
warning, bet is house to let. But here and there a shrewd and
not always very oblique humour creeps into the rhyme.
We have already seen trouble-and-strife for wife: there arc
God-ferbids for kids, gay and frisky is whisky, plates of meat
are feet. Then there is Mother Hubbard for cupboard, oily
rag for fag, bull, and cow for row (in the sense of a noisy
quarrel), didn't oughter for water, rat and mouse for house,
and a great many more in which the comic side of the idea
is exploited to the full.
In many ways the constant use of only the abbreviated
phrases makes rhyming slang even more bizarre than it would
otherwise be, and it is remarkable how the true rhyming slang
'"professor" uses nothing but the first, non-rhyming word, and
how his hearers always follow him with ease. He will call
his daughter bricks, from bricks and mortar (note how the
chosen rhymes are often more Cockney in accent than true
rhymes), refer to gin as needle, from needle and pin, and pat
a child on the once, for once a week (cheek).
But you cannot listen to much rhyming slang without
realizing that London was its birthplace and is still its true
home. Actual place-names
in the London area occur
time and again. Hampstead,
short for Hampstead Heath,
is widely used for teeth:
St. Martin's le Grand is hand;
Hackney Marsh is glass;
Colney Hatch is match; Chalk
Farm is arm, and Peckham
Rye more often just Peck-
ham is the generally ac¬
cepted term for a tie.
No one knows for certain
just how all this began, but
its origins go back to the
murky history of the London
underworld probably 150 or
more years ago. Many of
the additions are dated by
reference to persons or in¬
cidents of long ago, like Iron
Duke for fluke, Gertie Gitana (a famous music-hall star of
long ago) for banana.
This much is certain: rhyming slang as used today is
eminently respectable and is often employed by persons of
education when they lapse into the vernacular "'What's the
bird lime (time)?" but it was originally the cant spoken in
thieves' kitchens and the underworld generally. Footpads,
pickpockets, burglars, tricksters, felons and the rest used, and
presumably invented it, as part of their calling, and it was some
time before odd words here and there began to leak out into
the ordinary world, and even longer before it came into general
use by the citizens of London, and to a lesser extent to English
people everywhere.
From thieves' cant it has been promoted to a seriously-used
but semi-humorous slang, many examples of which have found
their way into English vernacular of an everyday kind. For
instance, the saying to get down to brass tacks is really rhyming
slang, for brass tacks are facts. Loaf (of bread) for head
("Use your loaf!") is used pretty widely a good many miles
from London, while Joanna for piano is almost universal slang.
Although sovereigns as gold coins are unknown in Britain
today, pounds are still referred to as Jimmy O' Goblins.
An interesting fact about rhyming slang is that it is not
generally found outside Great Britain, although odd expres¬
sions and words are commonly used outside London and much
of it is well known in the Army and both the Royal and
Merchant Navies, yet it has spread to parts of Australia and is
firmly established there. Doubtless it was introduced there
long ago by Cockney seamen and emigrants, just as Cockney
volunteers introduced it to the Armed Services.
r~ , , . ,, ^ (Cont'd on
From Australia it spread by sea to San Fran- paee 33)
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
YUGOSLAV MASTERPIECES
in the palm of your hand
Hardly any part of Europe can show a variety in art traditions to compare with that of Yugo¬
slavia. This land has not only been a meeting ground of East and West for centuries but also a
great cross-roads at which many antique civilizations flourished Byzantine, Romanesque, Gothic,
Baroque, Mohammedan. Ruins of Roman aqueducts rise along the Adriatic coast not .far from
the monumental walls of the palace of Diocletian in the heart of Split. Relics of Greek and other -
antique architecture and sculpture are being brought to light. Montenegro and Macedonia in the
south are treasure houses of ancient Serb and Macedonian cultures. In the Macedonian moun¬
tains are the famous medieval monasteries, sepulchres of medieval Serbian kings with their
frescoes which bridge an important gap in the history of painting from the 6th to the 13th
century. (See unesco courier N° 11, 1954.) The sculpture, architecture and painting on these
pages reveal a few of the masterpieces of Yugoslav art from the 9th century onward which the
Yugoslav Government has chosen as the designs for a series of twelve new stamps issued on March
26, to illustrate the development of Yugoslav art through the centuries.
Croat King
ibjâet
This relief portrays a Croat king (seat¬
ed on throne) from an early period
probably 10th century. Next to the king
is his counsellor, and at their feet a
bearded figure, possibly a vanquished
prince. Relief is found on stone slab in
former Temple of Jupiter, later converted
Christian baptistery, at palace of
Diocletian in Split. Split arose around
the great palace which Roman emperor
Diocletian built there in 302 A.D. Less
than five miles from Split, at Salona,
excavations have uncovered important
architectural remains and many prehis¬
toric objects now housed in Split Museum.
Pre-dates Giotto
FftFSK* lMp*0(
m
m
T
Sc
si
V
no
ra
cc
pe
PC
in
ba
le
A
W(
m
of
lis group of figures from a fresco
jpocani monastery in Serbia is expr
ye of grief at the death of the H
rgin. The first frescoes at - the n
stery were executed about 1265, a
nk among the finest and most valua
mpositions of European painting of t
riod. They pre-date Giotto and
rtrayal of human emotions and suff
5. Frescoes were painted against a golc
ckground which peeled off with tin
iving an intriguing under-tint behii
comparison of these frescoes with t
3rks of Greek origin shows how the e
:nts borrowed from Byzantium we
ten enriched among the Serbian artis
at
es-
3ly
Ki¬
nd
Die
lis
his
er¬
en
ie,
id.
he
le¬
re
ts.
Phantasy in Stone
These two female figures, bearers of the
sacred oil, chrism, are part of the Ro¬
manesque portal of the cathedral of Tro-
gir, on the Adriatic coast, considered
the loveliest anywhere in Yugoslavia. Its
decorations are symbolical representations
of Sin personified by the nude figures
of Adam and Eve while a series of other
figures from the life and torment of
Christ speak of Redemption. Executed
in 1240 by the master sculptor Radovan,
this portal depicts Christian legend, the
history of the years and the months,
plants and animals mingled in a phan¬
tasy in stone with ivory-like splendour.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Mysterious Bogomils
Peace in Bronze
This equestrian statue in bronze is the
work . of one of the outstanding living
sculptors of Yugoslavia, Antun Augus-
tincic, born in Croatia. Symbolizing
peace, it was a Yugoslav gift to the U.N.,
now stands in gardens of U.N. building
in New York. (See UNESCO COURIER
No 10, 1955; U.S. edition Dec. 1955.)
THE ILLUSTRATIONS ON
THESE AND THE FOLLOWING
PAGES ARE TAKEN FROM
THE ORIGINAL ENGRAVINGS
FOR THE SERIES OF 12
STAMPS ON YUGOSLAV ART.
THE STAMPS ARE PRINTED
WITH SERRATED EDGES.
This huge block of stone represents an art which has no parallel in either East or West.
It is a massive tombstone placed over, a grave by a sect of heretics (called Bogomils) who
challenged the Roman . and Eastern Orthodox churches in the 13th and 14th centuries.
Over 30,000 Bogomil -tombstones have been found in Bosnia and Herzegovina, others in
Serbia and Macedonia.' Often grouped in enormous cemeteries in remote forests or mountain
areas, they are decorated with scenes from the hunt or dance and with foliage or geometrical
figures. Their meaning is still obscure. Formidable figure, here, may symbolize a feudal
lord of yore, his raised arm suggesting his sway over lands and people, the bow and arrow
his warrior's prowess, the circle next to his hand, the moon or sun. But no one is sure.
Church or Castle?
The ancient church of St. Donat at Zadar (formerly Zara) on the Adriatic coast, resembles a castle
with its narrow slit-windows and forbidding high walls. Dating from the ninth century, and now
containing an archaeological museum, the church was built out 'of the remains of a Roman temple.
It is perhaps the most important Adriatic architectural monument of the pre-Romanesque epoch in
Yugoslavia. Its style reflects Byzantine and Ravenna influences. Art historians have compared
this church to the royal chapels of Charlemagne but St. Donat's'is simpler of line and more rustic.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
YUGOSLAV MASTERPIECES (Cont'd)
A Saint's
Story *
Genius
Ridiculed
rvj - SlBF.NIk
The Montenegro city of Kotor in southern Yugoslavia has been
compared to "a Venice without canals and a Verona without its
river Adige." Hemmed in on all sides by rugged mountains, it
is one of the most picturesque ports on the Adriatic. Here are
to be found some of the great masterpieces of Romanesque-
Gothic style sculpture executed in the 14th and 15th centuries.
Above, part of frieze from ciborium in Kotor cathedral. Reliefs
depict scenes from life of St. Tryphon, patron saint of the city,
tell of his healing the sick, expelling evil spirits, converting ' the
heathens,, and his suffering and dying for his faith. The harmo¬
nious restraint and light and shade effects are remarkable.
The great cathedral built at Sibenik on the Croatian coast
north of Split, is testimony to the great genius of Juraj Dalmatinac
(also called Matejavic). When Dalmatinac built it in 1431, foreign
experts ridiculed the cupola he set on a square tower. And
when he combined the ceiling of the nave with the roof built of
great blocks of stone, they said it would collapse under its own
weight. The section where the heads pictured above occur took
the great architect and sculptor 30 years to complete. A belt of
heads of sailors, ships' captains, citizens and peasants girding the
body of the cathedral are all Dalmatinác's work. Each head is
striking for its human expression, its gentleness or suffering.
Self Portrait Serbia's Golden Age Pulpit Saint
At té. **
ké
The monastery of Studenica provides a
striking example of the golden age of
Serbian architecture and sculpture.
Here we see a part of the arch and a
griffin from the western portal of the
church of the Holy Virgin in the mo¬
nastery. Built by the Serbian ruler
Steven Nemanja between 1190 and 1196,
the church combines Romanesque and
Byzantine elements. Important frescoes
adorn the interior.
1(11 R \ 1/ CR.KVL U BÉÍ.CU
70'*<; ,
norm PORTAL CRKVE U STUDENICT
Jfc.*T
Rihard Jakopic is considered one of the
outstanding representatives of modern
Slovene impressionist painting. Before
his death during the last war, he de¬
veloped his school of painting with a
group of artists at Skofja Loka, near
Ljubljana. This 100 dinar stamp repro¬
duces one of his self portraits.
Yugoslav churches in the middle of the
18th century abounded in a host of co¬
loured or gilt baroque figures. Many
are found on church pulpits such as
the siint shown here. The work of an
unknown artist, it adorns the church of
Maria Snjezna at Belec in the northern
part of Yugoslavia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Letters to the Editor...
Sir,
I would like to contact a primary
school teacher interested in an exchange
of correspondence between teachers and
children. I have a class of 9-year-old
boys and girls who would like to
correspond with children in their own age
group. Apart from promoting a better
understanding of their neighbours from
overseas it will also give them glimpses
into the life and customs of the people
and the geography of the country; features
which are sadly glossed over in many of
our textbooks. I would like to add my
congratulations on the success with which
The Unesco Courier is meeting in many
parts of the world.
Robert Buchan.
C/o Kaiti School,
Gisborne,
New Zealand.
Sir,
The publication in The Unesco Courier
of a letter I wrote produced the following
results: From the United States I received
an Esperanto textbook; letters reached me
from Alaska; my letter was reproduced in
French in "Franca Esperantisto," and I '
also received letters from French Esperan-
tists. This spontaneous "test" demonstrates
the international readership of your maga¬
zine and the widespread links of Esperanto.
Roubaix, France. L. GHoteaux.
Sir,
This is to convey our appreciation of the
January 1956 (European : N°. 11, 1955)
issue of The Unesco Courier. You have
done splendidly a job which long needed
doing and we hope that fairly frequently
you will find it possible to publish articles
on women's activities and economic advan¬
cement, as well as on the increasing oppor¬
tunities for education and training in tech¬
nical skills ; and also as soon as you think
the timing right, that you will have other
complete issues on the changing outlook
for women, i
Nina B'rodrick Price.
Chairman,
New York City Committee,
National Woman's Party.
Sir,
In issue N° 11, 1955 (U.S. - January
1956) of The Unesco Courier, you pub¬
lished a map entitled "1955 : No Vote
for Women in 15 countries" in which Ni¬
caragua was listed among "15 countries
where women have no political rights."
I should like to inform you that under a
law of April 20, 1955, the women of Ni¬
caragua were given the right to 'vote in
public elections.
Guillermo Sevilla Sacasa.
Ambassador of Nicaragua,
Washington, D.C, U.S.A.
Sir,
I am particularly aware of the effort of
intellectual integrity which contributors to
The Unesco Courier bring to each issue.
As an African and as a missionary in this
part of the world, I was particularly inter¬
ested in issue N° 11, 1955 (U.S. - January
1956). The status of women in Africa has
always been a vitally interesting question for
me, and that is why I cannot help being
surprised (pleasantly so) at the article
written by Alfred Metraux ("Women in
Primitive Society Exploding Some False
Notions.") I was astonished to find that
the author was able to look beyond the
superficial appearance of "primitive" insti¬
tutions and considered them in such a way
as to explain their full significance. For
this he should be thanked.
Father Raymond Tchidimbo.
Cours "Rene Caille", Kankan,
French West Africa.
Sir,
By a stroke of good luck I came across
the December 1954 issue of The Unesco
Courier (U.S. - March 1955). The series
of articles dealing with the atom and mo¬
dern chemistry presents the subject so
clearly and interestingly that it was easily
assimilated by one of my nieces who, until
then, had followed chemistry lessons with
dislike or indifference. What my explana¬
tions had been unable to arouse was achiev¬
ed by your magazine the interest, to the
point of enthusiasm, of this schoolgirl was
greatly stimulated.
Ch. Wolff.
Strasbourg (Bas-Iiliin),
France.
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier for January
1956 (U.S. - March) in the article "The
Uprooted," James Douglas writes : "Falling
within this class are the 11 million refugees
who have arrived in Western Germany (and
who are at present arriving at the rate of
approximately 1,000 a day...") I write to
enquire if these two figures are correct.
They seem extraordinary to me especially
as the percentage of the world total given
as 40 million.
Harry Crjcr.
Bristol, England.
Editor's Note. The figures are correct.
London's own language
(Cont'd from p. 29)
cisco and parts of the Pacific coast of U.S.A. Here, however,
it has largely dropped back into the underworld, and is still in
use among the criminal fringe there to this day. This degene¬
ration is interesting, since it shows that rhyming slang must have
some particular attraction for those whose ways are not all that
they might be!
There is, as yet, no complete and authoritative dictionary of
this slang, which is a serious sociological and etymological lack.
The scope for such a work of reference is obvious, and it would
be a volume of unique value. One or two small collections of the
commoner terms have been made, but they make no pretence to
completeness, and contain glaring errors. Such a dictionary ought
to be compiled, before some of the less-used die out.
When a Londoner calls his glass a Khyber pass, he is (probably
quite unconsciously) commemorating an otherwise long-forgotten
British Army defeat in Afghanistan in 1842! Such strange facts
ought not to be lost to posterity. When he calls the modern
police Flying Squad the Sweeney Todd, he is referring to the 1829
melodrama of that name about the Demon Barber of Fleet
Street, who shaved his clients too closely and disposed of their
bodies to an old woman who sold cooked meat pies !
Fancy calling your sister skin-and-blister, or your son your Bath
bun! Cherry ripe has nothing to do with fruit or the old cries of
London Town, but is a pipe. You might, perhaps, be justified in
calling your lodger artful dodger if he decided to half-inch (pinch,
steal) your tit-fer, (tit-fer-tat, hat), but that would be better than if
he took your rounds round the houses, trousers.
As might be expected, food and drink provide many an amusing
example of Cockney humour and ingenuity. Some bowl my hoop
would be a recognizable start to a good Jim Skinner, especially
if it were described on the me and you (menu) and a nice Joe
Blake is clear enough, but you might fight shy of a clothes peg,
although it would be merely an egg. A piece of stand at ease
would turn out to be cheese, nicer with some Harvey Nichol to
go with it, so long as it were accompanied by a slice of Uncle
Fred well spread with stammer and stutter !
As for drinks, pig's ear is the Englishman's usual choice, but
there is generally a choice of needle and pin, gay and frisky, finger
and thumb, Rosy Lee, Jack the Dandy, or just plain didn't oughter,
sometimes known as rat-catcher's daughter! Even a single drink
would be a tumble down the sink, but that would not make you
elephant's trunk. If it did, a policeman, originally a copper and
now successfully disguised as a grasshopper, might take you away
to lock you up for the night in a flowery dell. To pay the fine
you would need some bees and honey, and it would have to be
ready sausage and mash, which would be a nuisance if all you
had was a Lord of the Manor (tanner, sixpence) although even
half an Oxford (Oxford scholar, dollar) would probably not be
enough.
Some of the slang words are startling, like a butcher's hook,
which merely means a look, and a dig in the grave, which is what
men do every morning with some Cape of Good Hope and a
razor. If someone said he had something in his steak-and-kidney
pie, you would have to look in his eye, not in the pantry. Left
in the lurch, meaning church, and Westminster (Abbey) for
shabby, bring you back once again to the Cockney's forthright
type of fun.
There is no sign yet that this grotesque yet irresistible slang is
dying out at all, and long may it remain. Visitors to Britain
may start off by being confused and startled by it, but if they
listen carefully, and get the hang of it, they will end by being
fascinated by it. Fortunately, it is not very hard on one's down
the drains!
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
E,_JjNGLISH WITHOUT
TEARS : The unesco courier is
now an official language teaching
aid for students in Swedish and
Dutch schools. In Sweden, secon¬
dary students taking their matricul¬
ation examination this year will be
asked, as part of their English
language paper, to write an essay on
themes selected from recent unesco
courier issues. In Holland, where
subscriptions to the magazine
increased nearly threefold last year,
secondary schools use it as reading
material for English and French
lessons.
MOBILE MICROFILMERS :
Unesco has established a mobile
unit to aid its member states in
making microfilm copies of rare
documents and other library
materials and archives. The unit,
in charge of a Spanish expert,
is due to begin work shortly in
Paraguay and will later move to
other countries in Latin and
Central America.
810,000 PAINTING AWARD:
An award of $10,000 to be offered
every two years for the best contem¬
porary painting in the world is
announced by the Solomon R. Gug¬
genheim Foundation of New York.
The winning painting will be select¬
ed by an international jury set up
according to suggestions from three
international organizations closely
linked with unesco the Interna¬
tional Council of Museums, the
International Association of Plastic
Arts and the International Associa¬
tion of Art Critics. Prizes of
81,000 each will be awarded for the
best works in each of the 16 coun¬
tries where the three organizations
have national sections.
NOVAJOJ FROM UNESCO :
Editors of some 150 magazines,
reviews and information bulle¬
tins published in Esperanto in
all parts of the world are now
receiving a special information
bulletin of unesco news in Es¬
peranto, entitled "unesco nova-
joj". Published by the Informa¬
tion Department of the Uni¬
versal Esperanto Association,
which has consultative arrange¬
ments with Unesco, the bulletin
includes resumes from The
unesco courier, and other
UNESCO publications.
s,»OIL SLEUTH : Peru's 1,300-
mile -long coastal desert is to
be surveyed and its soils mapped
by a young Danish scientist to dis¬
cover regions where irrigation
through canals or wells would offer
the best chances of growing profit¬
able crops. The scientist, Prof.
Mogens Loie, will work at the Arid
Zone Research Institute, just estab¬
lished by the Peruvian Govern¬
ment and unesco. His mission is
part of UNESCO's world programme
of technical assistance for economic
development.
THERE:
Mexico recently became the fifth
country to ratify a Convention
creating an International Com¬
putation Centre in Rome. The
centre will carry out scientific
research, train specialists in this
new field and do complicated
computation work for members.
The Convention, drawn up with
. UNESCO's help, has been signed
but not yet ratified by seven
other countries. It will come
into force when ratified by ten
states.
lliNGINEERS FOR KOREA:
Nearly 400 young Korean engineers
recently graduated from Pusan
Technical High School after com¬
pleting training in workshops and
laboratories equipped by the u. n.
Korean Reconstruction Agency,
which provided 51,600,000 for
construction materials, shop machi¬
nery, equipment and supplies to re¬
establish technical high schools,
where students can learn the skills
so badly needed in Korea's indus¬
tries.
LESSONS IN THE DARK :
Some Paris schoolchildren are
now learning English in the
dark. Twice a month they visit
the cinema to see an English or
American film chosen for its
literary, cultural or historical
value. Films are discussed before¬
hand and afterwards children
are asked to write about them,
prizes being given for the best
essays. The cinema classes were
instituted by the Ciné-Club of
Language Teachers in the Paris
area.
B.	»OOKS IN VERNACU¬
LAR : Reading material published
in African vernacular languages for
literacy campaigns and new literates
will soon be speeding to new re¬
gions of Africa as a result of an
expanded programme of operations
launched by the Gold Coast Ver¬
nacular Literature Bureau. Unesco
is working closely with the Bureau,
set up in 1952, and has just sent an
American children's book publisher,
Edwin L. Read Jr. to be the Bureau's
new head. An American text-book
writer, Miss Ella Griffin, with long
years of experience in preparing
books for new literates is also with
the Bureau on a unesco mission.
GOOD FROM GREETINGS :
A record number of greetings
cards 4,650,000 were sold for
the U.N. Children's Fund
(unicef) in 1955, bringing the
Organization a net profit of
$226,913 % more than the
previous year. Profits from one
box of ten cards can provide
one week's supply of milk for
50 children, or enough vaccine
to protect them from tubercu¬
losis. This year, unicef hopes
to reach a target of 5,500,000
cards sold.
II OSTS OF WORKERS :
Nearly 150 Austrian workers will
visit Sweden, Denmark, the Nether¬
lands and Belgium during the next
few months on UNESCO-sponsored
study tours. Other Austrian workers
will play host this year to Greek
trade unionists, Norwegian forestry
workers, co - operative employees
from the Netherlands and Sweden,
French metalworkers and Dutch air
transport employees. Altogether
this year, 1,200 workers from
SURGERY REMOVES ST. SOPHIA'S SCARS
The Cathedral of St. Sophia in Novgorod about I 00 miles south of
Leningradis a remarkable example of early Russian architecture
dating from the middle of the eleventh century. As these photos
show, it was badly damaged during the Second World War, but has
now been completely restored. Pre-restoration research work
revealed many interesting facts about its construction, several
unknown frescoes being discovered as well as traces of previous
restoration. Apart from reconstruction work proper, arches and
vaults have been strengthened and restored to their former beauty.
When possible, walls have been rebuilt with the original materials.
16 countries will take . part in
unesco study tours, which give them
a chance to meet other men and
women doing similar jobs in other
countries. Since tours began in
1952, 4,370 workers have benefited
from them.
TOP TRANSLATORS :
Germany, France, Poland, Italy,
Israel and Japan were the lead¬
ing countries for the number of
translations published in 1954
according to the seventh volume
of "Index Translationum" , an
international bibliography of.
translations, recently published
by unesco. It lists 21,676 trans¬
lations published in 48 countries
during 1954, as compared with
18,139 in 47 countries during
1953. Most widely translated
book of 1954 was the Bible, but,
as in previous years, the writings
of Marx, Engels, Lenin and
Stalin follow in quantity of
translations. Old favourites such
as the fairy tales of Grimm and
Anderson and the Arabian
Nights were translated into more
than 15 languages in 1954.
Jl HE PLAY'S THE THING :
One of the oldest and most popular
of hobbies in Britain a country
where hobbies are pursued perhaps
more assiduously then in any other
is amateur drama. It has been a
part of English cultural life since
early medieval times. Today the
amateur theatre movement is strong-
;r than ever and some 500,000
people (about one in every hundred
Britons) take active parts in perfor¬
mances as actors, producers, scene-
painters and in other creative
occupations.
o
z
<
13
Z
o£
O
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Corning next month
An extra-special issue:
BUDDHIST
ART
'Unesco Courier' binders
now available
. In response to widespread demand we now offer subscribers
special binders for The UNESCO COURIER. These are hand¬
somely produced in half-cloth with the spine in an attractive
blue, and the title and UNESCO colophon embossed in gold.
Each binder will hold 12 issues. Copies can be bound easily
at home, and once in place are held securely. Issues can be
removed at will. A series of stick-on gold embossed labels will
accompany each order thus enabling readers to use binders for
any year desired.
PRICE : S2.50, 12/6, French fr. 600, Belgian fr. 100. Price
includes special packaging and postage. Orders can be placed
in other currencies through your local UNESCO agent.
HOW TO ORDER BINDER
1. Remittances should be sent to UNESCO agent in your
country, or direct to UNESCO (DPV), 19, avenue Kléber,
Paris, 1 6", France. (For payments in French francs: CCP
12598.48 Librairie Unesco, 19, avenue Kléber, Paris, 16*.)
2. Remittances must be accompanied by wrapper of latest
issue of UNESCO COURIER received. For CCP orders
wrapper should be addressed separately.
3. Supplies are limited. Offer is reserved for subscribers only.
If you are not a subscriber, your subscription must accom¬
pany order for binders.
* 2,500 years of art and
culture
* Buddha's influence on the
thought of Asia
Don't miss this issue. Subscribe today
to the UNESCO COURIER
Annual subscription rate 8/-, $2,50 or
400 French francs
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's National distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
AUSTRIA. Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27
Graben, Vienna I.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15, rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090, Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. M.E. Constantinides, P.O.
Box 473, Nicosia.
DENMARK. E¡nar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6, Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19, Avenue Kleber, Paris, 16".
CCP. 12598-48, Unesco Bookshop,
Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon, "
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bom¬
bay I; I 7, Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta
13. 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co..
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road, P.O. Box 4101, Tel-
Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni. Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
AMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6, Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco. Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box I 35, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26, Kings-
way, Valletta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni-
jhoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100, Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60, The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35, The Mall, Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo.P.O. Box
620, Manila.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5,
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2, rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 551-3, Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London. S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center; 475, Fifth Avenue, New.York,
17, N.Y,
Columbia University Press, 2960, Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. (except
periodicals).
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE PRINCE AND THE BEGGAR.- Yugoslavia's Art Through
the Centuries " is the title of a series of new postage stamps issued
by the Yugoslav postal administration to illustrate the striking
monuments of the past which abound in that country. Here, a
Renaissance painter, Nikola Bozidarevic has depicted St. Martin
as a handsome young prince on a white charger, sharing his
cloak with the beggar. The painting, executed in I 439, is a trip¬
tych panel in the Dance Church at Dubrovnik. (See page 30)
]]>
</page>
</document>
