<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078161eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
9
W O R LD
700,000,000
ILLITERATES:
TWO PERSONS
OUT OF FIVE
MARCH
19 5 8
(I Ith year)
Price: I /-stg. (U. K.)
30 cents (U. S.)
5 0 francs (France)
L_ 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
, FIRST-AID' FOR
G UATEMALA' S
COLONIAL ART
Shady cloisters of an ancient Capucine convent in Antigua, Guatemala, are being
used as a "casualty clearing station" for damaged and time-worn paintings due for
restoration in the "picture hospital" of Guatemala City. Propped against massive
pillars and lying on trestles, Colonial period paintings are being selected for treatment
by team of Guatemalan artists supervised by one of the world's leading picture
restorers, Helmut Ruhemann, (figure in background, on right). Ruhemann was
sent to Guatemala by Unesco to survey Colonial paintings, to start a restoration
programme and to plan training courses for Guatemalan restorers. (See page 32)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
îer
MARCH 1958
NTH YEAR
No. 3
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 IS WORLD ILLITERACY ON THE INCREASE?
By Bangnee A. Liu
9 WHAT IS AN 'ILLITERATE'?
10 HISTORY'S LARGEST LITERACY CAMPAIGN
By Serafima Liubimova
13 AN ILLITERATE IN PARIS
By Marguerite Duras
14 MOROCCO'S ROYAL CALL TO THE CLASSROOM
16 ILLITERACY AND NATIONAL INCOME
18 MAP OF WORLD ILLITERACY
20 THE MAN WHO TAUGHT HIS NATION TO READ
By J. Alun Thomas
22 FIGHTERS FOR LITERACY
26 BOOKS FOR THE NEW READING PUBLIC
By J.E. Morpurgo
28 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
29 STAMPS HELP TO FIGHT ILLITERACY
By C.W. Hill
30 SCIENCE HAS THE ANSWER
By Gerald Wendt
32 GUATEMALA'S PICTURE HOSPITAL
By Bertha Gaster
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER Is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The Uniced States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.122 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads " Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00 ; I 0/- stg. ; 500 French francs or equi¬
valent.
COVER PHOTO
There are about 700 million adult illi¬
terates in the world today. They
represent 45 per cent of the total world
population 15 years old and over.
Almost half of all the countries and
territories of the world are believed to
have fifty per cent or more illiteracy
among their adult population. In about
one-third of all countries there are at
least a million illiterates in each country
Such In broad terms is the magnitude
of the problem presented by world illit¬
eracy in the middle of the 20th century.
Photos: "O. Cruzeiro", Brazil and UNESCO
Ever since its foundation Unesco has been concerned with the
problems of widespread illiteracy among the world's peoples
and with the measures taken for its elimination. A large
portion of Unesco's efforts in the first ten years of its existence
has been directed towards the promotion of fundamental educa¬
tion, particularly in educationally less well-developed areas of the
world.
There is now abundant evidence to show that illiteracy goes
would have us believe that the illiterate inhabitants of distant
"exotic" lands should be left to keep their traditional ways, free
from the stress and hustle of technically advanced societies. Why
waste time and money on illiterate slum-dwellers or peasants who
appear to like it that way? Whatever case can be made out in
support of the thesis that isolated illiterate communities are or
once were stable, relatively happy and prosperous, there is now
hardly any region of the world where backward or pre-technical
societies are not feeling to some extent the disruptive impact
of modern technology.
There is now abundant evidence to show that illiteracy goes
hand-in-hand with under-nourishment, endemic disease, poverty,
endless and unrewarding drudgery, demoralization. This is not to
say that illiteracy has "caused" these ills or that they will be auto¬
matically removed by the. simple expedient of teaching everyone to
read and write. But it can no longer be denied that social and
economic improvement in these regions can be achieved only
through the assimilation of modern techniques of production, dis¬
tribution, medical and social welfare, etc, and that the assimilation
of these techniques requires education and that a basic part of this
education will be learning to read and write.
The relationship between the growth of literacy and changing
techniques is observable in the history of the technically advanced
countries. In Europe and North America the spread of literacy
accompanied the increase of industrialization begun by the Indus¬
trial Revolution. Mass literacy arrived only in the second half
of the 19th century, or even later. The introduction of free and
compulsory education was, and remains, the direct agent in the
process of reducing illiteracy. In some countries the extension
of popular education preceded the rapid industrial advance, in
others it followed ; but the two phenomena have always been
closely associated.
It would be a mistake, however, to regard literacy as merely
a function of industrialization. Literacy and industrialization are
both means, not ends. They are, or should be, means for
achieving a better life. Besides the improvement of his material
lot, a man must be literate if he is to take an intelligent and
active part in the organization and life of his community and
assume his full stature as a human being. As long as more than
two-fifths of the world's adult population cannot read and write
in any language, and are thus deprived of their full participation
in the cultural life of mankind, the question of world illiteracy
must continue to be of concern to all.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
700,000,000 illiterates
IS WORLD ILLITERACY
ON THE INCREASE ?
by Bangnee A. Liu
Chief, Statistical Division, Unesco
U.N.
WAR ON IGNORANCE is declared in Liberia as a low-flying plane "bombards" a village with leaflets to announce the opening of a nation-wide
campaign against illiteracy. In the front ranks of this campaign are teachers of the rural schools which are now being opened throughout the
country by the Liberian Government and staffed with graduates of a teacher training centre operated near Monrovia by the Government and Unesco.
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
T
he World Census of Population
which is to be taken around 1960
should help to answer one of the
vitally important questions of our
time : Is the world's illiterate
population increasing, in spite of the remarkable progress
made in many countries- towards the goal of universal
primary education ?
The number of adult illiterates (people over 15 years
of age who cannot both read and write in any language)
in the world around 1950 has been estimated at about
700 million slightly over two-fifths of the world's popu¬
lation at that age level. This figure is based on an
analysis of recent census results from 75 countries,
supplemented by estimates for the other countries, using
outdated or incomplete census data, school enrolment
figures and other relevant information obtained by Unesco.
Detailed results of this study, including methods of
defining and counting illiterates and analyses of data
for some 65 individual countries, are presented in a new
Unesco publication : World Illiteracy at Mid-Century
(Monographs on fundamental education, XI, Paris, 1957).
The only previous study on this subject, comparable in
scope though not in methods, is contained in a bulletin
of the U.S. Bureau of Education published in 1929. The
authors of that study gave an estimate of 850 million
illiterates in the world 10 years of age and over. If we
Were to use the same age level of population for our 1950
estimate, we would probably arrive at a world estimate
of 800 to 840 million illiterates, thus showing apparently
very little reduction in the absolute size of the world's
illiterate population in the last 25 years or so, even though
the total illiteracy rate was estimated at 62 per cent in the
earlier study, as compared with our estimate of 43-45 per
cent for 1950.
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
In Turkey the number and percentage of illiterate
persons 15 years old and over at the three censuses in
1935, 1945 and 1950 were as follows : 1935 census 7.7 million
illiterates (81.3%); 1945 census 8.1 million illiterates
(71.5 %) ; 1950 census 8.8 million illiterates (68.1 %).
According to Ceylon's 1946 census, there were nearly
2.5 million illiterate persons, 5 years old and over more
than at any of the previous censuses, though the illiteracy
rate had been steadily declining, as follows : 1901 census
2.2 million illiterates (73.6%); 1911 census 2.4 million
illiterates (69.0%); 1921 census 2.3 million illiterates
(60.1 %) ; 1946 census 2.4 million illiterates (42.2 %).
In Mexico the number of illiterate persons 6 years old
and over was found to be nearly 9 million in 1950, or
about the same number as in 1930. The illiterate
population aged 10 years and over in 1940 was 7.5 million,
as compared with 7.6 million in 1900.
In Portugal, there were 2.6 million illiterate persons
15 years old and over in 1950 almost exactly the same
number as in 1900, yet the illiteracy rate had gone down
from 73.1 to 44.1 per cent.
The number and percentage of illiterates 15 years old
and over in Venezuela were, between 1936 and 1950, as
follows: 1936 census 1.2 million (61.0%); 1941 census
1.3 million (58.5%); 1950 census 1.4 million (47.8%).
The magnitude of the Illiteracy problem and its
seriousness are brought home when it is looked at on a
world scale. A measure of the problem is given by
statistics relating to the 1950 census period which show
that 90 per cent of the world's illiterates are concentrated
in 43 large countries and 54 smaller ones, all with medium
to high illiteracy rates. These countries (shown in
Table 1, as groups A and B) are mostly situated in Asia,
Africa, Central and South America, and include some of
the territories in Oceania. Another 9 per cent of the
illiterate population are found in 20 countries (Table 1,
The phenomenon of an illiterate population increasing
¿n numbers or unchanged while the illiteracy rate
goes down is by no means as uncommon as one
would think. Here are a few examples from the figures
analysed in the Unesco study. There are probably many
other cases of this kind for which we do not have the
necessary statistics. The original sources of the data
which follows are usually the official census publications
of the respective countries, the latest issues only being
cited by title in the recent Unesco monograph on
illiteracy. The latest (1950) census in Brazil shows an
illiterate population of 15.3 million persons 15 years old
and over 50.6 per cent of the total population at that
age level. In comparison, the number and percentage
of illiterates at each of three previous censuses were as
follows : 1900 census 6.3 million illiterates (65.3 % ) ;
1920 census 11.4 million illiterates (64.9%) ; 1940 census
13.3 million illiterates (56.1 %).
Thus, while the illiteracy rate for Brazil has been
steadily going down, the number of illiterates has been
steadily increasing since the beginning of the century,
undoubtedly due to the rapid growth of population not
matched by the increased provisions for the rudimentary
education of children and adults.
Much the same situation is found in Egypt, as shown
by the census figures for 1907-1947. While the illiteracy
rate went down during those 40 years from 92.8 to 80.1 per
cent, the number of illiterate persons 15 years old and
over increased steadily from 6.2 million to 9.1 million (or
possibly 9.5 million) in the same period.
Illiteracy among the population 15 years old and over
at the 1951 census in India was 80.7 per cent according to
a 10 per cent sample tabulation of the census returns.
In pre-partition India, the illiteracy rate had declined
from 93.5 per cent in 1901 to 90.4 per cent in 1931, but
the number of illiterate persons had increased from
162 million to 182 million during those 30 years.
Table I. Estimated distribution of the world's
illiterate population, around I 950
Group of countries
Number
of
countries
Estimated
number
of adult
illiterates
Estimated
proportion
of world's
illiterates
A. Countries with estimated
50 per cent or more illiteracy
and 1 million or more adult
43
54
20
81
(millions)
600-640
15-16
55-65
8-9
(per cent)
88
2
9
1
B. Countries with estimated
SO per cent or more illiteracy
and less than 1 million adult
C. Countries with estimated less
than SO per cent illiteracy and
1 million or more adult illite-
D. Countries with estimated less
than 50 per cent illiteracy and
less than 1 million adult illite-
WOR.LD TOTAL	 198 690-720 100
group C) with low to medium illiteracy rates. This
group includes, for example, Japan, U.S.A. and France,
with illiteracy rates below 5 per cent but with an
estimated total of 5 to 7 million adult illiterates between
them. The remaining 1 per cent of illiterates, numbering
8 or 9 million, are scattered among 81 coun¬
tries (Table 1, group D), all with low to
medium illiteracy rates, and each with an
illiterate population varying from a few
hundred to almost a million.
Cont'd
on
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
700,000,000
ILLITERATES
(Continued)
THE GEOGRAPHY OF IGNORANCE
The world-wide scope of the problem is further seen
from figures showing the estimated size of population and
extent of illiteracy for each continent and geographical
region. In Table 2, these regions are defined as in the
United Nations Demographic Yearbook, with the excep¬
tion that the U.S.S.R. is included here with Europe and
not shown as a separate region.
The estimated extent of adult illiteracy in different
parts of the world as of 1950, is shown on the map
published on pages 18-19. It should be remembered that,
in certain countries at least, great progress has been made
in the last few years in reducing adult illiteracy, and in
such cases the map indications are not up to date.
Table 2. Estimated population and extent
of illiteracy in the world, around 1 950,
by continents and regions
Continent and region
AFRICA
Northern Africa 	
Tropical and Southern
Africa 	
AMERICA
Northern America
Middle America . .
South America. . . .
Estimated
population
Total
(all
ages)
Adult
(15 years
old
and over)
(millions)
198
65
ASIA
South West Asia...
South Central Asia
South East Asia . . .
East Asia 	
EUROPE (inc. U.S.S.R.)
Northern and Western
Europe	,
Central Europe 	 ,
Southern Europe 	 ,
OCEANIA
134
330
168
51
I I I
1,376
120
40
WORLD TOTAL
62
466
171
677
579
133
128
131
J2
2,496
80
223
126
30
67
830
37
287
102
404
405
102
96
95
9
1,587
Estimated
extent of
adult
Illiteracy.
(per cent)
80-85
85-90
80-85
20-21
3-4
40-42
42-44
60-6 5
75-80
80-85
65-70
45-50
7-9
1-2
2-3
20-21
10-11
43-45
Estimated
number
of adult
illiterates
(millions)
98-104
34-36
64-68
45-47
4-5
12-13
28-29
510-540
28-30
23 0-240
68-72
180-200
28-36
1-2
2-3
19-20
J_
690-720
Within the same countries, there are often striking
differences in the extent of illiteracy between the urban
and rural areas, the male and female populations, the
younger and older generations, and among various popu¬
lation groups distinguished by ethnic origin. These
differences usually point to uneven development of educa¬
tional opportunities within a country, and the need for
special attention to the education of the under-privileged
groups.
Almost invariably, higher illiteracy rates are found,
among the rural populations as compared with the urban
populations of the same country. For example, in Brazil
(1950), with a total illiteracy rate of 51 per cent, the rural
population was 67 per cent illiterate as compared with
22 per cent for the urban population and 39 per cent for
the suburban. In El Salvador (1950), with a total illit¬
eracy rate of 61 per cent, the rates for the urban and rural
populations were 35 and 77 per cent respectively. In
Venezuela (1950), the urban population had an illiteracy
rate of 30 per cent while the rural population was 72 per
cent illiterate ; and in Panama (1950), the rural popula
tion had an illiteracy rate of 43 per cent as compared
with 7 per cent in the urban areas. Even in the U.S.A.
(1952), the illiteracy rate for the rural farm population
was 5.7 per cent, while the urban and rural non-farm
populations had only about 2 per cent illiteracy.
The female population generally has a higher illiteracy
rate than the male population, particularly in those
countries with medium to high illiteracy rates. The
following are some examples of large (more than 20 per
cent) differences between the male and female illiteracy
rates.
Male, female illiteracy compared
Male Female
Malaya (1947) 	 43 per cent 84 per cent
Thailand (1947) 31 per cent 64 per cent
Turkey (1950) 	 52 per cent 83 per cent
Greece (1951) 12 per cent 39 per cent
Yugoslavia (1953) 	 15 per cent 38 per cent
Ceylon (1953) 	 24 per cent 46 per cent
Egypt (1947) 69 per cent 91 per cent
India (1951) 71 per cent 92 per cent
There are, however, a few examples of countries where
the female population has a lower illiteracy rate than the
male. For instance, in Cuba (1953), the male illiteracy rate
was 24 per cent as compared with 20 per cent for the
female population. In Western Samoa (1951), there were
only 6 per cent illiterates among the women but 23 per
cent among the men. Other examples of this kind are
found in Bermuda (1950), with 4 per cent male illiteracy
and only 2 per cent female illiteracy; and in the U.S.A.
(1952) where the illiteracy rate among men in the rural
farm areas was 7.1 per cent as compared with a rate of 4.1
per cent among women in the same areas.
Obviously the older age groups of the population in
any country are apt to have higher illiteracy rates than
the younger groups, especially where universal primary
education has been introduced only recently. The follow¬
ing figures from the Philippines census of 1948 are fairly
typical :
Illiteracy by age groups
in the Philippines
Age group
10-14 years 	
15-19 years 	
20-24 years 	
25-34 years 	
35-44 years 	
45-54 years 	
55-64 years
65 years and over
Male Female
illiteracy illiteracy
% %
34 32
24 25
25 31
32 39
37 49
48 65
59 76
72 84
It is quite common to find differential illiteracy rates
among the various ethnic groups of a population. Apart
from such examples as the U.S.A. (1952), where the illit¬
eracy rates for the white and non-white populations were
1.8 and 10.2 per cent respectively, and the Union of South
Africa (1946), where the African population was 72 per
cent illiterate whereas the white population
had less than 2 per cent illiteracy, marked
ethnic differences are reported in the cen¬
suses of other countries. These include
Barbados (1946), Bermuda (1950), British
Guiana (1946), British Honduras (1946),
Cont'd
on
page 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Mctrch 1958
COI
WALL OF ILLITERACY is gradually being pushed back in Africa by devoted men and women such as this teacher instructing an open-air class in
Southern Nigeria. Grown-ups and children come here to learn to read and write in Ibo, the local language, during a mass education campaign.
R. C. Ariel S. S. Benegal
GATEWAY TO LITERACY VILLAGE, a non-governmental educational institution, at Lucknow in India, spells new hope for all who enter it.
Operated by the India Literacy Board, it trains workers who take classes around flickering oil lamps in village homes. India's drive for literacy was
recently encouraged by Indian statesman Krishna Menon, who declared: "Every citizen who cannot read or write is a blot on the other man who can."
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
700,000,000
ILLITERATES
(Continued)
THE REAL THREAT: INCREASING POPULATION
Ceylon (1946), Fiji (1946), Leeward and Windward Islands
(1946), Malaya (1947), Mauritius (1952), North Borneo
(1951), Sarawak and Brunei (1947), Trinidad and Tobago
(1946).
There is naturally a direct relationship between the
growth of primary school enrolment and the reduction
of adult illiteracy in a given country over a period of time.
If all children of school age in a country attended school
for a sufficient length of time, there would of course
eventually be few adult illiterates in that country. On
the other hand, as long as a substantial proportion of the
school-age children are left out of school, the problem of
illiteracy can never be successfully resolved by recourse
only to emergency measures such as the organization of
literacy classes for adults.
8905. 7K)|
SABEN LEER NO
SABEN LEER
rWSJTllttlJ DC ASUNTOS C&HPUM0S
© Paul Almasy
HANDWRITING ON THE WALL in this Bolivian country school¬
room spells the eventual defeat of the army of illiteracy... for its recruits
are adults who never* had a chance to go to school. In Bolivia, the
Government is concentrating on improving education offered by rural
schools in order to give the country's new generation a head start
in the march to literacy. Because of the urgency of the illiteracy problem
in Latin America, Unesco has launched a ten-year major project to
extend primary education on the continent. Bolivia is a member of
the committee which will supervise the application of the project.
8
For example, in France, where primary education
became free in 1881 and compulsory in 1882, the illiteracy
rate rapidly declined from 16.5 per cent in 1901 to 3.3 per
cent in 1946. In the U.S.A., compulsory education laws
had been introduced in all the states by 1918; the illiteracy
rate is now down to 2.5 per cent for the country as a whole.
In Italy, compulsory education began in 1859 but did not
come into full operation until after 1904; the illiteracy
rate was nearly 50 per cent in 1901 but had dropped to
14 per cent in 1951. However, in Brazil where there is
not yet universal compulsory education, the illiteracy rate
had declined only from 65 per cent to 51 per cent between
1900 and 1950.
Countries which had less
children in. primary schools
cent or more adult illiterates
with less than 20 per cent
maintained high enrolment
at least since 1930. Thus
principle that the extension
education is the best single
of illiteracy in any country.
than 40 per cent of their
around 1930 all had 50 per
in 1950. Almost all countries
adult illiteracy in 1950 had
ratios (60 per cent or more)
it may be stated as a basic
and improvement of primary
method for the elimination
Historical evidence and current comparisons lead to
the conclusion that low levels of illiteracy in the
population are most often associated with an ad¬
vanced stage of industrialization. In England and Wales,
the decline of agriculturalism and of illiteracy both began
prior to the nineteenth century. By the beginning of this
century, only 12 per cent of the economically active male
population were engaged in agriculture, and only about
3 per cent of brides and grooms were signing the mar¬
riage register by mark. In Belgium, between 1866 and 1947,
the proportion of male active population engaged in
agriculture fell from 40 to 14 per cent, and the illiteracy
rate dropped from 40 to 3 per cent. In France, since
1872, the decline of agriculture has proceeded less rapidly
than in England or Belgium, yet the illiteracy rate has
been reduced from 33 per cent to about 3 per cent.
While the picture emerging from the Unesco study on
world illiteracy is on the whole encouraging showing
trends of progress in all parts of the world it gives no
grounds for complacency on the part of the world's
educational workers. Unless concerted efforts are made
continuously to bring still more of the world's children
into the schools to receive the rudiments of education
and to giving illiterate persons a chance to learn the
basic skills of reading and writing, the inevitable pressure
of population growth already experienced in many
countries may offset all the educational progress achieved
and leave just as many illiterate adults in the world of
tomorrow, if it does not actually increase their numbers.
At any rate, no one can be indifferent to the plight of
700 million people more than two-fifths of the world's
adult population who are forever handicapped in modern
society because they are unable to communicate with
their fellows by the written word.
Having assessed the magnitude of the task which
remains one of the principal objectives of Unesco's
educational programme we can only hope that the edu¬
cators, administrators and policy-makers of all countries
will rally to the effort in assuring for every man, woman
and child the right to education promised to him in the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights, whose Article 26,
states in part :
"Everyone has the right to education. Education shall
be free, at least in the elementary and fundamental
stages. Elementary education shall be compulsory..."
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
Photos © Paul Almasy
WOMEN'S LITERACY CLASS organized by "The Daughters of
the Nile", an Egyptian feminist movement, at Boulak, Cairo, is typical
of efforts now being made to give women a more active role in the
life of Arab countries. Illiteracy is high in Egypt (about ten million
adults or nearly eight out of ten, according to I 950 figures) and much
higher for women than for men. A I 947 census showed that the
overall figure was 80. 1 per cent and that the male and female illiteracy
percentages were respectively 68.5 and 91.3. Since 1950, follow¬
ing government campaigns, the proportion of illiterates has
dropped and educational opportunities for women have increased.
WHAT IS AN
'ILLITERATE'?
Amy efforts to find out how much illiteracy exists
in the world and where it is to be found
immediately come up against the problem of
terminology. Who is "'literate"? The concept of
literacy is very flexible. It can be stretched to cover
all levels of ability, from the absolute minimum to
write one's own name, for example to an unde¬
termined maximum.
So far there has been no general agreement on a
definition of "literacy" or "'illiteracy" applicable to all
countries and territories. In fact the United Nations
and Unesco have repeatedly pointed out in their
studies on the question the differences that exist in
national criteria of illiteracy.
The difficulty of arriving at a satisfactory common
definition is due only partly to the divergence of
national practices and traditions. A more basic cause
is the difficulty of reconciling the various concepts of
literacy. These range from the mere ability to
recognize and to write down certain words (or letters
of the alphabet hence "'analphabetism") to being able
to communicate adequately in writing with other
people and from here to the much higher level of
competence necessary to understand, to appreciate and
even to produce, literary works.
Most of the national statistics on literacy and
illiteracy are derived from population censuses.
Armed with a census schedule which includes such
questions as "Can you read and write?" or "Can you
read?" and "Can you write?", the census investigator
gets an answer from the person he is enumerating (or
from someone else answering for that person) and
enters it on his record. It is hardly possible for him
to test the validity of the answer by a detailed
examination. In most census operations, therefore,
the criterion of literacy adopted has to be more or less
a minimum one.
On the other hand, a special survey (probably using
a sampling method) on the literacy of a population
could be based on an objective test, which would
involve not only word recognition, but also compre¬
hension of a sentence or passage, and the ability, not
only to write from dictation, but also to compose a
statement in answer to a question or to some verbal
instructions. In such cases, the criterion of literacy
could be related to a so-called "functional" level, or
to a range of abilities from the minimum to a highly
functional level.
In 1948 the United Nations recommended that
literacy should be defined (for purposes of inter¬
national comparisons) as "ability both to read and to
write a simple message in any one language."
While this definition is undoubtedly suitable for
census purposes, it does not fully meet the needs of
educational surveys. It was therefore expanded
by a Committee of Experts on Standardization of
Educational Statistics, convened by Unesco in 1951.
This committee recommended the following definitions
of "literacy" and "semi-literacy":
A person is considered literate, who can both read
with understanding and write a short, simple statement
on his everyday life.
A person is considered semi-literate, who can read
with understanding, but not write, a short simple
statement on his everyday life.
Until international recommendations on the
measurement of illiteracy are generally adopted by
governments, statistical data collected and published
by them will continue to be based on different criteria
a fact which limits the international comparability
of such statistics.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
At the start of this century 75% of the Russian people were illiterate.
To have banished illiteracy from its vast territories within the space of
40 years is an achievement of which the Soviet Government is rightly
proud. Today more than 2,000,000 students attend institutes of
During the past 40 years, the Soviet Union has been
the scene of the largest literacy campaign carried
on in all history. In 1917, Russia was a poor, back¬
ward country. She was behind in many respects, but
worst of all in the matter of literacy. A census taken in
1897 revealed that 76 per cent of the population above
the age of nine was unable to read or write. Illiteracy
among women was three times as high as that among
men. Literacy varied sharply with nationality and region.
V.l. Lenin wrote in 1913: "No other country in Europe re¬
mains as wild as Russia, the masses of which have been
so despoiled of education, light and knowledge."
As long as illiteracy and ignorance prevailed, the people
could not be expected to participate effectively in the
building of a new life, in restoring the nation's economy,
developing science and raising technical standards. That
is why the wiping out of illiteracy became such a press¬
ing problem after the October Revolution. A Soviet
Government decision of December 26, 1919 "On the
Liquidation of Illiteracy Among the Population..."
started a country-wide literacy campaign to teach the
three R's to the entire illiterate population from 8 to 50
years of age.
During the first years of the Revolution (1917-1920) the
task of fighting illiteracy was no easy matter. The civil
war was in progress, but even then an important step
was taken to eliminate illiteracy. The army became a
huge school for the many millions of illiterate peasants
in uniform. Compulsory schooling was introduced in
every company, squadron, battery and detachment in Sep¬
tember 1919. When the war ended, the demobilized sol¬
diers returned to their native villages as literate men
and assumed the initiative in spreading knowledge in the
countryside.
From 1920, the fight against illiteracy began to be waged
on a tremendous scale. Government institutions, trade
unions, youth organizations, and various . voluntary
societies, such as the "Down with Illiteracy" organization,
all engaged in the work of teaching millions of workers
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 19S8
«I > i i I *»
" * -- -- - - r
A rf r+ * , ^ $
- - '
Soviet Information Bureau
higher education compared with 127,000 in 1914. Left, the early
years of the drive for literacyan elementary class for women at Tash
kent, capital of Uzbekistan, a Soviet Republic in Central Asia, in 1925.
Above, a present-day anatomy class at the Medical Institute in Baku.
and peasants to read and write. An all-Russian Emergency
Commission for the Abolition of Illiteracy was set up by
the People's Commissariat of Education (now the Ministry
of Education) in July 1920 to co-ordinate the efforts of
all the different bodies combating illiteracy.
Despite its meagre resources, the war-ravaged country
allocated thousands of tons of paper for notebooks and
textbooks, firewood and kerosene for heating schools,
warm clothing and boots for travelling instructors.
Literacy students had their workday cut by two hours
without loss of pay. Special anti-illiteracy departments
were set up under town and village auspices. Educational
authorities were allowed to use not only the schools but
other government and public premises to teach illiterates.
Teachers, doctors, agronomists, librarians, engineers,
government clerks and all college and senior high school
students were enlisted in the fight. Every literate person
felt it his patriotic duty to join in the growing national
drive against illiteracy.
Illiteracy fighters displayed the greatest ingenuity in
overcoming obstacles. Where ink was lacking they made
it from beetroot; if there were no notebooks they wrote
on wrapping paper or boards.
Local conditions determined the manner in which the
work was carried on. Instruction was conducted in the
language native to the student. In the East, where the
ancient, customs humiliating to the women continued to
hold sway in the early years of Soviet power, separate
schools were established for women. Nomads driving
their cattle from one grazing ground to another had
literacy schools follow in their wake. Special forms
and methods of instruction were devised for transport
workers, lumbermen and others engaged in seasonal
occupations. Nor were mothers forgotten,
rooms were provided where mothers could
leave their children while studying.
Children's
The vast scale on which the work was
conducted necessitated not only a variety
Cont'd
on
next page
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
LARGEST
CAMPAIGN
(Continued)
One library to every 500 persons
R hy». tu n,, ta« io t. nn it*.
Ooa mu tpfAOti »il»
Ott partie» n cuutu ,101e.
C -»on »a-MMi u>ir ttptw.
of approaches but a thorough revision of existing text¬
books and teaching aids.
The first Soviet primer for grown-ups was published in
1918. It was followed by scores of similar books issued
in millions of copies. Attempts to use children's primers
to teach adults failed. The elementary sentences used
in books for children brought smiles and laughter from
the grown-up students, so special books had to be written,
adjusted to the mentality of the new "pupils", who were
then able to make more rapid progress.
Different primers were also found necessary for urban
and rural schools as well as for the schools in the North.
Readers for adults contained poems
and stories on topics of the day as
well as practical articles on how to
combat drought, how to take care of
gardens, etc. At Russian language
classes, students were taught the art
of writing business letters. In teach¬
ing arithmetic attention was also
given to the interests of the pupils
who were shown how to figure up the
crops, production time and other
practical measures.
The literacy school curriculum
called for 330 hours of study, includ¬
ing 200 hours for the native tongue
and 130 hours for arithmetic, in the
case of total illiterates. For groups
just able to read and write, hours of
study were distributed as follows: the
native tongue 145, arithmetic 125,
geography 60. Simple reading ma¬
terial was recommended to those
finishing the literacy schools. A
special magazine, Down with Illiteracy
was published in large type, while a
peasant newspaper Bednota (The
Poor Peasant) produced a special
supplement for beginners. A series
of easy readers was also published.
Every effort was made by the State
and public organizations to develop a
wide network of libraries, clubs and
educational institutions to meet the
growing cultural requirements of the
newly-taught people; the publishing
business was also extended.
Since most of those engaged in
teaching illiterates were not pro¬
fessional teachers, it was highly
important to provide them with
guidance and proper methods. School teachers and
instructors of the teachers' training colleges proved very
helpful in this respect.
The public schools served as teacher-guidance centres
in the districts. They gave consultations, arranged
conferences which permitted an exchange of experiences,
and organized short-term courses. Advice and assistance
were given to all applicants.
The People's Commissariat of Education published
various teaching aids and magazines, recorded local
experience, and sent trained technicians to the provinces,
to provide advice in the field.
12
i ff! 35. im : I
atrtctoiMn 1»]nni>>!i Hmi:»i u iraiiuu tunuagiucn ng> 'iíimhujockii
Hy c iodée poaiwe fipaiar:
fl pacota«, tu aaraaa.
Hawa apenaae ooaua
CaepTe a raoeaa Aaa tuaAata!
.lipa ycAaaace rpnnaxaoi-tl paaopeara erpaau aar fropeacrj
WM TpyARoe; aa fyTuaaevr ACTicmntMiaio cogjijUBCTa-
BKMeantKa aa npauuiAifi Tvaapooekeea Meatxy opo-
** VI ataraam
a acaucACaaea-.
Coioï pa6oqH¡< h Kpecibsm Heno6e«M«!
'Down with Illiteracy'
It was from 1920 onwards that the fight
against illiteracy began to be waged on a tre¬
mendous scale in Russia. Government insti¬
tutions, trade unions, youth organizations and
many voluntary societies all joined in the work
of teaching millions of workers and peasants
to read and write. Teachers, doctors, agrono¬
mists, librarians, engineers, government clerks
and all college and senior high school students
were enlisted in the fight. One of the leading
groups in the campaign, the "Down with
Illiteracy" organization, published a special
magazine, printed in large type, a cover of
whichNo 3 5 of 1924 is reproduced above.
remember it with a
By 1926, the number of literates In the country had
more than doubled. In 1932, the "cultural army" of
literacy fighters comprised about 1,200,000 recruits, while
the "Down with Illiteracy" society had more than 50,000
local branches with a membership exceeding five million.
Upwards of 32,000,000 persons were taught to read and
write by the illiteracy elimination schools during 1929-1932
alone.
The campaign had been built up with astonishing speed
and results: 1,300,000 persons were taught to read and
write between 1927-28; 2,700,000 between 1928-29; 10,500,000
between 1929-1930 and 22,000,000 between 1930-31.
By 1939, no less than 95.1 per cent
of the men and 83.4 per cent of the
women in the U.S.S.R. were literate.
Even more striking were the results
achieved in the non-Russian republics
of the Soviet Union. During the
13 years from 1926 to 1939, literacy
showed the following advances: in the
Tadjik Republic, from 3.7 to 71.7 per
cent; in the Uzbek Republic, from
10.6 to 67.8 per cent; in the Turk-
menian Republic, from 12.5 to 67.2 per
cent; in the Kirghizian Republic, from
15.1 to 70.0 per cent; in the Kazakh
Republic, from 22.8 to 76.3 per cent.
Since the war, illiteracy has been
wiped out completely in the Union of
Socialist Soviet Republics.
Universal elementary and junior
high-school education has long been
established in the Soviet Union and
universal high-school education is
being introduced. Today, 50,400,000
people in the U.S.S.R., or one person
out of every four inhabitants, is
engaged in study of one kind or
another. The number of schools,
colleges and libraries is steadily
growing. The number of libraries has
increased by 147,400 during the past
10 years and now exceeds 400,000 so
that there is today an average of one
library to every 500 citizens in the
Soviet Union.
II ceepara leaKue HeApa.
Aoöumjo ciaaa a ueAi..
Hsrpajay Teöa a moApo
3a Teoa TpyAw a caeAa.
.H-J.Z.
11. fair ..,,.,..
Soviet Information Bureau
The first step in this gigantic
advance of culture was the arduous
struggle against illiteracy. Many
thousands of Soviet people, for whom
the illiteracy elimination schools
were the first step to education,
feeling of gratitude.
Further information on this subject is to be found in a booklet
"Forty Years of Public Education in the U.S.S.R.", by M. Deineko,
published in Moscow in 1957 by the Foreign Languages Publishing
House.
Serafima Liubimova began to work in schools for adults in 1917,
first in Moscow artd later in Central Asia. She has been active
in promoting public education in Moscow and other Soviet towns.
At the end of the 1930'.f she was a leading official of the Adult
School Department.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Morch 1958
AN ILLITERATE IN PARIS
In countries where free and compulsory education has been applied for generations, Illiteracy
is no national problem. Yet in all countries, even the most advanced, a small residue
remains of adults who, for one reason or another, have never learned to read or write.
At mid-century, the majority of the countries of northern and western Europe had illiteracy
rates ranging from one to three per cent. However, statistical trends also show that with
each passing decade the number of illiterates In these countries is steadily dropping. Thus,
the latest (1946) survey carried out in France revealed an illiteracy rate of 3.3 % but also
showed that between 1901 and 1946 illiteracy had decreased each ten years by 30 per cent.
Assuming the same rate of progress since 1946 as in the past, illiteracy in France today
could be estimated at not more than two per cent. But what is the position of the few
who have somehow slipped through the network of compulsory education? What does it
mean to be an adult illiterate in a society where life is organized on the assumption that
everybody can read and write? Recently a French journalist decided to find out and finally
managed to discover a middle-aged woman factory worker living at Romainville, a suburb of
Paris, who could neither read nor write. The answers she gives in the interview published
below reveal the poignant drama of an illiterate person living in a modern world capital and
the tragedy of being cut off from the written communication we take so much for granted.
"A
re there any words which you can recognize
even though you cannot read them?"
"'Yes, three words. The names of the two
Underground stations on the line I take every day:
'Lilas' and 'Chatelet' and my maiden name."
"Could you pick them out from a group of other
words?"
"I could recognize them from about a dozen others,
I think."
""What do they look like to you... like drawings?"
"'Yes, like pictures, if you want. 'Lilas' is a tall
word it's almost as tall as it is wide and it's pretty.
The word 'Chatelet' is too long, and it's not so pretty.
When you see it, you know it's not the same as the
word 'Lilas'.-"
"When you tried to learn to read, did it seem diffi¬
cult to you?"
"'You can't imagine what it's like. It's terrible."
"'Can you give me an idea of what you mean
exactly?"
"I don't really know. Maybe because everything is
so... so small. I'm sorry, I'm not very good at explain¬
ing things."
"'It must be quite a difficult thing for you to live in
a city like Paris and to get around from one place to
another without being able to read."
"Oh, if you've got a tongue in your head you can
get anywhere you want."
"How do you manage exactly?"
"Well, I do a lot of asking. And then I use my head.
It's funny how quick you pick up things and remem¬
ber what you see. Much quicker than other people.
It's like a blind person. There are places where you
know where you are. Then, I ask people."
"'Do you have to stop and ask your way often?"
"'Oh, about ten times when I come into Paris from
Romainville on an errand or something. There are
all those Underground station names. They mix you
up. You have to take another train back, ask again...
and then there are the names of the streets, the shop
names and the numbers."
"'The numbers?"
"I can't read them. When I get my pay or go
shopping, I can count the figures in my head, but I
can't read them."
"Don't you ever tell people that you can't read?"
"No, never! I always say that I forgot my glasses."
"But there must be times when you can't avoid it?"
"'Yes, sometimes. When they ask me to sign my
name at the factory or in the Town Hall. But I go red
when I have to say it. If you were in my shoes you'd
know what I mean."
"How do you manage in your job?"
"When I'm being hired, I keep it to myself. And I
always hope to get away with it. It works most of
the time, except when there are time-slips to fill in.
The rest of the time I make believe I can read."
'"Everywhere?"
'"Yes, everywhere. In the factory, in the shops I
look at the labels and the scales and make believe
that I'm reading them. I'm so afraid that people are.
cheating me, too. I'm always suspicious."
"'Does it bother you in your work?"
"'No, I'm a good worker. I've got to be more care¬
ful than the others. I use my head and I'm careful.
I don't have any trouble there."
"'What about your shopping for food and things?"
'"I know all the colours of all the brands I use.
When I want to change a brand I ask one of my
friends to come with me. After that I remember the
colours of the new brand. You've got to have a good
memory if you're like me."
"'What do you do for amusement? Do you like
the cinema?"
"No, I don't. It's too fast and I don't understand
the way they talk. The pictures always start with
a lot of writing. People read letters and you see it
on the screen. Then they look sad or happy and I
don't know why. But I do go to the theatre."
"Why the theatre?"
"You've got time to listen. They tell you every¬
thing they're doing. There's no writing. They talk
slow. I understand better."
'"Any other amusements?"
'"I like to go to the country and I like to watch
sports. You know I'm no more stupid than anybody
else, but when you can't read you're like a child."
"'When certain people talktake the radio for in¬
stance does it bother you in any way?"
"Yes, it does. It's like the pictures. They're always
using words they find in books. I'm not used to hear¬
ing these people and the words they use. Somebody
has to explain it to me all over again so as I under¬
stand.
"'Do you ever forget that you can't read?"
"No, I can't. As soon as I walk out of the house I
think about it all the time. It tires you out and
makes you waste time. You never want people to
notice it... that's what you think about all the time.
You're always afraid."
"Afraid?"
"I can't explain it. I think people must be able to
see it. You can't hide it."
Interview by Marguerite Duras. Reproduced by permission
of France-Observateur, Pons.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
MOROCCO ANSWERS
A ROYAL CALL
TO THE CLASSROOM
Wherever you travel, in Morocco you come across a poster showing the
country's ruler, King Mohammed V, his arms outstretched, calling the
people to attend literacy classes and, below, a small schoolhouse to which
men, women and children are flocking. The poster, displayed in even the
tiniest villages, launched Morocco's first national literacy campaign after it had
been heralded by the distribution of three million leaflets and announcements
through loudspeakers and loudspeaker vans.
This national literacy campaign was organized by the Moroccan League for
Fundamental Education and Literacy Work, founded in 1956, and to whose
appeal, teachers from State and private schools, as well as students, trades¬
people, workers and craftsmen responded with enthusiasm.
The League began its work by producing a literacy handbook, giving the
rudiments of reading, writing and arithmetic. The results of this handbook
exceeded all expectations, and soon, two more editions had to be printed. When
the campaign opened on April 16, 1956, 350,000 men and women applied for
enrolment in the schools, and nearly 10,000 men and women teachers had to be
recruited.
The thirst for knowledge and the general enthusiasm were such that every¬
where groups of people were to be seen reading through their lessons
together in shops, booths, offices, workshops and even at street corners. In
Casablanca grown-ups often tried in vain to force their way into the already
overcrowded classrooms. On its side, the League put everything it could into
the campaign and even arranged classes in prisons and for patients in hospitals.
A few months after the end of the 1956 literacy campaign, the Fundamental
Education Department instituted a term of revision to allow new literates to
consolidate the knowledge they had gained. Now, the Department proposes to
start a fresh campaign with a second series of courses to bring all the new
literates up to the level of the Primary Education Certificate.
In the early days of the first national campaign, the inexperienced voluntary
teachers ran into various kinds of difficulties which the League helped them
to overcome by organizing guidance courses in the schools or over the radio.
At a later stage other problems arose concerning the provision of reading
materials for adults at a very elementary stage of learning. The League there¬
fore decided to bring out a special weekly publication written in a simple, easily
comprehensible style, which it named Manar El Maghrib (Lighthouse of
Morocco).
Ir is also in Morocco that a new method for printing Arabic has been developed
which will bring newspapers and books within the range of thousands of
«newly-literate men and women. The inventor is Mr. Ahmed Lakhdar, Gene¬
ral Secretary of Morocco's National Commission for Unesco and head of the
Fundamental Education Section of the Ministry of Education.
The problem was this: although the Arabic alphabet contains 30 letters, some
475 to 800 typesets are needed for printing texts with the vowels. Mr. Lakhdar
has managed to reduce the number of typesets needed for printing Arabic with
vowels to a basic 87, thus making it possible to adapt the system to standard
typewriters and type-setting machines. When applied to the printing of news¬
papers and periodicals, the new system will provide an immense stimulus, by
encouraging new readers to continue their studies, and persuading illiterate
adults to join in literacy campaigns. Mr. Lakhdar 's system has been adopted by
the Moroccan Government, and it was studied with interest by National Com¬
missions for Unesco from eight Arab States which met in Fez, Morocco, in
February.
The Moroccan League has decided to extend its field of action and to set up
fundamental education centres all over the country. It feels that its work will
not really be completed nor its aims achieved until illiteracy is eradicated and
the Moroccan people as a whole have realized their civic responsibilities.
The measure of this task can be seen in figures given in the Unesco study,
World Illiteracy at Mid-Century: Around 1950, out of Morocco's population of
8,800,000,- 5,100,000 were adults aged 15 and over. Between 85% and 90% of
these were illiteratea total of between 4,300,000 and 4,600,000 people unable to
read or write. Despite the progress made since then, it is certain that the
proportion of adult illiterates in Morocco is still extremely high.
14
y
at'
t
Ç. \
WmWt'
ENRICHING EDUCATION in Morocco is
the work of the "Service of Youth and Sports ".
It organizes courses in subjects not sufficiently
covered by normal "schooling" and makes
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
chem available to educationally "underpri¬
vileged" sections of the community. Photos
show activities in centres created by the
Youth Service in all parts of Morocco. (I)
Young people express themselves and develop
artistic talent in drawing and painting classes
at Rabat. (2) Lino-engraving calls for a sure
hand and plenty of concentration. (3) One
Photos g) Gerda Böhm. Rabat
of Morocco's traditional crafts: carpet-weaving
in a girls' centre at the "Bidonville" (shanty
town) of Casablanca. (4) Captivated audience
watches a young actor at the Salé centre.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ILLITERACY
AND NATIONAL INCOME
How is a country's level of literacy related to its
wealth and prosperity as a nation? To this question
there can be no simple, straightforward answer.
The relationship between literacy and national income is
complicated, because the level of national and per capita
Income in a country depends not only on the technical
skills of its people, but also on its capital assets and
natural resources.
Moreover, figures for literacy are not very good measures
of all the skills that go into the operation of a modern,
industrialized economy. Some of these skills and techni¬
cal abilities may be the result of generations of experience
and cannot be reflected by literacy rates. In general a
country's capital assets are created through a long, for¬
mative process often lasting decades or even centuries.
We cannot then assume that a close relationship exists
between literacy rates and the level of national income,
though there are, nevertheless, sound reasons for consider¬
ing that they are to some extent related.
The United Nations' Preliminary Report on the World
Social Situation includes a table of the 1950 per capita
income of 75 countries and territories. This shows that
25 countries had per capita incomes equivalent to 300 U.S.
dollars or over, 10 countries between 150 and 300 dollars
and that 40 countries were below the 150 dollar level. By
dividing the countries into two categories at the 300 dollars
per capita income level and separating the adult illiteracy
rates of the countries at three levels high (50 per cent or
more), medium (20 to 49 per cent) and low (less than
20 per cent) we arrive at some idea of the association
between these two factors.
Taking figures for adult illiteracy rates and per capita
incomes of 41 countries in 1950 we find that 12 of
them which had high illiteracy rates also had rela¬
tively low per capita income. Of 16 countries with low illi¬
teracy rates, all except Japan had relatively high per capita
income. As regards the 13 other countries, with illiteracy
rates between 20 and 49 per cent, all except twrj Puerto
Rico and Venezuela had per capita incomes of less than
300 dollars.
From these general figures let us go on to examine the
development of per capita income in four specific coun¬
tries, in relation to the level and trend of their illiteracy
rates, starting with the United States of America. Here
the illiteracy rate declined from 20 per cent in 1870 to
10.7 per cent In 1900 and continued to fall after the
beginning of the century until by 1950 it had dropped to
3.2 per cent.
Expressed in terms of the 1929 dollar, the per capita
gross national product had increased from $268 in the
period around 1870 to $542 in the period around 1900.
Thereafter it continued to increase (except during the
depression years around 1930) until it reached a high level
of about S 1,200 in 1953. In other words, the per capita
income more than doubled in the 50 years after 1900.
At the same time it will be seen that the United States,
around 1870, started at a relatively high level of literacy.
While the country's rapid rise to prosperity was due to
many factors, including the discovery of natural resources
and the high annual rate of accruing capital, the evi¬
dence nevertheless shows a parallel development in the
reduction of illiteracy and increased per capita income.
In Norway, the rate of increase of the gross annual
product (in terms of 1938 prices) was greater than that
of the United States150 per cent, or from less than
1,000 kroner per capita at the start of the century to over
2,500 kroner in 1953. Data on illiteracy rates are not
available for Norway, but the high proportion of children,
aged from 7 to 14, attending school from at least 1875
16
justifies the assumption that the country had reached a
very high level of literacy at the beginning of the century.
(The percentage of school attendance was 84.3 per cent in
1875 and had risen to 91.4 per cent by 1940. Here again,
then, we find an indication of the association between the
educational level of a people and its productive capacity.
The example of Italy shows a rise in national income
at a slower rate than that of either the United States or
Norway. At the beginning of the century, the per capita
Income, in terms of 1938 prices, was around 2,300 lire.
By 1954 this had increased to about 3,500 lire a rise of
50 % in half a century. Italy's population was about
50 per cent illiterate in 1900, though the rate has declined
considerably since. (Around 1950 adult illiteracy was esti¬
mated to be between 10 and 15 per cent.)
The trends in Spain have been somewhat similar to
those in Italy. On the basis of 1929 prices, the per capita
income level rose from about 850 pesetas near the start
of the century to about 1,200 pesetas in 1953 something
less than 50 % over a half century. Spain entered the
20th century with an illiteracy rate even higher than
Italy, though today it may be considered among the rela¬
tively more literate nations with less than 20 per cent illi¬
teracy in the population 10 years old and over as of 1950.
The educational development of a country is perhaps
related to the distribution of income within it even more
closely than to the level of per capita income. Where
Income is more concentrated in a small proportion of the
population, education tends to be the privilege of the few,
and a large part of the people will remain illiterate. On
the other hand, as literacy skills and education in general
become more widespread, the gap between the high-
income and low-income groups will be reduced, and the
nation's total income will become more evenly distributed.
However, statistics on income distribution are only avail¬
able for a few countries, and are hardly comparable be¬
tween countries.
In the United Nations' report, already mentioned, the
example is cited of four countries Ceylon, El Salvador,
Puerto Rico and Italy where, around 1950, one-third or
more of the total income was received by the richest tenth
of the population. In five other countries Canada, Den¬
mark, Sweden, United Kingdom and the United States
the upper tenth accounted for less than one-third of the
total income. It should be remarked that the countries
in the first group all have higher illiteracy rates than
those in the second group. Furthermore, in the United
Kingdom and the United States, for example, the trend
towards less concentration of income in the upper
brackets, as compared with an earlier period, can already
be seen.
Another aspect to consider is the proportion of na¬
tional income devoted to educational expenditure. A
recent Unesco study (Public Expenditure on Educa¬
tion, Paris, 1955) shows that total expenditure on education
about 1950 by central and local governments varied from
less than 1 per cent to more than 5 per cent of the nation¬
al income of each country. If we separate the countries
according to whether they spent more or less than 2 per
cent of their national income on education, and relate
them to their adult illiteracy rates, we find in general
that those countries with high rates of adult illiteracy
spent a small proportion of national income on education.
A study of the statistics available shows, however, that
some countries with relatively low national income spent
a relatively larger part of it on education. Of course, the
absolute amounts of expenditure may still be very small
in such countries, as compared with the educational
expenditures of the more prosperous ones. Moreover, in
the latter countries, many other items of government
expenditure are also likely to be large, thus keeping down
the percentage expressed by educational expenditure.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
Photo: TuKc
GOOD NEWS for readers is brought to a Thai village by a poster (above, left) announcing the arrival of book-boxes in the village. The travelling
library which brings them is one of the most important arms of education in preventing literates from slipping back into illiteracy simply because they
have nothing to read. Poster was produced. (above, right) at Ubol, site of the Thailand-Unesco Fundamental Education Centre. Before a pony-cart
library started its travels in the district, handwritten "newspapers" posted in the villages were almost the only available reading material. These
news sheets are produced in schools attached to the teacher-training collage at Ubol, where Unesco experts are working alongside Thai educationists.
aWSw^
UNESCO photo by Bjorn Berndtson
TESTING GROUND FOR EDUCATION.
During a period of I 8 months, an experimental
training centre was set up in Mysore, India,
by the Mysore Adult Education Council and
Unesco to give practical training to specialists
in fundamental education who would even¬
tually work for Unesco, and to try out new
methods of literacy teaching. Experimental
classes for adults had to be set up in villages
surrounding the Centre. Villages competed
fiercely to be chosen for the classes: one
offered its best house, another its most attrac¬
tive classroom. Left, inauguration of one of
these classes. A teacher is performing a
dedication ceremony to the goddess of learning
with an offering of fire and flowers. New
methods resulting from world-wide research
by Unesco were tested for the first time and
proved highly successful. India has several
national literacy programmes, in some of which
Unesco is collaborating. Of special impor¬
tance is the National Fundamental Education
Centre now being set up near Delhi with
Unesco's co-operation. India is also bene¬
fitting from Unesco's programme for the
production of reading materials for new lite¬
rates. The Delhi Public Library, set up by
the Government with Unesco's help, also plays
a major role in the fight against illiteracy.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
WORLD ILLITERACY AT MID-CENTURY
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
Adult illiteracy is greatest in Asia and Africa and in parts of Middle and South
America, though millions of illiterate persons are still to be found in many other
countries where education is well-developed. Countries of South Central Asia
contain over 230 million of the world's 700 million adult illiterates. Rather
more than a quarter of the world's illiterates live in East Asia. Africa accounts
for at least 100 million illiterate persons (80 to 85 per cent of the adult popu
lation). A further 100 million illiterates are found in countries of South East
Asia and South West Asia. The whole of Middle and South America, with some
40 million adult illiterates, has an illiteracy rate approximately equal to the
estimated world average (about 44 per cent). Southern Europe accounts for
another 20 million illiterates and the remainder of the world's illiterate popula¬
tion is scattered over the rest of Europe, Northern America and Oceania.
According to Unesco's latest study, Illiteracy at Mid-Century, from which this map
is taken, countries with the highest rates of illiteracy in 1950 Included: Afghan¬
istan, Ethiopia, Nepal, Saudi Arabia and Yemen (95-99%); Sudan, Liberia,
Libya (90-95%); Morocco, Nigeria, Haiti, Iran, Iraq (85-90%); Algeria, Tunisia,
Cambodia, India, Indonesia, Pakistan, Vietnam, Laos and Jordan (80-85%).
18 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
by
J. Alun Thomas
Few men have accomplished more in their span of life
than a humble Welshman by the name of Griffith
Jones. He was born in 1683 in Penboyr, one of
several parishes lying on the delightful uplands above
Tivyside in South Wales, a land distinguished not only for
its compelling beauty, but also for its rich literary culture
and for the fiercely independent nature of its people.
Griffith Jones was a man of the people and his earliest
years were spent in helping the shepherds and in learning
the trade of woodturning. It is true that he spent a few
years at the Carmarthen Grammar School but he never
went to a university nor to one of the well-known aca¬
demies of the period; yet this man who had scant sym¬
pathy from the Church leaders of his day, this humble
country parson, was almost solely responsible for teaching
most of his fellow-countrymen to read and, almost
without realizing it himself, he became one of the pioneers
of adult education. Before we explain how he succeeded
in his task let us take a brief glance at the state of Wales
in the days of his boyhood, round about 1700.
The people were generally poor and though the popu¬
lation of the whole country was well under half a million,
yet it proved an almost intolerable strain on the agri¬
cultural technique of the time which, like most other
things, lagged well behind whatever progress was achieved
in England. But neighbourliness and sociability reached a
high level and there was little actual want.
An attempt at popular education had been made by
the Commonwealth Government in 1650 with its "Act for
the Better Propagation of the Gospel in Wales". About
60 free schools, mostly of the grammar school type, were
founded, but the Restoration of 1660 dealt a fatal blow
to the movement.
A considerable step forward in the education of the poor
was the extensive work of the Society for Promoting
Christian Knowledge (s.p.c.k.) founded in 1698. At first
confined mainly to London, its influence spread rapidly
into the rest of England and Wales.
The society proved an admirable friend to Wales, and
large quantities of Bibles, prayer books and religious
classics in both English and Welsh entered the country
and were either distributed free or sold at very small
cost. Through its correspondents in all parts of Wales
the society set up nearly 100 schools, and so infectious
was its enthusiasm for spreading knowledge that several
20
hundred more schools of the same simple pattern were
set up in all parts of Wales, and by 1714 as many as 12
diocesan and parish libraries had been established at
suitable centres to aid necessitous clergy and others.
These schools, though as a rule free, were in some places
fee paying; the three R's were again in evidence with the
pleasant addition of singing (which was not included in
the English schools) and some simple needlework for the
girls, the full course taking about four years.
Enfant terrible among the clergy
But the fine and consistent effort of the s.p.c.k. was too
limited in scope, too inadequate in conception, to
meet the needs of the people, and even by the third
decade of the century the country's condition was appall¬
ing, groaning as it was under the heavy burden of illi¬
teracy and vice. Could the illiterate masses ever be taught
to read and think? One man, Griffith Jones, a country
parson in South Wales, felt sure that he had the answer to
the problem. Rector of Llanddowror, and a brother-in-law
of Sir John Phillips, noted educationist and friend of the
Wesleys and of Francke, Griffith Jones was a brilliant
and persuasive preacher whom thousands of people would
walk miles to hear. An enfant terrible among the clergy,
honoured as a saint by his hearers, condemned and
insulted by his enemies, this man found an answer to
the grave problem of the times, and by his devotion and
persistence brought about a national revival.
The fiery preacher realized by 1730 that an illiterate
people could never be saved by the pulpit alone. Edu¬
cation there must be, free, simple in its aim and method,
and education in the language of the people. He had
already played his part in the s.p.c.k. school movement
and the society was to help him in his new project that
of the Circulating Welsh Charity Schools.
His plan was to train schoolmasters in his parish at
Llanddowror and send them itinerating from one parish
to another at the invitation of the incumbent, the school
in any one place remaining for about three months and
held generally in the winter months when the farmers
were not busy. They had to be entirely free so that even
the poorest of the poor could benefit, and adults as well
as children were invited to them.
The Dean of Bangor, Dr. John Jones, a man who had
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
already given practically all his fortune to educate the
poor, describes the poverty of the people in the Bangor
diocese in a letter dated 20 June 1716 : "It is impossible
in those parts to fix the poor children constantly and
regularly at School, because they must ever and anon beg
for victuals, there being no poor rates settled in those
parts. In harvest the poor parents take them out of
School, and declare they had rather they should not be
taught at all than be debarred the use and service of
them."
The reformer set to work on his great task in 1737 and
neither the death of his patron, Sir John Philips, in that
year nor the jibes and jeers of envious critics deterred
him from consecrating all his energies to the realization
of his vision.
There were encouraging signs, too, for a number of
clergy declared solidly for Jones and assisted him gener¬
ously in his appeal for funds; squires with Methodist
sympathies, and scientists and clergy in England, were to
prove strong financial supporters. But the reformer's
greatest gain was to have at his side for the best part of
20 years a collaborator of energy and ability in
Madame Bridget Bevan. Handsome and accomplished, she
stood by Jones' side right through to his death.
What were the schools like? Let Jones speak for
himself as far as their working was concerned: "Where a
Charity School is wanted and desired, or like to be kindly
received, no pompous Preparations or costly Buildings are
thought of, but a Church or Chapel, or untenanted House
of convenient Situation, is fixed on; and publick Notice
given immediately, that a Welch School is to begin there,
at an appointed Time, where all Sorts that desire it are
to be kindly and freely taught for Three Months; (though
the Schools are continued for Three Months longer, or
more, when needful; and then removed to another Place
where desired.)"
Masters toiled for three or four hours every night or
evening and instructed at that time from two to three
times as many as were taught in the daytime. Three
months was the time allotted for learning to read
and to understand the Catechism the three R's were
absent from the circulating schools. In his annual report
for 1745-1746 Jones writes: "We do not meddle with
teaching any of them Lettering or Cyphering, which
would require more Time than their Circumstances
and more Expense than my little Cash can afford."
The reformer was eminently practical; Instruction was
given in the language of the people, and the Welsh
language had an overwhelming preponderance at the
time. There is no scholar yet who has toiled patiently
through the manifold reports who has not been amazed
at the sweeping success of the schools. One village after
another was cured of illiteracy. Slowly but surely
darkness was being eliminated from the land. The
demand for schools far exceeded the supply of teachers
and books available. The people as a whole began to
show zeal for learning to read, and to think. As often
as not, the Bible itself would be their reader, the alphabet
and simple word constructions being printed on the fly¬
leaf; there, indeed, was infinite material for the learners
to ponder over. How was it that illiterate adults were
able to read in so short a time? One answer lies in the
fact that in its spelling the Welsh language is regular
and phonetic.
'Seventies' rush to buy spectacles
Griffith Jones' methods were rough and simple by
modern standards, but nevertheless the people's
interest and keenness were thoroughly aroused. In
some parishes the school would remain for one, two or
even three quarters of a year, moving from one place to
another in the parish. Much depended upon the keenness
of the local incumbent and upon the supply of funds avail¬
able. The enthusiam aroused among the masses can be
gauged by the heavy demand for spectacles so that the
older pupils, many of them septuagenarians, could benefit
from the instruction.
Apart from malicious attacks by his greatest detractor,
John Evans, Jones experienced some trouble with some
of the masters, particularly those who were inclined to
Methodism, a movement which was much to the dislike
of the clergy. But he strove to exercise discipline in this
as in other matters, and in his voluminous correspondence
he shows great sagacity and common sense. Though a
loyal priest of the Church who never neglect¬
ed his flock and taught the Church's doc¬
trine ¡wholly, there is plenty of evidence
that he was sympathetic at heart to reform¬
ation within the Church, and we have no
Cont'd
next page
Welch Piety:
OR, A ft- PLVUL.
COLLECTION
Of the fe-raal
ACCOUNTS
Of ihr CtRtl'tATISG
Welch Charity Schools,
From their Firft Rise, in the
Year 1737, to Miclxirlmai, 175^.
4e, t'orne iveriim' icvnocmpcPrsno atiô
jli fiuuikn lu Î-whî}*?* u.ifi Ïm foç)?ffaii->
>ri-f-Y AtCVtbtttQ {oJllCV.tif $ TOPIr» 'IU{> ^
lUtcli ifar nuïÂw /Wjtiiltï i -Vft-Wl^rwWÎéO-
emb k hkt béfete (fo tmruffi étjutAom cm
/? h - mux
EDUCATION BECOMES
A FAMILY AFFAIR
In the first half of the 18th century
Wales became a vast "classroom" and
education a family affair as old and young
alike flocked to the circulating schools
of Griffith Jones. An enfant terrible
among the clergy. Griffith Jones was a
pioneer of adult education. His circulat¬
ing schools were the most important
experiment in religious education in the
18th century, not only in Wales but in
Britain and her dominions. Photos show:
Opposite page, portrait of Griffith Jones
now in the Museum of the Carmarthen¬
shire Antiquarian Society; Far left,
fascimile of title page of Welch Piety,
a collection of several accounts of the
circulating schools from their start in
1737 until 1753. (It bears the auto¬
graph of Bridget Bevan, the greatest
collaborator of Griffith Jones; Left,
Llanddowror Church, of which Jones was
Rector for 45 years (1716 to 1761).
Photos courtesy National Library of Wal«
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
THE MAN WHO TAUGHT HIS
NATION TO READ ^t^;
record of his being hostile to churchmen with Methodist
leanings.
His schools were badly equipped and much of his time
was taken up with appeals for new impressions of the
Welsh Bible and suitable books for instruction. What was
available for him was hardly better than the English
"battledores" of the period, and in themselves they were
of very little help. For this reason the careful selection
and training of the masters was all-Important.
By modern standards the contribution of Griffith Jones
to national education looks very slight, but in its day it
fulfilled a truly national demand and that is why the
schools were so well attended.
Between 1737, when he began the work, and 1761, the
year of his death, no fewer than 3,495 schools were held
with 158,237 scholars attending them. When we re¬
member that most of the masters had many more pupils
attending in the evening than in the day classes, it is fair
to compute a grand total of at least 350,000 to 400,000
scholars, a figure that is accepted by the best authorities.
When !we consider that the whole population of Wales in
the middle of the eighteenth century was about 400,000,
the figures go to prove beyond doubt that this remarkable
pioneer working almost singlehanded, realized his dream
of teaching a whole nation to read in his own lifetime.
Lonely pioneer of adult education
When we consider the far-reaching scope of the ser¬
vice given, for every county in Wales was amply
catered for; when we note, too, the administrative
difficulties, the constant appeal for books, the raising of
funds, the training of teachers, the handling of endless
correspondence, the publication of the well-documented
annual reports, it is difficult to realize that all this was
planned and carried out by a man racked with asthma
who had already passed his fiftieth year at its inception.
His faith, ardour and courage are almost Pauline in their
grandeur. Unaffected by cynical enemies, undeterred by
the coolness of those in high places who should have been
among the first to help him, this lonely pioneer tolled on
and almost single-handed saved a nation and its language
from perishing. It was his achievement to bring into the
homes of the people the power to benefit by the rich prose
of Bishop William Morgan's translation of the Bible. In
a letter to a fellow-clergyman, December 24, 1744, he
reveals his passion for his native language:
"I was born a Welshman, and have not yet unlearned the
simple Honesty and Unpoliteness of my Mother Tongue;
nor acquired the oiliness of the English Language, which
is now refined to such a degree, that a great Part of it
is near akin to Flattery and Dissimulation." As David
Williams has rightly pointed out in his recent book, The
History of Modern Wales "it would be difficult to
exaggerate the greatness of Griffith Jones' work. His
conception of education was admittedly narrow, but he
should be judged only on the basis of his motive, which
was to save men's souls. Nor did he show any great
originality in ideas. His greatness lay in his remarkable
powers of organization and in his ability to translate his
purpose into practical form on a grand scale. He helped
to make the Welsh a literate nation, and his circulating
schools were the most important experiment in religious
education in the eighteenth century not only in Wales but
in Britain and all the British dominions."
We can go further and claim for him a place as an
honoured pioneer of adult education. His schools catered
for all ages. Before the end of the century Wales had its
own peculiar Sunday Schools which to this day are for
adults as well as children; such were the humble nurseries
which provided a strong and abiding framework for the
development of adult education throughout the land.
22
Louis Braille
Louis Braille unlocked the door to
education for millions of blind men
and women throughout the world
when he invented his simple "touch"
alphabet of raised dots. The son of a
French sadler, Braille was born near
Paris in 1809 and lost his sight at the
age of three. In his day the lot of the
blind was almost as tragic and hopeless
as it had always been in the past.
One mark of progress, however, had
© Association Valentin Haüy, Pans fo^ the opening of the world's first
school for blind children in Paris in 1784. Braille went there as
a pupil and eventually became a teacher (he also became one of the
best organists in Paris). At the school a system of embossed
letters was used to teach the children to read. Then came the
revolutionary idea of a French army officer, Charles Barbier
de la Serre, to represent letters by raised dots. But Barbier's
system was complicated (it was a code and had to be deciphered)
and it occupied too much space. So Braille reduced this system
of 12 dot squares to six dots which could be felt by Ithe finger tip
at one go, and he dropped the cipher, working out various combi¬
nations of dots to form the alphabet. When Braille died in 1852
he had no idea that his system would be universally adopted by
blind people, and he even had difficulty in getting the method
accepted as the official medium of instruction in his own school.
Yet today, without the Braille system, the world's 7,000,000 sight¬
less would undoubtedly be deprived of the most powerful key
to human freedom and scholarship ever devised for the blind.
Jaime Torres Bodet
When Jaime Torres Bodet became Di¬
rector-General of Unesco, in 1948, he
had already behind him a distinguished
career as poet, novelist, essayist, edu¬
cationist, diplomat and international
statesman. One of the high points of
his career and certainly one of the
most brilliant phases in the history of
Mexican education was the period
(from 1943 to 1946) when he served as
his country's Minister of Education
and initiated and developed a nation- unesco
wide campaign against illiteracy. No campaign of such scope or
originality had ever before been undertaken in Mexico. Torres
Bodet appealed to all educated Mexicans to become "emergency"
teachers for at least one of their illiterate countrymen, and he
toured towns and villages arousing and inspiring the people. Soon,
over 60,000 collective teaching centres were organized and lawyers,
doctors, business men, industrialists, farmers and landowners led
by the President of Mexico, Avila Camacho, and his wife, joined
in as teachers to make the campaign a success. Special wall
newspapers were printed and over 10,000,000 elementary reading
books and primers began flooding the country. For those of
Mexico's Indians who did not speak Spanish, Torres Bodet had
special primers prepared in their languages and where these lan¬
guages had never before been written down he called in teams of
linguists to do this. When the results were tabulated after only
two years of work, it was found that over 1,200,000 Mexicans had
been taught to read and write. The successful campaigns encourag¬
ed other Latin American countries to adopt similar methods.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
Domingo Faustino
Sarmiento
Official Argentine photo
Domingo Faustino Sarmiento was one
of the best-known of Argentina's 19th-
century writers, but his great life-work
was the creation from practically noth¬
ing of a national school system which
laid the foundations of all education in
his country and made it literate. A clear
and able writer, Sarmiento was above
all a prolific essayist and pamphleteer,
though he is also known for longer
works such as Facundo and Recuerdos de provincia (published in
French in the Unesco programme of translations of Representative
Works). As a youth he felt the urge to teach and when he
was 20 he opened Argentina's first school for adults, at San
Francisco del Monte. Because of his political activities he was
several times forced into exile in Chile. Here, as in his own
country, he steadfastly kept up his educational work, setting up
schools to which workers came in the evenings and on Sundays.
This resolute educator was convinced that for his people the true
path to freedom lay in the alphabet : "A literate people is the
strongest rampart against dictatorship," he said. Towards the end
of his long life (1811 to 1888) Sarmiento, who had fought fiercely
against the regime of the Argentine dictator, Rosas, found himself
elected President of the Argentine Republic. He summed up the
entire purpose of his life in one phrase when he declared : "We
must lay the foundations of the Republic, the government of
tomorrow and there can be but one base for this the school."
James Yen
During the first World War a young
Chinese volunteer student-teacher came
to France to work as an interpreter
among the 200,000 Chinese workers
serving with the Allied armies and in
war production. He found they were
completely isolated, unable to write to
their relatives or read the newspapers.
So he started literacy classes. That
was the beginning of the Chinese
Movement for Mass Education. When
The Press Association inc. the young teacher, James Yen (he
later became popularly known as "Jimmy") went back to China
he put his experiences in France to use when he set out to
"create citizens through education." He launched a "basic
Chinese,*" reducing the 40,000 or so characters in the Chinese
language to some 1,300, and the leaders of his movement worked
hard among the people to create what they called "a climate of
willingness to go to school.*" To supervise its programme of
one hour's lesson each day for four months, the movement even¬
tually had a service of 100,000 teachers, all unpaid volunteers.
It constituted a veritable revolution in China for it broke down
the thousand-year barriers and brought together coolies and
scholars. In 1930 it centered all its efforts on a county of
400,000 people, it opened demonstration schools and it went on to
use newly-discovered literacy to attack the fundamental evils of
sickness and poverty. The action of this pioneer movement gra¬
dually spread throughout China and paved the way for the Gov¬
ernment's adult education or rural reconstruction movement.
Frank C. Laubach Manoel Lourenço Filho
Standing in a jungle clearing and sur¬
rounded by some 40 or 50 people, a
tall man unrolled one of several charts
he held under his arm. The faces of
people lit up with anticipation.
They had come to hear a man who
said he could teach them to read. The
man was Frank C. Laubach. The
place was Ethiopia, but it could just
as well have been any of the more
than 60 countries where Frank Lau¬
bach has been combatting illiteracy for
more than a quarter of a century. Born in Pennsylvania, U.S.A.,
and trained as a sociologist and as a missionary, Frank Laubach
found his life's work while living in the Philippines. He discovered
that the Moro tribesmen of the interior had never had a written
language and so began his work of organizing a simple system
of charts and key words, teaching methods which would enable
people to learn their own language. Since then he has, as he
puts it, '"made lessons" in over 239 tongues and dialects. On
large charts he prints a phonetic alphabet having a symbol for
each sound of the language he is teaching. Key syllables and
words are visualized by pictures. Wherever he goes, Frank
Laubach enlists the aid of local teachers and linguists. Once he
has developed materials and helped launch the campaign, the
people themselves carry it forward. Having learned to read, most
persons are anxious to teach others. Laubach has dramatized this
technique with the phrase "Each one teach one", and this has
become a method which has helped his campaigns to win millions
from illiteracy in Asia, the Middle East, Africa and South America.
Brazil began a full-scale attack on illi¬
teracy in 1947 by launching a nation¬
wide adult education campaign. The
country's tremendous and sparsely
populated area and an adult illiteracy
figure of over 55 per cent created
problems whose solution called for bold
conceptions and methods of fundamen¬
tal education and for vigorous leader¬
ship. The man who gave leadership
and driving force to the campaign
was Manoel Lourenço Filho. One of unesco
Brazil's leading educators, author and professor of psychology,
Lourenço Filho had already devoted his efforts for more than
a quarter of a century to the cause of education in his country.
The cost of the first three years of the adult education campaign,
100 millions cruzeiros (55,000,000), was justified by the results.
In 1947, there were 10,416 "Campaign" schools in operation;
in the following year, 14,300, and in 1949 the number reached
15,300. In the first three years about 2,000,000 adults and
adolescents enrolled and more than 1,000,000 people were taught
to read and write. Brazil's approach to fundamental education
problems was watched with interest in other countries: the careful
balance maintained between school and adult education; the
building on a solid basis of statistical fact and the linking
together of the varied interests of communities in literacy, better
health and farming. Lourenço Filho's successful leadership of
the campaign won him international recognition, and at the 1949
Inter-American Seminar on Illiteracy and Adult Education, he was
hailed as El Maestro de las Americas (Teacher of the Americas.)
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
GUIDES AND LEADERS
FOR THE VILLAGERS
OF LATIN AMERICA
Key personnel for national fundamental education programmes, including
literacy campaigns, in Latin American countries have been trained since
I 951 in the regional fundamental education and production centre, opened
by the Mexican Government and Unesco at Patzcuaro, Mexico. The
philosophy of this centre was defined by its director, Lucas Ortiz, when
he declared: "It is no use teaching a man to read and write unless you can
convince him it will help solve the problems of his daily life. We teach
literacy when we teach health or home economics or agriculture." To
teach all these things men and women student-teachers from the centre
(CREFAL) have gone into villages around Patzcuaro for "on-the-spot"
training. In these communities they found the same problems of illiteracy
and poverty that existed in their own countries. An experimental literacy
centre has been arranged in a village close to Patzcuaro and here classes
in reading and writing are given to illiterate and semi-literate adults. These
classes offer a practical testing ground for teaching methods and materials.
Special courses have been given to CREFAL students who were to be
responsible for organizing national literacy programmes in their own
countries. Right, CREFAL student makes street name signs for village
of Santa-Ana, where previously there had been none because most of the
villagers were illiterate. Far right, student teacher from Patzcuaro explains
meaning of exhibit used in literacy campaigns to villagers of San Gregorio.
Photos CREFAL
: THE WATERWHEEL-For the
past two years an attractively-presented wall news¬
paper has been gaining a growing readership in the
villages surrounding the Arab States Fundamental
Education Centre (ASFEC) in the Nile Delta (see
opposite page). Each time it appears, the people
rush to read itor have it read to themand gather
.together to discuss its contents. For Al-Sakieh, (The
Waterwheel) as it is called, is their newspaper, pro¬
duced for them by the students and staff of ASFEC.
Al-Sakieh not only gives new-literate adults a chance
to practice their reading and encourages illiterate
ones to follow their example, it also broadens the
horizon of the village people by keeping them in
touch with local, national, regional and world events.
It also explains the work the centre is doing in the
villages, and, finally, it is an excellent training oppor¬
tunity for ASFEC students, teaching them how to
produce such materials and showing them how they
can keep contact with the people among whom they
are working. Above, masthead of the wall news¬
paper. Its title, The Waterwheel was chosen because
of the pleasant associations this has for the farmers.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
Photos ASFEC
TEACHERS FOR THE
PEOPLES OF THE
ARAB COUNTRIES
Sirs-el-Layyan is a large, straggling village In the Nile Delta some 40 miles
north of Cairo, where in 1952, the Egyptian Government and Unesco
opened a training centre (12 and 18-month courses) for the men and
women who will be leaders in fundamental education in ten Arab countries.
Since then, social centres, rural schools and agricultural and health units
have grown up in this densely populated district which has progressively
become a model experimental area. The villages round Sirs-el-Layyan
offer a testing ground for methods and materials which are developed in
the centre. In them are found cross-sections of the kinds of living condi¬
tions found, with many variations, in Arab countries. A major part of
the experimental work concerns literacy, developed into a programme
of general education which aims at educating villagers as individuals and
as citizens. This programme is closely related to community development
projects in such fields as health and agriculture, carried out in the "labo¬
ratory" villages. It also includes the production of "readers", literacy
"follow-up" materials, and a series of "Teach Yourself" books for people,
particularly women, who often cannot attend classes. Far left, listening
to the newsnewly-literate people are proud to demonstrate their skill
and those still illiterate are encouraged and stimulated to attend classes
when they see how quickly their friends have learned to read. Left, student
teacher from Sirs-el-Layyan holds literacy class for village women.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS FOR THE NEW READING PUBLIC
by J.Ë. Morpurgo
Once the reading-interest of a newly-literate person has
been aroused, the production of suitable follow-up litera¬
ture becomes the key to his development as a useful citi¬
zen. This is the concept behind an important UNESCO project
to encourage the production of reading materials for a tremen¬
dous area containing about 500 million people in South Asia.
Under this programme, Initiated in 1955 and now being put
into practice In countries like Burma, Ceylon, India, and Pakis¬
tan, research studies have been made, model books for new
literates prepared, authors and editors have been awarded
training and study fellowships and regional meetings of book
production specialists have been held. The most recent of
these was a "workshop" seminar in Rangoon which gave writers,
illustrators and printer-publishers a chance to discuss their
individual yet Interlocking problems. Mr. J. E. Morpurgo, Direc¬
tor of the National Book League, Great Britain, who was director
of the Seminar, discusses below some of the problems involved
In providing the right books for a vast new reading public.
The struggle to bring about the state of health which
Is literacy by ridding the world of the disease called
illiteracy has been going on for centuries. What is
new is the geographical spread of the wish for literacy
and the inevitable impatience with the methods of long-
drawn therapy.
I write as one who is not at all certain that it is possible
to abandon the patient processes which move a nation
generation by generation nearer to complete literacy. I
have my doubts as to whether it is possible to cut short
the centuries-absorbing business of improving education
and of making it available to all, of developing a tradition
of sound book publishing and bookselling and of creating
the political and economic atmosphere in which publish¬
ing and bookselling can survive. I feel that the desire
to read must be created and with it the opportunity. I
am almost certain that to provide the opportunity it is
necessary to work towards an Improvement of public and
school library services.
There is an argument at least, and one held in quite
responsible circles, that the whole fashionable business of
concentrating on the new literates and new readers is a
mistake, even for the new literates and new readers
themselves, and that it is only by ensuring the easy use
of books by those who are already attracted to books that
one can hope to improve the general standard of literacy
in the nations. This argument has as part of its justifi¬
cation much of the evidence in the history of Western
Europe, where it has been the improvement of facilities
for reading among the middle classes which has ulti¬
mately brought about complete literacy.
All these arguments for gradualism sit easily, I admit,
on one who comes from a country which (in census
terms at least) has achieved universal literacy; for
countries where the will to literacy is growing it is ne¬
cessary to look for abbreviations of the historical process,
even if it is essential to guard carefully the view that
there are some parts of the process which cannot be aban¬
doned.
It is not enough to teach a child or an adult to read
would seem obvious. Without the will to read and
the chance to read, the mere mechanical ability to spell
out words slips back into uselessness and may vanish
altogether. Even in those countries which have healthy
literacy statistics a considerable proportion of the func¬
tionally literate are emotionally illiterate. They glean
no advantage from their ability either in ideas, practical
improvement, image or pleasure, because, although they
can read they never do read. Worse still and more damning
for the literacy campaigns, there is in many countries a
considerable relapse into functional illiteracy even among
those who have just completed schooling or adult literacy
classes because so many who have acquired new skills do
not have the will or the chance to practise them.
26
On my recent tour through Asia and especially at the
Unesco Regional Seminar ön the Production of Reading
Materials for New Literates and the New Reading Public
(Rangoon, November, 1957), I gathered the impression
that among those primarily responsible for grasping and
holding the attention of the new public authors, publish¬
ers, illustrators there is a majority which would share
my view that the principal requirement for books for the
new reading public is that they should be attractive in
subject matter, style, production, quality and price.
Any sympathy which these book-professionals felt for
the prevalent view that it is necessary to combine the
task of creating readers with the task of enlightening
those readers on matters of policy or social education
vanished before their conviction (which I share) that even
the most sophisticated reader must be bullied before he
will read books about smallpox or drainage, and that the
first task of any reading materials project is to persuade
people to read and to hold them reading without slipping
sideways and even backwards into other forms of social
improvement.
All accept that it is possible to write a book on
smallpox which rings with the magic of art and
excitement, but it is extremely difficult, and to the diffi¬
culty is added the unattractiveness of the subject matter.
Would it not be better to trap readers with materials
which they are likely to find seductive? The range of
subject matter must vary from country to country. In
Asia I would venture that it would include religion, legend,
adventure, love-stories (as everywhere else in the world!)
and practical farming tips.
To produce these attractive books it is necessary to
train and encourage good professional publishers,
printers and illustrators. To bring them to the public
it is essential that we should find methods of creating pu¬
blicity, distribution outlets and sales points which do not
exist in many parts of the world. Again I would venture
a personal opinion which has the support of many who
were with me at the Rangoon Seminar: giving away
books or pamphlets is very often equivalent to wasting
them. The reading habit is not firm in the individual
until he learns to work for his reading, either in terms
of having to pay for it, or at very least in terms of having
to look for it on library shelves.
I know that in many countries wage levels are low and
the chances of working up much spending on an "essen¬
tial luxury" such as books small. Unfortunately it is often
these same countries which have a small public purse, but,
with most of my friends who came to Rangoon, I would
urge that it is as important to .spend the limited public
funds on providing free school books, on building up
school and public libraries and on publicizing the advan¬
tages of reading, as to go in for production programmes
which too often involve large-scale investment.
The book has come in quantity to many parts of the
world at about the same time as other and easier forms
of communication. Radio, the cinema, the television are
not enemies of the printed word indeed they are allies
but I would urge that they lack the timelessness and the
universality which give the book its peculiar virtue. It
is not possible to turn back a radio set or to read a film
at your own speed. The thought and the skills of all the
nations cannot penetrate so effectively into all corners of
the world by any other means than by the printed word.
To provide the printed word in sufficient quantities for
the new public demands active professionalism and it is
perhaps comforting that the Unesco Regional Seminar at
Rangoon, saw as the greatest need of the countries of
Asia not just more books but better training facilities for
publishers, printers, authors, illustrators and book distri¬
butors. Without these training facilities it is unlikely
that we will be able to provide the right books for the
new audience.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
de :
FABLES
!NOS VILLAGES
O
mm.mi in-.i,ii t in. i.i Toii.k
Uipnillf fljmen Mu»)
V |II7 I.'tit.-. I'fV.
AFTER CARE of newly literate people must include a steady supply of graded, Interesting and attractively-presented reading material. This is an
Important part of the work of "literature bureaux", the specialized central agencies which more and more countries are setting up (often with assist¬
ance from Unesco see opposite page) to deal with all aspects of teaching, research and book production. Above, front covers of some publications in
different languages produced In Asia, Africa and Latin America: (I) Hindi (2) Burmese (3) Spanish (4) FrenchBelgian Congo (5) ArabicThe Sudan.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Letters to th d i t o r
Sir,
Please do more numbers like Octo¬
ber 1957 (Rights for 900 Million Chil¬
dren) to try and help save the children
of the world. It is so easy to forget
people starve when one is not hungry,
and people must be reminded all the
time.
Mark Anderson
Walchwil, Switzerland
Sir,
My wife does an hour morning pro¬
gramme over our local radio station
and does a bi-weekly column in our
local newspaper. We work together a
great deal and she has passed along as
much information as she can from The
Unesco Courier. She is interested in
the U.N. and although her coverage is
not large in a metropolitan or national
sense, she does believe sincerely that we
do not hear enough about the positive
contributions being made towards peace
through humanitarian deeds and thought
John Haig
Belleville, Canada
Sir,
A group of us (all young parents)
were chatting about what we're going
to teach our youngsters in the difficult
future. I suggested that we should
give them The Unesco Courier and
the book, "The Family of Man" (see
The Unesco Courier, February, 1956).
In these they'll find the keys to toler¬
ance, understanding and, if it's vital,
contentment. And the more I read
your magazines the more I believe this
to be true. There seems a whole philo¬
sophy, a world of understanding, in
what they contain. It's a pity they're
not part of every school library and a
must for high school children... It seems
that there could be a day put aside all
over the world for something like "Man¬
kind Day". On this day we'd remem¬
ber all those who have given of them¬
selves, their cash etc. for mankind.
We'd think of every person (arts, crafts,
social sphere, etc.) who has made life
better, easier and contributed towards
mankind's progress. It need not be a
holiday but articles, films, TV shows,
radio works, etc., could be sent out to
mark the occasion. It would be a day
on which we'd think of who we are,
what we are, what others have
done for us, what many are sacri¬
ficing now, what's ahead and we'd think
about being human beings not Austra¬
lian, American or Russian, or black or
white, Christian or Jew. There's so
much each nation owes to others, whites
owe non-white and religions owe
each other. Schools could do much on
this day to get ideas about mankind
over. There could be a travelling exhi¬
bition with special features showing
how not one man, not one religion, na¬
tion or government gave us the many
blessings, health advances and good
things we enjoy just as not one man
or group has led us to the brink of
chaos. This day would be for- every¬
one to restore faith in ourselves and
show all are important. I have also a
few suggestions for Courier articles :
Oil-search ; how atomic energy will
react ; where oil is, its importance ; New
Zealand's Maori people no race prob¬
lem there ; Music all over world how
it differs, instruments used, folk music,
how used to train deaf, etc. People at
Play different sports organized and
played all over the world.
Stan Marks
Melbourne, Australia
Sir,
As a teacher I find great joy in your
excellent issues, especially the numbers
devoted to a special topic. But I often
regret that measures, weights and tem¬
peratures 'are generaly given in Anglo-
Saxon indications only. Would it be
possible to add the international terms
in brackets? Surely the English edi¬
tion has many readers outside U.S.A.
and U.K., especially in Scandinavia,
where we have only a very short¬
ened edition in our own language.
May I at the same time suggest a new
topic ? the work done by the U.N. to
fight the misuse of narcotics. It seems
that a lot of information has been col¬
lected on the production, effects, trade
in, use and misuse of ' narcotics and
of the fight against illicit traffic.
Wouldn't it be possible to have a num¬
ber on this ?
Birthe Levin Hansen
Hellerup, Denmark
Sir,
Dr. H.V. Evatt, one-time President
of the United Nations Assembly, with
whom I talked in Sydney recently, ex¬
pressed his determination to ensure a
gracious correction of the great case of
injustice inflicted upon the Australian
Aborigines, decimated from 300,000 to
70,000 in less than two centuries. The
immediate task objectives are (1) Aus¬
tralian and overseas scholarships for
Aboriginal pupils, (2) publicity encoura¬
ging the interest and initiative of indi¬
vidual citizens, and (3) co-ordination of
reports which will form the basis for a
Constitutional review of Aboriginal sta¬
tus. I hope the famous Prague Conser-
vatorium of Music and several Ameri¬
can Schools will be among the first
overseas institutions to welcome a few
selected Aboriginal boys and girls.
Some of your readers may take interest
in this project and provide inspiration.
Frank Sifer
Hobart, Australia
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom th« English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry of Educ¬
ation, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C'., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, 15 rue
du Tilleul, Genval (Brabant). I 00 Belgian
francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. Georges Street,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O* Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
28
FINLAND. Akateemlnen Kirjakauppa,
» 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kléber, Paris, 16'. CCP.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb lür Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nlcol Road,
Bomba/ I; 17 Chlttaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 3 6a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386. New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co.. Scindia
House. New Delhi; Raikamal Publicat¬
ions Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby Road,
Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P.O.B. 4154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commisslonaria San-
sonl, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruien Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashl, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. - N.V. Martinus Ni'j-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Qjiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press. 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. - A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
6.50 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook.
Tangier,
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA.- S.P.C.K. (Burma)
549, Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. - Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. "
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïga
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
POSTAGE STAMPS HELP
TO FIGHT
rtA¿jtjmuft fay&ndn/
by C.W. Hill
MEM
Peru is carrying
out a National
Education Plan
one of whose most
important as- ,
pects is rural
ed ucation . As
sixty-fou r per
cent of the popu¬
lation is rural,
the Government's
efforts are direc¬
ted towards the
inhabitants of the
sierra and the
montana rural
children, adoles¬
cents and adults,
in the school, the
home and the community. Compulsory tax
stamps, like the one shown here, help to pay
for these Peruvian educational campaigns.
H'l'l*M'h1M#li7Jii
[ÄMPÄHHÄdeEDUEÄCAOdeADULTDS f
Carrying out large-scale campaigns for adult
education is no easy task in a country like
Brazil where there are immense tracts with a
population of about one per square mile. But
this is what the Government has been doing
since 1947 after statistics revealed that over
50 per cent of the adult population was illiterate.
Deciding on a mass solution, the Government
initiated a plan for opening 10,000 even¬
ing schools for adult and adolescent illitera¬
tes. Stamp symbolizes light of education.
CORREOSOELECUADOR
AEREO
S/2
Stam p from
Ecuador, show¬
ing an Indian
being taught the
alphabet, recalls
that the coun¬
try's lite racy
efforts are d i-
rected specially
towards Andes'
villages where
most of Indians
(about 55",, of
country's popu¬
lation) live. In
1942 journalists
launched a na-
ri tion-wide fight
against illiteracy ,
using press and radio to give campaign wide
publicity. Two series of stamps were issued
to support the scheme. A 1950 census reveal¬
ed encouraging progress in literacy rates.
Removing the bandage of illiteracy
symbolizes, on this Mexican stamp,
the large-scale educational effort
made by Mexico in recent years.
One of the most remarkable achieve¬
ments was the nation-wide cam¬
paign initiated and developed bet¬
ween 1943 and 1946 by Jaime
Torres Bodet. Minister of Education
who later (1948-53) became Direc¬
tor General of Unesco. (See page 22)
CRRPRHfl HRCiOWRL PRO RLFRBETIZR£
CORREOS O
MEXICO Z
TALLERES OE IMP OE EST Y VALORES
££r-***-*ï he postage stamps of a nation are a picture gallery of its glories. They
I depict in miniature its famous men and women, the great events of its
history, its organizations, its industries, its natural wonders", writes
Mr. Arthur E. Summerfield, Postmaster-General of the United States of America,
in his foreword to a booklet published recently by the American Post Office.
With this assessment of the general educational value of postage stamps there
can be little quarrel, and it is therefore not surprising that stamps should also be
used for purposes even more precisely educational in character. Among such
purposes have been the raising of funds for schools and universities, the dissemina¬
tion of road safety propaganda, the encouragement of friendly correspondence
between young people of different countries, and, perhaps most important of all,
the attack on illiteracy.
In Mexico, 43 % of all men, women and children over six years of age are illiter¬
ate. Because of the increase in her population the number of Mexico's illiterates
was reduced only imperceptibly in forty years, from 7,636,000 in 1900 to
7,544,000 in 1940. Immediately after the Second World War the Mexican Govern¬
ment began a new attack on this recalcitrant problem and one of its first steps
was to issue, in November, 1945, a series of twelve postage stamps, all in the
same striking design. Inscribed Campaña Nacional pro Alfabetización the
stamps showed hands removing the bandage of illiteracy from the eyes of an adult.
Quitemos la venda! exclaimed the slogan at the top of the stamps. A year
later a single Mexican issue celebrated the progress of the campaign, its design
showing a man, no longer blindfold, learning the alphabet.
Brazil is another country where illiteracy among adults is an urgent problem.
In 1900 over six million Brazilians above the age of 15 could neither read nor
write and in 1940, because of the increase in the country's population, the number
of illiterates had risen to over thirteen million. As part of its plan to reduce
illiteracy among adults Brazil issued in 1949 a 60-centavos stamp inscribed
Campanha de Educaçâo de Adultos, and symbolizing the light of education.
Among other South American countries which have issued stamps to help in
the fight against illiteracy is Ecuador, whose 1953 series depicted various educa¬
tional activities among children and adults. In Peru a special 3-centavos stamp
was issued in 1950 in aid of the National Education Fund. Its design symbolized
the light of knowledge, and the use of the stamp on all mail was made compulsory.
Certain countries have considered that a simplification of their alphabet would
reduce illiteracy by making reading and writing easier to learn. Thirty years ago
Kemal Atatiirk adopted a Latinized alphabet for Turkey and a series of stamps
was issued in 1938 to mark the tenth anniversary of the change. Their design
portrayed Kemal Ataturk himself teaching the new alphabet, an action which may
have to be emulated in other countries before illiteracy is vanquished.
Ataturk, founder of the Turkish
Republic, initiated a striking edu¬
cational reform in I 928 when he
introduced the Latin alphabet
into his country to replace Arabic
script. On this stamp Ataturk
Is depicted teaching the new
alphabet. Within a short time
over two million more people
had learned to read and write.
Since then Turkey's efforts to
vanquish illiteracy have been con¬
centrated in its 40,000 villages.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Science has the answer
DO BATS FIND
THEIR WAY BY RADAR?
by Gerald Wendt
Many insects emit shrill, high-pitched sounds and
some of them are probably too high for the human
ear to hear but it is not known that they use them
as a guide in flying. Bats are not blind but their
sight is so poor that they can do little more than
distinguish a brighter from a fainter light and
locate its general direction. Thus they can
distinguish daybreak and nightfall. But they direct
their flight by their very sensitive sense of hearing.
They emit a very high-pitched sound, hear the
echoes of that sound from nearby objects, and judge
the direction and the distance of the object from
the nature of the echo. The sound has been
recorded by the use of microphones and has been
found to be about two octaves higher than the
highest sound the human ear can detect. Such
short sound-waves can be reflected from objects
that are too small or too thin to echo ordinary
audible sound. If bats are gagged so that they
cannot give out the sound or if- they are deafened
so that they cannot hear it, they are unable, to detect
obstacles and crash into them in the dark.
Radar also makes use of echoes but it is not
correct to say that bats use "'a sort of radar".
Radar waves are not sound waves. They are electro¬
magnetic waves, or short radio waves, which are
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
transmitted and reflected as light waves are and at
the speed of light. After they are reflected from an
object, such as a plane in the sky that may be
200 miles away, they are focussed on a fluorescent
screen and there make a visible picture, as on a
television screen.
More remarkable than the ability of bats to fly
safely in the dark is their ability to return to their
home roost or cave at night from distances as great
as 60 miles. They do not use their eyes, for tests
have shown that fully blindfolded bats arrive home
even more successfully than others. Their echo-
sense is also no explanation because they can hardly
detect echoes from objects more than 30 feet away.
Yet they reach home at their normal flying speed
of 10 miles an hour and so must fly there almost
direct. The only explanation seems to be that they
become as familiar with their home area through
their sense of hearing as birds and other animals
do by sight.
Is it true that antibiotics gradually become less effective against bacteria and
some insecticides become less effective against insects ?
Yes, any one antibiotic or insecticide can lose its
effectiveness against any one colony of bacteria or
of insects, respectively. This is because, in the case
of both bacteria and insects, many thousands or
even millions of individual bacteria and insects are
exposed to the drug or the chemical. Most of them
are killed but some of them do not get enough to
kill them. The few that are able to survive learn
to live with the drug or the chemical and, when
they reproduce, the next generation is so accustomed
to the drug that it can withstand a large amount of
it. So they are harder to kill and their resistance
to the drug or chemical makes them immune. For
this reason, it is usually wise to use enough of the
drug or chemical to kill all the bacteria or insects
in a colony. Those that have become immune to
one antibiotic or insecticide, however, are not
immune to another. For this reason, a second
treatment is often given with a different kind in
order to kill those that escaped the original treat¬
ment or became immune to it. A large number of
both antibiotics and of insecticides is now available
for this purpose.
Can plants be acclimatized as men and animals can ? For instance, can
tropical plants be gradually adapted for growth in cold climates ?
Man is the only animal truly adaptable to any
climate, but that is only because he has the
intelligence to protect himself from extremes by
building houses, wearing suitable clothes, lighting
fires for warmth, using fans for cooling and
changing his diet. Many animals can also make
moderate adjustments to a change of climate,
especially those species that make homes by
burrowing underground to protect themselves from
either the heat of the sun or the cold of winter.
But those animals that are best adapted to extreme
or particular conditions do not survive under
adverse conditions. Those that have heavy fur to
protect themselves from the cold such as polar
bears cannot endure hot weather because they
have no way of keeping themselves cool. Others
with bare skins like the elephant and the hippo¬
potamus can keep cool under tropic conditions but
are unable to stay warm in snow and ice. Most
animals are also equipped for hunting and eating a
certain kind of food, such as fish or underwater
plants or rabbits or snakes, and starve when they
cannot find them unless they are fed by man.
But in the course of many thousands of years
animals have wandered over the face of the earth
and have often adapted themselves to a different
environment by natural selection over many
generations. Thus different species of some animal
families, like cats, dogs, bears, deer, mice and even
camels, can live under climatic conditions that are
very different from those of other species of the
same family.
Plants are in general much less adaptable. They
are well fitted for certain conditions of moisture, of
temperature and of sunshine but will seldom survive
a change, or if they do survive, they will not bloom
or produce seeds and so die out. Juicy, thin-skinned
water-plants and swamp plants soon die if they are
deprived of water. On the other hand, the hard-
shelled cactus and other desert plants are unable
to cope with much water. The broad-leaved plants
are fitted for life in the shade of trees and seldom
do well in direct sunlight. But narrow, thin-leaved
plants, like the different grasses, are fitted to grow
in direct sunshine and will not survive under trees
or in the forest, because they do not get enough sun.
All leaves are killed by frost, that is, by a tem¬
perature of less than 32° Fahrenheit. In cold
climates a plant must either have oily needles
instead of leaves like the pines and spruces or it
must shed its leaves and concentrate its sap under¬
ground during the winter, as most plants of the
temperate zones do. One other device of many
temperate-zone plants is to produce hard, dry seeds
which survive the cold while the mother-plant dies,
so that a new generation appears each year. Since
tropical plants cannot do any of these three things,
they never survive a frost.
However, tropical plants can live outside the
tropics if the temperature does not reach freezing
point. But if they do, they grow much more slowly,
do not attain their normal size, and either produce
no flowers or their flowers produce no seeds. The
lowered temperature and especially the short warm
season do not allow them time enough to develop.
But equally important is the presence of insects to
fertilize the flowers. Many are dependent on
certain special varieties of insects to carry the pollen
from one flower to another, and when they are
removed from their natural environment the
necessary insects are usually absent and no seeds
are formed. Nevertheless, without seeds or without
flowers, tropical plants can survive in dwarfed form
in cooler climates but not in cold ones.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
GUATEMALA'S PICTURE HOSPITAL
by Bertha Gasfer
Not much more than a bus ride out
from the busy modern capital of
Guatemala, some eight or nine miles
over the mountains as the crow flies, lies
a ghost town. For over two hundred years
Antigua the Old Town was capital
of the Spanish captaincy-general of Guate¬
mala, second in its time only to Mexico
and Peru. In the eighteenth century it was
the most populous city in Central America;
its university was third on the American
continent, its printing-house second ; and
the great bells rang unceasingly over the
city from more than a hundred imposing
churches and convents.
All this pride and magnificence came to
a sudden end one afternoon in lune 1773.
A catastrophic earthquake destroyed the
town, and reduced most of the buildings to
rubble. With the removal of the capital
to Guatemala City, Antigua fell into decay.
For a long time it was left to the poorest
elements of the population to eke out a
bare living in hovels among the ruins, until
coffee-growing restored a modest prosperity.
Today pretty little houses in ice-cream
pink and green stand side by side with Ba¬
roque facades in its cobbled streets. Glimp-
32
ses of tiled patios can be seen from under
the crumbling arcades. And everywhere,
in abandoned gardens and over alley walls,
drip yellow jasmine, white and golden
roses and the scarlet hibiscus, as the old
town drowses its past away in the siesta
hour.
Attempts to preserve something of that
past for future generations have been going
on for a considerable time. Several of
the ruined facades of ancient mansions
have been restored, and sculpture and
carvings retrieved. On a sunny day in
December 1956 in the ancient cloisters of
Capucine convent the only one to sur¬
vive the earthquake comparatively un¬
touched specimens of another aspect of
that past had been gathered together.
Propped against massive pillars, exposed
on easels, lying on trestle tables, were a
number of paintings. Many of them were
religious pictures of Madonnas and Magda-
lenes and other Biblical subjects which had
been hanging in the churches of Guatemala,
some of them from the ruins of Antigua.
Others were portraits of bygone dignitaries
of the Spanish colonial era, or nineteenth
century generals and personalities of the
young Republic. All of them were in bad
condition, discoloured, peeling, some of
them still showing the rents and slashes of
the 1773 earthquake.
Four men were looking at them, moving
them to the light to inspect them, examining
the torn canvas and peeling paint. The
chief among them, Helmut Ruhemann, was
one of the best known experts on picture
restoration in the world. Originally in
charge of restoration work at the State Art
Galleries in Berlin, and later consultant to
the National Gallery in London until his
retirement two years ago, Mr. Ruhemann
has restored paintings by Leonardo da
Vinci, Rembrandt, Bellini and many other
famous artists, besides devising methods
and techniques of restoration, and training
students in their use. This was for him
the beginning of a three months' mission
for Unesco, under its programme of aid
to member states, to make a survey of
colonial paintings in Guatemala, and help
the country to preserve these records of its
historical past.
The three people with him, one a youth
of sixteen, followed his every move with
closest attention. For Mr. Ruhemann was
there not only to survey the paintings, but
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1958
also to train a small number of Guatemalan
artists in the technique of restoration, so
they could carry on the work after his
return to England. There had been many
applicants, but there was not work to justify
the selection of more than three, and Carlos
Morales, Luis Alvarez and his son Alberto
Luis Alvarez were the ones chosen.
The work of restoring the pictures select¬
ed was carried out in Guatemala City,
with the assistance and support of the
Ministry of Fine Arts and the directors of
the national museums and art schools, and
with equipment and material provided by
Unesco. Theoretical exposition and prac¬
tical training went hand-in-hand. "There
is no secret in modern restoration techni¬
ques", Mr. Ruhemann stressed, "but
without a thorough knowledge of correct
methods there is great danger of damaging
old pictures, and in fact, many great works
of art have been injured this way."
Mr. Ruhemann's three pupils followed
him step by step through the different pro¬
cesses. They were taught the first stage of
preservation, pasting tissue paper over the
canvas to hold the loose paint. Then the
picture was "lined", stuck to a new canvas
with the aid of a thermostatically controlled
electric iron. Afterwards it was cleaned
with a small swab on a stick, with a mix¬
ture of strong solvent and non-active diluent.
'"One of the trickiest jobs in my career",
recalled Mr. Ruhemann, "'was the task of
cleaning several Renoirs. It was risky too.
You' had to handle your swab in a certain
way or you ran the risk of removing
paint when you cleaned them." Old paint¬
ings in fact, declared Mr. Ruhemann,
presented a much less serious problem.
"The straight oil or egg paints used by the
masters of the Renaissance are much easier
to clean. From the eighteenth century on,
painters added soft resins to their colours
and the cleaning of their work was much
more delicate."
Finally came the re-touching. Most of
the pigments used to-day are the same as
those used in former times, and present
little difficulty. "But you have to be a
good painter for this stage of the work,"
said Mr. Ruhemann. "That is why you
have to choose your picture-restorers from
professional artists. Both M. Morales and
M. Alvarez were good painters. M. Al¬
varez in fact had been restoring paintings
for the Archbishop before I came, and his
son had been working with him on panel
work and gilding. I hope it is going to be
possible to arrange to send two of them
to Florence or London to complete their
training."
At the end of his stay in Guatemala, Mr.
. Ruhemann organised a small exhibition in
the School of Plastic Arts of the pictures
on which they had been working, to
demonstrate the techniques of restoration,
and the work achieved. An interested
public were able to see untreated pictures in
perfect or bad condition hung beside others
in various stages of restoration, repaired
but not cleaned, half-cleaned, and finally
completely restored, such as a picture of
the "Magdalene" dating from 1703. The
exhibition was a demonstration of what had
been achieved, and the training of three
restorers an assurance that the preservation
of Guatemala's historical and artistic past
in religious and secular painting would
continue.
The whole project has aroused such
interest that there is now some question of
a refresher course being organised in Ha¬
vana, where a magnificent new museum has
been built, to afford students from all the
South American and Central American
countries an opportunity of taking part.
Colonial art of Gua-
tamala is being
brought to light and
restored since Unesco
sent Helmut Ruhe-
mann, an expert res¬
torer, to this Central
American Republic.
During a three
months' mission
Ruhemann surveyed
colonial paintings, res¬
tored some of them
and prepared a train¬
ing programme for
Guatamalan restorers.
Left, student restorer
uses a special Iron to
transfer an old paint¬
ing to a new canvas.
Standing by easel, Hel¬
mut Ruhemann su¬
pervises cleaning of
18th century paint¬
ing of The Virgin
(the work also shown
on opposite page).
After preservation
techniques the next
process is to remove
the all dirty varnish
(opposite page). This
is cleaned away with
a swab dipped In a
mixture of acetone
and turpentine. Any
cracks or slashes are
filled in with putty
and retouching be¬
gins. Because a high
standard of painting
is needed, restorers
are usually chosen
from ranks of pro¬
fessional artists. Left,
Ruhemann, who has
restored many master¬
pieces, including da
Vinci's Virgin .of the
Rocks, gives a Guate¬
malan artist a les¬
son in retouching.
A pause for discussion
between Helmut Ru¬
hemann and his three
Guatemalan assistants
who followed him
step by step through
the restoration pro¬
cesses. (The youth
seated on left and the
man standing on right
are father and son.)
The work was carried
out in Guatemala City
with equipment and
materials provided by
Unesco, and the res¬
tored paintings were
later exhibited. The
portrait on the easel
is of Colonel Modesto
Méndez, the discove¬
rer of the great Maya
remains at Tikal.
UNESCO-Gay Grüner
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the UnescoNewsroom...
A;RT AT THE FRONTIER: Art
reproductions in colour should be
treated on the same basis as original
paintings, books, newspapers, educa¬
tional Alms and science equipment
which under a Unesco agreement are
now allowed duty-free into 26 coun¬
tries. This was urged at a recent
UNESCO-sponsored meeting in Gen¬
eva by government representatives
discussing wider application of the
Unesco "Free Flow" Agreement.
ARISTOTLE IN ARABIC : The
first complete translation into
Arabic of Aristotle's treatise on
"Politics" has been published in
Beirut in the Unesco series of
translations of great works. Other
classical authors already translated
into Arabic in the same series:
Descartes, Montesquieu, Pascal,
Shakespeare, Corneille, Locke, Ra¬
cine and Rousseau.
O'UT OF THE ASHES: Korea
will have one of the most up-to-date
training hospitals in the Far East
when its National Medical Centre,
now being built on the site of the
former City Hospital in war-damaged
Seoul, by the U.N. Korean Recon¬
struction Agency (Unkra) is com¬
pleted. Denmark, Norway and Sweden
have begun to despatch some $700,000-
worth of equipment and supplies for
the new hospital.
FIRST EUROPEAN' SCHOOL:
The first "European" secondary
school was opened recently in
Luxembourg as an addition to the
primary school which has already
been serving children of employees
at the European Coal and Steel
Community since 1953. Some
500 children of 11 nationalities at¬
tend courses which are given in
French, German, Italian and
Dutch and are planned to meet
educational requirements of the
six member countries.
U. K. BOOK BOOM : A record
number of 20,719 titles was published
in the United Kingdom in 1957 in¬
cluding a record figure for new titles
(14,798). The increase covers all
kinds of books, including fiction (up
by 300 titles) and children's books
(a striking rise of 200 more than last
year). Last record year for book
publishing in the U. K. was 1955
(19,962 titles).
YOUNG FARMERS* 'SWOP':
Under the auspices of International
Farm Youth Exchange scheme,
young farmers from Luxembourg
and the United States have been
exchanging jobs and finding out
more about farming methods used
in each other's countries. Re¬
cently a club was formed in
Luxembourg where the young
farmers of both countries meet and
exchange views and ideas.
34
'UNESCO: PURPOSE, PROGRESS,
PROSPECTS'
A frank appraisal of Unesco's achievements from 1946 to 1956 has
been made by Walter H. C. Laves (former Deputy Director-
General of Unesco) and Charles A. Thomson (a former United
States Representative at Unesco) in a recently published book,
"Unesco: Purpose, Progress, Prospects" (1), a 457-page volume which
outlines the character and scope of Unesco's programme. In their final
appraisal of Unesco's record the authors find that it has been "an in¬
strument and a symbol of international collaboration, adjustment and
understanding, contributing to the development of institutions needed
in a world community." They warn that Unesco "as the world focus of
men's aspirations in the vast realm of education, science and culture,
must always fall short of the hopes placed in it, for these hopes are as
limitless as the creative abilities of the human mind itself," but they
conclude that "if Unesco is properly used as a means by which peoples,
through their governments, can agree on goals important to all and
then devise practical ways of reaching these goals through joint efforts,
it is capable of almost unlimited achievement."
Indiana University Press, Bloomington 1957. Price $7.50.
M«. ORE MEDICAL SCHOOLS :
During the past ten years 108 medical
schools were created more then ever
before in a similar period reports
the World Health Organization in its
new World Directory of Medical
Schools. Each year, 66,700 doctors
graduate from 638 medical schools in
84 countries and territories. But dis¬
tribution around the world is un¬
equal: Europe (population over
619,000,000) has 253 medical schools;
Africa (210,000,000 inhabitants) has
only 16.
WHAT'S YOUR PROBLEM? A
provisional international compu¬
tation centre has been set up in
Rome under an agreement between
Unesco and the Italian Institute
of Higher Mathematics. It will
help countries which do not yet
have electronic computing equip¬
ment to make use of the services
of those which do, and in parti¬
cular it will assist them to put
their problems in a form suitable
for solution by calculators.
M CHROMOSPHERE PROBE:
Scientists at the Australian Go¬
vernment's solar physics labora¬
tory in Sydney will shortly be
using a special filter fitted to a
telescope to explore the chromo¬
sphere a mysterious region of hot
gases about 1,700 miles wide sur¬
rounding the sun, which is invi¬
sible through ordinary telescopes.
It is hoped that this research
part of the research programme
of the International Geophysical
Year will help to explain why
certain events on the sun affect
communications on the earth.
O
RilUSSIAN STAMP CENTENARY:
The 100th anniversary of the first
Russian stamp (1858) has been com¬
memorated by an exhibition at the
Central Museum of Communications
in Leningrad, which included stamps
issued independently in each of the
167 districts of tsarist Russia, as well
as more than 2,000 issues made in the
Soviet Union since August 1921.
Among the 3,000,000 specimens in the
Leningrad Collection are examples of
the world's first stamp frqm England.
'PIUM TRAFFIC DETECTIVES :
Scientists met in Geneva recently to
review an international opium re¬
search programme that aims to deter¬
mine the country of origin of opium
seized in illicit traffic. The program¬
me is a joint undertaking of the U.N.
and scientists from opium-producing
countries. Much of the research
work on samples supplied by these
countries is carried on in the U.N.
Research Laboratory at the Palais des
Nations in Geneva.
TECHNICIANS FOR GHANA:
The College of Technology at Ku-
masi, in the new state of Ghana, is
expanding rapidly and lecturers
from the Netherlands, Australia,-.
New Zealand, India, Israel and the
West Indies, as well as fram Ghana
itself and from the United King¬
dom have joined its staff. Nearly
1,000 students attend the college
whose courses include architecture,
building, technology, engineering,
pharmacy, business management
and agriculture.
u
z
<
*£
13
Z
<
O
UJ
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
MONOGRAPHS ON FUNDAMENTAL EDUCATION
World Illiteracy at Mid-Century is the first systematic
survey of Illiteracy on a world-wide scale ever made.
Tabulated information on the number of illiterates In
198 countries and territories is given, and a detailed
analysis of some 65 countries, based on census data re¬
lating to Illiteracy around 1950. Chapters are devoted
to showing methods used for counting illiterates, the
relation of Illiteracy to school enrolment, national
Income and urban industrialization.
ONE OF UNESCO'S MOST IMPORTANT STUDIES
TO DATE.
Price :$2.00; 10/- (stg.); 500 fr.
WORLD
ILLITERACY
AT
MID-CENTURY
ONOGRAPHS ON FUNDAMENTAL EDUCATION
THE TEACHING
OF READING
AND WRITING
WILLIAM S. GRAY
U N Ï
ímíiím
SCO
N E O
It is an accepted fact that everyone should be taught to read and
write, but for at least eighty years there have been major differ¬
ences of opinion both as to the alms of a reading or writing
programme and the methods to be usedwhether the learners
be children or adults. Without trying to give a final answer to
these questions, a recent Unesco publication, The Teaching of
Reading and Writing, reviews current practices, evaluates the
effectiveness of these methods and sums up the results of re¬
search and experience in the subject. This 286-page interna¬
tional survey by William S. Gray of the University of Chicago,
published in English, French and Spanish editions, will prove
a valuable book for educators and parents alike. Unesco dopes
it will form the basis for the preparation of teachers' manuals
in many languages.
Price : $3.00; 14/6 (stg.); 700 fr.
Educational Studies and Documents series :
Adult Education in Turkey (XIV) 	 S0.40 2/- (stg.) I 00 fr.
Fundamental, Adult, Literacy and '
Community Education in the
West Indies (XV)	 0.50 3/- (stg.) I 50 fr.
Literacy Teaching : A Selected
Bibliography (XVIII) 0.40 2/- (stg.) 1 00 fr.
Reports and Papers on Mass Communication series :
Periodicals for New Literates : Editorial
Methods (XXII) 	S 0.75 3/- (stg.) I50fr.
Periodicals for' New Literates : Seven
Case Histories (XXIV) 	 g 1.00 3/6 (stg.) I 50 fr.
Monographs on Fundamental Education series :
The Use of Vernacular Languages in
Education (VIII)
Co-operatives and Fundamental
Education	 1.2 5 7/6 (stg.) 3 50 fr
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
MODERN SCHOOLS FOR MOROCCAN GIRLf
"In that ambiance of modern culture
to which present-day life leads and
calls us irresistibly, it is essential
that the women of Morocco partici¬
pate ardently and usefully In the life,
of the nation..." These words were
spoken by Princess Lalla Aisha,
eldest daughter of King Mohammed V '.;
of Morocco, ten years ago, and since
then the women have, in fact, been
participating more openly in thé
now changing pattern of their coun¬
try's life. There has been no brutal
rupture with the traditions of the ~
past,. but a gradual change has taken
place, and in this evolutionary pro¬
cess thousands of Moroccan girls and
young women have been shown how
to adapt themselves to a more modern
form of life in Women's Centres
created by the Ministry of Education.,
In five years thirty-five centres we?e
opened, in all parts of Morocco, staf¬
fed by French women educators and .,-
teachers who are progressively train¬
ing Moroccan teachers to be their
successors. By educating these
girls and young women, the centresV
are also helping to reinforce the ranks
of voluntary teachers for Morocco'!?..-
annual national literacy campaigns.
Above, "musical hour" with songs
and rhythms at the Rabat centre ;
left, games in the sand at a girls'
holiday camp. (See pages 14 15.)
Photos ' Gerda Böhm, Rabat 3|
]]>
</page>
</document>
