<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078179eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Jí m
FEBRUARY 1961
(14 th year)
Price : l/-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U.S.)
0,70 NF (FRANCE)
T
A
* <4
OW OPEN ON THE WORLD
L \^^^y-.
¡
i
AFRICA
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
BRAIN TEASERS FOR AFRICANS. The Univer¬
sity of Accra in Ghana has devised a series of
special group tests used to determine the
capabilities of potential leaders sorely needed by
the new countries of Africa. See story page 24.
(Ü) Paul Almasy, Paris
'
I^V^THNf\1
SAfc^
Ú#
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier FEBRUARY 1961
14TH YEAR
Contents
No. 2
For reasons beyond our
control this issue appears
later than usual. We wish
to apologise to our rea¬
ders for this delay.
COVER PHOTO
Sixteen Independent Afri¬
can states took their seats
for the first time at the
recent Unesco General Con¬
ference (See page 4). Photo
shows Mrs Madeleine Sar, a
Senegal delegate, during an
interval between meetings.
Page
4 A TWO-YEAR PLAN FOR WORLD ACTION
By Daniel Behrman
6 ROVING CAMERAMAN IN UNESCO HOUSE
Candid shots of a conference
14 AN AFRICAN LOOKS AT THE WORLD
By F.I. Ajumogobia
17 THE CHANGING FACE OF AFRICA
18 AFRICA I96I-A SPECIAL MAP
22 countries have gained independence in five years
21 NEW SCHOOLS FOR AFRICA
By Georges Fradier
24 SIX MEN WITH A PROBLEM
Obstacle course to leadership
28 TOWARDS RACIAL HARMONY
Unesco's I 5 years of efforts against bias
By Alfred Métraux
30 VELAZQUEZ A LA PICASSO
I 3 versions of Las Meninas
32 THEY CALL THEIR TELESCOPE 'BIMA SAMT
Indonesia's eye on the Milky Way
By Victor M. Blanco
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Willy Roms, Paris
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational,
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon R. Behrens
Associate Editors
Scientific and Cultural
France
English Edition :
French Edition :
Spanish Edition :
Russian Edition :
German Edition
Ronald Fenton
Celia Bertin
Amparo Alvajar
Veniamin Matchavariani
: Hans Rieben
Arabic Edition : Amin Chaker
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German and Arabic. In the
United States of America it is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center.
U.S.A. 80 I Third Avenue, New York 22, N.Y.. Plaza 1-3860. Second-clais mail
privileges authorized at NewYork, N.Y. (M.C. 61.1.155 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors ol THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: P 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
© Willy Ronis, Paris
98 NATIONS CHART
A TWO-YEAR PLAN
FOR WORLD ACTION
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Tho Unesco Courler. February 1961
Unesco's programme of action
for the next two years is the
most ambitious since this U.N.
Agency was created 15 years
ago. What Unesco hopes to
achieve in 1961-62 and how its
programme and budget were
decided by the organization's
General Conference last Dec¬
ember are highlighted below
by Daniel Behrman
Under the flowing concrete drapery of a hall
resembling a timeless temple, a heartening
and almost unusual spectacle has been enacted
on a stage for all the world. This stage was
the Eleventh General Conference of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization in
Paris, and its actors were the delegates some in business
suits, others in flowing robes from ninety-eight nations
scattered over the face of the earth.
What was unusual about this spectacle was that It
produced a harmonious finale even though It overlooked
none of the realities and the facts of International life
upon which agreement has yet to be found. Such issues
as racism, disarmament, colonialism, and neighbourly
relations were faced squarely during some lively sessions
which led to Important resolutions (1). But from this
stage, where conflicting Interests met and compromised
with each other, has emerged a two-year programme for
Unesco which Is both the most ambitious and the most
realistic In the history of this United Nations agency.
It is ambitious because it Is by far the biggest series of
undertakings which Unesco has ever been called upon to
carry out. Corresponding to these obligations is a budget
of $32,513,228 for 1961 and 1962, the highest ever voted
by a Unesco General Conference. It Is realistic because
It faces squarely some of the world's major needs, parti¬
cularly In education and more particularly In Africa, that
sleeping giant of a continent now awakening with dra¬
matic speed.
Symbolically, the Conference met for five weeks In
November and December under the presidency of a
representative of Africa, Mr. Akale-Work Apte Wold of
Ethiopia. Africa also accounted for 16 of the additional
(1) One calls on Member States "to encourage and support... utili¬
zation of the means of information as a contribution to better mutual
understanding between peoples and t/iui to counteract any attempts
to use press, radio, televison, cinema and other means of information
for propaganda which deliberately or insidiously incites violation of
peace or acts of aggression"; a second states "thai colonialism in all
its forms... must be speedily abolished and that accession to freedom
and independence must not be delayed on the false pretext that a
particular territory has not reached a sufficiently high standard in
economic, social, educational and cultural matters ; a third resolution
calls on Unesco Member States "to include in their educational pro¬
grammes provisions for bringing up the rising generation in the
spirit of peaceful and neighbourly relations and mutual international
understanding and co-operation" ; a fourth condemns "any display of
intolerance among the different races or peoples as a violation of the
high principles which prompted the creation of the United Nations
and of Unesco."
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PLAN FOR WORLD ACTION (Cont'd)
Above, vast hall of Secretariat building, main artery
leading to delegates' lobby and Conference building.
Below, delegates at a committee meeting; in fore¬
ground, Mr. Mahmoud Haju Ahmed, Director of Edu¬
cation of Somalia, one of the new African nations.
'IN TERMS OF EDUCATION
NONE OF US IS RICH'
countries which have become members of Unesco since
the last General Conference in 1958, attended by repre¬
sentatives of 81 nations.
To carry out the programme adopted in Paris, Unesco
will not only have its regular budget, but additional
resources In 1961-62 from two other sources : $12,000,000
from the United Nations Technical Assistance programme
and $11,000,000 from the United Nations Special Fund.
Impressive though it may sound, this total of more than
$55,000,000 would have to be spread very thinly to cover
Unesco's obligations in the world.
That is why the General Conference wisely decided to
place a priority on education. Schools, schooling and
schoolteachers have failed to keep abreast of the present-
day rate of progress. This is true in countries with old and
established systems of education, but it is nothing less
than tragically true for new nations where the urgency
of needs is equalled only by the paucity of resources. And
It takes on dramatic proportions in Africa where the ink
has barely dried on a dozen declarations of Independence
and nationhood.
The immediacy of this problem brought forth a healthy
reaction from the conference: a reaction of universalism
which was stressed by Unesco's Director-General, Mr. Vlt-
torlno Veronese. It was universalism In deeds as well as
words. The director-general of Unesco had the pleasant
and almost startling experience of submitting a budget to
98 nations and having it rejected as... too low. Unesco
Member States first raised this proposed budget by one
million dollars and then pledged more than another
million dollars In a moving display of solidarity. This was
universalism in action: an International gesture by the
rich, the not-so-rich and the poor alike to further the
progress of education, particularly In Africa.
This priority on education Is reflected in a resolution
unanimously adopted at the conference. It states that
priority should be given to education in Unesco's pro¬
gramme and that the United Nations and its specialized
agencies should place the same stress on education for
the less-developed countries as Is placed on economic
development in a more narrow sense.
Delegates from all nations emphasized the need for
more and better teachers, schools, universities and tech-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
. '«V *
Photos <0 Willy Ronis, Paris
Above, General Conference Session in progress in
Plenary Hall, seen from one of booths used by simul¬
taneous interpretation staff. Above right, delegates
meet in committee room donated by Switzerland.
Eight other countries have furnished and decorated
rooms. Many other gifts have been made to the
Unesco H.Q., and during the General Conference, Iran
presented a magnificent carpet for delegates' lobby.
nical colleges In their own countries. Their plea was
summed up by Sir David Eccles, British Minister of Edu¬
cation, and head of the United Kingdom delegation, who
stated :
"In these fields, we are all underdeveloped. In the field
of education, we are all poor and some are poorer than
others. Unesco stands for Education in the broadest sense
as WHO stands for Health and FAO stands for Agri¬
culture. We have the right and duty to proclaim the
urgent needs of education and to press these claims
on our own goverments and on the whole family of the
United Nations."
Specifically, Unesco's education programme for the next
two years consists both of studies and services for the
general advancement of education, along with activities
aimed at helping countries develop their own educational
systems. In both cases, an accent Is placed on educational
planning and regional development.
These trends are to be seen In the services Unesco is
rendering to national systems of education. According to
decisions taken by the General Conference, It will be in
a position to offer assistance in these main fields:
Improvement of teacher training programmes and
school curricula.
Development of methods for teaching science and
modern languages.
The use of audio-visual aids.
In this last respect, mention might be made of a Confer¬
ence resolution calling upon Unesco to explore the possi¬
bilities of using the most recent advances in electronics
and communication in order to bring education to the
widest possible audience an audience limited only by
the range of television transmitters and Hertzian cables.
At present, the idea of man-made satellites girdling the
earth and beaming school television programmes to
hundreds of thousands of classrooms Is still in the realm
of science fiction. But It may not stay there very long.
In all, Unesco will send out more than 200 international
specialists to its member states to work In national
systems of education. Obviously, a '"system of education"
runs from the kindergarten to the graduate student work¬
ing towards his doctorate. Just as obviously, Unesco
Delegates converse between Picasso mural and one
of six giant gracefully-shaped concrete pillars which
support the Conference building roof at its centre.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
SILHOUETTES IN THE NIGHT
Formal session and informal talk are framed in these photos by windows of Unesco's
Conference Building. Below, conversation piece against window of delegate's
lounge. Far right, peeping Into Commission Room, night-roving camera finds
delegates in session. Right, activity on three levels, from press rooms (bottom)
to committee room with Its "halo" lighting over round table for delegates.
Photos © Willy Ronis, Paris.
PLAN FOR WORLD ACTION (Cont'd)
could not hope to span the full range of education without
diluting Its efforts.
This Is why stress Is being placed on primary and
secondary education, both technical and general, in
regional programmes for Africa, the Arab States and
Latin America. Universal primary education Is the target
In Asia. Here, Unesco is to create a regional education
office and two regional centres for research in school
buildings and for the training of school administrators.
The same goal Is to be found in Latin America where,
since 1957, Unesco has been operating a ten-year major
project for the extension of primary education. In the
Arab states, It Is planned to set up a network of associated
teacher training colleges.
Pressing though needs may be in these regions, the
situation in Africa Is nothing less than an emergency.
Here, Unesco's education department has to become a fire
department. As one example of the calls made upon Its
resources, it must recruit several hundred teachers for
secondary schools in the Congo Republic (Leopoldvllle) as
well as numerous experts in education and school admin¬
istration. This emergency assistance Is being financed by
the U.N. under its programme of aid to the Congo.
But the call of the new Africa for education is being
heard elsewhere as well. Unesco plans to move ahead with
assistance In school constructions, the production of
teaching materials, the providing of teachers, the sur¬
veying of educational needs and the awarding of fellow¬
ships.
Even before the General Conference ended, nations
made a number of generous offers. The United States of
America pledged to donate up to $1,000,000 for assistance
to Africa. The Federal Republic of Germany announced
a contribution of $100,000 to this programme. And, within
a few hours, representatives of a dozen countries offered
130 fellowships to Africans while ten more delegations
promised to make specific offers known In the near future.
This priority on education will also see an increase in
the scope of Unesco's activities In technical and vocation
al education during the next two years. Here, thanks to a
financial transfusion from the United Nations Special
Fund, Unesco will be able to participate in the founding
or the operation of a number of technological Institutes
throughout the world.
Among other measures in the field of education too
numerous to list here was the adopting by the General
Conference of the text of an international convention
and recommendation against discrimination In education.
This convention is intended to implement one of the
fundamental principles in the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights: the right to education. It defines discri¬
mination as any factor which "'has the purpose or effect
of nullifying or impairing equality of treatment in
education.1"
Turning to the natural sciences, the General Conference
approved an international plan of action to cope with
scientific problems of an urgent and worldwide nature
over the next ten years. These problems Include the ex¬
ploring of the world's oceans about which it has been
said we know less than we do of the moon and the
rational harnessing of science and technology to Indus¬
trialize the world's developing countries. (See Unesco
Courier July-August 1960.)
Perhaps the most dramatic aspect of Unesco's work in
the natural sciences will be Its collaboration in the Inter¬
national Indian Ocean expedition organized by the Spe¬
cial Committee on Océanographie Research. This expe¬
dition will see twenty océanographie research vessels from
fourteen nations at work in what is both the world's
least-known ocean and perhaps its most important one
in terms of the needs of the hundreds of millions who
live on its shores.
Through Its collaboration in this expedition and
through its own programme, Unesco hopes to be able to
assist in the training of oceanographers. In addition,
the Conference voted to set up an Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission with headquarters at Unesco.
On land, Unesco's programme for the development of
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
natural resources will see the continuation of Its work In
such vital fields as the humid tropics and the world's arid
regions. In Arid Zone research the next two years will
see a gradual transition from Unesco's Major Project
which ends in 1962 to greatly Increased national activities.
A perfect example of the type of problem which no one
country can hope to solve on its own is to be found in
seismology. Without "discrimination" by border or
region, earthquakes have struck harshly In recent years
in the Middle East, North Africa and South America. No
one can predict when an earthquake will occur, but a
great deal can be done to reduce Its devastation through
earthquake-proof construction and precise mapping of
seismic zones. This year and next, Unesco will send
missons to earthquake zones in the Andes and in the
Mediterranean basin.
The earth's crust is also the subject of another Unesco
plan of action aimed at taking an up-to-date inventory
of all the many methods now used in prospecting for
natural resources. At the same time, steps will be taken
for a long-term study of that most precious of all
resources, the soil Itself.
Another Important phase of Unesco's science pro¬
gramme concerns the role of science and technology in
the industrialization of new countries. Here, Unesco
has been called upon by Its member states to prepare an
international conference to be held in 1963 or 1964.
The purpose of this meeting will be to take stock of the
lessons of the past for countries which are now changing
over to an Industrialized society. In particular, a study
will be made of the delicate problems of helping agricul¬
tural countries to make this changeover without paying
the price of social and economic maladjustment.
Industrialization of developing countries is one of three
Unesco priority fields in science laid down by the General
Conference for the next decade. The two others are the
exploration of the earth's resources and the co-ordination
of scientific action on national and international levels.
Education and science were the two most prominent
features of Unesco's programme as it was carefully
discussed by the General Conference. But Unesco's
mission goes even further than this.
For example, under the heading of cultural activities
In the programme adopted by the General Conference arc
to be found specific and practical tasks In such fields as
research In the humanities, the spreading of knowledge
of art and literature, the safeguarding of cultural heri¬
tages and the development of museums and libraries.
For the next two years, the most Important of these
cultural activities will be the continuation of the Interna¬
tional Campaign for Safeguarding the Monuments of
Nubia, those priceless architectural and artistic treasures
of ancient Egypt which will be threatened by the rising
waters of the Nile once the new Aswan Dam has been
completed In the United Arab Republic (See Unesco
Courier Feb., April 1960). During the Conference, plans
for preserving the temple at Abu Slmbel, the largest of
these monuments, were presented.
In Southeast Asia, Unesco's cultural activities depart¬
ment will meet a problem which crops up everywhere as
a result of mass literacy campaigns for adults and more
schools for children. The "new literate" often tends to
become a "new Illiterate" ici a very simple reason: he
has nothing to read. Books and other publications are
either not readily available in his own language or else
they are offered at prices which he cannot afford.
This Is why Unesco will assist national book centres
and publishing associations in Southeast Asia, mainly In
Burma, Ceylon, India, Iran and Pakistan. Included In
this assistance will be production of reading materials at
a regional centre In Karachi and the awarding of prizes
for authors and Illustrators.
Unesco's major project for the mutual appreciation of
Eastern and Western cultural values will also be conti¬
nued during the next two years. Here. Unesco plans to
undertake studies In co-operation with Institutes In
Japan, India and Lebanon while research will continue
on the civilizations of the Orient and the Occident.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
PLAN FOR WORLD ACTION (Cont'd;
UNESCO TO SUPPLY STAFF FOR
KEY POSTS IN NEW NATIONS
Distances between cultures and distances between men
are also being shortened by the social sciences, which
represent an Important sector In Unesco's activities.
Here, two main fields are to be stressed: the teaching of
the social sciences and fundamental research; and the
study of problems resulting from economic and social
development. This latter theme will lead to studies on
urbanization and population problems in South Asia and
Africa. Research is to be conducted by two Unesco cen¬
tres: the Latin American Regional Centre for Social
Science Research at Rio de Janeiro and, at Delhi
University In India, the Research Centre on Economic
and Social Development Problems In South Asia.
At the same time, Unesco's social sciences department
will continue its work on the question of race relations
and on the study of discrimination between men and
women. After studying the nature of prejudice in past
years, it will now take up deep-seated causes of outbreaks
of racial hatred, particularly among youth. (See page 28.)
In mass communication, Unesco is to concentrate upon
three main tasks laid down by the General Conference:
aid to countries in developing or improving their
information media (newspapers, radio stations, etc.) ;
use of mass communication techniques in education;
the use of mass media to promote international under¬
standing.
In this respect, it should be mentioned that The Unesco
Courier, which Is now appearing in six languages-
French, English, Spanish, Russian, German.and Arabic-
will soon be published In seven. A Japanese edition is
scheduled to appear In April.
1,700 fellowships offered
during next two years
Under the programme adopted by the General Confer¬
ence, Unesco will continue to operate Its two Interna¬
tional centres for higher studies In journalism (one
at Strasbourg. France, and the other at Quito, Ecuador),
but It will also extend Its assistance In the training of
qualified professionals for the press, the cinema and the
rado to South-East Asia. Assistance will also be offered
Asian countries in the study of news agencies and the
problems of news transmission.
One Important aspect of UnesCo's programme Is Its
International exchange service which will administer more
than 1,700 fellowships during the next two years, in¬
cluding 1,200 financed directly by Unesco. Another Is its
financial aid, amounting to nearly one million dollars, to
non-governmental organizations working along lines
parallel to its own.
Finally, the General Conference approved a plan to
enable Unesco to supply developing countries with top-
level officials In education and science. Known as "ope¬
rational or executive personnel" they will be civil servants
of the goverments which have requested them, although
Unesco will be responsible for paying part of their
salaries. The United Nations has been operating a
similar service for several years In public administration.
Here, in summary form, we have endeavoured to pre¬
sent the highlights of Unesco's programme for 1961 and
1962 as approved by an International assembly of virtually
one hundred nations.
A speaker at the Eleventh General Conference stressed
the awakening of Unesco's member states to the needs of
Africa. Africa was the symbol of this conference, It was
pointed out. But Africa, perhaps, was also the symbol of
an even wider awakening by the nations of the world to
the fact, as stressed by Director-General Vlttorino Vero¬
nese, In his final remarks to the Conference, that "man
does not live by bread alone" and that ignorance in the
most remote corner of the globe represents a blight on
the sum of human knowledge and must be eradicated if
humanity is to survive.
10
Ground level view of a corner of the hall in the Conference
building taken from beneath .the overhead passage leading
to committee rooms. On far wall, section of Picasso mural.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. . Fcbruory 1961
Photos © Willy Ronis
Right, a delegate from one of the new
African states and another from Asia at
work during pause between meetings
in one of the sound-proof booths of the
Conference building hall. With their
benches upholstered in black leather,
these small hexagonal booths are used
by delegates for private talks. Left,
delegates' lounge with stairway and
terrace leading to committee rooms
decorated by Switzerland and the
U.S.A., and lower stairway to basement.
Above, in foreground, are basement windows of Conference
building In which press room, radio and TV studios and
committee rooms are housed. Lighted windows in centre
of photo are those running along wall of delegates'
lobby leading from the Conference building to Secretariat.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
IN THE CORRIDORS..
On these pages our candid camera photographer has caught delegates as they chatted Informally between sessions in the
lounge and main hall of the Unesco Conference building. (1) Head of Moroccan delegation and Unesco Executive Board
member Mohamed El Fasi. (2) Two Liberlan delegates admire photo-exhibition of flood-menaced Nubian monuments. (3)
G.P. Malalasekera (left) head of Ceylon delegation and ambassador to Moscow with Indian poet and writer Baldoon Dhingra.
(4) Two delegates from India. (5) Senegal delegate, Mrs. Madeleine Sar (with hat). (6) Austrian delegate, Alexander
Philippovich (dark suit). (7) Head of Ghana delegation and Minister of Education, A-J- Duwuona-Hammond (draped gown).
; '
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Il
...AT THE CONFERENCE
CAMPAGNE
INTERNATIONA
.POURLASAÜV
[DES MONUf
îE LA NUBIE,
MESSAGE FROM DWIGHT
D. EISENHOWER
Dedicated to broadening man's
understanding of himself and the
world about hint, Unesco encou¬
rages the peoples of many lands to
open wide the doors of educational
opportunity. Achievement of this
goal will speed the progress of
mankind and strengthen the foun¬
dation for a just and lasting peace.
In this critical hour, as nations
press forward to assure the highest
development of their peoples,
Unesco can provide an outstanding
service for all...
NATIONALISM
The age of nationalism has gone
it belongs to the past, even if
there are still people who do not .
know it yet... Nationalism is but
one of the forms of self-centredness
which makes us blind to other
human beings, other nations, other
social and cultural systems... For
the first time no single nation can
any more afford to neglect the
sorrows, the difficulties, the needs
political, economic and cultural
of any other nation.
Arnold BERGSTRAESSER
German Fed. Rep.
BOOKS NOT GUNS
Unesco must do everything to lay
the foundations of true peace based
on a profound intellectual and moral
renaissance of mankind. Such an
enterprise will, of course, be a costly
affair since it implies that the entire
population of our planet Will be en¬
sured of the basically needed school¬
ing at all levels. But how much less
costly will this be in the long run
compared to the ever-rising and un¬
productive expenditure on modern
armaments.
Paulo CARNEIRO, Brazil
THE NEGRO'S NEW ROLE
Whatever well-being we have
.received from the cultures of modern
countries... let us make no mistake:
a new society is emerging in which
we, as negroes, will have a far from
minor role.
A. RAKOTO-RATSIMAMANGA
Malagasy Republic
MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING
If Unesco wants to go ahead, it
must take account of the fact that
in our changing world its first
mission is to adapt its structure and
activities to the imperatives of the
times, to grasp the importance of
the great contemporary problems
and to contribute as best it can to
their solution. It must cast aside
all prejudices and fearlessly tackle
the question number one of our
time: understanding between peoples,
mutual knowledge and international
co-operation through education,
science and culture.
Mihai RALEA, Rumania
MESSAGE FROM
NIKITA KROUCHTCHEV
w
... All peoples are fundamentally
interested in the prevention of war,
In the rapid abolition of the ab¬
horrent colonial system, and the
consolidating of the principles of
peaceful co-existence In International
relations Unesco, tin- United
Nations Agency which deals with
education, science and culture, can
make a considerable contribution to
a lofty aspect of the creation of a
world without war, without arms,
of a world without oppressed and
enslaved peoples. It Is only under
a stable peace that really fruitful
collaboration of scientists, scholars
and educationalists of all countries
is possible collaboration aimed at
discovering solutions to many prob¬
lems of importance to humanity...
FRATERNITY OR DEATH
One is nonplussed that, despite
so much unhappincss and so many
catastrophes, men still cannot realize
that they are racing towards an
abyss and that in the face of all
the forces of nature they are in the
process of unharnessing their only
chance of salvation is not to fight,
but to unite...
Never has it been more obvious
that humanity is being driven inexo¬
rably to the inescapable alternative
fraternity or death.
Jean BERTHOIN, France
MEN'S MINDS EMANCIPATED
Culture is nothing more than a
perpetual attempt to eliminate
prejudices, to emancipate the
minds of men from all kinds of
prepossessions.
Sir Sarvepalli RADHAKRISHNAN
India
FABLE OF THE ELEPHANT
In a world in which men's minds
are shrouded in the darkness of
collective and individual vanities no
one can claim to see clearly. Seven
centuries ago one of our great
thinkers told the tale of a group of
people who, through curiosity,
penetrated a very dark room in
which an elephant was shut up. As
it could not be seen, each member
of the group tried to find out what
is was by feeling it. But each one
could only touch a single part of
the enormous body. So a discussion
took place in the dark. One thought
that the elephant had the shape of
a column, another that it looked
like a trump, a third that it
resembled a great leather bag, and
so on.
Similarly, in the obscurity of our
own time, whenever we hear diame¬
trically opposed definitions or
interpretations of the words, Peace,
Freedom, Democracy and Justice,
we should remember the story of
the elephant.
G.A. RAADI, Iran
Photos © Willy Ronis.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
AN AFRICAN LOOKS AT THE WORLD
An educator from one of Afri¬
ca's newly independent coun¬
tries raises challenging issues
which affect all men everywhere
by F. I. Ajumogobia
Federal Ministry of Education, Nigeria
I have heard the year 1960 described as Africa's
year. I am not sure that I agree with the
description, for In my view, no single year
can be properly described as the year of des¬
tiny of any people. Human evolution, whether
biological or sociological is a gradual and continuous
process; and so, significant as the year 1960 may appear
to be in the history of Africa, I would regard It as merely
the beginning of the many changes that must inevitably
follow the great wind which Is now blowing through the
continent.
During the year we have seen new States emerge In
Africa; but we have also witnessed, and are still
witnessing, an emergency In Africa.
In 1945 a world war, which like all wars had generated
Its own momentum, ended. Men were sick of war and
there was general talk of peace. And men of goodwill
from many lands said that never again should this evil
thing happen. It was In that atmosphere that this great
organization for peace, for education, for science and
culture was born. But memory appears to be short.
However, according to the Constitution of Unesco the
Governments of the States Parties on behalf of their
peoples declared: "That since wars begin In the minds
of men, It Is in the minds of men that the defences of
peace must be constructed; that ignorance of each other's
ways and lives has been a common cause, throughout the
history of mankind, of that suspicion and mistrust
between the peoples of the world through which their
differences have all too often broken into war"...
The greatest means at our disposal Is education, and
I am using the term in Its widest sense. There can be
no peace In a world of Inequality and of unequal oppor¬
tunities and prejudices, whether of race, colour, religious
persuasion or ideology: I believe too that wide differences
In the provision of educational facilities may well lead
to discontent and hence to disharmony and Instability
In the world. For there can be no true peace in a world
in which one part Is living in ignorance, in poverty and
stricken with disease, while the other part Is living In
plenty, in comfort, utilizing all the amenities that modern
science has placed at man's disposal.
All of human knowledge
is indivisible & universal
But true knowledge Is indivisible and universal and
should remain so. For example, what does it matter
if we give credit for the discovery of the calculus
to Sir Isaac Newton or to Dr. Leibnitz? To my mind what
matters Is the fact that a great and powerful tool has
been bequeathed to mankind. Surely a gas thermometer,
whether constructed in a well-equipped laboratory in the
Jungle of Tropical Africa or constructed in a modern
laboratory in Europe or America is fundamentally the
same instrument, and If suitable correction factors are
available it can be used in Africa with the same preci¬
sion as it can be used in Europe or America or Asia.
Again, It Is just over 60 years ago that the electron was
discovered In the famous Cavendish Laboratory of
Cambridge University by the eminent English scientist,
Professor J.J. Thompson. The follow-up work by Lord
Rutherford and others In the United Kingdom and
elsewhere in the next years led to the splitting of the
atom. No longer do elementary -science teachers describe
the atom as the smallest, indivisible particle of matter.
The atom has been split and what a tremendous source
14
of energy Is at man's disposal? But what a pity that the
first use to which the knowledge was put was in war, and
that the common man first came to hear of the atom in
terms of the atom bomb. One is not so sure that modern
man is altogether fit to use the tools nature is revealing
to him, no doubt through his own inquiry. Nuclear
power is a challenge of our times.
I believe that Unesco has a great rôle to play In world
peace. I agree with the head of the delegation of the
United States of America that Unesco is the most
promising organization for world peace. I also agree with
the quotation of Tolstoy given us by the head of the
delegation of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics:
"preparation and arms for war are as bad as wars them¬
selves".
In our shrinking world
we must unite or perish
We have heard great and forceful words spoken in
the name and the cause of peace. One can only
hope that these beautiful words have been spoken
not merely from the lips but from the hearts, and that
all leaders everywhere will spare no energy or effort in the
pursuit of peace and harmony in the world. How many
of us can genuinely repeat the wise words of the great
Mahatma Gandhi: "I cannot derive any pleasure from
living in a world which is not united"? In Unesco
we presume to be united. All our efforts should be
directed to strengthen that unity.
The ;chief weapon in the cause of peace is education
and the Unesco provision for educational projects in the
underdeveloped countries is most gratefully appreciated
by the peoples of those countries; but the needs are so
great that the present efforts do not even scratch the
surface. The whole of Unesco's programme and budget
for 1961-1962 is just over $31 m. We have been told that
some countries spend many times that amount on their
national education and at least as much as that for aid
in the territories dependent on them. It is obvious that
the resources of Unesco are at present very limited since
they depend almost entirely on contributions from
member states and associate members.
Most of the countries of Africa, especially Tropical
Africa, are in various stages of transition from tradi¬
tional economies based on subsistence agriculture. But
they are, by and large, the important suppliers of
primary products which serve the machines of the
Industrialized countries. Africa, for example, supplies
about 20% of the world's output of copper and manga¬
nese, about 25% of the world's antimony, over 50% of
the world's gold and cobalt and about 90% of the world's
diamonds. Tropical Africa supplies over 60% of the
world's cocoa and about 75% of the world's vegetable
oil, principally palm oil and palm kernels.
The -wheels of the world's machines would turn rather
slowly If these primary products were not supplied by the
countries of Africa and Asia. We live in a world In
which the countries are Interdependent: our world is
rapidly shrinking, in time If not in space. No one section
of the human race can now afford to be Independent of
the others. We so much depend one on another that
unity Is necessary for our survival. l
This article is an abridged version of an address delivered by
Mr. F. I. Ajumogobia, of the Nigerian Delegation, to the Unesco
General Conference on November 25, 1960.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. februorf 1961
Young couple from Dahomey
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
FACE OF THE EDUCATOR
Education has great priority in all of
Africa's many newly Independent countries.
Educators, like this headmaster of a com¬
munity training centre (photo above), are
the men of vision and purpose who work
to establish and maintain the schools
which will train tomorrow's leaders.
FACE OF THE SCIENTIST
The great importance given to science in
the modern world has not been overlooked
by Africa's newly Independent countries.
Young scientists (photo above right), many
of them trained In their own universities
and technical schools, are taking their
places in government and private labora¬
tories in all parts of the continent.
FACE OF THE DOCTOR
Modern and well-equipped hospitals are
now staffed and run by Africans themselves.
Such up-to-date operating rooms as this
one (right) in the University College of
Ibadan, Nigeria, form a nucleus from which
young doctors and nurses now in training
will go out to take their full part In
raising the health standards of their people.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unetco Courler. February 1961
THE CHANGING
FACE
OF AFRICA
Most boundaries have remained the same, but
independence has brought new recognition to
African states. The map published on the two
following pages will assist you in pinpoint¬
ing the continent's twenty-two new countries.
How well do we know our African geogra¬
phy? Everyone could identify a map of
the world's second largest continent,
and with a little help from school days,
point out within a layman's distance such places
as Cairo, Dakar or Addis Ababa. Most of us would
have a vague knowledge of the continent's topo¬
graphy with the vast desert to the north, the
rolling grasslands of the far south and the dense
tropical forests which lie between.
But when it comes to political boundaries, our
knowledge fails. Only a few years ago, the school¬
boy, glancing at his map of Africa, would know
that the red areas designated a territory belonging
to this country, the yellow, to another and the blue
to still another.
Suddenly all that has changed. In the past five
years 22 new countries have achieved independence
in Africa. It is not that they have been moved
around or simply sprung up from nowhere, but
that up to now, we have been in the habit of think¬
ing of them as part of this territory, or that terri¬
tory, and not as separate political entities with
their own lawmakers, heads of states, courts of
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
(O<U
l
>U
l
>E
§
§
O
s
O
s
J
í
-1
rs
i
fN
<O
JZ
0o
J
Z
Z
E
~
£
.5
U
U
c
r
O
0
e
r
o
55
-.
«
o
_
2
o
2
r
-
LO
O
H
D
o
E
2
-
ra
O
O
n
O
O
IB
76,02,60
©
21,0 1,10
oS
O
O
s
S
i
Oc
e
u
i
Z<u
0
0
r
~
.
»
O
«
o
N
O
t
o
t
o
»
o
t
o
w
%
O
s
O
s
O
s
O
s
O
si
l
O
s
i
r»
>
r%
í
i
1
0
0
«Ô
Ô
o
^
r
N
<
N
uu0te0
dé
sq.m0inh
<U
l
Z3
J
Z
E
£
e
r
o
<Z<
£6
-
c
z
o
«to
z3
¿
E
J
Zc
z
o
J
Z
e
r
o
LO
O
Z<OD
oum sq.m100inh
Yaouní167.0003,200,00
©
raco
u95,000s2,800,00
e
ral_u
<
L
O
OOC
O
O
s
ooo
*
oO
s
L
O
"c
r
-
L
O
ooo0
0
^
r
oooL
O
c
o
m
Z
@
aX
I
ra175,000 I0.330.C
(
0
e
Khart965,000 1I.400.C
tô
fN
O
s
_
«
>
»
e
o
,~
s
r
s
|i
<
-s
|
2
*-
r
s
|
S
ä
J
Z
«>
-
E&L
O
c
o
Z
e
a
3
d
E
i
e
r
o
LO
O
-
i
5
2
D
.
O
oo
oIm
o
2
o
o
O
o
a
.
ra
o
o
&
r
-
s
O
s
O
o<
N
©
ï
u
so"
2
C
O
t
o
m
r
s
I
í
H
<
3O(
0
U
L
OZOz
<
3
yo
.
S
©
s
E
S
e
r
o
LO
O
o
2
o
o
_
o
o
o
-
m
2
_
r
^
t
o
<
D
C
-
L
U
B
0
©
Of
e
r
o
LO
Q
o
2
o
o
o
o
m
O
.
OIHL
U
e
E
£
X
n
j
<
.
LO
O
LO
O
°
^
o
o
"O
O
O
<
~
C
O
s
o
s
r
rN
uuzU
l
ÛzU
l
0
.
U
l
ÛzÛU
l
z«oU
l
><X(ft
U
l
(0
s
0
)
<üEIL<
0_hz30ü0ÏhhZU
l
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
THE CHANGING
FACE OF AFRICA
(Cont'd from page 17)
law, and, to be sure, their own representatives taking their
places in the world councils.
Political independence has changed the names of two
or three of these new countries, but the countries them¬
selves, their inhabitants, towns and villages did not
radically change overnight. Neither are their frontiers
entirely new. You'll find most of them in an old atlas.
Gabon, Congo, Nigeria, Senegal, Guinea, Togo and Came¬
roun are certainly not newcomers. There are a few
unfamiliar names such as Central African Republic
(which means exactly what it says), Mali and Ghana,
both romantic sounding names recalling great African
kingdoms of the past (1).
If we look at the continent as a whole, we are struck
by the pattern of its various boundaries. They are not
without significance and many of them have a story
to tell. Some boundaries have, of course, evolved naturally.
The island of Madagascar is an obvious example, and the
Republic of Somalia with its homogeneous population is
another.
But many of the boundaries appear to have been
worked out arbitrarily with T-square and ruler as if some
statesman or military leader had tried to avoid complic¬
ations. The sharp geometrical boundaries of Kenya, Chad
and the Sudan are examples.
It may be some time yet before we know what shape
the boundaries of east Africa between the Zambezi and
Congo rivers will take in the atlases of the future, but,
on the west coast the less regular jigsaw shape of
boundaries testifies to a chequered history. The legacy
of ancient alliances, kingdoms, and the influence of
successive dominant peoples have all left their mark.
The results of this penetration into the interior have
left their traces on boundary lines all along the coast.
From the Congo to Guinea, we find a dozen countries
lying side by side, each with its strip of coast, extending
inland to the humid forest, on to the shrub-covered
.grasslands and sometimes as far as the savannahs.
None of these countries on the Atlantic seaboard
stretches as far inland as the desert. There, the arid
Sudan region extends in a broad band from the Senegal
River all the way to the Nile. Shepherds and their flocks
have always moved freely through this part of Africa
as have the traders' caravans and many civilizations of
the past. This is also true of Mauritania which lies
between Senegal and the Atlas mountains.
There are virtually no impassable natural barriers on
the African continent. With the exception of those
majestic eastern ranges which extend from the Abyssian
highlands down to the snowclad peaks of Kilmanjaro,
and those in the Sahara region, there are no mountains
which compare with Europe's Alps or North America's
Rockies. Africa's mountains traditionally are neither
impassable barriers nor savage regions held in dread by
a peaceful population. On the contrary, the mountains
of Kenya and Guinea provide good pasture lands, and
those of the Cameroun are covered with lush coffee
and banana plantations. If there are some highland
areas which are sparsely populated it is not because of
geography but the plague of the tsetse-fly.
Even the deserts of Africa have not always been
regarded as natural barriers. They have been used for
centuries as highways of commerce and communication.
Nor have the great virgin forests of tropical central
Africa completely cut off the north from the south.
Dense though they may be in certain regions, they
cannot be compared with the impenetrable Amazon
jungle with which they are sometimes confused.
While the African continent has few natural barriers
which prohibit the movement of its population, it does
lack good, navigable waterways. Rivers are comparatively
few for such a large land mass. Whereas the Nile River
played a distinct role in the development of a civilization,
not only along its banks but for half the ancient world,
as did the Euphrates River in Asia Minor, one cannot
say that the Zambezi, Congo or Niger Rivers were essen¬
tial factors in the rise of the civilizations of central Africa.
The old empires of Ghana, Mali and Gao which lay
astride the Senegal and Niger River valleys brought their
Sahel culture from the savannah. The most stable king¬
doms of that era revolved around agricultural and
religious centres, seldom following the course of water¬
ways. One might even conjecture that this lack of
natural water highways long hindered the building of
great states in Africa.
Road and rail networks will be among the most im¬
portant developments in Africa's future. It is fifty
years since the first man-made highways and rail lines
began to criss-cross the continent and they are continually
being expanded.
As for maritime transportation, tropical Africa owes
its great ports to external factors. Dakar, Abidjan, Lagos,
Leopoldville and Nairobi were developed to a great
extent by the world's great merchant navies, industries
and more recently aviation. On the other hand, the-
great towns of the tropical region which are purely
African in origin grew up from regional market places,
often the site of huge fairs. They remain essentially
centres of agriculture and artisan trades. Ibadan is a
striking example.
I N addition to the geographic and political features of
Africa, we must not overlook the continent's vast eco¬
nomic resources and its complex pattern of peoples, tribes
and languages. In the field of resources we are on more
familiar ground.
Everyone knows about the gold mines of South Africa
and the considerable amounts of this precious metal
found in all regions north of the equator. Congo's copper
and uranium deposits are world famed. Diamonds bring
to mind Angola and Tanganyika ; iron-ore, Liberia, Mau¬
ritania and Guinea. Both Guinea and the Cameroun also
have large deposits of bauxite, the raw material from
which aluminium is made.
There are the phosphates of Senegal, the palm and
peanut oils, and that appetizing favourite, cocoa, a source
of prosperity for African planters in Ghana and the
Ivory Coast. Add to these, coffee pride of Ethiopia and
the famed cattle herds of the Masai and Peuhls in
east and west Africa.
Most of us know about these African resources, but
this knowledge can also be a bit embarrassing. It concerns
a phantom Africa which we identify with the produce
of its soil and the wealth of its mines. We never think
of the people of Europe, Asia or the Americas exclusively
in terms of their crops, mines and factories.
Each country has a special personality of its own,
shaped by its history, its role in world affairs and its
contribution to mankind. It is only now that we are
beginning to think of African nations in this same way.
Here is the very heart of the change which an inde¬
pendent Africa is having and will continue to have on
the face of that continent. Until now we have tried to
study, explore and explain Africa from the outside.
Henceforth, we must see her with new eyes and listen
to her new voice. Africa will write her own history, will
produce her own philosophy, will interpret her religions
and will unravel the tangled skeins of her many
languages. As a part of the international community of
nations, she will make her contribution to the fields of
science, economics, politics and art. She is ceasing for
all time to be an object of curiosity, of pity, of greed, of
special interest. She will, herself, make known the great
vital forces and human qualities which will bring a
change and a new significance to the map of Africa.
(1) See The Unesco Courier, October 1959: Special issue on "Africa's
Lost Past: The Startling Rediscovery of a Continent."
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
NEW SCHOOLS FOR AFRICA
By
Georges Fradier
Unesco-Piul Almasp, Pari»
ULTRA-MODERN GIRLS' SECONDARY SCHOOL AT AKUAPIM IS ONE OF SEVERAL BUILT UNDER GHANA'S NEW EDUCATION PROGRAMME
The face of Africa has changed. Its rhythm
has changed. When we look at this huge
continent with its sharply contrasting
countries there is no single yardstick by which
to measure their dimensions, their resources,
and their history. The nations of tropical
Africa range from the old empire of Ethiopia to the
smaller territories on the west coast which were carved
out In the course of colonial partitions. They have
striking social, industrial and cultural differences
depending on whether they were influenced by Europe or
the Arab world. Yet despite all the differences, every
one of these countries is today launched on an extra¬
ordinary undertaking the provision
of full education to hundreds of
thousands of children whose fathers
never so much as saw a school.
Nowadays few persons are likely to be surprised by the
fact that there are currently 112,000 boys and girls in
Nigerian secondary schools and teacher-training schools,
that 1,600 pupils entered the secondary school sixth class
last year In Guinea and that there are 20,000 secondary
pupils In Madagascar. But what Is significant is that
most of these schools were hardly dreamt of a generation
ago. The visitor to an African university library or
scientific laboratory or trade training centre Is s*ruck by
the fact that everything is new; had he come to Africa
10 years ago he would have found very little. Today
he Is confronted with a sudden burgeoning; he sees not
a mere advance In education but an acceleration so
dynamic that it is virtually a crea¬
tion from the ground up.
Nowhere at any time has there
been so rapid a development in the
field of education. In 10 years the
number of schools and pupils in cer¬
tain regions has increased by 300 per
cent. At the end of the second world
war it would have been hard to
foresee that an independent republic
called Ghana would have more than
600,000 pupils at school by 1960; or
that there would be 130,000 school¬
children in Senegal and Mali.
Unesco has carried out a
survey of educational prob¬
lems in 22 countries of Africa.
In this third and concluding
article on education in Asia,
the Middle East and Africa,
Georges Fradier our roving cor¬
respondent, sums up his own
as well as Unesco's findings.
Fifteen years ago, eyebrows would
have been raised at the suggestion
that Addis Ababa would possess a
great university college and that the equipment of the
lecture rooms, libraries and laboratories of the univer¬
sities of Ibadan, Accra, Leopoldville, Fourah Bay and
Dakar would put that of some European cities to shame.
Today, students at these African universities are hardly
aware that their countries were forced to do without any
universities at all up until a few years ago.
This explains why African educa¬
tional authorities are ready to
discuss freely and optimistically the
problem of the number of children
still not attending school. In cer¬
tain cases the figures are gigantic.
In Ethiopia, Somalia, Mall, the Niger
and the Upper Volta, it Is not yet
possible to provide primary educa¬
tion for even a tenth of the school-
age children. Schooling is available
for fewer than three children in ten
In Sierra Leone, Liberia, Dahomey
and Tanganyika.
Even those countries which, edu¬
cationally speaking, are the richest
and most favourably placed will
have to take Seven-League-Boot strides to reach the goal
of education for all children in any way comparable to
that of Europe and America. At present all the schools
of the Federation of Nigeria, for example, have a total
enrolment of 2.7 million pupils of which primary schools
alone account for 2,6 million. But Northern Nigeria, a
vast region of 18 million inhabitants, lags far behind the
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
NEW SCHOOLS FOR AFRICA (Cont'd)
VAST UNESCO ENQUIRY SURVEYS 22 COUNTRIES
rest of the country In education with almost 4 million
children growing up uneducated.
Thus, although the countries of tropical Africa may see
their problems In similar terms, they can hardly be said
to be In a position to solve them in the same manner,
within the same length of time or with the same ease.
The fact Is that between the different regions of the
continent the disparities are enormous, and they are no
less so within each Individual country.
The largest cities of Africa compare favourably with
equivalent cities elsewhere in terms of comfort, amenities,
architecture and transport. Generally speaking, there Is
no shortage of schools in these capitals or rather there
Is a shortage only to the extent that the cities grow too
fast: it Is not easy to provide for the education of shanty-
town children.
Yet Africa remains and will continue to remain rural:
the vast majority of Its people will continue to live and
work In innumerable villages which seem all the more
scattered on account of the scarcity of roads. When, as
often happens, a school Is built in one of the markets
which spring up by the roadside, Its influence extends
for only a short distance around. Education Is still
Impossible for most young Africans unless they are ready
to travel great distances or quit their homes altogether a
solution which Is accepted as a last resort for boys but
rarely for girls.
The situation is particularly serious in sparsely populat¬
ed regions. In a large part of Ethiopia, in Somalia and
in the huge semi-arid plains which stretch from the Nile
to the Atlantic between the Sahara and the forest zone
there are less than five inhabitants per square kilometre.
No heating problems and
no window panes needed
UNDER-popuLATioN is disastrous in its effect on the
development of an effective and complete network
of schools. It may be said that the percentage of
African children attending school is always related to the
density of the population. Educational authorities,
however limited the funds available, are always ready to
provide a school and teachers if asked to do so by a town
with a population of 10,000, but they admit their helpless¬
ness when asked to provide the same facilities for 50 vil¬
lages of 200 inhabitants.
These 50 villages are not demanding that someone be
sent at great expense to build schools; most of them are
quite ready to build the school themselves and even to
build a home for the master. In most African countries
a school building can be of a very modest type: there Is
no heating problem and the windows can easily be left
without glass.
During the conference of education ministers and
directors which was organized by Unesco at Addis Ababa
in February 1960 (1), the representative of Somalia
declared: "Let us leave aside the building problem. If
necessary, a tree is enough to prop a blackboard up and
provide a little shade. It is the teacher who makes the
school, not the building. The real problem is the problem
of teachers."
Textbooks on African
history, people needed
If one considers the requirements in qualified staff for
Africa as a whole, the question of resources inevitably
assumes disturbing proportions. Some idea of what is
involved was given by the Emperor of Ethiopia in opening
the Addis Ababa conference: to provide the millions of
young Africans who still lack schools with the education
they are entitled to "more than 345,000 teachers" must
be trained, provided with accommodation and given the
means to live properly in the course of the next few years.
Thus the regional co-operation which several African
nations have decided to institute should give priority to
teacher training. This co-operation, to which the inter¬
national aid factor should be added, can also help to solve
the problem of textbooks.
Even when there are enough books they are not always
(1) The following countries took part: Republic of the
Congo, Belgium, the French Community (represented
by Dahomey, France, Madagascar and the Mali Federa¬
tion), Ethiopia, Ghana, Guinea, Liberia, Nigeria, Sierra
Leone, Somalia, United Kingdom.
Photos © Paul Almasy, Paris
The tiny villages of Africa are as eager as larger towns to have schools. But
education authorities admit they are often helpless to do anything about it. Most
villages though are ready to build their school themselves. Below, village council
-
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
suited to the pupils' real needs. There are African publish¬
ers and textbooksat least in East Africabut books are
mostly Imported from Europe. Designed for children with
a completely different social and geographical back¬
ground, they present young Africans with an additional
problem: the mastering of texts which, though excellent
according to English or French pedagogic standards, are
not designed for African needs.
Accordingly, all African educationalists urge that, at
least for certain subjects, publishers should produce books
which take Into account the history and the national and
ethnic characteristics of each country. Some action
along these lines has already been taken, notably in
Ghana, Nigeria and Guinea.
Adapting textbooks for primary school children raises
another vitally Important question, the need for language
reform and unification. Today, all the nations of
Africa irrespective of size face this problem of the Babel
of tongues. There Is not a single country in tropical
Africa where the same language Is spoken by all the
inhabitants, for in each country the different peoples and
provinces all speak different languages. No African today
can hope to make himself understood by all his fellow-
countrymen when speaking his native tongue.
In some countries children starting school begin by
learning to read in an African language which is not
necessarily their mother tongue but which is the most
common in their district or province. This language
introduces them to the basic rules and teaches them that
signs on paper represent sounds, pictures and Ideas. In
other countries they learn to read and write In their own
language much later (and If they particularly wish to):
from the first year, reading is taught In French or,
elsewhere, in Spanish, English or Portuguese.
In any case, those who begin by spelling out stories and
poems in Asante-Twi, in Yoruba, in Ibo, in Lingala or in
Ki-Swahlll know that the real medium of Instruction will
be a European language and that unless they learn it,
they will only have at best four year's primary education.
Visiting new schools,
a startling experience
One of the most serious problems of African education
is the lag in secondary education. It is a rather dis¬
concerting experience to visit some secondary
schools in Africa. They range from venerable ones
like Mfantsipim on the Cape Coast or King's College in
Th« Unesco Courier. February 1961
Legos to the new and luxurious Queen's College at Yaba
(245 young ladies are given a finished education at a cost
of £60 a year to their parents and 11250 to the govern¬
ment). There are the modern schools of striking architec¬
ture such as the Gabré Marlam Secondary School of Addis
Ababa and the stark, almost industrial Institutions like
the excellent secondary school of Conakry.
Everything here Is "like In Manchester" or "like In Tou¬
louse", Just as on crossing one frontier, schools and their
appearance, the curriculum, the regulations and atmo¬
sphere the whole life of these schools recalls
Liège or Cadiz. The only difference Is that the pupils
are African. In exceptional cases as many as 30 or 40 per
cent of the teachers and administrators are African, but
usually the proportion Is closer to one per cent. Sec¬
ondary education In Africa depends In the main on the
foreigner. Civil servants, missionaries, representatives of
"voluntary agencies", and teachers, come from Europe,
America or Asia (In Ethiopia and on the East coast many
teachers from India are to be found).
Only one child in twenty
reaches secondary level
All this is to the goodand the work accomplished by
these institutions cannot be minimized. They have
helped Africa to take its place In International life
and It would hardly be an exaggeration to say that It Is
in the lycées, in the secondary and high schools that the
independence of the young African nations was born.
Today the whole educational system of the new States still
relies on these schools- and will do so for a long time to
come. Nevertheless, they are Inadequate; there arc too
few of them and, except In a few countries, their develop¬
ment would be extremely difficult.
A Unesco inquiry carried out In 22 countries of tropical
Africa has shown that In 17 of them the proportion of
secondary to primary school pupils Is less than 5 per cent
and in only four countries Is the proportion higher than
7 per cent. Yet even this does not mean that out of 100
pupils more than seven complete a secondary course and
can pass the examinations corresponding to the British
General Certificate of Education or the French baccalau¬
réat. There are approximately 5,000 Africans In Kenya
secondary schools against 580,000 In the primary schools,
yet of these, In 1959, only 605 boys and 49 girls obtained
the Cambridge Oversea School Certificate, which must be
followed by another two years' school before It is possible
to enter a university or technical college.
discussing such a project. About 17,000,000 children In Africa have no chance to go
to school. As Emperor Haile Selassie of Ethiopia recently explained, one of the
reasons is that "more than 345,000 teachers" are lacking and must urgently be trained.
CONT'D ON PAGE 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Obstacle Course To Leadership
SIX MEN WITH A PROBLEM
All the young nations of Africa are today on the lookout for suitable candidates
to fill key administrative jobs. In Ghana, the Institute for Education at the Uni¬
versity of Accra has drawn up a series of group tests to assess the leadership
qualities of students and persons from private and official bodies. Photos show
six candidates undergoing two of these tests. Each test poses a problem which
can only be solved by collective action, careful thought and preparation. To
find the right solution and carry it out demands intelligence, initiative, clear¬
sightedness and organizing ability as well as energyand physical skill. It is left to
one man to assert leadership over others. A jury notes individual performances.
PROBLEM
Leadership problem posed to six
young Africans is shown in diagram
(above). Men must cross from A
to B over an imaginary precipice C
taking with them a heavy iron pipe
and a large metal drum. They are
allowed to use three tyres as sup¬
ports hanging over the "preci¬
pice." The men put their heads
together and one of them, Amissah,
comes up with an idea for the solu¬
tion which he explains to the others.
^>w
FIRST TRY
Amissah's idea is to use a rope to
pull two tyres to point A, then use
these to "launch" one man to the
third tyre and thus to point B.
But the attempt fails (photo left)
for this was not the correct solution,
and the man who tried to get across
could easily have fallen into the
"precipice." Amissah has shown
rashness in risking the lives of the
others, and the jury notes down:
"Not enough sense of responsiblity."
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
¿*
H
ir
SECOND TRY...
SUCCESS
Another member of the group,
Dunyoh, comes forward with a
new idea: "If we push the pipe
through the tyres it will act as a
bridge along which we can take the
drum. When we have all crossed
to the other side, all we need do is
pull the pipe after us and the
problem is solved." Above and
below, Dunyoh's idea workedhe
scores highly for the initiative and
organizing ability he has displayed.
Photos c Piul Aim«/, Pins
Kftffik
tfâ
i *»*
*
J**)l
%
e*
m,'Tjgaf;
il
ï \ ¡¿S** í
¿MA
1
-V
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
SIX MEN WITH A PROBLEM
(NUMBER 2)
A NEW TEST, far more difficult than the first, now
faces the six candidates. This time the iron pipe has
to be transported from one high wooden barrier to
another over an imaginary precipice. The team is
given a rope with indications as to the limits of what
they can do with it. Unlike in the first test, there
are no helpful supports hanging over the "precipice".
*&'$'?
'/- 11
WHÉ"*
*WatM*&?
y*r.W~
»Mte
r>^
FIRST TRY
Everyone agrees that the rope,
tied with a running knot, must be
thrown over and hooked to the
post on the far side and this is
eventually done. Three men then
try to snake their way over the
rope, but one falls into the "preci¬
pice" and is eliminated from the test.
I
Photos © Paul Almasy, Pari:
SECOND TRY
One of the men now comes up with
a new idea. Stretching himself
full-length along the rope, he takes
the iron pipe on his shoulder for
support and slowly inches across.
This feat calls for considerable skill,
determination and physical stamina.
IkMrngh/. k
1^**** ... -~m 1 /*. -a'
-*éa>.
%
3
tskf a
*
«
'
m*a
VICTORY
This is the only correct approach to
the problem. In the final scene we
see the pipe and the last men
successfully reaching the far bar¬
rier. The pipe, it should be noted,
is heavy and awkward to handle.
-,
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Februory 1961
NEW SCHOOLS FOR AFRICA
(Cont'd from page 23)
The existing secondary schools would probably be
sufficient to train suitable candidates needed for higher
education. But It is a mistake to regard secondary
education merely as as preparatory stage for college and
to assume that only as many students are needed as can
be absorbed by the universities, medical schools and
technical institutes.
Secondary education must be conceived rather as a
type and level of education on Its own, even when It does
not necessarily lead to higher education. As African
leaders point out, it has an Important part to play in
raising the cultural level of a nation as well as in promot¬
ing economic, social and political development.
Secondary education Is a necessary qualification for
those who hold many posts In trade and the civil service
and in the rural development programmes which are so
vital to Africa today. The need Is growing everywhere
for administrative and technical senior officials, for
skilled and semi-skilled workers, but this need cannot be
met by the present rate of secondary school graduates.
Even more serious is the lag In technical education on
the secondary level. Ghana, for example, with more than
500,000 pupils at school In a population of five million,
has been unable thus far to set up and maintain a single
technical school. And this despite Its many other second¬
ary schools and shop training centres (like those of the
Cocoa Board), despite its 500 students at Accra Univers¬
ity and almost as many at the Kumasi School of Technol¬
ogy and despite its admirable school radio system.
It is not difficult to discover the reasons for these
shortcomings. Few people believed that Industrial deve¬
lopment would take place so rapidly In the Independent
African nations. Then too, It has always been easier to
find good foreign teachers In languages, mathematics,
Latin grammar and similar subjects than In mechanics,
foundry techniques or electricity, Industrial design or
applied science.
Machines arrive faster
than do the instructors
Today, the equipment, the machines and the
material are arriving much faster than the
teachers. Already in general secondary as well as
in .technical education, the lack of qualified teachers has
created an alarming situation. Teachers are needed by
the hundreds for science, mathematics, English, French
and, in such countries as Somalia, even Arabic. It is to
be hoped that all nations in a position to send teaching
staff abroad will heed the appeal for help that the
countries of Africa have made.
But in the long run, this help, however generous It may
be, will not be enough. So long as independent Africa
has to rely entirely, or just about, on outside aid, it will
not obtain the complete educational system It needs and
wants. At best this will only keep education at its
present level. Future bilateral or multilateral assistance
would best be devoted primarily to the training of African
secondary teachers for general and technical education.
In all of tropical Africa there was only one training
college for technical and vocational teachers as of
January 1961. As to teachers of literature and science,
they must come from the universities, which are only
now beginning to provide the graduates needed for Indus¬
try, hospitals, the big plantations and the civil service.
Of the thousand students at the Ibadan university, 600
are studying science, medicine and economics; of the
remaining 400 there are many who will not become
teachers.
This is only one example but it is typical of most of the
countries in Africa. It is therefore urgent that teacher
training be speeded up by every possible means if a very
serious crisis in secondary education, and in education at
all levels, is to be avoided.
There was full awareness of this situation when the
Ministers and Directors of Education of the countries of
Tropical Africa met In Addis Ababa last February. They
made an urgent appeal to Unesco for help In the creation
and operation of regional teacher training Institutions,
chiefly for secondary schools.
Unesco has answered this appeal. Its programme for
1961-1962 provides for the creation In Tropical Africa of
two regional centres which will train educators for future
teacher-training colleges and also to carry out educa¬
tional research.
Furthermore, through the United Nations Special Fund,
Unesco will be able to help In the development of second¬
ary education. For example, In Nigeria It Is proposed
to set up a federal teacher-training college for secondary
schoolteachers, with the fund contributing $800,000 and
the Nigerian Government $1,800,000.
Most people simply do not realize the scope of the
gigantic tasks confronting the countries of tropical
Africa. Many believe that once the basic essentials are
achieved everything In the garden will be rosythat
education will develop automatically and quickly with the
smoothness of a well-oiled machine. The truth is that
most of the countries of Africa are going to be at their
wit's end to provide teachers for the thousands of schools
that need to be built.
Girls will go to school
when Dad is convinced
Nor can It be said that the children currently at
school are really receiving adequate primary
Instruction. Attendance figures are somewhat
misleading. Out of a thousand pupils In a given town or
district, how many will actually complete their primary
schooling? How many will give up after two or three
years in the lower classes?
Even for those who do go on until graduation, the use¬
fulness of the education provided Is often placed In doubt.
This Is particularly the case for girls. Relatively few
girls go to school except In two or three countries, they
account for barely 30% of the attendance. This Is some¬
times due to cultural, religious or traditional obstacles, but
Is more often economic In origin. Parents see the mate¬
rial advantages which education can bring to a boy, who
can thus obtain well-paid and socially desirable Jobs; but
they have no such hope regarding their daughters, and
besides there Is useful work that they can be given to do
at an early age.
Worse still, some families tend to feel that they are
making a useless sacrifice In sending their daughters to
school. What Is the use, they say, of bookish knowledge
requiring four to six years of study at the age when young
African girls are preparing for marriage a few years off?
And what good will It do them later, they add, when they
do assume the tasks and responsibilities of womanhood?
If the education of girls Is to gain wide acceptance, parti¬
cularly In farm areas, It must first prove Its usefulness,
economically and socially. Once It Is felt that because
they have gone to school women are better housekeepers,
better mothers, and even more prosperous shopkeepers,
then and only then will we see girls as numerous as their
brothers In the classroom.
No better investment than
money spent on education
Independence In Africa has seen the new countries
buckle down to the problems of education without
delay. The governments are perfectly aware that edu¬
cation, In the present circumstances of their national life,
calls for the same effort and vigilance as social stability
and economic prosperity and they do not hesitate to say
so bluntly. It may be trite and hackneyed to say that the
future of each country depends on the education given
the younger generation, but In Africa today It is being
said with firm insistence. It would Indeed be a pity If
the states or organizations responsible for the aid offered
to these countries were to think of development only in
terms of Industry, equipment and finance and were to
overlook the fact that there is no better. investment than
expenditure on behalf of education.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
TOWARDS HARMONY
BETWEEN RACES
by Alfred Métraux
The special Issue which The Unesco
\JT jf Courier published last October on
^/l "Racism" has had broad repercussions
NJ^ around the world. Many people
' Ä Ä have raised questions concerning
Unesco's past activities and expressed
interest in the organization's future
plans to fight the virus of racism.
In attempting to present the
picture of Unesco's action in this
field, I should like, first, to clear up one misappre¬
hension which seems to be widespread. Unesco is not a
political body. It is an international organization for
science, education and the arts, and can act only in those
fields which are within Its competence. It directs Itself
to the "minds of men"; It Is in the minds of men that it
seeks to construct the defences against war and racism,
leaving to other bodies action in the sphere of politics.
Unesco's Constitution denounces the "doctrine of the
inequality of men and races", but Unesco's struggle Is
aimed not only against the "racist doctrine" but also
against the attitudes and ways of thinking which are
at the root of this doctrine. Unesco's first task, there¬
fore, was to dispel the many false notions and easy ste¬
reotypes which are the basis and framework of racism.
It is surprising to see how ignorant the public at large
and even more educated groups often are on these
matters; one can even go so far as to say that there Is
a gap of at least half a century between science and
public opinion on the facts of race.
H The very Idea of "race" often breeds confusion. Ten
years ago, Unesco commissioned two groups of scientists
to draw up a Declaration on Race In which they set forth,
in "clear and simple form", the present state of our
knowledge of the problem of racial equality and of the
unity of the human species. This declaration was only
a brief summary of the results of the work carried on
for many years in research centres and laboratories.
To make available to the public Information on various
aspects of this problem and on the scientific facts behind
the Declaration on Race, Unesco published a series of
booklets entitled "The Race question in Modern Science."
For this series, specialists from various countries who had
distinguished themselves by their research on the race
problem were invited to expound their own conclusions
and those reached by other scientists as well (1).
The race problem involves human nature as a whole.
Consequently, It concerns many branches of science, both
the natural as well as the social sciences; no single branch
has the answer to all the questions. Thus, the psychol¬
ogist made his contribution by "pulling the rug" from
under certain tests designed to prove the inferiority of
one race as compared to another, by exposing glaring
errors of method used in these tests. The geneticist
produced a new definition of the notion of race In the
light of modern biology. The sociologist analysed the
nature and the forms of inter-racial conflict. The role
of the cultural anthropologist was to bring out the deci¬
sive influence of social environment upon the shaping of
personality. And only a speclallst In physical anthropo¬
logy was qualified to expose the absurd notion which so
many persons still have about the so-called harmful effect
of racial mixtures.
All these numerous facets of the same problem were
treated competently and objectively In the dozen booklets
28
Brazil ¡s a striking
example of a country
in which men and
women of different
racial groups live side
by side in harmony.
published in the series already mentioned. The scientists
who wrote them were careful to avoid any assertion of
an emotional or ethical nature. They concealed neither
our ignorance nor our doubts. However, they all felt that
they had to speak out, for, If the scientist himself
remained silent, it must have appeared that totally false
ideas and brutal doctrines were undisputed truths. That
is why it was important to impress on the public the fact
that no branch of science offers the slightest argument
in support of racism.
The Race booklets have met with considerable sucess,
and have now been translated into eleven languages, of
which the English edition runs to almost 250,000 copies.
The great interest shown by the public in the race pro¬
blem is reflected in the popularity of the Unesco Series.
The many articles that have appeared in newspapers and
periodicals based on these studies, the group discussions
which the booklets have inspired all these have combined
to bring the facts on racism, formerly available only to
the specialist, to a broad international audience, and have
thus been instrumental in reducing bias and prejudice.
The problems raised by racial prejudice and its
resulting discrimination are not only of a scientific
nature. It would be absurd to think that one could put
an end to racial conflict and its tragic consequences
merely by debunking the false Ideas and stereotypes of
racist thinking. Racism is also a problem of conscience.
And it Is for this reason that various religions and philo¬
sophies have expressed definite views on the problem.
To its collection "The Race Question in Modern Science",
Unesco therefore added a new series entitled "The Race
Question In Modern Thought". It comprises a group of
essays defining the attitudes adopted by the great world
religions towards the diversity of the human family.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. February 1961
Pierre Verger.
In the volumes published thus far, great theologians
and philosophers have discussed the attitude toward
racism adopted by the Catholic Church, the Protestant
churches. Buddhism and Judaism. The authors are dist¬
inguished not only for their scholarship but also because
of their position in the religious movements of our time.
While all world religions agree in condemning racism
and all proclaim the equality of mankind and human
dignity, they do so at times in different terms. It Is
because these differences of approach all lead to the same
conclusion that the cause of anti-racism is strengthened.
Few persons would deny that deep-rooted prejudices
and stereotypes those which are hardest to get rid of in
adults are acquired at a very early age. This means
that, to be truly effective, educational measures must
begin at school. As the UN Agency for education, Unesco
has therefore carried its campaign against racial bias
into the classroom. But realizing that the school curri¬
culum is already over-burdened In most countries, and
that the addition of a separate subject would be difficult,
it has sought to reach the student through the teacher,
by providing the latter with the most up-to-date findings
of modern science for incorporation in normal lessons.
With this purpose in view, Unesco commissioned two
textbooks: Cyril Blbby's Race, Prejudice and Education
in English (See The Unesco Courier, October 1960)
already translated into German and Hebrew, with other
language versions foreseen ; and Professor Juan Comas's
La Educación ante la Discriminación racial (Education
and Racial Discrimination), intended for school-teachers
in Latin America. A small illustrated pamphlet for
schools entitled What is Race? has also been published.
Parallel with this publishing venture, Unesco launched
a series of original research projects on race relations.
An enormous amount of research on this subject had of
course already been done by groups In many countries,
but Unesco's Investigations were focused on a relatively
llttle-studled aspect harmonious race relations.
The fact of the matter Is that the meeting of races Is
not necessarily marked by conflict or prejudice as some
people maintain. There are areas and regions where men
of different skin colour live slde-by-slde In perfect har¬
mony and are mutually enriched by their respective cul¬
tural backgrounds.
H The U.S. State of Hawaii and Brazil arc typical exam¬
ples of multi-racial lands where people get along very
well -with each other. Since race relations In Hawaii had
already been extensively studied, Unesco decided to carry
out Its research In Brazil. The task was entrusted to
teams of sociologists and psychologists who studied the
race situation in different regions of the country, both
In rural and urban environments. The results of this
work were set forth In several books, of which two were
published by Unesco (2) and the others by Brazilian Ins¬
titutions and publishing houses.
Along similar lines, Unesco organized other research
projects In countries where ethnic minorities were In
process of assimilation. Mexico, the French West Indies,
the United States and Yugoslavia offered research sub¬
jects of great Interest. The conclusions of these research
projects have been published by Unesco under the fol¬
lowing titles: Contacts dc civilisation en Martinique ct
Guadeloupe by Michel Lelrls (In French only); Racial
Equality and the Law by Morroe Berger, an excellent ana¬
lysis of American legislation to achieve racial equality.
A book prepared by Unesco but published by the Colum¬
bia University Press In the United States summarizes
field studies In the New World: Minorities in the Neto
World by Charles Wagley and Marvin Harris.
I The rapid development of African societies and the
growing number of Africans who are becoming prominent
In fields hitherto considered the prerogative of the white
race offer powerful arguments against theories of racism
and "racial pessimism", which are Invoked all too often
to justify discriminatory attitudes and measures. It was
doubly Interesting for Unesco, therefore, to make a scien¬
tific analysis of the process of modernization in Africa
which, far more effectively than any theory, proves the
aptitude of all ethnic groups to benefit from progress.
Sociological research on the new leaders who arc spring¬
ing up in Africa was carried out by Unesco In Dahomey,
Ghana and Nigeria. These studies were recently supple¬
mented by research on African women who, having
broken with their traditional environment, have now
joined the cultural revolution sweeping their countries.
Up until now, Unesco's attention has been concentrated
upon the positive aspects of race relations. But the
recent racist manifestations which have spread like wild¬
fire throughout the world have led Unesco to turn to the
question of racism and Its Influence on modern youth.
A large-scale International Investigation of a psychologi¬
cal and sociological character Is now being prepared
by Unesco to determine the depth of racial prejudice
among youth, Its causes, Its persistence and methods of
fighting It.
Furthermore, Unesco's last General Conference recently
adopted a draft convention and recommendations
concerning discriminatory measures in education, and the
adherence of Member States to this convention can hardly
fall to result In measures which are bound to counteract
racial prejudices.
I Finally, there are prospects that an International orga¬
nization will be set up to act as a permanent documenta¬
tion and research centre on race relation problems.
Unesco Is now studying the conditions under which It
can help such an organization to get started.
These are some of the main activities which Unesco
has undertaken or Is preparing to undertake to fight the
"social cancer of our time". Unesco Is well aware of the
responsibilities which, as a member of the U.N. family, It
has assumed In this field and It will not shirk them.
(1) A collective volume of these publications "The Hace Question
in Modern Science", 11 now in preparation and will be published
jointly by the Tultle Company of Tokyo and Unesco, l'aris. A special
U.S. edition will be published by the Columbia University I'ress,
New York.
(2) "Race and Clais in Rural Brazil" by Charles Wagley, and "Les
élites de couleur dam une ville brésilienne" IThe coloured /Hite in a
Brazilian Town) by Thaies de Azeiiedo (French only).
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Prado Museum, Madrid
> 'â
LAS MENINAS by DIEGO VELAZQUEZ.
VELAZQUEZ A LA PICASSO
When he was 14 years old, Pablo Picasso visited the Prado in Madrid with his father
and saw for the first time the famous painting, "Las Meninas" (Ladies in Waiting),
masterpiece of the 17th century Spanish artist, Velazquez (see special issue Unesco
Courier, December 1960). It was an experience he never forgot. The memory
of this court scene with its wealth of detail and the engaging figure of the tiny Infanta
haunted him for years. "What a picture," he once remarked to a friend. "What
realism !... What a marvellous achievement." In the autumn of 1957, Picasso brought
to artistic fruition years of pent-up feelings about Velazquez' great work. For two
months he shut himself away from his friends and created a series of 45 paintings
in which he took for his theme the whole or parts of " Las Meninas. " The largest
canvas, 6 feet by nearly 9 feet, painted in monochrome (below centre) incorporates
all of the main features found in the original. Many of the series are innumerable
variations of aspects of the original, particularly those studies of the Infanta which
reveal Picasso's remarkable versatility and his audacious treatment of the work.
ilia 1
f ^j
F ePi
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1961
Photos Pic © Editions Cercle d'Art, Pans
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
They call their telescope
Java's puppet hero, they say, was so tall he
straddled the Milky Way. What better name for a
telescope ¡n Indonesia's modern Bosscha observatory
by
Victor M. Blanco
; Estled on the western hills of the Island of
I Java, with a semi-dormant volcano as a
I backdrop, lies the Bosscha Astronomical
I Observatory, a unique nstltutlon in South-
I East Asia. There amid meticulously kept
gardens rises a monumental dome-shaped building
housing two of the large refracting telescopes of the
world. The telescopes, manned by young Indonesian
scientists are actively helping to widen man's scientific
horizons. The publications of the Bosscha Observatory
are read and collected In hundreds of scientific centres
throughout the world.
The Republic of Indonesia, while struggling with some
of today's most difficult socio-economic problems,
maintains the observatory. This shows that Indonesia
has in sight high cultural goals for its youth. The
Bosscha Observatory is a symbol of the opportunities that
the Republic envisions for Its young scientists. Thousands
of students of all ages visit it every year. Astronomy
often awakens a child's first scientific curiosity.
H The observatory is thus not only a symbol of future
goals but a busy centre of present-day popular education.
This rôle Is ntenslfled by the visitors from the city of
Bandung that flock to the observatory during holy days.
Bandung, a city of nearly one million inhabitants, is
spread like a carpet in a valley twelve kilometres distant
from the observatory. From the spacious lawns at
Bosscha, the public can view a striking panorama while
enjoying the cool mountain air.
The geographic position of the observatory, seven
degrees south of the equator, is important from the
astronomical point of view. Bosscha's telescopes can
sweep across some of the most important constellations
In the sky. The nucleus of our galaxy or Milky Way, for
example, lies in Sagittarius, a constellation that can not
be observed to advantage from the northern hemisphere
where most of the large telescopes are concentrated.
The solutions to many problems regarding the life
history and distribution in space of stars, such as our
own sun, involve studies of the nuclear regions of our
galaxy., Besides geographic convenience, Bosscha Obser¬
vatory enjoys a remarkably steady atmosphere. Astro¬
nomers iwho must study a star's light from the ground
are keenly aware of the vagaries of the atmosphere and
how often these spoil their viewing.
H The observatory owes its origin to the financial help
of a tea plantation owner, Karel A.R. Bosscha. The
principal instruments were installed in 1928 and 1929.
From the time of its founding and up to World War II,
several distinguished Dutch astronomers worked there.
The war and subsequent conflicts were disastrous to the
observatory. Not only did three leading members of the
staff perish, but the various military occupations resulted
in plundering and all-round deterioration of the
observatory's facilities.
The rehabilitation work started in 1947 and still
continues. In 1950, Unesco joined the Indonesian
government in the acquisition of a new telescope for the
Bosscha Observatory. An optical design developed by the
German optician Bernhard Schmidt (1879-1935) was
selected. A Schmidt-type telescope would be particularly
advantageous at this location, benefiting greatly from
the geographic position and good observing conditions.
32
This project developed during the last decade, and it
involved the co-operation of astronomers, opticians, and
engineers from Indonesia, the Netherlands, and the United
States. The optical parts for the telescope were donated
by Unesco and were prepared at the Yerkes Observatory
of the University of Chicago. The mechanical parts were
contracted for by the Indonesian government with the
engineering firm of Rademakers In Rotterdam. In the
spring of last year the glass or optical components of the
telescope met the metallic parts for the first time. The
assembly, adjustment and testing were completed by May
28 when the telescope was officially inaugurated.
An instrument of this kind requires the utmost delicacy
of adjustment in order to operate properly. Mechanical
difficulties were to be expected In the assembly work.
Fortunately the Bosscha Obervatory has a well-equipped
machine shop staffed by able specialists, and thanks to
them the difficulties were ironed out as they arose. It
was not always easy to obtain the materials required by
the machinists. However, in the city of Bandung there
are numerous junk shops where with luck one can find
suitable supplies. Some of the aluminium pieces for the
new telescope were carved out of wartime airplane
propellers. The Unesco optics are supported in the tele¬
scope's mounting with pads of sheet lead originally
intended for household plumbing.
HThe optical parts donated by Unesco for the new tele¬
scope include a delicately polished mirror twenty-eight
inches In diameter. The mirror Is used to converge the
rays of starlight to the focus. Telescope mirrors are made
by depositing on polished glass a thin layer of an alloy
of aluminium. For this purpose the aluminium alloy is
vaporized inside a vacuum chamber sufficiently large to
contain the glass, and the vapour then coats the glass,
giving It high reflectivity. The coating tarnishes with
time, however, and in normal use such mirrors must be
periodically re-aluminized.
Fumes from the nearby volcano Tangkuban Prahu,
whose crater is only five kilometres from the observatory,
may cause the new telescope mirror to tarnish or deterio¬
rate more rapidly than, is normal, or desirable. This
problem had to be solved during the assembly of the
telescope. Consultations between the astronomers, the
geologists and the chemists of the Bandung Institute
of Technology resulted In the building of an air purifying
system. This system frees the air of its sulphurous fumes,
pumps clean air into the sealed telescope and thus pro¬
longs the mirror's life.
Early in the planning, the new telescope was named
Bima Sakti. Blma Saktl, whose initials are also those
of Bernhard Schmidt, is one of the heroes of the Javanese
wayang or puppet plays, which are based on the great
Hindu epic Mahabharata. In Javanese mythology, Blma
Sakti is so tall that when he stands with feet resting on
opposite sides of the earth his legs form the arch across
the sky that we know as the Milky Way. The name of
this ancient hero is thus particularly appropriate for a
telescope that will be devoted to Milky Way observations.
The new telescope is regarded with endearment by the
staff and workmen of the observatory. One might say
that some of the ancient hero's personality has rubbed
off on the telescope. Blma Sakti, who fought against
evil in the old epics, is thus active again, helping to
advance science in Indonesia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. February 1961
Letters to the Editor
PITQA & ITS PEN-FRIENDS
Sir,
I was especially pleased to see the
article on "Pitoa pilot school ¡n a
Cameroon village" in your Septem¬
ber issue because I have always follow¬
ed with interest the devoted efforts
of Roger Lagrave. You might like to
know that there is a booklet telling all
about the letters exchanged between
Lagrave's pupils and those of other
French teachers. It is No 366 in the
"Bibliothèque de Travail" - Edition dé
l'Ecole Moderne Française ; Techni¬
que Freinet, and is entitled "L'Enfant
africain vu par l'enfant blanc" (The
African child as seen by the European
child.)
So the work you describe is not an
isolated case. Such exchanges often
take place (though perhaps with less
success) and are the fruit of the
Moderne" methods. My own
class exchanged letters with a class in
Tunisia in 1954, in Casablanca in
1955 and with a class on Reunion
Island in the Indian Ocean. All these
exchanges were achieved like that of
Lagrave under the aegis of the Frei¬
net educational techniques (Ecole Mo¬
derne) and we are convinced that if
such activities were generalized they
could do much to serve the cause of
peace and help to banish the affliction
called racism.
M. Nadeau
Azur, Landes, France
Sir,
I was happy to see Lagrave's work
in the Cameroons described in a fine
article. I hope it will be followed by
another explaining that this pen-friend
activity to bring better understanding
between peoples is not an isolated in¬
cident, but is being repeated thousands
of times between regions and between
nations.
Thirty children from a school in
the Loiret Department came to live in
our village in Calvados and the peo¬
ple here were delighted. We, in turn,
will go to visit them in the Loiret.
Links have been formed which I am
delighted to see maintained by my for¬
mer pupils and among adults too.
This year our school was making con¬
tacts with Egypt.
And so it goes on around the world
as people make use of the Freinet edu¬
cational methods to build bonds of
friendship.
M. Baucé
Sept-Frères, Calvados, France
Sir,
I read with much interest your
feature remarkably well illustrated
on the contacts between the Cameroons
school children and children in rural
France But it is a pity that you failed
to speak of the thousands of "Ecole
Moderne" classes which practise this
correspondence in France and else¬
where in the world, thus working for
a better understanding and friendship
between peoples.
It. Rufet
Lochrist, Morbihan, France
Sir,
I was so deeply interested in the
article on the Pilot School in a Came¬
roon Village. The exchange of let¬
ters between the little African child
and the French boy and, in fact, the
whole article is not only delightful but
most interesting.
Elsie Smith Cosfcllo
Board of Christian Education
The United Presbyterian Church
in the U.S.A.
Philadelphia 7, Pennsylvania
BELA BARTOK & FOLK MUSIC
Sir,
Today Bêla Bartok is universally
acknowledged as one of the greatest
men of our century. In his papers on
Folk tunes and Folk music he showed
the momentous importance of compa¬
rative research work in this field,
especially in certain territories such as
Greece, Turkey and Central Asia.
He stressed the fact that this job must
be done with no delay, modern times
everywhere revolutionizing the way of
life of the peasants and thereby de¬
stroying indigenous music. And, as
Bartok said, once perished, this pre¬
cious heritage of ours will be gone for¬
ever, never to be retrieved. He realiz¬
ed that only a powerful international
organization can carry through the
resoue work to be done on a large
scale.
May I suggest to you to dedicate
one of your next issues to this worthy
subject by publishing excerpts from
Bartók's and Kodaly's writings (with
pictures!) and by stating Unesco's
position in regard to the problems in
question and by reporting on its acti¬
vities in this field.
W.A. Schocken
Tel Aviv, Israel
THE EQUALITY OF PEOPLES
Sir,
By your untiring and purposeful
work you contribute towards a matur¬
ing of consciences which should bring
into being a universal humanism. I
am a coloured man and by this fact
I believe that the equality of peoples,
nations and races is not a "fiction".
It is said that this equality is true
before God, and I say that if it does
not exist in fact it is because that
there are men who still believe in the
superiority and supremacy of certain
nations. I think the author of "Plain
spoken or rose coloured" fa letter
published in the May 1960 issue] is
one of these people.
I believe that despite our great his¬
torical leeway we shall never place
the Papuan tom-tom on the same level
as Mozart for the simple reason that
we are well able to distinguish bet¬
ween different shades and values.
Frantz Chaloncc
Fort-dc-Francc, Martinique
MORE FOOD OR FEWER PEOPLE
Sir,
I was very pleased to read of the
great work of PAO in the world cam¬
paign against hunger, in your Septem¬
ber 1960 issue. I look forward to
reading more about this important
work in a future issue of Tur. Uni.sco
Courier. I cannot agree with the
views expressed by your Amsterdam
correspondent in his letter, headed:
"Millions more mouths to feed."
Family planning is not the answer to
population difficulties. People who
advocate it are surely going right
against the facts. The scientists who
are concerned with the actual work
of producing food and finding new
ways of increasing food supplies tell
us that the earth can supply plenty of
food for all. The real problem we
arc facing in the world today is that
of distribution, not ovcr-f>opulation.
A campaign (with all the money that
family planning advocates desire for
their purposes) to solve this problem
would be a far greater and more cons¬
tructive contribution towards coping
with food difficulties than family
planning. After all, to use a homely
example, if ten people need hats and
there are only eight hats available, the
common-sense solution is (o get two
more hats from somewhere, not to
cut off two people's heads !
T. McNicholas
Nazeing, Essex, England
PERILS OF THE TV VIEWER
Sir,
I should like to see in the columns
of The Unesco Courier a detailed
article answering the following ques¬
tions:
Is it harmful to watch TV broad¬
casts?
How does television affect the ner¬
vous system and the eyes of the view¬
er?
If there are harmful effects from
television, how are they to be avoided?
S. Voroshilovskaya
Kishenev, US.S.R.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Net
N UBIA'S TREASURES ON FILM :
A 41 -frame colour filmstrip depicting some
of the monuments of Nubia in Egypt and the
Sudan threatened by the waters of the new
Aswan Dam has been issued by Unesco.
Designed for public screening, the filmstrip
is one element in the campaign which
Unesco is waging to safeguard these an¬
cient monuments. It can be obtained, toge¬
ther with a descriptive booklet, including
commentaries on each frame, from Unesco
distributors in Member States. Further in¬
formation may be obtained from the Radio
and Visual Information Division, Mass
Communication Department, Unesco,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7")
JAPANESE ART IN HAIFA: The
people of Haifa, Israel, now have ex¬
ceptional facilities for studying and
appreciating Japanese art from among
the 4,000 items paintings, prints,
drawings, metalwork, lacquer ware
and ceramics owned by a museum
which opened there last year. Displays
are changed monthly to harmonize
with season or special occasion, only
a few objects being on display at one
time.
show any of the large, dark hollows
known as "seas" which cover a large
area of the visible surface.
Ail FRICAN DESERT INSTITUTE:
The Republic of Niger has offered to create
with Unesco assistance an international arid
zone institute for African countries south
of the Sahara, particularly in the Sahel re¬
gion encompassing Mali, Niger, Mauritania
and the Chad. The proposal was by
Dr Francis Borrey, of the Niger delegation
to the recent Unesco General Conference.
He suggested that it should be located in
the region of Agades where it could be in
contact with Sanaran areas of North Africa.
It would serve as a centre for research,
training, teaching and exchange of informa¬
tion.
HIDDEN FACE REVEALED : An
atlas of the moon's hidden face contain¬
ing 30 hitherto unpublished photographs
taken by "Lunik IV" has been publish¬
ed by the Soviet Academy of Sciences.
From these photos it has been possible
to identify 500 features of the relief on
the moon's surface which are described
in the catalogue included in the atlas.
The hidden side of the moon does not
KINGDOM OF THE OCTOPUS
Attention is called to the article by
Frank W. Lane, "The Kingdom of
the Octopus", which appeared in
our January 1961 Issue. This
article is copyright and may not be
reproduced without prior per¬
mission.
ViILLAGE FOR YOUTH: Young
refugees coming straight from camps in
various parts of Europe are the first inha¬
bitants of a village entirely for children
which has been founded in a rambling old
English manor house with 175 acres of
ground at Sedlescombe in Sussex. Even¬
tually 300 children of different nationalities
will live in the village which will be run
on similar lines to those already set up in
Switzerland and elsewhere. At first the
children will be kept in national groups so
that their own culture is preserved. Later
they will live in international groups to
"'fit them as world citizens".
CROPS FROM SAND AND SEA-
WATER: Experiments in the produc¬
tion of fruit and vegetables by a system
of "mixed hydroponics" using partly the
techniques of hydroponics (soilless cul¬
ture) and partly traditional agriculture
are now being made at an experimental
marine agriculture station at Orinon in
Spain. The main elements used are
sand from the beach and seawater.
Areas are marked out in the sand and
irrigation canals dug around them into
which the sea can flow. Areas are
prepared as in normal agricultural prac¬
tice, using chemical or organic fertili¬
zers, and already crops of maize, pota¬
toes, tomatoes and other vegetables
have been grown.
AiL N EASY DISEASE TO PREVENT:
Nearly 200,000,000 people all over . the
world suffer from enlarged thyroid, or en¬
demic goitre as it is usually called. Yet
the World Health Organization, publishing
these figures, points out that the disease is
now considered a "public health anachro¬
nism" and is very easy to prevent. The
great majority of cases are due to iodine
deficiency, and experiments in mass pro¬
phylaxis with iodized salt show that every¬
where the number of cases falls sharply fol¬
lowing increased consumption of the salt.
Effects of iodized salt have been marked
in Switzerland where it was introduced in
1923. At that time only 42.3 % of school¬
children had a normal thyroid, yet by 1937
the figure had risen to 99,3%.
RETIREMENT OF MR. JEAN
THOMAS : The retirement was
announced recently of Mr. Jean Thomas,
Assistant Director-General of Unesco.
A Frenchman, Mr. Thomas has been in
Unesco's service since its foundation in
1946, originally as Director of the
Department of Cultural Activities. He
has now agreed to become Chairman of
the Action Committee for Unesco's
International Campaign to Safeguard
the Monuments of Nubia.
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
The work of the International Bank
for Reconstruction and Develop¬
ment, one of the UN. Specialized
Agencies, is commemorated in the
stamp above which was Issued on
December 9 last year by the United
Nations Postal Administration.
Multicoloured and printed In 4 cent
and 8 cent denominations, the
stamp, the fifth U.N. commemo¬
rative stamp of I960, depicts a
double block hoisting an unseen
cargo, with the United Nations
emblem superimposed on the centre
of the block. Below, the second
stamp Issued by the United Arab
Republic to mark Unesco's Save
the Monuments of Nubia Campaign.
Printed In a 10 M (I piastre) deno¬
mination, it depicts the Temple of
Nefertari at Abu Simbel. Both
stamps can be obtained from the
Unesco Philatelic Service which
has stamps ' and first day covers
Issued by many Member States to
commemorate important events in
the history of Unesco and the
United Nations. As the agent in
France of the U.N. Postal Adminis¬
tration, Unesco's Philatelic Service
stocks all the United Nations stamps
currently on sale. Information on
items available, their price and the
methods of payment, will be sent
on request by the Unesco Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
ANNOUNCING.
A NEW ARABIC EDITIO
THE UNESCO COURIER is proud to announce tho launching of
an Arabic edition, published In Cairo under the auspices of tho
United Arab Republic National Commission for Unesco. The first
Issue has now been published and the second will appear shortly.
Subscriptions to the Arabic edition from readers living in tho United
Arab Republic should be sent to: National Commission for Unesco,
6 Shareh Abu Momen, Dekkl, Cairo, United Arab Republic.
Residents in all other countries should send for tho Arabic edition
to Unesco National Distributors (listed below). The price Is at tho
same rates as for other editions.
Readers now have a choice of six language editions: English, French, Spanish,
Russian, German and Arabic. A seventh language edition, in Japanese, Is scheduled
to begin publication In April.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaî, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 3 69 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria. (A. 15/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Seh.
50.-)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CC.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rueMarcq, Bruxelles, CC.P. 285.98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgièlei 151,
Antwerp.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 .Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, 7". CC.P. 12598-48
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb fur Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 8).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 3 86, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., I 7 Park
Street Calcutta 16, Scindia House,
New Delhi (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata",
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street. Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.f I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central. Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66i
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul
LIBERIA. ]. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's library, 26 Kingi-
way, Valetta. (10/-)
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.
30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (il 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C* (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop. P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Gren-
sen. 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374. 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49. Apartado de Correos 2018,
Panama. D.F. (Balboas 3.-).
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloia Nr. 4*.
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Ldi,
Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
RHODESIA Í. NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
S. -Rhodesia.
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Uncscoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B CE. Fritezcs. Kungl. Hovbokhandal,
Fredjgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, ru. du Marché, Geneva. CC.P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CC.P.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok,
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 lili-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore. Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria ( I 0/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlgt,
Terazi/e 27/1 I. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
-« mi-*
f% ^*
mmm m+w*ni*' *&
*' ïyP»j
iff ¡£*
^
\&üR|fc
Willy Ronis, Paris
TIME FOR REFLECTION: Lights burning in Unesco Secretariat building cast reflections on nearby cara night scene taken
during the recent Unesco General Conference. Delegates from 98 countries gave priority to education when they discussed
and approved the most ambitious programme in Unesco's history (see page 4). Of the 17 countries which have become members
of Unesco since the last General Conference in 1958, 16 are new nations of Africa (See special map and article, pages 17-20).
]]>
</page>
</document>
