<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078150eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Jí m
MARCH
1956
(9th year)
Price: 9d. (U. K.)
40 francs (France)
LANT
r.Boc/weMS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
M.
AN ARAB BOAT ON
THE EUPHRATES (School
of Baghdad, 13th century)
ARRIVAL OF SHIPS IN
BRAZIL Th. & J. de Bry,
(16th century engraving)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
MARCH - 1956
9th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
5 HOW BIASED ARE OUR HISTORY BOOKS?
By Herbert Abraham.
7 ASIA THROUGH WESTERN GLASSES
Nations take a fresh look at their textbooks
By Ronald Fenton
14 'DADDY, WHAT'S THE GOOD OF HISTORY V
By C. Peter Hill
16 THE CENTRE OF THE MAP
Each nation sees itself as the hub of history
By Marshall G.S. Hodgson.
20 DEODORIZED HISTORY
It may be wholesome, but it's unpalatable
By D.W. Brogan
24 SPECIAL EDITION
Yesterday's stories make headlines today
By J.G. Massée.
27 ASIA QUIZ
How much do you know about Asia 7
31 WORLD PRESS COMMENTARY
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM...
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9, Avenue Kleber, Pan's I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
'U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual arcicles noc copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER bue muse be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURRIER : 8/-; S2.00 or 400
French frs or equivalent (U.S. edition $2.50)
(MC 56.1.100 A)
THE NEW PANORAMA
OF HISTORY
Arnold Toynhkk, writing recently in the quar¬
terly review Diogenes (1) had some revealing
things to say about the new approach to the
study of history. "In less than one lifetime", he
remarks, "the face of the World lias changed almost
out of recognition, and the West's position in the World
has undergone the greatest change of all. If one has
been following the course of world affairs since 1914,
one is bound to have gained, from this alone, a good
deal of new knowledge about history; and meanwhile,
the forty years that have seen this new chapter of
history writing itself have also seen the orientalists
and the archaeologists recovering for us other chapters
of history that had been cither forgotten completely or
had been remembered only in a few shreds and tatters
of tradition. "
Toynbee points to the fact that "in our day the
Minoan Civilization has risen from its grave below the
Graeco-Roman Civilization; the Shang Culture in
China from below the classical Chinese Civilization;
the Indus Culture from below Aryan India; the
Hittite Civilization from below the Asia Minor known
to Herodotus; and at the same time our picture of the
Sumerian and Egyptian Civilizations, and of the
pr-Columbian Civilizations in the New World, has been
quite transformed by the new knowledge that the
excavator's spade has brought to light here too. This
re-discovery of the rather less recent past, together
with the portentous events of our own day, has given
us a wealth of new historical information. Our
vision of the history of Mankind, since the rise of the
earliest known civilizations about 5,000 years ago, has
been enormously enlarged and has also been brought
into much sharper focus. And since curiosity is one of
the characteristics of human nature, we find ourselves
moved, in our time, to take a new look at the new face
of history as a whole. "
And Toynbee adds : "As soon as one looks at the
new panorama of history, one sees that it bursts the
bounds of the current framework within which our
Western historians have been doing their work for the
last 250 years... As I write these words, I seem to catch
the faint sound of the busy archaeologist's trowel, as
he deftly uncovers new layers of buried civilizations
in Bucklersbury and Beycc Sultan and Palenque."
The very word "history", it is interesting to note,
comes from the Greek meaning "inquiry" or "investi¬
gation". All presentation of history is based on a
series of investigations and the asking of questions, as
varied and never-ending as the historian's field of
inquiry has broadened. In this issue, The Unesco
Coukiek examines a few of the questions histori¬
ans and teachers have been asking recently about the
picture of other countries and cultures which our
children seem to be getting from many history books.
(1) Published quarterly with Unesco's support by the Inter¬
national Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies. An
Knglish edition is published in New York, price §4.00 (four
numbers). French, Spanish, German, Italian and Arabic edi¬
tions are also published. Professor Toynbee's article is publish¬
ed in issue No 13. entirely devoted to Toynbee and his work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Copyright Adep-Verger
MACHiU PICCHU : THE 'LOST CITY' OF THE INCAS
Hundreds of years before the Europeans arrived on American shores,
at least three great centres of civilization had developed in North and
South America: the Mayas of Guatemala and Yucatan, the Aztecs of
Mexico, and the Incas who controlled a vast region in the Andes and
along the coast from Ecuador through Peru and Bolivia into Chile and
Argentina. If these great civilizations are not always described as
"cruel" or "barbaric", they are usually mentioned only insofar as they
are episodes in the conquests of Pizarro or Cortes and their gold-
hungry followers. Little or nothing is said in the textbooks of many
countries of these- peoples' achievements in the arts and crafts, archi¬
tecture, engineering and other domains. It is to the farmers of the
Inca empire, for example, that we owe the potato. And of all the
American Indians only the Incas had draught animals, using llamas as
mounts and as beasts of burden. Their craftsmen practised every style
of handweaving we know today. Their pottery was developed into a
highly refined art, they smelted metals and cast in moulds. They built
paved roads with suspension bridges and outpost houses at intervals over
the wildest mountain ranges and through the desert for hundreds of miles.
The Emperor of the Incas was called "the Inca", and the land he ruled'
"The Empire of the Four Parts of the World". Of the many remains of
Inca civilization scattered over the central Andean highlands, perhaps
the most mysterious is "the lost city" of Machu Picchu, north of Cuzco,
the ancient Inca capital. Discovered in 1911 by an American archaeo¬
logist, Hiram Bingham, it was entirely buried under a thick mass of
vegetation. No ancient chronicler had ever mentioned it. What hap¬
pened to its inhabitants remains one of the great enigmas of history.
Some authorities believe that Machu Picchu was a refuge for the last
Inca at the time of the Spanish conquest. Like other Inca cities, Machu
Picchu is surrounded by towering ramparts made of individual stones of
prodigious size and weighing many tons. No mortar was used, yet
after centuries these stones lie so perfectly fitted together that it is
still impossible to insert the blade of a knife between many of them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
HOW BIASED ARE OUR
HISTORY TEXTBOOKS ?
by Herbert Abraham
It is a shock to find that some
people regard you as a villain;
perhaps as much, of a shock to
learn that they ignore your existence.
If you read the history textbooks
published in other countries, you may
be offended sometimes in both ways:
at finding that your country is
regarded as the villain, and also at
that your country is virtually
ignored. If neither villain nor ignored,
you *will almost certainly conclude
that your country has been under¬
estimated, misrepresented and mis¬
understood.
Our own people, we have learned,
have on occasions been victims of
broken promises, treachery, and
massacres: the notion that "we" have
been the perpetrators of such infa¬
mies would be ridiculous if it were
not so revolting.
The British do not think of
themselves as an aggressor nation,
but it is clearly recorded in history
textbooks oí another country (and
one that is considered very friendly
to Britain) that the British started a
war against them: "Peace reigned,
yet they seized by treachery..." . The
French would not think of themselves
in the terms applied in a textbook in
another country: '"the pillage and
rapine of the invaders..." Americans
and British both feel some hurt in
their pride when they learn that there
exist accounts of the Second World
War from which it would be difficult
to deduce that their countries made
any sacrifices and took part in the
defeat of Hitler.
' Burn the books '
cry of the past
What attitudes toward other
countries do children learn from
their textbooks? It took the
First World War to spark interest in
this question.
Teachers' organizations and many
others devoted to the aims of the
newly-established League of Nations,
campaigned against "the teaching of
hatred". They denounced the kind
of history teaching which glorified
military conquests. French teachers
took the lead. The famous writer,
Anatole France, made a stirring
appeal: "Make hatred hated... Burn
the books which teach hate, burn
them all. Exalt labour and love."
Teachers, who were free to choose
textbooks for their classes, refused
to use those found "warlike". Teach¬
ers and historians from France and
Germany worked together to agree
on more objective accounts of
issues which had divided the two
countries: Alsace, for example. All
through Europe in the 1920's, plans
for revising school textbooks in the
interest of peace were propounded,
adopted and to a certain extent
were acted upon.
But nationalism took new and
virulent forms in the 1930's. The
friendly exchanges between French
and German teachers fell 'foul of Nazi
racialism, which enlisted textbooks
as tools for indoctrinating the young.
The belief that textbooks ought to
convey truth rather than falsehood
rose again when the world looked
forward to peace after the Second
World War.. Textbook revision was in
the air; there was the necessity of
producing new textbooks to replace
those used in Fascist countries;
educators in many countries were
conscious of their responsibility for
contributing to a peaceful world
order through education. When
unesco was established, an essential
part of its programme was to bring
about a review of textbooks with a
view to increasing their contribution
to international understanding.
The world scene has changed a
great deal since 1919. No one today
would use the words of Anatole
France, even in a crusading speech
for a good cause. These words "burn
the books" have an evil ring. The
temper in which educators approach
the question today has nothing in it
of boycott or censorship. It is not a
question of looking for "offensive"
passages and demanding, they be
deleted, nor of getting governments
to sign agreements to give fair treat¬
ment to one another in the textbooks.
One difference between the present
time and 1919 is that, in fact, history
books are a great deal better. There
is nothing new any longer in the idea
that the study of history should give
us some understanding of social,
economic and cultural life. There is
no need to crusade against the kind
of history that consists only of politics
and battles. Of course, the opinions
will differ as to whether a given
textbook goes into too much detail on
military campaigns, and the like.
But the general principle is widely
accepted that past wars should not be
the main feature of history teaching.
Historians have added enormously
to our knowledge of the cultures of
the past, and this is finding its way
to the textbooks. Moreover, with the
experiences of the last two genera¬
tions behind us, and with the
widespread understanding of the
perils of the future, not many people
are disposed to uphold war as a glori¬
ous experience. Overt militarism
does not sit well with the temper of
these times. Then, too, the writers
of textbooks today can build on the
work done between the two wars.
No longer seen as
picturesque ' natives '
When French and German histor¬
ians and teachers took up
again the consideration of his¬
tory textbooks after the Second
World War, they were able to take
as their starting point conclusions
that had been reached in consulta¬
tions held fifteen years. before. The
question of giving a balanced and fair
account of the story of Alsace-Lor¬
raine, for example, was not new to
them. Of course, there are obvious
difficulties in reaching agreement on
ways of treating recent events which
would not foster hatred, but which,
at the same time, would not violate
deeply-held national feelings. But
taking a long view of history, great
progress has been made toward pre¬
senting it dispassionately and objec¬
tively.
While it is true, then, that you may
sometimes be shocked by finding your
country presented as a villain in some
textbooks in other countries, you
will also sometimes be pleasantly
surprised by the scrupulous objecti¬
vity and sympathetic understanding
with which your country's past is
presented.
There is another important differ¬
ence in the scene today. We are
learning to think on a much larger
geographic scale. It was still true,
forty years ago, that when people
generally thought about the countries
that "mattered", they thought chiefly
of the Western European "Powers".
Today, we are learning to take all
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
HOW BIASED ARE
OUR TEXTBOOKS ?
	(Continued) 	
peoples into account. Ignorant as
most of us are of cultures widely
different from our own we no longer
look on millions of our fellow human
beings as more or less picturesque but
quite unimportant "natives".
This situation changes the point of
view from which we raise questions
about the teaching of history. It is
not a question of removing misunder¬
standing just between a small number
of great powers. Educators ask
themselves how they ' can better
promote understanding between all
peoples. They look at history text¬
books with this question in mind.
They find that the picture of world
history is distorted by omissions and
by a biased point of view.
' Religious fanatics,
avid for plunder'
This point emerged clearly at a
meeting of history teachers and
textbook writers which was
organized by Unesco in 1950. The
participants from western countries
had their attention directed some of
them no doubt for the first time to
the treatment of Moslem history and
civilization in the western textbooks.
It was pointed out that textbooks
emphasized only the warlike quality
of Islam ("militant, religious fanatics,
avid for plunder"). Islam and
Christianity were contrasted Chris¬
tianity spread through missionaries.
Islam through conquests. Islam
was presented as a menace from
which Western Europe was fortunately
saved at the battle of Poitiers. Social
customs of which the West disapprov¬
ed such as the veiling of women or
polygamy were presented as religious
teaching without any reference to-
their historical setting. While Arab
contributions to Western civilization
were mentioned, with stress on the
transmission of the Greek heritage,
little or nothing was said of major
Arab achievements, of the basic ideals
in which Moslems take a special pride,
such as freedom and brotherhood,
absence of race consciousness, the
care of the poor and of the weak.
In 1946, a pioneering enquiry was
made into the treatment of Asia in
American textbooks. This study led
to certain interesting conclusions, e.g.
that the material about Asian ques¬
tions in most of the textbooks under
consideration was so superficial and
episodic that pupils had little chance
of obtaining a coherent picture.
The conclusions reached in the
American study are borne out by
reports that have come to unesco of
studies made in some European
countries.
Unesco will follow up these studies
by urging Asian countries to look
carefully at what pictures their
textbooks present of Western Europe.
Regardless of whether Unesco itself
pursues these enquiries much further,
these reports will certainly have the
effect of stimulating contacts and
discussions among European and
Asian educators, and of course among
educators of other countries as well.
Obviously, the problem of giving a
better understanding of other peoples
all over the world cannot be solved by
adding to the present textbooks
masses of information about every
country. It calls for new thinking
about the ways history should be
taught and about the selection of
«w
\ #*"-
^
tFts^1 %
jfl h0 ,v « '
h r
( >
(
. ,
FATHER OF TODAY'S
TEXTBOOKS
This medal was struck in Czecho¬
slovakia in 1946 to honour John Amos
Comenius the first great textbook wri¬
ter of the age of printing. Comenius,
whose real name was Komensky, was
born in Eastern Moravia in 1592 and
died in Amsterdam in I 670. He pro¬
duced schemes for a complete system
of national education and a series of
textbooks to serve the system. Nothing
better than his two principal works,
Janua Linguarum and Orbis Pictus, was
produced for more than two centuries.
Comenius looked forward to the estab¬
lishment of a just and free common¬
wealth of men. That is why the in¬
scription on the reverse side of the
medal above reads : " To a forerunner
of the United Nations Organization ".
materials that will arouse interest
and give basic insight.
Reference has been made to
unesco's interest in the improve¬
ment of textbooks for international
understanding. Again, we may make
a contrast with the situation in 1919.
We now have an international organ¬
ization with a definite responsibility
for promoting education for interna¬
tional understanding, and conse¬
quently some responsibility for
promoting the improvement of text¬
books and teaching materials for this
purpose.
This does not mean that unesco has
either the authority or the desire to
rewrite any country's textbooks. The
only people who can improve text¬
books are the people in the country
which uses them. Unesco's work
starts with this as a basic assumption.
Responsible educators in many
countries believe that their pupils
should get a more balanced and more
objective view of other countries.
Obviously, they can be helped in their
thinking * about this by meeting
educators who are thinking along the
same lines elsewhere. Unesco has
organized international study confer¬
ences for teachers of history, geogra¬
phy and foreign languages.
Unpleasant facts
are not hushed up
As a result of one such meeting of
history teachers held in Brussels
in 1950, many smaller meetings
have been held in Western Europe,
most of these have been bilateral
meetings that is, educators from
two countries have met to talk over
the way they are presented in each
others' textbooks. Unesco encourages
this kind of frank and friendly
exchange.
At some meetings, historians have
discussed details which do not strike
the layman as being particularly
significant. It must be remembered,
though, that they are applying in
these minor cases a general rule
which is of great importance! that
whatever gets into the history text¬
book, whether in itself of minor or
major importance, should be based on
the best historical scholarship.
Sometimes the discussions have
turned on highly controversial issues
which are charged with intense na¬
tional feeling. The people taking
part in such discussions have on
occasion been wrongly accused in
their own country of agreeing to
cover up unpleasant facts in order to
please a foreign country. There
have been mistaken fears that these
meetings may produce some kind of
official version of history which sacri¬
fices truth in the supposed interest of
international understanding.
The facts do not justify these fears.
At 'bilateral meetings, the teachers or
historians bring to each others' atten¬
tion facts vyhich they think relevant
and reasons why different interpreta¬
tions are current in their respective
countries. Sometimes they agree in
recommending that some neglected
facts ought to be included in history
textbooks. Sometimes they recom¬
mend that children should learn that
different people do in fact interpret
events differently.
They all agree that any changes
that are to be worthwhile and sound¬
ly based, must be made at their own
free choice by the people who write
and publish textbooks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
ncTnM uiCTiiDV
AblAN nib 1 Uni
UNESCO
THE SACRED BULL OF SIVA, a huge animal figure carved in solid rock on the top of Chamundi Hill, overlooking the
city of Mysore. It dates from the I 7th century when Mysore was becoming one of the most powerful states in southern India.
THROUGH WESTERN GLASSES
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Govt, of India.
DANCE OF CREATION is executed by famed Indian dancer, Ram
Gopal, whose costume and gestures depict Siva, God of the Dance.
ASIAN HISTORY
THROUGH WESTERN GLASSES
Superficial, out of focus,
fragmentary, distorted
by Ronald Fenton
A United States ambassador, newly-returned to his
country from his post in India, was talking to his
son about the American school he would soon join.
"I'll bet," he said, "'that the world history you will study
begins in Egypt and Mesopotamia, moves on to Greece by
way of Crete, takes you through Rome and finally ends
.up. with England and France."
"'But that isn't world history," protested his son, "That
leaves out three fourths of the world." "Unhappily," says
Chester Bowles, the ambassador who tells this story, "I
won the bet."
What turned out to be true of an American school
applies equally to schools in other western countries where
textbooks are still bounded by what one educator terms
Exactly to what extent the vast conti¬
nent of Asia is given the "'cold shoulder" or is shown in
false perspective has now been revealed by an enquiry
into history textbooks made by some 25 Western countries
at Unesco's suggestion (1).
During the past year investigators in each country
(1) Ileports were submitted by National Commissions for Unesco,
not all neing officially endorsed cither by governments or by the
National Commissions themselves.
THE OTA OTA, a dance In slow rhythm based on the movements of men
engaged In a duel is performed by menfolk in a Malayan village. Women and
looked over history books with a series of specific ques¬
tions in mind. These were :
Is the space given to Asian countries (or some of them)
reasonable, given the subject and scope of the book?
What are the standards of historical accuracy? Are facts
given about the main features of Asian culture and the
great figures of Asian history? Does the book help to an
understanding of cultural values and the point of view of
the Asian peoples? Is the impression given that Asia is
important only as an incidental factor in Western (Euro¬
pean) development ?
From the reports which have now come in from
eighteen countries, the answers to these questions add up,
broadly speaking, to this: the image of Asia as present¬
ed to school children is badly out of focus in nearly all
countries and, as one report puts it, is "'superficial, epi¬
sodic, incomplete and impersonal." Aspects of cultural, re¬
ligious and intellectual life are commonly neglected and
even if a few great Asian figures are mentioned, they are
never convincingly presented.
The survey is marked by a spirit of frank self-criticism
which has turned the spotlight on the shortcomings of
textbooks in regard to Asia. A few countries appear to be
reasonably satisfied that they give quite sufficient cover¬
age to Asiatic material, while others find it adequate
considering the aim and scope of their school courses.
But the majority admit with few reserves that there are
serious gaps or distortions in their treatment of the most
important civilizations and peoples of Asia.
"Very great and often quite unjustified gaps appear in
all history textbooks." reports Italy (2). "Certain authors
limit Indian history to the period of British rule. In some
books, Chinese history begins in 1895 with the Sino-Japa-
nese Peace Treaty of Shimonoseki, as if the life of the
Chinese people had been of little interest until that time.
(2) Like Caesar with Gaul, the Italian report divides Asia into
three parts: (1) Mediterranean or semi-Mediterranean regions with the
Assyrians, Hittites, Arabs and Turks. (2) The Northern regions now
linked to Russian history. (3) India and the Far East. The Italian
enquiry deals only with the third category.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
COI. London. UNESCO
children are gathered here to watch these tra¬
ditional dances and games during village festival.
CLASSICAL DRAMA maintains its popularity in Japan. Most important of all are the Kabuki plays,
a combination of acting, singing and dancing with costumes and stage settings of fabulous colours.
Compared with the history of Japan, that of China is
rushed over hurriedly and its contemporary history is not
properly explained, nor are the reasons for the present
evolution dealt with thoroughly."
Similar criticisms come from Germany: "Some attempt
is made to treat the early history of the South, South-
East and Eastern civilizations. In general, books are si¬
lent about cultures other than those of the north of India
and China. During the modern era the most important
place is given to Japan. There is a great variation in the
treatment of China. Some books consider it as an object
of the foreign struggle for power, others stress the
Revolution of 1911 and the national evolution of the inter-
war period. Facts about India are limited almost exclu¬
sively to a few general references to India's position and
importance within the British Empire. In the books
examined, the whole of the South East Asian region is
almost entirely neglected."
The report summing up the situation in France recog¬
nizes that in primary schools history teaching Is center¬
ed on the history oí Europe and particularly Western Eur¬
ope. "The place and importance alloted to events and
civilizations outside Europe is proportional to the rela¬
tionship that they have (apparently, at least) with the
history of Western Europe. As regards Asian countries,
the further away they are geographically from Western
Europe the rarer the references become."
Sweden speaks of "'serious gaps," particularly in the
spread of Mohammedanism towards the East, Hinduism
and its historical background, and Russia's development
as a Great Asian Power. Referring to the spread of Mo¬
hammedanism Sweden admits that "Not only is no in¬
formation given on how and when this expansion occur¬
red, it is not even mentioned. The current controversies
in India therefore lack all background and are introduced
incoherently. The fact that the population of Indonesia
has been Mohammedan since the 16th century is not
mentioned at all. Nowhere is an account given of the part
Mohammedanism has played in the foundation of states
both in the past and the present, nor of present-day Islam
in North Africa, Pakistan and the Near East. It will, un
fortunately, not be saying too much if it is maintained
that most Swedish pupils leave school without having
clear ideas of the varied literature, art and world of ideas
of Persia, India, Indonesia and China."
A limited survey in England and Wales focuses on the
treatment of India and China in history textbooks used
by children in the 11 to 16 age bracket. "In general," it
says, it would seem that the amount of space and the
general significance accorded to China and India are ge¬
nerally adequate considering the aims and scope of the
syllabuses and the limited time available for historical
study. This adequacy, however, is not true of all books,
especially as regards many so-called World Histories, as,
for example in their sections dealing with Ancient Times.
Asia, apart from the Middle East, is rarely gi¬
ven due space and significance, the aim being (Cont'd on
to give a background to European culture, next page)
Eric Schwab-UNESCO.
' CELESTIAL
HELMETS'
and silken brocade
costumes are worn
by young dancers
in one of Bang¬
kok's 400 temples.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ASIA (Continued)
"Some books by
their titles purport
to deal with the
whole Modern
World, when in fact the Western world- is meant. Apart
from misleading titles, some books are perhaps providing
a rather simplified view in suggesting that our culture
and that of what is called Western civilization has its
roots only in the Middle East and the Mediterranean
world.
"Tn the books which cover Ancient history there is fre¬
quent omission of the early periods of Asiatic history
when India and China developed their own civilizations
and in the books
dealing with later
periods internal
developments in
these regions are
rarely mentioned
apart from inci¬
dental references
in connexion with
commercial, or mi¬
litary or colonial
contacts; while re¬
cent twentieth cen¬
tury developments
are rarely given
more than cursory
attention.
"There are com¬
monly references,
for example, to Da¬
rius and Alexan¬
der, to Marco Polo
and later voyagers,
and then no fur-
t h e r references,
until Western im¬
pact upon what
are presented as
decadent or disor¬
derly states of
later times is no¬
ted. It is not un¬
common in the
better books to find some reference to Buddha, Asoka,
and Confucius, and of our British and European debt to
early civilizations, including the Indian and Chinese, in
certain respects. One book notes that China 'had a settled
religion and culture many centuries before Christian
times', and refers to the patronage by Jenghiz Khan of
scientists and writers."
A report from Poland estimates that between 0,3 % and
6 % of textbook contents are devoted to the history and
cultural development of China, India and the Arabian
peninsular. "We realize", says the report, "that the space
alloted to the rich and ancient civilizations of the Asian
peoples is still too small, and we are at present studying
means of assigning more importance to this subject in
the curriculum, without overtaxing the pupils."
It is admitted by most of the countries surveyed that
Asian history is seen almost exclusively from the European
point of view. The Italian report goes even, further, stat-
IPyiif 11 r HI ' -jiy i^tmmmtmWm^mm
^L^F^Sifl,W W MM Hl m^^m^mW^^
tf íriuKMrJr
p'T<mJI
Govt, of India.
HAVA MAHAL, The Palace of the Winds
at Udaipur, northern India, is one of many
still surviving Rajput palaces and forts.
Werner Bibchof, Magnum.
KYOTO TEMPLE. There are well over
3,000 temples and shrines in what was
formerly the ancient capital of Japan.
ing "textbooks ge¬
nerally present
Asia as one of the
areas where the
enterprise and vi¬
gour of European
nations have been
most widely exer¬
cized. Only in text¬
books on contem¬
porary history do
we find any treat¬
ment of Asian
countries which is
not linked to Euro¬
pean expansion,
but even here the
approach is deci¬
dedly European."
This lack of pers¬
pective is also
mentioned in the
British report
which says that
India and China normally come into the picture only as
incidental factors in European or national development
and in relation to the extension of Western influence.
But in addition to glaring omissions and haphazard
treatment there is a dangerous tendency to see certain
people of Asia in terms of sweeping generalizations and
time-worn clichés.
Britain, however, reports that while "little positive con¬
tribution is in fact being made towards the understanding
of Asiatic peoples by the contents of most history text¬
books in common use, on the other hand, except for a few
prejudiced phrases or distorted references in a number of
books mostly published a considerable time ago, little is
done to harm reasonable relationships, " adding that this
is so only because so little relevance to the problem is
in fact being
covered at all.
Dealing with the
same question, the
Italian survey finds
that while text¬
book writers can¬
not be accused of
bias or social pre¬
judice the picture
given -of Asian
countries is based
on common clichés
which, even if they
can often be justi¬
fied, could well
stand revision or
at least more
subtle explanation.
These are some of
the examples
found in Italian
Morin-UNEsco. textbooks:
BABYLONIAN RUINS with animal
motif bas-reliefs on crumbling brick walls.
Hedda Hammer, Pekin.
«TEMPLE OF HEAVEN'. Classical Chinese architecture aims to
harmonize buildings with the landscape rather than to dominate it.
10
India : on the con-
trast between
pomp and pov¬
erty.
"Probably no country is poorer or richer than India."
"The population is mainly rural, poverty-stricken and
wretched, and is exploited by the nabobs."
China : on inertia and immobility.
"The Chinese Empire, immobile in its outmoded
.political and social structure, steadfastly refused to
modernize and open its doors to European trade."
"China, after reaching a high level of civilization in
the past, remained sunk in the torpor of its secular
inertia."
Japan :
The cliché on Japan (the most admired of Asiatic
countries in Italian history books) is that of "'the
pupil who surpasses the teacher", the teacher ob¬
viously being Europe. "In little more than 20 years
the Nippon Empire succeeded in creating
a completely modern society, fully equipped (Cont'd on
in the economic and social spheres. page 12)
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Jnesco Courier. March
THE CLOSED BOOK
As a result of a suggestion from Unesco that Western countries
set up committees to survey their history textbooks and see what
information their pupils are getting about Asia, the Belgian Federa¬
tion of History Teachers carried out three special studies. Below,
we publish their main conclusions which show crisply and frankly a
situation that is unfortunately typical of most Western countries
today. The findings do not necessarily express the views of the Bel¬
gian Government or the Belgian National Commission for Unesco.
Antiquity, as we get to know
it from our school text¬
books, is essentially Medi¬
terranean, and mainly Greek and
Roman. The existence of the
early Chinese civilizations, or of
the 1,500 years of Hindu evolu¬
tion before the birth of Christ
in short, the part played by Asia
in ancient times is completely
neglected. Alexander's expedi¬
tion is usually the sole excursion
that, metaphorically speaking,
we permit ourselves into the East.
Our view of the Middle Ages is
also systematically centred on
Europe. A few brief allusions to
Marco Polo and to adventurous
voyages in Asiatic seas are all
that we can rely upon to present
to youthful minds the existence of
a vast reservoir of human beings
and unknown civilizations on the
other side of the world. Our
Modern History is our modern
history ; Asia plays but a small
role in it. Generally speaking, it
is quite forgotten. If mention is
sometimes made of South East
Asia, it is to speak of the Portu¬
guese and Dutch Establishments;
if India is referred to, it is to
honour the memory of men such
as Suffren or Dupleix.
Only with contemporary history
does Asia really take shape be¬
fore us ; all our textbooks in
current use deal more or less
fully with that Continent. But
we should say at once that they
do not usually do so in a syste¬
matic or thorough manner, such
as would suffice to teach young
people about the ways of life, the
economies, the social structures
and the spiritual, intellectual or
moral outlook of the Asian peo¬
ples. After reading the princi¬
pal textbooks is use, we can make
the following observations:
The history of the Asiatic peo¬
ples is nearly always approached
from the standpoint of European
policy and interests. The facts
related under the heading "'Euro¬
pean Expansion in Asia" are
solely those which serve to
explain the military or economic
exploits of European countries.
The history of Asia is not only
superficial, but incomplete. Al¬
though Japan a first-class pow¬
er at the end of the 19th century
is fairly well known, China is
less known and India more ne¬
glected still, while Malaya, Korea,
Mongolia, Burma and the Nether¬
lands East Indies are omitted
from the picture altogether.
The human side of history is
left out of account. The school
manuals tell us, perhaps, about
the East India Company and the
Indian Mutiny; but the Japanese,
the Asiatic of whatever race,
continues to remain a closed
book. The ways of life, the so¬
cial structures, the aspirations of
these peoples remain veiled from
us; we learn nothing of their
standard of living, their level of
education, the meaning of their
religions, or their internal ad¬
ministration. The colonial and
imperialist tradition of nineteen¬
th-century Europe is palpable in
these pages; it is, therefore, not
as citizens of the world that we
discover the Continent of Asia.
A certain number of the text¬
books in use do not pursue their
subject beyond the year 1914. A
special study is sometimes devot¬
ed to Japan, but the rest of Asia
is left in obscurity.
The following general picture
may therefore be drawn:
1. The whole aspect of Human
History, so far as Ancient Times
and the Middle Ages are concern¬
ed, is liable to be falsified by
almost complete ignorance of the
principal centres of the civiliza¬
tion of Asia.
2. Contemporary Asiatic his¬
tory is so presented as to encour¬
age an approach to current
Eastern problems with the men¬
tality, almost, of a person living
at the end of the 19th century.
3. We know too little of the
inner life of these peoples, and of
their economic circumstances.
4. Only the great political issues
of concern to Europe are studied;
nothing without a European
context exists.
5. It might be desirable that
every Asian country should be
given a place in our Contempor¬
ary History, and that we should
be briefly documented on the so¬
cial, moral, intellectual, spiritual,
economic and artistic evolution of
the great Asiatic centres, past
and present.
6. In view of the current
reawakening of Asia, it is more
than ever important that our
school textbooks should deal with
the history of that Continent and
its development since 1918. It
would be desirable for them to
include a treatment of topical
problems a delicate matter,
which the popular press is so
ready to serve up to young minds
that are uninstructed or inexper¬
ienced in these questions.
In conclusion:
From the majority of textbooks
in use, it is apparent that, despite
their authors' evident attempts at
objectivity, little space is devot¬
ed to Asian countries in these
books; Asian history is seen al¬
most exclusively from the Euro¬
pean standpoint ; these peoples
remain little known, since their
dealings with other countries
teach us nothing about them;
our view of Asia remains frag¬
mentary and biased, and though
"modern" Europe may be fami¬
liar to us, Asia is certainly not.
1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ASIA (Continued) Europeanization' equals
Thus it managed to rival the most advanced nations
of the West."
"With amazing speed, the Japanese people accepted
European civilization, or rather, superimposed on its
ancient ways the products of Western mechanized
civilization."
As has already been noted, most Western history text¬
books tend to judge Asian people according to a completely
Occidental code. The following paragraph from the re¬
port based on Italian textbooks could apply to almost all
Western nations : The ability to adapt to European ideas
and techniques is considered a mark of merit. Proof of
the intelligence and educability of a people is sometimes
seen in the skill with which it "Europeanizes" itself. . A
country which has adopted a political structure on Euro-
Dean lines is considered to be really "civilized". Some¬
times the impression is given that European expansion
can never be regarded as anything else but a good thing.
Patronizing, pitying, attitudes
Prior to Unesco's international investigation, the first
and probably the most meticulous attempt to disco¬
ver what schoolchildren have been taught about Asia
and the Far East was made in the United States just ten
years ago. This study led to a number of general conclu¬
sions which are worth recalling today:
The wide variations in Asiatic cultures are often
submerged in uniform generalities. The great
personages of Asian history are virtually ignored.
The treatment of Asia in most textbooks is so epi
sodic and references are so light and scattered
that pupils are not likely to assemble them in
any coherent pattern.
Backwardness in industrial development is too
often left to mean backwardness in every aspect
of development.
Stereotyped phrases are commonly used, e.g.
"backward peoples of the Orient" ; "'natives" ;
"uncivilized" ; "white man's burden".
In U.S. history there is rarely a single, relatively
full account of American relations
with Asia ; the material is scatter¬
ed and unintegrated.
Asia's place in contemporary
affairs receives insufficient atten¬
tion.
In general, the 1946 study of Asia
in American textbooks found that
few statements directly engender¬
ed objectionable attitudes in the
minds of young readers. But stu¬
dents saw the culture, civilization and
standards of living of the peoples of
the East only through the Western
eyeglasses of a highly industrialized
civilization. This often created in
boys and girls a feeling of superiority
and a patronizing, pitying attitude.
A new report, submitted to Unesco
by the U.S. Office of Education in
January of this year, paints some¬
thing of a brighter picture and finds
the general situation "encourag¬
ing". Appraising what has happen¬
ed in the past decade, it notes in¬
creasing attention to Asian coun¬
tries in study courses, and a general
awareness of the need for more
teaching about Asia in teachers'
discussion groups and publications.
Talks with textbook authors and a
look at the textbooks themselves
show that progress has been made
in certain directions. Statements
that are derogatory to Asians, stereo¬
types which were commonly used,
expressions such as "'barbarian",
"uncivilized", "backward people"
have largely disappeared from textbooks. Editors and
publishers are trying to stress the similarities between
Asian and Western peoples rather than the differences.
Much perplexity seems to exist however as to where the
study of Asia should start, whether recent history should
be stressed, or the Golden Age, or the earlier origins of
Asian peoples and cultures. On the other hand, many
history teachers still feel very strongly that European
history should receive the greatest emphasis since it
serves as a background for understanding American civi¬
lization. If Islamic history is given new treatment it is
often because it is seen as the chapter in Asian history
which most touches the history of Europe.
The U.S. report concludes on a half-pessimistic, half-
optimistic note. "Changes come slowly and pressures for
the status quo are strong", it admits, "'yet some action
and change can be detected."
The difficulties all Western nations are encountering
in their sincere attempts to improve the treatment aï
Asia in their textbooks are as varied as their teaching
syllabuses are different. The geographical situation of a
country, its historical position and relationships, its views
as to the nature, scope and purpose of education generally
and of history teaching in particular, are all important
factors that cannot be lightly brushed aside. Yet despite
these great differences, each nation, in its own way, can
do much to promote a better understanding of Asia in the
classroom. The surveys in fact make a number of
suggestions which textbook authors might consider when
revising their books or preparing new ones.
The French report goes much further and raises a
fundamental question. Referring to history teaching in
primary schools where, it says, "the place given to Asia
is extremely reduced in every respect", it explains that
this situation reflects the present syllabus requirements
and asks whether a complete reorganization of history
teaching at this level should not be undertaken. like
the Belgian, Swedish and German reports it calls for the
inclusion of more civilizations and regions of Asia in the
teaching syllabus regardless of whether they have had
special contacts with the West. At present each Western
nation seems to concentrate on a specific region, e. g.
UNESCO.
ANCIENT ISFAHAN was once a capital city in the ancient kingdom of Persia. Two thousand
years ago before Its decline the Persian Empire stretched from the Indus River In the east to the
Aegean Sea In the West. Arts and sciences flourished again In later times under the Arabian caliphs.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
Great Britain on India, France on Islam and the Arab
world, Greece on Byzantium and the Near East, Hungary
on China, etc.
Some countries, like Belgium, Germany and the U.S.A.,
suggest that more place be given to recent developments
and to 20th century aspirations and movements in Asia
as part of the background of our complex and inter¬
connected world which future citizens need to understand.
O
Great Asians are neglected
THER specific suggestions for changed textbook treat¬
ment include:
More great figures in Asian history and culture
should be included, perhaps at the expense of colonial
heroes such as Clive in India. (Italian, British, Ameri¬
can reports). The Italian report notes: "History books
hardly pause to mention the great men of Asia. Those
most usually named are conquerors while poets, writers
and thinkers are neglected."
The great Asian civilizations should be presented as
integral wholes along with the life and cultural traditions
of peoples both before and after colonial conquest.
Asians should not be presented as living in static commu¬
nities, unable to develop without the inspiration of West¬
ern contact. Accounts should be given of the real levels
of independent civilization achieved without Western
influence as well as the specific contributions of Asia to
human progress.
Asian history should not be judged exclusively
through Western eyes but should be viewed in the same
spirit as that in which historians are prepared to view
Western developments, i.e. sympathetically but critically,
with proper regard for sources and in proper perspective.
(Italy, Germany, Britain).
When past conflicts and controversial questions are
treated they should be presented fairly and with balance.
Some countries suggest that more than one view should
be given of a controversial issue (U.S.A., Britain), others
that a "correct interpretation" be given (Poland).
Parallels with Western development should not be
overlooked (Italy, Poland), although points of variation
are more revealing. Some suggested topics : migrations
of peoples and imperial conquests within Asia ; feudalism
in its various forms in Asia ; nationalist movements ;
early industrialism in Asian countries; population prob-
i \c .
Morin-UNFSCO.
RIVERS ARE ROADS In Burma, where they form the main lines of communication between the
mountain barriers. Traditionally a land of Buddhist teaching and art, Burma is dotted with pagodas,
each village pagoda being also a local school where the children are taught by Buddhist priests.
PEOPLE OF CEYLON, even the most hu.nble, are still proud of the
ancient civilization which once flourished on their island. In the north,
the ruins of great palaces and temples tell the story of past glories.
lems; social struggles; struggles against nature and
disease.
It was widely pointed out that to obtain worthwhile
results greater use should be made of supplementary
materials more and better wallmaps and charts, back¬
ground books, anthologies and booklists in conjunction
with improved textbooks. Many countries feel that not
enough use is being made of materials such as trans¬
lations of classical and contemporary Asian literature,
pictures of art, sculpture and architecture, illustrations of
living conditions and cultural activities, nor are enough
schools benefitting from the facilities, offered by libraries,
museums and art galleries as well as
by the mass media teaching aids like
films, film-strips, radio and television.
It is obvious that textbooks and
school courses cannot be modified
with a flick of the wrist. The pro¬
blem cannot be solved by simply
adding masses of facts for which
there would be no room either in
school curricula or textbooks. In
many countries improvements, realis¬
tically speaking, can be hoped for
only in terms of a broader awareness,
a wider outlook and a balanced atti¬
tude toward Asia on the part of the
teacher, made possible through his
continued studies and his use of bet¬
ter and more plentiful supplementary
material.
In May of this year, teachers and
historians from Western countries will
be meeting at Unesco's headquar¬
ters in Paris to study these and other
suggestions in the light of all the sur¬
veys made and their own experience.
They will have to consider what basic
facts and ideas are really important
for an understanding of the Asian
people and how these can best be
presented in the classroom.
Their work will form a basis for
future exchanges between Western
and Eastern educators, and will be a
stepping stone to a second Unesco
study in which, this time, Asian
countries will be asked to take a look
at the picture their textbooks present
of Western countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
0*\
r -.ñ
/ t .
" "if ii 	JIB"~zz-¿"3'j
'Daddy, what's the
good of history?'
Copyright Lisel Haas
Birmingham
ç Ç-r*\ ADDY< what's the good of history?" With this ques-
II tion, put by a small boy to a father who was a
"^^^ historian, the French historian, Marc Bloch, began
his remarkable essay, Apologie pour l'histoire, ou Métier
d'historien. As Bloch observed, the small boy in his
apparently naive enquiry had with the embarrassing
directness of youth raised a fundamental question. -What
is the use of historical study in a practical world ? It is
a question that strikes with double force the thousands
of men and women whose daily task it is to teach history
to children of all ages in the schools of the world.
Bloch and other eminent historians of many lands have
argued cogently that history is a study worthy of the
adult mind, opening a door to wisdom and tolerance and
a power of profound criticism.
History can satisfy in a unique way the growing child's
curiosity about other people, about their lives, per¬
sonalities, deeds and ideas ; and it can awaken an
imaginative wonder and excitement about the whole
world of humanity past and present. History can develop
an understanding of the cultural heritage of mankind,
or provide a measure of background knowledge for the
appreciation of literature, art and ways of life of other
people. In the realm of intellectual discipline, the study
of history can train pupils to be accurate in comprehen¬
sion and expression, to weigh evidence, to separate the
trivial from the significant, to distinguish between pro¬
paganda and truth.
Rich harvest from classroom seeds
History can provide twentieth-century men with
standards of reference against which to measure
values and achievements of their own age ; it can
encourage an enlightened awareness of the problems of
modern communities, political, social and economic. Not
least important, it can train men to handle controversial
questions in a spirit which searches for truth, insists on
free discussion, and permits compromise. This is a rich
harvest for any school subject to yield. No teacher of
history would maintain that he can do more than sow
some of its seeds and nourish them so long as his pupils
are still at school. But he will assert confidently that the
seeds are worth the sowing.
There can be little doubt that the majority of history
teachers the world over, called on to justify their work,
would find common ground in a single conceptthat of
training for national citizenship. The child is one day
14
by C. Peter Hill (*>
to vote, perhaps to serve in the army, to pay taxes, to
take a part great or small in the working life of his
native land, to carry out the duties of a citizen. One of
the special functions of history teaching in schools
therefore has been to help to develop in children a love
of their own -country, and an understanding of its tra¬
ditions and ways of life ; how the homeland has become
united or has freed itself from foreign rulers, how its
system of government has come into being, what are its
distinctive customs and traditions, what changes have
taken place in its economic and social life, and so on.
A survey of history curricula in the schools of the
majority of member states of Unesco reveals that the
teaching of national history predominates at every stage
of the school course, and is as evident in countries with
a decentralized school system as in those where national
control of education is far-reaching.
This is understandable and reasonable. But the citizen
these days must concern himself with problems that
transcend national frontiers. For men now live on a
globe which is shrinking and a world which is fast
becoming a closely interrelated unit. Nation is dependent
on nation as never before. This dependence, clear in the
friendly intercourse of peacetime, has been driven into
men's minds and hearts by the terrible argument of war.
Men must learn to live together, and the two world wars
of this century have brought in their train the first
elaborate attempts to establish permanent international
organizations in the political field, the League of Nations
and the United Nations. The League did not endure ;
U.N. remains, embodying the political concept of the
twentieth century, that of constructive co-operation
between the nations of the world.
In the teaching of the past, historical truth has often
been sacrificed in the interests of national pride, and
history has often been distorted in order to arouse
patriotic emotions. Children have often been left with
the idea that contacts between nations in different parts
of the world are invariably connected, directly or
indirectly, with war. The chauvinist has made history
serve the purposes of nationalism ; the history textbook,
with its unavoidable generalizations and its necessary
has frequently been turned into a power¬
ful instrument of this nationalism. (1).
Certainly, in the last 50 years, the teaching of history
in many countries has greatly improved, in this as in
many other respects ; some textbooks have become more
objective in their presentation of facts, syllabuses have
become more international in their outlook and scope.
But the need for further improvement remains great, ana .
it becomes daily more urgent. Children of today must
grow up to know that there are other types of human
communities than their own and they must learn that
(*) This article is taken from "Suggestions on the Teaching of
History", published by Unesco.
(1) See the Unesco nolume, "History Textbooks and International
I'nilerstanding", hy J. A. I.nmoerys : 75 rents; 4/-; 200 frs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
the past has made other countries what they are, just as
it has made their own what it is.
History properly taught can help men to become critic¬
al and humane, just as wrongly taught it can turn them
into bigots and fanatics. For the child can begin to
develop, even from an elementary historical training,
qualities and attitudes of mind which all aid interna¬
tional understanding. He can acquire an abiding interest
in the lives and achievements of peoples outside his
own homeland and realize what they have contributed
to the common cultural inheritance of man ; he can .
learn to be accurate and critical and grasp the idea of
change as a factor in human affairs.
The cause of international understanding benefits yet
further when children reach adulthood knowing
something of the causes and results of past human
conflicts, and something of the history of man's efforts
towards international co-operation, and when the
history they have learned teaches them both about the
growing interdependence of nations and about the
strenuous efforts of millions of individual men to
establish human freedoms.
Few would deny that international understanding is
a desirable result of history teaching, and that the
teacher who strives to promote it is pursuing a laudable
end. But many will ask whether history which has
formerly been focused on national concerns is now to be
distorted to serve international ends. The answer is
emphatically "no". There may be teachers who believe
that by omitting or by glossing over the wars and in¬
ternational rivalries of the past they will thereby
promote the spread of international understanding in
the present ; but surely they are very few. This would
be a fallacious practice, educating the child to unreality;
peace is not gained by pretending wars have not existed.
Champollion and the Rosetta Stone
What principles might guide the teacher to select
materials which would contribute to international
understanding? Some suggestions on this score
have been advanced by a committee of eight experts, pro¬
fessional historians and teachers of history, at the request
of unesco. These suggested principles are as follows:
The search for truth: "History is a record of a people's
past based on a critical examination of documents and
other facts. The essentials of this historical method
are not beyond the grasp of even young children. Con¬
crete examples, such as the story of the Rosetta stone,
which enabled Champollion to establish the first prin¬
ciples of the deciphering of Egyptian hieroglyphics, vivid¬
ly illustrate the fundamental processes involved. This
search for the facts can be used to illustrate one side of
search for historic truth.
"The other side is the truth of historic interpretation.
The facts cannot be changed, but the interpretation of
them can and does change. An explanation of ar¬
chaeological techniques (excavation and research are
going on in most countries) will demonstrate how the
past can be investigated, what facts archaeological re¬
mains can reveal and what interpretations can be placed
upon them. If children can be brought to appreciate
the distinction between the objectivity of facts and the
inevitable subjectivity of interpretation, an invaluable
lesson will have been learnt. They will be less likely in
adult life to fall victims to propaganda."
History as an evolutionary process: "Pupils should be
helped to realize that history is an account of an evolu¬
tionary process, that man has conquered the world by
slow degrees and re-fashioned it to fit his needs; that
technological advances, to which peoples all over the
world have contributed, have accelerated the evolution of
human societies; that civilizations have developed, ma¬
tured, and died, to be replaced by new civilizations which
have always preserved some part of the heritage left by
those who had gone before. History should not be pre¬
sented as if it were static. On the contrary, it is a dyna¬
mic story of continual change. Pupils should be helped
to appreciate the unity of history, and not to view it as a
broken pattern of stories which they are all too likely
to equate with tales of adventure."
Mutual influence among Nations and Peoples: "In this
connexion children can be shown that races and nations
have never really lived in complete isolation from each
other. In technology, politics, culture and philosophy,
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
there have been constant exchanges, borrowings ana
mutual influences. Teachers should make a point of
seeking out examples of interchanges of this kind from
their national history. In order to develop a sense of
the interdependence of nations and to avoid encouraging
unwarranted feelings of superiority, what their own
country has received should be recognized as frankly as
what has been contributed to others."
Importance of economic and social factors: "The eco¬
nomic history of the past is still far from complete, but
the patient work of historians is gradually bearing fruit.
Today many school textbooks give considerable attention
to economic and social factors, and in most countries
sufficient information is now available to enable teachers
to show their pupils how important these factors have
been at all periods of human history. The struggle for
food and shelter, the bartering of goods, and the growth
of means of communication can be easily appreciated
even by quite young children. In this way a good basis
can be given for a later understanding of the complex
economic problems of our time."
Importance of intellectual and moral factors: "Intel¬
lectual and moral currents of thought have probably had
as great an influence on history as have economic and
social factors. Regardless of frontiers, they have in¬
fluenced millions of men and women throughout the
world and inspired them to action. These factors should
be brought home to children."
The struggle for tolerance and peace: "Throughout
history there has been a time-lag between moral and
material progress. Pupils should be helped to understand
why this has been so and to see that not only the desire
for power of rulers, politicians and national cliques, but
also ignorance, intolerance mutual distrust and the pre¬
judice and selfishness of groups and individuals have been
responsible. Moreover, intolerance has contributed both
to civil and to national wars. In many countries, exam¬
ples can be taken from national history to show that
intolerance and prejudices have been successfully over¬
come so that former enemies can live together in peace.
"At a suitable age, children must learn that war has
brought in its train not only death for millions of soldiers
and civilians, men and women, children and old people,
but also incalculable suffering and destruction of which
the defeated have never been the only victims. War has
frequently caused serious damage, or has brought utter
ruin in a brief space of time a few years, months, days,
even a few seconds to the results of centuries of human
effort, the achievements of generations of architects,
sculptors, painters, engineers and technicians, craftsmen,
peasants and labourers of all kinds."
If history is taught in the light of principles such as
these, children should be better able to see for them¬
selves how important it is to try to understand their
fellow-citizens and the citizens of other nations and to
help in the struggle of mankind against prejudice, intol¬
erance and selfishness.
Nefertiti, the
Queen of Egypt
some 3.000 years
ago. She was
mother-in-law to
the famous King .
Tutenkhamen.
Copyright J. E. Bulloz
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
IN THE CENTRE
OF THE MAP
Nations see themselves
as the hub of history
by Marshall G.S. Hodgson
In the sixteenth century the Italian missionary, Matteo
Ricci, brought to China a European map of the world
showing the new discoveries in America. The Chinese
were glad to learn about America, but one point in the
map offended them. Since it split the earth's surface
down the Pacific, China appeared off at the right-hand
edge; whereas the Chinese thought of themselves as
literally the "Middle Kingdom", which should be in the
centre of the map. Ricci pacified them by drawing
another map, splitting the Atlantic instead, so that China
appeared more central; and maps are still commonly
drawn that way in that part of the world.
Europeans of course have clung to the first type of map,
showing Europe in the upper centre; while the commonest
maps in North America show the U.S.A. in that post of
honour, even at the cost of splitting a continent in two.
The temptation not only to put one's own land in the
centre of the map, but one's own people in the centre
of history, seems to be universal.
The most famous case of this is indeed that of the
"Middle Kingdom". Many Chinese used to suppose that
the Temple of Heaven at the Emperor's capital, Peking,
marked the exact centre of the earth's surface. To be
sure, Chinese scholars even in the Middle Ages were
aware that China could not be said to be mathematically
central; they knew the general lay of Europe and Africa
and the Indian Ocean, and a writer could remark that
the "centre" of the earth was along the equator. Never¬
theless, even for sober historians the pivotal fact of
human history was the condition of the great Chinese
empire, in which was concentrated all the splendour of
polished civilization.
At times that empire was strong. Then (as they told it)
the Emperor was able to command peace among the fair
lands stretching out around his capital ; the choicest
products of the mountains on the one hand and the sea
on the other poured in to enrich the vast fertile plains of
the empire; and the barbarians of the less favoured lands
beyond deserts, mountains, and remote islands divided
and weakened by the Emperor's wise policies, came to
bring humble tribute and to learn what they could of the
arts of civilization.
Thus came the Koreans, the Japanese, the Tibetans ;
thus came also the English from their distant islands,
seeking Chinese luxuries and offering little in return the
Emperor could approve such as opium. Even the English
envoys were graciously received, but when they showed
want of proper respect for the Emperor they were
dismissed with contempt.
At other times the imperial power grew feeble, local
rulers seized power and tyrannized the people, prosperity
faded. It was then (as they told it) that the barbarians
came as insulting conquerors, and civilization was eclipsed
in the world. Thus came the Central Asian Turks, thus
came the Mongols under Kublai Khan; and thus came
the English when the Manchu dynasty was declining,
invading the Middle Kingdom (whose wealth attracted
every barbarous nation), and forcing their crude ways
upon the people.
It could in fact be claimed that for a time China was
16
the wealthiest and most populous, the most aesthetically
cultivated and even the most powerful state on the earth;
but when this fact was made the basis for the Chinese
picture of the world, the result was tragic miscalculation.
For the medieval Hindu the -world was a place for the
purification of souls. Kings and their empires came and
went, the gods themselves arose and perished time was
infinite, space immense, with unlimited opportunity for
every soul to reap in birth after rebirth what it had sown.
In much of the universe, indeed, souls dwelt in untroubled
bliss; it was the distinction of our own toiling, earthy
regions that here men could choose responsibly between
good and evil and. their consequences. Here life was
arranged for the exercise of virtue, each caste of men
having its own function in society; if a man fulfilled one
role well, in another life he would have a higher role to
play, and might eventually rise beyond the transient
vicissitudes of existence altogether.
Accordingly, so far as history was significant, it was as
ages varied in the degree to which society was well
enough ordered to give virtue its due place. As a given
cosmic cycle wore on, disorder increased and justice faded.
Our own age (they explained) was in the latter part of
such a cycle ; only in the central parts of the earthy re¬
gions in India, that is-was society still well ordered :
there Brahmins still offered sacrifices and the other
castes ruled or served according to their status.
In the benighted lands to the east and west so tainted
already with decline that pious Brahmins dared not set
foot there souls were doomed to be born as barbarous
Mlecchas; there they lived unhallowed lives till they
should earn the right to be born in India. As our degen¬
erate age drew on, even in India itself the social order
was upset, rulers rose from the basest castes, and finally
even Mlecchas entered as conquerors Muslims from the
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
west, and even the remotest Europeans. Through all this
outward humiliation, however, the Hindu could know that
there in the central lands where the sacred Ganges
flowed he could still live the way of truth and holiness
inaccessible to lesser breeds of men and aspire to the
highest degrees of rebirth.
To the medieval Muslim the world looked very different
from what it did to his Chinese or to his Hindu
contemporaries. History was not a matter of the
varying strength and weakness of an imperial centre of
authority and civilization, nor was it a passing incident In
an infinite succession of worlds. Rather it was the story
of a single species created just some 5,000 years ago by
God to do His will once for all. From Adam on, God had
sent thousands of prophets to the various peoples, bring¬
ing to each its laws and sciences; at last he sent Mo¬
hammed, proclaiming the final law in which all earlier
truth was perfected and which was gradually to prevail
over the whole world, replacing all former laws.
Many Muslims believed that Mohammed's birthplace,
Mecca, was the centre of the earth's surface. To Mecca,
men pilgrimaged yearly from the farthest parts of the
earth, and it was supposed that in the heavens above it
the angels themselves performed worship ; here was the
very throne of God, where heaven and earth were nearest.
To be sure, scholars knew that the earth was a sphere,
and God equally present everywhere in the hearts of the
believers. But their more sober picture of the world was
equally effective in supporting the eminence of Islam.
They thought of the inhabited quarter of the globe as a
land mass lying between the equator and the North Pole,
and between the oceans to the west and to the east
roughly Eurasia and northen Africa.
This was divided into seven "climes" from (Cont'd on
south to north, and from extreme heat to cold, next page)
FROM THE FIRST
KNOWN WORLD
ATLAS
The most important attempt of the ancient
world to place the study of geography on a
scientific basis was made by Claudius Ptolemy,
celebrated mathematician, astronomer and
geographer of Alexandria. His Geographia,
written in Greek around 140 A.D. comprised
eight books which included a general map
of the known world and twenty-seven maps
covering different countries. Ptolemy's ori¬
ginal work written on papyrus, has not sur¬
vived but copies were made, the oldest dating
from the I 3th century. In I 886 a manuscript
was discovered in the monastery at Mount
Athos, Greece, which included a reproduction
of Ptolemy's original world-map. The section
of this manuscript containing the map (left)
is now in the British Museum. The Geographia
was printed for the first time in a Latin transla¬
tion together with maps in Italy in the latter
part of the I 5th century. Its contents, how¬
ever, had already become known in Western
Europe through manuscript copies, and their
study influenced map-making in two ways.
They led firstly to the addition of degree lines
to maps and secondly to the compilation of
new maps of countries which had been inade¬
quately represented by Ptolemy. The map
above is a reproduction of an engraving on
copper made in Rome in 1478 by a German,
Arnold Bucking and published by another
German, Conrad Schweinheim, the same year.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
IN THE CENTRE OF THE MAP
(Continued)
Muslims writing in the latitude of Syria or Iran explained
that in the hot south men grew lazy and so remained
backward in civilization; and likewise in the far north
where it was too cold in northern Europe, for instance
men's skins were pallid and' their minds sluggish. Hence
it was that only in the central, moderate climes, like the
Mediterranean lands or Iran, were minds most active and
civilization most advanced ; from there the blessings of
Islam were gradually being brought even to the remotest
areas, among the Negroes in the hot south and the white
men in the cold north.
World histories written by medieval Muslims, might
therefore, have a preliminary section on the older Per¬
sians, Hebrews, and Romans; but, from the time of Mo¬
hammed, the modern part of the history dealt almost
exclusively with the Islamic peoples. Other peoples might
be curious in their quaint ways ; the Chinese might be
clever at gadgets, and the Greeks at philosophy ; but
now the only peoples whose story really counted were
those who had abandoned their old local creeds with
their many idols or their many saints' images and joined
in the imageless worship of the One God, in the interna¬
tional brotherhood of Islam which,- advancing farther
every year, already stretched
from the straits of Gibraltar
to those of Malacca. ' 	.	_^___
The West-Europeans of
the same age had many of
the same ideas of history
and geography as the
Muslims, getting them from
the sanie Greek and Hebrew
sources ; but their interpret¬
ation was very different.
For them history was the
story of God's progressive
dispensations of law or of
grace to his favoured people.
Out of the descendants of
Adam, God has first chosen
the Hebrews, but with the
coming of Christ it was a
"new Israel", the Christians,
that received His favours.
Even among the Christ¬
ians God had made a
further selection casting
aside those of the Levant
and Greece as heretics or
schismatics, in favour of the
West-Europeans under the
Pope at Rome. The favoured
people of each age lived unde'r a succession of great
monarchies : ^in earlier times Chaldean, Persian, and
Greek, which all conquered the Hebrews ; but last and
greatest, under which Christ Himself was born, the
empire of Rome in the west, which should endure till
Judgment Day.
The West-Europeans allowed, that the centre of the
world's surface was Jerusalem (by exaggerating the length
of the Mediterranean, their maps could show Spain and
China as equally distant from it); but they assured
themselves that, just as at the beginning of history
Paradise was in the east where the sun rises, so in these
latter days the centre of God's vicarship on earth was in
the west, where the sun sets ; henceforth Rome was the
centre of all authority, spiritual and temporal.
In modern times all these medieval pictures of the
world have vanished, or been modified. With the discov¬
ery of America and the circumnavigation of the globe,
the discovery that Earth is a tiny planet in an immensity
of space, that mankind has been upon it hundreds of
HOW ANCIENT HINDUS
SAW THE UNIVERSE
According to an ancient Hindu conception of the
universe, the world was supported on the backs
of several elephants, standing on a giant turtle.
The cosmos is depicted here by a snake, the Naga.
thousands of years and is still a newcomer, we have had
to rethink our situation. The great ideals of faith and of
culture have to be seen in spiritual terms rather than as
reflected in the very map of the universe.
The West-Europeans were the first to be really faced
with the new discoveries and have consequently led the
way toward creating a new picture of the world. But
they have not yet escaped the temptation to make geo¬
graphy and history centre upon themselves. One need
only examine the table of contents of any proper Western
"world history". Civilization began in Mesopotamia and
Egypt »(with perhaps some local variants in India and
China); but (it would seem) soon history was almost a
monopoly of the Greeks ; and though other peoples might
still be curious, in their quaint ways, hereafter it was
really only Europe that counted and after the rise of
Rome only Western Europe; here was the home of truth
and liberty.
If during long centuries it was hard to find either truth
or liberty in Western Europe, this period was regretfully
labelled the Dark Ages of mankind; but in modern times
the West-Europeans have duly gone forth to enlighten
(and subdue) the world so that the history of a hence¬
forth "Westernized" world may be safely reduced almost
to that of the West itself.
The map of the world is constructed accordingly.
Westerners distinguish five or six "continents": Africa,
Asia, North and South America and Europe. It is some¬
times ingenuously remarked
how much smaller Europe is
than the "other continents"
yet in political discussions,
in grouping statistics, or in
historical comparisons these
divisions repeatedly recur as
if fixed by nature
In European "w o r 1 d
atlases" each European
country has its own map,
with the rest of the world
in a few pages at the end.
The map ordinarily selected
to show the world as a whole
is ideally suited to reinforce
this way of seeing mankind.
On the Mercator world map
not only is Europe in the
upper centre : it is repre¬
sented as a good deal larger
than the other great culture
areas. Most of these lie
south of the fortieth
parallel, while Europe is
almost wholly north of it,
where Mercator's projection
begins to exaggerate the size
of things enormously.
Accordingly even on the world map, which ought to
provide a sense of proportion, there is space to name a
great many places in Europe, while in other populous
centre's like India or China, shown on a much smaller
scale, only a few chief places need be indicated. Although
equal-area projections of the world have long been avail¬
able, in which shapes as well as sizes are much less
distorted, Westerners understandably cling to a projection
which so markedly flatters them. They explain (as if
they were engaged in nothing but sailing) that the true
angles given on the Mercator map are of convenience to
navigators ; and in atlases and wall-maps, in books of
reference and in newspapers, when Westerners turn to see
what the world looks like as a whole their preconceptions
are authoritatively gratified.
The story is often told of a small tribe whose word for
"mankind" was the name for the tribe itself. Other tribes
were merely incidental in their picture of the world
perhaps not even fully human. Chinese, Hindus, Mus¬
lims, and Westerners alike have smiled perhaps too
quickly at the rather perilous naïveté of that small tribe.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
" a « in v* isny
ONE OF THE OLDEST CHRISTIAN WORLD-MAPS
This is how Beatus, a geographer and monk at the monastery of Valcavado, Spain, depicted the known
world in 776 A.D. Considered to be one of the oldest Christian world-maps, it was attached to his Com-
mentaria in Apocalypsin and was probably intended to illustrate the distribution of the apostoJic missions
throughout the world. It has survived only in ten copies, varying in date from the 9th to the I 3th century.
The one shown here, made at the monastery of St. Sever in France around 1030 A.D., the most valuable,
is now in the collection of the Bibliothèque Nationale, in Paris. The earthly paradise is shown at the east
of the known world (right of map). The adjoining inscription Gens Seres (The silk people), is Beatus's
description for the Chinese. Beatus has represented mountain chains by markings with sawlike edges.
Like earlier geographers he sees the world as an island in a circumfluous ocean filled with fishes and islands.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
A warning against
THE MEDITERRANEAN BASIN.
DEODORIZED
HISTORY
by D. W. Brogan
In the second week of January, 1956, the Historical
Association of Great Britain celebrated its fiftieth
anniversary. It celebrated it in two ways, by discuss¬
ing problems of research, teaching and what the French
call "vulgarisation" and by discussing the impact of history,
that is, of historical teaching and writing on society.
That in turn led to a discussion of the always topical,
always important question of the
treatment of history in schools; its
dangers and its possibilities.
The problem can be briefly stated. P\ F\ j\ P\ P|
One phenomenon of the nineteenth ~~_
and twentieth centuries has been the
rise of nationalism. The immense
growth of nationalist feeling and
spread of nationalist doctrine may
not have been the sole cause of the
great wars from which the world is
still suffering, but nationalism is
certainly one of the causes; its growth
one of the present dangers. It is
also a fact that nationalism, however
deep an emotion, however legitimate
a doctrine, has been aided in its
progress (if that is the word) by the
concurrent spread of general literacy,
by the creation of systems of educa¬
tion which had for one of their
primary objects, the teaching of a
national version of history, either of
the history of a nation or of the
history of the world.
So remote and
so innocuous
DISAPPEARING ACT.
Until recently, indeed, until after
the first world war, the idea
that there could be any other kind of history
teaching in schools would have seemed scandalous. The
object of history teaching was just to provide a factual
basis for nationalist feeling, to give to the boys and girls
brought into the state school system a body of organized
knowledge of the past of their nation and of its relations
with the outside world, not a vague, neutral, merely
academic body of knowledge, but a concrete "useful"
nationalist view of the nation and the world.
All educational systems aimed at this ; all achieved a
20
CHARLES MARTEL.
great deal of success in their aim. It would not be too
much to say that, before 1914, if it had been found that
French and German boys had been given the same picture
of a Franco-German controversy, it would have been felt,
on both sides of the Rhine, that the teachers had failed
miserably in their manifest duty. The object of history-
teaching was not to teach neutral views but to reinforce
natural, i.e. national, feeling.
Of course, some of this nationalist
teaching was remote and so inno¬
cuous. At school in Scotland during
the first war, I was taught a great
deal about the wickedness of King
Edward I of England and about the
absurdity of his claims to be overlord
of Scotland. But King Edward I died
in 1307 and such teaching did not
seriously distort the mind, although
it may have wasted school time. It
was very different when German
schoolboys were told more than once
of the burning of the castle of Hei¬
delberg by the French, and French
schoolboys of the burning of the
castle of Saint-Cloud by the Germans.
'Burning' questions
of the war of 1812
These were, if not recent events,
living in artificially fostered me¬
mories. An American schoolboy,
told of the burning of the White
House, but not of the burning of the
parliament building of Upper Canada
in what is now Toronto, was likely to
be at cross purposes with a Canadian
who had received a different version
of the war of 1812. (An English schoolboy would be under
another disadvantage ; he would not know of either.)
It would be easy to multiply examples of such artificially
fostered historical memories and historial disputes. Some¬
times, the disputes were not entirely artificial. If there
was a certain amount of historical bickering between
the scholars of the Netherlands and of Belgium
after the first war, there was also a genuine controversy
over the regime of the Scheldt.
But, for the most part, historical argument was
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Tbç Unesco Courier. March 1956
directed to backing up not only a specific national
position, but a general national position, too often to
stiffening the national morale against a permanent and
dangerous enemy. (It is not often noticed that the nation¬
alist preoccupation with "teaching the young how to
shoot" was an unconscious tribute to the natural good
sense and good temper of the young. It was felt, as it is
sung in the musical comedy South Pacific, "'they've got
to be taught").
If only the books
had been switched
It would be wrong to say that there had been no
improvement in history teaching or history textbooks
before 1914. True, it often took the form of finding
better scholarly reasons for telling the old story, but the
very idea that scholarship had
claims and usefulness in such a task
was, on the whole, a gain. But
some of the gain was superficial. If
French textbooks were less nation¬
alist, that was part of an internal
change in French politics, not
necessarily a gain for pure scholar¬
ship. If the official northern legend
of the origins and conduct of the
American Civil War was contra¬
dicted and, to some degree exploded
by southern historians and that
revision given currency in southern
textbooks, that was only a tactical
gain if the northern pupils still read
only the northern version, the
southern pupils only the southern.
If nations or sections could have simply changed text¬
books, that would have been different and better. As it
was the boast that "nous avons changé tout cela" was
empty. The details might have been altered but the
spirit was the same. History was a weapon, not a tool.
The ideas are commonplaces today, but we must remember
that they have only recently become commonplaces and
that they are far from being commonplaces universally
accepted in many parts of the world, especially in the
new school systems of the nations that have recently
come to independent status. It is, therefore, worthwhile
repeating that to think of history, not as a tool for the
understanding of our human situation, but as a weapon
to be forged for a war that, hot or cold, it is assumed
will always go on, is to risk creating a public opinion like
that of Europe in 1914 and, to some extent, in 1939.
The most simple solution to the problem and one that
has some merits is to secure that the common textbooks
NAPOLEON OUTSIDE MOSCOW,
in school use are not only written in
a spirit of objective scholarship, but
that they are controlled by an out¬
side body of scholars. This, in prac¬
tice, means that the textbooks of
nations which are supposed to have
a hereditary enemy, are to be revised
in the light of criticisms made by
scholars and educationists of the he¬
reditary enemy who, in turn, submit
the textbooks of their nation, to si¬
milar criticism.
As far as this goes, it is probably
useful. But not only does it not go -
far enough; it may be dangerous in damocles.
a way that is neglected. Ths first
danger of not going far enough, I
shall deal with later. The second
. o < calls for brief comment. If the
main fault of textbooks is harping
on old national controversies, giving
the idea that international relations
consists of war and the material and
spiritual preparation for war, it is
not enough to take up a series of
problems (for example the origins of
the war of 1870) and try to get
agreement on the question.
First of all, it may not be possible
to get agreement on the solution of
the problem. There may, Indeed,
be no solution at all.
We may never know what Bis¬
marck had in mind in 1870, as apart from what he said
he had in mind in 1890 and after. Frenchmen may natu¬
rally be less ready to give him the benefit of the doubt
than Germans or may be more so If they detest Napo¬
leon III more than they do Bismarck!
Winding up with
dull, dry history
But much more serious is the implication that, if you
clear up these controversies, you have got very far.
For this, in turn, may lead to dull history, to a neu¬
tral least-common-denominator history that is hardly
worth teaching and it may, which is more serious, rein¬
force the view that history is conflict, controversy, that,
indeed, there is much to be said on both sides, but that all
that matters is the result. That can lead inno¬
cently to worship of what William James called
"the bitch Goddess success". The old, pugna¬
cious, partisan history is no worse than that.
(Cont'd
on next
page)
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Deodorizing history
(Continued)
But the danger of not going far enough is greater.
Many, perhaps most of the most fruitful problems of his¬
tory are not problems of national conflict at all. They
may be success stories or stories of great efforts that, as
far as we can see, failed. But they are not national suc¬
cess stories or national failures either.
How much ink and temper has been
wasted in discussing whether Charle¬
magne was a Frenchman or a Ger¬
man, a question he could not have
understood had it been put to him in
the manner of a modern question¬
naire! How much more fruitful is a
discussion of the reasons for the
limited success of Charlemagne's
great experiment, how much more
fruitful the pursuit of understanding
than either the scoring of nationalist
points or laborious explanations of
national misunderstandings.
Wholesome but
just not good
If we want good history textbooks
and we should (it is one of our
greatest needs) let us think of
them positively. One of the greatest
problems of world society is created
by the belief, common in Asia and
Africa, that the West cares nothing
for their sentiments. How much
more useful than rewriting the story
of English rule in India in an
apologetic fashion would it be for
English school textbooks to ignore the
short period of English rule and
make India before the European in¬
vasions an historical theme of the first magnitude.
The deodorized history of some propagandists has one
weakness, it may have no faults but it has few merits. It
is boring and the young cannot learn if they are bored.
We must have legends. Why not change legends? Don't
tell the Swiss children
about William Tell, let
them learn about the Cid
or the Forty-Seven Ro-
nin. It will be less bor¬
ing. (Even I got tir¬
ed of the wickedness of
Edward I and the hero¬
ism of Wallace, the
fourth or fifth time I
was told about it.)
Anything is better
than indifférence to the
variety, dignity, interest
of the stories of other
peoples.
Let the French hear
BECOMING A KNIGHT.
MACHIAVELLI AND FRIEND.
about Florence Nightingale, the North Americans about
Bolivar or even of the Russian pioneers in Siberia. For
I harbour, and have always harboured, a dangerous
thought about some of the most touted reforms of nation¬
alist history teaching.
The textbooks that well-meaning reformers would like
to produce have one great weakness; they would be
unreadable. As the bogus prize poem said of Nebuchad¬
nezzar:
Sighed as he chewed the unaccustomed food,
It may be wholesome out it is not
good.
The beginning of wisdom will be
when we take to our hearts the
heroes of other people, not when
we write off heroism.
And there is one further advantage
in emphasizing the positive.
Make sure Marc
Antony was wrong
Heroes and heroic deeds last;
fortunately hereditary enemies
don't. If you spend your time
removing awkward passages from
narratives of past controversies, you
may find yourself without an au¬
dience; the young may not care.
Your work will be innocent
but useless. Fortunately it is not
true that:
The evil that men do lives after
them,
The good is oft interred with their
bones.
It is our job to make sure that
Mark Antony was wrong.
CAESAR AND CLEOPATRA.
IT ALL STARTED WITH EUROPA The drawings published
on pages 20 to 23 were made by Campbell Grant and are repro¬
duced from a wild and humorous romp through European
history written by Richard Armour with the title "It All Started
with Europa". The book dedicated to "history students and
history teachers who for generations have made each other
equally unhappy," deliberately sets out to present a humorously
unreliable account of European history, misremembering and
dismembering almost everything, from cavemen to 20th century
dictators. No historical era is omitted, no fact accurately pres¬
ented. In his unabashed distortions, the author acknowledges
that he has "made no use whatever of the works of Thucyd-
ides, Tacitus, Gibbon, and Arnold J. Toynbee," and cautions
that any resemblance between his book and the work of
any other historian, living or dead, "is highly unlikely."
DRAWINGS BY CAMPBELL GRANT FROM "IT ALL STARTED WITH
EUROPA," BY RICHARD ARMOUR, PUBLISHED BY McGRAW-HILL
BOOK CO., INC. COPYRIGHT I9S5 BY RICHARD ARMOUR.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Couric'r. March 1956
CHARLES DARWIN AND A LOWER ANIMAL
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Front page "lead" of April 14, 1493 would certainly have
been "The Columbus Story"if daily papers had existed.
Here is how it was presented in "News of the Nation".
This book in tabloid newspaper format helps to make
U. S. history immediate and alive. Copyright 'News
of the Nation", published by Prentice-Hall Inc., New York.
»1**1 I I P|
crossed the Rubicon'
by J. G. Massée
French children had a
chance to do some histor¬
ical reporting in a con¬
test sponsored by the
Archives Nationales de
France, last year. Prizes
were awarded to student
teams submitting the
best four-page report on
the fall of the Bastille.
Left, the front page of
the newspaper submitted
by the winning team.
Right, a two page -cover¬
age of the attack on the
prison in the newspaper,
dated July 14, 1789, which
won the second prize.
History is everything that ever happened, and
no-one can claim to know or understand
everything. Yet everyone looks to the past
listens at his father's knee to stories about his family,
hears the teacher tell old tales about his village or
his country or reads in books about ancient kings and
distant lands and tries to understand what has gone
before, because the past explains so many things
about himself and the present time and place in
which he lives.
' It is in books that one can learn most about the
past, but unfortunately the very magnitude, the huge
scope of recorded history often makes reading about
past persons and events an unsatisfactory experience.
' A reader may be especially disappointed in broad,
sweeping historical accounts because the necessary
condensation of material may make the past seem
too full or too lifeless, too monumental or too petty,
too simple or complex to be adequately understood.
In such history books, for instance, a man may be
remembered for leading an army or writing a law or
for dying, but little is conveyed of the flesh, the blood
and the mind that made up this man, of the facts
and factors which gave him his place in history.
In a sense, this is distortion of history because a
limited account limits comprehension. An incom¬
plete telling is not the whole truth, and thus it also
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March Î956
LAPMSEDELABASE/LLE
el ncus pix/--«":0'»s
¿Trr mitrailles á
leur pus*. D dllleunj
si tes canons onl
ete recules, 'ls serf
encare la. ftu apm
le Comité' Perma¬
nent etanl alerte',
il envoie le citoyen
Thur-ot qui se d'f"
eTecteur de S* Louis
en l'Ik. if &mvf a
vec deu* hommes
de la garde bour¬
geoise. Lei aiirres
Jt'kgUtS SOrteflt
prov'Ofluant" notre
etonnement, Thuriot
entre dans te lïou-
vernemeni. Mxjs ap
prenons par sts
compagnons qu'il
a demande de îéft
descendre tel cancnS
des tours . mais out
le gou-verneur, allé¬
guant cfu ¿* n'avaiY
pas d'ordres le lui
refuse. Un peu d*jî
tard nous voyons '
Thurfot condu'fà
l*tnhVv*-ieuf de. la for
her-rsa*. Maïs les
mêmes inquietudes
nous reprennent-
rapide me-iL L* bra¬
ve patriote Thuncf
a du £tc% rete na
Soudain jf le re-
"mdraue,se penrhart
au* eren** Bï.Je le
rnonh-e aux gens et
il sabe.app^udiMr
r-aus. -Nous ne voyais
toujours pas les ar¬
mes promises par
notre émissaire tf
il tarde bien á
faire bâiSstr les
Îonla. Subitement
ï vein au milieu
de. nous« sans avov
rJtn pu obtenir
reconduit d'un mai
vetnen'' si precis eh
si rapide que Je
pont de Í' Avance*
l'est Tïteve' derriè¬
re lui avant que
personnt n'»ie eu
te temps de. s v
pre'e. peter peur le
dt feu ont t'elah/.
Quelques ¿eldat;
rangent les gens
le Iongte
maisons. Je suis
dans un df tes gra>
pes avec un m»
que. mon voisin, ou«
¿si aile au* hnyli-
Inleerview
Je lut ai ail
ferai ei-w«»»* fe wi
p«sti auflatii« «
ht-nt :
0'- L.1,"'-C,1t.<)"*r-t
' tr où ête» -*oi»s atté
a »* basi.tte ?
J**s»í»t
if, : : .LI-. lj.i,(l p,
gjiti»itiJ" dti f*»c**
pris -Je 1 Hôte* dt
I« pr«kie*r t **.Ij r
toute ÏM-faUt, d'
enlevement' . j -v.n'*».n
'»ou* a. or.» rrtltnd»
d'*» d-flonaitiens
tis»-» éÎi«"iS "ï"!«"»
dun assaillant
. m mtmun. fwm - ;
et nt iMtoM yutte . fw*n ail a ta g*>ig*
Conduit' Nnir;^itaa4 *Sr*«i» «K«vm isWtmtét
l'avi|iid.mï Mutin
no«? amV^.'l fal¬
lait" »nartr.r< a-n.*i-
i>oii . flo-u'j a**uiv&
tramé U battent
-^ rtttus J'-'n-j.
Ç.- LaîrMut v»vs
ife> a«ivVv svi la
p\a-c r-*v«.vtm f
vu r\ rtsseati f ir
R-U-v^ectA-iWi-
ïiit mom , elt» MUtys
t».'.»' pt.ii t.rnl
sut t«i RutrftiBea,
bot Oiímr dr »af¿t-
t. i itek fr-mffte. neu
Íhit far ta s-*»«1
-tcr.Lt.0. 4tS
'11*. tí Pif W
ruiM'ir -i* la.tt.jl«
U i'M II', on
distt'vg.ua*t ¿ourte
Inmvt'íli-.Vi tl Its
tat«.
InuiHi eHe s ritt**
_.fi»n!rh b(M
rpCJlS...,«»« Ut*U*W<
ru«*;. btau<.eup .
JttU»'.fci*Jr<irteHi
-s'est" pas«' *u-*>
*m«i tspr.t as Mnft Cm*
maintenir baiis^ et
neuj n'aurons pas
pu cette Fois avoir
accès à l'alertai
clandestin Ou; e'ta&
te teul but de ccK
te expedition ¡suis
dternïst.Thur:ot'
va d 'ailleurs inv
me'dia-terncnt-a. I'
Hohel de Ville.
Lax Su'is-ps res¬
tent impassibles
sur leurs galènes
d cenf p'ed? de
nous et te gouver
neur est invisible.
Des ciameurs s'
eliveînf poor in¬
sulter nfK gr^rvlL
bâtisse. A tu tno-
des cot$>s
des «'a passe'.uxn
qui ne tirent pasenenr,
s'e'gaici'Unt, agitent
du sabrtx.cks ¿pái
des haches.
Ver; midi et demi
dt n&uv-eaux assai-
fents arrivent r"ïO-
re en poussant de
criJ furitu**:« Nom
wulctu 1« Basliltc!
Bas ks ponts f»
Ài un charron
Louis lôurnay(^ue
l'on cu/i. ¡au sa.il b« t
da«$ t dujrher
fcrigu'»! -ud*r -^ue le
ponr a eV leve'.gnnr
pe sur le tût tkv-
opet r pariumeur,
arrive sur U che-
mitl dt ronde, le
et au* acclama¬
tions du ptuptt par-
vent samet sauF
Sur le toit du corpi
de garde d« J 'Avan¬
cée, maigre' tel in-
jonchons puts le:
salves des Invah&i
de la BannicVe.
Ef il se met a ah-
taquer les chames
du pont-lwis aid«
par un camarade
qui apport» ckî ha¬
ches de rtnjort.
Avec un lernfcle fra
cas te pon! s 'abat
et toute une *qu'Pt
se precipite pour
-enfoncer la porte.
Nous nouj ruons
dans la courduGou
verne ment.
Mous crions aux
Suisjes et aux Inta-
lidcí :<v¿ei fit nt : \
Baissez fi.i ponhb
On voit te gouver-
neur s'approcher
d'un ere'heauyit
fait un signe. Immi
èiahmtnt nous at¬
tendons ce que ¿au-
nay va naut proeo-
5er, .Soudain, un Jeu
de salve, parhdw
tours crache Sa
rrMlrailje. Une ving¬
taine de patnotet
sont toe's. Nous es¬
sayons dt reculer
pour échappera
U gueJ-.foejis a-
bommaibJ*, mais
ceux du dehors pout
sent de foutes jeun
farces afin d'en-
h-er a leur roor.
Nous crayons è
VUE CAVALIERE
DE LA BASTILLE
SUITE DE LA
PREMIERE PAGE
Ire pns dans One
nasse d>nl aucun
de nous ne reenap
pera. Tout le mon¬
de cr«e. maudite
¡>ittrc qui re'pond
par des fui'Màates
a dés requête» U*
ciriquer^^nr -mut»
?liées. Noys reus-
issons a évacuer
les morts th les
bie'i£ilqU't quel¬
ques personnes
vont condwre a
I hotci de vilte où
elles feront le rd-
cir de cet Assassi
nat.
Les b aile -s continuent
siftter.Un petit
homme passe de
groupe en groupe
Suppliant -ou on rei¬
se Üc tirer: il u pre
bisd «isvove parU
GjTYiire; prèf^ue p»f.
sonne nt IVcóuli.
bes noinnnes torn
benf près de nous
il essaye dt lire
lint proclamation
mais nous n'y rom
prenons i-un csr
S-i "OU* y perd
dans un ou-naçan de
eu traverses par
le cre'piementefej
coups de d
LEUE55IN BE ¿A5EMAINE
Dea acclamations
nous parviennent.
Dans b rue S* An¬
toine . un groupe de
Ííens tous a«Wiote
uiilî avance avec
a sa hfrt un _¡a 1 1
n«r bUnc al or.DaS
tjreurae sont juchCt
sur des tnaiio-'is.ttioui
riposfom rnal%r-c' ru.
Jre armement as se a
précaire. Certains
rse-e/ih t*n$ même
Wer. D'autres, sur
te t»it de t échop¬
pes de U cour d '
entrée se cachent
derrière les cht*-
minees. Let Sunset
?ar un tir pre¬
is arrêtent la
Srtmtére vasrue
a%s aillants.
Mari une nouvelle
deVgafion arrive,
en nr** un tambov
piii; kl -¿'legues1
avec un drapeau
blane et Je procu
heur du roi tthis
de Corny. L« oVf*
ration gagna le
pont de pierre sa
fue'e par /es quo¬
libets de \a iTult
liprncï*!if hi dtr-
Tiitnet moutqucltt'
r*¡ %e lAllenr. Un
éi^tA» bUic eil
Int.« tur U ß.i'ife«.
V.., ir. urn dfefrdt.
£< .it i- un. diurne
¿t 1 1- :rw»í .{fMnl
restricts one's attempts to relate the past to the
present with any substantial validity.
But a complete telling, like complete knowledge or
understanding, is impossible, so what can the his¬
torian do to interest and inform his readers to the
greatest possible extent? He may focus upon one
small section of time or place and attempt to des¬
cribe it completely. He may look at a year, an epic
or an age from one specific viewpoint social, eco¬
nomic, political or philosophical. He may even write
a novel, thinking fiction a more meaningful way to
present facts. Among the many other methods of
presentation, he has recently attempted historical
journalism.
The writing of historical events as present-day
news stories overcomes some of the criticisms against
the encyclopedia-type book. History becomes imme¬
diate and alive. There is a truism that says there is
nothing older than yesterday's newspaper, but it is
equally true that nothing is as up-to-date as the
latest edition. A description of the invention of the
printing press written as if it were a news release in
the evening paper becomes as exciting, as unbeliev¬
able and as revolutionary as today's announcements
of coming space satellites.
Using the varied format of a modern daily news¬
paper gives the historian other opportunities. As an
editorial writer (with the unusual gift of hindsight),
he can be most profound in pointing out historical
trends and future possibilities based on "the news of
the day". As a feature writer he can develop back¬
ground stories to explain all the pertinent details
behind an historic event. As a columnist he can
vividly present the art, literature, customs or pecu¬
liarities of a period or intimately describe a persona¬
lity of the day. As a cartoonist he can show that
the past was as full of foibles as the present. All
such possibilities translate history as the down-to-
earth living that it actually was, enabling a reader
to view the past in more human terms and to see it
sharply, almost as he might have witnessed the
people and events had he been alive during the times
about which he is reading.
A typical example of this form of historical report¬
ing is a paper published in Jerusalem called "Chroni¬
cles, News of the Past", a six-column tabloid-size
journal. Its first thirty-six issues, presenting a his¬
tory of the Jewish people against the "background of
world history, take the reader from Joshua and the
conquest of Canaan through the period of Charlema¬
gne. The lead story in an early issue is topped by
the four-column headline announcing "King Saul Is
Dead" . and describes the rout of the
Israelite forces by the Philistines and the (Cont'd on
later suicide of the wounded King Saul. next page)
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Special Edition i^
An even more ambitious version of historical news¬
papers is a book called "News of the World" edited by
Sylvan Hoffman and C. Hartley Grattan. The book
comprises fifty four-page tabloid issues covering
world events of almost 5,000 years up to the end of
1949. Each issue spans an arbitrary era; the first, for
instance, reporting on the years 3,000 B.C. to
1,447 B.C. Its lead story concerns the industrial
revolution in progress due to the advent of metal
tools. Another typical story is headlined "Egypt
Powerful ; Social Changes Made". A later issue
announces "Caesar crosses Rubicon". This book is
a successor to one by the same editors, "News of the
Nation" which was confined to history of the United
States. Such all-inclusive summaries, while lacking
some of the illuminating details of papers covering
shorter time periods, are noteworthy for the clarity
with which a reader can grasp the repetitious cha¬
racter of history and discern its major forces and
the trends it follows.
This type of historical writing is, of course, limited.
m -l#^
m Chronicles
NIWI OF THf .HIT
Student team which won the French histo¬
rical reporting contest with its four-page
newspaper account of Bastille Day, 1789,
prepares to demolish the prison (in cake
form). M. Charles Braibant, Director of
the French National Archives, makes the
first breach in the walls. Ina Bandy, Paris.
However, many of its obviously elemental character¬
istics plus its liveliness make it especially valuable as
a tool to quicken children's interest in the past. A
variation of the idea was used most successfully for
this purpose in a contest for schoolchildren sponsored
last year by the Archives Nationales de France.
Prizes were awarded to student teams who submitted
the best four-page newspaper reporting on the fall
of the Bastille. Documents, pictures and assorted
records of the Musée de l'Histoire de France were
made available to contestants. These finally num¬
bered 244 boys and girls who submitted 54 news¬
papers; but more important, some four thousand
children were attracted to the museum during the
three months of the contest.
In our times, we have seen an accelerated pace of
historic events, speeded ever faster by fantastic scien¬
tific advancement. Happenings that took place yes¬
terday often seem gigantic and today's occurrences so
vital and all embracing that mere knowledge of them,
much less understanding, is a difficult accomplish¬
ment. For this reason alone, it seems that the possi¬
bilities for this journalistic treatment of the past
have not yet been fully developed; especially when
it can be used so successfully in making history an
absorbing, colourful, comprehensible subject for chil¬
dren attempting to know the world they came from
and the world they live in today.
Scandal
Century
I- TOP ROMAN OFFICIALS BRIBED!
In the columns of "Chronicles, News of the Past",
published in Jerusalem, (above) the history of
biblical times becomes up-to-the-minute news.
The U. S. historical newspaper, " News of
the Nation " (below) carried in its issue for
March 6, 1770, the announcement by the inventor,
philosopher and statesman, Benjamin Franklin,
that he had identified lightning as electricity.
Copyright 'News of the World".
fjred badly, for tliey did not lniowltli.il the French ha\e no intention of
how to meet the hit-and-run tactics withdrawing und that, on thy con-
of the Indian and Frelicll guerrillas, I trary,. it I« their intention to late
Electricity Works, Says Franklin
Br Neteë of the Nation Free*
. PHILADELPHIA, June, 1752-
Lightning has been Identified' a*
electricity. That was the interesting
discovery announced hexe today by
Benjamin Franklin, noted scientist,
who reveuled details of An experi¬
ment he made u few days ago.
During 3 recent rainstorm Frank¬
lin, accompanied by his twenty-oue-
yrar-otd um, went out-i]f-<loors to
test a theory he has entertained that
lightning iind electricity might he
similar, "lie sailed a kite very high
into the »ir, and attached a key near
the end of the string which he held
Benjamin Franklin
Inventor, phiíaeaphrrt
etateeman.
in his hand. As the rain increased
the kite's string became wet, and the
string acted as a conductor, permit¬
ting electricity to flow down to the
key. When the scientist touched the
metal with his kumkles he received a
shock, thus verifying his belief.
He believes that it may be txmi-
hle, nn the sume principle, to deflect
lightning from home* and barns.
Since metal i<¡ A conductor he be¬
lieves that steel rods placed on top
of buildings may absorb passing
lightning fl-Lshes and prevent them
from .striking ¡nilaiiim.tble wooden
parts. He is now testing this theory.
Freedom's Symbol
BOSTON, Massachusetts. Aog. 20,
1765 (N\P)-In almost every town
and city in the land "Lilierty trees"
ha-^'e been selected during the past
few months its a symbol of the pro¬
test against oppressive taxation. The
trees, usually in the middle of the
town, are the centers for meetings,
picnics, and "jtuinp sneaking."
Dustori is the latest city to desig¬
nate a "Liberty tree*" where two
nights ago an effigy of Andrew Oli¬
ver, a royalist officer, was hung. This
was in protest against the Stamp Act
which Oliver Is to udminister.
Oliver was so impressed by the
demonstration that he said he bad
no intention of forcing the Act.
, .< i
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
ASIA
How good is your
knowledge on Asia?
I
he series of questions given below is based on information which has
appeared in previous issues of the UNESCO courier. Subscribers will prob¬
ably find no difficulty in answering many of the questions. Some of the
photographs accompanying the questions may be found to be helpful clues.
Answers are given on page 34.
1. The world's population totals
2,528,000,000. Asia (excl. Russia)
accounts for what portion ?
(a) three quarters
(b) two thirds
(c) one half
(d) one fourth
2. Which country has the highest
literacy rate in the Far East?
(a) Burma
(b) Philippines
(c) Japan
(d) Korea
3. Which city of Japan is known as
the "City of Peace"?
(a) Nara
(b) Kyoto
(c) Yokohama
(d) Horiuji
4. A three-stringed Japanese instru¬
ment is known as a:
(a) Kabuki
(b) Samisen
(c) Geisha
(d) Bunraku
5. Which country in Asia is the most
dependent on irrigation for its
food?
(a) India
(b) Japan
(c) China
(d) Malaya
6. What world - famous historical
monument was almost demolished
for the value of its marble?
(a) Temple of Baalbek (Lebanon)
(b) Ruins of Palmyra (Syria)
(c) Krak des Chevaliers (Syria)
(d) Taj Mahal (India)
7. The Story of Genji is:
(a) a Japanese novel written by a
woman a thousand years ago
(b) a collection of Indian myths
(c) the story of a Tartar invader
of China
(d) part of the Arabian Nights
8. Which was the first country in
Asia to give women the right to
vote?
(a) India
(b) Philippines
(c) Mongolia
(d) Japan
S
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
ASIA QUIZ
(Cont'd)
9. Some 2,000 years ago medical men
of Asia advised that water be
purified by being boiled over fire.
They lived in:
(a) India
(b) China
(c) Japan
(d) Arabia
10. The Chinese dragon is an ancient
symbol of:
(a) ancestor worship
(b) water
(c) spring rice harvest
(d) teachings of Confucius
13. Chinese Opera is a combination of
three of the following. Which
description doesn't fit:
Photo copyright Pic
(a) dance
(b) acrobatics
(c) vividly coloured décor
(d) mime
14. Which one of these do we not owe
to the Chinese :
(a) papermaking
(b) gunpowder
(c) movable type
(d) the zero
15. In Japan, which creature of the
sea symbolizes tenacity and vitality
and is used to indicate a son in
the family?
16. Which language in use today has
the longest continuous written re¬
cord?
(a) Persian
(b) Arabic
(c) Chinese
(d) Japanese
17. Great experiments in artificial
rainmaking and other meteorolo¬
gical fields are going on at Quetta
in:
»«*-B«i*| | -j
(a) Malaya
(b) Afghanistan
(c) Pakistan
(d) Iraq
Mainichi newspapers
11. Before Tokyo, this city was the
political and cultural centre of Ja¬
pan for 1,000 years:
(a) Kobe
(b) Osaka
(c) Yokohama
(d) Kyoto
12. A Hindu spiritual
known as a:
(a) Siva
(b) Baisakh
(c) Muezzin
(d) Guru
28
teacher is
Mainichi newspapers
(a) salmon
(b) tuna
(c) carp
(d) pike
18. What great city of the East
constructed sewers 3,000 years
ago?
(a) Peking
(b) Bombay
(c) Nineveh
(d) Ur
19. One of India's two Hindu classics
is called "The Mahabharata". The
other is:
(a) Siva
(b) Putliwalla
(c) Parvati
(d) Ramayana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
20. Which country in Asia was once
known as "The Land of the Morn¬
ing Calm"?
20
(a) Tibet
(b) Korea
(c) China
(d) Ceylon
21. Japan's greatest dramatist, called
the "Shakespeare of the Far
East" was :
(a) Chikamatsu Monzaemon
(b) Ihara Saikaku
(c) Komei Ishikawa
(d) Matsuo Basho
22. The world's second largest pro¬
ducer of feature films is :
(a) India
(b) Japan
(c) China
(d) Italy
23. The world's third largest producer
of feature films is :
(a) India
(b) Japan
(c) China
(d) Italy
24. Which country developed an un¬
usual art form called stone
"rubbings" 2,000 years ago?
(a) Japan
(b) India
(c) Burma
(d) China
25. What are the Caves of Ajanta
famous for?
(a) earliest known human fossils
(b) temples and paintings
(c) largest in the world
(d) reputed hiding-place in "Ali
Baba and the 40 thieves"
26. What famous ascetic remained
atop a 50-foot column in Syria for
27 years without descending?
(a) St. Barnabas
(b) St. Paul
(c) St. Privat
(d) St. Simeon
27
27. In which country are lobsters,
seaweed and a fireman's parade
part of New Year festivities?
(a) Tibet
(b) Vietnam.
(c) China
(d) Japan
28. The inhabitants of Ceylon are
called :
(a) Celanese
(b) Senegalese
(c) Sinhalese
(d) Indians
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
29. The language of Indonesia is :
(a) Tamil
(b) Bahasa
(c) Urdu
(d) Tagalog
30. The Nobel Prize has been awarded
to scientists or thinkers of Asia :
(a) never
(b) twice
(c) three times
(d) five times
31. The game of chess was first evol¬
ved in India about :
(a) 2,000 B.C.
(b) 1,000 B.C.
(c) 500 B.C.
(d) 400 A.D.
32. The Tosa School in Japan was :
(a) a training centre for Samurai
warriors
(b) the oldest university in Asia
(c) a style of painting
(d) a group of ascetics who
preached against the luxury
of the court
33. This new Asian State incorporated
articles from the Universal De¬
claration of Human Rights into its
first Constitution in 1950 :
(a) India
(b) Indonesia
(c) Pakistan
(d) Burma
34. The six chief whaling countries of
the world are: Norway, Nether¬
lands, S. Africa, U.K., U.S.S.R. and:
(a) Indonesia
(b) Korea
(c) Japan
(d) Philippines »
Copyright "Progress'.'
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ASIA QUIZ
(Cont'd)
35. Jute and cotton are the "gold" and
"silver" fibres of :
(a) Ceylon
(b) Thailand
(c) Pakistan
(d) Laos
36. He is renowned as one of the lead¬
ing poets of Islam and Pakistan's
greatest :
(a) Iqbal
(b) Tagore
(c) Lao Tse
(d) Taha Hussein
37. A great emperor of India who
helped spread Buddhism through¬
out Asia. H.G. Wells said of
him "more living men cherish his
memory today than have ever
heard the names of Constantine or
Charlemagne." He was :
(a) Chandragrupta
(b) Kalinga
(c) Asoka
(d) Pandukabhaya
38. Marco Polo undertook his voyages
to the Far East in the :
(a) 10th century
(b) 12th century
(c) 13th century
(d) 15th century
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
39. Which two of these countries have
no outlet to the sea?
(a) Pakistan
(b) Afghanistan
(c) Iraq
(d) Ceylon
(e) Cambodia
(/) Laos
(fir) Viet-nam
40. This flower is the symbol of the
Imperial House of Japan :
(a) chrysanthemum
(b) lotus
(c) rose
(d) orchid
41. The tallest columns in the world
are found in the ruins of a Ro¬
man temple at :
(a) Palmyra
(b) Baalbek
(c) Babylon
(d) Ur
(b) Japan's largest shinto shrine
(c) northernmost island of Japan
(d) Japan's greatest opera singer
¿X
m±*	 J.
42. Emperor Hirohito is head of the
world's oldest monarchy. The dy¬
nasty has reigned since :
(a) 1500 B.C.
(b) 600 B.C.
(c) 850 A.D.
(d) 1200 A.D.
43. Hokkaido is :
(a) a great Japanese dramatist
44
Mainichi newspapers
44. Japan's great classical drama is
known as :
(a) Kabuki
(b) Bunraku
(c) Torii
(d) Kojiki
45. The great wealth of northern
Thailand lies in its :
(a) rice paddies
(b) teak forests
(c) Buddhist temples
(d) health resorts
46. Of the 15 countries in the world
where women have no right to
vote, 8 are in Asia. Can you name
at least 5.
47. Born a thousand years ago, this
Persian was Islam's greatest phy-j
sician - philosopher. Up to the
18th century, his medical works
were standard texts in all Euro¬
pean universities :
(a) Soliman the Great
(b) Avicenna
(c) Al Ghazali
(d) Ibn Khaldun
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
WORLD
PRESS
COMMENTARY
OUR recent issue which asked the question " Are
Women Inferior Beings? " and answered it with
scientist Ashley Montagu's conclusions "No, they
are naturally superior to men!" has touched off a little
hornet's nest in the world's press. As readers will recall
the Unesco Courier reported that the latest scientific evi¬
dence shows that women are naturally superior to men,
that they live longer, are healthier, are better "shock
absorbers" than men, and are more intelligent than men.
The issue (November 1955; U.S. edition January 1956)
surveyed women'sprogress in different countries over the
past sixty years and revealed that there were only fifteen
countries left where women still do not have the right
to vote (1). Since the publication of this number, a new
electoral law has been published in Egypt under which
women will have the right to vote for the first time. Men
over 21 must vote, but women need not do so. The same
issue exploded some false notions about women in primi¬
tive societies, and published the findings of a four-coun¬
try survey which showed that "the woman who does
nothing all day long but stay at home... works a 70-hour
week." Many newspaper and magazine clippings have
reached us giving factual reports or comment on
this issue. Below are a few from different countries.
'LIFE OF THE INSECTS'
'L'Express', Paris
Under an eight-column banner, "A
unesco Inquiry : Women are still not
free!", the Paris daily "L'Express" of
Nov. 25, devotes its entire two-page centre
spread to a detailed report of the infor¬
mation published by the Unesco Courier.
It begins with this introduction:
"Unesco has gone ahead and just
carried out a considerable piece of work
to establish a balance sheet of 'the
progress made by women in recent years
in their struggle for equality with men'.
The truth is that the world has never
been so preoccupied with women as in
the past ten years. Economists, demo¬
graphers, biologists reduce them to equa¬
tions and transform them into statistics
as if all the women in the universe had
been rounded up in an immense zoo and
the technicians given a free hand to
study this animal suddenly turned rum¬
bustious.
" ' And you, professor, what do you
think?'
" 'Mmm... Well, frankly, doctor, it
seems to me that...'
"And the women are successively in¬
formed that they are found superior, or
inferior, or equalbut always in terms
of the same invariable yardstick, i.e. the
male.
"Unesco's effort does not quite shake
off the atmosphere of a 'Study of the
(I) Afghanistan, Cambodia, Egypt, Ethiopia. Iran,
Iraq, Jordan, Laos, Libya, Liechtenstein, Nicaragua,
Paraguay, Saudi Arabia, Switzerland, Yemen.
Life of the Insects'. Painstaking ento¬
mologists, acting with the kindest of
intentions towards these insects have
piled up observations and figures to make
it possible to measure the march forward
of the women of the world in achieving
the principles affirmed by the U.N.
Charter: 'Free and equal in dignity and
rights... without distinction of any kind
such as race, colour or sex.'
"Free and equal in dignity... There's
something that will take a good deal more
effort. But, alas, since you have to start
with the rights so that dignity can follow
afterwards, here are a few of the results
gathered and recorded by Unesco's
investigators."
GOOD-BYE ILLUSIONS
'Le Matin', Antwerp
"Unesco (has just) exploded a big
bomb", declares the Antwerp daily "Le
Matin". "After months of strenuous effort,
and with the aid of Professor Ashley Mon¬
tagu, it has come out with some surpris¬
ing news: women have made consider¬
able progress in recent years.
"Alas! not every truth, however scien¬
tific, should be shouted from the house¬
tops, and our Professor would have been
wiser to reflect on this before relegating
all his fellow men to an inferior place.
But as the harm has already been done
we must take up the cudgels in our own
defence.
"Fellow men ! Here we are then, the mi¬
nus Habens of humanity, the protozoa of
the race, the invertebrates of society. We
needed Unesco to make us realize it, and
a professor to discover that woman is
stronger than her mate, that she handles
her emotions more satisfactorily than a
man, and that if she wished she could
do almost anything.
"No more and no less. Good-bye then
to our masculine illusions. Power will
change its sex and women will be in com¬
mand. But before we abdicate let us face
the fact that we are responsible for a
thousand calamities. If things are go¬
ing badly in the world, it is because of
us, because we have never given women
the chance to teach us how to love one
another. Unesco has said it and I shud¬
der especially when I see my concierge
thrash her husband."
WORLD A BETTER PLACE
' Gazette de Lausanne '
The "Gazette de Lausanne" in Swit¬
zerland quotes large extracts from
Professor Ashley Montagu's article, and
remarks: "Here is something which, curi¬
ously enough, links up in certain ways
with an opinion expressed in these col¬
umns some time ago. Doctor X, a Lau¬
sanne psychiatrist, had put forward the
view that women drivers cause less acci¬
dents than men. This statement caused
an outcry in the Paris press. But evi-
dence has since shown this to be quite
true. Let us therefore render justice to
women and place our confidence in them.
There is every reason to
hope th-*-!*. the world will be (Cont'd on
a better place." next page)
3I
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
'^Courier (Continued)
.
¡
Hi WOMEN
IIHIIII
BEINGS ?
m cm«!«
iium u
-itiiiiii
s**
^
- <f lím! ici
-I»lit11
-riii hm
m
t il
i
UNESCO IS RIGHT
' Caffaro', Genoa
"Caffaro" of Genoa, after taking up the
arguments as to why women are superior,
says: "The Unesco Courier is right". It
adds that as the Italian population is
composed of 23,969,000 women as against
22,769,000 men, a Commission composed of
leaders from the largest women's organi¬
zations in Italy, both religious and poli¬
tical, met in Rome recently, and decided
to launch an intensive campaign to give
women a much greater representation in
the administrative and legislative network
for the next elections."
SHOULD RULE MANKIND
' Neue Post ', Bonn
In Germany, the Bonn "Neue Post"
opens its article by stating "A United
Nations Organization has affirmed that
women are more intelligent than men.
Half the world, in other words all the
human males, will be astonished to learn
that according to scientific data women
are more intelligent, more resistant and
more healthy than men.
"To reach this astonishing conclusion
has needed years of work, the accuracy
of whose results cannot be doubted.
Behind this statement is Unesco with all
the weight of its authority. When one
considers the results of this enquiry, one
wonders why the world is not ruled by
women. Women should be able, not only
because of their charm and affection, but
also because of their intelligence and the
biological means with which nature has
endowed them, to take charge of the
destinies of the world."
A SCIENTIFIC ISSUE
Italian press
The "Gazetta del Popólo" of Turin, the
"Piccolo" of Trieste and the "Mattino" of
Naples, all remark that Unesco "has
carried the feminist and anti-feminist
arguments from the literary to the scien¬
tific debating floor." They point out that
eminent economists, biologists, politicians,
psychologists and other specialists of
various nationalities took part in the
enquiry. The Milan newspaper, "Gazetta
del Popólo", reprints several articles from
the Unesco Courier under the headline
"Revolutionary Conclusions from a
Unesco survey".
STARTLING STATISTICS
' Daily Express ', London
The London "Daily Express", has a
provocative short piece by one of its
leading columnists, William Hickey, who
dismisses Professor Ashley Montagu,
Unesco and women's superiority in quick
order. Under the headline "The Natural
Superiority of Women?... Huh! A cool
look at some startling statistics", this is
what he has to say:
"This is not the time when one should
be in a temper. Not a time when one
should be angry." (The column appeared
on December 23.) "But I am in a temper.
I am angry. And the cause is Unesco's
report on women by an American social
scientist, Professor Ashley Montagu.
"He is the author of a book called 'The
Natural Superiority of Women'. And his
report for the U.N. Organization which
we all support through taxes is enough
to make any man angry and any woman
flattered.
"He says that if men had to bear the
pain of childbirth the human race would
have been extinct long ago. Oh, what
profundity! Oh, what wisdom! And I
say that if women had to earn the rent,
and the housekeeping, and the insurance,
and the coal bill... well, civilization would
never have begun!
"The professor is also quoted as saying
that the housewives of the world work
46,000,000 hours while the rest of the
active population of the world work only
42,000,000 hours. I don't know how he
arrived at these figures. The professor's
final conclusion is that 'the hand that
rocks the cradle should also rule the
world.'
"And I say to the professor... jolly good.
How right you are. The hand that rocks
the cradle... or nurses the child in the
watches of the night... is generally a male
hand. Isn't it?"
FUTILE DIATRIBE
' Courrier ', Geneva
In the editorial columns of the Geneva
"Courrier", René Leyraz writes: "I have
never read anything quite so futile, apart
from the antifeminist diatribes setting out
to prove the definite congenital superiority
of man over woman.
"Science has a broad back.
"Here, in any case, the question of
'feminism' is raised badly and stupidly.
"Naturally the stubborn champions of
masculine superiority will lash out hotly
at such pretensions. Tney will line up
arguments which are just as convincing...
or just as silly. They will undoubtedly
defend their chromosomes. Why not ?
"We already have wars between nations,
between races, and between classes. Now
the charming Ashley Montagu, under
Unesco's auspices, wants to launch us into
a war between the sexes! That is exactly
what we needed. As if it was not already
difficult enough to get Adam and Eve
to live together; as if there were not
already enough family troubles, divorces
and separations?
"Masculine superiority and feminine
superiority are two equally dangerous
myths. As for the first, woman's 'pro¬
motion' seems to me to have been
conclusively proved. Thousands of things
which men thought the "weaker sex"
incapable of doing have, in our own times,
been brillantly accomplished by women.
The woman of today follows man to the
heart of the jungle or to the summits
of the Himalayas without flinching or
fainting and without making a fuss.
"I do not believe, moreover that we
are able to produce a valid argument from
the differences between the sexes against
women's voting rights. Complementing
each other the two sexes can and should
usefully give their advice on community
matters. In those countries where
women's voting rights have been recogniz¬
ed there have certainly not been any
social or political catastrophies. In fact
the list of countries which join with
Switzerland in its obstinate refusal to
grant women the right to vote is some¬
what" humiliating for us.
"We can drop our attitude of masculine
superiority, but at the same time we
would ask our womenfolk not to fall into
the equally silly trap of feminine supe¬
riority. Rather let each sex play its full
role in the natural and providential order
of things.'
LET'S BE GOOD LOSERS
' La Croix ', Paris
Under the headline "Woman is 'natu¬
rally' superior to man", the Paris daily
"La Croix" commends the arguments put
forward by Professor Ashley Montagu.
One of its women writers, declares:
"Let us all be good losers. If it is true
that we are 'naturally' stronger than men,
we should be thankful for it for the sake
of the future of the human race. But
let us remind ourselves that we have so
much need of each other that it is of
little importance whether one or the other
is 'naturally' the stronger, as long as this
strength serves a useful purpose: biologi¬
cal strength for the woman to give life
and develop it; muscular strength for the
man to help his wife, and a 'super¬
natural' strength for both, so that a
helping hand is there in times of need."
PUT MEN IN THE SHADE
' News Chronicle ', London
The London "News Chronicle" headlines
its story: "Women! You put men in the
shade brainier, stronger, healthier..." The
article continues with an analysis of
facts from the Unesco Courier, noting
particularly that only in politics are
women lagging, behind the men.
OH, FOR NEW GUINEA
Two quotes from extreme ends of
Europe "Aftontidningen" of Stockholm:
"Oh, for New Guinea where the women
work and men decorate themselves with
garlands"; "El Alcazar" (Madrid). "And
to think that there are hundreds of
women sighing for a man who will libe¬
rate them from six hours in an office so
they can work fourteen in a house."
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1956
Letters to the editor
Sir,
The photo of the "turbaned vi¬
sitor" on page 20 of issue No. 10, 1955,
on the United Nations (USA-Decem¬
ber 1955) and the caption below it
naturally attracted my attention. May
I have it placed on your official record
that the Indian part of the Punjab
is known as East Punjab. (The "tur-'
baned visitor" struck me as a typical
Pakistani but then I'm not in a posi¬
tion to affirm that for sure)
Press Attaché,
Embassy of Pakistan,
Paris.
S. N. Qutb
Editor's Note : The Unesco Couiuf.r
erred. The "turbaned visitor" was Sir
Khizar Ilayat Khan Tiwana, former Chief
Minister of United Punjab and today a
citizen of Pakistan. The Punjab was
(liuided in 1947, one part going to Pakis¬
tan, the other to India.
Sir,
My attention has been called to the
Unesco Courier of May 1955 (No. 2
European edition), where it is stated
that "The Russian language is taught
in all schools in Republics of the Soviet
Union not later than the third year
of compulsory education." Is it possible
to get some documentation for this
significant statement?
Theodore Andersson
Associate Director,
The Modern Language
Association of America,
New York.
Editor's note : The latest information
received by unesco shows that the Russian
language is taught in all schools not later
than the second year of compulsory
riluralion. About 200 different languages
are spoken in the Soviet Union. The
"Great Russians", or Russian-speaking
population only account for 37 % of the
Union. The Soviet Union has sixteen
autonomous republics and a number of
autonomous regions, national areas and
districts. In each of these the mother
tongue is the medium of instruction, but
Russian is introduced as a second language
in the second-grade and is studied intens¬
ively together with the vernacular. As
a result, children of all the Soviet nation¬
alities are able normally to speak, read
and write Russian by the end of their
elementary school training.
Sir.
I am delighted with the Unesco Cou¬
rier and feel it would be an addition
to any home. In its field, it is tops.
Elizabeth L. Drake
Chathom,
New Jersey, U.S.A.
Sir,
I think your magazine should be
read by everyone, whether French,
"European" or stateless, who is not
completely indifferent to the fate of
his fellow men and women. It gives
clear and complete facts on each of
the great problems of the day, on the
efforts that are being made to solve
them especially by Unesco.
The different language editions of
the Unesco Courier offer everyone the
chance to perfect his knowledge of an¬
other language. I am a student at the
EcoZe des Hautes Etudes Commerciales
in Paris and I read the English lan¬
guage edition of your magazine thereby
finding an added interest in the
articles.
François Sallé
Paris.
Sir,
I have just received and read with
great interest the issue of the Unesco
Courier devoted to women's rights
(No. 11 1955: U.S.A. January 1956).
Congratulations to Unesco on produc¬
ing a study which should undoubtedly
attract the attention of all women.
At the same time there are a number
of facts I should like to bring to your
notice.
The French woman barrister whose
photo you publish on page 7 has her
arms bare to the elbow! This is en¬
tirely contrary to the rules of dress for
a member of the French Bar. Certain
women barristers, I regret to say, do
appear dressed this way, but they are
an exception. Generally, if women
barristers have short sleeves under
their robe, they take care to pull down
the sleeves of their robe as far as the
wrist. It is a pity you chose this par¬
ticular photograph when so many
others are available.
Secondly, France is named as being
one of the countries where there are
more girls in secondary schools than
boys. This is a serious error. There
are about one third fewer girls than
boys as you will see if you refer to
official figures.
You also state that there are 860
French women lawyers. This figure is
inexact. In 1950, there were 1,170 and
this figure has increased considerably
since then.
You say, too, that in France in 1900,
there was not a single woman law
student. This is not correct. Mile.
Chauvin, the first woman lawyer was
sworn in in 1900 so she must, therefore,
have been on the rolls of the Law
Faculty three to five years before
and she was not the only woman.
In his article, "Women in Politics".
M. Maurice Duverger states that
women m Parliament and on the
higher administrative levels concen¬
trate on specialized matters generally
considered to be of special interest to
women.
A study of parliamentary activities:
speeches made, commission reports and
legislation proposed, shows that though
women are naturally very interested
in feminine matters, their attention is
also focussed on almost all other ques¬
tions. For example, in France, they
are members of all the large Parlia¬
mentary committees, with the excep¬
tion of two or three. It is also untrue
to say that the political parties in
1955 tend to turn women into work
considered to be of a particularly fem¬
inine nature. Up to a certain point,
it is true for the parties of the right
with the exception of the MRP (Cath¬
olic Popular Republican Movement)
but it is not the case with the left-
wing parties.
Andrée Lehman
President, French League for
Women's Rights,
Paris.
Editor's Note : Latest available statistics
show that more girls than boys attend
French secondary schools. During 1II33-
11151 there were !' 18,000 secondary school
pupils in France of whom 48.ri,!i00 were
girls and 102,100 boys. (See "Current
School Enrolment Statistics" published by
Unesco in January l'.lüfi, price 2/- ; * fl.lll
or 100 Fr. frs.)
Sir,
I read in your issue No. 11, 1955
(U.S.A.January 1956) that to be eli¬
gible to vote in the Lebanon a woman
must have a certificate of primary
education or its equivalent. Under a
law passed in February 1952, Lebanese
women were accorded full political
rights irrespective of whether they
were literate or not.
Laure G. Tabet
President, National Council
of Lebanese Women ;
Lebanon Representative,
U.N. Status of Women Commission,
Beirut, Lebanon.
Editor's Note : Our correspondent is
correct in stating that Lebanese women
have equal political rights with men.
They received them, however, under an
amendment of February Uli"»'! not Fe¬
bruary 1ÍI52 following a legislative
decree of December 1, lil.'iï.
Pen friends wanted
Tatsuo SATO, 22, of 76, Z-chome,
Matsuzaki - cho , Abeno-Ku, Osaka,
Japan. Hobbies : reading , fine arts
especially painting travel, sports,
music. He -writes: "I am interested
in world peace. Mutual understanding
of the ideas and ideologies , the hopes
and dreams , the customs and cultures
of the peoples of other lands and good¬
will are, I suppose, the sine qua
non to realize -world peace. We all
know that when each part of a chain
is firm, then the whole chain is strong.
In the same -way, when this proper
spirit is manifested in the life of
each individual, then the world as a
whole -will be on its -way to peace and
happiness."
Masao NISHIDA , 19 , of 885 , Honjo ,
Kawachi-City, Osaka, Japan. Learn¬
ing English, German, French, Es
peranto. Corresponds in English
and German. Hobbies : football,
literature, music. Interests : mathe¬
matics, computing machines.
Guy HENNEMANN, medical stu¬
dent, 22, of 33 rue Leopold, Louvain,
Belgium. Writes English, German,
French, Dutch. Special interests:
literature, painting, dancing. Col¬
lects postage stamps, match boxes.
Norberto Horacio Lopez HAURAT,
17, of Roca 2044, Florida -Buenos
Aires, Argentina, -wishes to corres¬
pond in English , Spanish and Portu¬
guese.
Julieta SILVA, 18, of 672, R. Fer-
nandes Tomas 2, Oporto, Portugal,
and her brothers -wish to correspond
other young people in English,
French or German.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A S 1 A QUIZ
A N S W E R S
1. (c) One half 20. (b) Korea
2. (c) Japan. All
children b e t -
21. (a) Chikamat su
Monzamon,
ween 5 and 14
go to school
17th century
playwright who
also wrote for
3. (b) Kyoto puppet theatre.
4. (b) Samisen 22. (b) Japan
23. (a) India
5. (a) India
24. (d) China
'6. (d) Taj Mahal. Fan
tastic as it may 25. (b) Temples and
seem, a proposal paintings, India
was set afoot in
1828 to demolish 26 (d) St. Simeon.
the whole build
ing for the value
27. (d) Japan
of its marble 28. (c) Sinhalese
and was se
riously consider 29. (b) Bahasa
ed for seven
30. (c) Three times:
years Rabindranath
7. (a) Japanese novel
written by a
Tagore (India)
for literature;
woman 1,000
C.V. Raman (In
years ago
dia) for physics;
H. Yukawa (Ja
8. (c) Mongolia, in pan) for phy
1924 sics
9. (a) India
31. (d) About 400 A.D
32. (c) A style of paint
10. (b) It represented
water in all its
ing
forms: the life- 33. (b) Indonesia
giving rain,
rivers, the storm 34. (c) Japan
and the sea, the
mysterious ebb
35. (c) Pakistan
and flow of 36. (a) Iqbal
water
37. (c) Asoka
11. (d) Kyoto, famed
for its university 38. (c) 13th century
and about 3,000
Buddhist tem¬
ples and Shinto
* 39. (b) Afghanistan and
(/) Laos
shrines 40. (a) The Chrysan¬
themum.
12. (d) Guru
41. (b) Baalbek
13. (c) Chinese theatre
uses practically 42 (b) 600 B.C.
no decor
43. (c) Northernmost is
14. (d) The zero
land of Japan
15. (c) The carp
44. (a) Kabuki
16. (c) Chinese from
45. (b) Teak forests
about 1400 B.C 46. Afghanistan,
Cambodia, Iran,
17. (c) Pakistan Iraq, Jordan,
Laos, Saudi Ara
18. (c) Nineveh bia, Yemen
19. (d) Ramayana 47. (b) Avicenna
From the Unesco
Newsroom...
M. NDIA'S YOUTH VOLUN¬
TEERS : Nearly 17,000 young In¬
dian men and women members
of the international voluntary
work camp movement (See
Unesco Courier No. 6 1955: U.S.
Sept. 1955) have recently aided
communities in many parts of
their country. Teams have been
'going into city slums to launch
clean-up campaigns and initiate
people into the fundamentals of
health, sanitation and child-
care. Others have helped vil¬
lages to build or repair schools
and libraries and have worked
on many other community pro¬
jects. The Indian work camp
movement is rapidly spreading
to all parts of the country and
its organizations maintain close
contact with Unesco's Youth
Section. Later this year a train¬
ing course for work camp leaders
will be held in South India.
Members of youth movements
in other South East Asian coun¬
tries are being invited to
attend.
PLAYTIME IN PARIS:
Thirty countries are to send
theatre groups to the third
international theatre festival
in Paris between April 10 and
May 31. Notable theatre
companies due to take part
include: the Abbey Theatre
players from Dublin in
Shaw's "Saint Joan", the
Berlin Schiller Theatre com¬
pany, the Piccolo Teatro of
Milan, the Stockholm Natio¬
nal Theatre Group playing
Strindberg's "Father", and
the Belgian National Theatre
Company in a performance
of "Barabbas" by Ghelderodé.
Troupes from Mexico, Spain,
Argentine, Poland, Hungary,
Rumania and many other
countries are also to take
part. Plans are now well
advanced for setting up a
permanent Theatre of the
Nations in Paris a project
announced after last year's
festival.
Calling young ar¬
tists: Two international con¬
tests with related themes are
open to children with artistic or
literary talents in all countries.
The Moringa Society of Japan
invites drawings or paintings
from children up to 14 years of
age on the subject "My Mother",
for an international exhibition
to be held in Tokyo on "Mo¬
ther's Day", May 13. Entries can
be submitted through Japanese
Embassies or Legations until
April 15. The International
Youth Library in Munich (see
Unesco Courier No 3/4 1955:
U.S. July 1955) offers prizes for
drawings or paintings and for
poems or stories up to a page in
length on "The Wedding".
Children between the ages of 4
and 16 may compete and entries
should be submitted before
March 1, 1956.
PRESS TRAINING PROB¬
LEMS: The first internation-
nal conference devoted ex
clusively to problems of
journalistic training has been
called by Unesco and will
take place in Paris shortly.
Some 30 directors of schools
of journalis/n, newspaper and
newsreel editors and radio
and television specialists
from more than 20 countries
will study current training
problems as they apply to
work in all the fields of in¬
formation. The conference
is the first stage of a new
Unesco project aimed at aid¬
ing and improving journa¬
listic training in general and
is in line with its aim to aid
the spread of news and in¬
formation to promote inter¬
national understanding.
B IGGEST SHOW ON
EARTH: toome lu,000,000,000
people attend film shows every
year in more than 100,000 cine¬
mas all over the world. Their
entertainment provides the
world's film industry with an
annual turnover of something
like $4,000,000,000. Biggest fea¬
ture film producer is the U.S.A.
(344 films in 1953, the latest
figure given) with Japan in se¬
cond place (302) and India third
(259). Largest producer in Eu¬
rope is Italy (163), which also
leads the world in production of
documentary and short films,
other than newsreels. These are
some of the facts in "Film and
Cinema Statistics", a recently
published Unesco study, price:
$0.50; 3/-; 150 Fr. frs.
B TRANSLATING WORLD
CLASSICS: Sixty, transla¬
tions of great literary works
are now being prepared and
30 others have already been
completed under Unesco's
auspices. Works in some
seven languages were re¬
commended for future trans¬
lation by a special commit¬
tee which met in Paris re¬
cently. One suggestion was
that the most important
works in Japanese literature
should be translated in Eng¬
lish and French. Coming
under Unesco's programme
for international understand¬
ing through art, the transla¬
tion project includes master¬
pieces in the literature of
Latin America, Iran, China,
India, Japan, Italy and the
Arab nations.
FiOLKLORE ON TAPE:
Since it was founded just five
years ago, the Hungarian In¬
stitute of Popular Art in Buda¬
pest has collected some 12,000
folk songs from all parts of the
country, as well as descriptions
of traditional festivals and
games. Most of the collection
is preserved on tape recordings
and documentary films and has
provided material for 235 pam¬
phlets on folklore already pub¬
lished by the Institute.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Special binder
available shortly
Coming in April :
KILLERS OF
THE INSECT
WORLD
Modern ' plagues ' spread by
insects. The staggering toll in
death, ill-health and poverty
from insect-borne diseases
Many readers have asked if the UNESCO COURIER could
make available special binders in which they could keep
their year's collection of issues. We are pleased to
announce that a handsome binder will shortly be available.
Full details as to price, including packing and mailing,
will be published next month. The binder, shown above,
is in red leatherette with THE UNESCO COURIER
engraved in gold lettering in English, French or Spanish,
as desired. Do not send orders now. Please wait for
next month's detailed announcement.
Don't miss this issue. Subscribe today
to the UNESCO COURIER
Annual subscription rare .- 8/-; $2.00 or
400 French francs
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's National distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
AUSTRIA. Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27
Graben, Vienna I.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15, rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). (UNESCO COURIER only)
Librairie Encyclopédique, 7, rue de
Luxembourg, Brussels IV.
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei, 151,
Ancwerp.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090, Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Colombo I .
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. M.E. Constantinides, P.O.
Box 473, Nicosia.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6, Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskacu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, 19, Ave¬
nue Kléber, Paris, 16'. CCP. Paris
12598-48.
Sales & Distribution Division, 1 9, Ave¬
nue Kléber, Paris. I 6*.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bom¬
bay I ; 17, Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta
13. 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal .
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay 1.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road, P.O. Box 4101, Tel-
Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6, Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.. Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26, Kings-
way, Valletta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni-
jhoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100, Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60, The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35, The Mall. Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., I 104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5,
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2, rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 55 1-3, Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building. Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, National Agency for Internatio¬
nal Publica:ions, 500, Filth Avenue, New
York 36, N.Y.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27' I I, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
v^ouncr
THE MANY FACES
OF CIVILIZATION
%
SMILING HEAD (Pre-Columbian
Totonacan terra-cotta, Mexico)
]]>
</page>
</document>
