<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078140eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Price 15 cents (U.S.)
7 pence (U. K.)
30 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
V
M ' OR most people, the beginning of the new year is a special occasion and
M the signal for happy celebrations. If we could travel around the world
^ on a magic carpet and peep at these celebrations in the various countries,
what a wonderful variety of customs we should find. The Feast of the Lanterns
concludes two weeks of a noisy, gay spectacle ushering in the new year for the Chinese
who almost seem to be celebrating all their holidays of the year at once. In Japan,
New Year's Day is even gayer. No matter how poor a Japanese may be he provides
himself with spotless new clothes and takes several days off to visit old friends or
entertain them at home. Every gatepost is adorned with dark green pines and light
green feathery bamboos while over the doorways hang vivid red lobsters and crabs,
and scarlet tangerine-like fruits, symbolic of long life and happiness. The streets
are thronged with children laughing and playing the whole day long, and everyone
beams with joy, bowing and offering best wishes even to perfect strangers. Scotland
celebrates New Year's Eve with a heartiness rarely surpassed. The tradition that
to be "first-foot" in a house brings luck for the whole year sends midnight revelers
into the streets, each one carrying cakes and food and drink to ensure his' host a
bounteous year. So, throughout the world, in the Orient, in Africa, Europe and
the New World, the new year is celebrated with elaborate festivities. It is an
occasion for making fine new resolutions alas, not always kept for forgetting
the disappointments of the past twelve months and for making a new start.
At the beginning of this new year, the Unesco Courier has wanted to do more
than just offer its readers the traditional season's greetings. It has sought to "make
a new start" too, and like the Japanese, to provide itself with "new clothes." In
response to the desire expressed by readers it is abandoning its tabloid newspaper
size for a new magazine format easier to read, handle and keep. It has increased
the number of pages, designed a new cover in colour and prepared a brighter yet
sober presentation. But these are not the only New Year's gifts the Courier
presents to its readers. As a non-profit publication, the Courier, now offering
better value, nevertheless asks less from its readers. Starting with this issue it
is reducing its annual subscription price by almost half : from 10/6d to 6/- , from
$2.00 to $1.50, and from 500 French francs to 300 Fr. frs. Special arrangements are
being made to extend the expiry dates of subscriptions recently renewed at the old
rates. (Please see page 32 for further details.)
In its contents the Courier will continue to remain faithful to its set goal: to
serve as a window opening on the world of education, science and culture through
which the schoolteacher in particular for whom this publication is primarily conceiv¬
ed and prepared and other readers in general can look out on to wide global
horizons. Each month it will present by text and image, features which are both
informative and thought-provoking, and will devote a section to an authoritative
treatment of an important world problem and show how it is being dealt with nation¬
ally and internationally. The Courier particularly invites comments, criticisms
and suggestions from its readers. To the teacher who demands something more
than run-of-the-mill fare, to those who are interested in people and problems of other
nations, in the dramatic but little known story of ordinary men and women working
together to raise standards of living, combat ignorance and disease, reduce racial
prejudice and foster international understanding, to all those who are alert to today's
events and problems in education, in the arts and the sciences, the Courier says:
This is a periodical specially prepared for you. Join us by subscribing today at
the new reduced rates.
The Editors
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
NUMBER 1-1954
7th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 LANGUAGE AND INTERNATIONAL
UNDERSTANDING
4 JIGSAW OF THE WORLD'S LANGUAGES
What are we up against ? By Felix Walter.
8 OLD LANGUAGES FIND NEW JOBS
Asian and Middle East States remould their ancient tongues
10 I SPEAK ENGLISH SNAKE SNAKE, FISH FISH
Trials of a language student In Thailand. By Manlch
Jumsal.
14 THE HORSE COMES BEFORE THE CART
Modern trends and gadgets In language teaching. .
18 THE GREAT LANGUAGE FAMILIES
A map of the world's linguistic groups.
20 TOO YOUNG FOR A FOREIGN LANGUAGE ?
Successful experiments in the U. S. By Theodore
Andersson.
22 THE TRANSLATING MACHINE
Help to the scientist. By Edwin Holmstrom.
24 THEIR BUS STOPPED AT LAPLAND
27 Parisian boys visit the Far North. By Paul Normand.
26 YOUNG ADVENTURERS IN SCIENCE
Science clubs combine creative study with organized
play. By Gerald Wendt.
28 THE DAYS OF OUR YEARS
Should we change our present calendar i
33 THE CAYE PAINTINGS OF AJANTA
Indian galleries carved out of solid rock.
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France.
Edltor-ln-Chlef
Sandy Koffler.
Associate Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton
French Edition: Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition: Jose De Benito
Any material not copyrighted may be reprinted from the COURIER provided
it ii accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of the COURIER: 6/-, or S 1.50 or 300 French francs.
MC. 53.1 78. A.
UNESCO COURIER - N" 1 -1954
This month's theme
LANGUAGES:
BRIDGE OR BARRIER?
This young Indian girl of the Amazon
lives in the most polyglot of the five
continents. Out of the 3,000 languages
estimated to be used in the world today,
more than 1,200 are spoken by Indians
of the Americas some tribes of which
number only a few thousand or even a
few hundred people. By studying many
of these obscure languages linguists have
made discoveries about the nature of lan¬
guage itself and have in turn helped the
language teacher with his problems.
IN his description of Gulliver's travels among the Laputans,
Jonathan Swift relates how his traveller was privileged to be
conducted through the Grand Academy of Lagado where, among
many other ingenious projects, he found the academicians
engaged on a scheme for abolishing words altogetner. Since, it
was argued words were only names of things, their properties or
behaviours, "it would be more convenient for all men to carry about
with them, such things as were necessary to express the particular
business they are to discourse on... I have often beheld two of those
sages almost sinking under the weight of their packs... who, when
they met in the streets would lay down their loads, open their sacks,
and hold conversation for an hour together.
"Another great advantage proposed by this Invention, was that it
would serve as a universal language to be understood in all civilized
nations... And thus, ambassadors would be qualified to treat with
; foreign princes or ministers of state, to whose tongues they were utter
strangers."
Today, of course, more than ambassadors are concerned to
converse with people to whose tongues they are utter strangers and
to say that a world-wide language problem exists is not only to state
a truism but to make an enormous understatement.
Unesco, as the educational, scientific and cultural agency of the
\United Nations, has; had to meet, probably more than any other in¬
ternational organization, the problems arising from the diversity and
frequent inadequacy of many of the world's languages.
Not only is there the obvious problem of understanding and
communication between people, but also how to make the best use of
languages, especially those that have no literature because no written
form of the language exists or those whose literature is based on
classical "and outmoded forms. It is widely agreed that the best
medium for teaching is the mother tongue of the pupil. But how can
one attack illiteracy which is both a symptom and a cause of social
and economic distress among millions of underprivileged people when
their languages have no written form?
In addition to studying languages as media for teaching in its
fundamental education activities, Unesco has fostered translation
projects in many fields: it has worked to make the world's literary
masterpieces available in other languages; in science it has sought to
make it easier for the scientist and the engineer to cope with technical
articles appearing in languages with which they are unfamiliar.
Last August, at Nuwara Eliya, in Ceylon, Unesco brought modern
language teachers together to discuss the current problems of their
profession particularly with regard to the wider issue of international
understanding. In so doing, it may have begun to approach the heart
of the problem. After all, none of the radical world solutions to the
language problem, sincere as many of them are, and promising as
many of them may appear, are likely to be adopted tomorrow, or even
the day after tomorrow. In fact, no drastic and all-embracing
solution may ever be achieved. In either eventuality, efficient
language-teaching with a minimum of time-wasting and a maximum
of results remains a necessity.
It would be a solid achievement and the goal is by no means
Utopian if every child on leaving school found himself equipped to
use even just one language other than his own. But this immediate,
down-to-earth practical aim is not the only one. Language is a key.
It unlocks the door to a real knowledge of other peoples. This Is why,
today, the role of the modern language teacher is such a vital one.
His job makes him or her the unofficial ambassador of some one
segment of the larger, all-embracing human community which has its
existence beyond the frontiers of each individual state.
"'Ignorance of each other's ways and lives", reads the Preamble to
the Constitution of Unesco, "has been a common cause throughout the
history of mankind, of that suspicion and mistrust between the peoples
of the world through which their differences have all too often broken
into war". Every day, in tens of thousands of schools, modern lan¬
guage teachers can play their part in dispelling just a little of this
Ignorance and can, by so doing, make the universal problem of lan¬
guage just that much less of a burden to the human race: just that
much less of a threat to its future happiness.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
FROM THE ARCTIC
To THE EQUATOR
and from the Equator to the Antarctic there rises a babble of different tongues. Some In the heart of Africa
and In the Northern wastes are spoken by no more than a few hundred or a few thousand people ; others by
450 million. But a study of the world's languages brings home to us a major consideration: whatever the
number of their speakers, all languages, be they "primitive" or "civilized", adequately express the concepts
of the culture from which they spring and of the people or peoples who use them. (Photos C.O.I, and N.F.B.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
THE JIGSAW
PATTERN OF
THE WORLD'S
LANGUAGES
UNESCO COURIER - N" 1-1954
By Felix Walter
WE live in a world that seems to be
becoming increasingly aware of
. the problems of language. That is
probably because our generation bumps
its nose against the barrier of language
more often and more violently than our
ancestors did. How could it be other¬
wise in an age that has made travel so
swift and devised ways of communication
that are almost instantaneous?
But it is all very provoking to the
human ego. We can devise atom bombs
to wipe out half the world or jet planes
to girdle it, but, so far as the tangle of
language is concerned, we are still in the
era of the Tower of Babel. Actually the
situation is much worse than that: we
have slipped back and are continuing to
slip back. Linguists say that there are
approximately 3,000 languages spoken
in the world to-day, and they don't
pretend they have finished counting yet.
What really aggravates the situation is
not that many completely different
tongues are spoken by groups of a few
thousand, or even a few hundred, in the
interior of New Guinea, or in the jungles
of Amazonia or in the heart of Africa.
What counts is that the thrust and drive
of new nationalisms are constantly
setting up new national languages with
full official status. There is nothing
iniquitous about this; a distinctive lan¬
guage is a very natural though not an
essential attribute of sovereignty, and it
TODAY as far as the tangle of languages is concerned we are still in the era of the Tower of Babel thousands
of years ago when this metal cylinder of Babylonia was made. In fact we are slipping still further back for
linguists say there are now nearly 3,000 languages in the world. (Photo Palais de la Découverte, Paris.)
is clearly silly and a waste of time to
scold the Irish, for instance, for reviving
their ancient tongue or the Indonesians
for adopting Bahasa in preference to a
European language of wide diffusion.
It is no wonder, though, that there is
an increasing desire, to solve what is a
world problem, once and for all, by radi¬
cal means. One drawback is that the
reformers offer so many different pana¬
ceas. Some advocate that we should all
learn one of the languages already widely
spoken in many parts of the world.
Unfortunately the identity of language X
nearly always depends on the nationality
of the advocate. The British and the
Americans see great inherent advantages
in English. French-speaking people are
persuaded that French has certain in¬
trinsic merits which give their language
a prior claim. Speakers of Arabic or
Chinese or Russian or Spanish can think
up equally good arguments without any
difficulty at all.
If the choice is to be one of the so-
called artificial languages, then which
one? Is it to be Esperanto, which has the
advantage of an undoubted head start
over the rivals, or one of the rivals them¬
selves with claims to being even more
scientific and even more simplified?
The ultimate solution may well lie in
one of these suggestions, or it may be of
a different nature altogether, but if the
solution is to be effective, it must be
adopted on a world-wide , basis and
arrived at by general consent. That will
be extraordinarily difficult and will
depend in the long run on the decisions
arrived at by governments and by the
peoples on whom governments depend.
That suggests that a first and very
necessary step in the solution of the
world problem of the diversity of lan¬
guages is for people everywhere to try
and understand the extent and nature of
that problem. Only then can they
properly come to grips with it.
Covering the centre pages of this issue
of the Courier is a language map of
the world. It is constructed on tradi¬
tional lines: that is, it shows languages
by "families". This is a convenience to
linguists but it should not lead ordinary
people astray. Thus the English-speak¬
ing person who imagines it should be
easy to learn Dutch or Danish, because
they also are "Germanic" languages, may
be disappointed. Languages, like mem¬
bers of human families, have a habit of
drifting away from one another.
It is this instable or dynamic charac¬
teristic of languages, coupled with the
fact that languages are often the play¬
things of political and economic forces,
which now favour and now retard their
expansion, that makes a languages map
and the general language situation so
changeable. The picture today is not at
all what it was even a generation ago.
A generation hence it will probably be
quite different again. To grasp this fact
one has only to survey the continents
briefly one by one.
Europe makes a good starting-point for
such a survey, because in Europe the
number of official national languages has
just about doubled in the space of a ge¬
neration. This is due to a number of
causes. When the Russian and Austro-
Hungarian empires collapsed as a result
of the First World War they were suc¬
ceeded by a number of smaller sovereign
units or by new regimes that took a more
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
FROM EGYPTIAN PICTURE-
WRITING TO A MODERN
FORM OF HIEROGLYPHICS
liberal view of the aspirations of lin¬
guistic minorities. Languages like
Slovene, Slovak, Czech, Lithuanian, Let¬
tish, Esthonian, White Russian and
Ukranian ceased being just picturesque
survivals, achieved full national or
regional status became official languages
of instruction in the schools.
In Western Europe, not all at once, but
certainly since the Second World War,
there has also developed an increasingly
liberal attitude towards the languages of
minority groups. People who now want
to talk Frisian or Breton or Basque, and
to have their children learn these lan¬
guages, are not in most countries any
longer looked on as anti-national agi¬
tators. Governments now go out of
their way to give such language groups
an equitable status in the community and
make reasonable linguistic concessions
to them. Even . Switzerland, already
saddled with the problem of three
national languages, judged it advisable
a few years ago to admit a fourth lan¬
guage Romansh, on a sort of junior
partnership basis.
Totting up the balance sheet for Eu¬
rope, the debit side shows a great
increase in the actual number of official
languages, the credit side a decided im¬
provement in the attitude towards mino¬
rity languages. This may be more
important than it seems, for nations, like
individuals, cannot hope to assess the
language problem sensibly unless they
divest themselves of prejudice.
A somewhat similar process has been
going on in the Americas. Ostensibly
the language pattern is simple with the
original European colonizing nations
providing either English, French, Portu¬
guese or Spanish (with Danish in Green¬
land and Dutch in Surinam and the West
Indies) as the official language or lan¬
guages for every one of the 22 countries
between Baffin Land and the Antarctic.
But a closer look reveals a rather more
complex weave. Mass immigration has
helped to complicate matters, especially
nowadays when the doctrine of the
Melting Pot with its insistence on lin¬
guistic and cultural uniformity is
nowhere applied as strictly and as illi¬
berally as previously.
When we talk of language we usually mean Its
spoken form, but the term can also be applied
to any conventional signalling system. We have
flag language or code, the language of road signals,
deaf and dumb language and written language.
Canada is a good example of the lan¬
guage patterns produced by immigration.
When Louis XV lost New France, 60,000
French-speaking Canadians changed
their allegiance. Their descendents
now constitute a durable linguistic block
of three and a half millions. But there
are many other second languages in Ca¬
nada besides English or French. A
school-boy in Winnipeg may study Ice¬
landic as his first foreign language, while
a farmer in Cape Breton may tune in to
broadcasts in his ancestral Gaelic.
Newspapers and books are published in
Bas-reliet of the Giotto Tower, Florence, symbol¬
izing language, and logic. (Photo Brogi-Viollet).
Ukranian and Finnish, in Polish and
Italian and thousands speak these lan¬
guages in their homes and pass them on
to their children.
In the United States the extension oí
the teaching of Spanish in the elemen¬
tary schools of the South Western States,
of French in those of Louisiana, and the
opportunity now given in many big city
schools of learning Hebrew or Polish
shows, among many other examples, that
a similar Une is being followed. No race
One form that has come down to us from the past
Is the ancient Egyptian picture-writing (above).
A modern version of this is the road signalling
system, but this, as Steinberg, the American car¬
toonist, has shown in drawings (right) can be
has been more affected by this liber¬
alizing trend than the American Indian.
It is now at last realized that language is
a vital and inseparable part of the cul¬
tural fabric and that the Indian who
has not been detribalized should not be
deprived of his language.
This knowledge has had even more
important consequences in Mexico and in
Central and South America where the
populations speaking pre-Columbian
mother tongues can be counted in mil¬
lions rather than in hundreds of
thousands. The former country,- after
centuries of unsuccessful efforts to turn
Nahuas, Tarascans and Mayans into
monolingual Spanish speakers, has set up
most enlightened programmes for tack¬
ling the problem of illiteracy in the native
language 'first, leaving instruction in the
national language to a subsequent stage.
Further south still, an increasingly pro¬
gressive language policy bids fair to bring
back into useful circulation languages
such as Quechua and Aymarâ.
A few significant dates, grouped closely
together, serve to set the pattern for Asia.
The independence of the Philippines was
proclaimed in 1946, of Burma, Ceylon,
India and Pakistan in 1947, of Israel in
1948, of Indonesia in 1949, Cambodia,
Laos and Viet-Nam have joined the pro¬
cession subsequently. These political
events have inevitably meant greatly
enhanced status for Burmese and for
Hebrew, for Singhalese and Tamil, for"
Bahasa and Tagolog, for Cambodian,
Laotian and Vietnamese, for Urdu and
its close cousin Hindi, to say nothing of
the fourteen officially recognized regional
languages of the new Republic of India
and all the regional languages of the
other nations which have recently
attained or recovered their independence.
In the meantime, north of the Hima¬
layas, great progress seems to have been
made in endowing the complex of lan¬
guages in Central and Northern Asia
with alphabets and also with new dignity
and status. What is bewildering in the
new Asia linguistically is that it seems to
consist more and more of a series of
Switzerlands on a gigantic scale.
Let us take the *ase of a boy or girl
just starting school somewhere in Bom-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER -N» 1-1954
T'V IRä/B
just about as baffling as the ancient Egyptian
variety. However, motoring abroad is becoming less
harassing for " Mr Smith" since many member
states of the United Nations have adopted a
simplified and standardized system of road signs.
bay State. The case is typical enough
of many other states both in and outside
India. The pupil will at home probably
speak either Gujerati or Marathi. His
or her first task will be to learn the other
state language, whichever it may be,
going on then to Hindi, the new federal
- language, and only after that tackling
one of the world link-languages.
It may seem a desperate situation but
no continent is attacking its language
problems with greater vigour. Teachers
are recruited in Syria to teach Arabic as
a living link-language to the Bengali-
speakers of East Pakistan; chairs of
Chinese are endowed in the great univer¬
sities of India; Indonesia sends future
teachers of English to study this world
language in Australia its nearest
English-speaking neighbour.
Though geographically far removed
from one another, Africa and Oceania
present similar patterns of linguistic di¬
versity and these patterns seem to be
shifting and changing in much the same
way. The dominant tongues, for official,
and generally for educational purposes as
well, are still the languages of the Euro¬
pean countries that hold political .autho¬
rity. ' More and more, however, the
tendency to use the local vernacular, at
least in primary education, is spreading.
But in areas where languages change
completely almost from village to village,
this otherwise sensible course cannot be
followed and in such cases the teaching
of the European language must be re¬
garded as the only alternative.
Another way round the obstacle is to
use a lingua franca, and these have a
considerable vogue in both Africa and
Oceania. Nationalism, particularly local
nationalism, is a factor that must be
reckoned with here too; it has a charac¬
teristically stubborn way of preventing
all-wise authorities from imposing one
dialect in preference to others and thus
"simplifying the language problem in the
interest of the native".
What the Immediate future holds
for these areas must depend in a
large measure on political developments
during the next quarter century, and a
(Continued on page 32)
ir^j ZZOiBAAVTUKQ
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
OLD LANGUAGES FIND NEW JOBS
Asian and Middle East States remould their ancient tongues
Our planet, as we have seen from
the previous article, is a veritable
jigsaw puzzle when it comes to
languages, with the pieces shifting and
moving about, growing smaller or larger
' or splitting off into new bits with the
passing of time. In Asia and the Middle
East the puzzle is particularly "jigged".
This -is not at all surprising when we
remember that Asia is the most dense¬
ly populated area of the globe, and
that a huge portion of it South and
Southeast Asia is still' more thickly
populated than Asia as a whole.
Within the past ten years, the jigsaw
language pattern of Asia has been made
even more complicated by a new factor :
a great upsurge of nationalism similar
to the one which swept through Europe
in the 19th century upsetting the lan¬
guage pattern that has been rolling
across Asia and producing major chan¬
ges in the world language map.
The Philippines, Burma, Pakistan,
India, Ceylon, Indonesia and Israel are
new-born States, and all of them have
adopted new official national languages.
Their educational problems are now very
closely linked with linguistic problems.
In most of these countries, the setting
up of the national language has meant
ousting European languages as the offi¬
cial idiom or relegating them to a secon¬
dary position. But the truth is that for
some time to come these new languages
will be just as foreign if not more so
to many inhabitants as the European
ones were.
As one Filipino linguist has pointed
out, Tagalog is much less widely spoken
and read in the Philippines than
English, and is a foreign language to
over 70 per cent of the Filipino people.
For the Bengali speaker of East Pakis¬
tan, Urdu is also a new language which
he will now have to learn.
India, where some 100 different lan¬
guages are spoken, has chosen Hindi as
its official federal language. But at the
same time others are recognized as offi¬
cial regional languages. For all official
business and for education, English
the official language during British rule
is being kept for 15 years so that the
change to Hindi may take place gra¬
dually. For the other 86 tongues, the
policy is to start school teaching using
the mother tongue of the child who at
the same time must learn his regional
language as well as Hindi and English.
If you were born on one of the thou¬
sands of- islands which make up the .
Indonesian Archipelago at the extreme
southeast tip of Asia, your mother ton¬
gue would be one of 200 languages and
dialects spoken by 80 million fellow
Indonesians. Most people though speak
one of the four main languages : Java¬
nese (40 million), Sundanese (12 mil¬
lion), Madurese (6 million), or Malay
(4 millions).
Of these "big four?' it was Malay-
spoken by the smallest number of peo¬
ple which, curiously enough, was cho¬
sen as the official national language
when the new Republic was born in
1949.
In reality, Malay is much more impor¬
tant than the figures would indicate,
since they apply only to native-born
speakers. Many people all over the Indo¬
nesian archipelago and elsewhere in
Southeast Asia can speak a form of
pidgin Malay. In fact as early as the
16th century, when European sailors first
landed on Indonesian shores, Malay was
already being used as a trade lingua
franca between the islanders. It was
not until the turn of the 19th century
that Dutch the official language of the
Netherlands Indies Government began
to replace it.
In 1930, agitation to make Malay the
common unifying language of all Indo-
Three quarters of the 80 million people living
in the Indonesian Archipelago speak one of four
main languages: Javanese, Sundanese, Madurese,
and Malay. Malay, spoken by the smallest of these
four groups, and renamed "Bahasa Indonesia" is
now the official language of the Indonesian Repu¬
blic. Today, most Indonesians, young and old
alike, are therefore having to set to work and
study their new national tongue.
nesia was strongly felt when a meeting
of all-Indonesia youth organizations
pledged support for "one nation, one
people and one language" and changed
the name "Malay language" to "Indo-
.nesian language" (Bahasa Indonesia).
The Japanese spurred interest in
Bahasa during their Invasion of the
Islands in the second World War by
banning Dutch and at first using Baha¬
sa to communicate with the people.
Schoolteachers and all government offi¬
cials had to study and use it as well.
As more and more people learned to
speak it freely the language flourished
and its vocabulary grew. By the end of
the war it had attained national stature
and with independence national adop¬
tion.
Yet to most Indonesians even today,
Bahasa remains to some extent a foreign
language or at least so different from
their mother tongue that they must
study the language to master it.
As one Indonesian linguist recently
asked, "What should be the position and
function of the Javanese, Sundanese and
Madurese languages in Indonesian cul¬
tural life in the future? Can a language
like Javanese bearing a rich literary
tradition simply disappear, or shall we
have in the future a rivalry for sup¬
remacy between the different Indone¬
sian languages ?"
It doesn't seem so. The Parliament
has a Javanese majority, the President
and the Prime Minister are both . of
Javanese origin, yet there is no move¬
ment in the Javanese-speaking coun¬
tries to abandon Bahasa as the national
tongue. That a people of over 40 million
should voluntarily accept the language
of a minority as the vehicle of Its politi¬
cal economic and cultural life is in¬
deed a remarkable phenomenon of our
present century.
Several thousand miles away, at the
far western tip of Asia, the new State
of Israel presents a completely different
linguistic problem : that of a dead lan¬
guage suddenly brought back to life and
rejuvenated to serve the needs of a
modern world. For a thousand years
ancient Hebrew had ceased to be a living
language. It existed only in holy books
and in prayers. Its resurrection and
modernization presented an enormous
problem.
Much of this work was done between
the two World Wars by pioneer settlers
who came to Palestine and determined
to use Hebrew as their everyday tongue.
Within a generation It had changed
from an archaic bookish idiom, rhetor¬
ical and involved in style, into a pre¬
cise, realistic modern language.
With the birth of Israel In 1948, the
government proclaimed Hebrew as the
state language. The year marked the
start of an amazing series of mass immi¬
grations. Jewish people came from
every corner of the world bringing with
them scores of different languages and
dialects. The great problem was and
still is teaching them the new national
language. This is no academic goal ; it
is a practical necessity.
The chief burden falls on the Hebrew
University of Jerusalem which sends tea¬
chers out to schools in villages and rural
settlements, In debarkation camps and
hostels. At each of these there are
classes for children during the day, and
night classes for adults. Manual wor¬
kers receive courses aimed at providing
a rudimentary knowledge of Hebrew to
permit immigrants to converse as quickly
as possible with their Hebrew-speaking
neighbours.
It would be idle to pretend that Immi¬
grants are easily acquiring even a rudi¬
mentary knowledge of the new lan¬
guage. On the contrary, it is very diffi¬
cult for many of them. Uprooted from
their environment, often being trained
In new jobs and trades, confused and
bewildereB by new surroundings, by the
housing shortage and unstable economic
conditions, many immigrants find it hard
to concentrate on learning the simplest
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Hebrew. The illiterate finds reading
especially difficult.
The effect on the school system of
teaching children speaking many differ¬
ent tongues is shown in an official
Israeli report. "It is practically impos¬
sible", it says, "to keep to the curricu¬
lum in its entirety in the new (primary)
schools. Most of the first years are dedi¬
cated to the teaching of the national
language. The children differ greatly :
those from Iraq are not the same as
those coming from Yugoslavia and Ru¬
mania. The teacher must therefore
adapt himself individually to every one
of these small groups of children coming
from all parts of the world. Only after
several years of adaptation have elapsed,
can there be any real possibility of
following the curriculum, by which time
the child has reached the age-limit of
compulsory education and leaves school
to go to work."
Politically, Israel and the Arab-speak¬
ing countries may not be on the friend¬
liest terms, but linguistically they are
brothers under the skin, and both offer
remarkable examples of how a classical
language can be revitalized to meet the
needs of the modern world. Among the
peoples of ancient civilization who, from
the Pacific to the Mediterranean now
face new linguistic problems, it is those
of the Arab world who have probably had
the longest experience in adapting their
language to the impact of the West.
Theirs is the story of a community
which, after enjoying a high standard
of culture, went through a period of
political, economic and cultural decline.
Arab civilization almost died when
Baghdad fell to the Tartar invaders in
1258 but it was saved by a handful of
scholars who fled to the Nile Valley.
It flourished again until the 16th cen¬
tury when the Turks invaded Egypt and
made Turkish the official language.
Arabic then deteriorated and lost its
vigour. Only a part remained in use :
the rest stayed in the "cold storage" of
old books and records.
The linguistic renaissance of Arabic
really began, interestingly enough, when
Napoleon landed in Egypt in 1798. He
brought with him many scientists and
scholars interested in the people, their'
language and their past. He founded
the Institut d'Egypte and opened the
door to cultural contacts between Egypt
and Europe. The French stayed in Egypt
only three years but their influence was
enormous and they opened the minds of
the people to the possibility of a new
and fascinating world.
As a result, Egypt took the lead in
modernizing Arabic. Western culture
came to Syria at a later date and to the
other Arab countries of the East much
later still.
Following Napoleon's departure, a new
governor, Mohammad Ali, instituted new
courses in medicine, pharmacy and the
sciences. He brought in foreign instruc¬
tors from France and Italy and sent
Egyptian missions to Europe. The diffi¬
culties of rendering the new modern
knowledge into Arabic were plentiful.
Here is an amusing example cited by
Dr. Ahmed Zaki of the Fuad I National
Research Council in Cairo :
"The foreign instructors could not
speak Arabic, and the Egyptians .-could
not speak either French or Italian, so
Mohammad Ali resorted to the help of
a middleman who stood between pro¬
fessor and students to translate. These
were mostly men who understood lan¬
guages but no science, so the system had
to be supplemented by the production of
Arabic books on the subjects taught.
This necessitated the co-operation of
four different people.
"First was the author who was usually
a European scientist. Then came a
translator whose knowledge of the
foreign language was more adequate
than his Arabic. Then came a scholar
whose strong point was Arabic. Finally
there was a man who went over the
proofs and who also had something to
do with the text."
To put an end to such a tortuous
system. Mohammad Ali set up a School
of Languages for Egyptian students, and
in 1821 created a government printing
press.
The creation of the first modern Egyp¬
tian university in 1908 (now.Fuad I Uni¬
versity) marked another important step
in the renovation of Arabic, but the lan¬
guage received its strongest impetus
following the first World War. In
schools and universities, in government
offices, in the press in fact in every
branch of activity in contact with modern
ideas and the West with its deluge of
new words, efforts were made to pro¬
duce Arabic equivalents. But most of
these were individual solutions and some
kind of co-ordinating body was felt
necessary.
In 1932 the Arabic Language Royal
Academy was founded with Egyptian
and other Arab state members. Its pur¬
pose was to create or standardize tech¬
nical and scientific terminology and
generally to modernize Arabic. Since
then it has begun work on a scientific
dictionary and already added over
10,000 scientific and technical words to
the language. It has laid the basis for
an etymological dictionary, discussed
UNESCO COURIER -N» 1-1954
simplification of grammar and spelling
but rejected a proposal to substitute
Latin characters for the Arabic alphabet
after much heated discussion.
However, because of the Academy's
heavy concentration on. scientific termi¬
nology, terms of a general nature have
tended to be neglected. Newspapers,
periodicals and the public must shift for
themselves and this has often led to the
creation of a score of words for one
modern expression. A jet plane, for
example is sometimes called "naffatha",
from a verb meaning "to spit out with
blowing", and sometimes "nafouria"
meaning "fountain-like".
Certain Arabic linguists fear the splin¬
tering effect that this may have on the
language in view of the wide gap that
already exists between the multitude of
colloquial forms of Arabic spoken by the
masses (with its dialects varying consi¬
derably from one country to the next)
and the written language. The written
form, classical Arabic, is closer to the
language of the Koran. There is a
general movement today to bridge the
gap between the two by improving the
classic form so as to make it the general
medium of Instruction at all school
levels.
This point is made by Dr. Zaki, writ¬
ing in the Unesco study "Vernacular
Languages in Education". "Many words
exist in colloquial Arabic", he says,
"which sound perfect to the Arabic ear
but which are not mentioned, in the
classical dictionaries. Writers are there¬
fore reluctant to use them. But words
like these might well be adopted and
used freely in writing, especially where
there is no Arabic equivalent for them."
Language problems are bound closely to educational ones in many recently independent Asian countries
which have introduced new national languages. A child starting school in Bombay Province, India,
will probably speak Gujerati or Marathi at home. At school he must begin by learning the other of these
two regional languages and then go on to learn Hindi, the official federal language. Only then will he
begin to tackle one of the world link languages.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
I SPEAK
ENGLISH
SNAKE SNAKE
FISH FISH/
The trials and tribulations- of a
language student in Thailand
by Manich Jumsai
According to a Thai language teacher, books for children learning a foreign language should not contain
stories and illustrations of the foreign country only, since these may not always be comprehensible to
youngsters in far-off lands. They should instead compare the life and customs of the foreign land
with the children's own environment. Here is a typical river scene of the interior of Thailand taken
from a Unesco film""World without End".
I WAS born in a. typical provincial
. village in Thailand far from modern
civilization. From my early child¬
hood I was eager to learn English and .
dreamt of strange lands where lived
those funny white-faced people (of whom
we sometimes heard) with blond hair,
who spoke in a strange tongue and had
strange customs... . I had never met any
one of these people. Why should I, when
even my provincial teacher had never
seen one of them, and our grim-looking,
strict headmaster, most learned of the
village people, did not know them?
One day, my curiosity getting the better
of me, I asked my master, and he in turn
asked the headmaster, the name of the
capital city of these strange white people
who spoke the foreign language we now
had to learn in all secondary schools,
even in the remotest village. But neither
of them could give me an answer. Such
were the conditions in Thailand when I
started to learn English forty years ago.
Of what use to us then were the direct
method theories? My teacher did not
speak English, he only read and trans¬
lated words from the blackboard, together
with their meanings, so that we could
learn them by heart. At the next English
-lesson we had to tell him the meanings
of the various words. As to writing, the
teacher would avoid it very carefully so
that, during my childhood, I did not have
much chance of writing anything other
than translations of sentences from
English into Thai or Thai into English,
usually from books. There was no
question of free translations being made.
Even when translating from books, an
English-Thai dictionary had to be used.
When we encountered a peculiar word or
grammatical construction, we had to use
it as instructed by our teacher. If we
asked why it should be used in that way,
we were told that that was the strange
English way of saying it.
As for the meaning of words, there was
no distinction in our minds between
apples, pears, peaches, cherries, grapes,
strawberries or raspberries, however large
or small, whatever their colour, whether
grown on vines or on trees. All we knew
was that they were "a kind of fruit"; the
teacher said so. We had never seen
them; and neither had the teacher. They
were English fruits which could not be
grown in a hot country like Thailand.
They were strange fruits which puzzled
our minds and our imaginations.
As to trees, flowers, animals, insects,
etc., while learning English at school I
had stored away in my mind many
strange names for each of them, but they -
were all the same to me-a kind of tree,
a kind of flower, a kind of animal, which
the English people had but we did. not
have. At last I grew impatient, and one
day I asked my teacher, the English
names for some of our local fruits,
flowers, trees and foodstuffs. Of course,
he could not tell me, and he looked
somewhat surprised that I should ask
such a silly question. Was I becoming
Insubordinate? Such things did not exist
in English books, nor in English! Then
I argued: "Supposing one of these days I
meet an Englishman, for I would like to
meet one, then I shall ask him many
things about his country. I .will take
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N" , 1 - 1954
mm Kpiiiatiinai 1 MlM
1 Ë" V
1
«É
ImmW * ^m\ mmr
H \ t W
4 C vi^LXW
/ 1
j M ip
English is the most popular foreign language taught ¡n Thailand today. Then come French,- Chinese and German. Certain private schools teach English
In the first four primary classes at the same time as Thai. But teachers are often bewildered when some beginners' textbooks prefer unusual words to the
more common equivalents, such as "jumbo" for "elephant", "nanny" for"goat", "cot"for "bed", "pup" for "dog", and "Brer Rabbit" for "rabbit" (U.N. Photos).
him round to see things. I will show him
the fruits we have (Noi-na, _ Lam-yai,
Chompoo, Mafuang) and ask him to taste
some of them. But what shall I call
them?" "Oh, curious child, what else
. would they be for these Europeans but a
kind of fruit?"
I would therefore repudiate a list of
basic words, if it contained words like
"bread", "apple", etc., instead of words
appropriate to the food grown in the
country where English was being taught.
I consider that such a list should contain
words which have a real meaning for the
child because he sees and uses the
articles described in his everyday life.
When it comes to English spelling and
pronunciation, we people of Thailand find
that the words are never pronounced the -
way they are spelt. It is of no use to
learn any rules, but only exceptions.
'Ou', for instance, is usually pronounced -
as in 'cloud', but in 'through' it is 'oo' in
it is 'oh'; and in 'tough', it is
'uf. Then comes a new invention: the
international phonetic script. This is a ^
device whereby we can see how the
various peculiar English words are
pronounced; but then we are introduced
to new signs and symbols. This, again, is .
like learning a new language. Is not
English difficult e"nough that we must
now read a new language?
Even this phonetic system is not a
satisfactory solution .to our problem.
Whatever signs and symbols are invented
for us, we do not pronounce them in that
way since our own language is so
different. We don't sound the endings
of our words as do the English, we don't
twist and roll our tongue to sound an T,
or an 'r', we do not make sounds through
our teeth like 'th', We do not have hissing
sounds like 's' and 'ss'. These are only
English idiosyncracies to make things
harder than they look.
After a certain time, we go back to the -
ordinary English spelling, but what is the
point when words are not all spelt in the
same way? Our eyes see different words
on paper, but our minds cannot identify
them as being the same. We have to
learn over again the quaint spelling and
irregular pronunciation. Words are not
written the way they are pronounced, as
is done in the international phonetic
script. What is the use of struggling to
learn all these quaint symbols if they are
not going to he used? Also, there are
exceptions and unusual things in the in¬
ternational phonetic script itself.
Then there are the various ways of
expressing oneself. The Thai and
English languages are fundamentally
different, having absolutely nothing in
common. Why should they? When all
is said and done, the English and Thai
peoples had never met until recently.
They are not descended from a common
stock with ancestors common to both
races. While the original Thai people
were still living in the valley of the
Yellow River, in brick buildings, and with
a fairly advanced civilization, the British
were living in prehistoric times; Britons
still wore leaves and animal skins and
dwelt in the forests. The two peoples
lived in worlds far apart, each developing
their own language to suit their different
needs without ever having , the op¬
portunity to discuss what they should say
for certain things, or how they should
express certain feelings or ideas.
Therefore, a Thai student starting to
learn English would say: "I speak English
snake snake fish fish." This does not
mean anything to an Englishman, but it
means everything to the Thai student.
When a person knows only a few odd
words of a language, such as snake or
fish, and has to use those same words all
the time because he knows no other, it is
obvious to a Thai mind that he really
knows very little of that language. On
the other hand, when he knows so much
of the language that the words flow from
his mouth without hesitation, like water
flowing from a spout, he will say: "I
speak English like water."' He un¬
derstands this clearly, although it will
not be understood by an Englishman.
Thai ways, sentiments, feelings and
understanding are not the same as those
of English people, and an Englishman
must not be led astray by thinking that
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
i "5*.
General view of Bangkok klongs (canals) showing floating fruit market (mahanark) and vegetable and
pottery markets. Fruits in the tropical land of Thailand are totally different from European or American
fruits. To Thai children learning English, the words apples, peaches, strawberries or pears convey no
real image. They are merely "a kind of fruit". (U.N. Photo.)
whatever he says is simple, straight¬
forward and therefore easily understood
by a Thai. For instance, look at these
phrases which are perfectly obvious and
clear to a Thai:
I have ox two body.
He woman have son ox two body.
Why should one say: -" "I have two
oxen"; "she has two young oxen", etc.?
Why should the language be made more
difficult by using has on one occasion and
have on another? Why should the_words
be changed to plural when singular can
mean the same object. Why should one
use a new word "she", when one can say
"a female he" or "he woman"? Why
should one say "young oxen" when they
are really "sons or daughters of oxen",
and so on?
There are two instances when a Thai
would say "yes" and an Englishman
"no", and yet both expressions have the
same meaning. Here are some typical
comparisons:
Englishman
Q. Have you never been to England?
A. No. (I have never been.)
Q. Good morning, John, how are you?
Or Fine Weather, isn't it?
Thai
Q. Have you never been to England?
A. Yes. (The fact that I have never
been there is "yes" in this case.)
Q. May you be (well, where have you
been.
In the opinion of a Thai, it is ridiculous
or even hypocritical to say "Good
morning" when it is actually cloudy and
cold, and therefore a "bad morning".
The English are great inventors; they
make grammatical rules and then start
to evade them by making exceptions and
creating more and more language
difficulties. The Thai language, on the
other hand, has no tenses, no -feminine
nouns, no comparative and superlative
adjectives and adverbs, no plurals. It is
quite straightforward. English grammar
is perhaps one of the most difficult in the
world to learn, owing to the number of
tenses and irregular verbs. Compare
these expressions:
English
He goes to school.
He is going to school.
He went to school yesterday.
He has already been to school this
morning.
' He went to school.
He did not go to school.
That
He go school.
He active go school.
He go school yesterday.
He go school already morning this..
He go school finished.
He ho go school finished.
As far as Thailand is concerned, I do
not know of a single book which has been
written by any of the eminent exponents
of a number of accepted methods of
teaching -English which would be per¬
fectly satisfactory and thoroughly un¬
derstood by the pupils. English is made
infinitely more difficult by the fact that
the books are written about things which
the indigenous child has never seen or
heard of during the whole of his short
life. .
During the seventeen years I worked
for the Ministry of Education in Bangkok,
I was fed profusely with samples of
various English reading series from
various English publishers, who pressed
me to prescribe their series for use in
Thai schools. Despite the fact that some
of them were beautifully printed and
illustrated they were not. ideally suited
for the teaching of English in Thailand.
Attractive illustrations are not the main
need of an English reader for a foreign
country; the contents of the book are
much more important.
. A Thai child starts to learn English at
the age of 11 plus, by which time his mind
is fully developed. He is a big boy or a
young man no longer a child. He has
a thirst for true stories, for adventure,
for culture, for his own social inheritance
something which is no longer childish,
-but which will fill his mind with future
ambitions, aspirations, adventures and
heroism. He is not a fool who can be
easily led to believe things which are
untrue, such as fairy tales, spirits, goblins
that inhabit the forests, and animals that
talk. English primers . written for
children of lower age level are therefore
not suitable for him. -
The books are full of childish things,
simple (not to say. foolish or stupid)
beliefs, and always contain the famous
Grimm and Hans Andersen fairy tales, or
stories taken from the Arabian Nights.
What is more important, they contain
| 'x~''Î:'a^ **J&JÊSËÈËi
r W
%y *$ "«t¿¿>.
i
; !
P* * vWfe'.
-JÊL3m\ mf.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER -N" 1-1954
strange words .which are never used by
adults and which cannot be found in
ordinary dictionaries, thus making it
more difficult for -the average Thai
teacher to understand and translate, his
method being to translate everything.
Instead of "'Bear", the books use "Teddy
Bear", "Brer Rabbit" for "rabbit", "Jum¬
bo" for "elephant", "Nanny *' for "goat",
"cot" for "bed", "pup" for "dog". Then
there are all the terms of endearment
which an English mother uses when
speaking to her baby.
Such things are outside the ordinary
English vocabulary. Also, children in .
England start to learn by using words
which are orthographically and phoneti¬
cally simple and not too long. So, in¬
stead of the usual word "'sleep", they use
"'nap", and in order to keep to simple
monosyllabic words they use the most
extraordinary words and stories. And a
Thai boy of 11 plus has to learn this
nonsense.
When writing primers for children of
11 plus, the mentality, curiosity, previous
knowledge and experience, as well as the
understanding of the child should be
taken Into account. Special books should
be written for children of this age in
order to make them feel that English is
not so difficult, confusing or nonsensical,
books which will help them to master the
simple normal language form.
Various primers have been' written to
cope with different factors, from the
phonetic and from the orthographic
angle, from the monosyllabic word list,
from the nursery word list, from the first
basic word list and so on, but none has
dealt with the difficulties of grammar.
English grammar and construction are
beyond the grasp of children whose
mother tongue is Thai. So many differ¬
ences and_ distinctions have to be
accounted for. Grammar should be
carefully analysed and graded, and
explanations introduced step by step as
these points occur in new phrases and
sentences. If there is a list of basic
words in English, there should be also a
list of basic grammatical points.
Those who attempt to improve the
teaching of English in Thailand should
make a complete analysis of the Thai and
English languages to see where lie the
parities, similarities and discrepancies in
both languages. When this has been
done they will then be able to understand
the mind of the child who is struggling
to understand a foreign language like
English. So far, no such analysis has
been made.
In many other countries, children
learning English as a foreign language .
often use textbooks written by English
people or by people whose mother tongue
is English,-who take for granted, as being
understood, so many of the small, trivial
details which are - confusing to a child
brought up in surroundings entirely
different from those of an English-
speaking person.
- In Thailand, for example, there are dif¬
ferent contentions about this. One per¬
son wants the books to be written with
an English background, while another
prefers a Thai background with, names,
objects and stories all derived from Thai¬
land. I think that it would be an ideal
I SPEAK ENGLISH
SNAKE SNAKE FISH FISH '
way to write the first book or two using
the boys' own environment as a back¬
ground, and discussing the things he
knows and understands. Then as his
vocabulary grows, English subjects could
be introduced English boys and girls,
their homes and customs, and the things
the student would see and do if he were
to visit England. Textbooks must show
comparisons between the things that
happen in Great Britain and Thailand;
that is to say, the first textbook should
cover the experiences that the student
encounters all the time in his own coun¬
try and then pass on to comparative
ones in England.
I feel that in order to understand the
many local difficulties encountered both
in teaching and learning English as a
foreign language, one must be a native
of the country, a person who knew no
English for the first few years of his life,
who, when he did start to learn it, had
to struggle through the various diffi¬
culties of the language until he had
mastered it. Only a person who has
passed through this experience himself
can comprehend the difficulties encount¬
ered by a child of his own nationality
who is learning to speak a foreign lan¬
guage 'and grasp what the child is
thinking of when he interprets certain
things in a certain way.
Notwithstanding the theories put for¬
ward by various eminent specialists of
modern languages, it is my firm opinion
that the series of books on this subject
will not be complete until consideration
has been given to the complete cycle of
effective development of the indigenous
child's mind.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE HORSE COMES BEFORE THE CART
IN LANGUAGE TEACHING
\
t
* 4
Correct pronunciation must be learned from the start, foreign language experts today declare. Pupils must be told how to set about making the correct
sounds. Later on is too late and makes it almost impossible to correct faulty speech habits. Inset shows typical positions of mouth in pronouncing French
vowels, A, E, I, O, OU. Photo shows position for the sound EU.
Like every other branch of human
activity, modern language teaching
has its sages and its charlatans, its
clamour of rival factions, its current
fashions and its awful heresies. Anybody
who sets out to explore this jungle would
be well advised to tread cautiously.
But at least there are consolations in
such a voyage of discovery... Nobody can
complete it without coming away with
the conviction that here, as in so many
other fields of human endeavour, man is
gaining the upper hand over the general
cussedness of nature.
We really do have a clearer idea in 1954
of how to go about teaching a living lan¬
guage for the common purposes of gene¬
ral enlightenment or general understand¬
ing than we did in 1940. The thirties
were a decade of great progress too, and
if you look back to the turn of the cen¬
tury, and the great controversies that
surrounded the birth of the Direct
Method, you can see how far we have
really come.
There are chastening factors too, of
course. It is a little disconcerting to be
reminded that Renaissance scholars ear¬
nestly recommended some of our most
up-to-date language-teaching methods
three and four centuries ago. Writing
in 1532, a Sicilian, Lucace Di Marinis,
spoke out strongly against over-emphasis
on grammar and urged that what little
grammar instruction was necessary be
taught inductively. Comenius, the
Czech, writing a century later, showed
that he knew more than a little about
vocabulary selection and structure
grading. Montaigne and Luther and
Locke had other enlightened notions on
this general subject.
' Language teaching in that age meant,
of course, teaching Latin, which was
still the living common tongue of scien¬
tists and educated persons generally. It
was a fearful and almost a fatal han¬
dicap for modern language teaching that,
when it did begin to come into its own,
during the second half of the nineteenth
century, it was as a rather despised poor
relation to Latin teaching and to a Latin
now quite thoroughly dead and become
a vested interest.
This had many odd consequences.
Where Latin was well taught, as it still
was in many places, students would
acquire proficiency in reading and writ¬
ing the language. Modern language
teachers were .therefore expected to
impart the same skills and no others,
which was putting the cart before the
horse with a vengeance. As late as 1893,
an eminent educator who occupied the
chair at a meeting of the National Edu¬
cation Association of the United States
exploded with the statement: "'I do not
believe, first and last, that we have
anything to do with the speaking or
conversational use of the modern lan¬
guages in the secondary school. And
the sooner the heresy is banished from
the secondary school the clearer the air
will be." At the time, he undoubtedly
voiced the opinion of the majority.
So for decades the modern language
teacher had to do what the Latin teacher
thought he was doing: sharpen the
intellect, broaden the mind, instill a
sounder knowledge of the mother tongue,
etc. This was an educational pro¬
cess that was all hypothetical by-pro¬
ducts with no end-product, practical or
otherwise.
Then at last came the age of the heroes
who arose in many countries to deliver
the damsel in distress: GouLn in France,
Viëtor in Germany, Alge in Switzerland,
Melon in Belgium, Nystrom in Finland,
Jespersen in Denmark and Sweet, the
Englishman, who was the model for
Henry Higgins the phoenetician in
Shaw's Pygmalion. There was now the
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
beginning of a real theoretical basis to
modern language teaching. The Natu¬
ral or Direct Method flourished, to be-
tolerated'in some school- systems, to be
imposed in others. Like all good things
it suffered at the hands of its more dog¬
matic advocates, but on balance it was
undoubtedly "a good thing" and, at the
hand of qualified teachers, brought life
and reality into many language class¬
rooms.
Since those days, many different devel¬
opments, taking place in many different
parts of the world, have broadened and
refined the techniques available to the
profession. They are not listed here in
any order of importance or even chrono¬
logically ; they all leadTup to the present-
day picture.
It was in the twenties and thirties that
the educational psychologists started to
play a useful part. They have taught
us a good deal already about what sort
of a learning process language-learning
is. They have still, among other things,
to tell us more definitely about the real
as opposed to the theoretical effects of
bilingualism and about the right age for
a child to start learning his first foreign
language, as well as devising tests which
will really measure more than the merely
mechanical aspects of language learning.
Then, in the thirties, much progress
was made by a group of well-trained and
highly intelligent teachers of English,
working in South Asia and in the Far
East. It was an accident that this was
the language they taught. They might
have come from other countries and have
gone out to teach any one of the world's
great link-languages Arabic or Chinese,
or French, or Russian, or Spanish, just as
well as English. The work of French,
Faucett, Gatenby, Palmer, West and
others of that generation is, of course, in
a sense, primarily of interest to teachers
of English, but in a wider and more signi¬
ficant sense it concerns teachers of any
living language.
These teachers learned - primarily to -
appreciate the difficulties which Asians
encounter when they are trying to master
a western world language, be it English
or any other language. They learned
what the essentials of a language are and
how to present those essentials econo¬
mically and attractively. The Basic
English movement and the interest in
simplified texts both owed something if
not everything to the experience these
teachers gained.
Over on the other side of the world; in
Nprth America, linguists who had been
working on Eskimo and Amerindian lan¬
guages were developing new theories of
the nature of language, which were soon
to be expressed by Bloomfleld, Trager,
Nida, arid others. It was their opinion
that the cardinal error of the past had
been to approach language philosophi¬
cally instead of scientifically and to make
statements about the form in terms of
the meaning, instead of doing it the
other way round. Exponents of this new
view passed on from rare languages to
the better known ones and ultimately
devised theories of their own about how
languages should be taught. It was at
about this time too that there occurred
what might be described as the Discovery
of the Phoneme (the sound unit of dis¬
tinctive difference), which to some lin¬
guists is as important as Newton's apple
was to modern physicists.
The "Second World War gave these
theorists a wonderful opportunity. They
were able to test many of their ideas
when the United States set up a scheme
for the language training of military per¬
sonnel under the Army Specialized Train¬
ing Programme (A.S.T.P.). The results
were flattering, though it must be said in
all fairness that other countries,' which
sponsored similar emergency training-
schemes, achieved equally spectacular
though less well advertized results even
though they made use of more - tradi¬
tional methods. It is probably too early
to say whether the theories of the des¬
criptive linguists can ultimately be uti¬
lized in the ordinary language class in a
school ; certainly no wide-awake lan¬
guage teacher can afford to be ignorant
of this whole body of doctrine.
After the last War, the need felt by
countries such as Australia and Israel to
set up machinery for dealing with great
polyglot waves of immigrants led to new
research in a neighbouring field: how to
teach a national language to mixed
groups with widely assorted social and
linguistic backgrounds. In both the
countries mentioned it meant devising
experimental methods, preparing special
text-books and training teachers. What
is really interesting is that both these
countries, working independently of one
another, came to roughly the same
conclusions regarding methods, which
call for marked emphasis on the spoken
language with all material carefully
graded and a marked stress on over-
learning.
Real progress has also been made
during the post-war years in some of the
smaller Western European States, like
the Netherlands and the Scandinavian
UNESCO COURIER - N° 1-1954
countries, speaking languages of limited
diffusion. New and attractive text¬
books have been issued and a special
attempt has been made to make lan¬
guage teaching lead to sound and up-to-
date knowledge of foreign countries.
Finally, in any review of the factors
which have contributed to contemporary
trends in language teaching, some men¬
tion must be made of the experience
acquired in countries such as India, Indo¬
nesia and the Philippines, where the
advent of independence had as one result
the setting up of new national languages
in place of the western languages which
had hitherto been paramount. The
details of this great experiment in pro¬
gress will, of course, take some time to
assess, but it is not unreasonable to
suppose that the East, which has hitherto
learned about language-teaching from
the West, will soon be in a position to '
give lessons as well as to receive them.
So much for some relatively recent
developments. What of the current
trends that have arisen from them ? It
might be worthwhile to try and list some
of them, bearing in mind, of course, that
these are just general tendencies among
up-to-date modern language teachers
and that they primarily concern school
needs and not the needs of, say, scientists
who want to learn to read technical arti¬
cles or tourists who want to buy post-
Thls picture shows a girl "photographing" her voice electronically. The machine Is used by experts In
phonetics to study differences in sound variations in the teaching of foreign languages. (Photo by Fritz
Goro. Reproduced by courtesy of Life magazine.)
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
cards or visit night-clubs when travelling
in a foreign country. And, in spite of
all the advice given by the experts, there
will still be tough-minded individuals
who will prefer to teach themselves lan¬
guages with a grammar, a dictionary and
a text. If they succeed, who is to say
that they used wrong methods ?
The First Approach. Current trends
favour what is called, somewhat pedan¬
tically, the oral-aural approach. This
puts speaking and understanding, before
reading and writing. The descriptive
linguists would say that this method is
sound because language is in its very
essence a spoken means of communica¬
tion and all written language merely an
arbitrary representation of the real thing.
Veterans of the Natural Method will say
that this is the best way because that
is how a child learns a language for the
first time.
What really seems to matter is that
numbers of experienced, non-dogmatic
teachers have in fact found that this
approach gives the best results and that
pupils can be led a surprisingly long way
into the heart of a language without even
opening a book, or taking a single note.
As a forceful participant at the Unesco
Modern Language Seminar at Nuwara
Eliya, Ceylon last August put it: "'You
don't learn to play the >piano by
watching, someone else play or by
studying counterpoint and harmony.
You learn by sitting in iront of.
the thing and pushing on the keys." '
Pronunciation. If the oral-aural ap¬
proach is in favour, it follows that ,the
pupil's (and the teacher's) first problems
will have to do with pronunciation. How
much latitude is to be allowed? Accord¬
ing to present trends, little or none.
The best authorities seem at present to be
convinced -that correct-' pronunciation
must be thoroughly inculcated right from
the start. Later on- is too late, and
merely encourages bad speech habits
that become almost ineradicable. This
does not necessarily call for elaborate
methods. Obviously it will not suffice
to keep urging the pupil to imitate the
correct sounds made by the teacher.^ The
pupil must be told how to set about
making the correct sounds.
The modern emphasis on grading and
selection, as well as on the significance
of phonemes, will normally lead the
teacher to concentrate primarily on the
sounds that matter and on those which
are most difficult for pupils to pro-"
nounce. It is doubtful whether all this .
requires the use of phonetic symbols,
though probably they do no harm. It is
also doubtful whether, as one linguist
advocates, pupils should have to master
the whole jargon of modern phonetics.
A child can probably learn to pronounce
the "th" in then without bothering,
about voiced interdental spirants.
Grammar. The modernists are against
it, or rather they are against the wrong
kind of grammar and against the intro¬
duction of almost any kind of grammar
too early or in massive doses. Certainly
the study of formal grammar for its own
sake is now considered to be the proper
. pursuit of professional grammarians, not
of school children trying to learn a Ian- _
guage. There are, of course, a good
many who say that the traditional gram¬
mar elaborated for most modern langua¬
ges, and based on classical concepts of
case, tense, mood and so on, are quite
meaningless and bear no relation to any
modern language except those directly
derived from Greek or Latin. For these
people, the real grammars of modern
languages are only now being written.
In the meantime, they and many others
think that the problems of grammar
should be dealt with as they arise, quite
incidentally, and that pupils should be
encouraged to draw their own gramma¬
tical conclusions from the linguistic facts
already in their possession.
Graded Structures. "'Structural Ana¬
lysis," "Structural Grading," "The Struc¬
tural Approach" these phrases occur
constantly in the contemporary literature
of modern language teaching. They
refer, of course, not to a new method but
to present-day emphasis on the need for
analysing language difficulties and then
for .presenting the basic patterns or
variants one at a time and in order of
Despite the impressiveness of certain new gadgets, the best aid to language learning is still and probably
always will be the well-qualified teacher. Here in the Trobriand Archipelago of Papua, New Guinea, a
teacher holds an open-air language class. (Australian Official Photo).
A number of new devices now exist to aid foreign
near Paris receiving instruction in special language
language drill. But
difficulty. Naturally the whole grading
process should be and is applied not only
to structures but to other features such
as vocabulary and intonation.
Drill, alias overlearning. There was
a time when textbooks started each
lesson with a list of new words, generally
quite unrelated to one another, which the
unfortunate pupil was supposed to learn
by heart. Even after vocabulary frequency
counts became fashionable the practice of
imposed memorizing did not cease. It only
really started to peter out when, first of
all, it began to be realized that a lan¬
guage does not consist of words stuck
together with grammar, like a wall made
of bricks and mortar, but that it consists
of phrases and, secondly, that there are
less laborious ways of remembering
phrases, or the words they contain, than
just memorizing them parrot-fashion.
Hence the modern technique of repeating
words and phrases aloud in many differ¬
ent real contexts until they are learnt
automatically and directly associated in
the mind with the objects or actions they
represent.
Gadgets. A gadget does not have to
cost hundreds of dollars or be so compli¬
cated that it breaks down every time
anyone looks at it. A blackboard and
a piece of chalk are gadgets, and very
useful ones. Textbooks are gadgets.
Such simple things as a pocket mirror
and a flashlight are almost indispensable
gadgets for anyone beginning to learn .
the pronunciation of a new language.
The more elaborate gadgets exist too,
and undoubtedly they have come to play
a pretty important part in language
teaching, particularly in financially pri¬
vileged parts of the world, such as North
America and Western Europe.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER -N" 1-1954
language teaching, particularly in financially privileged countries. Photos show multi-national personnel at SHAPE (Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers in Europe)
laboratory equipped with individual sound-proofed compartments. Each student has his own tape-recorder for recording his pronunciation, taking dictation and
such equipment is complicated and highly expensive, and most countries use simpler, though not less effective techniques.
In the United States, to take a rather
extreme example, a good number of
schools and colleges now have well-
equipped language laboratories with
sound-proofed compartments and tape-
recorders for individual use. The tape-
recorder, double or single channel, used
with or without film-strips, and intelli¬
gently used, is an invaluable aid to lan¬
guage teaching, but it is expensive. So
are language films, but so far language
teaching films have somehow ' failed to
measure up to the expectations and the
requirements of language teachers. Disk
recordings have, of course been in use for
years and have been found useful.
Film strips are cheaper and more
abundant than films. In the Nether¬
lands the showing of film-strips to lan¬
guage classes is combined ingeniously
with school radio programmes. Radio, ,
indeed, is perhaps the most effective
of all the audio-visual aids, and it is
used in a number of different ways in
different countries. In Australia, to take
an example, it can follow the migrant
to a remote up-country sheep-station
and enable him to continue his lessons
in the national language. In Sweden
it is one of several factors used in a
unique type of scheme for teaching
foreign languages to adults. In the
United Kingdom it is perhaps the chief
agent for marketing English as a foreign
language abroad. It is too early to
speak of television. All that one can
really say is that experiments in its use
for language-teaching have begun and
that the possibilities are immense.
The Time Factor. Do present-day
curricula give school-children enough
time to learn a foreign language ?
Elsewhere in this issue there is a dis
cussion of the beginning age for language
learning, which suggests that because
modern language teaching has, in so
many countries, been confined to secon¬
dary education, we are perhaps sacrific¬
ing some of the best years for lan¬
guage work. Important though it is,
there is no need to discuss that subject
further here. The question is whether
enough time is given to language-classes
in. most schools even under the present
restricted dispensation.
Experts are now inclined to think that
no pupil can hope to do justice to the
subject if he is only allotted three or four
hours a week. He probably needs five
or six. Educational authorities who
throw up their hands and answer that
there is no more time to spare in an
already overcrowded schedule might
reflect. The physics teacher or the
chemistry teacher who asks for labora¬
tory periods invariably gets them. Why
should not the language teacher ? The
extra hour or so, spent more informally,
with large classes split up into smaller
groups, can, under the guidance of an
imaginative teacher, be of very great
benefit.
These then are some of the trends
which have become apparent in contem¬
porary language teaching. It is these
trends that were most in evidence at
Nuwara Eliya last August when language
teachers from eighteen countries met
under, the auspices of Unesco.
In countries not given to over expe¬
rimentation, and where language teach¬
ing is closely integrated into a tradi¬
tional educational pattern that evolves
slowly, there is as yet only moderate
interest in these trends. Other lands,
with greater needs jfor immediate prac¬
tical results turn to new methods.
If space permitted, a discussion of
current problems should follow any
account of developments and trends such
as this one. And the greatest of these
problems is perhaps motivation. No one
can accurately say how essential a factor
this is in language learning, but cer¬
tainly its importance is very great. One
of the ironies of an educationally unbal¬
anced world is that in vast areas the
desire, or rather the imperative need to
learn languages, is everywhere apparent,
though qualified teachers, proper text¬
books and adequate funds are lacking.
Where teachers and money and books
and mechanical aids of every kind are
available, too often language classrooms
are filled with solid rows of pupils,
merely passive and not greatly caring
whether they learn ' or not. And yet
knowledge öf a language cannot be pour¬
ed through a hole in the top of a
school-child's head ; the will to learn is
absolutely essential.
It should not be beyond the capacity
of teachers to arouse that will. All the .
old bread-and-butter arguments are
still valid and still perfectly respectable
in a practical world. Today's argu¬
ment, the modern, compelling argument,
is the need for knowing and understand¬
ing other peoples in a shrinking world.
It is for this reason that the conscien¬
tious language teacher has come to play
at least as important a role as the teach¬
er of history, of geography, or of civics
in helping children - to understand the
world in which they live. And children,
innately idealistic as they are, can
quickly grasp the importance of language
as a key to international understanding
if it is put to them without mawkishness
and with sincerity.
F.H.W.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
30
Celtic
" Breton
Qaelic
Irish
Manx
Welsh
Greek
Gypsy
Romance
Catalan
French
Galician
Italian
Judaeo-Spanish
Portuguese
Provençal
Romansh (or Rhaeto-
Romanian)
Rumanian
Spanish
Armenian (3 main dialect
clusters)
Indo-lranian
Iranian
Persian (or Pehlevi)
Caspian (about 5 dia¬
lects)
Kurdish (3 main dia¬
lects)
Pamir (a group of about
8 main dialects spoken
in India)
Pushto (2 main va¬
riants)
Baluchi
Ossete (2 main dialects
spoken in U.R.S.S.
Other languages spo¬
ken in the Turkestan)
Indie
Marathi
Qujerati
Punjabi
Rajasthani
Western Hindi
Eastern Hindi
Oriya
Bihari
Bengali
URAL-
ALTAIC
LANGUAGES I
Samo/ede
Turkish
Mongolian
Esquimo-
Alcaic
INDO-
EUROPEAN
LANGUAGES
Korean
Japanese
Finno-
Ugnan
Germanic
Romance
Greek
i and others
Indo-
Iranian
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Map prepared by W. Schmidt
and reproduced from " De Bezíge
By Wereldatfas " , Amsterdam.
S
30
SEMITIC-
HAMITIC
Semitic
LANGUAGES \ Hamitic
CAUCASIAN
LANGUAGES
AFRICAN
LANGUAGES
V?,
60
PALEO-
ASIATIC
LANGUAGES '
90 120 150 180
l Yukïgu
Chuckchee-
Kamychadal
SINO-
TIBETAN
LANGUAGES 1
Ainu
Yenisei-
Ostyak
Tibet-
Burman
Tai-
Siamese
Bantu
Sudan
regions
Hottentot
and Bushmen
DRAVIDIAN
LANGUAGES
EAST
ASIAN
LANGUAGES
AUSTRON ESIAN
LANGUAGES
PAPUAN
LANGUAGES
AUSTRALIAN
LANGUAGES
AMERICAN
INDIAN
LANGUAGES
Indonesian
Melanesian
Polynesian
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
TOO YOUNG TO LEARN
A FOREIGN LANGUAGE ?
It is traditional in many countries to intro¬
duce the first foreign language " at the
beginning of the secondary school. Tra¬
ditions are often valuable or picturesque and
should be treasured. In education, however,
it seems appropriate to re-examine our tradi¬
tions periodically and I propose to re-examine
this one.
Why have foreign languages been introduced
at the beginning of our secondary schools or
.later? I can only surmise. Here are my
conjectures, for -what they are worth. It is
grown-ups who prepare the education fare for
our children. As those who have kept in touch
with children know, grown-ups are notoriously
lacking in imagination. They began their
second language in the secondary school and
therefore their children should obviously
begin there. They also remember the study
of a foreign language as a difficult and compli¬
cated business, clearly too difficult and
complicated for young children.
This line of thought rests on the assumption
that a foreign language is just another school
subject, to be mastered by dint of, hard work
and mental discipline. This view does not in
my opinion take into account adequately the
fact that a language, particularly in the early
stages is a skill, a skill involving the training
of the auditory and vocal organs and indeed
the entire behaviour of speech.
This "skill" aspect of the language, which is
basic to any real learning of a language, that
is, to the speaking of a language, is precisely
what adolescents and grown-ups come by with
such difficulty. A person who begins a foreign-
language in adolescence rarely learns to speak
it without accent. Adolescents find the mim¬
icking and facial contortions necessary to re¬
produce foreign sounds a little silly and they
tend to be self-conscious about it. They put
me in mind of Baudelaire's albatross. Ready
to 'soar in intellectual flight, they are held
captive on the - narrow deck of a ship and
waddle about clumsily and ludicrously.
The child, on the other hand, takes to a
foreign language like a fish to water. Placed in
a foreign environment, children can learn not
only one but several languages with incredible
ease and without accent. A British psycho¬
logist, J.'W. Tomb, living in, Bengal, has. cited
the case of English children born in Bengal
speaking Bengali with their nurses, Santali
with the garden attendant, Hindustani with the
house servants, and of course English with
their parents.
Mr. E. V. Gatenby, who writes perceptively
on this subject, observes that children don't
use languages but language to communicate.
He cites the case of the Turkish novelist Halide
Edip who noted in her memoirs that she Was
twelve years old before she realized that she
spoke two languages, English and Turkish.
And the Canadian Prime Minister, Mr. St. Lau¬
rent, thought in his youth that English was the
form of speech one used to communicate with
mothers and French the form used to commu¬
nicate with fathers.
The moral that Mr. Gatenby very properly
draws from all this is : "Let the pupils have
a chance. Give them a teacher who ¡knows the
language thoroughly and will use it all the
lime. Let them start learning at the earliest
possible age through pleasurable activities,
with the minimum of formal teaching and the
maximum use of the language in natural si¬
tuations."
Let us glance a little more closely at the
way infants and young children learn language.
In their babbling stage infants have been
observed to produce an amazing variety of
sounds, not only sounds in their own language
but also sounds of other languages and indeed
sounds which may belong to no language. In
fact, there is no reason to believe the very
young child incapable of producing any sound
in any one. of the nearly 3,000 languages of
th« world.
If the child is able potentially to utter any
sound in any language, why does he not retain
this wonderful gift ? The reason seems to be
that in addition to the joy of imitating and
inventing sounds the child craves the joy of
response. As he finds that the oh, so limited
grown-ups about him respond only to certain
sounds, he gradually discards the sounds which
fail to elicit a response and which thus prove
to be useless for communication. Gradually
his phonetic range contracts until he finds
by Theodore Andersson
himself hemmed in between. the narrow walls
-of his own mother tongue.
What conclusions may be drawn from all
this ? I believe that tentatively we are justi¬
fied' in establishing the following hypothesis :
Children possess in infancy great potentialities
for learning tha language skills and these po¬
tentialities decline steadily throughout child¬
hood, adolescence, and maturity. On the
" other hand, the rational or conceptual faculties,
which are present in embryonic state in infants
develop steadily through childhood, adoles¬
cence, and into maturity.
If this hypothesis is sound, the very first
year of school is none too early to begin a
second language. Every year's delay thereafter
represents a loss of the most precious language-
learning period. Differences in language apti¬
tude, which in adolescents are so marked and
so discouraging to teachers, appear to be
negligible in early childhood. Indeed, a num¬
ber of the teachers engaged in experimental
teaching at this level in the United States
report that there is by no means a dependable
correlation between general intelligence and
language aptitude. Some teachers report a
better correlation between musical aptitude
and language aptitude, but data in this field
are as yet inadequate and careful research is
needed.
What are the obstacles in the way of intro¬
ducing a second language at the age of 5 ? One
of the first objections raised is that the early
exposure to a foreign language may interfere
with the learning of the mother tongue. This
fear is, in my opinion, groundless. At the age
of 5 a child has had a four-year start in learn¬
ing to 'speak his own language. In the first
grade of school he has according to recent
estimates an active vocabulary of about 2,000
words and an understanding vocabulary of
about 24,000 words and is talking about as
easily as the grown-up in his environment. -
At school he is beginning to read and write,
whereas for the first two or three years his
exposure to the foreign language is aural and .
oral exclusively. Normally therefore there is
no possibility of interference between one's
mother tongue and one's second language. On
the contrary, the stimulation of learning a
second language and the resulting increase in
linguistic competence is likely to benefit the ..
mother tongue greatly.
A second objection which is frequently raised
is that the addition of a second language
crowds the primary-school curriculum, making
it more difficult to do the teaching of the basic
subjects, the so-called three R's properly. But
the testimony of the primary-school teachers
who have tried adding a language contradicts
this objection. The evidence is that, if any¬
thing, the children do better in the. three R's
after they start to learn a second language.
A third objection is the only one which in
my opinion has much validity: the .lack of
qualified teachers. There is of course a great
scarcity of teachers qualified to teach foreign
languages properly, especially in the early
stages, where a maximum of artistry and en¬
thusiasm are required and where a legitimate
accent is essential. But the solution of even
this difficulty has been suggested in some of
the American programmes.
In the first place, when we really start look¬
ing for native speakers of French or Spanish ~
the two languages in greatest demand in the
United States we find a surprisingly large
number of them able to teach young children
or willing to learn. Secondly, there is the pos¬
sibility of greatly increasing the exchanges of
teachers which already exist on a small scale.
And thirdly, so-called workshops for the train¬
ing of interested primary school teachers in a
foreign language have in some places' been
successfully organized.
In Los Angeles, for example, an enthusiastic
superintendent of schools announced in the
spring of 1943 that Spanish would be taught
on a city-wide basis starting in the Kindergar¬
ten. A workshop was organized in the sum¬
mer, .which has since then been continuous,
summer and winter, for the training of teachers
in Spanish. The programme has been very
successful.
Most of the existing programmes are ground¬
ed in sound theory though there is also room
for much improvement the quality of
teaching. Almost invariably the ear is trained <
before the tongue and the tongue is trained
before the eye and hand. In Cleveland and
Los Angeles, for example, the aural and oral
training continues throughout -the six years of
the elementary school before reading and
writing are begun. In my opinion reading
and writing are in these places postponed too
long. Secondly, tho important matter of moti¬
vation is usually well taken care of by the
judicious use of games, songs, and plenty of .
action and dramatization. The classes in the
early grades usually do not exceed 20 minutes
in length but they frequently occur every day,
Monday through Friday. Thirdly, the aims
are usually defined clearly. The two principal
ones are: (1) learning to speak the language
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER -N" 1-1954
and- (2) getting to understand better the
people whose mother tongue is being studied.
In some areas, notably in the Southwest and
in the state of Louisiana, improvements in the
social relations between different cultural
elements have been nothing short of revolu¬
tionary. In many towns in Louisiana where
children were formerly prohibited from speak¬
ing French in school or in the school yard the
French children are now looked up to and
respected for their knowledge of a language
that all the children are trying to learn. Thus
at one free stroke some 400,000 French-speaking
citizens of Louisiana are being more fully in
corporated into the life of the state and their
social status is being greatly improved.
In conclusion let me describe briefly the
twelve-year course I envisage as the ultimate
goal of this trend. I divide it into four parts
of three years each. The first three years are
given over entirely to aural and oral drill in
a large variety of ways, the emphasis on aural
and oral work continues throughout the twelve
years, but in grades four, five, and six training
in reading and writing is begun, which is then
continued throughout.
In grades seven, eight, and nine when,
children are of an age to take an active interest
in theoretical questions the grammar of the
language is analyzed. Structural patterns have
become automatic by' virtue of constant re¬
petition with variations, but children have now
reached the age of conscious analysis.
Grades ten, eleven, and twelve seem like
the proper time to study, in more systematic
x fashion than before, the history, geography,
civilization, and literature of the people whose
language is being studied. The students now
possess the instrument necessary for doing
this they cart understand, speak, read and
write the foreign language with reasonable
ease and accuracy.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE TRANSLATING MACHINE
helping to solve some of the language problems of science
ONE major obstacle to the inter-
nationality of science is the
diversity of languages, as a result
of which half or more of what is
published is useless to half or more of
thé world's scientists, technologists and
medical men.
The actual proportions so lost are very
difficult to estimate statistically, but a
rough idea, for science as a whole, can be
gained from the unshaded areas in the
diagram published with this article.
The proportion varies, however, from
one branch of science to another and
changes in the course of time. In
chemistry, for instance, German was the
leading language until shortly after the
First World War, when English took its
place. French at one time came second,
but after 1914 it ranked only fourth and
now Japanese competes with it for fifth
place. Nearly seventy years ago Russian
reached fifth place among forty lan¬
guages, but it is now competing with
German for second place.
All that part of scientific literature
which is represented by the < areas left
unblackened in the diagram is un-
exploitable, unless either, it is translated,
or the ability of scientists to read the
appropriate foreign languages is in-
by Edwin Holmstrom
creased above the level here assumed, or
scientific authors and publishers can be
persuaded to make use of languages more
widely understood than their own. Let
us briefly consider each of these alter¬
natives in turn.
Technical translating is slow, difficult
and uncertain. Since nobody can trans¬
late what he does not understand, it
follows that the translator must be
himself a scientist as well as acquainted
with the language he is translating from,
and competent as an author in the
language he is translating into. Especially
where the less common languages and
the more recondite specialities of science
are concerned these qualities are rarely
found in perfect combination.
But, from the consumer's point of view,
translating is necessarily expensive.
Where an original journal can be bought
for the equivalent of perhaps 50 U.S.
cents, a translation of a scientific article
in it, made by a specialist, will cost
perhaps $50. In other words it is not
worth paying to have done unless there
are grounds for supposing it will be worth
a hundred times as much to the scientist
who wants it as something on the same
topic in his own language. In some
countries, to spread the cost of trans¬
lating, bureaux exist in which manu¬
scripts of unpublished translations are
filed and from which copies are supplied
on payment.
The more technical a translation, the
less the part that the linguist as such
and the greater the part that the subject
specialist can play in making it a good
one. This being so, quite promising
experiments have been made in replacing
the linguist by electronic machines, built
on the lines of mathematical computers.
Such machines are able permanently
. to register sequences of code patterns of
electrical impulses corresponding to the
different letters of the alphabet, fed into
them by operating a typewriter keyboard. .
If two equivalent words in different
- languages have been so registered at the
same time, the "typing" of one of these
at any future time will cause the
machine automatically and instantane¬
ously to type out the other.
If that were all, we should have a
mechanical dictionary. It is possible,
however, to go considerably further. The
machine can be made to type, out code
letters which indicate how the words fed
povitunitr
Ml». »IUI
II
KHfHr E-STYC
DO
i
I III
III!
3]]]
(HI
>||.
JSSS
BitS
ill.
1171
III
IDO
lili
lili
1311
4*44
lili
SSSS
(its
lili
7111
IUI
iiii
9191
D00O
nu
7!
Uli
1444
S9SS
ii
7777
III
999
0IO|
¡m
IV,'
m
1444
ssss
II
7777
nu
999
l'IlMH
i'ii'n
IJJ!
3311
4441
9999
lit!
1777
III!
9999
Mil
727)
1119
4444
5SS5
IUI
7117
II
9999
00|0
Mil
7277
1333
1114
îsïs
t|ti
¡77 ;
a g s a
999|
IJJI
"¡I
Mil
1311
1444
n m ii u
SSSS
Uli
un
°MIII|û
Mil
2277
3133
1444
Mil
227
3333
4444
Í3SS
EIII6EII
1171
l|l|llll
1177
IUI
9999
«I
II"
7722
¡¡¡33
4444
SSSS
HIE
1111
Mil
7722
3331
H|||0|||||0
Mil
27|7
îîîi
4444
îî's'i
ÍSSS
1111
Hill!
9)99
Mil
2777
mi
4444
sss
| E E
Will.
7717
IIII
9999
l>o|||o|H||||||HHlH||
MM
7722
4 4 4 4
sis'3v-
III
7771
IUI
999]
Mil
2727
]33|B133
1444
sí: s
Ei|l
7117
lit!
9999
1444
S555
un
uun
7171
III
19 9
I I I I
2277
3331
4414
9ÍSS
USE
7711
Uli
9999
I I I I
2212
1313
1444
55S5
sut
777!
Ill
9999
I I I I
7777
3213
4444
SSS5
USE
7711
IUI
9999
Mil
1111
1111
1144
Í9IS
Sill
imn*
1777
IUI
9919
KftChyçsrvc
III I
UCLYfl
I I
*-a!.!:çiii"'Cirjv.'
II I
I I II lllllll
CFÇfTErTl.Y nïEnro
I I I I I
I I I III I I III
i ni nun i mu i i ii ni mum
I I llll
This card is punched with a sample Russian_language sentence (as
interpreted at the top) in standard IBM puncned-card code. It is
then accepted by the 701, converted into its own binary language and _
translated by means of stored dicticrnary and operational syntactical
programs into the English language equivalent which is then printed.
I I
II I I I I I I III
I II
THE JUAL1TY
CALORY CONTINT
CF COhL lb DETERMINED BY
FROM RUSSIAN INTO ENGLISH IN TEN SECONDS
On January 7 the International Business Machine Corporation,
producers of the world's largest electronic calculators, gave the
first public demonstration of a new type of translating machine
at work (Photo left). At the demonstration, held in New York,
the machine was given various sentences in Russian for translation
into English One of the sentences was: "Myezhdunarodnoye
ponyimanyiye yavlyayetsya vazhnim faktorom v ryeshyenyiyi polyi-
tyichyeskyix voprosov. " Ten seconds later the machine translated
in English "International understanding constitutes an important
factor in the decision of political questions. Above, the punch card
which translated "The quality of coal is determined by calory con¬
tent " from the Russian. Below left, card showing Russian sentence
"Obrabotka poyishayet kachyestvo Nyeftyi. ". Machine trans¬
lated this as "Processing improves the quality of crude oil."
The translating arrangement is mostly the work of Dr. Leon
Dostert, chairman of Georgetown University's Institute of. Lan¬
guages and Linguistics, and Dr. Cuthbert Hurd, Director of IBM's
Applied Science Division. Dr. Dostert, an American of French
origin first achieved prominence in the field of language translation
at the time of the Nuremberg trials. He was one of the experts
particularly responsible for setting up the simultaneous translation
system now currently used by international organizations. The
language-teaching methods used under his direction at the School
of Foreign Service of Georgetown University are among the most
modern to be found anywhere in the world. (Photos A. P.)
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER -N" 1-1954
the shaded areas re¬
present the relative
amounts of literature
that can be under¬
stood without trans¬
lation. Unshaded,
areas over two-
thirds of the whole
represent litera¬
ture which cannot be
read unless translat¬
ed. The widths of
the rectangles are
proportional to the
volume of scientific li¬
terature published in
each language, and
their heights are pro¬
portional to the num¬
bers of scientists able
to read each langua¬
ge. English, for in¬
stance, is the medium
of publication for mo¬
re than half the litera¬
ture, but as the dia¬
gram shows can be
read directly by less
than half the world's
scientists.
Current scientific literature is published mainly in six languages and is distrib¬
uted between them very roughly in proportion to the widths of these columns-
/
GERMAN
SPANISH
ENGLISH
FRENCH
JAPANESE
RUSSIAN
1
-
- 1
The chief
by scientis
six languages of science are understood
ts of all nationalities very roughly In the
proportions shown here.
into it in the language of origin are
grammatically modified or inflected.- It
need not be limited to single words but
may be "taught to recognize" a whole
unit phrase in one language and type out
the corresponding, syntactically quite
different, phrase in the other language.
Though the machine cannot produce -
by itself an intelligible translation let
alone one in good literary style when a
text in one language is "fed" into it, it
types out a string of words, alternative
meanings of homonyms, symbolic letters
and odd looking phrases which a
specialist in the subject of the text will
have no difficulty in editing and turning
into an acceptable rendering, even
though he may know nothing at all of
the original language. .
Though it is more likely to be in hand¬
ling very out-of-the-way languages that
such machines might find a possible use,
the following example so rendered from
French into English may be of interest.
Here A is the original text.'B is what the
machine typed out, and C is what the
subject specialist, not knowing French,
turned it into, (v means "'vacuous" or
meaningless; m means multiple, plural or
dual; z means "unspecific"; the sign
/ denotes the point of separation of
semantic elements.)
A. Il n'est pas étonn/ant de constat/er
que les hormone/ s de croissance ag/is-
sent sur certain/es espèce/s, alors qu'elles
sont in/opér/antes sur d'autre/s, si l'on
song/e à la grand/e spécificité de ces
substance/s.
B. v not is not/step astonish v of estab¬
lish ^v_ that/which? _v hormone ni of
growth act m on certain m species m,
then that/which ? v not operate m on
of other m if v one~äream/consider z to
v great v specificity of those substance m.
C. It is not surprising to learn that
growth hormones may act on certain
species while having no effect on others,
when one remembers the narrow speci¬
ficity of these substances.
Clearly it is better, if possible, for a
scientist to be able to read foreign arti
cles himself than to have to depend on
translations. In the Scandinavian coun¬
tries, the Netherlands, Switzerland and
some others, almost everyone has had to
learn to do this, but even in these
countries few know Russian or Japanese,
and elsewhere ability to read English,
German or French is far from universal.
In theory at least, proposals to encou¬
rage the use of one particular language,
whether natural or artificial, as the
medium of scientific communication in
all countries have much to commend
them. Science, however, is a branch of
culture and it is natural for each coun¬
try to feel that an efflorescence of its
own culture may best be encouraged
through the use of its own language.
The problem is a difficult one and too
large to be discussejd here.
All these questions, and many others,
are being studied in the Report on Scien¬
tific and Technical Translating and
Related Problems which Unesco is pre¬
paring for publication in 1955, utilizing
the valuable comments, suggestions and
information which are now being receiv¬
ed from some 250 experts in 29 countries
to whom a draft of the Report was sent.
Its final chapter, "Terminology and dic¬
tionaries", deals with a problem to which
the Department of Natural Sciences has
for some years past been devoting much
attention, a problem whose importance
deserves to be stressed here.
It is ideas, not individual concepts,
that have to be translated, and it is the
phrase, not the individual word, that is
the unit of language. In point of fact it
very seldom happens that an expression
in one language has its exact equivalent
in another. Their central meanings may
or may not be the same, but nearly
always the penumbra of meaning is dif¬
ferent. In English usage "welding" is
differentiated from "soldering", whereas
the French word "soudage" covers both.
"Concrete" in English and "béton" in
French, both mean a mixture of large
and small stones and sand stuck together
with cement or "ciment". But in French
the word "ciment", is also commonly
used as a synonym for "béton".
These are rather superficial examples,
but others like them which may have
serious consequences, even financially
occur in every branch of technicality.
Ideally, to eliminate such misunderstand¬
ings, the translator should be so accus¬
tomed not only to reading but to himself
reasoning about the technical subject-
matter in both languages, that the nuan¬
ces of the special terms are second
nature to him. In very specialized fields,
and for the less common languages, that,
however, is a counsel of perfection.
This means that dictionaries, although
dangerous, are a necessity. To make
them safe it is essential that they should
indicate not only the nearest equivalents
of the technical terms, but just how
inexact the equivalences are, enabling
the translator to introduce some quali¬
fying word or turn of phrase to correct
the inexactitude of meaning that would
otherwise be conveyed.
The ultimate remedy is standardization
of the meanings of technical terms on
the basis of definitions agreed upon by
the specialists concerned in each lan¬
guage. Unesco is about to publish a clas¬
sified bibliography of existing authorita¬
tive glossaries of this kind in single lan¬
guages complementary to its Bibliogra¬
phy of Interlingual Scientific and Tech¬
nical Dictionaries, a .third edition of
which is now being printed. The latter
contains references to about 1,630 such
works under nearly 400 subject heads,
interconnecting 72 languages.
Standardization in the full sense men¬
tioned above must inevitably be a slow
process. Meanwhile the production of
more and better special dictionaries is a
matter of urgent international impor¬
tance. This being so, the policy which
Unesco is pursuing is that of helping and
encouraging the international organiza¬
tions concerned with each field of science
and technology to produce dictionaries
which shall contain a mixture, typogra¬
phically distinguished, of terms and defi¬
nitions which are fully standardized,
terms which are recommended by those
organizations, and terms including
regional variations which fall into
neither of these categories but are liable
to occur in the technical literature.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THEIR BUS STOPPED AT LAPLAND
By Paul Normand
THERE were twenty-seven of them,
twenty-seven Parisian boys who
three years ago came to an im¬
portant decision : "In 1953", they said,
"we're going to go to the North Cape in
Lapland." As a rule such resolutions
don't get Parisian boys any further than
the city limits or the grande banlieue.
But this time it was different. Not only
did the boys go off but they managed to
cover 7,000 miles during their summer
vacation and got to know a lot about
eight countries in a way that no geo¬
graphy book or documentary fllm could
'have shown them, and yet the oldest of
the group was hardly 15 and the
youngest only nine !
How did they do it ? It wasn't too
easy, but then it wasn't too difficult
either. They bought the chassis and
engine of an old truck, had a new body
built on it by a friendly country mecha¬
nic and helped him to fit it out and
then painted it themselves. But, first of
all, they were members of a French
youth movement called "L'Association
du Compagnonnage Français".
The "Companionship" movement is a
non-profit organization which seeks to
foster the idea of international under-"
standing and friendship by encouraging
groups of boys to visit foreign countries
where they can meet young people of
their own age. The organization leaves
much to the initiative of the boys and
works to develop a . team spirit by
encouraging members to take part in
projects ,as a group. All trips are
conceived as mobile classrooms.
Although the journey to the North
Cape beyond the Arctic Circle was led by
24
one of the Association's organizers, a Pa¬
ris schoolteacher, M. Pierre Tue, it was
the boys themselves who took charge of
all the preparations for the "caravan"
including transport, financing and out¬
fitting. M. Tue went along as driver,
guide, teacher and friend. .
Raising the money for the truck and
for the other travel expenses wasn't
easy and called for lots of ingenuity and
effort as it was meant to do. Some of
the boys sold mushrooms they had
picked in the country ; others sold their
association's newspaper. On May 1 they
all became flower vendors, selling lilies
of the valley which everyone in France
buys on May Day. In addition they
charged entrance fees for sports events
they organized. One of the highlights
of their fund-raising campaign was a
special programme of films produced
and acted by themselves.
The boys received some financial help
' from their parents and were also
eligible for the holiday camp group
allowance provided by the French
Government. But the main effort was
their own. They even managed to raise
enough money to help defray - the
expenses of ten of their comrades whose
parents could afford to pay nothing at
all.
It took two years to prepare for the
great Arctic trip. But in the meantime
the boys managed to - visit a few
countries closer at hand. One summer
they boarded an old motor bus and
toured Switzerland and Austria. During
the winter .they went off on long hikes.
Last Easter - they spent twelve (water¬
logged) days camping in. Normandy.
Finally all was ready for the Arctic
adventure. The great day came when
the bus they had helped repair and
equip pulled out of Paris and headed
north with Professor Tue at the wheel.
Twenty-seven" young travellers sang
lustily behind him. Each day brought
them 150 to 200 miles nearer their
destination. Each day classroom geo¬
graphy lessons came alive as they saw
the cities they had studied in school
and spoke with their inhabitants. At
the evening halt they pitched their
tents and cooked their meal. The next
morning they were off again on the
next stage of their trip to Lapland.
The "classroom on - wheels" was
equipped with everything needed for
lessons and for living. Benches were
fitted along each side of the coach and
between them was a folding table. It
had lockers to hold camping equipment
and personal belongings, a first-aid kit,
and bookshelves for the group's library.
Lessons, of course, were informal. Notes
were taken during the day, and at the
evening halt the boys exchanged their
impressions of the day's travel and
looked up facts about the places they
would see the following day. Then they
set down this information in their note¬
books, together with their day-to-day
accounts of thé journey. The artists
among them illustrated the notes with
sketches and drawings.
Most informal of all were the language
classes. Meetings with other young
people (also on holiday) in Germany
and Denmark gave the boys many
chances to practise their German and
English, and in Denmark they once had
to use Spanish to make themselves
understood. But with the young Finns
IT WAS A THRILL FOR THESE PARIS SCHOOL-
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER- N" 1-1954
The French 'Companions' Youth Movement
The "Association du Compagnonnage Français" is an organization which seeks to
strengthen the ties between different peoples by creating permanent contacts between
children. The Association's 2,000 members come from Paris, Lyons, Bordeaux,
Reims and other large French cities, children being grouped in "caravans" of 24 "compa¬
nions" led by an adult. Everyone in the caravan has a job to do, taking care of such things
as finance, equipment, information or education. Several times monthly the caravans
make excursions into the countryside. In winter they visit the mountains and at Easter
hold camp ; to prepare and practise for a visit to another country in summer. In addition
to the physical traininghikes, camping, mountain excursions, ski-ingthe children are
required to make a good showing in class and are judged on their school reports. Cultural
development is aided by such activities as acting and choral singing. At least one quarter
of the cost of each outing or holiday must be raised by the companions themselves, the
parents or the Association helping with the remainder. Non-political and non-denomina¬
tional, the Association strives to bring about a thorough intermixing of children from every
section of the community and then to bring them in contact with children from other lands.
and Lapps they met towards the end of
their journey north, they had to resort
to sign language. But they managed all
right and even had some fun doing
so as boys would. For young boys can
achieve "international understanding"
in a host of ways swapping badges or
other souvenirs, or just playing a game
of ball in which everybody can join."
The trip though did make them see one
thing clearer than ever : how important
it is to know at least one other foreign
language.
The whole journey, to all the boys,
was an event, filled with duily surprises
and wonderment. Each had his own
story to tell his parents and friends
when he got back to Paris. Jean-Pierre
Beytout, a 13-year-old lad who wants to
be a chemist, told anyone who would
stop to listen how the reindeer and the
Laplanders live, about the great pine,
forests and the stretches of lonely steppe
he had seen.
The caravan's journalist and 14-year-
old man of letters, Jean-Jacques Jausse-
ly, described Lapland as "a combination
of the Far West with its log-cabin
villages, the Far North with its" lakes,
its mountains, its forests exploding with
colour, its Laplanders with their cone-
pointed bonnets, their heavy boots and
many-coloured costumes, their great
herds of semi-wild reindeer..."
"We met trappers, salmon fishers,
lumbermen and pioneer farmers living
in houses built of rough-hewn logs set
in forest clearings,1" he wrote. "We
often wondered if we were in Canada
or in the land of the Mohicans near one
of the American Great Lakes. And we
wouldn't have been a bit surprised if
one of Fenimore Cooper's Indians had
suddenly leaped out at us from the
undergrowth.".
The oldest boy in the" group was
Michel Clavelloux, a future engineer.
He has bagfuls of amusing stories to tell
about their adventures. With . a loud
guffaw, he explains, for example, how
his friend Jean-Pierre was the victim of,
his own gluttonous appetite. Gulping
down a huge mouthful of grated cheese
in a Stockholm restaurant he turned a
quick lobster-red and choked the
cheese was horse-radish ! .
He also tells the story about the
Finnish boy they met on a beach. He
liked the French so much and was so
overjoyed to meet a group of Parisian
boys that he rushed off to a shop with
his swimming trunks dripping wet,
crying "Francos ! ooh, Francos !" and
returned loaded with sweets.
The trip is over now but the memories
remain. And, in addition to the memo¬
ries each of them will cherish for years
to come, .they have all brought back
some souvenir : a Lapp hat, a reindeer
skin, reindeer antlers, or the alarm
clock that'rang at 10 o'clock every night
(in broad daylight) to remind them it
was time for bed. The most exciting
trophy of all though, is the huge wolf-
. skin a Laplander sold them.
Back in Paris now, there are new
plans a-brewing ... Canada ... the United
States ... the South American Andes ...
But Professor Tue is suggesting a
slightly less ambitious trip just a tour
around the entire Mediterranean coast¬
line by road. This would be a combined
study-tour and holiday for three months.
So while Jean-Pierre, Michel, and
Jean-Jacques are already pouring over
the map of North Africa, Professor Tue
is counting figures and adding up his
worries.
Because you see they haven't quite
finished paying for the motorcoach yet.
BOYS TO REACH THE ARCTIC CIRCLE AFTER THEY AND THEIR " MOBILE CLASSROOM " HAD CROSSED BY FERRY FROM DENMARK TO SWEDEN.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
YOUTHFUL ADVENTURERS IN SCIENCE
by
Gerald Wendt
HOLLAND. A Hobby
Club In Amsterdam watches
-a demonstration of a voice
and sound recorder with
which they can record and
hear their own voices. Some
of the members will then
build their own recorders
from spare parts and sup¬
plies which they buy with
their savings. Hobby clubs
are popular in Holland. Most
are devoted to radio tech¬
niques, photography, che¬
mistry, biology and phy¬
sics but also include carpen¬
tering, metal-working, draw¬
ing and the building of
models. They obtain some
financial support from Dutch
industries. The demons¬
trator in the picture- is
Mr. Leonard de Wies -who
has written a handbook
for Unesco on the organiz¬
ation and activities of science
clubs, (not yet published.)
ALL children are born explorers.
Before they can talk they explore
the world around them, looking,
feeling, listening, tasting. They explore
their own bodies, then their clothes and
toys, then the room around them. They
learn by experiment, not by words. Later
they ask endless questions. The world
is mysterious and wonderful to them, and
their curiosity is a natural human im¬
pulse. It is the same impulse that gave
mankind all its ^discoveries and all
science.
It is a precious source of pleasure and
of understanding for a lifetime If it is
kept alive. ' But there is much to learn
and schools must compress it all into a
few years. And so children soon must
learn from books and from teachers who
tell them the answers. There is not
time to explore, to discover, to prove
what the teacher or the book says. So,
too often, the instinct to explore is lost
and the child becomes a docile learner
who can memorize his lessons without
thinking and without questions. Such
children lose both the joy of exploration
and the ability to face gladly the many
problems that life brings and that cannot
be answered from books.
Many modern schools, especially in the
advanced countries, provide workshops,
laboratories and field trips under the
supervision of a teacher who does not
teach so much as he stimulates the chil¬
dren to learn for themselves. They
study the plants and animals of their
locality under the conditions of nature
and soon grow their own plants and raise
their own pet animals. They make their
own equipment in the workshop and do
their own experiments in electricity, with
light and sound, or in chemistry. They
learn accurate observation, learn the
laws of nature by discovering them for
themselves and, above all, learn to think
with precision. Indeed, they acquire the
habit of research which is the very
essence of science.
But in many countries the official
curriculum does not yet provide such
opportunities, partly because laboratories
are expensive and partly because busy
teachers have no time for such methods.
There the science club has its place.
The boys and girls organize it informally
under the guidance of an older person,
who may be a friendly teacher or a gra¬
duate of the school, a physician, some¬
times even a priest or a minister, or
perhaps some parent who enjoys scien¬
tific experiments. They can often impro¬
vise their own equipment and materials
and always work together in a spirit of
adventure and constructive play. Some
clubs are made up of young children in
the primary school, some do more. ad¬
vanced work based on -their studies in
secondary school, and others are compos¬
ed entirely of adult amateurs who find
relaxation and pleasure in scientific,
experimenting.
There are such clubs in many countries,
perhaps in all. And there are clubs in
almost every kind of science. A large
number are nature-study clubs, whose
activities include trips to the woods and
fields, to the ponds and streams, for the
collection of plants and the observation
of animals living in the wild. Some
specialize in birds or butterflies, some in
snakes or even in worms. Most of them
start their own gardens for wild flowers,
for mosses or for edible vegetables.
Others conduct aquaria for the culture
of , fishes or terraria for worms, small
reptiles or insects.
Closely related are the agricultural
clubs that study the best methods of
farming and raise their own food crops or
domestic animals. These children have
more time to learn than their parents
do and often -teach their fathers
new tricks in farming and even their
mothers new ideas in housekeeping.
But older youngsters, and especially
boys, are more likely to organize clubs in
technical subjects such as model air¬
planes, or railroads or automobiles, or
clubs that build radio receivers or even
transmitters and conduct programmes
for their village or their neighbourhood.
Often the boys become inventors and are
led to make a thorough study of the
sciences that are the foundation of their
hobbies. They become the best students
of physics and chemistry in their schools.
Another type of flub, "in industrial
cities, makes trips through factories,
mines, railroad shops and often builds
small models of their processes and
structures. - For this, chemical plants -
such as petroleum refineries, dye works
and drug plants are especially interest¬
ing. Other clubs often specialize in
building demonstration apparatus for
classroom use and thus help the teacher.
In the United States there are more
than ten thousand science clubs with
annual competitions among them and
many successful public science fairs at
which the members exhibit their work.
They are aided by Science Clubs of Amer¬
ica, which provides helpful materials,
such as project lists. (1). There are
several hundred clubs in India. In Hol¬
land, Belgium, Sweden, Germany,' Fin¬
land, there are active nature clubs some
of which undertake international summer
camps.
. If older persons are not attracted to
science it is because in their school days
science was a "discipline". But the
youth of today realizes that the instinct
to explore is natural and that . the
creative activities of amateur science and
hobby clubs are not only fun but just as
satisfying as amateur expression in art.
(1) Clubs may obtain such material by writing
to Science Clubs of America, c/o Science Service,
1719 .\ Street N. W., Washington 6. D. C. U.S.A.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER -N» 1-1954
INDIA. A girl in the science club of the Lady
Irwin Secondary School for Girls at New Delhi
has set up her own testing apparatus and is using
limewater to show that her exhaled breath con¬
tains carbon dioxide. Other members of the club
watch the test and take their turn. Miss K. Sen
Gupta, Principal of the Lady Irwin School, has
written and published an illustrated "Handbook
for Science Clubs in India" for Unesco, which
can be obtained by writing to the Unesco Science
Co-operation Office, C.S.I.R. Building, Old Mill
Road, New Delhi.
UNITED STATES. The sound from a musical broomstick Is playfully analyzed with an oscilloscope. There
are more than fifteen thousand science clubs, with more than 300,000 members, enrolled with Science
Clubs of America, and there are affiliated clubs in 48 other countries. Once a year most clubs give an
exhibition of their work and in 26 states there are state science-club fairs. For the entire nation there
is an annual "talent search". In 1952, 2,264 boys and girls competed in examinations for ten university
scholarships, worth SI 1,000, donated by an industrial corporation.
BRAZIL. Prof. Alberto Mello explains the operation of an electric distribution panel to members of a
science club sponsored by the Sao Paulo Section of the Brazilian Institute for Education, Science and Culture,
the National Commission for Unesco. The objectives of the club are to "train its members in scientific
techniques and methods, to serve the State and the nation, and to'stress the importance of science in every¬
day life". The Institute is organizing a series of clubs in various sciences and in several cities of Brazil.
Prof. Jayme Cavalcantl, Director of the Faculty of Medicine at the University of Sao Paulo, has said : " The
teaching of science in many of our schools is still too bookish. There is too much theory and almost no
laboratory work. At the clubs the opposite is true, and the student's enthusiasm for science develops
tremendously when he can take the Initiative and carry out his own experiments."
GERMAN FEDERAL REPUBLIC. - Members of
the German Youth Society for the Study of
Nature, at Liineberg-Kalkberg, are fascinated as
an expert prepares a bird that is to be stuffed and
mounted. They learn to do this work themselves
and prepare their own exhibits. The Nature
Study Clubs In Germany enjoy exploring the
fields, woods and beaches, especially in their
summer camps. They also exchange visits at
camps and on hikes with the members of Dutch,
Belgian and Swedish nature" study clubs. The
International Union for the Protection of Nature
is co-operating with them.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE DAYS OF
OUR YEARS
Has the time come to change
our present calendar?
JANUARY FEBRUARY MARCH
M
1st
Quarter
S M T W T F S S M T W T F S S M T W T F S
12 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10 11 12 13 14
15 16 17 18 19 20 21
22 23 24 25 26 27 28
29 30 31
12 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 13 14 15 16 17 18
19 20 21 22 23 24 25
26 27 28 29 30
1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 14 15 16
17 18 19 20 21 22 23
24 25 26 27 28 29 30
APRIL MAY JUNE
2nd
Quarter
S M T W T F S S M T W T F S S M T W T F S
12 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10 11 12 13 14
15 16 17 18 19 20 21
22 23 24 25 26 27 28
29 30 31
12 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 13 14 15 16 17 18
19 20 21 22 23 24 25
26 27 28 29 30
1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 14 15 16
17 18 19 20 21 22 23
24 25 26 27 28 29 30
JULY AUGUST SEPTEMBER
3rd
Quarter
S M T W T F S S M T W T F S S M T W T F S
12 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10 11 12 13 14
15 16 17 18 19 20 21
22 23 24 25 26 27 28
29 30 31
12 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 13 14 15 16 17 18
19 20 21 22 23 24 25
26 27 28 29 30
1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 14 15 16
17 18 19 20 21 22 23
24 25 26 27 28 29 30
OCTOBER NOVEMBER DECEMBER
4th
Quarter
S M T W T F S S M T W T F S S M T W T F S
1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 14- 15 16
17 18 19 20 21 22 23
24 25 26 27 28 29 30
12 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10 11 12 13 14
15 16 17 18 19 20 21
22 23 24 25 26 27 28
29 30 31
12 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 13 14 15 16 17 18
19 20 21 22 23 24 25
26 27 28 29 30
Worldsday, (a World
follows 30 December
World Holiday), W or
Holiday), W or 31 C
every year. The Le
31 June follows 30 Ju
ecember (365th day),
ïpyear Day, (another
ne in leap years.
THE WORLD CALENDAR
In this stabilized and perpetual Calendar:
ir Every year is the same.
t*t The quarters are equal: each quarter has exactly 9 1 days, I 3 weeks or 3
months ; the four quarters are identical in form.
Each month has 26 weekdays, plus Sundays.
ir Each year begins on Sunday, I January; each working year begins on
Monday, 2 January.
(V Each quarter begins on Sunday, ends on Saturday.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER -N» 1-1954
AN ANCIENT TIME-KEEPER was the Tower of the Winds in Athens (left). Before the door once stood a sun-dial. A water-clock within told time in cloudy weather.
In one form of such clocks, water dripped through a tiny hole at the bottom of a jar exposing marks telling the hours. At right, two Borneo tribesmen
measure the shadow cast by a stick of fixed length at noon on successive days. When the shadow begins to shorten from its maximal length the time for
preparing the land is near at hand. (Photo left: Copyright R. Viollet; right: British Museum).
THE earth on which we live is a globe,
spinning around on its axis once a
day, revolving in its great orbit
around the sun once a year, and with the
moon revolving around the earth once a
month. It is not an accident, nor is it
good planning, that these three motions
fit so neatly into our time-scale of days,
months and years. The truth is that the
motions are what they are, and have been
for countless millions.of centuries, deter¬
mined by celestial forces since" long
before man appeared on the earth. It
takes just a day for the earth to turn
once on its axis because the word was
made ,to fit the motion. A day is defined
as the length of time it takes for that
rotation. So, too, the words "month" and
' "year" were made to express astronomical
motions that man cannot alter.
Since those three independent astro¬
nomical motions are beyond human
control, we must take them as they are.
It is awkward that they are not related
to each other in any simple numerical
way. It would be much simpler if they
The ancient Egyptians devised many types
of calendar keeping. Their stone obelisks
(left) helped to keep a record of time as the
shadows varied during the different seasons.
The east-west layout of the Pyramids of Gizeh
also enabled the Egyptians to observe the
equinoxes, and when the rays of the setting
sun shone directly down the long avenue of
columns at Karnak it announced the evening
of the summer solstice. Shift to proposed
World Calendar (inset) is to be considered
by U.N. this year.- (Photo R. Viollet).
were arranged by the decimal system, for
instance, so that there Were ten days in
a month and a hundred days in a year.
Or perhaps by the dozen, with twelve
days in a month and twelve months in a
year. But nothing can be done about
that. The fact is that the moon makes
its circuit around the earth in 29 1/2 days,
while the earth makes a complete circuit
of its orbit' in close to 365 1/4 days. Even
without the fractions, these are odd
numbers and there is no simple relation
between them. That is the fundamental
problem of the calendar, with which men
have struggled for thousands of years.
Days must be counted and for human
affairs must be arranged in some sort of
order. There must be established periods
for business, for the seasons and for
. holidays and holy days. But the day does
not fit either the period of the moon or
of the sun, the month or the year. Most
ancient peoples in all parts of the earth
originally chose the motions of the moon
as the basis of a calendar, probably
because the moon's motion is easier to
observe. . So the Babylonian and Egyptian
calendars of six thousand years ago were
based on periods of the moon, and the
Chinese calendar four thousand years
ago also. In ancient Greece, every month
began with the full moon but the year
was counted independently as 365 days.
The Romans combined the two. For
them the year, of 365 days, was basic and
they gave it twelve months, irregular in
length, and not exactly related to the
moon's motion, as we do now. Then
Julius Caesar, in 45 B.C., allowed for that
extra quarter-day in the true year by
giving every fourth year 366 days,' and
thus established "leap-year". That made
the "Julian calendar" which was used
into modern times.
But it was not accurate enough. The
year is not exactly 365 1/4 days long.
It is 365 days, ¡plus 5 hours, 48 minutes
and 45.51 seconds. That is 11 minutes
and 14.49 seconds less than 365 and one-
quarter days. That is not much, but is
enough to amount to 19 hours in a
century and in 1,000 years to make the
calendar about a week behind schedule.
This is precisely what happened under
Julius Caesar's calendar. By the year
1582 A.D., the vernal equinox, when the
sun begins moving northward again and
so marks the first day of spring (autumn
in the Southern Hemisphere), was 10
days late. It came on March eleventh,
although the Council of Nïcea of the
Roman Catholic Church had decreed in
325 A.D. that it was to fall on March
twenty-first. There was nothing to do
but to correct the calendar by taking out
ten days. This was logically and con¬
scientiously done by Pope Gregory XIII.
He directed that the day after October 4,
1582, should be called October 15. Thus
the present, or Gregorian, calendar was
established.
It was immediately adopted by all
Roman Catholic countries but was
resisted by both the Protestant and the
Eastern nations. Thus for several cen¬
turies there was a difference of ten days
(and later even more) in the two systems
of numbering and naming the days.
Great Britain and her colonies did not
adopt the Gregorian calendar until 1752
and Sweden followed the next year. It
was adopted by Japan in 1873, by China
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ASTRONOMICAL OBSERVATORY. From China to Britain stone circles, avenues and menhirs were built over a period of several millenia to serve as astronómica
observatories. One of Britain's earliest sun-calendars is shown here. At Stonehehge (2,000 B.C.), on the morning of the summer solstice, the sun rising behind
the Slaughter Stone was aligned by the Friar's Heel Stone to a point within the Sanctuary. It was the signal that the new year had begun. The principle Is
similar to that used at Karnak, Egypt, the difference being that the temple at Stonehenge pointed to the sun rising at the summer solstice, while the temple of
Karnak pointed to the sun setting at the summer solstice. (Photo by Dr. J.K. St. Joseph, University of Cambridge. Crown Copyright reserved.)
in 1912, by the Union of Soviet Socialist
Republics, in 1918, by Rumania and
Greece in 1924 and by Turkey in 1927.
Simple as the change was in reality, it
was very difficult to put into effect. In
England there was an enormous outcry:
"Give us back our eleven days!" People
thought they were losing eleven days of
their lives instead of merely changing
the names and numbers. So too, today
there are people who think they are
losing an hour of life when daylight-
saving time is introduced and five o'clock
is called six. It is human to resist
change even when it is only a change of
a name or a number.
Pope Gregory made another change to
give the calendar its modern form: he
began the year on January first. Some
nations had begun it on December 25,
some on March 25, as England did, for
instance, until 1752. But the numbering
system had been adopted a thousand
years earlier. In what we now call the
sixth century A.D., a, Roman abbot
named Dionysius Exiguus proposed that
the years should be counted from the
birth of Christ. This was gradually
adopted all over the world, with A.D.
standing for the Latin words "Anno
Domini", meaning "Year of our Lord".
(Actually, modern scholars have found
that Christ was probably born four years
earlier than was thought in the days of
-Dionysius, hence in the year 4 B.C.)
Thus, after repeated changes and cor¬
rections, our calendar has come to us
unchanged for almost 400 years.
How much longer will it serve? There
are many reasons for improving it and
few reasons for opposing any change
except the enormous inertia of habit.
Astronomically it is now correct enough;
the seasons come when they should and,
with the several amendments of the
leap-year rule, they always will. But for
human affairs, and especially for the
conduct of modern business, the calendar
has many awkward features.
The two halves of the year are not
equal, for one thing. The first half has
181 days, the second has 184. Most
people work three extra days during the
second half, without extra pay. So, too,
the quarters vary from 90 to 92 days, and
the months from 28 to 31. The number
of working days in a month (at six days
a week) varies from, 24 to 27. All these
irregularities are unfair to someone and
cause endless irregularities in statistics,
such as banking figures, because months
and seasons cannot properly be compared
with each other.
Another serious defect of the calendar
is that the first day of the month is a
wanderer among the days of the week;
it may be on any day from Sunday
through Saturday and it will not be the
same next year as this year. Thus any
calendar holiday, like December 25, may
come on any day of the week while any
religious holiday, such as Easter may fall
on any date in the month. Only once in
28 years is the calendar exactly re¬
produced.
All this leads to many difficulties in
setting the dates for special holidays,
fairs, elections, the opening of the
legislature, and other public events. At
least in industrial countries it would be
very desirable to have such events as
Christmas and the national holiday fall
always on a Monday in order to give a
"long weekend".
And not to be forgotten are those
unfortunates who were born on February
29 and can have a birthday celebration
only once in four years. Worst of all,
perhaps, is that no one can really know
the calendar as he knows the alphabet. .
There are many who cannot remember
how many days there, are in any par¬
ticular month, August for instance!
Everyone must look to a printed calendar
to keep his dates in mind. Much money-
and paper is wasted annually in all
countries just to keep printed calendars
available to everyone. . In short, the
calendar is complicated and irregular so
that there have been many suggestions
for its improvement, which have recently
grown in number.
The French Revolution adopted a
reform that did not last, which had
twelve months of thirty days each, with
three "decades", or ten-day weeks, per
month. This accounts for only 360 days,
so that there was a five-day holiday
period before the start of the new year,
which began on September 22. Since
then there have been many proposals.
In 1849, Auguste Comte advocated a year
of thirteen 28-day months. This takes
"The Place Where the Sun is Tied" was the name
the Incas gave this huge suntower, hewn from a
single rock, near Cuzco. (Official Peruvian Photo.)
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER- N" 1-1954
days, so that he added a single day
as a year-end holiday. This calendar
had the advantage that the days of the
week always fell on the same dates of the '
month. . /
More recently the League of Nations
examined no less than 152 different
suggestions for improving the calendar.
One of them had a year of 73 weeks, each
week having five days with every fifth
day a holiday. Another had 20 months,
each of three six-day weeks, with leap-
weeks that had seven days five times a
year. Another had a year of twelve
30-day months which were divided into
five six-day weeks. After long study, the
League decided that the week of seven
days should not be changed and eli¬
minated from consideration all proposals
except two.
One was a calendar of thirteen months,
each with 28 days. The other was a
calendar of twelve months with 30 or 31
days in each, but 91 days in each quarter.
Both added up to 364 days and left one
day over as a special holiday. Both of
them retained the seven-day week.
The second of these calendars was the
"World Calendar" which was submitted
to the League by the delegate for Chile.
When submitted to the member nations,
14 were in favour of it, 6 were opposed,
7 considered it premature, and 18 made
no comments. As a result, the fourteen
years of study which the League gave to
calendar reform ended in 1937 with a
committee recommendation to the effect
that "it is not expedient, for the time
being, to contemplate convening a
Conference to carry out a reform which
in present circumstances would have no
chance of being accepted".
But the agitation for a better calendar
,has not ended. Now it is the Economic
and Social Council of the United Nations
which has received calendar drafts from
many countries and from many inter¬
national organizations. In 1950, Peru
submitted the same "World Calendar"
that had been considered by the League
of Nations. Most recently, in October
1953, the delegation of India asked that
the World Calendar be taken up at the
next session of the Economic and Social
Council. In submitting it, the Govern¬
ment of India stated:
"Such a revision has been the subject
of study and research on the part of
experts, institutions and international
organizations for many years. The
concensus of opinion is that a new time
system is necessary, adhering to the
customary twelve months; but that it
should be uniform an invariable ca¬
lendar, perpetually the same, more
regular, scientific and advantageous from
every point of view than the present
Gregorian calendar... The proposed
scheme of The World Calendar has
overcome the drawbacks of the present
calendar. It is scientific, uniform, stable
and perpetual, with but one unvarying
calendar every year."
This World Calendar is reproduced on
page 28.
Its chief characteristics are that each
of the four quarters is the same length,
91 days, and that the first day of each
quarter, and therefore of each half-year
and year, begins on the same day,
Sunday. The first month of each quarter
has 31 days and the next two have 30.
It is therefore more like our present
calendar than the other proposals that
have been made. Its one defect is an
inevitable one, that the year cannot be
divided into seven-day weeks without one
day being left over, because 52 times 7 is
364.
This one day; as in many other ca¬
lendar ideas, would remain as a year-end
holiday. It is proposed to call it "World's
Day" and to celebrate it throughout the
world as an international holiday. The
Indian proposal to the United Nations
describes this day as dedicate'd "to the
universal harmony and unity of man¬
kind". In leap-years, every four years,
a similar holiday would-be inserted and
observed between the 30th of June and
the first of July.
Among the advantages that have been
listed for this calendar are: the first day
of the first month is always a Sunday;
that of the second month is a Wednesday,
and that of the third month is a Friday.
It is a tidy arrangement. There will be
five Sundays in the first month of every
quarter and five Saturdays in the third
month. There will be exactly 52 weekly
pay-days every year.
Best of all, the calendar will be per-
The twelve signs'of the Zodiac in stained glass at the 1900 Paris Exhibition. The zodiac is an imaginary
belt in the skies through which the sun passes each month. Each sign is named after a constellation in that
part of the zodiac 2,000 years ago; but since then the sun and stars have moved and none of the constella¬
tions are in their former zodiacal place. (Photo Viollet).
The Aztec Calendar Stone, discovered in 1790,
is thirteen feet in diameter and weighs over
20 tons. This monolithic block in Mexican
National Museum suggests how the stone was
probably set on a platform.
manent and in future years it will always
be possible to know exactly on what day
of the week any date occurred or when
it will occur in the future. It would be
exactly the same in any year. Railways
would not have to make up new time-
schedules each year. Everyone would
know that Christmas day is always on
Monday. Banks and business houses
would appreciate the fact that the end
of every quarter falls on a Saturday so
that accounts can be closed for the
beginning of the new quarter. Radio and
television stations would be able to count
on exactly thirteen weeks in every
quarter. School terms, too, would profit
by being placed permanently in an un¬
changing calendar.
But there are objections, too. . Many
people will oppose the change merely
because it is a change. But one serious
objection is religious, chiefly because once
in every year and twice in leap-years
more than six days would intervene
between two successive Sabbath days.
Another objection is that the calendar
would be uniform and would destroy
variety which ia the spice of life.
Still another objection is that some
persons who were born on the 31st of
March, for instance, would lose their
birthdays altogether, for if this calendar
is adopted there will be no more thirty-
first days of March, May, August and
December. On the other hand, there
would be four days on which no one has
yet had a birthday because those days,
February 30, April 31, "World's Day" and
the leap year day, are not on the present
calendar. On the other hand, persons
born on February 29 would have a
birthday every year. But these consid¬
erations apply only to persons born
before the adoption of the new calendar.
They would be forgotten after that.
The Indian proposal to the Economic
and Social Council makes it clear why
the U.N. should take up the question of
Calendar reform now. The present
Gregorian and the proposed World Ca¬
lendar coincide on Sunday, January 1
1956, so that the change could be made
at that time with a minimum of fuss, and
everybody would have two years to
prepare for the new calendar.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION
BRINGS MORE VALUE
AT NEW LOW RATES
6/- instead of 10/6 d; #1.50 instead of
#2 00; 300 Fr. francs instead of 500 francs
The Courier is a non-profit publication of Unesco. In order to make
it possible for increasing numbers of teachers and other readers throughout
the world to read the Courier regularly, subscription and single copy
rates have been reduced by almost half. These new prices go into effect
immediately with the present issue. Single copies are obtainable at 7d,
1 5 cents and 30 francs. . >
Existing subscribers: Special arrangements are being made to extend
the expiry dates of subscriptions recently renewed at the old rates. For
example, a renewal starting with the January issue will not expire until
August, I 955; a subscription renewed with the October, I 953 issue will
expire in January, I 955.
Group subscriptions: Special group subscription rates are available
for teachers, students and educational bodies for copies supplied to one
address. Although the rates vary slightly from country to country, the
following are usually applicable:
25 copies & upwards
50 -
I00 -
200 - -
5 % discount
10% -'
I5%- -
20% -
These reductions apply equally to bulk purchases of single copies.
Copies may be ordered in bulk in one or several languages: thus, a subscrip¬
tion for 25 copies in English and 25 in French would benefit from the I 0 %
reduction.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTO RS
Unesco's National Sales Agents from whom the English edition
of the COURIER can be obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
Sales Agents are listed in the French and Spanish editions of the
COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346, Little Collins
Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Fnck Verlag, 27, Graben, Vienna I.
Canada : University of Toronto Press, Toronto.
Ceyton : Lake House Bookshop, The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon, Ltd., Colombo I.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantmides, P.O.B. 473, Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Norregade, Copenhagen.
K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly Pasha Street, Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
formóse : The World Book Company Ltd., 99, Chung
King South Rd., Section I, Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, I 9, Avenue Kléber, Paris
I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutschland, R. Oldenbourg,
München.
Greece : Elefthéroudakis, Librairie Internationale, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan Road, Kowloon.
India i Orient Longmans Ltd. Bombay, Calcutta, Madras :
sub-depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia House,
New Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Himalaya House,
Bombay 7.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Co. NV., DjaJan Nusantara,
22, Djakarta.
Iraq : McKenzie*! Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35. Allenby Road, Tel-
Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Harbour Streef»
Kingston; Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
japan: Maruzen Co, inc., 6 Ton-Nichome, Nilhonbashi,
Tokyo.
Jordan: J. J. Bahous and Co., Dar-UI Kutub, Salt Road,
Amman.
Malayan Federation and Singapore: Peter Chong and
Co , P.O. Box I 35, Singapore.
Malta: Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway, Valletta.
Netherlands: N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhouc 9,
The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications Centre, 7 De Lacy Street,
Dunedin, N. D. 2.
Nigeria: C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos.
Norway: A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingspiass 7, Oslo.
Pakistan: Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore, Peshawar.
Philippines: Philippine Education Co., Inc., I 104 Castillejos,
Quiapo, Manila.
Surinam: Radhakishun and Company Ltd., (Book Dept.),
Watermolenstraat 36, Paramaribo.
Sweden: A B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl. HovbokhandeljFredsgatan 2,
Stockholm 16.
Thailand: Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9, Raj-Damnern Avenue,
Bangkok.
Union of Burma: Burma Educational Bookshop, 55 1-3
Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
Union of South Africa: Van Schaik's Bookstore, Ltd., P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom: H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S.E.I.
U.S.A.: Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New
York.
LANGUAGE JIGSAW PATTERN
(Continued from page J)
great burgeoning of new official lan¬
guages on the Asian model is well within
the bounds of probability.
This very hasty scamper across the
continents has been undertaken mainly
to help the reader catch a glimpse of the
outline at least of the shadowy forest of
language, a forest which like the one in
Shakespeare's Macbeth is threateningly
on the move and never stationary.
Anyone who wants to take a closer look
at the individual trees of this forest
would be well advised to consult a recent
Unesco publication, The Use of Verna¬
cular Languages in Education (1), which,
in addition to much detailed information,
gives, in an appendix, a useful tentative
classification of the world's languages.
There remains the question of the so-
called link-languages, those languages
which are widely distributed over the
earth's surface or at least spoken by
many millions of men and women.
Estimates of the actual diffusion of such
languages vary greatly, but the list of the
13 languages spoken by 50 million people
or over which Professor Mario Pei of
Columbia University gives in his sti¬
mulating book, The Story, of Lan¬
guage (2), is probably accurate enough
for the layman. His list runs as follows:
1. Chinese (all dialects) : 450 million.
2. English: 250 million. 3. Hindi-Urdu:
160 million. 4. Russian: 140 million.
5. Spanish: 110 million. 6. German:
100 million. 7. Japanese: 80 million.
8. French: 75 million. 9. Malay: 60
million. 10. Bengali : 60 million. 11
Portuguese: 55 million. 12. Italian: 55
million. 13. Arabic: 50 million.
There is, of course, no guarantee that
the same 13 languages will appear in the
same order fifty years from now, or even
that such lists, drawn up in the not too
remote future, will necessarily show
Western languages in such an ad¬
vantageous position. In any case, people
,who speak a world-language as their
mother tongue should recognize their
good luck but refrain from being arrogant
about it. Above all they should refrain
from attributing this wide diffusion to
the intrinsic merits of the language in
question. AH languages, be they those of
"primitive" or "civilized" communities,
adequately express the concepts of the
culture from which they spring and of
the people or peoples who use them. All
lead the learner by the straightest and
surest road, perhaps by the only road, to
a knowledge and true understanding of
other cultures and other peoples.
Nor can one distinguish between
"'beautiful" languages and "ugly" lan¬
guages without falling into the same
absurdity. To people speaking a lan¬
guage with few gutturals or none at all,
German may appear "harsh" and Arabic
even "harsher", but are they "harsh" to
those who speak German or Arabic?
Assuredly not.
That wise old man Voltaire went
straight to the heart of the problem in
his philosophical tale L'Ingénu, for when
the Abbé de Saint Yves asked the in¬
genuous Huron which language he
preferred, Huron, English or French, that
simple American Indian replied, "Huron,
of course". Our own language is always
the best for us. All the more reason for
not imposing it on others.
(1) Available' through - Unesco National
tributors. Price $ 1.00 ; 6/- ; 300 fr.
(2) George Allen & XJnwln. London, 1952,
Dls-
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
AJANTA
MASTERPIECE OF
ROCK-CUT TEMPLES
AND OF FRESCO ART
ONE day in 1817, some British soldiers
on manoeuvres in the rugged,
wooded region of western India
inland from Bombay made a startling
discovery that was soon to arouse the
enthusiasm of the entire world of art. .
Some four miles from the tiny village
of Ajanta, in the State of Hyderabad,
they chanced upon a steep ravine formed
by the source of the river Waghora which
drops over a bluff 70 to 80 feet high in a
series of seven waterfalls. Scrambling
to the bottom of the ravine, they stopped
short in utter amazement. Before their
eyes they beheld a long row of cave tem¬
ples, hewn of the solid rock of the
precipitous wall.
Thus it was, by pure accident, that the
rock-cut temples of Ajanta today re¬
garded as one of the most remarkable
sights in India and among the noblest
memorials of Buddhism in the country
emerged from their millenial oblivion.
Here, Ln.the pre-Christian era, Indian
artists slowly, laboriously and patiently
had chiselled the steep, precipitous crust
of the rocks and through the centuries
laid the foundation of the great art tra¬
dition of Ajanta.
The caves, 29 in number, excavated by
Buddhist monks date from the second
century B.C. to about the end of the
sixth century A.D., and comprise a
series of halls of .worship (Chaityas) and
monastic living quarters (Viharas).
In one of the great Chaityas (Cave No.
X) there is a huge assembly hall with a
barrel-shaped roof supported by 39 dec¬
orated pillars. The hall measures over
95 feet in length, 41 feet in width and 36'
feet in height an amazing space to
hollow out of solid rock. In Cave No. I,
the veranda is 64 feet long, 9 feet wide
and 13 feet high. A door in the centre
leads into the central hall which is 64
feet square. The ceiling is supported by
UNESCO COURIER - N" 1-1954
INTERIOR of one of the 29 cave-temples of Ajanta in India showing richly carved and decorated pillars,
walls and ceiling. These temples are among the noblest memorials of Buddhism in India.
PARTIAL VIEW of Ajanta temples carved out of-
solid rock of steep ravine. Site was accidentally
discovered by soldiers In 1817.
a colonnade of 20 pillars surrounded by
aisles over 9 feet wide. Most of these
are decorated by carvings and sculptures.
Beautiful as the -architecture and
sculpture are, however, it is the fresco
paintings that have caused the greatest
admiration. When the caves were first
discovered the frescoes were fairly well
preserved, but today only a few caves
still retain, in varying degrees of preser¬
vation, the wall paintings that once
adorned all the caves.
Centuries of neglect have deposited a
veil of patina on the walls. But through
it can be seen even today the whole scale
of colours:, glowing browns reddish,
greenish, chocolate, and almost black
set off by lapis blue, pearly white, crim¬
son and green.
The walls - are covered with such a
variety of forms and figures, so vibrant
with life, that the earliest Europeans who
saw them could not believe that they
were religious. But the main theme of
the Ajanta paintings centres round the
Jataka stories, the legends of Buddha's
reincarnation. Human life, with its
drama of love, compassion, happiness,
death, suffering and sacrifice, is illumi¬
nated by a glow of religious feeling and
profound piety.
In the Intermingling of human beings,
plants, flowers and animals there is a
feeling of the deep and intimate spiritual
kinship among all forms of life. A broad
humanitarianism is sensed in all the
paintings and the tenets of Buddhist
thought are conveyed through simple
stories such as the one of Sibi Jataka (in
Cave No. I) .
According to Sibi Jataka, a hawk was
once- chasing a pigeon who, unable to
escape from his enemy, flew and took
shelter with the king of the Sibis. This
king was none other than the Compas¬
sionate Bodhisattva. The hawk came
to the king and demanded the surrender
of the pigeon as his lawful prey. The
Great Being, to redeem the life of the
pigeon, cut out an equal weight of flesh
from his own body and gave it. to the
hawk, thus saving the pigeon from death.
Similar sentiments are expressed by
Slokas (or verses) in some of the caves,
such as the one in Cave II which says:
"Blossoms are the ornaments of trees, it
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
MONUMENTS OF A
GOLDEN AGE IN
HINDU CULTURE
is flashes of lightning that adorn the big
rain clouds, the lakes are adorned by
lotuses and waterlilies; but virtues
brought to perfection are the proper
ornaments of living beings.''
Historically, the caves of Ajanta are
associated with the Vakataka and Gupta
dynasties under whose patronage Indian
painting and sculpture reached new
heights in the fifth century. This period
is often called the Golden Age or the
Hindu Renaissance. During this era
religious ideas developed and changed
without persecution. This was the
Golden Age of Sanscrit literature and
music and of the development of scien¬
tific thought and mathematics.
Although the supremacy of the Guptas
lasted only from 320 A. D. to little beyond
495 A. D., the renaissance in art which
they ushered in continued into the sixth
century A. D. Painting in the Ajanta
caves, however, was already a developed
art much before the Gupta age. But
like most other arts flourishing under the
Guptas, the Ajanta paintings reached
their maximum height of glory and
splendour in the fifth century. - With
THE COMPASSIONATE BODHISATTVA with lotus In hand. This painting Is considered one of the great
pieces of Ajanta Art. Cave I. It has been compared to the great figures of Michelangelo.
the sudden decline of the Gupta suprem¬
acy, a decline set in so that by the
eighth century the art of fresco painting
had lost all its vigour, grace and vitality.
The paintings of Ajanta hold a su¬
preme position in Asian art history.
They have for Asia and the history of
Asian art, the same outstanding signifi¬
cance that- Italian frescoes have for
Europe and the history of European art.
For the tradition of Ajanta, bound up
with the history of Buddhism in its
successive stages, gradually spread out
towards countries such as Indochina,
Indonesia and Malaya, Korea and Japan.
In China, it directly influenced and sti¬
mulated the art of the T'ang dynasty,
and the recent discovery of frescoes in
Central Asia, in Khotan, at Turfan and
at Tunhuang, have helped to increase
the interest inspired by the Ajanta
paintings.
The frescoes of Ajanta are generally
considered to be "the greatest monument
of this art" in India. One Italian
authority on fresco painting has said that
they "will bear comparison with the best
that Europe could produce down to the
time of Michelangelo/'
And speaking of one of the finest of
the Ajanta paintings the Compassion¬
ate Bodhlsattva (see photo, left) the
French Orientalist, René Grousset has
said: " "This is a figure that must be .
placed in world art alongside the highest
incarnations of the Sistine Chapel,
alongside those drawings most inspired
with a soul such as the drawing of Christ
In the Last Supper by Leonardo da Vinci."
As the first of a new Unesco World Art
Series devoted to the rare art master¬
pieces of the world, the New York
Graphic Society Is publishing by arran¬
gement with Unesco, an album of colour
reproductions of the Ajanta cave
paintings. (1).
In a preface to the portfolio, Prime
Minister Jawaharlal Nehru has summed
up the importance of Ajanta. "Ever
since the Ajanta frescoes were redis¬
covered and became generally known,"
he writes, "they have exercised an in¬
creasing influence on our thought and
on Indian art generally. They bring
out not only the artistic traditions of
1,500 years ago but make vivid the life
of those distant periods... History
becomes human and living and not
merely a record of some distant age
which we can hardly understand.
"Thus the appeal of Ajanta is not
merely to the artist or the expert, but to
every sensitive human being. Anyone
who would understand the past of India
must look at these frescoes which have
exercised such a powerful influence not
only in India but in distant countries
also.
"If I were asked to name three or four
places of paramount interest in India,
which give some glimpse into India's
mind in successive ages, I would mention
Ajanta as one of them."
(1) Unesco World Art Series. Volume I. "In¬
diaPaintings Prom Ajanta Caves". Introduction
by Madanjeet Singh. Preface by J. Nehru.
Price : $15, or equivalent. Available February
1054.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
AN APSARAS (celestial nymph). Cave XVII. A PALACE SCENE. (Cave XVII.)
THE CEILINGS of several of the Ajanta caves are covered with an amazingly rich variety of forms and figures, human beings, plants, flowers and animals.
Here are shown three decorative motifs on ceiling of Cave I.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
>
AJANTA The frescoes in the Ajanta caves of India, dating from the second century B.C. to the seventh century A.D.
and discovered by accident in 1817, constitute a rock picture gallery unique in the history of art. The appeal 1
of Ajanta is not merely to the artist or expert but to every sensitive human being. The fragment shown here is taken from a new album
of colour reproductions which Unesco is publishing to make these treasures better known to people everywhere. (See page 33.)
]]>
</page>
</document>
