<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078294eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^ >*\l A window open on the world
nLourier
November 1972 (25th year) - U.K.: 13p - North America: 50 cts - France: 1,70 F
A 21-point
strategy
for a global
revolution
in education
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
mmÊS ifjjH
Neolithic potters
of the Danube
TREASURES
WORLD ART
ROMANIA
Photo © Agerpres, Bucharest
Romania is rich in traces of
civilizations that flourished
on its soil from prehistoric
times, and in recent years
astonishing examples of Ne¬
olithic art have been recover¬
ed from the banks of the
Danube. Here, between 3000
and 2000 B.C., lived farming
and animal-rearing peoples
whose culture developed to
a remarkable degree. They
excelled in the art of painted
ceramics and fashioned stat¬
uettes and vases in elaborate
forms, such as the stylized
human figure (left) . The work
bears a remarkable resembl¬
ance to certain urns and vases
dating from around 1 000 A.D.
found in northern Argentina,
a distinctive example of
which (below) was repro¬
duced in the May 1972 issue
of the "Unesco Courier".
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
NOVEMBER 1972
25TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 12 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
1972
International
Book Year
Page
10
12
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
Annual subscription rates: £1.30 stg.; $5.00
(North America); 17 French francs or
equivalent; 2 years :£ 2.30 stg.; 30 F. Single
copies : 1 3 p stg. ; 50 cents : 1 .70 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese, Italian, Hindi, Tamil, Hebrew and Persian. For list
of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER," plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier Is indexed monthly In the Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Con¬
tents - Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7», France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editors
: Ronald Fenton (Paris)
: Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
: Francisco Fernández-Santos (Paris)
: Georgi Stetsenko (Paris)
: Hans Rieben (Berne)
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: Kartar Singh Duggal (Delhi)
: N.D. Sundaravadivelu (Madras)
: Alexander Peli (Jerusalem)
: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Howard Brabyn
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Illustrations : Anne-Marie Maillard
Research: Zoé Allix
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be eddressed
to the Editor-in-Chief
14
18
20
21
24
26
33
34
BLUEPRINT FOR A ' LEARNING SOCIETY
By Antony Brock
EDUCATION AND THE DESTINY OF MAN
By Edgar Faure
ANATOMY OF A WORLD CRISIS
THE EGG AND I...Q
Photo report
BRITAIN'S 'OPEN UNIVERSITY'
REVOLUTION IN LEARNING
FOR 770 MILLION PERSONS
Photo report
21 -POINT PROGRAMME FOR A GLOBAL
STRATEGY IN EDUCATION
PHILADELPHIA'S ' SCHOOL WITHOUT WALLS '
Photo report
ART FROM THE SOUND OF MUSIC
Photo report
BOTANICAL GARDEN FOR THE BLIND
Photo report
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
UNESCO NEWSROOM
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Neolithic potters of the Danube (Romania)
A WORLD INQUIRY
INTO EDUCATION
In 1971, Unesco set up an International
Commission on the Development of
Education. The conclusions of the
Commission's world-wide inquiry have
just been published by Unesco and offer
a bold blueprint for tomorrow's children
and adults alike. This issue is devoted
in its entirety to this unique study and
its guidelines, which, if adopted by
nations, could well serve as an answer
to the world crisis in education.
Cover design executed for the "Unesco
Courier" by Keith Paul,
Photo © AI Cooper, Macclesfield. U.K.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
BLUEPRINT FOR A
'LEARNING SOCIETY'
by Antony Brock
UNIVERSAL MAN. Detail of a monumental
sculpture in wrought iron executed by two Turkish
artists, llhan Koman and Cetin Kanra. Inspired
by a famous motif of Leonardo da Vinci, the
complete work is 13 feet high and 30 feet wide.
It figures in a travelling exhibition now touring
Sweden, and is seen here in a Stockholm square.
II F an international commission
which has just reported to Unesco is right, education
throughout the world is likely to change out of recognition
in the next generation.
To begin with, education will start much earlier as the
importance of pre-school education is more widely recog¬
nized; then it will never end, for the signs are that the
concept of lifelong education, already an ideal, is about
to become a practical reality. Examinations, the bane of
every student's existence, may wither away, for they will
be meaningless to people who are learning at their own
pace. Fixed subjects and curricula are likely to go into
the melting pot and schools themselves, if not as physical
locations then at least as places exclusively for children,
are threatened with extinction.
Above all, spirit and aims will change: the emphasis will
be on learning, not teaching, and education's products will
s . i *' >
*n o
i)
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
not be measured in terms of so much knowledge dispen¬
sed but of completely developed human beings.
The International Commission on the Development of
Education which arrived at these conclusions was called
on to make proposals that would help governments work
out strategies to meet their own educational situations (1).
The Commission drew on educational experience through¬
out the ' world. Furthermore, the composition of the
seven-man commission which included members from
France, Syria, the People's Republic of Congo, the Soviet
Union, Chile, Iran and the United States makes the fact
that they were able to reach wide agreement remarkable
and compelling.
M OR the ordinary reader, two
things are perhaps particularly striking in the Commission's
report: its understanding and even acceptanceof the
reasons for youth's rebellion against present-day education;
its belief that lifelong education Is not just a theory but
already a fact which educational systems should take
account of to help people cope in a changing world where
the quantity of knowledge increases faster than individuals
can keep pace with, and where, in some countries, half the
working population are in jobs that did not exist at the
beginning of this century.
Striking, too, is the commission's analysis of what edu¬
cation has been and is now: in other words, its diagnosis
of what is wrong with it. In the commission's view, man
is a learning animal. Learning is both natural and necessary
to him but the systems he has set up have all had a
tendency to set out to be a system and to end up as a
straitjacket.
Why? Because the tradition they were established to pass
on became a dead weight, because school became an
institution instead of an approach to life, because there
was too much emphasis on the written word, too much
subject-division, too much authoritarianism in a word, too
much school and not enough learning.
The present situation, the commission finds, is paradoxi¬
cal. There has never been so much demand for education
(between 1960 and 1968, the total number of school-age
children in the world increased by 20 per cent); and there
has never been so much dissatisfaction with, and rejection
of, education by the young. Never before has so much
education been provided but never has society so widely
rejected the product of institutionalized education, as the
increased rate of educated unemployed in many countries
goes to show.
What is to be done about the situation? The Commission
does nbt lay down ground rules for the educational sys¬
tems of the world. But it does suggest guidelines, and
from its considerations of the possible strategies to be
adopted a number of watchwords for educational reform
emerge. Among these are democracy, flexibility and con¬
tinuity.
The move towards democracy in schooling has several
causes, Including the general demand for qualified labour
to meet the demands of stepped-up technology. In some
countries ideology is behind the move, in others, the con¬
sequences of decolonization. In some cases the spur is
even the fear of social unrest. But the report points out
that there is a wide gap "between a decision of principle
to provide universal education and the democratization of
the systems, for, as they are currently structured, inequa¬
lity is built into them. "The universal right to education, in
which contemporary civilization takes such premature
pride", says the commission, "is often refused to the most
underprivileged."
Nutrition, family background and factors like housing all
(1) The report of the International Commission on the Development
of Education has been published under the title "Learning to Be' as a
Unesco-Harrap co-edition (see Inside back cover). In addition to the
French language edition ('Apprendre a être', published as a co-edition
Unesco-Fayard, Paris) editions in Arabic, Iranian and Spanish are In
preparation and publication in ten other language editions Is planned.
play a rôle In success at school. Throughout the world,
the disparities between social classes are strikingly reflec¬
ted in university enrolments.
Merely multiplying schools is not the answer. What is
needed is not equal treatment for everybody, but provision
for each individual of a suitable education at a suitable pace
for his particular needs.
Real solutions to the problems of inequality can only
be found in a sweeping re-organization on the lines of
permanent, lifelong education for "once education becomes
continual, ideas as to what constitutes success and failure
will change. An individual who fails at a given age and
level in the course of his educational career will have other
opportunities. He will no longer be relegated for life
to the ghetto of his own failure.
"Human beings, consciously or not, keep on learning
and training themselves throughout their lives, above all
through the influence of their environment."
Recognition of this should bring revolutionary conse¬
quences: not the extension of school by evening classes
but the integration of child and adult education; not the
occasional use of television to supply the lacks of
schooling but whole-hearted employment of media which
already teach as much and more as lessons. Education
"first helps the child to live his own life as he deserves
to do but its essential mission is to prepare the future
adult for various forms of autonomy and self-learning".
Schools, insofar as they continue to exist as we have
known them, cease, under this system, to be reserved
to children and become places of learning for future and
present adults. Pupils cease to regard learning as the
acquisition of a certain quantity of knowledge within a cer¬
tain time; teachers cease to be time-keepers and progress-
chasers and become channels through which pupils can
get at the knowledge they need.
Flexibility, the third characteristic of the education of
the future, is obviously necessary if lifelong education is to
work. As the divisions between subjects are eroded by
advances in knowledge, curricula will have to change to
meet specific needs grown-ups who want to turn to, say,
radio engineering will not necessarily have the time to
plough through the whole syllabus of heat and light before
they come to sound.
In any case, says the report, flexibility is required by
modern conditions. "At the rate technology is advancing,
many people during the course of their working life will
hold several jobs or frequently change their place of work...
Education rarely equips the individual -for adapting to
change, to the unknown. The world has not yét widely
accepted the principle of a general polytechnical educa¬
tion at secondary levelan education which would gua¬
rantee professional mobility and lead to lifelong education."
Yet such an education has given positive results where it
has been tried.
CONSIDERATION of new tech¬
niques occupies a substantial portion of the report. For the
first time since the textbook, the exercise book and the
blackboard were invented, the "hardware" of the teaching
trade has been substantially increased by a wide range of
audio-visual aids, closed-circuit TV and computers.
The focus of all the innovations of the last ten years
is significantly the same: on self-education, on learning, not
teaching.
This being so, the commission believes that the school
"will be less and less in a position to claim the educational
functions in society as. its special prerogative. All sectors
public administration, industry, communications, trans¬
port must take part in promoting education. In the com¬
mission's view, the trend must be towards the "learning
society".
How this learning society might be achieved makes up £
the last portion of this close-packed report, and its twenty- Jj
one recommendations on the directions of tomorrow's
educational strategies provide plenty of material for thought
and argument (see page 20).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ARCHITECTS OF A NEW
STRATEGY FOR EDUCATION
Right, the seven members of the Inter¬
national Commission on the Development
of Education which carried out a world¬
wide inquiry for Unesco. Comprising
prominent figures from different cultural
and professional backgrounds, the Com¬
mission reached wide agreement on the
problems of present day education and
on guidelines that could lead to their
solution. It proposed a far-reaching pro¬
gramme for world educational reform
based on the principle of lifelong educa¬
tion.
Graphic design executed for the "Unesco Courier"
by Keith Paul, United Kingdom
by Edgar Faure
6
I N many countries today
education is regarded as an excep¬
tionally difficult problem, but all
countries without exception agree it
is a task of the utmost importance.
Everywhere men anxious to build a
better world proclaim education to be
the keystone without which their work
is in vain. In setting up the Interna¬
tional Commission for Educational
Development, Unesco has shown that
it is alive to the political ¡issues of
our time.
Educational systems with long-
established traditions that have stood
the test of time, needing only a few
adjustments to keep them running
smoothly, are now the target for cri¬
ticisms that often question their
whole essence. Youth today is in
more or less open revolt against
established educational methods and
institutions, though it is not always
easy to determine exactly how much
of its general unrest and outbursts of
rebellion may be ascribed to this
specific cause.
In the developing countries educa¬
tional systems of recent date, usually
copied from a foreign model, have
run into trouble.
Emerging from the colonial period,
the developing countries threw them¬
selves wholeheartedly into the fight
against ignorance, which they viewed
quite rightly as an essential prelimi
nary to lasting liberation and real
development.
They believed it would be enough
to wrest the weapon of technical
superiority, as it were, from the hands
of the colonizers. They have now
realized that the models they chose
(which were often already out of date
for those for whom and by whom
they were devised) are not suited
either to their needs or to their prob¬
lems.
Their investment in education is far
beyond their financial capacity- More
graduates are produced than the
economy can absorb, so that many
remain unemployed; this is not only
unprofitable but causes psychological
and social damage so extensive as to
disturb the balance of society.
As they cannot bring themselves to
renounce one of the basic principles
for which so many sacrifices were
made and so many battles fought, they
are faced with an "agonizing reapprai¬
sal". Such a situation calls for an
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
FELIPE HERRERA
(Chile), professor,
University of Chile,
former president of
the Inter-American
Development Bank
1er execu
tive-director of the
International Mon¬
etary Fund.
ABDUL- RAZZAK
KADDOURA (Sy¬
ria), visiting pro¬
fessor at the Nu¬
clear Physics Lab¬
oratory, Oxford
University, and
member of the
I Board of Gover¬
nors of the U.N.
International Atom¬
ic Enerqy Agency.
HENRI LOPES
(People's Republic
of the Congo),
Minister of Foreign
Affairs and former
Minister of Educa¬
tion.
ARTHUR V.
PETROVSKY
(U.S.S.R.), secre¬
tary of the Psycho¬
logy and Physiolo¬
gy of Growth Sec¬
tion of the Acade¬
my of Pedagogical
Sciences of the
(U.S.S.R.
MAJID RAHNEMA
(Iran), former
Minister of Higher
Education and
Sciences and for¬
mer vice-president
of the U.N. Econo¬
mic and Social
Council.
FREDERICK
CHAMPION WARD
(U.S.A.), adviser
on internatio¬
nal education to
the Ford Founda¬
tion, and former
Dean at the Uni¬
versity of Chicago.
Photos Unesco Dominique Roger
effort of solidarity on the part of the
more favoured nations.
Lastly, some States regard their own
educational systems as fairly satisfact¬
ory and there is no authority competent
to say whether they are right or wrong.
They may perhaps be deluding them¬
selves and fail to perceive some deep-
lying deterioration invisible to the
superficial gaze. In that case the
awakening will be a rude one, as
France found in May 1968. But equally
possibly these countries may have
succeeded, by good management or
good luck, in achieving this adjustment
which others find so difficult.
Yet even those modern States
which think they are doing quite well
and are therefore not troubled by any
fears of crisis or pangs of conscience,
do not necessarily .feel that they have
nothing to worry about. On the con¬
trary, they generally pay great atten¬
tion to modernizing and improving their
institutions and methods and are not
afraid to innovate.
But they cannot ignore the rest of
the world.
When they are scaling the heights
of knowledge and power, how can they
fail to feel concern and even anxiety
at those vast areas of ignorance still
darkening our planet, like those other
persistent shadows of hunger and
early mortality?
The great change we are now exper¬
iencing calls in question the unity and
the future of the species and man's
very Identity. The danger lies not
only In the painful prospect of severe
Inequalities, hardship and suffering,
but in a real dichotomy of the human
race, split into superiors and inferiors,
masters and slaves, supermen and
submen.
Among the risks Inherent in this
situation would be not only those of
conflict and disaster (for modern
weapons of mass destruction might
well fall into the hands of deprived
rebellious groups), but the fundamental
risk of dehumanization affecting priv¬
ileged and oppressed alike.
Some people think there is no need
to "dramatize" the current problem.
This is an extremely mistaken view.
The situation we are considering is
entirely new and quite without preced¬
ent. For it does not proceed, as is
still too often repeated, from a simple
phenomenon of quantitative growth.
If we take a broad view of education
through the ages, we see that advan¬
ces in education accompany economic
progress.
In stable societies of the agrarian
type, education Is concerned with the
transmission of skills, traditions and
values. It does not raise any special
problems of its own, as distinct from
social, political and religious problems.
As the pace of economic progress
quickens, the educational system natu¬
rally tends to dispense an increasing
amount of knowledge to an increasing
number of persons, since more elabor¬
ate production requires a more highly
7
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
EDUCATION AND THE DESTINY OF MAN (Continued)
A new commitment to the use of technology
skilled labour force, and in addition,
this labour force promotes further
technical Improvements, as it throws
up inventors and innovators.
In the long term, education Is linked
to social and political development as
well as technical and economic pro¬
gress. Better educated people tend
to assert their rights as citizens and
if there are a lot of them, they press
their claims for democracy.
The view that educational institutions
are purely conservative or even repres¬
sive forces is not correct. Of course,
every Institution is by its very nature
a stabilizing influence, and teaching
implies a tendency to repetition and a
concern with form, formulas and form¬
ulation, in the same way as the prac¬
tice of law. In times of rapid change
this dual aspect becomes more strik¬
ing; education then seems to be an
obstacle to the movement which It has
nevertheless provoked.
H
8
¡ITHERTO, however, there
has been nothing comparable In its
consequences to what we now call
the scientific revolution.
For In fact, much technical progress
was made in earlier days through
scientific observation and the discovery
of "recipes" which involved no special
intellectual grasp of the secret forces
of nature. Only in relatively recent
times have conquests through fund¬
amental research penetrated to the
core of the problems examined, while
at the same time their practical applic¬
ations have entered ever more rapidly
into the daily life of the man in the
street.
The changes wrought by the
18th century industrial revolution and
the early machine age were concerned
with the physical and muscular capac¬
ities of the workers; but the scientific
revolution has invaded the intellectual
field with the automatic transmission
of information over any distance and
the invention and constant improve¬
ment of computers.
This phenomenon necessarily affects
the whole of mankind.
The effects of economic expansion
may differ greatly according to the
region and the social group, but mass
media and cybernetics reach everyone
everywhere.
The scientific revolution thus places
knowledge and training In an entirely
new perspective; man now has new
possibilities of thought and action and
for the first time their context Is truly
universal.
This fact inevitably comes to mind,
but it should be stressed that people
do not always deduce Its logical con¬
sequences.
In the economic and social sphere
people are no longer so easily resign¬
ed to class distinctions or national
disparities as in the days when these
were regarded as ordained by the
natural order of things. Nor are they
resigned to educational underdevelop¬
ment, particularly since they have been
led to believe that education for all is
the key to economic advancement.
The problem of democracy is even
more cogent. All nations now aspire
to democracy, and this has nothing
whatever to do with their GNP or their
enrolment rates. But the democracy
to which they aspire is different from
the type we have known hitherto.
In this field no nation is really satis¬
fied with its performance; and it Is a
field where the development of the
individual personality is paramount.
The technological age brings un¬
deniable benefits and opens up vast
prospects, but there is a debit side
too. Scientists warn us of dangers
on all sides, in terms that sometimes
mask their hallucinatory quality over¬
population to the point where it beco¬
mes inconceivable, destruction of the
soil and the countryside, asphyxiation
of cities, exhaustion of food and ener¬
gy resources, a new Flood caused by
the melting of the polar icecap, mind-
destroying chemicals in the atmos¬
phere, and so on. . .
Some do not hesitate to propose
the complete halting of growth "zero
growth" on the grounds of limiting
the damage; while others, without
openly going to this extreme, advocate
a revival of Malthusianism in the guise
of an "ecology policy".
Such solutions would ultimately con¬
solidate international disparities and
even accentuate distortions. Growth
must therefore continue, but in order
to exorcise its perils and reduce its
harmful side effects, communities must
be able to establish the necessary
priorities and controls in a democratic
manner, which assumes the presence
of adequately educated, informed and
responsible persons.
Growth oriented towards the quality
of life and the search for equilibrium
in human affairs cannot be left to
governments alone, bogged down in
their problems of administration and
often In systems founded on prejudice.
Only public opinion, If it can shape
world opinion, can manage to impose
simple and obviously essential measu¬
res, yet postponed ad infinitum, such
as a ban on nuclear weapons and the
switching of some portion of the
unproductive expenditure on military
preparations to social purposes.
If the people are to take over this
role, which is within their power, they
must become aware of their identity,
their aspirations, their strength; they
must shake off their fatalism and their
resignation, and this psychological
confidence can only be acquired
through education made available to
all.
'EMOCRACY now appears
to be the only way of preventing man
from becoming the slave of the ma¬
chine and the only condition compati¬
ble with human dignity and the human
intellect, and hence deserves our full
support.
The Commission considered it vital
that science and technology become a
basic element in education of every
type and for all ages including chil¬
dren, adolescents and adults.
Both developed and developing
countries will have to devise very
similar strategies, though their resour¬
ces differ.
In the developed countries the educ¬
ational system always or nearly
always has a dual character: the
education it dispenses is pre-techno-
logical and its social recruitment is
elitist (in the case of higher education).
This is the system with the same
characteristics which has generally
been introduced into the developing
countries, where it has the additional
disadvantage of not being adjusted
to the cultural background or to the
social and human environment.
In both cases, therefore, it is neces¬
sary to move from the pre-technolo-
gical to the technological stage and to
construct a broadly based education
for the people on the foundation of an
educational system limited to. the few,
for whom it was a guarantee of jobs
in the higher levels of the economy
and the administration.
Logically speaking, this dual trans¬
formation should be accomplished in
one operation, but this has not always
been the case.
Surprising as It may seem, countries
regarded as "developed" are faced
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
with an internal situation of educational
Underdevelopment. Students of work¬
ing-class origin exhibit (at least rela¬
tively speaking), symptoms of mal¬
adjustment and failure similar to those
observed in the ex-colonial countries
which adopted a western-style educ¬
ation, lock, stock and barrel.
So the spotlight falls in both cases
on the combined problems of motiv¬
ation and employment, which govern
the Intake and output of the educ¬
ational cycle.
Motivation Is the key to any modern
education policy.
Curiosity, the desire to understand,
to know or to discover, is one of the
basic drives in human nature. Through
the notations devised by science it Is
now possible for the dullest minds to
assimilate concepts which it needed a
genius to discover.
This ought to be the most powerful
motivation, if It were encouraged. But
it is not. On the other hand, the
stimulus of ambition and a good job Is
not strong enough to guarantee the
democratization of higher education in
a number of industrialized countries,
nor even to ensure regular school
attendance in the developing countries.
We then have the paradoxical situa¬
tion that in some regions where only
half the children can get to school,
half of that half fail to settle down and
drop out even in the first cycle.
HE employment motiva¬
tion, on the other hand, cannot secure
real democratization and also has the
serious drawback of giving credence
to the idea that a diploma entitles its
holder to a job of equivalent level.
Graduates who cannot find jobs
corresponding to their qualifications
feel that they have been cheated and
prefer to remain unemployed rather
than demean themselves by doing a
lower-grade job, for which they have
anyway not in fact been trained.
Modern democratic education requi¬
res the revival of man's natural drive
towards knowledge and the simulta¬
neous dismantling of the diploma-em¬
ployment mechanism which in many
cases (even in developed countries) Is
not viable economically.
Some educationists advocate far
more radical action, often based on
the same principles.
Because the educational system is
often obsolete and hidebound, they
propose it should not be reformed but
abolished. Because the school should
be in closer touch with everyday life,
some think it should simply be done
away with. Such views are usually
presented as progressive and even
revolutionary, but If they were in fact
generally adopted, their effects would
be far more retrograde.
The scientific and technical revolu¬
tion, with its mass media delivering an
endless flow of information, and many
other economic and social factors
have greatly modified traditional sys¬
tems of education, revealing the weak¬
ness of some forms of instruction and
the strength of others, broadening the
scope of self-learning activities and
enhancing the value of active and
conscious attitudes in the acquisition
of knowledge. Teaching methods bas¬
ed on reflection are acquiring increas¬
ing prestige.
The problems involved in teaching
and educating students of all ages,
including adults, lead to many forms of
out-of-school learning. Such education
offers a wide range of possibilities
which must be used productively In all
countries. Scorn for out-of-school
education ¡s a relic of the past and no
progressive teacher can hold such a
view.
Yet both now and in the future the
school defined as any agency dis¬
pensing systematic education to the
rising generation is the decisive fac¬
tor in training men fitted to contribute
to the development of society and play
an active part in life.
The Commission's attitude differs
both from the limited approach of
those still hypnotized by existing struc¬
tures and from the ideas of those who
dream of breaking them down and
rushing out into the unknown, with no
thought for the constraints of reality
and feasibility.
The Commission therefore stressed
two fundamental concepts: lifelong
education and the educational com¬
munity. If learning is the affair of a
lifetime and of a whole society, then it
is necessary to look beyond the
reform of "educational systems" and
think of an educational community.
That is the real educational challenge
of tomorrow.
The "age of change" provides us
with the necessary instruments for
meeting the quantitative and qualitative
demand for education which it pro¬
vokes. But we must know how to
recognize and adapt such instruments
for this purpose.
The two major innovations of the
technological age mass media and
cybernetics both relate to information
and are therefore naturally suitable for
applying to learning and education.
Yet little use is made of program¬
med instruction, radio, television, and
especially computers in education.
When they are used, radio and tele¬
vision are external and parallel to
formal education.
All countries, whatever their level of
development, must adopt the large-
scale use of educational technology
and technological principles, or in
other words, post-machinist Intellectual
technologies.
What ¡s a very valuable facility to
the developed countries appears to
the developing countries as the pre¬
requisite for tackling the general prob¬
lem. For most of them educational
innovation offers the only hope of find¬
ing a satisfactory solution in a reason¬
able time.
Present procedures do not offer any
solution for illiteracy affecting a large
fraction of the population (despite the
undoubted progress of functional liter¬
acy) nor in many cases for securing
the generalization and profitability of
school attendance, nor for promoting
adult education and the gradual Imple¬
mentation of the concept of lifelong
education.
The outlook is quite different If it
is decided to introduce the full-scale
use of educational technologies and
especially the dual method of pro¬
grammed instruction and radio-televi¬
sion programmes.
I|F we agree that the time
is ripe for educational reform, that
education is today facing a critical
challenge, that we must all join to¬
gether in rethinking it In its entirety,
then International co-operation and
world solidarity are clearly more
necessary than ever before.
The research organizations that will
have to be set up or extended to
develop forms of technological aid to
education can. benefit all countries.
The need for innovation is felt today
in many developed countries and their
problems are no different in essence
from those of the developing countries
they are trying to help.
The Commission found that present
forms of bilateral and multilateral aid,
the resources available and the basic
conceptions are not commensurate
with the educational requirements of
the world community. And the dispar¬
ity is even greater if renewal becomes
the top priority in educational activity.
Ways of broadening and strengthen¬
ing solidarity must be found. We are
convinced that they can be found
through the action and ingenuity of
countries, peoples, educators, resear- Q
chers, and International organiza- V
tions, especially Unesco, which has
a leading role to play in this field.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ANATOMY
OF
A WORLD CRISIS
10
MNCE the end of the
Second World War, education has
become the world's major activity In
terms of total spending. In terms of
expenditure from public funds, it
comes second only to military bud¬
gets. The tasks it is being asked to
carry out are increasingly complex
and vast, beyond comparison with
anything required of it in the past.
It is vital to every aspect of human
progress and development, and its
place In national and international
policy-making grows steadily.
For the first time in history,
educational development on a glo¬
bal scale tends to precede econo¬
mic development.
For the first time in history,
education is preparing men and
women for radically new types of
societies.
For the first time in history,
some societies have begun to
reject many of "finished products"
of formal education.
This new social, economic and
psychological situation is caused by
the speed-up in structural change and
development, which tends to accentu¬
ate the gap that normally exists
between structures, infrastructures and
superstructures. It shows how easily
educational systems can develop a
time-lag or become maladjusted.
A system designed for a minority, in
the days when knowledge changed
slowly and a person could hope to
learn all he would need for his intellec¬
tual and professional life in a few
years, quickly becomes out of date
when it is extended to mass education,
and when the volume of knowledge
increases at an ever faster pace
during a period of change and
upheaval.
Unequal growth, disparities in social
and economic development, diam¬
etrically opposing trends: all these
conflicts have a strong impact on
educational systems, which find it
difficult to keep up with the demands
of an expanding society.
Those they train, too, find it difficult
to adapt to change; and some socie¬
ties now categorically reject the qua¬
lifications and skills being offered
when these no longer correspond to
immediate requirements. This is
because unequal growth and "stop-
and-go" development can only create
equilibrium in one sphere by upsetting
it In another. Even so, the process
is not a wholly negative one, In spite
of the different re-adjustments it
demands, and the "growing pains"
which the educational world Is under¬
going today.
One other factor should be stressed.
Educational structures have a number
of common traits and trends. These
are far from evident to the same
degree everywhere, but significantly
the same ones appear in various
guises in all parts of the world. Des
pite the many cultural, historical,
economic and Ideological differences
existing among countries, or even
within a single country, education In
this respect, has a global character.
This is shown in a number of
Important ways. The first is the
choice of educational models. When
it comes to choosing between two
basic options highly selective or
open admission it is the latter that
is most often adopted. Many of the
problems industrially developed coun¬
tries are grappling with at present are
the result of a changeover from their
former highly-selective systems to a
more open structure.
Most developing nations opted for
open admission at first, but lack of
resources and the demands of eco¬
nomic development have often obliged
them to resort In practice to varying
degrees of selection. Seeking to
avoid both vocational control based
on a planned economy and laissez-
faire anarchy, they try to find solu¬
tions that reconcile respect for the
individual with the needs of society.
Then there is the adoption of so-
called technocratic systems designed
to train workers and qualified pro¬
fessionals and to promote science and
technology.
A more recent trend in educational
policies stems from the desire to
provide an outlet for the upsurge of
freedom-seeking aspirations from the
broad mass of society. This ten¬
dency Is increasing where economic
CONTINUED PAGE 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
I
Diagram prepared for the "Unesco Courier" by Keith Paul. U..K,
1965-66 1966-67 1967-68
Education's
rising share
of world
spending
World spending on education is increasing at a faster
rate than expenditure on armaments. As shown in the
diagrams above, the gap between the two rates widened
from 0.6 per cent in 1965-66 to 4.4 per cent in 1967-68.
World military expenditure in 1968 totalled $182,000
million, according to the report of the International
Commission. But total spending on education, including
$132,000 million from public funds, and sums spent on
industrial and other training programmes, education
programmes in mass communication and privately finan¬
ced education, was far greater. In the U.S.A., some
industrial firms are spending as much on the high-level
training of employees and customers as the instructional
budgets of some large U.S. universities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
«it* itmilllllfMit»! .'M
f*'
12
THE EGG AND I...Q
Current biochemical research on the brain suggests that
it has a largely unused potential (as high as 90 per cent
according to some authorities) and that under favourable
conditions its creative capacity could be tremendously
increased. Other studies, on mental mechanisms and the
learning process, have revealed the serious effects of
malnutrition on brain development. Under-nourishment in
the mother can make the new-born baby's nervous system
more fragile; malnutrition between the 5th and 10th month
following birth may reduce the number of cells in the brain,
which has virtually finished growing by the end of the
second year. The role of RNA (a genetic substance
controlling protein synthesis) in memory and consequently
in the learning process has also been closely studied,
revealing a link between protein-calorie malnutrition in
infancy and early childhood and impaired learning and
mental retardation in later life. "If such damage has been
done", says a U.N. report on the subject, "the consumption
of extra protein in adult life will not repair it, and if such
damage is widespread in a country, it will be likely to Impede
that country's future development in almost every respect"
Protein malnutrition is also a major cause of death among
infants and young children. A country's efforts to improve
nutrition during the pre-school period, especially up to the
age of four, would improve the performance of its educatio¬
nal system. I.Q., in fact, gets its real start "in the egg".
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
ANATOMY OF A CRISIS (Continued from page 10)
The growing emphasis on self-education
and social development calls for the
active participation of the whole
population.
The transfer of responsibility for
education is also being accelerated.
Until the end of the 19th century, It
was provided mainly by the family
and by religious institutions, grant
schools, apprenticeship guilds and
independent higher-educational estab¬
lishments, whereas today, In most
countries, the responsibility Is that of
public authorities or the State.
There are three main reasons for
this. First, a general tendency to
rely on public bodies to satisfy social
needs. Second, the belief in nearly
all countries that although the State
may allow and in some cases even
encourage private Initiative, It alone
is in a position to assume responsi¬
bility for overall educational policy.
Third, the determination of many
governments to keep control of edu¬
cation because of its ever-increasing
political role.
_ AS regards the structure of
educational systems, several trends
are emerging. Kindergarten educ-
ation, which still remains limited, Is
generally an integral part of the school
system. Primary education is widening
in scope and children begin school at
an earlier age. The number of years
spent at school is increasing too, and
reforms often lead to a link-up bet¬
ween primary schooling and the first
years of secondary education. The
number of children at school is grow¬
ing, and not only at the lowest levels:
enrolment in the higher classes shows
a marked increase.
However, as the school population
increases, there are more drop-outs
and more repeaters. In general in¬
take occurs at the lowest level of the
system and outflow either halfway up
(mainly because of failures) or else at
the top, after successful completion of
studies. Admissions and departures
or changeovers in mid-programme are
still rare, but are beginning to be
accepted. The validity of strictly sel¬
ective systems is questioned be¬
cause of their obligation to do more
to overcome the handicaps suffered
by the most underprivileged social
groups.
In spite of stubborn opposition,
school curricula are beginning to be
made less burdensome. Previous
inequalities in elementary school pro
grammes often the result of social
discrimination are rapidly disappear¬
ing. Instruction is increasingly given
in the mother tongue (1).
There is also a general tendency to
raise the age at which specialization
is required; but this does not prevent
technical and professional education
being increasingly diversified to fit
the growing variety of productive roles.
Cross-links are multiplying between
general and technical education, wide-
ranging cultural courses and specialist
training, the humanities and science
and technology. (Technology now
plays an Increasing role in general
education).
In higher education, traditional uni¬
versities are breaking up into smaller
units, and post-secondary education
as a whole is being widely diversified.
On the one hand, paradoxically, var¬
ious disciplines and facilities are being
grouped in single large establishments
or put under a centralized administra¬
tion ("multi-universities"); while on the
other, smaller, more flexible institu¬
tions are being created to cater locally
for the special needs of certain cate¬
gories of students.
Higher education also tends more
and more to be spread over a number
of different levels. Many new sub¬
jects of study are being introduced,
and interdisciplinary instruction is dev¬
eloping, as well as closer and closer
links with scientific research.
The whole scope of higher educa¬
tion is indeed being widened to meet
the new requirements of a larger stu¬
dent body, to satisfy the need for
expanded research facilities and com¬
munity projects, and to respond to the
demands of those who want the uni¬
versity to act as a catalyst for social
reform.
New kinds of structures, new types
of students and new curricula entail In
turn a thorough revision of selection
and evaluation procedures. Student
participation in the management of
educational institutions and the choice
of teaching programmes is growing.
All over the world, teachers now
constitute a major social and profes¬
sional group; In many developing
countries they form the largest group
of salary-earners.
To all this should be added a grow¬
ing tendency to extend the non-school
sector of education. Adult literacy
campaigns are making headway, and
the distinction between formal elemen¬
tary education and literacy program¬
mes is beginning to disappear.
Schools and universities are supplem¬
ented and sometimes replaced by a
multitude of extra-mural or semi-aca¬
demic activies, which call for the use
of methods long neglected by tradi¬
tional education or only recently intro¬
duced. These developments are of
two different kinds.
First, there are those that take place
within the professional context. A
whole range of programmes provide
civic and vocational training; schools
and other educational establishments
offer advanced courses, retraining or
special coaching; and universities
admit adults without any formal en¬
trance examinations.
Secondly, there are the develop¬
ments belonging to the general cultu¬
ral context. These have freer and
more flexible structures. People are
encouraged to teach themselves, with
the help of information material and
data sources; leisure activities and
social and community projects aim at
promoting participation and helping
people to teach one another.
Increasing stress is also being laid
on the link between educational dev¬
elopment and the many other aspects
of social and economic development.
I OST of the innovations
mentioned above may take various
forms. What counts is that even where
these common trends have not yet
emerged, contrary currents are rarely
found; and there is little indication that
such innovations are likely to be
reversed in the future.
This does not mean that highly di¬
vergent and even contradictory trends
do not exist on other levels. For ins¬
tance, the movement in some countries
is towards centralization, State control
and overall standardization (2). In
other countries, the trend moves to¬
wards decentralization, loosening of
State control and greater variety.
The fact remains, though, that many
developments show a general consis-
(1) In the Soviet Union, s/xty-s/x languages
are used.
(2) In the Soviet Union, for example, where
the basic principles of the educational sys¬
tem have been summed up by Prof. A. V. Pe-
trovsky, a Soviet member of the Commission,
as: "State control and centralized man- 1 Q
agement of public education; universal and | (J
compulsory schooling, free and open at all
levels; -unity and sequence In all types of
education.'
CONTINUED PAGE 16
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photo Open University, United Kingdom
BRITAIN'S 'OPEN UNIVERSITY'
Founded in 1969, "to provide education of university and professional standards . . . and
to promote the educational well-being of the community", Britain's "Open University"
became fully operational in January 1971. Today, with a student body approaching 40,000
it has become the largest university in Britain. No formal educational attainments are
required for admission, the only restrictions being that students must be over 21 and
resident in the United Kingdom. Students are expected to study for a minimum of
10 hours a week, 36 weeks a year. Degrees are awarded to students gaining six "credits";
one credit is granted for each study course completed. Instruction is given through a
combination of radio and television lectures, correspondence courses and direct counselling
by tutors at the 300 Study Centres scattered throughout Britain. Every week students
complete their assignments and send their work back to the University where it is marked
by computer. Each student following a foundation (1st level) course must spend one week
at a residential summer school. Left, aerial view of the Open University's headquarters
at Walton, in Buckinghamshire, some 50 miles north of London. Far left, the sorting room
at the University where assignments are prepared and despatched to some 40,000 students
each week. Below far left, a laboratory technician prepares rock samples. Below centre,
a student housewife unpacks a specially designed home laboratory kit Below, a taxi-
driver does his homework at the wheel of his cab between fares.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
CAUTION! CHILDREN AT WORK
By the year 2000, the number of young people of school and university age
will have grown by more than 1,000 million an average annual increase of
36 million potential pupils and students. From 1960 to 1968, during the first
United Nations Development Decade, the world's total school-age population
(children from 5 to 19 years) increased from 995 million to about 1,150 million,
or by 20 per cent. During the same period, world population increased 17 per
cent, from 3,000 million to almost 3,500 million. In other words, the "population
explosion" contains within it an even more remarkable "pupil explosion". Today'«
rapidly growing demand for learning throughout the world calls for radical economic,
social and educational innovations.
ANATOMY OF A CRISIS (Continued from
tency which is all the more remark¬
able in that the various situations
have evolved under the influence of
very different theories, challenges and
protest movements. These fall into
four major groups.
1. Educational Reforms
The first trend consists In reforming
or reorganizing existing educational
structures and modernizing- teaching
methods. With or without attendant
structural changes on the social or
economic level, reforms of this kind
are in course nearly everywhere.
Steps taken by public authorities, as
well as by scientific bodies and indi¬
vidual educators, have prepared the
way for major Innovations in a num¬
ber of countries (1).
Important changes have also taken
place in developing countries (2),
largely instigated by central govern¬
ments, although lack of means and
bureaucratic inertia sometimes put a
brake on innovation, as those in charge
16
(1) In the United States and Canada many
Important and meaningful reforms have been
Initiated, particularly In modernization of
programmes and the use of teaching machi¬
nes. In the Fed. Rep. of Germany, current
reforms elm at the democratization of
education and the overall development of
secondary education. Reforms are also being
planned or carried out In Sweden, Finland,
Japan, Costa Rica, Mexico, the Philippines,
the Netherlands (higher education) and Cze¬
choslovakia (vocational training). The educ¬
ational policy launched In France In 1968 was
focused mainly on higher education, but It
has had repercussions In other sectors.
(2) As In Bolivia, Brazil, Egypt, Iran, Rwan¬
da, Tunisia and Venezuela.
page 13)
prefer to wait until the results of ex¬
periments undertaken elsewhere can
be studied. In some countries with
very large educational and financial re¬
sources, the extent and gravity of cer¬
tain problems and the failure to cope
with them provide strong arguments
for those who insist that fragmentary
measures are ineffective and who
therefore advocate total reform.
2. Structural transformations
In countries which have gone
through social and political upheavals
in recent years, events have often led
to profound structural changes in the
educational world, affecting student
entries, access to education at various
levels, curricula reform and to a les¬
ser extent the modernization of
teaching methods.
The establishment of closer ties
between schools and the local popula¬
tion is a top priority In countries which
see education as a vast mass move¬
ment, where all those who have re¬
ceived training have a civic duty to
teach those who have not had the
same opportunities (3). Similar con¬
cerns are to be found in countries try--
ing to reduce the domination of the
State and socialize education by mak¬
ing it the direct and active respon¬
sibility of those involved (4).
3. Radical Criticism
The third trend is marked by those
who are in favour of "de-institution¬
alizing" education and "de-schooling"
society. Their theories have not yet
been tried out in practice (5).
Frank criticism or outright condem¬
nation of "Institutionalized" educa¬
tion may lead either to intermediary for¬
mulas or else to radical plans for the
total "de-schooling" of society. These
extremist theories are based on the
Idea that education, being an indepen¬
dent variable in each society, is a
direct cause of social conflict.
The school's position in society and
the power relationships to which it is
subject make it incapable of being the
instrument of a true education in the
service of men. On the contrary, it
serves the purposes of repressive,
alienating and dehumanizing societies.
So according to I Mich, institutions
should be "Inverted" and schools abo¬
lished, so that men may become free
agents again in a society unencum¬
bered by formal schooling, where they
can regain control of the Institutions
and thereby recover the Initiative for
their own education.
Even the most ardent partisans of
these ideas, however, recognize that
while young people can develop their
(3) Two examples are Cuba, with Its literacy
campaign, and the Democratic Republic of
Viet-Nam, with Its people's education pro¬
jects.
(4) As In Yugoslavia, where schools are run
by councils composed of representatives of
teachers, pupils, parents and the local com¬
munity, etc.
(5) The best known proponent of these
Ideas, Ivan Wich, and other of their advo¬
cates meet pt the Inter-Cultural Documenta¬
tion Centre at Cuernavaca. In Mexico. Their
theories, which have often been taken up
elsewhere, draw a clear distinction between
the development of the learning potenVal,
which they recognize, and the Institutionali¬
zation of teaching, which they oppose.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Sri Lanka (ex-Ceylon) Pakistan
characters and acquire knowledge and
understanding by participation in com¬
munity life and from practical exper¬
ience, some form of schooling is still
necessary for certain kinds of learn¬
ing.
In any case, these novel theories,
which closely reflect other movements
among young intellectuals, are chal¬
lenging both for the controversies and
new ideas they stimulate and for the
lively way in which Jhey pose the
basic problem of the true purpose of
education. They help to highlight pos¬
sible openings or solutions from which
other systems, however different, may
well draw inspiration.
4. Dissent
A fourth trend, swelled by the dis¬
satisfactions of the users themselves,
has developed in certain countries ,
where education Is of increasing con¬
cern to politicians, educationists, res¬
earch workers and scholars, as well
as to the students themselves and the
general public.
Analysis of the reactions of work¬
ing-class people confronted with the
rigidity of traditional educational sys¬
tems Is very instructive In this con¬
nexion. Where the school system re¬
mains the exclusive preserve of an in¬
tellectual elite springing from the
middle class which created the sys¬
tem and which continues to impose its
own laws and moral values, students
are often disconcerted by the divorce
between the outmoded education they
receive and the reality of the world
around them. They become frustrat¬
ed, waste their energies, grow bored,
or find some other outlet for their
hopes and aspirations.
Student unrest made its mark on
history when widespread criticism be¬
gan to undermine the hitherto impreg¬
nable fortress of education. Despite
its sometimes confused or naive char¬
acter and its two-edged radicalism,
it opened a breach in the defences.
Admittedly, however, apathy among
the student population constitutes, in
its own way, another form of dis¬
sent. The disaffection or lack of
enthusiasm found among students in
many countries are undoubted signs
that antiquated educational systems
are being rejected.
Yet interest in education has never
been greater. It increasingly becomes
the cause of conflict between parties,
between generations, and between so¬
cial groups of every kind, which often
amounts to political or ideological
strife. In fact it has become one of the
dominant themes of both empirical and
ideological social criticism.
It is easy to see why public figures
are taken aback when their authority Is
challenged not courteously, by a few
informed critics, as in the past, but
massively, by angry criticism of stu¬
dents and even by open revolt. The
reserve and suspicion with which many
of the more revolutionary conclusions
of present day research are greeted
are also understandable.
We believe, however, that all these
forms of dissent, whether tacit or ex¬
plicit, peaceful or violent, reformist or
radical, deserve for varying reasons
to be taken into account when edu¬
cational policies and strategies are
being mapped out for the coming years
or coming decades.
But how can we identify the true
characteristics of the present day
world among this constellation of con¬
verging or divergent trends and
methods, these teeming ideas and gen¬
erous Intentions?
For more than twenty years, atten¬
tion has remained focused on a few
major questions: the quantitative ex¬
tension and democratization of educa¬
tion, the diversification of structures,
and the modernization of curricula and
methods.
A few years ago a new analytical
attitude to the basic problems began
to take shape, which came down in
the end to three essential questions.
Are school systems capable of meet¬
ing the world-wide demand for educa¬
tion? Is it possible to provide them
with the vast resources they need? In
short, is it possible to continue dev¬
eloping education along current lines
and at the current rate ?
To these very pertinent questions
others of a very different order must
be added today, so as to bring out the
full dimensions of the problem as it
affects the future development of
mankind and conditions the full reali¬
zation of the human potential.
Given the present state of affairs,
we can and must inquire into the true
meaning of education in the modern
world, not only reassessing its respon¬
sibilities to the present generations
which must be prepared for tomorrow's
world, but also analyzing its underly¬
ing powers and myths, its prospects
and its fundamental aims or ends.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
'^J,r^JJ
iWe /' / >n
ïpi
A REVOLUTION
IN LEARNING
FOR 770 MILLION
PEOPLE
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
"For the entire nation, the country has today become a vast school undergoing
revolutionary changes", wrote Mao Tse-Tung in 1966 at the start of the reform of the
educational system for the 770 million people of the People's Republic of China. Follow¬
ing the complete renovation of educational structures, no distinction is made between
school" .and daily life, with students and teachers undertaking work of all kinds and
workers teaching and studying. This is the picture that emerges from "Educational
Reform (People's Republic of China)" by Léon Vandermeersch, one of the numerous
reports and studies examined by the International Commission on the Development of
Education. One feature of the new system, says the report, is the educational value
accorded to group manual work (photos bottom left). Photos left show children practising
the transliteration of Chinese into Latin characters by the Pin-yin method. Chinese
characters are still currently used, but are now written from left to right and no longer
only from top to bottom and from right to left in the traditional way. Below, school¬
children at a newspaper kiosk in Peking.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
A 21-POINT
PROGRAMME
for a global
strategy
in education
Lifelong education should be the keystone of all educational
policies in the years ahead, in industrially-developed as well
as developing countries.
The concept of lifelong education
could be applied in as many different
ways as there are countries in the
world. For all countries this question
is the crucial issue of our time.
Educational reforms recently pro¬
posed In Peru, for Instance, call for
a complete restructuring of education,
in and out of school, based on the
principle of lifelong education. Going
far beyond a reform of teaching, the
proposals are directly geared to radi¬
cal structural changes in Peruvian
society. They guarantee each per¬
son's right to choose the education he
prefers, and they aim to create an
education "based on an educational
community designed for dialogue and
responsible participation."
A striking Innovation is the proposal
to split all Peru's educational services
and programmes into "cells", with
communal education cells as the direct
concern of the local community, and
with schools, colleges, universities and
other educational Institutions forming
an Independent network.
20
Lifelong education presupposes a complete restructuration of
education. Education must cease being confined within school
walls. Education should become a true mass movement.
Today's tremendous demand for
education and the demands of tomor¬
row will not be met by present types
of educational systems. Rigid internal
structures need to be broken down
and education offering a far more
varied choice should be made widely
accessible.
In Canada, the Educational Planning
Commission in Alberta Province has
recommended that educational reforms
be centered on the idea of lifelong
education. "Education", it says, "should
develop ability to learn under a variety
of circumstances and conditions, on a
part-time basis, at home using a
variety of methods, and in Informal
settings... We believe that the school-
dominated, classroom-centered, full-
time, teacher-oriented, eight-hour,
eight or ten-month system is an
expensive one, and apart from the
demands of further population in¬
creases, very little additional invest
ment should be placed in this form of
education."
"Lifelong education," in the Com¬
mission's view "Is an integration of
learning Into our work and leisure.
Learning we see as a process of man's
growth towards fulfilment as an
Individual as well as a member of many
groups in societies... The time has
come to accept the principle that edu¬
cation is life and life is education."
CONTINUED PAGE 22
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
lili
1 mill,
[
IM" >ui m,
»h im,,,,
H^ÍHIiii, "i *M
!k* ' !!»
K^ v ! ' ^N^k. hi
^k d-
î
*
i
I i
Photos © USIS
Philadelphia's 'school without walls7
With too many pupils and a shortage of
teachers, school buildings and cash, Phi¬
ladelphia (U.S.A.) was facing an educ¬
ational crisis In 1968. Yet on either side
of Parkway, a broad avenue in the heart
of the city, stood roomy public buildings
such as the Municipal Library, the Benja¬
min Franklin Institute, the Academy of
Natural Sciences, the Fels Planetarium and
the Rodin Museum. Why not use parts
of these buildings as classrooms and the
experts who worked there as additional
teachers? From this idea was born the
now famous "Parkway Program" which, In
just under four years has developed into
the most revolutionary of American educ¬
ational experiments. Pupils, drawn by lot
from thousands of applicants, have a
choice of about a hundred courses. They
are divided* up into working groups of
15 boys and girls under the direction of a
teacher and a senior student For John
Bremer, the Englishman In charge of the
Parkway Program, and a specialist in new
educational methods, "life and education
are all part of the same process". Lessons
may take place in a factory, a garage, a
church, a museum, a bakery or chemical
laboratory. Above, strolling along Park¬
way a sociology group studies community
life. Left, future builders and architects
explore a futuristic plastic house exhibited
in front of the Benjamin Franklin Institute.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
21 POINTS (Continued)
Education should be provided in many ways. What counts is
not how a person has been educated, but what real knowledge
he or she has gained.
Everyone should have greater free¬
dom in choosing what to study, and
interruption of studies should not bar
anyone from resuming them later.
Full-time education, part-time educ¬
ation and education by correspondence
as well as the many forms of self-
education should be regarded as
equally valid and interchangeable in
order to meet a student's needs and
interests.
Many possibilities for education and
learning are available in virtually all
countries and cover a vast spectrum,
ranging from closed systems that tend
to be selective and competitive to
open systems that are generally non¬
selective and more loosely structured.
A great variety of educational activities
and institutions fall between the two
extremes. They Include on-the-job
training, agricultural extension ser¬
vices, community development centres,
clubs, co-operatives, labour and poli¬
tical organizations, etc.
An effort to broaden access to
higher education and offer greater
freedom of choice has been made In
the United States with the "University
Without Walls" programme (similar
experiments have been made in
several other countries).
In the U.S., participating institutions
at present include Antioch, Bard, Hof-
stra, Loretto, Heights, Montelth,
Nasson New College (Sarasota),
Northern Illinois State, Sarah Law¬
rence, Shimer and Stephens.
Basically, the University Without
Walls features: admission for anyone
between 16 and 60 wishing to continue
his or her studies; programmes design
ed to meet individual students' needs
and interests; Inventories of inform¬
ation sources (tapes, texts, laborator¬
ies, personal contacts, etc.); the
possibility for each student or group
of students to organize his or their
own studies; the obligation for each
student to spend at least half the
university year In a campus experi¬
mental centre; and a continual dialogue
between student and tutor.
The University Without Walls teach¬
ing staff includes professors and
teachers attached to a particular
campus, visiting experts from agricul¬
ture or business, scientists, artists
and politicians. A student wishing to
obtain a university degree merely
registers to sit an examination when
he feels ready to do so.
Artificial or outdated barriers between different branches and
levels of education and between formal and non-formal edu¬
cation should be abolished.
The introduction of a global, open
educational system would call for:
greater freedom of movement from
one level or place of education to
another; the right, at the end of com¬
pulsory schooling, to go on studying
or take a job (without forfeiting the
possibility of resuming studies later
on); the opportunity to enter higher
education without having previously
completed the period of formal school¬
ing traditionally required; broader
opportunities for combining work and
education.
All this, in turn, presupposes that
students would be able to leave and
rejoin the education system to suit
their needs; that education and labour
laws would be made more flexible;
that study grants now given to young
people would be gradually extended to
adults; and that workers who wished
to begin or resume studies would be
given greater facilities to take leave
from their employment.
One developing country, Sri Lanka
(Ceylon) has considered the adoption
of a "recurrent" educational system
of this kind. Among other features, It
includes:
the award of an end-of-study certi
ficate to the majority of young people
completing initial education;
immediate admission of a small
number of certificate holders to pre-
university studies;
orientation of all others towards
jobs or technical or professional
education;
the right of all to apply for ad¬
mission to pre-university studies after
two or three years, with selection
based on aptitude tests reserved for
those who have acquired pro¬
fessional experience or working skills.
Education for pre-school-age children should be a major objective
for educational strategies in the 1970s.
22
Education for pre-school-age children
(from the age of 2 or 3) should be orga¬
nized on a free, flexible pattern, finding
the best ways of getting families and
local communities to work together
and share expenses.
Mass communication media are
especially useful in this work when
pre-school education has to be brought
quickly to a large number of children,
especially those living in environments
with a limited cultural background.
Pre-school education is extensively
developed in the People's Republic of
China. Kindergartens are Imaginatively
organized, daily or weekly, to take
care of children aged from 3 to 7.
Some kindergartens are attached to
primary schools; others are provided
by factories or village or district autho¬
rities, or are organized and staffed by
street committees, including many
voluntary helpers. Assistance comes
from many people, especially grand¬
parents.
In the U.S.S.R., more than 9,500,000
children are currently enrolled in
crèches and kindergartens. The kol-
koz pre-school educational establish¬
ments, functioning either permanently
or seasonally, take care of a further
3 million children. Research in recent
years at the pre-school Education
Institute of the Soviet Pedagogic
Sciences Academy and In other insti¬
tutions has shown that young children
are capable of acquiring knowledge,
intellectual aptitudes and moral qua-
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
lities previously thought to be access¬
ible only to much older children.
The most important audio-visual
educational experiment aimed at pre¬
school-age children so far is the
Sesame Street programme in the
United States, and now extended to
Latin America.
It aims to prepare pre-school-age
children from underprivileged envi¬
ronments to enter school in circum
stances similar to those of the average
child. The programme is directed
especially at the working population
in poor districts without kindergartens,
but where nine families out of ten have
a television receiver.
Villagers in the Casamanca region
of Senegal have organized, financed
and are now operating some thirty day¬
care centres under the guidance of
social services. They function during
periods when village men and women
are entirely occupied with work on the
land.
The centres take care of all children
aged from 1 to 7, and also school-age
children before and after school hours.
Staff are recruited on the spot, and
are remunerated in kind or by having
their fields cultivated for them. In
one way or another, everyone in the
village helps the centres.
Millions of children and young persons are still deprived of
education. Universal basic education, geared to national needs
and resources should be a priority objective of educational poli¬
cies for the 1970s.
Global efforts to make primary
education available to all are a long-
term project.
But flexible arrangements that
enable greater use to be made of
existing school space can do much
to remedy the harmful effects of
today's "famine" in education. Such
formulas Include part-time primary
education, combined primary education
for children and adults and special
teaching programmes for teenagers
(12 to 16), especially those who have
not previously attended school.
Tanzania, for instance, uses its inte¬
grated primary schools as centres for
the development of human resources,
serving the whole community.
Classrooms with mobile partitions
are used for adult education, as day¬
care centres and kindergartens, and
large multi-purpose rooms serve,
among other uses, as training centres
for village industries.
igid distinctions between different branches of education
should be removed. Education, from primary and secondary
levels, should have a combined theoretical, technological, prac¬
tical and manual character. I
Technological education will need
to be developed if general education
is to become "general" in the full sense
of the term.
The teaching of general subjects
can produce its full educational value
only when a careful balance is main¬
tained between theoretical studies
and practical work.
In the German Democratic Republic,
for Instance, polytechnic education is
an integral part of the ten-year basic
educational cycle. Polytechnic educa¬
tion Is based on the interaction
between teaching theories and me¬
thods and technology. Research teams
have developed entirely new concepts
for polytechnic education, and the
results of experience and practice are
used as a feedback for further studies
and research.
In polytechnic education, practical,
manual work begins in the first grades,
and from the seventh grade includes
four hours weekly of pre-vocational
training in industry or agriculture or
in polytechnic institutions where stu¬
dents do practical work. The aim is
to familiarize students with techniques
and industrial processes rather than
train them for specific jobs.
"Family hostels", found mainly in
France and Italy, in rural areas with
set traditions, have devised experi¬
mental methods of education.
Their objectives are to avoid uproot¬
ing children at too early a stage in
education; to help children with a
deprived cultural background; to dev¬
elop education that promotes in¬
dividual motivation and is oriented
to local conditions.
Education should aim not only to train young people for spe¬
cific jobs, but also equip them to adapt to a variety of
occupations I
Though education has a major role
to play In vocational training, edu¬
cation systems of the traditional type
are unable to provide training that
keeps pace with the changing job
requirements of modern industry.
What the school can and should do
is to provide a solid grounding of
knowledge, and develop understanding
of scientific principles and the ability
to apply them technically.
In the U.S.S.R., one of the most
fruitful means adopted for achieving
universal secondary education while
leaving general school education its
leading role has been the develop
ment of professional and technical
schools which offer a secondary
education running parallel with pro¬
fessional specialization. The 1971-1975
development plan of the Soviet Union
provides for the training of 9 million
specialists who have had special or
secondary education.
CONTINUED PAGE 26
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Drawing © by Qanlol Alain 1955, taken from "L'Art et l'Illusion"
by E.H. Gombrich, Gallimard, 1971
Above, pupils in an English school at the turn of the century learning to draw by the old, mechanical
copying method as portrayed in an art instruction manual published in 1903, and a cartoon on the
same theme depicting a drawing class in the Egypt of the Pharaohs. "Could a more certain way of
stifling all imagination and spontaneity possibly be devised?" asked the famous English critic E.H. Gom¬
brich. "The entire artistic conscience of our day revolts against such methods." Below, the Spanish
artist-teacher Ramon Sancho-Miñano examines drawings by his pupils of the High School at Lugones,
made after listening to excerpts from classical music. Here an act of spontaneous creativity replaces
the sterile and mechanical process of former "classroom art".
Above, "The Rite of Spring" by Stravinsky as seen by
eleven-year-old Maria Paz Martinez. Right, the same
composer's "Fireworks" as interpreted by Leonor Huerta
Rodriguez, aged 10.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
ART FROM THE SOUND
OF MUSIC
"Education", says the report of the International Com¬
mission on the Development of Education, "has the
power to cultivate or stifle creativity." Regrettably, the
latter tendency has generally prevailed, turning edu¬
cation into a purely mechanical process for the trans¬
mission of knowledge and skills, often of doubtful utility,
with scant regard paid to the development of the pupil's
personality as a whole. Today the situation is beginning
to change. In the teaching of science, and even more
in the teaching of art "the individual's Imaginative faculty
must be developed." This is what the young Spanish
artist and teacher, Ramon Sancho-Miñano, is attempting
to do. In his art class at the High School of Lugones,
near Oviedo, he has broken with the traditional method
which prescribes mechanical copying. He asks his
pupils to draw directly upon their powers of imagination.
His method, which has been studied by Unesco experts,
is to make his pupils listen to a piece of classical music
after which, with no further guidance, they draw images
and impressions evoked by the music. In this way
Sancho-Miñano attempts to develop the imaginative
sense of his pupils and create in their minds "a veritable
integration of the two art forms." Their drawings, some
examples of which are reproduced here, often surprise
by their quality, considering that they are the work of
culturally underprivileged children of 10 to 12, whose
first experience of art is acquired in these classes.
Giving free rein to their imagination, the pupils of the High School at
Lugones express on paper the impressions evoked for them by (above),
"Spring", from Vivaldi's "The Four Seasons" (Maria Pilar Sanjosé
Calderón, aged II) and (below), "The New World Symphony" by Dvorak
(Emilio Prado Sanchez, aged 12).
"Air on the G string" by Johann
Sebastian Bach, as Interpreted
by Miguel Cortina Garcia,
aged II. Curiously enough, the
baroque, abstract music of the
great German composer has
evoked from the young Spanish
schoolboy an interpretation which
follows the style of modem
abstract art. Reproduction in
black and white deprives these
drawings of a great deal of their
allusive power.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
BOTANICAL GARDEN
FOR THE BLIND
In this botanical garden at Horw, near Lucerne (Switzerland), the
blind can associate the smell of a flower with its name inscribed
in Braille on a metal plate. Braille, invented in 1829 by the
Frenchman Louis Braille, consists of raised dots arranged in a
different order to represent each sound. All the phonemes of
a language can be transcribed by 63 different characters,
first invented, Braille was applicable only to French and its adapta¬
tion to other languages and its standardization was due to efforts
made in 1949 by Unesco, and by the adoption in 1950 of the
principle "one sound, one sign". International Book Year, 1972,
has seen the launching of a "Books for the Blind" campaign,
organized through the Unesco Gift Coupon Programme, which
aims to provide Braille and "talking" books for blind people
everywhere. As part of this campaign Unesco organized a gala
evening in Paris on September 25 starring the brilliant Amer¬
ican star Sammy Davis Jnr. and the popular French singer Sylvie
Vartan. The public responded warmly to this appeal by Ur.esco
on behalf of the blind, packing the theatre to see two great
artists who generously performed without fee to make this gala
an outstanding success.
	;	 -> *
^- ' 'tí r
H9B
<£ -
21 POINTS (Continued from page 23)
Responsibility for technical training should not fall exclusively
on the school system. It should be shared by schools, business,
industry and out-of-school education.
To meet its growing obligations in
technical training, education needs
the help of many other institutions.
This calls for active co-operation bet¬
ween educators, leaders of business
and industry, workers and govern¬
ments. In many countries, private and
publicly owned firms allocate part of
their profits to educating and training
their personnel. This practice should
be more widely adopted.
Japan has a highly organized system
of technical and vocational training
supported by business and industry.
At the beginning of this century, the
larger companies established their
own apprentice-training facilities. To¬
day, industrial plants participate in
the public vocational-training program¬
me supervised by the Ministry of
Labour. This comprises 407 training
centres with an enrolment of more
than 100,000 trainees.
In addition, most large firms have
within-industry training programmes
to provide initial instruction for new
employees, re-training and upgrading
of skilled workers, supervisory train¬
ing and management development
courses. The Yawata Iron and Steel
Company, employing 50,-OOQ persons,
is a typical example. Its policy is to
encourage all employees to improve
their skills through daily on-the-job
training given by their ¡immediate
supervisor. The programmes cover
the training of workers and foremen,
clerical and engineering staff and top
management personnel.
Higher education should be expanded and made varied enough
to meet individual and community needs. Traditional attitudes
towards the university must change.
26
Public acceptance of new kinds of
higher education institutions would
help to relieve pressure on presently
overloaded universities of the tradi¬
tional type. It would also enable uni¬
versities to reform their entrance
criteria, basing them less on candi¬
dates' school credits and diplomas
than on their motivations and pro¬
fessional aims. Higher education
would thus become accessible to a
wider range of entrants post-graduate
students, workers and professional
men and women requiring more
advanced training or "recycling"
courses.
The French university centre of Vin-
cennes, which now has twenty-six
departments, employing 400 full-time
teachers and many other lecturers
handling some 12,000 students, aims
to admit a maximum number of work¬
ers and students who have not passed
the French secondary school-leaving
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
-
# r?
*%'- r
.<* - - .
i.*"**.
1
examination (the baccalauréat). Two-
thirds of all students at Vincennes
are wage-earners and about half do
not have the baccalauréat.
A number of innovations tried out
at Vincennes have been adopted at
other French universities. Others, still
being tested at Vincennes, include the
replacement of formal teaching and
examinations by various forms of
team-work in which the teacher acts
mainly as an adviser who catalyses
and co-ordinates the activities of
small, semi-independent groups. Much
of the work consists of research on
themes chosen by the students them¬
selves.
In the Arab Republic of Egypt,
changes in the higher institutes of
technology and their fusion into a
university of technology provide an
interesting example of a search for
new paths towards higher education.
Having played an active part in train¬
ing skilled technical-executive per¬
sonnel during a certain period of
development, these institutes are now
acting as centres for the initiation and
renewal of contact between certain
branches of education and Egypt's
rapidly expanding industry.
The example of India shows that
progress and expansion of higher
education In a developing country
calls for a small number of "centres
of advanced studies". In India, thirty
such centres exist, 17 concerned with
science and 13 with the humanities
and social sciences.
The centres have received consider¬
able aid from Unesco, the U.K. and
the U.S.S.R. In addition, six Indian
institutes of technology have been set
up with an enrolment of about 10,000
about five per cent of the total
enrolment in technology.
ccess to different types of education and employment should
depend only on a person's knowledge, capacities and aptitudes.
Proper evaluation of progress
achieved by a pupil or student should
be based on a study of his work over
a period rather, than on examination
results. It should pay less attention
to the mass of facts he has memor¬
ized and more to the development
of his intellectual capacity (powers
of reasoning, critical judgment and
ability to solve problems).
With modern learning methods,
such as programmed or computer-
assisted instruction, television courses,
language laboratories and other self-
education systems, examinations can
be differently organized. It can be
foreseen that appointments to jobs
will be based increasingly on a pre¬
cise evaluation of candidate's apti¬
tudes for particular functions rather
than on diplomas gained at school or
university.
In Sweden the school-leaving exam¬
ination at the end of the secondary
cycle has been abolished, together
with university entrance examinations
of the traditional type. Varied ways
are now commonly used to assess
a candidate's ability, which he may
decide to demonstrate, for instance,
by making a short film or a tape-
recording, or by presenting a collect
ion of poems, a painting, a sculpture
or a town-planning project.
A number of universities use differ¬
ent means to open their doors to
people from all walks of life. In Po¬
land, for example, a widely spread
network of correspondence courses,
covering virtually all branches of study,
is the major method used for open¬
ing up post-secondary education.
Higher education institutions provid¬
ing correspondence courses or even¬
ing classes at a number of large fac¬
tories enable workers to study out of
working hours or to alternate periods
of factory work and study.
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
21 POINTS (Continued)
Development of adult education, in and out of school, should
be a priority objective of educational strategies during the next
ten years.
Adult education can have a direct
bearing on the progress of children
in school, since primary education
and the educational level of parents
cannot be disassociated. Children
cannot be properly educated in an
illiterate environment. Thus, adult .
education can no longer be a fringe
activity in any society. It should be
given its proper place in educational
policies and budgets, and firm links
established between school and out-
of-school education.
Step-by-step progress in adult
education Is not sufficient to meet the
present situation which calls for a
giant leap forward. This can only be
achieved by mobilizing the efforts and
resources of individuals and of public
bodies.
Yugoslavia's "workers universities-
provide both formal and out-of-school
education and are open to all adults
whatever their earlier training, the
only criteria for admission being indi
vidual aptitude. Courses are offered
at all levels, ranging from elementary
education to instruction in specialized
subjects for highly qualified workers.
Programmes . are adapted to local
conditions and are diversified accord¬
ing to community and individual needs.
Equal importance is attached to func¬
tional education (for professional,
civic or social progress) as to a
person's general and cultural develop¬
ment.
IB All literacy teaching should be geared to a country's objectives
in social and economic development.
Literacy teaching should have two
basic aims: functional literacy among
sections of the' working population
where incentive for literacy Is greatest;
mass literacy where social conditions
for development political, economic
and cultural enable the mass of the
people, to participate.
A mass literacy campaign is justified
to the extent that it enables thé people
as whole to share in improving local
conditions. Mass campaigns should be
promoted and supported by a wide
use of mass media, particularly radio
and television programmes.
Functional literacy, which is tailored
to the needs and literacy problems of
individual communities or areas, calls
for in-depth studies of local conditions
before being launched. One example
of a campaign based on this principle
is the functional literacy project in
Isfahan and Dez (Iran). Studies cover¬
ing economic, social, vocational and
demographic aspects of the areas
were the basis for 15 programmes
linked to the needs and learning in¬
centives of illiterate persons.
This ensured that literacy teaching
was integrated into a simultaneous
learning process which gave priority
to vocational training.
28
Aids to self-education, including language laboratories, libraries,
data banks, and audio-visual equipment, should be integrated
into all education systems. I
New paths taken by education and
an expansion of educational facilities
have helped to promote the principle
and practice of self-learning. Everyone
ought to be provided with the means,
tools and incentives for making self-
learning a productive and rewarding
activity.
Self-education, which has been far
too often neglected as an objective,
.should have its place in the educa¬
tional strategies of every country.
Even countries with limited resources,
should allocate part of the educational
budget to the development of self-
learning among priority groups of the
population.
An inquiry into self-education was
made in Canada by Prof. Allen Tough
and associates at the Ontario Institute
for Studies In Education. Carried out
among several hundred teenagers
and adults engaged in self-learning
projects, it revealed the broad scope
and possibilities of self-directed learn¬
ing in many fields. It also showed
that learners sought the help of a
wide range of persons, other than
teachers and librarians an indication
that many non-specialists qualify as
"teachers" in individualized learning.
Rapid, cheap and easily available
means such as radio should be more
widely used for mass education, parti¬
cularly in rural areas. Where resour¬
ces allow, modern communication
media would be effective as teaching
aids in many branches of education
higher technical education, for exam¬
ple.
A striking example of education via
the mass media Is the Tevec project
in 0ueDec (Canada) designed to bring
adults who have not completed nine
years of schooling up to that level.
The programme comprises "scholas¬
tic" subjects (French, English mathe¬
matics, etc.), and a theme chosen from
a variety of topics (health, the law,
community participation, social welfare,
government) aimed at fostering an un¬
derstanding of daily life in a rapidly
developing society and stimulating
citizen participation.
Methods used in the project have
included: 90-minute television pro¬
grammes, five days a week; corres¬
pondence courses (averaging 15,000
reply cards daily); personal contact
between participants and teachers
(regular visits to homes every three
weeks) and weekly tele-club meetings
to discuss the topic presented. Sampl¬
ing surveys show that 35,000 persons
viewed the programmes regularly, and
110,000 saw them more than once a
week.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
In the U.S.S.R., from five to eight
hours of special TV programmes for
teachers and children are broadcast
daily. The teachers' programmes bring
to the TV screen educators, psycho¬
logists and other specialists in educat¬
ion. Children's broadcasts aim to
supplement classroom learning on
some of the most advanced and im
portant subjects in the school pro¬
gramme. Many other radio and TV
programmes serve as guides to par¬
ents on problems of family education
and child and teenage psychology.
Other aids to selective, individual
education include video-tape cassettes
and cartridges which may be plugged
into a television receiver, and the
video disc, which is used in conjunc¬
tion with a video player. These com¬
paratively low-priced aids offer rapid
and selective access to programmes
which can be repeated as often as
required, factors which promise a
wealth of possibilities for the future.
Education systems should be conceived and planned in terms
of possibilities offered by new educational techniques.
Thus far, school systems have gen¬
erally been unable to make system¬
atic use of new possibilities offered
by technological and scientific pro¬
gress.
Mass communication technology is
currently developing in two opposite
directions: towards individualization of
education (as in programmed learning)
and towards mass distribution (as in
educational TV programmes by satellite
transmission).
One new technique is the use of
direct-wire television which makes it
possible to relay more than twenty
programmes simultaneously to the
entire subscriber network, or to serve
one subscriber with a single pro¬
gramme selected from a range of
several dozen.
Mass transmission techniques capa¬
ble of making education available to
millions of children and adults Include
two of great importance for developing
countries: radio and communications
satellite relays.
Radio is the only advanced com¬
munication technique which has found
Its proper place in developing coun¬
tries. Yet, insufficient educational use
is made of this virtually universal
means of communication.
Space communications have de¬
veloped at a staggering speed. Five
years after the first sputnik was
launched in 1957, Telstar was orbited,
in 1962; the first operational satellites,
Early Bird (United States) and Molnya
(U.S.S.R.), were placed in orbit three
years later. More than eighty nations
participate in Intelsat, which recently
orbited the first of the Intelsat IV
series, capable of relaying 6,000 tele¬
phone calls simultaneously.
For the moment, however, national
spatial telecommunications systems
are of interest only to regions with
a common language, to very large
countries such as India, Brazil and
Canada or to a few with disconnected
territories such as Indonesia and
Japan. Economically and technically,
it would not be feasible or justified
to carry out nationally organized pro¬
grammes virtually anywhere else.
Satellite-relayed broadcasting will
therefore have to be handled on a
multi-national scale, on the lines of
the Latin American cultural integration
scheme (SERLA) or the Franco-Ger¬
man 'Symphony-Socrates' project for
Africa south of the Sahara, for
example.
The development of data processing
also opens new paths for education.
Computers, particularly, render mul¬
tiple services ranging from aid to
management and research to strictly
didactic uses.
Universities and other educational
establishments in the United States
contain an estimated 3,000 computers,
or about 6 per cent of all computers
operating In that country. In the Soviet
Union systematic use is made of
computers at Sverdlosk University
and in technological Institutes at
Minsk, Kiev and Lvov. Computers
are used for experimental purposes in
the German Democratic Republic and
in Prague, Czechoslovakia. Of about
4,000 computers in Japan, some 200 are
used for teaching in universities. In
the United Kingdom, almost all
teaching computers are in the univer¬
sities, while many universities in the
Federal Republic of Germany have
also acquired computers.
In the school itself, architecture is
bringing changes. The classroom is
no longer necessarily a "compartment"
for thirty or forty persons. Many
schools have novel and original inter¬
ior layouts. Multi-purpose areas with
mobile partitions and separate booths
can be adapted at will to large or
small groups or to individual study.
Large areas may be used for debating.
The school is becoming a club, a
workshop a documentation centre, a
laboratory and a place of assembly
rolled into one. Student-space
arrangements, timetables, staff distrib¬
ution and allocation of equipment all
tend to be more mobile, and the
institution more flexible and better
adapted to social and technical dev¬
elopments. ,
ICTTeacher training programmes should
latest teaching aids and methods.
make full use of the
New resources provided by educa¬
tional technology should be system¬
atically introduced into teacher training
colleges. These institutions should be
progressively transformed into perma¬
nent training centres and opened more
widely to specialists in other fields
who are needed for short-term or part-
time teaching assignments.
Teacher training colleges will have
to give special training to future
educators in the supervision and
co-ordination of the new, mechanized
educational systems. It will also be
necessary to train specialists to devise
and revise curricula, produce new
teaching material and develop fresh
methods of work guidance and eval- yQ
uation. ^*»
The development of education will
necessarily involve an increase in the
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
21 POINTS (Continued)
t>
rr,
J
Photo 0 APN, M
SCHOOLS OUTMODED ?
"What applies to the countries in which education is in the grip of a crisis
does not apply to all countries and all of modern mankind", affirms Arthur
V. Petrovsky, Soviet member of the International Commission on the Dev¬
elopment of Education. "To say that education is reactionary", he adds
"is as wrong as it would be to assert that all education is progressive.
Highly disputable, and, in our view wrong, is the notion that schools are
becoming outmoded in modern society . . . Naturally, we are not implying
that teaching should stop the minute a person leaves a formal educational
establishment. On the contrary, education should go on throughout life."
Above, a young science student conducts an experiment in a Soviet physics
laboratory. Periods of re-training and booster courses are now an essen¬
tial part of any scientist's life.
number of teachers. Authorities will
have to see to it that the greater
expenditure on teaching staff produces
an equivalent improvement in results.
Hitherto, the continual rise in expen¬
diture on teachers' salaries has been
achieved at the expense of spending
on new equipment, innovation and
research. Teaching methods must
therefore be found which are as "pro¬
fitable" as possible, or running
expenses will reach. such a high level
that the cost factor will put modern¬
ization of educational systems out of
reach.
National authorities will have to
consider setting aside a fixed propor¬
tion of the annual increase in the
educational budget to developing new
ways of making the educational system
more efficient.
The radical changes that can be
made in education by large scale in¬
troduction of new techniques are being
demonstrated in the Ivory Coast. This
country's programme of education via
television aims to bring basic educat¬
ion to all school-age children and to
use TV on a nation-wide scale In
promoting cultural and political unity.
By 1980, about 16,500 classes will
be equipped with television receivers
making televised education available
to first-level classes and to young
people aged betwen 13 and 17, and
providing cultural, lifelong education
and information services to all adults.
By 1986 all children will be receiving
televised education.
The World Bank estimates that the
Ivory's Coast's project will cost 44 per
cent less than the maintenance of the
traditional educational system.
The new project is based on a broad
research programme covering teach¬
ing methods and curricula, modification
of school buildings and teacher train¬
ing. It has led to a new intensive
teacher training programme compris¬
ing not only an Introduction of new
subject matter, but also training in the
use of audio-visual techniques, com¬
munication, psychology, after-school
activities and new evaluation techni¬
ques.
The organization of classes and the
order in which courses are arranged
have also had to be altered, and these
modifications will eventually be carried
over into secondary education.
The repercussions of the Ivory Coast
programme are also being felt outside
classrooms and teacher training coll¬
eges. Out-of-school education will be
widely influenced by the introduction
of television and the ministries res¬
ponsible for these activities are having
to modify their own procedures to
meet the needs of this exciting new
venture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
All hierarchical differences among teachers in primary schools,
technical colleges, secondary schools and universities should
be abolished.
MMBHHBIBHBMIBHMH
Teaching is everywhere identical in
nature, value and purpose. A teacher
should specialize according to his
preference for teaching children, teen¬
agers or adults and his wish to live
in the country, in a town or in a big
city. The idea of promotion, with its
financial and other advantages, should
not draw him inexorably towards the
biggest city or the largest school or
towards the top level of higher edu¬
cation.
In some countries, differing levels
of training and pay for primary and
secondary teachers have already been
abolished. Czechoslovakia, Denmark,
U.K. and U.S.A., among other coun¬
tries, now train primary and secondary
teachers in universities or equivalent
post-secondary institutions.
Others, including France, Poland,
and the U.S.S.R. are now following
the same path by training teachers to
university level.
Teachers should be trained to be educators rather than specia¬
lists in the transmission of knowledge.
¡fe
Present day divisions between for¬
mal and informal, school and out-of-
school, child and adult education are
becoming blurred. Teachers who are
trained today will still be teaching
aftçr the year 2000. Teacher training
strategies should be drawn up with
these factors in mind. Programmes
for training tomorrow's teachers
should follow two main lines:speclali-
zation (in pre-school education, school
pedagogy, technical education, back¬
ward child training, adult education,
etc.) and the training of most teachers
as organizer-educators, capable of
teaching children and adults In and
out of school.
Tomorrow's education system will
require specialists in teaching mat¬
erials, self-teaching equipment and the
use of educational techniques, audio¬
visual auxiliaries, etc., as well as
community centre leaders, psycholo¬
gists, administrators with new skills,
systems analysts, etc.
Teacher training institutes recently
set up with Unesco's aid in six African
countries (Cameroon, Ethiopia, Ivory
Coast, Liberia, Niger, Togo) aim not
only to train teachers for specific
classes or subjects but to form rural
educators equipped to work under
local conditions and capable of initiat
ing and organizing a wide range of
community development services. The
institutes have two main objectives:
To train teachers for primary educ¬
ation in basically rural countries, who
would also be effective organizers for
community development.
To offer re-training and improve¬
ment courses to existing educational
personnel primary school Inspec¬
tors, education advisers, high school
teachers, headmasters and primary
teachers to bring them up to date
with reforms in education, and to train
them in new methods and techniques.
Skilled auxiliaries from the trades and professions (workers,
technicians and executives) should be brought in to teach
in schools. Students should also participate, educating them¬
selves while teaching others. I
Far more volunteer and auxiliary
teachers should be used in schools
and in the educational system gener¬
ally. They could not only carry out
non-teaching tasks so as to "free
teachers to teach", but also, after a
short training course, participate in
teaching.
The U.S.A. offers many examples of
volunteer services of this kind. A
volunteer parent aide, usually a mother,
may be asked to correct papers, check
for errors on written work, read to
small groups of children, make instruc¬
tional materials, supervise groups of
children on the playground or assist
the teacher in other ways.
Other helpers are volunteer commu
nity aides, persons with special skills:
handicraft workers, opticians, photo¬
graphers, stamp collectors, politicians,
salesmen, insurance experts, police¬
men, chefs, dairy farmers, members of
minority groups the possibilities are
endless.
Volunteer student aides also have
an important part to play. It Is widely
accepted that helping someone to
learn can also be a significant learning
experience for the person teaching.
On this assumption, many schools
provide opportunities for pupils to
teach other pupils.
The usual method adopted is for
an older child to come to the class¬
room of a younger one to read to him
or to listen to him reading, to drill
him on the fundamentals of arithmetic
or assist him in mastering some other
skill.
Since 1961, Cuba, for example, has
built up a day-care system catering
for 50,000 children up to the age of 5.
At the beginning the service was run
almost entirely by women with little
or no formal schooling, much less any
special training for running kindergar¬
tens.
All these volunteers had to offer
was their own experience and willing¬
ness to accept intensive in-service
training. Parents also help by provid¬
ing school maintenance teams for
carpentry, painting sewing and garden¬
ing, etc.
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
21 POINTS (Continued)
Contrary to traditional practice, teaching should adapt itself to
the learner. The student should have greater freedom to
decide for himself what he wants to learn and how and where
to learn it.
Children should be encouraged from
an early age to share in the organiza¬
tion of school life. In particular, they
should be able to discuss their rights
and duties, as laid down by school
rules rules that should gradually be
made more flexible.
The same reasoning applies to
teaching methods and subjects. The
learner, particularly the adult learner,
should be free to choose which school
or Institution to attend and the kind of
training he wants. He should be able
to enter the educational system at the
level which suits him best and select
optional additional subjects which
interest him.
All or most compulsory disciplines
in schools are, however^laid down in
terms of objectives the establishments
has set for itself. But this in no way
prevents possibilities for individual
choice being extended.
Many examples exist of institutions
that encourage learners to take res¬
ponsibility for their own education.
The Gesamtschulen, In the Federal
Republic of Germany, seek to stim¬
ulate students' capacity for choosing
their own paths and aim to bring their
working methods close both to uni¬
versity studies and modern professio¬
nal training. Students do not decide
on the kind of diploma they want to
acquire immediately on entering
school.
Studies are divided into three cate¬
gories: Studienfacher, or major choice
subjects; Orientierungsfacher, or com¬
plementary subjects; Grundfacher, or
basic subjects. The first and second
categories form the core of knowledge
regarded as necessary for the pupil's
adaptation to society, but are, how¬
ever, subject to choice. Only the third
category is compulsory for all and
comprises civic and social training, the
visual arts or music, physical training
and religion. But a certain freedom
is allowed as to the amount of time
the pupil devotes to each subject.
In England, the Prior Weston primary
school, London, is an outstanding
example of the increased rôle of the
learner and of recent widespread
changes in primary education in the
United Kingdom. Learning takes place
within a classless environment with
the different age groups working to¬
gether on various learning activities.
The "open plan ' surroundings prov¬
ide activity areas for subject study,
reading, art and other manual activities
and play. A mixture of 5, 6 and
7-year-old children work together on
the same mathematics project (for
example noting down and analysing
the physical characteristics of the
group) with the quicker pupils helping
the slower ones in the same group.
The timetable is flexible and pupils
may spend one or more days inves¬
tigating and describing a single theme
or topic, only moving on to another
activity when the project is completed.
The teaching of reading and writing
is based on individual interests with
the emphasis on creative expression
rather than copy-book exercises.
Self-discipline is encouraged through
co-operative activity and pupil partici¬
pation in the organization of much of
their work. The headmaster and
teachers maintain regular contact with
parents who are encouraged to share
in the school's activities and even act
as ancillary aides for play supervision,
manual training assistance, group
reading, etc.
Students and the public as a whole should be given a greater
say in decisions affecting education.
32
Student participation in the planning
and running of education is progress¬
ing. Such participation increases with
the age of the student, and varies in
different branches of education. Stu¬
dents responsibilities are greatest
where their social, cultural and mater¬
ial interests are concerned. In the
case of programmes and teaching
'methods, student responsibilities are
still limited, and, in most cases,
even more restricted in financing or
teacher recruitment. Student partici¬
pation should, in fact, be exercised
separately from, as well as in conjunc¬
tion with, that of teachers, parents and
others.
Some forms of participation (inspec¬
tion, co-management, self-manage¬
ment, etc.) are now common in certain
primary and community schools, in
secondary and technical schools, in
some adult education institutions, and
in organizations outside the school
system, handling such problems as
educational programmes, research,
teacher promotion, salaries, educa¬
tional investment, etc.
The most significant developments
today are going on in universities in
various parts of the world. Students
have for some time been given partial
or complete control over the "social"
sectonstudent hostels, sports, sanitary
and auxiliary services. They have also
been "consulted" on general policies
or have made their views known
through committees set up to propose
reforms.
In recent years, student representa¬
tion has spread to areas of university
management previously regarded as
the preserve of a few persons chosen
for their particular experience or qua¬
lifications. Today, educational methods
and study programmes are being
brought more and more within the
scope of participation arrangements,
and management bodies (faculty coun¬
cils, national and ministerial commit¬
tees) are admitting student representa¬
tives, in some countries students are
successfully demanding representation
on bodies which decide on admissions,
examinations, finance and the general
administration of education.
Student participation is today dev¬
eloping in Asia, and student influence,
direct (as in the Philippines, India
and Indonesia) or indirect (as in Malay¬
sia and Thailand) is being exerted at
both university and national levels.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
MAN'S ORIGINS
DEMYSTIFIED
Sir,
Congratulations on your splendid
August-September 1972 issue ("The
Emergence of Man"). Even for the
layman the mystery of man's origins Is
no longer so much of an enigma thanks
to the many fascinating and Informative
articles by leading authorities.
I read your "scientific" numbers with
great Interest, and generally find them
more rewarding than those dealing with
books or art, for instance.
Please devote more issues to science.
Martine Portier
Sceaux, France
SCIENCE MADE SIMPLE
Sir,
Your magazine deserves the highest
praise for its clear and down-to-earth
presentation of scientific subjects. The
Issue on the Emergence of Man is an
outstanding example of science popu¬
larization.
A reader of several years' standing,
1 have come to admire the "Unesco
Courier's" consistently rational approach
to all subjects.
Robert Beilanger
Montrouge, France
NORMAN E. BORLAUG'S
DEFENCE OF DDT
Sir,
Norman Borlaug's defence of DDT
("Unesco Courier" February 1972) is
groundless because he ignores many
commonly known facts. We can send
him a list of the mutagenic, gonadotropic,
embryotroplc, cancerogenie and terato¬
genic properties of the pesticides he so
furiously defends.
The major argument advanced by
Borlaug and his supporters that the
prohibition of the use of DDT and other
chemicals would mean starvation for
humanity holds no water. Why should
we poison all agricultural produce in
order to save 15 to 20 per cent of the
harvest? For this is no ordinary
poisoning but a threat of disastrous
mutations leading to the deterioration
of the health of present and future
generations, far worse than any hunger.
Perhaps Dr. Borlaug thinks that men
should meekly share the fate of the
99 per cent of animal species which,
according to H. Spencer, have dis¬
appeared from the face of the earth.
S. Yuzko, A. Khalitov and
M. Nikolskaya
Members of the Moscow Society
for Nature Protection
Sir,
I found Norman Borlaug's article in
defence of DDT profoundly depressing.
The author tries to disprove the count¬
less facts that demonstrate the disast¬
rous influence of DDT on the biosphere.
If it is not his ignorance, then what
lies behind his claims? I consider that
the production, sale and use of DDT
is a crime against humanity.
I have personally witnessed many
cases of sickness and death resulting
from DDT poisoning either direct or
through food crops treated with DDT.
It was a big mistake for the "Unesco
Courier" to devote space to Norman
Borlaug's article.
Prof. E. Velichko
Kuban Agriculture Institute
Krasnodar, U.S.S.R.
DOWN-TO-EARTH
UTOPIANISM
Sir.
As a student, I find your magazine a
mine of invaluable, practical information
that helps me in my studies and In
improving my general culture.
Some readers have criticized the
"Unesco Courier" for being a platform
for Utopian ideas, and have asked to
be spared "from the inept 'if onlys' of
Utopian dreamers." I hope you will
disregard such requests. If our Utopias
disappear, if men can no longer express
such views freely, then life will have no
meaning or purpose in a world that
appears to be dominated by hatred, war
and racism.
S. Bessicot
Montpellier, France
BOOK, DEAR FRIEND
Sir.
Reading your Issue "Book.DearFrlend"
(July 1972) was indeed a rewarding
experience. As an assistant-librarian,
I found it a rich source of Information
and enlightenment on the book and Its
future.
W. Gilles Cámara
Bamako, Mali
BOOKS CONSIGNED
TO THE FIRE
Sir,
In your issue "Book, Dear Friend"
a photo caption (page 7) says that the
systematic destruction of certain books
dates back to at least 600 B.C., and
quotes an Incident described in the
First Book of Maccabees. In fact, this
episode occurred in 167 B.C. during
the Maccabean revolt.
An example actually dating from
600 B.C. is the burning of a scroll on
the order of Jehoiakim king of Judah,
in 605 or 604 B.C., as recounted In
chapter 36 of the Book of Jeremiah.
Brother Paul-lrénée Fransen
Maredsous Abbey, Belgium
CULTURAL OLYMPICS
Sir.
After watching with admiration the
wonderful spectacle of the Olympic
Games at Munich, I reflected that man,
capable of such prowess in sport, is too
often Inclined to forget that the power
of thought Is his most valuable posses¬
sion.
Why doesn't Unesco take the ini¬
tiative of instituting Arts and Culture
Olympics? Previously unknown artists
and writers would be revealed to the
world and their work evaluated by-
recognized experts in the fields of
music, literature, painting, sculpture,
theatre, photography and amateur film¬
making.
José Manuel Briones Gonzalez
Madrid, Spain
CHILEAN LANDSCAPE
Sir.
The "Unesco Courier" is a never-
ending source of knowledge concerning
the peoples and cultures of the world.
I was particularly struck by the March
1972 issue on Latin America a theme
long awaited by your readers.
May I make a correction to the cap¬
tion for the photo by Mr. Roberto Mon-
tandon, on page 13 of this Issue, which
Is described as showing Chilean Pata¬
gonia. I understand from Mr. Montan¬
don that the photo actually shows the
"Puna" in the Atacama region of the
Cordillera in northern Chile.
Sergio M. Esplnoza
Santiago, Chile
MODEL OF THE GENRE
Sir,
I am a student at a Hungarian gram¬
mar school and am studying foreign
languages to become a linguist. I am
writing to tell you how much I appre¬
ciate the "Unesco Courler" and cannot
congratulate you too highly both on
the presentation and the quality of your
review. It has a profound sense of
history and art and I am constantly
showing It to my friends as a model of
the genre.
I should be glad to read more in the
"Unesco Courler" about translations
and language education in other coun¬
tries.
Balarsy Jozsef Attila
Magyarorszag, Hungary
POPULATION EXPLOSION
Sir.
Overpopulation Is one of the funda¬
mental causes (perhaps the most
important) of the despoiling of nature
because of the Industrial expansion that
inevitably follows it.
One way to reduce the birth rate
would surely be to limit the payment
of family allowances to three children
per family. A measure of this kind,
clearly, could only be adopted after an
intensive public information campaign
had been carried out.
In my view, the whole question of
birth control should be re-appraised and
the subject should be Introduced as a
part of general education In schools.
All countries would do well to reflect
on the gravity of the problem while
there is still time.
Adrien Grosrey
Geneva, Switzerland
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Learning to Be. The world of
education today and tomorrow.
Unesco-Harrap, 1972, 313 pp ($6, £2).
See opposite page.
Manpower Aspects of Educational
planning. Problems for the future.
Unesco-I.I.E.P., 1968, 2nd impression
1971, 264 pp ($3.50, £1.05)
Rights and Responsibilities of
Youth. (Studies and documents in
education No. 6), 1972, 72 pp ($2,
60p). Also available in Russian.
Script-writing for Short Films, by
James A. Beveridge. (Reports and
papers on mass communication
No. 57), 1969, 2nd impression 1972,
45 pp ($1.25. 35p)
Some Aspects of Cultural Policies
in India, by Kapila Malik Vatsyayan.
(Studies and documents on cultural
policies), 1972, 105 pp ($2, 60p)
OTHER BOOKS
Angkor and the Khmer Empire,*
by John Audric. Robert Hale, Lon¬
don, 1972, 207 pp (£2.80)
Creatures of Philippine Lower
Mythology, by Maximo D. Ramos.
University of the Philippines Press,
1971, 390 pp.
Geology, by W.C. Putnam and
A.B. Bassett. Oxford University
Press, New York, London, Toronto
1971, 586 pp
World Armaments and Dis¬
armament, SIPRI Yearbook 1972,
Stockholm, International Peace Re¬
search Institute. Almqvist and
Wiksell, Stockholm, Humanities
Press, New York, Paul Elek, London,
611 pp (75 Kr.. $16.50. £7.50)
Plant Myths and Traditions in
India, by Shakti M. Gupta. E.J. Brill,
Leiden, Netherlands, 1971, 117 pp.
ffl P
UD Gffi ÜÚ \a
1972 Literacy award winners
The Gram Shiksham Mohim (Village Dev¬
elopment Movement) founded in 1961 in
Maharashtra State, India, has been award¬
ed the 1972 Mohammed Reza Pahlavi Lit¬
eracy Prize presented by the Shahinshah of
Iran. Since 1961, the Movement has taught
9.7 million people to read and write and
has eradicated illiteracy In 36,693 villages
and hamlets. The 1972 Nadezhda K. Krup-
skaya Prize, sponsored by the U.S.S.R.,
went to Iran's Literacy Corps. Since 1962,
when the Literacy Corps was founded,
young Iranian men and women doing their
national service have taught more than a
million children and half a million adults
to read and write. The awards were
presented by Unesco's Director-General,
Mr. René Maheu, on International Literacy
Day, September 8.
Treasures of prehistoric art
Our Issue, "The Emergence of Man"
(August-September 1972) featured a num¬
ber of photographs by Jean Vertut, taken
from André Lerol-Gourhan's remarkable
book "Préhistoire de l'Art Occidental"
published by Editions Mazenod, Paris. This
authoritative study has been published In
English ("Treasures of Prehistoric Art") by
H.N. Abrams, New York, and has appeared
in several other language editions. The
illustrations published in the "Unesco
Courier" (on pages 30, 35, 36, 38 and 72)
were reproduced by kind permission of
Editions Mazenod.
International action
against art thieves
The stepplng-up of international action to
curb art thefts was studied by art and
security experts at a recent meeting spon¬
sored by Unesco and the Belgian National
Commission for Unesco at Ham Castle,
near Brussels. Among a broad range of
subjects dealt with were the problems
posed by security in museums, public
buildings and archaeological sites, the
control of trade In art, the insurance of
collections, and national and international
regulations governing the Import and
export of art works.
French physicist wins
Kalinga Prize
The 1971 Kalinga Prize for the Populari¬
zation of Science, awarded annually by an
international jury chosen by Unesco, has
been won by Professor Pierre Auger of
France. An Internationally-known physicist,
Prof. Auger was director of Unesco's
Department of Sciences from 1948 until
1959, and director of the European Space
Research Organization, in Paris, from 1962
to 1967. Author of numerous works on
science, Prof. Auger has directed several
series of science popularization program¬
mes for the French radio and Is now
supervising the preparation of a 10 volume
International encyclopaedia on science and
technology.
New format for "Museum"
Unesco's quarterly magazine "Museum",
which surveys activities and research In
the field of museography, has been given
a new format. Formerly bilingual, it now
appears in separate English and French
editions, slightly modified in size and with
an entirely new graphic presentation.
Résumés in Spanish and Russian, no longer
incorporated in the review, are printed
separately and sent to readers on request.
The current Issue (Vol. XXIV, No. I, 1972)
is devoted to "Problems of the museum
of contemporary art in the West." The
price of "Museum" remains unchanged at
$3 or 90p.
Books for peace
"The Book Messenger of Peace and
International Understanding" was the theme
of the book exhibition of the Ukrainian
Soviet Socialist Republic recently on view
at Unesco headquarters in Paris.
u
z
<
"Angel" by Canadian artist-designer
Allan Fleming.
UNICEF GREETING CARDS
Since 1949, over 600 million UNICEF greeting cards have been sold throughout the
world to help the United Nations Children's Fund provide medicines, food and education
to needy children in 120 countries.
UNICEF greeting cards for 1972, now on sale, offer a choice of 31 attractive designs,
including a Mondrian reproduction and illustrations from the world-famous Celtic master¬
piece the Book of Keils.
The sale of one box of cards can buy enough antibiotic ointment to cure 14 children
of trachoma and three boxes of cards provide enough Dapsone tablets to treat three
leprosy cases for three years.
Also on sale is the UNICEF engagement calendar for 1973, beautifully illustrated
with 53 reproductions of famous works of art.
UNICEF cards and envelopes are sold in boxes of 10 (12 in the U.S.A.); standard
cards cost $2 (U.S.A.), $1.75 (Canada), 70p (U.K.), 10 F (France). Prestige cards (the
Mondrian reproduction) cost $5, £1.50 and 15F, but are not on sale in Canada. Also
available are boxes of 25 mini-cards ($2, 85p, 15F); the engagement calendar costs $3,
£1 and 15 F. For orders write to: UNICEF Greeting Card Fund, 14, Stratford Place,
London, WIN 9 AF: U.S.A. Committee for UNICEF, 331 East 38th St., New York, N.Y.,
10016; Canadian UNICEF Committee, 737 Church St., Toronto 5, Ontario; Comité
Français pour la FISE/UNICEF, 35, rue Félicien-David, Paris-169.
PLEASE DO NOT ORDER THROUGH UNESCO.
o
I
o
I
o
z
<
o
O
LU
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
á¿
Edgar Faure
Felipe Herrera
Abdul-Razzak Kaddoura
Henri Lopes
Arthur V. Petrovsky
Majid Rahnema
Frederick ChampionWardr£
Learning
tobeThe world of education
today and tomorrow
Unesco Harrap
Just published
Examining one of the great problems of our time,
this unparalleled study reports the findings of the
world-wide inquiry carried out for Unesco by the
International Commission on the Development of
Education under the presidency of Mr. Edgar Faure.
"From different cultural and professional
backgrounds yet united in a common concern
for objectivity, the eminent members of the
Commission have drawn up a balance-sheet
of present-day education and proposed a
global educational strategy for tomorrow that
is unquestionably more comprehensive than
any formulated thus far."
René Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
313 pages
Price: $6: £2; 24 F
Co-edition Unesco-Harrap
Exclusive distributor in
the United Kingdom
Harrap. London.
Where to renew your subscription
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AUSTRALIA. Publications : Educational Supplies
Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale. 2100, NS;
Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Limited. Box 33, Post
Office, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent. United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
5th (loor, 134/136 Flinders St., Mel¬
bourne (Victoria). 3000. ($ Aus 3.60) AUS.
TRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme & Ca.. Arbeitgasso 1-7,
1051, Vienna (AS 110). BELGIUM. Jean De Lannoy,
112, rue du TrSne, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. (220F
beiges) BU RMA. Trade Corporation N* (9). 550-552
Merchant Stret, Rangoon. CANADA. Information
Canada. Ottawa, (Ont.) (t 5,00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop. Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244
Colombo 2. (Rs 25). CYPRUS. Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalana 51. Prague 1
(permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka
Prague 1. For Slovakia only : Nakladatalstvo Alfa, Hurba-
novo nam. 6 Bratislava. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard
Ltd.. 6, Norregade. 1165, Copenhagen K. (Dan. Kr. 27.00)
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications. N" 1 Talaat Hart» Street. Tahrir Squa¬
re, Cairo; Librairie Kasr El Nil, 38, rt ) Kasr El Nil, Cairo.
ILE. 35) ETHIOPIA. National Commission for Unesco.
P.O. Box 2»» 6. Addjs Ababa. FIN LAN D, Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes kuskatu. Helsinki (Fmk. 13.90).
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco. 7-9, place de Fontenoy,
7S-Paris-7\ C.C.P. 1 2598-48 (17 F). - GERMANY. All
publications ; Verlsg Dokumentation, Postfach 1 48.
Jaiserstrssse 1 3, 8023 MUnchen-Pullich. For the Unesco
Kurier (Germsn ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60,
Hamburg-Bshrenfeld. C.CP. 276650 (DM 16).
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd.. P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box
7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast, The
University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE.
Librairie H. Kauffmsnn, 28, rue du Stade. Athens ; Librairie
Eleftheroudakis, Nikis 4, Athens. HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akademiai Könyvesbolt, Vici u. 22,
Budapest V; A.K.V. Könyvtirosok Boltja, Nepköztirsasig
utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson
& Co.. H.F., Hafnarstrseti 9, Reykiavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Nicol Road, Ballard Estate, Bom¬
bay 1 ; 17 Chittaranj'an Avenue. Calcutta 13; 36a. Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 3/5 Asaf Ali Rosd, New
-Delhi 1 ; Sub- Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16 and Scindia House, New
Delhi; Publications Section,' Ministry of Education
and Youth Services, 72 Theatre Communication
Building, Connaught Place New Delhi 1. (Rs. 18,75).
INDONESIA. Indira P.T.. Djl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie
37, Djakarta. IRAN. Iranian National Commission
for Unesco. Avenue Iranchahr Chomali No 300,
B.P. 1533. Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop,
Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad; University Bookstore, Uni¬
versity of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, Baghdad. IRELAND.
The National Press, 2. Wellington Road, Ballsbridge,
Dublin 4. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly
Blumstein's Bookstores. 35 Allenby Road and 48, Nachlat
Benjamin Street. Tel-Aviv; 9, Shlomzion Hamalka Street
Jerusalem. (24 I.L.) JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores
Ltd., P.O. Box 3. i, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., P.O. Box 5050, Tokyo
International 1 00-31(Y 1 ,440). KENYA.The E.S.A. Ltd..
P.O. Box 30167. Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd.. P.O. Box
2942, Kuwait. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution. P.O. Box 34-
35, Tripoli. LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand -Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA.
Federal Publications Sdn Bhd.. Bala! Barita, 31, Jalan
Riong, Kuala Lumpur. MALTA. Sspienza's Library,
26 Kingsway. Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Com¬
pany Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (Rs. 17,45).
MONACO. British Library. 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout, 9, the Hague, (fl. 14). NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned
Ant.). N. V., Willemstad, Curacao. N.A. (NA fl. 7.80).
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office.
Government Bookshops at : Rutland Street, P.O. 8ox
5344. Auckland: 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721,
Christchurch ; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857, Hamilton;
Princes Street. P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington (8 3.00). NIGERIA
The University Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop
of Ibadan, P.O. Box 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsuka, The University Bookshop of Lagos. The Ahmadu
Bello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All
publications : johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl
johansgate 41/43. Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only; A.S.
Narvesens Litteraturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo6(K.23,00).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco
Publications House, P.O. Box 374 G.P.O., Lahore;
Showrooms ; Urdu Bazaar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree,
Highway, G/6-1, Islamabad. Pakistan Publications Book¬
shop, Sarwar Road, Rawalpindi; Paribagh, Dacca.
PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co.. 926 Rizal Ave¬
nue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. POLAND. All
publications : ORWN .PAN Palac Kultury I Nauki,
Warsaw. For the Unesco Courier only : RUCH, ul.
Wronia, 23, Warsaw 1 0. PORTUGAL. Dias.» Andrade
Ltda, Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon (Esd 05).
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Sdn Bhd., Times
House, River Valley Road, Singapore 9. SOUTHERN
RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 67 Union
Avenue. Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1 1 1 8, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications:
A/B C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2,
Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier : Svenska FN-Forbundet, Vasagatan 15, IV
10123, Stockholm 1 Postgiro 18 46 92 (Kr. 18).
SWITZERLAND. All publications : Europa Verlag,
5 Rimistrasse, ZUrich. Librairie Payot. rue- Grertus 6,
1211, Geneva 11. C.CP. 12-236 (Fr. S. 16.-). TAN¬
ZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Suksaparr Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (71.00 baht). TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal Caddesf. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala.
SOUTH AFRICA. All pubtlcacionsrVan Schaik's
Bookstore (Pty). Ltd., Librl Building. Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News Agency P.O. Box 1 033, Johannesburg.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops
in London. Edinburgh, Cardiff,- Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham. Bristol (£1.30).UNITED STATES. Unesco
Publications Canter. P.O. Box 4», New York. N.Y.
10016 ($5). U.S.S.R.- Mezhdunsrodnaja Kniga.
Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zaluzba Slo-
venije Mestni Trg. 26, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
School of tomorrow
Photo © USIS
The school of tomorrow as envisaged by some leading American educationists, architects and commu¬
nications experts. As shown in this artist's impression, it would have three towers for teaching human
resources, science and cultural media. Each tower provides education at kindergarten, school and
university level with the help of computers, radio, films, television and other audio-visual aids. Serious
obstacles and problems which have brought a crisis in world education will need to be overcome before
such ideal "scholastic cities" of the year 2000 become a reality. These problems are examined and
radical solutions proposed in the report on Unesco's recent inquiry into the state of world education
which provides the theme of this issue of the "Unesco Courier".
]]>
</page>
</document>
