<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078211eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^~^\ A window open on the world
Courier
November 1965 (18th year) U.K. : 1/6 stg. - Canada : 30 cents - France : 1 F
Menace
of the
Art
Thieves
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
WONDERS
OF
THE BUSH
UNICEF
In this painting by the Senegalese artist, Papa Ibra Tall, an uncle supports his young nephew high on his shoulders
as he introduces him to the plants, the birds, and other wild life of the bush. Entitled, "Wonders of the Bush", it is
one of the designs contributed by artists from many lands to the United Nations Children's Fund, for reproduction
on UNICEF greeting cards in 1965 (see page 32). Papa Ibra Tall grew up in Tivaouana, a well-known Senegalese
centre for handicrafts, and later studied in France. An artist of great versatility, whose work ranges from ceramics and
tapestry designing to painting and sculpture, he now heads the Plastic Research Section of the Dakar Art School.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
^"""^à A WIND OW OMN ON FN| WOlie
Courier
NOVEMBER 1965 - 18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2years:27/-stg.; 18 F. Singlecopies1/6-stg.;
30 cents ; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
tne opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim ElSawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Japanese Edition
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Italian Edition
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence shouldbe addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
Page
11
14
16
18
24
30
31
32
34
THIEF-PROOFING OUR ART MUSEUMS
By Richard LeBlanc
INTERPOL
A world-wide warning system against stolen art
MONA LISA ON THE MOVE
V.l. P. protection par excellence
57 PAINTINGS LOST IN ONE ROBBERY
HAVOC WROUGHT BY VANDALS
CONFRONTING THE IRASCIBLE IRAZU
By Haroun Tazieff
DISMANTLING ABU SIMBEL
By Louis A. Christophe
WORLD CONGRESS ON ILLITERACY
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
UNICEF GREETING CARDS
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Cover photo
Among the thousands of masterpieces
that have survived the centuries, their
beauty still intact, is this magnificent
statue on the Puerta Santa of the Cathe¬
dral of Santiago de Compostela, Spain,
which dates from the twelfth century.
But masterpieces of beauty are far too
often exposed to theft or vandalism.
Stricter protection of museums and
monuments open to the public is need¬
ed today when modern techniques can
facilitate surveillance. (See Page 4).
René Caloz
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
© Monuments Historiques, Paris
THIEF-PROOFING
OUR ART MUSEUMS
by Richard LeBlanc
4
It was a quiet afternoon. The citizens of Florence strolled
in the streets of their lovely city. And art-lovers flocked to
the Uffizi museum to view the rich collection of Italian
Renaissance paintings. But drama struck that day in one
of the modern art rooms. To the consternation of the
crowd collected around a painting of Morandi, the picture
suddenly fell from the wall with a crash. Upon inspection,
the authorities were dumbfounded to find scrawled on the
back of the canvas: "Thank you. I have always liked
Morandi." And the date of the theft was added. For theft
it was; the painting that had been hanging for weeks in that
spot was a reproduction.
And the newspapers had another headline.
I T is generally agreed that one of the happier
explosions taking place today is the increasing
interest in matters cultural. Symphony orchestras are
playing to full houses, theatres are enjoying long runs, and
museums are reporting ever-increasing crowds. Critical
publications have subscription lists almost as long as the
popular reviews Even the commercial cinema has done its
part with film biographies of artists and musicians.
However, there is another side to the coin. Too many
people have become too well aware of an artist's work
through the headlines: ANOTHER PAINTING STOLEN;
POLICE HUNT ART THIEF; RANSOM DEMANDED FOR
FAMOUS CANVAS. Too many who had never heard of
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
This "Adoration of the Shepherds" weighs 100 lbs (45 kg). It was stolen from the Basilica
in Saint-Denis, near Paris, one night in December 1963. A 17th Century altar front in gilt
vermeil, it measures 9 ft 1 0 ins by 2 ft 5 ins (3 m by 75 cm) . This splendid work is still missing.
Goya before, have been able to discourse learnedly on
the value of his "Duke of Wellington" since the painting
was stolen from the National Gallery in London in 1961.
And there are those who insist that the Louvre's "Mona
Lisa" by Leonardo is the more interesting (though hardly
on purely aesthetic grounds) for having been the victim of
a sensational theft just over fifty years ago.
Art is very much in the news, then. But the real irony
behind this boom is the danger to a museum's art treasures,
a danger which lies in direct proportion to the rise in
public interest. As countries make a greater effort to
display more works to a wider public, the shortcomings
of the museums become dramatically evident. Too few
of them increase the size of their staffs adequately, still
fewer the quality. A large European museum recently
opened 28 new rooms of art treasures, but not one extra
guard was hired to oversee and protect the new material.
This, of course necessitated a greater dispersion of the
existing guards.
This inadequacy in buildings and protective systems is
reflected in the increase in art theft as an industry. It is
said that in the United States alone three or four art -
objects are stolen every day from museums.
The problems of a museum are greatly increased by the
soaring value of works of art. If a painting by a modern
artist can sell for as much as $50,000, its attraction to a
thief is obvious.
Most stolen paintings are recovered, however. In one
six-week period of 1961, 65 canvases were stolen besides
the aforementioned Goya in both England and France.
All but one have been restored to their places of origin.
Some thieves are apparently unaware that police organi¬
zations the world over are given all details of a major
art theft and go to work immediately. Other thieves, who
have done their homework, realize that it is nearly
impossible to sell a recognized work. The normal proce¬
dure in such a case is to demand a ransom for the
picture a ransom which is all too frequently paid. Still
other criminals, more timorous perhaps, merely abandon
their treasures in the face of so much pressure.
Of course, in the case of other art objects, different
procedures can be used. Jewellery obviously lends itself
to the diamond cutter's art and can be reduced to readily
saleable cut stones. And sculptures can be and often
are, melted down, even if only to recover the intrinsic value
of the metal itself.
There are known cases where whole paintings have
been carefully cut up into smaller sections either for
attempted resale as a verifiable piece of a famous work
or merely for sale to the type of person who would rather
have a section of a celebrated painting than nothing at all.
Tapestries fall into the same melancholy category and
are frequently dismembered for piecemeal resale to the
unscrupulous.
The team that makes life so miserable for art thieves is
the International Criminal Police Organization known as
Interpol. It is Interpol that distributes reports on such thefts
to every major police force in the world, giving all the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THIEF-PROOFING MUSEUMS (Cont'd)
Security expensive ?... Not the morning after
pertinent data that may lead to recovery of the object.
This process has proved particularly effective in blocking
resales, since most pictures are taken for disposal to
countries other than those they were stolen from.
But Interpol is also aware of the high value of an ounce
of prevention; how, much simpler it would be if the thief
never managed to get away with that canvas.
To this end the International Council of Museums (ICOM)
has been working with Interpol since 1957. The Council, an
organization subsidized by Unesco, has given special
attention to the protection of museums against thefts. In
January of 1957 it asked Interpol to undertake a study that
would emphasize the preventive aspect, rather than
recovery, and would stress the combinations of human
beings and mechanical devices that might best discourage
any attempt at theft, or at least catch the thief before he
could leave the premises.
The results of this study have been published by Unesco*
in the quarterly magazine "Museum." The article was
written by Mr. André Noblecourt, chairman of the ICOM
Sub-Committee on Security in Museums and a technical
adviser on security to the museums of France.
Between the Interpol report and Mr. Noblecourt's article,
countries the world over were approached and asked to
contribute to the sum of knowledge on the subject. The
response was heartening. The presidents of national
committees of ICOM submitted reports of their own which
were collated in the final documentation.
The sixth ICOM General Conference, held in The Hague,
in July 1962, devoted considerable attention to the problem,
and the President of the ICOM Commission for Security
delivered a paper summarizing the progress made to date.
But the findings of these studies were often shocking.
NUMBER of countries reported using no pro-
. tective devices whatsoever to guard their art
treasures. Others listed inadequate or outdated methods
which would present no real problem to a determined
thief.
One of the most reassuring replies came from a museum
in Vienna. A system of thirty signals is activated if any
of the guards fail to report on a pre-arranged schedule.
When the alarms sound the main doors close automatically,
and local and federal police receive a "theft signal" by
means of a direct-contact cable. However, the museum
is forced to admit that the whole system is so expensive
to operate that it is only used to protect the most valuable
items. As the British point out, rather plaintively, "There
are no alarm systems which combine high efficiency with
low cost." The protection systems in the Louvre alone
cost over $45,000.
The consensus of museum experts Is that devices using
electromagnetic fields are the most effective. Instruments
such as television, radar and even infra-red detectors for
night-time can give the kind of spatial coverage which
protects large areas of the establishment by keeping them
constantly In view. The ¡mages from such fields can be
* "Museum" Vol. XVII No. 4, 1964.
led to a central observation post, thereby simplifying the
staff's job.
A museum in Columbia, South Carolina, which has
delicate devices attached to every one of its pictures,
reports that the paintings in one of its galleries are
"touched" 85 times every day. These are not thieves
but merely art lovers who cannot resist personal contact
with a canvas which attracts them strongly in the same
way that one Rembrandt lover has always wanted to pick
off that tiny point of white pigment that sits on the very
end of the master's nose in the self-portrait which hangs
in London's National Gallery.
The experts agree that a combination of systems is
preferable, since a single device could be studied and
overcome by a painstaking criminal or gang. It is also
pointed out that all systems dependent on electrical power
should have their own source of supply, since any interrup¬
tion in the regular current would put them out of action.
An important consideration in any system should be the
dispersion of the warning signal. Almost all authorities
are agreed that in addition to the resident guard unit, the
signal should go automatically to the police preferably
at a federal, as well as local, level.
HE mechanical techniques used in the protec¬
tion of works of art are often obvious. Armour
plating, pickproof locks, unbreakable laminated glass all
are in standard use, although rarely remarked by the
museumgoer.
Few visitors to a museum are aware that they are
constantly under surveillance through one-way glass strips
which are often disguised as decorative elements In the
gallery. But it is the "space-age" devices which are the
more exciting.
An enterprising thief, who had otherwise avoided the
devices elsewhere in the building, might find himself
caught out by a special microphone which can be so
adjusted as to "ignore" all other sounds except the noises
peculiar to his tools saws, hand-drills, blowtorches.
Certain instruments can be positioned so as to emit
a continuous ultra-sonic wave. When a would-be thief
breaks this wave, the resultant interruption activates an
electric cell which signals the fact to the guards.
Most of the rugs in museums are wired. At closing
time, the current Is turned on and anybody who steps on
the rug from that moment on closes a contact, sets off
an alarm bell and floodlights the room.
The professional burglar who feels that he is on to an
easy thing in exercising his craft in the realm of art, may
find that as his blowtorch starts to cut through a steel
plate he has caused a heat-sensitive detector to react.
One of the most effective follow-up devices, in this case,
is to have a charge of explosive set off by the detector,
designed to throw the thief Into a panic.
Close cousins to the ultrasonic devices are photo¬
electric beams, usually used in the daytime, and infra-red
instruments for the night. All work on the principle of
a field of waves which reacts to interruption.
Television cameras are highly practical aids to the
modern museum. Either fixed or "movable they can cover
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
This notice, issued jointly by the Toronto Art Gallery and the Canadian Police,
was circulated after the theft of six priceless paintings which were cut out of their
frames during the night of 14-15 September 1959 and stolen from the mu¬
seum. Doors of the museum were fitted with safety locks but not the windows,
and one had been broken. Two weeks later the paintings were recovered.
REWARD
FOR THE RECOVERY OF PAINTINGS
STOLEN FROM
THE ART GALLERY OF TORONTO
On Tuesday, September 15th, 1959
REMBRANDT:
'Portrait of a Lady with a Handkerchief"
Oil on canvas, 49 x 39'/j
REMBRANDT:
"Portrait of a Lady with a Lap Dog'
Oil on canvas, 32 x 25Va
HALS:
"Isaalc Abrahamsz. Massa"
Oil on canvas, 3 1 Vt x 255/s
HALS:
'Vincent Laurensz. van der Vinne"
Oil on canvas, 25 Vi x 1 9 Vi
RUBENS:
"The Elevation of the Cross"
Oil on paper on canvas, 28 x 52
RENOIR:
"Portrait de Claude"
Oil on canvas, 16 x 12'/¡
A substantial reward is offered for information leading to the recovery of any or all of these
stolen paintings. Telephone or wire collect to
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
INTERPOL
THEFT
WARNINGS
ALERT POLICE
IN
95 COUNTRIES
UNESCO and the International Council of Museums (ICOM)
have launched a campaign to make the museums of the
world more security-conscious. In this work, they are
being helped by Interpol, the International Criminal Police Orga¬
nization. Interpol, neither a super police force nor an inter¬
national detective agency, was founded in 1923 as a public service
to prevent and check crime. At the request of ICOM, Interpol
carried out the first world survey of alarm systems and other
devices used to protect museums against theft. When a theft
does occur, Interpol's own alarm system moves into action.
From Interpol headquarters in Paris, full details of the stolen
painting, sculpture or work of art are immediately circulated to
the police services of some 95 countries. No fewer than
fourteen different nations have notified thefts from museums,
galleries or public monuments during the last five years. Map
shows only thefts of publicly-owned works of art. It does not
list losses from private collections or galleries. There are
about 12,000 museums in the world today and they attract, be¬
tween them, some 220 million visitors every year. This is why
the problem of adequately protecting art treasures worries
museum authorities as never before.
8
CANADA
QUEBEC
MONTREAL
TORONTO
32 paintings :
Rembrandt, Corot,
Boudin, Monticefli,
etc.
1 Goya
1 Reynolds
1 Gainsborough
1 Raeburn
DUKE OF WELLINGTON by Goya,
stolen from National Gallery, London,
recovered in the left-luggage office
of Birmingham station this year.
PERU
URUBAMBA
OCONGATA
11 paintings
(many thousands of art
objects have been stolen
in recent years from pre-
Columbian burial sites).
DEATH OF JACOB, by Rembrandt, sepia wash and pen,
stolen from the galleries of the Montreal Museum of Fine
Arts in October 1964. This drawing still remains untraced.
NIGERIA
3 wood sculptures
stolen from lllobu
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
73 paintings :
Cézanne, Picasso,
Matisse, Duty,
Vlaminck, Signac,
Foujita, Utrillo, etc.
THE CARD PLAYERS, one of 8 paintings
by Cézanne stolen from the Aix en Pro¬
vence Museum in 1961. Recovered in 1962.
GERMANY
(Fed. Rep.)
1 Bertram
1 Wouwerman
AUSTRIA
34 sculptures
stolen from ten
different chur¬
ches.
2 paintings.
SWITZERLAND
CRANACH THE ELDER. This
16th Century portrait of Prince
Johann Friedrich was stolen in
1961 from the Museum of Fine Arts
in Basel, Switzerland. Recovered.
GREECE
1 sacred book (12-
th Cent.) stolen
from the St. Denis
Monastery of
Mount Athos.
ITALY
ROME
PALERMO
TURIN
FLORENCE
MINTURNO
MARZOBOTTO
FERRARA
SYRACUSE
GROSSETO
ASCOLI PICENO
AGRIGENTO
NAPLES
100 sculptures
and
works of art
Frescoes
(15th Cent.)
17 paintings,
retables and
triptyches.
This statue of
an Ephebe stood
two and a half
feet high in the
municipal mu¬
seum of Selinon-
te, Sicily. In Oc¬
tober 1962, it
vanished myste¬
riously and is
still on the
missing list.
SWEDEN
2 paintings :
Utrillo,
Frans Hals
(or school of)
NETHERLANDS
ROTTERDAM
HAARLEM
AMSTERDAM
2 Rembrandt
1 Provoost
BELGIUM
NAMUR
ANTWERP
BRUSSELS
GHENT
9 paintings
2 icons
1 Byzantine triptych
NEGRO HEADS, by Ru¬
bens, stolen from the
Musée d'Art Ancien in
Brussels on 16 February
1964. Painting was re¬
covered on the next day.
INDIA
16 bronze Buddhas
from the Nalanda
Archaeological Mu¬
seum.
14 statuettes stolen
in August 1961, two
more in March 1962.
Buddha
20 inches in height.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THIEF-PROOFING MUSEUMS (Cont'd)
Qualified guards & electronic traps
10
a wide field, can be realigned from a distance by remote
control, and enable a single man to watch an entire floor.
Even more useful for purposes of identification after a
theft, are photographic cameras which are set to film a
forced entry automatically. Used mostly in night work,
the cameras may be hidden and the criminal may not even
be aware that he is being "recorded" for Interpol.
Any and all of these systems have, normally, both
manual and automatic settings. They may serve to alert
the guard force by alarms, lights, or the direct vision of
a watching employee. They may also set off flares and
smoke bombs to further confuse a thief.
It is natural that museum authorities are loath to divulge
the types of devices they use. Even the makers of the
instruments keep details of their manufacture a closely
guarded secret and vary the designs frequently. Obviously,
if a thorough criminal could find out what systems a given
museum used, and could also study the devices them¬
selves, his work would be enormously simplified. Secrecy
about the entire subject is imperative as anyone who has
tried to discuss it with a museum security officer will know.
Museums, however, have every facility for finding out
about protective equipment. Detailed and attractively
designed catalogues are published by all the leading manu¬
facturers of anti-theft devices, and each offers to send
around an expert to advise a museum which equipment
to use for its particular needs.
But as the Interpol-Unesco report stresses, "Mechanical
devices alone are insufficient. The human being must be
there." Bells', smoke, dye sheet steel none serve any
purpose if the responsible museum staff cannot catch
the thief. And if the men responsible are sufficiently well
trained, the theft itself may never take place.
HE careful selection of able men (whose back¬
grounds can be checked) is an absolute requi-
l'errrv.t tor any museum. The quality of the personnel using
all these modern mechanical devices must be at least as
high as the devices themselves.
The guards or watchmen must be thoroughly familiar with
the layout of the museum. They must know of the presence
of all security devices and how to operate them. Their
patrols should normally be made at irregular intervals and
they should follow different routes.
In at least one New York museum the guards hired are
sworn into the regular police force and have all the powers
and responsibilities that go with such a position. In the
museum, there are a few of these security men whose job
it is to mingle with the art-viewers, pass through the galleries
with them, and even occasionally sit down with the crowds
to rest their weary feet but never their eyes.
According to Joseph Chapman, formerly with the United
States Federal Bureau of Investigation and currently an
international art "detective," the training of personnel
should be systematic, covering the areas of direct physical
intervention, warning procedures, and crowd control. He
points out that in 1964 a trio of thieves was able to take
the "Star of India" sapphire from its showcase in New
York's Museum of Natural History because the staff had
never been told of the existence of a contact alarm attached
to the case and had therefore not turned it on.
Mr. Chapman estimates that 40% of museum thefts are
the work of men who have secreted themselves in the
building while it was being closed down. They had thereby
eliminated their first problem that of entry but the fact
that they could do so is an indictment of the care taken
by the guards in their final-closing inspection.
A well trained staff must be constantly on the alert for
what is not visible, as well as for that which is. In one
provincial museum in France, a sketchbook of Cézanne
had lain open at the same page for some time before it
was discovered that an enterprising thief had cut out all
the pages from behind the two that were visible.
LLIED to this alertness is the need for a staff to
know exactly what the museum does contain, so
that a theft can be spotted as soon as possible or, if worst
comes to worst, an accurate description of the missing
object can be broadcast. Most museums keep multiple
records of all possessions. This precaution led to the
downfall of one dishonest employee of an American museum
in 1963. He carefully took all the records he could find on
the objects he had stolen, but was unaware of a further
set of records kept in a different place. This was enough
to trip him up.
Museum authorities in India suggest that in addition
to the normal records kept, a photographic file of every
picture should be made, preferably more than one of
each, and each file should be kept in a different locality
including a safe place outside the museum itself.
Overall responsibility for the security in a museum should
rest in the hands of one man, Mr. Chapman stresses.
Division of the load results in duplication of effort, and
greatly increases the risk of a "hole" In the system which
each person believes the other is responsible for.
Mr. Noblecourt has this to say on the financial aspect
of the problem : "... the need for (staff) quality involves
extremely careful selection. In order to obtain the services
of a picked staff who meet these criteria, it Is important
to make the posts well paid enough to attract and retain
good men. All those involved are agreed upon the
principle, but the same is not true of its application in
practice.
"Some foundations or private institutions which are
administered with an eye to profitability do not regard
money devoted to ensuring the protection of the collections
as unproductive ; the guards are therefore decently paid...
"We have thought it necessary to emphasize the primary
importance of the quality of the human factor, for however
efficacious material equipment may be, it must always
be borne in mind that the value of a fortress is measured
by the value of its defenders."
The sine qua non of the problem is the attitude of the
authorities toward their responsibilities. With more than
220 million people visiting some 12,000 museums throughout
the world, the problem has achieved vast proportions ; the
range of protective devices is impressive but they are
expensive. Yet, as Mr. Noblecourt concludes, "Security
is a field in which facts must be faced..."
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
^^ji#*«W«**
' Agraci, Pans
Mona Lisa
V.I.P. protection
par excellence
o
Photo © Pans - Match. Cournère
N December 14, 1962, in the dawn
light of a winter morning, a motor
car escorted by police pulled out
of the Louvre Museum in Paris (photo
left) and took the road for the port
of Le Havre: one of the world's most
famous paintings, Leonardo da Vinci's
"Mona Lisa" was off to America. It was
then exhibited for four weeks at the
National Gallery in Washington and for
a further month at the Metropolitan
Museum of Art in New York, to hund¬
reds of thousands -of admiring visitors.
In arranging for the "Mona Lisa" to
make this transatlantic voyage, the Lou¬
vre gave a demonstration par excellence
of how to protect a work of art against
every kind of danger. Technicians
planned the operation down to the last
detail. First, X-rays and large scale
photographs were made of the painting.
Then, removed from its frame, it was
placed between blocks of nylon as a
precaution against vibrations and packed
into a case weighing 80 kilogrammes
(187 lbs) specially designed to protect it
against shocks and changes of temper¬
ature (above).
The Louvre had already had occasion
to test the efficiency of similar air-con¬
ditioned containers when it sent paint¬
ings by Rembrandt to an exhibition in
Vienna. Even the possibility of a ship¬
wreck had been considered and to pro¬
vide maximum safety for such a VIP
passenger, the protective case had been
made unsinkablel Six guards kept
constant watch over the "Mona Lisa"
which travelled in a reserved cabin
fitted with a device to keep a 24-hour
check on the temperature.
The "Mona Lisa," now over 450 years | |
old, was brought from Italy to France
by Leonardo in 1516. It was given its
original name, "La Gioconda" because
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
MONA LISA
(Cont'd)
12
it is believed to be the portrait of the
wife of an Italian, Francisco del Giocon-
do. Francis I of France bought it from
Leonardo for 4,000 gold florins (a sum
that now corresponds to $600,000), but
its present-day value is inestimable. In
1911 it was stolen from the Louvre and
was not recovered until two years later
in Italy. In 1957 it was struck by a stone
thrown by a vandal who was trying to
mutilate it, but fortunately it suffered only
slight damage. Since then it has been
protected by a sheet of bullet-proof
glass.
In 1962, when the French Government
agreed to loan it to the United States,
the conditions under which it was to be
exhibited were specified in detail. While
on view in Washington and New York
it was under constant surveillance; only
natural lighting was used throughout its
exhibition and the use of flash bulbs by
photographers was forbidden the heat
generated by them might have changed
the temperature of the air-conditioned
hall. As the voyage of the "Mona Lisa",
proves, works of art can now travel
great distances without serious danger
of damage or deterioration, thanks to
modern protective techniques. "Mona
Lisa" returned to the Louvre in perfect
health on March 12, 1963 after being
seen by nearly 1,600,000 people in the
United States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
" Mona Lisa " in the National
Gallery, Washington.
Constant watch was kept
on the painting by
means of television cameras
covering the entire hall.
Image picked up by the cameras
was transmitted to a central
observation post.
Above, during the night,
one of the guards on
duty keeps his eyes fixed
on the masterpiece in
the now empty hall.
At the slightest sign of anything
suspicious he can sound a
general alarm.
Left, crowds file past
the " Mona Lisa ", guarded
by armed sentries.
As a further measure to
facilitate surveillance, only a
limited number of persons
at a time were allowed
into the hall.
Photos © Paris-Match
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
-.;-^"~ ....__.^ ^
The Bay of St.
Tropez (Duno-
yer de Segon-
zac). The only
one of 57 works
stolen from
the Annonciade
Museum in St.
Tropez in 1961
still missing.
The Jetty
at Honfleur
(Dufy)
57 oil paintings lost
in a single robbery
Westminster,
London
(Derain)
; »' - -- -*
iwwr iiij HÉÉ iMwwiMMMto^»^^^^^.,.-, ^^i^agir^-
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
V
X
I HE cleaning woman who opened the doors
of the Annonciade Museum at St. Tropez,
on the French Riviera, on the morning of
Sunday, July 17, 1961, got the shock of her
life. The walls of the ground floor galleries
were completely bare. During the night
thieves had broken in and helped themselves
to 57 paintings well over half the total collec¬
tion. The museum normally had a guard on
duty at night but on this particular occasion
he was absent, visiting a sick relative. Matisse,
Bonnard. Derain, Vlaminck, Marquet, Dufy the
names of just a few of the artists read like
a roll-call of giants in nearly half a century
of French painting, from 1890 to 1935. The
Annonciade Museum, in fact, was considered
to have one of France's finest collections of
modern painting, ranking, according to some
authorities, in fourth place after the two great
museums of modern art in Paris and the Gre¬
noble Museum. This was the fifth art robbery
to take place on the Riviera within a year.
Almost all the works taken in the earlier thefts
were recovered and many of the thieves were
arrested. The Annonciade Museum eventually
recovered all except one of the 57 paintings
(the missing one is shown opposite page, top).
*\
UZ^
?*
r?
0*
M
Woman at a Balustrade (Van Dongen)
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Associated Press
J. I.avaud
HAVOC WROUGHT
BY VANDALS
The Corcoran Gallery in Washington,
thwarted the thief who tried
to make off with this painting,
Rembrandt's
"Man with Hat Holding Scroll".
The painting, however,
was damaged slightly.
Museum restorer here works on cut
at bottom and right borders.
This Buddha at Pagan, Burma,
was the victim of man's greed.
It was completely disemboweled
by vandals in search of gold
they believed to be hidden inside.
Most of the statues
at Pagan are similarly mutilated.
16
¿3&:
tW»M
193
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
In January 1962,
the famed Uffizi Gallery in »Florence
suffered its worst case
of vandalism since the war.
One morning,
twenty-five masterpieces worth
almost 82 million were discovered
slashed and damaged,
all apparently by the same
deranged individual.
Finger in photo points
to long slash mark on 15th Century
masterpiece of "Madonna Enthroned"
by Hans Memling.
Museums are now redoubling
their efforts to safeguard
their art treasures.
TO protect their works of art mus¬
eums have to be constantly on
the alert. Museums know this,
but are often short of the material
means to provide proper protection.
A lack of surveillance, an excessive
dispersion of guards and the result
may be disastrous. Works of art may
not only be left as relatively easy and
tempting targets for the thief; they
can also become the victims of van¬
dalism of all kinds. In 1914 the
splendid "Venus" of Velazquez in
the National Gallery, London, was
slashed through and through by a
suffragette who chose this way to
alert the public to the urgency of
granting women's rights. In 1959 a
mentally unstable person tried to
slash a work by Rubens, "The Fall of
the Damned", in a Munich museum.
Two years later it was the turn of
a Montreal museum to suffer at the
hands of a visitor who, in a fit of
destructive fury, damaged valuable
works by Renoir, Daumier, Fantin-La-
tour, Monticelli and Coburn. Grapho-
maniacs are not satisfied with defac¬
ing public buildings and monuments.
To protect the painting, "La Source",
by Ingres from being defaced by
these scribblers, the' Louvre in Paris
has been obliged to cover it with
glass. Even true art lovers are some¬
times guilty of minor misdemeanours.
Delicate electronic devices attached
to paintings in one museum reveal
that they are touched anything up
to 100 times a day. To add to all
these problems, there is the omni¬
present one of finance, for as yet
there are no alarm systems which
combine high efficiency with low cost.
Associated Press
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Haroun Tazietî
On the night of September 27, 1965, the Taal volcano, in the Philippines, erupted
suddenly and violently, causing hundreds of deaths and widespread devasta¬
tion. Taal had already erupted three times since the beginning of the century.
Its last eruption in 1911 also caused heavy loss of life. The most recent catas¬
trophe is one more reminder of the vital need to keep constant watch over vol¬
canoes. Few eruptions fail to give some warning signs. If these are observed
and interpreted accurately and promptly, the local population can be evacuated
in time. Accurate methods of observation have now been developed. Principally,
these involve: the recording of earth tremors due to underground movements
of magma masses; the analysis of gases to detect changes in their composition
which occur before an eruption; and precise surveys of a volcanic crater as it
expands under the pressure of magma when an eruption is due. This last type
of diagnosis has been used by the American geophysicist, Robert W. Decker,
Last year he made repeated measurements with electronic equipment across
the Kilauea volcano crater in Hawaii, and recorded a 30 centimetre expansion
across its 4 kilometre diameter just before an eruption. Tellurometers, the in¬
struments used, have an accuracy of one millimetre per kilometre. Unesco is ac¬
tively developing a programme of international co-operation in volcano-logical re¬
search; since 1953 it has sent three missions to make on-the-spot investigations.
In 1964, Unesco sent a mission to Costa Rica following the eruption of the Irazu
18 volcano. This was led by the Belgian volcanologist, Haroun Tazieff, who de¬
scribes below the special problems of Irazu and the warning and protective mea¬
sures proposed by the mission.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
"Volcanology is like medicine," says the famous Bel¬
gian volcanologist, Haroun Tazieff. "Before a doctor
can give a prognosis, he has to know his patient. It
is the same with a volcano: the better we know it, the
greater chances we have of predicting its behaviour."
In March 1964 a Unesco emergency mission led by
Haroun Tazieff spent several weeks observing the
"feverish" volcano of Irazu in Costa Rica. Bell-shaped
helmet seen in this photo is the latest type of protec¬
tive headgear worn by volcanologists. It can withstand
the shock of a 60-pound weight dropped from 500 feet.
CONFRONTING
THE
IRASCIBLE
IRAZU
by Haroun Tazieff
I RAZU, a volcanic peak over 11,000 feet high In
the massive cordillera that dominates Costa
Rica, lies fifteen miles east of the capital, San José. Since
the day in 1723 when it awoke with fury, destroying the
city of Cartago, then the capital of Costa Rica, it has erupt¬
ed at least eight times.
Irazu had been dormant for almost half a century when
it suddenly erupted on May 13, 1963. Huge'clouds of vol¬
canic ash shot skywards; the earth near the crater was
blasted open for hundreds of yards and covered with
several feet of ash. Nearly four miles from the crater
ash soon lay a foot deep.
Yet the greatest threat to Cartago and nearby commun¬
ities was not volcanic fire, but the combination of ash
and water. Tropical rains can transform volcanic ash into
a river of mud that sweeps everything before it trees,
rocks, house-sized blocks of lava at the speed of an
avalanche. This was how Herculaneum was burled during
the eruption of Mount Vesuvius in 79 A.D. that also
wiped out nearby Pompeii.
In December 1963 a mud-flow coming down the Rio
Reventado on the slopes of Irazu advanced on Cartago
eight miles away, and swept through its lower section,
killing thirty persons and wreaking heavy damage.
Following this calamity, the Government of Costa Rica
asked Unesco to send an emergency mission to Ira7u
in order to study with Costa Rican engineers and scientists
the measures that could be taken to prevent a recurrence
of the disaster.
CONT'D ON PAGE 21
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ff'*- '
IRAZU (Cont'd)
A verdant landscape of woods
and growing crops surrounded
the volcanic peak of Irazu
until May 1963 when vast'
clouds of smoke and ash began
to belch forth from the volcano
(left, still in eruption in Feb¬
ruary 1964). Vegetation of all
kinds has since disappeared
beneath the deadly,rain of ash
(right) which covers everything
within a range of 12 miles and
in places is several feet deep.
With the arrival of tropical
rains, the mass of ash becomes
a sea of liquid mud, forming
torrents which slide down the
slopes, sweeping all before
them. Below, a jeep used by
the Unesco mission to Irazu
follows a narrow track cut
into a desolate mountainside.
Photos © H. Tazieff
>
*-.-
r
*
J ¿¥£\
fc (£* IP*
-*ki%
,
- -, $&
*t%***- >
}
-'.- r+
X >
H
«
'
j|
'4 <*
¥ »
I
«- 1 jij»
y . *
d 8s " \
j -
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
^f *
'S
s ï
Deadly rain of ash
In February 1964 we were entrusted with this volcano-
logical mission to Irazu.
The Costa Rican Government was eager to know how
the eruption that had been going on since May 13, 1963
was likely to develop. The crater was throwing out vast
quantities of ash (fresh liquid lava and old solid lava
pulverized by the explosions) which was jeopardizing the
coffee crop Costa Rica's chief economic asset and to
some extent was perturbing the life of San José, the
capital.
Was the discharge of ash going to continue, intensify
or cease? How great a risk was there of a sudden violent
explosion that might endanger the communities around the
volcano?
Such questions were difficult to answer, in the first
place because the present state of volcanology does not
permit acéurate forecasting either of the intensity or
duration of an eruption. Secondly, in this instance the
absence of previous studies meant that even an approxi¬
mate forecast was out of the question.
Volcanic forecasts often very reliable concerning the
start of an eruption are based on changes in certain
chemical and physical factors, essentially the composition
of gases, their temperatures and pressures, the nature
and depth of volcanic disturbances, the nature of micro-
seismic tremors, the tilting of the ground and so on. But
it is not yet possible to forecast the duration of an eruption
in progress.
The Costa Rican Government placed at the disposal of
the mission two jeeps fitted with radio transmitter-receiv¬
ers; a tracked vehicle without radio; a fixed radio trans¬
mitter-receiver; a petrol driven power unit for charging
batteries; two banks of accumulators and a volcanic bomb¬
proof shelter which was installed in a trench dug at our
request through the rim of the crater.
This shelter, the first volcanic observatory to be set up
on the American continent, was constructed of seml-
cylindric. steel sections placed end to end and covered
with earth. Entrance to it was gained through a doorway
at the valley side of the trench, while two windows,
protected by sliding timber shutters, looked out on the
crater side. The whole was erected speedily and effi¬
ciently by the Costa Rican Institute of Electricity, to which
the members of the Unesco Mission would like to express
their gratitude.
Once completed, this observatory-shelter became the
base station. A seismograph, installed in a concrete pit,
and generally functioning 24 hours out of 24, was connected
by cahle to a pen-recorder placed in the observatory. A
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
FIRST OBSERVATORY-RE
Protection against heat, explosions, showers of debris and
other hazards of a volcanic eruption has always been a major
problem for the volcanologist. Here, on the rim of the Irazu
crater, engineers of the Costa Rican Institute of Electricity
IRAZU (Cont'd)
The big killer: avalanches of mud
22
radio station was set up in the observatory by the Tele¬
communications Service of the Guardia Civil.
The mission then set up two mobile seismological sta¬
tions by placing a set of instruments seismograph, ampli¬
fier, recorder and chronostat in each of the radio-equipped
jeeps. These mobile stations were used to locate the
exact position and depth of the earth tremors.
This part of the programme was at first seriously hamper¬
ed, partly by difficulties with the radio-telephone links, -and
partly by noise interference picked up in the populated
areas where the mobile stations had to be sited. Several
nights had to be spent in trying to reduce such inter¬
ference to a minimum, and this additional work caused
extreme fatigue, for during this time it was vital to maintain
the daily recordings and observations.
During the six weeks it spent in Costa Rica, the seismo¬
logical team used six miles of recording paper for its
seismograms. This enormous, volume of data was analyz¬
ed immediately it had been recorded, thanks to the devotion
of the experts who often worked 18 to 20 hours per day.
It was thus possible to provide the government with a
day-to-day record of the seismic activity of the volcano
during that period.
The first studies of the volcano and its activity showed
that -there was little immediate danger of a paroxysmal
explosion though the possibility of it happening in the
future could not be excluded or of an outflow of lava.
However, there was a definite and very serious risk for
the whole area lying on. the leeward side of the volcano
in relation to the prevailing winds. The danger was from
torrents (or avalanches) of volcanic mud, known also as
"mud-flows", or lahars. It is difficult to understand why
this danger is everywhere so seldom realized, for on the
average, lahars cause greater losses of life and property
over the whole world than outflows of lava or volcanic
explosions.
Lahars can either occur during the violent phase of an
eruption, due to the sudden melting of snow or ice by the
glowing lava or, in the case of a volcano with a crater
lake, through the ejection of the water (sub-lacustrine vol-
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
UGE IN THE AMERICAS
build a volcanic bomb-proof shelter of reinforced steel sec'
covered with earth for the Unesco mission. Photos sh<
stages in the construction of this armour-plated volcanic
observatorythe first to beset up on the American continent.
Photos © H. Tazieff
canic explosion). They may also be caused by the effect
of rain falling on the thick layer of ash, sand and dust
that has accumulated on the slopes during an eruption.
It was the third cause with which we had to deal at
Irazu. By the time we arrived in the district the dry season
had already lasted two months, during which the eruption
had neither diminished nor changed in nature. Immense
quantities of ash, with no rain to wash them away had
gradually accumulated on the lee side of the crater.
Although stable when dry, such a mass does not remain
so when wet, and it seemed inevitable that heavy down¬
pours during the rainy season would create torrents of
mud capable of devastating the inhabited areas on the
slopes and at the foot of the volcano.
Our exploration of the slopes at Irazu showed that the
thick layers of ash had built up chiefly in the upper valleys
of the rivers Durazno (to the west), Tiribi (south west),
Reventado (south) and to a lesser degree the Taras (south
east). Ash also covered the northern and western slopes
of the volcano, but the danger here was less because the
forests had not been cleared for pasture to the same
extent as towards the south.
On the southern slope the danger was greater because
of the lack of vegetation and the effects of previous
erosion. There would thus be few obstacles to slow down
or halt the progress of mud-flows once they -had started.
Less than 30 per cent of water is enough to transform
dry volcanic ash into liquid mud. As a mud-flow builds
up and surges to the bottom of a valley, its initial volume is
swollen with debris of all kinds and sizes that the mud
sweeps along with it: trees are uprooted, rocks and stones
are torn away from the sides and bottom of the valley.
It has been found that a lahar may increase its volume
sixfold in this way.
While it remains, in the higher part of the mountain this
mass is contained by the deep ravines, or quebradas. 0Q
These, however, usually peter out suddenly where the
slope decreases near the foot of the volcano. At this
point the mass of the lahar suddenly spreads out like a
CONT'D ON PAGE 30
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Giant sandstone baboons over six feet
high (right) topped the facade of the
great temple of Abu Simbel until they
were cut into blocks last August. For
3,000 years they were the first figures on
the façade to be lit by the rays of the
sun as it rose above the hills on the far
side of the Nile. The dismantling of the
Abu Simbel temples must be completed
by August 1966; to reconstruct them on
higher ground will take until May 1970.
Photos Unesco-Nenadovic
DISMANTLING
ABU SIMBEL
by Louis A. Christophe
HE dismantling of the great temple of Abu
Simbel has begun; 300,000 tons of rock have
been removed; the hill above the temple has been
excavated. On the façade the frieze of baboons and the
hieroglyphic inscriptions beneath it have been cut into
blocks. Last August, the ceiling of the sanctuary was
removed and for the first time light from above shone down
on the gods seated in the darkness within.
The operations at present proceeding at Abu Simbel
the first of their kind in the world have but one object: to
save intact for posterity two unique monuments. These have
to be transported, block by block, to a position near the
original site but higher up so that the waters rising behind
24 the Aswan High Dam can never reach them.
The initial stage of the work is nearing completion. It
began with the separation of the two temples from the
hillside out of which they were hewn, by removing the entire
mass of surrounding rock. This called for precisely cal¬
culated protective works: the reinforcement of the façades
by sandhills as a precaution against damage being caused
to the statues by falling blocks of stone, and the installation
of scaffolding to support the ceilings in the interior of both
monuments.
Indeed, there is no denying that for the returning traveller
the remembered charm of Abu Simbel has vanished. And
this first sad impression is in no way mitigated by the
spectacle of the sandhills which cover the façades, by *hë
long laborious walk through the long metal tunnel leading
inside the monuments and by the sight of the complicated
network of scaffolding which fills the various halls.
But when reason finally triumphs over emotion, every¬
thing immediately becomes clear. The coffer-dam, some
400,000 cubic metres of rockfill material whose crest now
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
rises 135 metres above sea level, is there to remind us of
the danger which threatened this historic site. Had this
coffer-dam not raised its protective mass before the temples
of Abu Simbel, they would have been submerged and
damaged during the winter of 1964-65, and perhaps some
of their treasures the Osirian pillars with their huge statues
in particular would already have been destroyed.
The great temple is now completely separated from the
mass of rock which surrounded it and, in August 1965, the
first ceiling, that of the sanctuary, was cut into three blocks,
each weighing from 15 to 20 tons. These blocks were lifted
by a giant crane and deposited not far from the site where
they will be put back in place next year. A trench is now
being dug behind the sanctuary to facilitate the cutting of
the walls of that hall and of the four seated figures that are
its main adornment.
On the façade, other blocks have likewise been cut away
with infinite precaution and stored: first, those directly
surrounding the sculptured part, the pylon of the monument,
which is to be used again in the reconstruction so that the
framework will consist of the original stone; then those of
the façade itself the frieze of baboons, the cornice and
the hieroglyphic inscription just below the baboons. By
the end of August, the work had reached the horizontal
torus and it was planned to make an early start on cutting
up the top of the crown of the huge statue seated at the
south end of the façade.
The removal of the mass of rock from above the small
temple was begun much later and has just reached the
series of blocks which will be used again when the temple
is re-erected. However, since this monument is smaller
than its neighbour, it will be easier to cut up and work will
begin in the near future, even before all the blocks of the
great temple have been transported, on reassembling the
pieces of the small temple on the site now being prepared
for it.
In fact, as one climbs from the river bank to the plateau
towering over the temples of Abu Simbel, one passes
through a series of work-sites. Below, men are cutting
into the living rock; above they are levelling off sites for
the new foundations of the two monuments; nearby, tra¬
velling cranes are busily storing away the huge stone
blocks which are brought up several times a day by special
trailer lorries.
These different centres of activity, where workmen labour
for twenty hours out of the twenty-four, are linked by a net¬
work of asphalted roads. These roads also lead further
south to a village by now almost a straggling town
which is nearing completion. Workshops and equipment
stores have sprung up near the work-sites as well as
installations which supply water and electricity. A little
further away are offices and homes (the engineers often
have their families with them) built around a dining hall and
a club, where a swimming pool is now being constructed.
In front of these simple, rectangular houses built in
Nubian style, alluvial soil brought up from the river bank
when the lake was at its lowest level and just before the
beginning of the flood season has been laid down to
CONT'D ON PAGE 29
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
The façade of Abu Simbel as it appeared in
the spring of 1850 to the French writer,
Maxime du Camp, who took this daguerre¬
otype the first photograph ever made of
the temple. The colossi were half hidden by
a river of sand flowing down the hillside.
Abu Simbel was probably invaded by sand
during the XXVI Dynasty, 2,500 years ago.
Unesco Unesco-Laurenza
The statues of Rameses on the northern side of
the temple entrance as seen for half a century.
The huge sand dune which had half hidden the
temple was not completely cleared until 1910.
The rise and fall of
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
/if/ i-.- - ./ *#<**/ Mr +w * %s .
/ *v ;»-H u
V» 1
1964
y " '
i» i K
i»
if
. -
Bulldozer covers the façade with sand to
protect the giant statues of Rameses during
the dismantling operations. These are sched¬
uled to be completed in the autumn of 1966,
.* Klrtrt-n/^^M/1/1*
a
Photos Unesco-Nenadovic
History appears to be repeating itself.
Only the heads of the colossi emerge from
the man-made sand dune, as they did in
1850. Since September 1965 the statues
of Rameses have been completely hidden
from sight and the frieze of baboons
above them has now been cut up and
removed. (See drawing next page.)
the Nubian sands
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
*?
V
¿ /
^A' **
From left to right, hieroglyphic
inscription on upper façade
of the great temple at Abu
Simbel is split into huge blocks.
Left, hand saws, not power
tools, are used for this oper¬
ation. Blocks are numbered
(foreground, centre photo) and
stored to await temple's re¬
construction on hilltop. Far
right, section is gently lowered
to giant transporter. It bears
the graven inscription: "Rame¬
ses, beloved of the gods".
Photos Unesco-Menadovic
Í
Drawing VBB, Stockholm
Architect's drawing gives section view of great temple during dismantling operations. Arrow
marks emplacement of colossal statues of Rameses II on façade of the Great Temple of Abu
Simbel, totally covered with sand asa protective measure. Temple has been completely separated
from mass of rock around it. Statues surrounded by scaffolding are Osirian pillars of the first hall.
Last September, sanctuary ceiling was cut into three blocks each weighing between 15 and 20tons.
28
-d *S*tt
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
DISMANTLING ABU SIMBEL (Cont'd)
receive shrubs and flowers. Finally, beyond the hospital,
the round-roofed houses of the workmen hide the runway
where light aircraft land every day, maintaining rapid com¬
munication with Aswan.
The desert-like plateau, which was once the exclusive
domain of scorpions, snakes, jackals and hyenas, is now a
place of bustling activity, full of the constant movement of
squads of workmen, transport lorries, mini-buses carrying
foremen and engineers, and motor cars taking the key men
in this vast enterprise to points where the most delicate
operations are going on. Here, as elsewhere in Nubia,
birds are rare; they all seem to have flown away to more
fertile regions. There is only a flock of vultures at the
western edge of the village, attracted from no one knows
where by the cries of the animals at the slaughter-house.
In scorching summer heat and during the near-freezing
nights of the Nubian winter, engineers, foreman and labour¬
ers are working without respite to save the temples of
Abu Simbel from the threatening waters.
By the end of 1966, when the reconstruction of the
smaller temple will be well advanced, the first blocks of the
great temple are to be fitted into place on the new site.
And two or three years later, visitors to Abu Simbel will
have the surprise and pleasure of seeing that a dream has
become reality. The waters of the Aswan High Dam will
again mirror the majestic facades of the temples, behind
which, rebuilt exactly as before, the monuments will stand
within the heart of a man-made mountain.
This monumental achievement of modern times recalls
symbolically one of the noblest of the Osirian legends.
As the story is told, Set, being jealous of Osiris, imprisoned
his brother in a chest, and to gain undisputed sway over
Egypt, killed him, cutting his body into twenty pieces which
he cast into the Nile. Isis, the wife of Osiris, searched
along the river until she found the twenty pieces and was
able to reconstitute the body of her husband. After under¬
going the magic rites of embalming, Osiris ensured his
succession on earth through his son, Horus, before
descending to the underworld to become the god of
the dead.
In like manner, thanks to the international campaign
launched by Unesco, the temples of Abu Simbel will rise
again in all their ancient majesty.
t LOUIS A. CHRISTOPHE, Assistant Secretary-General of the In¬
stitut d'Egypte, was appointed by Unesco in 7960 to supervise
the work of preservation of the Nubian monuments in the UAR.
He is the author of many papers on ancient Egypt and has just
published a book on Abu Simbel (boxed note below).
The Discovery of Abu Simbel
Since the day on 22 March 1813 when the Swiss Traveller
Johann Burckhart stumbled upon the temples of Abu Simbel
deeply buried in the sands, the monuments of Rameses II
have had a long and eventful history. Their many adven¬
tures form the subject of a new book by Louis A. Christ¬
ophe "Abou Simbel et l'épopée de sa découverte" . An English
translation of the work ¡s in course of preparation. (Published
under the patronage of Belgium's Queen Elizabeth Founda¬
tion of Egyptology and with the co-operation of the Belgian
Ministry of Education and Culture. Editions P. F. Merckx,
Brussels, 1965. 35.50 French francs; 395 Belgian francs.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
IRAZU (Cont'd from page 23)
Interpreting
a volcano's
early warning system
fan, overflowing the banks of the river and destroying
everything in its path not only by flooding, but through
the tremendous battering-ram blows given by the rocks
and tree trunks it carries along.
To meet this danger two types of defence active and
passive can be adopted. Active defence consists of
diverting or deepening river beds, building dams or, as a
long term measure, drainage and reafforestation.
In the case of Irazu, with less than two months to go
before the onset of the rains, "active" defence methods
could have done no more than protect densely populated
places that were specifically threatened, and in particular
the city of Cartago on the lower reaches of the River
Reventado.
"Passive" defence techniques, on the other hand, could
be and were in fact put into effect immediately. Broadly,
these consisted of installing observation posts at carefully
chosen points. These posts functioned throughout the
24 hours, and were equipped with apparatus designed to
give the alarm, at any moment of the day or night and
whatever the weather, as soon as the warning level was
reached.
From Semaphore
to Satellite
History
of
Communications
%	
To mark the hundredth year of world co-operation
in telecommunications, the International Telecom¬
munication Union (ITU) has published a popular
history of the media since the beginning of tele¬
graphy. Entitled "From Semaphore to Satellite"
the 340-page, richly illustrated book offers a fascin¬
ating account for readers in all walks of life.
Young people will find in it the full experience of
a century of technical progress and international
collaboration in one of the most exciting branches
of knowledge, as well as the promise telecommuni¬
cations offer in the space age. Available through
bookstores or from ITU, Place des Nations, 1211
Geneva 20, Switz. in English, French or Spanish
(40 Swiss Frs. or US $9.50).
30
UR mission also recommended the installation
of automatic rain gauges which would transmit
a radio warning the moment rainfall reached a critical level.
We also suggested that automatic gauges be placed in the
ravines to alert the authorities to an excessive rise in the
water level.
This warning system had to be supplemented by careful
planning of the orderly evacuation of the people in the
threatened areas in case of an alert at any time of the
day or night.
Finally, arrangements had to be made for the eventual
rehousing of people whose dwellings might be destroyed,
and road maintenance carried out so as to provide alter¬
native escape routes to the main road, whose bridges, like
those carrying the San José-Limon railway, were threatened
with destruction.
The Costa Rican government decided to give effect to
the measures recommended by the Unesco Mission, which
can consider that its goal was achieved.
As it happened, two months after the departure of the
mission, the first lahars occurred at the start of the rainy
season. Only one life was lost whereas without the warning
system the death roll would have been heavy almost
certainly numbered in hundreds.
HAROUN TAZIEFF, Belgian geologist and volcanologist, is the
author of many scientific studies on volcanology and works for
the general reader. English-language editions of his books include :
"Craters of Fire", Hamish Hamilton, London, 1952; Harper, New
York, 1954; "The Orion Book of Volcanoes" , Orion, New York,
1961 (Volcanoes, Prentice-Hall, London, 1963); and "When the
Earth Trembles", Hart-Davis, London, 1964; Harcourt, New York,
1964. Haroun Tazieff has produced several prize-winning scientific
and documentary films on volcanic eruptions.
WORLD CONGRESS
THE first World Congress of Ministers of Education on the
Eradication of Illiteracy, which ended September 19 in Teheran,
addressed a unanimous appeal to the United Nations, its
specialized agencies (particularly Unesco), regional bodies, non¬
governmental organizations and public and private foundations to
help finance a movement to eradicate illiteracy which currently
blights 44 per cent of the world's adult population.
Among the most important points stressed in over 80 recom¬
mendations adopted by the 88 countries attending, were the fol¬
lowing:
Firstly, delegates from both industrial and developing countries
have recognized that illiteracy is truly a world problem. Delegates
from the more advanced countries have offered aid mainly for
training teachers specialized in literacy techniques.
Secondly, the need to integrate literacy fully into economic
development has now been unanimously accepted. This does not
mean, as several delegates observed, that education should be
regarded as important solely in economic terms. It is also the
leaven of cultural and intellectual growth and a means to make
every person aware of his rights and duties as a citizen.
Thirdly, delegates agreed that the conflict between schooling
for children and adult literacy is actually a false dilemma. In fact,
both are necessary, the former being a long-term investment and
the latter a short-term investment with immediate impact on nation¬
al development. This is why adult literacy must be integrated
into national economic planning to the same extent as the develop¬
ment of the educational system as a whole.
The congress gave its full backing to Unesco's experimental
literacy programme and particularly to pilot projects for which
financial help has been requested from the United Nations Special
Fund. Some delegates asked that this programme be extended
and the number of pilot projects increased.
Mr. René Maheu, Unesco Director-General, declared that Special
Fund's proposals were realistic and could be handled by the
mssmmsmustxi^
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
MUSEUMS OF THE FUTURE. The
training of personnel to better appre¬
ciate the place of museums in the life
of the community was proposed by the
650 participants at the meeting of the
International Council of Museums (ICOM),
held at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in
New York in September. Delegates to the
meeting criticised the present approach to
training and approved the Secretary of the
Smithsonian who said: "Museums must
establish themselves as essential and top
-rank educational institutions equal to...
all levels of educational activities".
MONUMENT PRESERVATION. A society
for the preservation of historic and
cultural monuments has been founded in
the Federal Republic of Russia in the USSR.
Some 30,000 monuments have been cata¬
logued so far. The new society will even¬
tually comprise a network of municipal,
regional and national organizations.
PREHISTORIC FLOODS. A new theory
that the ancient cities of the Indus
flood-plain were gradually engulfed by mud
is advanced by R.H. Raiker, writing in the
September 1965 issue of "Antiquity", the
British quarterly review of Archaeology.
Mr. Raiker, a hydrologist, cites recent field-
work at Mohenjo-Daro to support his hypo¬
thesis.
THE FIRST RAZOR ? Radio carbon dating
of charcoal discovered with an ancient
bronze razor during excavations in the
Chichen-lngushetian Republic of the Nor¬
thern Caucasus, makes it probably the
earliest piece of shaving equipment known.
The razor is between 10,000 and 13,000 years
old.
From the Unesco New
SOVIET STUDENTS. More than 3,500,000
students are now studying at Soviet
colleges and universities an increase of
some 250,000 over last year's figure. Only
370,000 of the 836,000 first-year students
are studying full time. The others are
taking evening classes or correspondence
courses.
GONE WITH THE VICUNA. In common
with many other animals, the vicuna is
threatened with extinction. The vicuna is a
ruminant related to the llama, that roams
in herds over the higher mountains in Peru,
Bolivia and Equador. Its wool is delicate
and soft and, although it is a protected
animal, it is estimated that tens of thou¬
sands are killed by poachers every year.
A meeting of experts, held recently in
Peru to study the protection of the vicuna,
counselled the creation of national parks
and reserves to protect the surviving herds
and the formation of experimental breeding
stations.
INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH IN BIO-
LOGY. A proposal for an international
laboratory for fundamental research in bio¬
logy has been endorsed by an expert
committee of seven leading biologists
meeting in Paris. But the committee recom¬
mended that if such a laboratory were
founded, it should be Europe-oriented, at
least for the first few years of its existence.
The Paris Committee included three Nobel
Prize winners Prof. Severo Ochoa of New
York, Dr. Max Perutz of the Medical
Research Council (United Kingdom) and
Dr. Peter Medawar, director of the London
Institute of Medical Research as well as
distinguished biologists from France, Bel¬
gium, Italy and the Soviet Union.
BOOKS IN BRITAIN : In the item entitled
"Giants of Publishing" (page 15, Sept.
1965) the United Kingdom was not listed as
third amongst the world's six largest produ¬
cers of titles of books. In 1962 the U.K.
published 25,079 titles as compared to
21,904 in the U.S.A. In 1963 the number
of book titles in the U.K. rose to 26,023
and that of the U.S.A. to 25,784. The
United States is rapidly catching up with
Britain in the number of titles published
each year.
CORRECTION : In our October Issue
we omitted to mention that the article
"Science, a New Social Force" by Mikhail
Millionshchikov was an abridgement of the
address delivered by the chairman of the
U.S.S.R. Pugwash Committee on Science
and World Affairs at the United Nations
in New York earlier this year.
SPURS FIGHT AGAINST ILLITERACY
Unesco secretariat. At the same time, he asked the Special Fund
to consider the possibility of increasing its effort for literacy.
He made it clear, however, that the problem of financing mass
literacy work will depend upon the extent to which nations concern¬
ed succeed in integrating literacy campaigns into their develop¬
ment plans. Each country, he said, must come to a sovereign deci¬
sion concerning the relative importance it wishes to give literacy in
these plans. In this way, the financing of literacy should become
part of the general financing of development.
In this context the congress also asked the U.N. and its
agencies to exert their influence on all responsible leaders to:
1) ensure that literacy is an integral and essential part of every
development plan in countries where illiteracy is a problem;
2) increase, as far as possible, the national and international
resources devoted to the fight against illiteracy;
3) make possible the provision of additional resources for de¬
velopment in general and literacy in particular as further funds
become available following a reduction in military expenditures;
4) harness fully all information media to progagate the new
concept of adult literacy.
ERTAIN developing countries expressed their intention
to increase funds devoted to literacy. Others stated
they had already reached a maximum figure which could not be
increased without running the risk of seriously disturbing their
national economy.
The congress also agreed that large-scale but spasmodic attacks
on illiteracy, despite the enthusiasm they may have aroused, have
not prevented thousands of adults from lapsing back into illiteracy.
This is why delegates placed a priority on functional literacy
conceived in conjunction with vocational training. In this .respect,
as many of them explained, every country cannot adopt the same
strategy: this must vary depending upon social and economic
structures, traditions and overall national goals.
Concerning public opinion, the congress stressed the need to
bring home to illiterates the reasons behind any literacy drive.
Strategy alone cannot make such a drive succeed, warned
Mr. Maheu, if it is not galvanized by public opinion. "It would
be impossible to carry out a large-scale campaign without mobilizing
public opinion," he said.
In discussing literacy methods, delegates from several countries
where many languages still have no written alphabets announced
they have recently been able to devise alphabets for these lan¬
guages. Others, on the contrary, appealed to linguistic institutes
for help in finding solutions.
During the closing session of the congress, Prime Minister Amir
Abbas Hoveyda of Iran announced that an annual prize will be
placed at Unesco's disposal to reward a person, or institution,
making a contribution in the field of literacy. Then Mr. Maheu
stressed the importance of the congress which marked decisive
progress in a field of ideas important to Unesco. Equally impor¬
tant, he added, was the remarkable unanimity with which delegates
adopted a strategy for national and international action. He stated:
"From their deliberations has emerged a new concept for concerted
means for large-scale action. Illiteracy can be wiped out in a
relatively short time if all those who seek to further progress in
developing countries will aid literacy as an integral part of deve¬
lopment. This is true for bilateral programmes, it is also true
for international programmes."
The congress, convened by Unesco upon the initiative of the
Shah of Iran, was opened by the Shah on September 8. "The
existence of an enormous mass of illiterates [is] the root cause
of the inequality which splits mankind into two separate segments,"
the Shah declared in opening the congress, adding, "it is a
constant menace to social peace [and] to peace itself." The Shah
then proposed that all nations help finance literacy by making
small deductions from their military budgets.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
ß'lrUu'l*.
/ « ; . . * ,i ft 4 iL
* ' * -f - » - \ * **"*- *
* * - 'j * - ; *i
«5
"Fairy Tale" by the Soviet artist Oreste Vereisky, whose skilful
illustrations have enhanced many books, including Nobel Prize¬
winner Mikhail Sholokhov's epic work "And Quiet Flows the Don."
UNICEF
GREETING CARDS
This year, "Unesco Courier" readers will find a wide
choice of designs among the 19 greeting cards
which UNICEF is putting on sale for the 1965-66
festive season. Each year the sale of greeting cards
enables UNICEF to help needy children in over
100 countries. In this way UNICEF last year raised
$2,400,000; this year it hopes to sell 40 million
cards. Fifteen artists from all parts of the world
have contributed this year's designs : Papa Ibra
Tall (Senegal see page 2) ; Brian Wildsmith
(United Kingdom); Beni Montresor, Mario Topi
and Paolo Tomasi (Italy) ; André Bouquet and
Louis Toffoli (France); Yaroslava Mills, Hope
Meryman and Andrew Wyeth (United States);
Oreste Vereisky (USSR); Maria Vail (Spain);
Christian Larsen (Denmark); Shalom of Safed
(Israel). This year's cards include the water colour
design which the French painter Raoul Dufy
donated to UNICEF in 1952. It depicts UN
Headquarters in New York and is being reissued
to commemorate the 20th anniversary of the
founding of the United Nations and to celebrate
International Co-operation Year. We reproduce
here some of the new UNICEF greeting cards.
"Dreaming of Christmas" (right) by
Christian Larsen, a young Danish
book illustrator and poster designer.
Africa South America
32
Asia Australia
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
r
World of fancy
Brian Wildsmith, a British artist, is one
of the world's most stimulating illustrators
of children's books. For UNICEF he has
done five designs entitled "A World of
Fancy" featuring favourite animals of chil¬
dren on all the continents. > Painted in
warm colours, they reflect the fantasy and
excitement of a child's imaginary world.
UNICEF cards come
in boxes of ten pric¬
ed at 7/6 (U.K.); $1.25
(U.S.A.); 7 F (Fran¬
ce). Large format
cards (design by An¬
drew Wyeth) cost
15/-; $2.50; 12 F. For
further information
(free illustrated full
colour brochure is
available) and orders
write to thé follow¬
ing addresses: U.K.
Cttee. for UNICEF,
New Gallery Centre,
123 Regent St., Lon¬
don W.1.; U.S.A.
Cttee. for UNICEF,
United Nations, New
York, N.Y. 10017; Ca¬
nadian Cttee. for
UNICEF, 737 Church
St., Toronto 5, Ont.;
Comité Français pour
l'UNICEF (section
cartes de vtux), 24,
rue Borghèse, Neuil-
ly-sur-Seine, France.
Please do not
address orders for
cards to Unesco.
33
Above, "Playtime", a design in colour lithography by Hope
Meryman, a young American artist.
Europe
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
34
YOUTH NOT YEAH-YEAH
I have just finished reading your July-
August issue the special youth num¬
ber. I was pleased to see that, after
reading those excellent articles, the
older generation will at least know
that some of us have other thoughts
and aims than those generally attri¬
buted to the youth of today. All we
hear about are juvenile delinquents
and the yeah-yeah set. But besides
these, there are other young people
who have to find their place in
contemporary society. It was also a
good idea to stress that today's youth is
not completely selfish. We try to help
those who need assistance as in the
case of the international work-camps,
which have so many supporters.
Cécile Clément,
Périgueux, Dordogne
France
MAHARAJA JAI SINGH
Sir,
We are not only surprised but
shocked to know that in the June
1965 issue of the Unesco Courier the
Prince Jai Singh II has been described
as a powerful Muslim ruler.
The Maharaja described as a prince
Is Maharaja Sawai Jai Singh II who
ruled over Amber from 1699 to 1727
A.D. He shifted his capital In 1727
A.D. to Jaipur after carefully and
systematically planning the city, and
ruled till 1743 A.D.
Anybody acquainted with the history
of the Muslims and Rajputs (Hindus)
would not have been confused. The
rulers of Amber and Jaipur have always
been Hindus,
The Royal House of Jaipur traces
its history from Lord Rama, who had
two sons Lava and Kusha. Since
the family descends in direct line from
Kusha the clan is known as Kush-
waha. They in the begining ruled
over Ayodhaya, then shifted to Gwa-
lior and Narwar, then to Dausa, later
to Ramgarh and finally to Amber
which was annexed from the Mina
clan chief.
Jaipur is not sixty but 191 miles
from Delhi. Maharaja Sawai Jai
Singh II is not the last Muslim ruler,
but ruled during the time of the last
powerful Mughal ruler Aurangzeb.
The only astronomical observatory
in the Amber territory was at Jaipur,
which was built while Mohammad Shah
the Mughal Emperor was ruling over
Delhi.
The other places where the remain¬
ing four observatories were built were
all in the Mughal territories as Sawai
Jai Singh was siding with the Emperor
at Delhi.
Maharaja Sawai Jai Singh was one
of the most outstanding rulers of Jai
pur. He was a great scholar, a fine
politician, a shrewd diplomat, an
expert architect and town-planner, a
capable mathematician and astrono¬
mer, a fearless soldier and an able
general; therefore, his name will go
down to posterity as the builder of a
kingdom and the founder of a civi¬
lization.
He came to the throne of Amber as
a very young man in 1699 and at a
period when the foundations of the
great Mughal Empire, built by Akbar,
had already started shaking, before
crumbling to pieces after the death
of Aurangzeb. The Maharaja had
great foresight and tact. He very well
realized the approaching changes. He
anticipated an era of peace and pros¬
perity and therefore decided to have
a larger kingdom, expanded his terri¬
tories and made himself powerful.
Once this ambition was fulfilled he
gave serious thought to having a new
capital for his state, because Amber
was surrounded by hills and could not
be expanded nor could it become an
ideal capital of the Kachwaha Raj, as
contemplated by him. After ruling and
thinking for twenty-eight years at
Amber and making additions to the
Amber Fort and building Jaigarh Fort
and Sudarshangash Fort (now known
as Nahargarh), he decided to have a
new city in the plains.
The foundation of the new city,
named after the Maharaja, was laid
in the year 1727. There are various
stories to account for the regular plan
of the city. One is that the observa¬
tory was the first thing made and that
the Maharaja, following his mathema¬
tical bent, had the city laid out
with mathematical precision. Another
account is that Constantinople was
taken as a model and yet another that
the Chandnl Chauk at Delhi gave the
Maharaja his idea. Whatever might
have given him the inspiration, the
result has been to produce a most
striking and remarkable city.
The Maharaja built astronomical
observatories at Jaipur, Delhi, Mathu-
ra, Bañaras and Ujjain. For himself
he built a palace at Jaipur which occu¬
pies one seventh of the total area of
the originally planned city.
Maharaja Sawai Jai Singh fought
many battles and was always success¬
ful because he had the resourceful¬
ness of Caesar and Hannibal, the
shrewdness of 'Napoleon, the political
sagacity of Pitt the Younger, the taste
for learning of Vikramaditya and the
planning of Vishvakarma. Thus by his
genius he extended the prestige of the
Kachwahas throughout the country and
his voice commanded great influence
at the Imperial Court and also in
Rajasthan.
His court was adorned by nine gems
who had shed lustre by their great
achievements in various spheres of
human activity. Rajamal, the Prime
Minister; Rao Kripa Ram, the am¬
bassador at Delhi; Pandit Ratnakar,
the preceptor; Samrat Pundarik, the
Purohit; Panna Miyan, the Nadir; Pan-,
dit Vidyadhar, the town-planner and
architect; Rao Dalel Singh of Dhula
and Deep Singh of Kasli, two famous
generals; and Juovierde - Silva, the
famous Portuguese astrologer.
Maharaja Jai Singh persuaded the
Mughal Emperor to abolish the hated
Jazia tax and was the first ruler of
Jaipur to get the title of Maharajadhiraj
Raj Rajendra and the rare distinction
of "Mahi Maratib"., He was the only
ruler who performed the Ashvamegha
Yagna.
Col. James Tod, the diplomat and
traveller, writes, "The astronomical
studies of Maharaja Jai Singh were
wonders of the age. The observato¬
ries which he erected in the early
18th century at Delhi, Mathura, Ujjain,
Bañaras and Jaipur are monuments
which irradiate this dark epoch of the
history of India. He attached himself
to no particular school but studied
Hindu, Muslim and European methods
impartially."
To sum up, in the words of the
English writer, Arthur Garrett: "Jai
Singh, firstly revived Hindu astronomy
and gave such an impetus to its study
as had not been known in India since
the time of Brahma Gupta in the
7th century: secondly he promoted the
study of mathematics, history and
learning and collected a large library;
thirdly he issued a revised star cata¬
logue, reformed the calender and pro¬
duced a set of tables of the sun, moon
and planets of greatly increased
accuracy; and lastly, he has left to us
the most important record of all, viz.
his instruments."
In the book "The Discovery of
India," Jawahar Lai Nehru, writing
about Jai Singh and his planning,
states: "The City of Jaipur was so well
and wisely planned.ihat it is still con¬
sidered a model of town-planning...
Jai Singh would have been a remark¬
able man anywhere and at any time."
Jai Singh was really a remarkable
man and a ruler who shall never and
should never be forgotten.
Sangram Singh
Director
Maharaja of Jaipur Museum
Jaipur, India
u
z
<
oí
<
13
Z
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Binders for the
UNESCO COURIER
We offer subscribers a special
binder for their copies of the
Unesco Courier. Holding a year's
issue of the magazine, these
convenient and attractive bin¬
ders cost :
12/6 stg.
$2.50
6 F.
Order from Unesco National
Distributors listed below.
Don't wait until the end of the year!
GIVE A NEW YEAR'S
GIFT-SUBSCRIPTION
TO THE
UNESCO COURIER
Each month friends will remember
your gift and thank you for it.
A full year's subscription only :
15/-stg. $3.00 (Canada) 10 F (France).
UNIQUE IN THE WORLD OF JOURNALISM
the Unesco Courier offers a vivid picture of the endless
diversity of peoples and countries, the great adventures of
art and science and the outstanding problems of our time.
A CHOICE OF EIGHT LANGUAGE EDITIONS
English, French, Spanish, Russian,
German, Arabic, Japanese, Italian.
Your friends will receive a card announcing your gift subscription
before the New Year, providing you place your order early and mark
it "please inform addressee ".
(Order from Unesco National Distributors listed below.)
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Boek-handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
112, rue du Trône, Brussels S. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
(	). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
(8 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 1 3/ 5 0). CHINA.World Book CoLtd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section I.Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722. Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L,
Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 17).
ETHIOPIA. Internacional Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja¬
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*. CCP.
12598-48. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R.Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren-
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kulcura,
P. O. Box. 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
lonsson it Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol
Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 1 3;Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386. New Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book 8c
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New Delhi 3.
(Rs.7). INDONESIA. P.T.N. "Permuta-Nusantara" c/o
Dept.ofCommerce,22,DjalanNusantara,D)akarta. IRAQ.
Mackenzie'sBookshop.Baghdad.I RELAN D.The National
Press. 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. 4.(15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O.Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. BahousS Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (10/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd., Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9 ; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/.). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 0/-). MONACO. British
Library 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9. The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C T. .Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box S344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721). Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). - NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops. P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litceratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks
115 (17.50 kr.).' PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, and Educacional Supply Co., Colonial Mutual
Building Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publi¬
cations : A/B CE. Fntzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagacan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publicacions :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
121 I.Geneva 11, CCP, 1-23 6. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala (1 0/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-
50). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil. Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sc. Adly-Pashi, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office. P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 3 4th St, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Kn-
jlg, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
CONFRONTING THE IRASCIBLE IRAZU
Irazu is one of Costa Rica's most formidable vol¬
canic peaks. It has erupted nine times in the past
250 years (1723, 1726, 1822, 1844, 1847,
1882, 1917, 1920 and 1963). In 1964, a Unesco
scientific mission led by Haroun Tazieff made an on -
the-spot study of this irascible giant (see page 18).
H. Tazieff
]]>
</page>
</document>
