<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078208eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window open on the world
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
1965: International
Co-operation Year
live in a world of conflicts and yet the world goes
WW on, undoubtedly because of the co-operation of
nations and individuals... Little is known, or little is said, about this
co-operation that is going on, but a great deal is said about every
point of conflict, and so the world is full of this idea that the
conflicts go on and we live on the verge of disaster. Perhaps
it would be a truer picture if the co-operation elements in the
world today were put forward and we were made to think that
the world depends on co-operation and not on conflict."
In these words, addressed to the United Nations General
Assembly, Jawaharlal Nehru, the late Prime Minister of India,
drew the attention of the world community to the relative silence
on the immense amount of co-operative work that goes on
between countries in contrast to the emphasis that is placed on
conflict in the world.
Mr. Nehru recalled a suggestion that the U.N. General Assembly
should ask all countries to devote a year "not to speeches
about peace", but to the furtherance of co-operative activities
in all fields. The dedication of such a year, he believed, might
direct man's thinking and energy to the idea of co-operation,
and thus create an atmosphere for solving problems more easily
and lessen the world's conflicts.
On December 19, 1962 the U.N. General Assembly unani¬
mously adopted the idea of an International Co-operation Year
and on November 21, 1963, it designated 1965, the 20th anni¬
versary of the United Nations, as International Co-operation Year.
HE Year will be commemorated under the symbol
of joined hands and with the theme "Peace and
Progress through Co-operation". Stamps issued by the U.N.
Postal Administration and a special medallion will commemorate
jointly the U.N. Anniversary and the International Co-operation
Year.
U.N. Specialized Agencies, the International Atomic Energy
Agency, non-governmental organizations and U.N. member states
have been asked to link their own special interests and activities
with commemoration plans for this year of co-operation. Member
states have been asked to consider ratifying a number of mul¬
tilateral agreements which have as yet been applied only on a
limited scale, particularly those relating to the Law of the Sea
and to Human Rights and related fields.
The Year of International Co-operation will have attained its
goal if it leads a greater number of the world's peoples to
concern themselves more directly with the problems of interna¬
tional co-operation, as well as its achievements, its hopes and its
potentialities.
II
Unesco-Ministry of Information. Government of India
The work of the World Meteorological Organization is one of
the longest-established examples of effective world-wide
co-operation. This specialized agency of the United Nations
grew out of the International Meteorological Organization,
an organization of national weather services created nearly
90 years ago. In the U.N. calendar for International Co¬
operation Year, March 23 has been designated as World
Meteorological Day. Here, a meteorological observation
balloon with transmitter is released from a research vessel.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Coúfíer
MARCH 1965
18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
Detail of operating wheels on
the world's first calculating
machine devised by Blaise
Pascal in 1642. Other inven¬
tors later improved on Pascal's
system, but it was not com¬
pletely replaced until 1946 in
the era of the electronic
computer (see page 15).
Michel Péron. Paris
17 SCIENCE AND THE COMMON MAN (Part two)
By Ritchie Calder
18 THE INVENTIVE GENIUS OF LEONARDO DA VINCI
Models of the earliest automobile, aeroplane, helicopter
>4 GENEVA : WORLD H.Q. AGAINST SMALLPOX
28 EDWARD JENNER, THE FATHER OF VACCINATION
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 UNESCO'S WORLD PROGRAMME FOR 1965-66
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL. SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
France
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
Jane Albert Hesse
Arturo Despouey
Victor Goliachkov
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
French Edition
Spanish Edition :
Russian Edition
German Edition :
Arabic Edition :
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly (11 issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German,
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : 1S/-stg. ; S3.00 (Canada);
10 French Francs or equivalent ; 2 years: 27/-stg. ; 18 F.
Single copies 1/6-stg ; 30 cents; 1 F.
(M.C. 65.1., 200 A)
N° 3, 1965
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Few people are unaware today that the
scientific explosion is transforming our basic
patterns of living, but precisely how it has
done so and the important role of funda¬
mental research are still far too often mis¬
understood. In Unesco's programme science
has now been given priority on an equal
footing with education (see page 34). This
was reflected last year when a world-renown¬
ed scientist was elected President of the
13th Session of the Unesco General Confer¬
ence. He was Prof. N.M. Sissakian, principal
scientific secretary of the Praesdium of the
Academy of Sciences of the U.S.S.R. and a
world authority on space biology. Last year
he was elected a member of the International
Academy of Astronautics. Below we publish
an abbreviated version of the address he
delivered following his election to the distin¬
guished world post.
Unesco's General
Conference in session
in the main hall at
Unesco's H.Q. in Paris.
Unesco - R. Lesage
THE INTERNATIONAL PROS
I
4
N the history of civilization, science has always
been a force for progress. Today, under new
social conditions, it is becoming a directly productive
force. Every human activity is closely bound up in one
way or another with the utilization of the achievements
of science and technology.
Thus, two problems take on major importance: the
extension of theoretical, fundamental research in such
branches of science as physics, chemistry and biology ;
and the application of science to production.
After Galvani made his famous discovery of electric
phenomena in living organisms, several decades went by
before the appearance of the first electric lamp. Today,
any important discovery very quickly reaches the production
stage, outstripping the most optimistic hopes of its inventors.
Every one knows that the development of mathematics
determined the growth of mathematical logic and cyber¬
netics which, in conjuction with the achievements in elec¬
tronics, led to the manufacture of computers and automatic-
control machines that play so important and vital a part
both in science and technology. Achievements in
theoretical and experimental physics gave man mastery
over the nuclear energy of the atom, and are now helping
him to gain control over thermonuclear processes so that
they can be used as a mighty and practically inexhaustible
source of peaceful energy.
Achievements in modern science ushered in the era
of the exploration of the cosmos with the aid of artificial
sputniks, rockets and spaceships, and led to the creation
of the indispensable basis for a deeper knowledge of the
natural phenomena of the universe, bringing, as it were,
the planets of the solar system nearer to our planet. The
development of modern biology, biophysics and micro¬
biology provided the basis for the development of bran¬
ches of industry concerned with antibiotics, vitamins,
ferments and pharmaceutics, all of which are vitally impor¬
tant to human life. Thus, theoretical research conditions
practical scientific achievement, makes possible technical
progress and can sometimes lead to the creation of new
branches of knowledge and of production.
While economic independence is essential to the achieve¬
ment of full political independence, economic progress is
unthinkable without the development of natural and applied
sciences in every country and without the rapid transla¬
tion of results into practice. The investigation of nature's
regular patterns, the discovery of new laws which increase
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
PECTS OF SCIENCE
by
Noraïr M.
Sissakian
man's control over spontaneous natural phenomena, so
that he can utilize natural resources more rationally and
enrich them all this is the task of the natural sciences.
Knowledge of natural resources is especially important
for the developing countries which are now becoming
industrialized and transforming their agriculture.
The development of chemistry has become absolutely
indispensable. This science enables man to produce more
and better clothes, to create new materials which are
stronger and more efficient than natural materials, to
preserve food and to eat better. We have all become
aware in recent years of the growing importance of deve¬
loping the chemistry of natural compounds, together with
the study of the mechanism of biochemical synthesis and
the investigation of the biological effects on the soil of
the chemicals used to control plant and animal diseases.
It Is at present impossible to maintain high livestock pro¬
ductivity and high yields in agriculture unless chemicals
are used. On the other hand, the indiscriminate use of
chemicals is fraught with danger for the health of men
and animals. That is why problems of soil biology, bio¬
chemistry and cell biology are so important and must be
investigated.
New technical principles involving the widespread appli¬
cation of the laws of living nature have emerged, as, for
example, in problems concerning reliability in technology
or in increasing the efficiency of mechanisms and tech¬
nological systems. At this level, complex interdisciplinary
study of the brain takes on a special importance.
The close links between science and education and the
growing role of science in our modern society have led
Unesco, to accord a priority to science in its programme
similar to that already given to education. It is impossible
to speak of the effectiveness of education if its results
are not incorporated in technical and scientific projects
and do not lead to the solution of technical and scientific
problems. In turn, the effectiveness of education is
determined by scientific and technical achievement.
Certain fears have been voiced in the past and unfor¬
tunately are still being reiterated by some people that
our planet's sources of energy are being rapidly exhausted
and that we shall be unable to feed an increasingly vast
population. Present-day achievements in the natural
sciences and in technology have answered these fears j)
and show that all grounds for pessimism are unfounded.
As I have said, recent discoveries in physics have
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL PROSPECTS OF SCIENCE (Cont'd)
An assessment
of world needs and resources
6
opened the way to controlling thermonuclear reactions. A
solution to this problem would fully satisfy the power
requirements of all mankind and for all time. As to our
capacity to provide adequate food supplies for the entire
population of the world, the following figures can be
quoted. The total, surface area of arable land, plantations
and orchards in the world amounts to 1,400 million hec¬
tares, while pastureland covers 2,600 million hectares, i. e.
only 11 to 12 per cent of the total land area. Let us
assume that these figures remain unchanged until the end
of the 20th century. By this time overall yields will have
risen to the level already reached in many countries of the
world: three tons per hectare of arable land and one ton
per hectare of pastureland. Even if we base our calcula¬
tions on these minimum figures, total production by the
end of the 20th century will amount to 7,000 million tons
of standard cereal units. This is sufficient to feed twice
the population which will inhabit the earth by the end of
the century, according to United Nations estimates.
HESE calculations do not include food resources
of the oceans and seas where the major part
of the organic matter formed on the earth is found. However,
so far the biological and mineral resources of the oceans
have only been sporadically exploited. It is only natural
that the rapidly increasing population of the earth should
want to use them to the fullest extent. This has now become
possible thanks to the rapid progress of science and
different technological developments. A recent French film,
"Le monde sans soleil " (World Without Sun) gives a good
idea of the wealth of resources in sea and ocean and of
the peculiarities, variety and beauty of marine life.
The biological riches of the oceans are mainly food
resources. They are a source of proteins the most
frequently deficient item in diets. They are also a valu¬
able food supply for birds and animals, and an essential
element in a variety of technological processes. Accord¬
ing to the most conservative estimates, the world catch
of marine food products will reach 50 million tons in the
near future. But this is not a ceiling. The figure can
be raised in the near future to 100 million tons a year.
The experience of Peru, which in the last ten years has
increased 200-fold the fishing haul in the central part
of its Pacific seaboard, is a striking pointer to future
prospects.
A knowledge of the laws governing production of
organic substances by marine organisms is essential if
we are to make use of the rich biological resources of
the ocean and increase productivity. Without this know¬
ledge it is impossible to project fishing standards or to
develop new strains or new fishing grounds.
The chemical and mineral resources of the ocean are
inexhaustible. Almost all the known chemical elements
in the Mendeleyev's Periodic Table occur in sea water or on
the ocean bed. So far, because of existing traditions in
economics and technology, it is mainly cooking salt, bro¬
mine, magnesium and calcium that have been extracted
from sea water. And yet, reserves of iron and manganese
in the sea and the ocean amount to 200 thousand million
tons, while oil and gas reserves on the sea-bed are com¬
parable with continental deposits, and may even exceed
them.
The study of seas and oceans and the exploitation of
their mineral and food resources raise many national and
international problems. They will have to be solved if the
fishing industry is to be developed, useful species accli
matized, useless and harmful organisms removed and the
industry diverted from one species to another and from
area to area, in order to preserve ocean resources from
exhaustion and create a stable source of raw materials.
Unesco must play an ever-increasing role in solving these
problems.
In another sector, the demineralization of sea water
opens up broad prospects for the satisfaction of mankind's
growing demand for fresh water. Not so long ago there
was no shortage of water over the greater part of the
world. At present the demand for fresh water has grown,
and is continuing to grow, to such an extent that the prob¬
lem of a water "famine" has arisen.
The provision of public water supplies for expanding
towns and rural communities goes hand in hand with an
increase in individual consumption. Agriculture, for reliable
harvests, needs irrigation, which demands ever increasing
quantities of water. Industry, and particularly the chemical
industry, uses tremendous amounts. This is why the ques¬
tion of the quality of water and the distillation of sea
water are now among the most important scientific and
technical problems of our time.
To solve these problems, the use of atomic energy is of
the greatest importance. The demineralization of sea water
through international co-operation and research by scien¬
tists from many countries is one of the main goals in the
application of atomic energy to peaceful uses. Atomic
energy should cease to be a potential weapon capable of
destroying man's material wealth and cultural treasures;
it should be made the means of turning deserts into
gardens and of meeting man's increasing needs for fresh
water.
But the demineralization of sea water is still not in every¬
day use. The collection and rational use of existing fresh¬
water supplies are thus of far-reaching importance. One
example of the successful solution of this problem Is the
construction of the Aswan High Dam with the prospects
it offers for the agricultural and industrial use of water and
for cheap water power.
ROBLEMS of water supply are complicated not
only by the fact that water is required in greater
quantities than ever before, but also because man replaces
much of the water he draws from his reserves by conta¬
minated waters, the majority of which are toxic even in
the weakest solutions.
Because of this toxicity, particular forms of fauna and
flora are destroyed, their reproductive process is damaged,
their fertility reduced and the quality of their progeny
lowered. Owing to the testing of nuclear weapons, various
radioactive substances fall into reservoirs. The peoples
of the entire world must achieve a complete cessation of
all types of tests of atomic weapons. The struggle for
a clean atmosphere, hydrosphere and biosphere therefore
becomes a task of prime importance.
According to a report by the World Health Organiza¬
tion, waterborne diseases, including typhoid, dysentery and
cholera, strike down five hundred million people every
year and cause the death of five million babies. In this
connexion it was decided at the most recent World Health
Assembly to take steps to expedite the preparation of
national programmes for ensuring that drinking water is
safe to use.
But the elimination of infectious diseases depends not
CONT'D ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco-Australian Commonwealth Film Unit
Aboard an océanographie research ship in an expedition sponsored by Unesco, a crew
member takes samples taken from the sea for laboratory analysis. In 1959 Unesco sponsored an
expedition to the Indian Ocean, joined by 24 countries. This survey will continue until the end
of 1965. In 1963 Unesco launched a seven-country expedition in the tropical Atlantic Ocean.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL PROSPECTS OF SCIENCE (Cont'd)
only on the protection of water from contamination, but
also on a profound understanding of the biochemical and
physiological processes which take place ¡n the cell, and
the organism as a whole. In this connexion, the co-ordina¬
tion of activities between the various organizations in the
United Nations system and the international non-govern¬
mental organizations is of growing importance.
There is a vast and rapidly developing scientific field
where international collaboration is particularly needed:
the earth sciences. Today, geophysicists are agreed that
it is quite impossible to grasp the laws governing the deve¬
lopment of the earth's crust by carrying out observations,
however thorough, in a single region. Only synchronized
and uniform observations throughout the world, only the
study of every object and every process, using all the
available methods and technical means, can substantially
further man's understanding of the nature of the processes
taking place in the earth's crust. It is particularly impor¬
tant to plan ways in which man may master these tre¬
mendous forces, these processes that unleash energy far
surpassing anything we have produced artificially, and
subordinate them to his will.
International scientific co-operation, successfully initiated
on an unprecedented scale during the International Geo¬
physical Year and since continued through new international
projects, should therefore aim not only at conducting
research in certain countries but also at applying the
results of this research to improve living conditions for
all peoples.
I
8
T is no mere chance that Unesco has been
called upon to play a leading role here.
Unesco's support of such international projects in the earth
sciences as the international project for the study of the
upper mantle, international oceanography research, the
International Years of the Quiet Sun and the programme
for the study of icebergs, earthquakes and volcanoes, will
help not only to make possible scientific observations that
build up the over all picture, but also to organize such
observations in developing countries. The creation of
suitable observatories, laboratories and services will lead
both to the general progress of science in these countries
and to the discovery of new natural resources. Foundations
will be laid for an active harnessing of nature that can be
effective only if undertaken on a world-wide scale.
Unesco's action under its seismological programme has
become particularly important. An overall picture of pro¬
gress in seismological research and in anti-seismic
construction has been obtained through missions carried
out in many earthquake-prone countries. With the know¬
ledge thus obtained it should be possible to solve the most
urgent problems of regions where the danger of earth
tremors is greatest. The mapping of danger zones and
the adoption of special measures, protective and construc¬
tional, will save human lives and prevent costly damage.
There is every reason to hope for fruitful results from
international co-operation in this field.
The significance of education is best exemplified by the
popular saying that an illiterate man cannot see even from
a mountain top. Education is of the greatest economic
and social importance especially nowadays when the
harmonious development of man's mental and physical
faculties must satisfy the needs of all sections of society,
serving as an essential basis for continued progress. As
for problems in the field of public education, every aspect
of these economic repercussions must be studied. One
example we may quote is the work of S.G. Strumilin, a mem¬
ber of the Soviet Academy, who has attempted to assess the
economic consequences of the development of educa¬
tion. Prof. Strumlin has reached the following conclusion:
the value of the work done by a person who has had four
year's primary education is 43 % greater than that of an
illiterate person, 108 % greater if he has had a secondary
school education and 300 % times greater if he had a higher
education. Taking these figures as a basis for calculation,
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
Educational
around
Reviewing Unesco's present work and
future plans, the Unesco General Conference
heard the views of 94 speakers, forty-
seven of them Ministers of Education. In
discussions on the world's educational
problems delegates reported on develop¬
ments in their own countries. Here we
present a few educational highlights from
these discussions. For other news of the
Unesco General Conference see page 34.
Costa Rica
Education has always been given a high priority in Costa
Rica where the two first presidents were schoolteachers
and primary education has been free since 1869. In 13
years (1950-63) Costa Rica increased school attendance
in the 7-12 age group by 21% (to 88%). Today more than
half the country's population aged under 25 attend schools
or universities.
Republic of Korea
Ninety-five per cent of primary school age children (about
five million) attend classes. To meet classroom shortages,
some classes are organized in two or three shifts. Korea
has a high literacy rate (about 90%).
Cuba
A nationwide campaign has reduced illiteracy from 23% in
1958 to 3.9%. Over two million people (out of seven million)
attended schools and universities in 1963. Since 1958 pri¬
mary school enrolment has almost doubled (1,280,000) and
5,000 extra classrooms have been built. Free and compul¬
sory education will be increased from six to nine years.
Bulgaria
Since 1939 student enrolment has increased tenfold. Recent
statistics rank Bulgaria in fourth place in the world for ratio
of students to total popuplation.
Tunisia
Helped by an educational planning policy introduced in
1962 school attendance has risen sharply. Compared with
ten years ago primary school enrolment has more than dou¬
bled and secondary school enrolment has tripled. The 1965-
68 Plan for Economic and Social Development includes a
literacy programme for 250,000 agricultural and industrial
workers.
Mexico
Five hundred and forty-six new secondary schools will be
built in Mexico following a decree recently signed by
President Gustavo Doas Ordaz. Mexico is now building
primary -schools at the rate of 4,000 a year.
Saudi Arabia
Progress in providing education for girls is revealed by a
tripled enrolment in the past three years. Four special
schools for the blind have been opened, including one for
girls. A new university has been set up in Jedda, a higher
technical institute in Riydah and a petrology institute in
Dhahran,
Venezuela
Venezuela's campaign for literacy has reduced the national
illiteracy rate from 47% to 13% in six years. In the past
five years primary school enrolment has nearly doubled
and over 6,000 classrooms have been built. Over 26,000
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
the world
workers have been trained under a programme sponsored
by the Co-operative Education Institute which now plans
to give vocational training to 60,000 young people.
Iran
Secondary school graduates of military age are drafted
into an Educational Corps. After a short military course
and an intensive teaching course, recruits are sent to isola¬
ted villages for 14 months to teach children and adults.
Uruguay
In Uruguay, whose illiteracy rate (9.69%) is one of the
lowest in Latin America, education is free at all levels.
Over 95% of children now attend school. Secondary
school attendance has increased fourfold in the past two
decades with a sharp rise in rural areas. Over 35% of
university students and 53% of secondary school teachers
are women.
Ghana
Science teachers for secondary schools and teacher train¬
ing colleges are now being trained at the University College
of Science Education, Cape Coast. A Department of
Natural Resources is to be set up at the Faculty of
Technology of Kwame Nkrumah University and will give
science courses at a higher level.
Greece
Under a new law the following educational reforms are
planned: education at all levels from primary school to
university will be free; compulsory education will be
extended to the age of 15; new universities will be set up
at Janina and Patras and an Institute of Advanced Pedagogy
will be opened in Athens.
Congo (Brazzaville)
A five-year education plan will provide schooling for vir¬
tually all children between the ages of six and fourteen.
National goal for 1973 is to have nearly 5,000 classes and
over 220,000 pupils.
Democratic Republic of Congo
In the past four years primary school attendance increased
by half a million (to 2,000,000) and secondary school atten¬
dance has nearly quadrupled. The Congo has three uni¬
versities and ten institutes of higher education.
Libya
To overcome the shortage of secondary teachers, the
government has decided that all university graduates, except
those in medicine and engineering, will teach in secondary
schools for two years. This year the first engineers will
graduate from the Institute of Technology set up with
Unesco's aid.
Spain
The 1964-67 National Development Plan, includes the organi¬
zation of literacy classes for 1,700,000 adults; 5,000 teachers
have been trained in literacy class techniques. Education
is now compulsory up to the age of 14; a programme to
build 15,000 new schools has been launched.
Guinea
Under a seven-year economic development plan a campaign
has been launched to reduce the country's 90% illiteracy
rate. In the past six years primary schools have increased
five-fold to 1,459, and school attendance four-fold
to 170,000.
Malaysia
Malaysia devotes a quarter of its budget to education.
The introduction of free and compulsory education in 1961
has raised attendance of school age children to 94%.
\
X
In every part of the world progress in education depends on the
availability of more teachers on every level. Above, spacious hall of
the teacher training college at Ondo, 200 miles north east of Lagos
in Nigeria. Construction is not yet completed, but 450 students have
already been attending lectures since May 1964. Below, setting up
a library in the college. Unesco has sent a specialist adviser to Ondo,
has contributed audio-visual material and granted fellowships.
Photos Unesco - Almasy
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
r.
fe
t*
¿LA
by Ted Morello
First grade primary school
children learn to read with
new teaching machine.
usis
10
T a time when the field of education is In
worldwide ferment, a single instructional pheno¬
menon has captured the attention not only of pro¬
fessionals but of laymen. It is the so-called "teaching
machine revolution" or, more properly, "programmed
instruction".
Some of the striking achievements attributed to pro¬
grammed teaching under experimental conditions help to
explain the fascination that auto-instruction exercises:
Children two and three years of age have been taught
to read and type... Without teacher, textbook or homework
eighth-grade pupils completed a full year's work In ninth-
grade algebra in a single semester... Three University of
Michigan students were taught by machine to speak fluent
Spanish in half the time required by traditional methods...
Studying for seven hours a day, an eleven-man group
learned as much Russian in 10 days as they would have
in one and a half semesters of conventional college study.
Referring particularly to emerging nations, one authority
says: "We are convinced that programmed instruction can
work miracles... in solving the world's educational prob¬
lems."
A "programme" consists of instructional material de¬
signed to lead a pupil almost unaided and without error to
a pre-selected level of learning by what amounts to a
Pavlovian stimulus-response-reward pattern. Behind any
programme lies the theory that the material must start with
something familiar to the student and progress with increas¬
ing difficulty through steps so small that the student can
move forward alone with reasonable assurance of respond¬
ing correctly. A programme may be presented in book
form or by mechanical devices (hence the designation,
"teaching machine").
As a practical matter, programmed instruction has not
yet progressed beyond the tentative, experimental stage.
There are those who contend that it never will, for nothing
approaching unanimity exists in academic reaction to this
unknown quantity clamouring for acceptance.
Few Innovations In teaching have generated so much
debate. At one extreme are those whose missionary zeal
for teaching machines borders on fanaticism. At the other
are those who, for a variety of reasons, condemn them just
as enthusiastically. In between Is the overwhelming bulk
of educators uncertain, cautious, even suspicious, but
hopeful, too, and eager to believe that here at last is a
sign pointing down the royal road to learning.
By recent count there were in the United States alone
well over 100 companies in the teaching machine field, and
the number is growing. Considering this mechanical explo¬
sion, it is not surprising that educators don't even agree on
what is and what Is not a teaching machine. However, a
definition by Dr. Douglas Porter, a programming authority
at Harvard University, is fairly representative. Teaching
machines, he says, are "devices which endeavour to' alter
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
the course of learning by automatically presenting the
student with a 'reward', or reinforcement, immediately
after he has made a correct response... All these devices
possess three operation characteristics: (a) they present
a sequence of problem materials to the student; (b) they
provide some means by which the student may record his
solution to the problem; and (c) they automatically and
immediately indicate correctness of the solution."
The fact that a student is responding frequently in an
explicit manner gives him a constant check on what he is
learning. Unlike a lecture situation, his active participation
makes any lapse of attention immediately apparent to him.
The impact of correction is infinitely greater because it
comes immediately instead of days or weeks later, as in
the case of written examinations. Finally, the Immediate
confirmation of correct response rewards and stimulates the
pupil to further efforts.
One of the most striking features of auto-instruction is
the fact that a student may move along at his own pace
neither held back by slow-learning classmates nor pre¬
cipitated into an area for which he is unprepared.
Dr. B. F. Skinner, a Harvard psychologist who used
laboratory pigeons to demonstrate the step-by-step
learning that underlies teaching machine instruction, adds
this rmportant point:
"The machine Itself, of course, does not teach. It simply
brings the student Into contact with the person who com¬
posed the material it presents. It is a labour-saving device
because it can bring one programmer into contact with
an indefinite number of students."
The Center for Programed Instruction, a nonprofit educa¬
tional organization in New York City that acts as a
worldwide clearing house for information in the field, puts
it this way:
"A teaching machine has been likened to the binding
of a book. Therefore, if a child learns anything, he will
learn as a result of the material in the machine (i. e., the
programme) rather than as a result of the teaching machine
itself. The machine in actuality has very little to do with
the process, and is in many cases unnecessary."
Indeed, research indicates that the mechanics of pro¬
gramme presentation whether by book or machine has
little effect on results.
The mechanical aspect of programmed learning is a
particularly sensitive one. Advocates of the system shy away
from the term "teaching machine" in favour of "program¬
med learning", "automatic tutoring", "auto-instruction" or
"psychomotor self-instruction". (The more implacable
critics scoff at the system as "instant knowledge" or....
"canned genius.") Nevertheless, "teaching machine" per- I I
sists among laymen as the most convenient and common
designation.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TEACHING MACHINES (Cont'd)
Students given
every chance to be right
12
A teaching machine may range from a device scarcely
more sophisticated than the traditional student work book
to a complex mechanical and even electronic tutor, that
presents not only written but audio-visual material. There
are about 100 models in various stages of development,
of which about half are in limited or full production.
Regardless of simplicity or complexity, a teaching ma¬
chine is only as effective as the programme the instruc¬
tional material that it presents to the pupil. As Prof.
Robert Glaser, who has devised programme books at the
University of Pittsburgh, observes:
"The fact that it ¡s a difficult and aversive task to
programme material and a much easier task to build the
accompanying hardware is indicated by the fact that at
the present time machines outnumber programmes by a
large factor. We are in the situation of having shells
without innards."
That point was underscored when a school board spent
$5,000 for 20 machines and then discovered that no
programmes were available for them.
OST researchers are satisfied that there no
longer is any doubt that programmed teaching
is effective. ("Even a bad programme is a pretty good
teacher", one experimenter says.) Emphasis now has
shifted to making programmed teaching efficient to pre¬
paring material that will guide a pupil in the desired direction
without meaningless or even damaging departures.
A sound programme is one that has been prepared
meticulously and tested rigorously. A programmer first tries
it out on a single student, changing a word or phrase or
adding or eliminating sections until the desired response
emerges. One by one, as many as ten other students
work through the material, which again is revised as neces¬
sary. Finally, the programme is group-tested. Ideally, it
is then capable of teaching efficiently perhaps ninety-
eight per cent of all students who are intellectually on a
par with those who participated in the testing programme.
Wilbur Schramm, director of the Institute for Communi¬
cations Research at Stanford University, says there has
always been a "deadly inflexibility" about the age at which
the average student was considered ready for any given
instruction. Underscoring the necessity of meaningful pro¬
gramming, he then asks rhetorically:
"But suppose that readiness depends upon teaching
method as well as upon subject matter. Suppose, for
example, that a student is ready for the -usual way of
teaching geometry only in the tenth grade but is ready for
another way of teaching it as early as the second grade?
Suppose that, as in the Soviet Union, intelligence tests
were to be minimized; and when a child could not under¬
stand an explanation or a concept, the blame were to be
laid, not on the child's supposed lack of intelligence, but at
least partly on the way the material is being taught?
Suppose the testmakers were to think of their assignments
not as selecting the fit from the unfit, but rather as selecting
the kind of instructional methods which will fit different kinds
of individuals?"
Programming falls into two broad categories: linear and
branching. A linear programme tries to guide the student
step by step toward a correct response, even prompting
him with thinly veiled hints. Dr. Skinner, a principal pro¬
ponent of linear programming, says:
"Teachers generally want students to be wrong. If
everyone knows the answer to questions, teachers make
them tougher. With teaching machines, you give the
students every opportunity to be right."
In the branching approach the pupil who responds with
the right answer moves along the trunk route to the next
question. But if he responds incorrectly, he is detoured over
explanatory material that provides the background to
correct his error. As he absorbs the subsidiary material, he
is led back, question by question, to the mainstream of
instruction. In other words, the student is either presented
with remedial material or accelerated to more advanced
material.
Programmed textbooks are by far the mostly widely
used presentation method indeed, virtually the only one in
curricular use. This despite one major distinction between
machine and text that favours the former. As one research
team has pointed out: "With programmed texts, nothing
but his conscience prevents the subject from gaining access
to the correct answer prior to making his own response."
Machines, on the other hand, are designed to be cheat-
proof, mechanically serving up problems one by one and
masking answers until the student has irrevocably res¬
ponded.
Other devices for presenting the curriculum material
include memory drums, rotating disks, film sequences,
slides, index cards and magnetic tape recordings.
In terms of Dr. Porter's "operation characteristics", how
a problem is presented depends on the design of the
machine; but in general the problem ranges from short
statement or question to a number of paragraphs pre¬
sented either visually (film, television or in writing) or orally
(by recordings) or both. The device then may either wait
for the learner to respond before reacting (learner-paced)
or it may move on to the next question at the end of a
predetermined period of time (machine-paced).
HE second step student response may be
taken in a variety of ways, again depending on
machine design. The student may write a word or passage,
punch a hole, push one or more buttons or Indicate his
reaction in some other way. Answer mechanisms tend to
polarize toward "multiple-choice" on the one hand and
"constructed response" on the other.
The final step confirmation of the solution's correctness
and reinforcement (reward) likewise depends In form on
the device used. Generally, revealing the answer by
exposing more of the programme both grades a student's
response and (when he is right) rewards him sufficiently.
However, the reward may also sometimes take the form
of flashing lights, bell-ringing, audio-visual evaluation, or
particularly for younger children the vending of candy,
marbles or small toys.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The boy at the type¬
writer is studying ocea¬
nography. The type¬
writer is part of a
teaching machine used
to demonstrate current
research on the human
learning process. A
series of lessons and
questions about ocea¬
nography appear on the
screen before the stu¬
dent. He reads and
responds by using the
typewriter to answer the
questions. The order
of succeeding lessons
depends on the appro¬
priateness of his answers
previously programmed
in a digital computer.
USIS
Here is the step-by-step operation of one simple auto-
Instructional device programmed for basic arithmetic. The
device consists of 12 sheets packaged In a cardboard
folder. A window In the folder exposes a portion of one
sheet: a box (or frame) containing one question or instruc¬
tional paragraph or both, and a second box left blank for
student response. When he has completed frame I, the
pupil slides the sheet upward to frame 2, exposing the
answer to frame 1, plus a new question or instructions
and second box for the written answer to question 2.
Frame 1, for example, reads: "In arithmetic, we must
understand numbers and what they mean if we are to get
correct answers".
Because this is instructional material rather than a
question, the "answer" box merely Instructs: "Go to the
next frame".
Frame 2 reads: "When we u	d numbers in
arithmetic we will get correct answers. Fill in the word".
In the adjoining box the pupil is expected to write,
"understand". He then moves the sheet upward, exposing
frame 3, which contains the correct answer to the frame 2
question and presents the new instructional material: "We
call the way numbers are put together a system". Frame
4 reads: "When we understand the number system, we
will get (right/wrong) answers. Choose the right word.
In the answer box the pupil writes, "right" and, is
rewarded when, on moving to frame 5, the word "right"
is exposed as the correct response to the frame 4 question.
At its most revolutionary, programmed teaching not only
guides a pupil through what to learn but shows him how to
learn. The distinction is roughly equivalent to that between
a lecturer and a tutor. Both provide facts, but the tutor
additionally helps the student to learn them..
Since the system focuses on guiding a pupil to a correct
response rather than trapping him into a wrong one, promp¬
ting is an integral part of programming. As specific
examples of good and inadequate prompts. Dr. David J.
Klaus, associate programme director for training and edu¬
cation at the American Institute for Research, in Pittsburgh,
lists the following problems:
Example X: "Fahrenheit and centigrade are scales of
temperature; Kelvin is a 	 ".
Example Y: "Fahrenheit and centigrade are scales of
temperature; Kelvin is also a 	 ".
Dr. Klaus observes that example X is a poorly cued frame
resembling "a test question rather than an aid to learning".
"By adding a single word, however, example Y illustrates
a very good frame", he says. "It is almost impossible for
a student to answer it incorrectly even if has never
seen the word 'Kelvin' before."
What can be expected from auto-instructional devices?
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TEACHING MACHINES (Cont'd)
Too costly for emerging countries ?
14
Three levels of programmed learning are usually mentioned.
At the lowest is so-called rote learning of such material
as vocabulary, arithmetic, spelling and the basic facts of
history and geography. A step higher is conceptual learning
in which a student not only must memorize facts but must
be capable of handling a wider variety of problems and
examples than can be specifically covered by the pro¬
gramme. Physics, statistics and economics present challen¬
ges in this direction. The most sophisticated instructional
level involves the teaching of such capabilities as creative
thinking and judgement.
"This may be the level of education at which auto-
instruction will yield its greatest fruit", says Dr. Klaus.
"The possibilities of developing a programme in this area
are derived from two simple observations. First, we have
sufficient data to indicate that creativity and judgement are
examples of learned behaviour. Secondly, we have evidence
to indicate that these behaviours can be taught. What Is
left is simply a problem of mechanics, that is, identifying
exactly those behaviours to be learned and then finding
the means to successfully establish these behaviours in
the student's repertoire with auto-instructional methods
and devices."
Yet it is precisely at this point that many educators split
with teaching machine enthusiasts. For while conceding the
device's role in purely quantitative teaching, they are du¬
bious about a machine's effectiveness as an instructor in
qualitative subjects.
In terms of the number of programmes available, the
field is dominated by mathematics, which lends itself to
programmed instruction because it is a subject of precise
answers that can be learned in small steps. English, including
reading and spelling, is probably second, followed by
psychology, foreign languages and physics.
Dr. Edward B. Fry, a teaching machine researcher at the
University of Southern California, remarks:
"It is probably quite safe to say that in the next few
years some programme will have been developed for every
subject taught in our schools."
contrary view comes from Dr. George D. Stod¬
dard, chancellor of New York University. He
accords the machine a place as an instructor In facts,
formulas, vocabulary and grammatical rules. But he fears
that such instructional methods will stultify rather than
stimulate a child's thinking, creative and performing pro¬
cesses.
"Perhaps a live teacher who infuriates a student is better
than a machine that leaves him stuffed with information but
cold as a mackerel," Dr. Stoddard says.
Much of the hostility toward auto-instruction is based on
economics; despite assurances to the contrary, many
teachers fear that machines will replace them. One so far
betrayed his hostility as to fail thirty per cent of a class that
had come to him via a programme-taught preliminary course.
And in at least two cases, indignant school administrators
have demanded legislation barring programmed instruction
from classrooms.
Among parents and laymen generally, opposition is often
based on sentiment the fear that "traditional" relation¬
ships between pupil and teacher will be destroyed.
Both categories of opponents visualize varying degrees
of automation, ranging up to the extreme of a 100 per cent
mechanized educational system from kindergarten through
university.
Proponents of the system scoff at such fears as ground¬
less. They reply that, with or without machines, pro¬
grammes can liberate teachers from the drudgery of purely
mechanical instruction so that they may be free for "those
inspirational and thought-stimulating activities which are,
presumably, the real function of the teacher," in the words
of Dr. S.L. Pressey, the Ohio State University psychologist
generally regarded as the precursor of the teaching ma¬
chine revolution.
NE educator has. said in the machine's defence:
"A human being should not be wasted in doing
what 40 sheets of paper or two phonographs can do. Just
because personal teaching is precious and can do what
books and apparatus can not, it should be saved for its
peculiar work. The best teacher uses books and appliances
as well as his own insight, sympathy and magnetism."
Auto-instruction would be irresistible even if its only
promised advantage were an impressive speedup in edu¬
cating the world's children. (Dr. A.A. Lumsdaine, an edu¬
cation psychologist at the University of California, Los An¬
geles, predicts that with machines, "bright pupils will be
able to finish the grade school curriculum by the time they
are 10 years old instead of 14"). The fact is, programmed
instruction is enormously attractive for other reasons.
In a world clamouring for more and more teachers, pro¬
grammed learning seems to offer a way of spreading out
the available supply. And with the soaring cost of ela¬
borate school buildings beyond the reach of impoverished
and even of many advanced nations, machines which can
be used in buildings of monastic simplicity or even at home
seem to be a budgetary blessing. Attracted by these and
other considerations, educators from Latin America, Asia,
Africa and Europe are eagerly watching developments in the
field. The first experimental steps already are being taken
in Sweden, France, Great Britain, Japan, West Germany,
South Africa and Nigeria.
Prof. Arthur French of Makerere College in Kampala,
Uganda, admits that there is widespread interest among
African educators ; but he adds that many administrators
are intimidated by the cost of teaching machines. Pro¬
grammers not affiliated with commercial "teaching machine"
manufacturers tend to agree that emerging countries would
be unwise to invest heavily in mechanical devices now.
Says P. Kenneth Komoski, president of the Center for
Programed Instruction:
"We are not going to help a country that is trying des¬
perately to create or acquire traditional textbooks by telling
them we have better books that cost more (as indeed they
dol). In fact, the less emphasis we put on the products of
programmed instruction, i.e., programmed texts and teaching
machines, the better off we will be. For one thing, teaching
machines will not work in developing countries today for
the simple reason that they do not work in this country.
They simply have not been sufficiently debugged... I
believe we would be foolhardy to chance mechanical failure
so far from home."
CONT'D ON PAGE 16
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Palais de la Découverte, Pans
Michel Péron, Paris
CALCULATED DISK
Advanced research in programmed instruction is
making increasing use of the potentialities of the
electronic computer. In the United States com¬
puters have been used experimentally in group
and individual learning exercises and examinations.
Below, computer memory disk capable of record¬
ing 500,000 words in the shaded area. Above and
left, the great ancestor of our modern computers,
Pascal's mechanical calculator, now preserved in
a Paris museum (detail shown on cover). It is
operated by turning the series of wheels; results
then appear in the sight holes at top of cover.
IBM, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
1
m¿
TEACHING MACHINES (Cont'd)
A simple teaching machine operated
with a typewriter roller action. Stu¬
dent writes answer to question in
window on right and can go on
to the next question if he is correct.
From " The World of Teaching Machines "
© 1961. Electronic Teaching Laboratories.
Washington. D.C.
A new technique of unlimited potential
For the immediate future, Mr. Komoski suggests, empha¬
sis should fall on "finding out how the principles of pro¬
grammed instruction may be generalized to all instructional
situations and applied to all available media" regardless
of culture. Such an approach is aimed at solving two
great unknowns about the prospect of worldwide use of
programmed instruction: (a) To what extent can pro¬
grammed instruction, still an almost wholly American phe¬
nomenon, be transferred merely by programme translation
to another nation even an English-speaking one? (b) How
many of the principles applicable to American-oriented
programme instruction would* be valid in constructing indi¬
genous programmes in other languages for peoples of
other nationalities, cultures or educational levels?
' While admitting that almost nothing is known about
programmed instruction except that it works, educational
psychologists in the field nevertheless are confident that it
is a new weapon of unlimited potential in the worldwide
war against ignorance. Pointing out that the global need
for teaching of literacy and technology "is so vast as to
be almost beyond comprehension," Dr. Schramm says:
"Could an intelligent use of programmed instruction signi¬
ficantly reduce the time and money required for that task?
Everyone who is familiar with programmed instruction and
has looked closely at the needs of the new states is most
optimistic about what could be accomplished. These coun¬
tries are desperately short of teachers; here is a device to
multiply good teachers. These countries have unusual
motivations to learn; here is a device to take advantage of
these motivations and provide a tool for self-teaching.
These countries have need for a considerable amount of
expert and specialized teaching which is often not within
the competence of many of their teachers. Countless one-
room schools are in charge of teachers who themselves
have only four to six years of education. How much the
learning opportunity of those one-room schools could be
increased by the addition of a small library of well-made
programmes."
Unesco
'workshops'
on
programmed
instruction
ZZ OR several years Unesco has
been studying the possibili¬
ties of introducing programmed
instruction in developing nations.
In 1963 it held "workshops" on
programmed instruction in Ra¬
mallah (Jordan) and Ibadan (Ni¬
geria) to introduce to educators
in the Middle East and West
Africa the techniques of pro¬
gramming instructional materials.
In 1964 another workshop was
held at Accra (Ghana) and a
work conference took place in
Zaria (Nigeria). Programmed ins¬
truction materials were also de¬
veloped in 1963-64 in Sao Paulo,
Brazil, where a Unesco pilot pro¬
ject on physics teaching was
launched. In 1965 two workshops
are planned for French-speaking
African countries (in Madagas¬
car) and for Arab educators con¬
cerned with teacher training. For
further information on program¬
med instruction and other new
techniques in education see "Pro¬
grammed Instruction in West
Africa and the Arab States" and
"New Methods and Techniques in
Education" (Nos. 52 and 48 in
the Unesco publications series
"Educational Studies and Docu¬
ments"; $1.00; 5/-; 3,50 F.).
16
H
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
This is a "portrait" of
the mathematical con¬
cept of geometric pro¬
gression. In the series
of reflections each boy
is half as high as the
next larger boy. The
sequence of heights
forms a geometric pro¬
gression. There are infi¬
nitely many boys in the
picture but if they stood
on each others heads,
the resulting tower
would not be infinitely
high. It would only be
twice as high as the boy
seen in the first mirror.
SCIENCE AND THE
COMMON MAN
by Ritchie Calder (Part two)
WmSSM,
*j»uiii'i iaw
-"«í> Ü- váí-SÍ -.- t£ A
mifeifaU*<til
B*&t<
.-.-R. n »*:
1
fp
1
Br $\ ~tXm l
1 II ^m
m r B
mjwf rT 1 1 1 * * ml^^^^MWi'' H^HI
&Û Cnkw
ÎAL/i ' H1MBHH BiAfll
3ÇG&Z&PZ5&??*?
¡y/*vs RT?W
¿-o^;í->í
»*.. r *7 oäv^****<
/n past times a "man of science" could
converse and communicate with any other
educated man. Today the cryptic language
and private jargons of the scientist have
built barriers between the ordinary man
and a proper understanding of science
the social dynamic of our times. In our
February issue, Ritchie Calder reviewed
these obstacles and stressed the dangers
for our civilization and for science itself
of the gulf separating the scientist in his
specialty from the wider community. Here
we present the second part of his article.
:w
.<>
rfriz
i, r
AN'S anxiety about his own search for know-
hedge and. for power is reflected almost uni¬
versally in myth and legend and still lurks in our own nature
today. Prometheus, in stealing fire, the prerogative of the
gods and appropriating it for the use of man, was terribly
punished for his presumptuous act. Pandora wantonly
unleashed forces which she could not control because,
again, she trespassed on the jurisdiction of the gods, but
since her action was accidental and innocent, mankind was
at least left with hope.
But when Faust invoked the Devil in order to usurp the
powers of the gods, there was nothing accidental about his
actions and he was consequently doomed to everlasting
punishment. The association of acquisitive knowledge with
evil and punishment is to be found in the story of the
Garden of Eden, and also In the ancient Egyptian saying:
"When man learns what it is that moves the stars, the
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Models of Leonardo da Vinci's automobile, helicopter, aeroplane
Photo © Three Lions, New York
Four centuries before their invention, the automobile,
the helicopter, the aeroplane, the parachute and
many other modern machines had already been
foreseen by one of the keenest minds of the Italian
Renaissance. Giant among painters, musician and
poet, Leonardo da Vinci in fact considered himself
first and foremost a man of science and an engineer.
Here we present some examples of his inventions
in the form of present-day models built to Leonardo's
drawings and notes. Below, a model of the earliest-
known design for a self-propelled vehicle. Based on
Leonardo's drawing (left), it is spring driven.
'
=«<KV
v. r **
u-i ^tsf? aiv
o I
Photos Michel Péron, Paris
» H*
\^-
V
*_±
j
© Three Lions,
New York
HELICOPTER. This drawing by Leonardo da Vinci, illustrat¬
ing the principle of the "airscrew", is a preview of the heli¬
copter. But the only motive power Leonardo could give it
was the strength of the human arm (model right). The inven¬
tor took the precaution to write his scientific notes so that
they could only be deciphered when reflected in a mirror.
AEROPLANE. Leonardo studied the flight of birds
and also experimented to discover how much lift
could be obtained from wings. This model of an aero¬
plane embodies the ideas in his drawings and notes.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
/
û X
DA VINCI (Cont'd) Photos Michel Péron
FROM PARACHUTE TO FIREMAN'S LADDER. The
versatile genius of Leonardo da Vinci found expres¬
sion in the most diverse fields of art. science and
technology. Documents bequeathed to us by Leonardo
abound in creative ideas for Inventions such as hy¬
draulic machines, excavators, piledrivers, cranes,
swinging bridges, spinning and weaving machines,
diving equipment and many others. Above, da Vinci's
own drawing and a model of the parachute he desi¬
gned. Below, this mechanical model of a scaling
ladder built to Leonardo's blueprint has a similarity in
some respects to ladders used on fire engines today.
£ Three Lions. New York
SCIENCE AND THE COMMON MAN (Cont'd)
The fear of being afraid
Sphinx will laugh and all life upon earth will be destroyed."
There is a built-in fear in most people that trespassing in
the Unknown will invite a kind of cosmic revenge on
mankind or, as the psychologists put it, "the tendency to
relapse into more primitive forms of thought and feeling
which is characteristic of much of the psychological
reactions of the public to nuclear energy can be ascribed
to a psychological mechanism known as 'regression' ".
There is no safety in ignorance. In October 1957, the
World Health Organization called together a group, of
which I was a member, to study the mental health aspects
of the peaceful uses of energy. One of the questions
studied by this group was apathy. One would have assum¬
ed that this was a sort of emotional carapace, but it was
not: it was the "fear of being afraid". People knew enough,
censed enough, or guessed enough to have their unspoken
fears, and they shrank from facts which might confirm or
exaggerate those fears. Their attitude was not "don't care"
but "don't want to know". And the psychologists recogniz¬
ed of course that this abdication does not produce reassur¬
ance but a neurosis which in the mass can give rise to
social malaise. It is better to have rational fears than
irrational ones.
ND so nuclear superstition grew up. The only
way to combat superstition is to confront it
with reason. But what happens if the custodians of reason
are not believed? The study group found that scientists
themselves were mistrusted. In part this was due to the
primitive sense that they were interfering with things which
they should not touch, but also in part to the manifest
evidence of their achievements people remember the bomb
but they forget penicillin. But the most serious part was
the distrust of the motivations of the scientists' evidence.
If the release of atomic energy had not happened behind
the silent walls of secrecy, if there had been free discussion
among scientists everywhere, the processes of the discovery
and the release would have "got through to the public" and
would have prepared people for the greatest achievement
of man since he mastered fire. Instead, without any pre¬
paration of the public, it exploded with the violence of a
bomb. The conditions of military secrecy continued and,
also, the fears engendered by the original bombs persisted
because of the testing of bigger and bigger weapons.
Scientists became the spokesmen of government policies.
They were called upon not only to give the facts, within the
limitation of their specialized knowledge but to extrapolate
those facts beyond that knowledge and to pass judgements
and to express opinions.
The fact that scientists, and the authority of science, have
been invoked in recent years to promote policies, or to
win appropriations or contracts, or to defend government
agencies and industrial concerns, or to "reassure the public"
on subjects such as fall-out or thalidomide, has tended to
make people suspicious of their motives and question the
integrity of their facts.
Even more difficult to analyse than the relationship of the
scientist to the general public is the relationship of the
politician to the scientist; it is a love-hate relationship. As
the published report of the WHO Study Group on the Men¬
tal Aspects of Atomic Energy (1) stated: "With regard to
science and the scientists, the position of political leaders
is often fraught with additional difficulties. Few, if any, have
the background which includes a thorough scientific train¬
ing, yet they are called upon to face situations which have
been built up, little by little, through the work of scientists
and which require for solution some conception of the
ultimate implications of the scientific world...
"Lack of adequate conceptual background may lead to
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
.and the philosophy of risk
a tendency to make a programme without real plans, and
this can lead to tremendous insecurity."
"Another aspect which generates anxiety is the un¬
certainty about who actually wields the power," said the
WHO report. "In one sense, the politician has power
over the scientist, but in another, he is dependent on
the scientist and hence is in his power. In this respect
an entirely new situation has arisen in many countries
of the modern world."
This danger of "the tyranny of the expert" is, and should
be, a matter of real public concern. The faceless men at
the elbows of the scientifically uneducated are becoming
decision-makers without being answerable to the commu¬
nity.
Scientists do not make the task of common understanding
any easier when they vacillate between statements which
are limited to their scientific competence and statements
which wear a meretricious mantle of science but which
are actually expressions of value and even of policy
decision.
One of the value judgements passing as scientific truths
is the concept of "maximum permissible dosage" of radia¬
tion. This belongs not to science but to the "philosophy
of risk." It has no more scientific authority than the forty-
mile-an-hour speed-limit sign on a highway, yet scientists,
including many eminent ones, have got into the habit of
quoting "m.p.d.s" as though they were scientific units.
The bandying of "m.p.d.s" by spokesmen-scientists in dis¬
cussing such things as fall-out, either to minimize or
exaggerate the risks, has bamboozled the public and in¬
creased its distrust of the scientist.
In November 1963, the World Health Organization, the
Food and Agriculture Organization and the International
Atomic Energy Agency, brought together world experts at
Geneva to consider the radiation hazards from peacetime
accidents. This meeting followed the suspension of tests,
so that the official scientists were no longer looking over
their shoulders, speaking with their tongues in their cheeks,
nor waiting for government reprimands if they said any¬
thing which, even if true, would be officially indiscreet.
The consensus of that meeting was that in terms of the
population at large no dosage was permissible, neither
maximal nor minimal. All radiation beyond the natural was
to be assumed to be bad. If an accident to a nuclear
installation was to occur and there was to be an escape
of radiation of any kind, no one was to say: "Until the
dosage is so-and-so, there is nothing to worry about."
Everyone's job, urgently, must be to restore the environment
to normal. A pseudo-scientific unit which had bewildered
the public for eighteen years was thus discarded, as far as
public health was concerned, although its usefulness as
a guide to risk still applied to the radiological protection
of individuals.
VER a century ago, the famous French physio¬
logist, Claude Bernard, made a pronouncement
which his modern successors would do well to heed: "True
science teaches us to doubt and, in ignorance, to refrain."
When the entire living environment has become a labora¬
tory, scientists ought to be restrained within the limits of
their knowledge; they ought to admit to themselves what
they do not know. Fall-out is a case in point (although we
can think also of pesticides and new drugs like thalidomide)
because it should remind them to compare notes with their
colleagues in other disciplines.
Another saying of Claude Bernard applies to the respon¬
sibilities of the modern scientists: "When you enter your
laboratory, put off your imagination as you take off your
(1) No. 151 of the Technical Reports series, Geneva. WHO, 1958.
coat; but put it on again, with your overcoat, when you
leave. Before an experiment and between whiles let your
imagination wrap you round; put it right away from you
during the experiment itself lest it hamper you and your
power of observation."
Outside his laboratory, the scientist is entitled to use
his imagination in politics, in religion, or in any other
social concern. Indeed, it is his duty to do so. He ought
to have some regard for the use, misuse, abuse, or non-
use of his discoveries. He is a functional citizen and
should be expected, as the repository of information, to
make that information intelligibly available, and, also, with
a sense of responsibility, to put forward arguments on
which social judgements can be sensibly made and with¬
out which social judgements cannot be made.
Today, many scientists, including the most eminent, earn¬
estly accept this responsibility. They take the initiative
on great issues issues which science itself dictates with¬
out arrogating to themselves the powers of the invisible
experts, the faceless men,' and bring their knowledge to
the bar of public opinion. The Pugwash Movement is the
conspicuous and impressive example of this. Scientists, in
this way, can form a very powerful benevolent "lobby" in
the interest of the lives and livelihoods of their fellow
humans.
OMMON understanding of science does not
mean just what is conveyed through the popular
press or radio or television or films, much of which is now
being done very ably and is introducing the ordinary person
not only to the exciting developments of science but to
the ways in which the scientist goes to work. Science
has to be understood at all levels. If we are to have science
effectively administered by governments and public bodies
or by the boards of industries, we have to educate those
who are to form the judgements about sciences and to de¬
cide priorities. Men of affairs have to be sufficiently well in¬
formed to know what it is that the scientistis talking about,
otherwise they may find themselves carried away by
the enthusiasm of the scientist, caught by the glamour of
the latest "scientific cult" or just bemused by the jargon
of science. Conversely, much that is worthwhile goes
a-begging because those who have to take the decisions
cannot properly understand.
This problem is one of education, at all ages. When
people ask "At what age do you teach a child science?"
the answer is simple: from the moment a child lisps "Why?"
Innate curiosity has to be encouraged instead of the child
being told: "Wait until you know all about kinetics and dyna¬
mics and you will understand." To discourage curiosity is to
discourage scientific inquiry in later years.
Recently, at an educational conference, I was asked to
speak on "Teaching science in general education in the
year A.D. 2000". I said I hoped that we would not be
teaching "science" as a subject in general education forty
years from now, but that science would pervade be as
natural as the blood corpuscles and that specialization
would be reserved for much later in the student's life.
Moreover, every university student should be introduced to
scientific method and given the background which will make
him, even when he is not going to be a career scientist,
capable of evaluating science.
An essential attribute of the rounded man in this day and
age is that he should know about the forces which are
changing and dominating his life and affecting culture in all
its aspects. This is a challenge to educators in every
country those which we call "developing" as well as those
which are highly developed scientifically and technologically.
In all this, the present-day science writers have a peculiar 21
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND THE COMMON MAN (Cont'd)
The inalienable right of curiosity
22
responsibility. There are not enough of them and not all of
them understand, nor do all of whose who do understand
accept the function of social interpretation which has been
elaborated here. Many regard their "popularization" merely
as the explanation of the latest gadget or of the latest cure
or of some exciting new theory. This is the easiest of all
science writing.
If the scientist, who has the facts, is patient, and the
journalist, who has to simplify these facts, is patient, there
is practically no scientific advance however abstruse it may
seem at first sight which cannot be made intelligible to the
general reader. The expositor may be a science graduate
trained as a journalist or a journalist who has acquired the
necessary background of science. In either case, he (or
she) must have the craft of presenting difficult concepts in
ways which will arrest and hold the interest of readers (or
listeners or viewers) who are not predisposed to science.
There are many layers of explanation. The scientist writ¬
ing in his own scientific journal, for his own immediate
colleagues, can use all the jargon he likes. If he Is writing
for a wider scientific group, he has to be less cryptic and
more descriptive but he can still assume (a) that they know
the basic concepts and (b) that they will concentrate on
what he is trying to explain.
Then there are journals about science (as distinct from
scientific journals) purveying a great variety of scientific
subjects for earnest people who may not be scientists but
who want to keep themselves informed. Such journals per¬
form a very important function because they "brief" well-
meaning politicians, civil servants, company directors,
teachers of the humanities, etc.; they are for an educated
élite who will grapple with a subject provided that the
language does not defeat them.
Then there are the "serious" newspapers which will give
space for explanations and whose readers will give atten¬
tion, again provided that they are not expected to under¬
stand the terminology until they have been introduced to
it. Then there are the large-circulation newspapers the
function of which is to inform (or entertain) rather than to
educate. This means "sneaking up on the reader" and
surprising him into being interested in a subject which he
would otherwise avoid.
ND there is the level of the "comic strip"
which is not to be altogether despised. In
Britain a whole generation was prepared for space travel,
years before the first space capsule was launched into
orbit, by the "Adventures of Dan Dare". Children knew
far more than the grown-ups about Mach numbers,
weightlessness, orbits and stagings. This was impressed
upon me by a fourteen-year-old who, on the morning
Sputnik I went up, asked how it was done. I told him all
about propellants, boosters, etc. He listened to me politely
and then said: "I know all that. But how did they get it
into that particular orbit?" He was more interested in the
science than in the technology. His instructor had been
Dan Dare, a comic strip with a great amount of substantial
information built-in. For "journals" and "newspapers"
read films, television and radio. The same considerations
apply.
The mere explanation of science, however, is not enough;
it has to be translated into the lives and experience of
ordinary people. There have to be, in this day and age,
interpreters.
The crisis of our times is the breakdown of communica¬
tions, not only in the semantics of politics and Ideologies,
but in this all-important area of science. Our lives, our
hopes, our survival as a species depend upon the uses
which are made of science. To progress, we have to use
scientific discoveries and knowledge to the utmost. Science
in the advanced countries is moving so fast that it is almost
impossible to keep up with the knowledge and the gadgets.
Science feeds fundamental truths to technology; techno¬
logy feeds back more and more elaborate instruments to
science; they speed each other up. Over three and a half
million original scientific papers are published every year
and the increase is exponential. Wisdom is being drowned
in a Niagara of information. The various branches of
science are out of step, encouraged or discouraged by
"cults" which impress the money-givers into providing dis¬
proportionate budgets.
Large areas of science are still enclosed within the
barbed wire of military security. Much is circumscribed
by industrial secrecy. Much more is fenced off by the
jargon of over-specialization. One set of scientists does
not know what another set is doing, even when their
areas of work impinge and may have a critical relevance
to each other.
I N the aggregation of experimental knowledge
we have lost the sense of natural philosophy.
With a singlemindedness that would have astounded the
eighteenth century, schools of research pursue their objec¬
tives. We are ¿now in th& cult of DNA and the study of
deoxyribonucleic acid and molecular biology probing the
secret of life before we know what we are going to do with
it when we have got it. Over $6,000 million a year is spent
on space research only a small fraction of the $43,000 mil¬
lion which the nations spend on armaments, but twice as
much as is invested in the developing countries.
There are too few communicators within science and
between the humanities and science. How are we to teach
people about science to enable them to make judgements
and to see that, with the inalienable rights of curiosity and
the quest for knowledge unimpaired, science, with all its
potential for good or evil, shall be directed to the benefit
of all mankind?
While we should certainly be encouraging the aspirations
of Man in breaking the gravitational boundary walls of his
planet, are we really maintaining at the same time a proper
sense of priorities? How much more resources and atten¬
tion should we be giving to the problems of this planet on
which 3,000 million people today and 4,000 millions by
1980 will have to contrive to live in conditions more consis¬
tent with human dignity than most of them now enjoy?
Is space adventure more important than food and popu¬
lation problems for instance? And how, with all the spec¬
tacular advances of today, can we close the widening gap
between the prosperity, scientifically and technologically
produced, in the advanced countries and the poverty of
two-thirds of the world?
The United Nations Conference on the Application of
Science and Technology for the Benefit of Less Developed
Areas, at Geneva, in February 1963, spelled out what we
know and what is needed. While we would be grateful for
some new breakthrough giving to food problems, for
example, the kind of answers which sulpha drugs, anti¬
biotics and DDT gave to medical services it was evident
from that conference that there are answers already wait¬
ing to be applied, and that it is not a question of know¬
ledge but of intention. It is a question of sharing know¬
ledge and skills and resources that we already have at
our disposal.
These are social judgements, fraught with stupendous
meaning, and they must be based on a proper understanding
of science and what it can make available. Th¡s transfer of
knowledge and skills has to be done rapidly if the Scientific
and Technological Revolution is to give substance to the
Revolution 'of Rising Expectations, which, as more and more
countries become independent, becomes more and more
insistent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Underwater
i Campagnes Océanographiques Françaises
Part of "village" built 40 feet below the surface of the Red Sea by French undersea
expedition of Commandant Jacques-Yves Cousteau. This feat was recorded in the
film, "World Without Sun" from which photo is taken. Building with onion dome
is a garage for the diving saucer in foreground. Occupying specially designed houses,
oceanauts learned to adapt to life on the sea bed. As Commandant Cousteau has
written: "Our team is bent on solving the problem of living under water at depths
of up to 600 feet. If we succeed we shall have given mankind the ability to colonize the
shallow seas fringing most large land masses ." Progress in science and technology
is leading to exploitation of new environments, as explained in article on page 4.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
MUMMY OF
RAMESES V
The mummified face of
the Egyptian Pharaoh,
Rameses V, shows clear
traces of a some terrible
disease. Medical histor¬
ians say it was smallpox.
:'r-'-'-:;>-;'>-L:.v:;
JiFv-,-^:-:£':S'
9
1%t - -
<k
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
International co-operation in health began in
the last century under pressure from deadly
diseases that were causing suffering and
death all over the world. In 1965, Inter¬
national Co-operation Year, World Health
Day is being devoted to one of these dis¬
eases smallpox. World Health Day 1965
will serve to focus attention on the cam¬
paign to eradicate smallpox from the world
which was launched by the World Health
Organization in 1958. As Dr. M. G. Candau,
Director-General of WHO has declared :
"The complete eradication of smallpox
would not only rid the world of a disease
which at present is a constant menace but
would also provide an example of what true
international co-operation can achieve." In
the meantime the world will need to
maintain a constant alert against smallpox.
In the days of swift air travel smallpox
can be transmitted from continent to
continent within hours.- Information on
all reported cases goes to WHO in
Geneva which immediately operates a
world-wide warning system. These emer¬
gency warning messages are given
a priority over international cables.
WHO photos
Geneva : world headquarters
in the fight against smallpox
N MAPQ KWABJ BADBO. This text of an ur¬
gent telegram addressed to "Epidnations, Gen¬
eve", and written in "Codepid", a world code for messages
about quarantinable diseases, tells the WHO International
Quarantine Service that a case of smallpox has been
diagnosed in Aden on January 15. One man sick in a
hospital is news for the world when the disease is smallpox.
From Geneva, cables are sent to neighbouring countries
as well as to countries connected with Aden by airline ser¬
vices. The information also goes by short-wave radio to
all continents. It is picked up by national health adminis¬
trations, by port health officers, by ships at sea, by airplanes
In the sky. By radio teleprinter service it goes to European
countries and to North America. It is repeated in the
Weekly Epidemiological Record printed in Geneva and dis¬
tributed by airmail.
For the next days and weeks, special precautions will
be taken by health authorities all over' the world pas¬
sengers arriving from or having passed through Aden.
Incoming telegrams in Geneva about quarantinable
diseases number about 3,000 a year. From them an over¬
all picture of the world smallpox situation can be built up.
In 1963, over 100,000 cases of smallpox were recorded.
India reported over 60,000 cases; Indonesia almost 8,000;
and Pakistan, the Democratic Republic of Congo and Brazil
over 5,000 each. Between 1,000 and 2,000 cases occurred
in a number of African countries Zambia, Nigeria, Congo
(Brazzaville) and Mali. Large epidemics also broke out in
Tanzania, Nepal and Afghanistan. During the year some
40 other countries reported smallpox including, in the Am¬
ericas, Colombia, Ecuador and Peru. In Europe, smallpox
invaded Sweden, Poland, Germany, Hungary and Switzer¬
land.
But for the vigilance of health officers and their intensive
efforts to confine outbreaks, the number of cases would
be far, far larger, for smallpox can spread like wildfire.
Even before the typical smallpox rash appears, the infected
person is breathing out the smallpox virus.
Infected persons can travel and so spread the virus from
country to country, sometimes before they themselves have
begun to feel really ill. Last year, smallpox travelled by
aircraft from south-east Asia to Sweden, from India to Po¬
land, and from central Africa to Switzerland. It travelled
by ship from Calcutta to Suez, where the health services
successfully prevented it from spreading further.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
SMALLPOX (Cont'd)
million deaths in 17th-century Europe
26
The disease runs its course a matter of say three weeks.
Cases range from the almost unnoticeable to the very
severe. Patients die (there is as yet no specific treatment)
or recover, and their recovery is of course helped by good
hospital care. On most patients the disease leaves its mark
trie pitted pock-marked skin, which in countries where
the disease is rare may still today be regarded as a sign
of evil by ignorant and superstitious people. In severe
cases, the after-effects may be more serious eyesight
may be affected.
One of the dangerous facts about smallpox today is that
in countries normally free of the disease few doctors have
seen a case, and especially a modified case that is, a
person with partial immunity the diagnosis of which does
not occur to them.
Widespread vaccination and swift preventive measures
during epidemics have freed many countries of smallpox.
But the disease persists and flares up dangerously in parts
of Asia, in Africa and to a lesser extent in South America
areas where efficient health services covering the whole
population are only now being built up.
With the number of air passengers running to tens of
millions a year, outbreaks In the developed countries now-
almost invariably start with a case imported by air.
Smallpox ¡s a world disease in that susceptibility is
universal. It is a world disease also because every
country is concerned with it, whether to prevent it from
being imported, to limit its ravages, or to eradicate it.
As long as smallpox persists anywhere, protective meas¬
ures will be needed everywhere.
Unarmed against this terrible enemy in the past, man
could only submit to its horrors and bemoan his fate:
"Smallpox strikes everybody sooner or later. We are
powerless against Its might. There is no climate, no age,
no sex, no temperament that is secure . . .".
ROM the earliest times, smallpox ravaged Asia
and Africa. About 1122 B.C., under the Chou
dynasty in China, the disease was already known by the
name of "tai-tou", and literature mentions a very serious
epidemic of smallpox in China about 200 B.C.
About 312 A.D. Rome was attacked ; smallpox caused
an enormous number of deaths, and played its part in
accelerating the Empire's decline and fall by its paralyzing
effect on social and political life.
In 675 A.D. the disease is believed to have reached
Ireland where it was called "bolgach" or "galar breac,"
the spotted disease. Then it was the turn of Spain,
where smallpox was Imported by the Saracens. These
warriors after having conquered the country took the
disease into France and soon smallpox spread over the
rest of Europe.
However, of smallpox itself little was known, and it was
Abu Bakr el Razi Rhazes (865-925), the great Arab physi¬
cian (see Unesco Courier, Oct. 1964, p. 33), who first gave
an accurate description of the disease. Yet the great Rhazes
made one mistake: he was convinced that it was normal for
young infants to contract the disease; their blood, he
thought, was like new wine which must ferment.
Century after century the scourge gained ground. No
continent was spared. One of Cortes' negro slaves
carried the disease to the Americas about 1520, during
the early stages of the Spanish conquest. As a result'
three and a half million Mexicans died of the disease
and this helped to pave the way for the conquering
Spaniards. In all, about six million Indiansthat is, about
half the original population died of smallpox during the
Spanish penetration of America. During the conquest of
North America also, smallpox decimated tribes, villages
and towns; in 1633, the Indians of Massachussetts and
of Narragansett numbered about 40,000 but soon only a
few hundred remained.
In 1707, Iceland was ravaged by an epidemic during
which 18.000 of the country's 50,000 inhabitants died. In
the same year, 14,000 people succumbed to the disease
in Paris. In 1721, the "Sea Horse," one of His Britannic
Majesty's ships, dropped anchor in the port of Boston.
There was smallpox on board. Of the town's 11,000
inhabitants, 5,984 contracted the disease and 894 died
of it. Even the most inaccessible countries were not
spared : in 1730, there was a severe epidemic in Green¬
land among the Eskimos. In 1776 in the month of June,
5,500 men of Washington's army of 10,000 fell ill, most
of them with smallpox. Some historians go so far as to
assert that because of smallpox Canada remained part
of the British Empire. In 1770, in India, three million people
died of the disease.
HE disease was so common that the scars left
on the face of those who recovered were
regarded as normal so much so that in England the
absence of pock marks on the face was a distinguishing
feature by which an escaped criminal, for example, might
be recognized. In the market places, slaves with no signs
of having had smallpox were cheap, while those with large
and evident scars fetched high prices since they were
likely to survive longer. It was estimated that during the
seventeenth century more than sixty million Europeans
died of the disease.
In India, the mortality from smallpox was appalling:
500,000 persons succumbed in the years 1873-1874. At
about the same time, more than 44,000 persons died of
smallpox in England. In France the last serious epidemic
occurred during the Franco-Prussian war and ravaged the
defeated army : 200,000 soldiers were struck down by
the disease and more than 25,000 of them died ; at the
same time, there were 200,000 cases and 18,000 deaths
among the inhabitants of Paris. France at that time was
the most heavily infected country in Europe.
At Montreal in 1885 a railway employee contracted the
disease ; smallpox was not immediately diagnosed, and
it spread to 20,000 persons, of whom 3,164 died the
town's 190,000 inhabitants had been reluctant to accept
vaccination. In 1893-1897, Russia was ravaged by small¬
pox which claimed more than 275,000 victims. At about
the same time (1896-1900) there were more than
3,000 deaths from the disease in Egypt. In London, there
was a serious outbreak in 1901-1902, with 6,000 cases;
in order to reduce the risk of infection, the British autho¬
rities installed floating hospitals on barges and even used
old warships out of commission to house the sick. The
statisticians registered 36,000 deaths in Bengal from 1903
to 1907, and 54,000 cases in a single year at about the
same time In North America.
In a report submitted to the Health Section of the League
of Nations, Professor Tarassevich, of Moscow, cited some
impressive figures: in 1919 there were 102,000 cases of
smallpox in the U.S.S.R. ; 1920 cases ; 1921
cases; 1922 25,047 cases. The drop shown by the last
figure is explained by the resumption of systematic vac¬
cination.
Throughout the ages man sought some way to protect
himself. Some medical historians like to think that anti-
smallpox inoculation is as old as the disease itself. In
the remotest times, in fact, physicians noted that people
who had recovered from smallpox were protected In some
way against a new attack.
In China and India, it was observed that the disease
produced pustules of varying gravity. The idea arose of
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
:wt
WORLD-WIDE THREAT. No country is free from the threat of smallpox. If health authorities were not
constantly on the alert, smallpox could spread like wildfire. Under international sanitary regulations,
countries must notify cases to WHO within 24 hours. Here, infected areas are being recorded.
transferring a mild Infection to healthy persons in order
to protect them against a serious attack. The Chinese
method consisted in blowing powder made from the scabs
of pustules into the nostrils of the person to be immunized,
through a copper tube. In India, pus from mild smallpox
pustules was introduced into the skin of the elbow of the
person to be protected. In short, a kind of preventive
smallpox infection was applied. The practice it was known
in 1715. In 1716, Pastor Cotton Mather in Boston learned
from his negro slave, who came from the Fezzan, that
smallpox inoculation was widely practised in Africa. In
Europe generally, however, the method made but slow
progress.
In Turkey, at the beginning of the eighteenth century,
smallpox inoculation was being practised. Lady Mary
Wortley Montagu, the wife of the British Ambassador to
Turkey, got to know about this method of prevention.
Lady Mary, a determined woman, was quickly convinced
and did not hesitate to have her three-year-old son
inoculated. In a letter to one of her friends she gave
some interesting facts concerning the technique of the
operation:
"A propos of distempers, I am going to tell you a thing
that will make you wish yourself here. The smallpox, so
fatal, and so general amongst us, is here entirely harm¬
less, by the invention of ingrafting, which is the term they
give it. There is a set of old women, who make it their
business to perform the operation, every autumn in the
month of September, when the great heat is abated.
"People send to one another to know if any of their
family has a mind to have the smallpox; they make par¬
ties for this purpose, and when they are met (commonly
fifteen or sixteen together), the old woman comes with
a nutshell full of the matter of the best sort of small¬
pox, and asks what vein you please to have opened.
"She immediately rips open that you offer her, with a
large needle (which gives you no more pain than a com¬
mon scratch) and puts into the vein, as much matter as
can lie upon the head of her needle, and after that binds
up the little wound with a hollow bit of shell ; and in this
manner opens four or five veins . . .
"The children or young patients play together all the
rest of the day, and are in perfect health to the eighth.
Then the fever begins to seize them, and they keep their
beds two days, very seldom three. They have very rarely
above twenty or thirty pocks in their faces, which never
mark, and in eight days they are as well as before their
illness."
This was how smallpox inoculation was practised in
Constantinople. For adults also the effects were mild:
eight days' incubation, two to three days of malaise, and
no scars after recovery.
When she returned to England in 1718 Lady Mary's
one thought was to promote smallpox inoculation. In 1721,
she took a spectacular decision and had her daughter pub¬
licly inoculated in the presence of the Court physicians.
The successful operation caused such a sensation that
Caroline of Anspach, the Princess of Wales, who herself
had had smallpox at the age of three, became one of
Lady Montagu's most enthusiastic supporters.
It was decided in the same year to carry out an experi¬
ment on six condemned prisoners at Newgate. The
experiment began on August 9 and ended on August 31
with the release of all the prisoners, who were pardoned
and sent home after having undergone the inoculation
with success. Posterity is therefore indebted to Lady
Mary Wortley Montagu for her intelligent and courageous
action and she deserves recognition as the forerunner in
England of Edward Jenner in the fight against smallpox.
There is no doubt that inoculation was a step
in the right direction. Tf|e technique was simplified later ,
the arm-to-arm method of inoculation was introduced,
using persons suffering from a slight attack of the disease ;
but there was a considerable element of danger in this
operation and sometimes serious symptoms would follow
in the inoculated person. There was yet another factor:
every inoculated person was a potential new focus of infec¬
tion far. from being reduced, the disease was thus main¬
tained and even disseminated.
Only with the introduction of the Jenner method of vacci- *
nation was the way found to protect the individual as well
as the community.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
In 1796 Edward
Jenner, an English
doctor, carried out
the world's first
vaccination, thereby
discovering how to
produce immunity
against smallpox. We
present here the
story of Jenner's
patient search for
a way to defend man
against a disease
that had plagued him
throughout history.
28
S a student he was rather dreamy, but also
gifted with great Imagination. There was a
poetic streak in him and he loved nature and the English
countryside of the 1770's. This 21 -year-old Englishman
was the third son of the Vicar of Berkeley in Gloucester¬
shire. For eight years already he had been apprenticed
to a surgeon apothecary, Daniel Ludlow of Sodbury, near
Bristol. The young man's name was Edward Jenner.
One morning during consulting hours a young country
girl came to see him. Like any other doctor he asked her
a number of questions and wanted to know whether she
had been ill before. Yes, she said, she had had the cowpox
and this was just as well, she added, for it would protect
her against the smallpox: "I cannot take that disease for
I have had cowpox".
Jenner's curiosity was aroused. He had of course been
taught the technique of inoculation like all medical students
of his day and was familiar with this means of protection
against smallpox, but he realized that it was not perfect.
In London, in Jenner's early days, smallpox killed one to
three thousand persons every year. Jenner came from a
country district where the belief was fairly widespread that
cowpox, an infection of the udder transmissible to man,
would protect the person who got it against smallpox.
Jenner practised smallpox inoculations but the scientist
in him suspected that improvements were possible. Ana¬
lysing the results of his inoculations critically he realized
that most of the unsuccessful inoculations those that
did not "take" occurred among .persons who looked
after animals and who previously had had cowpox. This
obviously called for further investigation.
Leaving Sodbury, the young man spent two years in
London as a resident house pupil with Dr. John Hunter, the
distinguished surgeon and medical researcher, at St.
George's Hospital. His ambition was to set up practice
in surgery and pharmacy at Berkeley. Before leaving
Hunter he wished to know what the great man thought
about inoculation. Was this technique not outmoded?
Could something better be found? Hunter's advice was:
"Don't think. Jenner, but try experiments".
Cowpox protects against smallpox this Idea obsessed
the young doctor of Berkeley. But proof was needed.
Opportunity offered it in the shape of a milkmaid, Sarah
Nelmes, and James Phipps, a boy of about eight years.
Sarah had developed a cowpox sore on her right hand.
The sore appeared so typical to Jenner that he had a
drawing of her hand made. Two other small pustules on
her wrist, he was convinced, were also due to cowpox. If
the matter in the pustules was really active, he argued,
then it should have its effect also on a child who had neither
had smallpox nor cowpox. So on May 14, 1796 he made
two superficial incisions in the arm of James Phipps and
inserted some of the liquid from Sarah's large pustule. In
this way he hoped to protect the child against smallpox.
Seriously, carefully, he followed up the results of his
operation. At first there was almost no reaction and the
incision marks practically disappeared, but then, when
everything seemed to be over, the skin where the insertions
had been made became red and slowly swelled up; a sore
appeared and grew. The boy felt quite well until the seventh
day when he had a slight pain under the arm. On the
eighth or ninth day he had some fever, shivered a little,
lost his appetite and had a slight headache. Throughout
the .day he felt slightly ill and that night he slept badly.
But the next day the boy was quite well again.
Neither Jenner nór his patient was the least bit worried by
the remaining scabs. Jenner was happy with the result.
The reaction had not been serious a little fever, a passing
indisposition, and no complications. But of course that
was only half the story. What would the future bring?
Would James Phipps escape smallpox ?
Edward Jenner wanted to be sure. In July he faced the
cardinal test and inoculated the boy with matter taken
straight from a smallpox pustule. What would be the out¬
come? Jenner was worried. He could not sleep, got up at
night and walked up and down in the consulting room in
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
cover him with ridicule and made fun of his method which,
they said, the doctor had simply got from a milkmaid.
The public showed strong opposition. The clergy even
spoke of vaccination as a kind of plot against the designs
of the Lord. In fact, there were vested interests at stake
and Jenner's method was opposed by inoculation "special¬
ists". The opposition did not hesitate to imply that Jenner
was an unscrupulous fellow who was out to make a for¬
tune by championing an ineffective method of treatment.
Matters became worse because Jenner was highly sensi¬
tive to criticism, could not put up with disagreement and
was rude to people who did not embrace his view. How¬
ever, after a good many tests and countertests, all of which
were successful, the wind started to turn. The simplicity
of the operation also proved to be a good argument. It
became increasingly difficult for the opponents to argue
their case, especially after Pearson and Woodville, two
prominent figures in British medicine, had confirmed
Jenner's results.
But something was wrong after all. Jenner and his
followers made the mistake of basing part of their argu¬
ment on the assumption that vaccination conferred lasting
immunity. This gave rise to some hesitation among English
doctors who, while supporting the principle of vaccination,
stressed the necessity for re-vaccination. At this point
of the controversy the promoters of vaccination showed
themselves to be too conservative. They were against
re-vaccination, not because they thought it would be alto¬
gether useless, but rather for fear of discrediting their
method and of weakening the confidence of the public.
The public, of. course, was only too easily put off by clumsy
vaccinations and occasional severe reactions.
his comfortable house at Berkeley. What if he had made
a mistake?
Time dragged heavily. Again he meticulously observed
every phase of the reaction. But the days went by and it
was not long before all trace of the vaccination disappeared.
Young Phipps did not get the fever, nor a:,y infectious
symptom. He seemed indeed to be resistant to smallpox:
the animal disease had immunized him. So, for Jenner,
the decisive experiment had been performed and hence¬
forth he was sure of the protective value of cowpox.
Jenner was so overjoyed that he treated James Phipps as
his son. Later, in 1818, he even had a house built for the
young man, the first person he vaccinated.
HE advent of smallpox vaccination was the
opening of a great chapter in the history of
world medicine. But Jenner realized that not everybody
would be convinced by his method so he pursued his
studies and repeated his experiments. It was not until 1798
that he decided to publish his findings in a little work of
60 pages entitled "An inquiry into the causes and effects
of the variolae vaccinae". His ideas, however, were
received rather sceptically at first.
Jenner spent three months in London. He was in the
prime of life and his friend, Edward Gardner, left the
following description of him: "He was rather under middle-
size, but robust, active, and well formed. He was parti¬
cular in his dress, and when I first met him, he was clad
in a blue coat with yellow buttons, buckskins, well polished
jockey-boots with handsome silver spurs, and carried a
smart whip with a silver handle. His hair, after the fashion
of the time, was done up in a club, and he wore a broad-
brimmed hat."
But the elegant Jenner looked in vain for volunteers on
which to try out his vaccination. There were numerous
supporters of the old method of inoculation who tried to
WHAT really counted was that the movement had
started and it could not be reversed. Despite
objections, it spread to many parts of the world. Benjamin
Waterhouse vaccinated in Boston though he complained
that the public was uninterested and suspicious. Seaman
vaccinated in New York; Coxe, Rush, Oliver and Currie in
Philadelphia, and James Smith in Baltimore. In Hanover,
Germany, Stromeyer also complained of the opposition of
his colleagues. Another vaccinator, Stuve at Görlitz, said
he had many enemies and that his fellow doctors were
jealous of him. In France, there was propaganda against
the vaccinators, but it did not go very far. In 1800, Wood¬
ville took vaccine to France and taught his French colleagues
the new method.
But Jenner was not to be satisfied with all this. Now that
he had determined the protective power of cowpox, nothing
would do but for vaccination to be practised everywhere.
He had set himself the task of protecting the whole of
mankind against smallpox.
General immunization, he was convinced, could only be
achieved through cowpox. But the pustules on the cow
did not last very long and they contained too little matter
for widespread use. Furthermore, sick cows were not
always to be had and it was out of the question to spread
cowpox among healthy animals. Jenner considered that the
sore produced in man was so like the cowpox sore that the
artificially produced sore could render the same services
as the original one. In other words, since the supply of
matter from cows was limited he would create another such
pustule in the next person. In this way, an uninterrupted
chain of solidarity against the disease might be created.
Jenner's obstinacy in experimenting this system was to have
its reward and he succeeded in continuing this person-to-
person vaccination for a period of 14 months without appar¬
ent loss of efficacy. He claimed that, after all these
passages, the vaccine was just as effective as if it had been
taken straight from a cow.
Sure of himself, Jenner continued his demonstrations,
countered every objection, and decided to carry the battle
to London. He set up house in Bond Street. Two years
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
m m
A ton
'-\*iv^:i-
prevention...
How to prevent smallpox through
vaccination has been known since the
end of the 1 8th century. Yet the disease
remains endemic in many Asian and
African countries and is still not
completely eliminated in Latin America.
The aim of an eradication campaign is
to vaccinate 100 per cent of the
population in countries where the
disease is prevalent. For this, enor¬
mous stocks of vaccine are needed. In
India, where 250 million people (out
of 450 million) were vaccinated bet¬
ween 1962 and 1964, vaccine is
being produced with assistance from
WHO and UNICEF. At the King
Institute of Preventative Medicine in
Madras, vaccine is prepared from virus
grown on the abdomen of calves (top
right). Freeze drying of this vaccine
(bottom and opposite page) produces
a stable product which can be stored
successfully in India's tropical climate.
WHO photos P.N. Sharma
^
y
l ». '
WK
X
FU
S:
7
ú
W^.m
J
f
JENNER (Cont'd)
A baby christened Vaccinov
30
later, his technique had been adopted by 40 doctors who
became enthusiastic supporters of the new method. In
1800, as many as 16,000 Londoners were vaccinated. In
1801, the number rose to 60,000.
News of victory came from abroad. In the United States,
Waterhouse was supported in his efforts by a propagandist
of choice: Thomas Jefferson in person, who had his entire
family vaccinated.
The Geneva doctors also were In the van; Dr Odier
obtained vaccine from England and was able to vaccinate
over 600 persons at the very time an epidemic of smallpox
had broken out. Nevertheless, the epidemic caused
254 deaths. His colleague, Alexandre Marcet, invented a
way of preserving the vaccine between two slides of
opaque glass wrapped in black paper.
Another Genevan, Jean de Carro, had the honour of
being the first and greatest propagandist for vaccination
outside Britain. He had established himself in Austria and
was won over by Jenner's method about which he had read
in a local paper. He did not hesitate to vaccinate his
two sons and soon after submitted them to the countertest
in the presence of Austrian doctors. After this convincing
demonstration, smallpox vaccination was adopted through¬
out Austria and Germany. As a reward, he was knighted
by the Emperor Francis II. Thanks to his enthusiasm,
vaccination soon spread to Poland and Russia. In St.
Petersburg, the royal surgeon de Lyndström made good
use of the vaccine sent by de Carro. Elisabeth Alexevievna,
Empress of all the Russians and wife of Alexander I, was
so enthusiastic that she not only sent Jenner a ring with a
large diamond but encouraged mass vaccination. At her
command, Anton Petrov, the first child to be vaccinated
in the Empire, was escorted in a coach through St. Peters¬
burg to be baptized, and was given the new name of
Vaccinov. The State paid for his upbringing and later
granted him a pension for life.
Carro, knowing that Jenner was trying to introduce the
vaccine in India, developed a new method of preservation.
The vaccine was dried on threads and pieces of ivory,
which were then enclosed in a wooden box as protection
against light. Using this method Carro sent the vaccine
to the British Consul in Baghdad. His initiative was
crowned with success: vaccinations were performed at
Basra on the Persian Gulf and soon in Bombay. Jenner
was so happy that he sent his friend a silver snuff box
with the inscription "Edward Jenner to Jean de Carro".
The vaccine was spreading. Dom Balmis, surgeon to
King Charles IV of Spain, brought it together with 22
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
children needed for person-to-person transmission from
La Coruna in Spain to the Canary Islands, to the Caribbean,
to Mexico, to Guatemala and to South America. Then, with
26 other children, he went to the Philippines and China.
At Naples and in Sicily, fervent religious processions were
held to fetch the vaccine prepared by Dr Sacco the new
method was almost credited with sacred power. In France,
Bonaparte, First Consul, admired Jenner's efforts and offi¬
cially encouraged vaccination. The year after he became
Emperor, he made vaccination compulsory for all his
soldiers.
One day, when he was about to set off again for the
wars, he was listening absent-mindedly in the presence
of the Empress Josephine to the reading of a letter request¬
ing the liberation of an English prisoner and was about to
say no when Josephine remarked "But it's Jenner who is^
making the request". Napoleon immediately changed his
mind: "Ah, Jennerl I can refuse nothing to Jenner."
The merit of having been the first head of state to decree
compulsory vaccination for all subjects goes to Felix Pascal
Bacciochi, Prince of Lucca and Piombino. His decree is
dated 1806. His example was followed by Bavaria the
following year, then by Denmark In 1810, by Sweden in
1816, and by Württemberg in 1818, where the King ordered
every infant to be vaccinated before the age of three.
Jenner subsequently led a somewhat secluded life in his
country house in Berkeley. He could now consider that
he had reached the goal he had set himself. Vaccination
was spreading with irresistible force. He spent many hours
alone working at the bottom of his garden in a summer
house which he had specially built. There he also pursued
his favourite pastime, birdwatching. On an appointed day
he still received all those who wished to be vaccinated,
in the summer house, which he called his Vaccina Temple.
Sure of his achievement, proud of the wide appreciation
his discovery had received, he continued to correspond
with men of learning up to the time of his death, which
occurred as he sat at his writing table, on January 26, 1823.
For long, however, smallpox vaccination was to have its
enemies. Some of them were important figures who did
their best to play on the fears of the public. For example,
in 1855, a work was published in Paris by Verdi-Delisle
entitled "The Physical and Moral Degeneration of the
Human Race caused by the Vaccine". In 1890, Alfred
Russell Wallace, "in the name of individual liberty", joined
the detractors and fought the idea of legislation that would
make vaccination compulsory and non-compliance punish¬
able by 'fines or imprisonment. Bernard Shaw himself
swelled the ranks of the opponents with his play, "The
Doctor's Dilemma."
All the arguments of the doubters, detractors and oppo¬
nents, however, lost ground against the favourable conclu¬
sions of the official reports on vaccination that gradually
accumulated: 1882 in Germany, 1885 and 1896 in England,
and 1913 in Pennsylvania, for example.
Jenner's discovery was first accepted and then advocated
in many places all over the world. As a mass preventive
measure, it soon changed the face of smallpox epidemics Q1
became less frequent and less serious. Jenner's tenacity,
maintained during 26 long years of struggle, was at last
bearing fruit.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL PROSPECTS OF SCIENCE (Cont'd from page 8)
An uninterrupted creative process
32
we see that money spent on education (approximately
2-3 thousand millions), can yield far higher returns
(approximately 70 thousand millions) in a few years' time.
If education is to be made more efficient, it must be
soundly planned. Social, economic, demographic, geogra¬
phic, organizational and other factors must be taken into
account in educational planning. In other words it must be
closely related to overall planning of national economic
development.
Great importance attaches to the social and economic
aspects of the question. The very nature of work is being
transformed as a result of changes in industrial relations
and the increasing degree of mechanization and automa¬
tion of production. . Industry today increasingly needs
highly trained workers, and technical education must meet
this need.
HE experience gained by the Soviet Union and
certain other countries in the elimination of
illiteracy and the rapid development of education underlines
the fact that reading, writing and arithmetic must be taught
initially in the pupil's mother tongue. The problem of creating
a written form for each language and teaching, primary
school pupils in their mother tongue is therefore immensely
important for the young, developing countries. A revision
of teaching programmes and a full use of technical aids
can not only contribute to the further development of
primary,, secondary and higher education, but also to
campaigns for adult literacy.
Problems arising in relation to education and scientific
and technical development cannot possibly be solved
unless serious attention is paid to the training of scien¬
tists and other specialists in each nation. Every develop¬
ing country must have its own national scientific centres
an academy of sciences or scientific councils and also
a network of scientific research institutes to serve the
main fields of economic and cultural development. Unesco
should furnish the developing countries effective assistance
in creating a national and regional framework for the deve¬
lopment of science.
Unesco's social sciences programme frequently comes
under discussion. The best way to increase the effective¬
ness of activities and research work in the social sciences,
it seems to me, would be to reveal the tremendous pos¬
sibilities which general and complete disarmament could
open up for the development of education, science and
culture.
We have only to consider the scale of the resources
needed for financing educational programmes and for
training technicians in all countries especially the deve¬
loping countries to realize what immense possibilities
the achievement of disarmament would bring. Studies of
the social, economic, cultural, scientific and technical
consequences of disarmament; an investigation of ways to
remove the effects of colonialism in developing countries;
a stepping up of the campaign against racial prejudice and
discrimination; efforts to foster greater mutual understand¬
ing of different ideas, methods and principles all this
would help Unesco to solve problems assigned to it by
its Constitution.
Works of art are of value only if they bring happiness and
if they help people to live richer lives and to judge world
history and world events correctly. This, to a great extent, is
why the works of the great masters of the past have
achieved immortality. Let us take the example of the
Venus of Milo. Greek by origin, Parisian by residence,
triumphantly touring from continent to continent, she has
become a citizen of the world. Or, as another, take
Eisenstein's film, "The Battleship Potemkin," which has
been winning acclaim in many countries for several
decades. The same will probably be true of the film
"West Side Story."
Every people has its favourite writers, artists and com¬
posers. The works of literature and art that have won
the esteem and affection of a people become the heritage
of all mankind. Surely this is borne out by the fact that
the works of Michelangelo and Shakespeare, Rembrandt
and Beethoven, Tagore and Maxim Gorky, Rodin and Mark
Twain, give joy and delight to all nations of the world. And
what enjoyment we derive from the still too little known
cultural heritage of Africa and Latin America.
Unesco would fulfil its role better if it used all the
means at its disposal to ensure that the cultural values
of mankind were' instrumental in furthering humanistic
principles, and in spreading and strengthening the concepts
of peace, friendship and international understanding.
The future of the whole world and the social, scientific
and technological progress of mankind depend on the
education of our young generation. Peace would be In
mortal danger if racial prejudice and revengeful and mili¬
taristic ideas were to triumph, The education of the youn¬
ger generation in the spirit of mutual understanding, peace
and friendship among nations, regardless of national dif¬
ferences and political and religious convictions is there¬
fore the sacred duty of Unesco and of us all.
A realistic assessment of the world in which we live
reveals the existence of economic, social and political
contradictions. However, the use of force to settle problems
can no longer be localized it will have dire consequences
for the whole of mankind. Therefore the repudiation of
force in settling problems and the subsequent application
of a policy of economic, cultural, scientific and technolo¬
gical collaboration and peaceful coexistence, are the right
path to be followed in relations among nations.
The peoples of all countries should make every effort to
achieve the complete cessation of all types of tests of
atomic weapons and to achieve general and complete dis¬
armament and the strengthening of economic, cultural and
scientific collaboration among countries with different
social systems in the name of the progress of all mankind.
IEWED in the light of social, scientific and tech¬
nological progress, the satisfaction for all time
of the food and energy requirements of mankind, the
elimination of infectious illnesses, the conquest of cardio¬
vascular diseases and cancer, the consequent achievement
of unprecedented longevity and a happier life than has yet
been known, and an unparalleled flowering of education,
science and culture now begin to appear real and close
at hand.
By its very nature and substance life is a contradictory,
an optimistic affair. It is the result of an uninterrupted and
stupendous creative process. We must all labour
incessantly to extend this process and to implant humanistic
principles more firmly in mankind while striving to remove
all obstacles that lie in the way.
Until now, it has always been considered normal that
an organism should age with the passing of time; this was
held to be a natural law. But man, armed with science and
the principles of humanism, is triumphing over this natural
phenomenon.
Unesco does not age with the years, for young states
are constantly joining it, its working methods are being
perfected, and its work is bearing fruit. May I express my
firm belief that our Organization will take an increasing
part in achieving the noblest aims of our age the streng¬
thening of peace and of fruitful collaboration in the field
of education, science and culture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WORLD SIDE STORY
Sir.
I came across Professor Kvaraceus'
articles on juvenile delinquency,
World Side Story (May, June and Sep¬
tember 1964) not in my capacity as a
schoolmaster, but as a leader of a
youth club.
It can be argued that what young
people need in a youth club Is no
rules and few, if any, organized acti¬
vities. We have rules some of them
of the "Thou shalt not" type but in
general this does not turn too many
away: As to organized activities, there
have been times when some of the
members have been unwilling to parti¬
cipate; yet when there are no such
activities planned there are complaints
of "nothing to do". I ought to add
that we have a committee of members
responsible, to some- extent for plan¬
ning the programme.
On the one hand these teenagers
want to rebel (albeit mildly) against
rules and organization; on the other
hand they feel somewhat lost if there
is no authority and are prepared to
accept what rules we have.
The committee illustrates their de¬
sire to have themselves as their own
authority, but also their inability as
yet to take full responsibility: they
are still willing enough for us to orga¬
nize things when they cannot.
I agree wholeheartedly with Pro¬
fessor Kvaraceus that the whole prob¬
lem of juvenile delinquency is ex¬
tremely complex and consequently
any solution must be just as complex.
I dislike superficial analyses which
state that the real key to the problem
is X and so the answer is Y. Similar
are attempts to classify teenagers Into
a few categories and then to rigidly
apply a set of rules to each class. They
are individuals and have to be treated
as such. The problem of juvenile de¬
linquency is surely as complex as the
number of Individuals caught up In it.
We hope that our youth club activities
and atmosphere, though both limited,
do in fact help some teenagers to be,
at least, better citizens of our society
than they would have been otherwise.
R. Tyler
Coulsdon, Surrey, U.K.
Sir,
After reading and re-reading the
World Side Story articles, I felt that
some essential element was still
missing. I agree entirely with the
author that parents bear much respon¬
sibility for defaults in the education
of young people. But there is some¬
thing else which could explain
inertia in parents and social inadapta¬
tion among youth. The author refers
several times to "insecurity", but fails
to develop the Idea. This, to me,
is a point to be stressed. What does
our present epoch offer to the young
people who will be tomorrow's adults?
The atom bomb nothing more, nothing
better.
We all realize that we may become
the victims of some act of imprudence
or negligence or even of a mistake on
someone's part. But we who have
lived for some time have known less
disquieting - periods; today's young
people have always lived under an
omnipresent threat. I believe this is
the real reason for today's juvenile
delinquency and for many other
symptoms of decadence.
M. Launay
Andenos-les-Bains, France
Sir,
I would list the chief causes of
juvenile delinquency as follows: (1) an
excessively highly-strung nature and
an insufficient or badly-chosen diet,
i.e. above all a question of health (2)
deprivation of affection (3) insecurity
in the family circle (4) "broken" homes
or quarrelling parents (5) a lack of
care, order and cleanliness.
Ethics should be taught to children
at the earliest age by properly trained
and experienced teachers who are
themselves fond of children.
Mme Govaerts-Rouvroy
Malines, Belgium
Sir,
I disagree completely with certain
ideas in World Side Story. Nowa¬
days we pay far too much attention
to young people, or rather, to their
problems. These are not real prob¬
lems, being of a transitory kind, and
are certainly not adult problems. I
am, however, in favour of youth
movements and sporting, cultural and
welfare associations whose basic aim
is the moulding of character. But
when young people are always
hearing about their problems they
tend to get an exaggerated Idea of
their own importance and this en¬
courages them to seek freedom pre¬
maturely. Aside from this I found
the articles extremely interesting; they
helped to clarify my ideas on the
subject.
Claude Rollet
Grenoble, France
Sir,
I would like to say that society
gets exactly what it appreciates or
rewards. A child wants to become
important in a good way. But if
overstrict parents or authorities do not
appreciate and encourage him when
he does something good, then the
only way to get attention Is for
him to be bad, so that at least he
can get a negative form of love.
Overstrict parents are the cause of
more human misery than can be cata¬
logued in any single volume.
Arthur J. Johnson
Chicago, Illinois, U.S.A.
HELPFUL MAPS
Sir,
The Courier gives an illuminating
picture of the world and its diverse
peoples. This is a function that
Unesco ¡s uniquely suited to perform.
I should like to see, with each arti¬
cle, a map which would give some
idea of the area or areas mentioned
in the text. As an American who has
not travelled extensively throughout
the world it is often difficult for me to
transport myself to regions elsewhere
which are not frequently mentioned in
the daily press. The maps accom¬
panying "People of the Deltas" by
Adriaan Volker, (July/August 1964
issue) is an excellent example of what
I mean. This would increase the
informative value of The Courier for
myself and others like me.
Joseph Bernstein
Gardena, California, U.S.A.
WOMEN IN THE NEW ASIA
Sir,
Thank you for the splendid issue on
Women in the New Asia (September
1964). Being a woman it was natural
that I should find it of greater Interest
than some of the issues dealing with
more technical subjects.
It is good to learn of the opportuni¬
ties that are being given to the
women of Asia and may we hope that
they will use these opportunities to
greater advantage than do many
women of our own country who have
enjoyed them for many years.
I hope in the near future Unesco
will give us a similar issue on
"Women of Africa". I have travelled
in Africa but have seen only slight
evidence of change of status for the
women of these countries.
In Egypt my hopes revived when 1
saw a group of women in the oldest
mosque In Cairo. Here they were
being taught to read and write and
given a knowledge of hygiene and the
care of children. The Egyptians
believe that much can be done
through the influence of the woman
on her family. This 1 believe is true
for the women of the whole world.
Ivy Crowson
Newcastle upon Tyne, U.K.
Sir,
The personal accounts in "Women
in the New Asia" no doubt bear
witness to a striking evolution, but
they only apply to the emancipation
of young women from well-to-do
families. You might thus be accused
of saying nothing about the position
of women in less prosperous families.
However, I am sure the issue will
Inspire everyone to reflect on the prob¬
lem and this ¡s a worthwhile result
as I strongly doubt whether many-
people, even in so-called "civilized"
places, concede to women their
rightful place.
Louis Henln
Le Havre, France 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
UNESCO'S PROGRAMME FOR 1965-66
34
UNESCO has now embarked on
the world programme in science,
education and culture which it proposes
to carry out in 1965-66. To finance this
programme, adopted by the Unesco Gene¬
ral Conference at the end of last year,
Unesco's member states are contributing
nearly $49 million almost $10 million more
than in 1963-64. During the next two
years Unesco also expects to use a
further $50 million, provided by the U.N.
Special Fund and the U.N. Expanded Tech¬
nical Assistance Programme to carry out
operations in member states at their
request.
The programme envisaged by Unesco
was debated and approved by delegates
from 117 member states, who included
64 ministers, 80 scientists and 150 specia¬
lists in educational and cultural affairs.
Here are some of its salient features:
Education, as a key factor In econo¬
mic and social development, is given con¬
tinuing priority and has been allocated
nearly one-quarter of Unesco's regular
budget. Special emphasis is given to
educational planning, for which Unesco set
up an international institute In Paris in
1963, and to a world attack on illiteracy.
The outstanding feature of Unesco's
new campaigns against illiteracy is the
special experimental programme for mass
literacy to be carried out in eight countries
as a preparatory step to the launching at
a later stage of a world literacy campaign
(see Unesco Courier, Oct. 1964). Ways
and means of eradicating what Mr. René
Maheu, Director-General of Unesco, has
called "the scandal and shame" of illiter¬
acy, will be worked out at an international
congress to be held in Teheran In Septem¬
ber of this year at the invitation of the
Shah of Iran. As a result of the Unesco
International Youth Conference In Gren¬
oble, France, last year, an International
Committee on Youth is being set up. It
will work with Unesco to promote youth
activities for international co-operation and
understanding.
Priority is accorded to science on
an equal footing with education. Unesco
has reshaped its science programme and
is using a large proportion of its science
budget for projects related to science and
technology for economic development.
Unesco projects, designed to "plant
the tree of science" in developing areas,
will assist the training of engineers and
the expansion of technological research,
as well as the creation, in collaboration
with leading universities, of an' Interna¬
tional network of refresher courses for
scientists.
January 1965 marked the start of
the International Hydrological Decade
launched by Unesco. This co-operative
international scientific venture seeks to
improve water management throughout the
world, to develop hydrological knowledge
and to encourage increased training for
scientists in this field (see Unesco Cour¬
ier, "Water and Life," July-August, 1964).
A unique service of S.O.S. earthquake
teams has been created by Unesco. These
reconnaissance missions will be sent
within 72 hours to the scene of severe
earthquakes. This is one of the innova¬
tions In Unesco's programme on seismo¬
logy and earthquake engineering which
also provides for the mapping of seismic
danger zones, research on earthquake pre¬
diction, research into protective measures
against earthquakes and the extension of
seismological observatories (see Unesco
Courier, Oct. 1963). Other studies and pro¬
jects will be carried out in geology, the
life sciences and oceanography. In which
Unesco has already promoted Important
international surveys covering the Indian
Ocean and, more recently, the tropical
Atlantic.
Unesco is continuing to promote the
growth of press, radio, films and televi¬
sion in the developing countries and the
training of technicians to work in these
fields. It is also encouraging the use
of mass media for adult education and
literacy campaigns.
A six-year project, now operating In
Senegal, Africa, provides a field laboratory
for Unesco and its African member states
to test the effectiveness of radio, television,
films and publications as aids for adult
education.
0 Broadcasting via space communication
opens up tremendous possibilities for
teaching vast new audiences and therefore
directly interests Unesco as a means of
promoting the flow of Information, the
spread of education and wider cultural ex¬
changes. This year Unesco will be co¬
operating closely In this field with the
International Telecommunications Union.
Unesco Is devoting increasing attention
to the social and cultural aspects of eco¬
nomic development, especially on the
Impact it makes on recently Independent
countries. Other major problems being
dealt with under its programme In the
the social and human sciences are the
struggle against race prejudice and the
economic and social consequences of disar¬
mament and peace research (see Unesco
Courier, Nov. 1964).
Unesco's 10-year Major Project on
Mutual Appreciation of Eastern and
Western Cultural Values as such Is sched¬
uled to end In 1966 when its effects will
be carefully analyzed. Unesco's efforts to
promote understanding between different
cultures will, of course, continue and will
be extended to Include African cultures.
In this context Unesco is to prepare a
"General History of Africa" which will
complement another major Unesco-spon-
sored historical work, "The History of the
Scientific and Cultural Development of
Mankind", the second volume of which is
due to appear In May (*).
For further facts we refer readers to
Unesco's Official monthly publication,
"The Unesco Chronicle", whose January
1965 issue is entirely devoted to the deci¬
sions of the 13th Session of Unesco's
General Conference. Published In English,
French, Spanish and Arabic editions, It can
be obtained from Unesco National Distri¬
butors (see inside back cover). Annual
subscription: $2.00; 10/-; 7 F.
* Volume II. The Ancient World, appearing In
three parts: (1) From about 1200 B.C. to 500 B.C.
(2) From about 500 B.C. to the Christian Era.
(3) From the beginning of the Christian Era to
500 A.D., published by George Allen and Unwln
Ltd., London (Price £6.6 0.) and by Harper and
Row, New York.
'TIMELESS TREASURE'
A new Unesco film
on monuments in peril
IN all parts of the world
works of art and monu¬
ments are threatened with des¬
truction by time and nature and,
Increasingly, by man himself. A
new Unesco film entitled, "Timeless
Treasure" warns how close
the world stands to losing forever
these unique vestiges of its past.
It shows the marks left on the face
of mankind's Irreplaceable historical
records by erosion, neglect and van¬
dalism. The film also reveals what
is now being done to save monu¬
ments and works of art. Some of
the work of protection and preser¬
vation is described by Dr. J. Har¬
old Plenderleith, director of the
International Study Centre for the
Restoration and Preservation of Cul¬
tural Property, set up by Unesco in
Rome. Dr. Plenderleith was a con¬
tributor (The New Science of Art
Conservation) to the special issue
of the Unesco Courier on Monu¬
ments in Peril (January 1965).
"Timeless Treasure" (running time
27 minutes, black and white, 16 mm.
and 35 mm.) exists in English,
French and Spanish versions; a
Russian version is being prepared.
Copies can be obtained by writing
to the Radio and Visual Information
Division Unesco, Place de Fonte¬
noy, Paris (7C).
2
<
z
<
cc
O
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Vohunc XVI] No 3 1964 ^m iHr~~^B W
MM
SFAM
A ^uir:. > .... Rcvuc trimestrielle publice ¡:.<- : ' i
The International Journal of Adult and Youth Education
is a quarterly technical journal intended mainly for spe¬
cialists in fundamental and adult education. Its articles
describe important activities in this field and it pub¬
lishes information concerning programmes and general
lines of policy.
Annual subscription: $1.75; 9/-; 6.50 F
Each number: $0.50; 3/-; 2.00 F
international
journal
of adult
and youth
education
u n e s c o vol. xvi (1964), no. 2
Museum, a quarterly review of activities and research
in the field of museography, is produced not only for
those professionally interested in the running of museums,
but also for teachers and students of art in general. Lavish¬
ly illustrated and printed entirely on art paper, it reports on
outstanding achievements in display and conservation,
presents new examples of museum construction and
describes what museums are offering to the public.
Bilingual (English-French) accompanied by summaries
in Spanish and Russian.
Annual subscription: $7.00; 35/-; 24.00 F
Each number: $2.00; 10/-; 7.00 F
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 70.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgièlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
112, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Ran¬
goon. (	). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, Sir Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B,
244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 13/50). CHINA. World Book Co
Ltd., 99 Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan
(Formosa). CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council,
P. O. Box 539,Nicosia.- CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. EjnarMunks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa.
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP.
1 2598-48. (1 0 F.). GERM ANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650 (DM 10). -
GHANA Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House
Commercial St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRI¬
TAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H.
Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade, Athens	 HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUN¬
GARY. Kultura, P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICE¬
LAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. (1 20 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Ni-
col Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 1 3;Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub/Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 1 6, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (1 5/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (	). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous
& Co., Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O.
Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Port-Louis (1 0/-). MONACO. British Bourbon Street,
Library 30 Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Niihoff. Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-). NOR.
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense 7, Oslo. For the
Unesco Courier also: A.S- Narvesens Litteratur Tjeneste,
Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks 115 (17.50 kr.). PA¬
KISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco
Publications House, P.O. Box 374 56-N Gulberg Indus¬
trial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES. The Modern Book
Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila. POLAND. "RUCH",
ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 1 0 (	). PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Lda, Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO, Spanish English Publi¬
cations, Eleanor Roosevelt 115, Apartado 1912, Hato
Rey. RHODESIA. The Book Centre, Gordon
Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenská Unescoradet, Vasa-
gatan 1 5-1 7, Stockholm, C (Kr. 1 2) ; SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus
6, 1211, Geneva CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News
Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (RL.50).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil Cairo. Sub/agent: La
Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham and Bristol. (1 5/-). UNITED STATES.
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 3 4th St, New York,
N.Y. 1 001 6 (S 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Kn-
jig, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
© Unesco 1964
Aboriginal Art from Australia
Among the Australian aborigines the arts area living force.
Every man at some time or another is called on to act as the
tribal artist, to engrave a sacred object, decorate a burial pole
orto paint designs on the cave wall or the body of a performer
in a ceremony. This cave painting from Western Arnhem
Land an aborigine in pursuit of the evil spirit Adungen
appears in Aboriginal Paintings from Australia, a new
volume in the Unesco Pocket Art Series. These inexpensive
paperbacks present high quality reproductions of art master¬
pieces in full colour. Other recent additions are Greek
Paintings of the Byzantine Period, Buddhist Paintings from
Shrines and Temples in Ceylon, and Czechoslovakian Minia¬
tures from Romanesque and Gothic Manuscripts. Unesco
Pocket Art Series are published in London by Collins (Fontana
Unesco Art Books; 6/- each) and in New York by the New
American Library (Mentor-Unesco Art Books; 95 cents).
]]>
</page>
</document>
