<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078347eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
BRUSSELS 1958
The Atomium : Symbol
of a peaceful world
JULY 1957
(70th year)
Price: 9d. (U. K.)
25 cents (U. S.)
4 0 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
CO VER PHOTO
Giant "Atomium," 360-foot
steel-and-light-alloy structure,
at World's Fair, Brussels. Nine
spheres represent arrangement
of atoms in an elementary crystal
of metal. (See pages 6-7)
Bold designs in glass
steel and perspex
Pavilions built by more than 50 nations and several international orga¬
nizations are now rising on every side in Heysel Park, Brussels, for the
1958 International Exhibition. Bold and advanced designs and revolu¬
tionary structural techniques reflect each country's desire to make
architectural history. Photos on this page show models of six of the
spectacular national pavilions and (opposite page) four striking buildings
out of the forty or so forming the Belgian Section of the Exhibition.
JAPAN
- - '1
THE HOLY SEE
FRANCE
FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY
SWITZERLAND GREAT BRITAIN
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TOWER OF ELECTRONICS
TIMBER INDUSTRY
CIVIL ENGINEERING
TRANSPORTS PAVILION
"UNESCO
er*
JULY 1957
No 7
I Oth YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGES
4 BRUSSELS 1958
"Balance sheet for a more human world"
By D. de Wouters d'Oplinter
6 THE ATOMIUM
Focal point and symbol
8 THE UNITED NATIONS PAVILION
Mirror of the world at work
By Henri Fast
10 ENTIRE <U.N. FAMILY' UNDER ONE ROOF
13 HUMANISM FOR A MODERN WORLD
By Maurice Lambilliotte
16 METEOROLOGY IN THE ATOMIC AGE
By Kaare Langlo
18 CHINESE GETS A LATIN ALPHABET
By Chou You-Kuang
20 THE GIANT MACHINE ON 'BIG WIND' HILL
By E.W. Golding
23 THE 'LOST LETTER* OF MAHATMA GANDHI
Tolstoy museum solves a 50-year-old mystery
By Alexandre Chifman
24 STEINBECK AND HEMINGWAY FAVOURITES IN
NORWAY
Unesco reports on youthful reading tastes
25 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
26 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
27 FAMOUS AUTHORS AS ARTISTS
An extra-special issue next month
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) In English,
French, Spanish and Russian. A small Japanese version is published in Tokyo
and a Danish version in Copenhagen. The United States of America edition
is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 152, West -42nd
Street, New York 36, N.Y., Pennsylvania 6-0851. Second-class mail privileges
authorized at New York. N.Y. (M.C. 57. 1. 1 M A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
credit Is given to THE UNESCO COURIER and two voucher copies are sent
to the editor. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions o! the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UNESCO or those of the editors ol THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $2.50 ; 8/- ; 400 French franca or equivalent.
Printed In France
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
BRUSSELS 1 958
'BALANCE SHEET
FOR A MORE
HUMAN WORLD'
by D. de Wouters d'Oplinter
Next year Brussels -will become a -world in miniature as
Belgium welcomes some 50 nations and seven inter¬
national and supra-national organizations to the
first World's Fair of the atomic era as well as the millions
of people (an estimated thirty-five million, some 60%
from abroad) who are expected to visit this exhibition.
Three years ago Belgium invited all the nations to par-
ticipate in what it described as "The greatest world event
of 1958", and declared that the World's Fairthe biggest
since the one New York put on in 1939would be placed
under the sign of Humanism.
The fact that some 50 countries and seven international
organizations (the U.N. and its Specialized Agencies, the
Organization for European Economic Co-operation, the
Council of Europe, Benelux, the Customs Co-operation
Council, the Red Cross and a supra-national organization:
the European Coal and Steel Community) are preparing to
take part fully demonstrates the interest the entire world
is showing in this gigantic stocktaking of the material and
spiritual wealth of mankind.
All the international bodies will be grouped together in
a special section which will include a "Palace of World
Co-operation". Here, the great problems of our time will
be evoked: the world and social evolution, the increasing
tempo of technical development together with the greater
needs of an ever-expanding population. The Brussels
Exhibition, as a whole, can really be said to centre on these
three main themes.
On a site covering some 500 acres in Heysel Park, about
four and a half miles from the centre of Brussels, a veri¬
table town is rising today. About one-third of the area is
set aside for Belgium, a similar space is taken up by
foreign countries and the rest is divided between the inter¬
national organizations, the Belgian Congo and Ruanda
Urundi, the Amusement Park, and a folklore section in a
quaint village, standing amid the modern pavilions in
glass, steel and perspex, and known as "Belgium in 1900".
of tropical plants
The 40 or so large pavilions in the Belgian section will
not only offer an overall view of Belgian economic
and industrial life, but will embrace scientific, social,
intellectual, religious and many other fields. Furthermore,
the participation of the Belgian provinces with exhibitions
like Antwerp's "'The Boat, Key to the World", and Ghent's
exhibit dedicated to "The Communes", will bring out the
great diversity existing between the various regions.
Outside this section an area of some 20 acres will be
devoted to the Belgian Congo and Ruanda Urundi, taking
as its theme "Fifty years of social, economic and religious
work in the Congo". Below its seven large pavilions a
"tropical garden" will be laid out with Equatorial plants
growing in artificially heated beds.
This part of the Fair looks across the wooded slopes of
Heysel Park to the areas reserved for countries taking part.
As the aim has been to complete major construction work
by the end of June 1957 the great steel frames of the
future pavilions have already risen on every side.
Organized at the mid-point in a century which has seen
dazzling progress in technology, the World's Fair will be a
vast stage with as its scenery, buildings embodying the
very latest architectural designs and building techniques.
Just as the Eiffel Tower, built for the 1889 Exhibition in
Paris, marked the advent of the steel age, so at Brussels
the 360 feet high "Atomium" will be symbolic of the atomic
age, calling to mind the prodigious force of atomic energy
and the latest conquest of man over matter.
Built entirely of aluminium-clad steel, it consists of nine
spheres, each 59 feet in diameter connected to each other
by tubular structures 10 feet in diameter. The structure
represents the arrangement of atoms in an elementary
crystal of metal.
UNITED STATES PAVILION at Brussels Fair, 340 feet in
diameter and 95 feet high, will be world's largest circular building
without any interior columns. One of the remarkable features of
this building is its "bicycle wheel" suspension roof of plastic at¬
tached to an inner metallic rim with high tension steel cables.
The Atomium will actually appear as an Immense cube
resting on one of its- angles. Each of the spheres will be a
large sound-proofed hall, thermically insulated and air-
conditioned. Visitors will travel from sphere to sphere by
escalators in the tubes, while the central column will have
the fastest lift in Europe,0 whisking' sightseers to the
topmost sphere in less than 20 seconds, to a restaurant
where they can enjoy a meal along with a panoramic view
of the fair and the city of Brussels beyond.
The lower spheres will be exhibition halls for displaying
the results of research into the peaceful uses of atomic
energy in different countries. One will be occupied by the
Soviet Union, among whose exhibits will be the small
nuclear power station displayed at Geneva in 1955. Other
countries displaying the fruits of their atomic research at
the Fair will include England, France, the Federal Repub¬
lic of Germany, Norway and the United States.
Designed by the Belgian engineer, André Waterkeyn, the
Atomium will certainly be the most extraordinary of the
many architectural achievements of striking grandeur
which will rise into the sky from the grounds of the Fair.
After studying the plans which the architects of each of
the national pavilions had submitted to the Commissioner-
General of the World's Fair, the Chief Architect, Mr. Van
Goethem, stressed the amazing thoroughness of the
research that had gone into them, and declared: "This
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
will bring about a revolution in the traditional principles
of architecture, not only with regard to form but also
through the use of entirely new kinds of materials."
Quite independently, the architects had nearly all opted
for a form of architecture whose impact is made by
constructional techniques rather than by outward
appearance. As the great majority of pavilions will have
transparent façades, the visitor will be more likely to
admire the ingenuity of the exposed armature bearing the
weight of the building, rather than the actual walls, whose
role is now a secondary one.
The aim of the Exhibition is to provide a panorama of
twentieth-century human activities; it is, in fact, dedicat¬
ed to Man and his aspirations. Though Man's material
activities often enough provide the key to an understand¬
ing of his character, cultural achievements are obviously
the truest reflection of his inner urges, his aims and his
individuality.
For six months, therefore, from April to October 1958,
the Exhibition will be the scene of a continuous series of
international cultural events in different fields literature,
U.S.S.R. SECTION of the Fair is planned around a gigantic rectan¬
gular parthenon in whose centre will stand a statue of Lenin. Pavilion
will be built in the U.S.S.R. and transported in sections (1,500 tons
of steel structure, 200 tons of aluminium, 16,000 sq. metres of
mirrors) to Brussels. Plans also include a 1500-seat theatre.
theatre, films, opera, music, choreography, and others.
To honour each nation, "National Days" have been set
aside when individual countries will organize large-scale
cultural activities.
The Soviet Union will send io Brussels the famous corps
de ballet from Moscow. From the United States will come
theatre companies and orchestras. The Comédie-Fran¬
çaise will travel from Paris, and the leading London sym¬
phony orchestras will also be present. In short, every
country will be sending of its best.
Apart from these national activities, the Belgian Com¬
missioner-General will himself be organizing some large-
scale international cultural gatherings. For instance, a
World Film Festival will be held at Brussels from April 21
to June 13, 1958. It will include world-wide competitions
for experimental films, a "shorts" film festival, and also
one for feature-films. Another film event, to be held from
October 12 to 18, will be a world competition for the best
film of all times.
The Commissioner-General's programme also includes
an international gathering of young people's orchestras
(July 13-21), a university theatre week (August 2-9), a
competition in electronic music (August 15-19) and a world
festival of records (October 5-11).
Many other activities are being arranged but their dates
have not yet been fixed. Chief among them is a world
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
festival of choreography, open to all Belgians or nationals
of other countries taking part m the Fair. There will also
be a series of international dramatic performances, arrang¬
ed with the help of the Theatre of the Nations.
Another type of cultural activity at the Exhibition will
be a series of lectures, for which the Commissioner-
General has invited speakers of world repute.
Lastly, as the Fair seeks to encourage the most extensive
contacts between men and women from all over the world,
it will be an assembly point for congresses.
In order to be approved by the special selection com¬
mittee, such congresses must be planned as study groups
to deal, so far as possible, with some social problem.
Their opening meetings will be held in the Exhibition
grounds, and their subsequent meetings in large buildings
either in Brussels itself or in other Belgian cities. It is
hoped that they will devote at least one meeting to a dis¬
cussion of the Exhibition's theme.
For all these activities, whether purely intellectual or
purely artistic, a special theatre with a seating capacity of
2,000 is being built in the grounds of the Fair.
In the message he sent to all the countries invited to
take part in the Exhibition, the Commissioner-General
wrote: "the harnessing of the world's sources of energy
and other material resources for man's use means increas¬
ing reliance on science. We are planning to build a large
International Palace of Science, because we feel that it is
only on an international scale that science can expand
and bear fruit as it should."
This Palace will be divided into four sections, corres¬
ponding to the fundamental bases of modern science; the
Atom (atomic physics), the Molecule (chemistry), the
Crystal (solid state physics) and the Living Cell (biology),
and it will give the visitor notably through the medium
of the cinema a general view of science's development.
The fifteen countries which have agreed to take part in
this particular enterprise will not install any national
stand in the Palace, but will contribute to a general pro¬
gramme of a purely scientific nature, so planned as to
capture the interest of the average visitor. It will be pos¬
sible for those taking part to indicate on the apparatus
they exhibit, the name" of the country of origin.
An international science committee, consisting of the
world's leading scientists, met recently in Brussels and
drew up plans for the presentation of scientific research
and apparatus.
Art panorama: prehistory to present
The same international principles are being adopted
for the Palace of Fine Arts. An international com¬
mittee, similar to the science committee, has been set
up. Works of art will not be exhibited in national sec¬
tions, but will be arranged according to the schools to
which they belong or by which they have been influenced.
Two international exhibitions, each lasting three months,
will be held in this Palace. The first (from April 18 to
July 21) will show contemporary painting and sculpture
covering the first half of the 20th century, and the second
(August 8 to November 2) will be entitled "Man and Art"
(world masterpieces from the Stone Age to the present
day). Many countries have already planned to send their
rarest collections to Belgium.
The Brussels Exhibition will be the largest international
gathering organized since the end of the war, and
Belgium is therefore sparing no
efforts to make it a true reflec¬
tion of Humanism in 1958. But
Belgium will not be alone in
having helped, by this enterprise,
to bring about greater under¬
standing between all men. Every
country officially represented will
have made its contribution. They
are all convinced that the ideal
is worth a world-wide effort, made
without restriction or reservation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
* ""3 vfltv
" I * \i
, i I I M V
i'f) r m ' ! i
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
THE ATOMIUM
Focal point
for millions
of visitors
Easily the most spectacular and unusual piece of architecture at
the World's Fair in Brussels will be the Atomium, consisting of
nine spheres representing the arrangement of atoms in an ele¬
mentary crystal of metal. Situated in the heart of the Fair, the
Atomium will be the centre of attraction for the 35 million
visitors who are expected there. This gigantic metallic construc¬
tion rising to a height of 360 feet will appear as an immense cube
resting on one of its angles, witheightspheres marking theextrem-
ities of the cube and one in the centre. The spheres, each
59 feet in diameter, will be connected to each other by tubes
10 feet in diameter equipped with escalators or travelling belts.
Every part of the remarkable structure will be open to the public.
The Atomium is symbolic of the importance to the future of the
world of knowledge relating to the structure of matter and
the peaceful uses of atomic energy. Thus, some of its spheres
large sound-proofed, thermically-insulated and air-conditioned
hallswill be used to display the peaceful uses of the atom. A
fast lift will take visitors up the central column to the top sphere
in 25 seconds. A special technical exhibition will be housed in a
circular pavilion built underneath the Atomium's base sphere.
Facings of the spheres will be in light alloy giving a brilliant
appearance. In the daytime the light casing is designed to give
off a dazzling reflection of sky, sun and clouds; at night, lights
moving around the spheres will imitate the rotation of electrons
around the nucleus of the atom.
Photos on these pages show the erection of the base of the
Atomium's central axis, a steel cylinder 50 feet high, the first
of the spheres taking shape and (last photo) the structure's
striking appearance as revealed by scale model.
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THE UNITED NATIONS PAVILION
* Mirror of the world at work
* A window on our planet's problems
by Henri Fast
Commissioner-General, U. N. and Specialized Agencies
Section, Brussels Exhibition, 1958.
CCrp he peoples of the world are soon to meet at a
I rfini-ioTvniK: with licht nnrl nfiar-.fi" These wererendezvous ith light and peace." These were
the words used by Baron Moens de Fernig, the
organizer of the 1958 International Exhibition of Brussels,
when he arrived in New York to invite the participation
of the United Nations.
Within the headquarters of the United Nations the
words rang a welcome bell for they echoed one of the
major aims of the world organization and one of the fun¬
damental goals of the Specialized Agencies which make
up the family of United Nations. Judging that the U.N.
family could not be absent from the "Balance Sheet for a
more human world" which is the theme of the Brussels
Exhibition nor from the spirit of international co-oper¬
ation that would prevail there, the United Nations has
accepted the offer to participate.
A major difficulty existed however. Although the efforts
of the United Nations family are directed toward one
common goal the ideal of world peace proclaimed in the
separate Charters of its international Agencies these
efforts embrace activities so diverse that their visual pre¬
sentation is often a complicated task.
It was therefore decided that the whole family of the
U.N. should be represented under a common theme, linked
both to the central subject of the
Brussels Exhibition, and to the
co-ordinated action of the United
Nations and its Specialized Agen¬
cies in fostering and developing
co-operation between peoples.
For no true solution, except on a
truly international level, can be
found to the problems which face
mankind today and block the
road to lasting world peace.
The work of the United Nations
and its Specialized Agencies will
be presented in a special U.N.
pavilion under three sections:
first, the challenge; second, the
results achieved so far; third, the
ultimate goal.
What is this challenge?
In the world of today the
tempo of political and technical
development is rapidly increasing.
With the widening of contacts
between peoples, brought about
chiefly by modern inventions such
as the radio, the cinema and
aviation, the benefits of civiliz¬
ation are being spread at a rate
undreamed of fifty years ago.
8
The present rapid tempo, however, is inevitably attended
by a thirst for new demands, further accentuated and
increased by the world's ever-expanding population (it
will be double today's figure by the year 2000) not to
speak of certain vital human requirements which we
cannot begin to satisfy with our present volume of human
productivity.
This situation raises many problems which are both
critical and urgent.
The problems relate to every factor conditioning the life
of men and the existence of nations. They relate to the
preservation of peaceful relations between nations and
the promotion of social and economic justice, the establish¬
ment of the rule of law between men and between nations.
They relate to economic development, to food, health,
welfare, education, culture and science. They are linked
with jobs and social security, with children's needs, with
resources, productivity and consumption, with communi¬
cations and transport, assistance to less-developed coun¬
tries, with help when disaster strikes.
The role of the United Nations and its Specialized
Agencies is to provoke, encourage and develop co¬
operation between men and nations in the search for
solutions to these problems and in realizing the promise
of the UJN. Charter for "social
progress and better standards of
life in larger freedom." The Unit¬
ed Nations family embraces in
its concern and interest men and
nations the world over and it
draws together the support and
allegiance of people of all cul¬
tures, of all religious and poli¬
tical allegiances.
But what is the action, the
concrete action taken under the
United Nations system to solve
these problems?
In the political field, first, what
are the international organiza¬
tions doing for the preservation
and development of peace?
The United Nations pavilion at
the Brussels Exhibition will show
how international co-operation
has been established through the
United Nations, through the U.N.
General Assembly and its Secu¬
rity Council. It will offer as
examples of positive results
achieved the ending of the war
in Korea, in Kashmir, in Pales¬
tine. It will outline the efforts
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
to secure world disarmament and the judicial procedure
for the peaceful settlement of conflicts, successfully
applied by the International Court of the Hague.
The U. N. pavilion will also illustrate the problems and
efforts connected with the establishment of a true com¬
munity of nations: economic development, particularly
through technical assistance ; technological exchanges
(including the peaceful uses of atomic energy); the trus¬
teeship system ; and the possibilities of advancement
given to non-self-governing territories.
A substantial portion of the U.N. pavilion will be devoted
to the measures taken to solve two problems of the utmost
importance both for the world of today and of tomorrow:
the development of the world's resources, and social deve¬
lopment. It is here that the predominant role of the
Specialized Agencies' activities will be emphasized.
The development of the world's resources concerns the
whole of the United Nations family in varying degrees.
But certain agencies have a specialized competence in
this sphere and their activities are particularly oriented
to aspects of the problem.
The development of the world's resources encompasses
three different fields. First, communications and trans¬
port, dealt with by the International Civil
Aviation Organization, the Universal
Postal Union, the World Meteorological
Organization and the International Tele¬
communication Union. Then, agricul¬
ture, resources of the sea, and forestry,
dealt with by the Food and Agriculture
Organization and by Unesco in its broad
Arid Lands programme. Finally, indus¬
trial development, water resources, electric
and hydraulic power production (includ¬
ing problems of financing) are dealt with
by several Specialized Agencies, particu¬
larly the International Bank for Recon¬
struction and Development whose invest¬
ments in dam construction now exceed
300 million dollars.
In the field of social development, the
action of the United Nations could be
divided, somewhat arbitrarily perhaps,
into four categories: Education, culture
and science are Unesco's prime interest;
health and welfare the World Health Orga¬
nization's; labour and social security the
International Labour Organization's; and
community development with which both
the United Nations and most of the
Specialized Agencies are concerned.
Other U.N. agencies are in search of solutions to one or
several of the problems indicated above. Thus the Inter¬
national Monetary Fund plays an important part in the
stabilization of currency; GATT (General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade) is working to reduce customs barriers;
and the new International Atomic Energy Agency will deal
with problems of the peaceful uses of atomic energy.
The purely humanitarian aspects of the work of the
U.N. family will of course not be overlooked, and the Office
of the High Commissioner for Refugees, the United
Nations Children's Fund, and. the agency for Arab refu¬
gees from Palestine will all have their place in the U.N.
pavilion at Brussels.
In presenting all these activities in stressing all the
collective efforts made to solve the problems of the modern
world, in demonstrating international co-operation in
the family of the United Nations hopes to promote
action and the interdependence of all peoples and nations
and extend international co-operation and mutual under¬
standing between men ultimately leading to a greater
wellbeing of mankind and the safeguarding of peace itself.
Only in an atmosphere of peaceful relations among the
peoples and nations of the world can the ideals of the
United Nations Charter really be fulfilled. International
co-operation can establish that climate which is indis¬
pensable if mankind is to achieve the twin goals of moral
and material wellbeing which now lie within its grasp.
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
To demonstrate its activities the U.N. will avail itself of
the most varied and ultra-modern techniques for its
pavilion. Of course such old stand-bys as the photogra¬
phic display and panels will not be entirely discarded,
but visitors will be able to study a miniature dam in full
operation, a large model of the U.N. General Assembly
Hall, a special presentation of air traffic control across
the North Atlantic, an "Atlas" of the clouds showing how
they influence weather forecasts, an unusual represen¬
tation of the interaction and mutual influence of Oriental
and Occidental cultures, as well as a series of other
exhibits.
Perhaps one of the most striking exhibits will be the
one depicting the vast programme launched by the United
Nations, and especially the International Labour Orga¬
nization, to improve the conditions of the Indians living
on the high plateau of the South American Andes.
To mark the U.N.'s participation in the Brussels Exhi¬
bition, a special series of 15 or 16 stamps (total value:
equivalent of two dollars) will be placed on sale in
the United Nations pavilion. Under a special arrangement
with the Belgian Government and by courtesy of the
Belgian postal authorities, the stamps will be valid for
letters posted inside the pavilion where an official post-
office will be installed. Philatelists interested in these
stamps (the issue will be fairly small) will have an oppor¬
tunity to purchase them by mail probably from February
1958 onwards.
A non-profit association has been set up to handle all
material arrangements for the U.N. family pavilion. Its
chairman is the former director of the International
Monetary Fund, C. Gutt (now Minister of State in the
Belgian Government). The president of the Belgian
National Commission for Unesco, Jean Baugniet, and the
Belgian delegate to the World Bank, H. Ansiaux, are mem¬
bers of the directorial board.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ENTIRE 'UNITED
NATIONS FAMILY'
10
c" n ' ' .:' rjv- y ..¡VV.
fi}&¿ V *'.**,
\*$0. \ \
¿&M
: V*
?ii: ilia
"1
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
As visitors to the 1958 World's Fair in Brussels
enter the 500-acre international city by the
"World Gate" they will see, on the far side of
the group of buildings erected by International
organizations, the pavilion (a giant cupola) which
houses the United Nations "Family". Here under
one roof they will see how the U.N. and its Specia¬
lized Agencies are meeting the challenge of today's
world problems.
Plan of pavilion shows (2 to 12) the ramp which
runs around half the cupola with (4)ornamental pools.
Three stands (43,43b and 40) will present Unesco's
activities and in addition special emphasis will be
given to Unesco's Arid Lands Programme (31a
to 3 Id and 59): its world action for education (41)
and its Human Rights Programme (43a).
7, 8, 9 and I I: The United Nations
13 and 15: International Civil Aviation Organiza¬
tion (ICAO)
15b and 16: Universal Postal Union (UPU)
17, 17a and 17b: World Meteorological Organiza¬
tion (WMO), International Telecommunication Union
(ITU)
26 to 3 I : Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
32: Model of a dam financed by the Internation¬
al Bank for Reconstruction and Development;
International Finance Corporation
34: International Monetary Fund
34a: General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade
(GATT)International Trade Organization (ITO)
33: Technical Assistance, the U. N. Economic
Commissions, International Atomic Energy Agency
35, 36, 37: Programme of the High Andean Plateau
42: World Health Organization (WHO)
23, 24, 25 and 33 adjoining: United Nations
Children's Fund (UNICEF); Office of the U.N. High
Commissioner for Refugees; U.N. Relief and Works
Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East
(UNRWA)
38 and 39: International Labour Org. (ILO)
43c: The United Nations Charter
44: The U.N. Post Office
51: Information Office for the "U.N. Family"
47, 48, 49 and 52: Sales of documents, books
and publications concerning the United Nations
All other numbers indicate information panels or
decorative motifs such as the atomic symbol (3 and 5).
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
U.N. PAVILION (Continued)
45 34 46 33 57.58 14 31) 31a 17 I
UNDER THE ROOF AN ATLAS 'OF THE CLOUDS'
47.48.49
Three architect's sketches showing how Interior of the U.N. Pavillion at the Brussel's World Fair will look wnen
completed. Display devices depicting varied activities of the U.N. and its Specialized Agencies will include a miniature
dam In full operation, an "Atlas of the Clouds " explaining how they influence weather forecasts, a presentation of air
traffic control across the North Atlantic and a large model of the U.N. Assembly Hall. Numbers on drawings cor¬
respond to those on plan published on previous pages, showing disposition of U.N. and Specialized Agencies'stands.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
HUMANISM FOR
A MODERN WORLD
The 1958 Brussels International Exhibition is opening
its doors wide to the interests of Humanism, taking
as its major theme, service to mankind. It also
seeks to present a complete balance sheet of this
prodigious era, and to provide a new approach to human
activity for a better world. Its theme also stresses the
increasingly urgent need for all men to know and to
understand each other better.
So far so good. No one could find fault with such
commendable aims. But the word Humanism, while not
equivocal in itself is, to say the least, polyvalent a
somewhat abstract term which can be construed in many
ways. Where does Humanism begin? And what is a
Humanist? Over a long period of time the term had a
very concrete meaning. Humanism implied classical
knowledge, a well defined branch of learning: that form
of intellectual attainment which, in particular, is impart¬
ed by the study of Latin and Greek. Thus, the typical
Humanist was a cultured man and a scholar, the gentleman
who knew his classics and could quote his references in
Greek or Latin.
Traditional Humanism is also almost automatically
associated with the Renaissance, with the discovery of
the world of the Ancients and of all its culture, which
the mystical and scholastically-mind-
ed Middle Ages does not seem truly
to have known, despite its learned
men, theologians and abstract specu¬
lators on the essence of things. Ron-
sard, so deeply inspired by Greece, is
a Humanist. But so is Erasmus and
in his case more comes into play than
form alone, more than the admiration
which his doctrines may arouse.
Here we already have a feeling of a
certain individualism, which has since
become .known as "the human dimen¬
sion" that which is measurable by
and within the grasp of man.
But is it within the terms of this definition certainly
valid and even noble, yet nonetheless somewhat narrow
that the Brussels Exhibition has sought inspiration for
its theme to illustrate the spirit which it hopes will emerge
from this meeting of nations, civilizations and cultures.
The ambition has been at once less abstract and yet,
in essence, more far-reaching. It is to highlight the most
significant characteristics of our times, and show that
the period of amazing expansion in which we live must
not blind us to, and less still make us disregard, the
part played in it by Man by each and everyone of us.
The aim too is to show what must be done or attempted
in order that our modern world, our increasingly col¬
lective and technological civilization, shall bear the stamp
of the primacy of the human being, and of "'the human
dimension".
No one can deny that ours is a prodigious era. Have
we not, in one century, made greater progress than in
the entire period of historical and prehistorical times
which preceded it? Of the past hundred years, a mere
speck on the page of time, the last twenty-five have been
the richest in discoveries which are transforming our
ways of life and the very basis of man's estate.
This dynamic and seething growth, this greatly acceler¬
ated conquest of knowledge and the expansion which
derives from them in every field, are evident to everyone.
All around us we see the effects of this growth, in our
daily existence, in our family and professional lives.
The expansion which overshadows all others and in
large measure determines them is the one expressed by
the demographic curve. In one century the population
of the globe has more than doubled. Within twenty-five
years it may well have increased by another 1,000 million.
It may reach or even exceed four and a half thousand
millions within one hundred years. This eruptive in
crease in the population of our planet obviously creates
a corresponding increase in needs of every kind. On the
world-wide scale our only scale of measurement possible
today the provision of food, clothing, and housing
presents enormous problems which scientific progress and
the growth of technical skills alone can solve.
The face of the world is changing literally before our
very eyes. Its most stable elements, once considered as
traditional, are disintegrating. Others are striving to
establish themselves. Peoples which for centuries have
slumbered, are now awakening. The demand for social
progress now universally echoed has aroused a desire for
independence which has sometimes assumed the form of
virulent nationalism.
But if demographic expansion and that of the needs
which it carries with it may be considered as the most
determining forces of the political and social changes
which we are now witnessing, they still only bring about
these changes through the equally irresistible growth of
human genius, expressed through inventions and discov¬
eries in sciences and technical skills.
Would the tremendous demographic expansion which
marks our times have been possible, for example, had
medical skill and hygiene not stepped in to arrest
infantile mortality and increase the
average life-span all over the world.
It is also through science, through the
organization of the exchange of goods,
Oy through the expanding media of com
munication and information, through
/ nmhlllinffp better techniques, methods of organi
zation and productivity, that man¬
kind can hope to find a positive ans-
byntheses, an in- wer tQ its gigantiC( growing needs.
And how vast is the potential for
progress in every field and in every
direction. We have reached a point
where we can no longer decide whe¬
ther to place our era under the sign of the discovery of
atomic energy, or under that of electronics and automa¬
tion, which soon will be entering more and more fields.
True, a gap still exists between resources and needs. Too
many people are still under-nourished. But we do know
that this gap can be bridged. Natural sources do exist
and human genius has already given sufficient proof, in
science and in technical skills, of its ability to multiply
still further the resources indispensable for the future.
The world has entered upon a phase which cries out for
and demands the co-operation of all men in every field of
endeavour. Not because co-operation, is, of itself, a great
and noble concept, but because it provides the only access
to such technical equipment as will ensure balanced
production for all peoples and the higher standards of
living to which they rightfully aspire.
Science, moreover, is increasingly revealing itself as the
birth-right of all mankind, a birthright to which neither
nations nor groups nor indeed scientists themselves can
for long claim exclusive rights and privileges.
By the very nature of the goals it sets in terms of
productivity and the fantastic resources it requires,
modern technology accentuates with each day that passes
the collective character of modern life. Our era is fast
leaving behind the day of the small craftsman and is
producing in its stead a "technicist and herd civilization".
It would be futile to attempt to oppose such a trend
the imperatives of which are all too obvious. And it
would be unjust to condemn it in advance and to consider
the hive-and-herd character of our times from a solely
critical point of view. The gradual rise in a
standards oí living, the decrease of individual Cont'd
physical efforts, the fading of age-old fears I
bred by hunger and disease (a relief not yet next pa£e
afforded to all peoples unfortunately) all I
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
HUMANISM
FOR TODAY
(Continued)
are, on the whole, definite factors of human progress and
new openings for individual and collective development.
This evolution (I believe it essential that all its charac¬
teristics be fully grasped) poses multiple problems which
affect man and the humanizing element of man directly.
Neither the equipment of industry nor the development
and modernization of technical methods to meet the
need of our expanding human race can be achieved by
the old methods applied up until now. At any rate they
cannot be applied in a short enough space of time to
count. A stage of planning and of co-operation at all
levels and in every branch of human activity is hence
essential. Certain phases of this co-operation have al¬
ready been carried out by many international organiz¬
ations during the past years.
But 'this undeniable and urgent need for close co¬
operation requires in turn more favourable moral and
intellectual exchanges between men and between nations.
These must get to know each other better before they
can hope to achieve better understanding. This is one of
the motivating concepts of the Brussels Exhibition.
The increasingly collective character of this "technicist
and herd civilization" which is spreading to all peoples
irrespective of historical or religious background further
implies an increased solidarity between men and increas¬
ed solidarity between the communities which they form.
The close relationship between this feeling of individual
responsibility and one of dignity is well established.
In fact that relationship opens up one of the avenues
towards a Humanism which may perhaps be termed
Empirical, and to which the 1958 Brussels Exhibition will
give particular emphasis. The vigour of this empirical
Humanism will in no way be diminished nor will it clash
with the most traditional forms of culture. On the
contrary, it will add a new dimension by directly linking
these cultural forms to our daily life.
A leading place will be accorded to the arts, to letters
and to science. Not only will the full sweep of human
progress down the ages be delineated, but the deep-rooted
kinship which unites mankind and has united it through¬
out history will probably be a revelation to many people.
From the new perspectives and trends already taking
shape and clearly emerging today, a new lesson is coming
to the fore: the importance now assumed by all those
values connected with the inner being which make man
really human. For the true sources of knowledge and
human creativeness are born within the individual, even if
the means of translating them into action and of giving
them body later develop in a collective group. The source
of all advancement, of all spiritual development is inner
inspiration. Moreover these high concepts must be lived.
Thus on a broad canvas and with generous strokes of
the brush, may be portrayed some of the outlines not,
indeed, of a new Humanism, but of an evergrowing
concern with the defence and safe-guarding of the most
authentically human qualities of each one of us.
In planning the Brussels Exhibition it was felt that
there was a duty to set forth, to the greatest extent
possible, the most striking characteristics of our era, so
that millions of people might have an inkling of the
many educational and cultural paths which can reinforce
the individual and human aspect within a civilization
dominated both by the technological and group-conscious.
The man of tomorrow can look forward to much from
a civilization of this kind provided he demands and
achieves the primacy of the human element.
14
' A -
q**W ' M^U V*
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
METEOROLOGY IN THE ATOMIC AGE
TWO PROBLEMS :
* Protection against
radio - active contamination
of the air
* Using atomic tracers
to study atmospheric
phenomena
There are certain aspects of the
utilization of atomic energy
which recently have received in¬
creasing public attention: firstly to
what extent the use of radio-active
substances can contribute towards the
solution of certain fundamental prob¬
lems in meteorology and secondly
the role which the meteorologist can
play in the "atomic age", for instance
in connexion with the work of safe¬
guarding the public against dangerous
contamination of the atmosphere due
to radio-active substances produced
by atomic plants.
It should be pointed out in the first
instance that the possibility of using
certain radio-active substances (iso¬
topes) in meteorological research, and
also in the closely related hydrological
research, is still in its experimental
stage. The research-projects men¬
tioned below should therefore not be
regarded as exhaustive, but rather as
examples of those possibilities which
at present look most promising.
One of the research projects which
particularly appeals to people's imagi¬
nation is the possible use oí a radio¬
active substance as a tracer to study
air currents in the atmosphere. The
main idea is to give the air current
a strong "injection" with a suitable
16
harmless radio-active substance, pre¬
ferably a gas, and subsequently study
the transport and dilution of the
radio-active gas in the atmosphere.
It has been suggested that this
method would be useful for the study
of the remarkably strong jet stream
which frequently exists at a height
oí 8 to 12 kilometres and which has
considerable importance in connexion
with the safety and economy of air¬
craft operation.
A large-scale experiment of this
type would require considerable pre¬
paration, not only to determine where
in the atmosphere it would be most
advantageous to release the radio¬
active gas, and at what time, but also
with regard to the choice of a radio¬
active tracer. This should have a
hali-life (1) of several years and it
should not be liable to be washed out
by precipitation.
Furthermore a world-wide network
of observing stations would have to be
organized and these should be in op¬
eration over a period of some years.
The first attempt would need to be
successful, for if it iailed, a second
trial could only take place after sever¬
al years, when the radio-activity of
(1) The time In which radlo-actlvlty Is
reduced to half.
the introduced tracer had diminished
sufficiently unless other and equally
good tracers were available.
Other possible uses of isotopes exist
due to the fact that radio-active
tritium can be used to "mark" water
vapour molecules without changing
their characteristics. Since water
vapour is an important link in the
hydrological cycle, there are reasons
to believe that the use of such tech¬
niques may be of importance, parti¬
cularly in hydrology. A similar me¬
thod has been employed in studying
the source of origin and movements
aï various types of surface water.
A third example is the use of radio¬
active measuring techniques to deter¬
mine the water equivalent of snow.
For various purposes, e.g. in con¬
nexion with the forecasting of river
floods and runoff, it is necessary to
know as accurately as possible the
water equivalent of the snow accu¬
mulated in a certain area in winter.
It has been suggested that the water
equivalent oí snow can be measured
with considerably greater ease than
with the present methods, by placing
a suitable radio-active substance at
the earth's surface below the snow,
and measuring the attenuation of the
radiation passing through the snow
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
layer. This method has already been
introduced on a trial basis at several
stations in the United States.
With regard to the second aspect of
the peaceful uses of atomic energy
the contamination of the atmosphere
is a field where the advice and
assistance of meteorologists would
be very useful indeed. Fortunately,
one of the characteristics of the
atmosphere is its ability to clean
itself, but this ability to dilute or
disperse "foreign" gases or particles is
limited, and varies with the season,
the time and geographical position.
The winter fog over London for in¬
stance or the common smoke-layer
over a great number of cities in the
morning always appears when the
conditions and movement of the
atmosphere are such that it does not
succeed in dispersing the contaminat¬
ing particles sufficiently rapidly.
The "waste-products" which certain
atomic plants are releasing into the
atmosphere may be several tens of
times more toxic than the waste-pro¬
ducts released from chimneys belong¬
ing to ordinary industry. It is there¬
fore of vital importance to find quan¬
titative expression for the relationship
between changes in the diluting abi¬
lity of the atmosphere and the result¬
ing concentration of radio-activity in
the air and on the ground.
This is a complicated problem, the
solution of which is mainly dependent
on accurate knowledge of wind and
temperature gradients and their
variations, horizontally, vertically and
with time. The topographical condi¬
tions around the atomic plant may
also play an important role in these
calculations.
The scope and type of assistance to
be given by the meteorologists in con¬
nexion with the establishment and
operation of industries based on atom¬
ic energy will naturally depend on
the site and size of the plant, and par
ticularly on the extent to which its
radio-active waste-products are ex¬
pected to contaminate the atmosphere.
It seems superfluous to point out that
the advice of the meteorologist should
preferably be obtained before the final
site for the atomic plant has been
agreed upon, unless other factors are
of greater importance.
Certain atomic plants may require a
permanent network of meteorological
stations which will have to undertake
frequent and regular observations.
These observations will be of impor¬
tance in ensuring that the operation
of the atomic plant at no time consti¬
tutes a risk for the population.
Neither the meteorologist nor the
atom-physicist should work indepen¬
dently on these problems. The nu¬
clear-physicists, chemists or engineers
will provide all information about the
source of the problems; amount, na¬
ture and properties of the radio-active
waste-products. The health physicist
will determine the permissible concen¬
tration of radio-activity in the air and
on the ground, and also the maximum
permissible doses of radiation. Taking
this information as a basis, the meteo¬
rologist will advise on the meteorolo¬
gical conditions which may lead to
concentrations of radiation exceeding
the permissible limits.
Both the health physicist and the
meteorologist will require a network
of observing stations to solve his part
of the task. As mentioned earlier, cer¬
tain meteorological research projects
are also dependent on a world-wide
network of observing stations. There
seems, therefore, to be some merit in
ensuring that the various measure¬
ments required for different purposes
are made at the same stations.
For health purposes, it is of the
greatest importance to measure the
total radio-activity due to air-borne
radio-active particles deposited on the
ground.
Tho Unesco Courier. July 1957
The meteorologist will, however, re¬
quire the following two types of radio¬
activity measurement: (a) at the
earth's surface; (b) in the free atmo¬
sphere.
The first of these will consist of
samples of radio-activity of rain water
and of measurements of radio-activity
of the air at the earth's surface by
means of a suitable filter (2). The se¬
cond type of observation is designed to
permit study of the vertical distribu¬
tion of radio-activity in the atmo¬
sphere, and requires relatively expen¬
sive equipment. Such observations
may consist of "filter" measurements
from aircraft or measurements made
by means of sounding balloons. The
latter method is still in an experimen¬
tal stage and is not considered as
sufficiently reliable.
It should be emphasized that the
establishment of stations for the
observation of radio-activity is closely
related to the peaceful uses of atomic
energy and a number of countries
have already set up such stations or
are in the course of doing so.
Steps to improve the world network
of stations for measuring radio-acti¬
vity to organize their programme of
observation and the collection of the
data are being taken in connexion with
the forthcoming International Geo¬
physical Year and it is believed that
this initiative will lead to a still closer
scientific co-operation between na¬
tions in this important field.
Whether we approve of the use of
atomic energy or not, the only course
open to us seems to be to prepare
ourselves in the best possible way to
use this new form of energy. In this
connexion the meteorologist should
accept his share of the work and of
the responsibility.
(2) The radio-activity of the filter Is mea¬
sured after a known amount of air has been
drawn through it.
RADIO-ACTIVE ISOTOPES are
today being considered for use in
meteorological research as "tracers'*
to study air currents in the atmo¬
sphere. Such substances are already
widely employed in medicine, agri¬
culture, industry and other fields.
Here, an industrial hygiene specialist
studies harmful airborne particles
in a factory. He counts the concen¬
tration of dust particles by coating
them with a radio-active substance
(metallic selenium). This research,
which includes testing the toxicity
of dusts on animals, is one type of
work performed by the Atomic
Energy Project at the University
of Rochester, in the United States.
SMOKE PLUMES coming from a
tower at U.S. laboratory, (opposite
page) enable meteorologists to
dermine the right weather condi¬
tions for releasing into the atmo¬
sphere air which has been used to
cool the laboratory's atomic reactor.
USIS Photos
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Chinese gets
a Latin alphabet
by Chou You-Kuang
Beginning this autumn, some of the
fifty million children in China's
primary schools will start learn¬
ing a new phonetic alphabet using
Latin letters. They will not stop
learning the traditional characters.
For the time being, both will be
taught simultaneously. This is a pre¬
liminary step in the big programme
to change China's written language
from a set oí ideographs to one in
which the words are "spelled out" in
letters denoting sounds.
Up until now students of Chinese
have faced the task of mastering over
3,500 separate characters before they
could read a newspaper or a simple
novel. Each character is made up of
anything from two to thirty strokes.
Besides recognizing what it means,
one has to learn how to pronounce
each one separately. There is no
correct indication of sound in the
character itseli. To reach university
level, it has been necessary to acquire
at least five or six thousand such
symbols. Even this is not a sufficient
key to the great treasure-house
of China's classical literature to
understand the writing of the past, a
scholar may need to recognize at least
10,000 characters.
Now the first big step has been
taken toward a change. Eventually
how soon it is not possible to say, for
we are dealing with a gigantic process
with many complications the Chinese
school child, after mastering 26 letters
and their sounds, will be able to
recognize and pronounce all the words
he knows. He will be doubly fortunate
because he will learn a spelling system
that is being worked out scientifically.
There will be iewer irregularities of
spelling such as exist in languages
whose orthography has grown up by
accidents of history, like English.
The need for such a reform has long
been recognized. To transform China
from a backward country into an
advanced industrialized one demands
the rapid education of the whole
people, and the wiping out of illiter-
racy. At present, simply to learn to
read takes months or years aï time.
The characters also run counter to
the needs of modern techniques
and communication. In the printing
press, types are set by hand. Chinese
typewriters exist but they are slow
and clumsy. In telegraphing, every
character must be changed into a
four-number code, which then has to
be deciphered at the other end a
great hindrance, among other things,
to journalism in these days of split-
second news reporting. Dictionaries
are arranged in several different ways,
18
none of them simple or quick. There
is no satisfactory method of indexing
records or everyday reference works
directories, yearbooks, encyclopaedias
and so on.
For the last sixty years, Chinese
scholars have tried to devise and
promote new systems of writing. The
adoption of the new alphabet by the
State Council was preceded by a
whole year of public discussion
of a drait scheme, prepared by the
Committee for Reforming the Chinese
Script. Over 10,000 language experts
and teachers took part in special
conferences organized by local and
national committees. More than 4,000
letters of suggestion and comment
were sent in, including many from
Chinese living abroad and from
philologists.
Finally, two alternative revised
versions were worked out and these,
together with the original draft and
three other proposed schemes, were
submitted to a special government
committee. The first revised scheme
finally won the approbation of 136
out of the 234 experts who took part
in the study. This was the basis of
the State Council's decision.
Why * was the Latin alphabet
preferred to others? The
reason was that, though not
entirely appropriate for reproducing
all Chinese sounds, it is the most
widely known one in the world.
More than 60 countries now use it,
including the majority of those in
Europe, the Americas and Southeast
Asia. Its letters are internationally
employed as symbols in mathematics
and natural science. Mastery of it
will permit Chinese people to learn
other languages more easily. Its use
will make Chinese more accessible to
foreigners.
Moreover, attempts to use the Latin
script to write Chinese have a long
history. The first was made by an
early Christian missionary scholar,
the Italian Jesuit Matteo Ricci, in the
year 1604. After the Opium War of
1840 more missionaries flooded into
China, and between 1847 and 1893
they "romanized" the sounds of. at
least 17 regional dialects for conveni¬
ence in translating the Bible. 'With
the development of foreign trade and
contacts, names ai places and persons
had to be given some form of spelling
for use in shipping documents, the
post office and the press abroad.
Among the methods devised by
foreigners for spelling the official
"Mandarin" language, the most widely
used was the "Wade system", publish¬
ed in 1867 by the British sinologist
Thomas F. Wade. This is still used in
the Chinese post oifice, and for
rendering Chinese characters in
English maps, dictionaries and so
forth, but no attempt was ever made
actually to write Chinese in it.
Following the short-lived "reform
movement" in the 1890's, during the
last period of the Manchu dynasty,
Chinese scholars began to study the
possibility of introducing the Latin
alphabet for the language. They
devised a number of different systems.
But at that time the majority 'favour¬
ed the adoption of simplified Chinese
characters. After the overthrow of
the Manchu dynasty, a set of 40 new
symbols, based on Chinese characters
and known as the Chu-Yin Tzu-Mu
(Phonetic Alphabet) was ratified by
the government of the day, in 1918.
Up to now these signs have been
printed alongside the characters in
dictionaries and primary school text¬
books to help the students pronounce
the words. Though it provides ade¬
quate symbols for the various sounds
of the language, these are incon¬
venient for reading and writing. The
symbols cannot be joined together in
a flowing script. They would be hard
to adapt for typewriting, typesetting
and telegraphy.
After May 4, 1919, intellectuals
began to consider more seriously the
problem of the reform of the written
language. They knew that popular
education and literature could not
flourish unless the gap between
the written and spoken word was
overcome. They stood for the use oí
everyday speech in writing, instead of
the antique classical style employed
till then in literary prose and poetry,
letter-writing and even the press.
For some years attention was centered
on writing the spoken language with
the old characters. By 1926, a group
of progressive philologists came to¬
gether to make research into ways of
writing Chinese phonetically and
brought out a scheme called Gwoyeu
Romatzyh (Chinese Romanization).
But this did not gain wide popularity.
The most successful and vigorous
efforts to introduce a phonetic alpha¬
bet in this period began in the late
1930's. Impressed by the successful
use of such scripts to provide written
languages and wipe out illiteracy
among some of the minorities in the
Soviet Union, a group of Chinese
revolutionaries, led by the Communist
writer Chu Chiu-pai, set to work in
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
Evolution of the Chinese character ma, meaning "horse".
1928 to devise a phonetic system ior
China. This was introduced in 1933
under the name of Latinxua Sin Wem
(New Latinized Writing). The follow¬
ing year saw the beginning of the
National Salvation Movement against
Japanese Invasion. In this movement
the Latinxua system took hold, and
was widely used.
In the following years, a number of
Latinxua associations were organized
in places like Shanghai, Canton,
Hankow and Hong Kong. Newspapers
and periodicals published articles to
promote it, and textbooks and other
materials were produced. During the
Anti-Japanese War it was taught to
the people of the Yenan area (the
Shensi-Kansu-Ninghsia Border Re¬
gion). It also caught on in the areas
of national resistance founded behind
the Japanese lines in north- and
northeast China and elsewhere, where
soldiers and people learned its use.
Following the deieat of Japan in
1945, the work of spreading the alpha¬
bet lapsed for a while. But those who
had learned the Latin alphabet did
not forget itfor instance, it was
recently found that in one county in
Hopei province, practically all middle-
aged men and women still knew how
to write in it. It continues to be used
for transmitting service telegrams on
all railways in Northeast China.
But even with the Latin alphabet,
there is still a lot to be done
beiore it becomes a workable method
of writing Chinese. One necessary
step already under way for some
time is to popularize what is called
"the common speech", the standard
Peking pronunciation. China has a
number of dialects and people from
different areas often find it difficult
to communicate with one another
orally (though they use the same
written language). To help them
learn a common language in addition
to their own dialect is desirable in
itself; it is essential if a phonetic
language is to succeed. Primary
school teachers and workers in other
educational fields all over the country
are now studying the standard
pronunciation. Radio, theatre and
cinema are popularizing it among the
people at large.
On the technical side, there are
still a number of unsolved prob-
blems concerning such matters
as spelling. Philologists have started
to study the homophones (words dif¬
ferent in meaning but the same in
sound) in the Chinese language so as
to work out a way for distinguishing
between them when written. For
instance fâ %. meaning a tree and
$fc ê] meaning a number are both
pronounced shumu. However, this is
not a very serious difficulty because,
when the words are printed in context,
confusion between them is unlikely.
Clear identification may be facilitated
by varying the spelling or inserting
hyphens in some words.
Another question is how to put
words together. Each Chinese cha¬
racter represents a separate syllable
and may stand by itself or be com¬
bined with one or several others to
form a word. For instance, the word
for a chicken consists oí two charac¬
ters, written ,]-«í% (hiau gi). Shall
it be written as one word or two?
And how shall we spell out numerals
and measurements? The characters
	f'-S-lf^-hiL W kian san
bai liu shi wu) mean one thousand
three hundred and sixty-five. Should
they be run together jikiansanbailiu-
shiwu, or combined by numbers and
units: jikian, meaning one thousand;
sanbai, three hundred; and so on?
These and similar problems, such as
the writing of Chinese versions of
foreign place names, will be settled
through study and trial. Only when
all are solved and the new practice
has won the assent of the public will
it be possible to say that a new
phonetic written language actually
exists. Only then will the new script
be recognized as a standard method
of writing, alongside the old charac¬
ter-method.
Even after the phonetic language
becomes universal for ordinary pur¬
poses, middle school and university
students will continue to study the
traditional Chinese characters, just as
some in Britain and France study
Latin and Greek. At present most
students who have reached university
level can only read works in the
modern literary style, or pai hua
common speech. Those specializing
in history, the Chinese language, and
literature will continue to study wen
yen, or the classical style, which is
widely different.
At the same time the classics will
be translated into plain modern lang¬
uage. This is already being done,
and later they will be transliterated
in the phonetic alphabet. So China's
ancient culture will not be buried.
On the contrary it will be brought
within reach of the whole people for
the first time in our history.
CHOU YOU-KUANG is a member of
the National Committee for the Popu¬
larization of Standard Spoken Chinese,
and also heads the Phonetic Research
Department of the Committee for the
Reform of the Chinese Written Language.
FOUR WAYS OF WRITING A CHINESE SENTENCE
Ideographs:
Wade system (1867):
Chu-in Tzu-mu (1919):
New phonetic
alphabet (1957):
English meaning:
T'ui-kuang p'u-t'ung-hua; chu-pu
*X\«X*. &X¿X¿rXY; 4X-Í7X
Tuiguang putunghua; zhubu
Popularize the "common speech"; gradually
&m #-!- itio
tsai-yung p'in-yin wên-tzù.
caiyng pinjin wenzi.
begin using the phonetic alphabet.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
FRANCE'S GIANT MACHINE
ON 'BIG WIND' HILL
EXPERIMENTAL WINDMILL which will be used for wind energy
research in Algeria. Built in England under French licence the machine
is one of the largest of its kind (its rotor is 80 feet in diameter). Total
annual energy from the generator It will drive is expected to be about
200,000 kilowatt hours. Photos show It being assembled in England.
by E. W. Golding
In this age of rapidly increasing mechanization for
almost every job originally done by man or his
working animals, power and development have become
Inseparably linked. To have an abundance of power is
to have means of development towards that better way
of life which is the legitimate aim of all peoples.
But from whence is this power to be provided? From
the so-called "fossil fuels"coal, oil or, perhaps, natural
gas but these are being exhausted at an ever-increasing
rate which has already achieved an alarming figure in
relation to the known world resources of such fuels.
Again, their distribution is extremely uneven; some coun¬
tries have an abundance of coal, some large reserves of
oil, but others have neither of these natural riches. Nor
have they always the means of importing them in suffi¬
cient quantity to serve as a basis for development.
Nuclear energy is coming to the fore so quickly in some
of the more technically-advanced countries that their
anxiety for the future of power supplies through fossil
fuels may be largely relieved, but both the technical and
economic problems involved in this new method are such
that it would be wrong to assume that nuclear energy will
overcome all the difficulties of power supply, for the world,
in the near future.
In some parts of the world it is possible to utilize "geo-
thermal" energy, i.e., energy obtained from the internal
heat of the earth, but special geological formations are
needed for this to be economical.
What are the other possibilities for power production?
They are the inexhaustible energy resources which consti¬
tute the world's annual energy incomeas distinct from
the energy capital, in the form of fuels, which is being
exhausted at such a high rate. These resources are water
from rivers and mountain lakes, the winds, solar radia¬
tion, and, in some regions, the energy from the tides, from
sea waves or that obtainable from the differences which
exist between the temperature of the water deep down in
the sea and that at the surfaceone of the other effects
of solar radiation.
Of these possibilities, water power is already providing
a major contribution to our energy supplies. In fact, it
is being exploited on such a large scale in North America,
Scandinavia and Western Europe that, in some areas, few
economic schemes remain for future development, but
there are great untouched sources of water power in
Africa, Asia and South America. These, undoubtedly, will
be used sooner or later but there are serious difficulties in
that the cost of building hydro-electric schemes is very
large and is often beyond the financial means of the
. countries concerned.
The locations of these schemes also are often far distant
from the centres of population where the power could be
used so that heavy costs would be involved in transmitting
the power to the users. Less serious, but still important,
difficulties arise, again, from the uneven distribution of
water power between countries and from its irregular
availabilityeither because of lack of rainfall in some
years or, seasonally, because of the water being ice-bound
in the high mountain lakes.
The other inexhaustible energy resources, vast though
they are in total, have so far been used for power pro¬
duction only to a very slight extent but their potentialities
are now being recognized and, encouraged by the new
technique of manufacture, and new materials, which have
been introduced during recent years, very considerable
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
efforts in research and development, all over the world,
are now being applied towards the perfection of machines
and operating methods for their exploitation.
As with water power, but in a rather greater degree,
these resources are irregular in recurrence; the wind
blows, or dies away, with no very certain pattern; the sun
shines with rather more certainty but only in the day
time; tidal power is usable at varying times of the day
at certain places where the conformation of the coast is
favourable, and so on. Because of the lightness of the
air for wind power purposes and the "thin" distribution
of solar radiation over the ground, machines to capture
the energy on a significant scale have to be large, and
unless designed and built with care and ingenuity, tend
to be expensive.
These unconventional energy sources of wind and sun¬
shine have, however, important advantages they are
widespread and are freely avail¬
able at many places where power
is badly needed so that questions
of power transmission are there¬
fore eliminated.
It is possible, of course, to store
energy so that a superabundance
at one time can be made to coun¬
terbalance a later deficiency.
But such storage is often ex¬
pensive and wasteful and a better
solution to the problem of effect¬
ively using random supplies of
energy is to be found in combin¬
ing that from several different
sources so that they may comple¬
ment one another.
News of an interesting experi¬
ment towards this end comes
from Algeria where the national
utility company, Electricité et
Gaz d'Algérie, is installing a
large windmill, of novel design
driving an electric generator
which will help to provide power
for the electricity network.
The demand for electric power
in Algeria has increased very ra¬
pidly in the past few years. To
meet it there are a number ai
modern power stations and also
some hydro-electric installations,
the most important being in the
Petite Kabylie region. These
power stations are linked by a transmission system which
includes a line operating at 150,000 volts, running along
the coastal region from east to west. Natural energy
resources likely to offer possibilities for exploitation are
few, with the possible exception of natural gas which was
recently discovered in the south and whose development is
now being studied.
For the past eight years, therefore, Electricité et Gaz
d'Algérie has been investigating the possibilities of wind
power which might perhaps offer a worthwhile auxiliary
to hydraulic power, though this has already been har¬
nessed by the capacity of the dams. Now the company
is to make tests with the windmill built by a British firm,
under French licence.
The site chosen for the installation of the windmill is*
a small, well-exposed hill (about 860 feet high), some six
miles from Algiers and five miles from the sea. This hill,
which has the promising name of "Big Wind", lies close
to a road and to a high tension line carrying 10,000 volts.
Extensive wind surveys in Great Britain have shown
that hills of a similar shape to this one in Algeria, espe¬
cially when near the sea, have a wind regime which is
very favourable for wind power.
Theoretically, the average annual production on this site
is about 2,000 kilowatt hours per cubic metre which would
mean that the machine could give an annual output of
energy equivalent to its running at full capacity for some
1,800 hours each year. *
The experimental wind-driven generator has a capacity
of 100 kilowatts so that the annual total of energy to be
expected from it will be about 200,000 units (kilowatt
hours). Although this is not a very large total as com¬
pared with the country's needs for energy, successful.
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
results from tests with such a machine would Indicate the
possibility of installing more, and larger ones to provide a
significant contribution of energy.
The late M. Andreau, of Paris, first expounded the novel
principle of operation followed in this new machine which
was built in Great Britain. One firm was responsible for
the project and another developed M. Andreau's ideas In
the machine's design and construction so that it is by far
the largest plant of this kind which has yet been built.
The principle can be explained as follows:
A wind-driven generator of any kind must have a rotor,
driven by the wind, and this rotation must be transmitted
to an electric generator. In other windmills the power
transmission has been through gearing to obtain, from a
slow-running rotor, the high speed which is needed for the
generator; both the gearbox and generator are usually
mounted immediately behind the windmill rotor at the
top of the tower. In the Andreau
principle the blades of the rotor
are hollow and are open at their
tips. The rotor hub and support¬
ing tower are also hollow. When
the wind causes the rotor to
rotate, air is flung out centrlfug-
ally from the tips of the blades
and a suction is created so that a
large volume of air actually, in
this machine, some 58,500 cubic
feet per minute when the wind
speed is 30 miles an hour is
drawn up the hollow tower and
through an axial-flow air turbine,
with a vertical shaft, mounted
near the bottom. The turbine
drives an a.c. generator carried
below it on the same shaft.
Although the 80 ft. diameter
rotor, which has two hinged, alu¬
minium alloy blades each weigh¬
ing 1,600 lbs., runs at only 100
revolutions per minute, the tur¬
bine and generator rotate at 1,000
r.p.m. The rotor runs downwind
of the tower. This facilitates
orientation to follow changes in
wind direction; the orientation is
power assisted and is controlled
by a wind-direction indicator
which is mounted above the front
of the hub.
The height of the hub, above
ground, is 100 feet and the steel
tower, which is supported by 12 galvanised steel cables, has
a diameter of 9 feet at the bottom and 3*5 feet in the upper
part. The weight of the complete machine is 60 tons.
Full output of 100 kilowatts will be produced by a wind
of 30 m.p.h. For higher wind speeds this same output will
be maintained by an automatic changing of the pitch of
the blades until, when the wind speed rises to 65 m.p.h.,
the blades are feathered and the rotor stops. For wind
speeds below 30 m.p.h., down to about 17 m.p.h., the ma¬
chine produces a reduced amount of power. The 3-phase
alternator, of the synchronous induction type, generates
power at 415 volts.
Advantages of the Andreau-type of wind-driven ma¬
chine are that the generating plant and control gear are
located at ground level, where they can be inspected
frequently and easily maintained, and also that the rapid
fluctuations in wind speed which commonly occur are
damped out by the very flexible drivethrough a long
column of airand so do not cause trouble by passing a
correspondingly variable power output into the network.
It will indeed be most interesting to follow this Algerian
experiment, with not only an unconventional source of
energy for the network, but with such a novel form oí
machine to capture and utilize it.
Photographs and explanations regarding the functioning of the
Andreau-type wind-driven machine referred to above figure
in the Unesco Travelling Exhibition, "Energy and its Transfor¬
mation". This Exhibition first opened in Paris in March 1956,
later visited New Delhi and Ahmedabad in India and is
now touring cities in the Far East. It has already been seen by
more than 270,000 people.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
WeBtminstur Palaoe Hotel ,
4, Victoria Street,
1 0 N D O M , W.C.
10.11.1909.
YyV
0
MAHATMA GANDHI
T*¥
Dear Sir:-
I beg to tender my thanks for your registered letter
in connection with t!;e letter addressed to a Hindu, and
with the matters that I dealt with in my letter to you.
Having heard about your failing health I refrained
in order to save you the trouble, frem sending an acknow¬
ledgment, knowing that a written expression of ray thank3
was a superfluous formality, but Mr. Aylmer Maude, whom I
have nowbbeen able to meet reassured me that you were keep¬
ing very good health indeed and that unfailingly and regu¬
larly attended to your correspondence every morning. It
was very gladsome news to me, and it encourages mé to write
to you "urther about matters which are, I know, of the
greatest importance according to your teaching.
I beg to send you herewith a copy of a book written by
a friend - an Englishman, who Is at present in South Africa,
In connection with my life, insofar as it has a mzy bearing
on the struggle with which I am so connected, and to which my
life is dedicated. As I am very anxious to engage your ac¬
tive interest and sympathy, I thought that it would not be
considered by you as out of the way for me' to send you the
book.
In my opinion, this struggl-i of the Indians in the Trans¬
vaal is the greatest of modern times, inasmuch as it has been
idealised both as to the goal as also th& methods adopted to
ree.ch the. goal. I am not aware of a struggle, in which the
participators are not to derive any personal advantage at the
en8 of it, and in which 50**¿ of the persons affected have under¬
gone great suffering and trial for the sake of a principle. It
has not feen possible for me to advertise the struggle as much
as I ahould like. You command, possibly, the widest public to¬
day. >Tf you are satisfied as to the facts you will find set
forth in Mr-. Doke's book, and if you consider thi»t the conclu¬
sions I have arrived at are Justified hy the facts, may I ask
you to use your influence in any manner you think fit to popu¬
larise the movement ? If it succeeds, it will be not only a
triumph of religion, love and truth over irreligion, hatred
and falsehood, but it is highly lilely to serve as an example
to the millions in India and to people in other parts of the .
world who may be down-trodden, and will certainly go a great
way towards breaking up the party of violence, at least in
India. If we hold out to the end, as I think we would, T en¬
tertain not the slightest doubt as to the ultimate success;
and your encouragement in the way suggested by you can only
strengthen us in our resolve.
The négociations that were going on for. a settlement of
the question hare practically fallen through, and together
with ray colleague I return to South Africa this week, and in-
rite imprisonment. I may add that my son hashappily Joined
me in this struggle, and is now undergoing imprisonment with
hard labour for sir months. This is his fourth imprisonment
in the course of the struggle.
mù*ù
rc*".*'-V>.
".-¿Ci-'viiA-,
"* vnjr A0,*-*»*«
>
«a
Is
, <i At
If y ou would to So
mcy I ask you to address
Box 653E.
reply to this letter,
to n« at Johannesburg, S.A.
Hoping that this will find you in good health, 1 remain
Your obedi ent' servant ,
ü«
PtJiÄU^**-.-*»-*!**.
Count Leo Tolstoi,
Yasna Polyana,
Russia.
* .: * «C**-?!
LEO TOLSTOY
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. 'July 1957
Tolstoy museum solves a 50-year-old mystery
THE 'LOST LETTER' OF MAHATMA GANDHI
by Alexandre Chifman
Tolstoy Museum, Moscow
The ideas of men of genius do not -wither with age. Though
nearly half a century has elapsed since the exchange of
letters between Leon Tolstoy and Gandhi, their
correspondence continues to be the subject of study in many
countries of the world. Scholars of the East as well as the
West have been drawn to the letters of these great thinkers and
have admired the profundity of judgment and the inspiring ideas
about friendship and peace between peoples expressed in them.
The Tolstoy-Gandhi correspondence was first published in
Germany in 1925 by Tolstoy's Russian friend and biographer,
Pavel Biryukov, in his book, Tolstoi und der Orient ("Tolstoy
and the Orient"). It was in this form that it subsequently became
known throughout the world.
When Romain Rolland discussed the universal cultural
influence of Tolstoy and Gandhi in his book La vie de Tolstoi,
published in 1933, he had Biryukov's edition of the
correspondence before him. So
did Stefan 'Zweig, when he wrote
about Tolstoy and Gandhi in his
Adepts in Self-Portraiture. The
same letters were published in 1939
by the Soviet review Literary
Heritage, in a special volume
devoted to Tolstoy.
Strangely enough, however,
editors and commentators in many
countries failed to notice that one
of Gandhi's most interesting letters
was missing from the collection of
fifty thousand letters received by
Tolstoy and carefully preserved in
the Leon Tolstoy archives in Moscow.
And yet this letter had undoubtedly reached Yasnaya Polyana
(the novelist's country home) and had been read by Tolstoy. A
copy preserved in India testifies to its existence, as do Tolstoy's
replies when carefully examined. But how did the letter disap¬
pear, and what happened to it? For nearly fifty years these
questions remained unanswered.
Recently, two staff members of the Yasnaya Polyana Museum,
Nicolai' Puzin and Yelena Nasselenko, were examining some old
foreign periodicals which Tolstoy had received during his lifetime
from all parts of the world. Flipping through the pages of an
English magazine of the period, they came upon a Russian
translation of one of the articles in the review, made for Tolstoy
by his daughter-in-law, O.K. Tolstaya. Underneath it lay the
"'lost letter". Tolstoy probably left Gandhi's letter there,
intending to reply to it. But on the same day he fell ill; the
magazine was taken from his study, and the letter lay hidden
for nearly fifty years. Thanks to this find, a missing link in
the correspondence between two great thinkers has now been
filled.
Gandhi wrote to Tolstoy for the first time on October 1, 1909,
from London, where he had come to negotiate with the British
Government's representatives about the position of Indians in
the Transvaal. His first message to Tolstoy was devoted to a
description of living conditions of the Indian population.
The great Russian writer was intrigued by this Indian from
faraway Transvaal who had written to him, but whom he had
never met. "'I was greatly touched by the letter from the Hindu
of Transvaal", he wrote to his friend V. Vhertkov. On Octo¬
ber 8, 1909, he sent Gandhi a friendly reply, expressing his
sincere sympathy for "our dear brothers in the Transvaal..."
He also approved Gandhi's intention to distribute among his
fellow Indians the famous article, Letter to a Hindu, which
Tolstoy had written in 1908. "I am very pleased", he wrote,
"that my letter should be translated and circulated in an Indian
language."
Tolstoy's letter of approval, reaching London at the moment
when Gandhi's negotiations had ended in failure, was a source
of great satisfaction to Gandhi, and he at once sent a second
letter to Yasnaya Polyana, in which he continued his account
of the Transvaal Indians' struggle against the local authorities.
This second letter is the famous "lost letter" which is reproduced
in full alongside.
Tolstoy was ill and did not reply, though he had been
interested by Doke's book on Gandhi which had been sent to
him at about the same time (1).
The correspondence was resumed five months later, in April
1910, when Gandhi sent Tolstoy
a third letter as well as his
book written in English, Indian
Home Rule. "I did the trans¬
lation from Gujarati myself",
Gandhi wrote. "It is strange that
the Government of India should
have confiscated my book in that
language, but that is why I have
hastened to publish a translation."
Gandhi asked Tolstoy to read
the book and give him an opinion,
which, he said would be of the
greatest value to him. At the
same time, he sent Tolstoy a few
copies of the Letter to a Hindu, as published and prefaced by
Gandhi himself.
Tolstoy, however, was never quite able to carry out his
intention of replying to Gandhi's letter in detail. On April 25,
1910, he sent him a short letter thanking him for the books
which had been sent.
At that time, the struggle of the Indians in the Transvaal had
reached an acute phase. Hundreds of Indian families which had
refused to submit to the local administration found themselves
ruined and homeless. In order to save the neediest among
them, Gandhi organized, on a property offered to him by his
friend Kallenback, a self-supporting colony which he called
"Tolstoy Farm". Gandhi and Kallenback told Tolstoy of all
this in a letter dated August 15, 1910.
Gandhi's new letter, his preface to Letter to a Hindu, and
especially the book he had sent increased Tolstoy's interest in
the fate of the Indian people. He notes in his diary that he
spent several days in absorbed reading of Indian Home Rule and
of Doke's book on Gandhi.
These letters as well as Gandhi's review Indian Opinion, which
had also been sent to him, were a source of great satisfaction to
Tolstoy. "Good news from the Transvaal about a colony of
non-resisters", he noted in his diary on September 6. The same
day, he dictated a reply which was to be his last letter to Gandhi.
Tolstoy wrote it only two months before he left Yasnaya
Polyana. It reached Gandhi after much delay not, in fact,
until Tolstoy was on his deathbed, in the Astapovo railway station.
So ended this remarkable correspondence. It stirs us even
today. It is like a torch, lighting the path for future generations.
(1) J. Doke, M. K. Gandhi. An Indian patriot In South Africa. London,
1909.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
STEINBECK AND HEMINGWAY FAVOURITE
AUTHORS OF NORWEGIAN YOUTH
Steinbeck and Hemingway are the favourite Amer¬
ican novelists among Norwegian youth, accord¬
ing to a survey made recently by an American
educator visiting that country on a Unesco grant.
East of Eden, Steinbeck's allegorical novel of a few
years ago, appears as top choice among a group of
selected 18 to 19-year-old readers. The Old Man
and the Sea, Hemingway's most recent major effort,
headed the list of the Nobel Prize winner's works
currently being read.
The survey conducted on a Unesco Regional
Cultural Studies Grant was made by Mildred Wilsey,
an Associate Professor of English at Wilson College,
in Chambersburg, Pennsylvania. Miss Wilsey made
these observations on American writers in a report
written upon her return to the United States in May
of this year. The six-month grant to Miss Wilsey
was made last August for study "in the field of the
literary background and literary taste of college-age
people in Norway."
Miss Wilsey's work was principally devoted to
reading trends, both fiction and non-fiction, in Nor¬
wegian literature. On literary tastes in general,
however she notes:
"The general feeling is that the level of reading
taste for fiction, at least, is down. Books of fact or
experience, the world and its personalities, are the
preference not creative writing. The reasons for
this are interesting to discuss: fiction may have
reached its zenith and be on its way out, or our need
to know about world activity has become too pressing
for reading of an imaginary sort. There is great
Interest in the actual world.
"This trend towards the practical in the end may
not be practical if it defeats other values.
"The new spread of culture since the war",
Miss Wilsey suggests, "'has meant that certain refine¬
ments of taste have been lost. When the ferment
has settled, perhaps new refinement will arise.
"But Norway reads. It has no distractions such as
TV. And Norway buys. It has never been much of
a country for circulating libraries. The accumula¬
tion of one's own library is a growing trend and
reaches deep into the country. And there is an
increasing sale of English and American books at all
levels."
Other American authors whose novels were cited
as prominent in the reading habits of Norway's
youth were Sinclair Lewis, Pearl Buck and Jack
London. Among some of the others noted were
Louis Bromfleld, Margaret Mitchell, Lloyd Douglas,
Erskine Caldwell and Warwick Deeping.
The most widely read Norwegian authors, accord¬
ing to Miss Wilsey's report, are Henrik Ibsen, B.
Bjornson, Arne Garborg, Alex Kiellard, Tarjei Vesaas
and Knut Hamsun. The outstanding choices in
English literature are Shakespeare and Dickens.
Among modern authors the following rank high:
Aldous Huxley, CS. Forester, Somerset Maugham,
John Galsworthy, A.J. Cronin, Daphne du Maurier
and Neville Shute.
In languages other than English and Norwegian,
Alexandre Dumas and Victor Hugo (French), Eric-
Maria Remarque (German), Leo Tolstoy (Russian)
and the Dutchman, Hans Martin, are chiefly read.
As a by-product of her visit to Norway, Miss Wilsey
established a list of titles of modern Norwegian
literature offering attractive reading to the non-
Norwegian reader. This was in fact no digression
from the main project of which the underlying pur¬
pose was to draw people of different countries closer
together through a shared experience in literature.
FORTHCOMING PRICE INCREASE
The Unesco Courier announces with regret that in view of ever-increasing production
costs it will no longer be able to avoid a slight increase in price. On and after November I, I 957,
the annual subscription rate will be "increased to:
$3.00 IO/-stg. 500 frs
and the price per copy will go up to
30 cents I /-stg. 50 frs
However, subscriptions for 1958 and 1959 will be accepted at the present lower rates
provided they are registered before November I, 1957.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1957
From the Unesco Newsroom...
M AN'S MAJOR CROPS: Wheat
continues to be the major crop sown by
man and rice the major crop he harvests.
In its latest Yearbook of Food and Agri¬
cultural Statistics, the Food and Agricul¬
ture Organization reports that world pro¬
duction of wheat in 1954 was 151.5 million
metric tons from a total area of 135 mil¬
lion hectares. Rice was planted on only
97.4 million hectares but the total yield
was 162.2 million tons of paddy (unhusked
rice). In third place for 1954 grain produc¬
tion was maize with 137.3 million tons.
******* COMPOSERS' RADIO ROSTRUM:
Works by three composers from Sweden
were among those recommended by the
International Music Council, which has
just met in Paris, to be broadcast during
the coming season over radio networks
in 12 countries. The composers are
I. Likholm, H. Rosenberg and Carl
Birger Blomdahl. Two more works, by
Goffredo Petrassl (Italy) and Irving
Fine (U.S.A.), were also recommended
by the Council. Music representatives
of radio stations in 12 countries helped
to select the works. Under another
plan to help works by contemporary
composers to cross national boundaries
and reach a wider audience, the Council
prepared thirteen programmes combin¬
ing little-known compositions with
works by better-known contemporary
musicians. The scheme, known as the
International Rostrum of Composers,
was started by the Council in 1954.
Each station represented at the meeting
agreed to broadcast at least two of the
programmes during the 1957-58 season.
NiEW AFRICAN HEALTH PLAN:
A new plan for health was outlined recently
at the first international seminar on public
health education in Africa, held in Dakar
under the joint auspices of the Government
of French West Africa and the World
Health Organization. Some 60 participants
and observers from most countries and
territories of Africa south of the Sahara
took part in the discussions. The aim of
health education in African countries, par¬
ticipants agreed, should be to show people
in rural areas how to attain better living
conditions by their own efforts. Films,
filmstrips, exhibitions, leaflets, posters, etc.,
were valuable tools for the educator, but
they must be adapted to local conditions
and resources. The immediate day-to-day
interests of a given community and the
degree of literacy must be taken into account
in preparing material. Participants stressed
the role of the press, radio and cinema in
diffusing basic scientific knowledge to the
public.
******- INDONESIA'S SCHOOL DRIVE:
The number of schools and pupils in
Indonesia is fast increasing as a result
of the country's tremendous effort in
education, reports a Norwegian specia¬
list returning from a Unesco mission
there. Dr. Asbforn Overas, assigned in
July 1956 by Unesco to work with the
Indonesian Ministry of Education in the
expansion of secondary schooling, says
there are now 400,000 pupils in Indone¬
sia's junior high schools compared with
about 20,000 in 1950. Senior high
schools, of which there are now 546,
UNESCO WARNING OF CRISIS IN
EDUCATION FOR ARAB REFUGEES
A warning of the serious crisis developing in the education of Palestine Arab refugees
was given recently to the Unesco Executive Board meeting in Paris. "The magnitude
of the crisis is not yet know", Dr. Luther H. Evans, Director-General of Unesco,
told the Board members, "but money is fast running out and there is not nearly enough
to continue in the current school year. Curtailment of Unesco's programme
in this area has already begun. The building of schools has stopped. Very soon,
technical and vocational training will have to be suspended.
"Unless the financial situation improves, we shall have to start closing primary and
secondary schools. This is the grave situation which faces the unfortunate children
whose education has been placed in our care."
Emergency educational assistance for Arab refugees has formed an important part
of Unesco's programme for a number of years. This aid is given in collaboration with
Unrwa (the United Nations Relief and Works Agency) which is responsible for the
feeding, housing, health and rehabilitation of some 900,000 refugees. Out of
Unrwa's budget, $7,300,000 is earmarked for education. Technical responsibility for
the education programme, which provides primary schooling for 150,000 children,
secondary education for 25,000 and fundamental education for about 44,000 persons,
rests with Unesco.
Unrwa is financed by voluntary contributions, mainly from Governments with the
USA and the UK contributing roughly 85 per cent of the total. The rest comes from
some 45 states. Unrwa is faced with a serious shortage of funds because
contributions have not been big enough nor paid promptly enough to enable it to carry
en. The Director of Unrwa, Mr. Henry W. Labouisse who is expected shortly in Paris
where he will confer with Unesco's Director-General, has announced his intention of
going to the USA and Canada to confer with government and UN officials on the
problem.
Already, Unrwa's Director has ordered stoppage of construction activities, a
decision which affects the education programme because it halts building of new
classrooms and vocational training centres.
Some 200 new classrooms are needed each year because the refugee population is
increasing. The stop on building will mean that some of the pupils will be taught in
tents a return to the situation of five years ago. The 1957 programme included
$2,250,000 for building vocational training centres. These are not likely now to be
completed.
Other steps which may have to be taken if Unrwa's funds are not increased in the
next few weeks are partial curtailment of the fundamental education programme and
the temporary closing of teacher-training colleges and also, as Dr. Evans warned
Unesco's Executive Board, the closing of primary and secondary schools.
are increasing their enrolments at the
rate of about 10,000 pupils a year, he
said. The immensity of the secondary
and primary education task which Indo¬
nesia is tackling, is indicated, he noted,
by the fact that the country has about
13,000,000 children of primary school
age 6 to 12 years but only something
like 60 per cent of them have as yet the
opportunity to attend school.
]\ O PASSPORTS NEEDED: Euro¬
pean travel formalities have been further
eased by a recently announced agreement
waiving the need for passports between the
German Federal Republic and three other
countries Belgium, Luxembourg and Swit¬
zerland. German and Swiss nationals may
now cross each other's frontiers on the
presentation of a standard identity card for
a period of three months and providing
they are not seeking employment.
RESTORING WORKS OF ART:
An International Centre for the Study
of the Preservation and Restoration of
Cultural Property is to be set up in
Rome following the signing of an
agreement recently between the Italian
'UNESCO^
^CHIYî^/
Government and Unesco regarding its
installation and legal status. Unesco's
last General Conference approved the
creation of the Centre which will collect,
study and circulate Information on
scientific and technical problems in the
preservation and restoration of works
of art. It will also co-ordinate, en¬
courage and carry out research in this
field, train research workers and tech¬
nicians and help to improve standards
of restoration work.
'OrASS-ROOTS' AMBASSADORS:
During the past few years, more t.-.uii
1,200 young farmers from the United
States, Latin America, Europe, the Middle
and Far East have spent from four to six
months abroad learning a different way of
life under the International Farm Youth
Exchange (IFYE) programme. The idea
was born after World War II when the
British Ambassador to the United States
visited an Iowa farm. The following year
six British farmers were invited to the
U.S.A. and the experiment proved so
successful that it was decided to extend the
project to more than forty countries.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
Sir,
I should like to tell you how much
I enjoy The Unesco Courier. You
offer your readers very interesting
facts and I am glad that you often
write about people in Asia and Africa.
I think that thanks to modern'
transport the world is now very small.
I am an old woman (80 years) but
I am very interested in the events of
the whole world. At the moment I
have the atom very much in my
thoughts and I think atomic radiation
is very dangerous.
One thing I cannot understand. In
your issue of April 1957 you have
written about radio-active conservation.
How is it possible that we shall eat
food which has been exposed to
radiation when this is so terribly
dangerous for men and genes?
Just one more thing. I have many
friends and relations in Germany, and
I am sorry that the Courier is not
translated into the German language.
Lotte Gerson
Orebro, Sweden
Ed. note: The radiation to which
the food is exposed is sufficient to kill
the spoilage bacteria which cause food
to deteriorate. However under the
effect of the radiation the food does
not become radio-active and is
therefore safe to eat, the radiation
having passed through it without
leaving any trace.
Sir,
I think both the content and
presentation of The Unesco Courier
are admirable, and especially (and
this is an important point) the average
width of its columns.
It might interest you to know (for
this concerns your distribution) that it
was not through one of my fellow
professors that I came across your
magazine, but quite by chance among
a pile of publications in a hairdresser's
shop a democratic meeting place par
excellence.
Claude Klein
Asnières, France
Sir,
In both its presentation and
contents, The Unesco Courier has
far too much magazine style for my
liking. I don't care much for the
confused appearance produced by the
lay-out of the articles; I would like to
see much more clarity, even to the
extent of giving it almost a textbook
appearance. The articles are of
mixed quality; the publication has an
American style; it aims more at
sensationalism than exactitude (some
statements seemed to me to be
erroneous). Professionally I get no
benefit from it and, in the field of
strengthening international relations,
The Unesco Courier teaches me
nothing whatever.
I don't deny that the publication
has some qualities, and certain articles
(or parts of them) have interested me
greatly. I am sure, too, that most
readers must be satisfied with it.
But in my case, with my profession,
my social position and my family
circle (I am the only member of my
family to read The Unesco Courier)
I don't find in it the things I would
wish to see.
Don't think that this is a general
condemnation of the publication; I
think that in its present form it can
still satisfy many people.
R. Vimay
Versailles, France
Sir,
As a subscriber to The Unesco
Courier for several years I can say I
appreciate it more and more. It
brings all kinds of subjects within
everyone's comprehension. It enables
those who have neither the time
nor the facilities to plunge into an
extensive documentation to keep
abreast of things culturally. I never
get tired of thumbing through the
January issue ("Rare Treasures of
World Art") and if it wasn't for the
really modest subscription price I
would say, let us have many
more issues like this. Texts like
"Walkabout in Australia's Bush" are
suitable for children. I know it will
be enthusiastically read by my young
audience. The Unesco Courier is,
for teachers like myself, an enrichment,
a relaxation and a colleague.
P. Orsini
Rhône, France
Sir,
May I suggest you devote a whole
number exclusively to the problems of
the Middle East, especially of Israel
and its neighbours.
There is so much muddled thinking
in the heads of most people, and the
problems are usually discussed only
from our own (British) point of view.
Your article about the Palestinian
refugees (No 7, 1955; U.S. Oct.) was
a good beginning.
Dr. G. Fielding
Nottingham, England
Sir,
Would it be possible to devote one
of your future issues to the subject of
Moslems and Arabs, their history and
their future.
Pastor Raymond Petat
Les Andelys, France
Sir,
In renewing my subscription, I
should like to say how much I like
your magazine, in general, particularly
the issues devoted to a single theme:
Buddhism, for example. Won't you
do the same for the Arab world, the
Japanese and the Jews...?
Pierre Chotard
Isserpent, France
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry ol Educ¬
ation, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street. Melbourne,
C I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C\, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15 rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. Georges Street,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
nt Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Í00 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kléber, Paris, 16'. CCP.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
' Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxlord Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission tor
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P.O. B. 4154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashl, P.O. Box 60S
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry ot Education. Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Saplenza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. - N.V. Martlnus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhouc, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. - Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., I 1 04 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
5.20 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panic, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 55 1-3 Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik'i Bookstore, Libri Building. Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center. 152 West 42nd St, New York.
36. N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga
Terazlje 27/11, Belgrade.
U
Z
<
ci
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
y -
s.
y ÎJiV .*
Coming ne xi ^Sï$Èg>>-
month (August) Jvjj¿
An extra -
special issue ¿
52 pages \
FAMOUS
AUTHORS
AS
ARTISTS
ii
Revealing little-known paintings
and drawings by great novelists,
dramatists, poets: ic Leon Tolstoy
* Goethe * Hugo * Valéry
* Kipling * Poe * Baudelaire
DON'T MISS THE AUGUST
ic D.H. Lawrence -k Ch. Brontë
* Thackeray ic Dostoievsky
r * H.G. Wells -k H. Hesse * Musset
r * Hardy * Carlo Levi * Tagore
, * Garcia Lorca * Andersen etc.
T ISSUE: "SUBSCRIBE TODAY
Above, a drawing for " Faust" done by Goethe
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Allgaier, Office Général des Eolienncs
WINDMILL WITH A NEW LOOK
The ever-increasing rate at which basic fuels like coal and
oil are being used up has sparked scientific research into new
applications of an old source of energywind power. Modern
windmills (like three bladed type shown here) reflect improved
knowledge in aerodynamics now applied by countries seek¬
ing to use wind as an auxiliary power source. (See page 20)
]]>
</page>
</document>
