<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078354eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
iífe
>'K ' ' ¿-
Ti "**"i-:-ia'-'Ví'*
- ^m^v-.* vRf kt »v £^
l ?T"-; " *% c ' Sí» -r ^JP
* .-' c r -*' W>'»: "y «.- TW *
i»r
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
, . '
jH^*" '%JÊb "^^'
dfel IN A DYING LAND
>
c<
This was once a green pasture where vege¬
tation flourished and life abounded. Long
spells of drought drained every inch of
the earth of all moisture and created a
stark landscape of dying trees, crackrid-
dled soil and desolation. For the story of
what science has been doing for the future
of the world's arid lands, see page 4.
WMO photo by Max-Pol Fouchet. From "Indian
Lands", published by La Guilde du Livre, Lausanne
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
No. 5
MAY 1962
15TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
4 THIRSTY LANDS-PAST AND FUTURE
By Gilbert F. White
5 (I) THE THOUSAND FACES OF THE 'DESERT
I I (2) STRATEGY OF SCIENTIFIC CO-OPERATION
16 WHEN THE SAHARA WAS A BLOOMING GARDEN
18 THE EMPEROR PENGUIN, MONARCH OF ANTARCTICA
By Jean Pre'vost
-Ï <
W&&
&e&'X^r<Wß
COVER PHOTO
This rock painting at Tasslli,
on the eastern borders of
the Sahara Desert 1,000 miles
south of Tunis, Is 5,500 years
old. Along with many other
recently discovered traces of
an ancient human occupa¬
tion, It reveals the fact
that this now utterly arid
region was once a green and
fertile place. (See page 16).
© J. D. Lajoux
24 THE LOST HYMNS OF GEORGIA
A Soviet linguist unravels an ancient musical mystery
By Pavle Ingorokva
28 MODERN JAPANESE FICTION
A break with literary tradition
By Ivan Morris
32 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
33 REMINISCENCES BY A FRIEND OF TAGORE
By Aurobindo Bose
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C. 62. 1. 1 69 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Venlamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United - Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Reader»' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
"ÜNES'CcSV
^^CHlVfc^.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WINGED PLAGUE Like huge snowflakes falling grotesquely onto the parched summer landscape of Morocco, a cloud of
locusts swoops down on the sparse vegetation. In the arid lands movements of this nomad scourge of
the insect world often correspond to the appearance of vegetation after seasonal or sporadic rains.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
0 THE THOUSAND FACES
OF THE 'DESERT'
Photo André Sonine © Reporters Associés, Paris
Unesco's Major Project to promote scientific
research on the world's vast arid lands is to be
brought to an end this year after six years of
operation. This period has seen the amazing
growth of national and international activities
for the development of arid lands in which the
training of new arid land scientists and basic
research have received a new impetus. The end
of Unesco's Major Project will not mean the end
of this work. On the contrary, it will now be
carried forward as part of Unesco's regular pro¬
gramme and on an even wider scale than before by
direct action made possible through the Technical
Assistance programme and the United Nations
Special Fund. In a recent Unesco booklet, Pro¬
fessor Gilbert F. White, head of the Department
of Geography of the University of Chicago, has
reviewed the situation of Science and the Future
of Arid Lands, which we strongly recommend to
our readers. (Limited supply available on
request). From this authoritative study the Special
Report on the following pages has been adapted.
Arid and semi-arid regions cover more than a
third of the land surface of the earth, while
cultivated ground represents barely a tenth. For each
acre of cultivated land, there are three or- four acres
which are practically unused -by man because they are
desert or covered with sparse vegetation permitting only
a precarious subsistence economy at best. Yet the world's
population, which now exceeds 2,700 millions is increasing
more and more rapidly, and at the present rate will
double itself in fifty years.
These regions cover an immense diversity of landscapes:
majestic expanses of rolling steppe land in central Asia
and North Africa; dry lake bottoms in central Australia ;
rugged mountain valleys in Baluchistan; nearly flat
deltas at the mouths of the Nile and the Colorado.
Archaeological evidence suggests that the earliest cities
were in the dry valley of Mesopotamia. Possibly the
earliest cultivators and herdsmen were on the dry uplands
or river fringes of south-west Asia. Whatever the precise
early chronology, the arid zone has been occupied by man
since civilization emerged on the earth and it now shows
both rich fruit from his evolving use of its limited
resources and deep scars from his protracted misuse.
In these sectors of the earth's crust men often scan the
skies for a sign of rain, for scanty rainfall is the common
theme and the common problem. Rain is measured in the
depth that falls in an hour or day or year, and often rs
expressed as a mean annual depth in millimetres.
Any land surface in the temperate latitudes with a
mean annual precipitation of less than 250 millimetres is
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Photos Unesco - J. Dominique Lajoux
THIRSTY LANDS (Cont'd)
Overnight magic in the wilderness
likely to suffer from shortage of moisture for crop
growth, but gross annual amounts are misleading if taken
alone, and they must be compared with the amounts of
moisture that would be used through evaporation or
transpiration by plants if a true measure of the adequacy
of water supply for plant growth is to be obtained. While
a place such as. Tartous, in Syria, may have a surplus of
moisture in a few winter months, it may have a shortage
throughout the remainder of the year.
The term "desert" is used very loosely by both scientists
and popular writers. The western interior of the United
States of America was dubbed "desert" by the pioneers
but would be considered humid by a Libyan herdsman on
the edge of the Sahara.
In the lands where summer daytime temperatures
commonly are high, vegetation, soil and ground water
also are sparse. Except for generally narrow strings of
tamarix, cottonwoods or similar trees along water courses
there are no dense stands of trees, and over large
expanses the herbaceous and shrubby plants are so thin
as to support only a few goats or a camel on 100 hectares
annually. In a few places there are major accumulations
of fresh ground water but generally these are meagre, in
many instances floating upon waters that are so saline as
to be unpalatable for animals and toxic for plants.
But if the water, soil and vegetation are marked by
sparsity they are also marked by variability both in time
and in place. It is not uncommon for a station in the
Nubian Desert or Negev to go 11 months without a drop
of rain and then to have a cloudburst of twenty inches in
a few hours.
Vegetation knows no orderly time-table here, but
responds in striking fashion to the vagaries of rain. This
is epitomized by the bright, delicate carpet of desert
flowers that may spring overnight from a seared desert
soil following one of the infrequent rains. Much of the
movement of nomads and of the nomad scourge of the
insect world the locust is in response to vegetation
which flourishes for a time in the wake of seasonal or
sporadic rains.
Just as arid lands vary with the years and seasons, they
vary tremendously from place to place. The unbroken
vista of sand dunes with »uniform ridges, soil, vegetation
and water conditions the traditional erg of the Saha¬
ra is in fact relatively rare.
Avast expanse of gently sloping plains in the
western Egyptian arid zone gives at first
glance a deceptive impression of uniformity. On closer
examination it is found to have a complex set of soils and
plants. The spottiness becomes greater to the east when
areas with greater differences in rock formation and relief
are investigated, as with the wadi systems that drain the
Sinai Peninsula and embrace a wide variety of land forms
and plant communities.
Tenacious human beings have established pockets of
settlement in these lands, leaving vast areas unoccupied.
From the standpoint of human occupation, scarcity,
variability and spottiness again are prominent charac¬
teristics. Arid lands encompass several of the' great
uninhabited wastes of the worldthe Sahara ergs, the
Atacama desert of the Chile coast, the Salt Desert of
Iran, and the Takla Makan of Central Asia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
SUNKEN OASIS. A few years ago an oasis cast Its green shade near Fort Flatters in the Sahara.
Today it has been swallowed up by the creeping sands and only the tops of three palm trees (left)
mark Its grave. Nearby is a lunar-like landscape (above) created by strange formations of vegetal
origin which formerly clung to the roots of trees, now dead and today petrified by time and weather.
These typically are crossed by caravan tracks and air
routes which connect settlements within and on their
borders. There and on the semi-arid borders are four
major classes of settlement. Perhaps most characteristic
are the pastoral nomadic groups which range across and
in the arid areas of the Old World in search of grass and
water but whose fortunes always are linked by trade or
tribute with sedentary areas.
Intensive farming is the rule in the Nile, Tigris-
Euphrates, Indus, Amu-Darya and Colorado valleys, as
well as in isolated areas like the Ouargla Oasis in Algeria
or the Imperial Valley of California and Fayum Depres¬
sion of Egypt, and it is in these areas that the greater
number of the people of the arid lands is crowded.
In some places linked with these agricultural areas and
in other places quite independent of them are fast
mushrooming cities like Cairo which have long been
capitals and in many instances owe their existence to
religious, mining, government, or trade functions which
are largely independent of the agricultural hinterland.
Thus Mecca and Jerusalem are holy cities, Karachi
and Teheran have taken on importance as centres of new
political administration, Kuwait and Abadan are centres
for oil exploitation. Quetta and San Diego are military
bases, and Phoenix and Yuma serve a relatively recent
invasion of urban dwellers who seek to enjoy the
amenities of sunshine and dry warmth.
In addition to the nomads, oasis farmers and city
dwellers, all of the arid lands have twilight margins of
semi-arid lands that are occupied in varying degrees by
sedentary farmers who try to wrest a living out of the
dry soil in the face of rains sometimes niggardly and
sometimes copious, and whose fortunes are at times as
variable as the rains. These marginal lands occasionally
have been the theatre of large-scale government occupa¬
tion, as in the case of the "virgin lands" programme in
the arid southern fringes of the Union of Soviet Socialist
Republics.
In the Americas and Australia the arid lands have been
largely free of pastoral nomadic occupancy although
their irrigated settlement has been one of the early
human chapters, and recently their use has turned on
new forms of urban and mining exploitation of climate
and location. Swimming pools ripple in the outskirts of
Los Angeles on land that once was worthless for forage.
It is highly problematical as to how most of
the arid landscape appeared when the earliest
agricultural settlements were established. Certainly the
plant cover has been changed radically since that time:
Syrian mountain slopes have been largely denuded of
trees, and grasslands have changed dramatically in plant
composition.
The records of abandoned fields and civilizations,
coupled with these instances of landscape change, have
fostered a popular belief that deserts around the world
are advancing. Sometimes these advances are attributed
to human destruction of resources, and sometimes to
climatic change.
The chronology is still confused and indistinct in many 7
periods, but from the patchy data a few conclusions
begin to emerge:
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THIRSTY LANDS (Cont'd)
30 centuries of
man-made destruction
1) With the polar recession of the last of the great
fluctuating ice sheets aridity was widespread in the desert
lands of south west Asia and Africa. There were marked
changes in temperature and precipitation during the long
glacial period, so that lakes filled in areas of both Asia
and America which are now dry, but by the end of the
period, perhaps 15,000 years ago, a general climatic situa¬
tion similar to the present had set in.
2) The prevailing aridity was relieved in Africa and
western Asia during about 5000-3000 B.C. by a time of
greater heat and moisture. It was in this Neolithic
period that the boundaries of the Sahara apparently
contracted and that it had animals, plants and soils now
found far from its margins in savannah country.
3) There have been harrowing, prolonged droughts as
in the terrible drought of A.D. 1276-99 in the south¬
western North American lands and these have been
followed by more humid times.
4) During the last 50 years there has been a slight
tendency toward higher temperatures and lower precipi¬
tation throughout most of the arid zone. This is of the
order of 5 to 10 per cent reductions, a trend which is
small by comparison with annual swings in precipitation.
5) The more dramatic examples of resource destruction
during the past 3,000 years must be traced to man rather
than climate.
We cannot predict with any confidence that the
arid lands will become more or less arid in the
decades immediately ahead. They have been in man's
short history on the earth both drier and wetter. While
aridity as a climatic phenomena is not spreading on a
broad front, human abuse of arid lands still is going lar¬
gely unchecked. The need to halt this deterioration and
at the same time to make better use of the remaining
resources as a means of improving the life of its bur¬
geoning population presents the central problem in the
development of the arid lands.
Behind the problem of social and economic development
of the arid lands lies the more basic problem of
understanding the processes by which resources are being
destroyed and by which they may be used more effectively.
While it is often maintained that the pastoral nomads
make an ideal adjustment to the sparse grasslands of
the Middle East, moving with their flocks to the places of
most abundant forage, their record for treatment of the
grass resource is far from encouraging.
The combination of inflexible land-tenure systems, a
heavy goat population on sub-humid margins, and a
growing human population has promoted grazing prac¬
tices that have not only effected a radical change in the
total plant cover but have selectively eliminated many
productive species and have substantially reduced the
carrying capacity of the ranges.
The upland pastures in the steppe areas of Syria are
reported by the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
Investigators to be subject to continuing replacement of
forage plants by »non-palatable species. Over great
expanses the useful species have disappeared or nearly so.
Often labelled as Public Enemy Number One or as the
"black locust", the goat continues to roam and scalp the
more humid Middle Eastern grazing lands.
The striking feature of the arid zone cities is their raw,
rapid growth. They are expanding at a high rate,
pushing out into surrounding dry lands, attracting popu¬
lation from agricultural areas, and in turn placing fresh
demands upon those areas for food supply and raw
materials. No cities in the United States of America
have sprawled more quickly over their dry borders than
Los Angeles and Phoenix. Some of this recent increase
reflects the mounting exploitation of petroleum reserves.
Countries like Iraq and Saudi Arabia which have
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Daily water minimum in
Arabian desert: 15 litres
undertaken alternative development programmes with oil
revenues may offset some effects of exhaustion.
What seems abundantly clear in connexion with
development efforts is that the needs commonly outstrip
the possibilities of human action and that two of the
principal barriers to effective action are lack of scientific
knowledge and failure to translate available knowledge
into positive action.
The slow process of scientific inquiry and the careful
building of educational institutions must be fostered.
These are the two major channels along which Unesco
has tried to move in improving the condition of people
in the arid lands:
A Berber tribesman and a California politician have in
common the question of whether or not there will be
water enough to go around. Shortage of water is the
unifying problem of the arid lands.
The one great source of water on land is the natural
precipitation. Determining the total supply that preci¬
pitation makes available at one place is complicated both
by the irregularity and spottiness of the records and by
the differing amounts of natural demand. Because the
arid lands are sparsely settled, the number of rain gauges
is smaller than in more humid regions and certain large
expanses such as the Salt Desert of Iran are wholly lack¬
ing in gauges.
In areas like the Negev where a few centimetres may
be highly important in planning new water control works
it is necessary to guess at means and annual variations
from the mean, using records only a few decades in
length at most, and to try to fill in the great gaps in
data by extrapolating from other records and from the
corroborating evidence of geochromology and archaelogy.
Nor is it yet clear how »much water a given field of
plants requires in order to attain optimum growth. There
are no ready ways of measuring them directly. At least
six different methods are in use for estimating required
water consumption, and these differ from each other by
as much as 30 per cent according to assumptions which
it is necessary to make about water and soil processes
that themselves are in doubt.
The design of new storage dams and canals in Lebanon
or in Peru depends upon these estimates of optimum
needs for water. Without them it is difficult to arrive
at appraisals of water-use efficiency.
It is not enough to have water of a given quantity; the
water must be of suitable quality. Water may carry
injurious amounts of either minerals in solution or solids
in suspension. One cost of permanent irrigation is
constant vigilance against salting.
S;rTiLL another hazard in water quality is the
silt load which, carried either in suspension or
as bed load, may clog up reservoirs and ditches. In many
ancient valleys, such as the Tigris-Euphrates, the decline
of early agriculture at certain periods is to be traced in
considerable measure to the failure of society to deal
carefully with the salt and silt menaces.
There is less »doubt about animal and human needs for
water than there is as to plant needs although man
exercises wide discretion in the surpluses with which he
supplies himself. The absolute minimum needed to
maintain life in a normal adult in the most intense heat
of the Arabian Desert is about 15 litres per day, Sanaran
workmen need a minimum of 7.5 litres and often more,
depending upon temperature and type of work. In tem¬
perate climates, daily need is sometimes taken as 3.7 litres.
Animal consumption of water varies with age, heat and
feeding conditions. Many mammals, such as the desert
fox, draw water entirely from their food intake. "
In a strict sense, water can be brought wherever man
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THIRSTY LANDS {Cont'd)
Tomatoes that drink
dew in the night
wishes if he is willing to take the trouble and pay the
cost of carrying out elaborate engineering works or of
effecting other changes in the natural cycle of water.
Increasingly these works are designed to serve multiple
purposes in an entire drainage basin, as in the Rio
Grande Basin in Mexico and the United States of Amer¬
ica, or in the Oom er Rbia In Morocco. Canals, aque¬
ducts, pumps, diversion dams, storage dams are common
devices for changing the place and time of water, but
their application to arid land conditions is severely
limited by factors of design ingenuity, of cost, and of
knowledge.
But there are other means than major engineering for
affecting the time and place of water in dry lands.
Through the spreading of flood run-off on permeable
Intake areas the supply of water flowing into underground
storage may be increased, as in the spreading grounds of
southern California. Plant control may be used in certain
favourable circumstances to increase the flow of water, to
reduce canal wastage, or to reduce the flow of water.
One of the fascinating technical possibilities is that
of reducing losses occasioned by evaporation from water
surfaces. In drainage basins like the Colorado the total
amount of water lost from reservoir surfaces in a year
may exceed the amount put to actual consumptive use in
the same basin. If there were a generally efficient means
of preventing such losses the available supply might be
greatly augmented. Promising experiments in evaporation
reduction are under way with mono-molecular films such
as cetyl alcohol. Practical application on a wide scale
awaits further refinement.
The schematic flow of water in the natural hydrologie
cycle is now seen to be subject to modification at many
points. Some of these changes, such as storage dams
and weather modification, increase the amount of water
effectively available to man.
The impact of man and the intricacies of the
plant-soil complex which he has modified are
nowhere more evident than in places where patches of
arid lands have been protected from goat and plough and
axe. In 1955 seven enclosures protecting a total of 29 hec¬
tares were established in Mauretania with support by
Unesco. Each enclosure gave a different combination of
soil, plant and microclimatic factors. Within one year
striking changes began to take place in the protected
areas. The total amount of vegetation increased.
It is not easy to predict the results of man's various
uses of vegetation and soil because there are so many
points at which knowledge of the basic life processes is
lacking. This is especially true of the processes by which
. plants use water and by which soil nutrients and solutions
are formed.
The selection and breeding of plants for the rigorous
drought situations of the arid lands can only be as
productive as that understanding. Thus, if it is recog¬
nized that a tomato plant can absorb dew from its leaves
at night, the way may be open to finding other plants
with similar capacities or to breeding up those characte¬
ristics in species which would not otherwise prosper in
areas with heavy dew fall.
Likewise, the exact means by which plant nutrients are
released from their mineral complex in the soil and made
available to plant roots through the medium of soil solu¬
tion or carried upwards by capillary action or downwards
by gravity is not well understood. These fundamental
processes of soil formation and plant nutrition are
important to the management of arid soils in several
ways.
If it were known as well how »minerals enter into the soil
water solution and how plants accommodate themselves
10 to different minerals, the prevention, cure, and adjustment
to salinity conditions would be greatly advanced over the
means now available to irrigation farmers.
Ajé 11 ii/ *l J
© STRATEGY OF
The desert is popularly viewed as an
inhospitable environment which repels
animal and man ; actually it supports
large populations in relatively healthy
state. Nowhere do extremes set up
insurmontable barriers to human
beings, whether roving or sedentary.
And as our knowledge of the physiology
of life in arid and semi-arid conditions
becomes greater the possibility of
making life more comfortable and
more productive is also multiplying.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
MIMOSA TREE seedlings being planted In the dunes
of the Gaza strip under a United Nations Relief &
Works Agency (UNRWA) desert reclamation project.
1; |w
jt If |#^i
â. n
SCIENTIFIC CO-OPERATION
I n Egypt the desert which for centuries has
been shunned is now seen as a place of
recreation, and in southern California the arid interior
valleys once roamed only by mining prospectors are being
subdivided for holiday use.
Two of the characteristic urban features in arid lands
are the rough new mining and oil towns which rise out of
bare desert wastes and the ghost town which marks the
site of abandoned mineral operations. The refinery
towers of Abadan, the pipeline pumping stations of Syria,
the uranium mines of the Transvaal, the copper mining
pits of Utah and Chuguicamata, and the well-drilling
rigs of the Algerian Sahara are samples of vigorous new
mineral developments.
What part of the extracted wealth will find its way into
stabilized grasslands or flourishing irrigation projects or
productive towns or in devices to harness solar energy?
It is estimated that at the current state of exploration
approximately 55 percent of all the proven reserves of
petroleum and a substantial part of the potential reserves
are in the arid countries bordering the eastern Mediterra¬
nean and the Persian Gulf. At present rates of produc¬
tion those fields should last many more decades.
The known copper reserves of the world are widely
scattered, but are heavily clustered in a few arid areas,
chiefly Chile, Northern Rhodesia and the western United
States. A few other minerals have high local importance.
Manganese in the Union of South Africa and the Ukraine,
chromite in Southern Rhodesia, phosphate in Morocco
and Tunisia, vanadium in Peru and south-west Africa,
11
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
PROBING THE SECRETS OF PUNT LIFE
m
i
%
Av
asa
VA« au»
C«v/
'
Manufacturing processes of plantsthe greatest factories in the worldare "taken
apart" and analyzed in this special agricultural laboratory in the United States. Scien¬
tists have now found that all growing plants contain a chemical which is activated by
red rays found both in daylight and artificial light. Part of the red end of the spectrum
promotes growth while another part encourages flowering. A fuller understanding of
these processes might enable the farmer of the future to benefit from a "light control"
of his crops, staggering the harvest season and making his schedule easier. Above, photo¬
grapher records difference in growth of two plants of same age which received same
amounts of food. Big plant received longer doses of light. Centre, hose lines carry
special nutrient solution to cocklebur plants and (right) bean plant. Everything known
to affect plant growth is strictly controlled and analyzed. Light, temperature, humi¬
dity and nutrients are changed at will. Basic research into the processes by which plants
use water and by which soil nutrients and solutions are formed is an essential part of
search for knowledge with which to make far better use of the world's arid lands.
'
THIRSTY LANDS (Cont'd)
Minerals as economic stimulants
zinc in Mexico, and lead in Australia, are examples. In
each case, a large share of the regional income is derived
from exploiting these deposits.
One of the direct effects of new mineral exploitation is
to open up new roads and airlines to previously inacces¬
sible areas. In time these developments will place still
heavier pressures on the remaining local resources of
grass and soil. There is, however, the possibility of so
using the income from the mineral resources as to pro¬
mote more effective use of resources which will be avail¬
able when the petroleum is gone.
During the mid-1950's, seventy per cent of the petro¬
leum revenues in Iraq was set aside for construction by
the development board of new manufacturing plants, fer¬
tilizer plants, transport facilities, and water-control
structures. Similarly, a substantial part of the petroleum
revenues in Iran has been used since the early 1950's to
support resources development, of which the land and
water programme in Quhistan is a major example.
The Quhistan regional development programme in¬
cludes construction of a hydroelectric and irrigation pro¬
ject on the Dez River, a new sugar-cane and sugar-pro-
12 duction scheme, a polyvinyl chloride plastics plant as the
beginning of a petrochemical industry, and a fertilizer
test and demonstration effort.
In a basic sense, the effectiveness of current use of
minerals to support permanent occupance of arid lands
may rest on the wisdom with which research results are
applied in the management of soil and plants and water.
Just as the natural resources of the arid lands are
spotty and variable, so also are the resources of skilled
scientists and experienced teachers to deal with the
underlying problems of research and of education.
Among the newer national units, such as Libya, there
are some with only a handful of trained scientists while
in others, such as the UAR (Egypt), there are long-estab¬
lished universities. Few have the highly organized cen¬
tral research facilities that are found in Australia, or the
Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, or the widespread
networks of agricultural experiment stations and agri¬
cultural extension workers that have spread across the
arid sectors of the United States of America.
In order to gain the quickest practicable flow of research
findings into areas where they are needed it is important
to speed up the conduct of basic and applied research
and to speed its results. No single country may be con¬
sidered to have solved the troublesome problems of water,
soil, vegetation, and sun, and the record indicates that
each must be prepared to draw heavily upon contribu¬
tions from outside its borders if it is to do so in a
reasonable period.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Some of the major centres for research on arid land
problems lie wholly outside of the arid zone. Basic work
on the organic content of arid soils is going forward in
laboratories in Zurich and Paris. Demineralization is the
subject of lively experiments in Japan and Florida.
Water balance studies are centred at a station in the
United States of America. The great Soviet Union soils
institute has its headquarters in Moscow, and the domi¬
nant agricultural research station in the United King¬
dom is outside of London.
At the same time there are vital centres of research in
the midst of arid terrain. Egypt's work on the Nile is a
monument of hydrologie research.
An example of the complex international collaboration
involved in a broad research programme is found in the
current attacks upon problems of salinity. The frontal
attack on the possibilities of converting salt water into
fresh is going forward on several fronts with Unesco
serving as a »clearing house for information among the
far-flung operations.
The problem of salinity recognizes common interests of
Soviet soil chemists, New Zealand animal breeders, Iraqi
archaeologists, and Iranian hydrologists in the hydrolysis
processes of soil formation. This is the view that led the
Iranian Government to sponsor jointly with Unesco at
Teheran in 1958 the first world symposium bringing toge¬
ther these diverse scientific approaches.
There is no precedent for an international operation
which seeks to speed up the research and the information
and education linked with it for a great expanse of terri¬
tory like the arid zone. Certain scientific disciplines have
achieved a fair degree of co-operation across national
boundaries through journals and occasional congresses.
Thus, the botanists bring together workers in plant
ecology at intervals of five years, and the geologists
gather every five years in a different country. The pro¬
ceedings of the International Association of Scientific
Hydrology regularly carry the latest research findings in
that field to its members around the world.
Confronted with the task of speeding up the action in
all these directions an international organization must
choose among many methods of helping. Attacking such
a problem for the first time, Unesco in its arid zone pro¬
gramme gradually charted a strategy that followed three
major lines.
Its most ambitious effort was to accelerate the whole
complex international flow of people and ideas that is
associated with the advancement of research. Secondly,
it sought to improve the training and education from
which scientists and technical workers may be drawn in
future. Finally, in a much more modest way it sought to
select critical and basic research problems deserving the
encouragement of definition and token support.
One issue of strategy which was raised at the inter¬
national level at the very beginning of the Unesco pro- 13
gramme and which lingers to plague every national co¬
operative effort is whether or not a specific research
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THIRSTY LANDS (Cont'd)
Research that will shape the future
14
institution should be named or set up as a centre of arid
zone research.
Unesco decided against a single centre and instead set
up an advisory committee representative of the coun¬
tries involved. This, however, only shifted the issue to
the national level where it continues to provoke debate
and alternative plans.
In addition to the long-established research centres in
other regions, there is now growing up a network of
Institutes within the arid zone. It would be ideal to have
a complete inventory of climate, geology, land forms,
water, soil, vegetation, energy sources and human popu¬
lation for each sector of the arid zone.
A practicable strategy of scientific co-operation must
recognize that the basic surveys, like the research work,
will make a spotted and diverse patchwork which will
rarely cover any one area adequately. The technician
and the scientist must be prepared to improvise and
interpolate, and to draw upon the best that comes from
workers elsewhere.
Within the domain of science are numerous channels
along which research workers and their findings may
move in advancing the limits of knowledge. The dis¬
tinctively international barriers to scientific advances are
the special concern of Unesco, and it tries to reduce them
by strengthening the national scientific agencies and by
helping speed up and extend international action. Its
stock in trade is ideas and people who can use them.
Thus, government committees have been established in
Iran and Pakistan to promote integrated research in
those countries and in each case the stimulus came from
the call to participate in a Unesco effort on a larger scale.
Astmple and 'direct way of speeding up the flow
of new ideas is to bring together represent¬
ative scientists from the chief countries involved to
exchange findings and views. In each case, papers
reviewing the current state of research are prepared in
advance, and then men from as many as two or three
dozen nations are given an opportunity to criticize that
work and report new contributions. Both the review
reports and the symposium papers are then published for
distribution to the many workers who were unable to
attend.
The impact of a scientific symposium of this sort is
widespread. A Tunisian hydrologist learns of new clima¬
tológica! methods which he can apply in designing water
control works at home, and he in turn teaches others the
concrete results of using archaeological studies of ancient
wells and terraces in the planning of new structures.
More common is the interchange between workers
which enables one of them to leap across what otherwise
would have been years of plodding through already disco¬
vered territory. A scientist returning to his laboratory
from one of the international symposia may carry only
a warm sense of fellowship with his workers in other
countries or he may be the means of radically revising
the research programme of his agency.
Universities of good quality cannot be created over¬
night where nomadic herdsmen or caravans make their
camps. However, for nations that are seeking to leap in
a generation over economic development that has taken
300 years in many other societies, a few years time in the
maturing of scientific workers may seem crucial.
It has already been noted that much of the resource
deterioration in the arid zone is in the face of sound
scientific knowledge of possible ways of preventing much
of it; from a technical standpoint many irrigated lands
need not be salted and the pasture lands need not be
eroded.
At least 90 per cent. of the Libyans are illiterate. Of
the more than 2,300,000 people who inhabit Somaliland,
Somalia and other dry lands of the "Horn" of Africa, at
least 1,700,000 are estimated to be pastoral nomads.
To reach these proud, roving people with new ideas or
even to facilitate their grazing operations by forecasts as
to available grass and water in the remote lands which
they prowl, is a formidable task calling for devices not
generally in use. To speak to them either in pictures or
words in a medium which is suitable requires sensitive
perception of their culture and an array of printed and
audiovisual materials that is not now available.
As one way of helping curb the unknowing abuse of
natural resources in the eastern Mediterranean area, a
special effort has been made to prepare simple educa¬
tional materials in the local languages. Kits of books,
pamphlets, posters, pictures and filmstrips have been
developed to give essential ideas about resources and their
more orderly use to children in the 12-14 age-group and
to adults in fundamental education centres.
T:hese kits were first tried for children in the
Arabic-speaking countries of Iraq, Jordan,
Lebanon, Morocco, and of the United Arab Republic on
an experimental basis. After some experience, they
were reviewed and work was begun on a final set of
materials which might be used widely in areas with
similar conditions of dryness, plant cover, and grazing
and farming systems.
It is in the realm of FAO technical assistance teams
and co-operative surveys that the outlines of better pas¬
ture management practices begin to take shape, or that
regional attacks on the vexing question of salinity in
irrigated soils are planned.
Man has the tools to produce more from the resources
at hand but lacks the social skills to use those tools.
We may regard the arid lands, and particularly their
sub-humid borders, as a key test of man's ingenuity in
applying his technical tools to keep production ahead of
population growth.
The role played by basic research in setting the limits
for social development in arid lands is nowhere more
apparent than in the struggle to narrow the gap between
scientific knowledge and practical action in resource use.
If there were miraculously to be an abundance of
teachers to work with the Somali grazers and if there
were adequate funds to pay for whatever pamphlets,
radio sets, slide projectors or posters they might wish,
there still would remain the question of what should be
taught.
F;1 UNDAMENTAL investigation by the anthropo¬
logist and geographer thus must precede
sound decisions as to effective ways of using the rich
store of developed technology to advance the basic
cultural aims of these people. No simple transfer of
"know how" will do.
It is remarkable that while there are many descriptions
of nomadic groups relatively little is known of the migra¬
tion routes they take and of the conditions affecting their
shifts and their relations to sedentary peoples. The
whole process by which nomads choose grazing animals
and schedules is obscure. Yet every sound effort to work
out an improvement in methods must take such informa¬
tion into account if it is to succeed.
Clouds of Ignorance cover numerous scientific areas
which, once exposed, could influence man's capacity to
live in and use the arid lands.
The important need is to get on with the primarily basic
research wherever there are competent men to direct it.
No sector of the arid zone has received more concentrated
applications of technology and education than Israel with
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
USIS
INVADING SANDS REPULSED. Standing on a sea of sand, a Colorado, U.S.A., farmer points
to a sea of flowers and grasses, a terrain which he transformed from barren rangeland and unpro¬
ductive sandhills, into a profitable ranch area. For this land reclamation, natural vegetation was
allowed to grow. Once established, these plants held the soil and furnished shelter for pasture grasses.
its heavy inflow of capital and trained people. Here,
there is a tendency to stress applied science, but there
is also lively concern for basic research.
"What is the rough balance sheet of human gains and
losses in each of the major types of environmental com¬
plex in the arid zone?
On the whole, the grazing lands appear to be deterio¬
rating. Notwithstanding large-scale provision of new
water facilities, the net volume of grassland resources
seems to be on the decline. Where nomadic grazers are
in command there is thus far no highly effective means
of ordering their operations.
Grassland surveys are setting the ground for needed
plans of improvement and management methods are
being perfected.
As the ability to select and breed drought and heat-
resistant strains of plants is increased, and as under¬
standing of the physiology of drought resistance and
endurance in animals is widened, powerful aids in enlarg¬
ing the producing capacity of the grasslands may well
be released. Meanwhile, social research on nomadic life
holds the key to unlocking much of the biological work
already accomplished but bound by custom and organiza¬
tion into compartments outside the daily stream of
resource management.
Among the lands already irrigated it has been shown,
however, that at least three major factors affect the
prospects for continued use:
1) The widest ead problem of salting whose threat to
the permanency of many fertile lands will be removed
only as farming practices improve and as the under¬
standing of soil-water relations is sharpened.
2) The low efficiency of current water use. This also
may be curbed in part by enlightened management and
in part by research which in this case might lead to
closer estimates of crop needs and of means of reducing
water losses through seepage and reservoirs.
3) The increasing competition for water as between
irrigation and industrial, municipal and recreational uses.
Taking these factors into account and balancing them
against the current investments in new irrigation works,
it appears that for the arid zone as a whole there is a
net gain in agricultural productivity and in the stability
of village life as a result of massive irrigation develop¬
ment. The new dams and canals are strengthening the
productive plant.
The most rapid growth in economic productivity in the
arid lands is taking place in the areas of oil and metal
exploitation, and there the typical sights are new piers,
refineries, and smelters.
Essentially, the task of helping make the most of the
sparse and variable arid lands is one of discovery and
dissemination: discovery of the fundamental facts about
social behaviour, water, soils and plants on which refined
technological advances may be grounded; and dissemina¬
tion of the new and practicable knowledge to those who
should use it. Thus, scientific research and education
march shoulder to shoulder, each reinforcing the other.
It is this effort to sharpen and speed up the scientific
and educational processes that has special urgency for
the arid zone while its waters are not yet fully appro¬
priated, while its soils and plants still have some recupe¬
rative capacity, and while its minerals still provide the
stimulation of investment capital.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Seffar is a typical dried-up and
eroded landscape of the eastern
Sahara. Yet in the caves among these
bare rocks are paintings and rock
engravings testifying that this
was once the seat of ancient
civilizations and fertile lands.
Photos © J. Dominique Lajoux, taken from
"Merveilles du Tassili n'Ajjer", to be pub¬
lished by Editions du Chêne, Paris, I 962.
WHEN THE SAHARA DESER
WAS A BLOOMING GARDE
y^ß-'
16
-ODAY withered, fossilized and eroded
the burning desert winds, Tassili n'Aj
in the Sahara (nearly 1,000 miles soi
of Tunis) was a green and fertile pla
5,500 years ago. This has been revealed
innumerable painted and engraved images j
its rocks. Analyses made of fossilized poll
from deep in the ground ha
jiow shown that in this area a Mediterrane
type vegetation grew profusely. It includ
lime trees, alders, hollyoaks, cypresse .
olive trees and cereals of various kinds.
Of all this variety and wealth of flora there
remain today but a hundred cypress trees.
.Íff!'»f!w4
Above, painting of a cow at Iherir dates from 2000
B.C. Left, these cattle engraved on a rock at Terrarat,
seem to be waiting to drink in the wadi when the next
rare rainstorm fills it with water. Opposite page, herd
of cattle, a painting going back to 3500 B.C. Some of
these rock paintings show as many as 1 00 head of cattle.
.' \~j¿-> -' "%' \ j /, ¿Lc .si »i ' m^'S- -*"-*.-' ' ' -i- £ . ¿MEEmWn'EeMv-M&'t
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
É9I
^ro» ^«g^pwm,
«4 v
0/^$')
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE EMPEROR PENGUIN
MONARCH OF ANTARCTICA
by Jean Prévost
OVER 100,000 EMPERORS,
largest and stateliest of the Antarctic
penguins, live for ten months of
each year in colonies on the ice like
the one shown here, in Adelie Land.
Of all the teeming flocks of seabirds which
»breed and raise their young on the islands
and coasts of the frozen continent of Antarctica and in
the sub-Antarctic regions to the north undoubtedly the
most curious and fascinating are the penguins or
Spheniscidae.
Comprising 17 species, the penguin family Is primarily
found in the frozen south, although some of its members
breed much further north. The more temperate habitats
of some penguins in southern Australia, New Zealand,
South Africa and the west coast of South America are
certainly explained by the existence of cold marine
currents from the Antarctic. The most striking example
perhaps are the most northerly colonies of penguins
which live close to the equator in the Galapagos Islands
MALE OR FEMALE? With no outward differ¬
ence between male and female emperors, iden¬
tification of the sexes is a difficult business. Weigh¬
ing them, as French biologist, Jean Prévost, is
doing here, helps to solve the problem as males
are on the average heavier than females. Studies
of this kind revealed that heaviest males weigh 88
lbs, females 8 I, at the start of the breeding season.
18
off the coast of Ecuador. (See The Unesco Courier, Sept.
1961).
With their endearing and amusing appearance and
habits, penguins have become the most "popular" and
best known of Antarctica's birds. On land they stand up
straight on short legs and walk with a flat-footed, clumsy
waddle. They are most at home in the water and, using
their short flipper-like wings as paddles, they are first-
rate swimmers.
While most of the species offer definite possibilities for
observation and studies, one in particular, the emperor
penguin, is of special interest. Unlike all other penguins
it reproduces its young in the depth of the polar winter
in extreme southerly latitudes on the sea ice near the
Antarctic continent.
The dangers of navigation by sea in these regions and
the utter impossibility in winter of crossing the barrier of
sea ice which is several miles deep explain the fact that
the first specimens of this species were only recently
discovered. It was not until 1820 that the Russian
explorer von Bellingshausen had the good fortune to
come across them some distance from the coast.
Access to the Antarctic continent is only possible during
the summer months after the break up of the ice. But
as this break up carries away the emperor penguins, it
was not until the beginning of this century that a colony
was first visited and studied, while most of the others
have only been reached in the last few years.
Until recently there were very few permanent missions
on the coast of the Antarctic continent and their limited
resources in mechanical transport confined them more or
less closely to their stations. Hence, although four new
colonies were discovered, it was not until the Inter¬
national Geophysical Year (1957-1958) that new resources
and the combination of movement by air, land and sea
with powerful and suitable equipment brought the total
number of colonies visited to 20.
The total population of Aptenodytes forsten (the scien¬
tific name of the emperor penguin) is currently estimated
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
All photos © Jean Prévost
at more than 100,000, though there is a chance that
various other colonies exist in some unexplored regions
of the Antarctic coast.
A few individual birds may move north as far as the
60th parallel but the colonies do not go beyond the polar
circle and they are not found further south than the
Antarctic coast itself. The most southerly colony is in
the heart of the Ross Sea, at Cape Crozier, 77° 29' latitude
south.
As already mentioned, the emperor penguin breeds on
the pre-coastal sea ice. With its heavy gait and relatively
small steps, the bird is better adapted to the smooth sur¬
faces of sea ice than to the frequently broken contours
of the continental ice which, moreover, would prohibit
the semi-permanent winter groupings. Two colonies,
however, have chosen to install themselves on the con¬
tinent which unquestionably affords better conditions
and greater security than the surrounding ice floe.
In consequence of their extreme latitude, these habitats
have a particularly cold climate. The average annual
temperature at Point Geology (Adelie Land, 66" 40' S,
140° 1' E), where one of the most northernmost colonies
is found, is in the region of -12° C which is between
4 and 5 degrees lower than for the Cape Crozier colony
in the Ross Sea.
Generally speaking, temperature is the determining
factor in climate, but in the Antarctic, and especially in
Adelie Land, it is the wind which, by its regularity and
strength, plays the paramount rôle. Its speed at Point
Geology reaches between 30 and 33 feet per second, where¬
as 50 miles to the east, at Port Martin, it is twice as high.
At the latter station, the temperature is two degrees
lower than that at Point Geology although the latitude
Is virtually the same. This clearly highlights the cli¬
matic advantages of the places inhabited by the emperor
penguins and is surely one of the reasons which guided
their choice.
In the course of his extensive research in Adelie Land,
Dr. Sapin-Jaloustre examined the potentialities of wind
action by means of a heat loss calorimeter of his own
construction; this enabled him to define the cooling power
of various Antarctic environments. Some figures from his
notes indicate the fundamental importance of this for
warm-blooded creatures »living in the Antarctic climate.
Given a temperature of -10° C without wind, it takes
67 minutes 30 seconds for the temperature of the calori¬
meter's water to fall from 40 to 20 °C whereas it requires
only two minutes at -15° with a blizzard-laden wind of
85 m.p.h.
Dr. Sapin-Jaloustre's many experiments led him to con¬
clude that while wind may greatly accelerate cooling
power, its high ice-particle content multiplies this factor
twofold. The foregoing figures all relate to general cli¬
mate as defined by daily meteorological checks at a height
of 6J feet for temperature and 33 feet for wind.
Although the emperor penguins have chosen a specially
favourable point on the Adelie coast, it is certain that in
such an atmosphere they would, normally speaking, have
little chance of living and breeding. But since their
height is less than 3 feet, they are in fact subject to very
much more favourable climatic conditions, as revealed
by the surveys of micro-climates.
As early as 1950, Sapin-Jaloustre established that, while
temperature varied little in relation to height, the vertical
gradient of the wind, on the other hand, was very marked.
His study of the micro-climate in the colonies of Adelie
penguins (a micro-climate between ground level and
20 inches above) led to the conclusion that its thermal
demand was 50% lower than that of the general climate.
A few years later, we were able to observe that the same
was true for the emperor penguin colony. The wind at
a height of 8 inches was between 50 and 60% lower than
the reading given at the same moment by the anemo¬
meter at the meteorological station.
Apart from these climatic advantages, the choice of
breeding ground would seem to be motivated by a second
consideration as important as the first. The existence
near the colony of a permanent opening in the ice or of
stretches of water free from ice is apparently essential
19
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
PENGUINS
(Cont'd)
ZIG-ZAG TRAIL
left by tail and feet of
emperor penguin in
freshly fallen snow
betrays a waddling
gait. Yet despite
their short legs set
far back on their bod¬
ies, emperors move
along with a majestic
and dignified air
which probably earn¬
ed them their name.
Unlike some other
penguins, Adelies, for
instance, the empe¬
rors walk with their
flipper-like wings held
close to their bodies.
jft
20
to provide the birds and their young with regular food
supplies thoughout the year.
The adult emperor penguin is approximately 3'9" in
length, the males being slightly longer than the females.
Weight varies greatly according to the time of year. It
reaches a maximum on arrival at the colony when males
of 88 pounds and over are by no means rare, with the
maximum for females being 81 pounds. This variation
between the sexes persists throughout the year, the ave¬
rage weight being in the region of 55 pounds, and has the
advantage of greatly facilitating the determination of sex
in the absence of any sound indication. The sounds made
by the birds provide the only criterion for separating
males and females since there is no outward difference.
the emperor penguin Is a particularly calm
and apathetic creature which moves over the
ice slowly and with dignity. This heavy, swaying gait is
in sharp contrast to the speed and agility which the bird
displays in the water and his remarkably streamlined
body and his sleek plumage indicate the extent to which
his morphology is adapted to the aquatic environment.
The pectoral muscles are far and away the heaviest in
the body and have several important functions. They
cushion the bird's fall when, in order to get on to the
ice surface, he throws himself from the water and lands
on his breast. They also provide considerable power to
the paddles which they operate and which are used not
only for swimming but also during fights within the colony
when the paddle may strike an opponent with sufficient
strength to knock him down.
The coloration of the plumage is noteworthy. The
head, the back part of the body and the flippers are
covered with a very close blue-black plumage. Two wide
orange-yellow marks divide the lateral sides of the head
and meet in the region of the neck where their coloration
gradually fades into the pure white of the front of
the body.
One of the species' outstanding characteristics is the
reversal of the breeding cycle. The first emperor pen¬
guins return to the colony site in the month of March,
the beginning of autumn in the southern hemisphere,
when the sea ice has only been covering it for a short
time.
The birds at this point are particularly bulky on
account of the considerable quantity of fat reserves Which
may exceed 25% of the total weight of the body.
By April, the whole colony of some 13,000 birds has
assembled and its songs and cries shatter the monotonous
silence of the Antarctic coast. Each bird seeks a mate,
and, after a series of mating cries, the couple come toge¬
ther and remain together throughout the mating period.
The creation of such couples is sometimes accompanied
by fights provoked by the intrusion of a third bird, gene¬
rally female, competing with the first female and seeking
to oust her. These momentary conflicts end when the
fc ñ
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
PENGUIN NURSERIES
FOR BUSY MOTHERS
(1) Handsome emperor couple with their pure white bodies
and blue-black head plumage at the start of the breeding season.
(2) Parents take an anxious look at the 4 1/2 by 3 1/2 inch egg
which is incubated by the male (he maintains a fast for up to three
months before and during this period) and loses as much as
45% of his weight. (3) New-born chick peeps out from beneath
its parent's feet where It is sheltered during its first two months
of life. (4) Mother nourishes the chick from the pulpy mixture
of fish and crustaceans she has stored in her stomach during a
prolonged feeding period at sea. (5) A "huddle" of chicks who
quickly learn to emulate their parents by gathering together in
densely packed groups as a defence against the cold. (6) "Nur¬
sery" of youngsters whose parents are away hunting for food.
On return the parents "call" in front of the group until they
have located their own chick. Family life is thus maintained.
All photos © Jean Prévost
third bird, attracted by the call of a member of the
opposite sex, abruptly leaves the couple in peace.
When separated by a scuffle of some kind, the two
mates almost invariably manage to join up again soon
afterwards thanks to the calls they utter and aided by
their ability to recognize one another visually over short
distances.
Proof of this recognition was obtained by the use of
rings. In order to reduce the disturbance caused by this
operation, we habitually ringed couples after they had
been formed. The operation calls for three men, two to
capture the couple and a third to place the numbered
rings on the paddles. The two birds are then released
side by side in an isolated spot where they can more
easily come together fairly quickly.
The first laying of eggs takes place in May. Each female
lays one egg weighing approximately 1 pound and having
a length of 41 inches and a diameter of between 3 and
34 inches. This volume and weight explains why the
expulsion of the egg is often slow and difficult. Once the
egg is laid, the female entrusts it to her male partner
and leaves the colony in order to seek her food in the
sea. The females have eaten nothing since their arrival
and have lost almost 25% of their original weight.
There are, however, certain exceptions to this quasi-
general behaviour. In 1956, we had occasion to observe
several cases of laying by females whose partners, for
some unknown reason, were absent from the colony.
Such females may hatch the egg for a period of several
days but they soon abandon it in order to rejoin their
kind.
The incubation of the egg, assured almost wholly by
male birds, lasts for from 62 to 64 days at a temperature
above 30°C. To maintain this temperature, the egg is
placed on the feet of the brooder and protected from
behind by a sort of incubation pocket and in front by a
fold of abdominal skin. Even while carrying this fragile
burden, the male can cover short distances in an upright
posture and can even glide on his chest without dropping
the egg.
S|Ince the egg is hatched in the middle of
'winter, it is not surprising that the birds'
physical and vocal activity should be greatly reduced.
Additionally, the brooders have taken no food since their
arrival and can only do so when their task is taken over
by the females. How do they manage to go without food
for so long in such a chilling atmosphere? The system
they have found is as simple as it is effective.
To reduce as far as possible their loss of warmth during
blizzards, the birds gather in extremely densely packed
groups or "huddles." Each bird in such groups, which
may include virtually all the brooders of a given colony,
is pressed close against the others and benefits from the
warmth which they radiate. Since the group as a whole
is all but impermeable to wind, the micro-climate within
the "huddle" enables each individual bird to effect a
slight reduction in his central temperature and thus eco¬
nomise on his fat reserves.
In this way the duration of the foodless period may be
¡markedly prolonged. Various experiments, moreover,
showed us that a bird subjected to total isolation and
directly exposed to the cold and storms had little chance
of completing incubation of the egg since his daily loss
of weight could amount to twice that of those birds able
to join a "huddle."
Some of these experiments were carried out on a
breeding ground which we set up on the exact site of the
colony. Between 6 and 12 birds were kept within this
ground, thus forming a sort of small-scale colony with
very much reduced means of defence against the cold.
Some of our captives remained there for over three conse¬
cutive months.
This special social behaviour or forming "huddles"
has been made possible by the absence of nests and hence
of fixed dwelling places and by the reduction of the
antagonisms and conflicts which are so frequent and so
extreme among other species of Spheniscidae.
Having completed their journey in search of food, the
females return to the colony a few days before or after
the eggs are hatched. In the latter case, the death of 21
the chick might seem inevitable but, in fact, such is not
the case since the male bird's crop is capable of secreting
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
PENGUINS
(Cont'd)
FRIGID ENCOUNTER between an emperor penguin (who
manages to look stiff and haughty despite his moulting plumage)
and his smaller cousin, the Adelie penguin. Emperors average
3 feet 6 inches in height; Adelies are rarely more than 15 ins.
FIRST VENTURE into the ocean by young penguin chick (left) marks
his complete Independence. From now on he will hunt for his own food.
Penguins lose their clumsiness the moment they enter the water. Won¬
derful swimmers (right) they can catch fish under water with great ease.
THE SNOW EATERS (foreground, above) are demonstrating
an old penguin custom drinking from snowdrifts, by plunging
their beaks deep inside and swallowing snow whose temperature
Is often as low as -20 degrees C. Below, penguins taken from
main colony by French biologists for heat loss studies. These
showed that isolated birds exposed to cold and storms could
lose twice as much weight as those grouped in large "huddles".
Life-saving huddle
a whitish substance resembling pigeon's milk even after
a foodless period of as much as three months.
The exceptional nutritive quality of this emergency diet
enables the chick to wait for the pulpy mixture of fish
and crustaceans which the females have kept in their
stomachs during their time at sea for the benefit of the
young bird. In July, the thin and famished males (who
have lost almost 45% of their weight since arriving) set
off in turn for a period at sea.
While they take no food during their stay in the colo¬
ny, they do drink regularly, finding this liquid in snow
they take from small and especially clean drifts. They
plunge their beaks deep in the drifts and absorb quanti¬
ties of snow whose temperature is often as low as -20° C.
The "snow eaters" tend be more numerous when the
humidity level of the air is low and we observed that,
for some time preceding the thaw, the majority were
females. This need for water is probably due at that
time to the preparation of the constitutive elements of
the egg.
Chicks weigh approximately 11 ounces when hatched.
The scattered grey down which they have at birth gra¬
dually thickens with age and eventually forms a sort of
thick fur an inch or more long. During the first two
months, the young bird remains sheltered by the feet of
the male parent or the female who takes over periodically
in order that her mate can feed. These two months,
moreover, are not wholly free of danger. A certain
number of birds of both sexes, having lost their own
chicks, are determined to steal those of their neighbours.
They sometimes succeed, despite the parents' resistance,
but there is every chance of the chick being crushed or
pecked to death during the fight between the adults.
After September, the chicks are able to
maintain their internal temperature at a
constant level unaided. At this point they are left to
themselves in the colony. They weigh about 4è pounds
and are too bulky to remain any longer on the adult's
feet. This abrupt transition from family life to freedom
exposes them suddenly to cold and blizzards. The death
rate would therefore be relatively high but for the fact
that the young birds group together for protection in
"huddles" like the adults.
Most deaths observed at this period occur during
blizzards. The chicks, weakened by undernourishment,
no longer have the strength to gather In "huddles" ; they
accordingly lie down on the ice to which they are soon
attached by deposits of snow. This ice gangue insulates
them from the external atmosphere but thereby only
prolongs their sufferings. Other chicks fall in the cre¬
vasse which opens at low tide between the land ice and
the sea ice; we succeeded in saving a number from being
crushed by the closing of the break at high tide.
From September onwards, the two parents are able to
go away together hunting for food to satisfy the growing
appetites of their offspring. Even so this change to an
independent existence does not lead to a sort of communal
pooling, with each adult feeding a chick taken at random.
On the contrary, family life is maintained and, on
returning to the colony, each parent calls in front of
various groups of young emperors in order to locate its
own offspring. In this search by calling which varies In
length according to how far the colony is dispersed over
its territory, visual recognition also plays a part.
After these preliminaries are accomplished, the chick
slips his beak into that of the adult which thereupon
regurgitates a part of his or her stomach contents. The
chick rapidly grows to a weight of 22 pounds, at which
point he can consume up to 6 or 8 pounds in a single meal.
By the beginning of December he weighs close on
30 pounds and his down begins to fall by patches and is
replaced by young plumage. When the down has almost
completely disappeared, the young emperor (who, for
several days past, has no longer been fed by his parents)
moves towards the sea. He is then quite independent.
After spending a complete year on the edge of the ice
pack, during which period his weight almost triples, he
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
'^ESs o
** -Ai*
*4¿^-
-
Ail photos © Jean Prévost
ANTARCTIC RENDEZVOUS for thousands of emperor penguins Is in Marchstart of the Southern
Hemisphere's autumnwhen they gather at some 20 colony sites like that above at Point Geology in
Adelie Land (13,000 birds have been counted here). Penguin, below, looking like a block of stone, has
Its back to the howling blizzard. One youngster has strayed from its parents and crouches down in
the snow to the rear of the penguin in the foreground. The warm side is already occupied by another chick.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
FENGUINS (Cont'd;
Crushed by an iceberg
acquires adult plumage at the end of a month-long moult
on the coast.
While the death rate for eggs and chicks is low during
life in the colony (roughly one-quarter of 6,000 eggs laid),
life on the sea, where virtually all the predators are to be
found, brings a great increase in mortality. A premature
break-up of the sea ice, before all the chicks have finished
growing, may reduce the number of survivors still further.
But we also saw a still more impressive sight. On
December 26, 1952, a piece of an iceberg freed by the
break-up came hurtling down with a thunderous crash
onto a group of chicks and scores were crushed to death
or drowned.
The emperor penguin's biology, which was such a mys¬
tery a few years ago, can now be seen and understood
more clearly.
The reversal of the reproduction cycle, probably due
to the winter period spent on the sea ice, enables the
chicks born in July to complete their period of growth
by the time the ice break-up takes place. They can
therefore take immediate advantage of the abundant ma¬
rine life of the summer.
The adult's highly developed individual and social
adjustments enable him to live and breed in the middle
of the Antarctic winter with a relatively low death rate.
The emperor penguin is truly a remarkable bird.
JEAN PREVOST is a member of the biological research staff at
the National Centre for Scientific Research, Paris. M. Prévost
spent the winters of 1952 and 1956 at Terre Adélie as biologist
for the Expéditions Polaires Françaises. He made a special study
of the emperor penguin for his doctoral thesis, "L'Ecologie du
Manchot Empereur," which has been published by Hermann,
Paris, 1961.
THE STORY
OF ARTHUR
& HALF PINT
24
In 1952, Jean Prévost and the
members of the French Ant¬
arctic Expedition encamped
for the winter at Point
Geology, Adelie Land, decid¬
ed to become foster parents
to two young emperor penguins. Their purpose was to
study the effect of artificial rearing on the growth and
behaviour of these two chicks. "We had no trouble in
finding things for them to eat", writes Jean Prévost,
"for the ice around was strewn with food which the other
youngsters in the penguin colony had discarded as too
large to swallow."
"Our two chicks quickly learned to come in answer
to a special whistle and soon appeared to look on us as
their parents.
"Arthur and Half Pint, as we named them, lived like
this for five months without ever seeing the colony
where they were born. Arthur became rather shy, but
hunger quickly banished fear when mealtimes came.
"When we left Adelie Land to return to France we
took the chicks with us. But Half Pint, the weaker of
the two, died before we reached Australia. Arthur,
however, quickly got used to the heat of the Indian
Ocean which probably reminded him of the stove in our
camp against which he used to warm himself. But he
was no luckier than Half Pint and died of food poisoning
while the ship was docked at Port Said".
Fresco painting of Euphemius Mtatsmideli (958-1028
A.D.) an Important Georgian composer of religious
music. The musical notation used in Georgian mediae¬
val hymns has for long intrigued and puzzled scholars
and It was only recently successfully deciphered.
Manuscript of ancient hymns copied at the end of the
1 0th century under the direction of Michael Modre-
keli, a great Georgian poet and composer. Miniature
in the margin depicts John Mtbevari, a Georgian 1 0th
century hymnologist and St. Basilius of Caesarea, to
whom the hymns in this manuscript are dedicated.
Miniature of a 1 3th century Georgian manuscript
representing a dancer and his accompanying mu¬
sicians playing cymbals, a lute, a flute and a tabor.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
LOST HYMNS
OF GEORGIA'
A 1,000-year-old musical mystery
unravelled by a Soviet linguist
by Pavle Ingorokva
All photos furnished by the author
Faun playing an aulos (flute). 1st century A.D.
bronze found in Georgia. Flute is missing.
H ERODOTus, the Father of History, began his
great work with an »account of the relations
between the Greece and the Colchis of hoary antiquity,
a full thousand years before our era. Colchis the
legendary land of Medea and the Golden Fleece lay in
the west of Georgia. Its mention by Herodotus gives some
idea of ancient sources of Georgian culture.
Situated in the Caucasus, the crossroads of Europe and
Asia, Georgia is a land of European culture blended with
that of the East, a kind of synthesis of both traditions.
Georgia's links in distant antiquity, with the lands of
the classical East Assyria, Babylon, the empire of the
Hittites and Urartu can be seen from monuments of
material culture and the »testimony of cuneiform
inscriptions dating back to the second millenium B.C.
Another indication of ancient Georgia's links with the
West, the world of Hellenism, is the existence of such
well-known legends as the voyage of the Argonauts from
Greece to Colchis, which stems from the Homeric epos,
or the story of Prometheus, chained by order of Zeus to
a rock in the Caucasus. This wonderful legend originated
in Colchis, and found artistic expression in Aeschylus's
masterly tragedy.
Later, during the Hellenistic and the Roman periods,
Georgia was an indépendant state with a high level of
culture. In the first and second centuries A.D., Georgia
played an important part in Rome's relations with the
East, the political authority of the Georgian state being
spoken of by ancient authors, who described the honours
paid by the emperor Hadrian to Pharasman II, king of
Georgia, during the latter's visit to Rome in 138 A.D.
The Georgian ruler took part in an important religious
ceremony, offering a sacrifice in the Capitol, and having
an equine monument raised in his honour in the temple
of Mars.
Christianity became the State religion of Georgia in
337 A.D., and during mediaeval times it was one of the
leading countries of the Christian East. Unlike Byzantium,
Georgia also saw an efflorescence of secular literature,
especially in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries, which
may well be called the Golden Age of Georgian culture.
It was during the latter period that there developed a
humanistic current comparable with the Renaissance in
Europe, which came later. This was the era of Georgia's
great poet, Shota Rustaveli, the author of a poem of
genius The Knight in the Tiger-Skin, a new translation
of which is being prepared by Unesco. This work by
Rustaveli, who can justly be called a great bard of
humanism, was an early forerunner of the ideas of the
Renaissance.
An important place in the cultural heritage of ancient
Georgia is held by manuscripts of professional music,
which go back through the Middle Ages to antiquity.
These records consist of manuscripts of early Christian
hymns, with the verses of the texts accompanied by a
musical notation located over and under each line of the
text. The musical characters are in vermilion, as distinct
from the text, which is in black.
The nine extant manuscripts of ancient Georgian music
refer to the tenth and eleventh centuries. Five of them
are in Georgia, one is at the Monastery on Mt. Athos in
Greece, and three are in the library of the Convent of
St. Catherine in Sinai.
Of these manuscripts, the . most important are two in
the possession of the Manuscripts' Institute of the
Academy of Sciences of Georgia. One is a collection of
hymns copied in the years 978-88 under the guidance of
Michael Modrekeli, a great Georgian composer and poet.
The other is a collection, copied by Jordan at the close
of the tenth century. The repertory of these manuscripts
pertains in the main to the eighth, ninth and tenth
centuries. The notation used was found to be much
older. The manuscripts contain a total of- about 1,300
chorals, the repertory being very extensive.
The music recorded in such ancient manuscripts, and
the system of notation used »have long intrigued scholars,
but until recently all attempts to decipher them were
unsuccessful.
This interest was enhanced by the fact that the
evidence of history shows that ancient Georgian music
was quite independent in character, quite distinct from
Western, in particular Greek, music.
An 11th century source speaks of the existence of two
kinds of vocal music Greek and Georgian, the former
being homophonic, and the latter being sung in three
voices. It is a fact that from most ancient times the
peoples neighbouring on Georgia knew only homophonic
music. For instance Greek music, both antique and
mediaeval, »and for that matter right down to modern
times, was homophonic. The peoples of the East use
homophonic music to this day.
cONSEQUENTLY, Georgian music with its de-
iveloped polyphony both in folk songs and
church music, and its original harmonisation was an
exception to the environment, a kind of island in a sea
of homophony. The Christian church inherited this
polyphony from pagan practice. Ancient sources point out
that whenever the texts of church hymns were translated
into Georgian from the Greek, the accompanying music
was written anew, for, as a twelfth-century Georgian
source points out, "alien to our people are the Greek
incantations."
The deciphering of ancient Georgian musical notation
was preceded by an important discovery in the field of
ancient Georgian poetry, which helped to unravel the
mystery of the notation problem.
In the course of my research into the history of ancient
Georgian literature, I made a study of church hymns,
i. e. texts supplied with musical characters. At first the
hymns I studied interested me as literary monuments.
It should be noted that these hymns were always
considered purely prosaic works, because there was no
division into lines of verse in the manuscripts. In ancient
times, however, verse was not divided in separate lines;
this is borne out by manuscripts with ancient Georgian
iambics.
I found I could discern a complex rhythm in the hymnal
25
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
LOST HYMNS (Cont'd)
Pattern of dots
texts, and then saw that they had a definite metrical
structure. I also saw that the dots in the texts could not
be considered ordinary punctuation marks. They seemed
to have some other kind of function. When I counted
the number of syllables between the dots, I found a
definite pattern. Thus, in the first paragraph in one of
the hymns the number of syllables between the dots was
as follows: 7, 7, 7, 11, 7, 7, 5; the following paragraphs had
the same pattern, and so right through till the end of the
first canto of the hymn. Another text revealed the
following pattern: 5, 10, 5, 11, 5, 8, 10, and this was
repeated in all the paragraphs of the text.
All the hymns, without exception, were built on the
same kind of pattern.
It followed that the dots in the texts denoted their
metrical form unrhyming verses with a clear strophic
structure. Each strophe was followed by an antistrophe,
which repeated the metrical structure of the first strophe
with absolute fidelity.
This parallel-strophe structure is analogous to that of
the ancient Greek choral lyrics, and also of the verses
sung in ancient Greek tragedies.
It was in this way that the discovery was made of a
new and rich field of »ancient Georgian poetry the
hymnic.
The discovery of the metrical form in the hymns led
me up to the problem of how their musical notation was
to be deciphered the close link between musical and
metrical rhythm in ancient times is well known. In the
texts examined, too, the complex rhythm and the wealth
and variety of the rhythmical pattern, as well as the
metrical conformity of strophe and antistrophe, indicated
the presence of an unseparable link between the verses
and the accompaniment. The problem was to uncover the
secret of that music, whose surge could be felt in the
texture of the verses.
There was one musical character
whose meaning I realized before I
started work on the texts of the
hymns. I have already mentioned
that the texts were in black, and the
musical characters in vermilion. All
the black dots in the texts correspond¬
ed to a red dot in the musical nota¬
tion. There was absolute consistence
in this relationship, so the evidence
seemed to show that each red dot had a metrical function.
To start with, I copied out and classified all the charac¬
ters, of which I found eighteen (including those indicating
variations). A detailed comparison of these characters
with those current in the musical notation used in
mediaeval Europe showed that they were quite different,
and, what was of special significance, the Georgian
characters were fewer in number than the European. It
was »clear that the former differed not only in outline
but in structure.
After long consideration as to why the Georgian musical
characters were fewer in number than the European,
I reached a conclusion that put me on the right track.
I realized that the Georgian characters were few in
number because Georgian notation was based on a
musical alphabet, distinct from the other mediaeval
Ghelatl, ancient centre
of Georgian music.
systems of notation, which were not alphabetic, but
hieroglyphic.
The first step lay in establishing the frequency of the
characters used in the notation how many times each
character was used in all the cantos of the manuscripts
with musical notation, and the number of syllables to each
character.
This count revealed that there were eight basic
characters in the system of notation, the others being
ancillary and rarely used. The supplementary characters
were not independent, but were a graphic variation of
the basic characters.
The discovery of eight basic musical characters or notes
confirmed the original surmise that the Georgian musical
notation was alphabetic, and the fact of eight characters
coming to light was an indubitable indication that the
notation was based on the octave the eight characters
represented the eight notes of the octaval scale.
This important step along the road to the uncovering
of the secret of the ancient musical notation of Georgia
was followed by an inquiry into the order of the notes
in the octave.
The octaval scale, as is well known, falls into two parts
the lower tetrachord or diatonic series of four tones,
and the upper tetrachord, also of four tones.
6(3»;-)
2
6(34-3)
i f r r~r
Í n tí tí
» r
3¿-3fl£ 33 -3íl-ey¿-s?3
zz:
tí tí
	&
M-]p-<zn
3^
e ^
ü o
\
n -
Modern transcription of a hymn composed by Gregori
Khandsteli (758-860) a composer of mediaeval Georgia.
The notation of the leading melody (leader of the voices)
or "cantus firmus" is given in the centre (above the
original 1 0th century notation). This hymn was noted
down by members of the Georgian Society of Church
Music in the 19th century. Parts for the accompanying
voices are noted here on the upper and lower staves.
The Georgian notation under discussion also has the
same division of eight notes into two series. One series
of four characters is written below the line, which makes
it obvious that it corresponds to the lower series of the
octave; four characters are written above the line, thus
giving us the upper series of the octave.
Next came the question of the order of the four
characters in the lower series, and the four of the upper
series.
This was ascertained from the shape of the characters.
As was to have been expected, and indeed proved to be
the case, the notes were not a chance array of characters,
but followed a definite system, which showed that the
graphical aspect of the Georgian notes was built to suit
the octaval structure. Indeed, the order of the notational
characters emerged from the graphical links between the
individual signs, the gradual transition from one to
another.
The coincidence of characters
does not stop at this stage.
and musical pattern
GEORGIAN NOTATION
The first four signs of the oc¬
tave were placed below the line. ?
26 V ^ \ The last four signs of the oc¬
tave were placed above the line.
The signs (left) which resemble modern shorthand writing are, in fact, ancient
musical notes. Each one of the eight signs shown either above or below the
centre line corresponds to one of the eight notes in the octaval scale in the
Georgian musical notation of the Middle Ages. This notation which might be
called "alphabetic" was a distinct advance on the "hieroglyphic" systems of
mediaeval notation (where a sign represented a group of notes or even several
musical phrases). The first four notes of the octave (the lower ones) become
simpler and smaller in size as they ascend and the last four (above the line)
gradually increase in size and become more complex in form as they ascend
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
;A~ Tl&fmw&Êm&na.,, J^Y^f^"-",i v-> " -.«&- 1 \>\ \| ~ N
v .p>fJMn .^~ .£***~~% -ry f '^..^u. .¿fr .^. .^^ , rç TI
^Ci^^.^^r Â. ¿ja	 jj ,w>A 	 /' . \ ..... .
Part of a hymn composed in the I Oth century by Michael Modrekeli and entitled "The Resurrection
of Christ." The meaning of these strange little musical characters written In red and placed above
or below the texts Inscribed in black, and their melodies remained a mystery for over 1,000 years.
The extreme characters, i. e. the first in the lower series
and the last, the eighth in the upper series are related in
outline. The eighth sign repeats the outline of the first
with the addition of a pennant. The parallel is logical,
since an inverted prime »becomes an octave.
The sequence of the signs was checked in other ways.
It has »been observed that the sign for the fifth tone of
the octave is of far more frequent occurence in church
incantations than the octaval, since the fifth forms, as it
were, the centre of the »melody in church music which
accounts for its having been called the dominant.
Further: the tonic, i. e. the prime or the eighth note
in the octave should be heard in the concluding measure
or bar of each hymn. This was also found in the nota¬
tion under discussion.
Thus, success attended the efforts made to establish
the sequence of musical characters in the notation. This
was the second step towards achievement of the aim set.
Further study of ancient Georgian sources enabled me
to find out the names of the signs and the notes of the
octave, which fully bore out the conclusions drawn from
the decipherment.
The next and most radical step was to determine the
tone denoted by each particular character, I.e. to find
the "key" to a reading of the octaval notes.
In the early stages of the inquiry I
noticed that the first line of each hymn
contained an indication of the voice it was
to be sung on. In all, eight voices were
named a sure indication of the diatonic
tonality typical of the music of the ancient
Christian church. Each "voice" provided
a precise indication of the way the signs
of the octaval gamut were to be read. It
follows that the "voices" in the ancient
Georgian notation performed the function of the keynote
in present-day musical notation.
This was the final step made towards the decipherment
of the musical notation used in ancient Georgia. It was
clear that the inscription as to the "voice" to be used
showed the existence of eight tones of the octave within
each voice. Indeed, eight characters were deciphered in
the manuscripts, all this bearing out the correctness of
the conclusions drawn.
It thus became possible to express the hymnic melodies
in notation. Just as in Roman Catholic church music
until the thirteenth century, in which only the leading
voice, the tenor or Cantus firmus was recorded in nota¬
tion, the Georgian manuscripts had the leading melody
in notation (the so-called dzlispiri the "leader of the
voices") the accompanying voices following the set
pattern of the Georgian folk harmonisation, and provid¬
ing a background to the melody.
Reading of the musical texts now became possible, so
I began to transpose the tenth-century notation into
Woman playing
the aulos.
A Georgian lute.
modern notation. I began with a hymn in honour of the
Virgin Mary, entitled. Gikharoden ("Ave Maria"), and I
cannot find words to express the thrill of first hearing
melodies dating back a thousand years.
Had the decipherment been false, the result would have
been a mere jumble of sounds. As it was, I heard a
splendid and impressive melody. In all the eighty hymns
I next deciphered, the result was the same music marked
by integrity and depth of thought.
I then decided to find out whether the ancient tradition
had been preserved in the church melodies used in
Georgia in the 19th. and 20th. centuries, and, if so, which
elements, and what relation existed betweeu the ancient
style and the modern.
The appropriate texts were
found at various libraries in Geor¬
gia. Among the numerous records
of 19th century church music that
were examined, over 300 hymns
with three-part music were discov¬
ered, whose texts coincided with
those of the 10th century hymns
analyzed. They had been taken
down in notation in the 19th century by members of the
national society of Georgian church music.
To what period does the invention of the ancient
Georgian musical notation belong? What place does
this music occupy in world musical culture?
The evidence available indicates that the Georgian
notation departed from the ancient Greek system, and
developed into an independent system of notation at the
beginning of our era.
The new element in the Georgian system of notation
lay in the application of the purely octaval principle,
which facilitated a more accurate expression of musical
notes, and made it possible to reduce the clumsy Greek
system of 23 basic signs to a system of eight characters.
Further, the antique notation had letter-like signs,
which made it possible to take down the text of music
for the purpose of study, but was ill adapted for reading
at sight. The Georgian system made up for this
shortcoming in the ancient Greek system, whose letter¬
like characters were replaced by simpler signs, which rise
and fall, their outlines facilitating visual perception of the
flow of the voice. Just as in the modern staves, a
definite system of characters helps us to visualise the
rise and fall in the vocal pitch, whereas the ancient Greek
notation had all the characters linearly located above the
text. This was a signal achievement. Ancient Georgian
church music, holds pride of place with the most ancient
musical cultures of the world.
Dr. PAVLE INGOROKVA of the Institute of Ancient Manu¬
scripts, Georgian Academy of Sciences, is an outstanding Soviet 27
authority on Georgian literature and linguistics and has deciphered
Hittite inscriptions on Georgian archaeological finds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE TREASURY OF ASIAN STORY
ASIA is the home of the short story.
Hundreds, and in some cases thou¬
sands, of years before Maupassant
and Chekhov, tales that were short stories
in the modern sense of the term were not
only being told in the market places but
were being put into writing in ancient Egypt,
in other countries which today speak
Arabic, in Israel, in China, and in Japan.
The riches of the classical short story of
the Far East are still, for the most part,
unknown in the West...
Although in certain great Asian cultures,
and in particular India and Persia, story¬
telling was first developed in other genres:
in the epic poem, the fable and the drama,
if we consider Asia as a whole, we may
well say that since ancient times the short
story form has never died...
Dozens of stories in the Bible, the Apo¬
crypha and the Arabian Nights, when
translated into living English, are revealed
as gems of the story-teller's art...
In China in particular there has been a
continuous two-thousand-year development
from the anecdotes, fables, 'myths, and
legends of earliest antiquity to the accom¬
plished stories of the twentieth century.
That the art of the Asian story-teller
is still a fruitful and powerful one is amply
evident from contemporary writing. In
many Asian lands the short story is now
the form of literary expression, yielding
only to poetry in others. There has
obviously been much influence on contem¬
porary writers by the European and Amer¬
ican masters of the genre, but the
influence of local tradition is equally strong.
A Treasury of Modern Asian Stories
(edited by D.L. Milton and W. Clifford,
Mentorbooks, New American Library, New
York), from the foreword of which the above
is. extracted gives convincing evidence of
the story-telling riches of the Asian conti¬
nent in its thirty tales selected from the
literatures of twelve countries and sixteen
different languages. As the editors of the
Treasury point out, they had thousands of
pages of stories, an enormous wealth of
material, to choose from. "It is high time",
they say, "that the world got to know of
the riches of Asian short-story writing, high
time indeed that not one but a number of
anthologies were published, at least one for
each country and one for each literature."
This, in a work published simultaneously
in England, the United States and Japan,
Unesco has now done for the Japanese
short story. Modem Japanese Stories *
published as part of the Unesco Collection
of Representative Works, is the fruit of
several years of co-operative activities by
the Literary Advisory Board of the Japanese
National Commission for Unesco, the
editor, Dr. Ivan Morris, Professor of Japa¬
nese history and literature at Columbia
University, New York, and his team of fine
translators.
Before the work of translating was begun,
the Japanese National Commission for
Unesco consulted a Board consisting of
the greatest men of letters of contemporary
Japan, and they, together with the editor,
finally narrowed down the choice to one
representative story of twenty-five import¬
ant writers. The result is a thorough
introduction to Japanese fiction in this
century, and, in a sense, a picture of the
contemporary Japanese mind.
MODERN JAPANESE FICTION
A break with tradition
by Ivan Morris-
T
JL i
28
he present literary scene in Japan is one of
immense activity. Publishers and literary
magazines abound, and the number of novels and stories
published every year is overwhelming. With books
extremely cheap an average novel costs the equivalent
of 6s. ($1.00) and of Is. 6d. (25 cents) in a paper¬
backed edition and the reading public large and alert,
sales are vastly in excess of those before the war; the
material rewards for literary success are considerable.
Some of the most substantial incomes in Japan are at
present earned by popular writers.
This situation is not without its dangers dangers
almost as great as those that beset the economically hard-
pressed writers before the war. There is a considerable
risk that "pure literature" (as it is rather primly termed
in Japan) will still further lose audiences to commercial
literature and to the so-called "middle novels," which
occupy a place somewhere between the artistic and the
popular.
In order to earn money many of the best writers
produce serial novels for newspapers and magazines of
large circulation. Sometimes an author will be working
on two or more serial novels at the same time, as well as
turning out articles on assorted subjects from birth
control to Japanese-American relations, giving lecture
tours and dashing off occasional stories to satisfy the
requests of the numerous literary and semi-literary
magazines.
One popular novelist recently became so confused by
the number of different things he was writing
simultaneously that he inadvertently changed the nam-i
of the main character in the middle of one of his serial
novels an error that was not caught up in proof and
which caused considerable bewilderment to his readers.
For the successful Japanese writer it never rains, it
pours. To remain successful he cannot afford to be long
out of the public eye, and the artistic energy necessary to
produce serious work is often dissipated by commercial
demands. Such conditions are, of course, not limited to
Japan, but the lack of solid tradition in modern Japanese
literature adds to the danger. Fortunately the risk of
total commercialization is recognized and deliberately
resisted by a number of the better authors.
The shi-shosetsu tradition of semi-autobiographical
"fiction" has survived into the post-war period, but it
is no longer as widely followed as some decades ago.
Most contemporary writers seem to be aware of the need
for a wider approach than is usually manifested in the
"I-novel" and the "I-story." Nevertheless, the confes¬
sional, diary type of writing, in which everything is seen
through the eyes of one lone, sensitive individual,
continues to be far more popular in Japan than in the
West.
After 1945 the torrent of translations from foreign
languages, which naturally subsided during the war,
reached new heights. Novels, plays, short stories and
poems from almost every country in the world were
translated and published for a public whose appetite had
been whetted by the years of official zenophobia and
isolation. The choice of books for translation was often
indiscriminate, sometimes incomprehensible. Nevertheless
in the influx a large mass of worthwhile literature from
the outside world has been made available.
To what extent, then, is current Japanese literature
influenced by that of the West? In the first place, it
should be emphasized that on the whole the influence is
not nearly as direct as is often assumed by Western
readers. Japan has now had some seventy years in which
to absorb the literary traditions of the West. European
and American literature have come to be taken for
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
ELLING
Among the twenty-five authors repres¬
ented are some who are already fairly well-
known outside of Japan, for example
Tanizaki, Kawabata, and Mishima, each of
whom have had novels translated by
Unesco, and Akutagawa and Kikuchi, both
of whom have had famous films, such as
Rashomon and The Gates of Hell, based
on their work. The reader will also find
stories of exceptional power and originality
by men equally deserving of world-wide
recognition, as Mori, Shiga, Muro, Niwa,
Sakaguchi, Inoué and Dazai.
The book also contains a long critical
"Introduction to Japanese Literature" (from
which the article below has been taken),
brief biographies of each of the twenty-
five authors, and a selective bibliography of
modern Japanese literature translated into
English. The whole forms a most attractive
and helpful guide to modern Japanese
writing.
* Published by Eyre and Spottiswoode,
London ; Charles Tuttle, Tokyo, and Rut¬
land, Vermont, U.S.A. (Price 30/-, $6.50.)
BOOKSHOP BUSTLE in Tokyo reflects the
Immense activity of the present literary scene
in Japan where publishers and literary maga¬
zines abound, books are cheap and the reading
public large and alert. Swarming book-buyers
here are crowding into a used book fair on
the Kanda, Tokyo's famous bookshop section.
The Japan Times Weekly, Tokyo
granted, and works from the outside no longer carry the
aura of the exotic and the startling that they had in the
early days of importation. Even more important, Ja¬
panese writers now have their own great literary figures
Natsume Soseki, Mori Ogai, among others (1). They can
now look back with a sense of belonging to an indigenous,
if recent, tradition.
Although in many ways the Pacific War and its
aftermath constituted a break with the past as great or
even greater than that provided by the Meiji Restoration
(1867-1910) there was no rupture with native literary
tradition such as occurred in the 19th century. Whereas
the new Meiji writers tended to look entirely to the West
for their models, the writers of the present day receive
their influence both from the West and from their own
writers of the past sixty years.
Even in the early days of importation, literary influence
in Japan rarely produced slavish imitation of certain
specific European or American models. It was usually a
much more indirect and complex process. As the young
post-war writer. Mr. Mishima Yukio, has pointed out,
Japanese novelists have usually assimilated only those
elements of foreign literature that are in some way close
to the recipient. This is more than ever true today when
the Japanese writer has such an immense selection of
world literature at his disposal.
Although the most conspicuous influences have certainly
come from Europe, it would be a mistake to discount
the effect of Chinese and Japanese classical literature on
certain modern writers. This classical influence is re¬
flected in the imagery, the descriptions, the general mood
and sometimes the structural techniques of many
(1) All names are given in the normal Japanese order, with
the family name preceding the personal one.
outstanding post-Meiji writers and their successors. One
of the most Interesting aspects of writers like Nagai Kafu,
Tanizaki Junichiro and Kawabata Yasunari is precisely
the way in which they succeeded in moulding classical
traditions with modern Western thoughts and technique.
However, the fact remains that the modern Japanese
novel and story are essentially Western forms; in so far
as literary influence has played a part, most Japanese
prose writers are indebted to modern Western literature
far »more than to their own country's classical tradition.
It is writers like Hugo, Poe, Whitman, Baudelaire, Dos¬
toievsky, Tolstoy, Hardy, Zola, Huysmans, Maupassant,
Wilde and D. H. Lawrence that have exercised influence
rather than Murasaki Shikibu, Saikaku, Bakin, and the
other famous prose writers of earlier centuries.
The. remark made in 1910 by Natsume Soseki, one of
the most important of the post-Meiji novelists, could well
be uttered by the vast majority of modern Japanese prose
writers: "What governs my mind at this. moment, what
will influence all my future work, is not, alas, the tradition
of my ancestors, but, rather, thoughts brought over from
across the sea, and by an alien race."
But few post-war writers in making this statement
would be inclined to include Soseki's expression of regret.
Japan is, of course, not the only country in which
imported literature has exerted an influence, but the
historical conditions of the Meiji Period made this
influence of primary importance. As Mr. Mishima (who
among the younger writers is particularly conscious of his
own country's classical heritage) has said, "In most other
countries there exists a strong literary tradition into
which writers can assimilate whatever is imported. In
Japan our literature does not rest on any such tradition. 29
Although our talented writers have managed to utilize
their abilities individually, there are very few of them who
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A CENTURY OF CHANGE IN WRIT¬
ING. After 1868 Japan's efforts to become
"modern" led to a sharp break with a past
epitomized by the traditionally garbed figures
depicted above in this painting by the 19th-
century artist Kyoden. The main effect of
Western influence was to encourage Japanese
writers to describe more realistically the
brave new world they saw growing about
them. Realism gave way to naturalism and,
after the First World War, to a school of
writing whose chief concern was the social
condition of city workers, seamen and farm
workers (right). Students (opposite) in a Tokyo
bookshop reflect today's book boom, with
sales vastly exceeding pre-war figures and large
material rewards crowning literary success.
Maupassant : a bombshell in Japanese letters
have managed to ground their works on secure tradition."
In Japan, as in most other countries, the story or tale
has an extremely long and varied history. Among the
earliest collections that have come down to us (leaving
aside ancient mythological collections where the literary
motive is secondary) are those from the Heian Period
(794-1185 A.D.) in which brief prose passages serve to
provide the background for thirty-one syllable classical
poems or to link a series of such poems by means of
rudimentary plots.
The Tales of Isé from the ninth century is the best-
known example; The Tales of Yamato (tenth century)
belongs to the same tradition; The Tales of Tsutsumi
Chunagon (which Includes the charming and original
fragment "The Lady Who Loved Insects") is a collection
of ten stories with well-defined plots and considerable
realism.
In the eleventh century Tales of Past and Present,
consisting of over 1,000 stories taken from Indian, Chinese
and Japanese history and folklore, represents a considera¬
ble advance in construction over the lyrical tales of the
early Heian Period. Otogi-Zoshi is the generic term for
collections of popular stories, most simply fairy-tales,
that were in circulation during the Muromachi Period
(c. 1300-1600).
±n a more recent period the numerous collec¬
tions of stories by Ihara Saikaku (1642-93) deal
in a more or less realistic way with the lives of contem¬
porary men and women, mostly members of the
seventeenth century townsman class. Tales of the
Moonlight and the Rain (1776), a famous collection of
nine ghost stories by Ueda Akinari, belongs to a tradition
of supernatural tales that goes back to the eighth
century (2).
We should also take note of a common form that is to
be found in much of Saikaku's work and elsewhere. This
consists of a collection of stories having a common thread
or theme; a typical example is Saikaku's Reckonings That
Carry Men Through The World (Seken Munesanyo, 1693),
which is a volume of twenty independent stories all
30 (2) The English translation is to be published by the Cam¬
bridge University Press in the Unesco Collection of Represen¬
tative Works Japanese series.
dealing with the torments that different groups of
characters experience on the last day of the year when
all debts become due for payment.
Despite this ancient and diverse tradition, the modern
Japanese story form in this century owed remarkably
little to the various -pre-Meiji collections of which exam¬
ples have been given above. It is true that a number of
the Meiji Period writers (including Higuchi Ichiyo, Ozaki
Koyo, Koda Rohan and Tayama Katai) recognized in
Saikaku's stories the same vigorous realism that they had
found in modern French literature.
Saikaku's realism, however, served to confirm such writers
in their already established literary approach, rather than
to inspire them. When it actually came to writing stor¬
ies, the main influences derived, not from Saikaku or the
other pre-Meiji masters of realistic fiction, but from the
recent literature of Europe and America.
The history of the modern story in Japan can be
considered to date from the introduction of Maupassant's
work in the 1890's. One of the earliest writers to attempt
to produce in Japanese the type of story that was current
in Europe was Mori Ogai, who after his return from
Germany in 1888 did so much to familiarize Japanese
readers with Western literary forms.
Of the two masters of the late nineteenth century short
story in Europe, Maupassant exerted considerably greater
influence in Japan than Chekhov. The reason is not far
to seek: the introduction of Maupassant's short stories
coincided with the rise of Naturalism in Japanese litera¬
ture and, indeed, was one of the important influences in
this movement. It was Maupassant's direct, realistic and
often harsh approach to his material that affected Japa¬
nese writers, rather than his mastery of the short story
form itself.
Although Maupassant, like Chekhov, regarded the short
story as being a genre in itself and although he contribut¬
ed so greatly to giving it the characteristic form with
which we are now familiar, his early influence in Japan
did not on the whole lead writers to make the clear
differentiation between the novel and the short story
that is accepted in the West.
The line of »demarcation in Japan between the two
genres has always tended to be vague. This is reflected
in the terminology. Both forms are known as shosetsu,
the word for short story being differentiated only by the
prefix tampen (short piece). Shosetsu Is also used with
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Photos Unesco - Marc Riboud
the prefix chuhen, (middle piece) to describe an inter¬
mediate length of work having about, 40,000 to 60,000
words; this roughly corresponds to what is sometimes
known as novelette, but the form is very much more
popular in Japan than in the West.
Thus there is a regular continuum from tampen-
shosetsu through chuhen-shosetsu to shosetsu. The only
real differentiation is in the matter of length, which
itself tends to be very indefinite. This is not simply a
matter of terminology, but extends to the conception or
rather, lack of conception of the short story as a distinct
literary form. Very frequently we find the same piece of
fiction being described alternatively as a novel and as a
short story.
One result of this vague differentiation is the absence
from so many Japanese stories of certain stylistic qua¬
lities that we have come to regard as essential to the
modern short story in the West. This is certainly not to
suggest that the story is a narrow form with certain
strictly defined rules or cannons. Far from it. A genre
that so greatly antedates the novel is bound to have enor¬
mous flexibility.
T;he history of the story in the West goes back
to the Tales of the Magicians (from the Egypt
of almost 4,000 years ago) and traces its complex descent
through Aesop, Boccaccio, Chaucer, the Bible and La
Fontaine, to name only a few of the great landmarks.
Any neat definition is both impossible and undesirable.
As the well-known short-story writer, Kay Boyle, has
said, "The only continuity it (the story) possesses is that
it was isolated individuals, sometimes writing centuries
apart, who spoke with freshness and vigour, In a short-
winded rather than a long-winded form, of people, and
ideas, and incidents, which seemed to the reader moving
and true."
Since the time of Gogol, however, the story has develop¬
ed in a certain manner that we may characterize as the
"style of the modern Western short story." Its outstand¬
ing feature is an economy of means. This has involved
a tendency to compression, to the dropping of inessen¬
tials. The tendency has continued until the present day
and has been given particular impetus by the short
stories of Ernest Hemingway, whom Mr. H.E. Bates
describes as the "man with an axe... (who) cut out a
whole forest of verbosity" (H. E. Bates: "The Modern
Short Story".)
Without economy there can be no short story in the
modern sense of the term. This, of course, does not pre
clude the existence of short stories of considerable length.
The tendency since the time of Tolstoy has certainly been
In the direction of brevity, but the modern story may vary
from a few hundred words to 15,000 or even 20,000. What
is essential Is the close construction, the casting of all
the material round a single central image and the overall
compression that have become the marks of the success¬
ful modern short story in the West.
By these general standards a considerable proportion
of tampen-shosetsu are not short stories at all; frequently
they appear to be sketches, essays or truncated novels.
A large number of Japanese story writers are primarily
novelists for whom stories tend to be what Miss Elizabeth
Bowen has called "side-issues from the crowded imagin¬
ation."
Since the novel and the modern short story are two
totally different genres it is most unlikely that a writer
will be equally at home in both, and this applies in Japan
quite as much as in the West. The plethora of literary
magazines in Japan has encouraged many writers to
produce stories when their style was better suited to the
novel. As a result, their work often lacks the stylistic
compression that is the essence of the modern short story.
This is not primarily a matter of word-length (though
it is worth noting that Japanese stories are as a rule far
longer than their modern Western counterparts,) but
of failure to apply the indirect, suggestive and dramatic
methods which are indispensable for economy of style.
In a country that has produced the most compressed
forms of poetry In world literature, it is remarkable that
stories should so frequently be marked by a turgid verbo¬
sity which cries out for the ministration of a red pencil.
Fortunately a number of good modern writers in Japan
have treated the short story as an equal and separate
genre of literature, not merely as an abbreviated novel or
as a sketch. Of the authors represented In Modern
Japanese Stories, the three who stand out in Japanese
letters as short-story writers are Shiga Naoya, Akutagawa
Ryunosuké and Nakajima Ton.
The fact that these three writers are all masters of
literary style is not irrelevent. Like the poem, the short
story is undoubtedly a type of writing in which style or
form is all-important. An indifferently written or poorly
constructed novel may impose by the ingenuity of its plot,
by the evocation of some unusual scene or atmosphere or
again by the vivid portrayal of a character; but a badly
written short story is almost bound to fail, regardless of
its content.
31
This article may notbe reproduced withoutpermission.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
SPACE TRAVEL
& CONTAMINATION
Sir,
Today when we not only have a win¬
dow but also a door towards space, there
are two related problems your worthy
publication could help us with.
Can space vehicles be entirely sterilized
so that not a single microbe escapes to
contaminate possible discoveries ? Are
they? Would not researchers themselves
carry contaminating microbes on their
explorations?
In reverse, what are the chances of
bringing to earth dormant microbes to
which man has developed no resistance
through cohabitation of the planet, and
which, if given the proper conditions on
earth, would rapidly devastate us?
These can no longer be considered
science fiction problems. The Unesco
Courier alone can deal with these topics
with the authority of the world scientific
organization. I have much appreciated
the treatment you accorded to other mat¬
ters of world concern.
George R. Schäfer
Montreal, Canada
Ed. note: A special issue on the Conquest
of Outer Space is in preparation.
FREEDOM FROM FEAR
Sir,
The mass of the world's people are
now tortured by fear as they never were
before. This fear psychology has built
itself into a widespread neurosis in which
the fear of nuclear war, with the appre¬
hension and dread of the inconceivable
horror of its aftermath, has resulted in
deeply disturbing feelings of frustration,
insecurity, hatred and suspicion, and these
feelings are the direct cause of a resur¬
gence of war hysteria, race hatred, juve¬
nile delinquency and crime and general
discord and disregard of human rights.
To survive, it is up to us to replace our
much-used negative emotions of fear,
hatred, suspicion and deceit, with our
slightly used endowments of reason and
judgment, tolerance and understanding,
together with the will to get along toge¬
ther and to sincerely extend compassion
and goodwill to all our fellowmen. These
are the only ways left us sanely to settle
international disputes, and we had better
start to use them right now.
Rufus J. Bean
Pabellón, Mexico
ARGENTINA SALUTES TAGORE
Sir,
We were surprised to see in the Decem¬
ber, 1961 issue of The Unesco Courier,
dedicated to Rabindranath Tagore, that
no mention was made of the homage paid
to his memory in Argentina by the- Com¬
mission formed in. this country to cele-
32
brate the centenary of his birth. We en¬
close a list of tributes paid to Tagore.
Victoria Ocampo
President, Executive Commitee,
Argentine Commission of Homage
to Tagore on the Centenary of
his Birth
Ed. note: This information not having
been communicated to Unesco earlier,
The Unesco Courier could not include it
in its Tagore issue. We are glad to do so
now. Argentina's centenary celebrations
included the presentation of Tagore's play
"The King's Postman" at the Teatro Na¬
cional de Comedia; a series of eight lec¬
tures at the National Museum of Decor¬
ative Arts, where reproductions of Ta-
gore's paintings and original manuscripts
were displayed; the publication of
Tagore's Birthday Book and of 13 poems
from Puravi; a special issue of the liter¬
ary magazine, Sur, devoted to Tagore; the
publication of a book, Tagore on the
Slopes of San Isidro, by Victoria Ocampo;
the issue of a record with poems from
Gitanjali, recited in English, French and
Spanish, the naming of a street in San
Isidro and the issue of a stamp bearing
his t portrait.
SAVE EGYPT'S MONUMENTS
Sir,
I feel that Egypt is my true home and
I can almost believe that I lived there
2,000 or 3,000 years ago. So I would hate
to see the treasures, temples and palaces
of Egypt destroyed by the waters of the
Aswan Dam. I am only thirteen years
old and so too young to do anything
about it. But as someone who loves that
beautiful country, I ask you to speak
out against the construction of the dam.
Jacqueline Lagrandie
Sarlat, France
Ed. note: Why disagree with the
building of a dam which is so badly
needed in Egypt? It is far better to object
to the destruction of the temples of Abu
Simbel and to do everything possible to
save them'
MULTILINGUAL PROBLEMS
Sir,
I refer to the letter from »Mr. John C.
de V. Roberts which you published in
your February issue. As an editor of
other publications I know only too well
your difficulties in producing the same
publication in several languages. An arti¬
cle written in one language, when trans¬
lated and made to fit a pre-arranged
space, might sometimes give the impres¬
sion of padding.
Only this month I had an article writ¬
ten for me by a well-known French jour¬
nalist on a French subject. The original
manuscript was, in my opinion, brilliant,
but I had to use it in English. Although
the subject matter is interesting, the au¬
thor's individual style has been lost and
I am less satisfied with the result.
Regarding the suggestion that you need
better authors, a perusal of one or two
back numbers chosen at random produces
such names as »Ritchie Calder, Madame
Desroches-Noblecourt, L.P. Kirwan, Sir
Julian Huxley, A.W.F. Banfield, André
Maurois, Enrique Lafuente Ferrari. All
these are acknowledged experts in their
own fields and any editor would be proud
to put them amongst his contributors. In
my opinion, you do an extremely diffi¬
cult job exceptionally well.
Reg Holmes
London, England
WOMEN IN PURDAH
Sir,
After reading your article, "Moslem
Women" (March 1961) I feel obliged to
make a few corrections concerning Pakis¬
tan. I returned to France in 1961, after
spending three years in »Pakistan includ¬
ing two and a half at Multan, the third
largest city in western Pakistan, and my
memories and impressions of Pakistani
women are still very fresh.
I do not agree with Mrs. Anne-Marie
Hussein. What she says is partly true no
doubt of Karachi, Lahore, Rawalpindi
and Peshawar, where half the women
one meets are unveiled. As for the rest
of the country, and especially Multan, I
don't think I have seen more than ten
women out of purdah during the whole
of my stay. And there is little hope of
improvement. On the contrary.
Wives of doctors or railway engineers
and women teachers in girls' schools, who
do not wear the veil in Karachi or
Lahore, are obliged to do so here or they
would be insulted and even molested in
the street. Schoolgirls go to college in
purdah. It is a strange sight.
J. Theureau
Annecy, France
JUNIOR UNESCO COURIER
Sir,
While I have an unbounded admiration
for Unesco, I do not care so much for
The Unesco Courier and have decided
to discontinue my subscription. I am a
schoolmaster in charge of the school
library where we have included the Cou¬
rier for the past year, among our other
periodicals; but I have decided to stop
our subscription. My experience is that
it is little read and this, I think, is due
to its unattractive lay-out. The photo¬
graphs are not too clear, the print is
uninteresting in appearance, and the sub¬
ject-matter does not beckon the child to
read it. Nevertheless, I do not apply
these criticisms on behalf of adults, for
whom the Courier is a valuable perio¬
dical.
Have you thought of producing a
Junior Courier?
E. H. Warne
Upminster, England
Ed. note: A Junior Unesco Courier has
been the subject of discussion by both
the Secretariat of Unesco and the Gene¬
ral Conference. This is a highly complex
problem which is still being studied.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
REMINISCENCES BY A FRIEND OF TAGORE
Sir,
Returning from a lecture tour on
Tagore in Finland, Norway and Sweden,
I saw your number (December, 1961)
with pictures and articles on my
"Gurudev" which put me in a
reminiscent mood. Perhaps you will
allow a pupil, who was the tenth to
join the Poet's experimental school in
1901, to relate some of his memories.
Ours was a real, closely-knit family
over which hovered the benign presence
of the Master. He was a born teacher,
and took our classes in Bengali and
"English, wrote elementary text books for
us to learn Sanskrit and English, and
read to us Shelley, Keats, Wordsworth
and Browning, and Matthew Arnold's
essays on English Literature. In the
evenings he would regularly join in our
"entertainment" hour, devising new
games for us, one of which was called
"Sense-training" i.e. we had to guess
from a quick look the length of a table,
shelf, door, etc.. I remember the Poet
was very keen on this "Sense-training".
Just as here in Paul Geheeb's school,
the children close their books and are
off skiing on a particularly fine winter
morning, so at Santiniketan too the
children welcomed the rains by rushing
out to get drenched to the skin, and
even the Master joined us occasionally.
We of course had our classes in science,
carpentry, gardening and Ju-jitsu (a
teacher was brought all the way from
Japan). I have often heard the Poet
nostalgically speak of those early days,
when the school was unknown to the
outside world and he was free to
experiment and learn by mistakes so
unlike today, when many tourists have
Santiniketan in their itinerary along with
the Taj Mahal and Delhi's Red Fort.
Coming from Santiniketan, I was
naturally interested in progressive schools,
and so visited the Odenwaldschule of
Paul Geheeb in 1927. I was so impressed
by all I saw and it reminded me so
much of my own Santiniketan days, that
I gave the Poet no rest till in 1930 he
visited Paul Geheeb (See The Unesco
Courier, Dec. 1961, p. 9) whom he
greeted on his sixtieth birthday "as my
spiritual comrade and friend of Man".
This is perhaps the only good deed I
have done in my life, in bringing these
two pioneers and revolutionaries in the
field of education from East and West
together.
In the earlier twenties, after finishing
Cambridge, I was a student of »Professors
Planck and Einstein in Berlin. The Swiss
Science Congress met in Lucerne in 1925
and I had the opportunity to speak a
lot about my "Gurudev" to Einstein,
especially about his lectures in Japan
and America during the »First World War,
in which he condemned narrow, aggressive
Nationalism and preached a larger
Humanism that embraced East and
West in bonds of fellowship. These
were in harmony with the thoughts of the
great humanist Einstein himself, and he
was very happy to read the book
"Nationalism" which I gave him soon
after my return to Berlin. This was his
very first acquaintance with Tagore's
writings.
In 1926 when Tagore came to Berlin,
they met in Einstein's flat for tea and
I acted as interpreter, as Einstein's
English was at the time not too perfect.
I remember that the social implications
of the extended use of machinery in
displacing men from industry and
agriculture, and thus increasing un¬
employment (in Germany the rising
figures of unemployment was just then
helping Hitler's mass-movement) was
troubling the sensitive conscience of our
great Western sage and on this point
he put several questions to our Poet.
I took Tagore in a taxi to Epstein's
studio in London, for him to see his
works. I remember that the robust bust
of Conrad a veritable sea-dog made
a great impression on our Poet and he
consented to sit for Epstein. I used to
sit in a corner watching Epstein work.
I liked the bust very much at the end
of the third sitting. But he worked for
two days more and, at least I felt, spoilt
it. He did not, I feel, succeed in capturing
Tagore's beautiful and expressive eyes.
Tagore was really like a child and had
to be taken about by his secretaries, and
he never carried a penny in his pocket.
In Munich station I saw him get down
from the train in June 1921 like a
cherub fallen from heaven his secretary
with his luggage in the second half of
the train cut off for some unknown
reason. Of course he had not a penny
with him and was boisterously enjoying
the funny situation. It was here in
Munich that the Sanskrit professor, after
Tagore's lecture in the University, an¬
nounced that the Poet had donated the
whole of the proceeds from the sale of
his works in German to feed starving
students.
I could write much more but must
end with just one more memorable re¬
collection. It was June 1921 in Tagore's
hotel in Berlin. His visitor was Prof.
Rudolf Otto of Marburg, whose famous
book Das Heilige has been translated
into many languages.
They spoke for over an hour on how
to build up a new world from the ruins
of a devastating war, and suddenly Tagore
exclaimed with fervour: "Your country
and mine, both are disarmed.. Let us
unite our efforts and with the might of
the spirit bring healing to this world!"
Alas for the Poet's dream! In a few
years Hitlerism engulfed Germany, pres¬
aging the outbreak of World War II.
In these days -to be a cynic is so easy!
But let us remember Tagore's very last
words:
"I shall not commit the grevious sin
of losing faith in Man.
"'I shall wait for the day when the
holocaust will end and the air will be
rendered clean with the spirit of service
and sacrifice."
The Unesco Courier has done a
service for the cause of »Peace and
Understanding in bringing out this
Tagore number, for which please accept
my sincere thanks.
Aurobindo M. Bose
Ecole d'Humanité
Goldern, Switzerland
REPOBLIKA MALAGASf)
tM)HiS$)0W A LTHU] 20-9 t96C
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
s r,s s j t s j s s rj-ssrfj-s-j-.r.rtJ-sj'J-
ON September 20, 1960, fifteen newly-
independent African countries be¬
came members of the United Na¬
tions. Some have since issued stamps
to commemorate the first anniversary of
their membership. Those shown here are
from: Republic of Dahomey (right) Issued
in 5, 60 and 200 Fr. denominations; Repub¬
lic of Malagasy (left) 25 and 85 Fr.; Re¬
public of Niger (centre) 25 and 100 Fr.
These stamps and other philatelic items
can be obtained from the Unesco Phila¬
telic service. As agent in France of the
U.N. Postal Administration, Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all U.N. stamps
currently on sale. For prices and further
details write The Unesco Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
RADICAL CURE FOR MALARIA:
No one need die of malaria now that fully
reliable means exist both for curing it and
for preventing the infection from making
further victims, says the World Health
Organization. This was revealed by dis¬
cussions during the Second European Con¬
ference on Malaria Eradication, held recent¬
ly in Tangiers. The Conference noted that
the radical cure of malaria was now pos¬
sible thanks to modern drugs (the 8-amino
quinolines, of which the most widely used
is primaquine).
INTERNATIONAL CO-OPERATION
IN SPACE: The United States regards
Unesco as one of the Specialized Agencies
of the United Nations best suited to further
international scientific co-operation, and
hopes it will collaborate with the World
Meteorological Association in implement¬
ing a recent U.S. resolution in the United
Nations on atmospheric science and techno¬
logy. This was stated by Mr George
V. Allen, Chairman of the U.S. National
Commission for Unesco, replying to a
message of congratulations from Unesco
on the successful space flight made by the
American astronaut, Colonel John Glenn.
Unesco's message read: "Please accept
Unesco's heartiest congratulations on great
achievement of American science success¬
fully completed."
UNIVERSITY FOR BRASILIA: Brazil's
new capital. Brasilia, is to have its own
university. Work is now going ahead based
on plans on which the noted Brazilian ar¬
chitects Oscar Niemayer and Lucio Costa
are collaborating with members of the new
university's own Faculty of Architecture.
FELLOWSHIPS FOR AFRICANS:
- Nine young musicians from Africa
will be studying in an academy of music
in Great Britain next year. Hundreds of
African student teachers will be taking
courses in countries from Bulgaria to Mexi¬
co and from Sweden to Israel. In Rome a
student from Somalia will be learning all
about film production. These are a few
samplings from a Unesco's publication,
"Fellowships for Africans" which list
10,000 opportunities for African students
to study abroad. This 50-page booklet
(printed in English and French) is avail¬
able free of charge from the International
Exchange Service, Unesco, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris T, France.
EDUCATION FOR ASIA'S WOMEN:
Delegates from 16 Asian countries met re¬
cently in Bangkok at Unesco's invitation
to take stock of the educational, cultural,
social and economic obstacles to adequate
education for women in rural Asia today.
The meeting studied problems at all levels
from primary schools to adult education
programmes, and recommended ways of
improving facilities available to women.
PROBLEMS OF YOUTH TODAY:
The problems facing youth in the mod¬
ern world are being studied during a
series of UNESCO-sponsored meetings by a
working group composed of international
non-governmental organizations and youth
associations. The latest, held in Paris,
dealt with difficulties faced by young peo¬
ple finishing school and setting out to earn
their living. Unesco's inquiry into youth's
needs and problems is being made in 15
34 countries. It is estimated that young peo¬
ple in the 15-20 age group make up one-
fifth of the world's population.
ALL THE WORLD'S SOILS: The Food
and Agriculture Organization (FAO) and
Unesco are co-operating in a joint project
to make the first soil map of thé world
which will show the major types of soil
and thus provide a key to better land use.
The work will take seven years and a first
outline of the world map will be studied
at the Congress of the International Society
of Soil Science to be held in Rumania in
1964.
TRAINING CENTRE FOR ASIA'S
EDUCATORS: India and Unesco
have signed an agreement for the setting
up of a regional centre in New Delhi where
Asia's educational planners, administrators
and supervisors can be trained. This is
one of four regional centres to be establish¬
ed this year under Unesco's programme
for the development of primary education
in Asia.
TWO NATIONS JOIN UNESCO:
Tanganyika joined Unesco on March 7
and Sierra Leone on March 28, thus bring¬
ing the total of the Organization's member
states to 105.
MORE TEACHERS NEEDED: Ano¬
ther 95,000 teachers will have to be
recruited in England and Wales by 1970 if
present educational requirements are to be
met, according to a recent report entitled
"Investment for National Survival" pub¬
lished by the National Union of Teachers.
By 1970, the total teaching force in England
and Wales for both state and private
schools, a training college and colleges for
further education will have to total at least
420,000.
WOOD HARDER THAN IRON: Two
rare species of birch tree found in the
Soviet Union apparently produce wood that
is harder than iron. Known as the
"Schmidt" birch and the Temiragach, or
"iron birch", they have wood which is
one and a half times as hard as cast iron,
sinks in water and is used instead of met¬
al for making gear wheels and other ma¬
chine parts. When the "iron birch" is cut
down it throws up new shoots within a
few days. Soviet specialists are now trying
to transplant these trees into other regions.
CjOLAR-POWERED 'EARS': Units which
are described as combination radio
and public address systems have been
sent to communities in Paraguay by the
Administration for International Develop¬
ment, a U.S. government agency. Using a
small slice of silicon to transform solar
energy into electricity, they are expected
to facilitate communications in Paraguay's
villages. Similar devices are to be sent
to India, Pakistan and Afghanistan.
WORLD BANK AID FOR GHANA:
An important boost was given to
Ghana's economic development plans re¬
cently by the decision of the World Bank
to make a $47 million loan to help finance
the construction of a giant rockfill dam
over the Volta River, 60 miles north of
Accra. The project will provide power
for a giant hydroelectric station and will
create a reservoir stretching 200 miles
northwards. It will enable new indus¬
tries rice growing, for example to be
started, and will generate electricity to
work an aluminium smelting plant at the
port of Tema, 44 miles away.
« EQUAL ACCESS TO SCHOOLS: The
United Kingdom recently became the
fourth country after the Central African
Republic, France and Israel to ratifiy the
Convention Against Discrimination in Edu¬
cation, adopted in December 1960 by the
Unesco General Conference. The Con¬
vention which enters into force on May 22
defines descrimination as including any
distinction "based on race, colour, sex,
language, religion, political or other opi¬
nion, national or social origin, economic
condition or birth."
GERMANY'S COMPUTOR SCHOOL:
The first electronic computor school
in the Federal Republic of Germany has
been opened. Known as. Ihe Tech¬
nical School for Mechanical Manipulation
of Data, it offers courses in the operation
of machines used in factories, offices and
public services, including such subjects as
electronics and perforated card techniques,
storage and classification of data.
LATIN-AMERICAN EDUCATORS
LOOK & LEARN: Educators from 15
Latin American countries recently wound
up a three-month European study tour in
Paris where they visited schools and met
education authorities. The tour, sponsored
by Unesco's International Exchange Ser¬
vice, enabled 43 specialists to make first¬
hand studies of educational planning pro¬
grammes in Spain, Italy, Switzerland and
France. It was part of Unesco's Major
Project for the extension of primary edu¬
cation in Latin America.
"K1 YE ON THE SKY: Soviet astronomers,
-*-i now have a new and extremely power
fcl telescope for astronomic observations,
which has been installed at the Astrophysics
Observatory of the Crimea. Reported to
be the largest telescope in Europe, the
apparatus has a mirror weighing 4 tons
and 2.6 meters in diameter, which was
fused at a Leningrad optical works factory.
The rotating lens can be synchronized with
star movements by means of one of the
telescope's 1 60 automatic electronic systems.
u
z
<
z
<
o
LU
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
a guide
for journal
-a |
abou' the
uniBBiations
and specialized
perman s
united
nanon;
A GUIDE
TO THE
UNITED NATIONS
A compact reference book on all aspects of the
United Nations and its many associated bodies
has just been published by Unesco. Tracing
the ideas behind the creation of the United
Nations, its birth in San Francisco and its early
history, this book shows clearly how United
Nations work has evolved and been divided into
different branches. There are, for example, the
political questions, economic and social problems,
humanitarian and social work, technical assis¬
tance, the trusteeship system for non-self-
governing territories and the legal work of the
U.N. Called "The Newspaperman's United
Nations", this 230-page volume is all that it
claims to bea guide for journalists about the
United Nations and the specialized agenciesand
more: it is the kind of book that those so inclined
can pick up and browse through for a few minutes
or an hour's informative and profitable reading.
In addition to producing a readable vademécum
for all who are interested in the U.N., the author
has compiled a first-class bibliography.
THE NEWSPAPERMAN'S UNITED NATIONS by Jerzy
Szaplro.
Cloth-bound: $2.25 I I /-stg. 8 NF.
Paper cover: $1.75 8/6 stg. 6.25 NF.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU.
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department. Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 3 69 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 50.-). BELGIUM. Office de Publicité S.A.,
16, rte Marq, Brussels. CCP 285.98. NV Standaard-
Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only : Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World -Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section I, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckich, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidssknftafdelingen, 6 Norregade,
Kobenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box I 20. Addis Ababa.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris, 7«. COP. 12598-48. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier, Vertrieb Bahren¬
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 8). Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asal Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street. Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
(Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 3 5, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1£ 5.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LUXEMBURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SINGAPORE.
Federal Publications Ltd., Times House, River Valley
Rd., Singapore. MALTA. Sapienza's Library,
26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-). MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS. N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G.C.T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications Centre,
I 00 Hackthorne Road, Christchurch. ( I 0/-). NIGERIA
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR¬
WAY. For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Lit-
teratur-Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks 115 (kr.
13.20) Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grensen
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-).
LIPPINES. Philippine Education Co. Inc., I 104 Castille¬
jos, Quiapo, P.O. Box 620, Manila. POLAND.
" RUCH " ul.Wiloza Nr. 46, Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias Sc Andrada Lda, Livraria Portugal,
Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. RHODESIA & NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications A/B CE. Fritzes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse
Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. «Courier» only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O., Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 80 1 Third
Avenue, New York, 22, N.Y. ($ 5.00.) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslo-
venska Knj;ga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
MODERN JAPANESE FICTION
BREAK WITH TRADITION (See poge M)
]]>
</page>
</document>
