<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078349eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE
VERSUS
OLD AGE
i Jl
!
1958
(llth year)
ice: 1 /-stg. (U. K.)
1 cents (U. S.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
© Almasy, Pans
"Everyone has the right to a standard of living adequate for the health and well-being of himself and of his family, including food,
clothing, housing and medical care and necessary social services, and the right to security in the event of unemployment, sickness,
disability, widowhood, old age or other lack of livelihood..." Article 25, The Universal Declaration of Human Rights. (See p. 4)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER 1958
11 TH YEAR
No. I0
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 THE GREATEST ENEMIES TO LIBERTY
By Aldous Huxley
6 UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS
Full text
7 THE CHALLENGE OF HUMAN RIGHTS TODAY
I I A SCIENTIST LOOKS AT PROBLEMS OF AGING
By Prof. R. E. Tunbridge
13 DENMARK'S CITY CALLED ' GAMLES BY'
18 'OLD DOC* CUMMINS
26 CLUBS INSTEAD OF OLD AGE HOMES
A new trend develops in Israel
28 MAN'S LIFESPAN : A ROUND CENTURY
Studies in a Soviet land of longevity
By Prof. G. Z. Pitskhelaun
30 A SMOOTHER WAY FOR BRITAIN'S COLOURED
IMMIGRANTS
By Hebe Spaull
3 I ROBERT OWEN : VISIONARY OF A NEW SOCIETY
By Peter Michaels
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22. N.Y. , Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.129 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads " Reprinted Irom THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00; I 0/- stg. ; 500 Fr. frs. or equivalent.
COVER PHOTO
This I know without being told,
'Tis time to live as I grow old.
'Tis time short pleasures now to take,
Of little Life the best to make,
And manage wisely the last stake.
Abraham Cowley, "Age"
© Almasy, Pans.
The struggle for human rights has gone on from the
beginning of recorded time. History has marked
the efforts of the seers and prophets, the philoso¬
phers, the lawgivers, the statesmen and the martyrs in
voicing demands for larger freedom. But the nerve
centre of the struggle for human rights is to be found
in the people themselves, in the attempts of ordinary men
and women to establish their claim to a decent, unmo¬
lested life in the face of despotism and bigotry, of ignor¬
ance and intolerance, of superstition and tyranny.
The English Magna Carta of 1215, the Habeas Corpus
Act of 1679 and the Bill of Rights of 1689; the American
Declaration of Independence of 1776; and the French
Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen in
1789 were all landmarks in this struggle. To these historic
declarations of the rights of man was added another on
December 10, 1948 when the General Assembly of the
United Nations adopted and proclaimed the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights "as a common standard of
achievement for all peoples and all nations/'
December 10, this year, the tenth anniversary of the
Universal Declaration, will be marked by special obser¬
vances throughout the world. Many organizations are
holding conferences, special meetings - or discussions
devoted to human rights in 1958. Through articles,
pamphlets and booklets, and by radio, TV and films,
knowledge of the Declaration will be spread throughout
the world and the achievements of the United Nations in
promoting Human Rights will be brought into perspective.
The United Nations has made much progress in its
work of promoting and encouraging respect for human
rights and fundamental freedoms, but their "universal
and effective recognition and observance" is still far from
being a reality. The Declaration sets a standard that
can become real only when its principles are applied by
individuals, among local groups and in communities
within nations and by governments in their relationships
with one another and with their citizens. December 10,
therefore, should serve to remind us that tremendous
efforts must still be made before Human Rights are
recognized universally.
The pages of The Unesco Courier this month are
therefore intended as a small contribution to the common
task of awakening renewed interest in and greater under¬
standing of the basic human rights proclaimed for the
first time in history from a truly universal standpoint in
the Declaration of December 10, 1948.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE GREATEST
TO LIBER
NEMIES
Y 1
, .4
* V i "J
"1 1 V
by Aldous Huxley
© Festspielleitung, Bayreuth
In 1947 while the U. N. Commission on Human Rights was working out an international bill of rights,
Unesco carried out a broad enquiry into the philosophic bases of the rights which could be inclu¬
ded in such a declaration. It consulted leading philosophers and writers of many countries and
obtained their personal views on the question. This symposium served as the basis for the final
conclusions which Unesco drew and which were forwarded to the U. N. Human Rights Com¬
mission to help to clarify its discussions and to help explore the ground for constructive agree¬
ment. Later the most significant texts of this symposium were edited by Unesco and published
under the title Human Rights : Comments and Interpretations (Publisher, Allan Wingate, London,
1949). On the occasion of the 10th anniversary of the adoption of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights, The Unesco Courier reproduces below Aldous Huxley's contribution. Though
it was written ten years ago it is just as timely and provocative today as it was then.
The increasing pressure of population upon resources
and the waging, threat of, and unremitting preparation
for total war these are, at the present time, the most
formidable enemies to liberty.
About three-quarters of the 2.2 billion inhabitants of our
planet do not have enough to eat. By the end of the present
century world population will have increased (if we manage
to avoid catastrophe in the interval) to about 3.3 thousand
millions (1). Meanwhile, over vast areas of the earth's
surface, soil erosion is rapidly diminishing the fertility of
mankind's four billion acres of productive land. Moreover,
in those countries where industrialism is most highly developed,
mineral resources are running low, or have been completely
exhausted and this at a time when a rising population
demands an ever increasing quantity of consumer goods and
when improved technology is in a position to supply that
demand.
Heavy pressure of population upon resources threatens
liberty in several ways. Individuals have to work harder and
longer to earn a poorer living. At the same time the economic
situation of the community as a whole is so precarious that
small mishaps, such as untoward weather conditions, may
result in serious breakdowns. There can be little or no
(1) According to the latest population statistics published
by the United Nations the world's population is now increasing
at the rate of 5,400 individuals per hour (47,000,000 eac/i year).
At this rate the present total of 2,737,000,000 will be doubled by
the end of the century. Editor
personal liberty in the midst of social chaos; and where
social chaos is reduced to order by the intervention of a
powerful contralized executive, there is a grave risk of
totalitarianism. Because of the mounting pressure of popula¬
tion upon resources, the twentieth century has become the
golden age of centralized government and dictatorship, and
has witnessed the wholesale revival of slavery, which has
been imposed upon political heretics, conquered populations
and prisoners of war.
Throughout the nineteenth century the New World provided
cheap food for the teeming masses of the Old World and
free land for the victims of oppression. Today the New
World holds a large and growing population, there is no free
land and over the vast areas, the much abused soil is losing
its fertility. The New World still produces a large exportable
surplus. Whether, fifty years from now, it will still have
a surplus, with which to feed the three billions inhabiting the
Old World, seems doubtful.
By destroying accumulated wealth and the sources of future
production, total war has sharply increased the pressure of
existing populations upon their resources and has thereby
sharply curtailed the liberties of vast numbers of men and
women, belonging not only to the vanquished nations, but
also to those which were supposed to be victorious. At the
same time the fear of, and busy preparation for, another
total war in the near future is everywhere resulting in an
ever greater concentration of political and economic power.
Bitter experience has proved that no individual or »group
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
of individuals is fit to be entrusted with great powers for
long periods of time. The socialist rulers of welfare states
may imagine that they and their successors will be immune
to the corrupting influence of the enormous powers which
total war and mounting population pressure have forced
upon them; but there is, unfortunately, no reason to suppose
that they will prove to be exceptions to the general rule.
The abuse of power can be avoided only by limiting the
amount and duration of the authority entrusted to any person,
group or class.
But so long as we are menaced by total war and mounting
population pressures, it seems very unlikely that we shall get
anything but a steadily increasing concentration of power in
the hands of the ruling political bosses and their bureaucratic
managers. Meanwhile conscription, or military servitude, is
almost everywhere imposed upon the masses. This means
in practice that, at any moment, a man may be deprived of his
constitutional liberties and subjected to martial law. Recent
history has shown that even socialist rulers are ready to resort
to this device for coercing persons engaged in inconvenient
strikes.
It is virtually certain that, at the present time, no govern¬
ment actually desires war. But it is also probable that many
governments would be reluctant' to give up all preparations
for war; for such preparations justify them in maintaining
conscription as an instrument of control and coercion. And
we may add that universal disarmament, if it should ever
be achieved, would not necessarily mean the end of con¬
scription. Compulsory service to the States will probably
persist in some other than military form as a scheme for
the "training of youth," for example, or as a "labour draft."
A constitutional bill of rights, whose principles are applied
in specific legislation, can certainly do something to protect
the masses of ordinary, unprivileged men and women against
the few who, through wealth or hierarchical position, effec¬
tively wield power over the majority. But prevention is
always better than cure. Mere paper restrictions, designed
to curb the abuse of a power already concentrated in a few
hands, are but the mitigations of an existing evil. Personal
liberty can be made secure only by abolishing the evil
altogether.
Unesco is engaged at present in facilitating the task of
mitigation; but it is in the fortunate position of being able
to proceed, if it so desires, to the incomparably more important
task of prevention, of the radical removal of the present
impediments to liberty. This is primarily an affair for the
scientific section of the Organization. For the problem
of relieving the pressure of population upon resources is
primarily a problem in pure and applied science, while the
problem of total war is (among other things, of course) a
problem in ethics for scientific workers as individuals and as
members of professional organisations.
Millions for destruction
To provide all of the 2.2 thousand million persons at present
inhabiting the planet with a nutritionally adequate diet,
it would be necessary to double the existing food supply.
It will takei years, by conventional methods, to achieve this
goal and by that time the population will be, not two billions,
but more than three and malnutrition will be very nearly
as serious and as widespread as it is today.
Every industrial nation spends huge sums on research into
the techniques of mass destruction. Thus, two thousand
million dollars went into the production of the atomic bomb
and many hundreds of millions more are at present being
spent upon research into rockets, jet planes, the dissemination
of pneumonic plague and the wholesale destruction of food
plants. If comparable amounts of money and scientific
ability could be devoted to the problem of producing food¬
stuffs artificially, it seems likely enough that methods would
quickly be found for providing the half-starved millions of
Europe and Asia with an adequate diet. The synthesis of
chlorophyll, for example, might be, for the later twentieth
century, the equivalent of what the exploitation of the empty
lands of the New World was for the nineteenth. It would
reduce the pressure of population upon resources and thereby
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
remove one of the principal reasons for highly centralized,
totalitarian control of individual lives.
The prosperity of an industrialized society is proportionate
to the rapidity with which it squanders its irreplaceable
natural capital. Over large areas of the earth's surface,
easily available deposits of useful minerals have already
been exhausted, or are running low; with the increase in
population and the progressive improvement in industrial
techniques, the drain upon the planet's remaining resources
is bound to be accelerated.
Useful minerals are very unevenly distributed. Some
countries are exceedingly rich in these natural resources,
others lack them completely. When a powerful nation
possesses a natural monopoly in some indispensable mineral,
it is thereby enabled to increase its already formidable
influence over its less fortunate neighbours. Where a weak
nation finds itself blessed, or cursed, with a natural monopoly,
its stronger neighbours are tempted to acts of aggression
or "peaceful penetration."
Science at the crossroads
Scientific workers have it in their power to postpone the
day of planetary bankruptcy and to mitigate the political
dangers inherent in the existence of natural monopolies.
What is needed is a new Manhattan Project, under interna¬
tional auspices, for the development of universally available
surrogates for the unevenly distributed and soon-to-be-
exhausted minerals, on which our industrial civilization
depends for its very existence e.g. wind power to take the
place of power produced by coal, petroleum and that most
dangerous of all fuels, uranium; glass and plastics as
substitutes, wherever possible, for such metals as copper, tin,
nickel and zinc.
A project of this kind would be valuable in several ways.
It would shift our industrial civilization on to a foundation
more permanent than that accelerating exploitation of
wasting assets, on which it rests at present; it would break
those natural monopolies which are a standing temptation to
war; and finally it would make possible an extension of per¬
sonal liberty and a reduction of the powers wielded by the
ruling minority.
We now come to the ethical problems confronting
scientific workers as individuals and as members of pro¬
fessional organizations. Whatever may have been the wishes
of the inventors and technicians involved, applied science has
in fact resulted in the creation of monopolistic industries,
controlled by private capitalists or centralized national
governments. It has led to the concentration of economic
power, strengthened the hands of the few against the many
and increased the destructiveness of war. Applied science
in the service, first, of big business and then of government
has made possible the modern totalitarian state.
The time has surely come when scientific workers must
consider, individually and collectively, the ethical problem of
"right livelihood". How far is a man justified in following
a course of professional action which, though involving no
immediate wrong-doing, results in social consequences which
are manifestly undesirable or downright evil? Specifically,
how far is it right for the scientist or technologist to
participate in work, the outcome of which will be to increase
the concentration of power in the hands of the ruling
minority and to provide soldiers with the means for the
wholesale extermination of civilians?
Up to the present applied science has been, to a great
extent, at the service of monopoly, oligarchy and nationalism.
But there is nothing in the nature of science or technology
which makes it inevitable that this should be so. Pro¬
fessionally speaking, it would be just as easy for the scientific
worker to serve the cause of peace as of war, of personal
liberty, voluntary co-operation and self-government, as of
monopolistic statism or capitalism, universal regimentation
and dictatorship. The difficulties are not technical; they lie
in the realms of philosophy and morals, of value judgments
and the will that acts upon those judgments.
First published in 1949 by Allan Wingate {Publishers) Ltd.,
London. All rights reserved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNIVERSAL
DECLARATION
OF HUMAN
RIGHTS
Art. 6-8, 10... Equality before the law. All drawings by Heiri Steiner
PREAMBLE
Whereas recognition of the inherent dignity
and of the equal and inalienable rights of all
members of the human family is the foundation
of freedom, justice and peace in the world,
Whereas disregard and contempt for human
rights have resulted ¡n barbarous acts which
have outraged the conscience of mankind, and
the advent of a world in which human beings
shall enjoy freedom of speech and belief and
freedom from fear and want has been pro¬
claimed as the highest aspiration of the com¬
mon people,
Whereas it is essential, if man is not to be
compelled to have recourse, as a last resort,
to rebellion against tyranny and oppression,
that human rights should be protected by the
rule of law,
Art. I... Equal rights for all.
6
Whereas it is essential to promote the
development of friendly relations between
nations,
Whereas the peoples of the United Nations
have in the Charter reaffirmed their faith in
fundamental human rights, ¡n the dignity and
worth of the human person and in the equal
rights of men and women and have determined
to promote social progress and better standards
of life ¡n larger freedom,
Whereas Member States have pledged them¬
selves to achieve, in cooperation with the
United Nations, the promotion of universal
respect for and observance of human rights
and fundamental freedoms,
Whereas a common understanding of these
rights and freedoms is of the greatest Impor¬
tance for the full realisation of this pledge,
Now therefore
The General Assembly proclaims
This Universal Declaration of Human
Rights as a common standard of achievement
for all peoples and all nations, to the end that
every individual and every organ of society,
keeping this Declaration constantly ¡n mind,
shall strive by teaching and education to pro¬
mote respect for these rights and freedoms
and by progressive measures, national and
international, to secure their universal and
effective recognition and observance, both
among the peoples of Member States them¬
selves and among the peoples of territories
under their jurisdiction.
Article I
All human beings are born free and equal in
dignity and rights. They are endowed with
reason and conscience and should act towards
one another in a spirit of brotherhood.
Article 2
Everyone is entitled to all the rights and
freedoms set forth in this Declaration, without
distinction of any kind, such as race, colour,
sex, language, religion, political or other
opinion, national or social origin, property,
birth or other status. Furthermore, no dis¬
tinction shall be made on the basis of the
political, jurisdictional or international status
of the country or territory to which a person
belongs, whether it be independent, trust,
non-self-governing or under any other limi¬
tation of sovereignty.
Article 3
Everyone has the right to life, liberty and
security of person.
Article 4
No one shall be held ¡n slavery or servitude;
slavery and the slave trade shall be prohibited
in all their forms.
Article 5
No one shall be subjected to torture or to
cruel, Inhuman or degrading treatment or
punishment.
Article 6
Everyone has the right to recognition
everywhere as a person before the law.
Article 7
All are equal before the law and are entitled
without any discrimination
to equal protection of the
law. All are entitled to
equal protection against any
discrimination In violation of
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
THE CHALLENGE OF
HUMAN RIGHTS TODAY
The United Nations was established in 1945 not only
to prevent war, but also to promote conditions of
international well-being and progress essential to
the maintenance of peace. Since its establishment it has
endeavoured to advance, through international co¬
operation, the material and social well-being of peoples
throughout the world. It has sought to promote human
dignity and equality and to make effective the right of
everyone to lead a free life in a free society. Thus, from
its very beginning the United Nations has been actively
concerned with the problem of human rights.
By the time the Conference of San Francisco met in the
spring of 1945 to draw up the Charter of the United
Nations, there was a strong public demand for broad
guarantees of human rights. A number of non-govern¬
mental organizations sent their representatives to the
conference and succeeded in convincing the official rep¬
resentatives of governments of the necessity of expanding
the original provisions of the Dumbarton Oaks proposals
concerning human rights. As a result, the promotion
of human rights was given much more emphasis under
the Charter of the United Nations.
The Commission on Human Rights, composed of eigh¬
teen members, came into existence early in 1946. For eight
years the Commission devoted itself mainly to preparing
an. international bill of human rights. In the beginning
there was much discussion of the form which the bill of
rights should take. Some thought that a declaration of
principle, or manifesto, was most appropriate, while others
favoured a convention. It was finally decided that the
international bill should be in three parts: a "declaration"
which would lay down general standards of human rights;
a "covenant or covenants" which would be legally binding
on states becoming parties thereto; and "measures of
implementation" which would establish international
machinery to exercise general supervision over the enfor¬
cement of the covenants.
Unanimous vote by
forty-eight nations
The Commission began its work in January 1947 with
Mrs. Franklin D. Roosevelt as its chairman. Almost
two years later, on December 10, 1948, the General
Assembly of the United Nations adopted the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights at the Palais de Chaillot in
Paris. Out of the fifty-eight nations represented there,
forty-eight voted their approval of the Declaration, none
voted against, eight abstained, and two were absent. The
first international declaration of human rights was
therefore adopted without a single dissenting vote.
It was not an easy task for so many countries to come
together and draft a declaration recognizing human rights
and fundamental freedoms in terms which all could accept
and understand. It was hailed by the President of the
1948 General Assembly, H.V. Evatt of Australia, on its
adoption, as a document to which "millions of people,
men, women and children all over the world, many miles
from Paris and New York, will turn for help, guidance
and inspiration."
In the nine years since it was adopted, knowledge of the
Declaration has been spread far and wide. It has been
translated into all the main languages of the world. The
date of its adoption, December 10, was proclaimed as
Human Rights Day by the General Assembly in 1950 and
it is celebrated every year in most countries. The
Declaration, or individual articles from it, are frequently
quoted in United Nations resolutions as setting the stand¬
ard which should be applied. The constitutions of various
countries drafted since 1948, such as those of Costa Rica,
Egypt, El Salvador, Eritrea, Haiti, Indonesia, Jordan, Libya,
Pakistan and Syria, have taken many of their provisions
from it.
The thorniest issue:
self- determination
Many international conventions and agreements, even
those not drawn up under United Nations auspices,
also show the effect of the Declaration. In the
Peace Treaty concluded at San Francisco in 1951, Japan
declares its intention to strive to realize the objectives of
the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. In the Trus¬
teeship Agreement for Somaliland, Italy accepts the Dec¬
laration as a standard of achievement in its administra¬
tion of the Territory. The European convention for the
protection of human rights and fundamental freedoms,
not only invokes the Declaration in its preamble; its subs¬
tantive provisions are based on an earlier version of the
United Nations draft convenant on human rights.
In the agreement relating to the Free Territory of
Trieste, the Italian and Yugoslav authorities undertake
to act in accordance with the principles of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights in the administration of
their respective areas. The agreement between France
and Tunisia concluded in June 1955 contains a provision
whereby Tunisia recognizes that all persons living in its
territory are entitled to the enjoyment of the rights and
guarantees enunciated in the Universal Declaration.
Once the Declaration was completed in 1948, the Com¬
mission on Human Rights was able to concentrate on the
draft covenants, but only in 1954 did it finish the prelimin¬
ary texts of a draft covenant on civil and political rights
and a draft covenant on economic, social and cultural
rights. These were transmitted, through the Economic
and Social Council, to the General Assembly. They are
still before that body for final drafting and adoption.
One of the most controversial issues raised in connexion
with the draft covenants is the inclusion of an article
on the right of peoples to self-determination. A majority
of the Member States are in favour of including an article,
but there is strong opposition to it. Some have even indic¬
ated that they may be unable to become parties to the
covenants if an article on self-determination is included.
Another question that has come up is whether there
should be one or two covenants, that is, whether civil and
political and economic, social and cultural rights should
be included in a single instrument or in separate
conventions. In 1951 the General Assembly, reversing its
previous stand on the question, decided that two covenants
should be adopted and opened for signature simultane¬
ously and should contain as many similar provisions as
possible.
The very slow progress made in complet¬
ing and adopting the covenants in no
way means that the human rights pro¬
gramme is coming to a dead end. Three
years ago the Commission on Human Rights
Cont'd
on
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
HUMAN RIGHTS
(Continued)
U. N. global survey on discrimination
engaged in a new programme which sometimes is referred
to as a programme of concrete action. In developing this
programme, the Commission changed the emphasis of its
work. The first years, during the preparation of the
Universal Declaration and the draft covenants, the Com¬
mission was concerned primarily with defining human
rights and laying down general standards. Now the
emphasis is oh the application of these standards.
The new programme has three aspects. First, govern¬
ments are being asked to report periodically to the United
Nations on developments in their respective countries in
the matter of human rights, including progress achieved
and difficulties encountered. On the basis of these reports,
the Commission on Human Rights will consider the
"general developments and progress achieved in the field
of human rights." It is not intended that the Commission
will sit in judgment and assess the successes and failures
of individual governments, but it will present to the Eco¬
nomic and Social Council "objective and general" com¬
ments, conclusions and recommendations on the status
of human rights in the world.
Dramatic progress in
women's emancipation
Secondly, the United Nations is maiking a series of global
studies or surveys on particular rights or groups of
rights. One of these studies, namely, a study on
discrimination in education has been completed; and
studies are now pending on discrimination in the matter
of religious rights and practices, on discrimination in the
exercise of political rights, and on the right of everyone
to be free from arbitrary arrest, detention and exile.
Finally this new programme authorizes the Secretary-
General to render, at the request of governments, advisory
services in the field of human rights. Three forms of
assistance are authorized: (1) advisory services; (2)
fellowships and scholarships; and (3) seminars. Under
this programme a series of regional seminars or confer¬
ences have been organized. The purpose of these
seminars is to bring together key people from various
countries and to give them an opportunity to exchange
their views and experiences and through their leadership
to encourage greater awareness of problems of human
rights within official circles.
Seminars were held in 1957 and 1958 in Bangkok, in
Baguio City, Philippines, and in Santiago, Chile. Particip¬
ants at these conferences included supreme court justices
and other senior judges, solicitors-general, deputy
ministers of justice, eminent professors, commissioners
of police and other ranking government officials.
The work of the United Nations in the field of human
rights has not, of course, been limited to preparing the
international bill of rights and implementing the new
programme developed by the Commission on Human
Rights. The United Nations has, over the years, dealt
with a number of special problems. One of these is the
promotion of Women's rights.
It is probably in the political field that the most dram¬
atic progress has been achieved. At the time of the
signature of the United Nations Charter, women had no
political rights in some forty sovereign countries of the
world. Since then, thirty-five countries have given
women political rights. These rights are particularly
valuable for women because only through participation
in the legislative, executive and judicial organs of
government can women obtain equality in the other
fields. In December 1952, a Convention on the Political
Rights of Women was adopted by the General Assembly
of the United Nations, ensuring to women the right to
vote, to be elected and to hold public office on equal terms
with men. It has been signed by forty-one countries and
ratified and acceded to by twenty-nine.
Other specific problems in the field of human rights
with which the United Nations has been concerned are,
inter alia, the prevention of discrimination and pro¬
tection of minorities, the right of peoples and nations to
self-determination, freedom of information, forced
labour, slavery, genocide, protection of refugees and
stateless persons, repatriation of prisoners of war, the
racial situation in South Africa. Several important
studies have been made and recommendations and
international conventions adopted by the various organs
of the United Nations on these questions. The prepara¬
tion, adoption and publication of these studies, recom¬
mendations and agreements have thrown the full light
of day on some of the great moral, social and political
issues of our time.
It is difficult, of course, to evaluate the progress
achieved on a day-to-day basis. One can judge progress
in this field only by looking at it in historical perspective.
As recently as 1920, no one would have dared to think
that an international organization would have as one
of its major concerns the international protection of
human rights. Human Rights Was considered a matter
exclusively within the domestic jurisdiction of States.
Indeed, it will be recalled that when, at the Peace
Conference at the close of the World War I, the Japanese
delegation suggested that the Covenant of the League of
Nations should proclaim the principle of racial equality,
the proposal was opposed by some of the great Powers
and was not adopted. When one compares this event,
which happened barely a generation ago, with .what has
been said above about the work of the United Nations in
the field of human rights, he will agree that, in spite of
all the difficulties, some progress has been made.
Action needed at
grass-roots level
Yet it would be wrong to believe that the most
important work in the field of human rights is
confined to the large arena of international discus¬
sion and decision. After all, human rights are enjoyed and
exercised only in actual human relationships, in actual
communities. The advances made at the international
level in the promotion of human rights become real only
when they are reflected in action at the local level.
For responsible community leaders, much of this local
action will be of a co-operative and educational char¬
acter education in what the United Nations is doing,
education in the basic attitudes and social concepts which
our times call for. Fundamentally, the task of promot¬
ing human rights is an educational one. It is a task of
educating public opinion, changing basic attitudes and
behaviour, eliminating outmoded concepts and implanting
in the minds of men, women and children those concepts
which reflect the realities of an inter-related and inter¬
dependent world society.
The above article is adapted from a chapter of "Teaching
Human Rights: A Handbook for Teachers", which is shortly
to be published by the U.N. in New York to mark the 10th
anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1953
UNIVERSAL
DECLARATION
(Continued)
this Declaration and against any incitement
to such discrimination.
Article 8
Everyone has the right to an effective remedy
by the competent national tribunals for acts
violating the fundamental rights granted him
by the constitution or by law.
Article 9
No one shall be subjected to arbitrary arrest,
detention or exile.
Article 10
Everyone is entitled in full equality to a fair
and public hearing by an independent and
impartial tribunal, in the determination of his
rights and obligations and of any criminal
charge against him.
Article I I
(1) Everyone charged with a penal offence
has the right to be presumed innocent until
proved guilty according to law in a public
trial at which he has had all the guarantees
necessary for his defence.
(2) No one shall be held guilty of any penal
offence on account of any act or omission
which did not constitute a penal offence,
under national or International law, at the
time when it was committed. Nor shall a
heavier penalty be imposed than the one that
was applicable at the time the penal offence
was committed.
Article 12
No one shall be subjected to arbitrary Inter¬
ference with his privacy, family, home or
correspondence, nor to attacks upon his
honour and reputation. Everyone has the
right to the protection of the law against
such interference or attacks.
Article 13
(I) Everyone has the right to freedom of
movement and residence within the borders
of each state.
Art. 12... Protection of the law.
(2) Everyone has the right to leave any coun¬
try, Including his own, and to return to his
country.
Article 14
(1) Everyone has the right to seek and to
enjoy ¡n other countries asylum from perse¬
cution.
(2) This right may not be invoked in the case
of prosecutions genuinely arising from non-
political crimes or from acts contrary to the
purposes and principles of the United Nations.
Article 15
(1) Everyone has the right to a nationality.
(2) No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of
his nationality nor denied the right to change
his nationality.
Article 16
(1) Men and women of full age, without any
limitation due to race, nationality or religion,
have the right to marry and to found a family.
They are entitled to equal rights as to mar¬
riage, during marriage and at its dissolution.
(2) Marriage shall be entered Into only with
the free and full consent of the Intending
spouses.
(3) The family is the natural and fundamental
group unit of society and is entitled to pro¬
tection by society and the State.
Art. 16... To marry and found a family. Art. 1 8/ 1 9... Freedom of thought & religion.
Art. 14... Right to asylum.
Article 17
(1) Everyone has the right to own property
alone as well as in association with others.
(2) No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his
property.
Article 18
Everyone has the right to freedom of thought,
conscience and religion; this right includes
freedom to change his religion or belief, and
freedom, either alone or in community with
others and ¡n public or private, to manifest
his religion or belief in teaching, practice,
worship and observance.
Article 19
Everyone has the right to freedom of opinion
and expression; this right includes freedom
to hold opinions without interference and to
seek, receive and impart Information and ideas
through any media and regardless of frontiers.
Article 20
(1) Everyone has the right to freedom of
peaceful assembly and association.
(2) No one may be compelled to belong to an
association.
Article 21
(1) Everyone has the right to take part ¡n the
government of his country, directly or through
freely chosen representatives.
(2) Everyone has the right of equal access to
public service ¡n his country.
(3) The will of the people shall be the basis
of the authority of government; this will shall
be expressed In periodic and genuine elec¬
tions which shall be by universal and equal
suffrage and shall be held by secret vote or
by equivalent free voting procedures.
Article 22
Everyone, as a member of society, has the
right to social security and
is entitled to realization,
through national effort and
international co-operation
and ¡n accordance with the
Cont'd
on
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNIVERSAL DECLARATION (Continued)
organization and resources of each State,
of the economic, social and cultural rights
indispensable for his dignity and the free
development of his personality.
Article 23
(1) Everyone has the right to work, to free
choice of employment, to just and favourable
conditions of work and to protection against
unemployment.
(2) Everyone, without any discrimination, has
the right to equal pay for equal work.
(3) Everyone who works has the right to just
and favourable remuneration insuring for
himself and his family an existence worthy of
human dignity, and supplemented, if neces¬
sary, by other means of social protection.
(4) Everyone has the right to form and to
join trade unions for the protection of his
interests.
Article 24
Everyone has the right to rest and leisure,
including reasonable limitation of working
hours and periodic holidays with pay.
Article 25
(1) Everyone has the right to a standard of
living adequate for the health and well-being
of himself and of his family, including food,
clothing, housing and medical care and neces¬
sary social services, and the right to security
in the event of unemployment, sickness, disa¬
bility, widowhood, old age or other lack of
livelihood in circumstances beyond his control.
(2) Motherhood and childhood are entitled to
special care and assistance. All children,
whether born in or out of wedlock, shall enjoy
the same social protection.
Article 26
(1) Everyone has the right to education.
Education shall be free, at least ¡n the elemen¬
tary and fundamental stages. Elementary
education shall be compulsory. Technical and
professional education shall be made generally
available and higher education shall be equally
accessible to all on the basis of merit.
(2) Education shall be directed to the full
development of the human personality and
to the strengthening of respect for human
rights and fundamental freedoms. It shall
promote understanding, tolerance and friend¬
ship among all nations, racial or religious
groups, and shall further the activities of the
United Nations for the maintenance of peace.
(3) Parents have a prior right to choose the
kind of education that shall be given to their
children.
Article 27
(1) Everyone has the right freely to participate
in the cultural life of the community, to enjoy
the arts and to share ¡n scientific advancement
and its benefits.
(2) Everyone has the right to the protection
of the moral and material Interests resulting
from any scientific, literary or artistic produc¬
tion of which he is the author.
Article 28
Everyone is entitled to a social and Interna¬
tional order in which the rights and freedoms
set forth ¡n this Declaration can be fully
realised.
Art. 20/21... To participate in government.
Article 29
(1) Everyone has duties to the community in
which alone the free and full development of
his personality ¡s possible.
(2) In the exercise of his rights and freedoms,
everyone shall be subject only to such limita¬
tions as are determined by law solely for the
purpose of securing due recognition and res¬
pect for the rights and freedoms of others
and of meeting.the just requirements of mora¬
lity, public order and the general welfare in
a democratic society.
(3) These rights and freedoms may in no case
be exercised contrary to the purposes and
principles of the United Nations.
Article 30
Nothing in this Declaration may be Interpreted
as implying for any State, group or person
any right to engage ¡n any activity or to
perform any act aimed at the destruction of
any of the rights and freedoms set forth
herein.
Art. 26... Right to education.
10
Art. 27... To share ¡n cultural life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
A SCIENTIST LOOKS AT
PROBLEMS OF AGING
by Prof. R.E. Tunbridge
The increasing proportion of the elderly and the
diminishing proportion of children are creating a
new form of society in the countries of Western
Europe and North Aemrica. By 1980 the over-sixties in
Sweden and Great Britain will constitute nearly one-third
of the voting power. If intellectual, emotional and per¬
sonality changes are a feature of increasing years, what
is to be the pattern of society? Such thoughts suggest
that a study of those who seem to have reached successful
old age is essential. Undoubtedly a man with many and
wide interests and with full retention of his faculties is
the one most likely to achieve a successful old age. In
the United States much thought has been given to prepar¬
ing people for old age and to advise for retirement. Other
countries are following the American lead, and there
would certainly seem to be a place for such programmes.
If senescence is a biological process, it may be necessary
to devise a new pattern of living, responsibility and
leadership being confined to the period of peak per¬
formance, with subsequent adjustments for the later
years.
The advances of medical science have led to a marked
increase in the expectancy of life at birth, particularly in
the countries of Western Europe and North America.
Medical science has not yet solved the problem of
senescence. Many of the disabilities associated with aging
are the result of disease, so that it is impossible as yet to
answer the fundamental biological problem.
The magnitude of the medico-social problem, however,
demands the provision of an increasing proportion of
national and international resources for research on aging
and into the causes of the degenerative diseases which
contribute so largely to the frailty of the aged. Lack of
health, mental and physical, is the major cause of the
disabilities attributed to aging.
A full and immediate understanding of the sociological
factors consequent upon a decline of the physical and
mental processes due to aging is essential if the elderly
are to be incorporated into the life of an aging society
instead of being rejected. Rejection could only lead to a
complete disruption of community life.
To sum up: aging therefore has scientific, economic,
social and political significance for the community as well
as for the individual, andwith all its ramifications
justifies consideration as a major biological problem of
the second half of the twentieth century.
R. E. Tunbridge is Professor of Medicine at the University of
Leeds (England) and a specialist in gerontology, the new science
of old age. He was chairman of tha Organizing Committee of
the Third International Gerontological Congress, and is à mem¬
ber of the Executive Committee of the Council of International
Organizations of Medical Sciences, the centralizing agency for
medical sciences set up jointly in 1949 by the World Health Or¬
ganization and Unesco.
The problems of aging are not new phenomena.
Throughout history man has been aware that both he
and the animals he hunted or kept in domesticity had a
limited existence, and that with the passage of the years
a decline in activity, strength and fertility would occur.
Strictly speaking, aging denotes merely the passage of
years, but it has come to have a sinister meaning and to
imply the deterioration that so frequently accompanies it
and is perhaps best referred to as senescence.
Historical records relate the existence of men still
distinguished in their 60's, 70's and even 80's. In the
Bible there is the record of Methuselah which, even
allowing for literary licence and a method other than
ours of estimating time, would suggest that he attained
what we* would call a ripe old age!
The comparative scarcity of true veterans until recent
times has meant that nearly all the descriptions of the
elderly have come from the pens of young men. Senes¬
cence, or the evidence thereof, has entered so early and
so untimely into human experience that almost all studies
of the phenomenon have been confused with the
associated metaphysical problems.
Greek thought has influenced western philosophy so
profoundly that it is not surprising that the Grecian
attitude to age has in part been adopted by western civili¬
zation. The Greeks certainly paid lip service to the aged,
and whilst octogenarians figure amongst" their great
philosophers, it was youth that for them was the age of
perfection. Sophocles, referring to old age, says: "The
understanding is quenched, what is done is unprofitable
and thereby griefs are vain." Aging was something to
be dreaded because of the physical disabilities and
deterioration that accompanied it.
Not all Greeks held disparaging views about aging. In
Sparta the constitution of Lycurgus provided a three-tier
structure of government; the kings, the five ephors, and
the Gerousia. The latter consisted of 28 men over the
age of 60, who were elected by popular ballot, having
previously indicated their willingness to stand for election.
The power of the Gerousia was, however, restricted. They
could not elect a president from their own number, one
of the kings acting in this capacity, and they could only
be convened by the ephors. They were in fact an
advisory body, but they held a privileged position in the
society of Sparta, which may account for the Greek
proverb: "Only in Sparta is it- good to grow old."
The abhorrence of age was a feature of other commu¬
nities, and in many nomad and hunting tribes the elderly
men, once they became unable to defend themselves, were
killed or were isolated from the tribe. Among the Gran
Chaco Indians it was considered the son's duty to kill his
father as soon as he was unable to keep up
with the tribe.
In contrast to most other communities,
the Chinese have revered old age from the
earliest days of their history. "And what is
your honourable age"' is one of the polite
Cont'd
on
next page
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE
& AGING
(Continued)
WHAT IS SENESCENCE?
questions asked on paying a call. This veneration of the
elderly was advocated by Confucius as an ethical duty,
but this ethical aspect assumed a more mystical signifi¬
cance through the linkage of Confucianism with Taoism.
The Chinese, however, despite their reverence for the aged,
were not oblivious of the physical and mental incapacities
of the aged, and some of their poems reveal perhaps the
greatest insight into the significance of aging to the aged.
Increasing years should benefit the animal's chance of
survival, for with greater knowledge and experience it
should be able to avoid some of the hazards of life and,
as a result of wider contacts, develop a greater degree of
immunity to infections. This could be true for man, but
because of the associated disabilities that accompany
chronological aging, the word has become synonymous
both in literature and science with senescence. Man has
always been interested in the cause of senescence. Is it
a state of physical exhaustion, a matter of wear and tear,
a genetically determined phenomenon, the result of
environmental stress, the accumulation of toxic sub¬
stances, the breakdown of a metabolic cycle, a lack of
enzymatic action, the failure of a specific organ or organs,
or a natural event ? These and many other theories have
been propounded and still have their exponents. The
surprising feature is the lack of variety in the theories of
aging. The same themes recur throughout history,
suggesting that the metaphysical concepts of society with
regard to aging have also influenced the scientists, with
a consequent lack of, and search for, objective data.
The use of special functions, such as fertility, as a
measure of senescence demonstrates admirably the diffi¬
culties of the subject. Eckstein cites the comparison of
one year in the life of a mouse, a dog and a human being:
"At its end the mouse has passed through puberty,
delivered probably most of the young it is likely to, and
has at most another twelve months to live. The bitch is
then sexually mature, but will probably not have produced
its first litter, while the human being is only just
beginning to walk and has not even thought about
reproducing itself."
Eating one's way to the grave
In some animals sexual maturity is almost synonymous
with the onset of reproduction, but in others, such as
man, several years what we term puberty may
intervene. Man is one of the few animals in which we
have knowledge of life after the cessation of the repro¬
ductive cycle. Farmers and stockbreeders are not
interested in prolonging the life of animals when their
stud activities are over, so that reliable data concerning
the duration of life in domestic animals after the cessation
of reproduction are not available. There is evidence that
reproductive exhaustion produces senescence in mono-
carpial plants and in fish, but such evidence hardly
justifies the widespread human belief that sexuality has
its price.
Another recurrent theory of senescence is that of the
accumulation of toxic products, perhaps most vigorously
expounded by Metchnikoff with his concept of intestinal
poisons and the need to change the bacterial flora.
Carrel records in Biological Time that he was able to
maintain the heart of a chicken beating for twenty-five
years, by immersing it in a suitable nutrient medium,
which was constantly changed to avoid the accumulation
of metabolites and was accurately controlled for temp¬
erature and oxygen content, and for the avoidance of
bacterial contamination. Many of the theories of nutri¬
tional influences on longevity are related to the concept
of the toxic effect of excessive food intake. McCay has
demonstrated that undernutrition will delay the growth
and prolong the life of rats if the undernutrition is begun
before the onset of the reproductive cycle.
Undernutrition after the development of
maturity did not prolong life.
The tissue changes reported by many
workers Cowdry, Lansing, the present au¬
thor and his group are certainly a feature -
Card games in a sheltered corner of the groundsa favourite dis¬
traction for the inhabitants of Copenhagen's Old People's Town.
"J.K.", aged 78, once had a prosperous tailor's shop in Copenhagen.
He is long-since retired, but still keeps active in his small workshop.
Concerts which are given benevolently by orchestras, singers and solo
musicians are a much looked-forward to divertissement each week.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
DENMARK'S
CITY NAMED
'GAMLES BY'
Main entrance to Old People's Town. High
wall hides a haven where life moves more
slowly than in bustling city of Copenhagen.
People are only allowed to take up residence
¡n "De Garnies By's" pleasant ivycovered flats
when they have reached the age of sixty-five.
Old age is relative and depends not on years but on com¬
panions. This is the way of thought in a special community
in Denmark where sixty-year-olds are regarded as young¬
sters and those in their seventies as at the "Prime of Life".
This is not a Hans Christian Andersen story, though it is a kind
or fairy tale ending for the lives of the old folks of Denmark.
Situated in the midst of busy, bustling Copenhagen, "De Garnies
By" which translated means "The Old People's Town" has an
existance of its own geared to the needs, capabilities and interests of
its inhabitants, none of whom are under sixty-five and some of
whom are in their late nineties.
A high wall separates "the town" from other parts of the city,
not to confine the inmates but to keep the outside world from
pressing too closely on this haven where life moves more slowly.
"De Garnies By " was built by the Corporation of Copenhagen
to provide a home for old people, incapable of looking after them¬
selves completely, yet still able to have semi-active lives. It can
accomodate some 1,560 occupants and was planned for the dual
purpose of giving the old folks a reason for living and at the same
time freeing hospital beds of patients who were only there because
they had no place else to go.
"The town" is divided into two sections the old buildings and
the new. The former are mainly occupied by pensioners, who each
have a bedroom of their own, share a communal recreation lounge
and take their meals in a central dining hall. Their pensions,
2,200 crowns per year for a single person and 3,500 crowns for
a couple, are paid into a central fund for their care and mainte¬
nance. They each receive 30 crowns a month as pocket money.
As the standard of meals is very high and costs more than could
be afforded by the communal fund, the deficit is met by City of
Copenhagen and the State. (A crown is about l/-or 15 cents.)
In the new section, the old people have small, but comfortably
furnished one or two-room apartments for a rental of some 35 to
46 crowns a month. These houses offer complete privacy and a
custodian, who is also a nurse, visits each home every day.
To take care of the bedridden, a special infirmary is attached
to the home and special attention is given to rehabilitating the
patients, so that, if possible they can look after themselves once
more the height of well-being and ambition of the aged.
Though basically an institution, every effort is made to give the
inhabitants as great a degree of independence as their strength
will allow and to maintain a close proximity to every day normality
in the activities of the-home so much so that even marriages take
place. But funerals are frequent, giving a constant reminder that
these old people are nearing the end of their life-span.
The old folks, however, do not have time to meditate on such
things. Flowers have to be tended, vegetable gardens weeded, baby
clothes knitted to welcome a great-great-grandchild, song parts
studied for the next meeting of the choir, library books to be
borrowed and the news of the day to be talked over not to
mention appointments to be kept with friends for card games or
draughts. And so life goes on at De Garnies. By.
U*X+m~ +*+
Veteran choir of 25 entertains fellow citizens. Added together mem¬
bers' ages total 2,000 years. Some citizens are in their late nineties.
"Municipal Library" is one of the most widely-used facilities. It is run
by a 72-year-old librarian, who was formerly a textiles manufacturer.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE
& AGING
(Continued)
No 'natural' death according
to latest scientific studies
of the aging animal, but whether they are cause or effect
remains unanswered and thus does not permit of any
generalization as to the mechanism of senescence.
Wear and tear is probably the most popular view of the
cause of senescence; but the very complexity of the
human organism with its different times for the attain¬
ment and for the duration of certain functions illustrates
still further the difficulty of using any single test of
function to assess what we mean by senescence. The
only mathematical formula one can apply to the study of
senescence is the actuarial life-table, which is really a
measure of the likelihood of dying. Many assumptions
are made in the construction of actuarial tables, i.e., that
there is no allotted span of life such as the psalmist's
three score years and ten, and that there are no gross
differences in the human stock used in compiling the
tables. Despite these and other difficulties, the actuarial
tables do provide information of value both to the
biologist and to the sociologist.
Biblical choice of three score & ten
Death in man is, in fact, accidental. There is no evi¬
dence for the view that natural death is due to the
gradual atrophy of the organs until they can no
longer provide the momentum for life. Vischer reported
the death of two centenarians who were apparently healthy
right up to the onset of their terminal illnesses, yet careful
examination of their organs after death revealed changes
which might have led to death at any time in the previous
thirty years. The experimental study of duration of life
in animal colonies has been vitiated by the incidence of
disease. Lack, however, has shown that the mortality of
wild birds is, after the first few months, independent of
their age. It would thus seem that there is no evidence
for the view that death is natural or that, even if we
could shield man from environmental hazards both
internal and external, he would survive to, say, 100 or 120
years; nor is there any other than biblical authority for
selecting three score years and ten as the natural span
of human life.
The changes in the age distribution of the population
have made senescence a topical problem. The discoveries
of medical science have increased the life expectancy at
birth. Many factors have contributed to the reduction
in infant mortality, but undoubtedly one of the most
important has been the development of the chemother-
apeutic agents the sulphonamides and the antibiotics.
The life expectancy at birth in the United States of Amer¬
ica was 351 years in 1789, 40 years in 1850, 50 in 1900,
55 in 1920, 60 + in 1930, and today it is nearly 70 years.
Similar changes have been reported in most of the
countries of Western Europe and North America. In
Switzerland in 1876-80 the expectation of life for men
was 47 and for women 51. In 1929-32 it Was almost 68 for
men and 70 for women. In Great Britain the expectation
at birth at the turn of the century was just over 50 years,
while today it is 68 for men and 70 for women.
Percentage
of sexage¬
narians
France Sweden England
and Wales Germany Italy
8 1790 1850 1910 1911 1860
10 1850 1882 1925 1925 1908
12 1875 1912 1931 1937 1952
14 1931 1940 1938 1951 l 1964
16 1950 1955 1952 1959 ' 1972
18 1964 1965 1962 1964 * 1988
(1) Western Germany only after 1945.
Sauvy in the above table shows clearly the increase in the
proportion of the population over the age of 60 in some
of the Western European countries. In the United States
of America, Canada, Australia, New Zealand and the white
population of Africa trends are similar. It is impossible
14
to forecast beyond 1980 because we cannot accurately
foretell the birth-rate. In the United Kingdom an unex¬
pected prolongation of the customary , post-war increase
in the birth-rate has occurred, making it impossible to
indicate anything more than trends. A position of bio¬
logical equilibrium, where the birth-rate just ensures the
replacement of one generation by another, with the
maintenance of life expectancy at the same level as it is
today, would mean that approximately 24 per cent of the
population in Great Britain would be sexagenarians.
In the United Kingdom today approximately 14 per cent
of the population are of pensionable age, that is to say,
men over 65 and women over 60, or, to put it in another
way, 2 out of every 15; and 1 out of every 15 is over the
age of 70. In 25 years' time 3 out of every 15 will be of
pensionable age, and 1 out of 9 will be over the age of 70;
in other words there will be approximately 5 million people
over the age of 70.
These population trends have considerable political and
economic significance, since the countries with a low (2-3
per cent) proportion of aged people are the so-called
underdeveloped countries, e.g. the countries of the Far
East and of Eastern Europe. Similar changes are taking
place in these latter countries, but at a much slower rate
owing to the continuing high birth-rate. In the more
developed countries those of Western Europe and North
America; the aging tendency of the population will grow
rapidly even if the downward trend in the birth-rate
ceased, because there is already such a large proportion
of the population in middle life progressing towards old
age.
Further, the advances in medical science have been
effective against infectious diseases, particularly those
affecting the young. The diseases of the second half of
life heart disease, renal disease, vascular degeneration,
cancer are usually insidious in onset, and it would take
several years before even rapid advances in therapy could
influence current trends. Ultimately, such discoveries
might completely alter the age distribution of the popu¬
lation by enabling man to overcome the major known
killing diseases and thus to live longer, 100 or more years
becoming the normal expectancy.
Executives' ulcers & miners' arthritis
Although life expectancy at birth has greatly increased
in the last 100 years, life expectancy for the middle
aged has changed very little. In 1901-10 the
expectation of life for a man aged 60 in the United
Kingdom was approximately 131 years; in 1950 it was
15 years, an increase of li years. The most recent returns
(1955) indicate a slightly more favourable outlook for the
present day, the increase being of over 3 years instead
of li years. The major change, however, remains the
increased expectancy at birth rather than in middle life.
The popular concept of aging is one of deterioration;
old age is the period of the wig, the ear trumpet, the
spectacles, the denture, the artificial leg, and the silver
wind pipe. Undoubtedly many of the disabilities of
advancing years result from the stresses and strains of
life, and from the effects of illness. The miner is more
liable to osteoarthritis of the knees than the clerk. The
business executive and those in positions of authority are
more liable to coronary disease, hypertension and peptic
ulceration. These effects of environmental stress are
becoming recognized, though we have not yet devised a
satisfactory way of living to avoid their deleterious
influence.
The different functions of the body do
not attain their point of maximum effi¬
ciency simultaneously, nor, having attained
their peak, do they lose their prowess at a
constant rate. Acuity of hearing and vision
attain their maximum before the age of 10,
Cont d
on
page I 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
Camera Press, London
PEACE AND CONTENTMENT are vividly expressed in pose and expression of this venerable old Japanese enjoying a game
of "Go" (Japanese checkers) and a cigarette in the Atami Old People's Home, near Tokyo. In the past decade, Japan has opened
numerous homes for its elderly folk, including this one with accomodation for 900 people at Atami, a resort noted for its hot springs.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE
& AGING
(Continued)
Great octogenarians
& their achievements
and yet it is not until the majority of adults reach the age
of 50 that they require glasses for reading. By the age
of 60 they are willing to move to the front of the church,
the theatre or 'the lecture hall, their hearing being not
quite what it was. In their sixties, especially their late
sixties, they are aware of their lack of mobility, of their
joints stiffening, and they avoid hurried movement. It is
also at this age that it becomes obvious that they are
shrinking in stature due to the narrowing of the interve-
tebral discs of the spine. In their early seventies mental
changes become obvious to their friends, though not
necessarily to the aged themselves.
Considerable differences of opinion exist as to the
nature and extent of the mental changes which come
with advancing age. It is often said that the elderly pass
through a stage of second childhood when certain peculiar
traits are accentuated, while many of the more pleasant
features disappear. Attempts have been made to assess
SOPHOCLES
lived to be 90. He wrote
Oedipus Rex when 75 and
Oedipus and Colonus at 89.
At the age of 83, he orga¬
nized defence of Athens.
the changes in intelligence, perception, memory and
mental efficiency brought about by age. It has long been
said that there is a marked deterioration in intelligence
in old age, but recent studies would suggest that there is
nothing more than a slow but steady decline from the
age of 20 to 60, with a slightly increased rate of decline
after 60.
Many of the tests used for children are quite unsuitable
for adults, and the conclusions drawn from such tests
must be treated with reservation. The question which
remains unanswered is whether the rate of decline is in
any way affected by the degree of attainment. In other
words, is the rate of decline constant, and therefore so
comparatively slight in a person of great intelligence that
even at 60 he still appears to be an intellectual giant?
Birren, using the Wechsler Bellevue scale, felt that it was
possible to assess four mental factors in the elderly and
to compare the results with those obtained from younger
age groups. The four factors were verbal comprehension,
non-verbal organization of visual perceptual material
(also called matrix test, which does not involve any writ¬
ing or speech and where people have to match patterns
and designs), memory, and induction.
What is so difficult in all testing is the fact that
memory tests are influenced by intelligence and habit
patterns. The complete lack of longitudinal studies has
been stressed by Lewis, and until we have had extensive
longitudinal studies it is dangerous to generalize about
the mental changes associated with age. The Rorschach
Test, which is known to have the risk of personal bias,
has tended to show that features of aging are: a reduced
responsiveness to emotional stimuli, an inability to use
new resources, difficulty in forming satisfactory social
relationships, and lessened instinctual control.
On the contrary, history is full of examples of men who
have written masterpieces or performed extraordinary
intellectual feats when in their late seventies and eighties.
Goethe completed the second part of Faust, Verdi compos¬
ed Falstaff, and Humboldt wrote Kosmos, when in their
eighties. In the past decade, also, almost every branch
16
of knowledge, science, music, art, literature, philosophy,
and even politics, has had outstanding men who were still
active and productive although nearly octogenarians. If
this is an indication of trends, the outlook for the future
is hopeful.
All the disabilities mentioned ahove would seem to be
the normal lot of man, but in some men they occur sooner
than in others. The effect of disease is often to hasten
the development of what one must call the normal dis¬
abilities. From the medical standpoint, therefore, the
increasing age of the population means that an increas¬
ing proportion of it will be limited in their capacities
unless new discoveries and appliances, similar to hearing
aids, glasses, dentures, enable the disabilities to be mini¬
mized, if not entirely removed. These disabilities, which
may be said to be normal in old age, lead to the problem
of the frail ambulant, when they are more severe.
There is the still more serious medical burden which
results from the nature of the diseases most likely to
affect the middle aged and the elderly. The prevalent
diseases of the second half of life are the degenerative
diseases, all forms of vascular degeneration including
hypertension, coronary, artery and renal disease, cancer,
chronic bronchitis, osteoarthritis, mental disorders and
diabetes mellitus. All are progressive diseases for which
at present we have no certain cure. Some, such as bron¬
chitis, may be largely environmental in origin, and the
removal of smoke and of the atmospheric pollution from
modern industrial processes would do much to minimize,
if not abolish, the condition.
The disorders named above, however, tend to run
protracted courses, often with recurrent periods in hos¬
pital, a high proportion of the patients ultimately becom¬
ing chronic invalids. The cost of medical care already
the most expensive of the social services is likely to
increase very considerably as the result of the altered age
distribution; it may be noted that more than half the
patients in the mental hospitals in Great Britain are over
the age of 60.
Pneumonia, in one form or another, and bronchitis used
to be very frequent causes of death in people over the age
of 50. Today antibiotic therapy enables many such
patients to overcome the infection; but they are left
physically enfeebled and succumb readily to a further
infection, often entering hospital for a period of six to
eight weeks several times a year. This problem has been
referred to as that of "medicated survival".
TITIAN
was 95 years old when he
completed his masterpiece,
The Battle of Lepanto, and
97 when he began to work
on a Descent from the Cross.
Health is almost the most important asset in the life
of a man. It is ill-health and the impairment of function
which cause the majority of the social problems of aging.
Great Britain has been the pioneer in the development of
the social survey technique. Charles Booth's famous
survey of life and labour in London was the first great
survey of what is now called the social science field.
Seebohm Rowntree, by his well-known studies of the City
of York has contributed greatly to our knowledge of living
conditions in the United Kingdom during the past 50
years; he Was also chairman of the first Nuffield
Foundation report, Old People.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
During the last 20 years social surveys on different
aspects of the life of the community have been made in
almost every country. Reference can only be made to a
few of them. The surveys by Seebohm Rowntree three
during the present century have provided invaluable
data concerning the development of the social pattern in
Great Britain as regards work, housing and poverty. The
last of the three surveys concluded that the two major
causes of poverty in the United Kingdom in 1950 were
chronic sickness i.e. where the bread-winner was off
work for more than six months on account of sickness
and old age.
Two surveys, by Dr. Sheldon, of Wolverhampton,
England, and by van Zonneveld of Groningen, Holland,
have produced valuable data on the medical and social
problems of an aging community. Dr. Sheldon visited a
sample of the population of Wolverhampton of pension¬
able age in their own homes. Wolverhampton is a town
of 150,000 inhabitants situated in the centre of England,
in the industrial belt. The sample was obtained by taking
1 in 30 of all the ration cards at the time of the survey
GOETHE
giant among thinkers and
poets completed the last part
of his monumental Faust
only a short time before his
death at the age of 83.
rationing was in force in Great Britain and provided a
valuable register of the population. From this sample
the names and addresses of men over the age of 65 and
women over the age of 60 were selected. The sample
comprised 593 individuals; for 552 of them a complete
form concerning the social history was obtained, and
Dr. Sheldon was able to complete the medical enquiry in
477 cases.
Rather less than a third (29 per cent) were receiving
medical attention at the time of the survey, and more
than a third (44.2 per cent) had received medical attention
during the previous three years. The assessment of the
physical state revealed that malnutrition was uncommon:
24.5 per cent of the group were classified as normal plus,
46.2 per cent as normal, and 29 per cent as subnormal.
These figures relate to an overall assessment and mask
an important difference between the sexes. The men were
more active and contained a significantly higher propor¬
tion of those who were in the normal plus group; in fact,
the men seemed to fall more into the extreme groups
than did the women; the majority of the women had
some disability, although not necessarily a severe one.
Sheldon comments on the different medical problems
that arise after the age of 70. Up to 70 the prevalent
illnesses and disabilities are those which are the common
lot of man, but after 70, weakness, vertigo, spondylitis,
difficulty in facing traffic and loss of confidence become
increasingly prevalent and affect most profoundly the life
and movement of this age group.
Reverting to the group of men over 65 and women over
60, two point five per cent were confined to bed, 8.5
per cent were confined to their own homes, and 22.5 per
cent has limited mobility, being able to walk only to the
end of the street. A third of the sample therefore was
severely restricted in mobility. A further analysis of the
figures into the different five-year age periods demonstrat¬
ed an even more marked increase in the percentage of
individuals suffering from restricted movement after the
age of 70. There were, of course, many factors contribut¬
ing to the impaired power of locomotion, such as defective
vision and pain in the feet. The latter could often have
been cured by chiropody, which would have considerably
increased the possibilities of a fuller life.
The mental state was classified as normal in 81.8 per
cent of cases and only slightly impaired in a further 11.2
per cent, the remainder being divided almost equally into
those who (were difficult to live with, and those in whom
there was evidence of mental disorder.
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
The incidence of sickness amongst elderly persons living
in their own homes is considerable. Sheldon found that
more than half of the group had experienced, after the-
age of 60, illness requiring a period of rest in bed. Most
of the married men were nursed by their wives, whereas
the women were dependent on the help of a neighbour
or relative. Sickness amongst the women interfered more
seriously with family life than did sickness amongst the
men, and often necessitated the absence from work of a
daughter of near relative, or the making of demands upon
the statutory services.
Periods in bed, if prolonged, or for other than minor
illnesses, place great strain on otherwise independent
couples, who manage together for everyday things so long
as there is no sickness. In 7.7 per cent of the sample the
physical burden of sickness was assessed as causing a
severe physical stress on the next generation. In a further
15 per cent, sickness interfered considerably with the
lives of near relatives, often to the extent of preventing
them from getting away and even of spending their holi¬
days with their own family.
Van Zonneveld carried out a similar survey in Holland
at Groningen, a town of 140,000 inhabitants and reached
almost identical conclusions. Once again there was a
higher proportion of women in the group with a moderate
degree of impairment of health. Some 40 per cent of the
sample group were in receipt of medical treatment at the
time of the inquiry or in the three months prior to the
onset of the survey. Ignoring the personal opinions and
the material circumstances of the group, Zonneveld estim¬
ated that for every 1,000 of the population over 65, 4.3
required accommodation in hospital, 34 in special nursing
homes or mental institutions, and 153 in residential homes.
A recent survey in Sheffield, England, a large industrial
city of over 500,000 inhabitants, by Hobson and others,
added few fresh data to those already obtained from the
excellent surveys by Sheldon and van Zonneveld, except
that the former were able to undertake physical examina¬
tions and to obtain from the participants blood and
other samples for laboratory investigations. In the
Sheffield survey 40 per cent were receiving regular medical
attention at least once every three months. The percen¬
tages of bed-ridden, confined to home, and With limited
VERDI
lived till the age of 88. He
composed the opera Othello
when 73, at.80 he complet¬
ed Falstaff, and at 85, wrote
the score for a Te Deum.
outside activities were very similar to Sheldon's findings.
One of the most interesting features of the survey was
the discrepancy between the patient's and the physician's
estimate of fitness. The physician found that 26.2 per
cent of the men could be considered fit, as opposed to the
men's personal estimate of 64.1 per cent. In the case of
the women, the physician estimated that 23 per cent were
fit, whereas '48.7 per cent of the women considered them¬
selves so.
Dr. van Zonneveld is now engaged in organizing a
complete survey of the elderly population in Holland, co¬
operating with the family doctors. This thorough and
important social survey will also include a careful survey
of mental health.
Sheldon found that in Wolverhampton 98 per cent of
all old people lived at home and only 2 per cent in
institutions. The latter percentage is today probably an
underestimate. Of the people living at home, 44 per cent
were married, a third of them living without and the other
two-thirds with their children. Another 44
per cent were either widows or widowers,
the latter tending to live with relatives,
whilst the former lived in their own homes.
It is of interest that more than half of
those living alone had children or near
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier October 1958
Y >
OLD DOC CUMMINS
When the photographs on these pages were taken, Dr. John B. Cummins was, at 98,
probably the oldest practising doctor in America with a record of service of over
60 years (average service among doctors is 34 years). Known as "Uncle Doc" to
his patients, he graduated from the University of Nashville Medical School in 1897. Photo,
opposite page, shows Dr. Cummins examining a patient on one of his daily rounds from
his office in Fort Worth, Texas, where he keeps up to date with new medical practices and
developments. Dr. Cummins' working day begins at 8 a.m. and lasts till 5 p.m., but he is
available for calls at anytime. As for retiring, he considers that is something for loafers.
Photos show : Above (from left to right), "Uncle Doc" in his office. His memory and his
records cover as many as four generations. Old car takes him on distant calls. In the old
days he rode a horse and where the horse could not go he walked. Rounds of house calls
find him stepping out in all parts of town. Right, after a visit, Doc. writes a prescription.
Below he lunches in his favourite restaurant and buys supplies in the local drugstore.
lohn R. Hamilton © Globe Photos, New York.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
A DECENT HOME
TO LIVE
Henri Cartier-Bresson £> Macnum Photos
Two types of homes, a 14-storey apartment building and two-storey row houses, are com¬
bined in architectural design of Cleveland. Ohio, housing project for old people.
Protection and comfort is ensured in bathroom (above, left), of a Florida community project
for old persons. All fixtures are anchor bolted. In kitchens low shelves make work easier.
USIS photos.
Every need of the aged has been considered In this Florida old people's home including, ample
storagespace, wide doors and a three-quarter height wall to provide air and light in kitchen.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
SCIENCE
& AGING
(Continued from p. 17)
Striking findings from
recent national surveys
relatives living either next door, within a short distance,
or who visited regularly.
The analysis of the health of an aging population in
the middle of the twentieth century reveals the extent to
which ill-nealth and disability increase the dependence
of the elderly upon the family, or upon the community,
be it good neighbours or the state. The fundamental
problem, as already stated, is not new; but the changing
social pattern and the increasing number of individuals
involved are necessitating a different approach. The
changing concept of family life is throwing more respon¬
sibility upon the community, whether it be the voluntary
or the statutory authorities.
In an underdeveloped and rural community, the centre
of social life is the family. Several families may unite in
a common task, such as farming or fishing; such com¬
munities will remain small, comparatively self-contained,
and with the family atmosphere dominant. They will
share a common mode of life and common culture, and
even in the next stage of development the head man or
leader will still assume a paternal position of authority
in relationship to the group. Such a family group must
utilize the skills and abilities of all its members, so that
work is required from both young and old, according to
their skill and capacity. There will be variety of company
for the elderly, and the doting grandparent to comfort
the disappointed child. Such a community will not be
able to understand the problems of pensions and taxes
and of divided responsibility.
The advent of the industrial age altered the life of the
communities, both geographically by demanding greater
mobility of labour, and also culturally because the
members of the family often followed different trades and
occupations. Furthermore the scattering of the family
lessened the paternal authority of the home and accen¬
tuated the individuality of the different members. The
development of wealth, centred upon minerals and manu¬
factured articles, necessitated new methods for safe¬
guarding estate and property other than land. The result
was the development of insurance to provide security for
the individual and his dependents against the hazards
of life.
Loneliness & insecurity
The diminishing size of the family has accentuated the
loneliness, sense of insecurity, feeling of uselessness
and of dependence that were already evident in the
early industrial period, and had led to the present phase
of organized society, commonly referred to as the welfare
state. It would be wrong, however, to assume that lone¬
liness, insecurity, a feeling of unwantedness and depen¬
dence amongst the elderly are something new that did
not exist in primitive communities; it is rather that the
evolution of the social pattern, through the breaking up
of the family, has accentuated these difficulties.
Disability and ill-health amongst the aging members of
a community obviously affect its productive capacity and
therefore its ability to maintain its standards of living.
Present population trends in Western Europe indicate that
the percentage of dependents children under 15 and
adults over 65 is likely to remain constant during the
next 20 years, the decrease in the percentage of children
under 15 being counterbalanced by an increase in the
percentage of adults over the age of 65. The economic
problem is whether it will prove more costly to maintain
the elderly than to rear the young. If full activity could
be maintained despite increasing years, no problems
would arise. Increased productivity could likewise coun¬
terbalance the cost of maintenance of the elderly, so that
undue despondency concerning the economic position may
prove unjustified.
The needs of the elderly in modern society have been
met in two ways by the provision of pensions or by relief
funds, dispensed either by voluntary charitable organiza
tions or by governmental agencies. Pensions are of two
kinds: the voluntary schemes subscribed to by individuals
or firms on behalf of their employees, and those provided
by state departments and state insurance schemes. Indi¬
viduals enter into agreement with insurance companies,
the policies really forming a variant of normal life
assurance. Many firms now have schemes to cover their
administrative, clerical, and skilled staff, and a few firms
cover all grades of staff. Such schemes are in the main
financed by the firm, the employee making some contribu¬
tion in the majority of cases. In state departments a
percentage of the salaries is deducted yearly, and pen¬
sions are usually based on the income during the last few
years before retirement and on the length of service.
Oldest ages = lowest incomes
State insurance pension schemes for all citizens usually
provide for a flat rate of benefit for all persons fully
insured on the attainment of a fixed age, on condition
that they are not earning more than a certain amount
per week or per month and have no private savings in
excess of a stated amount. These pensions are often
looked upon as a right, although they are more in the
nature of insured relief and are provided by contributions
from the employee, the employer and the state. The
amount of the pension varies considerably in different
countries, and in the past, rates have normally been below
the minimum wage that could be earned by an unskilled
worker, so that the pension should not be an inducement
to idleness. In recent years some countries have adopted
the principle that need should determine the rate- of
pension. Lord Beveridge, in his report on Social Insurance
and Allied Services 1942, advocated this principle, and his
idea has been largely incorporated into recent British
legislation.
That need exists has been shown by the analysis of
incomes of the elderly. Estimates of the incomes in 1949
in the United States of America showed the average
yearly incomes in the different age groups as follows:
35-44, $2,591; 45-54, $2,751; 55-64, $2,366; and 65 plus,
$1,016. The Federal Security Agency enquired into the
source of income of 11.5 million individuals over 65 in
1949 and found the sources of income to be as follows:
Per cent
Employment	 3.8 millions 33
Social insurance and related
programmes 3 . millions 26.1
Old age assistance	 2.1 millions 18.3
Other sources, including no income 2,6 millions 22.6
The Institute of Life Insurance in 1950 listed sources of
income for persons over 65 as follows:
Employment 34 -
Pensions 18
Private assistance	 17
Investments 9
Public assistance '. 	 22
Further analysis by the Federal Security Agency, using
a different method of computation (spending units),
revealed that approximately 75 per cent of persons over
65 had no income from investments or work, and that
28 per cent received no pension or allowance. Thus, even
in a wealthy country such as the United States, a
considerable proportion of the population over 65 are
unable to support themselves or are without relatives to
provide for them.
The pensions schemes have to be supplemented by
public or national assistance.
In Switzerland there is a national
pensions scheme, the Federal Old Age and
Survivors Insurance, which came into force
in 1948, but full annuities will not be
available until 1968. The rates are low, 720
to 1,700 Swiss francs per annum for a
Cont'd
on
next page
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
GRANDMA A CHAMPION BOWLER
Women members of the Worthing Bowling Club, England Camera Press, London
SCIENCE & AGING (Continued)
single person, 1,160 to 2,720 Swiss francs for a married
couple. Single men or women can draw their pensions
at 65; married couples get the full pension when the
husband reaches 65, and the Iwife 60. Supplementary
pensions and assistance are however necessary, and these
are the responsibility of the cantons.
In Denmark the social insurance scheme is a mixture
of insurance and national assistance. The benefit for a
married couple is approximately 45 per cent of an
unskilled worker's wage in Copenhagen. Some 60 per
cent of the population eligible are in receipt of such pen¬
sions. In the United Kingdom the position is very similar.
Approximately 60 per cent of all persons eligible on
account of age draw their pension, and over the age of
70 approximately one half require supplementing from the
National Assistance Board.
It will be seen therefore that in all the countries
considered the existing pensions schemes are inadequate
to meet the financial needs of the elderly. Furthermore,
private pensions schemes, although more likely to be
related to the retiring salary of the participant, depend
for their real value on the maintenance of a constant
value of the currency. In times of monetary stability
such schemes are excellent, but during periods of inflation
they are inadequate.
How to adjust pensions to provide reasonable financial
security for everyone is a major problem of the welfare
state. The enormous financial burden of an adequate
pensions scheme for everyone after the age of 65 raises
therefore the question of employment for the elderly.
Until the last war unemployment was a serious feature
of the life of industrialized countries. The guilds, and
later the unions, tried to combat unemployment by
restrictive practices^ a fixed rate for a fixed job, by
delaying the age of entry and fixing a retiring age. There
22
was also the fear that the older workers might work for
lower rates, their needs being more modest. The intro¬
duction of pensions schemes has had the effect *of
increasing the frequency of retirement at a certain age.
Retirement at 65 is four times greater in firms with
pensions schemes than in those without such schemes.
Further, smaller firms tend to retain the services of
workers beyond the retiring age more than do the larger
firms, i.e. the firms employing more than 500 workers.
Compulsory retirement at a specific age has adminis¬
trative advantages. It is uniform in application and easy
to administer, enables management to plan ahead to
anticipate replacements, and enables the worker to
prepare for retirement and to make alternative
arrangements.
Another reason for the tendency to fix a retirement age
is related to the problem of promotion. The younger
employees of a firm often feel frustrated if there is not a
reasonable opportunity for promotion, and retaining
employees beyond the normal retiring age undoubtedly
interferes with promotion. Union opinion is sensitive in
this matter as the unions tend to lay great stress upon
seniority. In the management of their own affairs, the
unions before World War II tended to demand that their
executive officers retire at 60, or in some cases even
at 55.
The heavy cost of pensions which is likely to increase
in Western Europe because of the aging of the popula¬
tion is an economic reason for recommending abolition
of a fixed age for retirement. Other factors must however
be considered. For instance, would postponement of
retirement be in the interests of the health of the
Individual? Is it fair and reasonable that a man should
work until he drops? Does the capacity for work
diminish with age? Does this capacity for work depend
upon the nature of the work? Should there be different
grades and different hours of work for the older
employee?
Analysis of the length of unemployment periods in the
different age groups, both in the United States and in the
United Kingdom, show these periods to be longest in the
55-64 age group and the 65 plus age groups. Pension
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
AND AN INTREPID SAILOR
m\'-*+-
Oakland Women's Rowing Club, California, U.S.A. Globe Photos, New York
schemes here have an adverse influence because insurance
companies usually demand a higher premium for older
workers; workmen's compensation rates are also usually
higher for the elderly. It is often stated that the older
workers are less efficient, less adjustable to new ideas,
and more difficult to train, and that they have a higher
accident and sickness rate. These comments from
employers are misleading and are not entirely borne out
in practice, since most firms like to retain their elderly
skilled craftsmen.
Experience gained during World War II, when labour
was at a premium, and also the findings of the University
of Illinois survey, revealed that there was less absenteeism
among older workers. Although their rate of work
was slower than that of the younger age groups, they
were more reliable; the numbers of articles rejected were
smaller, and the damage to instruments and machines
much less than with younger workers. The sickness rate
for minor illnesses of less than five days was lower than
for the younger age groups, though there was a greater
incidence of long-term chronic illnesses which often
necessitated a few of the older workers being absent for
long periods, thus making the overall loss of time for
sickness greater than in the younger age groups.
Le Gros Clark has recently analysed the age of men
employed in 32 occupations in Great Britain, involving
4,004,700 men, or 25.6 per cent of the total males occupied.
The number of men over 65 in these occupations was
17,400, or 25 per cent of the national total of occupied
males over the age of 65. Using "'survival rates" the
percentage of the total numbers of men known to have
reached their mid-sixties and still at work in their
normal job, maintaining a reasonable degree of
efficiency Clark was able to compare employment rates
of the elderly in the different trades. The results were
influenced by the introduction of pensions schemes, by
changes in the manufacturing process, and by changes
in market and consumer demands.
Clark concludes that a considerable number of workers
today will have to be found alternative jobs in their early
or mid-sixties if they are not to be forced into premature
retirement. There is evidence that some men are already
making this transition to lighter and less exacting work,
often 'within their own industry. Reviewing the results
collectively, Clark estimates that 30-40 per cent of the
men could not be expected to carry on with their normal
jobs after their mid-sixties, and that alternative work
would have to be found for them if they were not to retire.
He assumes that 10 per cent would be in such a state of
impaired health that no question of any work would arise,
but provision would be necessary for at least 20 per cent.
In 1951, the year of the analysis, there were 2,072,100 men
in the age group 55-64 in the United Kingdom. This
would mean that 400,000 would require alternative
employment over a period of ten years, or 40,000 a year.
This raises the problem of the type of alternative work
to reserve for the elderly and of the question of training
for alternative work. Experience in the placement of
disabled persons, and the introduction of a quota system
where all employers must employ a certain percentage
of disabled persons, have shown that such methods do not
solve the problem. Firms would naturally reserve the
special appointments for their own staff and would not
readily take on elderly staff who had not previously been
employed by them.
A special experimental unit sponsored by the Nuffield
Foundation in the University of Cambridge, England,
under the direction of Sir Frederick Bartlett and A. T.
Welford, have been studying experimentally the effect of
age on skill. They have concentrated on the earlier age
groups, 45-65, with a view to determining trends rather
than to solving the problem of the 65 plus group alone.
They found that there is a slowing of skilled actions in
the late twenties, followed by a considerable degree of
recovery; then there comes a return of the slowing in
the late thirties and middle forties, followed by the a
further period of improvement, before the onset of a
more progressive slowing in the middle or late fifties.
These conclusions apply to rapid skilled
work not involving heavy muscular effort.
Where moderate or heavy muscular work
is involved, there is a marked decline after
the middle forties.
The changes described are not so much
Cont'd
page 25
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Veterans of France
Henri Cartier-Bresson © Magnum Photos
OLDEST
LIVING
FRENCHWOMAN
The oldest living Frenchwoman,
Madame Louise Blanc, made her
first trip by air from Paris
recently to visit her birthplace
at Puylarens, near Toulouse, in
southern France. Aged 105,
she can still remember the last
time she travelled thereby
stagecoach, which was then the
only transport available. The
modern way, she declares, is
far more comfortable. At the
start of this century, when she was 47 years old, Madame Blanc's chances
of living to a ripe old age were, statistically speaking, very poor. The
average life expectancy in France was then about 45 years of age. By 1938
it had risen to 58 and today it is 66 double that of a century ago. In
France, as in other countries, there are more women than men in the
older age groups. In I 957 there were 1,550,000 Frenchwomen between
the ages of 70 and 80 compared with only 930,000 Frenchmen.
S Universal Photo, Paris.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier.
SCIENCE
& AGING
(Continued)
October 1958
Reti remen t a re effects more
damaging than beneficial?
in the effector as in the receptor mechanisms. An
analysis of the processes shows that the most variable
element in any skill requiring a series of accurate
adjustments to changing stimuli is in the interval
between an adjustment in one direction followed by an
adjustment in another direction. Older people look more
carefully at what they are doing and at the signals
necessary for the next stage. They are therefore suited
for work demanding a high degree of accuracy, especially
if they are able to ¡work at their own pace, but are much
less suited for belt work or processes where the rate tends
to be geared to suit the younger worker.
Welford and others have also found that older people
are less receptive to theoretical instruction. They often
prefer written instructions which they can study at their
leisure rather than group demonstrations. They learn new
processes which are based on their past experience with
comparative ease, but are much slower in adapting
themselves to fundamentally new or different ideas. It
is necessary to break down a new process into component
movements, which allow the elderly person to build up
the process more slowly. Younger people seem to exhibit
less delay in anticipating the next move. These valuable
experiments indicate the complexity of the problems; yet
they offer hope that, with further development and
extension of the study to job analysis in industry, it
should be possible to find suitable jobs for the aged.
For 'dream house' read 'nightmare'
But apart from the economic implications which
employment of the elderly has for society, there is the
importance of employment to the individual himself.
Undoubtedly many men and women continue working
after reaching retirement age because of financial need.
To many, work is purely a means of earning enough to
live, the work itself being without interest. But the fact
that the proportion of the self-employed and the skilled
craftsmen who remain at work until well into their
seventies is higher than in other categories of workers
shows that they have more than a mere financial interest.
Work is an important factor in their lives; it affords a
means of self-expression and makes them feel that they
are useful to society. Retirement is a serious break for
most men. It means loss of invaluable associations, it
brings a feeling of unwantedness, of dependence on, and
uselessness to, the community. For the man with few
interests, retirement often means that his world suddenly
becomes very limited.
Another important problem for the aged is accommo¬
dation. Many people save, often at great personal cost,
for their retirement. They select a site, quite likely build
a house but how rarely do they anticipate their real
accommodation needs ? The survey at Wolverhampton
by Sheldon emphasized some of the physical problems
of the elderly, their dislike of stairs, their tendency to
falls, and their immobility. The elderly adapt slowly to
changes of light intensity, and therefore require good and
even lighting, they also like warmth, and the provision of
central heating is desirable in accommodation specially
designed for them.
Many countries have paid special attention to the
designing of houses, bungalows, and flats for the elderly.
Such special accommodation should be planned in small
groups, preferably not in isolated communities, so that
normal housing which permits young relatives to live
within easy access is near at hand. The amount of
special accommodation for the elderly is nothing like
adequate. In Great Britain between the two wars over
3,150,000 houses were built1,440,347 by local government
and the remainder by individuals or private firms; yet
only approximately 1 per cent of all this building was
specially designed for the elderly.
Immediately after the war the building programme
concentrated upon houses suitable for young married
couples with children, and very little accommodation for
the elderly was constructed. This is now being corrected,
but there is considerable leeway to make up. Some 5-7
per cent of all new building in Great Britain during the
next 10 years would need to be allocated to old people if
most of them are to be housed in suitable accommodation.
It is recognized that there is a stage at which the
elderly, though they may be able to dress and attend to
personal details, are unable to look after themselves; yet
they do not require nursing or hospital care. The Salva¬
tion Army was the first organization to provide
accommodation for this category when they established
their first Eventide Homej in Norway in 1910. In Great
Britain today there are nearly 2,000 homes, or hostels,
caring for nearly 60,000 elderly people. One-third are
run by voluntary organizations and two-thirds by local
government. The majority house 30-35 elderly persons,
usually of one sex only, although an increasing number
are being planned for both men and women. In Swit¬
zerland 25,000 persons over the age of 65 are living in
public or private hostels. In the United States 217,000
persons over the age of 65 are housed in public or private
institutions primarily designed for the aged. Accom¬
odation of this kind is undoubtedly necessary, especially
nowadays when families are small and such a high
percentage of the frail ambulant individuals are without
relatives.
Collectives homes and hostels, however, do not afford
the ideal solution. Transference to such homes affords
security and, for many, eases the loneliness of old age.
On the other hand, for those with active minds and wide
interests, this kind of home can have a restricting
influence, and limited contacts with the outside world
often makes the inmates uninterested, quarrelsome and
unhappy. The aim when providing accommodation for
the elderly should be, whenever possible, to maintain the
elderly in their own homes. Grouping of bungalows or
flats so that a warden can be appointed to keep an eye
upon a group of elderly persons and, if necessary, to
provide a midday meal, is not only valuable in allowing
the elderly person to remain a member of the community,
but is often a more economical way of solving the problem
of care of the elderly.
'Pot & Pans' Service in the home
The provision of domiciliary services can do much to
help the elderly, particularly the frail, to retain and
live in their own homes. Many voluntary and charit¬
able organizations, the Churches, and Government De¬
partments play an important role in this respect. The
extent of the help varies according to districts and to
needs. It may include special nursing, provision of special
apparatus, the adaptation of the household fittings to
special needs, laundry service, a meals service. In
addition, a visiting service is often arranged. It may
consist merely of a regular friendly call, but may extend
to reading to the old person, looking after the garden,
undertaking shopping expeditions, the writing of letters,
a "pots and pans" service, and occasionally to the provi¬
sion of more comprehensive help the so-called Home
Help Service.
Special services, such as chiropody and physiotherapy,
are also organized for old people in their homes. For
the more active, the club movement with its discussion
groups, hobbies, talks, competitions, provides the opportu¬
nity to make friends, and minimizes the extreme
loneliness, which is probably the greatest single problem
of the elderly today. A certain degree of dependence
and an inhability to contribute actively to the life of the
community can only accentuate this problem.
Medical care is the most expensive of the social services,
and the high proportion of the elderly who require
hospital attention both for mental and physical illness
provides the hospital administrator with his biggest and
most costly problem. Special units, called geriatric units,
are being developed in the Scandinavian countries, in
Great Britain, and the United States to foster a more
progressive and active attitude of mind towards the care
of the chronic elderly sick.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
MAN-THE LONGEST
LIVED OF MAMMALS
There are more old people in the world today and life expectancy
is much higher than formerly. Yet the fact that more people
today grow older is but a "'return to nature". Man is the
longest-lived of mammals and it is an early death which is "unna¬
tural", according to a recent World Health Organization CWHO)
report.
The number of old people in European countries is reflected in
figures issued by WHO, showing population percentage of persons
aged 60 or more. These show that Monaco with 22.9% has most old
people. Then come France, 17%; England and Wales, 15.9%; and
Austria and Belgium, 15.6%. Of 25 countries listed those with the
fewest old people are: Yugoslavia, 8.9%; Roumania, 8.2% and
Turkey, 6.0%.
The population of 574 million in Europe and the U.S.S.R. in 1950
is expected to increase to 947 million by the year 2000, says WHO.
Yet in most countries, no co-ordinated efforts have so far been made
to solve all the medical social and economic problems arising from
the steadily increasing number of the aged.
Public health aspects of these problems were highlighted recently
in Oslo where specialists from eleven European countries attended a
WHO meeting to discuss health needs of the aged and how they can
be met.
When is a man old? To judge by the ages for retirement, or
pension, or old age benefits, this varies from country to country:
56 years in Argentina; 60 in France and New Zealand; 65 in Australia,
Belgium, Czechoslavakia, Denmark, Finland, Switzerland, the UJK.
and the U.S.A.; 67 in Sweden; and 70 in Canada, Ireland and Norway.
Through public health measures a great contribution can and is
being made towards preventing the aged becoming a burden to
themselves, to their families and to the community. Reviewing the
present situation, the WHO Advisory Group in Oslo made a series of
recommendations covering various aspects of care in old age.
They suggested that investigations should be made to' find out
whether retirement has an adverse effect on health and to determine
standards for mental and physical fitness related to occupations for
the aged. People capable of continuing work after reaching
retirement age should be given guidance on alternative employment,
including part-time jobs.
The group supported the principle that care for the aged is not a
.matter of charity, but of social justice. The aged are full particip¬
ating members of society who have a right to choose freely how they
wish to live and, when possible, to take care of themselves as long
as they desire. This implies provision not only of sufficient financial
resources, but also of all kinds of medical and social services.
Services for the next decades should be planned now.
The Oslo meeting will be followed by other activities relating to
the welfare of the elderly. WHO was advised to convene seminars,
study groups, advisory groups and expert committees, to provide
fellowships in gerontology and geriatrics, to train more workers in
the care of the elderly, and to appoint consultants to advise and
guide the planning and development of programmes.
Rudi vVeissenstein
THRIVING INDUSTRY in Neve Avot, an
Israeli village for the aged, is carpet weaving.
For most of the weavers this is a skill
they learned since coming to the village.
Israel
A NEW TREND
AWAY FRO
OLD-AGE HOMES
When Israel became an independent
nation ten years ago, it had no old
age problem. The average age of
the Jewish population was low, for it was
a pioneering country and those who flocked
to it were mostly young people who came
to study and train. Those who had come
in the early stages of the Zionist movement
and had grown old in the country were
well integrated either they continued to
work or else they were well taken care of
by their children or the settlements they
had helped to found. The handful of
destitute Jews who were drawn to the Holy
Land by their religious fervour and had
neither the physical ability nor the inclin¬
ation to earn their bread, were maintained
to a large extent by orthodox religious
groups from abroad individually or in
institutions which respected and admired
them; for were they not praying daily by
the Wailing Wall for the redemption of all
the world's Jewry?
Then with the tidal wave of immigration
that marked Israel's first years of state-
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier October 1958
hood, the picture changed. Jews streamed
to the State of their Fathers that received
them so joyously in their hundreds of
thousands. These were not hand-picked
pioneers, but entire Jewish communities.
In the displaced person's camps of Europe,
in the slums of Near and Middle Eastern
cities and in the far-off farming villages of
Afghanistan, Yemen, Morocco and Turkey,
Jews roused themselves and applied to be
taken to Israel.
It was only natural that such unrestricted
immigration should include a dispro¬
portionate percentage of destitute, aged
and sick or a combination of all three.
For those who had been a burden to their
families and communities sought the
economic and physical safety which seemed
to be offered by the Promised Land. The
demographic composition of the population
changed drastically: the proportion of the
very young and the very old grew, and
that of the working age-groups shrank,
which means that less people had to
produce for a larger number of dependents.
The demographic composition of the
population of Israel has only changed to
resemble that of many well-established
Western countries (Holland, Italy, Canada
for instance); but the period in which this
took place was so short that often it gave
the authorities no breathing space.
More often than not immigrants could
neither accomodate nor support the aging
parents they brought along with them. The
majority of them were unskilled in any
trades or professions and also lacked work
discipline. But to help the young take
root in their new country, care had to be
provided for their aged relations.
The first . solution proposed and also
the most costly was the establishment of
homes for the aged. The American Joint
Distribution Committee, (the world-wide
Jewish rescue and support organization),
came to Israel to help absorb the needy,
sick and aged immigrants. It established
a wide network of institutions for new¬
comers above the age of 65 (60 in the case
Rudi Weissenstein
TRAINED PHARMACIST, but unable
to obtain a post because of his age, this
immigrant ¡s now able to do a useful job in a
pharmacy attached to an old folks' home.
of women) where, entirely free of charge,
they could live out their lives carefree and
productively, sheltered from all physical or
mental worries. Various other semi-official
and private organizations also established
homes for those aged who did not qualify
for '"Joint" care veteran residents and
those who could not be 'classified as needy.
Moreover, the Organization of Central
European Immigrants has established a
novel apartment block for elderly working
persons, where they find independent life
in self-contained modern flats but where,
if needs be, they are taken care of by a
house-mother. There, even an ailing octa-
genarian can live on his own since he
knows that if he needs help he has only
to press a bellpush.
However, with the continued growth of
the higher age groups by immigration as
well as the natural growth of a people
with a high life expectancy (Israel's is
among the highest in the world) removal
to old age homes was not the solution,
especially so as in all advanced countries
there is a movement away from institution¬
alizing and towards the maintenance of a
closely-knit community in which the elder
citizens find their place.
National Old Age insurance, legislated
in 1953, which began supporting the aged
in 1957 with monthly cash allowances,
provides a very minimum subsistence for
old people of pensionable age who were
born after September, 1866. Immigrants of
a higher age, who do not qualify under
this insurance project, are supported by a
fund, contributed to in equal proportions,
by the Welfare Ministry, the Jewish Agency
for Israel which brought them to the
country, and the '"Joint" on the justified
assumption that thus, the demands for beds
in homes for aged would shrink.
Statistics show that of Israel's 140,000
citizens aged 60 or above, 35,000 (including
members of the Arab minorities) draw
insurance pensions; another 7,000 get
special support from the three agencies,
and 6,500 are accommodated in old age
homes (over 71% in "Joint" centres).
In addition an organization sponsored by
the government has set up workshops for
people above the age at which labour
exchanges would assign them to jobs. In
carpentry, cobbling and other shops for
men and handicraft and sewing workshops
for women, about 3,000 elderly persons
earn their keep. ..But because of the diffi¬
culties of marketing the products, this
scheme has to be ¡heavily subsidized.
A new project designed to restore the
aged to their communities concerns able-
bodied couples of a higher age group, who
are provided with small furnished apart¬
ments, together with, tools to enable them
to work at their trades. They are housed
on the ground floors of large apartment
blocks where they can live out their lives
normally in a normal neighborhood, and
where they take an active part in com¬
munity life instead of reminiscing with
their contemporaries in old age homes
about times long gone. Here, the burden
falls on the municipality. It grants this
new kind of citizen free services and utilities
and helps find work. Its welfare worker
has to be their constant guide.
The municipality is also responsible
though other authorities, also extend
material help and guidance in the very
new and successful project that has helped
enormously in integrating elder citizens:
clubs. Together with the old age pensions
which provide security from want, clubs
have made the decisive difference for
Paul Goldman
PROFESSIONAL TAILOR from Poland is
82, but still puts in a full day's work In the
sewing room at Neve Avot, either repairing
clothes or making new suits to measure.
thousands of aged between uselessly whiling
away long days and getting an enormous
amount of pleasure out of the last years of
otherwise often joyless lives. At daily get-
togethers, aged men and women spend
several interesting and productive hours
which on the one hand stimulate them into,
active community life and on the other
provide them with a small additional rev¬
enue in work projects handicrafts, garden¬
ing and the like. These neighborhood
clubs bring people together, and, where
they are attached to old age homes, they
tear down the invisible walls that had arisen
between the institutions and the communi¬
ties around them.
In clubs, the aged have found a kind
of raison d'être. They make friends; they
get a decent meal; for a while they are
away from the overcrowded home and
nagging children and grand-children; they
have a share in cultural life, are shown
movies and are taken on short trips; they
have counsellors with whom to discuss
their particular problems.
Clubs are not restricted to any particular
stratum of Israel's diversified community:
well-established "old-timers" from Central
Europe have a club in Haifa in which the
men play chess, read the daily papers (in
their German mother-tongue) and have a
big library; and the old ladies exchange
cooking recipes and shopping tips. Arab
residents of Acre were provided with a
club, next to the centre for aged Jews,
and it did not take long before members
went visiting each other and organizing
joint activities for both clubs.
What is needed is yet more clubs, in
city, town and village, for they have provid¬
ed proof if ever there was a doubt that
this is the kind of project that makes life
worth living at the "golden age." Cancella¬
tion letters regularly reach the "Joint"
from former applicants for places in homes
for aged. They explain that in the clubs
they have found what they had searched
for, thus confirming that what the old man
and the old women need is company in
their normal community, rather than a
sheltered existence.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
CENTENARIAN CHOIR, formed by the oldest members of the Abkhazian Folk Art Club in the Soviet Republic of Georgia, gives many
concerts. Members wear Georgian national costume. Out of Georgia's total population of four million, well over 1,000 people are known to
have reached the age of ninety or more. Of these, two-thirds are women. Some of Georgia's many patriarchs are shown on opposite page.
MAN'S LIFESPAN:
A ROUND CENTURY
Every man wants to live a long
and fruitful life. To put off old
age, to live "forever", has been
man's dream all through history.
Many a myth and tale of yore tells
us of his search for the "fountain of
eternal youth." In our day the prob¬
lem of longevity has attracted the
attention of science, too, and a whole
new branch of science, called geron¬
tology, has arisen. The International
Association of Gerontology formed
after World War II has already held
four international congresses to dis¬
cuss metabolism, the changes caus¬
ed by senescence, and regimes of
work for persons of advanced age.
The last of these conferences took
place in Italy last year.
The first theory of senescence to
be based on scientific experiment was
advanced in the last century by the
Russian scientist Ivan Mechnikov,
who showed that the prolongation of
life was possible and indicated prac¬
tical ways of influencing individual
28
by Professor
G. Z. Pitskhelauri
development in order to prevent
premature senility and death.
In the Soviet republic of Georgia
alone (population 4,000,000) there live
1,060 persons of 90 and over. Of
these, two-thirds are women. The
higher death rate among men is
apparently due to arterio-sclerosis,
heart diseases, a greater proneness to
accidental injuries, and so on.
Recently the Georgian Institute of
Industrial Hygiene and Occupational
Diseases carried out a detailed study
of one thousand long-lived persons in
the Soviet republic of Georgia. The
results are revealing.
Georgia is a country richly endow¬
ed by nature. The humid sub-tropi
cal area along the picturesque Black
Sea Coast gives way in the central
and eastern parts of the republic to
fertile plains. Dotting the Caucasian
mountains are sub-alpine and alpine
meadows and dense forests. The
pleasant climate, the great number
of health resorts and mineral springs
of medicinal value, tend to favour
longevity.
Of no less importance as a factor
making for longevity is work. It is
naive to think that the best way to
keep healthy is to do no work; the
facts prove that idle men never live
to a ripe old age. Besides giving a
sense of vitality, work helps to pre¬
serve a man's strength and his lively
interest in things. This is strikingly
apparent in the old men and women
still working on collective farms or
elsewhere, tending orchards, livestock
or poultry.
One of the most curious features
brought out by the investigation is
that nearly all of the thousand aged
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier October 1958
persons studied have been long marri¬
ed 50 to 80 years. Family life
apparently is conducive to health and
longevity. Most of the members of
the group have numerous progeny.
Only 24 of the thousand have never
had any children. 'About 200 have
had up to 10 children, and 35 up to
15 and over.
A tranquil life among the members
of their own family, good care and
normal hygienic conditions help these
people to preserve their mental and
physical strength.
None of the group suffers from
physical ailments. Most of them were
never sick in their lives; quite a few
never underwent medical examination
before this study was made.
More than 300 of the old people
studied look much younger than their
age. Many have retained good eye¬
sight. Only two old men were found
to have cataracts, 72 wear glasses.
Only 36 complained of deafness; the
rest have normal or only slightly
impaired hearing.
Most were found to have healthy
nervous systems and a good memory,
especially of events long past. Poor
memory was found only in 40 cases.
Honey and beans
for longer life ?
Another point of interest is diet.
As a- rule, the old folk studied
have three or four meals a day,
and at regular hours. They rarely
overeat. No special diet is observed:
meat, vegetables and dairy foods are
all included, as well as the bean called
"lobio" and hominy, cheese and
yoghourt. No more than 25 restricted
themselves to a dairy and vegetable
diet.« Some of them consider that
plentiful quantities of fruit, grapes
and honey account for their health
and long life. Most of them show
great moderation in drinking and"
smoking.
Study of the working and living
conditions of the long-lived citizens
of Georgia suggests the conclusion
that any man can postpone old age
by regulating his life sensibly.
The immediate task of public
health services in all countries, I
would say, is to register all their long-
lived citizens and keep them under
medical observation. Periodic medi¬
cal examinations of the aged is
important and should include exami¬
nation of their mental powers, analy¬
sis of their habits and interests and
of their experience. Such a study
would make it possible to outline
comprehensive medical and prophy¬
lactic measures calculated to prolong
the life and physical activity of the
aged.
A lifespan of a round century is
not a dream; it is a practical pos¬
sibility.
Aged 94 and formerly an expert hunter
and horse trainer, he now poses as model
for artists working in the Academy of Arts.
Though he is now aged 125, this ex-
forester from a collective farm can usually
be found hard at work in his garden.
Nearing his 1 00th birthday, this former
shepherd has many stories to tell of fights
with wild beasts which menaced his flocks.
At 124 years of age he still has all his
teeth. Former shepherd and blacksmith,
he has now a new occupation : gardening.
Georgians are great horsemen and horse
trainers. This is the job to which this
92 year-old has devoted nearly all his life.
For ail his 93 years, this surgeon still
works in a hospital. He receives a govern¬
ment pension, but prefers to keep active.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A SMOOTHER WAY FOR BRITAIN'S
COLOURED IMMIGRANTS
by Hebe Spaull
Visitors paying their first visit to London
after an interval of several years are often
asked what differences they note. Almost
invariably they refer to the great numbers of
coloured workers to be seen in the streets. It is
possible that the porter who carries their luggage,
the 'bus conductor who collects the fares and the
station attendant who signals the departure of the
underground train are all coloured. This strik¬
ing development has taken place during the past
few years. The British Transport Commission
alone is now employing tens of thousands oi
coloured workers.
How have the new arrivals fitted into the
pattern of British life? In view of recent racial
conflicts the answer to' this question has more than
academic interest.
It would be idle to pretend that the mass
immigration of so many coloured workers, nearly
all from the West Indies, has not been accompanied
by serious problems and complexities. As their
arrival has coincided with a period of full em¬
ployment there has not been the resentment that
their presence might otherwise have encountered.
On the other hand, their arrival has also coincided
with an unprecedented shortage of housing
accommodation and this has undoubtedly been a
complicating feature in the process of integration.
The Trade Union most affected by the employ¬
ment of coloured workers in the United Kingdom is
the National Union of Railwaymen. The Union's
policy is, of course, opposed to discrimination in
any shape or form and their aim is to see these
workers fully integrated into the British Trade
Union movement. Aware that some prejudice
based on misunderstanding was bound to exist on
either side, the London District Council of the
N.U.R. recently held a "get-together" of members,
to which coloured railwaymen were especially invit¬
ed to thrash out some of the misunderstandings.
About two hundred railwaymen responded to the
invitation, of which number about fifty Were white.
Some illuminating facts were brought to light in¬
dicating as the coloured workers were the
first to emphasize that not all the causes of
misunderstanding were on one side.
One of the things complained of by the coloured
workers was the situation in regard to housing.
They claimed that as soon as it was known that
accommodation was required for coloured tenants
prices tended to rise fantastically. But and here
the coloured workers were very fair this exploita¬
tion was not only carried on by some white
landlords. Coloured owners of property were
often just as bad.
One complaint was that although Jamaica !
from which the majority come is a British
territory, very few of their fellow-workers in Britain
seemed to have any idea of the difficulties that had
forced them to leave their sunny land. Few
people, they claimed, knew of the conditions in
which they were now living. They were frequently
compelled to crowd into single rooms because of
the excessive rents, with the result that the beds
were seldom empty, those on night duty occupying
them during the day.
Having few social contacts, street corners and
the windows of gaily lit shops were often their main
attractions. This, they stated, sometimes led to
complaints from white people that coloured men
were loitering intent on mischief. Their sense oí
homelessness and herding together was something
they often felt deeply and they thought they were
entitled to a little patience while they got adjusted
to new circumstances.
One of the striking things that emerged from the
conference was the fact that some of the grievances
brought forward by the coloured workers as
examples of colour prejudice proved to be due to
other causes. Sometimes people showed stupid
prejudice against the newcomers, but the prejudice
turned out to be identical with a general suspicion
of all "foreigners," white and English-speaking ones
as well. In fact a lot of their problems were those
which confronted any newcomers and had nothing
to do with colour.
When one coloured worker gave as an example
of colour prejudice the fact that his foreman had
shouted at him: "Get on with it, you lazy bligh¬
ter!," he was immediately assured by white
workers present that they were frequently bawled
at in similar if not stronger terms. This was but
one of a number of -minor grievances which
proved to be much less serious than had been
supposed.
An N.U.R. official said it would be good for
coloured workers to stand for some of the jobs in
their Union branches, so emphasizing their solidar¬
ity of interests with the other members as well as
extending their "off duty" contacts.
The London rail-workers proved what sociologists
have long claimed namely, that prejudice in social
relationships is usually based on ignorance and that,
given the will on either side to consider each
others' problems, prejudice can give way to
understanding, and suspicion to sympathy.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
ROBERT OWEN: VISIONARY
OF A NEW SOCIETY
by Peter Michaels
ÇÇ~T do not think that Napoleon was more untiring in his
_£_ perseverance, or that Swedenborg had a more im¬
plicit confidence in himself; and to this was joined
a temperament so sanguine that he was unable no matter
what rebuffs he met with unable, even as an octo¬
genarian, to conceive the possibility of ultimate failure."
So runs a tribute by Robert Dale Owen, U.S. Congress¬
man and later American ambassador to Naples, to his
famous father, Robert Owen, Who died a century ago.
It is one of many pronounced by his contemporaries on
the character of a self-made Welsh boy Who rose to a
commanding position in industry before he Was 25, became
perhaps the most enlightened employer of his day, a
pioneer in education, the father of trade unionism and the
co-operative movement, who founded a Utopian socialist
community in Indiana and ended as a spiritualist preach¬
ing the moral re-generation of mankind.
As the son of a tradesman in the Welsh marketing
village of Newtown, Robert Owen (1771-1858), received
little formal education. He left school at the age of nine
and was apprenticed to drapers in London and Manches¬
ter Where, at 18 and on borrowed money, he associated
himself with a mechanic to produce textile machinery in
a small way. Soon he became the manager of a firm of
yarn-makers but, baulked of the eventual prospect of
partnership in the firm, left to establish a business of his
own, Which prospered and soon gained a wide reputation.
In 1799, Owen bought the New Lanark mills in Scotland
from David Dale, whose daughter he married, and laun¬
ched himself on a spectacular career which brought him
international fame as a humanitarian and a social re¬
former decades ahead of his time.
Children's 1 3-hour working day
New Lanark was a typical village of the early industrial
era, built around the factory upon which depended
the livelihood of all its 2,500 inhabitants, directly or
indirectly. Conditions were deplorable: the working
day, even for children, was 13 hours long or more, there
were few educational facilities, much drunkenness,
insanitary housing, and wages were practically at starva¬
tion level.
Against the vigorous opposition of some of his partners,
Whom he was forced to change frequently until he ended
up in 1813 in association (with William Allen, the Quaker
philanthropist, and Jeremy Bentham, the leader of the
Utilitarian school of philosophy, Owen set about to make
it into a model community. He encouraged order,
cleanliness and sobriety and cut down working hours,
but his most remarkable venture was the so-called
Institute for the Formation of Character, a centre
containing schools, communal halls and a "play-ground"
or kindergarten.
in 1816, the Institute was run according to
principles set out by Owen in his book New View of Society
or Essays on the Principle of Formation of Human
character (1813) where he argued that man's character
is an inevitable product of his environment. "Any general
character, from the best to the worse, from the most
ignorant to the most enlightened, may be given to any
community, even to the world at large, by the application
of the proper means; which means are to a great extent
at the command and under the control of those who have
influence on the affairs of men", Owen wrote, and
proceeded to put his ideas into practice.
The children of New Lanark were put to school between
the ages of one and ten or twelve. They were not set
to learning passages of books by heart, which was the
conventional method of instruction then, but were taught
by means of lectures and what today we call teaching
aids (maps, charts, pictures, field excursions and so on,)
on the principle that education should be both spont¬
aneous and enjoyable.
Dancing & drilling to pipe-bands
There were neither rewards nor punishments and if
the curriculum was a little deficient in such subjects
as literature and the arts, of which Owen himself
knew little, it included physical exercise for both boys and
girls who danced and were drilled military fashion, to
the accompaniment of pipe-bands. In the kindergarten,
which was especially admired, toddlers were given no
toys to play with but were expected to create their own
diversions. There was a rule that they must never be
chastised or treated unkindly in any way.
The New Lanark schools created a considerable stir and
became a tourist attraction for visitors to Great Britain.
Over 20,000 people called to see them in 10 years, including
the Grand Duke Nicholas, son of the czar of Russia, who
was so impressed that he offered to take Owen and up to
two million of Britain's surplus population and establish
them on sufficient land in Russia to continue experi¬
mentation on a larger scale. Others criticized the schools
for the lack of religious instruction and were scandalized
by the freedom the children enjoyed. But in the opinion
of a modern writer, "one of Owen's wisest insights into
the nature of education was his grasp of the truth that
education has to do with the whole of life and the whole
of a human being, and not only with intellectual
processes".
By 1815, Owen, turned his attention to national affairs.
"Every step of my experience forced me more and more
strongly to feel the necessity of preparing governments
and people through a persevering system of new instruc¬
tion, to fit both for the change which I had
in view." Britain was at that moment under¬
going a severe depression following the end
of the Napoleonic wars, and Owen was cal¬
led upon to suggest remedies for widespread
Cont'd
on
next page
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
ROBERT OWEN
(Continued)
Advocate of a Universal Education
distress and unemployment. He proposed the setting-up of
co-operative villages which would be largely self-support¬
ing and his 1817 report to the House of Commons on the
Poor Law is widely considered to contain his first embryo¬
nic socialist ideas, amplified in 1821 in his report to the
County of Lanark. At the same time, Owen proposed a
factory bill which was to regulate hours and conditions of
work. It was finally passed as Peel's Act in 1819, in a
much watered-down form disowned by its originator.
Disappointed by his lack of success in England,
Owen left for the United States in 1825 to found the
Utopian settlement of New Harmony in the wilds of
Indiana. The experiment collapsed due largely to a lack
of realistic foresight strange in a man of proven practical
capacity, and cost Owen some four-fifths of his consid¬
erable fortune. He then returned to England only to
discover that, during his absence, a number of trade
unions and co-operative societies had sprung up, more or
less directly inspired by the ideas he had publicized after
1817. Though he had had little hand in their actual
organization, these bodies looked to Owen as their natural
leader and he found himself at the head of a movement
which seemed to be gathering force. When the parlia¬
mentary reform bill of 1832 proved to bring little relief to
workers, Owen thought it opportune to found the Grand
National Consolidated Trade Union (1834), an ambitious
venture intended to serve as a rallying-point for a nation¬
wide labour movement but which turned out to be
premature and unwieldy and soon sank into oblivion.
From sordid present to radiant future
By 1836 and with the publication of the Book of the
New Moral World, Owen embarked upon his purely
cultural campaign for the reform of society which
was to be the last major phase of his career and also the
least effective. As an attempt to apply an essentially
home-spun philosophy to the complex business of
changing the human character by changing environment,
it was impeccably high-minded but hazy. For Owen
was neither an original nor a particularly profound
thinker. His writings are repetitive and, it must be
admitted, often tedious: they reveal a mind much
impressed by a few simple, basic ideas Which never really
blossomed into a coherent system, nor changed greatly
as Owen's experience widened.
Robert Dale Owen shrewdly put his finger on some of
his father's most serious intellectual shortcomings: "His
specific plans, as a Social Reformer, proved, on the whole
and for the time, a failure; and this, for lack of cultivated
judgment and critical research, and of accurate know¬
ledge touching what men had thought and done before
his time; also because he strangely overrated human
progress; but more especially, perhaps, because, until late
in life, he ignored the spiritual element in man as the
great lever of civilized advancement".
The early Utilitarian philosophers, Jeremy Bentham,
James Mill and Francis Place, were those Who most
directly influenced Owen. He rejected religion and
wished to replace it by What, in company with many other
18th and 19th century thinkers, he hoped would turn out
to be the universal appeal of reason. He had great faith
in the power of persuasion and believed that people
could be brought to see the error of their ways by
argument and by example. The more subtle laws of
32
economics or psychology escaped him and he saw little
difficulty in expanding a limited experiment, such as the
one at New Lanark, to a national or even a world-wide
scale.
At the same time, and no doubt under the spell of his
own successes -and the rapidly changing nature of the
evolving industrial age in which he lived, Owen expected
to make the most far-reaching innovations in hardly
more than a generation. To him, very little really stood
between a sordid present and a radiant future, and what
little there was he proposed to sweep away, if not single-
handed then with the help of an ever-swelling number
of devoted disciples.
Monument to inspired common-sense
Yet when all wise and critical hindsight is done, Owen's
pioneering in education remains a monument to
inspired common-sense mixed with a much less
common and humble love of his kind, not collectively and
in the abstract but individually and in day-to-day contact
'with those around him, especially With children. After
a short trial, he discarded for ever the "monitorial"
system, very popular in his time and evolved by Dr.
Andrew Bell and Joseph Lancaster, Which was a
solution to the problem of a single teacher having to
deal with a large class and consisted of selecting the
brighter pupils, giving them concentrated lessons to learn
by heart, and then setting them to repeat these lessons
to groups of other pupils.
Owen rightly recognized that this Was mere instruction,
and that education must properly be much broader in
its scope. The same objection also underlies his suspicion
of books Which he regarded as too dry and abstract for
use by young children, though in this respect he was
perhaps led to exaggeration by the poor quality of the
textbooks and school manuals with which he had become
acquainted. By a remarkable instinct, however, Owen
anticipated views now largely accepted as valid by
modern educators, psychologists and social scientists,
particularly in respect to the spontaneous element in
learning. His humanitarianism told him that children
ought to be happy; his rationalism convinced him that,
in order to make for happy adults later and 'or a good
society, education must; be universal and useful knowledge
must be acquired.
A revolutionary ideaenjoy school
Realizing that, in order to reconcile these general
imperatives children must enjoy school and acquire
a taste for the accumulation of knowledge in a form
palatable to them, he reacted sharply from strict discip¬
line and the kind of compulsion which, in his day and for
many decades even after his death, Was still widely judged
to be the only way of getting youngsters through thé
painful process of education. How difficult it was to
implement such ideas in 1816 is shown by the fact that
Owen could find no teachers prepared to instruct in his
schools and therefore himself trained the first two an
unemployed handloom weaver and a village girl. With
this pair, and others, who followed in their footsteps,
Owen achieved what '"might almost be regarded as an
epitome of the progress made in English education during
the following 100 years".
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1958
Letters to the Editor
A PLEA FOR THE RABBIT...
Sir,
I was particularly" interested by
the article "'Gentle Little Goat: Arch
Despoiler of the Earth" in your issue,
"Man Against Nature" (Jan. 1958).
While I do not feel competent to criti¬
cize the facts in this article, I do,
however, disagree with the references
you made in a reply to a reader in the
April, 1958 issue regarding the depred¬
ations of rabbits.
"The rabbit", you wrote, "is a
delightful animal.. .but it is also an ani¬
mal to be feared. ..it is a harmful animal,
and its relatively complete disappea¬
rance is simply a source of annoyance to
some hunters and cartridge manufactu¬
rers".
I consider that the rabbit is not, in
itself, a harmful animal, and it only
becomes one when nature's balance is
upset and rabbits are no longer kept in
check by the animals that normally prey
on them. Then, of course, they multi¬
ply and devour crops and young trees.
This was the situation in France at the
start of the myxomatosis epidemic which
was undeniably a welcome thing for
farmers and forest rangers.
Unfortunately the repercussions are
much wider. In France, for example,
one of the secondary effects of myxoma¬
tosis was the increased destruction by
man of all animals considered as
harmful. This in turn deprived others
of their normal food and thus added to
man's destructive work.
Some predatory animals such as foxes,
badgers, weasels and buzzards were able
to make up these food losses by
attacking the multitude of rodents
(whose increase was due to the
disappearence of these same predators).
But such was not the case for the great
birds of prey whose physical aptitudes
make it difficult for them to hunt field
mice and the like. I have personally
noted that in several French provinces,
where a few years ago several species of
the larger eagles were numerous, these
birds have now completely disappeared.
We are now on the eve of a new
operation of the "myxomatosis" type,
this time against the birds of the corvus
family which have multiplied because
hunters have practically exterminated the
peregrine falcons and goshawks. Crows,
rooks and others of the corvus genus
can be considered harmful only as a
group and not individually.
But the epidemic will be non-selective
and they will all perish. The few
remaining peregrine falcons will attack
other prey and this will be used as an
excuse to complete their extermination.
And then what? Each operation of this
kind has usually led to the more or less
total disappearance of several species.
What will be left in a hundred years'
time?
Instead of seeking a solution in an
epidemic capable of completely annihi¬
lating a species of animal, wrongly consi¬
dered as harmful when, in fact, it is so
only because of its numbers, would it
not be better to bring about a return to
the original biological equilibrium.
Ph. Pouplard
Sartrouville, France
...AND A DEFENCE OF THE GOAT
Sir,
Regarding the reply to a reader
concerning the devastation caused by
goats, and published in the April,
1958 issue may I ask why we
should wipe out this animal which for
thousands of years has given sterling
service, especially to the poorest sections
of the community, by providing milk
and meat? All we need to do is to pro¬
hibit the unrestricted grazing of these
animals which can very well subsist in
closed-off areas or attached to a stake.
I look after my garden as well as I
possibly can, but if I allowed my hens
to run wild on my vegetable beds it
would not be long before they destroyed
everything in them. The solution is not
for me to exterminate my poultry but to
make it impossible for them to cause any
depredations...
M. E. Olivie
Ris-Orangis, France
WINDOW ON TWO WORLDS
Sir,
Like all other readers I have certain
preferences for some of the subjects
which The Unesco Courier presents.
But I realize that it is not possible to
satisfy everyone and I consider that in
its present form your magazine is wel¬
comed by the majority of readers. I
think it worth adding, however, that
you should be two things: a "window on
the world" (looking out on what one
might call "'present day history") and a
magazine offering first-rate science popu¬
larization material. The whole should
have a scientific background, completely
objective and free from dogmatism.
M. J. Vincent
Lodelinsart, Belgium
LOOK AROUND YOU & AHEAD
Sir,
I find much to praise in the photo¬
graphs and most of the articles you
publish as well as in your choice of
subjects. Yet I cannot help feeling that
there is something "static" about the
material. It is too often a reflection of
things past and far more rarely of things
present or future.
We should, I know, study our rich
social and cultural heritage, but I feel
you ought to inquire into and explain
the efforts and experiments which are
going on almost everywhere to "hu¬
manize" living conditions in general.
Here are some of the things I have in
mind: new conceptions of housing and
furniture adapted to man's needs; the
more truly educational role of the
family; studies organized on a national
scale which really lead people to
worthwhile outlets. And why not deal
with clothes in their social context? I
am sure, there is an abundance of
worthwhile facts to publish on the uti¬
litarian aspects of dress and "modes".
There is also the question of leisure time
occupations. It is in these moments
that the individual feels least of all the
constraints of society, is at his most
receptive and, if given the means,
expresses himself most completely. Yet
so many people do not make proper
use of their spare time because they do
not know how, never having been pre¬
pared, either by their life in the home,
or in school or by the radio and press...
And what about the efforts being
made to transform travel from an affair
of "tourists" (equipment: camera and a
certain contempt for '"foreigners" and
"the natives") to that of understanding,
friendly and inquiring human beings who
become familiar with other men and
their ways of life. ..arriving as strangers,
but taking their leave as friends.
All this may seem somewhat idealistic
but it does link up with the role of
Unesco, and from personal experience
I know that these things, and many
others, can be done...
M. R. Comin
Maisons-AIfort, France
IS PERFECTION POSSIBLE?
Sir,
For some time I have been showing
The Unesco Courier to my acquain¬
tances. It interests all who are eager
for culture, who wish to become
acquainted with peoples and cultures,
without leaving their armchair. In
Algeria I am introducing this magazine
everywhere I go because I believe in
peace, a peace based on mutual
understanding between the different
peoples of the globe. Can this under¬
standing ever be achieved without an
organization working for the populari¬
zation and understanding of art, of
beliefs, and of social progress; in other
words of culture itself.
I have always been delighted by the
articles in your magazine. It is a pity
that certain readers systematically
complain about insignificant things
which displease them in certain articles.
Can one ever really achieve perfection?
Sergeant Doumbouya Ibrahima
Secteur Postal 78349, AFN
PRIMARY SCHOOL «COURIER*
Sir,
There is an urgent need for a
"Courier" prepared and published for
the use of our pupils in the primary
classes (9 to 14 years old). Help us to
develop among these young people the
principles of brotherhood for which you
stand. Help us to give them a true
picture of the world and subscriptions
will pour in.
Etienne Maksud
Alluyes, par Bonneval, France
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
SOCIAL AND MORAL ASPECTS
OF USING ATOMS FOR PEACE
Scientists, economists, sociologists and psychologists met on common ground
recently to discuss one of the most important scientific facts of our time
the use of atomic energy. A score of experts from ten countries and
representing seven or eight scientific disciplines met in Unesco House, Paris,
to discuss the social and moral implications of using atomic energy and to
contribute, through their opinions and advice, to Unesco's future planning in
this field.
In a discussion of present legislation on the use of atomic energy in different
countries, Professor Dahrendorf, a sociologist from Hamburg University, outlined
some of the liabilities placed on society and on freedom by the new activity. He
pointed out that the use of atomic energy does not really constitute an industrial
revolution, but is the continuation of a process which started before the splitting
of the atom, and is one to which the development of automation also belongs.
Dr. Hans Hoff, World Health Organization, said the mental and genetic effects
of nuclear power were still uncertain. Psychologists insisted, however, that though
certain phenomena such as radiography and isotopes have been accepted, one factor,
the primitive, fear of world destruction and the punishment of those who violate
divine secrets, still haunts humanity. To exorcise such ghosts, to repair the evil
caused by lies and by the abuse of secrecy, to help new generations to become
familiar with atoms for peace and to study and classify the conditions and attitudes
of men, were among the primary tasks to be undertaken.
The discussion on education raised a number of important question: How can
teachers be kept up to date on scientific progress? Science moves so fast that post-
school education, supplementary courses for teachers and the revision of textbooks
must be considered in an entirely new light. A complete reorientation of edu¬
cation is necessary for scientists, engineers and technicians in order to avoid exces¬
sive specialization in an age when no science can stand alone.
Press, T.V. and radio must also play their part in forming public opinion. Here
again knowledge and scientific facts must be made available to those whose job
it is to inform the public. Leaders, politicians, intellectuals and the public at
large must all become acquainted with the social, moral and cultural implications
of the peaceful uses of atomic energy.
DRAMA FROM 'A' TO B':
Productions ranging from Aristo¬
phanes to Berthold Brecht's "An¬
tigone 48" have been staged by
student groups from Europe and
America at the International Fes¬
tival of University Drama held in
Brussels one of the highlights of
the theatre season at the World
Fair. Works presented by the
drama groups included British
playwright Christopher Fry's "A
Sleep of Prisoners", Archibald Mac
Leish's "J. B." [acted by Yale stu¬
dents) and a work by Aeschylus
staged by Paris students.
Bi PRESS TRAINING:
Ways of improving facilities for
education in journalism in Latin
American countries were studied in
Quito, Ecuador, recently by a
TJNEsco-convened meeting of experts.
This was part of Unesco's programme
for encouraging better training in
journalism as a way to improving the
quality of information. Unesco
encourages the setting up of regional
centres to train teachers in jour¬
nalism, like the one opened in
Strasbourg, France, last year. In its
series of publications on Press, Film
and Radio in the World Today,
Unesco recently published a booklet
34
entitled '"The Training of Journalists"
(Price $2.00; 10/- (stg); 600 frs), a
world-wide survey on the training of
personnel for the mass media.
VERY SENIOR STUDENTS:
Seven leading citizens from places
in Europe, the Middle East, the
Far East and Latin America are
to spend a month at U.N. Head¬
quarters studying the work of the
organization. As community lead¬
ers in their countries they will
then be able to promote better
understanding of United Nations
aims and activities among their
countrymen. These seven "senior
students" include newspaper edi¬
tors, a doctor, officials of U.N.
Associations and a woman member
of Malaya's Federal Legislative
Council.
J.NDIA GOES METRIC: India is
now gradually changing over to the
metric system of weights and
measures. The first area to be
affected is the jute industry where
the metric weights system was
introduced in July. From October 1,
it is being introduced into other areas
of trade, although the use of existing
weights will be allowed for a further
two years. Second stage of the
change-over will be linear and
capacity measures. By 1960 it should
be possible to extend the system to
the whole country.
THAI PONY TRAP' LIBRARY:
A pony-cart travelling library
recently left the Fundamental
Education Centre at Ubol, Thai¬
land, on its first trip to carry
books to villagers in the surround¬
ing area. The library-cart will
help solve a problem that has been
worrying the librarian of the Cen¬
tre, run by the Thai Government
and Unesco. Until now, the Cen¬
tre has been sending books to the
villages in boxes holding about
59 books as they could only be
changed every three months. A
bookmobile was out of the ques¬
tion, since it was too expensive
and roads are impassable for
motor traffic at certain seasons,
The idea of using a specially-
designed pony-cart was suggested
by the centre's Unesco librarian.
MT OLAND'S EAST-WEST WEEK:
A special East-West week to promote
knowledge and understanding of the
Orient is being organized this month
by the Polish National Commission
for Unesco. Focal point of this
campaign is an exhibition on "The
Development of Oriental Writing and
the Oriental Book" being arranged
by the National Museum in Warsaw,
for which Unesco National Com¬
missions in 17 countries were asked to
contribute books, as well as films on
national life, history and culture.
SUBSCRIPTION
Send this blank with your cheque or
money order to your local agent listed
on page 35
Please enter my subscription for
THE UNESCO COURIER
One year S3. 00; IO/-stg.; 500
French francs Cheque/Money Order
enclosed
Two years $5.50; £1 stg.; 1,000
French francs
Name ,. 	
Address 	
City 	
Country. . .
Profession 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TENSIONS
AND TECHNOLOGY
SERIES
THE NATURE
OF CONFLICT
Studies on the
sociological aspects of
international tensions
: ! y
" War begins in the minds of men... It is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be constructed."
To implement this sentence of its Constitution, Unesco decided
to include in its programme a systematic, co-ordinated study of
social tensions and their repercussions in international life.
Unesco has long been aware of the contribution that the social
sciences can make to the development of better international
understanding and the removal of tensions arising from precon¬
ceived stereotyped ideas about foreign countries and their inha¬
bitants.
The latest book published in "Tensions and Technology" series:
"The Nature of Conflict", presents four studies by Professors
Jessie Bernard, T. H. Pear, Raymond Aron and Robert C. Angelí
on this important subject.
An introduction to the book reviews the progress made since
1948 in UNESCO's tensions project, the purpose of which has
been not only to discover scientific truths about social tensions
but also to put the results to practical use as a means of fostering
better international understanding.
Following the introduction are two chapters by Professor Jessie
Bernard and Professor T. H. Pear surveying research in the field
of conflict and dealing with several different types of conflict.
A third chapter, by Professor Raymond Aron, brings out the
relevance of historical inquiries to the problems of international
conflict; and the concluding chapter, by Professor Robert C.
Angelí, discusses the planning of future research. Prof. Angelí
focuses attention on the most promising areas of research,
especially in relation to the practical problems of the mediation
of conflict.
The book includes a classified and annotated bibliography
prepared by the Centre d'Etudes Sociologiques listing over one
thousand titles, mainly published since 1945.
Price : US $ 4.00 - 21/- (stg) - 1.000 Fr. fr.
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaî, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
CI, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C',, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 47, rue du Midi,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications. Office de Publicité,
16 rue Maxçg^Bruxelles, CCP 285-98;
N V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei'l 5 I ,
Antwerp.
BRAZIL. Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa-Postal 3291, Rio de
Janeiro. ,'
BURMA. S.P.CK. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons RoadColombo 2. (Rs. 9)
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. E|nar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Pans, 7\ C.C.P. 12598-48.
(500 fr)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb fur Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ah Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co.. Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22. Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Jranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press. I 6 South
Frederick St., Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (£.l./4.--.)
ITALY. Librería Commissionana San¬
son), Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Ton-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L Bahous & Co ,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Port Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library. 30 Bid. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo (500 fr.).
MOROCCO. Paul Fekete, 2, rue Cook,
Tangier. (500 fr )
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martmus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. 49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniama
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm
16. (Sw.kr. 7.50)
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva CCP.
1-236. (frs. S. 6 50)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 569. London, S.E. 1.(10/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($3.00 ) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska KniTga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
