<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078379eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
November 1970 (23rd year) - U.K.: 2 -stg - Canada: 40 cents - France: 1.20 F
''""'V.'1*^* I
I
1
Wf
mk
,
y*
\
»
1r/J^l'l iroj
H^
_
f T»*.'.V --r"rt
100 armed conflicts
since World War II
:
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^ Brazil
Matriarchal mask
This wooden mask with its distinctive qualities of mysticism and tenderness was carved by a Negro
artist in 17th century Brazil. A unique work no other like it exists, even in Africa it symbolizes
the survival on the continent of America of a Yoruba (West African) religion transplanted centuries
ago. The mask is still worn during ceremonies in which members of an Afro- Brazilian cult honour
female ancestors. As in West Africa, religion impregnated and marked every activity of the
Brazilian Negro, creating a unique culture which continues to find expression in religious ceremonies,
art and folklore. This matriarchal mask, which comes from the temple of an Afro-Brazilian cult, figured
in a recent exhibition of Afcp-BrazjJia'r^aijt-and ci|lt*jre, at Unesco's headquarters in Paris.
-pmvwî$
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
NOVEMBER 1970
23RD YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 13 EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational. Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7»
Annual subscription rates: 20/-stg.; $4.00
(Canada);.12 French francs or 'equivalent;
2 years : 36/-stg. ; 22 F. Single copies : 2/-stg. ;
40 cents ; 1 .20 F.
The UNESCO COURIER Is published monthly, except
in August and September when it is bi-monthly (1 1 issues a
year) In English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese, Italian, Hindi, Tamil, Hebrew and Persian. In the
United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is Indexed monthly In The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Con¬
tents - Education. Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Page
4 THE ARMS RACE, ESCALATION
OF TOTAL MADNESS
by Philip Noel-Baker
6 POISONOUS MUSHROOMS
46 nuclear tests each year
9 FINAL SEQUEL TO THE LUCKY DRAGON'
12 SUPER-ARMS FOR THE
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES
14 THE INDEPENDENCE OF COLONIAL PEOPLES
10th anniversary of a historic U. N. declaration
15 THE HORROR OF BACTERIOLOGICAL
AND CHEMICAL WEAPONS
21 PEACE RESEARCH. THE SCIENCE OF SURVIVAL
by Bert V. A. Röling
23 100 ARMED CONFLICTS SINCE WORLD WAR II
25 THE EDUCATION REVOLUTION
IN LATIN AMERICA
by Miguel Soler Roca
33 UNICEF GREETING CARDS
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Matriarchal mask (Brazil)
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy Paris-7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition: Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernández-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition : Georgi Stetsenko (Paris)
German Edition: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneirn El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Takao Uchida (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Kartar Singh Duggal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: T.P. Meenakshi Sundaran (Madras)
Hebrew Edition : Alexander Peli (Jerusalem)
Persian Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Howard Brabyn
French Edition : Nino Frank
Photo Editor: Olga Rodel
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief
5
Cover
It may seem hard to believe but
the world has witnessed 100 wars
and other conflicts since 1945,
as the table published on page 23
of this issue shows. The dove
of peace would seem to be a rare
bird indeed on our planet
And yet the overkill arms race
keeps escalating with bigger and
bigger nuclear weapons, bigger
and "better" bacteriological and
chemical weapons. When will
this madness stop?
Photo © Luc Joubert
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
On September 21, 1970, five of the six living, Nobel Peace Prize winnersLord
Boyd Orr, Lester Pearson, Philip Noel-Baker, Linus Pauling and René Cassinpre¬
sented a declaration on peace and disarmament at United Nations headquarters
in New York calling for a moratorium on the development and deployment of new
offensive and defensive strategic nuclear weapons systems as a first step towards
full disarmament. The sixth Nobel Peace Prize winner, Ralph Bunche, endorsed
the declaration though he did not sign it because of his position in the U.N. Secre¬
tariat as Under Secretary-General. The United Nations hopes to make the Seven¬
ties a "Disarmament Decade" in a renewed effort to halt and reverse the insensate
arms race in which the real cost of world military expenditure, trebled between
1949 and 1968.
In this issue, which is largely devoted to the question of armaments and peace
research, Nobel Peace Prize winner Philip Noel-Baker presents a picture of the
current arms build-up on the basis of the findings of the Stockholm International
Peace |Research Institute (SIPRI) published in its Yearbook of World Armaments
and Disarmament.
^.i.s2S#l
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Arms Race
escalation of
total madness
by Philip Noel-Baker
Nobel Peace Prize, 1959
SUS *^
LLV-5I
* <
-r" l°-
|^F WIGHT D. Eisenhower was
not only President of the United Sta¬
tes; he was also Commander-in-Chief
of the greatest army, and victor of the
greatest battle, in human history. After
four years in the White House, he
said in a press conference in 1957:
"I know of nothing that has occurred
in our time where greater optimism
must be maintained... than in this whole
business of beginning disarmament...
The alternative is so terrible that you
can merely say this: All the risks you
take in trying to advance are as noth¬
ing compared to doing nothing, to
sitting on your hands."
On an earlier occasion, Eisenhower
said:
"War in our time has become an
anachronism. Whatever the case in
the past, war in the future can serve
no useful purpose."
Since he spoke these words, almost
every president and prime minister
in the world has re-echoed them, and
has declared that a nuclear war might
exterminate mankind. Scientists, be¬
ginning with Einstein and Cockcroft,
and weapons-experts, from Oppen-
heimer and Isidor Rabi to Sir Solly
Zuckerman and Herbert York, have
ardently, even passionately endorsed
this view.
But, nevertheless, the governments
have gone on sitting on their hands.
Khruschev's and Kennedy's great
disarmament plans were destroyed by
militarist opposition. The arms race
has continued with unparalleled fury;
world military expenditure, in real
terms, has increased by more than
60 per cent since 1957; the numbers
of nuclear warheads have increased
much more perhaps they have been
multiplied by 10.
Much worse, wars have raged in
various quarters of the world, wars in
which the dead and mutilated must
be reckoned in millions and often
mutilation is more terrible than death.
No-one outside the Institutes of self-
styled "strategic analysts" really
doubts that there is a causal connexion
between the arms race and the wars;
that if a Treaty of General Disarma¬
ment had been made by a compromise
between Kennedy's and Khruschev's
Draft Treaties of 1962, the world
would now enjoy unbroken peace.
The U.N. General Assembly in
1969 declared that the 1970s must
be the Disarmament and Development
Decade. Since then the Secretary-
General has been engaged in a vigo¬
rous disarmament campaign.
' In his report to the General Assem¬
bly in 1969, U Thant said: "The world
now stands at a most critical cross¬
roads. It can pursue the arms race at
a terrible price to the security and
progress of the peoples of the world,
or it can move ahead towards the goal
of general and complete disarmament,
a goal that was set in 1959 by a
unanimous decision of the General
Assembly... If it should choose the
latter road" (i.e. general disarmament),
"the security, the economic well-being
and the progress, not only of the
developing countries, but also of the
developed countries, and of the entire
world, would be tremendously en¬
hanced."
On May 22, 1970, U Thant said to
a conference in New York: "Progress...
in the field of disarmament can be
achieved only if there is a strong
political will on all sides to undertake
the policies and measures that could
CONTINUED PAGE 8
PHILIP NOEL-BAKER, Nobel Peace Prize,
1959, has devoted many years to research
on problems of peace and disarmament and
has written widely on the subject. Readers
will recall his special study on Science and
Disarmament published in our August-Sep-
tember 1967 Issue, "War or Peace?".
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Photo © UK Atomic Energy Authority
Photo USIS
Photo USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Poisonous
mushrooms
Photo © Panmage, Paris
The malignant crop of atomic mushrooms shown here is a tiny sampling of the
hundreds of nuclear test explosions that have blasted harmful radioactive
substances into the atmosphere during the past 25 years. Countries which signed
the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty in Moscow, in 1963, agreed to discontinue all
nuclear tests in the atmosphere, under water and in outer space. Yet the Moscow
Treaty, " does not appear to have had much success in reducing the amount of
nuclear weapon testing," reports the SIPRI Yearbook of World Armaments
and Disarmament. "From available data," it says, "it appears that the average
annual number of tests by all nations before the treaty was 40. The annual
average since the treaty has been 46." Since they concluded the treaty, the
USA, USSR and UK have exploded no nuclear devices in the atmosphere,
although underground nuclear tests have increased in number. But certain
countries that did not sign the Moscow Agreement have carried out atmo¬
spheric tests since 1963 (top right, nuclear explosion in Mainland China;
bottom right, French nuclear explosion).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ARMS RACE ESCALATION (Continued)
For every dollar spent on arms
only 30 cents for public health
lead to agreements. If we are to
make real progress toward disarma¬
ment, governments must approach
this subject in a new spirit. They
must stop questioning the seriousness
of purpose of others and think how
they can demonstrate their own."
In the same speech, U Thant said:
"There is another aspect of the Disar¬
mament Decade which... has been
largely overlooked... I refer to the
need for greater publicity concerning
both armaments and disarmament, so
that knowledge concerning these
matters can penetrate the conscience
of the people."
"Penetrate the conscience of the
people."
Yes, foreign policy, armament policy,
has been controlled for the last tragic
decade by those in the Establish¬
ments of almost every nation who be¬
lieve that armaments can promote
national security and national great¬
ness, and who believe that disarma¬
ment and the abolition of war are not
only Utopian, but even ignoble. Only
a great tide of world opinion can des¬
troy their power.
T
| HIS is the significance of
SIPRI's (*) great "Yearbook of World
Armaments and Disarmament." SIPRI's
authority has been firmly established
by its other works; but the Yearbook
is, and will remain, its chef-d'oeuvre.
The product of a dozen first-class
brains, from a dozen countries, work¬
ing within the Institute itself, who are
re-inforced, when needed, by experts
from outside.
The sections on military expenditure,
which open the Yearbook, more than
justify this claim. Chapter 1, which
sets out the trends of military expendi¬
ture in the world at large," in ^certain
regions and among certain groups of
countries, and even of some individual
"Great" Powers, is a masterly piece
of statistical analysis. The clarity of
its exposition, re-inforced by the
charts attached to this chapter, and
by the detailed tables of expenditure
in Part II, give a wholly new picture
of the long-term history of the arms
8
* SIPRI = Stockholm International Peace
Research Institute. The Institute was found¬
ed and Is financed by the Swedish Parlia¬
ment, which set It up to celebrate the end of
a century and a half during which Sweden
had had no war. It has an International Board
of Governors, of which Mr. Gunnar Myrdal
Is the chairman.
race, and of its immediate and terrify¬
ing significance today.
The constant increase of the burden
of military budgets has been a main
plank in the argument of those who
urge disarmament. But the tables
published hitherto have mostly been
at current prices and current exchange
rates; those who opposed disarma¬
ment often claimed, without proving
what they said by doing the sums,
that increases of expenditure were due
to a rise of prices, and that, in real
resources, the burden of expenditure
remained the same.
The opponents of disarmament also
found another way of distorting the
facts. They drew up tables showing
a nation's armament expenditure as a
percentage of its gross national
product, without explaining that the
G.N.P. had much increased; thus they
showed Britain's expenditure as over
10 per cent of G.N.P. in the early
1950s, and as 6.7 per cent in 1968;
this left the casual reader with the
impression that large reductions had
been made, when in fact the burden
in real resources had increased.
SIPRI puts all these muddles right.
There are tables at current prices and
exchange rates. There are tables at
constant prices, showing the trends
in real resources over many years.
There are evaluations of the percent¬
ages of G.N.P. spent on armaments
in different years by different powers.
These tables give a true picture of
the arms race since the present
century began. It is a picture that
will surprise, and shock, most people.
For 70 years, since 1900, the average
increase in the real burden of world
armaments has been 5 per cent per
year. Since 1948, the increase has
been greater: 6 per cent per year.
This meant that, from 1949 to 1968,
the real cost was trebled.
If the increase continues at the
present rate, the cost will double
again by 1980. The world total in
1968, at 1960 prices, was: $153,498
million.
In 1980, it would be: $306,996 mil¬
lion.
If the increase continues, at 5 per
cent per annum, then, says the Year¬
book: "By the early years of the next
century the world will be devoting to
military uses a quantum of resources
which is equal to the whole world's
present (1968) output."
"This is not so preposterous as it
sounds", says the Yearbook. "The
world is now devoting to military
purposes an amount of resources
which exceeds the world's total out¬
put in the year 1900."
There are also valuable comments
on percentages of G.N.P.
In 1913, just before the First World
War, "probably no more than 3-3i per
cent of world output was going to
the military. In the early 1930s, the
percentage seems to have been about
the same. The average over the last
18 years... has been around 7-8 per
cent more than double the 1913
figure".
Moreover, the world's output of
wealth has been increased at least
fivefold since 1913, so that in real
terms the resources "going to the
military" have been multiplied by 10.
There are other dismal facts given
in the Yearbook about this world
expenditure on defence.
It is greater in amount by 40 per
cent than the total sums spent by all
nations together on Education.
It is more than three times the
expenditure of all nations together on
Public Health.
These are depressing facts, particu¬
larly to those who care about Unesco
and its mission toward mankind.
But there are worse facts still to
come.
The arms race is spreading to
continents where it was not known
before.
The figures for Africa, over the last
few years, show that military expendi¬
ture there is rising by 7-8 per cent per
year more than the average for the
world.
I| N the developing countries
of all continents, military expenditure
has risen since 1960 by an average of
7è per cent per year. The developing
countries those which are receiving
economic aid from the International
Bank, the International Development
Agency, the U.N. Development Pro¬
gramme, and other sources have
spent many billions of dollars on
importing "sophisticated" weapons
warships, aircraft, missiles, tanks,
from the arms-producing nations.
This is a new and an alarming fact.
In 1955, no developing country had
supersonic military aircraft; today no
less than 32 such nations have them.
CONTINUED PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Final sequel
to the
'Lucky Dragon'
HIS fishing boat is a hulk lying on the mud-flats of a
garbage dump infTokyo Bay, inappropriately named "Island of Dreams" (Yumenoshima).
Still legible oni-4*~bj>w are the Japanese characters for Fukuryu Méru Lucky Dragon.
But like its re/ting place, the Lucky Dragon is ill-named. Sixteen years ago, on
March 1, 1954, the boat and its crew were hit by the fallout of a hydrogen bomb
explosion during a nuclear test in the Pacific.
At five o'clock on that March morning, the Lucky Dragon was near the Marshall
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
'LUCKY DRAGON' (Continued)
Islands fishing for tuna, when a huge incandescence rose above the western horizon.
The fishermen watched with awe. "The sun rises in the west," one exclaimed.
Before long, the boat was showered with a drizzle of small, white flakes which
clung to the crew's hair, eyes and nostrils. The vessel was 87 miles from an obscure
atoll named Bikini. During their two-week journey back to Japan, the crew members
were stricken with a variety of ailments.
It was not until some days after their return to port that the fishermen learned what
the flash was. They were taken to hospital in Tokyo for treatment In September 1954,
Aikichi Kuboyama, the ship's radio operator died the world's first victim of the
H-bomb. (For full story see "Unesco Courier", August-September 1967.)
In the years that followed, the Lucky Dragon was all but forgotten. After being
decontaminated several times, it was abandoned on the "Island of Dreams" garbage
dump, until someone decided it should be sold for scrap.
When this became known, committees were at once formed to save the boat, and
fund-raising campaigns were launched. Tokyo's Governor, Ryokichi Minobe, forbade
the scrapping of the Lucky Dragon, and two organizations, The Japan Congress
Against Atomic and Hydrogen Bombs and the General Council of Trade Unions of
Japan, made plans to preserve the boat.
Painted and restored, the Lucky Dragon will now have Its place alongside the
atomic museums of Hiroshima and Nagasaki, as another reminder of the horror of
nuclear weapons and their destructive effects.
11.02 AM
The hands of this clock in
Nagasaki, Japan, mark the
exact instant when an atomic
bomb was dropped on the
city on the morning of August 9
1945. Three days earlier, an
atomic bomb had levelled 4i
square miles of Hiroshima.
ARMS RACE ESCALATION
(Continued from page 8)
In 1957, no developing country had
long-range surface-to-air missiles; now
19 have them.
It is this military expansion which
has swallowed up the scarce foreign
currency resources which these deve¬
loping nations should have invested as
productive capital in projects for eco¬
nomic expansion and social progress.
In my opinion it is the real reason why
the U.N. Development Decade so
largely failed.
There are interesting facts in the
Yearbook about the percentages of
G.N.P. given to the military by two
leading nations, Britain and the United
States.
The U.S. figures are these:
Percentage of G.N.P.
Year spent on Armaments
1913 	 1.4
1928 1.1
1969 	 9.0
The U.S. is fighting the Vietnam
war; nevertheless, that nearly one-
tenth of its enormously increased out¬
put of wealth should "go to the mili¬
tary" is a fantastic thought.
Britain is fighting no war. Her fig¬
ures are these:
Percentage of G.N.P.
Year spent on Armaments
1913 	 3.4
1928 3.0
1968 	 6.7
Double the percentage of a national
output which has increased only less
than that of the United States.
Nothing so demonstrates the almost
incredible momentum of the arms race,
and the profound and all-embracing
militarization of world politics, as these
last figures.
The SIPRI Yearbook expands its
picture of the arms race by a new
and fascinating account of the tech¬
nological trends and advances in the
mass-destruction "weapons-systems"
of the major powers, and of conven¬
tional armaments as well.
"New" ? Much of the material is
from already published government
sources, some from unofficial sources,
some from SIPRI's own researches.
But "new", because no-one has yet
constructed so comprehensive and so
illuminating a synthesis of what is
familiar, what ought to be familiar, and
what so far has been virtually
unknown.
The story of the nuclear competition
between the Soviet Union and the
United States is terrifying.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Humpty Dumpty sat on a first strike capability
Some authorities in the United
States have added a new dimension to
its menace. They interpret the Soviet
missile SS9, with its multiple war¬
heads, and the great increase in the
number of Soviet I.C.B.M.s, not as a
belated and desperate attempt to
catch up with the vastly superior nu¬
clear strength of the United States, but
as an attempt to take a very dange¬
rous lead.
SIPRI quotes a U.S. spokesman:
"They (the Russians) are going for a
first strike capability. There is no
question about that."
This cuts at the root of the comfor¬
table, wishful-thinking theory that the
mutual deterrence of the nuclear
bombs gives us security from war.
SIPRI gives cogent reasons why this
view of Soviet policy is not at present
credible; they say that the large U.S.
superiority in I.C.B.M.s throughout
the period since the missiles first be¬
gan to* fly must have made it appear
"from the Soviet point of view ... that
it was the United States which was
attempting to preserve a first-strike
capability." And they quote authori¬
tative sources for the fact that for ten
years the U.S. have had the means to
render a million square miles of urban
areas in the Soviet Union uninhabitable
by human beings.
B' UT what General Staffs be¬
lieve may be more important than the
facts; their beliefs decide the policy
which their governments pursue. And
no doubt it is because the U.S. Depart¬
ment of Defense believe that the Rus¬
sians "are going for a first strike capa¬
bility" (i.e. for the power to destroy all
the U.S. nuclear weapons before the
U.S. can reply), that they are em¬
barking on a new programme of
missiles with longer ranges and with
multiple warheads (MIRV). Many of
the Polaris submarines will be con¬
verted to Poseidons; instead of one
Polaris warhead of 600 kilotons yield,
the Poseidon will have ten warheads
of 50 kilotons yield (50 kilotons is
3l times as powerful as the Hiroshima
bomb). Similar "improvements" will
be made in the land-launched missiles,
the Minutemen.
Departments of defence prefer to
take no chances.
The U.S. Department of Defense
appropriated $25 million for the de¬
velopment of a new manned bombing
aircraft in 1969, and $100 million in
1970.
They are doing vigorous research to
improve the accuracy of their missiles
if the average distance from the
target is halved, "the weapon yield
needed to eliminate a specific target is
reduced by a factor not of 2, but of
10."
They are spending large sums on
research in oceanography; on so im¬
proving submarines that they can re¬
main submerged for two months or
more (what kind of human beings will
the crew be when they come up?); on
giving submarines the capacity to dive
and cruise at greater depths "the
addition of 100 feet to the maximum
operating depth of a submarine adds
millions of cubic miles to the volume
of space in which the submarine can
navigate."
All these developments can be jus¬
tified as "defensive", if you apply the
method of "worst case analysis" to
your weapon systems, i.e. if you
accept the worst possible assumptions
about the reliability of your own wea¬
pons, about the effectiveness of your
enemy's defence etc. This is a me¬
thod that would be tolerated in no
other sphere of government; but in
respect of armaments, "you must
always err on the side of safety."
But, however these U.S. program¬
mes may appear in Washington (and
the ABM was only carried by the
Chairman's vote in a Senate divided
50-50), SIPRI is surely right in think¬
ing that in Moscow they will seem
to justify the view' that it is the U.S.
which is seeking in the 1970s, as, in
Soviet eyes, they did in the 1960s, to
preserve a first strike capability.
If both sides believe that first-strike
capability is the fixed purpose of the
other, and if their military research
and weapon programmes appear to
the other to be devoted to this aim, the
"stability" alleged to result from mutual
nuclear deterrence will not be of much
practical value for the peaceful con¬
duct of world affairs. And the SALT
talks in Vienna the secret U.S.-Soviet
negotiations about the possible limi¬
tation of "strategic" arms do not
seem to give much hope that the race
in these long-range nuclear weapons
will be ended in the early future.
MIRV poses the most difficult of ins¬
pection problems; and if SIPRI is right,
the point of no return may already
have been passed.
MIRV and ABM are only the most
dangerous of the weapon develop¬
ments now under way; there are innu
merable others which are dealt with
in the Yearbook.
On chemical and biological warfare,
SIPRI's authority is already estab¬
lished in the world. The Yearbook
chapter on the subject will enhance it.
So will:
The section on the role of helicop¬
ters in "conventional" war;
The section on submarine warfare;
The extremely valuable section on
the arms trade, and the remarkable
Arms Trade Register;
The outline of the disarmament ne¬
gotiations and proposals since 1945;
The compendious information given
on the Moscow Partial Test Ban, The
Antarctic Treaty, the Outer Space
Agreement, and the Non-Proliferation
Treaty;
The revealing diaries of events in the
Nigerian civil war and the Israeli-Arab
wars; and much more besides, with
which there is no space to deal.
c
^^OMETHING must be said,
however, about the Yearbook's analy¬
sis of the post-1945 phenomenon of
Government Military Research and De¬
velopment. It has long been plain that
Military Research and Development
(R & D) is the real dynamo which dri¬
ves the arms race. It is R and D which
makes the arms race a remorselessly
self-escalating burden on the nations'
wealth. It is R and D which drives
up the cost and scale of armaments
from year to year.
It has long been known that vast
sums were being spent on R and D.
But SIPRI has brought out something
profoundly significant and new.
"Behind this extremely rapid rate
of technological improvement in
weaponry," says the Yearbook, "so
much faster than that of civil goods,
there is an enormous disparity between
the two fields in research and devel¬
opment. . . For every $100 of military
procurement (i.e. actual purchase of
arms by the Government) in the Uni¬
ted States, Britain and France, there
is over $50 of research expenditure (*).
For the general run of manufacturing,
the research input for every $100 of
output ranges from $1.9 (France) to
$7.5 (U.S.). The disparity is not so
great in other countries, but it exists
everywhere.' 11
* The actual figures are: U.K. $62.2; U.S.
$54; France $57.
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ARMS RACE ESCALATION (Continued)
Moreover, the military research figu¬
res are understated they exclude
expenditure on space research and on
atomic energy research. All in all, the
research input for weapons is at least
ten times that for civil goods and ser-
vioes. This conjures up visions of
rotting urban ghettoes which modern
engineering ought to cleanse; of starv¬
ing children who ought not to starve;
of rampant diseases which science
could wipe out.
But worse than that:
"This tremendous research and de¬
velopment drive behind the advance in
weaponry has an impetus of its own.
Once massive funds are voted for
weapons research ... it is inevitable
that further improvements will be
made, and inevitable that new fields of
warfare will be explored. . .
"Weapons research proliferates in
another way. . .: each new weapon
spurs the development of counter-
weapons."
Alas, what might science do for the
betterment of human life and hap¬
piness if the balance of R and D were
ten to one the other wayl
This Yearbook is a sine qua non for
the proper understanding of world
affairs.
Lest I have given it a colour which
others might contest, let me end by
quoting the words of SIPRI's Director,
Mr. Robert Neild:
"The Yearbook is factual: but of
course the selection of the material
and the way in which it is presented
implies a set of valuations, and we
should make them explicit. Obviously
the staff drawn as they are from
many different countries have differ¬
ing views on a wide number of ques¬
tions of world armaments and disar¬
mament. The common elements in
their approach may be summarized
thus:, that the rise in world military
spending, and more particularly the
constant technological acceleration in
weaponry, is highly dangerous, and
that the attempts so far made to slow
down, halt or reverse the process
have been incommensurate with the
danger; that arms competition, though
it is not the sole or main cause of
world tensions and conflicts, is an
important independent factor which
increases and exacerbates tensions:
and that arms limitation or disarma¬
ment could help considerably to re¬
duce these tensions."
Amen.
12
The SIPRI Yearbook of World Armaments
and Disarmament 1968-1969, prepared by the
Stockholm International Peace Research
Institute, Is published by Almqvist i Wiksell,
Stockholm, Humanities Press, New York and
Gerald Duckworth & Co., Ltd., London.
(Prices, hardback and soft cover respectively:
60 and 32 Kr. ; $12.00 and $6.50; £5 and
£2.10.)
IMPORTS OF MAJOR WEAPONS
BY DEVELOPING COUNTRIES
(millions of U. S. dollars)
Importers
Greece and Turkey
Middle East
(including the UAR)
North Africa
(Algeria, Libya, Morocco, Tunisia)
Sub-Saharan Africa
(the rest of Africa excluding South Africa)
South Africa
Indian Sub-continent
(Afganistan, Ceylon, India Pakistan)
Far East
(excluding Mainland China, Japan, North Viet-
Nam and the Republic of Viet-Nam)
Central America
(All countries from Panama north to the USA)
South America
TOTAL excluding North Viet-Nam and the Republic
of Viet-Nam
North Viet-Nam and the Republic of Viet-Nam
TOTAL
240 640
1.470 1,200
1,500 | 1,670
Tables taken from the SIPRI Yearbook of World Armaments and Disarmament Figures
rounded to nearest 10. or to nearest 5 when under 10. Values calculated at constant
1968 prices.
EXPORTS OF MAJOR WEAPONS
to areas in table above (North Viet-Nam and the Republic
of Viet-Nam excluded)
(millions of U.S. dollars)
Exporters 1950 1958 1968
France
Canada
Mainland China
Federal Republic of Germany
Czechoslovakia
Sweden
All other
TOTAL
30
1,470 | 1,200
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Super-arms for developing countries
ILITARY expenditure in
the developing countries is only a
small fraction of the world total; but it
seems to have risen rather faster than
world military expenditure as a whole
and to have been accelerating
recently.
The spread of existing sophisticated
weapons through the Third World is a
very significant aspect of the arms
competition there. This "horizontal"
proliferation is the complement to the
technological arms race which is per¬
haps the most important feature of the
arms competition in the developed
countries. More and more developing
countries are acquiring fighters,
ground-to-air missiles, and so on. The
Third World countries do not, for the
most part, produce these sophisticated
weapons themselves; the weapons are
supplied by the industrial nations.
Some Third World countries, such as
Israel and India, are beginning to pro¬
duce more sophisticated weapons; but
these weapons are usually produced
under licence with a substantial pro¬
portion of imported components.
- The arms competition in the Third
World would be very different if it
were not for the fact that the great
powers are seeking influence there.
They may be looking for strategically
placed allies, they may be anxious to
support regimes friendly to them
against internal armed opposition, or
they may wish to protect their eco¬
nomic interests or to gain general sup¬
port for foreign policy (in the form
of votes in the United Nations, for
example). One of the main methods
of exerting influence is by supplying
arms.
There are some important qualifica¬
tions about the figures and information
discussed here and shown in the tables
opposite. The figures are, as far
as is known, the first comprehensive
quantitative estimates which show how
the trends have changed in the past
two decades. They are based on
incomplete unofficial information offi¬
cial figures are virtually non-existent.
The tables are limited to the
supply of major weapons: ships, air¬
craft, armoured fighting vehicles and
missiles. Because no support equip¬
ment and no other weapons are in¬
cluded, they represent only a part
but an important part of the arms
trade.
The figures are constructed to
represent the "real" transfer of resour¬
ces. They are based on comparable
values for comparable items, using
such criteria as speed, weight, type of
engine, date of production. They do
not take into account differing prices
or differing terms for individual trans¬
actions, such as aid, credit, loans or
subsidies. That is, they attempt to
measure the quantum of resources
represented by the weapons, not the
cost in foreign currency paid by the
recipient country.
"In drawing conclusions from these
figures," says the SIPRI report,
"we have allowed for their wide
margin of error. In dealing with the
arms trade with these countries, it
seemed right to construct the best pic¬
ture we could, using our own judge¬
ment on information from all kinds
of sources. The alternative using
official information only would have
meant that little or nothing could be
said on a matter of great international
importance.
"There is also a caution on the use
the military expenditure figures. They
cover the military expenditure of the
countries out of their own domestic
resources: military aid is included in
the budget of the donor countries."
Major weapon supplies to Third
World countries have been rising even
faster than their military expenditures.
The long-term trend from 1950 to 1968,
has been for the supply of weapons
to increase, in volume terms, by some
9 per cent a year, against 7 per cent
a year for military spending. It has
not been a smooth rise over the eigh¬
teen years: there was a high point
around 1958, when United States mili¬
tary aid was at its height, and there
has been a rapid increase since 1962.
In 1968 deliveries of major weapons
to the Third World countries, at
$1,700 million, were higher than ever
before: they were around $300 mil¬
lion, or 15 per cent, above the 1967
figure.
growing number of Third
World countries have acquired super¬
sonic fighters, anti-aircraft missiles
and helicopters for military use. The
helicopter is becoming more and more
important in the weapons inventory of
the great powers and this is also true
for Third World countries.
The two main areas responsible for
the increase in major weapon sup¬
plies since 1962 have been the Middle
East and North Viet-Nam and the
Republic of Viet-Nam. In 1968, these
two areas accounted for 70 per cent
of total major arms deliveries. In the
Middle East, it was not only the
re-equipment which followed the Six-
Day War which made up the massive
influx of weapons: there were exten¬
sive arms purchases by Saudi Arabia,
Iran and Kuwait. In addition, there
were in this period significant increa¬
ses in major arms supplies to South
Africa and the four North African
countries.
The pattern of the short-term in¬
crease from 1967 to 1968 was a little
different. Again, it was dominated by
the Middle East, but in addition there
were notable increases in arms sup¬
plies to the Indian sub-continent and
to South America: in both these areas
the trend had previously been falling.
The United States, the Soviet Union,
Britain and France dominate the mar¬
ket for major arms exports. During the
1950s these four countries accounted
for 80 per cent of major arms supplies
to the Third World. During the 1960s,
this proportion had increased to 90 per
cent, and it is still rising.
The United States share of major
arms supplies to the Third World has
fallen both absolutely and relatively
since the end of the 1950s. Since
1960, the emphasis of US military
assistance policy has shifted from the
defence of states from possible exter¬
nal attack to the defence of govern¬
ments from possible internal insurrec¬
tion: developing countries have been
encouraged to acquire counter-insur¬
gency equipment rather than sophisti¬
cated conventional equipment.
Such items include helicopters,
trainers, patrol boats, refurbished
World War II combat aircraft, which
are relatively inexpensive. The Arms
Trade Register for 1968 shows that a
large part of the equipment supplied by
the United States in 1968, particularly
in Latin America consisted of these
items.
Major arms supplies from the Soviet
Union have risen throughout the
period. In the last few years, the
Soviet Union has exported roughly the
same quantity of major weapons as
the United States. The most rapid
increase in Soviet major arms supplies
occurred in the second half of the
1950s. Between 1954-58 and 1959-
63, major arms supplies from the
Soviet Union doubled. Between
1960-64 and 1964-68, they rose by
only about 10 per cent.
The first arms agreement with Egypt
was made in 1955; it was followed
soon after by a similar agreement with
Syria. In 1958 the Soviet Union began
supplying arms to Iraq and Indonesia,
and a little later to Africa. Arms sup¬
plies to India and Cuba began in 1960.
Although major arms supplies to India
and the Middle East have increased
substantially in recent years, the total
Soviet rise has been relatively small
because of a considerable reduction in
supplies to Indonesia and Cuba, which
reached their height in 1962.
In the short term, major arms sup- .j n
plies from both the United States and I A
the Soviet Union have risen, particu¬
larly in the Middle East. The Soviet .
Union has been meeting the replace-
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES (Continued)
ment requirements of the U.A.R. and
Syria, while the United States has
been supplying sophisticated equip¬
ment to Israel, Jordan and Iran.
Britain and France together account
for approximately 20 per cent of total
major arms supplies during the period.
The British share has fallen since the
end of the 1950s. The level of sup¬
plies from France has risen throughout
the period, though not continuously;
it is now approaching equality with the
level of British supplies.
During the 1950s, a large propor¬
tion of British arms were supplied to
countries which had had traditional
military ties with Britain, or to ex-colo¬
nies. Many of these traditional reci¬
pients have turned to other sources.
The U.A.R. and Iraq turned to the Soviet
Union. Jordan is receiving more and
more weapons from the United States,
and India from the Soviet Union. An
embargo has been placed on British
arms supplies to South Africa, which
has consequently turned to France.
In the short term, there have been
rapid rises in both British and French
major arms supplies. In 1968, Britain
and France accounted for 35 per cent
of total major arms supplies. France
has determinedly expanded its markets
in South Africa and in Latin America
and South Asia. The embargo on
Israel has been accompanied by an
increase in orders from and deliveries
to the Arab countries. France conti¬
nues to supply arms to French ex-colo¬
nies A large part of the recent
increase in British major arms supplies
has consisted of deliveries to the oil
rich countries of the Middle East.
Among the other suppliers, Canada,
the Fed. Rep. of Germany and Italy
have increased their exports in the last
few years. Major arms supplies from
Italy and Canada were also high during
the 1950s, in relation to their current
level. Canada was selling Sabre
fighters, built under licence from the
. United States, during the 1950s; it is
now selling Canadian built and design¬
ed transports. Italy is selling trainers
and helicopters. During the 1950s,
Italian exports consisted primarily of
ships.
The rise in major arms supplies
from the Fed. Rep. of Germany to
countries outside Europe has consisted
of surplus equipment. Iran and
Venezuela, in particular, have pur¬
chased large quantities of ex-Luft¬
waffe F-86 fighters.
The Swedish defence industry is
comparable in sophistication to those
of Britain and France. However, Swe¬
dish exports of major weapons to the
Third World have been extremely low
and have fallen to an almost negligible
amount during the 1960s. This is prob¬
ably the result of the increasingly res¬
trictive Swedish arms trade policy.
14 The above text is abridged from the SIPRI
Yearbook of World Armaments and
Disarmament 1968-1969, published by the
Stockholm International Peace Research
Institute.
10th ANNIVERSARY OF U.N. DECLARATION
ON THE INDEPENDENCE OF COLONIAL PEOPLES
I EN years ago, the United Nations General Assembly approved the
Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and
Peoples. All peoples, it declared, had the right freely to determine their
political status and to pursue their economic, social and cultural development.
The importance of this historic Declaration was recalled recently by
M. René Maheu, Director-General of Unesco, on the occasion of the 25th
anniversary of the founding of the United Nations. Speaking in Geneva on
behalf of 21 international organizations of the U.N. family (1), he declared :
"It was within the United Nations that the idea and the process
of decolonization took definite shape. The Trusteeship Council
and the Fourth Committee of the General Assembly, in particular,
have been largely instrumental in bringing about the emanci¬
pation of many peoples formerly under colonial rule.
"The accession of these peoples to independence, however,
has not only profoundly altered the composition of the interna¬
tional community and the relations among its members, it has
also highlighted a number of problems which had never pre¬
viously appeared in their true colours and in all their gravity.
"I refer to the problems of underdevelopment. Mankind has
suddenly realized both that development has been the privilege
of a minority instead of being, as it can be, the condition of ail,
and that most of the countries seeking to achieve it were unable
to do so by their own unaided efforts.
"In this respect, a tribute must be paid to the Economic and
Social Council, the organ of the General Assembly mainly res¬
ponsible for the development of this new awareness that has
changed the spirit of our times. The Council hammered out the
idea of integrated economic and social development and secured
acceptance of it not only as a possibility but as a duty devolving
upon each individual country and upon the international commu¬
nity as a whole...
"... The world is still dominated by too many rulers and groups
who do not suit their actions to their words, who preach peace
while waging or preparing for war, who exalt justice while tole¬
rating discrimination and flagrant inequality, who pay lip service
to progress while diverting to armaments enormous sums which
they could more usefully spend on development, both in their
own country and abroad..."
During the past year, the "Unesco Courier" has on many occasions de¬
scribed the successes and setbacks, the aims and hopes of the global
struggle for the development of the under-privileged countries. Our Feb¬
ruary and October 1970 issues were largely devoted to the problems of
development and our January issue dealt with education, an integral part of
economic and social development.
(1) The International Labour Organization the Food and Agriculture Organization of
the United Nations the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organiza¬
tion the World Health Organization the International Bank for Reconstruction and
Development and its two affiliates, the International Finance Corporation and the Interna¬
tional Development Association the International Monetary Fund the International
Civil Aviation Organization the Universal Postal Union the International Telecom¬
munication Union the World Meteorological Organization the Intergovernmental
Maritime Consultative Organization the International Atomic Energy Agency the
General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade the United Nations Conference on Trade and
Development the United Nations Industrial Development Organization the United
Nations Children's Fund the United Nations Development Programme the United
Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees In the Near East the Office
of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees the United Nations Training
and Research Institute the World Food Programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Used as an offensive weapon for
the first time in World War I, poison
gas caused 1,300,000 casualties.
Photo showing a 1914-1918
cavalryman prepared for gas
-warfare is from the Italian
film "Fraulein Doktor".
Photo © Mondadorl Press, Milan
Last year an international group
of 14 specialists appointed by the
U.N. Secretary-General, U Thant,
undertook an extensive enquiry
into chemical and bacteriological
(biological) weapons and their
possible effects. The study was
made in collaboration with the
World Health Organization, the
Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion, the International Committee
of the Red Cross, the Pugwash
Conference on Science and World
Affairs and the Stockholm Inter¬
nationalPeace Research Institute.
Their report described by the U. N.
Secretary-General as " concise
and authoritative " and "a docu¬
ment which provides valuable
insights into the grave dangers'
posed by the production and
possible use of these dreaded
weapons ' '. was published by the
U.N. in July 1969. Here, we
summarize its major conclusions.
The horror of bacteriological
and chemical weaponry
I
|N the vast range of
weapons of war devised by man,
chemical and biological weapons stand
in a class on their own as armaments
having an effect solely on living matter.
Such weapons are capable of inflicting
unimaginable suffering, disease and
death on vast numbers of human
beings.
The notion of deliberately using
bacteriological weapons to spread
disease arouses universal horror.
The fact that certain chemical and
biological weapons have a potentially
unlimited effect, both in space and
time, and that their large-scale use
could have irreversibly harmful effects
on the balance of nature adds to
present world fears and tensions.
No form of warfare has been more
condemned than the use of chemical
and biological weapons.
As the destructive power of arms
increased over the years, and with it
the potential for the widespread use
of chemicals, efforts were made to
prohibit the use of chemical weapons
through international agreements. As
early as the latter part of the 19th
century, the Brussels Declaration of
1894 and the Hague Convention of
1899 prohibited the use of poisons and
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
BACTERIOLOGICAL AND CHEMICAL WEAPONRY (Continued)
Blister agents, choking agents, fungi, toxins ABC of the New Terror
16
poisoned bullets, and a separate
declaration of the Hague Convention
condemned "the use of projectiles the
sole object of which is the diffusion
of asphyxiating or deleterious gases."
Most of our knowledge concerning
the use of chemical weapons is based
upon the experience of the First World
War. Gas was first used in 1914 and
the first big attack in 1915 claimed
5,000 human lives. It is estimated
that from then until the end of the
war in 1918, at least 125,000 tons of
toxic chemicals were used, and
according to official reports, gas
casualties numbered about 1,300,000,
of which about 100,000 were fatal.
The agents used in that war were
much less toxic than those which
could be used today, and they were
dispersed by means of relatively
primitive equipment as compared with
what is now available and in accor¬
dance with battlefield concepts of a
relatively unsophisticated kind.
Since the Second World War, the
use of biological weapons has also
become an increasing possibility.
Their potential importance in warfare
is shown by the fact that infectious
diseases, even as late as World War II,
caused more casualties among comba¬
tants than all forms of enemy action.
Because there is no clear evidence
that these agents have ever been used
as modern military weapons, dis¬
cussions of their characteristics and
potential threat have to draw heavily
upon experimental field and laboratory
data and on studies of naturally
occurring outbreaks and epidemics of
infectious disease.
The outstanding characteristic of
these weapons, particularly the biolo¬
gical, is the variability amounting
under some circumstances to un¬
predictability of their effects which
depend on environmental and meteoro¬
logical conditions and on the agent
used.
They might bear not only on those
attacked but also on the side that
initiated their use, whether or not the
attacked military forces retaliated in
kind. Civilians would be even more
vulnerable than the military. The
development, acquisition and deploy¬
ment of chemical and bacteriological
weapons quite apart from the question
of protection constitute a real eco¬
nomic burden. And no system of
defence, even for the richest countries
of the world, and whatever its cost,
could be completely secure.
Chemical agents of warfare can be
defined as chemical substances
whether gaseous, liquid, or solid that
might be employed because of their
direct toxic effects on man, animals
and plants. Bacteriological agents of
warfare are living organisms, whatever
their nature, or infective material
derived from them, that are intended
to cause disease or death in man,
animals, or plants, and that depend on
their ability to multiply in the person,
animal,.or plant attacked.
Because they themselves do not
multiply, toxins, which are produced by
living organisms, can be considered as
chemical substances. As a class,
chemical agents produce their injurious
effects more rapidly than do biological
agents. The time between exposure
and significant effect may be minutes
or even seconds for highly toxic gases
or irritating vapours. Blister agents
take a few hours to produce injury.
Most chemicals used against crops
produce no noticeable effect until a
few days have elapsed.
On the other hand, a bacteriological
agent must multiply in the body of
the victim before disease or injury
occurs. This period is rarely as short
as one or two days and may be as
long as a few weeks or even longer.
For both chemical and bacteriological
agents the speed of action is affected
by the quantity absorbed.
The effects of most chemical agents
that do not kill quickly do not last
long, except in the case of some
agents such as phosgene and mustard,
where they might continue for some
weeks, months, or longer. On the
other hand, bacteriological agents that
are not quickly lethal cause illness
lasting days or even weeks.
Chemical weapons, in addition to
their highly toxic short-term effects,
may also have a long-term effect on
the environment in which they are
dispersed. If used in very high con¬
centration they might cause damage
by polluting the air or water supplies
and by poisoning the soil.
In circumstances that favour their
persistence, herbicides, defoliants, and
perhaps some other chemical agents
might linger for months, stunting the
growth of surviving or subsequent
plant life, and even changing the floral
pattern through selection. Following
repeated use, certain chemical agents
could even influence soil structure.
The organophosphorous, or nerve,
agents have never been used in war,
and no corresponding experience is
available to help form a judgement
about their possible long-term effects.
But since these agents are toxic to
all forms of animal life, it is to be
expected that if high concentrations
were dispersed over large areas, and
This is what the World Health Organization estimates
gical weapons were made on
VX NERVE GAS
Assuming 4 tons of VX nerve gas mixture released over a line 2 kilometres
long, and 150.000 persons exposed to a lethal concentration :
80,000 persons would die before help arrived.
40,000 more persons might die within 48 hours.
35,000 persons might be saved if given immediate treatment.
10,000 survivors would require intensive hospital care.
Hospitals would be swamped and it would take two weeks to bury the
dead.
In 1955, a new class of nerve gases known as V-agents were discovered
in a commercial insecticide laboratory; VX gas is one of the most lethal of
these chemical weapons.
VX gas, inhaled or absorbed through the skin, can kill quickly by poisoning
the nervous system. g
A minute quantity (0.1 of a milligram) of VX gas can kill if inhaled, 5 milli¬
grams are fatal when absorbed through the skin. Doses as small as this kill
within hours, heavier doses kill within half an hour.
1 VX nerve gas could also be used to create long-term contamination of
ground, vegetation and equipment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
if certain species were virtually exter¬
minated, the dynamic ecological equili¬
brium of the region might be changed.
Chemical agents, usually described
In terms of their physiological effects,
include the following:
Nerve agents: colourless, odourless,
tasteless chemicals, of the same family
as organophosphorus insecticides.
They poison the nervous system and
disrupt vital body functions. They
constitute the most modern war
chemicals known; they kill quickly and
are more potent than are any other
chemical agents (except toxins).
Blister agents (vesicants): oily
liquids which, in the main, burn and
blister the skin within hours after
exposure, but which also have general
toxic effects. Mustard gas is a good
example. Blister agents caused more
casualties than any other chemical
agent used in World War I.
Choking agents: highly volatile
liquids which, when breathed as gases,
irritate. and severely Injure the lungs,
causing death from choking. They
were introduced in World War I and
are of much lower potency than the
nerve agents.
Blood agents: also intended to
enter the body through the respiratory
tract. They produce death by inter¬
fering with the utilization of oxygen by
the tissues. They, too, are much less
toxic than nerve agents.
Toxins: biologically produced che¬
mical substances which are very highly
toxic and may act by ingestion or
inhalation.
Tear and harassing gases: sensory
irritants which cause a temporary flow
of tears, irritation of the skin and
respiratory tract, and occasionally
nausea and vomiting. They have been
widely used as riot control agents, and
also in war.
Psycho-chemicals: drug-like che¬
micals intended to cause temporary
mental disturbances.
What are the possible effects of a
nerve gas attack on a city?
The population density in a modern
city may be 5,000 people per square
kilometre. A heavy surprise attack
with non-volatile nerve gas by bombs
exploding on impact in a wholly un¬
prepared town would cause heavy
losses, especially at rush hours. Half
of the population might become
could happen if a minor attack with chemical or biolo-
a city of 5 million inhabitants
PNEUMONIC PLAGUE
Assuming an attack by a single bomber spraying 50 kilogrammes of dried
powder of pneumonic plague in the form of aerosol along a 2 kilometre line :
150,000 persons would be directly infected.
36,000 of these would die.
80,000 to 100,000 persons would require hospitalization and isolation.
Secondary cases would occur amongst the rest of the population with
perhaps 500,000 additional persons affected.
100,000 deaths in all could be expected.
People fleeing the city in terror would cause minor outbreaks in other
cities.
Burial and hospital facilities would be overwhelmed.
Plague, is highly infective, easy to prepare in large quantities and. when
stored, retains its virulence for many years.
Bubonic plague, the usual form of the disease, is spread to man by fleas
from infected rats. Between 25 and 50 per cent of its victims die if untreated.
The incubation period is 2 to 6 days.
Pneumonic plague, a more virulent form of the disease, is spread from
man to man by droplet infection. After an incubation period of 3 to 4 days
it causes primary pneumonia which is usually fatal.
The 'black death', the plague epidemic of 1348, wiped out over a quarter
of the population of Europe.
All figures and Information taken from "Health Aspects of Chemical and Biological Weapons",
a report published by the World Health Organization, Geneva, 1970 (Price $4.00, 24/-, 12 Sw.F).
casualties, half of them fatal, if about
one ton of agent were dispersed per
square kilometre.
If such a city were prepared for
attack, and if the preparations included
a civil defence organization with ade¬
quately equipped shelters and pro¬
tective masks for the population, the
losses might be reduced to one half
of those which would be anticipated
in conditions of total surprise.
Given a town with a total population
of 80,000, a surprise attack with nerve
gas could thus cause 40,000 casualties,
half of them fatal, whereas under ideal
circumstances for the defence, fatali¬
ties might number no more than 2,000.
It is inconceivable, however, that the
¡deal would ever be attained.
Bacteriological agents could be used
with the intention of killing people or
of incapacitating them for short or long
periods. The agents, however, cannot
be defined rigidly as either lethal or
incapacitating, since their effects are
dependent upon many factors relating
not only to themselves but also to the
individuals they attack. Any disease-
producing agent intended to incapa¬
citate may, under certain conditions,
bring about a fatal disease.
Bacteriological weapons could be
directed against man's sources of food
through the spread of persistent plant
diseases or of infectious animal
diseases. There is also the possibility
that new epidemic diseases could be
introduced, or old ones reintroduced,
which could result in deaths on the
scale which characterized the med¬
ieval plagues.
All such diseases occur naturally,
and the organisms that cause them,
with few exceptions, are known
to scientists throughout the world.
Different populations have varying
degrees of resistance to the diseases
produced by biological agents. An
infectious disease which might be only
mildly incapacitating in one population
might prove disastrous to another.
For example, when measles was first
introduced into the Hawaiian Islands,
it caused far more deaths than in the
relatively resistant " populations of
Europe.
A biological weapon which might be
intended only to incapacitate could be
highly lethal against a population
where resistance had been lowered as
a result of malnutrition. Conversely,
a weapon which was intended to
spread a lethal disease might only
cause occasional mild illness in people
who had been given a protective
vaccine or who had become immune
as a result of natural infection. The
history of epidemiology is rich with
surprises.
A large number of potential agents
can be directed against human beings.
Among those which might be used are:
Viruses: the smallest forms of life.
CONTINUED PAGE 20
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
D
ra
w
in
g
©
W
iz
a
rd
a
n
d
G
e
n
iu
s.
Z
u
ric
h
(S
w
itz
e
rla
n
d
)
caca>oc"8
3
0
)
oaraEin<
u
o
>
ciIS
C
T
5
,cu«0
c3ao
(0
Q
j
E
à
*
»
U
Ö
l
=
.8
-,
°>
|
ï
o
-
a
18
o5craE
.et!5:
ai
«
.Ec
i.
3
«
I
O
)
+
J
«
-
»
S
i
a
|
«
s
£
«
0
)
a4
3E3s
i
E3Û
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
BACTERIOLOGICAL AND CHEMICAL WEAPONRY (Continued from page 17)
The stockpiling of new types of 'secret agents'
20
Most of them can be seen only with
the electron microscope, and must be
grown on living tissue (tissue cultures,
fertile eggs, etc.). Genetic manipula¬
tion of the whole virus or chemical
manipulation of its nucleic acid, might
be used to acquire strains of higher
virulence.
Rickettsiae: intermediate between
the viruses and bacteria. Like the
viruses, they grow only in living tissue.
Bacteria: larger than viruses, they
can be easily grown on a large scale
employing equipment and processes
similar to those used in the fermenta¬
tion industry. Although many disease-
producing bacteria are susceptible to
antibiotic drugs, antibiotic-resistant
strains occur naturally and can be
selected or obtained through the use
of suitable methods of genetic mani¬
pulation. Similarly, it is possible to
select strains with increased resistance
to inactivation by sunlight and drying.
Fungi: these produce a number of
diseases in man, but very few species
appear to have any potential in biologi¬
cal warfare.
Protozoa: one-celled microscopic
organisms which cause several im¬
portant human diseases, including
malaria. Because of their complex
life cycles they too appear to have
little significance in the present context.
Parasitic worms: among them are
hook-worm and the filarial worms
which have very complicated life
cycles. They cause illness and
disability only after long exposure and
repeated infection and would be extre¬
mely difficult to produce in quantity,
to store, to transport or to spread in
a weapon. Insects are also difficult
to conceive of as weapons. Some,
such as the mosquito and the tick,
are transmitters of disease, and as
"vectors" have to be looked upon as
having potential military significance.
Biological anti-animal agents, such
as foot-and-mouth disease and anthrax
would be used primarily to destroy
domestic animals, thereby affecting
man by reducing his food supply.
Outbreaks of contagious disease in
animal populations, known as epi¬
zootics, may spread much more readily
than do epidemics among human
beings. Viral infections are probably
more serious for animals than those
caused by other micro-organisms.
Most of the bacterial diseases of
animals which could probably be used
in warfare are also transmissible to
man. Human beings would be expect¬
ed to get the disease if they were
affected by the attacking aerosol
cloud, and occasional individuals might
contract the disease from infected
animals.
The natural occurrence of devastat¬
ing plant diseases such as the blight
of potatoes in Ireland in 1845, the
coffee rust of the 1870s in Ceylon, the
chestnut blight of 1904 in the United
States of America, and the widespread
outbreaks today of cereal (especially
wheat) rusts has suggested that plant
pathogens might be used for military
purposes.
Large-scale bacteriological attacks
could have a serious impact on the
entire economy of the target country.
Depending on the type of agent used,
the disease might well spread to
neighbouring countries.
Whatever might be done to try to
save human beings, nothing significant
could be done to protect crops, live¬
stock, fodder, and food-stuffs from a
chemical and bacteriological weapons
attack. Persistent chemical agents
could constitute a particular danger to
livestock. Water in open reservoirs
could be polluted as a result of
deliberate attack, or perhaps accident¬
ally, with chemical or bacteriological
weapons. The water supply of large
towns could become unusable, and
rivers, lakes and streams might be
temporarily contaminated.
T.
ODAY a large number of
industrialized countries have the po¬
tential to produce a variety of chemical
agents. Many of the intermediates
required in their manufacture, and in
some cases even the agents them¬
selves, are widely used in peacetime.
Such substances include, for exam¬
ple, phosgene, which is used in the
manufacture of plastics and which
some highly developed countries
produce at the rate of more than
100,000 tons a year; ethylene-oxide,
which is used in the manufacture of
mustard gases, is also produced on a
large scale in various countries for
use in the manufacture of detergents,
disinfectants, etc.; mustard gas and
nitrogen mustard gases can be produc¬
ed from ethylene-oxide by a relatively
simple process. Other industrial pro¬
cesses could similarly be adapted for
the production of biological agents.
The development of sophisticated
and comprehensive weapons systems
for chemical or bacteriological warfare
would require a very costly additional
effort. Nevertheless, the possibility
that a peacetime industry could be
converted to work for military pur¬
poses increases the responsibility of
governments that are concerned about
preventing chemical and biological war
from ever breaking out.
The potential for developing an
armoury of chemical and bacteriolo¬
gical weapons has grown considerably
in recent years, not only in terms of
the number of agents, but also in their
toxicity and in the diversity of their
effects.
But chemical and bacteriological
weapons are not a cheap substitute
for other kinds of weapons. They
represent an additional drain on the
national resources of those countries
by which they are developed, produc¬
ed, and stockpiled. The cost cannot,
of course, be estimated with precision;
this would depend on the potential of
a country's industry.
Because chemical and bacteriolo¬
gical weapons are unpredictable, in
varying degree, either in the scale
or duration of their effects, and
because no certain defence can be
planned against them, their universal
elimination would not detract from any
nation's security.
Once any chemical or bacteriological
weapon had been used in warfare,
there would be a serious risk of
escalation, both in the use of more
dangerous weapons belonging to the
same class and of other weapons of
mass destruction. In short, the
development of a chemical or bacterio¬
logical armoury and a defence, implies
an economic burden without necessar¬
ily imparting any proportionate com¬
pensatory advantage to security. And
it imposes a new and continuing threat
to future international security.
Were these weapons ever to be
used on a large scale in war, no one
could predict how enduring the effects
would be, and how they would affect
the structure of society and the envi¬
ronment in which we live. This
overriding danger would apply as
much to the country that initiated the
use of these weapons as to the one
which had been attacked, regardless
of what protective measures it might
have taken in parallel with its develop¬
ment of an offensive capability.
A particular danger also derives
from the fact that any country could
develop or acquire, in one way or
another, a capability in this type of
warfare, despite the fact that this could
prove costly. The danger of the
proliferation of this class of weapons
applies as much to the developing as
it does to developed countries.
The momentum of the arms race
would clearly decrease if the produc¬
tion of these weapons were effectively
and unconditionally banned. Their
use, which could cause an enormous
loss of human life, has already been
condemned and prohibited by inter¬
national agreements, in particular the
Geneva Protocol of 1925, and, more
recently, in resolutions of the General
Assembly of the United Nations.
The prospects for general and
complete disarmament under effective
international control and hence for
peace throughout the world, would
brighten significantly if the develop¬
ment, production, and stockpiling of
chemical and bacteriological agents
intended for purposes of war were to
end and if they were eliminated from
all military arsenals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
'Atoms X", painted In
1969 by Anna
Szpakowska-Kujawska,
a young Polish artist
from Wroclaw.
Peace research
-the science of survival
by Bert V. A. Röling
BERT V. A. ROUNG is secretary general
of the International Peace Research Associa¬
tion and professor of international law and
director of the Polemological Institute at the
University of Groningen (Netherlands).
From 1950 to 1957 he was a member of the
Netherlands Delegation to the United Nations
General Assembly. He is the author of
"International Law in an Expanded World"
(1960) and "On War and Peace" (3rd edition,
1967, In Dutch). The present text is based
on a study by Mr. Röling, published in
Unesco's science quarterly, 'Impact of
Science on Society", (Vol. XVIII, N' 2)
April-lune 1968.
w
AR was long regarded as
a scourge of God, as a means
of chastising mankind. The London
City Council in 1665, for instance,
considered the plague epidemic afflict¬
ing their city as an atonement required
by the Lord for the impious writings of
Thomas Hobbes.
Only when war was seen as just
another facet of human inadequacy
could it become the subject of
scholarly contemplation. The first
branches of learning to regard war as
man-made were theology, ethics and
jurisprudence. However, each of
these naturally tended to take a
normative view, to set up standards of
Tightness and wrongness.
The study of war and peace as an
objective branch of learning could only
begin at a rather late period in history,
when scholars no longer sought to set
up judgements, but rather sought to
examine war and its causes with the
objective of understanding the factors
and relationships that play their parts.
The first contributions were made by
historians, political scientists, econo¬
mists and sociologists.
The First World War had already
made it clear that war had ceased to
be "limited", mainly involving armies,
and had become "total", involving the
entire population of a nation.
The Second World War added a
new dimension by the introduction of
nuclear weapons. Total war has now
evolved into its ultimate state: anni¬
hilating war.
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
PEACE RESEARCH (Continued)
22
This is the problem of our times:
war has now become unendurable, but
the relations between the states, the
international system, have remained
the same. We still have sovereign
states which seek security in their own
military power and want to ensure
peace by "deterrence", by the "balance
of terror", the modern interpretation of
the ancient adage: si vis pacem para
bellum if you wish for peace, prepare
for war.
Though total nuclear war can now
mean the end of our technical civiliza¬
tion, the prevailing system of peace
through power which implies further
arms research, a continuation of the
arms race, an increase in the arms
trade, the gradual spread of nuclear
weapons, must inevitably lead sooner
or later to nuclear war.
Peace research has its origins in the
anxiety aroused by this problem of
war. The desire for peace is no
longer based on moral or emotional
grounds, but now has its foundation in
the human reason. It is our soundly
rational fears which have caused the
question to be put whether a scholarly
approach to the problem of war might
not contribute to its solution.
Thus, after the Second World War
the field of peace research enjoyed a
rapid increase in interest and growth.
Today peace research institutes are
sprouting up everywhere in the world,
while numerous other institutions have
added peace research investigations
to their list of activities.
It seems to me that the whole
spectrum of peace research projects
falls into four well-defined categories:
war; peace; man, society and the inter¬
national system; the means of bringing
about change.
The Study Ot war. Research
projects in this category examine the
causes of wars, the various forms in
which war manifests itself, the functions
of war and the effects of war. Clearly
the study of war is a particulary diffi¬
cult one since causes, manifestations,
functions and effects will vary in each
case according to time and place
although in each case the various
elements are always interdependent.
The fact that each war has its own
history and its own process of develop¬
ment vastly complicates the study.
Ever since Von Clausewitz' Vom
Kriege, war has been primarily thought
of as a "continuation of policy by
military means." Von Clausewitz pro¬
vides what nowadays is often called
the strategic war model. As opposed
to this, there is the cataclysmic war
model, such as is outlined in Tolstoy's
War and Peace: war as an unwanted
and unpremeditated event, the result
of blind social forces, disaster arising
out of hazardous international inter¬
course, or to put it another way out
of dangerous international "traffic".
The difference may be stated thus:
in international traffic, the Clausewitz
war is a deliberate manner of driving,
the Tolstoy war a traffic accident.
If it may be said that strategic total
war has been eliminated from the
repertoire of practical international
behaviour, accidental total war, result¬
ing from the escalation of manoeuvres
in conflict situations, has not. Nor, as
a glance at the world situation tells
us, have either strategic or accidental
limited wars. What this all makes
clear is that the danger for the world
lies in the "accident", in conflict situa¬
tions, whether between big states or
small, chain-reacting out of control.
This spotlights the reason why the
aspect of peace research receiving the
greatest attention by workers in this
field is general conflict theory.
This entire study of war is now widely
known among peace researchers as
polemology, from the Greek, potemos,
"war". Some hold, in fact, that pole¬
mology is a field apart from but
complementary to peace research,
which they feel rather pertains to the
specific question of how to maintain
or re-establish peace. I myself believe
that in practice there is no real distinc¬
tion between polemology and peace
research and that the two terms are,
in fact, synonymous.
A few peace research institutions
are specifically oriented towards the
study of war. Among them may be
mentioned the Institut Français de
Polémologie in Paris. However, other
peace research institutions are also
strongly involved in this same area;
two-thirds of all institutions totally or
partially dedicated to peace research
are interested in general conflict
theory, a branch of polemology.
The attempt to formulate a general
conflict theory follows from the recogni¬
tion of two points: that conflict charac¬
terizes almost all social systems of
all sizes and that conflicts show fairly
similar patterns in the way they evolve.
Thus, conflicts within the family, in
economic life as illustrated by labour
strife in political life, in religion, in
race relations and in international rela¬
tions all have observable similarities.
The objective of studies of these
manifestations is to find the basic
generalizations which apply to all and
to assemble such generalizations into
a theory of conflict, similar in kind to
economic theory.
A general conflict theory, once
formulated, would enable the prediction
of results, as does any scientific
theory. As applied to conflicts, this
means the prediction of the course of
development and probable outcome
of a conflict situation, once the data of
the particular case and the known
structural facts of society have been
established.
Given the predicted probable out¬
come of the trend of a given conflict
situation, it would be theoretically
possible, if the trend indicated is
towards war, to put brakes on the
situation before it got out of hand.
Clearly, the development of a general
conflict theory, or even of a sound
working hypothesis, would be of great
value in reducing the chances of acci¬
dental wars.
Polemology not only includes studies
directly relating to general conflict
theory, such as comparisons between
industrial conflicts and international
conflicts, but other research projects
on such topics as the nature of cultural
conflicts in periods of change, rela¬
tionships between population increases
and war, the relationships between
war-mindedness in a culture and other
aspects of that culture, and general
military strategy.
Some projects in this area deal with
simulations of conflict situations, some¬
times using computers, and with
models of international conflict, wherein
the several national factors involved
in the development of international
conflicts are examined.
The study of peace. This
area of peace research examines the
various forms of peace and the pro¬
blems in a state of peace which tend
to destroy it.
When talking about peace, certain
basics must be realized. It can be
asserted that peace is not a natural
state. It is in the nature of man and
beast to be primarily concerned with
self, to identify self with things dear
to it, and to be stout in their defence.
This should not be misinterpreted.
I do not mean to say that war has its
roots in that which is animal in man,
because, among animals, a life-and-
death struggle between members of
the same species is a rarity. They
fight for a female, or for living space,
or in order to determine which is the
stronger. Moreover, the large-scale
group fight between bodies of conge¬
ners occurs, with the exception of
some species of rats, only among men.
So it is hardly scientific to call war
CONTINUED PAGE 30
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
1 00 wars and other conflicts
since World War II
More than 100 wars or other international and national conflicts and
disputes have occurred since the end of the Second World War. These range
in scale from outright international wars and major civil wars to incidents
with differing degrees of conflict. On this page, grouped by region, we present
a line-up of the major and other conflicts that have erupted in different parts
of the world between 1945 and 1968. How precarious the bird ofpeace!
Presentation below is based on tables published in the SIPRI Yearbook of World
Armaments and Disarmament, 1968-69.
EUROPE
Greek civil war (Greece, Yugoslavia, Albania, Bulgaria,
U:S.A.) ; Berlin crisis (U.S.S.R., NATO) ; Trieste question
(Yugoslavia, Italy) ; Corfu channel rights (U.K., Albania) ;
Cyprus independence (U.K., EOKA forces) ; Hungarian
crisis (U.S.S.R., Hungary) ; Cyprus (Cyprus, Greece and
Turkey, UN.intervention) ; Greek military coup (civil govern¬
ment and political parties, military junta) ; Cyprus question
(civil government and Greece, Turkish minority and Tur¬
key) ; Czechoslovaks crisis (Czechoslovakia, U.S.S.R.,
Poland, East Germany, Bulgaria and Hungary).
MIDDLE EAST
AND NORTH AFRICA
Iran (Iran, U.S.S.R.) ; Egypt Independence (U.K., Egypt) ;
Palestine question (Israel, Egypt, Iraq, Transjordan, Syria,
Lebanon) ; Arab-Israeli War I {Israel, Egypt, Iraq, Transjor-
dan, Syria, Lebanon) ; Morocco (France, Morocco) ; Tuni¬
sia (France, Tunisia); Iran (U.K., Iran); Algerian war of
independence (France, Algeria) ; Aden-Yemen border (U.K.,
Yemeni tribes) ; Suez invasion (U.K., France, Israel, Egypt) ;
Sinai campaign (Israel, Egypt) ; Spanish Morocco (Spain,
Morocco) ; Muscat-Oman revolt (U.K., Muscat-Oman) ;
Lebanon and Lebanon civH war (U.K., U.S.A., Jordan, Leba¬
non) ; Mosul (Iraq) revolt (Iraq government, rebel officers) ;
Tunisia-Bizerta crisis (France, Tunisia) ; Iraq-Kurds (civil
government, Kurds) ; Kuwait intervention (Iraq, Kuwait, U.K.,
Arab League) ; Morocco-Algeria border (Morocco, Algeria,
Organization of African States intervention) ; Yemen civil
war (royalists, republicans, U.A.R. and Saudi Arabia) ; Aden
civil war (U.K., Aden, Yemen, U.A.R.) ; Syrian coup d'état
(civil government military rebels) ; Arab-Israeli War II
(Israel, U.A.R., Jordan, Syria, Iraq, Lebanon).
FAR EAST AND SOUTH ASIA
Indonesian war of independence (Dutch government, natio¬
nalists); Indo-China war, Viet-Nam I (France, Indo-Chinâ,
Laos and Cambodia) ; Chinese civil war (Kuomintang, Chi¬
nese communist party, U.S.A.) ; Indian communal riots
(India, Pakistan) ; Taiwan-Formosa (Kuomintang, Taiwa¬
nese) ; Hyderabad, India (Indian government, Nizam and
Moslems) ; Kashmir (India, Pakistan) ; Philippines civil war
(Philippine government, Hukbalahap rebels) ; Burmese civil
war (Burmese government, Karen and Shan tribesmen) ;
Malayan insurgency (U.K., Malaya, and Malayan communist
party) ; Burmese border conflict (Burma, Kuomintang
forces); Korean war (North Korea, Mainland China, Rep.
of Korea, U.S.A. and U.N.); Tibet I (Tibetan govt., Mainland
China); Quemoy-Matsu Islands (Mainland China, Rep. of
China, U.S.A.); Tibet II (Mainland China, Tibetan guerrillas);
Viet-Nam war II {North Viet-Nam, Rep. of Viet-Nam,
U.S.A.); Naga revolt in India (Indian government, Nagas);
Burmese border conflict (Burma, Mainland China);
Indonesian civil war (government, communists) ; Laotian
civil war (royalists, republicans) ; Longju and Ladutch
incidents (Mainland China, India) ; Thailand, Cambodian
border (Cambodia, Thailand) ; West Irian (Indonesia,
Netherlands) ; Goa, India (India, Portugal) ; Nepal civil war
(government, insurgents) ; Viet-Nam war III (Rep. of Viet-
Nam, F.N.L., North Viet-Nam, U.S.A., Philippines, Rep. of
Korea, Thailand, Australia, New Zealand) ; Brunei revolt
(Brunei, U.K., Sarawak, North Borneo) ; Indian frontier war
(India, Mainland China) ; Malaysian confrontation (Indone¬
sia, Malaysia, U.K., Australia, New Zealand) ; Thailand
insurgency (government, Insurgents, U.S.A.) ; Rann of Kutch
(Pakistan, India) ; India-Pakistan (Pakistan, India) ; Indone¬
sian crisis (government, insurgents).
LATIN AMERICA
Bolivia (government, insurgents); Bolivia (government,
insurgents); Paraguay (government, insurgents); Costa Rica
(Costa Rica, Nicaragua); Colombia (government, insur¬
gents); Honduras {Honduras, Nicaragua); Honduras (Hon¬
duras, Nicaragua, Guatemala); Nicaragua (Nicaragua, Costa
Rica); Guatemalan intervention (Guatemala, U.S.A.); Cuba
(government Castro rebels); Venezuela (Venezuela, Domi¬
nican Republic); Dominican Republic (Dominican Republic,
U.S.A.); Cuba (Bay of Pigs) (Cuba, United States); Cuba
crisis (Cuba, U.S.S.R., U.S.A.); Cuba missile crisis (Cuba,
U.S.S.R., U.S.A., Organization of American States); Panama
canal (Panama, U.S.A.); Guatemala (government, insur¬
gents); Dominican Republic (government, insurgents, U.S.A.,
Organization of American States); Peru (government,
insurgents).
AFRICA
Madagascar (France, Madagascar); Kenya-Mau-Mau (U.K.,
Mau-Mau); Cameroons (France, U.K., nationalists); Ruanda-
Urundi (Bahutus and Watusi); Congo (Congo, Katanga
province, U.N. forces); Angola (Portugal, Angolans); Soma¬
lia-Ethiopia (Somalia, Ethiopia); Burundi (Ruanda, Burundi);
Portuguese Guinea (Portuguese government, nationalists, ;
Kenya, Somalia (Kenya, Somalia, U.K.); East African
mutinies (Kenya, Uganda, Tanganika, U.K.); Congo-Kinshasa
(government, insurgents, Belgium, U.S.A.); Mozambique
(Portugal, nationalists); Nigeria (coup d'état: government,
army); Ghana (coup d'état: government, army); Congo-
Kinshasa (Kisangani mutiny, government, army); Rhodesian
crisis (U.K., white Rhodesian minority rule); Nigeria (govern¬
ment, "Biafra" insurgents); Sudan, Uganda (Sudan, Uganda).
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
This year for the first time Unesco has awarded two literacy prizes.
At a ceremony in Teheran on International Literacy Day, September 8,
the Mohammad Reza Pahlavi prize (created by the Shahinshah of Iran
in 1967) was awarded to the "Radio Schools of Sutatenza" in Colombia
(see photo story below). The Nadezhda K. Krupskaya prize, donated by
the Government of the U.S.S.R., went to the Institute of Language and
Literature of the Mongolian People's Republic for its efforts to elimi¬
nate illiteracy in Mongolia (see "Unesco Courier", November 1969).
Honourable mention was given to organizations in Ethiopia, France,
India, Rwanda, Tunisia, Sudan, Iran, Mexico and Congo (Brazzaville).
The article by Miguel Soler Roca published opposite surveys the
problems of illiteracy in Latin America today within the framework of
the continent's overall development problems.
Photo © Pierre A. Pittet. Geneva
To bring education to Colombia's
Isolated mountain communities,
a young priest. Father José Salcedo,
(right) started a radio school in 1948,
In the Andean village
of Sutatenza, 140 kilometres
from Bogota (see "Unesco Courier",
February 1955 and August-September 1969)
Within a few years Radio Sutatenza
had over 200,000 pupils.
Today the network of radio schools
numbers more than 160,000 receivers,
and Acción Cultural Popular, as Radio
Sutatenza is now known, broadcasts
to groups throughout Colombia. Above,
youngsters tune in to their radio teacher.
Far right, villagers crowd into a
theatre run by Acción Cultural Popular.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
by Miguel Soler Roca
The education
revolution
in Latin America
T
HEY had made the long
journey through the jungle from their
distant villages and now, in the
welcome shade of a huge lapacho
tree, they settled down in a circle
ready to listen to us. We were
"somewhere in Latin America".
Our audience was composed of
leaders of groups of settlers who were
carving out a new life for themselves
on their jungle land-grants which they
were gradually clearing with fire, axe
and machete. Almost all of them were
young and they came from parts of
the country where the land was
exhausted and holdings, split into
minifundios, were too small to support
their families. Here in the jungle,
despite the many difficulties to be
overcome, they were getting a second
and, perhaps, a last chance.
We had been visiting similar settle¬
ments for several days. It was clear
that the settlers sensed the profound
change in their lives created by their
new circumstances and that they
wanted to educate themselves. The
group now surrounding us repeated
the same tale that we had heard
elsewhere: most of them, especially
the women, were illiterate; there were
no schools, but they were prepared to
build one and attend it, the children
in the morning, the women in the
afternoon and the men at night.
One of us asked, "Why do you want
an education? What good will reading
and writing be to you in the middle
of the jungle?" I noted down some
of the replies. "We have to sign
important papers with a thumbprint;
we want to be able to read them for
ourselves." "We have debts, but we
don't want to have other people keep¬
ing our accounts." "There are books
on farming which could teach us many
useful things." "We also want edu¬
cation for our wives; they could learn
how to feed the children better and
to nurse them when they are ill." One
man, more mature than the others,
summed up the replies when he said,
"We do not know why we are working
or who we are working for."
The. Education Ministers of the world
had said much the same thing, but in
more technical language, at the 1965
Teheran Conference on the Eradication
of Illiteracy, when they declared, "to
be effective, literacy programmes must
be sufficiently varied in form and
content to take into account differen¬
ces in age, sex, social condition and
environment, as well as the interests
of the adults themselves, their moti¬
vations and the possibilities for imme¬
diate application."
Since 1965, increasing efforts have
been made to promote global literacy.
It has become more generally accept¬
ed that a literacy campaign must aim
not merely to teach people to read
and write; that it must help them to
understand, to quote the settler's
words, "Why they are working and
who they are working for."
Unesco, therefore, is aiding a num¬
ber of countries to experiment with
methods based on the relationship
between literacy and the needs of
men and women in their work and
everyday life. Every year since 1965,
on International Literacy Day, Septem¬
ber 8, educators and political and
religious leaders re-affirm the need
for greater efforts to free the world
from ignorance. And scores of natio¬
nal, regional and international meetings
have studied the technical aspects of
the problem.
Much has thus been learned about
illiteracy and how to tackle It. Yet
estimates show that each year there
are five million more illiterate men and
women in the world. In 1970 the
global figure is 783 million, or 50 million
more than in 1960. This rising tide of
illiteracy, a paradox in an era when
man's expanding knowledge and skills
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
MIGUEL SOLER ROCA is Unesco repre¬
sentative at the Regional Office for Education
In Latin America, at Santiago, Chile. A
Uruguayan specialist in adult education, he
was director of CREFAL, the regional head- _
quarters for functional literacy programmes yfi
in rural areas of Latin America at Patzcuaro, imil
Mexico, from 1964 to 1969. He previously .
worked In Bolivia as a Unesco specialist In
rural education.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
EDUCATION IN LATIN AMERICA (Continued)
Literacy and social justice
have made possible astounding techno¬
logical achievements, focuses attention
on all the obstacles that prevent the
creation of just and stable societies.
In absolute terms Latin America
Is in a better position than Africa
or Asia. It has an estimated 50 million
illiterate men and women, but they
represent less than six per cent of
world illiteracy. And if we compare
illiteracy figures for 1960 or there¬
abouts with those of some ten years
earlier, the situation appears to be
stabilized.
But when we compare Latin Amer¬
ica with other regions of the Third
World, we should recall that: Latin
American countries achieved indepen¬
dence over 150 years ago; that the
ratio between Latin America's popu¬
lation and natural resources is by no
means disproportionate; and that by
the start of the present century, every
Latin American country had set up a
system of primary education which
should theoretically have served as
the foundation for economic progress
and political democracy. A compa¬
rison on this basis brings home the
harsh realities of the present situation
In Latin America.
The level of adult illiteracy in Latin
American countries today ranges from
4 to almost 90 per cent. Statistics are
often incomplete and out of date.
Those that do exist show that in six
of Unesco's 24 member states in Latin
America and the Caribbean, over half
the population is illiterate. In six other
countries illiteracy runs from 25 to
50 per cent and in a further seven,
from 10 to 25 per cent. In only five
countries is it lower than 10 per cent.
A direct link obviously exists
between the level of illiteracy and
the effectiveness of a regular educa¬
tional system. That is why Unesco
launched and supported a Major
Project for the expansion and improv¬
ement of primary education in Latin
America, between 1956 and 1966.
The project made spectacular pro¬
gress, and this helps to explain why
the problem of illiteracy, even in the
face of a massive population increase,
has not attained more alarming pro¬
portions. Primary, secondary and
university enrolments have risen at
a far higher rate than Latin America's
population growth a remarkable edu¬
cational achievement.
But even the 10-year Major Project
failed to solve the acute problem of
school drop-outs. Most children, even
at the primary level where schooling
is obligatory, were still failing to
complete their studies. The propor¬
tion finishing the sixth year," compared
to those starting school, fluctuated
between 8 and 50 per cent. In 13
countries, less than 25 per cent of
children remained in school for the
full six years.
Unesco is following up this problem,
taking as a principle that literacy
requires at least four years of primary
schooling to become definitive. Incom¬
plete education is obviously one of
the chief causes of illiteracy, yet how
many children stay at school for even
four years? The answer is, in the
cities the great majority; in the rural
areas very few.
The result Is seen in the statistics
of some Latin American countries.
These show a relatively low rate of
adult illiteracy, but a percentage of
people with less than four years of
schooling that is 20, 30 or even
40 per cent higher.
An alarming disparity thus exists
between statistical illiteracy and actual
illiteracy. It is here that the rural
primary school, ill-equipped, Isolated
and offering only a brief education, is
seen as the main source of adult
illiterates, men and women who relaps¬
ed Into illiteracy after leaving school
or who may never have been fully
literate in the first place.
B
OOK reading is another
yardstick for measuring the effective¬
ness of schooling and literacy pro¬
grammes. Here, statistics show that
public libraries in the U.S.A. and
Canada have more than one book
per head of population whereas libra¬
ries in some Latin American countries
have only one book for every 200
persons.
In the case of the daily press, the
visitor to Latin America may be misled
by the large number of newspapers
published in the capital cities. But
most of these papers have very limited
circulations. In fact statistics show
that whereas the annual per capita
consumption of newsprint in the United
States is 42 kilogrammes, in at least
seven Latin American and Caribbean
countries it is less than 2 kilogrammes.
If to all these facts we add that the
proportion of Gross National Product
allocated to education in Latin Ame¬
rica varies from 1.7 to 5.6 per cent,
it becomes clear that the difference
in levels of illiteracy reflects the limi-
The illiterate Is
blocked at the foot
of the economic and
social ladder. In
Latin America there
are still 50 million
illiterate adults, despite
tremendous strides
made In education
in recent years.
tations and weaknesses of the entire
educational system.
It Is nowadays a commonplace to
say that illiteracy is directly related
to a country's level of development.
Illiteracy and economic underdevel¬
opment are virtually synonymous. Thus
illiteracy co-exists with low incomes,
falling export prices, a dependent
economy, and a large rural population,
of whom the majority are employed
in farming. It is found where techno¬
logy is lagging, where productivity is
low, particularly in agriculture, where
life expectancies are 10, 15 or even
20 years lower than in the developing
countries, and where diets are defi¬
cient in calories and protein even on
a continent blessed with fertile soils
and a variety of climates.
And these are not the only conse¬
quences of illiteracy. Its effects are
seen in the rigidity of social structures,
the exclusion from political life of the
vast majority of the people, the exo¬
dus of able men and women from
countryside to city and sometimes
abroad, industries incapable of absorb¬
ing the surplus of manpower. It is
reflected, too, in unco-ordinated work¬
ing methods, instability in public
administration and politics, the absence
of coherent and responsible public
opinion, a widening . gap .between
generations and an increase in contes¬
tation, demonstrations and violence of
every kind.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
1
Photo © Yves Billon
Today a vast programme for the
promotion of literacy is under way in
which the most promising and most
discussed projects are those of
Unesco's Experimental World Pro¬
gramme of Functional Literacy. They
are operating in twelve countries,
financed from national resources and
from the funds of the United Nations
Development Programme. Through a
number of these projects, Unesco is
helping to evaluate the problems of
illiteracy in Latin America and is
supporting the efforts of each country
to overcome them.
Under the Experimental Programme,
Unesco has sent out teams to assess
literacy teaching programmes in a
number of Latin American countries.
Since the central aim of the programme
is to confirm the relationship between
functional literacy and economic de¬
velopment, each team is composed of
an educator and an economist.
Experimental projects based on
these exploratory studies were begun
in Ecuador in 1967, and in Venezuela
in 1969, the latter financed exclusively
from national resources. In Brazil,
Chile and Jamaica, a series of "micro-
experiments" have been studying
problems such as literacy teaching
methods, and the use of teaching aids
and audio-visual media.
Latin America has one of the first
centres for training educators created
under United Nations auspices
CREFAL (originally set up as the
Fundamental Education Centre for
Community Development in Latin
America). CREFAL, established at Patz-
cuaro, in Michoacan State, Mexico, in
1951, is an outstanding example of
effective collaboration between a host
country, Mexico, Unesco, the Organiza¬
tion of American States and a number
of U.N. Specialized Agencies.
F
ROM 1951 to 1960, CREFAL
concentrated on training teachers for
programmes of fundamental education.
From 1961 to 1968, it ran courses on
community development, and since
1969, when it became the regional
headquarters for functional literacy
programmes in rural areas of Latin
America, it has sought to promote new
ideas about literacy in the countries
of the region.
CREFAL organizes international
training courses, publishes studies on
teaching methods and materials, sends
its specialists to advise governments
and carries out educational research,
including practical tests of methods
and materials in villages near Patz-
cuaro.
Thus far CREFAL has organized
17 courses lasting from 6 to 18 months,
and 18 special short courses, attended
by some 1,500 Latin American educ¬
ators. Formerly in fundamental educa¬
tion and community development and
more recently in functional literacy,
CREFAL's influence has been con¬
siderable. Every educational service
in Latin America operating in these
fields has at least one CREFAL
graduate on its staff.
From its earliest days, Unesco has
sought to mobilize efforts and resour¬
ces in support of literacy campaigns
in the developing countries. Recently,
many new ideas and opinions regard¬
ing the world problem of illiteracy have
emerged. I would like to summarize
some of them.
There can be no choice between
literacy programmes for adults and
primary education for children since
they are complementary sectors of
education.
Mass illiteracy must be eradicated,
principally among young men and
women, and for this all the methods
and resources that countries can
mobilize are acceptable providing they
contribute to effective literacy teaching.
An operation of this size calls for
priorities. Functional education is
seen as an obvious priority since its
aim is to link basic education with
the priority needs of communities
undergoing economic and social de¬
velopment.
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
EDUCATION IN LATIN AMERICA (Continued)
Teaching men and women to think for themselves
Since literacy is only the first stage
of adult education, it is valueless
unless it encourages men and women
to go on learning. This they could do
through crash programmes of educa¬
tion, through courses teaching the
skills and knowledge needed for
development, or through out-of-school
education, now offering an increasingly
wide choice of subjects and serving
as the first step towards tomorrow's
systems of lifelong education.
To accomplish this will call for
something more than techniques to
reduce illiteracy and to provide under¬
privileged men and women with new
means to earn a living. Nor will it be
enough to offer them some ready-made
"official" definition of the society to
which they belong.
The aim is not to direct the mass of
50 million illiterates, and an equal
number of under-educated persons, in
Latin America towards what we, as
educators, believe to be the right goal.
The real problem is to teach them to
think for themselves, so that they will
not only free themselves from Igno¬
rance, but also from all forms of
injustice, and learn to participate as
conscious, responsible members of
society, a society that does not exist
as yet because they are still excluded
from it.
These principles are gradually
becoming accepted. To replace
illiteracy by "functional" literacy as far
as possible is now the goal.
But a problem that has been left
dormant for so long cannot be tackled
without causing some upheavals. One
difficulty is the pointless dispute
between those who wish to eliminate
illiteracy by concentrating all efforts
on educating the young and those who
believe that large sums should be
invested in adult education, whereas
the whole educational system is
creaking and groaning under an in¬
tolerable strain.
This disagreement can only be
settled by an effective system of
educational planning; otherwise action
undertaken will be subject to a "tug-of-
war" between the different educational
services.
Somehow, a way must be found to
reconcile two fundamental truths: that
without universal primary education,
illiteracy cannot be eradicated; and
that unless we succeed in changing
the attitude of adults towards the
social role of education, primary
schooling cannot become universal,
In 13 Latin American
countries, less than a
quarter of the
children complete
6 years of schooling.
These drop-outs soon
forget the little
they learnt during
their brief schooldays
and grow up to
join the ranks of
illiterate adults.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
since, in an illiterate community,
children with only a minimum of educa¬
tion quickly relapse into illiteracy.
This reconciliation calls for a consi¬
derable effort by the poor nations.
The cost of setting up effective
services of educational planning is an
extra burden on their shoulders, which
some of them see as a luxury they
cannot afford. But failure to recognize
the need for this effort would mean
the indefinite postponement of a
solution to the double problem of mass
illiteracy and ineffective primary educa¬
tion.
Cuba showed, in 1961, how illiteracy
can be tackled and overcome providing
certain conditions exist. In Cuba's
case they may be summed up as strong
political motivation, the ability to
mobilize national efforts for a common
objective, and a problem of relatively
small dimensions both geographically
(Cuba covers 114,500 sq. km.) and
demographically (a 23 per cent rate of
illiteracy when the campaign began).
The example of Cuba has given other
countries food for thought. On the
one hand it has shown how the chronic
weaknesses of certain literacy teach¬
ing services are aggravated by lack
of political and popular support, which
renders them completely ineffective.
On the other, it has demonstrated how
the problem can be overcome if con¬
ditions are right.
Certain Latin American governments,
convinced that circumstances now
favour a repetition of the Cuban
success, are speaking of literacy
programmes in terms of national mo¬
bilization.
Some governments are carefully
examining the problems of the function¬
al literacy approach, seen as an alter¬
native strategy (an attack on literacy
on a narrower front but in greater
depth). What form is it to take and
how is it to be achieved? Who is to
benefit first from the priorities implicit
in a system of functional literacy? In
three years time when current exper¬
imental projects have been evaluated,
it will be easier to answer these
questions.
B
UT we need not wait so
long. Reports and studies on functional
literacy are already reaching educators.
Once it is accepted that functional
literacy means literacy revitalized by
the daily needs and interests of men
and women, new programmes, methods
and materials will not be lacking
thanks not only to educators, but also
to specialists, technicians and workers
in other fields.
Nor do I believe that the choice of
where the functional literacy effort
should be concentrated should be
made exclusively by educators. It is
up to the development planners to say
where expenditure on literacy pro¬
grammes will become a worthwhile
investment.
Indeed, this vital need for co-ordina¬
tion forces us to change our approach
and to prepare literacy programmes in
direct collaboration with other sectors
of the development programme. It is
clearly more effective to locate the
areas in which economic development
is making headway and then to back
up this progress with a strong function¬
al literacy programme.
The idea that literacy is only a first
step in the system of adult education
has spread rapidly in Latin America,
especially since the Caracas Confe¬
rence in 1966. In other words, it is
now accepted that adults have right
of access to all levels of education
through crash programmes covering
literacy itself, primary education and
secondary education.
It is claimed that adults can complete
these courses in roughly half the time
required in the normal educational
system, and this is borne out by the
fact that more and more men and
women are attending evening classes
so as to obtain the baccalauréat that
enables them to enter university.
But here, two points should be made.
The first concerns the drawback to
providing adult education in a form
that merely parallels the normal educa¬
tional system. A good many people
in cities have personal motivations for
wishing to study systematically. But
how far is it possible to take more
advantage of this and open further
urban centres for accelerated second¬
ary education, without providing
vocational training for those employed
in offices, industry and farming? No
doubt the development planners will
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
EDUCATION IN LATIN AMERICA (Continued)
answer this after weighing the need
for employees with a higher level of
education and the pattern of supply
and demand in the labour market.
The second point relates to the role
of out-of-school education for the
newly literate person. The urge to
accumulate diplomas should be replac¬
ed by a desire for knowledge that
meets real needs. And the newly
literate man and woman must be
guaranteed the opportunity and means
to go on learning.
Unfortunately, this is still thought of
in terms of formal education, although
continuity in learning can also be met
adequately by a plentiful supply of
books and magazines, by radio and
television programmes, by club and
library activities and through individual
studies not necessarily linked to
complete programmes of secondary or
higher education.
One might add that the fundamental
aims of adult education are beginning
to be discussed in Latin America. But
the problem is much greater than it
appears at first sight. It calls for
reforms throughout the existing educ¬
ational system, conservative in its
attitude to social change, and trauma¬
tic in the psychological effects it pro¬
duces, particularly in the case of teen¬
agers.
If we reduce adult education, includ¬
ing literacy teaching, to a system for
cramming minds with a mass of know¬
ledge, we shall produce a better-
informed society, but not a more per-
(Continued from page 22)
PEACE RESEARCH, THE SCIENCE OF SURVIVAL
a manifestation of animalistic beha¬
viour, and to speak of "beastly" wars,
because animals just do not behave
that way.
That brings us to the second basic
point: that war is inextricably linked
to what in man is peculiarly and
uniquely human. As Raymond Aran
has written, in Guerre et Paix entre les
Nations, "The difficulties of peace
relate more to the humanity than the
animality of man . . . Man is the creature
who is capable of preferring revolt
over humiliation and his truth over
life."
Starting from such foundations,
peace must necessarily be a far from
simple matter. There are a number
of different concepts of peace which
must be taken into account.
There are, for example, the paired
concepts of negative peace, which is
simply a state of non-war, and of
positive peace, which implies the
making of accommodations between
groups so they can live together within
a mutually accepted system of values.
Our immediate concern is necessarily
this negative peace, the mere avoid¬
ance of war, and this is indeed, what
largely occupies the statesmen of the
world at this time.
30
Static and dynamic peace.
If we try to confine ourselves simply
to banning war as by a prohibition
such as that in the United Nations
Charter, what we are really doing is
excluding war as a way of resolving
conflict situations, yet without remov¬
ing the conflict situations and without
providing any alternatives to war.
This is an impossible situation,
because the conflict situations must
become so tense that they necessarily
erupt into violence. But as soon as
we attempt to make some arrangement
for the prevention of open conflict, or
arrangements for the peaceable solu¬
tions of conflict situations, we are
already within the realm of positive
peace.
Another distinction that may be
made is that between static and
dynamic peace: between peace attained
by the maintenance of a status quo
(the kind of peace envisaged in the
Covenant of the League of Nations)
and peace attained by the adoption of
ways and means to ensure peaceable
change and re-adjustment of local,
national and international social
structures.
In a dynamic era, it is much more
evident than in a period of stability
that peace is only possible if changes
can be adjusted to without violence.
We are living in an exceptionally
dynamic era, owing to the release of
atomic energy and the emancipation
of former colonies.
Among the peace research studies
dealing with the various factors of
peace in its several concepts are those
analysing the balance of power, cases
of prolonged peaceful relations bet¬
ween nations, United Nations peace¬
keeping operations, mediation and
arbitration, and non-violence as a
method of defence.
Another large group of studies deals
with the problems which have a strong
tendency to rend the fragile fabric of
peace. Two conspicuous examples
are world armament and world poverty,
but there are certainly others which
are closely related, such as popula¬
tion pressures, intra-national tribal and
ethnic group antagonisms, the shortage
of arable land, the inadequate world
food supply and the economic and
political underdevelopment of new
nations.
The urgency of the arms problem
can be seen by making a comparison
with the animal world. In the animal
world there exists a kind of equilibrium
between the degree of aggressiveness
peculiar to a given species and the
weapons which that species has at
its disposal. Aggressive species have
only weak weapons at their disposal.
Non-aggressive species may be heavily
armed. There probably have been
species which combined great aggres¬
siveness and a great potential for the
infliction of injury but, if so, these
species have died out.
The trouble in the case of man is
that science and technology have
multiplied the effectiveness of his
weapons millions of times, but this
process has not been counterpoised
by an adequate reduction of his
aggressiveness. This is the peace
problem relating to weapons, of which
there are too many at the disposal of
the wealthy countries.
The other major peace problem
follows out of the unequal distribution
of material benefits, with too few being
at the disposal of the poor nations
which represent two-thirds of the
world's population. The distance
between the rich and the poor is
widening every year. The widening
of the gap is bound to lead in the
long run to revolutions and wars.
Peace research projects which relate
to the major problems of peace and
to the formulation of the conditions
for peace include those on arms
control, the influence of industrial-
military complexes, the economic and
social consequences of disarma¬
ment, the social aspects of technical
assistance, and, in fact, all aspects of
economic development.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ceptive one. And factual knowledge
without self-awareness and a mind
open to the world may result in failure
to achieve the right objective.
In Latin America, the Brazilian
educator, Paulo Freiré, has rightly
stressed the importance of awareness
that enables men and women to use
their critical judgement and act accord¬
ingly; to understand social realities in
global terms.
Following his research in Brazil,
Paulo Freiré worked with the Govern
ment of Chile to develop and make
use of the "psycho-social" educational
method. Increasingly welcomed in
Latin America, this method has gained
much of its impetus from educators
associated with the Roman Catholic
Church.
If literacy is to become a driving
force for the liberation of men and
women, it will only do so by giving the
"literate" a clearer appreciation of the
world, and only through changes in
the composition of groups which take
decisions. The day illiteracy is era¬
dicated we shall see a change far
more important than the raising of the
average level of education. On that
day, the structure of decision making
will be transformed.
I recently attended the inauguration
of a new adult education programme.
Hanging above the assembled crowd
was a huge poster. Foreshadowing a
wind of change in Latin America, it
bore these words: "Literacy is revolu¬
tion."
About one-third of peace research
institutes are working on mathematical
models of arms races. Such models,
like all mathematical models of
complex dynamic structures, are
necessarily somewhat simplified but
can sometimes provide useful insights.
Man, society and the in¬
ternational system. This area of
peace research examines the world
as it is, not as it should be if we
want to prevent war. It investigates
the world as we find it, with the
people in it as they truly are people
with their rational and irrational
elements, with their loves and hatreds,
their suspicions and enmities and in
particular with their tendency to distort
the image of their environment until
it fits the picture of the world they
have made for themselves.
While man as he really is must be
the point of departure in our under¬
standing of this combative world, peace
research must also deal with the
groups in which man lives, the states,
collective bodies with their own
sociological laws, in which the past
plays a dominant part, where tradition
often carries the day and emotionality
plays a predominant role, within which
thought and action are based not on
humanity, but on nationality, in which
conformity is the rule and indepen¬
dent thought is looked on with suspi¬
cion, in which collective distortions of
reality, especially at critical junctures,
have a fatal effect.
Bearing on these matters are peace
research investigations into ethno-
centrism acceptance of the standards
of one's ethnic group as absolutely
right and appraisal of all other groups
by these standards into race rela
tions, into the sources and compo¬
nents of nationalism and into political
ideologies and war propaganda.
Finally this area of peace research
deals with the relationships and beha¬
viour of the world of sovereign states,
that underdeveloped community of in¬
dependent units organized into what is
called the international system, in
which right and justice receive hardly
any consideration when it comes to
vital issues, in which military power is
so frequently the clinching argument.
Experimental studies on small
groups, put into test situations where
we see aggression, threat and conflict
developing out of group behaviour,
particularly out of intergroup rivalries,
are providing insights not only into
similar behaviour between far larger
social groups which are segments of
national populations, but into similar
behaviour on the international scale.
Peace research projects are prob¬
ing into all the many factors involved
in international behaviour and interna¬
tional relations. They examine, for
example, the workings of international
diplomacy, the decision-making pro¬
cess in foreign relations, the role of
élites in foreign policy decisions, the
legal aspects of peaceful coexistence,
World Court practices, the significance
of geographic factors in international
relations, the effects of modern war¬
fare on popular ethical standards, and
the reasons for the successful federa¬
tion of peoples of different cultures
one example of this being Switzerland.
Other studies are devoted to mak¬
ing a semantic analysis of internatio¬
nal disagreements, appraising not only
how the opposing parties' different
ideas of the meanings of the same
words complicate conflict situations,
but also how the intensification of
conflict situations is manifested in a
changing terminology in interchanges,
particularly by an escalation in the use
of violent and threatening language.
The relations between states in the
international system are today, as vir¬
tually always throughout history, totally
"realistic", marked by a total absence
of considerations of morality.
As Machiavelli put in his handbook
for rulers, The Prince, "A ruler cannot
be good in a bad world." A modern
political scientist drew the same con¬
clusion: "The international environ¬
ment makes it difficult almost to the
point of impossibility for states to
behave in ways that are progressively
more moral."
It is this pessimistic attitude which
lies at the root of naked power
politics. Optimists, however, think that
the behaviour of an adversary in a
controversy may indeed be favoura¬
bly affected by a gradual rapproche¬
ment in matters of disarmament by
taking graduated unilateral steps. The
policy of the good example, in which
the risk of a small concession is taken.
In any case, the antagonisms bet¬
ween states arise out of conflicts of
interests. In some cases, the conflict
of interests is such that a gain
for one party must mean a loss for the
other, as, for instance, in territorial
disputes. Yet in the majority of cases
the situation is different and an agree¬
ment between the two or a joint action
would produce results advantageous to
both. Proportionate mutual disarma¬
ment between two states is an exam¬
ple of this, since both states would
maintain the same relative strength,
but at far less cost.
Yet it has always been the case that
the uncertainty which either party feels
as to the possible conduct of the
other, instead forces both of them to Q1
arm all-out, to engage in an unlimit- *»
ed arms race. The fact is that the
conduct of one state is more or less
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
PEACE RESEARCH (Continued)
32
determined by the conduct of the
other, or by its anticipations as regards
the other's conduct. States are
accustomed to act upon the premise
that other states, striving to promote
their interests, will behave badly
which causes them to behave badly
themselves.
The same state of mind applies in
many other aspects of the conflicts
between nations. States blindly pursue
their own individual paths as they
react to each other, including the path
to war, in the belief that they are act¬
ing realistically.
I feel that what is basically neces¬
sary is a different system of internatio¬
nal relations, incorporating new rules
of conduct based on rationality. That
is the task of international law combin¬
ed with a world-wide organization which
can keep a proper check on the obser¬
vance of the rules for international
behaviour it has laid down, and which
has the power to enforce their ob¬
servance.
The means of bringing
about Change. The fourth area of
peace research includes a considera¬
tion of those forces in society which
might help the world to realize the
basic conditions for peace. One might
think here of the churches, the arts
and sciences, education, and mass
communication, including the press,
radio and television. These studies
deal particularly with such questions
as: "How can a large body of people
be reached?"; "What is the role and
significance of protest?"; and "What
may be the influence of the idea of
militant non-violence?"
To find the answers to such ques¬
tions, peace research studies are being
conducted on such general topics as
the effects and effectiveness of non¬
violent protests, the effect of public
opinion on foreign affairs, the role of
mass media in relation to biases affect¬
ing international relations, the In¬
fluence of communication channels
and mass media on foreign policy
issues, the methods of communicating
the findings of social science to deci¬
sion-makers and to the general public,
and how the general public perceives
the intentions of other nations.
Still other studies evaluate the edu¬
cational programmes of international
organizations, the effects of student
interchanges on national attitudes and
the role of religious movements on
international relations.
Change in the present attitudes of
the world towards war will come
slowly. The degree of potential chan¬
ge in public opinion has been invest
igated. It appears that a considerable
percentage (40 per cent) of those inter¬
rogated in one survey had not altered
their views over a period of twenty
years, even in circumstances most fa¬
vourable to changes of opinion.
In other cases, the changes of
opinion were very slight. Each gen¬
eration has a relatively small radius of
attitudes. Major changes usually only
follow out of bitter experience, and
tend to coincide more or less with the
advent of a new generation.
In view of the components of the
vast problem facing peace research,
which are respectively man, the group
(state) and the world of states, it is
obvious that the science of peace must
necessarily be a broadly multi-dis¬
ciplinary one.
Since most of the topics of peace
research fall clearly into the domain of
the social sciences, the scientific
staffs of peace research institutions
are heavily weighted with specialists
in various social science fields.
Among them are those trained in
history, economics, international law,
international relations, political scien¬
ce, and social psychology.
However, specialists in other dis¬
ciplines at the margin of the social
sciences or in some of the physical
and biological sciences are increasing¬
ly finding a place on peace research
staffs. Many staffs now include spe¬
cialists in mathematics and statistics,
military science, geography, physics,
anthropology and psychology. Almost
one-third of all peace research institu¬
tions employ philosophers.
Controversy between two
schools. It is regrettable that the
number of biologists on peace research
staffs is still relatively low, for these
are the scientists who must appraise
man, to determine how his innate
biological characteristics affect his
behaviour. Many peace researchers
are not sure that the study of man as
an aggressive animal falls within the
scope of this field.
Co-operation between the discipli¬
nes is by no means an easy matter,
since the various branches of learn¬
ing have gradually isolated themselves,
developing their own apparatus of re¬
search, and wish to keep their res¬
pective spheres free from the taint of
outside influence. The process of
integration has been set in motion, but
it is still far from being completed.
While it is fundamental that the
science of peace must aim to become
more and more an exact science
approaching the natural sciences, it is
evident that, as a social science, it
can only make limited utilization of
the methodologies of the natural scien¬
ces.
Peace research methodologies may
be classified, generally speaking, as
being of two types, and there is a
controversy currently going on about
their respective merits. The first
approach is what we may call the
"traditional" or "historical-analytical"
approach. The second is the "mod¬
ern" or "mathematical" approach,
which turns to statistical methods, ma¬
thematical analysis and mathematical
model-making in the treatment of the
subject matter. The controversy be¬
tween adherents of the two schools
is an extension of the same contro¬
versy as is found in the fields of socio¬
logy and international relations.
My conclusion tends to be that both
methods are indispensable, because
they are complementary. The exact
method will often succeed in proving
beyond refutation what the traditional
method has suggested. Moreover,
figures form an international language
which can be understood across the
frontiers of states and ideologies.
Usually peace research starts within
a national context. In each country,
it bears a national stamp and employs
a national rhetoric. Each investigator's
outlook cannot fail to be conditioned
by the system of values prevalent in
his own country, by what Julius Stone
(in "Aggression and World Order")
called "the national versions of truth
and justice."
The investigator sincerely strives for
objectivity, but he does not escape
subjectivity. This has an advantage
in that he speaks the language of his
environment and is understood in con¬
sequence. Obviously, this is neces¬
sary for any social science which
wishes to have any impact on society
at all.
The drawback is that where diffe¬
rent approaches are made in different
parts of the world, as in western and
eastern Europe, for instance, there are
serious problems of mutual compre¬
hension. Hence the necessity of con¬
tact and of confrontation, for the ultim¬
ate establishment of common points
of departure and common bases of un¬
derstanding.
In our divided world, we shall be
very long in achieving the common
starting points, the Greek "topoi",
which according to Plato's ideal might
convince even the gods. But in a
situation where, I believe, peace can
only be finally realized as a universal
peace achieved by a universal culture,
it is imperative that this common
basis be established as soon as
possible.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
UNICEF
GREETING
CARDS
"Winter" (right) and "Summer" (below)
are from the "Four Seasons", a series
of works by the 16th century painter
Abel Grimmer. Reproduced by courtesy
of the Musée Royal des Beaux-Arts
d'Anvers, Belgium.
Offering twenty nine different designs on its Greeting Cards
for 1970, UNICEF aims to top the record 65,000,000 cards
sold last year, which provided over ten per cent of its total
revenue. Among the 1970 cards are five designs by children
aged from 8 to 13, a series of five angels, including a detail
from "John of Patmos" by Hieronymus Bosch, reproductions
of the "Four Seasons" by the 1 6th century artist Abel Grimmer,
and other traditional and modern designs by internationally
famous artists. One box of cards pays for enough antibiotics
to cure 12 children of trachoma. Also on sale is the UNICEF
1971 engagement calendar containing fifty-four coloured
reproductions of 8 ft square murals painted by children in
Mexico City for the XlXth Olympiad in 1968. Each painting
is accompanied by a bilingual literary quotation. There is a
choice of five editions : English/French, English/Spanish
English/the Scandinavian languages, English/Portuguese and
Dutch/French.
"The Three Kings" (above) by 13 year-old
Aatos and "Snow Scene" (above right)
by 8 year-old Jannis are from a series
of five UNICEF greeting cards designed
by children at the Pestalozzi Children's
Village, Switzerland.
UNICEF cards and envelopes are sold in boxes of ten for $1.50 (Canada and
U.S.A.) and 10 F (France); in the U.K. in packs of 5 for from 4/- to 6/- (according
to design). In the U.K. a special Family Pack containing 30 cards of previous
years' designs is on sale at the bargain price of £/ . Special edition cards (five
each of two designs by Victor Vasarely and ten of one design by Paul Klee) cost
$2.50 or 14 F; in the U.K. these cards are sold singly at i/9 each. For orders
write to U.S.A. Cttee for UNICEF, 331 East 38th St., New York, NY., 10016: Cana¬
dian UNICEF Cttee, 737 Church St., Toronto 5, Ontario; U.K. Cttee for UNICEF,
123 Regent St., New Gallery Centre, London, W.1.; Comité Français pour la FISEj
UNICEF, 35, rue Félicien-David, Paris-16*. Please do not order through Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
VOICES OF EXPERIENCE
Sir,
In answer to the letter "Forum for
Youth" (April 1970), how about a
"Letters to the Editor" page especially
inviting comments from aged readers?
In our time, youth from the ends of
the earth are invited to comment on
everything, everywhere. The aged, with
their store of experience have the right
only to sink deeper and deeper into
silence.
No, let us not discriminate against
anyone in the pages of the "Unesco
Courier", not even old fogeys.
J. Brooks
New York, U.S.A.
CRISES OF THE UNIVERSITY
Sir,
I was very struck by your article
on "The Five Crises of the University"
(June 1970). The deep-rooted causes
of the malaise affecting universities are
clearly and objectively analysed. I had
not fully realized the complexities of
these problems nor their significance.
We all know there are too many
students, that universities are over¬
crowded, but every profession now
demands a higher educational level and
a deeper and broader range of knowl¬
edge. And there is also the problem
of how to teach all this in the time
available. The syllabus, in fact, is never
completed and the student has not nearly
enough time to assimilate the accumu¬
lation of knowledge. Yet it seems
impossible to lengthen studies, if only
UNESCO ASSOCIATED
SCHOOLS' EMBLEM ?
Sir,
The College of Plastic Arts in Warsaw
Is one of the Unesco Associated Schools
[over 800 schools in 61 countries belong
1st Prize, Ewa Moczorodynska (aged 19)
for economic reasons. The problems
raised by your article seem insoluble at
the present time, yet we can no more
envisage the collapse of society than
the halting of evolution itself. Perhaps
our only hope for the future lies in the
progress of human intelligence and a
more mature attitude in society as
a whole.
Sophie Masson
medical student
Lyon, France
THE PLIGHT OF DEAF CHILDREN
Sir,
I should like to echo the sentiments
expressed by R.R. Pavri of Bombay In
his letter on problems of the deaf (July
1970).
My son, who is totally deaf, has been
struggling for nearly ten years in the
scholastic world of those who can hear.
Thanks to his tenacity, he is now in
his third year at university. He owes
his success primarily to himself and
also to a few exceptional persons who
have helped him along the way. But
what problems and frustrations he has
encountered.
When will deaf children be grouped
together In special centres so that they
may follow a normal secondary school
education, without having to ask for
favours from headmasters and solicit
the goodwill of teachers, and thus have
full opportunity of going on to higher
education ?
Solange Berger
Colmar, France
2nd Prize, Dorota Brodowska (aged 17)
to the Unesco Associated Schools sys¬
tem which aims at developing a spirit
of international understanding and co¬
operation through education]. In our
programme for the promotion of inter¬
national understanding we naturally aim
for high artistic standards in visual
information media such as our Unesco
Club Wall Gazette, and in the docu¬
mentation on our projects (the Unesco
Club Chronicle, albums and scapbooks
on Finland, etc.).
This led us to hold a competition for
the design of an emblem for the Asso¬
ciated Schools as a means of creating
interest in Unesco and of giving our
boys and girls a direct participation in
Associated Schools activities.
We feel it is a particularly apt project
for International Education Year, 1970
and we are happy to say that the
competition, in which 120 boys and girls
throughout the school took part, was a
great success. The entries were of a
very high standard, and five prizes were
awarded.
The children have suggested that the
winning entry (reproduced left) should
be adopted as the emblem of the Asso¬
ciated Schools expressing the common
aim which links the boys and girls of
these schools throughout the world.
Andrzej Chrupek, headmaster
Karyna Baudtke, teacher
College of Plastic Arts, Warsaw, Poland
PROTECTION FOR
THE MIGRANT BIRD
Sir,
I have heard some disturbing news.
It seems that the Italian government has
authorized the trapping with nets of
migratory birds. I am sure you will
understand my anxiety, particularly as
this is European Conservation Year. It
could mean the disappearance of mil¬
lions of birds, resulting in considerable
harm to agriculture.
Has anyone, In fact, the right to
capture these birds? They are the
common heritage of many other coun¬
tries whose rights and interests are thus
being encroached upon. Is there no
international regulation covering this
situation? Birds have as much, if not
more, value than, say, the temples that
were recently saved by a vigorous
press campaign. Man's genius can
always produce a work of art; it will
never be able to recreate a vanished
species.
O. Bisetti
Lausanne, Switzerland
The Italian law referred to by our
reader came Into force on January 28,
J970. It authorizes the netting of birds
after March 31, 1969, the date limit set
by a previous law. In Italy, this law
sparked off an Intense press campaign.
With the backing of the Milan daily
"Corriere délia Sera", a "nature move¬
ment" was launched which already has
hundreds of thousands of members.
Mr. Giorgio Ciraolo, Permanent Delegate
of Italy to Unesco, has clarified the
situation for the "Unesco Courier".
According to the Italian Ministry for.
Agriculture and Forests, the bill drafted
by the Italian Parliament has been mod¬
ified by the Italian government in order
to restrict the netting of birds as autho¬
rized by the previous law. 'As in other
countries", says Mr. Ciraolo, "the netting
of birds in Italy Is now only permitted
to provide aviary birds and to give
ornithologists the opportunity of study¬
ing disappearing species. Draft regu¬
lations are now being adopted which
will ensure that these limitations are
strictly adhered to. There is, there¬
fore, no reason to fear serious harm to
the bird population in the future".
Editor.
MODELS FOR MANKIND
Sir,
Having read your article on Marie
Curie (October 1967), ") suggest the
"Unesco Courier" publish more articles
on great men and women who have
sacrificed themselves for the welfare of
mankind. Such articles, even if they
were brief, would help readers to
understand the real purpose of life
effort and work.
Reading about the difficulties faced
and overcome by Marie Curie and other
scientists would enable young people
to realize that the victories of science
improve standards of human life and
that its defeats exact no toll of blood
and tears.
Alejandro Gharadi
Montevideo, Uruguay
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
NEW YEAR GIFTS?
A binder for
your 1971 collection
Now is the time to order a new binder for
your 1971 collection of the Unesco Cou¬
rier. We offer subscribers an attractive and
convenient binder, handsomely produced
in red cloth. It holds a year's issues of the
magazine and costs only:
20/-stg.
$4.00
12 F.
Order from Unesco agents listed below
Why not offer
gift subscriptions
to the
'Unesco Courier'
One year's subscription still only :
20/ -stg.
$4.00 (Canada)
12 F (France)
Order from Unesco
agents listed
below
Yours will be a gift remembered each
month by friends and relatives alike
Where to renew your subscription
and order ofher Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See lift
below ; namef of distributora in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in and one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Publications : Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O.
Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW; Periodicals :
Dominie Pty. Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brook¬
vale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent. United Nations Asso¬
ciation of Australia, Victorian Division, 4th Floor,
Askew House, 364 Lonsdale St., Melbourne (Vic¬
toria), 3000 ($ 2.75). AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg
Fromme & C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (AS 82).
BELGIUM. All publications: Editions'* Labor", 342, rue
Royale, Brussels, 3. Presses Universitaires de Bruxelles,
42, av. Paul-Higer, Brussels 5. NV Standaard-We-
tenschappelijke Uitgeverij Belgiëlei 1 47, Antwerp, I. For
the Unesco Courier (1 70 FB) and art slides (488 FB) only:
Jean de Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels S. CCP
3380.00. BURMA. Trade Corporation N- (9), 550-
552 Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Information
Canada, Ottawa, Ont. ($ 4,00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244
Colombo, 2. (Rs 12.50). CHINA. World Book Co.
Ltd., 99 Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa). CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(permanent display); Zahranicni literatura 11 Soukenicka
Prague 1. ForSlovakiaonly : Nakladatelstvo Alfa, Hurba-
novo nam. 6 Bratislava. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard
Ltd.. 6, Norregade. 1 1 65,Copenhagen K. (Dan. Kr. 1 9.00).
ETHIOPIA. National Commission for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND, Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskacu, Helsinki (Fmk. 11.90).
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7«. C.C.P. 12598-48 (12 F). GERMANY. All
publications : Verlag Dokumentation, Postfach 1 48,
Jaiserstrasse 13, 8023 Munchen-Pullach. For the
Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-
Chaussee 160, Hambourg-Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650
(DM 12). GHANA. Methodist Book Depot
Ltd., Atlantic House, Commercial Street, POB 100,
cape Coast GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE, Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens; Librairie Eleftheroudakis, Nikkis 4, Athens.
HONG-KONG, Swindon Book Co., 1 3-1 5, Lock Road,
Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt,
Vici u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Könyvtarosok Boltja,
Nepköztirsasag utia 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd., Nicol Road, Ballard.
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3;
36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; 3/5 Asaf Ali Road, New
Delhi 1 ; Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16 and Scindia House, New
Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Youth Services, 72 Theatre Communication Building,
Connaught Place New Delhi 1.(Rs. 1 3.50). INDONE¬
SIA. Indira P.T., Djl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37, Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1/1 54
avenue Roosevelt, B.P. 1 533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKen¬
zie^ Bookshop. Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad; University
Bookstore, University of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wellington Road,
Ballsbridge, Dublin, 4. ISRAEL. Emmanuel Brown, for¬
merly Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48,
Nahlat Benjamin Street.Tel-Aviv (IL 1 5). JAMAICA.
Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water
Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., P.O. Box
5050, Tokyo International 100-31. JORDAN. Joseph I.
Bahous & Co., Dar-ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Am¬
man. KENYA. The E.S.A. Ltd., P.O. Box 30167, Nai¬
robi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco
'.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd., P.O. Box 2942, Kuwait. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286.
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 261, Tripoli.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxembourg (F.L. 170). MALAYSIA. Federal Publica¬
tions Sdn Bhd.. Balai Berits, 31, Jalan Riong, Kuala Lum¬
pur. MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kingsway, Vallet¬
ta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30,
Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, the Hague,
(fl. 10). NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.). N. V., Willemsud, Cura¬
cao. N.A. (NA fl. 5.25). NEW ZEALAND. Govern¬
ment Printing Office. Government Bookshops at: Rutland
Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace.
P.O.Box 1721, Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857,
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mul.
grave Street, Private Bag, Wellington ($ 2.15). NOR¬
WAY. All publications: A.S. Bokhjornet, Akersgt 41 -Oslo
1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratur-
jeneste, Box 61 25, Oslo 6 (K. 2.75). PAKISTAN. The
West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publication House,
P.O. Box 374 G.P.O.; Lahore: Showrooms: Urdu Bazar,
Lahore, and 57-58 Murree, Highway, G/6-1, Islamabad.
Pakistan Publications Bookshop, Sarwar Road, Rawalpindi;
Panbagh, Dacca. PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co.,
928. Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila. POLAND. All
publications: ORWN PAN Palac Kultury ¡ Nauki, War¬
saw. For the Unesco Courier only: RUCH, ul. Wronia, 23,
(Warsaw 1 0. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livra-
ria Portugal, ruade Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115.
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. SINGAPORE. Federal Pu¬
blications Sdn Bhd., Times House, River Valley Road, Sin¬
gapore 9. SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales
(PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN.
AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications: A/B CE. Friezes Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan, 2, Box 16356, 103 27, Stock¬
holm 16. For the Unesco Courier : Svenska FN. For-
bundet, Vasagatan 15, IV 10123, Stockholm 1 Post-
giro 18 46 92 (Kr. 1 8). SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Librairie Pavot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11,
C.C.P. 1-236. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Book¬
shop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
(37.50 baht). Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty). Ltd.,
Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. UNI¬
TED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie Kasr
El Nil, 38, rue Ksar El Nil, Cairo. Sub-agent: La Re¬
naissance d'Egypte, 9Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED
KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham and
Bristol (20/-). UNITED STATES. Unesco Publi¬
cations Center. P.O. Box 433, New York, N.Y. 10016
($ 5). U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow,
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga. Te-
razije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zaluzba Slovenije Mestni
Trg. 26, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
K; THE EDUCATION REVOLUTION
IN LATIN AMERICA
(see article page 24)
]]>
</page>
</document>
