<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078424eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
on the world
1 I
December 1965 (18th year) U.K. : 1/6 stg. - Canada : 30 cents - France : 1
"'M
mi
-.» - - r^%»Ä*» '*¿.»'
' ' -
.'
ttí . Vir i*F&tu3 	
aJ3
iJMÁ
L.* '»
m
Ë»aV
. mm
ARTS
of Africa
Oceania
America
(pre-Columbian)
8 PAGES
IN COLOUR
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Gisèle Freund, Paris
AMPHORA in the form of a seated figure
with an air of utter dejection.
Polished red terra cotta. Pacific Coast Civilization,
Mexico (300-1250 A.D.). See page 33.
D. Olmedo Phillips Collection, Mexico City
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
DECEMBER 1965 - 18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'B.
Annual subscription rates: 15'-stg.; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
¿years : 27 '-stg.; 18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg. ;
30 cents ; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish. Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H M. Stationery Oflice, P 0 Box 569, London, S. E I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted trom
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
trie opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co.. New York.
Page J*E±¿0
4 THE STEP TO MAN
By John R. Piatt
10
17
19
27
31
41
42
43
THE LATITUDES OF BEAUTY
I. AFRICA
By Michel Leiris
II. OCEANIA
By Françoise Girard
8 PAGES IN COLOUR
III. PRE-COLUMBIAN AMERICA
By Henri Lehmann
MASTERPIECES OF ANCIENT MEXICO
36 THE GULF STREAM OF THE PACIFIC
By Konstantin Fedorov
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1965
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
At/correspondence shouldbe addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
Cover photo
Detail of large African sculpture
carved from a tree trunk, a work
recently displayed in a remark¬
able exhibition' of masterpieces
from the collection of the Musée
de l'Homme in Paris The com¬
plete figure is shown on page 10.
© Musée de l'Homme, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE
STEP
TO
MAN
by John R. Piatt
Can science keep on expanding indefinitely? The Amer¬
ican biophysicist, John R. Piatt, doubts ¡t and sees our
present era of change converging to a limit that may
usher in the most extraordinary transformation of all a
new type of man and a world society reaching across
the solar system.
-Jmmê
Text copyright © Reproduction prohibited
HANGE, change, change, continual change.
This is the watchword of modern life. We have
not only adjusted to it, many of us have begun to revel in
it. Conservative scientists have predicted the end of
change at various times, but they have always been proved
wrong. It seems it must go on forever. In the last two
decades, the changes have been coming faster than ever
before. Planes have passed the speed of sound, bombs
have become incredible and then incredible squared, men
are in orbit, and here below, new countries have proliferated,
television has become universal, and every corner of the
world is in a state of ferment.
Yet it seems to me that the excitement of our changes
and emergencies has led us to look at them on too short
a time scale. Let us not view them through the eyes of
the newsman with this month's crisis or of the advertiser
selling this year's cars or even through the eyes of the
planner announcing development programmes for 15 years
ahead. Let us look at our changes under the aspect of
history. Grandparents are still alive who saw the coming
of the motorcar and the airplane. Let us look at least as
far ahead, to the time when our children will be grand¬
parents in the 21st century; or 100 or 500 years ahead of
that to a time, say, as far away as the Renaissance is
today.
I think anyone who does this will soon realize that most
of the dramatic changes that have characterized the
20th century, like those in travel and communications and
weapons, cannot possibly continue at the present rates for
anything like these lengths of time. It becomes obvious
that many of them must converge rather soon to various
JOHN R. PLATT, former professor of biophysics and physics at
the University of Chicago, is now associated director of the
. Mental Research Institute at the University of Michigan. The
/} present article is a chapter from his forthcoming book, "The Step
to Man' to be published next year by John Wiley and Sons,
New York, London and Sydney. His "The Excitement of Science"
appeared in 1962.
kinds of limits, so that these aspects of society must begin
to take on much more stable forms.
Should it surprise anyone that there might be an end to
structural change in society? A boy does not go on grow¬
ing forever. He finally reaches manhood and stops
though his mature- accomplishments are just beginning.
Likewise if a world once becomes unified, by communi¬
cation and travel and mutual danger, into one world,
the situation must level off. What more is there to do in
that direction?
Many of our important indices of technical achievement
have been shooting up exponentially for many years, very
much like the numbers in the biologists' colonies of bac¬
teria, that double in every generation as each cell divides
into two again. But such a curve of growth obviously can¬
not continue indefinitely in any field. The growth of the
bacterial colony slows up as it begins to exhaust its
nutrient. The exponential curve bends over and flattens
out into the more general "S-curve" or "logistic curve" of
growth.
Stevan Dedijer, of the University of Lund (Sweden) and
Derek DeSoIla Price of Yale University, in his book Little
Science, Big Science (Columbia Univ. Press, New York,
1963), have recently emphasized that research-and-develop-
ment expenditures in the United States are now slowing
up their rate of growth in just this way and are already
beginning to be "past the middle of the S-curve." The
reason is clear. Big research-and-development depends on
big money, and these expenditures are beginning to exhaust
their nutrient.
But I think this phenomenon of slowing up is now be¬
coming much more general. Many scientists seem to sup¬
pose that we are just at the beginning of a curve of indefi¬
nitely accelerating change. They point out that Laplace and
then Michelson long ago predicted the end of change in
physics and that they were wrong. But it is one. thing
to see a slowing up of intellectual returns in .certain areas,
and another thing to see that life is short and the world is
small and that there are physical and natural and econo-.
mic limits to everything.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
jtByÈ
On a huge mural composition, 17 metres long by 3 metres high (55 ft. X 6 ft. 6 in.) the dist¬
inguished Swiss artist, Hans Erni, has depicted our modern civilization based on scientific and
technical progress. Its theme is the genius of man the planner and organizer and the entire
process of industrial creation. Here we present the composition, which continues on pages 6,
7 and 9. Erni shows us symbolically the machinery which the brain of man has created for his
needs : machines for writing and printing, computers and electronic equipment. This work in
colour, which was executed for the 1964 Swiss National Exhibition in Lausanne, has been repro¬
duced photographically on aluminium panels. It is now displayed in the Zurich Exhibition Hall.
I think it can be shown that many of our present changes
are already rushing rapidly toward such limits. And many
of our social adjustments to change are well on their way
to what might be called "steady-state forms" that could
accommodate orders of magnitude of further technical deve¬
lopment without much additional restructuring.
I suggest that it is time to consider a different view,
that we are not at the beginning of continually accelerating
change, but that we are in the middle of a unique transi¬
tional crisis, like adolescence, as we make the jump from
an undeveloped scientific and technological society to a
fully developed one. Who knows? we may be even be¬
ginning to be past the worst of the crisis, at least in coun¬
tries like the United States. The slowing down of growth
and the beginnings of our adjustment to it may become one
of the major social phenomena of the next 30 years. Do
you doubt this? Take a brisk excursion with me through
some of our important areas of change and see if it is
not so.
Consider for example what is happening at present in
certain technical fields, as typified, say, by the high-energy
accelerators of modern physics. DeSolla Price shows in
his book that for 35 years now, we have been increasing
the energies of our largest accelerators almost exponen¬
tially, as Fermi pointed out some, years ago. It is worth
quoting some of the numbers, although very approximate
figures will suffice for the points I want to make.
In the late 1920s, atomic particles could be accelerated
to roughly 500,000 electron volts of energy. Successive
inventions raised the limit to about 20 million electron volts
in the 1930s; to 500 million by about 1950, and to 30,000
million by the 1960s. Today, one machine under construction
is designed for 50,000 million electron volts. This is an
increase by a factor of 105 in energy in these 35 years,
or a multiplication of the energy by another factor of
10 in every seven years.
Can new inventions raise the energies by still another
factor of 105 in the next 35 years? Perhaps, but many doubt
it. The reason is money. At present there is talk of a
200,000 million-electron-volt accelerator which will cost far
over 100 million dollars; after that, of a billion (a million-
million) electron-volt machine. But this would be so large
that it might require international co-operation to finance,
and the work of thousands of physicists and engineers for
10 years to construct that is, a major fraction of all the
money and effort likely to be spent on physics in the whole
world in that period. There are protests from other scien¬
tists whose projects are equally in need of money.
Of course, this probable leveling-off of one expensive
field does not mean that the era of change is over, even
in physics. Other areas of exponential progress may
appear again and again. But this example shows us what
forms and limits, from now on, will shape them all. Re-
search-and-development is now a major social business, to
be planned for, to be encouraged more richly than ever,
to be put to immediate use when possible and to be
consciously limited to a fraction of the national resources
and the national budget that is probably not far above the
20,000 million dollars, or three percent, that is presently
being spent on it the United States. There is a plateau here,
an organizational steady state, that we have nearly reached
already.
Let us go on to consider another rapidly changing tech¬
nical field and one with more social impact, the field
of computing machines. In the last 20 years or so, the
10-place desk calculator has been surpassed first by John
von Neumann's ENIAC computer at the end of the war
and now by much faster and more sophisticated devices.
It is hard to give exact figures for the improvement in speed
and capacity of the machines in this period because the
principles of operation have changed drastically, but it
might be estimated as a factor of roughly 10\
In one instance that I know of, a brilliant student in the
early 1950s took two years on a desk computer to do a
quantum-mechanical calculation that was done five years
later on an electronic computer in 14 minutes. By now, thee
time required to do this calculation, once a machine has«
been programmed for it, is probably less than one minute.
Today the designers of solid-state and other advanced
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE STEP TO MAN (Cont'd)
Plateaux in science and communication
computers say that a further increase in speed and capa¬
city by a factor of 10 or 100 is in sight, but they do not
seem to expect another factor of 103 in the next 20 years.
When the information travels between the parts of a com¬
puter with the velocity of light, the natural limit to the speed
of operation has been reached, and this is a limit which
is no longer very far off.
It is true that we are probably on the verge of great deve¬
lopments in applying computers to pattern perception and
learning and to complex manipulating systems. But compu¬
ters are already an integral part of advanced science and
business and government. Machining and accounting and
management and strategy problems are increasingly being
turned over to them. It is therefore a little hard to see how
even a dramatic extension of their powers could make as
much further difference to our attitudes and ways of life as
their development up to the present level has already
made.
This may possibly be true even of the application of com¬
puters to automation, which is threatening to give us leisure
in the decade ahead. This is sure to produce in the long
run a great social restructuring; yet it is a restructuring
which is already well under way. The problems produced
by the elimination of labour are not the problems of the
30 hours a week, or 10 hours, or none, that a man
works. They are problems of coupling this to economic
distribution and to self-respect, and problems of idleness
and boredom in the 138 or 158 or 168 hours when he does
not work. They are not nearly as different from the present
situation as it is different from that of the last century;
and the time when we will be forced to find some sort of
solution to these problems is almost certainly within the
next decade or two. On the scale of history, are we not
almost there already?
Suppose we turn instead to the fields of communication
and travel. In communication, the coming of the telephone
and radio and of television, in the last 20 years now with
satellite relays across the oceans has taken us onto
a plateau that is obvious to anyone who thinks about it.
Once we can transmit sight and sound around the world
within two seconds whenever we want to, there is little
further to be done but to extend the networks.
It is not generally realized, however, that we are also
approaching an effective plateau in our speeds of travel.
I once had the idea that we ought to organize a Centen¬
ary Celebration in honour of the occasion when man first
traveled faster than the top speed of any animal or bird.
This important breakthrough in evolution must have occur¬
red about 100 years ago when the steam locomotive
first got up to 60 or 70 miles an hour.
Today millions of people fly at 600 miles an hour in com¬
mercial jets. Commercial supersonic transports for 2,000
miles an hour are on the drawing boards ; and experimental
rocket planes have passed 4,000 miles an hour.
How long can this acceleration of speed go on? This is
an easy question to answer, because it is finished. At
around 100 miles an hour, we give up land transport and
take to the air. At around 17,000 miles an hour, we give
up air travel because we are in orbit. And this step is
already behind us.
As a matter of fact, I think the full sociological conse¬
quences of high-speed transport are already implicit in
the jet-plane speeds we have today. Scarcely a hundred
years ago, going around the world meant months of sailing
around the Horn. Now civilians as well as armies can
reach almost any point on the globe in less than a day. Can
any further reduction in this time say to six hours by super¬
sonic transport, or to one hour by rocket ever make as
great a difference again? I think not. In most worldwide
plans and operations, travel time is no longer the most
significant variable.
Once horses had been tamed, men built their lives and
societies around them for thousands of years. Today the
United States is built around highspeed powered trans¬
portation. We have the automobile, the airplane, and the
Go-Kart. It is transport that shapes the layout of roads
and cities and airports and the structure and mobility of
youth and workers and families and business and govern¬
ment. Might not our accommodations to fast easy trahs-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
i£ 2 IT i., . '
y i«wk*ui
portation, and our attitude of taking it for granted, go on
again almost unchanged for hundreds or thousands of
years?
I must confess that I fail to see how any new vehicle, no
matter how marvelous, could again have the revolutionary
effect that the railroad, the automobile, and the aeroplane
had when they displaced the horse and carriage. Once
more, regardless of future developments, in some important
sense we are there already.
It is more surprising to realize that this is also almost
true of space travel today, even though at the time I am writ¬
ing this, it has been just seven years since the first orbiting
satellite, Sputnik, was sent up. Dramatic order-of-magnitude
improvements, and manned missions to the moon and
planets, and wonderful decades or centuries of exploration
are still ahead. But the moon has already been photo¬
graphed from close range and the Mariner flights are
under way, sending back detailed data from Venus and
Mars. Rockets already have the speed needed for explor¬
ing the solar system, and the time required would not be
appreciably reduced by new plasma or nuclear rockets.
The unexpected result is that the level of accessibility of
the solar system that we can develop in the next 10 or 20
years may quite possibly represent its level of accessibility
for hundreds of years to come.
Or to come back to terrestrial matters, consider the explo¬
ration of our own globe. Just since 1953, men have
climbed the highest mountain and reached the bottom of
the deepest sea. They have lived on a floating island in
the Arctic and at the South Pole all year around with run¬
ning water and hot showers. Much more remains to be
done, especially in exploring the oceans and penetrating
the solid crust, but it is clear that the whole surface of the
earth has become ours to study and use as we wish.
When there is no farther to go, there is no farther to go.
We have stepped up onto that plateau as well.
What about our technical achievements having to do
with life and death?
I think the same imminent leveling-off can be seen here
also. As everyone knows, bombs have increased in power
from the 20-ton chemical "blockbuster" of the early 1940s
to the 20,000-ton atomic bomb at Hiroshima and then the
20-million-ton hydrogen weapons after 1953 an increase
by six orders of magnitude within a single decade. Today
the largest hydrogen bombs are equivalent to about 100 mil¬
lion tons of TNT, and there are so many of them so much
"overkill" that they could wipe out all life on the planet.
But the largest ones are already too large to have maximum
efficiency for surface destruction, and the use of a number
of smaller ones is computed to be more "effective" for mili¬
tary purposes. Will we make larger bombs in the future?
We can if we want to, but even for the most overwhelming
military purposes, we do not need to.
Even in the matter of the control of nuclear weapons,
I think we may be approaching some sort of limit. This
takes a little explanation. How dangerous can the situation
get? At the present time we are near the edge of a
precipice. Every year or two there is some major inter¬
national crisis where there is a serious probability of an
"accident" that could trigger a nuclear war and escalate
into nuclear catastrophe for the world. Korea, Suez, Berlin,
Quemoy, Cuba, Vietnam. Last week's crisis, whatever it was.
It is nuclear roulette, so to speak, where the probability
of a fatal shot may be small each time you pull the trigger,
but where, if you play the game long enough, it finally, cer¬
tainly, kills you. Dedicated men have worked very hard in
each of these confrontations to avoid a nuclear incident,
but we may not continue to be so lucky.
As a result, some have estimated that cur" half-life" under
these circumstances that is, the probable number of years
before these repeated confrontations add up to a 50-50
chance of destroying the human race forever may be only
about 10 to 20 years. Obviously this is not an objectively
testable number. Nevertheless the idea is clear. We see
that our boasted decreases in death rates and increases
in the length of individual human lives in this century are
spurious, as long as this nuclear danger is so uncontrolled.
This is the first time in the history of the human race that
babies all babies everywhere forever have had such a
slim chance of survival.
Then why do I say that we are near a limit in these
dangers? Just because this cannot continue. No one lives
very long walking on loose rocks at the edge of a precipice.
Either very soon, in 10 or 20 years, or in 30 or 40, we fall
over the nuclear precipice; or else very soon, before that
time runs out, we argue some sense into our collective
heads and move back from the danger.
Some people talk of another possibility, that we might
have a nuclear war with some people still surviving at
least this time by going underground, in shelters and 7
mines. But this, even if it could work, is only a temporary
and horrible postponement of the problem like falling
partway down the precipice and then getting up, battered,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THE STEP TO MAN (Cont'd)
The cultural 'shock-front7 of history
to fall again. Do we come out of the shelters at last, to
bury and clean up and rebuild, only to have the survivors
going underground again with a resurgence of nuclear
powers in another 20 years or so? And then again 20 years
after that? Or do we stay underground for a thousand
years and hope we will mysteriously have learned how to
solve the problem of our competing nuclear threats after
that time?
This is obviously not an alternative at all. It is nothing
but a refusal to face the necessity for agreeing eventually
on a method of international nuclear control, a refusal to
see that no postponement in the shelters offers anything
but greater danger and difficulty.
I have gone into these alternatives here, simply to explain
the basis of my conclusion that within a few years the
situation will be over. Either we will be finished or half-
finished, trying to drag ourselves up again with none of the
problems solved or we will have drawn back from the
precipice by actually bargaining or paying for nuclear
restraints, with even the most difficult nations, so as to
give us all a longer half-life.
But if in this short time ahead we can find a way to
reduce these crises and probabilities by, say, a factor of 10,
then we might begin to have 100 or 200 years to think how
to reduce them further. And then we might begin to have
a chance of lasting 2,000 years or 20,000! hopefully,
say, as long as agriculture has lasted! I can only conclude
that if we live, and if we work to live, we are even now
within sight of a plateau and even a falling-off in the dimen¬
sion of terror. But time is running out, and it is the wisdom
and effort of men today, in this present generation, within
the very next few years, that will make this permanent
decision for us as to whether we live or die.
FINALLY, let us consider that other problem of
life and death, the population problem.
Julian Huxley once pointed out that the two major bio¬
logical inventions in historic times have been the control
of germ diseases, and artificial contraceptives. They date
from the work of Pasteur and of Goodyear just a hundred
years ago. It is these inventions and their successors that
are mainly responsible for our present population explosion
and for the hope of controlling it. They are the positive
and the negative feedbacks determining human numbers.
Today bacterial diseases are approaching extinction, and
virus diseases are coming under control. In the last
20 years, four of the last great killers, malaria, syphillis,
tuberculosis, and polio, have been essentially wiped out,
thanks to antibiotics and sulfa drugs and vaccines and DDT.
Cancer and circulatory diseases remain and let no one
belittle them! But most of mankind has already acquired
toward disease the Pasteurian attitude, one that we might
keep for a thousand years or forever, the attitude that we
can do something about disease and need not remain its
helpless victims.
The trouble is that this has led to an exponential growth
of population that looks overwhelming unless something is
done about it. And once more we discover that this present
age is the time of the transitional crisis. It is said that
Palaeolithic man doubled his numbers every 30,000 years.
Today the world population doubles every 30 or 40 years
roughly 1,000 times as fast.
This exponential growth is so steep that it cannot go on
for very long, on the scale of history. Today our population
is over 3,000 million. By the year 2000, with a 40-year
doubling time, it will be 6,000 million; by 2040, 12,000 million;
by 2080, 25,000 million; by 2120, 50,000 million. This is
almost 20 times our present numbers a horrible prospect
and close to the estimated limit of the earth's food supply,
even at the starvation level. But if the food supply is twice
or four times as great, it is only a matter of another 40 or
80 years. The problem is in the exponential character of the
growth, not in any particular numbers we put in.
We see that within an uncertainly of 50 years or so, the
time before the population growth slows up or levels off
from starvation is only a couple of long life-times, a time
no greater than the age of the United States. In fact, the
famine is beginning already, with the population going up
and the amount of food per capita now dropping steadily
year after year in several countries.
If the world wanted to level off its population at some
less extreme density before reaching universal starvation,
say at a density of no more than twice our present numbers,
we see that it would have to get agreements and apply
effective methods of control almost immediately, for it
would have to produce a leveling-off in less than 40 years.
The surprising thing is that this may now be technically
possible, because of the rapid development of cheaper and
simpler methods of birth control, such as oral contraceptives
and intrauterine coils, in the last decade.
The problem is orders of magnitude easier than was
believed even five years ago. The setting of birth rates
and growth rates for a country is ceasing to be a matter of
individual expense and resistance and is becoming a
question rather of public policy and persuasion and effort.
It is becoming a matter for conscious decision rather than
collective drift. The wide-spread acceptance of this attitude
in all countries and all religions is another plateau-step that
may be taken in the very near future.
I have taken pains to enumerate these many areas where
our civilization is beginning to be "past the middle of the
S-curve," just because it is not generally appreciated how
numerous and how central they are, or how convincing the
evidence is that there are limits in sight. I realize that pre¬
diction is uncertain and that my conclusions are novel, but
I think they are at least as plausible as the uncritical
assumption that changes like those of the 20th century will
go on forever. Marvelous developments lie ahead, parti¬
cularly in biology, but I do not think they will make as
radical a change in world society, as it is now being
restructured, as the changes of the last hundred years made
in 19th-century social systems.
If this is true, the present generation is the hinge of
history. It may be no accident that the approach to matura¬
tion in different fields shows a concurrent pattern. Our new
developments in power and communication and control all
support each other. And they are supporting and being
supported by the simultaneous changes in economic and
social and international structure.
I T is those aspects of technological change that
have been pressing humanity so rapidly toward
becoming a closely interconnected species, a species in
full possession of the world and its abundance and with
an adequate capacity for control and survival, that are
reaching toward mature and stable forms in this genera¬
tion. They are forms totally different from those of our
tribal warring past, but they might conceivably go on as
long as the old forms did, for hundreds or thousands of
years into the future. What is happening is that we are
in the midst of being compelled to reorganize the internal
structure and powers of the race into a mature human
integration that could be called manhood.
As a result, I think we may be now in the time of most
rapid change in the whole evolution of the human race,
either past or to come. It is a kind of cultural "shock-front",
like the shock-fronts that occur in aerodynamics when the
leading edge of an airplane wing moves faster than the
speed of sound and generates the sharp pressure wave
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
\tí&*
that causes the well-known sonic boom. The front edge of
this pressure wave is the shock-front. It is a thin region
where the low temperatures and pressures of the air ahead
of the plane change suddenly to the high temperatures and
pressures of the air immediately behind.
I think our present transitional crisis is a similar shock-
front for the human race, buffeting us about as sudden
changes in every direction come thick and fast. It is a
multiple shock-front, with each type of exponential change
reinforcing all the others. The Western world has en¬
countered this cultural shock-front first it is closer to the
airplane of history, so to speak but it would seem from
the speed of industrialization of Japan and Russia that the
rest of the world can be no more than 30 or 40 years behind.
Throughout the world, the farm and city ways of historic
man are being transformed rapidly to the ways of a high-
technology world society.
But the shock-front analogy is also an instructive way of
thinking about the times ahead. It suggests that after the
shock-front has passed, we will have reached larger powers
and interactions higher temperatures and pressures! but
that the buffeting of change will be reduced, and the times
will perhaps become .psychologically and socially calmer
than anything this generation or this century has known.
Life will go on being different, partly for the familiar
reason that we will go on having more population and
power, more communication and science, in every decade.
But it will also be different in a different way, because the
approach to a steady state is something rare in the history
of the world. We see that humanity is on the verge of a
new kind of life. 1 think an examination of the question of
what it will be like could be one of our most constructive
intellectual exercises today. It would show us how different
our present problems and solutions appear, when seen in
the perspective of the great changes and the different
structures just ahead. It would help us see what we must
do to make the changes less traumatic and to shape the
structures more intelligently.
The problem of arms control, for example, becomes a
different problem if it is seen as a temporary substitute for
other ways of keeping the peace in a disarmed world.
Innovations in education take on a different character when
seen as part of the total improvement in education that will
be needed for every child in the world in 50 years.
The need for philosophical integration of our new knowl¬
edge about the biological and intellectual and social nature
of man takes on great urgency when it is realized that this
is the substructure on which the social and political philoso¬
phy of our grandchildren's world must be built. Where are
our Montesquieu and Rousseau today? What have Freud
and the behaviourists taught us about irrationality and
educability that would help us design a good society and
a free and flexible society without the danger of recurrent
instability? Are many different good societies possible, and
can we choose among them or move at various times from
one to another?
These are problems for extensive debate, but even
without answering them it is easy to show that life in any
steady-state world must differ in many respects from ours.
One of the unexpected differences, for example, will be
the difference in age distributions and probably a related
difference in family patterns. Throughout history, children
have been a majority in most societies. The proportion of
children to total population was high because so many were
born who did not live to adulthood. It is estimated that at
most times and places, half the population has been under
age 15. Today in America, because of our post-war baby
boom, half the population is still under 20. This makes a
large "teen-age market" that many manufacturers are now
trying to reach.
But in a steady-state world no matter whether it has a
smaller population than ours or one many times larger the
same number of people would be born in every decade and
the same number would die in every decade. If our death
rate in early life continues to go down, there will then be
just as many people at age 40 or at age 60 as at age 10.
And If they all live to about 80, as it now seems they might,
then half of them will be over 40 and only one-fifth of them
will be children under 15. It will be very different from the
Indian village or the slum neighbourhood with children
everywhere underfoot. The curiosity and laughter of chil¬
dren will be scarce, and world will begin to be run, even,
more than it has been, by the old.
A strange world, for us. But it could be a good world, if
the old remain young in heart and vigour. They could use
their great excess of adult-power, prosperous and leisured,
to make the richest education for children that the world
has ever known. Perhaps childless adults will move in with
family groups, so they can share in the love and laughter
of the children and spend endless hours in teaching them, Q
in something like the old Hawaiian tradition. We may move
away from our small-family separateness and back toward
more tribal groupings as children become scarcer, and as
CONT'D ON PAGE 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
H
THE LATITUDES
OF BEAUTY
Above the entrance to the Musée de l'Homme in Paris are engraved
these words by Paul Valéry: "He who enters will decide whether I am
tomb or treasure, whether I am to remain silent or speak." Today,
museum treasures are speaking louder than ever before. Museums of
anthropology are broadening their horizons and their approach. Every¬
day objects from different lands are being exhibited to the public not
only for their cultural and historical interest, but also as things of beauty
in their own right. The cluttered collections may not be entirely a thing
of the past, but anthropological museum curators are making a deter¬
mined effort to attract larger groups of visitors from all walks of life.
This new spirit is increasingly evident everywhere. We find it at the
Museum of Anthropology of Neuchâtel, Switzerland, at the National
Museum of Anthropology in Chapultepec, Mexico, the Museum of History
and Technology in Washington. A noteworthy example is offered by the
recent exhibition of the Masterpieces of the Museum of Man. One hundred
works selected from amongst the pre-History, the pre-Columbian Ame¬
rican, the Africa and Oceana collections of the museum were brought
together first of all for their beauty as works of art and only secondarily
for their anthropological and cultural interest. On the following pages
the Unesco Courier is pleased to offer its readers a few glimpses from
this unusual exhibition as well as its accompaning catalogue a superb
work of art itself which featured illuminating texts by some of France's
most noted anthropology experts such as Michel Leiris, Georges Henri
Rivière, Henri Lehmann, Roger Heim and Françoise Girard.
A statue,
measuring
1.30 m.
(4 ft. 3 in.) \\
carved from
a tree trunk.
It was found
deeply
embedded
in the ground.
in a Dogon
village (Mali).
AFRICA
by Michel Leiris
LONG before the aesthetic
reassessment which at the
turn of this century led to the "dis¬
covery" of hitherto disdained arts,
Europeans had begun to show interest
in Negro art. By the second half of the
15th century, examples of work by
MICHEL LEIRIS, author and anthropologist,
is a leading authority on Negro cultures
of Africa and the New World, and is on the
staff of the Musée de l'Homme, Paris. Few
among his many published works have
been translated into English. Among these:
"Race and Culture" (Unesco, 1965; 3/6,
$0.60) and "The African Negroes and the
Arts of Carving and Sculpture" (in "Interre¬
lations of Cultures, Their Contribution to
International Understanding"), Unesco,
1953; out of print.
Article copyright © Reproduction prohibited
Negro artists were already reaching
Europe...
In the 17th century, a Jesuit priest,
Father Athanasius Kircher, who is still
remembered for his scholarly books
on a wide variety of subjects, founded
a museum in Rome (today the Pigorini
Museum). It was to house, among
other material, an important ethnugra-
phic collection which today includes
stone statuettes brought from the
Lower Congo towards the end of the
17th century.
Travellers were already expressing
admiration for what they had seen on
their journeys to tropical Africa. In
1668, Olfert Dapper of Holland des¬
cribed the city of Benin in glowing
terms. In 1704, Willem Bosman, also
CONT'D ON PAGE 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
MIGHTY OX DRUM
Though of strikingly
modern appearance,
this carving was
actually discovered
at the end of the
19th century in
the Ubangui River basin
of equatorial Africa.
A huge tom-tom shaped
in the form of an ox,
it is one of the
finest examples
of the African
drum-maker's craft.
Carved from
a single piece
of wood, it measures
no less than 2.29 m.
(7 ft. 6 in.) in length.
With the hollow
belly serving as
a sound-box,
the drum was able
to transmit messages
over a great distance.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Watching over
a tomb from atop
a wooden post,
this couple symbolize
the perpetuity of life.
In south west Madagascar
the burial grounds
are filled with
posts bearing
similar figures.
This one, 2.10 m.
(5 ft 8 in.) high,
dates from the
19th century.
AFRICA (Cont'd)
1915
The
revelation
of
Negro art
12
of Holland, recorded that, while visit¬
ing what is now Ghana, he had seen
gold objects "of pleasing shape" and
testified to the skill of the Negro gold¬
smiths. This tribute was confirmed a
century later by the British Envoy,
Thomas E. Bowdich, chiefly in his
description of the ornaments worn by
King Sai Tutu Çuamina of the Ashanti
people to receive the British mission.
Between 1795 and 1797, the Scottish
doctor and explorer, Mungo Park, was
struck by the skill of the Mandingan
goldsmiths, and in 1884, a report by
Ensign Besson, the first commander
of the French fort of Grand Bassam,
in the Ivory Coast, mentioned gold
objects from the Ebrié district which
"sometimes show a facility of design
and an understanding of proportions
rarely found among savage peoples."
Towards the close of the 19th cen¬
tury a number of scientific works
appeared such as the studies by Leo
Frobenius of Germany on the art work
of various African tribes, and two
English works by Charles Read in
association with Ormonde Dalton and
A.H. Pitt Rivers. All praised the ancient
art of Benin although they attributed
it to Portuguese influence, since in
those days it seemed inconceivable
that Africans could produce bronze
and ivory work of such consummate
skill all by themselves.
It was not until the early years of
this century that "Negro art" gained
full recognition. Artists in Paris, Dres¬
den and Munich seeking to instill new
life into Western art were drawn to
African wood carvings which fascinated
them and wherein they found not only
inspiration but new notions that helped
them to answer some of the questions
that perplexed them.
The first person to write of Negro
art as a great art worthy of being
taken seriously was a member of this .
avant-garde group, the German poet
and writer on aesthetics, Carl Einstein.
His Negerplastik was published in Leip
zig in 1915. It was a short work of
little ethnographic value but of great
aesthetic importance. In it Einstein set
forth the intrinsic qualities of African
sculpture in so far as it answered
some of the problems which were then
exercising the greatest exponents of
European art.
The art of Benin, and indeed the
earlier art of Ife, some remarkable
examples of which had been found
in 1910 by Frobenius, were already
known to the world when the Neger-
plastik was published. But there was
reluctance to regard these arts (which
were strikingly naturalistic) as a gen¬
uine product of the African Negro.
The Negro spirit was assumed to be
fundamentally opposed to naturalism
so that the Benin-lfe carvings were
explained as the result of foreign in¬
fluences introduced into tropical
Africa.
Things have changed since then.
We now appreciate far better than
our predecessors did the great diver¬
sity of Negro art forms. If Ife art
remains quite unique (the artists who
produced the bronze heads and figures
were naturalists who achieved a purity
of form as majestic as that of the
great Negro masterpieces conceived
according to completely different
norms), it is at least a factor which
cannot be disregarded in any assess¬
ment of the plastic arts of the African
Negro.
We are, moreover, beginning to form
an idea of the Negro artist rather dif¬
ferent from that which is even now
too often current. His anonymity is
now being recognized to be due essen¬
tially to the general absence of signed
works (due in turn to the fact that
writing is almost unknown in that part
of the world) and to the scantiness
of our information, which prevents us
from recognizing that a particular work,
considered of interest simply from the
point of view of discovering to which
ethnic group its creator belonged, may
CONT'D ON PAGE 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
In this rider with raised
arms the sculptor has
depicted the figure
of a mythical ancestor
sacrificed in expiation
of a ritual offence.
The 36 cm. (13 in.) wooden
figure comes from a Dogon
village (Mali).
Its patina of cinders shows
that it long remained
on the sacrificial altar.
All the legs of the mount
(possibly a horse)
have been broken.
Photos © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
MOUSE ORACLE
A contemplative figure, its back resting against
a piece of pottery, reveals the grace
which places the works of the Baule
artists (Ivory Coast) in the front rank
of African sculptures.
The pottery, 25 cm. '10 in.) high, was used for reading
omens. It fits into a circular wooden base and has
two compartments, one above the other.
Two hungry mice were placed in the lower one.
The upper one held a tortoiseshell covered with millet
on which ten small sticks were arranged.
Climbing up to eat the millet,
the mice disturbed the sticks whose
new patterns were interpreted by a soothsayer.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A KING AND HIS MUSICIANS
The sumptuous arts of the Ashanti
kingdom (Ghana) are attributes
of a great civilization in which guilds
of artists were formed to meet the
demands and elegant tastes of the court.
The profusion and beauty of ornaments
and precious objects astounded travellers
who saw them as early as the 18th century.
Left, a bronze kuduo or
sacred vessel in which
ritual offerings were placed.
In the centre of the lid (detail below)
the richly bejewelled king
smokes his pipe of state.
Around him are his musicians:
seven horn players following
the bearer of a double bell.
A seated figure facing the king
flourishes the royal sceptre.
The vessel and its figures were cast
by the lost wax process,
a technique known throughout
the lands along the Gulf of Benin,
where the science of working gold
and other metals became highly developed
in the service of the royal courts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
AFRICA (Cont'd)
Symbolism
and beauty
of design
have been executed by an artist of
high local repute. This is a fact now
established in respect of many areas
of Africa.
As comparative study is extended,
the African artist's products appear
less stereotyped within a given style,
and we are gradually coming to rea¬
lize that, despite the weight of tra¬
ditions, the artist still has a certain
margin of liberty and can thus in the
best cases, of course give his work
a personal stamp.
While, since the Negerplastik was
published, considerably more has been
learnt about Negro art, and while there
is no question that, even in its time,
that work was seriously marred by an
almost complete failure to understand
the sociological context in which any
work of art is set, it remains true
that Einstein was able to show very
clearly the priceless value of what the
Negro sculptors have done and what
any sculptor can learn from an exa¬
mination of the forms taken by their
works.
Reacting against the tendency of
those who were first fired with enthu-.
siasm for Negro art to concentrate
on the beauty of the objects alone,
without bothering about their exact
significance, most of the anthropolo¬
gists and others who have written on
this subject in the last few decades
have laid stress on the context of the
works, which had been neglected by
earlier writers on art, artists and art-
lovers. But they have laid so much
stress on the context that, when we
read much of what has been written,
we find the works themselves more or
less obscured behind the web of be¬
liefs and practices to which they cor¬
respond.
African arts are almost always highly
symbolical and functional in nature.
Yet, as many observers have noted,
there is a growing tendency on the part
of Africans to view their crafts aesthe¬
tically, as works of art, and no longer
exclusively as functional objects or
symbols.
Photos © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
GUARDIANS OF THE HARVEST
Carved on the door of a millet granary,
three capped and bearded figures
with bent knees call on the ancestors
of the Dogon people (Mali) to protect
the family harvest.
The double herring-bone pattern
bordering the panel symbolizes
the rain which makes
the millet sprout.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
l'A
titira ... ''^X"
: ' *'-Xf> vhIctbww*
£* .
. », y. '
}' %m n ¿m
R«i
' . fe
F ' ' X î-M?
>'X*
x«.
,'i.f .^,K
X,>!.^^.
» ;/ > ' ; v n
L ír i i- ly - .
* 4^
W;'::- m
. : » ., '
x fcrsK
. .; -
' * jn'
<
:¥
m
»
¿¿' î
»Vx'lx^
h
j>
'|,'X-:'X#
iß .«. «X
r/wfb ¿¿m
».V '
^
#*&
;y^mMmwm' -A
''ß-;i^Wmm^';- 'a-M
. .î *¿x*k
'v;-. V*: y:'w'>S,i
«#> "'»./V-'i.'t»
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Majestic and forbidding,
this massive head once
stood on the bare slopes
of Easter Island
in the Pacific.
Carved from volcanic rock,
it measures no less
than 1.55 m. (5 ft.)
The ancestors of
the present Polynesian
inhabitants hewed out,
perhaps only three
or four centuries ago,
an enormous number
of colossal statues
(some weighing
as much as 20 tons).
With their backs
to the ocean
these figures stood
like sentinels
over the mausoleums
along the seashore.
Photos © Musée de l'Homme
T first, the boldness of
of the South
Sea Island artists shocked Western
taste. Based as they were on artistic
canons completely alien to those we
were accustomed to, their works were
long regarded as curious, amusing,
even grotesque and hideous these
words appear again and again in the
accounts of the early explorers of the
Pacific. It was not until the narrow
confines of our aesthetic standards
had been burst apart by such revolu¬
tionary artistic movements as fauvism,
expressionism, cubism and, more espe¬
cially surrealism, which was drawn to
the art of the South Sea Islanders
above all for its astonishing wealth of
invention, that we came to appreciate
its true beauty.
Attention concentrated mainly on
the sculpture, as being more acces¬
sible and consequently easier to
study than other forms of art. The
paintings, many of them executed on
immovable supports such as tree
trunks or rock faces, are still little
known, as are also the dances and
music, by nature ephemeral.
Travellers to Oceania cannot help
being impressed by the innate sense
of beauty of its peoples. It is clearly
visible in their everyday life and in
the harmonious layout of their villages.
In New Guinea, the dance square,
the centre of community life, is sur¬
rounded by luxuriant vegetation
FRANÇOISE GIRARD is an assistant
director of the Musée de l'Homme, Paris,
and curator of its Oceania collection. She
has written many studies on anthropology
and is the author of the chapter on Oceania
in André Malraux's "Le Musée Imaginaire
de la Sculpture Mondiale" (The Imaginary
Museum of World Sculpture) published by
Editions Gallimard, Paris, 1964, 29 F.
OCEANIA
by Françoise Girard
Article copyright © Reproduction prohibited
forming a setting for the majestic
house of the menfolk, with its high
gable decorated with carvings of fan¬
tastic, symbolic paintings. In former
times, the houses in New Caledonia
were ranged on either side of a long
tree-lined avenue leading up to the
imposing dwelling of the chieftain, its
entrance flanked by massive bas
reliefs, its roof topped by a ridge pole
ornamented with carved shapes sil¬
houetted against the sky.
The artistic taste of these people is
evident even in the humblest domestic
objects, of finely burnished material,
beautifully designed and decorated.
For decoration is something more than
mere adornment: it is an adherent
part of the object, contributing in an
important degree to its efficacy. Thus
the Melanesian warrior believes that
it is the ancestral ¡mage on his shield
that defends him from enemy blows;
and it was the protective figures fore
and aft, no less than their nautical
qualities, that inspired the crews of
the big New Zealand boats with confi¬
dence in their vessels.
The image, in this part of the world,
has lost nothing of its evocative
power; it is closely associated with
the being it represents. A man
fashioning a statue of his ancestor
thereby imparts to him material form
and a certain measure of physical
existence. When the spirit, hitherto
invisible and intangible, has been en¬
closed by means of an appropriate
formula, in the tangible symbol repre¬
senting it, it will be more approachable,
more accessible to prayers and
offerings designed to solicit its help
and protection.
A statue must be an object of
beauty; but it has, in addition, a reli¬
gious significance.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
The fearsome features of
Ku-Kaili-Moku, a protective deity
whose effigy accompanied
the King of Hawaii
on battlefields in
the 18th century,
when Captain Cook
was making his voyages
of exploration. Effigy shown here,
67 cm. (26 in.) is composed
of a network of plant fibres
stretched over a wicker frame;
it has a rodent's teeth
and mother-of-pearl eyes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
OCEANIA (Cont'd)
18
To fulfil its religious function, a
work of art must obey certain laws gov¬
erning not only the mode of produc¬
tion, but the design as well; it must
conform to a traditional model which
has been handed down from gene¬
ration to generation, and proved its
worth. The origins of any innovation
in this field have to be vouched for.
Significantly, dreams are regarded as
one of the main sources of inspiration.
During sleep, the soul is believed to
leave the body and it may in the course
of its wanderings enter the world of
the dead and the realm of the gods.
The art of Oceania sets out to inter¬
pret a familiar world, and more espe¬
cially the world of living creatures.
Animals and the human form are its
favourite subjects. Curiously enough,
hardly any use is made of the decora¬
tive forms suggested by plant life,
except in a few areas under Islamic
influence.
From the outset it appears that the
artist bases his design on a concrete
example from real life. We watched
a Melanesian mountaineer drawing a
design that appeared to derive from
his imagination; but he protested this
was not so no design could be invent¬
ed, he said, and this one was to be
found on the shell of an insect. It is
quite possible that the geometric de¬
signs so typical of the westernmost
Polynesian island groups were original¬
ly stylized versions of natural forms.
Traversing these islands from east to
west, we see the classical frieze, re¬
presenting small dancing figures with
arms and legs bent, becoming gra¬
dually simplified until it is reduced to
a broken line.
The artist of Oceania does not seek
to make an exact copy of his model.
The statues fashioned for funeral cere¬
monies in New Ireland are clearly
indicative in this respect. The tradi¬
tional effigy does not bear the features
of the dead person, but is adorned
with the totemic emblems, known only
to his relatives and intimates, the idea
being that the effigy cannot then be
used by ill-intentioned persons in order
to harm the dead man's soul. Maoris,
so as not to give the deity too human
an aspect, depict him with a three-
fingered hand.
In Oceania, the artist strives to pro¬
duce a significant ¡mage by stressing
those particular physical, psychic and
social attributes he thinks most impor¬
tant. On the ridge poles of New Cale¬
donia, keen-sightedness is represented
by a protruding feature under prominent
eyebrows. In the valley of the river
Sepik, the long nose, regarded as a
sign of beauty and virility, is exalted
and so magnified as sometimes to
resemble the long beak of a bird.
A sculptured statue is not so much
a portrait as a symbol, into which the
soul of the dead man can enter.
The main theme of South Sea Island
art is the ancestor god; he it is who
has inspired so many outstanding
works of beauty which are for us a
source of unending pleasure.
Colour pages
Eyeless in Nuokoro
This remarkable wooden statuette (35 cm. ; 14 in.) carved
by an artist of the Caroline Islands (Nuokoro) in the Pacific,
shows the human face and form reduced to its simplest
denominator and is strikingly modern in appearance.
Oceania art emphasizes the everyday world. Favourite
subjects of Pacific artists: animals and the human figure.
Eyes of copper
Wooden figure (49 cm. ; 19 in.) entirely covered with copper
strips and wire once topped a sacred casket of the kind
used by many peoples of Gabon as a reliquary for the bones
of ancestors. Gabon funerary images include heads and
schematized figures such as this one by an Oseyba artist.
Beetle-browed mask
Sadness and mystery seem to be suffused across the face
of this wooden mask from the Dogon country of Mali. The
long indented bridge of the nose is accentuated by the
jutting forehead and ears, the narrow mouth and square
edged jaw. Mask is head of a monkey. (37 cm. ; 15 in.).
Sword to ploughshare
This life-sized, wrought iron statue (1.65 m. ;
5 ft. 8 in.) represents the good god Gu (or Ogun)
now the patron deity of chauffeurs and auto
mechanics and once the terrible god of war
and metals. Extraordinary in the daring of its
conception and balance, it is an example of the
accomplished art of Dahomey. Emblems on
rakish-angled headgear include hooks and hoes.
Peruvian painted fish
Detail of wall' drape or mummy shroud woven in cotton
(1.40 x 1 .32 m ; 4 ft. 7 in. x 4 ft. 4 in.), found near Lima, Peru.
The design of fishes is hand painted on the cloth, a techni¬
que in which Peru's artists excelled in most ancient times.
bïéfe te
i :
,îfc
Functional beauty
This almost church-like figure adorns not a stained glass
window of a European cathedral, but the upper half of a
Melanesian shield from the Solomon Islands. Mother-of-
pearl is fixed to tough wicker frame in long arrays of mosaic
squares. Everyday objects are worked with great love for
beauty of design. Figure is ancestor protecting hunter.
Maya dignitary
Stucco head found at Palenque (Mexico) where the great
Maya civilization attained its zenith. Stylized motifs and
figures fill the stucco-covered walls of Palenque, on which
the Maya people have left an outstandingly-detailed record
of their social ranks, dress, customs and physical traits.
Photos © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
I
*
2
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
^m**
ISë
'-" í T;-
SOÍ
bSSks
XX.::..»'
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
m
3tr¡\/
W&'
«M
it»
tll
wKJxà
t
,i?"jjj
,*t
yf
~Wr- :,:.!
>V".
ftfâ
»V
M
wr--<
:*rv 1»r
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
WM**
fwmv
» *W
*m<*>.
M*v***Trcw
*4i«M
:i****^
V** ^fc*
SÑ,
«
í : *
Ï &'
< !!%>it%>
*rrr/
-
-»«» *«r*f;£
.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
: ^ti/T***, .
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
' bSUR
Í ,;. '
,; -'
-''.''-'.:
mm
«3s
mM
v i*» ,
" #*-**:-
,
--y.'}
»'.'
; í:';:- :
-
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
PRE-COLUMBIAN
AMERICA
by Henri Lehmann
Article copyright © Reproduction prohibited
LESS than a quarter of a
century has passed since
pre-Columbian sculpture, ceramics and
metal-work first appeared in art exhi¬
bitions. Before being accepted as great
art, the works of the peoples who
lived on the American continent when
the Old World was unaware of its
existence were the subject of the most
outlandish judgements.
The reaction of an artist of such un¬
disputed taste as Albrecht Dürer to
the first examples of American work¬
manship to reach Europe should
have revealed from the outset that
here was genuine art. In 1520 the
great German painter had the oppor¬
tunity of seeing the gifts which the
Mexicans had sent by Cortez to the
Emperor Charles V. Filled with won¬
der at the "subtle genius", of the
inhabitants of the New World, he wrote
in his journal that never had he seen
anything so beautiful.
Among the first groups of Spaniards
to set foot in America, who alone had
the privilege of seeing the American
civilizations still unspoiled, there were
but few artists. Even so, some of the
Conquistadores were enlightened
enough to set other values on the
jewellery than the mere market price
of its gold. These men left chronicles
filled with admiration for the ornaments
of life in these American civilizations.
Bernai Diaz del Castillo gives an en¬
thusiastic description of the town of
Tenochtitlan; in an inventory of the
"treasure" of the 0ueen Anacoana,
Petrus Martyr dwells on the beauty of
the carved wooden seats called
"duho . . ."
Nevertheless, the artistic merit of
the objects brought back from Ame¬
rica escaped most of those who saw
HENRI LEHMANN is an assistant director
of the Musée de l'Homme, Paris, and
curator of its American collection. Well
known as an anthropologist and archaelo-
gist, he is the author of many studies on
pre-Columbian civilization; among his works
for the general reader are "Civilisations
précolombiennes" in the "Que sais-je ?"
collection published by the Presses Univer¬
sitaires de France, Paris, 1965; and "L'Art
Précolombien" , published by Editions Mas-
sin, Paris, 1960.
them in the sixteenth century; people
were simply surprised by their exotic
character, till then unknown. These
articles were much sought after but
only in order that they might take their
place in collections of curios. Fashions
changed, and no more was heard of
pre-Columbian products.
The end of the 18th century brought
about a revival of interest in the an¬
cient civilizations of America, now not
so much for their external forms as for
their content. The lead was given by
Alexander von Humboldt, scholar of
many parts, naturalist and ardent ex¬
plorer. In the course of extensive tra¬
vels in America, and notably in Mexico,
he saw sculptures, illuminated manus¬
cripts, divers vestiges of a bygone age.
His scientific outlook impelled him to
make an analytical study of these re¬
mains, and with his work began the
systematic examination of Mexican
manuscripts, and of the Aztec calendar
and symbolism. "Americanism" de¬
veloped into a science whose disciples
became ever more numerous . . .
Some specialists of this period
were interested in the religions, others
in the history, and others again in the
economic or social life of the conti¬
nent. No one, however, was concern¬
ed with its art; all seem to have been
quite indifferent to pre-Columbian aes¬
thetics. This lack of understanding was
blatantly displayed at the first inter¬
national congress of Americanists, held
at Nancy in 1875. The curator of the
American collections at the Anthropo¬
logical Museum in St. Petersburg de¬
clared:
"The monuments of American anti¬
quity arriving in Europe will continue to
increase in numbers, but not in beauty.
We are even compelled to say that in
the matter of art and aesthetics it
appears that no antique civilization is
worse off than that of America; a
single glance at the collections in the
Louvre is sufficient to convince one of
this, and the St. Petersburg collection
only confirms the impression . . . This
absence of all plastic beauty in the
works of aboriginal American art is a
fact which may perhaps pass unnoticed
by ethnographers and archaeologists,
but which artists are coming to
deplore, and which, in the eyes of the
historian, is of supreme importance.
For, in point of fact, he may infer from
it that as the ancient Americans were
entirely lacking in a feeling for beauty,
so were they destitute of all moral
sense..." The curator concluded this
bitter attack with a merciless condem¬
nation "Thus are these peoples (of an¬
cient America) quite dead and buried;
they lacked all lofty and noble aspir¬
ations and the sacred fire of great art
was unknown the them..."
In 1928 the Pavillon de Marsan, in
Paris, opened its doors to an exhibition
of "TheAncientArtsofAmerica", organ¬
ised by Georges-Henri Rivière, in
collaboration with Alfred Métraux. It
created such a stir that the Berlin
Academy of Fine Arts followed the
example given by Paris and four years
later presented a pre-Columbian exhi¬
bition. As a result of these exhibitions
several important private collections
were started. The Second World War
interrupted the activity of initiates, but
in 1947, on the occasion of the first
international meeting of Americanists
since the war the Musée de l'Homme
in Paris exhibited its "Masterpieces of
Pre-Columbian America," emphasizing
above all their aesthetic character.
The choice of the word "master¬
pieces" was in itself an indication of
the ground covered since the first con¬
gress. All the same, pre-Columbian
art had still not really come into its
own; it was described as a primitive
art, even when it was admitted to be
the product of "advanced" civiliza¬
tions. The exhibition of 1947 only par¬
tially succeeded in conquering these
prejudices . . .
How can we explain this prolong¬
ed denial of a form of plastic expres¬
sion which today arouses such enthu-
siam? It is probably to a compara¬
tive study of this art and that of the
Old World that we must look for the
answer.
On either side of the Atlantic, peo¬
ples which up to the 16th century had
had no contact with each other, invent¬
ed and developed arts under such
different conditions and with intentions
so diametrically opposed that when 97
they came face to face, they were
unable to discover their own system of
values in the opposite camp. European
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
PRE-COLUMBIAN AMERICA (Cont'd)
This austere mask with
its high pointed
head-dress
is a masterpiece
of the Totonac
art which flowered
on the coast
of the Mexican Gulf
over seven centuries ago.
Carved in basalt, it is
38 cm. (15 in.) high, and probably
served as an architectural
decoration crowning a wall.
28
art is commonly defined as the
expression through man's works of an
ideal of beauty. The quest for beauty
is not in itself the aim of pre-Colum¬
bian art ; art for art's sake was for the
ancient Americans so totally inconcei¬
vable that certain critics have termed
their art an extra-artistic phenomenon.
Nearly all pre-Columbian sculptures,
paintings, ceramics, etc. are intended
for cult purposes. They were used in
the countless religious ceremonies per¬
formed according to elaborate rites,
and for which the temples, statues,
vases, vestments, and trappings had
constantly to be renewed. The pre-
Columbian Pantheon was exacting, and
merciless ; what was expected from
men was not, as in the Christian reli¬
gion, a particular moral attitude, but
food in the form of mortification, offer¬
ings and sacrifices. The gods requir¬
ed regular sustenance, and if men had
abstained from their duty, they would
have let loose the worst catastrophes:
defeats, accidents, drought, even the
end of the world. Thus the art of
those who produced the objects of
such a cult was not free and dis¬
interested, but utilitarian.
As far as the ornaments and acces¬
sories of so tyrannical a religion were
concerned, their office was to inspire
terror, not love. Since these gods,
beyond human understanding, could
not be represented in a realistic hu¬
man form, the tendency was to suggest
their presence by a collection of sym¬
bolic elements, or again by a conven¬
tional group of realistic elements with
no logical connexion between them.
Hence those strange monsters which
for so long shocked European eyes...
When the Greeks wished to por¬
tray Demeter, they gave her the form
and features of any beautiful woman.
The Aztec Coatlicue, as she is to be
seen in the museum in Mexico City,
has only a very vaguely human form;
she is a Cyclopean block, adorned
with serpents' heads, claws, and a
necklace of hearts and severed
hands. The statue evokes purely and
simply the principle of generation and
X
\
;.',
*
-
' '^
. \.*t ', v
« M
'
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
MAYA WHISTLE
As it spread out
over vast areas
of central America,
attaining its zenith
between 300 and 900 A.D.,
the Maya civilization
produced an art
of exceptional richness
and complexity.
Left, Maya whistle
in the form
of a 19 cm. (8 in.) seated figure
from Yucatan (Mexico).
Maya whistles
had a soft-toned
penetrating sound.
Photos © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
THE GOD VENUS
Bearded head decorating
an incense burner (below)
was made by a 14th century
Maya artist in Guatamala.
It is believed to be
an incarnation of Quetzalcoatl,
the god of civilization, also represented
as a feathered serpent and,
in human form, as bearded
and white skinned. Tradition
taught that after bringing
the arts and sciences
to the Valley of Mexico,
Quetzalcoatl became the planet
Venus, and that as the morning
star he would one day return
from the east.
When bearded white men eventually
landed on the eastern coast,
the myth was still
so widely believed that
it paralyzed any chance of
organized resistance.
of destruction, the mother, and the
tomb, of all temporal life.
The necessity of an enormous out¬
put to satisfy the requirements of the
cult, meant that all the artists of the
pre-Columbian period were pressed
into its service. They were trained
according to tradition, and organized
into corporations, whose rules were as
strict as those of the religious orders.
One might call them craftsmen, for
they were considered as such. When
all were destined for the collective
task, it would have been inadmissible
for some to have been inferior to
others: everyone was required to attain
the same technical perfection.
A specialist, or a group of specia¬
lists sculptors, painters, potters, or
feather dressers would be charged
with a particular piece of work. This
would have to be executed in confor¬
mity with strict predetermined rules,
themselves an expression of the col¬
lective will of society. The style derives
from these rules hence the very marked
uniformity in the style of each site, or
rather, of each tribe. On the other
hand, the art of individual races is
highly characteristic, and it is impossi¬
ble to confuse one with another.
For example, the style of the Atlan¬
tes of Tula Toltec work has nothing
in common with that of the famous
calendar in the Mexico City Museum,
which is Aztec work. Thanks to the
fidelity of the pre-Columbian peoples
to their art styles, it is possible to trace
their migrations. Thus at Palenque we
see the Mayas at the summit of their
artistic achievement; when we come
upon them again at Chichen Itza, their
style is no longer pure; foreign motifs
have been incorporated in it. They
are the motifs created at Tula by the
Toltecs, and brought with them when
they came to settle at Chichen Itza...
Stylistic unity is the negation of
individualism. It is difficult' for us to
imagine that art can attain its fullest
expression without the individual con¬
tributions of artists, and it is from this
standpoint that we admire the works
of the great European painters and
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
-
;*\
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
PRE-COLUMBIAN AMERICA (Cont'd)
sculptors. But the individual contribu¬
tion does not appear in pre-Columbian
artistic creations. These are, more¬
over, never signed.
In Europe, we generally feel some¬
what reticent about anonymous works,
preferring that the object should bear
a signature. It is more satisfying to
our minds to be able to call by his
name the creator of a statue of Aphro¬
dite, of the Descent from the Cross, of
the Holy Family or of the Pilgrims at
Emmaüs, than to talk of that intangible
and depersonalized being who was the
master of Chichen Itza or of Tula.
It is true that our sculpture too re¬
mained anonymous during a part of the
Middle Ages and that the statues of
the cathedrals of Chartres, Rheims,
and Strasbourg seem to us no less
remarkable for all that. The fact is
that these statues are so clearly dif¬
ferentiated in their detail that it is quite
a simple matter to distinguish not only
the various masters, but even the
work of a master from that of his
pupils . . .
Should we say then that pre-Colum¬
bian art is entirely destitute of indi¬
vidualism? It is tempting to reply in
the affirmative; but it seems, never¬
theless, that certain Peruvian works
possess some individuality. The an¬
thropomorphic terracotta heads of the
North coast, which belong to the
Mochica civilization, allow a glimpse,
in certain unmistakable personal
touches, of the hand of one particular
artist . . .
Fifteen years ago, I attempted to
prove that according to European stan¬
dards anonymity and the absence of
individualism are characteristic of
what we term primitive art. Now it is
not possible to describe as primitives
the men who built the great Peruvian
towns of Cuzco, Machu Picchu, and
Cajamarquilla, nor again those who
constructed the pyramids of Mexico,
or of the Mayan zone in Guatemala and
Honduras. They were undeniably
great artists who had attained the sum¬
mit of their art. Their spiritual motives
alone had no connexion with those of
European artists.
Their conception of technique may
also disconcert the European observer.
On this point, by comparing, or rather,
contrasting the art of the two Worlds,
Alfred Schuster has propounded a new
theory (1). According to him, European
art is fundamentally linear and "two-
dimensional", the work being conceiv¬
ed in terms of lines and planes; pre-
Columbian art, on the other hand, is
plastic and "three-dimensional", its
success depending on the balance of
volumes . . .
Anonymity, an absence of indivi¬
dualism, a collective, social, magic-
religious, perhaps also, three-dimen¬
sional nature these are some specific
features by which pre-Columbian art
may be contrasted with European art;
these probably are the reasons for
which it remained so long ill-judged.
That time is fortunately now past, and
ancient America has henceforth ac¬
quired its proper status in the realm
of great art.
(1) Alfred B. Schuster: The Art of Two
Worlds. Studies in pre-Columbian and Euro¬
pean Cultures. Berlin (Gebr. Mann 1958)
Ibero-Amerikanische Bibliothek.
This fragment of green-veined stone has retained the forceful expression
of a funerary mask carved by an artist of the Teotihuacan
civilization nearly 1,400 years ago. The peoples of the high plateau of Mexico
fixed masks of stone (alabaster, porphyry and marble)
on the shrouds in which they enveloped their dead.
Musée de l'Homme,
Two monumental works
of Aztec art are shown here
in the newly-opened National
Museum of Anthropology at
Chapultepec, near Mexico City.
On the left, the great statue
of Coatlicue, the earth-goddess.
She has a human form,
two snakeheads
and the talons of a bird of prey.
She represents all living things.
In the background,
the Calendar Stone,
or "Stone of the Sun",
a monolithic disc-shaped
carving, representing
the history of the world.
In its centre
is the face of the sun god,
flanked by the four cartouches
which singly give the dates
of the four previous ages
of the world and together
represent the date
of our present era.
Historial accounts record
that the stone
was made in 1479 A.D.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
National Museum Anthropology, Chapultepec, Mexico
Masterpieces of ancient Mexico
ISCUSSING the richness
and diversity of Mexico's
ancient past, the noted Mexican scho¬
lar, Ignaz Bernai once wrote: "Just as
Western civilization is the sum total of
different national cultures, which we
now call Italian, French of Spanish
perhaps individually unintelligible,
but conjointly forming an intelligible
whole so the meso-American civili¬
zation is composed of former national
cultures Maya, Aztec, Zapotee,
among others which long ago came
from a single stock."
Some 11,000 archeological sites
have been found in Mexico, but it can
almost be said that archaeologists
have thus far barely scratched the sur
face. The people of Mexico were
incomparable architects and builders.
The British sculptor, Henry Moore,
once said that the conception of vol¬
ume and form in ancient Mexican art
has never been surpassed in the entire
history of sculpture in stone.
Pyramids and temples, massive fig¬
ures delicate statuettes hewn from jade
and marble, ceramics, works in terra
cotta, carved steles and painted mur¬
als these and many other works
have come down to us from Mexico's
past which goes back over 3,000 years.
Mexicans are now showing more
interest than ever before in their coun¬
try's past and are building museums to
house this unique heritage. Last year
in a single month no less than three
new museums devoted to pre-Colum¬
bian art were opened in the country.
One of these, the National Museum
of Anthropology in Mexico City's Cha¬
pultepec Park, former site of the Aztec
royal palace, has over 200,000 exhibits,
including what has been termed the
finest collection of pre-Columbian art
ever assembled. The second was ins¬
talled in the home of Mexican painter
Diego Rivera. It houses his immense
pre-Columbian collection which he
donated to the nation. ßl
The third museum was opened in
Teotihuacan, an ancient city in the
CONT'D ON PAGE 34
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
Photos © Gisèle Freund, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
THOUSAND AND ONE CHARACTERS
FROM THE HUMAN COMEDY
For nearly 2,000 years the pre-Columbian artists of central America
displayed extraordinary skill and imagination in modelling innumer¬
able figurines which record a thousand and one images from
everyday life. Sometimes with malice, sometimes ingenuously,
always with an astonishing vigour, they depict work, games, love,
motherhood, dancing. The acrobat (opposite page) is a vessel
modelled eight centuries before the Christian era by an artist of
Tlatilco in the Valley of Mexico; one leg twists over to touch his
head, the other serves as the mouth of the vase. The six figurines
below, 23 to 55 cm. (9 in. to 21 in.), were made by the Pacific Coast
civilization (Mexico) between the 4th and 13th centuries. A. D.
1 - Pelota player carrying a ball.
jL - Helmeted man brandishing a missile.
- Hunchback. Dwarfs and hunchbacks were often kept
at the courts of the "caciques" (chiefs) because they were
supposed to haye magic powers.
4 - A roguish-faced figure holding a long tube used to collect
agave juice from which an alcoholic drink was made.
D - A seated woman rests her chin on one knee.
O - Seated couples are favourite subjects. Here the man
places his arm affectionately around the woman.
"^Hí.
cy.
>1
p
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Gisèle Freund, Paris
Etienne Hubert, Paris
EAGLE KNIGHT
Below, head of an Eagle Knight,
a member of one of the great Aztec military orders.
He wears a helm shaped like
an eagle's head, a distinction reserved
for the famous warrior knights
of ancient Mexico (14th-16th centuries).
GOD OF SPRINGTIME
The Toltec civilization spread
over large areas of Mexico between
the 9th and 13th centuries. A.D., leaving
its imprint (the word "Toltec" signifies
"artist") on famous Maya cities such as Chichen
Itza and Uxmal. Left, head of
Xipe-Totec, the god who
symbolizes spring and seed time.
This 38 cm. (14 in.) fragment
of a terra cotta statue is now
in the Vienna Anthropological Museum, Austria.
BREASTPLATE OF GOLD
Right, breastplate in gold,
12 cm X 9 (5 in. X 3 i)
representing the god of the shades.
It was made by an artist
of the Mixtee people,
the great rivals of the Aztecs
who lived in the Oaxaca mountains
of central Mexico.
Mixtee artists probably
made the works which
Albrecht Dürer saw at Antwerp in 1520,
and which caused him to enthuse:
"I have seen the things
brought to the king from
the new land of gold...
Never in my life have
I seen anything that afforded
me so much pleasure.
These are astounding works of art,
and I was struck by the subtle genius
of the people in these strange lands."
© Gisèle Freund, Paris
ANCIENT MEXICO
(Continued from page 31)
Valley of Mexico, which attained its
zenith in the 2nd and 3rd centuries
A.D. only to decline and be abandoned
by its people towards the 10th century.
Teotihuacan with its mighty temple-
pyramids the Pyramid of the Sun,
65 metres (213 ft. high) and the Pyra¬
mid of the Moon, 42 metres (138 ft.)
covered an area of 142 square kilo¬
metre (54 sq. mi.). The cultural, reli¬
gious and historical fame of the city
continued long after Its decline and
fall. But it was not until 1905 that
archaeologists began systematic exca¬
vations. Today, completely uncovered
and restored, the centre appears much
as it must have done in the 3rd cen¬
tury.
In the course of these vast opera¬
tions innumerable works in stone and
ceramic were recovered. The works
will go into the Teotihuacan Museum,
itself a veritable museum-city in which
the painted murals now being removed
from Teotihuacan's walls will also be
placed.
Deeply conscious that its pre-Co¬
lumbian masterpieces are part of a uni¬
versal cultural heritage, Mexico is pre¬
serving them in its multiplying mu¬
seums, not as isolated relics of past
civilizations, but in their original ethnic
and social context one which gives
full meaning to their infinitely varied
forms of beauty. A few examples are
presented on these pages.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
im&&aalm?â
mÊHBOHKÊÊÊÊÊm
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE GULF STREAM
OF THE PACIFIC
by Konstantin Fedorov
On July 1, 1965, the first comprehensive multi-ship survey of the Kuroshio
Current in the Pacific Ocean began as part of the Co-operative Study of
the Kuroshio and Adjacent Regions undertaken by the Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission of Unesco. It is planned to carry on this
work over several years. Thirty-six research vessels from six countries
have undertaken the first phase of this study from July to October, thus
embarking on another large-scale international océanographie expedition
aimed at unravelling the secrets of the worlds' oceans. Scientific explo¬
ration of this part of the ocean will undoubtedly increase the economic
benefits to countries bordering it. It will also serve to develop scientific
potential of the region by stimulating broader scientific interest and stronger
national support for the programme. Delegates from the 54 member states
of the Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission met recently at
Unesco's H.Q. tc examine the first results of the Kuroshio study.
OST people are familiar with the famous
'oceanic current called the Gulf Stream and may
know that as it drifts eastwards across the Atlantic it
transports enormous quantities of warm water, thus serving
as a sort of "hot water bottle" for the whole of Europe.
Fewer are aware, however, that the Gulf Stream and the
temperature contrast it creates in the North Atlantic greatly
facilitate the formation of the atmospheric disturbances
known as cyclones which are of such concern to European
meteorologists.
It is perhaps strange, but true nevertheless, that even less
people have heard of the Gulf Stream's sister current in the
Pacific called the Kuroshio which, in its part of the world,
plays a role in many ways and for some nations even more
significant than that of the Gulf Stream in the Atlantic
area. Of course, my Japanese colleagues might point out
that there is hardly a schoolboy in Japan who does not
know about the Kuroshio, and this is true since the whole
life of this country depends on this strong and warm
oceanic current.
We are familiar from childhood with rivers and quite
naturally think that every river should have its shores.
The Gulf Stream and the Kuroshio are rivers without shores
great rivers in great oceans.
They are by no means undiscernable on the vast and
deceptive uniformity of the oceanic surface. Kuroshio is a
Japanese word meaning "black current." Seen from an
aeroplane it manifests itself by a sudden change in the
water's colour from azure to deep cobalt blue, almost ultra¬
marine. An observant passenger on a steamer seeing
nn KONSTANTIN FEDOROV is secretary of the Intergovernmental
¿g Océanographie Commission and director of the Office of Oceano¬
graphy at Unesco. A Soviet oceanographer, he has taken part
in many océanographie expeditions in the Arctic, Baltic and Medi-
' terranean seas and the Pacific and Indian oceans.
Arrow on map shows the course of the Kuroshio
Current in the Pacific Ocean to the south of Japan's coast¬
line, where its speed sometimes reaches 8 ft. a second.
flocks of sea birds on the water's surface would immedia¬
tely recognise the northern edge of the Kuroshio for, first
and foremost, an ocean current means "life."
In 1957, during the International Geophysical Year, I was
with a group of scientists looking for the Kuroshio aboard
the U.S.S.R. research ship "Vityaz". We were sailing
south along 150°W and had already left behind those lati¬
tudes where, according to all the textbooks, the Kuroshio
should have been found. Its absence was intriguing to say
the least. To our relief we came across it later, displaced
southward by a few hundred miles. As in many other
cases, the birds and flying fish were our first informers.
This shift southward of the Kuroshio was one additional
proof In the steadily accumulating facts showing that the
striking similarity in appearance between great oceanic
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Polychrome woodcut print of Mt.Fuji seen under the wavetops, executed by the great Japanese artist, Hokusai (1760-1849).
currents and ordinary rivers goes farther than simple poetic
metaphor. Like rivers on a plain, the Gulf Stream and
the Kuroshio are given to meandering through the oceans.
These meanders change their form and wander along the
stream in their own way, just as river meanders do, although
on a different time scale.
The speed of such an oceanic river as the Kuroshio is
quite amazing. While its average speed is slightly over one
metre per sec, its maximum speed south and east of
Japan sometimes attains as much as two and a half metres
per second which is comparable to the speed of many con¬
tinental rivers. This "river" is approximately 400 metres
(1,300 ft.) deep, 40 nautical miles wide, and transports an
average of about 50 million cubic metres of water per
second. To visualise this mass of water one would have
to join together about five thousand rivers as big as the
Volga.
Having read all these facts, the reader may think, "But
scientists seem to know quite a lot about the Kuroshio.
Why go to sea and study it, and even mobilize inter¬
national efforts for its scientific investigation?"
Well, at this point ends the poetic analogy between
rivers and oceanic currents. While we know for certain
that rivers flow down the slopes of continents, fed by
underground waters stored as a result of rainfall, nothing
as definite is known about oceanic currents except that
their major moving forces are the wind over the oceans
and dissimilarities in heat and salt distribution in oceanic
water.
Even this knowledge is not absolute, since any com¬
bination of these forces is possible and the forces of
friction and inertia, as well as the earth's rotation, also
affect oceanic currents in different and complicated ways,
making some of them strikingly similar (as the Gulf Stream
and the Kuroshio) and some of them totally different from
each other.
Again the reader might ask "Can currents in the
ocean be of different kinds?" They can, and to learn
their nature is a difficult task, still far from being solved.
It would perhaps be too technical to describe here what
we actually know with regard to the physical origin of the
so-called boundary currents such as the Kuroshio and the
Gulf Stream. So I will simply say that there already exists
a general hydrodynamical theory of boundary currents,
although the character of the complex interaction of the
forces mentioned above which can account for changes in
both transport and geographical position of the Kuroshio,
its meandering, and many other associated features is still
far from clear.
These changes are by no means insignificant. The
total transport of water, by the Kuroshio may deviate
by about 50% from the average figure of 50 million m3/sec
already mentioned. And no simple analogy with rivers,
which have a clearly seasonal cycle, is possible. Com¬
parison of the Kuroshio with the Gulf Stream, which would
involve looking closely at their similarities as well as their
differences, may help to throw some light on this problem.
Studying the dynamics of the Kuroshio could, of course,
be a purpose in itself, but it is not the only aim of the nn
Co-operative Study of the Kuroshio and Adjacent Regions "'
which started in July 1965 under the co-ordination of the
Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission. However,
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
GULF STREAM OF THE PACIFIC (cont'd)
The vagabond, bountiful stream
if we learn how to explain the behaviour of the Kuroshio,
we shall also learn how to predict it. As a consequence,
improved weather forecasting for the vast area influenced
by the Kuroshio and increased and predictable fishing
will become possible.
To ensure these benefits, complex studies of the Kuro¬
shio will need to be made covering all the appropriate
fields of knowledge, including meteorology, marine bio¬
logy and fisheries. Perhaps the greatest effort to be under¬
taken by the participating countries lies in the field of
fisheries research. But marine geophysics and marine
geology will not be neglected in view of the increasing
importance of mineral resources from the ocean.
I
38
have said that a current in the ocean means
"life". This implies that some parts of the
ocean may be more productive than others, just as are
different kinds of soils on the continents. The southern
edge of the Kuroshio, for example, marks a distinct boun¬
dary of a quite definite marine biological environment.
Numbers of commercially important species of fish, and
even whales, do not generally penetrate southward beyond
this boundary. Thus, this region of the Kuroshio offers local
fishermen a series of important fishing grounds which may
shift and change both in space and time.
To predict these changes careful studies will need to be
made of the influence of various environmental characteris¬
tics on fish behaviour through the whole reproduction cycle.
Thorough knowledge of changes in all the elements of
what is known as "food chains" in the ocean is also
very important. A programme of such studies for the
Kuroshio region, if written out in detail, would probably
occupy a thick volume in itself.
We have swung from a very theoretical interest in the
co-operative study of the Kuroshio to a very practical
approach to it. Between these two there is an enormous
number of scientific problems awaiting solution. Why, for
example, does an area of cold water form now and again
south of Japan between the main stream of the Kuroshio
and the coast and remain there for long periods, affecting
weather and fishing? Why does the Kuroshio penetrate the
East China Sea instead of following the Ryuku Islands chain
on their oceanward side? Why does the Kuroshio leave the
Japanese coast at approximately 35°N instead of following
it farther north?
Countless "whys" come to a scientist's mind when he
approaches a natural phenomenon of such magnitude as
the Kuroshio and, as his study proceeds, for every question
answered, ten new ones might appear.
Scientists look with expectation to the results which the
co-operative study of the Kuroshio will bring. New know¬
ledge is always exciting although perhaps quite a number
of years will pass before something really spectacular from
the layman's point of view will occur, either in terms of
scientific discovery or in terms of the application of this
new knowledge.
In this sense, the co-operative study of the Kuroshio
and the results which are expected have nothing in common
with those spectacular quasi-scientific projects reaching
us from the domain of science fiction where high oceanic
dams are built and warm waters of oceanic currents are
deflected to warm up countries suffering from the cold,
or to melt Arctic ice. It will be laborious work with slow
but sure progress a constant search for answers which
modern man dares to ask from nature.
International océanographie expeditions have become a
reality of our time since the International Geophysical Year
(1957-1958). It would perhaps be of interest to say a few
words as to how these expeditions are now being
organized.
Although the centre of the day-to-day co-ordinating
activities is' located in the secretariat of the Intergovern¬
mental Océanographie Commission in Unesco's headquar¬
ters, the soul and spirit of such an expedition is the inter¬
national co-ordinator appointed by the commission. He
must keep in constant touch with national co-ordinators of
participating countries and initiate important measures to
improve communications and the exchange of data and
information. He also serves as chairman of the international
co-ordination group which is the major planning mechanism
of an expedition.
Nor should one forget the data exchange system which
is a very essential element of the whole expedition and
which, in the case of the Kuroshio study, comprises not only
two World Data Centres (in Moscow and Washington)
but also a special Kuroshio Data Centre which has recently
been created in Japan.
The new international expedition has as its major
elements
: overall coverage of the whole vast system of the
Kuroshio by scientific observations from ships and shore
stations in different seasons,
continuous or regular (and frequent) observations in
selected areas representative in certain ways of the whole
system.
While the first approach will provide scientists with a
sort of "photographic picture" of the current, the second
will ensure liaison between successive "snapshots" and,
still more important, will enable scientists to study the
variability of the Kuroshio. When you realize that the
Kuroshio system spreads for thousands of kilometres, it is
easy to understand that, for a programme based upon the
above principles, many ships and many more scientists are
required. This explains the need for international co-opera¬
tion, for bringing together ships, scientists and experience.
Therefore, an international expedition is really the only
solution to this problem.
EIGHT years have passed since the International
Geophysical Year, and this year I was again
aboard a research vessel in the area where, in 1957,
"Vityaz" made its observations. This time the vessel was
"Atlantis II" of Woods Hole Océanographie Institution (USA)
one of the participants in the co-operative study of the
Kuroshio. Scientists aboard were aware of the work which
had been done there before by ships of other nations and
therefore the planning of new work proceeded on the basis
of knowledge already available. New instruments were
going down into the cobalt depths of the ocean, and from
these observations a new pattern was already emerging,
embodying in a single, coherent system the valuable infor¬
mation obtained from earlier research.
Aboard "Atlantis II", and no doubt also aboard many
vessels heading towards the open sea these days, there
was a feeling that the science of oceanography has
finally become truly international.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Illustration by Hans Erni,
from "Science",
the first of a series of eight volumes
composing an international compendium
of modern knowledge published by
the Macdonald Illustrated Library,
London, and Doubleday, New York.
Prepared by editorial
boards headed by such distinguished
scientists and scholars
as Sir Julian Huxley,
J. Bronowski, Sir Gerald Barry
and James Fisher,
the series has already been translated
into seven languages.
The artist and designer
is Hans Erni.
© Rathbone Books Ltd., London.
THE
STEP
TO
MAN
(Continued from page 9)
the reduction of the speed of change makes it easier for
the different generations to talk to each other again.
What will we do with our time in that leisured world?
Undoubtedly there will be still more travel and more vigour-
ous and daring outdoor recreation. Life will be dull other¬
wise. Perhaps thousands will climb Everest and millions will
ride dolphins. But I think the activities that will really begin
to bloom are the creative arts and education and science.
Not just Sunday painting, but Wednesday-Thursday-Friday-
Saturday-Sunday painting. Continual rebuilding of your own
home to your own taste, filling it with personal ingenuities
and bold designs, might become the fashionable thing to do.
And education and science may become activities for
everyone. Who kept up with the philosophers of the
French Enlightenment? The leisured classes of the drawing
rooms. Who did science, at first? Rich amateurs and
leisured clerics with an easy routine and the time to do
experiments. Already education and scientific research are
our fastest-growing industries. With pre-school enrichment
raising the level of intelligence, as some evidence now
indicates, perhaps increasing numbers will profit from
education all the way to the graduate level, and continuing
education for much of the population may become a lifelong
activity.
Likewise in science, many adults may fix up a laboratory
room in their houses, where they can work every day at
some scientific project, some study in crystallization or in
embryology or in teaching animals that could offer a life¬
time of unfolding discovery.
One other characteristic of a steady-state world that
deserves special mention is its requirement for a high
standard of social justice. If we survive at all, after this
great disturbing shock-front has faded into a phenomenon
of history, it can only be by working out a new attitude of
tolerance and mutual support for each other, between
coloured and white, between rich and poor, between
advanced nations and retarded ones. The unemployed, the
underprivileged, the underdeveloped, all the groups ne¬
glected 'or exploited by our present arrangements or con¬
demned to exclusion from our prosperity by the accident of
parentage or place of birth, form a perpetual seedbed for
spokesmen and would-be dictators whose juntas may take
over nuclear administration in the name of correcting these
wrongs.
Our failure to eradicate these evils depresses the
standard of living and shortens the probable "half-life" of
everyone. We are now realizing this, in the U.S. Congress
as well as in the councils of the world. What is fortunate
for us today is that our new understanding of the education¬
al and developmental basis of prosperity has made it
possible and profitable to cure these evils just at the instant
when our new weapons technology has made it absolutely
necessary to do so.
We can no longer afford poverty in the world if we ever
could. We can no longer afford ignorance or prejudice or
neglect. It is not so much that they are a sign of moral
wickedness as that they are a sign of incompetence in
design and administration. It is time to apply at least the
same standards of competence and satisfaction in running
the world that we apply in running a family or a business.
Any member of the world now not only deserves to be
shown, but must be shown, as surely as a member of a
rich man's family, how he can share in its abundance. Any
child in the world now not only deserves to have education,
but must have education, like a privileged child, for the full QQ
development of his potentialities from the age of one yearUJ
on up. It is necessary not only because we can afford it
but because we must afford it.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
THE STEP TO MAN (Cont'd)
A new knowledge and new biology
40
The world has now become too dangerous for anything
less than Utopia.
Will it all be static in this strange new world of the
steady state? The answer is no, nothing will be static.
What will begin to be steady is our acceptance of these
new ways of creative leisure and interaction as being the
most interesting and most satisfying ways of life. But all
our indices of flow, production, commerce, communication,
will be up from what they are now. The marvelous
accomplishments of a mature and integrated society will
be just beginning. And two fields, scientific knowledge and
biological technology, will surely go on changing and
developing indefinitely.
I see no end to the increase of knowledge. When scien¬
tific research has as many men and as much money every
year as society can afford, it will be adding even more
rapidly than now to our knowledge of nature and to the
ease with which we can control nature. And this world of
nature is infinite to us, for it includes the human brain
itself. After all the myriad galaxies of the astronomers are
charted as well as we want to chart them, we will still go
on studying the multimyriad complexities of the brain that
has measured them.
UR knowledge of nature will surely be used
increasingly for the improvement and variation
of our biological apparatus for living. If we can actually
set up a social structure that will enable us to live together
without killing ourselves, for a thousand years or a million
years a time as long as the time since man began it
will begin to give us the time we need to understand and
develop our full biological potentialities.
Things we now cut out of the human body by surgery
the appendix, the tonsils can they be eliminated from the
hereditary genes instead? Our eyes and ears that give out
when we are old, our hearts and arteries why not make
them better biologically from the beginning rather than by
doctoring after they begin to fail? We begin to see the
possibility of reshaping the human organism, as we have
been reshaping plant and animal organisms now for many
years, into a new form or into many new forms that will
begin to show the full potentialities of protoplasm and the
creative brain.
In such a time, man will cease to be at the mercy of the
evolutionary accidents that made his frame and his society
just as he has ceased to be at the mercy of the biological
accidents that made his diseases. It will be a time when
man can begin to plan what he wants man to be, as each
individual makes his personal plans today a time when
accident and drift will finally begin to be replaced by
conscious human values and decisions.
The accelerating powers and dangers and hammer-blow
stresses of these days make us anxious and afraid. But
I think it is clear that if we survive this shock-front, this
roaring waterfall of change, we could be within sight of
what Churchill once called the "sunlit uplands".
Various metaphors could be used to describe the situa¬
tion. In many ways, it is like a child learning to ride a
bicycle. There you were, up until that day, riding on the
three-wheeler where you couldn't hurt yourself very much.
But then you get the two-wheeler, and it seems terribly
scary, and perhaps you fall and skin a knee or an elbow.
But you get up again, and your father holds the handlebars,
running along beside you, and suddenly you are riding
alone.
At one instant you are incompetent, falling to one side
or the other and steering wrong, and the next instant it
comes right and you are in control, safe and balanced not
because you are fearful and slow but because you are
going faster than ever. Wobbling and weaving but neverthe
less choosing your own path and balancing safely at every
turn. So, I think, in 30 or 40 years, if we survive, the human
race will come through this time of wobbling conflict and
uncertainly and falling, and will suddenly be riding in its
own chosen direction, free, as only a co-ordinated and
confident organism can be.
To say it another way, it is like the time of adolescence,
when the teenager suddenly changes, with some thrashing
about, from the dependent child to the independent man.
Or it is like the moment of birth, full of pain and danger as
the baby in the womb is suddenly pushed through into a
new life where he must breathe alone and learn to walk and
talk and think. Or it is like the moment of metamorphosis
of the insect, when there is an incomprehensible swelling
and dizzy changes of shape and desire in the tight cocoon,
until suddenly it bursts open at the end of its own sharp
S-curve, its own era of change, to reveal an unimagined
transformation to a new free winged life.
This is the meaning of the leveling off of our S-curves.
We are now nearing the end of the era of change. We
have been isolated human beings, selfish, combative, igno¬
rant, helpless. But now for several hundred years the great
evolutionary hormones of knowledge and technology have
been pressing us, almost without our understanding it, into
power and prosperity and communication and interaction,
and into increasing tolerance and vision and choice and
planning pressing us, whether we like it or not, into a
single co-ordinated humankind.
The scattered and competing parts are being bound
together. Everywhere now we begin to see men and
nations beginning the deliberate design of development
with a growing confidence in the choice and creation of
their own future. The exponential changes have burst apart
our ancient attitudes and structures, and our failure to
adjust to this may yet kill us, but if we are wise and
energetic and understand our own nature and purposes
well enough to restructure and control these dangers,
mankind may emerge very quickly into co-ordinated forms
such as it has never known before. Our drastic changes
will not go on forever. They are converging to a limit.
It was implicit in the biological material all along, as surely
as the butterfly is implicit in the caterpillar. We have been
men. We are emerging into Man.
ET no analogy, not even that of metamorpho¬
sis, quite captures the suddenness and radi-
calness, the really complete restructuring, of the transfor¬
mation ahead. If the 2,000 million years of life are repre¬
sented by the 200-foot height of, say, the Rockefeller
Chapel at Chicago, the million years of man make a 1-inch
block on top of the chapel. The 20,000 years of agricul¬
ture make a thick postage stamp on top of that, and the
400 years of science make the ink on top of the postage
stamp.
Now, suddenly, we see what all this has been building up
to; and it is about to come within a single generation or
two that is, in the thickness of the film of moisture on top
of the ink on the postage stamp. In that short time we
will move, If we survive the strain, to a wealthy and powerful
and co-ordinated world society reaching across the solar
system, a society that might find out how to keep Itself
alive and evolving for thousands or millions or billions of
years, a time as long as all of evolution past. It is a tre¬
mendous prospect.
Hardly anyone has seen the enormous sweep and
restructuring and unity and future of it except perhaps
dreamers like H. G. Wells or Teilhard de Chardin. It is a
quantum jump. It is a new state of matter. The act of saving
ourselves, if it succeeds, will make us participants in the
most incredible event in evolution. It is the step to Man.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
LEFT HAND, RIGHT HAND
Sir,
In your issue of March 1965 on
page 19 you state, regarding Leonardo
da Vinci: "the inventor took precau¬
tion to write his scientific notes so
that they could only be deciphered
when reflected in a mirror." May I
point to the fact that Leonardo's so-
called "mirror-writing" was scarcely
a "precaution". He wrote everything
in this way but simply due to the fact
that he was left-handed. And for a
left-handed person writing from right
to left is much easier than our normal
direction.
In the drawing on the same page
it is clearly to be seen that the
hatching in his sketches is equally in
the opposite direction to what a right-
handed person would have done:
Leonardo hatches from top left to
down-right.
H. Friedlaender
Jerusalem, Israel
RACIALISM ISSUE
...Your issue on race and racialism
(April 1965) ranks with those on the
cost of world armaments, on human
rights and on illiteracy, among many
others, as an important contribution
towards real peace and better inter¬
national understanding. With this issue
the Courier attained even higher
standards by drawing attention to an
anachronistic and immoral situation
that exists in the mid-20th century.
Aureliano Veloso
Porto, Portugal
... One is forced to agree with the
economic measures recommended by
the General Assembly and the U.N.
group of specialists, for what I would
call "an economic blockade with huma¬
nitarian aims." But should not South
Africa also be isolated politically? The
African countries, which are directly
concerned with and deeply conscious
of the problem of freeing their "racial
brothers", realized this when they
met at the Conference of Heads of
State at Addis Ababa in 1963. Other
countries, having approved the Uni¬
versal Declaration of Human Rights,
should follow this example, and sever
diplomatic relations with the South
African Government.
Gilbert Renard
Brussels, Belgium
... Bravol to the Courier for dealing
with a problem as topical as this and
for exposing a serious violation of
human rights.
D.D. Krivorucho
Lomas de Zamora
Argentina
... I deplore much of the present
South African Government's racial
policies, but I believe in being truthful,
and both the picture and caption on
page 29 of the April issue appear to
give a totally misleading and false
impression. In the first place the pic¬
ture shows a building remarkably Jike
the Ernest Oppenheimer Hospital in
Welkom, 200 miles from Johannesburg.
Secondly, I have seen similar groups
of Africans as they appear after having
just arrived by plane (as many do
from the neighbouring northern coun¬
tries) to work on contract in the gold
mines where they receive training and
care superior to anything provided in
the purely industrial areas of Johannes¬
burg. Furthermore these men both
in the mines and in industry do have
a choice of work although this is
somewhat limited.
The Ernest Oppenheimer Hospital is
the largest native industrial hospital
in South Africa and was opened in
1952 to serve the native employees
of five mines in the Welkom, Orange
Free State area. It has 800 beds and
is staffed, equipped and operated at
a very high standard indeed.
N.V. Baldwin
Ringwood, England
... No one who reasons intelligently
can accept the idea of white racial
supremacy... all men have the right
to live in full independence, free of
all tutelage, free to develop the re¬
sources of their soil, free, above all,
to educate themselves.
F. Brunet
Grenoble, France
UNITED RELIGIONS
ORGANIZATION
In a world slowly growing to unity
there is not only a want of co¬
operation of peoples (international
solidarity) but also a want of co¬
operation of religions (interreligious
solidarity).
Next to the United Nations where
international deliberation on the
highest level has been taking place for
the past 20 years it seems to me it
would be useful to found a United Re¬
ligions Organization (U.R.O.) consist¬
ing of representatives chosen by the
great world religions for interreligious
deliberation on the highest level.
H. Spitzen
The Hague, Netherlands
DESTRUCTIVE PLAYTHINGS
Sir.
Women in Australia are concerned
at the prevalence of war and horror
toys for children. Protests by our
organization forced a large chain store
to withdraw its nation-wide window
display of jungle warfare toys. A
member of parliament protested to the
government about a T.V. advertise¬
ment of playthings featuring horror and
violence and had this particular adver¬
tisement withdrawn. A Committee For
Creative Toys has been formed in
Sydney to inspect toys and to advise
and encourage shops to stock
constructive instead of destructive
toys.
We have heard that, women in Eng¬
land, United States, France and some
Scandanavian countries are also
worried by the toys being offered to
children. Therefore we feel that the
matter of children's toys is now an
international one and that toys which
condition children's minds to accept
war and violence as an inevitable and
even desirable part of life are a viola¬
tion of Principle 10 of the U.N. Decla¬
ration of the Rights of the Child.
We would like the Unesco Courier
to investigate children's playthings
throughout the world and show which
will distort a child's mind and which
will prepare him to live in friendship
with his fellow men. We also think
that governments should be known
according to the training they give the
future citizens of the world.
Freda Brown
National Secretary
Union of Australian Women
Sydney, New South Wales
HUNGER FOR KNOWLEDGE
Sir,
I enclose 180 Viet-Nam piastres for
a subscription to the Courier. I'll let
you in on a secret I had to go
without breakfast for more than a
month to save this small sum. If there
should be any money left over, please
send me an interesting booklet on
science.
Hô Binh-An
Saigon, Republic of Viet-Nam
COURIER IN CURACO
Sir,
It is my intention in co-operation
with a few journalist friends, to pre¬
pare a booklet, chiefly containing
translations in Papiamento, our local
language, of articles which appeared
in the July-August edition of the Cou¬
rier on youth. Our idea is to circulate
this booklet in our island at this very
appropriate time in a large quantity,
say 20 to 30 thousand copies for a
total population of about 135 000.
Hector G. Suares
Curaçao, Netherlands Antilles
LITTLE-KNOWN PEOPLES
Sir,
We are already well-enough informed
about Italian, French, Greek and English
cultures, and those of the other "big
nations". We learned about them at
school and university and now hear
about them from the cinema and on
radio and television. But what is
known about the cultures of the Tur¬
kish or Ugro Finnish populations of
the Soviet Union: the Tatar, Bashkir,
Uzbek, Kazakh, Kirghis, Turkmen, Azer¬
baijan, Kumyk, Chuvash, Mari, Mordo¬
vian and Údmurt peoples, to name
only some? Almost nothing, I am sure.
i should like to read more in your
magazine about "unknown" peoples
such as the Indians of North America,
the forgotten peoples of South Ame¬
rica, the Kurds and the Berbers, and
the Pushtu of Pakistan. I should also
like the world to become familiar with
my own country and with its culture,
past and present.
Nourihan Fattah
Kazan, U.S.S.R.- 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New:
STUDENTS ABROAD: Some 290,000 stu¬
dents2% of the world's student popu¬
lation were studying abroad in 1964
according to the latest edition of Unesco's
publication, "Study Abroad". The U.S.A.
had the most foreign students (over 74,000),
followed by France (30,000), the Federal
Republic of Germany (25,000), the U.S.S.R.
(21,000) and the U.K. (14,000 in universities
and university colleges alone).
I NDIA'S NEW FISHERIES: An Indo-Nor-
I wegian project to develop India's south
coast fisheries has set up six fishing sta¬
tions with boat-building yards, ice factories,
freezing plants and insulated vans since
1952. The Norwegian Agency for Interna¬
tional Development is now compiling the
first fishing chart of the west coast of
India from data supplied by Indian sources
and research vessels of the International
Indian Ocean Expedition.
DEATH ON THE ROADS: In the past ten
years the annual road accident death
rate has more than doubled in many coun¬
tries. In 1962 U.S. traffic accidents killed
40,000 people twice as many as died from
infectious diseases. Ways and means to
halt this rising toll were recently reviewed
and assessed by traffic experts from
23 countries at a special seminar convened
in Alexandria by WHO.
WATER UNDER DESERTS: All of Saudi
Arabia, an area as large as western
Europe, is short of water, yet under its
deserts lie reservoirs of water which will
meet the country's needs for many years,
report water development experts of FAO.
42
POPULATION PROBLEMS
AND DEVELOPMENT
POPULATION TRENDS AND DEVELOPMENT
UNITED NATIONS
The latest U.N. commemorative
stamp focuses attention on the impor¬
tance of the world's population growth
and the urgent problems it raises for
economic and social development.
Population problems were recently
examined in a world-wide perspective
by a conference under U.N. auspices
held in Belgrade Yugoslavia. The
new U.N. stamp is issued in 4, 5 and
11 cent denominations. As agent in
France of the U.N. Postal Administra¬
tion, Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks
all U.N. stamps and first day covers
currently on sale. For further details
write to The Unesco Philatelic Ser¬
vice, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7).
These vast underground reserves," as well
as general land and water reserves are
now being investigated under'an agreement
between Saudi Arabia and FAO.
PEOPLE'S UNIVERSITIES: Some two mil¬
lion persons now attend 10,000 adult
evening courses in Soviet "People's Uni¬
versities". This represents*a fifty per cent
increase in the number of evening schools
opened in the past three years. Students
come from every walk of life and are of
all ages.
ALPHABETS FOR 700 LANGUAGES: The
Institute of Linguistics, a U.S. -based
international association of linguists, plans
to produce an alphabet and basic literature
for all the estimated 700 or more unwritten
languages used by the peoples of New
Guinea. Two-person teams from the insti¬
tute do repeated six-month periods of duty
with tribal groups, learning their languages
and customs and working out systems of
writing for them.
TRAINING THE SEISMOLOGIST: Twenty-
two trainees from 12 countries have
begun their courses at the International
Institute of Seismology and Earthquake En¬
gineering in Tokyo, operated by Japan's
Ministry of Construction and Unesco,
with funds from the Government of Japan
and the U.N. Special Fund. The Institute
gives advanced training in seismology and
earthquake engineering to scientists and
engineers from countries in seismic areas
where earthquake measuring and reporting
are not yet fully developed.
RESEARCH FOR PEACE: A proposal to
put scientific methods of amassing and
evaluating information to work in one of
the few domains where they have not yet
been applied international relations and
the preservation of peace is made in a
recent issue (Vol. XVII, N° 3, 1965) of the
Unesco quarterly, "International Social
Science Journal". In this issue, devoted
to peace research, Professor Kenneth Boul¬
ding, Research Director of the Centre for
Research on Conflict Resolution, at the Uni¬
versity of Michigan (U.S.A.), proposes a
world-wide system of social-data collecting
stations which would transmit information
to be centrally processed in much the same
way that information collected at meteoro¬
logical stations is processed into weather
maps and predictions.
WEATHER WATCH FROM SPACE: Late
this year or early in 1966 the Ameri¬
can "Tiros" satellite system will start to
provide cloud cover pictures of every spot
on earth at least once a day, reports the
World Meteoroligical Organization. The
satellite will orbit the earth every 113 mi¬
nutes at an altitude of 750 miles. Data will
be received and analyzed by the World
Meteorological Centres, of which three
have now been designated Moscow,
Washington and Melbourne as part of the
World Weather Watch.
MOBILIZING FOR LITERACY: In Mexico,
1 1 ,000 literacy centres have now been
established by the federal government while
state and municipal governments support a
further 2,870, and private enterprise 2,200.
Teachers and students from training colle¬
ges are being enrolled as instructors, and
over 34 million free textbooks have been
distributed in the past nine months alone.
ANEW NOAH'S ARK: Over 1,000 ani¬
mals, including the world's two lar¬
gest the 100-ft., 160-ton blue whale and
the smaller fin whale are in danger of
becoming extinct according to the World
Wildlife Fund. In a recent report (x) on its
world campaign for nature conservation
between 1962 and the end of 1964, the
Fund says that national appeals raised
£675,000 ($1,900,000) for this work.
(x) "The Launching of a New Noah's
Ark", Collins, London, 13/6, obtainable
from 2 Caxton St., Westminster, London.
SCIENCE FORUM FOR YOUTH: Young
people from 27 countries had lively
discussions on topics such as "nuclear
energy do the gains outweigh the risks?",
at the Seventh International Youth Science
Fortnight held recently in London. Lec¬
tures, seminars and scientific and cultural
visits were also features of this event
now a popular annual rendezvous for
scientifically-minded younsters from many
nations.
A CORRECTION: In our March 1965
issue we quoted a series of statements
made by delegates to the Unesco General
Conference in 1964. In the item on Cuba
we stated that the number of classrooms
in Cuba had increased by 5,000 since 1958.
This figure was erroneous and should have
read 20,000. At the General Conference
on October 23, 1964, Dr Armando Hart,
Minister of Education of Cuba, had in
effect said: "Before the Cuban revolution
there were 700,000 pupils registered in
primary schools; this figure has now risen
to 1,280,000 pupils. Before the Revolution
there were about 15,000 primary school
classrooms in existence; five years later,
in the school year 1963-64, this number
had increased by 20,000." Cuba's Nation¬
al Literacy Campaign began in 1961.
Flashes . . .
Polio is on the way out in every country
where mass vaccination has been applied
over the last ten years, reports WHO. In
1964 the U.S.A. had only 121 cases com¬
pared with 38,476 in 1954.
Singapore became Unesco's 120th mem¬
ber state on October 28.
The British Government is to grant the
National Institute of Adult Education up
to Z11 ,000 to finance an investigation into
the standard of adult education in Britain.
Unesco is to launch a six-year pilot pro¬
ject in teaching by television on the univer¬
sity level in Poland, in co-operation with
the government.
An "alarming increase" in deaths from
lung cancer in Europe and North America
is reported by WHO. In the ten years ending
1962 death rates more than doubled in
many European countries and rose by 60 %
in the U.S.A.
<
O
z
<
o
a:
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1965
January
MONUMENTS IN PERIL. Campaign to protect our cultural heritage
Science of conservation (H. Plenderleith) Venice, a sinking
city (P. Gazzola) Care of old paintings Aphrodite's city resusci¬
tated (colour pages) Map of Unesco conservation Stones also die
(R. Sneyers) Angkor, before, after Menace of the bulldozers
(J. Brew) Message to young people (R. Maheu).
February
SCIENCE AND THE COMMON MAN. Gulf between scientists and
society: Part one (R. Calder) Semantics and culture (S. Fersh)
World Population, Year 2000 Sanctuaries astride frontiers (F. Bour-
lière) Unesco and nature conservation What TV does to children
(W. Schramm) Coins, ambassadors of art (O. Wenger).
March
TEACHING MACHINES. Pros and cons (T. Morello) International
Co-operation Year International science (N. Sissakian) World
educational progress Science and the common man; Part two
(R. Calder) Leonardo da Vinci's inventions Battle against small¬
pox Jenner, father of vaccination.
April
RACE AND PREJUDICE. Biology and race (G. Debetz) Statement
on race Future of homo sapiens (J. Hiernaux) Mendel, father
of genetics (J. Rostand) Apartheid in South Africa.
May
ENGINEERS IN INDIA (V. Javoronkov) Bombay Institute (D. Behr-
man) Telecommunications 1865-1965 Caravaggio (colour pages)
History of Mankind: Ancestors of ball-point pen (L. Pareti); First
wheelbarrow (L. Petech); Town planning in Rome (M. Frederiksen).
June
STEPS IN SPACE. My first steps in space (A. Leonov) Asian
Highway (M. Ahmad) Jaipur Observatory Mohenjo Daro threat¬
ened (H. Plenderleith, C. Voute and Th. de Beaufort) Mystery
of Mohenjo Daro (M. Brion).
July-August
YOUTH WITH A PURPOSE. An explosion of vitality (P. François)
Global network of youth hostels Community service in Peru
(E. Barclay) Château de Guise rescued First Fair Play Trophy
American teen-agers in a grown-up world Young lifesavers of
Australia Poetry of Egyptian tapestries: colour pages (R. Wissa Was-
sef) Growing science club movements (F. Wattier) French
science club astronauts Junior Swiss archaeologists Japanese
lad creates "flying saucer" aeroplane Architecture from the young
Spartakiad sport festival 1,000 million under-25s (A. Deleon)
Three nations join hands in one camp (M. Rose) Volunteer-built
hospital in Nigeria Two dozen countries create international peace
corps (A. Gillette) Ballet of World Fraternity Changing Soviet
youth, a new generation of builders (Y. Kotier) Unesco and youth.
September
THE REVOLUTION IN BOOKS. Paperback revolution (R. Escarp»)
Author and public 12 countries produce two-thirds of world's books
Hispanic book market Books printed with a camera Unesco
and books (J. Behrstock) Publishing in South Asia (O. Prakash)
Publishing in Africa (C. Fyle).
October
GLOBAL DEVELOPMENT: TURNING POINT (U Thant) New Stra¬
tegy for development (R. Maheu) Technical co-operation (D. Owen)
The Great Revolution (W. Lippmann) Science, a new social force
(M. Millionshchikov) Unesco Technical Assistance.
November
MENACE OF THE ART THIEVES. Thief-proofing our art museums
(R. Le Blanc) Interpol warning system Mona Lisa protection
57 paintings lost in one robbery Havoc wrought by vandals The
volcano Irazu (H. Tazieff) Dismantling Abu Simbel (L. Christophe)
World congress on illiteracy.
December
THE LATITUDES OF ART. Latitudes of beauty (8 pages In colour):
Africa (M. Leiris) Oceania (F. Girard) Pre-Columbian America
(H. Lehmann) Masterpieces of Ancient Mexico The limits of
scientific expansion (J.R. Piatt) The Kuroshio, Gulf Stream of the
Pacific (K. Federov).
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 1 09 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
'Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
ßoek-handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only: Louis De Lannoy,
11 2, rue du Trône, Brussels S. CCP 3 380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
(	). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
(8 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 13/50). CHINA. World Book CoLtd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite-
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks¬
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S (D. Kr.",17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja¬
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7". CCP.
12598-48. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R.Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren¬
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road. Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura,
P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicoi
Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1:17 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 13;Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot:. Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New Delhi 3.
(Rs.7). INDONESIA. P.T.N." Permuta-Nusantara" c/o
Dept.of Commerce, 22, DjalanNusantara, Djakarta. IRAQ.
Mackenzie'sBookshop.Baghdad.IRELAND.The National
Press, 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbndge, Dublin. 4. (1 5/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O.Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. BahousS Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (10/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd. .Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 0/-). MONACO. British
Library 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus N¡¡hoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokh|ornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteratur Tieneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks
115 (17.50 kr.).' PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, and Educational Supply Co., Colonial Mutual
Building Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publi¬
cations : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1 211 .Geneva 1 1.CC.P. 1-23 6. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala (1 0/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-
50). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 St. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 3 4th St, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaia Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Kn-
¡ïg, Tzrazij« 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
The magazine :í
of international l$-l
science & culture !ll
. v.:»
Send a gift subscription
to all your friends
Annual subscription
15/stg.
$3.00 (Canada)
10 F (France)
Single copies
1/6 stg.
30 cents
I F
See address of distributor in your country overleaf
PUBLISHED
IN
English, French,
Spanish, Russian,
German, Arabic,
Japanese, Italian.
Lornere
]]>
</page>
</document>
