<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078417eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
G í
Courier
j7ThB "*" 1
1 9 5 9
(/2th year)
Price: 1/-stg. (U.K.)
W
J 30 ce Bi't»-»
1 60 fra ncs (France)
1'
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
1er
JUNE 1959
12TH YEAR
Contents A
A
A
e
o
A
PAGE
4 TOWARDS A WORLD HIGHWAY
By W. H. Owens
II CARAVAN ROUTES TO LIVE AGAIN
14 CAN WE SOLVE OUR TRAFFIC BOTTLENECKS?
By Henri Walter
16 WHOSE FAULT IS IT?
The chief causes of road accidents
20 PEDESTRIANS, LOOK OUT!
21 DRIVERS, WATCH YOUR SPEED
Think in feet per second not miles per hour
22 THE ROYAL HIGHWAY OF THE INCAS
By Jorge Carrera Andrade
27 CARTOONS BY SINE
Other articles
COVER PHOTO
USIS
28 LANGUAGE: KEY FACTOR OF INTEGRATION IN ISRAEL
By Pierre Vernier
29 A REACTOR NAMED WATER NYMPH
India's expanding nuclear research.
By Victor Hari
31 BULLS DO NOT SEE RED
Colour sense in the animal world.
By David Gunston
33 LETTERS TO EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM1
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (I 2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 59.1.137 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00; I 0/-stg. ; 4 00 Fr. frs. or equivalent.
N° 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TOWARDS A WORLD
HIGHWAY
by
W.H. Owens
© Almasy, Paris
Good roads are much more than efficient traffic
pavements. They link the nations and their
different ways of life, stimulate trade and travel,
and so help to advance the cause of international
understanding. The modern highway engineer, as he
conquers Nature's barriers and brings peoples closer
together, is making a really important and lasting
contribution towards World peace and prosperity.
Highway construction on a fast growing scale is in
progress in every continent today. Road teams are taming
the wilderness, stretching the frontiers of civilization, and
bringing remote and hitherto untapped areas of the
Earth's natural riches under development. As motor
transport replaces pack and draught animals in backward
territories, the primitive trackways and dirt roads of
tradition are being changed into all-weather surfaced
highways.
Great international projects like the Pan-American
Highway, the Trans-African Highway and the London-
Baghdad Highway are bringing the dream of a global
motor route nearer to fulfilment.- The time is surely
approaching when motorists will be able to drive round
the world on these trans-continental roads, stretching
from sea to sea and linked up across the oceans by a
network of air ferries.
Threading its way among peoples, scenery and climate
as diverse as any on Earth is the 15,000-mile Pan-American
Highway the world's longest road system. This is not a
single ribbon of road, but a super-international network
that includes the principal highways of all the countries
and states from Alaska south to the Argentine. There is
no specified route through the United States, for example,
because any one of a number of interlocking State and
national highways can be used to reach the Pan-American
system in Mexico or Alaska.
Over a century has passed since the U.S. statesman
Henry Clay first proposed a hemispheric road to unite the
Americas. Far ahead of his time he realised the
tremendous influence that such a highway could have on
the economic and cultural relations of the "Western
Hemisphere. Its importance is infinitely greater today
with the increasing development in Latin-American
countries.
By far the greater part of the Fairbanks-Buenos Aires
route has been open for years. Now road crews, backed
by further U.S. loans, are working with heavy mobile
equipment to pave the last, but most difficult, stretches
through the Central American Republics. These gaps
together total only 500 or 600 miles. But climate and
terrain in Guatemala, Costa Rica, Panama and neighbour
states have created vast problems and hazards, slowing
down the work. Sometimes the laborious work of years
has been destroyed by torrential rains in as many days.
This happened in 1955 on the Cartago-San Isidro stretch
Sine © THE UNESCO COURIER
Dangerous curves.
in Costa Rica, where 500,000 cubic, yards of volcanic soil
was washed right out of the newly laid road foundations.
No other continuous land route in the world can surpass
America's hemispheric road for spectacular and contrast¬
ing scenes. The Highway crosses the desolate frozen
wilderness, sun-baked deserts and the horizon-Wide
pampas; plunges through deep canyons and steaming
tropical jungles; winds up and down the escarpments of
mighty mountain ranges, 14,000 to 15,000 feet above sea
level. It enters the polar regions in Alaska and crosses
the equator in Ecuador. In Mexico and further south,
the Pan-American route runs hundreds of miles over
desert country where local Indian communities follow the
same primitive pattern of life as the white man found
when first he set foot in the Americas.
Some of the most important highway developments
outside America today are in progress in Africa, where,
despite rapidly changing conditions in the economic field,
communications are still among the most primitive in
the world. Thousands upon thousands of miles of bush
and jungle trackways form an intricate web over the
interior of Africa, linking village with village and pointing
out the safer paths.
But the motor vehicle has made its impact on that great
continent as everywhere else, and modern road transport
the key to future development cannot function efficiently
on routes that are extremely hazardous, and often im¬
passable, in the rainy season. This and the need for direct
links between new areas of production and markets have
made the construction of long-distance surfaced roads an
urgent matter. Prospects for African inter-territorial
trade are quite unlimited provided a modern system of
roads is built to carry it.
African transport conferences since World War II have
discussed the problem of long-distance motor highways.
The first steps towards an integrated network were taken
at the African Transport Conference at Johannesburg1 in
1950, where a number of primary routes linking the
various territories were worked out in some detail. Dele¬
gates agreed that the inter-territorial routes should per¬
mit safe travel at an average speed of 40 miles per hour.
Present road building operations inside Africa are widely
scattered, unrelated and planned primarily to serve new
CONTINUED ON PAGE 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Th*î Unesco Courier. June 1959
© Paul Almasy, Paris
NIGHTRIDE. Streaming south from Paris down the main highway to the Mediterranean coast, night-riding automobiles leave
a dazzling pathway of light as the beams of their headlamps are captured by a long photographic exposure. With 650,000 km. of
main and secondary roads and 119 km. per 100 sq.km. of surfaced roads, France has the highest density of roads In the world. Since
recent reconstruction work has been carried out, network is valued at £7,000 millionone-tenth of the country's total assets.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
HIGHWAY
(Continued)
1923 : THE MOTORWAY
IS BORN IN ITALY
mining, forestry, agricultural or irrigation projects.
Eventually, however, they will gradually become merged
together as part of a through continental highway system.
At the northern end of the future Trans-African route,
great highway improvements were made by Allied troops
in World War II. They completed the long Mediterranean
coast road from Tangier to Alexandria, while inland heavy
transport roads were laid over some of the traditional
camel tracks. So today there are two or three long¬
distance highways pushing southward across the Sahara
and the Sudan into the heart of Africa.
In May, 1957, the African Regional Road Congress met
at Salisbury, Southern Rhodesia, and was attended by
delegates and observers from East, Central and South
Africa, the Belgian Congo, Portuguese Africa and the
United Kingdom. Discussions centred on the £10-£15
million scheme to modernize the Cape-Nairobi Highway
the backbone of future long-distance transport in Africa
over its entire length, and to develop the necessary' link
and feeder roads into adjacent Belgian and Portuguese
territories.
The tremendous value of this trunk route for stimulating
the flow of inter-territorial trade was emphasized by
Congress speakers. A South African delegate estimated
that if the Cape-Nairobi Highway was brought up to
international heavy duty standards, trade between the
Union and East and Central Africa could alone increase
to some £250 million within the next decade.
A particularly difficult section of the Nairobi highway
was recently completed in the wilds of Northern Rhodesia,
between Chirundu and Lusaka. These 94 miles run
through steep mountains and densely wooded valleys, then
drop 3,000 feet into the Zambezi lowlands.
Maintenance camps had to be set up at frequent
intervals along the route to service heavy road-making
machinery working under abnormal strain, and four
wayside stone quarries supplied materials. The immense
problems created by the rough terrain, uncertain climate
and utter remoteness of the site were overcome only by
the most detailed organization combined with excellent
teamwork between Europeans and Africans.
Africans themselves are playing a big part in the
construction of highways and bridges, and work with
great keenness and enthusiasm side by side with European
engineers and technicians. At Tala, in the hills east of
Nairobi, the Kenya Road Authority has established a
training school where young Africans from many different
tribes learn all about modern road construction and how
to handle heavy mobile machinery. After a six months'
course they emerge as qualified road supervisors and plant
operators. Equipped with their newly-acquired skill they
return. to their own districts to take a responsible part in
turning bush tracks and game trails into all-weather
roads that will make Kenya's new farmlands more
accessible to the markets and railheads.
In Europe the most significant road development has
been the super highway, or motorway, designed and built
especially for the needs of motor traffic. (Such highways
are most common in the United States, of course, where
thousands of miles of them have been constructed over
the past thirty years.)
The first motorways in Europe were built by the Italian
Government as early as 1923, but these autostrade made
no provision for dividing the opposite traffic streams. It
was in Germany and Holland that motorways with
separate carriageways, grade separation and full control
of access were developed; the first of the famous German
autobahnen built . on such lines, between Bonn and
Cologne, was completed in 1932.
Germany's autobahnen have been described as the
most beautiful motor roads in the world. No effort was
spared to. make them so without affec'ting their high
standard of safety, and efficiency. In scenic areas like the
Black Forest and the Bavarian Alps, landscape architects
were employed to adapt the alignment of the new
motorways in harmony with the changing scenery.
Ever since the war Western Germany- has been pressing
ahead with the task of completing the national autobahn
programme that was interrupted in 1939. She plans to
double her pre-war 1,200-mile autobahnen network in the
next ten to fifteen years. In 1956 the West Germans spent
£29 million on new autobahnen alone. In 1957 the figure
rose to about £52 million, and in a few years expenditure
on new highways of all kinds, including improvements to
existing roads, will be averaging about £125 million a year. .
Other countries of Western Europe are also gradually
extending their motorway mileage.
The Netherlands has over 400 miles of motorways
completed or under construction, and another 600 miles
are planned. The Dutch spent nine and a half million
pounds on motorway construction alone in 1956.
France is planning to build 1,000 miles of motorways and
150 miles of other main roads at a cost of some £300
million. Between 40 and 50 miles of French motorways,
chiefly on the outskirts of Paris, are already open to
traffic, and a further 86 miles are under construction
Italy has 306 miles of autostrada completed and is now
building a further 530 miles while Belgium has 72 miles
of motorway open, and another 600 miles are planned.
In Austria a new motorway of 196 miles, between
Salzburg and Vienna, is under construction. Built to
Almasy, Paris
POLYGLOT PANEL. In the countries which adhere to the international agreement on road traffic signs sponsored by the United
Nations, most of the signs lining the highways bear standardized symbols. On this Danish road, the International sign indicating
that one half is closed to traffic is supplemented by a signal panel in five languages which also shuts off the area being repaired.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
© Dudley Noble
AFRICA HAS CHANGED since the days when David Livingstone was obliged to hack out a road through bush country and jungle
as he travelled from the Cape almost to the Equator. Road construction is being pushed ahead. Africa needs highways now to
develop both internal and international trade. Plans for new highways include one which will run from Cape Town to Nairobi,
with links to Belgian and Portuguese territories. In the north east, work on road construction and maintenance in Ethiopia has
developed rapidly since the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development made a S5 million loan in 1950. Photos show:
left, viaduct In Ethiopia's mountainous terrain ; right, a section of one of the 4,500 kms of all-weather roads in Ethiopia and Eritrea.
autobahn specifications, this first Austrian motorway will
link up with the West German system.
Thus it is seen that the countries of Western Europe,
too, are integrating their national road systems towards
an eventual network of Continental motor highways, built
to standard specifications throughout. Europe's longest
international route, E.5, runs from the seaport of Ostend
right through to Athens and Istanbul, and thence on to
Baghdad.
. While the western end of this route runs over some of
the world's most up-to-date motor roads the new
Ostend-Brussels Motorway and the famous autobahns of
Germany the Balkans end still has long stretches that
are far below European highway standards. But a great
deal of road construction and modernization is now in
progress in Yugoslavia, Greece and Turkey.
The major road-building achievement in Yugoslovia
since 1945 is the 240-mile motor highway between Zagreb
and Belgrade. This is the fastest traffic highway in that
country and, apart from its level crossings, might compare
favourably with the new motorway construction in
Western Europe. A ¡key link is the splendid new Save
River Bridge at Belgrade, connecting the capital and
Southern Serbia with the highway to Zagreb and Western
Europe. More than half the cost of this £3 million bridge
was covered by United States development funds.
In Greece, more than half the road system was
destroyed or made temporarily impassable during World
War II. But in the past ten or twelve years remarkable
progress has been made with its repair and reconstruction.
This small country has spent nearly £15 million on its
roads since the war, and with the aid of American
technicians more than a thousand bridges have been'
restored to use.
Turkey, too, has made considerable headway with the
modernisation of her road system, and has more than
doubled the mileage of all-weather surfaced highways
since 1948. Such highways now total about 11,000 miles,
and another 700 miles are under construction. Much
work has been done on the busy Istanbul-Ankara section
of the international route, E.5, and this has been
reconstructed as a motorway.
In Turkey the highways of the West meet those
legendary trade routes of bygone centuries, which stretch
far eastwards across Persia into the heart of Asia. These
are among the world's most romantic roads, for they
include the early silk routes between China and Western
Asia, age-old caravan trails leading through Afghanistan
and the Khyber Pass into Northern India, and roads that
cross desolate and uninhabited regions on the borderland
of Northern Persia and Russia Turkistan, east of the
Caspian Sea.
Someday the European motor road to Istanbul and
Baghdad may be carried on through Persia and
Afghanistan to make a continuous overland route from
Western Europe to Pakistan and India. This motorist's
dream may perhaps become a reality sooner than
expected. For recent discussions between Turkey and
Pakistan included the subject of a long-distance highway
to link the capital cities of Istanbul, Baghdad, Teheran
and Karachi. This Would be part of the projected Pan-
Asian Highway to India and Malaya. (See p. 11)
Road-building achievements' of the future in all the
continents are quite unlimited. As they gradually
materialize, greater opportunities for international trade
and co-operation in other fields as well as undreamed of
travel delights will be opened up. But if mankind is to
gain the wonderful freedom that travel on the world
highway can offer, the nations must agree, sooner or
later, to get rid of the artificial barriers and tiresome
frontier delays and restrictions at each national boundary.
So long as we cling to them the purpose of a global
highway can never be fully achieved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
PAY AS YOU GO. Turnpike gates (upper part of photo) on the highway
from New Jersey (centre). Through traffic to and from New Jersey uses-
centre lanes. Side lanes (left and right) lead to and from the Lincoln Tunnel
which takes traffic into New York City under the Hudson River.
PATTERN OF
SUPER HIGHWAYS
THE U.S.A.
One out of every seven Americans earns his living in some
phase of highway travel ; 80% drive to work; 85% take their
vacations and pleasure trips by automobile. With an ever-
expanding economy and an ever-growing fleet of automobiles,
trucks and buses (now well over 65 million), the United States
has embarked on a vast construction programme to provide
enough roads to accomodate the nearly 90 million vehicles which
are expected to be circulating by 1972. This 16-year building
programme will crisscross the U.S.A. with an inter-state super¬
highway network covering well over 40,000 miles, plus thousands
of miles of state and local roads. Reaching out into every corner
of the country, the new web of highways will link 42 state capitals
and 90% of all cities with more than 50,000 population. It w¡ll
cost 8100,000 millionnearly 300 times the cost of the Panama
Canalbut with fewer curves, no crossroads, and a wide centre
strip, the super system is expected to save 3,500 lives annually,
reduce accident costs by S725 million and save transport compa¬
nies a further $825 million by cutting delay, fuel waste, tyre and
brake wear. Construction on this scale is only possible because
of the power, speed and versatility of today's road building
machines: moving assembly lines or. "paving trains" can place
up to 3/4 of a mile of 12 foot concrete lane, eight inches thick, in
one eight hour day ; batching plants serve up just the right mixture
of rock, sand and asphalt at the touch of a button. Photos on
these pages show some of the arabesque patterns, whorls,
intricate "knots" and geometric cloverleafs which are found at
the junctions of some of American's existing superhighways.
TRAFFIC PROBLEM in. Californiafrom three million motor vehicles
in 1 940 to six million in 1955is being met by massive roadbuilding
programme: 1,000 miles of multi-lane highways built in past ten years.
Above, section of Arroyo Seco road linking Pasadena and Los Angeles.
NEW JERSEY TURNPIKE coming from bottom right of photo crosses
Passaic River (centre) and Hackensack River (top right). In foreground
the Pulaski 'Skyway' is seen 'leapfrogging' the New Jersey Turnpike.
The 'Skyway' is one of the major modern roads leading into New York.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
PENNSYLVANIA TURNPIKE, completed in 19 54, was one of U.S.A.'s
first superhighways. It runs 360 miles from the Delaware River in the
east to the Ohio border on the west, connecting Philadelphia and Pitts¬
burgh. This highway has no crossroads, sharp curves or steep grades.
PAY AS YOU GO. Turnpike gates (upper part of photo) on the highway
from New Jersey (centre). Through traffic to and from New Jersey uses
centre lanes. Side lanes (left and right) lead to and from the Lincoln Tunnel
which takes . traffic into New York City under the Hudson River.
(© Newsweek-Dale Healy
FOUR LAYERS of overpass bridges in Los Angeles, California, which
has more automobiles per number of inhabitants than any other city in
the world. The city has already built over I 00 miles of urban "freeways"
and is planning vaster network of highways to relieve traffic congestion.
LINKED MOTORWAYS. Near to Detroit, Michigan, these two motor¬
ways with double lanes, the other following the shore of Lake Michi¬
gan linked by ramps and underpasses. An arrangement of this type
keeps traffic moving at speed and cuts out dangerous intersections.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE BURMA ROAD which became a vital communications link for the Allies In the Second World War, is an old caravan route
reconstructed by modern road-building methods to meet the needs of motorized transport. The modernization of Asia's
famous caravan routes of old is the basis of the vast plan to create an Asian highway network running from Vietnam to Turkey.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
USIS
ASIAN HIGHWAY routes shown on this map are often ancient caravan trails, now destined to become an up-to-date highway
system. Circles Indicate where road is unsuitable for.motor traffic during the rainy season or where link roads are still Inexistent.
CARAVAN ROUTES
TO LIVE AGAIN
Motorists will soon be able to drive all the way across
the continent of Asia from Turkey to the shores of
Indo-China or Malaya on the famous caravan routes
of antiquity which are to be modernized and linked up in a
new Pan-Asian Highway.
Stretching for some 7,000 miles, the Pan-Asian Highway
is part of a bold and imaginative project conceived by the
Highway Subcommittee of the U.N. Economic Commission
for Asia and the Far East (Ecafe) to endow southern Asia
with an up-to-date international highway system. The
backbone of the undertaking will be the great network of
old caravan routes which have survived the ravages of time
although some date back to as much as 1,000 years before
the Christian Era. It is over these caravan routes that Marco
Polo and other travellers like Fa-Hsien and Ibn Batuta explored
the lands of the East, that the armies of Gengis Khan,
Alexander the Great and Tamerlane marched on their road
to conquest, and that the silk, jade and spices of the Orient
were transported by the traders of the past.
Twelve hundred years before Christ extensive trade rouies
were already in existence under the reign of Salmanasar I,
King of Assyria, and the nobles of his court wore precious
ornaments made with lapis lazuli and other jewels which came
from Afghanistan. The famous Silk Road ran from Chung¬
king through Burma and North India on to Delhi, and from
there to Teheran and Samarkand, then west across the Caspian
Sea and through Tiflis to the Black Sea.
It is hard for us today to realize the hardships and hazards
endured during journeys in those far off times: the vast
distances that had to be covered on foot or horse or camel
back often took months, even years; progress was impeded by
the huge stretches of dusty plains and parched deserts to be
crossed, the turbulent rivers to be forded and the high
mountain ranges to be. scaled. Then too, there was always the
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
CARAVAN
R O U TES
(Contliwed)
NEW PAN-ASIAN HIGHWAY WILL LINK
LANDS FROM MALAYA TO IRAN
lurking danger of cut-throat bandits who would hurl themselves
down on the slow-moving caravans, murdering the travellers
and making off with the rich cargo.
The caravans carried an extremely wide range of goods:
tin from England, copper ore from Spain, timber from northern
Europe, iron from central Africa, Iran and India, spices from
the Moluccas, silks from Sian Fu (China) and cottons from
Egypt and Mekran (now in Pakistan);
The development of trade routes was by no means easy.
Asia is made up of vast plains, some fertile others totally
desert, mountain ranges which include some of the highest in
the world, and rivers, mighty and long and often turbulent.
The trade routes naturally sought out the mountain passes
(most of them still in use) and followed the rivers. Where
possible, caravan routes were preferred to the hazards at sea.
The establishment of great kingdoms greatly helped in
stabilizing and providing some security to trade routes and
developing them, though the extent to which security could
be provided was limited by the rulers' ability and power. The
establishment of the Han dynasty in China, the rise of Cyrus
and of Alexander the Great, and the large-scale missionary
efforts of Asoka all helped towards stabilizing the caravan
routes and trade patterns in Asia.
The Romans, in the period 266 B.C-476 A.D., built roads
which extended over three continents. These were built
primarily for military purposes but good communications with
security of travel gave a considerable impetus to the develop¬
ment of trade and commerce. Exchange of commodities was
carried on through Greece and Syria, and merchants travelled
as far as Merv or Samarkand in Turkestan, Kandahar in
Afghanistan and through the Khyber Pass over the road across
north India to the Ganges plain. In the Byzantine Empire,
trade with the East by caravan flourished. Baghdad gave the
Moslem world good roadways with inns (serais) and provision
for relays of mounts for traders, pilgrims and official courtiers.
These roads were linked with those of central Asia and even
of China and constituted the great trade routes between the
East and the West, and the important international land links
between the cultures and civilizations of the Orient and the
Occident.
Today, however, many'of these land routes have fallen into
disuse and cannot possibly meet the needs of the developing
countries of south Asia. The creation of a vast network of
international highways, linking up the existing roads and raising
these to the standards needed for motorized traffic has thus
become an urgent, priority problem.
The highway project was born following a careful study
of this situation in 1955, when the Highway Subcommittee of
Ecafe undertook a study of the possibilities ' of a. highway
development plan to link all the countries between Vietnam
and Iran. This plan was approved by Ecafe early this year.
The region has been divided into three zones. The first will
cover the road network of Vietnam, Cambodia, Laos, Thailand,
Malaya and Burma. The second will englobe Burma's western
connexions, East Pakistan, India, Ceylon, Nepal and motor
roads to West Pakistan. The third will comprise West
Pakistan, Afghanistan and Iran.
Ecafe's highway experts agree that the first priority task
is to build the highway links needed to connect the existing
road systems. Already work has been started by some coun¬
tries.
As goods which will travel on the Asian highway will often
have to pass through several countries before reaching. their
final destination, it is proposed to simplify customs formalities
and border procedures.
Once the roads have been linked from country to country,
efforts will be turned to the progressive modernization of the
network as a whole. Thus the countries of southern Asia, once
largely isolated from the outside world, will be able to dev¬
elop their trade, will get to known their neighbours better, and
will also share fully in the economic and social progress of a
continent which has now turned resolutely towards the future.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
Deutsche Zentrale für Fremdenverkehr, Frankfort
RIBBONS OF CONCRETE cutting through plain and wood bring economic progress yet rarely spoil the natural scene.
Landscape architects adapted German autobahns to harmonise with scenery. Mare and foal near Munich to Salzburg Autobahn
(above) are as undisturbed by passing of automobiles as is the effigy of a stag beside Kharkov to Rostov motorway In the U.S.S.R.
Official Soviet photo
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CAN WE SOLVE OUR
TRAFFIC BOTTLENECKS?
by Henri Walter
The rapid and continuous growth of motor traffic
during the first half of this century has created a
major social problem in the second half. There are
now more than 100 million motor vehicles in the world,
operating most of the time in and around the large towns
and cities. Millions more are added to the total every
year, even allowing for replacements. Because of the
great concentration of urban activity, and the preponder¬
ance of the motor vehicle over other forms of transport,
traffic stagnation has for some years threatened the
world's larger cities.
Living standards everywhere depend more and more
on the increasing use of motor vehicles, and in many
countries two-thirds of all goods are now distributed by
them. So it is not at all surprising that streets designed
in and for an entirely different age of transport should
have produced a traffic situation that is already intoler¬
able and that unless bold remedies are undertaken, may
become rapidly worse.
Congested streets are responsible for an enormous
Waste of time and effort and, above all, incalculable human
suffering and misery through daily traffic accidents. In
the centre of London, where conditions are among the
worst in the world, the cost of traffic jams is estimated
at more than £200 million a year. Traffic studies made
in many countries have shown that by far the greatest
number of road accidents involving motor vehicles 75
per cent or more occur in built-up areas where all types
of traffic move in all directions. Ninety per cent of the
casualties among pedestrians also occur in built-up
areas.
Quite apart from the toll of accidents, present-day traffic
conditions in and about cities slow down production,
hinder ordinary commerce and, by creating high transport
charges, add materially to the general cost of living.
Already in the early 1920's the road traffic problem was
beginning to make itself felt in Europe and North America,
although the number of vehicles on the roads at that time
was but a fraction of what it is now. In the United
States, Italy and Germany the idea of designing roads
specially fitted to the needs of motor vehicles was develop¬
ed. The first of these special motor roads were the
American "parkways," built to provide safe, open routes
for fast traffic and attract drivers from the ordinary
overcrowded highways.
The U.S.A. uses the express way
Roads for the exclusive use of motor vehicles Were intro¬
duced into Europe by the Italians, but their early au-
tostrade made no provision for dividing opposite traf¬
fic streams. It was in Germany and Holland, and also in
the United States, that special motorways with separate
carriageways and controlled access Were built on a large
scale. The ¡German autobahn system, particularly,
became a model of efficient highway engineering.
By barring pedestrians, cyclists, horses and all slow-
moving traffic the motorway eliminates one of the principal
causes of accidents, namely, the mixing together of all
forms of road users travelling in different directions at
different speeds. Drivers get on or off the highway only
at specially designed safety junctions. There are no
crossings on the same level, all other roads passing over
or under it.
The controlled access highway is universally accepted
as a contributory factor to traffic safety, and in the past
20 years or so such roads have been built in many parts
of the world. While traffic speeds are much higher on
motorways than on ordinary roads, accidents are usually
.much lower. Comparison of accident rates on motorways
14
and ordinary general-purpose roads in Holland, for
example, has shown the motorways are up to 75 per cent
safer to use.
In North American cities, the building of controlled
urban motorways, or expressways, has had a remarkable
effect on the death rate in built-up areas. The U.S.
Bureau of Public Roads has estimated that the fatal
accident rate on highways built to expressway standards
is 2.8 per cent for each 100 million vehicle-miles travelled,
compared with 10.1 per cent for other roads in the same
areas carrying similar traffic.
For a time motorways were built primarily to speed up
traffic between important towns and cities. But it was
realised such "traffic pipelines" were needed most of all
in the cities themselves where congestion was far more
serious. American highway engineers who pioneered
urban motorways borrowed ideas, from the railways.
Trains proceed at fair speed without obstruction through
the most densely built-up areas because the tracks are set
apart, above or below street level. Why, then, argued the
expressway planners, should through motor traffic not
be similarly segregated ?
Brussels builds an aerial highway
So in large cities all over the United States, in Europe
Latin-America and elsewhere, spectacular motor
roads carry large volumes of motor traffic swiftly and
safely across crowded city centres. Elevated highways
stride on steel and concrete viaducts high above shopping
streets, market places, rivers, canals and railway yards.
Depressed motor roads run in cuttings, or underpasses, be¬
low bridges taJking the ordinary local street traffic. In
some cities the double-deck highway has been evolved as a
means of carrying the maximum flow of traffic through
an area where the land space is very restricted. Opposite
traffic streams run one above the other, while the covered
space under the decks is used as a car park.
In Brussels, where extensive street improvements were
made in time for the 1958 World Fair, cars now drive at
a steady 30 or 40 miles per hour from the outskirts of the
city into the centre. On the main road round the centre,
seven tunnels were dug at cross-roads to eliminate traffic
hold-ups. At one end of the road traffic suddenly "takes
off on to a 1 1/2-mile long viaduct built on stilts to
carry cars going in and out of the city above the "local"
traffic below.
The most spectacular tunnelling feat is a series of fly-
unders built at the Porte Louise junction. There, one
tunnel was ¡built at right-angles underneath another
tunnel. A third tunnel links up the other two, while the
existing road at street level is reserved for trams and
local traffic. Through traffic in any direction uses the
tunnels which have rid Brussels of what was once a
notorious blackspot for hold-ups.
At Rotterdam, too, one can drive through the city on a
fast sunken motor road giving through traffic direct
access to and from the fine modern highway tunnel under
the River Maas. And in Warsaw the new east-west traffic
route passes in a series of tunnels under the old city
centre. These are just examples from a large number of
cities in Europe which are tackling their traffic problems
in a constructive way by building new roads to fit present
and future needs.
Every road userthe pedestrian, cyclist, motorist or
commercial driverbenefits by the segregation of through
traffic from the local, stopping traffic. Street accidents
are materially reduced by the easing of congestion in busy
shopping centres, while such essential local traffic as
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
- _, unmit, ¿¿¿i tmsffjy - -a a r .', *s-jr
- W« wHHm*llllft ^
The Unesco Courier
ffl 	
June 1959
&** ^
USIS
KEEPING OUT OF TOWN. There are now more than 100 million motor-vehicles in the world and most of the time they are using
the streets of large cities. In Los Angelesone of America's fastest growing citiesthe authorities have found one answer to
the problem of keeping as many vehicles as possible away from the central areas. They have built a new business centre (above)
about six miles away from the overcrowded streets in the heart of the city and have provided it with parking space covering 14 acres.
passenger vehicles and tradesmen's delivery vans can
operate more efficiently and economically.
While traffic segregation goes a long way towards re¬
moving congestion in cities, the problem of the parked
vehicle still remains. In every large city or market
town more and more cars converge oh the centre each
working day. Available parking space is outgrown and
vehicles parked at the kerbside greatly reduce a street's
traffic capacity and indirectly cause accidents.
The problem that municipal authorities face is how to
provide sufficient off-street parking in or near to built-up
city centres. One solution is the multi-storey parking
garage which accommodates the maximum number of
vehicles on a minimum of ground space and affords drivers
quick and easy parking. Such garages have been develop¬
ed with success in a number of European and American
cities.
Managements of large city stores are finding it
worthwhile to ¡provide convenient parking accommodation
for customers who drive in from the surrounding suburbs
or outlying districts, and in America the tiered parking
terrace is becoming something like a standard annexe to
the leading departmental stores. One such store in Salt
Lake City, for example, has reported an increase of
nearly 20 per cent in sales since it built on a parking
terrace for 500-600 cars five years ago. According to the
management, each car space is Worth an extra 3,000
dollars worth of trade a year.
One of the world's largest store parking garages was
recently opened in the central shopping area of London.
Attached to a famous departmental store, the garage
accommodates 1,000. cars on seven floors, reached from
street level by a continuous ramp. There is direct access
for shoppers from each parking floor into the store and
the basement of the new building serves as an under¬
ground marshalling yard for the store's own fleet of goods
delivery vehicles.
Coventry centre of the British motor manufacturing
industry like Rotterdam, suffered wholesale destruc¬
tion through bombing raids in the last war. In both
these cities, which have been extensively replanned and
rebuilt, "traffic-free" shopping streets have been develop¬
ed. In this new conception of city planning, store pre¬
mises are served by rear-access roads and the usual street
carriageway in front of them is replaced by spacious paved
areas, laid out with gardens and ornamental features.
Arcaded footpaths and pedestrian subways are provided
to allow families to shop in safe and pleasant conditions.
The traffic-free shopping centre is another and very
important contribution towards the reduction of street
accidents in busy, congested cities and is likely to be
developed on a world-wide scale in the future.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
WHOS
FAIT Ii
M, XX \J JJ
flSEÄ- ^,
.w
iSa
IT ?
Road travel is the most dangerous form of transportation
in Europe today. This is clear from a report of the
Economic Commission for Europe dealing with the
prevention of road accidents, which suggests that even greater
casualty figures can be expected unless prompt action is taken.
The report reviews the main causes of fatal accidents and
injuries on the roads and gives a breakdown of the factors
responsible. It reveals the striking fact that the risk of death
on the roads of Europe for a given distance is ten times that
involved in travel either by aircraft or train.
Figures quoted for every 100 millions of kilometres
travelled by road vehicles Were: 18 people killed in Western
Europe, 10 people in Great Britain and less than five in the
U.S.A.
What are the causes of these road accidents? Are faulty
vehicles the chief culprits?... or faulty roads?... faults in the
traffic control?... or just plain, faulty human beings? There
are many contradictions and discrepancies in the reasons given.
Figures from one country incriminate the bad state of highway
surfaces; these from another blame faulty automobile brakes.
One reason for this is that different reports may record dif¬
ferent opinions as to the cause of similar types of accidents.
This is often true of a typical accident the collision of
two vehicles at a cross-roads where visibility is poor. The
driver coming from the left (the example here applies in
France, where drivers coming from the right have priority)
would in all likelihood be blamed by the police for entering
the cross-roads at an excessive speed.
A traffic specialist might object that the speed in question
(say 20 m.p.h.) was not excessive in view of the fact that the
automobile was designed to travel at speeds between 30 and
55 m.p.h., in normal conditions. The accident, he would say,
was due to the limited visibility at the cross-roads. Suitable for
the age of ox or horse-drawn transport, the cross-roads is
quite inadequate for the modern vehicles now using it. His
conclusion would be that the State was to blame for not
making the necessary changes. Which view is correct? In
reality the views expressed in both cases are subjective ones.
It is, however, possible to get an idea of the share borne in
accidents by faulty roads. German studies of the country's
autoroute system, for example, have led to the conclusion that
road improvements could halve accidents on these highways.
Faulty vehicles are on the average only alloted a low
percentage (5%) of responsibility for accidents.
16
WHO
What about the faulty human being? In Italy, the
"Ispettorato della Motorizzazione Civile" examined 2,000 road
accident cases in which there were almost always fatal results.
The study showed that accidents due to human error amounted
to over 52%; to faulty vehicles, 7% and to faulty roads, 40%.
The point has been made, regarding the comparison between
autoroute accident rates and those on ordinary roads in Europe
that the large number of accidents involving cyclists and ped¬
estrians on these roads is due to the very fact that they are
allowed to carry traffic of such a mixed nature. In other
words the fault is not with the pedestrian or the cyclist as
much as the inadequacy of the road itself.
It has been estimated that proper road development would
bring down the (roughly) 30% of accidents attributed to
cyclists and walkers to as low as 5%.
In round figures, accident responsibility on the roads of
Europe could be defined, on the basis of available figures, as
follows: faults of motor vehicles drivers, 20%; faults of
cyclists and pedestrians, 5%; faulty vehicles, 5%; faulty roads,
70%.
Better Living
Through Better Roads
Readers who wish to read more about international
(and national) road problems may be interested by
two magazines which are specially devoted to these ques¬
tions. The first is "'Road International" which is pub¬
lished 'quarterly by the International Road Federation
Ltd., of Abbey House, Victoria Street, London, S.W.I.
The aim of the magazine is that of the Federation:
"Better Living Through Better Roads". Orders for
"Road International" may be placed directly with the
International Road Federation or through a newsagent.
Each issue costs 3/6d or 50 cents. Annual subscription
rates (post free): United Kingdom 14/-; U.S.A. $2.00;
France 700 frs. The second magazine, published
monthly in French, is "'Etudes Routières", which offers
news and views on the economic and technical aspects
of road building and use around the world. Price per
issue is 7/- or $1.00; annual subcription, £3. 10. 0. stg.
or $10.00. Subscriptions can be taken out in U.K.
through Barclays Bank, 168 Fenchurch Street, London
E.C.3, or through "'Etudes Routières", 17, rue Necker,
Geneva, Switzerland, payment to be made by inter¬
national money order or banker's cheque.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
17-
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ROAD
SAFETY
IS THEIR
BUSINESS
1 , 2, 4, 5, 6, 7.© Almasy, Paris.
3. © Deutsche Zentrale für
Fremdenverkehr, Frankfort.
i
A familiar figure on the world's roadsin city street or on national highway highway code, directing traffic, and, when needed, lending a hand to the
traffic policeman does a vital job: seeing that road users obey the motorist in distress'. On these pages we present some traffic policemen
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
from widely separated parts of the world. On duty at a busy city
intersection in India or on horseback patrol in the Argentine, the traffic
policeman -is doing a vital job of work.
German Federal Republic. 4. Greece. -
I. Pakistan. 2. Argentina. 3.
5. India. 6. France. 7. Sweden.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Deutsche Zentrale für Fremdenverkehr
BY BARRING CYCLISTS, pedestrians, horses and all slow-moving traffic, the motorway eliminates one of the principal causes
of accidents, namely', the mixing together of all kinds of road users travelling In different ¡directions at different speeds. Photo
shows part of the Alpenstrasse in Upper Bavaria, a picturesque road linking Munich and Innsbruck across the Bavarian Alps.
PEDESTRIANS, LOOK OUT!
Pedestrians in the over 65 age group are nowadays the chief
victims of fatal traffic accidents and the mortality rate is
still increasing. An increase of one hundred per cent or
more in the mortality from traffic accidents among pedestrians
in this age group ' occurred in- some countries between 1950 and
1955. The death rate for young pedestrians, however, rose much
less in some countries and even decreased in others, according to a
study by the World Health Organization (WHO) covering 18
countries.
A comparison of the average annual figures for the period
1950/52 with those for 1953/55 shows that in most countries the
number of pedestrians killed per million motor vehicles has
dropped; that countries with the sharpest increase in road traffic
have the. highest rate in fatal accidents, and that there are far
more men than women among the victims.
The greatest increase in the death rate of pedestrians over 65
years of age has taken place in the Netherlands where it rose
from 40.5 annually per million inhabitants to 96.8 an increase
of 139 per cent, while the increase for all ages was -, 69.6.
Increases were, noted in five other countries, in the following
order: Norway, Japan, Union of South Africa and Denmark.
During the same period (figures for 1950-52 compared with those
for 1953-55) the increase in the United Kingdom Was from 154.1
pedestrians aged over 65 killed per million inhabitants to 178.9
an increase of 16 per cent.
The only countries where a decline in mortality has taken place
are the United States of America (12.8 per cent less for those
aged over 65; 13.4 per cent for all age groups) and Ireland (7.3
per cent and 5.9 per cent respectively).
20
Of all countries covered, by the study, Japan has the highest
overall rate of traffic deaths with an annual average for the
period 1953/55 of 2,336 pedestrians killed 'per million motor
vehicles compared with 129 in the U.S.A. where there are many
fewer people walking on the roads.
Here are the average annual figures in 1953/55 for 16 countries
covered by the study.
Inhabitants
Countries per motor
vehicle
Japan	 67
Spain 91
Italy 14
Finland 24
Switzerland	 10
Norway 14
Ireland 14
United Kingdom	 8
Denmark 10
Netherlands 12
Sweden	 8
Australia 5
Canada 4
New Zealand 4
Union of South Africa 	
(European population only) 	 3
U.S.A.	 3
Pedestrians
killed per
million motor
vehicles
2,336
1,283
1,272
861
534
416
405
390
363
338
316
309
291
153
145
129
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
DRIVERS WATCH YOUR SPEED
The assessment, of the various degrees of responsibility for
accidents involving injury or death on the roads of Europe
gives first place (70 per cent) to faulty roads and allots
less than a third of this percentage (20 per cent) to the drivers
of vehicles themselves. A 20 per cent responsibility, however, is
still a responsibility for one case in every five.
What, can be done to improve standards of driving ?
An expert makes the following point: "The results of road
safety teaching to schoolchildren are striking. Countries which
have made the greatest efforts in this direction have declared that the
number of road deaths among children has become stationary
or has even fallen... while the number of adult victims of road
accidents has continued to increase at a rate roughly equal to
the increase in circulation."
His suggestion is that what is good for children should be
equally good for adults, that "preaching" at people will get us
nowhere and that what is needed is simple instruction and
information.
In this connexion readers who are drivers of motor vehicles
may be interested in some figures published by a French car
manufacturing firm and circulated to users of their cars.
The first comment made is that the average driver might drive
more carefully if he iwould learn to think of his speed not in terms
of miles an hour but in feet per second.
Consider the figures:
Miles per hour... equals .. feet per second
87 127
37 55
15 23
12 18
Emergencies on the road call for action in terms of seconds
and split seconds. It is therefore realistic to consider speed
which reduces time available for action in terms of seconds.
Second comment: Road safety might improve if drivers would
think less of the time taken to get from A to B and more about
the time taken to stop a car in motion.
A motorcar moving at 62 miles an hour is covering 92 feet
every second. An obstacle appears. It is estimated that normally
about half a second passes between a driver seeing the obstacle
and applying the brake. In the half second the car has already
covered 46 feet.
If the road is good and dry, IF the car's brakes are efficient
and the tyres in new condition, four more seconds are required
before the car stops. In those four seconds it will have travelled
a further 188 feet.
To sum up: 62 miles an hour to a stop takes five seconds in
all, during which time the car cannot be prevented unless it
hits an obstacle from travelling a distance of more than 230
feet. On a wet road, and with worn brakes, this distance may
be increased to as much as 650 feet.
Note for those who like even an occasional drink while "out
for a run": alcohol, even in small quantities, has two effects on a
car driver. The first is that he tends to drive faster, the second
that his "reaction time" the time betweeen his becoming aware
of an obstacle and his taking action to stop or avoid it is
increased. Read the above paragraphs once more.
Third comment: instead of thinking about how powerful the
car engine is, drivers would be wise to think instead how powerful
their brakes are.
Consider the following facts:
Suppose that a car of 55-60 BHP weighing 1,000 kg, is moving
at a speed of 30 miles an hour. The driver can double its speed
within 17 seconds. Suddenly, a lorry swings across the path from
a side-road. Down goes the brake pedal. IF the road surface is
good, IF the brakes are efficient, the car can be brought to a
standstill within 4 seconds. This means that a retarding force of
190 HP has had to be applied equal to three times the engine
power of the car.
Yet despite all the mechanical strains and stress on motor
vehicle mechanisms, the share of faulty vehicles in the toll of
injury and death on European roads is put at only 5 per cent-
four times less than that attributed to faulty driving.
ROAD SAFETY CAMPAIGNS Inspired by the urgent need to reduce the heavy toll of accidentsespecially In towns, where
75% of those involving motor-vehicles occurare being given ever greater prominence. Public authorities and accident prevention
societies remind the public to "take care", with posters like those shown here, from, left, Great Britain and right, the Netherlands.
Let op voetgangers !
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Longest road built:
THE ROYAL
HIGHWAY OF
THE INCAS
by Jorge Carrera Andrade
HANGING BRIDGES, "little brothers of the roads", were ever impor¬
tant links in the Inca road system. They were constructed of bamboo and
fibre cordssome of this type still exist in South Americaand their upkeep
was entrusted to a "Commissioner of Roads and Bridges" a sketch of whom
(left) was made by Guarnan Poma de Ayala, the chronicler of Indian descent
in his 17th century Codex, "Nueva Crónica y Buen Gobierno". With its
drawings of bridges and royal halting stations, this work constituted a kind
of illustrated guide to the Inca roads as they existed in the 1 7th century.
There are many paradoxes in history, and one of the
strangest is surely that the Incas, who had never
heard of the wheel, should have built the greatest
road system the world has ¡known. Their network of
highways covered some 10,000 miles, stretching from Col¬
ombia all the way to Chile and from the shores of the
Pacific to the jungle forests of the Amazon, crisscrossing
almost all the territory now included in the Republics
of Ecuador and Peru, as well as portions of Bolivia, Chile,
northern Argentina and southern Colombia.
The Inca Empire began as a tiny kingdom on the shores
of Lake Titicaca about the year 1,000 A.D. For five
hundred years it grew and expanded until, after conquer¬
ing the Kingdom of Quito, it was the most powerful
civilization of South America and adopted the name "Land
of the Four Quarters of the World" (Tahuantinsuyu) to
signify its control of the four cardinal points of the com¬
pass.
The Inca road system was built to preserve the unity
and safeguard the economic life of the Empire. Its
construction is one of the wonders of human history,
defying all natural obstacles in one of the most rugged
terrains existing anywhere in the world. Though far less
known than the celebrated roads of Rome and other
ancient empires, the Inca highways are in many ways
even more remarkable.
The backbone of the network was a broad highway the
"Great Royal Road of the Incas"running the entire
Jorge Carrera Andrade of Quito, Ecuador, has done considerable
research into the ancient civilizations of South America. He is
the author of two books on the Incas and the Kingdom of Quito,
"La Tierra Sempre Verde" (The Evergreen Land) and "'El Camino
del Sol" \(Road of the Sun). A leading poet of Latin America,
his literary *works have been published in several languages. Since
1954 Carrera Andrade has been in 'charge of the Spanish edition
of The Unesco Courier.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
length of the Inca Empire from north to south, between
the two branches of the formidable Andean mountain
range. In certain places the road rose sharply to as much
as 15,000 feet; in others it. dropped steeply in mountain
valleys and gorges, traversed broad fertile plains and
bleak stretches of desert wasteland.
From the main highway branch roads cut through the
mountain in all directions, especially to the west, where
they linked up with another mighty highway known as
the "Coastal Road", which ran parallel to the Great Royal
Road along the sandy coastal plains and forests from
Tumbez to the north of Chile where it joined up with it.
It should not be imagined that the Inca roads were
mere mountain tracks or desert trails. The Great Royal
Highway was 25 feet in width and ran straight as an
arrow, without curves or detours of any kind, for 3,000
miles more than the distance between Gibraltar and
Moscow! Paved with stones along almost its entire
length, it traversed only the principal cities of the empire,
like Cuzco and Quito, the other towns being linked up
with the Royal Highway by secondary roads. On both
sides of the highway the Incas built walls of stone and
packed earth on top of which they planted agave cactuses
at regular intervals. In addition rows of trees. lined the
road to provide shade for travellers. Living in a bleak
landscape the Incas attached great importance to their
trees and the empire enacted stringent laws for their pre¬
servation. The penalty for cutting them down was death.
Along the side of the Great Royal Road ran a rivulet of
fresh water to quench the thirst of both wayfarers and
draft animals. At intervals of about twelve miles along
the entire stretch of 3,000 miles there were wayside
houses known as tampus where travellers could rest or
spend the night. . There were also chains of granaries and
royal depots stocked with food and all kinds of supplies
for the army, including clothing and leather footwear.
Grain and manufactured products were stored in huge
earthen jars. Strangers were accommodated with the ut¬
most hospitality in hostelrles called corpahuasis and were
provided with food and drink free or charge.
Every mile or so along the Royal Route the Incas bullt
edifices for a special category of imperial functionaries,
the chasquis or relay couriers, who raced on foot from
one end of the kingdom to the other bearing royal mes¬
sages by word of mouth. Sometimes messages were con¬
veyed by specially painted sticks or beans painted in
various colour combinations which had specific meanings.
The Incas resorted to these devices since they had no
written language.
This postal service was so efficient that it covered the
3,000 odd miles of the Great Royal Highway in a matter
of 20 days or so four times faster than the "pony express"
service Introduced by the Spaniards after the Conquest.
In the best season of the year, the chasquis covered the
distance between Cuzco and Quito in five days a feat
they continued to perform clandestinely during ,the
Colonial era to the amazement of the Spaniards who
dubbed this fleet-footed news-transmission system "post
office of the sorcerers."
The stone that wept blood
The astounding network of Andean roads and highways
was the achievement of three Inca emperors: Pacha¬
cútec, Túpac Yupanqui and Huayna Cápac, the man¬
power for the construction work coming from the tribes of
peoples they subdued. Pachacútec, known as the "Re¬
former", was particularly fond of stone and for the Royal
Highway he had enormous blocks of stone transported
hundreds of miles, particularly from the Kingdom of
Quito, using the Indians of that region and a tribe called
the Chancas. The treatment meeted out by the Imperial
guards (they were called Big-Ears) was such that the
Indians finally revolted and almost overthrew the Inca
kingdom. The earliest chroniclers relate how the huge
stones (some weighing 10 tons) Were carried such great
distances and tell a story of how one such block fell and
crushed a thousand Indians to death. It passed Into
legend as "the stone that wept blood."
Fifty years after the Conquest, a Spanish missionary,
José de Acosta, visited the New World and noted that the
Indians who worked on the roads "used no mortar, had
neither iron nor steel for cutting and working the stones,
no machines or instruments for transporting them, yet so
skilful was their work that- the Joints between the stones
were barely noticeable."
Tupac Yupanqui was the son of Pachacútec and carried
on his father's work. He extended the Royal Highway as
far as Chile in the south and beyond Quito in the north,
thus opening up new territories for trade and develop¬
ment. To consolidate the empire he built a chain of
fortresses near the Great Highway, and instituted a
system of "population transfers", shifting newly conquered
tribes to Peru and replacing them by loyal subjects.
Huayna Cápac, his successor, surpassed his father in the
field of public works. He built Temples of the Sun and
Inca Watchtowers along the Royal Highway. He repaired
the old roads and built new ones, and had platforms and
terraces made to prevent erosion of the soil.
But above all, Huayna Cápac was responsible for the
repair, strengthening and consolidation of the suspension
bridges. These bridges are one of the greatest feats of
the Inca road network. They appear frail and delicate
but proved astonishingly resistant. Flung across raging
torrents and formidable mountain chasms, they were
made of six-inch fibre and bamboo cables anchored into
stone piers, and were covered with a floor of wooden laths
solidly lashed together to resist the wind and other rava¬
ges of the elements.
Alexander von Humboldt was one of the many explorers
who gazed in awe and amazement at the Inca suspension
bridges. His description of one of them the Bridge of
From "Highway of the Sun" © Victor W. von Hagen-Duell, Sloan £ Pearce, N. Y.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
, ,...,.. Anu, 	XmAjm I wtmm^mà I miim\ miJmMmi
K ,,f.,Vn..J*- ^nliwtnMâmMitMdk .«/»-i*»»
\sar.imt, fi Ç.** O Sfym/rr* ¿a!., lAnig.« H~i
WmmmH*kmmm\ m*** tmmvCtfW mwmmmmmmmtC -£«
Au.iirptcl* ¡tkAan f"-' M»«*« ,«*«TrAf '*"''
J. |Éj_fj»nW« ?"< A« »n JLu**r,tjH4>-*iftk4t
Ymjimtirtrr rtliéV»«"r**!~*^" ' | mmmm
INCA HIGHWAY
(Continued)
San Luis Reywas the source of inspiration for novels by
Thornton Wilder and Prosper Mérimée. Humboldt consi¬
dered the whole Inca road system far superior to that
built by the Romans in Italy, France and Spain, and pro¬
nounced them "the most stupendous and useful works
ever executed by man."
But the Incas' passion for roads went much further
than building and engineering. They also set up a smooth
running system of road maintenance. A "Royal Commis¬
sioner of Inca Roads and Bridges" supervised a staff of
road inspectors whose duty it Was to tour the realm and
check on road conditions and on the toll-gate keepers
controlling the heavy traffic of llama trains laden With
produce. Large crews of yanakonas were always on hand
to sweep and clean the paved highways with brooms
made of vegetable fibre. Yvar Lissner did not exaggerate
when he said (in his book How Our Ancestors Lived) that
at the time when the roads of Europe were no more than
muddy, pot-holed ditches, the Incas had the finest high¬
ways anywhere in the world.
Surpassing Hannibal's Alpine road
The 16th century saw the Great Royal Highway con¬
verted into a major artery for violence and blood¬
shed. The Spaniards who landed in Ecuador bent on
conquering South America, found the vast Inca commu¬
nication network ideally suited for the quick seizure of
the great empire. Captain Pedro Cieza de Leon, writing
between 1533 and 1545, was the first European to give a
detailed description of the Inca roads "which surpass
24
those of the Romans as well as the road Hannibal built
over the Alps."
As they penetrated the land of the Incas,, the Conquis¬
tadores stared at the scene they saw with incredulous
amazement: down the wide, spacious highway came
groups of Indians carrying hammocks or litters contain¬
ing personages, of note. Other Indians drove trains of
llamas laden with sacks of coca leaves or ears of corn.
The very sight of these animals half ewe, half ass left
the Spaniards open-mouthed.
It soon became clear to them why the roads were in
such excellent condition: the only traffic on its paved
surface consisted of sandal-shod pedestrians and gentle-
footed llamas; Later, when the Conquistadores, landed
horses in the country (the Incas had never seen any be¬
fore) their iron-shod hooves and the wheels of the heavy
oxcarts were to cause havoc to the Llama Road and irre¬
parably damage the Great Royal Highway of the Incas.
Their conquest completed, however, the Spaniards
realized the advantages of the Inca road system and tried
to preserve it by following the Indian example, at least
in part. They adopted the llama caravans for carting
off the gold they collected either as booty or tribute or
which they extracted from the mines. Soon, long
caravans of Indians, columns of Spanish soldiers and
llamas could be seen heading for the coast where the
precious metal was stored aboard the Fleet of the Indies
for shipment to Spain.
The Inca road system was thus not only an artery of
blood but also of the gold of South America which went
to raise the standard of life of Europe and to add splen¬
dour to the Renaissance. An official chronicler of the
time, Leon Pinelo, estimated that 3,420 million gold doub¬
loons flowed into the coffers of Spain from the land of
the Incas.
The Royal Highway of the Incas, which cannot be
dissociated from the llama, the postal network, the gra¬
naries and roadside inns, was In fact the direct instru-
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
THE MIGHTY ROAD through the Inca
Empire, running straight as an arrow for more
than 3,000 miles from Colombia to Chile,
was one of the greatest achievements of road
engineering in history. Monuments, fortresses,
resting places for travellers temples and other
buildings were erected along the great
highway. Drawing (opposite page) showing a
section of the road and buildings, was made
about 1740 by Antonio de Ulloa, a Spanish
geographer near to the village of Cayambe In
what is now Ecuador. Photo (left), taken
recently In Bolivia, and engraving (below)
illustrate the contrast between road travel
then and now in this part of the world to
which the wheel was introduced many years
after the arrival of the Spaniards, who at first
made use the llama caravans for carting off the
gold they collected for shipment to Spain.
Engravings Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
) Almasy, Paris
ment in the economic expansion of the Inca State (Inca
society vested the entire wealth of the soil and sub-soil
in the State and there was no private ownership of land) .
As a result of the later neglect of .the Spaniards, the
inefficiency of Colonial, organization, the ravages of time
and above all, the excesses of the encomenderos (settlers)
who used the Inca roads as a quarry for the stone they
sought for their building, the whole highway network
finally disintegrated.
Nevertheless, traces of this unparalleled feat of engi¬
neering still remain today. In the course of numerous
journeys through Ecuador, I have personally come across
vestiges of the Inca Highway on several occasions in the
provinces of Imbabura and Pichincha. A Spanish geogra¬
pher, Antonio de Ulloa, visited this region in the 18th
century and has left us a detailed description of the
Highway, the watchtowers and the fortresses built by the
Incas (See drawing opposite page).
Little reed horses to cross the lakes
In the picturesque Imbabura Lake region, the Incas sup¬
plemented their road network by a fleet of small reed
boats and these are still to be seen in use today (the
Indians refer to them as "little reed horses"). The Azuay
region of Ecuador provides proof of the amazing solidity
of the Inca Highway and of the skill with which the
stones were fitted together. Despite the passing of cen¬
turies, and notwithstanding the continual, torrential rains
prevalent in the area, water has not succeeded in filter¬
ing through the joints between the stones. Instead, the
water has hollowed out a channel beneath the blocks of
stone and flows away like a river under the arches of
a bridge.
Further evidence of the Incas' skill, foresight and prac¬
tical turn of mind is seen in their secondary roads which
served as supply lines for the products vital to the king
dom. Thus Huayna Cápac built a road from Quito to
the Coca valley in the eastern slopes of the Andes for
the transport of the prized coca leaves; another road
knifed through the mountains to the coast and became
the supply route for shrimp and other sea food. This
coastal road also supplied platinum, mined in the region,
and salt extracted from the nearby island of Amortajada
close to the coast of Ecuador. Another road, running
laterally from Cuzco to the coast, made it possible to have
fresh fish (considered one of the greatest delicacies) in
the Inca capital within two days.
A striking example of the ingenuity and foresight of
the Inca engineers is visible today near Macu'sani in the
Carabaya gold country northwest of Lake Titicaca. In
his book' on the Inca roads, Highway of the Sun, Victor
von Hagen describes how the Royal Road climbs to a
CONTD ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
INCA HIGHWAY (Continued)
gM-_M-M-----MM-MM--MM-MMM---M----M-| - 	' -
\
THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAYthreading its way among peoples, scenery and climate as diverse as any on earth a
¡ng some 15,000 milessometimes follows the course of the ancient Inca roads. Above, a newly reconstructed stretch
Almasy, Paris
nd extend-
in Bolivia.
dizzying height of 14,800 feet and then passes under a
glacier. "Here," he writes, "the engineers, anticipating
the glacier's movement, had raised a retaining wall to
catch the cascading rocks and to divert the snows high
above the road. Here and there the eternal sweep and
retreat of the glacier had sent rock crashing into and
destroying a part of the road, but generally speaking it
was in a good state of preservation."
For centuries the Inca roads have aroused the interest,
curiosity and admiration of scholars and travellers alike.
But despite the fact that new information has been
collected on the subject since the 16th century, many
mysteries still remained unsolved. For example, we still
do not know the meaning of the apachetas, the little
mounds or pyramids found at intervals along the sides
of the roads. The mounds are made up of stones which
the Indians dropped there as they passed along the road.
This custom has been attributed to some strange, inexpli¬
cable superstition. It may, however, simply have been a
form of toll system by which travellers helped to trans¬
port the stone material needed for road maintenance.
But whether the apachetas were an offering to some deity
or the Inca people's contribution to the public works
system no one really knows.
Recent explorations have brought to light the existence
of a formerly unsuspected civilization on the Peruvian
26
coast the Land of the Chimus or "Kingdom of the Moon"
(the Chimus, who included the Nazcas and the Mochicas
with their fabulous pottery figurines, were worshippers
of the moon in contrast to the Incas who worshipped the
sun). The Inca's coastal Llano Road passed through the
land of the Chimus and it was over this highway that
the "Civilization of the Sun" of the Inca Empire came to
the "Kingdom of the Moon."
The road started at Tumbez, the legendary City of
Gold which the Conquistador Pedro de.Candia was the
first to visit and the riches of which he reported to
Pizarro. The latter raised an expedition to seize Tumbez
and the huge quantities of gold it harboured, but before
the Spaniards could get to the city the Indians had
emptied it of its riches in a spot which has yet to be
discovered. The Spaniards entered a ghost town. Today
it is nothing but a large rice field lying on the route of
the Pan-American Highway, which incidentally, follows
much the same itinerary as the old Inca Highway.
Despite the passing of centuries and the inclemencies
of nature, the general lines of the Royal Inca Highway
can still be discerned and stretches of it are still intact.
The suspension bridges in particular have withstood the
assault of time and are to be seen in Ecuador, Peru and
Bolivia where they are in use in districts where the wheel
is still unknown even today when the first man-made
rockets are being shot toward the moon.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
#
1	JtWaZ
-%-
«¡öS
-A^vrJU-
UNESCO COURIER. Reproduction prohibited.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
LANGUAGE: KEY FACTOR
OF INTEGRATION IN ISRAEL
by Pierre Vernier
Few countries have had to face educational problems
with such complications as those that have con¬
fronted the State of Israel in the last ten years. In
1948- the school population of Israel numbered some 100,000.
Today there are over 500,000 school children and students,
whose families have come from 60 different countries;
who use more than 70 languages and who have ways of
life and thought as varied as their tongues.
The measures taken to establish the educational system
of this country have been the subject of a study published
by Unesco under the title of "Education in Israel" in a
recent number of Unesco's "Education Abstracts." The
study, written by Mr. M. Avidor, Director-General of the
Ministry of Education of Israel, reviews "ten years' effort"
in the field of education.
Mr. Avidor points out that the salient factor in educa¬
tion in Israel is that "the school population has increased
five-fold during this period, although the general popula¬
tion has barely tripled itself. This brought in its train
serious problems of finding both buildings and materials.-
However, although at the beginning the situation was
difficult, in the last two or three years it has improved
considerably, each new village or community having a
school of its own, even if only a modest one."
Another acute problem was the shortage of teachers
whose numbers increased from 5,000 (1948) to 20,000 (1958).
During this period two major laws were passed affecting
education. The first, in 1949, made school attendance
compulsory for all children between the ages of 5 and
14. The second, in 1953, put most schools under State
control and regularized the system of education in all
schools. The period of compulsory education starts with
a year in kindergarten and moves through the elementary
schools. The young Israelis then have a choice of three
types of secondary education: secondary academic schools
under the control of the Ministry of Education and
Culture ; secondary agricultural schools under the
auspices of the Ministry of Agriculture or secondary trade
schools supervised by the Ministry of Labour. Students
continuing their studies can later proceed to one of three
fine universities : The Hebrew University in Jerusalem
which at the present time has six faculties arts, sciences,
médecine, law, agriculture and social science ; the Israel
Institute of Technology in Haifa which concentrates on
engineering and the Weizman Institute of Science at
Rehovot which engages in pure, and in some cases, applied
research in the exact sciences.
Classroom babble of tongues
Special schools have been established for young Arabs
living in Israel, mainly in the region of Nazareth
where 85 percent of the Arab population of the
country is concentrated. In these schools the Arab chil¬
dren, Moslem and Christian alike, are taught in Arabic,
Hebrew and English being regarded as second languages.
The school attendance of the boys is very satisfactory,
being over 90%, but only 50% of girls between the ages of
6 and 14 attend. Even this figure marks an improvement
on the period prior to the creation of the State of Israel.
The most interesting part of Mr. Avidor's report,
however, deals with the assimilation of the immigrants.
Coming from 60 countries, they speak more than 70
different languages and dialects and there was a danger
at one time that the Hebrew language would be submerged
under the influx of the new arrivals^some 700,000 in
four years.
"That this did not happen," writes Mr. Avidor, "Was due
to two factors the. multiplicity of languages which the
immigrants brought with them which forced them to use
one, and the rapid absorption of children into schools. In
each school the children arrived speaking a dozen or
more languages which made them turn quickly to a
common language, Hebrew, in order to communicate with
each other."
For the Israeli authorities, language is an essential
factor in the integration process, and the first objective of
the adult education programme, which is highly develop¬
ed all over the country, is to teach Hebrew to the new
arrivals. The Government, local authorities, labour or¬
ganizations and various voluntary bodies conduct courses
for adults, most outstanding of which are five or six-
month intensive courses held in the so-called "Ulpanim."
Though Hebrew constitutes a common denominator of
language, the problem still remains to find a common
denominator of culture for such a heterogeneous popula¬
tion in such a restricted area.
So adult education aims at giving a basic education to
new-comers who have never been to school and at the
same time providing general training to people over 16
who seek additional knowledge and skills. Courses have
been organised to this end all over the country and at all
levels by the Government, by the General Labour Federa¬
tion and by the Israeli Army which also performs a useful
educational function.
To accomplish so difficult a task, the educators and
leaders of Israel have used experimental methods and
Mr. Avidor notes that they have achieved more successes
than failures. This period of ten years has been long
enough to show that great progress has been made in
raising the cultural level of the new immigrants,
particularly of the younger generation, and the results
already obtained augur well for the future.
"Education in Israel" is one of a series of studies and
bibliographies published by Unesco on different national
systems of education.
WHAT ISRAELI YOUTH READS
The high literary standard of the books read by young
people in Israel is revealed by a recent study carried
out at the request of Israel's Minister of Education
and Culture among 1,500 eleventh grade pupils (aged 16-17)
attending 66 educational institutions.
Out of the 20 most widely read books, 16 were transla¬
tions and four were original Hebrew works. More than a
third of the young people questioned said that they preferred
translated works to original Hebrew ones. Heading the list
of favourite foreign authors was Tolstoy (32 per cent),
followed by Cronin (22 per cent), Steinbeck (20 per cent),
Pearl Buck (20 per cent) and Dostoïevski (19 per cent).
Among favourite Hebrew authors were Moshe Shamir
(65 per cent) and S.I. Agnon (26 per cent).
The survey showed that 80 per cent of the books read
by adolescents were novels. Top place was held by Hugo's
"Les Misérables", followed in order of popularity by "The
Diary of Anne Frank", "'War and Peace" and "The Caine
Mutiny". Researchers noted that all of the twenty most
popular books were prose works, one quarter were war
books, twelve had been published in recent years and three,
belonged to classical literature. .
Forty per cent of students questioned were members of
youth movements who had read an average of 56 books
apiece compared with 44 books read by non-members.
Secondary schools in the large towns have the highest
average of reading: 71 books. In teachers' training colleges
the rate is 60, in provincial secondary schools, 50. Classi¬
fication of readers according to parents' countries of origin
showed that the children of parents from Russia, Poland
and Lithuania read far more than any other groups.
Following the survey, the Ministry of Education and '
Culture has decided to introduce compulsory home reading
of books from a selected list in post-primary schools.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
A NUCLEAR REACTOR
NAMED WATER NYMPH
by Victor Hari
There are still people in India who have never seen a
motor-car or an eiectric light bulb. On the other
hand the first atomic reactor in Asia, outside the
Soviet Union, was built entirely by Indian scientists and
engineers at Trombay near Bombay arid will celebrate its
third birthday next August. Today India is the sixth
atomic power in the world not in terms of nuclear
weapons but research.
Why is nuclear research so vital to the progress of
India?
In the words of Dr. Homi Jehangir Bhabha, Secretary
of the recently constituted Atomic Energy Commission of
India: '"Atomic energy is the new branch of technology on
which the industrial revolution of the 20th century will
be based."
For India this 20th century industrial revolution is.
particularly important. In two years, the population of
the country will be 400 million and by 1975 it will amount
to 500 million. India's annual per capita income is Rs.295
($U.S.62) as compared to the American average of
Rs.10,000 (over $ U.S. 2,000). Thus we have to run even to
be able to stand still. .
But what about India's hydro-electric potential? What
about her coal reserves? Would it not be more realistic to
exploit these, first? The Government of India has under
construction a chain of multi-purpose river-valley projects
during the current Five Year Plan. But all the rivers
flowing across the face of India, and all the coal under¬
ground are not enough.
According to authoritative estimates India's coal
reserves amount roughly to 100 tons per head of popu¬
lation. This is one-twentieth of the per capita coal
reserves of China, roughly .one-thirty-fifth that of the
UK. and roughly one-hundred and fiftieth that of the
U.S.A. Now if an industrialized India were to consume as
much coal per head of population as. is done in the U.S.A.
today, it would exhaust its coal reserves in about
10 years!
India's major fuel: cattle dung
India's hydro-electric potential is estimated at between
35 and 40 million kilowatts. That is, when fully
harnessed and it is a costly and difficult process the
total hydel (hydro-electric) potential would be barely one-
tenth of a kilowatt per person, whereas it is 6 times more
in the U.S.A. and 11 times more in Norway even today!
And by the time the water power is fully harnessed,
the increase in population .will have, been formidable
enough to cancel the advantage.
The water power resources do not materially alter the
long-term problem of. India's energy needs. The world
reserves of oil are a small fraction of its coal reserves.
We therefore come to the inescapable conclusion that all
the reserves of hydro-electricity and conventional fuels in
India are insufficient to enable it to reach a standard of
living comparable with the present . standard of the
industrially advanced countries.
Actually the most widely used fuel in India today is
cattle dung. The ratio of coal, hydel, oil and wood to
dung for power use in India is 308 to 1,000, that is, two-
thirds of the fuel today is cattle dung: it amounts to about
225 million tons a year. Now if 225 million tons of dung
were put into the soil instead of being burnt, it would
make a big difference in agriculture.
Again for thermal power stations coal has to be
transported over great distances. Coal transport is
heavily subsidized, the subsidy varying from 30 to 100 per
cent of the cost of the coal. This enormous figure
becomes even more significant when it is "realized that
coal is one-third of the total ton-mileage of goods carried
by Indian railways. The relief to the railway-systemone
ton of uranium instead of 10,000 tons of coalwould be
enormous.
Energy hidden in the sands
But is nuclear power an economic proposition in India?
Estimates taken from England show that the capital
cost per kilowatt of atomic powerin a 250 mega¬
watt stationWould be Rs.1,600. Now, in a hydro-station
of the same power (250 Megawatts), for instance Koyna or
Rihand, the capital cost per Kilowatt is Rs.1.780 and
Rs.1.810. Of course, there are no fuel costs in a dam the
water does the job but nevertheless this large amount
of initial capital has to be found.
Has India the necessary nuclear fuel? A systematic
survey of uranium in ' the country began in 1949, and
modern techniques such as surveys by helicopters and
aeroplanes fitted with scintillo-meters were introduced in
1954. This has already doubled India's known reserves of
uranium. Although it is not rich in uranium, India can
produce enough for its purposes. Uranium will be con¬
verted into plutonium; and when this plutonium is fed
into a thorium -breeder-reactor, uranium-233 is bred from
the thorium and thorium can thus be used as the fuel
for India's power plants.
Once there. is enough plutonium for basic requirements,
natural uranium can be completely eliminated and only
thorium used.
India has one of the largest deposits in the world of
monazite, the thorium bearing sand. Thorium was.
previously imported (it was used for gas lamp mantles).
Today it is supplied by the Thorium Plant at Trombay and
India now exports thorium to countries in Europe and the
East. The important thing is that even the Indian known
reserves of uranium and thorium are equivalent in energy-
value to more than 30 times India's coal reserves. The
reserves of uranium and thorium are enough to support a
consumption of energy per person equal to that of the
most industrially advanced countries for over three
centuries.
The . Swimming Pool Reactor at Trombay, named
"Apsara"' water nymph which was inaugurated in 1957,.
last year completed 160,000 KW hours of operation, and
the demand on its time has increased so rapidly that it is
now running on a round-the-clock schedule.
The special facilities of this reactor are being exploited
to the maximum. One feature of the design, which
enables the core of the reactor to be worked at three
different positions, has proved particularly useful.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
WATER
NYMPH
(Continued)
Reactor with a round-
the-clock schedule
The reactor has been used for experiments in physics
and as an irradiation facility in biological and chemical
Investigations, and also in the production of small
quantities of radio-isotopes. Many new and interesting
results have been obtained in the study of low energy
nuclear reactions, such as the angular distribution of
secondary radiations from fission and the number of
neutrons emitted from fast fission.
The reactor has also been used extensively in the
applications of atomic energy to agriculture and biology.
Various types of agricultural material such as linseed,
cotton, sugar-cane buds, tapioca and wheat have been
irradiated in this reactor. These samples have been
provided by various' research institutions all over India.
Several interesting observations on the effect of
radiation on biological cells have been observed, such as
the possibility of early ripening of rice, and similar
experiments on other types of agricultural material are in
progress. Small investigations and- medical therapy have
been produced. A plant has been set up for the
production of high purity radio-isotopes for medical work.
Larger quantities of these will available to the public than
hitherto supplied.
The reactor is also being used as a source of neutrons
for producing the rarer isotopes to study nuclear
spectroscopy, and as a source of sodium 24 for the analysis
of heavy water. The reactor is also used for studying
radiation damage and chemical processes.
Many universities and research institutions- are now
making use of the research facilities of this reactor, and
fellowships have been offered to students in South East
Asian countries, Poland and Yugoslavia.
Certain death to insect pests
Another reactor, the Canada-India Reactor, is being
built near the Apsara. The special steel dome which
will house it is already completed and the civil
engineering work is in progress which will be completed
by December 1959. A few months later it will go into
operation using natural uranium as fuel.
Work on the first atomic station in India is scheduled
to start this year but it is likely that foreign exchange
difficulties may hold up the work.
Thorium will replace uranium as the nuclear . fuel, but
the quantity of thorium India can use after a certain
period will depend on what is done now. It will depend
on how much plutonium is produced now from uranium
in the reactors. The rate of expansion of nuclear power
plants is entirely determined by this process of "breeding"
thorium. .
The peaceful uses of India's work in the field of radio¬
activity holds out great hope for the future. India's basic
problem is food. But the problem is only marginal, the
deficit being only about three per cent. Much more than
three per cent is lost from rotting and from the scourge
of pests.. It is possible to control both of these by
irradiation. Considerable research has already been done
elsewhere in insect control. This work will shortly be
taken up at Trombay. It may soon be possible to irradiate
grain which goes to granaries so that once the grain is
stored no pests will touch it and the grain will not rot
because the pests and weevils are killed by radiation.
A storage block of the Canada-India Reactor is being
designed for research in the preservation of food. It is
even possible to prevent the growth of some species of
pests in nature. Male pests are made sterile by
irradiation and the sterile males are then released into
the field during the breeding season. The female of the
species mates only once, and if mating occurs with a
sterile male she does not reproduce. This automatically
reduces the number of pests.
30
TWO GREAT EYES cover most of the head of the dragonfly, each eye
having from 20,000 to 25,000 tiny eyes joined together. Scientific obs¬
ervations appear to confirm that among insects, those equipped with
multi-lensed eyes like the dragonfly (above) perceive colours most easily.
Photos © R.H. Noailles
BIRDS REACT in general to vivid colours and discern yellows, reds, greens
and oranges with special clarity. It is the brilliance of colour that attracts
a bird, whether it be some conspicuous patch on a plumage, the petals of a
flower or the glitter of bright objects. Photo shows a young rock dove.
MEMBERS OF THE SHRIMP FAMILY, whether of the larger species
such as prawns (above) or the smaller common salt water shrimp are known
to have colour sense. Probably all. the fish species which can change their
colour to match their surroundings can see those, and perhaps other colours
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1959
'Aficionados' won't believe this, but...
BULLS DO NOT SEE RED
by David Gunston
Do animals see colours? It is an interesting question,
hard to answer fully and conclusively. We, who
see everything coloured, can scarcely imagine a
world totally devoid of colour. For this reason we tend
at first to assume that all other creatures see the same
multi-coloured scene as ourselves. This is not so, of
course.
Colour is in itself such an arbitary, intangible thing,
and colour sense a faculty so difficult to test or explain,
that it has always been difficult for scientists to expound
about it with assurance. No object .really contains
colour, it merely absorbs the white light of daylight, as
everything does, reflecting back only one of the
components of that light, of the spectrum. Thus a green
leaf absorbs all the hues of the spectrum except green,
which it reflects, thus appearing itself to be green to
our eyes.
Just try to explain to a blind person, for instance,
what' red is without the use of comparison. It is quite
impossible. Quite' apart from the widespread prevalence
of partial or minor human colour blindness, and the
different interpretation put on the same intrinsic colour
by different people, it is also as well to remember that
our appreciation of colour is still developing and
changing. For instance, Homer always called the sea
wine-red, and the Ancient Greeks frequently referred
to the normal human face as green!.
Ultimately, everything depends on the optical receiving
apparatus involved.: A slight defect or variation there,
and the, person concerned may be partially colour¬
blind perhaps owing to the lack of one of the three
light-sensitive "pathways" from retina to brain. Each
transmits its own primary colour, red, green or blue (1),
Most people we call colour-blind are in fact only partly
so, having the green pathway missing, while a much
smaller group lack the red pathway, and so are red-
blind. These variations are physically very slight, and
are confined entirely to what we know as the nervous
system; there is thus the strongest evidence that
animals, many of which have eyes closely similar to our
eyes, lack these small features which give a colour sense
entirety.
Monochrome world of the mammals
From all this we can see just how difficult it is to apply
our own limited and tentative knowledge of colour
vision always remembering that we, ourselves, may
in some slight respect be colour-blindto other creatures.
The subject is one that, has provoked a great deal of
research, much of it inconclusive.
It is endlessly difficult to be dogmatic about whether
an animal can see a colour. No animal can reply
articulately to a direct question. Furthermore, in almost
all tests made with animals it is difficult to be absolutely
sure that the subject of the experiment is not choosing
or distinguishing between the colours shown by bright¬
ness or whiteness, and not by colour. For that reason,
any test that is to be of value must employ colours
of identical brightness and proportion of whiteness.
Otherwise, the creature, particularly if it is an intelligent
one, may distinguish between red and green solely by
brightness, just as many colour-blind human beings do.
(1) The term "primary colours" has become a somewhat elastic
description, embracing several different groups of colours distinc¬
tive for certain purposes. Red, yellow and blue are primary colours
to the artist, but scientifically speaking, the three primaries, or basic
colours each requiring its own cone cells in the eye for receiving it,
are red, green and blue (or violet). All the 160 odd colour shades
known to normal human beings can be made up of varying mixtures
of these three primaries but as light-waves, not paints.
But within the obvious limitations, we do know some¬
thing of the subject. Enough, for Instance, to say quite
definitely that almost all the mammals, with the notable
exceptions of the apes and the monkeys, do not see
colours at all. They live in a world of blacks and whites
and à fair range of greys. What they do often see quite
clearly is the difference in the intensity of the blacks,
and in the light intensity of the whites and greys, which
not infrequently leads people into thinking that animals
like dogs must in fact see certain colours.
How many times has a fond owner of a pet dog sworn
that his. or her animal can always, recognise a certain
coat or dress when worn by someone the dog may not
know, or can tell a particular dish or cushion solely by
its colours! It may sound strange to live in a monochrome
world, but most mammals are nocturnal, or at least cre¬
puscular, in habit, venturing forth only when the world
itself is a. shadowy, dark colourless place, lit only perhaps
by the pale deceiving light of the moon.
Learning to feed by colours
Bur we ourselves might not find it so strange. We have
never thought ordinary black-and-white movies
unnatural, and most newspaper and magazine photo¬
graphs are still reproduced in monochrome, yet we
recognise them as a reflection of life. Even a simple
black-and-white line drawing may be uncommonly
natural and vivid to our eyes; for all the human passion
for colour, we actually feel its absence less than we
imagine.
Dogs, cats, rabbits, rats, horses, sheep and even bulls,
we are certain, do not know colour in our sense of the
term. A great many experiments have been made on the
colour vision of bulls in Spain, in connexion with the
bull-fighting technique, and although they have all
shown that no bull can distinguish red as red, clear and
distinct from any other shade, and that bulls gener¬
ally are not in any way sensitive to red, the age-old art
of the toreador and his assistants with their red cloaks
is unlikely to be changed The red cloak is part of the
tradition of the sport and will doubtless remain, even
though those who use it know full well that it is the
fluttering, taunting sight that induces the beast to charge,
not its colour. A bull determined to charge will do-
so regardless of what colour is dangled before it.
A good deal of experimenting with other mammals
has achieved similar results, particularly with cats, horses,
rats and dogs. The tests usually take the form of training
the animal to associate food with a particular colour,
whilst showing it at the same time another colour un¬
accompanied by food. When the creature makes the
correct choice, more often than not, the colour with
no food attached must be gradually changed in intensity
to make sure that it is not only relative brightness that
influences the subject's decision.
If, at a certain stage in this colour "training", a change
in brightness is reached where the animal's reaction
breaks down and it expects food equally on either colour,
we can say with certainty that it is colour-blind, at least
by human standards. On the other hand, if the training
holds, and the creature invariably picks the correct colour
to obtain food, however much the intensity of the no-
food colour is altered, then we can deduce that it is able
to distinguish that particular pair of colours one from
another. However, this Is far from conclusive evidence
on colour vision, so the animal must then be re-trained
for another quite different pair of colours. Such experi¬
ments are inevitably lengthy and difficult, and care has
always to be taken external influences like smell, noise,
position of food, time of the day, presence of other colours
and distracting lights, etc. are avoided.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
BULLS DO NOT SEE RED re«,*»*»
Nevertheless, such tests have clearly shown the inability
of mammals generally to recognize colours, and the fact
that the apes and the monkeys do have good colour sense.
In this connexion between two groups of mammals, it is
Interesting to note that these colour-conscious species are
the only ones to have really bright colours on their own
bodies. (It might also be claimed that they have higher
intelligence, but there is no correlation between a
creature's intelligence and its colour sense birds, fish,
reptiles and Insects can in many cases see colours.) One
thinks immediately of the bright blues and pinks of
the mandrill and other apes, whose significance in
courtship rites is well known.
Most other mammals have bodies of duller hue: drab
greys, browns, black, fawn in endless combinations, or
white itself, largely designed for unobstrusiveness or
natural camouflage. Where a brightly-coloured animal
is seen, it is usually the result of human inter-breeding,
as with dogs, cats and cattle, or else the natural
camouflage shade of a creature viewed away from its
habitat. The red of the dog fox, the chestnut of the
squirrel, the golden-brown of the bear all merge harmoni¬
ously into their natural backgrounds. In fact, this pre¬
sence of bright colours is a rough guide to colour vision in
nature, if allowances is made for the possibility of natural
camouflage.
Hens are suspicious of blue grain
We see it most clearly shown with birds. They are
quite different from mammals, and can see most
colours with a vivid intensity. The striking
plumage of almost all birds plays a big part in their court¬
ship display, as everyone knows, which is ready proof of
their ability to see bright colours. Whether Darwin was
right in supposing that the bright coloration of male birds
has a survival value by being attractive to the female is a
matter for conjecture. ^What is obvious is the part such
plumage plays in a bird's life.
Birds generally see yellows, reds, greens . and oranges
most clearly. They cannot see blue so well witness the
comparative rarity of really bright blue birds while very
few birds can see violet, as far as we can tell. That shade
is. even less common on a bird. In addition, where blues
or purples do occur in avian plumage, they are nearly
always very brilliant, as with jays, kingfishers and
macaws, which seems to suggest that these shades can
only be distinguished by birds if they are unusually bright.
But the Australian lyre-bird, that feathered oddity of
great beauty and mystery, can see both blue and violet,
for it goes out of its way to select flowers of these colours
with which to adorn its arbour. In the main, however, it
is brilliance of colour that attracts a bird, whether it be
some conspicuous patch on a mate's or suitor's plumage,
the petals of a flower, the shining beam of a lighthouse
at night, or the glitter and sparkle of bright objects which
jackdaws and magpies steal and hide away.
Experiments on birds have been rather fewer than on
mammals, possibly because their ability to see colours is
so obviously demonstrated by their own persons. They
have also been almost completely confined to those species
Which can be kept in captivity with ease. One interesting
series of experiments with the ordinary domestic hen does
however illustrate the peculiar pitfalls present with
colour vision tests on birds. Grain was placed before the
hens and illuminated by a spectrum of coloured lights.
They immediately ate all the red, green and yellow grain,
but left that in the blue light, from which it was not
unnaturally concluded that these birds, at least, were
blue-blind. Only, later was it discovered, by further tests,
that hens would eat blue grain with a little persuasion.
The only reason they were originally shy of it was that
they never normally touch any kind of blue-coloured food.
Some fish can see certain colours. Perch, trout,
shanny, minnows and others have been proved by tests
to be able to recognize a fair range of shades. Perch and
other species have been regularly fed on red-stained
larvae, and then easily deceived with red wool. While
similar tests have been successful with food dyed yellow,
orange, green and brown. There is good evidence, too,
that prawns and shrimps have a colour sense. Probably
R. H. Noailles
BUTTERFLIES are classed among those insects which are known to
have the most marked sense of colour.. (Photo, greatly magnified, shows
a butterfly on a flower.) In the case of many pollinating insects, however,
the attraction to flowers is created as much by scent as by sight of
coloursas in the popularity of willow, ivy and lime flowers to bees.
all those fish species which can change their colour to
match their surroundings can see those, and possibly
other, colours. Curiously enough, however, no conclusive
tests have been made with chameleons, in spite of their
well-known colour-changing ability, although this crea¬
ture probably does see some colours. Certainly turtles :
have the faculty, and so have many lizards. Lizards
known to detest salt have been trained to reject salt-
soaked meal-worms on paper of several different colours.
Mosquitoes prefer a black shirt
Insects generally have a colour sense but it varies
considerably with species. There have been more
tests on the colour vision of bees than any other
creatures, which is hardly surprising in view of their value
as pollinators and honey-producers. A simple experiment
with bees was conducted as follows. Small squares of grey
paper of different shades but equal brightness were set
like the squares of a draught-board, and one blue square
was included in the middle. Each square was fitted with
a. tiny food dish, but only the blue square's dish had
syrup in it. After lengthy trials a bee could be taught to
fly straight to the iblue square, even when its position was
moved about the. board. Yet when a red paper of equal
brightness replaced the blue, the bee was flummoxed, and
could not tell it from the greys.
Bees are not only blind to reds: they live in a world
of blues, purples and yellows only, but they (and other
insects) can see further into ultraviolet than we can.
Many pollinating insects are of course attracted to
flowers as much by scent as by sight of colours witness
the popularity of willow, Ivy and lime flowers to bees.
As a rule only those insects with highly developed,
multi-lensed eyes have good colour vision. Dragonflies
probably have the best colour sense in the insect world,
with perhaps hoverflies, and some butterflies and moths,
as runners-up. House-flies know blue, and dislike it
enough to avoid blue-washed windows, or blue walls and
curtains, while mosquitoes, which are known to distinguish
yellow, white and black, appear to prefer the last-named
colour. In a special test made in an infested region in
Oregon, seven men ' wore / shirts of different colours.
Within half a minute. the black shirt had attracted most
insects, 1,499 to only 520 on the next infested "shirt, a
white one !
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Juno 1959
Letters to the Editor
VINES FOR COLD CLIMATES
Sir,
In your magazine I found a signpost
showing me how an ordinary person
can help to spread fundamental, know¬
ledge and also become an intermediary
for the exchange of information on
successful applications in science. I got
my idea from a story you published
about someone who excavated some
animal . fossils and decided to share
these precious relics among museums in
several countries.
Since 1 retired my hobby has been
horticulture, and on my small plot I
grow fruit trees mostly of the dwarf
variety and also grape-vines. Here, in
the Don region, vines need winter
protection and this means covering
them with earth. But burying them in
the Autumn and uncovering them in the
Spring is hard work, and the fact that
the buds tend to rot underground
affects the quality of the grapes.
The Vine-Growing Institute of
Novotcherkassk has therefore success¬
fully produced several dozen different
kinds of vines which resist temperatures
as low as between minus 30 and minus
36 degrees centigrade and it has made
them available to Soviet agriculturalists.
I have three of these vines and have
already had grapes from them.
As soon as I was sure that my vines
were capable of producing good quality
grapes I offered to send some to China.
Professor Chen-Tsun of the Peking
Agricultural Academy accepted my offer
and in return has sent me seeds of plants
which are rare here. These include
the prunus tormentosa (Chinese cherry)
the Chinese lemon tree and also the
wild vines of the Amur region which
are especially resistant to frost.
Now I would like to share my modest
stocks with some amateur horticulturists
in Western countries and thus, in some
small way, perhaps contribute to the
maintenance of peace in the world.
With the frost-resisting vines I think the
growing of vines should begin in Finland
and other Nordic countries. Perhaps
through your magazine I could make
contact with these countries.
Ibrahim S. Aitov
Simferopolskaya ul. 10,
Rostov-on-Don, U.S.S.R.
MORE ABOUT YOUNG PEOPLE
Sir,
Each month I am delighted to find
such an interesting selection of articles
in The Unesco Courier... I do not
agree with those who say that the level
of your articles is too highor too low.
It is impossible to please everyone. So
continue to choose the best you can
from current events and from the
material provided by your contributors.
I would like, however, to join the
Australian reader who asked for articles
on youth problems. But please also
tell us about the men and women who
are trying to solve these problems, about
the remarkable advances in the methods
used and about the institutions which
are successfully overcoming the sad
problems of maladjusted children and
juvenile delinquency. People are
unaware of much of this or are
insufficiently informed. They would
certainly be interested by it.
R. Trial
Aubais, France
AFRICAN MUSICAL ANTHOLOGY
Sir,
In your February number you an¬
nounced the issue, under the auspices of
the International Music Council, of
three records entitled "'An Anthology of
African Life." Can these records be
purchased? If so, where can they be
obtained and what do they cost? '
M. Périer
Lausanne, Switzerland
Editor's note: "An Anthology of African
Life" can be ordered from Ducretet-
Thomson, 3 bis, avenue de Friedland,
Paris, and costs 6,570 fr. frs.
YOUTH & NATURE PROTECTION
Sir,
In answer to your correspondent
M. Teulon, Aude, France, who enquires
whether any organization can help in
the education of young people about the
protection of Nature, I would offer
information on the activities of the
World Federation for the Protection of
Animals which has been admitted to
Consultative Status by Unesco.
This Federation has, as members,
over .150 animal protection societies in
more than 40 countries and has,
therefore, unique facilities . available
in many languages which are at the
service, cf any individual, organization
or government.
The aim of this Federation is to
further by educational, scientific and
cultural methods the humanitarian
outlook of Man towards the lower
creatures. Therefore the office of this
Federation acts also as a clearing house
in this field for information on
literature, exhibits and films which are
available in the different countries and
languages. If your correspondent will
be good enough to communicate with
the Federation detailing the needs of
his centre the Secretariat will endeavour
to supply such information or material
as is available.
Cecil Schwartz
Secretary General
46 Grosvem/r Road
Luton, England
ONE WORLD LANGUAGE
Sir,
In your April issue an Israeli suggests
that in a "truly international" university
courses should be given in "the main
languages, English, French, Spanish and
Russian." One wonders what Germans
will think of this set of languages or
a Chinese in, say, the year 2000; or
a. visitor from Mars. No, a United
Nations . University should use one
world language which is fair to all, not
the language of any particular nation.
The suitability of Esperanto has been
proved.
To my mind, rather than a multi¬
lingual university there should be an
intensive drive to teach Esperanto in
the top classes of primary schools as
soon as teachers can be trained, and
to use Esperanto in higher education as
the medium of instruction for teaching
world history and other universal sub¬
jects.
CM. Catlicr
Torquay, England
GANDHI'S LIGHTER SIDE
Sir,
I am writing a book on Gandhi's
wit and humour and instances of Gandhi
in lighter vein. I invite from 'your
readers instances of Gandhi's humour
with them or with any others they
know of, so that these facts could be
included in my book.
S. Durai Raja Singam
P.O. Box 16, Kuantan
Malaya
FOR OR AGAINST ABSTRACT ART
Sir,
I read with great enjoyment your
special issue devoted to Unesco's new
headquarters ' (November, 1958). As
usual, it was produced with abundant
good taste and the subject was given a
most convincing presentation.
I am studying technology at univer¬
sity, but I am also intensely interested
in painting. I was brought up to appre¬
ciate the works of painters like Nes-
terov, Repine and Vrubel, but this does
not mean that I think any the less of
paintings by Picasso or Matisse, and in
no way do I rate modern Western
painting as a falsification of true art.
I read the article by R.J. Laurenza,
"The Language of Abstract Art", with
the closest interest. It offered some in¬
teresting ideas on the important role
which the development of photography
has played in the evolution of abstract
art, on the link between abstract art
and the successive strata of history, and
also on the impact which science has
had on painting styles. Yet nothing
that was said offered proof of the main
thing: the aesthetic value of abstract
art.
I should like one of your future
issues to be devoted to the subject of
modern art, including conclusive argu¬
ments "for" and "against" abstract art.
It would also be useful to publish
reproductions of works by modern
painters the realists, including Soviet
artists. These reproductions (Soviet)
could even by judged and commented
on by Western critics; the results would
be interesting.
Rurik Povileiko
Baku, U.S.S.R.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
*I*RE-FAB' HOMES FOR POLAR
EXPLORERS: A pre-fabricated two-storey
house for polar explorers, which weighs
about twenty times less than a conventional
house of its size, has been designed by a
group of architects in Leningrad. The
completed structure consists of one or two-
room flats with central heating, water
mains and showers, drying cupboards and
electric cooking stoves. It can be packed
for transportation by tractor-drawn sleighs
or helicopter and can be assembled at a
base camp by about a dozen men.
AFRICA'S NEW TV NETWORK:
A television network is to go into
operation in Western Nigeria later this
year. Two transmitting stations with'
link equipment are to be set up near
Ibadan and Ikeja covering the largest
concentrations of population in the
country. These stations will devote
about half their transmission time to
educational programmes. Western
Nigeria has pioneered in the field of
education it was the first African
country to introduce universal free
primary education.
Electricity from the atom:
Recently the atomic reactor at Marcoule in
southern France started to supply electricity
which is now being used for industrial or
domestic purposes. France thus became the
fourth country in the world to use electricity
obtained from nuclear sources, the others
being the United Kingdom, the United
States and the U.S.S.R.
OUR UNKNOWN OCEANS: Today
when space research is much in the
news there is still another vast field of
research much nearer to home which
has been barely touched upon: oceano¬
graphy. Though the oceans cover two-
thirds of the earth's surface, scientists
admit that they know less about them
and the ¡ife hidden in their depths than
about the face of the moon. Now
efforts are being made to increase
exploration of the seas. Unesco has
already started a project in this field
and recently a special committee
appointed by the U.S. Academy of
Sciences discussed an ambitious ten-year
programme for unlocking the ocean's
treasures. Recommendations of this
committee include grants to universities
for the ' creation of departments of
oceanography, fellowships for research
students, the equipment of laboratory
ships etc. Other proposed projects
include mining of the ocean floor, some
parts of which are known to be rich
in deposits of cobalt, nickel and man¬
ganese, and other activities which would
call for a vast network of signal buoys,
research ships, bathyscaphs and ice-
breaking submarines.
w
the Electrical Research Association has
recently devised and tested an automatic
load-distributor which passes the power
output to various loads according to
priorities which can be fixed in advance.
Last December, for example, an 8 K.W.
wind-power plant gave an output of 1,080
KWH for a monthly average wind-speed
of 12 to 13 m.p.h. The diesel-electric set
held in reserve was only ' needed to
provide 17 KWH in the month.
ORGANIZATION UNDERWATER:
A new international organization with
a rather unusual title, "International
Underwater Confederation" , (Confédéra¬
tion Mondiale des Activités Sub-Aqua-
tiques) recently came into being. It was
founded at a meeting in Monaco
attended by delegates of national feder¬
ations of skin-divers and undersea
explorers from some 15 countries. The
confederation has set up two committees:
one devoted to underwater sports and
the other to technical problems involving
underwater photography, archaeology,
biology and speleology.
.INDIA'S YOUNG SCIENTISTS:
Over 300 science clubs are now operating
in secondary schools and in agricultural
extension services in India. The Science
Club movement was started by the All-India
Council for Secondary Education during
the 1957-58 school year. Besides organizing
lectures, discussions and practical scientific
work, the clubs help to maintain weather
records, set up science libraries and organize
scientific exhibitions.
NEVER TOO EARLY...: Some 400
teachers in schools in 40 countries are
making steady progress in showing that
building international understanding is
something that should start in the class
room. How they do so through the
Associated Schools Project sponsored by
Unesco was described recently by T.
Ivor Davies, head of Associated Schools'
work in Britain, to educators at the
Conference of Internationally-Minded
Schools, held at Unesco House, Paris.
He pointed out that teaching about
other peoples and their contribution to
the world can be included in nearly
every course in geography, science and
mathematics... and even a minimum
effort can jtelp to eradicate prejudices
among schoolchildren.
J. V NEWS OF NEIGHBOURS:
Televiewers in several European countries
have recently been able to follow on their
screens events in each other's countries on
the same day they have taken place. This
has been made possible by an experiment
in Eurovision an international television
link-up planned by the European Broad¬
casting Union for the exchange of news
programmes. . Programmes were filmed in
various countries and transmitted over the
Eurovision network during off-peak hours.
They were recorded on kinescope by the
receiving stations and, after editing,- were
included in newscasts on national networks.
JAPAN'S PEACEFUL ATOMS:
By an' agreement which was signed in
Vienna recently Japan became the first
country to buy nuclear fuel for research
purposes from the International Atomic
Energy Agency, and the Agency assum¬
ed its major role as a supplier of such
material for peaceful activities. Japan
is buying three tons of natural uranium
for use in a low power research reactor.
The uranium in question will be
furnished to the Agency free of charge
by the Canadian Government as part
of its contribution to the IAEA pro¬
gramme.
IND-POWER FOR THE FARM:
To supply electricity to isolated farms and
rural homes a wind-driven generator can
be an economic proposition providing that
all the energy becoming available at random
times is put to good use. In Great Britain
34
2,000 OF WORLD'S ELECTRONIC CALCULATION
SPECIALISTS TO MEET AT UNESCO CONFERENCE
A UNESCO-sponsored International Conference on Information Processing
will bring some 2,000 of the -world's leading authorities on electronic cal¬
culators to Paris this month. Opening at the Sorbonne on June 15, the
conference will be attended by scientists from thirty-three countries of Europe,
Asia, the Middle East, the Americas, Africa and the Pacific region. Among the
largest national groups due to take part are France (300), Germany (160), Italy
(60), Japan (20), the United Kingdom (100), the United States (300), and the
U.S.S.R. (60). . At sessions in UNESCO's Headquarters, from June 16 to 20,
specialists will hear and discuss reports on such themes as : methods of digital
computing, logical design of digital computors, common symbolic language for
digital computors, automatic translation of languages, pattern recognition and
machine learning. In all, fifty-eight scientific papers will be discussed. To
familiarize the public with the principles and applications of electronic calcu¬
lation, special lectures will be. given each evening, while plenary sessions and
symposia will also be open to the public. The first international exhibition of
information processing equipment '"Auto-Math 59" is being held in Paris
at the same time, and will thus serve both as a background to and illustration
of the main conference themes.
o
z
<
Z
<
ai
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW ON
THE WORLD
Once a month The UNESCO
Courier presents to its
readers a panorama of the
modern world. Without being
either too learned or too "popu¬
lar" in its approach, its well-
illustrated articles give a vivid
picture of the endless diversity
of peoples and countries. There
is no facet of the present-day
world on which it does not
touchthe sciences man has
developed, the cultures he has
created, the knowledge he has
amassed.
The Unesco Courier, now
in its twelfth year, does more
than merely satisfy the desire
for information about contem¬
porary problems; it throws
light on every aspect of human
endeavour, strengthens the links
between the peoples in every
corner of the globe, fosters
international understanding and
advances the cause of peace.
You can help by telling your
friends, colleagues and business
associates or your local libra¬
rian about The Unesco Cour¬
ier. It also makes an ideal
birthday gift. As a gift for
your friends abroad, you can
subscribe to the French, Rus¬
sian or Spanish editions.
A YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION
COSTS ONLY 10/- stg.; $3.00;
600 fr. frs or equivalent. (See
National Distributors, below.)
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C\, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, C.CP. 338.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité.
16, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado 113, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, T. C.CP. 12598-48.
(600 fr.)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura. P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I ; 36a, Mount Road., Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House. New Delhi; Raikamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2 Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge. Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (£.l./4..)
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P. O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (600 fr.).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174. Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos
2018, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo. P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN. Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street. P.O.
Box 724. Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50) other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. For " Le Courrier de ('Unesco "
only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des Vieux-
Grenadiers, Genève, C.CP. 1. 4811 (frs. S.
6.50)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E. 1.(1 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
AIR POLICE WATCH OVER
CITY TRAFIC
To keep the stream of weekend and holiday traffic moving
smoothly, New York City's police department supplements
its ground force with a fleet of helicopters. This double-
page photo shows a helicopter hovering over a main road
system in Queens, one of New York's five boroughs. Air
police constantly send radio traffic reports to headquarters
as thousands. of automobiles move out of and into the city
over scores of main thoroughfares, bridges, tunnels and
ferries. Reports are transmitted to motorists via radio. Air
police observe road congestion in the making and direct re¬
routing of traffic by radio? Spotting break-downs-, they call
for a repair truck. In emergencies they air-lift critically
ill or injured persons over congested highways to hospital.
]]>
</page>
</document>
