<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078423eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window open on the world
Suri er
stg. - Canada: 30 cents - France: 1 F
CE
UNESCO
ARCHIVES
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
I
i
USIS photos
THE GREAT EMANCIPATOR. Top, the immense
statue of Abraham Lincoln looks down on a vast
crowd gathered at a 1964 rally in support of civil
rights legislation before the Lincoln Memorial in
Washington D.C. This year the.world commemor¬
ates the hundredth anniversary of the death of
Lincoln, whose Emancipation Proclamation of 1862
opened the way to freedom for Negro slaves in the
United States, and the centenary of the final abo¬
lition of slavery through the adoption of the Thir¬
teenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, on
-December 18, 1865. Bottom, some of the two mil¬
lion people who annually climb the steps of the
Lincoln Memorial to honour the Great Emancipator.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
M WINDOW 0»IM OM TH| WO* 16
»r kurier
APRIL 1965 - 18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
And Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg.; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2 years : 27/-stg. ; 1 8 F. Single copies 1 /6-stg. ;
30 cents ; 1 F.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and two
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent.
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co.. New York.
8
12
16
20
28
29
34
BIOLOGY LOOKS AT RACE
by Georghi F. Debetz
A DOCUMENT OF PARAMOUNT IMPORTANCE
The biological facts of the race question
THE FUTURE OF 'HOMO SAPIENS'
Views of a biologist
by Jean Hiernaux
JOHANN MENDEL
by Jean Rostand
FATHER OF GENETICS
APARTHEID IN SOUTH AFRICA
A stark report by the United Nations
BIBLIOGRAPHY ON RACE
IT IS STILL NOT TOO LATE...
Proposals for a new course in South Africa
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
Allcorrespondence shouldbe addressedto the Editor-in- Chief.
Cover photo
Different yet similar, like
all human beings : two
photographs, positive and
negative, of the same sculp¬
ture by Antoine Bourdelle.
Musée Bourdelle, Paris
N° 4
1965
MC 65-1-201 A
On the occasion of this special issue on race, the Unesco Courier
wishes to recall the work carried out by the late Alfred Métraux
(1902-1963) who for 13 years was in charge of Unesco's pro¬
gramme on racial questions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
BIOLOG
LOOKS
RACE
by Georghi F. Debetz
At a Unesco meeting in Moscow, twenty-two scientists
drew up and unanimously adopted, on August 18, 1964,
a 13-point statement on the biological aspects of the
race question (see page 8 for full text). Here the chair¬
man of the meeting reviews its work and conclusions.
"- ..' 8f . :; ". , yijjfig
Gallo-Roman sculpture from the
3rd century B.C., now in the Bo-
rély Museum, Marseille, France.
{('. Jean Suquet. Paris
4
ACISM is the^expression of a system of thought
which is fundamentally anti-rational. Hate and
racial strife feed on scientifically false ideas, and live on
ignorance. They can also derive from scientifically sound
ideas which have been distorted or taken out of context,
leading to false implications. To demonstrate these errors
of fact and of reasoning, and to spread knowledge of the
conclusions reached by different scientific disciplines,
Unesco convened in 1949 a meeting of scientists .from
different countries (1) to draw up a declaration on the
nature and significance of racial differences.
The text prepared by these experts and published by
Unesco in 1950 was well received by the public, but drew
some criticism from anthropologists and geneticists who
considered that it caused confusion between race as a bio¬
logical fact and the idea of race as a social phenomenen.
Unesco therefore called a second conference in 1951, this
time exclusively for specialists in physical anthropology and
in human genetics. This group drew up a new text in which
the main conclusions of the earlier declaration were main¬
tained, others amended and certain deletions made. The
text of this new declaration was sent to fifty geneticists and
anthropologists for their comments, and the results of this
inquiry, including favourable comments and adverse cri¬
ticisms, were published in book form under the title "The
Race Concept."
Since then Unesco's action has been focused more on
the social aspects of race than on the biological ones. On
the other hand, scientific advances in the field of human
biology during the past fifteen years have clearly shown
the need for a fresh study of the 1951 declaration and its
revision in the light of the latest biological discoveries.
It has also been felt that its scope should be enlarged by
encompassing several points, dealing with the nature and
forms of racial prejudice in inter-racial situations, that were
not previously covered.
Unesco therefore decided to hold two successive meet¬
ings: one in 1964 to cover the biological aspects, and a
second, in 1966, to deal with the social and ethical aspects
of the problem and to draft a statement which, taking
account of the results of the 1964 meeting, would englobe
both the biological and social aspects of the problem of
race.
The first of these meetings was held in Moscow in
August 1964 immediately after the VII Congress of Anthro¬
pological and Ethnological Sciences which had taken place
in that city. It was attended by anthropologists and ethno¬
logists from 17 countries (2).
During eight sessions twenty-five reports devoted to the
main scientific problems related to the study of human races
were discussed. At the last two sessions a 13-point decla-
(1) Brazil, France, India, Mexico, New Zealand, U.K., U.S.A.
(2) Belgium, Brazil, Canada, Czechoslovakia, Federal Republic of
Germany, France, India, Japan, Mexico, Nigeria, Norway, Poland,
Senegal, U.K., U.S.A., U.S.S.R., and Venezuela.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
agi
^m
W&&MS'j&Äi
^
:,;o._
ration was drafted and adopted unanimously (see page 8).
This text will provide the biological elements for the new
declaration on race and racial prejudice to be drawn up
in 1966.
At one time the essential object of discussions between
anthropologists was to decide whether man had one or
several ancestors, whether the various races derived from
a single species of monkey or from a variety of species.
Today, this question can be regarded as finally settled. It
was not even raised during the 1964 Moscow meeting. The
declaration merely notes, as if to sum up earlier discussions,
that "all living human beings belong to a single species,
known as 'Homo Sapiens* and are derived from a common
stock origin."
The keenest discussion was concerned with the nature
of the concept of race as applied to human beings and
with the scientific evidence for this concept. It might be
thought that no discussion is called for on this question.
Everyone knows that as far as many physical features are
concerned, the people in various parts of the world fre¬
quently differ as regards colour of skin, type of hair, facial
characteristics, etc. It is true that the number of features
which all men have in common is very much greater and it
is equally true that such common features are biologically
of much greater importance than the divergent features.
At the same time, differences do exist and are evident at a
glance. If, for instance, we were to compare groups made
up of Congolese, Swedes and Mongols selected at random,
we would have nó trouble in identifying each of the three
groups. They would not even need to be dressed differently
or to speak. Their physical features alone would distinguish
them.
While everyone is agreed on this point, many anthropo¬
logists are now calling attention to another equally indispu¬
table fact. If, for example, one were to go on foot from the
sources of the Nile to the Nile delta, then across the Arab
countries of Asia, through Turkey, Bulgaria, Rumania and
the Ukraine to northern Russia and finally towards Mongolia
via the homes of the Udmurt, Bashkir and Kazakh peoples,
no difference of physical type would be apparent between
the inhabitants of any neighbouring points on this route.
However, if one were to compare the people encountered
at the beginning, middle and end of the journey, the
differences between them would be manifest. It is for
this reason, say the opponents of racial classification,
that the division of mankind into rigidly distinct categories
is scientifically unsound and results in a completely
unacceptable schematic approach.
On the other hand, those who believe that human races
should be recognized as distinct entities argue that the
existence of transitional stages between any kind of phe¬
nomena should not lead us to deny the reality of such
phenomena. The hypothetical traveller would not observe
any difference in climate between two adjoining points on
the route nor between the local fauna, yet classification by
regions is useful and even essential to a knowledge of .
climate and fauna. "Where is the dividing line between 3
the mountain and the valley?" ask the defenders of
classification. "Nobody denies the existence of valleys and
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
AFRICA (Uganda) AFRICA (Cameroon) AFRICA (Sudan) AFRICA (Egypt)
ASIA (Iran)
BIOLOGY LOOKS AT RACE (Cont'd)
ASIA (India) ASIA (Cambodia) ASIA (Philippines)
Racism : a distortion of scientific facts
mountains simply because they cannot point to such a
line."
Opponents of classification point out that physical fea¬
tures change not only in space but, even more, in time.
In central Europe as in other regions/the human head has
become much rounder over the last eight centuries but
more recently has tended to lengthen again; the average
height in certain countries has risen by 10 centimetres in
the last 100 years; and so on. Those opposed to classifica¬
tion likewise emphasize the considerable degree of indivi¬
dual variation in regard to all physical features.
The average width of face among the people of Azer¬
baijan, for instance, is one cm. less than in the case of the
Kazakhs; but this measurement varies from one individual
to another and some of the former have broader faces than
some of the latter. Supporters of classification admit this,
but argue that sometimes and even fairly frequently
women are taller than men. Is this a reason, they ask, for
denying the obvious fact that men are generally bigger
than women?
Having noted that opinions differed as to the importance
of racial classifications, participants in the Moscow meeting
nonetheless unanimously felt able to reach certain con¬
clusions which, while not wholly eliminating the disagree¬
ments, did Indicate that opinions might be brought more
into harmony with each other.
One of the points in their declaration was that "as
entities defined by sets of distinctive traits, human races
are at any time in a process of emergence and dissolution."
Still more important is another point in the declaration,
contending that "certain physical characters have a univer¬
sal biological value for the survival of the human species,
irrespective of the environment. The differences on which
racial classifications are based do not affect these cha¬
racters and therefore it is not possible from the biological
point of view to speak in any way whatsoever of a general
inferiority or superiority of this or that race."
All the experts attending the Moscow meeting were
specialists in the field of biological science. But a genuinely
scientific survey cannot be kept within the framework of
a single science. Biologists dealing with human beings
cannot bypass the phenomena of social existence. It is
indeed because of social existence, as the declaration
points out, that "human evolution presents attributes of capi¬
tal importance which are specific to the species." "As a
consequence," the declaration adds, "general adaptability to
the most diverse environments is in man more pronounced
than his adaptations to specific environments."
This is one of the most important biological differences
between man and all other biological species and derives
from the very nature of man and his social life. The follow¬
ing point in the declaration should also be noted: "For long
millenia, progress made by man, in any field, seems to
have been increasingly, if not exclusively, based on culture
and the transmission of cultural achievements and not on
the transmission of genetic endowment. This implies a
modification in the role of natural selection in man today."
Racism, a system which falsifies scientific facts, auto¬
matically ascribes to men all those phenomena observed
among animals.
The biological elements in the declaration adopted by the
1964 Moscow meeting are therefore a barrier raised against
racism. Man is primarily a social being and the funda-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
r
EUROPE (Greece) EUROPE (Denmark)
ASIA (Japan)
7
AMERICA (Brazil)
EUROPE (Hungary) ASIA (Jordan)
On foot across the continents
A traveller making his way across the continents
would probably notice few differences in phys¬
ical type among the inhabitants of neighbouring
regions. Differences become obvious when
a comparison is made between people from
widely separated areas. Thus, say those anthro¬
pologists who reject the idea of racial clas¬
sifications, the division of human beings
into rigidly defined groups can only give a
schematic and scientifically unacceptable result.
Photos, from left to right : 1, 3, 4, 5, 6. 7, c Paul Almasy, Paris;
2, » C. Tardits; 8, UNRWA; 9. U nesco- Almasy ; 10, 13, Unesco;
11, Unations; 12. Unesco - P. A. Pittet; 14, SUDENE.
mental nature of his history is determined by social
phenomena.
As is well known, wherever racists are in power they
seek to set men of differing races against each other and
to use every possible means of preventing the natural
intermingling process of the human race. One of
the racists' favourite techniques for falsifying science is to
assert that interracial marriages are harmful and that the
children of such marriages are physically and psychically
"deficient."
Here, the declaration is clear and categorical: "It has
never been proved that interbreeding has biological dis¬
advantages for mankind as a whole. On the contrary, it
contributes to the maintenance of biological ties between
human groups and thus to the unity of the species in its
diversity." Noting that the individual hereditary characte¬
ristics of the parents naturally influence their offspring
(it may happen that the combination of certain such
characteristics has undesirable consequences), the declara¬
tion emphasizes that this is not a question of racial
differences and that "therefore, no biological justification
exists for prohibiting intermarriage between persons of
different races, or for advising against it on racial grounds."
The declaration once again stresses that racial differences
do not coincide with national, regligious, linguistic or cultural
differences. Here again, social phenomena exercise an
influence on the formation of racial, i.e. biological, differ¬
ences. "Human beings who speak the same language and
share the same culture have a tendency to intermarry, and
often there is as a result a certain degree of coincidence
between physical traits on the one hand, and linguistic and
cultural traits on the other," says the declaration. "But
there Is no known causal nexus between these and there¬
fore It Is not justifiable to attribute cultural characteristics
to the influence of the genetic inheritance."
Racists claim that races are not equal in respect of
psychic qualities. The psychologists who help to draw up
the 1966 declaration will be dealing with this point. However,
the biologists meeting in Moscow could naturally not pass
over this important aspect of the race question.
Like certain major anatomical traits in the human species,
the genetic capacity for intellectual development belongs
to those biological characteristics which are universally
valid, because of its importance for the survival of the
species in any natural or cultural environment. The peoples
of the world today appear to possess equal biological
potentialities for attaining any level of civilization.
Differences in the achievements of different peoples must
be attributed solely to their cultural history:
"Certain psychological traits are at times attributed to
particular peoples. Whether or not such assertions are
valid, we do not find any basis for ascribing such traits to
hereditary factors, until proof to the contrary is given.
"Neither in the field of hereditary potentialities concerning
the over-all intelligence and the capacity for cultural
development, nor in that of physical traits, is there any
justification for the concept of 'inferior' and 'superior'
races."
The anthropologists and other biologists who unanimously
adopted the biological elements of the declaration did not
do so solely as scientists but also as men. In their desire
to emphasize this aspect of their work, participants in the
Moscow meeting concluded' their declaration in the follow¬
ing words: "The biological data given above stand in open
contradiction to the tenets of racism. Racist theories can
in no way pretend to have any scientific foundation and the
anthropologists should endeavour to prevent the results
of their researches from being used in such a biased way
that they would serve non-scientific ends."
GEORGHI F. DEBETZ, a Soviet biologist, is a professor at the /
Institute of Ethnography of the Academy of Sciences In Moscow.
He was chairman of the Unesco meeting of biologists, held in
Moscow in August 1964.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Biological aspects of race
A III UMENT
OF PARAMOUNT
IMPORTANCE
The undersigned, assembled by Unesco in order to
give their views on the biological aspects of the race
question and in particular to formulate the biological
part for a statement foreseen for 1966 and intended
. to bring up to date and to complete the declaration
on the nature of race and racial differences signed
in 1951, have unanimously agreed on the following :
1
All men living today belong to a single species, Homo sapiens, and
are derived from a common stock. There are differences of opinion
regarding how and when different human groups diverged from this com¬
mon stock.
Biological differences between human beings are due to differences
in hereditary constitution and to the influence of the environment on this
genetic potential. In most cases, those differences are due to the inter¬
action of these two sets of factors.
3
There is great genetic diversity within all human populations. Pure
races in the sense of genetically homogeneous populations do not
exist in the human species.
There are obvious physical differences between populations living
in different geographic areas of the world, in their average appearance.
Many of these differences have a genetic component.
Most often the latter consist in differences in the frequency of the
same hereditary characters.
8
5
Different classifications of mankind into major stocks, and of those
into more restricted categories (races, which are groups of populations,
or single populations) have been proposed on the basis of hereditary
physical traits. Nearly all classifications recognize at least three major
stocks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Since the pattern of geographic variation of the characteristics used
in racial classification is a complex one, and since this pattern does not
present any major discontinuity, these classifications, whatever they
are, cannot claim to classify mankind into clear cut categories; moreover,
on account of the complexities of human history, it is difficult to determine
the place of xertain groups within these racial classifications, in particu¬
lar that of certain intermediate populations.
Many anthropologists, while stressing the importance of human varia¬
tion, believe that the scientific interest of these classifications is limited,
and even that they carry the. risk of inviting abusive generalizations.
Differences between individuals within a race or within a population
are often greater than the average differences between races or popu¬
lations.
Some of the variable distinctive traits which are generally chosen as
criteria to characterize a race are either independently inherited or show
only varying degrees of association between them within each population.
Therefore, the combination of these traits in most individuals does not
correspond to the typological racial characterization.
In man as well as in animals, the genetic composition of each popu¬
lation is subject to the modifying influence of diverse factors: natural
selection, tending towards adaptation to the environment, fortuitous muta¬
tions which lead to modifications of the molecules of desoxyribonucleic
acid which determine heredity, or random modifications in the frequency
of qualitative hereditary characters, to an extent dependent on the pat¬
terns of mating and the size of populations.
Certain physical characters have a universal biological value for the
survival of the human species, irrespective of the environment. The dif¬
ferences on which racial classifications are based do not affect these char¬
acters, and therefore, it is not possible from the biological point of view
to speak in any way whatsoever of a general inferiority or superiority of
this or that race.
7 Human evolution presents attributes of capital importance which are
specific to the species.
The human species, which is now spread over the whole world, has
a past rich in migrations, in territorial expansions and contractions.
As a consequence, general adaptability to the most diverse environ¬
ments is in man more pronounced than his adaptations to specific envi¬
ronments.
For long millennia, progress made by man, in any field, seems to have
been increasingly, if not exclusively, based on culture and the transmiss¬
ion of cultural achievements and not on the transmission of genetic
endowment. This implies a modification in the rôle of natural selection
in man today.
On account of the mobility of human populations and of social fac¬
tors, mating between members of different human groups which tend to
mitigate the differentiations acquired, has played a much more important
rôle in human history than in that of animals. The history of any human
population or of any human race, is rich in instances of hybridization and
those tend to become more and more numerous.
For man, the obstacles to inter-breeding are geographical as well as
social and cultural.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
BIOLOGICAL ASPECTS OF RACE (Cont'd)
At all times, the hereditary characteristics of the human populations
are in dynamic equilibrium as a result of this inter-breeding and of the
differentiation mechanisms which were mentioned before. As entities
defined by sets of distinctive traits, human races are at any time in a
process of emergence and dissolution.
Human races in general present a far less clear-cut characterization
than many animal races and they cannot be compared at all to races of
domestic animals, these being the result of heightened selection for spe¬
cial purposes.
9 It has never been proved that inter-breeding has biological disadvan¬
tages for mankind as a whole.
On the contrary, it contributes to the maintenance of biological ties
between human groups and thus to the unity of the species in its diver¬
sity.
The biological consequences of a marriage depend only on the indi¬
vidual genetic make-up of, the couple and not on their race.
Therefore, no biological justification exists for prohibiting intermar¬
riage between persons of different races, or for advising against it on
racial grounds.
Man since his origin has at his disposal ever more efficient cultural
means of non-genetic adaptation.
11 Those cultural factors which break social and geographic barriers,
enlarge the size of the breeding populations and so act upon their genetic
structure by diminishing the random fluctuations (genetic drift).
As a rule, the major stocks extend over vast territories encompass¬
ing many diverse populations which differ in language, economy, cul¬
ture, etc.
There is no national, religious, geographic, linguistic or cultural group
which constitutes a race ipso facto ; the concept of race is purely bio¬
logical.
However, human beings who speak the same language and share
the same culture have a tendency to inter-marry, and often there is as a
result a certain degree of coincidence between physical traits on the one
hand, and linguistic and cultural traits on the other. But there is no
known causal nexus between these and therefore it is not justifiable to
attribute cultural characteristics to the influence of the genetic inheritance.
10
13
Most racial classifications of mankind do not include mental traits
or attributes as a taxonomic criterion.
Heredity may have an influence in the variability showh by individuals
within a given population in their responses to the psychological tests
currently applied.
However, no difference has ever been detected convincingly in the
hereditary endowments of human groups in regard to what is measured
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
by these tests. On the other hand, ample evidence attests to the
influence of physical, cultural and social environment on differences in
response to these tests.
The study of this question is hampered by the very great difficulty
of determining what part heredity plays in the average differences ob¬
served in so-called tests of overall intelligence between populations of
different cultures.
The genetic capacity for intellectual development, like certain major,
anatomical traits peculiar to the species, is one of the biological traits
essential for its survival in any natural or social environment.
The peoples of the world today appear to possess equal biological
potentialities for attaining any civilizational level. Differences in the
achievements of different peoples must be attributed solely to their cultural
history.
Certain psychological traits are at times attributed to particular
peoples. Whether or not such assertions are valid, we do not find any
basis for ascribing such traits to hereditary factors, until proof to the
contrary is given.
Neither in the field of hereditary potentialities concerning the overall
intelligence and the capacity for cultural development, nor in that of
physical traits, is there any justification for the concept of "inferior" and
"superior" races.
The biological data given above are in open contradic¬
tion to the tenets of racism. Racist theories can in no
way pretend to have any scientific foundation and the
anthropologists should endeavour to prevent the results
of their research from being used in such a biased way
as to serve non-scientific ends.
Prof. NIGEL BARNICOT, Department of Anthropology, Uni¬
versity College, London (U.K.).
Prof. JEAN BENOIST, Director, Department of Anthropo¬
logy, University of Montreal (Canada).
Prof. TADEUSZ BIELICKI, Institute of Anthropology, Polish
Academy of Sciences, Wroclaw (Poland).
Dr. A.E. BOYO, Head, Federal Malaria Research Institute,
Department of Pathology & Haematology, Lagos University
Medical School, Lagos (Nigeria).
Prof. VICTOR V. BUNAK, Institute of Ethnography, Academy
of Sciences, Moscow (U.S.S.R.).
Prof. CARLETON S. COON, Curator, The University Mu¬
seum, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa. (U.S.A.).
Prof. GEORGHI F. DEBETZ (Chairman of the meeting),
Institute of Ethnography, Academy of Sciences, Moscow
(U.S.S.R.).
Mrs. ADELAIDE G. DE DIAZ UNGRIA, Curator, Museum of
Natural Sciences, Caracas (Venezuela).
Prof. ROBERT GESSAIN, Director, Centre of Anthropological
Research, Musée de l'Homme, Paris (France).
Prof. SANTIAGO GENOVES (Vice-Chairman of the
meeting), Institute of Historical Research, Faculty of
Science, University of Mexico (Mexico).
Prof. JEAN HIERNAUX (Scientific director of the meeting),
Laboratory of Anthropology, Faculty of Sciences, University
of Paris (France) ; Institute of Sociology, Free University
of Brussels (Belgium).
Dr. YAYA KANE (Vice-Chairman of the meeting), Senegal
National Centre of Blood Transfusion, Dakar (Senegal).
Prof. RAMAKHR1SHNA MUKHERJEE (Vice-Chairman of the
meeting), Research Professor of Sociology, Indian Statis¬
tical Institute, Calcutta (India).
Prof. BERNARD RENSCH, Zoological Institute, Westfälische
Wilhelms-Universität, Münster (Federal Republic of Ger¬
many).
Prof. YAKOV Y. ROGUINSKI, Head, Chair of Anthropology,
Moscow University (U.S.S.R.).
Prof. FRANCISCO M. SALZANO, Institute of Natural Scien¬
ces, Porto Alegre, Rio Grande do Sul (Brazil).
Prof. ALF SOMMERFELT (Vice-Chairman of the meeting),
Honorary Pro-Rector, Oslo University (Norway).
Prof. JAMES N. SPUHLER (Vice-Chairman of the meeting),
Department of Anthropology, University of Michigan, Ann
Arbor, Michigan (U.S.A.).
Prof. HISASHI SUZUKU, Department of Anthropology,
Faculty of Science, University of Toyo (Japan).
Prof. J.A. VALSIK, Department of Anthropology & Genetics,
J.A. Komensky University, Bratislava (Czechoslovakia).
Dr. JOSEPH S. WEINER, London School of Hygiene &
Tropical Medicine, University of London (U.K.). j j
Dr. Vsevolod P. YAKIMOV, Director, Institute of Anthropo¬
logy, Moscow University (U.S.S.R.).
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A biologist's view
THE FUTURE
OF HOMO
SAPIENS'
by Jean Hiernaux
I
12
T takes considerable presumption to foretell
the future, yet it is a task that the research
worker cannot evade, although he may admit that his fore¬
casts are based on incomplete knowledge and on hypo¬
theses which are coloured by his own personality.
Man is the product of the evolution of animate matter;
and his future can be foretold only by projecting into the
future evolutionary trends which are perceptible today.
Throughout the natural history of life on our planet, we
may trace a series of forms, rising from the simplest to the
most complex from giant molecules, not yet completely
differentiated from inert matter, to mammals.
The main stages in this evolution reveal an increasing
degree of freedom from close dependence on the environ¬
ment. For example, by acquiring the ability to maintain the
body temperature irrespective of the temperature of the
external environment, which scientists call "horiothermy,"
the higher forms of animate matter have entered regions
in which previously they could not live.
As life became increasingly complex, the structure and
role of the brain grew larger. The maximum development
of the brain and the maximum freedom from the power
of the external environment were to be achieved by man;
and, having acquired that freedom, he gained increasing
control over the forces of nature, which he harnessed
to suit his needs.
Man is unquestionably the spearhead of evolution, but
he does not follow it's course in the same way as did those
forms which lived before him; at least, it may be said that
an evolutionary mechanism not previously in operation came
into being with man. Before his coming, evolution
was genetic in character; it consisted in changing the
qualities inherited by the various species in other words,
changing the stock of genes borne by them. It had nothing
to do with the will or with consciousness.
With the coming of man and, no doubt, as a necessary
condition for his emergence, an entirely different evolu¬
tionary mechanism came into being and developed the
transmission from one individual to another and from one
generation to the next of knowledge, inventions, and ways
H
|
of life which are not inherited, and which can be perpetuated
only through constant effort.
This is a less stable form of evolution, but it enables
man to advance along the path of freedom and to gain
control over his environment much more rapidly than he
can through genetic evolution. This is probably the reason
why, after a period of interaction between the two evolution¬
ary mechanisms (lasting from the emergence of man,
some two million years ago, until his appearance in his pre¬
sent form as "Homo sapiens" about 50,000 years ago),
evolution towards a higher state now takes place essentially
in the sphere of acquired ability, which we may call the
cultural sphere.
There is no perceptible difference between the anato¬
mical development of the skull of fossilized Homo sapiens
and our skull, but man's control over the forces of nature
has grown tremendously, and knowledge and techniques
are progressing with ever-increasing speed; cultural evolu¬
tion has taken the place of genetic evolution.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
>?^^,
V
If this explanation of the lack of change in the brain
over tens of thousands of years is correct, we must not
expect man in the future to have an enormous head; the
brain he has now is large enough for him, and in any case
he is already extending its range by means of electronic
computers.
It is true that, judging by the bone-structure, "Homo
sapiens" usually had coarser features in the stone age than
today (as have the modern representatives of that cultural
stage, the Australian aborigines). A certain refining of the
bony projections has accompanied cultural evolution. Yet
it is not to be expected that this trend will continue until
the head is markedly different; the ridges of the brow may
vanish, but the frontal bone cannot. There is also a ten¬
dency for the teeth to become smaller, and even for the
third molar to be missing. Here again, there Is no reason
to think that this situation will ultimately produce a toothless
human being. In any case, these processes are extremely
slow compared with cultural evolution.
Unesco - Kitrosser
A process still in operation today in the genetic sphere,
and there is no sign that it is nearing its end, is the modi¬
fication of the inherited traits of populations so as to secure,
from the genetic point of view, the best possible adaptation
to a changing environment. Our adaptation to our environ¬
ment, too, is increasingly cultural in character (take, for
instance, our clothing, heating and air-conditioning), and
advances in medicine are helping to lessen the importance
of natural selection; but we are constantly creating new
environments (such as that of the great metropolises) which
give rise to fresh biological problems. It will be a long time,
no doubt, before cultural measures make genetic adaptation
to local conditions unnecessary, and so put an end to it.
All that has been said so far concerns the spontaneous
biological evolution of man. Now, man has acquired
knowledge and technical ability which enable him to._
influence his inherited traits. The branch of science which 10
deals with this process is eugenics. It is based on the
theory that, for each inherited characteristic in which men
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
© Ilse Steinhoff IBM
FUTURE OF 'HOMO SAPIENS' (Cont'd)
Not superman, perhaps a supermankind
14
differ from each other (such as the A, B and O blood
groups, in which individuals are divided into four groups),
there is a determining factor (a gene) which is the best of
its kind, and which is found in all parts of the world.
Natural selection will tend to eliminate all alternatives
except the best. If a new gene appears, as a result of
mutations, either it will be better than the existing genes,
and will supersede them, or else it will be weaker, and will
be eliminated.
The aim of eugenics is to assist what is good in nature,
by discouraging deleterious genes (through preventing indi¬
viduals possessing them from reproducing) and by
encouraging the best gene (for instance by advocating arti¬
ficial insemination by semen which bears that gene). The
tendency is, therefore, for eugenics to produce a human race
composed of genetically identical individuals.
In many cases (when it is recessive), the elimination of
a deleterious gene, even by total eugenics (the complete
prevention of reproduction by those who bear it), requires
many generations. Apart from this practical aspect there
is a serious argument against the general application of
eugenics: recent research has revealed that in very many
cases natural selection does not move towards a state of
uniformity through the elimination of all genes except one,
but rather towards a state of balance between the fre¬
quencies of different genes.
Mankind has always exhibited considerable diversity In
respect of many hereditary traits, which is a good thing. This
is not only because the vitality of each population depends
upon such diversity (or polymorphism), but because a gene
may be beneficial in certain environmental conditions and
harmful in others. We know of genes, for instance, a certain
frequency of which is beneficial in malarial regions, but
which are by no means desirable in other regions.
Men have settled in all parts of the globe; they live in
widely differing natural environments which they are con¬
stantly modifying in ways that are not always predictable.
This being so, the genetic ideal is to maintain diversity
the opposite of the aim of eugenics. Eugenics is un¬
justifiable except in so far as it can eradicate very serious
hereditary diseases, of which there are few; if an appa¬
rently unfavourable trait occurs frequently in a population,
it is very likely to be desirable in some respect at present
unknown to us. If a gene is really undesirable in all re¬
spects, natural selection will keep its frequency very low.
HIS criticism applies to positive eugenics, the
object of which is to increase the number of
"good" genes, as well as to negative eugenics, which aims
to eradicate the "bad" ones; underlying both is the same
ideal uniformity. We have no reason to hope that a
Superman will be produced in the eugenists' test-tubes;
any highly gifted beings they might produce would not
constitute a biologically viable human race.
We should do better to devote, our energies to providing
populations and individuals with living conditions in which
their inherited potentialities can best be realized, rather
than manipulating genes; and that is not eugenics, but
what has been called euthenics.
There are hundreds of millions of human beings who,
through hunger or disease, are prevented- from realizing
their physical potentialities as they would have done under
better conditions. Differences between the intellectual
achievements of the various human populations appear to
be due entirely to the fact that their food, health and
educational conditions are different. Euthenics opens up
much broader and safer avenues for the betterment of
mankind than does eugenics.
The processes in operation today especially selection,
which has the effect of differentiating populations by genetic
adaptation to their living conditions, and cross-breeding,
which produces greater homogeneity, while at the same
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
FROM STONE TOOLTO COMPUTER. Ittook man hundreds of thou¬
sands of years to evolve his stone-cutting techniques (left), yet only
a few thousand years to advance from the stone age to the atomic age.
Between the anatomical development of the skull of "Homo sapiens"
of 50,000 years ago and our skulls today there is no perceptible difference.
Cultural evolution has taken the place of genetic evolution. Man is
now extending the range of his brain by means of electronic
computers. Above, perforated computer programming cards.
time putting a premium on polymorphism can, of them¬
selves, produce the state which appears to meet the bio¬
logical needs of our race, that is, unity in diversity. Indivi¬
dual adaptations are never very marked, and they are much
less characteristic of man than his genetic capacity for
general adaptation to varied conditions.
It would seem, therefore, that man is not destined to
undergo any striking biological transformation through
either spontaneous or induced evolution. He is, however,
undergoing an ever more rapid cultural evolution; it took
him hundreds of thousands of years the palaeolithic era
to bring his stone-cutting technique to a moderately high
standard, but only a few thousand years to advance from
the stone age to the atomic age. It is in the sphere of
cultural achievements that man can undergo a profound
evolution which, though different in kind from genetic evo¬
lution, as we have seen, is moving in the same direction,
and is the specifically human form of evolution.
This kind of evolution has become self-conscious; it is
dependent upon man's desire to advance and on the effec¬
tiveness of the measures he adopts to do so. It requires
of men a sustained effort to improve, both as individuals
and as a society. It does not appear to be necessarily
inevitable; our present state of knowledge, indeed, provides
mankind with the means of total self-destruction.
Are we then justified in predicting that the cultural
evolution will continue to progress? We may be somewhat
prejudiced on the side of optimism, but not without reason.
Under pressure of the forces of selection, the genetic
evolution has gone on, passing through numerous phases,
for over a thousand million years; and in every case the
more complex, more highly developed form has supplanted
the lower form when they have been present together and
in a competitive situation.
True mammals, for example, have supplanted marsupials
in all parts of the world except Australia, where they have
been but recently introduced. We may reasonably expect
that by a similar mechanism a more highly-developed
cultural form, when brought into contact with a less highly-
developed one, will supersede it. Examples of this may be
found in our past. One case is the extremely rapid expan¬
sion of the neolithic revolution, i.e. the invention of agri¬
culture and cattle-breeding.
Biological evolutionary forces (using the word "bio¬
logical" in the narrow sense) altered inherited traits; but
cultural evolutionary forces preserve whatever is felt to be
an incentive towards mankind's advancement. These inclu¬
de the desire for knowledge, which leads to scientific pro¬
gress, and the desire of individuals and human societies to
draw closer together, which impels us to love our neighbour,
to feel ourselves involved in whatever affects mankind as
a whole, and to strive for greater social justice.
It is true that, as in the case of genetic evolution,
these forces produce nothing more than trends, and do
not exclude the possibility of periods of retrogression and
partial failure; but, if we look at history from a sufficiently
high vantage-point, it seems reasonable to think that they
will succeed.
Where can this sort of evolution take mankind?
In some fields, it is moving very quickly; know¬
ledge is advancing with great rapidity; and, amidst storm and
stress, men are seeking for new forms of ¡social morality
consonant with their increasing awareness ¿f their unity and
of the interdependence of the elements of which the race
is composed.
When we observe the rate of our progress we may
wonder whether animate matter inhabiting the earth is not
about to undergo, in man, one of those changes of state
which dialectical thinking entitles us to visualize. It would
seem that, in' biology as in physics, slight but accumulated
quantitative changes may somewhat suddenly lead to qua¬
litatively new states (consider, for example, the changes
undergone by a block of ice which is heated gradually).
Thus, the increasing complexity of inert matter gave rise
to life, which had new properties, but within which chemical
particles retain their ordinary characteristics; it is the inter¬
action and organization of these particles which is char¬
acteristic of life. The increasing' complexity of animate
matter led to the emergence of man, a qualitatively new
creature in certain ways, as in his capacity for abstract
thinking, but whose cells possess the same general bio¬
logical properties as the amoeba.
If we try to apply this principle still further, we shall see
that the next critical threshold will bring us to a state in
which men differing but little from present-day men will, by
virtue of their desire to draw closer together and the inten¬
sity and nature of their interaction, constitute a qualitatively
new stage of animate matter.
So, if we see the matter aright, we are advancing towards
a Supermankind, and not towards Supermen. We may be
unable at our stage in evolution to gain a complete picture
of this future state, but already we know the paths that lead
to it. It may sometimes be difficult to abandon an untrou¬
bled immobility but if we are to accept our responsibilities
as human beings and respond to the forces of progress, we
must move forward along these paths the ways that lead to
knowledge and amity.
PROF. JEAN HIERNAUX was scientific director of the meeting of
biologists organized by Unesco in Moscow in August 1965 (see
page 8). An anthropologist, he is a director of research at the National
Centre of Scientific Research in Pans and also collaborates with
the Institute of Sociology at the Free University of Brussels, Bel¬
gium. Professor Hiernaux has written a number of popular science
works, including "Origine de l'Homme" (The Origin of Man]; "Nature
et Origine des Races Humaines" (The Nature and Origin of the
Human Races) and "L'Avenir Biologique de l'Homme" (The Biological
Future of Man). These have been published by the Cercle d'Education
Populaire, 20 rue de Verviers, Brussels.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
A century ago a Moravian monk discovered one of nature's
great secrets-the mechanism of heredity. All his life he
sought to have his ideas accepted but he died disheartened,
unknown and unrecognized. Today, the world salutes an extra¬
ordinary genius who was the father of the science of genetics.
EXACTLY one century ago this year, the
Austrian monk Johann Mendel Brother Gregor
in the Augustinian Order submitted to the Natural History
Society of Brunn a paper entitled "Experiments in Plant
Hybridization."
Mendel's paper, which he communicated in two parts,
on February 8 and March 8, 1 865, is one of the most astonish¬
ing masterpieces ever conceived by the mind of man. In
some fifty pages, in which the author consigned the fruits
of eight years of patient research, a new science and an
entirely fresh approach to biology was revealed. Mendel
was not, as is sometimes said, a precursor of genetics; he
was its veritable founder. All the essentials of the modern
science of heredity, all those aspects of it which continue
to evolve and develop along the most divergent paths,
were already contained explicitly or implicitly In that
memorable paper. Not a single line of it has become
dated, for it reports only faultless experiments and presents
hypotheses the future was to confirm.
Mendel's life was simple and obscure. Born in Hei-
zendorf, Moravia on July 22, 1822 the year of Louis Pas¬
teur's birth Johann Mendel came of a peasant family. In
his eleventh year he entered a school in Leipnik, then, after
attending, a school in Troppau and reading at the Uni¬
versity of Vienna, he decided on a monastic life. In 1843,
he was admitted as a novice at the Augustinian Monastery
of Brunn (today Brno in Czechoslovakia), where he took
orders in 1847.
Although he held no university degrees Mendel was
to teach natural history and elementary physics at Brunn.
Twice he sat for the examination which would have qualified
him for a higher post, but without success.
I
16
N 1856, he began experimenting in the cloister
garden with hybridization of the common pea.
His aim was at first a modest one: to bring about artificial
fertilization of ornamental plants with a view to obtaining
new colours. But as he proceeded with his crossings and
extended and varied his experimental material, his ambition
grew; he realized that he had raised the whole problem of
heredity and that he would have to elucidate it if he
were to understand his findings.
These findings impressed him by their regularity, their
clarity and their constancy, all expressed with mathematical
precision. Certain hypotheses became apparent and these
called for verification through further experiments. Finally,
after bringing about thousands of artifical fertilizations and
examining tens of thousands of seeds, Mendel believed
that he was in a position to formulate general conclusions,
equivalent to laws, and these he set forth in his paper
of 1865. Alas, the very magnitude and remarkable ori¬
ginality of his work was to render it incomprehensible to
his contemporaries. Despite all his efforts to bring it
to the attention of the specialists, he received no encour¬
agement from them and finally abandoned his research.
Elected abbot in 1868, Mendel died in 1884.
Thirty-five years elapsed before Mendel's work was rescu¬
ed from oblivion and it might have remained forever buried
had it not been briefly mentioned in a work on plant hy¬
bridization by the German botanist Wilhelm Focke.
Early in 1900 a Dutch botanist, Hugo de Vries, published
two papers on the hybridization of various plants and in one,
which appeared in Germany, he indicated that his disco¬
veries had in all their essentials been put forward long
before by a monk named Mendel, but in a paper so rarely
mentioned that De Vries did not learn of its existence
until his own work was to all intents completed.
In April of the same year, it was a German botanist,
Carl Correns, who reached findings in every way similar
to Mendel's. He, too, thought he had made an original
discovery.
Finally, in June 1900, an Austrian botanist, Erich Tscher-
mak, corroborated Mendel's observations, which came to
his knowledge only after he had completed his own.
HREE scientists remaking, almost at the same
time and independently of each other, the disco¬
very an obscure monk had already made, unknown to the
world; an astounding paper buried in the annals of a modest
local scientific society; an amateur botanist of genius who
in his cloister garden had outdistanced the prominent
scientists of his day here were facts to stir the imagination
and the emotions.
Mendelism, thus rediscovered, was straightway to meet
with an enthusiastic response and arouse exceptional in¬
terest all over the world. Confirmation was forthcoming
from all sides: the laws of hybridization immediately dub¬
bed Mendel's laws were to be extended to the animal
kingdom by Bateson in England, by Lucien Cuénot in
France.
Why was Mendel's revelation so important?
Mendel was certainly not the first to investigate the phe¬
nomena of heredity. Before him many observations had
been made concerning the transmission of organic charac¬
ters in plants, in animals, in the human species. Even
the .experimental study of heredity had been undertaken
by scientists such as Köhlreuter, Wichura, Lecoq, Sageret,
Goss and Seton, Naudin and others. But none of these
studies had produced anything clear or decisive. The re¬
sults of cross-fertilization or cross-breeding were always un¬
predictable to the investigator. It was as if the pheno¬
menon of heredity was essentially freakish, or at least too
complex to lend itself to exhaustive analysis.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
JOHANN
GREGOR
MENDEL
by Jean Rostand
of the Académie Française
Not so with Mendel. For his cross-fertilizations he had
had the foresight to choose very stable varieties of peas
with constant, clear-cut differences in their characteristics
differences in the form (wrinkled or round) or the colour
(green or yellow) of the ripe seed, in the form of the ripe
pod, in the colour of the ripe pod, in the colour of the
unripe pod, in the length of the stems, etc. Then after long
experimentation and examination of the findings, he was
able to predict precisely what would happen when two
peas differing in one or several unit-characters were
crossed.
To take a simple example, he was able to predict that
cross-fertilization of two peas differing in unit-characters A
and a would produce peas having only unit-character A;
and that if the hybrids of that first generation were then
intercrossed, unit-character a would reappear in the follow¬
ing generation, which would have an average ratio of
three plants with unit-character A to one plant with unit-
character a.
What is more, Mendel's work not only enabled the ex¬
perimenter to predict in itself a valuable advance. The
ratios he discovered were of profound significance, reveal¬
ing as they did the interplay of hidden and previously un-
thought of mechanisms. For in order to explain the results
of cross-fertilization or cross-breeding, it had to be assum¬
ed that the unit-characters of the parents separated or
segregated from each other in the reproduction cells
of the hybrids and, furthermore, that they segregated in¬
dependently. This led to the idea of discontinuity of
the hereditary basis, which then appeared as made up of
separable elements, more or less similar to atoms in
chemistry.
Finally, the behaviour of the Mendelian units today
Czechoslovak official photo
known as "genes" paralleled in striking fashion that of
the particles, or chromosomes, of which a definite number,
constant for each species, Is found in the cell nucleus of
all living things.
Mendelism led directly to the chromosome theory of
heredity intuitively elaborated by the German biologist
August Weisman at the end of the last century.
Henceforth, Mendelism and the chromosome theory were
to evolve in concert, lending each other enlightenment and
support, while all research continually confirmed the expe¬
rimental findings obtained from cross-fertilization or cross¬
breeding.
It was thanks to such collaboration that the school of
Thomas Hunt Morgan, a U.S. winner of the 1933 Nobel
Prize in Physiology and Medicine was able to carry out
on the fruit-fly (Drosophila melanogaster) its great work
one of the finest achievements of modern biology which
made it possible not merely to locate a great number of
genes in one or the other of this insect's four chromo¬
somes, but also to fix their exact position within each chro¬
mosome.
Now, the cytological stage has in turn been superseded.
We have reached the chemical stage and the gene is at
present regarded as a large molecule of deoxyribonucleic
acid (DNA).
Where does Mendelism stand today?
The universality of Mendel's laws must first be noted.
As the biologist, Robert Matthey puts it, "The Mendelian -j -i
universe can no longer be reduced, as might have been 1 1
supposed in 1900, to a garden with leguminous plants pro¬
ducing green or yellow, wrinkled or round seeds; it em-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
* *
18
JOHANN MENDEL (Cont'd)
braces within its laws the whole world of living things
from virus to man."
It should also be made clear that direct evidence of
the segregation of the genes during the formation of the
reproduction cells has been forthcoming.
Mendelism, besides underlying most of the disciplines
concerned with organic individuality, mutation and evolution,
the fine structure of chromosomes and the chemistry of
genes, in so far as genetics stemmed from it, has direct
applications in various fields, notably in human genetics.
It is the basis on which doctors can warn against the
unfortunate consequences of certain marriages and point
out the disadvantages of consanguinity.
If ever a negative eugenics is introduced to eliminate or
reduce certain hereditary diseases or defects in our species,
the data obtained by Mendelism will have to be taken into
account.
One of its best known applications is the genetics of
blood. Since we know how the Rhesus factor is trans¬
mitted we have been able to develop suitable treatment
to avert the risks to a baby when the Rhesus factors in
the blood of the parents differ and are thus incompatible.
Need it be added that a knowledge of the genetics of
blood is of value in some cases of disputed paternity?
Although it can never be proved by blood alone that a
man is the father of a particular child, it is quite often
possible to prove that the child could not be his.
Knowledge of Mendel's laws has rendered and still
renders great services to agriculture and stock-breeding.
By their judicious application racial characters can be
manipulated at will and several desirable characters from
different lines combined in a single race. In this way,
the sturdiness and resistance of cereals have been in¬
creased and the production of meat, wool, milk, eggs, etc.,
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
i -
Two remarkable animal oddities
spotted by an aerial cameraman
in the Rukwa Valley, a huge
animal reserve in southwestern
Tanzania. Left, a spotted
zebra runs with the normally
marked members of the herd.
Right, an albino giraffe. There
have been reports of albino
giraffe from other parts of Africa,
but spotted zebra are far more
rare. But, since these pictures
were taken, a game officer has
reported that the Rukwa Valley
zebra has foaled and that
the zebra colt too ¡s spotted.
Photos © Birnback Publishing
Service, New York
; ffc
has been improved both quantitatively and qualitatively.
In discussing Mendelism, it is impossible to overlook
the offensive to which it was subjected around 1948
along with Morganism by Soviet biologists of the Michurin
school grouped around the botanist Lysenko.
In the name of a certain dogmatism they anathematized
Mendel's views, which they denounced as reactionary, bour¬
geois, idealistic, conventional, etc. Ironic references were
made to the garden pea man and the monkish theory. . .
The same ones that execrated Mendel maintained that
wheat can produce rye and that life appears spontaneously
in the yolk of an eggl
This was a painful period for science which we should
remember if only not to forget the level of absurdity highly
esteemed and educated men can sink to when they yield to
doctrinal fanaticism.
Mendelism has been established once and for all in bio¬
logical thinking and nothing will oust it, for it expresses
a considerable part of the real basis of life itself. It
colours willy-nilly our manner of observing experimenting,
reasoning and thinking. The fame of Mendel, as of Darwin
and Pasteur, is not at the mercy of changing opinion.
As long as there are biologists on the earth, they will
honour the memory of the obscure monk in Brunn who,
richer in genius than in knowledge, was the first to shed
light on one of the greatest phenomena of nature.
JEAN ROSTAND, the French biologist and scientific writer, is known
throughout the world for his research on heredity and genetics, based
on three decades of experimentation with frogs and toads. He has a n
written over 40 books on his fields of research as well as on scientific I jj
thought, philosophy and pure science. A member of the French
Academy, he was awarded the Kalinga Unesco Prize for the popu¬
larization of science in 1959.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
"There is a clear prospect that racial conflict, if we cannot curb and finally
eliminate it, will grow into a destructive monster compared to which the reli¬
gious and ideological conflicts of the past and present will seem like small family
quarrels." These were the words used by U Thant, Secretary-General of the Uni¬
ted Nations, last year, to warn the world against the consequences of racial
discrimination. Racial discrimination, imposed as an official policy in the
Republic of South Africa, has created a dramatic and unparalleled situation that
in recent years has increasingly stirred the conscience of the world. In November
1962 the United Nations General Assembly set up a special committee to inves¬
tigate the policy of "apartheid" and its consequences in South Africa. The results '
of these investigations have been published in a series of comprehensive reports,
the most recent of which appeared in December 1964. These show the increas¬
ing gravity of the situation. The facts they relate, which The Unesco Courier
presents here in abridged form, speak for themselves. They depict in graphic
terms a tragedy in which millions of people in South Africa are being engulfed
for one reason alone: because of the colour of their skin.
REPORTING FOR WORK at a factory in Johannes¬
burg. In South Africa the vast majority of unskilled
jobs are done by Africans. An integral aim of "apart¬
heid" is to reserve the skilled and higher-paid profes¬
sions for the Whites. The U.N. Special Committee
reports that the ratio between the average wage earnings
of Whites and Africans in mining is fifteen to one.
O Paul Almasv. Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
APARTHEID
in South Africa
HE Republic of South Africa has... uprooted
thousands of families from their homes in the
urban areas and expelled many thousands of Africans to
distant reserves. It has arrested and convicted hundreds
of thousands of persons under pass laws and other racially
discriminatory measures. It has excluded non-Whites (1)
from new categories of employment. It has Instituted a
reign of terror against opponents of "apartheid": the leaders
of the non-Whites have been jailed or restricted, and thou¬
sands of persons have been thrown in jail for opposition to
"apartheid", with no certainty of ever being set free. Harsh
penalties have been imposed on members of the major
non-White organizations...
Meanwhile the government has spent much effort in
propaganda at home and abroad, describing its policy as
"separate development" of the races in order to deceive
world public opinion. The policy itself remains basically
unchanged.
Prime Minister Dr. Verwoerd stated in the House of
Assembly on January 25, 1963:
"Reduced to its simplest form the problem is nothing
else than this: We want to keep South Africa White...
'Keeping It White' can only mean one thing, namely, White
domination, not 'leadership', not 'guidance', but 'control',
'supremacy'. If we are agreed that it is the desire of
the people that the White man should be able to continue
to protect himself by retaining White domination... we
say that it can be achieved by separate development."
Government leaders admit that the non-Whites cannot
be treated forever as inferior, nor would they accept con¬
cessions which do not provide for equal rights. They claim
that the move towards self-determination of both the major
groups is the only solution which will preserve the nation¬
hood and the vital interests of the Whites. Hence the
development of "Bantustans" in the African reserves is
given great emphasis in government policy.
Under the government's plans, the African reserves will
be progressively granted the rights of self-government.
The Africans will exercise their political rights only in the
reserves and the Whites only in the rest of the country,
described as the "White" area.
(1) According to Information supplied to the International Labour
Organization by the Government of South Africa in 1962, the popu¬
lation of the Republic of South Africa comprises four very distinct
population groups of whom eleven million are Bantu, three million
of European origin, 500,000 of Asian origin and one and a half million
of mixed origin.
This ingenious formula represents, in fact, a serious
attack on the rights of a great majority of inhabitants. It
means that Africans will lose all existing rights, and all
hope of equal rights, in 87 per cent of the territory of the
country in return for self-government in the reserves which
constitute only 13 per cent of the territory.
The idea that the African reserves constitute the home¬
lands of the Africans is based on a distortion of history
and a negation of present-day realities. Only 38 per cent
of Africans today reside in the reserves, which cannot
provide an adequate livelihood for even their existing
inhabitants. The Africans constitute a majority in both
the "White" urban areas and "White" rural areas. A large
percentage of the Africans were born or have lived for long
periods outside the reserves and have little contact with
the reserves...
NE of the first acts of the Union of South Africa,
formed in 1909 by agreement between the two
major White elements in the country, was the promulgation
of the Native Land Act of 1913, which limited African land
rights to 10 1/2 million "morgen" (about 21 million acres).
The Native Trust and Land Act of 1936 provided for the
acquisition of an additional 15 million acres for African
occupation, and for the liquidation of the "Black spots"
(African-owned land) in the rest of the country. When this
additional land is acquired, the African reserves will cover
less than one seventh of the country.
The traditional geographical separation is mainly a
restriction on landownership imposed by the government
in which the Africans had no voice and which the African
leaders had protested strongly. The reserves contain only
38 per cent of the African population of the country, and
even a government commission found that they can decently
support only half of their present population. The majority
of Africans live outside the reserves. The Africans out¬
number the Whites in the urban areas. The number of
Africans is about four times the number of Whites in the
"White" rural area.
The National Party came to power in 1948 after a cam¬
paign in which it stressed the alleged dangers of Increasing
African population outside the reserves, and the trend
towards economic integration. It embarked on a series of
laws to outlaw all social intercourse between the racial
groups, to restrict the rights of Africans outside the
reserves, and to reinforce tribalism1.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
[RÄKKETTE SLECS BLANKES
IPARCELS furqpeans ONLY
APARTHEID (Cont'd)
Paul Almasy. Paris
13 million persons in a web of restrictions
The Bantu Authorities Act of 1951 abolished the Native
Representative Council and authorized the Governor-Gene¬
ral to establish Bantu "tribal authorities". The establishment
of these authorities was opposed by the Africans and the
government had to impose them by threats, deportation
and arrest of African leaders and severe police action.
African resistance had been ruthlessly quelled in Tembuland
and East Pondoland between 1957 and 1960.
Under the so.-called Promotion of Bantu Self-Government
Act of 1959, the small number of qualified Africans were
deprived of their right to elect a few White members to
Parliament. The Act provided for the gradual consolidation
of the 264 scattered African reserves into eight "national
units" and the establishment of territorial authorities in
these units. Territorial authorities were established in the
Transkei (1) and in five other areas by the end of 1962.
A number of comments may be made on these moves
towards "the creation of Bantustans."
First, these moves are engineered by a government in
which the African people have no voice and are aimed at
the separation of the races and the denial of rights to the
African population in six-sevenths of the country.
Second, the "Bantustans" were not demanded by Afri¬
cans but are being imposed against their wishes. The
leaders of the African people are imprisoned or silenced,
entry into reserves by Whites Is controlled by permit, and,
22
(1) The Transkei, situated on the coast in the northeastern part of
the Cape Province, has an area of 16,350 square miles and a population
of over two million.
under Proclamation 400, the Transkeians are denied free¬
dom of assembly and speech.
Third, the self-government granted to Transkei at present
is limited in many ways. Paramount Chief Sabata Dalin-
dyebo of the Tembu, one of the biggest tribes in the
Transkei, declared recently:
"The freedom you are getting in the Transkei is a fowl-
run. A cattlekraal would be better."
Fourth, the scheme aims at strengthening tribalism and
utilizing the tribal system against African aspirations for
equality.
Fifth, the "national units", made up of scattered reserves,
are not economically viable. They do not provide a mini¬
mum standard of living even for the existing population
of less than four million. They have few known' mineral
resources and are almost devoid of industries. Their
economies depend largely on the export of labour to the
"White" areas at the rate of over half a million migrant
labourers a year.
The creation of "Bantustans" may, therefore, be regarded
as designed to reinforce White supremacy in the country
by strengthening the position of tribal chiefs, dividing the
African people through the offer of opportunities for a
limited number of Africans, and deceiving public opinion.
The policy of the Government of the Republic of South
Africa, as indicated earlier, is to keep most, if not all, of
South Africa under White control by treating Africans out¬
side the reserves as transient aliens allowed to remain only
to minister to the needs of the Whites. The movement of
Africans to the "White areas" is strictly regulated and
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
'
© Holmes-Lebel. Paris - Ernest Cole
On a railway platform (left) signboards warn the traveller that he must only use the service allocat¬
ed to his racial group. Parcels offices, refreshment rooms, telegraph and telephone services are
all segregated for Whites and non-Whites. Right, as a train pulls out of the station Africans
are still trying to force their way into the already packed carriages reserved for non-Whites.
African family life is restricted. Any African who is unem¬
ployed or becomes a "problem" is expelled. Some of the
disabilities imposed on the Africans and other 'non-Whites
are briefly reviewed below.
The Group Areas Act of 1950, which provides for the
forcible separation of racial groups, continues to be im¬
plemented actively though the General Assembly has
repeatedly called upon South Africa to refrain from enforc¬
ing Its provisions. "Black spots", where Africans hold
freehold rights, are being rapidly cleared.
Between November 6, 1962 and the end of August 1963,
"group areas" were proclaimed in about 40 cities and
towns. Tens of thousands of families, mostly of non-Whites,
are forced to move from areas in some of which they have
resided for generations...
This uprooting of settled communities has created serious
hardship for the families which are obliged to move to
distant new locations. It has caused great insecurity and
bitterness.
In line with its policy of territorial separation, the govern¬
ment is proceeding with plans to replace and remove the
African population of 250,000 in the Western Cape and
reserve the area for the Whites and the Coloureds. Thous¬
ands of Africans are being expelled to the reserves.
The scheme has been opposed by many industrialists,
farmers and political leaders. The United Party leader, Sir
de Villiers Graaff, speaking In the House of Assembly on
May 28, 1963, said that the National Party seemed to see
the Western Cape as "the stronghold of White civilization"
where the Whites in a kind of siege could make a last stand
while there was trouble elsewhere.
Under the Bantu Laws Amendment Act of 1963, popularly
known as the Servants Act, the residence of African domes¬
tic workers on the premises of their White employers is
severely restricted.
The Department of Bantu Administration and Develop¬
ment sent a directive to all local authorities on February 14,
1963 curbing any further expansion of African private enter¬
prise in urban areas.
The pass system has often been described as perhaps the
most serious grievance of the African people as it restricts
their freedom of movement at every turn. Over the years,
the African people have staged numerous protests against
the passes, regarded by them as "badges of slavery",
including the demonstration at Sharpeville and other areas
in 1960.
Under the Natives (abolition of Passes and Co-ordination
of Documents) Act of 1952, the National Party Government
replaced the passes of the Africans by "reference books."
The rest of the population has been Issued identity cards.
While non-Africans rarely suffer penalties for non-
possession of Identity cards, the Africans are subjected
to severe punishments for even accidental misplacing of
reference books.
The reference books contain permits to remain in an
urban area, tax receipts and other particulars. Africans
found outside the reserves without permits are taken to
courts, for fine or imprisonment, and expelled. Juvenile
offenders may be sentenced to whipping.
The regulations were strengthened during 1962,
particularly by the requirement that all African women
must carry "reference books" from February 1, 1963. The
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
APARTHEID (Cont'd)
A multitude of arrests and convictions
24
extension of the pass system to African women has always
been strongly resented by Africans, as the subjection of
women to the procedures may lead to serious consequences
for their families. Mothers of small children may be
suddenly arrested. Husbands and wives may be arrested
separately and expelled to their respective "homelands"
which may be hundreds of miles apart. A mother may be
"endorsed out" even though her child was born in the
city: if she takes the child with her, the child loses the right
to return to the city without special permission.
One of the most striking features of the South African
racial policies is the multitude of arrests and convictions
under the numerous laws and regulations which restrict the
freedom of movement and residence of the African people.
The number of convictions in 1962 was 384,497, or over a
thousand a day. The total convictions in the previous
decade was 3,886,568.
The urban Africans are In constant dread of being
expelled from towns and sent to the reserves. Such orders
seem to have greatly Increased as the Government proceeds
even more vigorously with its "apartheid" policies. In 1962,
4,254 African women and 677 African children were
"endorsed out" of African townships of Johannesburg.
The Johannesburg Star, on June 10, 1963, reported two
case histories, narrated by an African social worker, which
disclose the hardships encountered by the urban Africans.
"The parents of two young boys were both working
in the city to make ends meet, so they sent their children
to their grandparents in the country to be properly
brought up and educated.
White & non-White
definitions
The South African Population Registration Act of 1950
classifies the population into racial categories which
it defines as follows:
WHITE: "White person means a person who in
appearance obviously is, or who is generally accepted
as a White person, but does not include a person who,
although in appearance obviously a White person, is
generally accepted as a Coloured person."
This definition was revised in the Population
Registration Amendment Act of 1960 to free citizens
of certain countries with which South Africa has
diplomatic or consular relations from the restrictive
measures applied to non-White people. According to
the new definition, a White person can also mean a
person who is generally accepted as a White person
even though obviously not in appearance a White person.
NATIVE: "Native means a person who in fact is, or
is generally accepted as, a member of any aboriginal
race or tribe of Africa."
COLOURED PERSON: "Coloured person means a
person who is not a White person or a Native."
In Proclamation No 46 of 1959, Coloured people are
sub-divided as follows: "Cape Coloured, Cape Malay,
Griqua, Chinese, Indian, 'other Asiatic' and 'other
Coloured'." The last group comprises persons not
included in any of the other groups, and who are neither
White nor Native.
(From "L'Afrique du Sud et la Primauté du Droit »
"South Africa and the Primacy of Law a report
published by the International Commission of Jurists,
Geneva, in 1961.)
"When the children had finished school and were old
enough to work, they found there was no work for them
In the country, so they were brought to Johannesburg.
But in Johannesburg they were 'endorsed out' because
they had not lived in the city. And when they returned
to the country they were 'endorsed out' of that district,
where they had spent their childhood because they were
born in Johannesburg.
"Legally they are not living anywhere they are
displaced persons. So what do they do? They live
illegally with their parents in Johannesburg, lying low by
day and roaming the streets at night workless, shiftless,
mal-nourished and hopeless.
"Another boy lived in the country with his parents until
they both died and he came to Johannesburg to live with
an uncle. He was caught in a pass raid and 'endorsed
out' of Johannesburg because he was not born there and
had not lived there for 10 years.
"He was told to go back to the place in the country,
but he had lost touch with the people there since the
death of his parents and no longer knew anybody who
could give him a home. He is only 17. So he continues
to live illegally with the uncle, hoping not to be 'picked
up', and his uncle supports him.
"What does the future hold for him? Will his uncle have
to support him In idleness for the rest of his life?
"Is it any wonder that many of them became tsotsis
[juvenile delinquents] even criminals?"
N integral part of the "apartheid" policy is the
»preservation of the skilled and higher-paid
professions to the Whites and the limitation of African
workers to unskilled and low-paid occupations. Through
the implementation of this policy, the Republic has provided
for its White inhabitants one of the highest standards of
living in the world, while the non-Whites receive only a
fraction of White earnings.
The National Party Government has greatly extended the
"colour-bar" in employment. The Industrial Conciliation Act
of 1956 provides for the reservation of occupations for
particular racial groups. As the Whites monopolize political
power, their Interests are paramount when there is com¬
petition among racial groups. The non-Whites can never
be certain of being able to utilize the skills they have
acquired or seek to acquire.
Five work reservation determinations were made in the
past year, reserving the driving of motor-trucks, skilled
jobs in the building industry and bartending in various areas
to Whites only. Other reservations are under investigation.
These decisions have created great bitterness.
Such blatant discriminatory measures as job reservation
are facilitated by the fact that the Africans have no political
rights and, Indeed, are denied even trade union rights.
African trade unions cannot be registered and cannot
engage in collective bargaining. African workers are not
permitted to strike: penalties reach a fine of 1,000 Rand,
three years' imprisonment, or both.
In the public services, the Whites not only monopolize
the higher levels but form a majority, though they account
for less than a fourth of the population.
Registration of the population by race continues to evoke
serious resentment, especially in view of recent reports
that hundreds of Coloured families had been reclassified
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
For their efforts to obtain equ -
ality of rights in South Africa,
many Africans have been ar¬
rested and condemmed to long
terms of imprisonment. One
of them is Nelson Mandela,
an African leader, shown here
(centre). He was one of a
group of 91 Africans who were
tried in 1962. He was again
tried on new charges in 1963
and on June 12, 1964, was
sentenced to life ¡mprisonnent.
Photos © Holmes-Lebel, Paris - Ian Berry
as Whites. In many cases, one part of the family Is
classified as White and another as Coloured.
Hundreds of persons are annually convicted under the
Immorality Act, which prohibits mixed marriages and carnal
intercourse between members of different races.
Though mixed sports are not prohibited by law, Govern¬
ment leaders have pressed sports associations to segregate
members by race. Segregated sports facilities have been
established under the Group Areas Act and local bodies
have prevented mixed sports. Passports and other facilities
have been denied to mixed teams and legislative measures
have been threatened unless the associations comply with
Government policy. Such measures have led to proposals
in International sports organizations to exclude South Afri¬
can teams.
One of the most significant aspects of the policy of
"apartheid" is the determined effort to bring education
under government control, segregate the educational
system on the basis of race and tribe, and train the non-
Whites for the Inferior position assigned to them by
government policies.
A major step In this direction was taken in 1953 with
the promulgation of the Bantu Education Act transferring
responsibility for African education (except higher educa¬
tion) from the provincial governments to the Central
Government, and granting wide powers to the Minister over
both government and private schools.
Religious missions were obliged to transfer control over
their schools to the government or lose state subsidies if
they chose to remain as private schools. Only a small
number could survive without subsidies.
A separate account was established for grants-in-aid to
non-government schools. The government's contribution
was pegged at 13 million Rand [A Rand is the equivalent
of 10/- sterling or $1.40], with the result that the
Africans were obliged to pay for educational expansion
through Increased taxes and contributions by communities.
The government then proceeded to extend "apartheid"
into higher education by dividing the higher institutions on
a racial and tribal basis, and locating African colleges out¬
side urban areas.
In 1959, legislation was adopted to take over control of
the Fort Hare University College and to establish separate
university colleges for non-White persons. No White person
may attend any of the colleges for non-Whites, and after a
transition period (during which students already enrolled in
one of the "open" universities were to be allowed to finish
their courses subject to the annual approval of the Minister),
non-Whites are restricted to their colleges.
The Council and the Senate of each non-White university
college is composed of White members only. Non-Whites
serve on the Advisory Council and the Advisory Senate.
HE Government claims that the transfer ol
African education to its control has resulted in
great expansion of educational opportunities. The number
of pupils, for instance, increased from 938,000 in 1953-54
to 1.6 million in 1961. The figures on such expansion,
however, deserve some qualifications and comments.
First, as the government's share in financing African
education is pegged at 13 million Rand, increases in expen¬
diture must be provided by direct taxes on Africans. The
result has been a decrease in per capita expenditure on
education.
Second, of the 6,927 schools for Africans, only 169 are
government schools; the rest are state-aided schools.
Third, 97 per cent of the children attending school are in
the primary grades and of these only about one quarter
are in higher primary grades (the second four years of
primary school). Only 911 sat for the matriculation examina¬
tion in 1962.
Fourth, many African leaders and educationists oppose
"Bantu education" on the ground that it seeks to promote
tribalism and restrict learning by emphasizing mother-tongue
instruction and greatly reducing instruction in English and
Afrikaans. Primary schools have been organized on an
ethnic basis, with each providing education in one of the
seven recognized African languages. English and Afrikaans
are taught as subjects, and each is allotted less than two
hours a week. A petitioner before the Special Committee
stated:
"This means that the standard of English and Afrikaans
remains very low making it even more difficult for the
African to fit into an economy run by Whites who do not
speak tribal languages, and even to communicate with
Africans of other tribes."
Fifth, the increase in university enrolment of Africans is
misleading, as it is mainly in extension or correspondence
courses In the University College of South Africa and in
non-degree courses at tribal colleges.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
All labour legislation in
South Africa is based on
separation in employment
according to race. In
1957 this racial discrimina¬
tion was extended to the
nursing profession by the
Nursing Act. Left, at a
meeting in Johannesburg
a White nurse joins non-
White colleagues in protest¬
ing agains the "apartheid"
regulations. Right, this
young non-White nurse
would not be allowed,
according to law, to serve
on the council that deals
with the registration, train¬
ing and discipline of nurses.
And whatever her qualifica¬
tions, she would never be put
in charge of White nurses.
Photos <© Holmte-Lebel, Paris -
Ian Berry.
APARTHEID (Cont'd)
One Bantu child in three in infancy
The iniquities suffered by the non-Whites under individual
laws or aspects of policy provide but a partial picture of
the varied effects of the "apartheid" policy in terms of
poverty, malnutrition, disease, breakdown of family life,
humiliation and racial tension.
Because of racial discrimination, the White population of
the Republic of South Africa has been able to enjoy one
of the highest standards of living, while the non-Whites are
denied an equitable share of the national income. A few
facts from a recent report to the Economic Commission for
Africa are illustrative:
The ratio between the average wage earnings of
Whites and Africans In the mining industry is approxi¬
mately 15:1; in secondary industry it Is 5:1.
In 1960, the Whites who constituted 19.3 per cent
of the population accounted for 67 per cent of the national
income; the Africans who constituted 68.4 per cent
of the population received 26.5 per cent; and the
Coloureds and Asians, who constituted 12.4 per cent of
the population, received 6.5 per cent.
In 1959, the Whites had a per capita Income of £425
a year; Africans £39; and Asians and Coloureds £54.
Poverty, malnutrition and disease are so widespread
among the non-Whites in South Africa, despite the vast
economic resources of the country, that the situation has
caused national concern and led recently to debates in the
Parliament and the press.
A number of recent surveys show that the average income
26 °f African families is far below the minimum monthly
expenditure required for decent living.
Surveys In Durban showed that 60 per cent of African
workers had no breakfast at all and that a large number of
African school-children had nothing whatever to eat until
supper-time. In a hospital survey in the Cape, 54 per cent
of the non-White children were found to be severely under¬
weight and 17 per cent to be at a level Indicative of gross
starvation. Dr. Hansen, associate professor of Child Health
at Cape Town University, stated in October 1962:
"The total mortality rate for all cases in the age group
one to four shows that Bantu children are dying at
25 times and Coloured children at 15 times the rate of
White children."
In Cape Town, one hundred times as many non-Whites
as White children die per year of gastro-enteritis. Kwashior¬
kor, which is considered medically as being the index of
the general state of malnutrition in a community, was found
in five per cent of the Bantu children treated by doctors
who assisted in a recent study.
The general infant mortality rate of African children is
one of the highest in the world, varying from over 200 per
1,000 in the cities to 300 to 400 in some of the rural areas.
The corresponding figure for White children is 27, which
is one of the lowest in the world.
Added to the poverty, malnutrition and disease are the
constant humiliations suffered by the Africans because of
the complex laws restricting their freedoms and laying
down heavy penalties for breaches.
An African cannot enter an urban area without a permit
and cannot stay for more than 72 hours without a work
permit. An African cannot establish the right to residence
in an urban area unless he has lived there continuously
since birth or worked continuously for a single employer
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
committed a crime or of possessing information on the
commission of a crime. This legislation evoked widespread
criticism in South Africa and abroad as ending the rule of
law and creating a police state.
The Minister of Justice is now empowered to ban political
organizations and public meetings. He is authorized to
prohibit persons from public activities, restrict their move¬
ments, banish them, place them under "house arrest" or
detain them for recurring periods of ninety days each.
He may prohibit publications or require deposits of
20,000 rand for registration of newspapers. In many cases,
the Minister Is not required to give grounds for action or
may only have to charge the victim with furthering the aims
of communism, defined so widely as to cover all active
opposition to the policies of "apartheid." The powers of
the courts to review his actions are extremely circum¬
scribed.
In June 1963, the Commissioner of Prisons revealed that
5,293 persons had been arrested in the previous year for
alleged security crimes; of these, 2,047 had been arrested
on charges of attempting to further the aims of the African
National Congress or the Pan-Africanist Congress.
Hundreds of persons were tried in the past few months
on charges of sabotage, association with or furthering
the alms of unlawful organizations...
Sabotage, it may be noted, is defined very broadly and
carries the maximum penalty of death.
One result of this series of repressive actions was the
growing conviction among the opponents of "apartheid,"
including all the major non-White organizations, that there
was no legal means of fighting the policy and that violent
resistance was essential to secure equal rights for all the
people of the country.
for ten years, nor is the wife or unmarried child under eigh¬
teen of an African meeting such requirements. Even then
he can be "endorsed out" if he takes employment in
another area or fails to report within three days of his
being unemployed.
The wife of an African worker in town can visit him for
no, more than 72 hours and only if she obtains a permit
from officials on the ground, for example, that she wishes
to conceive.
Such laws and regulations have led to serious social
problems. The rate of illegitimacy among African children
in urban areas Is extremely high. The Annual Report of
the City Medical Officer of Health for Durban for 1961 states
that out of a total of 5,864 births amongst the Africans,
3,665 were illegitimate.
For infractions of the onerous laws and regulations, in
the making of which they have no voice, the Africans are
summarily imprisoned, fined or "endorsed out" of their
towns.
Flogging is a mandatory punishment for various offences.
Official figures Indicate that in the past ten years 850,000
strokes have been inflicted on penal offenders. Floggings
are currently running at the rate of 80,000 strokes a year
on 17,000 offenders. The number of offenders flogged
today is eight times what it was 20 years ago.
Not surprisingly, the situation has led to bitterness and
racial tension and this is recognized even by responsible
officials who support the policies of "apartheid."
The South African Government has enacted a mass of
repressive legislation in recent years to silence and suppress
all opposition to the policies of "apartheid." Such legisla¬
tion has been further strengthened during the past year.
The General Law Amendment Act of 1963, promulgated
in May, provides inter alia for the detention of persons for
90 days at a time without trial on suspicion of having
HE non-White people of South Africa had tried
a variety of peaceful means to achieve their
aims and faced harsh persecution by the Government.
In the post-war period alone, one may recall the Indian
passive resistance movement of 1946-48 in which 2,300 per¬
sons courted arrest; the Campaign of Defiance against
Unjust Laws in 1952 in which over 8,500 persons of all
races were arrested for non-compliance with "apartheid"
regulations; and numerous demonstrations, boycotts, and
strikes. All these had been countered by the harshest
measures of repression and ever more rigorous laws. The
government has consistently refused to recognize that the
demand by non-Whites for a share of political power in
the country is legitimate, and has put down all such demands
as mortal dangers to the social order.
To cope with the increasing tension in the country, the
government has undertaken a tremendous expansion of all
branches of the armed forces, the setting up of air com¬
mando units, the establishment of police reserves and
home guards, the training of civilians in the use of arms,
the development of the radio network to link all of the
nearly one thousand police stations, the import of vast
quantities of modem arms, and the great increase in the
defence and police budgets.
During the period between 1960-61 and 1963-64, the
defence budget has nearly quadrupled, while the expen¬
ditures on police increased by over one-third. Estimates
for the current year are far in excess of the highest annual
expenditure during the second World War when South Afri¬
can forces saw action In many theatres.
The problem in South Africa is not merely the perpetua¬
tion of inequalities arising from historical developments
or the continued existence of such inequities as the denial
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
APARTHEID (Cont'd)
Incalculable harm to persons of all races
of franchise to a majority of the population, the separation
of people by race or the discrimination in the sharing of
the fruits of labour. Such terms as segregation and discri¬
mination can hardly describe the humiliation and oppression
to which millions of people, who constitute a large majority
of the population of the country, have been subjected by
the policies of its government
The problem, moreover, is not one of a peculiar political
or social system which democratic-minded peoples find
objectionable, nor one of colour or race, but the con¬
sequence of a racialist ideology enshrined as state policy
and implemented by force against the majority of the people
of the country, in violation of the obligations of the South
African Government under the United Nations Charter.
The racist creed that the policies of "apartheid" are based
on is the very antithesis of the concept of international
co-operation which is at the root of the existence of the
United Nations.
The Special Committee noted that the major non-White
organizations favour equality of all citizens, irrespective of
race, and that they have repeatedly expressed a desire for
discussions to ensure progress towards equality. It has
also noted with great satisfaction that among those who
oppose the policies of "apartheid," despite severe repres¬
sion, are members of all racial groups in the country,
including many Whites.
The United Nations has already made clear .In General
Assembly resolution 616 B (VII), reaffirmed in subsequent
resolutions, that the peaceful development of a unified
community in multi-racial societies such as the Republic
of South Africa would best be assured "when patterns of
legislation and practice are directed towards ensuring equa¬
lity before the law of all persons regardless of race, creed
or colour, and when economic, social, cultural and political
participation of all racial groups is on a basis of equality."
The Special Committee feels that this is the only course
which can serve the true interests of all the peoples of the
Republic of South Africa, irrespective of race or colour.
The harsh repressive measures instituted by the govern¬
ment frustrate the possibilities for peaceful settlement,
enhance hostility among the racial groups, and precipitate a
violent conflict with incalculable harm to persons of all
racial groups in the country, to friendly relations among
states, and to the maintenance of peace in Africa and
the world.
UNESCO PUBLICATIONS ON RACE
out of print
** being reprinted
THE RACE QUESTION IN MODERN SCIENCE, Paris, UNESCO, 1959.
373 p. $5. 20/- (See page 35).
RACE AND SCIENCE, New York, Columbia University Press, 1961.
506 p. $5.
THE RACE QUESTION IN MODERN SCIENCE Series:
Racial Myths, by Juan Comas, 1961, $0.30, 1/6; Race and Society**,
by Kenneth L. Little, 1961, $0.30, 1/6; Race and Culture, by Michel
Leiris, 1961, $0.30, 1/6; Race and History, by Claude Lévi-Strauss,
1961, $0.30, 1/6; Race and Biology, by LC. Dunn, 1961, $0.30, 1/6; The
Significance of Racial Differences, by G.M. Morant, 1961, $0.30, 1/6;
Race Mixture, by Harry L. Shapiro, 1953, $0.25, 1/6; The Roots of Prejudice,
by Arnold M. Rose, 1960, $0.30. 1/6; Race and Psychology**, by Otto
Klinebero. 1961, $0.30, 1/6; The Jewish People, by Harry L. Shapiro, 1960,
$0.70, 3/6; Race Relations and Mental Health, by Marie Jahoda, 1961.
$0.50, 2/6; The Race Concept, Results of an Inquiry*, 1958.
RACE AND SOCIETY Series:
Race and Class in Rural Brazil, by Charles Wagley, 1963, $2, 10/-;
Racial Equality and the Law*, by Morroe Berger, 1954; Equality of Rights
between Races and Nationalities in the U.S.S.R.*, by I. P. Tsamérian and
S.L. Ronlne. 1962; The Defence of Human Rights in Latin America (16th
to 18th Centuries), by Silvio Zavala, 1964, .$0.70, 3/6.
THE RACE QUESTION AND MODERN THOUGHT Series:
The Catholic Church and the Race Question*, by Father Yves M.J.
Congar, 1961; The Ecumenical Movement and the Racial Problem*, by
W.A. Visser't Hooft, 1954; Jewish Thought as a Factor in Civilization,
by Léon Roth, 1961, $0.50, 2/6; Buddhism and the Race Question, by
G.P. Malalasekera and K.N. Jayatilleka, 1958, $0.50, 2/6.
INTERNATIONAL BULLETIN FOR SOCIAL SCIENCES
Vol. II, No 4, 1950Racial Problems*; Vol. IX. No 4. 1957The Negro
in the U.S.A.*; Vol. X N° 3, 1958Recent Research on Race Relations*;
Vol. XIII. No 2, 1961Recent Research on Race Relations*; Vol. XVII.
N°. 1, 1965Biological Aspects of Race.
Annual, subscription: $7 .OX); 35/-.
ARTICLES ON RACE PUBLISHED BY THE UNESCO COURIER
NOVEMB»ER 1949: The Question of Race and the Democratic World,
by Arthur Ramos.
JANUARY 1950: What Is Race? by Humayun Kabir.
JULY-AU»GUST 1950: Fallacies of Racism Exposed; The Scientific Basis
for Human Unity (Statement prepared by the Unesco Committee of
Experts on Race Problems); Race and Civilization, by Alfred Métraux
SEPTEMBER 1950: An Indian Girl with a Lesson for Humanity; Study
of Brazilian Ethnic Groups Will Help Unesco to Fight Race Prejudice.
APRIL 1951: Brazil, Land of Harmony for All Races? by Alfred Métraux
OCTOBER 1951: Don't Trust the Valonians, by Georges Fradier.
JANUARY 1952: It Happened in a Tiny Village, by Georges Fradier
FEBRUARY 1952: The Book that Roused a Nation a Hundred Years Ago,
by Jacques Guérif
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1952: An Inquiry into Race Relations in Brazil,
by Alfred Métraux; The Negro's Role in Brazilian History, by Gilberto
Freyre; Sao Paulo, by Roger Bastide; Rio de Janeiro: Melting Pot of
Peoples, by L.A. Costa Pinto; Shades of Colour and of Meaning, by
Harry W. Hutchinson; Attitudes in the "Blacklands," by Charles Wagley;
Bahia, the Negro Metropolis, by Thaies de Azevedo
AUGUST-SEPTIEMBER 1953: A Man with Racial Prejudice is as Pathetic
as His Victim, by Alfred Métraux; The Origins of Races Still Steeped
in Mystery, by W.W. Howells; The Racial Heritage of H.M.S. Bounty,
I by Harry L. Shapiro; The Christian Attitude towards Race, by Father
I Yves Congar; To Worship, Live and Work Together Regardless of
Race, by W.A. Visser't Hooft; You Have to Learn to Make Friends,
by Syeda Saiyidian (Age 9); Sociological Aspects of Race Relations,
by E. Franklin Frazier; The Bushmen of Australia in Modern Civilization,
by A.P. Elkin; Race Relations and Public Housing in the United States,
by Patricia Salter West and Maria Jahoda
NOVEMBER 1953: They Challenged Slavery to Free Men in Chains
FEBRUARY 1954: Hawaii, Racial Crossroads of the Pacific, by Harry
Shapiro
JUNE 1954: A Look at U.S. Race Relations, by Morroe Berger; The
Decision Was Unanimous, by Murray Stedman, Jr.; The Greatest Test of
"Civil Rights," by Thurgood Marshall; Social Scientists Testify on
Segregation, by Otto Klineberg; Going to School with the Negro;
The Road towards Equality
FEBRUARY 1956: The Power of Words, by Cyril Bibby
JUNE, JULY, AUGUST, SEPTEMBER 1958: The Roots of Prejudice, by
Arnold M. Rose
APRIL 1959: Current Misconceptions about the Australian Aborigines,
by Ronald M. Berndt
OCTOBER 1960: Race, Prejudice and Education, by Cyril Bibby; A
Look at Modern Anti-Semitism, by Léon Poliakov; The Racial Landscape
of Latin America, by Alfred Métraux; X-Ray of the Racist Mind, by
Marie Jahoda; Frank Conversation at an Empty Table, by Khushwant
Singh; The Cinema Says Nol to Racism, by Louis Marcorelles
JANUARY 1961: Christianity and Anti-Semitism, by Father Yves Congar;
A Few Comments, by Léon Poliakov; Letters to the Editor on October 19(30
Issue on Race.
FEBRUARY 1961: Towards Racial Harmony, by Alfred Métraux
Note ; With die exception of October 1961, all the issues listed are out of
print. We refer readers to their local library.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
^-=""
i A"
WW
* Í.I *
A group of Africans
is marched off to an
employment centre
in Johannesburg. For
these men no choice
of work exists. In
urban areas the
movement, residence
and employment of
non-Whites is strictly
controlled. People
of the "Coloured"
groups are also sub¬
ject to these rules.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
,- JSK
IT IS STILL NOT TOO LATE
Supported by laws and acts of repression, the policy of "apartheid" in South Africa has
opened the way to violence and to forces that are now leading at an accelerating pace
towards disaster. On December 4, 1 963, the Security Council of the United Nations appoint¬
ed a group of specialists to examine ways of resolving the present situation in South Africa
through the full, peaceful and orderly application of human rights and fundamental freedoms
to the entire population, regardless of race, colour or creed. Below we publish an abridg¬
ment of the recommendations and comments of this U.N. group. Working under the chair¬
manship of Mrs. Alva Myrdal, the distinguished Swedish sociologist, who was formerly
director of Unesco's Department of Social Sciences, the group comprised Sir Edward
Asafu-Adjaye, one of Ghana's leading jurists, Mr. Dey Ould Sidi Bara, Deputy Permanent
Representative of Morocco to the United Nations, and Sir Hugh Foot, (now Lord
Caradon, Permanent Representative of the United Kingdom to the United Nations).
THE future of South Africa should be settled
by the people of South Africa all the people
of South Africa in free discussion. There can be no settle¬
ment and no peace while the great majority of the people
are denied the fundamental freedom to participate in deci¬
sions on the future of their country. We are convinced
that a continuation of the present position including a
denial of just representation must lead to violent conflict
and tragedy for all the people of South Africa. We wish,
therefore, to emphasize the first and basic principle that
all the people of South Africa should be brought Into consul¬
tation and should thus be enabled to decide the future of
their country at the national level.
In order to give effect to this essential principle, we
consider that all efforts should be directed to the estab¬
lishment of a National Convention fully representative of
the whole population. Such a representative National
Convention would consider the views and proposals of
all those participating and set a new course for the
future (1).
(1) The disenfranchised part of the population constitutes four-fifths OQ
of the whole. Under the franchise restricted to White voters only ¿v
about half voted in 1961 for the Nationalist Party, now in power,
and the rest voted for parties which oppose the present "apartheid"
policies of the Government.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
SPOKESMEN FOR
FREEDOM 6l JUSTICE
-
Q Holmes-Lebel, Paris - Ian Berry
Many White South Africans are opposed to the poli¬
cy of "apartheid." Above. Alan Paton, author of
the famous novel, "Cry the Beloved Country,"
which has been published in 16 languages. He is
president of a party which draws its members from
all racial groups and which since 1960 has campaign¬
ed actively for the introduction of universal suffrage.
Albert J. Luthuli, a former Zulu chief, who was awarded the Nobel
Peace Prize in 1960, has consistently fought the policy of "apart¬
heid" by methods of non-violence. He has described South Africa
as "a vast camp of displaced persons." For his resistance to "apart¬
heid" he has been banished to Natal until 1969. Restricted to this
area, he now has practically no contact with the outside world.
Right. Miriam Makeba. the well-known South
African singer. She has been banished from
South Africa and now lives in the United States.
In July, 1963, she appeared before the U.N.
Special Committee. The time has come, she
declared, for all mankind to act with firmness
to stop the South African Government from
dragging the country into a horrifying disaster.
.' > .:, . -
IT IS STILL NOT TOO LATE (Cont'd)
A racial policy condemned the world over
30
[In March 1961, an All-in-African Conference unanimously
demanded a national convention of elected representatives
of all adult men and women on an equal basis irrespective
of race, colour, creed or other limitations. This demand
was supported by different parties and organizations and
prominent persons in academic, religious and public life.
A national convention would carry out sweeping reforms.
It would introduce a Bill of Rights, incorporating the funda¬
mental principles set out in the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights. It would set up a Supreme Court vested
with authority to defend equality of rights for all citizens.
It would draw up a new constitution for South Africa.
Among its other tasks would be the solution of broad
economic and social problems, the establishment of rights
of freedom of movement and residence and of freedom
of opportunity in employment. It would also guarantee
education for all, irrespective of race.]
We believe that the mounting condemnation by world
opinion and the growing insistence on positive action should
now be directed to the achievement of this purpose. It is
only on the road of free and democratic consultation and
co-operation and conciliation that a way can be found
towards a peaceful and constructive settlement. Only
thus can all people of South Africa be saved from catas¬
trophe and the world from a conflagration of incalculable
consequences . . .
We wish to draw special attention to two main factors
in the present situation. On one side is the mounting
International condemnation of the racial policy of the
South African Government and the growing determination
of the African States, in particular, to take positive action
against South African racial discrimination and domination.
On the other side is the increased persistence and military
preparation of the South African Government, coupled
with repressive action and legislation which leave many
South Africans with the conviction that they have no
means of resistance other than violence. These forces
are set on a collision course. They approach the crash
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
at accelerating pace. As the explosion grows nearer the
need to endeavour to prevent it becomes ever more
urgent.
United Nations concern about South Africa started in
relation to the problem of the treatment of people of Indian
origin and the status of the Mandated Territory of South
West Africa, but for more than a decade since in 1952
the "campaign of defiance against unjust laws" was organ¬
ized by non-White organizations in South Africa the
United Nations has directed its attention to the whole
problem of "apartheid" in South Africa. Throughout this
decade there have been repeated appeals to the South
African Government from the United Nations to abandon
its policies of "apartheid" and growing demand for action,
leading up to resolution 1761 (XVII) of the General Assem¬
bly of November 6, 1962 which was passed by a vote
of 67 in favour, 16 against and 23 abstentions. Thus for
the first time a resolution calling on Member States to
impose diplomatic and economic sanctions against South
Africa was passed in the General Assembly with more than
a two-thirds majority.
During 1963, the Security Council and General Assembly
passed further resolutions calling for an abandonment of
"apartheid", the liberation of political prisoners, the cessa
tion of the political trials against opponents of "apartheid"
and the termination of sale of armaments and ammunition
to South Africa. In regard to the question of South West
Africa, the General Assembly made an appeal to Member
States not to supply petroleum and petroleum products
to South Africa. The Assembly's resolution calling for the
termination of political trials was passed by a vote of 106
to 1 (South Africa), and the Security Council's resolution
of December 4, 1963 was unanimous.
During the recent debates in the Security Council and
the General Assembly, condemnation of the policies of
South Africa in the strongest terms came from the
overwhelming majority of Member States, including those
with the closest ties with South Africa. On August 6,
1963 the United Kingdom Permanent Representative spoke
of the policies of "apartheid" as "evil, totally impracticable,
and leading Inevitably to disaster in South Africa itself",
and to "certain tragedy". Mr. Patrick Wall, M.P., speaking
for the United Kingdom delegation in the Fourth Committee
of the General Assembly on November 12, 1962, described
"apartheid" as "morally abominable, intellectually grotes¬
que and spiritually indefensible." On December 4, 1963,
the permanent representative of the United States said that
"progress in Africa is over-shadowed by the racial bitter¬
ness and resentment caused by the policies of the South
African Government." He went on to say that it was the
duty of the Security Council to ensure an end to the
injustice of "apartheid." "not in bloodshed and bondage,
but in peace and freedom."
EANWHILE, the South African Government has
become increasingly isolated. In 1961 it left the
Commonwealth. It had earlier withdrawn from Unesco and
has now withdrawn from the Food and Agriculture Organi¬
zation and the International Labour Organisation, and has
been suspended from the Economic Commission for Africa.
Pressure for action, particularly for sanctions, has come
most strongly from the African States, and at the Confer¬
ence of Heads of State and Government held in Addis
Ababa in May 1963 a Committee of Liberation was estab¬
lished to co-ordinate material aid to movements of national
liberation in Africa . . .
In contrast to and conflict with the increasing interna¬
tional condemnation and demands for positive action to
bring "apartheid" to an end, the South African Govern¬
ment has pressed on with greater persistence and gather¬
ing speed in the application of the policies which the
world has condemned.
In pursuing this course it has been encouraged, and
perhaps given a sense of impunity, by a wave of economic
prosperity. Dr. Diedrichs, the Republic's Minister of
Economic Affairs, was able to claim on March 4, 1964,
that South Africa's economy is "among the most dynamic
in the world . . ."
These boom conditions have strengthened the determi¬
nation of the South African Government to pursue its poli¬
cies of "apartheid" and to supplement its massive powers
of suppression by increased financial allocations for repres¬
sive action . . .
On March 16, 1964, Dr. Donges, Minister of Finance,
announced a record defence budget of 310 million Rand
(£155 million). This is 52 million Rand (£26 million) more
than in the current year, and this follows on the qua-
drupling of the defence budget in the past four years. 31
South African production of armaments has risen in those
years by 80 per cent. Dr. Donges told the South African
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
IT IS STILL NOT TOO LATE (Cont'd)
I N. Mandel
Painter Gerard Sekoto is the son of a mission teacher in the
Transvaal. He left South Africa for the U. S. A., where his
work has been exhibited in Washington'sNational Gallery. For
the past 1 5 years he has continued his painting career in Paris.
In exile
free to
speak
Ezekiel Mphahlele. a
young South African
writer, was a secon¬
dary school teacher
in Johannesburg be¬
fore he emigrated in
1958 to Nigeria, to
teach at the Uni¬
versity College, Iba¬
dan. Since last year
he has been director
of the Chemchemi
Cultural Centre in
Nairobi, Kenya. He
has written many
bOt/KS and articles on
problems of Africa.
Congress of Cultural Freedom
Faber and Faber, London
Born in Johannesburg
in 1919, Peter Abra¬
hams lived there un¬
til he was 20. A jour¬
nalist and writer he
returned to South
Africa as a special
correspondent in
1952. In 1955 he went
to Jamaica where he
now lives. He is the
author of many books
and short stories in¬
cluding "Wreath for
Udomo,""Songofthe
City," "Dark Testa¬
ment" and "Tell
Freedom" (an auto¬
biography of his
early years in Africa).
Last chance to avert an
Parliament in introducing his budget that the 25 per cent
increase in defence expenditure was to "discourage foreign
aggression." South African Ministers have, however, never
sought to disguise the fact that defence and security
expenditure is largely, if not primarily, intended for action
within South Africa. Nor have they disguised the fact
that the Army and the Air Force as much as the police
are concerned with internal security. As the Minister
of Defence, Mr. J. J. Fouche, said in the Senate on March 28,
1960:
"The task of the Army and Air Force is to take
action for internal security as soon as disturbances
have reached a degree where the police are unable
to control them . . . Greater mobility, armoured protec¬
tion and increased striking power have been given to
twelve of the infantry units at strategic places in the form
of Saracens. These Citizen Force units, together with
the two Mobile Watches which are organized as Saracen
units for internal security, form a shock element
in the Army . . Besides these Watches and
the units of the Citizen Force the commandos
have been organized over the past years in order to
ensure that they will be able to act more efficiently
for internal security. At the moment, there is a scout
corps of twenty-five men with each commando and these
will be available immediately in case of internal emer¬
gency	"
HESE forces of conflict cannot be disregarded
or minimized. Only when the extent of the
danger is fully realized is there any hope that action suffi¬
ciently drastic will be taken to prevent it...
A race conflict starting in South Africa must affect race
relations elsewhere in the world, and also, in its interna¬
tional repercussions, create a world danger of first magni¬
tude . . .
We emphasize the special importance of world opinion.
Many countries, particularly African countries, are directly
identifying themselves with the cause of the oppressed
people of South Africa, but there is a wider International
concern. The conscience of the world has been stirred,
and there is a recognition in world opinion generally
that the South African problem is unique, demanding excep¬
tional treatment. There is an international crisis of cons¬
cience; it arises from the fact that in South Africa there
¡s a government professing to speak in the name of
Christianity and the "European race" which is the only
government in the world which chooses as its guiding
policy not a striving to attain justice, equality and safe¬
guards for human rights, but a determination to preserve
privileges, defend discrimination and extend domination to
such a degree that it amounts to the organization of a
society on principles of slavery. In South Africa the
denial of human rights and fundamental freedoms is
openly pursued as an avowed policy...
Some may think that time is past when there is any hope
of avoiding the collision which is now approaching, and
that the recent declarations and actions of the South
African Government rule out any possibility of negotiation.
Certainly time is short, and the dangers grow rapidly nearer
and greater.
Nevertheless, there is some ground for hope that the
point of no return has not yet been reached and that a
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
ordeal of violence and hate
fruitful dialogue may yet take place among the different
sections of the South African population.
Chief amongst the encouraging factors is the insistence
on constitutional measures and methods advocated over
many years by the parties and organizations opposing
"apartheid." Their leaders have displayed outstanding
political responsibility and have throughout emphasized
that all South Africans of whatever race should enjoy equal
rights.
Chief Luthuli, in his Nobel lecture delivered in Decem¬
ber 1961, made his famous declaration:
"The true patriots of South Africa, for whom I speak,
will be satisfied with nothing less than the full demo¬
cratic rights. In government, we will not be satisfied
with anything less than direct individual adult suffrage
and the right to stand for and be elected to all organs
of government. In economic matters, we will be satisfied
with nothing less than equality of opportunity in every
sphere, and the enjoyment by all of those heritages which
form the resources of the country which up to now have
been appropriated on a racial 'white only' basis. In
culture, we will be satisfied with nothing less than the
opening of all doors of learning to non-segregatory insti¬
tutions on the sole criterion of ability. In the social
sphere, we will be satisfied with nothing less than aboli¬
tion of all racial bars. We do not demand thes^e things
for people of African descent alone. We demand them
for all South Africans, white and black."
At the Conference at which the Pan-Africanist Congress
was established in 1959, Robert Sobukwe said that every¬
body who owes his only loyalty to Africa should be
regarded as an African; and that there is only one race,
the human race.
Nelson Mandela of the African National Congress when
on trial in 1962 before being sentenced to five years
imprisonment told the court:
"I am no racialist, and I detest racialism because
I regard it as a barbaric thing, whether it comes from a
black man or from a white man."
The struggle in South Africa is not a struggle between
two races for domination; it is a struggle between the
protagonists of racial domination and the advocates of
racial equality.
WE believe that if a new course is set now it is
still possible to envisage all South Africans
enjoying political justice and freedom under a constitution
guaranteeing human rights and providing for a democratic
system of government. Removal of the restrictions on
employment and residence and movement will open up
possibilities for far greater industrial and agricultural pros¬
perity. The economy of South Africa can surge forward if
the barrier of discrimination is removed. Reduction of
expenditure on military and repressive measures will free
large sums for development and welfare. And if equal
opportunities for education, are granted, a great new
reservoir of human capacity and skill will be created to
contribute to fruitful and peaceful progress. When the
burdens of oppression and discrimination and isolation are
lifted all South Africans will benefit.
We have no doubt that the cause of emancipation will
prevail in South Africa. The great majority of the popula
tion cannot be forced back into already overcrowded
reserves constituting less than 13 per cent of the country.
The right of the human person, the right of each individual
to live and work and move freely In his own country cannot
long be denied. A political, economic and social system
built on the domination of one race by another by force
cannot survive.
What is now at issue is not the final outcome but the
question whether, on the way, the people of South Africa
are to go through a long ordeal of blood and hate. If so
all Africa and the whole world must be involved.
We believe that the course of reason and justice which
we have advocated a course which could be promptly
and honourably accepted by all offers the only way and
the last chance to avoid such a vast tragedy.
The report of the U.'N. Group of Experts was submitted to the
U.N. Secretary-General on April 20, 1964.
In a letter dated May 22, 1964, the Permanent Representative
of South Africa claimed that the report of the Group of Experts
"consists to a large extent of inaccuracies, distortions and
erroneous conclusions on false premises" and declared that
"for obvious reasons the South African Government can see no
useful purpose in commenting on the detailed proposals for a
National Convention and its agenda."
On June 9, 1964, the Security Council urged South African
Government to "renounce the execution of the persons sentenced
to death for acts resulting from opposition to the policies of
'apartheid' and to end forthwith the trial in progress, instituted
within the framework of the arbitrary laws of 'apartheid'."
On July 13, 1964, the Government of South Africa replied, and
reiterated that South Africa regards "intervention by the United
Nations in the judicial processes of a member state as completely
illegal..."
On June 18, 1964 the Security Council renewed its appeal
to the Government of the Republic of South Africa "to liberate
all persons imprisoned..." and to accept the main conclusions
of the Expert Group that "all people of South Africa should be
brought into consultation and thus be enabled to decide the
future of their country at a national level."
On the same day, the Security Council invited the Secretary-
General of the United Nations, in consultation with appropriate
United Nations specialized agencies, to establish an educational
and training programme to allow education and training abroad
for South Africans.
On November 6, 1964, three leaders of the African National
Congress, Vuysile Mini, Wilson Kjayinga and Zinaxile Mkaba
were executed in Pretoria.
On November 16, 1964, the South African Government declared
that it would not respond to the appeal and invitation addressed
to it by the United Nations to examine the conclusions of the
report by the Group of Experts.
The case for economic sanctions against South Africa has often
been stated in the General Assembly and has been taken up by
the Special Committee and the Group of Experts. Recommen¬
dations have been made for states to place embargos on the
supply of arms, oil and rubber to the Republic of South Africa;
to ban the import of gold, diamonds and iron-ore from South
Africa; to refuse docking facilities to ships and servicing facilities
to aircraft bound for or returning from South Africa; and, among
other measures, to refuse to furnish technical assistance or equip¬
ment to the Republic of South Africa. The report of the Group
of Experts concludes: " It is only through a unanimous decision nn
of the Security Council that the weapon of sanctions can be Jo
rapidly effective. Only if action is agreed and complete can the
threat of sanctions achieve its purpose."
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
34
WHAT THE WORLD
SPENDS ON ARMS
Sir.
Arms or Aid? The world can ill
afford both, as your excellent Nov¬
ember 1964 issue showed so clearly.
1965 is International Co-operation
Year. We believe that the best
contribution from every government
would be for them to cut at least
1% from the arms spending each
year starting in 1965. The money
so saved to be handed over to the
various U.N. agencies for aid to the
developing countries. This would help
them to raise their living standards
and begin closing the gap between
the "haves' and the "have-nots".
Unless people everywhere see the
urgent need to substitute a planned
aid programme for the arms program¬
me half of humanity will continue to
suffer premature death from hunger
and preventable disease, while the
other half lives, in fear, with its vast
expensive War Machine.
Mary Clarke
(Women Strike for Peace), U.S.A.
Kathleen MacPherson
(Voice of Women), Canada
Margaret Curnen
(Liaison Committee for Women's
Peace Groups), U.K.
Sir.
It is disturbing to discover that
centuries of "progress* have brought
us, on the pretext of national defence,
to the threshold of total annihilation.
One can only deplore the fact that
governments have not had enough
imagination or human feelings to find
another answer to the problems of
international relations than the ruinous
use of force.
V. Larret
Veyrac, France
Sir,
Your November issue was the most
impressive I have yet seen. Bravo!
for sounding a warning that deserves
to be heard all over the world. Could
you arrange for off-prints to be made
of its contents at least the articles
by Linus Pauling and Alexander Kuzin?
Marcel S. Mandrin de Bruin
Aarau, Switzerland
Ed note: Off-prints of the facts and
published by TJie Unesco Courier
on arms spending in the world are now
available free of charge in English,
French, Spanish and German language
versions. Requests should be sent to
Public Liaison Division, Unesco, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris.
Sir,
Your November issue diagnosed a
critical condition. You helped us to
understand the reality of our world
where nations base their security on
material force. Also you showed us
the possibilities of a world without
war, or its costly preparation. You
described the symptoms and then you
went on to show that the cure, the
return to wealth was possible. But
hasn't the most important part been
omitted? Like a good doctor Unesco
should show us the causes behind
the symptoms and how to act resolut¬
ely so as to realize the cure.
The United Nations Postal Admi¬
nistration has a text which condemns
the use of nuclear arms as being
'incompatible with the spirit and the
letter of the charter". Is their prepa¬
ration any less so?
Should not peace research direct
its efforts towards finding a more
effective form of safeguard for world
peace and human liberty than de¬
pendence on military power? Surely
it is this inability to put aside military
power which is the real barrier to
world problems being settled on an
international basis? Military power
cannot be shared equally; there always
remains a certain domination; the more
powerful the nation, the less likely
to take the risk of making its power
international.
Could a truly international peace
front base its persuasion on any other
than moral force, which only asks to
be shared, which will suffer itself,
rather than make others suffer, to
convince?
Surely behind the "arms race"
there lies a wrong conception of secu¬
rity and ideological persuasion? Could
you not devote some space to these
important questions? Is it possible to '
make peace with a weapon in the
hand?
Patrick Hutchinson
Carsan, France
Sir,
Your excellent issue on the prob¬
lems of disarmament has revealed
the enormous waste of human and
material resources that could other¬
wise be used for the further develop¬
ment of science. You should now
devote an issue to the achievements
of different countries in using atomic
energy for peaceful ends. The fine
examples of international co-operation
in this field are proof that efforts are
being made to remove the danger
of war.
Simon Bachhrih
Permi, U.S.S.R.
Ed note: The Unesco Courier has devoted
two issues to the Peaceful Atom (Dec.
1953, Nov. 7954) and has published many
articles and photo stories on the subject
since then. Another issue on "Atoms
for Peace" is planned for 1966 or 1967.
Sir,
I am an angry woman, angry be¬
cause $120.000,000.000 is spent each
year in preparation for mass slaugh¬
ter and I am afraid that the story
of "The Last Flower" by James Thur-
ber may well become a reality.
Ariette Robert
Maisons-Alfort, France
Sir,
The November issue is most im¬
pressive and timely. Very few of the
people I know are aware of the full
issues and possibilities of disarma¬
ment.
This issue should be made available
to as many people as possible in
order to strengthen the belief that
something can be done about peace.
J. L. Moon
Shepperton, England
Sir,
As a child who experienced the
horrors of the last "war to end wars"
I am grieved to see how easily many
people accept the possibility of an¬
other war, never realizing that it
would be on a scale incomparable
with any previous conflict. There
can be no doubt about the salubrious
effect on public opinion of your
November issue. Everyone must
realize the consequences of accept¬
ing the possibility of war and also
what may be lost by rejecting the
solution of disarmament. This is
something that concerns us all.
As I should like to help in making
these facts known, I enclose a cheque
for ten copies of this issue.
Jeanne Goldberszt
Paris, France
Sir,
The best way to combat the evil
of armaments is to keep the public
fully informed about the military
projects of each nation. Everyone
should be told how much is being
spent on conventional arms and atomic
weapons and made to realize the
physical and political dangers that this
involves.
I admire your courage in exposing
with such clarity the shameful facts
about what countries now spend on
arms.
R. Jennar
Jodoigne-Souveraine, Belgium
Sir,
The increasing power and efficiency
of modern armaments have now made
the issue of peace or war the world's
No. 1 problem. The Moscow Test Ban
Treaty is an important step on the
road to disarmament, but it is vital
and urgent to take it a stage further.
All non-signatory countries with
nuclear weapons should adhere to
the treaty, and the ban on nuclear
explosions should be extended to
cover all types of atomic weapons'
tests.
Serge Lair
Paris
Next month :
EXTRA PAGES
IN FULL COLOUR
u
z
<
<
a
z
o
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE RACE QUESTION IN MODERN SC1EN»CE
¿4-4,
MMIfl LEWIS
THE .RACE QUESTION IN MODERN SCIENCE
RACF,
TIM
THE RACE QU.ESTION IN MODERN SCIENCE
THE .RACE QUESTION IN MODERN SCIENCE
RA0IAI:
m
LEVI-ÏTAAUSS
¡ML
Have you read Q
all these Unesco f
booklets on race
The Race Question in Modern
Science
$5.00 20/	 14 F
-jV Race Relations and Mental Health
by Marie Jahoda
$0.50 2/6 1,75 F
Race and Class in Rural Brazil
by Charles Wagley
$2.00 10/	 '7 F
-fc Race and Biology
by L C. Dunn
$0.30 1/6 1 F
-ykr Race and Culture
by Michel Leiris
$0.30 1/6 1 F
-^- Race and History
by Claude Levi-Strauss
$0.30 1 /6 1 F
-£- Racial Myths
by Juan Comas
$0.30 1/6 1 F
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 232»4 V, Melbourne C I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C I. (Victoria). f22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
1 1 2. rue du Trône, Brussels S. CCP 3380.00. - BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Ran¬
goon. (	). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, Sir Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B,
244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 1 3/50). CHINA. World Book Co
Ltd., 99 Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan
(Formosa). CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council,
P. O. Box 539, Nicosia.- CZECHOSLOVAKIA.S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks¬
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa.
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). - FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*. CCP,
1 2598-48. (1 0 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650 (DM 10).
GHANA Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House
Commercial St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRI¬
TAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H.
Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUN¬
GARY. Kultura, P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICE¬
LAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. (120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Ni-
col Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 13;'Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (	). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous
& Co., Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O.
Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LUXEM¬
BURG, Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd. .Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. S 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/.). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Port-Louis (1 0/-). MONACO. British Bourbon Street,
Library 30 Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174. Lagos (10/-). NOR¬
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense 7, Oslo. For the
Unesco Courier also: A.S- Narvesens Litteratur Tjeneste,
Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks 115 (17.50 kr.).' PA¬
KISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco
Publications House, P.O. Box 374 56-N Gulberg Indus¬
trial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES. The Modern Book
Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila. POLAND. "RUCH",
ul. Wronia, 23. Warsaw 1 0 (	). PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO, Spanish English Publi¬
cations, Eleanor Roosevelt 115, Apartado 1912, Hato
Rey. RHODESIA. The Book Centre, Gordon
Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN. Af Bashir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska UnescorSdet, Vasa-
gatan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus
6, 1 21 1 , Geneva CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News
Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (RL.50).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38. rue Kasr El Nil Cairo. Sub/agent: La
Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES.
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 1 001 6 (S 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Kn-
¡ïg, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
APARTHEID
For the results of a U.N.
inquiry into the consequen¬
ces of racial discrimination
in South Africa, see page 20.
A. P. N.
]]>
</page>
</document>
