<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="080978eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
AUGUST 19H - » French franc*
'I*"*»-
'
.
Heritage
'lUSr* Í
«£
!|
FOR ALL ..*i .
3ß
vï
*
-
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Sigiriya (Sri Lanka)
Cover: Photo R. Singh © ANA, Paris
The ancient city of Sigiriya lies at the foot of an
¡Egv immense rock of red gneiss, 180 m high, on the summit
llHafTl °f w^ich King Kasyapa I built a fortified palace in the
HBHMl 5th century AD (aerial view, front cover). Access to the
palace was via a staircase hewn in the rockface, leading
up from an enormous statue of the forequarters of a
crouching lion at the foot of the cliff. It was for this lion,
of which only the paws remain (above), that the rock
and later the city was named. On the death of the king, "Lion
Mountain" was given back to the Buddhist monks who had formerly
lived there, but was gradually abandoned. The ruins of the palace
and its cisterns of fresh water are very impressive. The aristocratic
quarter of the lower city is equally remarkable for its terraced
gardens and monumental ruins from which encroaching vegetation
has recently been cleared. But Sigiriya is above all famous for its rock
paintings halfway up the west face of the cliff. The paintings depict
21 graceful female figures known as the "Maidens of the Clouds",
comparable in their beauty to the famous frescoes at Ajantâ. This
site, which was inscribed on the World Heritage List in 1982, is
extremely vulnerable and requires constant attention. Unesco has
launched a comprehensive programme in support of archaeological
excavations, conservation and site development. Painstaking conser¬
vation work is currently being carried out on frescoes damaged by a
cyclone in 1978 and affected by erosion and insect attacks. To
reinforce the plaster on which the frescoes are painted, synthetic
resin is injected by syringe into the holes bored by the insects.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
August 1988
«
A legacy for all
by Federico Mayor Zaragoza
Director-General of Unesco
The world's wild places
by Alison Jolly
12
&
The conservation
of ancient cities
by Mounir Bouchenaki
16	
Time regained
A historical perspective
on cultural sites and monuments
by George Michell
27
A sense of the sacred
The values enshrined in holy places
by Oleg Grabar
32
The world heritage concept
by Michel Parent
34
An idea in action
The World Heritage Convention
and how it works
The World Heritage List
The CourierML
A window open on the world 4 1st year
Published monthly in 35 languages English
French Spanish Russian German
Arabic Japanese Italian Hindi
Tamil Hebrew Persian Dutch
Portuguese Turkish Urdu Catalan
Malaysian Korean Swahili Croato-
Serb Macedonian Serbo-Croat
Slovene Chinese Bulgarian Greek
Sinhala Finnish Swedish Basque
Thai Vietnamese Pashto Hausa
For many years Unesco has been committed to
the protection of the cultural and natural
heritage the splendid monuments and sites
created by past' civilizations and the natural
environment in which peoples have lived and
formed their cultural identity. The best-known
example of this commitment, the International
Campaign to Save the Monuments of Nubia,
was launched by Unesco in the 1960s and
enabled some of the finest vestiges of the past
to be saved for posterity.
The adoption of the World Heritage
Convention by Unesco's General Conference in
1972 signalled the opening of a new chapter in
this story. The Convention broke fresh ground
by affirming the existence of a World Cultural
and Natural Heritage which belongs to the
whole of mankind and by inaugurating a vast
project to define and inscribe on a World
Heritage List sites and monuments of such
outstanding value that their protection is the
responsibility of everyone. In so doing, it
ushered in a new form of that co-operation and
solidarity between nations and peoples which it
is Unesco's mission to promote.
Eight years ago, in August 1980, the Unesco
Courier devoted an entire issue to this project.
The present number brings the story up to
date. It provides an overview of the different
categories and groups of properties inscribed on
the World Heritage List, as well as brief
descriptions of a selection of them. The
number of inscriptions is so high (288
properties located in 65 countries) that making
a fully representative sample is no easy task. (It
should be pointed out that some countries with
a notable cultural and natural heritage are not
Parties to the Convention and consequently do
not appear in the following pages). Two criteria
helped to guide our choice. Properties which
featured in our August 1980 issue have not
(with two exceptions) been given coverage.
Secondly, we have concentrated on less
well-known sites and monuments which,
although quite as remarkable and beautiful as
their more famous counterparts, often do not
receive the attention they deserve.
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A legacy for all
BY FEDERICO MAYOR ZARAGOZA
Director-General of Unesco
THE cultural heritage of each
people is an expression of the
thousand and one facets of its
genius and of the mysterious continuity
which unites all it has created over the
centuries and all it has the potential to
create in the future. The preservation of
this heritage is an activity inherent in a
people's vitality and creativity.
The natural environment in which a
people lives also contributes to the sha¬
ping of its cultural identity. Works of
human creativity are set in landscapes
which are themselves sources of inspira¬
tion and beauty. The natural heritage is
the complement of the cultural heritage,
from which it is indissociable. It is of
fundamental importance for science and
for the conservation of plant and animal
species, which constitute an irreplace¬
able resource and are indispensable for
the maintenance of life on our planet.
The heritage, whether it be architectu¬
ral monuments and ensembles, land¬
scapes or nature reserves, is continually
exposed to many risks of deterioration,
resulting from such causes as the wear
and tear of time, irresponsible human
action, erosion, humidity, pollution,
rampant urbanism, and mass tourism.
In face of such dangers, which are
everywhere tending to become more se¬
vere, a new awareness of the need to
safeguard the heritage and a new desire
to co-operate actively to conserve and
present it to the public are beginning to
make themselves felt at world level.
Legislative, financial, technical and
administrative efforts deployed in this
field by different States have been given a
large measure of encouragement and
support from Unesco.
One of the most important of Unes¬
co's initiatives has been the framing of
the Convention Concerning the Protec¬
tion of the World Cultural and Natural
Heritage, which rests on the fundamen¬
tally new idea that such protection is not
the separate responsibility of each indivi¬
dual State in which there is a property
worthy of preservation, but a joint res¬
ponsibility incumbent on the whole of
humanity, which is the trustee of all the
great landmarks in the natural and cultu¬
ral history of the globe.
The Convention, adopted by the Ge¬
neral Conference of Unesco in 1972,
established a Committee of twenty-one
Member States which has the task of
examining, according to carefully defi¬
ned criteria, cultural and natural proper
ties of outstanding value which may jus¬
tify their inclusion on the "World
Heritage List".
States Parties to the Convention
nominate to the Committee properties
within their borders which they consider
to possess such outstanding value. In so
doing they undertake to protect the pro¬
perties in question. But, if their nomina¬
tions are accepted by the Committee,
they may also be eligible for certain
forms of assistance from the inter¬
national community under the World
Heritage Fund established by the
Convention.
The Fund, which is financed by
contributions from States Parties and
donations from other States, from insti¬
tutions and private individuals, makes it
possible to provide material or technical
support to those countries that need it. It
also makes possible the training of spe¬
cialized staff.
The success of the Convention in the
last fifteen years can be gauged from the
fact that 102 States have become Parties
to it, and that 288 properties have been
inscribed on the World Heritage List. It
is to be hoped that one day the List will
be fully universal and will constitute the
accepted reference for masterpieces of
nature and culture whose protection
concerns, henceforth, all countries and
all mankind.
For the Committee is not simply enu¬
merating cultural and natural properties.
It is attempting to create a world list
which will be as coherent and complete
as possible, following a thematic and
regional approach and reflecting the in¬
terdependence of cultures and the
complementarity of ecosystems in space
and time.
Inclusion on the World Heritage List
brings new prestige to the properties
inscribed there. For the people of a
country in which a World Heritage pro¬
perty is located such recognition is an
opportunity to take stock of the finest
elements of their heritage. But even more
important is the opportunity thus
offered to people of other countries to
discover and cherish these properties,
some of which are already well known,
others less so.
The compilation of the List makes it
possible to measure the extreme wealth
and diversity of this heritage. Faithful to
its mission, Unesco is thus contributing
to the discovery by each of the heritage
of all.
BY ALISON JOLLY
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Mount Taishan (People's
Republic of China)
Inscribed on the World He-
5¡"Q ritage List in 1987 for its ex-
Ilffpy ceptional association of
cultural and natural ele
ments, Mt. Taishan is the
oldest and the most impor¬
tant example of an ancient
geological transformation
system in eastern China, rich in fossils da¬
ting back to Cambrian times. Up to 462
species of medicinal plants are known to
come from the area, and some of the trees
are hundreds of years old. Twenty-two
temples, 97 sites of ancient ruins, 819 stone
tablets and 1,018 cliffside and stone inscrip¬
tions are among the many traces of China's
rich cultural heritage which have been
found in the area. Here, in one of the birth¬
places of Chinese civilization, evidence of
human activity dates back 400,000 years.
During Neolithic times (5,000-6,000 years
ago), the Dawenkou and Longshan cultures
flourished, on the north and south sides of
the mountain respectively. These moun¬
tainsides were also the sites of 2 rival States,
Qi and Lu, and their cultural artefacts cre¬
ated between 770 and 476 BC. Ruins of a
500-km wall built by the State of Qi can still
be seen in the area. Some of the temples on
Mt. Taishan, such as the Temple of the
Heavenly Rock, the Temple of the Queen
Mother of the West, and the Temple of the
Azure Clouds, are important Buddhist and
Taoist centres.
The world's wild places
AN old man climbed the steep
mountain. Oak forests spread their
canopy below him; pines and Cy¬
prus clung with gnarled roots to the fissures
of stone beside his path. His disciples fol¬
lowed, their thigh muscles quivering with
strain. They reached the painted temple at
the summit and slept, huddled in their
robes. The old man rose again before dawn.
He stood on a rock overhanging the abyss.
Far beneath, the plain stretched unbroken
for 200 kilometres towards the eastern sea.
The sun rose and suddenly flared, refracted
by layers of still air into a two-part goblet of
red jade. "The world is small!" exclaimed
the old man, and his disciples wrote it
down.
It was two and a half thousand years ago
that Confucius watched the sunrise from
Taishan Mountain. Last year, in December
1987, at the proposal of the Chinese Gov¬
ernment, Mount Taishan was declared a
World Heritage site. In addition to its sig¬
nificance for the hundreds of thousands of
Chinese who climb to its summit each year,
it is also a global treasure.
Approximately one-third of the sites in¬
cluded on the World Heritage List are there
because of their natural beauty and scientific
importance. They include mountains such
as Sagarmatha, Mother of the Universe,
which Westerners call Mount Everest,
gorges such as the Grand Canyon, and sea-
coasts such as Australia's Great Barrier
Reef. Some are remote and difficult of ac¬
cess, such as Tassili n'Ajjer in the Algerian
Sahara. The significance of some sites is not
widely appreciated. A knowledge of evolu
tionary theory is needed, for example, to
understand the importance of the rainbow
array of fish flapping in a fisherman's net on
the shores of Lake Malawi.
Many World Heritage sites possess a nat¬
ural grandeur that has drawn people to them
for worship through the ages. Ayers Rock
in Australia is sacred to the Aborigines, as
Machu Picchu in Peru was to the Incas. Not
only Confucius but most of China's em¬
perors and even the modern leaders of Chi¬
na have climbed Mount Taishan. Temples,
bridges and a 6,660-step staircase have been
built there, and inscribed stone stelae
erected.
The World Heritage natural sites de¬
scribed below fall into three groups. The
first group comprises habitats of the great
herds of large mammals which are among
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
«.
aBÈËf***
£;^^
1
rt
-a
c
U
¿c *pS?Mr
© ^
'.flWr' -
3
-Û
O
U
"o
_c
s
0
S
-C HH 1 1 V"~v
^Wood Buffalo National Park
(Canada)
Straddling the border between
Alberta and Northwest Territo¬
ries in northern Canada, Wood
Buffalo (44,800 km2) is one of
the world's biggest national parks. On its
vast northern plains are found such typical
animals of the region as wolf, lynx, Amer¬
ican hare, black bear, muskrat, beaver and
marten. But it is renowned above all for its
free-ranging herd of some 6,000 bison. The
Park was created in 1922 to protect the last
survivors of the North American bison
population and repopulated with bison in
the following years. Inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1983, it contains one of the
world's biggest inland deltas where the
great Athabasca and Peace rivers flow into
Lake Athabasca, attracting hundreds of
thousands of migrating birds. The winters
are long and hard; the summers short and
hot. The dry climate is a cause of the forest
fires which have helped to create the present
mosaic of plant life. The Park management
plan is designed to cope with the fire prob¬
lem and to regulate access, facilities for vis¬
itors, the protection of the bison and the
exploitation of resources by local people.
Nature's most spectacular phenomena. The
second group features wetlands, and the
third Biosphere Reserves, areas where a
whole new concept of management is being
practised with the aim of harmonizing the
needs of people and nature.
Homes of the large mammals
Serengeti National Park is in the United
Republic of Tanzania, which has set aside a
larger proportion of its land for various
forms of conservation than any other coun¬
try. The Park was declared a World Heri¬
tage site in 1981. Not far away, in the strata
of the Olduvai Gorge, lie the skulls and
handbones of our earliest ancestors, Homo
habilis and Homo erectus. Not all the mam¬
mals they knew have survived, but if we
ever hope to imagine what it was like to be
only one fragile mammal among many, it
must be on the African plains.
The Serengeti National Park covers
14,763 km2, an area with the greatest con¬
centration of plains animals left anywhere in
the world. During the rainy season wilde-
beeste and zebra feed on the short-grass
plains of the southern Serengeti. They
browse among purple and yellow wild
flowers in November, then, as the grass
dries, male wildebeeste begin to circle their
females, gathering harems together. At the
height of the rut in May the plains shimmer
with heat and yellow dust, as the bulls
frantically charge round and round their
collection of jostling, bleating mates.
Then, on some signal still unknown to us,
the whole mass of animals turns northward.
They gallop for days towards the better
watered bush country in the north. The grey
torrent of wildebeeste pours over the banks
of streams and swims across rivers. The
six-month-old calves run to keep up with
the other animals; many die on the way.
Whatever the strange urgency that drives
them, only death can keep them from their
goal.
Today discoveries are still being made
about the behaviour of the great mammals
that roam the world's wild places such as the
Serengeti. Perhaps the most startling is that
of elephant infrasound. Elephants, like
other mammals, have a complex social
structure. Matriarchal groups of females
roam apart from the bachelor bulls, al¬
though the two sexes sometimes join each
other as if by telepathy. Dr. Katherine
Payne of Cornell University (USA) has
found that elephants bellow to each other at
frequencies far below the range of human
hearing, with a volume that carries over
several kilometres.
Africa is not the only continent of vast
herds. When the first Europeans reached
North America, perhaps 50 to 60 million
bison roamed the plains. A portion of that
heritage is preserved in another World Heri¬
tage site, Wood Buffalo National Park, in
Canada, which at 44,800 km2 is one of the
world's largest national parks. Its 5,000 to
6,000 bison are the last remnant of North
America's great wild herds. They graze on
the salt-adapted grasses and wild flowers of
saline meadows, where the puddles are ring¬
ed with white rime, and wallow among the
grass and sedge of the huge inland delta of
the Peace and Athabasca Rivers. They roam
through woods of spruce and jackpine, as¬
pen, poplar, tamarack and birch. The bison
share the land with hundreds of thousands
Lake Malawi National Park
(Malawi)
Of all the African lakes which
are known for their great depth
and volume of water, Lake Ma¬
lawi is perhaps the most impor¬
tant biologically. It has more than 500 spe¬
cies of fish, of which 90 per cent are
endemic. One well-known group, the col¬
ourful Mbuna, consists of rock-dwelling
fish with highly localized home-ranges.
This and several other species occur in small
populations of a few hundred individuals.
The sedentary nature of most of the lake's
fish species, including the Mbuna, restricts
them to shoreline locations along specific
islands. The Lake Malawi National Park,
which covers about 94 km2, includes the
relatively large Cape Maclear Peninsula, 3
other smaller mainland areas and 12 islands
of varying size. The protection given to lake
waters within 100 m of all terrestrial parts
of the Park, though it protects only 7 km2 of
water area, preserves the habitat of the
endemic species of fish. Several Iron Age
sites are located in the Park, which was
established in 1980 and inscribed on the
World Heritage List in 1984, primarily in
recognition of its natural value. Although
the Park represents only 0.04 per cent of
Lake Malawi, it has contributed greatly to
the recognition of the lake as part of Mala¬
wi's natural heritage and to the improved
management of the resources of the lake as
a whole. Lake Malawi National Park was
inscribed on the World Heritage List in
1984.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
of migrating waterfowl, with nesting
whooping cranes, with bear, beavers, musk-
rat, and wolves. Especially wolves. The bi¬
son are regulated by their own natural pred¬
ators, not by the reluctant calculations of
game managers.
The original inhabitants of the Park are
the rare, shaggy, forest-adapted wood bi¬
son. Many of the herd, however, are plains
bison descended from a small group saved
from extinction in the last century by the
New York Zoological Society. Nowadays it
is true for Wood Buffalo Park, as for the
Serengeti, that "no significant component is
missing; no natural influence is excluded".
More and more of the great parks and
large mammals need the active care of hu¬
man beings. One such case is that of the
white rhinoceros of the Garamba National
Park, in northern Zaire, on the Sudanese
border. With a total area of some 4,480 km2,
the Park ranges from fairly dense woods in
the south to tree savannah in the north. It
has a unique population of the heavy,
square-lipped white rhino, whose territory
is cut off to the south by Zaire's great rain
forest. The Park was founded in 1938 specif¬
ically to help save the white rhino, of which
there were an estimated 1,000 in 1960. By
1980, when Garamba became a World Heri
tage site, after two decades of war and
poaching there were just twelve white rhi¬
nos left.
Rhino horn sells at a high price and at¬
tracts mounted bands 'of poachers armed
with high-powered rifles and automatic
weapons. The Park staff burn the grass as a
preventive measure early in the season, so
that the animals take cover in dense riverside
woodlands. Otherwise the poachers would
set fire to the high late-season grass, and kill
their prey as it flees before a wall of flame.
Now, with international support, the
staff of Garamba can begin to count their
successes. Every rhino wears a radio that
transmits its ranging patterns, and the Park
monitors the animals by plane. This year's
cohort of calves has raised the total pop¬
ulation to twenty-three.
It is not only in Africa that war destroys
animals as well as people. The last wild
European bison was killed in 1919. It lived
in Bialowieza forest, which straddles the
Soviet and Polish borders. Ironically, the
forest itself exists in part because during the
Middle Ages there were bloody disputes
between neighbouring princes, and the re¬
gion was almost entirely depopulated. In the
fifteenth century it became a royal hunting
preserve. Today, the central core of 47 km2
is almost the only true virgin forest in cen¬
tral Europe.
Once the forest sheltered auroch, the now
extinct ancestor of modern cattle, and tar-
pan, which survived there until the eight¬
eenth century. The bison herd numbered a
few hundred animals at the start of the First
World War. Soldiers and poachers wiped
them out. Then, in 1923, Professor Jan Szto-
loman of Poland proposed that efforts
should be made to reconstitute the herd.
British, German, Polish and Swedish scien¬
tists discovered fifty-four bison in the zoos
of Europe, though many were hybrids with
domestic stock. Careful back-crossing, a
pedigree book in which every bison calf is
named, and management through winter
feeding and summer surveillance have mul¬
tiplied the herd. Today, some 500 bison
wander the cathedral-columned glades of
Bialowieza National Park, which is now on
the World Heritage List. A further twenty
live in stalls, in strict isolation as a reserve
stock, in case of epidemic. And elsewhere in
Europe there are about 200 other breeding
centres for bison.
Wetland sites
If land is often a scarce resource, so is
water, and the world's wetlands are often
subjected to a tug-of-war between different
uses. This is illustrated by the five World
Heritage sites described in this section: two
lakes, one wild river, and two low-lying
swamps.
Lake Malawi, which is over 760 metres
deep, was created only some 5,000 years ago
in a fissure of the Great Rift Valley. Below
the plunging mountainside the valley is rich
and fertile. Around the edge of the lake are
small farms and villages. Fishermen paddle
their boats, ply the lake in craft powered
with new outboard motors, or haul ashore
U-shaped nets containing rainbow-hued
fish belonging to species that exist nowhere
else on Earth.
Perhaps two dozen species of African fish
entered Lake Malawi after the cataclysm of
its birth. Now, in an evolutionary instant,
their numbers have risen to between 500 and
1,000 species, virtually all of them endemic.
The explanation for this multitude of spe¬
cies seems to be that most fish have a great
love of home. The shore of Lake Malawi is
divided into rocky points and sandy bays.
Fish which live among the rocks rarely cross
the sand to the next set of rocks, and sand-
loving fish, though more mobile, still do not
travel far. The lake is thus divided into a set
of discrete habitats, each with its own, limit¬
ed gene pool. The fish of each point or bay
are different.
If Lake Malawi demonstrates what isola¬
tion can do to produce species, Lake Ich-
keul in Tunisia shows how one site can be a
crucial link in an international chain of hab¬
itats. It is a winter refuge for vast numbers
of migrating waterfowl. Almost the entire
population of Europe's greylag geese winter
there, as well as large fractions of the pop¬
ulations of pochard, widgeon and shoveler
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ducks. One census reported as many as
188,000 coots. In summer, when the mi¬
grants leave, some 600 of the rare and shy
white-headed duck remain to breed and
dabble among the reeds with their sky-blue
bills. Almost any European or North Afri¬
can bird can be seen here at some season.
Even Lake Ichkeul's water is not isolated.
It lies near to the Mediterranean, and while
runoff from rivers normally replenishes the
fresh water, in seasons and years when the
flow slackens off, saline water seeps in from
the sea. The reeds and aquatic life are adapt¬
ed to the changes, but now there is in¬
creasing human pressure to dam the rivers
and divert their water for irrigation. Studies
suggest how sluices might help to control
the freshwater flow and allow the coexis¬
tence of both lake and irrigation, and there
is hope that agreement will be reached.
Sometimes, however, wetland sites are
the focus of a direct confrontation. One
notable case, a proposal to dam the lower
Gordon River in Tasmania, Australia, and
its tributary, the Franklin, to produce elec¬
tric power for bauxite refining, ended with a
search for another site for that purpose.
Tasmania is rich in National Parks. The
7,693-km2 group of Western Tasmania
Wilderness National Parks contains one of
the world's last great temperate rain forests.
This is an area of quartzite peaks, limestone
caverns, and rivers whose rapids foam
through deep gorges. Loggers sought out
the region's Huon pines, some of which are
2,000 years old. Botanists, on the other
hand, treasure the forests of Nothofagus, the
southern deciduous beech, which is a relict
of the era when Tasmania, Australia and
Antarctica were all joined to South America
and Africa. This huge southern continent of
Gondwanaland was the home of the south¬
ern beech, which survives only in a few high
rainfall zones like the lower reaches of the
Gordon and Franklin rivers.
Djoudj National Bird Sanctuary, in the
delta of the Senegal River, illustrates how
tough decisions about the use of natural
wonders may be. A Sahelian country, beset
by drought in the interior, Senegal faces the
problem of apportioning land between no¬
mads and settled farmers, as well as meeting
its needs for irrigation and power. Large-
scale dams are being built on the Senegal
River, thus threatening the ecological bal¬
ance in the delta park of Djoudj, which has
three million visitors a year the palaearctic
birds which land after a gruelling 2,000-km
flight across the Sahara. Pelicans, herons and
ducks paddle beside typical desert mam¬
mals. The endangered Dorcas gazelle has
even been reintroduced here, since this is
one of the few Sahelian habitats where wild
grazers can hope to survive.
The Djoudj delta is subject to a desert
people's needs for water. The Sundarbans,
the wilderness of mangrove trees at the
mouth of the Ganges in India, is subject to
mountain peoples' needs for fuelwood, and
the needs of millions of plains peoples for
timber. Building wood is so expensive now
in India that it is sometimes cheaper to use
steel. In the Himalayas, the trade-offs be¬
tween natural forest for villagers' use, and
commercial pine for cash-cropping, have
provoked legal battles, riots, and social
movements like the Chipko, the women
who hug trees to stop them being felled.
The deltaic mangrove system of the Sun¬
darbans covers some 10,000 km2 of India
Sian Ka'an (Mexico)
The Sian Ka'an Biosphere Re¬
serve is located some 150 km
south of the tourist centre of
Cancun, on the ancient lime¬
stone plain of the Yucatán Peninsula. The
Reserve's 528,000 hectares include tropical
evergreen and semi-deciduous moist for¬
ests, marshes and mangroves, as well as a
large marine section with the second long¬
est barrier reef in the world. There is an
abundance of wildlife, including 1,200 plant
species, 5 species of cat (jaguar, puma, oce¬
lot, margay and jaguarundi), the Caribbean
manatee and Geoffroy 's spider monkey.
Sian Ka'an means "origin of the sky", the
name given to the region by the Maya
peoples who lived there in the 5th century
AD. Over 20 Maya archaeological sites have
been registered in the Reserve. Today some
800 people live there, some of them descend¬
ants of the Maya. Most live from lobster
fishing and have organized themselves into
co-operatives, which regulate the number
of fishermen and the size of the catch in
order to maintain this resource. Local peo¬
ple are also working with scientists on a
major ecological research programme. A
model farm has been established to develop
intensive cropping techniques, with the aim
of reducing the land area to be cleared for
agriculture. The site, which was inscribed
on the World Heritage List in 1987, is a
good example of the combined conserva¬
tion, research and development functions of
a Biosphere Reserve. Right, gathering of
pelicans and terns.
Sundarbans National Park
(India)
The Sundarbans, extending
over 10,000 km2 of land and wa¬
ter across India and Bangladesh,
is part of the world's largest del¬
ta, formed from sediments deposited by
three large rivers, the Ganges, the Brah¬
maputra and the Meghna. The core area in
west Bengal, India, was established in 1984
as the Sundarbans National Park, and in¬
scribed on the World Heritage List in 1987.
Situated in an area where cyclones and tidal
waves are relatively frequent and intensive,
the Sundarbans forms a barrier which pro¬
tects the interior regions from these natural
hazards. Some of the tidal waves whose
force is dispersed within the plains of the
delta can reach a height of 75 m. The low
mangroves, salt water forests, beach forests
and sand dune vegetation are the habitat of
a variety of fauna. Most importantly, they
are the home of the largest population of
the Bengal tiger (left), estimated at 264 in
1963, in India. Aquatic mammals such as
the Ganges dolphin, the Indo-Pacific
hump-backed dolphin, and the finless por¬
poise, also frequent the area. The setting for
the most intense human-wildlife conflicts in
India, the Sundarbans is a site that symbol¬
izes mankind's commitment to protect the
Bengal tiger.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
and Bangladesh. The Indian part is a World
Heritage site covering 2,600 km2 in a strictly
controlled nature reserve, the Sundarbans
National Park, which contains India's sin¬
gle largest population of tigers. When the
reserve was founded in 1973, there were 153
tigers; by 1980 there were 264, and the
numbers continue to grow.
The mangrove habitat is both sea and
land. Five species of dolphins and porpoise
and the rare saltwater crocodile live in the
Sundarbans. Tigers, which elsewhere hunt
wild antelope and the wild cattle called gaur,
are here known to catch fish, monitor liz¬
ards, and sea turtle. As India's Project Tiger
emphasizes, tigers are the index of the health
of their habitat. If people cut the mangroves
for wood, or drain islands for agriculture, or
even lose all control of the rivers' flood
regime, the tiger will be the first to go.
The world's wetlands face many threats,
from drainage to floods. Their resources
may be diverted to agriculture and power
generation. They may be polluted by runoff
of chemical toxins and fertilizers. No nat¬
ural site is now isolated from human influ¬
ence, so we must pioneer forms of manage-
. ment which try to reconcile diverse needs,
without waiting for confrontations to
develop.
Biosphere Reserves: living in
harmony with nature
The purpose of a Biosphere Reserve, as
envisaged in Unesco's Man and the Bio¬
sphere (MAB) Programme, is to reconcile
the needs of people and natural habitats.
This concept is today being used to conserve
World Heritage natural sites. Ideally, a Bio¬
sphere Reserve includes a core of minimally
modified natural habitat, outside which lie
one or several buffer zones, which people
use in such a way that the core continues to
exist. Biosphere Reserves form a worldwide
network which aims to conserve biological
diversity and to provide information which
will help people to live in harmony with
nature. The key to success is sustainable
buffer zone use, which provides both eco¬
nomic benefit and an environmental ethic
for local people.
Such use may, in fact, stem from local
traditions. The Sian Ka'an Biosphere Re¬
serve is located in Mexico's Yucatán Penin¬
sula. It protects more than 5,000 km2 of
tropical moist forests, marshes, mangroves,
and coral reef. Within the Reserve live about
800 people, descendants of the Maya Indi¬
ans who called the region Quintana Roo,
and left temple sites which date from the 5th
century BC. The modern Maya are mainly
lobster fishermen, but they practise age-old
farming methods, and gather traditional
plants for medicine, food and housing.
There is an entire research station dedicated
to understanding and improving the Re¬
serve, which also means learning from its
people.
Biosphere Reserves are intended to pre¬
serve typical samples of each of the planet's
ecosystems. Some are locally important, but
not spectacular enough to be included on
the World Heritage List. There are forty-
three Biosphere Reserves in the United
States alone, but only five of them are on the
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
World Heritage List: Yellowstone, and Ev¬
erglades, Redwood, Olympic and Great
Smoky Mountains National Parks. The
Great Smokies of North Carolina are tiers
of wooded Appalachian hills, which, seen
from a distance, are covered with a blue
haze which gives them their name. They
stood south of the great glaciers of the Ice
Age, and a number of plants which survive
there, such as ginseng, are closely related to
plants found in central China. Amphibians
also proliferate in the Great Smokies, in¬
cluding twenty-two kinds of salamander,
the largest of which is the hellbender, which
can be 75 centimetres long.
This wilderness of oak and mountain lau¬
rel, whitetailed deer and black bear, is far
from free of people. There is no question of
driving out the residents or of limiting tour¬
ist access, but building and clearing must be
carefully controlled in order to maintain the
tourist revenue that supports the region.
Above all, pollution from both automobiles
and distant industries can change the very
nature of the soil. It will be a sad com¬
mentary on our sense of values if we let acid
rain wipe out the forests which even the Ice
Age spared.
A variety of strategies are needed for the
development of conservation and manage¬
ment systems. Sometimes this means mas¬
sive investment projects in the nearby re¬
gion to offer the people an alternative way
of life. Sometimes, on the other hand, it
means reinforcing the support base of tradi¬
tional life.
Soon, it seems, we may need a much more
complicated system, the cluster Biosphere
Reserve. According to the cluster concept,
the management of a number of separate
areas is co-ordinated to perform the func¬
tions of a Biosphere Reserve, so that a
number of different ecological and socio¬
economic situations are englobed within
one biogeographical province. Such innova¬
tive macro-conservation offers some of the
flexibility needed in a rapidly changing
world.
Three more World Heritage sites St.
Kilda, Tassili n'Ajjer, and the La Amistad
park serve to illustrate the dangers and the
opportunities facing Biosphere Reserves.
St. Kilda is a place where the local culture
did not survive. It is a group of small islands
some 160 km west of Scotland. Its sea-cliffs,
which rise up to 430 metres above the
pounding Atlantic waves, are the highest in
Europe. St. Kilda is also a largely man-made
landscape. It was settled at least 2,000 years
ago, and Viking sagas record a voyage there
in AD 1202. The people led a hard life. They
ate fulmar and other seabirds, and dressed in
wool from their flocks of sheep. Until the
eighteenth century, traditional dwellings
were stone "black houses", where livestock
and manure were kept in an outer room.
Tourists, merchants and naturalists began
to visit the islands, and a school and medical
posts were built. Knowledge of how to
survive on fulmar and barley as well as any
desire to do so was forgotten. On 29 Au-,
gust 1930, the last remaining islanders left
for the Scottish mainland. Today there are
only a military base and a weather station,
vast colonies of seabirds, and the Soay sheep
which have reverted to the ranging patterns
of their wild ancestors.
The St. Kilda islanders adapted to chang¬
ing social conditions; the Tassili plateau of
Algeria bears witness to changes in climate
St. Kilda (United Kingdom)
This tiny archipelago lies in
splendid isolation in the Atlan¬
tic Ocean, some 160 km off the
west coast of Scotland. It orig¬
inates from an ancient volcano which has
been weathered and glaciated to produce a
bare, rocky group of islands with dramatic
cliffs which rise vertically to 430 m above
the waves and are the highest and most
spectacular in Europe. St. Kilda demon¬
strates how the ecological isolation of small
populations of animals can result in genetic
divergence: the tiny St. Kilda wood mouse
and the St. Kilda wren are different from
their mainland cousins and found nowhere
else. The seabird populations form one of
the largest concentrations in the North At¬
lantic, and include gannets (52,000 pairs),
fulmars (30,000 pairs) and puffins (300,000
pairs). Over 1 million seabirds may live on
St. Kilda at any one time. In spite of the
isolation and inclement living conditions,
St. Kilda was inhabited more or less contin¬
uously for 2,000 years: local people harvest¬
ed seabirds for their eggs and meat, and
spun the wool of the Soay sheep, an ancient
rustic breed which now lives in the wild. In
1930 the islanders finally left their home for
the mainland. Today St. Kilda, which was
inscribed on the World Heritage List in
1986, is protected as a National Nature
Reserve. The old village has also been re¬
stored for the few tourists who manage to
land in the summer months to admire the
stark landscape and wildlife of this remote
archipelago.
View of Great Smoky Moun¬
tains National Park, United
States
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
itself. Isolated in the sands of the Sahara,
Tassili n 'Ajjer is a rocky region some 100
km wide by 700 km long. Pinnacles of
banded rock sprout from the massif, a few
pools of "fossil water" offer relief, and,
strangely, a few springs of volcanically heat¬
ed water bubble out. Several hundred Tua¬
reg nomads, dubbed the "Blue Men" of the
Sahara because of their indigo dyed clothes,
drive their herds between the oases.
In this desert museum, rock paintings
dating from 8,000 years ago, when the cli¬
mate was far moister, show giraffe, buffalo,
elephant, hippopotamus, rhinoceros.
Around 6,000 years ago, these depictions of
savannah wildlife give way to representa¬
tions of piebald white and red-ochre cattle,
which must have been domestic herds. Por¬
trayals of horses on the rock walls date from
about 3,000 years ago, and depictions of the
first camel caravans were made around AD
200. Today, the only survivors of this
kinder age are a few Cyprus trees in the
canyons, their trunks 5 metres in diameter,
and strange relict fish. There were croco¬
diles, too, but the last was killed in the
1940s.
As both our societies and our climate
seem bound to change increasingly rapidly
in the coming decades, we can look back for
instruction to St. Kilda and Tassili n'Ajjer.
We can also look ahead, at one of the
world's great bridges from North to South.
Talamanca Range-La Amistad Bio¬
sphere Reserve (Costa Rica) connects two
countries, two oceans and two continents.
Its name comes from a friendship ("Amis-
tad") zone declared between Costa Rica and
Panama, and it includes some 8,000 km2 of
land set aside for conservation. The Bio
sphere Reserve stretches from the Atlantic
to the Pacific, here little more than 150 km
apart. It includes one of the most diverse
biotas on Earth, because it was here that the
plants and animals of North America came
into contact with those from the south,
when upthrusting volcanoes connected the
two great continents. The area is still thrust¬
ing upward: earthquakes and vulcanism
have lifted the highest peaks above 3,500
metres. There is dry woodland on the Pacif¬
ic coast and true jungle on the Atlantic side,
a haunt of jaguar which can only be pene¬
trated machete in hand. On the heights there
is magnificent pine cloud forest where the
quetzal flies, and, ultimately, alpine rock
gardens where furry lycopodium club-
mosses huddle against the cold. La Amis-
tad's inner valleys are almost untrodden by
man: besides the rich variety of known
species, there are certainly many more crea¬
tures to be discovered.
La Amistad covers 10 per cent of Costa
Rica, and is home to more than 40 per cent
of Costa Rica's Indians. People of the Bri-
bri, Cabecar, Brunca and Guaymi tribes live
within the Reserve. The Indians are well
aware of Western lifestyles, wear Western
clothes, and would like their school build¬
ings to be made of brick, even if the bricks
have to be flown in by helicopter.
The World Heritage Convention is one
way of linking the interests of people within
each region to the interests of the world
community. No one ever said it would be
easy. But it is clearly essential, if we wish to
preserve the world's wild places, not just as
relicts of the past, but as bridges to the
future.
ALISON JOLLY, of the United States, is a
zoologist who has been Visiting Lecturer at Prin¬
ceton University since 1987. She is the author of
several books including Lemur Behaviour. A Ma¬
dagascar Field Study, Chicago University Press,
1966; A World Like Our Own: Man and Nature
in Madagascar, Yale University Press, 1980; and
The Evolution of Primate Behaviour, Macmillan,
New York, 2nd ed. 1985. 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The conservation
of ancient cities
BY MOUNIR BOUCHENAKI
12
AMONG the many opportunities
available throughout the world to
the traveller or tourist of today, one
of the most exciting is the possibility of
visiting the remains of ancient cities and of
lifting a corner of the veil that shrouds the
civilizations of the past in mystery. Yet we
are light years away from the era of roman¬
tic reverie among ancient ruins, from the
time when the German poet Schiller could
declaim:
Are we to find again that which was lost?
Come Greeks and Romans, come!
Lo, ancient Pompeii is restored,
The city of Hercules is built anew!
Since the end of the nineteenth century,
and above all during the twentieth, the de¬
velopment of the historical sciences and
archaeological research, aided and abetted
on occasions by chance, has led to decisive
progress in our knowledge of ancient sites.
Some sites, like those of Troy, in Asia Mi¬
nor, and Nineveh, in Mesopotamia, had, to
be sure, been brought to light at a time when
enthusiasm for vanished civilizations, far
from being widespread, was limited pri¬
marily to curiosity-seekers and a handful of
scholars.
In the contemporary world, however,
there is clear evidence of an upsurge of
interest in ancient ruins, in their safeguard
and protection. How else can we explain the
vast movement of international solidarity
that sprang up during the 1960s and was
behind the rescue of the famous temples of
Philae and Abu Simbel in Upper Egypt
from the waters of the Nile?
This feeling of solidarity enabled Unesco
to develop the concept of a common human
heritage and to establish a World Heritage
List on which a number of major archae¬
ological sites are inscribed. Sites such as
Aksum (Ethiopia), Chan Chan (Peru),
Hampi (India), Sigiriya (Sri Lanka), Teoti-
huacán (Mexico) and Timgad (Algeria) are
so prestigious that it hardly seems necessary
to explain why they have been inscribed on
the World Heritage List, or why the coun¬
tries in which they are situated have decided
to safeguard them. The one thing they have
in common is that they are archaeological
sites, that is to say that, apart from their
attendants, they are entirely uninhabited
and the only sound now heard in their
streets is the echo of visitors' footsteps.
They could be dubbed "dead cities", since at
some point in the history of each one of-
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Teotihuacán (Mexico)
irff^r
The pre-Columbian holy city of
Teotihuacán is located in the
mountains 50 km north-east of
Mexico City. Founded between
the 1st and the 3rd century AD, the city
extended over 36 km2 at the height of its
development, and supported a population
of 200,000. The imposing ceremonial centre
marks a high point in the art of Mexican
classical civilizations, with its main build¬
ing, the Pyramid of the Sun (left), rising
over 75 m from a 350 m2 terrace; the Pyra¬
mid of the Moon, 42 m in height; and the
Temple of Quetzalcóatl, the plumed serpent
of the Aztecs. The city's 4,000 buildings of
volcanic rock, stuccoed with mud or lime
plaster, and its finely-sculpted palaces, were
laid out in a rectangular grid pattern based
on principles of cosmic harmony. A wide
avenue bisected the city and linked markets,
monuments and plazas. The main industry
was the production of obsidian, from which
cutting tools were made for barter. In the
6th century, Teotihuacán controlled a pow¬
erful State with extensive territory, but
around the year 650, for reasons still ob¬
scure, the city was burned down and sub¬
sequently abandoned. When, in the 14th
century, the Aztecs discovered the ruined
metropolis with its enormous pyramids,
they thought that it must have been con¬
structed by the gods, and accordingly gave
it the name Teotihuacán "Place of the
Gods". The site was inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1987.
Aksum (Ethiopia)
Situated in the Tigre region of
northern Ethiopia, the city of
Aksum was the capital of a fa¬
mous kingdom of Antiquity to
ffih
which it gave its name and which is de¬
scribed in a 3rd-century-AD Greek text as
the "third kingdom of the world". The Ro¬
mans also knew of Aksum at that time. The
city lay on a trade route along which passed
such precious commodities as rhinoceros
horn, ivory, tortoiseshell and obsidian.
Many traces have survived of the past
splendour of Aksum, covering a vast area.
They include gigantic stelae, the highest of
which (right) stands 33 m high and is the
largest known obelisk ever carved and
erected, stone columns engraved with Ethi¬
opian legends, and royal tombs. Legend has
it that beneath one tumulus is the tomb of
the Queen of Sheba. In the western part of
the site are the ruins of 3 ancient castles
built sometime during the first millennium
of the Christian era, and an 18th-century
basilica that provides valuable testimony
about Ethiopian architecture of that time.
As part of the international campaign for
the preservation and presentation of the
cultural heritage of Ethiopia, restoration
work will soon be carried out at Aksum,
which was inscribed on the World Heritage
List in 1980.
them, for reasons that are in some cases not
clear, all activity ceased despite the fact that
their ruins bear eloquent witness to the
ingenuity and vitality of the people who
dwelt there. These cities, once important ,
centres of civilization, are now the domain
of archaeologists and curators who super¬
vise their preservation and their presenta¬
tion to the public.
A rapid survey of these ancient cities
reveals first of all the existence of great
urban civilizations each of which is typical
of the part of the world in which it is
located. Thus, the ancient colony of Tim-
gad, in Algeria, is a city whose structure
reflects the values of Roman civilization into
which has been incorporated the dynamic
force of the indigenous people.
This site, whose symmetrical layout is
still quoted as an example in architectural
and town-planning manuals, is a product of
a comprehensive theory of town-planning
moulded by Oriental and Hellenistic influ¬
ences. This theory precisely encapsulated
the idea that the Ancients had of what a city
should be. As the Greek geographer Pausa-
nias wrote in the second century AD: "How
could I grace with the name 'city' a place
which has no theatre, no agora, no assembly
rooms and no gymnasium?"
The plan and layout of the settlements at
Aksum, Chan Chan, Hampi, Sigiriya and
Teotihuacán have been preserved like
those at Timgad although they belong to
different culture areas and different histor¬
ical periods, and are located in different
parts of the world. They represent a valu¬
able asset for modern man, since contempo¬
rary societies appear to have become aware
of the values attached to archaeological re¬
mains, whose disappearance would be an
irreparable loss for all humanity.
àafeiâa*à*tf3* 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
At a given moment in the human story,
each of these ancient cities was the setting
for a specific way of life which bears witness
to the activities, resources, beliefs and orga¬
nization of mankind, in a word, to culture.
It is the duty of the international communi¬
ty to preserve and not to disfigure these
sites.
Although documentary sources for an¬
cient times are generally speaking rare, the
presence of substantial remains buried in the
.soil or visible in the landscape, such as the
giant stelae of Aksum or the temples of
Chan Chan as well as the ruins of the other
cities mentioned, makes it possible to com¬
pile data which deepen our understanding of
how people lived, worked and worshipped
in the past. This stock of knowledge must be
safeguarded, a task which is not always easy.
A country in which there are sites that
usually cover hundreds of hectares, or even,
as at Hampi and Teotihuacán, tens of square
kilometres, is faced with a number of prob¬
lems such as their maintenance and super¬
vision. The inscription of such sites on the
World Heritage List reduces the scale of the
dangers that they face, but it does not elim¬
inate them entirely.
Those responsible for the heritage are
fully aware that the conservation of sites is
often regarded as an activity quite distinct
from the realities of modern life, particular¬
ly by regional planning authorities. As a
result these great archaeological complexes
Timgad (Algeria)
Timgad is the modern name of
the Roman city of Thaugadi,
which was founded by the em¬
peror Trajan in AD 100 as a
defensive military camp north of the Aurès
mountains. Thaugadi grew rapidly. After
the Vandal invasion in the 5th century, it
was destroyed by the mountain people of
the Aurès, then enjoyed a period of revival
in the 6th century under Byzantine occupa¬
tion before being abandoned. Archaeolog¬
ical excavations carried out since 1880 have
revealed the ruins of a city laid out accord¬
ing to the finest and most rigorous princi¬
ples of Roman urban planning and contain¬
ing such characteristic Roman public
buildings as a forum, capitolium (temple of
Jupiter, Juno and Minerva), theatre, baths,
temples, markets and a public library. The
remains of churches show that Christianity
was introduced to Timgad in the 3rd centu¬
ry. The conservation and presentation of
the site raise a number of problems. The
original extent of the settlement must be
precisely determined, taking into account
those parts which have not been fully exca¬
vated. It has been decided to remove the
best mosaic floors from the houses to the
site museum in order to preserve them from
extremes of temperature. An annual music
and drama festival has been established at
Timgad by the local authorities, but certain
events which caused damage to the ancient
theatre have been halted. Timgad was in¬
scribed on the World Heritage List in 1982.
Below, general view showing the triumphal
arch; left, a votive stela.
£**
£<V.u¿4*¿it-¡Z
*géü£3fe^
3jri^
>
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Petra (Jordan)
Half-carved, half-built in spec-
Br tacular pink sandstone cliffs
1 util south of the Dead Sea, this an-
ÜHiBl c¡cnt Arabian city was the cap¬
ital of the kingdom of the Nabataeans (4th
century BC-2nd century AD). Situated at
the meeting point of 2 caravan routes, it
became an important centre for trade in
Arabian incense, Indian spices, Chinese silk,
Egyptian gold, and Nubian ivory and
slaves. Between the 1st century BC and the
1st century AD, Petra reached the height of
prosperity and built its first monuments. It
became part of the Roman empire in AD
106, and enjoyed a further period of great¬
ness until the development of alternative
trade routes dealt a death-blow to its econo¬
my. Later, Christians inhabited the city and
crusaders built fortifications which can still
be seen today. Access to Petra is through a
narrow 2-km-long ravine. Temples, tombs
and palaces hewn from the sandstone form
a magnificent setting in which Oriental tra¬
ditions blend with the Graeco-Roman style.
Today adverse atmospheric conditions and
erosion are damaging the ruins. Specialists
have studied the reasons for the deteriora¬
tion of the stone, and a complete photo-
grammetric survey of the site has been car¬
ried out. The World Heritage Committee
has recently provided the Jordanian au¬
thorities with financial aid for the preserva¬
tion of Petra and the restoration of the
Palatial Tomb. Petra was inscribed on the
World Heritage List in 1985. Above, ed-
Deir ("the convent"), a rock-hewn monu¬
ment outside the city which may have been
a royal tomb (2nd-3rd centuries).
are exposed to the risk of destruction. The
development of infrastructures, the building
of tourist accommodation and the use of
monumental sites for the staging of public
spectacles without ensuring that the neces¬
sary precautions are taken, are all dangers
that it is difficult for a national conservation
official to fight against. Added to this is the
constant threat of theft by clandestine
treasure-hunters and unscrupulous pseudo-
researchers, especially in sites that extend
over a large area and are therefore difficult
to supervise.
The inclusion of a site on the World
Heritage List can sometimes carry weight
with decision-makers, since the need to re¬
spect the criteria that classification entails is
backed up by the moral force of the in¬
ternational community. However, there are
many examples throughout the world of
conservation officials and those responsible
for development (such as town-planners,
architects, and tourist authorities) working
closely together to preserve the archaeolog¬
ical heritage and to find solutions to the
complex problems created by the need to
protect ancient remains. The archaeological
site of Carthage is a case in point for, despite
the huge sums of money at stake in the
property market, it has been possible to
create an archaeological park and a building-
free zone and thus to safeguard structures
vital to the understanding of the devel¬
opment of ancient cities.
Another problem may arise within the
very services responsible for safeguarding
the heritage, when, with the legitimate ob¬
jective of advancing knowledge, they are
obliged to undertake a dig in an unexplored
section of an archaeological site. Remains
are obviously better protected if they are left
underground, but where a site has been
largely uncovered the stratigraphie sampling
method, essential for example for the confir¬
mation of a dating, will have the least harm¬
ful effect on conservation.
Another subject of debate among special¬
ists is how far it is permissible to go in
restoring or reconstructing ruined struc¬
tures in order to present them to the public.
The problems that arise with regard to sites
of such exceptional quality that they have
earned inclusion on the World Heritage List
are leading to a reappraisal of attitudes and
to new approaches. Ultimately, the best way
to implement a policy of safeguarding ar¬
chaeological sites is to ensure that people
know about them and visit them, and more
use should be made of the media for this
purpose, particularly as far as young people
are concerned.
We could well apply to archaeological
sites the remark André Malraux once made
about the past in general: "We do not really
know why we are attached to our past, yet
we know very well that we are and that
today all nations are attached to theirs.""
MOUNIR BOUCHENAKI ¿5 a staffmember of
Unesco's Cultural Heritage Division. A historian
and archaeologist who was formerly chief curator
in the Algerian Antiquities Service, he has worked
on a number of archaeological sites in the Medi¬
terranean basin. He is the author of Cités An¬
tiques d'Algérie (Algiers, 1978), Fouilles de la
nécropole occidentale de Tipasa (Algiers, 1976)
and other studies and articles on archaeological
themes. 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Time regained
A historical perspective
on cultural sites and monuments
BY GEORGE MICHELL
16
WHILE the cultural sites of the
World Heritage List may be doc¬
umented, analysed, catalogued
and subjected to the hopefully beneficial
processes of restoration, they must never be
divorced from the destiny of man. These
sites are permanent records of human en¬
deavour, the material artefacts of world his¬
tory. Here are displayed the deeds of man¬
kind, from the noble and the spiritual to the
heroic and the tragic. The cultural sites are
visible demonstrations of the survival of the
past into the present era. The World Heri¬
tage Convention is a valid attempt to recog¬
nize the unique qualities of this heritage and
safeguard its survival into the future.
Many of the great monuments and cities
of the past, whether ruined or still in use
today, are inextricably bound up with the
careers of powerful individuals. Only empe¬
rors and princes, military commanders and
generals, and popes and bishops could com¬
mand the considerable economic and artistic
resources that were essential for the erection
of large-scale monuments, let alone the lay¬
ing out of the public spaces and ensembles
of buildings required for a city centre.
Though many of the cultural sites on the
World Heritage List have obviously been
identified for the aesthetic quality of their
architectural or urban character, their his¬
torical dimensions must never be forgotten.
The royal individuals who built splendid
residences for themselves were sometimes
visionaries. Their architectural legacy is of¬
ten imposing and inspiring; sometimes it is
intended to intimidate. Architecture here is
truly in the service of mundane purposes.
This is true of many of the palaces identified
in the World Heritage List, from those of
the Ming emperors in China, and the
Mughals at Fatehpur Sikri in India, to the
châteaux of the French kings at Chambord,
Fontainebleau and Versailles, or the great
houses of the English lords as at Blenheim.
No less concerned with the expression of
power are the ceremonial centres at Perse-
polis in the Islamic Republic of Iran, Teoti¬
huacán in Mexico and Hampi in India, or
the Great Wall of China and the fortifica¬
tions of King Edward I at Gwynedd in
Wales.
Governing nations in almost all periods of
world history were concerned to develop an
architecture based on power. Their military,
administrative, judicial and ceremonial con¬
structions are reminders of past ambitions,
sometimes in eras of enlightenment, at other
times in eras of oppression, but almost al¬
ways in periods of intended glory. The
ensembles of buildings that form the cores
of such historic cities as Istanbul in Turkey,
Aleppo in the Syrian Arab Republic and Fez
in Morocco, for example, are testaments to
continuous state patronage of urban archi¬
tecture over many centuries. The same is
true for the European cities of Toledo, Flo¬
rence, Budapest or Cracow, in addition to
CONTINUEDON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
-.*- ^.--^
H The destiny of Potosí, a small
hamlet perched at an altitude of
4,000 m in the Andes, was trans¬
formed when its silver lodes, the
richest in the New World, began to be
intensively mined in the 1540s. By the 17th
century, the new town had a population of
160,000 colonists and 13,500 Indians who
worked in the mines under the mita system
of forced labour. Mining activity, which
only slowed down after Bolivia became in¬
dependent in 1825, has left spectacular
traces in the city and its surrounding re¬
gion, including the dams that controlled the
water supply to the ore-grinding mills, and
the royal mine complex, the biggest and
best conserved of some 5,000 mines that
pitted the high plateau and its valleys. In
the colonial city are monuments in the ba¬
roque style mingled with Indian influences
which spread through the central Andes.
They include more than 20 churches, gra¬
cious patrician houses whose luxury con¬
trasted with the bare simplicity of the ran¬
cherías in the indigenous district, and the
royal mint whose stamp marked the thou¬
sands of tons of silver which made Potosí a
pivot of the European economy in the 17th
and 18th centuries. In the last ten years,
Unesco and the United Nations Develop¬
ment Programme (UNDP) have been help¬
ing the Bolivian authorities to protect Poto¬
sí. An inventory of the historic monuments
has been made and historical studies have
been undertaken. Work will continue in the
next few years as part of a UNDP/Unesco
project. Potosí was inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1987.
Historic Quebec (Canada)
The capital of New France was
3J5p founded in 1608 by Samuel de
jjjfl'Yi Champlain on a plateau over-
looking the St. Lawrence river,
a headland later known as Cape Diamond.
In 1759, the city, which was strategically
important for transatlantic trade, fell under
British domination which soon extended
throughout Canada. The population of
Quebec grew rapidly because of its busy
port, and two towns developed, each with
different functions. The older Lower Town
is the business and merchant shipping dis¬
trict. It includes houses dating from the
17th and 18th centuries and the church of
Notre-Dame des Victoires. The Upper
Town became the centre of administrative
and religious life. Parts of the original struc¬
tures of the convents of the Ursulines, the
Jesuits and the Recollets, which were built
there in the 17th century, have survived.
Quebec is thus an exceptional example of a
North American fortified colonial city and
an important landmark in a crucial period
in the history of the continent. The historic
area of Quebec was inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1985. The Quebec author¬
ities are committed to the safeguard and
presentation of all the elements which qual¬
ify Old Quebec as a World Heritage site.
But since the historic area forms part of the
city centre, it is subject to an urban dynam¬
ic which must be reconciled with the preser¬
vation of its authenticity. The Château
Frontenac, left, dominates the city. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Colour page opposite
J | . | 'j~xk.
Hampi (India)
Founded at the beginning of the
14th century, the city of Vijaya-
nagar, near the present village
of Hampi on the Deccan plat-
Mr
eau, was the capital of a vast Hindu em¬
pire which dominated southern India and
kept Muslim armies from the north at bay
for more than 2 centuries. The rulers ring¬
ed the city, which natural defences made
almost invulnerable, with 7 fortified en¬
closures which also surrounded farmland.
The king and his immense retinue lived in
a complex of buildings in the heart of the
city. The growing power of the Vijayana-
gar empire attracted the attention of the
Muslim rulers to the north, who sacked
the city in 1565. Inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1986, Hampi poses con¬
servation problems on account of its sheer
size and the number of its monuments
(500). Sugar-cane or rice now grow above
some of the old city streets. The integrity
of other parts of the site is threatened by
building development. Since Hampi is a
popular centre of pilgrimage, facilities for
visitors must be built to safeguard the site
from wear and tear. Photo shows detail of
the gopura (entrance gateway) to the tem¬
ple of Qampapathi.
View of Djoudj National
Bird Sanctuary, Senegal (see
article page 5)
Centre pages
IRt
The Old City of Sana'a
(Yemen Arab Republic)
Situated on a plain ringed by
mountains, Sana'a (page 20)
was a stronghold of the Yemeni
kingdom of Saba' as early as the
5th century BC and an important cross¬
roads for caravan routes. In the 4th cen¬
tury AD brick walls were added to its
natural defences and a remarkable urban
settlement began to be organized. Con¬
quered in the 6th century by the Persians,
Sana'a embraced Islam, and began to fill
with houses, mosques, gardens and public
baths. All the buildings in this urban mas¬
terpiece are of beaten earth or brick and
are decorated with whitewashed motifs.
The conservation of the historic city raises
complex questions owing to the difficul¬
ties of adapting ancient structures and to
the lack of certain public amenities. The
water supply is inadequate, and seepage
from defective conduits, combined with
the poor quality of the sewerage system,
have caused the foundations of the build¬
ings to deteriorate. The dust raised by
congested motor traffic on irregularly
maintained roads is also causing damage.
In 1984, in order to help the Yemenites
preserve the old city of Sana'a, Unesco
launched an international campaign
whose aims include improving the sani¬
tary infrastructure, strengthening the
foundations of the houses, resurfacing the
streets, restoring the historic monuments,
and renovating the süqs. Efforts are also
being made to develop tourism in Sana'a,
which was inscribed on the World Heri¬
tage List in 1986.
Talamanca Range-La
Amistad (Costa Rica)
This 500,000-hectare Biosphere
Reserve (page 21) is a sanctuary
for the wildlife of central Amer¬
ica. Its plant and animal life is
exceptionally rich and diverse owing to
the area's marked differences in climate,
soils and altitude (ranging from near sea
level to 3,819 m) and to its position as a
"land bridge" connecting biogeographi-
cally distinct regions of North and South
America. No less than 8 distinct life zones
have been identified in the area. The in¬
ventory of its natural resources is not
complete, but investigations have shown
that 13 species of mammals, 15 of birds
and 10 of reptiles and amphibians are
found only within the Reserve, which was
inscribed on the World Heritage List in
1983. Since access is difficult and the steep
slopes and mountains are unsuitable for
agriculture, there has been relatively little
human settlement. Nevertheless, archae¬
ological evidence indicates the presence of
sedentary cultures dating from 500 BC.
Today some 10,000 Indians live in the
area, most of whom maintain a traditional
lifestyle. The Talamanca Range-La Amis-
tad Biosphere Reserve is thus serving to
protect the cultural heritage of central
America as well as providing invaluable
knowledge about the region's natural re¬
sources.
18
Phoro Juan A. Fernandez © Incafo, Madrid
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
..-
i -
,^*r*^
~- " . ?
í<g& ^
if
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ÍJ
"H ll.^J .
rSfi mrny»
^B^B^m^^^HT
1
1 }'
I -.
M^wstf
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
- »&. ! ->:
lSJM
' i$*n
:
»«mi '
v.-
.
''>* . .
k«»' JJS«
-TV.**;
* i¿
m
d£j -
ám
^
t»/' - >
3lf*»f .
:;
I .- ; .
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
// :
«£'*»Í33H* "Ä*
«4
-
¿3fc
'
* rf*
' ** S Mi .
VS
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Colour page opposite
1 l -.
k
Photo A. Larramcndi © Incafo, Madrid
Uluru (Ayers Rock-
Mount Olga) National Park
(Australia)
Located in central Austra¬
lia, some 300 km southwest
of Alice Springs, this vast
sandy plain is dominated by
2 exceptional geological formations. Ayers
Rock is a huge, rounded, red sandstone
monolith, 9.4 km in circumference, the
smooth slopes of which rise 340 m above
the plain. Caves around the base of the
rock, a sacred place to Australian Aborig¬
ines, are decorated with rock paintings
some of which are 10,000 years old. The 36
steep-sided rock domes of the Olgas cover
3,500 hectares and rise to 546 m above the
desert. Uluru National Park is the habitat
of rare or endangered plant and animal
species. In addition to the coarse spinifex
grass, there are over 20 species of native
mammals, including several rare marsu¬
pials, which suffer from competition from
introduced mammals including the red
fox, cat, house mouse, European rabbit,
wild dog and camel. Perhaps 80 aboriginal
groups live in the Park, subsisting by
hunting, gathering and controlled burn¬
ing. Apart from the protection of the
natural and cultural heritage, the man¬
agement plan for the Park is concerned to
preserve the culture of the Aborigines by
reconciling the demands of their tradi¬
tional way of life and the conditions of an
increasingly popular tourist site. Uluru
National Park was inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1987.
Photo Michel Escobar-Véronique Hemery © Incafo, Madrid
Delphi (Greece)
SBt
In a spectacular rocky amphi¬
theatre on the southwestern
slopes of Mount Parnassus, less
than 10 km from the Gulf of
Corinth, stand the ruins of the temple and
oracle of Apollo, the most prestigious reli¬
gious sanctuary of ancient Greece. At Del¬
phi Apollo was worshipped and his coun¬
sel uttered through the medium of a
priestess, the Pythia. The extent of the
ruins shows the religious and political im¬
portance of Delphi which at its zenith in
the 6th century BC was the religious cen¬
tre of the Greek world. The influence of
the Delphic oracle lasted until the rise of
Christianity. The Sacred Way, lined with
treasuriessmall temples built by illustri¬
ous cities to house their offeringswinds
up to the temple of Apollo (4th century
BC). Above the temple are a theatre, a
stadium and, near the Castalian spring, a
gymnasium, all built for the Panhellenic
Pythian Games. Beyond the spring is the
sanctuary of Athena Pronaia, whose most
famous building is the tholos (left), a mar¬
ble rotunda dating from the early 4th
century BC. A town stood on a plateau
above the sanctuary. The site is endan¬
gered because it is at the heart of a seismic
zone and has already been shaken by
earthquakes, most recently in 1981. Some
damage has been caused by climatic condi¬
tions, such as rockfalls following frost,
rainwater runoff and infiltration. So
many tourists visit Delphi that the site
authorities have planned an obligatory
itinerary around the temples to prevent
wear -and- tear of the stone paving. Be¬
fore inscribing the archaeological site of
Delphi on the World Heritage List in
1987, the World Heritage Committee in¬
sisted that a plan to establish an alumini¬
um processing plant nearby should be
abandoned. The Greek authorities have
complied by arranging for the plant to be
built 55 km from Delphi.
A 10-volume series
and a guidebook
on the world heritage
With technical assistance from Unesco, the
Spanish publishing house Incafo (Castelló,
59 Madrid), is bringing out a monumental
work in 10 large-format volumes which
present to an international public all the
cultural and natural properties inscribed on
the World Heritage List. The books, 8 of
which have already been published in Span¬
ish (entitled El Patrimonio del Mundo) un¬
der the imprint of Plaza & Janes, Barcelona,
are fully illustrated with colour photos com¬
plemented by texts providing historical, art¬
istic and technical information about each
property. Incafo and Unesco have also com¬
piled and co-published a single-volume
guide to the world heritage, Guía del Patri¬
monio Mundial (over 500 pages extensively
illustrated with colour photos).
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 1 6
Venice with its splendid lagoons which have
miraculously isolated the city from the
threats of motorized traffic.
Some rulers were of foreign origin and the
architecture that they sponsored made in¬
tentional reference to other places and peri¬
ods. The World Heritage List includes sites
of colonial splendour such as the cities of
Oaxaca in Mexico, Cuzco in Peru, Salvador
de Bahia in Brazil, and even Quebec, all of
which are distinctively European in style.
Other urban examples have until recent
years been overlooked by modern devel¬
opment; their buildings are sometimes de¬
scribed as traditional, meaning that they are
identified with an unchanging social and
cultural environment, even if this is more
imagined than historically true. Thus the old
walled cities of Shibam in Democratic Ye¬
men, Esfahan in the Islamic Republic of
Iran, or Cairo in Egypt are not merely
repositories of domestic and civic monu¬
ments of undeniable qualities, they are also
testaments to a past way of life that is fast
disappearing. Such buildings cannot be di¬
vorced from the lives of their inhabitants,
even if these lives have inevitably become
transformed in the late twentieth century.
Some monuments may be appreciated
from the point of view of their symbolic
historical value. The Statue of Liberty was
an emblem of hope for millions of migrants
to the United States. Other monuments
such as Auschwitz Concentration Camp in
Poland serve as reminders of man's capacity
^mi to destroy himself. Yet, most cultural sites
24 cannot represent the extreme range of hu
man history; they belong to a changing
environment in which a diversity of human
needs and ideologies continue to evolve.
There arc cultural sites which continue to
affirm their relationship with the past; today
they are the abandoned, dilapidated and
perhaps recently restored relics of history or
even prc-history. The traces of the cities of
Memphis in Egypt, Delphi in Greece, Hatra
in Iraq, and Chan Chan in Peru are dramatic
artefacts of vanished civilizations. The time
co-ordinates of these sites, so to speak, have
been extended into the present era only by
the modern activities of archaeological re¬
search and that increasing industry of hu¬
man movement known as tourism. Other
edifices of the past have been subjected to
historical processes which have permitted
them to survive into the present as still
living architectural or urban environments.
Such buildings or cities have been reused
over many centuries; for this reason they
have survived, even if in altered form.
With its superimposition of Roman, Byz¬
antine, Baroque and contemporary struc¬
tures, the centre of Rome provides a graphic
cross-section of the fortunes of an empire
and a capital over more than 2,000 years.
Like other cities such as Anuradhapura in
Sri Lanka, Jerusalem, or Santiago de Com-
postela in Spain, Rome was also a place of
pilgrimage. Its religious monuments housed
the worshippers of different cults which,
like the built environment of the city, con¬
tinued to evolve through time. Other urban
centres which form part of the World Heri¬
tage List will develop their historical per-
C0NTINUED0NPAGE26
The Old Town of Avila
(Spain)
lb
Known to Castilians as "the city
of saints and stone", Avila was
founded by Celtic tribes and
later became a Roman outpost
that was captured by the Visigoths. It was
converted to Christianity in the 1st century
by St. Segundo, who became its first bishop,
and was Muslim from the 8th to the 11th
centuries. In 1090, after the expulsion of the
Muslims from Castile, mighty stone ram¬
parts began to be built around the city. This
2.5-km-long wall, with its over 80 semi¬
circular forts and 9 imposing gates, still
exists (see photo). Avila has many religious
monuments, notably a Gothic cathedral
(late 12th-13th centuries) whose crenella-
tions surmounting the Romanesque choir
are another reminder that the town was a
defensive bastion. Among the other reli¬
gious buildings are the late 12th-century
Romanesque church of St. Vicente, rich in
sculptures, and the convent of St. Tomás
(late 15th century), which contains the
tombs of Tomás de Torquemada, the grand
inquisitor, and of Don Juan, the only son of
the Catholic rulers Ferdinand and Isabella.
The convent of the Incarnation was built on
the site of the house of the Spanish nun and
mystic St. Teresa of Avila (1515-1582). A
native of Avila, St. Teresa reformed the
Carmelite order and wrote some of the
world's greatest spiritual classics. The old
town of Avila, with its extra-muros
churches, was inscribed on the World Heri¬
tage List in 1985.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Historic Centre of
Cracow (Poland)
Bb
The old city of Cracow stands
on Wawel hill, overlooking the
Vistula river. Located on a trade
route between western Europe
and Asia, Cracow was from the 14th to the
16th centuries the prosperous capital of the
kingdom of Poland. Many historic monu¬
ments testify to its rich past and its cultural
and commercial stature. The royal castle,
originally Gothic, was transformed in the
16th century into a sumptuous Renaissance
residence in the Italian style. In the market¬
place, the largest medieval square in Eu¬
rope, stands the imposing Drapers' Hall
(14th-16th centuries). The Gothic cathedral
(right) contains the tombs of the kings of
Poland, and the church of the Virgin Mary
has a masterpiece of sculpture, the great
polychrome wood altarpiece created by Veit
Stoss in 1477. The Jagiellonian university,
founded in 1364 by Casimir the Great, was a
major centre of east European intellectual
life from the 14th to the 17th centuries. To
combat the deterioration of this historic site
as a result of pollution from exhaust fumes,
traffic vibration, coal smoke, and water sa¬
linity, the Polish authorities have set out to
reduce pollution sources, notably by closing
down a nearby aluminium plant and replac¬
ing coal for heating by gas. They are also
carrying out a comprehensive restoration
programme on the old buildings. The his¬
toric centre of Cracow was inscribed on the
World Heritage List in 1978.
Nesebar (Bulgaria)
Thracians, Greeks, Romans and
ajjB Byzantium all left their mark on
', fllTl tn* town "' Nesebar, which
stands on a rocky Black Sea
promontory connected to the coast by a
narrow strip of land. According to legend
the first settlement established on the site
was founded by Mena, a Thracian from
whom it took its original name, Menebria. ^
In the 6th century BC the Greek colony of
Mesembria was founded on the peninsula.
Archaeologists have discovered remains of
the Greek agora, the theatre and the temple
of Apollo near buildings dating from the 1st
century BC, when the site was occupied by
the Romans. Towards the end of the 4th
century AD, Mesembria became a strong¬
hold of the Byzantine empire. In 1453 it was
captured by the Turks. Among the excep¬
tional monuments left in this "living mu¬
seum" by 3,000 years of history are many
fine churches, including the Old Metropoli¬
tan Church, rebuilt in the 9th century; the
10th-century church of the Virgin; the
New Metropolitan Church, founded in the
11th century and continually embellished
until the 18th; the church of St. John the
Baptist: and a number of 13th- and 14th-
century churches. The town, renamed Ne¬
sebar in 1934, was inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1983 as an exceptional cul¬
tural property bearing witness to several
vanished civilizations. A long and delicate
operation has begun to save the 16th-
century frescoes, especially those in St.
Stephen's church. Conservation of the
houses is particularly necessary both to
preserve the original ceramics and timber-
work of their façades and to make them
accessible to public. Right, the church of
the Pantocrator.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Angra do Heroísmo
(Portugal)
¡¡b
This port on the island of Ter-
ceira in the Azores was a link
between Europe and the "New
World" for more than 3 centu¬
ries. As early as the 15th century it was a
port-of-call for Portuguese fleets returning
to Europe from the Indies. Its site, admi¬
rably chosen by the early Atlantic naviga¬
tors, is sheltered by hills from the prevailing
winds. The port consisted of 2 natural ba¬
sins, the Beacon and the Anchorage (Angra
in Portuguese), from the latter of which the
settlement took its name. Soon after Angra
was founded, the large fortresses of Sao
Sebastiäo and Sao Filipe (today Sào Joäo
Baptista) were built, providing the port
with an impregnable defensive system. At
the same time a town was planned accord¬
ing to an original urban design in which the
checkerboard plan often followed when new
towns are built was modified to take ac¬
count of the prevailing winds. Angra do
Heroísmo is thus a unique example of the
adaptation of an urban model to climatic
conditions. A number of baroque monu¬
ments were built in Angra after it became
the seat of the Archbishop of the Azores in
1534. They include the cathedral of the San-
tissimo Salvador, the churches of the Miser¬
icordia and of the Santo Espérito, and the
convents of the Franciscans and the Jesuits.
In 1980, the town was shaken by an earth¬
quake which severely damaged many old
buildings. In 1983, its historic centre was
inscribed on the World Heritage List. Since
then, Unesco has sent several expert mis¬
sions to help the authorities draw up a plan
to safeguard the area as part of an overall
urban development programme, the major
concern being to restore earthquake-
damaged monuments and dwellings while
respecting the architectural traditions of
Terceira and preserving the town's
authenticity. Left, façade of a building;
below, general view of the town.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 24
spective only in the future; one of them is
Brasilia, perhaps the most formally planned
of all twentieth-century capitals.
Ultimately, the cultural sites of the World
Heritage List are material links between the
world of the past and that of the future.
They are of inestimable value for mankind
because they are the physical embodiment
of the passage of time. Historical processes,
even if bound up with the careers of individ¬
ual States, are not limited by them; these
processes should be understood as a human
legacy rather than a national one. The pre¬
sent, though by definition only a fleeting
moment, is the only one over which man
can exercise any control. For this reason, it
is imperative that cultural sites of the World
Heritage List be recognized and valued as a
material record of man's historical identity.
GEORGE MICHELL, ofAustralia, is an archae¬
ologist who has specialized in Hindu temple archi¬
tecture. He has written and edited numerous
publications including (as editor) The Islamic
Heritage of Bengal (Unesco, ¡984), Architecture
of the Islamic World and The Penguin Guide to
the Monuments of India. He is currently co-
director of an extensive documentation project at
Vijayanagar in southern India.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A sense of the sacred
BY OLEG GRABAR The values enshrined
in holy places
A large number of the cultural
properties on the World
Heritage List are religious
monuments. They range in size
from a small medieval wooden
church in Norway to a sacred
city in Sri Lanka; some are
located in the heart of historic
city centres, others in remote
rural areas. Are such
monuments bound by a thread
of common values which
transcends their diversity? Can
the significance of still-used
religious buildings only be
fully grasped by those who
worship in them? How should
the temples and sacred edifices
of long-dead religions be
interpreted? In the following
article a noted American
scholar examines these and
other complex issues raised by
religious monuments and their
conservation.
CERTAIN values attached to reli¬
gious monuments are peculiar to
them and to them alone. Three of
these values, which may be called spiritual,
aesthetic and cultural, are of particular im¬
portance, because each one affects the ways
in which religious monuments can be ex¬
plained and interpreted to those who wish
to see or understand them.
To talk about spiritual values in relation
to religious monuments is not as tautolo-
gous as it may seem. To begin with, it is not
always easy to understand the functional or
transcendental aspects of monuments be¬
longing to religions which have disap¬
peared, such as those of the ancient Near
East or of classical Antiquity. In order to
sense the sacred remoteness of an ancient
Egyptian temple, the subtly rational pro¬
portions or the siting in nature of a Greek
sanctuary, there is need for a knowledge of
the ceremonies, liturgies, ideas and beliefs
which made such monuments possible, but
which no longer play a role in human life
today.
Nor are spiritual values interchangeable.
To interpret a Muslim holy place in terms of
Buddhist spirituality is obviously intellec¬
tually improper and ethically wrong. Very
different spiritual approaches are, for exam¬
ple, required to understand such different
sites as Delphi and the Jesuit missions in
South America.
What is at issue here could be called the
spiritual integrity of a religious monument,
and its expression through the information
provided about it. The need for such in¬
formation is obvious in the case of monu¬
ments of abandoned religions, but it is even
more acute in the case of living religions,
especially when the monument is also a
living one. How should Christian or Mus¬
lim spirituality be presented in buildings
which have become museums, like Hagia
Sophia in Istanbul, which was built as an
imperial church and then turned into a
mosque of considerable ideological signif¬
icance? How should the spiritual values of
Chartres be presented without trivializing
religious practice into a kind of show? Or
should we say that religious buildings are
spiritually restricted to those who belong to
the faith concerned? These questions raise
fundamental issues about the ethics of spiri¬
tual property which, to my knowledge, have
not been discussed.
We seem to be on safer ground when we
turn to aesthetic values, since agreement can
easily be reached about the visual qualities
of a monument. To an overwhelming de¬
gree, the artistic heritage of mankind has
been inspired by the piety and beliefs held
by men and women since time immemorial.
At various times great artists have been
asked or have volunteered to build, deco¬
rate, or otherwise create religious monu¬
ments. And there is a degree of consensus
about the definitions of aesthetic quality, at
least for times somewhat removed from our
own. In part, these definitions derive from
the constantly evolving taste and judgment
of living societies, but aesthetic definitions
are not only the fickle judgments of various
periods. Much in them comes directly from
knowledge and understanding of the time
and place in which the monument was cre¬
ated. It is always assumed that those who
created the monument invested in the best
available competence to produce something
whose high quality would be recognized
by the people of that time, if not by
posterity.
Difficulties begin to appear when one
seeks to understand similarities and differ¬
ences between masterpieces of religious art.
For instance, nearly all religions have raised
at one time or another the question of
whether art and belief can coexist. Answers
have varied, and Christianity or Buddhism
have provided at different times contradic¬
tory responses to an issue which is central to
any religion with a transcendental divine,
while Islam or Judaism have remained, on .
the whole, set on a single and more or less
consistent course.
Such variations have obviously created
very different emphases and approaches to
visual creativity. Nearly all religions have
both congregational requirements and ways
of expressing private piety. These have led
to very different solutions, the huge congre¬
gational mosques of Islam at one extreme;
CONTINUED ON PAGE 31
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
fifrn
Mosque City of Bagerhat
(Bangladesh)
This city, originally known as
Khalifatabad, was founded in
the 15th century by General
Ulugh Khan Jahan in the
southern part of the world's biggest delta,
near the coastline of the Bay of Bengal. A
devout man, the general constructed brick
mosques, palaces, public buildings, bridges
and mausoleums, as well as paved roads
communicating with other cities. Large res¬
ervoirs of fresh water, indispensable in this
region of brackish water, catered for the
needs of the population. Architecturally,
the spectacular ruins of Bagerhat are a
unique blend of the imperial style of Delhi
and the local style of Muslim Bengal. The
mosques are sober and austere. A typical
example is the Shait Gumbad mosque
(right), which is renowned for its 77 domes
and its immense prayer hall divided into 7
naves. The site, inscribed on the World Her¬
itage List in 1985, is threatened by the mon¬
soon, encroaching vegetation, and the ex¬
treme salinity of the soil and the
atmosphere which is corroding the monu¬
ments and weakening their foundations. In
1985 Unesco launched a campaign to safe¬
guard Bagerhat and Paharpur, another
World Heritage site in Bangladesh. The first
priorities are to reinforce the weakest sec¬
tions of the buildings, to set up a drainage
system to stop rainwater from seeping into
them, and to combat vandalism.
The Convent of St.
(Switzerland)
Gall
In the valley of the Steinach river, where
the Irish monk Gallus had his hermit's
retreat in the 7th century, abbot Otmar
established a Benedictine community in
Whi
747 and founded a monastery and a school. In the 9th
and 10th centuries, St. Gall became one of the most
important centres of culture in the West. Its schools of
chant and illumination, and above all its scriptorium
or copying room in which scribes produced illumi¬
nated manuscripts of outstanding beauty, were famed
throughout Western Christendom. The abbey was at
the height of its glory in the 9th century under abbot
Gozbert, when it was rebuilt according to a new
design which was a remarkable illustration of Car-
olingian architectural ideas. Today the only surviving
vestiges of the splendour of the Carolingian monaste¬
ry are the foundations and a number of architectural
elements discovered during probes made in the 1960s.
Rebuilt between the 16th and the 18th centuries,
the monastery incorporates a fine baroque cathedral
(above) and library. A major landmark in the history of
Western intellectual and religious life, the Convent of
St. Gall was inscribed on the World Heritage List in
1983.
Jesuit Missions of the Guaranis (Argentina, Brazil)
ffihi
As part of their efforts to con¬
vert the Guarani Indians to
Christianity, Spanish Jesuit
missionaries in 17th- and 18th-
century Latin America created villages
known as reducciones in which the Indians
could be concentrated and given a religious
education. Five of these Jesuit Missions, Sao
Miguel das Missöes in Brazil, and San Igna¬
cio Mini, Santa Ana, Nuestra Señora de
Loreto and Santa Maria la Mayor in Argen¬
tina, were jointly inscribed on the World
Heritage List in 1983 and 1984. They were
all built in accordance with the same ba¬
roque masterplan, with church, Jesuit fa¬
thers' residence, school, Indians' houses and
cemetery all grouped around a large square.
For several years Argentina and Brazil have
been engaged on study and restoration
work in some of the Missions. In Argentina,
exploration, site-mapping and clearing
have been carried out at Santa Ana; tourist
facilities have been improved at San Ignacio
Mini, which is better preserved than the
other Missions; and undergrowth has been
cleared at Nuestra Señora de Loreto. In
Brazil, consolidation, site-mapping and
cleaning are under way at Sao Miguel.
Unesco will soon be launching a major
international campaign to safeguard the
Jesuit Missions. Consultants are already
advising on steps to consolidate the build¬
ings. Unesco has also, among other mea¬
sures, financed meetings to plan future ac¬
tion programmes, carried out site
inventories, published a booklet on The Je¬
suit Missions of the Guaranis and co-pro¬
duced a documentary film. Right, church of
Sâo Miguel d^s Missöes (Brazil), and detail
of façade, San Ignacio Mini (Argentina).
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo Unesco Photo F.F. Ortiz/Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
Cistercian Abbey of
Fontenay (France)
iÜfhi
Situated in northern Burgundy,
Fontenay was founded in 1119
by Bernard of Clairvaux, one of
the most forceful personalities
of his time. As a young man, St. Bernard
entered the Cistercian order, newly found¬
ed by a reformer who wished to restore
rigour and austerity to Western monasti-
cism. Painting, ornate sculpture and all
forms of embellishment liable to cause dis¬
traction were prohibited from the walls of
Cistercian monasteries, and consequently
tjie Cistercian edifices of Europe are ad¬
mired by those who look for clarity, logic
and plainness in architecture. The church at
Fontenay was built between 1139 and 1147.
Its transept is towerless. Apart from the
cloisters (left) and the chapter house, which
were built at the same time as the church,
the warming room, the refectory, and the
long, magnificently vaulted parlour have
also survived, along with the dormitory,
whose timberwork was restored in the 15th
century and has not needed repairs since
then. The forge (c. 1 180) is one of the oldest
industrial buildings in Europe. Abandoned
in the 18th century, then sold, the abbey
had not been too seriously damaged by its
owners when all activity came to an end
there in 1902. Four years later, a new owner
embarked on the restoration of the abbey.
He successfully achieved his goal and today
the onerous task of upkeep is being scrupu¬
lously carried out by his heirs with the aid
of the French State. The abbey was inscrib¬
ed on the World Heritage List in 1981.
ffifbi
The Great Mosque and
Hospital of Divrigi (Turkey)
This highly original architectu¬
ral ensemble in the mountain¬
ous region of eastern Anatolia
was founded in 1228-1229 by
emir Ahmet Shah of the Turkish Menguce-
kid dynasty. Both the mosque and the ad¬
joining marestan (a hospital for the insane)
were built by the same architect, Khurram-
shad of Ahlat. The single prayer room in
the great mosque has 5 naves and stone
vaulting which displays astonishing tech¬
nical skill and mastery of space. Above the
prayer room are 2 cupolas of unequal size,
one above the ablutions basin, and the main
cupola which rises above the mihrab (the
decorated niche indicating the direction of
Mecca) and is itself surmounted by the
mosque's most accomplished piece of archi¬
tecture, a ribbed hexagonal spire supported
on pendentives. The walls of Divrigi are
pierced by 3 monumental gates (left) sump¬
tuously decorated with floral and geometric
motifs recalling contemporary Armenian
or Georgian designs. The mosque and hos¬
pital were inscribed on the World Heritage
List in 1985.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
mm
Studenica Monastery
(Yugoslavia)
tffh
Founded in 1183 by the Serbian
prince Stefan Nemanja and de¬
veloped by his sons, the monas¬
tery of Studenica became the
necropolis of the Nemanjic dynasty and
remained a focal point of Serbian history
for centuries. Within the walls of the mon¬
astery more sanctuaries were built in addi¬
tion to the original church, and decorated
by medieval Christian artists with beautiful
marble sculptures and graceful frescoes
such as that of the Birth of the Virgin
(above) from the famous "King's Church"
of St. Anne and St. Joachim, completed in
1314. The wall paintings (1208-1209) in the
Church of the Virgin display new ways of
depicting human expression and space and
are a landmark in the history of Byzantine
and Western art. The works of the late
13th-century Italian painters Cimabue,
Duccio and Giotto spring from this new
awareness. The monastery, inscribed on the
World Heritage List in 1986, is well-
conserved. However, the authorities are
concerned by plans to construct a dam
in the vicinity and divert the Studenica
River. In autumn 1988 Unesco experts will
visit the site to study the likely effects of
this project.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 27
individual and private icons, reliquaries, or
altars at the other.
Other examples can easily be provided of
different, even antagonistic, purposes and
assumptions underlying aesthetic creativity.
Should one, for instance, tend to emphasize
the similarities, the constants, of spaces cre¬
ated for large numbers or of the need for
official or esoteric signs and symbols? Or
should one, on the contrary, argue that since
aesthetic enjoyment is a personal matter, its
expression can only be defined around indi¬
vidual monuments and not on a universal
level? Are there a religious art and aesthetic
of faith and piety? Or are there only large
numbers of religious monuments, each of
which provides one or more aesthetic solu¬
tions to discrete and specific needs?
These brief considerations of spiritual and
aesthetic values lead automatically to my
third category, that of cultural values. What
I mean by this are such features as enhance
and strengthen the awareness an individual
or a group has of the past, both in an ethnic
or biological sense and in a geographical or
regional sense.
It is assumed that a knowledge of one's
roots is an asset in the definition of one's
identity, and certainly religious beliefs ex¬
pressed through writing, through traditions,
and through monuments are part of every
person's heritage. But, in addition, the va¬
garies of history have given to many ethnic
or national groups the guardianship of the
monuments of other pasts and other reli¬
gions than their own. The issue here is how
to interpret other religions within one's own
consciousness and within one's own heri¬
tage, or else how to have access to one's
religious monuments located in other and at
times inimical lands.
This is a relatively recent issue, for in the
past new religions or new States did not
hesitate either to destroy the remains of
older faiths or to adapt them to their own
purposes. The ancient Egyptian temple at
Luxor was in the past transformed into a
church, as was the Pantheon in Rome, and
Hagia Sophia became a mosque, while the
first mosque at Delhi was built on top of a
Hindu temple whose destroyed elements
were reused in the mosque. In many ways
the truth of any one religion implies the
falsehood of other faiths, and the tragic
human consequences of this state of affairs
throughout the ages are well known.
It is probably best to assume that, in our
time of complex relationships both to the
past and to land, each person will maintain
some sort of equilibrium between his or her
own religious culture, the religious cultures
of the land in which he or she lives, and a
universal acceptance of diversity. Only then
will it be possible to see religious monu¬
ments as national heirlooms, as the property
at one level of all men and women and at
another as expressions of piety for restricted
groups only.
A common thread binds spiritual, aes¬
thetic and cultural values when they are
applied to religious monuments. It is the
thread of integrity. There is the integrity of
the monument, which conservators, cura¬
tors and academics of all sorts are ready to
preserve, but must above all try to explain at
different levels, from the highest and most
esoteric scholarship to the very important
level of primary education. There is also the
integrity of the pious believer, who must
not feel that fame and recognition may have
robbed his or her shrine of some particle of
grace but who realizes that this holy place
can also be a work of art. Finally there is the
integrity of the citizen of a country who
feels pride in its monuments. Through the
magic of artistic creativity, it is possible to
partake of the power of a religious monu¬
ment, without sharing in its holiness or even
liking its aesthetic values.
The questions raised in this essay can only
be answered if we are ready to furnish the
considerable educational effort which
would make religious monuments accessible
and meaningful to all. Such an education
must go further than the mere provision of
information. It requires a protean sensitivity
which combines humility towards all be¬
liefs, pride in the age-old accomplishments
of artists and artisans, and emotional or
aesthetic satisfaction in their works.
OLEG GRABAR, of the United States, is a
distinguished art historian who has been since
1980 Aga Khan Professor of Islamic Art and
Architecture at Harvard University, where he
was Chairman of the Department of Fine Arts
between 1977 and 1982. He was a member of the
Steering Committee of the Aga Khan Award for
Architecture between 1978 and 1987. He has been
a member of the American Academy ofArts and
Sciences since 1978 and was recently elected to the
British Academy. He is the author of numerous
articles and books on Islamic art and architecture
including, most recently, Islamic Art Until 1250,
Pelican, London, 1987 (written in collaboration
with the late R. Ettinghausen). 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The world heritage
concept
BY MICHEL PARENT
32
THE establishment of the World
Heritage List is not an academic ex¬
ercise. It is an international under¬
taking of a juridical, technical and practical
nature designed to mobilize active solidarity
for the safeguard of the cultural and natural
heritage.
This heritage is under constant threat
from the effects of underdevelopment or
ill-advised development. International co¬
operation is required to ensure the survival
of vestiges of vanished cultures and of the
riches of living cultures, to save living spe¬
cies from extinction, to make possible the
sustained renewal of natural resources and
to maintain the ecological balance. The im¬
plementation of the 1972 Convention is in
the forefront of this effort.
Making an inventory of properties of uni¬
versal value is an exciting intellectual en¬
terprise, but one which calls for a more
restrictive definition of the notion of heri¬
tage, which is tending to . become all-in¬
clusive under the impact of scientific devel¬
opment and the expansion of the concepts
of history and culture. It is true that every¬
thing belongs to history and that the whole
of nature and all human artefacts leave traces
worthy of interpretation. But the world is
changing rapidly and if the truly essential
traces of the heritage are not given special
universal recognition, then even they may
be swept away by the forces of change. If
this happens, the notion of permanent value
and its expression in specific sites and arte¬
facts may be lost.
The properties chosen for inclusion on
the World Heritage List are not the only
ones that deserve to be safeguarded, how¬
ever. On the contrary, properties privileged
by inclusion are intended to serve as exam¬
ples and to encourage the formulation of
national or local policies for safeguarding
the environment as a whole. The objectives
of the Convention are thus both ambitious
and credible. It affords to every State Party
prestige, specific assistance and safeguards
in the event of catastrophes against which
no country can be forewarned, not even the
most developed and the best equipped.
All countries possess an appreciable cul¬
tural and natural heritage. Many of the 102
States Parties to the Convention have sub¬
mitted dossiers to the World Heritage Com¬
mittee and obtained the inscription on the
List of numerous properties. But, it might
be asked, why have they not all done so? It
is not very logical for a State to ratify the
Convention (unless it attaches only a sym¬
bolic value to ratification), and then to take
no further action. And why are there only
102 States Parties to the Convention? Why
has the 1972 Convention not won unani¬
mous, universal support? Joint efforts by
the States Parties, Unesco, and the Interna¬
tional Council on Monuments and Sites
(ICOMOS) to define fields of international
co-operation (by areas of common culture,
beliefs and architectural techniques, or by
major communication and trade routes) are
thwarted by the blank spaces which appear
on the maps, like the gaps which indicated
terra incognita in early atlases.
Admittedly there are also great disparities
between States deriving from their size,
population density, the age of their culture,
the vicissitudes of their history or the care
they have hitherto taken to conserve their
cultural heritage. Likewise, the fact that
cultural properties far outnumber natural
properties on the List is not in itself signif¬
icant. A cultural property may be a small or
isolated building or even an archaeological
vestige in the midst of a wilderness; a nat¬
ural property may be an immense national
park bigger than some States.
Tassili n'Ajjer (Algeria)
This vast plateau (tassili in
the Berber language) covers
72,000 km2 of the central
Sahara in south-eastern Al¬
geria. It is a kind of natural
fortress, penetrated only by
a few deep gorges. In the
West, the plateau (on aver¬
age 1,500 m high) ends in a sheer, 500-m
cliff, almost 700 km long. A network of
canyons cuts through the interior, some of
them with pools, springs or even permanent
streams fringed with vegetation. Sedentary
groups of Tuareg peoples have long been
settled in these oases, and nomadic Tuareg
roam elsewhere on the plateau, although
they too are tending to settle down as a
result of drought and declining plant re¬
sources, thus further threatening the del¬
icate ecological balance. Tassili n'Ajjer is
famous for the thousands of rock paintings
and engravings which make it the world's
biggest open-air prehistoric museum. This
Neolithic (6000-2000 BC) rock art and
many other archaeological remains indicate
that the region was occupied during a less
arid period, when flora and fauna were
much more abundant. The site was in¬
scribed on the World Heritage List in 1982
in recognition of its cultural riches as well as
its natural value. A management plan is
being worked out with Unesco assistance
under the terms of the Convention. Right,
engraving of oxen at Tegarghart, near Dja-
net. Below right, polygonaceous shrub at
Essendilène.
As the field of application of the Conven¬
tion is gradually defined, it is becoming
clear that the means needed to accomplish
its aims are far beyond the resources of the
World Heritage Committee, which can only
finance urgent work, expert studies, under¬
funded projects carried out over a long
period, and the preventive work necessary
to avoid the deterioration of properties and
the costs that ensue, and to guarantee their
authenticity.
The publication of information about the
World Heritage in the media should help to
encourage major safeguarding operations,
but the rigour with which the List is estab¬
lished and the need to make it representative
and fully credible will determine the success
of media coverage. Finally, solidarity in aid
of World Heritage properties calls for per¬
manent monitoring of their condition, in
order to guarantee that the Convention is
respected and that financial aid is put to
good use. There should be no question of
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
inscribing unworthy properties on the List.
Fortunately this is not the case. But the
extension and success of the World Heritage
concept call for vigilance. The exercise of
supra-national control should not be seen as
an infringement of the sovereignty of States,
since they have made their commitment
freely after weighing up the advantages and
constraints.
Any community can find in the Conven¬
tion support for the safeguard of its cultural
identity which goes beyond material aid and
may help to prevent the clandestine de¬
struction of its heritage or to combat in¬
terests which have scant respect for it.
MICHEL PARENT, ofFrance, was President of
the International Council on Monuments and
Sites from 1981 to 1987. As a member of the
committee which drafted the World Heritage
Convention and as rapporteur and later chairman
of the World Heritage Committee, he made a
leading contribution to the birth and development
of the world heritage concept. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
An idea in action
The World Heritage Convention
and how it works
34
Who participates in the World Heritage
mechanism?
Depending on their national procedures,
States may ratify, accept or accede to the
"Convention Concerning the Protection of
the World Cultural and Natural Heritage".1
These countries (called "States Parties")
thus become full participants in the Con¬
vention's mechanisms. Adopted by Unes¬
co's General Conference in November
1972, the Convention entered into force in
1975, once a "critical mass" of States Parties,
set at twenty, had joined. The United States
of America was the first to do so, on 7
December 1973. It was followed in rapid
succession by nineteen others from all lat¬
itudes (Egypt, Iraq, Bulgaria, Sudan, Alge¬
ria, Australia, Zaire, Nigeria, Niger, Islamic
Republic of Iran, Tunisia, Jordan, Yugosla¬
via, Ecuador, France, Ghana, Syrian Arab
Republic, Cyprus, and Switzerland).
As of 1 June 1988 there were 102 States
Parties from all the world's regions. Of
Unesco's total membership, only fifty-six
States are yet to become Parties to the Con¬
vention, making it not only Unesco's most
broadly accepted international instrument
but also the world's most ratified agreement
on conservation. So, just as its framers in¬
tended, the day is not far off when the
Convention will extend its protection to
"the world heritage of mankind as a
whole".
The States Parties meet in General As¬
sembly once every two years to elect
twenty-one of their number to the World
Heritage Committee. Each State's term of
office is six years, but one-third of the
membership changes every two years. The
first Committee was elected in November
1976. It held its first session in June 1977, at
which principles and methods of work were
agreed. By the following year, with the
1. The Convention applies to immovable property. Thus
it defines cultural heritage as "monuments, groups of
buildings and sites" natural heritage as "natural features
(e.g. physical and biological formations), geological and
physiographical formations and natural sites".
inscription of the first twelve sites, the Con¬
vention became operational.
The Committee's current members are
Algeria, Australia, Brazil, Bulgaria, Canada,
Cuba, France, Greece, India, Italy, Leba¬
non, Malawi, Mexico, Norway, Pakistan,
Sri Lanka, Tunisia, Turkey, United Repub¬
lic of Tanzania, United States of America
and Yemen Arab Republic.
Unesco officers responsible for the heri¬
tage preservation programmes provide the
secretariat of the Committee and implement
its decisions. The Committee is advised,
particularly in the selection of properties for
the World Heritage List, by specialists in
the non-governmental organizations active
internationally in safeguarding the cultural
and natural heritage the International
Council on Monuments and Sites (ICO-
MOS) and the International Union for Con¬
servation of Nature and Natural Resources
(IUCN). The two organizations also con¬
tribute technically to the safeguard of World
Heritage sites, together with the Interna¬
tional Centre for the Study of the Preserva¬
tion and the Restoration of Cultural Proper¬
ty in Rome (ICCROM), founded under the
aegis of Unesco.
How are World Heritage properties
chosen?
States Parties begin the process by nomi¬
nating properties in their territory that the
Committee may consider to be of "out¬
standing universal value", hence deserving
inscription on the World Heritage List. The
Committee then inscribes on the List those
properties that meet criteria which focus the
easily understandable but broad, and neces¬
sarily subjective, concept of "outstanding
universal value". These criteria have been
carefully worked out over the years. The
process has involved long hours of study,
comparison and discussion among natural
scientists and historians of art and architec¬
ture as well as within the Committee itself.
But even today uncertainties remain and
certain inscriptions can be agreed upon by
all only after animated discussion.
Bfaj
St. Mary's Cathedral and St.
Michael's Church, Hildesheim
(Fed. Rep. of Germany) ^
The layout and interior deco¬
ration of these 2 monuments
throw light on an important pe¬
riod in the history of religious
art of the Holy Roman Empire during the
Romanesque era. Founded in the 9th centu¬
ry and rebuilt in the 1 1th, St. Mary's Cathe¬
dral (right) is embellished with major works
of art, notably its bronze doors depicting
scenes from the book of Genesis and the life
of Christ, and a bronze column, inspired by
Trajan's Column in Rome, whose spiral
decoration depicts scenes from the New
Testament. Both works were commissioned
by bishop Bernward (933-1022), who was
the leading counsellor of emperor Otto III
and a passionate art lover. St. Bernward
was also the founder of the ancient Bene¬
dictine abbey church of St. Michael (mainly
llth-12th centuries). St. Michael's is the
masterpiece of Ottonian Germanic archi¬
tecture, with its symmetrical layout, its
treatment of volumes, and its original sil¬
houette in which 4 elegant circular turrets
contrast with the 2 massive lantern towers.
In the crypt is St. Bernward's tomb. The
painted wood ceiling of the nave depicts a
gigantic Tree of Jesse and Christological
scenes. These 2 buildings were inscribed on
the World Heritage List in 1985.
Garamba National Park
(Zaire) |
Among the great mammals
which roam the vast expanse of
the Garamba savannah in
north-eastern Zaire is one of
Africa's rarest and most threatened species,
the northern white rhinoceros (Ceratothe-
rium simum cottoni). Larger than the black
rhino, it owes its name to its rectangular
jaw, the word "white" being a corruption of
the Afrikaans word wyd (wide, or large).
The white rhino is actually dark grey, when
it is not covered in the red lateritic mud in
which it wallows. Garamba National Park,
founded in 1938 to save the white rhino,
was inscribed on the World Heritage List in
1980. Thanks to a project organized within
the framework of the World Heritage Con¬
vention and jointly funded by the World
Wildlife Fund (WWF), Frankfurt Zoo (Fed.
Rep. of Germany), Zaire Institute for the
Conservation of Nature and Unesco, the
white rhino population, which in 1985 had
fallen to a critical threshold of a dozen, is
now around twenty. The main purpose of
the project, which will continue for several
years until the rhino's numbers have in¬
creased sufficiently to ensure its survival, is
to combat poaching. Hippopotamus, ele¬
phant, buffalo, giraffe and leopard also live
in the 4,480 km2 Park. A balance between
woodland and grassland is maintained by a
policy of preventive burning which lets the
new grass grow for pasture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Committee meets every autumn to
inscribe properties nominated and is aided
in its evaluation by ICOMOS and IUCN,
who use their international networks of
specialists to assess each site against the
criteria. Since 1978 therefore there has been
an annual cycle of nomination, evaluation
and inscription. The List's rate of growth
has been striking, with an average of thirty
new properties added each year since 1978.
The List has grown much more rapidly in
cultural properties: out of 288 so far in¬
scribed 211 are cultural, 68 natural and nine
so-called "mixed" properties such as Tikal
National Park in Guatemala and Mount
Taishan in China, sites that combine great
natural and cultural significance. One
hundred and thirty-three of these properties
are found in Europe and North America, 36
in Latin America and the Caribbean, 48 in
Asia and the Pacific, 32 in Africa and 39 in
the Arab States.
Today's List is clearly not yet universally
representative.- Nor does it include certain
properties whose worldwide importance
would be recognized immediately by the
man in the street, not to speak of the art
historian or natural scientist. This is simply
because a third of the world community has
not yet joined the Convention. And the
order in which the List has been established
reflects the priorities of States Parties them¬
selves.
What is the practical benefit of
inscription on the List?
Since better protection of World Heritage
properties is the Convention's essential pur¬
pose, the immediate and obvious benefit of
international listing is to strengthen the 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Mogao Caves (China)
This ensemble of Buddhist cave-
3_£J^ temples is located on the edge of
iJtt TI the Taklamakan desert, Gansu
^^^^* Province, in north-west China.
Monks first began work on the caves in the
4th century AD at a place where, according
to legend, a monk had a vision of a thou¬
sand Buddhas. The site, which was on the
Silk Road, saw intensive activity until the
14th century, by which time hundreds of
caves had been hewn out of the rock and
decorated with frescoes (detail, right) and
sculptures by artists from diverse tradi¬
tions. Today 496 caves still exist. After a
period (4th to 6th centuries) marked by the
influence of Graeco-Buddhist art and the
predominance of illustrations of jätakas,
stories relating former lives of the Buddha,
Mogao art reached its zenith between the
6th and the 9th centuries with the evoca¬
tion of Buddhist scriptures or sütras, scenes
from daily life and historical subjects. From
the 10th to the 14th centuries, with the
decline of the Silk Road and the recruitment
of artist-functionaries to decorate the caves,
a more academic style evolved. Mogao was
inscribed on the World Heritage List in
1987. In 1988, Unesco sent a team of experts
to help the Chinese authorities set up a
conservation plan for the site, which is in an
earthquake zone prone to sandstorms. De¬
spite the arid desert climate, the morning
mist in spring and summer can trigger a
chemical reaction which alters the colours
of the frescoes. Training courses in the con¬
servation of wall paintings are planned for
staff working at Mogao.
36
hand of those who are committed to their
protection and enjoyment. These may be
the conservation personnel of national an¬
tiquities or parks services, who must com¬
pete with other government departments
for limited funds. They may be local author¬
ities or even private associations of con¬
cerned citizens.
But international notoriety and moral
support are not enough. Thus the World
Heritage Fund created by the Convention
makes it possible to provide concrete fi¬
nancial and technical support to countries
with limited resources. All States Parties
have to contribute to this Fund: either 1 per
cent of their share of Unesco's Regular
Budget as a compulsory contribution, or a
voluntary contribution that should at least
equal that 1 per cent. The Convention also
provides for contributions from non-gov¬
ernmental bodies and private individuals.
The World Heritage Committee allocates
the annual budget of the Fund2.7 million
U.S. dollars in 1988 to a wide range of
activities. These include the identification of
potential World Heritage properties, the
study of their state of conservation and of
the conservation measures they require
($100,000 allocated in 1988); the provision
of expert advice, technical support and
equipment for conservation (some $700,000
allocated); the strengthening of training in
conservation ($500,000) and finally, emer¬
gency assistance when properties have been
suddenly damaged by a disaster or threat¬
ened by one ($200,000).
Furthermore, the Committee may also
choose to place a severely threatened site on
the "List of World Heritage in Danger".
Such listing provides the opportunity to
take urgent steps and raise funds for the
large-scale operations needed to avert the
danger. To date seven natural and cultural
sites have been so listed.
In all cases, the framers of the Convention
clearly stipulated that the national author¬
ities, who are the direct depositary of the
heritage in question, should match the com¬
mitment of the international community.
With honour comes responsibility and, in
the ultimate analysis, accountability. By the
same token, the Committee has not rested
content with simply inscribing more and
more properties year after year. It has set up
a system of monitoring the state of conser¬
vation of listed sites and of intervening ap¬
propriately when local resources prove to be
insufficient.
Since 1978, a total of some 5 million
dollars has been disbursed by the Fund, a
paltry sum in relation to enormous needs
the world over and a pittance when com¬
pared to the vast amounts nations spend on
weapons of destruction. Yet the money has
gone a long way, for it has been used to
supplement national investments, to cata¬
lyze local resources and, perhaps most
important of all, to stimulate support at
various levels, both national and inter¬
national, for the conservation of a common
heritage.
In Haiti, for example, a comprehensive
4-million-dollar conservation and training
programme has been developed for the his¬
toric Citadel, Sans Souci Palace and Ramiers
site. The Fund has contributed $ 100,000,
Unesco's Regular Budget the same amount,
and the United Nations Development Pro¬
gramme (UNDP) some $ 1.2 million. Bilat¬
eral reinforcement of the government's in¬
vestment comes from Austria, Canada,
Chile, France, the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many and the Netherlands. The World
Monuments Fund has also raised almost
$ 200,000 from American philanthropic
sources. Similarly, support from the World
Heritage Fund has led to a vast movement
of solidarity in favour of Zaire's splendid
Garamba National Park, the last refuge of
the northern white rhino.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The World Heritage List
Photo © Rinnie Tang, Paris
288 properties as at 31 December 1987
(211 cultural sites, 68 natural sites and 9 mixed sites)
Algeria
Al Qal'a of Beni Hammad. Tassili n'Ajjer. M'Zab
Valley. Djemila. Tipasa. Timgad.
Argentina
Los Glaciares. Iguazu National Park.
Argentina and Brazil
Jesuit Missions of the Guaranis: San Ignacio
Mini, Santa Ana, Nuestra Señora de Loreto and
Santa Maria la Mayor (Argentina); ruins of Sào
Miguel das Missöes (Brazil).
Australia
Kakadu National Park. Great Barrier Reef. Wil-
landra Lakes Region. Western Tasmania Wilder¬
ness National Parks. Lord Howe Island group.
Australian East Coast Temperate and Sub-Trop¬
ical Rainforest Parks. Uluru National Park.
Bangladesh
Historic mosque city of Bagerhat. Ruins of the
Buddhist Vihara, Paharpur.
Benin
Royal Palaces of Abomey.
Bolivia
City of Potosí.
Brazil
Historic town of Ouro Preto. Historic centre of
the town of Olinda. Historic centre of Salvador
de Bahia. Sanctuary of Bom Jesus do Congonhas.
Iguazu National Park. Brasilia.
Bulgaria
Boyana Church. Madara Rider. Thracian tomb of
Kazanlak. Rock-hewn churches of Ivanovo. An¬
cient city of Nesebar. Rila Monastery. Srebarna
Nature Reserve. Pirin National Park. Thracian
tomb of Sveshtari.
Cameroon
Dja Faunal Reserve.
Canada
L'Anse aux Meadows National Historic Park.
Nahanni National Park. Dinosaur Provincial
Park. Anthony Island. Head-Smashed-In Bison
Jump Complex. Wood Buffalo National Park.
Canadian Rocky Mountain Parks."" Quebec (His¬
toric area). Gros Morne National Park.
Canada and United States of America
Kluane National Park/Wrangell-St. Elias Nation¬
al Park and Preserve.
China
Mount Taishan. The Great Wall. Imperial Palace
of the Ming and Qing Dynasties. Mogao Caves.
Mausoleum of the First Qin Emperor. Peking
, Man site at Zhoukoudian.
Colombia
Port, fortresses and group of monuments, Carta¬
gena.
*The Burgess Shale site, which was previously
inscribed on the World Heritage List, is part of
the Canadian Rocky Mountain Parks.
Costa Rica
Talamanca Range-La Amistad Reserves.
Côte d'Ivoire
Tai National Park. Comoé National Park.
Cuba
Old Havana and its fortifications.
Cyprus
Paphos. Painted churches in the Troodos re¬
gion.
Democratic Yemen
Old walled city of Shibam.
Ecuador
Galapagos Islands. Quito (Old City). Sangay
National Park.
Egypt
Memphis and its Necropolis: Pyramid fields from
Giza to Dahshur. Ancient Thebes with its Necro¬
polis. Nubian monuments from Abu Simbel to
Philae. Islamic Cairo. Abu Mena.
Ethiopia
Simen National Park. Rock-hewn churches, Lali-
bela. Fasil Ghebbi, Gondar Region. Lower valley
of the Awash. Tiya. Aksum. Lower valley of the
Omo.
France
Mont-Saint-Michel and its Bay. Chartres Cathe¬
dral. Palace and Park of Versailles. Vézelay,
Church and Hill. Decorated grottoes of the Ve-
zère Valley. Palace and Park of Fontainebleau.
Château and Estate of Chambord. Amiens Cathe¬
dral. Roman Theatre and Triumphal Arch,
Orange. Roman and Romanesque monuments,
Aries. Cistercian Abbey of Fontenay. Royal Salt¬
works of Arc-et-Senans. Place Stanislas, Place de
la Carrière and Place d'Alliance, Nancy. Church
of Saint-Savin sur Gartempe. Cape Girolatta,
Cape Porto and Scandola Nature Reserve, Corsi¬
ca. Pont du Gard (Roman aqueduct).
Germany (Federal Republic of)
Aachen Cathedral. Speyer Cathedral. Würzburg
Residence with Court Gardens and Residence
Square. Pilgrimage Church of Wies. Castles of
Augustusburg and Falkenlust, Brühl. St. Mary's
Cathedral and St. Michael's Church, Hildesheim.
Monuments of Trier. Hanseatic city of Lübeck.
Ghana
Forts and castles, Volta, Greater Accra, Central
and Western Regions. Ashante traditional build¬
ings.
Greece
Temple of Apollo Epicurius at Bassae. Archae¬
ological site of Delphi. Acropolis, Athens.
Guatemala
Tikal National Park. Antigua Guatemala. Ar¬
chaeological Park and ruins of Quirigua.
Guinea and Côte d'Ivoire
Mount Nimba Strict Nature Reserve. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Haiti
National Historie Park Citadel, Sans Souci, Ra¬
miers.
Holy See
Vatican City.
Honduras
Maya site of Copan. Rio Plátano Biosphere Re¬
serve.
Hungary
Budapest, banks of. the Danube with district of
Buda Castle. Hollokö.
India
Ajanta Caves. Ellora Caves. Agra Fort. Taj Ma¬
hal. Sun Temple, Konarak. Group of monuments
at Mahabalipuram. Kaziranga National Park. Ma¬
nas Wildlife Sanctuary. Keoladeo National Park.
Churches and convents of Goa. Khajuraho group
of monuments. Group of monuments at Hampi.
Fatehpur Sikri. Group of monuments at Pattada-
kal. Elephanta Caves. Brihadisvara Temple,
Thanjavur. Sundarbans National Park.
Iraq
Hatra.
Islamic Republic of Iran
Tchogha Zanbil. Persepolis. Meidan Emam, Es-
fahan.
Italy
Rock drawings, Valcamonica. Historic centre of
Rome. Church and Dominican Convent of Santa
Maria delle Grazie with The Last Supper by
Leonardo da Vinci. Historic centre of Florence.
Venice and its lagoon. Piazza del Duorao, Pisa.
Jordan
Old city of Jerusalem and its walls. Petra. Quseir
Amra.
Lebanon
Anjar. Baalbek. Byblos. Tyr.
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya
Archaeological site of Leptis Magna. Archaeolog¬
ical site of Sabratha. Archaeological site of Cy-
rene. Rock-art sites of Tadrart Acacus. Old town
of Ghadamès.
Malawi
Lake Malawi National Park.
Malta
Hal Saflieni Hypogeum. City of Valetta. Ggantija
Temples.
Mexico
Sian Ka'an. Pre-Hispanic city and National Park
of Palenque. Historic centre of Mexico City and
Xochimilco. Pre-Hispanic city of Teotihuacán.
Historic centre of Oaxaca and archaeological site
of Monte Alban. Historic centre of Puebla.
Morocco
Medina of Fez. Medina of Marrakesh. Ksar of
A'it-Ben-Haddou.
Nepal
Sagarmatha National Park. Kathmandu Valley.
Royal Chitwan National Park.
New Zealand
Westland and Mount Cook National Park.
Fiordland National Park.
Norway
Urnes Stave Church. Bryggen. Roros. Rock
drawings of Alta.
Oman
Bahia Fort.
Pakistan
Archaeological ruins at Moenjodaro. Taxila.
"3 O Buddhist ruins of Takht-i-Bahi and neighbouring
city remains at Sahr-i-Bahlol. Historical monu¬
ments of Thatta. Fort and Shalamar Gardens,
Lahore.
Panama
Fortifications on the Caribbean side of Portobe-
lo-San Lorenzo. Darien National Park.
Peru
City of Cuzco. Historic sanctuary of Machu
Picchu. Archaeological site of Chavin. Huascaran
National Park. Chan Chan archaeological zone.
Manu National Park.
Poland
Historic centre of Cracow. Wieliczka Salt Mine.
Auschwitz Concentration Camp. Bialowieza Na¬
tional Park. Historic centre of Warsaw.
Portugal
Central zone of the town of Angra do Heroísmo,
Azores. Monastery of the Hieronymites and
Tower of Belem, Lisbon. Monastery of Batalha.
Convent of Christ, Tomar. Historic centre of
Evora.
Senegal
Island of Gorée. Niokolo-Koba National. Park.
Djoudj National Bird Sanctuary.
Seychelles
Aldabra Atoll. Vallée de Mai Nature Reserve.
Spain
Mosque of Cordoba. Alhambra and Generalife,
Granada. Burgos Cathedral. Monastery and site
of the Escurial, Madrid. Parque Güell, Palacio
Güell and Casa Mila, Barcelona. Altamira Cave.
Old town of Segovia and its aqueduct. Churches
of the Kingdom of the Asturias. Santiago de
Compostela (Old town). Old town of Avila with
its extra-muros churches. Mudejar architecture of
Teruel. Historic city of Toledo. Garajonay Na¬
tional Park. Old town of Cáceres. Cathedral,
Alcazar and Archivo de Indias, Seville.
Sri Lanka
Sacred city of Anuradhapura. Ancient city of
Polonnaruwa. Ancient city of Sigiriya.
Switzerland
Convent of St. Gall. Benedictine Convent of St.
John, Müstair. Old city of Berne.
Syrian Arab Republic
Ancient city of Damascus. Ancient city of Bosra.
Site of Palmyra. Ancient city of Aleppo.
Tunisia
Medina of Tunis. Site of Carthage. Amphitheatre
of El Djem. Ichkeul National Park. Punic town of
Kerkuane and its Necropolis.
Turkey
Historic areas of Istanbul. Göreme National Park
and rock sites of Cappadocia. Great Mosque and
Hospital of Divrigi. Hattusha. Nemrut Dag.
United Kingdom
Giant's Causeway and causeway coast. Durham
Castle and Cathedral. Ironbridge Gorge. Studley
Royal Park including ruins of Fountains Abbey.
Stonehenge, Avebury and associated sites. Castles
and Town Walls of King Edward in Gwynedd.
St. Kilda. Blenheim Palace. City of Bath. Ha¬
drian's Wall. Palace of Westminster, Westminster
Abbey and St. Margaret's Church.
United Republic of Tanzania
Ngorongoro Conservation Area. Ruins of Kilwa
Kisiwani and ruins of Songo Mnara. Serengeti
National Park. Selous Game Reserve. Kilimanja¬
ro National Park.
United States of America
Mesa Verde. Yellowstone. Grand Canyon Na¬
tional Park. Everglades National Park. Indepen¬
dence Hall. Redwood National Park. Mammoth
Cave National Park. Olympic National Park.
Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site. Great
Smoky Mountains National Park. La Fortaleza
and San Juan Historic Site, Puerto Rico. Statue of
Liberty. Yosemite National Park. Chaco Culture
National Historical Park. Monticello and Uni¬
versity of Virginia, Charlottesville. Hawaii Vol¬
canoes National Park.
Yemen Arab Republic
Old city of Sana'a.
Yugoslavia
Old city of Dubrovnik. Stari Ras and Sopocani.
Historical complex of Split with the Palace of
Diocletian. Plitvice Lakes National Park. Ohrid
Region and its Lake. Kotor and its Gulf. Durmi-
tor National Park. Studenica Monastery. Skocjan
Caves.
Zaire
Virunga National Park. Garamba National Park.
Kahuzi-Biega National Park. Salonga National
Park.
Zimbabwe
Mana Pools National Park, Sapi and Chewore
Safari Areas. Great Zimbabwe National Monu¬
ment. Khami Ruins National Monument.
States Parties to the World
Heritage Convention
The following States, in addition to
those mentioned in the List above, are
also Parties to the Convention Concern¬
ing the Protection of the World Cultural
and Natural Heritage: Afghanistan,
Antigua and Barbuda, Burkina, Burun¬
di, Cape Verde, the Central African Re¬
public, Chile, the Congo, Denmark, the
Dominican Republic, Finland, Gabon,
the Gambia, Guyana, Jamaica, Lao Peo¬
ple's Democratic Republic, Luxem-'
bourg, Madagascar, Maldives, Mali,
Mauritania, Monaco, Mozambique, Nic¬
aragua, Niger, Nigeria, Paraguay, the
Philippines, Qatar, Saint Christopher
and Nevis, Saudi Arabia, the Sudan,
Sweden, Thailand, Uganda, Viet Nam
and Zambia.
The emblem of the World Heritage Convention
symbolizes the interdependence of cultural
and natural properties: the central square
is a form created by man and the
circle represents nature, the two
being intimately linked. The emblem
is round like the world, but at the
same time it is a symbol of
protection
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Back cover
Serengeti National Park and
Ngorongoro Conservation
Area (United Republic of
Tanzania)
Serengeti National Park, 1.5
million hectares of savannah
and open woodland, contains
the world's largest herds of
grazing animals. The migration of wilde¬
beest, zebra and gazelle in May and June,
when they move from the central plains to
the water holes in the west of the Park, is a
wildlife spectacle second to none. In some
cases the caravans of animals, trailed by
their predators, can extend over 10 km. The
Park and the adjoining Ngorongoro Con¬
servation Area form the biggest wildlife
reserve on Earth. In the centre lies the
grandiose Ngorongoro Crater, an extinct
volcano 2,286 m above sea level at the rim,
15 to 20 km across and over 600 m deep. The
region has been home to generations of
Masai herders, whose cattle, sheep and
goats share pasture and water holes with a
rich variety of wildlife. Excavations in the
Olduvai Gorge, to the west of the Ngo¬
rongoro Crater, led to the discovery of
fossilized animal and human remains, in
particular those of Homo habilis, which
provide crucial evidence about man's evolu¬
tionary ancestry.
Chan Chan (Peru)
m
The spectacular ruins of this an¬
cient capital of the Chimú king¬
dom testify to the grandeur of a
vanished civilization. Around
1200 AD, the Chimú civilization succeeded
the Mochica culture in the Moche valley,
which was the centre of a vast empire
stretching from the Gulf of Guayaquil in
the north to Paramonga in the south. In
this arid area a sophisticated irrigation sys¬
tem channelled river water along an 80-km-
long canal, bringing a degree of fertility to
Chan Chan which it is hard to imagine
today. With an area of 20 km2, Chan Chan
was the largest city in pre-Columbian
America. The central zone is divided into 9
great rectangular compounds whose
straight parallel streets are enclosed by
earth ramparts. Each of these compounds,
which were doubtless inhabited by royal or
aristocratic families, was filled with temples,
houses, gardens and cemeteries grouped
around squares. The adobe walls are often
decorated with relief friezes depicting ma¬
rine deities. The Chimú were skilled crafts¬
men who produced excellent work in wood,
in textiles and in gold, silver and copper.
Chan Chan is threatened by 2 major prob¬
lems: looting, from which it has suffered for
centuries, and natural erosion which is at¬
tacking the fragile adobe walls. Conserva¬
tion work has been carried out on the fres¬
coes and wall paintings and in 2 of the
palaces. But the safeguard of the city will be
a continuing task calling for systematic
consolidation of the buildings. The archae¬
ological zone of Chan Chan was inscribed
on the List of World Heritage in Danger in
1986.
You too can contribute
to the safeguard
of the World Heritage
Although the World Heritage Fund is supported
essentially by States Parties, the World Heritage
Convention does not exclude and in fact encou¬
rages gifts or bequests from pub¬
lic or private organizations or from individuals.
You can play a part in the valuable work of th<
Convention by contributing to the Fund. Contri
butions may be sent to the following address:
The Secretariat,
World Heritage Committee,
Unesco,
7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris
in French francs to
Unesco Account (No. 0330-1/5-770.002-4)
Société Générale
Agence AG, Bureau FB
45, Avenue Kléber
75784 Paris Cedex 16
in United States dollars
a) by transfer to:
Unesco Account (No. 949-1-191558)
Chase Manhattan Bank, N.A.
International Money Transfer Division
1 New York Plaza
New York, N.Y. 10015
b) by cheque to the order of Unesco
(Account No. 949-1-191558) to be sent to:
Chase Manhattan Bank, N.A.
International Agencies Banking Unit
380 Madison Avenue
New York, N.Y. 10017
Please note that donations should be accompa¬
nied by a clear indication that they are contribu¬
tions to the World Heritage Fund.
Unesco World Heritage
Desk Diary 1989
now available
Tri-lingual: English/French/Spanish
54 colour photographs of sites and monuments on the
World Heritage List
Price: 64 French Francs; 10 US dollars
Proceeds from sales of the Desk Diary will go to the
World Heritage Fund. Orders may be sent to national
distributors of Unesco publications or to the Unesco
Press, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 35 languages by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
A selection in braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Nedael Khazen
Spanish edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos,
Miguel Labarca
Arabic edition : Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille edition:
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Georges Servat
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions:
Solange Belin
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggyjulien
Non-Headquarters editions
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefrallgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croáto-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder fora year's issues : 62 FF
Individual anieles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by : ( 1 )
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris ; (2)
University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691 , U.S.A.
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Imprimé en France (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : Cl -
Août 1988.
Photogravure-impression: Maury- Imprimeur S.A.
Z. I. route d'Etampes, 45330 Maiesherbes.
ISSN 004 1-5278
N°8-1988-CPD-88-l-459A
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The Ngorongoro Crater in the United Republic of Tanzania, above;
below, the ruins of Chan Chan in Peru.
(See descriptions page 39.)
]]>
</page>
</document>
