<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="081592eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
VOLUME III-No 10 PRICE : 10 Cents (U. S.), 6 Pence (U. K.), or 20 Francs (FRANCE).
UNITED NATIONS DAVY
October 24, 1950
"There shall be peace"
"There shall be peace. This has been decided. WE have
decided it-we, the peoples of the United Nations, who constitute
more than nine tenths of the people on the face of the earth.
For once, let us be impatient. Let us brush aside all the timi-
dities, the hesitancies of mere talk about the"hope"of men,
women and children to have the chance to live in peace. It has
been decided. There is more than talk and hope.
For, five years ago our DETERMINATION that there shall be peace
was written-written not only in ink but large and clear enough
in our faith and will to justify all the blood, sweat and tears that
had gone before. Five years ago, we said in our Charter, the
Charter of the United Nations, that we are :"DETERMINED to
save succeeding generations from the scourge of war."Now, five
years later, the slogan for United Nations Day-for the generation
of the United Nations, for the century of the United Nations-is :
"THERE SHALL BE PEACE."
But peace is not merely an absence of war-a refuge for cowards,
a cave for hermits, a playground for idlers-a kind of surrender
ih the face of the enemy.
Peace calls for heroes, who do more than hold their ground and
rest on their fading laurels. It comes from the power, the courage,
the intelligence of man, age-old weapons against the traditional
enemies of men-war, famine, pestilence, ignorance.
This is the kind of peace we are building-we the people of
the United Nations-five years after we signed the covenant we
call the Charter.
And of the new weapons we are using, the new tools we are
using, none is more important than the United Nations Programme
for Technical Assistance. For this programme will help in a great
task of peace-a difficult, yet entirely feasible task-nothing less
than the remaking of the world-in which men, women and
children may live in the reality of peace and with the sound hope
for a better life.
United Nations Technical Assistance in Haiti. Travelling on a UN Fellowship, Mr. Milord (right) studied modern
irrigation methods in France. Now he takes part in a major irrigation project which will give Haiti more land
for cultivation. This tiny Caribbean republic Is of special interest as a centre of the first comprehensive United
Nations experiment in technical assistance for under-developed countries.
NOVEMBER 1950
Courie
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-PAGE 2
A SCIENCE MUSEUM GOES ON TOUR
December appearance in Havana
next month, during a conference of
representatives of Unesco National
Commissions in the Western
Hemisphere.
Trip To The Stars
so far, the astronomy section of the
museum has proved to be one
of the biggest attractions.
There, a portable planetarium, which
can be viewed by as many as sixty
persons at a time, takes visitors on
a trip to the stars. (At the end of
its run, the planetarium folds up into
units no larger than a table.)
This astronomy section also inclu-
des photographs of such phenomena
as comets, sunspots and meteorites
as well as illustrated explanations of
the workings of the solar system and
of the giant telescopes used to study
it. Part of this section is devoted
to a telescope built by an amateur
astronomer to demonstrate that this
science can be appreciated and
enjoyed with simple equipment-the
kind that a schoolboy might cons-
truct.
The physics exhibit is the first to
greet the visitor, since it begins with
the beam of light broken on entering
the museum, setting the photo-
electric cell in operation and auto-
matically recording the visitor's
entrance. It displays operations in
mechanics, heat, sound, electricity
and electronics, optics and nuclear
physics.
Among the equipment which the
During its visit to Lima, Peru, the Unesco Travelling Science Museum was seen by up to
5. 000 people each day. One or its biggest attractions was the astronomy section (above)
whose exhibits included a portable planetarium.
THE National Library of Peru,
in the heart of Lima, created
a traffic jam early last month,
which was repeated every day for
more than two weeks. Outside the
library, the sidewalk was crowded
with adults and children. As they
filed past the entrance, they were
counted by a photo-electric cell,
clicking monotonously at a rate
which went as high as 5, 000 visitors
a day.
The attraction was a travelling
museum, intended to explain simply
the newest developments in science.
The story of crowds in front of the
National Library in Lima goes back
to Paris-to Unesco's Department
of Natural Sciences. There the idea
was first conceived of a prefabricated
museum, which could be crated, pla-
ced in a train or the hold of a ship
and then set up on short notice.
The purpose of the museum was to
take science out of the bewildering
terminology of the laboratory and
bring it to the public in Latin
America-both to adults and chil-
dren. Unesco's funds, however,
were limited, and the museum
became a reality only with the offer
of help from universities and science
organizations in the United States.
When, last August, the museum
had been stowed in Boston aboard a
ship bound for Callao, Peru, it repre-
sented the combined efforts of
Unesco, the Massachusetts Institute
of Technology, the Harvard College
Observatory and the Science Clubs
of America. Its construction was
carried out under the eyes of
Mrs. Christine Buechner, an official
of the National Research Council of
the United States.
The portable museum's first stop
was Lima, where it was shown under
the auspices of the Peruvian Minis-
try of Education. After the coun-
try's senate registered a vote of
thanks to Dr. Jaimes Torres Bodet.
U n e s e o's Director-General, the
museum moved on to Quito, capital
of Ecuador. It is scheduled for a
museum displays is a triple-axis
motordriven gyroscope which visitors
are invited to attempt to push off
balance. Then there is a Van de
Graaf generator, an electrostatic
machine that builds up high voltages
by charges carried on a moving belt.
This machine, which steps up the
speed of slow-moving ions (posi-
tively-charged particles) or electrons
(negatively-charged particles) is
often used by scientists to investigate
nuclear atomic structure or to pro-
duce high-power X-rays.
As a whole, the museum is desi-
gned to be understandable to children
and yet valuable to adults who have
some background in science.
Although there are simple models to
explain each principle, the texts
accompanying the display develop
the theories and the applications of
these principles.
This travelling science museum is
much more than an educational road
show. Its main objective is to give
youth in Latin America a good look
into the wonders of modern science
in the confidence that this will
encourage some of these boys and
girls to make science their life work
and thus to become the technicians
and the engineers their countries
need so urgently.
NEW PRICE FOR COURIER
IN U. S. AND CANADA
Due to increased costs, the
subscription price of the Courier
in the U. S. and Canada will be
increased from $1 to $1. 50. effec-
tive lanuary 1st. 1951. The single
issue price will correspondingly be
increased from 10 cents to 15 cents.
JUST over a year ago, an eminent
Brazilian educator described the
stat  of primary education in most
Latin American countries in the
following terms :
"Over a large part of the continent,
primary schooling is not only in-
adequate, it cannot even fulfil its allot-
ed task of helping to raise the commu-
nity's standard of living This explains
the people's, indifference to it, the poor
school attendance and teachers' lack of
social prestige and their low salaries. "
The educator, Professor Lourenco
Filho, of Brazil, was making the closing
speech at the inlet-American Seminar
on Literacy Campaigns and Adult Edu-
cation, whose work he had directed,
near Rio de Janeiro. In it he summed
The UNESCO COURIER is an international periodical devoted to the work
of UNESCO and to activities and developments throughout the world in edu-
cation, science and culture.
A full year's subscription (12 issues) costs only $1. 00 US., or 5/-or 200
French Francs.
SUBSCRIBE NOW ! Tell your friends about the UNESCO COURIER and
get them to subscribe too.
Write to our agent in your country listed below, or directly to UNESCO
House, 19, avenue KIeber, Paris, 16', France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana S-A., Alsina 500, Buenos-Aires.
Australia : H. A. Goddard Ltd, 255a, George St., Sydney.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, Graben 27, Wien I.
Barbados : SPCK Bookshop (Regional Office) Caribbean area, Broad St., Bridgetown.
Belgium : Librairie encyclopedique, 7, rue du Luxembourg, Bruxelles IV.
Brazil : Livraria Agir Editora, Rua Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 3291, Rio-de-Janeiro.
Canada : The Ryerson Press, 299, Queen Street West, Toronto.
Chile : Libreria Lope de Vega, Moneda 924, Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera 9a, 1791. Bogota.
Cuba : La Casa Belga, René de Smedt, O'Reitly, Havana.
Czechoslovakia : Orbis, Narodni. 37. Praha I.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6, Norregade, Copenhagen.
Egypt : Librairie James Cattan, 118, rue Emad el Dine, Cairo.
France : Maison du Livre Francis, 4, rue Felibien, Paris (6'). (Booksellers Only)'.
Great Britain : H. M. Stationery Office : London : York House, Kingsway (Retail Counter
Service) : P. O. Box 569, London S. E. I. (Post orders}.-Manchester 2 : 39-41 King
Street.-Edinburgh 2 : 13a Castle Street.-Cardiff : 1 St Andrew's Crescent.-
Greece : Eleftheroudakis, Librairie Internationale, Athens.
Hungary :"Ibusz"Akademia-u. 10. Budapest V.
India : Oxford Book and Stationery Co, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Israel : Leo Blumstein, Book Shop, 35 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv.
Italy : Messaggerie Italian, Via Lomazzo, 52, Milano.
Lebanon and Syria : Librairie Universelle, Avenue des Francis, Beirut.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo Sierra 16, Mexico DF.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhotf, Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
Norway : AjS Bokhjornet, StoJt. ingsplass 7, Oslo.
Pakistan : Thomas 6. Thomas, Fort Mansions, Frere Road. Karachi 3.
Peru : Libreria Internacional del Peru. S. A. Gir6n de la Uni6n, Lima.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co, Inc., Corner Tanduay and Vergara Streets,
Quiapo, Manila.
Portugal : Uniao Portuguesa de Imprensa, 198 Rue de S. Bento, 3° Esq., Lisbon.
Sweden : C. E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2. Stockholm.
Switzerland : Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette, 469, avenue de 1'Independance. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
Union of South A/rica : Van Schaik's Bookstore, Pty. Ltd., P. O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United States of America : Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, : New York
27, N. Y.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperación Cientifica. Avenida Agraciada 1875 JJontevideo.*For France : Retail sales : Unesco Sales Service, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris (16').
up the. findings of a seminar group
which dealt with problem of primary
education and which reported :"its
quantitative and qualitative deficiencies
are one of the principal causes of illite-
racy on the continent."
Last month, solutions to sone of the
tremendous difficultie facing primary
schools in t. he Am ericas, where
J 9, 000, 000 children of school age are
deprived of schools, were again being
suugtlt hy a group of educators, this
Time, at a Seminar entirely devoted to
primary education.
The Seminar, whicll was formally
opened in Monlevideo on October 2nd.
sponsored by ttie Covernment of Uru-
guay. the Organization of American
States and Unesco. was in reality a
continuation of work done by the 1949
Seminar in Rio.
Three Vital Questions
A LTHOL'GIl most discussions concern-ed Latin American problems, ex-
perts had come from other parts
of tile world to discuss those common
to their own areas and to contribute
their knowledge and experience to the
work of the various study groups.
Unesco contributed extensive inform-
ation on primary education in non-Ame-
rican countries and sent t. o the Seminar
four dislingnisllcd specialisls.- Mr. Ro-
her. Dottrens. Director of the Geneva
Institut universitaire des Sciences de
L'Education, Professor P. Rosselo, As-
sistant Director of the international Bu-
reau of Education. My. GiovanniVozzcr,
Secretary of the Halian Commission for for
Education'nail Reconstruction, and Mr. Fa-
ker Akel, Inspector of Schools and Pro-
fessor of Education.
Tile seminar study groups had before
Ihem live main themes for discussion :
the organization of elementary school
systems ; plans, curricula and methods :
universa), free and compulsory educa-
tion ; the education of teachers, and
textbooks and schools materials.
Some of the vital questions for which
these educators were seeking the most
effective answer were cited by Unes-
co's Director-General. M. Jaimc Torres
Bodel. in a message to the Seminar.
I. Torres Bodet said :"... The following
three problems of primary education
deserve, I feel, special consideration by
Latin American educationalists : How
may the liberacy campaign be speeded
up without relaxing effort to introduce
the necessary reforms in primary school
curricula? How should curricula be
varied to suit regional conditions, and to suit
more nationally adapted to the needs
of rural communities? How is the prin-
ciple of compulsory education to be
made a reality? ?
"In short, illiteracy must be resolute-
ly stamped out, and living standards
gradually raised, throuth a programme
in which eaually effective provision is
made for primary education and for
literacy campaigns..."
FIRST REGIONAL CONFERENCE OF UNESCO NATIONAL
COMMISSIONS TO OPEN IN HAVANA NEXT MONTH
THE first Regional Conference of UnescoNational Commissi s-the co-operat-
ing bodies set up by Unesco's Member
States to associate their peoples with the
work of the Organization-will open in
Havana, Cuba, early next month.
Representatives of National Commis-
sions in nearly 20 countries in the Western
Hemisphere will concentrate their efforts
on educational, scientific and cultural pro-
blems in Latin America, and Unesco's
possible contribution to their solution.
The Conference, aided by Unesco's
Regional Office in the Western Hemis-
phere, at Havana, aims to make Unesco's
programme and work better known among
the general public and intellectual leaders
of Latin America. It will also work to foster
the growth and help perfect the working
methods of National Commissions there.
In addition, detailed studies will be
made of subjects in Unesco's programme
that are of special interest to Latin America.
These include Fundamental Education,
Technical Assistance, the organization
of work of the National Commissions
and the Dissemination of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights. This last
subject will be of particular significance,
as"Human Rights Day"will be celebrated
in all parts of the world on December 10th
- two days after the Conference opens.
Working parties will study this and other
conference agenda subjects and their
findings and recommendations will be
submitted to plenary sessions, for prac-
tical action to be taken by the National
Commissions.
A Committee of Experts will also dis-
cuss Unesco's contribution to international
exchange of persons programmes, basic
aspects of exchanges of persons and
recommendations for the programme in
Latin America.
The Conference will end on December
20th with the adoption of a work plan for
the Latin American National Commissions
for 1951.
IN LATIN AMERICA
EDUCATORS SEEK ANSWERS TO PROBLEMS
OF PRIMARY SCHOOLS IN THE AMERICAS
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Page 3-UNESCO COURIER
"J'wo great postulates-
solidarity, in the face of
aggression and mutual aid for
the prosperity of all."
Jaime TORRES BODET
Director-General
of Unesco
ft IVE years ago today,the United Nations
Organization was
born into a war-torn world
- a lodestar for the hopes
of peoples still mourning the
death of more than twenty
million men. The purpose
of the new body was to
substitute for a tradition shl1
"... United in hatred
of war and in hope
for a better lire..."
0
"WE THE PEOPLES OF THE UNITED NATIONS..."World citizens
of tomorrow read the preamble to the United Nations Charter. Every hour,
every day, the work of the United Nations and its Specialized Agencies goes
on all over the world-constructive work-work for peace that seldom gets
into the headlines...
our own troubled hearts to which we
must oppose à true answer which will
satisfy at once the claims of man's rea-
son and his hopes of a less unhappy
future. That answer already exists as a
principle : in a world tempted to despair
of all human activities, the United Na-
tions offer men the chance of ensuring
the peace in freedom under the law
which is alone consistent with their di-
gnity. That answer, which. is in con-
flict with all the forces opposing 0
world organization, demands active
assent to the two great postulates of the
United Nations-solidarity in the face
of aggression and mutual aid for the
prosperity of all.
If we wish to achieve total security,
these two postulates are indivisible.
The mutual interdependence of the
peoples, at all levels of their activities,
links the fates of all countries. Yet that
circumstance might open the way to
abuse 01 power by the strongest if
there were no rule of law to impose
upon all men the moral judgment of
mankind. Thus solidarity must be ex-
pressed in a system of internationai
law and in effective guarantees of se-
curity.
SELF-FULFILMENT UNDER
LAW AND EQUITY
NEVERTHELESS, any solidarity bas-ed purely on defence of the sta-
tus quo would run the risk of
crystallizing those same conditions in
which the weak and unfortunate feel,
not without reason, that their legitimate
aspirations are being thwarted. Such
a solidarity as this, founded only to
perpetuate a static situation, could not
withstand the irresistible march of his-
tory. Seeking only to stabilize what is
by definition liable to change, it would
be doomed to violent disruption unless
balanced by that other principle which
I have described as mutual aid bet-
ween the nations.
It is not a question of abolishing
rights ; rather must their enjoyment be
extended to the largest possible num-
ber of human beings. It is mutual aid
between the nations which will ena-
ble the weaker fully to play their pro-
per part in the economic, political and
moral organization of peace. In the
United Nations system, while political
organs such as the Security Council
guard the peace, it is the task of the
Economic and Social Council and the
Specialized Agencies-the World
Health Organization, the Food and
Agriculture Organization, the Interna-
tional Labour Organization, and Unes-
co-to make this peace more fruit-
ful for all. The object of these bodies
is the same ; to ; ajford every man the
means of free self-fulfilment under a
system of law and equity to which all
have free access, in which all have
their place.
These two complementary principles
of collective security and mutual aitl
between the nations are not mere sub-
Jects for academic oratory ; in the cour-
se of this very year there have been
two outstanding demonstrations of
their effectiveness.
The principl. e of collective security
was challenged by armed attack
against the Republic of Korea,. Never
have the United Nations and the Spe-
cialized Agency. yes reacted with such
singleness of mind. Each organization
took steps to answer the victim's cry
for aid ; to help restore peace and, each
in its own sphere, to ensure that, when
peace returned, that peace should ha-
ve its full human significance. It may
be that all the general public has noti-
ced is news of the battles in South
Korea : nevertheless, what really gives
to the sacmice of the United Nations
soldiers its true meaning is the hope
that, when peace comes, health, work,
culture and education will be not mi-
nor considerations, but matters of pri-
me importance, and the fact that even
now the Specialized Agencies are tak-
ing practical steps to improve existing
conditions as soon as the time for
reconstruction comes.
ARMED RESISTANCE
IS NOT ENOUGH
ALMOST simultaneously with theecurity Council's decisions on
Korea, the principle of mutual aid
was strikingly demonstrated when the
Conference on the United Nations pro-
gramme for Technical Assistance, with
its 54 participating countries, approved
the allocation of more than twenty mil-
lion dollars for the economic advance-
ment of under-developed countries.
Here we are no longer concerned with
the restoration of peace on the princi-
ple of collective security, but with rais-
ing the standard of life of the peoples
by helping them to develop their hu-
man and material resources.
It is obvious that the bond of union
between activities so different in them-
selves must be a view of life derived
from a particular concept of mankind.
We are convinced that man will find
the way to self-fulfilment only in a
community living in freedom under the
law, and striving for social progress,-
in other words, seeking always to
excel its own past. That is the order
which the United Nations are endea-
vouring to establish in ja World
of greed and passion. That is the order
which Unesco would, through educa-
tion, science and culture, wish to see
reign in the minds of men and in the
practice of their lives.
Most of the criticism directed against
the United Nations and their Speciali-
zed Agencies springs from a defeatist
attitude towards the heavy responsibi-
lity laid on twentieth-century man to
strive for a united world. Indifference
to aggression is unthinkable, but it is
just as wrong to imagine that armed
resistance is enough in itself to avoid
or repel aggression. The difficulties
which the United Nations must inevi-
tably encounter can only arouse the
spirits of all men of goodwill. For this
victory they must not spare their
strength. Nevertheless what we must
recall to the minds of the peoples in
such days as these is not merely the
fact that it is necessary to guarantee
collective security, but also the prin-
ciple which makes such a guarantee
essential. That principle is the one
which brought the United Nations and
the Specialized Agencies into being
- that peace, to be enduring, must
be based on right-and that the
rights which ensure the liberty and
dignity of man must be won and de-
fended, under collective security by
mutual aid.
Let us hope that, in the peaceful fu-
ture to which Unesco is dedicated, the
balance of these two forms of human
solidarity may be preserved. The one
is as necessary as the other for the
safeguarding of peace and for our
common progress.
UNITED NATIONS APPOINT
KOREAN RELIEF COMMITTEE
The United Nations Economic and So-cial Council adopted on October 16,
an Australian resolution appointing
a Temporary Committee of seven members
of the Council to examine the probable
needs of Korea for relief and rehabiliation.
The countries represented on the Com-
mittee when it held its first meeting on
October 18th were : Australia, Belgium,
Chile, Denmark, India, Pakistan and the
United States.
The United Nations has also received a
proposal from the United States for the
appointment of a director-general to be
in charge 0/Korean'economic recons-
truction. According to this proposal, the
director-general would head a new body
to be known as the Korean Rehabilitation
Agency. This would be independent of
other U. N. Commissions and would be
completely responsible for the economic
reconstruction of the country.
Among his other tasks, its director-
general would be required to determine
the types of goods and services required
for the aid programme, to obtain sea
transport for these materials and to advise
Korean authorities on the allocation of the
aid.
IT is now five years since the
United Nations Charter set forth
the principles of a new world
order. The past twelve months have
been dangerous and difficult for the
nations and the peoples of the world ;
a future of danger and difficulty
confronts us all. And yet the United
Nations still stands ; the forces of
Member states have rallied around
its flag to turn back armed aggres-
sion ; the Fifth Session of the General
Assembly has begun with an unpre-
cedented demonstration of purpose to
work effectively for peace.
It is this purpose to work for
peace by every means available
which-coupled with enduring
patience-is needed to see us
through. I have never imagined
that there was an easy way. A year
ago on the anniversary of the United
Nations I said that the United
Nations way is a slow and often
discouraging way to go about the
work of building a peaceful world,
but there is no short-cut.
The stake is the future of a : t
mankind, the future of alL cultures
and alL civilizations and alL the varied
ways of life which men have deve-
loped to meet their needs and their
circumstances. If we succeed, the
future is limitless in its possibilities
for growth and for good ; if we fail
there will be no future worth the
having for any of us. We must not
fail.
NEXT TO PEACE-
PROSPERITY
NEXT to the problem of peace,
but allied to it, is the problem
of raising the living standards
of the many millions throughout the
world who now exist in poverty.
This problem, too, we must solve if
we are to live together in amity and
with a clear conscience. The United
Nations in the past year has made a
start towards solving this problem
in the expanded programme of
technical assistance ; it is only a
beginning, but a good one. We must
follow through ; again we must not
fail.
I have said that"we"must not fail
in patient working for peace ; in
patient working for higher living
standards. By"we"I do not mean
only the governments of the Member
states of the United Nations, or the
members of the Secretariat, although
certainly they are included in the
obligation. By"we"I mean all of
us, all men and women of good will.
The United Nations is our United
Nations, its strength derives in the
last analysis from all the peoples of
the world who are united in hatred
of war and in hope for a better life
for everyone, everywhere.
IJNITED NATIONS DAY, O[TOBER 24, 1950
Trygve
LIE
Secretary
General
of the
United
Nations
tcjnted by trickery and violence. a system of solidarity
and mutual aid mindful both of the established order
and of the new demands for its social transformation.
Since then peace in freedom under the law has
become the prey and the victim of conflicting propa-
ganda ; these terms, expressing the idea, us for which
so many lives were aiven. hcwe today become peri-
lously ambiguous. A great wave of disappointment ha, ;
swept over the world, begetting doubt, fear and
despair.
We cannot allow belief in the inevitability of war to
paralyse action in favour of peace. Education, science
and culture, all the forces and all the achievements of
the human mind demand that we fight against any
such abdication of the spirit. It is a myth fathered by
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 4
THE KING OF THE BAMOUNS AND HIS ALPHABET
THE rich complexity of
civilization in advanced
countries is frequently
advanced as an argu-
ment to demonstrate the basic
superiority of the"white
race"in character and intel-
ligence."Have the Negroes
or the Indians produced a
Plato, a Shakespeare, a Des-
cartes, a Newton ? is the
question which has greeted
even the most convincing
scientific evidence of the ba-
sically equal abilities of all
branches of the human family.
To compare such varied cul-
tures in order to prove that
the Negroes or Indians are
congenitally inferior to the
whites is a process of reason-
ing without V"e. The fun-
uaiiientl discoveries oh 7.'hich
our whole civilization has
been built-fire, weaving,
pottery, agriculture, rearing of
stock-were made by men
whose skin pigmentation is
today unknown, but whose
stage of development was
certainly far behind that of
the peoples of Africa or lame-
by
Dr. Alfred Metraux
writing and instructed his
people in its use, should help
ill-informed sceptics to over-
come their doubts about the
creative spirit of the Negro
race. The details of the
following story are taken from
an article written for a scien-
tific journal by the French
scientist Maurice Delafosse.
In 1899, when the Germans
occupied his kingdom, Njoya
needed to communicate with
his village chiefs and with
those of his people attached to
the German Command, but he
; jid not want the Germans to
know what'was in his letters.
He therefore decided to invent
a writing that the Europeans
could not understand. Call-
ing together his head men, he
explained his plan and asked
their assistance in finding
signs for each of the words of
thus creating a syllabic writ-
ing.
These signs acquired a pu-
rely phonetic and conventional
value, instead of suggesting
objects or ideas. For instance,
a calabash (ka) was first
shown by the drawing of a
gourd ; later this same but
simplified drawing was used
to signify the syllable"ka..
which forms part of many
words.
In a few years, Njoya had
advanced from picture-writ-
ing to a phonetical system-
achieving what the Egyptians
accomplished, and then in a
very imperfect fashion, only
after centuries of stumbling
efforts. For a time, King
Njoya's system of writing re-
mained half-pictorial, h a I f-
phonetic, yet all the while the
syllabic side was nevertheless
being perfected.
Five yes. later, the king,
influenced this time ùy obser-
vations made in a missionary
school, introduced a new re-
form by giving his system a
purely alphabetic character.
rica. One may even say,
without wanting to sound
paradoxical, that a savage
living in an isolated region
and provided with few cultural
advantages, required far more
genius to discover the bow or
the boomerang than inventors
today in their work to split
the atom and to perfect the
machines which are the pride
of this modern age.
Each new discovery is the
product of people engaged in
simultaneous research, who
frequently arrive at identical
results at the same time. La-
boratories and research wor-
kers collaborate so closely in
this twentieth century that
individual discoveries are be-
coming increasingly rare and
difficult to achieve. The pro-
g r e s s of our civilization
indeed relies on this vast
network of reciprocal contacts
and on this collective research
performed by teams of experts.
To evolve a new technique
from nothing, as one might
say, is obviously a much slower
and more difficult process.
The Unknown lit-roes
C CENTURIES ago, a poetsadly recalled the her s
who had died unknown,
because there was no Homer
at that time to record their
valorous exploits for future
generations. One could spe-
culate on the number of great
men who lived among the pri-
mitive races but of whom we
know nothing simply because,
lacking the written word, all
remembrance of them has
been lost. If we study ancient
chronicles, missionary ac-
counts, books of travel and
works of modern ethnogra-
phers, we can discover an
amazing gallery of talented
men, even men of genius,
among the so-called"inferior
races", who have been so
lightly dubbed"the white
man's burden".
A man's accomplishments
are limited by his cultural
background. The story of
King Njoya of the Bamouns,
in the Cameroons, who invent-
ed, by himself, a system of
the local language.
The system of writing de-
vised by the king in collabo-
ration with his counsellors,
began as a picture language
in symbols, each sign repre-
senting either the drawing of
a definite object or"the ma-
terialised shape evoked by an
abstract idea". Each s i g n
thus corresponded to a word,
but without relation to the
number of syllables in this
word.
A Stroke CM Genius
SEVERAL years later, Njoyaconceived an idea that
was truly a stroke of
genius. Words were no longer
to be represented by drawings,
but the same drawings were
to represent groups of sounds,
He decided to keep only 80 of
the 350 original signs, and
those that represented the
first ten numbers. He stipu-
lated that"each of the alpha-
bet signs should represent one
sound only, the numerical
signs keeping, in addition, the
value of figures".
Frankly speaking, this last
step towards alphabetic writ-
ing was by no means perfect.
The royal phonetician did not
succeed in breaking entirely
free from syllabism, so the
phonetic value of the 80 signs
was not always clearly shown.
Aware of the faults in his
system, he made several
attempts to simplify it. In
1916, the year when his writ-
ing-method was the subject of
the story here outlined, his
system seemed well on the
Native kings. such as this West African ruler, must exercise judgement
and statecraft or the same kind as heads of state in larger and more
"advanced"countries, though the problems are different. But, men like
these are little known to the world, chiefly for l<lck 0/Boswells. It was
a native'ruler. Niova. King 0/the Bamouns. for example. who. with a
superlative use of intelligence and initiative invented a form of picture
writing, and within ten years transformed it into an efficient alphabet.
The evolution or our own and similar alphabets took many centuries.
way to becoming purely alpha-
betic. The signs bore less and
less relation to primitive pic-
ture-symbols and became let-
ters with increasingly simple
outlines.
A Royal Teacher
ONCE having evolved amethod of writing, this
wise man launched a
large-scale campaign to teach
the alphabet to his people.
He bought slates from the
whites and personally taught
pupils who, in turn, became
teachers. The period of ins-
truction over, the king conti-
nued to correspond with them
and this interchange of letters
kept alive their interest. By
the middle of 1907, more than
600 of his subjects knew how
to read and write. Njoya
formed offices of administra-
tion, a public records depart-
ment and a Registrar of re-
ceipts and expenses.
Attempts may be made to
belittle the genius of Njoya by
stating that he probably ob-
tained the idea of writing
from the Arabs or the whites.
But this in no say detracts
from the significance of his
discovery. He may have
known that the whites used
written symbols to communi-
cate with each other, but he
certainly could have known
nothing of the method. His
own system originated out of
his native intelligence and in-
itiative. Let us also remember
that cutting through time and
tradition he achieved results
in a few years that other sys-
tems of writing known to us
today took centuries and even
thousands of years to attain.
About the middle of the
19th century, another Negro,
Momuru Doalu Bukere of the
Vai tribe in Liberia, invented
a system of writing which won
a certain fame. Based on the
pictorial writing used by his
tribe, he gave a phonetic value
to the signs. Today, thousands
of natives still use this system
invented by the"noble and
modest"Momuru Doalu Bu-
kere.
The story of King Njoya was
deliberately chosen for this
article because documents are
available, and a study of them
enables us to follow Njoya's
line of reasoning. Many
examples of talent, sometimes
of genius, could have been
cited among primitive tribes.
A great deal could be said of
the Maya Indians of Central
America, who, entirely removed
from outside influences, had
already-between two and
three thousand years ago-
discovered the zero and given
a positional value to figures.
The so-called"savage"or
"barbarian"state does not
originate from any congenital
inability. It is simply one
transitory form of culture
among others, equally trans-
itory. Neither primitive nor
advanced civilizations have
explored the full possibilities
of mankind. One thing that
seems certain, however, is the
statement in the Declaration
on Race published by Unesco,
which affirms that :"the
range of mental capacities in
all ethnic groups is much the
same."
TilE development. of social
H sciences during the last
fins years holds as rich
a promise'f, it' mankind today as
did natural sciences at the
beginning of the last century.
Man is alarmed by the bitter-
ness and anguish, which go with
the transition from one form of
civilization to another and
demands to know if science can
help him to understand the
laws which govern the complex
relationships between and
within different societies and
thus to control the great
changes of our epoch.
The role of the social sciences
within Unesco has been con-
ceived to answer the specific
aims upheld hy the Organiz-
ation. All activities must be
t-pccificaUy directed to serve
the cause of peace within the
international framework. To
serve these two conditions has
been the aim of the Department
of Social Sciences.
It is now time to draw prat-
ical conclusions from research
carried out over three years
with the collaboration of scient-
ific organizations and eminent
special1sls. The sum total of
this knowledge offers a rational
basis for the recommenda-
tions that L'nesco proposes to
place before governments and
non-governmental organizations
anxious to preserve peace.
Tile programme, to be sub-
mitted to Unesco's Executive
Board this month, marks a
definite step forward. It is
proposed that L'nesco inves-
tigate the scientific methods
and techniques which offer the
best means for overcoming cer-
lain existing tensions.
Hundreds of governmental
or private agencies in many
countries are striving to abate
racial prejudices and to fight
the discriminatory measures
which result from them. So-
ciologists and psychotogists, for
their part, suggest new ways
by which the energies at pre-
sent wasted in fruitless fighting
can be directed to constructive
ends. Groups and individuals
continue their efforts in diffe-
rent dircctions without refe-
rence to the experiences of
their neighbours. To mal, e
these methods more widely
known, to assess their efu-
ciency and encourage the use
of those which pruve the best,
is one of the ta"k"which fal1s
to Unesco.
Social tensions are fed by
wrong ideas based on irralionàl
beliefs or outmoded scientific
interpretations. The authority
that its international character
gives Unesco, enables it to
undertake a campaign to put
within the reach of the masses
the resu1ts achieved bv scient.-
ists in their studv of racial
problems and the effect of
the discriminatory measures
against minorities.
Unesco played an important
part in the drafting of the Uni-
versal Declaration of Human
Rights. It is, therefore, mo-
ra) ty responsible to uphold and
disseminate these rights which
it. helped to formulate. Unesco
must fight racism and all forms
of social discrimination, in
confurmity with the spirit and
lelter of its Constitution.
Unesco is making an impor-
tant contribution to the United
Nations broad programme of
technical assistance to help
economically under--developed
countries to enjoy the benefits
of science and industry. \gain
it becomes the responsibility of
t. he social sciences to bear in
mind the human factor in the
transition from one type of
economv to another. MaterIal
developments must harmonise
with the cultural and social
chart's which wi1l inevitably
result. Unesco will play a
useful role if it helps prevent
a too sudden dislocation of
cultures, with its aftermath of
suffering and squandering of
energy and goodwi)).
H can be foreseen that, in
a fevr years, new states will
he added to the already large
family of existing ones. These
states will have to prepare,
with as little delay as possible,
a complex syslem of institu-
tions, without whicll they
cannot survive in the modern
world. The adoption of enti-
rety new organizations and
procedures will provoke inter-
nal anguish and violent fen-
sions. Cnesco's experience in
this field wi1l perhaps be
turned to good account by
those states who accept the
co-operation which will then
be offered to them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
"ECONOMIC UNDER-DEVELOPMENT"-Enemy Of Man :
ECONOMISTS were the first to use the phrase"under-
developed areas". Yet as a definition solely in the
language of monetary exchange-in dollars, pounds, pesos,
rupees or gourdes-it is grossly inadequate. A better
definition would have to include the overtones of graphic
descriptions of famines, epidemics ; of unceasing and un-
rewarding labour, of the plight of hundreds of millions of
human beings, prevented by ignorance from finding a way
out of their misery. Statistics fail to give these overtones of
tragedy that alone can provide an adequate definition. Yet
statistics are used here for their graphic simplicity.
In 1939, a survey was made
of fifty-three nations on all
the world's continents These
countries were divided into
three groups ; the first was
of fifteen nations with a per
capita annual income of more
than $200 ; the second, ten
countries, with a per capita
annual income of between
$100 and $200 ; the third,
twenty-eight countries, with a
per capita annual income less
than $100. The first group
made up one-fifth of the
world's population ; the second,
one-sixth ; the third, making
about two-thirds of the world
people, was co-terminous with
the"under-developed areas"
The Yawning Gap
THIS was before a tremend-ous war which wid ed
the gap between the high-
est and the lowest. Here are
some further differences :
1. Life expectancy at birth
in the first group was sixty-
three years,"Under-developed
areas"showed, when figures
were available, an average of
forty years, in some cases fall-
ing as low as twenty-seven
years.
2. Out of every 100, 000 per-
sons in the first group, sixty-
four died of tuberculosis
annually. In the third and
largest group, the rate was 333.
3. In the first group, less
than five per cent of the
population were unabie to read
and write. In the"under-
developed"countries, the it-
literacy rate averaged 78 per
cent. Eighty per cent of the
world's literate people lived in
countries which made up only
40 per cent of the world's
population.
4. It has been estimated
that a man needs a diet cont-
aining 1, 800 calor'es as a vital
minimum for life. In the first
group, the average food supply
was 3. 000 calories ; in the last
it was 2, 150 calories, a slim
margin against poor harvests
or insect plagues.
Hunger And Ignorance
THE shortage of doctors andteac ers was greatest in
the regions where they
were most needed. In the
relatively healthy countries ofthe first group, there was
more than one physician for
every 1, 000 persons. In the
last group, there was only one
for every 6, 000. The countries
with less than five per cent of
illiteracy had almost four
elementary schoolteachers for
every 1. 000 persons. Those
where illiteracy was as high
as 90 per cent had less than
two elementary schoolteachers
for every 1, 000 persons-less
than half.
In food production, the story
was similar. The hungriest
peoples, partly through lack of
technical knowledge produced
the least food. In the first
group of countries, wheat
fields were as high as forty
bushels per acre in the period,
1935-39 ; in the third group,
the figure fell as low as eleven
bushels. Properly cultivated,
an acre of rice land was made
to yield-as a national aver-
age-seventy-six bushels, but
in countries where rice was
the staple diet, production fell
as low as twenty-six bushels.
Human Realities
MECHANICAL energy- the greatest liberator
of man from drudgery-
was developed in few countries
and was pitifully absent in
precisely the regions where it
was most needed. In the first
group, the average person had
26. 6 horse-power hours a day
at his command ; in the last,
he had 1. 2.
These facts and figures-
horsepower hours, teachers per
1, 000 persons, bushels per
acre, life expectancy-con-
tribute to a definition of
under-development. But the
human realities are more
eloquent. A phrase like"life-
expectancy"has echoes of
tragedy in a nation which,
while trying to increase its
standard of living, finds that
disease carries off its popula-
THE CHILDREN WHO WAIT-AND HOPE. These
children are symbolic of hundreds of millions of human
beings who, in misery and suffering, wait and hope for
the chance of a new life. Most of them are to be found
in the"under-developed"areas, where two thirds of the
world's population live and where poverty, malnutrition
and starvation, disease and ignorance are the common
condition. Today, their hope lies in the promise offered
by the United Nations Expanded Programme of Techni-
cal Assistance-the first great international attack on
poverty and its related Ills.
tion."Teachers per 1, 000" is
a very immediate problem to a
young nation building for the
future."Horsepower hours"
translate into money for
development or the lack of it.
All these conditions continue
to exist now. But what is
new and encouraging is the
fact that they have now been
recognized as a world problem
which requires a world solution.
"TECHNICAL-ASSISTANCE"-A Weapon For Man
WHEN a member of a family falls a family falls ill. it doctor is called.
\Vhen a child reaches school age, he is taken to the
W class oom.
These simple sentences are statements of fact, however.
only if an individual or a community has the money to pay
for the services, and if the persons with the right qualifications
to perform them can be found. For a whole country, the money
needed may amount to millions of dollars or pounds. The
persons with the proper training and education may be
thousands of miles away. A rich country can get what and
who it needs, if not at home then abroad. But where can a
poor country find an expert on the newest technique in
insecticides or a man qualified to run a soil research laboratory
And how will he be paid ?
One important form of mu-
lual technical assistance among
nations has already been
suecpssfully in operation either
on a Regional or on a bi-
lateral basis, through publie
and private agencies, and
increasingly through the United
Nations and a number of the
Specialized Agencies.
In December, 1948, the
United Nations General As-
sembly voted the modest sum
of $'288, 000 for technical
assistance, mainiy through
fellowships and expert advice.
In March of the following year.
the UN Economic and Social
Council instructed the Secre-
tax'-General to work out an
expanded programme of tech-
nical assistance.
Four Basic Conditions
TilE next step in the de-velopment of technical
assistance as a major
objective of the UN was a
report drawn up for the Council
by representatives of the UN's
8peeialized. Agencies. They
outlined an international
scheme for technical aid In
agriculture, transport, industry,
labour, education, finance,
health and welfare. And to
carry out the new programme,
the Council formulated a set of
operational conditions. These
points were emphasized :
l. It would be a Joint, co-
operation programme for ae-
sistance In economic develop-
ment, given only on the
request of the aountry eonMrn-
ed ;
2. The assistance would be
designed to increase productiv-
ity in fields where benefits
could be distributed to the
entire population ;
3. The government receiving
asslstanoe would assume part
of the costs ; (in practice as
high as 50 per cent) ;
4, The assistance would not be a
means of foreign political or
economic interference with the
domestlo affairs of the country,
receiving it.
The Council also created the
framework of the administra-
tive structure of the pro-
Tile delegate of Liberia--
I am authorized by my
Government to pledge the sum
of $8,000.
The delegate of Ceylon--
We regret that we cannot
ourselves make a very large
monetary contribution. My
Government has instructed me
to say that it will contribute a
sum in Ceylon currency equi-
valent to $15, 000.
Fifty Nations'Fund
THE money poured in - in-shillings, afgha is, pesos,
sucres. cruzeiros, dollars,
lempiras, dinars, ilorins,
pounds, francs, sols, rupees,
and other currencies-to
make the total of $20, 012, 500.
The majority of the nations
contributing were the very
ones which had the greatest
need for aid.
The 50 counlries pledging
funds were Afghanistan, Ar-
gentina, Australia, Austria,
Belgium, Bolivia, Brazil, Burma,
Canada, Ceylon. Chile, China,
Colombia, Costa Rica, Cuba,
Denmark, Ecuador, Egypt,
Salvador, Ethiopia, France,
Greece, Haiti, Honduras, India,
Indonesia, Iran, Israel Italy,
Korea, Lebanon, Liberia,
Luxembourg, Mexico, Monaco,
Netherlands, New Zealand,
Norway, Pakistan Philippines.
Sweden, Switzer and, Syria,
Turkey, the United Kingdom,
the United States, Uruguay,
Venezuela, Yemen and Yugo-
slavia.
The money has now been
allocated to the United Nations
and its Specialized Agencies In
the following manner :
per cent
United Nations........ 23
Food and Agriculture Or-
ganization.......... 29
World Health Organiza-
tion 22
-UNESCO 14
International Labour Or-
ganization......... 11
International Civil Avia-
tion Organization.... 1
Unesco's share, therefore, is
$2, 300. 000 to cover technical
assistance activities for econo-
mic development, undertaken
by the Organization up to
December, 1951.
In July of 1950, the Technical
Assistance Board reported that
it had received requests from
fift. y-seven countries : some
under the normal programme
01 the UN and its agencies,
others under the expanded
technical assistance scheme.
ON MARCH 4, 1949, THE ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL
COUNCIL OF THE UNITED NATIONS adopted a
resolution requesting"... the Secretary-General in con-
sultation with the heads of the interested specialized
agencies... to prepare a report setting forth : 1. A compre-
hensive plan for an expanded co-operative programme
of technical assistance for economic development..."
Thus was the signal given for the preparation of the
vast programme which M. Trygve Lie, U. N. Secretary-
General, has described as"wnat should become and
can become one of the world's greatest achievements
for lasting peace and for the social progress and better
standards of life proclaimed in the Preamble to the Char-
ter of the United Nations."
gramme, is a manner designed
to avoid duplication and wasted
effort. It decided that the UN
would itself take care of
requests which did not fall
within the specific provinces of
its Specialized Agencies, such
a. s industrial development and
transport. And it proposd
the formation of a Technical
Assistance Board, made up of
representatives of the UN's
agencies, to co-ordinate the
programme.
The Council's proposals were
submitted to the fourth session
of the UN General Assembly.
They were unanimously ap-
proved on November 16, 1949.
Spirit Of Generosity
The next step was to financethe programme. The
Assembly asked contribu-
tions from the UN Member
States and they were given
generously at the United
Nations Technical Assistance
Conference held at Lake
Success in June, 1950. Fifty
nations not only reached the
conference's goal of $20, 000, 000,
but exceeded It by another
$12, 500.
The conference had the
atmosphere of an international
competition in generosity. This
started when the United
States pledged $10, 000, 000 if
other contributions totalled
$., 000, 000. Then the American
delegate offered to raise the
United States'share to
$12, 500, 000 provided that it
amount, at that sum, to not
more than 60 per cent of the
total reached.
The responses of other dele-
gates marched the American
spirit.
The delegate from Venezuela
-. My Government is prepared
to raise its contribution to a
totat of $44,000, 000, an increase of
$4, 000 over the amount pre-
viously pledged.
The delegate of the United
Kingdom-H'e regard it as
important that than figure
($20, 000, 000) be reached. We
propose to increase the United
Kingdom contl'ibution to
$. 760, 00, that is, an additionat
$28, 000.
The delegate of the Nether-
lands-Two days ago our
delegation ptedged 1, 500, 000
Dutch guilders. Now we find
that it is only $396, 000. We
should like to raise this $4, 000
to make the $400, 000 1'Ound
figure and help in altaining
the $400, 000 round figure and
help in attaining the $20, 000, 000.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 6
THAT ALL MAY LEARN is a film made under supervision of the United Nations Film Board, to show
the world-wide fforts of Unesco in the fight against illiteracy. Set in a small Mexican community, the
film demonstrates the down-to-earth values of being able to read and write. Here, peasants are being
told by an educated member of their community what they must do to reclaim land that belongs to them.
Bare literacy is not the end and may not even be the beginning of education, yet the printed word is a potent
means of conveying ideas. The mind of the illiterate is often closed to ideas which are essential to eco-
nomic and political development.
BEFORE the end of next year, 250 Libyans-some of them now illiterate-
will have learned enough about Arabic typing and shorthand so that
their country, n w a Unit d Nations tru teeship, will have clerks to man
government offices when it gains its independence in 1952.
During the same period, an engineer will have surveyed the length
and the breadth of the major rivers of Ecuador to determine the best sites for
future dams to tap their hydro-electric resources.
And, also by the end of 1951, farmers in Ceylon will be learning how to
read and, at the same time, how to produce more food from the same amount
of soil, thus preparing themselves to be shock troops in their country's peaceful
campaign to recapture three fourths of its land area from the jungle.
These examples from three
continents are culled from a new
programme of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization. They represent the
realisation of part of a world scheme
of"technical assistance for economic
development", now being carried out
by the United Nations and its agen-
cies, nations and organizations.
Haw is a technical assistance project
set in motion ? The administrative
machinery set up by the Unit d
Nations for its programme is extra-
ordinary in its simplicity.
Basically, the process of asking inter-
national aid for economic development is
no more complicated than that of writ-
ing a letter. In this case, the letter out-
lining what is wanted is written by a
government and sent to Unesco or one of
the United Nations agencies.
In every case, the letter is turned over
to the United Nations Technical Assist-
ance Board, which is charged with the
responsibility of finding exactly the right
Agency-or Agencies-to deal with it.
TQ cope with the question of priority,
the Board and the Agencies have before
them six basic standards by which to
measure the importance of any request.
These are :
1. The relation of a project to economic
development or to the betterment of
soolal conditions essential to economic
development ;
2. The increase) In productivity which the
project would bring about ;
3. The utent to which the requesting
nation can help In the execution of theproject ;
4. The financial ability of the requesting
government to continue the work begun
by the UN after the asslstenoe has
ended ;
6. The possibilities of applying the bene-
fits of the projeot to other countries In
the same region ;
8. The urgency of the aid requested ;
7. The equitable distribution of aid to the
different regions of the world.
The responsibilities of requesting gov-
ernments are mainly financial. They
include the payment of subsistence allow-
ance to cover the living expenses of
experts ; the payment of such costs as
transportation and medical expenses ; the
provision of office facilities ; and sharing
in the cost of fellowships and scholarships
offered as part of the aid programme.
UNESCO FIELDS OF ACTION
THE formulation of requests by govern-ments is n t a difficult procedure.
Unesco and the other Specialized
Agencies have made clear just what they
are prepared to do to aid the economic
development of a country. Unesco's fa-
cilities for technical assistance, which is
usually provided in co-operation with the
other UN agencies, can be summarized
under the following headings :
1. ELEMENTARY EDUCATION. The
Organization is prepared to help in
educational administration and finance,
curricula and teaching methods, text-
books, school buildings and equipment,
the planning of compulsory education
programmes and the adaptation of
educational systems to meet changing
community needs.
2. FUNDAMENTAL AND ADULT
EDUCATION. To raise the standard of
living of the people through education,
Unesco offers aid in literacy campaigns,
education in health and agriculture, the
development of co-operatives, and the
encouragement of small industries and
handicrafts.
3. TECHNICAL EDUCATION. Unesco
has interpreted this term to mean
education and training for industries,
trades, agriculture and commerce from
the primary school to the university level.
Aid is available in the organization and
financing of such schools, and on
problems relating to their buildings and
equipment, textbooks, the selection of
staffs, and the co-ordination of their
programmes with the country's overall
economic development.
4. BASIC AND APPLIED SCIENCES.
This extremely important phase of
Unesco's technical assistance covers both
teaching and research in the Natural
Sciences. Physicists, chemists, mathema-
ticians, biologists... all are essential to eco-
nomic development.
5. SCIENTIFIC INFORMATION. This
field is a broad one, covering various
forms of documentation needed for scien-
tific and technical education for carrying
out research and for developing industry.
SERVICES UNESCO OFFERS
THESE are the fields in which Unescois prepared to offer aid. Gov rn-
ments requiring assistance in one or
several of these fields, normally indicate
the form of aid they feel will be most
effective. Here again, Unesco has drawn
up a simplified list of the methods avail-
able to governments seeking technical
aid. They are divided into four main
types of services, as follows :
EXPLORATORY MISSIONS. These
are teams of specialists intended mainly
to aid countries on fact-finding projects
in education and the natural and social
sciences. The exploratory mission is
usually of short-term duration and, under
normal conditions, completes its work
within six months.
ADVISORY SERVICES. This form of
aid is intended for countries which have
already carried out their own exploratory
missions and gathered the preliminary
UNESCO'S SHARE II
TECHNICAL ASSIST
The meaning of Technical Assis-
tance and the desperate, almost
world-wide, needs it is designed to
serve are dealt with on Page 5 of this
issue of the COURIER.
Of the total funds, $ 20, 012, 500,
pledged by fifty countries for the
whole programme of the United
Nations and its Specialized Agencies,
Unesco has been allocated 14 0/0,
S 2, 300, 000, for its share in the work.
TWELVE REQUESTS ANSWERED
IN the case of Unesco, as well as1 t at of the other United Nations
Agencies, there was no shortage of
request. s to put the money to work.
In July of 1950, the Technical Assis-
tance Board reported that it had
received requests from fifty-seven
countries. Unesco, at present, has
requests from nearly two dozen coun-
tries on hand, and it has already taken
action on twelve of them.
These twelve countries, are Ceylon,
Ecuador, India, Indonesia, Iraq, Le-
banon, Liberia, Libya, Mexico, Pakis-
tan, Persia and Thailand. in their
requests, they produced twelve diffe-
rent intepretations of"Technical As-
distance for Economic Development"
that is, interpreting it to fit their
own immediate needs.
These varied interpretations are
completely in line with the United
Nation's conception of technical aid.
This programme has no intention of
setting up a production line from
which would stream prefabricated
economies and, even worse, stan-
dardised societies and cultures. The
new economies will be fitted into the
needs of the countries-not vice
versa.
data needed for a proposed project. In
this case, a government may request an
advisory mission to guide it in projects
in education, basic and applied sciences
and the use of the radio and visual
material for educational purposes.
Unesco's experience in operating re-
gional scientific offices around the world
suggested a longer-term type of advisory
service-the Advisory Science Office. If
requested by a country, such offices will
be set up to supply scientific and technical
information.
TRAINING. Unesco is prepared to
help in the training of teachers, scientists
and other needed personnel by facilitating
study abroad through fellowships or by
assisting in the establishment of training
centres within a country. Unesco is also
prepared to call study groups for short
intensive studies of problems arising in
technical assistance, and may help set up
demonstration projects to show people by
example just what the use of new
educational and scientific techniques can
do for a region. Unesco is also equipped
to aid governments in setting up centres
for producing educational films and radio
programmes.
RESEARCH TEAMS AND INFORM-
ATION SERVICES. The research team,
as defined by Unesco, consists of a group
of scientists who will aid a country in
research on technical or scientific prob-
lems standing in the way of economic
development. One of the main inform-
ation services offered is the biblio-
graphical centre, including a library
designed to collect, classify and digest for
ready use, scientific documentation on
problems of technical assistance. The
information series will also include a
photographic reproduction office to handle
microfilmed documents. The biblio-
graphical centre will make its services
available to United Nations Agencies
working on technical assistance problems
and to scientists and industrialists in the
entire region. The information services
available through Unesco also cover public
information teams ; that is, press and
radio specialists to aid countries in telling
the largest possible number of people the
aims of specific technical assistance pro-
jects.
The above categories of technical assist-
ance teams and facilities are available to
under-developed countries for 1950-51.
But here again, Unesco's view of tech-
nical assistance is an elastic one. This
"prospectus"does not necessarily mean
that the Organization's activities will be
limited to such services. If the needs of
countries call for other techniques, the
way is not barred to their use. In a sense,
it will be the countries receiving aid who
will help determine what Unesco's future
technical assistance programmes will be.
This principle explains the em-
phasis which the United Nations and,
in particular, Unesco have placed on
the educational side of technical as-
sistance. If a nation does not have
an adequate number of trained scien-
tists and educators to pick up the
work begun by specialists from
abroad, technical assistance will
merely die of inertia.
It also should be remembered that
$ 20, 000, 000 is all that the United
Nations has available at the present
moment for the needs of the entire
world. With that sum there will be
no deserts blooming overnight, or mud
huts mushrooming up into skyscra-
pers. Therefore, Unesco has decided
that the amount of money it has on
hand will give a greater return if it
is invested in men instead of in
drawing up grandiose paper projects.
Unesco cannot build dams, but it can
train engineers and teachers of engi-
neering. When the money for the
dams is available, the men-native,
not foreign-will be there to build
them.
TECHNICAL AVID PHILOSOPHY
THIS might be called the philosophyof technical assistance as conceiv-
ed by Unesco and the United
Nations, Here, in twelve coun-
tries, is how it is being transformed
from a philosophy into a programme
of action. Space does not permit
detailed treatment for each of these
twelve countries. The single case
history of Libya, described in a sepa-
rate story on this page, will serve to
illustrate many of the principles and
methods to be used by Unesco in its
part of the work of technical assis-
tance.
CEYLON. This country, on its own
initiative, launched a large-scale pro-
gramme to reclaim its so-called"Dry
Zone", which makes up 75 per cent
of its land area. Unesco is aiding
this programme with a fundamental
education centre, emphasizing, literacy
training and better farming methods.
Ceylon also will have the services of
two geologists to make an inventory
of its mineral resources.
ECUADOR. Here, a four-man team
of scientists and educators will be sent
into the field. One member of the
team, a chemical engineer, will assist
in setting up a chemical engineering
institute to put added research faci-
lities at the disposal of Ecuadorian
industry. The second will work with
Ecuadorian educators on improving
AGAINST FAMII
TO FIGHT HUNGER through technics ! assista
is a lob at which the Food and Agricultural Or ;
has already been working in many countries. Pa
to the problem of increasing food production
use of hybrid corn. FAO shipped this high-yield
East to improve agriculture there, as it had
war-devastated Europe. The FAO has also proylc
on flsheries, animal disease control and fores
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Page 7-UNESCO COURIER
[JfUNITED NATIONS
Z\NCE PROGRAMME
the organization and the curricula of
the country's universities ; the third
will assist the country in its literacy
campaign, and the fourth will be the
electrical engineer previously men-
tioned. In this joint mission, the ILO
will send three advisers on industrial
education and handicrafts.
INDIA. At a cost of $ 229, 200,
Unesco is helping India in its na-
tional programme of improving faci-
lities for scientific research and train-
ing. As one phase, Unesco is sending
seven experts in such fields as plas-
tics, dam design, electrical engineer-
ing and low temperature physics.
The second part of the programme
will see Unesco help India to set up
a bibliographical centre for scientists
working in India, in technical assis-
tance programmes in the region and
in all of South-east Asia. At present,
India has a tremendous number of
scientific documents on its hands
with no adequate facilities for putting
them into a condition where they can
be readily used.
INDONESIA. Unesco will help In-
donesia set into motion a training
programme for teachers in resettle-
ment areas, as well as. to establish
an adequate primary school system (at
present only 25 per cent of the coun-
try's school-age children are in class-
rooms).
IRAQ. The University of Baghdad,
building up its science department, is
suffering from a shortage of teachers.
In response to the government's
request, Unesco is sending out a biolo-
gi-st, a mathematician and an indus-
trial chemist to become temporary
members of the faculty and, from a
long-term viewpoint, is providing- fellowships to enable Iraqui science
teachers to study abroad.
LEBANON. Here Unesco, during
1950-1951, will make a study of the
country's technical assistance needs,
especially in the field of scientific and
educational research.
LIBERIA. This African country
presents a strange picture of economic
development far outstripping what
might be called human development.
To enable Liberians to reap the full
benefits of the tremendous changes
'being made in their country's econ-
omy, Unesco is helping their govern-
ment with a broad educational pro-
gramme. This scheme will concen-
trate on the expansion of facilities at
Liberia College, the country's only
higher educational institution and, at
the same time, will work out methods
of raising educational standards
throughout the country-not an easy
task since Liberia's population of
1, 500, 000 is divided into nearly twenty
language groups.
LIBYA. By January 1, 1952, this
country will become independent, but
it is desperately short of civil servants.
Unesco is helping in the operation of
what can only be called a clerical and
typing school and, in addition, is sup-
plying funds to enable prospective
holders of higher governmental posi-
tions to study abroad. (For addition-
al details of the programme in Libya,
see separate story on this page).
MEXICO. Here Unesco, in coopera-
tion again with the ILO is planning
to assist Mexican industrial training
schools. At the same time, a biblio-
graphical centre very much like the
one planned for India will be set up
to serve countries throughout Latin-
America.
PAKISTAN. Two missions are
to be sent to this country. The first,
a team of four scientists specialised in
seismology, atmosphere and magnet-
ism research, will help set up the
first institute of geophysics in Asia.
Once it Ls in operation, its initial task
will be to survey Pakistan's vast desert
area to assess the possibilities of
salvaging land, through irrigation, for
food production. The second mission
will seek to develop radio broadcasting
and receiving facilities in Pakistan in
order to make them effective media
for adult education.
PERSIA. A scientist sent out by
Unesco will advise the Persian Go-
vernment on its seven-year economic
development programme and will help
determine where Unesco's technical
aid facilities can fit into this pro-
gramme.
THAILAND. A team of educators
specialised in primary school training,
vocational education, and the teach-
ing of science and the English lang-
uage, is going out to Thailand to
help cope with a shortage of 20, 000
teachers in a country where only one-
third of the 70, 000 available teachers
have had adequate training.
In all of these countries, every
foreign specialist will have his count-
erpart studying abroad on a fellow-
ship to replace him at the end of his
mission. In most cases, too, the accent
has been placed on training teachers
rather than students. Unesco does
not want to become an international
faculty : rather, it wants to give
educators in individual countries the
initial impetus they need to get their
own systems under way.
TECHNICAL AID IS NOT A NEW DEA. Unesco and other United Nations Specialized Agencies have
been straining their limited resources for several years to carry out their own"technical aid"programmes.
Unesco has given aid in education, science, mass communication, and in various cultural fields. To pre-
pare audio-visual materials for fundamental education, for example, Unesco set up an experimental centre
in China. Filmstrips, posters and pamphlets dealing with health precautions were tested in local villages.
This photo shows members of a Unesco team preparing for a film show. The materials and lessons
learned from the experiment will be available to educators all over the world.
IN March 1950, Adrian Pelt, theUnited Nations Commissioner in
Libya, sent a letter to Unesco
asking for help. Mr. Pelt's assign-
ment in the former Italian colony was
to put into effect the resolution of the
United Nations General Assembly pro-
viding for the establishment not later
than January 1, 1952, of a constitutional
government in a free, united Libya.
The area involved was under three
different administrations : Tripolitania,
administered by the British, with a
population of 800, 000 ; Cyrenaica, with
a semi-independent government advised
by a British Resident, and a population
of 200, 000 ; and Fezzan, with a popula-
tion of 40, 000 under French administra-
tion. Mr. Pelt needed help in training
a corps of Libyan minor civil servants
who would be prepared to carry out
their tasks as soon as the new govern-
ment began functioning.
Mr. Pelt's first requirement was for
helpers well below the level of minis-
terial rank. He merely wanted persons
who could help him provide the new
nation of Libya with enough file clerks,
stenographers and typists to carry on
the normal business of government.
Unesco responded at once to the
appeal, sending to Libya a representa-
tive equipped to make for Mr. Pelt an
expert survey of the situation. The
Unesco expert reported that Libya had
E, DISEASE AND DISASTER
B'programmes
litation (FAO)
fthe solution
 been wider
m to the near
eady done in
I expert advice
: onservation.
TO FIGHT DISEASE, which saps the energy and vigour needed
to overcome obstacles to development is a global task for the
World Health Organization (WHO). Malaria, already being fought
by teams of WHO experts, in Asia, the Middle East and Europe,
strikes an estimated 300 million people each year ; 2 to 3 million
die ; others are weakened. In India, the trainees, shown here
examining DDT spraying machines used In the WHO campaign,
will soon be taking over this campaign themsetves.
AIR SAFETY through international co-operation is the goal of
the International Civil Aviation Organization (iCAO) ; one of the
specialized agencies taking part in the technical assistance
programme. Types of assistance being considered by ICAO
include aerodrome and air route administration and control,
training schools for flying, navigation, radio, meteorology and
other technical professions and the despatch of technical mis-
sions. This photo shows a balloon with weather recording
instruments being launched from one of the U. N. weather ships
operated today by ICAO along the principal Trans-Atlantic Rou-
tes, providing pilots with the latest meteorological data, and
maintaining rescue services.
not produced a secondary school gra-
duate since 1939. Before 1939, the
general level of education had been very
low because of economic backwardness.
It was only in 1947 that secondary
schools were opened again in Tripolita-
nia and Cyrenaica. No students would
therefore graduate until 1951.
FIRST TASK LITERACY
THE task of training Arabic typistsand stenographers seemed relati-
vely simple until it was discovered that
the available personnel was illiterate
and would, first, have to be taught to
read and write.
The Unesco report also showed that
the prospective nation's deficiencies in
competent government personnel were
equally great in the higher brackets.
To remedy this lack, it was suggested
that fellowships and scholarships for
study in foreign countries as well as in
Libya be provided. These were pro-
posed to cover courses in local govern-
ment methods, forestry, customs admi-
nistration, police work and accountancy.
It was also suggested that seven Libyans
with teacher training be offered an
opportunity to make further studies in
England, for three or four months. The
shortage of teachers in Libya was so
grave that they could not be spared
for a longer period.
Acting on the basis of the report, and
on requests received from the adminis-
trations of the three areas which will
form United Libya, Unesco decided to
help in three ways : first, by esta-
blishing a clerical training centre ;
second, by providing scholarships to
enable prospective holders of higher
governmental positions to prepare
themselves for these new duties through
study ; and third, by providing scholar-
ships in education to ten men and
women from the Fezzan.
TRAINING CENTRE OPENED
THE total cost of this project is$ 57, 500. In common with all the
other technical assistance projects un-
dertaken by Unesco, the sum is to come
from resources outside the Organiz-
ation's normal budget. The clerical
training school will cost Unesco $ 32, 000
to operate during the year 1950-51, a
figure which includes the salaries of a
principal and thirteen teachers. Unesco
and the United Kingdom will share the
other costs of operating the centre.
These include subsistence allowances for
pupils, the purchase of thirty-one Ara-
bic and thirty-one English typewriters
and the repair of the school building.
The training centre is already operat-
ing in Libya. Literacy training plays
as important a part in its curriculum as
the proper techniques oft writing a bus-
iness letter.
The case of Libya is an example of
the kind of technical assistance which
Unesco can offer, for it represents the
maximum utilization of a small amount
of funds to accomplish a definite pur-
pose within a given time.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
MODERN society is the result of man'sincreasing but still incomplete. conques  of nature. Technology
and engineering are powerful weapons
in effecting this conquest. Historically,
there are good reasons for the advanced
technological society of the West.
Today, however, as the Dutch historian
R. J. Forbes has written :"IF e live in
a stage of human history in which the
answers to the common problems that
occupy metf's attention at every point 0/
the globe are no longer limited to certain
areas and artificial lines on a map. The
new science has established an interna-
tional brotherhood 0/scientific thought".
It is this recognition which accounts
for the key role played by science in
all programmes for technical assistance.
As the Indian monthly journal, Science
and Culture, has said (speaking for all
under--developed territories) :"We are
convinced that the only way to achieve
economic independence and regeneration
would be through intensive application
of science and technology to all pro-
ductive endeavour".
The Republic of India is indeed
moving into action along these lines.
Prime Minister Nehru has declared :
"1 believe that all problems, both world
problems and national, should « ue a
scientific approach". India herself has
a great scientific tradition. In recent
by
Maurice GOLDSMITH
years, great Indian physicists like Sir
C. V. Raman and Professor H. Bhabha,
and chemists such as Sir Shanti Swarup
Bhatnagar, have made unique contri-
butions to world science.
To Na.... ow A Gap
THERE is much to do in India, acountry with a population of over
300, 000, 000, and natural population
increase larger than any nation in
Europe (with the exception of Russia).
Taking the amount of energy available
per head of population as an index of
the level of technical civilization, India
uses yearly the equivalent of less than
one-fifth of a ton of coal per head as
compared with the USA's 9 tons and
Britain's 4. The technical assistance
programme is designed to help narrow
this gap for countTies whose ill-
nourished millions demand the material
means for better lives.
Unesco will make available to India
$229, 000, a large share of its technical
assistance budget for the first year.
Specialists will be engaged by Unesco
to assist India in several aspects of her
own national programme. For example,
In this Indian jute research laboratory, an expert examines fibre bundles to determine the
strength and extension of the yarn. Information from such research centres will be"digested"in the giant bibliographical centre which Unesco is helping to set up in India, and
then made available to scientists and technologists in South-East Asia generally.
Professor Turner Alfrey, of the USA, is
to set up a division of plastics and high
polymers in the National Chemical
Laboratory. This is but one of the many
new research institutions now being set
up.
Three scientists are to go to India's
T OWAI1I) tile clo : ; e of the last cen-tury ph'sical science, intoxicated- *-with its own success s, reached
a state of complacency seldom
attained before in any branch of intel-
lectual endeavour. The universe, it was
felt, is a great machine, and the laws
regulating its working had been disco-
vered and understood. Apparently the
many features of the inanimate world
- the courses of the stars, electricity
and its magic effects, the frenzied
jostling of the molecules of matter-
were all suhservient to the laws of phy-
sics as then kno. wn. 1'lwre was a gene-
ral feeling among physicists that tile
only tasks remaining to them were the
rounding out of details here and there
and the sharpening of measurements
wherever that appeared desirable.
Then, almost at the turn of the century,
the discovery of radioactivity, of -ra-s
and of electrons shook the world of
science. The era of modern physics
was born.
not long thereafter ca me the first hint
that something about our understanding
of the physical world was not quite in
order. The trouble was precipitated by
a study of the radiation of light from a
glowing solid object, such as a hot coal.
Classical physics, eminently successful
in accounting for the minute details of
light in all its other manifestations, was
apparently powerless to explain the
observed distribution of brightness In
the light coming from an incandescent
lump of solid matter.
Ellergy DOlle up
ill Packets
T JlE problcm was Iinally solvedsuccessfully by the theoretical
'"'physicist Max Planck in De-
cember of 1900. exactly half a century
ago, but the solution was haselI on
assumption so novel and so ultcriw
dilTerent from previous concepts tint.
the Hrst reaction of the world of
science was one of outraged scorn.
For, in order to make theory match
observation, Planck was forced to
assume that tote radiation of light is a
discontinuous, intermittent process-not
at all comparable to the smooth, steady
flow of water from a tap, but more like
the discharge of bullets from a ma-
chinegun.
The individual"lmlJets"of course
must he exceedingly small to give tie
appearanee of steady illumination ordi-
nail observed. Indeed, it turned out
that an average ImlJet-ol'quantum-
of visible light carried only about onc
millionth of the energy expended hy a
mosquito in climbing a. distance equal
to its own length.
If this novel idea of"energy done
up in packets"lIad succeeded only in
explaining the single phenomenon of
radiation from a heated solid it might.
have remained a mere scientific curio-
sity, provisionaily tolerated only until
the"true"l'xplanation should t. UI'll up.
Rut this ways not to be the case.
When, presently, the Danish physicist
Xeiis Bohr began to look for an explan-
: ilion of the radiation from individual
atollls and molecules of matter, lie
found that Planck's quantum idea gov-
erned this field also. Moreover, it did
so with a precision equalting that with
which Newton's gravitation described
the wheeling of the planets in space.
. \nd even earlier. Einstein, shrewdly re-
cognised that quanta were lurking be-
hind the operation of a photo-electric
eels-the now-familiar"electric eye"
that is the very heart of sound motion
pictures and television and that per-
forms automatically such practical
tasks as opening dOl\l's, SOrUJJg llIanuf ; IC-
urged product--.
warning of H"e
- all through
the medium of
a beam of
tight. Max Planck
Since 1900. physical theory and the practice of fire lighting have apparently developed along
contradictory lines. Only a half century ago, it was assumed that all energy"Bowed"
as smoothly as water from a hose, as in the picture on the left. Now it is known that
energy is communicated only in spurts,"bundles"or"quanta". as suggested by the drawing,
right, of an old-fashioned bucket brigade. The smallness of the units of energy, and the
rapidity of their succession, concealed the true process from generations of scientific observers.
V « <Mre*a Ieeep « <M<Nøt"re8 D f' ! eptio8
lJØDlø8""
A : \1) o in spite of the fact that it
was completely at variance with
the nolion of continuous How of
energy assumed by the older
physics, the quantum idea has become
- through its speetaeular successes-an
accepted and indispensable part of mo-
dern science. It might be said that
science has become resigned to the fact
that whenever energy is transported
from one place to another. Nature
allows it to pass only in separate, de-
taclled spurts, or quanta. We are
deceived inlo believing that we witness
a continuous rather than an intermittent
process, only because the individual
bundles are so minute and so numerous.
Yet, strange as it is, the quantum no-
tion fits into place alongside two si-
milar ideas with which science has long
been familiar,-the discontinuous na-
ture of both matter and electricity. The
fact that matter itself is not continuous,
but made up of individual particles-
atoms-was surmised by the ancients
and was convincingly demonstrated
about a century and a half ago. Not.
much later there arose the notion that
electricity, too, must be made up of
unassociated bits-a concept that finally
culminated in the discovery and mea-
surement of this ultimate unit, called
the electron.
Thus the quantum reinforces our
conviction that certain aspects of the
universe are, in a sense, granular. And
there may be other quantities besides
('upr ! !'\,. matter and electricity which
will be found to be of this nature, too.
Perna ps space itself is one of them ;
time may be another. But here, we
are st. ill in the province of pure spe-
culation.
It you are interested in I'eading more
about the Quantum J'heory, write to the
lJivision for the Popularization of
Science, Unesco, 19, avenue Kleber, pa-
ris, for a 6WfY bibliography on this sub-
ject, which will be sent free of charge.
National Physical Laboratory to do
research in low-temperature physics.
The technical equipment is to be
provided by Unesco. Other scientists
- specialists in marine engineering, naval
architecture, dam design and geo-
physics-are to work at the Indian
Institute of Technology.
In addition, Unesco is to aid India in
·wetting up a giant bibliographical centre.
This will be designed to keep Indian
scientists informed of all aspects of
activity. Its facilities will also be
available to other United Nations
technical assistance missions and to
scientists in South-east Asia generally.
One of this Centre's major tasks will be
to"digest"more than 12, 000 scientific
articles published yearly in India alone.
The wise use of science in such
countries as India can make the technical
assistance programme meaningful, and
demonstrate to the world how the
conquests of science can help liberate
all mankind from many of its ancient
ills.
Unesco Asks Five
Nations To Aid In
High Altitude
Research Work
THE process of acclimatization ofman living at sea level to the
atmospheric conditions of high
altitudes is still insufficiently known.
Continued research work is needed to
solve this problem-and is also impor-
tant for gaining a better comprehension
of the respiratory function of the blood.
Research dealing with the physiology
of men living on the high plateaux of
Peru, by scientists from the National
institute of Andean Biology, of San
Marcos University, Lima, Peru, was
recently recognized by the Joint Com-
mission on High Altitude Research
Stations, which urged that it should
be extended to other Latin American
countries.
Undertaken by Professor Carlos
Monge and other members of the
Peruvian institute, it showed the neces-
sity to establish norms in medical
practice-of blood counts, chest mea-
surements, etc.-for people living at
high altitudes. The Peruvian scientists
accumulated a large number of norms
which are necessary for medical prac-
tice on high plateaux.
In its resolution, the Joint Commis-
sion on High Altitude Research Stations
requested Unesco to draw the atten-
tion of medical and university autho-
rities in Bolivia, Colombia, Ecuador,
Mexico and Venezuela, where there
are people living at high elevations, to
the opportunity they have to co-operate
in this field. It also suggested that
these countries form a Joint Committee
to initiate and co-ordinate this type of
research in their territories.
Unesco has now officially informed
the governments of these five countries
of the suggestions.
UNESCO COURIER-Page 8
I I I I'I'I I'I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Page 9-UNESCO COURIER
AN international agreement which will allow a wide rangeof educational. scientific and cultural materials to move
across frontiers free of duty will be opened for signature
on the 22nd of November, at United Nations headquarters. Lake
Success, New York. The text of the Agreement was adopted
unanimously at the last General Conference of Unesco, at
Florence.
All Member States of Unesco and of the United Nations may
adhere to the"Agreement on the Importation of Educational.
Scientific and Cultural Materials."as the new pact is called.
It will come into force following ratification by ten countries.
Sponsoring the Agreement, the Unesco General Conference
urged Member States to sign and ratify it and to implement
its provisions in the most liberal manner. The United Nations
Economic and Social Council has also drawn the attention of
Member States to the"practical importance"of the agreement.
countries, books continued
to enjoy immunity from
tariffs affecting most other
classes of goods. The tariff
rates introduced by France in
1892, for example, gave com-
plete exemption to books re-
gardless of origin. By 1906
Austria-Hungary, Germany,
Japan and many smaller
countries had followed the
French lead. Italy, Russia,
Spain and the United States
allowed books in foreign
languages to enter freely but
imposed a duty on imported
books printed in the native
language.
WARS RAISE BARRIERS
THE outbreak of war in 1914brought this comparatively
happy period to a close.
During World War I itself,
tariffs rose generally and new
restrictive measures were de-
vised to meet the emergency.
Of these, the most notable was
the licensing system, which
enabled governments to exer-
cise an unprecedented degree
of control over foreign trade.
Since the aim was to restrict
trade in goods considered non-
essential to the war effort,
many articles of educational
value suffered.
By the end of World War I,
the whole structure of pre-war
trade had been shattered. The
economic depression of the
1930's led to a host of restric-
tions more rigid and extensive
than those adopted after 1914.
The division of the world into
currency blocs and the intro-
duction of quota systems plac-
ed an even greater check on
world trade. Informational
materials suffered particularly,
though films enjoyed some re-
lief under the"Convention to
Facilitate the International
Circulation of Films of an
Educational Character", which
"ESSEMDAL GOODS"ONLY !
THE vast devastation causedby the rec nt war and the
external indebtedness of
many countries struck a final
blow at the multilateral trading
system. Informational mate-
rials, which had never been
more greatly needed, suffered
as much, or more, than other
commodities, since internatio-
nal trade was still largely
confined to the exchange of
"essential goods"and nearly
all countries were faced by
extremely complex payments
difficulties.
Despite the growth of
restrictions generally, many
countries were
disposed to pro-
vide special fa-
cilities for trade
in instruments
of knowledge. It
was necessary,
however, for an
inter-govern-
mental agency
to draw atten-
tion to the pro-
blem as a whole,
to stimul-
ate governments
into concrete
action and to
provide a frame-
work within
w h i c h remedial measures
might be effected.
Unesco's first undertaking
was to sponsor a new agree-
ment to replace the League of
Nations Convention on educa-
tional films, already mention-
ed, which had lapsed during
the war. The draft of a con-
vention, broadened to include
many other audio-visual ma-
terials, was approved by the
Unesco General Conference In
November, 1948. Known as the
"Agreement to Facilitate the
International Circulation of
fied by three (Norway, Pa-
kistan, Yugoslavia). Ratifica-
tion by ten countries is needed
to bring it into force.
When the Unesco General
Conference met at Beirut
in November, 1948, it instruct-
ed the Director-General to
prepare the draft of a second
international agreement, de-
signed to faciiitate the inter-
national circulation of public-
ations. A draft was drawn up
and the Director-General took
the opportunity to submit it
for consideration by the Con-
tracting Parties to the General
Agreement on Tariffs and
Trade (G. A. T. T.), which met
at Annecy, France, in April
1949. Thirty-four nations, in-
cluding 26 Unesco Member
ONE day, some years before
the Second World War.
a l rge oblong crat
turned up at the Customs
warehouse of a busy port.
The Customs inspector, upon
opening the crate, discovered
that its contents consisted of a
smooth and graceful piece of
solid brass, shaped rather like
a banana standing on its end.
The inspector was completely
at a loss as to how he should
classify the object. Finally, he
arrived at a decision : the
object was"block matter"-
and duty was charged accord-
ing to the relatively high rate
for imported raw material.
But the importer challenged
the inspector's decision. The
"raw material"turned out to
be the abstract sculpture"Bird
in Flight buy the noted Ru-
manian sculptor, Brancusi,
and, in the opinion of art
critics, one of his finest works.
After much delay and ar-
gument, the inspector's ruling
was reversed by the courts and
the piece of sculpture was
allowed to enter duty-free.
The inspector's view that the
Brancusi was just a piece of
brass, is not as extraordinary
as it might seem. It is reject-
ed in the tariff regulations of
many countries which tend to
regard not only works of art
but other educational, scientific
and cultural materials as or-
dhlary commodities, subject to
the same restrictions which
are imposed on commercial
imports.
This tendency has for
many years seriously hinder-
ed the international circula-
tion of educational, scientific
and cultural materials. Some
countries tax imported films
by the foot and sculpture by
the pound. Duties on books
range as high as 300 per cent.
Scientific equipment, needed in
research laboratories, is taxed
with equal severity. Exhibi-
tions and collections, destined
for schools or art galleries,
languish in customs ware-
houses while their sponsors try
to raise the heavy bond often
required by the authorities.
HISTORY OF RESTRICTIONS
MOST of the tariff, quotaand currency restric-
tions on the movement
of informational materials
are of fairly recent origin. In
many cases, moreover, they
have been extended to instru-
ments of knowledge as part of
a general trend toward control
which engulfed these materials,
along with othèr"commodi-
ties", fortuitously rather than
by design.
During the earlier part of
the period between 1850 and
today, informational materials
benefited by the general mo-
vement in favour of
free trade. The Indu-
strial Revolution and
the absence of major
wars led to a general
demand for tariff re-
form, which in Europe
led to the conclusion
of a number of com-
mercial treaties inspir-
ed by liberal princi-
ples. Thus, in 1860,
the United Kingdom
concluded with France
a commercial treaty
providing for free
trade in books.
Though the next 20
years witnessed a re-
turn to protectionist
practice in various
had been adopted by the
League of Nations in 1933. The
24 signatory States to this
convention had agreed to
exempt educational films from
import duties and gran them
the same tax privileges as
might be enjoyed by locally-
produced ones. But in the
troubled years preceding World
War II, political preoccupa-
tions diverted attention from
the damage done to education,
science and culture generally
by tariffs, quotas and exchange
controls.
Auditory and Visual Materials
of an Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Character", this
convention is designed. to re-
move duties, quotas, licences
and other restrictions on
films, filmstrips, microfilms,
sound recordings, glass slides.
models, wall charts, maps and
posters.
This agreement is open for
acceptance by all countries,
Members of Unesco and of the
United Nations. It has been
signed by 18 nations and rati-
States, took part in this mee-
ting.
The conference set up a
seven-nation working party,
under the chairmanship of
Belgium, to consider the Unes-
co Agreement. The working
party concluded that Unesco's
general objective to remove
trade restrictions on instru-
ments of knowledge would best
be furthered through a broad
international agreement to
facilitate the international cir-
culation, not only of publics-
tions, but of a wide variety out
educational, scientific and cul-
tural materials. The working
party then proceeded to draft
such an agreement and the
G. A. T. T. conference, after
approving the text, recom-
mended the convention to
Unesco for sponsorship.
RECENT UNESCO ACTION
THE General Conference ofJt Un sco, t its 4th sessi n
in September, 1949, ins-
tructed the Director-General
to circulate this text to GoV-
ernments and to convene a
meeting of experts to revise it
in the light of comment re-
ceived. Delegates from 25
Member States met in Geneva
for two weeks in March 1950
and reached agreement on a
revised text. The Agreement
on the Importation of Educa-
tional, Scientific and Cultural
Materials, as it was now called,
was submitted to the General
Conference, at its 5th Session
in Florence, and, with a num-
ber of further revisions, was
adopted unanimously. Its
terms are described in an
accompanying article.
The General Conference
urged Member States to sign
and ratify it and to implement
its terms in the most liberal
manner. In a statement to
the Conference, the Director-
General declared that the
entry into force of the Unesco
Agreement would represent a
substantial contribution, in the
technical field, to mutual un-
derstanding and peace.
UNESCO MEMBER STATES SUPPORT
SCHEME FOR IMPORTED PUBLICATIONS
TilE ÐiI'erlor of the Oniversal Postal
l'nion ! lèlS informed postal administra-
lions throughout the world of favour-
; lhle replies whirll Cnesco has received from
member States to its request that they sup-
port measures for wider circulation of
printed materials through postal channels.
UMoaskmrMtoppoaCnesco asked : \Iember States to support a
scheme, initiated by the Universal Postal
Cnion, wtlÍch allows readers to pay in their
national currency, at their local post office.
for subscriptions to newspapers and maga-
zines published in other countries. Belgium.
Denmark, the Netherlands. Norway and
Sweden informed l) nesco that they were
already applying the system in regard to
certain countries and that they were increas-
ing the number of countries from which
their nationals could obtain publications.
In addition, HaJy advised Unesco that it
would establish the service with all countries
willing to carry out such exchanges.
L'nesco also asked Member States to carry
out provisions of the Universal Postal Con-
vention. by which a 50 per cent reduction is
allowed in postal rates for newspapers.
periodicals, books and pamphiets. Iraq
replied that it was willing to reduce rates
fnr publications mailed from its territory.
TIÍ1, ; brings to 3Gt) the number of LnescH
Member States which have announced their
agreement to reduce postal rates for printed
materiats.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page I 0
(C. O. i. Fi. ms.)
A new technique in educational film. similar to that used in French and Italian art film was used in"Local
Government", which teaches schoolchildren about the history 01 local government in England, taking the
city of Norwich as a typical example. It was made from a series of stills, meticulously drawn in period
style like the one above, showing Norwich in the 15th century, with the camera providing the movement.
3pecially composed musical accompaniment creates the right atmosphere for each period.
THE SCREEN-
A NEW \\ BLACKBOARD If
IN BRUTISH SCHOOLS
LESSONS'''èome alive"
t and schoolchildren
understand and r e-
member them more
easily when teachers can
supplement explanations with
visual impressions of the sub-
ject being taught. Only a
few years ago, however,
teachers were obliged to
improvise nearly all their own
visual aids. Many adults can
certainly still remember their
teachers using an orange, an
apple and a lighted candle to
give a crude, but effective
demonstration of the rela-
tionship between the earth, the
sun and the moon.
Today, with films, wall
charts, filmstrips, models and
special maps supplementing or
replacing teacher-made devi-
ces, one of the countries
giving a valuable lead, espe-
cially in the field of films, is
Great Britain, where the
development of such visual aids
has been going on for many
years.
The belief in the value of
films as educational aids began
to grow in Britain about 1920.
Since then, the interest and
activity shown by teachers
associations, education insti-
tutes and Local Education
Authorities has encouraged
film makers to produce mate-
rial suitable for the school
curriculum.
Further development is being
made possible today through
the National Committee for
Visual Aids in Education.
formed to plan and develop a
visual aid policy for England
and Wales, and the Educa-
tional Foundation for Visual
Aids (E. F. V. A.) whose work
includes the provision of infor-
mation and facilities for edu-
cational authorities and
teachers and help, in an advi-
sory capacity, to sponsors and
producers of new educational
films.
Industrr Helps Education
EDUCATIONAL film librarieshave been set up by such
bodies as the British
Electrical Development Asso-
ciation, the Petroleum Film
Bureau, the British Iron and
Steel Federation, the Inter-
national Wool Secretariat and
the Tea Bureau. The first of
these groups, for instance, has
produced over 15 films dealing
with the basic theories and
principle of electricity.
These ten minute films explain
in simple language the why
and wherefore of electricity
and its different applications
in the home and in the
factory. They are loaned
to teachers together with
detailed notes and question-
naires which help them to
make the fullest use of the
films as visual aids.
In all, 1, 000 prints of 15
films are in constant circulation
throughout the country today,
and in the case of"Generation
of Electricity"and"Trans-
mission of Electricity", 120
prints of each film have been
made to meet the needs of
schools and technical colleges.
An important contribution
to the teaching of science and
engineering has been made by
the iron and steel industry.
Films and filmstrips cover the
obtaining of raw materials and
the production of iron and
steel. Area training officers in
the steel industry use them for
training apprentices, but they
are also available to schools
and technical colleges.
Wool has always played a
large part in British national
life. Accordingly, the industry
has for years helped develop
the use of visual aids for the
teaching of economics, geo-
graphy, chemistry, biology and
domestic science. Similarly,
the tea industry has done a
great deal to instruct teachers
in the use of visual aids and to
provide schools with material
which will enliven lessons on
geography, history, transport
and social customs. In addi-
tion to films, exhibitions are
organised ; cardboard models
with sheets of cut-out figures
made for children to assemble
in the course of a lesson.
English In Six Weeks
EVERY kind of visual nidwas mobilized by the
National Coal Board in
1947 to meet a thorny pro-
blem-the teaching of thou-
sands of foreigners from over
twelve different language
groups, enough English in six
weeks to follow their training
course in mining. Although
the lessons were based on the
"direct"method-the teacher
speaking sentences for the
pupils to repeat-filmstrips
played an important part and
were found to be useful
because they forced the
trainees to focus their atten-
tion on one picture at a time
as it was projected on the
screen. Films were found
useful for revision and for
dramatisation of normal
straightforward conversation
Ordinary documentaries were
used, but the sound track was
replaced by a commentary
which kept strictly to the lan-
guage level reached by each
particular group.
Among recently produced
films dealing with language
teaching was"La Famille
Martin"which enables the
pupil to see French characters
talking naturally, and acting
naturally as they do in
everyday life. The tempo of
the film is deliberately normal
and not slowed up for fear of
creating an artificial and
erroneous impression.
Such films enable children
cribing"Map Projection",
"Latitude and Longitude"and
"Day and Night". The last
named, produced in colour, is
exceptionally clever in its use
of revolving models and inge-
nious lighting.
Geographical films, pro-
duced from an unbiased point
of view, have done much to
create a better understanding
of other peoples'problems.
Every recent British produc-
tion of geographical films and
filmstrips has tried to do more
than teach the children the
bare facts. An attempt has
been made to show people in
other lands as real people,
with families and homes.
Hence, there is little generali-
sation. A filmstrip on Persian
oil-fields, will take a specific
Persian worker and tell the
story of his daily life against
a background of the oil-fields
and will thus create an under-
standing of his problems.
(G. B. Instructional Films.)
Children no longer find it. difficult to understand the meaning of liners
drawn on a map or the world when it is explained to them as clearly
as in the film"Latitude and Longitude" (above).
"Digestion"-one 01 the films on physiology made in Great Britain-
is remarkable for its clear exposition of the entire digestive system and
four its painstaking degree 0/accuracy. Such films, in which colour is
used to make every detail visible and intelligible, make even the most
difficult subjects amazingly easy to understand. This photo shows the
route oi digested iood through Mesentor veins into Portal vein.
(Basic Films Ltd.)
LIFE ACROSS THE CHANNEL. Through the film."La Famille Martin,
English schoolchildren are able te see French characters talking naturally
and behaving as they do in everyday life. Such films serve a dual
purpose-language teaching and making children iamlliar with other
peoples'ways of liie.
who cannot hope to go overseas,
to see other peoples'ways of
life.
An outstanding achievement
among films on physiology
was"Digestion", because of its
clear exposition of the entire
digestive system, and for its
painstaking degree of accuracy.
Every muscle contraction is
shown in animation. Colour is
used to make every detail visi-
ble and intelligible. It is a
fascinating production which
makes the subject seem amaz-
ingly easy to understand.
Other Peoples'Problems
IT is perhaps in the geo-JL gra hy lesson that the film
and filmstrip come into
their own. And here remark-
able results have been
achieved. For example, child-
ren have always found it
difficult to visualise the world
and to understand the meaning
of the lines drawn on the
revolving globe. A series of
films has been produced des-
Another pointer to a growing
awareness of the international
value of education is found in
the efIorti'made to obtain fo-
reign films for teaching in
English schools. British pro-
ducers and British teachers are
looking across the seas for
available material.
The day is fast approaching
when such exchanges will be
facilitated by the removal of
customs barriers through two
international agreements
sponsored by Unesco. The
first agreement would relieve
educational films from licences,
quotas and tariffs and the
second (described on page 9 of
this issue of the Courier)
would also free the movement
of films as well as other edu-
cational materials.
Such exchanges are expected
to give an added incentive to
commercial firms and indus-
trialists willing to undertake
the production of films for
schools, by providing a wider
market for their productions.
(G. B. Instructional Films.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Page II-=-UNESCO COURIER
MURDER OF PEOPLES OUTLAWED BY U. N. ACTION
GEN OCIDE CONVENT I ON EFFE CTIVE JA NUARY 12. 1951
THE United Nations Convention on the Prevention and Punishment
of the Crime of Genocide-the deliberate mass extinction of
human groups-has now been approved by a sufficient number
of countries to bring it into force on January 12, 1951.
On October 14, five states ratified or acceded to the Convention,
bringing to 24 the number of states who have become parties-four
more than was required to bring it into force.
The text of the Genocide Convention was adopted by 58 nations
at the General Assembly of the United Nations in Paris, two years
ago.
Nations adhering to it confirm that"genocide, whether committed
in time of peace or in time of war, is a crime under international
law which they undertake to prevent and to punish."
The Convention defines Genocide as acts committed with intent
to destroy a national, ethnical, racial or religious group by killing or
causing serious bodily or mental harm to its members, inflicting on
them conditions likely to bring about its physical destruction,
imposing measures to prevent births within the group or forcibly
transferring children of the group to another group.
In addition to genocide itself other acts related to it which are
punishable under the terms of the Convention are conspiracy, incite-
ment, attempts and complicity in genocide. The Convention also pre-
scribes that persons committing genocide shall be punished, whether
they are constitutionally responsible rulers, public officials or private
individuals. ;
The States which had submitted instruments of ratification or
accession to the Convention by October 14 were the following :
RATIFICATIONS
Australia, Ecuador, EI Salvador, Ethiopia, France, Guatèmala,
Haiti, Iceland, Israel, Liberia, Norway, Panama, Philippines
(with reservations regarding Articles IV, VI, VII and IX ;,
Yugoslavia.
ACCESSIONS
Bulgaria (with reservations regarding Articles IX and XII),
Cambodia, Ceylon, Costa Rica, Hashemite Kingdom of Jor-
dan, Korea, Monaco, Saudi-Arabia, Turkey, Viet-Nam.
EXPERTS PLAN ACTION TO RESOLVE INTERNATIONAL COPYRIGHT TANGLE
O : \ Ocluùn' : ? : 3, a gl'oup of intel'l ! ational cOPllright.,-pel'ls 1//et in',"ashington at the incitation of
Unesco to considCl'the drafting of a Unirersal
Conccntion on Copyright. The lIleetiny mar/ied an im-
pol'lant step in Unesco's efforts to protect creatire 1corker
and to help l'emo'e intellectual and cultuml ùa1Tiel'S
between peoples. A majority of the 37 countries 1which
hare thus fal'replicd to a Unesco questionnail'e al'e in
farour of the establishment of a Unicel'sal Convention. As
the expel'is met, they had before them a proposal that
Unesco convene an intel'-govel'mnental conference to
prepare the lfmft. In the article below arç desC1'ibed
some of the problems caused by the maze of legal dif-
fel' ('nees in the field of copyright,
THE writer, the musician
- any creative worker-
has two important rights
in the product of his labour :
the right to a proper share in
the profits of its sale and the
right to have its original form
and meaning preserved. These
things taken together form
what is known as"Copyright,.
or"literary and artistic owner-
ship."The Universal Declara-
tion of Human Rights gives it
special mention in Article 27 :
"Everyone has the right to
the protection of the moral
and material interests result-
ing from any scientific, literary
or artistic production of which
he is the author."
But, in the same afticle, the
Declaration mentions another
right no less important :
"Everyone has the right free-
ly to participate in the cul-
tural life of the community, to
enjoy the arts and to share in
scientific advancement and its
benefits."In other words,
literary and artistic works
must be as easily accessible to
the public as achievements in
the scientific field.
At first sight, these two
prerogatives may seem to
conflict : the right of the
author to protect his work ;
and the right of the public to
have access to it. One of the
most serious problems to be
faced in any definition of
copyright is the need to main-
tain a delicate balance bet-
ween interests equally deserv-
ing of consideration. Accord-
ing to the importance which
legislation places on author's
rights or those of the public,
Experts Study History
Textbook Improvement
for Unesco Programme
committee of experts met at Unesco House on October 23 tostudy the recommendations of the Unesco-sponsored Seminar
on"The improvement of Textbooks, Particularly History Books",
held at Brussels in August, including plans for a booklet designed
to aid writers of history textbooks.
The Committee met under the chairmanship of Professor Alfred
Weiler Director of the Lycée Experimental Henri IV, at Montgeron,
France, who directed the work of the Brussels Seminar. It included :
Howard R. Anderson, United States Office of Education ; Manich
Jumsai (Siam), Unesco Department of Education ; J. A. Lauwerys,
Professor of Comparative Education, University of London ; Georges
Panchaud, Director, Lycée Municipal de Jeunes Filles, Lausanne ;
L. R. Sethi, Education Secretary, Office of the High Commissioner
for India and Professor Haakon Vigander, Professor of English and
History, Oslo College.
United Nations assistance for Palestine refugees driven from their
homes by military operations in the Middle East saved hundreds 01
thousands from starvation. Today, as this photo shows, the work is
still going on. It was taken in Jericho, where Arabs are making their
own bricks and building their own village in the barren desert sands,
as an experimental re-settlement project, suggested by a U. N. survey
mission. It will be watched with interest as a"model"lor future projects
designed to give employment and homes to nearly 700. 000 Arabs refugees.
Unesco's work for Palestine refugee children has resulted, thanks to
the co-operation of relief organizations and the generosity of donors all
over the world, in the opening of over 62 schools now attended by over
33. 000 children. To enable the education and training of these children
to continue, Unesco's Fifth General Conference issued an appeal for
further assistance him the name of civilization and humanity".
the definition varies of lite-
rary and artistic copyright.
Many other factors play their
part in the promulgation of
copyright laws, not the least
of which are the interests of
distributing agencies.
When Cl'eatiye works
Cross Border
EACH country has to
contend with internal
difficulties according 
its own legislation. But the
problems of copyright go
beyond national frontiers :
books are translated, pictures
reproduced, plays adapted and
performed outside the country
where they originated. As
soon as we examine copyright
from the point of view of its
international application, the
problem becomes even more
complex. For instance, how
can a French musician exer-
cise his rights when one of his
symphonies is performed in
another country ? Clearly, due
consideration for the artist's
rights must be safeguarded in
foreign countries as well as in
his own. If not, what would
happen ?
The creative work, lacking
adequate protection, could be
freely reproduced, its author
receiving no profit at all ;
there is even the possibility of
distortion or wrongful use.
The author is in no position to
take defensive measures.
To widen the sphere of pro-
tection over literary and artis-
tic works in different coun-
tries, international agreements
on copyright have been estab-
lished. But since there are
several of these agreements,
the international protection
of the artist's ownership is not
uniformly assured throughout
the world. In some regions,
there is no protection at all.
A book published in English
by a British citizen in Great
Britain is automatically pro-
tected in the whole of the Bri-
tish Commonwealth, in 22 Eu-
ropean countries, two South
American countries, Israel and
five Arabic-speaking coun-
tries. The same book is also
protected, with reservations, in
seven other countries.
Towards A UniyersaI
Convention
TAKE the case of a book
published in Chile, writ-
ten in Spanish by a
Chilean. If the author has
fulfilled the formalities re-
quired by Chilean legislation,
which include the deposit of
extra copies for each of the
signatory countries to the
Convention of Rio-de-Janeiru,
his rights will be safeguarded
only in ten Latin American
countries, in four European
countries and in three Arabic-
speaking countries.
Foreign works come under
different regulation in almost
every country. Some laws give
equal protection to national
and foreign works Others only
protect works created or pub-
lished on national territory.
Others again give varying
treatment to foreign authors
according to whether or not
they belong to a country with
which an agreement has been
signed.
Such cases give only a par-
tial idea of the confusion that
exists regarding copyright, and
of the need for the work un-
dertaken by Unesco.
This work is not so much
intended to achieve a stan-
dardization of national legisla-
tions, but to unite internatio-
nal conventions now in force
into a single-convention that
will include not only countries
which adhere to existing
agreements but also those
which have so far remained
outside any form of conven-
tion.
gl ltapp. twuJ
in'YliJD1lI1ÚJJlJl...
BENVENUTO CELUN !
un 1 November lUU an
artist was born in Flo-
rence who was almost
perfectly"typical"of the
vigorous and questing
spirit of the Renaissance.
His compatriot Baldinucci
described him as fol-
lows :"Benvenuto, ren-
owned for his Nute play-
ing and his great skill as
a goldsmith, an excellent
engraver of medallions, a
sculptor of more than or-
dinary distinction, an ar-
chitect and metal-/c-under.
an ardent admirer of Mi-
chelangelo, skilful. vigo-
rous, bold of speech and
with a natural eloquence, ready at all times with
the cutting phrase or repartee, and wont to ex-
press his opinions with the utmost frankness,
irrespective of his audience, even to people of
the highest rank..."
THE METRIC SYSTEM
In their decree of the 13th Brumaire in the
year IX (4 November 1800) the Consuls of the
French Republic laid down :"First the decimal says.
tern of weights and measures shall be used
throughout the Republic..."Man thus ceased to
be the measure of all things. Cubit, foot, inch,
acre, yard and fathom, gave place to more exact
and objectively definable quantities as did the
grain, pint, bushel, quart and pound.
Huygens and the mathematician Picard had al-
ready proposed that the unit of length should be
that of the pendulum whose oscillation measured
seconds, but it was not until the Revolution that
universally applicable measures were adopted :
the metre-a ten millionth part of a meridional
quadrant of the earth ; the kilogramme-the
weight of a litre of pure water at 4 centigrade.
'FOR THE PURPOSES OF MUTUAL
UNDERSTANDING...'
Five years ago, Unesco was established. On
16 November 1945, representatives of 40 govern-
ments and 7 international organizations, assembled
In London, signed the Final Act, which is now
the Constitution of Unesco. On behalf of their
peoples, the governments then declared that :
''The States parties to this Constitution, believ-
ing in full and equal opportunities for education
for all. in the unrestricted pursuit of objective
truth, and in the free exchange of ideas and
knowledge, are agreed and determined to develop
and to increase the means of communication bet-
ween their peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual understanding and a
truer and a more perfect knowledge of each
other's lives".
LEO TOLSTOI
Two months before his death, on November 20,
1910, Count Tolstoy, greatest wri'er of his time.
wrote a letter to Mahatma Gandhi, then a lawyer
practising in Johannesburg, on non-resistance,
another name for the"law of love which has
b2eh preached by all the sages... and expressed
most clearly by Christ...""The aspiration of the
soul for communion with our fellow men", he
wrote,"is the only ultimate law of life"."And
so", he told the young Hindu,"your work in the
Transvaal, which seems to us to lie at the utter-
most end of'he earth, is yet the thing on which
our interest is concentrated ; it is the most im-
portant work in the world today..."
ROBERT LOUIS STEVENSON
On 13 November 1850,
Stevenson began the fe-
verish life which was to
take him from his native
Scotland through a suc-
cession of seaside resorts,
hotels and sana'oria to
the fabulous islands of
the Pacific. His tubercu-
losis gave him little
peace, yet the creation of
a new book marked al-
most every stopping-place
on his distressful journey.
The last phase of his life
began in 1890 when Ste-
venson, his wife and his
adopted son, cruising in
the Pacific, landed in
Samoa, where Stevenson started to build a house.
He was to remain there until his death, as the
protector of the people, the friend of the king,
and almost a king himself, exhausting himself
by his efforts to stir the world to indignation
against colonial exploitation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SCHOOL IN THE MAILBOX
Australia's"Phantom Schools"
Serve 18, 000 Children
By Walter GEORGE
EEL'CATION in Australia is free and compulsory, and yet 18, 000children don't go to school. Instead, the school goes to them by
way of His Majesty's mails. ion each of the Commonwealth's
six capital cities there is a school, complete with complement of
teachers, yet no pupils are to be seen ; a kind of phantom school.
If you ask, you'll be told that its pupils are all over an immense
land-in the mountains and forests of Victoria perhaps ; in the tropics
of Queensland, or the Northern Territory ; in the far north of Western
Australia-anywhere, in fact, where Australian children need educa-
tion and are out of reach of Australian schools.
These are the Correspondence Schools. Since early in the first
World War, they have been taking education to children, and to
some adults. Some pupils lived in lonely, outback homesteads or
prospector's camps, or were isolated in lighthouses, or travelling
with some circus. Others were bedridden or in hospital.
Several years ago, two children did a full course while travelling
with their mother through England, Europe, and America.
In Victoria, for example, educa-
tion by correspondence began in
1914, when a countryman who lived
more than eight miles from the
nearest school asked the Education
Department if anything could be
done to teach two of his boys. The
Chief schools'inspector passed the
question on to the principal of the
Teachers'Training College, who
put it to some of the students.
Five of them volunteered to try
teaching the boys by correspond-
ence, each one making himself
responsible for a subject. Before
long, they were sending out lessons
to a younger brother as well, and
soon afterward,, there were so
many requests for correspondence
work that the student teachers
could not cope with them.
That was when the correspond-
ence schools officially came into
being. Other States soon followed
suit, and now, although there is
some slight variation between
States, the broad plan is Common-
wealth-wide.
At each of the headquarter,, ;
schools, those phantom schools at
the State capital, is a headmaster
or mistress with a staff of one
teacher to about every 40 or 45
pupils enrolled.
Keynote of the work is a friendly
personal interest, and letters and
gifts that come to the schools show
what a happy bond exists.
The schools usually provide three
courses of instruction. The primary
course covers all the 1Iormal
subjects children learn during their
first seven years at school, and in
the last two years the girls learn
plain sewing and cookery. In the
super-primary course, children
prepare for the Qualifying Cer-
tificate (common entrance) exami-
nation, and most of the work is in
English, with craft-work like
fancy stitching, free-hand drawing.
elementary design, some applied
arts, knitting, and crocheting. The
secondary course is for those
preparing for the Intermediate
(junior local), and Leaving Cer-
tificate (matriculation) examina-
tions.
Pupils receive a set of lessons
once a fortnight, or once a week
in some States. These are usuallv
in the form of instructional leaflets,
which take the place of textbooks.
Only for English literature and
geography subjects are textbooks
needed, and these are available in
cheap editions. Each child has
three note-books for each subject,
so that while one is being correct-
ed, the second is in the post. and
the third is being used.
Postage is free both ways. The
correction of books is very care-
fully done, with lucid explanations
The teachers call the children by
christian name, praising what has
been done well, gently reproving
untidiness, and usually including a.
little message for mother or super..
visor.
,
Parents Learn Too
All this brings about a closefriendship between teacher,
parents, and pupils, for
teachers sometimes have to instruct
supervisors as much as they du
children.
Usually the supervisors are
mothers who, despite the many
duties of the outback housewife.
are willing to do anything to help
their children receive an education.
It is noticeable that the less
educated a mother is, the more
determined she is that her children
shall learn their lessons.
One mother wrote :"I will du my
best to keep the children's wurk up
to stamlard, but when I tell you
that I have five children between
the ages of five and cleven, as well
as a tiny baby, yuu will understand
just huw difficult it is at times tf)
cupe with everything".
One mother could read only very
little herself when she applied to a
school for lessons for her first
child. When the first set arrived,
she learned the lesson herself
before giving it to the child. After
a few weeks she managed t 0 get
one set ahead. She carried on like
this for years until, in fact, her
child passed the Qualifying exami-
nation. Eventually her five children
completed the course.
Many of the children, too, do
their work under great difficulties.
One little girl who could not walk,
did everything up to the Leaving
examination hy correspondence.
Another, who lived far out on the
Nullarbor Plains, in Western
Australia, was left motherless at
the age of nine. She carried 011
bravely with cooking, bread-making.
sewing and mending for the family.
and found time to do her own
correspondence lessons and super-
vise those of her two brothers. Her
lesson books were always a model
of neatness.
One hov who was totally deaf
from birth reached grade four
after three years of correspondence
work. With inrredihle patience.
and helped by a special course of
Je""uns, hi"l1IuLher laught him to
speak and to follow the speech of
others by lip reading.
At regular times during the
week, the Australian Broadcasting
Commission gives school broadcasts,
and at times these are by a corres-
pondence school teacher. In such
case the children listen delightedly
to people they know so well by
letter, but usually have never seen.
One little girl always puts on her
best frock and brushes her hair
nicely before sitting down to her
radio lesson. Even the boys feel
that the occasion is a special one,
and habitually wash and tidy them-
selves is honour of it.
Sense Of t'olDlDunit"Life
S U\IETL\IES, of COllI'se. lIle childrelldo meet their teaehers. for
"* families are encouraged to
visit the school when they come
down to the cities, and hundreds of
them do so. In this way, close
personal attachments grow. and
teachers come to be regarded us
distant members of the family.
Besides giving formal instruction
in school subjects, the correspond-
ence schools do a great deal to
foster a sense of community life
among outback children, and to
lead their interests into wider
fields.
Not onlv children learn from the
schools. Many adults have taken
advantage of the lessons, and the
school rolls include well-sinkers,
opal miners, station hands, and
alien immigrants rivho want to
learn English.
These, then, are the correspond-
ence schools Their work is not
as well known as it should be in
the cities, but they have a very
real place in the'hearts of the
country people. This is easy to
understand, for the schools bring
friendly help to harassed mothers,
education to children who other-
wise would be untaught, and
eniIghtment where it has been
previously shut. out.
]]>
</page>
</document>
