<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="081721eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
NOVEMBER 19M - 9 Frvnch fr»nc»
A World Decade
for Cultural Development
Bibliotheca Alexandrina: revival off the first universal library
Rediscovering the Silk Roads
The gondolas off Venice
Fernando Pessoa, many poets in one
Wat Phou, treasure of Khmer civilization
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Thracian carnival These masked figures (sourvakari) taking part in Shrove Tuesday
festivities in a west Bulgarian village are engaged in a ritual which
recalls an ancient Thracian cult of Dionysus. After going from door
to door, dancing rounds and presenting their good wishes to each
family, they perform a mime which is thought to represent
the creation myth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The World Decade
for Cultural Development
by Federico Mayor
8
Bibliotheca Alexandrina
The revival ofthe world'sfirst
universal library
by Lotfallah Soliman
12
Rediscovering the Silk Roads
A major international study project
on the ancient commercial and cultural routes
between the Orient and the Occident
16
The International Fund
for the Promotion of Culture
18
Unesco-40 years, 40 artists, 40 countries
20
WatPhou
Saving a treasure
ofKhmer civilization
by Ruth Massey
24
The gondola of Venice
Floating symbol ofa city
by Arthur Gillette
30
Fernando Pessoa, many poets in one
by José Augusto Seabra
Cover: Born Alive in New Zealand, composition-
of painted metal cut-outs by Richard Killeen,
of New Zealand. Back cover: Dancing Couple,
patchwork painting by Pacita Abad, a Filipino
artist.
Both works appear in an album of artworks
entitled Unesco: 40 ans, 40 artistes, 40 pays
(see pages 18-19).
The Courier J
A window open on the world 41 stye;
Published monthly in 35 languages English
French Spanish Russian German
Arabic Japanese Italian Hindi
Tamil Hebrew Persian Dutch
Portuguese Turkish Urdu Catalan
Malaysian Korean Swahili Croato-
Serb Macedonian Serbo-Croat
Slovene Chinese Bulgarian Greek
Sinhala Finnish Swedish Basque
Thai Vietnamese Pashto Hausa
An international effort in southeast Asia to save an
ancient Khmer temple from the encroaching
jungle; a massive enterprise in Alexandria to create
an ultra-modern institution that will be a worthy
successor of one of the wonders of the Hellenistic
world, the Library founded by the Ptolemies with
the aim of assembling "the books of all the peoples
on Earth" ; a major international project to study
the "Silk Roads", the great commercial and
cultural arteries which once linked China and
the West; commemoration of the life and work
of a modern Portuguese poet the articles in
this issue evoke just four of the many thousands of
cultural activities in which Unesco is currently
co-operating.
They assume a special significance this year,
which marks the beginning of the World Decade
for Cultural Development (1988-1997)
proclaimed by the General Assembly of the
United Nations and "placed under the auspices of
the United Nations and Unesco". The
fundamental aim of the Decade, which is
introduced in the article overleaf by the Director-
General of Unesco, Mr. Federico Mayor, is to
restore cultural and human values to their central
place in technological and economic development.
Unesco has drawn up a detailed Plan of Action
for the Decade which invites the fullest possible
participation from the international community as
a whole. The Unesco Courier will periodically be
publishing reports on efforts carried out within
the context of the Plan, as part of its mission to
present to its readers the multifarious
achievements of human creativity all over the
world and to encourage a dialogue between
cultures rooted in mutual respect and freedom of
expression.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The World Decade
for Cultural Development
Thrust (1959), oil on canvas by the American artist Adolph Gottlieb
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Logo of
the World Decade
for Cultural Development
(see photo page 6)
BY FEDERICO MAYOR
Director-General of Unesco
THE experience of the last two decades has shown that
culture cannot be dissociated from development in
any society, whatever its level of economic growth or
its political and economic orientation.
Culture is an intrinsic part of the life and awareness
conscious and unconscious of individuals and communities.
It is a living fund of the creative activity, past and present,
which has shaped over the centuries the system of values,
traditions and tastes which defines the distinctive genius of a
people. Thus culture is bound to make an imprint on economic
activity and define the strengths and weaknesses of a society's
productive processes.
These conclusions emerge from the experience, both posi¬
tive and negative, of all countries. Whenever a country has set
itself the target of economic growth without reference to its
cultural environment, grave economic and cultural imbalances
have resulted and its creative potential has been seriously
weakened. Genuine development must be based on the best
possible use of the human resources and material wealth of the
community. Thus in the final analysis the priorities, motiva¬
tions and objectives of development must be found in culture.
But in the past this has been conspicuously ignored.
From now on culture should be regarded as a direct source
of inspiration for development, and in return, development
should assign to culture a central role as a social regulator.
This imperative applies not only to developing countries,
where economic extraversion and cultural alienation have
clearly and sometimes dramatically widened the gap between
the creative and productive processes. It is also increasingly
vital for the industrialized countries, where the headlong race
for growth in material wealth is detrimental to the spiritual,
ethical and aesthetic aspects of life, and creates much dishar¬
mony between man and the natural environment.
The same imperative applies to the relations between na¬
tions and between regions, at a time when the processes of
social change are rapidly becoming worldwide in scope a
phenomenon which is encouraging a growing exchange of
ideas, individuals and goods and is bringing people and nations
closer together, but which is also leading to a dangerous
uniformity of cultural values, and increasing the inequality of
opportunities for progress at world level. As a consequence,
human creative diversity may be impoverished and the
domination of those who define these values may increase.
A skilfully managed linkage between culture and develop¬
ment can make it possible to strengthen creative identities, to
inhibit standardization, and to encourage greater equality of
opportunity for self-expression for different cultures, thereby
promoting increasingly fruitful exchanges between them.
Such a linkage must be based on the rejection of any discrimi¬
nation, either between nations or between individuals, and on
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
the assertion of the universal humanist values of democracy,
justice and solidarity, without which no dialogue is possible. It
must be based on the encouragement of freedom of research,
invention and innovation which is the prime condition for any
cultural life.
Thus every effort must be made to allow creative diversity
to prevail over the dead hand of standardization, the basic
aspirations of mankind to prevail over the conflicts of interest
groups, and human solidarity to prevail through the free
self-expression of the individual.
As I remarked at the ceremony held to launch the World
Decade for Cultural Development on 21 January 1988, the
aim of the Decade is to promote awareness of the cultural
imperative and to foster a new state of mind that will lead to
the emergence of a variety of proposals devoted to "a diversity
which unites, a creativity which brings together, and a solidar¬
ity which liberates".
The four major objectives of the Decade constitute guide¬
lines rather than a rigid framework:
Acknowledgment ofthe cultural dimension ofdevelopment:
ways must be found in which production and creativity can be
linked, and economics can be rooted in culture.
Affirmation and enrichment of cultural identities: the en¬
couragement of all individual and collective talents and
initiatives.
Broadening participation in cultural life: mobilizing the
forces of freedom of expression and creativity in the individual
and the community, in the name of human rights, free will and
independence of mind.
Promotion of international cultural co-operation: seeking,
increasing and strengthening the means whereby a culture
freely draws sustenance from others and in turn nourishes
them, while respecting a nucleus of universally accepted
truths.
The Director-General of Unesco, Mr. Federico Mayor (right),
receives the logo of the World Decade for Cultural Development
(1988-1997) from its designer, Hans Erni, at a ceremony held
to launch the Decade on 21 January 1988. The artist describes his
design as "Five faces from the five continents of the Earth
symbolizing the manifold creativity of social and cultural life.
Expressing the joy of living, they are seen against the sunlight whose
rays reflect the many and varied aspects of Unesco's work."
Mahaweli Community Radio
(MCR), Sri Lanka's first regional
radio station, was set up with
Unesco assistance and funding from
DANIDA (Danish International
Development Agency). The service
is aimed at some one million farming
families who were moved
between 1977 and 1986 when dams
and irrigation canals were being
constructed along the course of the
Mahaweli River, in the northeast of
the island. The station broadcasts
reports from areas where the
farmers have been relocated and
programmes on local cultural
events. It also sponsors a street
theatre group and their musicians
(photos 1 and 2), who perform plays
based on the daily life of the villagers
and linked to development problems
such as the impact of
modernization, destruction of the
forests, or disputes in the
community. After the performance,
an MCR reporter interviews village
elders to record their reactions
(photo 3).
The improvement of living
conditions in urban settlements
with a low quality of life is one of the
priorities set forth in Unesco's Plan
of Action for the World Decade for
Cultural Development. Several
Unesco-supportcd projects in the
field are already under way,
including one to rehabilitate the
Barrio Río Salado (right), a riverside
settlement near La Romana in the
Dominican Republic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The revival of the world's first
universal library
.
.
m K¿yy.
^
j Ef'OiEI
...
Hellenistic mosaic by Sofitos II
represents an allegory of the city of Alexandria
The Greek mathematician Eratosthenes (284-
192 BC), who calculated the circumference of
the Earth, was also the father of geography. His
geographical system, reconstituted in 1 803 on
this map by the French geographer Pascal
François Joseph Gosselin, was of fundamental
importance to the development of
mathematical geography. Eratosthenes, called
to Alexandria by King Ptolemy II, became
director of the great Library there.
Alexander the Great is said to
have been welcomed in Egypt
as a liberator. He showed great
respect for the people's customs and
beliefs, and as a professed defender of
religion, won the support of the priests.
He openly consulted the Egyptian ora¬
cles, particularly that of Amon, to
which he journeyed with great cere¬
mony. Moreover, he very quickly
understood the central role which
Egypt could play in the expansion of
world trade, and he lost no time in
lending his support to it.
One of the most far-reaching deci¬
sions that Alexander made in this con¬
nection was to found the city of
Alexandria. Legend has it that he
chose the location himself a small
- - -. --* .^
O
T i <2 ' r.
V
ln>-' äs
c
T * « i
t'Mdt S\r"r
1. i B V r
h«*UhuUr
TTTT *T
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Bibliotheca Alexandrina
BY LOTFALLAH SOLIMAN
Mediterranean port whose site had
attracted him, as the shelter of the
offshore island of Pharos formed two
natural harbours, ideal as a Greek naval
base. Legend also relates that Alexander
personally traced out the boundaries of
the new city, construction of which
began in 332 BC to the design of the
Rhodian architect Dinocrates.
Thanks to its favourable geographical
situation and its shrewdly designed
port, Alexandria became one of the
most renowned commercial and mari¬
time crossroads of Antiquity. Until it
was conquered by the Arabs in 641 AD,
the city played a major role in Egypt's
history.
When Alexandria was first built its
population included, in addition to the
0 c f
l N
.RAPHiQVK n Kh vrosrin m
^"- PFJ OmwiUMm, vim t m
SK""^rtl/
indigenous Egyptians, the Macedonian
guard, a colony of Greek immigrants
and a Jewish minority. The city grew
rapidly, and during the rule of King
Ptolemy I Soter* it welcomed many
scholars and artists, who enjoyed royal
protection and patronage. The king
closely followed the spirit of the policies
instituted by Alexander. Respectful of
the local civic and political institutions,
creeds and religions, he created a climate
of tolerance and security in Egypt that
was exceptionally favourable to cul¬
tural development. Thanks to him,
Alexandria began to approach its
founder's dream of an ideal capital city,
an illustrious centre of intellectual and
artistic influence.
Ptolemy 1 ordered the construction of
:	:	 ,	
the famous Pharos lighthouse, one of
the seven wonders of the ancient world,
and during his reign plans were laid for
the most celebrated public library of
Antiquity, the Library of Alexandria.
His son, Ptolemy II Philadelphus
(308-246 BC), brought the library pro¬
ject to fruition. At the same time, he
made Alexandria the world's leading
commercial centre. Greeks, Romans,
Ethiopians and Jews came to this cos¬
mopolitan city to conduct their business
among copyists, clerks, librarians, inter¬
preters, ambassadors, court officials and
public administrators. A patron of the
arts and of literature, Ptolemy II sur¬
rounded himself with eminent scholars
and poets, including Callimachus
(died 240 BC), whose name would
come to be associated with the expan¬
sion of the great Library.
The first known library is thought to
have been built at Memphis, where visi¬
tors were welcomed by the words
"Medicines for the Soul". However,-
when Ptolemy I decided to create a lib¬
rary in Alexandria, he chose to model it
on that of Aristotle in Athens. He may
have even acquired the books from
Aristotle's library, one of the richest
collections of Antiquity.
Right from the start attempts were
made to obtain copies of all the works of
Greek literature for the Alexandrian
Library. This objective was soon
achieved, however, and copies of all
works of good quality in other lan¬
guages were sought. Finally, complete
universality became the goal, and the
Library tried to obtain copies of all .
existing manuscripts.
Acquiring these copies became one of
" Ptolemy Soter ("the Saviour"), Macedonian general of
Alexander the Great, became ruler of Egypt (323-
285 BC) on Alexander's death. Editor.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
.:,V^yW%
the main tasks of the librarians, who
arranged for all known works to be sent
on loan from Athens in return for a
deposit, and to be borrowed long
enough to make one, or sometimes
several copies. Manuscripts found on
ships moored in the harbour were also
temporarily "confiscated" and copied.
Thanks to this gigantic effort to col¬
lect and conserve writings from all over
the world, the Library of Alexandria
became the first truly universal library
in history and attracted the most emi¬
nent philosophers, scholars and re¬
searchers of their day. The exact number
of papyrus scrolls which made up the
collection is not known. Estimates vary
between 400,000 and 700,000, as one
scroll could contain several works, just
as a single work could cover several
scrolls.
The Library did not confine itself to
collecting manuscripts written in their
original languages; it also embarked on a
massive translation programme. For ex¬
ample, seventy-two Jewish scholars
were given the task of translating the
Old Testament into Greek, and transla¬
tions of Babylonian and Buddhist
manuscripts were commissioned.
It was also the first library in history
to establish a set of rules for the classi
fication and inventory of its collection.
The monumental catalogue was com¬
piled by Callimachus, who perfected a
method of retrieving each work,
together with a synopsis or even a critic¬
al appraisal. These listings, known as the
"Pinakes", from the Greek word for
"tablets", have unfortunately been lost.
Records of them from the ancient world
are sufficiently abundant, however, to
give an idea of the enormity of the task.
The Library of Alexandria formed
part of a larger complex, the Mouseion
("Museum", or temple of the Muses), a
research institute which opened its
doors to the arts and the sciences, with
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Among the scholars attracted by the intellectual
climate ofAlexandria was Euclid, who founded a
celebrated school of mathematics there in the
3rd century BC. In this engraving by the French
artist Jean François Pierre Peyron (1744-1814),
Euclid is shown giving a geometry lesson.
an astronomical observatory, a zoo¬
logical and botanical garden, and.
meeting rooms.
Thus some of the greatest scholars
and creative artists lived in or visited
Alexandria, delving into the Library's
priceless treasures to help them in their
work and their discoveries. An intellec¬
tual and cultural movement grew up
around them, embracing all fields of
knowledge and creativity.
Among these men were Herophilus
(c. 340-300 BC), who established the
rules of anatomy and physiology;
Euclid (330-280 BC), the inventor of
geometry; Eratosthenes (284-192 BC),
who calculated the circumference of the
Earth; Aristarchus (215-143 BC) and
Dionysius Thrax (1 70-90 BC), who sys¬
tematized the grammar of classical
Greek; Hero (fl. 62 AD), who wrote
several books on geometry and mecha¬
nics and invented the dioptre, a sur¬
veying instrument; and Claudius
Ptolemaeus (90-168 AD), founder of
cartography and developer of astro¬
nomy. Thus the Library played a vital
role in the development of Graeco-
Roman culture.
Nothing remains today of this monu¬
ment to human genius. It is thought that
the main part of the collection was des¬
troyed in a fire which ravaged the port
when Julius Caesar took Alexandria
in 48 BC. Mark Antony made amends
for the damage to a certain extent when
he gave Cleopatra the rich collection of
the library at Pergamum (Asia Minor).
This library, carefully built up by
Eumenes II, the king of Pergamum, is
thought to have possessed some
200,000 works written, for the first
time, on parchment.
The astronomer and geographer Claudius
Ptolemaeus (90-168 AD) is shown in the
observatory at Alexandria in this engraving by
the 19th-century French artist Charles Laplante.
Other catastrophes were to follow, as
if to emphasize the great fragility of
works of the mind. The Library and the
Museum of Alexandria may have been
destroyed in the civil war which tore
Egypt apart in the third century AD.
But Alexander's dream was not in
vain. The Government of Egypt and the
University of Alexandria, in collabora¬
tion with Unesco and the United
Nations Development Programme
(UNDP), have initiated a project to
revive the famous Library. It is intended
to endow the new Library with modern
facilities which should enable it, at the
dawn of the third millennium, again to
fulfil its ancient role. But this time it
will be linked by computer with ar¬
chives and documentation centres all
over the world. While recapturing the
spirit of the original, the new Library
of Alexandria will, at last, be
indestructible.
LOTFALLAH SOLIMAN, Egyptian writer and
journalist, is currently preparing a study on the
history of Palestine.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A major international study project on the
\'Z<.
ÍT
m
Two cities on the Silk Roads, thousands
of kilometres apart: Venice, Italy (above)
and Xian, China (below).
r VZT,i ' ^THBT'**.''7»^-.-.'.. .1
FOR many centuries caravans of
merchants passed beneath the
western gate of the city of Xian,
capital of China during the Tang
Dynasty, their camels laden with luxury
goods that would find ready buyers in
the markets of Europe over 6,000 kilo¬
metres away. Most famous of the com¬
modities they bore on their hazardous
journey through the deserts, steppeland
AK^
~.*T
fuESP m i '
«f - VI
*»«£jjgp
.
J" - * -
- ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
ancient commercial and cultural routes between the Orient and the Occident
Rediscovering the Silk Roads
and mountain passes of Central Asia
was silk, the precious fabric whose
manufacturing secrets China guarded
for thousands of years. It was this that
caused the nineteenth-century German
geographer and geologist Ferdinand
von Richthofen to coin a new term to
describe the caravan routes that thus
linked East and West the Seiden¬
strassen, the Silk Roads.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Silk was not the only cargo carried by
the caravans, nor was the traffic only
one-way. A host of natural and man-
made products ranging from bronze and
porcelain to wool and cobalt were trans¬
ported over the centuries from East to
West and West to East. Above all the
Silk Roads, with their overland and
maritime extensions westwards as far as
Rome, Venice and Cadiz, and eastwards
as far as Nara, were a channel for the
spread of ideas, technologies, religious
concepts and the arts, and contributed
to the cross-fertilization between
civilizations.
Many studies have been made of these
great arteries of cultural and commercial
exchange by scholars acting individually
or with academic institutions. So far,
however, no complete study of an inter¬
disciplinary nature has been carried out
by a truly international team. Now, as
part of an important new Unesco pro¬
ject within the framework of the World
Decade for Cultural Development,
scholars and scientists from many
different fields of study and many
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Three poster designs created by the Japanese artist Ikuo Hirayama
for Unesco's major project entitled
"Integral Study of the Silk Roads: Roads of Dialogue"
countries are preparing to follow in the
footsteps of the merchants of old.
The project, entitled "Integral Study
of the Silk Roads: Roads of Dialogue",
was approved by Unesco's General
Conference in 1987. It is still in its early
stages but has already been warmly wel¬
comed by scientific circles, non-gov¬
ernmental organizations and the media.
Over the next five years it will involve
over a thousand specialists working in
close co-operation with the more than
thirty countries situated along the old
Silk Roads.
It will provide an opportunity to redis¬
cover the three major routes, which will
be followed by a caravan consisting of an
international team of scholars. Some fif¬
teen international seminars will be held at
the key sites and meetings will be orga¬
nized at each place with scholars from the
locality or country concerned.
Interdisciplinary co-operation on the
widest possible scale is hoped for, with
specialists in such fields as paleogeogra-
phy and paleoethnography clarifying
such questions as the ecology of the
Silk Roads.
Some thirty associated projects are
planned. For one of them the Sultanate
of Oman has agreed to put an Omani
ship, the Fulk Al-Salamah ("Ship of
Peace") at the disposal of Unesco for a
maritime expedition to be known as the
"Voyage of Dialogue". With some
thirty scholars and scientists on board,
the ship will set sail from Venice (Italy)
late in 1 990 and arrive in Osaka (Japan) a
hundred days later after calling at over
thirty ports in some twenty countries.
The itinerary of the "Ship of Peace" will
also include places in which Unesco is
engaged in the field such as Alexandria
(see page 8), and also the city of Sana'a in
the Yemen Arab Republic and the his¬
toric site of Shibam in Democratic
Yemen, both of which will be restored
with the help of Unesco.
Other associated projects include a
sea voyage on board the Cocachin, an
ancient Chinese junk, which will set sail
next November to retrace Marco Polo's
homeward trip from Cathay, also mak¬
ing a technical and scientific reconnaiss¬
ance for the 1990 expedition.
Two other expeditions planned for
next year include one from the Chinese
capital Beijing across the Gobi desert to
Ulan Bator in Mongolia, possibly
continuing as far as Minussinsk in
Siberia. Another, in autumn 1989, will
travel from Odessa to Baku on the
Caspian Sea.
An Historical Atlas of the Silk Roads
is also planned. The latest technology
such as remote sensing techniques and
computer animation will be used in its
preparation, and, in the spirit of the
project ¿s a whole, the Atlas is intended
to be of value to the general public as
well as the scholarly community.
The Silk Roads project will culminate
in two events of international import¬
ance which will take place in Paris in
1992: a conference to review the studies
which have been carried out and a major
exhibition bringing together important
collections for the first time.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The International Fund
for the Promotion
of Culture
The International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture is unique in the sense that it is
Unesco's only organ created by inter¬
governmental decision that operates on the
basis of direct contact with private and public
institutions, groups and individuals active in a
myriad of. cultural fields. This makes the Fund a
flexible and fast-moving mechanism.
While it is staffed by members of Unesco's
Secretariat, the Fund's policy- and decision¬
making are entrusted to an autonomous fifteen-
member Administrative Council. Men and
women of distinguished achievement in the arts,
cultural administration and finance, the mem¬
bers of the Council are chosen in their personal
capacities by the Director-General. Thus they
speak not on behalf of governments but for
themselves, and in the name of innovation,
creativity and cultural values.
Giving a concrete boost to the notion of the
cultural dimension of development was a basic
motivating factor in the Fund's creation. The
original idea of an international "cultural bank"
was launched in 1970 by Mr. Edward Seaga,
now Prime Minister of Jamaica and then Minister
of Finance and Planning, who crystallized the
thinking of a small band of pioneers struggling to
release culture from the vicious circles of in¬
adequate funding. Their efforts to nurture an
international financial institution to provide and
promote direct support for cultural activities gra¬
dually gained momentum. By the end of the
1970s, generous donations from governments
(principally Venezuela, Saudi Arabia and the
Islamic Republic of Iran), supplemented by con¬
tributions from bodies such as the Gulbenkian
Foundation, the Agnelli Foundation, the Lee
Foundation (Singapore), the Association of
Hellenic Banks, the Tata Trust (India), the A.G.
Leventis Foundation, the Hamdard Foundation
(Pakistan), the Kuwait Foundation for the
Advancement of Science and Technology, and
the International Cultural Society of the Republic
of Korea, made for a handsome endowment.
The total of Fund contributions and earnings
now approaches the $9 million mark. Since it
began its operations the Fund has lent its sup
port to some 273 projects in 85 different coun- '
tries. While funding has been generally limited to
"seed money", the Fund's support has taken a
multitude of other practical forms, calling upon
the human and institutional resources and net¬
works at Unesco's command. The Fund's invest¬
ments in cultural creativity and infrastructure
development have covered fields too numerous
to be listed here, but the examples cited in these
pages should reflect some of that polyvalence.
The Fund is clearly an ¡deal instrument to help
achieve tangible and exemplary results during
the World Decade for Cultural Development, for
the goals It has pursued since 1977 anticipate
the ambitious worldwide purposes now defined.
The challenge of the Decade in turn highlights
the challenges now facing the Fund.
First and foremost is the challenge of fund-
raising, so as to make the Fund itself a more
powerful and influential instrument. A linked
challenge is that of focusing the Fund's activi¬
ties, after over ten years of very broad-based
operations. Concentration on the areas of emph¬
asis identified for the World Decade is bound to
yield effective synergisms resulting in more sig¬
nificant projects. This in turn implies a more
"pro-active" role for the Fund as a broker of
innovative ideas, in identifying means of im¬
plementing them, in using its own resources to
build partnerships and networks and in securing
complementary financing for them. In so doing
the Fund will also fulfil one of its statutory pur¬
poses, that of serving as a clearing-house
for information on the financing of cultural
development.
While the Decade seeks above all to achieve a
new state of mind, this truer awareness of the
cultural dimension of development must lead to
tangible results: increased investment in cultural
activities the world over. Meeting that goal will
not be easy, as the Fund's own experience has
shown. But even small sums can go a long way,
provided they initiate really well-designed pro¬
jects that are able to catalyze resources and
mobilize support at all levels, achieving in cul-
xiral terms that elusive "multiplier effect".
In 1981 the Government ofJamaica, with
assistance from the Fund, set up a "memory
bank" to record theJamaican people's heritage
enshrined in oral traditions, music, poetry,
customs and beliefs. Right, a farmer explains to
a memory bank interviewer how cassava is
grown, while three other farmers listen
intently. The use of cassava has been inherited
from the Arawak Indians who inhabited
Jamaica when Christopher Columbus arrived
therein 1494.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
In 1987 the first part of a new five-volume
history of Korean music was published by the
National Commission for Unesco of the
Republic of Korea, with the assistance of
Unesco's International Fund for the Promotion
of Culture. The fully illustrated books will cover
ritual Buddhist chants, courtly music, musical
notations and musical instruments. With their
accompanying cassettes they will constitute an
anthology of the different currents forming the
Korean musical tradition. Left, cover
illustration of the first volume.
The National Museum of Mali, established
in 1982, has become a focal point in Mali's
cultural life through its spread of activities
(below) ranging from the preservation of the
cultural heritage and the training of specialists
to art and environmental education. With the
Fund's financial assistance, the Museum has
purchased audio-visual equipment enabling it
to extend its activities to the country as a whole.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The five works reproduced on this
double page are among those shown at
an exhibition held in October 1986 to
mark Unesco's fortieth anniversary.
The exhibition, which was organized
by the International Association of
Art and held at Unesco's Paris
Headquarters, featured works created
for the occasion by forty artists from
forty countries. The catalogue has
now been published in the Unesco
Collection of Representative Works
under the title Unesco: 40 ans,
40 artistes, 40 pays ("Unesco: 40 years,
40 artists, 40 countries"; La
Bibliothèque des Arts, Paris/Unesco,
1988). Each work is an expression of a
distinctive cultural identity. As an
introductory text to the catalogue
points out, "The murmuring of
cultural waves and winds is crossing
the Americas, and rippling from Asia
to Africa, carrying echoes from
Europe and the wide Pacific. In the
late twentieth century nothing lies
outside the bounds of the artist's
curiosity, but at the same time
nothing can make the artist reject
what is dearest to him in his past
and present." ,
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
years
artists
countries
2 3
1 . Oil on canvas by Hoiyung Tai (China),
inspired by a 4th-century Chinese silk scroll
painting entitled TheMonitor's Instruction to the
Ladies ofthe Court.
2. "Sugar Loaf Mountain", copper and wood
composition using earth and rock pigments
mixed with acrylic resin, by Manfredo de
Souzanetto (Brazil), echoes the famous rock
formation in Rio de Janeiro bay.
3. "Fragment of Relief", oil on canvas by
András Felvidéki (Hungary), is influenced by
Graeco-Roman art and classical architecture.
4. "The Inconsolable Space or Love as a
Memory", traditional ink on clay panel by
Mahmoud Rachid Koraïchi (Algeria). Here the
artist has used the Tassili n'Ajjer rock paintings
as his inspiration.
5. "Festival", oil on canvas by Nadejda Kouteva
(Bulgaria), whose work draws on her country's
folk traditions.
	 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Lao musicians playing
traditional instruments
it the bad welcome ceremony
WAT PHOU
$£* *
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Saving a treasure
of Khmer civilization
BY RUTH MASSEY
The northern temple,
built in the 11th century.
of the Sanctuary
of Vat Phou
	3Lt
CHAMPASSAK was animated de¬
spite the sweltering heat of
mid-morning. Women dres¬
sed in sarong-like skirts and white
blouses converged on the community
hall that overlooks the palm-shaded
river meandering through the village.
The women of Champassak had been
cooking for several days. Enough rice,
fish, pork and poultry had been pre¬
pared to feed the whole village and its
guests. Many of the men were inside the
community hall awaiting the arrival of a
group of visitors from Vientiane, the
capital of their country, the Lao Peo¬
ple's Democratic Republic. They had
seen the orange dust cloud in the wake
of the vehicle bearing the visitors long
before it came to a halt in front of the
hall. The group of men and women who
emerged Lao, American, Indian,
Bulgarian and British-had all been
waiting for this moment: their first
glimpse of Wat Phou, the legendary
temple that had been built in this
remote corner of Laos in the days of the
Khmer empire.
While the elders led the visitors into
the community hall, the village orches¬
tra struck up an undulating rhythmic
song played on traditional instruments:
flutes, clarinets, xylophones with bam¬
boo crosspieces, drums, cymbals, and
the khen, a hand-held pipe organ that is
the national instrument. In a large room,
about seventy men sat around a centre¬
piece in the form of a tree made from
banana leaves and flowers and sur¬
rounded by symbolic foods. The had
ceremony, marking the importance of
the occasion, was about to start. While a
lay priest intoned benedictions and
prayers, the villagers tied cotton strips
around the wrists of their guests, sym¬
bolizing good health, prosperity and
happiness.
At the banquet that followed the had,
women served steaming dishes of fish,
pork and chicken and the staple of all
Lao mealssticky rice. There were
toasts in lau lao, the potent locally-
brewed rice liquor, followed by
speeches dedicated to the purpose of the
gathering: the restoration of Wat Phou.
Built by the Khmer kings on the
slopes of the mountain that emerges
from the forest surrounding the village,
Wat Phou is in ruins. Champassak was
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
celebrating the fact that the temple was
about to be saved from the tidal wave of
vegetation in which the heavenly dan¬
cers of its bas-reliefs were drowning.
The visitors represented years of effort
by the Government of Laos and the
international community to save this
national treasure, efforts that had cul¬
minated in the United Nations De¬
velopment Programme (UNDP) and
Unesco agreeing to finance and assist in
the renovation work, and in the estab¬
lishment of a museum in Champassak to
house some of Wat Phou's more vulner¬
able artefacts.
Two hundred years older than
Angkor Wat in Democratic Kam¬
puchea, Wat Phou was built in the
second half of the fifth century. At that
time it was a centre of kingly power on
the lower Mekong River, one of a col¬
lection of principalities stretching along
the coast but extending inland to en¬
compass what is now southern Laos.
The temple was the site of a cult closely
associated with the Indianized monar¬
chies of ancient Indochina, part of the
vast Khmer empire that, some 200 years
later, made Angkor its capital.
The speeches over, the group from
Vientiane, accompanied by village
elders, drove the short distance through
the forest to the temple. A long cause¬
way led them into the centre of an
architectural composition whose
ancient stones were bathed in the golden
light of the late afternoon.
Rising above the Mekong River, Wat
Phou is a majestic ruin covered with a
mantle of vegetation, a symbol of what
the Lao themselves had suffered and
withstood invasions, colonialism and
wars. Nowadays, Wat Phou's battle is
against the vegetation that relentlessly
attacks its ancient stones. The conflict is
between the ruins and the jungle which
has overrun them.
At the end of the causeway, two ex¬
quisite rectangular pavilions made of
sandstone stand near a large artificial
lake, believed by the Khmers to have
possessed extraordinary purificatory
powers. For the god-kings of the Khmer
empire Wat Phou was a favourite royal
bathing place, with its grand approach,
its majestic flight of steps flanked by
statues of lions and mythical animals.
Today the lions are faceless and the
statues have lost their heads. Buffaloes
stand motionless in the once virtuous
waters of the lake, only their heads
showing.
The rectangular pavilions used to be
temples for segregated worshipone
for women and the other for men. Roots
follow the outlines of the masonry along
the temple walls, mimicking the
architectural motifs which they cover. A
whole section of wall is cracked and
prevented from disintegration by the
roots' embrace. Ferns and underbrush
have attached themselves to walls,
screening the idealized representations
of the Khmer aristocracy, while beneath
the onslaught of vegetation, the power¬
ful Brahman gods of the Khmer
empire Krishna, Vishnu and Indra
riding the elephant Airavata are
slowly suffocating.
A wide avenue leads from the temples
to a majestic stairway carved into the
side of the mountain. At the top is the
sanctuary which had once housed the
idol of the cult. Here time has wrought
wonders with the sandstone, and the
sun and rain have softened the decora¬
tive instincts of the Khmers. Local
legend has it that the Emerald Buddha,
which now sits in Bangkok, is a fake and
that the authentic one is hidden here.
Behind the sanctuary the side of the
mountain rises perpendicularly to the
skies. From here it is easy to imagine the
beauty of this site in its prime. The view
spreads out harmoniously from moun¬
tain to plain. First the sanctuary, then
the immense staircase interspersed by
large terraces, the esplanade with the
two rectangular temples, the artificial
lake, the park, the forest and, beyond it,
the course of the majestic Mekong flow¬
ing towards the horizon.
By the time the visitors had climbed
down the stairway and reached the fore¬
court, the day was waning. A group of
boys strolled through the ruins. They
had come to this once exclusive place to
burn incense-sticks at a small Buddhist
Detail of a carved portal from Wat Phou
("mountain temple"), before restoration. This
immense temple complex, the oldest part of
which dates from the 5th century AD, is located
in the south of the Lao People's Democratic
Republic.
shrine made of sticks and paper. It was
all that was left from a festival that had
been held in the previous month. For
four days Wat Phou had basked in some
of its ancient splendour, with proces¬
sions and fireworks and hundreds of
people from the surrounding regions
chanting and praying to the rhythm of
the khen and the deep sounds of gongs.
In just over an hour night would de¬
scend over the mountain sanctuary. The
last rays of the sun lit up the growth of
tropical vegetation, highlighting the de¬
terioration of the buildings. The task of
restoration is immense and greatly ex¬
ceeds the resources of the Government
of Laos. In associating itself with the
efforts of the Lao people, the world
community will help to conserve a
monumental site which is not only the
work of a particular people, but also
belongs to the common heritage of
mankind.
RUTH MASSEY is an Information Officer with
the United Nations Development Programme in
New York.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
These and other ancient statues from Wat Phou
are now conserved in the site museum, in the
neighbouring village of Champassak.
¿r*.
-.vs ^Z^P^?S - ^Z%j^.yCZ^.
	< -_c stairway and terraces ¿(fil " V* ^.	. B-_\
.'3¿N»^>^»r main sanctuary >-""'-
- '^" "
northern temple
as ;
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The gondola of Venice
Gondolas moored on a Venetian canal, sterns riding high out of the water
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Floating symbol of a city
BY ARTHUR GILLETTE
Like the Yankee clipperships and
Arab dhows, the Venetian gon¬
dola is both a specific craft and
part of a myth.
Strangely, the boat that has come to
symbolize Venice, and that exists no¬
where else in the world, may well not be
Venetian in origin. There is a semantic
wrangle about the word itself. Some
etymologists think it is a corruption of
the Greek konkula ("hard little peel").
Others trace it to khontilas (Greek for
"short boat"). A further explanation
points to the similarity between the
shapes of the gondola and a Roman boat
of the fourth century AD with the
hypothetical name fundula.
The first hard evidence of the gondo¬
la's existence in Venice goes back
to 1094, when Doge (Duke) Vito Falier
issued a charter granting certain Lagoon
villagers the right to build a gondula.
Over the centuries, the craft has
evolved continually. Today's gondola is
the product of unceasing changes and
improvements made in response to the
socio-economic development of Venice
itself. Its history is a kind of maritime
application of Darwin's theory of evo¬
lution, a dialectical relationship between
a boat and its geographical and human
surroundings.
Venice grew into a city from a loose
federation of scattered villages. As its
population increased, a network of can¬
als was dug. The network spread and
became increasingly dense until it
formed the watery maze we know
today, which the twentieth-century
town planner and architect Le
Corbusier called "a perfect cardiac sys¬
tem". This very specific kind of urban
development, which could never de¬
pend to a very great extent on animal
transport, required a craft able to carry
more and more people over lengthening
distances through narrow, hard-to-
negotiate canals at ever-swifter speeds.
The gondola evolved in response to
those changing needs.
The gondola is renowned for its svelte
line, and the hull exudes the excitement
of a racer. Odd as it may seem in such a
feline craft, the boat is flat-bottomed
and has been since its inception, the
adjective "flat" being used by
Doge Falier in the eleventh-century
manuscript mentioned above. This
minimal draught was perfectly adapted
to the Venetians' amphibious existence,
first among the marshes of the Lagoon,
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
then along the city's canals. The canals
are shallow and the gondola flat-
bottomed to this day.
The first known blueprint of a gondo¬
la, drawn up in 1555 at the Arsenale
shipyard, shows that after at least
500 years' evolution, the boat already
had a diminutive beam. During the next
four centuries, it narrowed even further.
Now, the generally practised overall
length is 10.87 metres, for a beam
measuring a mere 1.42 metres, a ratio
of 7.7:1.
A narrowed beam coupled with the
need to ferry more passengers made it
impossible for the gondolier to stand, as
he previously had done, inside his craft.
As a consequence, a perch was built for
him in the shape of a poop deck flush
with the gunwhales as far astern as pos¬
sible. The rower's upright position gave
rise, in turn, to two further innovations
that are peculiar to gondola navigation.
The first is a long heavy sweep oar.
Fashioned from a single length of beech,
this oar is 4.2 metres in length and
weighs a daunting 4.3 kilos. These ex¬
ceptional characteristics require a strong
rower, but also give him extraordinary
leverage. They also call for considerable
dexterity.
The second improvement required by
the gondolier's standing position was a
sturdy, high and curiously shaped oar
lock. Called the foreóla ("fork"), and
looking like a gnarled little tree trunk, it
is hewn from a block of walnut. In
addition to being a striking piece of
sculpture, it serves as an ingenious
multipurpose fulcrum. Pivoting his oar
from one or other of the lip-like
indentations in the stern side of the fork,
the gondolier can choose between a fas¬
ter and a slower forward speed.
Displaced to the extreme stern of the
boat, the gondolier's 50 to 70 kilos
made it imperative to provide a counter¬
weight at the bows. So came into exist-
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Races of gondolas and other typically Venetian
craft had become popular by the late
15th century. Both men and women competed,
as can be seen in the engraving (left) by the
Italian artist Giacomo Franco (1556-1620). The
Regata Storica(above), one of Venice's
traditional festivals, has taken place along the
Grand Canal in September for seven centuries.
It opens with a magnificent procession of
gondolas and other Venetian craft with persons
in historical costume on board.
The construction of gondolas is a dying
industry. One of the last Venetian gondola
yards, at San Trovaso, is being restored with
the aid of an International Committee for the
Defence of the Gondola which was set up with
Unesco backing.
ence il ferro ("the steel"), a heavy steel
blade from which protrude six horizon¬
tal "teeth". These are said to symbolize
the six historical quarters of Venice,
while the cornucopia-like metal plume
atop theferro is thought to represent the
shape of the Doge's ritual hat.
The above innovations seem to have
been more or less fully integrated into
the gondola by the end of the sixteenth
century. But the craft's gradually ex¬
tended length and increased weight en¬
hanced friction. To overcome this prob¬
lem, the stem and stern of the gondola
were progressively lifted out of the
water, to reduce wetted surface and con¬
sequent drag. Today, only the central
three-fifths of the hull are submerged,
leading a Venetian author to compare
the gondola to "a half moon posed on
the Lagoon".
The gondola continued to evolve into
the twentieth century, when the last two
characteristics that make the craft truly
unique were refined to perfection. To
grasp them, look at an empty gondola
moored between two piles. It is im¬
possible not to notice that the gondola is
unbalanced (it lists sharply to starboard)
and twisted (the hull is markedly
assymetrical). What purpose is served
by these bizarre features?
Already four centuries ago, but parti¬
cularly after the fall of the Venetian
Republic when many a noble house was
ruined, single gondoliers became popu¬
lar, more and more frequently replacing
the expensive pair of rowers used ear¬
lier. When he rows, the single gondolier
does not stand in the middle of the small
poop deck, but to port, so as to transmit
maximum propulsive force to the sweep
oar, pivoted around the foreóla fitted to
starboard. To compensate for the
weight of the gondolier standing off-
centre to port, the hull was made to lean
to starboard as early as the fifteenth
century. When empty, the boat lists to
starboard; the gondolier steps aboard
and takes up his position, and the craft
rights herself.
The intentional list did not, however,
solve all the problems caused by the use
of a single gondolier. His oar is ma¬
noeuvred off the starboard side only.
Without a corrective J-stroke, the gon¬
dola would always veer to port. But
such a J-stroke reduces speed. A most
improbable solution to this dilemma
was found toward the end of the last
century, by twisting the gondola's hull.
Today, the craft is markedly
assymetrical. At her point of maximum
beam, she is 24 centimetres wider to
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Many gondolas have metal supports in the
shape of sea-horses (above) next to the passenger seat,
to which a rope is attached as a handhold.
port than to starboard. Compared with
a theoretically straight keel line, her
bows show a clear deviation to
starboard.
The gondola is unbalanced and
twisted, and it may be added in
passing-graceful to the point of beauty.
None of these features precludes pro¬
fitability, however. Quite the contrary,
the gondola is also extremely efficient.
One man can propel a gondola, loaded
and displacing up to 1,200 kilos, at a
sustained speed of nearly three knots.
No wonder that the Director of
Venice's Naval History Museum,
G. Rubin de Cervin, analysing speed
output yielded by energy input, judged
the gondola to be "the most profitable
craft afloat in the world".
Marvellous as she is as a technical feat,
the gondola would not have such unde¬
niable fascination were it not for the
men (and occasional women) who have
rowed her throughout the last ten
centuries.
According to a chronicler of 1493,
early gondoliers were often black slaves,
a contention borne out by a contempor¬
ary painting by Carpaccio. The de casa¬
da gondoliers (attached to the house¬
holds of wealthy families) had,
moreover, many other non-maritime
tasks, and were little different from
other menial servants.
As time passed, the gondoliers be¬
came a distinct group with its own char¬
acteristics. One of these is their profes¬
sional pride, the more openly displayed
since in numerical terms they were far
from a marginal category. At the end of
the fifteenth century there were
between 15,000 and 30,000 gondoliers
in Venice, and at certain periods in the
city's history they and their families
seem to have accounted for a quarter of
the population. Today their number has
shrunk to about 400.
Gondoliers also use a very special
language, an offshoot of the Venetian
dialect which itself is a unique mixture
of Italian, Spanish and Arabic. Many of
the terms designating the gondola's
dimensions and 280 different wooden
parts, as well as the tools and techniques
used in gondola building, have remained
unchanged for centuries while being
largely incomprehensible to people
(including boat builders) from other
parts of Italy. A gondolier of the 1980s
has little problem in understanding the
technical annotations appended to the
1555 blueprint mentioned above.
In Venice, the borderline between
celebration and work is not always
clear. Numerous civil and religious fes¬
tivals gave gondoliers the opportunity
to bridge the gap between these two
vital aspects of Venetian life.
The arrival of illustrious foreign dig¬
nitaries often led to veritable competi¬
tions among gondola designers for the
most elaborate decorations. In 1682, a
French ambassador, Monsieur Amelot,
made his entry into Venice on a baroque
craft described by a contemporary chro¬
nicler as follows: "The entire gondola is
covered with gilt carvings.... At the four
corners of the hull are four seated sta¬
tues representing the virtues of the
ambassador, each designated by its own
symbol. Vigilance [is symbolized] by a
lamp and rooster, Fidelity by a dog,
Discretion by a key across lips, and
Eloquence by Mercury's wand and a
hive of honey bees".
Particularly popular among the gon¬
doliers are the regattas that enable them
to show off their physical abilities and
technical skill amidst public rejoicing.
Truly mass events, the regattas of gon¬
dolas and other typically Venetian craft
were already popular at the end of
the 1400s. Dropped many years ago, the
annual Regatta was resumed in 1976,
which is only fair when one considers
that the word "regatta" is Venetian in
etymology. Now each year hundreds of
professionals and amateurs enthusiasti¬
cally participate in a gruelling 32-
kilometre water marathon.
The number of gondolas and gondo¬
liers has declined sharply in this cen¬
tury. The trade has so little appeal that
its transmission has been made no
longer hereditary. On the other hand,
there are some encouraging signs. The
games and above all the Regatta have
been resumed. A Unesco-backed Inter¬
national Committee for the Defence of
the Gondola has been set up and is
helping restore one of the last remaining
gondola yards at San Trovaso. On
balance, however, the gondola's fate
seems sealed. It now has only a decora¬
tive function as a tourist attraction.
Venetians themselves limit their use of
gondolas almost exclusively to cere¬
monial occasions such as weddings
and funerals. The gondola's central
purpose as Venice's main means of
passenger transport was pre-empted
just a century ago when motor vessels
were introduced.
ARTHUR GILLETTE is editor of Unesco's in¬
ternational quarterly Museum. The author of se¬
veral articles on sailing and shipping, he has
worked as a deck-hand on sail-powered fishing
boats in the Bahamas and in 1969 crossed the
Atlantic on a 7.6-metre cutter.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
At the bows of a gondola, as a counterweight to the gondolier who stands near the stern,
is a heavy steel blade with six "teeth" which are said to symbolize the six historical quarters
of Venice. The metal plume above is thought to represent the Doge's ritual hat.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Fernando Pessoa
BY JOSÉ AUGUSTO SEABRA
This year has been marked by the
worldwide commemoration of
the centenary of the birth of
Fernando Pessoa, Portugal's greatest
modern poet and one of the great uni¬
versal poets of our time. The crowning
event of the celebrations was a tribute
paid to Pessoa at Unesco Headquarters
last June.
Pessoa may already be said to number
among the great tutelary poets adopted
by the whole of humanity: Homer,
Virgil, Dante, Camöes, Shakespeare,
Goethe, Pushkin, Whitman, Mallarmé,
Machado ... In any event, it is true that
the Pessoan galaxy is constantly ex¬
panding through the growing number
of languages into which the poet's work
has been translated. And notwithstand¬
ing his statement that "My country is
the Portuguese language", Pessoa wrote
a part of his work in English and even
tried his hand at French. Like the gen¬
eration of which he was the guiding
spirit, his horizons were those of the
world: "We are Portuguese who write
for Europe, for all civilization ; as yet we
are nothing, but what we are now doing
will one day be universally known and
recognized".
Such indeed, according to Pessoa, was
the goal of the generation of writers and
artists associated, under his leadership,
with the review Orpheu: "To create a
cosmopolitan art, transcending time and
space", in other words, "an all-arts-in-
one art", "in which the languor and
mysticism of Asia, the primitivism of
Africa, the cosmopolitanism of the
Americas, the exoticism of Oceania and
the decadent machinism of Europe
merge, converge and intermingle".
Through the different aesthetic and
poetic theories that he upheld and the
different identities or "heteronyms"
that he created for himself to embody
those theories each heteronym having
	 30 	
a name, a life and a certain conception of
poetry-Pessoa presented himself in a
wide variety of guises and revealed
Portugal in its multiplicity as a mirror of
the entire universe. Just as every nation
is "a world in its own right", so every
"good Portuguese is several persons at
once", bearing such names as those of
the poet's chief heteronyms, Alberto
Caeiro, Ricardo Reis, Alvaro de
Campos or Fernando Pessoa "himself",
not to mention the "semi-heteronym"
Bernardo Soares for whom "the uni¬
verse is also the Rua dos Douradores",
the street of the gilders in the commer¬
cial heart of Lisbon, his "home" where
he wrote the Livro do Desassossego
("Book of Unrest").
For Pessoa, as for Goethe, the par¬
ticular and the universal are the same. A
wharf in the port of Lisbon, whence
ships would set out on the great voyages
of discovery, was for him "the world in
a nutshell". Similarly, the heteronyms
were emblematic of the people of
Portugal, and in their imaginary lives
they relived the adventure of the
Portuguese in the world.
Ricardo Reis, for example, the eldest
of Pessoa's heteronyms, born, claimed
Pessoa, in Oporto in 1887-one year
before his creatorhad received a clas¬
sical education and been trained as a
doctor, expressed himself in Latinate
Portuguese, was imbued with a Hellenic
sense of beauty and exiled himself to
Brazil for political reasons, travelling
from north to south and from east to
west, and going back from the present to
the past in search of a traditio.
Alvaro de Campos, on the other
hand, supposedly born in Tavira
(Algarve) in 1890-two years after
Pessoa had received a modern educa¬
tion and been awarded a degree in naval
engineering in Glasgow, Scotland, was
attracted to futurism, journeyed to the
CONnNUED ON PAGE 3}
"The Poet Fernando Pessoa and his
Heteronyms" (1978), a painting by the
Portuguese artist Costa Pinheiro, illustrates one
of the most original aspects of Pessoa's life and
work-his creation of alter egos ("heteronyms")
whose poetry he wrote as well as his own. Pessoa
invented names such as Alberto Caeiro, Ricardo
Reis and Alvaro de Campos for these imaginary
poets, but they were more than just
pseudonyms. Pessoa endowed them with their
own life-stories, and an individual outlook, style
and conception of poetry so that their works
differed from his own-although taken together
they expressed different personalities which he
felt to exist within himself.
Pessoa's three major poetic heteronyms,
Alberto Caeiro, Ricardo Reis and Alvaro de
Campos, as visualized byJosé de Almada
Negreiros. Pessoa created other heteronyms,
including the writer Bernardo Soares, "author"
of the "Book of Unrest", and Alexander Search,
to whom Pessoa attributed some of his poetry
in English.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
many poets
in one
Fernando Pessoa
photographed in the Baixa
(lower town),
the historic centre of Lisbon.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Extract from
Tabacaria ('The Tobacconist's')
I have dreamt more than Napoleon achieved.
I have clasped to my hypothetical heart more humanities than Christ,
I have in secret fashioned philosophies that no Kant ever wrote.
But I am, and perhaps for ever will be, the one who belongs in a garret,
Even though I live elsewhere;
I'll always be the one who wasn't born for that;
I'll always be the one who was gifted;
I'll always be the one who waited for someone to open the door in a wall where there is no door,
And who sang the song of infinity in a chicken coop,
And heard the voice of God in a blocked-up well.
Believe in myself? No, nor in anything else ...
Let Nature pour over my burning head
Her sun, her rain, the wind that tugs at my hair,
And as for the rest, let it come if it has to come, or let it stay put.
Cardiac slaves of the stars,
We conquered the whole world before we rose from our beds;
But when we awaken everything is opaque,
When we get up everything is alien;
We go out and the world is all the earth
Plus the solar system and the Milky Way and the unnamed boundlessness.
Alvaro de Campos
Translated by Michael Fineberg
\ftmv " ^
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
CENTENAIRE DE LA NAISSANCE DE
FERNANDO PESSOA
( ixnmtmonhao
-Mintupárnj**línfti«pt¥ni£jeiv
-M* ¡um n: b kngur pûnufpnc-
loonfry » [he p «iu(fuof Wi^-iuftf
2. Palais dc l'Unesco
7, Place Fontenoy 75007 Paris
Poster published to mark the centenary of
Pessoa's birth, which was commemorated at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris from 13 to
17 June 1988. Accompanying the reproduction
of a pen and ink portrait by Almada Negreiros is
the poet's statement "My country is the
Portuguese language".
Pessoa spent most of his life in the old quarters
of Lisbon, such as this street in the Bairro
Chiado.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 30
Orient via the Suez Canal and then went
from south to north and from west to
east, in order to move on from the pre¬
sent into the future, with his avant-
garde aesthetics, his poetry of machines
and his inclination towards revolutio.
Fully in keeping with the underlying
pattern of the poetic drama enacted by
the heteronyms, Alberto Caeiro, the
Master, born in Lisbon in 1889, received
"almost no education" apart from
"learning to unlearn", and remained in a
village in the province of Ribatejo as a
"herdsman", plunged in the contempla¬
tion of things "outside time and space",
in the innocence oiinfans, characteristic
of the quintessential poet.
Fernando Pessoa "himself" was born
in Lisbon in 1888. After the death of his
father, he spent his childhood and
adolescence with his mother and step¬
father in South Africa, before returning
with his English education to Lisbon
which he would virtually never leave
again and where he would exercise the
profession of commercial translator.
Thus we see in Pessoa's life and work,
which in fact are one, a dual tendency to
put down roots and to strike off into the
unknown, the simultaneous appeal of
traditio and revolutio characteristic of
the Portuguese in general, of their atti¬
tude to life at home and abroad and of
the way in which they reconcile the
particular and the universal.
"I do not evolve, I TRAVEL," Pessoa
once wrote. But he travelled only "in the
grip of the imagination", even when
remembering real journeys, in particu¬
lar the sea voyages of the Portuguese
and his own, between Lisbon and the
Cape of Good Hope. Through the
workings of the imagination, the jour¬
ney gradually assumes a symbolic
dimension, becomes a spiritual, initia¬
tory quest, as is revealed in his esoteric
poems. For as he journeys, the poet
sheds each of his assumed identities:
Travelling! Losing country after
country!
For ever being someone else...
Thus he travels, irompessoa topessoa,
from nobody to nobody ("pessoa"
means "nobody" in Portuguese), from
mask to mask. For the poet, the per¬
sonality is no more than a "terminus"
to which one returns, where the point
of departure and the point of arrival
coincide in the infinite circularity of a
journey for ever beginning anew, like
that of the "clockwork train" in the poem
"Autopsychography" in which the poet
describes himself as a "fake" even when
he "experiences things for real".
In fact, Pessoa's entire work is an
endless, imaginary poetic journey a
journey through languages, literatures,
aesthetics, philosophies, religions and
world views which the heteronyms
adopt in turn, and in opposition to one
another. Here again the keynote is uni¬
versality. Echoes of myriad civilizations
and cultures resound throughout the
poetry and prose of Pessoa. Attracted
by all forms of knowledge and spir¬
ituality, irrespective of their origin, he
devoted endless commentaries to them.
Suffice it to recall here his ecumenical
pan-religiosity, embracing paganism
and Christianity, Judaism and Sufism,
Taoism and Buddhism. This was
marked by an esotericism which drew
its inspiration from the Rosicrucians
and the Templars and was given sup¬
reme expression in the messianism of a
"Fifth Empire" of universal peace and
fellowship in its Portuguese form,
known as "Sebastianism". Centred on
the myth of the return of King Sebastian
of Portugal, who died in the late six¬
teenth century at the Battle of
Alcazarquivir in Morocco, this messian¬
ism is seen mainly in Mensagem ("Mes¬
sage"), the only book in Portuguese
published in the author's lifetime (he
also published poems in English, but
most of his extensive work remained
buried in a trunk whose inexhaustible
contents were gradually revealed only
after Pessoa's death).
The title of that book, now available
in a bilingual Portuguese-French edi¬
tion in the Unesco Collection of Repre¬
sentative Works, clearly demonstrates
Pessoa's concern with universality it
was chosen at the last moment to replace
the original title "Portugal". May this
Message be, in accordance with the
poet's wishes, a message of hope for all
peoples, for all human beings.
JOSE AUGUSTO SEABRA, Portuguese poet
and essayist, is professor of literary theory and of
Portuguese literature at the University of Oporto
and a specialist on Fernando Pessoa. A former
member of parliament and Minister of Education,
he is currently serving as his country's Ambassa¬
dor to Unesco. Among his recent publications on
Pessoa are an introduction to the bilingual (Portu¬
guese/French) edition of Mensagem (published by
Librairie Corti, Paris, 1988) which features in the
Unesco Collection of Representative Works.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Fernando Pessoa:
a biographical sketch
1888: Fernando Pessoa born in Lisbon, son
of Joaquim de Seabra Pessoa, music critic,
and Maria Madalena Nogueira.
1893: His father dies of tuberculosis.
1895: His mother marries the Portuguese
consul in Durban (South Africa), and the
following year she and her son join him
there. In 1899 Pessoa begins secondary
education at Durban High School.
1903-1904: Passes the entrance examination
of Cape Town University, winning the
Queen Victoria Prize for English style.
Writes poetry in English under the names
("heteronyms") Alexander Search and
Robert Anon.
1905: Returns to Lisbon and settles there
permanently. Enrols at the Curso Superior
de Letras but ceases to follow the courses
there after 2 years.
1908 : Finds work as a commercial translator,
and exercises this profession until the end of
his life. Starts to write poems in Portuguese
and composes fragments of his great poem
Fausto. In 1910 Portugal is proclaimed a
republic, which Pessoa welcomes.
1912: Contributes articles on new
Portuguese poetry to A Aguia ("The
Eagle"), organ of the literary movement
Renascença Portuguesa ("Portuguese
Renaissance"), in which he prophesies the
coming of another great national poet, a
"Super-Camoes".
1913-1914: Writes O Marinheiro ("The
Mariner") and, in a single day, composes the
36 poems in the collection O guardador de
rebanhos ("The Herdsman"), which he attri¬
butes to his heteronym and "Master",
Alberto Caeiro. This, he would record
20 years later, was his "triumphal day". His
other major poetic personalities, Ricardo
Reis and Alvaro de Campos, would derive
from different facets of Caeiro. Pessoa initi¬
ates two movements, Paulismo and
Interseccionismo.
1915: The first issue of the avant-garde
review Orpheu, launched by Pessoa in col¬
laboration with Mario de Sá-Carneiro, José
de Almada Negreiros and other Modernist
poets and artists, causes an outcry.
1917: Using the heteronym Alvaro de
Campos, Pessoa contributes a manifesto en¬
titled Ultimatum to the first issue of the
review Portugal Futurista.
1918: Publishes two booklets of poems in
English, Antinous and 35 Sonnets. Together
Pessoa (right) with his friend Costa Brochado in the Martinho da Arcada café, Lisbon,
one of the literary meeting places that he frequented.
with Inscriptions (1920), they are issued in
one volume as English Poems in 1921.
1920: Meets Ophelia Queiroz and writes
love letters to her until their break-up a short
time afterwards. This is Pessoa's only
known affair of the heart.
1921-1922: Contributes a story, O ban-
queiro anarquista ("The Anarchist Bank¬
er"), and some poems which would later
be included in his book Mensagem, to the
review Contemporánea.
1924: Launches the review Athena, which
publishes his "Odes", attributed to Ricardo
Reis, and an essay on a "non-Aristotelian
aesthetic", signed by Alvaro de Campos.
1928-1931: On the establishment of the
military dictatorship in Portugal in 1926,
Pessoa publishes a political manifesto which
gets him into trouble with the censor. Re¬
news his relationship with Ophelia, then
breaks it off for good two years later. Pub¬
lishes the first part of a major prose work,
Livro do Desassossego ("Book of Unrest"),
which would only appear in its entirety
50 years later. Writes occult verse and the
poem Autopsicografia ("Autopsycho-
graphy").
1932: Further parts of Livro do Desassossego
published. Salazar becomes Prime Minister
and Pessoa writes satirical verses repudiating
the dictatorship.
1934: Publishes Mensagem and enters it in a
national competition. A minor poet wins the
award, Pessoa receiving only a "special
prize".
1935: In a letter to the critic Adolfo Casais
Monteiro, Pessoa explains the "genesis of the
heteronyms". His later poems are written in
French or English. His last written words
are in English: "I know not what tomorrow
will bring". Pessoa dies on 30 November in
the Hospital of San Luís dos Franceses,
Lisbon, where he is buried. In 1985, the
fiftieth anniversary of his death, his body is
removed to the Jerónimos Monastery.
1942: Publication begins of Pessoa's exten¬
sive work. Many of his manuscripts, which
he kept in a trunk now preserved in Lisbon
National Library, are still unpublished.
Photo credits
Front and back cover, pages 18, 19: © La Bibliothèque
des Arts, Paris/Unesco. Page 2: ©Ch. Juskesseliev.
Page 5: © Metropolitan Museum of An, New York.
Page 6: Unesco/Michel Claude. Page 7 (three photos
above): Unesco/ Arnaldo; (below) Unesco/
Tochtermann. Page 8: © UDF/La Phototèque,
Gallimard Publishers, Paris. Pages 9, 10. 1 1 : ©Roger
Viollet, Paris. Pages 12/1 J: Unesco/Bailey. Pages 12
(above). H, 1 5, 24. 25. 26 (below), 29: Unesco/
Dominique Roger. Pages 16, 17, J3 (below): All Rights
Reserved. Pages 20, 21, 22, 21 (above): UNDP/Ruth
Masscy. Page 23 (below): illustration irom Art Khmer
Classique by H. Parmcnticr, Ecole Française de
l'Fxtrcmc Orient, Paris. Page 26 (above): Cauboue©
Rapho, Paris. Page 27: © Cameraphoto, Venice.
Page 28: J. E. Pasquier©Rapho, Pans. Pages 3C, 31
(below): © Modern Art Centre. Calouste Gulbenkian
Foundation, Lisbon. Page 31 (right): ©José Fabiao.
Page 32: Rémi Berli © Rapho, Pans. Page 34: ©
Manuela Nogueira, Lisbon.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 35 languages by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
A selection in braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition : Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda el Khazen
Spanish edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos,
Miguel Labarca
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille edition:
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Georges Servat
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions:
Solange Belin
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Non-Headquarters editions
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Sri Ram (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: PaikSyeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papagcorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: DaoTung(Hanoi)
Pashto: NasirSeham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by:(l)
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2)
University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48 1 00, U.S.A. ; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691 , U.S.A.
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-chiefin Pans
Imprime en France (Printed in France) - Depot legal : C 1 -
Novembre 1 988.
Photogravure-impression: Maury-ImprimeurS.A.
7..I . route d'Etampes, 45330 Maleshcrbes.
ISSN 004 1-5278
N°11-!988-OPI -88- 1-462 A
World decide for cultural development
Décennie mondiale du développement culturel
Decenio mundial para el desarollo culturel
1966-1997
I
DE LOS TESOROS DEL HUNDO
0 J 796
Above, membership card of the "Friends of the World Treasures" network, established in
September 1988 by the World Federation of Unesco Clubs, Centres and Associations
(WFUCA) as a contribution to the World Decade for Cultural Development. Receipts from the
sale of the cards will be used to support WFUCA projects to restore, safeguard or present
monuments and sites forming part of the cultural and natural heritage. Members may choose a
project to which the proceeds from their subscription will be channelled.
AVAILABLE TO MEMBERS:
an annual newsletter
a catalogue of current projects
free guided tours of "World Treasures" sites
and monuments, organized by the Unesco
associations, centres or clubs responsible for
the projects
Card exists in Gold ($1 00) and Green ($1 0) versions
For further information, please write to: FMACU-WFUCA, Unesco, 1 rue Miollis,
75732 PARIS CEDEX 15, France.
'GAME, SET AND MATCH
Création Henri REGNIER C 1988 - UNESCO/FIDEPS
Game, set and match is a board game based on the rules of tennis. It can be played by
2 players for a singles contest or 4 players for a doubles. The game, which has received the
approval of the International Tennis Federation, is published by Unesco's International Fund
for the Development of Physical Education and Sport (FIDEPS) in collaboration with a French
insurance group, the Union des Mutuelles de l'Ile de France. Proceeds from the sale of the
game will be used to provide sports facilities for the disabled, especially in the developing
countries.
Game, set and match, presented in a plastic case (43 x 33 x 5.5 cm) is available either
directly or by post from Unesco/FIDEPS, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. Price 280 French
francs, plus 30 francs postage. Special rates for group orders. Prices in local currency will be
supplied on request.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
r
{*
-V
£-0-7 yyjr-
% M
c, *ÍÁ
/.
Mefc
I ft i |
]]>
</page>
</document>
