<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="083386eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
JULY 1989 - 15 French francs
-if
SÜ-\
.
THE
AMIÜ
AST AND
»RESENT
0 IN THIS ISSUE:
INTERVIEW WITH
BRAZIUAN WRITER
I
JORGE
mmi\
*Aro»<
I
<*É#*^
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
La Realidad. ..ni pintada
(Vermeer et Mondrian)
"Reality...not even
painted (Vermeer and
Mondrian)", 1985, acrylk
on canvas (1.16 x 0.89 m)
by Herman Braun-Vega,
a Fteruvian painter who
has lived in Paris since
1968. The Peruvian
writer Julio Ramón
Ribeyro has written that
Braun-Vega's work,
which telescopes images
from different cultural
landscapes, is an example
of "the increasingly
visible advance of the
Third World into the
West's exclusive territory,
and the first signs of a
new civilization based on
contact cross-
fertilization, ethnic
intermingling and cultural
syncretism".
w^L
.
.«**
Â
With our photo of this
work by Herman Braun-
Vega we launch a new
regular feature,
"Encounters", which
seeks to highlight the
process of cultural
cross-fertilization. We
invite readers to send
us photographs to be
considered for
publication in this
feature. Your photo
should show a painting,
a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any
other subject which
seems to be an example
of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could
send us pictures of two
works from different
cultural backgrounds in
which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add
a short caption to all
photographs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
4
Interview with Jorge Amado
WHERE PEOPLES AND CULTURES
HAVE MINGLED
9
THE FAMILY
PAST AND PRESENT
48
SCIENCE
AND SOCIETY
AFRICA'S 'WONDER WEED'
NINETEENTH-CENTURY RUSSIA
HEARTH, HOME AND RURAL COMMUNITY
by Hélène Yvert-Jalu 10
ANCIENT CHINA
THE EMPIRE OF THE ANCESTORS
by Qi Yanjen 16
AFRICA
LINES OF DESCENT
by Manga Bekombo Priso 22
THE MIDDLE EAST AND NORTH AFRICA
THE FUTURE OF THE FAMILY 25
THE CHANGING JAPANESE FAMILY
UNDER NEW MANAGEMENT
by Kurimoto Kazuo 28
EUROPE
MARINA, SARAH, MICHEL AND JEAN
by Andrée Michel 34
Cover: Retirantes, Peasant Exodus (1982), acrylic on
canvas (200 x 200 cm) by the Brazilian-bom painter
Gontran Nato, who has lived in France since 1969.
Back cover: Family Reunion (1987) by Thihui Lim. This
Chinese sculptor often works wiè houséold objects-here
wooden spoonsused by the Miao, a Chinese mountain people
with whom he has lived since childhood.
LATIN AMERICA
THE WOMEN OF AREMBEPE
by Mariza de Athayde Figueiredo and Danda Prado 38
QUEBEC
NEW FAMILY STRUCTURES
by Francine Descarries and Christine Corbeil 42
'OUR HOME IS YOUR HOME'
A VISIT TO AN UZBEK FAMILY
by Claire Foumier 46
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
A noted Brazilian writer talks to the Unesco Courier
about the originality of his country's culture
Jorge Amado
m Where peoples and cultures
have mingled
In many respects Brazil is a microcosm, a mixture ofpeoples If you look into the ancestry of any black-skinned Brazilian,
and sensibilities drawn from all over the world-all his or her mother or father, grandparents or great-
bumanity in a nutshell. It is also one country, with one grandparents, you will always end up by finding a white
government and a set ofnational institutions. Which ofthese ancestor somewhere.
two aspects do you consider the most important in your
countrydiversity or unity? Is it possible to speak of a Are there any pure whites?
Brazilian people and a Brazilian culture? - Among the immigrants of long standing, there are perhaps
In my opinion, one can speak of a single people, with some in the south, but they are very few and far between
its own culture, born of the intermingling of all the races and difficult to find. There are some pure whites among the
who have passed that way. recent arrivals, first-generation immigrants and their
children. But the next generation begins to mix with the
Which are these races? others, to become integrated.
First of all, of course, there were the Indians. Then came Finally, we should not forget the Arabs, above all the
the Europeans, mostly the Portuguese. But gradually the Christian Arabs who came from Lebanon and Syria. They
groups from Europe became more diversified. By the fif- were often referred to as Turks, because their countries were
teenth century Portugal itself already had a very mixed then provinces of the Ottoman empire.
population. Among the people were those who were known
as the Moors. There were also the "new Christians" as they Surely all these different peoples cannot just have fused
were calledjews fleeing from the Inquisition who, although peaceably into one? There must have been inequalities,
they had been converted, were still being persecuted. In ad- power struggles. , .
dition, there was a large Dutch colony. Of course. There were political, economic and social strug-
Then there were the Africans, brought in as slaves. With gles which were aggravated by ethnic and cultural dif-
them, racial intermixture began to accelerate. Anxious to ferences. The black peoples, for example, soon revolted
split up the original tribes, the slave-owners would buy against their conditions and there were large-scale conflicts,
groups of slaves of different tribal originsa Yoruba, a Several black republics, settlements known as quilombos,
Bantu, a Congolese. were even set up in the mountains by rebellious slaves. One
of them lasted nearly forty years and repulsed the attacks
So the slaves interbred among themselves; but did they also of four successive government armies.
interbreed with their white masters? After the abolition of slavery, successive new waves of
Yes. The Portuguese interbred very readily and this mix- immigrantsItalians, Germansarrived to work in the cof-
ing was so widespread that today there are no pure blacks, fee plantations. Finally on this point I would like to say that,
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
m
I
^í^^íjí
/
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
absorb racism in the mixture of races mm a
although the history of Brazil has included its share of in- desire to intermingle. It is a way of looking at life that is
equalities and conflicts, there has never been a break in the to be found at the heart of all the various forms of expres-
process of ethnic and cultural intermingling. That is what sion, but nowhere in such striking fashion as in Carnival,
is typical of Brazil. And from it all a Brazilian culture was when everything blends together, within each one of us and
born, based on the Portuguese language which was spoken between us all. For a Brazilian, Carnival is the greatest
by all. festival in the world.
What are the main components of this new culture? Is this attitude reflected in the field of religion?
- The European, African and Indian elements all play an - Absolutely. There is syncretism in religion just as there
irreplaceable part, but I am inclined to feel that the source is syncretism in art. And once again the African influence
of its vitality is Africa. The Brazilian soul emerged from the has been the determining factor. The Africans brought with
confrontation between Portuguese melancholy and African them their vision of cosmogony, their gods and their cults,
joie de vivre. The Portuguese are pessimists, full of doubts which came up against and combined with each other, since
and preoccupied with death. Africans exude life, are at ease members of different tribes lived together. In turn, these
with themselves physically and with nature and know how various contributions mixed with Catholicism, because, on
to laugh, celebrate and enjoy themselves. They brought their arrival, the Africans were immediately baptized.
a rhythm and a vital energy to the new culture which are Thus, in Brazil, we are all Catholics, even if at heart we
immediately recognizable. If you hear Brazilian music or are fetishists, animists or Protestants. Even the gods have
watch a Brazilian dance, you will see it straight away. intermingled and Carnival is also the carnival of the gods.
African gods have shown amazing powers of survival, even
Is this African contribution evident in allforms ofexprès- during the dark night of slavery, when the slaves, forcibly
sion of Brazilian culture? converted to Catholicism, obviously could not honour their
At first, the European contribution was predominant in gods as such. So they identified them with Christian saints,
written forms of expression, but the African influence Take, for example, the Catholic feast of Saint Anthony,
gradually came to permeate them. The first great Brazilian Just like the whites, the blacks used to say "we are going
poet, Gregorio de Matos, was a mulatto. In the eighteenth to celebrate the feast of Saint Anthony", but, in fact, they
century, most writers were mainly of white origin, but there were celebrating the feast of Ogun, a popular black god of
were also some of black origin. It was, however, already metal and of war. Gradually, the saint and the god fused
becoming difficult to differentiate between those of black together.
or white origin. The greatest Brazilian novelist of the nine¬
teenth century, Machado de Assis, was also a mulatto, a fact So there is no racism in Brazil?
which sums up nicely what I am trying to say. There was, and still is, some racism. In Brazil, as in other
Of course, the dominant cultural influence varies from parts of the world, racism rises to the surface or erupts
region to region. In the Amazon, the mixture is whenever different ethnic groups find themselves in a situa-
predominantly Indian, to the north-east black, in the south tion of conflict. Nevertheless, Brazil is not a racist society,
white. Nevertheless, it is everywhere a mixture and because any tendency towards racism is countered by a
everywhere there are truly Brazilian components. general tendency towards intermingling and syncretism. In-
One has only to look at the nine countries which sur- stead of being deep-rooted, institutionalized and encouraged,
round usArgentina, Bolivia, Chile, Colombia, Ecuador, racism tends rather to be defused by the movement towards
Paraguay, Peru, Uruguay and Venezuelato understand the mixing, by this drive which accommodates differences and
importance of this typically Brazilian cultural adaptability, weds opposites. Mixture is the key word of Brazilian culture.
Despite their common language and the desire for unity they My sons are of Italian blood through their mother. My
all feel, they remain nine distinct countries, whereas Brazil, grandmother was Indian, my great-grandfather was black,
which is of continental size, has maintained its unity. Of and my name has definite Arab connections. And I am corn-
course, there are many reasons for this, but, to my mind, pletely at ease as a Brazilian, with a feeling that I come from
the determining factor has been this ability to intermix, this all over the world and am so much at home in Brazil. Let
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
/ havefought all my life
with this hope in mind
me tell you an amusing anecdote about my name. One day
I received a letter from the embassy of an Arab country.
My secretary telephoned and found herself talking to the
cultural attaché at the embassy, who insisted that I should
"correct" my name. It should not be written "Amado", but
"Hamadou", since, according to him, it is a name of Arab
origin. From the beginning of the period of colonization,
many Portuguese families with the name of Amado came
to Brazil. How far back do they go? Probably to the Arab
conquest of the Iberian peninsula. They may also, perhaps,
have been of Jewish origin. A resume of humanity, you
might say.
So, for you, intermingling is the sole antidote to racism?
Absolutely. From a very early age I have had to fight
against a variety of injustices and prejudices and, in par¬
ticular, against racism, which is without doubt the most con¬
temptible of all prejudices. I am convinced that, in the long
run, there is only one real solutionto absorb racism in the
mixture of races.
In situations where thepolitical or economic climate is un¬
favourable to certain peoples or to certain social classes,
can this intermingling be any more than the cultural
crushing of the weakest by the strongest?
Economic and political weakness must not be confused
with cultural weakness. Even when it is in the keeping of
an oppressed community or class, a culture can preserve its
values and even impose some of them on its oppressors. This,
as I have pointed out, is what happened with the black
peoples of Brazil, even though they were reduced to slavery.
The same is true of the black peoples of the United States.
From Antiquity, we have the example of Greece helleniz-
ing the culture of her Roman conquerors and occupiers. And
in more recent times, have not India, Pakistan and Egypt
succeeded in preserving, and, indeed, reviving and revitaliz¬
ing their cultures in face of their contact with Western
colonial culture?
What is the situation in Brazil today? Has this interesting
process of interbreeding finally abolished racism?
We have just celebrated the hundredth anniversary of the
abolition of slavery. That is to say that only a hundred years
ago black or mainly black people were still slaves. Things
have progressed enormously, but a lot remains to be done.
The white/black divide still coincides to some extent with
the division between the very rich and the very poor, and
this does not exactly favour the growth of fraternal feelings.
This means that we must do all we canthrough
democratic political struggle, social reform and cultural
actionto resolve these problems and bring people closer
together. In the cultural field, in particular, we must fight
the cult of violence in television and the cinema. It is not
a matter of prohibiting films that glorify violence but of
creating new works that glorify its oppositelove, friend¬
ship and solidarity. It is a difficult path to follow, but, in
the long term, I believe it to be the right one.
After all, in spite of everything things have improved,
have they not, since the world began? I do not know
whether one day a world will exist in which man will no
longer be the enemy of man, and in which difference in skin
colour will count for no more than difference in agea
world in which all men are brothers. But we have to fight
on in the hope that this will come about. Otherwise we are
left with nothing but anguish and wretchedness. I have
fought all my life with this hope in mind. Of course, I have
had some disappointments and some painful moments,
under the dictatorship and when I had to change my mind
about certain ideas that I had long held sacrosanct. But I
have never given up that hope. Had I lost it, I would not
have been able to continue the struggle, to write. It would
have been the end of everything for me.
Can you give us an image of hope?
Yes. The image of Carnival. All those fair-skinned, brown-
skinned, black-skinned people, who sometimes talk of the
segregation of the races but who come together, dance
together and finally marry each other!
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
I
n many myths, cosmogonies and religions the human age begins with the creation
of a coupleApsu and Tiamat, Yama and Yami, Adam and Eve. Is this image of
the primordial family unit comprising a man, a woman and their offspring on the
way to becoming a universal model today?
When we look back into history, however, we find larger and more complex family
structures: hordes, clans, tribes, lineages, urban and village communities where several
generations lived and worked together, where the example set by the ancestors
continued to inspire their distant descendants, where the same customs were
perpetuated down the centuries, and where religious cults were deeply rooted.
The family, in the widest sense of the term, is the source and the refuge of its members,
an institution with codes and hierarchies which may be oppressive to some but which
provide a sense of security for all. For thousands of years it has been society's most
durable link and the most effective means whereby the distinctive
characteristics of a people's culture have been maintained and transmitted.
But today this link is tending to slacken as the family is increasingly confronted
with the disintegrating forces of modern life. The existence of the small nuclear family
and the single-parent family raises the questions of whether the basic units of society
are everywhere being stripped down to their simplest form of expression and whether
the cultural diversity which they have hitherto vehicled is inexorably yielding ground
to uniformity and monotony.
A certain tendency for the family to contract is apparent, but the need for community
ü ¿ (122 y'i22 °m) bv Persists- Perhaps humanity, eternally creative and unpredictable, is engaged in the
the Soviet painter painful process of exploring new ways of living in society which will at last reconcile
Aleksandr Grigorievich
Sitnikov. family solidarity with individual liberty.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Hearthy home and rural
10
THE
FAMILY
PAST
AND PRESENT
NINETEENTH-CENTURY
RUSSIA
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
community
The Couple (1931), by the
Russian-bom French
sculptor Osip Zadkine
(1890-1967).
Asking her Hand in
Marriage, by the 18th-
century Russian painter
Mikhail Shibanov.
BY HÉLÈNE YVERT-JALU
The basis of peasant society in rural
Russia, the family long defended the
identity of an oppressed social group.
T .
JL HE population of the Russian empire at the
end of the nineteenth century was overwhelm¬
ingly rural. The 1897 census shows that, of a total
of 124.6 million people, 106.2 million (85 per
cent) lived in the countryside.
In 1913, on the eve of the First World War,
only 18 per cent of the population lived in the
towns and cities. It was sometimes difficult to
draw the line between town and village, as three-
quarters of the people were employed in
agriculture and there was a strong link between
the urban and the rural environment, largely
because of seasonal workers (otkhodniki) who
divided their time between the fields and the
factories.
It was not until 1962 that the urban popula¬
tion exceeded the rural population. This indicates
the importance of peasant society, which was
based on the family. "All the institutions, all the
distinctive characteristics of Russia, everything
which makes her different from the West, have
deep roots which must be disinterred in order to
understand the country's problems", wrote the
French historian Henri Jean-Baptise Anatole
Leroy-Beaulieu in 1881. These roots are to be
found primarily in the organization of the tradi¬
tional Russian family iij the rural environment.
The mir, a village commune
Traditional Russian peasant society was founded
on a unique institution, the agrarian community
known as the obshchina or mir. This was a form
of local government based on regular meetings
of the heads of peasant families (domokhozïanes,
literally, "masters of the house"). These men
shared the responsibility for village affairs, under
the direction of an elder, the staroste, whom they
elected. The peasants did not own their land.
Fields and meadows belonged to the communi¬
ty, which periodically redistributed them among
the families on the basis of the number of "souls"
or married men in each family. Neither women
nor single men were taken into account.
According to some historians, the mir form
of organization has ancient roots going back to
the time when the Slavs farmed collectively, in
large kinship groups, land held in common by 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
the group. This arrangement may have reflected
a specific mentality that was far removed from
the individualistic tendencies of the West. Other
historians believe that this institution may have
been a form of organization imposed on peasants
by the authorities for administrative or fiscal
reasons. Whatever its origins, among the Russian
peasantry the mir developed a community spirit,
the individual's attachment to the social group,
in particular the immediate family, and solidari¬
ty between different members of the community.
The head of the family was designated in ac¬
cordance with the male line of succession. The
responsibility passed from a father to his son or
to the eldest brother, and usually fell to the oldest
man in the household. A matriarchal system
might exist on a provisional basis in the case of
a widow with no adult men in the house.
As his family's representative at the village
assembly, the domokhozïane was responsible for
paying taxes and providing recruits for military
service. His domestic role was to manage com¬
mon property and to use the household's man¬
power to work the land, keep the stove supplied
with firewood, repair old buildings and construct
new ones, and maintain tools and equipment. He
was also the arbitrator in family quarrels.
In the early nineteenth century the "big fami¬
ly" commonly comprised between twenty-five
and thirty people. The dwelling, which together
with the outbuildings was known as the dvor
(literally, the "yard"), was also home to sons and
their families, unmarried daughters, and various
relatives and friends of the family.
By the end of the century, however, this kind
of arrangement was much less common. Married
sons, after living with their parents for a few
years, would leave the family home and set up
their own "hearth". Between 1880 and 1890, the
typical village had only seven or eight people in
each dvor. The 1897 census- for European Russia
gave an even lower average of 5.9 persons per
household in the countryside.
Marriage as a means
of access to common lands
The authority of the head of the household over
his family was similar to that of the emperor over
his subjects, a relationship cast in the image of
divine power. The autocratic power of the head
of the family is evoked by an ancient proverb
which says, "The master in his house is like the
Khan in the Crimea". The obedience due to the
head of the family was an extension of the respect
shown to old people. "Where there's white hair,
there's reason", says another proverb.
The power of the domokhozïane was not,
however, absolute, for it was customary for him
to consult the "family council" before taking par¬
ticularly important decisions. This council, con¬
sisting of the married men of the household,
could in certain exceptional circumstances have
him deposed for incompetence or unworthiness.
As in all hierarchical societies based on
patriarchy, it was the norm for men to dominate
women, older members to dominate younger,
and married people to dominate the unmarried.
The unmarried were not considered to be
people in the fullest sense, as indicated by some
of the words used to describe them: a single man
of whatever age was called malyi (a lad), an un¬
married woman was known as deyka (a girl). On
marriage they formed part of the adult domestic
community.
Marriage itself was a prerequisite to the use
of communal land. It could be said to replace a
coming of age ceremony, as indicated by the term
muzh, which was formerly used to refer to both
"man" and "husband". A bobyl, that is a peasant
with neither land nor family, was seen as an un¬
fortunate being overwhelmed by fate.
It is not surprising under these circumstances
that Russia had the highest proportion of mar¬
ried people in Europe. The 1897 census shows
that in the countryside, only 4 per cent of women
and 3 per cent of men aged between 40 and 50
years remained single. And people married
young. For a first marriage, the average age was
21.2 years for women, and 23.5 years for men,
at least two years younger than in France at the
time. Only those who entered monastic orders,
or the physically or mentally disabled, did not
marry.
The high mortality rate meant that widows
and widowers were common, but most men
remarried. A widower needed another wife to
take care of his motherless children and to help
out with the farming. A widow was unable to
benefit from her deceased husband's land and
became a heavy responsibility for the family. Left
alone, she was condemned to a life cf poverty.
The rituals surrounding a proposal of mar¬
riage show that matchmaking was a collective
rather than a private affair, masterminded by the
head of the family and supervised by the village
community. In taking a wife, a man furnished the
community with an extra pair of hands. The
young bride would leave her father's house and
move in with her in-laws. The ideal woman was
first and foremost a good worker.
Custom dictated that the suitor's parents send
svaty (matchmakers), relatives or friends of the
young man, to his proposed fiancee's mother and
1 he wall where icons were
hung in an isba, the
traditional wooden
dwelling of the Russian
peasant.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
I aiH
-:^'< '
I : I
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
/i. Russian family
photographed at the
beginning of the century.
father in order to make inquiries and negotiate
the terms of the marriage. In practice it was not
unusual for parents to ask children for their opi¬
nion. Self-interest and sentiment were not
automatically at odds. But, even then, tradition
demanded that the fiancée should weep for her
single days and that she should voice the fears in¬
spired in her by a new life in the house of
"strangers".
Where several generations lived together, the
oldest woman carried out the duties of the
mistress of the house. In general she would be
the wife of the domokhozïane, who was respon¬
sible for organizing and sharing out the
housework between the various women of the
14 family.
These women lit and maintained the great
stove which took up almost a quarter of the isba,
or wooden dwelling, fetched water from the
village well, prepared meals for the family and
the animals, cultivated the vegetable plot behind
the house, looked after the farmyard, milked the
cows and made dairy produce, and collected ber¬
ries and mushrooms in the forest. In summer,
they helped out on a more or less regular basis
with work in the fields, which was the men's
main responsibility. The women passed the time
in the long autumn and winter evenings by spin¬
ning or weaving flax, hemp or wool.
They were allowed to build up their own
little nest egg through the sale of surplus wool,
cloth or dairy produce. In certain regions this was
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
HELENE YVERT-JALU,
of France, is a lecturer at
the University of Paris I.
She is the author of a
number of studies on
population questions, the
family and women in the
USSR.
known as their "casket" or "basket" (korobka).
Girls would take this money with them on their
marriage. When a woman died, her "casket"
would usually go to her daughters or her unmar¬
ried sisters, and in this way a system of in¬
heritance between women was established. On
the other hand, a woman had no claim on the
property of her father's family, nor on that of
her husband. Only sons had the right to inherit
from their father, and in return they had to look
after the needs of their aged parents.
The overall birth rate in European Russia
(49.5 per cent in the period 1869-1900) bears
witness to the lack of any birth control. Taking
account of factors which curbed people's natural
fertility, such as breast-feeding infants up to the
age of one or two years, or sexual abstinence dur¬
ing religious fasts and when the husband was
working away from home, it has been calculated
that a peasant couple would bring between eight
and ten children into the world, of whom almost
a third would die before their first birthday.
The country wife, working
woman and guardian of moral
and religious values
The peasant woman did not take any rest during
her pregnancy.' Children were born with the help
of the village midwife, and even the husband
would lend a hand if his wife was working in the
fields when her labour started. Rural life was hard
for a woman. Always busy, she worked harder
than the muzhik, or peasant, who in winter could
allow himself to sleep late in the warmth of the
stove. As the poet Nekrassov wrote:
The keys to female happiness
To our cherished freedom
Have been mislaid, lost
By God himself.
Foreign observers of this rural world have
often been shocked by the number of insulting
sayings about women, such as "Long in the hair,
short in the mind", or "The more a woman is
beaten, the better the soup". But accounts by
authors originating from the peasantry give the
impression that women were valued as indispen¬
sable partners in working the land.
There is even a Russian literary tradition
which regards women as superior to men, in the
sense that they embody purity, self-sacrifice,
humility, courage, enthusiasm for work, and
faith. In other words, they are seen as guardians
of moral and religious values.
A cosmic Christianity
In Russian society under the Tsars, and especially
in the villages, the Church had an enormous
influence. It defined good and evil, beauty and
ugliness, honour and shame. It kept the parish
registers where everyone's civil status was
recorded. Each birth, marriage and death
necessarily took on a sacramental nature,
permeating the whole of family life with religious
ritual.
One of the most important rites of the Rus¬
sian Orthodox Church, that of marriage, equated
the conjugal union with that of Christ and the
Church, thus implying that marriage was in¬
dissoluble. There were a few exceptions to this
rule. Divorce was permissible, for example, in the
case of adultery. The party recognized as inno¬
cent had the right to remarry. But the peasant
class were not often aware of this possibility.
The Russian people on the whole were deep¬
ly devout and the practice of religion was tightly
interwoven with their daily life through its many
festivals. The Christianity of the peasants could
be described as a "cosmic Christianity", linked
to the rhythm of the seasons and intermingled
with the traditions and beliefs inherited from the
pagan past. Though they were devout Christians,
the peasants still believed in domovoy, the spirit
of the house, leshy, the spirit of the woods, and
rusalki, the water sprites.
Deeply bound by its secular traditions, wary
of any change, this rural civilization was light
years away from the Westernized world of the
Russian intelligentsia. For a long time the
peasants were the focus of contradictory ap¬
praisals by the country's intellectual élite. Either
they were held in contempt and considered as
"rustics wallowing in filth and ignorance", or
they were idealized as "custodians of the most
unique aspects of Russian civilization".
Both these points of view were based on a
misunderstanding. Long humiliated, freed from
serfdom only in 1861, the peasants could only
resist pressure from the authorities and from
poverty by taking refuge in their community life,
with its rituals and beliefs which allowed them
to express their collective personality. For them
the family was a haven within which they passed
on their cultural heritage and stood up to all the
adversities that came their way.
«
ill
}
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
'Man is to woman as the sun is to the
moon. He leads, she follows; thus har¬
mony reigns.' In ancient China, an
unchanging order based on ancestor
worship and the submissiveness of
women ruled the traditional family.
ay
X. HE virtue of the Emperor is like the wind,
that of the common people is like the grass; the
grass must bow at the passage of the wind."
"A prince must bear himself like a prince,
a subject must act like a subject and a son must
behave like a son."
For centuries Chinese society was imbued
with the concept of the social hierarchy embodied
in these sayingsan immutable order in which
each person had his own station in life. Under
the influence of Confucianism, in particular, the
Celestial Empire conformed to a strict order
based above all on the family.
The traditional Chinese family was a larger
unit than the nuclear family of today, consisting
of three or four generations all living under the
same roof and encompassing not only direct
descendants but also collateral kinsfolk such as
aunts and uncles.
The existence and durability of this type of
family grouping were reinforced by the standards
and teachings of religion as well as by civil law
and social custom.
The complexity of the relationships that
governed family bonds was such that it even af¬
fected the development of the language. Whereas
in the West such general designations as aunt,
uncle and sister are considered adequate, the
Chinese language is richly endowed with more
precise appellations: "Jie Jie" (elder sister), "Di
Di" (younger brother), "Jiu Jiu" (maternal un¬
cle), "Shu Shu" (father's younger brother) "Sheng
Sheng" (wife of a father's younger brother).
While this kind of family was the norm for
the bourgeoisie and the aristocracy, the situation
was quite different among the lower classes.
Economic difficulties resulting from famine and
sickness as well as from the fragmentation of land
holdings into tiny plots, made the task of main¬
taining large family units such as these well-nigh
impossible. And once a family was broken up
there was little chance of it ever being
reconstituted.
Ancestor worship and duty
Ancestor worship was one of the essential
characteristics of the traditional Chinese family.
It emphasized the strength of the ties that bound
its members even beyond the grave. The spirits
of the ancestors, with whom the spirits of the liv-
BY QI YANFEN
1 his 19th-century painting
depicts yin (the feminine
element) and yang (the
masculine element), the two
complementary forces or
principles which are present
throughout nature (sky and
earth, light and darkness,
fire and water, etc.). Their
interplay, according to
traditional Chinese
cosmology, creates the
harmony of the universe.
A family meal in China
at the turn of the century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The empire of the ancestors
THE
FAMILY
PAST
AND PRESENT
ANCIENT CHINA 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ing, themselves "future ancestors", would one
day be reunited, were so many links in the con¬
tinuous chain of humanity.
Emperor Qang Si (1662-1722) of the Qing
dynasty once told the Papal Legate: "We know
perfectly well that the souls of the ancestors can¬
not come and dwell in the tablets and cartouches
that bear their names, but we try to convince
ourselves that we are in their presence."
Hence the practice of offering them gifts
which varied according to locality: pigeons,
chickens, fruit, wine, wheat or rice. A part of
every house was set aside for ancestor worship
and, if the family was wealthy enough, a temple
would be erected. On great occasions, such as the
anniversary of Confucius, ceremonies were held
in the house of the headman of the village.
These religious traditions go far back into An¬
tiquity. From the fifth century BC, the teachings
of Confucius laid great stress on the importance
of filial piety. Above all, this involved the duty
of ensuring the continuity of the family line. For
a man, this meant fathering a son; for a widow,
it meant rejecting all thought of remarriage and
devoting herself to bringing up the children,
especially the male children, of her deceased hus¬
band or adopting one of her husband's nephews.
A couple that had only girl children had to adopt
one of their sons-in-law who then took the name
of his father-in-law.
Respect for the hierarchy of the social classes,
which upheld the structures of the traditional
feudal society, was firmly rooted in the family.
Power was in the hands of the oldest generation.
Then, within a single generation, the elder
members always dominated their juniors. Thus,
a nephew, even though he might be older than
his uncle, still owed him respect and obedience.
The power an older man exercised over his in¬
feriors (members of younger generations,
younger brothers and women) was virtually ab¬
solute and even gave him the right to inflict
violence upon them.
Obedience and segregation
of boys and girls
The established order was inculcated into children
from the earliest age by teaching them the rules
of filial piety and fraternal duty. During the first
years of education, even though the two sexes
were educated together, the difference of status
between boys and girls was clearly defined.
The birth of a boy was an occasion for ritual
and ceremony and an official presentation. The
arrival of a girl into the world went by virtually
unremarked. Very early on, the boys would be
taught to show their dominance and the girls to
be humble and submissive. A little later, the two
sexes would be physically separated. The children
would no longer sit on the same school bench
or take their meals together.
Even before they reached adolescence, the
children belonged to two totally separate worlds.
The precept "Nan Zhu wai, Niizhu nei" (man
is master of the outside, woman of the inside) was
QI YANFEN
is a member of the Chinese
permanent delegation to
Unesco. A former professor of
French at the University of
Beijing, she has published a
study of Western civilization
and several articles on French
literature. She has also
translated a number of works
from French into Chinese,
including Simone de
Beauvoir's novel Le sang des
autres (1944; The Blood of
Others, 1948). Her thesis,
published in 1983, was a study
of female characters in the
works of Simone de Beauvoir.
CW>
A notary distributes the
family property among its
members. (19th-century
Chinese engraving)
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
1 his photo of an early
20th-century Chinese
courtesan illustrates the
traditional Chinese
criteria offeminine beauty:
beautiful features,
a perfect figure, and above
all small feet.
one of the corner-stones of Chinese society. Boys
therefore would be taught the rules of social
behaviour and the girls the principles of domestic
life.
Although these basic principles were the same
for all social classes, there were, nevertheless, im¬
portant differences. Women of the upper classes
did not work and lived within a very closed
setting. Their activities were restricted to running
the house, supervising the servants and the
feeding arrangements and looking after the
children. Working-class women, however, had to
share in the work of the family and sometimes
even work in the fields. Apart from bringing up
the children, their work usually consisted of look¬
ing after the mulberry trees and the silk worms,
weaving, and being responsible for the seed store
and the distribution of foodstuffs. Their
economic contribution, therefore, was far from
negligible.
The feminine ideal
of ancient China
Children were prepared for their future situation
in life. The future father was given considerable
power and, if he was destined to become the head
of the family, this power was virtually absolute.
The future mother was readied for a life of sub¬
mission and humility. Anything that might make 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
her more free and independent was strictly for¬
bidden. Thus it was held that "lack of culture is
a virtue in women".
Naturally enough, a girl of strong character
occasionally succeeded in rebelling against this
kind of education and in affirming her identity as
an individual. Such an attitude, however, met
with general disapproval and was seen as a
catastrophe for her parents. Some confirmation is
to be found in literature of the existence of such
exceptional girls, but their story is always
presented as an example not to be followed.
The ideal young lady should as far as possi¬
ble be pleasing to the eye. Beautiful features and
a perfect figure were very important, but not
more so than having small feetfeet "like the
crescent new moon that danced divinely on a
large golden lotus flower". A woman with small
feet acquired an air of nobility and fragility which
enhanced her chances of making a good marriage,
aroused the esteem of those around her and, so
it was said, ensured that her husband would re¬
main faithful.
This criterion of physical perfection emerged
very early on. It was widespread among the
wealthier classes under the Song dynasty
(960-1280) and by the end of the seventeenth cen¬
tury it was common to all classes. The custom
of binding the feet, one of the most unusual to
emanate from Chinese society, did not disappear
until the time of the protest movement of 4 May
1919, under Sun Yat Sen.
Wedding procession in
Beijing, 1911.
A woman's grace did not, however, depend
solely upon physical attributes. Her mother
would have taught her a whole range of
behaviour patterns: she must be humble, good-
natured and respectful, open her lips as little as
possible when she spoke, laugh without being
noisy, never raise her voice, make sure she could
not be seen if she looked outside, drink no
alcohol, never go out at night. These rules com¬
plemented certain moral qualities that were
judged to be important: she should always place
herself a little in the background, never mention
her own qualities, never make excuses for her
faults, accept criticism without seeking to defend
herself, always be discreet.
This "ideal" education did nothing to en¬
courage the development of a woman's personali¬
ty, but it prepared her to fit perfectly into the
family structures of traditional society.
Feminine submissiveness
A girl brought up in this fashion was ready to
conform to the principles propounded in the
classic formula: three obediences, four virtues.
The three obediences were those owed to her
father by a girl, to her husband by a married
woman and to her son by a widow. The four vir¬
tues involved a woman's duty to her parents-in-
law, respect to her husband, good relations with
her sisters-in-law and good neighbourliness.
Woman's permanent obedience to man is in-
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
herent in the traditional Chinese cosmological
system: the Yin (female principle) is always subor¬
dinate to the Yang (male principle), while at the
same time being linked and complementary to
it. Confucius embodied this immutable order in
the following formula: "Man is to woman as the
sun is to the moon. He leads, she follows; thus
harmony reigns."
Absolute obedience to the father became ap¬
parent in marriage as in all other matters, and a
girl would take as her husband the man chosen
by him, nor could she refuse to do so. As the pro¬
verb puts it: "Marry a cock and follow a cock,
marry a dog and follow a dog." In this particular
domain a young man was no freer than a young
woman. If he did not like the girl but she suited
his parents who felt that "she is just what we
want", he would still have to perform his con¬
jugal duties towards her to the end of his days.
If, on the other hand, he liked her but his parents
found her unsuitable, he would have to renounce
all thought of her.
The young wife had as many duties towards
her parents-in-law as to her own parents. Often
she would find herself at the foot of the ladder
of the family hierarchy and cast in the role of a
servant, especially if it was a modest rural fami¬
ly. In some cases, if her situation became in¬
tolerable, she might have no other recourse than
to flee or commit suicide.
Against such a background, the importance
attached to female virginity can well be imagined.
Its loss was considered to be particularly scan¬
dalous and to provide justifiable grounds for the
annulment of a marriage. A woman's virginity
was an essential bargaining factor in the marriage
settlement and a key indicator of her virtue.
Wife to one man only
In traditional Chinese society, therefore, marriage
was primarily a family affair rather than the
union of two individuals and was often arranged
at the time of the birth of the future bride and
bridegroom. In no circumstances was it based on
love or personal choice. Indeed, a marriage ar¬
ranged on such a basis would have been viewed
with scorn. Even when the engaged couple had
been secretly intimate before marriage, the girl's
family could promise her to another. In China,
just as anywhere else, love affairs and elopements
could occur, but under the Ming and Qing
dynasties the fugitives would be pursued by the
forces of the law, brought back and forced into
submission. If one of the lovers were to die,
decency demanded that the other did not survive
him or her. The legend of Liang and Tso, the
Chinese Romeo and Juliet, is an exemplary story
of lovers who died for their love.
When a girl got married, she became a full
member of her husband's family group and her
primary duty was to produce a son to continue
the family line. Confucians viewed inability to
produce a male child as a serious fault, since it
deprived the husband of his posterity. In such a
case, therefore, the man was permitted to take a
second wife or mistress to ensure continuation
of the family line. Nevertheless, the first wife kept
her position in the family hierarchy and the se¬
cond wife was subordinate to her. The children
of a second union were "attributed" to the first
wife, who remained the only legitimate spouse.
If a wife was widowed, she was expected to
remain faithful to her deceased husband. A de¬
cent woman was wife to only one man. The
virgin widow who married the spirit of her
fiancé, who had died before the wedding had
taken place, was held in the highest esteem:
The man has vanished like the morning dew,
The woman in the frost of night remains,
The river in its endless flow runs on,
The lone-left bird laments eternally.
On the other hand, there is a proverb which
says that "while it is easy to remain a virgin,
widowhood is hard to bear"; so after three years
of mourning the widow could think of remarry¬
ing. The parents-in-law would then arrange the
marriage contract and would receive the gifts of¬
fered by the new husband, a just recompense for
those they themselves had given for the bride pur¬
chase. The parents-in-law might also remarry the
wife or fiancée of their dead son to a man without
fortune and adopt the child of this second union.
In this manner, then, the Confucian family
was perpetuated down the years and it was not
until the end of the nineteenth century that
thousands of women rose up to throw off the
shackles of their enslavement.
A two-wheeler for
transporting all the family.
»is
4
<
Í
t 5 1 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Lines of descent
ira^SMJÊsatSÊÊÊiÊÊÊÊÊÊÊ^ÊÊÊ^ÊKÊÊÊÊÊim^ÊÊmÊa^^a^
' *$&** ";,.*'' c.
* f '
4-'
-
'
i
fi *T 1 ]
W& il
w
/ 'TT
1
\
! 1 W jju. À
il rM ^^ÊËzr-
f ^
A ^1 Vcia^w K^ B
10 ^
i 1
4k * - 1
la - j
Ém \Mk
m h
r
mJ T
fui i .
F
22
THE
FAMILY
PAST
AND PRESENT
AFRICA
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
BY MANGA BEKOMBO PRISO
Chief Togo and his
offspring at Ouahigouya
(Burkina Faso).
Ashanti queen mother
(Ghana). This polished
black wooden sculpture
(height 40 cm) was placed
on the altar of the
ancestors.
MANGA BEKOMBO
PRISO,
of Cameroon, is a sociologist
with the French National
Centre for Scientific Research
(CNRS) and the Ethnology
and Comparative Sociology
Laboratory of the University
of Paris X, where he is
engaged on research into
lineal kinship systems and the
development process in
Africa. He was co-editor of
Marriage, Fertility and
Parenthood in West Africa,
published in 1978 by the
Australian National
University, Canberra, and a
contributor to a recent
Unesco work, Famille, Enfant
et Développement en Afrique
(1988).
Modern legislation in Africa is tending
to encourage individualism and weaken
social cohesion. The traditional African
family is adapting to new circumstances
and proving more resilient than once
seemed likely.
T
A HE children of a modern Western family
belong legally neither to the family of the father
nor to that of the mother; they are, first and
foremost, the children of a couple. In the most
widespread of the African kinship traditions,
however, lineal kinship systems are the rule and
the children are attached to one or other of their
parents' families. The father and the mother are
therefore not both members of the family to
which their children are linked.
There are two main unilineal kinship
systemsthe matrilineal and the patrilinealbut
in certain cases the interconnections are so exten¬
sive as virtually to constitute bilineal systems.
Societies in which matrilineal kinship systems
are the rule are of two kinds. In one, marriage
as an institution is unknown and is replaced by
what might be called "recognized cohabitation".
This system, which is comparatively rare, is
found among the Senufo of Côte d'Ivoire and
Burkina Faso. In the other, which covers a much
wider cultural field (Côte d'Ivoire, Ghana,
Nigeria, and the Congo Basin), marriage is
recognized and the wife leaves her home to live
in the home of her husband or her father-in-law.
In this case, the mother's brother rather than the
natural father is considered to be the true father
of the children.
Patrilineal societies are by far the most com¬
mon, and it is with them that we are primarily
concerned here. In contrast to modern societies
which tend to stress the natural, biological link,
African traditional societies lay emphasis upon
a contractual social link based on the notion of
the "parental role", which may be played by
several people.
All the true sisters of the "genetrix" (natural
mother), and women of the same age group, may
be considered to be her children's "mother".
Similarly, children will address all the genitor's
brothers and close friends as "father". The child
is, above all, the child of the lineal group to which
he or she belongs. Members of the paternal or
maternal clan, as well as the husband's other
wives, share in rights and duties with regard to
the child.
As well as the importance attached to the
child/maternal uncle and brother/sister relation¬
ships, the particularly loving, "friendly" relation¬
ship between grandparents and grandchildren 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
should also be noted. The grandson is the mir¬
ror image of the grandfather and thus becomes
the "little husband" of his grandmother. Similar¬
ly, the granddaughter who bears her paternal
grandmother's name becomes the "mother" of
her own father. These relationships are more than
just a game and people around them adopt at¬
titudes towards the children which correspond
to the status of the personages the children enact.
24
Marriage strategy
The organization of a marriage involves a number
of phases. First of all, the head of a group of mar¬
riageable young men offers the head of the poten¬
tial bride's clan a series of services or gifts of food
or other objectsincluding a particularly valuable
one, which is wrongly called the dowry and in
exchange receives the desired girl. The first group
then decides which of the boys will marry the
girl, while the second group decides who is to
receive the dowry and thus, in his turn, be in a
position to acquire a wife. ,
By virtue of the dowry paid, the husband's
clan acquires right of paternity over children of
the marriage. In return, the bride's clan obtains
an extension of its territorial rights and the right
of intervention in the affairs of the clan to which
it has become linked through the person of the
bride. Normally, the dowry goes to the bride's
brother, preferably born of the same mother and
her immediate senior or junior. Otherwise it goes
to another brother from the maternal home or
to another son of the same father, or to a cousin.
The brother who receives the dowry will
have a special relationship with his sister's
children. His wife, bought with this dowry, is
obliged to be submissive in relation to the sister-
in-law thanks to whom she was able to get mar¬
ried. In some societies in central Cameroon, the
two sisters-in-law are regarded as husband and
wife and address each other in these terms.
The new bride sets up home on the territory
of her husband's clan, usually on the father-in-
law's property where the son may have his own
huts. She is received by her mother-in-law who
completes her education, teaches her the customs
of the family and, later, declares her fit to manage
her own "kitchen".
The mother-in-law refers to her daughter-in-
law in the same terms she uses in speaking of her
husband's other wives who are junior to her.
Wives of this category belong by right to the
female founders of the householdusually the
first two wives. The ambition of these founding
wives is to produce a line, if not a lineage, with
a distinct name. To do this they have to gather
together as many young women as possible who
will produce many childrentheir sons' wives
and other women, generally from their own
former village, whom they bring and eventually
place at their husband's disposal.
The man attempts to obtain other women
from households that are already established.
African traditional
societies lay emphasis upon
a contractual social link
based on the notion of the
parental 'role', which may
be played by several
people. "
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Thus, polygamy is as much the business of the
husband as of his consorts and seems to be less
an expression of the man's power and wealth than
a means of perpetuating a form of society.
Polygamy makes it possible to achieve two
apparently opposed objectives. It signifies a man's
ascent in the social hierarchy (the man most en¬
vied is the man at the head of the largest com¬
munity), and it also tends to divide that
community into matrifocal-based households
each seeking autonomy (lineages attached to a
single founder-wife).
In the traditional African setting, marriage is
a matter of considerable importance. It is through
marriage that the constituent elements of socie¬
ty reproduce themselves and that groups and in¬
dividuals further a complex strategy. Women play
a crucial role in this process, since they gather
together and control other women as wives and
companions for brothers, sons and husbands.
The community
and its households
The African family to which this process gives
rise is an extended family which may consist of
fifty to a hundred people living in a single
domestic community. The men of the communi¬
ty form a sub-group organized in a hierarchy
based on social position and order of birth. The
hierarchical aspect is, however, moderated by a
collective sense of the equality of all who can
claim descent from the same ancestor.
The women's group consists, on the one
hand, of the unmarried girls and widows of the
lineage and, on the other, of women introduced
into the community by marriage. The women's
sub-group is organized into a hierarchy based on
age and also, for the wives, on the order of ar¬
rival and status conferred upon them by the ritual
of marriage.
Thus the adults of the community consist of
the male group, linked by blood, and the female
group composed of women from different
families who are united by a common duty of
solidarity with the group that accepted them.
The children have different prospects before
them. The boys will remain to ensure the con¬
tinuation of the lineage. The girls will leave to
found new lineages but without breaking with
their parents. For although a woman remains an
outsider in her husband's family, she maintains
close links with her group of origin within which
she retains both duties and privileges.
In practice a woman spends as much time
with her parents as in her adopted group and re¬
mains very independent of her husband. Her hus¬
band may have the right to repudiate her for
misconduct or sterility, but she too can decide
to leave her husband on the grounds of lack of
security or incompatibility with his way of life.
In the latter case her brothers and fathers must
assume responsibility for the consequences.
11 COUNTRIES
ON FILM
Little-known aspects of 11
developing countries are
shown in a new video
series "Terres d'espoir",
produced by ORCHIDÉES,
The World Picture Agency,
in collaboration with
Unesco. The series, com¬
prising documentary films
made between 1984 and
1988, takes viewers to
Benin, Burkina Faso,
Cameroon, the Congo,
Ghana, Mali, Mauritius,
the Philippines, Senegal,
Thailand and Viet Nam.
To obtain the series,
please contact:
ORCHIDÉES, L'Agence
d'Images du Monde,
The World Picture Agency,
BP 043,
94200 Ivry, France.
Tel: (33.1) 46.71.82.53
THE MIDDLE EAST AND NORTH AFRICA
The future
of the family
The future of the family in the Middle East and North
Africa was discussed at an international seminar held at
the University of Tunis between 20 and 23 February 1989.
The seminar, organized by Unesco and the United Na¬
tions Population Fund (UNFPA), will be followed by 4
other meetings on the same subject as part of prepara¬
tions for the International Year of the Family which will
be proposed for 1994 at the General Assembly of the
United Nations in New York later this year.
JL HE Tunis meeting was attended by twenty-
four participants and forty-eight observers from
many countries of the region and from different
social and professional backgrounds (teachers,
doctors, journalists, film-makers) and academic
disciplines (history, sociology, economics,
education).
The meeting reached the following conclu¬
sions. The region stretching from Mauritania to
Pakistan, across the Arabic, Iranian and Turkish
cultural areas, is still largely dominated by the
model of the endogamous extended family, an
authoritarian, strongly hierarchical and close-
knit social institution.
However, from the second half of the nine¬
teenth century, contact with European col¬
onialism exposed this model to major social and
economic shocks which tended to make it more
flexible and led to a diversification of family
types according to their degree of integration in¬
to modern life.
Two subjects received special attention at the
meeting: family migrations and relations bet¬
ween men and women. Migration was con¬
sidered, like the media and tourism, as an
essential factor in acculturation. The families of
migrants experience a dual processslow
disintegration in their country of origin, and
adaptation to their host country.
As for relations between men and women,
the meeting noted a change in practices concer¬
ning the choice of partner, age of marriage, con¬
ditions of divorce with important psychological
and even pathological consequences.
There was general agreement that the fami¬
ly is slowly but continually changing; that it will
certainly remain the basic unit of society; and
that the Western-type nuclear family is not
necessarily a model to be imitated.
The changes which are today taking place
in the family may not always be perceptible to
an outside observer, and a superficial impression
of rigid continuity with the traditional order is
sometimes given. But profound changes in
customs and ideas are continuing to take place,
sometimes causing tensions to erupt in the in¬
dividual or collective mind. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The woman who founds a household is con¬
sidered to be the mother of all the children born
in it, including those born to her husband's other
wives. The children of the "same mother" rank
in the hierarchy in accordance with the
chronological order of their mother's marriage
and the importance of the ritual with which the
household was founded. The autonomy of the
household increases with the age of the first-born
son, the father's heir presumptive, and the arrival
of other women and children. The eldest son will
thus become the head of the household of which
his "mother" is the mistress.
The household can thus be seen as a specific
area in which the mother, the son and the
mother's brother occupy the leading positions.
In traditional African societies, despite
decades if not centuries of contact with the out¬
side world, the totality of social relationships, in¬
cluding economic relationships, are governed by
kinship. Social scientists who imposed blueprints
for the evolution of these societies that were in¬
spired by European history have been surprised
by the durability of this phenomenon. According
to these blueprints, a small degree of industrializa
tion, accelerated urbanization, the introduction
of schooling and conversion to Christianity and
the insertion of African countries into the world
political and economic order should have brought
a complete upheaval in the family structure.
However, the old attitudes and practices have
not disappeared; they have simply been adapted
to suit the conditions of modern life. The authori¬
ty of the leaders of the lineages remains
sociologically stronger than that of the state.
Polygamy persists, even if it is now practised
more discreetly, with wives being dispersed in dif¬
ferent places. The rules of the unilineal kinship
system are still applied despite modern legislation
which recognizes the family as consisting only
of two parents and their children.
Many legal dispositions, primarily those
relating to the individual ownership of proper¬
ty, are profoundly impregnated with modern no¬
tions of individualism which clash with the
African tradition whereby the community is the
main component of all identity.
The step from the right of the family com¬
munity to occupy land to private, individually
owned property has dealt a blow to the cohesion
Damming a stream in
Burkina Faso. The elders
are repairing tools beneath
the palaver tree.
26 -jß**t§
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
of the family group. Now the eldest son is no
longer content to manage a shared land heritage;
he is tempted to appropriate it for himself by
establishing the title deeds in his own name. In
so doing he runs the risk of becoming engaged
in a long and tortuous legal process in which he
will be in opposition to his brothers and sisters.
This often leads to the breaking up of the
patrimony into separate parcels of land, or its li¬
quidation. These frequent legal procedures break
the previously indestructible link that united the
members of the community among themselves
and with their ancestors.
Furthermore, the appearance of the modern,
centralizing state has rendered superfluous many
of the functions of the family head. The transmis¬
sion of title deeds and responsibilities has become
less important than that of goods and property
left by bequest. This makes it important to
distinguish between biological children who are
entitled to inherit directly, from the brother's
children (in patrilineal societies) and from the
sister's children (in matrilineal societies).
The new African family
All this is leading to a strengthening of the pro¬
cess of individualization and to the break-up of
traditional family unity. This does not mean,
however, that the traditional African family is be¬
ing transformed into the small, Western-style,
nuclear family. Rather it is giving rise to single-
parent families built around either the father or
the mother. The movement towards in¬
dividualization clashes with the need to be a part
of a network of solidarity which, for the most
part, remains the lineage. Some individuals join
associations based on age or social position which
offer their members social assistance and
psychological support.
These few examples demonstrate the limits
of change in the social and family fabric. This
resistance to change may be explained in terms
of an underlying rejection of individualistic
ideology or of the limitations of state power. It
seems likely, however, that the encounter bet¬
ween Western ideology and traditional social
values will give rise to new family structures
fashioned by a society undergoing a rapid
transformation.
Students walking home after
school near Addis Abeba, Ethiopia
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Bound by economic ties as well as kin¬
ship, the traditionalJapanesefamily has
undergone sweeping changes in modern
times. Its members have achieved greater
independence..but at what cost?
T
28
HE traditional form of the Japanese family is
designated by the word ie, which denotes an
original concept embracing not only the struc¬
ture of the family but the bonds uniting its
members, the family assets, and the activities con¬
nected with it.
In most cases, this basic family unit consists
of a sonusually the eldest son living with his
parents after marriagehis children, and his un¬
married brothers and sisters. But ie also includes
deceased forebears and unborn descendants. The
continuity of the family depends largely upon the
maintenance of the material basis which
guarantees its social status and way of life. Since
its survival is closely connected with the
maintenance of its activities, the Japanese family
is often defined as a family business. The heritage
is just as important as the continuation of the
family line, and more so than the prosperity or
even the life and death of individual members of
the household.
The ie is primarily based upon family ties,
the most important of which are those with
parents and ancestors. The eldest son is
responsiblein most cases alonefor
perpetuating the ie. When they get married, the
younger sons will in turn be called upon to found
other ie. In theory the younger branches continue
to owe allegiance to the senior branch, but in
practice they soon achieve autonomy and their
founders become ancestors of new ie. The only
ones which remain linked are those families
which are bound to each other by strong finan¬
cial interests, or which live in the same
neighbourhood. Few Japanese are well acquainted
with their collateral family, and it is not uncom¬
mon for a Japanese to be incapable of quoting
the exact names of his eight great-grandparents.
The wife as servant of the ie
In this typical organization, the wife's role is
essentially to provide heirs for her husband's
family. If the marriage proves to be sterile, the
wife is sent back to her parents, and the adop¬
tion of a male child must then be considered. A
wife's entire education prepares her to become
the servant of her husband's lineage. In the early
Under new
Nlealtime in a modern
Japanese household.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
management BY KURIMOTO KAZUO
THE
FAMILY
PAST
AND PRESENT
THE CHANGING
JAPANESE FAMILY 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
1 he women of a Japanese
household prepare a family
meal c. 1930.
eighteenth century, the principles which should
govern a wife's behaviour were defined by the
moralist Kaibara Ekiken. They can be summariz¬
ed as follows:
When a wife enters her husband's house she
must follow the instructions of his parents, wait
upon them and be agreeable to them at all times.
They should avoid excessive affection which
would make her capricious, and they should not
allow her to have a will of her own.
A wife must respect her husband's brothers and
sisters.
She should be prudent and strict in her personal
behaviour, rise early, retire late, and her atten¬
tion should be concentrated upon the house
throughout the day.
She should rarely appear in public before the
age of forty.
Her behaviour should be dignified and
reasonable, because her misconduct would ruin
the house.
Even a wife who is surrounded by servants
should take an interest in everything, because
"that is the wife's law".
And so the heavy task of maintaining the
peace and ensuring the proper functioning of the
house falls upon the wife. Her personality should
be relegated to the background.
By contrast with the subordinate status of the
wife, the powers enjoyed by the head of the fami¬
ly are very extensive. He can remove from the
family register (koseki) any member who might
harm the ie. Since the end of the nineteenth cen¬
tury, he has been the sole owner of the family
assets. No other member of the family, even an
adult, may 'enter into a contract without his per¬
mission. His powers, which may seem exorbitant,
are based upon a profound consensus within the
family.
The head of the family
On the other hand, the head of the family has
certain responsibilities, and he may be
stripped of his authority if he proves incapable
of managing the family fortune. The "instruc¬
tions for the head of a family" of a retail kimono
merchant in Kyoto laid down that "even the head
of the family may not neglect his work by lying
in bed late or going out frequently in the even¬
ings and indulging in gambling. If this happens,
the older members of the shop's staff, who are
responsible, should report the matter to his
parents. When the family's capital and goods have
been valued, compensation shall be paid to the
head of the family and he shall be obliged to retire
from management of the family business". The
head of another Kyoto family stipulated that "if
any of my potential successors begins to spend
irresponsibly, and there is reason to think that
he is not a trustworthy heir to the family
business, the family, after consulting the parents,
shall give him 5 per cent of the family assets and
create a branch for him. When this separation has
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
been completed, a reliable person shall be chosen
to succeed him".
Although succession is hereditary, the head
of the family or any other undesirable relative
can be excluded. Such is the overriding impor¬
tance of the ie's continuity, that it is not uncom¬
mon for a new member to be adopted.
The basis of the nation
The traditional ie is more in the nature of a socio¬
economic institution than a community linked
by blood-relationships. The head of the family
strongly resembles the head of a business. When
the question of his succession arises, this business
does not necessarily give priority to his "blood
child". The paramount consideration is that the
enterprise be headed by a competent manager.
The ie system is of very ancient origin. It goes
back to the eleventh century, but it was during
the second half of the Tokugawa shogunate that
it became consolidated and officially established,
partly under the influence of Confucian doc¬
trines. The ie type of organization soon ceased
to be confined to the samurai caste and the rich
merchant and farmer class, and became a model
for all Japanese families. It became the very basis
of the nation and one of the main components
of Japanese identity.
Although it was criticized after the Second
World War on the grounds that it had justified
militarism and was an obstacle to democratiza¬
tion, the ie concept has survived in big firms,
although divested of its former political and
ideological connotations.
Absentee fathers
The Japanese family has evolved considerably
since the 1946 Constitution came into force.
Although the traditional ie still survives, new legal
structures favour the development of nuclear
families (63.4 per cent in 1970) by granting equal
rights to men and women and imposing a
distribution of the estate among the children.
This trend has been strengthened by post-war in¬
dustrial and urban changes. Nowadays, families
are much smaller, usually consisting of only one
or two children. The generations live apart from
each other and the children, even the unmarried
ones, soon acquire their autonomy.
This trend accelerated from the 1960s on¬
wards, with the growth in the number of jobs
and the resulting mobility. Initially it was main¬
ly young workers who left rural areas for the ur¬
ban industrial centres. Then, many heads of rural
families took seasonal employment in expanding
urban areas, leaving the cultivation of the land
to their wives, children, or other members of
their families. These seasonal jobs soon became
permanent and so it became common for heads
of families to be absent most of the year. This
trend is not confined to manual workers.
A group of men eat together in a
Japanese restaurant. Because of
professional commitments Japanese fathers
today are more often absent from the
family table than in the past.
jMLany elderly persons live with their
children, whereas in the past it was the
children who lived under their parents'
roof." Below, a little Japanese boy makes
music for his grandfather.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
In today's small two-
generation families the
bond between mother and
child is closer than ever.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Transfers of managerial and executive staff to new
project sites are becoming increasingly necessary
because of economic expansion.
It is difficult for a family to follow the father
if he is moved around too often. Finding family
accommodation is quite a problem, and too many
moves are bad for children and their studies.
The phenomenon known as tanshin hunin
(unaccompanied transfer of a member of the fami¬
ly) is common in Japan today, but it is giving rise
to problems. The family head may find a
substitute for ie in his links with his firm-
employment for life, membership of a communi¬
ty, concern for its prosperity and its perpetuity
but he suffers from the loosening of family ties.
Many men only see their families at weekends.
This may be one of the causes of the depressions,
stress and alcoholism which afflict so many men.
The solitary wife
The wife suffers no less than her husband. She is
increasingly isolated. Even when he lives at home
during the week, her husband goes to work early
in the morning and comes back late in the even¬
ing. Children are at school all day or go off in the
afternoon to juku (extra private lessons). Many
married women react to this solitude by looking
for a job or taking part in the activities of cultural
groups.
Relations between mothers and their children
are also changing. The bonds between them are
close and exclusive. Because of the decline in the
birth rate, children find fewer playmates in their
neighbourhood and almost none at home.
Deprived of contacts with children of their own
age, they cling to their mothers' apron strings.
In the extended families of the past, the
psychological link with the mother was only one
family relationship among others. Since children
formed their own society within the group, they
had less difficulty leaving home. Now separation
from the mother is becoming much more painful
for both mother and child. For the mother, the
chief concern is her child's success at school. For¬
ty years ago a child who was accompanied to
secondary school by his mother would have been
the laughing-stock of his schoolmates. Nowadays,
many mothers accompany their children, not on¬
ly to secondary school, but even to the university.
Newspapers wax ironical about mothers who ac¬
company their sons as far as the door of the firm
on their first day at work.
The ageing of the population is having other
consequences. For a long time life expectancy in
Japan was 50 years, but by 1982 it had risen to 75
for men and 80.4 for women. In 1930 most
fathers died before their youngest child had com¬
pleted university studies, and the mother rarely
outlived the head of the family. Now, when the
youngest child has finished his or her studies, it is
common for the father to have a life expectancy
of a further twenty years and the mother thirty.
In many cases the parents are neither financially
nor psychologically prepared for the departure of
their children. This is an unprecedented situation,
and no cultural model exists to help them to cope
with it. A new life-style will have to be created
which will enable older people to take an activé
part in the life of the community, assume their
social responsibilities and define their new iden¬
tity. In fact, there is no ready-made answer to this
problem.
Many elderly persons live with their children,
whereas in the past it was the children who lived
under their parents' roof. Under the present law,
each descendant receives an equal share of the
family estate, and the question arises which of the
children shall take in the elders. The average
household rarely possesses the necessary resources
and space. The nuclear family is often faced with
a crisis when it has to assume responsibility for
the health care of its elders.
The broken bond
This crisis is reflected in customs relating to the
organization of meals. Formerly, meals were ritu¬
als which strengthened the cohesion of the fami¬
ly group. Now this essential function is on the
wane and in many families most meals are no
longer taken in common. About 60 per cent of
fathers do not take part in the family breakfast,
and 30 per cent of them are absent at dinner time.
Most mothers have lunch alone at home. The
decline in the frequency of meals eaten in com¬
mon is weakening the psychological bonds be¬
tween members of the same family.
Developments in the mass media also run
counter to the family spirit. The family is ceas¬
ing to be a place for the exchange of news. With
the growth in the number of channels, cable tel¬
evision and the diversification of programmes,
watching television is becoming an individual ac¬
tivity. Increasingly, each member of the family
has his or her own sources of information and
tends to share them less and less with the rest of
the family.
However, this may be just a passing phase,
and new modes of behaviour may emerge. For
instance, there is an increase in the number of
"houses for two generations", in which elderly
parents and their children can live together while
preserving their independence. It is also proba¬
ble that the revival of traditional feasts, bringing
together members of different generations, and
in which everyone has a role to play, points to
a tightening of family links. Perhaps a new cul¬
tural model is about to emerge?
I
KURIMOTO KAZUO,
of Japan, is a Unesco staff
member specializing in
educational administration
and management.
ill 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Marina, Sarah, Michel
'Conventional' marriage in Europe
today is facing competition from new
forms offamily life shaped by the aspira¬
tions ofboth partners to an equal chance
offulfilment.
IYIaRINA is thirty-three years old and is the
mother of five-year-old Sarah. She is expecting
a baby boy. Starting off with no money, no in¬
fluential contacts and relying solely on her own
courage, tenacity and intelligence, and on some
limited funding from the French Ministry of
Culture, she has created her own theatre com¬
pany which she runs singlehanded, selecting the
repertoire, organizing tours both in France and
abroad, and hiring and training the members of
the troupe.
Marina is not married, but when she goes off
on tour she entrusts Sarah to the care of Michel,
Sarah's father, or to Jean, her lover and the father
of the child she is expecting, but who does not
live with her. The friendship between Marina and
Michel has survived not only the ending of their
period of cohabitation but also the new liaison
with Jean. There is no jealousy between the two
men and they take turns, in perfect harmony, to
look after Sarah during her mother's absences.
Whenever they are free to do so, they give Marina
a hand when she is putting on a show in Paris
or in a town in the immediate suburbs that is
close enough for them to get to after work.
How many couples are there in Europe that
have had the same kind of success in finding fulfil¬
ment while breaking the conventions which
make cohabitation the criterion of existence as
a couple and the sacrifice of her professional life
the condition of a woman's personal happiness?
Their number seems to be increasing. But before
we examine these new family life-styles let us take
a look at the general situation of the family in
Europe.
Research carried out in twelve countries of
Eastern and Western Europe shows that, in
families where the parents are married, the wife
always spends more time than the husband on
domestic tasks and the education of the children.
In France and the United Kingdom, for exam¬
ple, the women of the household devote four or
five times more time per day than their husbands
to these tasks. Even when the women have a pro¬
fessional activity, the gap is still three times
greater. Similar discrepancies are to be found in
34 many East European countries.
The time spent on domestic and educational
tasks increases, of course, when couples have
children. But the wife always spends much more
time on domestic duties than the husband. When
his wife has a professional activity, the husband's
participation is greater, but it remains only
"help" and can in no sense be seen as equal
sharing.
The husband as breadwinner
Although 43 per cent of married women in
Europe are gainfully employed, the proportion
falls far short of that of gainfully employed men,
which ranges from 78 per cent to 90 per cent ac¬
cording to the country concerned. Husbands are
more often the family breadwinners than wives,
who, when they do work outside the home,
generally earn much less. Wives work part-time
much more frequently than husbands. In some
countries (the United Kingdom, Ireland, the
Netherlands and the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many), the presence of young children in the
home reduces by ten times the likelihood that a
woman has outside employment. In other coun¬
tries (France, Belgium and Denmark), the number
of children rather than their age is the determin¬
ing factor.
Despite the progress noted in recent years,
attitudes towards role-sharing within the family
are evolving only slowly. In 1987, 41 per cent of
Europeans said that they were in favour of
families in which both parents had an occupation
which both found equally absorbing and in which
domestic tasks and child care were equally shared.
Some 29 per cent preferred a situation in which
the wife had a less demanding activity than the
husband and 25 per cent preferred a family in
which only the man went out to work.
The search for happiness and
new family life-styles
The traditional division of tasks between the sexes
does not seem to please all Europeans. A grow¬
ing number of men and women are looking for
life as a couple outside conventional marriage.
Throughout Europe the decrease in the mar¬
riage rate is offset by an increase in the number
of unofficial unions. In France alone, which is
still far behind the Scandinavian countries, 10 per
cent of all couples (that is to say about one million
couples) live together in these free unions.
Among young couples living in the Paris conur¬
bation and in which the male partner is under
twenty-five years of age, the proportion is as high
Small Family (1986), a
lithograph by the Greek artist
Arghyro Paouri.
THE
FAMILY
PAST
AND PRESENT
EUROPE
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
andJean BY ANDREE MICHEL
v^ 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
In Europe, there has
been an increase in the
number of single-parent
families, in which the
children live with only one
of the parentsin most
cases with the woman."
36
ANDREE MICHEL,
of France, is a research
director at the French
National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS),
where she founded a study
group on sex roles, the
family and human
development. Among her
many publications are
Sociologie de la famille et du
mariage (Presses
Universitaires de France,
1986), Le féminisme (PUF,
1986) and Down with
Stereotypes! Eliminating
Sexism from Children 's
Literature and School
Textbooks (Unesco, 1986).
as 50 per cent. A quarter of these French couples,
of all ages, have and bring up children. More
young women than men of equivalent class prefer
these unofficial unions, since this new life-style
seems to them to be more egalitarian.
The men and women of Europe are no longer
prepared to put up with unhappy marriages.
Since 1965, there has been a big increase in the
number of divorces throughout the continent.
Yet divorce is much more frequent in the nor¬
thern countries of Europe (Scandinavia) than in
the southern countries (France, Italy, Spain). Ex¬
cept in Ireland, where divorce is still forbidden,
the authorities in most countries have made
divorce procedures easier, although legislative
changes have lagged behind changing public
attitudes.
One consequence of these changes has been
an increase in the number of single-parent
families, in which the children live with only one
of the parentsin the majority of cases with the
woman (90 per cent in France, 93 per cent in
Denmark). In the view of the European Parlia¬
ment, the single-parent family must be considered
as a "family unit" and must not be subject to any
"discrimination"."'
With the increase in unofficial unions, the
number of children born out of wedlock has in¬
creased significantly. In 1980, 40 per cent of
Swedish children were born to unmarried
mothers, a status all the more acceptable to public
opinion in that social reforms have favoured the
single parent with a child. In France, the number
of children in this situation increased by 50 per
cent between 1982 and 1986 to reach a total of
about 171,000, or 22 per cent of all births, a sure
sign of a profound change in attitudes and
behaviour. The traditional situation of the
woman being abandoned by the child's father is
becoming less widespread. Along with this a new
pattern is emerging in which the child is
acknowledged by the father. In 1980, in France,
50 per cent of children born outside marriage
were acknowledged by the father, as compared
with 22.5 per cent in 1968.
Except in Scandinavia, European law-makers
continue to treat couples living together outside
marriage unfavourably in comparison with mar¬
ried couples, but in most countries an attempt
is being made to lessen discrimination against
children born out of wedlock. In Ireland, for ex¬
ample, reforms tending in this direction were
passed in 1986.
How is life organized in single-parent
families, most of which are the outcome of
divorce or separation? In at least 90 per cent of
cases the custody and upbringing of the children
are entrusted to the mother. The husband is
obliged to pay a maintenance allowance to the
wife for the upkeep of the children. In some
countries (Luxembourg, Denmark, France) the
authorities may even pay the share of a defaulting
husband so that a wife without resources and
with children to support is not left unprovided
for.
More than in the past, European law-makers
are taking note of the desire of the couple for
equality of status and the growth in the number
of women entering the labour market. Denmark
has even gone so far as to give equal parental
authority to both partners, whether or not they
are married or living together, so as to meet the
aspirations of single fathers who, if there is a
separation, have many fewer rights than the
mother over the children. In France, alternating
custody of the children is on the increase.
Overcoming loneliness
Where does Marina, whose story we outlined
above, fit into this scheme of things? She and her
daughter can hardly be considered a single-parent
family since, strictly speaking, the paternal role
played by Michel, Sarah's father, and Jean, the
father-to-be of the expected child, excludes them
from this category. There are many other forms
of family that are equally hard to categorize. Be¬
ing neither legal marriages, unofficial unions nor
single-parent families, they figure in none of the
statistics and in no sociological data.
Most European countries are experiencing an
increase in the number of people, especially
young people, living singly. In France, in 1985,
records showed that 27 per cent of men between
the ages of 30 and 34 and 26 per cent of women
in the same age group were living singly. What
kind of a life do they lead? Are they hardened
bachelors withdrawn into themselves and im¬
mured in solitude? Or have they created around
themselves, as a substitute for the family group,
a social network from which they draw the af-
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
fective and social support necessary to maintain
their personal equilibrium?
Among them are those who do not live with
their partners, each member of the couple living
in his or her own home, but both putting a pro¬
portion of their resources into a common fund
so that, if they have children, they can between
them fulfil this new financial commitment.
There are also cases where members of the
same sex live together. They may be a homosex¬
ual couple, friends or people linked by the need
for mutual economic assistance (the unemployed
or those who cannot find or afford accommoda¬
tion). The growing number of "households" (in
the statistical sense of the term) consisting either
of a single person living alone or of two or more
people of the same sex, covers a multitude of
diverse forms of social life, all of which are
substitutes for the traditional family framework.
Despite change,
parent/child solidarity
persists
This variety of horizontally developing family
forms contrasts with the stability of the vertical
relationships within a family group and the per¬
manence of intra-family solidarity.
All surveys show that the desire to live a hap¬
py life within the family group remains pre¬
eminent. Young adultsmothers and "new
fathers"derive the greatest satisfaction from
bringing up their children. And at parties held
to celebrate the rites of passage (birth,
adolescence, marriage, death) families gather
together to renew their links of social solidarity.
This solidarity shows no signs of disappear¬
ing. Young adults benefit from the support of
their parents in many circumstancesduring their
studies, on marriage and in the early stages of life
as a couple, on the purchase or fitting out of a
home or of a house in the country. The same
solidarity may be in evidence later, on the occa¬
sion of a major unforeseen expense, illness or in¬
terruption of work due to an accident or
unemployment. In return, in their old age parents
are helped by their children, who visit them fairly
regularly and may even give them financial help.
Today the individual European considers that
he or she has a right to happiness. Very often
there springs from this a refusal to enter into or
remain within the rigid framework of the fami¬
ly or of marriage with its fixed conventional
codes. A further consequence of this is the ever
more widespread practice of defining for oneself
a life-style in which the search for personal hap¬
piness can be fulfilled.
Europeans are now less willing to allow
legislators to set rules of behaviour for their
private lives and tend to reject legal discrimina¬
tion between those who are married and those
who are not married, between those who are
divorced and those who are not, between
1 he desire to live a happy life
within the family group remains
pre-eminent. Young adults-
mothers and 'new fathers'derive
the greatest satisfaction from
bringing up their children. "
* *' s-
lit
heterosexuals and homosexuals and between
legitimate children and "natural" children.
The notion is spreading in Europe that
human rights are not exclusively political rights,
but also concern the liberty of individuals to
choose the form and content of their private lives,
particularly with regard to the identity of their
partners, the right to divorce, the number of
children they have, and contraception. These are
the issues in a struggle that is spreading in all
European societies, at least in those where social
movements, often inspired by women, are
fighting against the survival of patriarchal stan¬
dards now thought to be incompatible with the
rights of the individual and with happiness.
* "Femmes d'Europe: 10 ans", in Femmes d'Europe, No. 27, June 1988 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The women of Arembepe
Many heads offamilies in Brazil are
women. The case ofArembepe, afishing
village near Bahia, suggests some reasons
why this is so.
38
X HE colonization of Latin America by the
Portuguese and the Spanish was decisive for the
organization of family life in this part of the New
World. Since colonial times, the patriarchal
family has been the predominant model, either
nuclear (essentially in the towns and cities) or
extended (in the countryside). Matrifocal families
centred on a woman and her children are also
found, although in smaller numbers, notably in
the regions densely populated by blacks or
mulattoes.
The black population of Latin America were
brought there as slaves early in the seventeenth
century. The indigenous populations (heirs of
such brilliant civilizations as those of the Mayas,
the Incas and the Aztecs, or fragile communities
threatened with extinction) refused to work for
the European invader, and slavery came to
provide a supply of labour for the gold and silver
mines, and the sugar, tobacco and cotton
plantations.
Even after the abolition of the black slave
trade, clandestine ships continued until the mid-
nineteenth century to bring their human cargoes
to Latin America's two main slave ports, Salvador
de Bahia in Brazil and Cartagena de Indias in
Colombia.
This period saw the establishment of a rigid
social stratification related to economic power
but also to skin colour. The rich landed
proprietors were white, and the poor agricultural
labourers were former black slaves. At the same
time mixed unions brought about a mingling of
the three ethnic groups (indigenous, black, and
white) and a synthesis of their cultures.
By separating the female slaves from their
menfolk (a group of slaves was never allowed to
consist of more than one third of women), the
slave trade actually encouraged their sexual
exploitation by their masters. It was not unusual
for the latter to recognize and bring up the
children they had had by a slave. The slave
woman, for her part, transmitted her own culture
to the master's children along with her milk, her
lullabies, her legends and her games.
'.
--,
1 erra-cotta Maya statuette
of the pre-classical period
(1500 B.C-300 A.D.).
1 he marriage of a black
couple in the house of a
rich family is depicted in
this engraving by the
French artist Jean-Baptiste
Debret (1768-1848).
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
BY MARIZA DE ATHAYDE FlGUEIREDO AND DANDA PRADO
THE
FAMILY
PAST
AND PRESENT
LATIN AMERICA 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Migration is a growing
source of insecurity for
women, especially if the
men who leave for the
cities fail to send money
home or leave at a crucial
time of the agricultural
year. " (United Nations
Population Fund "State of
World Population" Report,
1989).
40
MAR1ZA DE ATHAYDE
FIGUEIREDO,
Brazilian sociologist,
journalist and
photographer, is an editor
of the Rio de Janeiro
feminist magazine
Impressoes. She has
published articles in a
number of magazines,
including Tiers Monde and
Feminist Issues. Her doctoral
thesis (University of Paris
VII, 1981) was a study of
the social and economic role
of women heads of families
at Arembepe, Brazil.
DANDA PRADO
is a Brazilian educationist,
psychologist and teacher
with a special interest in the
social role of women.
Among her published works
are O que é familia (1982,
"What is the Family?") and
O que é aborto (1983,
"Vfhat is Abortion?"). She
has contributed to several
anthologies, including
Sisterhood is Global (Archer
Press, New York, 1984).
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
A Brazilian woman at
work in a light engineering
plant.
1 he man goes, the
children stay."
w*P^B^I
m
JL-ti!
¥ s f^ * ^B
t ... ^' v» :
Families that were not patterned on the white
model were mostly extended families grouping
children around their mother. On the other hand,
the civil code of the whites in most cases upheld
the patriarchal régime. Legislation inspired by the
Napoleonic Code of 1808 attributed inferior
status to women and kept them dependent on
men, according to the norms of the classic patriar¬
chal family. This statute has only recently been
modified to give greater autonomy to women and
to allow marriages to be dissolved.
The contemporary family
Cultural and ethnic intermingling, rampant ur¬
banization (in Brazil today 70 per cent of the
population lives in the towns and cities), inter¬
nal and external migration, changes in women's
status and the profound transformation of models
of reproduction, have contributed among other
factors to the appearance of new family structures
and favoured the emergence throughout Latin
America of the woman as head of the family.
This phenomenon, which is not new, is com¬
ing to be seen as part of a survival strategy for
needy populations. It has been brought about by
circumstances and not choice, since women and
men invariably aspire to contract a legitimate
union before the priest and the mayor.
The man considers himself to be the head of
the family and wishes to be treated accordingly.
The mores of patriarchal society confer authori¬
ty on him whether or not he assumes the obliga¬
tions springing from it, notably that of feeding
his wife and children. Furthermore, by virtue of
the virility cult known as machismo, the man has
a right to maintain extra-conjugal relations or to
gamble and drink, which does not always leave
him enough to provide for his family.
When she is forced to assume the role of head
of the family, the woman generally adopts an am¬
biguous attitude towards her husband or partner.
This ambiguity is the result of her contradictory
situation, since society has promised her a man
who would provide for household needs, leaving
her to do the housekeeping and bring up the
children. She does not boast of being the head
of the family; on the contrary she conceals this
disagreeable status by maintaining that she is
simply helping to meet household expenses.
It was not until 1978 that this phenomenon
became the object of major sociological and
economic studies, notably at the request of the
United Nations. In 1974 it had already been
calculated that one third of the world's heads of
families were women. However, only now is
awareness of the problem and its impact on
developing countries beginning to make itself felt.
Arembepe is a fishing village near Bahia in
Brazil, with a population of 2,000 which is
swollen in summer by an influx of
holidaymakers. There is evidence that it already
existed as a settlement of Tupinamba Indians in
1509 when the Portuguese arrived. A represen¬
tative microcosm of rural communities both in
Brazil and elsewhere in Latin America, in 1981
Arembepe was the subject of a survey on women
heads of families.
The expansion of industry and tourism has
transformed the Arembepe fishermen into
salaried workers. The factories do not employ
women, who are reduced to taking ill-paid jobs
working for holidaymakers. However, 25.5 per
cent of the women of Arembepe are heads of
families and are responsible for one or several per¬
sons. They are more numerous in the poor
categories (57.62 per cent) than among the
better-off.
The situation of these women is not covered
by the official definition of the Brazilian Office
of Geography and Statistics, whereby only the
husband is considered to be a head of the family,
independently of his contribution to the family
budget and the legal situation of the couple.
Thus the single, separated or widowed
women who house and feed their children, grand¬
children and elderly or handicapped parents are
deprived of the title of head of the family. If they
have a partner with them on the day when the
census official arrives, he is considered to be the
head of the family, whether or not he is the father
of any of the children, contributes to the family
income, or has been living there for years or on¬
ly a few months.
The man's role as head of the family is thus
often no more than symbolic. His material
obligations towards his wife and children are
those he wishes to recognize. The woman has no
way of forcing him to assume the role of
economic provider which is socially and cultural¬
ly his.
In general, the women begin by hiding the
reality from themselves by saying that male fail¬
ings are temporary. When they have accepted
that these are irremediable, they look for another
man. If half of the women heads of families at
Arembepe have had a single regular union, 35.59
per cent of them, notably the youngest, have had
two. This second union reflects the search for a
new male social reference, even if it offers no
material guarantee or stability.
After several fruitless experiences, the woman
finally establishes a matricentred family group
and only has occasional relations with men. The
man goes, the children stay.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
New family structures
.oTW:Wrrj*#
h
\,
in ,.
MTW*
n
I
42
THE
FAMILY
PAST
AND PRESENT
QUEBEC
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
BY FRANCINE DESCARRIES AND CHRISTINE CORBEIL
«?
» J-U^à
J\ing and Queen, a work
by the British sculptor
Henry Moore (1898-1986).
Past Recovery (1979) by
Esther Parada. This
monumental family
portrait (2.50 x 3.70 m)
consists of one hundred
hand-toned photographs.
With the works of other
artists ofpast and present,
it features in an exhibition
on "The Family" being
held at The Museum of
Fine Arts, Houston (USA)
from 30 April to 6 August
1989.
The impact of change on the patri¬
archal and pro-natalist pattern of
traditional family life in Quebec
JL HERE have been many changes in family
structures and standards in North America over
the past twenty years, but nowhere else in the
West have these changes been so spectacular as
in Quebec. The religious and legal traditions of
Quebec society long favoured the maintenance
of a conservative matrimonial and family ethic
and provided a rigid framework for conjugal and
parental relationships. It was not until the end
of the 1960s, very late in comparison with other
areas of North America, that traditional family
behavioural and reproductive norms began to
change, as part of the wider movement towards
secularization which was then current in Quebec.
Three statistics demonstrate the scope and
direction of the changes that have occurred since
then.
In 1965, the marriage rate, that is, the
percentage of single people likely to get married
before the age of fifty, was around 85.9 per cent
for men and 93.5 per cent for women. Twenty
years later, the rate had gone down to about 49
per cent for men and 51.7 per cent for women.
In other words, during that period there was a
significant trend towards rejection of the
traditional rules governing the organization of
family life and a diversification of forms of union.
This phenomenon may also explain the fact that
in 1988 a third of all births occurred outside
marriage, whereas in the late 1960s the
proportion was less than 10 per cent. The fact
that births occurred outside legal marriage,
however, does not necessarily imply that they
were not the fruit of some form of union.
The divorce rate provides another significant
pointer. In 1988, it was estimated that more than
one in three marriages contracted during the year
would end in divorce. Twenty years earlier, when
divorce was legally more difficult to obtain, only
one marriage in ten was likely to be dissolved.
Finally, with the women of Quebec being
among the most fertile in the West, Quebec had
long had a steadily increasing birth rate. On the
eve of the 1990s, however, the situation has
changed radically. The current (1988) fertility rate
of 1.47 is not enough (2.1) to ensure maintenance
of existing population levels. In recent years,
Quebec has experienced one of the lowest fertility
rates in the world. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
A family of Quebec
farmers. According to a
survey of Quebec
households carried out in
1986, women do three
times more housework than
men: an average of36.6
hours per week as opposed
to 11.2 hours.
The role of mothers
in family change
More than ever before, women are playing a
critical role in the evolution of Quebec society.
The family is no longer the only setting in which
they can achieve personal and social fulfilment.
Their position strengthened by the advances
made by the women's movement in promoting
the equality of the sexes, the right to abortion
and to the use of contraceptives, and the right to
autonomy and self-fulfilment outside the family
and marriage, they are no longer obliged to
44
FRANCINE DESCARRIES,
of Canada, is a professor of
sociology at the University
of Quebec, Montreal, where
she is head of the Feminist
Research Centre. Among
her recent publications are
L'école rose et ¡es cols roses
("Pink School, Pink
Collars") and, with Shirley
Roy, an essay on currents
of thought in the women's
movement.
CHRISTINE CORBEIL,
of Canada, is a professor of
social work at the
University of Quebec,
Montreal. She is engaged on
research with Francine
Descarries, with whom she
has published a study on
maternity and the women's
movement in the Revue
Internationale d'Action
Communautaire (1987).
choose in such a limited and uncompromising
manner as before between "being" a wife, "be¬
ing" a mother and "having" a profession.
One woman in two of working age is now
in the market for gainful employment and the
percentage of women with children under sixteen
who are part of the working population has risen
from under 40 per cent at the beginning of the
1970s to about 60 per cent today.
Care of children after their birth raises ques¬
tions of planning and organization and leads to
discussion and hard bargaining among couples,
especially when each partner has career ambi¬
tions. Who will be prepared to forego his or her
professional activities, either wholly or in part,
to take on this other unpaid, singlehanded,
unremarked task? Which of them will agree to
give only secondary consideration to job securi¬
ty, promotion prospects and participation in
society in order to devote himself or herself to
the service of the child and the family?
In a society in which the objectives of a lov¬
ing relationship, the family and professional life
are no longer necessarily compatible, the declin¬
ing acceptance of the model of the full-time
mother and housewife is leading to a re-alignment
of roles and functions within the couple and the
family.
The delicate task
of sharing responsibilities
Apart from the two parents' normal, permanent
participation in family life, it is difficult to speak
of any real sharing out of tasks or any real
redefinition of models and roles. It is still the
woman who feeds, washes, dresses, nurses, super¬
vises, listens, advises and consoles. At best, fathers
only make a supplementary contribution,
specializing mainly in social activities such as
playing, educating and punishing. The paternal
contribution remains part-time, ad hoc and in¬
termittent, whereas the mother's is permanent,
unchanging and continuous.
A survey of 1,332 Quebec households carried
out in April 1986 revealed that women do three
times more housework than men, on which they
spend an average of 36.6 hours per week as op¬
posed to 11.2 hours for men. These statistics show
an increase in the contribution made by men, but
according to those who carried out the survey,
each hour of work in the home carried out by
men adds a quarter of an hour to that done by
their womenfolk. The women of Quebec are still
fighting to get men to take a more equitable share
in domestic tasks and family responsibilities.
The fathers' response
For some years now, certain groups of men have
been demanding an extension of the paternal
sphere of action, thus expressing a desire to play
a larger part in their children's lives. They are
demanding the right to be more fully involved
in their children's arrival into the world, in their
introduction to society and in their education.
They are critical of the old parental stereotypes
and want to establish new parent/child relation¬
ships based on collaboration and generosity.
Playing down their role as "providers", they
want to accentuate the psychological and affec¬
tive aspects of their relationships. Only a minori¬
ty of men, however, favour this redefinition of
the father's role, which does not necessarily in¬
clude an explicit desire to take a share in
housework. Nevertheless, it forms part of a
movement towards the sharing of parental rights,
privileges and duties upon which the survival of
the Quebec family ultimately depends.
In Quebec over the past twenty years, as
elsewhere in North America, the death of the
traditional family has more than once been an¬
nounced. The media increasingly extoll the two-
parent, two-salary family as the height of social
success, whether bound together by marriage or
not, in which more flexible hierarchical relation¬
ships between its members replace, at least out¬
wardly, the traditional order based on patriarchal
authority and the submission of wife and
children. In this egalitarian-type family, the hus¬
band would, ideally, share in the parental respon¬
sibilities, duties and privileges, participating more
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
actively than formerly both in household tasks
and in the upbringing of the two children who
are seen as the couple's joint project.
The revival of the family
Thus, transcending structural change, the tradi¬
tional family continues to be seen as the setting
above all others in which the affectivity of the
individual, whether child or adult, can be given
expression. Similarly, the great majority of
Quebec women still share the desire to have
children. In a recent survey, 93 per cent of
women between the ages of eighteen and forty-
nine said that they wanted to have at least one
child.
This emotional attachment to the family unit
and to children, coupled with the emergence of
new family structures based on new ways of
managing conjugal and parental relationships,
reflects a renewed appreciation of privacy and of
the home as the place of understanding, loving
relationships and comfort that is to be found to¬
day throughout North American society. In
short, while free unions, reconstituted families,
divorce, a drop in the birth rate and gainful
employment for women provide the backdrop
to the family scene in Quebec today, paradox
al competitor in a snow
sculpture contest held
during the Quebec city
carnival puts the finishing
touches to a carving of a
family on a sledge.
ically, the family and its values are more than ever
perceived and sought after as a shield against the
cold loneliness and violence of the outside world.
After the final break with the traditional
patriarchal family with its rigid, inegalitarian
structure, we must now look towards the family
of the year 2000. We must abolish sex-based divi¬
sion of labour both in the public and in the
domestic arena, revitalize social services con¬
cerned with marriage partnerships and family
support, and encourage the state and the various
agents of society to find new solutions to the
problems facing women and their families. It is
only on this basis that we can resolve what some
have described as "the major crisis facing the
family in Quebec", but which we prefer to see
as the crisis of a model of family relationships
which today is outmoded.
4.
r
& it
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
'OUR HOME IS YOUR HOME'
A visit to an
A French journalist specializing in family questions
describes a recent visit to Soviet Uzbekistan.
M,
46
LY husband and I stayed in an Uzbek household
comprising a couple, both university teachers, whose
second daughter lived with them. Their elder daughter
was already married. Despite its European
characteristics, this family of intellectuals is firmly at¬
tached to a traditional way of life that reveals the vigour
of an ancient culture and religion.
Like all visitors, we had to leave our shoes in the
hallway. The apartment was a blend of east and west.
Modern furniture was set among an array of rugs and
cushions.
Uzbek hospitality is legendary. Throughout our
stay, we were showered with kindness and copiously
fed. "Our home is your home," the mistress of the
house said time and again, her hand on her heart as
a sign of respect.
We were offered a wide range of national dishes,
including the celebrated plov, a rice and mutton dish
traditionally eaten with the fingers from a vast earthen¬
ware platter (see Unesco Courier, December 1984). We
were never given pork, which is prohibited among
Muslims.
Most of the time it was the daughter of the house,
Rano ("Rose-Red"), who served the meals, without sit¬
ting down herself. She followed a particularly graceful
ritual when serving the green tea, slowly pouring a little
of the hot liquid into red and gold porcelain goblets
which she offered to us, held in the tips of her fingers
without touching the rim, palm upwards.
Her mother, Ferouza ("Turquoise"), confided to
me how important it was that her daughter should have
good manners and be a skilled housekeeper, for these
are the qualities which will be most appreciated by her
future in-laws.
Rano was twenty years old. Matchmakers had
already been calling on her parents for two years, but
the latter were in no great hurry to give her hand in
marriage, partly because they wanted her to finish her
economics studies at university, and partly because
weddings are very expensive and it was not long since
Rano's elder sister had been married. "With us," they
explained, "it is usual to have a large number of guests
at the weddingone or two hundred, sometimes even
three hundred, and the celebrations go on for at least
three days. People often run up huge debts."
The bride's dowry also had to be constituted.
Rano's parents, who enjoy a comfortable standard of
living, must provide the furnishings for two rooms:
all the carpeting, bedding and crockery for a bedroom
and a dining room. Their daughter's trousseau would
include around forty outfits and a dozen pairs of shoes.
Ferouza was extremely concerned about this. "We
can't do less for the younger one than we did for her
sister," she said with a sigh, "otherwise we shall be
criticized."
Custom dictates that a young couple should go to
live with the husband's family. The in-laws must
therefore provide their son with two rooms, even if
this entails moving house.
Lengthy preparations are made before an Uzbek
marriage is celebrated. In Tashkent, the capital of the
Uzbek Soviet Socialist Republic, marriages are normal¬
ly contracted only between natives of the city. "There's
no chance," explained Ferouza, "of a city girl marry¬
ing a provincial, and a Muslim girl wouldn't usually
marry a non-Muslim."
When a young man has reached marriageable age,
his mother looks for a wife for him. Generally accom¬
panied by one of her female relatives, she pays an in¬
itial visit to the family of a suitable girl. The two
women note the conditions in which the potential in¬
laws live and ask about future prospects. If this
preliminary meeting is considered satisfactory, the
women will come back again and the two families will
get to know one another better. Each side does some
detective work. If the two families eventually reach
agreement, an informal rendezvous is arranged between
the two mothers, accompanied by the young people.
The meeting occurs as if by chancewhen leaving
work, for example.
"I don't want to marry Rano off against her will,"
Ferouza explained. "Nadir, my husband, had to resort
to trickery in order to marry me. After turning down
several girls which his mother had picked out for him,
he finally pretended to give in to her reluctantly when
she suggested my name. In fact he had already chosen
me. But she was convinced that she had chosen her
son's wife herself."
Ferouza abides by family traditions but finds them
onerous. "There are a lot of family reunions and
festivities," she said, "and I always have to serve a dish
that I've made myself, which means that I have to stay
up late to prepare my lectures. On top of the prepara¬
tions for Rano's wedding, I also have to prepare for
my grandsons' circumcision feast, which is coming up
soon. New clothes will have to be bought for them
and there'll be lots of guestsit will be very expen¬
sive. After Rano is married, there will be more children,
more family festivities and more expense. I'm a bit tired
of it," she admitted.
Her husband seemed more relaxed. A high-spirited
man, he organized entertainment for us. It will be a
long time before I forget a trip we made into the coun¬
tryside, with the beautiful mountain scenery, the warm
welcome we received everywhere, the eastern-style
dances, open-air barbecues and traditional pastries. All
Nadir's relatives would have been asked to contribute.
"We'll do anything he asks of us," said his brother-in-
law Farkhad, who is slightly younger than Nadir.
"He's the head of the family because he's the oldest."
Much respect is shown to the elders. To put elderly
relatives in an old people's home would be unthinkable.
They are looked after, we were told, by the family.
Respect for older people and the extent of Uzbek
hospitality were the things that most impressed us dur¬
ing our stay. After wishing us a safe journey home,
Ferouza, Nadir and Rano, hands on their hearts, said:
"Come back. Our home will always be yours..."
NLarriage of an Uzbek
couple at the madrasah of
Shirdar, Samarkand.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Uzbek family BY CLAIRE FOURNIER
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND SOCIETY
Africa's 'wonder weed'
M,
48
I ILLIONS of people in the developing
world may be spared the debilitating and
sometimes fatal effects of schistosomiasis,
a parasitic infection also known as bilhar-
zia, if the results of a discovery made by
an Ethiopian scientist twenty-five years
ago are fully exploited.
It was in 1 964 that a young Ethiopian
parasitologist, Aklilu Lemma, discovered
that the berries of a bush commonly found
in areas of Ethiopia where schistosomiasis
is endemic were a safe and effective
molluscicide against snails which carry the
bilharzia parasite.
Sent to Adwa in northern Ethiopia
after a recent outbreak of bilharzia, Dr.
Lemma discovered that life for the people
of Adwa revolved around the Guagua and
Asem rivers. He began to examine the
snail population along the banks of the
rivers. It was known that the snails were
hosts to the parasite, and the objective
was to find a way of interrupting the
breeding cycle during their earliest
development.
"Over a period of time," says Dr. Lem¬
ma, "I began to notice a pattern of dead
snails in the areas downstream from
where the women washed their clothes.
I saw this repeatedly and wondered if
there was some connection."
Dr. Lemma decided to gather some
live snails in a small bucket and take them
to where the women were washing. "I
asked a woman to put a little of her suds
in the bucket, and when she did, the snails
fizzed and died, shrinking in their shells."
The suds which killed the snails were
produced by berries from the wild endod
plant (Phytolacca dodecandra), which had
been known to Ethiopian women for cen¬
turies as the "soapberry bush". The
women had collected the unripened ber¬
ries and dried them in the sun. On
washing days they would grind a handful
of berries in a basin, and mix in a little
water to produce a foaming lather. This
traditional detergent was credited with the
stark whiteness and softness of their
dresses.
The young scientist reaffirmed the ef¬
fects of the suds on snails in the
laboratory, and in doing so began a strug¬
gle for scientific recognition of the plant
and its low-cost molluscicidal properties
which continues today.
Dr. Lemma's discovery led to a five-
year survey which measured the incidence
of bilharzia in each household in Adwa
Abridged from ATAS News, a
publication prepared by the Centre
for Science and Technology for
Development of the United Nations
Secretariat.
'£&.
V
a^F A 1 «
B
before and after the introduction of scien¬
tifically measured berry extract to the
rivers.
"Before the introduction of endod we
found that about 50 per cent of the
children between the ages of one and five
years were infected by bilharzia," says Dr.
Lemma. "Five years later that figure had
been reduced to about 8 per cent."
Further research showed that the
natural berry product was biodegradable,
breaking down into inert organic materials
similar to food spices within 48 hours.
The cost of producing an endod berry
extract$10 to $25 per person per year
in infested areasis a key factor in the en¬
dod equation. One of the most effective
commercial molluscicides on the market
is Bayluscide, which also kills the snail host,
but which has remained prohibitively ex¬
pensive (about $25,000 a ton) to poor
communities which need it most.
A discovery of such potential in a
western country would have excited ma¬
jor financial support, but with a few
notable exceptions in the US, Canada and
Europe, endod has not generated much
enthusiasm.
"It has been very difficult to overcome
the biases," says Dr. Lemma. "One of the
problems is that it's too simple, too cheap.
There are already chemicals in the
marketplace and people don't want to in¬
vest in something which is unlikely to
make a lot of money. We have been
unable to attract the kind of resources
necessary to develop a product quickly
which has all the seals of approval."
The constraints appear to be easing,
however. A high-yielding endod plant has
been developed which is resistant to insect
pests, has high potency berries, and grows
to a size suitable for large-scale cultivation.
Scientists who have worked on the
development of the new "Type 44" plant
believe it has considerable economic
potential for farmers in poor highland
areas of the developing world where it
could be intercropped with maize and
potato and sold to the lowland com¬
munities where bilharzia is endemic.
Cultivars of 'Type 44" have been
transplanted internationally and are doing
well in Kenya, Tanzania, Uganda, Zim¬
babwe, Zambia, Swaziland and Brazil.
The main obstacle to this low-cost ap¬
proach to schistosomiasis control is the
passage of endod through various inter¬
national scientific protocols which would
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
endorse it as a safe product, and give the
green light to greater financial support
from the international community.
Professor John D.H. Lambert of the
Department of Biology at Carleton Univer¬
sity in Ottawa, Canada, is confident that
endod will ultimately pass muster : "What
one has to realize with this product," he
says, "is that it has been safely used by
people ¡n Ethiopia for centuries. We are
dealing with a product which people have
used to wash themselves and their
clothing, and if there is a problem it should
have manifested itself in some way by
now. The whole idea now is to extract the
product from the berries on a large scale
using the same low-cost water extraction
they use for traditional soap making."
An endod Scientific Advisory Group
formed by the International Development
Research Centre of Canada (IDRC) has met
under the chairmanship of the World
Health Organization's Pesticides Section
and laid down procedures for repeating
some of the laboratory work done in
Ethiopia in the 1 960s and early 1 970s. The
IDRC will be covering much old ground,
but the outcome will be recommendations
from internationally recognized
laboratories under "Good Laboratory Prac¬
tices" (GLP) standards. The Group has also
identified the necessary toxological tests
to be done in tandem with agronomic
studies, prior to large-scale field evalua¬
tions in a number of countries, including
Ethiopia, Zambia, Swaziland and
Zimbabwe.
The final irony emerging from the en¬
dod story is that the industrialized nations
which ignored it for so long may ultimately
be among the principal beneficiaries. Dr.
Robert M. Parkhurst, senior organic
chemist at Stanford Research Institute in
California, says that most of the chemistry
to identify the active principles in the en¬
dod berry has been done at Stanford, and
that the berry is just the tip of the iceberg
as far as the plant is concerned.
Parkhurst has labelled endod the
"wonder weed of Africa". "Every time we
examine this plant we find a new poten¬
tial for it," he says. In addition to the key
molluscicidal saponins, which Stanford has
named "Lemmatoxins" after the
discoverer, the Institute has identified a
score of other commercial possibilities
ranging from liver fluke control for
livestock and larvocides against malarial
mosquitoes, to the development of
natural skin cosmetics. B
IN BRIEF
Cancer drug
triggered by light
The use of a light-activated drug known
to the ancient Egyptians has been pro¬
posed for the treatment of certain cancers.
Dr. Richard L. Edelson, writing in Scientific
American, describes how cancerous cells
removed from a patient's body are dam¬
aged by the drug, known as 8-MOP,
which is activated by ultraviolet radiation.
When the cells are returned to the body,
they trigger off an immunological attack
on the remaining cancerous cells.
Nuclear electricity
shows increase
Installed capacity for generating electrici¬
ty with nuclear power increased by about
8% worldwide in 1987, reports the Inter¬
national Atomic Energy Agency. During
the year 22 new reactors came on line in
9 countries. This brought the world's total
to 41 7 operating nuclear power plants, ac¬
counting for more than 16% of the
world's total electrical power generation.
Young flat-earthers
Most under-1 0-year-olds assume the Earth
is flat, according to a survey carried out
for the U.S. National Science Teachers
Association. The survey, carried out in 65
schools in the U.S. and Israel, showed that
most children are taught that the Earth is
round when they are about 10 years old,
and until then they rely on their own
perceptions.
Prehistoric foundling
Researchers A. Tikhonov (below left) and
V. Simonov of Leningrad's Zoology In¬
stitute measure the body of a baby mam¬
moth found by the crew of the Soviet ship
Porog in the soil of the Arctic's Yamal
peninsula. The ancient animal's frozen car¬
cass, which has survived largely intact,
aroused interest in many sciences.
Microbiologists in particular are trying to
detect microbes and viruses which may
have been conserved in the extreme cold.
Cool cats
Scientists have drawn on principles of
physics, anatomy and evolution to explain
why cats survive falls that would kill peo¬
ple. Of 132 cats treated in New York's
animal medical centre for injuries compati¬
ble with falling from a great height, 90%
survived. Because cats have a larger sur¬
face area in relation to volume than
humans their maximum rate of descent is
lower and impact stresses are much less.
But why should cats suffer less severe in¬
juries after a fall than dogs of the same
size? According to Prof. Jared Diamond of
the University of California, cats have in¬
herited certain safety mechanisms from
their tree-living ancestors. When a cat falls,
its muscles relax so that its legs splay out
horizontally. It descends parachute-fashion
and lands on all fours, in a way that
minimizes the impact on any one part of
its body.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco
^-*courier
Mí
Published monthly in 34 languages and ¡n braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Borvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (París)
50
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkm, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Baüey (Tel.: 45 68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta, Majda Dalal
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel :45.68 45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
»NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Sri Ram (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kossler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bengali: Ahmed Hedayet (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45 64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68.45.66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (Tel.: 45.68.45.80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26.51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed anides reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinons of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply officia endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de fontenoy, 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100, U S A , (3) NCR Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, inc , in West 40th Street, New York, U S.A.; (4) Bell and
Howell Co . Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Pnnted m France) DEPOT LEGAL CI JUILLET 1989
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure impression:
Maury Imprimeur SA, 2.1 route d'Etampes.
45330 Malesherbes
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. 'Ndermarrja e perpjes se libnt'. Tirana ARGENTINA. Librena el
Correo de la Unesco - EDILYR, SRL, Tucumán 1685. 1050 Buenos Aires.
AUSTRALIA. Books only:: Educational Supplies Pty Ltd., P.O. Box 33,
Brookvale 2100. NSW: Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O.
Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agents: United Nations Association o(
Australia. Victorian Division. 328 Flinders Street. Melbourne 3000 Hunter
Publicatipns. 58a Gipps St.. Collmgwood. Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional. Arab Regional Office. P O. Box 726. Bahrain; The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co.. Al Mutanabi St.. PO Box 156. Manama BANGLADESH
Kanm International, GPO Box No: 2141. 64/1 Manipun Para, Tetgaort.
Farmgate. Dhaka. BARBADOS. University of (he West Indies Bookshop.
Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64. Bridgetown. BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy, 202
Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundaçào Getúlio Vargas. Serviço del Publicaçoes,
caixa postal 9.042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188. Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000;
Books only: Imagem Latinoamericana, Av. Paulista 750. 1 andar, caixa postal
30455, Sao Paulo CEP 01051. BULGARIA. Hemus, Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6, Sofia. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9). 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd.. 1294
Algoma Road, Ottawa. Ontario Kl B 3W8. (Stores: 61 Sparks Street. Ottawa,
21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. Sales office: 7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Sie. 305. Si.
Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre. PO Box
123. Limbe. Commission Nationale. BP 1600. Yaounde. CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria S A., Departamento de Importaciones. M. Luisa Santander
0447. casilla 10220, Santiago; Editorial 'Andrés Bello', Av; R. Lyon 946,
Casillo 4256. Santiago de Chile; Dipubiic. Antonio Varas 671 . 2o piso, casilla
14364. Correo 21, Santiago. CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Expon Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura), Carrera 3A, n° 18 / 24, Bogota; Books only: Librería
Buchholz Galena, Calle 59. No; 13-13. Bogota. CYPRUS. 'MAM', Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avene. PO Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L,
Spaiena 51-H3 02. Prague 1; ForSlovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Publishers.
Hurbanovo nam. 6.893 31 Bratislava: PNS-UED, Jindnsska 14. praha 1:
Slovart. Gortwaldovo Nam 6, 805 32 Bratislava. DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation. PO Box 4227. Aden. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG, Tidsskriftservice, 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco, Avenida Bolivar. No; 402, esq
Hermanos Oeligne, Santo Domingo. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre, No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. ETHIOPIA, Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco, PO Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, P. O- Box 128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen
Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2 01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans Periodicals only: Unesco CPD /
V-1 . rue MiolhS. 7501 5 Pans. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. BuChex-
port. Postfach 140. Leninstrasse 16, 7010. Leipzig. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum. Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb. Basaltstrasse 57. 05300 Bonn 3; UNO-Verlag. Simrockstrasse 23.
D-5300 Bonn 1; S. Karger GmbH, Verlag Angerholsirasse 9, Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München. For scientific maps only:Geo Center. Postfach
800830. 7000 Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Soofrs only: Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd.. PO Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., PO 7869, Accra;
The University Bookshop of Ghana. Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon. PO Box 1 , Legon. Periodicals only:
Fides Entreprises. P.O. Box 14129. Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore, 4 Nikis
Street. Athens: John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O.
Box 10073, 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission lor unesco, 3
Akadimias Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15 Lock
Road, Kowloon: Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., Tokwawan. Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services, Publication Section. Hong Kong;
Periodicals only: Beaconsf leid House 6th floor, Queen's Road Central, Victor¬
ia. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.OB. 149-H-1389, Budapest 62.
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9. Reykiavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038:
17 Chitaranjan Ave.. Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai. Mount Road. Madras 2:
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd.,
Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda. Hyderabad-500001. Sub-agents:
Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 1 7 Park St.. Calcutta 70016; Sandia House,
New Delhi 11 0001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29,
J1. Oto Iskandardinata 111, Jakarta: Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratuiangie 37.
Jakarta Pusat IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco. 1 188 Englab
Ave.. Rostam Give Building, P.O. Box 11365-4498. Teheran 13158.
IRELAND. Periodicals only: The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.. PO Box
43A, Walkmstown, Dublin 1 2; Books only: T DC Publishers. 1 1 North Frederick
Street. Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions, Inc., c/o Steimatzky Ltd..
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv; A B.C. Bookstore Ltd.. P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Rd..
Tel Aviv 6 1 000. ITALY. Licosa (Ubreria Commissionana Sansoni, S p A ), Via
Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552. 50121 Florence; via Bartolmi 29, 201 55
Milan; FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalia. 00100 Rome. JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113. JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency. PO Box 375. Amman. Periodicals only: Jordan
Book Cerjtre Co. Ltd., PO Box 301 , Al Jubeiha, Amman. KENYA. East African
Publishing House. PO 30571. Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd, Quran
House, Mangano Street, PO Box 45245, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission lor Unesco. P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942, Kuwait: Periodicals only: Farafalia Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541 , Kuwait. LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A. Naufal
et Frères, BP 656. Beirut. LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre, PO Mazenod.
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlin and Carey Streets. PO Box
590, Monrovia; Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.. PO Box 286. Monrovia.-
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg; Periodical Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 1022, Luxembourg. MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office. PO Box 30044. Chichin. Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop. Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St.. Valletta. MAURITANIA GRA.LI.-
CO.MA., 1 rue du Souk X, Avenue kennedy, Nouakchott. MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St.. Port-Louis. MEXICO. Libreria El
Correo de la Unesco. Actipán 66, Colonia del Valle, Apartado postal 61 1 64,
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte
Carlo. MORROCCO. Librairie 'Aux belles images'. 282 ave. Mohammed-V,
Rabat; Librairie des écoles, 12 ave. Hassan-It, Casaglanca; Société cherifien-
ne de distribution et de presse, SOCHEPRESS, angle rues de Dinant et St.
Saens, BP 13683, Casablanca 05. MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livro
edo Disco (INLD), avenida 24 de Julho, 1921 r/d1° andar. Maputo. NEPAL.
Sajha Prakashan Polchowk. Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Books only:
Keesing, Boeken B.V., Hogehilweg 13, Postbus 1 118. 1000 BC Amsterdam.
Periodicals: Faxon Europe. P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V., PO Box 200, Willem-
stad. Curaçao, NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box
14277-Kilbirme, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of He: The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 266; The University Bookshop of Nsukka;
The University Bookshop of Lagos: The Ahmadu Bella University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum. P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1;
Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret. Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo
3: Periodicals only: Narvesen A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten. P.O.B. 61 25 Etterstad,
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam.
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for
Book Development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society. P.O. Box
8950, Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional, Apartado
7571. Zona 5. Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store Inc., 701 Rizal
Avenue. Manila POLAND. Orpan-lmport. Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch. Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda Uvraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70. Lisbon. ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export- Import. Piata Soenteii. no. 1, PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan. Olaya Mam Street, Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building. Riyadh. SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd.. Kingsgate
House. PO Box 131. Mahé: National Bookshop. PO Box 48. Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College. Njala University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises. P.O. Box 562.
Kallang Basin Post Office. Singapore 9133. SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. General Establishment for Publishing, Distribution and
Advertising, Souf Al Mahmoudi St.. PO Box 959, Tripoli. SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General, PO Box ùàô, Mogadiscio. SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA. apartado 1223, Casteiló 37. Madrid 1: Ediciones Liber, apartado
17. Magdalena 8, Ondárroa (Vizcaya); Donaire, Ronda de Outeiro. 20.
apartado de correos 341, La Coruña; books only: Librería Castells. Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15, Barcelona 7; Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya.
Palan Moja, Rambla de los Estudios 118. 08 002 Barcelona. SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop. 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata. P.O.B. 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A/ B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel. Regenng-
sgatan 12. Box 16356, S-103 27 Stockholm 16: For the Unesco Courier:
Svenska FN Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; For
periodicals on/y.Wennergren-Williams AB. Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104. 23
Stockholm; Esselte Tidskriftscentralen. Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -101. 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zürich; Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey, Montreux. Neuchâtel and
Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establishment, University of Aleppo.
Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402. Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9.
Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road.
Bangkok: ROEAP, PO Box 1425, Bangkok 10500. TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair. Port-of-
Spam. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklàl Caddesi. No 469, Posta Kutusu
21 9. Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. PO Box 7145. Kampa¬
la. UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. PO Box 1 5408, Al Am,
Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, PO Box 276, London.
SW8 5DT; H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh, Belfast. Manchester,
Birmingham, Bristol; Third World Publications, 151 Stratford Road, Birming¬
ham B11 1RD; for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd.. 122 King's Cross Rd.
London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB,
Periodicals Department, 461 1-F Assembly Drive. Lanham, MD 20706 4391.
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho, S.A., Maldonado 1092. Montevideo. USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva 113095.
YUGOSLAVIA. Miadost. Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba. Zopitar-
jeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 13/ VIII. 11000 Belgrade; penodicals only:
Jugosolvena Kniga. PO Box 36, YU 11001 Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre. Harare.
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 7 1989 OPI 89- 1 -470 A
PHOTO CREDITS
Front cover, pages 3 (right), 35: © FDAC/Conseil Général du Val de Marne, France. Back cover: © Association Culturelle Confluences:
Europe-Asie, Paris. Page 2: © Pestana/Herman Braun-Vega, Paris. Page 3 (left): Celik Erkul © Gamma, Paris. Pages 5, 7: Pelletier © Gamma,
Paris. Page 8: © AIAP/Bibliothèque des Arts, Paris, from Unesco: 40 Artists; 40 Years; 40 Countries. Vages 10, 13: Anatole Zabolotski ©
Molodaya Gvardia publishers, Moscow. Page 11: © Marc Vaux, Paris. Pages 14, 19 (above), 20, 30: © Roger-Viol let, Paris. Page 16: Roland
Michaud © Rapho, Paris. Page 17:© Jean-Loup Charmet, Bibiliothèque des Arts Décoratifs, Paris. Pages 18-19, 38-39: ©Jean-Loup Charmet,
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Page 21: Bruce Dale © National Geographie Society, Washington, D.C. Pages 22-23, 26: © Orchidees/CIRIC,
Paris. Page 23: © Michel Gurfinkel, Paris, Maurice Nicaud collection. Pages 25, 27: © Mark Edwards/Still Pictures, London. Pages 28-29:
S. Franklin © Magnum, Paris. Page 31 (above): Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Paris; (below): E. Schwab © WHO, Geneva. Page 32: © Francisco
Hidalgo, Paris. Pages 36, 37: © Léon Claude Vénézia, Revest des Brousses, France. Page 38: © Mazenod/Citadelle publishers, Paris. Page
40 (above left): Heccor Cattolica/UNFPA; (above right): Sebastiäo Salgado © Magnum, Paris; (below): © M. Figueiredo. Page 42: © The
Museum of Fine Arts, Houston. Page 43: © The Tate Gallery, London. Page 44: Hervé Gloagen © Rapho, Paris. Page 45: Marc Pataut
© Fotogram, Paris. Page 47: © APN, Paris. Page 48 (below): from Histoire de la médecine dans l'Antiquité © Hachette publishers, Paris.
Page 49 (above): UN, New York; (below): © Novosti Press Agency, London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
¡HM
SI5L
INTERNATIONAL
SOCIAL
ß45//. BLACKWELL/
UNESCO
SCIENCE
JOURNAL
Modernity and Identity:
A Symposium
Culture, economy and
development
Basil Blackwell / ITESCO
A quarterly
interdisciplinary journal
which reports on major
current trends in the
social sciences with
contributions from
specialists of
international reputation
Influences of the
French Revolution 119
Muslim societies, Japan,
Latin America
Basil Blackwell / UT3SC0
Recent articles include:
GEORGES BALANDIER:
An anthropology of violence and war
ALAIN TOURAINE:
Modernity and cultural specificities
IMMANUEL WALLERSTEIN:
Should we unthink nineteenth-century social
science?
mERKSBBBSP
§
International Social Science
Journal ¡s published four times a
year, in February, May, August
and November by Basil Blackwell
Ltd, 108 Cowley Road, Oxford
0X4 1JF, UK, or PO Box 1320,
Murray Hill Station, NY 10156,
USA, for the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
mm
TE
shËIP
^HaH
mm
Hi
ffiÊm
isas»
n
ses
eraP
PETER M. ALLEN:
Towards a new science of human systems
«Hg
' in i
5«
m
BT
IHNfl
Attractive, fully-illustrated layout
JEAN-TOUSSAINT DESANTI:
The role of science in culture
arara»
Tablais
WsWÊÊPi
Jffl Wsm
111111111
"
' : -.
Wl
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
