<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="084201eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
a
% .
m 1 14 1 1
mystery tour
.
NOVEMBER 1989
15 French francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send
us photographs to be
considered for publication
in this feature. Your
photo should show a
painting, a sculpture,
piece of architecture or
any other subject which
seems to be an example
of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could
send us pictures of two
works from different
cultural backgrounds in
which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
sM'V.
Buddha Shakyamuni
1987, painting on cotton executed with crushed natural pigments,
by Nathalie Gyatso
The art of thang-ka, a form of Tibetan religious painting or drawing on
woven material, is governed by strict rules. "But," writes the French-
born artist Nathalie Gyatso, "there is room for creativity and invention
in thang-ka art. Here, for example, I wanted to symbolize the calming
effects of the Buddha's appearance by showing aggressive clouds
retreating before the light, and vegetation overgrowing massive,
threatening mountains. While following the same rules, a Tibetan
painter would have made a different iconographical choice, perhaps
associating peaceful motifs with a peaceful deity."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical barriers
to exploration, the barriers of
mutual ignorance between
different peoples and cultures
have in many cases still not
been dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can voyage
to the ends of the earth. But
a different kind of Odyssey
now beckonsan exploration
of the world's many cultural
landscapes, the ways of life of
its different peoples and their
outlook on the world in which
they live.
It is such an Odyssey that the
Unesco Courier now proposes
to you, its readers. Each
month contributors of
different nationalities will
provide from different cultural
and professional standpoints
an authoritative treatment of
a theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes will be
respect for the dignity of man
everywhere.
11
A MATHEMATICAL
MYSTERY TOUR
ANCIENT EGYPT AND MESOPOTAMIA
PRIME NUMBERS
by James Ritter
INDIA
LILAVATI, GRACIOUS LADY OF ARITHMETIC
by Francis Zimmermann 18
CHINA
7T IN THE SKY
by Jean-Claude Martzloff 22
ANCIENT GREECE
THE ODYSSEY OF REASON
by Bernard Vitrac 29
THE ARAB WORLD
WHERE GEOMETRY
AND ALGEBRA INTERSECT
by Roshdi Rashed 37
FROM THE MIDDLE AGES TO THE ENLIGHTENMENT
THE ROOTS
OF MODERN MATHS
by Catherine Goldstein and Jeremy Gray 43
The Editors wish to thank Mr. Tony Levy
for his help in the preparation of this issue.
Interview with
FEDERICO MAYOR
Director-General of Unesco
49
12 PORTRAIT
GABRIELA MISTRAL,
POET
AND HUMANIST
50
SCIENCE
AND SOCIETY
AN ACADEMY OF SCIENCES
FOR THE THIRD WORLD
by Akhtar Mahmud Faruqui
Cover:
The Geometry Lesson (1561),
by the Flemish painter
Nicolas de Neuchâtel.
Back cover:
Computer image generated using
a formula from the new field of
fractal geometry.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
Federico Mayor
Federico Mayor' was elected Director-General of Unesco for a 6-year term in
1987. He had previously served as rector of the University of Granada, president
of the Spanish Society of Biochemistry, founder-director of the Madrid Centre for
Molecular Biology, Spain's Minister of Education and Science, and as a member
of the European Parliament in Strasbourg. On the occasion of the 25th session of
Unesco's General Conference, he sets forth here his reflections on the role of the
United Nations system in the world today.
Although public opinion in most countries may be aware
ofthe existence ofthe United Nations system, it is not always
very sure ofthe system's use in practical terms. Do you really
think that the UN system is indispensable?
The system is even more necessary today than it was in
the past. In 1945 it responded to a bitter, lucid analysis (lu¬
cidity and bitterness often go together) made in the after¬
math of a disaster. Today it responds to an acute awareness
of the increasingly global nature of problems which we can
only face together.
The system has not solved all the problems with which
it has been confronted, far from it. But it has shown itself
to be increasingly irreplaceable as a meeting place, as a forum
of conciliation and reconciliation, as a place where new ap¬
proaches can be sought, and avenues of co-operation care¬
fully explored. It is, fundamentally, the seat of a new identity,
that of the "global village". A pluralistic and multiform
village which regroups, and must protect, all cultural iden¬
tities, the infinite diversity of peoples, and the irreplaceable
originality of each community.
Contrary to what is often thought, the United Nations
system was not constructed ex nihilo, arbitrarily established
in 1945 on the decision of a handful of idealistic visionaries.
It is the prolongation of a long history. It is the outcome
of a historical process that began in the late nineteenth cen¬
tury whereby an increasing number of individuals, currents
and nations have become aware of the need to create com¬
mon structures of consultation and co-operation on an in¬
ternational scale.
This awareness was a response to new realities: people
were starting to realize that the world was one: communi¬
cations were intensifying; commercial, industrial and finan¬
cial interests were no longer confined within national and
even continental frontiers; information was beginning to
cross the oceans on a regular basis. This emergence of a world
system called for the organization of mutual consultation
on a worldwide scale.
So the system was created in response to a need?
The human species is the only one which is endowed with
the distinctive faculty of creativity. There are always some
far-seeing persons who take timely initiatives in response
to new challenges.
The first institutional international structurethe
League of Nationswas created after the First World War.
This terrible convulsion revealed that the world was not only
a market to be shared but a heritage to be protected. Some
statesmen, but also philosophers, scientists and writers,
thought then that it would be useful to have two distinct
organisms, one to settle political differences (the League of
Nations) and the other to promote intellectual and cultural
co-operation (the International Institute of Intellectual Co¬
operation).
Of course, when I speak of heritage I am not only
* Author of many scientific publications, several books of
poems, and an essay entitled Mañana siempre es tarde
(Espasa Calpe publishers, Madrid, 1987).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
t
i
-
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
_
i
aaffLa^
',}
thinking of our physical heritagethe natural, environmental,
artistic and architectural heritagebut also of our common
spiritual and intellectual heritagethe fruits of knowledge,
human rights, the universal values and principles.
But the League of Nations was not strong enough to
resist the hurricane of fascism in the name of all this. The
Second World War was a much more serious warning for
humanity. Not only were the death and destruction it caused
out of all proportion to those of the earlier war; not only
did the scale of the conflict gradually extend to five conti¬
nents; in addition, the explosion of two atomic bombs
showed to everyone that for the first time in history
mankind had endowed itself with the means of self-
annihilation. A third world war could mean the extinction
of the human race.
Until then, all warsall conflictshad had their win¬
ners and losers. Now all sides faced the threat of losing. War
became a nonsensical proposition. Almost imperceptibly the
civilization of war gave way to the civilization of peace, not
through an access of virtue but through fear of the power
now commanded by the technology of destruction. The cul¬
ture of peace was to be born, not of the wisdom of men
but of their infinite distress. It was at this turning point-
to my mind perhaps the most important in human history
that the United Nations system was established.
Much more ambitious than the League of Nations, the
UN set itself the goal of extending the field of co-operation
to all nations and to many fields of intellectual, social, eco¬
nomic and humanitarian activity. The United Nations Or¬
ganization is the political organ of this system, which is
completed by a range of international organizations, agen¬
cies, programmes, funds and commissions: Unesco for edu¬
cation, science and culture, the WHO for health, Unicef for
children, the ILO for problems related to work, the High
Commissioner for aid to refugees, the FAO for food and
agriculture, etc.
Of course, the successes great and small, the spectacu¬
lar and less spectacular achievements, the inadequacies or
the failures, of the organizations of the United Nations sys¬
tem are closely dependent on the state of mind of the com¬
munity of nations and especially on the aptitude of the most
influential states to agree to ensure that a desire for concili¬
ation prevails. If these favourable factors exist, the United
Nations family can fully exploit the dynamics of multilateral
co-operation and promote the elaboration in common of
solutions which cannot be found individually.
This, I think, is the real purpose of the work of the Unit¬
ed Nations. The UN is there to remind us that we belong
to a single species and inhabit a single planet. What would
become of us if we were ever to forget this?
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
You speak of the organizations and agencies belonging to standing. But this certainly does not mean that everything
the United Nations system. Some people may accept the in all cultures is of equal worth, and that it is impossible
needfor institutions to promote international consultation to transcend cultural specificities. There is no naivety in
with a view to co-operation and regulation in politics, Unesco's approach: cultures are not untouchable entities;
health, agriculture orfinancial affairs, but what about cul- they are the product of a history. Each one has its highlights
ture? Is there not a contradiction between the idea of and its dark corners, its grandeur, its impulses towards the
organization-with its rules, programmes and choices-and sublime and its dreams of fraternity, but also its less posi-
the idea ofculture, which is by definition synonymous with tive inclinations. Our role is to appeal to what is best and
creation, that is, with freedom and spontaneity? most fully human in all of them, to what, naturally, produces
Clearly Unesco's mission is not to intervene in the a spirit of peace,
processes of creation but to encourage the conditions in
which cultural activities can develop and bear fruit. But first Given these considerations, how would you define the pur-
of all we must distinguish between some different meanings pose of Unesco's work?
of the word culture which often tend to be confused. - It is to cut across cultural pluralism and give weight to
At first culture was set in opposition to nature, to whatever brings men closer together, whatever is universal
differentiate man the creator from animals which can only in each culture. To do this, it is necessary to begin at the
obey natural laws. The word has also been used to distin- beginning, with the basic idea that each culture, which is
guish between the education of the mind and the produc- often in its turn a melting pot of other cultures, has its own
tion of goods by manual labour. Different definitions of genius, its own trademark in the history of human civiliza-
culture have been formulated, some extensive, some less so. tion, the identity mark whereby it recognizes itself at each
For some, culture only includes the sublime masterpieces moment of its trajectory, and whereby it can also be recog-
of thought and creation; for others, culture englobes nized by the rest of the world,
everything-from the most sophisticated products to beliefs, I am a Catalan; I profoundly love my country and the
customs, ways of living and workingwhich differentiates language in which I have always addressed my parents. This
one people from another. This second meaning was adopt- culture, the fruit of several civilizations, defines our specific
ed by the international community at the intergovernmen- profile. I know that only if I can develop it without hin-
tal Conference on Cultural Policies which was held in Venice drance, can I work for the unity of Spain, for the strength-
in 1970. In 1982 a second Conference, "Mondiacult", which ening of all the other national cultures. In the past, ignorance
was held in Mexico City, ratified this "active" approach, of this fundamental truth has often been at the roots of con¬
tempt for others. There are grounds for thinking that in
This definition has been criticized by some intellectuals on the future mutual consultation will become easier to the ex-
the grounds that it may tend to privilege the most trivial tent that peoples will have learned to know themselves; to
rather than the highest expressions ofthe mind, and to stress understand their motivations, their ways of being and their
the values specific to each people-those which separate respective scales of values; and to discover that over and
them from others-instead ofthe universal values ofTruth, above these specific expressions they share great common
Good, Beautywhich bring men closer together. aspirations and ideals which often coincide on essential
I think this criticism is aimed at the wrong target. It is matters.
based on a misconception of the frame of reference of our This is why Unesco's primary mission in the field of
definition, which is of a practical, operational order. In the culture is naturally, as expressed in its Constitution, "to de-
United Nations system, in which different philosophies velop and to increase the means of communication between
coexist, the bases of agreement are bases of action, of ac- ... peoples ... for the purposes of mutual understanding and
tion which is of course guided by the major principles on a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives",
which the entire system rests. Unesco seeks to promote contact and meetings between
Definitions are points of departure. And in cultural co- artists, craftsmen, intellectuals, painters, educators, architects,
operation, the only possible point of departure is recogni- writers and poets from all regions and all countries, and to
tion of diversity and respect for this diversitywhich is the publicize the discussions and conclusions that emerge from
basic form of respect for the dignity of individuals in differ- these encounters. These people constitute the principal
ent cultures. More specifically I will say that each person wealth of humanity. They can not only enlighten us about
is biologically and socio-culturally unique and that recog- the meaning of the past but also and above all about the
nition of this uniqueness is the sine qua non of mutual under- possible shape of the future. It is in collaboration with
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
non-governmental organizations, associations of profession- to the blossoming of creativity, to the stimulation of learn-
als, artists and creators that Unesco draws up and executes ing, to the broadening of horizons and the mutual enrich-
its cultural programmes. ment of the sources of inspiration available to every artist.
I never tire of saying that the most perfect monument At the same time it fosters a more profound understanding
is the human being; that the most preciousand the most of the universal significance which artists can find in their
threatenedcultural works are the minority languages, the own cultures,
oral traditions, the songs, dances and customs of the many
countries which do not yet participate in the great cultural The relationship between deeper mutual knowledge, in-
concert of the world. I strongly insist on this. Just as the creasing cultural exchanges and the strengthening ofpeace
freedom of artists must be protected, so the survival of the is not obvious to everyone. There is a striking
arts, folklore and popular cultures must be ensured. These number of conflicts between neighbouring peoples which
two imperatives go together. know and communicate with each other. And the two
world wars broke out in Europe, between peoples who
Major Unesco activities such as the rescue ofAbu Simbel shared essential cultural values and benefited from ad-
and Borobudur are well known. Today there is much talk vanced means of communication,
ofan agreement between the different Cambodian parties It is often neighbouring peoples, neighbouring cities,
concerning Unesco's role in the conservation ofAngkor Vat. which find mutual understanding most difficultbecause
Unesco is ready to act as soon as circumstances permit, they confront each other face to face and each is tempted
But its work in the field of culture goes much further than to become immersed in its own traditions and despise those
the rescue of monuments and sites. Unesco administers three of others. Mutual understanding is not automatically
international juridical instruments of major importance: the produced by the political or commercial contacts established
Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the between peoples. These contacts may just as easily lead to
Event of Armed Conflict; the Convention on the Means conflicts as to agreements, depending on whether the reflexes
of Prohibiting and Preventing the Illicit Import, Export and of fear, suspicion, and mutual contempt are fostered, or the
Transfer of Ownership of Cultural Property; and the Con- aptitude, latent in all peoples, to appreciate truth and beauty
vention concerning the Protection of the World Cultural wherever they may be found, to respect the diversity of ideas
and Natural Heritage. and styles, to prefer tolerance and seek conviviality.
Unesco is also concerned with the translation and pub- Take the nazi ideology, for example. How was it en-
lication of literary masterpieces from many countries, with grafted onto German culture? By perverting the noblest
listing, recording and diffusing a unique collection of pieces aspects of that culture, by exalting only the fibres of self-
of music from all over the world.... In many countries to- love. The nazi leaders ignored the humanism of Kant, the
day, books, records and radio and television broadcasts give universalism of Goethe, the generosity of Beethoven. They
increasing exposure to works from other countries, to the systematically proclaimed racial superiority and the morbid
realities and problems of the most diverse regions. Slowly cult of violence, striving to accustom their compatriots to
but surely the universal is entering the daily life of every- the idea that all German history led naturally in that direc-
one. This is one of the important and appreciable aspects tion. Similarly they also had to falsify German history by
of Unesco's work. reducing it to racial confrontation; by keeping alive
memories of past wars and emphasizing everything that
What of cultural creation in the strict sense? denigrated others, to whom they imputed the responsibility
It is and can only be the province of individuals who are for Germany's misfortunes; thereby justifying future
absolutely free to follow their own inspiration, conscience revenge. Today all that seems mad, unreal.
and talent. Nothing should thwart or censor this freedom. In this respect, it is interesting to recall an experiment
On the contrary, everything possible should be done to pro- in which Unesco was directly involved. Just after the war,
tect it and allow it to flourish. I would say that the place one of the tasks our Organization embarked on was the re-
for Unesco's action is before and after this freedom. On the vision of history books through the identification of factual
one hand, it is concerned with denouncing possible viola- errors and biased judgements. Historians from both sides
tions. On the other, with encouraging the optimal condi- in the recent conflict took part in the project. They got down
tions for its creative exercise. to work with plenty of good will. But the experiment was
It is clear that the free circulation of ideas and works a failure. They differed not only on the interpretation of
from all cultures is one of the conditions most favourable the facts, but sometimes on the very existence of certain facts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
What conclusions do you drawfrom this? Had the war left
so deep an imprint on people's minds that it was unrealistic
in its immediate aftermath to hope to achieve an objective
view of things?
I think it was much too soon. But the evil ran far deeper.
As I suggested, the war had ploughed land which had al¬
ready been prepared. It had opened far older wounds, dug
deeper into furrows traced by earlier wars, by manipulating
culture and history. The same thing has happened since in
many other conflicts, even if their protagonists have not
gone so far as to advocate a final solution.
War has deep roots in the past of many peoples. To ex¬
tirpate these roots a constant and courageous effort in the
service of truth is needed. Political leaders are naturally called
on to play a decisive role in this process. But they are not
alone. Philosophers, artists, film makers and journalists all
contribute, whether they know it or not, to the extent that
they arouse interest, respect and admiration for the culture
of others as well as for their own.
Here Unesco can take the lead as an instrument of
mobilization and movement on the world level. Scientists,
and teachers in schools and universities, must also take part
in this effort. The unfettered circulation of scientific and
technological information throughout the world is an ir¬
replaceable vehicle of intellectual complicity and practical
mutual assistance between researchers of all regions. The ex¬
change of experience between educators from all over the
world is also gradually spreading the conviction that each
one of us is the repository of a precious portion of truth....
And that no one, absolutely no one, possesses the whole
truth. It is on this difficult borderline between doubts and
certainties, between self-respect and respect for others, that
we must stand if we are to serve freedom and promote a
permanent creative tension.
On the eve of this new phase in world history which
is opening beneath the emblem of a culture of peace, edu¬
cation and access to knowledge must become the common
destiny of all without exceptionno longer the privilege of
certain persons in certain countries. This is our dream. The
dream of a new page to be written in a new language formed
day after day by free citizens expressing their thoughts and
creativity without constraint. A language that reflects an
authentically peaceful state of mind; a language shorn of all
exclusivity and segregation. A language which may be at last,
uniquely, a vehicle for culture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
E T 0 R I A L
M
.ATHEMATICS is one of the most abstract forms of intellectual
activity. And yet we use mathematical skills not only when engaging
in speculative thought but when trying to solve many practical problems
of our daily lives. The development of these skills in early times was
closely connected with that of writing. In a word, mathematics forms
part of our cultural background and history.
Many of us remember the concentration and application that were
necessary when we made our first steps in the world of maths. The same
tenacious application, allied to a passion for the subject, is characteristic
of advanced students and professional mathematicians.
This issue offers readerseven those for whom the laws of arithmetic
have always been a closed booka guided tour of some of the highways
and byways of mathematics at different times and places in world history.
The assignment was a challenging one for our specialist contributors who
were asked to give a succinct treatment of their subject in straightforward,
non-technical terms. Wherever possible they have tried to put the history
of mathematics in its social, cultural and even linguistic context.
Union of the 3s in the
numerical cube,
by the Mexican artist
Juan-Luis Diaz.
Is there a common denominator, a single thread of reasoning which runs
through all mathematical operations? There are many indications in these
pages that this has often been the case. As the Greek philosopher Proclus
remarked fifteen hundred years ago, mathematical reasoning is a
demonstration of the unity that lies within multiplicity, the indivisible
within the divided, and the infinite within the finite.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Prime
numbers
ANCIENT EGYPT
AND MESOPOTAMIA
BYJAMES RITTER
M,
12
LaTHEMATICS and writing have a close, sym¬
biotic relationship. Indeed, recent archaeological
discoveries have shown that it was the need tó
measure, divide and distribute the material wealth
of societies that gave birth to the first writing
systems.
For a society to develop a mathematics that
goes beyond simple counting, a material support
of some kind is essential. Without writing, the
limitations of human memory are such that only
a certain degree of numerical sophistication can
be achieved.
By allowing us to follow the development of
two writing systems, one in southern Mesopota¬
mia towards the middle of the fourth millenni¬
um BC, and the other in the area around Susa
in Iran, slightly later, archaeological discoveries
in the last few decades have shown that the in¬
verse is equally true. For a society to develop
writing, material needs and, in particular, the
need for record-keeping, are central.
In these societies the material support was
clay, which is virtually indestructible, and the first
documents are accounts. Cuneiform (wedge-
shaped) Mesopotamian writing in. particular
was to know great success over the succeeding
3,000 years. Used to write not only the original
Sumerian and Akkadian, but also Hittite, Ela-
mite, Hurrian and many other languages of the
ancient Near East, it died out only at the begin¬
ning of our era.
Meanwhile, an independent civilization de¬
veloped rapidly in Egypt towards the end of the
fourth millennium. Here the situation concern¬
ing writing is less clear. First of all, the material
support, for other than monumental inscriptions,
was principally papyrus, the reed-like plant grow¬
ing along the Nile and in the Delta, and, to a less¬
er extent, other perishable materials. Egypt has
thus yielded fewer documents than Mesopotamia
by a factor of thousands.
Number systems
The third millennium marks, for both the
Mesopotamian and the Egyptian civilizations, the
gradual emergence of an abstract concept of num¬
ber. Originally each number is attached to a given
system of units. The "four" of "four sheep" and
"four measures of grain" are not, for example,
written with the same symbol.
Above, part of a rod used
in ancient Egypt to measure the cubit, a unit
of length equivalent to 525 mm.
JKight, air view of the site of Ur (Iraq),
dominated by the ziggurat (top).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
:tW:
O*
*%
-a /->:
>
"1
v
r t
ft //**#
C i
-.^;
m
m*.*
^f
.
,>4( / //y
as«
V
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
iL
\ N \ *V V
Equally, the different systems of units are not
connected among themselves. Measures of area,
for instance, have no simple relationship to meas¬
ures of length since the connection between the
twothat area could be calculated from the
product of a length and a widthwas not yet
operational.
But the very practice of writing things down,
yielding permanent records of measures, opens
up the possibility of observing regularities and
patterns. This possibility was taken advantage of
in these two societies over a period of about 1,000
years so that by the end of the third millennium
Egyptian and Sumerian scribes had learned how
to calculate areas and volumes from lengths, how
to divide rations among workers, how to calcu¬
late the time necessary for a given job of work
from volumes, numbers of men, and work rates.
Next our evidence shows how a new level of ab¬
straction was reached in which the concept of
number became more and more detached from
its metrological context.
By the beginning of the second millennium
both civilizations had succeeded in developing
equally abstract systems of numeration, though
they had chosen different paths to represent their
numbers. The Egyptians, like the vast majority
of modern societies, had a written number sys¬
tem based on ten; that is, one counts up to nine
of each unit before moving up to the next higher
unitafter nine "ones" comes a "ten", after nine
"tens" comes a "hundred", etc. But, unlike
JtSelow, two scribes are
shown recording an
Assyrian king's spoils of
war in this drawing of a
lost nco-Assyrian wall
painting.
modern systems, their writing of numbers is "ad¬
ditive", that is there are separate signs for units,
tens, and hundreds, and these are repeated as
necessary.
The Mesopotamians used a base of sixty for
their mathematical calculations, and they deve¬
loped the first known system of position. The
signs for numbers repeat after fifty-nine, the ac¬
tual value being determined by the position of
the digit in the number as a whole.
A scribe's training
Learning how to manipulate such number sys¬
tems requires a specialized training and the
creation of schools can be traced back to the same
time as the invention of writing. Furthermore we
know that the learning of arithmetic began ear¬
ly in the schoolchild's career, along with reading
and writing, and that mathematics, then as now,
was considered one of the "hardest" subjects.
Around 2000 BC, Shulgi, one of the kings of
the Ur III empire in Mesopotamia, was the sub¬
ject of a literary hymn which became a model
text used as a school exercise during the first half
of the second millennium. In this document he
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
4 ^wsxsyvy
LA
V ' - *î
V.
X't «^
> *
\
boasts of his academic achievements and proud¬
ly states: "I am perfectly able to subtract and add,
[clever in] counting and accounting."
Over a thousand years later the Assyrian king
Assurbanipal was to repeat much the same thing
in one of his hymns: "I can find the difficult
reciprocals and products which are not in the
tables."
What would be the history of a young scribe
destined to become a "mathematician" in ancient
Egypt or Mesopotamia? He (and it is almost cer¬
tain that it would be a boy; girls, while not for¬
bidden a scribal formation, are almost entirely
absent from the records) would of course first go
to school. The sons of the rich and powerful
rubbed shoulders with less fortunate young peo¬
ple, who found in education one of the rare
means of social ascension.
What would the scribe learn during his
schooling, which lasted at least ten years? We pos¬
sess, from both civilizations, examples of school
exercises including mathematical texts, and can
catch a glimpse of student life through the so-
called "scribal disputes". An example from
Mesopotamia has one scribe boasting to another
of his achievements:
"I want to write tablets:
tables [of measures] from 1 gur of barley to
600 gur;
tables [of weights] from 1 shekel to 20 minas
of silver,
with the contracts of marriage that may be
brought me,
the commercial contracts...
the sale of houses, fields, slaves,
pledges in silver, contracts for the rental of
fields,
contracts for raising palm trees...
even the tablets of adoption; I know how to
write all that."
In this typical text from Egypt one scribe
taunts another as follows:
"You come here and fill me up with your
office. I will show up your boastful behaviour
when a mission is given to you. I will show up
your arrogance when you say: 'I am the scribe,
commander of the work gang.' ...
"A ramp, 730 cubits [long] and 55 cubits
wide, must be built, with 120 compartments filled
with reeds and beams; with a height of 60 cubits
at its peak, 30 cubits in the middle; with a slope
of 15 cubits; with a base of 5 cubits. The
jKelief above, from the
tomb ofAkhethotep (5th
dynasty of the Old
Kingdom, 2450-2290 BC)
shows Egyptian scribes
drawing up the accounts of
a funeral precinct.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Early Egyptian
and Babylonian numerals
These two groups of symbols show how scribes of
ancient Egypt and Babylon would have written
1989 using their respective number systems.
Egypt
? f f
f ? ?
nnnn
nnnn
1 1 1
1000 900 80
The Egyptian numeral system, here shown in
hieroglyphic writing, was based on 10. We see one
sign for thousands, nine signs for hundreds, eight
signs for tens, and nine signs for ones.
Babylon
<í YYY
33 9
The Babylonian numeral system was based on 60.
Using base 60, one thousand nine hundred and
eighty-nine would be written as thirty-three sixties
and nine ones. The position of the nine to the right
indicates that it constitutes the ones, while the 33,
one place over to the left, represents the sixties.
16
JAMES RITTER,
of the United States, teaches
mathematics and the history
of science at the University
of Paris-VIII. His main
research interests are in the
theory of relativity and its
history, and in the uses of
reasoning in ancient Egypt
and Mesopotamia. He has
contributed to a collective
work, Elements d'histoire des
sciences (Bordas publishers,
Paris, 1989), prepared
under the direction of
Michel Serres.
quantity of bricks is demanded of the troop
commander.
"The scribes are all assembled but no one
knows how to do it. They put their faith in you
and say: 'You are a clever scribe, my friend!
Decide quickly for us, for your name is famous.'
... Let it not be said: 'There is something he does
not know.' Give us its quantity in bricks. Behold,
its measurements are before you; each of its com¬
partments is 30 cubits [long] and 7 cubits [wide.]"
But these are literary and not real mathemat¬
ical texts. In fact, we possess some mathematical
school texts from each civilization, almost all of
them from two distinct periods: the first half of
the second millennium and the period of Greek
and Roman domination at the end of the first
millennium. They are of two kinds, table texts
and problem texts.
A typical example of a table text is a square
root table from early second millennium Babylo¬
nia. The systematic and organized writing of a
table shows the high degree of abstraction already
attained. What does the scribe do if he needs a
square root? If it is not on the table, it can easily
be calculated from the surrounding values that
do appear. This procedure was standard in almost
all cultures including Western ones until a quite
recent date, and this is how the Babylonians and
the Egyptians used their tables of multiplication,
square roots, and sums of fractions. This is also
the way in which they used the problem texts.
A typical example, from an Egyptian papyrus of
the middle of the second millennium, begins with
a statement of the problem to be resolved:
"A pyramid. Its side is 140 [cubits] and its
slope is 5 palms 1 finger [per cubit]. What is
its height?"
Here the data are presented in the form of
concrete numbers rather than abstract variables,
followed by a step-by-step solution with the an¬
swer at the end. Each step makes use of either
the result of a preceding step or of one of the data
given at the beginning of the problem.
No argument is given to justify the procedure
nor is any explanation offered for its form. But
even with the numerical values included, the na¬
ture of this form is quite clear. Thus the student
would be able to solve any other problem of the
same type. Moreover these problems are often
grouped in such a way that the techniques learned
can be immediately applied in other cases. The
above problem, for example, follows a problem
concerned with the determination of the slope
of a pyramid given its length and height, and is
followed in its turn by a problem involving the
calculation of the slope of a cone.
However, not all mathematical problems
were as practically oriented as this one. The main
purpose of mathematical school exercises was to
give the student scribe practice in the mathemat¬
ical techniques used in solving problems. Tech¬
nical drill, not direct application, was the main
point. For this reason many of the apparently
"practical" problems in these texts are far re¬
moved from real life: a Babylonian tablet pro¬
poses a problem in which a broken measuring rod
is used to measure a field; an Egyptian document
asks a scribe to calculate the original size of a herd
of cattle based on the number of cows used to
pay a cowherd's taxes...
The pedagogical purpose of all this is clear.
Moreover, the structure of the problem and
table texts permits an alternative approach to
abstraction and generalization in mathematics.
Rather than take the path of increasing symboli-
zation marked by a hierarchy of "levels of gener¬
ality", the Egyptian and Babylonian approach is
to create a network of typical examples in which
a new problem can be relatedby a form of
interpolationto those already known.
Exactly the same approach can be seen at
work in other areas of ancient thought such as
medicine, divination and astrology. All these sub¬
jects were treated by the Egyptians and Mesopota-
mians as constituting a special domain of
"rational practice".
No word for 'mathematician'
Ample documentary sourcesaccounting texts,
lists of professions, references in literary and
historical texts, even painting and sculpture-
enable us to follow the professional life of the
aspiring scribe once his education is complete. We
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
-4rr- r - 'J' !/
-All; . «43
: -M
'
1
IA
i '
1
<Wl A-
^ J ÏU
l '..I..
i
1
'
M
=J
i ¿e Rhind Mathematical
Papyrus, a scroll copied
around 1650 BC from an
earlier work, is the source
of much information about
ancient Egyptian
mathematics. Detail, above,
shows part of the table for
doubling odd fractions.
Left, fragments of a
Mesopotamian tablet from
the beginning of the 2nd
millennium BC.
will look in vain, though, for any mention of a
"mathematician" in the modern sense of a per¬
son working within a recognized community of
researchers on the properties of number and
geometric figure. No word for "mathematician"
exists in any of the ancient languages of Egypt
and Mesopotamia.
There were two paths that a young scribe
could follow. A few would become teachers of
mathematics themselves, perhaps exploring fur¬
ther problems that could be presented to a new
generation of schoolboys. In the course of time
this did lead to a deepening and broadening of
the mathematical techniques available to the two
societies.
The graduate could also become an
accountanta calculator of work, rations, land
and grain. Scribes are omnipresent and their in¬
dustrious labourings are carefully depicted on
Egyptian wall frescos and Assyrian palace reliefs,
always hard at work on the business of their
master, who might be either the state or a pri¬
vate landowner. They seem to have held
privileged though subservient positions. Like
their schoolteaching colleagues, they were not the
movers of ancient society but they served those
who wereand well enough to be immortalized
on their patrons' walls as the visible symbols of
that concentration of power and wealth they
laboured so hard to calculate. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
INDIA Lilavati, gracious
lady of arithmetic
BY FRANCIS ZIMMERMANN
Detail of a manuscript copy
(date unknown) of a Sanskrit
text composed in 750 AD
and illustrated with
geometric figures.
Opposite page, sundial at
the open-air observatory at
Jaipur (India), built in 1728.
URING the eighth century AD, Arab
scholars working in India on Sanskrit mathemat¬
ical texts made two major discoveries which they
developed and later transmitted to the Western
world: the place-value notation of figures using
the decimal system coupled with the "zero" con¬
cept, and a trigonometry which incorporated the
use of sines.
It was not merely by chance that these major
advances in the fields of writing, calculation and
18
A simple problem taken from
the twelfth-century Indian
mathematician Bhaskara's Lilavati
('Arithmetic')
qsaf>i,jf<e$WT.^îiti'T>U5'î5r: fotfpá «m-
êrmja iwm wifa À ^isfe^^f ^ n
Example of the reduction of fractions
to a common denominator:
One-fifth of a swarm of bees flew towards a lotus
flower, one-third towards a banana tree. (A number
equal to) three times the difference between the two
(preceding figures), O my beauty with the eyes of
a gazelle, flew towards a Codaga tree (whose bitter
bark provides a substitute for quinine). Finally, one
other bee, undecided, flew hither and thither
equally attracted by the delicious perfume of the
jasmine and the pandanus. Tell me, O charming
one, how many bees were there?
Let x= the number of bees
x = x+_x t 3x([-l)+ 1
5 3 3 5
Reducing the fractions to a common denominator,
we get:
x = 3_x + 5_x + 3 x (5 - 3) + 1
15 15 T5 ^
x = 15
triangulation were made by Indian mathemati¬
cians; they all touched on matters of traditional
interest in India, whose scholars had always
shown a particular taste and talent for grammat¬
ical forms.
Mathematics, like all the other scientific dis¬
ciplines in ancient India, was subject to the con¬
straints and stylistic forms of the Sanskrit
language as well as to the demands of verse since
most scientific texts were written in verse form.
The great mathematical treatises, written in
Sanskrit, usually by a Brahman (a member of the
highest, priestly caste), consisted of a basic, often
cryptic, text made up of sutras or aphorisms, or
else of verses that were learned by heart. A stream
of prose commentaries explain the full meaning
of these ancient texts, confirming that they were
aphoristic in nature and deliberately conceived
as summaries of a master's teachings, expressed
in such a way as to stick in the memory of his
pupils.
Evidence of the early use of numbers, in the
sense of graphic symbols, is to be found in in¬
scriptions on stone or copper that have been
studied by archaeologistssuch as the numbers
4 and 6, for example, found in the Asoka inscrip¬
tions which date back to the third century BC.
They are very rarely to be found, however, in
proper mathematical texts. Arabic numerals, so
called because they were made known to the rest
of the world by Arab authors, are, in fact, of In¬
dian origin. In general, however, they were rarely
used in Sanskrit texts, in which numbers are writ¬
ten out in full or symbolized by alphabetical
codes. To be more precise, we must distinguish
clearly between the basic texts, generally written
in verse, and the prose commentaries which alone
provide us with information about the way in
which numbers were written down during the
actual process of calculation.
Numbers were set out vertically over sever¬
al lines, or at least this is what emerges from a
commentary written by Bhaskara the Elder in
629 AD on the Aryabhatiya. Unfortunately, the
life-span of Indian manuscripts was short, aver¬
aging only about three centuries. Written on
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
m
k m
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
paper or on palm leaves, they were a prey to mil¬
dew and insects. The manuscripts of Bhaskara's
commentary that have come down to us are
modern copies and cannot be taken as evidence
of the manner of writing of more ancient times.
The twelfth-century Bakhsali manuscript, which
is probably the oldest document in this sense,
shows calculations in Arabic numerals spread
over several lines and contained in cartouches, or
boxes, within the body of a mathematical text
written in Sanskrit.
The absence of graphic symbols and numbers
in the aphorisms and verses of the classic mathe¬
matical texts does not mean that symbolism is to¬
tally excluded, but that the symbolism employed
is grammatical or rhetorical in nature. Thanks to
the virtually limitless synonymical possibilities
of the Sanskrit language, numbers are represent¬
ed" by. literary phrases and metaphors. Thus,
nayana (eye) or bahu (arm) are the names of the
number 2. Agni (fire) means 3 (by allusion to the
three Vedic forms of ritual fire) and adri (moun¬
tain) means 7 (a reference to the seven mountains
of India of Hindu religious geography). The San¬
skrit words for "sky" or "space" stand for zero.
The order of the figures making up a number is
the reverse of modern numerical systemsfor
example, the number 23 would be written as
agninayana.
This symbolism is useful for writing in verse
form series of figures which today would be laid
out in tabular form. In India, as elsewhere, the
astronomical data in almanacs have for centuries
been presented in columns of numbers. But this
mode was an Arab invention and in the ancient
Sanskrit texts numbers were presented in the
form of a line or a verse of poetry.
Another form of numerical symbolism fre-
20
The ratio of the circumference
of a circle to its diameter (n)
sfrjxws' cTrTH^jpi srrmrw ïï^nnni
*|yrl¿MW^MWlH^>-clTmr(Ull«4: Il
caturadhikam satam astagunam dväsastis tathä
sahasrlnim
ayutadvayaviskambhasyäsanno vrttaparinähah
"Add four to one hundred, multiply by eight, add
62,000. This will give you the approximate value
(asanna) of the circumference of a circle with a dia¬
meter of two myriads."
This verse, written by the sixth-century Indian
mathematician Aryabhata, gives the oldest known
formulation of the approximate value of the ratio
that later became known as n :
circumference
diameter
62832
2C000
3.1416
quently used in astronomical and mathematical
texts is based on the Sanskrit alphabet. Several
such systems exist. The katapayadi system, which
is widely used in southern India, makes it possi¬
ble for very large numbers and trigonometric
tables to be expressed in the form of mnemonic
words, aphorisms or verses. The system is flexi¬
ble enough to enable such numbers to be ex¬
pressed in phrases which also have another
meaning. For example, the priestly injunction
acaryavag abhedya, which means literally "The
word of the Master must not be betrayed", is cod¬
ed writing of the number 1434160, a chronogram
for the 1,434,160th day of the era of Kali, the day
on which the philosopher Sankaracarya in¬
troduced 'certain reforms.
Did this poetic form of expression have an
influence on mathematical reasoning? Was there
some specific characteristic, something special in
the way of thinking or the social status of Indian
mathematicians which led them to shape their
teachings in a literary mould?
There has never been a caste or even a real
school of mathematicians in India. Mathemati¬
cians, if we class as such those who wrote or used
Sanskrit texts dealing with geometry, arithmetic
or algebra, worked in fairly close collaboration
with experts in Vedic and Brahmanic ritual. Brah-
mans or members of a high caste and steeped in
Sanskrit culture, they were classed among scien¬
tists zsjyotirvid, or "experts on stars". Mathemat¬
ical texts were usually inserted in treatises on
astronomy, and trigonometry only really came
into its own in the study of the angular distances
between stars.
Like all the Brahman sciences (the sastra),
lLleventh-century bronze
effigy of the god Shiva as
Vinadhara (master of
sciences and arts).
In Indian numerical
symbolism, the Sanskrit
word Rudrasya (the
5 faces of Siva) denotes the
number 5.
FRANCIS ZIMMERMANN,
French philosopher and
ethnologist, is director of
research at the National
Centre for Scientific Research
(CNRS).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
mathematics had been developed primarily for
religious purposes, as an aid to the proper per¬
formance of ritual. We know nothing of the life
of the great Indian mathematicians, but we can
picture fairly accurately the ritualistic and scholas¬
tic setting within which they worked, so heavily
coloured by it is the style of Sanskrit texts. After
the pupils had memorized à text by repeating it
word for word, time and again until it was
"clasped to their bosoms" (until they had learned
it by heart), the teacher would provide them, oral¬
ly, with the illustrations, demonstrations and cal¬
culations that the text concealed. This was the
key that opened up the paths of knowledge and
an instrument of spiritual fulfilment.
The Lilavati, a text by the twelfth-century
mathematician Bhaskara the Learned, was tradi¬
tionally used for this purpose for arithmetic and
this explains why it terminates with a verse with
a double meaning in which Bhaskara compares
his Lilavati, his "gracious one" (it also means
arithmetic), to a woman endowed with all the
graces of the jati (a word which means both of
noble lineage and, in a technical sense, the reduc¬
tion of fractions to a common denominator).
"Joy and happiness in this world shall continu¬
ally increase for those who hold her kanthasak-
ta, close in their arms or clasped to their bosoms
(learned by heart by repetition)."
From ritual geometry
to Bhaskara's treatise
'The oldest of these texts that have come down
to us are the sulbasutras, "maxims concerning
measuring cords", which are believed to have
been written between the fifth and the first cen¬
tury BC. They are treatises which lay down the
rules for building altars used for Vedic ritual
sacrifices and made of bricks laid in accordance
with symbolic forms. The geometric construc¬
tions which are taught in these treatises are based
on knowledge of several special cases of right-
angled triangles (for example, with sides measur¬
ing 3-4-5, or 5-12-13, 7-24-25, etc.) and on the
general rule according to which "the diagonal of
a rectangle produces (by the construction on it
of a square) the equivalent of the product of both
the rectangle's length and breadth; and the di¬
agonal of a square produces (by the construction
on it of a square) twice its own area." Here,
however, the rule is not expressed as a theorem,
but as a maxim, as a formula to ensure the proper
functioning of ritual and as a building guideline.
The word sutra itself, which at first meant
"aphoristic in style", came, in the later treatises,
to mean a "rule" in the technical sense of a rule
for building.
There are no theorems in Indian mathematics,
only rules based on reasoning which starts from
an intuitive point of departure. The rules,
aphorisms and the mnemonic verses of the basic
texts are not the outcome of a demonstration but
rather guidelines for a geometric construction to
l\anda, the adoptive
father of Krishna, consults
an astrologer. Miniature
of the Kangra school
(late 18th century).
be carried out by the reader or the commenta¬
tor. Even in algebra, the typical line of reason¬
ing links areas to the products of factors and
implies the construction of a geometric figure.
It has often been said that the Indians were
algebraists rather than geometers yet, in fact,
throughout all the commentaries on the teach¬
ings of Aryabhata (sixth century), Brahmagupta
(seventh century) and Bhaskara (twelfth centu¬
ry), geometry was the source of the practical ap¬
plications of the rules of arithmetic and algebra.
A geometric space and a numerical ensemble were
taken together as two facets of the same reality.
The algebraic solution was grafted on to the geo¬
metric construction. To demonstrate was to dis¬
play the solution, to render it intuitively manifest.
As one commentator said: "A demonstration by
quantities should be made for the benefit of those
who do not understand the demonstration by
areas." Thus, in Indian mathematics, to reason
is to explain an intuition. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
71 in the sky
BY JEAN-CLAUDE MARTZLOFF
22
PREDICTION OF CELESTIAL
PHENOMENA WAS A
MAINSPRING OF EARLY CHINESE
MATHEMATICS
T
V-/HINESE mathematics", defined by the
Chinese themselves in ancient times as the "art
of calculation" (suan chu), covers a vast range of
practices and currents of thought that grew up
in China between the first millennium BC and
the fall of the Manchu dynasty in 1911. After that
date Chinese mathematics became westernized
and the traditional practices were virtually im¬
penetrable to those without specialized training.
Divination, astronomy
and mathematics
Although writing already played an important
role in China at the time of the composition of
the earliest canonical writings (the "classics"
which were always so essential in the training of
intellectual élites), mathematics was not then con¬
sidered to be a body of knowledge that it was
necessary to record in specialized texts.
It seems, however, that mathematics was in¬
strumental in the emergence of what the sinolo¬
gist L. Vandermeersch has judiciously called
"divinatory rationality". Beginning with oracles
in the form of tortoise shells, animal bones or the
leaves of the Chinese yarrow, the prognostics
made using this form of divination were based
on the interpretation of all manner of natural
signs, especially meteorological and astronomi¬
cal phenomena such as rainbows, halos, winds,
meteors, positions and conjunctions of stars,
eclipses and sunspots. This magical worldview did
not however exclude recourse to purely rational
investigations. The diviners attempted with some
success to fit all their' 'observations into numeri¬
cal and arithmetical schemes devised for the
recording of memorable past phenomena and the
prediction of certain recurrent events. Some
predictions of periodically recurring celestial
1,420 stars are depicted on
this polychrome sky map
made in 1453. The map
forms part of a panelled
ceiling in Beijing's
Longfu temple.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
1 he legendary emperor
Yao requests the
astronomers Hsi and Ho
to establish the calendar
'and pay tribute to the
heavenly bodies. Engraving
from the late Manchu
period (1905).
phenomena began to be confirmed by observa¬
tion, and led to the birth of the calendar and
mathematical astronomy.
Each successive dynasty in China made its
mark by introducing a new system for comput¬
ing the calendar so that the historical events
recorded by annalists could be reassessed and fu¬
ture events predicted. The ruling class therefore
needed qualified personnel who specialized in
calendrical and astronomical calculations. A body
of imperial chronologers thus gradually came into
being, serving both as historian-annalists and
astronomer-calendrists.
The continuing requirements of Chinese dy¬
nasties down the ages explain why the search for
appropriate methods of predicting the most visi¬
ble celestial phenomena (conjunctions of stars, oc¬
cultations, eclipses) was foremost in the minds of
mathematicians.
However, as the astronomer-calendrists of
24
egresa gffWHgtfi^^KSg
imperial China usually had a lowly social status,
and as their knowledge was handed down from
father to son, their activities were often denigrat¬
ed and looked upon simply as a static way of up¬
holding tradition.
The overwhelmingly dominant factor in the
history of Chinese mathematical astronomy is the
extraordinary durability of conflicts between rival
schools. From the beginning of our era to the six¬
teenth century, the Chinese calendar underwent
no less than fifty reforms. However, these con¬
flicts turned out to be more constructive than des¬
tructive in that they were almost always settled
by the concordance between observed reality and
the predictions.
Unfortunately, very few works devoted ex¬
clusively to mathematical astronomy have sur¬
vived. Monographs written by non-specialists,
abridged versions of which were included in the
annals of successive dynasties, are practically all
that remain.
The social background
of Chinese mathematics
During the Han dynasty (206 BC to 220 AD),
another branch of mathematics appeared, this
time recorded in specialized manuals. Collections
of problems and their solutions were organized
in chapters according to their practical applica¬
tions. The descriptions in these texts are often so
detailed and realistic that it is almost possible to
reconstruct from them entire chapters of Chinese
social and economic life at a given period.
Whether they are about tax collection, corvée
labour, weights and measures, currency, the con¬
struction of dykes or canals, the management of
manpower, land or river transport, policing
or military logistics, no practical detail was
neglected. Generations of "civil servant-
mathematicians" were trained for the imperial
bureaucracy by the study of such manuals.
The Tang dynasty (618 to 907 AD) set up an
examination system whose syllabus included
mathematics as well as letters. Although least im¬
portance was accorded to mathematics, study of
the subject at the Guozijian, the "College of the
Sons of the State", lasted seven years and was
based on a classic textbook, "The Ten Mathemat¬
ical Manuals" (Suanjing shi shu). In 1084, under
. the Southern Sung dynasty, this text was print¬
ed. Yet after 1230 mathematics was banished from
the examination syllabus for good, in favour of
literary subjects.
Paradoxically, the high-water marks of '
mathematics are not to be found in the short
periods when the teaching of the subject was
institutionalized. On the contrary, the most
remarkable advances took place when the empire
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Diagrams illustrating problems in spherical trigonometry
examined by the astronomer-mathematicians Kuo Shou Ching
(1276, left) and Hsing Yûn Lu (1600, right).
was divided, in time of war and bureaucratic
breakdown. During the Warring States period
(453 to 222 BC), the Moists (followers of Mo-tzu
who challenged the dominant Confucian ideolo¬
gy) developed the rudiments of theoretical geo¬
metry, but their method had little influence on
the main current of mathematical thought. The.
greatest mathematician of ancient China, the de¬
tails of whose life are unfortunately unknown,
was Liu Hui, who elaborated several mathemat¬
ical theorems at the time when China was split
into three kingdoms (220 to 265 AD). During the
Mongol conquest in the thirteenth century,
a wealth of original achievements took
root, flowered, and were quickly consigned to
oblivion.
The last and greatest of the Sung mathemati¬
cians was Zhu Shijie (fl. around 1300), a wander¬
ing scholar who travelled far and wide teaching
the results of his research. Also during these
Lid ofa coffer dating from around the beginning
of the Warring States period (c. 433 BC).
The Great Bear (at centre) is surrounded by the names
and symbols of the 28 lunar mansions.
troubled times, the hermit Li Zhi (1192-1279) or¬
ganized a private group devoted to the study of
the mysteries of the world and of numbers, which
led to the development of algebra in China. And
in the nineteenth century, shortly after the
Opium War, when the Chinese empire was over¬
taken by major disasters, Li Shanlan (1811-1882)
failed his literature examinations and dedicated
himself to the joys of mathematics. He discovered
an astonishing series of perfectly correct formu¬
lae which were to baffle even a twentieth-century
mathematician of the calibre of Paul Turan of
Hungary.
The reasons behind these sudden and short- 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
lived flashes of brilliance are poorly understood.
Perhaps political anarchy freed the intellectual
élite from the obligation of preparing the sterile
mandarinate examinations. Confucianism, the
dominant ideology, relegated mathematics to a
minor role. Those who were attracted by the sub¬
ject could therefore give free rein to their intellec¬
tual curiosity without great risk. Even in stable
times, however, many Confucian scholars used
their leisure hours to study mathematics. From
the eighteenth century onwards, more and more
philologists and specialists in textual criticism
dreamed of turning mathematics into a branch
of history. Some of them tried their best to use
mathematical astronomy to authenticate the clas¬
sics. They wanted to define by calculation the
historical reality of natural events recorded in an¬
cient documents (especially eclipses of the Moon
or the Sun). Others enthusiastically studied "con¬
crete sciences" such as economics, hydraulics,
civil engineering or architecture. Out of these ex¬
cursions along lonely and difficult paths there
sometimes grew a taste for pure mathematics, in¬
dependent of any particular application.
Contact with other cultures is also of impor¬
tance in the history of Chinese mathematics: with
India during the first millennium AD as Budd¬
hism was being preached abroad; with the Arab
\jilt bronze equatorial
Moon dial. Qing Dynasty
26 (1744).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
COUNTING-ROD NUMERALS OF ANCIENT CHINA
The use of counting-rod
numerals, which may have
originated with the UNITS
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
arrangement of actual rods
laid out on a flat board,
HUNDREDS
TEN OF THOUSANDS I II III IUI lllll T T ¥ ¥
developed in China around
the 3rd century BC. Units
were noted vertically, tens
TENS
THOUSANDS ___
	 = = J_ _L =!= =
horizontally. The value of
the signs was determined
by their position: THE NUMBER 34,567
WRITTEN AS:
III = lllll J. T
and Persian peoples at the time of the Mongol
expansion; and with European missionaries from
the late sixteenth century onwards. Although
many similarities can be seen between mathemat¬
ics in China and in other cultures before 1600,
it is unclear whether this is a sign of actual in¬
fluence or simply of parallel development.
For example, the Chinese symbol for zero,
which was written as a small circle as it is today,
appeared for the first time around 1200 in astro¬
nomical tables and could have been of Indian ori¬
gin. A number of ancient and medieval
mathematical games, whether from the Hellenis¬
tic or the Arab world, India, Europe or China,
have a surprising family likeness. Very similar
mathematical techniques existed at the same peri¬
od in China and in Greece. To cite but two ex¬
amples, Euclid and Liu Hui both discovered
methods of determining the volume of a pyramid;
Archimedes and Liu Hui found the volume of
a solid by the intersection of two orthogonal
cylinders.
Even if these parallels do indicate the trans¬
mission of influences, Chinese mathematics had
an internal coherence and developed indepen¬
dently.
Geometry without parallel
In traditional Chinese mathematics there is no
geometrical reasoning based on axioms, postu¬
lates, definitions and theorems. There are no ab¬
solute truths in the manner of Euclid, but only
relative and provisional truths. In geometry, there
are no angles nor even any parallel lines, but only
lengths, areas and volumes. Neither is there any
algebra in the Arab style, nor the search for the
roots of equations using radicals or intersecting
curves. And there is no "rhetorical" algebra en¬
shrined in prose or verse.
Yet Chinese mathematics is based not on
purely empirical procedures but on heuristic prin¬
ciples. The emphasis is on the answer itself, rather
than on explaining the intermediate stages in get¬
ting there, which are taken for granted. For ex¬
ample, one of the cardinal rules of Chinese
geometry stipulates that the surface or the volume
of a figure remain the same after it has been
broken up and re-assembled, even though the
number of the fragments is potentially infinite.
This type of principle does not at all exclude the
recourse to an axiomatic system, but it is true that
Chinese geometric figures were not usually ab¬
stract ideals. They were, rather, like tangible
pieces of a puzzle that can be distinguished by
their colour and manipulated at will. Chinese ge¬
ometry basically relies on a shrewd and
meticulous examination of a problem to reveal
certain results. This method is not only impor¬
tant in the calculation of areas and volumes, but
also in bringing out certain properties of the right-
angled triangle, in calculating the total of a series,
in resolving equations or systems of equations,
and in the visual proof of mathemathical identities.
What is more, Chinese geometry sees noth¬
ing wrong (as Euclid would have done) in resort¬
ing to calculations or any other method that may
be useful to solve a given problem. This attitude
shows Taoist influence, and Chinese mathemati¬
cians of the third to the fifth centuries AE
declared their boundless admiration for Zhuang-
zi, the father of philosophical Taoism. This ec¬
centric sage had rejected the use of language as
a notably effective way of reaching the truth, on
the grounds that the fallacious arguments of the
sophists showed its limits.
He had concluded that all attempts to reach
the truth founded on discursive argument, that
is to say on a method capable of engendering
manifestly false conclusions, would be doomed
to failure. Hence the tendency of Chinese
mathematicians, influenced by Taoism, to place
only limited faith in the power of language. On
the other hand they tended to make use of all the
means at their disposal, without ever ignoring the
evidence of their senses. This is why they were
JEAN-CLAUDE
MARTZLOFF,
French sinologist, is a
researcher with the
National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS).
He is particularly interested
in the exchanges between
Chinese science and other
scientific traditions. He is
the author of a history of
Chinese mathematics
{Histoire des mathématiques
chinoises, Masson publishers,
Paris, 1987).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
so fond of calculations and all kinds of manipu¬
lations, so long as they could avoid putting them
into words. Only as a last resort did they have
recourse to discursive arguments.
How did mathematicians apparently so ob¬
sessed by the concrete have produced sophisticat¬
ed results? In fact the practical nature of Chinese
mathematics does not imply any lack of abstrac¬
tion in their thinking. On the contrary, some of
the results obtained from manipulating their puz¬
zles presuppose great ingenuity and a remarkable
capacity for abstraction.
Moreover, Chinese mathematicians often
deliberately distorted reality, as they could not
easily teach their subject using as examples the
increasingly complex problems of daily life. This
is why many Chinese mathematical problems
conceal purely fictitious situations behind a
veneer of practical reality: values which are im¬
possibly large or small, or that make no sense
(fractions of men); data arranged in an arbitrary
manner, as when areas are added up with volumes
and prices; inversion of known and unknown
values as when calculating the dimensions of ob¬
jects from their volume, or capital from the in¬
terest gained, or quantities of goods from the
share received by each person. Obviously such
methods opened up very much more interesting
situations from the mathematical point of view.
Chinese algebra developed on this "fictional
territory". In the oldest manuals are many cal-
culatory formulae for resolving limited classes of
problems. In extreme instances, each problem
constitutes a specific case. Later, generalized
procedures appear by which an increasingly wide
range of problems could be solved, so fictitious
situations were no longer required.
All this could not have taken place without
Chinese computational methods, which were
based on mechanical aids. The abacus is perhaps
the best known of these, but it appeared at a
late date (around the fifteenth century). Chinese
mathematicians relied above all on the manipu¬
lation of counting-rods (chousuan), which were
arranged to represent the various coefficients
of numerical equations. Mathematical problems
transferred to arrangements of counting-rods
were, so to speak, divorced from their practical
context and taken into the realm of abstraction.
This method of calculation by tabulation is
generally known as fangcheng (fang meaning
"square" or "rectangle" and cheng meaning "di¬
vide up") and involves arranging the counting-
rods to form a square or a rectangle (a matrix).
Two types of rod were used, red and black or
positive and negative, representing the com¬
plementary forces which controlled the Chinese
universe, yin and yang.
Here we have an "instrumental" algebra
which dispenses with all discursive methods of
argument. This is its strength, but also its weak¬
ness, as during the manipulations of the counting-
rods, calculations vanish without trace as soon
as they are completed. This "art of the rods" is
like the art of a musician who plays without look¬
ing at the score, and it is no coincidence that some
Chinese mathematicians explicitly compare
mathematics with music.
Calculations and manipulations are the bas¬
ic ingredients of a form of mathematics which
has never felt itself to be bound by any dogma,
and which at various phases of its history has
syncretized many elements from other cultures.
I he gelosia or grating
method of multiplication as
shown in a Chinese book
of 1593.
O m -y.
asjs
H
ffl
t
S\
M
A it
XA f
/A
III/
/>
V V +
A
x Ixight, detail from a 12th-
century Greek manuscript
of Euclid's Elements.
	
^ oO f HJUpt GOV
t f turtèhp«
n
M-*^1 u
£i-*Ti p »P TIT? <*4
W (cOI»i'»P-*OCK.«
J-7 pop («UXJUUf
of IM CjO |»T* CT» *
rt'ífuxoa¿\£i.
|K^AS TP* r
\377lWp*wf-jLCj
£ u-Vb/ajui oíTóuf i
	 .* l "-¿írL.
TH> «T>"7r» woccüTí
rv**«»eiVM.*»M-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
ANCIENT
GREECE The Odyssey of reason
BY BERNARD VITRAC
^? [
^V
JU* CK.«CT«P ft %J>Cj\omJ~¿4J'.~
\
~-S
*> P «P i* OT5 *TT>E O p o P r-, o p 3 -y -
rfp»p
"N al ^ « \
»XKe-j^ftnT _
J * n p it*« t(^y-^ t "p f" °"~^
OOP«
\ *
PÏiTB'^Tr^lup»»' i^opflö tí ^
°t?YM q- .fUpojoT»w 7«íM- ^
poucoC
» e ^m *** riV»jiTiáMcTcr
/-O J V « ^"TV a. /
*« *7n çT^i'^TÔW-* ° *!**£
Ä" cr/oç-^i*IU»p:COH M4 poC » î*-K.o
«CCI t «p r»«rt%JL.YV0i;.X0.4-1 "»
r^y. eu r»p co trtjo oe y^uu
** I TTTCjO P o-j "^tp o»u.ulOL^| tftr
«k>«^*i e ***** y «u c^n^¿,,
"CÍ^Lx
T is scarcely necessary to recall the importance
of the role played by the mathematics of ancient
Greece in the development of this discipline in
the West. The very words "mathematics" and
"mathematician", or their equivalents in most
European languages, are derived from the Greek
word meaning "to know" or "to learn". Before
the classical era, however, when it took on the
specialized meaning that it has today, the Greek
word mathema meant "that which is taught", in
other words all branches of knowledge.
The teaching of mathematics
We know very little about the teaching of
mathematics in ancient Greece. It seems that
some philosophical schools played a major part
in the training of mathematicians, at a time when
intellectual specialization was still the exception.
During the classical era there is reference to
the existence of "scientific" schools, such as those
at Chios and Cyzicus. However, we do not know
whether these schools offered general or special¬
ized education, or whether they were anything
more than groups of scholars gathered around a
famous teacher.
As with medicinefor the existence of
schools of which there is earlier and more solid
evidenceit seems that family background may
have had an influence on professional training.
We have few biographical details about the
early mathematicians, but we do know that
Archimedes was the son of an astronomer, that
Hypsicles' father was a mathematician, that the
geometers Menaechmus and Dinostratus were
brothers and that Hypatia, the only Greek wom¬
an mathematician about whom we know any¬
thing much, was the daughter of the
mathematician Theon of Alexandria.
In the centralized states of the Near East of
ancient times, the need to train a class of scribes
and functionaries was recognized at an early stage..
The Greece of the classical era, however, consist¬
ed of small, independent city-states, continually
warring among themselves, or of loose, clan-like
associations, and had no need of organized educa¬
tional systems such as those of Egypt, Babylon
or China.
Although trade, land surveying and naviga¬
tion demanded a certain minimum knowledge
of mathematics, and although elementary calcu¬
lation was taught in schools, the Greek city-
state paid scant attention to the intellectual and 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
technological education of children and youths.
Schools, some of which were to achieve consider¬
able renown, were the fruit of private initiatives.
The two great Athenian masters of the beginning
of the fourth century BC, Isocrates and Plato,
each founded his own educational
establishmentIsocrates a school of rhetoric and
Plato a school of philosophy.
Both of them regarded mathematics as an in¬
dispensable tool for intellectual development and
valued the "mental gymnastics" and concentra¬
tion this discipline required. But their approaches
to mathematics differed. Isocrates thought that
mathematics, like the adversarial debates that
young people were so fond of, should develop
"well-formed minds", even if the subject matter
I ythagor
(6th century BC) as
depicted in a 16th-century
engraving.
was of little value to the citizen, who, ideally,
would devote himself to political life. Plato,
however, whilst recognizing its propaedeutic
value, saw mathematics as a preliminary to the
study of philosophyin other words, of Platon¬
ic idealismand also as a method of selection,
since the mathematics and the philosophy he
taught together constituted a form of intellectu¬
al asceticism essential to his project for political
reform.
The third and second centuries BC witnessed
a considerable development in the mathematical
sciences. Most of the works that have come down
from this period are those of mathematicians
more or less closely linked to Alexandria, the cap¬
ital of the Greek Ptolemaic dynasty which ruled
Egypt from 306 to 31 BC. It is known that the
Ptolemies adopted a broader policy of state
patronagepreviously restricted to a few in¬
dividuals, often poetsby creating a number of
institutions, the best known of which were the
Alexandria Library and Museum. These new in¬
stitutions undoubtedly gave an impetus to liter¬
ary studies. That they had an effect on scientific
development is probable but less certain, but the
favourable climate they created could only be
beneficial to it.
However, we do not even know if the great
scholars of the time, whose presence in Alexan¬
dria is well documentedHerophilus of Chal¬
cedony, Euclid, Strato of Lampsacus, Aristarchus
of Samos, Eratosthenes of Cyrene, Apollonius of
Pergataught their disciples or. gave lessons or
even lectures, whether under the auspices of the
Museum or privately. Indeed, it was only in the
time of the Roman Empire that the Museum was
to operate as a university, to be copied in this at
Ephesus, Athens, Smyrna and Aegina.
Alongside pure mathematics, in the Greek
tradition, there was also a corpus of mathemati¬
cal texts that might be termed "calculative"
similar to those to be found in Egyptian, Babylo¬
nian or Chinese mathematical writings. For ex¬
ample, a body of comparatively late mathematical
texts, attributed to Hero of Alexandria, was com¬
piled and used right up to the Byzantine era,
probably for the training of technicians. As in
Babylonian and Egyptian texts, the problems set
refer explicitly to a factual situation, even if this
is merely a teaching device.
Nothing like this is to be found in the classic
treatises of Euclid, Archimedes or Apollonius,
who showed scant regard for practical applica¬
tions. Euclid's exposition of the theory of num¬
bers even manages to avoid reference to
numerical examples. The works that have sur¬
vived seem to indicate a strict separation between
pure research and practical applications. Yet even
though the two are so clearly distinguished, the
same authors gave equal attention to both "pure"
and "applied" mathematics.
That section of Greek mathematics which,
by convention, we have designated as "pure" had
four basic characteristics:
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
1 hales of Miletus (late 7th-
early 6th century BC).
17th-century engraving.
BERNARD VITRAC,
of France, teaches mathematics
and is (with James Ritter) co-
director of a scries of
publications on the history of
science entitled Histoires des
sciences, published by the
Presses Universitaires de
Vincennes (University of Paris-
VIII). The author of a study-
on medicine and philosophy at
the time of Hippocrates (1989),
he is currently preparing a
translation with commentary
of Euclid's Elements, the first
volume of which will be
published later this year by-
Presses Universitaires de
France.
Deductive presentation: the classic treatises,
such as Euclid's Elements, are organized on deduc¬
tive lines. The results are proved by demonstra¬
tion, either from results previously achieved, or
on the basis of principles established from the
start. This might be described as a semi-axiomatic
approach, which emphasized the logical, ineluc¬
table aspect of mathematics. It should, however,
be noted that this is often difficult to dissociate
from the rhetorical aspect, which had the advan¬
tage of compelling the attention of the student,
aimed at psychological and pedagogical effective¬
ness, and concentrated on the necessary objective
structure of reasoning.
Geometrical orientation: even when they
were concerned with the theory of numbers,
statics or astronomy, those treatises that were
demonstrative in style were basically geometric
in their approach. Ancient mathematicians had
introduced various symbols to designate numbers
and fractions and also employed certain abbrevi¬
ations, although these did not constitute a com¬
plete set of algebraic notations such as we use
today.
However, it was in the use of geometrical
figures that the Greeks went farthest in their ex¬
perimentation with the use of "representative"
symbols. The possibility of breaking figures up
into elements, of establishing rules of construc¬
tion that could be quoted, and the revelation of 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
I V/ m',^*
.# >'
1
aa^	J	)	^
'"
W.
T\ '
A ffi
_tL.l_J	 1IU .- >-,i.I.
" 1
rVTvV
>-
u Kfl
- v-
at^-'-l .. v - ±tPv ta '
-, -. ^"-.r;/Y-Y^ vCT-
h*-4 ¿fcv
Y*»
5*1
il
' I .'
*fii
'ii
Sis».
32
-Y
.a^
^riy?
!y/,
p*
.L-1-'i ~-v t#
J
-M m
'M
¡^> JrawîM
* ^^
fY ?/;/*
tV"
at *VS.
r 	' ^^
-: '
a«> *^4. ^n^atttSrí''Sël* » mnnwiHi^iMHiyinipi mmiia i m iiiiPi il iwii *,
«H
yyy^y;
'a-
-ut
" î
IJel
ir >~
.YtVp Vrr-
	.
rr
;tt
t- . J».i-ai . aw . ¿i ¿* rj , aaa. 1 «rv*!a»**JV<F
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
*«1 -d4» î Äfc*^-^*m««« «41 ««(** Js.
. . .-,' ' ';. li «lÄl
. *
properties which seemed already to be "present"
in the figures, all these features were perfectly
suited to the method of deductive exposition.
The ideal of disinterested science: the love
of knowledge itself was the driving force behind
the study of mathematics.
Mathematics and philosophy: the develop¬
ment of mathematics was contemporaneous with
the development of philosophy.
Philosophers
and mathematics
These developments in mathematics were
paralleled by the opening of a methodological and
ideological debate on the sciences. The classifica¬
tion of the sciences proposed by the Greek
astronomer-mathematician Geminus (see box
page 34) affords a good example. His classifica¬
tion assumed the existence of a body of scientif¬
ic knowledge already fairly well developed and
very varied. It adopted a differentiation between
the sciences which favoured abstract study, which
it detached from possible practical applications.
According to Aristotle, mathematics was the
study of properties that could be "abstracted",
from the objects of the physical world. Further¬
more, like all the demonstrative sciences, it was
based on principles, so that one science could
presuppose another and, in Aristotle's words: "be
subordinate to another." Optics, for example,
was "subordinate" to geometry. Thus there was
a logical hierarchy of the sciences. This had to
be distinguished from the division, commonly
stressed by Greek authors, between "practical"
and "disinterested" mathematics. Only the lat¬
ter, according to Aristotle, was worthy of inclu¬
sion in a liberal education. "To be free" was an
end in itself.
The art of embellishment was superior to
practical technology, but disinterested science, an
end in itself, was the supreme activity. For Plato,
the mathematics developed by the Barbarians,
prestigious though their civilizations might have
been, ranked as mere arts, since they were en¬
cumbered by the constraints of necessity.
Greek philosophers thus based their argument on
a mixture of methodological and ideological
considerations.
Though treatises on optics and astronomy
adopted the style of geometrical exposition, the
deductive method being particularly suited to the
elimination of anything that smacked of the "tan¬
gible" and the "practical" (see box page 34), it
is not easy to see how Greek mathematicians
managed to identify themselves with this way of
looking at their activities. Moreover, though it
is tempting to do so, we should refrain from con¬
fusing the modern distinction between "pure"
and "applied" mathematics with the ancient di¬
vision between "intelligible" and "tangible",
since the concepts do not coincide.
Evocation of the ideal of "disinterested science" 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
PRECEDING PAGE
1 he Death ofArchimedes.
In this mosaic found at
Herculaneum, the Greek
mathematician is shown
drawing geometric figures
when surprised
by a soldier of the Roman
army which took Syracuse
in 212 BC. When called
on to give himself up,
Archimedes is said to have
replied, "Do not disturb
my circles".
leads on to the problem of what motivation there
was for the advancement of mathematics. A dis¬
tinction has to be made between external forces
and what might be described as internal in¬
fluences. Among the former, an important role
was played by optics and astronomy, which we
classify as physics but which the ancients included
in mathematics. To these should be added statics,
the science of equilibria.
What is known of the internal influences?
Perhaps they are to be found in the prefaces with
which, from Archimedes onwards, author/
mathematicians seem to have introduced their
works. What emerges from these prefaces is that
far from being the product of psychological
characteristics peculiar to the Greek mind, dis¬
interested research presupposes the existence of
a community of mathematicians all abiding by
certain standards.
First and foremost, these mathematicians felt
under no obligation to justify the fact that they
were practitioners of science for its own sake; that
went without saying. At the most they might ac¬
knowledge that they had opted for mathematics
rather than for "physics" or "theology" because
it was a more certain and rigorous discipline that
was "stable" (unlike physics), yet nevertheless
"accessible" (unlike theology).
34
Geminus' classification
of Mathemata
Others, among them Geminus, claim that
mathematics should be sub-divided in another
fashion. On one side they place tangible things, or
anything connected with them. No doubt they
would call intelligible the subjects of contempla¬
tion that the soul elaborates within itself, cutting
itself off from things material. They rank arithmetic
and geometry as the two first and most important
sectors of that form of mathematics that deals w ith
that which is intelligible. With regard to the
mathematics which covers things tangible, they
designate six sectors: mechanics, astronomy, optics,
geodesy, canonics and logistics.
On the other hand, for them, unlike others,
tactics is not worthy to be considered a part of
mathematics, even though at times it involves logis¬
tics, as in the enumeration of troops, and geodesy,
as in the surveying and the division of land. Even
less do they consider either history or medicine to
be part of mathematics, despite the fact that the
authors of historical works often refer to mathe¬
matical theorems to indicate climatic conditions or
to calculate the size of a town, its diameter and its
perimeter, and that physicians use these procedures
to throw light on many matters within their com¬
petence. The value of astronomv to medicine has
been made perfectly clear by Hippocrates and all
those who studied the seasons and regions.
Proclus, Commentary on Book I of Euclid's Elements, 38.
During the Hellenistic era, mathematicians
formed an "international" community whose
members were scattered around the shores of the
Mediterranean (Greece, Asia Minor, Egypt and
Sicily). They maintained personal contacts, either
by paying each other visits or by circulating their
latest works. Above all, they would set each other
problems, solve those that were sent to them, or
criticize solutions submitted by others which
they considered to be flawed. By this means some
of them acquired a commonly recognized status
of authority. Publications were submitted to their
judgement which they in turn circulated to others
considered worthy to receive them. Among them
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
also were a few impostors who would be un¬
masked by the expedient of setting them impos¬
sible problems which they would claim to have
solved. These contacts, of course, remained per¬
sonal and were not made within the framework
of any form of institution in the modern sense
of the term.
The ideal of "disinterested mathematics"
seems, in short, to have been linked to the exis¬
tence of a group within which problems of rival¬
ry and competition were not altogether unlike
those characteristic of the modern scientific com¬
munity. The comparison should not be pressed
too far. There is, for example, a marked differ
ence in scale between the ancient and the modern
communities. The number of scientists, and in
particular of mathematicians, in the Hellenistic
era certainly never exceeded a few hundred. Like¬
wise, there can be no doubt that, in the absence
of any true form of institution, the community
they formed was a very precarious one. From the
Roman era onwards, the best authors (Ptolemy,
Pappus) were concerned, so it would seem, only
with perfecting results already achieved. The
rivalry and the search for new theories that
marked the preceding era had apparently disap¬
peared.
1 he famous lighthouse
known as the Pharos of
Alexandria is pictured in
this engraving made
in 1801.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE ARAB WORLD Where geometry and
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
algebra intersect Historian of science Roshdi Rashed on
the Arab contribution to the history of
mathematics
1 he city of Baghdad as
depicted in a Turkish
miniature of 1534.
How would you describe the beginnings ofArab
mathematics?
Arab research into mathematics seems to have
begun early in the ninth century when, in Bagh¬
dad, the movement to translate the great Greek
authors into Arabic was at its height. For in¬
stance, Al-Hajjaj ibn Matar made two translations
of Euclid's Elements and Ptolemy's Almagest, and
Hilal ibn Hilal al-Himsi translated the first four
volumes of Apollonius of Perga's Conies. Sever¬
al works by Archimedes, Pappus and Diophan-
tus, among others, were also translated in the
same century.
This major undertaking was noteworthy for
two very important features, in that the transla¬
tions were made by leading mathematicians and
were inspired by the most advanced research of
the time. For example, volumes V to VII of Apol¬
lonius' Conies were translated by the great
mathematician Thabit ibn Qurrah, who died in
the year 901. Moreover, all the indications are
that Qusta ibn Luqa was prompted to translate
the Arithmetica of Diophantus around 870 on ac¬
count of studies already being carried out on in¬
determinate analysis.1
Many other examples could be cited to
demonstrate the close links between such trans¬
lations and the innovative research already being
done at this high point in the dissemination of
Hellenistic mathematics in Arabic.
Al-Khwarizmi is the best known of the Arab
mathematicians.What was his contribution to
mathematical thinking?
It was at this time, in the ninth century, at
the Baghdad Academy, or "House of Wisdom"
as it was known, that al-Khwarizmi wrote a
work that represented a new departure in terms
of both content and style. This was the Kitab
al-jabr wa'l muqabalah ("The Book of Integration
and Equation"),2 from which algebra emerged
for the first time as a separate and independent
mathematical discipline. This was a crucial
development, and was recognized as such by
al-Khwarizmi's contemporaries, as much for its
new mathematical style as for the nature of its
subject-matter and above all for the rich promise
it held out for further advances.
In terms of style, it was both algorithmic, in
that the author set out a series of computational
procedures, and demonstrative. A new mathemat¬
ics had to be devised that was general enough to
be capable of handling different types of formu¬
lation while existing independently of those for¬
mulations. In al-Khwarizmi's work, an algebraic 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Detail from a treatise on
equations by Sharif al-Din
al-Tusi
(late 12th-early 13th
century). The manuscript
dates from 1297.
expression could refer to a number or to an irra¬
tional quantity or to a geometrical magnitude.
This new mathematics and its combination of the
demonstrative and applied approaches was a strik¬
ing innovation for the thinkers of the time.
The novelty of the conception and style of
al-Khwarizmi's algebra, which did not hark back
to any previously known tradition, cannot be
over-emphasized. The new algebra already afford¬
ed a glimpse of the enormous potential for ap¬
plying one mathematical discipline to another
that lay ahead from the ninth century onwards.
In other words, while algebra, by virtue of its
widespread scope and the new concepts it in¬
troduced, made such applications possible, their
number and variety were thereafter constantly
to change the face of mathematics.
Al-Khwarizmi's successors increasingly ap¬
plied arithmetic to algebra and vice versa, arith¬
metic and algebra to trigonometry, algebra to the
Euclidian theory of numbers, and algebra to ge¬
ometry and vice versa. All these applications
-
-
-
-
a»
-
-
'- -
^
38
paved the way for new disciplines or at least for
new chapters in the history of mathematics.
Could you give us a significant example of the
encounter between arithmetic and algebra?
One example that springs to mind is the con¬
tribution which Arab mathematics made to clas¬
sical number theory.
By the end of the ninth century, the most im¬
portant Greek texts on arithmetic, such as Eu¬
clid's own volumes on the subject, the Introductio
arithmeticae of Nicomachus of Gerasa, and the
Arithmetica of Diophantus of Alexandria, had all
been translated. Further chapters in the theory
of numbers were opened in the wake of these
translations and could in a sense be said to have
been a reply to them. For example, two signifi¬
cant steps were taken in respect of the theory of
amicable numbers. The first of these led, in the
context of Euclidian arithmetic, to a new set of
findings, while, as a result of the application of
algebra to the theory of numbers, the second step
culminated some centuries later in the creation
of a field of number theory that owed nothing
to the Greeks. We can look into these two aspects
more closely.
Although Euclid put forward a theory of per¬
fect numbers at the end of Volume IX of his Ele¬
ments, neither he nor Nicomachus of Gerasa had
developed the theory of amicable numbers.3
Thabit ibn Qurrah, who translated the work of
Nicomachus and revised a translation of the Ele¬
ments, decided to work on this theory. He came
up with and demonstrated, in pure Euclidian
style, a remarkable formula for amicable num¬
bers which now bears his name.
If we disregard the mystique which had sur¬
rounded amicable numbers and look only at the
mathematics, it has to be acknowledged that, up
to the end of the seventeenth century at least, the
history of amicable numbers merely consisted of
a passing reference to Ibn Qurrah's formula and
its transmission by later mathematicians. These
included such Arabic-speaking mathematicians as
al-Antaki, al-Bagdadi, ibn al-Banna, al-Umawi and
al-Kashi, whose differing origins in both time and
place clearly show the widespread dissemination
of Ibn Qurrah's formula, which crops up again
in the work of Pierre de Fermât in 1636 and in
that of René Descartes in 1638.
The second step is noteworthy for the fact
that the celebrated physicist and mathematician
Kamal al-Din al-Farisi, who died in 1320, wrote
a paper in which he deliberately set out to demon¬
strate Ibn Qurrah's formula, but by a different
path. Al-Farisi based his new demonstration on
a systematic knowledge of the divisors of a whole
number and of the operations that can be applied
to them. However, this demonstration involved
a reorganization which gave rise not only to a
change in the perspective of Euclidian arithmet¬
ic, but to the promotion of new topics in num¬
ber theory. It accordingly became possible to
speak of a non-Hellenistic area in number theory.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Ç»V-r a» aaa* tW aV* .Jr"*1"»- **"
t^vaW ^*Aaou_ya«AaÎ4a. q r-*at ar
Ci*-'. aVvaí. üfL-yCtt í/*» Í»-C lfr.ll»»* .»»V V
aKi -î,i *_<*<* a»»*» ait^ ar*air-«**
P/ - -
r,»w*iiV.«*.a^r ^ x	^
. '^Maaaal AtM .. i-\j-&
(lihail'UMfclSti««-»»!«'!««*
f\ «alita* » »V** ^aa, r»" f
_}fV|^ 5.W.I Clavan« r^íHt ^í-VvCKfíf fc
-'a. a. ..a 3aC ,aT~aaa. *-tl5 aij*t r4 Xe.
i?t*lfcZL» i*yr\¿ifi¿^iixight, part of a Latin
translation of al-
Khwarizmi's treatise on
algebra in a manuscript
dating from 1145. Far
right, a commentary on
Euclid's Elements of
Geometry by Nasir al-Din
al-Tusi (1201-1274).
(15th-century Persian
manuscript)
In order to make it possible to engage in this
new study of divisors, al-Farisi had to establish
explicitly certain facts that had only been latent
in Euclid's Elements. He also had to make use of
the advances in algebra since al-Karaji's time in
the tenth and eleventh centuries, and especially
of combinatory methods. Hence, al-Farisi's ap¬
proach was by no means confined to demonstrat¬
ing Ibn Qurrah's formula, but enabled him to
embark on a new study involving the first two
arithmetical functions: the sum of the divisors of
a whole number and the number of those
divisors.
This style, which applied algebra and com¬
binatory analysis to Euclidian arithmetic, was still
prevalent in Europe in the seventeenth century,
at least until 1640. The analysis of al-Farisi's con¬
clusions and of the methods he used thus goes
to show that, by as early as the thirteenth centu¬
ry, it had been possible to produce a set of propo¬
sitions, findings and techniques that had hitherto
been ascribed to the mathematicians of the seven¬
teenth century.
What about the new relationship that was
established between algebra and geometry?
We have already seen that the mathematical
landscape was no longer the same from the ninth
century onwards; it was transformed and its
frontiers were rolled back. Greek arithmetic and
geometry became increasingly widespread. In ad¬
dition, non-Hellenistic areas were developed wi¬
thin the corpus of Hellenistic mathematics itself.
The relationship between the old disciplines was
no longer the same, and a host of other group¬
ings were formed. This changing pattern is cru¬
cial to an understanding of the history of
$_*, A-aî.*f rt -J»» af « .)* a* a.ta
(it- j,""aa j_--4-^ J)t>-~a .a«^»-
a^a~ afcaWai (A*»*5*.^« Üa*¿ t>«»« ,?U>Jaa, ûa&a)
<««*naH ïùijv.nv» mV ACaVtCaaVâaJaV v-«-«aît"a-j
.v-^ä^£~i; Ait lifT^cvieZte^S-tgl T¿+~r'X
lf*r-*,'',J,'**,;i-* n*-!««.« *
. wl
H*&>jB
ifHaa JVÄ- f~t a.» va« J*J.tV f-z'
*-<f**$cip£»4?f~*
Líi*í -»»S «~a«-â Ha-.'^f-^fc; JL» Caa»î.	» ia-a<Aaa*< .afra) « Jf_
* . ,.*" ** ^TtÍT*" »TÜ*!*1 a^-ta-?*»^» ai/» n-falj
/^Y
I A
V
\i.'v.v73-«.v
'.4Vc-*.^C''v
; a« -i~ »/»-a^-4 '"
Xa-i'rfjJP^ij/^-iJjiJ^Jlï/i^ui/j i
jJgVj-a-o-j Ja> Aíjt-á-yatJj. JlaiJj.aP
¿jai > *"g/Ù ' 't-ilr'lijSplJ S Ja a¿>
^Ja> a»a-l^aiacii't^'^<a*> -{J^
Ja^j^tr>aWW^/WJ>^'>>'aWU>-
mathematics generally, for the new relationship
between algebra and geometry gave rise to tech¬
niques of enormous potential.
The mathematicians of the tenth century em¬
barked on a two-way exercise in conversion
which had never previously been envisagedthe
translation of geometrical problems into the lan¬
guage of algebra, and vice versa. They translated
into algebraic terms solid problems that could not
be constructed with ruler and compass, such as
the trisection of the angle, the two means, and
the regular heptagon. Moreover, algebraists and
also geometers such as Abu al-Jud b. al-Leith,
when faced with the difficulty of using radicals
to solve a cubic equation, were able to turn to
the language of geometry and apply the intersect
ing curves technique to the study of this type oi
equation.
The first attempts to provide a basis for these
conversions were made by al-Khayyam (c.
1048-1131). In his bid to go beyond the specific
cases represented by a particular form of cubic
equation, al-Khayyam developed a theory of al¬
gebraic equations of a degree less than or equal
to three which at the same time provided a new
model for the formulation of equations. He then
studied cubic equations using conic sections in
order to reach positive real solutions for them.
In order to construct his theory, al-Khayyam had
to visualize the new relationship between algebra
and geometry in clearer terms before being able
to formulate it. From then onwards, the theory
of equations appeared, albeit still tentatively, to
bridge the gap between algebra and geometry.
In his celebrated treatise Algebra, al-Khayyam
produced two remarkable findings which histori¬
ans have wrongly attributed to Descartes. These
ROSHDI HASHED,
of France, is director of
research at the National
Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS). He is the
author of many studies on
the history of Arah
mathematics. Several of his
articles were published in
Entre arithmétique et
algèbre, Recherches sur
l'histoire des mathématiques
arabes (ï.es Belles Lettres
publishers, Paris, 1984).
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
f?Mi
ïït
IUH
m
-
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Left, the Istanbul
observatory is shown in
this Turkish miniature
dating from 1581.
JKight, title of a
manuscript of 1228 which
sets forth the theory of
amicable numbers
formulated by Thabit ibn
Qurrah (d. 901).
1. The last five books of
Diophantus' Arithmctica are
principally devoted to the
solution of indeterminate
equations, i.e. those with more
than one variable and a large
number of solutions. Editor
2. The word algebra is derived
from the title of this work which
was translated into Latin many
times in the Middle Ages and had
a strong influence on medieval
Western science. The word
algorithm, which designates any
method of computation (such as
the decimal system) involving a
series of steps, is derived from the
Latinized form of al-Khwarizmi's
name. Editor
3. A number is perfect if it is
equal to the sum of its own
divisors (for example 6 = 3 + 2
+ 1; 28 = 14 + 7 + 4 + 2 + 1).
Two integers form a pair of
amicable numbers if the sum of
the proper divisors of one is
equal to the other. This is true of
the numbers 220 and 284, which
were for a long time the only
known pair of amicable numbers.
are the generalized solution of all third-degree
equations by means of two intersecting curves,
and the possibility of performing a geometric cal¬
culation by defining a unit length, which was a
fundamental concept.
Some fifty years after al-Khayyam, his suc¬
cessor Sharaf al-Din al-Tusi made a further step
forward. In an attempt to demonstrate the exis¬
tence of the point of intersection of two curves,
he arrived at the problems of finding and separat¬
ing the roots of the equation and of dealing with
the conditions under which they existed. In ord¬
er to find a solution he defined the notion of max¬
imum values for an algebraic expression and tried
to find concepts and methods for determining
such "maxima".
This not only led al-Tusi to the development
of concepts and methods, such as derivatives, that
were only to be named as such at a later date,
but also compelled him to change his approach.
He discovered the need to use local procedures,
whereas his predecessors had only considered the
overall properties of the objects being studied. All
these findings and the theory embracing them are
obviously important and have often been at¬
tributed to mathematicians who only came sever¬
al centuries later.
These are the main features of the dialectic
between algebra and geometry. To complete the
picture, however, two impediments which
slowed down the progress of the new mathemat¬
ics should be mentioned. These were a reluctance
to use negative numbers as such, at a time when
they had not yet been defined, and the shortcom¬
ings of symbolic notation. Both issues were to
preoccupy later mathematicians.
In political historiography distinctions are made
between Antiquity, the Middle Ages, the Renais¬
sance and modern times. Do you think that this
breakdown is relevant in an account of the his¬
tory ofmathematics, and especially of the Arab
contribution?
It is true that "medieval" mathematics has been
contrasted with "modern" mathematics. The first
historical corpus, covering Latin, Byzantine and
Arab mathematics, and Indian and Chinese
mathematics as well, could be distinguished from
another body of work which came into being
with the Renaissance. I don't feel that this
dichotomy is relevant in either historical or
epistemological terms. Arab mathematics clear¬
ly represents a continuation and outgrowth of
Hellenistic mathematics, which was its breeding-
ground. This is also true of the mathematics
which grew up in the Latin world from the
twelfth century onwards. Finally, the work ac¬
complished in both Arabic and Latin (or Italian)
between the ninth century and the early seven¬
teenth century cannot be split into separate
periods.
On the contrary, all the indications are that
the type of mathematics involved was the same.
This is borne out by the fact that we can now
compare the work on algebra and numerical com¬
putation produced by al-Samaw'al in the twelfth
century with that of Simon Stevin in the six¬
teenth century; al-Farisi's findings in number the¬
ory with those of Descartes; the methods used
by al-Tusi for the numerical resolution of equa¬
tions with that of François Viète in the sixteenth
century or al-Tusi's search for maxima with
that of Fermât; al-Khazin's work on integral
Diophantine analysis in the tenth century with
that of Bachet de Meziriac in the seventeenth cen¬
tury, and so on. If we were to disregard the work
of al-Khwarizmi, Abu Kamil, al-Karaji and others,
how could we understand the work of Leonardo
of Pisa and the other Italian mathematicians in
the twelfth and thirteenth centuries, or the
mathematics of the seventeenth century?
True, the later seventeenth century was
marked by the emergence of new methods and
new areas of mathematical interest in Europe.
However, that break did not necessarily occur all
of a sudden, nor did it take place at the same time
in every discipline. Moreover, the dividing lines
seldom coincide with the works of different
authors, but often cut right across them. In num¬
ber theory, for example, the innovation did not
lie in Descartes' and Fermat's use of algebraic
methods, as has been claimed, since they simply
rediscovered al-Farisi's findings. The break can
actually be identified within Fermat's own work
around 1640, with his invention of the "infinite
descent" method and his study of certain quad¬
ratic forms.
It was really from the mid-seventeenth cen¬
tury onwards that the tangled threads come
together and the main breaks in continuity are
identifiable. The contribution made by the Arab
mathematicians thus fitted into a coherent pat¬
tern which grew up between the ninth century
and the first half of the seventeenth century.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
FROM THE MIDDLE AGES TO THE ENLIGHTENMENT
The roots of modern maths
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
BY CATHERINE GOLDSTEIN AND JEREMY GRAY
'-J* beazLDc *yLr*£ir
oy
Icrrmiu tTtlfT cxcud . al«.T Ttnd
JL HE mathematics teaching offered by the Eu¬
ropean universities around the time when they
were founded in the late twelfth and early thir¬
teenth centuries, was largely inherited from the
traditions of classical Antiquity. At Paris, Oxford
and Bologna, the curriculum covered the quad-
rivium of arithmetic, geometry, music and as¬
tronomy. However as the study of divinity,
leading to the elucidation of the basic Christian
texts, was considered to be of more importance,
the arts faculties, which ran mathematics courses,
enjoyed much less prestige than the faculties of
law, medicine and above all theology.
The content of maths courses was rudimen¬
tary, consisting of the elementary principles of
arithmetic and the first books of Euclid's treatise
on geometry, the Elements. Principles of motion
were also studied in the works of Aristotle, and
at Oxford and Paris, mathematical methods were
beginning to be applied to the study of natural
phenomena. The fourteenth-century French
bishop and economist Nicole Oresme, for exam¬
ple, attempted to make a graphical representation
of variations in speed in a given period of time
in certain types of movement.
Measuring the land
and charting the heavens
In the late Middle Ages, mathematics was being
used by two distinct groups of people, in some
cases graduates of the same universities: on the
one hand there were tradesmen such as surveyors,
engineers and accountants, and on the other there
were physicians and astrologers, who had a higher
social status.
Economic change in the fourteenth century,
the development of the towns and of trade,
favoured the rise of mathematicians in society.
The increasing complexity of trade called for
specialized calculating and accounting skills.
Mathematicians gave consultations in "abacus
shops", where they drafted contracts and calcu¬
lations in layman's terms, and resolved banking
problems concerning interest rates, the exchange,
circulation and value of currency, and the distri¬
bution of profits.
In order to make a decent living, these trades¬
men had to prove their worth against their com¬
petitors and convince their employers or clients
that their skills and know-how were useful. Their
mastery of the algebraic techniques borrowed
from the Arab world was one reason for their
professional success.
At first, algebra was not formulated as it is
today, by using symbols to express relationships
between numbers. It served instead to classify the
L Académie des sciences et des beaux-arts,
an engraving by Gottfried Stein (1687-1747)
after a painting by Sébastien Le Clerc. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
possible relationships between unknown values
and to describe general methods of determining
them. These methods were usually set out in
treatises as practical examples. The adoption of
a system of decimal notation in Europe was both
part of and a great incentive to the advancement
of mathematics. Texts packed with approxima¬
tions of roots and complex fractions proliferat¬
ed, their publication facilitated by the advent of
printing.
Thus the growth of mathematics as a skilled
profession, whose prestige was linked to that of
its chief clients, the merchants, was a corollary
of changing economic and social priorities.
New perspectives
Not only the financial world was in a state of up¬
heaval. A number of practical inventions, such
as the compass and binoculars, appeared in the
West towards the end of the Middle Ages, and
descriptions of measuring instruments and how
they worked were sometimes published with
texts on algebra. The voyages of discovery, in fact
all commercial sea traffic, popularized the use of
the astrolabe and the quadrant. Part practical, part
theoretical treatises on perspective were written
by artists, cartographers and architects, associat¬
ed with what is now known as geometrical op¬
tics. There was no hard and fast division between
mathematical theorists and practitioners.
The late fifteenth century saw the rise of the
Humanist movement, which concentrated on the
study and dissemination of the texts of classical
Antiquity. At first the movement did not really
favour mathematical methods. If Humanist
scholars in the late fifteenth century showed any
interest in arithmetic, it was because of their
study of Plato or of Pythagoras, but on the whole
they despised arithmetical calculation.
Intellectual life, of which the Reformation
was one of the most spectacular manifestations,
was more concerned with the study of texts than
contact with craftsmen. Humanist scholars
produced a new batch of translations of key
works of Antiquity, from Arabic, then directly
from Greek. In going back to the Greek geome¬
ters, they were responsible for a revival of interest
in mathematics.
The mathematical heritage of Antiquity
flourished because it did not fall on barren soil.
European rulers increasingly sought the services
of scientists, such as the astronomers Tycho Bra-
he and Johannes Kepler who were attached to the
court of Rudolf II in Prague, not only to cast their
horoscopes but to construct fortifications or
resolve ballistic problems as interest grew in the
application of mathematical skills to warfare.
Mathematics began to find a place in the largely
Humanist education of the aristocracy, and some
military engineers were even ennobled as a re¬
ward for their services. The growing interest in
mathematics in the sixteenth century is typified
in the works of such men as John Dee, the En¬
glish alchemist and astrologer who wrote the
preface to the first English translation of Euclid;
Gerolamo Cardano, the Italian physician and as¬
trologer whose book on the "Great Art" is one
of the cornerstones of the history of algebra; or
François Viète, the French jurist who specializecf
in cryptography and introduced the first sys¬
tematic algebraic notation.
The indifference, bordering on hostility,
which was felt towards applied mathematics be¬
gan to weaken with the backing of certain
reformers of the education system, such as the
French philosopher Pierre de la Ramée (Petrus
Ramus) who dedicated his teaching chair at the
College Royal in Paris to mathematics and its
practical applications. One of his disciples, the
Dutch astronomer and mathematician Willebrord
1 he Banker and his Wife
by Quentin Metsys (1455-1530).
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Snell, was active in the introduction of universi¬
ty mathematics courses in Holland, aided by the
foundation of a military engineering school at
Leiden. Mathematics, geography and hydraulics
competed with and then gradually replaced as¬
trology in European universities.
The rise of the academies
The rediscovery of the works of Greek mathema¬
ticians was at its most intense in the early seven¬
teenth century. While translations and reissues
were still widely available, many attempts to
reconstruct lost or corrupt texts show how
widespread mathematical culture was becoming.
Mathematics gained in prestige through such
events as Galileo's discovery of the satellites of
M-^ÍT
46
The Pythagorean quadrivium
The writings of Plato (and of Isocrates) tell us of
the generally accepted organization of the mathe¬
matical sciences that was current during the
Hellenistic era. In the medieval educational system
it was called the Pythagorean quadrivium. It con¬
sisted of arithmetic, geometry, astronomy and
music. Astronomy could mean either elementary
notions about the rising and setting of stars, the
calendar and the seasons, or more elaborate mathe¬
matical notions concerning the real and apparent
movements of the Sun, the Moon and the planets.
The strictly mathematical aspects were sometimes
called Spherics, owing to hypotheses concerning the
spherical shape of the Earth and the cosmos that
were current from the fifth century BC. Similarly,
music in this context signified the theory of musical
intervals, in particular the numerical determination
of consonant intervals. It was also known as canon-
ics. It seems that this system existed from the fifth
century BCperhaps indeed linked to the
Pythagorean school in the context first of
"higher", then of "secondary" education.
Bernard Vitrac
Jupiter, which he named Sidera Medicea in
honour of the Medicis, whose family emblem was
Jupiter. Galileo believed that mathematics was the
key to understanding the language of the
universe: "The Book of Nature is written in
mathematical characters... the triangles, the cir¬
cles and the other geometric figures without
which it is not humanly possible to understand
a single word," he wrote.
Scientific academies modelled on earlier
Italian societies also began to appear in Europe.
Some of them, such as the Academia dei Lincei
to which Galileo belonged, were founded by pa¬
trons of the arts and sciences; others were autono¬
mous groups of scholars who met to exchange
new books, scientific and literary news, to watch
a dissection or to observe the stars.
Printed books and journals, especially scien¬
tific ones, were still few and far between, so these
academies made a considerable contribution to
the dissemination of knowledge. One of the best-
known groups met regularly with the Abbé
Marin Mersenne in Paris and attracted such emi¬
nent scientists as Blaise Pascal, René Descartes,
Pierre de Fermât, Gilles Personne de Roberval
and Gerard Desargues.
Brought up on the great classical authors,
these mathematicians were close to the Humanist
tradition. But they were also the heirs of the
tradesmen-mathematicians, as shown by the im¬
portance attached in their work to algebraic tech¬
niques. Some of them were the sons of merchants
who had grown wealthy and bought patents of
nobility.
Seventeenth-century mathematicians no
longer depended on patrons, nor did they live on
their earnings from writing or even from teach¬
ing. They combined their calling with that of
parliamentary adviser, monk, diplomat or soldier.
Formerly, masters of the art of mathematics
could boost their income by defending their repu¬
tation in public. To best an adversary on a mathe¬
matical problem would bring in clients. Although
mathematicians still offered their interlocutors
tricky problems to which only they knew the an¬
swers, this seemed to be more of a demonstra¬
tion of skill or a way of encouraging others to
study the subject. Following the lead of Descanes,
these men drew a clear line between "geometry",
based on reasoning alone, and "mechanics", ap¬
plicable to the practical demands of craftsmen.
Their geometry did not necessarily resemble
that practised by the Greeks, however. Descartes
and Fermât turned it into an analytical science.
The correspondence and treatises of these men
are packed with references to investigations of
tangents and curves, calculations of surface area,
estimations of probability in games of chance,
problems of whole numbers. They were also
interested in optics, in fact in all natural
phenomenanow held to be governed by mathe-
« I Tí S
In this wood engraving of
1503, arithmetic (centre)
seems to be settling the
dispute between "abacists",
the supporters of calculation
using counters, and
"algorists" who used
written notation, in favour
of the latter.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
matical laws. This scientific rigour, a trend which
began at Oxford in the fourteenth century, had
mechanics as its model.
In the mid-seventeenth century, the state
took over from private initiative to support, at
least in part, the development of the sciences. In
1662 a number of academies in England were in¬
corporated by royal charter into the Royal Soci¬
ety of London, and the French Académie des
Sciences, founded by the minister Jean-Baptiste
Colbert in 1666, counted among its early mem¬
bers those who had worked with Mersenne. Peri¬
odicals such as the French Journal des Savants and
the Royal Society's Philosophical Transactions
made the latest scientific discoveries known to
all who were interested.
The second half of the seventeenth century
saw an increase in studies based on analytical
geometry. Other mathematicians' discoveries
relating to methods of calculating area and tan¬
gents were synthesized, independently, by the
English physicist Isaac Newton and the German
philosopher Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz, each of
whom elaborated a different but in each case
coherent theory of differential and integral
calculus. Neither of their theories was wholly
acceptable to their contemporaries and a major
row went on for years over the priority or the
superiority of both contenders.
These developments marked a new phase in
the relationship between mathematics and the
physical world. In his masterpiece Philosophiae
Isaac Newton, very great
head of school but not
pompous" is the title
of this Japanese engraving
attributed to
Hôshû(c. 1890).
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Naturalis Principia Mathematica (The Mathemati¬
cal Principles ofNatural Philosophy) published in
1687, Newton set forth a unified theory of plane¬
tary motion expressed in geometrical terms simi¬
lar to those used in Euclid's Elements. This
theory, on which numerous commentaries were
written in the following century, led to greater
understanding of natural phenomena. In the
1730s, following study of Newton's work, the
French mathematician Alexis Claude Clairaut
specified the periodicity of certain planetary
phenomena, including that of the celebrated Hal¬
ley's Comet (named after the British astronomer
who was the first to calculate its orbit).
The Age of Enlightenment
The "tradition established at the end of the seven¬
teenth century was carried on in the eighteenth.
But while soldiers and diplomats, knights and no¬
bles, continued to show an interest in mathemat¬
ics, they were gradually overshadowed by
professional mathematicians looking for full-time
employment. In some countries, mathematicians
were attached to educational institutions, in
others they belonged to scientific academies or
royal courts. Preference was given to the practi¬
cal applications of mathematics and their contri¬
bution to the advancement of technology and to
human welfare. In France, especially, the Enlight¬
enment encouraged the spread of scientific ideas
that would ensure the "march of progress" and
"free minds from religious prejudice". The
French mathematician and encyclopaedist Jean
Le Rond d'Alembert wrote a number of articles
on mathematics for the Encyclopédie. Men too
circulated, as well as ideas. When the Swiss physi¬
cist Leonhard Euler moved from the Prussian
Academy of Sciences at Berlin to the St. Peters¬
burg Academy, the Italian-French mathematician^
Joseph-Louis Lagrange left Turin to fill Euler's
post at the invitation of Frederick II the Great,
on whose death Lagrange went to the court of
Louis XVI in France.
Even more systematically than in the previ¬
ous century, mathematicians were writing, ex¬
changing theses and problems, and publishing
articles on research in progress as well as finished
treatises. They broadened the scope of the calcu¬
lus and sought to increase its applications. Eul¬
er's Introduction to Infinitesimal Analysis (1748),
was one of a number of didactic works written
by leading mathematicians to make the new ways
of thinking accessible to students. They suggest¬
ed methods of notation and standardized the
problems considered to be of interest. Confidence
was growing in algebra as a tool. Calculus no
longer sought justification in geometry and at last
became an independent discipline.
The rediscovery, assimilation and surpassing
of the Graeco-Arab heritage thus spanned sever¬
al generations of social change and intellectual
liberation. It came about through men whose in¬
terests ranged from new techniques of drainage
or construction, to cosmogony and methods of
calculating area.
CATHERINE
GOLDSTEIN, French
mathematician, is a
researcher with the
National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS).
Her research is mainly
concerned with the theory
of elliptical curves and the
history of the theory of
number in the 17th
century. She was a
contributor to Eléments
d'histoire des sciences
(Bordas publishers, Paris,
1989), prepared under the
direction of Michel Serres.
JEREMY GRAY,
of the United Kingdom,
teaches mathematics at
Britain's Open University.
He has published several
works on the history of
modern maths, including
Ideas of Space (Oxford
University Press, 2nd ed.,
1989) and recently co-edited
(with John Fauvel) an
anthology entitled The
History of Mathematics and
the Reader (MacMillan,
London, 1987).
48
1 he solar system according
to Galileo is shown in this
anonymous 16th-century
engraving.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAIT
GABRIELA MISTRAL
POET AND HUMANIST
JL HE life of Gabriela Mistral, who was
born on 7 April 1889 in a village in north¬
ern Chile and died in New York in 1957,
was devoted to an intellectual and spiri¬
tual quest. From her early days in Chile's
Elqui valley to her European travels on
cultural and diplomatic assignments, the
story of her career reads almost like a
myth. The needy peasant girl becomes
the doyenne of Latin-American literature.
The humble rural schoolteacher is award¬
ed some of the world's highest honours,
including the Nobel Prize for Literature
in 1945.
Gabriela Mistral's poetry, from her
1922 collection Desolación ("Desolation")
to Lagar ("The Wine Press") of 1954, was
written in harsh, powerful and colloquial
language. Like her massive output of
prose, it is informed by a visionary,
prophetic sense of the destiny of Latin
America. But readers in Europe and
countries as culturally diverse as Israel,
China and Japan, also found a meaning
in the humanism and poetry of her work.
In many books, theses, poetic and
philosophical reflections, it is possible to
trace the influence of this Latin-American
writer from a country which, within a
mere half century, produced three writers
of world stature: Gabriela Mistral,
Vicente Huidobro and Pablo Neruda.
Why has Gabriela Mistral's work had
a universal impact? As in the case of all
true creative artists, attachment to her
own familiar world did not exclude a
strong feeling for other languages and cul¬
tures. She acknowledged her debt not
only to Saint Theresa and to the Spanish
poet Luis de Góngora y Argote but to
Dante, Rabindranath Tagore, and the
great Russian writers, and, Christian
though she was, to the great sages of
Buddhism.
Closely identified with her country
and with her people ("I am and will
remain," she said, "a daughter of my
land"), Gabriela Mistral described her
personal experience with a voice which
all humanity could recognize, drawing
from a tragic love affair a song of love and
tenderness which speaks to people every¬
where. In her sympathy for the down¬
trodden and her readiness to defend their
cause, poetry and humanism become one:
"We must give expression to the soul in
all its intensity, and boldly utter the mes¬
sage which springs from the heart before
it ceases to beat."
The above text has been adapted from an article by
Mr. Gastón Von Dem Bussche, professor at the
Metropolitan University of Chile. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE AND SOCIETY
An Academy of Sciences for the Third World
sCIENCE has been described as the
highest expression of international¬
ism, the common preserve of the
"haves" and the "have-nots". Yet its
diffusion has been dramatically un¬
even. While science in the industrially
developed nations of the North goes
from strength to strength, in the
South scientists are relatively few.
They work in isolation from the world
scientific community and the
resources at their disposal are scanty.
In the last few years a new insti¬
tution, the Third World Academy of
Sciences (TWAS), has emerged as a
leading contributor to efforts to
bridge the science gap between
North and South. The Academy,
which is based in Trieste, Italy, is the
first international forum to unite men
and women of science from the Third
World with the aim of promoting
basic and applied sciences in develop¬
ing countries.
The Academy is the brainchild of
Nobel Laureate Abdus Salam of
Pakistan, who has devoted more than
forty years of his life to helping scien¬
tists from impoverished developing
countries overcome their isolation
and participate in advanced scientif¬
ic work at the frontiers of knowledge.
The headquarters of TWAS are
in Trieste, Italy, on the premises of the
International Centre for Theoretical
Physics (ICTP), which is celebrating its
twenty-fifth annniversary this year
and which Professor Salam was also
BY AKHTAR MAHMUD FARUQUI
instrumental in founding and has
headed since its inception.
First mooted by Professor Salam
in 1 98 1 , the Academy was officially
launched in July 1985 by the Secre¬
tary General of the United Nations,
Mr. Javier Perez de Cuellar.
In the four years since it was
founded, the Academy has floated
and implemented a variety of
schemes to bolster South science. It
has awarded some 300 research
grants to scientists working in a
broad spectrum of fields including
optics, nuclear physics, solar energy,
seismology and laser physics. Appli¬
cants, whose projects are vetted by
four international referees, have been
drawn from many countries-
Jamaica, China, Argentina, India,
Brazil, Pakistan, Mexico, Angola,
Peru, Thailand, Turkey and Madagas¬
car, to name just a few.
Through a donation programme
run in collaboration with ICTP, the
Academy also provides scientific liter¬
ature to developing countries facing
shortages of foreign currency. A joint
appeal to libraries, publishing com
panies, laboratories and individuals to
donate books, journals and equip¬
ment to developing countries has met
with an encouraging response. Un¬
der the programme, some 50,000
books and journals are being supplied
annually to some 500 institutions in
90 countries.
One important TWAS project is
a South-South Fellowship Programme
designed to enable a scientist from
one developing country to work in
another. So far 1 25 of these Fellow¬
ships have been awarded. The Acade¬
my also supports visits by Third World
scientists to biology, chemistry and
geology laboratories in Italy.
In 1987 the Academy instituted
a History of Science Prize to highlight
the work of a scientist from a Third
World country whose achievements
had not been previously recognized.
The first prize was awarded in 1 988
for an essay on the astronomical ta¬
bles which were compiled by the
great mathematician Shams al-Din al-
Khalili and used in Damascus for
timekeeping from the fourteenth
century to the nineteenth. The com¬
petition, which is open to scholars of
any nationality, carries a cash prize of
$10,000.
TWAS has also awarded annual
prizes of $10,000 to outstanding
scientists from Third World countries
in the fields of physics, chemistry,
mathematics and biology, and or¬
ganized conferences on major
problems confronting the Third
World. A Conference on the Role of
Women in the Development of
Science and Technology in the Third
World, held in October 1988 in
Trieste, was attended by 240 wom¬
en scientists from over 70 countries.
A non-governmental, non-profit-
making organization, TWAS is cur¬
rently funded largely by Canada and
Italy. Its members, ten of whom are
Nobel Laureates of Third World ori¬
gin, consist of 106 Fellows from 42
developing countries, 42 Associate
Fellows (scientists from industrialized
countries who were either born in de¬
veloping countries or have distin¬
guished themselves in Third World
science) and 3 Corresponding
Fellows.
In late 1988, only three years
after its creation, Ronald Léger of the
Canadian International Development
Agency commented that TWAS had
already brought significant changes
to many Third World scientists work¬
ing in isolation. "For them," Léger
pointed out, "TWAS has meant spare
parts for a lab, or travel grants and
South-South exchanges for young
scientists, or a subscription to a scien¬
tific journal for an isolated scientist.
Above all, TWAS has meant a new
hope for science and technology in
developing countries."
AKHTAR MAHMUD FARUQUI ¡s editor of the
Newsletter of the Third World Academy of
Sciences.
PHOTO CREDITS
50
Cover, page 3: J. Blaud © Artothek, Munich/Bayer. Staatsgemäldesamlungcn i. Germ. Nationalmuseum, Nurcnbcrg. Back cover: H. Jürgens, H.-O. Pcitgcn, D. Saupe (Universität Bremen) © Tlx
Beauty of Fractals, H.-O. Pcitgcn, P. Richter, Springer Verlag, Heidelberg, 1986. Page 2: © Nathalie Gyatso, Montfort I'Amaury, France. Pages 3, 6 (inset), 9 (inset): Unesco/Michel Claude.
Pages 5, 9: Unesco/Belmenouar. Page 10: © Pedro Tzontemoc. Page 12: Erich Lessing, Kunst und Kulturarchiv © Länderpress, Düsseldorf. Pages 12-13: Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris.
Page 14: Taken from Eléments d'histoire des sciences, general editor Michel Serres, Bordas publishers, Paris, 1989. © Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Archives Photeb. Paris/Louvre Museum.
Pages 14-15, 44-45: © Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Louvre Museum, Paris. Pages 16, 27: AU rights reserved. Page 17: © Trustees of the British Museum, London. Page 18: Wellcome
Institute Library, London. Page 19: Scheldeggcr © Rapho, Paris. Page 20: © Roger Viollet. Musée Guimet, Paris. Page 21: © Roland and Sabrina Michaud, Paris. Pages 22-23: © Vivian
Bastian-Olmi, Switzerland. Pages 22-23, 25 (below), 26: © Commissariat General for International Co-operation of the Flemish Community, Brussels. Pages 24, 25 (above), 28: Taken from
Science and Cn-dizatim in China by Joseph Needham, vol. 3 © Cambridge University Press, UK. Page 29: © J.-L. Charmet, Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. Pages 30, 31: © J.-L. Charmet,
Paris. Pages 32-33: © Städtische Galcrie-Licbighaus, Frankfurt am Main. Pages 34-35: © The Mariners' Museum, Newport News, Virginia, USA. Pages 36-37, 39, 40: Roland and Sabrina
Michaud © Rapho, Paris. Pages 38, 41: © Roshdi Rashcd, Bourg-la-Reine, Paris. Pages 42-43: © Graphik Sammlung ETH, Zürich. Pages 44, 46, 48: © Viollet Collection, Paris. Pages
46-47: © Albert I Royal Library, Brussels, Special Reserve. Page 47 (right): © Stillman Drake, Institute for the History and Philosophy of Science and Technology, Ibronto. Page 48: © Roger
Viollet, Paris. Page 49: © Unations. Page 50: © Third World Academy of Sciences, Trieste.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Published monthly ¡n 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue Francois Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Sahgat Finad'
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcorr.D
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Aiain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel 45 68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette R;ngelstein {Tel : 45 6846 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68 47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Public relations: Claudie Duhamel (Tel. :45 68 45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish ana Korean: Marie Dominique Sourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidottt (Rome)
Hindi: Shri Krishna Kumar Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra lígazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitn Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bengali: Ahmed Hedayet (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88), Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité,
Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo,
Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Mot reff (45 68 45 64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68.45 66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (Tel.: 45.68.45.80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26.51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Micheiet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted rnay be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an Internationa; reply coupon
covenng postage Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published m the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is
produced m microform (microfilm and/or microfiche} by: (1) Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Micnigan 48100. U SA , (3) N C R Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc , 111 West 40th Street, New York. USA, (4) Bell and
Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road, Wooster. Ohio 44691. USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) DEPOT LEGAL . CI NOVEM8RE 1989
Photocomposition The Unesco Courier
Photogravure impression Maury Imprimeur S A , Z I route d'Etampes.
45330 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 1 1 . 1989 - OPI 89 1 474 A
This issue comprises 54 pages and a 4 page advertising insert
between pages 10-1 1 and 42 43
A new binder
for the
new-look
Courier
We offer readers an attractive new binder which
has been specially designed for the new-format
Unesco Courier. Each binder holds 12 issues of
the magazine and costs only 68 French francs.
Why not order today by sending
your cheque or money order made out to
Unesco to the following address:
The Unesco Courier - Subscription department,
31 rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
