<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="084413eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
DECEMBI
15 Frene!
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
v
We invite readers to
send us photographs to
be considered for
publication in this
feature. Your photo
should show a painting,
a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any
other subject which
seems to be an example
of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could
send us pictures of two
works from different
cultural backgrounds in
which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add
a short caption to all
photographs.
Idole gardienne de
la réminiscence
1986, oil on canvas
(53 x 94 cm)
by Irène Dacunha
"My paintings are not
nostalgic evocations of
faraway things," says the
Swiss artist Irène
Dacunha, "but the trace
of my relationship with
my own environment, a
pragmatic society which
is losing its spirituality."
Her work, which draws
inspiration from a variety
of artistic traditions,
attempts to restore to the
humdrum modern world
a sense of myth and
mystery.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
DECEMBER 1989
CONTENTS
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to you, its readers. Each
month contributors of
different nationalities provide
from different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect
for the dignity of man
everywhere.
9
HIGH DAYS
AND HOLIDAYS
THE FESTIVE SPIRIT
by Jean Duvignaud
MOCK LION AND REAL HEROES
by Mamadou Seek
SKELETONS AT THE FEAST
by Javier Pérez Siller 19
THE PAVILION
OF THE SECOND MOON
by Laurence Caillet 24
FAREWELL TO WINTER
by Hélène Yvert-Jalu 32
SAMBA TIME!
by Sergio Alves Teixeira
LIBERTY, EQUALITY, FESTIVITY!
by Laurence Coudart
4
Interview with
NAJIB MAHFOUZ
...true artists can accept
outside influences which
help them to achieve
self-expression...
w3.
" 47
PORTRAIT
17 FATHER DAMIEN,
CITIZEN OF THE WORLD
48
LETTERS TO
THE EDITOR
38 Cover:
The Rio de Janeiro Carnival
(Brazil).
	 Back cover:
A carnival musician, Bale
42 (Switzerland).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
with Najib Mahfouz
Najib Mahfouz, of Egypt, is widely
considered to be the greatest living
writer in Arabic. Born in Cairo
in 1912, he was awarded
the Nobel Prize for Literature
in 1988 for his lifetime's output
of novels, short stories and plays.
Here he reflects on the Egyptian
cultural identity and more generally
on the impact on creative artists
of influences from outside
their own culture.
In the course ofits long history, Egypt has faced many chal¬
lenges stemming from its encounters with other cultures-
Greek, Roman, Byzantine, Arab, and Turkish. Since Bona¬
parte's expedition and especially since the British occupa¬
tion, Egypt has been at grips with the modern Western
world. This latest influence seems to be more profound and
significant than all those that preceded it. How has the
Egyptian identity emergedfrom this encounter? Has it been
weakened, strengthened, or transformed?
cultural encounter with the West was not a new
experience for Egypt nor for the Arab world. As you have
rightly pointed out, before the flowering of Islamic culture,
Egypt had been exposed to far-reaching influences from the
cultures of India, Persia, Greece and the Mediterranean
seaboard, not to mention that of ancient Egypt. All these
encounters with other worlds were rewarding and enriched
our traditional identity and classical culture. They added
vigour to our living organism rather than impoverishing it
or inhibiting its development.
There has been a fresh encounter with the West over
the past two centuries. In some respects this contact has been
negative. But if we look carefully at the results as a whole,
the positive features can be said to have outshone the rest.
Look what happened with literature. Western ideas and
writings were imported and we accepted them. Thanks to
them, we have created new and specifically Egyptian forms
of the novel, the short story and the essay. Naturally, our
narrative style has its origins deep in the Arab past, but we
can say that its roots have been renewed and given a fresh
lease of life by the currents of thought emanating from
Europe. Those currents have become so integrated into our
environment and culture that they can no longer be distin¬
guished from them. They have become so acclimatized that
they appear to have been here for ever.
...true artists can accept outside influences
which help them to achieve self-expression...
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
i
life
;JÊk
«VT-**,..
à*>
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Many developing countries have close contacts with The characters in your writing seem to be moved by a
Western civilization. Because ofthisproximity some intellec- passion which tirelessly follows them through the old
tuals in these countries adopt attitudes that are even more quarters ofCairo. You invest them with a tremendous love
European than those of the Europeans themselves. So of life, yet at the same time they possess great serenity,
they produce works which are mere imitations ofEuropean Through them, wefeel that you are perfectly at peace with
models. Are Egyptian intellectuals susceptible to such yourself and, moreover, overcome with gratitude...
temptations? true. I have always given thanks for the almost
have passed through a number of stages in this respect, sacred privilege I have been granted of being able to "iden-
the first of which was the translation of European works tify" the human beings of this city which I know and love
into our language. The second stage was the adaptation of so well. Once those lives which go on around me enter my
those works and their integration into our environment, field of vision, they become characters, in other words they
in other words the "Egyptianization" of an alien cultural become creatures of my own flesh and blood. My gratitude
product. The third stage is that of maturity, when a writer's becomes a creative act.
own personality attains its full self-expression.
We have been strongly influenced by Europe, as Your novel Midaq Alley* is bathed in a religious
you say, and there have been imitators. But imitation is not atmosphere. Is this a reflection of your personal universe
art, nor is it a sign of cultural maturity. To my mind, true or one aspect of the reality that inspires you?
artists can accept outside influences which can be assimilât- "atmosphere" features in several of my works, but
ed in order to better express the truth that they bear within it is not a literary device nor a denominational choice: it
themselves. I suppose something similar to this occurred in is part of the reality I am describing and which is most often
both North and South America, for example. At the out- set in the old quarters of Cairo. An artist, to my mind, has
set, the old world may perhaps have been imitated, but later to depict that reality without distorting it. Without going
a specific literature was created which has in its turn in for fanaticism or ideological commitment and without
influenced European writers. In short, following a cultural speaking out in favour of one belief or another,
shock, external models may be copied at first, but it is
important to go beyond this stage and find richer outlets In view of the current growth of technology and the des-
for the expression of one's creativity. tructive purposes for which it is sometimes used, and of the
threat to nature all over the planet, what values are left?
Let us look at a cultural movement which followed a Do you think that religion can offer a response to these
different path. A number ofwriters in Arabic emerged in challenges and limit the risks of dehumanization?
the Americas early this century. They formed part of the -The progress made by science and technology has not
wave of immigration to the New World that took place always been negative. It has been of immense service to
from 1910, and they were known as the Mahjar (emigration mankind. Of course there are some destructive aspects, but
or exodus) writers. Did this emerging Arab literary I think that this process of dehumanization can be fought
movement have any influence in its turn on the Arab with the aid of two great forces: religion and art. Through
world? these forces it is possible to turn scientific progress to hu-
It had a considerable influence! It contributed to the man advantage. But I insist on the fact that there is no need
renewal of Arabic language and literature. I followed with to be afraid of scientific progress; science and technology
admiration the progress of the Mahjar writers, especially the are capable of correcting their own mistakes. One example
poets, and they left a profound impression on me. The fact can be seen in current efforts to produce non-pollutant ener-
that they were writing far from our own land did not gy. Progress cannot be stopped, but we must not surrender
diminish the great attraction they had for us. Their litera- to panic. I am optimistic that science, guided by a sense of
ture, born on another continent, has a very special flavour awareness, can constantly adjust its trajectory. Art and
and resonance that we greatly appreciate in the Arab world, religion are there to lighten the way.
Their works reflect the milieu in which they lived, they are
permeated by the landscapes and societies of the New World. interview by the Argentine writer and philosopher victor
To a great extent, they are at heart "American" writers. Massuh, a former Chairman of Unesco's Executive Board.
Through them, the Americas acquired a certain presence in	
my OWn WOrk and, generally Speaking, marked the recent * English translations of the works of Najib Mahfouz include Midaq Alley
i i i r 1 i f 1 n -n (Heinemann Educational Books, London, 1976) and Respected Sir
cultural renewal ol the Middle hastern countries. (Quartet Books, London, i986).
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
m reasons
for offering
oäsco
WS»««» ..
subscription
Courier
It ¡s the only international cultural magazine
published in 35 languages and read by
hundreds of thousands of people in 120
countries
Each month it explores the astonishing
diversity of world culture and knowledge
Hi
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission
of furthering "universal respect for justice,
for the rule of law and for human rights and
fundamental freedoms...without distinction
of race, sex, language or religion..."
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
LL societies, past and present, seem to have had their feasts and festivals,
their high days and holidays when people could abandon themselves to the spirit
of the occasion and momentarily forget the trials and tribulations of their daily
lives. Today however it is often said that some spark, some element of mystery
that enlivened the festivals known to our ancestors seems to be dying out.
The world's festivals form a variegated tapestry in which many different threads
are woven: ritual and spontaneity, tradition and licence, the sacred and the
profane, rich and poor, individual solitude and collective warmth. They have
always been occasions when differences could be reconciled, if only temporarily.
At once chaotic and planned, they were times when the usual rhythms were
periodically disrupted and the group rediscovered the secret of the origiAof
the world. The need for order triumphed over disorder.
It is understandable that feasts and festivals should perform such functions in
rural societies with a strong sense of community spirit, societies where life is
punctuated by the unchanging cycle of the seasons and human lawsreem
implacably to reproduce a cosmic design. But how do they fit into life in modern
cities where the individual is a lone face in an anonymous crowd, discovers that
there is a difference between the laws of nature and the laws of society, and has
to assume responsibility for his ovv^fciestiny and that of his communfl^?
While the religious meaning of many traditional festivities is fading, functions
with mass appeal such as popular music festivals and sporting events are
proliferating, and private conviviality seems to be as widespread as ever.
Festive occasions thus respond to a need which is universal but not easy to define.
Do they perform the same function in the modern world as they did in traditional
c Ä , societies? What values are celebrated today by the colourful events which, as
owirling aggfers at tm «flfc
Rio camWal, 1989. the following pages show, are still going strong?
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
'
a/
-
«
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Feasts and festivals as a
cornerstone of community life
The festive spirit
BY JEAN DUVIGNAUD
V»
taLKS
HAT is the significance of feasts and fes¬
tivals? Are they celebrations hallowed by custom,
or curious pieces of folklore? Only after the
meeting and confrontation of different cultures
was it possible to grasp the originality and authen¬
ticity of each. Likewise, it was historians, ethnol¬
ogists and psychologists studying other countries
than their own who saw that festivals are acts of
self-expression, manifestations of a dynamism
constantly renewed, and even in some cases the
reflection of Utopian yearnings.
The French sociologist Emile Durkheim,
writing at the beginning of the century, saw feasts
and festivals as an "effervescence" the intensity
of which cements the solidarity of a group or a
people, a representation of the invisible relation¬
ships between man and the laws of nature, a
veritable institution whereby the bonds between
the members of a society are maintained, regener¬
ated and reproduced.
Writing around the same time, but in a to¬
tally different context, Sir James Frazer, the
author of The Golden Bough, saw feasts and fes¬
tivals as acts which reproduce the great systems
of beliefs and mythologies. From these major
celebrations emerged religion, magic and politics.
Similar statements are found in the work of other
anthropologists such as Boas (on the Eskimos),
Frobenius and Griaule (on the Africans), and
Malinowski (on the Melanesians).
A bonfire to celebrate the feast of St. John in the
Marne département of France.
The meaning of feasts and festivals may ac¬
tually be as problematic to those who take part
in their rituals as to outside observers. But rather
than attempting to find a common denominator
between such manifestations, let us try to draw
up a brief catalogue of them.
Some festivals consecrate a milestone in life-
birth, initiation, marriage, burial. Such events are
collective acts whereby a society responds to the
insurmountable constraints of naturesex,
deathand tries to deliver men and women from
their individual fears.
Thus community participation in sexual
union through the marriage feast follows a pat¬
tern which varies little in different parts of the
world. In marriage ceremonies at Douz in
southern Tunisia, for example, families camp on
the side of a dune during the night. The
bridegrooms wait in a tent for their future wives
to arrive, riding on dromedaries accompanied by
a singing and dancing throng. On their arrival,
the whole group springs to life, seized by an ir¬
resistible impulse to take part. In Nepal, this time
in broad daylight, the community is also present
at the bride's preparations for marriage, and
responds with the same magical fervour. Euro¬
pean and American marriage celebrations still
perform a similar function, in highly schematic
form, although the participants may not even
realize it.
The expression "rite of passage" is an inade¬
quate description of such events. In Casamance,
for example, south of the Sahara, the passage of 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
a corpse on a stretcher adorned with the horns
of an ox generates an excitement which provides
the living with a way of socializing death.
Brazilian children in a suburb of Salvador laugh
and sing as they follow the coffin of one of their
friends. In Mexico, the Feast of the Dead trans¬
forms the macabre apparatus of funerals into
farce, as if seeking to abolish the anguish caused
by the inevitability of death.
Another type of festival, which could be
described as "restorative", spectacularly revives
the memory of a vanished past or culture. One
example is the Bolivian Diablada at which Indian
miners and craftsmen dress up as figures from the
ancient Inca empire and confront a triumphant
St. George in a symbolic struggle. Another is the
Rocío, the curious Andalusian festival of the
Virgin of the Marshes, in which Arab, Christian
and Gypsy allegories overlap. A celebration on
the beach at Yemanja in northeastern Brazil is
a mirage in mime and dance of a distant Africa
of which the sea is the location and the symbol.
The participant sects abandon themselves to
dancing and trance before leaping into the water
which formed them.
Festivals based on ritual are of a different
order. Their repetition of a liturgy gives them a
dramatic dimension and aesthetic grandeur. In¬
donesia's wayang shadow puppet drama, which
so fascinated Antonin Artaud, belongs to this
category, as does India's Kathakali dance drama,
mass bathing in the sacred river Ganges, and,
more generally, all the celebrations which Budd¬
hism has inspired in Asia. European history con¬
tains a number of accounts of the manifestations
of Roman Catholic mysticism in Italy and Spain.
Something of their spirit has survived in the great
festival held on the cathedral forecourt at Guada¬
lupe, near Mexico City, when Indians and mes¬
tizos reconstitute for a day the union once
concluded between the Virgin and one of their
number, a slave.
Urban festivals such as the processions of an¬
cient Athens, Chinese imperial ceremonies,
"royal entries" into European cities of the Renais¬
sance, the wedding of the doge of Venice and the
sea, and the Lord Mayor's Show in London have
tended to be more highly orchestrated. Traces of
such traditions survive today in the Palio of Siena
and the carnivals of Venice, Bale, Munich and
Flanders.
Other, more serious urban festivals are the
anniversary celebrations organized by all régimes
and all nations to commemorate symbolically the
pact or contract made between a people and a
founder, or the event which led to the formation
of the state. Festivities with a didactic intent, such
as France's National Festival on 14 July and
International Labour Day on 1 May are organized
to provide a seal of political legitimacy.
Even a brief catalogue of festivities would be
incomplete without an evocation of private con¬
viviality. Many kinds of small-scale celebrations
are held purely for the sake of entertainment,
shared enjoyment or for the simple satisfaction
of being together. Communal meals, the agape
("love feasts") of the ancient Greeks, banquets
in town and country, brotherhoods, initiatory
groups, gatherings for dancing and music, inti¬
mate or Utopian celebrationsminiature festivals
of this kind are found in all civilizations and are
flourishing thanks to video and other modern
facilities.
The participants in these often deeply felt
common experiences accept no other ritual than
that which they have chosen themselves. Such oc¬
casions, on which community feeling is expressed
even more intensely than in larger-scale events,
are deeply woven into the fabric of regional or
national life.
A claim on existence
The form and meaning of all these festivals vary
between different cultures and religions and are
influenced by fashion and technology, but each
one, whatever its scale, is the vehicle of a tran¬
scendent power to anticipate or to create.
1 he "Gangaur" spring
festival in honour of
Gauri, goddess of
Abundance, in Rajasthan
(India).
KJpposite page, (above)
Samoan dancers, (below)
shamanistic festival in the
Himalayan monastery of
Matho, Ladakh.
JEAN DUVIGNAUD,
of France, teaches at the
University of Paris VII,
where he is director of the
laboratory of the sociology
of knowledge and the
imagination. He is the
author of several works on
feasts and festivals, notably
Le Don du rien. Essai
d'anthropologie de la fête
("The Gift of Nothingness.
Essay on the Anthropology
of the Festival"; Paris, 1977)
and Fêtes et Civilisations
("Festivals and
Civilizations"; Paris, 1984).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
we) ^:>'s
_- . - - - *
When the Indians of the North American
plains draw the great circle of the world and the
Sun, their action cannot be seen as a mere thea¬
trical representation of magical or religious
beliefs. Those who take part in this ritual are
absorbed in an operation of far wider scope, one
that unites their bodies, the cosmos, a common
perception of life, almost a lust for life. This is
metaphysics in action. So-called "tradition" or
"authenticity" is not at all a passive state but a
claim made on existence.
The Africans deported to the "New World"
as slaves revived Yoruba rites in northeastern
Brazil. The drumbeats and frenzied gestures of
the Candomblé and the Macumba conjure up
a trance which brings back the lost homeland.
However repressed these rites were in the past,
however distorted they may appear in some
places, they helped the slaves to maintain their
human estate in the face of servitude and poverty.
The French ethnologist Roger Caillois wrote
of the "hurly burly" which turns established hie¬
rarchies upside down at festival-time. Georges
Bataille believed that feasts have a force which
leads to the transgression of established rules. In
this respect the Paris Commune of 1871 was a
festival, and so was May 1968 in Paris. These
events called in question everyday customs, and
called for a "new deal" in man's relations with man.
Of course these were ephemeral moments,
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
but their turmoil was a breeding ground for new
attitudes and new desires. Without feasts and fes¬
tivals, would not the human species be reduced
to the state of the beehive or the ant-hill?
Decadence or renewal?
What has become of all these festivals in McLu-
han's global village? What is the outcome of the
confrontations between these celebrations which
were hitherto separated by history, politics, cul¬
ture or distance? Is it true, as some regretfully be¬
lieve, that a process of "planetary banalization"
is underway? Is the audience ruining the show?
For a festival is a show. It needs a public. I
am not thinking here of the pitiful and more or
less faked scenarios rigged up for tourist consump¬
tion. I am thinking of those who are not con¬
sumers of folklore, of the innocent eye of the
African watching an Indian festival on television
or the response of an Amerindian villager who
sees a European carnival for the first time.
Such spectators will feel encouraged, invited
to join in themselves, to accept if they have the
chance, the festive delirium of the Brazilian
"Bumba meu boi" or the collective excitement
of an evening around a marabout shrine in
Morocco. The Aborigines of Australia have made
the choice to present themselves through the me¬
dia to foreign audiences. They have shown the
same desire for recognition as the people of an
Italian village in the Val de Lunigiana who once
came to Paris to stage a single performance of a
local festival.
Does the televising of festivals and their
production before foreign audiences indicate that
they are in decline? This is the belief of purists
who would like to stop the clock and confine fes¬
tive elation to a scenario that never changes, or,
more cunningly perhaps, turn it into a piece of
marketable folklore. And yet, contrariwise, the
ANTICLOCKWISE
FROM LEFT:
1 he Venice carnival
1 raditional Inca feast
to mark the summer
solstice at Cuzco, Peru.
Jtiehind the scenes at
a performance of wayang,
the Javanese shadow
puppet drama.
A funeral rite in
Casamance, Senegal.
\jypsy pilgrimage to the
shrine of the "Virgin of the
Marshes" in Andalusia,
Spain.
global village which has made us all contem¬
poraries seems to encourage the invention of new
forms. Who would complain if the festival were
to become an art form?
The threat which has caused festivals to dis¬
appear from industrial societies has come about
through the development of what Lewis Mum-
ford called megalopolis, of urban and suburban
agglomerations which are not communities but
vast, amorphous concentrations of people. In the
last hundred years or so, what continent has es¬
caped this proliferating centralism?
Where then can festivals be celebrated
without provoking hostility or indignation?
Proliferating slums, streets and squares jammed
with traffic, people living packed together in tow¬
er blocks, alienation within big organizations
which discourages day-to-day contactall these
factors are hostile to the festive spirit.
Religion, ideology and sport attract crowds
to events which sometimes assume the allure of
festivities. But such mass celebrations are short¬
lived. The hypermarkets of the megacities are also
skilled at exploiting the tawdry aspects of the
festive spirit to lull their customers into spending
freely a travesty of joyful and sumptuary con¬
sumption.
Will the story of feasts and festivals end in
these distortions of the festive spirit? Does what
the architect Paul Virilio has called the "censoring
city" present the ultimate barrier to that intense
communion, to that frenzied awakening of
awareness of others, to that perception of the
world and the future through which, as the
French sociologist Marcel Mauss said, "the social
body is truly realized"?
Surely not. Feasts and festivals, with all their
unexpected, transient, gratuitous and spontane¬
ous aspects are a motor of community life. From
them man draws on the exquisite pleasure of what
André Breton called the "limitless infinite". 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Mock lion
from Senegal, a ligbthearted traditional
game with serious undertones
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
and real heroes
BY MAMADOU SECK
IN Africa collective celebrations have always
been held to strengthen community spirit and
group solidarity, as well as to break the
monotony of everyday life. Most of these popular
festivals have a significance which goes back to
very early times.
Some festivals, like Senegal's bao-naan, a ritual
dance calling for rain in drought-stricken times,
pay tribute to a divinity and appeal for his good
offices. Others celebrate the birth of a child, an
abundant harvest or some other happy event.
Festive occasions such as light-hearted wrestling
matches between champions from different
villages simply offer an opportunity for displays
of strength and agility. But all the festivals up¬
hold threatened values such as generosity, a sense
of honour and dignity, and courage in the face
of adversity, and although during them things
sometimes seem to take a violent turn, univer¬
sally accepted rules are always respected.
All these features are combined in the game
of the mock lion, known in Senegal as Simb. I
saw this game when I was young, and my
memory of it is still undimmed.
The whole district was in festive mood. A
dense and colourfully dressed crowd jostled
around the platform of honour on which the
notables had taken their places. The oldest people
had brought makeshift seats since they could not
stand up for long. Each spectator flourished on
his forearm a piece of cotton thread studded with
knots died red with cola. This thread, which was
sold by teenage volunteers, was the entrance
ticket to the show and afforded protection against
the lion's fury. Woe betide those who had no
piece of thread!
All around tom-toms were beating time while
women danced. The nearby streets pulsated with
activity. Vendors of water, soft drinks and coco¬
nuts pushed their way through the crowd. On
each side of the main street, lines of headscarves
and loincloths fluttered in the wind. Beneath
them were teenage girls wearing their finest
boubóus, and decked out with jewels sparkling in
the sun. No one was allowed to cross these lines
without paying a kind of forfeit, the lo-lambé.1
The smallest coin conferred the right to put one's
hand on the intimate parts of the women who
were taking the money. No one took offence.
That was how it had always been.
The Game of Simb (1989),
by the Senegalese artist Ousseynou Sarr. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Six o'clock in the evening. Suddenly there
was an indescribable commotion, punctuated
with wild applause. Preceded by an imposing
escort, the mock lion entered the arena. He was
unrecognizable as a man. He wore a wig with a
mane attached to it. His face was covered with
black soot, his eyes adorned with ochre powder.
Everything about him gave the impression of a
wild beast, of the king of the forest, symbol of
strength and courage. From time to time he
opened his mouth wide and slobbered a whitish
liquid. Then he began to roar, looking nastily at
the crowd. His legs were ringed with jangling
amulets and knickknacks. He was a fearful sight.
Feigning panic, a lion-tamer hurled himself
before the "lion", brandished a long piece of
cotton thread and loudly recited an incantatory
prayer: "Daar Ndé Gaînde Ndiaye. Daru mala
Yala la dar. Ku Yala dar nga daru."2 Seemingly
hypnotized by these words, the beast crouched
down and pretended to sleep. During this brief
moment of respite, the crowd applauded raptu¬
rously, not forgetting in their excitement to bran¬
dish their protective threads to extinguish the
man-animal's murderous intentions.
This was the moment when a group of bare-
chested youths rashly pulled the piece of cloth
which served as the mock lion's tail. Some threw
stones at him or chewed and snapped old bones.
In unison the spectators sang out the ritual war¬
ning cry: "Det! Way det! Gaînde bagne na Kuy
dam yax."3 Then the lion roared louder than
ever and set off in hot pursuit of those who had
provoked him. There was pandemonium as the
animal engaged in a flurry of biting and boubou-
ripping. He knocked one spectator down. The
tamer ran along behind, reciting prayers to get
the victims out of their predicament. What mad¬
ness! What a release!
Suddenly the mock lion changed direction
and advanced rapidly towards the platform of
honour, sowing panic among the tiny tots hiding
beneath their parents' clothes. He went up to a
special guest, who wondered for an instant whe¬
ther this could really be happening to him, and
discreetly pulled a handkerchief from his pocket
to wipe away a bead of sweat. Everyone was
shouting. The man-animal fixed his eyes on ano¬
ther guest, whose lips began to tremblethe poor
man had no cotton thread. An irresistible oppor¬
tunity! The "wild animal" leapt on the guilty
spectator like an eagle on its prey, pinned him
to the ground with a smart blow from a paw, and
then let fly with his fists. By the time the tamer
had managed to cool the lion's ardour by utte¬
ring incantatory prayers which were drowned in
the general hullaballoo, the poor victim was lying
on the ground, his face covered with blood. He
was taken away after someone had lent him a cot¬
ton thread. The festival went on at full tilt until
sunset.
That night everyone had something to talk
about. The mock lion was a hero. He had dis¬
played energy and perseverance in pursuing and
punishing those who had disobeyed the law of
the community. The teenagers who had shown
their mettle by provoking the wild beast and then
standing up to him were heroes too. Their appe¬
tites for excitement satisfied, people went to sleep
thinking of the children of the forest, past and
present, who had stood their ground before the
king of animals. In an afternoon of festivity, man
had rediscovered his pride.
1. A Wolof word meaning: "How much do you touch with?"
or more precisely: "How much do you give to have the right
to touch?"
2. "It is not I who tame you, but Allah. When He tames you,
you must obey." (Wolof)
3. From the Wolof: "No, no, the lion hates it when people
break a bone!".
18
. *
Oimb the mock lion,
Dakar.
MAMADOU SECK,
of Senegal, has been director
of the Unesco Press since
1984. He was founder-director
of the Senegalese publishing
house Nouvelles Editions
Africaines, which he headed
for ten years, and is the
author of a novel entitled
Cicatrices pour demain ("Scars
cor Tomorrow"; L'Harmattan
publishers, Paris, 1989).
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Jtff Skeletons at the feast
BY JAVIER PEREZ SILLER
A unique blend ofpre-Columbian
and Hispanic myths, Mexico's Feast
of the Dead brings together past
and present, devotion and mockery,
the commercial and the spiritual
IN October in the Mexican countryside, the
crows flock in their thousands to peck at the fresh
corncobs. The agricultural year has ended and it
is time for the people to gather in the fruits of
their labour and celebrate the fertility of the
earth. It is also time to prepare for the Feast of
the Dead.
This is the most important and popular of
all Mexican fiestas. On 1 and 2 November (All
Saints' Day and All Souls' Day), signs of the
coming festivities appear in the city streets. Imi¬
tation skeletons are stationed in shop-windows,
advertising a variety of products. Bakers sell the
traditional "bread of the dead", decorated with
*t4&
\:jÊ*Êt*ajSSfc*idfàSU
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
«7^
shinbones made of flour and eggs. Market stalls
are set up to sell toys, sweets and all sorts of
delicacies whose shapes evoke death.
Newspapers publish supplements containing
calaveras (death's-heads), illustrated verses in
which well-known public figures are shown dead
or in the great beyond. Continuing a tradition
which dates back to the end of the nineteenth
century, these verses with their musical cadences
usually lampoon politicians or comment on
current events and problems.
Children take part in the festivities. They run
through the streets asking adults for money "for
my death's-head" and show people objects they
have made. Some of them carry elaborately deco¬
rated cardboard coffins from which dancing skele¬
tons jump out, while others pierce holes in gourds
to make eyes, nose and a big toothy mouth, and
then light a candle inside them. Some even invent
stories about creatures beyond the grave, or
disguise themselves in cadaverous masks and go
out into the streets to frighten the wits out of un¬
suspecting people. In the elegant districts of large
cities it is common to find children and young
people celebrating Hallowe'en in American
stylea variation of the Celtic feast which origi¬
nated in Ireland. These carousers are the most
dangerous, for if they do not get what they want,
they bombard homes and shops with bags of
flour.
A bewildering range of toys are evocative
20
1%
\
Left, skull ofpolished
rock crystal
(15th 16th century).
Jtiight, the owl on this
pasteboard skull represents
wisdom.
Opposite page, the
macabre confectionery that
children love includes sugar
skulls with names
emblazoned across their
foreheads.
PRECEDING PAGE
An Aztec myth on the
cycle of life and death is
enacted to the sound of a
conch shell.
of death. They include calacas, wire and clay
skeletons which jump and dance; skulls that grin
when their jawbones are manipulated; jolly horse¬
men mounted on the skeletons of horses, and au¬
tomats which at the turn of a handle bring to life
the skeletons of acrobats, boxers, or tilicas
trembling, spineless joke skeletons. Many young
men buy one of these puppets for their
sweethearts. Others prefer to give sweets which
confectioners make specially for the occasion-
usually sugar or chocolate skulls with the be¬
loved's name written across the forehead.
The fiesta also gives rise to a variety of cul¬
tural activities. In the big cities people go to ex¬
hibitions on death in the pre-Columbian world
or to the theatre to enjoy the Calaveras de Posadas
or the traditional play Don Juan Tenorio by the
Spanish Romantic author José Zorrilla. On. the
night of 2 November wooden or cardboard
puppet-skeletons bearing topical captions are dis¬
played as part of a calavera competition held at
Mixquic, a township near Mexico City.
As well as festivities in the city streets and
competitions organized in the villages, there are
popular dances and fairs at which people eat their
fill, enjoy themselves, get drunk and defy death
because "life is worthless". The festivities can take
a violent and sometimes tragic turn when old
quarrels flare up amid the shouting and the fumes
of alcohol, and one or two of the living brutally
join the dead.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The combination of festivity and commerce
in the streets is the backdrop to more intimate
celebrations of the cult of the dead. During the
two days of the fiesta, people prepare to welcome
their dead, to honour their memory and perform
again the rites and ceremonies they learned in
their families. These rites vary according to the
traditions and social status of each family, but
they all feed the collective imagination by giving
shape to the mosaic of elements that make up the
"Mexican personality".
Such rites are performed in the privacy of the
home and the sacred atmosphere of the cemetery.
In elegant modern cemeteries, people bearing
flowers pay their respects at the graves of their
loved ones. But these moments of sadness and
nostalgia do not prevent them from joining in
the festivities in the street later at night.
Things are very different in the countryside,
where the festivities and rites are more
deeply rooted in the past and more closely
associated with the celebration of fertility. In this
the country people are perpetuating a blend of
several religions and in some very remote areas
they even recreate pre-Columbian traditions and
beliefs. Even so most of their rites are basically
Christian.
Visits from the dead
The principle is always the same: the living are
going to be visited by the dead, and preparations
are made to receive them. On 1 November,
known as the day of the Angelitos (little angels),
the souls of children and young people "troop
smilingly through the cornfields, as if they had
just been let out of school". They stay in the
houses for twenty-four hours and leave on 2
November when the adults arrive. During these
two days, doors are left open and families are
under the obligation to welcome all visitors and
friends, since "the souls like to arrive and find
a fiesta going on".
Imagine for a moment that we are watching
this ceremony in a small Mexican township...
A tightly packed crowd of women of all ages
surges through the cobbled streets. Some of them
are carrying their babies swaddled in black rebo¬
zos (shawls) on their backs. The men go on ahead,
accompanying the orchestra and singing tuneless¬
ly, while children amuse themselves by running
from one end of the procession to the other.
When they arrive at the cemetery, the people
spread out among the tombs, which are decorated
with wreathes of yellow cempasuchil (marigolds).
Dozens of lighted candles encircle the graves. The
whole scene is illuminated in a shining cloud in
which the scent of resin is mixed with the
fragrance of incense and flowers.
W Wl w* .f ^ 4* n
rfMiaftlf'
t* 0 1 * «I
jmfcr "| * ¿Um' ~
l * vi 1
^Ê^^^m. ffl^ ^ y _^^^^^^|
**S"^J 1
Er^l^^^^KpP
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
'
I , V
*sftr
fe-
<<v
!
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
K^emetery on the island of
Janitzio, in Mexico's
Michoacán state.
JAVIER PEREZ SILLER,
Mexican sociologist and
historian, is a member of
the faculty of political
science at the National
Autonomous University of
Mexico. He contributed to
a study on festivals of death
published by Association
d'Idées, Paris, 1988.
At midnight, the church bells peal out,
announcing the arrival of the dead. At the same
moment rockets are fired and the orchestra starts
to play. There is widespread rejoicing and every¬
body joins in a hymn of welcome to the dead.
The living and the dead then go together
from the cemetery to the houses. In order to
ensure that the souls do not lose their way, the
path is marked out with flower petals from the
threshold to the heart of the dwelling. In its fur¬
thest recesses, framed by an arch of cempasuchil,
is an altar complete with an offering of everything
the deceased needs to recover from the journey:
a glass of water, succulent dishes including mole
(spiced meat), chocolates, atole (a cornmeal gruel
drink), "bread of the dead", alcoholic drinks such
as brandy, tequila, mezcal or pulque, cigars, a
pack of playing cards, and sweetmeats made of
pumpkin and sweet potato. There is even the
fragrant smell of incense and candles which burn
all night and cast their light on images of the
saints and photographs of the departed.
In the darkest corners of the room, the old
grandmother sits whispering. "Souls of my
ancestors, are you satisfied with what we have
done for you today? My sons have worked
hard this year and we have been well rewarded.
The harvest was abundant and the corncobs
are fat. Thank you for your help, for without
you the offering would have been small. How
is St. Joseph? Did he receive the masses I said
for him?"
People are said to be able to detect the
moment when the souls approach, since "the
flames of the candles flicker violently" and, once
the deceased have eaten, "the food no longer has
any taste". The family then asks the dead to stay
longer and eat and drink together "as in the good
old days".
The revival of Indian myths
The word "fiesta" is used to describe a wide range
of rites and celebrations which have sprung from
ancient Mexican culture and that of the Spaniards.
The myths evoked all set out to answer the same
questions, where we come from and where we
are going.
For the pre-Hispanic peoples, death had a
fleeting and ritual meaning. Life and death were
regarded as merely two sides of the same coin.
The dead carry on living in another plane of real¬
ity from where, with the help of the gods, they
will be reborn. Thus say the myths of the cycle
of the five Suns and that of Quetzalcoatl, who
dared defy the Aztec god of the dead and seek
the bones with which he had to create human
life from Mictlan, the underworld. At the same
time man is responsible for conferring life on 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
the gods themselves and for the renewal of the
cosmos. Once created, man becomes a creator.
From 1521 onwards, when the Spaniards
conquered Mesoamerica, this mythology was
combated by a kind of spiritual colonization as
the Catholic Church sought to replace "pagan"
rites and myths with its own. The new myths
claimed that man was created to worship God
and that his fate after death depended on whether
he had performed that task and on whether his
behaviour had conformed to the moral tenets dic¬
tated by the Church. In short, judgement was
passed on his acts.
While the descendants of the Europeans
adopted Christianity, a syncretic religion emerged
among the mestizos and the Indians. It was based
on the two sets of myths under the patronage of
such awe-inspiring images as that of the Virgin
of Guadalupe, Queen of Mexico and Empress of
America. But the Indian customs were banned
and remained hidden from prying eyes.
In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries the
situation changed radically, and Indian myths
began to be revived. With independence, the
search for a national identity or "Mexicanity" led
intellectuals to extol the Indian past. With the
separation of Church and state, religious burials
were not allowed and the administration of
cemeteries passed into the hands of the govern¬
ment, weakening the Church's control over
burial rites. After the Mexican Revolution
(1900-1917), the Indian was regarded as a "nation¬
al asset" and attempts were made to revive Indian
myths. As a result, the government now partici¬
pates in the promotion of the Feast of the Dead.
The Feast's vitality was dramatically demon¬
strated in 1985. Some weeks before it was due to
take place, a violent earthquake destroyed part
of Mexico City and took a heavy toll of lives.
In the afternoon of 2 November, thousands of
people paraded through the city centre laying
offerings of flowers before the ruins of the tall
buildings which had been turned into tombs. Car¬
rying lighted candles, they arrived two abreast in
Zócalo square and, as if they were re-enacting the
Náhuatl cosmic myth, divided the square into
four parts. One group tendered an offering to the
Cathedral, which is on the site of the old Aztec
temple, while the rest held up placards of protest.
As well as an act of protest this was a spirited
gesture of mobilization against death, an ac¬
knowledgment of man's weakness before the
forces of nature and of his appeal to a divine
power. It was simultaneously a political, religious
and mythical action, but it turned into a fiesta
that gave expression to man's creative dimension
and to his ability to halt for a brief moment the
24 inexorable march of time.
^ , The Pavilion
BY LAURENCE CAILLET
The Japanese greet the New
Year with a time-honoured
religious ritual inspired
by the myth of the water of youth
X OR many years the West pictured Japan as a
land of geishas and cherry blossom. Today this
once-familiar image has been displaced by that of
a country of contrasts between old and new, a
land of samurai and motorcycles.
It would be wrong, however, to see tradition
and modernity as opposing forces in Japan, a
country which ever since the seventh century has
been a centralized state and where time-honoured
community traditions have actually served to
encourage, not hinder, modernization. The
picturesque and joyful festivals which periodically
strengthened community ties have survived
industrial development and still attract pilgrims
and tourists. And although their purely religious
function has atrophied, they still transmit the
centuries-old syncretic beliefs of Great Vehicle
Buddhism and of Japan's indigenous religion,
Shinto, the Way of the Gods.
Japan's main festive period was and is the
New Year, which under the ancient lunar-solar
calendar was celebrated shortly before spring
ploughing. This was the time of the festival of
the water of youth, a rite which is generally
known as Omizutori (the drawing of water) and
whose observance is traditionally believed
necessary to bring about the return of spring. The
best description of the meaning of Omizutori is
found in a haiku by the poet Riôta (1718-1787):
Drawing of water!
The water of whirlpools warms
From this day also.
Every year since the eighth century the
festival has been celebrated at the Buddhist
LJance of the bodhisattvas
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
of the Second Moon
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
monastery of Tôdaiji, at Nara, an ancient capital
of Japan. Today it takes place in the first and
second weeks of March, at a time corresponding
to the second moon of the old calendar.
In the Pavilion of the Second Moon, a vast
wooden building on the top of a hill to the east
of the monastery, twelve monks meet to honour
Kannon, the bodhisattva of infinite compassion
and mercy. Guided by giant torches whose em¬
bers are collected by the faithful as talismans, they
return to the pavilion fifteen nights in succession.
They walk around the altar, tirelessly intoning
hymns of praise and penitence. From the prayer
room, which is separated from the holy of holies
by a long veil of transparent linen, the pilgrims
can see the outsize shadows of the monks praying
for the peace and prosperity of the world.
On each of the fifteen days of ritual, six serv¬
ices are celebrated at specific moments of the day
and night. Through ten or more hours of incan¬
tation to Kannon, of chanting and ritual kneeling,
the participants seek to expiate sins committed
the previous year and to accumulate merit.
The thousand circumambulations
Almost every night, special ceremonies are held
as part of the penitential rites. According to the
"Illustrated History of the Origins of the Pavilion
of the Second Moon", the oldest manuscript of
which dates from the sixteenth century, a Tôdaiji
monk named Jitchû celebrated the feast of the
drawing of water for the first time in 752. When
he reached the paradise of the bodhisattvas, Jitchû
contemplated their ceremonies and asked how
they could be imitated and performed by men.
The bodhisattvas replied as follows: "A day and
a night here correspond to 400 human years. And
so it is all the more difficult, in the short human
time-span, to perform the rites according to the
rules and to carry out the thousand circumam¬
bulations solemnly, without overlooking any
detail. Furthermore, how could men reproduce
these rites without a Kannon with a living body?"
Jitchû then said: "The ceremony must be speed¬
ed up and the thousand circumambulations per¬
formed at a run.... If I call on him with a sincere
heart, why should a Kannon with a living body
not come?" And he returned to transmit these
rites to men.
Because of the difference between human
time and godly time, the monks run a strange race
around the altar dedicated to Kannon on the last
three days of each of the two weeks of ritual. At
first the monks walk very slowly, rolling up the
sleeves of their robes and their stoles; then they
fasten the lower parts of their garments to their
legs. Meanwhile, the curtain concealing the holy
1 orches illuminate the
Pavilion of the Second
Moon.
Intoning the name of
Kannon to the
accompaniment of the
sistrum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
mum» '¿#1
m
r »»
11
.ûyJ .-
LAURENCE CAILLET,
French ethnologist, is a
researcher with France's
National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS).
Her publications include a
study on the water of youth
ritual in Japan entitled
Syncrétisme au Japon
Omizutori: le rituel de l'eau
de jouvence (Paris, 1981),
and a book on annual
Japanese festivals and rites. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
of holies is lifted so that the crowd of pilgrims
suddenly sees the splendour of the rites and ex¬
periences a joy equal to that felt by Jitchû when
he reached paradise. Bells are loudly rung during
this part of the ceremony.
Suddenly all noise ceases, and in the astonish¬
ing silence that follows, all the monks begin to
run barefoot around the altar. One of them
abruptly leaves the group and rushes into the
antechamber of the prayer room where a woo¬
den board known as the plank of prostration is
fixed parallel to the floor by a kind of spring. He
leaps onto the plank, striking it energetically with
his knee, and then returns to his place. Each time
the monks go around the altar, one of them runs
and strikes the plank with his knee, the part of
the body which symbolizes the forehead, elbow
and knees, with which the worshippers must
touch the ground as a sign of penitence. Eventu¬
ally the pace slackens, the curtain falls, the into¬
nation starts again, and the silhouettes of the
monks are only visible as grey shadows.
On other evenings, the gods themselves come
and dance, disguised as eight monks whose faces
are masked by their hair. The first to arrive is
the water divinity, who skips and runs with tiny
steps and sprinkles the prayer room with lustral
water. Next come the god of fire, who scatters
embers, and the god Keshi, who sprinkles grains
of rice cracked in the fire. Everyone dances and
leaps to the noisy rhythm made by three other
gods with a rattle, a conch shell and a bell. Two
more brandish a sabre and a willow rod to drive
away evil spirits.
The well of the god Onyû
During these nights of dancing the water of youth
is drawn and distributed to the pilgrims. What
is the origin of this ritual? The "Illustrated His¬
tory of the Origins of the Pavilion of the Second
Moon" records how "In the province of Wakasa,
Onyû, a god who possessed the river Onyû, lin¬
gered while out fishing and arrived late at the rites
of the twice seven days and seven nights. Pro¬
foundly regretful, the god said to Jitchû the monk
that as a sign of contrition he would make the
lustral water spring near to the place of the feast,
and at that very moment two cormorants, one
black and the other white, suddenly rose from
the rock and perched on a nearby tree. From the
traces of these birds sprang water of incompara¬
ble sweetness. Stones were laid there and it be¬
came the spring of lustral water, aka-i..."
And so, on the second day of March, the
priests of the sanctuary of Onyû pour into the
river a phial of lustral water which is supposed
to flow through an underground channel and
reach the spring of the Pavilion of the Second
Oil
. :: i! i
*
j
Loi
ir"*
Distributing holy water to
the pilgrims.
Left, the penitential ritual
Moon during the night of the twelfth to the
thirteenth.
On that night, at two o'clock in the morning,
the "master of esoteric rites", wearing a brocade
hat, leaves the pavilion and turns towards the hill
where the miraculous spring is located. With him
is a faithful layman wearing a hermit's white
robe. He is followed by monks bearing magic
rods to which conch shells and bells are fastened.
The conch shells are sounded and then, guided
by a lay torch-bearer, everyone goes down the
steps leading to the spring. At that moment, an
orchestra begins to play ancient Chinese music
and the monks pray for the water to gush out.
Today the spring is concealed beneath a
flimsy building with a grey-tiled roof, the four
corners of which are adorned with birds. Some
think the birds are pigeons, others that they are
messenger cormorants of Onyû, the god of fish¬
ing and sovereign of the waters which according
to Japanese beliefs form a reservoir of longevity,
if not of eternity. He is also associated with cin¬
nabar, the essential component of the elixir of im¬
mortality which the Taoists of China and Japan
tried to concoct in ancient times.
Only the hermit and the master of the eso¬
teric rites enter the building which covers the
spring. The water, carried three times in buckets
to the Pavilion of the Second Moon, is poured
into a wide tub of light-coloured wood which is
immediately covered with a white cloth and
offered to Kannon. From that day on it is dis¬
tributed to the thousands of pilgrims who flock
to receive in the palms of their hands a few drops
of this extraordinary liquid which encourages lon¬
gevity and is a panacea for all ills.
In spite of its extreme solemnity, this rite is
not very different from that with which peasant 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
¿m
WÊ
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Left, the shadow ofa monk falls
on the altar curtain.
i\ight, the plank ofprostration.
Oelow right, rice cake offerings to Kannon.
families welcome the spring. On the eve of the
first day of spring, the master of the house, his
eldest son or a specially chosen servant rises while
it is still dark. He dons a traditional kimono and
bows before the altar of the household gods after
sprinkling himself with a few drops of purifying
water. Then he puts on new straw sandals and
goes to the nearest spring. Beside the spring or
on the lip of the well, he offers the water-god rice
cakes and, while reciting a magic formula, draws
with a new ladle and bucket the first water of the
year.
Without speaking to the people he meets on
his way, he returns home and places the freshly
drawn water on the household altars. Then he
awakens the members of the family and each one
drinks tea brewed with this water of youth which
as far as possible compensates for the aging caused
by the New Year. According to tradition, peo¬
ple become a year older at New Year, not on
their birthday.
The origin of this marvellous water is
described in the following story from the
southern island of Miyako: "Once, long ago,
when men settled on the beautiful island of
Miyako, the Sun and Moon wished to give them
an elixir of immortality and sent them Akariya-
zagama, a young servant with red hair and a red
face. On the night that marked the changing of
the season, Akariyazagama came down to Earth
with two buckets, one of which contained the
water of immortality and the other the water of
mortality. The Moon and the Sun had ordered
him to bathe men with the water of immortality
and to bathe the snake with the water of death.
As Akariyazagama, tired after his long journey,
put down the buckets beside the road and uri¬
nated, a great snake appeared and bathed in the
water of immortality. Weeping, Akariyazagama
had men take a bath of death and then returned
to heaven. When he described how he had carried
out his mission, the Sun was furious and said to
him: 'Your offence against men is irreparable...'
"Since then, the snake is reborn when it sheds
its skin, whereas men die. However, the gods
took pity on men and wished to enable them, if
not to live for ever, at least to grow somewhat
younger. And so each year, on the night before
the day of the feast of the new season, they send
from heaven the water of youth. That is why
even now, at dawn on the day of the feast of the
first season, water of youth is drawn from the
well and all the family bathes in it."
The water of youth which rises at the foot
of the Pavilion of the Second Moon, like that
which bubbles up in family wells, thus comes
from the other world. It is carried by waves from
the distant land of the gods, the land of Tokoyo,
a world both sombre and luminous, a land of
abundance and immortality, but also the resting
place of the dead on the other side of the sea.
Penitence and the absorption of holy water
are two facets of a single hopeless desire to ob¬
literate the wear and tear of time and establish
in the world of men something of the eternity
which is the prerogative of the gods. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
Farewell
to winter
BY HÉLÈNE YVERT-JALU
JL HE Russian carnival, Maslenitsa, whose origins
are lost in the mists of time, is still celebrated with
undiminished vigour. The celebrations include a
number of ancient customs, such as the eating of
blini (pancakes), tobogganing and sleigh rides. To
these have now been added a host of other
diversions, such as ski races, skating competitions
and dancing and singing to the accompaniment
of accordions and balalaikas, which make the
"Farewell to the Russian Winter", as it is
commonly called today, more of an entertain¬
ment than a rite. Even though " certain ancient
rites are from time to time resurrected, the deeper
meaning of such traditional practices is being
gradually lost.
The name Maslenitsa is derived from the
Russian word maslo, meaning "butter". During
the week preceding the six-week period of Lent
that leads up to Easter, the eating of meat was
forbidden by the Church and so people ate dairy
products, fish, eggs and blini maslenye, pancakes
to which melted butter was added to make them
more creamy.
The word Maslenitsa signifies both the
carnival itself and the grotesque doll-figure that
personifies it. In Moscow, by the eighteenth
century, the symbolic aspects of the carnival had
already been lost, but they survived in the
countryside and in some villages carnival was still
being celebrated in its traditional form at the
beginning of the twentieth century.
The festivities began with the welcome of the
Maslenitsa, a doll made of straw and rags, usually
in the likeness of a woman. It was dressed in a
The evergreen popularity
of the traditional
Russian carnival to
welcome the spring
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
} S; V»
» *
ê > ám
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
JtSlini ready for the feast
tarewell to winter as the
Maslenitsa burns...
blouse and a sleeveless peasant's smock and a scarf
was knotted on its head. Sometimes it was
attached to a wheel at the top of a long pole,
sometimes the role of Maslenitsa was actually
played by a person. It was then paraded through
the village, accompanied, on foot or on sleighs,
by a noisy crowd of villagers who gave vent to
their joy with shouts and bursts of laughter and
by dancing and declaiming poems of welcome:
The worthy Maslenitsa, generous boyar,
Has come to descend our snowy slopes,
To feast on blini
And to abandon herself
To wholehearted enjoyment.
Then the Maslenitsa was placed on a mound
or other high point where it remained until the
end of the week.
It is sinful not to drink
to the Maslenitsa
The welcome ceremony triggered off a variety
of entertainments. These ranged from horse races,
pitched battles between unarmed men and attacks
by horsemen on the defenders of forts made of
snow, to swings and seesaws. Above all there was
tobogganing, which was very popular with the
young men and women since it gave them an
opportunity to get better acquainted with their
wives or husbands to be. Young married couples
would shoot down the slopes together in full view
of the whole village with the wife sitting on her
husband's knees. By popular demand, a couple
had to kiss before and after making a descent.
Sometimes a young couple would be buried
together for a brief moment in the snow.
The richer families would begin preparing
their blini on the Monday, the poorer ones on
the Thursday or Friday. The women would make
the batter in accordance with a given ritual. At
moonrise some would add snow to the mixture;
others, acting with the utmost secrecy, would set
to work at night at the river's edge when the stars
came out. In some districts, the first pancake to
be cooked was placed on the window-sill for the
souls of the departed. In other areas, it was given
to beggars so that they could commemorate the
dead. Pancakes, served very hot with sour cream,
herrings and caviare, were lavished on relatives,
friends and acquaintances. The laws of hospitality
required open house to be kept throughout the
carnival. People ate and drank their fill and more,
as if sating themselves so as to get through the
long period of Lenten abstinence. As the popular
saying went: "It is sinful not to drink to the
Maslenitsa."
It was also customary for a young wife's
mother to invite her new son-in-law to a meal
of blini liberally washed down, a custom which
gave rise to countless charming songs. The young
married couple would come bearing presents and
might stay for two or three days. Sometimes, to
welcome them, a Maslenitsa figure would be
attached to the roof gable.
On the Thursday or Friday, tobogganing
would give way to sleigh rides. Young couples,
and particularly newly-weds, would parade
around their village before setting off for neigh¬
bouring villages or even the nearest town, all
anxious to show themselves off in their finest
equipage and their richest attire. The horses'
manes would be decorated with ribbons and
paper flowers, the sleighs would be covered with
rugs and the curved wooden cross-piece that 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
\ v
-y * * "ai,
5
#a*
y :. /
x '--y*:-: m
.#'-. ràfL '
-'Wa». iL yif*' w\
Til l!S
IFiP>'' Iy " 11
kÄj^lift
' W "tiSPà
aj /' Vy
rather Frost and the Snow
Maiden, two legendary
figures from the Russian
New Year carnival.
HÉLÈNE YVERT-JALU,
of France, is a lecturer at
the University of Paris I.
She is the author of a
number of studies on social
and cultural questions in
the Soviet Union.
36
passed over the horses' withers, freshly-painted
in bright colours, would be hung with sleigh-
bells. The women would leave their cloaks half
open so that their fur linings could be admired.
In short, elegance was all.
On the last Sunday of carnival, known as
Pardon Sunday, the villagers would take their
leave of Maslenitsa, the farewells being made in
the same noisy bustle as the welcome a week earli¬
er. Once more the straw doll-figure would be
installed on a sleigh, but this time the procession
accompanying it took on the air of a burlesque
funeral. A broken-down nag, rigged out in a pair
of torn trousers, pulled a dilapidated sleigh
covered with threadbare matting. The driver, a
village elder dressed in rags, his face blackened
with soot, would indulge in all kinds of buffoo¬
nery, some of which, in other circumstances,
would have been considered to go beyond the
bounds of decency.
Sometimes a small boat or a feeding-trough,
both of which were associated with ancient bu¬
rial rites, were placed on the sleigh. At the head
of the procession walked a man or a woman
dressed up as a priest and holding an old shoe
dangling from a piece of string and representing
a censer. Wearing grotesque masks, the priest's
assistants intoned parodies of religious chants.
Arriving at the edge of the village, the proces¬
sion would halt in a freshly-sown field to "kill"
the Maslenitsa. In some ceremonies, the Maslenit¬
sa would be stripped of its clothing, torn apart
and cut up into hundreds of little pieces which
were then buried in the snow. In other cases it
would be drowned in a river or burned on a huge
funeral pyre of straw, wood and a heap of old
rubbish collected, or in some districts stolen, for
this purpose by the young people of the village.
This ceremony, the high point of the car¬
nival, also signalled the end of the festivities. On
Sunday evening the sound of rejoicing was
hushed as if by magic. This was the moment of
Pardon. The villagers would ask each other's
forgiveness for any wrongs they might have done
one another and then embrace as a sign of
reconciliation. At the cemetery, the dead too
were asked for forgiveness and blini were placed
on their graves.
On "Holy Monday", the first day of Lent,
houses were given a thorough cleaning, after
which the villagers would go to the bania (the
bath-house) to bathe themselves. This was the
beginning of a period of spiritual and physical
purification following the excesses of the festival.
A holy time
What is the significance of the Maslenitsa rites?
Those who accept the approach of the mytho¬
logical school, whose ideas were fashionable in
the middle of the nineteenth century, see the
festival as an echo of the ancient Slav cult of the
Sun. It was a celebration of the Sun-King and the
interment of winter. The pancakes, whose round
shape recalled the shape of the sun, were intended
to ensure its return. The bonfires, generally lit
on high ground, were intended to unite earth and
heaven and thus to speed the coming of warmer
days.
Rimsky-Korsakov took this theme as the
basis of his opera Snegurochka (Snow Maiden,
1
I
n L.\'!
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
1881). The death of his heroine at the end of the
opera made possible the return of Yarilo/Sun to
shine again in the kingdom of Berendei and for
spring to come again.
For those who favour the theory of borrow¬
ings, which dates from the end of the last century,
the Maslenitsa derives from Greek-influenced
Roman rites that may have been transmitted to
the Slavs by minstrels from Byzantium.
Othersamong them most Russian
specialistsbelieve that, like other popular
festivals, the carnival is based on pre-Christian,
Slav agricultural cults and that the festivities were
intended to ensure good crops. The earth, which
is seen as female, is induced to become produc¬
tive by means of magical procedures, the most
important being the invocation of the dead and
the rites of preparation and of fecundation. Blini
are offered to the dead so that they will tend the
seeds and seedlings that have been placed in the
bowels of the earth, where the dead dwell. Erotic
activities were also seen as a method of making
the earth fertile. Drawing a parallel between
human fecundity and the fertility of the earth,
they attributed magical powers to sexuality;
hence the attention paid to young couples during
the festival. Hence also the wearing of masks
which facilitated licentious behaviour. Finally,
the fertilizing power of the ear of corn,
represented by the straw of which the doll-figure
was made, was transmitted to the earth when the
figure was buried or burned. The magical power
of the laughter that accompanied the "killing"
of the doll-figure was thought to help the earth
become fruitful.
For many historians of religions, however,
the significance of the Russian carnival goes
deeper than this merely agricultural explanation
might suggest. They believe that the Maslenitsa
is important because it belongs to that category
of festivals that proclaim the end of one period
and the beginning of anothera crucial moment'
in any traditional society. Marking the transition
from winter to spring and, in ancient Russia, the
beginning of the New Year, it is a festival of the
recreation of the universeagriculture being only
one aspect of the symbolism of periodic
regeneration.
The cult of the dead, a vestige of the
ceremonies that accompanied the transitional
period between two cycles, forms a link with this
myth of eternal renewal. Seen in this light, the
reversal of values, such as the parody of interment
and the general licentiousness, may represent the
primordial chaos which must be mastered to
make possible the cyclic recommencement of the
order of things. The confession of sins and
Pardon Sunday express the desire for a return to
the purity of this new beginning of primordial
time. Finally, creation is symbolized by that
essential element of the festival, the lighting of
fires.
1 he Winter Carnival
(1916), by the Russian
painter Boris Mikhailovich
Kustodiev (1880-1927).
-^W
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Samba time!
M,
38
LENTION the word "carnival" and every¬
one thinks immediately of Brazil. Two weeks
before the festival begins, all important business
is postponed until after the four frantic days
during which the whole country grinds to a halt
and everyone takes time out to dance. At carnival
time the press, radio and television talk about
nothing else. And when Brazilians travelling
abroad are asked about their country, the subject
of carnival always crops up sooner or later. In
short, it would be impossible to imagine Brazil
without its carnival, an event unique in scope and
in the collective passion it arouses.
Less well known is the increasingly impor¬
tant role played in the carnival by Brazil's samba
schools, the first of which was founded in 1928
at Mangueira, a suburb of Rio de Janeiro. Many
more schools were started, but at that time they
had no direct connection with the carnival.
Products of the poorer quarters with high black
populations, they played no part in the festival,
which took place in the centre of Rio and was
celebrated by the middle class. Poor people who
wanted to take part in the carnival did so virtually
in secret; they were even chased away by the
police when they attempted to sing and dance in
the centre of the city.
The samba, however, soon made itself felt as
a particularly vital form of expression of black
identity, which by then had survived three and
a half centuries of slavery. It spread rapidly to
thefavelas (shanty-towns) in the hills around Rio
de Janeiro. Soon the samba had its own public
parades and then, in 1935, the Rio authorities
gave official standing to the carnival in its popular
form.
The samba schools were given subsidies from
the public purse, ceasing to be informal groups
and developing into organizations which received
monthly subscriptions and had their own
premises, articles of association and elected boards
of directors. A federation of samba schools was
established and only its members could take part
in the parades. The growing interest of the state
in these parades, coupled with general public
demand for exciting spectacles, speeded up this
process of "bureaucratization".
In the 1970s, the schools became full-blown
show-business companies operating permanently
throughout the year. The transient glory of the
parades is the product of a continuous effort of
which the spectators are quite unaware. The time
is long past when the schools thought about the
carnival only a day or two before it began.
Today the schools get far more of their
income from balls and rehearsals (many of which
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
BY SERGIO ALVES TEIXEIRA
\
The story of the
samba schools which
make the Rio
carnival one of the
world's most
colourful and
exciting spectacles
Left, the "Children of
Gandhi" samba school at
the carnival of Salvador de
Bahía, Brazil.
Opposite page, Rio
carnival parades. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
are open to the paying public and attract as many
as 15,000 spectators), from the commercial
exploitation of their cultural product, and from
the patronage of the bankers behind the bicho (a
kind of lottery), than they do from the monthly
subscriptions paid by their members.
The institutionalization of the schools has
also changed the profile of their staff. Most of the
accountants, lawyers and administrators that they
have hired come from a different social back¬
ground from that of their founders and the
schools have had to adapt to their viewpoints.
The largest schools now aim to set themselves up
in modern premises similar to those occupied by
clubs patronized by the middle classes.
Two Brazilian writers, Amaury Jorio and
Hiram Araujo, have memorably described the
exciting moments before the carnival begins.
"The abre-alas, the leading float that symbolizes
the school, is in position. Between it and the
allegorical floats that follow come the dancers.
The carnival committee is busily at work. The
leading figures slowly take up their positions. The
musicians tune their instruments. When the com¬
mand is given, the leading singer, high up on his
float, intones the samba-enredo, the theme of the
samba. In accordance with custom, the entire
school listens as he sings it through once and then
the musicians take up the melody and everyone
starts to sing, repeating the samba two or three
times without moving as they await the arrival
of any latecomers. Then suddenly, as if by mag¬
ic, the whole school moves off. This is the be¬
ginning of the most beautiful spectacle of popular
art in the world. As though out for a stroll, form¬
ing a procession, dancing and singing the samba,
diffusing joy and rapture, the school parades
before us."
The 'sambadrome'
Tiered seating was erected when the spectacle had
developed sufficiently to attract large crowds who
were prepared to pay. to. see it. An area was
blocked off by means of temporary fencing so
that only those who had paid an entry fee could
watch. This roused considerable protest from
those who could not afford to pay.
In 1984, for the first time, the parades took
place in a fixed purpose-built locationthe
"parade causeway", or "sambadrome" as it is
popularly known. Thirteen metres wide, 700
metres in length, the sambadrome is located on
the Avenue Marqués de Sapucaí and can accom¬
modate 85,000 spectators. It is the work of
Brazil's most famous architect, Oscar Niemeyer.
The causeway comes into its own on carnival
Sunday and Monday when, at nightfall, the top-
ranking samba schools parade for an hour and
a half each.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
An explosion of colour,
Rio 1989.
SERGIO ALVES
TEIXEIRA
is a Brazilian anthropologist
who teaches at the Federal
University of Rio Grande
do Sul, Porto Alegre. His
publications include studies
of rites of passage,
cockfighting, and the
significance of feasts and
festivals.
Everything is strictly regulatedthe marking
system followed by the jury, the parade time
allotted to each school, the minimum number of
participants, the dimensions of the allegorical
floats, the theme of the samba, the individual and
collective figures that are to illustrate it, and the
order of presentation of the items.
Today, each school organizes its parade
around a theme of its own choice, but this was
not always the case. Freedom of choice was the
rule at the beginning, but, from 1939 until the
end of the 1960s, successive dictators imposed
themes illustrating the history of the nation.
Then, in response to pressure from an increas¬
ingly demanding public, the schools recovered
their freedom of choice.
Samba themes dominate not only the parades
themselves but the entire musical content of the
carnivalat the balls, in the streets, on television,
radio and on records. They have become products
of the culture industry.
Television gives the carnival exceptionally
wide coverage. Not only does it transmit nation¬
wide programmes on the parades staged by Rio's
top samba schools, it also screens regional balls
and parades both locally and nationwide. In 1989,
an estimated 65 million viewers watched these
transmissions.
Another key innovation has been the appear¬
ance of the carnavalesco, the specialist organizer
of parades. He conceives the theme, designs the
effigies and the allegorical characters, sees to it
that the necessary accessories are at hand, selects
the materials to be used, chooses the colours, is
responsible for the overall direction of the spec¬
tacle, rehearses the performers and, more recent¬
ly, even has his say in the wording of the samba
themes.
Many of these carnival experts are intellec¬
tuals who have studied choreography, the arts and
folklore. Under their direction the parades have
become grandiose spectacles, not so much
through the number of performers taking part
(between 3,000 and 4,000) as through the richness
of the colours and the ordered movements and
rhythms they have introduced.
This new sumptuousness has won far from
unanimous approval, and many a purist critic has
called for a return to the original, simple
tradition. Yet, miraculously, the changes have not
extinguished the ardent emotions and joy of the
ordinary samba-lover. All those unknown men
and women, the real driving force behind the
carnival, who are willing to spend up to three-
quarters of their annual salaries just to enjoy these
few days of fantasy, still thrill to the mysterious
vibrations of the carnival. "It is as though I have
entered the gates of heaven. Were I to lose my
balance, I should lie down and weep." 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Mob insurrections often turned
into popular festivals at key
moments in the French Revolution
which were later commemorated
by the state
T:
42
HE French Revolution ushered in an age
which proclaimed itself to be one of liberty,
equality and fraternity. This radical new
departure after centuries of monarchy did not
come about without incident. Between 1789 and
1794, the peopleabove all the people of Paris,
the centre of political powerconstantly took
to, the streets. Full of hope in the future, the
participants in this great upheaval turned it into
a popular festival which lasted for five years
almost without interruption.
The most striking symbol of this great surge
of revolutionary hope is to be found in the many
"trees of liberty" that were planted during these
years. In the countryside, a "maypole", whether
a tree or simply a post, was traditionally planted
on such occasions as weddings and harvest-time
as an emblem of fertility, joy and success. During
the Revolution, it became a symbol of the
destruction of feudalism, then the emblem of
liberty. A popular festival was inconceivable
without a tree of liberty. Each village planted its
own. Adorned with red, white and blue ribbons,
with cockades, flags, red bonnets or the text of
the Declaration of the Rights of Man, the tree
was the centrepiece of the gathering. Beneath its
branches liberty newly won was feted and rounds
were danced. It was held to be sacred. When it
was planted, a solemn ceremony was held which
often ended with farandoles and singing.
Let's dance the Carmagnole!
Long live the cannon's roar!
The songs which had long been used to
accompany popular dances had a special place in
the revolutionary landscape. More than 2,000 of
them have been listed for this period alone. In
a society in which half the adult male population
was illiterate, songs were a powerful vehicle of
revolutionary debate. The streets resounded to
patriotic, civic or satirical lyrics. Wars between
songspatriotic songs versus royalist songs
sometimes broke out. Street singers were
ubiquitous and attracted crowds which joined in
songs that usually featured old and well-known
tunes to which new words had been set.
People sang everywhere and on every possible
La Carmagnole. Anonymous print (1792).
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
a *
Liberty, Equality, Festivity!r
BY LAURENCE COUDART
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
1 he National Guard
accompany the people
on their triumphant return
to Paris from Versailles,
6 October 1789.
Anonymous etching.
1 he fountain of
Regeneration "among
the ruins of the Bastille"
during the festival
of 10 August 1793.
Contemporary engraving
by Isidore-Stanislas
Helman.
44
occasion: in public squares but also in popular
assemblies and meetings, in prisons, theatres, and
even at the tribune of the National Assembly.
Once when a citizen had sung at the bar Danton
inveighed against what he called this "singing
mania". "I have in my nature a good measure of
French gaiety," he cried, "but I demand that from
now on at the bar of this Assembly we should
only hear reason in prose." Everything was good
for a song: public events, swings of opinion, the
decrees of the National Assembly. All the
struggles of the time, internal and external, found
expression in song.
Every popular insurrection was punctuated
with singing. The great revolutionary "days"
sometimes ended with spontaneous festivals, as
on 5 and 6 October 1789, when almost 7,000
angry Parisian women marched on Versailles,
invaded the royal château and won satisfaction
for their demands.
Louis XVI was brought back to Paris amid
a dancing, yelling, laughing crowd. Thousands of
people accompanied the royal coach: "We're
bringing him!" they shouted at the bystanders.
Women seated on cannon, wearing the hats of
grenadiers of the National Guard who had come
to lend a hand, surrounded the king and several
wagons loaded with grain, flour and barrels of
wine. It was a day of rejoicing and fraternization
symbolized by the poplar branches which
protruded from the gun barrels and which some
carried in their hands. It was a day of gaiety, in
spite of the deaths of the bodyguards whose heads
were borne on pikes: woe betide anyone who
dared resist the sovereign people!
The heads were warnings rather than
trophies. "The Parisian," wrote Sébastien Mercier
in his Tableau de Paris, "makes a joke out of these
tumultuous days." It is true that the most
fantastic and outlandish tricks were played amidst
the shouts of a people which, Mercier added,
"wished to repair in one day the painful
repression which it had endured for several
centuries." A vast crowd took to the streets and
mingled with this strange procession, while
certain onlookers were struck dumb at the sight
of the "terrible gaiety" of the "multitude" which
surrounded the monarchthe last absolute king
to rule by divine right as if he were a prisoner.
These popular demonstrations inevitably call
to. mind the traditional carnival. The people
expressed their joy in impromptu dancing and
gesticulation. They treated with derision all that
societythe old societyheld sacred, giving vent
to a vast outpouring of revolutionary feeling. In
spite of the battles, the deaths and the blood, they
danced with mingled gaiety and fury. They
danced to exorcise their fear as they consigned
the past to oblivion.
During the insurrection of 10 August 1792
which inaugurated the Republican era, the Paris
mob sacked the château of the Tuileries, mas¬
sacred the Swiss guards who had fired on the
crowdtheir heads were brandished on pikes
and danced to celebrate its victory over the
monarchy. The Carmagnole, a famous song still
sung today, exalts that day of the "second revo¬
lution". Its refrain, "Let's dance the Carmagnole!
Long live the cannon's roar!", is a good illustra-
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
tion of those hours of joy and violence. Groups
dancing farandoles and rounds were seen again
on 21 January 1793 at the place of execution of
Louis XVI, known as "Louis the last".
The triumph of the goddess
of Reason
The popular festivals which made the strongest
impact on contemporaries were undoubtedly
the dechristianizing masquerades. The promul¬
gation of the Civil Constitution of the Clergy
in 1790 divided the French clergy into those who
agreed to swear an oath of loyalty to the new
Constitution and those who refused after the
Constitution had been condemned by the Pope.
An important section of the clergy gradually took
the side of the counter-revolution and for the
people the Church became an enemy of the new
liberty.
New saints, the "martyrs of liberty" who had
died for the Revolution, replaced the old. The
deputy Lepeletier de Saint-Fargeau, the journalist
Marat (author of the popular newspaper L'Ami
du peuple) and the municipal official Charlier
all three of whom were assassinated in
1793became the focus of popular veneration.
Their busts were displayed at crossroads, in
squares, meeting-places and theatres, and adorned
with flowers"civic crowns". Processions were
organized and hymns composed in their honour.
The names of these republican heroes were even
bestowed on new-born babies.
On 10 November 1793 a great festival in
honour of liberty was held in Notre-Dame
cathedral. An actress from the Opera played the
role of the goddess of Reason. While hymns were
sung, a procession of floats decked out with
flowers, of sans-culottes, children, members of
popular societies and official bodies accompanied
the goddess as she symbolically released a black
slave from his chains at the foot of an artificial
mountain erected outside the cathedral. The
attributes of royalty and religion were burned in
a bonfire around which people danced and drank
to fraternity until dawn. After this festival, Notre-
Dame became the Temple of Reason. The cult
of Reason soon spread throughout provincial
France, and the churches were secularized.
Such was the setting of the wave of dechris-
tianization which took place during the first six
months of the Year II of the Republic (autumn
1793-spring 1794). In Paris and in provincial
villages grotesque and disorderly processions
assembled. Rigged out in priestly garments,
dressed up as bishops or the Pope, riding donkeys,
pigs and goats which were also decked out with
crosses, mitres and Bibles, the participants in these
carnivalesque gatherings mocked the Church and
all established forms of power. Pantomimes were
staged, people drank from chalices, and made a
terrific din as they followed wagons laden with
holy-water stoups, confessionals, ciboriums,
statues of saints, crosses, the feudal titles of former
lords, carved fleurs de lys (symbols of the
monarchy) and effigies of foreign kings or the
Pope.... This hétéroclite cargo was unloaded
on to an immense bonfire. Everyone danced
farandoles around the fire or the tree of liberty
and drank wine"the holy water of the
Republicans".
No more kings, no more impostors,
liberty or death!
The French leaders were alarmed by these
manifestations of popular rejoicing in what were
simultaneously festivals of destruction and
regeneration. Efforts were made to bring order
and morality to outbursts which some compared
to orgies. In opposition to these atheistical
happenings, a festival of the Supreme Being (God)
was established in 1794. It was also intended to
celebrate the universal religion of nature in
which, it was solemnly declared, "the French
people recognizes the immortality of the soul".
It was as part of a Rousseauist desire to promote
social education and community spirit that the
festivals were arranged for and by the people
Above, the "Festival
of the Supreme Being",
staged by the artist
Jacques Louis David
and celebrated on the
Champ de Mars, Paris, on
8 June 1794. Contemporary
engraving.
1 op, Planting a Tree
of Liberty, a watercolour
by Etienne Béricourt
(18th century).
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
which was both "spectator and actor". The com¬
mittee of public instruction of the National
Assembly was still responsible for organizing
them.
The aim was to dramatize the break with the
old inegalitarian society and to glorify a new
social harmony by emphasizing the republican
"virtues": love of man and nature, of one's
homeland, of friendship and justice, but also
hatred for kings and tyrants.
Festivals such as those of 14 July and
10 August which commemorated the great
revolutionary "days" legitimized the events
whereby the Republic had been founded and the
break with the past. The festivals held on the
tenth day of every ten-day week were republican
liturgies which glorified the peoples of ancient
Greece and Rome of whom the French people
were the heirs. Civic songs and oaths were the
order of the day at these festivals which were
dedicated to modesty, truth and conjugal love and
were supposed to present the new code of
morality. The oaths were all more or less in the
same vein. This one was pronounced by the
people with arms outstretched towards a bust of
Brutus, who had assassinated Julius Caesar to save
the Roman Republic: "Brutus, we swear to fol¬
low thy example, to maintain the Republic one
and indivisible. No more kings, no more impos¬
tors, liberty forever, liberty or death!"
The festivals included such popular features
as trees of liberty and bonfires, as well as sans¬
culotte symbols such as the Phrygian bonnet and
the pike. They proclaimed a political and social
messagethe unity of the country.
The festival of 10 August 1793 in Paris,
commemorating the popular insurrection of 1792
which had brought about the fall of the
monarchy, was one of "Unity and Indivisibility",
a true republican slogan. Conceived as an old-
style procession, the festival brought together
the population in arms, arranged according to sex
and age. For hours the procession wended its way
through streets decorated with oak-leaves.
The first of several places where it halted was on
the site of the Bastille before a fountain of
Regeneration; the second was before an arch
of triumph representing the women of 5 and
6 October 1789 with cannon and laurel crowns.
The third halt was on the Place de la Révolution
(today Place de la Concorde), where thousands
of birds were released while emblems of the
monarchy and feudalism were thrown on to an
immense fire beside an effigy of Liberty carry¬
ing a pike and wearing a bonnet. Next stop was
the Invalides opposite a colossal statue represent¬
ing the French people, with cudgel and fasces,
slaying the hydra of aristocracy. The fifth and last
stop was at the Champ de Mars where, near the
altar of the patrie, 200,000 persons took the oath:
"Liberty, equality and fraternity, or death". The
festival ended after a fraternal banquet on the
grass, with the celebration of the victory of the
revolutionary armies over the combined armies
of the tyrants.
In spite of their official aspect and, in some
cases, their obscure symbolism, the national
festivals were a great popular success, above all
in the towns and cities. Opposing superstition
with reason, they made it possible to weld
together the new society by a civic cult which
gradually engrafted itself on to the old practices.
But in rural France the Fête-Dieu, the festival of
St. John and the patron saints were still celebrat¬
ed and retained the pagan character which they
had had long before the Revolution.
1 he Festival of Unity
and Indivisibility",
10 August 1793,
Place de la Révolution,
Paris. Painting
by Pierre Antoine Demachy
(1723-1807).
LAURENCE COUDART,
French historian, is a staff
member of the Institute of
the History of the French
Revolution at the Sorbonne,
Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAIT
"The political and journalistic world can boast of very few heroes who compare
with Father Damien ofMolokai. It is worthwhile to look for the source of such heroism."
GANDHI
FATHER DAMIEN, CITIZEN OF THE WORLD
1840-1889
I OSEPH de Veuster, who was born in a little
Flemish village in 1840, joined the Society of
the Sacred Hearts of Jesus and Mary at Louvain,
Belgium, when he was twenty. At the age of
twenty-three, before he had even completed his
novitiate, he sailed for the Hawaiian Islands
where he was to devote his life to the care of
lepers. He died on Molokai Island a quarter of
a century later, after contracting leprosy himself.
In the mid-nineteenth century, Protestant
and Roman Catholic missions, as well as sizeable
minorities of Americans and Chinese, settled
among the Kanaka people of the kingdom of
Hawaii. This influx of people not only brought
new ideas and resources to the islands, it also led
to the introduction of diseases such as smallpox,
influenza, cholera, venereal diseases and, worst
of all, leprosy. In the hundred years between 1770
and 1870, the Kanaka population, which proved
to be terribly vulnerable to these diseases, plum¬
meted from 250,000 to 50,000.
Leprosy, in particular, spread like wildfire. In
the 1860s a policy of isolating those afflicted was
introduced, not only because of the fear of con¬
tagion, but because leprosy was such a disfig¬
uring disease that the authorities were afraid of
spoiling the archipelago's beautiful, peaceful and
prosperous image. Before long, those showing the
first symptoms were being systematically rounded
up and isolated on a peninsula of Molokai Island.
The Catholic missions were especially
concerned about the fate of the lepers. In 1873
it was decided that four young priests would
take turns to work on Molokai Island, thus en¬
suring that missionaries would always be present
there but would not have to endure a long un¬
broken stay in such a terrible environment.
De Veuster, who had taken the name of
Father Damien, immediately volunteered. He
organized a parish, set up associations, celebrated
the Eucharist, took confession, visited the sick in
their homes and administered the last sacraments.
He developed a popular liturgy for the celebra¬
tion of marriages and for processional use.
He took an interest in the material as well as
the spiritual aspects of life at Molokai and,
respectful of Hawaiian customs and lifestyles, did
his best to help develop the scarce local resources,
notably by putting pressure on the government.
In addition to his pastoral duties, Damien
performed a great service to the lepers by
reminding them of their sense of dignity and
treating them as human beings whose lives were
important, and whose sufferings, efforts, and
struggle against death had meaning and nobility.
There was a death in the community almost
every other day. Medical facilities were still
perfunctory. The risk of contracting leprosy
increased as the years went by. Damien, who
made little attempt to protect himself, eventually
succumbed to it. His own physical suffering
was his way of sharing that of the people
around him, and he said that it was nothing
compared to the frustration he felt before the
lack of understanding on the part of the religious
authorities, not to mention the incessant political
and doctrinal quarrels which followed him to
his grave.
But news of his struggle spread and his
work became widely appreciated. His fame
crossed the Pacific and he received moral and
financial support which helped him to care for
his lepers and to extract long-awaited sanitary
and humanitarian measures from the authorities.
The eyes of the world turned in compassion
to this remote island. Once synonymous with
horror, the name of Molokai came to evoke a new
challenge for humanitythat of vanquishing
leprosy while respecting the dignity of those
afflicted with it. Damien became the symbol of
this challenge.
In 1889, the year of Father Damien's death,
a fund was established in his memory in London,
under the patronage of the Prince of Wales. The
inauguration of the fund, the forerunner of the
British Leprosy Relief Association (LEPRA), was
soon followed by many other initiatives elsewhere
in the world. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
As promised, we are
reinstating our
"Letters to the Editor"
column featuring
readers' comments,
questions and criticisms.
Most of this month's
mailbag is concerned
with reactions to the
Courier's new format.
Letters to the Editor
Good, but could do better
I'm all in favour of the new-style
Unesco Couner. Congratulations on
a fine piece of work. The June
number on the bicentenary of the
French Revolution was most interes¬
ting. I eagerly await future issues and
urge you to be even more innovative.
Tahraoui Farid
Mulhouse (France)
An addition to my library
Congratulations on your June Issue,
1789: An idea that changed the
world. The texts, Illustrations, even
the paper on which they are printed,
are all very fine. This Issue is a wel¬
come addition to my library.
Pierre Gesneau
Orleans (France)
The right track
As a regular subscriber since 1961,
it Is with some misgivings that I wai¬
ted to see what the new-format
Unesco Courier would look like. I was
particularly afraid that advertising
matter would intrude on to your
pages.
But the magazine has managed to
stay on the right track. Congratula¬
tions on the quality of the layout and
the judicious choice of subject-
matter. I hope you will continue to
follow this path.
Gilbert Gassmann
Pines (France)
Was it really necessary?
I have been a subscriber to the
Unesco Courier since 1973. It's my
favourite magazine because it unites
all mankind without taking sides or
Imposing political barriers. I would
not have altered the format, although
no doubt you Introduced the chan¬
ges in response to views expressed by
your vast and diverse readership.
But what is the point of all these
full-page Illustrations? And won't the
de-luxe presentation mean a steep
price rise, which may put off poten¬
tial readers from social groups which
should be able to benefit from the
magazine?
All the same, I remain a faithful
Courier reader. I'll just have to get
used to the new format.
René Rousseau
Bagneux (France)
No to commercial pressures
I am disappointed by the new for¬
mula: it's only a copy, on heavier
paper, of many other magazines on
the market. I preferred the old for¬
mat, perhaps because it was slightly
old-fashioned, whence its originality.
When dealing with universal
cultures, it's a shame to give in to the
purely commercial considerations
which have imposed a dictatorship on
magazines in the last few years.
I have already cancelled my subs¬
cription to one leading weekly after
it bowed to commercial Imperatives
in its presentation. I'm reserving jud¬
gement as far as the Courier is con¬
cerned until my current subscription
expires.
Lucette Perrin
Decazeville (France)
Herder's true message
As editor and translator in France of
the works of Herder, I would like to
qualify Alain Flnkielkraut's argument
In his article "Sieyès, Herder, Goethe:
Universality and national identity" in
your June 1989 issue.
The conflict between the universal
and the specific is very ancient. The
eighteenth century, through the phi¬
losophes, the French Revolution and
German "idealist" philosophy, revi¬
ved these concepts and made an
issue of them. Alain Finklelkraut relies
heavily on these august sources for
his exposition.
He praises the merits of universal
literature dear to Goethe, and goes
out of his way to vilify Herder,... who
is guilty in his eyes of all kinds of par¬
ticularisms and nationalisms, In short
of all kinds of prejudices.
It is by no means certain, particu¬
larly in the eighteenth century, and
particularly in the case of Herder, a
great translator in all senses of the
word, that frontiers were ever as
impenetrable as all that. There are
cross-currents, convergences and
conflicts between cultures; they are
never truly isolatedIn a word, they
communicate.
If nineteenth-century philosophy
contributed anything to this debate
it was probably to substitute for the
crude dash between the universal
and the specific a process of reflec¬
tion on the mingling of cultures,
whether these presuppose a latent
universality (K.O. Apel), or whether
they discover and produce it (Jürgen
Habermas).
One of the lessons of history has
been that too much haste in labelling
a standpoint or a literature as univer¬
sal soon leads to imperialism...
Mr. Finkielkraut's attack on Herder
Is contrived, to say the least. Herder,
who fought all his life against illusions
of universality (while defending, with
a keen critical sense, a true universa¬
lity), who sought the "progress of
humanity" (and not, consequently,
that of any particular people), would
never have wished to "place all uni¬
versal values in the dock and have
them tried and condemned by
human diversity"...
He simply saw, as a forerunner of
a sociology to which Mr. Finkielkraut
perhaps attaches little Importance,
that to leave the specific is not to be
transported directly Into the univer¬
sal. He certainly did not confuse what
is with what should be. He unders¬
tood that the universal only comes
about, ideally and gradually, when
each one of useach people, each
individualcan first be himself or her¬
self, with his or her own language
and history, that universal liberty can¬
not be the product of force or any
form of oppression...
Doubtless It was a good rhetorical
ploy for Alain Finkielkraut to transmit
his message of universal by means
of historical examples. But that is no
reason why his examples should not
be relevant. The injustice he commits
with regard to Herder, through
Ignorance, contravenes his desire for
truth.
Pierre Pénisson
Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
\ s**
!Rp
Towards a better future
I am retired, and after taking your
magazine for several years I still read
the articles with as much interest as
ever. Their universality will, I hope,
help to bring peoples closer together
and build a better future for
mankind.
Jacques Pare
Neuilly-en-Thelle (France)
Time for a change
Bravo for the magazine's "shake-up"!
I much appreciate the new presenta¬
tion, illustrations and additional infor¬
mation for the reader.
I think the time had come for a
change, and you clearly agree with
me. The Courier's Interest lies in the
fact that it offers reflections on a spe¬
cific question from people of different
nationalities and widely different cul¬
tural backgrounds.
A reader
(France)
World problems today
and tomorrow
Congratulations on your choice of
themes, especially that of the family
(July 1 989). However, it seems to me
that the human race is beginning to
collapse under the weight of its own
numbers, and I feel that the conflict
between wanting more children and
limiting the birthrate, at the national
and the world level, ¡s a subject that
needs covering in greater depth.
Another important theme which
the Unesco Courier could tackle as
part of its mission is the development
of a society based on the best kind
of education and science, human
rights, and peace. This is perhaps a
Utopian dream, but it would set a
practical goal for our children.
Let me express my thanks for your
worldwide action.
Jean-Michel Delvat
Grand-Quevilly (France)
UNICEF
greetings cards
Artists and museums around the world have again
contributed an attractive range of designs and
paintings to this year's UNICEF greetings cards. The
1989 selection features a series of large-format
cards with reproductions of the works of modern
masters such as Henri Matisse, Georges Braque,
Vincent Van Gogh and Pierre Bonnard.
Proceeds from sales help UNICEF (the United
Nations Children's Fund) to finance its programmes
for bringing improved health care, nutrition, edu¬
cation and sanitation to millions of needy children
in the developing countries of Africa, Asia and La¬
tin America. In the last 35 years, around 200 mil¬
lion dollars have been raised in this way. For only
one dollar, 9 children can be vaccinated against
measles, or 1 3 against polio, or 30 against tuber¬
culosis, or 50 against diptheria, whooping cough
and tetanus. One dollar will also buy schoolbooks
for 10 children, or 6 packets of lettuce seeds, or
a stethoscope to monitor the foetal heartbeat.
The greetings cards and other stationery,
diaries and gifts are available at UNICEF sales
points, often to be found in banks and post offices
as well as in shops and stores throughout the
world. A free catalogue and further information
about the work of the organization can be ob¬
tained from the United Kingdom Committee for
UNICEF, 55 Lincoln's Inn Fields, London WC2A 3NB
Tel. (01) 405 5592.
'Bleu Soleil'
I am taking advantage of your appeal
for readers' letters to draw attention
to an association named "Bleu Soleil"
which was founded in 1988 with the
aim of rediscovering the wealth of
human creativity, in other words the
spiritual, cultural and human values
preserved by traditional societies.
The association seeks to reveal to
the countries of Europe and else¬
where, within the context of cultur¬
al, scientific and humanitarian
contacts between "North" and
"South", authentic musicians,
dancers, poets, writers, painters and
other creators of unpublished works
of great value.
Four projects are already under
way. They are "Nianadié", a show
which was cancelled in 1989 for lack
of funds but which will be performed
in the summer of 1 990; an exhibition
of work by a Nicaraguan painter;
another exhibition, on the
Apocalypse and the Tarot of Mar¬
seilles, by a French poet who has lived
for the last 20 years in Africa; and a
grant to enable a brilliant self-taught
Malian Tuareg researcher to com¬
plete and publish his research into the
Tuareg dialects of the Adrar des
Ifhoras mountains in Mali.
If "Bleu Soleil" is now established
and has done a certain amount of
promotion, it is essentially due to the
personal financial contribution of its
president, to a few subscriptions and
to the voluntary support of a hand¬
ful of friends. This is, I think, proof
of the serious approach and determi¬
nation of this young association.
"Bleu Soleil" must find financial
support if It Is to carry out important
projects to inform the public of the
need for cultural and scientific rap¬
prochement between men, in a spirit
of human solidarity.
Let us not forget the prophetic
words of Amadou Hampate Bâ:
"When an old man dies, a library
goes up in flames."
Guy Roque
Marseilles (France)
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
PHOTO CREDITS
Cover, pages 3 (above left), 8, 38 (above
& below), 40 (above), 41 (above): L.
Giraudou © Explorer, Paris. Back cover:
P. Cheuva © Explorer, Paris. Page 2: ©
Irène Dacunha, Lausanne. Page 3 (above
right): René Burri © Magnum, Paris. Page
5: Michel Barer © Rapho, Paris; (inset):
Hartwell © Sygma, Paris. Pages 10-11:
Hug © Explorer, Paris. Pages 12-13
(above): Le Naviose © Campagne-
Campagne, Paris. Page 13 (above):
Unesco/Georges Servar; (below): ©
Monique Pietri, Paris. Page 14 (above): C.
Lenars © Explorer, Paris; (below left):
Vuillomener © Rapho, Paris; (below
right): Mike Yamashita © Rapho, Paris.
Page 15 (above right): H. Silvester ©
Rapho, Paris; (below left): E. Linder ©
Rnpho, Paris. Pages 16-17: © Ousseynou
Sarr, Paris. Page 18: © Le Soleil, Dakar.
Page 19: © ERIK, Paris. Pages 20 (above),
21 (above, centre & below): Ch. Gibier
© Cedus, Paris. Page 20 (below left &
right): J. Oster © Musée de l'Homme,
Paris. Pages 22-23: © Nacho Lopez,
Mexico. Pages 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31:
© Yoshishihiko Shinada, from The Great
Monastery ofthe East. The drawing ofwater:
Description ofthe penitential gathering ofthe
second month at the Pavilion of the Second
Moon, by Ohga Tetsuo, Shôgakhan,
Tokyo, 1985. Pages 32-33, 36 (above):
Y.Somov © APN, Paris. Page 34:
Y. Kaver © APN, Paris. Page 35 (left):
B. Kavashkin and I. Zotov © APN,
Moscow; (right): Y. Somov © APN,
Moscow. Pages 36-37: © Izdatelstvo
Izobrazitelnoe Iskusstvo, Moscow
/Museum of Russian Art, Leningrad.
Pages 38 (centre), 40-41 (below):
O. Pighetti © Explorer, Paris. Page 39:
Samuel Costa © Explorer, Paris. Pages
42-43, 44 (above), 45 (above), 46: ©
Bulloz, Musée Carnavalet, Paris. Page 44
(below): © Bulloz, Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Page 45 (below): ©
Bulloz, Paris. Page 47: © The Friends of
Father Damien, Brussels.
The editors wish
to thank
Ms. Myriam Rosen
for her valuable
contribution to the
preparation of our
October issue,
Strangers on the
Screen.
50
Unesco Courier Index 1989
January
THE FRAGILE FOREST. The sacred tree (J. Brosse). Why we need forests. The relentless march of deforestation;
Towards a Green Revolution in forestry; The fuelwood crisis (S. Postel and L. Heise). Arboreal oddities. Farming the
forest (M. Hadley). Sustainable use of tropical forests (I. Muul). The Christianization of Kievan Russia: Millennium
celebrations (Metropolitan Juvenaly).
February
INDIA. 5,000 years of Indian culture (V.S. Naravane). Makers of modern India (S. Gopal). Indian cinema (K. Mohamed).
A new policy for education (A. Bordia). India's lifeline (A. Jung). Rural development (S.B. Roy). The philosophical
tradition. Fairs and festivals. The scientific legacy. Project Tiger (R. Singh). The anger of the sea-goddess (T.S. Pillai).
March
A SILKEN BOND BETWEEN EAST AND WEST (A.H. Dani). Mihai Eminescu: Romania's national poet. Decoding
Hafez' mystic message (R. Feiz). Hafez and the golden age of Persian literature (C.-H. de Fouchécour). The once and
future revolution (M. Agulhon). The mermaid of the Dniester (O. Petrash). Pollution unlimited (F. Bequette).
Rediscovering "The Islands of the Moon" (A. Libioulle). Educational planners go back to school.
April
CAMÔES AND THE PORTUGUESE VOYAGES OF DISCOVERY. The dawn of a new age (L.F. Barreto). Of
caravels and cartographers... (L. de Albuquerque). Japan in early Portuguese maps (A.P. Marques). Luis de Camôes,
Portugal's great epic poet (V. Graça Moura). The Lusiads (E. Lourenço). Camôes and Brazil (J. de Souza Montello). Rivalry
in the Red Sea (Ibn Iyas). The Portuguese in India (J. Correia Afonso). Portuguese art in the maritime era (R. de Faria
D. Moreira). Fernando Pessoa and the spirit of discovery (JA. Seabra).
May
MODERN MANUSCRIPTS. The written word... (L.S. Senghor) ... A fragile heritage (JC. Langlois). Libraries to the
rescue (G. Cartier). Microwaves that save manuscripts (D. Sergent). France's Bibliothèque Nationale, a library in action
(F. Callu). From the world's archives. The quest for authenticity (G. Tavani). The Archives Collection, a laboratory
for the future (A. Segala). Literary detection and Latin American writing (F. Ainsa). The birth of a language (R.B. Saguier).
A thousand years of Catalan history (F. Vallverdú), Romanesque treasures of Catalonia (E. Carbonell i Esteller). Gaudi
and Dalí, the art of excess (D. Giralt-Miracle).
June
1789: AN IDEA THAT CHANGED THE WORLD. Interview with François Mitterrand, President of the French
Republic. The Republic's citizens of honour (E. Naraghi). Tom Paine: the antimonarchist who tried to save a king (J.
Lessay). In the Antilles, "Liberty for All" (Y. Benot). The eagle and the sphinx: Bonaparte in Egypt (M. Hussein). Sieyès,
Herder, Goethe: universality and national identity (A. Finkielkraut). The Republican dream (Simón Bolívar). Poetry,
freedom and revolution (S.S. Averintsev). Chomin: the Rousseau of the East (Shin'ya Ida). China: rethinking the Revolution
(Zhilian Zhang). The spirit of '89 (T. Ben Jelloun). An idea and its destiny (F. Furet).
July
THE FAMILY. Interview with Jorge Amado. Nineteenth-century Russia: hearth, home and rural community (H. Yvert-
Jalu). Ancient China: the empire of the ancestors (Qi Yanfen). Africa: lines of descent (M.B. Priso). The Middle East
and North Africa: the future of the family. The changing Japanese family (Kurimoto Kazuo). Europe: Marina, Sarah,
Michel and Jean (A. Michel). Latin America: the women of Arembepe (M. de Athayde Figueiredo and D. Prado). Quebec:
new family structures (F. Descarries and C. Corbeil). A visit to an Uzbek family (C. Fournier). Africa's "wonder weed".
August
STREETSCAPES. Interview with Richard Attenborough. Berlin: the Friedrichstrasse, a link in the chain of history
(C. Mengin). Tokyo: a city of towers and traditions (S. Zarmati). Bogota: a trip along the Séptima (A. Berty). Abidjan:
a colourful kaleidoscope (P. Haeringer). Moscow: Gorky Street, fifty years of change (A. Kopp). Cairo: in the heart
of an ancient capital (A. Bonnamy). Houston: highways in the city (B. Ouvry-Vial). Beijing: the street of the glazed
tile factory (P. Clement). Under the roofs of Paris (A.-M. Chatelet). Families of the world (H. Tremblay). International
co-operation in space (D. Spurgeon).
September
GREAT EPICS. Interview with Jean-Claude Carrière: the Mahabharata, Great History of Mankind. The poet's tale
(M. Hussein). Gilgamesh, the king who did not wish to die (J. Bottéro). Aeneas, Rome's man of destiny (J. -P. Brisson).
The Epic of the Kings (N. Tadjadod). llya the invincible (H. Yvert-Jalu). The Secret History of the Mongols (S. Bira). The
Mahàvamsa, Sri Lanka's non-stop epic (A.W.P. Gurugé). Shaka Zulu, a living legend (K.I. Bosco). Knights of the Far
West (G.N. Granville). Mapping the human genome (J. Richardson).
October
STRANGERS ON THE SCREEN. Interview with Jean Lacouture: Champollion, a heio of the Enlightenment. Creatures
from inner space (C. Aziza). Macunaïma, the eternal outsider (A. Rodrigues). Germans screened through French eyes
(R. Prédal). An Orient of myth and mystery (A. Fahdel). Tristan and Pavlova through the looking glass (M. Fellous).
Behind the veil (A. Djebar). Charlie Chaplin, stranger and brother (M. Oms). "Slaves of one man": the American Indian
in 17th- and 18th-century French literature (C. de Grandpré). Understanding global change (A.M. Clayson).
November
A MATHEMATICAL MYSTERY TOUR. Interview with Federico Mayor, Director-General of Unesco. Ancient Egypt
and Mesopotamia: prime numbers 0- Ritter). India: Lilavati, gracious lady of arithmetic (F. Zimmermann). China: H
in the sky (J.-C. Martzloff). Ancient Greece: the Odyssey of reason (B. Vitrac). The Arab world: where geometry and
algebra intersect (R. Rashed). From the Middle Ages to the Enlightenment: the roots of modern maths (C. Goldstein
and J. Gray). Gabriela Mistral, poet and humanist. An Academy of Sciences for the Third World (A.M. Faruqui).
December
HIGH DAYS AND HOLIDAYS. Interview with Najib Mahfouz. The festive spirit (J- Duvignaud). Mock lion and
real heroes (M. Seek). Skeletons at the feast (J. Pérez Siller). The Pavilion of the Second Moon (L. Caillet). Farewell
to winter (H. Yvert-Jalu). Samba time! (S. Alves Teixeira). Liberty, Equality, Festivity! (L. Coudart). Father Damien,
citizen of the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The Mnesco
^aJ^COURlER
	 42nd YEAR
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceii Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Studies and research: Femando Amsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel 45.68 46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel. 45 68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solarge Beim
Secretariat: Annie Brächet {Tel.. 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Public relations: Ciaudie Duhamel fiel .:45 68 .45.86)
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique 3ourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Georg: Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mano Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Kumar Singh (Delhi)
Tamil: M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Az;zah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S J Sumanasekera ßanda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68 45.88). Assistant: Marie-
Noëlle Branet (45 .68 .45.89), Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse
Hardy (45.68.45.65), Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité,
Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo,
Miche! Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45 68.45.64),
Accounts: Liliane Tasch (45.68 45 66), Cultural projects:
Ricardo Zamora-Perez (Tel : 45 68.45.80),
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45 68.47.50)
ADVERTISING
Publicat: 17, Boulevard Poissonnière, 75002 Paris.
Tel.: 40.26.51.26
Sales director: Benoît Rosier
Advertising director: Daniele Michelet
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45 65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 68 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years. 180 FF
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is
produced in microform {microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48100. US A , (3) N C R Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc . Ill West 40th Street, New York, u S A .. (4) Bell and
Howell CO., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U SA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE .
(Printed in France) DEPOT LEGAL : Cl DÉCEMBRE *989
Photocomposition The Unesco Courier
Photogravure impression Maury Imprimeur S A , 2 t route d-'Etampes,
45330 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 12 1989 OPI -89 1 -475 A
This issue comprises 54 pages and a 4-page advertising insert
between pages 10-11 and 42-43
THE LIBRARY
LIBRARIES
Unesco Collection
of Représentative Works
m
wm
THICKHEAD AND
OTHER STORIES
BY HALDUN TANER
TRANSLATED FROM
TURKISH
BY GEOFFREY LEWIS
£8.95
FOREST BOOKS,
LONDON AND BOSTON/
UNESCO, 1988
Inj"*»*»
»ZhouaV T«*B»
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Z
rñ
TTu:
1 *ti«<a
m\
fin
il _ -j a : -'
f F
ff
/
II
"fc' p^
-". .!----"
]]>
</page>
</document>
