<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="086461eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Vi
GUST 1990
>
i! fe*
M 1205 9008 -15.00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
Canoes for
Indian visitors
These terracotta Indian
canoes were made by
children aged between
six and twelve at a
workshop held at the
Arts Centre in Amiens
(France) They were
offered as a tribute to a
group of North American
Indian film-makers taking
part in the VII
International Film Festival,
Amiens, 1987. Touched by
the children's enthusiasm,
several of the film-makers
spent a day introducing
them to Indian culture
through songs, dances
and stories.
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
JFmmm
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
AUGUST 1990
N N
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to its readers. Each month
contributors of different
nationalities provide from
different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect
for the dignity of man
everywhere.
4
ART NOUVEAU
ART NOUVEAU:
AN INTERNATIONAL AESTHETIC
hy Arthur Gillette 10
THE ETERNAL BLOOM OF ART NOUVEAU
by Manfred Speidel 13
THE FARAWAY SOURCES: JAPAN
A FRESH LOOK AT TRADITIONAL FORMS
by Hiroyasu Fujioka 18
THE FARAWAY SOURCES: EGYPT
FROM HORUS TO AÏDA
hy Mona Zaalouk 20
THE HOUSE AS A TOTAL WORK OF ART
hy Cécile Duhère 22
FROM FANTASY TO FUNCTIONALISM
by Andreas Lehne 27
NORTHERN LIGHTS
by Maria Nashtshokina and Boris Kmkov 32
MODERNIST BARCELONA
by Albert Garcia Espuche 35
A CUBAN MYTHOLOGY
by Enrique Capablanca 37
Interview with
ERNESTO SÁBATO
41
IN BRIEF... 41
HERITAGE
Unesco and 'architecture
with a smile'
by Hans-Dieter Dyroff 42
REFLECTIONS
Ä terrifying and edible beauty'
by Ezio Godoli 44
ENVIRONMENT
S.O.S lemurs!
A new biosphere reserve
in Madagascar
by Edouard Bailby 46
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR 49
FORUM
The International African Institute
A 'hunger for books'
by Peter Lloyd 50
ARGENTINA: AN AESTHETIC REVOLUTION
by Jorge O. Gazaneo
Cover: entrance hall of the
yj Hôtel Tassel, Brussels, by
Victor Horta, 1893.
Back cover: interior detail,
Igumnov residence, Moscow,
39 by Nikolai' Pozdeiev, 1892.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
N T E R V I E W
Ernesto Sábato
A sense
of wonder
One of
the greatest
living writers
in Spanish,
the Argentine
novelist
and essayist
Ernesto Sábato
analyses what
he sees as
the spiritual
crisis of
our time
You have written many essays, notably a collection and above all since the advent of positivism, science has with-
entitled Hombres y Engranajes (1951; "Men and Gears"), drawn to a kind of Olympian retreat, cut off from humanity.
on the dehumanizing effects of science and technology. The absolute sovereignty of Science and Progress over the
How did a scientist like yourself come to see things in greater part of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries has
this lightí reduced the individual to the status of a cog in a gigantic
Although I studied physics and mathematics, disciplines machine. Capitalist and Marxist theorists alike have con-
which offered me a kind of abstract and ideal refuge in a tributed to the propagation of this sadly distorted vision in
"platonic paradise" far from the chaos of the world, I soon which the individual is melted into the mass and the mystery
realized that the blind faith that some scientists have in of the soul is reduced to physically quantifiable emissions
"pure" thought, in reason and in Progress (usually with a of radiation.
capital "P") made them overlook and even despise such
essential aspects of human life as the unconscious and the Yet, even in the nineteenth century, there was a strong
myths which lie at the origin of artistic expression, in short, philosophical current that questioned the monumental
the "hidden" side of human nature. All that was missing rational edifice constructed by Hegel, the weight ofwhich
in my purely scientific workthe Mr. Hyde that every Dr. crushed the individual. We are thinking ofKierkegaard,
Jekyll needs if he is to be a complete individualI found about whom you have written extensively.
in German romanticism and, above all, in existentialism and Kierkegaard was the first thinker to question whether
surrealism. Lifting my eyes from my logarithms and sinu- science should take precedence over life and to answer firmly
soids, I looked on the human face, from which I have never that life comes first. Since then, the object deified by science
since looked away. has been dislodged as the centre of the universe and been
replaced by the subject, the man of flesh and blood. This
Some great contemporary writers have managed to recon- led on to Karl Jaspers and Martin Heidegger, to twentieth-
cile science and creativity... century existentialist philosophy in which man is no longer
That may be so, but it does not lessen my belief that an "impartial" scientific observer but a "self" clothed in
our era is strongly marked by the opposition between science flesh, the "being destined to die" of whom I have written
and the humanities, which today has become irreconcilable, and who is the source of tragedy and metaphysics, the
Since the Enlightenment and the days of the Encyclopaedists, ' highest forms of literary expression.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The novel answers all these questions, not simply by
expressing ideas, but through myth and symbol, by drawing
on the magical properties of thought. All the same, many
of the characters in novels are just as real as reality itself.
Is Don Quixote "unreal"? If reality bears any relationship
to durability, then this character born of Cervantes' imagi¬
nation is much more real than the objects that surround us,
for he is immortal.
So literature interprets reality?
Fortunately, art and poetry have never claimed to
dissociate the rational from the irrational, the sensibility
from the intellect, dream from reality. Dream, mythology
and art have a common source in the unconsciousthey
/ believe in art, dialogue,
liberty and the dignity of
the individual human being
But not the only ones...
Of course not, but to my mind they are the most
important because of their tragic, transcendental dimension.
One has only to think of Dostoyevsky's Notes from the
Underground, that bloody diatribe in which, with almost
demented hatred, he denounced the modern age and its cult
of progress.
We are right into literature now...
Yes, because the novel can express things that are beyond
the scope of philosophy or the essaysuch as our darkest
uncertainties about God, destiny, the meaning of life, hope.
reveal a world which could have no other form of expres¬
sion. It is absurd to ask artists to explain their work. Can
you imagine Beethoven analysing his symphonies or Kafka
explaining what he really meant in The Trial? The notion
that everything can be "rationally" explained is the hall¬
mark of the Western positivist mentality typical of the
modern age, an age which overestimates the value of science,
reason and logic. Yet this form of culture represents only
a brief moment in human history.
You seem to consider our age to be thefinalphase in a line
ofmodern thought beginning in the middle ofthe nineteenth
century and ending in our own times.
Literary fashions should not be confused with the major
trends of thought. In the vast and tragic movement of ideas
there are advances and retreats, sideways excursions and
counter-currents. It is clear, however, that we are witnessing
the end of an era. We are living through a crisis of civiliza¬
tion in which there is a kind of confrontation between the
eternal forces of passion and order, of pathos and ethos, of
the Dionysian and the Apollonian.
Can this crisis be resolved?
The only way we can escape from this harrowing crisis
is by snatching living, suffering man from the gigantic
machine in which he is enmeshed and which is crushing him.
But it must not be forgotten, at the dawn of a new millen¬
nium, that an age does not end at the same moment for
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
everyone. In the nineteenth century, when Progress was
triumphant, writers and thinkers such as Dostoyevsky,
Nietzsche and Kierkegaard were not "of their time", for
already, despite the optimism of scientists, they had a presen¬
timent of the catastrophe that was in store for us and which
Kafka, Sartre and Camus were to portray.
7s that why you reject the concept of "progress" in art?
Art can no more progress than a dream can, and for the
same reasons. Are the nightmares of our contemporaries any
more advanced than those of the prophets of the Bible? We
can say that Einstein's mathematics are superior to those
of Archimedes, but not that Joyce's Ulysses is superior to
Homer's Odyssey. One of Proust's characters is convinced
that Debussy is a better composer than Beethoven for the
simple reason that he was born after him. There's no need
to be a musicologist to appreciate Proust's satirical irony
in this passage. Every artist aspires towards what may be
Design for
stained-glass
window, oil on
cardboard, by
the Uruguayan
artist Joaquin
Torres Garcia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
For a human being
learning means taking
part, discovering
and inventing
form their own opinions, even if, at times, this means
making mistakes and having to go back to the beginning
again. They need to explore new paths and experiment with
new methods. Otherwise we shall, at best, merely produce
a race of scholars or, at worst, of bookworms or of parrots
regurgitating ready-made phrases from books. The book is
a wonderful tool, provided that it does not become an
obstacle that prevents us from pursuing our own research.
called an absolute, or towards a fragment of the Absolute, How do you see the educator's role?
with a capital "A", whether he be an Egyptian sculptor in Etymologically speaking, to educate means to develop,
the time of Ramses II, a Greek artist of the classical age, or to bring out what exists in embryonic form, to realize poten-
Donatello. This is why there is no progress in art, only rial. This "labour", this delivery by the teacher is rarely fully
change and new departures that are due not only to the sen- accomplished, and this perhaps is the origin of all the faults
sibilities of each artist but also to the tacit or explicit vision of our education systems. Students must be made to ask
of an epoch or a culture. One thing at least is certain; no themselves questions, and be convinced of their own ignor-
artist is better placed than another to attain these absolute anee and of ours, so that they are prepared not only to ask
values simply because he was born later. questions but to think for themselves, even if they disagree
with us. It is also very important for them to be able to make
So you do not believe that there can be a universal aesthetic? mistakes and for us to accept questions and approaches that
The relativity of history is reflected in aesthetics, may seem odd. Given this state of mind, students will
Each period has a dominant valuereligious, economic or understand that reality is infinitely more complex and
metaphysical colours all the others. In the eyes of mysterious than the small area encompassed by our
the people of a religious culture preoccupied with the eternal, knowledge. Everything else will follow automatically. This
Ramses IPs hieratic and geometric colossus would encapsu- is what gives rise to questionings and to certainties, the
late more "truth" than a totally realistic statue. History mixture of tradition and innovation that constitutes the cul-
shows us that beauty and truth change from one period to tural dynamic. As Kant said, people should not be taught
the next, that black culture and white culture are based on philosophy, they should be taught to philosophize. This is
different criteria. The reputations of writers, artists and the method of Plato's "Dialogues", based on direct, spon-
musicians are subject to swings of the pendulum. taneous exchange, in the course of which questions emerge
from our awareness of our fundamental ignorance.
There is no justification, therefore, for speaking of the
superiority of one culture over another? Can you give us a specific example?
Today we have come a long way from conceited A long time ago, I travelled through Patagonia in a jeep
positivist certainties and from "enlightened thought" in with a forester who told me how much the forest was
general. Following the work of Levy-Bruhl, who after forty receding with each successive forest fire. He told me of the
years of research admitted in all honesty that he could see defensive role played by cypress trees, which he compared
no "progression" in the move from magical to logical to the stoical heroes of an army rearguard since they sacrifice
thought and that the two had inevitably to coexist in man, themselves to delay the spread of a fire and to protect the
all cultures must be seen as deserving equal respect. We have other trees. This made me wonder what the teaching of
finally come round to rendering justice to what were once geography could be like if it were linked to the struggle
condescendingly called "primitive cultures". between species, the conquest of the oceans and of the con¬
tinents, and to the history of mankind, which is pathetically
You are, nevenheless, dissatisfied with the education dependent upon the terrestrial environment. In this way the
currently available in schools and universities. What do pupil would get the idea of a true adventure, of a thrilling
you think it lacks? battle against the hostile forces of Nature and of history.
When I was young, I was made to swallow a mountain Far from the dead weight of encyclopaedic knowledge, from
of facts that I forgot as quickly as I could. In geography, dusty volumes and ready-made ideas, knowledge thus
for example, I barely remember the Cape of Good Hope perpetually renewed would give each pupil the feeling of
and Cape Horn, and perhaps that's only because they are discovering and participating in an age-old story. For
often mentioned in the newspapers. Someone once said that example, to engrave indelibly on students' minds the corn-
culture is what is left when you have forgotten everything plicated geography of the American continent, as a lived-
else. For a human being, learning means taking part, dis- through rather than a book-learned experience, would not
covering and inventing. If people are to advance, they must the best way be to teach it through the adventures of great
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
We have to kindle
astonishment at the profound
mysteries of the universe
explorers such as Magellan or conquistadores such as Cortés?
We should be formed, not informed. As Montaigne said,
"Learning by heart is not learning". What an exciting
manual of geography and ethnology for teenagers Jules
Verne's Around the World in Eighty Days would make! We
have to kindle astonishment at the profound mysteries
of the universe. Everything in the universe is astonishing
if you think about it. But familiarity has made us blasé and
nothing astonishes us any more. We have to rediscover a
sense of wonder.
You even recommend "back to front" teaching, starting
with the present and reaching back into the past.
I believe that the best way to interest young people in
literature is to start with contemporary authors, whose lan¬
guage and concerns are closer to the students' own hopes
and fears. Only later can they really become interested in
what Homer or Cervantes wrote about love and death, hope
and despair, solitude and heroism. The same could be done
with history by tracing back to the roots of current
problems.
It is also a mistake to try to teach everything. Only a
few key episodes and problems, enough to provide a struc¬
ture, should be taught. Few books should be used, but they
should be read with passion. This is the only way to avoid
making reading seem like a walk through a cemetery of dead
words. Reading is only valid if it strikes a chord in the
reader's mind. There is a kind of pseudo-encyclopaedic
teaching, invariably associated with book-learning, which
is a form of death. As if there were no culture before
Gutenberg!
For years you have been pointing out the risks inherent in
nuclear weapons, in the arms race and in ideological con¬
frontation throughout the world. Aren't the upheavals of
recent years, and in particular ofrecent months, taking some
of the force out of this message?
I'm not so sure about that. First of all, the proliferation
Wood engraving, anonymous, 16th century.
»*«®SfcA¿ff
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Temple, 1949, oil on canvas by the Belgian artist Paul Delvaux.
of nuclear weapons is a fact. Many countries already have
their own atomic "mini-bombs" and a chain reaction
starting with some irresponsible terrorist action cannot be
discounted. But this is only the purely "physical" aspect
of the question, monstrous though it is. What really worries
me is the spiritual catastrophe facing our era, which is the
sad outcome of the repression of the forces of the uncons¬
cious in contemporary society. I see evidence of this in the
proliferation of all kinds of protesting minorities, as well
as in our collective history. We live in an anguished, neu¬
rotic, unstable age, hence the frequency of psychosomatic
disorders, the upsurge in violence and in the use of drugs.
This is a philosophical rather than a police matter. Until
quite recently the "peripheral" regions of the world were
unaffected by this phenomenon. In the East for example,
as well as in Africa and in Oceania, mythological and
philosophical traditions maintained a certain harmony
between man and the world. The abrupt, unchecked irrup¬
tion of Western values and technology has wreaked havoc,
just as, during the Industrial Revolution, the mill-owners
of Manchester swamped with their cheap cotton goods
peoples who knew how to produce exquisite textiles. This
mental catastrophe is leading us towards a terrifying psy¬
chological and spiritual explosion which will give rise to a
wave of suicides and scenes of hysteria and collective mad¬
ness. Ancient traditions cannot be replaced by the transistor
industry.
Do you see nothing positive in the balance-sheet?
Yes, perhaps, but frankly I suspect that I belong to a
race that is on the road to extinction. I believe in art,
dialogue, liberty and the dignity of the individual human
being. But who is interested in such nonsense today?
Dialogue has given way to insult and liberty to political
prisons. What difference is there between a left-wing and
a right-wing police state? As if there could be good or bad
torturers! I must be a reactionary because I still believe in
dull, mediocre democracy, the only regime which, after all,
allows one to think freely and to prepare the way for a better
reality.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Art Nouveau: an international
BY ARTHUR GILLETTE
10
X OMPOSITY of intent and orthodoxy of
stylethese were the main traits of European
architecture against which Art Nouveau rose up
towards the end of the last century. It was a time
of rapid urban growth, when the rich wanted to
show off their newly-acquired wealth in town
houses and other architectural statements that
took themselves so seriously that they seemed
heartless. Art Nouveau, in contrast, was a vision
that sprang straight from the heart as a rejection
of the grey uniformization of the environment:
of dwellings, furniture, tableware and other
artefacts that strongly shape the ways in which
people live and feel about their daily lives.
Art Nouveau expressed nostalgia for Nature
and the past, for the non-urban and the non-
modern, for the anti-rational swirls of vines and
flower stems, the rough texture of pine cones,
and more generally for pre-industrial asymmetry.
It also grew in tune with the medieval longings
that so marked the aesthetics of the late
nineteenth century, and were often connected
with movements of national revival. But Art
Nouveau also looked ahead, happily seizing the
materials of its day and proving itself to be a
force for ingenious innovation. Did stone attest
to the solidity and incomes of the wealthy,
whose pomposity Art Nouveau mocked? The
new style flaunted its creativity by making this
staid material come alive with turbulent
vegetation, mythical beasts and human beings
with expressions so pure they seem to pre-date
the very notion of sin. Art Nouveau worked
stone as though it were clay, and also embraced
new media such as polychrome glazing, wrought
iron, exposed steel, and glass (stained or
futuristically sworled), often in astonishing and
unprecedented combinations in the same work,
be it a house or a piece of furniture.
In terms of inspiration and impact, the Art
Nouveau vision also looked outwards. Japanese
pictorial treatment of Nature was an explicitly
recognized source, and japonisme was seldom far
from the minds of many Art Nouveau
practitioners. Moghul influence can also be seen
(in certain towers, for instance), and some Art
Nouveau exponents in Central Europe drew on
references from further to the east.
And what of impact? There is today a
widespread misconception according to which
Art Nouveau was an overwhelmingly European
expression, with some minor overflow reaching
the shores of North America. Nothing could be
further from the truth. After flowering in the
Old Worldfrom Helsinki to Rome, from
Moscow to Paristhe seeds of Art Nouveau
spread far and wide on the winds of what turned
out to be the first truly international architecture
and design movement of our century. An
indigenous and vigorous branch sprang up in the
United States (whose influence returned to
Europe), while the Catalan Modernist variant
(Modernismo) disembarked in Cuba (where it was
"tropicalized", in cigar box labels for example),
and Belgians and Italians built sumptuous Art
Nouveau villas in Argentina and Chile
respectively. The movement also made its way to
North Africa, Turkey and Japan.
In its international embrace, as well as its
innovative choice and use of materials and forms,
the Art Nouveau vision was intimately linked
with its epoch. One expression of this, and a
further indictment of stolid pomposity, was the
movement's sense of humour and whimsy. A
widespread feature was the
omega-shaped door, which might be interpreted
as a happy mouth: Art Nouveau's approach has
understandably been called "architecture with a
smile". The horror of the First World War
struck the movement a death blow.
With its swirls and humour replaced in the
1920s by Art Deco's angular obsession with
(apparent) functionality, Art Nouveau began its
trek through the wilderness. And still today it is
mocked, despised, or simply ignored in many
quarters. At present, there is cause for serious
concern about the fate of Art Nouveau
ornaments and even entire buildings in Dublin,
Moscow, Paris, Tunis and Valparaiso, to cite but
five cities among many others where Art
Nouveau creations are threatened.
Yet the present state and prospects of Art
Nouveau are contradictory. On the one hand, its
buildings continue to be torn down or simply
left to rot; on the other, there is growing
international recognition that Art Nouveau has
an intrinsic and timeless value, that it should be
viewed as part and parcel of humanity's
architectural and stylistic heritage, and
consequently should be protected and preserved.
In the last twenty years, Art Nouveau has
come back into fashion. Already in the 1970s in
some European cities Art Nouveau décors were
being designed for certain new restaurants and
shops. In Glasgow, designated Cultural Capital of
Europe 1990 by the European Community, a
"House for an Art Lover" designed by the
Scottish architect Charles Rennie Mackintosh
(1868-1928) is at long last being built. Perhaps
Art Nouveau, born on the eve of the twentieth
century, will enjoy a revival on the eve of the
twenty-first.
ARTHUR GILLETTE is editor-in-chief of Unesco's
international quarterly Museum.
Stained-glass skylight (detail),
auditorium of the Palau
de la Música Catalana, Barcelona,
by Lluis Domènech i Montaner, 1905-1908.
W5»V
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
aesthetic
JA. 1 i. Y -rMt YA i 1 >^ PT^T^r
J * Vi il j^^ * ^k <mi^^m tBÎ^L^ r^ïCLY^ U if WPffc'^fc
.s\
' s
L>/
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
r
Above, Hungarian postcard,
c. 1900.
Right, stained-glass window
(detail) of a Brussels
apartment building.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The eternal
bloom of
Art Nouveau
BY MANFRED SPEIDEL
A,Lnyone who has ever seen dried flowers and
leaves that have been pressed for years between
the pages of a book and remembers how the faded
petals, leaves and stems were twisted and entwined
in a two-dimensional pattern should be able to
visualize some of the favourite decorative motifs
used by Art Nouveau artists to decorate the
façades of buildings.
Flowers and plants depicted in this way are
quite different from the naturalistic flower pic¬
tures painted by late nineteenth-century artists
who made pastiches of Gothic or Renaissance
ornamentation. Often enclosed within a frame,
Art Nouveau plants are stylized, they are
geometrical iff shape or their proportions are so
different from those of real plants as to be almost
unrecognizable. The graphic effect is invariably
surprising. The images have a pent-up vitality so
explosive that they seem ready to burst out of
their frames.
Anyone who has observed the world of
plants is sure to have noticed how twigs are
thicker where they part from the branch and at
the bud; how branches twist and turn to form
complex concave and convex patterns; how rocks
are sometimes embraced by an overgrowth of
roots. Using moulded plaster or cast iron, expo¬
nents of Art Nouveau like the French architect
Hector Guimard transformed such natural sculp¬
tures into architectural forms so ambiguous that
they might equally well have been inspired by
pictures of bones and muscles in anatomical text¬
books. These artists would take the functional
aspect of walls and other architectural features as
the starting point for the creation of organic
forms, just as a pearl grows around a grain of sand
in an oyster or a branch grows around an
obstacle.
Art Nouveau artists and architects were also
fascinated by the way in which the tendrils of
climbing plants such as pumpkins spiral around
a support. Using the elasticity and tensile strength
of wrought iron they produced such creeper-like
effects in their designs for stair railings, lamps and
other features of interior decoration. In the
houses he designed in Brussels, Victor Horta com¬
bined the standards and other structural compo¬
nents of electric lamps with more flexible
supports and wiring to make a lattice of sinuous
interwoven lines.
The influence
of the Far East
The inspiration for using plant images in this way
and transforming them into works of art came
from Japanese prints and Japanese and Chinese
calligraphy, which began to appear on the
Western art market in the 1860s. European artists
were excited by the skill with which Oriental
artist-calligraphers drew complex characters with
ink and brush, and by the balance they achieved
between black ideograms and white background.
Victor Horta (in his use of woodwork with
wrought iron) and Henry van de Velde (in his
early designs for chairs) were among the brilliant
exponents of this kind of balance between figure
and background.
This method of transforming flat surfaces was
also used by Horta to break up structural ele¬
ments and dissolve the heavy monumental wall
structures of traditional European architecture so 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
as to produce effects of light and a sense of fluid
movement which give the same impression as late
Rococo.
How was this impression of lightness
reproduced on solid stone walls? In Brussels
Horta made the transition from stonework to
ironwork by paring down the stone where it
meets the metal into two or three fine steps so
that the stone seems to consist of thin layers. The
iron is embedded in a hard inner layer of stone
which is enfolded in the thin and softer outer
layers as if in a piece of cloth. The effect of fine
drapery enwrapping a clumsy load-bearing struc¬
ture could be achieved more cheaply in plaster,
and consequently the Art Nouveau period
marked a high point in the use of stuccoed surfaces
which gave a rich and light appearance through
variety of texture.
The graphic explosion
The idea of using a beautiful surface both to pro¬
tect and embellish an architectural structure had
been put forward in the early nineteenth century
by the German architect and writer Gottfried
Semper, who pointed out that in early times the
walls of dwellings had often been covered with
fabric which, like the carpets in a nomad's tent,
was both decorative and a means of insulation.
Around 1895 the Viennese School led by
Otto Wagner took up this idea and began to
experiment with it. Perhaps stimulated by
developments in architecture, graphic artists were
working along similar lines. Thus another facet
of Art Nouveau design originated in Vienna: the
construction of thin layers of surface materials
in stone and glass. One way of suggesting that
these were thin, non-load-bearing slabs was to
leave exposed the screws with which they were
fixed to the wall; another was to enclose them
within a frame. Wagner and his school thus tried
to achieve delicate effects through simple
geometrical façades without having to transform
stone surfaces into patterns of plants and drapery.
So much for the work of Art Nouveau artists
as designers of façades, interiors and furniture.
The less gifted architect or craftsman could pick
up from art magazines their ideas and patterns
for stucco decoration and, by adding a curved
gable here or an omega-shaped window there,
make it seem that he had designed a building in
a new style even though its ground plan was tradi¬
tional in conception. However, wealthy clients
Above, detail of gilt
bronze plate by
Hector Guimard, 1909.
Right, "Waterlily" lamp in
chased gilt bronze from a pair
created by Louis Majorelle in
collaboration with Daum
brothers glassworks, 1905.
Below right, stair railing,
Folkwang Museum, Hagen
(Fed. Rep. of Germany), by
Henry van de Velde, 1901.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Above left, arum lily vase in
"Favrile" iridescent glass, by
Tiffany Studios, Corona, New
York, c. 1900-1910.
Left, front door handle,
Brussels.
Below, detail of stair railing
in Victor Horta's house (now
the Horta Museum), Brussels,
1898.
and their architects sought to create surfaces
which were nothing less than works of art. The
most ambitious architects supervised every detail,
inside and out, of the buildings they designed,
from heating equipment to door handles. They
created a fantastic illusory world of mirror walls
and translucent stained glass. Today it is hard not
to be amused by the extravagance of invention
displayed in the design of such accessories of a
luxurious life-style as a door handle transformed
into the erotic figure of a woman wrapped in
whirling drapery.
An international movement
with national variants
Is it possible to subsume this great variety of
decorative art into a single "style"? Although the
forms differ, they are linked by a common inten¬
tion to create an impression of lightness in load-
bearing structures. But finding a generic name for
this style is not easy. Unesco's project on this
theme (see page 42) uses both the French term
Art Nouveau and the German term Jugendstil. We
should also speak of Sezessionstil in relation to
Austria and Modernismo for Spain. Each of these
terms refers to a specific situation.
"L'Art Nouveau" was the name of a shop
opened in 1895 in Paris by Samuel Bing, a dealer
in Japanese prints and East Asian objets d'art who
also exhibited contemporary furniture and crafts.
When he showed his collection in Dresden in
1897, it was billed simply as "Bing. Art Nou¬
veau." Around 1900, by which time Bing had
begun to turn to other styles, art critics adopted
the name of his shop to describe the work of Gui-
mard or Horta. Horta disliked being labelled as
the exponent of a style. He considered himself
to be a rationalist. Guimard wrote on his
drawings "Style Guimard".
The German word Jugendstil is derived from
the Munich weekly Jugend ("Youth"), which was
launched in 1896. In 1900 Berlin critics wishing
to disparage nonconformist paintings coined the
word Jugendstil ("Jugend style"), but in 1902
another critic took up the word as an apt descrip¬
tion of the fresh spirit of the new movement.
The German term Sezession ("secession") was
used to denote separatist movements opposed to
established and officially-supported groups of
artists and conservative, nationalistic cultural poli¬
cies. Secessionist exhibitions at Munich in 1892,
at Vienna in 1897 and at Berlin in 1898 were
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
ostentatiously internationalist. But the term Sezes-
sionstil ("Secession style") eventually came to be
associated with the work and approach of artists
working in Vienna.
All these terms were used both by conserva¬
tive critics and by advocates of the new trend,
which was known in Italy as Stile Liberty (after
Liberty of London, a leading manufacturer of
printed cotton fabric), and in Britain as "Modern
Style". Many ironical names were also coined,
including Dolce Stile Nuove in Italy, Style Nouille
("noodle style") in France, and Paling Stijl ("eel
style") or Coup de fouet ("whiplash") style in
Belgium.
In many countries the new style became an
emblem of a struggle for political independence
and cultural identity, and artists often claimed to
belong to the movement even when their work
showed otherwise. In Finland and Hungary, for
example, the more abstract motifs of Art Nouveau
Above, detail of façade, 185
rue Belliard, Paris, 1913.
Right, 34 avenue de Wagram,
Paris, by Jules Lavirotte,
1904. Sculpture by Laphilippe.
were enriched by borrowings from folklore and
history. There seems to have been a common
effort to discover and define through the move¬
ment a truly national art which could replace out¬
moded international and historicist styles. In
many cases Art Nouveau proved unsatisfactory
for this purpose and more monumental styles
were evolved to satisfy national aspirations.
Architects
and art magazines
The search for distinctive national styles seems
inconsistent with the rapid international vogue
for Art Nouveau. Few Art Nouveau architects
worked exclusively in their country of origin.
Although Horta in Brussels, Guimard in Paris,
Saarinen in Helsinki and Wagner in Vienna all
found commisions in their native cities, the Bel¬
gian architect van de Velde emigrated to Ger¬
many and worked at Hagen, Berlin and Weimar.
His hopes of settling in Paris came to nothing.
Joseph Maria Olbrich of Vienna, who founded
the artists' colony at Darmstadt in 1889 on the
invitation of the Grand Duke of Hesse, worked
in Germany until his death in 1908. One of the
finest Jugendstil buildings in Munich is by the
Hungarian architect F. Nyilas, and the Italian
architect Raimondo d'Aronco was employed by
the Sultan in Istanbul when he designed the
pavilions for the 1902 Turin Exhibition which
made his name. Charles Rennie Mackintosh
worked in Glasgow (Scotland), but also executed
commissions for Viennese clients. The Viennese
architect Hoffmann's best-known design is the
Palais Stockt in Brussels.
The new theories were also transmitted
through Europe by schools of architecture. Otto
Wagner's classes at the Vienna Art School
attracted pupils from the countries of the Austro-
Hungarian monarchy and their neighbours,
including Italy. Yugoslavians and Scandinavians
studied at German universities and Scandinavian
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
From left to right and top
to bottom: entrance to
machine hall, Zollern coal
mine (Fed. Rep. of
Germany), by Bruno
Möhring, 1902. Pediment of
private house, Calle Llausá,
Barcelona. Window of
Saint-Cyr hotel, Brussels, by
Gustave Strauwens, 1903.
Entrance to apartment
building, Katajanokka
residential district of
Helsinki, c. 1900. Faenza
theatre, Bogota, c. 1900.
Entrance, Gallery of
Modern Art, Subotica
(Yugoslavia), by F. Reichl,
1904. Detail of façade,
Avenue Cogels-Osylei,
Antwerp (Belgium), by Jos
Bascourt, 1895.
MANFRED SPEIDEL is
professor of the theory of
architecture at the Technical
University, Aachen (Fed. Rep. of
Germany). The author of a
history of traditional and modern
Japanese architecture (1983), he
has recently edited the complete
works of the German architect
Bruno Taut (1880-1938).
students visited Britain. Finland and Hungary had
artistic connections with many other countries.
It was largely due to these schools, and to
magazines such as The Studio in England, Dekora¬
tive Kunst in Germany, and many others, that
the new ideas spread so rapidly. Only two years
after it had begun publication, Jugend was
warning against the dangers of copying the new
style. The designs which appeared in its pages
became so popular that after 1900 they were pro¬
tected by copyright.
Outside Europe the new ideas spread through
colonial or post-colonial connections, such as
those between Britain and the Commonwealth
and between Spain and Latin America. European
architects and their local colleagues enriched the
new style with injections of local tradition. It is
impossible to list all the exchanges, direct and
indirect, national and international, which created
the paradox of an international movement
embracing a tangle of national and local Art Nou¬
veau styles.
This complex and subtle style became so
widespread that there are few cities where
unknown local builders or plasterers have not
enriched entrance halls, staircases or windows
with Art Nouveau motifs, thus endowing entire
urban districts with a distinctive appearance and
atmosphere.
The triumph of asymmetry
Elaborate decorative effects and the subtle inter¬
play of surface textures were not the only achieve¬
ments of Art Nouveau. The freedom of
asymmetry was rediscovered in planning floor-
space, together with new ideas about movement
and space in domestic architecture. A new
architectural vocabulary was created at Otto
Wagner's School in Vienna, expressed in the
extensive use of horse-shoe- and omega-shaped
arches over doors or windows, perhaps
influenced by Islamic or Chinese architecture.
Equally typical is the contrast between massive
walls, pillars and other structural elements and
the airy lightness of the roofs and skylights
between them. The Wagner School also
introduced the curtain wall, a concept adapted
by Olbrich for his entrance gate to the Darmstadt
Exhibition in 1901 in the form of a huge piece
of cloth hung between two towers.
The shapes of buildings were also radically
modified. Olbrich, for example, designed houses
at Darmstadt with oblique or curved polygonal
walls which foreshadowed the dynamic lines
made possible by reinforced concrete in the 1920s
and the automobile-age architecture of Erich
Mendelsohn.
Art Nouveau, bold yet delicate, has some¬
thing in common with the art of Debussy. Once
again it has captured the imagination of a world
tending towards uniformity, but its subtlety, like
that of the plants which inspired it, renders it
fragile and difficult to preserve. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE FARAWAY SOURCES
JAPAN
A fresh look
iT is widely recognized that the Japanese aesthetic,
and especially its penchant for disymmetry and decora¬
tive surfaces, was one of the principal sources of inspi¬
ration for Art Nouveau, which reached Japan in the
early years of the twentieth century. What kind of
reception did it have in this country to which it owed
so much?
Art Nouveau was introduced to Japan by a handful
of artists and architects returning from Europe. In 1900,
the artist Asai Chu, who was studying in Paris with
the decorator Fukuchi Fukuichi, was invited by Samuel
Bing to visit his Art Nouveau pavilion at the Universal
Exhibition. A champion of the avant-garde and a col¬
lector of Oriental art, Bing had visited Japan in 1875
and had become a promoter of Japanese art forms and
culture in France.
Another friend of Asai was Natsume Kinnosuke,
who under the pen-name of Natsume Soseki became
one of Japan's leading modern novelists. He too visited
the Paris Exhibition and then moved to London where
he lived for three years. He was a great art-lover and
a regular reader of the avant-garde English magazine
The Studio.
On his return to Japan, Asai was appointed profes¬
sor at the School of Decorative Arts that had recently
been founded in Kyoto. Besides working as a painter,
he was responsible for a number of creative innova¬
tions in the decorative arts, especially in the techniques
of maki-e (painting in gold and silver on lacquer). The
influence of Art Nouveau on his work, as well as on
that of Fukuchi, is evident.
Natsume was equally receptive to Art Nouveau.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
at traditional forms BY HIROYASU FUJIOKA
In 1905 he published the first volume of his novel
Wagahai wa neko de aru ("I Am a Cat"). The cover,
by Hashiguchi Kiyoshi (also known as Goyô) was in
Art Nouveau style. Art Nouveau influence was even
stronger in the cover designs of the second volume
(published in 1906) and of his other books, which were
produced by the same artist, closely supervised by
Natsume himself.
Outside this restricted circle, Art Nouveau had
little effect on the decorative arts. Much greater was
its influence on architecture, which reached Japan via
architects who visited Europe or the United States or
who had contacts with Europeans.
The new style from the West influenced the design
of many shops, especially their façades. One noted
example of this fashion, which continued until the
mid-1910s, was the "Kamimoto Barber Shop", built
at Osaka in 1903 but since demolished.
The best known of these architects was Takeda
Goichi, who visited Glasgow during a trip to Europe
between 1901 and 1903 and was greatly impressed by
the works of the Scottish architect Charles Rennie
Mackintosh. On his return to Japan, Takeda designed
a house for Fukushima Yukinobu which was the most
typical of the buildings inspired by Art Nouveau in
Japan. In this house, completed in 1907 and now
demolished, the influence of Art Nouveau was apparent
throughout, from the front door to the motifs on the
fusumathe traditional movable partitions.
Few buildings incorporated the sinuous lines dear
to Horta or Guimard. Takeda himself favoured the
rectilinear style of Mackintosh and the architects of
the Vienna Secession as being more in keeping with
traditional Japanese architecture.
Generally speaking, Japanese artists, bound up as
they were with the artistic style and craftsmanship of
their own country, showed little enthusiasm for Art
Nouveau. Even Takeda only worked sporadically in
what he regarded as just one new style among others.
This lack of interest may perhaps be explained by
the resounding success achieved by Japanese decora¬
tive arts at a number of great international exhibitions
held in Europe and the United States. Seeing this as
an opportunity to develop Japanese exports, the
government strongly encouraged the traditional arts.
The important thing for Japanese artists was to create
a purely national art rather than a European art form
seen through Japanese eyes.
The situation in architecture was different. The
Meiji government, established in 1867, wanted to show
the people of the West that Japanese civilization was
a match for their own. Buildings comparable to those
in Western cities should be constructed as a matter of
prestige. And Art Nouveau did not seem to lend itself
to the concept of "prestige architecture".
The overall impact of Art Nouveau in Japan was,
however, far from negative. Art Nouveau demonstrated
that it was possible to look at traditional forms through
new eyes and gave Japanese architects an opportunity
to concentrate once more on design, to emphasize the
importance of surfaces and the aesthetics of disymmetry.
It also helped them to achieve a new awareness of their
own traditions.
From left to right: cover
design by Hashiguchi Kiyoshi
(Goyô) for the second volume
of Natsume Soseki's novel /
Am a Cat, 1906. Ink blotter
in silver and horn by Ernest
Cardeilhac, France, 1900.
Netsuke (Japanese ornamental
toggle) carved from boxwood
in a mushroom design, late
18th century. The Watch of
the Angels, appliqué on felt by
Henry van de Velde, 1893.
Woman with an Umbrella,
print by Okajima Toyohiro
(1773-1828).
HIROYASU FUJIOKA, of
Japan, is associate professor in the
architecture department of the
Tokyo Institute of Technology.
A specialist in modern
architecture and town planning,
he has published a number of
articles on Japanese architecture,
focused particularly on the
conservation of his country's
cultural heritage. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
From Horus to Aïda
BY MONA ZAALOUK
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
THE FARAWAY SOURCES
EGYPT
SUSPENDED in time between the medieval and the
modern, a handful of Cairo buildings inspired by Art
Nouveau principles have survived in a city in the throes
of a building boom as monuments to the complex cul¬
tural relationship between Egypt and Europe in the
nineteenth century.
Art Nouveau was an eclectic movement and its
adepts sought new ideas and sources of inspiration out¬
side Europe. In this they continued a trend that may be
said to have started in the eighteenth century when the
Baroque movement had shown an interest in Oriental
motifs. In the nineteenth, an age of rapid political, tech¬
nological and economic upheaval, new developments in
popular journalism, the increasing use of photography
and the telegraph and many other improvements in
communication and transport hastened the propagation
of ideas, forms and discoveries from country to country.
A flow of travel books, guidebooks and magazines were
produced, stimulating European interest in distant lands
and peoples. Late in the century Art Nouveau was a
mirror of this new receptivity and among the many
influences that shaped it those of ancient Egyptian art
and thought played a part, albeit subtle and indirect.
A key episode in the transmission of Egyptian cul¬
tural influence to Europe was Napoleon's expedition
to Egypt in 1799. Over 120 scholars accompanied the
expedition with instructions to study and catalogue
Egyptian monuments. The results of their work, pub¬
lished in illustrated folio editions after 1809, laid the
foundations for a European vogue for styles in architec¬
ture, arts and crafts inspired by ancient Egypt.
Towards the end of the nineteenth century, echoes
of ancient Egyptian art and mythology can be found
in the work of European artists and thinkers seeking
to re-establish spiritual values in a materialistic society.
The fantastic dream world of Symbolism, one of the
many currents that flowed into the stream of Art
Nouveau, is in several ways reminiscent of Egyptian
mural paintingin its interest in themes of death and
the afterlife, in its fondness for the feminine.
A more direct Egyptian influence on Art Nouveau
can be seen in many of the decorative objects and
Top, falcon bowl in faience,
by Emile Gallé, 1885-1889.
Above, brooch with hornet
and lotus motifs, by Georges
Fouquet, 1901.
Below left, entrance to a
Brussels apartment building,
1900.
Opposite page, cigar box with
scarab motif, in wood and
"Favrile" iridescent glass, by
Tiffany Studios, Corona, New
York, c. 1900.
MONA ZAALOUK, an
Egyptian artist, has published
many articles in Cairo Today, a
magazine on art and literature.
jewellery created in the 1900s by artists such as Gaillard,
Gautrait, the Pier brothers and Georges Fouquet.
Working with precious metals and stones, coloured
glass and enamels, they used motifs from ancient Egyp¬
tian art such as the lotus flower, the scarab, the snake
and the winged god Horus. In ancient Egypt too, art
had permeated everyday life, an ambition shared by
Art Nouveau artists.
While Europe was discovering Egypt, Egypt began
to turn its eyes to Europe. As part of his drive to
modernize the country, the visionary Egyptian leader
Mohammed Ali (1769-1849) created scholarships and
encouraged scholars, thinkers and researchers to go to
France to study. By the second half of the nineteenth
century many upper class Egyptians were looking to
Europe as a source of fashion. The Cairo Opera House,
built by Khedive Ismail for the first performance of
Verdi's Egyptian-inspired opera Aïda, staged to mark the
opening of the Suez Canal, is a smaller replica of La Scala
in Milan. Both in Europe and in Egypt it had become
current to look to other cultures for inspiration.
When, around the beginning of this century, many
European artists, craftsmen, architects and intellectuals
emigrated to Egypt, they thus found no lack of patrons
among well-to-do Egyptians who were eager to adopt
European habits and models. One result of this encoun¬
ter was that a new style of architecture inspired by Art
Nouveau began to appear in Cairo and Alexandria,
replacing the traditional style practised since the
Fatimid era. Elaborate sculptural ornamentation was
introduced into private homes and public buildings.
Human figures or columns, or intertwined plants,
replaced the more sober traditional architecture which
also, however, had featured ornamented ceilings and
was initially a source of inspiration for Art Nouveau.
Notable buildings of this period include the Cecil
Hotel in Alexandria and Cairo's Cosmopolitan Hotel
and Groppi tea-rooms, the latter built by a Swiss
emigrant. Patient exploration would reveal other more
anonymous examples of the period dwarfed beneath
the tower blocks of modern Cairo. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The house as a total work
of art BY CECILE DULIERE
Y STUDTHE- IO
An Hla/trMed AA^^inc
of Fine ¿Applied An
4tLo<c/TCT$giiMT
LOSDON WC
MootHy
Top, cover of the English
magazine The Studio.
Above, vignette by Henry
van de Velde, 1905.
Opposite page, main staircase
of the Hôtel Solvay, Brussels,
by Victor Horta, 1894-1898.
Oil painting by Théo van
Rysselberghe, 1902.
22
JL HE birth of Art Nouveau can be dated to
1893, the year when the first issue of The Studio,
a magazine devoted to the propagation of ideas
about art in interior decoration, was published
in London. It was also the year in which the Bel¬
gian architect Victor Horta built the Hôtel
Tasselthe first private residence to be con¬
structed in a radically new technical and plastic
style and to be conceived as a "total work of art".
"Art Nouveau", a term which symbolized
a feeling that a new age was breaking away from
the past, was an artistic phenomenon closely
linked to the Industrial Revolution. In the
nineteenth century new forms of energy (elec¬
tricity), new mass-produced materials (iron and
glass) and new inventions (the railway, teleg¬
raphy, the telephone, photography) 'transformed
both landscapes and ways of living.
Confidence in human progress and faith in
the future were reflected in a series of great inter¬
national exhibitions. The first of these was held
in 1851 in London, the capital of the world's then
most powerful and most highly industrialized
country, in a vast construction of iron and glass,
the Crystal Palace. The 1851 Exhibition attracted
over six million visitors and was a huge popular
success. English artists were, however, revolted
by the ugliness of mass-produced articles for
everyday use. They mobilized in protest.
Arts and Crafts
The English artist William Morris (1834-1896)
launched a crusade against the "virus of ugliness".
He maintained that rather than enclosing them¬
selves in an ivory tower and serving only the
privileged few, artists should work for the greatest
number and play a part in the creation of
everyday objects. The distinction between artist
and artisan should be abolished, together with the
traditional differentiation between the "major"
arts (painting, sculpture, architecture) and
"minor" arts such as cabinet-making, ceramics,
and tapestry. Despite its rejection of the machine,
Morris's Arts and Crafts Movement was impor¬
tant for making the first attempt to apply artistic
principles to the fabrication of everyday
objectswhat later came to be known as design.
True to his principle of "decorative honesty",
Morris did not conceal the natural colour of the
bricks of the "Red House", the home he had
built at Upton in Kent, beneath the usual
covering of stucco, and he commissioned his
painter, architect and sculptor friends to decorate
and furnish its interior. In 1861, he established
his own firm, Morris and Company, in London,
to market the new artistic style of furnishing and
interior decoration which had become his major
preoccupation. Several English painters, sculptors
and architects followed his example and became
"artist designers".
Walter Crane (1845-1915), the "philosopher of
the nursery" as he was jokingly called, took
Morris's ideas even further. He set out to instil a
sense of beauty in children at the earliest possible
age and the success of his children's books did
much to publicize the ideas of the Arts and Crafts
Movement elsewhere in Europe. The propagation
of these ideas owed more, however, to a number
of specialized magazines, the most famous of which
was The Studio. An Illustrated Magazine ofFine and
Applied Art. Resolutely modern in tone and with
"Use and Beauty" as its motto, it carried inter¬
views with artists and reviews of exhibitions
organized prize competitions and was lavishlj
illustrated, mainly with photographs.
Morris brought a new style of floral decora¬
tion to his wallpapers and printed cotton and
velvet fabrics. Abandoning the stylized flowers
of the past, he established a much closer link with
Nature, selecting for his designs humble meadow
or garden plants such as pimpernels, daffodils,
violets and daisies or, more often, such climbing
plants as blackthorn and honeysuckle. His experi¬
ments with the decorative effect of sinuous plant
stems and silhouettes against a monochrome
background were continued by others including
Charles Annesley Voysey (1857-1941) and Arthur
Mackmurdo (1851-1942), who, in the early 1880s,
designed a number of flame-like abstract floral
motifs.
The sinuous lines of this floral decoration, the
dynamic play of interlaced curves, became the
hallmark of Art Nouveau whose influence was
transmitted through fabrics designed for soft fur¬
nishings and through the illustration and design
of books and magazines. The terms Modern Style
used in France, and Stile Liberty and Stile Inglese,
used in Italy, reflect the great debt Europe owed
to English proto-Art Nouveau.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Ill
F&i
!.
=v=_=-*»nr
ürát?.
^*¿T ^ l i\%
iá^f Rt
5a4 *U HLt ,#*
Ly#^
ti
all
A ¿'lam
ÜIb
ral Btl a
pit
B£ -^ Y
fliii 'í^- 'Yl F ,
3LJB^BI^'*^^^^i
^^^, Jf-AffMi
7 "
1 -
"
V
» f
*S i,
IM 5M
A S- ...
-
ñ
	"*"
«PS «
H
--^"""^ 	 - -4
; .. .
^?3
¿ SMr mm Bfa
i -
L II
rr7~JJI
c?Bsi=-.
ii
i
1
Y I -
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Below right and below, the
Villa Bloemenwerf, near
Brussels, by Henry van de
Velde, 1895. He also designed
the lady's gown.
It was in Belgium, however, that these new
ideas from England really blossomed and were
given an architectural dimension they had pre¬
viously lacked. It was from there that Art Nou¬
veau spread through Europe. In the 1880s Brussels
was a leading centre of avant-garde art. Formed
in 1883, the Brussels group known as "Les XX"
(the Twenty)which ten years later became "La
Libre Esthétique"invited the most original and
controversial foreign artists to its annual exhibi¬
tion (it was there that Van Gogh made his only
sale). From 1891, the exhibition was opened to the
applied arts and included items such as illustrated
books by Walter Crane, tapestries, ceramics and
even complete room furnishings, such as the
"craftsman's room", exhibited in 1895, created
by the architect and decorator Gustave Serrurier-
Bovy (1858-1910), who was the first to import
into Belgium textiles and objects made in
England.
William Morris's social and artistic ideas were
most fully adopted by the Belgian painter Henry
van de Velde (1863-1957), who gave up painting
in 1893 and devoted himself to the decorative arts
with the avowed intention of "destroying the
virus of ugliness". When he married, he decided
to create single-handed the entire décor of his new
homethe Villa Bloemenwerf in Uccle near
Brussels (1895). Going even further than William
Morris, he drew the plans for the house, designed
the furniture, the wallpaper, the cutlery and even
the clothes his young wife would wear. He
seemed to be a universal man, the "complete
artist". As a writer, he propagated his theory of
"ornamentation as a living necessity" engendered
by the dynamics of line, which "reflects primarily
the movement induced by the inner life"
In 1898, he established in Brussels his "arts
of industry, construction and ornamentation
workshops". His work was well received abroad,
particularly in Germany where he settled in 1901
and where his ideas about the decorative arts were
widely propagated.
A revolutionary architect
Art Nouveau was given full all-round expression
for the first time by the architect Victor Horta
(1861-1947) in the house he designed in 1893 for
Emile Tassel, a professor at the University of
Brussels. Conceived as a "total work of art", from
the foundations to the minutest detail of its
interior decoration, the Hôtel Tassel represented
a radical break with the architectural and decora¬
tive language of the past.
Horta revolutionized domestic architecture
by making full use of the qualities of iron as a
building materialit had hitherto been reserved
for constructions built by engineers, such as exhi¬
bition halls, railway stations, warehouses, green-
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Left, settee upholstered in
"Tulip" chintz, by Arthur
Mackmurdo, 1886.
Right, heating appliance,
Hôtel Solvay, Brussels, by
Victor Horta.
houses and the like. In 1889, as a young man,
Horta had seen the famous iron tower erected by
the French engineer Gustave Eiffel, but to use this
industrial material, thought of as vulgar, in the
construction of a house in a conformist bourgeois
setting was a huge challenge.
Far from concealing this bold initiative,
Horta gave prominence to bolts and rivets and
in so doing developed an entirely new architec¬
tural and decorative language. He radically altered
the disposition of the interior, which he opened
up by using delicately fashioned metal load-
bearing structures in place of partition walls. His
combined iron and glass partitioning enabled light
to penetrate to every corner and made the stair
well the glowing centre-piece of the residence.
This was an architectural plan of outstanding
originality.
The architect draws a plan and the façade of
a building is merely the reflection of this plan.
The layout of the interior, dictated by the tastes
and life style of the future occupants, is pre¬
eminent. As Horta wrote concerning the Hôtel
Winssingers (1894), a house is the "portrait" of
those who are going to live in it. In this case, the
layout of the main floor, its variation in levels
and the choice of furniture were all explained by
the fact that the wife of the man who had com¬
missioned the house could only move around
with difficulty.
In this kind of highly personalized architec¬
ture, everything is the architect's business. For
the Hôtel Tassel Horta designed the complete
interiorthe panelling, the windows, the mosaics,
the wall paintings, the carpets, the ironwork and
even the door handles. He also ensured the per¬
fect harmonization of the lighting and heating
equipment.
The architecture and decoration cannot be
separated. The line of the load-bearing structures
is prolonged and softened by the decoration,
which seems to originate from the supporting
pillars and to extend to the ceilings, the walls, the
floor, accentuating the continuity of the interior
space. Serpentine curves and counter-curves ter¬
minate in a whiplash. In them can be seen the
vital thrust of a growing plant, but a plant with
neither flower nor leaf. "What I like in a plant,"
said Horta, "is its stem." Making use of the widest
possible variety of materials, Horta exploited the
contrasts of texture and colourthe cold smooth¬
ness of marble, the ribbing of dull riveted metal,
CECILE DULIERE, Belgian
archaeologist and an official at
her country's cultural heritage
ministry, teaches at the Royal
Academy of Fine Arts, Brussels.
She was curator of the Horta
Museum from 1975-1980 and
has edited the memoirs of
Victor Horta, published in
1985. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
the softness of light-coloured wood fashioned like
sculpture.
The success of the Hôtel Tassel earned Horta
commissions for two more prestigious houses,
one for the industrial magnate Armand Solvay,
the other for Edmond van Eetvelde. In both cases
provision had to be made for vast reception areas,
but, faithful to his principles, Horta adapted the
plans for the two buildings to match the per¬
sonalities of his clients. For the Hôtel Solvay he
designed a quadrangular double staircase as the
setting for a magnificent pointilliste painting; for
the Hôtel van Eetvelde, an octagonal area with
an oblique staircase of the utmost refinement.
Horta not only designed everything, he also
personally supervised the execution of every
detail of the work which he entrusted to the finest
craftsmen. The cost in work, time and money
was considerable.
The rich clients who commissioned Horta to
build these fine residences belonged to the class
of businessmen and industrialists that had
emerged from the Industrial Revolution. In this
new architecture, which was freed from the
burden of mixed styles and made extensive use
of new techniques and materials, they saw the
expression of their time "à temps nouveaux, art
nouveau" ("a new art for new times").
In 1896, Horta was asked to build the new
Maison du Peuple in Brussels. Behind its cur¬
vilinear façade of glass and iron, it housed co¬
operative shops, a café and offices. On the first
floor was a vast room for meetings of Belgium's
young Socialist Party, fêtes and conferences. The
site, in the centre of the city, was expensive and
some of the funds for it were donated to the
Socialist Party by Armand Solvay, man of
progress, founder of scientific institutions and one
of Horta's clients.
The inauguration, in 1899, of this "house
whose luxury was in the air and light so long
excluded from the workers' hovels", was the
occasion of enthusiastic celebrations that marked
the high point of the period of grace during which
the progressive bourgeoisie and the Belgian
Socialist Party combined their efforts in a
common faith in the universality of progress and
culture.
Dissension began to appear at the beginning
of the new century. Art Nouveau became
fashionable and many brilliant architects busily
emulated Horta. In new districts of Brussels Art
Nouveau façades mushroomedmore than 500
of outstanding interest have been counted,
earning the city the title of "the capital of Art
Nouveau". But these are mainly personalized
façades of buildings whose layouts are extremely
banal. The house as "a total work of art", as con¬
ceived and built by Victor Horta, was, alas,
beyond the means of most people.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
From fantasy
to
functionalism
BY ANDREAS LEHNE
I
Portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer,
by Gustav Klimt, 1907.
N 1895, a German specialist in Oriental art
named Samuel Bing (1838-1905) opened a gallery
in Paris which he called "L'Art Nouveau".
Among the modern artists whose works he
showed were Henry van de Velde, Louis Com¬
fort Tiffany, Félix Vallotton and Constantin
Meunier.
These works were praised in the German
press, and some of them were shown in Dresden
in 1897 at an international art exhibition at which
van de Velde's interior designs caused a sensation.
Van de Velde, who was soon inundated with
commissions, became the driving force behind
Jugendstil, the German version of Art Nouveau.
Jugendstil in Munich
However, it was Munich, not Dresden, which
became the main centre from which the influence
of Jugendstil would spread in Germany. A rela¬
tively small city, Munich had become the leading
artistic centre of nineteenth-century Germany
thanks to the ambitious policies of the Wittels-
bachs, the Bavarian ruling house. In 1893, the 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
. £: x-.:.~.
riin.i lÉiÉiiini
Entrance to the Vienna
Secession House, by Joseph
Maria Olbrich, 1898-1899.
28
ANDREAS LEHNE, Austrian
art historian, works with the
Austrian National Office of
Historical Monuments. He has
published several works on 19th-
and 20th-century art.
Munich public discovered the works of the Dutch
Symbolist painter and illustrator Jan Toorop
(1858-1928), who displayed his mastery of the
new style in the sinuous locks of the Javanese girls
who feature in many of his paintings.
Hermann Obrist (1863-1927) was one promi¬
nent member of the new movement. In 1894, this
great traveller, familiar with all the trends of
avant-garde art, transferred to Munich the
embroidery workshop he had set up in Florence.
His embroidered wall hanging entitled Peitschen¬
hieb (1895; "Whiplash") is one of the finest
examples of German "floralism". This "brilliant
interlacing of stitches flowing over ornamental
forms like the cells of a living organism" has some
affinities with the celebrated stucco relief (now
destroyed) which embellished the façade of the
Berlin architect August Endell's Elvira photog¬
raphy studio (1897-1898), a fantastic piece of deco¬
ration which was also endowed with organic life.
Both these artists sought to vie with Nature.
The Munich painter Richard Riemerschmid
(1868-1957) revolutionized interior design
through his blend oíJugendstil and local tradition.
In 1900 his "Room for an Art Lover" was shown
at the Paris Exhibition. He designed a theatre
whose fluent, elegant lines expressed a balanced,
mature style which had not yet become purely
geometrical. Riemerschmid was one of the co-
founders of the Vereinigte Werkstätten für Kunst
im Handwerk ("Workshops for Arts and Crafts")
which set out to raise the aesthetic standard of
everyday objects but, unlike the British Arts and
Crafts Movement, fully exploited the technical
possibilities of mass production.
The reputation of Munich was based essen¬
tially on its art journals such as Pan and the
popular magazine Jugend from which the German
Art Nouveau movement took its name.
Otto Eckmann (1865-1902) gave illustration
and typography a completely new look. In his
work plant forms meld into zoomorphic or
abstract motifs, in an endless metamorphosis.
Water changes into plants and plants into swans
or snakes which then acquire human attributes.
Typographical characters are intertwined like
creepers, then transmogrified into flames and bil¬
lowing columns of smoke.
Freshness, humour and satire are the
hallmarks of these journals, partly illustrated in
colour, which propagated the ideas oí Jugendstil
with great speed. In the pages of Pan and Sim-
plizissimus artists such as Gulbransson, Arnold,
Thöny and Paul published vitriolic caricatures;
a stylized dachshund playfully drawn by Theodor
Heine is transformed into a decorative motif full
of irony.
Jugendstil in Berlin
By the turn of the century, Berlin had become
a great modern city with a vigorous cultural life
which placed it in the forefront of modern trends.
In 1898, the artistic avant-garde finally turned its
back on the outmoded cultural policy of the
imperial court. Major architectural projects
showed the influence of passing trends. Van de
Velde designed spectacular shop interiors. With
modest resources at his disposal, August Endell
redecorated the auditorium of the Buntes
Theater, creating a world of bizarre, fantastic,
organic forms in a similar style to that of his
Elvira studio. The same harmony of colours was
used throughout, even in the uniforms of the
attendants. The department stores designed by
Bernhard Sehring and Alfred Messel still bore the
influence of historicism, but some features such
as the visible structure of the display windows
and the glass surfaces into which the façade dis¬
solves, prefigure modern architecture.
Above all, Berlin offers monumental, eclectic
variants oíJugendstil, one notable example being
the law-court in the Littenstrasse (1896-1905),
with its startling contrast between the building's
colossal dimensions and its graceful staircases.
Unlike Germany, the Austro-Hungarian
Empire (although Hungary had enjoyed a large
measure of autonomy since 1867) was a multina¬
tional state subject to the centralized power of
Vienna.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Vienna Secession
In Vienna Art Nouveau found a champion in
Otto Wagner (1841-1918), who was professor
of architecture at the Vienna Academy and a pas¬
sionate advocate of the need for an architectural
style detached from historical pastiche and
responsive to the demands of the modern age.
"Only the functional can be beautiful," he told
his students.
In the stations of the Vienna metropolitan
railway, which he was commissioned to design
in 1894, Wagner initially exploited all the graphic
resources of floralism, but soon moved towards
a more economical, functional style. He faced
his "Majolica House" with a cladding of ceramic
tiles to provide easy maintenance and a solid
appearance, deliberately limiting embellishment
to surface decoration. The influence of Art
Nouveau was totally absent from his Cubist-
style apartment blocks on the Linke Wienzeile.
The Austrian version of Art Nouveau was
created in 1897 by a group of avant-garde artists
who founded the movement known as the
Wiener Sezessionthe Vienna Secession. "This
freshly kindled flame needs an appropriate setting
to display it, a home of its own", wrote one con¬
temporary art critic. Such a building, the Haus der
Left, Samuel Bing's Art
Nouveau pavilion at the
Universal Exhibition, Paris,
1900.
Below, auditorium of the
Buntes Theater, Berlin, by
August Endell, 1901.
V
.V.NVhV.V.
.\V.7mV..i
	 -I. .Z, a.-. -,..	-	 '«
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Wiener Sezession (the Secession House, 1898-
1899), was designed by Joseph Maria Olbrich
(1867-1908), the most gifted of Wagner's pupils.
It resembles a classical temple, but is surmounted
by a dome of golden leaves, symbolizing Art
Nouveau's break with traditional conventions.
In 1898, the Secession launched an ambitious
review, Ver Sacrum, and organized in the Seces¬
sion House successful exhibitions encompassing
all the arts. For one exhibition devoted to
Beethoven in 1902, Gustav Klimt (1862-1918), the
undisputed leader of the Secessionists, painted
frescoes inspired by the Ninth Symphony, which
was conducted for the occasion by Gustav
Mahler.
At the same exhibition, Josef Hoffmann
(1870-1956), another Secessionist and former
pupil of Otto Wagner, showed an abstract, Cubist
sculpture which, despite passing virtually unno¬
ticed at the time, heralded an important turning-
point in the history of Viennese Art Nouveau.
The age of ornamentation was coming to an
end. Following the example of Hoffmann (and
also displaying a strong Scottish influence),
geometrical forms suddenly took over. From
now on, ornamentation was only sparingly used
and priority was given to exploiting the beauty
of natural materials.
Hoffmann showed the full measure of his
talent in the residence he built in Brussels
between 1905 and 1911 for the Belgian financier
Adolphe Stockt. A total work of art, in the spirit
of Horta, the Palais Stoclet, despite a certain
luxuriance, marks the triumph of pure, unembel-
lished forms displayed to full advantage by quality
materials and fine craftsmanship.
30
Left, façade of the
Majolikahaus ("Majolica
House"), Vienna, by
Otto Wagner, 1898.
Right, detail of the
Hochzeitsturm
("Wedding Tower") at
Mathildenhöhe,
Darmstadt, by Joseph
Maria Olbrich,
1905-1908.
In a series of brilliant articles Adolf Loos
(1870-1933) attacked Jugendstil as contrary to
the very principles of modern (by which he
meant something like "hygienic") civilization.
Hostile to ornamentation, he was the pioneer of
an international urban style.
In other parts of the Austro-Hungarian
empire the use of folk imagery was seen as a
means of creating a genuinely national architec¬
ture. The Hungarian version of Jugendstil con¬
tains many references to folklore. The tension
between Viennese cosmopolitanism and national
roots was felt by many of Otto Wagner's pupils
during the inter-war period. It was most fruitfully
expressed in the work of the Slovak architect
Josef Plecnik, known as the "Slav Gaudi", who
successfully reconciled the demands of function-
alism, formal invention and inspiration from
folklore.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Darmstadt:
the rigours of form
A notable champion of new ideas in the arts,
Grand Duke Ernst Ludwig of Hesse-Darmstadt
(1868-1937) commissioned two British architects,
M. H. Baillie-Scott and C.R. Ashbee, to work on
the private apartments of his palace. Wishing to
encourage his country's arts and crafts, he invited
a number of leading modern artists to settle in
Darmstadt and work there in complete freedom,
their material needs taken care of. The colony
of artists which came into being in 1899 on
Mathildenhöhe hill near Darmstadt was thus
meant to express one of the major aspirations
of Jugendstil, the synthesis of art and life. One
member of the colony, the young Viennese
architect Olbrich, designed a "House of Work",
a "Temple" to the cult of artistic activity, as
well as the houses of all the artists except for
Peter Behrens (1868-1940) of Hamburg who
built his own. The almost crystalline limpidity
and rectilinear design of Behrens' house con¬
trasted with Olbrich's decorative approach
and aroused considerable interest. This building
marked the second, "purified", phase oí Jugend¬
stil. In Vienna, but also more generally, Jugend¬
stil now seemed to be simply a fashion, whose
commercial and industrial exploitation aroused
criticism.
Behrens was a key figure in these develop¬
ments. The former painter and illustrator of
Pan not only sealed the fate of floralism in
Germany, but soon became the pioneer of
architectural functionalism. The turbine factory
which he designed for the electrical firm A.E.G.
heralded the era of industrial architecture.
A number of architects who worked in his studio,
such as Walter Gropius, Mies van der Rohe
and Le Corbusier, later won an international
reputation.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Northern lights
BY MARIA NASHTSHOKINA AND BORIS KIRIKOV
.A.
32
Lrt Nouveau in Russian architecture was accom¬
panied by a profound interest in old traditions. At the
turn of the century, the enchantments of Nordic art,
with its powerful streak of archaism, were rediscovered,
and Russian artists dreamed of combining modern art
techniques with images from the folklore and wild
natural beauty of the north.
They were captivated not only by the medieval and
vernacular architecture of northern Russia, but also by
the culture of Finland and the Scandinavian countries.
For as well as being neighbours, or, in the case of the
Principality of Finland, linked to the Russian empire,
these countries were seen as being spiritually united.
This was the beginning of what Sergei Diaghilev called
a "Nordic Renaissance", in which curiosity about the
past and the Nordic identity rooted in it combined with
a strong desire to explore all the possibilities of new
forms of expression.
There were two major trends. The first was the
neo-Russian style, which drew inspiration from the
architecture of Novgorod, Pskov and northern Russia,
and flourished in Moscow. The second, with which
this article is concerned, was modern Nordic art, a
branch of Art Nouveau that flourished mainly in the
then capital of Russia, St. Petersburg (today Leningrad).
Its rise was closely linked to Finnish and, to a lesser
extent, Swedish "national Romanticism".
The affinities between the Finnish and the St.
Petersburg schools of architecture, nurtured by geo¬
graphical proximity, were further accentuated by the
presence in St. Petersburg of practising Finnish ar¬
chitects and by joint participation in national and
international exhibitions. The versatile painter Akseli
W. Gallén-Kallela (1865-1931), well-known for his
paintings inspired by the Finnish national epic, the
Kalevala, was one of the fathers of Finnish national
Romanticism. He took part in the Russian national
exhibition held at Nizhni-Novgorod in 1896 and in
others held in St. Petersburg, and produced many
architectural projects for St. Petersburg, Moscow and
Revel (now Tallinn).
Russian and Finnish architects harmoniously com¬
bined technical innovation and extreme stylization of
Scandinavian, Russian and Karelo-Finnish art motifs-
solar symbols, animal and plant imagesand skilfully
combined natural materials such as wood and stone.
The favoured setting for this style, St. Petersburg,
was a city with two faces. On the one hand it was a
bourgeois, mercantile, European city looking out over
the Baltic, a monumental, rapidly-growing Rome of
the north. On the other it was the result of an extraor¬
dinary encounter between the force of its natural set¬
ting and the force of the human will, an ephemeral
Babylon in danger of being swallowed up by the marsh¬
lands on which it had been built.
Nostalgia for the beauty of the natural world found
full expression in modern Nordic art. In the architec¬
ture of many St. Petersburg buildings this love of
Nature, so extreme that Diaghilev described it as
"pagan adoration", burst forth on façades teeming with
stylized animals, birds, fish, trees and flowers. Under
Finnish prompting, the expressive potential of rough,
grainy surfaces such as that of granite, and the evoca¬
tive power of combinations of natural and man-made
materials, were revealed. The rough masonry of the
walls recalled old Celtic legends of "evil stones".
Beneath the surface of daily life were strong romantic
undercurrents.
At that time there were Swedish and Finnish colo¬
nies in St. Petersburg. Born in St. Petersburg, but of
Swedish nationality, the brilliant architect F. Lidval
was the father of Nordic Modernism in the city. His
first major work (1899-1904), a forerunner of the
masterpieces he later created in Sweden, was an apart¬
ment house at 1-3 Kamenoostrovsky Avenue (now
Kirovskiy Avenue) which displays all the characteristics
of the new stylefree interplay of volumes, diversity
of window-design, subtle harmonization of materials,
and, from the mysterious world of the forest, ornamen¬
tation whose profusion in no way detracts from the
building's rational functionalism.
Perhaps the finest jewel in the crown of St. Peters¬
burg Nordic architecture is an apartment building at
11 Stremiannai'a Street (1906-1907) by N. Vasiliev
and A. Bubir. The highly stylized symbolism of the
ornamentation blends with the architectural structure
to form an organic whole. The elegant simplification
of form to which Nordic Modernism aspired here
achieves perfection.
It was in such buildings that the Nordic Renais¬
sance subtly reaffirmed the Baltic character of St. Peters¬
burg, while leaving its European aspects untouched.
Staircase window (detail),
apartment building in
St. Petersburg (now
Leningrad), by A. Gimpel and
V. Iliashev, 1905-1907.
MARIA NASHTSHOKINA, of
the USSR, is a researcher with
the National Institute of the
Theory of Architecture and
Town Planning, Moscow.
BORIS KIRIKOV, of the USSR,
is a researcher with the Institute
of the Theory of Architecture
and Town Planning, Leningrad.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
*.!K
I
From top to bottom and left to right:
gable of apartment building, St. Petersburg,
by F. Lidval, 1899-1904 (a).
Front door, Eira residential district,
Helsinki (b).
Entrance to Gorky Museum, Moscow,
1902 (c).
Detail of entrance porch, St. Petersburg, by
E. Morosov, 1911-1912 (d).
Front door, Katajanokka-Katudden district,
Helsinki (e).
Entrance, Eira district, Helsinki (f).
Colonnaded entrance, Katajanokka district,
Helsinki (g).
Sculpted ornament, house in Eira district,
Helsinki (h). 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Bracelet
by Lluís Masriera, 1900.
Modernist
Barcelona
BY ALBERT GARCIA ESPUCHE
W.HEN Barcelona's ancient fortifications were torn
down in the late nineteenth century to provide much-
needed room for the city to expand, the vast open
spaces around the old city became the site for develop¬
ment that made a major contribution to the history
of modern town planning.
In the 1870s the new Barcelona began to take shape
with the construction of a middle-class residential area
around the famous Paseo de Gracia thoroughfare. The
transformation and development of this part of the city
mark the emergence of Modernism (Modernismo), the
Catalan version of Art Nouveau.
By 1900, the high-water mark of Modernism, the
new city had already been mapped out. Around the
centre known as the Eixample (the Paseo de Gracia
and the streets nearby) with its prestige buildings, were
a number of cheaper housing schemes, large buildings
such as hospitals, prisons, and abattoirs, and an indus¬
trial estate.
In this area, Modernism found full expression in
major urban complexes such as the Sant Pau hospital
on the outskirts, and, in the centre, in the development
of the elegant area around the Paseo de Gracia which
came to be known as the "Quadrat d'Or" ("Golden
Rectangle"). Much private housing was built. Some
apartment blocks, such as Gaudi's Casa Milà (1905-
1910), popularly known as La Pedrera ("The Quarry")
replaced earlier buildings.
But as well as designing new apartment blocks,
Modernist architects transformed, improved and em¬
bellished existing buildings. The famous Modernist resi¬
dences in the Paseo de Gracia such as the Casa Lleó
Morera, the Casa Amatller and the Casa Batlló,
designed by the architects Lluís Domènech i Montaner,
Josep Puig i Cadafalch and Antoni Gaudi respectively,
were conversions of earlier buildings. Luxury shops
built on the ground floors of older houses were another
expression of this trend.
One striking feature of the new style was its
propensity to invade all forms of aesthetic expression.
At the turn of the century, the exuberant inventions 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
À
i
^ - %* ~E¿2
: ""
1 '"'
s*
Itp 1
Palau de la Música Catalana,
by Lluís Domènech i
Montaner, 1905-1908: above,
staircase; left, mosaic ceiling
(detail).
Below left, detail of mosaic
ceiling by Josep Pey, Casa
Lleó Morera, Barcelona.
Below right, settee by Joan
Busquets i Jane, 1902.
36
ALBERT GARCIA ESPUCHE,
Catalan historian of architecture,
is the author of a number of
publications including studies of
urban space and society in pre-
mdustrial Barcelona (1984), and
the architecture and design of the
1888 Universal Exhibition in
Barcelona (1989).
of Modernism formed the setting of middle-class life
in Barcelona, and fine Modernist paintings, drawings
and sculptures by Catalan artists such as Ramon Casas,
Santiago Rusiñol and Juan Llimona can still be admired
in the city's museums today.
The ornate interiors created by Modernist ar¬
chitects gave the impression that the refined and or¬
namental treatment of the façades had spilled over into
interior walls and ceilings. Floors, ceilings, chimney-
pieces, doors, windows and other features were all
designed and made with meticulous craftsmanship.
Tables, beds, cupboards, screens and other furnishings
were perfectly integrated into their setting, together
with other decorative elements such as carpets, lamps
and door-knobs.
The leading Modernist architects excelled at creat¬
ing such "total" environments. They enlisted the col¬
laboration of specialized artists and craftsmen who
under their direction produced a consistent output of
work that was as robust and exciting in its overall
design as in its component parts. The Palau de la Música
Catalana and the Sant Pau hospital designed by Lluís
Domènech i Montaner and his team are impressive
examples of this approach.
But architects such as Domènech and his contem¬
poraries Gaudi, Cadafalch, Rafael Masó, and Josep
Maria Jujol revealed even more astonishing skills when
they produced "total" works of art in more modest
settings. The Casa Lleó Morera is an outstanding
example of this. On a small triangular site with uneven
contours, Domènech i Montaner was faced with the
difficult task of embellishing an existing building and
transforming it into a representative example of the
new style. He made imaginative use of the site and
directed the work of artists and craftsmen who designed
all the external and internal features, from stained-glass
windows and sculptures to tiling and furniture. The
result was a marvellous transformation of a small non¬
descript building into a palace.
There are many examples of the outstanding skills
of Catalan Modernist architects and craftsmen. In
Gaudí's La Pedrera it is impossible not to admire the
ingenuity with which the stucco ceilings and stone
pillars were designed by his collaborator Josep Maria
Jujol, a man who could make a humble brass inkstand
that was a small masterpiece.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
BY ENRIQUE CAPABLANCA
A Cuban mythology
MCA C^
Entrance hall of the Museum
of Pharmacy, old city of
Havana, early 20th century.
M<LOST of the masons, stonecutters, blacksmiths, car¬
penters and other craftsmen who came from overseas
and settled in Cuba between 1902 and 1930 were of
Spanish, mainly Catalan, origin. They brought with
them their traditions, styles and techniques, and it
would be hard to overemphasize their role in the
development of Cuban Art Nouveau. At first the new
trend was even known by its Catalan name, Moder
nismo, and only several decades after its introduction
did the expression "Art Nouveau" come into use.
Although the direct Catalan influence was
undeniable, young local architects and craftsmen were
avid readers of foreign periodicals which made them
familiar with the main currents of Art Nouveau and
its variants. However, distance tended to blur percep¬
tions of the new style, which was often modified
ENRIQUE CAPABLANCA,
Cuban architect and sculptor, is a
staff member of the National
Centre of Conservation,
Restoration and Museology,
Cuba, and teaches at the
University of Havana.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Above, headquarters of the
"Golden Sceptre" company in
central Havana.
Below, an example of colonial
architecture, one of the
sources of inspiration for
Cuban Art Nouveau.
through contact with another world and a different
architectural tradition.
Because of a failure to clearly understand the
nature of the movement, any building heavily deco¬
rated with flowers and garlands was initially described
as Art Nouveau. Most of these buildings were actually
a compromise between the new aesthetic and fin-
de-siècle eclecticism, which sometimes worked surpris¬
ingly well. But the features and forms characteristic of
the new style were soon recognized and began to
appear in the streets of Havana and the other major
towns, especially in private residences. Art Nouveau
motifs were rarely seen in public buildings, perhaps
because the style was considered too frivolous to
represent the young republic in an appropriate
fashion.
Cuban Art Nouveau is heavily indebted to French,
Belgian, Italian and Catalan models. But it also has
its own originality. European influences were rapidly
assimilated because they had certain affinities with
Cuban culture. Composite arches, dynamic curves,
a taste for coloured ceramics and glass, and elaborately-
wrought ironwork, were long-established features of
the Cuban architectural heritage.
Like many of its European models, the Cuban
variant of Art Nouveau is a blend of styles, and
it is not unusual to see neo-Gothic, neo-Mudejar and
other historicist elements amicably rubbing shoulders
in many Cuban Art Nouveau buildings. Another
characteristic is the use of sculpted animal and human
forms, as well as plant motifs, to depict a kind of
mythology unique to Havana.
The popularity of Art Nouveau in Cuba was not
due to a small number of architects, but to a multi¬
tude of craftsmen who worked in the building trade
and created architectural features which were then mass
produced and used on hundreds of façades all over the
island.
Some of these building contractors were so suc¬
cessful that Art Nouveau was soon regarded as a
speciality of master masons and consequently as a
minor form of architecture. The next step was to
disparage the movement, and it was taken in the
1920s when art historians and critics dismissed it as
exaggerated and decadent. Architects concerned about
their reputation began to turn their backs on Art
Nouveau, and some of those who had contributed
to its rise turned towards more classical and conven¬
tional styles.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
ARGENTINA
An aesthetic revolution
BY JORGE O. GAZANEO
A.ROUND the turn of the century, the new visual
and structural language of Art Nouveau won a following
among many young Latin American intellectuals who
had studied in Paris, Brussels, Berlin and Barcelona, and
among a prosperous middle class whose members were
frequent visitors to these and other European cities.
One South American country in which it found
a particularly receptive terrain was Argentina, where
its products found favour with an élite of rural and city
landowners, bankers, merchants and investors. Some
members of this élite were descended from families
established in Argentina since the late eighteenth cen¬
tury, but most came of more recent immigrant stock
and belonged to an expanding well-to-do middle class
of first-generation Argentines. Many of them would
become key reformist and modernizing figures in
politics, the economy and the arts.
Argentina at the beginning of this century was a
democratic, progressive society in the throes of change. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
In the late nineteenth century the country had been
host to large'-scale immigration from Europe and a
massive infusion of foreign investment. There had been
a railway boom, major irrigation projects had been
undertaken, and residential areas had been constructed
for a burgeoning middle class employed in government,
commerce, industry and banking. A new generation was
coming to the fore with political ideas that were more
outward-looking than those of the old Creole Spanish-
colonial families which had painfully constructed the
republics-
Settlers and investors were welcomed by the host
society, especially in the port areas of Buenos Aires,
Rosario and Bahia Blanca, and by the end of the cen¬
tury the original identity of these cities had been modi¬
fied to the point where their colonial roots had almost
vanished. Buenos Aires in particular was an emporium
of banking and finance, the hub of government and
state employment. It was in these urban areas that Art
Nouveau flourished.
Recent studies suggest thai the coming of Art
Nouveau was part of a wider intellectual trend in
Argentine society in the late nineteenth century. As
one historian has written, "when in 1885 or there¬
abouts some of the more thoughtful young intellectuals
directed their interests to socialism and politics, others
chose to engage in the fight for the renewal of the arts".
Just as there were political links between the Partido
Socialista Argentino and the Belgian Workers Party,
there were also aesthetic links between Argentina and
the Brussels group La Libre Esthétique and the period¬
ical L'Art Moderne, both of which played an impor¬
tant role in the genesis and diffusion of Art Nouveau.
Preserved in the library of the Faculty of Architecture
at the University of Buenos Aires are collections of
European periodicals which popularized new trends
in the arts, such as The Studio, Art et Décoration and
La Revue des Arts Décoratifs, also suggesting that the
adepts of the new style were well informed and con¬
nected with their European colleagues.
Argentine architects and decorators imported
building materials in bulk from Europe, mainly from
France and Belgium. Complete sets of furniture came
from the Belgian architect Gustave Serrurier-Bovy; mir¬
rors, stained glass, bronze and ivory from Lauque and
Gallé; iron structures from Usines Eiffel. Space was
handled in accordance with what European masters had
accomplished using the new technical resources that
had emerged from the Industrial Revolution. Buildings
were more open to the air and sun since the use of iron
made it possible to design wide openings in what had
formerly been exclusively load-bearing walls. The
colours of new materials such as majolica and irides¬
cent glass offered local craftsmen a range of decorative
possibilities never seen before. The results were exciting
and eye-catching when compared to the prevalent drab
Victorian or French Empire styles, and rich in pastel
colours. Today most of these interiors have disappeared
or look diminished as parts of the furnishings have been
dispersed or replaced with unsuitable intrusions.
The aesthetic impact of Art Nouveau was destined
to be short-lived in Latin America where, a late
response to the Belle Epoque way of life, it faded away
after the First World War.
Above, the corner of this
Buenos Aires building, by J.J.
Garcia Nunez, is reminiscent
of the Hôtel Tassel in
Brussels (detail, right),
designed by Victor Horta in
1893.
il
tasa
JORGE O. GAZANEO,
Argentine architect and member
of the International Council of
Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS),
teaches at the Belgrano
University and at the University
of Buenos Aires.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF
Population and the
environment
World population is
increasing by 3 people every
secondabout a quarter of
a million each dayfaster
than at any point in history.
The highest rate of
demographic growth is in
developing countries. This
increase could have
catastrophic consequences
for the environment, warns
the 1990 report from the
United Nations Fund for
Population Activities
(UNFPA), which suggests
action in three major areas:
change from fossil fuels to
renewable resources such as
wind and solar energy; halt
deforestation; and slow
down population growth.
The first flower
A 120-million-year-old fossil
just over 2 cm long may be
the ancestor of today's
flowering plants, according
to researchers at Yale
University (USA). The fossil,
unearthed a decade ago In
Australia, was thought to be
that of a non-flowering fern.
High-resolution photography
has now shown it to be a
portion of a branch from an
angiosperm, a plant whose
seeds are enclosed in an
ovary. This discovery may be
the "missing link" which will
explain the apparently
sudden appearance, in
evolutionary terms, of large
flowering plants.
Simón Bolívar Prize
Vaclav Havel, President of
Czechoslovakia, has been
awarded the International
Simón Bolívar Prize for 1990.
The $25,000 prize,
established in 1983, is
awarded every two years by
the Director-General of
Unesco. Its purpose is to
reward activity of
outstanding merit which has
contributed to the freedom,
independence and dignity of
peoples and to the
strengthening of a new
international economic,
social and cultural order, in
accordance with the ¡deals
of Simón Bolívar, the
Venezuelan Liberator. Such
activity may take the form of
Intellectual or artistic
creation, a social
achievement or the
mobilization of public
opinion. Former laureates
include King Juan Carlos of
Spain and Nelson Mandela,
who was awarded the prize
during his imprisonment.
Spanish gold
A gold ingot, not much
bigger than a chocolate bar
but weighing 680 g, has
been salvaged from a
Spanish galleon wrecked off
south-west Florida. The
wreck is thought to be part
of a treasure-laden convoy of
ships that set sail from
Havana in 1622, nine of
which were destroyed In a
hurricane. The ingot was
brought to the surface by an
ultra-sophisticated
underwater recovery vehicle,
a remote-controlled
computerized machine with
the capacity to map, film
and pick up objects as small
as a grape pip.
Letters from the
Americas
A 16th-century manuscript
copy of unpublished
correspondence from
Christopher Columbus to the
Spanish rulers Ferdinand and
Isabella has recently come to
light. Historians consider
these letters, in which
Columbus describes his
voyages of exploration, to be
a valuable contribution to
the 500th anniversary of the
European discovery of the
Americas, to be
commemorated in 1992. The
correspondence has now
been published, with an
accompanying volume of
critical study, by the Spanish
Ministry of Culture and
Testimonio Compañía
Editorial, Madrid, as part of
the "Tabula Americae"
collection on the discovery
and the encounter between
two worlds.
Spanish-American
co-production
Isabella and Ferdinand of
Spain, the legendary royal
couple who were granted
the title of "Catholic
sovereigns" by Pope
Alexander VI, are to be the
subjects of an ambitious
Spanish-American television
series in 6 episodes. The 15-
million-dollar co-production,
in English, aims to paint a
historically accurate picture
of 15th-century Spain. The
noted American scriptwriter
for the series, James
Goldman, will be advised by
Spanish historians. Filming
will take place entirely in
Spain and is expected to be
completed by 1992.
Frogs sound the alarm
Zoologists all over the world
are alarmed by the rapid
decline of the frog
population in several regions
of the United States,
Canada, Australia and in
some European countries
such as the UK, Denmark,
Poland and Hungary. The
cause of the frogs'
disappearance is thought to
be climate changes brought
about by degradation of the
environment, acid rain, and
pollution by herbicides and
pesticides. According to Pere
Alberch, director of the
Natural History Museum in
Madrid and a specialist on
amphibians, frogs are
hypersensitive to climate
changes and their declining
numbers should be seen as a
warning.
The birth of a dinosaur
Spanish researchers have
reconstituted the skeleton of
a hitherto unknown type of
dinosaur from fossilized
bones found at Lérida, in the
southern foothills of the
Pyrenees. Pararhabdodon
isonense, a herbivore of the
Iguanodon family, lived some
65 million years ago. It was
5 metres long, had very
short forelimbs and walked
on Its hind legs.
Palaeontologists are
particularly interested in this
discovery because it dates
from the late Secondary Era,
when dinosaurs were
virtually extinct.
Children's rights
After ten years of preparation,
the Convention on the Rights
of the Child was adopted by
the United Nations on 20
November 1989. For the first
time in the history of
international law, children's
rights have been codified in
the form of a treaty which
will be legally binding on
signatory states. The
Convention modifies and
consolidates the existing
standards on children's rights
and introduces a range of
new issues of major
importance. Its provisions
cover anyone under 18
except in countries where
legal majority is attained
earlier. The Convention will
enter into force when 20
countries have ratified it. To
date there are 7 signatories
(Ghana, Viet Nam, the
Vatican, Belize, Guatemala,
Ecuador, France).
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
H
UNESCO AND
'ARCHITECTURE WITH A SMILE'
BY HANS-DIETER DYROFF
N,Iineteen countries* are today co¬
operating in a Unesco project to
study and protect the architectural
heritage of Art Nouveau and
Jugendsi// described at a recent
meeting of specialists as "architecture
with a smile".
The notion of cultural dialogue,
today a central feature of Unesco's
programme, was already fore¬
shadowed in the Art Nouveau move¬
ment. Nowhere Is this more apparent
than in the Hungarian town of
Kecskemet, where the seeds of the
Unesco project were sown at a meet¬
ing of specialists held in 1985.
Kecskemet has a number of magnifi¬
cent buildings dating from the turn
of the century, including a town hall
designed by the Hungarian architect
Odön Lechner (1 845-1 91 4). Though
uniquely Hungarian, these buildings
are also the product of a closely knit
network of international influences
and exchanges, and bear witness to
a powerful movement whose dynam¬
ics spread not only through the coun¬
tries of Europe but also to other
continents.
The Art Nouveau project soon
generated great interest. The German
ft
National Commission for Unesco in
Bonn, which acted as co-ordlnator,
drew up an initial plan which won
wide approval at Unesco's General
Conference in 1985. The following
year, a group of European specialists
met at Heiligkreuztal in the Federal
Republic of Germany and defined Art
Nouveau architecture for the pur¬
poses of the projecta difficult task
in view of the great diversity of cre¬
ators and processes involved. They
adopted a definition which was
broad enough to include not only the
work of leading figures who set out
to use a combination of artistic skills
in order to create "all-inclusive works
of art" but also the contributions of
less well-known architects and builders
many of whom played an important
role, whether in shaping urban dis¬
tricts or in helping the transmission
of Art Nouveau internationally.
The next stage was to assemble
and evaluate information about Art
Nouveau buildings as a basis for pos¬
sible preservation work. A fund of in¬
formation about international
exchanges, building techniques and
especially the experimental use of
new materials at the turn of the cen-
1
tury has gradually been created. As
far as the spread of Art Nouveau is
concerned, it would be impossible to
emphasize too strongly the influence
exercised by popular illustrated peri¬
odicals such as the German magazine
Jugend, which made extensive use of
photographs to document new
trends in architecture and the arts.
Not surprisingly, therefore, one Im¬
portant activity of the Unesco project
is the assembling of photographic
documentation on Art Nouveau
buildings and on efforts being made
to preserve them. The Unesco Nation¬
al Commission of the German
Democratic Republic has already
mounted an exhibition which has so
far been shown in its country of ori¬
gin, in Finland and in the Federal
Republic of Germany. The other
countries participating in the project
intend to prepare similar exhibitions.
There are many reasons for the
growing interest in the project. One
of them is the fascination exercised
by an age in which the development
of new engineering tools and tech¬
niques, the expansion of transport
and communication, and belief in
progress, gave a strong impetus to
architectural and aesthetic innova¬
tions. Another is a general revival
of interest in the work of great ar¬
chitects such as Henry van de Velde,
Hermann Obrist, Otto Wagner, Eliel
Saarinen and many others.
A considerable amount of exper¬
tise and knowledge has by now been
accumulated, ranging from bibliog¬
raphies reflecting the current state of
research in different countries, to lists
of monuments, experts, firms, materi¬
als and other information. The
Unesco project group is now ready
to offer its advice and assistance to
specific conservation operations, fully
aware that its co-operation in such
efforts can only be based on the
initiative and involvement of local
groups.
* Argentina, Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Czechos¬
lovakia, Cuba, France, the Federal Republic of
Germany, Finland, the German Democratic
Republic, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Luxem¬
bourg, Norway, Portugal, the Soviet Union and
Yugoslavia
HANS-DIETER DYROFF, German art
historian, is director of the cultural section at
the German National Commission for Unesco
in Bonn (Fed Rep of Germany) He is the co¬
ordinator of Unesco's International joint study
and action project on Art Nouveau/Jugendstil
architecture
pSSma
42
T -Q- * -BAS n hmmmiM ' fliï 1 1
rrlfB « J? ^P^i^ffl
, . , ,r as-, mm mm '
T T T t|_
ají-. ---
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Drawing board dreams:
realization, restoration,
destruction
Far left, music room of the
"House for an Art Lover",
designed by Charles Rennie
Mackintosh in 1901 for an
architectural competition
launched by a Darmstadt
magazine. Mackintosh's project
is to be realized at lastthe
house is now being built at
Glasgow Left, design for the
Valtionhotelli (west façade) at
Imatra, Finland, by Usko
Nystrom, 1903-1905 This hotel
complex has recently been
meticulously restored. Right and
far right, interiors of the
Valtionhotelli after restoration.
Above, Art Nouveau motif on
the main façade of August
Endell's Elvira photography
studio, Munich, which was
demolished in 1944
H
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
^Htooftnrü
'A TERRIFYING AND EDIBLE BEAUTY'
BY EZIO GODOLI
Above and opposite page,
left to right: cover design by
André Derain for Minotaure
magazine.
No. 3-4, 1933, which
featured an article by
Salvador Dali on Modern
Style architecture. Four
aspects of Antoni Gaudi's
work in Barcelona: balcony.
Casa Batlló, 1904-1906;
dragon sculpture and
pavilion, Güell Park,
1900-1906; ornamental
chimney, Güell Palace, 1910.
44
/Art Nouveau architecture in Latin
Europe embraced such a wide range
of styles, even within individual coun¬
tries, that ¡t is hard to find a common
denominator between them.
It spread like a language, like a
lingua franca that was enriched by
contact with and borrowings from
local dialects, but kept unchanged
certain elements of syntax. A form of
architecture intent on collaboration
with all the figurative and decorative
arts, it could call on a wide diversity
of artistic traditions. Its composite
nature and its variety were due as
much to its cosmopolitan tendencies
as to a desire to extend the traditional
repertoire of regional or national art
forms.
Art Nouveau architecture deve¬
loped somewhat later in the Latin
countries than elsewhere in Europe
and, with the exception of Catalan
Modernism, in which the early stir¬
rings of a desire to affirm national
identity can be detected, there were
no strong local movements to help
it on its way.
Although it would be vain to try
to discover a common stylistic thread
linking the Latin countries of Europe
(with the possible exceptions perhaps
of Spain and Portugal), the poetics of
their distinct architectural languages
do share certain common features
which may help us define some
essentially Latin characteristics of Art
Nouveau architecture.
This line of approach was first
suggested by Salvador Dali in one of
the earliest and most penetrating
assessments of Art Nouveau architec¬
ture, his essay On the Terrifying and
Edible Beauty of Modern Style
Architecture, which was published in
1 933 in the Parisian surrealist maga¬
zine Minotaure.
With this provocative appraisal of
Art Nouveau architecture made in the
mid-1 930s, at a time when the rest
of the world subscribed to the the¬
ories of rationalist architecture, Dalí
issued a double message which
historians should take into account.
Drawing from the poetics of Art Nou¬
veau those elements most readily
assimilable by surrealist art, he
declared firmly that, between Art
Nouveau and the twentieth-century
avant-gardes, there was a network of
inter-relationships far more complex
than most historians admit. By
emphasizing the most "alogical",
almost "demential" aspects of Art
Nouveau architecture, he showed
that, to fully understand the contri¬
bution of Art Nouveau to modern art
and architecture, those works most
tainted with bad taste should not be
ignored. Highly significant artistic
statements can even be found by
rummaging through these artistic
rejects.
Some Art Nouveau buildings in
Paris and Barcelona possess the
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
"terrifying and edible beauty" of
which Dalí wrote (among the
examples used to illustrate the
Minotaure article were works by
Guimard, Jules Lavirotte and Gaudi1).
The values highlighted by Dalí are
found not only in Catalan and
Parisian Art Nouveau architecture but
also in that of other Latin regions.
This is particularly true of the quality
of "movement which. ..is primarily
intended to arouse a kind of great
'primeval hunger' ", like "the ultimate,
¡deal architecture which would
embody the most tangible and
delirious goal of hypermaterialism...
not only because It denounces the
violent materialistic banality of
immediate needs..., but also because
it unashamedly alludes to the nutri¬
tive, edible nature of houses of this
type, which are nothing other than
the first edible houses, the first and
only erogenous buildings whose
existence is an affirmation of that
'functional' trigger of the amorous
imaginationto be able in the realest
possible sense to eat the object of
desire."
Is not this need for "hypermateri¬
alism", given metaphorical expression
in the art of cooking, the thread that
links certain Paris buildings by S.
Wagon and Paul Auscher, whose
florid ornamentation calls to mind
some elaborate piece of confec¬
tionery, to those works of Gaudi
which are decorated with ceramics as
some cakes are decorated with crys¬
tallized fruit? Is it not also this same
need that links the subtle erotic allu¬
sions of certain Modernist Catalan
architects to the unabashed triviali¬
ties of Lavirotte's building in the
Avenue Rapp, in Paris, orto some of
the more fantastic projects of the
Italian architect Adolfo Coppedé?
Is not the revolutionary architec¬
tural framework that Gaudi, thanks
to his remarkable knowledge of con¬
struction techniques, introduced in
some of his buildings (one has only
to think of La Pedrera, which seems
to defy the laws of gravity, or of the
prolific Doric colonnades of the Güell
Park) in some respects a unique
manifestation of "the profound
devaluation of intellectual systems"?
And is it not in the Latin coun¬
tries that we find the most eye¬
catching examples of ornamental
excess, of "hysterical sculpture", of
the multiple metamorphoses of
Baroque/Art Nouveau and Rococo/
Art Nouveau pastiche, from which all
sense of restraint is absent? Are not
the dragons of a fantastic Orient
refashioned by Gaudi's imagination,
or the strange cast-iron fauna
evoking the world of the ocean
depths and recalling the sculptured
gargoyles of Gothic cathedrals, that
adorn Guimard's buildings and lend
their forms to his entrances to the
Paris Metro, virtually unique
examples, in the European context,
of that incursion into the fantastic
world of dreams, that return to
infancy of which Dalí speaks?
EZIO GODOLI, Italian art historian, is
professor of the history of architecture at the
University of Florence He has published a
number of works on Art Nouveau, including
Vienna, 1900 (with F Borsi, Lund Humphries,
London, 1 986), Pans, 1900 (with F Bora,
Rizzoli International Publications, USA, 1988),
and a dictionary of Art Nouveau and
Symbolist illustrators (with G Fanelli, Florence,
1990)
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
S.O.S. lemurs!
A new
biosphere reserve
in Madagascar
BY EDOUARD BAILBY
46
r^MONG the attractions of the
Paris zoo in the Bois de Vlncennes
is a group of unusual animals whose
family, the lemurians, is in danger
of extinction in its natural habitat.
Lemurians are proslmlan primates
whose rarest species is the aye-aye,
which is about 40 centimetres long.
Arboreal mammals with large marble-
like eyes, forward-facing ears, and
long bushy tails, lemurians are found
in their natural state only on the
island of Madagascar, where they
arrived 35 million years ago from
Africa.
In the study of evolution, lemu¬
rians are to Madagascar what the
finches, on which Charles Darwin
based one of his major arguments for
his theory of natural selection, are to
the Galapagos islands. They are an
inexhaustible source of information.
Unfortunately, their existence is
threatened because they are being
deprived of their natural habitat by
man-made forest fires, the extent of
which has been revealed by satellite
photographs. This is an ecological
catastrophe fraught with many con¬
sequences. In ten years at most no
lemurians will be left if nothing is
done to protect them.
To avoid this irreparable out¬
come, Unesco has recently approved
the creation of a biosphere reserve at
Mañanara on the east coast of the
island, at the request of the Malagasy
authorities. In the next few years four
more reserves will be created in the
hinterland. Thanks to large-scale
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Left, an aye-aye,
the rarest species of lemurian.
Below, aerial view of
the Mañanara biosphere reserve
on the east coast of Madagascar.
financial assistance from the United
Nations Development Programme
(UNDP), the World Bank, the European
Economic Community and the Federal
Republic of Germany, $ 1 0 million will
be invested in the project, which is
bound to have economic and social
consequences. In addition, thanks to
Unesco scholarships, young Malagasy
have begun to follow training courses
which will enable them to take an
active part in the scheme.
Dr. Jean-Jacques Petter, who is
responsible for the conservation of
animal species at the Vincennes zoo,
is in charge of the technical aspects
of the project. A medical doctor by
training, Dr. Petter has been carrying
out research in Madagascar for thirty
years. He talks with enthusiasm and
affection of a country he knows well
but at the same time does not con¬
ceal the gravity of the situation.
"Every year," he says, "300,000
hectares of forest are destroyed by
fire in Madagascar. This phenomenon
is not unique to the island. We are
familiar with devastating fires in the
South of France, many of criminal
origin. In the case of Madagascar, all
the same, they have particularly dra¬
matic consequences since each year
some 200,000 lemurs, 200,000
sifakas and 600,000 members of
other animal species disappear."
One factor in this complex
problem is Madagascar's very high
rate of demographic growth. The
average family has eight children.
Rural populations practise slash and
burn subsistence farming and grow
rice or maize in forest clearings.
Unfortunately the soil is crystalline
and soon ceases to be fertile. After
a few years nothing grows, and the
villagers burn more forest. Such
widespread forest burning eventually
has an impact on the climate. On the
east coast rainfall is less abundant
than it was.
The systematic destruction of the
forest, which a Malagasy proverb
wrongly maintains is eternal, also
causes the loss of many plant species
which are only found in Madagascar
and to which the existence of the
lemurians and other animal species
is closely linked. The primitive plant
and animal life of Madagascar is of
great scientific interest and should be
strictly protected if only because
Madagascar has been separated from
the continent of Africa for tens of mil¬
lions of years and its ecosystems are
unique.
"At Mañanara," Dr. Petter
explains, "we began to make the
local people aware of the problem a
few years ago. Thanks to the existing
village structures we gradually suc¬
ceeded in signing contracts with the
villagers to safeguard the forest. With
the exception of a few die-hards', we
are now sure that the 20,000 inhabi¬
tants of the surrounding region will
cease to burn these 40,000 hectares
of fine forest."
In exchange for their co¬
operation, the villagers benefit from
a development programme which
will intensify as a result of the trans¬
formation of Mañanara into a
biosphere reserve. Irrigation projects
will be launched, small dams will be
-
. a «9i
u \^*~ J*zà
..
.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
built, new crops will be introduced,
and sheep and goat farming
increased. Fish-farming, apiculture
and animal vaccination programmes
will also be carried out. In addition
the villagers will be provided with
schools and dispensaries which will
encourage them to settle in one
place. In a word, a partnership
between man and Nature will
become possible. Dr. Petter summed
up the policy as follows: "To protect
the lemurs is to protect the
Malagasy."
As the most recent biosphere
reserve to be inaugurated by Unesco,
Mañanara stands to gain from
experience accumulated in other
reserves in the humid tropics. Like
other biosphere reserves, two-thirds
of which are located in industrially
developed countries, Mañanara con¬
sists of three zones: a strictly pro¬
tected core area; a carefully
delineated buffer zone destined for
research, education and environ¬
mental training activities, as well as
leisure activities and tourism; and a
transition area where efforts are
made to encourage co-operation
between researchers, managers, and
the local population, with a view to
promoting long-term development of
the region's resources while fully
respecting the aims of the reserve.
The director of Unesco's Division
of Ecological Sciences, Mr. Bernd Von
Droste, believes that the purpose of
biosphere reserves goes far beyond
the material aspects of development.
.He sees the reserves as a cultural
enterprise in the widest sense of the
term and a justification of interna¬
tional solidarity. Of fundamental
importance for the future of
humanity, they are what J. Ronald
Engel of the University of Chicago has
called "sacred spaces". By associating
the protection of animal and plant life
with the economic and social
development of local populations,
they contribute to the conservation
of biological diversity, genetic
resources and ecosystems.
The 286 biosphere reserves in 72
countries play a key role in Unesco's
Man and the Biosphere (MAB)
Programme. Created in 1971, MAB
seeks to provide the scientific basis
for the study of problems related to
the wise use of resources, by
associating in each case the local
populations who are directly con¬
cerned. National MAB committees
have been created in over a hundred
countries and work in close associa¬
tion with the Unesco Secretariat.
The financial resources of the
MAB programme are still very
modest. Perhaps the story of the
lemurians of Madagascar, whose
name is of Latin origin and means
"the spirits of the dead", will help to
awaken the conscience of mankind.
EDOUARD BAILBY, French journalist
and former foreign correspondent on
the weekly magazine L'Express, served
for a number of years with the Unesco
Office of Public Information
A United Nations documentary
film crew at Mañanara.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
r +
c
Money and the emergence
of humanity
"The need for a form of money to
serve as a medium of exchange arose
at a very early stage in history..." says
the editorial of your January 1990
issue. The Fortunes of Money.
This statement raises several
questions. When and why did this
need become apparent? Why did
man feel the need to set a value on
goods and services, to pay for them,
and save?
Ali Boulhabel
Grenoble (France)
These are fundamental questions in the
human and social sciences, and the
following brief comments cannot pretend
to answer them completely.
Exchange, like the use of forms of money,
is associated with the gradual emergence
of humanity from the animal state. The
concept of exchange should not be re¬
duced to that of the market (the process
of making reciprocal gifts is a form of
exchange, and the commodities involved
in an exchange may be imaginary). Nor
should the currency of these ancient
societies be confused with the rudimen¬
tary instruments of the "primitive" market
¡s primarily a means of normaliz¬
ing social relations, and trade is only one
field in which it is used. Moreover, in
"primitive" societies, the basic functions of
moneyas a medium of expressing prices
and values and as a means of payment-
are more than just economic. As Karl
Polanyi has shown, economic relations in
such societies are closely linked to kinship
systems, political alliances, beliefs and
cults.
It is tempting to imagine that the first
exchanges were made principally to pro¬
cure the goods necessary for survival, but
this does not seem to have been the case.
Anthropological studies have shown that
man can survive in surroundings that are
a priori ecologically unfavourable, and that
"primitive" forms of exchange primarily
involve goods that do not play a funda¬
mental role in biological reproduction.
Such forms of exchange are, however,
important instruments for defining differ¬
ences in social status, between men and
women, the older and younger members
of families, and so on.
Hierarchies and dominance relation¬
ships between human beings are not
modern inventionsthey are found in
"primitive" societies and even exist in pri¬
mate groups. The development of forms
of exchange and money as instruments for
defining and standardizing social distinc¬
tions is a process that bears witness to the
emergence of humanity.
Jean-Michel Servet
University of Lyon II (France)
A 12th-century
Song of Roland?
I enjoyed reading the two issues of
the Courier on historiography, but I
was puzzled by one of the illustra¬
tions in the April issue, The Making
of History. The photo in question
shows a scene from a film of the
medieval French epic "The Song of
Roland", apparently the knights'
departure for Spain. This episode
actually took place around 778 AD,
but the knights in the photo are
standing in front of a church doorway
which has a Gothic ogival arch! After
considerable research I have been
able to identify the church in the
photo as that of Saint-Loup-de-Naud,
near Provins (France), which dates
from the 12th century...
In other words there is an
anachronism of four centuries. Such
inattention to historical detail by
a film-maker is bound to confuse
cinema-goers.
Pierre Nagant
Sambreville (Belgium)
Full marks for historical accuracy! But there
is no anachronism Franck Cassenti's film
is actually set in the 12th century. It tells
the story of a group of pilgrims and
storytellers travelling to the shrine of St
James at Santiago de Compostela, Spam
When they halt on their journey the
storytellers describe the exploits of Roland.
According to Les 100 chefs-d'oeuvre du
film historique by Jean-Pierre Fnmbois
(Marabout, Belgium, 1989), this "out¬
standingly original film was misunderstood
when it appeared". Editor
Towards a non-polluted
world
I have only recently discovered your
fine magazine through two 1988
issues, Man and Animals and The
World Heritage: A Legacy for All.
The Romanian ecological move¬
ment to which I belong is engaged
in a struggle similar to your own.
We would like to change our com¬
patriots' view of nature, teach them
to live in harmony and solidarity with
everything in the cosmos, respecting
the rights not only of man, but also
of plants and animals. In order to
survive and to progress, the human
species needs a non-polluted environ¬
ment and an understanding of the
interrelationship between all living -
things. We must create a "clean"
world in our own countries and else¬
where. We must see to the health of
our minds as well as our physical
health. He who enslaves another
man or animalis not free.
Doctor Stefan Milicescu
Bucharest (Romania)
The biblical Genesis
In your May 1 990 issue, In the Begin¬
ning. ..Imagining the Birth of the
Universe, why didn't you publish an
article on Genesis as it is described
in the Bible? For thousands of men
and women of different races and
cultures this wonderful account still
provides the answers to the really
fundamental questions...
Marie-Laure Valero
Plan-de-Cuques (France)
When I read your issue on the origins
of the universe, I was disappointed
that there was nothing about the bib¬
lical Genesis. If only for its simplicity
and grandeur, the story should have
been considered. What a pity!
Delphine Gigon
(Switzerland)
The third class
I would like to point out an error in
the otherwise excellent article on the
Vedas which opens your May issue.
Farmers do not belong to the fourth
social division or caste, but to the
third, the Vaisyas, of which they are
the most important group because
they provide food These "twice-
born" have access to the sacred
books, that is to say, to the science
of the mind.
J. Gabeur-Rasorre
Marseille (France)
Island hospitality
Your issue on The Art of Hospitality
(February 1990) was first-rate, but I
was sorry there was no article about
the hospitality offered by island com¬
munities. One of the great qualities
of ¡slanders is the warm welcome
they give to those who have come
from far away. They take endless
trouble to show visitors the beauties
of their island and tell them about its
history, customs and economic life.
Luis Balbuena Castellano
La Laguna, Tenerife
(Canary Islands)
Irony and Compassion
As a faithful Courier reader since
1956, I would like to make two
points about the remarkable article
by Octavio Paz in your June 1990
issue, Winds of Freedom.
First of all, as far as I am aware,
Buddhism does not recognize pity but
compassion, and the two should not
be confused.
Secondly, I would like to draw
readers' attention to the following
passage from The Epicure's Garden
(1895) by Anatole France:
"The more I think about human
life, the more strongly I believe that
Irony and Pity should be its witnesses
and its judge.... Irony and Pity are two
wise counsellors; the one, smiling,
makes life pleasant; the other, weep¬
ing, makes it sacred. The Irony of
which I speak is in no way cruel. It
mocks neither love nor beauty. It is
gentle and benevolent. Its laughter
moderates anger, and it teaches us
to scorn the wicked and the foolish,
whom we may otherwise be weak
enough to hate."
René Barbe
Montpellier (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
F R M
THE INTERNATIONAL AFRICAN INSTITUTE
A 'hunger for books'
[A "hunger for books" in develop¬
ing countries is one of the cultural
challenges of the age and "threatens
to undermine efforts to promote
universal literacy, education for all
and access to culture".1
The situation is especially serious
in Africa, which "through lack of
funds and chronic foreign exchange
constraints is becoming a tragically
bookless society".2 While in most
developing countries the number of
books published per million inhabi¬
tants grew slowly from 1 960 and ac¬
celerated during the 1980s, in Africa
this did not happen. Although the
number of titles published in Africa
almost doubled between 1960 and
the end of the 1970s, it fell during
the 1980s.
Apart from the fact that teachers
and pupils in African schools often
lack basic materials, many African
academics are denied access to inter¬
national research in their fields. A
BY PETER LLOYD
number of university libraries have cut
their subscriptions to periodicals to a
fifth of the level of the 1970s. New
books cannot be purchased and are
often unknown in the area to which
they refer. Many local journals estab¬
lished in the 1 960s and 1 970s are no
longer being published. African
scholars are being increasingly mar¬
ginalized. "A generation of students
is now being taught by lecturers who
are unable to gain access to current
research and scholarship."2
Alleviating Africa's book famine
is one of the major concerns of the
International African Institute (IAI), an
international non-governmental or¬
ganization with consultative status at
Unesco and UNICEF. The Institute
seeks to publicize the results of
research by African scholars both
within and beyond the continent and
facilitate their access to the work of
Africanists in the rest of the world.
It publishes directories, bibliographies,
50
International co-operation is founded on a network of daily
contacts, exchanges and initiatives which create bonds of
solidarity between men and women all over the world. In
addition to the intergovernmental agencies of the United
Nations system, hundreds of non-governmental organizations
(NGOs) today form part of this network. These organizations
exist thanks to the dedication of people with similar professional
interests or common aims who wish to share their experience
and combine their efforts. Our regular feature "Forum" gives
them an opportunity to talk about their activities.
monographs on ethnology, history,
sociology and linguistics.
The London-based IAI (formerly
the International Institute of African
Languages and Cultures) was found¬
ed in 1 926 as a centre of information
on African ethnology, linguistics and
social sciences, to organize research
in these fields and to present its
results in a useful form.
The Institute is financed by mem¬
bers' dues and donations from
governments and non-governmental
bodies. It also receives research grants
from African and European govern¬
ments, foundations and Unesco.
Members, both individual and cor¬
porate (universities, museums,
libraries, bookshops, seminaries,
governments and institutes) are
drawn from some ninety countries.
The most prominent of the Insti¬
tute's publications is the quarterly
Africa, now in its sixtieth year and still
one of the leading journals on Afri¬
can affairs and culture. It brings an
inter-disciplinary approach to the so¬
cial effects of development. Many of
its contributors are African scholars,
and even greater participation is be¬
ing sought from them. The journal's
policy is to give, increased coverage
to African publications in its book
reviews and articles.
The Institute tries to make its
publications available at moderate
cost throughout Africa By organiz¬
ing seminars, workshops and other
projects, inviting donations and con¬
tributing to co-operation between
publishers, it is attempting to break
the vicious circle in which many Afri¬
can scholars are trapped.
1 Third Medium-Term Plan (1990-1995),
Unesco, 1990
2. The African Book World and Press. A
Directory, Hans M Zell Publishers, London,
4th edition 1988
The International African
Institute
Lionel Robbins Building
10 Portugal Street
London WC 2A 2 HD
Acknowledgements
Cover, pages 3 (left), 17 (centre
left & below right), 22 (below), 24
(below right), 30, 33 (g), 40
(below): © Ch. Bastin & J. Evrard,
Brussels. Back cover, pages 10-11:
© Keiichi Tahara, Tokyo. Page 2:
© Centre d'Art, Amiens. Page 3
(right): © Alicia Segal, Buenos
Aires. Page 5: R. Lounes
© Gamma, Paris. Page 6: © Galerie
Marwan Hoss, Pans. Pages 8, 22
(above): © All Rights Reserved.
Page 9: © Edimedia, Paris. Private
Collection, Brussels. Sages 12-13,
14 (below), 15 (below left), 17
(above left, centre, below left), 36
(centre): ©M. Speidel, Aachen.
Pages 12 (left), 29 (above): ©J.L.
Charmet, Paris. Pages 14 (above
left), 19 (right), 25: © Edimedia,
Paris. Page 14 (above right):
© Philippe Sebert. Hervé Chayette-
Laurence Calméis, Paris. Pages 15
(above), 20: from Chefs-d'oeuvre fin
de siècle dans la collection Silverman,
by Alastair Duncan © Bordas,
Paris, 1989. Page 15 (below right):
© Edimedia, Paris. Horta Museum,
Brussels. Pages 16, 17 (centre
right), 28, 45 (above right &
below): © Felipe Ferré, Paris. Page
17 (above right): C. Sarramon
© Rapho, Paris. Page 18 (left):
©Japan Diet Library, Tokyo;
(right): Roger Guillemot
© Edimedia, Paris; (centre):
Giraudon, Pans. Musée des Ans
Décoratifs, Paris. Page 19 (left):
© CFL-Giraudon, Paris.
Kunstgewerbe Museum, Zurich.
Page 21 (above): © Réunion des
Musées Nationaux, Paris. Musée
d'Orsay, Paris; (centre): René
Percheron © Artephot, Victoria and
Albert Museum, London. Pages 21
(below), 31, 45 (above left): M.
Loiseau © Archipress, Paris. Page
23: © L. Wittamer-de Camps, Hôtel
Solvay, Brussels. Page 24 (above):
© Woodmansterne Publications
Ltd., Watford. Page 24 (below
left): © Jean Boucher, Brussels.
Archives de La Cambre, Brussels.
Pages 26-27: Erich Lessing
© Magnum, Paris. Österreichische
Galerie, Vienna. Page 29 (below):
© Editions d'An Albert Skira,
Geneva. Bildarchiv Preussischer
Kulturbesitz, Berlin. Page 33
(above), (a): © Igor Palmine,
Moscow. Pages 33 (b), (c), (e), (f),
(h), 37, 43 (below left): © A.
Gillette, Pans. Page 33 (d): © S.
Fédorov, Moscow. Pages 34
(above), 35 (right), 36 (below left
& below right): © A.G. Espuche,
Barcelona. Olimpiada Cultural,
Barcelona. Pages 34 (below left),
39 (below): © E. Godoli, Florence.
Pages 34 (below right), 35 (above),
36 (above): © Eloi Bonjoch,
Barcelona. Pages 35 (below), 44
(right): Hervé Donnezan © Raplio,
Paris. Page 38 (above): © E.
Capablanca, Havana; (below): C.
Rausch © Rapho, Paris. Pages 39
(above), 40 (above): ©J.O.
Gazaneo, Buenos Aires. Page 42
(left): © The Art Lover's House
Ltd., Glasgow. Glasgow School of
An; (right): © A. Valpas, Helsinki.
Page 43 (above): © Bildarchiv
Foto, Marburg; (below right):
© Max Plunger, Helsinki. Page 44
(left): © Editions d'Art Alben
Skira, Geneva. Page 46: Visage
© Bios, Paris. Pages 47, 48: D.
Roger/Unesco. Page 50: Y.Z.
Nakpata/Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 7501 5 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca. Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey fiel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein Gel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kassier (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M, Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakite, Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65).
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 68 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright
photos will be supplied or request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Couner staff The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Couner is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, (2) University Microfi:ms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100, USA., (3) N.CR. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head. Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th street. New York, U.S.A , (4) Bell and
Howell Co., Old Mansf-eld Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL : C: - AOÛT 1990
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP
Photocomposition: The Unesco Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury mprimeur S.A., 2.1 route d'Etampes.
45330 Malesherbes
Would you like
to know more
about Art Nouveau
Order the next issue of
museum
No. 3, 1990
This issue is devoted to Art Nouveau architecture and design, a
little-known part of our heritage. The richly illustrated articles cover
town houses converted into museums, Art Nouveau collections,
and the architectural archives of 18 countries ranging from
Argentina, Canada and Cuba to Japan, as well as Belgium, France,
Norway, the USSR, Yugoslavia and other European countries.
For Courier readers, the Art Nouveau number of Museum is offered
at the special rate of 40 French francs (normal cover price, FF 48),
or the equivalent in convertible currency. Please send a cheque made
out to Unesco, with your name and address clearly printed, and
indicate which language version you wish to receive (Arabic,
English, French, Russian or Spanish), to:
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 8 1990-OPI-90 3 483 A
Museum, CC/CH, Unesco, 1 rue Miollis, 75015 Paris, France.
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page advertising insert
between pages 10-11 and 42-43
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
> m 7v,
it;
/me *f
i/^SH
CS >
La « »
.1 I
!.. - '« TTi. *
/
4 '.
]]>
</page>
</document>
