<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="087206eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
I
OCTOBER 1990
The automobile
Machine and myth
M 1205 9010 15,00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
FEET FIRST
1990, line engraving
(30 x 40 cm) by
Denise Fernandez Grundman
This work by French
artist Denise Fernandez
Grundman symbolizes
a young African girl's
leap into modernity,
leaving behind her
ancestral customs.
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER 1990
N N
Today there are no more
unexplored continents,
unknown seas or mysterious
islands. But while we can
overcome the physical
barriers to exploration, the
barriers of mutual ignorance
between different peoples
and cultures have in many
cases still not been
dismantled.
A modern Ulysses can
voyage to the ends of the
earth. But a different kind
of Odyssey now beckonsan
exploration of the world's
many cultural landscapes, the
ways of life of its different
peoples and their outlook on
the world in which they live.
It is such an Odyssey that
the Unesco Courier proposes
to its readers. Each month
contributors of different
nationalities provide from
different cultural and
professional standpoints an
authoritative treatment of a
theme of universal interest.
The compass guiding this
journey through the world's
cultural landscapes is respect
for human dignity.
9
THE AUTOMOBILE
MACHINE AND MYTH
THE AUTOMOTIVE AGE
by Jean-Francis Held 10
THE SERENE PLEASURE OF SPEED
by Françoise Sagan 15
MEMORY LANE
by Mahmoud Hussein 16
THE NEW FORD
by John Steinbeck 20
FAFNER THE DRAGON
by Julio Cortázar 20
A REVOLUTION ON WHEELS
by Robert Braunschweig 22
THE GODDESS
by Roland Barthes 24
THE WRONG TRACK
by Nicolas Langlois 27
SEX DRIVE
by Stephen Bayley 30
ART ON THE ROAD
by Moira F. Harris 31
KUSTOM CARS IN THE USA 32
DRIVING INTO HISTORY
by Alvaro Casal Tatlock 36
4
Interview with
CLAUDE
LÉVI-STRAUSS
41
IN BRIEF... 41
NEW FEATURE:
A COMMON HERITAGE
The World Heritage
Convention:
a new idea takes shape
A common responsibility
by Azedine Beschaoucb
International campaigns
to safeguard the cultural
heritage of mankind
by Abdelkader
Brahim Errahmani
44
45
46
The World Heritage List 48
ANNIVERSARY
A great Renaissance
library 49
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR 50
A VINTAGE CROP
Cover: Hispano, 1986, sculpture
in polished bronze by the
Swiss artist Emmanuel Zurini.
Back cover: Expressway
38 interchange, California, USA.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Claude Lévi-Strauss
You are the author ofa considerable body ofwork which
has won respect all over the world. Those who know
your name are more numerous than those who arefamiliar
with your work. And so we should like to ask on behalf
ofour wide internationalpublic some basic questions about
the key elements in your thinking. But first of all, could
you tell us something about your career, about your
early days?
As a writer I was actually a comparatively late starter.
My career has had its ups and downs. After embarking on
the study of law I turned to philosophy and then moved
on first to sociologyit was to teach sociology that I went
to the university of Sào Paulo in Braziland then to eth¬
nography. It was only during the war, when I had taken
refuge in the United States, that I began to write. On the
one hand I used some of my field studies on the Nambik-
wara, and on the other I began my theoretical work by writ¬
ing The Elementary Structures ofKinship.
This early research was doubtless accompanied by
anxieties...
I would prefer to speak of uncertainties rather than anxi¬
eties. It would be more exact. My theoretical thinking took
a certain direction which I could not see clearly. Then, while
I was in the United States in 1942, 1 met the linguist Roman
Jakobson and discovered that these vague ideas existed in
the form of a body of doctrine in structural linguistics. I
was immediately reassured.
At that time we were both teaching at the New School
for Social Research in New York, a kind of university in
exile which had been founded by French-speaking refugee
scholars. We attended each other's lectures. I found in Jakob-
son's teaching the interpretative guidelines I needed. He en¬
couraged me and even urged me to go further with my
lectures on kinship.
Lectures which led to a book...
Yes, my first major book, The Elementary Structures of
Kinship, which was also my doctoral thesis.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The great French social anthropologist
looks back at his life's work and
retraces the steps
of his intellectual development
What coincidences did you find between the linguistics of
Jakobson and the ethnographical research you were then
carrying out? Linguistics and ethnography are two very
different disciplines.
The differences are enormous. I was in no way attempt¬
ing to transpose mechanically into ethnology what was be¬
ing done in linguistics. It was rather a question of the same
overall inspiration. With this very clear feeling, right from
the start, that we were certainly not talking about the same
things and that we could not talk in the same way about
different things. But linguistics confirmed two points which
until then I had only vaguely realized.
The first is that, to understand very complex phenome¬
na, it is more important to consider the relationship between
them than to jstudy each of them in isolation. The second
is the notion of the phoneme, as Jakobson developed it. Pho¬
nemes are distinctive sounds such as e, t, q, a, b, c, which
signify nothing in themselves. It is the way in which they
are combined to make words which makes it possible to
differentiate the meanings and r mean nothing but in
English they differentiate pot from tot.
This idea seemed to me to be extremely fertile. Once
again, it was not a question of comparing ethnological facts
with phonemesthey are realities of a different order. But
when I tried, for example, to understand the extraordinary
and apparently arbitrary diversity of the marriage rules
which prevail in a given society, I did not ask myself the
question people had asked until then: what does this rule,
taken by itself, mean within this society? On the contrary,
I considered that the rule meant nothing in itself, but that
the way in which all the rules were combined, in opposi¬
tion or in juxtaposition, was a means of expressing certain
significations. For example, these rules served to formulate
or stimulate cycles of exchange within the social group.
Cycles of exchange which are themselves significant and
which vary from society to society.
How would you sum up this new method?
Let's say that in all human societies there are first-order
ensembleslanguage, kinship, religion, and law, to name
only a few. In the early stages of research, it is perhaps wise
to consider them as separate units. But at a later stage, one
must ask what relationship there can be between these first-
order units and the more complex second-order units which
they constitute when combined. We thus gradually reach
the idea of the "total social fact" as formulated by the French
sociologist and anthropologist Marcel Mauss. It comprises
a variety of representations, at once linguistic, legal, religious,
and so on.
But this is within a given society taken as a totality...
Initially yes. But later one tries to understand the corre¬
lations and oppositions that may exist between neighbour¬
ing or distant societies.
You have written of "hot" and "cold" societies to differen¬
tiate between societies with a historical perspective and
static societies...
These are theoretical poles. All societies are actually lo¬
cated somewhere along a spectrum. So-called primitive so¬
cieties are not primitive at all. Their ideal is not to change,
to remain in the state in which the gods created them at
the beginning of time. Of course they do not succeed. They
also exist in history. But they have a tendency to neutralize
changes, to maintain an ideal statethat represented by
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
myths. On the other hand, in societies which I have called
"hot", we try to define ourselves in opposition to our an¬
cestors. Change is thus much more rapid. We are not only
aware of the existence of history but we wish with the
knowledge we have of our past to reorientate the future,
legitimize or criticize the evolution of our society. History
for us is an element of our moral conscience.
Would you definefor us the notion ofmyth as you present
it in your work Mythologies?
Basically the notion of myth is a very flexible one. For
an American Indian, myth is a story of the time when hu¬
man beings and animals were not distinct. I think this is
a very good definition. For, in spite of the efforts deployed
by the Judaeo-Christian tradition, no situation seems more
tragic for the heart and mind than that of a humanity which
coexists with other living species on an earth which they
share, without being able to communicate with these spe¬
cies. Myths refuse to see this flaw in creation as something
which always existed. They see its appearance as the event
which inaugurated the human condition. Myth, unlike the
Cartesian approach to a problem, refuses to divide the
difficulty, never accepts a partial response, aspires to expla¬
nations which englobe the totality of phenomena.
I have tried to see the role played by myth in the think¬
ing of members of a society. I have tried to discern its inner
logic before going on to ask myself about its social func¬
tion. In all the sciences there is a question that could be de¬
fined in biological terms, like the relations between anatomy
and physiology, between the way in which an organism is
Works by Claude Lévi-Strauss
translated into English include:
Elementary Structures of Kinship (1949),
Beacon Press, Boston, 1969.
Tristes Tropiques (1955), Atheneum
Publishers, New York, 1974.
Structural Anthropology (1958), University
of Chicago Press, 1963, 1976.
Savage Mind (1962), University of Chicago
Press, 1966, 1968.
Mythologies: Vol. I, The Raw and the
Cooked (1964), Vol. II, From Honey to Ashes
(1967), Vol. Ill, The Origin of Table Manners
(1968), Vol. IV, The Naked Man (1971).
University of Chicago Press.
The Way of the Masks (1975). University
of Washington Press, 1982, 1988.
Myth and Meaning (1978), Schocken
Books, New York, 1979.
The View from Afar (1983), Basic Books,
Harper & Row, New York, 1987.
Anthropology and Myth: Lectures
1957-1982, Basil Blackwell, Oxford, UK,
1987.
constituted and the way in which it functions. Of course
myths function within societies-they perform a role. But
before asking how they function it is necessary to know how
they are made, it is necessary to know their anatomy. We
could not have had Darwin if Cuvier had not gone before
him. My Mythologies corresponded to the Cuvier stage. I was
trying to anatomize myths.
You gave two lectures at Unesco, at an interval of twenty
years. The first was entitled "Race and History", the se¬
cond "Race and Culture". Would it be true to say that in
each ofthem your main preoccupation was to reconcile the
notion ofprogress with the principle ofcultural relativism?
The notion of progress implies that certain cultures are
superior to others, at given times and in given places, that
Poster for an exhibition on
"The Americas of Claude Lévi-
Strauss" (Paris, October
1989-Aprll 1990) shows an
oil painting by the French
artist Jean-Baptlste Debret,
Indian Giving the Signal to
Attack (1827).
Left, Tllnglt Indian mask,
British Columbia (Canada).
Below, painted wooden frontal
mask of the Makah Indians.
Washington State, USA.
some produce works that others would have been incapable
of producing. According to cultural relativism, which is one
of the bases of my ethnological thinking, there is no absolute
criterion for asserting that one culture is superior to another.
If some cultures "move" while others do not, it is not
because the former are superior to the latter. It is because
some historical situations lead to collaboration between
societies which are not unequal, but different. These cultures
then begin to move through mutual imitation or opposi¬
tion. They fertilize and stimulate each other. At other times
and in other places it happens that cultures remain isolated
and static.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
] HB
flft H^B^^^^BI ^JIF I £'<: V
F
^BWS^^^fc
BLiP Jç ' 1
HF
M^Eé^C^) * hV ««1
' frT^S^^^A ¿ir^ jBtt*
i §/7 j í* iV^^B ^llaU
> ii' nP^I in. :^ - 1
jniK t Ly uftv «f %m^«
Does thefunction ofart also vary between one culture and
another? Is it not more collective in the societies which you
call "cold"?
I think this is because art in such societies is closely linked
to collective beliefs. The purpose of art in these societies
is not individual or group enjoyment. It has a function,
which is to provide communication between the society and
a supernatural world in which all its members believe. Art
thus here performs a function which is indispensable to the
group.
A social function...
Social and religious. When religion, religious beliefs, are
shared by the totality of a group, it is impossible to dissoci¬
ate the two aspects.
This function has ceased to exist in "modern" societies.
I think this is largely related to the disappearance of a
great common faith. Our societies have lost this capacity
for a great collective belief, a common élan.
7s this one manifestation of the separation between the in¬
dividual and the world brought about during the history
of Western culture?
By isolating human beings from the rest of creation,
Western individualism deprived them of a protective wall.
As soon as people believe that their power is limitless, they
are heading for self-destruction. Think of the concentration
camps. Think, for all humanity this time, of environmental
problems.
Looking back to your early days, how do you judge the
results ofyour research? How do you see the path you have
taken?
I feel that I have always done the same thing in the sense
that I have tried to study different fields using the same ap¬
proach. I started out by grappling with problems of family
and social organization. Then one thing led to another and
I was invited to take a chair in the religion of peoples without
writing at the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes in Paris.
And so I turned towards religious matters, especially mythol¬
ogy. The problems to be solved were even more difficult
than those of kinshipa field in which a lot of work had
already been done, even if not satisfactorily in my opinion.
Apart from extremely old and confused theories which
everyone could see were out of date, myths belonged to a
field of study that was still largely unfilledexcept, of course,
through the pioneering work of Georges Dumézil, and he
explored the circumscribed field of Indo-European
mythology.
The problems raised by this new research were of the
same order as those relating to kinship. Just as the marriage
rules of the different societies I had studied seemed arbitrary,
so myths seemed incomprehensible, and even absurd. When
the myths of different, even very distant populations are
compared, they can be seen to have common characteris¬
tics. After trying to instil a little order into the chaos of kin¬
ship and marriage rules, I wanted to do the same thing for
mythology. And drawing inspiration from principles that
I had defined at the beginning, to try to understand what
myths meant.
This long-term project took me twenty-five years be¬
cause of the immense volume of material I had to absorb.
The ethnographic literature contained a mass of myths
which ethnologists had collected over a century with ad¬
mirable zeal and then transcribed into a corpus of publica¬
tions which no one had used. I felt that this was an even
richer source of material than that we possess for ancient
Greece and Rome. "For two thousand years," I told my¬
self, "commentators have been studying the beliefs of the
Greeks and Romans without exhausting the subject, and
constantly finding new interpretations."
And so I tried to exploit this unexplored continent of
documents relating to North and South America. I hope
that I have succeeded in showing how the mythological
world of the American Indians is constructed.
Interview by Peruvian journalist Manuel Osorio.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
-
- :t v
VA
TROMÇ
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
T
Production line, 1968.
HE automobile is the supreme emblem of modern societies. On the
one hand it holds a powerful appeal to the imagination. On the other
it is a mainspring of industrial economies. It has helped to determine
the way of life of millions and to shape patterns of individual and
collective behaviour that are, for better or worse, characteristic features
of our century.
The world's leading car manufacturers such as Daimler-Benz in Germany,
Citroen in France and Ford in the United States, were trail-blazers of
capitalism. By introducing mass production on a moving assembly line,
Henry Ford reduced costs and turned what had been a luxury for the
few into a product that the many could afford.
If the demand for automobiles grew so rapidly that within a few decades
the auto industry was the driving force of market economies, it is because
the car embodies so many of the needs, longings and fantasies of modern
men and women, especially the dream of freedom of movement at speed
in a self-propelled vehiclehorsepower without the horse.
What future lies ahead for this offspring of the marriage between dream
and industry? How serious is the risk that we may destroy the car's
potential as an instrument of freedom by becoming its slave?
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
How to stop
the golden
dream of
rapid mobility
from
becoming
a guilt-edged
nightmare
10
JEAN-FRANCIS HELD,
French writer and journalist,
has been editorial director of
the French weekly L'Evénement
du Jeudi since it was launched
in 1984. He is the author of
several works of fiction and
of essays, some of which are
devoted to the social impact
of the automobile.
The automotive age
BY JEAN-FRANCIS HELD
'ELE bounds from the earth. (...) When I bes¬
tride him, I soar. (...) My horse is my mistress."
With these words the Dauphin of France, a vain¬
glorious nincompoop, extols the virtues of his
charger on the eve of the battle of Agincourt, in
Shakespeare's play Henry V.
If one is going to talk about horsepower,
what could be more natural than to start with
the horse? When trying to unravel the mysteries
of modernity, why not go back to the Hundred
Years War? Speed has always been the stuff of
dreams, especially the dreams of males anxious
to extend the range of their puny legs by don¬
ning seven-league boots. From the days of
Pharaoh's chariots to those of the stage-coaches
that opened up the American West, people have
always wanted to break the barriers of distance.
Even today, echoes of the horse-mad Dauphin's
Shakespearean paean to his charger can still be
heard in bars the world over, but today the Dau¬
phin's successors sing the praises of Porsche or
Ferrari.
The automobile has universalized the dream
of mobility and speed. The open road, a steering
wheel, the promise of superhuman energy
waiting to be unleashed by a touch of the right
footall this adds up to much more than the
simple process of getting from point A to point
B. It evokes prospects of escape from the weight
of collective and material responsibilities. Space
is dominated. Time is mastered. The horse is a
gift of nature and, as the saying goes, one should
never look a gift horse in the mouth. The
automobile is an artefact, a purpose-built reflec¬
tion of the human will. No other object has been
so richly charged with meaning. It has been dwelt
on by literature, by the cinema and even by
modern art. The automobile typifies man, and
vice versa. If, after a nuclear cataclysm, some
skilful archaeologist of the future were to unearth
from a garage-tomb a collection of automobiles
that had escaped destruction, he would be able
to deduce from them everything that we were.
\
^
'
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Like father, like son.. A recent example of the representativity
of the automobile is the Trabant, a vehicle
that has become a symbol of the reunification
of the two Germanies and earned itself a place
in the world's museums. The Trabant embodies
the failure of totalitarianism and the frustrations
to which it gives rise, just as the Mercedes and
the BMW symbolize the success of capitalist
free enterprise, with all its wealth and its often
relentless pride. Before the First World War,
the President of the United States, Woodrow
Wilson, perceptively declared: "Nothing has
done so much as the automobile to encourage the
spread of socialist ideasit symbolizes the
arrogance of wealth." On the other side of the
coin, the Trabant symbolizes the humiliation of
poverty.
A standardized symbol
Before that, however, the automobile had become
a Western fetish. The Third World and the
former colonies are still entranced by the Mer¬
cedes, the Peugeot and the Land Rover, in the
former German, French and British possessions
respectively. Time has changed virtually nothing.
Although the Japanese may conquer the market,
the magic of these European makes still retains
a profound, indelible cultural impact. After the
rifle, the automobile has been seen as a means of
becoming strong, rich and fast-moving, like the
Whitesa kind of neo-colonialist vehicle.
Automobiles used to reflect cultural and
national differences, but the switch from custom-
building to mass-production has gradually ironed
out differences in personality. Little survives of
a specifically Latin, Germanic or British approach
to making cars. Once upon a time it was impos¬
sible to confuse the ethos of a Bugatti or an Alfa
Romeo with that of a Bentley or a Mercedes.
Ettore Bugatti (1882-1947) ridiculed the Bentleys
which regularly defeated his blue-liveried
thoroughbreds on the Le Mans circuit: "They are
the fastest trucks that have ever been made," he
scoffed. Today, all racing-cars look alike and are
built to the same specifications.
The same goes for the average car, which con¬
forms to economic, technical and commercial
imperatives dictated by the stateless computer. It
is almost impossible to tell if one is in a Fiat, an
Opel, a Renault or an Austin. The romance has
gone. Unhampered by tradition, Japan makes
good automobiles, that is all. Only the United
States still makes a few limousines that bear the
true American stamp, but for how much longer?
Libido at the wheel
The automobile may have become standardized,
but not the way in which it is used. Tell me how
you drive and I will tell you who you are. Drivers
differ by virtue of their temperament and even
their sexwomen drivers are more detached, less
deadly than the more competitive male. But
above all ways of driving reflect cultural differ¬
ences. The Italians, the Germans, the French and 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
the British have a style of driving which reflects
their national ethos. More recently-motorized
countries are gradually developing their own.
With a longer history of driving behind them,
the Americans (if we discount the occasional
gangster exploit or James Dean-style folly) con¬
trol their libido on the highway. Nevertheless,
throughout the world, controlled or not, the
demons are there, not far beneath the surface.
A man dreams that he is at the wheel of a
sleek, powerful, red convertible. He comes to a
slope that extends as far as the eye can see. The
engine starts to cough and splutter, and the man
wakes up, sweating with fear. There's no need
to have read Freud to know that the libido is the
key to the dream. Psychoanalysts know what
place the automobile occupies in the landscape
of our unconscious. Man identifies with it as an
instrument of power, an extension of his realm.
To touch its metal body is to commit an act of
aggression. To obstruct its passage is a castrating
challenge to the omnipotence of his Ego.
There is another aspect to the eroticization
of the automobile. In all Westernized societies,
the automobile is a seductive object like the stag's
antlers, the lion's mane or the peacock's feathers.
Beautiful cars fascinate the ladies, not always the
most prudent amongst them.
The link between the automobile and desire
is flagrant and advertisers exploit it. Twenty years
ago, the gradual shrinkage of the huge American
limousine to more moderate, almost European,
dimensions, coincided with a reduction in the size
of the enormous bust-lines of magazine pin-ups.
None of the sociologists who study the vicissi¬
tudes of the automobile considered this to be
mere coincidence.
You are not convinced? Ask yourself, then,
why it is that the vast majority of European
drivers scorn the automatic gear change, while
the Americans have overwhelmingly adopted it.
This is simply because virility symbols differ
to each his own gear lever.
Things start to go wrong, the man/machine
relationship becomes poisoned and the love affair
turns sour when man's real or imaginary frustra¬
tions take over the automobile and turn it into
A 1960 Cadillac Sedan.
a refuge, a compensation, even a weapon. The
automobile holds such an important place in
people's dreams that one might expect the dream
to become a nightmare. Sometimes a driver
incensed by a "challenge" from his enemy the
man in the other carbecomes so exasperated
that he seeks "revenge" by carrying out dan¬
gerous, potentially fatal aggressive manoeuvres he
would not even dream of as a civilized pedestrian.
The children scream with fright, the siren of the
ambulance can already be heard? To hell with
it. ..overtake or bust!
It is possible to be mad about cars and see
them as the most wonderful toys ever invented,
and stillespecially todayask a few questions.
They have become too much of a good thing.
The reasons for this metamorphosis are clear even
if the remedies for it are not.
When dreams come true, they usually bring
disappointment. At the time of the Bugatti,
roughly speaking between the two World Wars,
the automobile was inaccessible to most people.
Even in the 1950s, Europeans who saw films like
The Grapes of Wrath could not understand how
it was possible to be very poor and still have a
car. For them the automobile was something that
tomorrow would bring, along with freedom, hap¬
piness and middle class status. Then, twenty years
after the United States, the rest of the Western
world became wealthy and acquired its own
automobiles. But alas, when everyone is
privileged, privilege ceases to exist. From being
the few, drivers became the many. They took it
badly. Disenchantment gave birth to collective
neuroses that have become part of daily life, so
common, in fact, that those who deplore them
are voices crying in the wilderness.
This disenchantment undeniably exists. What
happened to the wonderful, exclusive gift we
were once promised? In ten years the number of
automobiles in the world has increased by 30 per
cent. If we discount the poorest countries where
the automobile age is still a dream, the increase
is staggering70 per cent in Spain, 51 per cent
in Japan, and so on. The tide is rising less steeply
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
in the industrialized countries of Europe, which
were already approaching saturation pointin
France alone, traffic has increased by 5 per cent
and there has been a 2.5 per cent increase in the
number of automobiles.
The 'right' to drive
If theoretically almost everybody can own a car,
it is impossible to let loose at the same time on
the public highway all these hundreds of millions
of vehicles. The traffic jams would be enormous.
Rampant individualism is thus a thing of the past,
especially in the towns. A social approach to the
automobile is needed, and this inevitably involves
restrictions. It is very badly received by drivers
who cling tenaciously to the "right" to drive at
all costs.
Yet, insidiously, little by little, the absolute
freedom of the motorist has been eroded. The
two oil crises provided a pretext for the aboli¬
tion of many privileges. With some difficulty
speed limits were imposed, the wearing of seat
belts was made obligatory and paid parking in
urban areas was introduced. The automobile has
been brought down to earth, curbed and, theo¬
retically, is losing its status as a sacred cow.
One large oil company even ran a brief cam¬
paign to remove the car "from its pedestal"
the antithesis of the famous "put a tiger in your
tank" slogan invented by one of its competitors.
For the first time some dared to talk about safety
rather than performance, but all too often the
message fell on deaf ears. To keep up sales,
automobile manufacturers continue to produce
fast vehicles which are totally unsuited to daily
traffic conditions, and succumb to the temptation
to use aggressive advertising whilst knowing full
well that nobody buys a vehicle capable of speeds
in excess of 200 kilometres an hour so as to be
able to travel at 130 kilometres an hour with the
rest of the herd on the motorways.
There are many automobile civilizations. In
the United States, with the exception of a few
paranoiacs, people obey the rules and remain
good citizens even when they are at the wheel.
This is not yet the case in France, for example.
Although in other respects a highly civilized 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The longest limousine
In the world, made to order
for the American actor
Sylvester Stallone.
country, France enjoys the grim distinction of
more than 10,000 road deaths each year.
And yet this hecatomb is not the worst
symptom of the wayward misuse of the automo¬
bile. You only die once. But where neuroses
abound and where frustrated individualism
remains all-powerful, daily life becomes sheer
hell, with monster traffic jams, waste of time and
money, heightened nervous tension, weekends
transformed into endurance tests of patience. A
sense of civic responsibility gives way to exasper¬
ation. People break the law, cheat, become aggres¬
sive, and the authorities, which turn a blind eye,
find their respectability compromised. This is bad
for democracy. What can be expected of the
citizen who, desperately seeking release, each day
becomes one ant among many in an ant-hill gone
wild?
14
A long process
of psychotherapy
The automobile must change its ways. Indeed, it
has already done so, but not always for the better.
The free-wheeling days of the past are long gone.
We have mistakenly felt obliged to build cities
for the car. Los Angeles is not really a success.
The great cities of the world, ancient and
modernRome, Paris, Mexico, all of themhave
been spoilt and polluted by the ubiquitous
automobile.
What is to become of this abomination, the
much-desired automobile? Is it for ever doomed?
Not necessarily. But if we are to cure ourselves
of the automobile disease we shall need stringent
remedies and a long course of finely-tuned
psychotherapyin short, political courage.
Restrictions will doubtless have to be
imposed. The frustrated will have to be taught
to consider the welfare of all. The flood of
individual vehicles will have to be stemmed so
as to make way for public transport, swarms of
convenient taxis and all those forms of transport
which our obsession with the automobile has
reduced to the last resort of the poor. We will
have to show that we can travel along other roads
than the saturated public highways on which rage
and resignation are the rule. Finally, we must
make the automobile what it once was, an instru¬
ment of happiness.
Once again signs of hope can be seen in the
United States. The Americans have learned and
accepted the rules of mass transportation. They
have, as we have seen, learned good behaviour
at the wheel. They have begun to make a distinc¬
tion between the automobile as an instrument of
work and as a source of pleasure. The ingenious
system of car pools, whereby neighbours share
their cars for driving to work, is one example.
(W
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
.	
'i ' -
This is an idea with a future, though it will raise
the hackles of those who would rather share their
wives than their precious cars. Nikita Khruschev
had another good idea when he thought of
creating huge car-hire centres rather than
providing each Soviet citizen with his or her own
narcissistic talisman/vehicle. How far off that
seems...
We shall have to learn, or rather relearn, to
have fun with automobiles away from roads used
for transportation. We should play with the
veteran gems of days gone by, when the automo¬
bile was still a wonder; hold races on purpose-
built tracks with racing-cars, lawn-mowers, steam¬
rollers; go for drives in the desert without dis¬
turbing other people. As for the practical,
utilitarian side of things, it would be better to
travel in mobile music rooms, the last refuges of
conversation, rather than in the ferocious tanks
let loose on our highways and boulevards.
A gloomy prospect? Not at all! This could
be the salvation of the automobile. ..and our own
salvation too.
ïïie serene pleasure of speed BY FRANÇOISE SAGAN
Extract from Avec mon meilleur souvenir, © Gallimard, Paris, 1984.
he tempi of speed are not those of music. In
a symphony it is neither the allegro, the vivace
nor the furioso that corresponds to 200
kilometres an hour, but the andante, a slow,
majestic movement, a kind of plateau you get
to when you go beyond a certain speed, where
the car no longer resists or accelerates, where,
on the contrary, it lets itself go, the body too,
in a kind of wideawake, alert daze which is
usually described as intoxicating. It happens on
deserted roads at night, and occasionally in the
daytime when you are miles from anywhere.
It happens at moments when words like "pro¬
hibited", "safety first", "insurance", "hospital"
and "death" cease to have any meaning, their
sense annulled by a simple word which men
have always used when describing a silver rac¬
ing car or a chestnut horse: the word "speed".
This is a speed at which something inside one¬
self transcends something outside, a moment
when reckless violence erupts from a machine
or an animal running wild, and is barely con¬
trolled by the intelligence, the senses, skill-
sensuality tooat any rate not controlled
enough to prevent it from becoming a pleas¬
ure, perhaps a deadly pleasure. How odious is
this age of ours, when risk, the unpredictable,
the unreasonable are constantly rejected, con¬
fronted with figures, deficits, calculations; a
wretched age in which people are forbidden to
kill themselves not because of the incalculable
value of their souls but because of the calcu¬
lated price of their carcasses.
In fact a car, his own car, gives the person
who is at the same time its master and its slave
a paradoxical sensation. He is free at last, back
at his mother's breast, in a state of primal soli¬
tude, and far, very far from any prying eyes.
Neither pedestrians, nor police, nor other
motorists, nor the woman who waits for him,
nor life which does not wait, can dislodge him
from his car, the only possession, after all, in
which for an hour a day he can again return to
the physical state of solitude, as when he was
born. And if, in addition, the waves of traffic part
before his car like those of the Red Sea before
the Hebrews, if the red lights become fewer,
then disappear altogether, and the road starts
to vibrate and murmur at the pressure of his
foot on the accelerator, if the wind rages
through the door, if every corner is a threat and
a surprise and if every kilometre is a small vic¬
tory, then is it surprising that mild bureaucrats
marked out for brilliant careers should execute
a beautiful pirouette and, a jumble of iron,
gravel and blood, make a final plunge to earth
and a final rejection of their futures? These
somersaults are described as accidental, it is
said that the victims were distracted, they had
something on their minds people totally miss
the point, which is this sudden, unfathomable
and irresistible encounter between a body and
its mind, the joining of an existence to the sud¬
denly luminous idea of that existence: "What,
who am I? I am myself, I live; I live like this. I
go at 90 kilometres an hour in town, 110 on
the main roads, 130 on the motorway, 600 in
my head and 3 in my body, in obedience to all
the laws of the constabulary, of society and of
despair. What are these ill-adjusted rules which
have surrounded me since childhood? What is
this speed imposed on the course of my life,
my one and only life?..."
But here we are getting away from pleas¬
ure, from speed considered as a pleasure,
which is ultimately the best definition. Let's say
at once, like Morand, like Proust, like Dumas,
that it's not an impure, diffuse or shameful
pleasure. Going too fast is a precise, exultant
and almost serene pleasure, leaving behind the
safety of a car and the road it takes, slipping
the bonds of earth, and perhaps one's own
reflexes. And let's say too that it is definitely
not a question of passing a self-imposed test,
an idiotic challenge to one's own talent, it is not
a contest between self and self nor a victory
over a personal handicap, it is rather a kind of
light-hearted bet between pure luck and one¬
self. When you go fast, there is a moment when
everything starts to float in this iron canoe in
which you are on the razor's edge, on the crest
of the wave, hoping that the current, not your
skill, will keep you from capsizing. Love of speed
has nothing to do with sport. Just as speed has
something in common with gambling and
chance, so it does with living happily and con¬
sequently with the vague hope of dying which
is always part of a happy life. Ultimately, that
is all I believe to be true: speed is neither a sign,
nor a proof, nor a provocation, nor a challenge,
but an upsurge of happiness.
FRANÇOISE SAGAN, French writer (b. 1935). Her works
translated into English include Bonjour Tristesse (1954), A
Certain Smile (1957), Wonderful Clouds (1960), Unmade Bed
(1977) and Painted Lady (1981). 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
\
.-**Vr..-1 \
'Cars lit for
us all the fires
of the modern
world: the
desire for
escape and
self-assertion,
a love of
technical
efficiency, the
emancipation
of women,
freedom...'
16
MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
is the pen name of two
Egyptian writers who have
published several books of
political sociology, most
recently Versant sud de la
liberté, Essai sur l'émergence
de l'individu dans le tiers
monde ("The Southern Face
of Liberty, an essay on the
emergence of the individua!
in the Third World",
La Découverte, Paris, 1989).
Memory lane
BY MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
IT was the early 1940s. It was wartime, but our
village, in the northernmost part of Egypt, east
of the Nile delta, was far from the scene of action.
Little did we know that over there, deep in the
Libyan desert, a battle was being fought between
the Allied armies and the Axis powers that was
to mark a decisive turning point in the war.
We were between six and ten years old. We
were allowed to play in freedom at the end of
the long schoolday. We had to stay within the
area of the village or its immediate surroundings.
But sometimes we would venture as far as the
highway between Damietta and Izbet El Borg....
Barely a few hundred metres away from the
crossroads where the highway intersected with
the little road that led to our village was a British
army base with a radar station. Soldiers of var¬
ious nationalities bustled all around.
To rid us of any desire to take a closer look,
we were told that the soldiers would seize the
slightest opportunity to kidnap lone children.
Sometimes they ate them. Sometimes they raped
them. Had they not been living for months,
perhaps years, far away from women? The terror
inspired in us by these threats assumed
apocalyptic proportions when the nocturnal
silence was suddenly shattered by the sound of
muffled explosions which startled us from our
sleep. We were told that these were German
torpedoes smashing into Allied ships out at sea.
Our earliest memories of motor vehicles date
from that time. Convoys of sand-coloured army
trucks and jeeps wending their way to and from
the base. Outlandish machines bristling with
weapons and swarming with otherworldly
figures, each of which represented a danger for
every one of us.
From time to time, however, a different kind
of vehicle would appear. It would pass fleetingly
along the road, sometimes even stopping for a
moment or two at the crossroads to drop off a
grown-up returning from Damietta. These were
private cars containing Egyptians.
:'. HV
UT
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Bahrlya oasis, Egypt.
We had no reason to be frightened of them.
We could give free rein to our sense of wonder.
All of our senses responded to the utter newness
of these contraptions which were so different
from the familiar landmarks of our lives by virtue
of their flawless lines, the smooth finish of their
bodywork, their even, gleaming colours, the purr
of their powerful invisible engines, and the smell
of petrol and exhaust fumeswhich we would
greedily fill our lungs with, racing for the
privilege, and which was as intoxicating to us as
the headiest of perfumes.
Then the marvellous machine would set off
towards the town, whose unknown charms it
epitomized, all those charms that then seemed to
us for ever out of reach.
We did not know that shortly those of us
who had successfully completed the course of
compulsory education would have the
opportunity to continue our studies in Damietta
itself. At least the well-to-do or educated families
would seize this opportunity for their children.
The first journey
Damietta was too far away for us to go there on
foot or even by donkey. So one fine day, without
any warning, we were taken to the famous
crossroads and told to wait. We didn't know what
we were waiting for but we were very excited.
It was the first time that, instead of going there
by ourselves, without any grown-ups knowing,
we had been taken to the crossroads by one of
them, acting on behalf of all our parents. A car
approached, slowed down and stopped. The
driver looked at us with an encouraging smile.
Then our hearts missed a beat. He asked us to
get in.
During that first car ride we were just as
frightened as we were thrilled. But fright soon
disappeared. On days when it wasn't too hot
some of us would stand on the running-board,
clinging to a window ledge, leaving the seats for
grown-up passengers. What words can express the 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
elation induced by speeding headlong into the
wind, at that moment when we cast off for ever
the weight of our childhood? In the fields, the
peasants would often stop work to watch us
whizz by, so quickly that we had no time to give
them the customary sign of greeting.
Two or three years later, when the war was
over, some families decided to go and settle in
Damietta, or to send their eldest children there
to live with other families who had already made
the move. This gave us an opportunity to explore
a town that we had until then only glimpsed as
we hurtled through it in the collective taxi that
took us from the village to school and back.
Explore was the word. Damietta seemed immense
to us, with empty squares so huge that each one
could have held an entire village, with tarred
roads along which plied buses, trucks, private cars
and taxis, and across which nonchalant donkeys
ambled at random. The small crossroads at the
entrance to our village that had for years seemed
to us to be a rendezvous for all the traffic in the
world, was no more than a pathetic memory.
Disturbing images
But our discoveries were only just beginning.
Another enchantment lay in store for us in
Damiettathe cinema. The magic of light-borne
images. And stories that unfolded, with a begin¬
ning and an end, with heroes whose love, courage
and kindness enabled them to triumph over fate.
And for whom the present ceased to be a mere
repetition of the past.
Most of the films were Egyptian. But some
of them were foreignEnglish or American and
they were even more disturbing. These men and
women were indefinably different from us. We
were affected by their sufferings and their joys,
but why did we feel that they nevertheless
belonged to a different planet from ours? Because
of their uninhibited way of talking about them¬
selves? Because of their way of tackling life head
on, of seeing an adventure through to its conclu¬
sion, of deciding and acting according to their
own desire and judgement, without bothering
about what the family thought or what the neigh¬
bours would say?
These men and women...but particularly the
women, so incredibly free in their speech and in
their movements. Their image remains engraved
on our memories. Young, beautiful, blonde, ele¬
gant, they drove convertibles. Why did this image
disturb us so? Around us were other pretty girls
and women whom we sometimes saw in the
streets bareheaded, with their hair loose. They
might be stylishly dressed, in frocks or skirts that
discreetly emphasized the'curves of their bodies.
But they had to be accompanied by father,
brother, uncle or husband. Even for a quick
errand, on a donkey, a woman had to be escorted
by a man. And now here was this fabulous
American actress who went out alone and drove
all by herself, controlling unaided a piece of
machinery so mysterious, so complicated, that it
seemed to be pre-eminently the preserve of men.
On the brink of adolescence cars and women
were to be a source of other mixed emotions. A
few of the older boys took us out of the town
at nightfall, to an isolated spot where, between
the trees or by a fence, parked cars could be made
out. The older boys encouraged us to go nearer,
18
American actress Grace Kelly
at the wheel of a convertible
In Alfred Hitchcock's film To
Catch a Thief. 1955.
Room at the top on a
crowded Egyptian bus.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
**>
w^
I
using all our stealth and guile, to look through
the window and see what was going on inside.
A man and a woman were kissing passionately,
impetuously. Once or twice it seemed to us, in
the darkness, that they were going even further.
We watched them, torn between a sense of shame
at intruding on their privacy and fear that we
would be caught spying on them. We would
make a bolt for it when the man's gaze met ours
or when the woman suddenly stared at us with
terrified eyes.
The privileged few
Cars thus lit for us, one by one, all the fires of
the modern world, so alien to our ways, which
were however already directly exposed to them:
the desire for escape and self-assertion, a love of
technical efficiency, the emancipation of women,
freedom....
But for most of us the ownership of a car
would long remain an unattainable dream. We
had left Damietta and were continuing our studies
in Cairo. At university, some students occasionally
turned up in their parents' cars. A few others,
even less numerous, drove their own. They were
the most privileged of all.
The rest, if they came from far away, had to
take the bus. This was the 1950s when public
transport was a disaster. Buses were old wheezy
vehicles sagging beneath the weight of too many
passengers. It was impossible to get in through
the jam-packed doorways unless you were ready
for a fight. Being young, we were lucky enough
to be able to get in through the windows. Envious
looks and sometimes insults were cast our way
by those whose girth or social standing prevented
them from doing likewise....
Imported luxury goods were subject to
increasingly restrictive measures. And these
measures applied especially to private cars. Yet
mysteriously these steadily increased in number.
City streets, which had not been designed to
accommodate such a concentration of traffic,
became each year slightly more congested than
before. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The new Ford BY JOHN STEINBECK
Extract from East of Eden (1952) © William Heinemann Ltd.
ni noon one day Will Hamilton came roaring
and bumping up the road in a new Ford. The
engine raced in Its low gear, and the high top
swayed like a storm-driven ship. The brass radi¬
ator and the Prestolite tank on the running-
board were blinding with brass polish.
Will pulled up the brake lever, turned the
switch straight down, and sat back in the leather
seat. The car backfired several times without
Ignition because it was overheated.
"Here she Is!" Will called with a false en¬
thusiasm. He hated Fords with a deadly hatred,
but they were daily building his fortune.
Adam and Lee hung over the exposed sides
of the car while Will Hamilton, puffing under the
burden of his new fat, explained the workings
of a mechanism he did not understand himself.
It Is hard now to imagine the difficulty of
learning to start, drive and maintain an automo¬
bile. Not only was the whole process complicat¬
ed, but one had to start from scratch. Today's
children breathe In the theory, habits and idio¬
syncrasies of the internal combustion engine
in their cradles, but then you started with the
blank belief that it would not run at all, and
sometimes you were right. Also, to start the
engine of a modern car you do just two things,
turn a key and touch the starter. Everything else
is automatic. The process used to be more com¬
plicated. It required not only a good memory,
a strong arm, an angelic temper, and a blind
hope, but also a certain amount of practice of
magic, so that a man about to turn the crank
of a Model T might be seen to spit on the
ground and whisper a spell.
Will Hamilton explained the car and went
Scene from Ella Kazan's 1955 film version of
East of fden.
back and explained it again. His customers were
wide-eyed, interested as terriers, co-operative,
and did not interrupt, but as he began for the
third time Will saw that he was getting no place.
"Tell you what!" he said brightly. "You see
this isn't my line. I wanted you to see her and
listen to her before I made delivery. Now, I'll go
back to town and tomorrow I'll send back this
car with an expert, and he'll tell you more in a
few minutes than I could in a week. But I just
wanted you to see her."
Will had forgotten some of his own Instruc¬
tions. He cranked for a while and then borrowed
a buggy and a horse from Adam and drove to
town, but he promised to have a mechanic out
the next day.
There was no question of sending the twins
to school the next day. They wouldn't have
gone. The Ford stood tall and aloof and dour
under the oak tree where Will had stopped it.
Its new owners circled it and touched It now and
then, the way you touch a dangerous horse to
soothe him.
Lee said, "I wonder whether I'll ever get
used to it."
"Of course you will," Adam said without
conviction. "Why, you'll be driving all over the
county first thing you know."
"I will try to understand it," Lee said. "But
drive it I will not."
The boys made little dives in and out, to
touch something and leap away. "What's this
do-hickey, Father?"
"Get your hands off that."
"But what's it for?"
"I don't know, but don't touch It. You don't
know what might happen."
"Didn't the man tell you?"
"I don't remember what he said. Now you
boys get away from it or I'll have to send you to
school. Do you hear me, Cal? Don't open that."
They had got up and were ready very ear¬
ly in the morning. By eleven o'clock hysterical
nervousness had set in. The mechanic drove
up in the buggy in time for the midday meal.
He wore box-toed shoes and Duchess trousers
and his wide square coat came almost to his
knees. Beside him in the buggy was a satchel
In which were his working clothes and tools. He
was nineteen and chewed tobacco, and from
his three months in automobile school he had
gained a great though weary contempt for hu¬
man beings.
JOHN STEINBECK, American novelist (1902-1968), Nobel Prize
for Literature 1962. His works include Tort/Ha Flat (1935), Of
Mice and Men (1937), The Grapes of Wrath (1939) and The
Winter of Our Discontent (1961).
Fafner the Dragon BY JULIO CORTÁZAR
Extract from Los autonaulas de la cosmopista, viaje attemporel París-Marsella
© Carol Dunlop and Julio Cortázar, 1983.
20
I his short but essential chapter is an auto-
quotation (a perfectly appropriate word in this
case) from a text written long ago whose title
is: Correction of Proofs in Haute-Provence.
So from time to time I stop working, I
wander around In the streets, I go into a bar,
I observe what's happening in town and I gossip
with the old man who sells me my lunch-time
sausage because the Dragonit's high time I
introduced you to himis a kind of moving
house or seashell on wheels that my obsessive
love for Wagner impelled me to call Fafner. A
red Volkswagen with a water-tank, and a seat
that lets down into a bed. I have added a radio,
a typewriter, books, bottles of red wine, pack¬
ets of soup and cardboard mugs. Plus swim¬
ming trunks for whenever the opportunity
arises, a lamp and a gas-ring that turns tinned
food into a meal while I listen to Vivaldi or pen
these words.
This stuff about the Dragon stems from a
long-felt need. I have rarely accepted the names
that are stuck onto things like labels, and I think
this is reflected in my books. I do not see why
we should always have to put up with what
comes to us from the past and from elsewhere.
So I have given to the beings I love and have
loved names derived from an encounter, a coin¬
cidence between secret codes. So women be¬
came flowers, birds or woodland animals. There
were friends whose names changed once a
cycle had run its course: a bear became a mon¬
key, a pale-eyed woman was first a cloud, then
a gazelle and finally a mandrake. Anyway, let's
get back to the Dragon. When two years ago
I saw him arrive in the Rue Cambronne, fresh
from the factory, with his wide red face, low-
set sparkling eyes, and laid-back air of bravado,
something in me went click and he became the
Dragon, and not just any old dragon but Fafner
who guarded the treasure of the Niebelungen
and who, according to legend and Wagner, is
brutal and stupid but has always aroused a
sneaking sympathy in me, perhaps because he
is doomed to die at the hand of Siegfried. I can't
forgive heroes that kind of thing: thirty years
ago I could never forgive Theseus for having
killed the Minotaur (I have only made the con¬
nection between these two things today). On
that particular afternoon I was much too busy
with the problems I was going to have with the
Dragon when it came to changing gear and
manoeuvringhe was much higher and wider
than my little old Renault. Now It seems obvi¬
ous to me that I only obeyed the instinct that
always leads me to defend those the estab¬
lished order regards as monsters and exter¬
minates as soon as it can. In two or three days
I became the Dragon's friend. I told him that
as far as I was concerned his name was no
longer Volkswagen. Poetry was, as so often,
right on target, for when I went to the garage
to have his number plate fastened on and saw
the mechanic screw a large F on his backside,
I was sure my hunch was correct. And even if
the mechanic would have insisted that the F
stood for France, the Dragon understood per¬
fectly. On our way home he showed me how
delighted he was by enthusiastically mounting
the pavement and scaring the wits out of a
housewife laden with shopping baskets.
JULIO CORTÁZAR, major Argentine writer (1914-1984). His
works translated into English include End of the Game, and
Other Stories (1967), and the novels Hopscotch (1963), A
Manual for Manuel (1973) and We Love Glenda So Much (1980).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The capital, far bigger though it was than
Damietta, suffered an even more massive inva¬
sion. Whole districts, suburbs and satellite towns
sprang up around it. And as the distances grew,
so new highways were built, and were immedi¬
ately submerged by more and more cars. Except
for a small minority of people who worked and
lived in the same neighbourhood, it became
increasingly difficult to do without a means of
mechanical transport. How could one walk to an
office, factory, faculty, or cinema miles from
home, or to the homes of friends and relatives
who were now scattered far and wide?
In the buses, the number of which never kept
up with the increase in the working population,
travelling became a mental and physical ordeal.
Taxis, which were too expensive, could be taken
only from time to time. The private car became
a necessity as well as a status symbol. People paid
for them by instalments, or purchased imported
second-hand models which could be tinkered
with all day long. But those who had succeeded
in business or saved some money while working
for a few years in an oil-producing country made
it a point of honour to buy, cash down, ¿"brand-
new German sedan.
..%
Driving into an impasse
Cars were no longer a pipe-dream. Either you had
one or, if you didn't, you wanted one. But for
everyone they had lost their mystery. They were
everywhere, they could be seen, they could be
touched. All the streets were lined with them,
bumper to bumper, the latest models and ancient
jalopies. Cars no longer partook of the eternal
springtime of dreams. Every day we saw
specimens in every stage of physical deterioration.
There were traffic jams, accidents, breakdowns,
causing endless problems both for drivers and for
the millions of passers-by. Everywhere people
cursed the fact that they needed cars and
bemoaned the frustration they caused....
Strangely, the car seems to have created as
many problems as it has solved. A gigantic game
which ends in a draw, in which everyone may
be said to feel a little freer and slightly more
trapped. We produce more, we consume more,
we drive more. At the cost of gutted cities,
expressways strung between apartment blocks,
blocking off the sky in whole districts, parks
sacrificed for the sake of parking lots and pollu¬
tion that sets a screen between us and the light
of day....
Perhaps, despite everything, the car remains
a pipe-dream. Or a marvellous machine that
meekly obeys us, on roads that do not disturb
the beauty of the landscape or the cows' slumber.
But the dream is no longer one of the future. It
is nostalgia for a lost childhood, near the end of
the war, at a deserted crossroads.
Traffic congestion In a Cairo thoroughfare.
mm a*
<i/r
-M
r-jr^r
-* I
» * r
.v. L
«*V
i
~. 3
f
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
BY ROBERT BRAUNSCHWEIG
A revolution
on wheels
Solutions must
be found to
environmental
and other
problems
surrounding
the automobile,
victim of its
own success
22
ROBERT BRAUNSCHWEIG
is a Swiss engineer who has
been writing about motoring
since 1932. From 1943 to
1980 he was on the staff of
Revue automobile/Automobil
Revue, latterly as
editor-in-chief. He is the author
of many articles and
technical studies on cars
and driving.
Or'NLY a century ago, cars were few and far
between. They coughed and spluttered along roads
intended for pedestrians, cyclists, and the horse-
drawn carriages which in shape they strongly
resembled. Regarded without enthusiasm by those
who happened to get in their way, these new¬
fangled machines were the realization of man's
ancient dream of personal mobility. A revolution
was about to begin.
Today, there are more than 500 million
motor vehicles in the worldabout 400 million
private cars and 100 million commercial vehicles.
It should not be thought, however, that the
automobile has become a means of transport
available to all. One-fifth of the world's popula¬
tion, living in North America, Western Europe,
Japan and Australia, runs 80 per cent of all the
motor vehicles on the planet. Cars are beyond
the reach of most of humanity. They symbolize
the gap that separates plenty from penury.
Before and after
It is hard for us today to imagine what life was
like around 1890, when there were no cars, tele¬
phones, televisions or electrical household appli¬
ances, when equal rights between men and
women did not exist, and there were no paid
holidays. In those days the only way for most
people to avoid a long daily trudge to and from
work was to live near their workplace. How
different is the situation today when millions of
office-workers drive to work each day from their
homes in the distant suburbs of the world's great
cities. Once upon a time people bought what they
needed each day at the local shops. Nowadays
they drive to distant shopping centres and return
home with enough provisions to keep them going
for weeks. Once fields were ploughed by teams
of plodding horses or oxen, and farm hands cut
hay with scythes and loaded it onto hay-carts
with pitchforks. Today machines have taken over
from human muscle and do the work much more
quickly.
In town and country alike people now have
cars. Once the prerogative of a small minority,
holidays far away from home are within reach
of the many. Holidaymakers drive to distant
countries, or fly there and hire a car at the airport.
The servants once employed by the wealthy have
almost entirely disappeared. Anyone still able to
afford domestic help must be ready to provide
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Above, prototype design by
computer, 1989.
Left, a Ford production line,
1923.
them with parking space. Teenagers drive around
in cars or on motorcycles. People travel long dis¬
tances to go fishing, camp, or practise their
favourite sports.
But for today's car-owner this mobility is far
from being synonymous with total freedom of
movement. Where there are too many of them
concentrated in one place, cars defeat their own
object. Traffic grinds to a halt. At holiday time
there are interminable traffic jams, even on major
highways. In towns and cities the search for a
parking place is a daily chore. Roads and cars have
become safer and men and women more skilful
in using them, but United Nations statistics show
that the automobile takes a heavy toll of human
lives. More than 200,000 people are killed every
year and even more are injured, in many cases
seriously.
?A tool or a weapon?
Intrinsically, the automobile is neither good nor
bad. It all depends on the use to which it is put.
It can serve doctors and patients, bank robbers,
truck drivers and kidnappers. Is it not primarily,
to paraphrase the Swiss writer Friedrich Dürren¬
matt, a high-quality "artificial limb"? 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Goddess BY ROLAND BARTHES
Extract from Mythologies (1957), translated by Annette Lovers © Jonathan Cape Ltd., 1972.
I
24
think that cars today are almost the exact equiva¬
lent of the great Gothic cathedrals: I mean the
supreme creation of an era, conceived with pas¬
sion by unknown artists, and consumed in ¡mage if
not in usage by a whole population which appropri¬
ates them as a purely magical object.
It is obvious that the new Citroen has fallen
from the sky inasmuch as it appears at first sight
as a superlative object. We must not forget that
an object is the best messenger of a world above
that of nature: one can easily see in an object at
once a perfection and an absence of origin, a
closure and a brilliance, a transformation of life
into matter (matter is much more magical than life),
and in a word a silence which belongs to the realm
of fairytales. The DSthe Déesse or "Goddess"
has all the features (or at least the public is unani¬
mous in attributing them to it at first sight) of one
of those objects from another universe which have
supplied fuel for the neomania of the eighteenth
century and that of our own science fiction: the
Déesse is first and foremost a new Nautilus.
This is why it excites interest less by its sub¬
stance than by the junction of its components. It is
well known that smoothness is always an attribute
of perfection because its opposite reveals a tech¬
nical and typically human operation of assembling:
Christ's robe was seamless, just as the airships
of science fiction are made of unbroken metal. The
DS 19 has no pretensions about being as smooth
as cake-icing, although its general shape is very
rounded; yet it is the dovetailing of its sections
which interests the public most: one keenly fingers
the edges of the windows, one feels along the wide
rubber grooves which link the back window to its
metal surround. There are in the DS the beginnings
of a new phenomenology of assembling, as if one
progressed from a world where elements are
welded to a world where they are juxtaposed and
hold together by sole virtue of their wondrous
shape, which of course is meant to prepare one
for the idea of a more benign Nature....
It is possible that the Déesse marks a change
in the mythology of cars. Until now, the ultimate
in cars belonged rather to the bestiary of power;
here it becomes at once more spiritual and more
object-like, and despite some concessions to
neomania (such as the empty steering wheel), it
is now more homely, more attuned to this subli¬
mation of the utensil which one also finds in the
design of contemporary household equipment.
The dashboard looks more like the working sur¬
face of a modern kitchen than the control-room
of a factory: the slim panes of matt fluted metal,
the small levers topped by a white ball, the very
simple dials, the very discreteness of the nickel-
work, all this signifies a kind of control exercised
over motion, which is henceforth conceived as
comfort rather than performance. One is obviously
turned from an alchemy of speed to a relish in
driving.
The public, it seems, has admirably divined the
novelty of the themes which are suggested to it.
Responding at first to the neologism (a whole pub¬
licity campaign had kept it on the alert for years),
it tries very quickly to fall back on a behaviour
which indicates adjustment and a readiness to use
("You've got to get used to it"). In the exhibition
halls, the car on show is explored with an intense,
amorous studiousness: it is the great tactile phase
of discovery, the moment when visual wonder is
about to receive the reasoned assault of touch (for
touch is the most demystifying of all senses, unlike
sight, which is the most magical). The bodywork,
the lines of union are touched, the upholstery pal¬
pated, the seats tried, the doors caressed, the
cushions fondled; before the wheel, one pretends
to drive with one's whole body. The object here
is totally prostituted, appropriated: originating from
the heaven of Metropolis, the Goddess is in a
quarter of an hour mediatized, actualizing through
this exorcism the very essence of petit-bourgeois
advancement.
ROLAND BARTHES, French essayist and critic (1915-1980).
His works translated into English include Writing Degree Zero
(1953), On Racine (1963), Critica/ Essays (1964), Elements of
Semiology (1965), S/Z (1970) and A Lover's Discourse (1977).
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Delivering fuel at Luxor,
Egypt.
Right, traffic congestion
In a Paris suburb, 1923.
But some people regard driving primarily as
a sport. Burning up the kilometres is their dream.
The car has not changed the character of men or
women, the latter often being more resistant to
its attractions than the former. There are all sorts
of driversthe timid and the adventurous, the
cautious and the quick-tempered, the discreet and
the flamboyant.
In those parts of the world where car-
ownership is particularly widespread, the car is
a major consumer of non-renewable energy and
one of the most significant causes of nuisance and
environmental pollution. A solution to these
problems will not be found by turning the clock
back but by making correct technological choices.
More respect must be shown for the interests of
the community at large and less for those of each
individual. This process is likely to take time.
The poorer countries
In the less motorized regions of the EarthAsia
(excluding Japan), Africa, Latin America and cer¬
tain parts of Oceaniathere are, for every thou¬
sand inhabitants, about forty times fewer cars
than in North America and Western Europe. In
some rapidly growing cities of the South, such
as Rio de Janeiro, Hong Kong, Mexico City, Tel
Aviv, Cairo and Singapore, the traffic concentra¬
tion is intense. But in most of these places car
ownership is the privilege of a chosen few-
wealthy private individuals and those who have
the use of an official vehicle. There were only
280,000 cars in China in 1980, for example, just
over twice as many as in Luxembourg! Commer¬
cial vehicles far outnumber private cars, which
are seen as a luxury, and the road network is often
inadequate. Heavy-duty vehicles are used to trans¬
port goods and buses to carry people.
Popular motoring
The idea of a "popular" car began to take shape
at the turn of the century in the form of simpli¬
fied versions of the classic models of the day, but
fifty years were to elapse before the idea came
to fruition. During this period there were three
major developments in production techniques:
the change from hand-crafted construction to
standardization, the introduction of the assembly
line, on which more than 10,000 vehicles could
be manufactured annually, and finally
automationthe introduction of robots capable
of carrying out most operations and the use of
computerized manufacturing programmes.
These revolutionary changes did not take
place everywhere at the same speed. The first
production line was installed in the United States
by the great pioneer Henry Ford, who wanted
to "put America on wheels" by producing an
automobile that was both robust and cheap. In
1909, his Model T, the famous "Tin Lizzie",
came on to the market and was an enormous
success. By 1927 more than fifteen million Model
T's had been produced. The rest of the American
automobile industry followed Ford's example,
and within a few years the United States had
become the only country in the world where car
ownership was the rule rather than the exception.
In Europe, its birthplace, the car remained
a rarity for much longer. Expansion of the
automobile industry was interrupted by two
world wars. Assembly-line production was most
notably successful in France, thanks to three
entrepreneurs, André Citroën, who was the first
to branch out into this activity, Louis Renault
and Robert Peugeot.
In Italy, Giovanni Agnelli, the founder of
Fiat and grandfather of the present head of the
company, built two factories whose prospects
were improved by the favourable attitude of the
fascist regime towards the automobile. Germany,
exhausted by its defeat in 1918, was unable to
follow the trend immediately, although Ford
relaunched the production of German cars at its
Cologne subsidiary, followed shortly afterwards
by General Motors, which took over Opel. The
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Entrant In a rally of
vehicles powered by
solar energy,
Switzerland, 1986.
26
coming of the Nazi regime paved the way for the
expansion of the German car industry. By a cruel
irony of history, the world-famous Volkswagen
the "people's car"owes its existenceto Adolf
Hitler.
Improvements in quality
Within a few decades production methods in the
automobile industry have been revolutionized.
These changes, which are far from over, have led
to remarkable improvements in quality. While
the basic conception has not changed, many
aspects of the car have been transformed, above
all by automation. Electronics and microcom¬
puter technology are used not only to control
seats, windows and doors, but also the engine,
transmission and suspension.
The "popular car" now exists. The Japanese
car industry, a relatively late starter but today the
world's leading producer, has largely contributed
to its development. Far from being the uncom¬
fortable midget it once was, today's popular car
has all the latest equipment. Since it is small, it
can take chaotic urban traffic conditions in its
stride. Its main competitor is the second-hand car
which offers yesterday's comfort at cut price.
Today twenty American, European and
Asian companies produce 99 per cent of the
world's cars. Inheritors of the 6,000-odd compa¬
nies that feature in the history of the automobile,
they are established all over the world. Although
they are competitors, they work more and more
closely together. They are studying projects to
take over the stricken industries of Eastern
Europe. They are the nucleus of a huge sector
of diversified activity to which our age owes part
of its wealth.
What does the future hold for the automo¬
bile? More necessary than ever, it must solve the
environmental problems that its success has
spawned. Today much unpublicized work is
being devoted to efforts to transform the automo¬
bile, at a time when an alarmed public opinion
in one half of the globe feels pessimistic about
its future, whilst people in the other half feel
cruelly deprived of its benefits. The second
automobile revolution has begun.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The wrong
track
BY NICOLAS LANGLOIS
NICOLAS LANGLOIS,
of France, has been a
journalist with the French daily
Le Monde (1972) and
the weekly (.'Express
(1973-1978). In 1979
he launched a bimonthly
magazine, Le Journal de
l'Automobile, of which he is
editor-in-chief.
Xhings have changed in the East. And what
slipped through the first breach in the Iron Cur¬
tain but the automobile. The car-manufacturing
West, whose ramifications stretch as far as
Southeast Asia, had found a new stamping
ground. In the Soviet Union, perestroika and
automobile are hand in glove. All the world's car
makers have made the trip to Moscow.
So does the automobile mean freedom? Yes,
if we're talking about free market economics.
Yes, when we remember that buying a car is
always an exciting event. Yes, when we think of
some drivers, the privileged citizens of
unprivileged countries. Or when we dream of
exploring wide open spaces.
But are we not being taken in by a myth, the
myth of freedom to go anywhere, effortlessly, at
a speed that mere physical effort cannot permit?
The idea is seductive, but given the way it has
been put into practice it seems likely to defeat
its own object. Won't a surfeit of cars bring the
traffic to a halt?
Taking the world as a whole, the car is no
more than a dream for nine persons out of ten.
In Western Europe it means a job for one person 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
out of ten. In Europe, North America and Japan,
cars are the occasion for trade fairs, the object of
market strategies, a social issue. Their fantastic
magnetism leads to all kinds of abuses.
On the road
Let's not indulge in misplaced nostalgia. Let the
so-called developed world sort out its inconsisten¬
cies and burn its own idols. The rich have taken
the car for a ride, side-tracked it from its voca¬
tion. A wonderful contrivance has become an
intrusive machine, a chrome-finished gadget, a
status symbol. The modern equivalent of the
circus games of ancient Rome, motor sports eulo¬
gize speed and reach a worldwide audience
through television. But cars can also kill, damage
the environment, pollute. Let's not be indifferent,
either. The spoiled children are far outnumbered
by the forgotten millions excluded from the
benefits of growth. More than 85 per cent of the
cars manufactured in 1989 were sold in North
America, Western Europe and Japan.
This versatile mechanical aid has so many
uses. Cars, trucks, buses and coaches break down
the barriers of isolation, facilitate trade, bring
people together, and realize certain hopes for
development.
The materialization of a dream of freedom,
the car also promotes a kind of equality. It is
industry's gift to democracy and a social leveller
second only to television. Drivers trapped in a
traffic jam are all equal, however much their
vehicles cost and however fast they can go. But
at a time when the world's population is tending
to concentrate in towns and cities, the car is
becoming an expensive amenity. But to think that
we are poisoning the planet just to travel in some
kind of comfort...
Great expectations
Dreaming and negligence have turned the car into
a scourge of our times, but a scourge which is
considered indispensable, sought-after and
encouraged. It is a fomentor of disarray, a lord
of misrule. Once an instrument of pleasure, it has
become a necessity, an indispensable means of
coping with the constraints of new life-styles. Its
reign heralds anarchy and overpopulation. The
car factories produce in order to provide much-
needed jobs. They turn out cars; the cars are
bought. Everybody wants one. What can be done
to put this juggernaut back on the right track?
Perhaps a few restrictions are starting to be
imposed here and there. Some uses of the car have
been codified. Many people think that cars are
being used as a scapegoat for the pollution of the
planet. Cars may cause pollution, but they are
an exposed target. We pay lip service to the
quality of the air, but at the same time we carry
on digging, building roads, underpasses and
highways to absorb the constantly increasing den¬
sity of traffic.
We ask so much of the car. Think of all those
young Americans who have to learn to drive at
the age of fifteen if they want to go anywhere.
Think of all those poor souls cooped up for hours
on end in their steel containers. What does it
matter whether they are going on holiday or
going to work? There is no other transport
system to get them into town. For the private
individual, the car is the least costly modern
means of transport.
Why, at the end of the twentieth century, in
a so-called developed country, does a middle-class
homo sapiens spend more of his income on his car
than on his house? Because the car is all things
to all men: source of taxes, dynamo of economic
development, provider of jobs. The automobile
industry is set to create new jobs in Eastern
Europe just as it once rescued southern Italy and
northern France, and still helps sustain the British
economy.
The commuter's nightmare
When the traditional mainstays of the economy
fail, when the steel industry winds down and the
construction industry goes into recession, the
motor industry is always there to save the day.
Whatever burdens they may have to shoulder,
drivers love their cars and go on doing so whatever
the price. It's a good thing too, since they often
have no choice.
Back in the 1950s, the idiotic game of com¬
muting to work by car was invented. In the cities
the tramlines were torn up, dormitory suburbs
were built, and trains were replaced by coaches
and trucks. Little thought was given to the
victims.
In modern cities white lines, have taken the
place of tramlines. These are the major achieve¬
ments of an age which will not accept that
different things have different uses. Versatile
though it is, the car is doubtless not made to com¬
pete with the aircraft, the train or the bicycle on
their own terms. But people are the easiest com¬
modities to transportthey know how to wait,
they travel alone, they do not deteriorate.
Competitor In the Kenya
Rally, 1984. In background,
Mount Kilimanjaro.
Cadillac-shaped villa
In California.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
r
And so we have decided not to think too
much. We build roads to accommodate the
machines which pour from the factories at a rate
of over 150,000 a day. And so it goes on, an endless
game of follow-my-leader.
The mainspring of the economy must not
give way. When the Japanese rely on their cars
to set the seal on their economic supremacy,
other countries try to riposte in their own way.
To escape invasion, loss of profits and jobs, coun¬
tries add more muscle to their own automobile
industries. But perhaps without thinking about
what they should really be doing. In other fields
we listen to the experts. The ideal range of an air¬
craft is well known. It is common knowledge that
up to a distance of 700 kilometres, the train is
superior to air transport. We know that we're
producing the wrong kind of vehicle.
Only a few years ago, the budget of a country
like France was equivalent to the turnover of the
world's leading car-maker. Today, in the world's
seven richest countries, car firms, followed by the
oil companies, still lead the economy in terms of
turnover and profit.
The dream of blue horizons
So far the elastic has not given way. The lust for
cars is still as powerful as ever. It still keeps the
wheels of big business turning, and fuels interna¬
tional trade. These colonizers do not even need
to evoke other culturesthey make and sell a
dream. Has car-worship not been a religion in the
so-called developed countries?
So let's take it easy. Too bad if the car slows
to a halt. Too bad if certain inequalities appear
again. The dream is getting some rough treat¬
ment. It's had its day. Today only advertising can
show wide open spaces, our dreams of blue
horizons and the romance of travel.
What does it matter? Let maturity wait for
another century, for other generations worship¬
ping other gods. Let them try to sort things out...
as long as they can still draw breath. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Sex drive BY STEPHEN BAYLEY
Extract from an article in the International Herald Tribune
Centennial Magazine, 1987. All Rights Reserved.
30
nu alluring car always reflects the culture that
created it. A Jaguar, Britain's most desired automo¬
bile, was modelled on the interior of the English
country house; perhaps only in a Jaguar and a
house in the Thames Valley will you find leather
and wood used so confidently.
The Germans' passion is for what they call
research, a concept perhaps best articulated by
the Porsche designer who said his cars should
have "the winning look that weapons have". Hitler
chose Ferdinand Porsche to design his "people's
car", the Volkswagen, to enable families to savour
the German forest from the Reich's toll-free
autobahns. Porsche, jailed by the French for his
wartime activities, spent his internment designing
a sports car.
Porsche became the most notorious and
desirable of sports cars when movie star James
Dean, 24, died at the wheel of his Spyder in 1955
and left behind a cult of mourners. (Some women
are haunted by another traumatically unforgettable
image of death by car: Isadora Duncan snapping
her neck when her long red stage scarf caught in
the wire spokes of a low-slung Bugatti.)
The eros of the engine is not always morbid.
Remember the Beach Boys singing "She's so fine,
my 409"? Equating cars and sex is not just a pop
cliché. It also is probably the marketing coup of
the century. Curvaceous cars recall other svelte,
sculpted forms, and engine power is an easy
metaphor for active sex. The Corvette, for
example, was 1950s teenage libido cast in plastic,
chrome and Naugahyde. It was supposed to be
America's version of the European sports car. But,
with its bulbous tyres and delivery-truck handling,
it was a car for drive-ins, not for driving. Ads often
showed a two-seater Corvette as a love seat for
a premarital couple sublimating their mating
games.
Design, so often touted by manufacturers, is
never innocent. Memorable cars embody cultural
temperaments. Ferraris have to be red; the
Mercedes-Benz fias to be the colour of hard metal,
not of crushed soft fruit. The London taxi, a func¬
tional box on wheels, has been called the perfect
industrial car design but has never really caught
on elsewhere.
National personalities are so strong that It is
possible to recognize a car's origin from the
merest fin. France's Citroën unveiled its modern
sedan without Its wheels to enhance the sculpted
shape. Called the DS (a variant of its factory code),
it quickly became the déesse, French for goddess
a veneration prolonged in French drivers' velour
seats, foam-filled dollops offering ectomorphic
embrace.
In Germany, Porsche's successor generation
demilitarized their cars' look in keeping with the
te -T
Mercedes-Bem FormeM-Rennwagen
W 196 R Stromlinie, 1954,
acrylic on canvas by Andy Warhol.
The work was commissioned In 1986
by the car manufacturers.
times. In a BMW glowing with red dials, the most
prominent instrument is often the clock. Punctu¬
ality symbolizes the reliability Germans expect in
their machinesso different from the ostentatious
rationality offered, say, in a Volvo, which appeals
to the taste for sensible technology and environ¬
mental consciousness.
The car of the future seems likely to come
from Japan. Japanese industrial power makes inno¬
vation easy and the goal is the zero-defect vehicle.
That would be something new. Cars, like people,
have to be flawed to be interesting. My advice is,
get it while you can.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
In Panama,
Haiti and
Colombia,
traditions of
popular art and
culture are
reflected in
colourfully
decorated trucks
and buses
MOIRA F. HARRIS
is an American art historian
who specializes in forms of
popular culture such as
outdoor murals and painted
vehicles. She is the author of
Art on the Road: The Painted
Vehicles of the Americas,
Pogo Press, Minnesota. 1988.
Art on the road
AlCK a street, any street, in Panama City or
Port-au-Prince and you'll probably see them.
You'll find them in Medellin, Colombia, as well,
but there you must visit the outskirts of town
or the market area. "They" are the wonderfully
decorated buses and trucks which are the
privately-owned public transportation of these
cities. Ride a tap-tap, chiva or bus and you're in
for an aesthetic treat. You'll travel down the
street in a marvellous mix of art and words,
accompanied by flashing lights and pulsating
music.
Each of these vehicles began life as a solid
colour truck or bus accented with chrome. Each
has now been rebuilt for its new role in life and
decorated to suit the current fashion. Students of
popular culture agree that the paintings and
words decorating these vehicles offer an insight
into widely shared attitudes and beliefs, into the
"soul", perhaps, of Panama, Haiti and Colombia.
BY MOIRA F. HARRIS
The art of decorating these painted trucks and
buses basically started after the Second World
War, although there may be older examples of
it. Chivas, tap-taps and buses quickly won an
important place in the local economies and affec¬
tions. Every so often other types of buses or
trucks are brought in to replace the painted
vehicles, but these interlopers will never obscure
the place which chivas, tap-taps and buses have
already earned in the literature and art of their
respective countries.
In Panama, yellow school buses built in the
United States are the raw material. The original
colour is quickly hidden under layers of sprayed or
airbrushed paint. Along the sides of the bus,
beneath the windows, very long images are
The canine characters painted on this Colombian truck are
Inspired by advertising calendars produced by the Brown
and Blgelow Company In the 1930s and Illustrated by a
New York artist, Cassius M. Coolldge.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Kustom cars in the USA
i
32
n the United States kustom cars are one of
a kind, unique expressions of an owner's dream.
They cannot be found in a manufacturer's
advertisement or in a dealer's showroom.
Instead, they are created, painstakingly, in
specialized garages and backyard workshops.
Owners often design, then build and rebuild
these cars which are either stripped for speed
(the "hot or street rods") or so heavily loaded
that they can barely move (the "lead sleds" and
"low riders").
Hot rods began as small Fords from the
1930s, especially the 1932 Ford two-door or
"deuce coupe". Although Ford did not build
these cars for speed, with a few changes, race
cars they became. The body needed to be
streamlined so off came all the chrome. Door
handles, bumpers, sometimes even fenders and
running-boards, were stripped away. The roof
was lowered and windows reduced in height.
Hot rod owners challenged each other to
races on city streets, "burning rubber" in their
quick starts. Thus tyres often had to be
replaced. Moviegoers will remember such
challenges in the film American Graffiti. Speed
was the message even in the rod's paint.
Instead of wings, painters laid patterns for
flames beginning at the engine and curling back
to engulf the sides and doors of the cars.
Today's flames come in many hues. Numerous
layers of metal flake and candy coloured
acrylics allow iridescent effects to shine
through. Flames in combinations of green over
purple, blue against yellow, or pink with red are
then outlined with the thin calligraphic lines of
pinstriping.
The lead sled aesthetic is in sharp contrast
to that of the hot rods or street rods. Builders
of lead sleds use the heavier, bulkier body of
a 1936 Ford or a Mercury, Chevrolet or Dodge
from the 1950s. The body is lowered by cut¬
ting away horizontal sections, chrome is
removed and the holes may be filled with lead.
Exhaust pipes attached to the sides of the car
emphasize its new ground-sweeping ride. Head¬
lights and taillights may be recessed or
"Frenched", and rear wheels covered by fender
skirts, again extending the low line of the car
body. Unlike the classic car owner who insists
on repairing his automobile with original equip¬
ment, the lead sled builder is more concerned
with the look than the source. One lead sled
owner spoke proudly of the parts he had used
from twenty-two other cars to create his
masterpiece.
Inside the lead sled, the owner replaces
upholstery, installs air conditioning and a tape-
deck. Lead sled owners like smooth tuck and
roll upholstery, while low rider owners from the
southwest prefer crushed velvet upholstery
inside the car and often inside the trunk as well.
When the car is finished, the proper final touch
is a pair of large fuzzy dice hanging from the
rear view mirror.
The lead sled's exterior paint will match the
name given to the car. "Toad", for example,
was a 1949 Oldsmobile painted a dark lilypad
green. "The Black Widow", a 1951 Ford, was
black with red pinstriped webs near door and
trunk handles. Pinstriping, flames and scallops
have been painted on lead sleds since the
beginning, but murals are a more recent style
of decoration. Airbrushed murals became
fashionable for the side panels of vans and
small trucks in the 1970s. A recently painted
mural of the California Raisins animated clay
characters appears on the trunk of a 1935
Hudson lead sled.
Both the fast and slow members of the
kustom car world originated in southern
California. Car shows, car clubs and car maga¬
zines soon proliferated across the United
States, so that today rods and sleds can be ;
found almost everywhere. Low riders or carros
bajos are mainly found in the Hispanic cities of
the southwest from San Antonio, Texas, to San
José, California.
So much time and expense is involved in
building them that these cars are no longer
driven every day. They once provided cheap,
basic transportation, but are now too valuable
for such duty. Many lead sleds and street rods
are driven only in good weather when they will
"cruise", or drive slowly to car shows. Slowly
they cruise so everyone can admire them.
Slowly they cruise because for the hot rods,
lead sleds and low riders it is, above all, the
custom.
A writhing dragon adorns
this Panamanian bus.
Kustom car In Pennsylvania,
USA.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
shown. A speeding semi-trailer truck, a mermaid
in her undersea home, a view of mountains with a
distant castle, or even the turning, writhing form
of a dragon are among the images painted here.
Bus art
The rear emergency door is regarded as the most
important spot for bus art, a focal point where
an artist concentrates his best work, probably
because the rear door is seen the most easily and
for the longest time as the bus passes. Artists sign
these back door paintings with name or nick¬
name, sometimes with "Painted by..." and, occa¬
sionally, with a telephone number so that other
customers may locate them.
The subject for a back door bus painting can
be religious or secular, but it is almost never polit¬
ical. Artists become adept in certain categories.
Those bus owners who want Christ, the Virgin
Mary, or various saints painted know which
artists to choose, as do those who prefer comic
strip superheroes like Mexico's Kaliman, com¬
mercial cartoon characters like the Playboy
Bunny, or television actors. A star's popularity
could well be rated by his appearance or disap¬
pearance from bus art. Hollywood's "Mr. T" in
his gold chains and Don Johnson, the Miami Vice
cop, may well be painted over now that their
programmes no longer appear on prime time
television.
Jesus Teodoro de Villarue, or "Yo Yo" as he
is affectionately known, is regarded as one of the
old masters of Panamanian bus art. Yo Yo taught
his sons and other apprentices how to paint, but
he felt that there were other bus artists who
needed his guidance as well. So Yo Yo created
for posterity a series of lessons in rear door
painting. Carefully numbered and titled "Arte
Popular", Yo Yo's lessons can be seen on the rear
doors and windows of twenty Panamanian buses.
Ferocious lions, fierce eagles and even cigar-
smoking dogs are portrayed on the back doors
of buses and trucks. Two painters, one in Panama
and the other in Colombia, were inspired by the
same advertising calendar printed by the Brown
and Bigelow Company, a North American adver¬
tising specialities firm. For many years Brown
and Bigelow calendars have featured a series of
dog paintings originally created by a New York
artist named Cassius Marcellus Coolidge who
died in 1934. Often shown smoking fat cigars
(Coolidge had earlier painted cigar box lids), these
bulldogs, collies and Great Danes played cards,
billiards and baseball, and went to the races.
While Panamanian bus art reflects the changing
urban popular culture of television, movies and
music, the subjects for Colombian chiva painters 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
focus more often on rural life. Chivas are rebuilt
trucks, converted to carry both passengers and
agricultural products from Colombian villages to
markets in larger cities such as Medellin, Cali or
Cartagena. Both the names for these trucks and
the styles of decoration vary from one Colom¬
bian province to another. Many observers feel
that the camion de escalera or ladder truck of
Antioquia province is the most beautiful of all.
Cows and coffee
To rebuild a large Ford or General Motors truck,
workers remove the entire cargo area, replacing it
Religious and secular themes
Intermingle In tap-tap
decoration, Haiti.
34
with a partially enclosed structure. The interior
is arranged with rows of removable seats which
can be entered from the outside at every row.
This arrangement was copied from old trolley
cars which also had numerous side entrances. If
the chiva's load is large, two cows, for example,
or multiple sacks of coffee, it is easy to remove
most, if not all, of the seats.
The design along both exterior sides of the
chiva is, by longtime convention, geometric.
Carefully measured triangles, circles and lines are
painted in the area below the windows and
between the rows of seats. The rear door is
reserved for the chiva painter's major effort.
The clients of chiva painters bring postcards
to suggest the subjects that they want to see
painted on the rear door. Perhaps San Francisco's
Golden Gate Bridge, a cottage in a mountain
valley, or a jumbo jet in flight, will remind the
chiva owner of places he might like to visit
someday. Religious scenes are often based on
chromolithographs, as they are in Panama and
Haiti. The Virgin and Child, St. Peter against a
fluffy background of clouds, or scenes from the
Life of Christ, all can be traced to readily avail¬
able printed sources. A particular scene showing
Christ carrying the Cross is intended to refer to
a pilgrimage site in the nearby town of Girardota.
What is completely missing in the range of
Colombian chiva painting is any reference to the
worlds of television, movies and popular music.
Tina Turner, Rambo and Janet Jackson have not
made it to Colombia. When the chiva heads
down the road to the market in the nearest big
city, the passengers may well have glimpsed a
copy of Millet's The Gleaners on the back door,
but not a whiff of Miami Vice.
Medellin does not allow chiva drivers to
follow routes within the city as they once did
since it is felt that overloaded chivas are dan¬
gerous. In Haiti, overloaded or not, tap-taps are
everywhere. For short trips within the cities or
for long hauls between towns, tap-taps and their
larger cousins, the bois fouille trucks, rule the
routes.
In Haiti a tap-tap begins life as a pickup truck.
Once tap-taps were built on the bodies of Fords
and Chevrolets, but now the names of Isuzu,
Mazda and Toyota are more often seen on the
tailgates. The cargo area of a pickup may be small,
but it can be arranged to provide seats and easy
access. First the tailgate is removed. It is divided
with the sections placed on either side of what
is now the entrance to the tap-tap. Sides and a
roof are built of wood making the "habitat" in
which the passengers will ride, seated on benches
paralleling the walls. Even though this size tap-
tap does not have a great deal of space to decorate,
whatever room there is on the exterior walls and
doors is painted with fruits, flowers, birds and
animals. The habitat of the large boisfouille truck
is built with an open side entrance, the opening
often having a carved and brightly painted frame.
Tap-taps have names painted over the wind¬
shields and along the roof of the habitat. Bumpers
and fenders provide space for a constantly
expanding literature of slogans, mottoes and refer¬
ences to biblical verses. There is not always
enough space to transcribe an entire passage from
the Scriptures, so tap-tap painters abbreviate by
writing Psaumes 1, Exode 14:14, or Romains 15:7
in available places. Names include those of family
members and friends, names of saints, places, or
those of well-known people such as Jean-Paul
Belmondo, Al Capone, or Diego Maradona the
soccer player. Tap-tap writing is a multi-lingual
world of Creole, French, Spanish and English
which freely mingles the topical and the religious,
but seldom includes any political comment.
Erzulie Freda's flamingoes
At first the portraits of the saints and of the Holy
Family on Haitian tap-taps seem very familiar
since they are often based on the same stock
images used by artists in Colombia and Panama.
However, the viewer's interpretation may not be
the same at all. Believers in vodun, the syncretic
religion of Haiti, look at St. James the Major (or
Santiago) and see Ogun the "loa" or god of war.
The Virgin Mary in crown and robes as the
Queen of Heaven is understood to be really
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Ê9fP5Bl
I vAV^i
ri^fMiA
s<
A Haitian bofs fouille truck. Erzulie Freda, the loa of love in Haiti. Colours,
birds, animals and flowers are linked to certain
loas so the tap-tap artist will often incorporate
Agoue's boat, Ogun's sword, or Erzulie's
flamingoes in his overall design. Paintings and
slogans showing Christ as the Good Shepherd
may be interpreted both as Christian imagery and
as the tap-tap owner's wish for divine protection
in his often risky business.
Haiti's tap-tap painters are said to have been
inspired by the example of one car painted by
many artists in the 1940s. It was a jeep owned
by DeWitt Peters who had come to Port-au-
Prince to teach English, but stayed to become the
founding father of the contemporary art move¬
ment in the country. Peters' students painted and
repainted that historic jeep which then served as
a prototype for tap-tap painters who wanted to
expand their repertoire beyond the lettering of
routes, fares and owner's names.
Both the words "tap-tap" or "quickly" in
Creole and "chiva" or "little goat" in Spanish
suggest the speed with which these trucks travel
in search of passengers. Music from radios and
tapedecks heralds their passage through crowded
streets. Tap-tap drivers string Christmas tree
lights around the habitats' roofs while the engines
of Panamanian buses are draped with blinking
lights so the buses seem like enormous pinball
machines when they are driven after dark. Plastic
streamers fastened to rear view mirrors flutter in
the wind to accent the speed of buses and trucks.
With each of these vehicles there is a sense
that a rider is entering a driver's private domain.
Lured by the music, the fluttering ribbons and
the flashing lights, the rider climbs aboard to find
more paintings and words within. On the dash¬
board may be a small shrine where a protective
figure stands surrounded by flowers, charms and
medallions. Painted on the back windows are
swags of curtains with fringes and tassels, a per¬
fect touch to complete the decor of a travelling
home. While outside the slogans hint at the
driver's bold, macho persona, inside the dash¬
board shrine suggests his awareness of the daily
risks and gambles he takes as a driver. Driving
isn't an easy way to earn a living. Traffic is fast
and the competition for riders constant. Riders
won't choose a poorly painted vehicle and
perhaps may bypass one with the wrong religious
message or outmoded decor. So the paintings are
renewed and replaced, the slogans are reworded
and repainted. With new music and new lights
on their vehicles, drivers seek new business in the
constantly developing world of art on the road.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Veteran
roadsters
prized as
collectors'
items and
museum
pieces
Driving into
BY ALVARO CASAL TATLOCK
36
ALVARO CASAL TATLOCK,
Uruguayan journalist, is a
member of the Society of
Automotive Historians of the
USA and director of the
Uruguay Automobile Club
museum. He has published
many articles in specialist
journals and was co-author
of The Complete Encyclopedia
of Commercial Vehicles (USA)
and The Complete Encyclopedia
of Motorcars (Ebury Press. UK).
IT is hard to evoke the passion aroused by old
cars without talking about money. Some models
are now worth millions of dollars, and whenever
there is a vintage car sale record-breaking prices are
paid for such and such a make or model, or even
for such prized accessories as a Lauque radiator
cap. What was in the early 1980s the secret vice of
a handful of enthusiasts has become a field in
which rich speculators are ready to pay out sums
of the order of £5,500,000 for a Bugatti Royale.
To realize how things have changed, it is
enough to compare old car sale catalogues with
those compiled for major auctions today. The
catalogue for Sotheby's London sale of 4
December 1989 weighed more than one kilo and
provided connoisseurs with descriptions of the
sixty-nine vehicles to be sold that day, together
with some 650 accessories and fittings described
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
i
^^^^^ 1
N^hiV
* *
i ^u
fa
history
The Mille Mlglla ("Thousand Miles")
event In northern Italy, 1987.
This pencil drawing (c. 1950), by the
German artist Carlo Demand, shows
Marcel Renault cornering at speed during
the 1902 Paris-Vienna race.
as automobilia. One 1912 Rolls Royceand a not
particularly attractive one at thatmade £915,000
and eight other cars topped the £100,000 mark.
In 1950, no motorists in their right mind would
have entertained the idea of buying such mon¬
sters for which today's collectors are ready to
fork out immense sums.
What makes one vintage car more or less
expensive than another? The layman may think
that the main factor would be age or rarity, but
this is not so. Veterans of the heroic age of
motoring cost less than more recent models.
Unwieldy and not very roadworthy, they are of
more interest to museums than to private owners.
However, pre-1905 vehicles are valued because
they are eligible to take part in the celebrated
London to Brighton Run. The rarest models only
fetch high prices if they have other desirable
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Bugatti Royale Napoléon coupé of 1930, the personal car of Ettore Bugatti, Is preserved at the National Automobile Museum, Mulhouse, France.
A vintage crop
E.»ARLY in the morning a cream 1929 Ford
truck bearing red inscriptions stands outside a
shop in a Montevideo street. At the wheel a
milkman prepares to set off on his round.
In any other country this might be a scene
staged for an advertisement, but in Uruguay
such a sight is fairly common. The truck is one
of a fleet of veteran utility vehicles, some of
them fifty years old, which are still being used
by the same firm to which they have always
belonged.
Veteran cars of all kinds, some of them
dating from the 1920s, are also an everyday
38
sight on the roads of Uruguay. The owners of
1930 Grahams, 1947 Singers, 1950 Panhards
and 1960 Hansas, find it quite natural to go out
in these old-timers for a daily spin.
Never mind if the model is out of date and
spare parts are impossible to find. In Uruguay
all vehicles are systematically used, repaired,
cannibalized, and kept on the road, whatever
their make or their age.
There are so many old cars and so many
makes in Uruguay because when cars became
popular there were no specific import restric¬
tions on vehicles. For many years Uruguayans
had no trouble importing cars of all kinds. Then,
when heavy customs duties began to be levied
on imports during a period of economic crisis
in the 1950s, car owners took care to preserve
their cars for as long as they possibly could.
Since then the frontiers have been opened,
with certain restrictions concerning engine
capacity and type of coachwork, and a local
In Uruguay, vehicles of all makes
and ages are kept on the road.
industry has developed to assemble imported
cars and manufacture spare parts. But Uru¬
guay's fleet of cars had already been largely
constituted, and even today many Uruguayans
prefer to drive a museum piece which costs less
to buy, and less in road tax and insurance, than
to invest in a new car whose price can easily
represent two years' salary for someone who
earns a good living.
This is why the Montevideo milkman still
drives his old Ford gas-guzzler. Perhaps he
thinks that fuel is the least expensive item in
running a car!
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
features. The Bugatti Royale, for instance, is an
extremely rare model, but it is worth millions of
dollars because many people regard it as a master¬
piece of automobile design.
The automobile as objet d'art
The fact is that old cars are worth the price that
collectors are prepared to pay for them. What
other explanation can there be for the fact that
the market price of a 1957 Chevrolet convertible
is higher than that of earlier or later models of
the same make? Perhaps people who are prepared
to pay more than $30,000 for an old car in per¬
fect condition either could not afford such a car
in its heyday or did own one and are trying to
recapture their lost youth.
Financial speculation in old cars has given rise
to a thriving international trade. In South
American countries like Argentina, Uruguay and
Brazil, where many 1920s and 1930s models are
still in everyday use, agents in search of rare
specimens for rich foreign customers had a won¬
derful time in the 1970s. The authorities in these
countries eventuallyalbeit rather late in the day
concerned about what was happening
and, following the example set by India, which
imposed a complete ban many years ago, placed
restrictions on the export of cars of historical
interest.
Original models are worth so much today
that their owners are often reluctant to expose
them to the hazards of road traffic. Full-scale
reproductions of the most prestigious makes are
now available. In Uruguay, for example, it is pos¬
sible to obtain for about $20,000 a copy of a 1920s
Mercedes SSK complete with a modern Mercedes-
Benz engine. The price is not high given that an
original is worth at least ten times as much.
Perhaps international counterfeiters will be
tempted to move into the vintage car market, as
they have done with paintings, furniture and
objets d'art.
All this is bound to upset people who really
love old cars. However, some have responded to
the craze by founding vintage-car clubs and
organizing races, parades and rallies. Scarcely a
month goes by without at least one such event
being held somewhere in the world, and the
membership of the International Federation of
Vintage Automobiles is constantly increasing.
Automobile museums are proliferating. What
Only cars manufactured
before 1905 are eligible to
take part In the annual
London to Brighton Run.
The first self-propelled vehicle
was a tricycle-mounted
steam-driven carriage built by
the French engineer Nicolas
Joseph Cugnot In 1770.
krtjfeí&wjfr^ y if
*««»?
4* - 1
j^^^
^^^
wÊm
makes an old car a museum piece? Kenneth
Behring is one person who has answered this
question to his own satisfaction. In 1988, he con¬
ferred the title of Art Museum on the establish¬
ment bearing his name in Danville, California,
in which he keeps his collection of 150 cars. He
regards cars as the most beautiful form of sculp¬
ture he has ever seen. Giancarlo Amari, the
curator of the Carlo Biscaretti di Ruffia automo¬
bile museum in Turin, regards automobiles as
products of human genius and as the results of
an authentic creative endeavour which have also
been useful to society. The automobile could be
regarded as the supreme form of kinetic art.
Recent history
These are relatively recent notions. They were
certainly not current at the beginning of the cen¬
tury. The automobile only became a historical
phenomenon in the 1920s, when a group of
English gentlemen had the idea of holding a vin¬
tage car Run between London and Brighton to
commemorate the day in 1896 when the decision
to increase the speed limit for motor cars to 12
miles (20 kilometres) an hour at last made it pos¬
sible for horsepower to compete with the horse.
This annual Run, which is only open to cars built
before 1905, could be said to be the Ascot of the
horseless carriage. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
The Veteran Car Club of Great Britain,
whose members own cars more than twenty-five
years old, was founded in the United Kingdom
in 1930. The first automobile museums were not
created until the 1950s. When Lord Montagu of
Beaulieu decided to open his stately home to the
public in 1952 and put the five vintage cars in its
garage on display, he probably did not imagine
that he was laying the foundations for Britain's
National Motor Museum, which now houses
more than 200 old cars. Today there must be
more than 300 automobile museums all over the
world, as well as hundreds of other museums that
have cars in their collections, including the
Museum of Modern Art in New York, which has
a superb Cisitalia.
Clubs, books and magazines
The first nostalgic articles and specialized maga¬
zines about old cars also began to appear in the
1950s. Fanauto in France, The Automobile in the
United Kingdom and Motor Klassik in Germany
are just three of the host of periodicals devoted
to veteran vehicles which are published today in
many languages.
In addition, more and more books are being
published about old jalopies, their history and
technical specifications. Each year the American
publishing firm Motorbooks International issues
a catalogue of more than a hundred pages con¬
taining references to specialized books, makes,
prices, gadgets, addresses of repair shops, and
other information of interest to veteran car
The National Motor Museum,
United Kingdom, founded
by Lord Montagu of Beaulieu
In 1952.
enthusiasts. The latest catalogues also list selec¬
tions of video-cassettes for enthusiasts who want
to see their favourite models being put through
their paces or to watch old films advertising them.
All this may suggest that lovers of old cars
have never been happier than they are today.
Their passion is now acknowledged all over the
world. There are hundreds of clubs where owners
of the same makes or even the same models can
meet250 such clubs exist in the United
Kingdom aloneand there are skilful craftsmen
who can make spare parts for obsolete models.
The number of specialized publications is
increasing, as are the competitions, rallies and
other events where owners can display their
treasures, swop experiences and gather invaluable
information. Yet many vintage car owners feel
some misgivings as, for environmental and safety
reasons, the law is increasingly hard on the pol¬
luting engines and rough and ready braking
systems of their beloved vehicles, and regret that
prices rise to stratospheric levels as a result of
speculation.
The historian of the automobile is inclined
to wonder whether any of today's vehicles will
be capable of igniting as much passion in fifty
years' time as venerable Duesenbergs, Bugattis,
Bentleys, Mercedes and Rolls Royces do today.
Will people be prepared to pay millions of dollars
for a 1990 vehicle, spend hundreds of hours
repairing it and hand-crafting parts that were
originally mass-produced? Will any 1990 vehicles
still be in running order in half a century? Only
time will tell.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF
Brain imbalance and
addiction
Many biologists suspect that
some people are more prone to
addiction than others because of
inherited imbalances in their
brain chemistry. Attempts are
consequently being made to
locate genetic markers that
indicate this vulnerability so that
persons at risk can be identified
at an early stage. A step
forward has been reported by
scientists at the University of
Texas and the University of
California at Los Angeles who
have identified a gene that may
play a role in alcoholism and
possibly other forms of
addiction. Of a group of
alcoholics they studied, 77%
had the gene. Many social
scientists are critical of this
approach to addiction research.
They believe it is wrong to focus
only on biology and ignore the
social forces at play. Those at
highest risk, they point out,
come from impoverished urban
backgrounds.
The Ramayana tours
Europe
Performers from Thailand,
Malaysia, Bali, Java and India
toured France, Italy and Spain
this summer in a dramatization
of the great Indian epic poem
the Ramayana ("Life of Rama").
Thought to have been created
by Valmiki, a 3rd-century BC
Indian sage, the Ramayana is a
poem of 24,000 couplets.
Composed in Sanskrit, it was
then translated or freely
paraphrased into almost
every Indian language and
most of the languages of
southeast Asia, each version
adapting the story to local
cultures and traditions.
Aid from rich countries
drops
According to a report published
in June 1990 by the
Organization for Economic
Co-operation and Development
(OECD), official development
assistance from the leading
industrialized countries (in the
form of grants, soft loans and
technical aid) amounted to
$46.5 billion in 1989, a drop of
2% in real terms compared with
1988.
In absolute terms, Japan
was the leading donor with
$8.96 billion (a rise of 4% on
1988), followed by the United
States with $7.66 billion (a drop
of 27%). France stayed in third
place with $5.14 billion,
followed by the Federal Republic
of Germany ($4.95 billion).
The Nordic countries-
Denmark, Finland, Norway and
Swedendevoted the largest
share of their GNP to aid (on
average 0.92%), three times
more than the average for all
the OECD countries (0.33%).
Among the richest countries,
France was first with 0.54% of
GNP and the United States last
with 0.15%.
The ratio of official
development assistance to GNP
recommended by the United
Nations, once 1%, today stands
at 0.7%.
Protecting the ozone layer
At a United Nations conference
held in London in June 1990,
70 countries agreed to
important measures to protect
the Earth's ozone layer from
damage by chlorofluorocarbons
(CFCs), gases used in aerosol
sprays, refrigeration and air
conditioning. The agreement,
which went much further than
the Montreal Protocol signed by
56 nations in September 1987,
committed signatories to halt
production and consumption of
CFCs by the year 2000. After
long negotiations ¡n which
Mr. Mustafa K. Tolba, Executive
Director of the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP)
played a key role, it was agreed
to provide aid for developing
countries in phasing out CFCs.
CO molecules discovered
4 billion light years away
A team of French and American
astrophysicists have detected
molecules of carbon monoxide
in a quasar some 4 billion light
years away, twice as far as the
distance at which molecules had
hitherto been observed. First
detected in the early 1960s,
quasars are cosmic objects
whose brilliant luminosity
enables them to be observed at
vast distances. The new
discovery may call in question
current theories about their
origin, notably the hypothesis
according to which their central
energy source may originate in
gas spiralling into a gigantic
black hole.
Rebuilding Lisbon
In June 1990 Lisbon city council
approved a plan for the
restoration of the city's historic
district ravaged by fire in 1988.
The ambitious project, drawn up
by architect Alvaro Siza, goes
further than the restoration of
the twenty-odd buildings
destroyed by the fire. It involves
extensive modifications to the
urban fabric as part of an effort
to restore life to the old city
centre which was gradually
becoming derelict. The
Portuguese government and a
number of international bodies
are making important financial
contributions to the project,
which is scheduled for
completion in 1993.
Solar lighting
the sunflower way
Five years after his solar lighting
system was presented at the
international science exposition
at Tsukuba, Japan, where it lit a
giant tomato plant that
produced more than 10,000
tomatoes, Japanese engineer Kei
Mori has been posthumously
awarded an honorary doctor of
science degree for his invention
by Carnegie-Mellon University in
the United States. His Himawari
(Sunflower) system uses roof-
mounted glass lenses and fibre
optic cable to capture solar
energy. It has many applications
and can bring the properties of
sunlight into the sunless places
where many urban dwellers
spend much of their time.
Poverty in Latin America
A study published in July 1990
by the United Nations Economic
Commission for Latin America
and the Caribbean (ECLAC)
indicates that 44% of Latin
Americans (183 million persons)
live below the poverty line, 21%
(88 million) of them in extreme
poverty. The study points out
that the countries of the region
experienced a period of
economic growth in the 1970s,
but in the 1980s economic crisis
has worsened living conditions
for millions. Between 1980 and
1986, the number of poor
families increased in 6 of the 10
countries studiedArgentina,
Brazil, Costa Rica, Peru, Uruguay
and Venezuela, and only fell in
Colombia and Mexico. The study
points out that poverty is chiefly
an urban phenomenon. In 1970,
37% of the disadvantaged lived
in towns and cities; in 1989 the
figure had risen to 57%.
The secret of the sexes
British researchers from the
Imperial Cancer Research Fund
and the National Institute for
Medical Research. have identified
a gene which seems to play a
crucial role in determining the
sex of embryos. Located in a
tiny region of the Y
chromosome, the gene triggers
a series of transformations that
influence the sex glands to
become the male testis rather
than the female ovary.
The researchers think that
the gene is found in all mammal
species. The discovery, published
in the 19 July 1990 issue of the
review Nature, has been
described as a landmark in
scientific progress.
Citizens of Europe
Four years ago, the signatories
of Charter 77, the manifesto
published in January 1977 by a
group of Czech citizens calling
for respect for human rights in
their country, began to think of
a Europe united in diversity, a
Europe whose main actors
would be citizens, not state
institutions. At the opening
session of a European Citizens'
Assembly, which will be held in
Prague on 19, 20 and 21
October 1990, their ideas will
come to fruition. To mark the
occasion a pan-European cultural
event entitled "People to
People" is being organized in
the Czech capital. All fields of
artistic creation will be
represented and culture will be
shown as vigilant in the face of
hatred, intolerance, xenophobia
and racism.
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF IN BRIEF
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
A common
heritage
In response to many requests from readers,
in December the Unesco Courier will be
launching a new feature devoted to the
outstanding historical landmarks in art
and architecture and the exceptional
natural sites which constitute the common
heritage of humanity.
Reports will evoke the universal interest of
each site, describe any dangers that may
confront it, explain what steps are being
takenoften under Unesco auspicesto
counter these threats, and say what needs
to be done to preserve the site for future
generations.
To introduce the world heritage
feature, we publish on the following pages
a special section of articles on the notion
of a common heritage, on the World
Heritage Convention, and on
international campaigns which have been
organized to safeguard certain particularly
representative sites.
Victoria Falls, at the border between Zambia and Zimbabwe.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
I
/ '* .
V>-
.
#'
..# f
4S
_	_
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
The World Heritage Convention:
a new idea takes shape
44
I he "Convention concerning the
Protection of the World Cultural
and Natural Heritage" or World
Heritage Convention is a legal in¬
strument through which states
voluntarily commit themselves to
protect monuments and sites within
their territory that are recognized
to be of such outstanding value
that safeguarding them concerns
humanity as a whole. States parties
to the Convention also undertake
to respect the heritage of universal
value located on the territory of
other states and to make a financial
contribution towards safeguarding
this heritage in countries which
lack the means to do so.
One hundred and twelve
states are already parties to the
Convention.
1960, a decisive year
In the 1960s, there was a danger
that the monuments of Nubia
would be permanently submerged
beneath the waters of the Nile
following the construction of the
Aswan High Dam. The international
community became aware that the
disappearance of these monuments
would be an irreparable loss, not
only for Egypt and the Sudan, but
for humanity as a whole. It was dear
that the considerable resources re¬
quired to save the monuments
were beyond the means of the two
countries concerned. The idea of a
common heritageand of a com¬
mon responsibility to safeguard
ittook shape. On 8 March 1 960,
Mr. René Maheu, the Director-
General of Unesco, launched an
international appeal and some $30
million were eventually collected to
save the Nubian monuments.
Around this time more and
more voices were being raised in
defence of the environment and
for the protection of natural sites.
This movement, which has grown
constantly since then, has fostered
an awareness of the need to
respect the riches of nature which
are indissociable from the past and
future of humanity.
The World Heritage Conven¬
tion is a result of the meeting of
these two trends. By affirming that
the works of man and the works
of nature belong to a single
heritage, the Convention was a
profoundly original document
when ¡t was adopted by Unesco's
General Conference in 1972.
An inventory
of the world heritage
The idea was to identify the cultural
and natural properties within each
country whose protection would
be a matter of concern to the
international community as a
whole. The text of the Conven¬
tion describes these treasures as
properties of outstanding universal
value from the point of view of
art or history, science or natural
beauty.
States parties to the Conven¬
tion draw up an inventory of
properties which they consider to
fall within these categories and
then nominate them for inclusion
on the World Heritage List. The
World Heritage Committee, an in¬
tergovernmental committee com¬
prising representatives of twenty-
one states parties to the Conven¬
tion elected on a rota basis, studies
these nominations in the light of
detailed reports prepared by two
non-governmental organizations,
the International Council of Monu¬
ments and Sites (ICOMOS) and the
International Union for Conserva¬
tion of Nature and Natural
Resources (IUCN). The number of
dossiers studied each year is con¬
siderable, but only a handful of
properties are inscribed on the
World Heritage List.
The List currently comprises
322 properties located in 69 coun¬
tries. It is an attempt to create a
world inventory which will be as
comprehensive, representative and
coherent as possible.
The criteria for selection
The cultural monuments and sites
chosen should:
constitute a unique achievement
(the Fort and Shalamar Gardens,
Pakistan; the Château of Cham-
bord, France);
have exercised considerable in¬
fluence at a certain period (the
historic centre of Florence, Italy);
provide evidence of a civilization
which has disappeared (the Royal
Palaces of Abomey, Benin; Machu
Picchu, Peru);
illustrate a significant historical
period (Abu Mena, Egypt; the
historic centre of Salvador de Ba¬
hía, Brazil);
constitute an outstanding exam¬
ple of a traditional way of life (the
M'Zab Valley, Algeria; the village
of Holloko, Hungary);
be associated with ideas or be¬
liefs of universal significance (the
sacred city of Kandy, Sri Lanka; In¬
dependence Hall, United States).
Natural heritage properties
should:
illustrate a stage in the Earth's
evolution (the Galapagos Islands,
Ecuador);
represent ongoing geological
processes (the Hawaii Volcanoes,
United States; Los Glaciares,
Argentina);
constitute remarkable natural
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
formations or areas of exceptional
natural beauty (Kilimanjaro National
Park, United Republic of Tanzania;
Cape Girolata and Scandola Nature
Reserve in Corsica, France);
contain the natural habitats of
endangered species (Garamba Na¬
tional Park, Zaire; Wood Buffalo
National Park, Canada).
The properties inscribed on
the List very often meet several of
these criteria. Some of them are of
outstanding cultural and natural
value.
Threats
to the world heritage
Some of the problems facing the
world heritage are associated with
development and changing
lifestyles, demographic pressure on
natural resources, industrialization,
the modernization of urban
centres, or pollution. Others are the
result of neglect or lack of means.
Some sites are endangered by
mass tourism, the facilities created
to cater for tourism, and the cul
tural shocks that they may lead to.
In other cases, natural catastrophes
such as floods, earthquakes or cy¬
clones may cause serious damage.
The number and the gravity of
these problems are growing dra¬
matically and it is no exaggeration
to say that the entire world
heritage is to some extent at risk.
The role
of the Convention
The Convention only applies to
properties inscribed on the World
Heritage List, although the cultural
and natural heritage at large is
threatened. But the international
community primarily wishes to draw
attention to the most representa¬
tive properties and to organize
effective international co-operation
to ensure that they will be pro¬
tected and transmitted to future
generations.
Inscription on the World
Heritage List undeniably confers
new prestige on a property, but at
the same time it creates obligations
A common
responsibility
Through the work of the World Heritage Committee, Unesco has over the
last two decades been winning support for the new notion that the safeguard¬
ing of the world's heritage of monuments is a matter of concern to the human
community as a wholeeven if it is a responsibility that devolves primarily
on the country in which each monument is located.
Although there have been many obstacles and although a spirit of domi¬
nation has not yet entirely been replaced by a desire for co-operation, we
are slowly but surely feeling our way towards a philosophy of the cultural
heritage. This philosophy implies the end of a romantic view of history. Monu¬
ments can live again, but the past can never be revived. It also means, above
all, the rejection of political history. There is no question of commending one
civilization and discrediting another, of drawing up a kind of pecking order
of cultures. The aim is to make known the many forms of human creativity
that have left their mark on the centuries. Appreciation of the creative works
of the past should not be seen as an attempt to revive obsolete values. It
is, rather, an effort to find roots and define national identity and to confer
universal dignity on these works.
But through the World Heritage Convention Unesco is pursuing another
goal of great importance. When human beings express themselves by working
for the continuity of their culture, they must not in so doing harm the natural
world. They must safeguard their natural environment and consider it too
as an irreplaceable heritage.
By regarding the heritage as both cultural and natural, the Convention
reminds humanity of the fundamental need to preserve the balance between
man and the environment, and of the interaction between culture and nature.
As the time approaches for a preliminary assessment of the impact of
the Convention, which will be twenty years old in 1 992, one might point
already to the way in which the network of solidarity between all countries
has expanded and to the way in which information about the heritage of
each country has been transmitted all over the world.
It is gratifying to be able to say that today the catalogue of wonders
of the world no longer stands at seven. Thanks to the World Heritage Con¬
vention, the world is starting to realize that cultural monuments form a single
immense memorial to the centuries and that the preservation of natural sites
is becoming a categorical imperative for all humanity.
Azedine Beschaouch
Chairman of the World Heritage Committee
Restoration work In the convent of San
Francisco de Lima, Peru.
Right, the emblem of the World
Heritage Convention.
Opposite page, Mount Taishan, China.
for the state concerned, which
must ensure that the property is
protected and take responsibility
for it vis-à-vis the international com¬
munity. The World Heritage Com¬
mittee, with the support of the
media, may remind a state of its
obligations if these are not being
respected. Many positive results
have been achieved by this kind of
pressure, such as the cancellation
of projects to construct dams, pol¬
luting factories, or over-intrusive
tourist facilities.
The World Heritage Commit¬
tee also acts directly on behalf of
protected sites at the request of
states parties to the Convention.
Through the World Heritage Fund
(some $2.5 million a year), interna¬
tional co-operation can be or¬
ganized, specialists and equipment
can be provided, training and
educational activities can be under¬
taken, and funds can be raised for
major projects such as the restora¬
tion of monuments or the manage¬
ment of nature reserves. Such
projects may be carried out as part
of International Safeguarding Cam¬
paigns like that in which Unesco is
currently engaged for the old city
of Sana'a in the Republic of Yemen.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
FROM THE NUBIAN TEMPLES TO THE KATHMANDU VALLEY
International campaigns to safeguard
the cultural heritage of mankind
BY ABDELKADER BRAHIM ERRAHMANI
FcOLLOwiNG the rescue of the temples
of Abu Simbel in Upper Egypt, the
greatest archaeological salvage oper¬
ation of all time, and the reconstruc¬
tion of the great Buddhist sanctuary
of Borobudur in Indonesia, Unesco
is now campaigning for the safeguard
of twenty-four other groups of monu¬
ments and sites which form part of
the universal cultural heritage.
Some of these campaigns are
already far advanced. One of them
is that for the restoration of Venice,
which was subsiding into the waters
of its lagoon. Tourists can still admire
the celebrated Byzantine horses rear¬
ing on the outside gallery of St.
Mark's Basilica, but they are
reproductions of the originals, which
have been restored and are now
sheltered from the rigours of the
Venetian climate.
For over fifteen years, painstaking
work has been carried out at the site
of ancient Carthage, where ar¬
chaeologists from all over the world
have been helping their Tunisian col¬
leagues to unearth the ruins of the
ancient Roman city and Punic capi¬
tal, once thought to have been com¬
pletely destroyed.
In Pakistan, much progress has
been made in a long-term project to
protect the site of Moenjodaro, the
"City of the Dead" of the ancient
Indus civilization, from flooding and
corrosion by salts.
Off the coast of Senegal, restora¬
tion work has been going on for the
past ten years on the island of Gorée,
once a "centre of the slave trade. Today
the lustre of its colonial architecture
can once again be admired in streets
edged with bougainvillea.
Ouadane, Chinguetti, Tichit and
Oualata, four medieval cities on an
ancient caravan route through
Mauritania, are threatened by desert
encroachment. They are fighting to
survive as testimony to seven centu¬
ries of civilization.
In Haiti, efforts are being made to
preserve three monuments, La
Citadelle de la Ferrière, the Sans
Souci Palace, and the Ramiers site,
historic witnesses to a resolute desire
for independence.
In Sri Lanka three sacred places
Anuradhapura, Polonnaruva and
Kandyare being restored, together
with the ancient city of Sigiriya,
famed for its rock paintings.
The first royal capital of Thailand,
Sukhothai ("dawn of happiness"),
is gradually recovering its serenity.
International solidarity is supporting
efforts to restore over 800 endan¬
gered monuments and sites in
Nepal's Kathmandu Valley.
Other extensive safeguard opera¬
tions involving the preservation of
historic sites and districts and their in¬
tegration into the fabric of modern
urban life are being carried out at
Istanbul, Turkey; the Plaza Vieja in
Havana, Cuba; the holy city of Fez,
Morocco; the old cities of Sana'a (the
"pearl of Arabia") and Shibam, and
the Wadi Hadramaout valley in the
Republic of Yemen; the site of An¬
tigua in Guatemala, once a centre of
the Maya civilization; and San Fran¬
cisco de Lima, one of Peru's finest ar¬
chitectural ensembles of seventeenth-
century colonial architecture.
Hue, the ancient capital of Viet
Nam and witness to the country's cul¬
tural and artistic creativity, has
suffered from the ravages of both
time and warfare.
Other safeguarding campaigns
concern the rock-hewn churches of
the Göreme Valley in the heart of
Anatolia, Turkey, and Kotor in Yu¬
goslavia, which is the site of Mon¬
tenegro's most outstanding historical
monuments and was seriously
damaged by an earthquake in April
1979.
On the borders of Argentina, Brazil,
Paraguay and Uruguay, efforts are
being made to save the artistic
heritage of the Jesuit Missions of
the Guaranis which date from Span¬
ish and Portuguese colonial times.
The site of the Acropolis in Athens,
Greece, is threatened by industrial
pollution.
Malta, a crossroads of cultures, is
committed to saving its citadels,
towns, medinas, tombs and
catacombs from the ravages of time
and from damage caused by man.
The Buddhist temple of Paharpur
Vihara and the Mosque City of
Bagerhat in Bangladesh are also in
need of international assistance.
An appeal for international solidar¬
ity has been launched for the
safeguarding of four Ethiopian sites
and monuments: Tiya and its stelae,
the last vestiges of a mysterious and
little-known civilization of 6,000 years
ago; Aksum, the African Babylon;
Harare, the fortress of the Red Sea
sultans; and the rock-hewn churches
of Lalibela, traditionally thought to
date back to the reign of Menelik I,
legendary son of Solomon and the
Queen of Sheba.
Above, the Palais des Rohan In
the Grande lie district of
Strasbourg, France.
Above right, Kilimanjaro National
Park, United Republic of
Tanzania.
Right, Cape Girolata, Corsica
(France).
Below, the main cloister of the
convent of San Francisco de
Lima, Peru.
I fi £
*'*!Í
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
'*# %À<mmfiûad..*ÊàdÀ*
Finally, in Egypt there is a project
to construct two museums: a museum
of Egyptian civilization in Cairo, and
a museum in Aswan for the master¬
pieces of Nubian art.
How campaigns
are launched
An international campaign originates
in a resolution adopted by Unesco
member states during a General
Conference.
The Unesco Secretariat then carries
out technical studies for use in
drawing up a plan of action which
defines the safeguard, restoration
and presentation operations, and
their cost.
This plan of action is submitted for
approval to Unesco's Executive
Board, which then authorizes the
Director-General to launch an appeal
to international solidarity. Such ap¬
peals solicit technical and financial
support from member states, govern¬
mental and non-governmental or¬
ganizations, foundations, public and
private institutions, and from intellec¬
tuals, artists, writers and the general
public.
The Director-General's appeal is
accompanied by promotional activi¬
ties designed to inform the public
about the specific problems involved
in each campaign and encourage
people to contribute. All contribu¬
tions are voluntary. There is no pro
vision in Unesco's budget to finance
major infrastructure work. Local and
international experts form a joint
committee or working group respon¬
sible for the implementation of the
plan of action and the allocation of
funds received as a result of the
Director-General's appeal.
The twenty-four current campaigns
call for national and international
investment estimated at US$1.5
billion. This indicates the scale of the
challenge to international solidarity.
The challenge does not end there.
Safeguarding campaigns give rise to
a wide range of social and economic
problems involving the development
of sites and the redefinition of the ar¬
chitectural functions of buildings and
their place within the urban frame¬
work. Far more than aesthetic inter¬
vention is involved. Safeguarding
campaigns lead inevitably to the res¬
tructuring of human settlements,
since newly-restored ancient build¬
ings must be integrated into the
fabric of modern life, and allotted
new functions which preserve their
essential character while meeting the
needs of the communities of which
they form a vital part.
ABDELKADER BRAHIM ERRAHMANI
is in charge of promotional activities In
Unesco's Cultural Heritage Division. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The World Heritage List
322 properties as at 15 December 1989 (234 cultural sites, 75 natural sites and 13 mixed sites)
Algeria. Al Qal'a of Béni Hammad.
Tassili n'Ajjer. M'Zab Valley. Djemila.
Tipasa. Timgad.
Argentina. Los Glaciares. Iguazu
National Park.
Argentina and Brazil. Jesuit Missions
of the Guaranis: San Ignacio Mini, Santa
Ana, Nuestra Señora de Loreto and Santa
Maria la Mayor (Argentina); ruins of Sao
Miguel das Missôes (Brazil).
Australia. Kakadu National Park. Great
Barrier Reef. Willandra Lakes Region.
Tasmanian Wilderness. Lord Howe Island
group. Australian East Coast Temperate
and Sub-Tropical Rainforest Parks. Uluru
National Park. Wet Tropics of
Queensland.
Bangladesh. Historic mosque city of
Bagerhat. Ruins of the Buddhist Vihara,
Paharpur.
Benin. Royal Palaces of Abomey.
Bolivia. City of Potosí.
Brazil. Historic town of Ouro Preto.
Historic centre of the town of Olinda.
Historic centre of Salvador de Bahia.
Santuary of Bom Jesus do Congonhas.
Iguaçu National Park. Brasilia.
Bulgaria. Boyana Church. Madara Rider.
Thracian tomb of Kazanlak. Rock-hewn
churches of Ivanovo. Ancient city of
Nesebar. Rila Monastery. Srebarna Nature
Reserve. Pirin National Park. Thracian
tomb of Sveshtari.
Cameroon. Dja Faunal Reserve.
Canada. L'Anse aux Meadows National
Historic Park. Nahanni National Park.
Dinosaur Provincial Park. Anthony Island.
Head-Smashed-In Bison Jump Complex.
Wood Buffalo National Park. Canadian
Rocky Mountain Parks.* Quebec (historic
area). Gros Morne National Park.
Canada and United States of
America. Kluane National
Park/Wrangell-St. Elias National Park and
Preserve.
Central African Republic. Pare
National du Manovo-Gounda St. Floris.
China. Mount Taishan. The Great Wall.
Imperial Palace of the Ming and Qing
Dynasties. Mogao Caves. Mausoleum of the
First Qin Emperor. Peking Man site at
Zhoukoudian.
Colombia. Port, fortresses and group of
monuments, Cartagena.
Costa Rica. Talamanca Range-La Amistad
Reserves.
CÔte d'Ivoire. Tai National Park.
Comoé National Park.
Cuba. Old Havana and its fortifications.
Trinidad and the Valley de los Ingenios.
Cyprus. Paphos. Painted churches in the
Troodos Region.
Ecuador. Galapagos Islands. City of
Quito. Sangay National Park.
Egypt. Memphis and its Necropolis:
Pyramid fields from Giza to Dahshur.
Ancient Thebes with its Necropolis.
Nubian monuments from Abu Simbel to
Philae. Islamic Cairo. Abu Mena.
Ethiopia. Simen National Park. Rock-
hewn churches, Lalibela. Fasil Ghebbi,
Gondar Region. Lower valley of the
Awash. Tiya. Aksum. Lower valley of the
Omo.
France. Mont-Saint-Michel and its Bay.
Chartres Cathedral. Palace and Park of
Versailles. Vézelay, Church and Hill.
Decorated Grottoes of the Vézère Valley.
Palace and Park of Fontainebleau. Château
and Estate of Chambord. Amiens
Cathedral. Roman Theatre and Triumphal
Arch, Orange. Roman and Romanesque
monuments, Aries. Cistercian Abbey of
Fontenay. Royal Saltworks of Arc-et-
Senans. Place Stanislas, Place de la Carrière
and Place d'Alliance, Nancy. Church of
Saint-Savin sur Gartempe. Cape Girolata,
Cape Pono and Scandola Nature Reserve,
Corsica. Pont de Gard (Roman aqueduct).
StrasbourgGrande He.
Germany (Federal Republic of).
Aachen Cathedral. Speyer Cathedral.
Würzburg Residence with Court Gardens
and Residence Square. Pilgrimage Church
of Wies. Castles of Augustusburg and
Falkenlust, Brühl. St. Mary's Cathedral and
St. Michael's Church, Hildesheim. Roman
monuments, Cathedral and Liebfrauen
Church, Trier. Hanseatic city of Lübeck.
Ghana. Forts and castles, Volta, Greater
Accra, Central and Western Regions.
Ashante traditional buildings.
Greece. Temple of Apollo Epicurius at
Bassae. Archaeological site of Delphi. The
Acropolis, Athens. Mount Athos. Meteora.
Palaeochristian and Byzantine monuments
of Thessalonika. Archaeological site of
Epidaurus. Medieval city of Rhodes.
Archaeological site of Olympia. Mystras.
Guatemala. Tikal National Park.
Antigua Guatemala. Archaeological Park
and ruins of Quirigua.
Guinea and Côte d'Ivoire. Mount
Nimba Strict Nature Reserve.
Haiti. National History ParkCitadel,
Sans Souci, Ramiers.
Holy See. Vatican City.
Honduras. Maya site of Copan. Rio
Plátano Biosphere Reserve.
Hungary. Budapest, banks of the Danube
with district of Buda Castle. Holloko.
India. Ajanta Caves, Ellora Caves. Agra
Fort. Taj Mahal. Sun Temple, Konarak.
Group of monuments at Mahabalipuram.
Kaziranga National Park. Manas Wildlife
Sanctuary. Keoladeo National Park.
Churches and convents of Goa. Khajuraho
group of monuments. Group of
monuments at Hampi. Fatehpur Sikri.
Group of monuments at Pattadakal.
Elephanta Caves. Brihadisvara Temple,
Thanjavur. Sundarbans National Park. .
Nanda Devi National Park. Buddhist
monuments at Sanchi.
Iraq. Hatra.
Islamic Republic of Iran. Tchogha
Zanbil. Persepolis. Meidan Emam, Esfahan.
Italy. Rock drawings, Valcamonica.
Historic centre of Rome. Church and
Dominican Convent of Santa Maria delle
Grazie with The Last Supper by Leonardo
da Vinci. Historic centre of Florence.
Venice and its lagoon. Piazza del Duomo,
Pisa.
Jordan. Old city of Jerusalem and its
walls. Petra. Quseir Amra.
Lebanon. Anjar. Baalbek. Byblos. Tyr.
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya.
Archaeological site of Leptis Magna.
Archaeological site of Sabratha.
Archaeological site of Cyrene. Rock-art
sites of Tadrart Acacus. Old town of
Ghadamès.
Malawi. Lake Malawi National Park.
Mali. Old towns of Djenné. Timbuktu.
Cliff of Bandiagara (Land of the Dogons).
Malta. Hal Saflieni Hypogeum. City of
Valetta. Ggantija Temples.
Mauritania. Banc d'Arguin National
Park.
Mexico. Sian Ka'an. Pre-Hispanic city
and National Park of Palenque. Historic
centre of Mexico City and Xochimilco.
Pre-Hispanic city of Teotihuacán. Historic
centre of Oaxaca and archaeological site of
Monte Alban. Historic centre of Puebla.
Historic town of Guanajuato and adjacent
mines. Pre-Hispanic city of Chichen-Itza.
Morocco. Medina of Fez. Medina of
Marrakesh. Ksar of Aït-Ben-Haddou.
Nepal. Sagarmatha National Park.
Kathmandu Valley. Royal Chitwan
National Park.
New Zealand. Westland and Mount
Cook National Park. Fiordland National
Park.
Norway. Urnes Stave Church. Bryggen.
Roros. Rock drawings of Alta.
Oman. Bahía Fort. Archaeological sites of
Bat, Al-Khutm and Al-Ayn.
Pakistan. Archaeological ruins at
Moenjodaro. Taxila. Buddhist ruins of
Takht-i-Bahi and neighbouring city remains
at Sahr-i-Bahlol. Historical monuments of
Thatta. Fort and Shalamar Gardens,
Lahore.
Panama. Fortifications on the Caribbean
side of Portobelo-San Lorenzo. Darien
National Park.
Peru. City of Cuzco. Historic sanctuary
of Machu Picchu. Archaeological site of
Chavin. Huascaran National Park. Chan
Chan archaeological zone. Manu National
Park. Convent ensemble of San Francisco
de Lima.
Poland. Historic centre of Cracow.
Wieliczka Salt Mine. Auschwitz
Concentration Camp. Bialowieza National
Park. Historic centre of Warsaw.
Portugal. Central zone of the town of
Angra do Heroísmo, Azores. Monastery of
the Hieronymites and Tower of Belem,
Lisbon. Monastery of Batalha. Convent of
Christ, Tomar. Historic centre of Evora.
Monastery of Alcobaça.
Republic of Yemen. Old city of Sana'a.
Old walled city of Shibam.
Senegal. Island of Gorée. Niokolo-Koba
National Park. Djoudj National Bird
Sanctuary.
Seychelles. Aldabra Atoll. Vallée de Mai
Nature Reserve.
Spain. Mosque of Cordoba. Alhambra
and Generalife, Granada. Burgos Cathedral.
Monastery and site of the Escurial, Madrid.
Parque Güell, Palacio Güell and Casa Mila,
Barcelona. Altamira Cave. Old town of
Segovia and its aqueduct. Churches of the
Kingdom of the Asturias. Santiago de
Compostela (old town). Old town of Avila
with its extra-muros churches. Mudejar
architecture of Teruel. Historic city of
Toledo. Garajonay National Park. Old
town of Cáceres. Cathedral, Alcazar and
Archivo de Indias, Seville. Old city of
Salamanca.
Sri Lanka. Sacred city of Anuradhapura.
Ancient city of Polonnaruva. Ancient city
of Sigiriya. Sinhara Forest Reserve. Sacred
city of Kandy. Old town of Galle and its
fortifications.
Switzerland. Convent of St. Gall.
Benedictine Convent of St. John, Müstair.
Old city of Berne.
Syrian Arab Republic. Ancient city of
Damascus. Ancient city of Bosra. Site of
Palmyra. Ancient city of Aleppo.
Tunisia. Medina of Tunis. Site of
Carthage. Amphitheatre of El Djem.
Ichkeul National Park. Punic town of
Kerkuane and its Necropolis. Medina of
Sousse. Kairouan.
Turkey. Historic areas of Istanbul.
Göreme National Park and rock sites of
Cappadocia. Great Mosque and Hospital of
Divrigi. Hattusha. Nemrut Dag. Xanthos-
Letoon. Hierapolis-Pamukkale.
United Kingdom. Giant's Causeway and
causeway coast. Durham Castle and
Cathedral. Ironbridge Gorge. Studley Royal
Park including ruins of Fountains Abbey.
Stonehenge, Avebury and associated
megalithic sites. Castles and Town Walls of
King Edward in Gwynedd. St. Kilda.
Blenheim Palace. City of Bath. Hadrian's
Wall. Palace of Westminster, Westminster
Abbey and St. Margaret's Church.
Henderson Island. The Tower of London.
Canterbury Cathedral, St. Augustine's
Abbey and St. Martin's Church.
United Republic of Tanzania.
Ngorongoro Conservation Area. Ruins of
Kilwa Kisiwani and ruins of Songo Mnara.
Serengeti National Park. Selous Game
Reserve. Kilimanjaro National Park.
United States of America. Mesa
Verde. Yellowstone. Grand Canyon
National Park. Everglades National Park.
Independence Hall. Redwood National
Park. Mammoth Cave National Park.
Olympic National Park. Cahokia Mounds
State Historic Site. Great Smoky
Mountains National Park. La Fortaleza and
San Juan Historic Site, Puerto Rico. Statue
of Liberty. Yosemite National Park. Chaco
Culture National Historical Park.
Monticello and University of Virginia,
Charlottesville. Hawaii Volcanoes National
Park.
Yugoslavia. Old city of Dubrovnik.
Stari Ras and Sopocani. Historical complex
of Split with the Palace of Diocletian.
Plitvice Lakes National Park. Ohrid
Region with its cultural and historical
aspect and its natural environment. Natural
and cultural-historical region of Kotor.
Durmitor National Park. Studenica
Monastery. Skocjan Caves.
Zaire. Virunga National Park. Garamba
National Park. Kahuzi-Biega National
Park. Salonga National Park.
Zambia/Zimbabwe. Victoria
Falls/Mosi-oa-Tunya.
Zimbabwe. Mana Pools National Park,
Sapi and Chewore Safari Areas. Great
Zimbabwe National Monument. Khami
Ruins National Monument.
The following states, in addition
to those mentioned in the list
above, are also parties to the
Convention concerning the
Protection of the World Cultural
and Natural Heritage:
Afghanistan, Antigua and Barbuda,
Burkina, Burundi, Cape Verde, Chile, the
Congo, Denmark, the Dominican
Republic, Finland, Gabon, the Gambia,
Guyana, Jamaica, the Lao People's
Democratic Republic, Luxembourg,
Madagascar, Maldives, Monaco,
Mozambique, Nicaragua, Niger, Nigeria,
Paraguay, the Philippines, Qatar, Saint
Christopher and Nevis, Saudi Arabia, the
Sudan, Sweden, Thailand, Uganda
and Viet Nam.
*The Burgess Shale site, which was previously
inscribed on the World Heritage List, is pan of the
Canadian Rocky Mountain Parks.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
N N I
** fJi'!'?Tî'.'ïI *j'i*" ''ViTÜ'*'''"*
^^rwU-Mm.!^.. ii i ib i.
Ir,U.t ... -i~J- r,^fc
W.p j, li. i r *i,* - n .
Ihis year marks the 500th anniver¬
sary of the death of King Matthias I
of Hungary (1443-1490), often
known by his byname Corvinus which
was derived from the raven (Latin
corvus) that featured on his escutch¬
eon. A Renaissance ruler who was
renowned among his contemporaries
as a "friend of the Muses", Matthias
was elected king in 1458 and went
on to make his court a magnificent
centre of humanism to which artists
and scholars of European-wide repu¬
tation were attracted.
Linguist, scientist and patron of
the arts and learning, he founded at
his capital of Buda a great library, the
Corvina, which he built up with the
help of an army of agents who pur¬
chased books for him throughout
Europe, scribes who copied them,
translators who rendered them from
Greek and Italian into Latin, and ar¬
tists who illuminated them.
Other great collectors of that
timethe Medicis, the Sforzas, the
Neapolitan kings, the Prince of Urbi-
no, the kings of France, and King
Wenceslas of Bohemia and Germany
manuscripts of dazzling
beauty, but in terms of numbers
of books and wealth of contents
Matthias's collection was considered
second only to the Vatican Library.
One contemporary visitor to
Buda noted: "I inspected all the
books. But should I say books? Rather
they were treasures, all of them. It
seemed to me that I was not in a
library but, as they say, in the lap of
Jupiter. Legions of Greek and Hebrew
volumes could be seen. ..and there
were more old and new Latin books
than anywhere else on earth."
The culture of the book and the
library was a new phenomenon in the
intellectual life of fifteenth-century
Europe. The book became the
supreme treasure of the intellect, the
A great Renaissance
library
| A P\ RCÍ DiONE PBANO TR AIAVTF. Ï JRfCOArftJ
"
F VM MC MO MtA*< '<.'
imoaotfiv^tiuniini m«Ti
Ím.i>««i\it-^1 ri" \'tnrvmpi>r»i|i!i[i! Nulli» it ffl^nofrif
t'rt-JïitttmiuttitjKrT ieA Afïwnii' |
noOH <-.> rt»«f in"i iirijwiui» í>*»nimftn*m »¿fifi
n \im î» S fccaram nJWunun milln> <hmiu umurmi
. .1 t1«Jt lit
-tHTIlt-l» «*'
mi
I tri.util mit Iwn
¡«i- nmnJjMwl \»m rwfi »i Men
fcrJi^ci si.ti jrrrhantu rmnwnnM *inii«i.'"*w«i*tç
t.\mit1ui . i .,v -mt,1 rtiOvwfl Jrmn .ti>tf£>iMiiivt
Inn tr»tof4 ti\ ffA A'irú f«Ttth- il fad wmwuw i*
\ft n m.im tut ,iu n',»f i>a«.iii i« nanti . foirt p
[ ft pn*pHMfc<W T*iiiií"<írmA'«iV A pnum»^rr«fnm fi
inmií t*rtmri<t(JítiAtm/m«t^>t ii-Tiir
< i ttmlimirKUitri ijiiftí ¡v4tUlr «tritt, &>i rft iptin»*»
um romMWMin <«"»« ifirm-tiii tjtijr ctuíha tur
ntii* ttrrimm A'rwpWt « fraaimdrihlf.
IMIHIMIur (i .i*ft'ï^r:<*tntnMJ«liit«*liiri'tYiiwti
tr» Unufmjrtftii'i finit anmrnm bmimhnwcil «««m
iSm Jium*\n*
Manuscripts from the Corvina library:
Above left, page from a commentary on Cicero's works on rhetoric by Calus
Marlus Vlctorlnus. Prior to 1462.
Above, The Fount of Knowledge of St. John of Damascus. Florence, 1485-1490.
Above right, page from a Gradual (book of plalnsong for Mass), 1480-1490,
decorated with the arms of King Matthias and Queen Beatrice of Hungary.
vehicle and preserver of the literary
and scientific heritage of classical An¬
tiquity. As efforts were made to copy
as much of this heritage as possible,
and collect everything relating to it
that had survived, libraries became
the workplace of scholars and centres
of intellectual activities and debate.
Although printed books, or in¬
cunabula, were starting to circulate
through Europe by the second half
of Matthias's reign, they were far out¬
numbered in his library by hand¬
written books or codices. Such
manuscripts were the result of pains¬
taking work by scribes who had not
only to be proficient in Latin, the lan¬
guage of medieval literature and
science, but also had to decipher a
host of abbreviations which authors
used to save time and space. Their
work was physically as well as men¬
tally exhausting. "Three fingers write
and the whole body toils," they often
wrote when they came to the end of
a volume.
Styles of script changed from
time to time in accordance with the
dictates of fashion. In the Corvina
manuscripts four basic styles are
represented: Gothic textura, Gothico-
antiqua, Humanist rotund and
Humanist cursive. The script is
meticulously executed on high quality
vellum. The manuscripts' most beau¬
tiful feature, however, is their hand-
painted ornamentation and illumina¬
tion. The codices made or acquired
for the Corvina in the 1460s and
1470s were decorated in the relatively
glctuu poftu Ih foyer inc. '
simple style of the age, bordered with
scrolls of white foliage on a coloured
background. Later, in its heyday, the
library acquired quintessential Renais¬
sance masterpieces adorned with roy¬
al emblems and, in some cases, with
portraits of Matthias and his queen.
But superb though the Corvina
manuscripts may have been as ob¬
jects, it was the wealth of the library's
holdings that won it the acclaim of
contemporaries and of posterity. We
have no direct evidence of the size of
the collection at the time of Matthias's
death, but it is thought to have con¬
tained between 2,000 and 5,000
volumes. Works by classical Greek
authors in Greek and in Latin trans¬
lation were strongly represented.
Extrapolating from the surviving
manuscripts, of which 216 are
known to exist scattered around the
world in libraries and private collec¬
tions, it may be assumed that about
two thirds of the collection was secu¬
lar in content with the remaining
third being devoted to theology.
The Corvina treasures were not
merely for show. The codices were
consulted by the king, who also guid¬
ed acquisitions and attended sympo¬
sia of leading scholars that were held
at the library. Every field of science
and literature was represented:
poetry and drama, philosophy and
theology, astronomy and medicine,
geography, rhetoric, grammar, ar¬
chitecture, military science and
mathematics. In addition to works in
Latin, Greek and Hebrew, the first ef¬
forts of the budding Hungarian liter¬
ature also found their way to the
Corvina.
By the close of Matthias's reign,
the Corvina was at the height of its
fame. On his death it slowly began
to decline, and in 1526 when Buda
was overrun by the Ottomans the
great library was destroyed. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
50
No comment
In your May issue on the birth of the
universe you did not follow your
usual practice of publishing captions
to the cover photographs. I hoped to
find some information about these
photos in the June issue, but in vain.
Marcelle Achard
Versailles (France)
We thought that the photographs were
self-explanatory, and simply gave the
names of the photographers and the
agencies holding the copyrights, as we
always do, in the "Acknowledgements"
column on page 50. Editor
Full page spread
Your May 1 990 issue is magnificent,
but what a pity that the impact of
some of the illustrations is spoiled be¬
cause they are reproduced across the
fold over two pages or are overprint¬
ed with captions or title (like the
cover). You may not be trying to com¬
pete with art magazines, but please
remember your mission to make cul¬
ture available to all, regardless of their
financial resources. What a pity too
that the marvellous photographs you
reproduce cannot be detached from
the magazine for display.
M. Cherre
Seiches-sur-le-Loir (France)
S.O.S. Amazonia
All over the world there is growing
anxiety about ecological problems,
and it is not surprising that the inter¬
national community should turn its
attention towards Amazonia, where
North American satellites have re¬
cently detected increasing signs of
burning and deforestation. The con¬
sequences may be catastrophic. They
include global warming as a result of
the buildup of carbon dioxide in the
atmosphere, with the risk of melting
polar ice raising the sea level and
leading to the submersion of coastal
towns and low-lying regions.
To forestall such a catastrophe,
urgent steps must be taken on three
fronts:
1. The United Nations should
urge its member states to channel
some of the money they spend on
arms to the conservation of the
Amazonian forest through an
"Amazonian tax" which would be
paid to the countries of continental
Amazonia.
2. These resources and part of
the external debt of the countries of
the Amazon basintransferred by
the creditor countriesshould be
used for the creation of a World Na¬
ture Conservation Park in Amazonia.
3. Under the auspices of the
United Nations, a joint plan should be
adopted by the countries of the
Amazon basin Bolivia, Brazil,
Colombia, Peru, Venezuela and the
Guianasfor the protection and
management of those parts of the
world park which fall within their
respective national jurisdictions.
This would be a major step
towards world peace and towards
awareness of the need for all peoples
to find a solution to problems which
affect the whole of humanity.
Maria Marcina
Pimentel Coimbra Bueno
Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)
"A past that won't
go away"
In your April 1 990 issue {In pursuit of
the past making of history), you
published an interview with Hinnerk
Bruhns entitled "A past that won't go
away", in which Dr. Bruhns maintains
that the German Democratic Republic
did not seek out war criminals and
bring them to trial. The person who
carried out the interview did not think
it fit to draw attention to this glar¬
ing error, which makes the historian
in question look extremely ill-
informed.
Pierre Huguenin
Helsinki (Finland)
Taken out of its context, the part of the
sentence quoted may indeed lead to mis¬
understanding. In the immediate post-war
years, "denazification", purging of the ap¬
paratus of state (especially in the case of
teachers and judges, but seemingly to a
lesser degree in the case of the military)
was carried out more systematically in the
Soviet occupation zone than in the
Western zones, and Soviet military
tribunals often handed out extremely
heavy sentences. This phase came to an
end in 1948-1949. After the creation of
the German Democratic Republic (GDR) in
the autumn of 1949, there was another
series of trials of war criminals, the last of
which was held in 1 988. But this was not
the subject of the interview. The official
ideology of the GDR regarded fascism as
a form and consequence of capitalism.
The shadows of the national-socialist past
were thus projected onto the Federal
Republic of Germany and the GDR refused
to accept any moral responsibility for
crimes committed by Germany during the
war. This responsibility (with its financial
implications) was only recognized after the
fall of the regime by the new government
of the GDR. Lumping together national
socialism on the one hand, with fascism
and capitalism on the other, obscured the
problem of the racist policy. It was not
until the 1 970s that the persecution of the
Jews was treated by the historians of the
GDRbut there had not been any really
serious public debate about this issue. In
this context, efforts to remember what
happened still remain to be made in the
GDR.
Hinnerk Bruhns
Paris
Languages of the world
In the interview with Camilo José Cela
published in your May 1990 issue, the
Spanish Nobel laureate commented
that "in a few years' time there will
be only four languages left in the
world... English, Spanish, Arabic and
Chinese."
What a pity that a Nobel
Prizewinner should have such a
blinkered vision of the global commu¬
nity and should show so little con¬
sideration for the diversity of human
nature.
We are entering an era of
democracy and coexistence. Empires
will no longer rule the world. Let all
people preserve their own roots, but
also understand the faith and culture
of others.
As I see it, this noble ideal is also
that of Unesco, for which as a con¬
sequence I have infinite respect.
Paramendra Kumar Bhagal
Kathmandu (Nepal)
Hands that read...
and write
On page 10 of your July 1990 issue
(One billion illiterates, a challenge for
our time), you published a photo
showing the hands of a blind person
on a tablet of Braille.
I should like to point out that the
hands shown are not reading but
writing. This being the case, the blind
person should be holding the tablet
lengthways in front of him or her, not
sideways. Furthermore, a blind per¬
son would never put both hands at
the same place on the tablet, as
shown. The right hand writes from
right to left, and the left hand holds
the perforated bar with which the
characters are printed, but not at the
place where the right hand punches
the letters. Finally, Braille is written
from right to left and the paper is
then turned over to its embossed side
and read from left to right.
Yvonne Tavel
Lausanne (Switzerland)
Acknowledgements
Cover, page 3 (left): © Jean-Loup
Princelle, Paris. Back cover: Burt
Glinn © Magnum, Paris. Page 2:
© Denise Fernandez Grundman,
Aix en Provence. Page 3 (right): S.
Bassouls © Sygma, Paris. Pages 4,
6, 7: © Musée de l'Homme, Paris.
Page 5: Vauthey © Sygma, Paris.
Page 8: Doisneau, © Rapho, Paris.
Page 9: © Sygma, Paris. Page 10
(above): T. Graham © Sygma,
Paris. Pages 10 (below), 12
(above), 13, 14 (below): ©Loup,
Paris. Pages 11, 26, 27 (above):
Dingo © Vandystadt, Paris. Page
12 (below): F. Le Diascorn
© Rapho, Paris. Pages 14-15: T.
Campion © Sygma, Paris. Page 15
(below): Valéry Assenât © Publicis-
Conseil-Renault 25 Baccara. Page
16: F. Le Guen © Sygma, Paris.
Pages 16-17: Georg Gerster
© Rapho, Paris. Pages 18-19:
© Cinémagence, Paris. Pages 18
(below), 24 (above): John G. Ross
© Rapho, Paris. Page 20 (above):
© Kipa, Paris; (below): © V.A.G.
France/Volkswagen-Audi. Page 21:
John Launois © Rapho, Paris. Page
22 (above), 27 (below), 36 (left),
38 (above): © Musée National de
l'Automobile, Mulhouse, France.
Pages 22-23 (below): © Keystone,
Paris; (above): © Relations
Publiques Citroè'n-XM. Page 24
(below): Erich Hartmann
© Magnum, Paris. Page 25:
© Robert Braunschweig, Berne.
Page 28: Bill Nation Picture
Group © Rapho, Paris. Page 29:
Yann Arthus Bertrand
© Vandystadt, Paris. Page 30:
© Daimler Benz, Stuttgart/Galerie
Hans Mayer, Düsseldorf. Page 31
(above): J. Prayer © Sygma, Paris.
Pages 31 (below), 32, 33, 34, 35:
© Moira F. Harris, Minnesota.
Pages 36-37: Bernard Asset
© Vandystadt, Paris. Page 37
(below): © Galerie Vitesse, Paris.
Page 38 (below left): © Alvaro
Casal Tatlock, Uruguay; (below
right): Serraillier © Rapho, Paris.
Page 39 (above): Dave Cannon
© Vandystadt, Paris; (below):
© Musée National des
Techniques/Conservatoire National
des Arts et Métiers, Paris. Page 40:
© National Motor Museum,
Beaulieu, UK. Pages 42-43: ©José
Serra, Lima. Page 44:
Unesco/National Commission for
China. Page 45, 46 (below):
Unesco/S. Mutai. Pages 46-47
(above): Unesco/Monuments
Historiques Alsace, J.P. Beck. Page
47 (below): Unesco/F. Charafi;
(right): Unesco/M. Bâtisse. Page
49: © MTI, Budapest/Országos
Széchényi Konyvtár Collection,
Budapest.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco
^courier
Published monthly in 34 languages and in braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoud.
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Carole Pajot
(Tel.: 45.68 46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Belin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Mane-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Bozidar Perkovtc (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San 5ebastian)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangfa: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45 88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45 68 45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45 65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Satah El Dm,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45 68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45 68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68,45.65
1 year: 126 French francs. 2 years: 234 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 68 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 99 French francs. 2 years: 180 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco
individual ameles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations The Unesco Courier is
produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 7S7O0 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48100, U S A.; (3) NCR. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc . Ill West 40th Street, New York, U.S A.; (4) Bell and
Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL CI OCTOBRE 1990
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocomposition The Unesco Courier
Photogravure-impression Maury Imprimeur S A , Z I route d'Etampes,
45330 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 10- 1990 -OPI- 90- 3 -485 A
three good reasons for
offering your fnenas a
gift subscription to the
Unesco Courier
mm
gn&n
imm
¡«Pi
mm
su
m
m
mi
V&A*
It is the only international cultural magazine
published in 35 languages
and read by hundreds of thousands of people
in 120 countries
Each month it explores
the astonishing diversity of
world culture and knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's
mission offurthering "universal respect for
justice, for the rule of law and for human rights
and fundamental freedoms...without distinction
of race, sex, language or religion..!'
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page advertising insert
between pages 10-11 and 42-43
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
"
]]>
</page>
</document>
