<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="087746eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1991
k
I
i
^
I
I/
__;
-
V ^vl
J
\\>/ m
M1205 9102 18.00 F
IM
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
_l
encounters
WOMAN IN
AN INTERIOR
1982, pastel (81 x 57 cm)
by Irakli Parjiani
This work by a Georgian
artist born in 1950
contains echoes of
interiors by the great
seventeenth-century
Dutch master Vermeer.
In it, writes Ketevan
Kintsurashvili, an art
historian with the
Georgian Art History
Institute (Tbilisi), the
artist uses a style that
is resolutely modern to
express nostalgia for
classical art.
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1991 N NTS
4
Interview with
FRANÇOIS JACOB
The Unesco
^courier
44th YEAR
Published monthly in 35 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if it is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of Unesco,
London, 16 November 1945
43
IN BRIEF..
44
REFLECTIONS
Imaginary cities
by Cristina Grau
LISTENING
Recent records
by Isabelle Leymarie and
Claude dayman
48
10 WORLD HERITAGE
The rock-hewn churches
of Cappadocia
by Antony Brock
SOMEWHERE, NOWHERE...
The quest for utopia
ATTEMPTING THE IMPOSSIBLE
by Federico Mayor 11
j\j
LETTERS
TO THE EDITORA CONTROVERSIAL IDEA
DO WE NEED UTOPIA?
by Fernando Ainsa
THE FIASCO OF PARADISE
by Gilles Lapouge
A PLATONIC PARABLE
by Alain Frontier
13
16
20
DREAMS AND REALITIES
AKHET-ATON, CITY OF THE SUN
by Ayyam Wassef
A GOLDEN AGE
by Ananda W.P. Gurugé
THE AMERICAN LABORATORY
by Ronald Creagh
PARADISE IN 4338?
by Vsevolod Revich
BLUEPRINTS FOR AN IDEAL COMMUNITY
by Colin Ward
23
25
26
30
34
A UTOPIA FOR OUR TIMES?
NON-STOP LEARNING
by Gilbert Leckre 39
Cover: Score for an
Undefeated Barbarian (1989),
watercolour by Joël Cazaux.
Back cover: Detail from
Rapports au seuil, mixed
media composition by the
contemporary Venezuelan
artist Pancho Quilici.
DOCUMENT
A PLANETARY UTOPIA
by Julian Huxley 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
N
François Jacob
In one of your books, The Logic of Life (1970), you
show that the history ofscience and the history ofmankind
coincide, and that the results ofbiological research influence
our changing image of the world. How do things stand
today when mastery of the mechanisms of life, and espe¬
cially of the keys ofhuman heredity, is causing both hope
and anxiety?
In that book I was trying to understand the evolution
of our ideas about life, about the way in which living beings
are produced. Our understanding of the processes of life has
grown constantly. Until the sixteenth century each birth
was seen as a creation. Each new being was shaped by divine
intervention. At the origin of each life was an act by the
Creator. It was not until the late seventeenth and the early
eighteenth century that the idea of reproduction replaced
that of creation.
Until the eighteenth century, the study of living beings
was limited to their external appearance. Investigation went
no further than the visible structure. Natural history classi¬
fied and compared forms in this way and defined genera or
species. Around the end of that century, there came a rad¬
ical change in the way of analysing living beings, as the use
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
of the term "biology" suggests. It was discovered that there
was an "organization" within the bodies of man and animals.
Then, in the middle of the nineteenth century, it was realized
that the body consists of elementary units called cells. At
the end of the century investigation went even deeper and
chromosomes were discovered. Then, at the beginning of
this century, came the discovery of the genes, which, in the
nucleus of the cell, govern characteristics. Finally, in the
middle of this century, molecular biology penetrated even
more deeply into the secrets of life when it discovered the
chemical and molecular structure of the gene: DNA or
deoxyribonucleic acid.
Molecular biology seeks to explain the astonishing
properties of living creatures in terms of the structure and
the interactions of the molecules which comprise the var¬
ious cells of the organism. In particular, this new biology
has tried successfully to solve the age-old mystery of heredity.
What is the status of the notion of teleology, which has
haunted all modern thinking on reproduction? You wrote
in The Logic of Life that "For a long time, the biologist
treated teleology as he would a woman he could not do
without, but did not care to be seen with in public. The
concept of programme has made an honest woman of
teleology".
The problem is couched in these terms: as a general rule
nature does not follow a plan. But in the case of living beings,
there clearly are phenomena which take place according to
We are programmed,
but programmed
to learn..,
Opposite page, the Escherichia coli bacterium, which was used
by Professor Jacob in his research on cellular genetics.
Below, model of the molecular structure of DNA
(deoxyribonucleic acid).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
a plan in order to attain a goal. Reproduction is one example.
Its result is known in advance. We know that only a duck
can result from the coupling of two ducks. For a long period
people wanted to explain this finality in terms of a "life
force" which was not governed by the laws of physics and
chemistry. Molecular biology has shown that the chromo¬
somes of the fertilized egg, half received from the father and
half from the mother, contain in coded form all the instruc¬
tions required for the making of a new organism. They con¬
tain what has been called a genetic programme. This is how
we can explain the apparent finality which manifests itself
in the development of an embryo.
Does the genetic programme also have a bearing on
psychological characteristics? What is current thinking on
the old controversy about nature and culture, innate and
acquired characteristics?
I think it is absurd to postulate a complete antithesis
between the innate and the acquired. Modern biologists see
hereditary structures and learning as mingled and continu¬
ally interacting. If you blindfold a cat at birth and prevent
it from seeing, when the blindfold is removed two weeks
later the cat has become blind. But if you put the blindfold
on when the cat is two or three months old, the cat can
see normally when you remove it.
An individual is thus the result of a programme inscribed
in the genes received from its two parents. However, it is
different from them. Why? Evolution has found a clever
way of ensuring that all organisms of the same species are
different from each other. Each time the blend is different,
with half of the programme coming from the mother and
half from the father. Thus the genetic equipment of each
being contains the indelible traces of its individuality, of its
differences from all its past, present and future congeners,
except for identical twins.
These differences permit evolution to encourage some
rather than others. Each programme is not entirely rigid.
It defines structures which are potentialities, probabilities,
tendencies. Genes only determine the constitution of the
individual.
We are all different, and the way in which living beings
reproduce is arranged so that we shall be so. This is why
the day came when man needed to formulate the concept
of equality. If we were all identical, like a population of bac¬
teria, the idea of equality would be quite unnecessary.
Stages in the development of a mouse.
From left to right:
the fertilized egg divides;
the two cells divide into four;
the fully-formed embryo.
The whole system probably functions in this way.
Learning stabilizes certain circuits and the others degenerate.
It chooses from among pre-existing possibilities. The making
of an individual, physically, intellectually, morally and men¬
tally, corresponds to a permanent interaction between the
innate and the acquired.
Would it be correct to say that in every child who is
deprived ofopportunities forfulfilment, we kill a Mozart?
Let's not exaggerate. Each individual harbours possibili¬
ties of excelling in a certain field. It may be music, or high
jumping, or carpentry. We just have to find out which one.
That's the most difficult thing. I think that education does
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
not try hard enough to exploit the potential of each child.
But that doesn't mean that in each child the genius of a
Mozart is only waiting for an opportunity to express itself...
You have also written that "Each being contains in
its chromosomes all its own future, the stages ofits develop¬
ment". So what margin offreedom do we have?
considerable margin. We exploit to a greater or lesser
degree the possibilities inscribed in our chromosomes. And
each culture orientates these possibilities in its own way.
You learn to speak Bantu or Eskimo, depending on whether
you are born among the Bantu or the Eskimos. That is one
system of selection. The genetic programme fixes in the
individual a framework into which the culture introduces
a certain hierarchy of values, certain forms of incentive or
motivation. We are programmed, but programmed to learn...
To imagine?
Yes. We are rather special animals who never stop learning
and searching. Horses gallop, birds fly, fleas jump. In our
case, we function with our imagination. In this context I
should like to discuss a widely-held idea about the supposed
difference between scientific and artistic activities. It is often
said that the imagination, the creative capacity attributed
to the artist, whether he is making a picture, a symphony
or a novel, is absent from scientific work. The scientist is
supposed to lift the veil which hides a pre-established truth.
It's not as simple as that. In scientific work as in the work
of the artist, the element of imagination is, at least at the
outset, very similar. If you look at the process from the
beginning, the elucidation of the structure of the atom or
of DNA is as much a creation as a discovery.
There is room for astonishment, for the unexpected.
The whole system is so arranged that we don't know what
will happen tomorrow. And yet we can only live in rela¬
tion to the future. This accounts for the astonishing interest
in astrology! We spend our time looking ahead, trying to
make sense of things. Man finds it hard to accept that
the world is what it is and not otherwise. Why do bodies
fall, not rise? Why do we age? Why are there leaves on the
trees? That's the way it is! We want everything to have a
meaning.
Take the case of evolution: we find it hard to accept
that it is purely a matter of tinkering. However different
they may appear, organisms all consist of the same elements,
which are simply redistributed and rearranged differently
in different organisms. What distinguishes a lion from a but¬
terfly, a fly from a hen or a worm from a whale, is simply
the different organization, the different arrangement of the
same materials, the same cells, the same molecules. It's
amazing but that's the way it is.
What's more, there are lots of cases where this process
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
has been unsuccessful in nature, in the human body. Do you
know how many spontaneous miscarriages take place in
nature? Fifty per cent. The mechanism that governs the
entire system of life has a 50 per cent failure rate. And yet
the system works. Amazing isn't it?
Shall we not want to influence this molecidar tinkering
ourselves, ifit is technically possible? There is a frightening
possibility of genetic manipulation...
The great success of molecular biology has been to under¬
stand the functioning of the genetic mechanisms of heredity.
After finding out how genes function and reproduce them¬
selves, we have acquired the capacity to affect the genes
themselves through genetic engineering. It is, for example,
possible to isolate a gene, splice it to others, and even
insert it into another organism. Genetic engineering is
simply the imitation of nature's tinkering in laboratory
conditions.
This power, it is true, is causing anxiety. Modern biology
appears so formidable because it is concerned with what is at
the very heart, not only of every living system, but of every
social system, at the heart of the intellectual and emotional
structuring of every living being: reproduction and heredity,
fields which long remained sacrosanct.
Here we must make a distinction of crucial importance.
On the one hand between the input of new knowledge-
research which is by definition unpredictable, and whose
unpredictability and alarming aspects must be accepted
and on the other its potential applications. The day man
was able to use iron, he could make a knife and use it just
as easily to peel an apple as to murder one of his fellows.
The application of scientific knowledge must be under¬
taken by decision of society as a whole. A society must be
able to decide whether to encourage or to prevent a given
application of a scientific discovery.
But society should not restrict, still less prevent, the quest
for knowledge in the life sciences. This quest must be car¬
ried out in total freedom, since it makes a great contribu¬
tion to our knowledge of ourselves and to the struggle to
improve the human condition. At the same time, the appli¬
cations of this knowledge must kept under constant surveil¬
lance. We must be vigilant.
Genetic engineering has become the indispensable tool
for all research on living beings. It is necessary for studying
Diagrams showing how a virus reproduces.
From left to right: injection into a cell of genetic
material from the virus; reproduction of the virus
within the cell; appearance of the complete virus
within the cell; destruction (lyse) of the cell and
release of the virus.
The French biologist François Jacob who (with André Lwoff and Jacques Monod) was awarded the Nobel Prize
for Physiology or Medicine in 1965, is one of the great figures of contemporary science. He originally intended
to become a surgeon, and was a medical student when he joined the Free French Forces in 1940. After the war
he finished his medical studies but, unable to practise surgery because of wounds contracted during the Normandy
landings in 1944, he turned to biology. In 1950 he joined the Pasteur Institute (Paris) as a research assistant and
ten years later became head of the department of cellular genetics. He has also been president of the Institute's
board of governors. In 1964 he was appointed professor of cellular genetics at the Collège de France. His work
has been principally concerned with the genetic mechanisms of bacteria and bacterial viruses, the transmission
of genetic information and regulatory activities in bacteria. His publications translated into English include The
Logic ofLife and The Possible and the Actual (new edition, Penguin, London, 1989) and his autobiography, The
State Within (Unwin Hyman, London, 1988).
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
the development of the embryo, hereditary diseases, the
brain, and even evolution. It provides medicine with
weapons of matchless power of diagnosis, prevention and
treatment.
Genetic engineering, for example, makes it possible to
understand the mechanisms at the origin of cancers. Human
body cells form a society and obey precise regulations. In
the case of cancer, some cells start to multiply anarchically
because they have become deaf to the signals governing their
multiplication. But it is only in the last few years, as a result
of genetic engineering, that we have learned how to locate,
in different types of cancer, the mutant genes which allow
the cell not to heed these signals. For the first time, we thus
have the possibility of access to the very mechanism of the
illness. Only genetic engineering will enable us to analyse
the AIDS virus and thus to stop it.
a personwho would then transmit them to his or her off¬
spring. To touch the reproductive cells is to touch the human
genome, the genetic heritage of humanity. Biologists and
doctors are unanimous that this should be absolutely
forbidden.
What exactly is the genome?
It is the set of genes that constitutes the genetic material
of a given individual or species. These genes are carried by
chromosomes whose principal constituent is DNA, a very
long molecule formed by the sequence of four chemical
radicals. In man, the forty-six chromosomes contain some
3,000 million of these radicals and correspond roughly to
What can genetic engineering do in the case of heredi¬
tary diseases?
We must make a distinction between the cells in a person's
body, or somatic cells, on the one hand, and the reproductive
cells on the other. It is possible to treat a sick person's
somatic cells through genetic engineering. In the case of a
hereditary blood disease, for example, it is possible to modify
the genetic constitution of sick cells by replacing a damaged
gene with a healthy gene, then reinjecting into the patient
his own cells thus treated. This treatment follows the same
principle as that of artificial limbs, grafts, or organ trans¬
plants. Only the somatic cells of the patient are targeted;
the reproductive cells are not touched. There is no reason
why this kind of treatment should not be used when we
know how to do it properly.
But I believe that for a long time to come we should
totally forbid any kind of experiment on the injection of
genes into all the cells, including the reproductive cells of
the 100,000 genes which are necessary for a human being
to take shape and live.
It was long thought that the more complex an organism
is, the more DNA it would contain. But it has been found
that the salamander and the lily have about ten times more
DNA than a person. Even leaving anthropomorphism aside,
a human being seems more complicated to make than a
lily or a salamander. It would seem that the genome of
rather complex organisms contains only a small fraction
of DNA, from 5 to 10 per cent, corresponding to real
genes. We don't really know what the rest is for. It
contains many repeated sequences which are probably
useless. Some believe it is a kind of waste, a residue of
various genetic mishaps...
The human genome is being studied more and more sys¬
tematically. Efforts are being made to map it with preci¬
sion. One day we shall be able to fully decipher the
hereditary information contained in human chromosomes.
This will be an extraordinary tool, not only for medicine.
We shall have to take great care if we are to make good use
of it. In the name of freedom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
m
*&**
I
m
>
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
ATTEMPTING THE IMPOSSIBLE
BY FEDERICO MAYOR
'I
imagination is more important than But what kind of utopia? And on what terms?
knowledge," said Albert Einstein, and his Utopia is by definition transcendent, a child
remark seems more relevant than ever of excess which nevertheless remains within the
today. The world is changing so rapidly that bounds of reason. Such "reasonable immoder-
our complacency and established ways of think- ation" can make an impact on the real world
ing are continually being challenged. The more by raising its aspirations, without for a moment
the technocrat's certainties and the planner's losing sight of respect for mankind. Did not
pride are confounded by hard facts, the more this kind of ambition and utopianism inspire
the individual capacity for inventiveness is at Martin Luther King, Mahatma Gandhi, and
a premium. "All is flux," said Heraclitus over Nelson Mandela? Such "open" utopias are quite
2,000 years ago. Have we forgotten that change different from those which confine the corn-
is inherent in the human condition? We are munity within a logic that denies individual
living at a time when the pace of historical expression and tends to crush it.
change is such that there is an unparalleled need This sense of vision in utopianism should be
for new thinking. regarded as a liberating, dynamic force for
And what do we see? At the very moment immediate, universal action, an encouragement
when we ought to be guided and impelled by to bold thinking. In the words of Bernard
the creative spirit, people are asserting that Lown, president of International Physicians for
utopia is dead. What justification is there, in the Prevention of Nuclear War, which was
fact, for rejecting the idea of utopia as a beacon awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1985, "Only
of inspiration and a guide to action? Many those who can see the invisible can do the
researchers today see a propensity to look impossible". To increase in this way the
beyond existing reality as the hallmark of the power of the imagination and strengthen the
Utopian impulse, of the intense desire for human desire to go ever further, is to equip
change that re-emerges whenever pragmatism mankind to face reality and respond to the
sinks into arid, sterile routine. Most of them unexpected.
believe that any great human adventure, Can utopia be a guarantee of freedom? No
whether in science, religion or politics, is an final answer has yet been given to this
offshoot of some form of Utopian thought, question. But it is a question that is worth
pairting0^ the Perhaps utopia can sketch a profile of the asking.
future. 11
Venezuelan artist
Pancho Quilici
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The concept of
utopia, an imaginary
ideal society, has
been a fertile source
of controversy. For
some it has been a
beacon of hope for
the future. Others
regard Utopian
thinking as
anathema, and see
Utopians, however
well-intentioned, as
the unwitting
accomplices of
totalitarianism. A
third school of
thought believes that
while utopia can
never be a practical
proposition, it can
stimulate a fruitful
quest for knowledge.
Right, depiction of a 21st-
century space colony by the
American painter Don Davis
(1975).
Opposite page, anonymous
engraving for a 1518 edition
of Thomas Mores Utopia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
' -i
4
-' ? »¿¿3??
DO WE NEED UTOPIA?
BY FERNANDO AINSA
J.AKING its name from the fictional land
depicted in Sir Thomas More's book of 1516,
utopia has become a generic term for all imagi¬
nary worlds in which a society radically different
from our own existsone that is normally in
every respect superior to the real world. It is a
notion that is currently out of fashion, for
nowadays Utopian thought is suspect for its sup¬
posedly totalitarian tendencies.
Recent years have seen the collapse of more
than one would-be real-life utopia, and the dream
of an ideal societylong considered essential for
the fulfilment of human potentialhas for many
people turned into a nightmare. Even the way
the word is now used in everyday speech reflects
its current discredit. It has become synonymous
with pipe-dreams, unrealistic ambitions, and airy-
fairy ideas. For many people, the Utopian vision
has finally been laid to rest.
Such a view may be premature. Contem¬
porary historical, political and philosophical
thought has not entirely lost its Utopian dimen¬
sion. Although utopianism has been condemned
for the ideological wrong turnings it has
encouraged, perhaps it remains indispensable if
we are to conceive of alternative models of the
future.
It is often wrongly thought that utopianism
is a form of literary escapism. Its practitioners
have usually been deeply involved with the polit
ical, social and economic concerns of their day.
The aim of most Utopian works has been to make
people reflect critically about their time. The ideal
societies they have depicted have always been
related in some way to the values of the world
around them.
Thomas More himself was a humanist,
diplomat and politician who rose to be lord chan¬
cellor of England. The marvellous island he
described in his Utopia housed an ideal society
that served to contrast with descriptions of an
existing England sapped by poverty, taxation and
rapacity. More was to pay for his audacity with
his head.
Similarly, the Italian author Tommaso Cam-
panella, writing from prison, proposed the ideal
community of his City of the Sun (1602) as an
alternative to the injustices of the contemporary
world; in fact he even sought help to turn his
ideas into reality. James Harrington's Oceana,
published in 1656, was a challenge to the England
of Oliver Cromwell, while the philosopher and
statesman Francis Bacon, in his New Atlantis of
1627, drew up a programme of political action
for an enlightened monarch.
History may have inspired these imaginary
worlds, but some utopias have in their turn
affected history. Writing in the first shock of the
European encounter with America, Thomas
More thought that things no longer possible in 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
,p
. Ñ1Ü
The Utopian community
imagined by Rabelais in the
16th century Is shown in this
engraving by the French
illustrator Albert Robida
(1848-1926).
14
FERNANDO AINSA,
Uruguayan writer, is a Unesco
staff member. He is the author
of many essays and novels
including Los buscadores de la
utopia (Monte Avila, Caracas,
1977), Identidad cultural de
Iberoamérica en su narrativa
(Gredos, Madrid, 1986), and
Necesidad de la utopia (Nordan
Comunidad, Buenos
Aires/Montevideo, 1990).
the Old World could perhaps be brought to fru¬
ition in the New. In fact there were several
attempts to put his ideas into practice in sixteenth-
century Latin America, from the communes of
farmers and craftsmen established at Michoacán
in Mexico by Bishop Vasco de Quiroga to the
ideal world of Verapazliterally, "True Peace"
that Bartolomé de las Casas sought to create at
Chiapas.
In the succeeding centuries, the missions and
Indian settlementsthe so-called "Reductions"
set up by the Jesuits over a vast area of Brazil,
Argentina and Paraguay drew the inspiration for
their theocratic regimes from both Campanella
and Plato. In the nineteenth century, various
attempts to set up Utopian socialist communities
were made in England, France, the United States
and Latin America.
Criticizing the present
to change the future
Every project for an ideal society is an attempt
to invent the future. That is what distinguishes
utopianism from ideology. As Karl Mannheim,
the author of Ideology and Utopia (1929), put it,
utopias bear a message of hope in the sense that
they signify that change is possible. Whilst
ideology is a vehicle for the world view of people
in power, utopias are by their very nature sub¬
versive; they oppose existing authority and
challenge the view of reality that it imposes.
Some authors consider poor living condi
tions, and the protests they inspire, to be the Uto¬
pians' greatest ally. For E.M. Cioran, author of
Utopia and History (1960) and an acerbic critic
of modern values and of Western civilization,
"The wild thoughts of the indigent set things
moving....; a crowd of hotheads want another
world, and they want it now. These are the
people that inspire utopias, and it is for them that
they are written." Utopian thinking turns to its
own purposes the ancient myth of the Land of
Plenty, and assimilates all the Lands of Cockayne
in which the hungry peasants of the Middle Ages
dreamed of filling their bellies without effort.
Utopianism has in fact often provided an
inspiration for social progress. Many recent
improvements in living conditions were long con¬
sidered Utopian fantasies. Whether with regard
to working hours, sexual equality, welfare poli¬
cies, leisure, alternative energy sources, environ¬
mental protection or town planning, More,
Campanella, Bacon and others can now be seen
as prophets whose dreams have in some cases
become reality.
By no means -all of the realized visions,
however, have been constructive. In the course
of the present century some have come to fruition
in ways that have inspired anxiety and even terror.
Numerous works have described the
increasing mechanization of modern life, the
growth of bureaucracy, the depersonalization of
the individual and the increasingly intrusive
powers of the state, and have denounced their
alienating effects and the assaults on liberty they
represent. Such books normally exaggerate their
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Below, model of the
"Matrimandir", the enormous
sphere of meditation which is
the focal point of Auroville
(Tamil Nadu, India), an
international cultural
community inspired by the
work and ideals of the Indian
mystic and philosopher Sri
Aurobindo (1872-1950).
Auroville was founded in
1968 with Unesco support.
Below right, a scene from
Brazil (1984), a film directed
by Terry Gilliam.
Bottom, plan of "Las
Delicias", the capital of an
ideal country described by the
French-born Argentine writer
Pierre Quiroule In his book La
ciudad anarquista americana
("The American Anarchist
City"), published in Buenos
Aires in 1914.
critique of present-day conditions to the point of
caricature by projecting them into the future: a
future which, unlike that of traditional, idealist
utopias, is the stuff of nightmare.
The classics of this pessimistic school include
Yevgeny Zamyatin's We, published in 1924,
Aldous Huxley's 1946 masterwork Brave New
World, George Orwell's 1984 (which first
appeared in 1949), and Ray Bradbury's Fahrenheit
451, which came out five years later. In these
works, the benevolent monarch of classic Utopian
fiction gives way to the tyrant who sweeps aside
human rights in the name of order and state
security, violates the human conscience and
denies either privacy or individuality to his
victims.
Analysing the way in which totalitarian
systems impose a supposedly rational social order
by means of state violence, the philosopher Karl
Popper came to wonder whether totalitarianism
is not inherent in the Utopian vision. In the name
of rationalism and idealism, those who dream of
perfect societies, he claimed, always became dog¬
matists once in power.
The Russian thinker Nicholas Berdyaev
(1874-1948) presented the idea in a different way.
For him, the twentieth century has proved
utopias to be more attainable than anyone had
imagined. He saw the totalitarian results in the
many would-be ¡deal societies around him. That
insight led him to a bitter question: How can we
be spared utopia?
The fascination of the impossible
The odd thing is that those views of the future
that have historically had the greatest influence
and that people have most often tried to turn into
reality have not, as one might have expected, been
the most realistic, and hence realisable, ones. Take
the case of the author of A New World ofLove,
Charles Fourier, whose radically original ideas
have had great significance for two divergent
groups of people, for totally different reasons.
.":-**-
iß . --X-
"^^: ^£&¡m * \ / . ~p.
^ pp^^f- &
i
Mp^Bt mi-í ^>
.
i
1 J
EM
¡Clip!];
^i'- ví
On the one hand, disciples who took his message
at face value set up communes faithful to his ideas
in Argentina, the United States, Brazil and
Mexico. On the other, the surrealists who were
fascinated by the visionary and subversive aspects
of Fourierism precisely because they considered
them to be unrealisable.
Whether or not it is confronted by the test
of reality or has the fascination of the impossible,
the vision of utopia seems to be one of the motors
of human history. Ultimately it is the measure
of the hope that drives humankind forward.
Although Cioran is generally hostile to social
idealism, even he recognizes that utopias are
part of the quest for human happiness. However,
he attacks the very concept of happiness, which
he holds responsible for many of the great
tragedies of history. Products of history, most
utopias in his view degenerate into tyranny and
servitude.
Other writers would be less willing to dismiss
the quest for a perfect society as merely a cata¬
logue of forlorn hopes. For the Italian essayist
Ignazio Silone, a world without a Utopian dimen¬
sion would be claustrophobic and suffocating,
and would end in a stagnation worse than mad¬
ness. The American theologian Paul Tillich was
even more emphatic: "Without utopias to open 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
up possibilities, the present is sterile and stag¬
nant.... Without utopias, a culture... rapidly falls
back into the past. The present is only fully alive
in the tensions between the past and the future."
On the other hand, a modern social theorist,
Ernst Bloch, draws attention to the risks of "auto¬
matic optimism" and a "blind and limited faith
in the future". He prefers realistic pessimism to
false optimism. In his view, social utopias need
not lead to alienation. They can be realistic and
liberating, just so long as they represent a clearly-
held position free of all adventurism.
Ideal and
nightmare worlds
16
The alternative societies that Utopian literature
has sketched out are much more varied than
might be suggested by the everyday use of the
word, which is now loosely taken to describe
anything from anarchy to tyranny or liberty to
dictatorship, and can be applied to either ideal
or nightmare worlds. Basically, though, they can
be divided into two categories. On the one hand
are those that stress order, with Campanella as
their original inspiration; on the other are those
inspired by liberty, which trace their descent to
the work of Thomas More.
The first kind depicts ideal states; their
imagined worlds are institutional and collective,
not to say totalitarian. The seconddrawing on
popular and revolutionary traditionsdescribes
the best imaginable ways of being. Fear of seeing
the totalitarian utopias turn into reality can easily
blind us to the liberating potential of the other
variety.
"Do what you will" was the motto of the
Abbey of Thelema, the paradise of pleasure
Rabelais depicted in Gargantua and Pantagruel.
It could serve as a rallying-cry for all the liber¬
tarian utopias, from the Renaissance through the
socialist model societies of the nineteenth century
to the alternative communities of the present day,
giving them their "light of dream and passion",
in the phrase of William Morris, author of News
from Nowhere (1890). This sense of wonder shines
like a flame in every work in which the aspira¬
tion towards liberty struggles to overcome all the
rational obstacles that confront it.
For libertarian Utopians, the task is to restore
humanity to the fullness of its nature. In
Morelly's Basiliade of 1753, everything that stands
in the way of individual liberty is abolished:
property, politics, marriage, privilege and law all
go, and humanity is finally free to live in har¬
mony with nature. A similar quest for total liber¬
ation reappears today in the work of the
American fantasy writer Ursula Le Guin, partic¬
ularly in her novel The Dispossessed (1974). The
utopia it depicts arouses both hope and terror,
neatly encapsulating the current uncertainty the
concept provokes.
Maybe it is time to overcome our ambiva¬
lence, and to look beyond the real-life experience
of social engineering that has thrown the whole
idea of ideal worlds into disrepute. In so doing,
it might be possible to recapture the liberating
vitality and dynamism of the original Utopian
dream.
THE FIASCO OF PARADISE
BY GILLES LAPOUGE
SOME people think that when God drove Adam
and Eve out of the Garden of Eden He was
warning Utopians that the ideal society is not
something for this world but for the next.
Certainly the fiasco of Paradise, had human
beings only learnt a lesson from it, could have
saved us from many disappointments. We should
never have had to put up with those radiant
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
societies that lapse inevitably into despotism,
mania, torture and genocide, or with those com¬
munities which promise to deliver the world
from evil and actually do the opposite.
The Bible's advice unfortunately fell on deaf
ears. For as long as people have been capable of
thought, Utopians have peered into their crystal
balls, scribbled down grandiose schemes, and
sketched out never-never lands.
They told themselves that the Garden of
Eden was pleasant, and full of good intentions,
but a bit sloppy, very muddled, and perhaps (of
all things) even anarchic. So they produced more
modern, more cruel, and better-organized models
of Paradise. Utopians are suspicious of every¬
body. They are disciplinarians who like their
cities to be correctly laid out, prefer calculation
to love, evict tramps and dreamers, execute
deviants, and do away with the family, individual
destiny and Old Father Time.
So they produce assembly-line people, aseptic
and uniform. They put their charming societies
into straitjackets and clap freedom in irons. They
do away with controversy and destroy the
pathogens of evil. Too bad if people die, or live
in slavery. Utopian skies, which should be blue,
are actually black.
Hippodamus and Plato:
the demon of geometry
Five centuries before Christ, Hippodamus of
Miletus lived in Ionia, a blessed land on the
Aegean coast of Asia Minor which brought the
Greek genius to its apogee. There, between sea
and sky, an elegant civilization blossomed,
carefree and gay. Unfortunately from the other
side of the Taurus Mountains the armies of
Darius, King of Persia, cast covetous eyes on the
smiling coast. The Ionians led a revolt, and set
Expulsion from the Garden of
Eden, oil on canvas by the
American Romantic landscape
painter Thomas Cole
(1801-1848).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
fire to Sardis. Darius flew into a rage and
unleashed his troops on Ionia; and in 494 BC the
town of Miletus, between Halicarnassus and
Ephesus, was stormed and sacked.
Hippodamus the architect was very pleased.
Here was a chance in a million to build a city
from scratch, rather as Oscar Niemeyer in the
twentieth century would build Brasilia on a site
untrammelled with any historical associations.
"Hippodamus," says Aristotle in his Politics,
"invented the geometric grid plan for towns. He
designed a city of 10,000 inhabitants sub-divided
into three categories, craftsmen, farmers and
militiamen."
Let us remember the grid plan, a design that
marks Hippodamus out as the earliest known
Utopian. The Milesian architect wished to con-
finenature within straight lines and virtually
abolish it, forging a mould that would produce
a clean, tidy, egalitarian, public-spirited, rational
society.
Plato went further than Hippodamus. In the
Laws he describes a blissfully happy society, and
in the Republic he explains how it works.
The city centre is dominated by an acropolis,
from which twelve spokes radiate so as to divide
the city into twelve sections. The streets are
straight, the squares circular, and all the houses
alike. This is a far cry from Athens, the real
Athens, which is a network of delightful, dirty,
winding streets. The city in the Laws, like Hip-
podamus's, is geometrical: it is a beehive, the cells
of which are occupied by people. There are few
amusementsmusic and dancingand all inno¬
vations are prohibited. Poetsdirty, unpredic¬
table dreamersare banished. People eat in
canteens. Statistics are impeccably kept: in the
city of the Laws there are no individuals, only
Left, oil on canvas by the
American artist John Martin.
Below, illustration from a
15th-century edition of The
City of God by Saint
Augustine (354-430).
citizens. Idlers, dreamers, tramps and bachelors
are outlawed.
This mathematical city works like a com¬
puter, without mistakes or breakdowns. The idea
is to cram the soul into the pattern of the city
and the city into the pattern of the cosmos ("the
well-organized"). Plato wants to protect society
from the disastrous whims of "sublunar nature"
and the bloody horrors of history.
Plato's society was divided into three layers:
at the top were the philosophers, who kept the
state together and took the decisions. (Being
immune from unexpected circumstances and the
caprices of history, the ideal city should have no
need of a strong government. In the more
extreme utopias that came later, government
withers away: the city alters itself, unfailingly
reproducing the same movements. The cosmos
needs no rudder; it spins of its own accord, and
never goes off the rails.)
Plato, however, kept a government. The
philosophers who constituted it were assisted by
guardians or watchdogs, who needed to be both
"irascible and also philosophical". They in turn
were in charge of the third category, viz. the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
workers and peasants. The guardians were fierce
because the workers were uneducated people
with "covetous souls" who only did stupid
things. These mindless people even allowed them¬
selves the luxury of having instincts and feelings,
loving their neighbours' wives, adoring their chil¬
dren and grieving when their mothers diedin
short, of harbouring a multitude of germs which
Plato, the skilled physician, set out to kill. Plato
was an obsessional disinfecter: he wanted an open
society of passionless citizens devoid of memory
and imaginationa dreary collection of "people
without attributes".
The abolition of the family
The philosophers who govern the city in Plato's
Laws are indefatigable. They are on the lookout
for trouble night and day. They strike at the first
hint that any feeling, desire or softness is creeping
into the crystal city. Everything "organic" is to
be organized out of existence.
Hence the family is one of their favourite
targets. For Utopians the family spells disaster,
trauma and calamity, for it contains within itself
the seeds of everything primitive, dark, instinc¬
tive and "organic". The state could of course
Roman mosaic depicting Plato
teaching his followers.
GILLES LAPOUGE,
French writer and journalist,
has published several novels,
including Les pirates (Phébus,
Paris, 1987), travel books such
as Equinoxiales (Flammarion,
Paris, 1977) and two essays
on utopia, Utopies et
civilisations and Le singe de la
montre (Flammarion, Paris,
1982).
negotiate with the family, or put it in a strait-
jacket. Many despotic states did this later on but
they all came to grief on the rock of the family.
More shrewdly, Plato opted for a radical solution:
realizing that the family would always be an
obstacle to a dictatorial state, he abolished it.
Children are taken from the bosoms of their
families and returned to the state. No more
mothers, fathers, sisters or cousinsand good rid¬
dance! The family expands to the size of the city,
and is thus dissolved.
Destroying the family in this way is both log¬
ical and insane. Logical, because a mathematical
society cannot tolerate the untidiness of the
family, its warmth and intimacy, its demands, and
its murky depths. Insane because the family is
intractable. It resists and will always resist attacks
on it from the state.
It may seem odd that mammals are not good
at setting up rational societies. Even beavers are
anarchists, rogues and eccentrics by comparison
with ants or bees. Mammals are politically inept
because the familya husband's link with his
wife, a mother's with her childrenstands up to
all acts of violence by the state.
This is where social insects excel. In beehives
and anthills the young are taken over by the state, 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
so there can be no bond of affection or sentiment
between parents and their offspring. Heedless of
the passage of time, immobile and submissive,
contemptuous of individual liberties, blindly
obeying pre-programmed instructions, an anthill
fulfils the irrational dream of absolute reason. The
mistake made by Plato and all the Utopians who
followed in his footsteps was to suppose that man
is a political animal. He is not, but ants are. Plato
was a philosopher for bees and termites.
The diktat of the clock
Plato's designs were never implemented. The
philosopher's advice was rejected by Dionysius
the Elder, the tyrant of Syracusehimself no sen¬
timentalist. Nevertheless the philosophical exer¬
cise initiated by Plato was to beget many
offspring, including Thomas More, Etienne Cabet
and Robert Owen.
Even in Antiquity other thinkers constructed
ideal cities. The Stoic Iambulus has left us a
description of seven "happy isles", but they are
not attractive. Anyone stranded on one of these
islands would have wanted only to get away. The
islanders were divided into groups of 400. Procre¬
ation and education were state-controlled, with
the aim of making all the children physically
equal. The citizens were all alike and could not
be told apart. Intellectual and mental equality was
engineered by means of monotonous working
shifts continually repeated.
Historians of utopia tend to neglect the
Middle Ages, which is not right, for that obscure
period produced two very important Utopian fea¬
tures, convents and clocks.
Convents, abbeys and monasteries were oases
of peace and quiet in a stormy world, harmonious
settled communities that would have delighted
Plato. There were no families, nor even
individuals. Monks and nuns did not even use
their own names. The rule of St. Benedict was
so strict and all-embracing that abbots and
mothers superior had nothing to supervise but
stillness and the meticulous, contented repetition
of the same rituals. This was a glowing success
one of the few successes of utopia. But it becomes
less impressive when one realizes that the splen¬
dours of monastic architecture belong to eternity
rather than history.
Clocks came into being, by chance, in a con¬
vent, that is in a Utopian environment. The
mechanism of this magnificent invention-
unchanging, inhuman and implacable, incapable
of error, free from whims or inconsistencies, and
immune from the constraints of history, . is
reminiscent of a perfect society. It is because they
are timeless that clocks can show the time.
Plato's utopia was based on a model, the
cosmos, and drew its inspiration secretly from
another model, the anthill. Post-Renaissance Uto¬
pians in their dozens used another model to feed
their rational hallucinations: the watch.
A PLATONIC PARABLE
BY ALAIN FRONTIER
IXT the beginning of Plato's Republic,
Thrasymachus, one of Socrates' questioners, flies
into a towering rage. Socrates, he says, is making
fools of them all as usual. He is pretending to be
a simpleton, saying nothing clear, letting others
do the talking for him, taking pleasure in seeing
them get mixed up in their own contradictions.
The irony of Socrates, and through him the
irony of Plato whose mouthpiece he is, is not
gratuitous. He wants to destabilize certainties
before pursuing the only inquiry that matters:
what is justice? Thrasymachus's answer is clear.
It is the established sovereign power that decides
what is justice. Thrasymachus decides to stick to
the reality of things. What interests Socrates is
not the real but the true. And to explore the true
he proposes the path of utopia.
Let us observe, says Socrates, through the
word, the logoshe insists on this verbal
dimensiona city that is in the process of being
constituted. Why a city? Because a city is bigger
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
than an individual and thus easier to observe. By
seeing how men will live in it, we shall perhaps
have occasion to see justice and injustice consti¬
tute themselves there at the same time.
This city does not exist, it is a fiction. But
it is not entirely a lie since it is subjected to the
moral requirement that is love of truth. By
pushing it to its conclusion is there not a chance
of coming close to a reply?
Let's act as if it were a myth, says Socrates,
even though we know that it isn't one. There's
no pretence in this fiction. Nor any nostalgia: the
verbs are not in the past tense. With its future
indicative, utopia offers itself as a pure project,
we don't even need to dream about its execution.
It is not the exposition of an ideological
programme! Utopia does not present already
acquired ideas of which one can be sure. "I don't
know," Socrates says. "I don't know yet. We
must continue. We must go where the logos takes
us as the wind blows a boat." Utopia is like a
slow voyage which takes its time.
And yet what difficulties, what risks!
announces Socrates to those of his listeners who
wish to accompany him on this fictitious adven¬
ture. Utopia will meet with incredulity, it will be
taken for the ramblings of a dreamer. Even worse.
What I fear, says Socrates, is not so much making
people laugh as travestying the truth. I would
move forward more boldly if I were sure of
knowing. But I doubt and I seek. Perhaps it is
necessary, he adds, to bring a certain proportion
to our utopia, to impose certain limits on it.
No, replies Glaucon, another participant in the
discussion, we must go on, even if it takes the
whole of life.
Utopia. Has anyone ever noticed the strange
way in which Thomas More during the Renais¬
sance created his neologism from the Greek? At
first sight the word seems simple. Derived from
the Greek word topos meaning "place" and the
negative ou, "utopia" designates that which is
found in "no place". But logically More should
have used the privative form a which should be
used in this situation (as in apolitical, etc.). Why
did he not do so? Why did he not want to use
the word "atopia"?
I think there are two reasons. First of all, the
word atopia already existed in Greek to designate
something extraordinary, new, strange, extrava¬
gant or absurd. This is not a definition of the
utopia described by More (and after him Rabelais
and others). Then, by beginning the word with
a negative adverb ("not"), More deliberately
emphasized that the place he describes does not
exist anywhere, has never existed and will never
exist. That it should not exist. Woe betide anyone
who tried to apply to the real world what is only
a figment of thought, a method of understanding
and approaching the truth.
If Plato's city existed, it would be the worst
of all cities. Is this a reason for burning his
Republic} Banish the philosopher from our city?
The world's problems come not from utopias but
from those who were foolish enough to confuse
them with programmes of political action.
Panel from a series of
allegorical frescoes on "Good
and Bad Government"
(1337-1339), painted by the
Italian artist Ambroglo
Lorenzettl for the Palazzo
Pubbllco, Siena.
ALAIN FRONTIER,
French poet and grammarian,
teaches ancient Greek In Paris.
He is the author of textbooks
on the Greek language and of
several works of fiction,
including Portrait d'une dame
(TXT, Brussels, -1987) and
Comment j'ai connu Harry
Dickson (Muro-Torto, Berlin,
1988). 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
History provides many
examples of people who
have attempted, with
varying degrees of
success, to realize the
dream of utopia. Over
3,000 years ago the
Pharaoh Akhenaton built
a "city of the sun" on
the banks of the Nile. In
India in the third century
BC the Emperor Asoka
took inspiration from
Buddhist egalitarian
ideals. In the nineteenth
century a crop of
Utopian communities
blossomed in the United
States. A prolific
futuristic literature
produced in Russian
since Tsarist times has
expressed the intuitions
and torments of society.
Some Utopian thinkers,
by imagining original
solutions to the
problems of the
industrial age, have
influenced, for better
or worse, the way we
live now.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
AKHET-ATON, CITY OF THE SUN
BY AYYAM WASSEF
Left, Akhenaton, Nefertiti and
their daughter worship Aton,
the solar disc. Limestone bas-
relief from Tell el-Amarna
(Asyut province, Egypt).
Above right, Akhenaton
portrayed on a sandstone
pillar statue from the Temple
of Aton at Karnak (1370 BC).
wHEN Plato sought to visualize the ideal state,
the illusory hope of creating a republic founded
on reason led him prudently to propose banishing
poets. Utopia, it would seem, cannot tolerate in
its ideal world the subversive force of the
imagination which is, ironically, the very ele¬
ment that gives it birth. Things change, however,
when the Utopian dreamer has the power to put
his visions into effect through the fact that he is
kinga real king, who as it happened in this case
was also a poet.
Akhet-aton (literally, "city of the horizon")
was a real-life utopia that lasted only as long as
the heretical views of its creator, the Pharaoh
Akhenaton. What is left of its twelve-year exis¬
tence can be found in Middle Egypt, on the banks
of the Nile at Tell el-Amarna. There are some
palaces, a workers' residential quarter, a sculptors'
workshop, several temples. These vestiges bear
witness less to the town's existence than to the
fact of its demolition. They are stone fragments
of an interrupted poem, fixed forever in its
moment of inception.
Until 1842 even the name of the city was for¬
gotten, let alone its history. People had at best
an inkling that somewhere midway between
Egypt's ancient capital of Memphis and Thebes,
the town that supplanted it, a city of gold-
encrusted temples lay hidden, concealed both by
the sands of the desert and by the still more cor¬
rosive dust of neglect.
It was not until 1912 that German Egyptol¬
ogists discovered the painted bust of Nefertiti,
now in the Berlin Museum, that was to become
one of the most precious of Egyptian artworks
and was by its luminous beauty to cast light on
the strangest and least-known episode of the
country's Pharaonic history. It immediately
raised the question of who its subject might have
been, for her name had been carefully removed
from most of the records. It took fifty years'
research to establish that the splendid, high-
crowned queen had been the wife of Akhenaton,
whose name had also been proscribed, featuring
in none of the official lists of Egypt's rulers. In
effect, the historians of ancient Egypt had deliber¬
ately expunged thirty years of their own history.
The extent of the conspiracy suggests just
how significant the Amarna episode was for
ancient Egyptians. The radical programme that
Akhenaton introduced, inspired as much by
poetry as by politics, was so profoundly
unsettling that even now it appears an aberration
fitting uneasily into any straightforward chrono¬
logical account of Egyptian history, belonging
instead, it would seem, in some hidden corner of
the memory, on the threshold of a dream.
At this distance, Akhenaton's own person¬
ality is difficult to reconstruct. Some people see
him as a tragic préfiguration of Christ, a precursor
of monotheism, Moses before the letter. For
others he is the heretical Pharaoh, the great stain
on the history of his nationand by extension
on its geography, which through his creative
endeavours he permanently marked with a small,
enduring, sun-coloured spot.
For in an arid and burning place where the
sun might have come up on the very first day of
creation, Akhenaton decided to build a city that
was to be the centre and focal point of his own
new religion. In defiance of the powerful priest¬
hood, he banned the cult of Amon, king of the
gods, and established in its place the worship of
Aton, the sun. The break came abruptly at the
beginning of his reign, around the year 1362 BC.
The king changed his royal title from Amenophis
IV the name meant "Amon is satisfied" to
Akhenaton, "he whom Aton loves", and left the
royal city of Thebes to start work on the new
capital. A hundred thousand technicians, engineers
and workers were employed to build his
metropolis, which was planned to hold an even
larger number of inhabitants. Akhet-aton was to
be a city of the sun, of art and love and joy. It
was almost certainly the first urban centre to have
been designed from scratch.
Ingenious means were found to bring the
finest and most suitable materials to the site. To
lighten the architecture, and so increase the con¬
trast with the massive stone monuments of earlier
reigns, wooden beams were used to support walls
of mud-brick. A royal avenue bordered by the
most expensive houses ran through the middle
of the city. The houses of less privileged citizens
occupied the adjoining district, and beyond lived 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
I»
* ti ' .Ci. *
Któv
""
-a-~
^w
*
-
24
all the tribe of hopefuls who came to Akhet-aton
in search of a new life. The great temple in the
city's centre was formed of several courtyards
leading to a sanctuary; the whole building was
oriented to the rising sun and laid open to its
sacred rays, for it had no roof. Thus the Pharaoh
and his fellow-worshippers could commune
directly with their god, bathed in a light made the
more dazzling by the yellow colour omnipresent
throughout the town.
The most impressive building of all, however,
was the Northern Palace, built a short way out¬
side the town for Nefertiti. It was a world in
miniature. Set amid pools and gardens, a vast,
square lake bordered by colonnades was sur¬
rounded by enclosures containing rare birds and
beasts, a happy intrusion of nature into the daily
human round.
We now have a fairly clear idea of the daily
life of Akhet-aton: of its many banquets, its fes¬
tivals in honour of the sun-god. But we still know
little of its political activity. The world of affairs
apparently took second place to the Pharaoh's
aesthetic preoccupations.
Nevertheless, the fact that its god could be
seen suggests that there must have been some¬
thing of a revolution in people's perception of
secular power. For in a city whose god is open
to view, people live close to, and within the
compass of, the divine. This new relationship
between god and man lies at the heart of
Akhenaton's revolution, and its significance can
be summed up in a metaphor of looking. Aton
the all-seeing is, as it were, the eye of the sun;
and the sun itself is the eye of god, both seeing
The ruins of Akhet-aton, the
capital city of the Pharaoh
Akhenaton at Tell el-Amarna.
AYYAM WASSEF,
Egyptian essayist, is preparing
a doctoral thesis at the
University of Paris I on the
theme of the individual in
contemporary philosophy. Her
publications include a study of
the German-Jewish philosopher
Martin Buber. She is currently
writing an account of her
experiences as an Egyptian
living in Paris.
and seen. The old hidden god, Amon, saw every¬
thing without being observed, never revealing
himself except through a glass darkly in the form
of multifarious carved and graven images that
served as scattered symbols of the divine presence
among men. Maybe Akhenaton's heresy lay in
wanting to break through such substitutions, to
do away with this distance of symbols and instead
to bask permanently in the godhead's shining
light.
That is why his creation was Utopian in the
true sense of the word. From a poetic point of
view, utopia implies the promise of finally
achieving a true and exact apprehension of reality.
The Amarnan aesthetic lends itself to a kind of
exacerbated realism. Imitating the solar disc itself,
which radiates outwards in countless individual
rays, the artist's regard moves forth towards the
object of its attention, the objective other that
is also watching it. King Akhenaton is represented
as he was, formless; a king whose reality lay in
the regard of other people.
One glimpses here the germs of the incipient
democratic sense that some people have discerned
in Akhenaton's programme. Universally visible,
dispensing light and life to all with equal bounty,
the sun is the very emblem of a just monarch,
indeed of utopia itself. But a kingeven one who
was also a poetwould find it hard to maintain
such an exalted level in the day-to-day governance
of any human community. Akhenaton's courage
lay in not having presupposed failure, and
thereby having for a short time blurred the
boundary between what is desirable and what is
possible.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A GOLDEN AGE
BY ANANDA W.P. GURUGE
BUDDHIST texts speak of an ideal golden age in
the distant past, when prevailing standards of
moral propriety precluded the need for kings and
government or even private property, boundary
marks or fences. Then deceit and theft brought
a gradual degradation and led to the need for all
these institutions. A king, the Great Chosen One,
was democratically elected. This, in a nutshell,
is an explanation of how contemporary society
and its institutions came into existence.
Buddhist writings contain no Utopian remedy
for a return to the lost golden age, but they do give
plenty of advice about how to improve society,
especially in the form of ethical principles. An
ideal king must possess ten qualities: generosity,
moral conduct, sacrifice, honesty, gentleness,
asceticism, the. capacity to refrain from anger,
non-violence, forbearance and non-oppression.
A community should guarantee its stability
by assembling for consultation in harmony, trans¬
acting its business in harmony, and dispersing in
harmony. It should not introduce revolutionary
laws or break away from established conventions.
Elders should be honoured and obeyed. Women
should be respected and safeguarded. Spiritual
obligations should be performed and free access
and facilities to saints and holy persons should
be allowed.
An individual gained merit not only by per¬
forming religious observances but by rendering
services to fellow-beings, such as providing them
with roads and water, shady trees and rest-houses,
medicine and food. The old and the very young
were also to be protected.
Buddha did not confine himself to the
promulgation of an ideal social order. He actu¬
ally experimented with one. The community of
Buddhist monks, the sangha, was an institution
whose members observed monastic vows which
enabled the Buddha's Utopian social values and
norms to be applied. Rules governing property
ownership emphasized the egalitarian structure
of the sangha. Every giftand originally gifts
were the only form of revenue as the members
of the sangha did not engage in economic
pursuitswas received collectively and held in
perpetuity in the name of the sangha. No one had
any private possessions. When a monk died or
left the sangha, his personal effects reverted to col¬
lective ownership and were redistributed to
others according to need.
Fortnightly meetings were held at which the
members of the sangha confessed and atoned for
any transgressions and collectively committed
themselves to observe the rules of conduct227
in the southern Buddhist tradition, 250 in the
Chinese tradition.
Because of its elaborate procedures and the
extremely demanding regulation of behaviour,
the sangha was a social model which only the
most highly motivated could adopt. Thus,
although it continues to exist and thrive after
more than twenty-five centuries (with some relax¬
ation in its original rules), the sangha was never
a model that could be applied to society at large.
Nevertheless, many of its elements were emulated
by later Hindu institutions such as the monastic
communities founded by Sankara, and the Arya
Samaj movement founded by Dayananda Saras-
vati in 1875.
But above all, a practical application of Budd¬
hist ethical principles can be seen in the extraor¬
dinary experiment carried out in the third
century BC by the Emperor Asoka, who deve¬
loped a humane socio-political system for the
governance of his empire, the largest ever to exist
in the Indian sub-continent.
Nearly 200 inscriptions have been discovered,
which reveal Asoka's twofold strategyon the
one hand of seeking to convince people through
admonition and on the other of issuing decrees
and orders. Preferring the first course to the
second, he used education to propagate his prin¬
ciples, appointed a cadre of officers who under¬
took regular tours of inspection, and inscribed
edicts and instructions on rocks and stone pillars.
Asoka's socio-political system operated suc¬
cessfully for at least two decades. But his empire
declined and was dismembered almost immedi¬
ately after his demise. Was this because its foun¬
dations were Utopian? This is a question which
historians have yet to answer.
Lion capital from a pillar
Inscribed with an edict of the
Emperor Asoka (3rd century
BC). It was found at Sarnath
(Uttar Pradesh), one of the
holy places of Buddhism.
ANANDA W.P. GURUGE
is Sri Lanka's ambassador to
France and permanent
delegate to Unesco, where he
is a member of the Executive
Board. A specialist In Asian
and Buddhist cultures, he has
published over twenty books in
Sinhala and English, including
The Society of the Ramayana
(1960). 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE AMERICAN LABORATORY
BY RONALD CREAGH
26
A HE dream of a paradise on Earth is a persis¬
tent feature of the history of humanity. It has
inspired countless Utopian experiments in com¬
munity living in different parts of the world.
These attempts to create an ideal society have
aroused widespread scepticism and still do. Is
there not a contradiction inherent in trying to
bring to life the notion of a place which is by
definition located "nowhere"?
The function of utopia has been to incite
people to escape from history, to reject conven¬
tions and break away from the established order
of things. Subversive by nature, the idea of utopia
stretches the collective imagination beyond its
limits. This subversiveness distinguishes Utopian
communities from those modelled on the
dominant ideology of the society around them.
Perhaps more than any other country in the
world, the United States has been the setting for
a wide variety of experiments in community
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Left, a village of the Amana
society or Community of True
Inspiration founded in Iowa
(USA) in the mid-19th century.
Above, a "Time Note", worth
five hours' labour. This form
of payment was introduced by
the Welsh social reformer
Robert Owen (1771-1858) for
trade in the National Equitable
Labour Exchanges which he
set up in several English
towns in 1832.
living. Both recent immigrants and long-time
Americans have participated in these Utopian
associations, most often in rural areas but some¬
times in towns and cities.
Utopianism and reality have been intertwined
in America ever since colonial times. In the seven¬
teenth century, William Penn founded a refuge
from religious intolerance in "Pennsylvania",
where he established a democratic form of
government. Penn represents a kind of transition
between English revolutionary thought and
American religious communitarianism. Visions
of an earthly paradise mingled with more prosaic
motivations in the conquest of new frontiers.
Two main trends, one religious and one
secular, can be distinguished in the rich history
of communal movements that has been a marked
feature of American history. The religious
impulse led to the quest for a heavenly Jerusalem.
Such groups as the Shakers (who have since dis¬
appeared), the Rappites and the Amish turned
their backs on the exploitation of the masses by
industry and rejected the worship of technology
and its amenities. The quest for a perfect life here
and now and the hope of establishing a Kingdom
of God on Earth characterized the thinking of
these groups in which myth and utopia were
mingled.
The pathway
to a new harmony
The second, parallel trend is not centred on the
supernatural, although its adherents have some¬
times used a religious vocabulary. These experi¬
ments in community living have been
rationalistic, and specifically designed to bring
about a political and economic regeneration.
A first crop of associations appeared during
the period of westwards expansion and lasted
until around 1860. Most of them had European
leaders who, like the prophets of old, hoped to
create a new people. The Welsh philanthropist,
socialist and former factory-owner Robert Owen
designed his New Harmony community in
Indiana as a prototype for future humanity and a
model for general application. Equally optimistic
intentions were expressed by the German tailor
Wilhelm Weitling and by the French and
American disciples of Charles Fourier and
Etienne Cabet.
A second flowering began almost a century
later, in the late 1950s. For the most part these
new associations claimed more modest aspirations
than their predecessors. They sought to escape
the constraints of city life, technocracy and the
state, and to combat psychological, economic and
political insecurity. These communities came in
so many shapes, sizes and styles and were often
so short-lived as to defy attempts at classification, 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Above, the closing procession
at a meeting of the Shakers,
an American religious
community which reached its
peak In the mid- 19th century.
Left, Amish boys on their way
to school on homemade
scooters. Austerity and
opposition to modern
civilization are characteristics
of the Amish, a religious
group most of whose
members live in Pennsylvania
(USA).
. but they included urban collectives, co-operatives,
and communes.
Many of these projects were based on a redis¬
covery of subjectivity, of the individual's relation¬
ship with society, and of ecology. They were a
breeding ground for activism against the Viet
Nam war, the consumer society, environmental
pollution, and the marginalization of women and
homosexuals.
Between these two major explosions of
vitality there was an intermediary phase in which
socialist co-operatives and communities were
created by immigrants and anarchists fleeing
persecution in other countries. In these zones of
freedom a radical tradition was upheld, and all
forms of authoritarianism were rejected.
Modern Times
One of the most remarkable experiments of the
anarchist and libertarian movement was "Modern
Times", a community founded by Josiah Warren,
the father of American anarchist individualism.
An eccentric community that was the source of
28 some scandal in its time,- Modern Times was
RONALD CREAGH
is professor of American
civilization at the Université
Paul Valéry, Montpellier,
France. He is engaged on
research into utopias with
international groups, notably
with members of the
philosophy department of the
University of Rome. His
publications include
Laboratoires de l'utopie: les
communautés libertaires aux
Etats-Unis (Payot, Paris, 1983),
and a work in English on the
history of American anarchism
(Columbia University Press,
USA, forthcoming).
created in 1850, when Josiah Warren and his
Fourierist disciple Stephen Paul Andrews bought
a piece of land on Long Island, east of New York
City on the site of what is now the town of Brent¬
wood. Warren wanted to create a community
close enough to a big city for it to survive eco¬
nomically until it reached the ideal population
of 1,000 persons which would enable it to be self-
sufficient.
The sandy soil, covered with tough, dense
brushwood, was difficult to clear and required
expensive fertilizer to cultivate. Sparks from the
locomotive of the Long Island Railroad had
caused more than one forest fire, and hardly any
trees were left to provide protection from the
wind. Only wild animals lived on this desolate
tract of land.
Two years later, a community of neat little
cottages had been built. The site was divided into
forty-nine blocks by seven streets running from
north to south and seven avenues running from
east to west. The streets and avenues were wide
enough to give all the dwellings good access to
air and light. Land was sold at a fixed price to
anyone who wished to buy. No one was allowed
to purchase more than three plots.
Overlooking the private dwellings was a
square two-storey building which housed a forge,
a carpentry shop and a general store as well as
apartments. The hard-working and strictly
vegetarian inhabitants of Modern Times cleared
the brush to create vegetable gardens, and planted
pines to protect the town from the wind. In spite
of disappointments and setbacks, they were soon
producing enough fruit and vegetables to
exchange among themselves and feed the commu¬
nity. Apple and cherry trees were planted along
the main thoroughfares so that travellers passing
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
through could eat the fruit rather than having to
beg for food.
Newcomers to the community had to be able
to provide for themselves and to follow a trade
producing marketable goods, and so tailors, cob¬
blers, smiths, carpenters and other craftsmen were
invited to join. The community had its own
currencynotes which engaged the bearer to pay
others in hours of work. Bonuses were added for
the harder types of work. These "Time Notes"
were accepted in nearby villages, were unaffected
by the 1857 currency devaluation and were even
used to pay taxes. Due to all these factors, many
people who joined the community with modest
resources were soon able to purchase their own
homes.
The right to be different
Individualism was the rule, but the group was
interested in communal solutions to cost-cutting
and labour-saving as long as they respected
individual tastes and interests. Members of the
community enjoyed complete freedom of
opinion. Each woman was free to choose the
father of her children, and a ribbon on a girl's
finger indicated that she was "taken". Thus mar¬
riage was rarely legalized. This doctrine, which
was based on Fourier's theory of the affinities of
love, was responsible for the undeservedly scan-
' dalous reputation of Modern Times.
This original experiment encouraged
creativity and innovation among the commu¬
nity's members. Two of them introduced stenog¬
raphy into the United States. One family
developed safety belts to secure children in chairs
and carriages. Clark Orvis, who later perfected
the bicycle, invented an early form of self-service
restaurant.
The community's fame spread as far as
Russia, and the London-based leaders of the Inter¬
national Workers Association, including Karl
Marx, took an interest in its activities. Cabet,
Owen, Weitling, Auguste Comte and other well-
known social reformers studied Warren's theories,
as did the leaders of the American labour
movement.
The story goes that during the Civil War the
people of Modern Times sailed away to South
America in a little ship with white wings, but this
romantic story is only symbolically true. The
increasing population in the area around Modern
Times hastened the end of the experiment. Josiah
Warren went to live in Boston. For him the time
for experimentation was over. From then on he
devoted himself to expounding his theories.
The Modern Times experiment is striking for
its complete absence of dogmatism. The right to
be different made it possible for people to live as
they pleased and find fulfilment in their own
inventiveness and intellectual and spiritual pur¬
suits. It was an "open" utopia which through its
image of serenity and love of life gave new impetus
to the quest for freedom.
The futuristic city of Arcosanti
in the Arizona desert (USA) is
the brainchild of visionary
architect Paolo Soleri.
Construction began 20 years
ago.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
PARADISE IN 4338? BY VSEVOLOD REVICH
u,
30
'TOPIAN writers have often presented their
message in the form of semi-political, semi-fantastic
stories, and today the frontier between "pure"
Utopian writing and science fiction is very hard to
define. Although Russian Utopian literature has
produced no world-famous books such as More's
Utopia and Campanella's City ofthe Sun, it never¬
theless provides instances of remarkable insight.
In the mid-eighteenth century, Russian fic¬
tion consisted almost entirely of Utopian writings,
which showed traces of the influence of the
French Enlightenment. Whether the setting was
an imaginary island or a real place like ancient
Rome, utopianism was a form ideally suited to
philosophical moralizing.
When describing his novel Numa, or
Flourishing Rome, Mikhail Matveevich Kheraskov
wrote as follows: "This story is not absolutely
true historically. It is embellished with many fan¬
tasies which make it more beautiful without
depreciating Numa's deeds." Numa's wise rule
prompts the author to give a piece of sagacious
if somewhat cautious advice to sovereigns which
still seems relevant today. The true glory of a
sovereign, he says, "is not always won with
weapons. ..for the triumphant cries of the victors
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
are often accompanied by the lamentations of
widows and orphans". Kheraskov sadly notes
that his story will have hardly any impact, but
"if there is no happy society on Earth let it at
least exist in books and afford us the consolation
that we too can be happy one day".
A pretext
for political confrontation
Many novels of this kind were written in late
eighteenth-century Russia. The best-known was
Alexander Radischev''s Journeyfrom St. Petersburg
to Moscow, a denunciation of serfdom which con¬
tains a Utopian account of how prosperous free
farmers could be. At the other end of the polit¬
ical spectrum, Prince Mikhail Scherbatov's A
Journey to the Ofirian Land vigorously opposed
Peter the Great's reforms, described cities as a
source of moral degradation and their buildings
Above, the covers of. French
editions of two works by Ivan
Efremov (1907-1972), a
master of Soviet science
fiction.
as "heaps of stones", and advocated a return to
the patriarchal way of life.
The 1825 Decembrist uprising against Tsarist
autocracy left a mark on nineteenth-century Rus¬
sian history and on philosophical dreams of
Russia's destiny. The Decembrist Wilhelm
Küchelbecker wrote The Land of the Headless, a
satirical sketch in which the narrator lands on the
Moon where he finds a social system which
embodies the worst aspects of Russian life.
Küchelbecker had discovered that utopias may
have undesirable features, a new slant which gave
rise to a flood of "anti-utopias" a century later.
The major Russian Utopian work of the first
half of the nineteenth century was an unfinished
story by Vladimir Odoyevsky, The Year 4338. In
4338, according to Odoyevsky's calculations, the
Earth should cross the path of a massive comet
and possibly even collide with it. The plot centres
on human efforts to avoid this disaster. In
Odoyevsky's utopia, the Moon is uninhabited
and serves as a source of supplies for the Earth,
which is threatened by overpopulation. Electric
vehicles are driven along underground tunnels.
Siberia is heated by energy from volcanoes. Per¬
sonal aircraft are used. Clothes are made of glass
fibre. St. Petersburg has merged with Moscow,
forming an immense megalopolis.
Odoyevsky makes the same mistake as many
other writers about utopia. He talks about the
general improvement of conditions, but devotes
no attention whatever to the spiritual life of the
people who live in these flourishing societies.
Nikolai Chernyshevsky tried to avoid this error
in "The Fourth Dream of Vera Pavlovna", a Uto¬
pian chapter of his novel What is to be Done? In
this socialist Song of Solomon, Chernyshevsky
depicts the future as a Kingdom of Lovenot
puritan, abstract love, but earthly love which
brings people the joy of life. Unlike Odoyevsky,
with his preference for the city, Chernyshevsky
believed that a healthy and happy life is only pos¬
sible in a natural environment.
In contrast to these writers, Feodor
Dostoyevsky in his A Dream ofa Funny Man has
no good word to say for socialismor for what he
calls socialism. Alas, it appears that Dostoyevsky
was right on many points.
Perfect worlds,
soulless worlds
Around the 1890s, Russian Utopian thought
started to become more diversified and original.
One notable example of a new cosmic trend is
Nikolai Fyodorov's Philosophy of the Common
Cause (1906, 1913), a remarkable book in which
Fyodorov imagines the resurrection of all the
people who ever lived on Earth. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
At the Machine Tool, by the
Soviet painter, designer and
sculptor Alexandre Deineka
(1899-1969).
32
VSEVOLOD REVICH,
of the Soviet Union, is a
literary critic and essayist. A
student of utopia and fantasia
in fiction, he has written over
200 works including essays
entitled "Neither Truth nor
Invention", "Tragedy and
Fairytale" and "Realism in
Fantasy".
Reactionary writers afraid of the changes that
were impending in Russia laced their views with
sober warnings which unfortunately were not
heeded. The radical young were unable to find
a rational message in treatises permeated with
great-power chauvinism.
The characters in Nikolai Shelonsky's novel
The World ofthe Future (1892) find themselves in
the thirtieth century faced with a map on which
Germany and Italy no longer exist. England and
America have survived but in an "uncivilized
state"they are capitalist countries characterized
by the pursuit of profit, extremes of wealth and
poverty, and militarism. On the other hand, the
alliance between Russia and Francebased on the
Orthodox faithhas enabled these countries to
attain an extraordinarily high level of spiritual
and social development. The book also contains
many inklings of future developments-
television, synthetic fabrics, the Channel Tunnel,
and even anti-matter.
At the other political extreme, the most
notable socialist fantasy of these years was Red
Star by Alexander Bogdanov, an associate of
Lenin until ideological differences drove them
apart. The Red Star is Mars, which is inhabited
by humanoids who are practically indistinguish¬
able from human beings. The communist prin¬
ciple reigns supreme: from each according to his
abilities, to each according to his needs. The Mar¬
tians' basic need is to work, and they often change
jobs to enjoy the pleasures of diversity. Economic
stability is maintained by information-computing
machines. Just imagine, computers in 1908!
Here again spiritual life leaves much to be
desired. The Martians are polite and considerate,
but incapable of emotion. The logic of expe¬
diency takes the place of inner motivation. In this
atmosphere Sterney, a mathematician, works out
a project to annihilate humankind and colonize
the Earth. Whether intentionally or not, Bog¬
danov makes the prophetic statement that mons¬
trous, inhuman projects can be generated by a
rationally organized society if it does not rest on
firm moral principles.
The end of an illusion
Andrei Platonov, artistic genius and prophet, re¬
alized much earlier and more clearly than his con¬
temporaries that attempts to build a new society
on servility or by decree were immoral and
doomed to failure. Such enterprises can lead only
to a common grave in which the builders of the
society either lie down of their own free will (The
Foundation Pit), or are dispatched there by other
means (Chevengur). And if Mikhail Bulgakov
went wrong in his grotesque play Adam and Eve,
it was only in his supposition that a few people
would survive the use of weapons of mass des¬
truction.
The hero of Sigiezmund Krzhizhanovsky's
story Recollections of the Future, written in the
late 1920s, invents a time machine and travels
several years into the future, but what he sees is
so horrible that he hurries back and tells nobody
about it.
In the same alarmist vein is Yevgeny
Zamyatin's famous futurist novel We (1924),
one of the key books of the twentieth century.
To the indignation of the Soviet press, it was first
published abroad. The critic Alexander Voronsky
denounced it as a hostile caricature of com¬
munism. He could not have known of the sinister
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
-*rnk i ; i .i . i h i la n£ . i n i i.ax i,.y
Right, The Burial of the Cat
(1858), a lithograph in the
Russian folk art tradition
known as lubok. It is
thought by some to be a
representation of the burial of
Tsar Peter the Great by the
peasants.
Below, Multicephalic Machine
(1989), wood engraving by
Paul Kichilov.
HjrßfcMUUA II» AM
\l '.' 1 ii
A; AAHAUI
umrxy i-iiu.« h< rAt in in tait'.
!"l «'Uta ILh I IIIIIANA .MIKI'IUTA ¡l'A 'lUHUAÍ tí MWIIA-V.'. MHA» ¡MU tt/WM i-Vil' I i' 1, íl
Ai'TI'AKAHirA .VnAAMA KA.IANRA IWTÍi HAH;*. .MllMIM «ATA llf I I ».fcAAM fliAIIO HIJUVTA lll'Alh'JHAlM i: N>
' > rAi)*ii'ii :t . iatta limn Ki\|ii.h'ii »tu iha'iam mjMM niiau» ki'ohihh h llAVHlue
* llUA ' 1 HU« A.IIUA . ' lA-lA 1> UATI, HI A.I.ATI I, > I V li 1A||.H'IA l/.UAT|. AR1 HUM MNEATATA H NB
ka fwm« IMUHU IIWMH I* iciTi. m ry.h it imvnirii lin.lncTkli ftiucA.«;. HII"Iiaih.ma MPAFitAPAAlft wiLIKTiurr. Chopa .huiiiij
r'AKPA-MKA H-1AJULJJ0 ulwlfl'III.A n.llJI ia r ,i m VVKAIIA t'l rxil* ftAITI III I.Al'll.lll KftTA'fMtM'IA XIIA.IH.lll K.IMMIIW ,1/illMKA.IH IftAM« IIKJB"TA flan
HAJU lín* Mrm HAi.mnKA Himiiu uiuuuluvun ajviuh JIiijMIH.ma.iii ai ivlmuir :i>, iajw lim aA»I» HnT.vtjmKA rnrijiA It.lAn.MA 11.1,1.a IA
HiiBH'inTki m>lMíTA.lA mUHmrTM HnTAiptM'IA ¿hfma.ia TAHn mjilli.1 HUTA in.MHHA.IH «rnrprHHI. JnnHliA.III
I..., **j, »*;* BBTUfi ktfi »Jí i :i-i4i r" (* I;a,i t ¿
developments that would transform Zamyatin's
fiction into reality only ten or fifteen years later,
that Zamyatin would manage to emigrate, and
that he, Voronsky, would end his days in a prison
camp set up by Stalin's secret police, which bore
an astonishing resemblance to the Guardians
described in the novel.
Such a pessimistic view of man reduced to a
number is a grotesque exaggerationor is it? The
twentieth century, so rich in invention, has
brought several similar surprises. Signs of
Zamyatin's world can be seen wherever indepen¬
dent thought is suppressed, the individual is en¬
slaved, and people are trained like animals to
respond to a ringing bell. Have we not seen entire
nations seized by a paroxysm of admiration for
their "Benefactor", as Zamyatin calls him?
A wild hope
The Utopian writers of the 1920s were the chil¬
dren of their age. Their novels invariably begin
with the triumph of world revolution. Thus, in
one of the first Soviet Utopian novels, The Coming
World by Yakov Okunev (1923), two men wake
up 200 years into the future. What do they see?
"There are hardly any open spaces left on the
globe. As far as the eye can see there are streets,
gardens, squares, more streets.. .a boundless world
city." Okunev, like Odoyevsky, seems to view
nature as an enemy that should be conquered and 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
tamed. Today hardly anyone would be delighted
to see such a concrete jungle.
A similar picture emerges in V. Nikolsky's
A Thousand Years After (1926), which describes
the world of the thirtieth century as brighter,
cleaner and richer than ours, but containing
hardly anything that had not been imagined sixty
years before, except that in Nikolsky's world
everything is bigger, stronger, and faster. The
author extrapolates from the world he knows:
machines are as big as railway carriages or weigh
100 tons, a mine is 2,000 kilometres deep, and
an artificial satellite orbits the Earth.
In the early 1930s, when Stalin was fashioning
ideology with his callous hands, forecasts of the
future ceased to appear. From then on, those who
wrote about the future had to base their work
not on the study of real life or on their own fan¬
tasies but on prevailing ideological dogma, which
meant armed confrontation between socialism
and imperialism, with the former winning a quick
and easy victory.
A painful awakening
The appearance of Ivan Efremov's novel
Andromeda in 1957 is closely associated with the
reawakening of social consciousness that took
place after Stalin's death in 1953. Today it is
difficult to share Efremov's unflagging optimism
about the future of humanity, but his novel is
the most complete picture of communist society
in the history of Utopian thought. In fact Efremov
depicts a depoliticized society which has rid itself
of all kinds of oppression.
Perhaps the most attractive feature of the
society he describes is that it provides all its
members with an opportunity to fulfil them¬
selves, rather than providing guarantees of wel¬
fare or longevity.
Efremov depicts the world with more
warmth than his predecessors, and it is really pos¬
sible to conceive of living in it, which is more
than can be said for the sterile barracks described
by some of his predecessors. This is not to imply
that everything is perfecttoday's reader is sure
to note Efremov's indifference to ecological
problems. The threat to the environment escaped
the attention of most science fiction writers.
The utopia imagined by Efremov will prob¬
ably be the last to evoke a society of absolute har¬
mony and tranquillity. Efremov's euphoria soon
evaporated. His next novel about a distant future,
The Hour of Taurus, written only ten years later,
is filled with dark foreboding.
The highroad of history seems to have taken
an unexpected turning. But where is it leading?
The next generation of Utopian writers will have
plenty to think about.
BLUEPRINTS FOR AN
HiLlSTORICAL studies of plans for ideal cities
tend to be preoccupied with geometry and sym¬
metry: they are all square, circular, polygonal or
hexagonal. Aristophanes, in his play The Birds,
makes fun of the concept of geometric cities, of
Plato and his disciples and of all rigid planners
of other people's futures.
The recurrence of geometric plans in utopias
down the ages is partly explained, of course, by
the nature of the walled and fortified towns of
classical and medieval times, and partly by the
fact that all these schemes are what economists
would call "models" or what sociologists would
call "ideal types". If they were ever realized, they
would be modified to accommodate existing
physical features, artefacts and social institutions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
IDEAL COMMUNITY by colin ward
There was little recognition of this among
Utopians before the humanist writers of the
Renaissance.
The fifteenth-century Italian architect Leon
Battista Alberti, for example, did not attempt to
design an ideal city (although his projects include
an ideal Fortress for a Tyrant, in which the palace
is protected equally against the external and the
internal enemy). He insists that it is enough to
discover the principles that can be adapted to any
site and the needs of the citizens.
During the Renaissance Europeans began to
travel the world as a prelude to conquest and
exploitation. The tales they brought back
influenced a series of Utopian books. Thus the hero
of Thomas More's Utopia, Raphael Hythlodaye,
Left, Work, by the English artist
Ford Madox Brown (1821-1893).
Above, 19th-century depiction of a phalanx,
the ideal community advocated
by the French social theorist Charles Fourier,
who was inspired by Renaissance images
of utopia.
is cast as a Portuguese sailor from the crew which
sailed with the explorer Amerigo Vespucci.
More's book, written in Latin, takes the form
of a discussion in the garden of a house in Ant¬
werp, between himself, Raphael Hythlodaye and
a Flemish friend, Peter Gilles. Hythlodaye
. remarks that life is fairer in the island of Utopia,
where property is owned by the community,
than in the England of their day.
To prove his point, he describes the common¬
wealth of Utopia. Particular attention is given to
the architecture and planning of Utopian cities:
"Their buildings are good, and are so uniform,
that a whole side of a street looks like one house.
The streets are twenty feet broad; there lie
gardens behind all their houses. ..every house has
both a door to the street and a back door to the
garden.... There being no property among them,
every man may freely enter into any house what¬
soever. At least every ten years they shift their
houses by lots."
In More's ideal city everybody understands
farming. Children learn it at school and in visits
to the country. Everyone turns out to help at har¬
vest time. If the population of any city grows,
they do not build over the gardens, but "fill up
the lack in other cities", or "build up a town in
the next land where the inhabitants have much
waste and unoccupied ground".
Utopian writing of the European Enlighten¬
ment in the eighteenth century also used stories
of the exploration of unknown regions as a device
to criticize the familiar world of the European
states. Even before Australia was "discovered" 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
h n n iizn
by voyagers, the French writer Gabriel de Foigny
published New Discovery of Terra Incognita Aus-
trails (1676). He was the first Utopian to conceive
of a society without government. Following the
French navigator Louis-Antoine de Bougainville's
exploration of the islands of Oceania in the 1760s,
Denis Diderot wrote his delightful Supplement to
Bougainville's Voyage. Published posthumously,
after the French Revolution, it consists of an
imaginary conversation between an old man from
Tahiti, who describes the freedom and plenty that
existed before the Europeans came, and a French
sailor who tells him of the misery of the poor
in pre-revolutionary France.
Worlds of industrial plenty
The nineteenth century changed everything,
including utopias. The steam engine, iron and
steel, the railway, the factory system and the huge
growth of towns and cities all led to Utopian
writing which projected the pace of industriali¬
zation into the future. In 1816 the philosopher
and economist Claude-Henri de Saint-Simon was
already predicting that France and its population
would be organized as one vast factory. Later
in the century, in The Coming Race: or the New
Utopia (1870), Lord Lytton foresaw a future
in which machinery and robots would be
powered by a new form of energy called vril.
This was followed by another widely read
industrial utopia by the American writer Edward
Bellamy, Looking Backward (1888), in which
the hero awakens from a hypnotic state in
the year 2000. His host explains what has
happened:
"The movement toward the conduct of bus¬
iness by larger and larger aggregations of capital,
the tendency towards monopolies, which has
been so desperately and vainly resisted, was recog-
XT
\festerday
tiring uní/ Working in the Smokt.
To-day
- :,;: ..... ' '.
uSaÈrWSi: - ,
..i ;-
living m l/tt Subiiili v IMin¡¡ m /At- Jknt*.
To-morrow
U v/rtfi* Uivtjrjp? ttti/teStmui »7
-
36 Ti» " "~~n~rr -tin-n-T
Publicity poster produced in
1921 was designed to attract
people to the new garden city
at Welwyn, Hertfordshire (UK).
It contrasts the industrial city
with the modern suburb and
shows the garden city as a
natural progression.
nized at last, in its true significance, as a process
which only needed to complete its logical evolu¬
tion to open a golden future to humanity....
When the nation became the sole employer, all
the citizens, by virtue of their citizenship, became
employees, to be distributed according to the
needs of industry...."
The optimistic scientific utopias of the
nineteenth century gave rise to a whole genre of
deeply pessimistic anti-utopian literature in the
twentieth: savage satires on the trends of indus¬
trial society by such writers as H.G. Wells,
George Orwell and Yevgeny Zamyatin.
A simpler life
There also arose in the 1890s a stream of alterna¬
tive Utopian thinking, looking towards what we
would now call a post-industrial, ecologically
viable human society.
The English poet and craftsman William
Morris was so outraged by Edward Bellamy's
vision of the world as one vast factory that he
wrote a history of the future that he wanted. In
News from Nowhere, the author awakens in a
future England which has abandoned not only
factories but government and money too. It has
become a nation of craft workers, delighting in
making beautiful things, whose idea of a holiday
is to row up the river to work in the fields at har¬
vest time. The "big murky places which were
once the centres of manufacture" have disap¬
peared, and the ecological change in the human
environment is the result of a change in the pur¬
pose of work.
Citizens of the future explain to the time-
travelling Morris: "The wares which we make are
made because they are needed; men make for
their neighbour's use as if they are making for
themselves, not for a vague market of which they
know nothing, and over which they have no con¬
trol.... Nothing can be made except for genuine
use; therefore no inferior goods are made.
Moreover, as we have now found out what we
want, so we make no more than we want; and
as we are not driven to make a vast quantity of
useless things, we have time and resources enough
to consider our pleasure in making them. All
work which would be irksome to do by hand is
done by immensely improved machinery; and in
all work which it is a pleasure to do by hand,
machinery is done without...."
Two contemporaries of Morris also had an
immense concern for the details of productive
work and the decentralization of human settle¬
ments. Peter Kropotkin, a Russian geographer
and anarchist, argues in favour of mixing factory
work with farm work, brain work with manual
work, and town jobs with country jobs, in his
Fields, Factories and Workshops (1899).
Looking at the enormous productivity of
small workshops and horticulture as opposed to
large-scale industry and farming, Kropotkin
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Ce>Z0SSOI STslTÏ7J5<i/"Jf0tr2fT\ATIfO$ s*rr7¡uC.
* StiJtrtt nÀ/'t/t mmS fa fatt sr<-*rt>/f /<'>/ /4<- n-n/crf/uif /¿¡t/t,//f\>tM Mr fap efmr /turn/tAurtt/fvm.rvútfirtM ¡ù*/ut/. *'- MP A' yíír* Jfrvr */ // ïw 4' /*/// MrlM fl <r¿y /?*st- tM
ÉMÉMU.Ml.t^l^l^l^MáHdhlllMMÍHII.^fiáÉni
The Greek architect
Dinocrates (died c. 278 BC) ¡s
best known as the designer of
the Egyptian city of
Alexandria. This English
engraving illustrates his
project to carve Mount Athos
into a colossal statue of
Alexander the Great. Water
from the mountain was to
flow into a basin held in one
hand of the statue before
running through a city on its
way to the sea.
claims that the future lies with the dispersal of
both. The significance of this book, which gives
it relevance almost a century later, is that it is a
plea for "a new economy in the energies used in
supplying the needs of human life, since these
needs are increasing and the energies are not
inexhaustible".
Another Utopian contemporary of Morris
was an obscure English inventor and shorthand
writer, Ebenezer Howard. The question he asked
himself was very simple. How can we solve the
problems of desperate overcrowding in the
metropolitan city, with all the human misery it
produces, and at the same time cope with the
depopulation of rural areas from which the young
and active escape precisely because of the lack of
opportunities?
Howard's answer was the garden city. His
book Garden Cities of Tomorrow (1898) advocates
a network of planned small towns, providing
homes and employment and incorporating
agriculture with industrial work, surrounded by
a green belt, and linked by public transport to
form a "Social City". It was very influential in
the ideology of town and country planning.
Howard himself founded two garden cities in the
United Kingdom, Letchworth and Welwyn
Garden City, and his work inspired the British
government's New Towns programme after the
Second World War.
Ecological Utopian thinking
There is an extraordinary gap between the widely
read Utopian writings of the 1890s and the new
environmental, ecological awareness that emerged
in the 1970s, with its consciousness of the finite
nature of the world's resources and the terrifying
rate at which they are being exhausted. Few Uto¬
pians have explored the implications of an eco¬
logically aware civilization.
One notable exception is the American
science fiction writer Ursula Le Guin. Her novel
The Dispossessed (1974) presents the experiences
of a visitor from one planet, where a Kropot-
kinian ethic of mutual aid has won a viable
society from an arduous environment, to another
planet where society is built upon self-indulgent
consumerism. Another American novel, Ernest
Callebach's Ecotopia (1975), carefully examines
the dilemmas which would face a society which
attempts to adopt a green or ecologically aware
ideology.
One book that I would like to put into the 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
.1 » IT ITT
i %
' I
V(/*iGIH<¡ OKU**
t Ö - , K, o_ «ttlAMAk "..».Kr
.«(»15 f>US«lAr
^.* .tt co-OPieA« V>..
ïkaSÀâôi»«
m
n
/
i
f.
í
H
H
T«SM AW.»AH
Totvoi^jn-j,
-i. *,.
I
/
/'
/
I
!
H»A«,H*«*A»'-" -
IJ^.' "
».».. . 	 - . ».«"^
lAHIKi »luí
Í*\ÍI*(* «0i«V-
(OiTHMr
hands of anyone interested in the connections
between utopia, architecture and ecological cons¬
ciousness is an older American exploration of Uto¬
pian imaginings. This is Communitas: Means of
Livelihood and Ways of Life (1947) by Paul and
Percival Goodman. They were brothers, a poet
and an architect, and they compiled this book
during the Second World War as a modest and
dissident contribution to the worldwide debate
"post-war reconstruction". Numerous workson
38
of this kind were produced in many countries,
most of which have been completely forgotten.
Communitas survives because, as the philosopher
Lewis Mumford put it, it is the only modern con¬
tribution to the art of building cities which "deals
with the underlying values and purposes, polit¬
ical and moral, on which planning of any sort
must be based".
The Goodman brothers saw a "community
plan" not as a layout of streets and houses, but
as the external form given to human activity:
"There is a variety of town schemes: gridirons,
radiations, ribbons, satellites, or vast concentra¬
tions; what is important is the activity going on,
how it is influenced by the scheme and how it
transforms any schemes, and uses or abuses any
site, to its own work and values."
Their book examines the three main types
of city plan which had emerged in the previous
hundred years, grouping them into Green Belt
Plans, Industrial Plans and Integrated Plans. They
see the first as a reaction against the ugliness and
squalor of the factory systemattempts to
recreate pre-industrial values, or to live decently
with industry. Next they turn to city plans
centred on production, with an absorbing discus¬
sion of forgotten urban utopias dreamed about
in the Soviet Union in the 1920s, and of the tech¬
nological solutions appropriate to an advanced
economy put forward by the American engineer
Buckminster Fuller. His "Dymaxion" house,
conceived in 1929-1932, was based on the mass
production of lightweight self-sufficient houses
which did not require public utilities, but did
Bibliography for Three Ways
of Life Today, by Paul and
Percival Goodman:
IEfficient Consumption;
IIElimination of the
difference between production
and consumption;
III Maximum Security,
Minimum Regulation.
COLIN WARD
is a British author whose many
books include Anarchy in
Action (1973), The Child in the
City (1978), Arcadia for All
(1984) and Welcome, Thinner
City (1989).
depend on an industrial system in the back¬
ground.
Finally the Goodmans examine those Utopian
plans which integrate city and country, such as
American architect Frank Lloyd Wright's dream
of Broadacre City where the whole population
is dispersed over the entire countryside and
dependent on small farming and vaguely decen¬
tralized industry. This formula was more effec¬
tively argued for many years by another
American, Ralph Borsodi, who declared that by
cutting out the costs of transportation and mar¬
keting and a host of middlemen, at least two-
thirds of the goods and services required in a
home could be more efficiently produced domes¬
tically with electrically powered tools.
Yet the brothers were sternly realistic. They
had the honesty to emphasize, rather than
minimize, the fact that we all have different Uto¬
pian dreams. Aware that someone's utopia is
someone else's hell, they arrived at three quite
different formulae for ideal communities.
The first is the City of Efficient Consump¬
tion, which can be recognized in most European
or American cities today. The second, the New
Commune, is an idealized version of the small
workshop economy that actually sustains the
Italian region of Emilia-Romagna today.
The third, in which they envisage a two-level
economy, they call Maximum Security:
Minimum Regulation. Everyone would be
obliged to work for a short time (as in military
conscription) in a basic economy, attending the
machines which provide food, clothing and
shelter, distributed free to all. The rest of the time
would be occupied in a luxury economy in which
the choice of activity is left to the individual.
Needs such as medicine and transport would be
taken care of by a financial arrangement between
the subsistence economy and the secondary
economy. This solution may well prove instruc¬
tive to politicians seeking to resolve the contradic¬
tions between the ideology of a welfare state and
the virtues of a free market.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
A UTOPIA
OUR TIMES?
NON-STOP LEARNING
BY GILBERT LECLERC
A radical approach
to education as a
means to the
complete fulfilment
of the individual
I
Socrates Teaching Children,
oil on canvas by the Italian
artist Pier Francesco Mola
(1612-1666).
S the idea of lifelong education Utopian? Partly
it is a matter of definition. Strictly speaking, the
only projects that qualify to be called Utopian are
those that envisage a new world radically different
from our own, based on aims and values entirely
different from those of the established order and
drawing on a common will for change. Absolute
otherness is the hallmark of -utopia.
So to answer the question we must find out
whether or not the concept of an educational
experience stretching from the cradle to the grave
implies the complete transformation of present-
day education and whether or not it presupposes
a new model of society.
The fact is that lifelong education involves
a great deal more than a learning experience
lasting from infancy into old age. It also embraces
the idea that education should no longer be exclu¬
sively confined to schools. Instead it should
embrace all of lifework, leisure, the environ¬
ment, family, job, society, international relations.
It requires that people should become their own
teachers so as to realize their full intellectual, emo¬
tional and artistic potential. And it demands that
in this quest everyone should have an equal
chance of success.
In this new view of education, every aspect
of a person's life has some educational sig¬
nificance. The whole panoply of educational
resources must be available to all, so every
individual can attain his or her full potential.
This last objective is of central importance
for all the pioneers of the new philosophy, and
particularly those who have worked with Unesco
in this field. Lifelong education seeks nothing less
than the complete transformation of the
experience of learning, which it attempts to
expand to its uttermost limits in time, space,
and the social arena. It aims to replace a part-time
and compartmentalized system with one that is
both continuous and integrated. Under its aegis,
every aspect of peoples' existence would be
open to the lessons of a world in which educa¬
tion is omnipresent. The theory demands a
completely new perspective. Opened up in all
directions, the horizons of education become
almost limitless.
The idea, then, is certainly revolutionary in
its educational implications, but does it presup¬
pose a social transformation of similar scope?
Once again its proponents would answer "yes".
A society genuinely dedicated to education in its
widest sense requires both new structures and
altered ways of thinking. Such a commitment
would not be compatible with a profit-oriented
consumer society. Nor would it sit easily with
a technocratic world in which knowledge is the
restricted property of specialists, or with a
bureaucratic society that tends to obfuscate the
ways in which it is run.
So by its very nature the concept of lifelong
education would seem to be Utopian. The old
ideal of an education fulfilling all aspirations and
developing every potential has doubtless never
before been pushed so far. It is hardly surprising, 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Above, mature students at a
Paris university.
Below, "At School", a plate
from a set of colour
lithographs entitled fn the
Year 2000 (French, early
20th century).
GILBERT LECLERC,
of Canada, is head of the
research and development of
lifelong education at the
University of Sherbrooke,
Quebec. The author of a
number of articles on Utopian
thinking, he has also
published, with Guy Bouchard
and Laurent Giroux, a book
entitled L'utopie aujourd'hui
(Presses Universitaires de
Montréal, 1985).
then, that it has induced thousands of men and
women to try to construct a new world.
Although it is only thirty years since it was first
formulated, this dream has already inspired
countless projects and experiments in many parts
of the world, and in so doing has played an
important role in the development of contem¬
porary education.
It is the fate of utopias, though, never to be
realized in full. Whenever enthusiasts have tried
to transplant their vision from the written page
to the real world, whether by democratic or by
revolutionary means, they have either been mar¬
ginalized or forced to compromise to some degree
with the existing systemalways assuming that
they have not simply had to give up. In one sense,
then, the history of utopia is an unbroken
sequence of failures, for the dreamed-of perfect
society has never been brought to fruition.
From another point of view, though, its pages
are studded with success, if one considers the
untold number of genuine, practical achievements
that the Utopian vision has inspired. Viewed in
this light, utopia appears less as a blueprint for
action than as a motive force that, by creating
new horizons for social progress, has the power
to get history under way. And if human destiny
is so rich in potential, it is because the deepest
truths about mankind and society cry out for an
imagined world that cannot be found in a
revamped version of the existing one.
Human activity only takes on its full sig¬
nificance if it can be conceived of as an incessant
search for totalization. People have always held
before them as a beacon a vision of some state
or condition that would lead them away from the
particular and towards the totality of experience.
Inevitably they have drawn inspiration from the
imaginary, since the condition they seek does not
yet exist; insofar as it is not simply a variant on
existing conditions, it is necessarily Utopian,
which is to say radically other. No genuinely
innovatory change is possible without this
visionary dimension.
As education is particularly concerned with
the totalization of experience and with the ful¬
filment of human potential, it is bound to feed
on utopias. Without them it would be caught in
a vicious circle of repetition and stereotypes.
Need one add, then, that a Utopian approach to
education is just as essential as a scientific
approach? Imagination and reason both have a
part to play in shaping tomorrow's education.
The role of the imagination is to come up with
new models, better adapted than existing ones to
the individual's changing needs. Reason must test
these visions and put into action those that are
viable. The road to reality must pass through the
creative imagination.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT A PLANETARY UTOPIA
BY JULIAN HUXLEY
In 1946 the British
scientist and
humanist Julian
Huxley (d. 1975),
soon to be Unesco's
first Director-General,
wrote a long paper
entitled Unesco, its
purpose and its
philosophy, in
which he set forth
guidelines for the
new organization.
The document was
highly controversial.
it was regarded by
some as an attack
on religion, by others
as pro-communist.
Eventually Unesco's
General Conference
refused to sponsor
its publication. Over
forty years later,
Huxley's "planetary
utopia" has lost none
of its force or
topicality. Published
below are salient
extracts.
IN general, Unesco must constantly be testing
its policies against the touchstone of evolutionary
progress. A central conflict of our times is that
between nationalism and internationalism, be¬
tween the concept of many national sovereignties
and one world sovereignty. Here the evolutionary
touchstone gives an unequivocal answer. The key
to man's advance, the distinctive method which
has made evolutionary progress in the human sec¬
tor so much more rapid than in the biological and
has given it higher and more satisfying goals, is the
fact of cumulative tradition, the existence of a
common pool of ideas which is self-perpetuating
and itself capable of evolving. And this fact has
had the immediate consequence of making the
type of social organization the main factor in hu¬
man progress or at least its limiting framework.
Two obvious corollaries follow. First, that the
more united man's tradition becomes, the more
rapid will be the possibility of progress: several
separate or competing or even mutually hostile
pools of tradition cannot possibly be so efficient
as a single pool common to all mankind. And
secondly, that the best and only certain way of
securing this will be through political unification.
As history shows, unifying ideas can exert an
effect across national boundaries. But, as history
makes equally evident, that effect is a partial one
and never wholly offsets the opportunities for
conflict provided by the existence of separate
sovereign political units.
The moral for Unesco is clear. The task laid
upon it of promoting peace and security can never
be wholly realized through the means assigned
to iteducation, science and culture. It must en¬
visage some form of world political unity, whether
through a single world government or otherwise,
as the only certain means for avoiding war.
However, world political unity is, unfor¬
tunately, a remote ideal, and in any case does not
fall within the field of Unesco's competence. This
does not mean that Unesco cannot do a great deal
towards promoting peace and security. Specifi¬
cally, in its education programme it can stress the
ultimate need for world political unity and
familiarize all peoples with the implications of
the transfer of full sovereignty from separate
nations to a world organization.
But, more generally, it can do a great deal to
lay the foundations on which world political
unity can later be built. It can help the peoples
of the world to mutual understanding and to a
realization of the common humanity and
common tasks which they share, as opposed to
the nationalisms which too often tend to isolate
and separate them. (...)
Our evolutionary analysis shows clearly
enough that a well-developed human individual
is the highest product of evolution to date. This
provides external and scientific support for the
democratic principle of the dignity of men, to
which by its Constitution Unesco is committed.
It also constitutes a complete disproof of all
theses, like those of Hegelian philosophy, of fas¬
cism, or of nazism, which maintain that the state
is in some way higher than the individual, and
that the individual exists only or primarily for
the state.
On the other hand, we have been brought
to realize that the evolution of man, though a
natural continuation of that of the rest of life, is
quite a different process, operating by the essen¬
tially social method of cumulative tradition, and
manifesting itself primarily in the development
of societies, instead of in the genetic nature of the
individuals composing them. And this at once
makes it equally obvious that the opposed thesis
of unrestricted individualism is equally erroneous.
The human individual is, quite simply,
meaningless in isolation; he only acquires sig¬
nificance in relation to some form of society. His
development is conditioned by the society into 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
which he is born and the social traditions which
he inherits; and the value of the work he does
in life depends on the social framework which
benefits by it or transmits it to later time.
Thus Unesco's activities, while concerned
primarily with providing richer development and
fuller satisfactions for the individual, must always
be undertaken in a social context; and many of
its specific tasks will be concerned with the social
means towards this general end the improve¬
ment of social mechanisms or agencies, such as
educational systems, research organizations, art
centres, the press, and so forth.
In particular, Unesco must clearly pay special
attention to the social mechanism of cumulative
tradition in all its aspects, with the aim of ensur¬
ing that it is both efficient and rightly directed
in regard to its essential function of promoting
human evolution.
The unifying of traditions in a single com¬
mon pool of experience, awareness, and purpose
is the necessary prerequisite for further major
progress in human evolution. Accordingly,
although political unification in some sort of
world government will be required for the defini
tive attainment of this stage, unification in the
things of the mind is not only also necessary but
can pave the way for other types of unification.
Thus in the past the great religions unified
the thoughts and attitudes of large regions of the
Earth's surface; and in recent times science, both
directly through its ideas and indirectly through
its applications in shrinking the globe, has been
a powerful factor in directing men's thoughts to
the possibilities of, and the need for, full world
unity.
Special attention should consequently be
given by Unesco to the problem of constructing
a unified pool of tradition for the human species
as a whole. This, as indicated elsewhere, must in¬
clude the unity-in-variety of the world's art and
culture as well as the promotion of one single
pool of scientific knowledge.
But it must also eventually include a unified
common outlook and a common set of purposes.
This will be the latest part of the task of unify¬
ing the world mind; but Unesco must not neglect
it while engaged on the easier jobs, like that of
promoting a single pool of scientific knowledge
and effort.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
The Great Wall
lengthens
Chinese archaeologists say
they have discovered a new
section of the Great Wall of
China. Until recently the
5,000-km-long Wall was
thought to end near the
coastal town of Shanhaiguan
in northern China's Hebei
province. The archaeologists
now claim that a 1,000-km-
long M-shaped section of the
Wall stretches through
Liaoning province as far as
the city of Dandong.
Epidemic takes toll
of Mediterranean dolphins
The dolphin population of the
western Mediterranean is
dying at an alarming rate. In a
two-week period during the
summer of 1990, 50 dead
dolphins were found on
French beaches alone, as
many as are usually found in a
year. The toll in Spain was up
to 250 in less than 3 months.
Laboratory tests showed that
the deaths were due to the
same type of virus that killed
some 20,000 North Sea seals
in 1988. Autopsies also
showed that the dolphins'
tissues are contaminated
with metals and toxic
chemicals. Their immune
systems weakened, the
dolphins become more
vulnerable to disease.
The Mediterranean is now so
polluted that many marine
mammals are at risk.
Waste not
The members of the European
Economic Community (EEC)
have decided to stabilize by
the year 2000 emissions of
carbon dioxide, the gas
mainly responsible for the
greenhouse effect, at 1990
levels. Another important
recent measure to protect the
environment was the adoption
by 64 leading industrial
nations of a proposal from
the Nordic countries
(Denmark, Finland, Iceland,
Norway and Sweden) to halt
within 5 years all disposal of
industrial waste at sea and
to encourage its recycling or
treatment.
Galactic giant
American astronomers have
identified the biggest
galaxy yet known. Located at
the centre of a cluster of
galaxies known as
Abell 2029, it is 60 times
bigger than our Milky Way
galaxy. With a diameter of 6
million light-years, it contains
1,000 billion stars whereas
our galaxy contains
barely 2 billion. The previous
record was held by the
Markarian 348 galaxy,
which is 1.3 million light-years
in diameter.
Giacometti at Madrid
The Centro de Arte Reina
Sofia in Madrid has reopened
its doors after a facelift.
Housed in a 6-storey
building that was a hospital
in the 18th century,
the museum seeks to be a
beacon for 20th-century
Spanish art, much as the
Prado Museum
is a showcase for older art
treasures. As well as housing
its own 13,000-piece
collection of modern Spanish
art, it will put on temporary
exhibitions. From November
1990 to January 1991
it held a major retrospective
of Alberto Giacometti,
with some 300 sculptures,
paintings and drawings.
The Madrid exhibition
gave a foretaste of Giacometti
exhibitions to be held
in Paris and Zurich later
this year, the 25th anniversary
of the great Swiss artist's
death.
Climate change and
agriculture
Possible climate warming
may have a severe impact on
world agriculture and increase
the risk to food supplies in
many countries already
suffering from hunger and
malnutrition in regions
such as Central America,
Africa and Southeast Asia.
In these regions agricultural
yields could drop by
25%, producing a 20% rise in
the cost of major food
products on world markets,
warns Dr. Martin Parry of
the University of Birmingham
(UK), who led the agricultural
impact assessment conducted
by the Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate Change
(IPCC). His report, Climate
Change and World Agriculture,
prepared for the United
Nations Environment
Programme and the
International Institute for
Applied Systems Analysis,
is available from Earthscan
Publications, London
(1990).
Columbus was here
The 500th anniversary of
Christopher Columbus's
arrival in the Americas will be
commemorated in 1992.
Archaeologists excavating the
site where Columbus and his
men founded a colony, at La
Isabela, in what is now the
Dominican Republic, have
identified the stone
foundations of the
settlement's main buildings,
which include a large
storehouse, watch tower and
sentry posts, a powder house,
hospital, church and
cemetery, and what was
probably Columbus's house.
They have also unearthed a
large quantity of mercury,
which the Spaniards
had brought for separating
from the mineral matrix the
pure gold they had hoped to
find in abundance.
Plants galore
The colossal task of preparing
a computerized catalogue of
the world's plants was
launched at an international
conference of botanists held
at the Royal Botanic Gardens,
Kew (UK), last November.
Some 250,000 plant
species are known today, a
massive increase on the
8,000 classified and
described by the great
Swedish naturalist Carl von
Linné (Linnaeus) in the
18th century.
A leap backward
Until recently palaeontologists
believed that the first
aquatic animals which
left the water to colonize the
land did so some 400 million
years ago. However, three
British geologists working
near Ludlow, Shropshire,
have now discovered the
remains of the carapaces,
legs and antennae of
centipedes and of a spider¬
like creature which are
414 million years old. These
animals were already
perfectly adapted to
terrestrial life, which implies
that the first terrestrial fauna
must have appeared much
earlier, perhaps as long as
470 million years ago.
Unesco prizes
for Vaclav Havel
In 1990 Vaclav Havel,
President of the Czech and
Slovak Federal Republic,
was the recipient of two
Unesco awards. On 21
November Federico Mayor,
the Director-General of
Unesco, presented him with
the International Simón
Bolívar Prize, rewarding
"activity of outstanding merit
which has contributed
to the freedom, independence
and dignity of peoples
and to the strengthening
of a new international
economic, social and cultural
order". On 10 December,
the anniversary of the
Universal Declaration of
Human Rights, Mr. Havel
was awarded the 1990
Unesco Prize for the Teaching
of Human Rights.
Aid for tropical forests
Germany is to finance an
inter-regional co-operation
project for the protection
of tropical forests. An
agreement to this effect
was drawn up in October
1990 under the auspices of
Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) programme.
The two-year, million-dollar
project will be implemented by
Unesco in Africa, Latin
America and Asia. Its goal is
to develop local knowledge
and competence in order to
tap natural resources without
destroying them, and to
ensure the better spread of
technical and scientific
information.
IN BRIEF IN BRIEF. . . IN BRIEF. . .
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
N
IMAGINARY CITIES
BY CRISTINA GRAU
IVL
44
Iany famous writers have por¬
trayed city life. They have taken over
real cities and transformed them into
literary objects and they have creat¬
ed imaginary cities with lives of their
own. They have reconstructed urban
settings from scattered fragments of
memory, and have brought fame to
cities that were previously unknown.
A stroll through the urban land¬
scapes of literature reveals a vari¬
ety of creations: cities depicted with
a high degree of realism, cities in the
abstract, cities which merely provide
background atmosphere, and cities
which are themselves protagonists in
works of fiction.
The realistic city
Joyce's Dublin, Proust's Paris, Kaf¬
ka's Prague, and the Buenos Aires of
Borges are realistically depicted ci¬
ties which help to shape the course
of the fictional events which take
place in them.
Although Kafka rarely refers to
Prague In his novels and short sto¬
ries, his native city has a very spe¬
cial place in them. Prague is never
actually named in The Trial, for ex¬
ample, but the meandering corridors
and passages, the disconnected set¬
tings through which Joseph K.
wanders in an attempt to find out
why he is being tried, evoke the at¬
mosphere of Gothic Prague and the
labyrinth of narrow streets in its Jew¬
ish district.
The city is seen as if in a dream or
through the mists of memory, in
black and white, with the contrasts
of light and shadow that appear in Ex¬
pressionist films. The impression of
being in a dream is reinforced by
topological distortions (as when
something distant suddenly seems
very near, and vice versa) and by
changes of scale which make space
seem to expand or contract, depend¬
ing on K.'s state of mind. The vision
of reality is phantasmagoric.
The building in which K.'s trial is
to be held "was of unusual extent,
the main entrance was particularly
high", but when K. enters it he gets
lost in a maze of corridors, landings,
stairways and empty roomsit is
more like a tenement than a law
court. On another occasion, K. opens
the door of a lumber-room in the
bank where he works and "finds him¬
self suddenly in the court precincts".
In his story Amerika, Kafka depicts
New York, where he never set foot,
as an abstract, futuristic version of
Prague. The outstanding features are
the towering skyscrapers and geo¬
metric layout that differentiate it
most strongly from his native city,
with its labyrinth of winding streets
Capriccio (1795) by William Marlow.
and alleyways. When Karl, the hero
of the story, leans over the balcony
of his uncle's New York house (a bal¬
cony is not exactly typical of New
York buildings), he is fascinated by
the sight of the street which "ran per¬
fectly straight between two rows of
squarely chopped buildings and
therefore seemed to be fleeing into
the distance". Here too, the city is
perceived in monochrome. Despite
the crowds and the skyscrapers, Kaf¬
ka's imaginary New York does not ex¬
ist except in terms of Prague, which
he uses as a kind of blueprint.
The camouflaged
city
Many cities in literature are inspired
by real cities whose names are
changed, perhaps because the
author wishes to eliminate local
colour, to conceal the true identity
of the characters, or simply wants a
better-sounding name than the origi¬
nal. But even under its new name,
the real city can still be seen beneath
the camouflage. Vetusta, the setting
of The Regent's Wife by the Spanish
novelist Clarín (Leopoldo Alas) is a
faithful reflection of the Spanish city
of Oviedo. What is most memorable
in Clarin's description is the sense of
space which can be felt from the very
first chapter in which a priest climbs
to the top of the cathedral bell-tower
to spy through a telescope on the
comings and goings of parishioners
who reveal their sins to him in the
confessional.
The little town of llliers near
Chartres (south of Paris) was immor¬
talized as Combray in Proust's A la
recherche du temps perdu and is
now officially known as llliers-
Combray. The fictional town is so
skilfully superimposed on the real
town that a visitor to llliers who has
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
read Swann's Way, the first part of
Proust's great novel, has no difficulty
in recognizing the setting of the prin¬
cipal scenes Aunt Leonie's house,
the church of Saint-Hilaire, the main
square, the château of Tansonville,
the Pré Catelan. Stone by stone,
street by street, llliers coincides ex¬
actly with Combray.
The imaginary city
A city cannot be created out of noth¬
ing. The ostensibly imaginary cities
of literature are actually an amalgam
of fragments of cities which the
writer has known. As a rule it is im¬
possible to identify these hetero¬
geneous monsters.
The mythical city of Santa Maria is
a thread that runs through the work
of the Uruguayan writer Juan Carlos
Onettl and gives it unity and univer¬
sality. The city is never far from the
thoughts of his characters. As a
result of Onetti's desire to eliminate
anecdotal details and references to
existing places, Santa Maria could be
any provincial city on the banks of a
river, with low-roofed houses, a
resplendent new hotel and a plaza
bordered with arcades. Argentine
and Uruguayan readers may be
tempted to identify the river as the
Above, Metropolis
(1916) by George Grosz.
Below, The Thermae of Titus,
engraving by Piranesi (18th century).
Río de la Plata and Santa Maria as the
city of Colonia, if they try to relate
Onetti's laconic, even contradictory,
indications to their own memories
and experiences.
In Onetti's novel A Brief Life, lor ex¬
ample, there is a reference to "a
broad river, a narrow river, a solitary
and threatening river, in which clouds
heavy with torment were reflected".
These contradictions introduce an
element of ambiguity which allows
the river of Santa Maria to be identi¬
fied with all rivers. The descriptions
of the city are always very general
and appeal to other senses than that
of sight, as if to blur the contours of
objects: "It came to me like a per¬
fume, an aroma that I had long ago
inhaled in a confused impression of
streets, compost, ivy, an image of a
tennis court and of a lantern sway¬
ing at the corner of a street."
As "a city hemmed in by a river and
a colony of Swiss settlers", Santa
Maria seems to have precise bound¬
aries, unlike Gabriel García Márquez's
fictional Colombian township of
Macondo, which is presented at
different times as a large hacienda,
a village or an entire kingdom, with
no temporal continuity. Since there
is no single narrator, Macondo ap¬
pears as each person sees it or wish¬
es to see it.
In García Márquez's novel One
Hundred Years of Solitude, the logic
of space and time is often violated
as near merges with far, the order of
events is mixed up, and the passage
of time is slowed down or speeded
up. And In the story entitled Big Ma¬
ma's Funeral, where the Supreme
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
Pontiff, on his way to the funeral in
Macondo, glides in his long black
gondola past the famous sights of
Rome (mixed up with those of
Venice), García Márquez abruptly
writes: "At dusk the resonant peal¬
ing of St. Peter's Basilica mingled
with the cracked tinklings of Macon¬
do." But the Pope does not arrive in
Macondo in his gondola, but In a ca¬
noe loaded with yuccas, bananas and
chickens.
The township of Cómala in the
works of the Mexican writer Juan Rtil-
fo, and the City of the Immortals in
the works of Jorge Luis Borges, are
two sides of the same coin, nightmar¬
ish places inhabited by the dead or
by those unable to die.
Cómala is a place of memory and
dreams, haunted by all those who
have lived there and by the dreams
they have dreamed. To read Rulfo's
Pedro Páramo is to be assailed by im¬
ages of the ghost towns of the Ameri¬
can West. Abandoned like the mines
which made them rich, they have the
surrealist appeal of Giorgio de Chiri-
co's paintings of plazas where there
is no human presence, only marble
statues or tailor's dummies. The
equally uninhabited City of the Im¬
mortals described by Borges in his
story The Immortal is situated on the
banks of a river which grants immor¬
tality to those who bathe in it.
The narrator, a Roman tribune ar¬
riving at the end of a long and ardu¬
ous journey, like that of the mythical
heroes Gilgamesh and Achilles,
describes his first contact with the
city in the following terms: "I began
to glimpse capitals and astragals, tri¬
angular pediments and vaults, con¬
fused pageants of granite and
marble." This architecture, arranged
in a disorderly and chaotic manner
In a labyrinthine structure, consti-
Above, The Great Metaphysician
(1949), by Giorgio de Chirico.
Below, View of the Ideal City.
Italian, 15th century.
tutes the city: "In the palace I imper¬
fectly explored, the architecture
lacked any finality."
This boundless, chaotic, disorder¬
ly, unpopulated city appears to be the
work of immortal builders or dement¬
ed gods. With its magnificent ar¬
chitecture completely divorced from
anything on a human scale, it evokes
the precincts of a Roman forum, the
classical fantasies of a Piranesi en¬
graving, or cities like Petra which
have been abandoned for unknown
reasons.
Borges has said that his vision of
the City of the Immortals was in¬
spired by the tombs in La Recoleta
cemetery in Buenos Aires, small tem
ples that bear no resemblance, if only
because of their scale, to the place
which the reader sees through the
eyes of the Roman tribune: "This City
(I thought) is so horrible that its mere
existence and perdurance, though in
the midst of a secret desert, con¬
taminates the past and the future
and in some way even jeopardizes
the stars."
A dusty and sordid city-cemetery,
an infinite marmoreal city-
cemeterytwo mythical and equal¬
ly monstrous places.
The invisible city
In Invisible Cities, the Italian writer
Italo Calvino adopts a different ap
proach to the city, which becomes
the protagonist of his story. The book
is meant to be an account of the trav¬
els of the Venetian explorer Marco
Polo to the cities of Kublai Khan's
empire. The exoticism of the narra¬
tive can be felt in the very names of
the cities Maurilia, Despina, Zirma,
Tamara descriptions of which, al¬
ternating with meetings between
Marco Polo and the Great Khan and
the asides of Calvino himself, dis¬
orientate the reader who has the im¬
pression that this is a travel book
rather than a work of fiction. In this
way the reader is gradually made to
understand that these apparently re¬
mote and fabulous cities are actual¬
ly the cities of our everyday lives.
After Marco Polo has described at
length the many cities of the Empire,
the Khan asks him to speak of one
city which he has not yet
mentionedVenice. And Marco Polo
replies: "Every time I describe a city
I say something about Venice. To dis¬
tinguish the qualities of other cities,
I must start from a city that never
changes. For me that city is Venice."
In, point of fact, Marco Polo's
Venice is San Remo, which Calvino
admits is the basis of all the cities
described in his books: "I cannot
overlook the native and familiar land¬
scape. San Remo is the backcloth in
all my books. ..especially in many of
my invisible cities."
For each of these writers it is, af¬
ter all, their native city, the city they
know, which provides the foundation
for the cities of their imagination
a Platonic archetype fleshed out with
endless variations to shape cities
which are always new but always
similar.
CRISTINA GRAU,
Spanish architect, is professor of
architectonic projects at the
Universidad Politécnica of Valencia,
Spain. She is the author of Borges y la
arquitectura (Cátedra, Madrid, 1989).
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDS
listening
JAZZ
Gene Ammons and Sonny Stitt.
Boss Tenors. Straight Ahead from
Chicago August 1961.
Gene Ammons (tenor sax.), Sonny
Stitt (alto sax.), John Houston
(piano), Buster Williams (bass),
George Brown (drums).
1 CD. Verve 837 440-2.
Ammons and Stitt, partners in
the early 1960s, counterbalance,
or rather counterattack, one
another in a battle of giants.
Ammons' earthy, hard-driving
sound, typical of the blues of his
hometown of Chicago, is set
against Stitt's highly-strung East
coast virtuosity, bringing new life
to "There is No Greater Love" and
"Blues Up and Down". Solid
mainstream jazz brought up to
date with a rare swing.
George Coleman.
Manhattan Panorama.
Coleman (tenor sax.), Jamil Nasser
(bass), Harold Mabern (piano), Idris
Muhammad (drums).
1 CD. Theresa TRCD 120.
Apart from the "Mayor Koch"
track, this set_was recorded live
at the Village Vanguard in New
York, and the warm and
welcoming atmosphere of the
club pervades the music.
Coleman, one of the best
saxophonists in the world, creates
direct, energetic music with no
frills but packed with innovative
ideas. He sings with gusto in
"Mayor Koch", his own
composition; launches into the
"New York Suite" (including
"I Love New York", "Manhattan",
"How About You?", "Harlem
Nocturne" and "Autumn in New
York") in a mode reminiscent of
late 1960s jazz, and paints his
"El Barrio" in vibrant Latin
colours.
FOLKLORE
Chine: L'Art du Qin ("China: The
Art of the Qin"). Li Xiangting.
1 CD. Ocora C 560001.
This recording was made for
Radio France in February 1990. Li
Xiangting is the greatest living
exponent of the qin, a 7-stringed
zither. The poetry in these subtle
and refined compositions from the
traditional Chinese repertoire is
evident from their titles, such as
"Three Variations on the Plum-
Flower", "Autumn Declaiming on
the Great Wall" and "Flowing
Waters". The ear is gradually
captivated by the tiny nuances of
phrasing which lead into a
dreamlike universe that is difficult
to leave.
Anthology of the Music of Niger.
1 CD. Ocora C 559056.
Niger, on the fringes of the
Sahara, Is influenced by the music
of the desert. This recording
brings together the music of the
Zerma, Songhai, Hausa, Galla,
Tuareg and Fulani peoples. The
sudden changes of voice,
surprising to the unprepared
listener, create a dramatic mood
that suits the songs of praise or
exorcism common to the music of
Niger. Detailed accompanying
notes are provided by Tolia
Nikiprowetzky, an
ethnomusicologlst specializing in
West Africa.
Mali. La Nuit des Griots ("Mali.
The Night of the Griots").
Ousmane Sacko and Yakaré
Diabate in Concert.
2 cassettes. Ocora 4558662/3.
This is a recording of a concert
by the guitarist Ousmane Sacko
and his wife, the singer Yakaré
Diabate, at Le Havre, France, on 8
January 1983. They are both
griots who belong to the tradition
of the Mandingo people of West
Africa. Some songs from the
traditional repertoire praise the jali
(griots), while others such as
"Apollo" and "Saheli Véri" deal
with more contemporary themes
and social problems. Sacko and
Dlabate are backed by Boubakar
Diabate on the kora and Brahima
Kouyate on the balafon. A great
art form, which the non-African
world is only just beginning to
discover.
POPULAR MUSIC
Lecuona Cuban Boys.
1 CD. Calig CAL 50586.
A long-awaited reissue on a
German label of tracks recorded
between 1935 and 1937. The
Lecuona Cuban Boys, formed in
the 1930s by the composer
Ernesto Lecuona, were important
ambassadors for Cuban music in
Europe and America. The band
concentrates particularly on
rumba and conga, the most
popular dances of that time. The
arrangements and the old-
fashioned vocal style evoke pre¬
war films. As the expression of
the spirit of an era of Cuban
music of which few recordings
exist, this is a document of great
value.
Ray Lema. Nangadeef.
1 CD. Mango CIDM 1000.
An excellent example of African
cross-fertilization. Lema's
arrangements, backed by fine
session musicians, range from
reggae ("Hal 99") to Oriental
("Pongi"), to soca or Zairian
rumba ("Moni Mambo") or to
house music ("Boye Te").
"Orchestra of the Forest",
evoking the atmosphere of the
African forest, and the brilliant
saxophone playing of Courtney
Pine on "What We Need", are
particularly outstanding.
Various Reggae Refreshers.
The Wailers, Black Uhuru, Gregory
Isaacs, Steel Pulse, Third World,
Jimmy Cliff, Toots and the
Maytals, Burning Spear.
1 CD. Mango 846 269-2.
This compilation of tracks by
great Jamaican bands expresses
all the fighting spirit of reggae, as
in "Hard Road to Travel", "Burnin'
and Lootin' ", "Tribal War" and
"War in Babylon". The regular
strong accent on the backbeat
makes reggae rather monotonous
rhythmically, but its lasting
success with young people
everywhere shows that they
wholeheartedly identify with its
message and with its charismatic
musicians.
Isabelle Leymarie I
CLASSICAL	
Gyorgy Ligeti.
Requiem. Aventures. Nouvelles
Aventures. ("Requiem.
Adventures. New Adventures.")
1 CD. Wergo 60 045-50.
An exceptionally fine recording
of 3 of the most beautiful works
by the Hungarian avant-garde
composer. Ligeti, who divides his
time between Vienna, where he
lives, and Hamburg, where he
teaches, is obviously influenced
by the Viennese school, especially
by Alban Berg. His austere and
difficult music here gives pre¬
eminence to the voice. In the
accompanying notes he describes
his approach to musical
composition in Aventures and
Nouvelles Aventures: "the 'text',
written in phonetic lettering, was
not drafted before the
composition, but developed at the
same time as the music; that is to
say, that as pure composition of
spoken sound, it is itself music.
The point of departure for the
spoken sound composition was an
idea of the interrelations in
emotional behaviour, and not an
abstract plan of construction."
Benjamin Britten. Peter Grimes.
Peter Pears, Covent Garden
orchestra and choruses conducted '
by Benjamin Britten.
3 CDs. Decca 414 577-2.
Some musicians sum up an
entire culture: Bartok in Hungary,
Sibelius in Scandinavia and Britten
in England, where classical music
had been dormant since Purcell
and Handel. Britten's opera Peter
Grimes, which launched his career
in 1945, was followed by such
works as The Rape of Lucretia
(1946) sung by the young
Kathleen Ferrier, Billy Budd
(1951), The Turn of the Screw
(1954) and Death in Venice
(1973), his last opera. Although
the tenor Peter Pears was
Britten's lifelong friend and
principal interpreter, his version
does not compare with that of
Jon Vlckers, conducted by Colin
Davis. Decca's efforts to reissue
the bulk of Britten's work are
nevertheless to be applauded.
Heitor Villa-Lobos.
Concerto for Guitar and Small
Orchestra.
Narciso Yepes (guitar), London
Symphony Orchestra conducted
by Garcia Navarro.
1 CD. D.G. 423 700-2.
This late work, dating from
1951 (Villa-Lobos died in 1959), is
a superb synthesis of Brazilian
folklore and the neo-classical
music of the twentieth century.
The great Brazilian composer's
spellbinding magic, well ahead of
its time, conjures up the kind of
cultural syncretism that is so
fashionable today.
Claude dayman 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
world heritage
is.
I
Hi
The rock-hewn churches of Cappadocia
by Antony Brock
48
I he setting for the rock-hewn
churches of Cappadocia in Turkey is,
literally, like nothing on earth. At its
bleakest, it could be a moonscape.
At its most fantastic, it could be a sur¬
realist scene imagined by Salvador
Dali.
Its origin was dramatic: a volcan¬
ic eruption millions of years ago that
covered the terrain with lava. But its
most bizarre features are due to a
centuries-long process of erosion
that has etched the volcanic rock and
ash into steep-sided valleys, some¬
times white, sometimes yellow,
sometimes slashed with horizontal
bars of different colours.
Here and there, where isolated lay¬
ers or fragments of volcanic rock
proved more resistant to erosion
than the surrounding ash, nature has
produced shapes stranger than any
human sculpture. Singly and in
groups, there rise from the valley
floors rock cones, needles and what
the local people call "fairy chim¬
neys", slim pillars topped by horizon¬
tal slabs that sit on them like hats.
Yet what is visible in the valleys of
Göreme and Zelve is less strange
than what is hidden: Byzantine
churches with frescoes, flat ceilings,
domes or vaulting, tunnelled into the
ciiff faces or hollowed out of rock
cones by men who used the friable
"tuff" as material to reverse the nor¬
mal sequence of architecture, taking
away rather than adding on, carving
out rather than building up.
Christianity came early to Cap¬
padocia, long before the Emperor
Constantine made Byzantium into
"New Rome" in 330 AD. For centu¬
ries it flourished, and Asia Minor
abounded in Christian bishoprics.
When Constantinople became Istan¬
bul, the capital of the Ottoman Em¬
pire, in the fifteenth century, the
most recent churches in the Göreme
valley were already 300 years old.
The oldest churches probably date
from the seventh century, but when
the first Christian inhabitants arrived
can only be guessed at. Possibly,
they were hermits who hollowed their
cells from the soft rocks. It is possi¬
ble, too, that the mushroom shapes
of the "fairy chimneys" attracted the
"stylites", those early Christian pole-
squatters who spent their days on
the top of pillars, to prayer on their
insecure summits.
However, the variety of styles In
the rock-hewn churches indicates
that they were constructed at differ¬
ent dates by different waves of
migrants. Most of the churches ap¬
parently belong to the later Byzantine
period, when the new faith of Con¬
stantine had become the old religion,
when the Church he made respecta¬
ble had become in many instances
a persecuted sect.
The wild regions of Cappadocia
offered natural refuges for monks
who wanted to live in peace in self-
supporting communities. Where
these developed, they attracted
peasants to live around them, some
in cave dwellings like those in Gö¬
reme, which riddle the cliffs like holes
in some gigantic Gruyère cheese.
Should armies come to their remote
havens, monks and peasants had a
second line of retreatunderground.
The "tuff" could be excavated down¬
wards as well as laterally, and there
are some twenty underground
refuges In the Göreme area extend¬
ing to seven or eight levels below the
surface. Small entrances and narrow
connecting passages which allow
only one crouching invader to pass
at a time have made those who used
these pre-atomic age fall-out shelters
secure from all except starvation
through long siege.
In one of these underground vil¬
lages Is a Christian chapel with a
stone altar and carved cross, but
Detail of a wall painting
in the Elmali church.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
scholars cannot agree whether reli¬
gious settlers created them or sim¬
ply took over the refuges of earlier
communities. Whatever the case, it
takes no imaginative leap to see the
church architects as not only moti¬
vated by the easily workable nature
of the rock but also by the opportu¬
nity it gave to keep the mysteries of
their religion away from hostile eyes.
Perhaps they saw in the rock-hewn
churches a link to the catacombs of
Rome and the reputation of the Ear¬
ly Christians as "gens lucifugera"
the people who flee the light.
They left behind a veritable muse¬
um of Byzantine styles. For example,
in the Elmali or Apple church, one of
seven in Göreme and the Zelve val¬
ley selected for priority restoration
work, two layers of decoration can be
seen. The first, painted directly on to
the rock, is made up of crosses and
geometrical patterns and probably
dates from the iconoclastic (literally
"image-breaking") period before
about 850 AD when the representa¬
tion of living forms was forbidden.
The second, painted on to plaster,
shows a Pantocrator, or Christ the
Almighty, on the central cupola, with
other frescoes depicting scenes from
the life of Christ in the style of the
eleventh century.
Cross-domed like the Elmali church
is the eleventh-century Karanlik, or
Dark church, which gets its name
from the deep blue-grey of its fres¬
coes, still well-preserved and illustrat¬
ing the sophisticated style of
Constantinople. In other churches of
the valley, like the church of the Vir¬
gin Mary, the style is more provincial,
showing the hand of local artists.
The barrel-vaulted El Nazar church
is an example of a cruciform struc¬
ture in which the main apse joins
directly on to a central square
without an intervening east cross-
arm. Unlike the Dark church, which
Includes a refectory and a dormito¬
ry, and many of the others, it is not
connected with a monastery but set
apart in an isolated tent-shaped rock
cone.
Over the centuries, the Christians
left their settlements and the
churches were neglected until the
1920s and 1930s, when the writings
of a French priest, Fr. Guillaume de
Jerphanion, drew the attention of
scholars and tourists. What had been
religious communities became farm¬
ing communities. Peasant families
made their homes in the caves, many
of them continuing to live there un¬
til recent years. In at least one case,
this secularization had an advantage:
the frescoes of the Dovecote church
in Cavusin were well preserved be¬
cause the church was sealed-up un¬
til 1964 so that pigeons, valued in
the area for their guano, could be
kept in it. But the Dovecote church,
like the Carikli, or Sandal church of
Göreme, has been brutally exposed
to the elements. In both cases the
narthex, where once congregations
stood in worship, has crumbled away
and the modern tourist climbs a me¬
tal staircase to enter.
For the delicate rock which made
the churches possible and the ero¬
sion which gave them their unique
shapes are today the chief threats to
their continued existence. Rain has
soaked into the decorated surfaces,
fading colours and flaking paintwork.
More dangerously, it has seeped into
cracks, then frozen and fissured the
structures. Göreme is in a seismic
zone and it was thanks to an earth-
slip that the church of St. John the
Baptist was discovered as late as
1957. But tremors have destabilized
more churches than they have rev¬
ealed. Some churches have been to¬
tally destroyed, leaving only traces
behind.
These threats explain why Unesco
has not only put the rock-hewn
churches onto its list of monuments
belonging to the cultural heritage of
all mankind, but has launched an in¬
ternational appeal to save them for
future generations. The perils to body
or soul which drove the Christian
communities of Cappadocia into
these bleak valleys have long since
faded. The men who conceived the
churches, hewed them from the liv¬
ing rock and lovingly decorated them
have been forgotten for centuries.
But their faith and their artistry creat¬
ed something unique, that still hush¬
es a group of modern visitors into
silent wonder.
ANTONY BROCK is a Paris-based British
writer and journalist who specializes in
educational and cultural topics. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR ^
50
An issue on death?
Your extremely interesting issue
on Sacred Places led me to think
about the different ways in which
people come to terms with death.
How about an issue of the
Courier on different customs and
attitudes towards death?
Please accept my
congratulations on the
quality of your magazine.
Cédric Deharbieux
Saint-Georges-d'Orques
(France)
We are considering this as a future
theme. Editor
Unlovely Härtung
The theme of your December
1990 issue was one of the most
edifying subjects in human
culture: beauty. You Introduced
the theme by astutely showing a
photo of Marlene Dietrich side by
side with a superb profile of
Nerfertiti. Then came a series of
¡mages and texts which I found
quite admirable.
Then, as if you had been
leading us up the garden path,
you closed the thematic part of
the issue by throwing at us a
photo (on page 44) of a work by
Hans Härtung that is the negation
of all you claim to like on the
preceding pages. This clumsily
executed composition with the
colours of a decomposing fish is a
stupid work which brings shame
on humanity. It is an image of
contemporary chaos, without
either hope or quality.
Beauty is irrelevant where such
a picture is concerned.
Pierre Lohner
Art teacher
Paris
The choice of this painting by Härtung
the end of a brief survey of art
from Fra Angélico to the 20th
centuryillustrates how modern art
broke away from the traditional concept
of the beautiful. Your point of wew
shows something that we wanted to
emphasize in our issuethat a feeling
for beauty is both deep and relative.
Editor
Towards the same ¡deal
I cannot decipher Arab calligraphy
and I do not know what
feelings guided the hand of
Mr. Hassan Massoudy when he
drew the magnificent calligraphic
design which appears on
page 39 of your December 1990
issue devoted to beauty.
However, as I look at it through
the prism of my Western
culture I dream of an irresistible
movement in which man is
freed from the chains of
gravity and soars towards an
Infinity radiant with peace and
serenity.
If I had to choose a work of
French literature to illustrate with
this calligram, it would be
Victor Hugo's poem "Plein ciel"
from his collection La Légende
des siècles, which appeared over
a century ago. In this poem
Hugo already brilliantly foresaw
man freed from gravity
and journeying in the infinity of
space.
Is it possible that our cultures,
different though they are, are
converging on the same ideal?
I look forward to reading the
Courier each month with
impatience and curiosity.
Eugénie Gulchard
Saint-Michel-sur-Orge
(France)
H Cars for hire
I enjoyed reading your issue on
the Myth of the Automobile
(October 1990) but I was sorry
there was nothing in it about
the use of cars in towns and
cities. All major towns and cities
today are choked with traffic.
Driving around in search of a
parking place wastes time and
increases pollution. Who will have
the courage to tackle this
problem?
It has been suggested that
traffic in towns should be
prohibited, except for priority
vehicles such as ambulances
and fire engines, and that self-
drive vehicles for hire should be
made available. Ideally such
vehicles would be battery-
powered, would function with a
magnetic card and be paid for
according to the length of time
for which they were hired.
After use the vehicle would be
returned to a special stationthe
only place where the driver could
get his or her card back.
Microchip technology is so
sophisticated today that this
solution would surely be feasible.
In one European country
(Greece?) efforts have been made
to control traffic by allowing only
cars with even registration
numbers to be used on even days
of the week, and vice versa.
Perhaps this system would be
more difficult to apply because it
requires too many controls...
Clearly public transport must be
kept. But would it not be possible
to simplify the payment system
(for example, by charging a single
fare in all medium-sized French
towns) or even to make public
transport free?
Raymond Forget
Gruffy
(France)
The notation of figures
Bravo for your issue "A
Mathematical Mystery Tour"
(November 1989).
However, what I should really
have liked to see was a table
showing the evolution of the
notation of figures from the
Indians to the Arabs and in the
Middle Ages.
Could you help me to find this
information?
Henri Croiset
Sanary
(France)
The Histoire universelle des chiffres by
the Moroccan historian Georges Ifrah
(Paris, 1981) provides information of
the kind you are looking for. Editor
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3 (right): ©Joël
Cazaux, Paris. Back cover, page 10:
© Pancho Quilici/Galerie du Dragon,
Paris. Page 2: All Rights Reserved.
Pages 3 (left), S (above): All Rights
Reserved. Pages 4, 5 (below), 6-9:
©Institut Pasteur, Paris. Pages 11,
48: Unesco/Dominique Roger. Page
12: ©Dite/NASA, Paris. Pages 13,
26, 27, 28 (above), 36, 37:
© Explorer/Mary Evans Picture
Library, London. Page 14: ©J.L.
Charmet, Paris. Page 15 (above left):
Dominique Darr © Gamma, Paris;
(above right): © Revue du Cinéma,
Paris; (below): from Dos utopias
argentinas, Editions Solar/Hachette,
Buenos Aires, 1976. Pages 16-17:
© Museum of Fine Arts, Boston/Gift
of Mrs. Maxim Karolik for the
Karolik Collection of American
Painting, 1815-1865. Pages 18
(above), 30: © The Image Bank,
Paris. Page 18 (below): J.L. Charmet,
Paris/Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
Page 19: Nimatallah © Artephot,
Paris/Museo Nazionale, Naples. Pages
20-21: ©Scala, Amelia, Florence.
Page 22: © Lauros-Giraudon,
Paris/Cairo Museum. Page 23:
© Lauros-Giraudon, Paris/Musée du
Louvre, Paris. Page 24: Irela
© Artephot, Paris; (inset): M. Babcy
© Artephot, Paris/Ashmolean
Museum, Oxford. Page 25: ©J.L.
Nou, Paris/Sarnath Museum. Page 28
(below): Dite/IPS, Paris. Page 29:
Salaber Liaison © Gamma, Paris.
Page 31: from Les maîtres de l'étrange,
Editions Atlas, Paris, 1985. Page 32:
© Edimédia, Paris. Page 33 (above):
from Le loubok, Editions d'An
Aurore, Leningrad, 1984; (below):
© Paul Kichilov, Paris. Pages 34-35:
© Manchester City Art Gallery,
Manchester. Page 35 (above): © J.L.
Charmet, Paris/Musée des Arts
Décoratifs, Paris. Page 38: from
Utopia, by Ian Tod and Michael
Wheeler, Orbis Publishing Ltd.,
London, 1978. Page 39: Held
© Artephot, Paris/Museo Caccia,
Lugano. Page 40 (above): Patrick
Zachmann © Magnum, Paris; (below):
© Kharbine-Tapabor, Paris. Page 41:
Unesco. Page 42: M. Freeman
© ANA, Paris. Page 44: All Rights
Reserved. Page 45 (above): © Dagli
Orti, Paris/Thyssen Bornemisza
Collection, Lugano; (below):
© Explorer Archives, Paris/Nathan
Chaikin Collection, Geneva. Page 46
(above): © Artcurial, Paris; (below):
Dagli Orti, Paris. Page 49: Unesco/E.
Hattori.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
^courier
Published monthly in 35 languages and In braille
by Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Russian edition: Georgi Zelemn
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Carole Pajot
(Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions: Solange Beiin
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15).
Mouna Chatta
Selection in braille In English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanim (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kossler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88).
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie. Manchan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk. Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.6845. 65),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs. 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of
the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by
Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (3) NCR. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc.. 1 1 1 west 40th Street, New York. U.S.A.; (4) Sell and Howell Co..
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) DEPOT LEGAL : Cl FEVRIER 1991
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocomposition; The Unesco Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury Imprimeur S.A.,
2.1. route d'Etampes, 45330 Malesherbes.
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 2 - 1991 OPI 91 3-490 A
three good reasons for
offering your friends a
subscription to the
Unesco Courier
É
.,W<0>>* Each month it explores
the astonishing diversity of
world culture and knowledge
It associates its readers wié Unesco's
mission offurthering "universal respect for
justice, fir the rule of law and for human rights
and fundamental freedoms...without distinction
of race, sex, language or religion..."
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
'J***"*
"-**>-
SC
>.
'
á¿ "
%;
.
]]>
</page>
</document>
