<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="088099eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
APRIL 1991
i Mini
ft.ft.ft
itWlWHii
Html
m
<* <
/
M 1205 9104 18.00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
_l
encounters We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
HERALD ANGEL
gilded oil painting on wood
by María Irma Zalazar
Executed with remarkable fidelity to the spirit and techniques of the
masters of the 18th-century Cuzco school, this painting is one of a
series in which the Argentine artist María Irma Zalazar has recreated a
typical image of Andean baroque art, "the Angel with the Arquebus".
Sometimes portrayed as a soldier, sometimes as a musician, always
beautifully dressed in the Spanish style, the Angel is at once a warrior
and a messenger of peace. This figure inspired by Christian imagery is
one of the most original creations of Latin American mestizo art.
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
APRIL 1991 CON NTS
4
Interview with
FAROUK HOSNY
The I Inesco
jg^COURIER
44th VE4R
Published monthly In IS Isneusftt and In IraHli
The Governments of the Stat««
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare.
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded. If It Is not to
fail, upon the Intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO.
London. 16 November 1945
PERCEPTIONS OF TIME
COMING TO TERMS WITH TIME
by Paul Ric 11
MEASURED MOMENTS
by Jean Matricon 16
AT PEACE WITH THE PAST
by Xiong Bingming 20
DISTURBING RHYTHMS
by Honorât Aguessy 25
A MANY-SIDED CONCEPT
by Ahmad Hasnawi 26
PRESENT IMPERFECT
by Fernando Ainsa 29
QUARTZ TIME
by Ayyam Wassef 33
'A DESIRE FOR ETERNITY'
by Alexandre Cioranescu
41
IN BRIEF..
42
READER
PROFILE
Analysis of replies
to a UNESCO Courier
reader survey
44
USESCO IS ACTIOS
WORLD HERITAGE
Safeguarding the splendour
of the pyramids
by Gérard Bolla
46
VSESCO IS ACTIOS
TOWARDS
A DEMOCRATIC CULTURE
The Montevideo Declaration
47
USESCO IS ACTIOS
THE SILK ROADS
Ambassadors, adventurers
and empires
by François-Bernard Huygbe
49
LISTENING
Recent records
by Isabelle Leymarie
50
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
Cover photo by
David Harding
Back cover:
Nebula (1989), painting
(160.5 x 140 cm) by the
57 Korean artist Bang Hai-Ja.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
FAROUK
HOSNY
is one of Egypt's most outstanding
contemporary painters. He has lived
and worked for many years in
Europe and is receptive to artistic
trends in both the Arab world and
I
the West. Today he is Egypt's
Minister of Culture.
You are a painter who has become a government
minister. How compatible are these two occupa¬
tions? Artists are supposed to live in the world of
I the imagination, while ministers are administrators
u'r» take action to try to achieve precise objectives
on behalf of the state. Isn't it impossible to recon¬
cile these demands?
There is a contradiction, certainly, but how
serious it is depends on the people and circumstances
involved. In my own case, I find it quite easy to
resolve. I can't conceive of being a minister-
especially a Minister of Culturewithout imagina¬
tion and without being able to mobilize imagina¬
tion, my own and other people's, in the service of
a bold cultural policy.
The raw material of my ministry is memory,
talent and beauty. When we deal with the cultural
heritage, we are managing the products of society's
imagination throughout history. In the case of new
creative work, we deal with the most innovative
. Opposite page,
4 a painting by Farouk Hosny (1990).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
elements of society, with visionaries and poets. With
other ministries we share the responsibility of
reflecting on major future projects which must
respond to long-term social needs that are barely
perceptible today.... At all these levels, the artist's
intuition is just as necessary as the administrator's
efficiency.
If we want to gear up for the future while
keeping our feet on the ground, if we want to fulfil
even a fraction of our dreamsthen we always have
to make a compromise between ambition and
reason, between the risk that must be taken and the
error that must not be committed....
Of course my functions as a minister are a brake
on my personal work, my career as a painter. But
that is a choice one makes, and I am not the only
person who has made such a choice. I think that
artists in many countries today feel a need to devote
part of their time to other things than their creative
work. They go into television or advertising, they
become active in a political party, a human rights
association or an environmental protection organi¬
zation. Sometimes they even go into businessor
join a government.
I think this trend is probably irreversible. Not
only politics but industry, finance, and education,
increasingly demand a wide range of talents, cultural
inputs, ethical and aesthetic points of view that can
only come from the world of letters and arts. Today
perhaps Mozart and Modigliani would not have died
in isolation and poverty.
Let's look at the matterfrom another angle. Some
states refuse to create ministries ofculture because
they think such institutions act as a kind of
bureaucratic straitjacket, a limitation on the
freedom to create and perhaps even a way of
dragooning artists. It's true that they cite the
examples of ministries of culture that have been
notorious for stifling true culture.
Culture can be stifled by a ministry, but it can
also be stifled by a market governed by the laws of
vulgarity, where competition encourages mediocrity
and commissions only go to the most conventional
artists.
This is what happens in many Third World
countries where private patronage doesn't exist,
where entrepreneurs who venture into the field of
culture do so for strictly commercial motives and
the vast majority of creators have no chance of
making an impact because they lack the basic
resources to do so.
What can a Ministry of Culture do in these cir¬
cumstances? As you have just suggested, it can try
to plan artistic productionthat is to say, to define
the areas to be encouraged and those to be dis¬
couraged, promote one direction rather than
another, in short, treat artists as sub-contractors and
works of art as products that can be produced to
order like canned sardines or luxury textiles. This
happens, and it has led to disasters. We must hope
that it will soon be only an unhappy memory.
In this country, on the other handand
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
increasingly, as far as I can judge, elsewhere in the
worldthe Ministry of Culture seeks above all to
be a place where creative work is stimulated and sup¬
ported, and the freedom of the creator is protected.
We generally intervene indirectly. We do not define
objectives, we offer meeting-placescultural
centresor provide creators with opportunities to
make radio or television programmes, to produce
plays, organize exhibitions of their paintings, or pub¬
lish their poems. We insist on quality but we make
no ideological demands.
Outside Cairo and a few other big cities, theatre
or film production would be impossible without a
subsidy from the ministry. Our role is to increase
the opportunities available to artists all over Egypt
and do all we can to present their work to the widest
possible public.
There is another reason why a Ministry of Cul¬
ture is absolutely essential in a country with a
heritage as outstandingly rich as Egypt's.... What
other institution could mobilize the resources, skills
and efforts that are needed to preserve this heritage?
The same problems arise in Greece, India, China
and France.
If a country has a heritage which includes the
pyramids and the Temple of Karnak, to whom can
it entrust their protection and safeguard? Local enter¬
prises don't have the resources, and a foreign mul¬
tinational would soon incorporate them into a hotel
complex. These are not reasonable options. These
wonderful monuments and sites are the property
of the Egyptian people, who assume the moral
responsibility for their upkeep, not only for them
selves, but on behalf of all humanity. Only the Egyp¬
tian state, which carries out research, excavates,
makes inventories and protects all the treasures of
the heritage from pilfering by local thieves as well
as from big international predators, is in a position
to meet the needs of site protection as well as those
of tourism, which offers our heritage to the admi¬
ration of the world.
What specific dangers threaten these sites?
Egypt's antiquities are in danger, but they are not
alone in that. Antiquities are threatened everywhere
today. Not because of neglect but because even the
most advanced techniques that are used to protect
them have some side-effects. We do not know for
certain what precautions to take against these side-
effects.
The problem exists on a much larger scale, the
ecological scale. Modern technologies are beneficial
to humanity in many fields but beyond a certain
threshold they often have repercussions that are
harmful to our healthand to the health of plants
and the stone with which the masterpieces of Antiq¬
uity were built. When car exhaust gases, factory
smoke and radiation are added to the results of cli¬
matic change, humidity, drought, and the wear and
tear caused by the passage of time, then the
chemistry of the stone, the freshness of the colours,
the delicate harmony of forms and volumes are
insidiously altered....
It is possible to combat some kinds of wear and
tear, but not others. To take one example, the vibra¬
tions caused by traffic can to some extent be reduced
by prohibiting the use of vehicles within a certain
radius around important sites. But it's much more
difficult to take precautions against the vibrations
caused by aircraft. The threat of pollution from
industrial activity can only be countered locally.
What can be done about threats from an ecological
disaster on the other side of the world? We had
nothing to do with the Chernobyl disaster but we
have not escaped some of its consequences. We face
a Sisyphean task. But we must resist wherever we
can. We must never give up.
Paradoxically, the very wealth of Egypt's histor¬
ical, artistic and architectural heritage poses
problems. Every square metre of Egyptian soil may
conceal unsuspected treasures. To date we have
brought to light 2,000 Pharaonic tombs of great
value. Let's suppose that it would take two years'
work to restore each of them. That means it would
take no less than 4,000 working years to finish the
job! As for restoring them all at once, that's far
beyond the country's capacities.
We operate like firefighters whose priority is
to extinguish fires as and when they occur. We con¬
centrate on the antiquities in most immediate
danger, those that must be preserved from irremedi¬
able deterioration. Unfortunately there's not much
we can do as things stand at present. I would have
liked to do more and better, to restore all the won¬
derful things that successive civilizations have created
in Egypt over fifty centuries, and show them to the
world in perfect condition.
You say that restoration means usingprocedures
that sometimes cause certain materials to deteriorate
more quickly. Why is this?
There are different schools of thought about resto¬
ration and we should beware of making categorical
judgements. A particular process may be efficient
within certain limits for the restoration of one
material but it may destroy another. It is often neces¬
sary to change from one process to another, to com¬
bine several and adapt some of them to unforeseen
circumstances.... Apart from technical procedures,
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
the very philosophy of restoration is sometimes
questioned. To restore an ancient city which
has long been abandoned or has been destroyed
by war, it may be legitimate to rebuild entire
districts. To restore the Sphinx we should clearly
try to restore its original appearance without
changing anything.
Mistakes are sometimes made. They were made
in previous attempts to restore the Sphinx. Products
were used and elements added which would have
modified its appearance. Fortunately, we were able
to step in before it was too late. The new processes
being used to protect the stone should not so much
maintain the Sphinx in its current dilapidated state
as restore it to its former splendour.
Some ten years ago there was a highly controver¬
sial project to develop the famous plateau of the
pyramids. You yourself have initiated a new
rehabilitation project with UNESCO's help. How
do things stand at present?
There is a fundamental difference between the
two projects. The first would have devastated the
site forever, since it involved the construction of
-hotels, villas, swimming pools and casinos. That
would have been a violation of its historical dimen¬
sion and sacred character. The new project, on the
other hand, aims at clearing away all extraneous
elements: resthouses, public toilets, warehouses, the
homes of certain officials. There are plans to replace
the existing tarmac access roads by stone-paved
paths, remove the street lamps and stop encroach¬
ment by dromedaries, horses, sheep and goats.
But it wasn't always like that....
No. These are quite recent developments. Only
twenty years ago, the site was separate both from
the town of Giza and the outer suburbs of Cairo.
When visitors arrived they found themselves, in a
place of magical silence, they were right back at the
dawn of time.... But surreptitiously some of the
more chaotic features of our time have been allowed
to invade this mythical space, to erode and gradu¬
ally smother it.... At this rate, it will soon be impos¬
sible to distinguish the Sphinx from the newest
buildings in the village of Nazlet el-Simman....
We can't destroy this village but we can, and
should, mark the boundary of the site with a wall
to isolate it from the buildings around it. This solu¬
tion will not restore to the Sphinx the perspective-
open to infinitythat it had for thousands of years.
It will impose a fixed perimeter on the site but at
least the site will be protected. And from certain
angles, visitors will still be able to appreciate the
majestic beauty of the place.
M A more general question about the durability of
the construction materials ofthe pyramids and the
Sphinx. Nothing lasts for ever. Can such ancient
material be maintained indefinitely? Isn't there a
risk that one day the problems will become
insoluble?
I don't believe that there are any insoluble
problems in this field. But there are problems which
cost too much to solve. We are often faced with ter¬
rible dilemmaswe have masterpieces to restore and
the technical solutions exist, but the price is far
beyond what we can afford. A choice then has to
be made between masterpieceswhich ones should
be sacrificed? This is always heartbreaking. Egypt's
drama is that it has produced so many wonderful
things, each of which would be the pride of any of
the world's great museumsand most of them are
crumbling away, disappearing before our eyes.
Of course, the pyramids and the Sphinx are
among the treasures that will be saved whatever the
cost. But what about the materials they are made
of? The Sphinx is carved from a limestone rock that
has already endured much.... I am not talking about
the Sphinx itself, which is about 4,500 years old. I
am talking about the rock, which is more than 50
million years old. For a long period the statue was
completely buried in sand. Herodotus, for example,
does not mention it. The sand concealed it from
view but also protected it from the ravages of time.
Since the sand has been cleared away, the Sphinx
is once more exposed to the wind and sand-storms
that will gradually erode it.
You know, the Sphinx was already in need of
restoration 3,500 years ago at the time of Thutmose
IV, again during the period of Roman rule 2,000
years ago, and again at the beginning of the present
century. Its history is full of ups and downs, times
when it was neglected and times when it was care¬
fully looked after. Our own age is doubtless the most
paradoxical of all. There is universal concern for the
Sphinx yet modern conditions and tourism are
exposing it to forms of aggression it has never had
to endure in the past.
Can we square this circle?
We shall never give up. We shall find the
resources. We shall continue to improve our
methods. And the world is not content simply to
look on. It is backing us. And UNESCO, notably,
is giving us very valuable support.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
1
*H, ,
C
.-.-
*4v.-. .
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
1
, ^ =¿1
_
- -
On the banks of the Ganges
at fflsMkatlV--
Uttar PraïeWTrSdla).
jt*
"C"- «*!*
To dominate an anguish shared by all mankind,
each culture has shaped its own conception of
time. These conceptions have found expression
in myths, epics and works of literature in which
symbolic structures are used in an attempt to
come to terms with the ephemeral and the
eternal.
As the French philosopher Paul R i cBur sug¬
gests in the present issue, this symbolization
constitutes "human time". It has produced a
wide range of systems for organizing temporal
experience. We have tried to give some idea of
this diversity by citing examples from very
different societies.
But as well as experiencing time, human
beings in a sense affect time, if only through the
invention of the quartz and atomic clocks which
have revolutionized our capacities for measur¬
ing it. The same time-system now holds sway
' throughout the world. Perceptions of time
. rooted in the religious beliefs of many cultures
are retreating in face of an invasion by electronic
timekeeping. This crisis can be seen in the con-
v text of a more general crisis about the purpose
-- of life and the values that govern it.
-, - V From the diversity of cultural expressions of
time to the way in which they are being modified
by sophisticated measuring devices, this issue
.yf% is inspired by Henri Bergson's famous remark:
"Time is invention or it is nothing."
* *
V
-
iS¿:'"' -
I tí"
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Coming to terms with time
by Paul Ric
Mankind has invented powerful symbolic structures in order to cope with the immensity of cosmic
time and the brevity of human life
Xwo extreme viewpoints on time suggest them¬
selves to us, and we try to mediate between them.
On the one hand there is the harrowing
experience of life's brevity, with death looming
on the horizon. This fundamental experience is
not endured in silence. The groans of the suffering
are translated into language in the lyrical mode
of lamentation, which mobilizes all the resources
of poetry. Attached to lamentation is a corpus
of popular wisdom which tells of the passage of
time by means of metaphors that are rich in
philosophy.
Thus we say that time flows or flies, sug¬
gesting that its somehow furtive passage prevents
the present from staying with us forever. We also
say that our recent experiences sink into the past
and that once they are in this receptacle they can
no longer be changed, even though the memory
which we have of them and which preserves them
is threatened with destruction by forgetfulness.
Again, we say that the future, which we both
desire and fear, is uncertain, although feared
events arrive too quickly and longed-for events
too slowly, and that in any case what happens
will thwart calculation and foresight.
Antithetical to this elementary symbolization
of the experience of time passing in an existence
that is all too short, is the symbolization of the
immensity of cosmic time which unflaggingly
returns in the great cycles of years, seasons and
days. We say that this time is all-enveloping. We
represent it symbolically as a great immobile
receptacle. Thus we say that our existence takes
place "in" time, and suggest by this spatial
metaphor the precedence of time over thought,
which aspires to circumscribe its meaning and
envelop it.
It is true that ways of measuring time, which
will be discussed below, express a certain mastery
of thought over something which eludes all
attempts to grasp it. But these forms of measure¬
ment, which are themselves inordinately vast,
strengthen the feeling of an enveloping immen¬
sity which contrasts with the experience of life's
brevity.
Other symbolic structures seek to overcome
the disparity between cosmic time and human
time. But to appreciate their significance we must
look more deeply into the nature of this disparity
by identifying some of the speculative resources
of the two metaphors of flight and envelopment.
The paradox of experience
With regard to cosmic time, major scientific dis¬
coveries have brought a keener appreciation of
the ways in which increasingly long time spans
fit together. In Western culture, for example, the
world was long considered to be several thousand
years old6,000 was a figure sometimes men¬
tioned.
The story of how these limits have been
transgressed is fascinating in itself. Improved
knowledge of geological eras has forced us to
accept the idea that the Earth is much older than
anyone could have guessed a few centuries ago.
The discovery of fossils has shown that there was
life on Earth far earlier than was once believed.
Human origins are also being dated further and
further back on a time scale reckoned in millions
of years. The concentric durations in which we
trace the origins of man, the origins of life, the
origins of the Earth and the origins of the solar
system are themselves enveloped by astronom¬
ical time calculated in light-years. Thus the
immediate experience of an immense and all-
enveloping time is reduced to a manageable level.
But the disparity between human time and
cosmic time is not expressed in numerical terms
alone. The main significance of the discordance
between the two viewpoints is qualitative.
Let us return to the phenomenon of time
passing in a fleeting instant. The notion of an ins¬
tant has two distinct and irreconcilable meanings, 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
depending on which of the two viewpoints we
adopt. From the viewpoint of cosmic time, which
precedes human consciousness and to that extent
is without witness, an instant is simply some kind
of breach in the continuity of movement or,
more generally, of changes in dynamic systems.
To talk of a breach is to imply that any instant
can be "now", like a point on the line of time.
However, for there to really be a "now" it
must be experienced by a consciousness which
perceives it as the passage of the future towards
the past across its present. The real disparity
between cosmic time and lived time is that
between quantitative time and qualitative time,
between a time without a present and a time with
a present.
This incommensurability can be expressed in
the form of a paradox. It is within the most insig¬
nificant of time spans, in quantitative termsthat
of a consciousness stretched between birth and
deaththat the very question of the meaning of
time arises, at the heart of the living present, with
its retentions and protensions. By using the imagi¬
nation it is possible to extend the range of
memory until it equals the immensity of sidereal
time, and that of foresight until it reaches a pos¬
sible end of the world. However, in addition to
the fact that the imagination is overwhelmed by
McMath solar telescope at the
Kitt Peak National
Observatory, Arizona (USA).
12 * Cultures and Time, 1976.
an excess of grandeur, as in the experience of the
sublime in Kant, there will always be something
missing between the immeasurable past and the
future and that is the pivotal experience of lived
time, which does not belong to the representa¬
tion of quantitative time.
Taking this phenomenon of disparity as a
starting point, it is possible to appreciate the
power of symbolic structures which, by medi¬
ating between cosmic time and lived time, con¬
stitute what can properly be called the cultural
experience of time.
To get some idea of the immensity of this
enterprise of mediation we must go back to
myths and to mythical time. Cultural anthropol¬
ogists refer to what the French comparative phi¬
lologist and mythologist Georges Dumézil called
"great time", the function of which is to syn¬
chronize cosmic time with the time of societies
and of people living in societies. Dumézil did this
by making a single, global scansion of time, so
that cycles of different duration, the great celes¬
tial cycles, biological recurrences and the rhythms
of social life can be related to each other. By the
regularity of its celebration, ritual expresses a time
whose rhythms are vaster than those of ordinary
action, and gives to the representations of myth
the complement of a practical scansion.
I will say no more about the problem of
mythical time, which I discussed in an earlier
study published by UNESCO.* I will deal
directly with those symbolic structures which can
be situated at the point of inflection between
mythos and logos. It is at this median level that it is
possible to place the temporal structures which
one philosopher, Krzysztof Pomian, has called
"chronosophies" to distinguish them from the
chronographies with which they are intermingled.
Chronosophies and calendars
At this level history is divided into major periods,
eras or epochs. This is a scansion of time which
takes its cue from events which can be described
as "epoch-making" in the sense that they are
linked to the origin of something. In a perspec¬
tive which is still mythical, the most archaic divi¬
sions into periods of time attach these epoch-
making events of history to the acts which them¬
selves created the cosmos. Political chronology
then takes over from religious chronology, while
retaining the imprint of cosmic time.
We need only think of the distinction
between the Golden Age, the Bronze Age and the
Iron Age, or the division into four monarchies
that the prophet Daniel deciphered from the parts
of the image whose head was made of gold, the
arms of silver, the thighs of brass, and the feet
of iron and clay. Later, St. Augustine divided the
history of humanity into six episodes, each of
which was supposed to correspond to a day of
the Creation and an age of life, before the eternal
Sunday of eschatological time. These two forms
of dividing time into periods deal with linear
time, whereas that of Ibn Khaldun applies to a
form of cyclical time in which there is a super¬
position of astral conjunction, the duration of
dynasties and the ages of human life.
These half-theological, half-political ways of
dividing time moved into the background of
European thinking in the late Middle Ages, but
the need for divisions of some kind can still be
seen in school textbooks today. After all, the
notion of the Renaissance evokes a form of
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Instruments at the
18th-century astronomical
observatory at Jaipur,
Rajasthan (India).
PAUL RICwUR,
French philosopher and former
professor of philosophy at the
University of Paris X (Nanterre)
and at the University of
Chicago, is director of the
French philosophical journal
Revue de métaphysique et de
morale. Among his many
published works translated into
English are Fallible Man:
Philosophy of the Will
(Fordham University Press,
New York, 1986), The Rule of
Metaphor (University of
Toronto Press, 1977/Routledge
& Kegan Paul, London, 1986),
and Time and Narrative
(3 vols., University of Chicago
Press, 1984, 1986, 1988). He
has edited 2 collections of
studies for UNESCO, Cultures
and Time (1976) and Time and
the Philosophies (1977).
division in which any innovation is justified by
the revival of Greco-Roman Antiquity. As for the
idea of progress, which seems to exist in a single
linear time, it evokes new divisions. In addition
to the great divide between ancient and modern
times, it projects a universal history which, from
Voltaire to Hegel, divides time into reigns or
kingdoms (in Hegel, the Oriental, Greek, Roman,
and Germanic).
The major function of these chronosophies
is to establish, over and above ephemeral
individual lives, and even the lives of peoples and
their changing dynasties, a time which is more
than human and which, in one way or another,
constitutes a transition between the time of the
cosmos and that of ordinary mortals.
Chronographies have survived the
chronosophies with which they are mingled since
they constitute a more fundamental attempt at
mediationnamely an inscription of human time
in sidereal time. This inscription consists of the
invention of a third time, calendar time. There are
many different calendars, but they do possess cer¬
tain common features which enable us to talk in
terms of calendar time. Together, these features
make possible the computation of time: a founding
event, which is considered to open a new era (the
birth of Buddha or Christ, the Hegira, the acces¬
sion of a sovereign), is the starting point from
which all later events can be dated.
In this way chronological time is connected
to chronosophical time, from which it neverthe¬
less differs since it provides an axis of reference
in relation to which it is possible to pass through
time in the two directions, from the past to the
present and from the present to the past: our own
lives are part of these events to which we look
back or forward. We decide on a set of units of
measurementdays, months, yearsto designate
the constant intervals between the recurrence of
cosmic phenomena.
Calendar time is a symbolic mediation struc¬
ture in the sense that it is inscribed both in cosmic
time (on the basis of astronomical knowledge),
and in human experience (on the basis of
founding events which belong to the collective
memory and are commemorated in celebrations).
The pastthe absentee
from history
With calendar time we have entered historical
time, with its dual value as the time of events
which really happened and the time of the dis¬
course which reports them. At first it seems that
this duality is the result of an unfortunate con¬
fusion, since in many languages the same word
history designates the res gestae (things done) and
the reconstructions which historians make of
them. The justification which can be offered for
this apparent ambiguity leads to the heart of the
cultural experience of time. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
On the one hand, the past is that of the
actions (and sufferings) of people like ourselves,
and this activity demands to be saved from ob¬
livion, demands to be recounted. But all that
remains of these past actions are the traces which
the historian treats as documents by assembling,
selecting and criticizing them. As for the past, it
is the absentee from history.
On the other hand, if we ask ourselves about
the relationship between written history and a
given segment of the past, we must start with the
fact that historians' history is not a carbon copy
of the past. It is of course impossible to compare
the supposed copy with the lost original, and yet
constructions of chains of events linked together
by causes or reasons do set out to be reconstruc¬
tions of what took place.
This link between scholarly construction and
reconstruction characterizes history as a major
symbolic structure of the cultural experience of
time. To represent the past is to construct an icon
of it, not a copy but a kind of model in which
what is written is tantamount to..., stands for...,
that absentee from history which is the past. This
representational, proxy relationship is inherent
in the intentionality of historical knowledge. It
justifies the dual meaning of the word history
mentioned above.
A similar duality exists with the word time
as used in the expression "historical time". On
the one hand there is time as experienced collec¬
tively by people in the past; on the other there
is time in the written account which is made of it.
In the first sense of the term, historical time
Levels of time
On the first level is physical time, a very precise representation of
which is provided by the modem science of nature. This is a very
elementary time, which in a sense underlies all the others. Next
comes the time of life, considered essentially in its evolutionary
aspect; we may therefore speak at this level of an evolutionary time.
At the highest point of evolution, we see the appearance of highly
complex nervous systems, and correlatively a form of time which
may be called neuronic (or neurological) time, the properties of which
are described by neurophysiology.
With the appearance of the human phenomenon, we see the
emergence ofpsychological time, which is associated with individual
behaviour, then historical time, which is associated with the life of
societies, civilizations and cultures. But man feels the bite of time
and aspires to escape from it. For him this is a fundamental problem
which plays a crucial role in the origin of the idea of salvation and
is thus closely linked to the religious dimension of existence. The
category of salvation is a fundamental anthropological category.
Time considered from the perspective of this category has a specific
form which may be described as soteriological time.
Jean Ladrière
Belgian philosopher
("Approche philosophique du temps: fe temps cosmique et le temps vécu",
from Temps et devenir © Presses Universitaires de Louvam-la-Neuve, 1984.)
14
is vaster than that of mortal beings although it
is not on a par with cosmic time. It is the time
of peoples, nations and, in general, of social enti¬
ties which are more durable than individual lives.
People are only of historical interest to the extent
that they are considered with reference to nature
and to changes in a specific society at a specific
time and place. To emphasize the reality of this
vanished past, it must be noted that the events
connected to the event constituted by the actual
writing of the historical account are dated in the
same calendar time.
This historical time is the correlative of the
time involved in the narration of events.
Recounting takes time and above all organizes
time. Composing a written account is a con¬
figuring act which, from a simple succession,
extracts temporal forms organized in closed total¬
ities. This configured time is structured by machi¬
nations which combine intentions, causes and the
workings of chance. Corresponding to it is the
time of the persons who feature in the written
account, which, one might say, simultaneously
becomes a machination in its own right. Thus the
actors of history are given a unique identity: the
narrative identity.
It then becomes possible to connect the two
aspects of historical time. The written account
can confer a posteriori on the historical entities
which are peoples and nations, and on commu¬
nities of all kinds, a narrative identity which is
comparable to that of the characters in a story.
These communities become the collective heroes
(and also the victims) of machinations which take
place on the historical time scale. Between the
time when the events actually happened and the
time of historical account there is the same sym¬
bolizing relationship which makes the latter the
representative of the abolished past, the absentee
from history. History as it is told takes the place
of history as it is collectively experienced.
The force
of the present
Let us now return from historical time to
individual time, which we left on a note of lamen¬
tation and lyricism.
The following observation provides us with
a transition: historical communities, although
they cannot be decomposed into a dust of
individual actions and reactions, cannot be
defined without reference to the individuals
which are their partners, i.e. those who take part
in them as if they are characters in a story which
concerns them personally. The link between col¬
lective time and individual time is a corollary of
this link between society and the individual. Just
as the notion of narrative identity can be applied
analogically to individuals and to historical com¬
munities, so the structure of the present, pregnant
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photomontage
by Hervé Bernard.
with the recent past and the imminent future (in
memory and nostalgia on the one hand, in plans
and hopes on the other), applies analogically to
collective time and to individual time.
Historical time can be seen as a relationship
between what the German philosopher Rein¬
hardt Koselleck calls the horizon of expectation
and the space of experience. By space of
experience he means the totality of all the
heritages transmitted by tradition to the histor¬
ical present; by horizon of expectation, the
deployment of projects and hopes which insert
the future into the present. The space of
experience can be narrow and poor if the
heritages are sclerotic, dead, immobile. The
horizon of expectation can be brought nearer in
the short term of the everyday organization of
time, or pushed back almost infinitely in utopias
of regeneration, reconciliation and reintegration.
Koselleck points out that we cannot derive
the horizon of expectation from the space of
experience. Only in the present does the concen¬
tration of the past in the space of experience inter¬
sect with the deployment of the future in the
horizon of expectation. But the exchange is only
fruitful if the present is itself a force of initiative
(Nietzsche spoke in this sense of the "force of
the present").
This triple structurethe horizon of expec¬
tation, the space of experience, and initiativeis
exactly symmetrical to the constitution of
individual time in the living present. St.
Augustine wrote in his Confessions of time as
engendered by the threefold present. "The
present of things past," he says, "is memory. The
present of things present, sight; the present of
things future, expectation." The "still" of the
recent past and the "already" of the imminent
future are each rooted in the force of the present
which, in terms of representation, is called
vigilance, in terms of action, the capacity to begin
something in the course of things.
This analogy between the structure of histor¬
ical time and that of individual time can be under¬
stood in two ways. The first may be thought of
as the interiorization of the way in which a com¬
munity is located in historical time; the second
as the extrapolation of the triple present of the
individual soul. This double reading is justified
by the resemblance between individual narrative
identity and the collective narrative identity
which in its turn reflects the parallelism between
plot and character in written history and
biography.
We have now come full circle. We began with
the lamentation of the poet deploring the flight
of time, the erosion of memory, and disappointed
expectations, and contrasted this elegy of the
unhappy awareness of individual time with con¬
templation of the sidereal order and its immense
time. We have not covered all the ground. We
have simply discussed a series of mediations
which propose ¿pacified crossing of the interval:
the great time of myths, eras and chronosophies,
calendar time, historical time which is vaster than
the individual, and individual time which can be
seen as the final point of an interiorization of all
these times which, degree by degree, symbolize
the immense time of the universe.
Lamentation has not been refuted. It has
simply been compensated for by experience of
the initiative and the vigilance which give the
present its force. And it is in the element of lan¬
guage, carried by its symbolic structures, that we
have followed the gradual constitution of the cul¬
tural experience of time. 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
by Jean Matricon
From the sundial to the atomic clock, the search for split-second accuracy
16
XlME is both the most familiar and the most
elusive of concepts, yet it is one which human
beings know that they will never fully grasp. The
most they can hope for is to make the best use
of the time allotted to each one of them.
How can time be measured? Length, volume,
mass, energyalmost all the physical values of the
world around us submit to our manipulations.
Time is an exception. It is impossible to cut out
a segment of time and compare it with another
segment taken from somewhere else. To measure
time, we must select some other phenomenon
which we can manipulate and which recurs in
identical fashion. We do not measure time itself,
but its manifestation through a physical
phenomenon of our choice.
As well as the inherent difficulty of meas¬
uring time, there is another problem which stems
from the ambiguity of what is being measured.
Most of the instruments devised for this purpose
measure intervals of time, or duration, notions
which give a sense of the irreversibility of the
march of time but do not enable us accurately
to situate the chronology of events. Measuring
time also implies situating events in relation to
each other, in other words, dating them.
By providing a time scale with a periodic
return of identical situations, which can be cal¬
culated, the time divisions offered by the cycles
of the stars, the rhythm of the seasons, the phases
of the Moon, and the alternance of day and night,
enable us to establish such chronologies.
Chronologies and calendars
Very early on, observation of the sky, by day and
by night, revealed the complexity of the move¬
ment of the stars. A complete rotation of the
Earth in relation to the pole star (a sidereal day)
takes four minutes short of twenty-four hours.
The Sun's leisurely visitation of the thirteen con¬
stellations of the zodiac is completed in 365 and
a quarter days. This movement puts the Sun a
little more out of phase with the stars each day
and produces a solar day of twenty-four hours.
As for the Moon, its revolution around the Earth
period from one new Moon to the next-
takes about twenty-nine and a half days.
All these data seem to have been accurately
measured by Babylonian astronomers as early as
1800 BC. They were used to establish a calendar
based on a lunar month consisting sometimes of
twenty-nine and sometimes of thirty days. Predic¬
tion of these intervals required a remarkable
knowledge of the apparent movements of the Sun
and the Moon. The Egyptians, whose life was
linked to the flooding of the Nile, opted for an
annual calendar with a year of exactly 365 days.
This put the calendar year out of phase with the
solar year, and therefore with the agricultural
(seasonal) year, by one day every four years. Thus
the civil (calendar) year only coincided with the
solar year once every 1,460 years!
Almost all civilizations have based their
calendars on either the lunar month or the solar
year, despite the inherent difficulty that the year
is not made up of an exact number of lunar
months. Each civilization thus invented its own
more or less fixed, more or less arbitrary, system
of adjustment. This put great power into the
hands of the religious or political hierarchy
which took this decision. Although today these
adjustments are no longer arbitrary, the variety
of calendars and of cultures that they reflect
remains.
The role of the calendar has not changed since
the time of its ancient origins. It is the guarantor
of the cyclical recurrence of natural phenomena,
such as the tides and the seasons, and of human
events, such as religious and civil festivals. It also
makes possible the establishment of a chronology
attributing to each event a date and a precise posi¬
tion in the unfolding of time. The calendar is
undoubtedly one of the most stable and most
specific elements of any society.
The demands of daily religious and domestic
life created a need for some kind of time scale
or chronology of night and day. The Egyptians
were skilled astronomers, and drew up a list of
the stars that rose every day just before the Sun,
thus signalling the final hour of night. Having
decided, for the sake of simplicity, to allot the
JEAN MATRICON,
French scientist, is professor
of physics at the University of
Paris VII (Jussieu). As scientific
adviser for an exhibition
entitled L'invention du temps
("The Invention of Time") held
at the Cité des sciences et de
l'industrie, La Villette, Paris, in
1989, he wrote a catalogue
(with Julien Roumette), which
will be reissued in October
1991 as Le temps et les
hommes ("Time and Man") by
Collection Explora, Editions
Presses-Pocket, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Intlhuatana at the ancient
Inca fortress city of Machu
Picchu (Peru). A monumental
carved rock surrounded by
walls, doors and
passageways, it is thought to
have been a solar calendar.
An early 19th-century French
water clock or clepsydra. The
water is contained in a drum
divided by partitions pierced
by small holes. It slowly flows
through the holes, causing the
drum to turn and descend
between the graduated
uprights as the 2 cords
attached to its axis unroll.
role of herald of the dawn to the same star for a
period of ten days before passing it on to another,
they drew up tables showing, for each night of the
year, the order in which they rose, from twilight
to dawn. Thus, for the 365 days of the year, there
were thirty-six ten-day periods. During the short
summer nights twelve risings of these herald stars
could be observed and it was therefore decided
to divide the night into twelve "hours".
During the day, the height of the Sun and the
shadow cast by a column, or gnomon, on a gradu¬
ated scale was also used by the Egyptians to
measure the passing of time. From the middle of
the second millennium BC, we find these "solar
rulers" indicating a division of the day into twelve
hours. Thus the Egyptians can be said to have
invented the twenty-four-hour day. These hours,
however, were not all of the same length since
days and nights vary in duration throughout the
year.
The most ancient sundials were Egyptian, but
it is certain that similar devices existed very early
on in other civilizations, notably in China,
Babylon and pre-Columbian America. Ranging
from a simple stick thrust vertically into the soil
to the refined instruments by means of which,
as late as the end of the last century, mechanical
watches could be set by the Sun, the sundial, in
all civilizations and at all latitudes, has proved to
be the most reliable, the most widely accessible
and the most accurate timekeeper.. .provided, of
course, that the Sun shone.
The first mechanical
devices
Very early in history, instruments that measured
duration, or periods of time the start of which
could be selected at will by the user, were to be
found alongside chronological timekeepers. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The oldest known water clock dates from
1400 BC. It consisted of a cone-shaped vase
with a hole in the bottom and with a series of
graduated lines drawn horizontally on the inside.
The vase was filled with water and as it slowly
emptied the level of the remaining water indi¬
cated the time that had elapsed since the filling
of the vase. An immense variety of these water
clocks, or clepsydras, were made in different
civilizations.
From Greco-Roman times, the technique was
known of using the dynamic power of water to
drive a system of gears which in turn could
operate visual time indicators and set off sound
signals. This tradition was perpetuated and the
mechanisms perfected by the Arabs. In the year
602 of the Hegira, al-Jazari described the construc¬
tion of impressive instruments that acted both as
clocks and as astronomical calendars.
A huge water-powered astronomical clock,
housed in a twelve-metre-high tower, was built
and perfected in China in 1094 by Su Song. Only
a written description of this clock has survived.
Telling the time
Since machines for telling the time were made,
there must have been a need for them. In the
Middle Ages, the great majority of the world's
population were peasant farmers, and the time
indicated by the Sun in the heavens was adequate
for agricultural purposes. Accurate knowledge of
the time of day was, however, a necessity of
Muslim calendar in wood
(41 x 28 cm) from Benin.
The circles on the upper part
represent the days of
the week and important times
of the day; those on the
lower part represent the days
of the lunar year.
; ü so©*
s ? <-s : g s*e
18
?' Í>c '¡'f ""r -««
*>3fcMJ	i	-
L»- 0-**	--1* ;; i»u..kyl^(
g
Einstein' s theory
of relativity
The most salient feature of the doctrine of relativity is the
negation of the idea of time, such as it has been conceived since
there were men and they thought, to paraphrase La Bruyère.
Peter and Paul are in a bedroom. Paul goes for a walk. On
his return, Peter says to him: 'You have been away for an
hour. "
"How do you know?" Paul replies. "All you can say is that
you have spent an hour in this bedroom, because you have not
moved. But time slows down for a being in movement. My
absence lasted less than an hour if I was on foot; even less if I
was in a car; still less if I took an aeroplane. If I had travelled at
the speed of light, I would have returned at the very instant
when I left. If I could move faster than light, I would have
returned before I left. "
Daniel Berthelot
French chemist
(ta physique et /a métaphysique des théories d'Einstein,
© Payot, Paris 1922)
religious life, and for both Muslims and Chris¬
tians the hour of prayer had to be scrupulously
and accurately observed. Others who needed to
know the time of day included astronomers and
astrologers who, though few in number, were in
all countries close to the centre of power. In the
Islamic world and other places where the climate
made the use of sundials or water clocks feasible,
these needs were met. This was not always the
case in regions such as northern Europe where
the Sun is often hidden by clouds, the days are
short in winter, and water is liable to freeze.
During the eleventh and twelfth centuries, a
new form of urban life developed in Europe.
Banks and industry came into being and crafts
flourished. These activities brought with them the
need for more precise and permanently available
means of telling the time. The old instruments
were unsatisfactory, and by the end of the thir¬
teenth century the time was ripe for the inven¬
tion of the mechanical clock operated by weights
and pendulums. The appearance of these devices
marks one of the great turning points in the his¬
tory of science and technology.
The earliest clocks were neither accurate nor
reliable, but the method of measuring time that
they introduced, which was independent of the
stars or the elements and a pure product of
human ingenuity, was to revolutionize our ways
of life. Advancing to the rhythm of the pen¬
dulum, the new instruments would lead the way
to the technological and industrial civilization we
know today.
From the thirteenth to the twentieth century,
in response to increasingly stringent demands,
mechanical clocks were constantly improved and
became more accurate, more reliable, smaller and
A modern Nepalese calendar.
*-'
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
less costly. The first clocks took as long as a year
to make, could easily gain or lose an hour a day,
and lasted only about ten years, whereas the best
mechanical marine chronometers made in the
nineteenth century were accurate to within a
tenth of a second a day and are still working as
well as ever.
Universal time
Until the last century few people travelled and
those who did travelled slowly. Each town and
village lived by its own time as registered by its
own sundial, which was more accurate than any
mechanical clock. All this changed with the
coming of the railway and the telegraph, which
gradually drew all the cities of the world into a
single network and obliged them to agree upon
a coherent time system.
An international system of time zones, under
which the hour in each zone differs whilst
Bronze pins from the
Mesopotamian site of Susa
(3rd-4th century BC) being
analysed by ultraviolet
spectrometry. The pins can be
dated by measuring the
radiation given off after they
are heated by the electrical
arc, and comparing It with
that of control objects.
minutes and seconds are synchronized with
Universal Time (mean solar time at the Green¬
wich meridian), was proposed in 1885 and in less
than thirty years had been adopted worldwide.
Synchronization was initially regulated by tele¬
graph, but today satellites, accurate to a millionth
of a second, have taken over the task.
Quartz and caesium clocks
Since the seventeenth century all mechanical
clocks have been regulated by the oscillation of
a pendulum or of a balance-wheel connected to
a spiral hair-spring. Until the twentieth century
no more accurate form of oscillator was known.
In 1928, however, following the discovery that
the mechanical vibration of a quartz crystal is
accompanied by electrical oscillation, the possi¬
bility was envisaged of replacing the old balance-
wheels by suitably cut crystals.
The first quartz-crystal clock was cumber¬
some and only moderately accurate. Sixty years
later, thanks to advances in electronics, cheap
quartz watches can be more accurate than the
finest mechanical observatory clocks. Amazingly
accurate timekeeping suddenly became widely
possible. Wherever we may be, the time is posted
up for us to see, with minutes and seconds the
same throughout the world.
When the atom, a new and even more
accurate oscillator, became available to the
world's physics laboratories, even the rotation of
the Earth itself, which used to be the absolute
standard of time, revealed its inaccuracies. The
atom, and especially the caesium-133 atom, now
provides the basis of the new standard of time.
The best atomic clocks can keep time with an
accuracy of the order of a second over a period
of a million years. But scientists are still not
satisfied-
Time, however, is more than just an abstract,
regulated framework for our activities, univer¬
sally controlled and posted up around us on mil¬
lions of clock faces. It also embraces the
biorhythms, the internal impulses that have no
dials or hands but to which all living beings are
subject. Some of these last only a few thousandths
of a second, others several years. Most of them
are synchronized with astral, diurnal, lunar or
annual rhythms.
In a few hundred years, man has pushed back
the frontiers of space, both outward towards
immensity and inward towards the infinitesimal.
We have achieved the same with time scales. We
are capable of measuring the fifteen thousand
million-year lifetime of the universe and also a
femto-second (one thousand million millionth of
a second).
Yet people have not changed the pace at which
they walk, the pace of their heartbeats or even,
significantly, their life-span. The rhythms of life
have not varied. Even though certain hours may
seem longer or shorter than others, time is the
same for everyone, for it belongs to no one. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
At peace with the past
Chinese humanist thought contemplates the passing of time with equanimity
I
20
XIONG BINGMING,
Chinese writer and philosopher,
was formerly professor of
philosophy and Chinese
literature, and director of the
Chinese department, at the
Institut National de Langues et
Civilisations Orientales, Paris.
His publications include Zhang
Xu et la calligraphie cursive
folle.
N Chinese culture, the supreme goal is the
accomplishment of an ideal person. This hu¬
manism is so deeply embedded in Chinese
thought that strictly speaking it leaves no room
for philosophical debate about the nature of time.
The Chinese have always been strongly aware
of the relationship between space and time and
the living world, as the very terms used in their
language to describe the world and the universe
attest, but they have never sought to study these
concepts in the abstract. Instead they set about
developing instruments and techniques for meas¬
uring time. China had a functioning calendar by
the second millennium BC, and it was in China
that the sundial and the clepsydra or water clock
were first developed.
What philosophical problems has the idea of
time raised in China? And how has the subject
been treated in Chinese literature, especially in
poetry? These are the questions I intend to
address, starting from the definition of time given
in the Huainanzi, an important philosophical
work written in the second century BC: "time
is that which goes away and becomes the past;
that which arrives and becomes the present."
'The Sun at its zenith
is already going down'
For the ancient Chinese, the world was not the
work of a Creator. Only later do texts describe
the creation of the world by Bangu, a "cosmic
man" whose body gave birth to the different
parts of the world. And not until the fourth cen¬
tury AD, with the pantheon of Taoist gods, do
we find a symbolic conceptualization of the var¬
ious aspects of the universe at its creation. Then
the original, undifferentiated state of non-being
becomes the August Lord of the Way of Empti¬
ness (Xu huang daojun), who engenders existence.
If we can divide the past into two great
channels, the history of the universe and of the
human race respectively, it becomes apparent that
the followers of Kongzi (the man better known
in the West as Confucius) were primarily
interested in the latter, which is to say in history
properly so-called, putting the emphasis on social
life and on cultural tradition. When Confucius
refers to history, he is really only speaking of the
reigns of the emperors Yao and Shun. In his view,
cultural life and moral consciencethe great Con¬
fucian principlesonly made their appearance in
Chinese life under these two exemplary
emperors.
The Taoist vision, though, extends beyond
human life to examine the origins of the Earth
and the heavens. According to Laozi (or Lao-tzu,
as he used to be known in the West), the author
of the basic Taoist text the Daodejing ("The Book
of the Way and its Power"), "There was an
indeterminate being before the formation of
Heaven and Earth." In another passage he pushes
back the horizons of time: "The Dao begot One.
One begot Two. Two begot Three. And Three
begot all other beings."
This "succession" obviously takes place in
time, but it also goes beyond the very notion of
temporality. For "non-being" does not disappear
with the creation of being; on the contrary, it is
the very basis of being. Its primordial importance
can be compared with that of the space in a house,
the emptiness without which the house itself
could not exist.
Laozi has nothing to say about what preceded
non-being at the very origin of the universe. Two
centuries later another Taoist philosopher, Zhu-
angzi (Chuang-tzu), turned his mind to the
problem, only to conclude that reason cannot
provide any satisfactory response because of the
limitations of language. For him as for Laozi
before him, true knowledge transcends language:
"Who knows does not speak, who speaks does
not know."
The Legalists of the eighth to the third cen¬
tury BC were particularly interested in the theory
and practice of politics. The only history that
concerned them was social history. Their greatest
figure, Hanfeizi, who died in 234 BC, had a
"dialectical" conception of social development
that has parallels with the theories of some
modern historians. He introduced the idea of
progress in history, departing radically from the
Confucianists and Taoists for whom the ancient
world was the ideal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The bl, a flat disk with a hole
in the centre, was an
astronomical instrument in
ancient China, where it was
also regarded as a symbol of
heaven. A hollow tubular
eyepiece fitted into the hole.
Left, the notches around the
circumference of the jade
model shown here (c. 500 BC)
correspond to the bearings of
the major constellations.
But it was Huishi and Gongsun Long, the
philosophers of the school of thought known as
the Dialecticians, who in the fourth and third cen¬
turies BC became the first to consider time in
itself as an abstract principle. Unfortunately, vir¬
tually nothing remains of Huishi's works other
than the "Ten Paradoxes" that his friend Zhu-
angzi passed down without, however, including
the reasoning that would explain the master's
thought processes.
One of Huishi's formulas, "The Sun at its
zenith is already going down", emphasizes the
way in which time is both instantaneous and
continuous. Another much-discussed paradox
that has been explained in many different ways
runs: "Today I am going to Yue (a region of
southern China), and yet I arrived yesterday." Its
purpose seems to be to underline the relative
nature of such notions as "today", "tomorrow" or
A Chinese-designed
clepsydra (water clock) in
which time was measured
by the water level rising in
the lowest reservoir. It was
used in the 11th century.
(19th-century German
engraving).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
"yesterday". Almost as soon as we use the word
"today", it has after all passed into yesterday.
Two of Huishi's other paradoxes "An arrow in
flight is motionless even though it has not
stopped", and "The flying bird's shadow does not
move" seem inspired by the philosophical thesis
that it is not possible to conceptualize movement.
The Chinese interest in history showed itself
very early on. In the Shang era, eleven centuries
before the birth of Christ, court chroniclers were
already recording events and discourses. When¬
ever one dynasty succeeded another, scholars
were summoned to write the history of the
dynasty that had ended. Many historical works
were also written by individuals. Confucius
initiated the genre with his Annals ofSpring and
ofAutumn, which sought to provide both moral
instruction and a critique of the past.*
The Chinese live in a symbiotic relationship
with the past. This explains the importance of
the clan and the cult of ancestors in daily life. In
philosophy, it leads to a stress on the continuity
of Chinese cultural traditions from the remotest
past. Chinese writing has not changed over the
centuries, and the problems debated by thinkers
3,000 years ago are still topical today. The events
and personalities of China's long history still
inspire writers and artists, who keep them alive,
rich with symbolic associations, in the collective
consciousness.
Ways of defying time
"We do not even understand life, so how could
we possibly know death?" Confucius asked.
Although his followers paid great attention to
funerary rites and to the etiquette of mourning,
they were not much concerned with the thought
of what happens after death or the fate of the soul.
They did believe, however, that dead people lived
on in the memory of the living, and they pro¬
posed rules of conduct to assure that kind of sur¬
vival. In the sixth century BC, for instance,
Shusun Bao defined "Three things that will not
decay": "practise virtue", "acquire merit" and
"write texts to pass on to posterity".
For their part, the Taoists were so enamour¬
ed of life that they sought actively to prolong it.
Laozi thought that it was possible to achieve lon¬
gevity and defy the passage of time by preserving
a child's vitality. The Taoist religion came up
with various ways of doing this, from breathing
exercises to the consumption of cinnabar-based
elixirs. It sought to change humankind radically
and give it immortality.
Buddhism, through the doctrine of samsara,
introduced the idea of reincarnation. An adept
who accumulated sufficient merit in the course
of one life could be reborn in the next on a higher
plane of existence, continuing in the same way
through subsequent lives until he finally reached
Sage beneath a Willow
or The Drunken Poet,
anonymous Chinese painting
of the Song dynasty
(10th-13th century).
r\r\ * See tne article by Huo Datong, "The emperor's all-seeing eye",
¿.¿. in the UNESCO Courier, March 1990.
a state of timeless perfection in which the wheel
of reincarnation would cease to turn. The Budd¬
hist way thereby became a quest for self-annih¬
ilation "without life or death" as the monk Faling
put it at the beginning of the Tang era.
Buddhism also introduced into Chinese
thought the idea of the end of the world, which
was to come only after long and precisely-
calculated cycles of creation and destruction. Both
the concept itself and this way of enumerating
the different stages in the process were adopted
and developed by the Neo-Confucianists of the
Song dynasty, from the tenth to the thirteenth
centuries AD. It is typically Chinese that the
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The savour of time
The arts of China, poetry, painting and pottery, are
marked by a strong yet delicate impressionism which
in itself denotes a way ofsavouring time. Chinese
sensitivity being wholly attuned to the changing states
of nature, fleeting variations of delight and the most
exquisite moments of harmony were always
illuminating not only the lives of noblemen, scholars
and the monks of the great monasteries, but those of
the uneducated poor as well.
The quality of time was appreciated in the same
way as that of tea, paper, silk or any other of the
thousand and one things which lend charm to life.
Time came, went and returned: the time of the plum
branch, of the bamboo stalk, of the maple leaf, and of
pine branches, the time of the greylag's harsh cry, the
sweet song of the oriole, the call of the quail.
So many different savours and scents impinging
upon the consciousness stamped the quality ofpassing
time. Poems and paintings were placed and dated and
the solar period (twenty-four in a year) of their
composition noted.
Claude Larre
French sinologist
("The empirical apperception of time and the conception of history in Chinese
thought", from Cultures and Time © Unesco, Paris, 1976.)
annihilation of the world, however tragic it might
seem, is nevertheless seen as a natural
phenomenon rather than a punishment visited on
the world by the gods.
The present: action or contemplation?
"Everything flows like water, nothing stops by
day or night," Confucius wrote with feeling. The
sight of running water brought to his mind the
passage of time, tormenting him with a tragic
awareness of the way in which life confronts man
with tasks he knows he cannot accomplish. It is
the first poetic meditation on the ephemeral in
Chinese culture.
Faced with such transience, how should we
react? Confucianists believe that people should
seize the passing moment, develop strong perso¬
nalities and make themselves useful to the com¬
munity. Such restlessness and social responsibility
are alien to the Taoist ideal, which is concerned
with contemplation and communion with the
universe. The Taoist sage seeks a path to the time¬
less even in the passage of time itself. His only
Celebrants light incense
sticks during a ceremony held
to honour ancestors at the
Temple of Foshan, Guangdong
province, southern China.
ambition is to enjoy existence in the quietude of
a peaceful and simple life. Time's passing causes
him no anxiety that cannot be dissipated through
the exercise of wisdom.
There is a well-known story by Zhuangzi, in
which the author dreamed that he was a butterfly
fluttering hither and thither without knowing it
was Zhuangzi. When he woke up, he did not
know whether he was Zhuangzi dreaming that
he was a butterfly, or the butterfly dreaming that
it was Zhuangzi. Maybe life itself, the story
implies, is just a long dream from which death
will awaken us.
It was, however, the writers and poets rather
than the philosophers who were to express most
sublimely the terror of time's passing. Expressing
his anxiety about serving his country in a long
autobiographical poem, the Lisao, at the turn of
the fourth century BC, Qu Yuan, one of the
founders of the nation's poetic tradition, speaks
of his disillusionment and laments the flight of
time. "Old age is taking me/Before I have been
able to win renown." By the end of the Han era,
in the second century AD, the attitude of poets
diversified. Some chose Epicureanism ("Let us
rejoice today./Why wait until tomorrow?").
Others pursued fame and reputation: "The
human body.. .dies like everything that lives.
Making a name, that's the real treasure." Yet
others' sought a solution in alcoholic oblivion.
"It's an illusion, swallowing the drugs of immor¬
tality; better drink good wine and go dressed in
silk."
In its ambiguity, the attitude of the best-
known of the Song poets, Su Dongpo (1037-1101)
seems particularly indicative of the Chinese poetic
sensibility. In his Memory of the Red Cliff, he
praises the heroic age of the Three Kingdoms
while at the same time regretting that they have
disappeared like so many chimeras. Is he
optimistic or pessimistic? I would say both. He
has a Confucian ardour for addressing worldly
matters, yet at the same time shows a
metaphysical detachment, not to say lack of
involvement, that derives from Taoism.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Fon vodun cult dance in
honour of Hebioso, divinity of
celestial phenomena and
germination (Nigeria).
24
HONORAT AGUESSY,
Beninese specialist in
sociology and literature, is a
former researcher at the
French National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS) and
dean of the faculty of letters,
arts and human sciences at
the University of Benin. He is
currently a staff member of
UNESCO's Regional Office in
Dakar (Senegal). His many
published works include
Histoire de la pensée africaine
and L'Afrique et le monde.
Visions et perceptions
traditionnelles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
by Honorât Aguessy
New social and economic forces are disrupting the traditional African awareness of time
Af
This 30-day calendar
of the Fon people of Benin
consists of cowries, fruit
stones, pebbles and other
objects stitched onto a strip
of cloth. Each object
corresponds to a specific day.
The calendar was hung
lengthwise on the wall and a
marker was fixed to the cloth
to indicate the day.
LfricA is so vast a continent and englobes so
many societies that it is impossible to give a single
all-embracing definition of what time means to the
people who live there. There is time as it is
experienced by individuals, but there is also what
might be called "social time" which varies
according to whether the context is political, eco¬
nomic or religious.
In the economic context, time seems to go
by at dizzying speed. New consumer goods
appear on the market at a rhythm which conflicts
with that of the deeply-felt needs of indigenous
African society. In politics, the time of the domi-
nators is out of phase with that of those they
dominate. The former seek permanence and
the latter seek change. In religious life, the rapid
pace of modern life is tending to strengthen
attachment to the unchanging cycles of sacred
time.
Time in African society is thus complex,
dense and opaque. People live in a shifting
kaleidoscope, feeling that everything is in a cons¬
tant state of flux but that fundamentally nothing
ever changes. The Fon people of Benin have a
proverb which says that "Life is like a leaf tossed
about on the surface of the water". Time in the
individual conscience is not isolated from collec¬
tive time. It overlaps with the different forms of
collective time and is modified by them.
Exposed to the frantic rhythm of the con¬
sumer society, people find that their attention is
captured and diverted by an endless torrent of
new products. To parody Descartes, one might
sum up this form of subjection to time with the
formula "I consume, therefore I am". In spite of
themselves, people are caught up in a social time
scale which is alien to that of local modes of
production.
It is just as difficult for the individual to
master the processes of time in politics. People
find it hard to grasp the ins and outs of political
situations which are full of surprising conspira¬
cies and futile clashes, and are not even intelligible
to those immediately involved. They simply get
the impression that politics is a complex pattern
whose strands are woven and unravelled more
slowly than those of the economic fabric.
In contrast to these fluctuating temporalities
there are the permanence and the recurrence of
religious life. Whether the dominant context is
that of Christianity, Islam or traditional religions,
the religious year is cyclical and its course is punc¬
tuated by the recurrent events that mark its
eternal return. It has not been much affected by
the changes that have occurred elsewhere in
society. Although there are signs that traditional
religions have adapted to the demands of the
modern world, their spiritual foundationsthe
true memorial of the history of African
societiesremain intact.
In the traditional calendar, which is based on
well-omened days and ill-omened days, the
organization of time has not changed. In the Fon
calendar, which governed the actions of the reli¬
gious authorities (although other people also took
an interest in it), symbols on a piece of cloth indi¬
cate the significance of different lunar days which
correspond to certain events in people's lives. The
day on which everything you undertake will be
successful is symbolized by a kind of smooth,
shining, grey-green bean, the ajikwin. A small
bone indicates a day on which it is best not to
attempt anything. This calendar was constantly
consulted by people who wanted to be sure of
not swimming against the tide. The underlying
idea is that every important undertaking has its
time and its rhythm.
This social stratification of time sheds some
light on the nature of underdevelopment in
Africa. Underdevelopment is not a lack of
development but development of a dual, distorted
kind. Endogenous development is disturbed and
thwarted by exogenous development, just as time
perceived as communion with the memory of .
society and the cosmos is disturbed by time which
is associated with the repeated appearance of
new gadgets and the pressure of economic
precariousness.
The time of renewal, for Africa, is that which
respects the values of this memory and perpetuates
it in such a way that society can be receptive to
modernity. African society bends before blind and
ephemeral forces from outside, but it does not
break. Its time is only just beginning. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
A many-sided concept
by Ahmad Hasnawi
The vision of time in Islamic culture has so many aspectsreligious, philosophical and scientific-
that it cannot be reduced to a simple formula
W
26
AHMAD HASNAWI,
Tunisian philosopher, is a
researcher at the French
National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS), Paris. The
author of studies on al-Farabi,
Avicenna and Averroës, he is
currently carrying out research
into the "natural philosophy"
of Muslim philosophers.
HEN seeking to describe the concept of time,
space or any other basic notion specific to a given
civilization, it would be useful if we could find
a distinctive form of words to sum up that civili¬
zation's character.
But this would be to fall victim to two sim¬
plistic assumptions. One is that civilizations are
discrete and unconnected. The other is that each
civilization has its own special insight into time,
which is reflected in various ways in the
"regions" of that civilization.
The following brief comments about the con¬
cept of time in Islamic culture are intended to sug¬
gest that these two assumptions cannot be
accepted at face value.
Qur'anic time
We cannot here consider the Qur'anic view of
time in all its richness, and shall therefore dwell
on three points only.
The first is that the Qur'an integrates time
as an essential aspect of revelation. The "divine
teaching" was adapted to the circumstances of the
Prophet's actions, and responded to his doubts,
his questionings, and the situation of the infant
Islamic community as regards both its organiza¬
tion and its relationships with other communities.
The second concerns "sacred history" as it
develops in the Qur'an in accordance with this
divine teaching. The early Meccan revelations
focused on the cycle of creation-cosmic break-up
and total destruction-recreation, in which every
soul is judged according to its actions. But in the
middle of the first Meccan period (from the begin¬
ning of the revelation until the years 615-616) reli¬
gious history acquired temporal substance. In the
first phase this history mainly took the form of
the manifestation of divine judgements on the
peoples who rejected the Word and on sinful
communities. But soon this aspect, while not dis¬
appearing altogether, gave way to a history of the
divine revelations, which established a genealog¬
ical and spiritual continuity between the bearers
of these revelations, each confirming his
predecessor's message.
The third point concerns a basic temporal
notion in the Qur'an, that of a "stated term" or
"fixed term" (ajal musamma), which is applied
in particular to the lives of people, human com¬
munities, and the world. Behind this and similar
expressions lies the idea of an "allocated span"
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
.e. ':
I LDI ,k.vl,
i
Î Hl v07S s
Copper sundial dating from
the reign of the Muslim ruler
Nur ad-Din (Nureddln), late
12th century.
"Worship timetable"
indicating the hours of prayer
at the Great Mosque of Xian,
capital of Shaanxi province,
northwest China.
whose duration is fixed by divine decreean idea
in keeping with the affirmation of God's pres¬
cience and omnipotence, but also containing
within it the notion that the life-span of beings
and things is in a sense subject to quasi-natural
laws, to a divinely-ordained legal system.
Astronomy and liturgical time
The Muslim calendar is lunar. Liturgical time,
especially the determination of the beginning and
end of the fasting month (Ramadan), is bound up
with observation of the New Moon. For secular
time and the timing of the daily prayers unequal
hours were used, their length varying according
to the season and the latitude. Equal hours were
mainly used in astronomy.
Muslim astronomers carried out intensive
research into ways of predicting the appearance
of the crescent Moon and of measuring time
(there was a science of the measurement of time,
Urn al-miqat). Particularly interested in liturgical
time, they drew up tables to determine the hour
of prayer for every day of the year, and developed
sundials and astrolabes marked with curves cor¬
responding to these times.
We feel tempted to suggest that these scien¬
tific developments were not actuated by liturgical
needs. Firstly, jurists tended to exclude arithmetic
when it came to forecasting the new Moon;
and secondly research into the visibility of the
new Moon was part of the natural development
of astronomy. Indeed, prayer curves were prob¬
ably only a sort of appendage to the theory and
art of sundials and astrolabes. Scholars who
claimed that their work was of value to the faith
probably only did so in order to please the
enlightened ruler who had encouraged them to
take it up.
On the other hand, however, scholars' preoc¬
cupation with religion can be interpreted as a sign
that they were fulfilling a social demand. This is
confirmed both by the frequent use of sundials
in mosques and also by the tendency of mosques
to employ the services of a muwaqqit, or specialist
in the measurement of time, who might, like the
fourteenth-century Damascene Ibn al-Shatir, be
a great astronomer. This social demand provided
astronomer-mathematicians with a testing-ground
for their theories.
Universal histories
Muslim historiography is characterized by its
richness and the scale of its output. It was also
extremely diverse, both in its subject-matter
(urban, regional, provincial and universal histo¬
ries; religious and secular histories) and in its
method of presentation (genealogical, dynastic,
annalistic or by generation), all these approaches
sometimes being combined.
With the beginning of a strictly Muslim era,
starting with the Prophet's Hegira or migration
from Mecca to Yathrib (Medina), the annalistic
form, in which events are recorded on an annual
basis, gained a valuable chronological framework.
The universal histories also contain attempts to
synchronize the histories of the different peoples
of the pre-Islamic period. The idea of a universal
history in fact implies a single temporal con¬
tinuum into which natural and cultural events are
fitted. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The General' s watch
Paris 23 Feb 1789.His Excellency General Washington
Dear General,
Upon my arrival at this Place I spoke to Mr. Jefferson on the
Subject of your Watch. He told me that the Man who had made
Maddison's was a Rogue and recommended me to another,
Romilly. But as it might happen that this also was a Rogue
I enquired at a very honest Man's Shop, not a Watch Maker, and
he recommended Gregson. A Gentleman with me assured me
that Gregson was a Rogue, and both of them agreed that Romilly
is of the old School and he and his Watches out of Fashion. And
to say that of a Man in Paris, is like saying he is an ordinary
Man among the Friends of Philadelphia. I found at last that
Mr. L'Epine is at the Head of his Profession here, and in
Consequence asks more for his work than any Body else.
I therefore waited on MT. L'Epine and agreed with him for
two Watches exactly alike, one of which will be for you and
the other for me....
Gouverneur Morris
(Letter to George Washington, in A Diary of the French Revolution
by Gouverneur Morris 1752-1816, Minister to France during the Terror
© Houghton Mifflin Company, Boston, 1939.)
28
At the end of the eighth century and the
beginning of the ninth, most Muslim theologians
adopted an atomist doctrine, which dealt both
with matter (and the accidents that might attach
thereto) and with time. According to this doc¬
trine, bodies consist of indivisible homogeneous
particles, which are distinguished from each other
only by the presence in them of accidents which
endow them with a given characteristic. Some
theologians (the Mu'tazilites) held that bodies
comprising these atoms and certain accidents last
beyond the moment when they come into being.
Others (the Ash'arites) considered that every acci¬
dent is continually recreated by God, just as
atoms and bodies only last by virtue of an acci¬
dent which is continually recreated in them by
God.
The world: finite or eternal?
Muslim philosophers, whose philosophical ac¬
tivity followed in the wake of Aristotle and the
neo-Platonists, opposed the theologians not only
over the doctrine of atomism (for them, as for
Aristotle, time was continuous) but also as regards
the eternity of the world.
Al-Kindi (d. circa 866) held that the world
had a finite span; but from al-Farabi (d. 950)
onwards philosophers adopted the thesis that the
world is eternal. They did not deny the world's
causal dependence on first principles, and on
God, but they did not recognize a first moment
marking the beginning of the world. The debate
between supporters and opponents of the idea of
an eternal world involved problems relating to
infinity, causality, the logical difficulties inherent
in the idea of a beginning of the world, and the
relationship between knowledge and divine will
on the one hand and time on the other.
This brief account of Islamic thinking about
time shows that it is not a single body of thought
characteristic of Islamic culture as a whole; nor
can it be defined by a form of words that would
englobe all its variants. There have been sporadic
attempts to explain certain temporal behaviour
patterns in present-day Islamic societies by
presupposing a specifically Muslim view of time;
but this is merely to introduce (in addition to the
two assumptions mentioned at the beginning of
this article) a sort of "cultural fatalism" to the
effect that man's conduct and image are deter¬
mined by a vision laid down as a timeless
paradigm.
Water clock with automata as
described in al-Jazari's
13th-century Book of
Knowledge of Ingenious
Mechanical Devices.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The concentric bands of colour In
agate, right, correspond to successive
layers of deposition from solution in the
cavities of rocks.
Present imperfect
by
Trapped between a mythical past and radiant visions of the future, the present in Latin America is
often overlooked
JLh.HE further the boat goes the more its pas¬
sage becomes a journey into time and the history
of the landscape." Thus, in surprise, the hero of
the novel Canaima, by the Venezuelan writer
Rómulo Gallegos, as he travels up the Orinoco
to its source in the heart of the forests of Guiana.
His character needs no Wellsian time machine to
cross the watertight bulkheads of seemingly time-
arrested Latin American history.
Such an experience is no mere literary
gambit. Travellers who range the continent may
get the impression that they are living in another
era. By boat or plane, on foot or on muleback,
they can trace the course of history backwards
from ultra-modern capitals to villages and tribes
living as at the dawn of history. Past and present
lifestyles coexist cheek by jowl, albeit separated
and insulated from one another like the geolo¬
gical strata that mark out the history of mankind.
This gives any thought about the perception of 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Is not time
as love i s ?
And an astronomer said, Master,
what of Time?
And he answered:
You would measure time the
measureless and the immeasurable.
You would adjust your conduct
and even direct the course of your
spirit according to hours and seasons.
Of time you would make a
stream upon whose bank you would
sit and watch its flowing.
Yet the timeless in you is aware
of life's timelessness,
And knows that yesterday is but
today's memory and tomorrow is
today's dream.
And that that which sings and
contemplates in you is still dwelling
within the bounds of that first
moment which scattered the stars
into space.
Who among you does not feel
that his power to love is boundless?
And yet who does not feel that
very love, though boundless,
encompassed within the centre of his
being, and moving not from love
thought to love thought, nor from
love deeds to other love deeds?
And is not time even as love is,
undivided and spaceless?
But if in your thought you must
measure time into seasons, let each
season encircle all the other seasons,
And let today embrace the past
with remembrance and the future
with longing.
Khalil Gibran
Lebanese writer
(The Prophet © Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1964)
time a spatial connotation. "Latin America is a
continent in which prehistoric man, medieval
man and modern man can shake hands with each
other", to quote the striking image of the Cuban
writer Alejo Carpentier.
This characteristic, which means that the
successive layers of pre-Columbian, colonial,
African and modern art can all be seen at one
and the same time, sometimes in a single land¬
scape, has intrigued many travellers. When André
Breton visited Mexico in 1938 he thought
that in this world of superimposed eras he had
found the natural setting for the Surrealist revo¬
lution. Others were to use expressions such as
"magical realism" and "marvellous reality" to
describe various features of the Latin American
scene.
The perception of time has clearly become
a matter of controversy since the European dis¬
covery of America. Past, present and future suc¬
ceed one another not in a smooth sequence but
in a chaotic evolution closely related to subjec¬
tive factors such as intentions, wishes, life itself,
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
and to the feeling that Oswald Spengler called the
"organic character" of time.
The idealized past of the pre-Hispanic Indian
world contrasts strongly with the notion of a
future of high technology and the hectic pace of
international economic activity. But the past
stands also for the nostalgia evoked by a pre-
industrial, rural, patriarchal order of a kind that
survives in many parts of the continent. It is a
past that may be the model for a future sought
both by reactionary conservatives and romantic
revolutionaries.
No sooner was America discovered by Euro¬
peans than it became the repository of beliefs no
longer current in Europe. There were many signs
to suggest that the golden age of the origins of
mankind existed in the New Worldan era of
plenty, of human happiness and loving coexis¬
tence, as celebrated by the poets and historians of
Greece and Rome, with heavenly Arcadian land¬
scapes, a warm climate, and a cornucopia of fruit
a state of nature. The time lost in Iron Age Europe
was caught up in sixteenth-century America.
Street scene in Cuenca
(Ecuador).
Christendom was to find a new eschatology
in America. Instead of the traditional view, under
which a temporal earthly world is set against an
eternal celestial one, America saw the outset of
an immanent dualism in which "times past" were
part of this world. The era of early Christianity,
the golden age and Paradise lost could be repro¬
duced in a different setting here below.
Moreover, as the Mexican historian Miguel
León-Portilla has pointed out, pre-Hispanic
myths collected by missionaries and chroniclers
themselves refer to an era in which mankind lived
in happiness and plenty. Some people saw the
American Indians as a people naturally inclined
to justice, knowing nothing of the evils of pro¬
perty. There were even forecasts of a "silver age
of the Indian Church", in which the virtues of
the early Church would be recreated thanks to
this rediscovery of spiritual purity.
This idealized version of the Indian past was
served up by historians throughout the sixteenth
century, became a commonplace, and survives to
the present day in many books about ancient
American civilizations. Endowing the pre-
Columbian past with the virtues of an ideal eco¬
nomic, social and political system eventually leads
people to believe that all the continent's subse¬
quent ills stemmed from the Spanish conquest.
This Manichean simplification of the situation
before and after 12 October 1492 is still keenly
topical. Five centuries after the shock of the
encounter between two worlds, the conflicts bet¬
ween America's past, present and future still give
rise to controversy and polemic.
The future as change and progress
The ideas of the Enlightenment, and a century
later of positivism, gave America an acute per¬
ception of time to come. The passage of time
became "evolution", and could even bring radical
changes. Thus when their nations achieved inde¬
pendence people aspired to invent the future.
Politicians and intellectuals began to organize
what they called new times.
Time and change became inseparably linked,
but the extent of change proposed for a given
time span varied. Some peopleSarmiento in
Argentina and Vasconcelos in Mexico, for
instancehad such faith in progress that they
thought of the future as a present in continual
evolution, its growth depending on education and
the momentum of population increase, whether
stemming from immigration or a "cosmic" race
born of interbreeding.
Others favoured radical, revolutionary
change. A clean break should be made with the
past. An impatient sort of trust in providence
guided revolutions that shook countries in which
nothing would ever be the same again.
Such telescoping of the future tends to make 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Incas, an 18th-century
French wallpaper motif
inspired by Jean-François
Marmontel's philosophical
romance Les fncas ou fa
destruction de l'empire du
Pérou (1777), which
denounced intolerance and
religious fanaticism.
the consciousness of individuals coalesce on a
shared time scale. And this collective time scale
is at one with a world view that has its own
rituals, social values, beliefs, metaphors and lan¬
guage. In this situation time is not merely repre¬
sented; it is also experienced. It produces a spe¬
cific feeling.
Between past and future
This feeling about time seeks its bearings in an
oscillation between past and future. Human
beings naturally tend to idealize the past and see
it as better than it was, and also to neutralize their
illusions about the futurethe more so as they
get closer to the present. This habit of continually
upgrading the past and the future seems to meet
people's deep need to justify their existence and
give direction to their lives. The French writer
and sociologist Jean Cazeneuve, who has inves¬
tigated relationships between time and happiness
in various cultures, speaks of recognition (in the
sense both of acknowledgement and gratitude) of
everything that becomes a memory. The
archetypes of anticipatory awareness, on the
other hand, are sustained by many clichés about
the past. The Mexican essayist Alfonso Reyes has
emphasized the need people feel to think that
they have come from a better age and are moving
towards another better agethe urge to counter¬
balance memories and hopes.
This dialectic of old and new, which has enor¬
mous symbolic significance, is not always fully
appreciated in historical writing. Perhaps great
literature can take account of it: Jorge Luis
Borges, in Historia de la eternidad (1936), says that
"preservation and creation, though at variance
here below, are synonymous in heaven". In other
words, the only possible reconciliation between
the conflicting components of time is in eternity.
Such a solution is not likely to satisfy an empiri¬
cist, for in Latin America this reconciliation bet¬
ween past and future is related to the difficulty
of living in the present.
The great majority of the peoples of Latin
America, a prey to problems of surviving in mar¬
ginalized poverty or exposed to political instabi¬
lity and economic inflation, can only live from
day to day. They are condemned to perform a
daily balancing act, ignorant of the past and
unable to rely on the future. The very word
mañana, so often repeated in this context and
habitually associated with the Latin American
condition, is simply a way of deferring the solu¬
tion of immediate difficulties to an equally ques¬
tionable future.
Rather than idealizing or denigrating the past,
or placing undue faith in the future, the best thing
in this continent which is still known as the New
World would perhaps be to engage in a search
for the present. Such a search, as Octavio Paz said
in his Nobel Prize acceptance speech in 1990,
means neither renouncing the future nor forget¬
ting the past. "The present," he said, "is the meet¬
ing place of all three times." This is true time
"the present, being present".
32
FERNANDO AINSA,
Uruguayan writer, is a UNESCO
staff member. He is the author
of many essays and novels
including Identidad cultural de
Iberoamérica en su narrativa
(Gredos, Madrid, 1986), and
Necesidad de la utopía (Nordan
Comunidad, Buenos
Aires/Montevideo, 1990).
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
M
IWWP^ m
B '<jr SÛT* A '^|
f IÍ
A ^Vj ^
By x ^
M
^^.
^^
*/*
LT N^
r^&.H^i
fea^^V |
~2
i'^Hl ^^
»' *"'
Quartz time
The modern world has shattered the
concept of time on which Western
society was nurtured
Quartz (the colourless
variety known as rock
crystal), from Brazil.
X ACED with the imponderables of time, history
and the meaning of life, the so-called post-
industrial societies of the West are chanting the
sad refrain of crisis. Yet what is seen as a crisis
is often no more than a period of change from
one state of the human condition to another, the
death rattle of one system of symbols challenged
by another more capable of reflecting a new
vision of the world. Modernity's cry of terror
could only emerge from a way of thought still
rooted in a vanishing world.
Modernity is, by definition, in a state of cons¬
tant rupture, firstly with the old worldthat of
the Christian universeand secondly with the
new world, itself destined to become old in its
turn. Condemned to continual renewal, moder¬
nity is a perpetual process of drift. Freed from
the rationality of the past, the most insignificant
aspects of the present break off in all directions.
The legendary rivers of time, which once charted
a linear vision of History, have merged into an
ocean in which anything is possible. The history
of events, with its clear-cut succession of cause
and effect, has disintegrated, and a host of
thematic studies attempt to reconstitute, step by
step, a prism with an infinite number of facets.
What has been lost, seemingly for ever, is the
sense of a continuum that held everything
together. What substitute could there be for linear
time stretched between two pointsfrom sin to
redemptionother than a discontinuous percep¬
tion of a fragmentary temporality? Bereft of the
will of God and of the unity of values that gave
it cohesion, time becomes no more than an
absurd succession of isolated moments. The
vision of the flow of time is replaced by that of
the passing of individual seconds. The notions of
duration and expectation are replaced by those
of instantaneity and precision. As the French
thinker Gaston Bachelard said, "Time no longer
flows, it erupts".
Quartz and the search for precision
Yet, subjected though we are to this senseless dis¬
persal of moments, are we not still aware of a
"code of poetic fidelity" to time? Where concep¬
tual vision is lacking, are there not new
metaphors of time? When we moved from geo¬
metric, space-defined time to more functional
numerical time, we thought we were finally rid
of time metaphors. Not a bit of it. Time may
have pulverized space, but the dust of space is a
new metaphor. And what if, against all expecta¬
tion, in an allegedly disenchanted world, we are
all wearing a metaphor on our wrists?
In a quartz watch, time is no longer meas¬
ured by mechanical movement but by the
vibration of a quartz crystala mechanically
immobile, electronically regulated vibration that
takes just one forty-thousandth of a second.
Quartz has no part in any theological vision of
time. Here, time emerges from the vibration
immanent in the original matter and from that
immanence alone. Instantly, just before they
vanish for ever, the seconds show up in a flicker 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
of light. Liquid crystals display their hasty passage.
Then, more slowly, the internecine warfare of
minutes and hours is revealed. Time is "crystal¬
lized" to satisfy our compulsive interest in details,
details, details. The contemporary mind is
obsessed with the infinitesimal. Infinity is
reversed and reconquered in the perfect density
of the crystalline instant. Liquid crystalsthe
metaphor reunites discrete particles and reinvents
flow. Time's crystals melt into duration and
spread out into daily life.
Thus, the vibrations of a quartz crystal are
calculated so as to attain extreme precision, which
in turn determines the value of the watch itself.
Yet, although they may be indispensable for
scientific research, ultra-sophistication and pre¬
cision in the measurement of time have little
impact on our ordinary sense perceptions. Our
eyes ignore the gaps between one numerical ins¬
tant and another, thus recreating the sense of
duration. There is, indeed, a larger time scale than
that of the self-consuming second; there is a sense
of duration that the micro-eternity of divisibility
cannot smother. Watches go out of fashion, bat¬
teries run down, wrists become wrinkled.
Living at top speed
At the very heart of his existence, modern man
is enmeshed in a tangle of time scales and a var¬
iety of distinct yet simultaneous rhythms.
Whether we like it or not, Universal Time con¬
trols our collective time. The same throughout
the world, time has become a form of currency.
The division of time into fixed units enables us
to sell or to buy packets of activity which have
become virtually autonomous objects.
Thus time becomes a closed dimension, a
complete assemblage of empty compartments
that have to be filled, that is to say, to be used
in the best possible way. When time is not used,
it is lost: nothing has been produced in it. The
purpose of technology is, above all, to gain time,
in other words to turn out, in the shortest pos¬
sible time, products that will be consumed in an
even shorter time. The time gained is used for
further production.
Spare time, paradoxically, is subject to the
same pressures. It is like capital that we possess
and must not lose. Spare time is taken up with
leisure activities and entertainment, just as work
takes up time, and we apply ourselves to it in the
same spirit of productivity. The product that we
consume is a sense of well-being which we put
to the service of greater productivity, which
remains the only real objective.
This induces in us the absurd feeling that time
is shrinking. The pace of life accelerates to com¬
pensate for this terrible diminution. That "life
is short" is not a new perception, yet the Western
Monumental clock face
(c. 1500), by the Flemish
artist Quentin Metsys.
world no longer builds cathedrals that will
endure. A comparison of the quartz watch and
another, very ancient, method of measuring time,
the clepsydra, or water clock, will help us to grasp
the change that has occurred.
The clepsydra measures the passing of each
hour taken from us by the flow of water from
one receptacle into another. However, the time
that passes, like the water that flows, is not lost,
but is stored in memory just as the water is stored
in a receptacle. Loss is converted into gain, the
gain increases as time passes and something
remains of what is no more. Finally, when
nothing is left, the receptacles are exchanged and
the cycle starts again.
The notion of the cumulative nature of time
and of perpetuity ensured by transmission (of a
collective, linear memory) are lacking in contem¬
porary perceptions of time. On the face of a dig¬
ital watch the seconds flare briefly but for
nothing. Nothing remains, nothing is gained.
Time seems to be rushing headlong, wasted,
towards. ..nothing.
By breaking with the notion of a linear con¬
tinuum which, as it were, propelled humanity
towards its ideal goal, and within which every
event was meaningful to the extent that it
favoured or compromised its achievement, we are
breaking with a whole range of valueshistory,
progress, hope for a better future. The hope that,
at the end of time, all this would be achieved
which kept people in suspense has given way to
an anguished search for instant satisfaction. The
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
A floral clock
In St. Mark's Square, Venice, the pigeons assemble in their
thousands at 9 o'clock and 2 o'clock every day. They wait
there for the grain that people throw to them, not because
the clock strikes but because they have an instinctive and
approximate knowledge of the time.
What unconscious internal metronome determines this
vast gathering? The answer is not simple and does not
depend, like Linnaeus's floral clock, on a simple reaction
to a known physical stimulus. Linnaeus proposed a floral
clock consisting of 13 different flowers whose calyxes
opened and closed at different hours between 6 in the
morning and 6 at night.
Edouard Boné
Belgian biologist
("Temps et durée au regard du biologiste", from
Temps et devenir © Presses Universitaires de Louvain-la-Neuve, 1984.)
quest for day-to-day pleasure is a more modest
and less uncertain goal.
With no future in our sights, our desires can
only be fulfilled by frantic consumption of the
present. When the objective is eliminated, it reap¬
pears in many places but in impoverished and
diminished guise. Just as the death of God as
announced by Nietzsche has led to a desperate
proliferation of the sacred, so the lack of a final
justification for existence has spawned a desire to
give some kind of meaning, however derisory,
to even the briefest spans of time. Nevertheless,
however rapid the pace of consumption and the
acceleration of the rhythms of life, people die,
finitude bears them ineluctably away.
Rhythm and repetition
Contemporary art forms reflect this rupture
of the time continuum. One piece of evidence
for this is the demise of the long book. In litera¬
ture, narrators seem to have run out of steam;
they no longer tell stories. At best they describe
the trivial course of ordinary lives. Beckett is
the supreme example of the writer of contem¬
porary tragedy. He evokes a world of hiatuses,
a world which is, along with language, at the
point of dissolution.
However, though the tale may dissolve and
fiction be impossible, the timbre of the voice, the
punctuation, the scansion and the pace give time
a new lease of life. The problem brings its own
solution. Unity is rediscovered by expressing the
The Genitron, a digital quartz
clock, was started in 1987 at
the Georges Pompidou Centre,
Paris. It is counting down the
number of seconds until the
year 2000. For 13 years, with
no maintenance, it will be
accurate to within a
thousandth of a second.
fracture that has destroyed it. The death of time
can only be evoked in time reborn.
This time reborn, however, is a different sort
of time. Its unity is not that of a homogeneous
flow, but lies in regularity and the mastery of
rhythm. In music, rhythm has taken the place
of harmony. It brings order to multiplicity,
and makes a compromise between the tumult
of the perceptions and the rationality of the
senses.
The novelty does not lie in the new rhythms
introduced by technology, but in the develop¬
ment of rhythmic technology. No longer merely
one possible interpretation among many, rhythm
has become the fixed, autonomous framework
within which variations are set. The "rhythm
machine" dictates the broad outlines of a piece
of music; everything else is a kind of musical small
talk. In order to retain some freedom for inven¬
tion, we have to concentrate on the technolog¬
ical production of new sounds or, as a last resort,
on exaggerating the constraints of rhythm and
giving vent to a terrifying torrent of verbal vio¬
lence from between the ever more closely spaced
bars of a cage of sound.
Contemporary music reflects the bewilder¬
ment of the voice caught up in the repetitive,
impersonal world of technology. Xenakis was
very near the mark when he spoke of the impos¬
sibility of communicating through repetition. All
that technology has to offer is the possibility of
manipulating and juggling with the basics of
sound.
The cybernetic age
In its present state, music, par excellence the art
of tempo, of manipulating tempo within time,
gives us a picture of how, within the logic of
cybernetics, the instant is assimilated to the
notion of duration. For a computer, duration is
simply a series of instants and their storage, and
memory is merely a data bank. It is not just by
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Micrographie image of a grain
of sand taken through a
polarizing filter.
36
AYYAM WASSEF,
Egyptian essayist, is preparing
a doctoral thesis at the
University of Paris I (Sorbonne)
on the theme of the individual
in contemporary philosophy,
and writing an account of her
experiences as an Egyptian
living in Paris.
chance that the logic of cybernetics has emerged
in an age when children can be conceived of
fathers who died several years earlier. The future
is no longer controlled by the laws of transmis¬
sion, but by those of composition.
The age of creation by composition is
equipped to combine temporalities in a general¬
ized anachronism. It is still too early to say what
effect this will have on our common perception
of time, but it will certainly be considerable, since
we are here touching upon one of humankind's
oldest certaintiesthe laws of birth and death,
reproduction and transmission. Already the
immense capacities for storing information
everything, from the genetic code to the master¬
pieces of the Renaissance, has become
"information" have rendered obsolete the
notion of collective immortality based on the
transmission of knowledge. It would seem that
we are returning to a certain form of deter¬
minism, in the sense that everything is already
there and that the future will depend upon com
binations of pre-existing possibilities. The past
and the future are becoming merged into a com¬
pound present.
The age of creation by composition began
with the visual industries, of which television,
which creates more varied time warps than the
cinema, is the most typical. With "live" broad¬
casts there is every likelihood that viewing time
will become confused with real time. Television
abhors the messiness of reality, and (like nature)
it abhors a vacuum. When, due to some technical
failure, there is such a vacuum, the presenter
stammers away in real time perhaps the only
real time ever seen on television and a moment
which seems to the viewer painfully long and
inadequate. But the messiness of real life is never
shown. Every effort is made to filter out the
coarse realities and to blend them into a
homogenized narrative sequence.
Television time comes to replace all other
forms of time in our awareness. An event only
happens if it has been seen on television, and
however long it may actually have lasted, its
importance is gauged by the viewing time allotted
to it by the producer. A news item, the same
pictures of which have been shown over and
over again, becomes a tragedy with as many acts
as the number of times it is screened. What
does it matter, it may be asked, if the impression
is false, provided that it has been collectively
experienced? Are there, in fact, any truths other
than shared lies? The viewer is reduced to a
terrifying state of solitude. His or her only
interlocutor is television itself, which indulges
in endless self-appraisal and ensures that there is
never the slightest moment of silence. Time is so
crowded with images that it becomes impossible
to see.
Is there any family resemblance between the
liquid crystal display of a quartz watch, which
registers a succession of instants frozen in time,
and the television screen on which images appear
in an artificially recovered continuum? Perhaps
there is, but it is too approximate to be worth
dwelling upon.
The uninterrupted procession of images on
television has nothing in common with the agility
of crystals suspended in an invisible flux. Time
exists between the inscription of two seconds;
above all, there is the possibility of a meaning.
Between two recorded seconds, there is some
empty, lost time. All that is needed to dispel the
absurd is to build a bridge between the two
seconds. Just as it makes a break between two
instants, this gap alone makes possible their true
reconciliation.
Thus, time torn apart, time interspersed with
gaps, time shot through with emptiness, so
bewailed by moderns, is perhaps the best hope
of rebuilding new links between man and the
world, between reality and meaning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
'A desire for eternity'
by Alexandre Cioranescu
Novelists who are haunted by time, manipulate it in their work, and try to escape from it by the
very act of writing
Above, Where Do We Come
From? What Are We? Where
Are We Going? (1897),
by the French artist
Paul Gauguin (1848-1903).
0,'F all the familiar features of our daily lives,
time is the one we know least about. We shall
never fully understand its mysteries, still less iso¬
late and tame it.
Yet time is not a distant, indifferent truth,
like a star which we know to be inaccessible. We
are totally dependent upon it. Time makes and
unmakes us, obliges us to exist and yet not know
what will become of us. Our pact with time is
both metaphysical and make-believe. Yet though
it leaves a permanent and indelible mark, its
presence escapes us.
The important place time holds in literature
and the arts is revealing, for not only does it have
an impact on our lives and our thinking, it also
weighs like an obsession on our imagination and
on our feelings.
The old man with the scythe
Although no specific image is attached to it, the
concept of time is omnipresent in the plastic arts.
It has been portrayed countless times allegorically
or symbolically, in terms of its attributes and of
the traces it leaves behind.
First of all, time is seen as responsible for
physical decline and death. Thus it has been iden¬
tified with the figure of Death, traditionally por¬
trayed in Western art as an image of old age and
decrepitude and sometimes even as a corpse.
Generally speaking, however, Time is depicted
in medieval and Renaissance art in the shape of
a skeletal old man with a long white beard. He
holds a great scythe, the symbol of collective
death, and carries a lantern, indicating that a life
is about to be extinguished. This allegory is used
to portray both Time and Death.
Some painters have evoked the passing of
time by showing the contrast between old age and
childhood or between the ages of man. The suc¬
cession of the generations may be represented as
a peaceful guarantee of continuity. It can also be
portrayed as the violent irruption of the young
who eliminate the old, the classic example being
that of the Greek god Chronos (the Roman
Saturn), who toppled his father from the throne
only to be toppled in his turn by his own son
Zeus (the Roman Jupiter). The notion of time is
also evident in the theme of decomposition, as
seen in sculptures of the dead and in certain
paintings, the most eloquent of which is the
Spanish artist Juan de Valdés Leal's famous work 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
Finis Gloriae Mundi (1672). Another form of
reflection on the theme of the passing of time can
be seen in the studies of ruins which were
fashionable in the painting, poetry and garden
design of the late eighteenth century.
Novelists who conjure
with time
In literature, obsession with time is even more
central. There are many ways in which the dread
of time enters the process of literary creation, for
literature more than painting lends itself to the
evocation of time. In literature an image of time
can be created which, if not more exact, is at least
more intelligible and closer to our phantasms.
Literature has always drawn its inspiration
from real life, from the mysteries of the inner life
or the problems of human relationships. It is not
surprising, therefore, that time should be so
important in the structure of literary works, espe¬
cially in epic or narrative literature. Time punc¬
tuates the novelist's thoughts. As the French critic
Albert Thibaudet (1874-1936) once remarked,
temporality is the key to the composition of the
novel.
As in the theatre and in the epic poem (a
genre that today has disappeared), the content of
the traditional novelits plotis a voyage
through time that mimics what happens in life.
The episodes unfold in chronological order. It is
rather like what happens in the theatre, where
no actor would venture on stage before receiving
his cue.
Logical and easy to follow, this type of nar¬
rative has been used in imaginative literature for
Finis Gloriae Mundi
by the Spanish artist Juan de
Valdés Leal (1622-1690), an
allegory on the vanity of the
world and the flesh.
over 2,000 years. It also allows a writer to take
certain liberties. From time to time a classic
author may suddenly say "I forgot to say that..."
as a pretext for departing from a strict chrono¬
logical framework in order to recount an episode
which it would have been difficult to describe in
its proper time sequence. Some novelists make
excessive use of this subterfuge just for the
pleasure of playing with time. In Laurence
Sterne's Tristram Shandy (1759) the sequence of
the story returns so often to the past that the
action seems to go backwards rather than
forwards.
With the Romantics, playing with time
became current practice in narrative literature.
The simplest method was to use a kind of con¬
juring trick as the American author Washington
Irving did in his famous tale Rip Van Winkle, the
hero of which falls asleep for twenty years,
perhaps to escape from his shrewish wife, whom
he allows enough time to die.
Roaming through the centuries
The European Romantics gave a new importance
to the recapturing of the past through memory.
In the words of George Sand's Lélia (1833), "The
main occupation of my life was constantly to turn
back to lost joys". In the twentieth century,
Marcel Proust's novel A la recherche du temps
perdu is dominated by the narrator's search for
"lost time". But "the remembrance of things
past" is a difficult process because of what Proust
calls the heart's intermissionswhen feeling and
memory do not go hand in hand. Memory only
lights up the past in fits and starts. It is through
an involuntary memory, not true remembrance,
that time is regained.
Other writers have gone much further back
in time. The great nineteenth-century Romanian
poet Mihail Eminescu made his Poor Denis travel
back to the beginning of the fifteenth century.
Ravage, by the contemporary French author
René Barjavel, is a novel of paradox: his traveller
into the past finds himself unable to return to the
present.
Novelists move about just as freely in the
future. Anticipatory novels already have a long
and glorious history stretching from the seven¬
teenth century to the present day. One of the
earliest was the seventeenth-century writer Abbé
de Pure's Epigone. H.G. Wells's The Time Machine
(1895), is a classic of time exploration which has
inspired many modern works. Louis Sébastien
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Death and the Woodcutter
(1859), engraving after a
painting by the French artist
Jean-François Millet.
Historical time
and cosmic time
All my generation, from the Marxists to Sartre, is
dominated by the discovery of History and of
historicity, insofar as man is a being who lives in
irreversible historical time. But I am opposed to such a
reduction, not that I am afraid of History, but because
man also lives in a non-historical time: dream time,
time within the imagination, etc.
I do not see, in particular, any reason for the
exclusion of cosmic time, which is not irreversible but
cyclical, and so important for the human species, which
is also part of the cosmos, as we are too inclined to
forget. I simply mean that we cannot dismiss
something that everyone experiences and knows: the
rhythmic succession of day and night, the ceaseless
round of the seasons. These are human experiences of a
cosmological nature, in which time is cyclical. To take
them into account does not entail an escape from
History, but an opening upon an admirable and
entirely palpable transcendence, which makes possible
communication with nature, animals, and plants.
Mircea Eliade
Romanian historian of religions
(Temps libre No. 2, summer 1981, Paris)
Mercier's visitation of Paris in The Year 2440
(1771) is another notable example of the genre.
There is another form of literature that
delights in breaking the rules of time. Superfi¬
cially it appears to respect chronological order
but actually it scorns the notion of life-span, of
"real" time, and, like the Wandering Jew, its
characters roam across the centuries. The hero
of Virginia Woolf's Orlando (1928) is sixteen
years old at the start of the novel and thirty-six
when it ends. This would be a perfectly normal
period were it not for the fact that, in the mean¬
time, 342 years have elapsed, during which the
hero has assumed a variety of characters of both
sexes. In Borges' story The Immortal, a twentieth-
century antique dealer rubs shoulders with the
great figures of Antiquity.
Many modern writers have no scruples about
chronology and refuse to see time as a narrative
constraint. The novel ceases to be action and
becomes "stasis", or a contraction of time. In
Alain Robbe-Grillet's "film/novel" Last Year in
Marienbad (1961) the universe becomes "a per¬
petual present, which makes all recourse to
memory impossible". Chronological telescoping
and banality of action are the hallmarks of the
works of Claude Simon. In William Faulkner's
writing chronological disorder is so marked that
to his Absalom, Absalom! (1936), an exploration
across time which pays no attention to the
chronological sequence of events, he felt it neces¬
sary to add a chronology indicating the time and
place at which each episode occurred.
Seizing the moment
This deliberate attempt to banish temporality
from literature is liable to be seen purely as an
exercise in virtuosity. Is it not, perhaps, more
apparent than real? Even when the attention is
not drawn to it, the sense of time remains
indelibly in the background. To pretend to forget
time is to wish to eliminate the precarious,
ephemeral nature of all that is touched by time.
It is not time that the writer seeks to suppress
but the fragility that time imposes on all things.
Here the absence of time implies not a void, but
a desire for eternity.
The mind is troubled by the eternal, the
desire to endurethe dread of history is only a
passing anxiety. Anguish comes from the cruel
knowledge that eternity can only be attained
within the void of the after-life. It is felt by all
writers and poets. This is what William Blake was 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Imaginary View of the Grand
Gallery of the Louvre in Ruins
(1796), by the French
landscape painter Hubert
Robert (1733-1808).
40
ALEXANDRE CIORANESCU,
Romanian-born writer
specializing in literary studies,
has published a number of
works on French, Spanish and
Romanian literature, as well as
essays on comparative
literature including "The
Baroque or the Discovery of
Drama" (in Spanish) and "The
Mask and the Face" (1983, in
French). He has also translated
Dante's Divine Comedy, the
writings of Christopher
Columbus, and other historical
works.
thinking of when he wrote that it was his duty
to "open up eternal worlds".
How can this challenge be met? Some valiant
attempts have been made to identify the point
at which the contradictions of time disappear. For
Dante, these contradictions are resolved in a
present that he finds in God. For Shelley, in a
concomitant vision of past, present and future.
For Novalis, time is a condensation into a
spiritual present which identifies past and future
by merging one with the other. If all these intui¬
tions are no more than subterfuges of the imagi¬
nation, they are nevertheless ways of giving
permanence to time.
One much-used way of achieving this con¬
cretion is to make time stand still at a given
moment. Jean-Jacques Rousseau relates how, on
the island of Saint-Pierre, he experienced
moments of happiness in which time ceased to
exist and the present seemed to be eternal.
According to Proust, "a minute freed from
the order of time has recreated in us, so that we
can feel it, a man freed from the order of time"
it liberates us from what we have called the dread
of history. In Finnegans Wake (1939), James Joyce
condenses (or expands) the content of a moment's
experience into 600 pages. The experience,
however, is frustrating, since the time it takes to
read the book dilates and dispels its time frame.
Writers have other ways of dispelling the
dread of history. One of them is to create an
artificial paradise. For Baudelaire, intoxication by
wine or hashish is one way of obliterating time.
Suicide, apologia for which are to be found in the
works of Schopenhauer and in John Donne's
Biathanatos, is another. Any method is valid if
we accept Baltasar Gracián's proposition that
"living is a way of dying every day". Yet it is
a hollow victory to defeat death by dying.
What, then, is time in terms of the writer,
the time experienced by the creator at work?
Writing is a way of arresting time or escaping
from it. Mircea Eliade wrote of "liturgical time",
which vitrifies the present, links all such vitrified
moments outside real time, and thus gives us a
glimpse of eternity. Whether in literature, the
visual arts, or scientific research, the creator is
enmeshed in an imaginary present which, like
mystic meditation or the contemplation of an
artificial paradise, obliterates awareness of other
times.
What does time mean for the reader? My
own view is that the possibility of eluding the
dread of history by escaping into what is perma¬
nent, if not eternal, has a counterpart in the free
space of time spent reading. Readers are also cre¬
ators in their fashion, since they rebuild in their
imagination images which would otherwise
remain lifeless and inert. At the same time they
are immersed in the fixed time of reading. They
may feel anguish but it will be a cathartic anguish
that will affect their own present.
Reading, too, is a kind of liturgy. Perhaps
Cortázar's "dear reader" was right in feeling, as
he read, that "everything had been decided from
the beginning".
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF..
EARTH'S CHANGING
SPEED
Palaeontological studies of the
growth rate of fossil corals
and other sedimentary
remains have shown that
between 300 and 400 million
years ago the Earth took some
400 days to travel around the
Sun, not 365 days as ¡t does
now. This suggests that the
speed at which the Earth
spins around its axis has
decreased correspondingly. An
American astronomer has
recently produced figures
which bear out this
hypothesis. During the past
3,000 years, the Earth's
rotation has slowed by a
47,000th of a second.
THE CHAIN OF LIFE
The World Wide Fund for
Nature (WWF) warns that the
interdependence of species is
such that if any link in the
chain is broken, the
equilibrium of all life on Earth
may be threatened.
Unfortunately, millions of
species disappear before they
are identified. Of the
estimated 30 million insect
species, only some 900,000
have been classified, and
while some 250,000 plant
species are known today, ¡t is
thought that twice as many
more remain to be discovered.
FLEA-FREE FLEDGLINGS
Researchers in Philadelphia
(USA) have discovered that
starlings build their nests from
certain fresh green leaves,
perhaps because these leaves
secrete substances which act
as an insecticide. Parasites in
the nest would weaken the
fledglings and reduce their
chances of survival.
A PUBLIC HEALTH
NIGHTMARE
The World Health Organization
(WHO) estimates that each
year there are some
250 million new cases of
sexually transmitted diseases
(STD), which range from
genital herpes to acquired
¡mmuno-deficiency syndrome
(AIDS). In many countries
these diseases have
become "a public health
nightmare", says
Dr. Hiroshi Nakajima,
Director-General of WHO.
The age-group most affected
is 20-24 years, followed by
15-19 years and 25-29 years.
According to Dr. André
Mcheus, head of WHO'S STD
programme, these diseases
are under control neither in
the developing world nor in
the industrialized countries,
although in the latter the
number of cases is rising less
quickly than in the 1960s to
the 1980s.
BREAST-CANCER
GENE
IDENTIFIED
A team of French researchers
led by molecular biologist
Pierre Chambón have
identified a gene thought to
be responsible for the spread
of breast cancer in the body.
Writing in the British
scientific journal Nature, they
report their discovery that a
certain enzyme, named
stromelysin-3, is activated
by this gene and degrades
the stromal tissue
surrounding the primary
tumour, thus allowing
malignant cells to spread. The
researchers conclude that the
enzyme may represent a
potential target for breast
cancer therapy.
PIONEER 6
AT AGE 25
The American deep-space
probe Pioneer 6, orginally
planned to stay in service for
6 months, has been orbiting
the Sun for 25 years and is
still transmitting data on the
solar wind. Since its launch
from Cape Canaveral, Florida,
on 16 December 1965,
Pioneer 6 has travelled some
24,000 million km, orbited the
Sun 29 times, provided the
first measurements of
interplanetary space,
measured the Sun's corona
and, in 1973, the tail of
Comet Kohoutek.
DEBRIS IN SPACE
The American National
Aeronautics and Space
Administration (NASA)
estimates that by the year
2010 the quantity of man-
made debris circling the
planet will total 3 million tons.
Atmospheric drag, which
causes objects to fall to Earth,
has no effect at very high
altitudes, so NASA has agreed
with the Japanese and the
European Space Agencies
that spacecraft should be
designed which will not eject
any component at a height
greater than 200 miles
(322 km).
WORLD POPULATION
GROWTH
According to World Bank
projections, world population
(estimated at 5.3 billion
in 1990), will grow by more
than 90 million annually
until the late 1990s.
Within 20 years, it will total
7 billion and could reach
11 billion by the end of the
next century.
REMOTE SENSING
AND THE
ENVIRONMENT
The 24th International
Symposium on Remote
Sensing of Environment will
be held in Rio de Janeiro,
Brazil, from 27-31 May 1991.
Remote-sensing techniques
involve the measurement
from aircraft or satellites
of electromagnetic
radiation from the ground,
and the data is
generally displayed in the
form of photograph-like
images. Possible applications
include cartography,
agriculture, sylviculture,
hydrology, geology,
oceanography, and mineral
and oil exploration.
Access to such data is
essential for resource
planning and mitigation of
the effects of environmental
degradation.
MAX ERNST
CENTENARY
A major exhibition to mark the
centenary of the birth of
German painter and sculptor
Max Ernst (1891-1976), a
leading advocate of
irrationality in art, is being
held at the Tate Gallery,
London, until 21 April, when it
moves to Stuttgart
(until 4 August), Dusseldorf
(until 3 November) and
Paris (until 27 January 1992).
On show are 200 paintings,
drawings, collages and
sculptures on loan from
European and American
galleries. They include
three major works,
The Elephant Celebes (1921),
Pietà (1923) and Oedipus
Rex (1921), which mark the
artist's move from Dadaist
nihilism to Surrealism.
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
ANALYSIS OF REPLIES
TO A UNESCO COURIER SURVEY
READER PROFILE
We have recently completed an analysis of replies to a
questionnaire that was sent out with the January 1991
issue of the UNESCO Courier to subscribers to the French
edition. The number of replies we received far exceeded
our expectations and in Itself demonstrates the
considerable interest our readers take in the magazine.
Those who took the time and trouble to reply have
provided us with a mine of detailed information about who
they are and what they expect of the Courier. This
information will be invaluable in helping us to further
improve all aspects of the magazine, while remaining
faithful to an editorial formula which readers strongly
endorse.
We hope you will appreciate the improvements we are
planning to introduce in the coming months. Meanwhile,
in response to a wish expressed by many readers who
answered the questionnaire, we are publishing below the
main results of the survey. They give a general profile of
subscribers to the French edition and their verdict on the
first twenty issues of the new formula introduced in 1989.
We should be happy to receive your comments as a reader
of the English edition.
How much time do you spend reading
the UNESCO Courier?
20% 1 hour
4.7%
Over 4 hours
24% 2-4 hours
An above-average figure reflecting an interested, motivated
readership.
What is your occupation?
Managerial 16.7%
Clerical 3.5%
College student
13.2%
High school student
10.5%
15.1% Teacher
6.6%
Other
professional
10.9% Other
23.6% Retired
42
How regularly do you read the UNESCO Courier?
Every month
85.8%
0.8%
1 to 5 issues per
year
11.7%
6 to 10 issues per
year
1.7% 3 to 5 issues per
year
Some 85% of subscribers have a reading pattern identical to
that of people who buy a periodical at the newsstand, in that
they read each issue they receive.
What is your level and/or branch of education?
Technical 10.5
University 46.1%
28.8% Secondary
3% Primary
5.2% Other
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
What do you do with your issues
when you have read them?
of the UNESCO Courier
Keep 68.6%
11.7% Bind
SSfH. 2.3% Throw
^^te away
^W 17.4% Lend
The Courier is kept for future reference.
maÊÊËÊÊÊÊÊÊÊËÊitËËËÊÊËËÊÊ^
What are your sources of information?
Television 33.3%
31.8% Radio
34.9% Press
A balanced range with a slight preference for the written press.
Why do you buy the UNESCO Courier?
For the interviews 5.4% A^^tf 31.7%
For the themes
i ^^. '
^«M 2.3% Other
^^^H reasons
8.9% Ideology
For its overview ^^B ^^r
Strong approval for the Courier's cross-cultu ral content.
Apart from yourself, how many people
household read the UNESCO Courier?
in your
1-2 persons ^1
57.9% _^B
^Ê
17.1%
reply
Did not
3-4 persons 18%
7% More than 4 persons
How much time do
an average day?
you devote to cultural activities in
^^ 25% 1 hour
1-2 hours 38.6%
¡^B
5.3% Other
:) 6.4% 4-6 hours
W
24.6% 2-4 hours
Readers who enrich their minds through intellectual pursuits and
seek a wide range of information to develop their tastes,
opinions and critical faculties.
How interesting did you find the thematic content of the
first 20 issues of the new formula?
very fairly slightly not at all
1789: An idea that changed the world 43 42 9 6
The family past and present 39 41 8 12
Streetscapes 35 44 16 5
Great epics 38 44 8 10
Strangers on the screen 28 48 15 9
A mathematical mystery tour 43 33 18 6
High days and holidays 30 35 21 14
The fortunes of money 44 39 12 5
The art of hospitality 52 37 7 4
History and memory 55 31 8 6
The making of history 62 29 5 4
The birth of the universe 62 30 5 3
Winds of freedom 46 40 8 6
The challenge of illiteracy 56 32 10 2
Art Nouveau 47 34 12 2
The media. Ways to freedom 35 43 15 7
The automobile 24 42 20 14
Sacred places 64 23 7 6
The enigma of beauty 56 29 11 4
Cities under stress 55 37 8
45.7% 36.6% 11.1% 6.6%
82.3% 17.7%
43
Survey carried out by Hot Line, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
the spknàur of the pyramids
by Gérard Bolla
44
jTew groups of great monuments blend so
well with their natural surroundings as the
pyramids of Giza. At night beneath a canopy
of stars, or in the blinding light of the desert
in daytime, the pyramids rise, impressive and
alone in a world of rock and sand. Those who
built this royal necropolis long ago clearly
intended it to be a haven of peace, isolation,
and silence.
The tranquillity of the archaeological site
is today threatened by a rash of uncontrolled
building development, and the plateau is being
taken over by tourist coaches and amenities.
Some promoters have even envisaged making
golf courses and artificial lakes for pleasure
boats. In short, there is a risk that one of
the wonders of the world may lose its
splendour owing to the anarchic growth of
tourism.
To prevent this from happening and to
restore serenity to the plateau, the Egyptian
Minister of Culture, Farouk Hosny, has
decided to take a number of measures.
Access to the plateau, today open to all, will
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
be strictly controlled, as is the case with almost
all historic monuments elsewhere in the
world;
The modern buildings which have been con¬
structed near the site over the years, contrary
to the advice of architects, will be demolished.
Also scheduled for demolition is the structure
which houses the famous royal boat of
pharaoh Khufu and which disfigures one side
of the Great Pyramid near which it was exca¬
vated. The boat will of course not be removed
until all the necessary technical precautions
have been taken to prevent damage to this
fragile masterpiece;
The tarmac roads, whose colour clashes with
that of the site, will be replaced by roads made
of solidified sand;
Motor traffic, a source of noise and pollu¬
tion which damages the stone of the monu-
IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
ments, will be prohibited. Archaeologists and
service staff will use electric vehicles;
Unsupervised animals such as dogs and goats
which harm the monuments and discourage
visitors will be prohibited;
Bridle paths will be designed to provide spec¬
tacular views for visitors on camel and horse¬
back. They will also make it easier to keep the
site free of litter;
Also in the interests of tourists and visitors,
the area set aside beneath the Sphinx for son
et lumière shows will be extended. This area
will be lowered so as to improve the view of
the Sphinx and the pyramids from the eastern
access road to the plateau;
As is the case with other historic monu¬
ments, revenue from visitors will contribute
to the conservation of the irreplaceable
heritage left by the ancient Egyptians;
The existing buffer zone will be defined
more clearly and improved both aesthetically
and functionally, so as to provide a better view
of the monuments and to respect the dignity
of the site. The cafeteria to the east of the
pyramids will disappear.
It is clearly necessary that the plateau
of Giza should be fenced off to channel
the movement of visitorsat least in the
part which is accessible to everyone. Incon¬
spicuous light fencing would be quite suitable
for this.
Anyone who has ever marvelled at the
mysterious silhouette of the Sphinx and the
majestic mass of the pyramids as they suddenly
come into view from behind a sand dune will
appreciate the importance of safeguarding
their timeless splendour.
GÉRARD BOLLA, Swiss jurist and economist, is a
former Assistant Director-General of UNESCO.
From 1971 to 1981 he was in charge of UNESCO's
programme for the conservation of the cultural
heritage, and was notably responsible for archaeo¬
logical safeguard and rescue operations at Philae
(Egypt), Venice, Borobudur and Carthage. He has
served as chairman of an international advisory com¬
mittee of experts on the development project for
the plateau of the pyramids.
NEW WORLD HERITAGE
SITES
In December 1990, 17 sites were inscribed on
UNESCO's World Heritage List, bringing the total
number to 337.
The new sites are:
The palace and parks of Potsdam and
Berlin (Germany).
The Jesuit Missions of the Chiquitos
(Bolivia).
Mount Huangshan (China).
Delos (Greece).
The monasteries of Daphni, Hossios Luckas
and Nea Moni of Chios (Greece).
The historic centre of San Gimignano
(Italy).
Tsingy de Bemaraha Strict Nature Reserve
(Madagascar).
Te Wahipounamu (New Zealand).
Tongariro National Park (New Zealand).
La Amistad International Park (Panama).
Rio Abiseo National Park (Peru).
The Colonial City of Santo Domingo
(Dominican Republic).
Saint Sophia Cathedral and related
monastic buildings, Kiev-Pechersk Lavra,
Kiev (Ukrainian SSR).
The historic centre of Leningrad and
related groups of monuments (Soviet
Union).
Itchan Kala (Soviet Union).
Khizi Pogost (Soviet Union).
The Kremlin and Red Square, Moscow
(Soviet Union).
Six statesBelize, Fiji, Mongolia, Romania,
Czechoslovakia and Venezuelahave recently
ratified the Convention concerning the Protec¬
tion of the World Cultural and Natural Heritage,
bringing the total number of states parties to the
Convention to 115. In 1992 UNESCO will be
celebrating the 20th anniversary of the adoption
of the Convention.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
IN ACTION
46
EUROPEAN FORUM
FOR UNESCO CLUBS
A meeting of European UNESCO
Clubs was held at Strasbourg
(France) from 17 to 21
December 1990. The main
themes discussed were the
natural and cultural heritage,
human rights, democracy and
citizenship, cultural
development, interdependence
and solidarity.
UNESCO Clubs, the first of
which was created in Japan in
1947, are groups of people of
all ages and from a variety of
professional backgrounds who
support UNESCO's work. Today
there are some 500 UNESCO
Clubs and Associations in
Europe, and 3,200 more in
about 100 different countries.
' For those wishing to find out
more about the activities of
UNESCO Clubs, a number of
publications are available from:
The Division of National
Commissions and UNESCO
Clubs/The World Federation of
UNESCO Clubs and
Associations, 1 rue Miollis,
75015 Paris, France.
UNESCO AND
CHERNOBYL
UNESCO has launched a
programme to intensify
international co-operation in
efforts to remedy the
consequences of the disaster at
the Chernobyl nuclear power
station in April 1986. An
agreement on this programme
was signed on 9 January 1991
by the Director-General of
UNESCO and the permanent
delegates to UNESCO of the '
Soviet Union, the Byelorussian
SSR and the Ukrainian SSR.
The programme consists of
some 70 projects designed to
assess the medical and
ecological impact of the
disaster, to safeguard the
region's cultural heritage, to
construct new settlements, and
to develop public education and
information. In accordance with
UNESCO's mandate, the
projects are primarily concerned
with the human aspects of the
accident. Priority is being given
to the safety of the 4 million
people living in the disaster
area, and to that of some
600,000 members of the armed
forces, Chernobyl staff and local
volunteers who helped to limit
the initial damage.
Projects for the 800,000
children in the area include the
creation of prototype schools
and of international exchange
programmes.
YOUNG REPORTERS
The first international festival of
video-reporting by young people
will take place in Port de Bouc,
France, from 20 to 23 June
1991. It is being organized by
the municipality of Port de Bouc
under the auspices of UNESCO.
Entrants must be between
13 and 25 years of age and
their videos must be submitted
by an organization (university,
school, audiovisual workshop,
UNESCO Club, youth club,
cultural centre, works council,
town or local association, etc.).
Entrants may choose from
12 themes including nature, the
environment, ecology, sport,
entertainment, and work
yesterday and today. A jury of
television and other audiovisual
professionals will make a
preliminary choice of videos for
the festival and the final
selection of prizewinners.
For further information and
entry forms, write to: Festival
International du Jeune
Reportage, Hôtel de Ville,
13110 Port de Bouc, France.
Fax: 42 06 28 92. Video-
cassettes must be received by
15 May 1991 to be eligible for
the competition.
UNESCO MAPS AND
ATLASES
For many years UNESCO has
produced important scientific
maps and atlases, alone or in
conjunction with other
institutions.
An illustrated catalogue is
available which classifies the
maps and atlases under the
following headings: general
geological, tectonic,
metamorphic, quaternary,
mineral and metallogenic,
hydrogeological, climatic, soil,
vegetation and océanographie,
and is provided with an
alphabetical index, price list,
and list of national distributors
of UNESCO publications.
A copy of Scientific Maps and
Atlases: UNESCO Catalogue can
be obtained by writing to the
Sales Division, Unesco Press,
1 rue Miollis, 75015 Paris,
France.
TOWARDS
A DEMOCRATIC CULTURE
THE MONTEVIDEO DECLARATION
A conference entitled "Democratic Culture and Development: Towards
the Third Millennium In Latin America" was held in Montevideo
(Uruguay) from 27 to 30 November 1990. Organized under the
auspices of the government of Uruguay by UNESCO and the PAX Insti¬
tute, the conference was attended by leading politicians and scientists
from Latin America and other world regions.
The conference drew up a Declaration which refers to UNESCO's
mandate for the promotion of human rights and peace and calls on the
Organization to give priority to action which would encourage a
democratic society and cultural life. At the opening session, the
Director-General of UNESCO, Mr. Federico Mayor, pointed out that
this was the first time the Organization had taken action on an inter¬
national scale to promote democracy.
The Montevideo conference will be followed up by meetings which
will be held later this year in Prague (Czechoslovakia) and Gorée
(Senegal). We publish below salient extracts from the Montevideo
Declaration, whose title, "Democratic Culture and Governance",
emphasizes its guiding principles.
PREAMBLE
In almost every region of the world. ..the foundations are being laid in
public life for the difficult transition to political and economic structures
that restore responsibility, initiative and decision-making authority to
all members of society. Authoritarian or centralized forms of organi¬
zation, which give a hegemonic state the exclusive right to determine
political, social and economic options, are giving way to an increas¬
ingly general desire for a new legitimacy based on the popular will and
on the recognition of political life as subject to the rule of law....
Democracy and sustainable development will depend in large
measure on the ability of individual societies to modernize from within,
especially through changes and adjustments that enhance the state's
efficiency and legitimacy in the arbitration of conflicts and the adminis¬
tration of justice and in providing encouragement and guidance in the
economic and cultural fields. It is only in this way that existing dis¬
parities can be overcome and a new national consensus promoted
around the common goal of a more just and more effectively pluralist
civil society....
PRINCIPLES AND RECOMMENDATIONS
The conference. ..unanimously reaffirms the vital importance of
democracy for the future of mankind in that it is:
(a) the only political system and practice based on the sovereignty of
the people, open to the active participation in public life of all sectors
of society and all shades of opinion, without any discrimination;
(b) the only system and practice for public life capable of bringing
about a society based on the iule of law and on the recognition of
human rights and of civil and individual freedoms as the ethical basis
for a civil society of free and equal individuals, and where the state
is supreme defender of those rights and freedoms;
(c) the only system and practice for social life which is geared to the
peaceful and concerted pursuit of social justice, equity and individual
and community well being under the law....
The conference recommends in particular that UNESCO, which has
a specific responsibility within the United Nations system with regard
to human rights and peace, should give priority In its biennial
programmes and medium-term plans to activities aimed at promoting
democracy In social and cultural life. Specifically, it should, in co¬
operation with interested member states and with relevant public and
private institutional networks:
(a) promote and organize forums for reflection and exchange of ideas
among the intellectual and political communities;
(b) develop for subsequent inclusion in general human rights and peace
education programmes material on democracy and democratic values;
(c) carry out comparative studies concerning existing mechanisms
for (i) negotiation and peaceful settlement of conflicts of interest,
(ii) interaction between civil society and the state, (iii) horizontal social
participation and communication.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Ambassaèrs,
and empires
V/N the thirty-first public festivities were
held at Junthia or Siam to celebrate the acces¬
sion of the King of Portugal to the throne. The
foreign vessels fired a number of rounds of
cannon and let off fireworks. The following
day, the first of November, Monsieur Con¬
stance invited me to a great feast to celebrate
the event. All the Europeans in the town
attended and cannon were fired continually
all day long. After the meal there was acting,
beginning with the Chinese, then there were
some Siamese whose posturing I found
ridiculous and not nearly so good as our Euro¬
pean players..." The tourist who penned these
lines was a French nobleman, the Chevalier
de Chaumont, who in 1685 led a mission to
Siamnow Thailandin response to a dele¬
gation sent the previous year by the Siamese
king to the court of Louis XIV at Versailles.
The "Monsieur Constance" mentioned by
the Chevalier de Chaumont was a remarkable
person. A Greek from Cephalonia, he was also
The arrival of French ambassadors
in Siam (now Thailand)
c. 1686. Contemporary watercolour.
adventurers
UNESCO
IN ACTION
THE SILK ROADS
by François-Bernard Huyghe
known as Constantine Hierarchy, and
adopted the name of Constantine Phaulkon
on his arrival in Asia. Born into a Catholic
family, he was converted to Anglicanism and
then reverted to Catholicism before his mar¬
riage to a Japanese Christian. He started out
in life as a cabin boy on an English merchant
ship, sailed to Thailand, and became inter¬
preter to the mandarin in charge of the
Treasury. Later he became Superintendent of
Foreign Trade. He was ennobled and became
acting minister of finance and foreign affairs
in Thailand.
Plotters and adventurers
at the Thai court
The English doubtless instructed Constantine
to favour the English East India Company's
interests at the expense of the Dutch, who had
forcibly acquired a virtual monopoly of Thai
trade with China. Instead, he schemed to
establish French power in Thailand. There fol¬
lowed some rather murky episodes involving
Jesuits and Roman Catholic missionaries (who
were in competition with the large numbers
of "Moors" who were spreading the Islamic
faith). French garrisons were established at
Mergui on the Indian Ocean and at Bangkok.
The francophile party triumphed, but not for
long. King Narai fell victim to a suspicious ill¬
ness to which he eventually succumbed, and
a general named Petraja took the throne. He
had his rivals executed, along with Constan¬
tine and a number of missionaries, and closed
the country to outside influences. Thus came
to an end the reign of Pra Narai, a sovereign
who loved literature so much that he spoke
in verse and only took pleasure in the com¬
pany of poets.
The history of the Thai court at Ayuthaya
in the seventeenth century abounds in perso¬
nalities like Constantine. Another prominent
figure was the Japanese Yamada Nagamara,
who was head of the Royal Guard and the epi¬
tome of Japanese influence in Thailand. These
foreigners who intervened in Thai political life
illustrate the cosmopolitan nature of the
society in which they played such a promi¬
nent role. Their emergence was to some extent
due to the existence of the Silk Roads. No less
>*;>
**+
m*f ** t
!.] S*
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
The observation of a solar eclipse
In Siam (now Thailand), c. 1688.
French contemporary engraving.
than forty foreign communities lived at
Ayuthaya.
For the members of UNESCO's Maritime
Silk Roads expedition, the ambiguous and
picaresque careers of these men are a spec¬
tacular reminder of how the great trade routes
could influence the processes of history. This
idea took root when the expedition's ship, the
Fulk al-Salamah, first arrived in Thailand at
Phuket, from whence it sailed on to Malaysia
and Indonesia before returning to Bangkok.
Between the Indian
Ocean and the South China Sea,
the barrier of Indochina
The Indochinese peninsula marks an impor¬
tant frontier on the Silk Roads. Early on, fear
of Malaysian pirates, or perhaps a wish to
make use of the monsoon winds and avoid a
long detour southwards, attracted traffic
between the Indian Ocean and the South
China Sea. Our expedition visited the beach
on the west coast of Thailand where Arab
ships dropped anchor, perhaps as early as the
ninth century. On the east coast, on the shores
of the South China Sea, we searched for frag¬
ments of Chinese ceramics which can be
picked up there as easily as seashells.
How did merchandise cross the peninsula?
According to a theory put forward a few years
ago, it was carried in boats which were hauled
over logs by elephants. When a television com¬
pany carried out an experiment to see if this
was feasible so many planks (and so much por¬
celain) were broken that doubt was cast on
the theory.
Our next port of call, Melaka, formerly
Malacca, again confirmed the influence that
trade has exercised on people's lives. Much has
been written about the different cultures and
peoples of Malaysia, but how many people
know that at the beginning of the sixteenth
century no less than eighty-four languages
were spoken in Malacca, including three
different types of Malay, each the language of
a specific social class? And that the Indian,
Arab, Persian and Chinese communities each
had their own district and played an impor¬
tant part in the life of the community?
Between the foundation of the city at the
end of the fourteenth century by Paramesvara,
an exiled prince from Sumatra, and the Por¬
tuguese colonization of 1511, a state developed
whose destiny was dominated by its maritime
vocation. The Chinese Ming emperor Yonglo
immediately realized the importance of this
port strategically situated on the Strait of
Malacca.
As early as 1403 the Chinese began to send
missions to Malacca and established diplomatic
relations with the city. One imperial envoy
was the Muslim admiral Zheng He who led
several naval expeditions which were typical
examples of the Ming emperors' policy of
maintaining prestige and promoting commer¬
cial expansion. Throughout our journey we
w-s-sry
came upon traces of his fleet, which was one
of the largest in history both in the number
and size of its ships.
The spectacular development of Malacca
was a justification of Chinese diplomacy. A
halfway point on the Silk Road between India
and China, the city overflowed with cloves
from the Moluccas, wood from Timor,
Chinese and Japanese objects, goods from
India, spices, perfumes, medicinal herbs, rubies
from Sri Lanka, gold and silver. Merchants
from every nation bartered their cargoes or
waited there for a favourable wind.
These riches reached Europe via Hormuz
and Basra or Suez and Cairo. Malay became
the lingua franca of the region. Malacca, which
lived entirely from trade, prospered and soon
came to control the peninsula and eastern
Sumatra. It conducted an intelligent fiscal
policy which enriched the state without dis¬
couraging foreign merchants.
Islamization also brought benefits to
Malacca. This was the result of a mission sent
by the king of Pasai (North Sumatra) after the
ground had been prepared by Muslim traders
and possibly by the Sufi mystics who accom¬
panied them. First Paramesvara was con¬
verted, then his nobles, and finally the people
at large. Islam soon became the official
religion, facilitating relations with the Arab
and Persian merchants who dominated trade
in the Indian Ocean.
The structure of the state reflected the
importance of commerce. The sultan and his
chief ministers (including the Shahbandar or
"harbour master") were, in the words of a
Malaysian specialist, "simultaneously the
holders of authority and the principal mer¬
chants of Malacca". Their fortune was con¬
siderable. Every merchant whose ship
anchored in Malacca knew he would have to
hand over to them a proportion of his profits.
;>
mm
Many nations and religions met in this thalas-
socracy in which a Portuguese chronicler of
400 years ago declared that he had seen "the
greatest number of merchants and ships that
can possibly be found in the whole world".
The Indonesian maritime empire
If there is one country that embodies the idea
of diversity and openness to the world it is
surely Indonesia, with its 13,700 islands, 250
ethnic groups and even greater number of lan¬
guages. Our visit to Indonesia gave us the
opportunity to attend a seminar where we
learned something about the kingdom of
Srivijaya, which is so little known that some
people wonder whether it ever existed. And
yet, between the seventh and the fourteenth
century, this kingdom called by the Chinese
San Fu Qi emerged in Sumatra from among
the numerous ports of the Indonesian
archipelago that were struggling for maritime
and commercial supremacy. Both Hinduism
and Buddhism flourished there, and Chinese
monks visited Palembang, the capital of
Srivijaya, to study sacred texts.
In the thirteenth century this kingdom
probably held sway over fifteen other realms,
including Sri Lanka. Its hegemony extended
over a large part of Southeast Asia, from
Thailand to Sumatra. This warrior state was
slowly transformed into a trading kingdom
and became the centre of a complex network
of sea and river ports which were conduits for
international and local trade and enjoyed a cer¬
tain degree of autonomy.
Once again the Silk Roads had made and
brought down empires.
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE, French writer and
journalist, is a former member of UNESCO's
Division of Cultural Heritage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDS
listening
JAZZ
by Isabelle Leymarie
Charlie Haden and The Liberation
Music Orchestra.
Dream Keeper.
With the Oakland Youth Chorus.
Arrangements by Carla Bley
(conductor). Musicians include
Charlie Haden (bass), Branford
Marsalis (tenor saxj. Ken Mclntyre
(alto sax.). Earl Gardner (trumpet),
Paul Motian (drums).
CD Polydor 847 876-2.
A fine orchestra, with a fresh, non-
conventional sound somewhere
between folk music and jazz, plays
committed music mainly from South
America and South Africa.
"Spiritual", by Haden himself, is
dedicated to Martin Luther King and
other Afro-American leaders. Here
Charlie Haden has assembled a line¬
up of musicians who do not usually
play together.
Wallace Roney.
The Standard Bearer.
Wallace Roney (trumpet), Gary
Thomas (tenor sax.), Mulgrew Miller
(piano), Charnett Moffett (bass),
Cindy Blackman (drums),
Steve Sernos (percussions).
CD VG 651 600622.
The brilliant young trumpeter
Wallace Roney, a disciple of the
great Art Blakey, joins some of his
peers to provide new interpretations
of standards such as "Con Alma"
and "Giant Steps". Roney's playing
has a rounded, warm and powerful
tone, something like that of Lee
Morgan, whom he acknowledges as
one of his heroes. Berrios, a former
associate of Mongo Santamaría,
adds some Latin spice on "Loose".
Moffett, Blackman and Miller are
some of the most admired sidemen
in jazz today. Gary Thomas, whom
I heard for the first time on this disc,
will surely go far. Powerful, solid jazz.
CLASSICAL
Gluck.
Les pèlerins de la Mecque ou La
rencontre imprévue ("The Pilgrims
to Mecca or the Unexpected
Encounter").
Orchestra of the Lyon Opéra,
conducted by John Eliot Gardiner.
2 CDs. Erato 2292455162.
This is the first recording
of a light opera which was composed
when Turkish styles were at the
height of fashion and was first
performed in Vienna in 1764. The
scene is set in Cairo, where Sultan
Reiza wanders in search of his
beloved, whom he believes to be
dead. After many trials and tribulations,
the lovers are reunited. The music is
lively and elegant, the arias
delightfully fresh.
Classiques des Amériques
("Classics of the Americas").
Vol. 1. Cervantes, Saume//,
Gottschalk.
Georges Rabo/, piano.
CD Opus 30-9001.
The Martinique-bom pianist
Georges Rabol gives a marvellous
rendering, alternately light and
sombre, of works by three 19th-century
Creole composers. Cervantes and
Saumell were the great Cuban
masters of the danza and
contradanza. Louis Moreau
Gottschalk, born in New Orleans,
made several visits to Cuba and
Puerto Rico, bringing Caribbean
rhythms back to the United States.
The impact of Spanish Romanticism
can be felt, but it is mingled with
Afro-Caribbean influences to which
the music owes its strongly
syncopated quality, reminiscent of
ragtime. Each piece evokes the
charm and gentleness of the tropical
region of its origin.
Manuel de Falla.
La obra para piano ("Piano Works").
Jean-François Heisser, pianist.
CD Erato 2292-45481-2.
This is a brilliant and inspired
recording of Manuel de Falla's piano
works, whose nuances are rendered
by Heisser with unerring accuracy.
"The Three-Cornered Hat" and the
"Obras Españolas" (which include,
curiously, a languid "Cubana") are
charmingly played. "Pour le tombeau
de Paul Dukas", a serene and
meditative tribute to the great
French composer, leaves an
impression of classical limpidity.
The spirit of Andalusia which
penetrated every fibre of Falla's
being lives again in "Love, the
Magician". Heisser provides an
intelligent introductory text. Nobody
understands music better than
musicians.
Sergey Prokofiev.
Two Violin-Piano Sonatas and five
Violin-Piano Melodies.
Régis Pasquier (violin),
Pascal Rogé (piano).
CD Adda 581195.
Too seldom heard, these sonatas
and melodies are among Prokofiev's
finest works. A blend of Slav passion
and formal rigour, the Sonata for
Violin in F Minor, Opus 80, was
perhaps inspired by Handel. The first
person to hear it, the Russian
violinist David Oistrakh, wrote that
"Such a beautiful and profound work
has not appeared in the violin
repertoire for decades".
Régis Pasquier is the founder of the
Trio Pasquier, and Pascal Rogé
an outstanding interpreter of Satie
and Poulenc.
Claude Debussy.
La mer/Prélude à l'après-midi
d'un faune/Nocturnes.
Orchestre de la Suisse romande,
conducted by Armin Jordan.
CD Erato 2292-45605-2.
The Orchestre de la Suisse
romande is one of the best in the
world for late 19th- and early 20th-
century music. Here it renders
Debussy's passionate symphonic
poems "La mer", which he began to
write in Burgundy and completed in
Jersey; the "Prélude à l'après-midi
d'un faune", inspired by Mallarmé's
eponymous poem; and "Nocturnes",
which may have been inspired by
another French poet, Henri de
Régnier, and by the American
painter Whistler. Armin Jordan
conjures up all the nuances of these
works which rank among Debussy's
finest achievements.
Anthologie de la mélodie russe et
soviétique
("Anthology of Russian and Soviet
Melodies").
Elena Vassilieva (soprano),
Jacques Schab (piano).
2 CDs. Le Chant du Monde
LDC 278 972/73.
Vassilieva and Schab perform
a selection of 19th- and 20th-
century works ranging from classics
by Glinka, Mussorgsky, Tchaikovsky,
Stravinsky, Prokofiev and
Shostakovich, to pieces by less well-
known composers such as Gurilev,
Dargomizhsky, Roslavetz, Firsova,
Denisov and Knaifel. This remarkable
anthology reveals new aspects of
Russian and Soviet vocal music,
sometimes close to folk traditions,
as in Mussorgsky's celebrated
"Enfantines", sometimes mannered
and exquisite as in Glinka's
"Venetian Night", but always
surprising.
FOLK
Cuba: Les danses des dieux
("Cuba: Dances of the Gods").
CD Ocora C 559051.
The heartbeat of Africa still
throbs in Cuba, which has preserved
one of the most vigorous folk
traditions in the Americas.
Descendants of the Arará, who
came from Dahomey, still worship
deities close to those of Haitian
Voodoo, which also features
on this recording. During the
18th-century uprisings
in Haiti and San Domingo, many
planters and freed slaves took
refuge In Cuba's Oriente region,
where their musical traditions
have survived to this day.
The santería, a syncretic cult of
Yoruba origin, is still going strong,
and batà drums used
in santería cult dances have been
adopted by dance bands
like Irakere, of Havana. Instruments
such as the conga belong to
the rich Congolese heritage,
as does the dance, song and
instrumental form known as rumba
brava. The erotic guaguancó,
in which the man pursues the
woman in a ritual seduction, and
the Columbia, a country
dance performed mainly by
men, are two forms of the rumba
brava.
POP
Yalla.
Let's Go. Hitlist Egypt.
LP Mango MLPS 1040.
The new Egyptian pop music,
little known elsewhere at least in
the Westhas made great strides
since the time of the Egyptian
singing star Urn Kalsum. The
classical heritage, in particular the
romantic mawal, still survives, but
disco, rap and synthesizer
music is dressing up the songs
in a new way. This album
features shaabi music, vibrant
songs from the Cairo streets written
in reaction to the saccharine big
bands of the Nasser era. Nubian
music, which is more African in
character, is also featured
with Nubian singer Khedr's rendering
of "Balsam Shafee" (Healing
Balsam).
Yomo Toro.
Gracias.
CD Mango CIDM 1034 842 921-2.
Puerto Rico-born Yomo Toro
is the leading exponent of the
cuatro, a type of lute, in Latin
American music. Long used
exclusively in folk music, the
instrument has now won its spurs
in salsa. On this recording, a jovial
and exuberant king of salsa
brings rural love songs (jabaro)
up to date with arrangements
for violins and synthesizers.
Even the most grumpy listener
will find it hard to resist this
good-humoured disc, ideal for
dancing.
M.C. Solaar.
Bouge de là (trie Mix).
Maxi 45. Polydor 879 205-1.
An amusing disc by a young
African-born rapper who grew
up in the Paris suburbs. Our hero
meets a number of personalities
on his adventurous journey
into the city. The "Irie Mix" version
of the title song is lively
and rhythmic, but I prefer
the warm voice of M.C. Solaar
in the a cappella version
on the other side. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR ^
50
Megalithic mistake
There is an error on page 25 of
the November 1990 Courier
("Sacred Places"). Newgrange is
situated near the east coast of
Ireland, not "in western Ireland."
Stella M.B. Webb
Dublin (Ireland)
Newgrange, one of the finest Megalithic
tombs in Europe, is of course in County
Meath. Editor
Reporting on
the environment
I was pleased to read that you are
going to publish regular reports
on major environmental issues.
I learned a great deal from the
excellent articles "Our small blue
planet" (November 1990) and
"Reviewing the accounts"
(January 1991), by Michel Bâtisse.
What with the greenhouse
effect, pollution, deforestation,
and so on, environmental
problems have become of crucial
importance today.
Pierre Samuel
Professor Emeritus
Université de Paris-Sud (France)
Under the microscope
I find the UNESCO Courier an
Invaluable source of information
and inspiration on Third World
topics. Your contributors, from
differing cultural backgrounds,
present views not usually covered
in national publications.
I was sorry, however, to find the
articles by Michel Bâtisse on
global environmental concerns
relegated to the back pages, after
the record reviews and the news
briefs.
While the use of colour makes
your pages more attractive, colour
under small type reduces
legibility. Your choice of type-size
could be kinder to those with poor
eyesight.
John Kirby Abraham
Journalist
Radio France Internationale (Paris)
Demography and
the environment
As a demographer, I am
increasingly interested in
environmental questions.
Population is one of the four
pillars of our "small blue planet",
as Michel Bâtisse rightly pointed
out in your November 1990 issue.
Your efforts to elucidate and
reflect on major environmental
problems are worth following up
and expanding into major articles.
Demography deserves a central
place in your coverage.
Jean Marie Poursin
Paris (France)
Keep up
the good work!
I have been a member of a
contemplative order of nuns for
56 years (I am 75 years old). '
I lost my sight in 1964, and one
of the other sisters, knowing that
I like to study, arranged for me to
receive the Braille edition of the
UNESCO Courier.
Needless to say, after reading
one issue, I ordered it regularly.
I should like to express my
gratitude to you. I have also
received a free subscription to the
' ink-printed edition. Everyone to
whom I have passed on my copies
has read them with great
pleasure.
I am still interested in
everything that is beautiful and
noble, in music, poetry and art,
and highly appreciate your
excellent magazine. I pray for
your success.
Sister Emmanuelle Chanat
Communauté des Soeurs
Contemplatives du Bon Pasteur
Saint-Martin-d'Hères (France)
Words and pictures
Your magazine is a quality
publication which also establishes
human contact with its readers.
But I would like to see more solid
and detailed articles, with less
prominence given to the titles
and, above all, fewer full-page
photographs. What interests me in
interviews is what people have to
say their personality, not their
portrait.
Georges Tardy
"Le Moulin"
76730 Rainfreville (France)
An avid reader
A student, I read widely for
pleasure and especially make it
my business to go carefully
through the press. I can assure
you that the UNESCO Courier Is
unique. It is the only reasonably
low-priced magazine to publish so
many concise, informative
features presented in such a
polished and rigorous way (colour,
layout, attention to detail).
Last but certainly not least, it
is the only magazine to provide a
truly international perspective on
topical issues such as war and
peace, industrial development and
the environment, democracy and
oppression.
Hervé Pesson
Les Trois Fontaines
Fussy (France)
BACK NUMBERS
A subscriber to the French
edition of the UNESCO Courier
since 1960, I am looking for a
complete set of back numbers up
to December 1959, Including the
Unesco Monitor which was
published in August 1947 and
was followed by the first edition
of the Courier proper in February
1948.
G. Tricoche
4, rue M. Lambert
16600 Ruelle (France)
I have every copy of the
French edition since 1965, when I
took out a subscription. As I am
over 80 years of age and nobody
I know can take them, I'm looking
for a possible purchaser.
Marcel Cancre
Grands Champs
Noyant-d'Allier
03210 Souvigny (France)
A long-time subscriber, I still
have around a hundred copies of
the French edition, dating from
1959 to 1979. I would be happy
to part with them to someone
wishing to complete their
collection.
Guy Colard
10 bis rue des Batignolles
75017 Paris (France)
I want to dispose of my
collection (French edition), which
runs from April 1975 to
December 1990, and will consider
any offers from other readers.
Nicole Riboulot
53 avenue de Paris
51000 Chalons-sur-Marne (France)
I wish to sell my collection of
the French edition, complete for
the following years: 1978, 79, 82,
83, 84, 86, 87, 88, 89 and 90.
Mme Gunck
109 rue de Sèvres
75006 Paris (France)
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3 (right): David Harding
© Cosmos, Paris. Back cover: © Bang
Hai-Ja, Paris. Page 2: © María Irma
Zalazar, Buenos Aires, Pages 3 (left),
4, 6, 7 (above): All Rights Reserved.
Page 5: © Farouk Hosny, Cairo.
Page 7 (below): © Fotogram-Stone,
Paris. Pages 8-9: © Monique Piétri,
Paris. Page 10: Frederic ©Explorer,
Paris. Page 12: © Charles Lénars,
Paris. Pages 13, 18 (right), 26:
© Roland and Sabrina Michaud, Paris.
Page 15: © Hervé Bernard, Paris.
Page 17 (above): © Dagli Orti, Paris;
(below): C. Choffet © Futur Musée
du Temps, Palais Granvelle, Besançon.
Page 18 (left): J. Oster © Musée de "
l'Homme, Paris. Page 19:
© Laboratoire de Recherche des
Musées de France, Paris. Page 21
(above): © Musée Royal d'Art et
d'Histoire, Brussels; (below): ©J.-L.
Charmet/Bibliothèque des Arts
Décoratifs, Paris. Page 22:
© Artephot/National Palace Museum,
Taiwan. Page 23: © Claude
Sauvageot, Paris. Page 24: M. Huet
© Hoa-Qui, Paris. Page 25: © Musée
de l'Homme, Paris. Page 27:
© Explorer Archives,
Paris/Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
Page 28: © Dagli Orti,
Paris/Bibliothèque Topkapi, Istanbul.
Page 29: Sinclair Siammers/Science
Photo Library © Cosmos, Paris.
Pages 30-31: Thomas Ives ©ANA,
Paris. Page 32: © Explorer Archives,
Paris/Musée des Arts Décoratifs,
Paris. Page 33: Roberto de
Gugliemo/Science Photo Library
© Cosmos, Paris. Page 34: Paul Laes,
Brussels © Stedelijke Museum,
Louvain. Page 35: All Rights
Reserved/Collection Fondation
Cointreau pour la Création
Contemporaine, Paris. Page 36:
Michael Siegel © Cosmos, Paris. Page
37: Bridgeman © Artephot,
Paris/Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.
Page 38: J. Martin © Artephot,
Paris/Hospital de la Caridad, Seville.
Page 39: © Explorer Archives, Paris.
Page 40: Patrick Broquet © Explorer
Archives, Paris/Musée du Louvre.
Pages 44-45: Garrigues © Rapho,
Paris. Page 47: ©J.-L. Charmet,
Paris/Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
Page 48: © Edimédia, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
le Courrier
Published monthly in 35 languages and in braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational.
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whrtcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévéque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca. Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Russian edition: Georgi Zelenin
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, Carole Pajot-Font
(Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein {Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15).
Mouna Chatta
Selection in braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Mane-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner MerkH (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanmi (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Suva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wall Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: SJ. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler ¡Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassar (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M, Sharafuddm (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45.88).
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle 3ranet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68,45.65),
jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité. Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard.
Michelle Robillard. Mohamed Salan El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Gmette Motreff (45,68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65).
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs, 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher cop¡es are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express ne opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO Courier. Photo captions and headlines
are written by the UNESCO Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published m the magazine do no: imply official endorsement or
ücceptance by JNESCO or the United Nations. The UNESCO Courier
is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by (1) UNESCO.
7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox),
Am Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian
Head. Inc.. Ill West 40th Street. New York. U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell
Co . Old Mansf ed Road, wooster. Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed In France) DEPOT LEGAL : CI AVRIL 1991.
COMMISSION PARI' AIRE MO "'1844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP,
Photocomposition; The UNESCO Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury Imprimeur S.A..
2.1 r;»ute d'Etampes. 45330 Maiesherbes.
LETTERS OF LIFE
A MAJOR PUBLICATION ON WORLD LITERACY
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 4- 1991 -OPI-91 -3 491 A
UNESCO and Editions Nathan of Paris have co-published an album of photographs and texts, entitled
LETTERS OF LIFE, to mark the close of International Literacy Year (1990) and to illustrate the fight against
illiteracy in 22 countries.
Fifty-two full-page photographs by Dominique Roger present different aspects of literacy work. The
accompanying texts have been contributed by 52 distinguished people from all walks of life. The book is
a "living alphabet" of their messages, from "A" (Corazón Aquino and Oscar Arias) to "Z" (Wou-Ki Zao and
Zouc), all of which emphasize the importance of literacy to development.
LETTERS OF LIFE was published on 13 February 1991 at an open day at UNESCO Headquarters in Paris.
On the same day, UNESCO launched a vast campaign in France to mobilize children aged between 6 and
15 to buy pencils and exercise books for pupils in developing countries who lack these basic learning materials.
It is hoped that this campaign, supported in France by the television channel Antenne 2 and the Ministry
of Education, Youth and Sport, will be extended to other countries.
Part of the proceeds from sales of the book will go to the UNESCO Special Account for World Literacy.
Price: 250 French francs
Trilingual: English, French, Spanish Format: 32 x 24 cm ISBN: 2.09.284.763.5
On sale in bookshops and from Editions Nathan, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
' ' '. B
K^^^H
^BHHb. 'jU
H H Ir l J^H
4^Hr - - I
E B^B ' 5*^3» H
1
,
-;,:.-
t->": V-' r - - " i-
!*H
' / ' ÎP-
W 1 SSPu 1
f;,
' i ^ i » vß^fiPP^H
1 * I :. " r aPs»? . - ^íS^IkbSb^I
hK&m¿¿
1 . H >» 1 i
- 1
fflÉB8L,^k¿ .
&
»$£ È-,
1 i - ' 1 . -
H^fl ' ' - -'. ' 1
1 - ' . . ' - . '- '- ¿ " 1
W«£¿iír 1
** " r ****' iH"' ' ^SivÄfc9S^JI Ç^sSjraït; '.'V'
i';í ' ^^E&v^ l'j
' .1 *3MBQM5HEaBWBir. jfl hSfljtf^V -Ai ' ~ B'
WÊ^Ê^Êâ^ V " ' . - .. ' --'.
'- *' B in ' *"" ¿t _ wm^^^^^^^ßWß^t^.-'
*' .' -iV*-> 5^^àtL-"xfi ' <¿m
£ 11' - ~ ^C^ ^TjHÈv v^U \^sBft£SS18^b 1 '
l^H : '- . - " v:. r-^K" " . 1
" '
. ií-*p¿ H SiftBi
^ *-'' 1 H^L^SnEiMEk **
, V ¿*> -S&C'íJt'~3ti*5¿ ..;: ,.' .; > . :; -.-:. . j|
£-'^îfVBefe^> ^ "
r '51 ' -;- %v^aIB%^^SSÍ
j'fey^-l^; -'"'
]]>
</page>
</document>
