<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="088517eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco
L II I)
COURIER
JUNE 1991
ï
M 1205- 9106 -18,00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
J
encounters
We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
SORTIE AU JOUR
1988, mixed technique on canvas (2.30 x 2.30 m)
The last triptych in a series of seven
by Sophie Golvin
The French artist Sophie Golvin has spent several years at Karnak
in Egypt, painting among the ruins of ancient Thebes. "By
getting to know the natural cycles and physical features of this
district," she writes, "and living with them over a period of time,
I have tried to assimilate the spirit of the forms and collective
imagination of an ancient civilization and sought to express its
presence."
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JUNE 1991 CONTENTS
4
Interview with
JORGE LAVELLI
The
TÏÏÏÏÏ
Unesco
^courier
44th YEAR
Published monthly lr 35 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it Is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if It is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO,
London, 16 November 1945
45
USESCO IN ACTIOS
Ä* ft-. r-"
THE EARTH
FROM EVERY ANGLE
by Lydwine
d'Andigné de Asis
UNESCO IN ACTIOS
COPYRIGHT
<^^ '^** IS EVERYBODY'S
W^'Vfc- * BUSINESS
<J^J
rtL%
9
MAPS AND MAP-MAKERS
THE NEW HISTORY OF CARTOGRAPHY
hyJ.B.Harley 10
IMAGINING THE WORLD
by Catherine Delano-Smith 16
ATLASES, WAYS AND PROVINCES
by Sobhi Abdel Hakim 20
THE TREASURES OF MONTEZUMA
by Miguel León-Portilla 24
ZHENG HE'S SAILING CHART
by Mei-Ling Hsu 27
THE PATHFINDERS
by Alfredo Pinheiro Marques 28
WHEN MAPPING BECAME A SCIENCE
by Norman], Thrower 31
THE PERSPECTIVE FROM SPACE
by Jean-Philippe Grelot 35
A BIT OFF THE MAP
by Aleksandr S. Sudakov 39
CELESTIAL CARTOGRAPHY
by Werner Merkli
Interview with
Milagros del Corral
50
UNESCO IS ACTIOS
THE UNIVERSAL
COPYRIGHT
CONVENTION
by André Kéréver
Cover: Detail of a sealskin
and plywood map of islands
off Greenland, made by an
Eskimo hunter in 1925.
Yellow represents swampland,
black indicates lichens, and
uncoloured wood the area
covered by tides.
Back cover: The Ark on
Mount Ararat and the
division of the world between
the 3 sons of Noah: Shem in
Asia, Ham in Africa, and
Japheth in Europe. Scene
from a 15th-century
manuscript of Jean Mansel's
La fleur des histoires.
The Editors wish to thank
Prof. J.B. Harley
of the University of Wisconsin-
Milwaukee and
Mme Jasmine Desclaux,
cartographer, for their help in
the preparation of this issue.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
JORGE
LAVELLI
Jorge Lavelli is the director of the Théâtre National
de la Colline in Paris, founded in 1988. Born In
Argentina in 1931, he has staged more than eighty
major works in the classical and contemporary
European repertoire.
Since 1962 the hallmark of his productions has
been stringency, rituality and violence in its tragic
or absurd aspects. They have revealed the theatre
of Gombrowicz, Arrabal and Copi, but also that of
Seneca and Panizza. Attracted to opera, Lavelli has
since 1975 adopted a boldly innovative approach
to classics such as Idomeneo, Faust, La Traviata,
Madame Butterfly, Norma and to contemporary
works (Luigi Nono's In the Great Sun of Blossoming
love, Arrigo's The Return of Casanova, Sutermels-
ter's Berenger I, and Zygmunt Krauze's The Star).
Lavelli now works alternately as a theatre and
opera producer, being especially drawn to the operas
of Mozart (The Marriage of Figaro, La clemenza di
Tito) and the plays of Shakespeare {The Winter's
Tale, The Tempest, A Midsummer Night's Dream).
What, in your view, is theatre?
Whenever you have one or more people
performing in front of an audience, you have
theatre. Wherever this takes place, it consti¬
tutes a theatrical act in the strict sense. If, for
instance, at this precise moment, you were just
listening to my words and not engaging in a
dialogue with me, then we could talk about
the adumbration of a theatrical act. Theatre
is the primordial act of communication.
Will it cease to exist one day, like so many
other forms of artistic expression?
No. Theatre is an exceptional, unique acti
vity which brings together in the same place,
within the same unity of space and time, indi¬
viduals who are to transmit a message
whether in the form of physical expression or
wordsto a passive audience. Once these con¬
ditions have been met, you have theatre. But
the fact is that these conditions can be found
in any place and at any time. This is why
theatre cannot cease to exist. It cannot even
appear outdated.
It is, however, ephemeral. Hence it is des¬
tined to die, but only to be constantly reborn
in different forms, in any form whatsoever
that is rooted in the imagination, but always
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Jorge Lavelli receives an
award for his production of
Steven Berkoff's Greek at the
Théâtre de la Colline, Paris.
observing the unity of these two basic ele¬
ments: space and time. Even though, in a
theatrical performance, time is artificialwe
know that between eight and half-past nine
this evening it will be theatre timethe
audience and the actors or singers, those who
are going to pass on the message, live in the
same space and time during the performance.
It is an ephemeral act, but it can be repeated
ad infinitum.
Considering that, even though it is
repeated, this ephemeral act is unique, can
it not be said to take on an absolute value?
Indeed it can. A performance lives only in
the memories of those who were there, who
witnessed the theatrical act, and this is some¬
thing which is very specific to it. The only
place where it can live again is in their minds.
There is no other artistic activity about which
this can be said.
What's more, the time of the performance
does not coincide with the artificial time
created on stage. The action may unfold at a
very remote time or in the immediate present,
but the time created on stage is not real time
as it is experienced in everyday life.
Does a man ofthe theatre like yourselfget
a specific pleasurefrom working in this essen¬
tially ephemeral medium?
Definitely, because each performance is at
the same time a form of expression in which,
as though to raise this ephemeral moment to
the highest pitch of intensity, a large number
of elements play a part: the actors, the per¬
formers; objects which take on a different sig¬
nificance according to how they are placed on
stage; the architecture, the lighting; all these
are factors that shape and determine the way
in which the performance is perceived.
You didn't mention words.
Of course, words play an essential part. But
you can have theatre without using words. A
gesture can be just as eloquent as a speech.
There's also dance, mime, the theatre of
silence. But words are part and parcel of the
dramatic art.
Do you try to put on a play that will be
the same every day or do you accept the fact
that no two performances can be identical?
Every evening there will be some change,
which may be perceptible only to me.
Unforeseen events are bound to occur, just as
I'm sure they do when you're preparing your
magazine. Doesn't a page sometimes turn out
to be badly printed or a photo to be of poor
quality? It's the same in the theatre. Accidents
may happen that are outside your control. A
power cut or a storm if you're performing in
the open air will alter the climate of the per¬
formance. The mood or state of health of the
actors will also have an effect. These are acci¬
dents in so far as human beings are not the
same every day, even though they are readying
themselves to enact a ritual that has long been
studied, worked at and rehearsed over and
over again. They will also be influenced by
the size and behaviour of the audience. As for
the members of the audience, they will have
their own individual interpretation of the
play, which will depend on their own partic¬
ular sensibility, on their intelligence, on how
concerned they feel about what they are being
shown, and even on where they are sitting in
the theatre.
Let's talk about yourpersonal sensibility,
your identity. Would you say that in Argen¬
tina theatre is based on European theatre or
does Argentine theatre exist in its own right?
Argentina is a country of immigration, a
patchwork of peoples, in which Europeans
have a special place. Needless to say, Argen¬
tines of Spanish, French or Italian origin
brought with them their culture and hence
their theatre. But since the mid-nineteenth cen¬
tury there has also existed a specifically Argen¬
tine theatre with its own characteristics. Why?
Because every society finds in theatre a means
of analysing, studying and expressing itself.
Argentine theatre is the reflection of a culture,
an attitude to life, a way of responding to the
things around us. In Argentina, the French,
English and German classics are well known,
Goethe, Shakespeare and Molière are regularly
staged, but plays by Argentine writers are also
performed. In its form, however, Argentine
theatre is similar to European theatre, just like
American theatre as a' whole. It would in any
case be rather surprising if, in Argentina, that
farflung corner of Europe, the prevailing
theatrical influence were Kabuki, No or
Chinese theatre.
Who are your favourite playwrights?
At the Theatre de la Colline I have deliber¬
ately chosen to give precedence to contem¬
porary playwrights, to reveal present-day
authors to the public. But before being made
director, I staged a large number of produc¬
tions, in Paris, in the rest of France and in var¬
ious other European countries. Where the
choice of authors is concerned, I have always
followed my own inclination, for there is a
very close relationship between a producer's
sensibility, temperament and intellectual out¬
look and the plays he chooses to put on. Those
that I have chosen represent so to speak the
successive chapters of a novel that will come
to an end when I myself leave the theatre. A
novel that can be said to exist only for me, that
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A monument to the Spanish
playwright Jacinto Benavente
(1866-1954) In Madrid.
I alone can read from end to end. And one
that has a secret unity, a secret consistency.
For example, between the classical and
modern authors whose works I've put on
there are points of similarity. With hindsight
I would say that they share a freedom of
expression that enables them to go beyond
naturalism and to penetrate into the world of
the imagination, both in the patterns of lan¬
guage and in their musical organization. They
all show human beings in the round, in their
psychological and social dimensions, but also
with their inner lives and dreams. They tran¬
scend reality in the interests of lyricism,
expressing the inexpressible by virtue of a
different kind of stagecraft, a different idea of
the expressive value of gesture, a more effec¬
tive way of occupying space than would be
possible with a purely naturalistic approach.
This seems particularly relevant to your
production ofShakespeare's A Midsummer
Night's Dream...
Yes, a play dealing with love's taboos, with
the difficulty of being happy. I have, I think,
in my career in the theatre, remained faithful
to this theme of the aspiration to happiness.
I have put on other classical works, like
Life Is a Dream and The Wonder-Working
Magician by Calderón de la Barca, or The Tri¬
umph of Sensibility, a rarely performed play
by Goethe. Among modern authors, there is
Witold Gombrowicz, whom I introduced into
France with The Marriage, Yvonne, Princess of
Burgundy and Operetta, or Eugène Ionesco,
with whom I staged the first production of
Killing Game and put on The Picture and Exit
the King. There's also Fernando Arrabal,
Steven Berkoff, Carlos Fuentes, Thomas Bern-
hard, Mikhail Bulgakov, Copi of course, and
many others... This choice of contemporary
authors follows an inner logic, and of course
it's the same logic that's behind my work at
the Theatre National de la Collinewhere
there's no competition between classical and
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
modern, but an exclusive concern with the
theatre of today.
Contemporary theatre follows on directly
from classical theatre and can be just as
exciting, interesting and controversial. It can
also, by exploring new directions, applying
new approaches and providing a reflection of
the sensibility of our time, shed light on the
society in which we live and guide our polit¬
ical, cultural, spiritual and intellectual choices.
But don't you think that Shakespeare,
Corneille andMozart achieved such a degree
of perfection in their art that no one can
match them today?
No, this is the effect of distance, of all the
years that have come between. The contribu¬
tion of the twentieth-century playwrights is
considerable. Take someone like Eugene
O'Neill: the inventiveness of his theatre and
the vast range of his characters are staggering.
In his work, as in that of Shakespeare, the
mainsprings are ambition and the thirst for
power. But at the same time he creates, in
plays like Strange Interlude, a dreamlike
theatre, unconfined by realism, focusing on
extreme situations and emotional and phys¬
ical relationships of a rare violence. He opened
up vast possibilities for those who came after
him.
I'm also thinking of Pirandello, one of the
pillars of contemporary theatre. Without him
we wouldn't have had Ionesco, nor even
Beckett. This whole dialectic between form
and content, this duality of man at grips with
himself, of the individual face to face with his
own inwardness, these are extraordinary
insights granted to us by the contemporary
stage. Unsuspected horizons have thus been
revealed, bringing into the theatre the findings
of both science and psychoanalysiswhich
was unknown in Shakespeare's day. It is quite
possible that in three or four hundred years'
time these authors will have the same stature
as their Greek predecessors.
Take the case of Mozart, around whom
a cult has sprung up in our time and who
seems to be in the process of being redisco¬
vered. In the nineteenth century his music was
hardly ever performed. He was regarded as a
composer of genius but one who dealt in
trivialities. This point of view is no longer held
today. People have looked closely into what
he wrote, wondered why he chose particular
texts, and come to realize that there were the
same relations between certain of his
characters in many of his works and that this
recurrence of the same themes in different
guises was a way of developing a particular
world-view, of putting across a message; and
that this blend of seriousness and lightness
which runs through all his work had nothing
trivial about it. That on the contrary, there
was perhaps no view of life more profound.
So it happens that time corrects the impres¬
sion that a writer, a composer or an artist has
made upon his contemporaries.
How do you see the role of the producer?
His role is to recreate the play in his imagi
nation, to situate it in his own space and time
'in order to put it across more effectively and
to imprint upon it the colour of his own sen¬
sibility. When you are producing a play you
are not simply piecing it together, reducing
it to its bare bones or attempting a historical
reconstruction; you are taking a fresh look at
a piece of writing, reinterpreting it, mingling
your dreams with the author's.
You don't find this too restrictive?
No, certainly not. It's all part of the
ephemeral nature of the performance, of this
unique, fleeting moment which is theatre.
There is always an author and a text, and the
text is always open to new interpretations.
Actually, a theatre producer enjoys the same
freedom as a novelist: he can tamper with
time, set his own pace.
An act of theatre is an act of love, a work
of creation. If I put on a play, it is of course
because I like the play. So I bring something
to it, the feelings and emotions that it triggers
in me, my own way of seeing life, my own
response to words. When all is said and done,
it is an expression of absolute fidelity and, for
that very reason, demands the utmost
freedom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
'_ V L mtmmn
L¿ : ^.A *W A
Tixiwr m
, ^
la-
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A
1
CgaV
EDITORIAL
Men doubtless tried in very early times to make a
mental picture of their spatial horizons and of the
principal natural features they came across when they
journeyed by land, sea or river. Not that a need for
landmarks is an exclusively human characteristic.
When herds of wild animals make their annual trek
across the vast distances that separate their winter
quarters from their summer pastures, what do they
do but follow a map of their territory mysteriously
engraved in their memory?
Man, however, has made it his business to depict
the world around him in durable form. Using rudimen¬
tary instruments he began to reveal a kind of map¬
ping impulse by scratching symbolic representations
of his environment on cave walls and the bark of
trees. This impulse may have sprung from a need to
record for later generations the location of hunting
grounds and springs, hazards and havens. Perhaps
it was also part of an innate human desire to achieve
intellectual mastery over a world where unknown
lands stretched far beyond familiar landscapes.
As the centuries went by, human knowledge and
productive capacity increased, instruments for meas¬
uring distance were invented and improved, travellers
covered ever greater distances. The need to record
space visually according to increasingly formal rules
was extended to continents and then to the Earth in
its entirety. Methods and techniques of map-making
gradually became more sophisticated and accurate
thanks to the dedicated work of pioneering scientific
map-makers engaged on projects which in some
cases lasted for many years.
The story of cartography has been an epic of human
perseverance in the face of natural obstacles-
deserts, mountains, oceans. The longest and most
arduous task of map-makers, however, has been that
of overcoming the distorted visions and cultural
prejudices inherited from a past in which each people
naturally saw itself at the centre of the universe. This
issue of the UNESCO Courier shows how cartographers
have grappled with these and other problems and
presents some of their remarkable achievements.
The Miller Atlas (1515-1519), a Portuguese nautical chart
of the Indian Ocean. %.'.=,
¿r^
2s^
rÄ\'
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The new history of cartography
hy IB, Harley
Long portrayed as essentially
European, cartography
is now seen as a much more
universal visual language
10
A world map dating from
1109. It belongs to a
tradition of rectangular maps
that can be traced back to a
now-lost prototype In the
Commentary on the
Apocalypse of Saint John by
the Spanish monk Beatus
of Llebana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
IN the beginning there were maps. There has
always been a mapping impulse in individual
consciousness. The sensing of space and the
development of cognitive structures to under¬
stand it can be traced from the earliest societies
to the present. It was, however, only with the
first visible act of cartographic representation
the drawing of a map on whatever medium was
to handthat a documented step in abstract
thinking initiated the history of cartography.
By substituting an analogical space for a real
space in the process of mapping, human beings
acquired intellectual mastery over their world. In
many societies maps preceded both writing and
mathematical notation. Only much later in the
nineteenth century were they associated with the
modern disciplines we now call cartography. Yet
maps produced before then penetrate to the
deepest roots of our culture.
What may be regarded as the oldest authen¬
ticated map in the world, dated to approximately
6000 BC, was unearthed in an archaeological exca¬
vation at Çatal Hüyük in west-central Turkey in
1963. Its subject was the neolithic town of that
name. Painted on a wall, it showed the streets and
houses in plan form, lying beneath the profile of
the mountain of Hasan Dag with its volcano
erupting. But though this map, which shows a
layout corresponding to that of the excavated
town, bears some resemblance to a modern plan,
its purpose was very different. The site from
which it was excavated was a shrine or holy
room, and the image was created as part of a ritual
act, as a "product of the moment", and not
intended to last beyond that event.
A Eurocentric vision
Only in recent years have maps such as that of
Çatal Hüyükand comparable engravings and
paintings in the rock art of Africa, the Americas,
Asia, and Europebeen studied as a distinctive
category of prehistoric cartography. That this
should be so is not merely a reflection of
problems of identifying maps in these early cul¬
tures. It is also an expression of a more deep-
seated tendency in the history of cartography that
has restricted the canon of "acceptable" maps.
From the nineteenth century the history of
cartography has been portrayed largely as that of
Western tradition, originating in the ancient
Near East, Egypt, arid in the Greco-Roman era,
and reaching its culmination via a European
pedigree in the developed world of today. Though
interrupted in the Middle Ages, and exhibiting
both minor reversions and major revolutions,
that cartographic history was seen as proceeding
developmentally from simple forms toward a
more advanced level of numerical application.
Maps were assigned a position in the evolu¬
tionary sequence. The corollary was to exclude
from serious study those maps judged to show
no signs of progress toward the goal of objec¬
tivity. Even some of the earlier maps of Euro¬
pean culture, like the great world maps of the
Christian Middle Ages, were once dismissed as
being unworthy of study. Thus, at the beginning
of the present century, Charles Raymond Beazley
could describe two of the most celebrated world
maps of the later Middle Ages, the Hereford and
Ebstorf maps as "non-scientific. ..monstrosities",
and write of their "complete futility".
Maps in non-European cultures were consi¬
dered even further alienated from the epicentre
of cartography. Traditional approaches to the his¬
tory of Islamic cartography, for example, reflect
this tendency of European scholars to see the
world in their own image. The maps of Islam
were explained largely as a Greek heritage,
ignoring the extent to which translations into
Arabic of works such as Ptolemy's Almagest and
Geographia had been ingeniously appropriated
and adapted to the specific purposes of Islamic 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
culture and religion. Arab maps such as those of
the Balkhi School of geographers in the tenth cen¬
tury were assessed by a Ptolemaic yardstick rather
than being understood as a fusion of mapping tra¬
ditions, even though they embodied Persian as
well as Greek elements.
The maps of non-European cultures were
only allocated more space in Western histories
when they revealed features similar to those deve¬
loped on European maps. The focus was on car¬
tographic similarities in these distant cultures
rather than on their differences. Thus the rich his¬
tory of Chinese cartographywith datable
artefacts surviving from the fourth century BC
was recognized by one leading scholar as "the
same science" that had earlier developed on the
European scene. Much emphasis in this compara¬
tive cartographic history was placed on the iden¬
tification of mathematical aspects of mapmaking,
on the codification of methodological principles
for cartography (such as those of Pei Xiu
[223-271], the "father of scientific cartography"
in China), and on the appearance of technical
innovations such as grids, regular scales, abstract
conventional signs, and even contoursall aspects
that fitted the Western model of cartographic
excellence. Thus the maps from the Han dynasty
found in a tomb near Chansha in Hunan
province were seized upon by both Chinese and
Western scholars as confirmation of an early
scientific development of cartography. They
became the lineal ancestors of the modern map.
The "scientific" traditions of mapping in
Chinaand their diffusion into Japan and
Koreareceived an attention that was not
accorded to cultures that had no analogy with
Western mapping practices. Thus the indigenous
maps drawn in India before the British occupa¬
tion, with their unfamiliar signs and pictorial
style, have found no place until recently in con¬
ventional accounts of cartographic history. They
were either not recognized as maps at all or dis¬
missed as quaint curiosities, to be collected with
other ethnographic specimens. Lowest of all on
the ladder of rational progress were the "primi¬
tive" maps of preliterate non-Western cultures.
Detail from the mosaic map of
Madaba, which formed the
floor of a 6th-century church
In Madaba (Jordan). It shows
the estuary of the river
Jordan.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Ranging from paintings produced by the
Aboriginal peoples of Australia to maps of the
Native Americans, and from the stick-charts of the
Marshall Islanders to the battle plans drawn on
the ground by Maori warriors in New Zealand,
they were widely regarded as an inchoate stage
in the cognitive history of cartography. To the
extent that they lacked orientation, regular scales,
and the Euclidean geometry of modern maps, or
were drawn on unfamiliar media, little effort was
made to crack their codes of representation. They
remained on the periphery of Western carto¬
graphic achievement.
In such ways, the history of mapping became
a prisoner of the categories and definitions of
scholars. The rich variety of ways in which space
has been represented in the global mosaic of
human culture still had to be recorded. It was to
remedy this Eurocentric perspective that in 1987,
in the first volume of a new History of Cartog¬
raphy, we adopted a definition of maps that would
allow a measure of relativism into the study of
the history of maps.
A universal language
In the belief that each society has, and has had,
its own natural ways of seeing and producing
images of space, we came to define maps simply
as "graphic representations that facilitate a spa¬
tial understanding of things, concepts, conditions,
processes or events in the human world." The
rationale of such a broad definition was that it
applies to maps in all cultures at all times, and
not only to those of the modern age. Moreover,
it allows the writing of a more contextual history,
by treating maps as a form of "knowledge" as
a whole and not solely as the products of long-
term technological diffusion from a European
hearth.
So, a new shape is starting to emerge for the
history of cartography, one in which cultures
speak for themselves. It has two main strengths.
First of all, there is now a growing awareness that
cartography is not only much older but also,
despite the many gaps in the artefactual record,
a much more universal visual language than was
formerly supposed. By accepting some of the pit¬
falls of cross-cultural comparison and by
expanding the definition of what a "map" can
beso that it now embraces, for example, cos-
mological and celestial representations as well as
those of the Earthwe are beginning to inscribe
mapping traditions that were previously blank
spaces in the history of cartography. The develop¬
ment of mapping in India serves as an illustra¬
tion of these changes in the writing of the his¬
tory of maps.
Despite India's major contribution to the
development of the mathematical sciences, rela¬
tively few geographical maps have survived from
the pre-European period. What fills the carto¬
graphic archives are largely cosmographical maps.
All three of the main ancient religions of India-
Buddhism, Hinduism, and Jainismhave left a
complex legacy of cosmographical representation.
In some maps, the Earth and the universe are
often centred on the axis of Mount Meru
(Sumeru) around the base of which the continents
are arranged. On other maps, the universe is ver¬
tically stratified, with graphic representations of
numerous heavens and nether worlds through
which the soul could travel.
Natural features might be given fabulous sizes
and shapes: in Buddhist cosmography, for
example, the world containing India was known
and portrayed as Jambudvipa, the Rose-apple
Island, after the jambu tree which grew at its
centre. To judge India's cartographic history in
the light of the European tradition of terrestrial
mapping is to misunderstand fundamentally the
Weltanschauung of Indian culture and to fail to
grasp concepts of space and time that are
unfamiliar to Western eyes.
Not only are traditional histories of cartog¬
raphy dramatically enlarged by embracing this
"new" corpus of cosmological mapsand estab¬
lished concepts vastly enriched by the Asian map
experiencebut we learn also a new respect for
maps from other regions. As we extend our car¬
tographic encounter into Southeast Asia and into
Tibet, into pre-nineteenth-century Africa, or into
Sumerlan terra-cotta tablet
(c. 2100 BC) showing plots of
cultivated land belonging to
the city of Umma (today Tell
Jokha, southern Iraq).
J. B. HARLEY,
of the United States, is
professor of geography at the
University of Wisconsin-
Milwaukee and director of the
Office for Map History in the
American Geographical Society
Collection of the University's
Golda Meir Library. He is co-
editor, with Prof. David
Woodward, of a multi-volume
History of Cartography of
which vol. 1, Cartography in
Prehistoric, Ancient, and
Medieval Europe and the
Mediterranean was published
in 1987 by the University of
Chicago Press. Further
volumes are scheduled for
publication from 1991
onwards. The History of
Cartography project is
supported by the National
Endowment for the Humanities
of the United States
Government and by several
private foundations. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
pre-Columbian America and the Pacific realm
before Cook, we meet other map traditions that
bear no resemblance to modern European maps
but that are no less valid cartographies. The old
preconceptions about the scope of maps in
human history have been challenged and the old
histories of cartography are in continuous
revision.
Jain mándala (Gujarat,
18th-19th century).
The 7 oceans and the
divisions of time are disposed
around Mount Meru, the pivot
of the world.
Thus the second strength of the new history
of cartography is a greatly enlarged understanding
of the purpose to which maps have been put.
There are few aspects of human action and
thought that have not been mapped at one time
or another. The more we explore the terrain of
maps across the major cultures of the world, the
longer the list becomes of different activities to
which they may have "made a difference". Uses
range from the prosaically practical to the seem¬
ingly speculative.
In ancient China, for instance, the utility of
maps as instruments of political power as
boundary and cadastral maps, as bureaucratic
record, as diplomatic protocol, as plans for water
conservancy, as a means of assessing taxes, as stra¬
tegic documents in military logisticsare all well
documented. Equally, Chinese maps enter into
other cultural dialogues. Far from being just a
science of measurement, maps have been closely
linked to literature and painting. They have been
integrated into historical scholarship; they have
been used to reconstruct geographies of the past
and have been carved on stone in public places
as witnesses to cultural continuity. They have
been used in ritual, as is confirmed by their
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
presence in tombs; they became tools of divina¬
tion or were used as talismans to mediate between
unseen forces. They have been used in the astro¬
logical prediction of celestial events.
Mental images
China was by no means unique in the range of
uses it developed for maps. In Western as much
as Eastern societies, maps have resulted in a car¬
tography that invariably combines the objective
with the subjective, fact with value, myth with
documented event, and locational silence with
coordinated place. If in traditional Eurocentric
histories we have neglected the mythic, the psy¬
chological, and the symbolic uses of maps in
favour of the practical, it is our obsession with
scientific models rather than with the actual his¬
tory of cartographic practice that is to blame.
The insights thus gained from the study of
non-Western mapping traditions and practices
can be applied to the history of maps throughout
the world. As we identify many more local tra¬
ditions of mapping, cartographic history can no
longer be seen as part of a one-way process by
which cultural hegemony was exercised by Euro¬
peans over colonized peoples. In the Americas,
for example, evidence is mounting of the extent
to which maps of colonial territories published
in Europe from the sixteenth to the nineteenth
centuries were underpinned by geographical
knowledge contributed by indigenous peoples.
Even in situations of conflict, maps in many parts
of the world were a means of cultural exchange
that reached over the barriers of language. And in
other cases, maps were also a means of resistance
by which colonized peoples sought to oppose the
appropriation of their culture and territory.
In order to explore these new directions, map
historians are embracing theories derived from
the humanities and social sciences at large. The
well-worn story of the achievements of a numer¬
ical technology in the way the world is
represented is being challenged. No longer are we
content to accept that even our modern maps,
though generated by Landsat satellite and com¬
puter graphics, are above the machinations of
power. No less than a map of an Indian cosmog¬
raphy or an Aztec map of the universe, these
satellite-based maps are socially constructed. Car¬
tography, we now begin to realize, is the product
of wider discourses, a form of power-knowledge
caught up with the major transformations of
world history, created and received by human
agents, exploited by elites, to materialize as a
world seen through a veil of ideology.
From the beginning maps have been a mental
image. Today they are still recognized as a way
of seeing, but we begin to understand what
"seeing" is. Rather than thinking of maps as the
mirror of the world, we now see them as a
simulacrum: sometimes preceding the territory;
constantly redescribing the world in all its cul¬
tural diversity.
Redrawing the Earth
In 1973, a German cartographer, Arno Peters, unveiled a new map projection which
he had devised In an attempt to give a true representation of the relative sizes
of the Earth's land masses. One of the avowed alms of the Peters projection is
to eliminate the "geographical superiority" enjoyed by countries of the northern
hemisphere In a number of other projection systems, Including that established
by the Flemish cartographer Gerard Mercator In 1569 and described In the text
below. However, it Is impossible to reproduce the spherical Earth on a flat sur¬
face without some kind of distortion, and the Peters projection has stirred up
vigorous controversy In many quarters, including within the United Nations system.
The Mercator projection
The Mercator projection (Map 1) provided European seafarers with the
fidelity of angle they needed to line up their compass bearings with points
on the map. But to achieve this Mercator had to place the lines of latitude
progressively further apart as they moved away from the equator. This
makes Greenland and all northern hemisphere countries grossly exagger¬
ated in size, and Europe appears to be at the centre of the world.
The distortions of Mercator's map did not seem strange to Europeans
in the sixteenth century, an era of expanding colonial empires. Yet today,
although European colonialism belongs largely to the past, Mercator's
sixteenth-century map still retains much of its grip.
Many attempts have been made to improve on Mercator, for example
by using a rounded grid as in the Winkelsche projection (Map 2). But this
means that north-south and east-west directions are lost. Also the coun¬
tries on the edges of the map are distorted in shape.
Things would be simpler if we could replace these various versions with
just one projection reflecting what most people actually want from a world
map. This is precisely what Arno Peters has tried to do.
Fidelity of area and direction
Peters fixed on two things which a world map must have to be interna¬
tionally acceptable: fidelity of area and true north-south and east-west direc¬
tions. Beyond these two fixed principles, the compromises have to start.
As no map can give any country exactly the same shape it has on the globe,
the ideal is to minimize distortion.
The Peters map
On the Peters map (Map 3) the maximum shape distortion occurs in the
polar region where countries like Iceland tend to be flattened, and along
the equator, where Zaire and Sumatra look longer than we are used to.
But maximum shape distortion on the Peters map is never more than 2:1,
compared with a 4:1 distortion of Europe on the Mercator map.
This new, equal-area map is the first fruit of what Peters sees as "a
new cartography", free of the historical perceptions that have shaped
earlier world maps.
Source: United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
by Catherine Delano-Smith
The maps of yesteryear
often recorded myths
and legends as well as
hard facts. How far have
things changed today?
I
16
MAGINATION has played a key role in the his¬
tory of cartography. Long before the fifth cen¬
tury BC, when Greek scholars found the Earth
to be a globe, and in far corners of the Earth never
touched by their learning, people imagined the
shape of the Earth they lived on. The Aztecs saw
their world as five squares; ancient Peruvians as
a box; ancient Egyptians as egg-shaped. Some
early Chinese also believed the Earth to be like
an egg or like a ball, and derided those who
thought of it as flat and square within circular
heavens. In Japan, before Christian missionaries
arrived at the turn of the seventeenth century
bringing with them the notion that the world is
round, there seems to have been at least one
theory of the Earth as a cube.
Such ideas have been expressed in map form
from prehistoric times onwards all over the
world. In rock art, circles and squares, thought
to represent the world, are common motifs in
cave paintings or on carved rocks from Scan¬
dinavia to India and from Asia to the Americas.
The Korean Ch'iian Chin's image of a cubic
Earth is found in a manuscript of 1547. The five
squares of the Aztec "world" were painted on
the opening page of the Fejérváry Screenfold, a
ritual book of the pre-conquest period.
To some early societies, symmetry was
important. In pre-classical Greece, at the time of
Homer, the circle of the world was divided by
an equator, roughly along the line of the Mediter¬
ranean Sea. The ancient philosopher-geographers
of classical Greece drew lines around the sphere
dividing the Earth into parallel zones or climata,
all places within one zone having roughly the
same length of day. Some of the global symmetry
was lost when Pliny divided the part of the Earth
best known to the Greeks and Romans into seven
zones, all north of the equator, in order to allow
three for the "wilderness" of the far north.
In Hindu India, some authorities depicted the
world with four continents, corresponding to the
four cardinal points, although they had as yet no
"knowledge" of the Americas. Geographers in
the Roman period illustrated their textbooks with
diagrams of a spherical Earth subdivided into the
three continents they knew about (Asia, Africa,
Europe). Some, like Strabo in the first century
AD, suspected the existence of other land masses,
perhaps even a fourth continent, and a few early
historic maps from Europe seem to suggest this.
It was not, however, until after the last decade
of the fifteenth century that Europeans could
start to put the Americas onto their maps of the
world because some of them had seen the "new
lands" for themselves. Even so, it was not always
easy to know just what to draw. One map of 1502
(the Camino map) shows the two Americas
widely separated; another (1528, by P. Coppo)
shows North America as a group of small islands;
yet another (1548, by G. Gastaldi) depicts North
America as a continuation of Asia.
Several sixteenth-century maps showed a
Mare Indicum or Sea of Verrazano, almost
bisecting the northern continent. This was the
result of one voyager's too-hasty identification of
a stretch of inland water along the eastern sea¬
board of North America with the Pacific. Yet
other geographical myths concerned the penin¬
sulas of Florida and Yucatan, discovered by Euro¬
peans in 1513 and 1518-1519 respectively but first
charted as islands. Then there was the problem
of California, first correctly charted as a penin¬
sula after a Spanish fleet sent by Cortes had suc¬
cessfully navigated to the head of the Gulf in
1540, but nevertheless shown as an island on
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
-
I r
i'^-n
S*
y
! ¡J
t Jtigiii
I, '
p RAt%
Ixdilirici no1;
l'illi Tl' nil'll
î
»iliV.tVirfoli \
%
; I
j(! I SA' i
y k . - --
"p»rc>uwuiw«jgi" , ',
]
î
'
î
M TAA^
! ufe J I
[j.Vlv.rCJTCPnpiv.iiott>fiiilO>> i , -r J" K PT»/v n ^ ' «I» * U '
toniniioqiUivn-Ui.l.lhWo f LKKTÄlO ,
hoorn.\ro^coiccluiicriot«f /t = 5*,,,.-,J;,i, . .
Icqiulricvmnfllulcri-iiucV -7 . «& -ja
£lnc!>o crccllcnflmio c
Votvtifl'mio ijw.itor cl qn-ilf; . lUIlflU
*
»
many seventeenth- and eighteenth-century maps.
A similar misconception was a belief in a con¬
tinuous northwestern sea passage across North
America, providing a northern route to China.
Ortelius showed it clearly on a map of 1564. In
1592 a Greek sailor reported he had reached its
western end. Thereafter, for three centuries,
Europeans vied with each other to find this
mythical passage, driven by the hope of gain
through the trading advantage the way through
to the Pacific was thought to bring them.
The location of legends
Many maps depict famous events. These events
may be historically testifiable ones such as the
sites of recent battles. Others show where a
historic event was thought to have taken place.
Some Indian maps from the eighteenth and
nineteenth centuries show not only Vraj (the
birthplace of Krishna) but also a host of places
sacred to Hindus as part of the Krishna legend.
Still others showwithout any annotation or
stylistic differentiationthe location of wholly
imagined events. Atlantis and a host of other
legendary islands were shown on maps of the
Atlantic in the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries
especially.
Long-lived legends about famous personages
such as Alexander of Macedonia are other
examples of the historical imagination which
were depicted on maps. The "Alexander myth"
is seen on Ptolemy's maps of Asia in the Columns
of Alexander (representing the Caspian Gates
through which Alexander was said to have
passed). It is found too on a late eighteenth-
century Indian map of the world on which Alex¬
ander is seen with the men who allegedly asked
for his help against the mythical giants Gog and
Magog and with the wall he was said to have built
to imprison the accursed ones. A Christian map-
pamundi of the thirteenth century depicts just
such a Wall of Gog and Magog in northeast Asia,
probably an echo of the real Great Wall of China.
- ' öUiuiciratrrc
Detail of the Fra Mauro world
map of 1459. The map Is a
compendium of geographical
sources, Including Portuguese
expeditions to Africa,
Ptolemy's Geography, the
Marco Polo narratives, and
portulan charts.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
Asia was also supposed to be the home of the
priest-king Préster John, an early medieval Euro¬
pean legendary hero who would, it was said, help
the Christian world against the Muslims in the
Holy Land. By the mid-fifteenth century, though,
Préster John's kingdom was believed to be in
Ethiopia, part of an India which extended over
much of Africa as well as Asia. After 1488, by
which time the Portuguese had opened a new
seaway to India round the southern tip of Africa
and past Abyssinia, maps of Africa showed an
enthroned Préster John, his palace, or the royal
mountain, Mount Amaro, in which his sons were
supposed to have been incarcerated until the
order of succession called each to the throne in
turn.
Fictional as well as philosophical literature
has spawned a different category of imagined
historical places, where the entire country or
region depicted on the map is mythical. An early
example is the woodcut map produced by Hans
Holbein in 1518 for the second edition of Thomas
More's Utopia. The tradition continues today.
Imagination and power
Maps have also carried graphic messages about
the imagined political supremacy of nations or
societies. They may have been drawn to back ter¬
ritorial claims or support chauvinistic notions
about status (such as maps drawn by Nazi
archaeologists to show the distribution of
Neolithic "Germans" in Greece and Bronze Age
"Germans" in Scandinavia).
One traditional conception of China placed
the heartland of the royal domains in the centre
of four concentric zones, the outermost of which
represented the zones of "allied barbarians" and,
most distant of all, of "cultureless savagery". The
Chinese were thus less than impressed when the
Jesuit missionary Matteo Ricci arrived and
showed them maps of the world in which Europe
and the Atlantic occupied the central positions.
Tactfully, Ricci drew another map centred on the
Pacific Ocean.
Maps may reflect the economic competition
that so often underlies political concerns. Maps
from the period of European discovery
represented the often fabulous mineral wealth of
the "new" lands to justify the discoverers'
exploits and to encourage further investment in
their voyages.
From the Americas came the legend of the
alluring Kingdom of Gold and the even more
attractive El Dorado. The latter was the legen¬
dary city of the king of "Manoa", situated on the
shores of an equally mythical "Lake Parima",
which the Spaniards heard about in 1530 and
which they supposed to lie in the basin of the
Orinoco river. The legend gave rise to numerous
expeditions to the highlands of Guiana, one of
which was dispatched from England by Sir
Walter Raleigh. Part of Raleigh's manuscript map
(1595) survives, showing "that mighty, rich and
beautiful Empire of Guinea, and. ..that great and
golden city which the Spaniards call El Dorado
keep out the "barbarians".
Detail from the 13th-century and the naturals [call] Manoa". The Frenchman
^:rshMoawp;Partthoefrsh t- ^7 -s^ * «weg** map -m ^
legendary wall built by on which the elusive Lake Parima was promi-
Aiexander the Great around nently shown, with equally fabulous creatures
the kingdom of Magog to n£arby) such as headless men and fears0mely
armed womenthe Amazonians of another
ancient myth.
A new world
seen in terms of the old
Similar reasons of self-interest led European map-
makers to represent the landscapes of what was
to them a new world in terms of the old. To
avoid alarming prospective colonists, maps por¬
trayed the landscape as gentle: open parkland,
dotted with round trees like the familiar oaks and
elms of the undulating plains of southern England
or lowland France. Colonial settlements were
ranked in terms of the European social order;
native settlements were discreetly marked. In fact,
the existence of natives was altogether better
ignored, according to this view. The myth of a
European, not an Indian, country was thus early
perpetrated by maps. It is still there, in the Euro¬
pean place-names which dispossessed the Indian
ones.
Even in their own countries, European map-
makers could be equally selective in what they
put on or (just as significant) omitted from their
maps. In the seventeenth century, the neat, ord¬
erly and wholly bland appearance of the early
atlases portrayed an imaginary landscape that
pushed the social and economic contrasts and
political disorders of real life out of mind. By the
late eighteenth century, standardized shading had
CATHERINE DELANO-SMITH,
of the United Kingdom, has
taught historical geography at
a number of British universities
and is currently Visiting Reader
in London University's
Department of Mediterranean
Studies. Her special interests
in the history of cartography
include prehistoric maps, the
history of map signs before
1800, and maps in bibles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
reduced the entire urban scene, with the houses
and workplaces of the great and the poor, to a
mythical uniformity, another landscape of the
mind.
In search of an earthly Paradise
Finally, but fundamentally, maps have been used
from the beginning to portray the imagined
worlds of religious man. Like the question of the
shape of the geographical world, the structure of
the cosmos has varied according to the sacred
myths and the teaching of the gods in each
society.
Cosmological maps tend to be schematic in
style and often symmetrical. Common to many
cosmologies, especially in Asia, dominated by the
heights of the Himalayas, is the concept of a cen¬
tral mountain, the vertical axis of the cosmos, like
the Mount Sumeru of the Buddhists and the
Mount Meru of the Hindus. Muslim cosmolog¬
ical maps placed Mecca at the centre of the Earth
because of its position opposite the centre of the
sky.
Of vital concern to every believer is the
journey from this world to the next. Maps have
been made to guide the newly dead. In the New
Hebrides early in the twentieth century, the
labyrinth design was still being sketched out in
the sand to teach initiates The Way. The route
had to be memorized. From Australia to Siberia,
complex designs painted on shamans' drums
served as aide-mémoires. In ancient Egypt, maps
were painted on the outside of coffins together
with relevant extracts from The Book of the
Dead. Here word and image were inscribed
together to ensure the individual's safe journey
through the underworld.
Maps of the geographical world have also
been richly, sometimes excessively, invested with
religious myth and symbolism. Christians came
to identify each of the three continents of the Old
World with one of Noah's sons (Shem for Asia,
Ham for Africa, and Japheth for Europe). From
the eighth century AD onwards, their figures or
names were sometimes included in diagrams
drawn to illustrate, in the Roman tradition, new
copies of older written geographical descriptions
of the world (the so-called T-O maps).
Another feature imposed on European
regional and world maps by the Christian theo¬
logical imagination has been the terrestrial para¬
dise or Garden of Eden. In the fifth century AD
an Irish monk, St. Brendan, sailed westwards to
find what he believed were the Isles of Paradise.
St. Brendan's islands remained on maps for many
centuries, even when, as on the Hereford map-
pamundi, Eden was marked in the east. St.
Brendan's islands (sometimes marked as the For¬
tunate Isles) were often confused with real
Atlantic islands. Usually, though, in accordance
with the description in Genesis chapter 2, Eden
was placed in the east. On medieval maps it was
placed prominently at the edge of the map.
With the emergence of Protestantism in the
sixteenth century, and especially John Calvin's
insistence on a literal interpretation of the bib¬
lical text, Eden had to be shown close by the Tigris
and Euphrates, two of the four rivers said to water
it. The religious drive to find an earthly Eden
could be strong. Despite increasingly detailed
knowledge of real world geography, the search
continued to recent times. In 1666, M. Carver
published a map in his book showing Paradise
in Armenia, and in 1882 General Gordon put for¬
ward his idea that, before the Flood (yet another
of the world's "great myths") Paradise had been
situated on Praslin in the Seychelles.
Perhaps we should not dismiss the topic of
imagined worlds too lightly, as if it illustrated
merely some of the quainter sides of human
nature or human history. We still often prefer to
imagine the world or to lead others to see it in
a preferred way. National maps may present a
"scientific" face but it is not difficult to deduce
omissions, such as military installations, airfields,
or politically sensitive targets such as biological
research centres. Nor is it difficult to discern the
way modern geographical "myths" are created
through, for example, the removal from the map
of settlements after rumours of certain types of
man-made disaster, or the translation of sea or
city names on the map as a cartographic substi¬
tute for political aggression less easily achieved
overtly. In modern as in ancient maps, myth and
legend remain ingrained.
Above, a map of the world
embellishes an Initial capital
letter In a 1417 manuscript
of the De Chorographia,
a treatise by the Latin
geographer Pomponius Mela
(1st century AD).
Detail from an atlas by the
French sailor and
cartographer Guillaume Le
Testu (1556).
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
Atlases, ways and
provinces
by Sobhi Abdel Hakim
Building on the heritage of Antiquity, the Arabs made their own original
contributions to cartography, ushering in a golden age
It is very difficult to form a value judgement
of the Arab maps produced in the Middle Ages
since, despite all the searches made, only a very
small number of originals have been found.
The maps constructed by al-Khwarizmi (the
planisphere drawn at the request of Caliph al-
Ma'mun), al-Balkhi, al-Istakhri, Ibn Haukal, al-
Maqdisi and the anonymous author of the Limits
of the Universe, have been lost. Even al-Idrisi's
famous map is only a copy dating from the
fifteenth century.
The history of cartography among the Arabs,
as among all other peoples, is closely bound up
with the development of geography and its many
related fields. From ancient times the Arabs too
needed precise bearings to regulate the course of
their lives and their activities. The advent of Islam
made this all the more necessary. In order to fulfil
the obligations of prayer, fasting and ritual pil¬
grimage, they had to be able to decipher the
cosmic clock and know which way to turn to face
Mecca.
Heirs and successors
However, it was not until Arabic translations
were made of ancient books, especially those of
the Greeks and of Claudius Ptolemaeus (Ptolemy)
in particular, that Arab cartography became a
major field of scientific study. These translations
were made possible by the generous patronage
of the caliphs, who understood the value of the
knowledge built up by the ancients. Wishing to
incorporate that knowledge into Muslim culture,
they provided a variety of rewards for those who
translated the scientific works of Antiquity into
Arabic. Caliph al-Mam'un, for instance, paid
translators an amount of gold coins and bars
equivalent in weight to the works translated.
The Arabs were careful to preserve this
heritage and throughout the Middle Ages cons¬
tantly added to it, both with contributions of
-*c
SOBHI ABDEL HAKIM,
of Egypt, is professor of
human geography at Cairo
University, of which he was
formerly Vice-President.
their own and drawing on the work of Indian
scholars. In the period extending from the
seventh to the twelfth centuries, the pole of
geographical learning thus shifted. From Europe
it moved to the great centres of scientific study
and investigation of Baghdad, Cordoba and
Damascus. It can therefore be said without risk
of error and despite the lack of direct contact
between Arab and European cartographers, that
the resurgence of mathematics and astronomy in
Rome, Oxford and Paris in the thirteenth cen¬
tury was simply the direct result of the advances
made by the Arabs in cartography. The Arabs
kept the torch burning and paved the way for
the great blossoming of science that occurred in
the West during the Renaissance.
The Arabs were right to regard the work of
Ptolemy as the peak of the achievements of the
Greeks and Romans. Yet they did not follow
blindly the teachings of the great Greek
astronomer, mathematician and geographer. The
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Arab travellers disputed a fair number of his ideas.
The Arab astronomers for their part calculated
anew the distance represented by a degree and
arrived at very precise results. They were not
merely links in the transmission of learning.
Eager to build on what was already known, they
naturally started out from where their
predecessors had left off.
These efforts culminated in the writings of
al-Battani and al-Mas'udi in the tenth century.
Al-Battani questioned many of the hypotheses
put forward by Ptolemy. Unlike Ptolemy, who
thought that Africa and Asia were joined near the
Malaysian peninsula, he believed that the Indian
Ocean was an open sea. Al-Biruni's writings on
the East and those of al-Idrisi on the West
rounded off the Arabs' knowledge of the world.
Several factors, which it would take too long
to list here, contributed to the development of
the geographic and cartographic sciences among
the Arabs. Islam, which had become their religion,
encouraged them to pursue knowledge to the
four corners of the Earth. Huge expanses of land
had been won through conquest, and the
resources they contained needed to be assessed
in order for the most suitable tax system to be
introduced. In addition, three of these territories
(Mesopotamia, Persia and Egypt) were cradles of
civilization. If the Arabs were to govern them,
they had to know about them.
Travellers and cartographers
So big did the empire become that a postal service
and a road system became necessary. These in
their turn were instrumental in developing trade,
fostered by the unification of language and
religion. Increasing numbers of books described
"the ways and provinces". The pilgrimage to
Mecca also played a great part in developing the
Arabs' taste for travel and for geography. The pil¬
grim would converse in the same language with
Detail of a map by the Arab
geographer Ibn Haukal
showing part of central Asia
and Transoxlana, the land
between the Oxus and the
Jaxartes rivers. Samarkand,
the chief city of Transoxlana,
Is shown at centre of map.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
other Muslims from different places and from
different social backgrounds. These pilgrimages,
which took up a considerable amount of time,
often afforded invaluable opportunities for study,
exploration and trade. Upon their return, the
travellers-cum-pilgrims-cum-traders wrote
accounts of their experiences that were mines of
geographical information. There were many car¬
tographers among their number, including Ibn
Haukal, al-Mas'udi and al-Idrisi.
More than one Arab geographer was marked
by the teachings of Ptolemy, which served as the
starting-point for the mapping of the heavens and
the Earth alike.
Mohammed Ibn Musa al-Khwarizmi laid the
foundations for Arab geography. His Book ofthe
Configuration of the Earth (Kitab surat al-ard),
written in the early half of the ninth century,
incorporates and amends the findings of Ptolemy.
He is believed to have designed his work, together
with his celebrated planisphere, in collaboration
with other scholars, at the request of Caliph al-
Ma'mun. Unfortunately, most of the maps that
al-Khwarizmi helped to construct have been lost.
Only four of them have come down to us. They
are the oldest Arab maps known to exist.
In the tenth century the most famous Arab
cartographer was Abul Hassan Ali al-Mas'udi.
Born in Baghdad, he spent his early years travel¬
ling, visiting in turn India, Ceylon, the China Sea,
Asia Minor, Syria, Palestine, Zanzibar,
Madagascar and Oman. Towards the end of his
life he went to Egypt where he met his death,
at al-Fustat. Al-Mas'udi must have read a large
part of the geographic literature then available.
He mentions a large number of works which
have since disappeared. His major work, The
Meadows of Gold and Mines of Gems (Muruj adh-
dhahab wa ma'adin al-jawahir), is a conspectus of
his experiences. Al-Mas'udi wrote several other
works. His planisphere of the then known world
is one of the most accurate Arab maps of the
time. He believed that the Earth was a sphere.
He added two continents to the known world,
one in the South Seas and, for the sake of balance,
another on the opposite side of the globe.
A new kind of map, more like a cartogram,
then made an appearance with Ibn Haukal's map
of the world, which was a treasure house of eco¬
nomic information. This was an expanded ver¬
sion of al-Istakhri's Atlas consisting of a simpli¬
fied outline in which shores are shown as curves
or straight lines, and islands and inland seas, such
as the Caspian Sea and the Aral Sea, as circles.
The Golden Age
The golden age of Arab cartography, which had
started to develop a century earlier, was the tenth
century (fourth century of the Hegira). It was sig¬
nalled by the publication of a series of maps
Úte Atlas of Islam-which were inseparable parts
of a large number of works on "the ways and
provinces". The method employed to describe
the Muslim world, introduced by a man hailing
from Balkh (al-Balkhi), was taken up and deve¬
loped by a Persian scholar from Iran (al-Istakhri)
whose work served in turn as a starting-point for
a great traveller and geographer born in Baghdad
(Ibn Haukal) who revised, corrected and consider¬
ably expanded it.
There was no longer anything in common
between these maps and the Ptolemaic models.
The Atlas of Islam still contained twenty-one
maps, in an order laid down once and for all, with
the first showing a spherical world in its entirety.
This was followed by six maps representing
Arabia, the Persian Sea, the Maghreb, Egypt,
Syria and the Mediterranean. The last fourteen
maps represented the central and eastern parts of
the Muslim world. The aim was to show exclu¬
sively the Muslim world as understood by al-
Istakhri and, especially, Ibn Haukal: "I have con¬
sidered in detail the lands of Islam, province by
province, region by region, district by district..."
All this cartographic activity focused mainly
on the eastern part of the Muslim world, but the
western part was not forgotten. The final
flowering of Arab cartography, represented by
the work of al-Idrisi (twelfth century), occurred
in the Muslim west.
After studying in Cordoba, al-Idrisi settled in
Sicily, where the Norman king Roger II commis¬
sioned him to prepare a giant planisphere and to
write a detailed commentary on it. The-
planisphere showed the entire globe including,
in the geographer's own words, "the regions
together with their countries and cities, rivers,
lands and seas and roads, with an indication of
distances and all that was to be seen there". It
has been lost, but al-Idrisi's commentary has
come down to us in a work entitled The Pleasure
Excursion of One Who is Eager to Traverse the
Regions ofthe World {Kitab nuzhat al-mushtaqfi
ikhtiraq al afaq), better known by the name of
The Book of Roger {Kitab Rudjar).
This work helped Western geographers to
widen their field of knowledge, and also helped
the Portuguese explorers to find their way around
unknown regions in the fifteenth century. For
Al-lstakhrl's world map
(12th century). According to a
convention of Islamic
cartography, the south Is at
top of map.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
al-Idrisi, the Earth was "as round as a ball; water
adhered to it naturally and did not fall off; and
land and water were suspended in the cosmos like
the yolk of an egg in its shell". Al-Idrisi appended
an atlas of the world to his commentary, with
some maps in colour.
The work of al-Idrisi, which is the crowning
glory of Arab cartography, also marks the begin¬
ning of its decline. The concepts of latitude and
longitude are missing. The Ptolemaic "climates"
are shown, but in bands of equal breadth, with
no regard for astronomical data. Details are not
as clearly identifiable as on al-Khwarizimi's maps.
There are also certain errors of calculation in the
distances and contour lines. But we must be indul¬
gent towards the cartographer: King Roger's
death and the ensuing unrest prevented him from
making the necessary corrections to his atlas. Al-
Idrisi stands at the meeting-point of two worlds,
the Christian and the Muslim. Small wonder then
that he was known as the "Arab Strabo". His
atlas, which is regarded as the major work of
Arab cartography, is also the one that enjoyed
the greatest success in the West throughout the
Middle Ages.
So far, but no further
Despite all these efforts, Arab contributions to
cartography are few to the amazement of all
those who study its history. Why should this be
so? The Arabs were familiar with the whole of
Europe (except for the northernmost part), the
southern part of Asia, North Africa as far as lati¬
tude ten degrees north, and the east coast of
Africa. Their geographic knowledge was not
confined to the Islamic countries. It extended far
beyond that of the Greeks, who were very
roughly acquainted with the regions beyond the
Caspian Sea and were completely ignorant of the
east coast of Asia north of Indochina. The Arabs
for their part were familiar with both the land
route leading all the way to the sources of the
Yang-Tse and the east coast of Asia, as far as
Korea. It is true that their knowledge of Japan
was uncertain. The Japanese archipelago was
already shown on eleventh-century maps, but
there can be no question that the Arabs ever
reached it by sea. Their image of Japan was
perhaps based on the information they had
picked up in Central Africa, a region they knew
well. As for Africa, the Arabs were the first to
describe it in detail and their description was to
serve as a bench mark until the arrival of the
European explorers in the nineteenth century.
These fabulous journeys, which could not
have been undertaken by any of their European
contemporaries, should have been a matchless
source of information for cartographers. But such
was not the case. Arab cartography, which had
managed to produce the wonderfully accurate
Atlas ofIslam, did not prove able to produce its
equivalent, even in the form of loose maps, for
the other parts of the world, highly knowledge¬
able about them though it was. It no longer
benefited from the accumulated stock of
geographical knowledge; instead of breaking new
ground, the most recent maps did no more than
copy earlier ones. It is true that at that time Euro¬
pean cartography did not show much originality
either and was just as much out of touch with
the latest advances in geography.
World map by the Arab
cartographer al-Idrisi
(12th century).
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The rich and little-
known cartographic
heritage of the Aztecs
and Maya of Mexico
The treasures of Montezuma
24
MIGUEL LEÓN-PORTILLA
of Mexico, is currently serving
as his country's ambassador
and permanent delegate to
UNESCO. Professor emeritus at
the Autonomous National
University of Mexico, he is the
author of a number of books,
articles and papers on pre-
Columbian cultures, which
have been translated into
several languages.
¿AMONG the gifts that Hernán Cortés, the
Spanish conqueror of Mexico, sent to the
emperor Charles V in 1522 were two maps of the
lands he was then engaged in conquering in the
name of Spain. The maps had been painted by
Indians on cotton fabric.
These maps, so different from those to which
Europeans were accustomed, were much admired
at the court of Valladolid. One of the first people
to see them, the Italian humanist Piero Mártir de
Anglería, noted in his "Decades of the New
World", "We have examined one of the maps of
these lands, thirty feet long and almost as many
wide, on which all the territory is traced in great
detail on a piece of white cotton, with the
friendly and hostile peoples of Montezuma. Also
shown are the great mountains which surround
the plain, and the southern coastline.... We have
also seen another, smaller map, which is no less
interesting and shows the same city of Tenustitán
(Mexico City-Tenochtitlán), with its temples, its
bridges and its lakes, all hand-painted by
natives...."
Cortés describes in his detailed letters to
Charles V how, two years before, he had received
another map from Montezuma, the last Aztec
emperor of Mexico: "I asked the said Montezuma
if there was anywhere on the coast an estuary or
a creek through which vessels could come and
go, and he told me that he did not know but that
he would provide me with a painting of the coast
with its rivers and bays.... The next day, a
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
^p^fsÄ
;--)
j-	
K
T^V-
©!
representation of the whole coast was brought
to me on a piece of material, showing the estuary
of a river which seemed much wider than the
others."
The speed with which Montezuma produced
this map for Cortés shows that the Aztecs kept
original manuscripts in accessible places in which
they could quickly be copied. Perhaps the storage
place in this case was the "house of books" {amox-
colli in Aztec) which contained what Bernai Díaz
del Castillo described in his Historia verdadera de
la conquista de la Nueva España ("True History
of the Conquest of New Spain", 1568) as "the
many collections of paper folded like Castilian
linen".
Equally striking is the copyist's scrupulous
attention to detail, which was remarked on by
Bernai Díaz del Castillo who wrote of this map
that "All the estuaries and creeks of the northern
coast could be seen painted and indicated natur¬
ally, from the río Panuco to Tabasco, a distance
of 140 leagues" (some 600 km).
What has become of the painted manuscripts
and maps which the Indians preserved in their
archives? Only fifteen or so survived the con¬
quest. Two of them, the Fejérváry-Mayer and Tro-
Cortesianus codices, seem to be symbolic
representations of the world as it was envisioned
by the peoples of pre-Columbian Mexico.
At the centre of these maps which show in
symbolic form the cemanáhuac (the land mass sur¬
rounded by water), the gods preside over the
cosmic division of the world into regions directed
towards the four cardinal points of the compass.
Each region has its own specific attributes,
colours, flora and fauna. Glyphs designating the
north, east, west and south show that the Maya,
the Aztecs and other Mexican indigenous peoples
used signs to indicate the cardinal points.
Manuscripts of great historical and genealog¬
ical interest produced by the Mixtee people of
Oaxaca have also survived. Two of them, the Nut-
tall and Vindobonensis codices, contain many
symbolic depictions of places where important
events took place, while towns, villages, moun¬
tains, rivers, lakes, roads and coastlines are named
and their location shown by patches of colour.
An aerial view
of the valley of Mexico
The colonized Indians of Mexico continued to
produce documents which were to some extent
cartographical in the sixteenth and seventeenth
centuries. Some were made at the instigation of
the Spanish authorities and of missionaries.
Others were drawn to define the boundaries of
estates.
Some maps showed entire regions, complete
1 2
5
3 4
5 6
7 8
Detail of the Codex
Vindobonensis, a historic
manuscript of the Mixtee
people (1200-1500). Above,
symbols designating towns
(1), small settlements (2, 3,
4), and the cardinal points (5,
6, 7 and 8).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Fragment of a painting on
vegetable fibre shows part of
the city of Mexico-
Tenochtitlán. The manuscript
Is probably pre-Hispanic, with
post-conquest additions.
with towns, forests, roads and rivers. Others, such
as that which the lords of Xicalango provided for
Cortés before he set out on his expedition to
Honduras, as he describes in his "Letters", were
route-maps. Yet others were cadastral maps
which were also valid as title deeds for pieces of
land. When these maps are compared with their
pre-Columbian models, a definite European
influence can often be seen.
One particularly interesting document is the
Xólotl codex, an early copy of a pre-Columbian
manuscript. Named for an indigenous chief men¬
tioned in it, this document preserved in the Bib¬
liothèque Nationale in Paris consists of eight full
pages and two fragments, each of which consti¬
tutes a kind of aerial view, as if taken from a satel¬
lite, of the valley of Mexico at various moments
in its history.
Equally interesting is the Teozacualco Map,
which represents a part of the Mixtee country of
Oaxaca and was sent as part of a report to Philip
II of Spain. It includes genealogies which are
depicted in the form of figures associated with
their respective villages or fiefs. It is accompanied
by a Spanish text which is the key to the hiero¬
glyphics denoting the names of members of the
different lineages. The Teozacualco Map is thus the
Rosetta Stone of the pre-Hispanic manuscripts
from this region.
The notion of scale seems absent from the
maps mentioned so far. In them exaggeration is
used to show the importance of features such as
rugged terrain or settlements.
However, some chroniclers claim to have
seen maps or plans in which scale was used to
show the limits of seigneurial jurisdiction or
estate boundaries, with signs indicating the
perimeter of each plot. All settlements of a cer¬
tain size had archives in which these plans were
deposited for consultation or modification as the
need arose.
In the National Anthropological Museum of
Mexico there is a fragment of a large map (2.38
m x 1.68 m) on locally produced paper. It is a
scale representation of Mexico city before the
arrival of the Spaniards, with its system of canals,
street layout and property boundaries. Although
the notes scribbled in the margin date from after
the conquest, the style and appearance of the
document show that it is of indigenous origin.
In the archives, libraries and museums of
Mexico and elsewhere an abundance of still
unstudied documents testify to the cartographical
activity of the Amerindians of Mexico. Even if
most of them date from the sixteenth century,
and thus from the colonial period, they are
largely inspired by pre-Columbian concepts and
representational techniques.
Study of these documents would shed more
light on an ancient cartographic tradition which
was independent of that of Europe. It would be
an opportunity to analyse the form of cultural
intermingling between Hispanic and Indian tra¬
ditions which took place in cartography as a
specific example of the encounter between two
worlds.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Zheng He's sailing chart
by Mei-Ling Hsu
A nautical guide
which retraces the
last epic voyage
of a Chinese
Admiral in the
fifteenth century
Above right, detail of the
chart portraying Chinese
Admiral Zheng He's last
voyage (1431-1433) shows
the coast of India (above left),
Africa (below) and Sri Lanka
(right). It Is taken from Wu
Bel Zhl ("Treatise on
Armament Technology",
1628).
MEI-LING HSU
is professor of geography at
the University of Minnesota,
Minneapolis (USA). Of Chinese
origin, she is a specialist in the
geography of China, computer-
assisted cartography,
cartographic design and
communication, and the
history of cartography. She
has published a number of
studies and articles in
specialized journals.
X HE earliest surviving Chinese sea map is the
celebrated sailing chart of Admiral Zheng He,
which was made in the mid-fifteenth century. A
script map measuring 20.5 cm by 560 cm, it por¬
trays the voyage between the Chinese city of
Nanking and Jazireh ye Hormuz, in the Strait
of Hormuz, and ports on the east African coasts.
At the request of emperor Yongle, Zheng He
(1371-1435), undertook seven expeditions between
1405 and 1433 and travelled as far as the Strait of
Hormuz and the coasts of east Africa. The expe¬
ditions were on a grand scale. The first comprised
a fleet of 317 ships, including 62 large "treasure
ships", the largest of which was about 100 m long
and 50 m broad, and displaced 3,100 tons.
The sailing chart mainly portrays Zheng He's
last voyage in 1431-1433, but it also includes infor¬
mation accumulated on his earlier voyages and
from voyages by other sailors in and prior to the
fifteenth century. Originally a strip map that
could be rolled up, it was later divided to fit into
forty pages to be printed in a book, Wu Bei Zhi
("Treatise on Armament Technology", published
in 1628).
From right to left, the chart portrays the
12,000-km voyage between China and ports along
the Arabian and African coasts. It reaches the
western extremities at Khorramshahr and Jiddah
in Asia and Kilwa Kisiwani Island in Africa. It
is most detailed along the coasts of China and
southeast Asia.
Using diagrammatic and side-view symbols,
the chart shows, besides sea routes, several other
types of features, including shore lines, bays, estu¬
aries, capes and islands; ports and mountains
along the coasts; important landmarks such as
pagodas, temples, official buildings, flagpoles and
bridges; and other information useful to sailors
such as havens, shoals and half-tide rocks. Many
other features and places are not symbolized but
are named at their respective locations on the
chart. Enclosed in rectangles are the names of
many places such as provincial capitals, defence
sites, and foreign countries along the coastline.
In sum, the chart contains over 500 place names
and over 40 names of landmarks. About 300 of
the named places are outside China.
/ f§k Mít*MtraJÖhV.% US ] 'U im
L
n
^11 /*k*\L Jg$5Ê^\ Ils
The most valuable contents of the chart are
the sea routes, which are shown by dotted lines.
Sailing instructions are also given. From the
mouth of the Yangzi river to Sri Lanka where
ships sailed mostly near the intricate coastlines
and in shallow waters around islands and reefs,
detailed sailing instructions are noted along the
sea routes. These instructions are given in a con¬
cise form: "from A, steer X degrees, after Y
time/distance, the ship reaches B." Sometimes
depth soundings are also provided.
The steering instructions are mostly accurate,
and expressed in terms of the Chinese zhen lu
(compass direction) system. They are the
products of a wealth of knowledge of navigation
and the use of the magnetic compass. The
compass rose consists of 24 divisions of 15-degree
increments, and a supplement of 24 subdivisions.
Thus one can read 48 directions with 7.5-degree
increments.
The final section of the chart covers a large
area, which extends from the tip of India to the
Arabian and African coasts, where ships sailed on
the open seas. Instead of information on land fea- >
tures and on compass directions between short
distances, fifty notes on stellar altitudes are given
along the sea routes from which the latitude loca¬
tion and orientation of the ship can be calculated.
Like other pre-modern charts, Zheng He's
chart is less detailed in depicting areas far away
from China but is remarkable for the accuracy
with which it depicts the coasts of China and
nearby regions of Asia. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Portuguese navigators made great maritime discoveries, brought
innovations to map-making, and propagated a new geographical
vision of the globe
28
ALFREDO PINHEIRO MARQUES,
of Portugal, is professor of
history at the University of
Coimbra. A specialist in the
cartography of the great
voyages of discovery from the
14th to the 16th centuries, his
most recent publications
include Or/gem e
desenvolvimento da cartografía
portugesa na época dos
descobrimentos (Lisbon, 1988),
and, in English, The Dating of
the Oldest Portuguese Charts
(1989). He is currently
preparing an International
Bibliography on the Discoveries
and Overseas Encounters.
jL/XTRAORDINARY developments in geography
took place in Ancient Greece and the Hellenistic
world. The work of Claudius Ptolemy, the Greek
mathematician and geographer who lived in Alex¬
andria, Egypt, in the second century AD, was a
major landmark in this intellectual enterprise. He
described the projection methods used in cartog¬
raphy and drew the first maps of the world as
it was then known to scholars of the eastern
Mediterranean. This corpus of knowledge disap¬
peared in the West with the barbarian invasions
and was only rediscovered in the late Middle
Ages.
A new type of map, the portolan chart,
appeared in the thirteenth and fourteenth centu¬
ries. Essentially destined for use at sea, its distinc¬
tive feature was a system of rhumb lines, lines
that radiate from a centre in the direction of wind
or compass points. Pilots used these lines to chart
courses which could be followed by compass
navigation and by estimating distances.
The great Mediterranean cartographers at
that time were the Italians (above all the Genoans
and the Venetians), the Catalans and the
Majorcans. The Catalan Atlas, one of the most
famous of its time, is attributed to the school of
Abraham Crescas, a cartographer of Majorcan
origin.
The portolan marked a new departure from
Ptolemaic cartography, which was exclusively ter¬
restrial, accepted the sphericity of the Earth, and
even represented the world by a system of projec¬
tion of latitudes and longitudes, but only showed
Europe, the Mediterranean, the Near East and
North Africa. The Indian Ocean was a closed sea
and the configuration of Asia was purely
speculative.
Throughout the fifteenth century, long
before the voyages of Christopher Columbus, it
was the Portuguese who opened up the era of
great transoceanic voyages by undertaking a
D
-\ h r * *CH\\>
*
systematic reconnaissance of the west coast of
Africa and the Atlantic islands. Courage was at a
premium in these early voyages, which were not
associated with any decisive technical innovation.
The Portuguese had learned from the Majorcans
the techniques of nautical cartography, and their
maps resembled the Mediterranean portolans.
Navigation by the stars began to be practised
by the Portuguese in the second half of the
fifteenth century, during thé reign of John II.
This new method made it possible to establish
a ship's position in relation to the height of stars
on the horizon and thus to sail far out to sea.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
% q«*' 'Jfm
i
i bilDilh..!/
The Catalan Atlas of 1375 Is
attributed to the school of the
Majorcan scholar Abraham
Crescas. Drawn on leaves of
parchment glued to wooden
boards, It Is the oldest
surviving European map to
show the world extending as
far eastwards as China.
Cartographically speaking, it led to the introduc¬
tion into the portolan of a graduated meridian
which gave the latitude. This was a major con¬
tribution by the Portuguese to the techniques of
navigation and cartography.
The scale of latitudes found on Ptolemaic
maps was unusable at sea. In the Mediterranean
sailors did not stray far from the shoreline. The
Portuguese navigators found new solutions to the
new problems posed by ocean navigation. They
took aboard and adapted to nautical use, astro¬
nomical instruments, notably the astrolabe,
which were already known to the Arabs.
By opening up the way to the great maritime
discoveries at the beginning of the fifteenth cen¬
tury, the Portuguese inventors of astronomical
navigation propagated a new geographical vision
of the globe which was taken up by the other
European cartographic schools.
Many Portuguese cartographers worked in
other lands and spies were common in Lisbon.
The findings of Bartolomeu Dias, the Portuguese
navigator who had become the first man to sail
around Africa, can be seen in a map drawn in
Italy in 1489only a year after Dias' exploit-
by the German cartographer Henricus Martellus.
Later, an Italian agent named Camino took into
his pay a Portuguese royal cartographer, who
passed on to him an anonymous map which was
sent to Italy. Known as the "Camino Map", it
is still preserved at Modena.
The Cantino Map is possibly the most impor¬
tant map in the history of cartography. The first
known planisphere, it gives an almost complete
image of the world. It presents in recognizable
form the New World, Africa, India and a rough
Ptolemy's world map from
the Latin edition of his
Geographla published In Ulm,
1482.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Martin Waldseemüller's world
map of 1507. This was the
first map on which the New
World was named "America",
in honour of the Italian
navigator Amerigo Vespucci,
who Is shown (top right) with
Ptolemy.
outline of the Far East. The only map which can
be compared to it is the Spanish map of
Christopher Columbus's pilot, Juan de La Cosa,
which depicts the islands and coasts of central
Americaalthough Africa is very roughly drawn
and Asia is quite imaginary.
The geographical discoveries of the Por¬
tuguese and the Spaniards made a decisive con¬
tribution to the renewal of Ptolemaic cartography,
which was itself revolutionary in comparison with
the maps produced in medieval monasteries. But
information derived from the voyages of dis¬
covery had to be incorporated into Ptolemaic car¬
tography and this took time. The humanists who
were reviving Ptolemaic geography through the
spread of printing and the navigators who were
actually making the discoveries were separated by
different traditions of thoughtthe former scho¬
larly, the latter empiricalwhich did not facili¬
tate communication.
After 1490, there was a long gap before
the publication of new editions of Ptolemy's
Geographia. The reasons are not hard to find. In
1488, Dias sailed round the southern Cape of
Africa, in 1492 Columbus sailed to America, and
in 1498 Vasco da Gama arrived in India.
Ptolemy's work was not republished until 1507,
with new "modern" maps which take account
of the Portuguese and Spanish voyages.
In the early sixteenth century, the Spaniards
occupied central America, but the Portuguese
were present in many parts of the world: in India
(1498), Newfoundland and South America (1500),
in Persia, at Hormuz (1507), in Indonesia and
China (1513), and in Japan (around 1542). Most
of the maps printed in Europe in the sixteenth
century were based on surveys made by Por¬
tuguese navigators, the age's leading suppliers of
geographical information.
This knowledge was propagated by the
humanists, aided by the development of printing,
and paradoxically it was in Italy and northern
Europe that the new cartography inspired by the
Portuguese emerged. The map showing the New
World which appeared in 1507 in the expanded
edition of Ptolemy's Geographia was by Johan
Ruysch. Another edition of the same work
produced at Strasbourg in 1513 with maps by
Martin Waldseemüller circulated widely. In 1507
Waldseemüller published a map on which the
word "America" appeared for the first time, and
in 1516 an important planisphere, Carta Marina
Navigatoria Portugallensium. . ,
Dominated in the fourteenth and fifteenth "
centuries by the Italians and the Catalans, cartog¬
raphy thus had its golden age at the Renaissance
under the impulsion of the Portuguese. Then
came the turn of the Dutch, who systematized
the use of printing and introduced such innova¬
tions as Mercator's projection, the basis of
modern cartography.
But the Dutch cartographers developed their
work throughout the sixteenth century through
contact with the Portuguese. The projection
devised by Gerard Mercator is an application of
the theoretical principles set forth much earlier
by the Portuguese mathematician and astronomer
Pedro Nunes.
30
-yylir. ->v>i
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
When mapping became a science
by Norman J, Thrower
Modern scientific
cartography was
born in eighteenth-
century Europe
D,
Above, frontispiece of the 4th
edition (Amsterdam, 1619) of
the Atlas of Gerard Mercator
(Gerard de Cremer). Mercator
Is shown at left and the
geographer Jodocus Hondius
at right.
'URING the eighteenth century, France
became the leader in topographic or general map¬
ping. The foundations of this achievement were
laid in the preceding century when the
astronomer Giovanni Domenico Cassini
(1625-1712) came from Bologna to the newly-
founded Paris Observatory. Through Cassini and
his successors France became the first country to
produce a detailed and accurate map of its national
territory in multiple sheets, based on triangula¬
tion, and using uniform symbols for roads, set¬
tlements, forests, rivers, and other features. A first
step was the accurate measurement of the length
of a degreeof latitude near Paris where mapping
was begun.
After the death of his father, the survey of
France was continued by Jacques Cassini
(1677-1756) under whose direction the triangu¬
lation network was greatly extended. In this work
the second Cassini was assisted by his son, César
François (1714-1784) who carried the
topographical mapping of France to virtual com¬
pletion following his father's death. A few sheets
not finished by the third Cassini before his death
were completed by his son Jacques-Dominique,
comte de Cassini (1748-1845). Thus it took the
dedicated work of four generations of the Cas¬
sini family over more than a century to produce
the 182 map sheets on the large scale of 1:86,400
which constituted the first true, topographic map
of a country.
A topographic survey of Britain (Ordnance
Survey) was begun in 1783 under the direction
of General William Roy (1726-1790). The French
and British triangulation networks, which are
fundamental to this type of mapping, were con¬
nected across the Channel in 1789. The value of
topographic mapping was quickly appreciated by
many rulers and administrators who introduced
the new survey in their realms. For example,
topographical mapping on the European model
was shortly initiated in Bengal, which led to the
Great Trigonometrical Survey of India.
Geodesy
and thematic maps
If more accurate maps of world or continental
areas were to be made, knowledge of the shape
of the Earth was necessary. As a result of the
French topographic survey doubts had been
raised about this. Isaac Newton (1642-1727) had 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Measuring longitude. Detall of
an Illuminated manuscript of
the French mariner Jacques
de Vaulx's treatise on
hydrography (1583). The
Illustration shows the Sun,
Moon, and stars useful to
navigators.
32
postulated from the behaviour of the pendulum
at different latitudes that the Earth was a spheroid
flattened at the poles. Measurements taken on the
equator and in the high northern latitudes by
French scientists during the 1740s affirmed the
general correctness of Newton's hypothesis.
In his great work the Principia, Newton exa¬
mined many fundamental problems of physical
science and numerous mappable phenomena.
This work was promoted by Newton's younger
contemporary, Edmond Halley (1656-1742), who
made signal contributions to cartography,
including thematic or special-purpose maps.
During a year spent on St. Helena, Halley
prepared, and soon published, a southern
hemisphere star chart, and a terrestrial map which
has been called "the first meteorological [really
climatological] chart"of the trade and monsoon
winds. After two years at sea in the Atlantic on
a scientific voyage Halley also published in 1701
the first printed, isogonic map, i.e. a chart of mag¬
netic variation. Shortly after this he published a
map of the variable heights of tides in the English
Channel. Later, in 1715, Halley made a map of
the shadow of the eclipse over England in that
year, before the event it depicted. Halley became
Astronomer Royal at Greenwich Observatory in
1720, in which capacity he conducted investiga¬
tions into the problem of finding longitude at sea,
on the nature of the core of the Earth and other
geophysical phenomena.
Nautical charts,
longitude and the chronometer
As in the case of topographic mapping, the
French were the early leaders in scientific coastal
charting. The accurate mapping of the shorelines
of France led to the establishment of an official
hydrographie office in the country in 1720. In
Britain, much coastal surveying was at first
unofficial or quasi-official, with the East India
Company playing a prominent role in producing
nautical charts of overseas areas before the
founding of the British Hydrographie Office in
1795. During the eighteenth century, the maritime
nations of the world charted many coastal areas
of special interest to them.
Determination of latitude both on land and
at sea could be accomplished with considerable
accuracy from a fairly early date. This was made
possible by the use of a variety of instruments
such as quadrants and sextants which were
improved after telescopic sights were fitted to
them. Longitude measurement on land was
feasible by astronomical means provided the
observer had appropriate tables and referred to
a specific prime meridian. There is a natural
Chart of magnetic variation
was drawn by the English
astronomer Edmond Halley In
1700 and corrected In 1756
by William Mountalne and
James Dodson.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
starting-point for latitude: 0° latitude equals the
equatorequidistant from the poles. By contrast,
the origin of a system of longitude is quite
arbitrary.
Through the centuries a number of prime
meridians have been used and in the eighteenth
century a line running through the Observatory
in Paris or Greenwich Observatory was gener¬
ally employed. The problem of finding the lon¬
gitude of a place is basically simple since 15° of
longitude equals one hour of time. Therefore, one
needs only to know the time at a chosen prime
meridian and the local time, wherever the
observer might be. But at sea the unstable deck
of a ship made impossible the necessary observa¬
tion, or the use of a pendulum clock. The
problem was solved only after the invention of
the marine chronometer by John Harrison
(1693-1776), an English artisan, in the second half
of the eighteenth century.
Captain James Cook (1728-1779), a trained
marine surveyor who charted much of the
world's unexplored coastline, took two chronom¬
eters on his second Pacific voyage (1772-1775).
One of these was set for Greenwich time and one
adjusted to local time with which he was able to
determine longitude at sea with great accuracy.
Cook's and other voyages also disproved the age-
old idea of balancing continents, with equal land
masses in the northern and southern hemispheres.
They revealed that the southern hemisphere is
predominantly water-covered, and that most of
the land is in the northern hemisphere.
Except in relatively shallow waters, the con¬
figuration of the ocean floor remained unknown.
However, Nicholas Cruquius (1678-1758) pub¬
lished an isobathic (depth) chart of a distributary
of the Rhine in 1729 and Philippe Buache
(1700-1773) one of the Channel in 1732.
Other developments in the eighteenth cen¬
tury included the invention of several ingenious
map projections. The Swiss/German mathema¬
tician Johann H. Lambert (1728-1777) con¬
tributed more than any other individual in this
\m;ii
Cadastral map showing land
use in the village of Banhars,
Aveyron (France, 1807).
Detail of an Isobathic chart of
the river Meuse by Nicholas
Cruquius (1729).
fieldthe conic equal area, conic conformai,
cylindrical equal area, azimuthal equal area, and
the transverse Mercator projections all being
attributed to him. A tradition of globe making
established by the Venetian, Vincenzo Coronelli
(1650-1718), continued during the eighteenth cen¬
tury with celestial and terrestrial globes of
different sizes and for different purposes being
produced in a number of centres.
The nineteenth century:
expansion, consolidation and diversity
The story of mapping in the nineteenth century
begins when Alexander von Humboldt
(1769-1859) landed in South America. Early in the
year 1800 Humboldt made a reconnaissance map,
based on his own explorations, of the drainage
between the Orinoco and Amazon river basins.
He then travelled in the Andes before arriving
in New Spain (Mexico) in 1803. During a year
spent in the area he compiled a map of that large
colony which served as a model for similar maps
of other continental interiorsAfrica, Asia,
North and South America and Australiaas
explorers from many countries provided the
necessary data. It would be many years before
these surveys were superseded.
Meanwhile, the coastlines of the continents
and islands continued to be charted, as, for
example, in Matthew Flinders' (1774-1814) map¬
ping of the Australian coasts. Occasionally a great
breakthrough was made, as with the work of the
American, Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873).
Following his appointment in 1842 as Superin¬
tendent of the Depot of Charts (later divided
between the United States National Observatory
and the Hydrographie Office) in Washington,
Maury devised maps showing the quickest pas¬
sages for sailing ships between specific ports based 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
on winds, currents, etc. These routes were not
normally great circles (the shortest distance
between two points on the globe). Many lives
were saved by Maury's work before steamships
superseded sailing vessels in the second half of the
nineteenth century.
Climatic maps became more common as offi¬
cial weather stations were established. A wind
scale which bears his name was devised by Francis
Beaufort (1774-1857), head of the British Hydro-
graphic Office, and is still in use. For a short time,
Washington, D.C. was used as a prime meridian
on maps of the United States. But as the result
of an international conference held in
Washington in 1884, the problem of a universally
recognized prime meridian (0° longitude) was
resolved when Greenwich (UK), was selected. A
great advantage of this is that the antipodal inter¬
national date line (180° longitude) runs essentially
through oceanic areas.
Cadastral and geological mapping
An extremely ancient genre in cartography is the
cadastral map, which is concerned with land
ownership and taxation. Over most of the world
unsystematic land subdivision by metes and
bounds has been used. In a few areas, notably in
the western two-thirds of the United States,
cardinally-oriented, systematic, rectilinear surveys
were required. This resulted in a great flurry of
surveying and mapping activity as settlers
clamoured for land in the nineteenth century.
Similar rectilinear surveys were undertaken in
western Canada and some other more recently
settled, primarily agricultural areas of the world.
Economic exploitation of the land in the
nineteenth century also led to the development
of geological mapping. The father of geological
mapping is William Smith (1769-1839), who pub¬
lished his map "The Strata of England" in 1815
after nearly a quarter of a century of research.
Soon European scientists not only mapped their
own countries geologically, but were employed
in this work in Russia and elsewhere. In the
United States, geological mapping began in the
eastern states but it was in the west, in the second
half of the nineteenth century, that it came into
its own. So important was this activity considered
to be that when the United States established its
primary topographic mapping agency in 1879, it
was designated the United States Geological
Survey (USGS). This is in contrast to earlier
topographical surveys which had a geographical
or military foundation.
Censuses and thematic mapping
The holding of regular censuses as we know them
began in Sweden in 1749, in the United States in
1790, and in Britain in 1801. Other countries soon
followed so that in the nineteenth century a great
mass of statistical data became available for map-
34 ping. This included not only population but
education, crime, disease and other phenomena.
Henry Drury Harness, a pioneer in this field
employed by the Irish Railway Commission,
published in 1837 a series of highly original
thematic maps in which several quantitative tech¬
niques now employed in small-scale mapping
were used to show population density and traffic
flow. In 1855, Dr. John Snow (1813-1858) used
uniform symbols to show deaths from cholera
in London and thus identified a lethal water
pump in that city.
Atlases, globes and projections
Much of the geographical knowledge of the
period was disseminated and popularized through
atlases, which were produced in increasing
numbers in the nineteenth century. The inven¬
tion of lithography, which gradually replaced the
earlier copperplate and even earlier wood
engraving, facilitated the production of atlases.
Approximately 4,000 county cadastral atlases
were produced in the United States in the
nineteenth century. Some state and provincial
atlases were published and the first true national
atlasthat of Finland in 1899. Globes of many
sizes continued to be produced, including giant
spheres which were a feature of the expositions
that characterized the nineteenth century.
Among the new projections which were devised
in this period were the Albers conic, Molleweide
(homolographic) named for their inventors, and
the Polyconic invented by Ferdinand Hassler.
These projections remain popular today.
II
M
.»
Terrestrial and celestial globe
made In 1786 for Louis XVI of
France by Edme Mantelle.
NORMAN J.W. THROWER,
of the United States, is
professor of geography at the
University of California, Los
Angeles, and has been
appointed director of the
University's 1992 Columbus
Quincentenary Programs.
Trained in geography and the
history of science, he is the
author of many scholarly
articles and books. He has
recently edited a series of
essays, On the Shoulders of
Giants: Newton and Halley,
1686-1986 (1990), and is co¬
author of A Buccaneers Sea
Atlas: The 1 680 Waggoner of
Basil Ringrose, which will be
published later this year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
MNÍ
The perspective from space
by Jean-Philippe Grelot
.?#<
Advances in computer
science and the mass
of data transmitted
from remote-sensing
satellites are taking
cartography into a
new era
Aerial photography is used
systematically In map
production. Partly overlapping
photos are assembled in a
mosaic (above).
VMRTOGRAPHY is a very ancient art. As long
ago as the time of the Pharaohs, surveyors were
drawing up plans of plots of cultivated land in
order to re-establish property boundaries or
replace cornerstones buried under the silt brought
down by the floodwaters of the Nile.
The great voyages of discovery of the fifteenth
century led to the transformation of world maps.
Returning from their voyages, the great navi¬
gators of those days recounted their experiences,
which cartographers working quietly in their
homes incorporated into more accurate maps.
The emergence of modern cartography,
however, dates from the eighteenth century,
when scientific expeditions such as the French
expeditions to Lapland and Peru finally con¬
firmed Newton's hypothesis that the world was
shaped like a sphere slightly flattened at the poles.
It was through these expeditions that cartog¬
raphy acquired the mathematical basis it needed
to become the instrument for the accurate,
graphic, scale representation of our knowledge
of the Earth that it is today.
The starting-point of all cartography is the
science of geodesythe determination of the size
and shape of the Earth and the exact position of
a series of reference points on its surface. By
means of successive readings taken in turn from
each of these points, the co-ordinates of these
points on the surface of the Earth are determined
and then transposed to a flat surface.
Today, methods and instruments have com¬
pletely changed. Using a small calculator linked
to an aerial, geodesists "listen" to the specialized
satellites of the Global Positioning System, which
give them their precise position immediately.
During the previous three centuries, however,
they would have had to take readings with the¬
odolites of the various topographical features
around them. On the basis of these reference
points, topographers would have made a detailed
examination of the terrain so as to locate the
roads, houses, forests, rivers, etc., that they had
observed.
From about 1930, aerial photography, a tech¬
nique which had been perfected during World
War I, radically modified this painstaking work
and signalled the end of direct accumulation of
data by observation on the ground. Aeroplanes are
flown in a series of straight lines and photographs 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
are taken at fairly close intervals. Each section
of terrain flown over is photographed twice, from
different angles. In this way the aerial photo¬
graphs provide the binocular effect of human
vision, which makes possible the appreciation of
distance and relief.
The cartographer makes use of this
stereoscopic effect which, used in conjunction
with extremely precise measurement techniques,
gave rise to the science of photogrammetry (the
measurement of photographs applied to sur¬
veying and mapping, as well as for engineering
and other purposes). Through the twin eyepieces
of their photogrammetrical reconstitution equip¬
ment, each of which is focused on one of the two
successive aerial photographs, the stereo-operators
get a true picture of the terrain in relief, with its
heights, its valleys, houses and trees. All that then
has to be done is to trace the relief with a cursor,
whilst operating certain controls, for the co¬
ordinates of the various features to be recorded.
However, a certain amount of fieldwork
remains necessary to check the correct identifi¬
cation of detail, to fill in details not visible in areas
in shadow, or to add information such as place-
names or administrative boundaries that aerial
photographs cannot supply.
The documentation thus produced is cor¬
rected by the map editor and then printed. The
process calls for great care and precision and is
quite lengthy. About two years should be allowed
from the taking of the aerial photographs to the
publication of the map.
The computer invasion
Computers came upon the cartographical scene
in the late 1950s. They were first used in geodetic
calculations. Some ten years later experiments
were begun with computer-assisted design,
although this did not go beyond the laboratory
stage. Then, in the 1970s, the data on maps were
recorded in numerical form, which greatly eased
their use and updating.
Geodetic surveying afloat.
Below, members of a
scientific expedition climb
Mount Pelvoux, France's
highest geodetic point (1910).
In the 1980s computers invaded every sphere
of cartography, including photogrammetry. Like
the micro-computer, equipment for computer-
assisted design became smaller and smaller and
at the same time more and more powerful. Par¬
ticularly spectacular progress was made in the
development of conceptual models and data
banks and in numerical data-handling capacity.
Computerized cartography has developed into a
full-scale "Geographic Information System" with
its own data banks and its own equipment and
application programs.
With their powerful analytical capacity, com¬
puters have considerably reduced the time
required to produce a map; but the demand is still
for faster results. To meet it, cartography is
turning towards a new toolremote sensing by
means of Earth observation satellites.
Remote sensing satellites
What are the broad principles of this new and
revolutionary technique? Remote sensing satel¬
lites capture by means of scanning sensors the
varying electromagnetic radiations emitted by the
points the satellites observe on the Earth's surface.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Top, the site of the 1992
Winter Olympics at Albertville
(France) as viewed from the
SPOT satellite. Altlmetrlc data
are used to make a numeric
model of the site In which the
relief Is depicted In grid form
(middle photo). The model Is
then combined with the SPOT
Image to obtain a perspective
view (bottom).
The nature of the electromagnetic radiation
emitted by a given point on the Earth's surface
depends upon the characteristics of the Earth's
surface at that pointfactors such as temperature,
humidity, the presence or absence of vegetation,
and the nature of rock formations.
The satellite then transmits the data it has
obtained to a ground station, either in photo¬
graphic or numerical form. Analysis of this data
enables the characteristics of the points observed
to be deduced. Thus, like aerial photographs,
satellite images require interpretation by a
specialist, but with the aid of a computer.
Broadly speaking, satellites may be classified
into three groups according to the orbits they
follow:
Low-orbit satellites, like the American space
shuttle and like most military observation satel
lites, circle the Earth at an altitude of between
200 and 300 kilometres. Subject to the braking
drag of the atmosphere, they have an effective life
span which varies from a few days to a few weeks.
The photographs they take are of a scale of the
order of 1:100,000, which means that objects of
a metre or more can be distinguished. The pho¬
tographs are transmitted during the satellite's
return to Earth or when a capsule fitted with a
parachute is ejected.
Satellites in heliosynchronous orbit circle the
Earth at ,an altitude of 800 to 900 kilometres.
Those in the American Landsat (or ERTS) series
(five satellites since 1972) or the French SPOT
series (two satellites, one in 1986 and one in 1990)
have a life span of a few years and record numer¬
ical images each of which covers an area of from
3,500 to 35,000 square kilometres. Their resolu¬
tion varies from about fifty metres for Landsat
to about ten metres for SPOT, which, using
stereoscopic methods, is the first system of Earth
observation to "see" in relief. They pass over the
same point of the Earth at the same time in rela¬
tion to the Sun (hence the term heliosyn¬
chronous) approximately every twenty days. By
orienting the mirrors of its sensors, SPOT can
record details of a given zone every three days,
meteorological conditions permitting (SPOT
satellites cannot pierce cloud cover). The whole
of the Earth's surface is covered in a period of
two to three weeks.
Geostationary satellites, like Meteosat, are placed
in an equatorial orbit at an altitude of 36,000
kilometres. They record numerical images
covering a quarter of the globe with a resolution
of about five kilometres. Since their position in
relation to the Earth is fixed they are within cons¬
tant view of a ground reception station to which
they transmit images every half hour. They are,
however, unable to scan the polar ice caps.
Satellite images make possible the continuous
updating of maps, with a reduction in the margin
of error and in the time span. A satellite like
SPOT makes possible the updating of the car¬
tographical cover of a country in a matter of
months, as compared with ten years or so using
classic methods.
Today evolving computer technology has
combined remote sensing and cartography and
taken advantage of their complementarity. As a
result, now that we can handle both cartographic
data and the images on which they are based,
whether these be numerical or graphic, we talk
nowadays in terms of "integrated" geographical
information systems
Practical applications
The first field of application for geographical
information systems is resource management in
both urban and rural areas. Now that it can pro¬
vide the most accurate information about the con¬
dition of a given area and furnish a visual and
data-based synthesis of it, cartography is in a 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
position to optimize the efficiency and cost-
effectiveness of that area's management.
The supply and waste utility networks of an
urban area (water, electricity, telephone and tel¬
evision cables, waste water conduits, household
waste collection and road networks) are all inter¬
twined within a restricted space. As they become
older they have to be renovated and adapted to
meet new needs. Work of this kind has to be care¬
fully planned to cause the least possible distur¬
bance to users, to reduce the risk of accidents and
to keep costs to a minimum. Cartography also
has a part to play in other sectors, such as public
transport and the siting of medical and educa¬
tional facilities. In fact, all aspects of the life of
the community are involved. Three-quarters of
the data handled by urban authorities are local¬
ized data and thus come within the sphere of
geographical information systems.
In agriculture, the main application of car¬
tography is in the study of land-use and cultiva¬
tion methods, monitoring plant cover, harvest
forecasting and the assessment of the conse¬
quences of such climatic hazards as drought or
floods and of the incidence of such events as epi¬
demics or fires.
Coupled with management is development,
on which the whole aspect of an area depends.
This includes town planning, the construction of
the road infrastructure and agricultural improve¬
ment. Here, project mapping, which is limited
in both space and time according to the nature
and scope of the project envisaged, is used as well
as overall, basic cartography. This is a specific
type of cartography based on a specific range of
data. It is dependent upon precision, constant up¬
dating and a permanent observation system. In
this domain, aerial photography and satellite
imagery play a decisive role because of the speed
with which they can furnish information.
Lastly, understanding and control of the
environmenta more recent concern directly
connected with developmentcall for broad car¬
tographical involvement, for here too thinking
must be in terms of spatial analysis. The factors
that have to be borne in mind are multiple and
complex yet they require simple formulation.
The areas involved are becoming larger and larger
so that the interactions and spread of phenomena
can be taken into account. Satellites that roam
in space unhampered by national boundaries are
the ideal tool for the acquisition of the necessary
global information. This is even more true now
that computer science is beginning to provide the
means (vast storage capacity thanks to the new
optical disks, rapid data handling by means of
parallel processors, transmission by local net¬
works and integrated service networks) for rapid
and efficient handling of the vast mass of data
these satellites transmit.
Cartography still retains its essential didactic
function. A synthetic science that reveals the lines
of force of global phenomena by demonstrating
their spatial relationships, it also pioneers the way
to new horizons of knowledge. And, feeding back
to us as it does the image that we are giving to
our land, it has become a prime witness to our
cultural development.
A satellite Image forms the
basis of this map of Bamako
(Mali).
JEAN-PHILIPPE GRELOT,
French geographer, is sales
director of his country's
National Geographical Institute.
He teaches cartography at
France's School of
Geographical Sciences, and is
vice-president of the
International Cartographic
Association. He has published
many articles on cartography
in French and other journals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
A bit off the map
For years the excellent
maps produced in
the Soviet Union were
not accessible to the
general public
%
Below, a Soviet tourist map
dating from 1963. The scale
Is not Indicated.
Laps and plans that are a secret for the the counter. New maps of regions and cities are
country's population are an absurdity, a torch being produced and published which are more
kept extinguished," wrote the Soviet geologist informative than those published ten or twenty
A.P. Gerasimov seventy years ago. Unfortunately years ago.
this was the case for years in the USSR, where Paradoxically, Soviet cartography has been a
the achievements of Soviet cartography were not victim of its own success in making extremely
generally accessible to the public. To take one accurate and informative maps. In pre-
example among many, people often used a Revolutionary times, detailed maps only existed
detailed up-to-date Hungarian plan to find their for the European part of the Russian empire. Sur-
way around Moscow, rather than the official veying the hitherto unstudied regions in the years
Soviet tourist guide which showed only the main after the Revolution was a great scientific feat,
thoroughfares. Work went on over a vast area and had to
Today, however, the notion that Soviet maps be done in harsh climatic conditions in such
are primitive and distorted is becoming a thing regions as Siberia, the deserts of Central Asia and
of the past. One result of current changes in the the mountains of the Caucasus. Geodetic work
USSR is that some of the detailed maps which had to cover 22.4 million square kilometres to
were once unavailable can now be bought over provide a single system of co-ordinates and
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
ALEKSANDR SERGEEVICH
SUDAKOV,
of the USSR, is the editor-in-
chief of the Central
Department of Geodesy and
Cartography, which is
responsible to the USSR
Council of Ministers. He is a
member of the editorial boards
of a number of major
cartographic publications and
the Soviet Union's permanent
representative on the Scientific
Committee on Antarctic
Research (SCAR) working
group on geodesy and
geological information.
Below left, a detailed plan of
central Moscow, available
since 1989. Previous plans
(right) were vague and
sometimes Inaccurate.
heights for the entire area of the Soviet Union.
Heights and co-ordinates throughout the country
had to be determined with great accuracy in rela¬
tion to the Baltic Sea and the reference point at
Pulkovo near Leningrad. This in turn required
astronomic and gravimetric work throughout the
country, the development of triangulation and
levelling grids, and the construction of tens of
thousands of geodetic signs, some of them over
40 metres high.
The late 1930s and the eve of the Second
World War were a time of universal suspicion,
mistrust and spy mania in our country. Measures
were taken to protect information, including
information about topography. Detailed large-
scale maps that had had limited circulation were
made secret. But the objective formulated for
Russian cartography over 150 years ago, "the col¬
lection and distribution in Russia and beyond of
as full and reliable data about our native land as
possible", was never abandoned. In 1947, the
Chief Department of Geodesy and Cartography
was awarded the Gold Medal of the Geographic
Society for having completed the state map of the
USSR to a scale of 1:1,000,000.
This success made it possible to start work
on a new 1:2,500,000 (1 cm = 25 km) map, which
in the 1950s served as the basis of a series of
detailed regional maps. These years also saw the
start of planning for a project unheard-of in any
'
£*rnrt * -.»
" ft
C i
Samojëcnflj
"TIT
Cvelnoj bul'var
-13-2-
Al /vv
»
"»jacStihafev
Kolh-wnaja jj
KolHoinaja'oj "3/a °Jh02-~
«¡Pankral>\4 j"
P"
P..
Su**'. _r>.
,; ;t
*«
le-dn.j P"
Ontovln P"
Him'fvi
" V Bol S»i*IW««l *'
tax p £
Of«*'j k
i^Triib,11;] PWalnUnv
ft' ^
5 a?
«oideslvenskij fySSrefení
= ^Sretenskih g hul\-
Vorot¿ -,... /^«^.fcskil,
p *
isk/j
W
toaeonaai
other country: large-scale (1:25,000, i.e. 1 cm =
250 m) surveys of the entire territory of the Soviet
Union. The effort took some forty years and over
250,000 maps were produced.
In the early 1960s, certain maps began to dis¬
appear from the shops. The small-scale maps that
were produced to replace them inherited old mis¬
takes and distortions and incorporated new ones.
The location of sites in relation to the carto¬
graphic grid was changed. Geographical co¬
ordinates were no longer shown on maps that
were transformed into schematic representations
of low, information value. This practice was
rendered meaningless by the development of
space imagery, but we continued to publish maps
of the Aral Sea coast as it was traditionally seen,
for instance, while maps produced in other coun¬
tries using space technology showed its actual
state.
Although some restrictions have now been
lifted, there are still many problems. The mili¬
tary think that circulation of detailed
topographical maps is premature, especially those
on the 1:100,000 and the 1:25,000 scales. But
tourists are attracted above all to little-known
forests and mountains, the parks near Leningrad,
the towns and countryside of old Russia. People
want to get to know their own country, and to
be able to explore it on foot. For this they need
reliable large-scale maps.
SoMnM>smi
MO)'
-- Turgcncvshuia
-
* Ml." Kiruvskaja '-,
A»,
<N
&f
^
\\
S"**,
C.ítnoi Bui «ar
®
KolhMMu) «
^ Bol S»tjn»Hii| P*'
«
,11t"1"' Bui»
"'a..,
"
Pul',.
X
O
o
O)
**«.
Turginftikifi
-
*£? \
*
3 KutnccMJ Most '
c¿
Vorovskogof
I"*
<
K,\<
PI
Svrrdlom
?n*b pi a. *»	
" L tV-rt tDier/.inskogo
Ç1 f"a ^¿DifrilnsVaja
P¡. Sverdlov/ *j$ 1&fr
pi. Revoljucii
a
r
»r. X
<?
TMoiii
n
=> ® KuMckii Mod
. .
jetijal
brin 5
PI. Krfoljiuii' Q
Pokrovsl
Vorol
(»S«/}.Srffdlcva
'x®m
f.
%
4.pn1
fcPI. Nogina »On.
Art
®,
®
® °
<farUau '
®
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Celestial cartography
Astronomical map-making from the star
catalogues of Antiquity to the electronic
images of today
X ROM very early times, the stars in the firma¬
ment have held a strong fascination for man. In
the movements of the stars the Ancients saw the
operation of supernatural forces which could
influence human destiny. Believing that there
were portents to be read in the stars, our distant
ancestors began to observe and make precise
descriptions of the heavens.
Thus astronomy has a very long history. Ves¬
tiges of astronomical observatories and instru¬
ments dating back to 3000 BC have been found
in Sumer, Babylon, China, Egypt, Mexico, Peru
and the United Kingdom.
The earliest known star catalogues were the
work of Babylonian astronomers and date back
to about 1700 BC, during the reign of the great
Babylonian monarch Hammurabi. Calculations
concerning the movements of the Moon and of
the planets, especially of Venus, were almost cer¬
tainly made for astrological purposes. For the
Egyptians, Sirius, the Dog star, to which they
accorded divine attributes as "Sothis", or the
"Star of Isis", was "the bringer of the new year
and of the floodwaters of the Nile". In fact, the
day of the year on which Sirius was first visible
on the horizon, just before sunrise, usually coin¬
cided more or less with the rising of the Nile
waters, on which subsequent sowing and then
harvesting of crops depended.
It was not long before the Ancients became
aware of the slow progression of the Sun, the
Moon and the five great planets of the solar
system (Venus, Mercury, Mars, Jupiter and
Saturn) along a regular path across the heavens.
This belt around the sky, first observed by the
Babylonians and later by the Greeks, is divided
into twelve segments, or astrological signs, which
correspond to the constellations which occupied
these segments some 2,000 years ago (Taurus the
bull, Cancer the crab, Leo the lion, etc.). The
Zodiacal belt corresponds to what modern
astronomers call the "ecliptic", the apparent
annual path followed by the Sun.
The Greek astronomer Hipparchus (161 to
127 BC) was the first to draw up a star catalogue
worthy of the name. He indicated the position
of about a thousand stars, attributing to each of
them a magnitude based on its luminosity, or
brightness.
Star catalogues
An accurate listing of the stars was essential for
navigation on the open sea and for making large-
scale land measurements. Until the end of the
Middle Ages the Almagest, an astronomical and
mathematical encyclopaedia compiled by
Ptolemy around 160 AD, remained the authorita¬
tive reference book for astronomers. The
Almagest, which survived in an Arabic transla¬
tion, is a digest of the mathematical knowledge
of Antiquity. It contains a catalogue of forty-eight
constellations and 1,022 stars with their ecliptic
co-ordinates and magnitudes.
The first really usable astronomical atlas,
however, was the German astronomer Johann
Bayer's Uranometria, which was drawn up in
1603. It consisted of fifty-one maps and listed
1,277 stars, with the stars in each constellation
being designated in decreasing order of brightness
by the letters of the Greek alphabet. When fur¬
ther letters were needed, the Latin alphabet was
used.
With the aid of the telescope at the Green¬
wich Royal Observatory, the English astronomer
John Flamsteed added considerably to the
number of stars listed. His Historia Coelestis
In this Illuminated design from
the psalter of Blanche of
Castile (1230), an astronomer
makes observations with an
astrolabe. He Is assisted by a
clerk and a computlst.
WERNER MERKLI,
Swiss printer and publisher, is
editor of the German-language
edition of the UNESCO Couner.
He has produced astronomical
maps of the stars, the planets
and the Moon. 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
Britannica, published in 1725, designated some
3,000 stars by number and exceeded all earlier
catalogues both in accuracy and in the number
of stars listed.
For a long time observation was limited to
the northern skies. The explorers and navigators
of the sixteenth century were the first Europeans
to see the southern skies and constellations in
their totality. The first catalogue of the stars of
the southern skies, complete with the positions
of 341 of them, determined by telescope, was
drawn up in 1676 by the English astronomer
Edmond Halley from the south Atlantic island
of St. Helena.
During an expedition (1750 to 1754) to the
Cape of Good Hope, the French astronomer
Nicolas Louis de la Caille listed some 10,000 stars
grouped in fourteen constellations, as well as
several new nebulae. His star catalogue was pub¬
lished in 1756.
The Bonner Durchmusterung, established in
the middle of the nineteenth century under the
direction of the German astronomer Friedrich
Argelander, is still today a basic reference work
for the stellar astronomy of the northern skies.
Based on observations made at the Bonn obser¬
vatory, it gives the position and characteristics
of some 350,000 stars. After Argelander's death,
the "BD" catalogue was extended to cover the
southern hemisphere, with a listing of some
500,000 stars being added by observatories in Cor¬
doba (Argentina) and Cape Town.
During the last century visual observation of
the stars was largely replaced by the use of pho¬
tographic plates. Objects whose luminosity is too
faint to be registered by the human eye can be
photographed, and the introduction of this form
of observation led to the discovery of millions
of previously unknown stars. For practical pur¬
poses, rather than referring to star maps
astronomers tend to make use of star catalogues
and listings of stellar co-ordinates, whether these
be exhaustive catalogues or what are called fun¬
damental catalogues which furnish extremely
accurate details of the positions and motions of
a reduced number of selected stars well dis¬
tributed over the sky.
Flattening the sky
It is impossible to produce a projectiona sys¬
tematic representation on a flat surface of the
features of a curved surface, such as that of the
Earth which is both complete and wholly
accurate. Even using Mercator's famous cylin¬
drical projection, which presents the globe as
though it were an unrolled cylinder, there is
inevitably a degree of distortion of angles, dis¬
tances and surfaces. Similar problems arise in
mapping the sky.
Above, the world-system
devised by the Portuguese
cosmographer Bartolomeu
Velho In 1568 reflects the
close links between
cosmography and cartography
at the Renaissance.
Above right, detail of one of
the "Original drawings of the
patches of the Moon" made
after observations by Giovanni
Domenico Cassini between
1675 and 1677. The date and
hour are Indicated by
annotations In Cassinl's own
hand.
Right, component of an
astrolabe made at Louvain In
1565 In the workshops of
Gauthier Arsenius, geographer
of the emperor Charles V.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
ï' ' -
TSR ? ' jÄ
fei
r l
L
. Hj
S
The planets, air, fire, sky
and water are disposed
around the Earth In
concentric circles In an
Illuminated design from a
manuscript (1245) of
L'Image du Monde
("The Mirror of the
World"), a treatise
about the universe by
Gossuin de Metz.
ipiiauous
fmctnöic o»^j«. cftot
'if.quctcuouàûtMr
que Uuu fair lautn
To draw up a map of the celestial sphere, the
positions of the stars are established in relation
to two arcs which are perpendicular to each other
and which are analagous to terrestrial longitude
and latitude. Individual heavenly bodies, such as
the Sun, the Moon or the planets, are usually
represented in the form of a sphere in perspec¬
tive, as though the observer were situated some¬
where in space, like a camera aboard a spaceship.
The hidden or the visible face of the star is shown,
as, for example, in the case of the Moon, or else
the sphere is shown cut up into three segments,
with two additional segments for the poles. Points
or surfaces at the eastern and western extremi¬
ties, or at the top and bottom of the sphere, will
be seen in extremely foreshortened perspective.
For scientific purposes a Mercator projection is
used with the addition of separate representations
of the poles.
The inconceivably huge distances that are
involved in stellar systems, like those that separate
the planets of our solar system, with their rings
and moons, cannot be reproduced without great
distortions. However, mathematically calculated
reduction scales enable us to have some idea of
the positions, trajectories and revolution phases
of these bodies.
Movement in the Universe
Though we speak of "fixed" stars which rise each
night above the horizon, the universe is in per¬
petual movement. The Sun, the Moon and the
planets, comets and shooting stars soar through
space but leave no trace of their passing. How
can such movement be mapped? In ancient times
astronomers constructed armillary spheres, com¬
plex assemblages of moving rings which
represented the movement of the planets, and
astrolabes, which furnished a picture of the sky
at a given moment. These instruments remained
in use until the seventeenth century.
For centuries the Earth was depicted as a flat
disc, situated in the centre of the universe, above
which moved the majestic span of the celestial
vault with its fixed stars. Yet, in ancient times,
Greek sages such as the Pythagoreans Hipparchus
and Erastosthenes had observed the curvature of 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
the Earth's surface and had deduced from this that
it was probable that the Earth was spherical in
shape and moved like a planet round the Sun.
Anaxagoras found himself accused of atheism
and banished for maintaining that the Sun was
a ball of fire bigger than the Péloponnèse. Some
1,500 years later the Italian mathematician and
astronomer Galileo (1564-1642), in his turn, was
forced to foreswear his discovery that the world
was a sphere. The heliocentric model of the
universe had failed to gain acceptance in Antiq¬
uity and the geocentric vision of the universe held
undisputed sway from the days of Ptolemy to the
Middle Ages, being defended by the Church with
increasing vigour. It was only after the publica¬
tion of the works of such famous astronomers
as Copernicus, Galileo and Kepler, who estab¬
lished the laws of gravity that rule the movements
of the planets, that the heliocentric model finally
triumphed.
Signs and images
Exploration of our solar system by spacecraft,
both manned and unmanned, and by the Hubble
space telescope, has given fresh impetus to the
mapping of the Sun, the planets and their moons.
Electronic video cameras send a constant stream
of high-definition images back to the Earth,
where they are juxtaposed and mounted, usually
in the form of spherical projections or as Mer¬
cator projections.
The Chinese used to represent the stars as
circles or dots, the Arabs depicted them as small
coloured discs and the Egyptians and the Greeks
as radiant star shapes. Until the modern age,
European cartographers followed the Egyp¬
tian/Greek example, but since the introduction
of stellar photography, the stars have been shown
as dots proportional in size to their luminosity.
It is more difficult to depict the nebulae,
galaxies, binary stars, star clusters and comets, and
harder still those heavenly bodies such as pulsars,
quasars and black holes, that are beyond the
reach of optical astronomy and whose existence is
revealed to us by the radio waves they emit.
Special charts are used to portray magnetic fields
and solar winds, which are depicted as curves.
The US National Aeronautics and Space
Administration (NASA) has also published
colour maps showing mineral formations on the
surface of the Moon.
The nomenclature used to designate the relief
features of stars in the solar system is governed
by the Paris-based International Astronomical
Union (IAU), the highest authority in the field
of astronomy. One of IAU's achievements has
been to establish a common nomenclature for the
main relief features of the Moon. To facilitate
international understanding of sky maps all the
names on them are usually written in Latin. With
the same objective in mind, each star listed in
the star catalogues has its own identification
number.
Preliminary topographic map
of Venus drawn from data
transmitted by the US space
probe Pioneer in 1980.
^¡r 'jmsssi
£*>¿L
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
So//, mineral deposits, tectonic
structure, vegetation, climate...
many chapters in the story of the
planet recorded in scientific maps
and atlases produced by UNESCO
IN the earth sciences, the maps produced by
UNESCO are mainly geological, tectonic,
metallogenic or metamorphic. These maps
generally show a continent in its entirety,
hence their small scaleusually 1:5,000,000 or
1:2,500,000.
GEOLOGICAL MAPS
The first map in this series is of Europe. The
innovations it contains paved the way for a
new generation of geological maps. For
example, the Pleistocene cover (major part of
the Quaternary), which is relatively thin in
the area of the Baltic Shield and the British
Isles, is not shown. In areas where this cover
is thicker, however, it is shown either by trans¬
parent signs or by full colour, if strong tec¬
tonic activity played a decisive role in the
process of sedimentation.
In addition, intrusive magmatic rocks
(rocks produced by molten matter being
forced up from the Earth's interior into pre¬
existing formations) and volcanic magmatic
rocks have been subdivided according to age,
chemical composition and relation to orogeny
(process of mountain formation). Generally
speaking, age is shown by colour and the
nature of the rocks or lithology by over¬
printed signs.
The map of Africa was the first to show
LYDWINE D'ANDIGNE DE ASÍS
is a programme specialist with UNESCO's Division
of Earth Sciences.
The Earth from every angle
ty Lydáe iM$é de Asís
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
the geology of the continental shelf and the
seafloor. Along with depth measurements
(bathymetry), it shows the age of the crust,
magnetic lineation, fracture zones, isopachs
(sediment thickness), the siting' of drillings, the
limits of volcanism and thrust sheets and the
epicentres of earthquakes.
Besides the geological map of Africa on
a scale of 1:5,000,000, UNESCO has recently
published a map of South and East Asia on
a scale of 1:5,000,000 and a geological map of
the world on a scale of 1:25,000,000.
TECTONIC MAPS
The tectonic map of Africa which, as its name
suggests, shows distortions in the earth's crust,
also contains some decisive innovations. For
the first time in the history of cartography,
the signs and symbols of the Precambrian are
entirely based on geochronology, i.e. on
"absolute ages" (expressed in thousands or
millions of years) determined radiometrically
on the basis of certain properties of isotopes.
The various orogenies are shown by
specific colours while overprinted conven¬
tional signs represent the ancient structures.
The depth of the basins and the thickness of
the surface cover are indicated by gradual
shading rather than by isobathic curves.
Tectonic maps provide a considerable
^1 V
^3tj- - * ' _ '
« P.;%¿ HjT¡
's V^7¿TO? "í,7iff? ; ,
Eis- .-. ' ^mH'L
^1^%X, A «V
An I
fènèfiye i
Detall of »haet 9 of the International tectonic r
of Africa (ÍS.OOO 0001
amount of data not given by geological maps.
Dynamic geology serves as a means of
explaining structures and is a source of insights
into the laws governing the evolution of the
Earth's crust. This knowledge is useful in par¬
ticular for a more practical approach to
prospecting.
METAMORPHIC MAPS
These maps show the metamorphic belts,
which are rock masses altered by heat and
pressure, highlighting mineral associations and
faciès (sediment characteristics, considered
from the point of view of their development).
The spatial distribution of these faciès is a
source of significant information concerning
the thermal history of the Earth. In some
cases, on account of the scale used, various
types of faciès corresponding to a given tem¬
perature have had to be grouped together,
irrespective of the pressure undergone.
Pressure-induced facies are also considered
together, in terms of temperature and pressure
gradients.
METALLOGENIC MAPS
These maps represent a big step forward in
metallogenic studies and the methodology of
prospecting. They show the principal litho-
logical, tectonic, magmatic and palaeogeo-
Detatt of «heel 2 of th« Metallogenic map of Europe
I12.SOO.OOOI
of ah*el 9 of th* International Quaternary map
of Euro». 11 2.500,0001
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
V	j-
UNESCO IN ACTION
graphie features contributing to strata forma¬
tion and indicate the limits and specific charac¬
teristics of mineral provinces.
They also show other important features,
namely, age of orogeny and the various sur¬
face irregularities, age of contours and
lithology of platform cover, mineralizations
with the mineral content and its importance,
and age of the mineralization along with its
genetic type.
Work is in progress towards the publica¬
tion of a map of the mineralizations of Africa,
the first sheet of which is in press, and the
mineral atlas of the world, for which the signs
and symbols have been defined.
THE SOIL MAP
OF THE WORLD
This original map in eighteen sheets is accom¬
panied by a volume of explanatory text for
each continent: the legend covers no less than
5,000 physico-chemical soil types or pedolog-
ical units. It provides a means of arriving at
an initial estimate of world soil resources and
opens the way for more extensive studies.
Since its publication, other projects have been
launched, in particular a world desertification
map and a world map of soil degradation.
THE QUATERNARY MAP
In this series only the map of Europe has so
far been published. The information presented
is not limited to glacial phenomena but
includes fluvial, lacustrine, marine and aeolian
deposits, whether of detrital or chemical
origin, and volcanic rocks. Certain geomor-
phological features are also shown on these
maps, together with the limits of marine trans¬
gressions and ice movement.
Designed for specialists, but also for
teachers, to whom they should be of invalu¬
able assistance, UNESCO maps provide a
state-of-the-art overview of our knowledge of
the Earth while opening the way for ever
more precise local investigations on an increas¬
ingly large scale. One of their aims is to trans¬
late a maximum of scientific data into an inter¬
national language understandable to all earth
scientists.
The international
language of maps
Situated at the interface of art and science,
cartography offers an irreplaceable syn¬
thesis of information scattered through
numerous books, articles and documents.
It therefore calls for the co-operation of
specialists in a variety of fields from all over
the world. The unique position occupied by
UNESCO among scientific institutions
enables it to take an active part in this type
of activity.
UNESCO plays a major role in the publi¬
cation of continental maps and world maps
covering such scientific fields as the earth
sciences (see article page 45), the water and
environmental sciences and seafloor geology.
These maps are based on national docu¬
ments prepared by UNESCO member states
themselves and then compiled and assem¬
bled by international drafting committees.
In the water sciences, UNESCO is con¬
tinuing to prepare hydrogeological maps of
the European and African continents and of
Latin America and the Caribbean.
The maps published by UNESCO make
use of the most modern techniques of satel¬
lite imaging, data processing and scanning.
The trend as regards traditional maps
printed on paper is towards the preparation
of supplementary or derived maps, prepared
to order on the basis of computerized data.
UNESCO's vast cartographic programme
is being carried out in close co-operation
with such bodies as the Commission for the
Geological Map of the World (CGMW),
UNESCO's main partner for thematic earth
science maps, the FAO (the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations) and the International Association
for Quaternary Research (INQUA), which co-
publish soil and Quaternary maps with
UNESCO, the International Association of
Hydrologlcal Sciences and the International
Hydrographie Organization.
UNESCO maps can be ordered from
the Office of the UNESCO Press,
1 rue Miollis, 75015 Paris (France)
and the Organization's sales
agents worldwide.
A small brochure in English, Scientific Maps ":?:':-; '& ]^§
and Atlases, UNESCO Catalogue, contains j j j j ;"{
a detailed, illustrated inventory of UNESCO
maps and atlases. Copies may be obtained
from the UNESCO Press, Sales Division, Bjjjji*^*^
1 rue Miollis, 75015 Paris (France). .:.::..:..
Detail of sheet D2 of the International hydrologeological
map of Europe (1:1,500.000).
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Copyright is everybody's business
For almost forty years UNESCO has been working to promote a universal copyright system which protects the rights of creators,
facilitates the diffusion of their work and contributes to international understanding. In this interview Ms Milagros del Corral,
director of UNESCO'S Book and Copyright Division, describes what is at stake.
48
Why is UNESCO concerned with
copyright?
Copyright, the legal framework for the pro¬
tection of literary, artistic and scientific works,
is a human right and as such is recognized in
Article 27 (2) of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights, which states that "Everyone
has the right to the protection of the moral
and material interests resulting from any scien¬
tific, literary or artistic production of which
he is the author". The right of creators to the
protection of their works is an aspect of the
right to culture. A delicate balance exists
between copyright protection and access to
culture, education, information and scientific
research. Copyright protection and access to
culture are also crucial to the development of
any country. In view of UNESCO's constitu¬
tional concerns in these fields and with the
defence of human rights, one might well ask
how UNESCO could fail to be closely
involved with copyright.
Could you tell us more about the role of
copyright in today's world} Who is affected
by it?
Everybody is affected, whether they realize
it or not. The copyright chain is a very com¬
plex one. In the first place, of course, there
are writers, musicians, creators of the plastic
arts, software authors, photographers, and
translators. Their work is made available to
the public by a large number of "mediators"
who acquire copyright by contractor licence
and assume the risk of producing and dis¬
tributing their work. Traditional mediators
include the publishers of books, periodicals
and newspapers, radio and television broad¬
casters, programme producers, cinema and
video corporations, theatres, and the adver¬
tising and show-business industries. Relative
newcomers to the field are distributors of
programmes by cable television, satellite trans¬
mission and the software industry.
In short, there is a very wide range of cul¬
tural industries that use protected works as the
raw material of their commercial activities. In
the industrially developed countries, industries
working on the basis of copyright contribute
between 3 and 6 per cent to the Gross
Domestic Product (GDP). Last in the
copyright chain comes the general public.
When we read a book, a magazine or a
newspaper, listen to the radio, watch televi¬
sion, use a personal computer, or attend a con¬
cert or theatre performance, we are "con¬
suming" copyright materials.
The role of copyright is to ensure that
authors are recognized by society and
remunerated for the use of their works. The
law should also prevent any distortion that
may prejudice an author's reputation. In an
increasing number of countries the rights of
performing artists are also protected.
So the sale of every single copy of a
work should provide remuneration for
the author and in some cases for the
performer?
Exactly. Unfortunately, however, copyright
is very vulnerable and the development of new
reproduction and communication technologies
represents a challenge to it. Unauthorized
copies can be produced very cheaply and can
compete illegally in the market, representing
immense losses for authors, copyright and
other intellectual rights holders throughout
the world.
Piracy represents a clear violation of
authors' rights and is causing enormous
damage. Free private copying authorized by
national laws has also attained dangerous levels
in many countries as it has gone far beyond
the original intentions of legislators. It is
impossible for authors to control the
increasing number of uses of their work, and
collective administration of rights by authors'
and performers' societies is the only reasonable
way of coping with the problem. At the inter¬
national level much work has already been
done to solve these problems, but they remain
on the agenda because of the speed of techno¬
logical change. It is not always easy to adapt
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
legal notions to these changing scenarios and
we have to proceed with caution.
What you have said relates to protection
at the national level. How can copyright pro¬
tection be ensured internationally?
This is a very important point, since the
circulation of protected works knows no
frontiers. The use of protected works in for¬
eign countries is governed by two major inter¬
national conventions, the Berne
Conventionthe International Convention
for the Protection of Literary and Artistic
Works, which is administered by the World
Intellectual Property Organization (WIPO);
and the Universal Copyright Convention
(UCC), which was adopted under the auspices
of UNESCO.
The Berne Convention seeks more exten¬
sive and stronger protection. To take one
UNESCO IN ACTION
The French mime
Marcel Marceau
uses gestures to explain
copyright.
copyright are discussed by experts from
different regions. A data base on copyright
legislation, including a detailed analysis of
national legislations and international conven¬
tions, is being compiled for CD-ROM publi¬
cation in 1994-1995. We also intend to include
a compendium of selected case law along with
a bibliography in the copyright field. This
ambitious project has been made possible
through voluntary contributions from the
USA, the UK and, we expect, from Spain and
France. It is a huge task but we are confident
that this data base, once completed, will prove
an irreplaceable tool for governments,
decision-makers, lawyers, and users of
copyright works all over the world.
example, it requires recognition of moral
rights and a fifty-year term of protection fol¬
lowing the author's death. The UCC is more
sensitive to the needs of developing countries,
many of which are net "copyright importers"
and seek easier access to copyright materials
for educational purposes. The UCC is less
extensive in its recognition of rights, allows
more exceptions from protection, and the
term of protection is twenty-five years after
the author's death.
What are UNESCO's activities in the
copyright field?
UNESCO's copyright programme is
divided into three principal areas. First,
encouraging accession to international conven¬
tions. UNESCO also encourages its member
states to adopt legal measures in conformity
with certain recommendations adopted by
UNESCO's General Conference, with regard
to the protection of translators, the
safeguarding of folklore, the status of the artist
and the safeguarding of works in the public
domain.
Second, UNESCO has recently embarked
on a major effort to introduce the teaching of
copyright into university studies. A syllabus,
a textbook and a basic bibliography have been
prepared, and universities in Latin America,
the Arab countries (and soon Africa and Asia)
are being encouraged to use them. The
training programme also includes seminars for
judges and magistrates, who play a key role
in law enforcement, and for journalists and
librarians, who can do much to increase social
awareness of copyright matters.
UNESCO's third concern is to inform
specialists and the general public. We publish
a quarterly Copyright Bulletin in English,
French, Spanish and Russian, in which the
main principles and problems of international
We are also trying to heighten public
awareness of copyright through video cassettes
that make the principal copyright notions easy
to understand. The first one is a remarkable
twelve-minute performance by the French
mime Marcel Marceau, who explains with
humour and sensitivity what copyright is and
why it needs to be protected and respected.
Finally, UNESCO is making preparations
for an international debate on the role of
copyright in the societies of today and
tomorrow, on an interdisciplinary basis. All
the international organizations involved, as
well as a number of famous authors,
producers, publishers, television stations,
copyright experts, sociologists and economists,
will be invited to discuss how copyright could
help to foster sound cultural and economic
development and to establish an open dialogue
for better eo-operation between developed and
developing countries. We feel this could also
be the best way to commemorate the fortieth
anniversary of the Universal Copyright Con¬
vention in 1992. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
50
1 he Universal Copyright Convention (UCC) is
an international instrument which was drawn up in
1952 under the auspices of UNESCO. If it were to
be as universal as its title claims, the Convention not
only had to recognize copyright as a human right
but also to act as a kind of bridge between the
world's different legal and social systems. As an
attempt to devise a legal common denominator
which would foster respect for the rights of creators
and also encourage the international circulation of
literary, scientific and artistic works, the UCC had
a dual thrust.
Before the Second World War, steps had already
been taken to remedy the paradoxical situation
whereby the United States was cut off, legally
speaking, from the countries of Europe and Asia
which since 1886 had become signatories to the
Berne Conventionthe International Convention
for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works.
Under United States law authors could only be
protected if they carried out certain administrative
formalities such as registering their work with the
US Copyright Office. This legislation had affinities
with that relating to industrial property, which only
recognized an inventor's rights if his or her inven¬
tion had been registered. This requirement stood in
the way of the United States' accession to the Berne
Convention, which enshrines the principle that a
work is protected purely by virtue of its creation.
There was thus no legal mechanism whereby a
work originating in the United States could be pro¬
tected in Japan or in the countries of Western
Europe, or whereby a work originating in the latter
countries could be protected in the United States
except when the requirements of American law were
observed.
The Universal Copyright Convention of 1952
provides a simple and ingenious solution to this
problem. It prescribes that the formalities required
by the national law of a contracting state shall be
considered to be satisfied if all the copies of a work
originating in another contracting state carry the
symbol ©, accompanied by the name of the
copyright owner and the year of first publication.
Ratified by the United States and by almost all
the states parties to the Berne Convention, the UCC
has successfully served its purpose as a pathway of
UNESCO IN ACTION
communication between different legal systems,
while also improving the international protection
of intellectual works.
The creators of the UCC set themselves another
goal in relation to the universality asserted by its
title. They wished to anticipate and provide for the
prospect following the Second World War of a con¬
siderable increase in the number of sovereign states
as a consequence of decolonization. Legal norms for
the protection of authors should be sufficiently flex¬
ible and open to accommodate states at different
stages of development, or states belonging to
different economic and social systems. These norms
could thus not be as precise and restrictive as those
of the Berne Convention, while nevertheless
providing sufficient recognition of authors' rights.
The 1952 Convention satisfies these two condi¬
tions. Its protective norms are expressed in the form
of general principles which can be given different
shades of interpretation depending on the specific
identity of each state. The Convention limits the
term of protection of copyright to twenty-five years
after an author's death, thus permitting the acces¬
sion of the USSR. But correlatively the Convention
provides for the works of the citizens of each con¬
tracting state the same protection in other con¬
tracting states as it does for the works of authors
belonging to those states. The prohibition of any
discrimination in a given state between authors who
are nationals of that state and foreign authors who
may invoke the Convention is evidence of a
universal concept of the protection of intellectual
works.
The 1952 Convention created a legal structure
which could accommodate the United States, the
USSR, the industrially developed countries and the
developing countries. It also influenced its
predecessor, the Berne Convention. Fruitful co¬
operation led to the closer alignment of the two
Conventions, which were revised in 1971. This revi¬
sion gave concrete form to the twofold movement
initiated in 1952 by the UCC: furtherance of the
legal rights of creators and acknowledgement of the
specific needs of developing countries.
ANDRÉ KÉREVER ¡s a former member of the Conseil
d'Etat (France).
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3 (right): © Explorer
Archives. Library of Congress,
Washington, D.C. Back cover:
© Bibliothèque Royale Albert I,
Brussels. Page 2: © Sophie
Golvin, Paris. Pages 3, 7: All
rights reserved. Page 4:
© Bernand, Paris/Théâtre
National de la Colline. Page 6:
© Muños de Pablos, Paris. Pages
8-9: © Edimedia, Paris. Pages
10-11, 18: © British Library,
London. Page 12: Erich Lessing
© Magnum, Paris. Page 13: Erich
Lessing © Magnum, Paris/Louvre
Museum. Page 14: © Jean-Loup
Charmet, Paris. Page 15:
©UNDP, Geneva. Pages 16-17:
© Dagli-Orti/Marciana Library,
Venice. Page 19 (above):
© Explorer Archives/Rheims
Library, France. Page 19 (below):
© Service Historique de l'Armée
de Terre, Vincennes, France.
Pages 20-21: © R. and S.
Michaud/Suleymanie Library,
Istanbul. Page 22: © R. and S.
Michaud/University Library,
Leyden. Pages 22-23: Oronoz
© Artephot/lnstituto de
cooperación con el mundo árabe,
Madrid. Pages 24-25:
© Osterreichische
Nationalbibliothek, Vienna. Page
26: © Instituto Nacional de
Antropología e Historia, Mexico
City. Pages 27, 30, 32 (above),
42: © Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris. Pages 28-29: © Explorer
Archives, Paris. Page 29: © Jean-
Loup Charmet, Paris/Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Page 31:
© Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris/
Bibliothèque Mazarine, Paris.
Pages 32 (below), 33 (below):
©Norman J.W. Thrower, from
Maps and Man: An Examination
of Cartography in Relation to
Science and Civilization,
Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey,
1972. Page 33 (above):
© Musée de l'Histoire de France,
Archives Nationales, Paris. Page
34: © Dagli-Orti/Chêteau de
Versailles. Pages 35 to 38, 43
(below): © I.G.N., Paris. Pages
39, 40: UNESCO Courier,
Moscow. Pages 41, 43 (above
right): © Edimedia/Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Page 43 (above
left): © Paris Observatoire. Page
44: © DITE/NASA, Paris. Pages
45 to 49: © UNESCO, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The IJnesoo
^COURIER
44th YEAR
Published monthly in 35 languages and In braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca. Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey. Carole Pajot-Font
(Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Administrative assistant: Pnthi Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud E!-Shenit¡ (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa (Dares Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhafa: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alnassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68 45.88),
Assistant: Marie- Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89).
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard.
Michelle Robillard. Mohamed Salan El Dm,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65),
Mall: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68. 4565
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 Frerch francs. 2 years: 194 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier".
plus date of issue, arid three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
Photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
es returned unless accompanied by ar international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed a-.icles express the opinions of the authors
a-icJ do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO Courier Photo captions and headlines
arc written by the UNESCO Courier staff The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not Imply oficial endorsement or
acceptance by UNESCO or :hc United Nations T-ie UNESCO Courier
is produced in microform (microfilm andior microfiche} oy: (1) UNESCO.
? P'iice de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100 U.S.A. (3) NCR Micocard Fdition. Indian
Head, inc . Ill West 40th Street, New York. J S A ; (4) Bell and Howell
Co.. Ole Mansfield Road, Wooste'. Ohio 44691, U.S A
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
¡Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL CI JUIN 1991.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 - DIFFUSE PA^ LES NMPP
Photocomposition: The UNESCO Courier
Photogravure-impression: Maury impnmeu- S.A..
Z.l. route d'Etampes, 45330 Malesherbes
NATURE &
RESSOURCES
NATURE &
RESOURCES
UNESCO's quarterly review of research for
sustainable development, has been relaunched
in a well-illustrated format, with a carefully
focused editorial policy.
It provides in-depth reviews of environmental
issues from an international perspective, thanks
to its reliance on both established and new
authors from around the world.
Annual subscriptions
£25 individuals
£50 institutions
for the English, French and Spanish editions:
Parthenon Publishing
Casterton Hall,
Carnforth, Lanes.
LA6 2LA United Kingdom
For details on special rates for readers in less
developed countries and on the Arabic, Chinese
and Russian editions:
Editor
Nature & Resources
UNESCO
7, Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France
Qualité et disponibilité de l'eau
la NATURALEZA
v sus RECURSOS
Problemas de \a investigación oceánkj y costera
NATURE &
RESOURCES
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 6- 1991 OPl -91-3 493 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
-->->..,=*.!
\g
-
L
V
MtfM
;> ^
y
>*Ty»'- >
4
»M"- .'
Ü^K^^pL*? m*Mi& ^üfotí r*/»£ ^ ow 1°;
|>^ÎB$|vvÎ f»t««í 5*fr ¿fit »mo&^ug -V
pAtticù- ttcftoxort aie Sunfccß CtftM
]]>
</page>
</document>
