<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="089961eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
B
t
Î
w*
OCTOBER 1991
1205 9110 18,00 F
lM
Wm STARTING IN THIS ISSUE
UNESCO IN ACTION:
. ^KMI THE FIRST 45 YEARS
mmjm*
THE STORY
OF A GRAND DESIGN
by FEDERICO MAYOR
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
STARTING IN THIS ISSUE:
UNESCO FROM THE BEGINNING: A CHRONOLOGY OF KEY EVENTS
THE STORY OF A GRAND DESIGN
BY FEDERICO MAYOR
Director-General of UNESCO
T,HE memory of an institution is at once more reliable and
more precarious than that of an individual. More reliable,
because it is not subject to physical decay and also less subjective,
since its collective nature provides it with a permanent capacity
for checking and cross-checking.
But at the same time it is more precarious. Partly as a result
of compartmentalization, the members of an institution do not
always realize the importance of those fragments of the past
of which they are the sole repositories. All too often they rely
on others to transmit the heritage of history and information
which they share with their colleagues. The institutional
memory is also fallible because institutions live longer than
people. As soon as those who have served an institution since
its foundation start to leave it, the record of its history is exposed
to destruction, to oblivion.
However essential they may be, and however well-
organized, archives can never fully replace the living testimony
of eyewitnesses. The play of influences, the power and charisma
of certain personalities, the enthusiasm of great moments of
unanimity, the clash of controversyall these factors elude the
archival memory, along with the anecdotes which can bring
a situation back to life and which are often, perhaps wrongly,
disdained as trivia. The atmosphere in which events unfold and
decisions are taken cannot be captured and preserved in dossiers.
Something of this atmosphere seems to me, fortunately, to
have been preserved in the chronicle presented on the following
pages, which has been prepared not only from documentary
evidence but also with the aid of conversations with those who
took part in the events described. These individual contribu¬
tions are important today. Now that UNESCO is forty-five
years old, its existence outspans the careers of even those who
have served it longest.
The late 1980s were a milestone in UNESCO's history.
They were a time for taking stock and breaking new ground.
Today one generation is handing over to another. To the new
generation I would particularly recommend this chronology,
which will provide it with a humus of memory and tradition
in which its energy can take root. To the departing generation,
to those who at all levels of responsibility, through doubts and
certainties, failures and successes, have made the history of
UNESCO and are its living memory, this chronology is natur¬
ally dedicated.
In such a context it would be equally impossible not to
think of the promoters and precursors of UNESCO, the
pioneers whose role is recalled in these pages: the resolute men
and womeneducators, jurists, writers, philosophers, great
scientistswho believed, while war was still raging, that one
of the priorities of the postwar world would be the dedicated
search for alternatives to ignorance and philistinism, injustice
and violence.
I wonder whether the exemplary nature of this enterprise
has been sufficiently recognized and whether enough thought
has been given to the small group of founding fathers who in
war-torn London in 1942 pooled their abilities and their con¬
victions in order to give shape to their intuition, with a serenity
and farsightedness that enabled them to look beyond the grim
events around them. Have we paid due respect to the
disinterestednessso characteristic of devotion to great causes
that involved them in this enterprise whose credibility every¬
thing then seemed to deny?
The objectives they set forth are still far from being
achieved. "It is UNESCO's vocation to be a permanent ques¬
tion". This phrase, which featured in UNESCO's fortieth
anniversary exhibition in 1986, summed up the thinking of
some of the Organization's great figures. It seems to me to be
extremely apt. It is impossible to be certain of the outcome of
such a vast and ambitious mission as oursone which may
sometimes seem thankless to those who seek tangible and
immediate results, yet inspiring to those who are convinced of
its long-term necessity.
Finally let me express the pride I feel in exercising my
responsibilities at a time which is doubtless difficult but when
the opening of the last decade of the century and the millen¬
nium invites us to look back and to reflect. In this issue the
Courier begins publication of a chronological record of
UNESCO's history, a testimony to the accomplishments and
events which have marked its life since its inception. This record
of achievements that are already considerable will, I am sure,
serve as a reminder of our springs of action and inspire us with
the vigour of renewed commitment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
vafff
i<ii-j
;»
I ELT* /
*
- Í
v *
4
- ^%fc W
« - -T* H»
5 "^^r
The opening of the first General Conference of UNESCO at the Sorbonne. Parts, on 20 November 1946.
UNESCO's ftst 45 yean
~ NY chronicle of the achievements and events that have marked the
four and a half decades of existence of the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization is bound to be selective. It is also
bound to highlight the three major aspects of UNESCO's activities: their
range in space and time, since they extend to all the continents and most
of them are long-term; their diversity of type and content; and the spirit
of perseverance which inspires them in pursuit of the common goal of
helping to bring humankind together and to promote international under¬
standing. These qualities characterize both the most spectacular of
UNESCO's activities, such as its international campaigns for the preser¬
vation of great monuments, and thosefar more numerousthat may
long go unnoticed before their results finally take tangible form.
Raising awareness and stimulating action; formulating experimental
models and pilot projects; providing technical assistance, consultation
with specialists; acting as a source of documentation and information;
traininga fundamental activity whose effects multiply over the years;
standard-setting activities; drawing up intellectual guidelines for action
this is the substance of UNESCO's work. By these means UNESCO accom¬
plishes its mission of breaking down geographical barriers to the spread .
of knowledge and encouraging dialogue between cultures. In this way
UNESCO seeks to carry out the mandate assigned to it by its Constitution,
of "advancing, through the educational and scientific and cultural rela¬
tions of the peoples of the world, the objectives of international peace".
This is a long-term effort which it is difficult to present in calendar form.
We hope however that it will appear in the background of this chronology.
The chronology is divided under seven headings. The firstGeneral
Policysubsumes the major decisions of UNESCO's General Conference,
the evolution of the Organization's governing bodies, UNESCO's rela¬
tions with its Member States, and activities which extend over several
fields of its programme. Five other headings correspond to UNESCO's
five sectors: Education; Exact and Natural Sciences; Social Sciences;
Culture; Communication. The seventh heading (Events) covers all the
exhibitions, visits, seminars and celebrations that in a sense constitute
the social life of UNESCO while contributing to its cultural influence.
Considerable space has been given to the collaboration which began
at a very early stage between UNESCO and international non¬
governmental organizations (NGOs), some of which have a very close
working relationship with the Organization. The NGOs are partners of
great importance for UNESCO, since their members are internationally
known specialists in UNESCO's fields of competence. Some of them were
created before UNESCO, most subsequently, and several at UNESCO's
initiative. In the chronology their activities are briefly referred to, and
special attention is given to those which co-operate technically with the
Organization.
The chronology naturally stresses UNESCO's programme activities
under the five main headings. These programmes and projects appear
either under the date when they were first decided upon, or when they
were inaugurated, or when they entered one of their most significant
stages.
MICHEL CONIL LACOSTE M
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
From left to right:
Ellen Wilkinson;
Jaime Torres Bodet;
Jacques Maritain;
Léon Blum;
Eleanor Roosevelt with
René Cassin;
Julian Huxley with
Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan.
mim
THE EARLY DAYS
16 November 1942.
London.
First meeting of the Conference of Allied
Ministers of Education (CAME) held on the
initiative of R.A. Butler, President of the Board
of Education of England and Wales. CAME,
which soon expands to include other countries,
notably the United States, holds many sessions
until the end of 1945. From its meetings the idea
gradually emerges of creating an organization
which will primarily be concerned with
promoting co-operation between the wartime
allies in the field of education.
1944 .
The poet Archibald MacLeish, Librarian of
Congress, is a member of the U.S delegation to
CAME and plays an important role in drafting
UNESCO's Constitution. The extension of
the future organization's field of competence,
especially to science, is discussed: should it be
UNEO, UNECO or UNESCO? The campaign
to put the S (for science) in UNESCO is led by
the British biochemist and historian of science
Joseph Needham and by his colleague Julian
Huxley, who will be UNESCO's first Director-
General.
9 October 1944
At Dumbarton Oaks (Washington, D.C), the
final preparations are made for the conference
at San Francisco, the following year, which will
create the United Nations Organization.
April-June 1945
The United Nations Conference on International
Organization (UNCIO) is held at San Francisco.
Acting on a motion by France and certain
Chinese and Latin American proposals, the Con¬
ference, on the sidelines of its discussions on the
organization of postwar security, recommends
that a conference be convened to establish an
international organization on "intellectual co¬
operation". The terms of the motion indicate the
French preference for a new organization built
around a revived and reorganized International
Institute of Intellectual Co-operation (IIIC).
(Founded in Paris in 1925 as the executive body
of the International Commission for Intellectual
Co-operation of the League of Nations, the IIIC
was in a sense the League's UNESCO.) There
is unanimous agreement on the basic principle
defined by Georges Bidault, the French Minister
of Foreign Affairs and head of the French dele¬
gation: "In addition to the economic and social
cornerstones, the international edifice needs a
third mainstay".
24 October 1945
The United Nations Charter adopted at San
Francisco comes into effect. Article 57 provides
for the creation of a specialized agency in the
fields of education and culture.
1-16 November 1945
A Conference to establish an Educational and
Cultural Organization of the United Nations
meets in London, at the invitation of the British
and French governments. In his welcoming
address, British Prime Minister Clement Attlee
says that "Today the peoples of the world are
islands shouting at each other over seas of mis¬
understanding. . . . 'Know thyself, said the old
proverb. 'Know your neighbour', we say today.
And the whole world is our neighbour." On 16
November, the Constitution of UNESCO is
signed by 37 States and the Final Act by 41. A
Preparatory Commission is created.
16 November 1945
The first meeting of the Preparatory Commis¬
sion is held in London. The Commission's first
secretary, the sociologist and historian Sir Alfred
Zimmern, is soon replaced for health reasons by
Julian Huxley.
im
General policy
16 September: The Preparatory Commission
for UNESCO moves from London to Paris
(Hotel Majestic, Avenue Kleber).
4 November: UNESCO's Constitution comes
into force with its ratification by the 20th signa¬
tory State, Greece.
November/December: The first session of the
General Conference opens at the Sorbonne under
the presidency of Léon Blum (France). There is
an enthusiastic atmosphere but also a debate
between those for whom "the action of
UNESCO presupposes a philosophy. . . , a
coherent general doctrine which enables it to see
things from a unique angle" (Julian Huxley) and
those who believe that it can and should do
without such a doctrine, in view of the practical
nature of its aims.
At the first session of UNESCO's Executive
Board, Julian Huxley (United Kingdom) is
elected Director-General.
UNESCO's first annual budget is set at
US$6,250,000.
31 December: The International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation ceases its activities,
which it had continued after the war. On 19
December it signs an agreement with UNESCO
"to ensure the continuity, under the responsi¬
bility of UNESCO, of the work accomplished
since 1924" by the Institute. The agreement pro¬
vides for the transfer to the United Nations from
the League of Nations, of the assets of the IIIC,
especially its library, its archives, stocks of pub¬
lications and the copyrights and publication
rights pertaining thereto. This transfer will be
effective in 1947.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Exact and natural sciences
An agreement between UNESCO and the
International Council of Scientific Unions
(ICSU) inaugurates UNESCO's policy of co¬
operation with the major international non¬
governmental organizations (NGOs). Created in
1931, ICSU today consists of 20 international
scientific unions (organized by discipline), 74
national members (academies of sciences) and 29
scientific associates.1 UNESCO/ICSU co¬
operation will constantly develop over the years
in the form of joint programmes in such fields
as geological correlation, climate change, scien¬
tific and technological information, and training
in biology in developing countries.
Culture
The International Council of Museums
(ICOM) is founded in Paris. Its documentation
centre, which becomes the UNESCO/ICOM
Documentation Centre, is a unique repository
of information on all aspects of museum manage¬
ment. ICOM's first director is the distinguished
French museologist Georges-Henri Rivière. Its
members include over 8,000 individuals and insti¬
tutions in 120 countries.
Communication
A section concerned with communications is
created in the UNESCO Secretariat.
Events
The French writer André Gide notes in his
Journal: "I send to Huxley, as epigraph to
UNESCO's programme, the last line of the
second book of the Aeneid, endowing it with a
symbolic meaning: '. . . and assuming the full
charge of my heritage, I shall strive towards the
heights'. Isn't this what UNESCO is trying to
do?"
mi
General policy
At the second session of the General Confer¬
ence, held in Mexico City, the ideological debate
which had marked the first session continues
with important contributions from Sarvepalli
Radhakrishnan (India) and Mgr Maroun
(Lebanon). In a notable address, Jacques Mari-
tain, head of the French delegation, distances
himself from Huxley's "evolutionary
humanism" and from his desire to provide
UNESCO with a specific doctrine. In the
"babel" of contemporary thought, he notes,
"Dig as we may, there are no common founda¬
tions for speculative thought. . . . Because the
goal of UNESCO is a practical goal, agreement
between minds can be reached spontaneously,
not on the basis of common speculative ideas,
but on common practical ideas, not on the affir¬
mation of one and the same conception of the
world, . . . but upon the affirmation of a single
body of beliefs for guidance in action. No doubt
this is little enough. ... It is, nevertheless, enough
to enable a great task to be undertaken."
At its second session the Executive Board
adopts for 1947 a programme whose main thrust
is the reconstruction and rehabilitation of educa¬
tional, scientific and cultural life in war-
devastated countries, principally in Europe, with
the accent on libraries, museums and the free
flow of information.
The first UNESCO Associations are founded
in Japan and the United States. This spontaneous
movement of support for UNESCO and the
propagation of its ideals spreads quickly. In 1991
there are almost 3,800 UNESCO Associations
and Clubs in 104 States in all the continents.
Exact and natural sciences
The first "Field Science Co-operation Offices"
(later to become Regional Offices for Science and
Technology) are founded in Cairo, Rio de
Janeiro, Nankin and New Delhi.
Communication
UNESCO carries out a survey in 12 war-
devastated countries on technical needs in press,
radio and films.
1
General policy
1. Statistics in this chronology not relating to the year
under which they are given are valid for the first half of
1991.
Jaime Torres Bodet (Mexico) is elected
Director-General on the expiry of Julian
Huxley's 2-year mandate.
UNESCO's General Conference meets in
Beirut and adopts by acclamation a resolution
instructing the Director-General "to stimulate
the dissemination of information about the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights"
adopted a few hours earlier by the United
Nations.
UNESCO's fellowship and study grant
programme is inaugurated. Awards are made
largely by the Education Sector (709 for
1984-1985), and by the Science Sector (355 for
the same period), for an average length of 6
months. The main beneficiary regions are Africa,
Asia and the Pacific, and the Arab States.
Launch of a Book Coupon Programme to
make it easier for people in soft currency coun¬
tries to buy books, and subsequently other cul¬
tural and scientific material, from hard currency
"" ,
'"'>, ill
I
O JEUNE HOMME
TOUfIC l>»»ir-N
The covers of three early
UNESCO publications.
countries. Almost $300 million worth of
UNESCO Gift Coupons sold by 1986.
UNESCO's trilingual quarterly Copyright
Bulletin is launched.
The first issue of the UNESCO Courier is pub¬
lished.
Education
At Utrecht, an international conference
organized by UNESCO and the Netherlands
government paves the way for the creation of
the International Association of Universities
(IAU), a centre for world-wide co-operation in
higher education (official foundation date: 1950).
Exact and natural sciences
The International Union for the Protection
of Nature (IUPN) is founded at Fontainebleau
at a conference convened by UNESCO and the
French government. Now named the Interna¬
tional Union for Conservation of Nature and
Natural Resources, it has its headquarters at
Gland (Switzerland).
At Beirut, the General Conference adopts a
resolution proposed by India instructing
UNESCO to examine the possibility of estab¬
lishing an International Institute for the Arid
Zone. The idea will be taken up three years later
in the form of a UNESCO programme.
Culture
A programme for the translation of classic and
contemporary literary works in the "UNESCO
Collection of Representative Works" is inaugu¬
rated. This programme, with which Roger
Caillois, Etiemble and Jean Thomas are closely
associated, was partly due to an "arts and letters"
unit of which the Greek novelist Nikos Kazant-
zakis was a member.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The first issue of Museum, a quarterly maga¬
zine devoted to significant new developments in
museography, is produced in association with
ICOM. Museum is published in French, English,
Spanish, Russian and Arabic (plus special issues
in other languages).
The International Council on Archives (ICA)
is established.
On the initiative of Julian Huxley, the Inter¬
national Theatre Institute (ITI) is set up to pro¬
mote international exchange of knowledge and
practice in theatre arts and to stimulate creativity
in this field. Members and activities include 9
international organizations, 69 national or
associated centres; in co-operation with
UNESCO, the itinerant "University of the
Theatre of Nations". The ITI is currently
preparing a World Encyclopaedia of Theatre.
Communication
The "Beirut Agreement" for facilitating the
international circulation of visual and auditory
materials of an educational, scientific and cultural
character is signed. (It will come into force in
1954).
IW
General policy
A decision of the Economic and Social
Council of the United Nations (ECOSOC) sets
up an extended programme of technical assistance
to underdeveloped countries, leading to opera¬
tional action by UNESCO, where a department
of technical assistance headed by Malcolm
Adiseshiah (India) is established.
Education
A fundamental education pilot project is
launched in the Marbial valley (Haiti).
The first international conference on adult
education is held at Elsinore (Denmark): 3 similar
conferences will be held in 1960 (Montreal), 1972
(Tokyo) and 1985 (UNESCO HQ, Paris).
The first volume of Study Abroad, an inter¬
national handbook providing details of oppor¬
tunities for international study in UNESCO's
Member States, is published.
Social sciences
At the instigation of the United Nations,
UNESCO launches an information campaign,
based on meetings of anthropologists and biolo¬
gists, to expose the fallacies of racism. The Swiss
anthropologist Alfred Métraux plays an impor¬
tant role.
The International Social Science Bulletin, (later
the International Social Science Journal), a mul-
D tidisciplinary quarterly designed to foster com
munication and the exchange of knowledge
between professionals in the social sciences, is
published in English and French. Later, Spanish,
Arabic, Chinese and Russian editions are added.
Selections of articles occasionally appear in other
languages.
An exhibition is organized at the Musée Gal-
liera in Paris by UNESCO and the French
government as part of efforts to publicize the
Declaration of Human Rights. Texts and illus¬
trations are published in book form the following
year. This initiative comes from an "Ideas
Group" created the previous year in the Depart¬
ment of Mass Communication.
Culture
The first Catalogue of Reproductions of
Paintings, a listing of high-quality colour
reproductions, is published. UNESCO's
programme of travelling exhibitions of reproduc¬
tions will develop from this.
The International Council for Philosophy and
Humanistic Studies (ICPHS) is created on
UNESCO's initiative.
The ICPHS groups 13 international non¬
governmental organizations representing all the
disciplines of the human sciences (philosophy,
history, linguistics, anthropology, "classical"
studies, African and Asiatic studies, etc.). Its net¬
work of individual members and scientific bodies
are drawn from 145 countries. Publications con¬
nected with UNESCO's programme include:
Sources for the General History ofAfrica, Sources
for the History ofAsia, Corpus ofpre-Columbian
Archaeological Material, language atlases (China,
the Pacific), Concordance and Indexes ofMoslem
Tradition, an edition of the Mahabharata. The
ICPHS advises UNESCO on the choice of
authors for the literature translation programme
(later joined by International PEN for contem¬
porary authors).
At UNESCO's initiative, the International
Music Council (IMC) is set up. Today it groups
27 international professional organizations and
is represented in 68 countries. Its programme
includes the International Rostrum of Com¬
posers, the International Rostrum of Young
Composers, and the Music Rostra of Africa,
Below left, young members of the UNESCO
Club at Mangalore in India; right, a
performance by the itinerant University
of the Theatre of Nations, which works
with the International Theatre Institute.
Latin America and the Caribbean, and the Arab
world. The IMC is preparing a world history of
music written for the first time in a fully inter-
cultural perspective. The first volumes, devoted
to the Americas, will be published in English in
1992 by the Smithsonian Institution
(Washington, D.C), under the title The Universe
ofMusic: a History.
The first volume is published of the new series
of the Index Translationum, an annual multilin¬
gual guide to translations of books published in
UNESCO Member States. UNESCO thus con¬
tinues, after an interruption of 10 years, the work
of the International Institute of Intellectual Co¬
operation, which had created the guide and pub¬
lished it between 1932 and 1940.
For 1948 the Index lists 8,570 translations pub¬
lished in 26 countries. Volume 38 (published 1991
and covering the year 1985) lists 57,374 for 59
countries.
The most translated works and authors in the
last decade: the Bible, Lenin, Marx, Agatha
Christie, Jules Verne, Barbara Cartland, Leo Tol¬
stoy. Main trends: the rise in popular literature
and children's literature.
Since volume 32 (1979), this reference work
prepared mainly for publishers, translators,
writers, teachers and students has been com¬
puterized.
Collaboration begins between UNESCO and
the International Commission for Translation,
Lebanon (translation from and into Arabic.)
Communication
A first study on the professional training of
journalists is undertaken.
UNESCO sends the Canadian film-maker
Norman McLaren to China to train village edu¬
cators in animation techniques for the prepara¬
tion of cartoon films.
UNESCO creates a small radio recording
studio and broadcasts a weekly 15-minute
programme on-education, science and culture.
The programme, "UNESCO World Review",
is soon being broadcast in 18 languages by radio
stations in 47 countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER 1991 CONTENTS
8
Interview with
GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ
TheljNESCO
¿^COURIER
44th TEAR
PuMlthtd monthly in 35 l*nli»(» and In Br»lll*
"Th* Government» of the State»
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men. it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if it is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO.
16 November 194S
CHILDREN IN DANGER
THE RIGHT TO BE HEARD
by Michel Manciaux 13
CHILDREN OF THE STREETS
by Flor Romero 16
CHILDREN IN GANGS
by Carl Rogers 19
AFRICA'S LOST GENERATION 22
PAULA LI, MOHAMMED
AND THEIR FRIENDS
by Ana Vásquez 25
STRESS AT AN EARLY AGE
by Tariho Fukuda 29
THE SPOILED CHILD
by Anne Rose 32
THE TWELVE WHO SURVIVE
by Robert G. Myers 34
CHILD LABOUR
IN THE WORLD TODAY 37
THE CONVENTION
ON THE RIGHTS OF THE CHILD 39
2
The story
of a grand design
by Federico Mayor
3
UNESCO's first
45 years
by Michel Conil Lacoste
46
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
Sana'a, the pearl of Arabia
by Lotfallah Soliman
49
IN BRIEF..
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
A MIRROR FOR CHILDHOOD
by François Vallet
Cover:
Detail from / want to go
home, 3 work by a 5-year-old
from China.
Back cover:
Five minutes from happiness,
by Pance Narmov, age 15
43 (Yugoslavia).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
GABRIEL
GARCÍA
MÁRQUEZ
Born in the Colombian village of Aracataca
in 1929, Gabriel García Márquez made his
mark as a master of the modern novel with
the publication of Cien años de soledad in
1967 (published in English as One Hundred
Years of Solitude in 1970). His reputation
was cemented with the award of the Nobel
Prize for Literature in 1982. In this interview
he speaks of his personal vision of Latin
America and evokes some of the principal
themes of his work, in which elements of fan¬
tasy and the marvellous mingle with the most
banal reality to give everyday life a mythical
and universal dimension.
García Márquez's other major works pub¬
lished in English include No-one Writes to the
Colonel, (1963), The Autumn of the Patriarch
(1976) and Chronicle of a Death Foretold,
(1983). His most recent work is Love In the
Time of Cholera.
In Latin America different cultures have
come together to create something new and
rich. Are Latin Americans aware ofthis inter¬
mixing?
Speaking for myself, I only became aware
of it a few years ago, even though my
experience as a writer and my frequent con¬
tacts with different societies and political
systems have increased my understanding of
other aspects of Latin American culture.
When I was travelling in Africa, I noticed
similarities between some forms of popular art
there and those of various Caribbean coun¬
tries. That gave me a clearer understanding of
our own cultural situation as well as of the
relationship between elements of different cul¬
tures generally.
Through such insights, you can discover-
both what is unique and what is universal in
a culture. There is a whole network of links
between peoples that they may not necessarily
be aware of.
Isn't that the starting-point ofyour novels?
Their main theme, even?
I wasn't really conscious of the multicul¬
tural influence when I was writing them. It
came to me of its own accord. It was only
afterwards that I realized that almost uninten¬
tionally there were elements of this cultural
Interview by Manuel Osorio,
8 Peruvian journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
In the Caribbean, and in Latin America
in general, we consider so-called magical situations
part of everyday, life
mingling in my work, elements that had crept
in gradually as I was writing.
In Latin America various influences have
mixed and spread across the continent:
Western culture, the African presence, even
some Oriental elements, all added to the
native, pre-Columbian tradition. That's why
I don't think one can talk of a Mexican or
Colombian culture as such. Speaking per¬
sonally, I no longer think of myself as Colom¬
bian; first and foremost I am Latin American,
and proud of it.
I should add that it's a mistake to think
of the history of Latin America as starting
with the Spanish conquest. That's a colonial
viewpoint. We must never forget that the
nations forged by the Spanish viceroys were
the results of arbitrary decisions from outside,
not of our own special needs.
To understand our current problems, we
have to go back to the time before the Con¬
quest. The borders that were drawn between
the Latin American countries were only
created to manipulate us, and still, whenever
there's a need for it, the cry of nationalism
goes up. Obviously, that only sets us against
one another, stops us from seeing and feeling
the problems that we have in common. Each
country has its own special circumstances, but
what really matters is our underlying common
identity.
So is there such a thing as a Latin
American culture?
I certainly don't think one can say there
is a homogeneous Latin American culture. For
example in Central America, the Caribbean
region, there is an African influence that has
resulted in a culture different from that of
countries with a sizable indigenous popula¬
tion, like Mexico or Peru. You could make
a similar point about many other Latin
American countries.
In South America, Venezuela and
Colombia have more in common with the
Caribbean than with the Andean Indians, even
though both countries have an Indian popu¬
lation of their own. In Peru and Ecuador,
there is a divergence between the coastal
regions and the mountains. Similar situations
exist throughout the continent.
These diverse influences come together to
give Latin American civilization its special
flavour, its uniqueness in relation to the
world's other cultures.
What part does Spanish influence play in
this context?
There's no denying the strength of Spanish
influence in Latin America, and of Portuguese
influence in Brazil. It is there in every aspect
of our lives. We even speak Castilian Spanish.
It is a very rich influence, if also a con¬
troversial one that is often disparaged. Even
though the heritage is part of our cultural per¬
sonality, there is a mistrust of everything
Spanish in Latin America that complicates
everything and seems to me to be excessive
and dangerous. As far as I'm concerned, I am
proud to have inherited that culture, I'm not
ashamed of it in any way. Spanish coloniza¬
tion is no longer a problem today. It's true
that we were created in a way from a Euro¬
pean overflow, but we're no mere copy of
Europe. Latin America is something else again.
Where did the urge to write come from,
the storytelling inspiration that gave us One
Hundred Years of Solitude, The Autumn
of the Patriarch, Chronicle of a Death Fore¬
told, Love in the Time of Cholera. . . ?
I think it all comes from nostalgia.
Nostalgia for your childhood? For your
country?
Nostalgia for my country and for life itself.
I had an extraordinary childhood, sur¬
rounded by highly imaginative and supersti¬
tious people, people who lived in a misty
world populated by phantasms. For instance,
my grandmother used quite unselfconsciously
to tell me stories at night that would make my
hair stand on end.
Your grandfather seems to have been some¬
thing of a family legend. Did hé play an
important part in your childhood?
He was an enormous old man who seemed
to be suspended in time and in memory, and
I was very fond of him. He died when I was
eight years old, and I was deeply upset. He
used to tell me about his life and everything
that had happened in the village and the sur¬
rounding district since time immemorial. He
described in detail the wars he had fought in
and the terrible massacres in the banana plan¬
tations the year I was born, massacres that left
a lasting trace on Colombian history.
Did your mother also influence you as a
writer?
She's an enchanting woman. When
someone asked her about me, what she
attributed her son's talent to, she replied
without batting an eyelid "Scott's Emul¬
sion".* There's another revealing anecdote. I
have several brothers. Well, whenever one of
us takes a plane, she lights a candle and says
a prayer that everything will be all right. But
we're no longer all living at home, and the last
time I saw her she told me, "Now I always
keep a candle burning, in case one of you takes
a plane without my knowing about it".
All my family are very important to me,
and they all appear in one way or another in
my writings. I never forget that I am the son
of an Aracataca postal worker.
* A children's tonic. Editor
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Life In Tenochtitlán,
by the Mexican muralist
Diego Rivera
(1886-1957)
evokes the ancient
capital of the Aztecs,
built on the site of
present-day Mexico City.
Originally you camefrom the Caribbean,
and your books reflect the feverish, over¬
flowing life of the region. Is that where you
found the magical realism that has made your
work so popular around the world?
In the Caribbean there's a perfect
symbiosiswell, let's say one more evident
than elsewherebetween the people, daily life
and the natural world. I grew up in a village
hidden away among marshes and virgin forest
on the Colombian north coast. The smell of
the vegetation there is enough to turn your
stomach.
It's a place where the sea passes through
every imaginable shade of blue, where
cyclones make houses fly away, where villages
lie buried under dust and the air burns your
lungs. For the Caribbean peoples, natural
catastrophe and human tragedy are part of
everyday life.
I should add that the area is soaked in
myths brought over by the slaves, mixed in
with Indian legends and Andalusian imagina¬
tion. The result is a very special way of
looking at things, a conception of life that sees
a bit of the marvellous in everything. You find
it not just in my novels, but also in the works
of Miguel Angel Asturias in Guatemala and
Alejo Carpentier in Cuba. There's a super¬
natural side to things, a kind of reality that
ignores the laws of reason, just like in dreams.
/ believe it's not
too late to build a utopia
that would allow us
to share an Earth
on which no one would
take decisions
for other people
I once wrote a story about the Pope visiting
a remote Colombian village, something that
seemed quite impossible at the time. Well, a
few years later the Pope visited Colombia.
In view ofthe influences you've described,
the presence of the marvellous throughout
your work, do you think critics are justified
in describing you as a fantasy writer, as
baroque?
In the Caribbean, and in Latin America in
general, we consider so-called magical situa¬
tions part of everyday life, like any other
aspect of reality. It seems quite natural to us
to believe in portents, telepathy, premoni¬
tions, a whole host of superstitions and fan¬
tastical ways of coming to terms with reality.
I never try to explain or justify such
phenomena in my books. I see myself as a
realist, pure and simple.
The relationship between Europe and
Latin America has always been full of
unhelpful misunderstandings. Do you think
it's necessary to clarify the relationship and
to put ill feeling behind us ifwe are to reach
a new equilibrium between North and South?
The problems our continent faces are so
huge that they prevent us from seeing things
clearly, even though we are right in the midst
of the situation. So it's not surprising if
Europe, absorbed by the spectacle of its own
culture, lacks adequate means of understanding
us. The Europeans have inherited a great
rationalist tradition, and it is only to be
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
expected that they should constantly judge us
by their own criteria, without taking into
account the differences that exist at other lati¬
tudes. It's not surprising either if they fail to
see that the need for prosperity and a sense
of identity is felt just as keenly in Latin
America, or in Africa and Asia, as it once was
in Europe, and still is today. Even so, any
attempt to interpret one part of the world
using the criteria of another is bound to lead
to terrible misunderstandings, and can only
entrap people more deeply in alienation, soli¬
tude and isolation.
Europe should try to see us in the light
of its own past. It's as if the present imbalance
has made it lose sight of the vicissitudes of its
own history. Who remembers that it took 300
years to build a wall around London? That
Rome wasn't built in a day but over many cen¬
turies, or that it was an Etruscan king who
took Rome into the arena of history? That
Tenochtitlán, the Aztec capital, was bigger
than Paris when the conquistadors arrived?
Europeans of vision, people doing their
best to create a more just and humane society
across their continent, could really help us if
they changed their way of judging us. Any real
sympathy with our dreams and hopes should
take the form of aid for people whose only
ambition is to live their own lives in a world
where there is a real sense of human
brotherhood.
Why shouldn't the southern nations
attempt to copy the solutions the Europeans
are adopting in Europe, even if the conditions
and methods are different?
Do the problems come from inside or out¬
side the continent?
I think we have to stop pretending to our¬
selves that all the violence, misery and dissen¬
sion that afflicts Latin America is the result
of a plot hatched thousands of kilometres
away, as if we couldn't imagine any other des¬
tiny for ourselves than being at the mercy of
the global powers.
Confronted with inequality, oppression,
exploitation and neglect, our answer must be
life itself. Not even centuries of warfare have
dimmed its obstinate affirmation. Forty years
ago, William Faulkner refused to accept the
possibility that mankind might come to an
end. Today we know that what he feared is
a straightforward scientific possibility. Given
that terrible fact, and the knowledge that the
links between nations are stronger than ever
before and that a new era is dawning, I believe
it's not too late to build a utopia that would
allow us to share an Earth on which no one
would take decisions for other people, and
where people on the margins would be given
a fresh chance. A world in which solidarity
could become a reality.
It's an aspiration that is reflected in your
work, bound as it is to Latin America and
an awareness of its destiny.
That's right. I don't think one can live with
such a nostalgia, try for so long to describe
a country or understand a continent, without
feeling deeply linked to them, and through
them to the entire world.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
In June 1989, the three-master Messager de la ville de
Nantes left the Breton coast to sail to Dakar, Fort-de-France
and New York. On board were a dozen young people of
different nationalities, aged from twelve to sixteen. They
were joined by about fifty more on the island of Gorée,
offshore from Dakar, and a third batch boarded the ship in
the West Indies.
The children came from five continents, notably from
the regions of the South. The voyage had a twin symbolic
purpose: to retrace the old slave route from Africa to
America, and to permit joint reflection on the main articles
of a projected Convention on the Rights of the Child. At
journey's end, the children went to United Nations
headquarters in New York to present the Secretary-General,
Mr. Javier Pérez de Cuéllar, with a petition they had written,
requesting that the project, under consideration since 1959,
should finally be ratified.
The Convention, which was eventually adopted by the
General Assembly of the United Nations on 20 November
1989, fills a major gap, for hitherto children and young
people had no legal rights before reaching the age of
majority. This, moreover, is a time when growing numbers of
them are deprived of parental protection and the security of
a family, being literally thrown out onto the streets as a
result of wars, famines, catastrophes or population
movements. More insidiously, others suffer as a result of
economic changes which tend to destroy community
structures and marginalize the poorest and weakest sections
of society.
It is important that the international community should
give serious attention to the question of the global status of
children and should do its best to find a morally and
judicially satisfactory solution to the problems posed. In this
respect, the voyage of the Messager, undertaken by
youngsters many of whom had themselves endured years of
hardship, has great symbolic significance, especially since
the venture symbolically linked the misfortunes of today's
endangered children with the suffering of slaves in a
previous epoch. With the passing of the centuries, the
struggle to affirm human dignity has passed into ever
younger hands.
The UNESCO Courier's contribution to this theme takes
the form of case studies from different countries and an
analysis of the Convention on the Rights of the Child. The
articles were written by adults; illustrations by children
12 seemed the natural accompaniment.
In Dakar, one of the children who sailed on the
Messager de la ville de Manies
reads from the Convention on the Rights of the Child.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The right to be heard
by Michel Manciaux
The child's right to self-expression is now recognized by the international community.
How do things stand in practice?
'The child shall have the
right to freedom of
expression; this right
shall include freedom to
seek, receive and impart
information and ideas of
all kinds, regardless of
frontiers. . . .'
(Article 13 of the Convention
on the Rights of the Child).
IT may seem paradoxical to affirm the child's
right to speak and be given a hearing, for surely
a child is someone who does not know, cannot
speak and therefore has no say in matters. Etymo-
logically, the word infantfrom the Latin
infansimplies speechlessness. And even when
children do start to talk, adults often reduce them
to silence by telling them to be quiet.
The child's right to be heard is also to some
extent controversial. Many cultures forbid young
people to speak in the presence of their elders for
fear of showing lack of respect. The Nigerian psy¬
chiatrist Michael Durojaye has drawn attention
to the conflict between the rule of silence
imposed by family and clan and the encourage¬
ment of speech at school.
Nor is the right, in many cases, easy to exer¬
cise. The British sociologist Raymond Illsley
claims that children from underprivileged back¬
grounds often come into regular contact with a
vocabulary of no more than 300 words, many of
which have become distorted through use and
have lost much of their original meaning. This
language is quite different from that which the
school tries to inculcate.
So this is a limited right. There is, after all,
not much point in talking if nobody is prepared
to listen, and that is the lot of many children,
even in cultures that do not challenge their
freedom of speech. Adults preoccupied with so-
called serious matters simply may not pay atten¬
tion to the remarks or questions of the young.
"Be quiet!" "Later!" "Not now!", they say. But
as the Chilean poetess Gabriela Mistral eloquently
put it, children cannot wait, their name is
"Today".
"In the beginning was the word"
(St. John's Gospel, 1-1)
The biblical assertion that "In the beginning was
the word" may not literally hold true for children,
who do not have the power of speech in early
infancy. Yet even before the first vocalizations,
babies express themselves non-verbally. For
several decades now, child psychologists and
paediatricians have been detailing in their works
the ability of young babies to communicate with
parents and other adult carers through gestures,
glances, mimicry, smiles or tears, all of which can
convey a wealth of meaning.
If the baby, receives even a minimal response,
a real process of interaction gets under way, and
the ensuing exchanges can be an important factor
in the child's development, especially if they take
place in a climate of affection. France Straus has
shown that a baby only a few days old can
vocalize in response to the sounds its mother
makes, on condition that there is eye contact and
emotional bonding. Once the infant is making
baby noises, the first syllables are not far away.
Whatever the language may be, the noises are
usually taken to represent "Mama" or "Dada", to
the delight of parents who are thereby reassured
in their family roles.
The days when infants were regarded as glori¬
fied digestive tracts, requiring nothing more than
feeding, are long gone. But there is still much to
be done if they are to be recognized as people
in their own right and provided with the best pos¬
sible conditions for embracing the gift of
language.
"The development of language in childhood
remains an insoluble mystery", wrote the
Flemish poet Stijn Streuvels at the beginning of
the century. Although much still remains mys¬
terious about the gift of speech, his statement is
no longer entirely true. We now appreciate the
crucial importance of the child's linguistic
environment. Teaching children to speak involves
talking to them, answering their questions and
treating them with gentleness, patience and
affection.
Many children are slow to learn linguistically.
Sometimes the problem is undiagnosed deafness,
and a child's hearing capacity should always be
checked if there is any unexplained delay. More 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
When my world Is angry,
by Ari Sindu Prawlta, age 15
(Indonesia).
often, though, their linguistic development is
retarded because people are not talking to them.
Many parents fail to understand their children's
need for speech, and converse with them too little
or not at all. Others stick too long to baby talk,
which does not provide their children with the
vocabulary necessary for successful socialization.
The right to speech necessarily includes the right
to be considered worthy to be spoken to, and the
family's part in this basic process of education is
fundamental and difficult to replace. And this
second right subsequently entails another one-
being taught to read and write.
A good word is like a tree with solid
roots whose branches reach up to heaven.
It gives forth fruit in all seasons.
(The Qur'an, Surat XIV, 29-30)
What children say should always be listened to
with respect, if not necessarily followed. Their
constant questions and requests for information
deserve an answer, for that is how children
acquire new knowledge.
It is even more important to show consider¬
ation when the interests of the children compete
or conflict with those of the adults responsible
for them, for example in cases of marital break¬
down or divorce. Similarly, children should be
consulted on questions concerning their health
as soon as their age permitsand that can be
earlier than many adults imagine. The American
philosopher Dan W. Brock has rightly stressed
the competence even of young children to make
sensible decisions in this field, so long as they are
adequately informed and consulted.
Children, then, are often capable of finding
the good word of which the Qur'an speaks. It
is up to adults to listen to them if they want to
talk, to take what they say seriously and to accept
their right to express disagreement.
It is good to speak, and better to be silent
(La Fontaine)
The fabulist's maxim is sometimes valid, for chil¬
dren also have the right to be silent. For instance,
it is unfair to expect children to act as judges in
parental disputes that are painful to them.
However well-intentioned they may be, attempts
to get them to say which parent is right, or which
parent they prefer, may have a traumatizing
effect. Real respect for children and their rights
entails not overwhelming them with questions
and knowing which questions they should not
be asked.
Who will speak for children?
In certain cases children who are too young or
too involved in a situation whose ramifications
they cannot fully understand will need someone
to speak for them. The aim is not for this sur¬
rogate to replace them as individuals, which no
one can do, but to act on their behalf.
Who should speak for children? "A represen¬
tative or an apppropriate body", says article 12-2
of the International Convention on the Rights
of the Child, a vague formula which has the
advantage of leaving a great deal of latitude to the
signatory States. Some countries provide some¬
thing like an advocate in the legal sense of the
term. Others favour a mediator who acts as a kind
of children's ombudsman. Elsewhere the job may
be done by a parent, a relative or some other
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
adult, possibly a professional, whom the child
trusts. The main thing is to ensure that the child
has "the opportunity to be heard in any judicial
and administrative proceedings affecting the
child".
Nevertheless, the learning process must begin
earlier than that. The business of learning to
speak, without which the right to education does
not exist, must get under way in the first months
of life.
Mother says No, No, No.',
by a Norwegian girl, age 13.
"An extraordinary hope for human rights"
(Hélène Dorlhac, France's Secretary
of State with responsibility for the Family)
The United Nations Convention on the Rights
of the Child is a victory for all the world's chil¬
dren. It recognizes for every child "who is capable
of forming his or her own views" the "right to
express those views freely in all matters affecting
the child" (article 12 - 1), "the right to freedom
of expression" (article 13 -1), and "to freedom of
thought, conscience and religion" (article 14 - 1).
Article 17 underlines the importance of giving
children access, through the mass media, "to
information and material of social and cultural
benefit" to theman essential condition if they
are to express themselves in a manner that is well-
informed and free.
Education provides the tools of knowledge
and the child's right to education is solemnly
affirmed by articles 28-31 of the Convention. But
according to the details spelled out in article 28,
education only seems to begin with "primary
education compulsory and available free to all".
Schooling from an early age is obviously essen¬
tial, even though it is far from being achieved in
a world where, according to the preamble to the
World Declaration on Education for All which
was adopted at the World Conference on Educa¬
tion for All held at Jomtien (Thailand) in March
1990, more than 100 million children, most of
them girls, have no access to primary schooling,
and where almost one billion adults, two-thirds
of whom are women, are illiterate.
"Education for all, a priority for the planet"
(Federico Mayor,
Director-General of UNESCO)
The right to speak will remain a dead letter until
education from an early age becomes a fact.
UNESCO made this point forcefully at the
World Conference on Education for All. Article
5 of of the World Declaration states that
"Learning begins at birth" and that the "initial
education" can be provided "through arrange¬
ments involving families, communities or institu¬
tional programmes, according to need". It is a
good thing to highlight the all-important role of
the family. A child cannot have any real right to
speak unless this right is established and recog¬
nized early on. As well as being the first people
to speak for the child, the parents are also those
who can and must help it to learn to find and
freely use its own voice.
Parents are the prime movers in their chil¬
dren's education. Their power is very real, but
sometimes they may not be up to the job, either
because no one has helped them to develop their
capacities to help their children, because there is
no opportunity for them to use their skills or,
most seriously of all, because their power is
undermined by professional child-care experts or
by the society in which they live.
Failure to develop and use parental capabili¬
ties is a terrible waste. Helping parents to dis¬
cover, develop and apply their skills is undoubt¬
edly the best way of establishing their children's
right to speak.
MICHEL MANCIAUX
¡s a leading French specialist
in paediatrics and public
health, A member of the World
Health Organization's expert
committee on maternal and
child health, he is the author
of many scientific publications
including L'enfant et sa santé
(Paris, 1987) and Les
accidents chez les jeunes:
place de la recherche (1989). 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Children of the streets
by Flor Romero
Adrift in the world's great cities, millions of young people live, sleep,
and sometimes have children of their own
%
Untitled,
by Dolores Rocha Sánchez,
age 4 (Mexico).
16
FLOR ROMERO,
is a Colombian writer who has
published a number of
biographies, novels and short
stories. Crépitant Tropique, a
French translation of her novel
Triquitraques del Trópico,
features in the UNESCO
Collection of Representative
Works.
HO are they, the children who haunt the
streets of our big cities? Where do they come
from, those streetwise juvenile hippies whose
very existence municipalities do their best to
conceal?
Underage urban guerrillas, some people call
them. Self-raised, they live on next to nothing.
Street children have always been with us,
their presence recorded in such novels as Victor
Hugo's Les Misérables. What is new today is the
scale of the problem.
One hardly dares guess how many hundreds
of thousands of street children there are in the
world's capitals, swarming like flies around the
passers-by begging for hand-outs. They first
appeared in Latin America thirty years ago. They
made their entrance on the streets as shoe-shine
boys or newspaper-sellers, then never left, drawn
to the pavements as if by magnetic attraction and
unwilling to leave them to go home.
In fact many of them have nowhere else to
go. Typically they come from broken homes:
they are the offspring of single mothers, or of
wife-beating fathers who cruelly mistreat their
own families. Home for them is hell, a den of
poverty where there is little money for food and
even less to pay for school equipment or bus
fares.
Worn out by looking after the home and the
children, their mothers struggle to feed them, and
can only watch helplessly when they take to the
streets. Their fathers bring home next to nothing,
and their rage at working so hard for so little
makes their rule over the household all the more
brutal.
THE OFFSPRING
OF POVERTY
Abandoned children are the offspring of poverty.
Impoverished communities that cannot look after
their children simply leave them to the streets.
One would think that no society could have
any goal more important than to take care of its
young, to educate them and provide for their
future, to take pains to form them into citizens
healthy in body and mind. Yet that is evidently
not the case, since the problems of coping with
street children are often left to religious organi¬
zations and charitable institutions.
The grim truth is that the poorest developing
nations face so many other problems that they
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
have neither the time nor the means to protect
their young.
When Pope Paul VI announced his intention
to visit Bogotá in 1968, the city authorities took
it upon themselves, as part of the feverish prepa¬
rations for his arrival, to round up all the young¬
sters at large in the city's streets and lock them
in the Santamaría amphitheatre. They did not
want the Supreme Pontiff to discover that in a
Catholic country there were children wandering
the streets begging for bread and stealing from
shops, or simply looking for a newspaper or a
cardboard box to cover them for the night. They
wanted to hide the realities of Colombian child¬
hood from the Pope. At least they felt ashamed
of the situation, and that was something in itself.
ON THE STREETS
Anything from three to eighteen years old, these
ragamuffins wander the thoroughfares of the big
cities, importuning passers-by. Up to all kinds of
mischief, they heedlessly put off all thought of
settling down until they have grown up, when
they may change their ways but may equally well
persist in their delinquency, a course for which
their lengthy schooling in insolence and indolence
naturally prepares them.
It is instructive to strike up a conversation
with a Bogotá street urchin.
"Why do you keep moving around?"
"I have to keep moving, otherwise my
mother will find me."
"What do you want to do when you grow
up?
"Have lots of money to give to my mother
and my brothers and sisters."
Such children are always on the move. Tire¬
less vagabonds constantly en route from one
place to another, they scour the town hanging
from the back of buses. Most talk fondly of
their mothers; they want to protect them, to
console them for the loss of the fathers they
never knew or against the stepfathers who beat
The Junior Red Cross in
San Salvador,
by Mirtala Francisca Guevara
Zelaya, age 15
(El Salvador).
V 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Untitled,
by Mercedes Castillo,
age 13 (Guatemala).
them. As the conversation suggests, their greatest
ambition is often to support their mothers. They
talk of them as though they were saints.
"She came from Medellin," one of them
told me. "She used to work in a café, but she
didn't earn enough to feed us two kids. They
wanted her to have us adopted, but she refused.
She decided to come to Bogotá instead. I think
she and dad used to quarrel, and that's why
they split up after five years together. She met
Raúl Rocha here. He likes her, but I get on
his nerves. He used to tell me off or punish me
every chance he got. That's why I left the
house."
"I'm nine years old, and I've already been in
several reform schools," he went on. "At the
Redeemer, we used to call the streets lleca (an ana¬
gram of the word calle, Spanish for "street"). The
lleca is something else; it's our home. During the
day, we're on the lookout for the police, but at
night it's great. We sleep snuggled up head to toe
to keep warm. Me, I'm with the Grand Gautier
Vf* '"i«
mob. I feel safe and strong with them, I'm not
afraid of anything."
Street children cannot survive on their own,
so they naturally form gangs. They devise their
own special languages for protection, if not by
rearranging words then by a secret vocabulary of
gestures, cries, whistles or grimaces. They give
each other aliases so they won't be recognized:
Stoneface, Eagle Eye, Rat, Rabbit, never their real
names.
As agile physically as they are mentally,
they are extremely adroit, and can whip off a
windscreen-wiper or remove a tyre in the twin¬
kling of an eye. Their manual dexterity is
amazing.
Because chance rules their lives, they are
superstitious. There are streets they will not ven¬
ture into and words they will not utter. They do
not "work" on Sundays, because it's bad luck:
instead, they play football with their friends,
sleep, bathe in any pool they can find or go to
the cinema with their girlfriends, who are gener¬
ally street-dwellers like themselves.
"MY KIDS WILL GO TO SCHOOL
AND LEARN A TRADE"
For there are girls on the streets too, though not
as many as the boys. They sleep under bridges
or between sewage outlets, doing what they can
to avoid selling their bodies. They may have run
away because they had been punished, or to
escape harrassment by fathers, brothers, cousins
or uncles. But it usually isn't long before they
turn to prostitution.
Listen to the old newspaper seller: "Not that
one, not her". "Why not, if she's the one I
want?" the man replies. "Someone's looking after
her. Don't forget these girls have boyfriends to
buy them presents and take them to the cinema.
You shouldn't touch a gang-leader's girl."
Her cousin Theresa had already had two kids
by the time she was sixteen, and they lived with
her in the street. Two restless babies the street
children looked after, taking turns to give them
the bottle.
The girls are just as unruly as the boys, whose
behaviour they ape, but even though they beg
and sometimes steal they are less aggressive. Only
rarely would they snatch a handbag; more often
they are the lookouts, warning their companions
when danger is approaching.
They are more docile than the boys, and it
is easier to persuade them to learn a trade. You
can find girls who have left the street sewing,
embroidering, weaving or working as shop assis¬
tants. They try to get a regular roof over their
heads, above all to protect their children.
"I wouldn't let my kids go on the streets for
anything in the world," one of them told me
recently. "I'd make sacrifices, I'd work till I
dropped for them not to want what I never had.
My kids will go to school and learn a trade. You
can count on that."
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
by Carl Rogers
The tragedy of inner-city
youth drawn into
delinquency and drug trafficking
A HE 1980s witnessed the explosive resurgence
of an historic American urban social problem:
children and youth in gangs. From New York
to Los Angeles, from Chicago to Miami, over
forty-five American cities have an identified
youth gang problem.
The number of youth gangs in the United
States is on the rise and their involvement in the
drug trade is resulting in dramatic increases in
gang-related violenceincluding homicideand
arrests for criminal activities in almost every
American city. The scope and the nature of the
problem vary widely from city to city, but it has
been estimated that over 50,000 children and
youths are gang members in the city of Los
Angeles and that there are over 600 youth gangs
in California alone.
Popularized in "the 1950s musical West Side
Story, youth gangs have been a recurring social
problem in U.S. cities at least since the second
half of the nineteenth century. Their emergence
and growth, primarily in poor, urban neighbour¬
hoods, were frequently fuelled by successive
waves of immigrants arriving in the United States,
and were symptomatic of the problems these
groups encountered in trying to adapt to a new
and at times radically different culture. Today
many youth gangs continue to reflect the difficul¬
ties of assimilation of immigrant populations.
Youth gangs are usually defined as groups of
young people who frequently engage in illegal
activity on a group basis. They are usually ter¬
ritorial in nature, identifying with a particular
neighbourhood and protecting their "turf" from
encroachment by other gangs. Better organized
gangs often control economically motivated
crime such as burglary, extortion or drug-
trafficking at the neighbourhood level. They may
also sell "protection" from criminal activity to
legitimate merchants. Youth gangs usually iden¬
tify themselves by a name ("Crips", and
"Bloods" are the names of two Los Angeles-based
gangs), and may further distinguish themselves
by a particular style or colour of clothing, by use
of symbols, or by wearing certain kinds of
jewellery.
A MILLION DOLLARS A WEEK
FROM CRACK
The recent dynamic growth of youth gangs and
related violence is directly attributed by most
sources to the increased sale of cocaine, particu¬
larly in the form known as "rock" or "crack".
This lucrative illegal activity is helping to trans¬
form gangs into drug trafficking criminal organi¬
zations. In 1988 Los Angeles police officials
acknowledged that they were aware of at least
four gangs in their city grossing over $1,000,000
per week through the sale of cocaine. A recent
article in the U.S. magazine Time ironically noted
that the crack cocaine trade may be one of the
biggest job programmes for inner city youth in
the United States.
Drugs, by Ewa Szydtowska,
age 18 (Poland).
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Graffiti on New York
subway cars.
20
CARL ROGERS,
of the United States, is an
expert on child and family
issues. He serves as the public
policy liaison officer for the
American National Council on
Child Abuse and Family
Violence, a U.S. private sector
initiative for the prevention and
treatment of child abuse,
based in Washington D.C.
One reason why children become involved
in drug trafficking is that the laws governing
juvenile crime are more lenient than those
governing adult crime. Ironically, as the U.S.
"war on drugs" has intensified, with both
increasing arrests for drug trafficking and more
severe penalties for adults convicted of drug-
related crime, the value of youth gang members
has increased. While an adult convicted of selling
drugs in most states is subject to a mandatory
prison sentence of anywhere from two years to
life imprisonment, a young person under the age
of eighteen will seldom be committed to a cor¬
rectional facility for a first offence, and even if
committed is not subject to mandatory sentence
lengths. It has become both increasingly
profitable and safer for adult criminals to enroll
children and youths in the drug trafficking
business.
PEEWEES
AND WANNABEES
The average age of youth gang members con¬
tinues to decline. Most experts place the figure
at around thirteen to fifteen years of age, while
law enforcement officials in Los Angeles, Chicago
and other cities note that children as young as
nine or ten years are frequently found in today's
gangs. These young recruits, often called
"peewees" (slang for little members) or "wan¬
nabees" (slang for "want to be" gang members),
become casually involved with older gang
members who live in their neighbourhood, attend
their school, or are members of their own fami¬
lies. Initially, younger children may be asked to
perform "favours" for older gang membersto
watch for police in the neighbourhood, or to
deliver packages which may contain drugs,
money or weapons. In exchange, the children
often receive expensive gifts or money.
As they demonstrate their trustworthiness
and reliability, these children assume more
difficult and more dangerous roles. Children as
young as ten or eleven years of age are frequently
involved in gang-related drug trafficking. Younger
children are routinely employed as "spotters"
watching and reporting on police activity in their
neighbourhood to other gang members, as
"weapons carriers" for older gang members, or
in other roles, and earn anywhere from $200 per
week to $100 per day. "Runners", usually slightly
older children, may earn up to $300 per day
keeping street corner dealers supplied with drugs
from a hidden cache. Enterprising youths as
young as fifteen or sixteen may advance to the
level of street corner dealers, routinely earning
between $400 and $1,000 per day. In a particu¬
larly good market such as New York City,
authorities indicate that dealers can make up to
$3,000 per day.
Few dealers, however, work full time, and
two different studies in Washington, D.C. would
suggest that a street corner dealer's average
earnings are more likely to be in the range of
$4,000 to $7,000 per month. In contrast, most
states in the U.S. set a minimum employment age
of sixteen years, and most legal entry-level jobs
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
available to young people pay less than $40 per
day, or approximately $800 per month.
Once a child is involved with a gang, it may
be virtually impossible for him to quit. Gang
membership usually leads to truancy and ulti¬
mately dropping out of school, closing off escape
from a criminal lifestyle through education. The
gang member also finds it difficult to give up a
more lucrative lifestyle in exchange for unem¬
ployment or employment at minimum wage.
The gang member who attempts to quit is
also subject to social pressures to continue his or
her involvement. At best, attempting to leave the
gang may lead to social ostracism; at worst it may
lead to direct intimidation.
IMPOVERISHED INNER-CITY
NEIGHBOURHOODS
To truly understand the youth gang problem it
is important to understand the social context
within which the gangs emerge. First, they are
almost universally a product of impoverished
urban neighbourhoods, where unemployment
routinely exceeds 20 per cent of the workforce
and in some cases exceeds 50 per cent. Families
consist overwhelmingly of single mothers with
children and often rely primarily on public
assistance for their livelihood. Nationally, 20 per
cent of all children in the United States live in
families at or below the established federal
poverty level. In many inner-city neighbour¬
hoods this figure approaches 100 per cent. These
communities are characterized by generally high
crime rates, limited legitimate business activity
or employment opportunities, and poorly func¬
tioning public education systems.
In contrast to the phenomenon of street chil¬
dren in many Third World countries, or to the
problem of runaway or "throwaway" children
(children, usually teenagers, expelled from their
homes by their parents), most youth gang
members live at home with their families. Some
parents actively support their child's gang
involvement or are totally indifferent, but most
parents do care. Even the best intentioned parent,
however, can find it difficult, if not impossible,
to keep his or her child from becoming involved
with a local gang. Every neighbourhood has its
history of gang revenge against individual chil¬
dren or their families for resisting the gang. The
combined factors of intimidation on the one hand
and some financial support on the other eventu¬
ally result in tacit collusion on the part of these
parents. An uneasy truce develops where the
parent, while not condoning or supporting the
child's gang involvement, nonetheless does little
to try to stop this involvement and welcomes the
child's periodic financial contributions to the
family budget.
So far, the overall public policy approach to
this social problem has focused on three broad
strategies: suppression of drug use and drug
trafficking; suppression of youth gangs; and
prevention of youth involvement in gangs. To
date, while national statistics suggest an overall
decline in the use of illegal drugs, this decline
appears to have had little effect on the growth
of the gangs or on the frequency of gang-related
violence. Similarly, attempts at direct suppression
of the gangs through law enforcement activities
appear to have had limited effects, despite the
mobilization of extensive resources. It is argued
by many, however, that these efforts have slowed
the growth and spread of gangs. Alternatively,
some have suggested that efforts at gang suppres¬
sion through arrest and detention of gang
members actually lead to increased levels of gang-
related violence as other gangs compete for con¬
trol of territories once controlled by the sup¬
pressed gang.
Most experts agree that the only viable long-
term solution to the problem is to prevent chil¬
dren and youths from getting involved in gangs
in the first place. Most current programmes seek
to provide support for high-risk children and
their families. They focus on children between
the ages of six and fourteen, since it appears to
be generally agreed that prevention efforts must
begin before young people develop well-
established patterns of delinquent behaviour or
become seriously involved with gangs. Key ele¬
ments in many of these programmes include the
provision of social and recreational activities, and
educational assistance, as well as efforts to prevent
the children from dropping out of school and to
enhance their self-confidence and self-esteem. The
success of prevention efforts ultimately depends
on whether these children and young people have
a sense of hope in their own future and a belief
that through their own efforts they can lead
useful, productive lives.
Graffiti by Axone,
age 19 (Paris).
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Poverty and economic crisis, hunger and homelessness, epidemics, illiteracy
and environmental degradation are taking a terrible toll of the continent's youth
In November 1990 a seminar was held
under the auspices of UNICEF and
UNESCO at Cotonou (Benin) to discuss
the problems of children in difficult
circumstances. It was attended by
representatives of twenty African
countries and delegates of non¬
governmental and international
organizations who exchanged views and
experiences. The picture that emerged
from the discussions was distressing. Some
of its main features are sketched in this
extract from the final report.
TJLh
22
.HE vast majority of the street children are
boys. This does not mean that girls are not also
at risk, but their situation is different. Some turn
to prostitution at an early age. Others are single
mothers and face many material, emotional and
social problems. Others take jobs in domestic
service, or are sold into it, and are frequently
exploited or mistreated. So while girls may be less
visible than boys in the danger areas, their
problems are as great.
It is difficult to find out the exact ages of the
children concerned. Since they are illiterate and
have no family connections or identity papers,
the ages they give must be regarded as approxi¬
mate. Nevertheless, various sources of informa¬
tion suggest that their ages range from seven to
twenty-five years. In several countries, more than
half are aged between thirteen and eighteen.
Their backgrounds vary from country to
country and according to the category to which
they belong (young workers, street children,
unoccupied children from poor districts). Many
of them come from rural areas. This is the case
of the talibés, street beggars who complain that
they live far from their families. These children
can go for five to ten years without seeing their
home village.
Children who have never gone to school rub
shoulders in the streets with others who have
dropped out. The latter constitute the majority
in most of the countries represented at the
Cotonou seminar. Most of these children never
finished primary schooling, though some have a
few years of secondary education behind them.
Poverty is the usual reason for dropping out of
school, though sometimes poor grades are also
a factor.
To survive and feed their families, the chil¬
dren turn their hands to a whole range of activi¬
ties whose economic significance is usually under¬
valued. But the little money they make is not
enough to meet their needs, especially since much
of it often goes to their families, or else to their
guardians or a gang-leader.
BASIC NEEDS
Street children, like the children of the poorer
districts generally, are almost always ill-fed. Some
survive on barely one meal a day; others get by
on scraps from restaurants or by scavenging from
dustbins. In one group studied, the children used
drugs to suppress their hunger. Generally
speaking, drug use is quite widespread on the
streets, and it is thought that hard drugs are
becoming more popular.
The lack of hygiene in their liveswhich in
the case of those who beg may be deliberate, to
inspire pityincreases the chances that cuts and
scrapes picked up in the streets, where accidents
and assaults are all too common, will become
infected. It is hard for street children to go to dis¬
pensaries, partly because of the cost but also as
a result of their own embarrassment and the
reception they are likely to get. The young are
particularly vulnerable to sexually-transmitted
diseases, especially AIDS, about which they know
very little.
As far as education is concerned, "the chil¬
dren and young people on the streets are exposed
to a whole host of different and sometimes con¬
tradictory influences," said one participant in the
seminar. "This predisposes them to a disturbed
adult life, marked by personal and social
problems they never leave behind them,"
Children who have never been to school
generally want to go, and often go to great lengths
to achieve their wish. Most of those who have,
however, have grown tired of schooling. Like the
youth of the poorer quarters generally, many of.
the street children express a wish for some sort
of occupational training that would enable them
to work as drivers, welders, tailors and in similar
occupations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Giriama children pounding
millet, by Suril P. Patel,
age 11 (Kenya).
As for games, sports and leisure activities,
their needs are very poorly provided for. Many
seek refuge in the cinema, and what they see there
usually does little to help them come to terms
with the difficult world they live in. The lack of
leisure and sports facilities is yet another problem
confronting the children of the streets and slums.
THE POVERTY TRAP
"The causes of the tragedy," according to another
participant in the Cotonou seminar, "are many
and various. They include the economic recession
and the steady fall in the price of the raw materials
that form the mainstay of our economies, at a
time when the cost of the manufactured products
we need to import from the industrialized world
at our present stage of development has soared.
Reduced amounts of money are reaching us, and
as a result of high interest rates, merely servicing
our large external debts absorbs up to a third or
more of our export earnings. ... In short, we
have lower revenues and less to live on; we are
experiencing an accelerating downward spiral
into poverty."
Recent studies have shown that the
programmes of structural adjustment that various
African countries have agreed to undertake have
made things worse for the most vulnerable sec¬
tions of the population, whose purchasing power
is constantly falling.
Increasing poverty has forced some parents 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Carnival,
by Tolulope Adeyeuri,
age 13 (Nigeria).
24
to use their children as subsistence earners. There
is evidence that the number of street children
increases where there is high unemployment.
Child labour reinforces the vicious circle of
poverty, for most working children come from
impecunious families, whether in the towns or
the countryside.
Yet economic problems do not explain every¬
thing. The break-up of traditional patterns of
social and community life also lies at the heart
of the problem.
Many observers refer to the crisis in the
family, the reason most often given by the street
children themselves to explain their decision to
leave home. The growing number of divorces, the
increase in single-parent households and the des¬
truction of the old family structures are all
familiar themes in any analysis of the problem.
Another factor is the erosiondisappearance
might not be too strong a wordof traditional
African values, which in many cases has left a gap
that has not been filled.
The perception of the child's place in society
has changed radically. From being at the hub of
life in traditional societies, children have now
become for many families a means of survival,
their labour something to be farmed out and
exploited. As the bonds linking families, commu¬
nities and regions have been loosened, children
and adolescents have increasingly turned to street
gangs to find the love and friendship otherwise
missing from their lives. One young man made
the point eloquently when he said, "There was
only one place where I felt any solidarity, and
that was the street".
Some surviving customs that once formed
part of social and economic life only make things
worse today. Forced marriage at an early age now
contributes to the spread of divorce. The so-called
"geographical polygamy" practiced in African
towns creates tensions and often results in a lack
of paternal authority, creating insecurities in chil¬
dren for whom school does not provide the
framework of discipline they so badly need.
THE NEED FOR POSITIVE
THINKING
On top of everything else, these children have
an image problem. The disturbing idea that
people have of them makes it harder to reinte¬
grate them into their families and society as a
whole. So it is important to stress another aspect
of their lives: the range of skills they display daily.
They show great ingenuity in exploiting the
opportunities and resources of the street to earn
a living, and in so doing demonstrate much more
initiative than many adults locked into a daily
routine. In addition, they often possess manual
skills that would be the envy of apprentices in
any trade, and establish dynamic networks of
relationships that provide both solidarity and
mutual aid.
One underprivileged child employed in a
workshop making toys for day-care centres spoke
for all his peers when he told an interviewer: "I
don't know very much, it's true, but I can still
show someone else what I do. Then he could
show a third person if he wanted. That way,
you'd end up with no one left to say, T don't
know anything'."
Whether handicapped, abandoned or
orphaned, holding down a job or living in the
streets, these children seek the respect due to
people who count upon themselves and can in
turn be counted upon. They need to be able to
make some practical contribution to their family,
their gang, their village, their communityand
themselves. They want to have friends and families
and a normal love life, to be treated like anyone
else. In short, they want their place in the social
contract, along with the rest of humankind.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
by Ana Vásquez
The foundations of tomorrow's multicultural Europe are being laid in primary schools
across the continent
ÍE speak Arabic and French at home."
"At our place we speak Chinese with our
parents, but my brother and I talk in French."
"I've got a Spanish grandfather, and I've
already picked up a few words from him."
This conversation between Mohammed,
Paula Li and Véronique, three French schoolchil¬
dren not yet twelve years old, illustrates a situa¬
tion that is becoming increasingly common in the
schools of Western Europe's main urban and
industrial centres. In Liverpool and Liège, Got¬
tingen, Geneva and Lyons, changes in the so-
called migrant population are altering the tradi¬
tional nature of the school enrolment. With this
in mind, my colleagues and I have for the past
three years been studying the social interaction
between pupils, both French and foreign, in a
state primary school in a working-class district
of Paris.
WHO IS FRENCH
AND WHO IS FOREIGN?
What makes a child foreign? Of those considered
as such in the class we were studying, 70 per cent
were born in France and 85 per cent had attended
local kindergartens, and so, from the age of three
or four, had gone through the normal process of
socialization provided by the French school
system. As for the parents, most had lived in
France for at least ten years. This shows how
ambiguous the term "foreigner" can be. It is
always hard to know whether it refers to place
of birth, to family culture, to a value system
acquired in childhood, or simply to an uncons¬
ciously accepted set of stereotypes.
As Paula Li explained to her friends, she
speaks Chinese with her parents but French with
her brother. Mohammed speaks Arabic at home.
Both, in other words, continue to speak their
parents' language while also mastering French.
The same was true of almost all the children of
foreigners in the class. All but one of them (a girl
who had recently arrived from Haiti) spoke
French at school without any noticeable accent
and even when playing.
This situation had an effect on the children
whose parents were French, as Véronique's com¬
ment indicates. Her conversation with Paula Li
and Mohammed took place when the pupils were
asked to say what languages they spoke at home.
Véronique felt that she too ought to come up
with a foreign relativein her case a Spanish
grandfatherto show that she was learning
another language than French.
Her reaction is significant in two ways. First,
it indicates that speaking another language at
home is not necessarily demeaning. But it also
suggests that the issues raised are global, and that
the problem is not so much one of the integra¬
tion of foreign children as of a new situation
common to all young people, no matter where
their parents come from, in which questions of
ethnic identity and difference are everyone's
concern.
Who do these children play with and how do
My classmates as animals,
by Sylvia Voss, age 8
(Germany).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
they choose their friends? In the course of our
three years of observation at the school, the com¬
position of some of the playgroups remained
stable, but the children receiving the most
widespread acceptance or rejection did not stay
the same.
Ethnic origin was not the main factor in the
choice of playmates; other criteria influenced the
forming and breaking up of groups. The children
explained their choice of friends, whether for
play, study or discussion, in terms of likes and
dislikes, sentiments they could not clarify further.
Paula Li was voted the most popular pupil, and
Mohammed and another boy named Hubert
were the least. This was not the case at the start
of our study, when Paula was not very well-liked.
She was shy and uncommunicative but eventu¬
ally developed new qualities, notably a capacity
for study and a serious approach to life. The result
was that many children trusted her, not only
when it came to work or discussion, but also at
playtime, for she was scrupulously honest.
HOSTILITY TO FOREIGNERS
In the course of our study, we noted only one
case of aggressive behaviour towards a foreign-
born child.
The dispute took place between Hubert and
Mohammed in the course of a school outing.
These two pupils aroused the most negative
feelings among their schoolmates, and although
very different in personality both had serious
problems in relating to other people. Mohammed
was talkative and sometimes very funny, but also
anxious and often unstable. He could attract a
group around him, but then usually irritated the
others and reacted aggressively to their dis¬
pleasure. Hubert, on the other hand, was a loner,
reserved, unfriendly and often bad-tempered at
play.
The two began to squabble during a visit to
a museum. Both wanted to be closest to the guide
and the objects on display. On the way back to
school they started a fight over a seat, which
Mohammed eventually won. Hubert then began
to chant in an undertone racist slogans about
Mohammed the Arab, the foreigner, someone
stupid and ridiculous.
Their schoolfellows, half of them children of
foreigners themselves, seemed confused and said
nothing. Not knowing how to react, they simply
moved away from the disputants. Mohammed
lost his temper. After telling Hubert to shut up
two or three times, he dug himself down into his
seat. The whole episode only lasted for a few
minutes until the mistress in charge, realizing that
something was going on, came up to the group
and made Hubert shut up.
The incident was significant in several ways.
In situations where different ethnic groups mix
together, it is easy for interpersonal conflicts to
take on racist overtones. Offensive remarks of the
kind that were made are of course never harm¬
less, but in this case they served to mask the
difficulties in relating to others experienced by
the two boys, especially Hubert. Hurt,
Mohammed was incapable of defending himself
as he normally would have, whether by words
or blows. The attitude of the other pupils showed
how disturbing this kind of aggression is for chil¬
dren of their age. The only way they could find
of expressing their distaste was to move away. It
is also worth noting that the scene took place out
of the classroom, where the schoolmistress is
always in charge.
The teacher was aware of these problems, and
had often stressed, both in her lessons and in her
attitudes, the importance of respect for others.
In this case, she simply told Hubert to stop
chanting, and stayed close to Mohammed without
Children ot Mindo,
by Lusmira del Valdes Baeza,
age 12 (Chile).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
saying anything further. Back at school, she
neither reprimanded nor punished Hubert, but
she did change the work schedule so as to be able
to talk about the need for mutual respect between
peoples. She took time to speak of the cultural
and scientific achievements of the world's
different peoples, specifically mentioning the
Arab invention of algebra. Later in the year, she
also organized other activities with the same aim.
WHO AM I?
We also had to find out how the children see
themselves. Through games and questionnaires
concerning their qualities and defects, we
obtained several self-portraits of the pupils.
Knowing how adult immigrants react to this
kind of enquiry, one would have expected
national origin to have figured prominently in
the responses, and skin colour or the shape of the
eyes to have been seen as dominant physical traits.
Yet only one of the children mentioned ethnic
origin, and the same was true of skin colour, and
then only as part of a list ("I am: black, black-
haired, dark-brown eyes, I can run very fast.")
Néryal's drawing
(see article).
Even so, the influence of different cultures
did show through to some extent in the students'
attitude to beauty. Among the children of French
parents, it was the girls who called themselves
beautiful or said that they had beautiful hair or
eyes, while among those from North African
backgrounds it was more likely to be the boys.
There was not enough evidence, however, on
which to base a definite conclusion.
The qualities and defects the pupils consi¬
dered important reflected the same influence.
Some attributes were seen either as positive or
negative, depending on family background and
values. For some of the children the word
"patient" had good connotations, for others bad,
and the same was true for "obstinate", "ambi¬
tious" and "inquisitive". All the children consi¬
dered wearing spectacles a significant physical
trait, while other characteristics such as big or
small and fat or thin were often overlooked. The
conclusion seems to be that in a multicultural
environment ethnic origin is less important than
other traits in forming an individual's self-image.
DESIRES AND DREAMS
In order to understand how the children saw their
place in French society, we had to explore their
desires. We devised a drawing game in which the
pupils were asked to imagine a situation other
ft* frtft Yf>W&
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
than that familiar to them in daily life. By
requesting them to show their ideal of family life,
we hoped to gain an understanding of the ties
binding the foreigners' children to the land and
culture of their parents.
Confronted with real-life problems,
individuals often seek to escape into an imaginary
never-neverland. In the case of adult immigrants
© EH!
m / /.¿ 'lu 1«
lltRt
Paula Li's drawing
(see article).
28
ANA VASQUEZ,
Chilean-born French
psychologist, is currently
engaged in research with the
French National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS) in
Paris. She is the author of
many studies and essays on
the problems of exile and the
processes of transculturation.
(and foreigners in general), this usually takes the
form of the country they have left behind, seen
in an idealized light. The same holds true of inter¬
personal ties. There is a tendency to romanticize
the way things were before the old country was
left behind.
What we learned from the children, however,
was that, regardless of their place of origin, they
shared a common dream of a luxurious and exotic
retreat in which they could live like millionaires
on a permanent holiday close to nature. In their
ideas of happiness and their aspirations to greater
well-being and comfort, they all looked to similar
models, drawn in large part from the media.
Two drawings were especially revealing.
Paula Li showed her family in a huge, luxurious
mansion. While she played with her little sister,
her mother read and sunbathed by the swimming-
pool, her brother swam, and her father lay on
an inflatable mattress with a drink by his side.
Perhaps this vision of comfort and luxury was
shared by her parents, who both worked hard
and lived in confined surroundings.
A girl called Néryal was less specific. In her
drawing, the tip of a palm-tree sufficed to indi¬
cate that the scene lay somewhere far away, in
a tourist-brochure version of the tropics. But
there was nothing ambiguous about the way in
which she portrayed her family. Her sister dis¬
appeared entirely and Néryal, easily recognizable
by her spectacles, appeared as an only child. Even
more striking were the changes made to her
family, in real life extremely conservative in their
dress and style. She removed her father's
moustache and depicted him in tie and shorts, a
symbolic image of the ideal father on the perfect
holiday. The woman with him looked totally
different from NéryaPs own mother, indicating
how feminine role-models can change in the
course of long-term social displacement.
It would be wrong to conclude that the chil¬
dren had no interests or values in life other than
material comfort. Paula Li was one of the most
promising pupils in the class, and also, as we have
seen, one of the most popular. Néryal was a hard
worker who had made steady progress and she
talked of joining the medical charity Médecins
sans Frontières. ("I want to help poor people. .
. . Thousands of people are dying of hunger, and
I want to stop them from dying that way.")
Despite the fact that they had grown up in
a district where the foreign population was large
and mixed, all the children in the class had
imbibed the same values and role-models as
French children from the same background: they
did not consider themselves as foreign, or even
different. And their ambitions were centred on
the land where they now lived. Some of them
obviously could expect to encounter difficulties
in the course of their school careers, but they
would be the same as those confronting their
French counterparts.
More important than ethnic origin, the
lifestyle and academic level of the children's
parents, on the other hand, did appear to have
had a real influence on how well each was doing
at school. The children's own level of curiosity
and interest had also to be taken into account,
as did the amount of family support from which
they had benefited.
THE SCHOOL AS A PLACE
OF SOCIALIZATION
In France, the school provides all children with
a set of models and norms that contribute to the
socialization process and help new generations to
learn to live in society. For children whose
parents are French, the values expressed are
largely those encountered within the family,
although there may be some divergences . in
different social classes from what is taught at
school.
In the case of foreign children, the role of the
school is even more crucial. It is there that they
learn the language and become familiar with rou¬
tines and habits that form a kind of cultural
imprint, affecting such matters as rules of polite¬
ness, table manners, and the organization of time.
School also provides a setting outside the family
circle in which they can meet other local people,
both children and adults, French and foreign-
born. It is a place where the pupils can establish
social relationships of their own.
It is largely because they have spent so many
years at school that these children can succeed,
without too many shocks, in crossing the cultural
divide and participating in the social life of the
land in which they live. In many European coun¬
tries, this new generation of under-twelves is
laying the foundations of the multicultural
society of the 1990s.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Stress at an early age
by Tariho Fukuda
Angst, by Sabine Wagner,
age 13 (Germany).
NcI OBORU is an ordinary ten-year-old Japanese
schoolboy. His typical school day is much the
same as that of thousands of other children like
him. His mother Chiako wakes him up at seven,
saying: "Get up, son, your father is about to leave
for work." Noboru gets out of bed reluctantly
because he is still feeling sleepy, but he knows
he must greet his father, who had not arrived
home when Noboru went to bed at eleven the
night before.
His father, Takeo, who has been working for
an international company for many years, says
to Noboru as he is leaving:
"Good morning Noboru, how are you? Did
you study hard yesterday?"
"Yes. I think so, father."
"Keep it up and do your best. I'll see you
later."
When the stereotyped words of their
morning ritual have been spoken, Takeo closes
the door behind him. Noboru wishes he could
talk to his father more often, but he knows how
busy Takeo is. Even on Sundays he often has to
leave the house early to go and entertain his cus¬
tomers on the golf course.
Noboru has breakfast with his mother, who
asks him the same questions, wanting to know
who in his class at school and at the fyuku or prep
school he attends in the evenings got the best
marks in mathematics. She gets him so upset that
he refuses to answer.
AT HOME ALONE
In April last year Chiako asked her son if he
wanted to attend a good prep school not far from
home after regular school hours. Noboru
accepted, knowing full well that most of his class¬
mates were attending evening classes of this kind
in order to prepare for the highly competitive
entrance exams into junior high school. So for
the past year, four days a week, Noboru has been 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
going to evening classes and not particularly
enjoying it. But he also knows that his parents
hope that he will get into a good private junior
high school. If he does, he will not have to take
any other entrance exams before going to univer¬
sity. He tries to persuade himself that this, as his
parents have suggested, is the ideal solution . . .
but he is not convinced.
Noboru was surprised that his mother took
a job as an insurance agent when he began to
attend his Jyuku. Chieko explained that she was
working to pay for the extra school tuition, and
so now he feels more indebted to his mother than
Mother is always at me to do
my fessons,
by a 12-year-old (Norway).
30
TARIHO FUKUDA
is professor of social work at
Meiji Gakuin University, Tokyo.
A member of several Japanese
government advisory
commissions on children,
youth and the family, he is the
author of "Welfare for
Tomorrow", "The Japanese
Family" and a number of other
works.
ever. And no matter how much she insists that
the flexible hours enable her to spend more time
with him, the truth is that Noboru, like many
other Japanese children, returns to an empty
home when he finishes school.
When he gets home, he finds a note from his
mother which he glances at before throwing it
in the wastepaper baskethe knows what it says
by heart: "I put your favourite ice-cream in the
refrigerator. Be careful on your way to Jyuku.
Love, Mother." While eating his snack, Noboru
reads a comic book, watches television or plays
a computer game. When he cannot find the solu¬
tion to the game, he calls up his friend Fumio,
who has the same software. The two boys are
neighbours, but they would rather talk on the
phone than see each other because they attend
different prep schools at different times.
Before heading for school, Noboru spends
two hard hours on his homework both for
regular school and Jyuku. At about five o'clock,
he drops in for a light meal at a fast-food
restaurant where he meets up and chats with
some classmates before they all go on to school.
This is a rare moment when he can relax with
friends.
During the three hours of prep school, he
puts everything into his work, because whereas
at regular school the children are of different
levels, the pupils at Jyuku are all at the same level,
which makes it easier for the teachers. In addition,
the Jyuku teachers are specialists in the subjects
they teach, so that the work there is more
interesting, at least for the able pupils.
Noboru does not get home until nine in the
evening; he then watches television while eating
the meal his mother has prepared for him. But
the day's work is not over yet. His mother is soon
urging him to carry on studying until eleven.
This explains why foreigners visiting Japan
might be surprised to see children carrying
school-bags in the streets or in public transpor¬
tation at night. How did this situation come
about?
THE DEMANDS OF
AN INDUSTRIALIZED SOCIETY
For centuries, Japan was one of the most conser¬
vative societies in the world, with an apparently
unchangeable value system and static socio¬
economic and political structures. After the
Second World War, it unexpectedly became the
model of modernity. Although pre-war Japan was
a great Asian industrial power, in 1945 73 per cent
of the population lived in rural areas. In the next
twenty years, the ratio was reversed and today
80 per cent of the population is urban. Despite
its lack of natural resources, Japan is today one
of the world's most industrialized countries. It
has to import most of its raw materials and
manufacture highly value-added products for its
survival. The availability of top-level skilled
labour and advanced technology is vitally impor¬
tant for Japan.
One result of rapid urbanization was the
break-up of the extended family. The average size
of households dropped from 4.97 in 1955 to 3.1
in 1990 (2.3 in the Tokyo area), with 76 per cent
of households today constituted by nuclear fami¬
lies. The post-war birth-rate plummeted from 2.7
million in 1947 and 1948 to 1.2 million in 1990.
This means that Japanese couples are having
no more than one or two children. They love and
cherish their offspring, want them to be successful
in life, and, with the best will in the world, tend
to overprotect and expect too much of them.
They want to put their children on an escalator
that will take them to the top by trying to get
the best possible education for them, from kin¬
dergarten to university level. As a consequence,
entrance exams into private schools have become
highly competitive. Hence one comes across the
tragicomic situation in which infants are sent to
prep schools in order to help them to get into
good kindergartens! From the age of two or three
they have no free time to play.
DEVELOPING THE PERSONALITY
THROUGH PLAY
I have been involved for nearly fifty years with
child welfare in children's homes, hospitals, child-
guidance centres and mental hospitals in Japan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
We often use play therapy in the treatment of
problem children because we know that through
play children can express their feelings, their
impulses, their dreams and their fantasies, and act
out their hidden fears, anxieties, tensions and
uncertainties. If children were given more oppor¬
tunities to play freely, they would develop along
healthier and more wholesome lines and would
not need help from the social services.
Personality development begins at birth and
play has a considerable role in it. From this stand¬
point, I must confess that the situation of Japanese
children is very disturbing. They may seem
My father Is angry,
by Michiru Shioji, age 3
(Japan).
happy, they are well fed and well dressed, get a
good education and can play the most advanced
electronic games. Look more closely, however,
and you will see that they are deprived of time,
space and true relationships with their peers.
We are coming across more and more
problem children who are isolated, marginalized
and alienated at school because they have never
learned how to establish positive relationships
with others. I remember a teenager, Asako, who
could only answer yes or no when she first came
to my child-guidance clinic. For the first few
weeks I let her do whatever she wanted: read,
watch television, listen to music or paint. Then
one day she told me that she might be able to
express her thoughts in writing. So we began
exchanging letters. I suggested that she write
about her happy memories of her mother and her
early childhood, and she did this beautifully.
Asako had had a very harmonious relation¬
ship with her mother until she turned nine, when
her mother sent her to a prep school in order to
improve her chances of getting into a well-known
girls' school where only one out of twenty appli¬
cants was accepted. From then on, Asako had no
days off, no leisure time and no friends to play
with. Every Sunday she had to go to another prep
school to take a trial entrance exam for that par¬
ticular girls' school. "When she was accepted by
the school, the family was delighted, but soon
after that Asako found that she was incapable of
making friends with children of her own age or
of establishing rewarding relationships with
others. She confined herself to her study and
refused to speak to her parents, whom she held
responsible for her maladjustment. Finally, she
joined the growing ranks of Japanese children
who play truant from school. According to Edu¬
cation Ministry figures, there are about 40,000
"non-attenders" among junior high school chil¬
dren in Japan, while about 123,000 drop out of
high school altogether.
WHAT KIND OF FUTURE
DO WE WANT
FOR OUR CHILDREN?
Although the high-school drop-out rate is actually
only 2.2 per cent, I believe it is about time we
asked ourselves whether we want to provide the
kind of education we once did, that will turn our
children into physically, morally and socially
developed human beings, or whether everything
is to be sacrificed on the altar of achievement in
an advanced technological society that tends to
depersonalize all human relations.
Some glimmerings of a solution can be seen.
Japan has more than 3,700 community halls
where children can play and take part in creative
activities with play-leaders. At Children's Castle,
the national centre of these community halls, all
kinds of experimental activity programmes take
place for the wholesome physical and mental
development of the young.
Many youth organizations offer excellent
programmes where children and young people
can meet and get to know each other. Each year
about 170 child-guidance centres receive some
25,000 problem children, an increasing number
of whom are suffering from emotional and psy¬
chosomatic disturbance stemming from pressure
to achieve scholastic success and fear of failure.
When asked what would make them happiest,
most of them answer: "Good marks at school".
It is therefore urgent that our system of values
should be reappraised in terms of our future
society, the shape of which will depend on our
children. It is they who will transform our dreams
into reality. This is why, for our own good, we
should carefully examine the new United Nations
Convention on the Rights of the Child. When
all is said and done, our future welfare depends
on the happiness of our children. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The spoiled child
Are some children loved too much?
by Anne Rose
%
To sit in a small chair,
by Mike Batty, age 17
(Canada).
HEN people talk of ill-loved children, they
usually mean those who are loved too little or
not at all, rarely those who are loved too much.
It may be good news that, in some social classes
at least, adults now take an active interest in their
children, but even so the kind of relationship that
is developing still deserves some attention. Obser¬
vation of contemporary society suggests that in
many cases children have become a new kind of
god, sacred and untouchable beings so precious
that they must be preserved at all costs from life's
ups and downs.
32
In this context, "taking the child into
account" comes to mean making him or her the
centre of the parents' lives. Many couples say,
with the best will in the world, that their child
means everything to them, when the situation
should be the other way round: it is their job to
serve as guides and mentors to the child.
Children at least those who are wanted
often end up serving as alter egos for their
parents. They fill a gap. They are the couple's
greatest success. Who can say no to a little god?
Nothing can be refused to a child that has been
granted divine status. The parents will make
sacrifices rather than see their child's whims frus¬
trated. Some will change jobs, move house or
even divorce, all supposedly for the good of their
child. In return, of course, the infant is expected
to repay in the course of time the great expecta¬
tions invested in it.
Such a relationship, in which the parents are
at the child's beck and call, can be parasitical, con¬
cealing the parents' own neuroses. The
camouflage is all the better in that doting of this
kind is encouraged both by social consensus and
by commercial pressures.
You can see the childhood cult in operation
in the heart of our cities, near schools or on buses,
in public gardens or in restaurants. Its leitmotif
never varies. It goes under the name of "pro¬
tecting the child", but it might just as well be
called stifling the child's initiative and
encouraging laziness.
The parents' behaviour rests on two
presumptions whose consequences are question¬
able at best. One is that human beings should
suffer the least possible discomfort if they are to
grow up harmoniously, "harmony" being
defined as an absence of conflict rather than as
a balance of complementary forces. The other is
that a child's real needs correspond to its
expressed wishes, at least in so far as these accord
with the parents' own view of things. This of
course presupposes that children have no sooner
come into the world than they instinctively know
what is good for them. This extraordinarily low
view of human consciousness as a mere acting out
of instinct makes a fitting pendant to the con¬
trasting excesses of Victorian morality in the
nineteenth century.
Though this strange new morality purports
to be influenced by psychoanalysis, it in practice
contradicts its findings that children need a mix¬
ture of success and failure in getting what they
want. Occasionally frustrating children's wishes
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
moil'1 5/r/¿S/A|i55£ .'
Divorce,
by a 12-year-old (Norway).
ANNE ROSE
is a French psychotherapist
and anthropologist who is
engaged on a study of the
myth of woman and child in
the West today. This article is
inspired by an address given at
a seminar held at UNESCO
headquarters in January 1990.
can help them to develop by forcing them to con¬
front limitations, thereby enabling them to
handle similar setbacks better in future. The
ability to overcome disappointments is one way
in which youngsters can cultivate their own
individuality. Yet it is almost impossible to
encourage this dynamic process when the con¬
sensus is that the child must always get what it
wants.
The adult's role should be to help children
become adult. This is best done by teaching them
to confront reality, not to escape from it. When
well-meaning parents try to screen their children
from the outside world, they prevent them from
experiencing real life and so rob them of the
chance to map its ways.
Although it is necessary to talk to children,
the infinite patience some parents show in
providing endless explanations and humouring
even the most puerile utterances can actually
harm their offspring. It takes away their ability
to see reality in all its dimensions, leading them
to believe that life will always treat them with
kid gloves even when they are in the wrong.
Overprotectiveness can also deprive children
of a knowledge of the feel of things, giving them
instead a purely cerebral understanding of life. It
is one thing to know that certain things sting, but
quite another to have actually touched them and
been stung. Children of their own accord search
-p. ««'v-'- ;' ** \
for barriers and limits, which teach them just how
far they can go. If they do not find them, the dis¬
satisfaction caused by their absence will ulti¬
mately provoke a reaction.
Because our children no longer learn to come
to terms with the world, the sloughing off of
childhood that accompanies adolescence often
comes as an intolerable agony. The symptoms are
typically a deep depression mingled with cyni¬
cism and nihilism. It is as though adolescents were
exhibiting the hollowness of their own experience
of life for all the world to see. Having never been
touched by anything, they want to show that
nothing can touch them.
Adolescents of this type see the least sign of
opposition as violence against them. The raw
vitality of life is altogether too much for them.
Aware of an unfulfilled need, they thirst for a
love that will give a structure to their lives rather
than merely enveloping them, while also instinc¬
tively recoiling from any situation that might
expose them to the shock of the real. Caught
between aggression and melancholy, they no
longer have the strength to meet life head-on.
So social workers, doctors, psychologists and
psychoanalysts increasingly find themselves
dealing with a new kind of despair. Only this time
the young person's problems spring not from an
unhappy childhood but from a spoilt one.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The t survive
by Robert G. Myers
Twelve out of thirteen new-born babies now reach age one. What future lies
in store for them?
0,
My family,
by Bilgundi T.M. Tarkewada,
age 5 (India).
34
'ver the last three decades, extraordinary
progress has been made in reducing infant and
child mortality rates. Whereas five out of every
six children born in 1960 survived to age one,
twelve out of thirteen will reach their first
birthday in 1991. By the year 2000 the figure
could easily reach nineteen out of twenty. A great
deal of money and emotional energy will rightly
be spent during the coming decade in trying to
save the one child who is at risk of death. But
what will happen to the twelve out of thirteen
who survive? Who is concerned about their early
years? Who is looking beyond the mere fact of
survival to ask the question "Survival for what?"
Unfortunately, in their earliest months and
years most of these children will live in condi¬
tions that compromise their physical, mental,
social and emotional development. Through
neglect, millions of young survivors will be con¬
demned to lethargic, unrewarding, unproductive
and dependent lives.
And yet the Convention on the Rights of the
Child adopted by the General Assembly of the
United Nations in 1989 and ratified by 139 coun¬
tries, says that "States Parties shall ensure to the
maximum extent possible the survival and
development of the child" (article 6). It "recog¬
nizes the right of every child to a standard of
living adequate for the child's physical, mental,
spiritual, moral and social development" (article
27). Furthermore, the Convention urges signa¬
tories to "render appropriate assistance to parents
and legal guardians in the performance of their
child-rearing responsibilities", and to "ensure the
development of institutions, facilities and services
for the care of children" (article 18).
The Convention offers hope. It takes a com¬
prehensive view of development. It emphasizes
the role of parents (not just the mother), but also
recognizes the need for support for parents
through the creation of appropriate institutions.
It makes an explicit link between work and child
care. In brief, the rhetoric is good. But there is
a need to translate rhetoric into action. Where
do we stand in this process? Could we do better?
FLORINDA AND CARMEN
It is 7:00 AM and already the market in Huan-
cayo, Peru, is bustling. Florinda Quispe has set
out the baskets that she will try to sell. Tucked
in amongst them is her daughter, Carmen, aged
two. Now too big to be slung on the back,
Carmen must spend the day on the ground near
her mother, trying to keep out of troubleno
mean challenge. There is no child-care arrange¬
ment in the market. Other family members are
busy at other tasks. The skimpy sales will not
allow Florinda to pay for someone to watch her
daughter; she barely has enough to make ends
meet. So Carmen spends a great deal of the day
sitting unhappily, or being scolded for her inno¬
cent play.
Carmen's mother is coping in the best way
she knows how. But she needs support and that
is not forthcoming. Florinda does not know
about the Convention on the Rights of the Child.
If she did, she might be sceptical about its
meaning and intended effects. And yet that need
not be. Elsewhere in Peru, even in these difficult
times, there are promising initiatives providing
child care for families in need. Some of these are
associated with community kitchens in which
families group together to cook meals in
common, reducing costs, improving nutrition,
and providing opportunities for other joint activi¬
ties, such as child care.
Other programmes are linked to the forma¬
tion of women's groups. In Venezuela, Colombia,
and Ecuador, programmes of home day care have
been established, with local women who have
been trained in child care taking neighbourhood
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
children into their homes during the day. This
frees others to work and provides modest
earnings for the day-care mother.
In a village in northeast Thailand, Tisana
places her four-month-old son in a hammock
where he will spend a great part of the day. The
weight of the child brings the hammock together
at the top, making an almost closed cradle. This
practice leaves the baby with only the smallest
view of the home's thatched roof through the
narrow slit that remains open. Tisana knows that
she is protecting her child, bjut she is not aware
that she is depriving him of the stimulation he
needs to develop mental alertness.
Nor is Tisana aware of a programme in
another part of the Northeast in which home
visitors have been trained to support families in
their childrearing, encouraging those practices
that are favourable to development and helping
to change those that are unfavourable. A home
A happy childhood,
by Bianca Chiriloiu, age 11
(Romania).
visitor's simple suggestion of placing two sticks
between the cloth sides at the top of the ham¬
mock has provided other Thai babies with addi¬
tional visual stimulation and has helped to facili¬
tate development. The programme, in which
local mothers serve as home visitors, also includes
a nutritional component and attention to feeding
practices, both of which are helping to alleviate
undernutrition. But its benefits have not yet
reached Tisana and her baby.
THE PRE-SCHOOL
AT ABEOKUTA
At 10:00 AM, in an outlying area of Abeokuta,
Nigeria, a group of three- to five-year-olds are
barely visible to those who pass by on the main
road. Partially hidden behind an oil drum, a cot,
and an unusual collection of items for sale
(machetes, brooms, mattresses, cloths), twenty
children are squeezed on four small benches set
close together under a corrugated metal roof. In
the shadows in from of them, one child is
pointing to letters chalked on a disintegrating
blackboard. Just outside, a younger child, prob¬
ably aged two, with a distended belly suggesting
malnutrition, is idly dipping water out of a plastic
pail and pouring it on the dusty ground. No adult
is visible.
This "pre-school", with its makeshift locale
outside a combination store and home, is typical
of many such informal arrangements throughout
the world whereby people are trying desperately
to fill a void in the only way they know how.
Child care has been left to private devices for the
most part, but family members must work. Chil¬
dren do poorly in the first grades of schools, but
no institutions in the government or outside seem
concerned about their preparation, symbolized
in the above example by memorizing ABCs. The
young child with the distended belly, although
unattended, is much better off than many chil¬
dren throughout the world who are left alone for
long periods during the day, enclosed in small
rooms, sometimes tied to posts or pieces of fur¬
niture while mother goes off to work.
From one perspective, the Abeokuta model
provides a negative example of how to approach
pre-schooling. From another, it provides an
opportunity for governments and non¬
governmental organizations interested in the
improvement of early childhood development,
indicating a need and a willingness on the part
of families and communities to seek local
solutions.
LOOKING FURTHER
Intentionally, none of the above examples has
been taken from extreme conditions in which
young children are, for instance, suffering from
third-degree malnutrition in a famine such as that
which struck Ethiopia. Children in such special 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
circumstances require special treatment. Their
physical plight is more obvious and more likely
to be attended to. However, such emergency
treatment has tended to be short-sighted. Little
thought is given to what will happen to the chil¬
dren if they manage to survive. In many cases no
attention is paid to the social and psychological
stress and/or lack of nurturing and stimulation
that can permanently affect development. In these
more extreme cases, an extra effort is required to
look beyond the tragedy of the moment to longer-
term, more integrated and humane treatment.
Since the International Year of the Child
DROUGHT
ÍÍ ¿"(¿P*****
Drought,
by Zehra Zaidi,
(Pakistan).
age 9
36
ROBERT MYERS,
of the United States, is co¬
ordinator of the Consultative
Group on Early Childhood Care
and Development, which
gathers and disseminates
information about early
childhood programmes in the
developing world. He is the
author of Towards a Fair Start
for Children (UNESCO. 1990)
and the forthcoming The
Twelve Who Survive (Routledge
& Kegan Paul, London, 1991).
(IYC) in 1979, considerable progress has been
made towards improving the lot of young chil¬
dren at risk. Without doubt, the IYC generated
a new interest in this question. Many descriptive
and analytical exercises were undertaken at the
national level, intended to identify needs, to
create awareness and to mobilize people around
the idea of attention to "the whole child". Many
small-scale pilot or demonstration projects were
begun that marked a significant opening towards
nonformal programmes set within a context of
community development. Parental education
programmes were also begun, as were others
directed towards the care of younger children by
older brothers and sisters. At the same time, con¬
siderable energy was devoted to promoting and
expanding formal pre-schools. These efforts have
provided many cost-effective models that can be
drawn upon.
But the enthusiasm and the activities gener¬
ated by the International Year of the Child have
often withered for want of continued support.
Governments and international organizations
have been timid and tepid in their approaches
to early childhood. The economic recession of
the 1980s reinforced sceptical tendencies in
these organizations about the value of such
programmes. The emphasis on survival, narrowly
and medically defined, also distracted attention
from a broader and more integrated view focusing
on human development.
As a result, we can point to progress, but in
most countries:
coverage for identifiable, organized programmes
is still relatively low. This is particularly true for
sub-Saharan Africa.
Many projects and programmes continue to be
pilot or demonstration activities that are innova¬
tive, effective and capable of being replicated, but
have not been extended in a significant way.
The distribution of programmes, particularly
the more institutionalized ones, while improving,
often continues to favour the cities and to miss
children who are "at risk". (There are, of course,
exceptions.)
Reaching children before the age of three, and
particularly between the ages of one and three,
continues to be a challenge. Day care that takes
into account both the needs of children and their
working mothers remains at a very low level,
both in extension and in quality..
Programmes of support and education for
parents have grown dramatically in some coun¬
tries but are virtually nonexistent in others, par¬
ticularly with respect to the psychosocial com¬
ponents of early development. And there is a ten¬
dency in these programmes to impose, rather
than to reconstruct and expand knowledge.
Often the quality of the programmes is poor,
so that the effects on children are minimal. The
combining of elements of integrated attention to
the child remains a challenge, despite some suc¬
cesses and an increasing awareness of the
problems.
THE ALL-IMPORTANT
EARLY YEARS
The Convention on the Rights of the Child pro¬
vides us with an opportunity to pay greater atten¬
tion to the early years in programmes addressed
directly to children, in programmes of parental
education and support, and in community
development projects that have effects on the
child.
The arguments in favour of social investment
are compelling. The need and demand are
widespread and growing. Although some progress
has been made, we are at a very early stage and
much remains to be done, not only for children
in exceptional circumstances but for those who
endure the "normal" day-to-day effects of grinding
poverty. We have examples to draw upon. The
cost need not be high. There is little reason why
we cannot do a better job than we are doing to
improve early childhood development.
- Let us hope that the Convention will help
give the signatory nations, and perhaps others,
additional force to dedicate the resources and
energy needed for the sound development of the
twelve who survive. It is they who will be the
leaders and builders and creators of our world in
the twenty-first century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Child labour in the world today
G/HILD labour in today's world is over¬
whelmingly concentrated in three eco¬
nomic sectorsagriculture, the so-called
"urban informal" sector, and domestic
service. In each of these sectors children
are badly exploited, and none of the three
has been effectively penetrated by
mechanisms for containing child labour
and the abuses associated with it.
The agricultural trap
Today as in the past most of the world's
working children are employed in
agriculture. It is tempting to imagine
them working at traditional tasks under
the benevolent eye of parents who want
to provide them with the skills they
will need in adult life. Their environment
is often assumed to be physically and psy¬
chologically healthier than that of city
children. This bucolic vision reflects the
romantic notions of city-dwellers who
have little direct experience of rural
poverty and does not correspond to the
facts.
All over the world, the industrializa-
Difficulty, by Jeeranat Madee, age 13 (Thailand).
tion of agriculture is changing the struc¬
ture of production, and with it the way
rural families earn their living. More and
more country dwellers are working for
other people, because they have either no
land of their own or not enough to sup¬
port themselves.
Agricultural work is often organized
in such a way that children work as long
and hard as their parents in order to en¬
sure family survival. In some places adults
are only employed on condition that
their children help as well. This is one
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
reason why rural working children are es¬
pecially likely to be unschooled and il¬
literate. The protection their families can
provide is strictly limited.
With the modernization of agricul¬
tural technology, even children working
on family farms are now exposed to dan¬
gerous machinery and chemicals
unknown only a few years ago. Controls
on hazardous insecticides and herbicides
are generally weak, and as a rule neither
children nor their families are taught how
to handle safely even the most widely-
used machinery and products. In many
countries there is growing concern about
the accident rate among child agricultur¬
al workers.
It is worth noting that rates of child
mortality, illness, malnutrition, disabili¬
ty and illiteracy are almost everywhere
substantially higher in rural than in ur¬
ban areas. Many of the exploited children
found in the cities have fled there from
the countryside or been sent there be¬
cause the situation was desperate at home.
In the coming years rural children
will come under greater pressure because
of the rapid restructuring of world
agriculture. Many will end up vulnerable
to exploitation, whether in impoverished
rural communities or in the overbur¬
dened cities to which they migrate. The
pawns of social forces that they cannot
control and do not understand, these chil¬
dren have few options. They constitute
a young and vulnerable workforce for the
two other problem areas.
The informal sector
The term "informal sector" is generally
used to designate relatively small un¬
registered enterprises which typically are
exempted from, or not covered by, regu¬
lations governing larger businesses.
Although it exists everywhere, the infor¬
mal sector is particularly large and
vigorous in urban areas. Its vitality has
only recently been recognized, and in
many countries today it is expanding
rapidly, sometimes with government en¬
couragement. In some industrialized
countries and in most developing nations
the informal sector is a major engine of
growth and accounts for as much as a
third or more of all economic activity.
Fed by migration from the country¬
side and the increasing decentralization of
38 production, it is already the fastest-
growing area of child labour employ¬
ment. By the beginning of the next cen¬
tury it could well overtake agriculture as
the principal area of child labour. In most
cities it already encompasses the vast
majority of children who work outside
the home to earn a little money or their
keep.
Children often participate in the in¬
formal sector as employees of enterprises
such as brickmaking, construction, han¬
dicrafts and food services. Some of these
occupations are among the most danger¬
ous in which children are engaged, and
many of the cruellest child labour abuses
that have been documented are in this
sector.
Children working in brickyards car¬
ry heavy loads that can leave them
weakened, injured or deformed. In carpet-
weaving workshops they can ruin their
eyesight and damage their limbs and
backs. Young pencil-makers, who
manufacture pencils other children use at
school, breathe in hazardous slate dust
that can condemn them to early disabili¬
ty and death from lung disease. Many
similar examples could be cited, all of
which have long been recognized and
condemned.
These situations still persist, for one
thing because many countries exempt
small and family-run businesses from the
provisions of their child-labour laws,
despite the fact that most employed chil¬
dren work in businesses of this kind.
Another problem is that labour enforce¬
ment systems are overstretched and can
barely even meet their commitments in
the formal sector.
Some city children work on their
own account. Most of them practice
street trades such as hawking, shining
shoes, washing cars, even prostitution.
Numerous countries and cities have laws
prohibiting their activities, but they have
proved difficult to enforce, and their wis¬
dom is in any case doubtful. Labour in¬
spection is an impractical approach to this
sort of work, and other means are re¬
quired to protect these children from the
violence, exploitation and abuse they fre¬
quently encounter.
Domestic servitude
Youngsters working as domestic servants
may be the most exploited of all, and the
most difficult to protect, particularly if
they live in the homes of their employ¬
ers. Their numbers are thought to be
huge, particularly in Africa, Asia and La¬
tin America, but it has proved virtually
impossible to count them. The vast
majority are girls, frequently pré¬
adolescents, who live with and are utter¬
ly dependent on their employers. Inves¬
tigators believe that the number of
children in domestic service is growing
in some regions, in response to increas¬
ingly desperate poverty and the unwill¬
ingness of adult women to do this work
in such bad conditions.
Sometimes children are placed by im¬
poverished parents with relatives or ac¬
quaintances on the understanding that the
latter will support and educate the child
in return for its labour. In other cases the
child is hired out for wages, typically paid
largely or even entirely to the parents.
Some parents simply sell their children
into bondage for cash.
"When such a sale is to an agent rather
than directly to the final employer, par¬
ents and child may lose contact perma¬
nently. Some children are unwittingly
sold in this way into forced prostitution.
It is possible that many child domes¬
tic workers are reasonably well treated by
their employers. Even so, they are utterly
at the latters' mercy, and therefore high¬
ly vulnerable to abuse. Typically they are
expected to work long hours, often with
no regular days off. Even though most
work in relatively well-to-do homes,
many are malnourished. They are not al¬
lowed to eat the family food even when
they cook it, and are provided with
neither room nor bed, commonly sleep¬
ing on the kitchen floor.
Sexual abuse by members of the
household is said to be common, and var¬
ious investigators also suspect a high in¬
cidence of physical abuse. It is doubtful
whether many of these children of school
age are permitted to attend educational
institutions on a regular basis.
Domestic servants are vulnerable in
many ways. They are open to abuse be¬
cause of their age, their sex, their confine¬
ment, their invisibility to the outside
world, their total dependence on their
employers, and often their lack of
familiarity with the world beyond the
doorstep.
Source: Still so far to go: Child labour in the world
today. International Labour Organisation, Geneva,
1989.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The
The Convention on the Rights of the Child
has been described as a Magna Carta for
children. It has fifty-four articles detailing
the individual rights of any person under
eighteen years of age to develop his or her
full potential, free from hunger and want,
neglect, exploitation or other abuses.
The outcome of ten years of
negotiations, the Convention was adopted
by the United Nations on 20 November
1989 and entered into force on 2
September 1990 after being ratified by
twenty States. So far 139 countries have
either signed the Convention or have
become States Parties to it by ratification
or accession*. When ratified by a State,
the Convention becomes binding law in it.
A Committee of ten experts will monitor
compliance in the States Parties to the
Convention.
The Convention goes beyond previously
existing instruments by seeking to balance
the rights of the child with the rights and
duties of parents or others who have
responsibilities for child survival,
development and protection, and by giving
the child the right to participate in
decisions affecting both the present and
the future.
Among the pressing issues addressed,
some of which appear for the first time in
an international convention, are obligations
to children in particularly difficult
circumstances, such as the needs of
refugee children (article 22), protection
from sexual and other forms of child
exploitation (articles 34 and 36), drug
abuse (article 33), children in trouble with
the law (article 40), inter-country
adoptions (article 35), children in armed
conflicts (articles 38 and 39), the needs of
disabled children (article 23), and the
children of minority and indigenous groups
(article 30).
Education is the subject of two major
articles (27 and 28), which were reinforced
by the World Conference on Education for
All, held at Jomtien (Thailand) from 5 to 9
March 1990. Primary education is to be
compulsory, free to all, and should be
directed to the development of a child's
personality, talents and natural abilities,
with due respect for cultural identity,
language and values. Stress is placed on
equality of educational opportunity for girls
and boys.
The inherent strength of the new
Convention lies in its flexibility, its
capacity to accommodate the many
different approaches of nations in pursuit
of a common goal. It has not evaded
sensitive issues, but has found means to
adjust to the different cultural, religious
and other values which address universal
child needs in their own ways.
Below is a summary of the main
provisions of the Convention.
* As of 25 July 1991. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
THE MMN PROVISIONS OF THE CONVENTION
Preamble
The preamble recalls the basic principles of
the United Nations and specific provisions
of certain relevant treaties and proclama¬
tions. It reaffirms the fact that children,
because of their vulnerability, need special
care and protection, and places special
emphasis on the primary caring and protec¬
tive responsibility of the family.
It also reaffirms the need for legal and
other protection of the child before and
after birth, the importance of respect for the
. cultural values of the child's community,
and the vital role of international co¬
operation in securing children's rights.
Definition of a child
(art. 1)
A child is recognized as a person under 18,
unless national laws recognize the age of
majority earlier.
Non-discrimination
(art. 2)
All rights apply to all children without
exception. It is the State's obligation to pro¬
tect children from any form of discrimina¬
tion and to take positive action to promote
their rights.
Best interests of the child
(art. 3)
All actions concerning the child shall take
full account of his or her best interests. The
State shall provide the child with adequate
care when parents, or others charged with
40 that responsibility, fail to do so.
Nursing victims of an earthquake,
by Ayan Chatterjee, age 7 (India).
Implementation of rights (art. 4)
The State must do all it can to implement
the rights contained in the Convention.
Parental guidance and the child's
evolving capacities (art. 5)
The State must respect the rights and
responsibilities of parents and the extended
family to provide guidance for the child
which is appropriate to her or his evolving
capacities.
Survival and development
(art. 6)
Every child has the inherent right to life,
and the State has an obligation to ensure the
child's survival and development.
Name and nationality (art. 7)
The child has the right to a name at birth.
The child has also the right to acquire a
nationality and, as far as possible, to know
his or her parents and be cared for by them.
Preservation of identity (art. 8)
The State has an obligation to protect, and
if necessary re-establish, basic aspects of the
child's identity. This includes name, nation¬
ality and family ties.
Separation from parents
(art. 9)
The child has a right to live with his or her
parents unless this is deemed incompatible
with the child's best interests. The child also
has the right to maintain contact with both
parents if separated from one or both.
Family reunification (art. 10)
Children and their parents have the right
to leave any country and to enter their own
for purposes of reunion or the maintenance
of the child-parent relationship.
Illicit transfer and non-return (art. 1 1)
The State has an obligation to prevent and
remedy the kidnapping or retention of chil¬
dren abroad by a parent or third party.
The child's opinion (art. 12)
The child has the right to express his or her
opinion freely and to have that opinion
taken into account in any matter or proce¬
dure affecting the child.
Freedom of expression (art. 13)
The child has the right to express his or her
views, obtain information, make ideas or
information known, regardless of frontiers.
Freedom of thought, conscience
and religion (art. 14)
The State shall respect the child's right to
freedom of thought, conscience and
religion, subject to appropriate parental
guidance.
Freedom of association (art. 15)
Children have a right to meet with others,
and to join or form associations.
Protection of privacy (art. 16)
Children have the right to protection from
interference with their privacy, family,
home and correspondence, and from libel
or slander.
Access to appropriate information
(art. 17)
The State shall ensure that information and
material from a diversity of sources is acces¬
sible to children, and it shall encourage the
mass media to disseminate information
which is of social and cultural benefit to the
child, and take steps to protect him or her
from harmful materials.
Parental responsibilities (art. 18)
Parents have joint primary responsibility
for raising the child, and the State shall sup¬
port them in this. The State shall provide
appropriate assistance to parents in child-
raising.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Protection from abuse and neglect
(art. 19)
The State shall protect the child from all
forms of maltreatment by parents or others
responsible for the care of the child and
establish appropriate social programmes for
the prevention of abuse and the treatment
of victims.
Protection of a child without family
(art. 20)
The State is obliged to provide special pro¬
tection for a child deprived of the family
environment and to ensure that appropriate
alternative family care or institutional place¬
ment is available in such cases. Efforts to
meet this obligation shall pay due regard to
the child's cultural background.
Adoption
(art. 21)
In countries where adoption is recognized
and/or allowed, it shall only be carried out
in the best interests of the child, and then
only with the authorization of competent
authorities, and with safeguards for the
child.
Refugee children
(art. 22)
Special protection shall be granted to a
refugee child or to a child seeking refugee
status. It is the State's obligation to co¬
operate with competent organizations
which provide such protection and
assistance.
Disabled children
(art. 23)
A disabled child has the right to special care,
education and training to help him or her
enjoy a full and decent life in dignity and
achieve the greatest degree of self-reliance
and social integration possible.
Jumping onto the see-saw at Harvest
Thanksgiving, by Chang Hua-Jung,
age 12 (Korea).
Health and health services
(art. 24)
The child has a right to the highest standard
of health and medical care attainable. States
shall place special emphasis on the provi¬
sion of primary and preventive health care,
public health education and the reduction
of infant mortality. They shall encourage
international co-operation in this regard and
strive to see that no child is deprived of
access to effective health services.
Periodic review of placement
(art. 25)
A child who is placed by the State for
reasons of care, protection or treatment is
entitled to have that placement evaluated
regularly.
Me going to school,
by Mailin Bedoya Rivero,
age 9 (Cuba).
Social security
(art. 26)
The child has the right to benefit from
social security including social insurance.
Standard of living
(art. 27)
Every child has the right to a standard of
living adequate for his or her physical,
mental, spiritual, moral and social develop¬
ment. Parents have the primary responsi¬
bility to ensure that this responsibility can
be fulfilled, and is. State responsibility can
include material assistance to parents and
their children.
Education
(art. 28)
The child has a right to education, and the
State's duty is to ensure that primary edu¬
cation is free and compulsory, to encourage
different forms of secondary education
accessible to every child and to make higher
education available to all on the basis of
capacity. School discipline shall be consis¬
tent with the child's rights and dignity. The
State shall engage in international co¬
operation to implement this right.
Aims of education
(art. 29)
Education shall aim at developing the
child's personality, talents and mental and
physical abilities to the fullest extent. Edu¬
cation shall prepare the child for an active
adult life in a free society and foster respect
for the child's parents, his or her own cul¬
tural identity, language and values, and for
the cultural background and values of
others. 41
A<VK
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Children of minorities or
indigenous populations
(art. 30)
Children of minority communities and
indigenous populations have the right to
enjoy their own culture and to practise their
own religion and language.
Leisure, recreation and cultural
activities
(art. 31)
The child has the right to leisure, play and
participation in cultural and artistic activities.
Child labour
(art. 32)
The child has the right to be protected from
work that threatens his or her health, edu¬
cation or development. The State shall set
minimum ages for employment and regu¬
late working conditions.
Drug abuse
(art. 33)
Children have the right to protection from
the use of narcotic and psychotropic drugs,
and from being involved in their produc¬
tion or distribution.
Sexual exploitation
(art. 34)
The State shall protect children from sexual
exploitation and abuse, including prostitu¬
tion and involvement in pornography.
Sale, trafficking and abduction
(art. 35)
It is the State's obligation to make every
effort to prevent the sale, trafficking and
abduction of children.
Make peace, not war, by Mihir Desai
age 5 (Mauritius).
Other forms of exploitation
(art. 36)
The child has the right to protection from
all forms of exploitation prejudicial to any
aspects of the child's welfare not covered
in articles 32, 33, 34 and 35.
Torture and deprivation of liberty
(art. 37)
No child shall be subjected to torture, cruel
treatment or punishment, unlawful arrest
or deprivation of liberty. Both capital
punishment and life imprisonment without
the possibility of release are prohibited for
offences committed by persons below 18
years. Any child deprived of liberty shall
be separated from adults unless it is consi¬
dered in the child's best interests not to do
so. A child who is detained shall have legal
and other assistance as well as contact with
the family.
Armed conflicts
(art. 38)
States Parties shall take all feasible measures
to ensure that children under 15 years of
age play no direct part in hostilities. No
child below 15 shall be recruited into the
armed forces. States shall also ensure the
protection and care of children who are
affected by armed conflict as described in
relevant international law.
Rehabilitative care
(art. 39)
The State has an obligation to ensure that
child victims of armed conflicts, torture,
neglect, maltreatment or exploitation
receive appropriate treatment for their
recovery and social reintegration.
Administration of juvenile justice
(art. 40)
A child in conflict with the law has the right
to treatment which promotes the child's
sense of dignity and worth, takes the child's
age into account and aims at his or her rein¬
tegration into society. The child is entitled
to basic guarantees as well as legal or other
assistance for his or her defence. Judicial
proceedings and institutional placements
shall be avoided wherever possible.
Respect for higher standards
(art. 41)
Wherever standards set in applicable
national and international law relevant to
the rights of the child are higher than those
in this Convention, the higher standards
shall always apply.
Implementation and entry into force
(arts. 42 to 54)
The provisions of articles 42-54 notably
foresee:
1) the State's obligation to make the rights
contained in this Convention widely
known to both adults and children.
2) the setting up of a Committee on the
Rights of the child composed of ten experts,
which will consider reports that States Par¬
ties to the Convention are to submit two
years after ratification and every five years '
thereafter. The Convention enters into
forceand the Committee would therefore
be set uponce 20 countries have ratified it.
3) States Parties are to make their reports
widely available to the general public.
4) The Committee may propose that spe¬
cial studies be undertaken on specific issues
relating to the rights of the child, and may
make its evaluations known to each State
Party concerned as well as to the UN
General Assembly.
5) In order to "foster the effective
implementation of the Convention and to
encourage international co-operation", the
specialized agencies of the UN (such as the
ILO, WHO, and UNESCO) and UNICEF
will be able to attend the meetings of the
Committee. Together with any other body
recognized as "competent", including
NGOs in consultative status with the UN
and UN organs such as the UNHCR, they
can submit pertinent information to the
Committee and be asked to advise on the
optimal implementation of the Convention.
42 Source: United Nations Centre for Human Rights and
> UNICEF
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
¿¿
A mirror for childhood
In the cinema, children seek an image of their own condition
lYlosT films about the young portray
childhood as a perpetual act of defiance
directed at the indifference and contempt of
the adult world. On screen, two camps-
children and grown-upsconfront one
another, though with occasional attempts at
reconciliation and understanding. The young¬
sters must struggle constantly to have their
rights and status recognized.
To understand why, one must go back to
events that predate the invention of cinema.
According to the French historian Philippe
by François Valet
Above, a scene from 300 mil do nieba,
a film by the Polish director Maciej Dejczer.
Ariès, "A considerable change in manners
took place from the end of the seventeenth
century".1 Previously children had lived in
the heart of the community. They learned
from teachers or from tradesmen or master
craftsmen to whom they were apprenticed,
sharing their work and worries but also the
world of the imagination, festivals and games.
Compare this fluid world of free exchange
and shared identity with the current situation,
in which children are pigeon-holed into school
and the family unit. Our century has seen 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
adults lose childhood from their lives, and
with it has gone a part of their soulsmaybe
the most important one.
Because of the wall that now separates
childhood from the adult world, children have
become mysterious to their elders, incompre¬
hensible, almost alien creatures. The result is
that young people have turned to cinema to
find their own self-image. Adults who wish
to help them must first break down the walls
separating the two communities.
Lonely and
misunderstood
Usually it is within the family unitwhat we
now call the "nuclear family"that children's
alienation becomes most disturbingly
apparent. Their isolation is dramatically
reflected in such works as François Truffaut's
Les Quatre Cents Coups (France, 1959) and
Robert Benton's Kramer versus Kramer
(U.S.A., 1979), which depict the effects of a
broken marriage. The children in these films
are truly "misunderstood", to borrow the title
of Luigi Comencini's masterpiece Incompreso
(Italy, 1966).
Another class of film depicts children
struggling against the established order at
school or in other institutions that prove
incapable of meeting their emotional demands.
These children are often shown trapped in a
kind of limbo, cut off from an adult world that
they cannot share and with which they are not
even able to identify.
Feeling unloved, they are tempted to
make a getaway which brings them a brief
taste of freedom. Sometimes they run away
to find a father figure. A similar quest provides
the plot of Jacques Doillon's Le Petit Criminel
(France, 1990), though in that case the search
is for an elder sister whom the main character
has never seen. Whatever their object, these
childhood odysseys can be alarming, as the
two young Polish protagonists of Marcel
Dejczer's 300 mil do nieba (Poland, 1990) find
out to their cost.
Children of institutions and the nuclear
family, all these rebels reject the persona
imposed on them by the adult world via
changes in social customs. Because the condi¬
tion of childhood as we now know it is a
product of the familya purely adult
inventionchildren in response feel the need
to invent themselves, to create their own
image. In this respect, cinema becomes not so
much a mirror of childhood as the search for
a mirror, in which the child's true quest is to
discover him- or herself.
44
Four scenes from recent films
about children.
Above: Pixote, directed by
Hector Babenco.
Below, left: Halfaouine,
l'enfant des terrasses,
directed by Ferid Boughedir.
Above, right: Salaam Bombay,
directed by Mira Nair.
Below, right: Incompreso,
directed by Luigi Comencini.
Street children
Early on, cinema found a spokesmanperhaps
"role-model" would be a better word, for
there is not much speaking in most scenes
where the young confront the adult world
for all children in the shape of the little vaga¬
bond, Charlie Chaplin's companion in The
Kid (U.S.A., 1921) and the hero of dozens of
later films. Whatever their setting, films seem
to get closest to childhood when they portray
it straightforwardly, without any elaboration.
The child is the simplest and most authentic
of human beings.
From The Kid to Charles Lane's Sidewalk
Story (U.S.A., 1990)a silent film made in
black and white that treats the same theme of
abandoned children helped by a down-and-
outa horde of homeless children have
paraded across the screen. The successors of
yesterday's little vagabonds now roam the
alleys of Third World megalopolises like
Bombay, Bahia or Sao Paulo in such films as
Ciro Duran's Los Gamines (Colombia, 1978),
Hector Babenco's Pixote (Brazil, 1980), and
Mira Nair's Salaam Bombay (India, 1988).
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
These films could hardly be further from
the cheery Hollywood comedies of the years
from 1930 to 1950, in which tiny troupers,
their heads haloed with curls, filled the screen
with their carefree capers. This was the time
when Shirley Temple, Judy Garland and
Mickey Rooney were turning out film after
film. Only a few exceptional productions
dating from this period still captivate audiences
today, notably Victor Fleming's unforgettable
Wizard of Oz (U.S.A., 1948), Charles
Laughton's Night ofthe Hunter (U.S.A., 1955)
and Fritz Lang's Moonfleet (U.S.A., 1955).
In the 1960s and 1970s, the cinema reacted
against the angelic image of a protected child¬
hood and instead made children the focal point
of a number of horror movies. Such films
established the point that the simplistic schema
by which childhood equalled good and the
adult world evil was outdated. Once the
images of innocence, children now became
witches and warlocks, creatures possessed by
Satan or the Antichrist or, in Wolf Rilla's Vil¬
lage of the Damned (United Kingdom, 1960),
dangerous mutants.
The Hollywood ideal of childhood was
just as far away when the young were depicted
in the heat of battle in Viet Nam, the Second
World War or elsewhere. The paradise-garden
of childhood was spattered with blood in such
works as René Clement's Jeux Interdits
(France, 1951) and Steven Spielberg's Empire
of the Sun (U.S.A., 1987).
Nor have films shrunk from confronting
children with the facts of life. Frerid Bough-
edir's Halfaouine, l'enfant des terrasses (Tunisia,
1990) treats the subject of sexuality with tact
and discretion. The shadow of death and its
effect on the film's young protagonists is the
theme of La fracture du myocarde by Jacques
Fansten (France, 1991). Children also serve as
witnesses counting the costs of racial prejudice
and segregation in such films as Louis Malle's
Au revoir, les enfants (France, 1987), The
Kitchen Toto by Harry Hook (U.S.A./U.K.,
1988) and Andrzej Wajda's Korczak (Poland,
1991).
The anti-hero
of the late 20th century
In most of the films mentioned above, the child,
in Truffaut's words, "invents life, knocks up
against it, but at the same time develops
powers of resistance." But children can also,
by a subtle role-reversal, watch over adults,
acting as their guide and protector. The child
thereby becomes father to the man, as Pinoc-
chio does when he pulls Geppetto from the
belly of the whale in Comencini's Adventures
ofPinocchio (Italy, 1972), or' in Cuore (Italy,
1984) when Rabucco takes his illiterate father
to school.
Throughout its history, the cinema has
shown us, in the most truthful way, childhood
as a state of exposure. Confronting real
dangers, accepting challenges and fighting
injustice, the child is the anti-hero of the
closing years of the century. There is nothing
of Rambo or Mad Max here. Children's
strength and resources lie in demonstrating the
sensitivity and intelligence of which they are
capable. The main reward, as ever, is a place
in the adult world.
For children have one formidable weapon:
their sense of humour, or to be more precise,
the unspoiled impertinence that is their most
characteristic quality. Long may the cinema
portray it. For even when so many films set
^ out to destroy the last illusions concerning
childhood, even though it may irritate over-
serious adults, the impertinence of childhood
remains our best guarantee of a different
future.
1. L'enfant et la vie defamille sous l'Ancien Régime,
Seuil, Paris, 1973.
FRANÇOIS VALLET
is a French novelist whose work focuses on the
condition of children and young people today. He
is the author of an essay on the image of the
child in the cinema (Cerf publishers, Paris, 1991). 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
km% tk pá oj Mhk
i
LOTFALLAH SOLIMAN,
Egyptian journalist and writer, is the author of
A <5 Pour une nist0're Profane de 'a Palestine (La
4b découverte publishers, Paris, 1989).
N the 1950s, word went round that a rich
American had offered to buy the city of
Sana'a, minus its inhabitants, from the Imam
Ahmed for $40 million, an enormous sum at
that time. The plan provided for Sana'a's
population to be rehoused in a new city which
was to be specially built for them in the
vicinity.
When this anecdote is told today, the
people of Sana'a smile with a certain com¬
placency. Sana'a is now the capital of all
Yemen, and the renovation of its old city,
which is inscribed on UNESCO's World
Heritage List, is well under way.
Fact and fiction
Located at an altitude of 2,200 metres, too high
for mosquitoes to survive, Sana'a is worth
seeing for its site alone. It is not a city that
wears its heart on its sleeve. Like that of fairy
tales, its magic only works on those who have
not lost a capacity for wonder. It does not
reveal its charm to the visitor who summarily
orders it to "Open Sesame". The Italian poet
and film-maker Pier Paolo Pasolini was right
to use Sana'a as the setting for his film The
Thousand and One Nights.
Until they began to retreat into them¬
selves under the Zaydi imams, Sana'a and the
Yemen were places of meetings, confronta¬
tions and ancient loyalties.
Sana'a is a meeting place of fact and fan¬
tasy. Consider some of the stories told about
it. That it was founded by Shem, the son of
Noah. A legend. That the kingdom of Saba,
over which it ruled, was one of the richest and
most ancient civilizations of Antiquity. Fact.
That a great queen ruled over it, the "Queen
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
of Sheba" whose existence is recorded only
in sacred literature, not in any secular text or
archaeological inscription. Probably a legend.
That the largest Christian edifice south of the
Mediterranean was built at Sana'a. Fact
although the story that it was built to com¬
memorate a visit by Jesus of Nazareth is fic¬
tional. That the city's Great Mosque was built
during the Prophet's lifetime. Partly fact,
partly fiction. That its library is only rivalled
by those of Cairo and Kairouan. Fact. Doubt¬
less more archaeological research will be neces¬
sary to help us distinguish the authentic from
the spurious, truth from legend.
More literally, Sana'a was a meeting place
of caravans bearing gold and silver from the
Orient. The kingdoms of Saba (950-1 15 B.C.)
and Himyar (until c. 525) became wealthy
through the myrrh and frankincense coveted
by Ptolemaic Egypt, and later through moka
(the original name for coffee), the trade in
which would be disputed for many years by
the Portuguese, the Ottoman Turks and the
British.
It was also a meeting place between poly¬
theism and monotheism, a scene of confron¬
tation between Judaism and Christianity, until
Islam cut the quarrel short. The Yemen and
its capital Sana'a gave themselves totally to the
new faith. They provided Islam with soldiers
and technicians who left traces as far away as
Andalusia, where even today strongholds and
palaces have Yemeni names.
Finally it was a place where old and new
met, sometimes in confrontation. Until the
revolution which brought the imamate to an
end in 1962, the outward appearance of the
Yemen remained unchanged for centuries.
An outstanding architectural
heritage
For over a thousand years mosques, palaces,
madrasahs (Qur'anic schools), caravanserais,
hammams (public baths) and multi-storey
houses were built at Sana'a in an unvarying
style. In the 183 hectares of the old walled city,
these buildings of from four to seven storeys,
their façades adorned with whitewashed
friezes and beautiful carved windows, formed
a strange and extraordinary architectural
ensemble. Each storey had its own specific
material, decoration, use, plan, alabaster
plasterwork or stained glass windows. Each
house had its own well and sanitary facilities-
liquid wastes were recycled to water gardens
and solid matter was dried and burned to heat
water in the hammams. The winding streets
were narrow, but they were quite adequate
when the traffic was limited to people and
animals.
In 1962 the fall of the monarchy which
had preserved the medieval tranquility of
Sana'a profoundly disturbed the traditional
structure of society. Within a few years, the
city's population had risen from 55,000 to
420,000. Around the old city a new one was
built with modern facilities such as running
water, electricity, the telephone, schools,
universities, clinics, hospitals, restaurants,
cinemas and public buildings. The young,
soon followed by their elders, deserted their
traditional family houses and went to live in
more comfortable quarters in the new town.
The old city of Sana'a, once famed as "the
pearl of Arabia", went inexorably into decline.
Its population fell from 55,000 to 35,000, and
its composition changed. Both those who
remained and the newcomers who moved in
lacked the means to maintain the old
dwellings, which deteriorated and fell into
ruin. Since the inhabitants of the Old City also
wished to enjoy the benefits of modern house¬
hold amenities, electric wires and cables were
strung above the roofs of the houses, which
began to bristle with television aerials. Cheap
plastic piping laid under the roads to bring
running water burst beneath the weight of
uncontrolled traffic. Waste water infiltrated
into the ground, making the buildings even
more fragile.
Saving
the old city
At the end of the civil war in 1972, the Yemeni
government passed a law to protect its
architectural and archaeological heritage, with
particular reference to the old city of Sana'a.
But the government's resources were very
limited. UNESCO also wished to help to
preserve what could still be saved of Sana'a,
and in 1980 its General Conference adopted
Left: A general view of the old city of Sana'a,
looking towards the west.
Right: A plasterer restores a building
in Sana'a. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
a resolution authorizing the Director-General
to collaborate with the Yemeni government
in drawing up a plan of action for the preser¬
vation and restoration of the old city. In 1981
and 1982, architects, historians, sociologists
and engineers were mobilized to study the
problems posed by the safeguard of a site
which, it was felt, should not be mummified
but given new life in accordance with its old
traditions.
By 1983 the plan had been approved by
the Yemeni government and UNESCO, and
its implementation began. In December 1984,
before the city's inclusion on the World
Heritage List (which did not take place until
1987), the restoration and safeguard of Sana'a
were placed by presidential decree under the
authority of a High Committee chaired by the
Prime Minister. The Director-General of
UNESCO launched an appeal to the interna
tional community to help the Yemeni govern¬
ment carry out a rescue operation with an esti¬
mated cost of $300 million.
Several countries responded to
UNESCO's appeal. Italy played an active part
in pluridisciplinary studies connected with the
rescue operation and became the first country
to take part in the rehabilitation of an entire
district of the old city. Its example was fol¬
lowed by the Netherlands, Norway, Ger¬
many, France, the Republic of Korea, Swit¬
zerland and Japan, and by the United Nations
Development Programme, whose contribu¬
tion notably sought to revive traditions of
craftsmanship.
In June 1988, the Director-General of
UNESCO, Mr. Federico Mayor, visited Sana'a
to get a first-hand impression of the extent and
complexity of the task. It will take fifteen
years of constant effort and much devotion
to save Sana'a.
Above: A craftsman at work on
a stained-glass window.
Below: Houses in the old city.
1 (."'
I X '
mm x<¿BÉft"¿
irr-f'ri
"in
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
A day for the African child
As a mark of their concern for
their youngest and most
vulnerable citizens, the leaders
of the 51 Member States of
the Organization of African
Unity (OAU) have declared 16
June the "Day of the African
Child". The OAU wants to-
ensure that war, economic
recession, drought and the
AIDS tragedy do not deprive
African children of the
possibility of a hopeful future.
The date was chosen in
memory of the children
massacred at Soweto in June
1976.
Kites for peace
On 13 October 1991,
thousands of kites will rise
into the sky above Moscow,
Beijing, Sydney, Berlin, Paris,
Bombay and other cities to
proclaim the need for a world
free of conflict. The 6th One
Sky, One World Kite Festival
for World Peace and
Friendship will bring a
message of peace and
international goodwill to every
continent. Started in Colorado
(U.S.A.) in 1986, the festival
has become an annual event
that last year attracted more
than 200,000 spectators and
participants in 23 countries.
A small world of music
From 21 to 29 August, the
8th annual Orchestrades
Européennes welcomed 30
musical groups from 15
countries to the French town
of Brives. Nine hundred music
students came together to
practice their skills and extend
their experience in workshops,
rehearsals, open-air
performances and concerts.
This year as previously, the
highlight was the performance
of a new work specially
commissioned for the festival
and given its première in a
spectacular final concert
conducted by its composer,
Gérard Calvi.
Fair copies
The Vatican Library has given
UNESCO a facsimile of the
manuscript of Dante's Divine
Comedy, illustrated by
Botticelli between 1490 and
1497. To mark the occasion,
UNESCO's own library staged
an exhibition entitled "Great
Facsimiles from the Vatican",
featuring reproductions of
some of the Vatican's rarest
and most beautiful works. The
facsimiles were produced in
the 1980s to enable the
public to discover
masterpieces that were
inaccessible because of their
fragility-
Conserving biological
diversity
At the invitation of the United
Nations, representatives of
more than 100 countries met
in Madrid in June to discuss
the terms of an international
convention for the protection
of biological diversity. The
Convention, which has been in
preparation since 1988, may
be signed at the International
Conference on Environment
and Development which will
be held in Rio de Janeiro in
1992. According to the
experts who met in Madrid,
40,000 species are
disappearing annually around
the world, disturbing the
balance of nature. It is often
pointed out that the extinction
of a single insect or micro¬
organism could lead to the
destruction of a crop that
would have been beneficial to
humankind.
Intelligent cars
No, it's not science fiction in
the U.S.A. some cars are
already equipped with radar
equipment that provides them
with intelligence of a sort. The
device warns the driver when
other vehicles approach
dangerously close. The next
step will be to add
electronically-operated brakes
that will automatically slow the
car down and reduce the risk
of an accident.
A survival from
the Stone Age
Prehistoric paintings have
been found in a cave in the
Alava region of Spain. The
news was kept secret until a
few months ago, to allow
experts to check the
authenticity of the works. In
all there are 75 rock
paintings, including images of
animals, handprints and other,
probably symbolic designs. j
The specialists describe the I
find as a Stone Age sanctuary, ¡
about 13,000 years old. i
The ocean thermostat
A study undertaken in the
U.S.A. over the past few years
by California State University
and the Scripps Institution of
Oceanography suggests that
the Earth may have a natural
thermostat that prevents the
surface temperature of the
oceans from exceeding 31°C
at any point. When the
temperature rises to 27°C,
intense evaporation causes
the formation of clouds which
act as a kind of mirror,
reflecting the Sun's rays and
thus reducing the amount of
heat reaching the surface of
the planet.
To what extent may this
automatic regulatory system
protect us from global
warming produced by the
greenhouse effect?
Unfortunately, the Interplay of
the forces which maintain
global equilibrium is so
complex and delicate that
it is by no means certain that
the mechanism will always
work as well as the theory
suggests.
Child health targets for
the next decade
In the Middle East and North
Africa, the target of 80 per
cent immunization coverage of
the child population, fixed by
UNICEF for 1990, has been
achieved. The figure for
sub-Saharan Africa has risen
from 58 to 75 per cent,
despite civil wars in the
region. Objectives for the year
2000 set by the first World
Summit Conference for
Children, held at UN
headquarters in New York on
29 and 30 September 1990,
now seem attainable. They
include the global eradication
of poliomyelitis, the
elimination of neonatal
tetanus (by 1995), a 90 per
cent reduction in measles
cases and the maintenance
of a high level of
immunization coverage (at
least 90% of children under
one year of age).
The protection of
copyright
The 1st Ibero-American
Congress on Intellectual
Property will take place in
Madrid from 28 to 31
October, under the
sponsorship of the Spanish
Ministry of Culture in
collaboration with the World
Intellectual Property
Organization (WIPO). Spanish
and Latin-American specialists
will debate such subjects as
the protection of computer
software, authors' control over !
the uses to which their works
are put, and the role of the
State in protecting intellectual
property.
IN BRIEF. . . IN BRIEF. IN BRIEF.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
THE WORLD THROUGH CHILDREN'S EYES
"Whenever I go there, I come out completely changed," said
one Norwegian recently of Oslo's International Museum
of Children's Art. The Museum was founded in 1986 by
Rafael and Alia Goldin, who still run it today. It contains
some 100,000 works of artpaintings, drawings, ceramics,
collages, tapestries, sculptures, books and other articles, all
created by children from more than 130 countries.
The Goldins and their colleagues consider children's art
to be one of the liveliest and most original aspects of popular
culture, as well as an important part of the world's cultural
heritage.
The museum has a threefold purpose. Firstly, it collects,
classifies and preserves graphic art, literature and films from
all over the' world, and also houses a vast library of books
about children's art. Secondly, it organizes classes in drawing,
painting, dance, music, theatre, cinema and other subjects,
open to both children and adults. Thirdly, it organizes com¬
petitions and travelling exhibitions, one of which, on the
theme of natural catastrophes, will visit Athens in December
1991. The Museum also publishes reproductions, catalogues
and books, and furthers the understanding of children's art
by holding conferences and seminars.
Above, Rafael Goldin and a group of children at the
Museum.
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
We should like to thank the International Museum of Children's Art (Oslo) for
allowing us to reproduce the works from its collection shown on the following
pages: Cover, Back cover, Pages 7 (right), 14, 15, 16 (left), 16-17, 18, 19, 23,
24, 25, 26-27, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 50: ©The
International Museum of Children's Art, Oslo. Page 3: UNESCO/Eclair
Mondial. Page 4 (3): UNESCO/Dominique Roger. Page 4 (4): AGIP/Robert
Cohen, Paris. Page 4 (1), (2), (5), (6): UNESCO. Page 5: UNESCO/Archives.
Page 6 (1): Harumi Imaizumi, Bangladesh. Page 6 (left): © UNESCO Clubs.
Page 6 (right): ITI/ITU/UNESCO. Pages 7 (left), 8: Merillon © Gamma, Paris.
Page 10: Ulf Andersen © Gamma, Paris. Page 1 1: Mireille Vautier © ANA, Paris.
Page 12: © Claude Sauvageot, Paris. Page 20: Ernst Haas © Magnum, Paris.
Page 21: © Eric Larrayadicu/Editing, Paris. Pages 27 (below), 28: © Ana
Vasquez, Paris. Pages 43, 44, 45: © Les Cahiers du Cinéma, Paris. Page 46:
UNESCO/Gérard Bolla. Pages 47, 48 (above): UNESCO/Pascal Maréchaux.
Page 48 (below): UNESCO/J.P. Heim.
The credit line for the front cover photo of our August-September issue was
inadvertently omitted. It should have read: Photo © Stock/VIoo, Paris.
50
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
A timely clarification
You commissioned an article from me on the concept of time in the Islamic
world. It appeared in the April 1991 issue of your magazine under the title
chosen by your editors "A Many-sided Concept". The article underwent too
many changes, made without my knowledge, for me to ratify them by my
silence. Entire passages were cut, sometimes distorting my argument; the
order of the paragraphs was changed, muddying the exposition, and much
of the savour of the piece was lost.
To make things worse, it was accompanied by a box containing a letter
from Gouverneur Morris (the U.S. Minister to France during the French Revo¬
lution) to General Washington. I should be glad to learn what possible
relevance this might have had to the contents of the article. If there was
none, as seems to have been the case, then you might at least admit that
this ill-chosen box should not have been there in the first place.
Ahmad Hasnawi
Paris
(France)
As we inform each of our authors, we reserve the right to edit their articles,
if necessary, so as to make them suitable for an international cultural maga¬
zine like the UNESCO Courier which is produced for a wide audience. Natur¬
ally, in so doing we aim to maintain absolute fidelity to the meaning and spirit
of the piece, seeking only to make it fully intelligible to our readers.
As for quotations from other authors, these are interpolated in the text
not only to provide information about the theme of each issue but also to
add variety to the contents and appearance of the magazine. Sometimes the
links with individual articles are direct; at other times they are not.
Multiple encounters
With reference to your "In Brief" column of March 1991, you should really
have specified in your note on Spanish emigration to the Americas that 1992
is the 500th anniversary of the third [or possibly three hundred and third)
"encounter between the Old and New Worlds".
Aside from the "discovery" of America by Norsemen (no longer deemed
a mere possibility), the Old World met the New in who knows how many fresh
transmigrations via the Bering Strait over tens of thousands of years. However
galling it may be to the monumental egos of Europeans, their ancestors had
nothing to do with the original settlement of the Americas.
Robert MacLeod
Sirdar
(Canada)
West Indian rhythms
As a West Indian, I very much enjoyed the March 1991 issue, entitled "A
World of Music". Here in Trinidad and Tobago we have music from all corn¬
ers of the globe, and from it we have produced our own blends, namely calyp¬
so, which originated here in the days of slavery, and the pans, the instru¬
ment of the steel bands, which has been the musical invention of the 20th
century. Steel bands have travelled to all corners of the earth, a move pi¬
oneered by the early, still-strong bands like the All-stars and the Samaroo
Jets. The pans play everything from classical to calypso music and jazz. It
was a pity they were not mentioned in any of the articles.
In the world today, the need to Interact is greater than ever. The con¬
cept of World Music is a manifestation of this.
R.P.I.Gajar
Sacarigua
(Trinidad and Tobago)
Learning to appreciate art
Thank you for reproducing "Woman in an Interior" by the Georgian artist
Irakli Parjiani in your February issue. Despite the importance of art for hu¬
mankind, the ability to appreciate it Is not within everyone's reach, and I feel
that more should be done to educate public opinion in this respect. Why not
get together a group of art critics, sociologists, psychologists, philosophers,
artists and possibly a number of readers of the Courier to discuss the problem?
It would also be interesting to hear what the specialists have to say about
art education for the young.
Ketevan Kintsurashvili
Tbilisi
(USSR)
An open letter to Professor Schwartzenberg
The interview with you published in the July issue of the Courier came as
a ray of hope, providing a better understanding of the terrible disease of
cancer. It was impossible not to be moved by the interest you take in each
of your patients, or by your brave message of life in the face of death. Above
all, you helped dispel some misapprehensions about euthanasiaa terrible
choice that demands great courage of both patient and doctor.
Laurence Tissier
Charbonnières-les-Bains
(France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
^courier
Published monthly in 35 languages and in braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin. 75015 Paris, France.
&EE i
ïkme of the next im:
i
i
.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
I
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévéque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Lrbina
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, (Tel.: 45.68 46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstem (Tel.: 45.68.46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Administrative assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection in Braille In English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dominique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Metra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wall Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dares- Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou ¡Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kessler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Zmarai Mohaqiq (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Manager: Henry Knobil (45.68.45 88),
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45,65),
jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngonekeo. Michel Ravassara,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salah El Din.
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: Gmette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45.65),
Mali: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel. 45.68.45.65
1 year: 139 French francs. 2 years: 259 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 108 French francs. 2 years: 194 FF
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs not copyngh:ed may be reprinted
p-ovidmg the cedit line reads 'Reprinted from the UNESCO Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
he returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
aid do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO Couner Photo captions and headlines
a-e written by the UNESCO Courier staff The ooundaries on maps
p irjiishec m the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations The UNESCO Courier
is produced in microform (microfilm and/or micro? che) by (1) UNESCO.
7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48 100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Mfcrocard tditmr . Indian
Head, Inc., Ill West 40th Street. New York, US A: (4) Bell arc Howell
Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. USA.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE
(Printed in France) - DEPOT LEGAL Cl - OCTOBRE 1991.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocomposition: The UNESCO Courier
Photogravure-impression Maury Imprimeur S.A.,
Z.l. route d'Etampes. 45330 Malesherbes.
;
I
-
7
ENVIRONMENT AND DEVED
'
,'
v
,/' SUSTAINABLE
:
1
I
ISSN 0041-5278 N" 10- 91 OPI-91 3 497 A
Ab featuring:
an interview with
' TV ' -; : .
Marine explorer
Jacques-Yves Cousteau
Federico Mayor
Mnrn nmtmm on
This issue comprises 54 pages and a 4-puge advertising insert
between pages 10-1 1 and 42-43
mwen ¡pp on
UNESCO's new programme
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
