<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="090316eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
DECEMBER 1991
CONTENTS
Interview with
MELINA MERCOURI
"''W-
"awt tttm <MM) M) ttn ht < ? < ottMh
"OMtt <) MMM h « M< MMOMtwtty
wus e 1Ar talte. oA awar
et a am,
, ; \W) MM thw peMtMt M « M) CMte
dt 1, k i in th nt ot msn
j<MM<t xt tt <t the < eexM
oasbuabA. a, :
<tmMfM. <M) awt<h<) M « <t<Mt
M), X) M<t<tMtHM<&lt;ehw) <tM) meM<
MXO)  ef m<ttMt<&lt;.
' ttMM MMe"*, th* aMM
\.'. pMMM... *f* *<f « *a<
XteptM<&lt;t<tB « «) thty thM< ntMMt
<tr<t<t t) Mt) M< « <t< <M) <Mt
   f d moral
selrlr ot msl.
prss.. : n  ad
oIt s mans ef
Ottt t<MM ttftet) tXM*tw) M< ef
".'""etM) Mtt) « H))) <M. '. 
It and  
asamoryat Imord· 
'/K. MttM) 
ot tr  r ir tl
iAa. 8 r ; t
____
AL-ANDALUS :
WHERE THREE WORLDS MET
SINGULAR AND PLURAL :
THE HERITAGE OF AL-ANDALUS
)'Kf7/if : e 15
THE ROOTS OF COEXISTENCE
by M : g « e/ CrKZ//o ? Mnz 20
THE RISE OF THE UMAYYAD DYNASTY
IN SPAIN
by J Derek Latham 24
CORDOBA THE MAGNIFICENT
by Pierre Guichard 28
THE CHRISTIAN CONTRIBUTION
by Rosa Guerreiro 32
CONVERGENT STREAMS
by Haim Zafrani 35
THE PURSUIT OF LEARNING
by t7 : ef 38
THE TOLEDO SCHOOL
by MKrff ? ! t !  Bd ! f ! 40
BORGES IN SEARCH OF AVERROES
by Racbid Sabbaghi 42
UNESCO'S FIRST
45 YEARS (Part III)
by Michel ; 7 Ztcotc
' t/Nsco/N/tcno
TENTH
ANNIVERSARY
OF THE UNESCO PRH
FOR PEACE
EDUCATION
by Betty Reardon and
Ungku 4MH/4ztz
< UNESCO lN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
The Topkapi harem :
a forbidden enclave
by Ctr'0/Mf/Mf<t
49
' NMVa : M/
YUNUS EMRE
by 7< Sait Halman
UNESCO COURIER
INDEX t991
Cover : untitled (100 x 81 cm),
1988, mixed technique on
canvas by the French artist
Isabelle Grange.
Back cover : arches of the
Great Mosque in Cordoba
(Spain).
___ __
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
" "
Yy
. J 
 
sc xan  re n.. ,.
v, < r
ycDC/paw)))) 
a
E%  ! N : 4'/9 *'*"' *'< /
'SSM ..'-
.. :, .. 4 
a   ,, ., )   IICtOr-ienail. 1'e 18,
"MMtMe UNE, <t tHt of dteUN General ekcted Director-Genera ! in 1962. : :
S.'S.' :'" utgtht-tMNt'f... AMt. a'tt' in dte * TheIntenNtioodConventionfortheProtec-
tion of Pet&Mmers, Produces of PhotMtgrmM
S  : : % .-",  :'''"''' !. S'".''-' <'aM &tr'poehd  [pMtt of atdt and BroadeMtu Orgtnizations (the"Rome
ISM'. 'm'  : - Coteation'isdMwnupjomdybyUNESCO,
 :   : S''.. SQ.. ', ; L. 'OjGMH<. :,  M &Msic Aet the WotM Inte ! ! ectuat Propetty OrgmBatIon, ;
'. .  IJW'-j'tH Prof. Pien-e (WIPO) and the International Labour Organi-
;  : 'tle UN aad satioa (ILO).
ttl in 195t.
- : U.'JS-J.- ; \. r. & : :  AW ; ' pabB jtO) M by the UN md sation ( ! LO).
SX ths-taaamBem. of between UNICBF tnd UNESCO. :, bepm,
e& ; \$.  Botfly m prinMry md earty duldhood. edu-; Edtal= T Y P'Y
"'''MA MM S H ! gh Bwa s ! aaa<j PreMd ! <t a ceremony cation.
' :''Ssh M o<) tM<&amp;. <"-''* UNQO'hetdMBH, AadMdnm corn-N The Erst Regiomd ConfereMe of Mincers of
CSf/. SSx' j'-, \j" ;  ; iB<e*, < EdtMttton M hetd at Addis Abeba. Between 1961
ana 1986, 24 such conferences are held (for
P"* ;' Sjtt 22 ittaetaad teaBt me moted, 40 technKat AMca ; Latin America and the Caribbean ; the
Aras States ; Asia and the Pacific ; and Europe).
 ; erM.,/OOBtri of gSfenunenB and other tCtef- An emergency pftramme ts launched M part
 ; S.. aaaoaat'MUtces, pubSe andpeaate, toMt $56 of UN action to maintain educationa ! services
'M ! -\--  :. inCongo-LeopoMviue (todayZaire). MoKd ! an'
&$t'S3M' .'.'.'. a hundred specialists are sent and he ! p isprovided
Se'MN ; St',"--. ; : ?"'''.""'for the recruitment of some 800 teachers.
F
9
' N UNESCO sends a mission into the seismic
zones of Asia, South Amaia Africx, leg
,  ,. .   
', 
.   
to the crtioa af a study Prognmme on uth-
;- : taber ;   « t thcKsijsnattonof Vit-ouakes and other natural hards.
'."'"''tonaeemtmeheahhreasoas. ReneMaheu t) UNESCO estaMishes in Rome the Intema-
A. aec  7't ; onat Computation Centre (ICC) later to1A 
A ! 
 
Wf 
tCuiyi4, INl7f1 ilf  '.' : : l1111  becomes the InMrgovemmentalBuKau of Imbr-
matics (IBI).
8 The UNESCO Collec : tions of Traditional
Music are launched in rollaboration with the
IMC (ISO LPs released by 1986). Today the Col-
lections have been issued on SO compact discs.
 y. 
 *', '°r4. 3.  '' "  
 
 LTNESCO tions t
'`  ; p 
.    c l r. tion 
cW Fund, UNESCO bècins action on projects
 
F, . . 
 . ;  '.   150 d . p
. "  t. *''` kcticas h ct on 50 co pcx 
be traùiecL
y
,  w  In . oaon with the Uited Nations Spo-
 [ p  ion Qa 
4F
Y_ 35, Afix) x wbich tho> ef 
(teachas 
WIll
r  ·, PV " 94-i'r. ", OC 1.
r  , f
 n x ic
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
. MMWB
'
. :/MM'tMMt) 
'M<B ! M. <9WWM<&lt; :''.' : \ ; ; :'. ; 
. 
 
.. 
ttMN'tts
--nH ! ! t
f  ! '
 :'. aB
' :".
''wNr's MR
S-' :'-'MB ". 
! 
<_'
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
! !.. lr° ;'-'. f  1.  h.
- r,. . ArJ` 
, ar. :  E' ; d, , t, : tw.  .., : ;, p.... : : , va 
:r a Y, xS , e. it'L z'I ... l.y'n.... a' 1..,....'i'i  z,.. 4 FI a_.,-r >° _t : pL,.., . . S'm. ... f "-#,:,'3^t., 
y 
! 
a..
a. 4 g $., f,.. ``°... h t. 
Y 
.. 
 % i  
W
. 1.Y'a. G. 
1.. 
 
i. 
=^XS t 
_. >
: . y. i :
, ;. t.y 1 *. s< " : ar t 
Y.,
.. 
-rt'. w x`
;
 r 4  : ̂ ; st Y/t ji'.,. a. fyt 'e.. t,,,,
m a # 
·
t,.'r
e ,'..-. ·.'. . #, ... >
rc^ 3.. * 
yy, y, y y'm1 !^F. ''i'Sd 
7 , y ! !'' 
`,.
`t   f7 .' fy  W  '
 x lilL  11w '11lL   1,.v. < Dh r Y 
:. 
t YP 
 
9 d y5 " i. : :. r : 
=......
Y `
 
c,- ,. ·t. x.. :  y. 3 ..
.-. t.,,  . 'o °
s-v... 
;''e.
. a h ° 3 R.r
.., . `.. · > " : " :  ,. ;  · r. :.....'..
a'` r 
 
f ='r,. , t  v :..  ; s  : ", ·..
. 
 . : y. ``>3..,  L .., i 
G
o- " t , 3 ; t''-: 2`c$.   "  :  r,'.  '' ,, 1  Illui` 
.
y,, ,, 
_.  TA14- ;... ·. ` lGli'.....
:'IH-iQC ..
'Y''f
. " (RL.  Y k :.=i'. r y , ., `, ·r _-· " "
* :.
` 
" ̀ 
" ·  : g 1 oe  :
, t
t , ta'rtad
.,. L.,.-k .  : b ' .'x ..: z : " ;̀ - x'',, i' l. C  5o-
r.
 
u 
S' u " v', 
, 
.. ` 
L 
 h.. 
, 
a - 
:y5 :)
, `d w 1...'v..
R ; rY-`. n ldt.  .'im " 
Y'> # : _. 1
.','x,   _  3 ;'$ 4l   y k S.  t h N,£'fr 4 5 
a`. 
i " >h..,.  S. m. . 
f.IY ! (
W.. ZS^
r x-, f'-r sk'h,.  ;,n
y
` r " f " , "  
..
:em ̂h, *, : r',
» j` -' r '... 'y ̂
.. a. .. "   " ;.. r 
.-n 
, 
. v , .. : ,', °. : 
   4''
, 
i' , , .. ;
r  
 #   S ., nd
i'' ;' r ;, f 
r
 
` " '  M y' ; s, 4` 
r a,..
, s, t
 <  
! 5.. 
fiyy4 Y f <
,, WV'.,. 
d' 
cT ? 
4,,,,/tir 
1Z 
3`'.
. , 
"'-s ;,,  _,h far·. Y W ;., : 
 !   
" !'K f 
. 
· ·.
,
a., a   k u . y.
... 
-'''.'4n.'.,-.. 
_ 
y. " 
>iT. ? a 
? 
r_s, 
t 
 ; 
=, si...
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Stage and screen actress, deputy and minister, You were very young when you first
Melina Mercouri has had an eventful career which has been became interested in the theatre. Tell us some-
..... -t    j   OKf fc ctor' ! CM'/f. W% < ! f  GrfCKcrowned with success m many feMs. A standard-Dearer     ,  
of liberty at the time-of the co/oneh'reg/me, she is think about the stage ?
regarded with affection by the Greek people, for whom-My family has been involved in politics for
...,,.. < t-n generations. My grandfather, who adored meand whom 
I adored, was mayor of Athens for
more than twenty years. The house was
always full, for at that time the mayor of
Athens was as powerful as a minister, maybe
even more so. That was theatre for me. I had
a stage, an audience, partners, dialogues, some-
times even long tirades.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
. Were there women in politics at that time ?
- No. Politics was for men. But when I was
a child, I often used to imagine what it would
be like to be In my grandfather's shoes. Politics
didn't enter into it, I understood nothing
about hat. What mattered was the drama, the
speeches... and the audience.
So the theatre was a part of me from my
early years. And then my grandfather often
took me with him to see plays. I felt at home
there, even though I couldn't follow the plots.
In some ways it was like being at home.
Even when I was very young, I was a
rebel. When I was seven or eight I used to
MEDNA MERCOUR)
tatksto
Bahgat E ! na (t ! an () A (te ! Rifaat
escape from the house and go off with a friend N things were as you describe them, how
to the cinema or to a cafe to listen to music. did you set about 0'ucrcom ! ? !  f osfc/es*'
Once we got dressed up in our mothers'finery-I got married at seventeen ! To a wealthy
and went to a sailors'tavern, where they aristocrat who had studied at Cambridge
served tea and played music. In all innocence, University. Politically he was conservative,
we got up and danced. We just enjoyed per-not to say reactionary, but he had extremely
forming, putting on a show and being liberal ideas on the role of women. He didn't
applauded. My mother soon put an end to that try to turn me into a submissive wife. He
little adventure. A woman who had seen us didn't even make me take his name, as was
tipped her off, and she came looking for me. normal at the time. I stayed Melina Mercouri,
She took me back home and severely punished for him and for everyone he introduced me
me. Never mind. I had made my decision. I to. Thai's how I broke free from my family
wanted to go on the stage. I wanted applause ! and how I was able to study and prepare for
Obviously, my parents didn't see things In the the audition that would get me into the Drama
same way. School of the National Theatre of Greece.
N Why not ? Was the life of an actor or actress · Then came the war and the Occupation.
considered isreputable ? Could you describe what it was like ? Or is
- No. But for the Athenian upper middle it something you prefer not to talk about ?
class to which I belonged, It wasn't done to-Why shouldn't I talk about it ? We had three
go on the boards, even to play a heroine of years of Occupation. I saw swollen bellies and
Sophocles or Euripides. What's more, there people dying of hunger. I saw carts going by
was no security in the artist's life. One day with the corpses of men and women piled up
you could be rolling in money and the next on them like carcasses of cattle. I saw people
you could be starving. For children of good living from day to day, not knowing what
family, the theatre was risky, tomorrow would bring. I saw the continual
I don't think my parents thought there uncertainty drive some to heroic acts of
was anything dishonourable about acting, resistance and others to collaboration.
They would have had no objection if they Nobody in my family collaborated with the
could have been certain that I would be a enemy. My younger brother was in the
success ! They were behind me throughout my Resistance. Not me. It's the one thing I really
political and artistic career. It would certainly regret. But it wasn't through lack of courage
have been the same with my grandfather, if or fear of death.
he hadn't done me the dirty trick of dying in One day I was in a tavern with three
the meantime, friends when three SS men entered. They were
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A scene from Topkapi (1964), directed by Jules
Dassin. In foreground, Maximilian Schell,
'Melina Mercouri, Peter Ustinov and Robert Morley.
. Are audiences different, or is there really
only one audience ?
- 
Audiences are different. In England,
1
t sf
', 4s i
brawl. In Greece they're colder. You have to
y
/, t 
·
.-Audiences 
America, even France, audiences are often
ready for the fray as soon as they've got their
tickets ; they're expecting to take part in a
work hard to win them over, to warm them
up, get them to react, take part.
dead drunk. They asked us to sit at their table. talk to me. At length and tirelessly. He talked * Z.  so fc r/M or < ! n c
When we didn't move, one of them drew a to me about Greek tragedy, about Its poetry, audience has been conquered. Who does it
revolver. My three friends got up then and the tradition, the significance it had for the applaud : MMfrcoKn, o ?' ; Mp<H
went over to join them. I don't know what Greek people. Eventually he convinced me. played ? Does each character have its own
got into me because my head was empty, but He made theatre a religion for me. That is no reality, its own message, or is it really always
I didn't move. The SS man was furious, he exaggeration ; there was something religious Melina who is in control ?
kept on at me. He pointed the pistol and about my devotion to Greek tragedy. Back-Melina is always there, naturally, but to give
started counting. " Ein, zwei, drei...."I still home, I would rehearse Marguerite's mono-birth to a role created by someone else, a
didn't move. I wasn't scared. He fired, and the logue on my knees. I rehearsed it so many character for whom she is only a surrogate
glass in front of me shattered. Now I was times that I wore out the carpet. mother. At every performance, Melina gives
furious, and I got up and started shouting What could the SS do against Medea or birth. Now, there are some people who talk
insults at him. I never considered that he Antigone ? Thanks to them, I moved through down the role of the surrogate mother.
might keep on firing. I wasn't thinking of any-the war like a sleepwalker. Without getting They're wrong. The baby Melina brings forth
thing. Then the military police arrived and into psychoanalysis, I think you have to look for the audience has been in her guts after all.
dragged him out of the tavern, to my love of the theatre for one of the essen-It's no longer the exclusive property of the
I didn't know what fear was. Even so, I tial keys to my behaviour, author, any more than it's exclusively
didn't join the Resistance. When I think about Melina's. It has a life, a reality of its own. It's
it now, I wonder If the main reason wasn't N Fo « <M yoMr career on the stage just incredible, what I'm saying, but that's what
my burning ambition to be an actress ! At after the war. What does playing a role happens. And it's wonderful.
drama school from two till six every day, the involve for you ? What goes through your It's all the more outrageous because the
outside world ceased to exist. There was no head when yoK'rc performing a part that director is also mixed up in this process of no
more Occupation, no more Germans, no someone else has written ? longer knowing who is who. The director is
more Melina even. There was only Mar--It's when I'm rehearsing that the most a go-between. And a good director will know
guerite, Ophelia, la Locandiera, Electra. And important hings happen. It's during rehearsals how to make the actor part of a whole corn-
then there was the sublime Dimitris Rondiris, that the character, who as you say has been pany on stage. Without that, even an actor
our teacher. He demanded from us a commit-created by someone else, becomes alive in me who is a genius will end up like a meteorite,
ment to the theatre as total as his own. His and through me. Actors carry their roles inside lost in too much space. In the theatre it's team-
Oresteia remains the greatest theatrical them, just as pregnant women carry babies. work that works wonders.
experience of my life. You can feel it physically, like a pregnancy.
It was Rondiris who taught me to control It's a very sensual experience. It's that gesta-N W% crc o c !' ? ! cm< !  !'n fo < !//1 Ws
and modulate my voice. He used to say that tion that constitutes the creative part of acting. it part of your adolescent dreams ?
I was made for tragedy. I was quite prepared Later, when you confront the audience, it's-It certainly was ! Mind you, in the early
to admit that Electra was the greatest role an more like bullfighting. You have to kill them, 1950s, Greek cinema only wanted actresses to
actress could play, but even so I used to beg of course, but the instruments are already play young innocents. Above a)) they had to
him, sometimes with tears in my eyes, to there. You've prepared them during have big eyes and tiny little mouths. I wasn't
admit that I wasn't Electra ! Then he would rehearsals, built for the job. I was too big and my mouth
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
was too wide. Even so, I didn't give up hope.
. sy, h s. Gt "2 ; 
somewhere else, in France or England. And
u
Korda gave me a screen test. We both burst
out laughing when we saw it ; I looked
., a 1' s 7 9  :  lt
 
! II k
everyone else too, that the theatre was the
only place for me. When Iacovos Campanellis
I told myself that maybe I'd have a chance ` 
 t ̀  ̀ 
sure enough, one day in London Alexander
ridiculous. 'wi i
I'd finished up by convincing myself, and s'_, k "' !
 il, Iy (I !
wrote the part of Stella for me, he saw it as
a stage role. By chance, though, he had asked Melina Mercouri between
Anthony Perkins and Jules Dassin (right)Cacoyannis to direct it. There was a moment 
men  "
when things were touch-and-go. Cacoyannis Cannes Film Festival, where I almost won the
wanted to make it into a film, but Campanellis Best Actress award. It was the start of M, by a long chalk. Then that wonderful
didn t want anyone but me to ptay Stella. As Cacoyannis's international career. Thirty-five film Celui qui doit mourir ( " He who Must
far as he was concerned, I was Ste !) a,"the most years later, the film hasn't aged a bit. They Die "). It came out of the encounter between
emancipated woman in Greece". So they showed it on television recently and the Kazantzakis. Jules Dassin a d Crete. Crete is
decided to give me a screen test. That was a viewing figures were exceptional. The splendid, Kazantzakis a genius and Dassin aweird experience. Cacoyannis started by pho-character Campanellis created remains abso-very director
tographing me from every angle, then he set lutely modern. Cacoyannis used to say of I can still visualize the village where It was
up the camera in front of me, made me howl Stella : " She's gay. She's vibrant. She's proud shot. They'd never seen acamera before. We'd
with laughter and shot me with the camera of her body. She's proud of her liberty. She agreed that all the villagers hould appear asfocused halfway down my throat. When I saw has lovers and she has friends. She refuses to extras, and we'd assembled them in the church
the rushes, I understood that something had think of marriage as a form of security, and 
square. Dassin read the script and I translated.
happened. It was the start of a love-affair she doesn't want society's blessing. She's sus-There were good and bad characters in the
between me and the camera, picious of everything society approves of. " script, rich people and poor people.
Stella was a success. It was shown at the When we came to give out the roles,
- 0//<- y   r -,   py e goodies, which is
tional career, which one stands out for you to say the poor people. It was no use my telling
Mercouri. in a scene from the f)) m 10. 30 p. m."0.   g gj g weren't JUSt rich, they a scene from the film 10.30 p. m.
Summer (1966). also had more important parts, so the people
who played them would make more money. I
still couldn't persuade them. Finally I told them
that I couldn't do anything about it, that that
was how Kazantzakis had plotted the story.
of them didn't know how to read. But the
None of them had read the novel, in fact most
wanted them to. It brought tears to my eyes.
moment I mentioned Kazantzakis's name, they
: all immediately agreed to play whatever role he
I made other films with Dassin. In each
of them he managed miraculously to create
an atmosphere of camaraderie and joie de vivre
that transfigured everyone involved. I would
like to mention here the film he made about
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
the unrest at the Ecole Polytechnique in moments ? Well, here are two that come to over a whole people, seemingly for ever. The
Athens. The whole film was shot indoors, In mind. Greek people seemed to have been reduced to
one room. Yet through Dassin's magic, all the First of all, there was the Greek sailor I silence. But my sailor's gesture showed how
anger, all the nobility, all the beauty of the met in the docks at Genoa in Italy. It was five deceptive the silence could be. I've learned
Greek people are there in it. It's a pure gem. o'clock In the morning. He was heading back since then never to believe that a people is
to a merchant ship with some other sailors, happy with its government just because It is
* Now do you explain the stir Melina made My heart started pounding. Any Greek you silent. Silence never indicates contentment.
when she weMt into politics ? Melina, who met at that time immediately became a com-Contentment is voluble, noisy. Silence can
hadn't joined the Resistance during the War ? rade, a brother. I went up to talk to them. I only be imposed by force.
- 
That wasn't he same at all. During the War wanted to discuss the situation in Greece, The other incident made me reflect above
I was very young, and there were the Drama invite them to a meeting we were holding that all on the fragility of human intelligence. How
School courses to isolate me, literally to spirit evening. We hadn't exchanged a word when could anyone believe such an obvious absur-
me away from the fighting.. their officer arrived and ordered them to dity as that story of 50, 000 communist
With the dictatorship of the colonels, it return to their ship immediately. My sailor invaders ? But leaving the'details aside, the
was very different. I had reached a completely went off with the others. I just stood there, question Is still relevant oday. How Is it that
different emotional and political maturity, my arms stretched out to nothing, suddenly people can be conditioned to the point of
The coup d'etat affected me like a rape. You feeling very alone. But then just before he dis-losing their sense of logic, of applauding the
can't react calmly to being raped. You shout, appeared from view, without even turning very people who are tormenting them ? It can't
you protest, you scratch. I was abroad when round, my sailor put his hand behind his back all be explained In terms of economic or polit-
the colonels eized power. Well, I shouted as and gave me the victory sign. I cried for joy. ical self-interest. There were plenty of sincere
loud as I could. I shouted, I sang, I danced for The second memory is very different, people among the colonels'backers who stood
liberty. I wasn't a spoiled child anymore. I was because you must realize that I wasn't popular to gain nothing from the dictatorship.... I
someone to be reckoned with. with all Greeks. Far from it. In America, have to admit that I still haven't found a satis-
Europe too, there were Greeks who would factory answer to the question.
N What special memories do you have of that insul me, boo me, threaten me. How can I
time ? forget the demonstrators who shouted under N One gets the impression that you gradu-
- Special memories ? Every minute of it is a my window that I was a communist bitch, or ally lost interest in the theatre and the cinema
special memory ! The phone ringing. Or the person who rang me up to tell me-in after becoming involved in politics....
maybe not ringing, or not when you expect Greek, what's more-that " the colonels had-Wrong ! I didn't lose interest. It was the
it to. Getting caught up in action, and then stopped 50, 000 communists who were getting cinema nd theatre producers who lost interest
the agony of doing nothing. It's all there, ready to invade Greece from Yugoslavia nd in me. I got fewer and fewer offers of work.
lurking somewhere In my memory. If I let It Bulgaria ", before going on to add that It would I was living dangerously, under constant threat
all out, we'd be here till tomorrow morning, be just as easy to " stop me " too. of attack. I was travelling from country to
How can I choose the most striking Those two incidents how two faces of the country, and the insurance companies didn't
tragedy of the dictatorship. Unscrupulous want to know about me.
Melina na M.,.. ur. and p. err. vaneck 
colonels, in Greece as elsewhere, can cast a pall
in a scene from HB wnc Must Die cssn, · Eventually the colonels fell, but you stayed
directed by Jules Dassin. ZZZ polItZCS..
- 
When we went back to Greece, after the
fall of the colonels, I hesitated for a bit. Should
I stay in politics full time ? Then Andreas
 : Papandreou rang up to ask me to be a candi-
date in the legislative elections, for the Piraeus,
the second istrict. It was a difficult consti-
tuency for a woman. The voters were sailors,
miners, macho types. I pointed out that I
would feel more comfortable in Athens,
where, as I said earlier, my grandfather had
been mayor and my father had been a deputy.
. 
Ir  x ;` '' .'2'Papandreou won me over by his reply. He
said, " Melina, you celebrated Piraeus in Never
on Sunday and made it known around the
w
12 
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Medea for two months. That was the role of there, side by side. It was strange how much
my life, the greatest role ever written for the easier conversations became.
ta'theatre. It was my greatest uccess, too. Medea
!. 
. 
 was the reward for all my efforts for the · Was it di ; cult to make up your mind ?
theatre, for the cinema, for Greece.-All the more difficult when the competing
After we won the legislative lections on projects were good ones, and it was only
$. aS))) ! ''tt) tt  October 1980, Andreas Papandreou asked because of a lack of resources that one had to
me to become Minister of Culture. It was a choose between them. It's horrible to abandon
new challenge. I was caught up in the general a project because you don't have enough
" ' euphoria, I thought that at last the world money to carry it through. But you have to
belonged to us, so I accepted. Those were eight force yourself to decide.
F-,  =,  happy years. We made mistakes and we paid
for them. But we also achieved a great deal. · Did that cause problems for you ?
- Yes, of course. But that's the kind of
i · Being a minister was a new role for you problem I can stand. In the office, I never let
to play-one you were thrown into without any of my regrets show. It was only when I
>v
any chance to rehearse.... got back home that I would sound off, and
- There weren't any rehearsals, that's for sure. it was my friends who suffered from my bad
But the field the ministry covered was familiar temper. But I never went back on a decision
to me ; it included theatre, music, cinema. once it was taken.
Which is to say that I wasn't entirely an
intruder. There was archaeology as well, cer-· Don't you ever feel that a life as full and
tainly. But for that I surrounded myself with diverse as yours can be a heavy load to carry ?
competent people.-Oh no ! Just the opposite ! If I hadn't become
When I took up office, the ministry of involved in politics, I would now just be a has-
Culture was a small one. Then its responsi-been of stage and screen. That would be awful.
_ 
xH bilities were extended to include athletics, I'm very happy that people don't talk about
world. In Piraeus you' ! ! be able to smash the sport, youth, Greeks living abroad.... It me in the past tense. I'm still " Melina " for
right and the left as well. " I put forward my became a very big ministry. To cope, I had them, just as I always have been. It even goes
! candidacy. to decentralize. I decentralized like mad. further than that. Because at a time of very
I campaigned in the same way that I For the ministry people and my visitors great distress I expressed their hist for life,
rehearse parts in the theatre. Furiously, but as well, I was the barefoot minister, I never because I loved them then and still love them
with pleasure. I used to go into cafes and play wore shoes. I was also a minister who never now with all my heart, they sculpted a mask
t backgammon with the old men. That received people sitting at a desk. Desks create of me and engraved on it : " Our Melina ".
t improved my standing, because I used to win. a distance between people. So I had a table They know I'm " their " Melina. For me, that's
I campaigned door to door, and people would brought in, and when people came to see me, a source of very great happiness. N
t gather groups together in their homes, any-I would get up and we'd go over and sit down
thing from ten to thirty people. I immersedmyself fr  ten to thirty people. I i mersed
were huge. There had been terrible rains that me$ Dassin and Inge Morath.
year, and there were serious drainage
problems, all the more urgent because the " °-s
buildings didn't have very solid foundations
and the state of the roads was deplorable.'`
Gradually these people's problems became my
own. One day I even took to the streets with
them agamst the police.
There were five candidates for the seat,
and I won it in the first round of voting.
I still pursued my theatrical career. Dassin
staged Brecht's ThYeepenny Opera, and it was
a huge success. Then I went to Salonika to play
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
w
WHY should the history of al-Andalus-the eight cen-
turies during which the Iberian peninsula lived under Muslim
influence-seem to many people today to be that of a golden
age ? Why is it attracting growing interest from modern
scholars, one of whom has even gone so far as to talk of
it as a " paradise lost ".
The exceptional coexistence of three cultures-Islamic,
Christian and Jewish-which was a salient feature of al-
Andalus during part of its history occurred within a historical
context marked by asperities and outbreaks of violence. From
Its beginnings in the eighth century until the fall of Granada,
the last bastion of the Muslim presence, in the fifteenth, the
history of aI-Andalus was complex and tumultuous.
But It was exceptional all the same. Al-Andalus seems
to have been a very special place where groups of people
met, talked and worked together, whereas had they lived
elsewhere at that time they would have been locked in hatred.
In spite of constant tensions, a mysterious and lasting
accord was made between a place, the people who lived there,
and the ideal they tried to put into practice-that of tolerance.
This is the extraordinary achievement of al-Andalus.
Unique in Its time, this coexistence enriched not only
the Iberian peninsula but also the Maghrib and Europe, In
ways that are only now beginning to be fully appreciated.
Through al-Andalus the foundations of Greek culture, and
elements of philosophical and scientific knowledge from
India, Persia and China were transmitted to Europe. This
Arab Spain linked Orient and Occident, past and future,
Antiquity and the Renaissance.
The present issue is an attempt, not to make a defini-
tive statement about a remarkable episode In world history
but to show some of its many facets. We have focused largely
on one period, that of the caliphate of Cordoba, the brilliant
city which was the setting for the golden age of al-Andalus.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Contact between the three cultures OM/M ? 0 yMTMS : K-MrM, MC f, M/-
lingualism, and shared customs and festivities
\/NE of the most striking features of thé
Muslim presence in Spain is the enduring
influence it exerted over Iberian Christianity. Ii
times of peace, the relationship between thé
Christian and Muslim kingdoms on the penin
sula was marked by what the French historiar
Henri Terrasse has called " a sometimes cordia
symbiosis ". There were Christian and Jewisl
communities within Islamic Spain, just as Jew :
and Muslims were later to live In the crown land :
of Castile and Aragon.
In cultural matters contacts never ceased
there was no clear-cut line of division betweer
Chess players.
An illustration from the 13th-
century Libro del Ajedrez
( " Book f Chess ").
the Islamic and Christian worlds. From the
earliest days of the Arab-Berber conquest, an
extraordinary ethnic mixing took place In al-
Andalus. In the Islamic melting-pot, Arabs,
Berbers brought up In the Arab culture and
Christians, whether share-croppers or high-born
landed proprietors. intermarried with one
another and with the urban middle classes to
form a fairly homogeneous whole. Sustained con-
tact between Muslims and Spaniards obliged the
conquerors to learn Romance, a derivative of the
Iberian Latin that was the language of the
country, and one which the Mozarabs or
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Arabized Christians also used as a common
dialect. Meanwhile, some young Christians In the
ninth century began to turn away from Latin cul-
ture and their traditional religious education.
Some of them could read and write in Arabic,
knew pre-Islamic poetry and took up the study
of Arabic literature.
Andalusian Jews spoke Romance and Arabic
in addition to Hebrew. Installed In Spain since
Roman times, Jewish communities gave proof of
their loyalty to the Umayyad dynasty and were
not persecuted. Eight generations of Jews In al-
Andalus were to benefit from the tolerance and
protection of the Umayyad rulers.
An intellectual
and linguistic ferment
A substantial proportion of Spain's Islamic popu-
lation was bilingual. The Muslims of al-Andalus
used Romance colloquially and even In their
palaces.'Abd al-Rahman III, caliph of Cordoba
from 912 until 961 and himself the son of a Chris-
tian captive, switched easily between Arabic and
Romance when talking to his courtiers. Imperme-
able to fanaticism, he displayed exceptional toler-
ance and open-mindedness.
Two examples of his magnanimity are par-
ticularly striking. Rabi b. Zayd, baptised as
Recemundo, was a cultured Christian of Cordoba
who worked as a secretary in the offices of the
Umayyad chancellery and spoke Arabic as well
as Latin. The caliph sent him as a legate to the
Above, a pa) nt ! ng featuring
ladles and horsemen adorns
the vaulted roof of the
Sata de tos Reyes (Ha)) of the
Kings) n the Alhambra
palace, Granada
() ate 14th century).
Left, a page from a
13th-century Spanish version
of KaMa) wa Dlmna, a
collection ofanimal fables.
German Empire and to the court of Constan-
tinople, tasks he performed so zealously that his
employer obtained for him the bishopric of the
small Andalusian town of Elvira.
Among the dignitaries of the Cordoban court
was a Jew from Jaen named Hasday ben Shaprut,
a man of great culture. The director of a finan-
cial department, he knew Arabic, Hebrew, Latin
and Greek as well as the Romance dialects. He
acted as interpreter into Arabic when Christian
envoys arrived In the capital, and also translated
into Arabic Discorides'medical treatise, sent to
'Abd al-Rahman III by the Byzantine Emperor
Constantine VII.
A distinguished doctor as well as a capable
diplomat, he successfully carried out a difficult
mission to the Christian territories, In the course
of which he helped cure King Sancho I of Leon
of obesity and also obtained ten strongholds from
the king's grandmother, old Queen Toda of
Navarre, in return for a Cordoban alliance.
Thanks to the caliph's protection, Hasday was
able to act as a patron for the Jewish writers of
Islamic Spain, and the symbiosis of Jewish and
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Arabic culture was evident in the work that
resulted. The Judaeo-Spanish poet Dunash ben
Labrat even persuaded his Jewish compeers to
adopt Arabic metres for their Hebrew verses,
while the brilliant philologist Hayyudj rivalled
the Arab grammarians.
In the Spain of three religions, the Jews were
notable for their multilingualism. Spanish Jews
acted as interpreters between Christians and
Muslims. The degree to which the Jewish com-
munity in the emirate of Granada was accultu-
rated has been frequently remarked upon.
Boabdil, the last sultan of Granada, had two
Jewish Interpreters, Isaac Perdoniel and his son-
in-law Yehuda. Reviving a tradition set in the
twelfth century by the famous theologian and
doctor Ibn Maymun (Moses Maimonides), several
of whose works were composed In Arabic, the
last Jewish poet of Granada, Se'adiyah ibn Danan,
wrote his grammatical works in Arabic. When
Malaga fell to the Catholic Kings In 1487, it was
noted that several Jewish women emerged from
the town speaking Arabic and wearing Muslim
dress.
The Castilian language borrowed much from
Arabic. There were elaborate linguistic contacts,
and many Arabic words entered the Iberian lan-
guages In the Middle Ages. The influence still sur-
vives in modern Spanish, particularly In the
specialized vocabularies of irrigation, fortifica-
tion, civics, urban life, commerce, botany and
food.
The transmission
of knowledge
In terms of cultural exchange, Islamic Spain was
a link In the transmission of Hellenistic science
and Greek philosophy to the Christian West. In
Toledo throughout the twelfth century, scholars
brought together on the initiative of the arch-
bishop, Don Raimundo, translated the most
influential works of Arab culture into Latin,
notably treatises on astronomy, medicine, physics,
natural history and philosophy. The translators
of Toledo spread through medieval Europe the
works of Aristotle, Galen and Hippocrates, with
commentaries by thinkers as distinguished as
Avicenna and Averroes. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Left. a page from Samuel ben
Ttbbon's 14th-century Hebrew
translation ofthe Guide of the
Perplexed by Moses
Maimonides.
Right, a page from an Arabic
version (12th-13th century) of
De Materia Medica,  treatise
on pharmacology by the
Greek nhvsician DiMcoridM
18
A century later, in 1251, the Infante Alfonso
of Castile, the son of Ferdinand III the Holy, had
the famous collection of fables known as the
Kalila wa-Dimna translated from Arabic into
Castilian. In the following centuries this was to
have a pronounced influence on Western litera-
ture, notably on the. Roman de Renart, on Boc-
caccio's Decameron, and on the 7/M of La
Fontaine.
When he became king In 1252, Alfonso sur-
rounded himself with jurists and men of science,
with historians and troubadours. He set in
motion the work of translating and adapting into
Castilian the heritage of Arabic culture. Muslims,
Christians and Arabic-speaking Jews all collabo-
rated in the task, among them Fernando of
Toledo, Juan of Aspa, Rabi Zag, Moses ha
Cohen, Abraham Alfaquin of Toledo and Master
Bernaldo el Arabigo.
In Murcia, Alfonso X founded the first college
in which adepts of the three religions could follow
the courses of the Arab scholar Muhammad al-
Riquti, originally from the district of Ricote, who
had stayed in the town after the entry of the
Castilian forces in 1266.
A model
of civilization
The pattern of life In Christian Spain was strongly
influenced by Arab civilization. From the early
Middle Ages onwards, the refined customs of the
Muslim towns penetrated the little Christian
courts of the north of the Iberian peninsula. They
brought the aristocracy a taste for luxury and a
sense of comfort.
Later, Muslim ways were adopted by the
Christian elites of Castile and Aragon. The
enthusiasm for things Arabic and Jewish shown by
Pedro I of Castile (1350-69) is often quoted by way
of example. In 1418, King Alfonso V of Aragon
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
wore a silk-bordered toque and gold-embroidered
vestments sent to him, along with other gifts, by
the Sultan of Granada, Muhammad VIII.
A European traveller, Leon of Rosmithal,
Baron of Bohemia, was astonished at the welcome
he received at Burgos in the palace of a powerful
lord when he visited Spain in 1466. Among the
Castilian count's entourage were several women
dressed in Muslim fashion, and he was offered
Arab-style food. In Segovia, King Henry IV of
Castile surrounded himself with Muslims and
Jews. Rosmithal recorded that he ate, drank and
dressed in the Muslim manner.
Shared games
and festivals
Some games were popular in both communities.
Chess, known in Arabic as skitrandj, was
introduced to Cordoba in the ninth century by
the musician ZIryab. It won great popularity in
al-Andalus, and was soon introduced to the
kingdom of Leon under the name of ajedrez. In
King Alfonso X's reign, it was the favourite
pastime of Castilians. The king and his wife,
Queen Violante of Aragon, shared their passion
for the game with knights and ladies of the court,
soldiers and monks, nobles and peasants, Muslims
and Jews.
Muslims and Christians also both staged
jousting tournaments. Lists were set up in the
main squares and gardens of Granada, and even
in the Alhambra itself. In the Jaen region on the
Feast of St. John, the Andalusian nobility fer-
vently competed in the juego de MM, a sport at
which the Muslims also excelled. A delegation of
the King of Granada achieved great success at the
court of John II of Castile by practising this form
of jousting before the monarch.
Besides the specifically Muslim festivals, two
seasonal festivals fixed by the Julian calendar
which indicated the different periods of the fiscal
and agricultural year, were celebrated In
Andalusia. They were known by their Persian
names : Nayruz was the Iranian New Year, while
Mahradjan fell on 24 June. In the towns and the
countryside of al-Andalus, people of all social
classes commemorated these days with entertain-
ments and merry-making.
There were carnival disguises and celebrations
in the Andalusian towns just as there were in
Christian Spain. In Andalusian poetry of the
eleventh and twelfth centuries there are frequent
references to Christian religious festivals, espe-
cially Easter, known as/M&.
As early as the twelfth century, the Muslims
of al-Andalus bought pastries to celebrate the
Christian New Year and Maundy Thursday. In
the second half of the thirteenth century, Andalu-
sians began to celebrate Christmas and New Year
in imitation of their Christian neighbours. On
1 January by the Julian calendar, the day they
called Yannayr, Andalusians gave each other
presents and cooked raised pastries shaped like
towns, called mada'in, thereby anticipating the
later Christian custom of making Twelfth-cakes
for Twelfth Night, though without small gifts
hidden within the pastry casing, t
RACHEL AR) E,
French istorian and Arabist.
doctor honoris causa of the
University of Granada. is
research director at the French
National Centre of Scientific
Research (CNRS) in Paris.
Among her publications are a
study on " Muslim Spain at the
time of the Nasrids
(1232-1492)" (De Boccard
publishers, Paris. 1990) and a
volume of studies on the
civilization f Muslim Spain
(E. J. Brill publishers. Leyden.
1990).
" TreeslIcsoz i b F `
nficrtce, 
_ 
galy re t 
   :
Ivlcris kigs. Trt a s. 
av bee inented b  
 ; : :
thea : tres az glic . : 
thaugh tley vere,    
xFF ere  : 5 c  
dcba s tle oly e it : .
. ;.-' ;''
.mJKc Me,
'MMnA
. have.t tres'
pets
. dobtwas'the Q$ ! y
'Geametty,
te'moawch,'
''
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The social and historical ! 0/ C ? t MOC
ofcKKM/-- M M
T
THE periods between 711 and 1086 AD in the
Islamic territories of aI-AndaIus and between 1085
and 1370 in Christian Spain were golden ages of
social and cultural coexistence. What religious and
legal foundations were they based on ?
Judaism never defined a social status for other
religions, since until the Babylonian diaspora it
considered itself the only monotheistic faith.
Thereafter, when It lost its political independence,
its own social status became identified with that
of the Jewish people.
At first Christianity too had no status as an
independent social entity. Saint Paul directed
Christians to accept the Roman Empire, to pay
taxes to it, obey Its magistrates and observe its
Deta)) from a 12th-century
Andaluslan Qur'an.
laws, holding that the power it exercised was
God-given. It was only after the conversion of
Constantine's day, when Christianity became the
civic religion of the Empire, and the Empire was
Christianized by the Church, that the tolerance
early Christianity had shown was gradually
eroded.
In the Middle Ages, Christians came to con-
sider Jews as deniers of the faith because they had
refused to regard Jesus of Nazareth as the
promised Messiah, and as deicides insofar as they
were held collectively responsible for his death.
As for Islam, medieval Christians at first consi-
dered it a fraud and its prophet, Muhammad, an
impostor. This view was only gradually modified
as a result of cultural coexistence on the Iberian
peninsula.
Islam, on the other hand, took as a starting-
point the fundamental unity of the Faith, as
revealed to the first man, reiterated by all the
prophets, and socially codified by divine mes-
sengers, notably by Moses in the 7b for the
Jews and by Jesus in the Gospels for Christians.
Muhammad was then sent in his turn because
these religious laws had become distorted and
were incomplete. For Muslims, Muhammad is the
final messenger, the seal set on the work of the
prophets, and the Qur'an is the true and defini-
tive revelation of the Faith.
Muslims consequently considered Jews and
Christians as People of the Book (Ahl al-Kitab),
whose incomplete systems of belief nonetheless
allowed them to know and venerate God, to
understand and obey His commandments, and to
merit eternal salvation.
People of the pact
Following the principles spelled out in the
Qur'an, Islam gave full recognition to only one
social grouping, the « K77M, the community of the
faithful, whose members are theoretically equal.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The apothecary,
a mural of glazed and pain
ti) es (azufe/os) executed at
Seville around 1900.
But the faith expanded into lands that were
socially highly organized and inhabited largely
by Christians and Zoroastrians, with Jewish and
Buddhist minorities. AI-AndaIus, with Its
Mozarabs and Jews, was one of these lands. All
those who possessed a revealed Book and who
agreed to a position of subordination by signing a
pact became " tributaries ". There was no legal
problem where Christians and Jews were con-
cerned. Zoroastrians, initially at least, were granted
a similar status, even though they were not con-
sidered to have a revealed Book.
Legally speaking, the tributaries did not
belong to the umma, but enjoyed protected status
as dhimmis or " people of the pact", and were
implicitly treated as the members of another
society, which did not exist in political terms but
whose religious structure assumed responsibility
for administering the tolerated social rights.
The relationship between the umma and the
ahl al-Kitab was based on the concept of a pact
which could be either expressed or tacit. In the
Christian context, the parties to the pact were,
on the one hand, the Christian nobility and
bishops, and on the other the caliph. The accord
held good not just for the Umayyad rulers of al-
Andalus but also for those of the taifas, the petty
kingdoms that flourished after the collapse of the
caliphate.
When, from the ninth century on, the Chris-
tian kingdoms of the Iberian peninsula began to
englobe sizeable Jewish and Islamic
communities-the latter of which were known
as M<e/7'M-the Christian kings took up the
Islamic policy of offering protected status. As the
incarnation of the link between the different com-
munities, the kings of Castile and Leon even
assumed, in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries,
the title of " Lord of the Three Religions ".
A unique social fabric
The way In which medieval Islamic society was
organized does not easily lend itself to forms of
class analysis practised by modern social science.
In any case, the cohabitation of Muslims with
dhimmis (Mozarabs and Jews) took different
forms in the different social strata within each
community, and the relationships that were estab-
lished did not always exactly coincide with those
prescribed by law.
Social cohabitation and cultural coexistence
worked to the advantage of the Islamic
aristocracy, the khassa, which consisted of the
ruling family and the upper ranks of the military
and civil authorities, and of the freedmen and
clients of the monarch. The notables of Islamic
society (a'yan)-men of learning, successful
craftsmen, merchants and great land-owners-also
benefited from the arrangement. The masses, on
the other hand, found it hard to live alongside
Mozarabs and Jews.
Among the Mozarabs, those who had the
closest cultural connections with Muslims were
the nobility ; a class composed of the descendants
of the Visigothic comites, the upper ranks of the
clergy and some scholars. We know from the
writings of such strong champions of the 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Mozarabic identity as Alvaro and Eulogio of Cor-
doba that they associated with Muslims, shared
their literary tastes and fashions, and even took
pride in speaking good Arabic.
As for the Jews, the guides (rabbis and
scholars), rich merchants, traders and financiers
also associated with the Islamic and Mozarabic
upper classes, but had almost no dealings with
the lower social orders. Cultural coexistence
between Jews and Muslims was, however, more
tangible than that between Muslims and
Mozarabs, because the Jews had accepted Arabic
as their language of thought and culture.
The law known as the fiqh maliki proved an
effective instrument for regulating the relations
between the different social groups. It had origi-
nated in certain traditional Arab usages dating
from the pre-lslamic period that reflected the
influence of Roman jurisprudence and had
provided a basis for the " canonical " principles
of Islam.
Craftsmen, shopkeepers, merchants and small
landowners of the Mozarabic and Jewish com-
munities were able to maintain their traditional
way of life without much difficulty. Obviously,
though, this process of convergence broke down
whenever religious disputes arose.
Patterns of coexistence
Cultural coexistence took many forms, weaving
a pattern of contact and tradition, creation and
rediscovery. It was of decisive importance in the
eighth, ninth and tenth centuries, when the legal
and ideological principles that gave it Its justifi-
cation were working satisfactorily.
The contact between external influences,
Above, an frustration from th<
Spanish monk Beatus of
Llebana's Commentary on the
Apocatypse, a manuscript
produced atthe abbey of
Saint-Sever (southwestern
France) ! n the middle of the
llth century. The scene ! s
from a part of the manuscript
devoted to the genealogy of
Chrtst. The tnftuence of Arabic
art ts notable.
Left. the menorah (a
candelabrum with seven
branches) ! s shown ! n thts
miniature from a Hebrew Bib) t
illuminated by Joseph
Assartatt a Cervera ! n Spain
() ate 12th century).
notably Islamic cultural imports from the Orient,
and intellectual life in Muslim Spain, was
genuinely extraordinary, as a glance at the art,
astronomy, mathematics, medicine and thought
of the caliphate shows. The cultural legacy of al-
Andalus is impressive in its scale and splendour
even though, for obvious reasons, Mozarab cul-
ture was closed to some aspects of Islamic
thought. Jewish thinking, on the other hand, was
so open to Muslim influences that two parallel
yet communicating currents are apparent in
Andalusian philosophy : on the one hand the
Arab-Islamic tradition of Avempace, Ibn Tufayl
and Averroes, on the other the Judaeo-Arab
heritage of Ibn Gabirol and Maimonides, thinkers
who used Arabic as their medium of expression.
There were certainly differences between
Islamic and Jewish culture, but they did not
extend to such common and universal fields as
astronomy, mathematics, science, medicine, logic
and metaphysics. One example, taken from my
own speciality, philosophy, will suffice to show
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
the creative possibilities that sprang from cultural
coexistence.
Comparisons have often been made between
the Summa contra gentiles of St. Thomas Aquinas,
Maimonides'Guide of the Perplexed and Averroes's
Incoherence of the 7coAerccc, a rebuttal of al-
Ghazali's work Te/McoC7-CMce o/c t/o.
It is undeniable that the three works are unique
of their kind and in their time. The similarities
between them lie in certain common themes of
medieval thought, in the use of certain formal
procedures, and In their method.
It is true that the Incoherence of the Incoher-
ence cannot be understood without reference to
specifically Islamic ideas ; similarly, the Guide of
the Perplexed raws on the rabbinical tradition,
and the Summa contra gentiles on the Christian
Inheritance. Yet all three heritages share a
common link with Greek thought, but not as it
had been recreated by Islamic philosophy.
The relationship between the three works Is
a complex one, full of reciprocal influences. Two
MtGUEL CRUZ HERNANDEZ.
of Spain, is professor f
Islamic thought at the
Autonomous University of
Madrid and formerly taught at
the Universities of Granada
and Salamanca. Among his
many published works are a
2-volute history of thought in
the Islamic world (1981). a
history of thought in ai-Andaius
(1985) and a study on the life.
work. thought and influence of
Averroes <1986).
of them were written by Andalusian thinkers,
and even the third-the Summa-would not have
been possible without the contribution of the
ideas of Avicenna and Averroes, passed on via
translations made In Toledo. After Aristotle,
Averroes Is the author most frequently cited by
St. Thomas.
Cultural coexistence of this kind was made
possible by religious and legal principles that were
far-reaching In their implications even though
they were often transgressed In practice. The
Andalusian experience was an exceptional
moment In history, probably unique In Its own
time and rarely matched In any other. Its most
worthy, notable and creative feature was that
cohabitation and coexistence were based on reli-
gious and legal principles. Our own era, which
prides itself on the liberalism and universality of
Its ideas, offers few examples to match It. t
/'"''.''a. 
In Spait 
re 
; eraticn c, ann,  
 t, '
the barbariazj hnrdes : t rr t.
the Arb rrqercrs.,.,.   a 
 ·
ctia far tnre t 
 in..,. ' : 
to us iat yug, rrbst, 
u 
'
.'t Spam
aer its it that i ` ̀    `
'the. ! M [rb ' ! Mt
A-<X ! a'pera ! . S ;
boht vith it c , 
& : oa  BMtMsSS
teastMyK&t. 
t was  Ceit
lie ari ad 
repd C i   y4rt   'xy
trozg t  `
 S'Yf tf 
 
f
cocd it : vr - ,
lit ta, ys 
ef tt
EttiL I lI1'PSt1 ti ; 
ii W a t
  
 S
4j  : r x  tly t,'t `'  
k
'the. sMM''
x ss` w'iiiStil Ttt tl. ̀   t  r 
 
. of JaaMB 
.
. toics Chia' ; '''y. . 
-.-.-.'''*''-.' :/-----'--.''/-''-- ? <'t--'''''-. 
.
ttr a&.
'
'
,
saeac'
.. ..''
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
7M an exiled nMCC M ! CM SMCCO CTMM  MMMP Mf <MMt
between Orient and Occident
) ated ! nes tndtcate th
txtenston of Islamic territory
n the) ber) an pen) ntu) a in
! 50. 1100, 1200 and 1257.
i. N the year 93 of the Islamic era-the Hijra-
and 711 of the Christian era, the great Muslim
Arab empire was ruled from Damascus in Syria
by al-Walid I, sixth caliph of the House of
Umayya. From Kairouan in the country now
called Tunisia, al-Walid's governor, Musa ibn
Nusayr, was pursuing a policy of westward
expansion spearheaded by his Berber freedman
Tariq, commander of some 7, 000 Berbers from
North Africa. Before the end of the spring of 93
Tariq was on the rock from which Gibraltar takes
its name-Jabal Tariq, " Mount Tariq ".
Tariq's landing was the first step on a long,
hard road which led 200 years later to the estab-
lishment of the caliphate of Cordoba by a scion
of the House of Umayya. The second step was
the conquest of the lands beyond Gibraltar. With
his Berber troops, greatly reinforced from North
Africa, Tariq soon defeated the Visigothic King
Rodrigo, already harassed in the north by the
Basques. The tottering, unpopular Visigothic
regime was now doomed. The fall of its capital,
Toledo, to the north was followed in October
711 by the capture of Cordoba in the south.
July 712 saw Musa himself in the Iberian
peninsula. Grudging his freedman the glory of
conquest, he had crossed the Straits of Gibraltar
with some 18, 000, mainly Arab, troops. His rela-
tionship with Tariq was strained, but this did not
prevent them from pursuing their common
objective of conquest. By 714 Musa and Tariq had
conquered all but the most inaccessible parts of
the peninsula and gained for the Umayyad crown
in Damascus a jewel of impressive resplendence.
To this new, rich province the Arabs gave the
name " al-Andalus ", which is thought to derive
from " Vandalicia ", the name the Vandals gave
to the old Roman province of Baetica In southern
Spain. In English, " al-Andalus " is often translated
as " Andalusia ", but in its strict sense it designates
Muslim Spain.
Like Rome, the Cordoba of the Umayyad
caliphate was not built in a day. The glitter of
that golden city did not materialize like Aladdin's
genie at the rub of a magic lamp. It was born of
the Umayyad emirate, and behind its glitter there
lay a long and complex history.
The establishment of
the Umayyad emirate in Spain
In 750 the'Abbasid revolution in the east swept
away the Syrian Umayyad caliphate and savagely
butchered its princes. Miraculously, one of the
latter,'Abd al-Rahman, grandson of the caliph
Hisham, cheated his hunters of their prey and
embarked on a perilous odyssey that took him
to Morocco, where he won the protection of his
mother's Berber tribe. After careful thought he
decided to go to Spain, banking on support from
elements owing loyalty to the Umayyads. Once
on Andalusian soil, he played his hand and
won-despite some militant opposition to his
cause. In May 756, his final battle won, he entered
the provincial palace of Cordoba. There, in the
city's mosque, he led the Eriday prayer and was
proclaimed emir of al-Andalus. A young man in
his mid-twenties at the time, he was to reign for
over thirty years as the first of five Umayyad
rulers of Spain to bear the name'Abd al-Rahman.24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Copy of a map by ai-istakhri
showing the Iberian peninsula
(right) and North Africa
(14th century).
The establishment of the emirate was on !)
the start of a gruelling climb to power whos<
complexity is explained by the pattern of Andalu
sian society at that time. Al-Andaius was ;
country in which Arab and Berber immigrant :
had, at different times and under differing con
ditions, settled among the great mass of thé
HIspano-Roman population. Many Hispano
Romans had converted to Islam and, as neo
Muslims (muwalladun), become completel)
Arabized. Yet there remained a large Christiar
HIspano-Roman community of Mozarabs- :
term taken from the Spanish form of an Arabi (
word meaning " Arabizer ". As well as their owr
language, the Mozarabs spoke Arabic and adoptee
many Arab customs. Finally, there were the
native Iberian Jews.
The Mozarabs and Jews caused'Abd al
Rahman no trouble. They were only too glad tc
be rid of Visigothic tyranny and to live in peace
The Arabs, however, were to turn any dream :
of peace he may have cherished into something
of a nightmare born of tribal feuds, jealousies anc
grievances, which led to sedition, armed conflict
and open rebellion. Moreover, the Berber :
resented not being treated as equals by their Arab
fellow-Muslims, whose traditions and culture
were quite different from their own.
And so, the prospect of revolts and uprising :
was very real. The emir perceived the risk oJ
siding with any single group within al-AndaIus
He could count on unselfish loyalty from no one
not even from his Umayyad relations and clients
And so he recruited a highly disciplined profes
sional army of Berber mercenaries and slave
troops from Europe north of the Pyrenees. This
was the only answer to internal turmoil anc
external danger from the Christian north.
'Abd aI-Rahman was a Syrian, and the
administrative system he created In Muslim Spain
was in the Syrian Umayyad tradition. At It<
centre he made his own office of emir a unifying
symbol, and in the provinces he appointed loyal
and capable governors.
When he died In 788, he could be said to have
proved himself an extraordinarily able statesman ;
whose greatest achievement had been to pacify
and defend his realm. Today we see him as the
founder of a dynasty that lasted more than twice
as long as that of his Syrian ancestors and became
a light that far outshone the brightest lights In
contemporary Europe.
An eventful history
All his successors sought, with varying degree*
of success, to consolidate their political and mill-
tary strength In a situation that was fraught with
danger.
In many areas of the Iberian peninsula corn-
munications and transport militated against firm
central control. Local notables, appointed a<
governors to uphold Umayyad authority in
regions far from Cordoba, acted as powerful over
lords serving not their ruler's interests but their
own, and often taking the opportunity to rebel.
This was particularly the case in the"Marches".
sprawling tracts of nomansland separating the
Christian realms to the north from the emirate's
Muslim lands In the south.
The attitudes of the nee-Muslims and
Mozarabs also changed, leading to insurrection
and disorder. Cordoba itself was the home of cer-
tain Muslim political and religious malcontents. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The site teofMad) nata)-Zahra'
the ceremonial capital of the
Umayyads founded tn the
10th century near Cordoba.
At the same time, the emirate was saddled with
the perennial need to protect its northern borders
against Christian invaders.
During the reign of ai-Hakam I (796-822)
there was a spate of troubles : disaffection in
Toledo, savagely crushed in 797 by the massacre
of its mainly neo-Muslim notables ; the mass
uprising in 818 of the so-called Suburb
( " Arraval ") of Cordoba, encouraged by disgrun-
tled Muslim religious leaders and ruthlessly put
down ; protracted campaigns In the Marches of
Saragossa, Toledo and Merida against recalcitrant
leaders ; and, finally, the permanent loss of Barce-
lona to the Christians.
The emirate faced two other thorny
problems. First, the initially peaceful Mozarabs
became involved in a serious religious protest
begun by Christian fanatics seeking martyrdom
through public denunciation of the Prophet
Muhammad. The protest, starting late in the reign
of the kind and tolerant ruler'Abd al-Rahman
II (822-852), led to tensions and conflicts which
neither the prince nor many of his Christian sub-
jects relished. Secondly and more importantly,
the reign of Muhammad I (852-886), witnessed
In 880 a determined attempt by Ibn Hafsun, a
rebel of neo-Muslim descent and later an apostate,
to make himself ruler of aI-AndaIus from his
centre of power, Bobastro, in the south of Spain.
His insurrection, which commanded wide non-
Arab support, dragged on for almost fifty years.
Largely because of ai-Hakam I's draconian
measures to enforce peace, his son'Abd al-
Rahman II, a very able monarch, enjoyed some
thirty years of relative calm and prosperity,
marked by significant improvements in the
administrative system and a sharp rise in stan-
dards of culture and civilization. The emir's
enthusiastic patronage of music and the arts was
matched only by his zealous preoccupation with
the creation of a strong navy capable of out-
classing Norse squadrons that had found his
shores a gateway to rich pickings.
An exceptional ruler
The most disastrous period In the emirate's his-
tory came with the reign of'Abd Allah (888-912),
whose legacy to his grandson and successor'Abd
aI-Rahman III (912-961) was nothing but an
empty treasury and the general disintegration of
Umayyad Spain. This legacy of leaden metal was
to be miraculously transmuted into gold by the
alchemy of a ruler who at the time of his acces-
sion was barely in his twenties. Endowed with
patience, emotional stability and maturity of
judgement beyond his years, the young'Abd al-
Rahman combined the energy and stamina of
youth with political acumen and unswerving
devotion to duty. As much European as Arab-
his mother and paternal grandmother were of
Christian stock-he was an observant Muslim but
no fanatic. Throughout his reign he adopted,
whenever possible, a generally tolerant policy
towards Mozarabs and Jews.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Upon his succession,'Abd aI-Rahman
brooked no opposition to his authority.
Governors who refused or ignored his request for
allegiance had to yield either to diplomatic per-
suasion or to force. In 913 he imposed his rule
on the important city of Seville. The next year
saw the start of a long war of attrition against Ibn
Hafsun of Bobastro, the master of much of
southern Spain. The struggle, continued by his
sons after his death In 917, ended only in 928.
It was not until 932 that the pacification of al-
Andalus was complete, with the submission of
the AIgarve, eastern Spain, Toledo, Saragossa and
other important strongholds.
The apogee of the caliphate
The most memorable event in Spanish Umayyad
history took place in 929 : the establishment of
the caliphate. In proclaiming himself caliph,'Abd
aI-Rahman III assumed, In addition to the caliphal
title " Commander of the Faithful ", the throne-
name"Defender (aI-Nasir) of God's Religion ".
The decision to revive the caliphate, lost by the
Syrian Umayyads in 750, was largely his response
to the growing power and prestige of the Shi'ite
Fatimids, who had proclaimed their own
caliphate in North Africa and were coming dan-
gerously near to al-Andalus.
When he died In 961, al-Nasir had enforced
respect for the frontiers of a country united under
J DEREK LATHAM,
of the United Kingdom. Doctor
of Letters in the University of
Oxford, isprofessor emeritus
of Arabic and Islamic Studies
and former head of the Muir
Institute in the University of
Edinburgh. He has been joint
general editor and contributor
to The Cambridge History or
Arabic Literature and a
contributor to Encyclopaedia of
Islam (new edition). Notable
among his other published
works are Isaac Judaeus : On
Fevers (Arabic text and English
translation with notes. 1980).
and From Muslim Spain to
Barbary : Studies in the History
and Culture or the Muslim
West (1986).
The field of intelligence
While the West saw the soft, lunar reflection of God,
the East and Arab and Jewish Spain contemplated
him In his fertile Sun, in His creative power which
pours forth His gifts in torrents. Spain was the field
of combat. Where the Christians appeared, there
was desert ; where the Arabs were, water and life
spurted forth on all sides, streams flowed, the earth
grew green, became a garden of flowers. And the
field of intelligence also flourished. What would we
barbarians have been without them ? Shameful to
say, it was not until the eighteenth century that our
Treasury adopted Arabic numerals, without which
it is impossible to carry out the smallest calculation.
Jtties Michetet
French istorian (7 ! brMc ct. RetMM&Mce, t855)
a strong central government. Me had made al-
Andalus second to none in the Western world,
prospering thanks to a thriving domestic
economy and a lucrative network of pan-
Mediterranean trade. Cordoba, with about ten
times the population of Paris, far outshone any
other capital in Europe. In reputation and pres-
tige, it surpassed Baghdad and rivalled Byzantine
Constantinople, through diplomatic exchanges
with which the caliph had ensured that his realm
was seen as its equal. European envoys from
France, Germany, Italy and elsewhere had eagerly
made their way to his court. In addition to mis-
sions from North Africa, part of which he actu-
ally ruled, he had received delegations from Chris-
tian Spain, some of whose rulers he had made his
tributaries.
His successor, aI-Hakam II (961-976), was able
to preserve his father's heritage of peace and
prosperity. One of the biggest and best libraries
of Islam was born of his passion for books and
learning-a passion which also compelled him to
promote scholarship, both religious and secular
(astronomy and mathematics, for example), and
to provide some education for the poor. In the
Great Mosque of Cordoba, which stands to this
day as a lasting memorial to Umayyad glory, he
expressed his deep piety and refined artistic taste
by almost doubling Its size through the addition
of a most pleasing extension and enhancing its
prayer niche with ornamentation so exquisite as
to make it a masterpiece.
Al-Hakam's death was the death of true
Umayyad rule. The reign of his son HIsham II
(976-1013)-a mere boy at the time of his
accession-led to the caliphate's slide into extinc-
tion in 1031. t
Smat ! tvory casket bearing
the name of at-Mughira.
one of the sons of'Abd a !-
Rahman III, the illustrious
Umayyad caliph of Cordoba
(10th century).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The mMg K-nc o  -ctMry c M/
D
BEFORE the foundation of the Umayyad
caliphate by'Abd al-Rahman III at Cordoba in
929, the cultural and scientific development of
Muslim Spain had been that of a modest offshoot
of a simple provincial Arab Muslim culture that
was highly dependent on Oriental Islam.
Under the caliphate a cultural flowering came
about, largely because Cordoba became increas-
ingly important politically. The city was the
centre of a strong and respected power which
sought, consciously or unconsciously, to equal
the prestige of the'Abbasid caliphate of Baghdad
at the height of its splendour and to create in al-
Andalus the conditions for similar achievements.
The Andalusians did not aspire to create a new
civilization but to imitate or outstrip Baghdad in
every field.
We must beware of the chronological errors
that are often made by those who attribute en
bloc to the Cordoban caliphate all the cultural
achievements of the Andalusian civilization. To
take one example, the oldest and not least original
parts of the Great Mosque of Cordoba were
The interior of the Great
Mosque ofthe Umayyads in
Damascus (Syria), founded
in 705.
completed under the emirate, not during the
caliphate. It was only after the caliphate, at the
time of the taifas (principalities governed by petty
kings) that Andalusian poetry attained its greatest
refinement. Some of the best-known monuments
of Muslim Andalusian art, such as the Giralda
(the minaret of the Almoravid mosque in Seville)
and the Alhambra palace, built by the sultans of
Granada from the late thirteenth century
onwards, date from long after the time of the
caliphs.
All the same, the most remarkable achieve-
ments of Arab Andalusian culture do bear the
imprint of the relatively short-lived caliphate,
which only lasted around a century.
An influential
capital
In the tenth century Cordoba became one of the
leading political and cultural centres of the
Muslim world, a city comparable in importance
to Baghdad and Cairo. The geographer Ibn
Hawqal, who visited Cordoba In the second half
of the century, judged It to be equal to " half of
Baghdad", and wrote that it " has no equivalent
In the whole of the Maghrib, nor in Upper
Mesopotamia, Syria or Egypt with regard to the
size of Its population, Its extent, the spaciousness
of its markets, Its cleanliness, the architecture of
its mosques and its large number of baths and
caravanserais ".
At a time when the greatest cities of Western
Europe had no more than a few thousand inhabi-
tants, Cordoba had a population of at least a
hundred thousand and extended over several
hundred hectares (tenth-century Barcelona
occupied less than ten hectares !).
The first caiiph,'Abd aI-Rahman III, who
reigned until 961, built the vast palatine city of
Madinat aI-Zahra'on the lower slopes of the hills
along the northern bank of the Guadalquivir, a
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
few kilometres downstream from Cordoba. In
contrast to the paucity of our information about
Cordoba itself, we know the precise area of this
Versailles of the Andalusian caiiphs thanks to
archaeological and written evidence. Madinat al-
Zahra'was almost completely abandoned at the
end of the caliphate, to whose wealth and power
Its ruins bear eloquent witness.
The walls enclosed about a hundred hectares,
with room for several tens of thousands of Inhabi-
tants. The city was dominated by palaces and
gardens on several evels, which have been exca-
vated and partially restored. Spanish archaeolo-
gists and architects have done notable work in
reconstituting the salon rico, a lavishly decorated
building which gave onto a wide esplanade In the
centre of which was an enormous pool. We know
from written evidence that this edifice was used
for official audiences.
The apotheosis
of the mosque
Equally sumptuous was the extension of the Cor-
doban mosque carried out by the son and suc-
cessor of'Abd al-Rahman III, aI-Hakam II, who
reigned from 961 to 976. The finest part of the
building, around the mihrab, the niche in the wall
which shows believers the direction of Mecca
towards which they must turn to pray, was
adorned with magnificent arches In a new style,
a highly complex design of interwoven, multifoil
horseshoe arches, decorated with interlaced
marble and other sculpted stonework enriched
with white or red polychrome patterns.
The polychrome decoration recalls the con-
trast between red and white In the alternating
stone and brick archstones'which were an original
feature of the oldest parts of the mosque, built
during the emirate. However, the similarity
between the two phases of construction Is limited
to a few discreet echoes of this kind. The simple
elegance of the eighth-and ninth-century arches
contrasts strongly with the exuberant ornamen-
tation of those built under aI-Hakam II, which
are a brilliant testimony to the wealth of the
caliphate at the height of Its power, and to the
inventiveness and virtuosity of the artists who
worked for it.
The most outstanding features of the part of
the Great Mosque built during the caliphate are
undoubtedly the magnificent domes In the
antechamber to the mihrab and above the cen-
tral nave leading to it. They were built using a
technique of interlaced stone arches or ribbing
which was quite new in Andalusian art, and had
a strong influence on later " Hispano-Moorish "
art from the twelfth to the fourteenth centuries.
Some art historians even believe that these original
forms of Andalusian art may have influenced the
development of ogival art in Christian Europe.
The prayer hall of the Great
Mosque, Cordoba.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Opposite page, the mfhrah of
the Great Mosque in Cordoba.
Above, deta)) of mosaic ! n the
mthrab.
Although these forms were intrinsically
decorative, and their effect was enhanced by the
polychrome work described above, the architects
and decorators of Cordoba went even further by
using mosaic. Craftsmen had to be brought from
distant lands to execute this technique, which was
rarely employed in medieval Islam. For this the
caliphate mobilized its financial resources, the
technical skills of Its craftsmen, and also its diplo-
matic relations, soliciting the help of the emperor
at Constantinople, who sent a cargo of coloured
glass cubes to Cordoba as well as a master mosal-
cist to get the work underway and instruct local
craftsmen in the intricacies of the new technique.
A cultural
crossroads
The Great Mosque reveals more strikingly than
anything else that Cordoba during the caliphate
The city with the most books
A polemical debate was held in the presence of al-
Mansur Ya'qub, king of the Maghnb, between the
philosopher Ibn Rushd (Averroes) and the chief
Abu Bakr Ibn Zohr. In the course of the debate
Ibn Rushd said to Ibn Zohr, referring to the
supremacy of C6rdoba :"I don't understand what
you say, but it so happens that if a wise man dies
In Seville and they want to sell his books, the books
are taken to C6rdoba, and that if someone wants to
get rid of his musical instruments, the instruments
are taken to Seville. " And he added :"Cordoba is
the city that has more books than any other in the
whole world."
jM. Mahm
Tunisian hiNonan (A <&lt;f-7 ! )
was a cultural crossroads. A more detailed look
at the building will help to show why this is so.
The old columns and capitals that were re-
used in the Great Mosque were brought from
Roman buildings elsewhere in Spain or even from
much farther afield, in particular from what is
today Tunisia where there were many ancient
ruins.
The origin of the horseshoe-shaped arches so
characteristic of Hispano-Muslim art is a vexed
question. The form is found occasionally in the
Middle East at the time of the Umayyads and the
possibility cannot be excluded that it was deliber-
ately imported from Syria by the emirs.
However, it is generally considered to be a bor-
rowing from Visigothic art, that is from the
indigenous architecture that existed In Spain
before the Muslim conquest.
Another original feature of the parts of the
Mosque built during the emirate is the superpo-
sition of two rows of arches, enabling the ceiling
to be raised to a greater height. This practice had
already been followed, though less elegantly and
less skilfully, in the great Umayyad mosque in
Damascus which may have inspired the first
builders of Cordoba. But it is more widely
believed that the idea was suggested by Roman
aqueducts, whose superimposed arcatures curi-
ously recall those in the Great Mosque. The use
of alternating archstones of white stone and red
brick may originate in local building methods
used during the later Roman Empire, or be
modelled on Oriental Umayyad buildings, them-
selves Byzantine in inspiration, such as the Dome
of the Rock in Jerusalem.
The caliphate adopted most of the styles
which had been used earlier during the emirate,
but enriched them considerably and added to
their complexity by intersecting arches,
introducing original features into their interfoil
decoration, and importing, probably from the
Orient, new techniques for constructing domes.
Underlying all this was a desire to exalt the gran-
deur of the Umayyads, without abandoning the
link with an earlier Syrian tradition.
The hand
of the ruling dynasty
However, we must not misunderstand the multi-
cultural character of the Cordoban caliphate. The
brilliant civilization that developed in Muslim
Spain, mainly from this period onwards, was cer-
tainly In part the result of spontaneous contact
between the cultures and traditions of the three
monotheistic religions that then coexisted on the
Iberian peninsula. But the exchanges that sprang
from the relations between Islam, Christianity and
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
:'. '. . ! M ; .'.  ; 
[ ? . '.  : .... <
f , 1 ` f
. ay the tc. t  crtts 
' :'i
' at » e tt " t`a i'.
"M'. tMW&'pS
) S ! ''
; ;,. ;-'.", 1
. 
Iat4tslli Kflwi  . 
t#  
:,. ̂', F 
i . 
 r ;
M'X$% .''
' 
1 ti1' " t'ti  * 
1*17-  s .
; :. $. M. 
e ? ''. . ; .'V"
KMW
t, t SSA't    B.
. $M ! t-') t'. : J
ii't t .. ft-.
MBt
B. . tM
'l ; e : $$./w'was
.. C'Ff
&'' ; "'
-ttW
. @tMMm$<tS
 ; M'm$
<&lt;'M
Judaism were not on a basis of equality. The hand
of the ruling dynasty is everywhere evident. The
influences that contributed to the formation of
Andalusian civilization were primarily Oriental-
'Abbasid and Byzantine. And the Umayyad State
was strictly Muslim and Arab.
It would doubtless be an exaggeration to deny
the existence of local Hispanic influences in the
development of Andalusian civilization. Even if
they had wished to do so, the eighth-century
Arab-Berber conquerors could hardly have made
a clean sweep of the peninsula's pre-Islamic past.
Many elements, even If only the materials avail-
able, remained and mingled in varying propor-
tions with those brought from the east and from
North Africa. However, these elements were re-
used in a totally different context and helped in
the creation of original structures in which many
other elements taken from the Orient played a
part.
In some cases the caliphate seems to have used
the material and human resources it concentrated
In Cordoba to create works whose originality is
startling. The carved ivory caskets which are
among the most refined achievements of tenth-
century Andalusian craftsmanship are a case In
point (see photo page 27). They have few antece-
dents, although perhaps here too we should see
a certain influence from Byzantium, where ivory
carving had reached a very high standard.
But there is no doubt about the novelty of the
style nor the source of its Inspiration, since all
these objects were made in palatine workshops.
The caliphate seems to have been to some extent a
pre-condition for the creation of these ivories,
which rank among the most beautiful achieve-
ments In the history of world art. Their manufac-
ture virtually came to an end with the disappear-
ance of the caliphate.
t
PIERRE GUICHARD,
professor f medieval history
at the Universite Lumiere Lyon
2. is a French istorian who
specializes in the relations
between Muslims and
Christians i  the Iberian
peninsula during the Middle
Ages. Notable among his
published works are studies on
Muslim Spain and Sicily in the
llth and 12th centuries
(Presses Universitaires d
Lyon, 1990) and on the
Muslims ofValencia and the
Reconquest from the 11t to
the 13th century (published by
the French Institute,
Damascus, 1991).
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Arabized Christians of Spain
tn)  t'0 CM/tMnM   ?
intermediaries between two worlds
w
WHO were the Mozarabs and what contribu-
tion did they make to Andalusian civilization ?
In its strict sense the term Mozarab, which only
appeared in the eleventh century, designates an
Arabized Christian, but it is more widely used
to designate the Christians of the Iberian penin-
sula who lived under Islamic domination.
The result of a complex process of rejection
of and assimilation with the dominant society and
culture, the Mozarabic community was far from
homogeneous. The " real " Mozarabs were people
who were more or less profoundly assimilated.
The status of the Christians of aI-AndaIus
depended on their initial attitudes to the Invader.
Many of them came to terms with the latter and
carved out Christian enclaves in the newly
Muslim lands. The people of cities such as
Coimbra and Santarem, which did not offer
resistance to the Invader, were spared and kept
their prerogatives. Those which did resist some-
times paid a heavy price.
Once the lands were divided among the
different groups of conquerors, the Christians
were allowed to enjoy their land and liberty In
exchange for tribute in the form of a land-tax,
the jarach, and a poll-tax, the djizia. These tributes
became more onerous as time went by and other
exceptional forms of taxation were added to
them, provoking violent outbreaks of social dis-
content.
Like the Jews, the other people of the Book,
the Christians were allowed to keep their laws,
to retain and when the case arose to choose their
civic and religious leaders, and to practise their
religion freely. At first new monasteries were
built In Cordoba as guardians of the Christian
tradition and centres of culture where Latin
remained alive. It was only later that discrimina-
Moses bars the Egyptians
from crossing the Red Sea.
Miniature froma 10th-century
Mozarabic Bible pr served in
Leon (Spain).
tory measures appeared, such as the duty of
wearing distinctive garments and the refusal of
permission to build new places of worship.
Assimilation
and martyrdom
No statistics are available with which to trace the
course of the Islamization of the peninsula.
Doubtless this came about in stages, starting with
the rural areas where Christianization was not
deeply rooted. The practice of mixed marriages
and the close neighbourly links which were estab-
lished between peasant communities led in the
long run to a natural erosion of Christianity.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Where Christianity did survive, It sometimes
took unorthodox forms. The Mozarabs were
attracted by certain heresies uch as adoptianism
which, by denying the divinity of Christ, seemed
to bear some resemblance to Islam. Christianity,
even in its dogmatic version, eventually assimilated
certain Islamic practices such as circumcision,
food taboos and even, surreptitiously, bigamy.
Assimilation also took place in the other
direction. The Muslims, while remaining faithful
to their religion, came to take part in the main
Christian festivals. Language played a decisive
role in this process of intermingling. While
Mozarabic, a Romance language, was widely
spoken (it was even used at court and in the
administration), and used in folk literature,
Arabic was adopted by the Christians as the lan-
guage of culture.
In the Arab-Andalusian melting-pot, Arabi-
zation was thus a factor of integration, the course
of which was not, however, entirely smooth. In
the ninth century, a group of Mozarabs who were
partly Arabized but remained profoundly
attached to their Christian and Visigothic roots,
were willing to sacrifice their lives in order to
preserve their identity. Most of these candidates
for voluntary martyrdom were the offspring of
mixed unions, and were thus in the eyes of society
Muslims. By making the supreme sacrifice, they
wished to denounce the attitudes of other Chris-
tians whom they considered to be too lukewarm
and assimilated. Because they feared reprisals,
many Mozarabs then preferred to convert to
Islam whilst others, wishing to keep their Chris-
tian faith, chose to take the path of exile towards
the Christian lands in the north of the peninsula.
In the tenth century, when the Cordoba
caliphate was at the height of Its splendour, a
period of peace opened for the Mozarabs. To turn
their talents to full account, some of them drew
on their dual cultural affiliations. The Calendar
of Cordoba by Recemundo (Ibn Zaid), a man of
a great culture, as versed in Latin as he was In
Arabic, and a skilful diplomat at the court of Otto
I (953), founder of the Holy Germanic Roman
Empire, bears witness to this juxtaposition of the
two Andalusian cultures, Latin-Christian and
Arab-Muslim.
This almanach, incorporating meteorological
and agronomic information and a calendar of the
festivals of Christian saints which even notes the
places where they were celebrated, is written both
in Arabic (but in Hebrew characters) and In
Latin.
Translators and commentators
The trilingualism of the Mozarabs qualified them
as translators who could build a bridge between a
Western, European culture and an Oriental cul-
ture. Among the sumptuous gifts offered to
Caliph'Abd aI-Rahman HI by the Byzantine
emperor was a manuscript of the. Historiarum
<A'M<Mg<M Z. ! n W7by the Christian writer
Orosius, a contemporary of St. Augustine. Trans-
lated into Arabic by a Mozarab, this work became
immensely popular. It enabled the Arabs to learn 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
''. .'iPreeSpMtS ''
Freedom of thought and expressioajMd inM'tc-
tMl integrity and creativity constitute three essen-
<Nt characteristics of the original Inte ! tuat produc-
tion of AndahtSm the eteventhCeatary.
In the taifas scholars and inteMectuak often
experienced dramatic vidssimdes in ir forto
as a result of poittica ! conditions. Freedom of
expression existed, however, in spite of the
aamero restrictions limiting it, as the writmjgs
of scholars of the day in many fields show....
The inteUectuats were act radically hostile to
the tat Mngs, who did not persecute all scholars.
On the contrary, they needed them po ! itica ! ly and
caed to attract the greatest possible number to their
courts. The importance of this phenomenon ties
ia the ftCtthat some of the most celebrated ru ! ees
of HM were themselves cholars....
Yet... most of the scholars developed their
ideas outade of the poutiea ! sphere of the ruts* !,
workingindependendy....
. ;. ;"' :'. ;"'''." ;''.-. ; MMtC :. N « M&N''.MoMcom MMOfMB ("T hiSNiphy < at-Aa<Ms
< dM t ! tne < the tN& StfM !", m tM « <&amp; Ocaatt
M&n<M  <  AMttenxM, po. <0, 1
A miniature from the Cantlgas
de Santa Mana, an anthology
of pious ongs in honour of
the Virgin, made by Alfonso X
the Wise (1221-1284).
Be) ow, acast nd engraved
bronze wer in the form of a
peacock (12th century). A
bilingual Inscription preceded
by a cross is engraved on the
bird's crop. it reads (in
Arabic) work of the servant of
the ChftsNan Mng and (in
Latin) work of Salomon (a
Latin form of Suiayman).
ROSA 6UERRE) RO
is a medievalist of joint
Brazilian d Swiss nationality.
A former assistant lecturer at
the history department of he
University of Geneva, she is
currently preparing a doctoral
thesis t the University of Paris
IV-Sorbonne. She has written a
number of papers on cultural
and spiritual life in the Iberian
peninsula during the early
Middle Ages.
about the Greco-Roman past and inspired some
of them to see in Arab-Andalusian history the
natural prolongation of Hispano-Christian and
Visigothic history.
The Mozarabs were not only translators but
also brilliant commentators in Arabic who con-
tributed to the transmission of Visigothic culture.
The Etymologiae, a summary of all the sacred and
profane knowledge of his time by Isidore of
Seville (sixth-seventh century), the last Father of
the Western Church, circulated with extensive
commentaries in Arabic, into which some parts
of it were even translated.
Among the Mozarabs in fact Latin seems to
have lost its traditional role as the vehicle of
knowledge and the liturgical language. Parts of
the Bible were translated early on into Arabic,
as were the canonical texts, accompanied by com-
mentaries in Arabic to guide the thoughts of
Christians, who were increasingly attracted by
Arabic literature.
The scriptures in Arabic were not only read
by Arabized Christians. Arab-Andalusian writers
of such stature as the eleventh-century theologian,
historian and poet Ibn Hazm, reveal a profound
knowledge of the Bible in works which were
written, admittedly, in order to refute the prin-
ciples of Christianity.
To sum up, it might be said that, over and
above the movements of attraction and rejection
which punctuated the coexistence between the
two communities, in the tenth century the Arab-
Andalusians assumed their Hispanic identity and
the Mozarabs their Arab identity, while con-
tinuing to respect their respective religions. This
was no small achievement in a world and at a time
when the tendency was for different peoples and
confessions to be locked in mutual ignorance and
attracted to mutual destruction, t
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
/M COM&K-t  1 Ot, M 0 OMM MO tr K', Op/,
poetic xdCMtC OnZMM  0 CMnc M/MMM CKZMM
) UDAISM has never interrelated more closely or
more fruitfully with another culture than It did
with the Islamic civilization of al-Andalus. Even
though the status enjoyed there by Jews and
Christians as peoples of the Book was often
precarious and in some ways oppressive, the legal
position it guaranteed was, all things considered,
liberal in comparison with the conditions the
Jews encountered elsewhere in Europe, providing
as it did a high degree of legal, administrative,
fiscal and cultural autonomy.
The largely secularized character of the
Islamic civilization of al-AndaIus allowed the
peoples of the Book to consider themselves the
heirs of a great and respected cultural tradition.
The dominant language, Arabic, was less closely
wedded to the prevailing religion than Latin was
to the Roman Catholic and Eastern Churches,
and was widely used by Jews when commenting
on their own sacred texts.
The " bourgeois revolution " of the eighth and
ninth centuries in the Islamic world saw the
appearance of an entirely new Jewish society, one
very different from that of medieval Christian
Europe. While Jews in the pre-lslamic era had
mostly been farmers or small craftsmen, they
now rose to dominant positions in public life and
the upper ranks of the administration, as well as
in industry, finance and the professions.
With time and money to spare, these new
elites had wider intellectual horizons, more
refined tastes, and heightened expectations of a
more exalted spiritual life. Like their Muslim and
Christian counterparts, they devoted themselves
to science and poetry, to artistic activities and
fashionable occupations of all kinds, both serious
and frivolous. It was a time of travel, when Jewish
communities were spreading across the Islamic
lands and migrating between countries.
In linguistic terms, the symbiosis meant that
Arabic, the new international language of civili-
zation and culture, replaced the former vehicular
language, Aramaic, which henceforth was used
only for Talmudic texts. The Jews employed
Arabic In all their intellectual activities : sacred and
profane literature, science and religion, transla-
tions and commentaries on the Bible and the
Mishna. It was used for liturgical purposes, in
theological treatises, in grammars, dictionaries
and in correspondence.
Jewish and Muslim philologists alike became
aware of the kinship between Arabic, Hebrew
and Aramaic. But it was only the Jews who,
knowing all three, were in a position to lay the
foundations for a comparative study of these lan-
guages.
In literature, an examination of Jewish and
Arabic traditions, both written and oral, reveals
common elements and structures. There is a
striking similarity between, on the one hand,
A page of the polyglot Bible
published early in the
16th century by the
University ofAiacaia de
Henares. near Toledo, under
the auspices ofCardinal
Cisneros. The text, written in
Greek, Hebrew. Latin and
Chatdean. is printed in parallel
columns.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Astreet in the otd Jewish
district of Cordoba.
Jewish folklore, the Talmud and the Midrash (a
collection of homilies and legends), and on the
other their Arabic counterparts, the Hadith
(spoken traditions attributed to the Prophet
Muhammad) and the Islamic verse-chronicles.
There are also common subjects and heroes-
Abraham, Moses, Job and Joseph, for example-
in the stories, verse and proverbs of the two
peoples.
Hebrew poetry was transformed by contact
with Arabic verse. Indeed, it owes the greater part
of its prosody to the Andalusian inheritance. In
the tenth century, Dunash ben Labrat laid the
foundations of a new system of scansion that
replicated the quantitative metre of Arabic verse,
whose rules he adopted. The MMMM/M/M, a poetic
form originating in al-Andalus, also became a
familiar mode of expression in Hebrew poetry.
Alongside the renewal of Oriental Jewish
styles, a novel and prestigious form of poetry
gradually developed to express the new elite's love
of art, comparable both in its form and its inner
meaning to the Arabic model. It displays a
manifest desire to emulate the intellectual and
social elites of the Muslim world.
The Arab contribution to this literary
heritage was thoroughly digested and assimilated
until it finally became a naturalized part of the
Jewish tradition. Jewish writers achieved an
almost total blending of the cultural components
of the Judaeo-Arab world of their day. At the
same time that interconfessional tensions were
abating, an attempt was made in poetry to
remove the discrepancies and discordances that
the abrupt encounter of the Hebrew language and
orthodox Jewish thought with a foreign tongue
and culture could have occasioned. One can see
in the works of Ibn Khalfon and his successors
the attempt to adapt an essentially Jewish rhetoric
to the task of describing a secular world of which
Judaism had up to that time known nothing.
The lessons of Sufism
It would be impossible to understand or even con-
ceive of the existence of Jewish spirituality and
esotericism had it not been for the Islamic
environment and the knowledge Jewish authors
had of Sufi mysticism.
A comparison of the ancient Jewish mysti-
cism centred on the Merkava, the divine chariot
described by the prophet Ezekiel, with such
Islamic practices as dhikr (ritual repetition of the
name of God) and breathing exercises might sug-
gest that archaic Jewish gnosticism contributed
to the formation of Islamic esoteric traditions. In
fact, the influence went very much in the oppo-
site direction. The relatively incoherent utter-
ances of the Jewish Gnostics of the fifth and sixth
centuries gave way to the fervent eloquence of
the Islamic mystics, who possessed in the Arabic
language a first-class means of expression. From
that time on, Muslim pietism left its mark on the
mysticism, spirituality and ethics of Judaism as
it existed on Islamic soil.
It was via Sufism that many Jewish mystics
and ascetics received their apprenticeship in a new
form of spirituality that they subsequently passed
on to their own culture, first of all in its original
language, Arabic, then through translations into
Hebrew and other vernacular languages. This
work was accomplished by such scholars as Bahya
Ibn Paquda, Abraham Abulafya, and Abraham
and Obadya Maimonides, the son and grandson
respectively of the great Moses Maimonides.
Common ground between Jewish and Muslim
mysticism and esotericism can also be found in the
practices of the Andalusian Sufis and the teachings
of Ibn'Arabi (1165-1241), a prestigious figure in
the Sufi world who was born in Murcia in Spain.
The experiences and teachings of al-Ghazali
(1058-1111), one of the greatest Islamic
philosophers and theologians, exerted a consider-
able influence on the intellectual history of the
West and the East, and especially on Jewish
thinkers. The influence was felt at two levels and
at two distinct times.
During the twelfth and thirteenth centuries,
it affected Jewish authors writing and thinking
in Arabic. One such was Judah Halevi, al-
Ghazali's most fervent disciple who, sharing his
master's view of the danger posed by philosophy
to revealed religion, took as his starting-point the36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
A miniature from the Hebrew
Farhi Bible, copied and
illustrated by Elisha Crescas,
who lived and worked in
northern Spain and the south
of France during the second
half of the 14th century.
HA) M ZAFRAN)
is professor of Hebrew at the
University of Par ! sV ! !) and
director ofaresearchun ! t on
Judaism in Islamic lands. He is
the author of 11 books and
many articles on Jewish
thought. literature (written and
ora !) and languages ! n the
Muslim West His study of
Jewish poetry in the Muslim
West (Poesie juive en Occident
musutman. Paris. 1977) was
translated into Hebrew in
1984. and his Mille ans de vie
juive au Maroc ( " A thousand
years of Jewish life in
Morocco". Paris. 1983) was
translated into Hebrew in1986
and into Arabic in 1987.
charge of incoherence brought by al-Ghazali in
his masterwork Tahafut al falasifa (The Incoher-
ence of the Phiiosophers) against philosophers in
general and Aristotelian philosophy In particular.
It Is also accepted that Moses Maimonides knew
al-Ghazali's works, and especially his refutation
of philosophy.
From the thirteenth century onwards, the
works of aI-Ghazali were translated into Hebrew,
and were read, studied and commented on by
Jews in non-Arabic-speaking Provence and Spain,
where they achieved immense popularity. In fact
some of the writings of al-GhazaII and of
Averroes (Ibn Rushd), the great Cordoba-born
twelfth-century Islamic philosopher, have only
survived in Hebrew.
The communication of Greek learning
In philosophy, one of the most outstanding fea-
tures of the Judaeo-Arabic symbiosis was the
irruption of Greek science and culture into the
Jewish world through the medium of Arabic liter-
ature. The Hellenization of Jewish thought via
Islam is all the more surprising in view of the fact
that many Diaspora Jews had close and some-
times fruitful contacts with the Graeco-Latin
world.
However, the example of Philo of Alexan-
dria, a philosopher of the Diaspora who lived
sometime between the first century BC and the
second century AD and was familiar with Greek
philosophy, had no strong impact on Jewish cul-
ture, and the countless traces of the Greek lan-
guage and of Hellenic civilization that are to be
found in Talmudic or Midrashic literature sug-
gest only a superficial influence. Such a rejection
can perhaps be explained by the Jews'defensive
instinct to protect their religious identity, dictated
by an intransigent monotheism confronted with
the temptations of the paganism that Graeco-
Latin culture represented.
A more conciliatory attitude towards Greek
learning only became possible after the victory
of the monotheistic principle In the form first of
Christianity and then, more importantly, of
Islam, which was closer to Judaism in Its unitary
conception of divinity.
Judaism subsequently successfully passed the
test of Hellenization. Yet it always maintained
Its independence of Islam In the matter of reli-
gious fundamentals, even while travelling down
the paths of Muslim philosophy and accepting the
latest findings of the new sciences. This explains
why the masterworks of the Jewish theologians
and philosophers of the tenth, eleventh and
twelfth centuries, notably Ibn Gabirol and Moses
Maimonides, have remained classics of orthodox
Judaism, t
"-''''Vestothe'. 
Initiatly, the balance of the relatM) Bship between
a ! *Andalus and the lands of the Orieat indined in
fayow of the latter. Sehobrs ma 1dey,',
from AncMuat t the Orient Aw  verM,
beemse the current of civHizatioa M ftos
from centres of higher culture to the lests developed
are. 8. AJt-Andatus leased heavily at first oa Oriestat
] BBwkdge, which aeonsidered thBMainbead
the Xndatusiaas E ! <at to know.
That is why the voyages were aa ekaMBt in
consolidating and reinforcing the links between the
two regions, permitting Andalusian scieettEc Md
cSMetode'mabraThey
BMAndatuspasmthestatasit
backward country that copied the Mastic ! Oneat
to that of a competitor that sometimes surpassed
its. \"."
&... --"..' ; 
j :, Msof] an {"if.-tpMMaee et < ;')) ! j () ! t-'bem the (MeM at-Aad"mi&iWM
MM) Ot e &t AMttMM 
''...-'-- ; 
-"
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
A bridge between cultures, al Andalus transmitted to Europe Arab science and philosophy as well
as the work of Aristotle and other elements of ancient Greek thought
Abuicasis, a distinguished
Arab surgeon who lived
in 10th century Cordoba,
is shown visiting the city's
hospital in this
iate-19th-century engraving.
i. T 
was only in al-Andalus that scholars of the
early Middle Ages had access to the entire corpus
of scientific knowledge of their time written In
Arabic, Hebrew, Greek or Latin.
To take one example of the transmission of
knowledge to Muslim Spain, Byzantine envoys
took there a copy of the Materia Medica, a well-
known treatise by the first-century-AD Greek
doctor DIoscorides. By comparing it with an
existing Arabic version, It was possible to fill in
many gaps, notably with regard to the precise
identification of plant species. This task was car-
ried out in collaboration with a monk named
Nicolas, who came from the East expressly for
the purpose.
In the same circle of scholars were the Jewish
minister and doctor Hasday ben Shaprut ; Ibn
Juljul, historian of medicine and pharmacology ;
and also perhaps the great surgeon Abu aI-Qasim
az-Zahrawi, known to Christians as Albucasis,
whose work was soon translated into Latin. He
wrote an outline of all the medical knowledge of
the day, providing descriptions of such diseases
as haemophilia and scabies, of various surgical
instruments, even of a way of using a particular
variety of ant to heal wounds.
Maslama al-Magriti's name also belongs on
the list. The works of this Madrid-based
astronomer and alchemist circulated In digest
form in Western Europe almost as soon as they
were written, thanks to Latin adaptations pre-
pared by the Mozarabic monks of the monastery
of Ripoll in Catalonia. From there they were dis-
patched to monasteries in the Rhine valley,
notably Saint Gall in Switzerland and Reichenau
in Germany.
In the tenth century the natural passage still
used by modern tourists travelling from central
Europe to Spain was the only means of commu-
nication beween the peninsula and the rest of the
continent. The route through the central and
western Pyrenees had been closed since the defeat
of Charlemagne at the battle of Roncevaux in
778.
The importance thus accorded to Catalonia
explains why the oldest surviving astrolabe, a
hybrid product of the Arab and Visigothic cul-
tures, is set to function at the latitude of Barcelona.38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
It was to the Catalan marches that the young Ger-
bert of Aurillac, later to become Pope Sylvester
II, travelled to study science. By the time he
returned to France, he had learned so much that
at first he was taken for a necromancer or magus.
It was some time before the new knowledge that
he helped to introduce to Europe-of such subjects
as decimal numbers, the abacus, the construction
of astrolabes, sun-dials, armillary spheres and
other instruments-became widely available there.
When he quit the Iberian peninsula, Gerbert
knew that he was leaving behind him not just a
land whose scientific culture was vastly superior
to that of Christendom but also one whose
researchers (if one can use that word to describe
tenth-century scholars) were making continued
progress in their respective fields. In order to keep
abreast of their work, Gerbert corresponded with
an acquaintance in Barcelona-one Lupitus,
recently identified as the archdeacon Sunifred-
whom he requested to send him the latest
writings from al-Andalus.
A fruitful partnership
In the same way, Christian envoys to Cordoba
such as Gomar, the future Bishop of Gerona,
profited from their residence in al-Andalus to co-
operate with their Muslim counterparts. Gomar
wrote a chronicle of the Frankish kings at the
request of the future caliph al-Hakam II al-
Mustansir. An edited version of this work was
soon circulating In the Orient, and it has come
down to us In the great Arab traveller and ency-
clopaedist al-Masudi's Murudj al-Dhahab.
The same ruler was also responsible for the
enlargement of the palace library, which eventu-
ally contained some 400, 000 volumes, only one
of which has survived. His bibliomania drove him
to pay a fortune for any book that caught his
interest. That is why the first copy of Abu al-.
Faradj'Ali al-Isfahani's " Book of Songs ", a col-
lection of poems set to music that contains much
information on social and cultural life during the
first centuries of Islam, was known in Cordoba
before it was In the Orient.
It has been established from the dates at which
some surviving works were imported that It was
possible for books to make the journey from the
Orient to Cordoba and then on into the Chris-
tian world in less than two years. The speed with
which knowledge was transmitted can be
explained by the close collaboration that existed
between scholars of different religions and cul-
tures. For instance the monk Recemundo, author
of a celebrated liturgical calendar, was successively
Andalusian envoy to the Holy Roman Empire,
to Constantinople and to Jerusalem. His work,
which was amalgamated into the oo o/ ! 
of Arib ben Sa'd, a doctor and civil servant who
was his contemporary, contains popularized ele-
ments of Indian and Iraqi astronomy as well as
a mention of the great astronomer aI-Battani.
The Christian writer Orosius's Seven 600
of Histories against the Pagans (Historiarum
< : c/Mg<tM (M Z. ! r : 77 was translated into
Arabic by two men, Qasim ben Asbagh, a
Muslim cadi or judge, and his Christian counter-
part, Walid ben Khayzuran. The treatise known
as the Mathematica Alhandrea probably had a
similar genesis. A series of brief texts In Latin,
it contains In more or less accurate form the
Arabic names of many stars, among them Rigel,
Betelgeuse, Altair, Vega and Aldebaran-
appellations that are still familiar today.
Other, more technical knowledge was also
propagated abroad. Maslama of Madrid, an
astrologer at the Umayyad court, adapted the
tables of aI-Kharezmi, the great Baghdad
mathematician, for the Cordoba meridian. He
also wrote notes on the construction of astrolabes
and carried out astronomical observations. His
work soon became known In Europe, though not
under his own name. Latin translations and
digests also helped many Arabic words, such as
al-sumt, azimuth, to enter other languages.
The new knowledge was also transmitted to
Europe via Arab prisoners of war held on Chris-
tian territory. Ibn Hayyan, the greatest historian
of al-Andalus, specifically refers to their influence.
Some of these captives were men of great
learning, and their captors knew how to profit
from their knowledge, t
This copper astrolabe
made) n earty-llth century
Cordoba) Is one of the oldest
in the world.
JUAN VERNET,
Spanish Arabist, is professor
emeritus at the University of
Barcelona and a member of
the International Academy of
the History of Sciences. A
specialist inthe field of Arab
science and its transmission t<
medieval nd modern Europe.
he is the author of many
artiniM and RturttM
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
TM MO   y MO ! M 
transmission 0 the 40-G cultural
legacy from alAndalus to Europe
i. T was not until the twelfth century that the
first college of translators from Arabic into Latin
was set up in Spain, in the city of Toledo. It was
founded by Don Raimundo, archbishop of
Toledo from 1126 to 1151. A Benedictine monk
who had been born at Agen in south-western
France, Raimundo was convinced of the impor-
tance of the Arab philosophers for an under-
standing of Aristotle, and he decided to make
their works available in Latin.
Domingo Gundisalvo, archdeacon of Segovia,
was one of the most eminent of the scholars
recruited by Raimundo. He translated much of
the encyclopaedic At al :/a' ("Book of
Healing ") by Ibn Sina (Avicenna) as well as al-
Ghazali's MM //M !/ ("The Aims of the
Philosophers ") and aI-Farabi's/M't !/- «/M
( " Catalogue of the Sciences ").
But Gundisalvo knew no Arabic. He used a
Jewish or Muslim intermediary to translate from
Arabic into Castilian, and then put the Castilian
into Latin. Among his Jewish collaborators two
names feature prominently : a certain Salomon
and, more importantly, one Johannes Avendeath
(who also appears as Avendear, Johannes ben
David, Johannes Hispanus, and also John of
Seville). The exact identity of these two has
aroused much discussion.
The most important of the Toledan trans-
lators was undoubtedly Gerard of Cremona
(1114-1187). Thanks to a brief notice left by his
pupils on his life and work, we know that Gerard
came to Toledo after finishing his studies in Italy,
in order to learn more about the 4/wMt. This
vast astronomical treatise by Claudius Ptolemaeus
ABDURRAHMAN BADAW).
of Egypt. is a philosopher and historian ofphilosophy. A
former head of the departments of philosophy at a number
of universities in Egypt, he Libyan Arab Jamah ! hya. and
Kuwait, and a visiting professor at the Sorbonne. Paris, he is
the author of over a hundred publications i  French and in
7t Arabic, mainly concerned with existentialism. Greek and
V Arab philosophy, and contemporary German philosophy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
(Ptolemy), the celebrated second-century-AD
Greek astronomer, mathematician and
geographer, was then only available in Arabic.
In fact Gerard discovered a multitude of scien-
tific works in Arabic in Toledo, and immediately
began to learn the language so as to read them
and, later, to render them into Latin. He eventu-
ally translated more than seventy of them,
including the 4/gc, which he completed in
1175.
His translations cover virtually the entire
field of science of his time. Among them are
several treatises by Aristotle (The Physics, 0
Heaven ! M EA, 0 GccrfzoM J Co ?'y-
tion, and 7% c  ? 0), as well as books by al-
Kindi, Ptolemy, Isaac Israeli, Ibn SIna, Galen and
others.
The other great translator was Michael Scot
(c. ll75-c. l235). Born in England, he studied at
Oxford University and then in Paris before
settling in Toledo. After learning Arabic and
Hebrew, he became a prolific translator of Arabic
into Latin. Near the end of his life he was invited
to the court of the Emperor Frederick II in Sicily,
the other great centre of translation from the
Arabic.
Scot's translations included many commen-
taries on Aristotle by Ibn Rushd (Averroes) as
well as al-Bitruji's work on the spheres, which
was to have a great influence on astronomical
knowledge.
The Toledan translations raise problems of
attribution. The French writer and historian
Ernest Renan wrote in a study of Averroes : " It
is certain that the Latins who journeyed to
Toledo had no scruples about appropriating the
work of their secretaries, and... the name of
the translator was often a fiction.
" Nearly always a Jew, often a converted
Muslim, did a rough translation, substituting
words in Latin or the vernacular for the Arabic
original. A clerk would supervise this process,
taking responsibility for the final Latin version
and putting his name to the work. This explains
why one translation is often attributed to
different individuals. "
Renan's view was shared by the great
American medievalist Charles Homer Haskins in
his book on the twelfth-century Renaissance. It
is also supported by some translations in the Bib-
liotheque Nationale in Paris, which were ren-
dered from Arabic into Latin by way of Spanish.
The extraordinary achievements of the
Toledan translators were in reality the joint work
of Muslim Arabs, Jews and Latin Christians. It
would be unjust to give the credit exclusively to
the latter, even though many of the manuscripts,
and many historians, mention only their names.
Gundisalvo, Gerard of Cremona, Michael Scot
and others all called on the help of Muslim Arabs
or more often of Jews in the course of their work.
Sometimes the task of the Latin Christian trans-
lators was limited to putting into good Latin what
their assistants had already translated into bad
Latin or Spanish.
The great enterprise of translation from
Arabic into Latin began in Spain in the twelfth
century, and Toledo was its most active centre.
But it also took place in other cities of the penin-
sula including Barcelona, Tarragona, Segovia,
Leon and Pamplona. The task was subsequently
taken up on the other side of the Pyrenees, in
Toulouse, Beziers, Narbonne, Montpellier and
Marseilles.
It was thanks to these translations that
Europe came to know both the works of the
Greek philosophers, mathematicians, doctors and
astronomers and those of their Arabic commen-
tators or emulators. As Haskins wrote, " The
reception of this knowledge by western Europe
marks a crucial turning-point in the history of
European thought."t
Of Arabic origin, the word
alcazar is used to designate a
type of medieval fortified
palace in Spain. Left, a view
of Toledo in which the alcazar
can be seen on the horizon.
Right, detail from a passage
describing the treatment of
goitre in an i)) uminated
Latin manuscript of
Avicenna's Canon of Medicine
(13th century).
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
A great Argentine
nr K) M/
attempt to recreate 
atmosphere of
intellectual life in
al Andalus
i. HE medica ! doctor, philosopher and jurist Ibn
Rushd or Averroes (1126-1198), the greatest Arab
commentator on Aristotle, is at home in Cor-
doba. He is busy writing a philosophical work,
the TM/Mt-/'TM/Kt (Destruction of Destruc-
tion) " in which it is maintained, contrary to the
Persian ascetic al-Ghazali, author of the TM/Kf-
M/-/M/fM/ (Destruction of Philosophers), that the
divinity knows only the general laws of the
universe, those pertaining to the species, not to
the individual.
" He wrote with slow sureness, from right to
left ; the effort of forming syllogisms and linking
vast paragraphs did not keep him from feeting,
like a state of well-being, the coot and deep house
surrounding him.
" In the depths of the siesta amorous doves
called huskily ; from some unseen patio arose the
murmur of a fountain ; something in Averroes,
whose ancestors came from the Arabian deserts,
was thankful for the constancy of the water.
" Down below were the gardens, the orchard ;
down below, the busy Guadalquivir and then the
beloved city of Cordoba, no less eminent than
Baghdad or Cairo, like a complex and delicate
instrument, and all around (this Averroes fett
also) stretched out to the limits of the earth the
Spanish land, where there are few things, but
where each seems to exist in a substantive and
eternal way."
The above passage is taken from Z, busca de
Averroes ("Averroes's Search", 1947), by the great
Argentine writer Jorge Luis Borges (1899-1986).
Themes and figures of Arab-Islamic culture are
recurrent features of the work of Borges, who
once proclaimed that the Thousand and One
Mg/7h was the Book of Books. Of all the writings
he devoted to Arab-Islamic culture,"Averroes's
Search " best represents his special relationship
with that culture and, more particularly, with one
of its unique facets : the world of al-Andalus.
At-Andatus as depicted by Borges Is the scene
of an extraordinary spiritual adventure. It is a
place where commentaries are written on
Aristotle, " this Greek, fountainhead of at)
philosophy ". Where people " exhaust the pages
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Left. Jorge Luis Borges
Below, water channel and
fountains in the gardens of
the Generatife, the summer
palace of the Nasrid rulers in
Granada (14th century).
of Alexander of Aphrodisia ". Where scholars
proudly examine rare manuscripts collected by
princes who are passionate bibliophiles. Where
questions of poetry and rhetoric are discussed
with fervour. Where an examination of the
authenticity of " marvels " can turn into a discus-
sion of the created or uncreated character of the
Qur'an.
Great intellectual receptivity, rich and con-
trasting characters, a profound respect for other
people's freedom of opinion, conversation and
the exchange of ideas raised to an art : these are
the characteristics of the Andalusian elite as
described by Borges. Averroes takes issue with
another character in the story, Farach the the-
ologian, by refusing to accept that " an excellent
variety of the perpetual rose... is found in the
gardens of Hindustan "-a Borgesian theme par
exce//eHcc-"whose petals, of a blood red, exhibit
characters which read :'There is no god but the
God, Muhammad is the Apostle of God.' " But
this disagreement does not provoke a polemic.
The viewpoint of the orthodox theologian, for
whom a miracle is the very sign of divinity, can
coexist with that of the rationalist.
In the person of Abulcasim the traveller
Borges mischievously presents a kind of antithesis
to the three other characters in the story-Farach
the theologian, Abdalmalik the poet and
Averroes himself. A down-to-earth, practical
man, Abulcasim, whose " memory was a mirror
of intimate cowardices, " has a very different
experience of the world from that of the men of
ideas and convictions. When asked to relate a
marvel, he reflects that " the moon of Bengal is
not the same as the moon of Yemen, but it may
be described in the same words. " A prudent man,
he never answers directly, but takes the pulse of
his audience and softens the asperities of the ques-
tions put to him by means of dialectical agility.
Could it be the memory of other, less tolerant
lands far from al-Andalus that explain this wari-
ness ? Was al-Andalus really the idyllic land Borges
describes ? Did it not, like any other country, have
its share of stupidity and horror as well as its
exemplary splendours ? The life of Averroes him-
self seems to confirm that this was so, if any proof
were needed. He knew opprobrium as well as
glory, suffered repression at the hands of obtuse
authorities, was present at the burning of books
that had cost him dear in hard work and self-
denial, and came to know not just the loyal sup-
port of true friends but also the stubborn hatred
of mediocrities.
But Borges's al-Andalus is not that of history,
nor that of a literary realism that would seek to
reconstitute objectively a life, a place, a time. He
does not set himself that goal, still less allow him-
self that illusion. The point of Borges's fiction is
quite different. The Spanish title of the story, La
busca <4fe'OM, can be read In two ways, as the
quest undertaken by Averroes himself, or as the
quest for Averroes-Borges's own attempt to
recreate the philosopher and his destiny in the
truest manner possible.
In the first paragraphs of the story, Averroes
is depicted hard at work in his library. He is grap-
pling with a problem that causes him great con-
cern. At the beginning of Aristotle's Poetics, on
which he is writing a commentary, he has stum-
bled over two words, tragedy and comedy. " No
one in the world of Islam could conjecture what
they meant. " He consults all the sources, pores
over the versions of the Nestorian Hunain ibn-
Ishaq and of Abu Bashar Mata. But in vain. And
yet " it was impossible to elude... these two
arcane words " from the great philosopher's
Poetics.
Borges twice puts Averroes in the presence
of the answer that he is seeking. The first occa-
sion is a scene in which he is distracted from his
work " by a kind of melody ", looks down from
his balcony and sees " below, in the narrow ear-
then patio, some half-naked children were
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Awtffett, tb « w<) <ft, wtth
Pythent*. A det8l1 of Ttt*
Sehoe<efA<h<m*, <fnMce
px) <tt « ht 150<-mo by th<
) t<))) tttp<))) <tf) <tp) MH) ntht
StM) Md<) hS<t<MtMn)) nt) x
Wtttean.
RACHtD MMMH),
Moroccan writer and jouma ! ist,
is the author of an essay on
20th-century French
philosophy which will shortly
be published in Arabic. He is
also preparing a study on
French travellers inMorocco,
which will appear (in French) in
1992.
Extracts from"Averroes's
Search " by Jorge Luis borgne ;
translated by James E. Irby.
Copyright @New Directions
Ptthtiahinc fnmnratinn
playing. One, standing on another's shoulders,
was obviously playing the part of a muezzin ; with
his eyes tightly closed, he chanted'There is no
god but the God.'The one who held him motion-
lessly played the part of the minaret ; another,
abject in the dust and on his knees, the part of
the faithful worshippers. The game did not last
long ; all wanted to be the muezzin.... "
The second time is through a story told by
the traveller Abulcasim about a strange thing he
had seen in China : " One afternoon, the Muslim
merchants of Sin Kalan took me to a house of
painted wood where many people lived. It is
impossible to describe the house, which was
rather a single room with rows of cabinets or bal-
conies on top of each other. In these cavities there
were people who were eating and drinking, and
also on the floor, and also on a terrace. The
persons on this terrace were playing the drum and
the lute, save for some fifteen or twenty (with
crimson-coloured masks) who were praying,
singing and conversing. They suffered prison, but
no one could see the jail ; they travelled on horse-
back, but no one could see the horse ; they fought,
but the swords were of reed ; they died and then
stood up again.
"'The acts of madmen,'said Farach,'exceed
the previsions of the sane.'
"'These were no madmen,'Abulcasim had
to explain.'They were representing a story, a
merchant told me.'
" No one understood, no one seemed to want
to understand....
"'Did these people speak ?' asked Farach.
"'Of course they spoke,'said Abulcasim..
..'They spoke and sang and perorated.'
"'In that case,'said Farach,'twenty persons
are unnecessary. One single speaker can teil any-
thing, no matter how complicated it might be.
, "
The words tragedy and comedy presuppose a
knowledge of theatre, an art unknown to Arab
culture In Averroes's day. The philosopher, a.
prisoner of his own culture, cannot imagine what
these words can mean unless he has some idea
of theatrical representation itself. This Is why,
when he has an example of it before his eyes-
the children playing at being muezzin-he cannot
see it. One can only see something of which one
already has a concept ; everything else remains
" invisible ". Since theatre does not exist as a cul-
tural category, another category that is familiar,
that of the story-teller, takes its place.
Averroes returns home at dawn and goes to
his library. Under the impression that he has
finally found the meaning of the two obscure
words, he adds these lines to his manuscript :
" Aristu (Aristotle) gives the name of tragedy to
panegyrics and that of comedy to satires and
anathemas. Admirable tragedies and comedies
abound In the pages of the Qur'an and in the
mohalacas of the sanctuary.... "
Borges then adds a postscript in which he
explains that in the story he has " tried to nar-
rate the process of a defeat ", the failure of a quest
blocked by Its own cultural frontiers, adding,
however, that his own quest for Averroes fails
for the same reason : " I felt that Averroes,
wanting to imagine what a drama is without ever
having suspected what a theatre is, was no more
absurd than I, wanting to imagine Averroes with
no other sources than a few fragments from
Renan, Lane and Asm Palacios. "
Can one ever really know another culture
than one's own ? Putting the bleakest possible
interpretation on Borges's words, it might be said
that cultures are closed to one another. If this is
the case, the quest for what al-Andalus was
becomes impossible, and attempts to recreate at-
Andalus are bound to give a distorted impression.
But such a quest also provides an ethical lesson :
to know is to be aware of otherness, of the " com-
pletely other", and to respect it-a very different
thing from the disastrous pretensions of the
" panoptic overview ".
" Few things more beautiful and more
pathetic are recorded In history than this Arab
physician's dedication to the thoughts of a man
separated from him by fourteen centuries,"
Borges says of Averroes.
Borges's story is a fine contemporary tribute
to the exceptional moment in intellectual life that
was al-Andalus. *
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
i
which was launched in 1984 and
now has a membership of 255
instltutfons in 130 countries. The 
r°`r °''
UNESCO IN ACTION new network will describe how
each member has developed' 
 
curricula in discipiines such as  
 ; . 
.
physics, chemistry, biology and N ` ,   
x   
mathematics. The computerized . ') - BotA'
data base will be on-iine and
available on both diskette and hard copy.
Orace iBumfbry nansd
UNESCO amfbassador
The celebrated American opera V
singer Grace Bumbry has been -
: rausn ' :  : ! SL''. 
 "h. r   States has banned the TtMES PnMr PC. Eduaon  awaMed fOf ?. f
an artist and for her woh< in''  "     .  ? 0. 000 P. d<d by a gift fromartist and for her work in
support of education, heatth and room the Peten region of . MpaR) but) MNFound
youth  : n : "" <d
implementing a UNESCO'mXTieconctn'th. conventionwhistheonty --a) yC<&lt;MyUNESMh<.
'"'"'". stingT < ! hTd<nbyDintemational forum on " Culture  i ii5. fie ( af ! ! 
d8$ignat8d by the DirACtOr-.
and Democracy " heid in Prague at 
instrument deaNng with the illicit' '" trade in cuituraiobjts. The 6eMMthabaarMmmend<&lt;ttonantn<
September erector"""'   '  statespenons, wh<ch rnvtews tt) e many nomtna-
Generat. Mr. Federico Mayor. rmar'TX Sar. e ttOM WMch are seK fmm a « Over ? 0 WM to USCO.
presented Ms Bumbry with her foal request for the ban to theMs Bumbry with her u'oennderthe ) nthepaedua) th ! ntO''apUbOp) nionandmot ! Mizethe
Mr'. TSd's'mbry c. nv. n.. sint. d<t. Mp c<nsc<encencauseofpeace"hasgen
Mr. Mayor said that Ms. Bumbry   n 
"symboiizes in her talent and its stop Sain''   "n tt deserves and urgentty requires.
use a unique synthesis of what we 
2·200 archaeologal sites in the
a unique synthesis of what we p  towtandarea of tropical T pnze has made and is making a notables change in that direc-
mean by a cutture of democracy. " forests. Acxording to the tjOn. it ig brirtging 
to ever wider attention a message articutated
 GuatemaianGovenwnent aseanyasl911byoneofthefirsttwoiaunMtes, honoured) ntttftttt incre singiy sophisticat d tooting
A UNESCO docMmwnttfy"M affected more than 85% ouf
tune sites. The U. S. ban covers cannot be secured... unless the spirit for peace is there in the
UtefacyDwy vases, bowis. drums, effigy minds and witts of the peoples. This is a matter of education."
A 52-minutie documentary vessets and artefacts of jade, ftint,highlighting the hardships 
of she)), bone and other materiats. Over the years the jury has selected a diverse group of
streetchiidreninAfricahasbeen Thisisthe4thtimethatthe iaureatesrepresentingaverybroadfangeofaetivitiesinpeaceedu-
produced by UNESCO in""ted SMes has appHed Artier gj  recentiy carried out a survey of the laureates which
collaboration with the 9 of the Convention  the Illicit
intemationatCathoiicChMd transfer of cultural objects (1970). reveaied that the prize has spurred greater efforts for peace. Heiena
Bureau. The film, entttted May trte which has been ratmed by 71 Kekkonen ofRniand (1981) reflected that"The reputation brought
nt&estMttisessenttaity States, by ? 0 UNESCO prize did a iot towards increasing the interest of
targeted for televisicn but w111 also' '  ". ' F'""'sh educators and people in general in peace education....
be available for non-commercial
use. Shown for the first time on 9''S**'*""*'"t985-1987. taws obliging'chiidren and young people to be
September at a ceremony heM at""H<e pnM *""''*"'brought up with a will for peace'came into effect in Finland."
UNESCO HQ to mark the 26th J ° To^annua ! ernaMorLacy Ta « em) tsu and French Several prize-winners eported becoming more active within
MayNtenWttbeshoftispartofa mustcotogist deques CtMUttey UNESCO and the United Nations ystem. The intemationat Peace
c<mpa) gn to ttraw attention to the'n'* Research Association, for example, has undertaken a project on
, growing worid probln ot sbreet In^ationai NC! chandTrning CoundMUNESCOPrM. AspMM"Cuiturai 
Symbiosis in al-Andalus " (see page 31).
Today and than 100 mittton ment) enwentto<tte (u<teamus The funds awarded to the laureates have helped them to carry'Today mae tl lNkx
chitdrenofpnmaryachootage TneaurwaaoSve ? furthertheirservicetotheadvancementofpeaceeducation. Among
The 3 leurostqs aleo resdhave rver sdt toot in anrsetfootina UNESCO's MoMrtMeda). the endeavours supported by the prize money have been : financing
'Ta) MmMtu. 6e,) snotMtfM-w thetraveiofpeaceresearchersfromdeveiopingcountriestopar-
------ '''" ? 1"" ticipate in the 1990 biennial meeting of the intemationai Peace
. <&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<&lt;<) OccMetntttnaonetMt).,-. ;HMf BohtMt <m<t hta<rum<n<t. meM<&lt;t (t ResearchAssociation ; thefundingofaworkonpeacekeepingthat
e) t) ttta<y MemtaMMt ? erton) twh : R<&lt;t is used as a basic text for the professional preparation of military
'S**. 'S'*4. officers and diplomats ; the promotion of a book on the struggles
\-.'M « SCOtwtt<euntx'o<n) mme ChtM. M. MMitMM. t'tttM.',.'.. :. : :.' f. f ee..
t « ) Mth<ootnpuMrM<t-'wcott<he'.'*MM)) 6) it'""''''' for peace of Egyptian and israeii women ; research on a just world
order ; a series of films on development and peace.
This tWjMt ) t'Vtf WW WM '"'-. "K     BETTY R6AROOM AMD UMCKUABDULAZ) Z at'''
;  i'1 d it h. t
''sS ! S"''-'''*S%  This arttcie is based on a ionger study by Betty Reardon (United States) '". .''" : 
` 
` 
* "  ,  and Ungku Abdul Aziz (Malaysia), both members of the Intemationsl Jury
 0f'Ir  "   °. of the UNESCO Prize for Peace Education.
t
I
'  c 
 . A "''bi   e   v
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
c
SULTAN, seraglio, harem : such words long
epitomized Ottoman civilization in the
dreams of Westerners. The master of an
immense empire stretching from Egypt to
Persia and from Baghdad to Belgrade, the
sultan seemed to be a fabulous character who
enjoyed limitless power and endless pleasure.
It was easy to imagine him living in his harem
as if in a garden of earthly delights.
The reality was very different. The harem
was a restricted enclave governed by punc-
tilious protocol and strict rules, subject to the
authority of the / :  </f, the ruling
suttan's mother. In it love was codified, if not
ritualized. And if some sultans abused its
pleasures, others only went there for the sake
of custom ; and the majority only visited it in
moderation.
In the middle of the sixteenth century the
women of the sultan's eraslio moved into the
: AROUNE HAARDT,
rench journa ! ! St. was a staff member of
JNESCO's D ! V ! s ! on of Cu ! tura ! Herbage from1983
o 1987. She is currently preparing an exh ! b ! t ! on.
! S part of the UNESCO Silk Roads project, on the
roere Jaune. a motor ally from Beirut to Tibet
e ! d ! n 1931. 1932.
harem of the Topkapi. a new palace which was
to be the imperial residence until the
nineteenth century. Marvenousty situated on
a hi ! ! overtooking the Sea of Marmara, the
Bosphorus and the Golden Horn, the
immense complex covers 700, 000 square
metres, with its vast gardens, its murmuring
waters and its terraces overlooking the sea. At
its heart was the harem, where only the sultan
had the right to enter and move around freely.
This forbidden domain adjoined the bar-
racks of the haiberdiers-with-tresses, tough
mountain troops from Anatolia who cut the
wood that fue ! ted the palace fires. To avoid
temptation, these soldiers wore high collars
that made it impossible for them to turn their
heads, and their long, braided locks served as
blinkers.
As time passed, the harem grew, spreading
Ot] tW3rn', in) n\rtnttnnctnr) nfrt) tn) r' :
46
 Topkapi &  
 c Mf
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Cupolas and minarets of the harem.
Right, the sultan's baths.
central core. There are more than 400 rooms
in its three precincts : the living quarters of the
black eunuchs ; the women's quarters, where
the apartments of the suttan's mother,
daughters and odalisques were situated ; and
the men's apartments, where the sultan and
the princes of the b) ood hved.
One enters the harem through a gate
leading into the Domed Hall with Cabinets,
where merchants deposited jewellery, furs and
clothing for the concubines. The living quarters
of the black eunuchs, which have a courtyard
decorated with btue, green and turquoise cer-
amic tiles, are three storeys high. The size and
decoration of the apartments and the baths
varied according to the eunuchs'rank.
At the entrance to the women's quarters,
an inscription on the bronze door recalls the
suttan's overeignty. This is a world where the
play of tight, the splendour of the ancient
tiling and the refinement of the decoration
combine to produce an impression of paradise
on earth. In these apartments with their rich
hangings, luxurious carpets and deep divans,
it is easy to imagine the beautiful kadins (the
sultan's principal consorts, officially recog-
nized as such though not married to him)
waiting bejewelled for their master.
The way to the apartments of the valide
sultan ties through a courtyard, decorated with
twenty-five marble columns. From a small
wooden belvedere situated nearby, it was pos-
sible to survey all the activities of the harem.
These palatial quarters comprise a series
of rooms in the Western style, with
monumental chimneypieces, mirrors and areas
of wait decorated with paintings. In the
bedroom are panels painted with imaginary
landscapes, a baldaquin of gilded wood, and
divans with shimmering fabric. An arched
doorway leads to the queen mother's private
prayer room.
The queen mother's baths are arranged in
the same way as those of her son. The first
room was for undressing, white sipping drinks
or sherbets ; in the second cold water was
provided ; hot water in the third. The basins
and tubs were of alabaster.
The suttan's private apartments consist of
four great rooms, the most beautiful and the
best preserved of the harem. In the Imperial
Halt, a dais with marble columns and a balus-
trade of gilded wood encrusted with mother-
of-peart was used by mate musicians and
singing girls. The sultan's throne, surmounted
by a baldaquin, stood on a peart carpet which
had been embroidered in the harem. On his
visits to the harem this was where he gave the
receptions that no one from the city or even
the palace could attend, where the women
danced, played music and recited poems.
The vast Privy Chamber of Murad III,
which was built by the great architect Sinan,
displays all the splendour and nobility of tate-
sixteenth-century Ottoman art. Its beautifully
worked dome is supported by four arches. The
decoration ofthe walls is handled in such a way
as to present a subtle gradation of colours and
tight, from lower panels coated with a unique
red varnish (the secret of their manufacture
perished with the Iznik craftsman who made
them) to stained-glass windows above. A foun-
tain decorated with stone flowers and a huge
gilded hearth are set opposite one another.
" Water is the source of life, " the Qur'an
proclaims. There are many fountains In the
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Harem, and the incessant murmur of water,
it is said, served to muffle the voice of the
prince during his secret conversations....
Beneath the Privy Chamber, the women
disported themselves in a marble swimming-
pool, opening on one side onto a second, out-
door pool.
Other rooms still wait to be visited : the
apartment of the crown prince, where gold,
mother-of-pear ! and ivory are fabulously min-
gled ; the so-cailed Meeting Place of the Jinns,
a narrow corridor that was nonetheless an
important artery of the harem In which many
a conspiracy was hatched ; the Golden Way,
the passage the sultan used to go to religious
cetebrations. It is said that when a new sultan
ascended the throne, he would throw golden
coins at all the women of the harem lined up
along these walls.
Leaving the harem by the Aviary Gate is
like waking from a dream. The harem is
unlike any other palace. It is an unreal resi-
dence, a paradise that enchants by its refine-
ment but chills by its prisonlike aspect.
Iron rules
The harem has been the theatre of many dra-
matic events, but Its inflexible laws remained
the same for four centuries.
All the women of the harem were bought
and became slaves of the sultan. They were
magnificent girls, recruited from among the
captives of conquered lands. The age of entry
ranged from five to sixteen. In the intrigue-
filled chambers of the court, it was beauty, not
The feadin mom of Ahmad
birth, that could win advancement by
attracting the sultan's eye. Most of the girls
were destined to remain servants, but those
picked out by the harem superintendent, a
woman known as the kaya kadin, received a
thorough education, so they might please the
ruler.
Life in the harem was punctuated by the
festivities held to celebrate births and mar-
riages. Normally girls who failed to attract the
sultan were freed at the age of twenty-five,
when they received a pension for life and were
given in marriage to a member of the court
or the clergy.
It is hard to say exactly how many women
lived in the harem. Ottoman sources ay 700,
which would seem to be a maximum in view
of the space alloted them. A document dating
from the beginning of the seventeenth century
puts the figure at 456.
In the harem, the word of the valide sultan
was law. Through weakness or incapacity,
some sultans even allowed their mother to
govern in their place. She alone possessed
sumptuously decorated apartments and a civil
and a military household. Even more signifi-
cantly, her apartments were the only ones that
had access to the sultan's private chambers.
The custom of employing eunuchs to
guard the palace women was a very ancient
one. Orieinatine in Mesopotamia, it spread
around the world, from China to Rome. The
Ottoman harem was no exception to the rule.
The black eunuchs who had charge of it from
the end of the sixteenth century retained their
power and influence until the end of the
imperial period.
The eunuchs, who came from Africa,
especially Ethiopia, were subjected to an iron
discipline. Their most important tasks
included preventing outsiders from entering
the harem and stopping the women from
absconding. They received a training com-
parable to that given to the royal pages ; they
lost their own names, being given those of
flowers instead, and were taught music and cal-
ligraphy. Their commander was the third
highest officer of the empire.
A fragile jewel
In order to draw the attention of the interna-
tional community to the wonders of the Tur-
kish patrimony, the Director-General of
UNESCO launched an appea) in 1983 for the
protection of the historic quarter of Istanbul
and other sites. One of the priorities was the
restoration and rehabilitation of the Topkapi
Palace.
In the nineteenth century, the sultan
moved to the palace of Dolmabahce and Top-
kapi was abandoned to the surveillance of a
few guards. The building suffered substantial
damage : there was a fire in 1863 and an earth-
quake in 1894, white in 1871 some buildings
were demolished to make way for a railway
line. After the proclamation of the republic,
the palace was transformed into a museum,
but only part of the complex was placed under
the control of the its directors.
The harem is, naturally, one of the ; ewets
of the palace ; its architecture is an exceptional
memorial to the richness and diversity of
Ottoman civilization. Its reputation has con-
tinued to grow. Projects, excavations and
investigations have multiplied ; more than 400
studies of it have been published.
Built as it is of wood, it is particularly vut-
nerable to the risk of fire, and the first pri-
ority is an efficient system of alarms and extin-
guishers. Restoring the building is no easy
task, for, as with any monument, its architec-
tural features need to be respected, both inside
and out. That means using the original
materials, including ivory, ebony, teak and
go) d) eaf, ai ! hard to come by these days. In
spite of the precautions taken to protect it
from unfavourable weather conditions, the
edifice is rapidly ageing and considerable main-
tenance and repair work is needed. N
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T
1 His year we celebrate the 750th anniver-
sary of the birth of Yunus Emre, who was
probably the most significant foik poet in the
history of Islamic literature, besides being the
most important Turkish poet up to the twen-
tieth century. His poetry embodies the quin-
tessence of Turkish-Anatolian Islamic
humanism and has been a source of inspira-
tion in Turkish intellectual life through the
ages. His verses include eloquent specimens of
tolerance and universalism :
Mystic is what they call me,
Hate is my only enemy.
I harbour a grudge against none.
To me the whole wide world is one.
Many of Yunus Emre's fundamental con-
cepts are rooted in the Sufi tradition, particu-
larly as exemplified by the thirteenth-century
mystic and poet Rumi, who lived in Anatolia
but wrote in Persian. In this Rumi resembled
the writers and thinkers of medieval Europe
who used Latin in preference to their national
languages. But Yunus Emre, like Dante,
adopted the vernacular of his own people.
Because he spoke their language and brought
a message of divine love, he became a legen-
dary figure and came to be regarded as a saint.
For seven centuries his verses have been
memorized, recited and celebrated in the
heartland of Anatolia. Even today most Turks
can read and appreciate him without too much
recourse to the dictionary, while they find
many classical poets of the fourteenth to
nineteenth centuries quite unintelligible.
But it is not for reasons of language alone
that Yunus Emre appeals to us today. His
themes and concerns are both timeless and
universal, relevant to not only to Turkey but
to the whole world, and as much now as ever
before. For we live in an age that sees war as
evil and the supreme crime against humanity.
Love is the celebration of life, an idea which
is forcefully expressed in the catchword from
the 1960s and 1970s : " Make love, not war ".
Translated into mystical terms, this means that
it has both a human and a divine dimension,
and it is here that we catch an echo from the
poetry of Yunus Emre :
Portrait of Yunus Emre
by the contemporary Turkish artist
Siiheyl Unver.
1am not here on earth for strife.
Love is the mission of my life.
It is a poetry that speaks to us through the
centuries, expressing the ecstasy of com-
munion with nature and union with God.
This theme of union with God frequently
appears in his writing as an ideal which is
about to be realized, while his humanism
includes, in Hegel's words, the " urging of the
spirit outward-that desire on the part of man
to become acquainted with his world".
Yunus Emre spurned book learning if it
did not have a humanistic relevance, because
he believed in man's godliness. In this sense
he had affinities with Petrarch, also writing
in the fourteenth century, and with Erasmus,
a century later, who, as part of their classical
or Renaissance humanism, shunned the dog-
matism imposed on man by scholasticism.
Like them, he sought to instil in ordinary
people a renewed sense of the importance of
life on Earth, but like Dante, he explored the
ethical dimension of mortal life while
depicting the higher values of immortal being.
Yunus Emre's lines are memorable :
Whoever has one drop of love
Possesses God's existence.
About Yunus Emre's life we know very
little, and what we do know tends to be a
matter of legend rather than ascertainable fact.
He is said to have been illiterate for most if
not all of his life, yet the poems display an eru-
dition and a richness of allusion that could
hardly be expected from an illiterate. In any
case, it is the poems themselves that count, and
some of them are magnificent.
Yunus Emre's poetry is dominated by a
unitary vision of man and nature. Through his
humanism he seeks to enrich human existence
and to ennoble it by liberating man from
dogma nd by placing him in a relationship of
love with God. His view of love is creative and
non-exciusive : " In God's world there are a
hundred thousand kinds of love ", and " When
love arrives, all needs and flaws are gone. " He
was concerned about all people, particularly the
deprived, and this is what gives his poetry its
intensely moving quality. He was the first poet
in Turkish history to create an " aesthetics of
ethics ", and in this he has never been surpassed.
He stressed the ecumenical ideal :
We regard no one's religion as contrary to ours.
True love isborn when all faiths are united.
Much of his work is a testament to the
equality of all human beings. In an age marked
by conflict and destruction, Yunus Emre gave
voice to an aft-embracing love, proclaiming a
belief in a universal fellowship that transcends
all schisms and sects :
The world is my true ration
Its people are my nation.
He was a man of the people and for the
people-a spokesman for social justice who
spoke out courageously against the oppression
of the underprivileged by rulers, landowners,
officials and religious leaders. He thus stood
in the mainstream of a humanist tradition that
has always claimed the moral right to criticize
the Establishment and the powers that be.
And, in what could be seen as an anticipation
of the spirit of the United Nations and
UNESCO, he made a poetic plea for world
peace and fellowship which is still supremely
relevant in today's world, convulsed as it is
by violence and war :
Come let us all be friends for once
Let us make life easy on us
Let us love and let us be loved ones
The world shall be left to no one. N
TALAT SA) T HALMAN,
of Turkey, was formerly his country's Minister of
Culture and is currently a professor fNear-
Eastern languages and literatures at New York
University. He has published more than 40 books
in Turkish and English, including 3 on Yunus Emre.
49
Yunus Emre
j 
[MM) LMfC
 Sf f M
_____
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO Courier Index 1991
January
CITIES UNDER STRESS. Interview with Daniel J.Boorstin. The urban experience (W. Tochtermann). Citizens who help themselves
(J. E. Hardoy and D. Satterthwaite). A new heart for old cities (S. Bianca). The mutilation f Bucharest (M. Lykiardopol). Can Leningrad
be saved ? (0. Nosareva). Chandigarh, a planner's dream (R. Aujame). Berlin, a testing ground for urbanism (H.-W. Hamer). The squatter-
builders of Lima (A. Wagner de Reyna). The Jesuit missions to the Guarani (C. Haardt). Reviewing the accounts (M. Batisse). In the
wake of Marco Polo (F.-B. Huyghe).
February
THE QUEST FOR UTOPIA. Interview with Francois Jacob. Attempting the impossible (F. Mayor). Do we need utopia ? (F. Ainsa).
The fiasco ofparadise (G.Lapouge). A Platonic parable (A. Frontier). Akhet-Aton, city of the Sun (A. Wassef). A golden age (A. W. P.
Guruge). The American l boratory (R.Creagh). Paradise n 4338 ? (V. Revich). Blueprints for an ideal community (C.Ward). Non-stop
learning (G. Leclerc). A planetary utopia (J. Huxley). Imaginary cities (C. Grau). The rock-hewn churches of Cappadocia (A. Brock).
March
A WORLD OF MUSIC (1. Leymarie). Interview ith Manu Dibango. The birth of the blues (E. Bours and A. Nogueira). Brazil :
a kaleidoscope f sound (M. de Aratanha). Tex-Mex music (M. Pena). Latin jazz. The rockers' [ament (A. Sokolansky). Echoes from
afar (V. Brindeau). From guitar to qanun (J. Jalal Eddin Weiss). Song of India (R. Maitra)."Wor) d Music" (A. Gardinier). Ouro Preto,
city of black gold (A. C. da Silva Telles). Coping with uncertainty (M.Batisse). Threading through t e past (F.-B. Huyghe).
Apr !)
PERCEPTIONS OF TIME. Interview with Farouk Hosny. Coming to terms with time (P. Ricceur). Measured moments (J. Matricon).
At peace with the past (X. Bingming). Disturbing rhythms (H. Aguessy). A many-sided concept (A. Hasnawi). Present imperfect (F.
Ainsa). Quartz ime (A. Wassef). " A desire for eternity " (A. Cioranescu). Safeguarding the pyramids (G. Bella). Towards a democratic
culture. Ambassadors, adventurers andempires (F.-B. Huyghe).
May
PEOPLE AT PLAY. Interview with Sadruddin Aga Khan. An appetite for living (M. Mauriras-Bousquet). Between order and chaos
(G. Scheines). Doing what comes naturally (S. Amonashvili). Smile, smile, smile (M. Paribatra). Child evelopment through play (R.
Dinello). Play and the sacred in Africa (B. Comoe-Krou). Games without fun (J. d'Ormesson). Sport and play (G. Magnane). TheDogon,
people ofthe cliffs (C. Haardt). The fabulous land of Cathay (F.-B. Huyghe).
June
MAPS AND MAP-MAKERS. Interview with Jorge Lavelli. The new history of cartography (J. B. Harley). Imagining theworld (C.
Delano-Smith). A lases, ways and provinces (S.Abdel Hakim). The treasures of Montezuma (M.Leon-Portilla). Zheng He's ailing
chart (Mei-Ling Hsu). The pathfinders (A. Pinheiro Marques). When mapping became a science (N. J. Thrower). The perspective from
space (J.-P. Grelot). A bit off the map (A. Sudakov). Celestial c rtography (W.Merkli). The Earth from every angle (L. d'Andtgne
de Asis). Copyright is everybody's bu iness (M. del Corral). The Universal Copyright Convention (A.Kerever).
Mf
July
THE MYSTERY OF GENIUS, MOZART AND THE ENLIGHTENMENT. Interview ith Leon Schwartzenberg. A Europe of
travellers (B.Massin). The age of genius (J.Starobinski). Mozart as a man of the Enlightenment (J. Lacouture). " Every ang l's terrifying "
(0. Messiaen). Two kindred spirits : Goethe and Mozart (M. Osten). A long journey from obscurity (H. Garcia Robles). A composer
in his time. The Amazon symphony. The rock an of Tassili N'A)] er (C. Haardt). From awareness to action (C. Hopkins). The kingdom
of Silla nd the treasures of Nara (F.-B. Huyghe). Freedom of the press : an appeal by the Director-General of UNESCO.
Auguet-September
SEA FEVER. Interview with Tahar Ben Jelloun. Fragments for a private iconography of the sea (E. J. Maunick). The wondrous deep
(R. Sabbaghi). The legacy ofConfucius (W. E. Cheong). In the wake of Ulysses (A.Kedros). Pacific pioneers (T.O'Regan). Music of
the waves (G. Moustaki). Yemanja, goddess of the sea (M. de Aratanha). Night watch, alone (A. Gillette). The shipwrecked sailor's
story. The strange destiny ofUrashima T re (Ninomiya Masayuki). Moby Dick, monster of the forbidden seas (A. R. Lee). Reflections
on the ocean (E. Mann Borgese). Sailor beware ! (P. Giovanni d'Ayala). A scientist looks at the sea (D. Walsh). The ghost hip of the
Antarctic (D. Gunston). The four pillars of Neptune's temple (J. Ferrier). The Blue Plan for the Mediterranean (M. Batisse). Manu
National Park, Peru (J. Serra Vega). The return of the fM/ al-Salamah (F : B. Huyghe).
October
CHILDREN I DANGER. The story of a grand esign (F. Mayor). UNESCO's fir t 45 years ; 1945-1949 (M. Conil Lacoste). The
right to be heard (M. Manciaux). Children ofthe streets (F. Romero). Children i  gangs (C. Rogers). Africa's lost generation. Paula
Li, Mohammed an their friends (A. Vasquez). Stress at an early age (Tariho Fukuda). The spoiled child (A. Rose). The twelve who
survive (R. G. Myers). Child labour in the world today. The Convention on the Rights ofthe Child. A mirror for childhood (F.Vallet).
Sana'a, the pearl of Arabia (L. Soliman).
November
ENVIRONMENT AND DEVELOPMENT : A GLOBAL COMMITMENT. Interview with Jacques-Yves Cou teau. A partnership
with nature (M. Batisse). The citizen and the environment (C. Villeneuve). Rwanda : land of a thousand hills (C. Jeanneret). Energy
for a sustainable world (J. Goldemberg). Hungary : the pitfalls of growth (1. Lang). A world fit to live in (L. Brown, C. Flavin and
S. Postel). What future for Amazonia ? (1. Sachs). Noroom in the Ark (B. von Droste). The first Earth Summit. Time to act (F. di
Castri). UNESCO's fir t 45 years ; 1950-1959 (M. Conil Lacoste). The stones of Aachen (H. Lepie and R. Wentzler). Interview with
Federico Mayor, Director-General of UNESCO.
December
AL-ANDALUS. Interview with Melina Mercouri. The heritage of aI-Andalus (R. Arie). The roots of coexistence (M. Cruz Hernandez).
The rise of the Umayyad dynasty inSpain (J D. Latham). Cordoba the magnificent (P. Guichard). The Christian contribution
(R. Guerreiro). Convergent streams (H. Zafrani). The pursuit of learning (J.Vernet). The Toledo school (A. Badawi). Borges in search
. of Averroes (R. Sabbaghi). Yunus Emre (T. S. Halman). The Topkapi harem (C. Haardt). UNESCO's fir t 45 years ; 1960-1967
' (M. Conil Lacoste).
ACKNOWLEDGEMENT
Cover and Page 3 (righ) : @ Isabelle
Grange, Paris. Page 2 : @ Bernadette
Fevrier, Melun (France). Back cover, JPages 29, 36 : 0 A. Munoz de
Pablos, Paris. Page 3 (left) :
@ Reporters A socies/Gamma, Paris.
Pages 4, 6 (below) :
UNESCO/Dominique Roger. Page 5
(above) : UNESCO/C. Bablin. Pages
5 (below), 6 (above) : UNESCO.
Page 7 (above) : UNESCO/R.
Lesage. Page 7 (below) :
UNESCO/Bracher. Page 8 : J. P.
Laffont @ Gamma, Paris. Pages
10-11, 12 : @Cahiers du Cinema,
Paris. Page 13 (above) : Maria Issaris
@ Gamma, Paris. Page 13 (below) :
Marshall @ Gamma, Paris. Pages 15,
16 (below), 34 (above), 35 : Oronoz
0 Artephot, Paris. Library of the
Escurial, Madrid. Pages 16-17, 44 :
Oronoz @ Artephot, Paris. Page 18 :
@ Bibliotheque Nationale, Paris.
Pages 19, 21, 25, 26, 30, 31, 43, 49 :
@ Roland and Sabrina Michaud,
Paris. Page 20 : @ Roland Michaud,
Paris. Library of the University of
Istanbul. Page 22 (below) : @ Dagli
Orti, Paris. National Library, Lisbon.
Page 22-23 : @ J. L. Charmet, Paris.
Bibliotheque Nationale. Page 27 :
@ Roland Michaud, Paris. Louvre
Museum. Pages 28, 32-33 : @ Dagli
Orti, Paris. Library of St. Isidore,
Leon. Page 34 (below) : @ Reunion
des Musees Nationaux, Paris. Louvre
Museum. Page 37 : S. D. Sassoon,
taken from Hebrew Illuminated
Manuscripts @ Keter Publishing
House, Jerusalem. Page 38 : @J. L.
Charmet, Paris. Page 39 : @ Roland
Michaud, Paris. Royal Scottish
Museum, Edinburgh. Page 40-41 :
Roland Michaud <S) Rapho, Paris.
Page 41 (right) : F. Garnier
@ Artephot, Paris. Pages 46, 47, 48 :
taken from Topkapi, The « ce o
fc/tftty, conception a d photography :
Ahmet Ertug @ Ertug and Koluk,
Beyoglu, Istanbul.
CORRECTIONS
Mr. Jose Serra-Vega, the author of
the article " An ecological Eldorado,
Peru's Manu National Park ", which
appeared in our August-September
1991 issue, has asked us to make
certain amendments to the text as
published. The spectacled bear (page
75) is found in many parts of South
America. For " black lizard " (page
76) please r ad " black cayman "
(Melanosuchus niger). There are only
about a hundred giant otters in the
Park (page 76), and in most parts of
the Amazon basin these animals are
near extinction. The anaconda and
the aquatic boa (page 77) are identical
creatures. We apologize forthese
errors, which did not feature inthe
original text as written by Mr.
Serra-Vega.
The sculpture " Masked Phantoms "
by Clara DeLamater r produced in
the " Encounters " feature of our
November 1991 issue ( " Environment
and Development : A Planetary
Commitment") is of bronze and not
clay.
The credit for the photo on page
32 of the same issue is @ Charles
Lenars, Paris.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
_ __,. _ ''°'' " ' 'E ;'lII ! 1 !'tE i  `-   f ,  ;
Rtlev.  'r,  --  : l., 
 , v
 ,  l'.  m..  ;  
. , 
 fl ``,  " °.r
t ? e'i ill'. l'` ,  
: 
:'',
` ",
'`-
,, "  , _.  : r  ; _.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
