<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="090796eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
&
~%
V-H'
V I \»
Vi
il
Í
Women
speak out
on the
environmen
S.O.S. DUBROVNIK
BY JEAN D'ORMESSON
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
Two cultures:
same glow
Paper collage
by V. Balu
Two women, one
Japanese and one
Indian, are depicted in
this collage by V. Balu
of Bangalore (India).
Their dresses differ,
but the beauty and
glow of womanhood
are the same. So, too,
is the light whose rays
converge from a paper
lantern and an oil
lamp, sources that
suggest the cultures of
the two women.
sss
iim*
B A 'LU
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
MARCH 1992 CON NTS
8
INTERVIEW
VANDANA SHIVA
talks to Judithe Bizot
ThelllNESCO
^COURIER
45th YEAR
Published monthly in 36 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if it is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO,
London, 16 November 1945
1
12
WOMEN SPEAK OUT
ON THE ENVIRONMENT
WOMEN AND NATURE,
AN ALLIANCE FOR SURVIVAL
by Perdita Huston 14
SOUNDING THE ALARM
by Maria Cherkasova 19
KENYA'S GREEN BELT MOVEMENT
by Wangari Maathai 23
THE TASK BEFORE US
by Joan Martin-Brown 26
MIUDA'S WORLD
by Grazia Borrini 28
Japan's Seikatsu Club
BEYOND THE CONSUMER SOCIETY 32
'HOMES NOT SLUMS'
by Marta Trips 34
RAISING OUR VOICES
An interview with Bella Abzug 36
SAHEL WOMEN FIGHT DESERT ADVANCE
by Joséphine Ouedraogo 38
WHO IS REALLY SPEAKING
IN THE ENVIRONMENT DEBATE?
by Peggy Antrobus and Nan Peacocke
4
UNESCO'S FIRST
45 YEARS
(Part VI)
by Michel Conil Lacoste
UNESCO INACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
44
UNESCO INACTION
WORLD
HERITAGE
S.O.S. Dubrovnik
byJean d'Ormesson
47
BOOKS
L'UNESCO:
'Une entreprise erronée'?
reviewed by Lotfallah Soliman
REFLECTIONS
The music of Myanmar
by Khin Mya Kyu
50
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
39
Cover:
A group of village women in
Bihar state (India).
Back cover:
A Mayan woman and her
children in festival dress, San
Cristobal de Las Casas
(Mexico).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S FIRST 45 YEARS
by Michel Conil Lacoste
mi
General policy
The Second World Congress of UNESCO
Clubs sets up a World Federation of UNESCO
Clubs and Associations.
The ABC ofCopyright is published. It will later
be translated and published in many languages.
Education
In the framework of the International Year
of Disabled Persons, UNESCO and the Spanish
government organize at Torremolinos (Spain) a
World Congress on Actions and Strategies for
Education, Prevention and Integration of the
handicapped. UNESCO later helps to implement
in the field of education the World Action
Programme launched as part of the UN Decade
of Disabled Persons (1983-1992).
Exact and natural sciences
A conference and an exhibition are held in
Paris to mark the tenth anniversary of the Man
and the Biosphere programme.
The protection of Venice and its lagoon are
discussed at a scientific gathering.
Culture
An exhibition and a seminar organized in Paris
in collaboration with the Organization of the
Islamic Conference celebrate the commencement
of the 15th century of the Hegira.
An international symposium marks the 100th
anniversary of the birth of the theologian,
philosopher and palaeontologist Teilhard de
Chardin.
A working group is set up to study the prepa¬
ration of a General History of the Caribbean.
A meeting of experts on Celtic cultures takes
place in Dublin.
With UNESCO support, Barbados hosts the
4th Caribbean Festival of Creative Arts.
Community radio,
a short-cut to development
Communication
With technical assistance from UNESCO, a
citizens-band FM radio station goes on the air
from Homa Bay (Kenya). Other, similar stations
will be opened at Guirandurokotte (Sri Lanka)
in 1984, and on the Pacific island of Niue in 1986,
the latter utilizing solar power.
The Asian News Network, a consortium of
press agencies, is set up in Kuala Lumpur.
Events
The centenary of the birth of Pablo Picasso
is celebrated at UNESCO's Paris headquarters.
Joan Miró designs a commemorative medal,
I Above, dancers perform at a gala evening in
honour of Bolshol star Galina Ulanova held at
UNESCO headquarters on 16 November 1981 for
the benefit of handicapped children.
Below, a medal designed by Joan Miró and
produced to commemorate the centenary of the
birth of Pablo Picasso.
offering the original design to UNESCO through
the International Association of Art, of which
he is honorary president.
A gala evening is held as a tribute to Bolshoi
star dancer Galina Ulanova, for the benefit of
UNESCO's programme for handicapped
children.
1
General policy
Meeting in extraordinary session, the General
Conference adopts a Medium-Term Plan for
1984-1989 that incorporates 14 major
programmes predicated on an updated analysis
of world problems. The 14th programme marks
a new departure by grouping together for the first
time all UNESCO's activities to improve the
status of women.
UNESCO now has 158 Member States.
Culture
In Mexico City, the World Conference on
Cultural Policies sums up and renews current
thinking on cultural problems in the modern
world. It adopts the Mexico Declaration on Cul¬
tural Policy and recommends a World Decade
for Cultural Development, stressing the interac¬
tion between culture and development.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Social sciences
Communication
A World Congress on Books is held in London
and adopts a sixfold plan of action that is later
confirmed at the 1983 General Conference.
UNESCO signs an agreement with the Arab
Gulf Programme for United Nations Develop¬
ment Organizations (AGFUND) on a $2-million
trust fund for the development of communica¬
tions in Africa.
The Pan African News Agency (PANA) is
established in Dakar with the assistance of
UNESCO, under a programme of support for
regional news agencies that also extends to Latin
America and the Arab countries. Financial
backing for PANA comes from AGFUND, from
the United Nations Development Programme
(UNDP) and from UNESCO via the Interna¬
tional Programme for the Development of Com¬
munication (IPDC). Other agencies are supported
by a fund in trust established by the Federal
Republic of Germany.
Events
Allen Ginsberg, Breyten Breytenbach, Kazuko
Shiraishi, Sony Labou Tan'si, Thiago de Mello,
Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Andrei Voznesenski and
other poets contribute to "War on War", a poetry
gala held at UNESCO headquarters to celebrate
the 34th anniversary of the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights.
A forum of Asian writers, organized in co¬
operation with the Asian Federation of UNESCO
Clubs and Associations, meets in Tokyo to discuss
"Cultural Identity". Participants include Ai Qing
(China), Yasushi Inoue (Japan) and Faiz Ahmad
Faiz (Pakistan).
im
Participants in "War on War", a poetry evening
held at UNESCO on 10 December 1982 to mark
the 24th anniversary of the Declaration of Human
Rights. From left to right: Andrei Voznesenski,
Jean-Jacques Lebel, Michèle Lalonde, Catherine
Ringer, Mahmoud Darwish, Jean-Pierre Faye and
Jean Metellus.
UNESCO, U.S. Secretary of State George P.
Shultz announces his country's intention to with¬
draw from the Organization.
Education
An Intergovernmental Conference on Educa¬
tion for International Understanding, Co¬
operation and Peace and Education Relating to
Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms, with
a view to Developing a Climate of Opinion
Favourable to the Strengthening of Security and
Disarmament is held in Paris.
An international congress to mark the thir¬
tieth anniversary of UNESCO's Associated
Schools project is held in Sofia (Bulgaria).
M A Round Table is held in Paris to mark the
100th anniversary of the birth of the philosopher
Karl Jaspers.
Culture
The latest catalogue of the UNESCO Collec¬
tion of Representative Works, UNESCO's
literary translations programme, lists more than
900 works from 90 different literatures; the
authors published include 11 Nobel Prizewinners.
The main aim of the programme is the transla¬
tion of classics of world literature into widely-
used languages, notably French and English.
Examples from the catalogue include Cao Zhan's
Dream of the Red Chamber translated from
Chinese into French, Speculative Hymns of the
Veda rendered into French from the original San¬
skrit, a selection of Octavio Paz's poems trans¬
lated into English, and an anthology of Hun¬
garian poetry translated into Spanish. Con¬
versely, Shakespeare and Hemingway have been
translated into Indonesian, Plato and Goethe into
Tamil and Cervantes into Hindi.
Restoration work at Borobudur (Indonesia) is
completed, bringing to an end the most impor¬
tant programme of its kind since the interna¬
tional campaign to save the monuments of
Nubia.
Communication
A first meeting of experts on Co-operation
among Regional Communication Training Insti¬
tutions is held in Paris.
As part of World Communications Year,
UNESCO supports an experimental exchange of
television news transmissions by satellite
involving 25 countries in Africa, Asia and the
Arab world.
General policy
In a letter to the Director-General of The temple of Borobudur (Indonesia), which was restored under UNESCO auspices.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
| A fine harvest Is reaped from Improved
varieties of wild cranberry, a species protected
in the South Atlantic Coastal Plain Biosphere Reserve, USA.
The McLuhan Teleglobe Canada Award is
created under UNESCO's patronage. Offered
every two years, it aims to reward works or
actions of individuals or groups that "have con¬
tributed in an exceptional manner to furthering
a better understanding of the influence exerted
by communications media and technology on
society in general and in particular on its cultural,
artistic and scientific activities".
Events
At the inaugural session of the 22nd session
of the General Conference, François Mitterrand,
President of the host country, states: "Thus we
find UNESCO returning to its original source
of inspiration: to build in spite of storms; to build
a world in which hope will find its place".
King Juan Carlos I of Spain and Nelson
Mandela (imprisoned at the time) share the first
Simón Bolívar Prize. Established jointly by
UNESCO and Venezuela on the basis of a
Venezuelan fund, the award seeks to honour
those who, in the spirit of Simón Bolívar, "have
made an outstanding contribution to the
freedom, independence and dignity of peoples
and to the strengthening of solidarity among
nations, or who have fostered their development
or facilitated the quest for a new international
economic, social and cultural order".
Three empty chairs
M
General policy
UNESCO's regular budget for 1984-85
amounts to $374 million (about two-thirds the
price of a nuclear aircraft-carrier), of which
38% is allocated to education. Extra-budgetary
resources for the same biennium amount to $231
million. The budget for 1981-1983 had been $430
million.
The Executive Board establishes a Temporary
Committee to recommend ways of improving
the functioning of the Organization. The
Director-General sets up four consultative
working-groups to study staff management,
budgeting, evaluation techniques and public
information, and a fifth to conduct a critical anal¬
ysis of the programme.
In December, a year after giving notice of its
intention to do so, the United States withdraws
from UNESCO.
The United Kingdom and Singapore give notice
of their intention to leave the Organization.
Education
Campaigning for Literacy, a report prepared
for UNESCO by the International Council for
Adult Education, is published. It describes and
evaluates literacy campaigns in eight countries.
The "African languagesHorizon 2000"
project is introduced as part of a ten-year plan
to promote African languages, particularly in
education, communication and social life.
1984-85: As part of the "Education for All"
programme, a Major Project in the Field of Edu¬
cation in Latin America and the Caribbean and
a Regional Programme for the Eradication of
Illiteracy in Africa are launched.
The Action Plan for Biosphere Reserves is
adopted. Biosphere reserves are zones designated
under the Man and the Biosphere programme
for the conservation of the plant and animal
genetic heritage, for research into human use of
ecosystems, for recording environmental change
and for education and training. In 1984 there are
252 Reserves in 66 countries.
Culture
The first meeting of the editorial committee
preparing a General History ofLatin America is
held in Buenos Aires in the former home of the
noted Argentine woman of letters Victoria
Ocampo, who had generously bequeathed the
building to UNESCO.
A meeting of experts is held in Rio de Janeiro
to discuss the preservation and development of
handicrafts in the modern world.
The 5th International Congress of Southeast
European Studies is held.
Communication
With the co-operation of France and the
Friedrich Eben Foundation (Fed. Rep. of Ger¬
many), a mission is sent to the Pacific to prepare
the first sub-regional project for the training of
radio broadcasters and technicians.
im
General policy
The 23rd session of the General Conference
is held in Sofia (Bulgaria). In his opening speech,
the President of the Conference, Nikolai
Todorov (Bulgaria), states that "UNESCO has
held firm. It has stood firm while moving with
and adapting to the times, but without ever
denying that which constitutes at once its basis
and its ultimate purpose."
For the 1986-87 biennium, the General Con¬
ference votes a budget of $307 million, later
reduced to $289 million after the withdrawal of
the United Kingdom and Singapore from
UNESCO.
The General Conference takes note of the for¬
mation of UNESCO support groups in Spain,
India, the U.S.A., the United Kingdom, France,
Latin America and Africa, and invites the inter¬
national community to intensify its activity in
this respect.
In his closing address to the 23rd session, the
Director-General refers to "the irreplaceable role
which the intellectual and scientific communi¬
ties play on behalf of UNESCO", and appeals
to them "to find their rightful place again within
UNESCO, in accordance with the intentions of
the Organization's founding fathers". In an
earlier speech, he had recalled that the original
idea of UNESCO's founders had been that the
intellectual community should form one of the
three roots that fortify "the forum for human
communications that is UNESCO", the other
two being the political realities of Member States
and the dedication and competence of an inter¬
national secretariat.
The withdrawal of the United Kingdom and
Singapore from UNESCO takes effect.
A study of UNESCO's work entitled
UNESCO on the eve ofits fortieth anniversary is
published.
Education
Although there are still 889 million illiterates
in the world, the rate of illiteracy in proportion
to world population has fallen from 37.1% in
1970 to 27.7% in 1985.
Two joint UNESCO/IAU (International
Association of Universities) programmes are
launched: an international inventory of research
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
projects on the problems of higher education, and
a series of studies on the impact of satellite tech¬
nology on university teaching and research.
Exact and natural sciences
An Intergovernmental Informatics Programme
is launched to improve access to information
technology in countries that do not possess such
technology.
Social sciences
As part of International Youth Year, the
World Congress on Youth is held in Barcelona
in July.
Consecutive Round Tables are held on al-
Ghazali, the great Muslim theologian and
philosopher, and on Maimonides, Aristotelian
philosopher and Talmudic scholar.
Culture
The 15th UNESCO travelling exhibition of
reproductions of works of art is devoted to Slavic
art. Its two successors will be devoted to Budd¬
hist and Celtic art respectively.
Communication
Awarded for the first time, the IPDC-
UNESCO Prize for Rural Communication goes
to India's "Kheda" project, which uses traditional
forms of cultural expression to create audio-visual
An award-winning entry In an International
competition for young architects organized by
UNESCO on the theme "Tomorrow's Habitat".
Winning projects were exhibited at the
international exhibition held at Tsukuba (Japan)
In 1985,	
programmes and also relies on advanced telecom¬
munications satellite technology.
A Symposium on the Cultural, Social and Eco¬
nomic Impact of the New Communication Tech¬
nologies is held in Rome.
Events
UNESCO organizes a worldwide competition
for young architects on the theme of
"Tomorrow's Habitat" in the framework of an
international exhibition held at Tsukuba in Japan.
UNESCO in troubled waters
m
General policy
Following budgetary cuts resulting from the
withdrawal of the United States, the United
Kingdom and Singapore, 800 posts are abolished
or "put in reserve" in the UNESCO Secretariat.
With half a dozen exceptions, the staff members
affected are redeployed within the Secretariat.
Meeting in Addis Ababa, the 22nd summit
conference of the Organization of African Unity
pays tribute to the Director-General and hopes
he may continue to serve the cause of interna¬
tional co-operation at the head of UNESCO.
The 8th summit conference of the Non-
aligned Countries movement affirms its total sup¬
port for UNESCO.
The amount received by UNESCO up to 1986
from AGFUND is almost $15 million, benefiting
30 projects in Africa, Latin America, the Carib¬
bean, Asia and the Arab countries.
Following the People's Republic of China
(1985), the Republic of the Maldives becomes the
90th state to ratify the World Heritage Conven¬
tion. 216 sites on 5 continents now feature on
the World Heritage List.
During the two years 1984-85, UNESCO car¬
ried out an estimated one thousand operational
projects, organized 838 instructional and
refresher courses attended by 30,000 specialists,
devoted almost $30 million to its major scien¬
tific programmes, contributed to the education
of 3,000 young people and launched or continued
20 international campaigns for the safeguard of
historic monuments and sites.
Since its creation, UNESCO has published
more than 7,000 titles, covering all its fields of
competence, in 70 languages and 150 countries.
Education
StCClO
ai^^ .L
GUATEMALA
»» "l
uHiwi«'"'
PMUTALU»
The Regional Programme for the Universali-
zation and Renewal of Primary Education and
the Eradication of Adult Illiteracy in Asia and
the Pacific is prepared.
Exact and natural sciences
The Intergovernmental Committee for the
Intergovernmental Informatics Programme holds
its first session.
Social sciences
UNESCO's contributions to the International
Year of Peace include a Yearbook on Peace and
Conflict Studies, which lists studies produced
throughout the world on the educational, scien¬
tific and cultural factors favourable to peace, and
the 7th edition of the World Directory of Peace
Research and Training Institutions. Other activi¬
ties targeted primarily at young people make use
of the network of UNESCO Associated Schools
and UNESCO Clubs.
Culture
The United Nations Economic and Social
Council (ECOSOC) transmits to the UN
UNESCO's projected action programme for the
possible proclamation by the General Assembly
of the United Nations at its 41st session of a
World Decade for Cultural Development, under
the joint 'auspices of the UN and UNESCO. The
launch is scheduled for 1988.
The 48th congress of PEN International is
held in New York with the participation of
UNESCO.
Events
Jean-Jacques Servan-Schreiber, Andrew
Young, Abdus Salam, Mahdi Elmandjra, Kobo
Abe and others take part in a Round Table on
"The Future of International Co-operation: Per¬
spectives for the 21st Century", held in Tokyo.
UNESCO's 40th anniversary is celebrated
worldwide. In London it coincides with the offi¬
cial founding of a "Friends of UNESCO" group.
Ceremonies are also held in the United States,
notably organized by "Americans for the
Universality of UNESCO". At Paris head¬
quarters, the World Federation of UNESCO
Clubs and Associations organizes an "Open
Door on the UNESCO Movement" involving
some 250 representatives of UNESCO Clubs and
Associated Schools from 40 countries.
Communication
UNESCO's problems attract widespread
media attention. Partly as a result of misunder¬
standings, controversy continues about
UNESCO's position regarding communications.
It dies down three years later with the abandon¬
ment of the concept of a "New World Informa¬
tion and Communication Order".
TO BE CONTINUED
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
talks to Judithe Bizot
Vandana Shiva is an Indian physicist and feminist militant
who works with many community action groups fighting against
environmental destruction. In this interview she examines the links
between the ecological crisis, the marginalization of women
and the dominant model of economic development.
You are a physicist who abandoned your
country's nuclear energy programme to
devote yourself to nature and to halting its
destruction. How did you reach yourpresent
position?
Ever since I was a child, love and knowledge
of nature have given me my deepest satisfac¬
tion. I was very,lucky to have been born the
daughter of a forester in India and to have
grown up in the Himalayan forest. Then I
studied physics. The real basics of nature as
defined in the reductionist scheme of things
are understood through physics, the founda¬
tion of all the sciences. I had the opportunity
to study biology and chemistry too, but real,
profound understanding of nature was sup¬
posed to be reached through physics. Then I
went into nuclear physics, where I experienced
massive disappointments. It was only when I
was doing my master's degree that I realized
how unthinking nuclear scientists were about
the question of radiation hazards. We were
taught how to create chain reactions in nuclear
material and we knew all about energy trans¬
formations, and so on, but nothing about the
interaction of radiation with living systems.
I learned about radiation impacts from my
sister, who is a doctor. When I was working
in a nuclear reactor in India she kept saying:
"Promise me you're never going to go back
there!" "But why?" I'd say and she would
reply, "but you could have babies with muta¬
tions. You don't know what's going to happen
to you."
When I was groping my way and
exploring these issues, senior physicists would
say, "You don't need to- know these things."
Again this was an exclusion and a violation
of my search for knowledge. If science means
to know, then I had no scientific training. So
I went to Canada and enrolled on a Founda¬
tions of Physics programme, where some of
the basic questions about science that were
troubling me were being asked.
I knew that if I continued studying the
foundations of quantum theory I should be
marginal to my situation and I decided that
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
I must do something to relate myself to the
Indian context. I shifted to science and tech¬
nology policy issues. In the meantime, the
Chipko movement had been created and
because this had happened where I was from,
I kept going back and doing volunteer work
and writing for them. Before I knew where
I was, ecology had become my primary
concern.
What is the Chipko movement? In your
hook Staying Alive you talk of the forest, for
instance, not as a product for the market hut
as prakitia life-givingforce. You talk ofthe
importance ofwomen in the struggle against
the massive consumption ofnatural resources.
I responded to the destruction of the forest
first because I was a child of the Himalayan
forests. They were my identity and my sense
of being. The erosion of the forests hit me very
hard. Just before I left for Canada, I wanted
to go back and visit a favourite spot of mine,
a place where the British had built lovely rest
houses from which the foresters managed the
forests. There was one I particularly loved,
near a stream in the beautiful oak forest. I
went back there, and the oak forest had
become a mere sprinkling of trees, and the
stream was no longer gushing with water.
When I talked to the people in the area I found
that the stream had disappeared because they
had cut the oak forest down to plant apple
orchards, an enterprise which had never really
been successful. (Apple trees need very fertile
soil and virgin forest is usually cut down for
this purpose.)
As for my involvement with Chipko, a
movement of Himalayan women dedicated to
the protection of the environment, I first got
to know a leading figure in the movement
named Sundarlal Batinguna, who was a great
inspiration to people like myself. But at a
second and more lasting level my involvement
was with the ordinary women who form the
bedrock of Chipko. It was their perceptions
and their beliefs that were the really rich foun¬
dations of my knowledge of ecology. They
offered me a new sensibility about relation¬
ships. Ordinary people don't theorize. They
have visions and beliefs. The germ of an idea
or insight that I have developed has always
been a phrase or an action from a person com¬
mitted to act in a concrete situation. All my
theory-building has come out of this nature-
centred and woman-centred action. The spe¬
cial relationships women have with the
environment are due to this. In my book
Staying Alive I attempted to explain why my
insights came from women who were consi¬
dered ignorant and marginal, who were not
given a platform of any kind by society.
Why is it that women sense destruction
faster and are more persevering in the struggles
against destruction? Why do they carry on
when everyone else is cynical and hopeless?
The reason is that women have a distinctive
perception of what life is, a sense of what is
really vital, which colours their view of what
is at stake in the world.
Can women lead the way in the new con¬
cern for the environment?
I think women are taking the lead today.
The important thing is that their leadership
should be taken seriously. For us in India
Chipko marked the reawakening of an eco¬
logical consciousness, in a movement
stretching from the villages of central India to
the western Ghats. This new ecological cons¬
ciousness is as old as our civilization, but what
is new is its re-emergence as a political force
in response to destruction, a force like Chipko
in which ordinary women define the issues.
It doesn't take much effort to say, let's
bring women in. The crucial issue is let's not
push women out. Because of its very specific
nature, the relationship between women and
the environment differs from one place to
another. The movements that have led me
towards my own commitments and decisions
originate in the most marginal sectors of our
society, in the so-called backward communi¬
ties and specifically among the women of
those communities.
1 hese oak trees
save and worship them,
because their roots store water,
their leaves have milk and fodder,
the breeze blows cool
over the beautiful rhododendron flower.
A song of the Chipko movement
If societies have succeeded in reproducing
themselves for centuries, they are examples of
sustainability. Today, unfortunately, these are
the societies that are labelled backward,
whereas the societies that give up too quickly
traditional ways of doing things are called
progressive. That definition, of course, is
biased. It is in countries like India that you
find groups of women who are embedded
both in nature and in sustainable cultures.
Perennial civilizations, not ones that burst into
growth and collapse, have something very spe¬
cial to offer. They enshrine the capacity to
regenerate, the capacity to heal, the capacity
to give and take, to build and create.
But I believe that women in the North are
also intimately linked to the environment.
Even in the most advanced societies women
have been left to care for children, homes and
health. A wonderful study was carried out in
Helsinki which showed that, whatever yard¬
stick you taketime, energy, workwomen
are running Finnish society and the Finnish
economy. It's wrong to say that women are
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Water-bearers in Rajasthan (India).
unproductive, that they don't work. It is often
said that women who stay at home do not
work, but in fact they work harder than
anyone else.
Nature for me comprises the life-giving
forces, the life-support systems, the ecological
systems that make life possible. These things
are violated in the cities and in the country
through nuclear hazards, toxic wastes, con¬
taminated water and polluted air. We need
those life-giving sources of pure air, pure
water, pure food, no matter where we are.
Are we not in the process of amputating
something from ourselves by rapidly
diminishing our powers of regeneration?
The term "feminine principle" is basically
just an English translation of prakiti, a force
in nature and life which exists all round us,
in women and in men. To me, the rise of
modern patriarchy tended to kill the feminine
principle in all its fullness, and in particular
to annihilate it totally in man. In a sense, the
rise of the masculine mode of knowledge,
production and governance was a way of
crushing something essential to society as a
wholeto males and to females. Fortunately,
however, whereas the patriarchs considered
that they were ruling over-passive creatures
(women and nature), they could never fully
take that life away. They could distort and
stifle it but they couldn't destroy it entirely.
I can't imagine any recovery or flowering
of these creative forces of nature, of women
coming into their own, that would leave men
untouched. Men will do one of two things.
Either they will react violently because this
flowering creates a new kind of insecurity and
inadequacy. Or, hopefully, more men will
sense that they have impoverished themselves,
and the feminine principle will emerge as a
creative force which values nurture above
domination, sustaining above destruction,
rooted and experienced concrete knowledge
above abstract, irrelevant knowledge. Surely
these values are important enough for men to
recognize and support them.
Are you saying that male-dominated
knowledge should be thrown out?
Every society except contemporary indus¬
trial society has had criteria as to what it
should say "no" to. Industrial society is the
only one which believes that if you have the
power to do something you must do it. Indian
philosophy is built on the concept that "yes,
you might have the power, but it is impor¬
tant that you use your discrimination in the
exercise of that power". A society should be
able to make choices and judgements about
means, to have values as ends.
I feel that plurality of choice creates an
opportunity to decide what is needed and
desirable, and what is not, and what is good
and what is not. If that kind of opportunity
is honestly and scientifically made available to
society, with the idea of maintaining quality
of life, with participation by people, then it
will undoubtedly be taken. It should also be
recognized that scientists are as fallible as
anyone else and that science and its institutions
are more often than not prostituted to eco¬
nomic interests, since the structure of power
is so closely married to the structure of
knowledge. Many technologies are used to
serve the economic interests of the powerful,
not choices based on ecology and ethics.
Women have already made their choices on
these issues.
Does the exploration ofother planets have
a place in a world-view which is concerned
with improving the quality of life, joy,
sharing, and meeting basic needs?
It's all right to explore. What is wrong is
to justify the exploration of outer space in
terms of solving the problems of this planet.
I believe it is immoral to use people and their
needs as the reasons for outer-space
programmes, which should be seen as what
they are: the indulgence of a group of very
privileged people and countries. Everyone has
a right to explore, but to use that right as an
imperative into which everyone must fit is
another matter. It's hiding the other agendas
which go along with space programmes,
which are not simply pursued for their own
sake but for military and other ends.
What is your attitude to global, planetary
management and the question of local versus
global ecologies?
So-called "primitive" peoples have always
had a planetary cosmology, and for them the
planet has existed in every action they have
taken. The most isolated communities have
had a view not just of this planet but of how
it relates to others and of how balance must
be maintained. The planetary has always
existed in the local. Any attempt to disenfran¬
chise local communities of their planetary
consciousness is unethical.
In what specific ways do local communi¬
ties understand or use planetary knowledge?
Traditional systems of agriculture in every
society have been based on the relationships
between planets, which have provided the
basis for deciding which is the right time to
sow and which crops should be grown
together. For example, many peasants possess
a kind of scientific knowledge which enables
them to recognize certain types of insect
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
W*KV
.'
behaviour which indicate impending floods,
so that they move out in time. But all this is
a thing of the past because pesticides have
killed these living indicators. We create
systems which seem more reliable than tradi¬
tional systems but are actually more vul¬
nerable.
I see two ways in which industrial society
has been impoverished. Ethically, it is the only
society which cannot distinguish between
good and bad, which does not provide a
chance to say no, which has no restraining
criteria, values or limits to action. Secondly,
it seems to lack any realization that its systems
are increasingly based on highly vulnerable
forms of organization. There is no compre¬
hension of how these systems break down
when most needed. If my relationship to
nature provides me with knowledge and a
feeling for what's happening to the world and
what changes are coming, it helps me guide
and protect my animals, myself and others.
I have certain indicators available to me
without risk of breakdown by which I can act
in informed ways. Satellites, computer net¬
works and so on are made to replace what is
considered unreliable, but they are actually
more vulnerable.
What influence can women have? How
can they make a difference? How can they
improve their lives and their environment?
The first thing is that they should not lose
faith in the knowledge they have and that they
should trust in themselves. I also believe that
when those Himalayan streams were disap¬
pearing women knew that deforestation is
linked to desertification and stood their
ground, even though the foresters said that
forests have no link with watershed manage¬
ment. Women's instruments of resistance are
standing their ground, believing in their
knowledge, having faith in their values, not
losing confidence, not feeling inferior. The
dominating system imposes its choice on
people by transforming every multiple choice
into a tragic last possible one. Things are not
black or white. I think that in our time it is
very important to be able to turn around and
say, no matter how powerless one is, well
things could be different, could they not? I
don't think that merely increasing the number
of choices necessarily enriches people's lives.
The criteria of choice are what really count.
Merely to increase the number of choices is
to adopt a supermarket mentality of consumer
choice. It is essential to know when a choice
is not a real choice, and that is impossible
unless people have a sense of discrimination
within them. Relating to nature, being
embedded in it, provides the ethical frame¬
work for choice between different scientific
and technological options.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
speà
on the environment
l
12
HIS issue of the UNESCO Courier is testimony to what women
all over the world are thinking and doing about the ecological crisis
affecting our daily livesthoughts and actions that have their roots in
centuries of observation and understanding of nature. It raises the ques¬
tion of whether women, through their closeness to the earth and their
instinct to protect and nurture all that is near to them, have a special
environmental awareness.
The following pages show that women are in many cases victims
of the destructive forces in the environmental struggle and prime movers
against them. They are claiming a place in the forefront of environ¬
mental action strategies. They maintain that nature does not belong
to humankind but humankind to nature.
The women who write here represent the experience of thousands
of others who share their concerns about the health of our peoples,
our lands, our waters, our wastes, our systems, our values, our societies.
Whether in rural areas or in towns and cities, they are through their
actions showing the way to a healthy environment. Fully aware of the
global ecological situation, they are acting locally to start to make things
better.
The writers warn us to question the notion of unlimited economic
growth and expansion. They speak out against the marginalization of
peoples and countries, whether in the North or in the South. They
protest against the disappearance of biological and cultural diversity,
and challenge those military and industrial processes that cause envi¬
ronmental degradation and the displacement of peoples, overconsump-
tion, debt and poverty.
Instead, they commit themselves to a relationship with the envi¬
ronment based on principles of regeneration and reciprocity, and on
the forming of partnerships between cultures, religions, classes, languages
and genders.
JUDITHE BIZOT
JUDITHE BIZOT is an American sociologist and a former UNESCO staff member who currently works
Opposite page, a Mauritanian with a number of non-governmental organizations engaged in community action and the protection of the
village woman. environment. She was special consultant for this issue of the UXESCO Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
I
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Women and Htim, an âme for survival
'Women know
intuitively that a
society which
turns its back on
Nature is doomed'
14
PERDITA HUSTON,
who has dual French and U.S.
nationality, is a former director
of the Population and
Sustainable Development
Programme at the World
Conservation Union. The
author of Third World Women
Speak Out (Praeger, New York,
1979), she is currently a
consultant with the United
Nations Development Fund for
Women.
X ROM the very beginning of human experience,
women's work has been close to, and dependent
upon, Nature. In early hunter-gatherer societies,
women collected seeds, nuts and roots to feed
their families and communities. Survival was
dependent upon an intimate knowledge of
Nature and her ways. This remains true in many
regions today. Women know intuitively that a
society which turns its back on Nature is
doomed. And many women today believe that
the dominant forces of global society are, in fact,
ignoring Nature's needs.
Everywhere the natural environment is being
over-exploited, weakened and soiled. Evidence
abounds that the dangers of uncontrolled indus¬
trialization are leading to the pollution of lakes
and rivers and to human tragedies like that which
occurred at Bhopal (India), where thousands died
as a result of a deadly gas leak from a chemical
plant in 1984. Just as obvious are the large-scale
loss of tree cover, soils and biological diversity
as a result. of uncontrolled economic develop¬
ment, and the horrors of chemical warfare and
nuclear power and testing.
Women have learned that their breast milk
is contaminated with dioxin, that pesticides and
herbicides are present in ground water. They are
told that the life-giving Sun is becoming dan¬
gerous due to a weakened ozone layer, that chil¬
dren everywhere are vulnerable to genetic dis¬
orders caused by contaminated environments.
Women have observed these phenomena and feel
alienated from a society which has lost touch with
the beauty and power of Nature. They fear that
future generations will be deprived of the diver¬
sity of Nature's creatures and of the music of bird
song.
Another fear emerges from women's histor¬
ical experience. Over the millennia women have
watched as men fought each other, often over
by Perdita Huston
access to Nature's resources. Women always then
picked up the pieces, planted crops anew, nursed
the sick and wounded, and carried on. So it still
is today.
As the planet's natural resources diminish,
and as a growing world population increases
demands on those resources, competition for
access to them will escalate. This struggle for
limited resources may well result in new resource
wars. Evidence of growing pressure is found in
nations which depend on the Nile or the
Euphrates, in Europe where the fouling of soils,
rivers and air by neighbouring nations is a source
of sickness and friction, and in the world's seas
where competing mechanized fishing fleets of
powerful nations deplete fish stocks of the poor
coastal and island peoples.
Fear for the futureof a damaged and dan¬
gerous natural environment or of the violence it
bringsis what unites women in today's world.
Margarita Arias, the former First Lady of
Costa Rica, added another dimension to women's
perspective when she said, "No one speaks out
for the protection of the environment with
greater moral authority than women. Only those
who have fought for the right to protect their
own bodies from abuse can truly understand the
rape and plunder of our forests, rivers and soils."
Her words reach deeply into women's experience
and being, and also help to explain women's dis¬
missal of the argument which focuses blame for
environmental degradation solely on uncon¬
trolled population growth.
Environmental degradationwho are
the real culprits?
It is true that excessive population growth rates
in some areas far exceed the capacity of commu¬
nities or nations to provide for new citizens. It
is also true that pressures on the fragile
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
V
!*V
'
'««**
:«v
i..rf!
\i
*
«sf
¿t-'* - '-vr
s
,
1
">'.
-ST*
*».
ecosystems of some nations with high fertility
rates are increasing at an alarming rate. At the
same time it must never be forgotten that a child
born in an industrialized country makes far more
demands on the world's natural resources than
a poor child in a poor nation. Industries and bus¬
inesses which consume resources and produce
polluting wastes are also more likely to be located
in the highly industrialized nations. Addressing
consumption patterns at the same time as one dis¬
cusses population growth rates is necessary to
refocus attention on the complexities of the
problem.
The major environmental threats to life on
Earth are the weakening of the ozone layer,
which protects all living creatures from the
damaging effects of the Sun's rays, and the
phenomenon of climate change with its attendant
rise in sea levels and changes in food production
patterns. These occurrences can hardly be blamed
on the large families of the poor. Unclean indus¬
trial production, chemical pollutants, the burning
of fossil fuels and official reluctance to curtail the
damage they cause are more appropriate candi¬
dates for attention.
Consumption patterns in wealthy nations,
militarism and poverty are major causes of pres¬
sures on natural systems. Paring back needless
"Women's labour has been
unpaid, and thus considered
without 'value', since time
began." Above, women
washing clothes in Sumatra
(Indonesia).
consumption and allocating a fraction of military
expenditures to human development and social
services and to the eradication of poverty, would
diminish pressures on the natural environment.
Hundreds of millions of w.omen have no
access to reproductive health care or family plan¬
ning services. Half a million of them die each year
of pregnancy-related causes. Millions more are
permanently maimed or ill. This is a major
public-health crisis which has gone unnoticed for
far too long. Providing reproductive health
services to the 300-500 million women who wish
to plan their families would improve women's
health and lower birth rates as well. It is simply
a matter of allocating the needed resources.
Plundering the 'free gifts'
of Nature
Women believe that the present world economic
order is the major cause of environmental degra¬
dation. The global reach of the current economic
structure is well known, and in the free market
system, which seeks profit at all costs, it is easy
to disregard Nature: her "gifts" are free.
Who could be better placed to understand
this point of view than women? Women's labour
has been unpaid, and thus considered without
"value", since time began. In Gross Domestic 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Product (GDP) accounts, no monetary value is
attached to women's contributions to national
economies as family-farm labourers, food
processors, providers of health care, carers for the
elderly, cooks, cleaners, laundresses, and teachers
and nurturers of children. Through long
experience women have learned that societies
attach little value to that which can be exploited
without cost. And so it has been with Nature.
We live in a world which has plundered its life-
giving ecological systems for the benefit of the
few.
In Africa, Asia and Latin America, impover¬
ished peasants drift into crowded cities. In Europe
and the United States agro-businesses are pushing
family farms out of existence. In the state of Iowa
'alone, 20,000 farming families left the land in the
last decade because they were unwilling or unable
to compete with profit-driven, high-tech,
mechanized, chemical-assisted agriculture. Like
their counterparts in the developing world, these
farm families are often obliged to seek employ¬
ment in hostile urban settings.
Foreign 'aid'
from poor to rich
The debt burdens of poor nations have resulted
in structural adjustment policies mandated by the
multilateral lending institutions. Such policies
require the reallocation of national resources to
Right, women in Burkina Faso
grind karite nuts to extract oil
seed for cooking.
Opposite page, a mother
breastfeeds her twins while
weeding around seedlings at a
tree nursery in the Paro valley
(Bhutan).
Below, learning to use
pesticides at a workshop
organized in Sumatra
(Indonesia) in October 1991
by the United Nations
Development Fund for
Women.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
systems and the societies which depend upon
them.
They are speaking up and pointing out the
connections between economic policy and
environmental and human impoverishment.
They arc deeply troubled by the increasing in¬
equities between the quality of life in the indus¬
trialized nations and that in the so-called
"developing" nations. While millions of women
walk for hours every day in search of a few twigs
with which to cook a single meagre meal, others
open cans of chemical-laden foods and cook them
in microwave ovens. Women are outraged by dis¬
parities in the nutrition, education, health and
opportunities available to the world's children.
Tens of millions of street children are the result
of failed "development".
They are demanding accountability from
governments and corporations. They realize that
they have been poorly informed about the
dangers of the contemporary world. They iden¬
tify with the ill-informed victims of dumped toxic
wastes, the residues of faraway industry, and of
military activities which damage the environment
and are shrouded in secrecy in the name of
national security.
They are denouncing those traditional
national security strategies, saying they no longer
apply to the contemporary world. Based on
weaponry, domination of trade and of regions of
provide for debt repayment. All too often, social
service budgets are diminished in the search for
additional funds, depriving families of health care,
education and family planning services. In addi¬
tion, in an absurd form of reverse foreign aid,
poor governments export precious natural
resources and capital to repay "national debt" to
the commercial banks of wealthy nations.
A recent series of meetings held in prepara¬
tion for the United Nations Conference on
Environment and Development brought together
women environmentalists, social workers, poli¬
ticians and feminists from diverse cultures and
nations (see pages 27 and 37). From these
gatherings emerged consensus on the dimensions
and causes of the human and ecological crises
which we witness today. Women from the so-
called "developing world", industrialized nations
and the new nations of Eastern Europe expressed
similar views on the state of the world. They no
longer feel separated by geography or by polit¬
ical systems for they recognize a common threat
to long-term human survival.
They denounce the development model
which has produced such shameful consequences.
The international economic order is not only
unbalanced and unjust, it also destroys ecological 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
the world, these concepts are creating the very
problems which undermine the security of
natural systems.
The logic is simple: there can be no national
security without global environmental security.
Weaponry cannot provide us with global
environmental health. Only a change in lifestyles,
the adoption of ethical values consistent with
long-term respect for and protection of Nature,
and the development of environmentally-friendly
industries and energy sources, will allow us to live
lightly on the planet. As a basic human right,
"natural systems security" presupposes a radical
change in the thinking and responsibility of
global and national leadership. Yet "leaders" con¬
tinue to conduct business as usual, continue to
,take secret decisions affecting the world's seas,
polar regions, skies and forests.
Next June delegations from all over the world
will gather in Brazil to discuss global environment
and development policy for the next century at
the first "Earth Summit", the United Nations
Conference on Environment and Development
(UNCED).
The Conference is providing a rallying point
for those concerned about the long-term habita-
bility of thé 'planet, but will the participants
recognize that survival depends on a redefinition
of development and its underlying values, a res¬
tructuring of the world economy to preserve
human and environmental rights? Will this Earth
Summit produce the acts of political vision and
courage which have been so lacking in the past?
Development must be built on a foundation
of human and environmental rights and dignity.
People-centred, environmentally sustainable
strategies must replace the economically oriented
policies of the past. Adjustments in life-style and
expectations must be made and, yes, all' this will
no doubt be costly. But the cost of not acting will
be far greater.
Transforming the way
we live on Earth
At the conclusion of the Global Assembly for
Women and Environment and the World Con¬
gress of Women for a Healthy Planet, held in
Miami, Florida, in November 1991, delegates
denounced nuclear power and called for boycotts
of non-environmentally friendly industries and
products. Cancellation of official bilateral debt
was deemed a first step in alleviating the
devastating structural adjustment demands made
on poor countries. This new women's move¬
ment, which joins environmental and human
rights, is bound to grow and strengthen. It is a
movement which calls into question the sectoral
approach to world problems and outmoded ideas
of security.
The women's visions that created Rachel
Carson's Silent Spring, the Greenham Common
protest in the United Kingdom, the Kenyan
Green Belt Movement and Costa Rica's Guarari
community housing, will prevail. But although
women are finding remarkable solutions at the
local level, they realize that these efforts will fail
if spoliation at the global level continues. Women
now challenge the world's governments and the
United Nations system to work with them to
create a healthy global environment in which all
species will thrive.
Indian women laden with
baskets of coal.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Sounding the alarm by Maria Cherkasova
IVhen a Russian Journalist invited her readers to take part
in a survey on the environment, many of them told a grim story
of eco/og/ca/ disaster and despair
A year ago I asked readers of Znanie-sila, a
popular science journal for which I write an eco¬
logical column, to reply to an environmental
survey. In all the twenty years I have spent
working on the magazine, I have never received
so much mail. Letters poured in from all over
Russia and also from other republics, or states as
they now are. They came from men and women
of very different ages and professional back¬
grounds. But it was the women who wrote the
most detailed accounts, marked by the strongest
emotions.
When I collected all the letters together and
absorbed what the participants in this long¬
distance Round Table had to say, I was appalled
by the mass of terrifying information that had
come through my mail-box.
Take the case of Zoïa Islamova, who wrote
to me from the town of Kasli-5, in the Chelya¬
binsk region of the southern Urals. Zoïa had been
the victim of a nuclear disaster that took place
long before Chernobyl, an explosion that
occurred on 29 September 1957 in the nuclear
waste storage facility of the Mai'ak chemical com¬
plex, and led to the release of almost 20 million
curies of radioactivity.
"Nobody told us what had blown up," Zoïa
wrote, "and we were not allowed to discuss it.
The neighbouring villages were evacuated. People
who refused to leave were forcibly expelled and
their houses were burned down, even though set¬
ting fire to the buildings was the last thing that
should have been done. We only learned exactly
what had happened in 1989, when it began to be
talked about in the newspapers and on television.
The rumour was that they were going to evacuate
our town too, but that would have cost the state
so much that they decided to leave us where we
were, like laboratory guinea-pigs. . . .
"The places where traces of radioactivity
could still be detected were turned into protected
zones. But people who didn't know what had
happened used to go there to collect mushrooms
or berries. There were signs all over the place
indicating that they were protected zones, but
there was no mention of radioactivity."
Zoïa fell seriously ill not long after the acci¬
dent. Her husband, who was also affected, is now
an invalid. "There is a lot of sickness in our
town," she went on, "bronchial asthma, allergies,
skin conditions, problems with joints and the
digestive tract. We were never measured for levels
of radioactive exposure, and doctors refuse to
make the connection with the 1957 explosion.
But we all think it is the cause of our problems.
We no longer trust anyone or anything. Life is
terrifying. . . ."
The southern Urals area is the only region
of the world to have suffered three nuclear
Hiroshima, a painting by
10-year-old Jolja Stepanenko
from the Chernobyl region.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
catastrophes. Even before the 1957 explosion,
radioactive waste was being dumped directly into
the River Techa. A partial evacuation took place
when people started falling ill, but others are still
living on the river bank. In the spring of 1967
there was a new disaster. A violent wind carried
radioactive particles from the dried-up banks of
Lake Karachai, which served as an open dump
for nuclear waste. Almost a million people
suffered to some extent from the radiation.
The southern Urals region is a monstrous
radioactive dustbin. Besides the billion curies of
radioactivity that have already accumulated there,
especially in the open-air reservoirs, there are
also deposits of irradiated material stored in
containers that are ageing rapidly. These deposits
contain plutonium. Nobody is safe from another
catastrophe.
Faced by such a terrible prospect, people have
naturally not remained idle. One of the most
active has been Natalia Mironova, a deputy of the
Chelyabinsk regional council, who runs the
movement to promote nuclear safety. She is con¬
vinced that the world should learn the truth
about the Maïak explosion, a disaster comparable
in importance with Chernobyl despite the fact
that it has been carefully hushed up.
'I want to shout!'
But the Urals is not the only region that can be
compared with Chernobyl, to judge from this
letter from Semipalatinsk, a city in what is now
the state of Kazakhstan: "I don't just want to say
it, I want to shout it out loud!" wrote S.
Maïdanov, an electrician. "Nowadays there is a
lot of talk about Chernobyl. It was a terrible dis¬
aster. But we have been living with a similar one
since 1949! Until the signing of the nuclear test
ban treaty, there were tests here both on the
ground and in the air. Only the Ministry of
Defence knows how many Hiroshimas there
have been in our region. The hydrogen bomb was
tested here. And all that over a.forty-year period,
100 kilometres from the city. How many lives
has it cost us over the years, how many shattered
hopes?
"I don't know the figures for infant mortality
in the region, but you only have to go to a
cemetery to get an idea. Similarly, there is no
need to check the statistics on childhood illness.
Just go to the paediatricians' surgery and chat
with the long queues of mothers whose eyes are
worn out with crying. I have more than once
heard doctors say that children here suffer from
a very high percentage of blood ailments. Many
are born with physical and mental deformities.
On the ecological map, our region should be
painted black."
Unfortunately, there are only too many such
black spots on the map, and they keep on
spreading. In my survey, I asked readers to
appraise the ecological situation of their own
_ _ regions. Out of a hundred letters chosen at
¿A3 random, nineteen correspondents judged the
*.
-m * M i
..
V *
Rusting boats on the dried-up
bed of the Aral Sea, which
has lost 40 per cent of its
surface area since 1960
because of massive irrigation
of the cotton fields on its
shores. The local fishing
industry is now virtually
ruined.
situation to be catastrophic; forty-three described
it as serious; twenty-five as unsatisfactory; twelve
as satisfactory; one as good. So two-thirds of my
correspondents live in conditions that could be
described as difficult at best. Most of them inhabit
the great industrial conurbations of the Volga
basin, the Ukraine, central Russia, the Urals or
Siberia. And all, without exception, think that
the situation is getting worseeven those who
describe it as already catastrophic, which might
seem to suggest that things could not be much
worse!
I also asked readers to state what caused them
most concern. "The forests! The fields! The
rivers! The blue sky! Life!" answered V. Sergeev,
a schoolboy from the city of Nizhnekamsk.
Health was the greatest concern of those who
wrote to me, and particularly children's health,
which preoccupied all the women. Even though
the medical authorities refuse to make the con¬
nection between the state of the environment and
health, no-one is fooled.
"The condition of the atmosphere is
alarming," wrote one anonymous correspondent
from Dzerzhinsk, a heavy-chemicals industrial
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
» * :
*<*.
*#
« * V*
- -. *
"
« *
t
*
centre near the Volga. "The town is full of asth¬
matics and people with lung infections. My son
suffers from chronic bronchitis and asthma. The
water is just as bad. It affects the teeth and
kidneys. My daughter has been ill since early
childhood. Her teeth are completely black. One
person in two suffers from allergies."
She went on to draw a terrible conclusion:
"I can't stop wondering where it will all end. I
also feel that childless women are less to blame
than I am, for having condemned two to live
exposed and defenceless in this filthy swamp. The
children are sick, losing their hair, dying. If their
mother works in a chemical plant, they are poi¬
soned even in the womb. People just give up, they
all think there's nothing more they can do. . . ."
Many letters came from the Volga area. What
was once Russia's great river is now disfigured
by gigantic dams and transformed into a sewer
for military and industrial waste. "We don't
bathe in the Volga any more," wrote F.
Babicheva, who lives near Volgograd; "we don't
eat fish from it, and at night, the air around it
is not fit to breathe. It is particularly bad on
holidays, when no-one is around and the factories
dispose of polluting wastes. In summer, when it
rains, the leaves on the trees turn black, the vines
lose their leaves, cucumbers and tomatoes shrivel
up. It's not water that falls from the sky but
acid." From Volgograd itself, E. Sokhina, a
geographer, added: "We are seeing here a signifi¬
cant increase in the number of malignant
growths. This is a stark index of the quality of
the water, of the atmosphere, of foodstuffs and
of genetic modifications."
'Each year there are 5,000
more cancer cases'
There were also many letters from Siberia. V.
Kleinina, a lecturer at the Tomsk Polytechnic
Institute, wrote that "This catastrophic situation
is a result of the industrialization of the war years,
of ill-thought-out decisions by the authorities, of
the incapacity and irresponsibility of our rulers.
The city was founded in 1604 on the banks of
the Tom, a river that used to be renowned for
the abundance and beauty of its fish-stocked
waters. Now it might just as well be called the
Carbolic Acid. Cancers, stomach problems and
kidney ailments have all increased by leaps and
bounds." It is the same story in Vladivostok,
according to a doctor who reported that "each
year there are 5,000 more cancer cases".
Every letter described the same ecological
problems, and told the same grim story of misery
and despair. Only the name of the town or vil¬
lage changes. It is worth quoting one more wit¬
ness, however. "I'm seventeen ... I have to live
here and bring up my children. I'm frightened
for the next generation: what will be left for it?"
The words are those of Natasha Chernikova, who
lives in a small town in the Ukraine and dreams
of becoming a doctor.
I was in the Ukraine for the fifth anniversary
of the Chernobyl disaster, in April 1991. 1 visited
Zitomir, one of the regions which suffered the
most from radiation. Our guide was Inna Smir-
nova, who is involved with the aid organization
that groups together the various local associations
protecting the rights of the residents of the
affected districts and who devotes her time to
bringing visitors from all parts of the world to
the sites, so they can see the results of the dis¬
aster with their own eyes and understand what
happened.
She took us to Narodichi, a large village full
of flower gardens but a place where no-one can
live any more. In the centre of the village, now
almost abandoned, there is a new type of monu¬
ment: the scorched trunk of a huge fir-tree deco¬
rated with a black cross, a peal of bells on a
wooden frame, black tombstones. Only the
stones do not bear people's names but the names
of dead towns and villages, wiped out for ever
by radiation.
In the Narodichi area alone, 13,000 people
about half the populationhave been evacuated.
I recently received an article written by a doctor
from the district. In 1990 the mortality rate was 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
twice the birth rate. Of the twenty-two subdivi¬
sions of the Zitomir administrative region, only
four have seen their population grow, and those
only slightly. In all the others, the number of
deaths has exceeded the births. Zitomir is
experiencing a long death-agony. And the story
is much the same in many other regions, not all
of them necessarily affected by radiation.
Arousing the survival instinct
What can we women do in face of such a threat?
First of all, we must do all we can to sound the
alarm and wake the dormant survival instinct of
the human race, first and foremost among the
representatives of the stronger sex that hold
power, and yet seem singularly powerless. Sadly,
convincing evidence of this fact was provided on
14 March 1990, during a stormy session of the
Third Extraordinary Congress of Deputies of the
USSR. The subject at issue was the Constitutional
Law defining the role of the President of the
Soviet Union. A. A. Zakharenko, the head of a
school in the Ukraine, made an emotional speech
to the assembly. "I would ask the Praesidium and
the Congress to pay the closest possible attention
to my proposal," he said, referring to his sugges¬
tion that the performance of the President of the
USSR should be evaluated annually on the basis
of such criteria as the health and longevity of the
population, which constitute qualitative and
quantitative parameters of the community's
legacy to the next generation. Two-thirds of the
deputies voted against the amendment, which was
rejected.
My own belief is that ecology will ultimately
determine the future of the democratic changes
in my country. Everything will eventually boil
down to the question of whether we manage to
survive physically and safeguard the health of our
children. We cannot afford, as is often suggested,
to concentrate on solving our economic problems
before even thinking about ecological problems.
The two are closely linked, and the situation is
so critical that we may react too late.
This is what we women must first understand
if we are to obtain rapid and effective action from
the new institutions of government. We must
demand that the country should move immedi¬
ately to a path of peaceful development, and reject
colossal military expenditure, atomic bombs and
other even more sophisticated weapons, the arms
trade, the priority given to heavy industry ever
since Bolshevik days, and huge, destructive
projects.
Instead let us insist on the rapid adoption of
a survival strategy that would give priority to
physical and moral health and to the safeguard
of the natural and cultural bases of life. For
myself, I would include as a basic part of this
strategy the abandoning of nuclear energy, an
enormous and tragic error on the part of
humanity. Then, too, we must ensure that the
wise Ukrainian deputy's criteria for presidential
evaluation are put into practice. It would also
doubtless be sensible to create special power
structuresand why not a Women's Parlia¬
ment?to defend the rights of women and chil¬
dren and to propose an alternative, crucial for
humanity's future, to the male military and tech¬
nocratic model that has brought the world to the
edge of the abyss.
My country's misfortune is that of all
humanity, which suffers from the same sicknesses
and the same ecological catastrophes. It is just that
for us the processes have been speeded up by
historical circumstances and have reached their
logical conclusion here sooner than anywhere
else. But some people have still not understood
that message. Maybe it was to make us listen to
reason that the Chernobyl bell tolled.
Chimneys belch smoke from a
paper factory at Bratsk in
Siberia, part of a lumber
industry complex.
MARIA CHERKASOVA,
a Russian journalist and
biologist specializing in
environmental problems, is
also director of the Centre of
Independent Ecological
Programmes of the Socio-
Ecological Union in Moscow.
She has published more than a
hundred articles and books.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Kenya's Green Belt Movement by Wangari Maathai
A community-based project created and directed by women
I
A tree nursery of the Green
Belt Movement near Nairobi.
HOUSANDS of Kenyan women are today
playing an active part in a nationwide environ¬
mental protection campaign which takes the tree
as a symbol of hope and an indicator of what
must be done to conserve the environment and
ensure development that meets today's needs
without jeopardizing the world of tomorrow.
The campaign is being waged by the Green
Belt Movement, which was launched in 1977
under the auspices of the National Council of
Women of Kenya (NCWK) as a grassroots
struggle against desertification, deforestation, soil
loss and fuelwood scarcity. Its main practical
objective is to halt desertification by encouraging
tree planting and soil and water conservation in
rural communities. At the same time it is com¬
mitted to increasing public awareness of the rela¬
tionship between environmental degradation and
such issues as poverty, unemployment, malnutri¬
tion and the mismanagement of natural resources,
and the impact of these problems on the polit¬
ical and economic situation throughout Africa.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
If you are interested in supporting the
Green Belt Movement you should write to:
The Green Belt Movement,
P.O. Box 67545, Nairobi, Kenya
24
Above, cover of a brochure produced
by the Green Belt Movement.
Right, Kenyan village women get
together to try to continue food
production for their families on land
earmarked for the cultivation of sugar
cane on a commercial scale.
The story of the Green Belt Movement began
in 1977 when a small group of NCWK members
launched a tree-planting project called "Save the
Land Harambee". (Harambee is a Swahili expres¬
sion which means "let's all pull together"). We
had no tree nursery, no staff and no funds, only
a conviction that there was a role for ordinary
country people in efforts to solve environmental
problems.
We held our first tree-planting ceremony in
Nairobi on 5 June 1977, World Environment
Day. From then on interest in the project grew
rapidly, and soon people from all over the
country were asking us where they could find
tree seedlings.
To help them we approached the Depart¬
ment of Forestry in the Ministry of Environment
and Natural Resources, which has a national net¬
work of tree nurseries. The head of the Depart¬
ment laughed when we told him that we intended
to plant a million trees, and without hesitation
promised us all the seedlings we needed. Less than
a year later he had to go back on his decision
when he found that we had distributed more
seedlings than he could afford to give away. From
then on we had to pay for seedlings from govern¬
ment nurseriesfortunately at low prices and
with useful guidance and support from govern¬
ment foresters.
The project grew by leaps and bounds. In the
last fourteen years over a thousand nurseries have
been established at which women grow seedlings
that are then released to small farmers and to
public institutions such as schools and churches.
The women are paid for the seedlings they grow,
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
and many jobs have been created, mostly in the
rural areas. To date some 10 million trees have
been planted and have surviveda survival rate
of about 70-80 per cent. Up to 80,000 women are
today involved in work at nursery sites.
The trees have been planted to meet
immediate community needsto provide fuel-
wood and material for fencing and building, and
to give shade. Gradually, however, people learned
that trees also prevent soil erosion and the con¬
sequent loss of soil fertility. They came to see the
link between loss of soil fertility, poor crop yields
and famine.
The Green Belt Movement harnesses local
expertise and resources and encourages commu¬
nities to stand on their own feet. We deliberately
discourage direct participation by high-powered
technicians and managers from outside. We want
to create confidence in local people who are often
overwhelmed by experts and come to think that
they are incapable and backward.
The aims of the Green Belt Movement are
inspired by the needs and problems of Kenya
we encourage, for instance, the use of indigenous
trees and shrubs in order to help protect the
genetic resources of Kenya's different ecological
zones (see box). Four years ago, however, our
Movement entered a new phase of its activities
when it approached a number of other countries
in eastern and southern Africa and launched what
will, it is hoped, become an All-Africa Green Belt
Movement Network. Our objectives are valid for
many other countries, not only in Africa but else¬
where in the world.
WANGARI MAATHAI,
of Kenya, is the founder and
co-ordinator of the Green Belt
movement. She has received
many awards for her work,
most recently the 1991 Africa
Prize.
Seven steps
to conservation
In our 1 5 years of field experience in Kenya, we have deve¬
loped a procedure for spreading the conservation message
that has produced good results. The elements of this proce¬
dure, listed below, may also work in other developing
countries.
The message should respond to a local need.
Most people in developing countries are poor and concerned
about basic needs such as food, water, firewood and
clothing. Conservation cannot be presented to them as a
luxury issue. The Green Belt Movement introduces the idea
of environmental conservation through trees because trees
meet many basic needs of rural communities. We encourage
small farmers to plant trees to meet their own needs, and
as we work with them we try to help them appreciate that
trees also do a lot for their communities and for the country
as a whole.
The message must make good sense.
How is it possible to explain the importance of protecting
genetic resources to members of a women's group, most
of whom are illiterate?
We explain that trees which have survived in a certain part
of the country since time immemorial are better suited to
our environment than recently introduced foreign trees. We
often ask members of women's groups to list the ways in
which they or their parents use local treesas a source of
medicine, perhaps, or as pest-resistant wood, or in traditional
ceremonies. This type of discussion helps to make the
environment seem a real and living part of their community
life.
The project must be honest.
If the members of a community feel that a project is honestly
run and designed specifically to benefit them, they will sup¬
port it.
The project should work patiently to motivate
communities.
Spreading the conservation message is a slow process. It
is not easy to motivate rural communities, but if they come
to believe in your own motivation they will begin to walk
along with you and eventually to work on their own for the
message.
Ensure that the project offers some short-term
successes.
It is important for people to see some success stories within
a reasonable period of time. Developing both short-term and
long-term objectives will create momentum for a project.
When a Green Belt nursery Is set up, for example, the first
crop of tree seedlings are released to the community within
three to six months. The women's group responsible for the
nursery then receives compliments and gains respect from
the community.
Try to reach the decision-makers as well as reaching
the rural communities.
Decision-makers in the developing world often pay lip service
to conservation. Without their support, however, it is impos¬
sible to take the conservation message effectively to rural
communities. Decision-makers must realize that they will
benefit if the masses work to prevent desertification.
The message should thus be taken to the powerful and
to the communities almost simultaneously. Even though it
may take a long time before the support of decision-makers
is more than rhetorical, it is essential that they should give
a verbal commitment to the project. Rural communities will
be even more enthusiastic about the project if their leaders
are supportive.
Create a forum for continuous dialogue.
In taking the message to rural communities, the teachers
must also become the pupils. We all have much to learn from
each other. There must be continuing dialogue until people
believe that the protection of our world is for the benefit of
all.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The task before us by Joan Martin-Brown
Wo
"Those who are In positions
of leadership have a special
duty to support people In the
front lines of environmental
crises. They must raise their
voices for the voiceless."
Below, women and children
near Rosso in Mauritania.
ÍOMEN and the environment both provide
societies with shadow subsidies; each is an under¬
valued resource. Yet after all these years we are
still talking about the difficulty of putting dollar
signs on the value of nature and female labour.
In many communities civic concern about
the environment is the "Trojan Horse" for
citizen participation in local decision-making, and
many of the most courageous actors are women.
In many nations their commitment to live in har¬
mony with nature and to respect its capacity to
support life means questioning 300 years or more
of the compartmentalization of knowledge and
its separation from values. The process has gone
so far that today we try to divide urban from
rural policy and national from global realities.
Throughout history women have been the
integrators, the thread linking children and the
elderly, home and the resources of the commu¬
nity, the fruits of the field and the products
people use. If we are to survive the twenty-first
century and beyond, we must draw on their skill
to reconnect many disciplines the better to per¬
ceive the relationships between them. We need
to share the countrywoman's knowledge of food¬
stuffs, of flora and of fauna with the botanist, the
genetic expert, the technologist, the pharmacist,
the agricultural expert, and the engineer who
builds roads and dams in rural areas. We need
woman's voice in the design of habitats, whether
urban or rural, for around the world she is the
primary dweller. Male perceptions of social pri¬
orities and approaches to solving environmental
problems need to be enlightened and augmented
by the perceptions of women. By their inclusion,
the prospects for human development may be
doubled.
In recent times, many cultures and nations
have striven to dominate nature, to act as if they
are not part of it. Concurrently men and women
have found themselves increasingly cut off from
their children and communities. This is the exact
opposite of the situation in traditional cultures
and agrarian societies. We are the first generation
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
to put ourselves, through our self-indulgent ways,
in direct and deliberate competition with our chil¬
dren and their future.
Women must assert themselves to achieve
peace with nature. More and more they now
occupy positions of influence. Those who are in
positions of leadership have a special duty to sup¬
port people in the front lines of environmental
crises. They must raise their voices for the
voiceless.
Women must turn their attention, too, to the
decision-making processes which cause environ¬
mental destruction. They must be prepared to
educate others. Men have pretended for too long
that they can conquer nature; women can show
them how to conquer the future by placing their
decisions and activities within the context of what
nature can tolerate. This means no longer con
fusing needs and wants. What people need, the
environment was designed to provide. What
people want may put us all under sentence of
death.
All this can be changed. The human capacity
needed to heal the world is not lacking within
the community of women. The ability of women
to say "no" is alive and well. They must say "no"
to inappropriate development. They must say
"no" to industries which expect public money
to clean up what should not have been despoiled
in the first place, or expect the vast subsidies of
public taxes and growing bureaucracies to deal
with pollution. Women must say "no" to the
death and disease borne by contaminated land,
air and water systems. Only by women saying
"no" in this way can the world have hope in
saying "yes" to future generations.
JOAN MARTIN-BROWN,
of the United States, has for
more than 25 years held posts
in U.S. and international
organizations dedicated to
protecting the environment
and improving the status of
women. In 1991 she served as
co-ordinator of the Global
Assembly of Women and the
Environment, organized in
Miami by the United Nations
Environment Programme
(UNEP) and WorldWIDE
Network, which she founded.
The Global Assembly of Women
and the Environment
OMBARDED by news of oil spills, contamination by
toxic wastes and all kinds of environmental hazards, people
often wonder what they as individuals can do about it all.
Quite a lot, was the answer given recently by women from
seventy countries who met at a Global Assembly of Women
and the Environment to share their experiences of working
to combat environmental degradation.
The Assembly, held in Miami. Florida, from 4 to 8
November 1991, was organized by the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP) and WorldWIDE Network,
an international non-governmental organization dedicated
to advancing women in environmental management. It
aimed, in the words of Dr. Mostafa K. Tolba, Executive
Director of UNEP. to "establish benchmarks for how men
and women can work together in specific ways to help
solve national, regional and global environmental
problems."
Over 200 projects presented at the Assembly showed
how women have taken the lead In heading off all kinds
of environmental disasters. These accomplishments,
chosen because they were "affordable, repeatable and
sustainable", ranged from the design of smokeless stoves,
solar cookers and solar greenhouses to action against
environmentally harmful projects such as dams that would
have eroded fertile soil and threatened drinking-water sup¬
plies, and road construction that threatened to cause
flooding.
Two projects, one from Asia and one from Latin
America, illustrate the kind of action being undertaken.
In India's Andhra Pradesh state, the degradation of produc¬
tive land had led to the erosion of topsoil and the choking
of water drainage systems, causing salinity, loss of food
crops and increasing unemployment in the villages. Led
by a local woman called Vasanth Kanibera, groups of vil¬
lage women decided to pool their resources and lease
degraded land. No bank was prepared to lend them money.
but they managed to raise a loan from a development
society.
They then revived the land by the use of traditional
farming methods in place of heavily-subsidized, market-
oriented, mono-crop agriculture. The techniques they
employed meant that there was no loss of topsoil, of crop
diversity or of wasted rainwater. The project eventually
involved 400 women in twenty villages. In three years, 700
acres of land were restored to productive use. The project
was so economically and ecologically sound that the
Government of India endorsed it for the entire state of
Andhra Pradesh.
Meanwhile, across the world in Brazil, a woman
doctor's investigation of a metallurgy factory that had
operated for two decades without proper controls provided
a case-study of successful action against industrial pol¬
lution. The factory had been emitting so much lead and
cadmium into the atmosphere that the surrounding area's
cadmium levels were found to be the highest in the world
and its lead levels among the world's worst. A local river
had also been despoiled by industrial wastes. Worse, the
factory had been offering free "dret" (powdered wastes
left after lead extraction) to poor families for paving
gardens, backyards and roads. It had also distributed, free
of charge, used filters from factory chimneys, which were
put to use as bedspreads and rugs. Ten per cent of the
children living near the factory were considered highly
intoxicated by lead and cadmium poisoning and another
17 per cent at risk. Intoxication causes brain and kidney
damage.
The doctor, Tania Tavares, took the lead in inves¬
tigating and rectifying the situation. Under her direction
a team of scientists and students of chemistry, biology
and medicine from the University of Bahia researched the
problem and proposed guidelines and solutions to local
authorities.
The factory management was obliged to reduce the
emissions of lead and cadmium and to accept responsi¬
bility for the medical care of poisoned children and adults.
Lead levels were subsequently reduced by about 38 per
cent and cadmium levels by 68 per cent. Nonetheless, the
local population continued to show high levels of exposure,
and Dr. Tavares and her team are still pursuing their
investigation. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Mf'uda's world by Grazia Borrinii
Reconciling
locai and global
issues in
environmental
care
28
GRAZIA BORRINI,
Italian physicist, has taught
and carried out research into
the interactions between
health, environment and
development Issues at the
University of California,
Berkeley, and at the Istituto
Superiore di Sanità in Rome.
One of the originators of the
Primary Environmental Care
(PEC) strategy, she has
recently edited a review of
case-studies In PEC ("Lessons
Learned in Community-based
Environmental Management").
I met Maria Carvalho last summer, in a squatter
settlement in Salvador da Bahia, Brazil. Maria,
who likes to be called Miuda, is forty-three years
old, illiterate, and a grandmother of eight chil¬
dren. She, her husband and four daughters (the
last one two years old) illegally occupy the land
on which they live. All her other children, old
enough to be married and away from home, live
in other illegal settlements.
Miuda was born in the countryside, where
her father owned a small farm. The whole family
worked in the fields, growing crops and tending
a few cows and goats. Life was not bad then, but
her father fell ill and the family had to sell the
land to a cattle ranching company. The money
did not last long, and Miuda, then six years old,
was taken in by a family in a nearby town. She
got lodging and food in exchange for minor
domestic work.
At age fourteen Miuda married and gave birth
to a daughter. Her husband abandoned her two
years later. When she was eighteen she met her
present companion, Antonio, and moved in with
him. With Antonio she had fourteen children,
but only nine are still alive (the others died in
infancy or childhood). In 1969 Antonio decided
to move to Salvador in search of a good job. A
construction company hired him as an unskilled
worker on a limited time contract.
A year later Miuda and the children joined
him, and the family settled in a rented flat in the
suburbs. Miuda did domestic work, took care of
the children and washed clothes to earn a small
income. Yet there was never enough money. The
family had to move several times, every time to
a cheaper and worse living arrangement. In May
1977 Antonio got seriously sick and could not
work at all. With no money to pay the rent, the
family had to move to a squatter settlement.
Miuda bought the lot on which they now live
from Mr. Bahia, a previous illegal resident who
had weeded the area and so gained some sort of
"right" over it. The lot, close to a brook at the
bottom of a hill, looked like a swamp, and Miuda
and Antonio had to fill it with earth before
building a mud home. There was some sort of
water supply (a well not far away) but no sanita¬
tion, no road, no rain drainage, no electricity and
no garbage collection. The sewers from the
housing schemes on top of the hill discharged
openly into the brook, and every time the rain
got heavy (a frequent event in the tropics) the
mud home was flooded with sewage water.
In 1983, after heavy rain, floods and constant
water infiltrations, the house of Miuda and
Antonio fell to pieces. With the support of a local
organization they joined other residents, and all
of them asked the municipality to help them
rebuild their houses. Initially, only the local
organization gave any concrete help, but a few
months later the municipality also provided some
construction material. Now Miuda's house has
brick walls (the pavement is still pressed earth),
but the infiltration persists and the water around
the house has to be drained almost every day.
Miuda still works, washing clothes for other
people; her husband gets sporadic jobs. She and
a few other illegal residents are quite active in peti¬
tioning authorities for services, but they have the
feeling that no-one listens to them. As a whole,
the community is apathetic, without any form
of organization.
Miuda believes that life in Salvador is better
than in the countryside because town people can
work and earn some money. Also, some of her
children went to school (she gave this informa¬
tion with pride). She likes to live in the settle¬
ment and will leave the area only if forced to do
so. Yet she feels insecure, even after having been
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Above, a relatively well-
organized recent squatter
settlement on a hillside in
Salvador de Bahia (Brazil).
Left, garden plots have been
planted among the shacks.
a resident for thirteen years. There are frequent
rumours that the police will come, destroy the
illegal shelters and send the people away. She says
that many families tried to leave the area to find
a better place to live, but most had to come back
because of economic difficulties. Miuda feels sick
and tired, and looks much older than her age.
The story of Miuda is anything but excep¬
tional. Like her, millions of poor people around
the world bear with courage and ingenuity a daily
burden of personal misery, lack of social support
and environmental problems.
Local and global issues
You and I, and Miuda, her husband and her
friends, will all suffer from the consequences of
global environmental problems. We all are, or
will be, affected by the thinning of stratospheric
ozone, the disruption of the Earth's climate, the
depletion of non-renewable resources and the loss
of unique habitats and the genetic diversity that
goes with them. But while you and I can dedi¬
cate time and resources to discussing and trying
to solve these problems, can Miuda afford to do
so? Can she worry about the disappearance of
local plant varieties if her family must clear some
forest to set up a home in a decent place? Can
her husband be concerned about throwing used
car oil in the brook, when every day he has to
drain someone else's sewage from his home? Can
we ask them to worry about worldwide popula¬
tion growth and plan their families accordingly,
when their children are their best helpers and
friends, and their only support in old age?
Environmental advocates and policy-makers
should consider these questions before drawing
up plans for environmental protection. No
amount of education will get people to care about
environmental problems that affect us all when
no-one helps them solve the problems they face
alone. In other words, is it at all effective, let alone
efficient, to concentrate our attention on global
issues when so many local issues are left
unresolved?
To date, the main focus of environmental
concerns has been on large-scale problems such
as the hole in the ozone layer or oil spills in the
oceans. The media, environmental groups and the
public at large are highly concerned about such
issues, and those concerns have even helped to
achieve difficult international agreements in a
relatively short time. On the other hand, local
environmental problems that are directly felt by
particular communities and rooted in local con¬
texts appear less interesting and are usually
neglected or subsumed under headings like sani¬
tation, housing or agriculture, which share little
of the current glamour of environmental affairs.
It is not difficult to understand this
phenomenon. Global problems are impressive. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
In Salvador, homeless families
burn forest to make room for
more squatter dwellings.
30
They are relatively few in number, clearly
defined, and affect, actually or potentially, human
multitudes. On the contrary, most local problems
are prosaic. There are many of them. They are
ill-defined and complicated by a variety of local
factors. Moreover, each local problem affects only
a limited number of people. Yet it affects these
people today, unequivocally and often severely.
And since there are so many local problems and
they are interconnected, their total impact on
human health, economic resources and ecolog¬
ical surival is huge.
Two basic considerations. The first is that the
problems facing Miuda and her neighbours also
concern the municipality as a whole, which faces
rising costs (for instance for health care and police
surveillance) and gathers little revenue from the
squatters. Also, the land value is affected by the
environmental degradation, and the polluted
brook (lost as a source of usable water) goes to
increase the pollution of Salvador's beaches and
sea. In fact, the economy, social life and ecology
of the whole city and region surrounding it are
in many ways related to the presence and cur¬
rent fast growth of squatter settlements. Local
environmental problems easily feed into
municipal, regional and even national problems!
The second consideration is that for Miuda
and for many other people in similar situations-
issues related to the physical and the socio¬
economic environment are not neatly stacked in
different piles but are perceived as a whole.
Solving local environmental problems means
solving basic needs problems, and vice versa. For
instance, as long as the water supply remains
illegal and sporadic, there will be fights with the
neighbours and little opportunity to improve the
hygienic habits of the children. As long as there
is an open-air sewage discharge nearby, the
squatters will not build or use latrines. Without
security of tenure and social recognition, no-one
will invest time and money to improve the family
shelters or the common areas in the settlement.
With no hygiene and poor shelters people will
easily get sick, will work less and less produc¬
tively, become poorer and have even less hope
of 'securing a piece of land for themselves.
The women in Miuda's community could
organize themselves and start some income-
generating activity, but they will not manage to
do so as long as they do not know where to leave
their children or how to take care of the finan¬
cial and legal requirements of an association.
Having neither land nor money to set up a
shelter, they will not be able to organize a self-
run kindergarten. And they all have many chil¬
dren and very little money.
Community empowerment
The only hope seems to be the empowerment of
Miuda herself and the whole squatter community.
This is a lesson learnt from innumerable past
experiences. Problems such as the ones men¬
tioned above can be solved only with the full
involvement of local people, as individuals,
groups and community organizations. I use the
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
term "empowerment" to indicate an increased,
active control over the factors affecting life and
well-being.
What does this mean for Miuda? It means
that if she is to have any hope of improving the
life of her family and community she should not
wait for solutions to be provided by distant
authorities, but begin with a gathering of her
neighbours to discuss common problems, iden¬
tify resources and organize possible solutions.
This process is likely to involve the creation of
ad-hoc groups or formal community organiza¬
tions to pool resources and face international
bodies. For instance, a legal Residents' Associa¬
tion in Miuda's community would have a good
chance of solving at least one of the most pressing
problems of the squatters, namely land tenure.
Primary environmental care
In light of the above considerations and from a
wealth of experience in community development
and local environmental action, some basic
requirements have been identified and grouped
as a strategy of Primary Environmental Care
(PEC). PEC is defined as a process by which local
communities, with various degrees of external
support, organize themselves and strengthen,
enrich and apply their own means and capacities
for the care of their environment while simul¬
taneously satisfying their needs.
The basic ideas behind PEC are not new, and
to many they may appear as simply good
common sense. What is new is the attempt to
lend strong support to an approach that integrates
different concerns and builds upon the under¬
standing of two key ideas: that community-based
environmental management is essential for local
as well as national and global environments and
economies; and that for such management to suc¬
ceed, environmental, social and economic objec¬
tives must be combined, and pursued with the
full involvement of the affected groups and
individuals.
Women make palm oil (left)
and attend a functional
literacy class (right). Both
activities are part of a
UNESCO educational project
for Togolese women.
Who should do what to set the PEC strategy
in motion? The peculiarity of problems and solu¬
tions characteristic of local contexts and the very
definition of community empowerment preclude
a meaningful general answer to such a question.
Yet very few local communities can succeed
without external help. As things are today,
governments are the prime partners in PEC, and
they are indispensable. They need to allow the
process to happen, and provide the legislation and
sectoral services essential to sustain it. Above all,
governments should ensure that communities
have both access to natural resources and secu¬
rity of tenure, since it is only when tenure is
secured that long-term commitments can be made
and environmental improvements emerge.
Even when political conditions are favourable,
however, most communities still need external
support for specific initiatives. They may need
access to information, technology, credit or
training in new skills and practices (e.g. methods in
agro-ecology, small business management, low-
cost housing, sanitation and disaster pre¬
paredness).
But external support is not enough. Commu¬
nity empowerment is a process that requires the
contribution of all community members and it
can only grow along with their sense of" social
identity. The community should organize, iden¬
tify its own problems and resources and try out
different initiatives to discover what is best for
the local situation. Needless to say, obstacles will
arise, such as conflicts among different groups
within the community or between the commu¬
nity and external stakeholders.
Some solutions are at handat least in terms
of awareness and capacities but in many cases
the institutional and behavioural changes needed
to put them into practice are likely to take a long
time. History teaches us that it is a long way from
ethics to ethos. And this is why "strategies" are
needed. To give visibility, legitimacy, incentive
and impulse to what needs to be done.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Beyond the consumer society
32
The Seikatsu Club, which takes
its name from the Japanese
word meaning "life", was
founded in 1968 by 200 Tokyo
women who wanted to fight
inflation. Today it is a major
network of non-profit-making
co-operatives that has
400,000 members in Japan
and 300 representatives on
local councils. The Club, 80
per cent controlled by women,
seeks to bring consumers and
producers closer.together and
promote the distribution of
natural, high-quality,
"environmentally-friendly"
products. It also encourages
debate and action on other
social issues such as the
status of women, working
conditions and the problems of
old people.
JLwENTY years ago only two kinds of tooth¬
brush were available in Japanone kind for
adults and one kind for children. Ten years ago,
the children's market was divided up. There were
brushes designed for infants, brushes for kinder¬
garten pupils, brushes for primary schoolchil¬
dren, and brushes for secondary-school students.
Today, market segmentation has gone even fur¬
ther, and you can buy toothbrushes for one- to
three-year-olds, two- to four-year-olds, three- to
five-year-olds, and four- to six-year-oldsnot to
mention separate brushes for the front teeth, the
back teeth, bridges and interdental spaces.
And yet Japanese dentists are still as busy as
ever, for the fact is that the proliferation of tooth¬
brushes has had no effect in combating tooth
decay. Dentists still say what they have always
said, that the important thing is for people to
spend sufficient time cleaning their teethseven
minutes a day is a figure often suggested. But in
Japan's consumer society advice from dentists is
not enough. Consumers must be persuaded to
buy products by advertising.
The morning shampoo is another example of
consumerism in the Japanese personal-hygiene
industry. In spite of many warnings about the
dangers of washing one's hair too often, a daily
morning shampoo has become fashionable, par¬
ticularly among young people and housewives.
The shampoo industry has latched onto an
opportunity to extend its market, not just by
selling more of the core product but also by mar¬
keting such incidentals as specially-designed
morning-shampoo basins and towels. (The latter
have been tested for water absorption and found
to be no different from any others.)
The side-effects of this commercial bonanza
include a 50-per-cent increase in the volume of
water used per family in the mornings, and
increased pollution caused by flushing away the
active ingredients in the shampoo. Many young
people are suffering premature hair loss as a result
of washing their hair too often. The big profits
from the morning-shampoo market have gone to
private corporations, but the costs of cleaning up
the water have been paid by the public in taxes.
The Japanese food industry has grown fat on
Japan's affluence, and because of market satura¬
tion now finds it difficult to launch new products.
The latest catchwords are "fresh" and "perish¬
able". Even sake, wine and beer are described as
perishable. They should, it is suggested, be
decanted straight from the bottle into the glass.
Consumers who know no better are per-
Japan's Seikatsu Club
suaded by the "perishable" label to buy more
foodstuffs, even products that may have been
heat-treated to conserve them. As a result, market
volume is boosted, but at the cost of increased
dumping of products suspected by their pur¬
chasers, perhaps wrongly, of having gone off.
Consumers thus play into the hands of manufac¬
turers, who encourage them to consume to the
hilt and then throw things away.
Food has become a commodity like any
other. Transplanted to cities, farmers forget how
to farm and children do not learn how to grow
things. City kids can be forgiven for thinking that
tomatoes and peppers are produced in green¬
grocers' shops and that the cows back home on
the land are creatures of myth. The inhabitants
of Third-World countries where lobsters are
trapped cannot afford to eat them, but must
export them to Japan, where only parts of the
head are eaten and the rest is thrown away.
Reforming the structures
of consumption
We Japanese, a century after our Industrial Revo¬
lution, are in danger of becoming puppets of the
market economy, but this trend is not going
unchallenged. One organization which is trying
to do something about the situation is the Seikatsu
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Top, members of the Seikatsu
Club tour one of the Club's
dairies.
Above, in a Tokyo street,
demonstrators show how to
make home-made soap from
used cooking oil.
Left, shoppers appraise the
wares at an organic-food
market in the Japanese
capital.
Club, a 400,000-strong consumers' co-operative.
Actually, we do not call ourselves consumers.
The word itself derives from the Latin consumere,
"to take up wholly, to consume, waste, squander
or destroy". It acquired its present meaning with
the development of industrial capitalism, which
saw the consumer as a passive receiver of pub¬
licity and advertising, which by awakening wants
and needs dreamed up by the corporations would
link mass consumption to mass production.
In the Seikatsu Club, we reject this commer¬
cial definition of consumerism. Instead we see
ourselves as autonomous individuals forming an
integral part of the whole cycle of production,
distribution and disposal.
The Club has pioneered the joint purchase
of essential goods in Japan. Its members are
referred to not as consumersby implication,
passive acceptors of merchandisebut as "the
living people". We speak of "necessities of life"
rather than of consumer goods, rejecting a term
that implies production in the name of profit and
that fails to recognize the link between consumer
and producer.
We want to speak out against the evils of
industrialized society, and also to create a sus¬
tainable communal society in its place. We hope
to breathe fresh life into the idea of a lifestyle of
individual autonomy in co-operation with others.
We think of the Club as a weapon: the power
to buy also implies the power not to buy, in other
words to boycott. Our goal is not just to offer
safe consumer goods at reduced prices, or to pass
on organic or environmentally-friendly produce
at rather higher prices, in the name of an intelli¬
gent and well-informed consumerism. On the
contrary, we want to reform the structures of
consumption in depth.
The joint buying system aims to focus the
power of our members so as only to purchase
necessities produced by like-minded producers.
We hold joint discussions about the disclosure of
ingredients, additives and, where applicable,
processing measures and pesticides employed,
thereby establishing direct linkage between con¬
sumers and producers. We aim to create an alter¬
native market, one in which value-added and
surplus-value-added profits do not increase costs.
In our Club only the intrinsic value of the
product matters.
An alternative lifestyle
We will not buy synthetic detergents, which
harm the environment, nor chemically-flavoured
foods nor products we consider inessential. We
do buy soap, 100-per-cent fresh orange juice and
the dried bonito used to make miso soup. We pur¬
chase reusable bottles and cans but not plastic
containers. We have two dairy farms of our own,
and our members collect used cooking oil in their
workplaces to form the basis for natural soaps.
The next step is to extend the principles of
the Club as the basis of a universal alternative
lifestyle. Therein, we believe, lies the key to
instilling the new values society needs. Further¬
more, the Club's style of co-operative action can
also be used as a tool to reform political, educa¬
tional and cultural institutions.
The goal is for every individual in the Club to
think for him- or herself, and to act indepen¬
dently in order to create a new civil society based
on the slogan "Autonomy in Life". We are
calling on our neighbours to join us in doing so;
for this form of struggle is the best way to say
goodbye to the consumer society once and for all.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
'Homes not slums' by Marta Irejosi
A self-help
project that built
a sense of
community as
well as decent
housing for
homeless families
VJuARARÍ, a housing complex built five years
ago on the outskirts of San José, the capital of
Costa Rica, is the result of an extraordinary
experiment undertaken by a group of women
who campaigned under the slogan: "Homes, not
slums". Their daily struggle against poverty gave
them some ideas for solving their housing
problems.
The women represented more than 30,000
families, most of which were of rural origin. They
missed the fresh air of the countryside, and
wanted to do something about the problems of
urban overcrowding.
The building and town-planning regulations
applied by the authorities recreated in new
housing projects the urban structures that had
given rise to shanty-towns. The women reacted
strongly to this and rejected official housing
programmes. "We want a house to live in, not
a roof to sleep under," they proclaimed. "We
need a school and a dispensary nearby; we want
our children to be able to play in safety, climb
trees and enjoy nature; we want jobs."
The homeless families seemed to regard all
social problems as interlinked. They wanted to
get rid of the shanty-towns, and at the same time
they wanted to make sure that their families were
properly fed and their health and education needs
were provided for. They fought for genuine
improvements in their living conditions along
with their new housing.
Lending a hand
The women were helped by the Feminist Infor¬
mation and Action Centre (CEFEMINA), an
institution dedicated to the defence of the rights
of women which had already backed similar
projects in several other Costa Rican towns. To
get a house in the new development, each family
had to put in 700 hours' work. Not all this time
necessarily had to be spent on the building site.
Other options included looking after children,
preparing collective meals, and serving on com¬
mittees concerned with such matters as health,
legal questions and the environment.
A volunteer group of women technicians
designed a new type of housing to meet the needs
expressed by the women of Guaran. Government
experts yielded to pressure from them, especially
since the projects the women put forward were
s less costly than the alternatives.
Next the women buckled down to the con¬
struction of the houses. No task was too hard for
them. They took everything in hand, from
directing the teams of workers to providing
building materials and organizing the thousands
of volunteers who gave up their spare time to
work on the project. At weekends the site was
34
MARTA TREJOS,
Costa Rican sociologist, is the
Executive Director of the
Feminist Information and
Action Centre (CEFEMINA) in
Costa Rica, and co-ordinator of
the "Woman and the
Environment" movement in
Central America.
*5« j^*í-
V . A' ." --Kr**
	
:*
___
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Above: "The women buckled
down to the construction of
their houses. No task was too
hard for them."
Left: "Everyone lent a hand,
including the old. . . ."
a hive of activity as people crowded in to help
to build the houses. Everyone lent a hand,
including the old, the handicapped and children.
During moments of relaxation on the site, the
volunteers gave advice to groups of women on
such subjects as food hygiene, breast-feeding,
birth control, social legislation and sanitation. As
a result of this active solidarity, not only did the
houses go up in record time but the new com¬
munity developed a way of life that seems likely
to endure.
Contact with nature
Constructed in blocks of a hundred, the houses
were built in a variety of forms adapted to the
lie of the land. They give onto shared internal
courtyards, where trees can grow in sheltered
conditions. In this respect, Guarari is a model
development, for it has encouraged the protec¬
tion of numerous endangered plant species,
including trees that were formerly associated with
coffee growing but are now superfluous because
of modern agricultural techniques.
Thanks to its leisure areas and communal
green spaces, the Guarari district has plenty of
land that everyone can enjoy while keeping up
the neighbourly relationships formed during the
construction work. The cultivation of vegetables
and medicinal plants and animal rearing on a
small scale provide jobs and bring in money to
finance a variety of activities which are co¬
ordinated by a large community centre. Known
as the Casa de la mujer (the Woman's House), the
Centre houses a dispensary, a legal advice bureau,
a centre for battered women and children, old
people's associations and sports and leisure clubs.
Traffic is restricted in Guarari. Most of the
roads are for pedestrians only, so that children
are shielded from the danger of road accidents and
that while they are playing their mothers can
keep an eye on them from their kitchen
windows.
Modern construction techniques, using
materials light enough for women to handle, have
also provided a solution to the problem of waste¬
water disposal. Guarari has a water-treatment
plant that cleans effluent before discharging the
water into watercourses. The opening of the plant
coincided with the launch of an anti-pollution
campaign aimed at cleaning up the local rivers.
It was decided to protect the basin of the river
that crosses the district and to turn it into a park,
primarily to save the stream from being used as
a public drain that would create social and sani¬
tary problems for the community. The river's
flora and fauna have been inventoried and pro¬
tected. Children learn to live in harmony with
nature while playing on the river-bank.
In the course of coping with the difficulties
of everyday life, the people of Guarari have found
solutions to wider problems, thanks to an active
community life and particularly to the dynamism
of the womenfolk. The last word should be left
to one of them. "Everyone's an expert and an
instructor here. We go to specialists for advice
so we can find out how to get by without them.
We learn from one another, and everyone gets
the advantage. Our real triumph is that the entire
community now recognizes that bringing women
into its public life has benefited everyone." 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Raising our voices
A leading feminist sets forth her views on the eve
of the Earth Summit
Women play an important
role in rural development in
Guinea.
"Women have been trained to speak softly and carry
a lipstick. Those days are over."
BELLA ABZUG
A former member of the U.S. Congress, a
lawyer and feminist activist, Bella Abzug has
become a leading advocate of environmental secu¬
rity and a more economically just world. As spe¬
cial adviser to Maurice Strong, the Secretary-
General of the United Nations Conference on
Environment and Development (UNCED), she
is encouraging women around the world to speak
up and take part in the Conference's decision¬
making processes.
"I want to see women remobilize on a global
scale," she says. "Women are the very core of
the environment, which is the sine qua non of
existence. Women's knowledge, skills, experience
and instincts have not been taken into consider¬
ation. Yet women, who constitute 50 per cent
of the world's population, are also the majority
of the world's food producers80 per cent in
Africa, 60 per cent in Asia, 40 per cent in Latin
Americaas well as its major users and con¬
sumers. They are the most concerned about
threats to the health of our planet, the most active
in cleaning up man-made messes. But women
must be more than global housekeepers, and until
they are treated equally with men nothing will
change.
"I believe women will bring a new vision,
with new perspectives as to how and what to
change. It's easier with women because they are
not part of what has taken place. They are totally
unshackled, not only by lack of ownership but
by lack of involvement in decisions to date. They
are freer and more independent.
"So we are going to strengthen the existing
networks of women (of which there are many),
not just for the Rio conference but for the next
century. Things have to change from the bottom
up. I'm involved in organizing international
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The logo of the World Women's
Congress for a Healthy
Planet, held in Miami (USA) in
November 1991.
conferences where women come who act locally
even while they learn to think globally. I am
going to tell people about the need to create a
movement to change the world and the condi¬
tions for women's self-empowerment.
"The Miami Congress (see box this page) gave
women significant strength and a sense of them¬
selves. It brought women together to talk about
the interconnection of hunger, disease, poverty,
maldevelopment, misallocation of resources,
illiteracy, war and peace. None of this is in isola¬
tion. Environment and development are
connectedsustainable development is only pos¬
sible in a sound environment. So the agenda we
are launching for the twenty-first century is for
a world in which we settle disputes peacefully,
give priority to health and conquering poverty,
disease and illiteracy; in which people are housed
and have food and other securities; in which
women share equally with men the power to
decide what the world looks like, a peaceful
world in which to educate our children in an
environmentally sound planet.
"We have a message for the Heads of State
who will attend the Earth Summit. Our message
is very simple. We are here to say that this mad
race towards self-destruction must stop and the
great military powers must show the way by
working much harder for peace and disarmament.
We are here to say that no country has the right
to call itself a democracy when it denies equal par¬
ticipation in policy-making to women. We are
here to say that women must be represented at
every level, that our exclusion from economic
and political power must end.
"I believe that the political empowerment of
women may well provide the missing part of the
equation that is needed to restore the health of
our planet. Over the years, women have lobbied,
marched, toiled, pleaded, prayedthere was
always music and dancing. But for some time this
has stopped. It is now time to start up the music
again."
The World Women's
Congress for
a Healthy Planet
Following on from the Global Assembly of Women
and the Environment (see page 27), the World
Women's Congress for a Healthy Planet, held in
Miami the following week, brought together more
than 1,200 women from 83 countries. The Congress
was organized by the International Policy Action Com¬
mittee, a body created by Bella Abzug. It summed
up its deliberations in an Action Agenda for the 2 1st
Century, which it described as "a challenge to women
and men to work together to create a safe and sus¬
tainable future." Some of the major points on the.
Agenda were:
To demand full and equal participation for women
and men in decision-making and policy implementa¬
tion at international, national and community levels.-
To recommend that all public policy-making groups
contain no more than 60 per cent and no less than
40 per cent of either sex.
To work for adoption of an International Code of
Environmental Conduct by business and industry as
well as by governments and UN agencies.
To demand time-use studies of women's work,
including housework and care of children and the
elderly.
To urge governments to agree to a timetable for
implementation of full-cost accounting that would
include environmental and social costs in both
national accounting systems and in calculating sub¬
sidies and incentives in international trade.
To demand an end to nuclear testing and the dis¬
mantling of existing nuclear weapons.
To demand the creation of gender-balanced
national civilian commissions to open all military
activities and expenditure, including research and
development, to public scrutiny.
To demand that armies be used as environmental
protection corps to monitor and repair damage to
natural systems.
To support indigenous people's efforts to protect
their natural environments.
To pledge to use women's consumer power to boy¬
cott businesses and institutions that are not eco-
conscious, and to support and commend those that
are.
To encourage global networks of women to facili¬
tate the analysis of consumer goods, from the extrac¬
tion of the raw materials through the production
process to their use and disposal.
To promote environmental ethics education in
schools.
To call for the creation of a permanent gender-
balanced UN Commission on Environment and
Development to promote environmental awareness
and to investigate complaints.
To call on world leaders attending the 1992 Earth
Summit to sign a Global Climate Change Convention,
with industrialized countries making a minimum com¬
mitment to a 20% reduction of carbon dioxide by
the year 2000. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Safiel women fight desert advance
by Joséphine Ouedraogo
Re
A village that
owes its survival
to its womenfolk
38
JOSEPHINE OUEDRAOGO,
of Burkina Faso, is a
sociologist and former
government minister. She is
currently working at the
Panafrican Development
Institute at Douala (Cameroon),
where she is the co-ordlnator
of a project on Women and
Health In Sub-Saharan Africa.
LOURFA is a village in the Sahel region of Niger.
Since the last great drought some fifteen years ago,
it has owed its survival to its womenfolk.
The people of Kourfa, which is situated 260
kilometres north-east of Niamey, are farmers and
former herdsmen condemned to a sedentary life
because of the degradation of pastureland. Reduced
rainfall and the drying-up of watering-places and
vegetation, combined with violent sand-storms, have
virtually deprived the village of harvests for the past
five years. The men have had to travel far away to
find seasonal work, and sometimes they have not
come back. In 1988, there were only 900 people left
in Kourfa, most of them women, children and old
people.
It is the women who keep Kourfa alive. Despite
the few resources at their disposal, the solitude and
the hard physical labour which they are forced to
perform because of the absence of their menfolk,
they have succeeded in supporting the most vulner¬
able members of the community, the old people and
the children. To survive, they gather dead wood and
dry grasses which they sell as fuel in the market at
Abala, seven kilometres away. The money they earn
enables them to buy some provisions.
Each day brings a new round of domestic tasks.
Looking for wood and water is an exhausting busi¬
ness involving several hours' walking and effort
beneath an implacable sun. The children suffer from
nutritional deficiencies, and the nearest chemist is
seventeen kilometres away.
Until 1984 the village had only one well, 60
metres deep and overused, which barely sufficed for
the domestic needs of Kourfa and the neighbouring
villages. The Association of Women of Niger
obtained a grant from the American Development
Foundation to finance the drilling of another well,
and to provide equipment for market gardening and
small-scale farming.
With the help of an agricultural adviser, the
women have laid out a small market garden around
the well. One hundred and forty of them have plots
there in which they grow vegetables to feed their
families. A small part of the harvest is dried for sale
in the market at Abala, providing the women with
the wherewithal to procure other goods, including
the cereals they lack since Kourfa no longer receives
sufficient rainfall to permit the cultivation of millet.
Men returning to the village have been surprised
to find that life has become possible there again
thanks to the courage of the women. Some are
tempted to stay and take up vegetable-growing
themselves, but there are not enough allotments to
go round, and too little water. So Kourfa's women
are now calling for a second well, an extension of
the market garden, agricultural materials and seed.
They are willing to pay the necessary price "so the
men won't go away again".
In the last twenty years, the social and economic
problems associated with the desertification of the
Sahel have generally grown worse. Hundreds of vil¬
lages in the area are now in danger of disappearing.
Let us hope that the decisions taken at this year's
Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro will bring the
people of these steadily deteriorating areas some
improvement in their living conditions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Who is really speaking in the environment debate?
'The real dialogue
is about the
model of
development and
about values'
by Peggy Mrobus and Nan Peacocke
L
Women gather in Nairobi
(Kenya) in 1985 for the World
Conference to Review and
Appraise the United Nations
Decade for Women: Equality,
Development and Peace
(1976-1985).
, famous painting by Pieter Brueghel, entitled
Landscape with the Fall of Icarus, depicts a beau¬
tiful harbour with houses rising from the water¬
front. The reason for its title is not immediately
apparent, and the viewer has to look very care¬
fully to find the subject of the painting, the two
legs of Icarus protruding from the surface of the
water.
The picture can be taken to symbolize what
is happening in the environmental debate. The
story being told "on stage" does not represent
what is happening "off stage" where real life is
being lived. On stage the North often claims that
it is trying to protect the environment, while the
South, bent on development, is destroying it. But
these are simplified characters. Off stage some¬
thing else is happening. In order to understand
the real story we have to leave the stage.
"The North" destroyed much of its own
environment and that of the South as part of the
colonial project. As the ecological consequences
of this became apparent, Northern environ¬
mental groups began to challenge the practices
of unrestrained industrialization and the nuclear
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
40
age. The membership of these groups was diverse,
ranging from grassroots movements concerned
about health and land rights to members of the
scientific community and "nature-lovers".
However, "environmentalism" only emerged in
a leading role on stage when financial interests
saw an opportunity to capitalize on this situation
by offering technological solutions to the
environmental crisis.
"South" is also a complex character. Southern
governments have a legitimate concern about
creating a better life for their people. However,
this project, Development, becomes corrupted by
the alliance between certain Northern financial-
technological interests and certain Southern
interest groups. "Developmentalism" emerges as
a kind of industry, absorbing the time and talent
of millions of people in its management and
shaping the lives of hundred of millions more.
Hidden persuaders
If the characters of North and South are imper¬
sonators, who is really speaking? We have already
identified the financial interests concealed beneath
the cloaks of North and South. Their interest is
in capital accumulation promoted through inter¬
national trade. Unless these interests are clearly
identified the dialogue is meaningless. Some of
these interests are involved in exploiting the
natural resource base of the South with technol¬
ogies which destroy the environment. Others are
selling "environmentally-friendly" technologies
chiefly to Northern industries which can afford
them.
One implication of this is that the terms
"North" and "South" are not useful. On the one
hand they mask the pervasiveness of Northern
financial-technological interests in South econo¬
mies. On the other they conceal the common
interests of grassroots movements in both North
and South built around issues of health and
environment, and worst of all they set up a false
dichotomy between North and South.
The position of the North is ostensibly about
"protecting the environment", that of the South
is about "promoting development", but there are
strong voices in the South which seek to protect
their environments from the negative conse¬
quences of a development model which is
exploitative of both natural and human environ¬
ments, just as there are voices in the North
challenging the excesses of the same development
model on their health and livelihoods.
Indeed, as experience in the South shows,
there is no necessary conflict between human
livelihoods and environmental security. The con¬
flict between these two is another consequence
of the colonial project. Colonial expansion led
to the large-scale appropriation of the most valu¬
able land for the benefit of Northern industrial
interests. Millions of peopleperhaps the
majority of the Earth's populationare still being
displaced and driven to struggle for subsistence
on shrinking economic marginswhether in the
deserts of Africa, on eroded hillsides in the Carib¬
bean, in refugee camps in the Middle East, or in
the urban slums of Asia and Latin America. The
same process of marginalization is evident in the
ghettos of the United States and the polluted cities
of Eastern Europe.
The actions that are threatening to annihilate
humankind and the planet are rooted in the con¬
flict between industrial society and naturea con¬
flict in which the imperatives of industrial society
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Bangladesh's Grameen Bank
provides small sums of credit
to the rural poor, and
particularly to women (below
left) who make up over 90%
of its clients. A loan from the
bank enabled 26-year-old
Feroja (below, right), to open
a drinks stall which she has
now expanded into a small
grocery. Borrowers contribute
to a fund which helps to
provide education for needy
children, above.
PEGGY ANTROBUS,
Barbadian economist, Is
General Co-ordinator of the
Women and Development
(WAND) unit at the University
of the West Indies, and
president of DAWN
(Development Alternatives for
Women for a New Era).
NAN PEACOCKE,
also from Barbados, is a
publications editor with the
WAND unit. She writes on
cultural and environmental
issues in the Caribbean.
dominate both the human and natural environ¬
ments. The environmental crisis is the conse¬
quence of an inequitable world system between
countries and within countries. The real dialogue
is therefore about the model of development and
about values. This model of development leads
to overconsumption in the North and among a
small group of people in the South and, on the
other side of this coin, underconsumption among
the majority of people in the South and a
minority in the North.
Women in search
of development alternatives
Third World women are in the forefront of the
challenge to this model, and there are an
increasing number of women in the North who
share this perspective. Women, as key decision¬
makers in consumption, are also well placed to
play a special role in changing consumption pat¬
terns. Two projects illustrate what can and is
being done: the Women & Development Unit
(WAND) of the School of Continuing Studies of
the University of the West Indies (a regional
project) and the network of Third World
feminists advocating Development Alternatives
for Women for a New Era, DAWN (an interna¬
tional project).
WAND, which was established in 1978, is an
initiative of Caribbean women determined to
ensure that the regional university would play a
more active role in advancing programmes within
the framework of the United Nations Decade for
Women. Over the years, as a result of its anal¬
ysis of the destructive impact on women of struc¬
tural adjustment policies imposed from outside,
its programmes of training, technical assistance,
communications and networking have shifted
from a focus on "integrating women in develop¬
ment" to "empowering women for social
change".
The recognition of the need to make this con¬
ceptual shift was facilitated by the involvement
of women from the Caribbean in discussions at
the international level. A meeting of Third World
women researchers, activists and policy-makers
in Bangalore, India, in August 1984 assessed what
had been learned from our experience over this
period. As we talked, the theme "crisis" emerged
as the common motif linking African food secu¬
rity, Latin American and Caribbean debt, Middle
Eastern fundamentalism and nuclear testing in the
Pacific. Our analysis showed that these appar¬
ently separate crises were related through the
growth-oriented economic model which domi¬
nated our countries, and the need for women to
organize to change the structures which keep
them marginalized. The group produced a docu¬
ment for the End-of-Decade Conference in
Nairobi and formed the DAWN network.
DAWN's perspective
on the environment
DAWN's analysis has the following charac¬
teristics: it is holistic; it is feminist; it builds on
a synthesis of regional diversity which places, for
example, the consequences of tourism in one part
of the world and desertification in another in a
context which relates them to their common
structural origins, thus linking the experience of
women at the level of their daily lives (the micro
level) to economic trends and their global
environmental impacts (the macro level); and it
is politicalit makes a critique of political systems
that ignore women's unpaid work at the level of
social and economic planning.
In relation to the environment, DAWN's ini¬
tial analysis traced the links between the food-
fuel-water crises through neglect of poor Third
World women's position as food producers,
providers and managers. Neglect of women's
work, the vital link in this chain, has been
detrimental not only to women's interests but to
the ecological systems which sustain their
livelihoods.
DAWN's current analysis focuses on the
themes of Environment, Reproductive Rights and
Population, and Alternative Economic Frame¬
works. The common conceptual framework for
the analysis will be that of livelihoods: recog¬
nizing the relationship between environmental
degradation, population pressures and economic
frameworks.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
What does the ecological crisis
mean for women in the 'South'?
The ecological crisis is the other side of the coin
of the macroeconomic model. Since the end of
World War II efforts to organize a global mode
of production have been steadily gaining ground.
This mode of production has two consequences:
on the human environment (increasing dispari¬
ties between social groups and countries); and on
the natural environment (ecological degradation).
For a poor woman the global economic and
ecological crises are experienced together, and
they are experienced most immediately at the
place where her survival is affected. A woman
whose child is starving cannot be expected to
ponder the aesthetic value of a tree. Where the
ecological destruction brought on by the model
of economic growth deprives her of land, the
source of her livelihood is destroyed.
Meanwhile, disenfranchised women in the
"South" are actually being blamed for many
environmental problems. One of the limitations
of the current debate is the failure to distinguish
between macroeconomic systems and micro-level
realities. Global phenomena such as depletion of
the ozone layer, global warming, and pollution
are overwhelmingly the result of the widespread
sale and use of Northern technologies. However,
the discussion tends to ignore macroeconomic
factors and tends, perniciously, to focus instead
on problems associated with poverty and popu¬
lation, which are more immediately observable.
Perspectives on "the environment" are
informed by people's realities. There are many.
From a "South" point of view, a tendency within
the "North" to separate the natural from the
human environments obscures some of the
common structural origins of the threat to all life.
Similarly, the line drawn between an abstract
"nature" (benign, vulnerable, endangered) and
human beings (exploitative, and viewed by some
as nature's enemy) is a dangerous line. From
where we stand, the issue can be described in
more political terms: currently, the imbalance
between man-made productive systems and
natural systems is jeopardizing the productive
base, that is, jeopardizing both the natural
environment and the productive capacity of
human beings. When you look at the environ¬
ment issue from the perspective of poor women
what you see are issues of health and livelihoods.
Take any one of the key environmental issues
and follow it through its various permutations
and it will be clear that women are linked to eco¬
nomic policy and the international economy
because of their sectoral activities and social roles.
All of this points to the need for a framework
which allows for policy shifts that will address
each of the linking factors.
Country-dwellers are flocking
to Mexico City at the rate of a
thousand a day, swelling the
population of districts like the
Borde de Vias, above.
The Wheel of Life, a Buddhist
symbol from the temple of
Likir (Ladakh).
rW/<?52
;4¡"oljjU
< y Km
^i W
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
Rebuilding Beirut
UNESCO is to help Beirut rebuild
its commercial district, assisting
with such matters as
documentation research,
archaeological research and field
surveys. It will also take part in
the rehabilitation of historic sites
and the National Museum, and in
the development of a multi¬
purpose theatre, a cultural centre
and the National Library. In
accordance with an agreement
made in October 1991, UNESCO
and the Lebanese Council for
Development and Reconstruction,
the government agency with
responsibility for rebuilding Beirut,
will together seek the funds
necessary for these operations.
New UNESCO publications
UNESCO's Young Child and the
Family Environment Project (YCF)
has published a book on early
childhood care and education
(ECCE) programmes in 88
countries. Entitled Early Childhood
Care and EducationA World
Survey, the 130-page book is
based on responses to a
questionnaire sent to all UNESCO
Member States. The survey shows
three growing trends in the
provision of ECCE:
parent/community participation,
the expanded role of day-care
centres and the role of the
extended family. The book is
available free of charge and can
be obtained by writing to
Wolfgang Schwendler, director of
YCF, at UNESCO.
Education for AIDS Prevention is
a bibliography of worldwide
documentation on information and
education for the prevention of
AIDS. Compiled using information
from a computerized data bank,
the bibliography includes indexed
references of over 1,000
documents collected by the AIDS
School Education Resource Centre
(ASERC), a centre for the
collection, analysis and
dissemination of educational
materials on AIDS prevention
which is based at UNESCO
headquarters. The 218-page
bibliography, which is published in
English, French and Spanish, is
aimed at educators, social
workers and others who are
"facing problems of didactics and
pedagogical methods with respect
to the prevention of AIDS." It is
available free of charge.
The latest (1991) edition of
UNESCO's indispensable
Statistical Yearbook contains in
table form information on
education, educational
expenditure, science and
technology, libraries, book
production, newspapers and other
periodicals, cultural paper, film
and cinema, radio and television
broadcasting, international trade
¡n printed matter. The Yearbook is
published in a trilingual (English,
French, Spanish) edition and costs
375 French francs.
Help for Bangladesh
UNESCO has approved a $50,000
grant to help cyclone-prone
Bangladesh to introduce a
disaster-preparation programme in
its primary schools. The grant has
been made in response to an
appeal for international aid
following the devastating cyclone
which hit the country in April
1991, killing more than 140,000
people and causing damage to
educational buildings, material
and equipment estimated at
almost $900 million. It will also be
used to help train technicians to
manage work on the construction
of cyclone-resistant school
buildings which can serve as
places of refuge during natural
disasters.
How Mexico's Indians saw the
conquistadors
L'Amérique de la conquête peinte
par les Indiens du Mexique, by
Serge Gruzinski, has been
published in the UNESCO
Collection of Representative
Works in collaboration with
Editions Flammarion of Paris to
mark the 500th anniversary of the
encounter between two worlds in
1492. The author, assistant
director of the Research Centre
on Mexico, Central America and
the Andes at the Ecole des
Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales-CNRS in Paris, has used
remarkable images taken from
many Indian codices to show how
the Indians of Mexico saw the
conquistadors and the upheavals
experienced by their civilization.
The images, most of which are
published for the first time, shed
light on a poignant episode in the
history of humanity and a unique
example of the interpénétration of
civilizations.
Al-Andalus
The timetable of meetings
organized by the International
Peace Research Association
(IPRA) on al-Andalus and
announced in our December
1991 issue "Al-Andalus: where
three worlds met" (page 31) has
been modified. The third
meeting will be held at UNESCO
headquarters in mid-March
1992. Other meetings will be
held at the Euro-Arab university
in Toledo (Spain) from 13 to 20
June 1992 and in Malta from 25
to 27 June 1992.
Women and museums
How are women and
womanhood presented and
interpreted in museums? What
is the status of women working
in the museum professions and
how can their career prospects
be improved? These are some
of the questions addressed in
"Focus on Women", number
171 (1991) of Museum,
UNESCO's international quarterly
on museography. The cover
shows four 15th-century French
manuscript illuminations
portraying women at work-
writing, mining, painting and
teaching.
Economics and ecology
The first international Salon-
Forum of technologies and
environment (ECOSITE), held in
Paris from 7 to 9 January 1992,
focused on the proposition that
the protection of the
environment could become a
motor of growth. The president
of ECOSITE, Daniele Rousseau,
thinks that the combination of
economics and ecology has a
bright future, and that with the
expanding, market for eco-
products and the growing
search for environmentally
sound procedures, the
protection of the environment
must now form part of the
development strategies of
successful companies. Two
recent issues of the UNESCO
Courier were presented at the
Salon: "Environment and
Development: a Global
Commitment" (November 1991)
and "The Demographic
Dimension" (January 1992).
The Benedictine Abbey and
Altenmünster of Lorsch
(Germany);
Shark Bay, Western Australia
(Australia);
The historic city of Sucre
(Bolivia);
Serra da Capivara National
Park (Brazil);
Pöblet Monastery (Spain);
Old Rauma; the fortress of
Suomenlinna (Finland);
The banks of the Seine in
Paris; Notre Dame cathedral,
the Abbey of Saint Rémi
and the Palais du Tau, Reims
(France);
Komodo National Park;
Ujung Kulon National Park;
Borobudur Temple compound;
Prambanan Temple compound
(Indonesia);
The Historic Centre of Morelia
(Mexico);
llha de Mozambique
(Mozambique);
Air-Ténéré Reserve (Niger);
Historic Centre of Lima
(Peru);
Danube Delta (Romania);
Golden Temple of Dambulla
(Sri Lanka);
Royal Domain of
Drottningholm (Sweden);
Thungyai-Huai Kha Khaeng
Wildlife Sanctuary;
Historic Town of Sukhothai and
associated historic towns;
Historic City of Ayutthaya and
associated historic towns
(Thailand).
Twenty-three new sites
included on
World Heritage List
In December 1991 the following
sites were added to the World
Heritage List:
Museums for tomorrow's
Africa
Some forty African countries
were representated at a series
of meetings on tomorrow's
African museums held in
November 1991 in Benin,
Ghana and Togo under the
auspices of the International
Council of Museums (ICOM),
an exceptional event that
aroused great interest among
museum professionals,
politicians and economic
decision-makers wishing to
develop African museology.
Several international
organizations, including
UNESCO, were associated with
the meetings, from which
four priority themes emerged:
the administrative and financial
autonomy of African museums;
closer collaboration between
existing muséographie
structures; a new direction for
training programmes; and
increased contact between
museums and society.
Museums were defined as
instruments of public
education, cultural pluralism,
national development and
democracy. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
by Jean d'Ormesson
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
44
VJleaming in the sunlight, looking out
imperiously from its rock to . the island-
studded Adriatic, enclosedby on all sides by
ramparts, Dubrovnik is perhaps the most fas-
' cinating and certainly one of the most beau¬
tiful cities in the world. If there is any place
on Earth where culture, light, a beautiful set¬
ting and all the riches of art and history are
concentrated in a small space, it is in
Dubrovnik, which has been included by
UNESCO on its World Heritage List along
with other remarkable monuments and sites
from every region and culture.
Look at a photograph, preferably one
taken from the air, or even better study a
model of the Old City of Dubrovnik. What
is immediately striking is the homogeneity,
unity and harmony of the site. Surrounded by
ramparts that have survived intact, flanked by
a tiny old port protected by bastions,
Dubrovnik appears as a tightly-woven fabric
of houses of light-coloured stone, dominated
here and there by towers, palaces, churches
and cloisters.
Art in Dubrovnik is closely linked to
nature, and both are linked to freedom.
Nature means first and" foremost the sea: the
Mediterranean, or to be more precise the Adri¬
atic. Across it lie the Italian towns of Bari,
Brindisi (where Virgil died), Ancona, and
Ravenna, with its mosaics and its churches
built by Justinian, Emperor of Constan¬
tinople, and by Theodoric, King of the
Ostrogoths. Above all there is Venice,
Dubrovnik's model and rival.
On the Dubrovnik side, the Adriatic is a
string of islands with enchanting names
Lokrum, Mljet, Korkula, Hvareach one
more verdant, more beautiful and more mys¬
terious than the next. To the south lies Mon¬
tenegro and the breathtakingly beautiful Gulf
of Kotor, formerly the Gulf of Cattaro, where
the mountains plunge sheer into the sea. For
mountains are as omnipresent here as the sea.
High hills, many of them covered in forest,
dominate the port of Dubrovnik on every
side. Nowhere has nature, under a pure-blue
sky and a generous Sun, provided art with a
more precious setting.
But it is to people and their genius that
the city owes the greater part of its grandeur
and its beauty. Art, beauty, freedom and talent
made their appearance here very early, the
result, as so often, of the shock from the
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
meeting of two cultures. Early in the seventh
century, Slav tribes took control of an ancient
colony of the Greek city of Epidaurus on the
Dalmatian coast, attached in Roman times to
the province of Illyricum. The colony's
Greco-Roman inhabitants sought shelter a
little further to the north, on a small island
called Ragusium or Ragusa. On the mainland
opposite, a Slav tribe settled in the midst of
oak grovesDuhrava.
Centuries later, the narrow arm of the sea
separating the Greek and Latin city from the
Slav settlement was filled in, and over-it was
built the fine straight boulevard known as the
Placa, or Stradun, which you can make out
on any photograph of Dubrovnik to this day,
crossing the town from one side to the other
and bordered by churches and palaces. The
destinies of Ragusa and Dubrovnik had
become one.
The pupil and rival of Venice
The Placa is the centre of a city that was devoted
for centuries to maritime trade and to art, and
has managed despite the cold winds of history
to preserve both its unique character and its
independence. Established on the border
between the former Western and Eastern
Empires, Dubrovnik gradually filled with
palaces and monuments which seem to follow
a rigorously ordered plan. Venice, which took
over suzerainty of Dubrovnik from Constan¬
tinople in 1204, was to exercise a considerable
influence on it. In fact Dubrovnik, long con¬
sidered the "Athens of the Southern Slavs"
for its humanists, philosophers, poets,
mathematicians and artists, was both a bold
and brilliant pupil of Venice and also its rival.
The Clock Tower rises at the other end
of the Placa. It forms the centrepiece of the
square that groups Dubrovnik's masterpieces,
foremost among them the Sponza Palace,
whose façade is decorated with a gallery sup¬
ported by pillars forming half a dozen
supremely elegant arches. The baroque
Church of St. Blaise faces the palace. In front
of it stands the column of Roland, erected in
1418legend has it that the nephew of
Charlemagne landed at Ragusa with a
Frankish fleet despatched by the emperor to
fight the Saracens.
Perhaps the most beautiful of all
Dubrovnik's monuments is the Rector's
Palace, just a stone's throw away. First built
in the twelfth century, then damaged by a vio¬
lent earthquake that destroyed much of the
town, it was rebuilt as a dwelling for the city's
Rector. A new office-holder was elected to the
Opposite page, the old city of Dubrovnik,
which was struck by shellfire
on 6 December 1991 (above).
post each month. The incumbent was not
allowed to leave the building in the course of
his term of duty. Hence the Latin inscription
on its façade: Obliti privatorum publica curate
("Forget your private affairs and look after the
public good").
Situated on the edge of the Ottoman
Empire, just as Venice, until the start of the
thirteenth century, had been located on that
of the Byzantine Empire, Dubrovnik accumu¬
lated masterpieces as the centuries passed by:
rare and precious objects, rich fabrics, vases,
sculptures, paintings by Titian and Raphael,
Tintoretto and Tiepolo. Technical and social
progress combined with the cult of art and tra¬
dition. As early as 1347, Ragusa had a hospice
for old people. Torture was abolished in 1416.
So was the slave trade (which has left an echo
in Venice in the Riva degli Schiavoni, which
runs along the lagoon from the Piazzetta to
the environs of the Arsenal). Public'education
attained a high level early on.
In the midst of the triumph of humanism
and the cult of progress, tradition remained
strong. In the Church of the Franciscans, there 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
is a fifteenth-century painting of St. Blaise,
patron saint of the city. In his hand he holds
a model of Dubrovnik. And in spite of the
centuries that have passed, the wars, the fires
and the earthquakes, the city still looks very
much today as it did then, half a millennium
ago.
Fear stalks the streets
Yet Dubrovnik has undergone many trials, few
of them crueller than that it endures today.
The town has been under siege for 'several
months. Water is in short supply. Provisions
only arrive in small quantities via the new
port, some kilometres away from the Old
City. Shells have fallen throughout the city,
starting fires in the outer suburbs and causing
damage in the Old City. Fear stalks the streets
of Venice's rival.
Many other peoples throughout the
world, who cannot boast Dalmatia's history
or art treasures, doubtless suffer as much or
worse. And the life of men, women and chil¬
dren is as precious in one place as in another.
Yet history has endowed Dubrovnik with a
special status. It is a small piece of the past that
has survived into the present, a fragment of
beauty that lightens the world. And people
need beauty just as they need bread and love.
Throughout its brilliant history, among all the
ups and downs of fortune, Ragusa has not only
Built over the channel
that once separated
the Greco-Roman
island of Ragusium
from the Slav coastal
settlement of Dubrava,
the street known as
the Placa cuts through
the heart of
Dubrovnik's old city.
The bell-tower of the
Franciscan Church
rises in the
background.
embodied the highest artistic values, but has
also defended its independence, served the
cause of humanity and, within the limits of
its physical and spiritual resources, been in the
vanguard of progress and human rights.
UNESCO's task is very difficult in the
trials being experienced by Dubrovnik today.
It is impossible for an international organiza¬
tion in which Yugoslavia has long played an
important role to take sides in a fratricidal war.
But for all those who believe in the fun¬
damental principles of UNESCO, it is equally
unthinkable to remain inactive or indifferent
to the risk of seeing a cultural treasure des¬
troyed. All people of goodwill must mobilize
to save Dubrovnik. More, they must work to
bring the war to an end and to help reconcile
adversaries who may be separated by their pas¬
sions but whom history and geography con¬
strain to live together.
JEAN D'ORMESSON, French writer, is Secretary
General of the International Council for
Philosophy and Humanistic Studies and Editor of
Diogenes, an international review of the human
sciences published with the aid of UNESCO. A
member of the French Academy since 1973, he is
the author of many essays and novels, a number of
which have been published in English, including
The Glory of the Empire (New York, 1974) and At
God's Pleasure (New York, 1977). He visited
Dubrovnik while it was under siege in December
1991 on board the Ranee, a French vessel engaged
on a humanitarian mission.
UNESCO AND
THE DUBROVNIK
EMERGENCY
In addition to the Old City of Dubrovnik. eight
other sites in Yugoslavia are included on
UNESCO's World Heritage List: Stari Ras and the
monastery of Sopocani; the historic centre of
Split, with the Palace of Diocletian; Plitvice Lakes
National Park; the regions of Ohrid and Kotor;
Durmitor National Park; Studenica monastery;
and the Skocjan caves. These sites are covered
by two international conventions, both ratified
by Yugoslavia: the Convention for the Protection
of Cultural Property in the Event of Armed Con¬
flict (1954), and the Convention concerning the
Protection of the World Cultural and Natural
Heritage (1972).
Since September 1991, Mr. Federico Mayor,
the Director-General of UNESCO, has made
repeated and urgent appeals for the protection
of Dubrovnik's historic Old City and of other
World Heritage sites threatened by the fighting
in Croatia. On 28 October, in response to the
mounting danger, he sent a personal represen¬
tative to Dubrovnik to remind the authorities con¬
cerned of their obligations under the two Con¬
ventions. He made a number of appeals for the
parties involved to begin negotiations for a
peaceful resolution of their differences.
UNESCO's General Conference, meeting in Paris,
called for the withdrawal of hostile forces from
Dubrovnik, "whose splendour belongs to all
humanity".
On 28 November, two UNESCO observers
arrived in Dubrovnik, with instructions to record
the damage done to the Old City and to keep the
Director-General informed of the situation on a
daily basis. Up to that time, the Old City had been
largely spared by the fighting, but on 6
December the historic centre was severely
damaged by heavy artillery fire.
The UNESCO observers examined the
damage on site then, from their shelter, reported
by telephone on the extent of the damage: some
buildings were seriously damaged, others were
on fire. Among the buildings affected were the
Pile gate, the Dominican monastery, the Church
of St. Blaise, the Sponza Palace, the Serbian
church and the Rupe Museum. The Director-
General expressed his "consternation and
outrage", and solemnly demanded in the name
of international law that all hostile action against
the city should cease at a time when "the flags
of the United Nations are flying over [its] historic
quarters."
In December 1991, the World Heritage Com¬
mittee representing 123 States Parties to the
World Heritage Convention, including Yugoslavia,
felt compelled, "considering the emergency sit¬
uation of the Old City of Dubrovnik ... to inscribe
it on the List of World Heritage in Danger in order
to encourage special measures to be taken for
its preservation."
A new observer mission was sent to the city
on 17 January 1992 to draw up an inventory of
the damage and to gather the information
needed to draw up a plan for its restoration.
UNESCO is proposing to create a fund for the
safeguard of Dubrovnik, with $200,000 being
allocated for the most urgent tasks. It is also
planning to launch an international fund-raising
campaign for the restoration of cultural monu¬
ments damaged by the war in Yugoslavia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
JUST PUBLISHED
Lotfallah Soliman on a new
critique of UNESCO
L'UNESCO:
'Une entreprise
erronée'?
by Chikh Bekri
Editions Publisud, Paris 1991
Space Flight (above) is a sculpture symbolizing
the scientific and cultural achievements that
have made possible the exploration of the
cosmos. Presented to UNESCO by the USSR, it
spent 16 weeks in space on board the Soyuz
7 spacecraft in 1982.
c;hikh Bekri's book L'UNESCO: "Une
entreprise erronée?*' is a heartfelt statement
from a man who was a senior international
civil servant for twenty-five years and between
1976 and 1987 occupied the posts of Assistant
Director-General of UNESCO and head of its
Director-General's Executive Office. Its pur¬
pose is to try to halt "the kind of creeping state
intervention which will end by robbing the
institution of its special identity".
Even for those who do not share Bekri's
idealism, the book is essential reading. It is the
work of a thoughtful and well informed
author who at no point in its 300 pages allows
himself to be carried away by the passion
within him. He scrupulously charts the his¬
tory of UNESCO, not in order to describe
how it works or to make a list of what it has
and has not done but to reveal the malforma¬
tion, which he regards as "congenital", that
has led it from "brilliance" to "inertia" and
may eventually cause it to disappear or dis¬
integrate into a group of "small, specialized,
purely technical institutions, tightly controlled
by those who hold the purse-strings".
The title of the book is borrowed from
the Italian philosopher Benedetto Croce,
though Bekri has carefully added a question-
mark. This is a way of suggesting that
UNESCO could conceivably not be "a mis¬
taken enterprise" after all. But in what circum¬
stances might this be so? To answer this
question, the author first draws a genetic
map of UNESCO with the aim of identifying
its constituent parts and discovering the fun¬
damental reasons for its functioning and mal¬
functioning.
UNESCO, in his view, is an international
organization with a difference. It is essentially
an "ethical" or "moral" enterprise that must
be served by "missionaries". Like the Jesuits
who do nothing that is not "for the greater
glory of God", UNESCO's staff must devote
themselves totally to "the greater glory of the
League of Intellects" (here he takes up an
expression of Paul Valéry, who said in 1930
that "the League of Nations presupposes a
League of Intellects").
Starting his enquiry from these Kantian
perspectives, Bekri notes that politics have
been an ever-present factor in UNESCO's
history, not to mention its prehistory:
"politics were written into the Organization's
genes". The very affirmation of a desire to
"contribute to peace and security by
promoting collaboration among the nations
through education, science and culture" is in
itself a political act. To challenge such an
objective is also political.
The divergences that appeared at the time
of the conference held in November 1945 to
establish UNESCO were not between politi¬
cians and others, but between "those who
wished for the creation of an organism of tech¬
nical intellectual co-operation in which emi¬
nent scholars and great thinkers of incon¬
testable moral and spiritual authority would
predominate (as they had at the time of the
League of Nations in the International Com¬
mission for Intellectual Co-operation) and
those who wanted an intergovernmental
organization that would be political in its
nature, ethical in its objectives and technical
in its fields of action, in which decisions would 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
be taken exclusively by those who have the
power, the responsibility and the means to
carry them out".
So there never was any question of
creating a kind of gigantic non-governmental
organization. In UNESCO the political
powers-that-be controlled from the outset not
merely the material but also the legal means
of international co-operation. UNESCO's
great achievements in Italy, Egypt or
Indonesia would, for example, certainly have
been impossible without the authorization,
not to mention the participation, of the
governments concerned.
Chikh Bekri has too much experience of
international co-operation to be put out of his
stride by this. However, a reading of his book
makes it possible to see where his own prefer¬
ences lie. If governments must be involved, it
is in order to provide the "missionaries" with
the means to carry out their programmes, not
to make them subject to their political
interests.
For Chikh Bekri, UNESCO's founders
put the fat in the fire when they failed to
clarify "the ambiguous relationship between
political power and the intellectual commu¬
nity". That, in his view, is UNESCO's
"original sin". From that point onwards,
political interference steadily increased at the
cost of the "League of Intellects". This has not
been without "disastrous consequences", since
such interference not only threatens to end up
by failing to manage UNESCO but by itself
becoming unmanageable.
The author's attitude to UNESCO is at
once understanding and critical. He recognizes
that UNESCO cannot be the "League of
Intellects" that he would like to see, yet it is
in the name of such a League that he makes
his principal criticisms of it. He develops his
argument from an uncomfortable position,
both "inside" and "outside". He looks for
inspiration to the tripolar model of the Inter¬
national Labour Organisation, which, he feels,
rests on a viable compromise. "A greater role
(in national delegations and the executive
board) for intellectuals organized as such
through their associations and unions . . .
would reduce the influence of the politicians
and would allow educators, scientists and men
of culture to make their voices heard".
This proposal raises a problem. It would
be attractive if it were possible to define pre¬
cisely what the term "intellectual" means, but
this reviewer for one is obliged to confess that
he has long since given up trying to do that.
iO There is no such thing as a professional
intellectual. Teachers, engineers, doctors, jour¬
nalists, even writers, are none of them neces¬
sarily intellectuals. Look in the encyclopaedias
and you will find no-one listed there as an
"intellectual"not Diderot, not Hegel, not
Marx, not Sartre, not Bertrand Russell. Edgar
Morin is referred to as an anthropologist and
sociologist. He becomes an "intellectual"
when, as an offshoot from his academic work,
he makes a stand on a given issue and takes
risks.
The intellectual, then, is a phenomenon
that has no existence as such but can only exist
conjuncturally. Outside a given situation in
which they become involved, ask questions
and explode myths, intellectuals are jour¬
nalists, writers, engineers, doctors, physicists,
lawyers, civil servants or whatever.
So there can be no association of intellec¬
tuals "as such". Any association of this kind
is instrumentralized right from the word go.
And when pseudo-intellectuals gather in such
pseudo-associations, it is usually for reasons
that have nothing to do with the life of the
intellect.
Nowhere, either in the initial proposal
made to the Conference of Allied Ministers
of Education, in the French project, or in the
final documents that were approved by the
Conference at which UNESCO was estab¬
lished (all published by the author as appen¬
dices to the main text), does the word
"intellectual" appear as a noun. The expres¬
sion "intellectual co-operation" only appears
(and there with great frequency) in the French
project, and seems to have been used (albeit
sparingly) in the final document simply to
satisfy the French delegation.
Chikh Bekri is aware of this, and at one
point uses the expression "intellectual
workers" instead of "intellectuals". But then
the whole concept of the "League of
Intellects" is cast into doubt, for the civil
service (to cite only one example) is full of
"intellectual workers", so called only to dis¬
tinguish them from "manual workers"a dis¬
tinction which, moreover, is becoming
increasingly vague.
The idea of a "League of Intellects" is an
honourable one. Chikh Bekri wants to remind
us that the species is not extinct. He should
be heeded as a wise man for whom ethics,
morality and devotion to a just cause are ines¬
timable values.
LOTFALLAH SOLIMAN, Egyptian writer, and
journalist, is the author of a history of Palestine,
Pour une histoire profane de la Palestine (La
Découverte publishers, Paris, 19S9).
The musk
On the stage of an open-air
theatre in Rangoon, a
gorgeously-costumed woman
performs an introductory Nat
dance in front of the drums
and gongs of an orchestral
ensemble, the hsaing-waing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
R E F L E C T I O IM S
of Myanmar by Khin Mya Kyu
1he music of Burmanow officially
known as the Union of Myanmaris close in
spirit to those of the Southeast Asian civiliza¬
tions of Thailand, Laos and Cambodia. The
Indian influence is less perceptible here than
in the nation's mythology and religious beliefs,
or than in such other arts as the shadow-
theatre and dance-drama.
The most complete Burmese instrumental
ensemble is the hsaing-waing, which consists
basically of a set of from eight to twenty-one
drums suspended by leather thongs on a cir¬
cular rattan frame, and of a circular array of
gongs. In addition there may be anything from
seven to twelve other instruments, among
them oboes, bamboo clap-sticks, hand-
cymbals, flutes and mouth organs, bells, xylo
phones and zithers. As in all the countries of
the region, however, drums and gongs
predominate. In traditional orchestras, they
come in many shapes and forms: double-
headed drums struck with wooden sticks,
double-headed horizontal drums played by
hand, single-headed pottery drums. The gongs
may be flat or bulbous, suspended or sup¬
ported on wooden frames. Most of these
instruments, including the drums, produce an
unvarying sound. For that reason, they nor¬
mally come in pairs, one for sharp tones and
the other for flat.
Burmese musical practice, in which the
notes are identified in descending order,
resembles that of other Southeast Asian coun¬
tries: the octave is divided, theoretically, into
seven equal intervals. Whatever mode is used
to play a melody, the structure of the scale
remains the same.
Improvization plays an important part in
traditional Burmese music. Whereas in most
parts of the world the instruments of the
orchestra are meant to be played in unison,
in the traditional Burmese orchestra,
instrumentalists start from a common melody
but are free to play whatever variations they
like, provided they join up with the ensemble
from time to time. Sometimes the results
could be called "heterophonic", but they do
not lack harmony for all that.
In Myanmar, as in the rest of Asia, music
is closely linked to the performing arts,
notably plays, puppet-shows, shadow theatre,
dance-drama and opera. In drama, the Indian
influence is preponderant. All the characters,
whether heroes or gods, originate in the
Ramayana or Mahabharata epics, or in the
Jataka, narratives relating episodes from the
Buddha's previous incarnations. Performances,
which often take place in the open air, may
last for several hours, sometimes even for days.
Ancient instruments,
modern rhythms
Burmese music has not escaped the contagion
of Western pop, which is widely broadcast by
the media. Some musicians have tried to create
a synthesis by adapting Burmese lyrics to
Western rhythms or by performing translated
French and English songs to a Burmese
backing. This so-called "new music" is a
hybrid genre whose artistic value is at best
uncertain. But it is popular with the young,
and the influence of radio, television and
cinema will eventually establish its grip.
Yet Myanmar remains the land of 100,000
pagodas, for each village has at least one
monastery and a pagoda. The chimes of bells
and metal gongs, carried on the wind, are
relayed from community to community in an
uninterrupted chain. This music at least will
long remain an irreplaceable feature of the
Burmese landscape.
KHIN MYA KYU, formerly head of the French
Department at the Institute of Foreign Languages
in Rangoon, is currently a staff member in
UNESCO's Office of Public Information. She has
published several works on the art and culture of
her country, including Shingyan ou Fêtes de Vean en
Birmanie (1990), and has collaborated on a French-
Burmese dictionary that currently runs to 14
volumes. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
nPOSTS VACANT
AT UNESCO
Title: Reference archivist
Post No.: DIT-048
Professional category (P-3)
Bureau of Documentation, Informatics
and Telecommunication
Information, Library and Archives Division
Archives and Micrography Section
Duties and responsibilities
Be responsible for the reference
service concerning UNESCO's history and
activities;
Index by computer resolutions and
related documents of the General Con¬
ference (ICONFEX data base);
Arrange records and describe them in
inventories, guides and other finding aids;
Appraise records with a view to their
disposal;
Study new and progressive methods
and techniques of archival services.
Qualifications and experience required:
University degree or equivalent attain¬
ment (degree in history an asset).
Diploma in the field of archives.
Extensive general education and wide
cultural background.
Experience in the organization and
administration of historical or administra¬
tive archives at national and/or interna¬
tional level with growing responsibilities
(5 years minimum).
Knowledge of microcomputer/office
automation is fridispensable.
Languages required: English, French
Duration of appointment: Two years,
renewable, starting as soon as possible.
Closing date: Applications should reach
the Chief of the Human Resources
Development Division, Bureau of Per¬
sonnel, UNESCO, 7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France, not later than 9 April
1992.
Please quote: DIT-048.
Title: Chief of Section
Post No.: ED-343
Professional category (P-5)
Technical and Vocational Education
Section,
Division for the Development of Edu¬
cation,
Education Sector
Duties and responsibilities
Under the general supervision of the
Director of the Division, the incumbent
will, in particular:
co-ordinate the planning and execution
of the regular programme activities and
extra-budgetary projects in technical and
vocational education;
promote the application of the Revised
Recommendation concerning Technical
and Vocational Education;
assist Member States, at their request,
in the design of national programmes for
the development of technical andvoca-
tional education;
provide technical and administrative
support to operational projects in the
field of technical and vocational edu¬
cation.
Qualifications and experience required:
Advanced university degree and inter¬
nationally recognized qualifications in the
field of technical and vocational edu¬
cation.
Experience of technical and vocational
education, the development of policies
and programmes and/or ¡n teaching.
Familiarity with special conditions and
problems of technical and vocational
education in the developing countries.
Languages required: English, French.
Closing date: Applications should reach
the Chief of Human Resources Develop¬
ment Division, Bureau of Personnel,
UNESCO, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, France, not later than 9 April 1992.
Please quote: ED-343
50
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
When the cup overflows
If Gabriel Garcia Marquez (in the
interview published in your October
1991 issue entitled "Children ¡n
danger") considers that he is the
result of a European "overflow",
that is his business. But it seems
to me not only unjust but
historically inaccurate to extend that
remark to all of Latin America.
Does he not know that Europe,
and more especially Spain, sent
over gentlemen (if that title means
anything to him) who were gallant,
enterprising, hard-working and
honest in every respect? And let's
not forget that we Latin Americans
also trace our lineage, in varying
degrees, to the indigenous peoples,
who were subjugated to a greater
or lesser extent, and to the
infamously-treated Africans.
What's more, Garcia Marquez
goes on to declare that Europe has
lost sight of the vicissitudes of its
own history (and dare one add that
Europe itself was born of an
"overflow" of the Roman Empire or
of the barbarian invaders of the
fifth century?), that Tenochtitlán in
the fifteenth century was larger
than Paris, and that the African
influence is particularly marked in
some Latin-American countries. . . .
So what does this European
"overflow" in Latin America really
amount to?
Gustavo Restrepo Uribe
Quito (Ecuador)
Al-Andalus in 13th-century
Marseilles
Pottery, often considered a minor
art, has recently afforded us
archaeologists with a remarkable
illustration of the cultural exchanges
between Andalusian Spain and
Provence. Convincing evidence of a
transfer of technology to Marseilles
early in the thirteenth century has
been provided by the discovery of
a pottery workshop unearthed
during a rescue excavation
undertaken in co-operation with the
city's Cultural Heritage Workshop.
Building work in the Sainte Barbe
district revealed the presence of a
medieval suburb outside the city's
ancient walls occupied by potters
who shared the same cultural
background and specialized in
enamelwork and glazing using the
lead ore known as alquifou. Large
deposits of pottery were found
around their kilns (one of which
employed Arab technology), and the
variety of the work left little doubt
of the potters' links with the Muslim
world.
The opulence of the candle-
holders, plates, dishes, cups, vases
of the types known as ataifor,
redoma and limeta, and alcadafe
basins found there has no
equivalent in contemporary
Provençal work, which shows no
sign of techniques that had been
used since the tenth century in
Murcia, Granada, Malaga and in the
Sicily-North Africa region. Stills,
filtration-vessels, jugs with spouts in
the form of animals, painted cups
and paving-tiles indicate the
versatility of the workshop, the
oldest pottery yet discovered north
of the Pyrenees. Its work was
continued in the fourteenth century
in the Avignon region, when the
papal court moved there.
Archaeology has thus revealed an
unexpected staging-post in the
transmission of a form of
specialized technical knowledge
which influenced later ceramic
production.
H. Marchesi, J. Thiriot, L. Vallauri
Laboratory of Medieval
Mediterranean Archaeology,
ERA 6-CNRS,
Aix-en-Provence (France)
Environmentalists
in the firing-line
It is a pity that so much ecological
nonsense found its way into your
November 1991 issue on
Environment and Development.
Jacques-Yves Cousteau uses
inaccurate statistics and makes wild
statements, for example (and this is
my favourite) that "we shall all end
up panting to death if amounts of
carbon dioxide continue to
increase". In fact, if carbon dioxide
poses a problem at all, it is
certainly not a respiratory one. And,
incidentally, two Danish
meteorologists have recently shown
that there is a close correlation
between average air temperature in
the northern hemisphere and the
duration of sun-spot cycles, which
suggests that the greenhouse
effect may be far less significant
than had previously been thought.
It was amusing to see
WorldWatch Institute's
representativesLester Brown,
Christopher Flavin and Sandra
Postelmaking the case for solar
energy as a panacea for all ills at
the very time that a major
constructor of solar-energy
equipment was going bankrupt.
Bernard Gilland
Espergaerde (Denmark)
Utopias and socialism
Reading your February 1991 issue
on utopias, I was struck by the
similarities between ancient utopias
and present-day socialism.
Nevertheless, I do not share the
view of Plato's work expressed by
Gilles Lapouge in his excelled
article "The Fiasco of Paradise".
The Greek philosopher formulated
two paradoxical ideas of the ideal
state. If he denied the family in The
Republic, he made a civic duty of it
in The Laws.
G. Konovalova
Yekaterinburg (Russia)
Sardinian maps
I read your issue on maps and
map-makers (June 1991) with great
interest, particularly the articles
concerning the production of the
first maps in France. In this
connection, I should like to point
out that Savoy's first cadastral map
was produced in 1730 in Piedmont
on the initiative of Victor Amadeus
II. (Savoy was not then part of
France.) Called "Sardinian maps"
from the joint kingdom of Sardinia
and Piedmont of which Victor-
Amadeus was the first ruler, the
plans were still being consulted in
the Savoyard town of Ugine in
1945. They are beautifully executed
in colour, with contours, trees
and marshland all depicted
according to a precise system of
codification.
G. Dalas
Chambéry (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco
-^courier
45th YEAR
Published monthly in 36 languages and in braille
by UNESCO, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31. rue Frarçois Bonvin, 75015 Paris. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkm
French edition: A am Lëvèque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Studies and research: Fernando Ainsa
Art UnhVProduction: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey, (Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel: 45.68.47.15),
Mouna Chatta
Administrative assistant: Prtthi Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Mane-Domimque Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morrón (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wall Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonarc J. Shuma ¡Dar-es-Saiaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofer (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: SJ. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Manatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Manni Kössler (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Dhuorg (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khawe'i (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassar (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelrrakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández
(Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Assistant: Marie-Noëlle Branet (45.68.45.89).
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, A'pha Diakité, Jacqueline Louise-
Julle, Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard. Mohamed Salah El Din,
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk, Ricardo Zamora-Perez
Customer service: G nette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: (45.68.45 65),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel. 45.68.45.65
- year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 132 Frenen francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
a articles and ohotographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
g the credit line reads "Repr nted from the UNESCO Courier",
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sen: to the editor
S'gned articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-cooyright
m i be sjppüed on request. Unsolicited manuscipts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an r terna t onal r«n y coupon
tg postage. Signed articles express tie opinions cf the authors
ot necessarily represent the opm ons o* UNESCO or :hose
I tors of the UNESCO Courier. Photo captions 3nd headlines
ore wntten by trie UNESCO Courier staff The boundaries or maps
».ib1 m en in tne magazine go not imply official endorsement or
:e by UNESCO or the United Nations. The UNESCO Courier
i produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) UNESCO.
I i.i: ie Fontenoy. ?5700 3aris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox).
- Michigan 48100. U.S. A :(3)N.CR. Mice-card Edition. Indian
1 1 1 West 40th Street. New York, u.S A .: [4] Ben and Howeü
.Oc Mansfield Road, vvooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
IMP» MÉ EN TRANCE
..ted n France) C^OT LEGAL CI MARS 1992.
II ' SSION PARITAIRE NO 71844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP.
Photocompos'ton: Tne UNESCO Courier-
Photogravure- impression: Maury Imprimeur SA..
Z.I. 'oute d'Etamoes. 45330 Maiesherbes
Theme
of the next issue
(April mi):
ART
IN THE STREET
Also featuring:
an interview with American writer
William Styron
ISSN 0041-5278 NO 3- 19920PI-92-3-502 A
Acknowledgements
Cover, pages 3 (right), 24-25: © Claude Sauvageot, Paris. Back cover: © Charles Lenars, Paris.
Page 2: © V. Balu, Bangalore. Pages 4 (above), 5 (above): UNESCO/Michel Claude. Page 4
(below): UNESCO/R.A. Zampclla. Page 7: UNESCO/Jean-Claude Bernath. Pages 8, 9, 37: All
Rights Reserved. Pages 11, 15: © Lam Kim, Paris. Page 13: United Nations/John Isaac.
Pages 14, 19, 23, 26, 28, 32, 34, 36, 38, 42: Roland Michaud g Rapho, Paris. Pages 16-17, 17
(below), 38, 42 (above): ©Mark Edwards/Stills Pictures, London. Page 16 (below): united
Nations/Irena Dankelman. Page 18: ©Patrick Pounaud, Paris. Page 19: ©International Museum
of Children's Art, Oslo. Page 20-21: David Turnley ©Rapho, Paris. Page 22: Paolo Koch
©Rapho, Paris. Page 26 (below): ©Jörgen Schytte, Copenhagen. Pages 28, 29, 30 (above):
UNESCO/Y.E. Nakpata. Page 32, 33: The Seikatsu Club, Tokyo. Pages 34, 35: © Cefemina.
Page 36: UNDP/Michael Lutzky. Page 39: Barxi ©Sipa, Paris. Pages 40-41, 40 (below), 41
(below): Mike Theiler ©Sipa, Paris. Pages 40-41, 40 (below), 41 (below): Mike Theiler ©Sipa,
Paris. Pages 44, 46: Fabian © Sygma, Paris. Page 45: J. Jones © Sygma, Paris. Page 48-49: Carl
Mydans © Rapho, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
*à
v
'\
íüf
]]>
</page>
</document>
