<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="090835eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheUnesco «>
iïïïïï
JANUARY 1992
^
a*
y
I?--^
M 1205-9201-22 00 F
M I III III II I
I £3^
i \
1H-
Xf<^>>
4
;
i *
éè
1
liül ^TU^T*. ^^^^%^AÍ 11
lAul
\ .
>.
..<£".- fer'»-'
lvfl&, " .j .-'
kssrp
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
encounters We invite readers to send us photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature. Your photo should show
a painting, a sculpture, piece of architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an example of cross-fertilization
between cultures. Alternatively, you could send us pictures
of two works from different cultural backgrounds in which
you see some striking connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all photographs.
On the Silk Road
1990, acrylic on wood and gold leaf
triptych (74 x 80 cm)
by Luis López Casado, alias Monseñor
Painted in a style that harks back to the
European Middle Ages and Greco-Roman
Antiquity, this triptych by the Spanish painter
Monseñor conceals hidden treasure beneath its
wings: a seductive portrait of an Oriental woman,
limned with almost hieratic solemnity.
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 1992 CON NTS
8
Interview with
CARLOS FUENTES
Courrier
~de i UNESCO
le
45th YEAR
Published monthly in 36 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States
parties to this Constitution on behalf
of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds
of men, it is in the minds of men
that the defences of peace must be
constructed...
"that a peace based exclusively
upon the political and economic
arrangements of governments
would not be a peace which could
secure the unanimous, lasting and
sincere support of the peoples of
the world, and that the peace must
therefore be founded, if it is not to
fail, upon the intellectual and moral
solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States
parties ... are agreed and
determined to develop and to
increase the means of
communication between their
peoples and to employ these means
for the purposes of mutual
understanding and a truer
and more perfect knowledge of
each other's lives..."
Extract from the Preamble to the
Constitution of UNESCO.
London, 16 November 1945
THE DEMOGRAPHIC DIMENSION
by Raúl Urzúa
THE DEMOGRAPHIC TRANSITION
by Jacques Véron 17
POVERTY, POPULATION, POLLUTION
by Nafis Sadik 18
THE ENVIRONMENTAL CHALLENGE
by Ronald Lee 22
THE NUMBERS CRUNCH
by Harold Brookficld 25
SIXTY MILLION ON THE MOVE
by Alan B. Simmons 30
THE URBAN EXPLOSION
by Mehdi Amani 34
MIGRANT AFRICA
by Aderanti Adepoju 37
4
UNESCO'S FIRST
45 YEARS
(Part IV)
by Michel Conil Lacoste
12
IN BRIEF..
13
APPRECIATION
Hampâté Bâ,
the great conciliator
by Diélika Diallo
45
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWS
46
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
Petra: the rose-red capital
of a forgotten people
by Jacëk Rewerski
49
LISTENING
Recent records
by Claude Glayman
and Isabelle Leymarie
50
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
Cover:
A mixed-media work by
the French artist Gaiizère.
Back cover:
Ink on watercolour paper
by the Egyptian artist
Faouzia Niazi-Lane.
THE GREYING OF THE PLANET
by Jean-Claude Chasteland 40
The Editors wish
to thank Messrs. Raúl
Urzúa and Mehdi
Amani for their help
in the preparation of
this issue.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S m$l 45 MRS (Part ll/j
by Michel Con/7 Lacoste
Education
The rescue of Abu Simbel
m
General policy
At its 15th session, the General Conference
takes the first step towards medium-term plan¬
ning with the decision to draw up the broad out¬
line of a plan for 1971-1976.
René Maheu is reelected for a new six-year
mandate.
UNESCO has 125 Member States.
4 new literacy pilot projects are inaugurated
(Ethiopia, Guinea, Madagascar, Tanzania); 3
others will follow: in Venezuela (1968), Sudan
(1969) and Zambia (1971).
The World Crisis in Education, by Philip
Coombs, is published.
The Youth Division is created within the Edu¬
cation Sector (it is currently part of the Sector
of Social and Human Sciences).
Exact and natural sciences
A Conference on the Scientific Basis for
Rational Use and Conservation of the Biosphere
is held in Paris. This meeting, the first inter¬
governmental conference on the environment,
leads to UNESCO's programme on Man and the
Biosphere (MAB).
Social sciences
First edition of Birthright ofMan, a selection
of texts on human rights prepared under the
direction of Jeanne Hersch.
Culture
Meeting in Italy, the Executive Board exa¬
mines a UNESCO report on the problems of
Venice. The report was later published in Italy
(Mondadori/UNESCO) and in France ( Sauver
Venise, Robert Laffont/UNESCO).
The Abu Simbel temples, reconstructed 64
metres above their original site on the banks of
the Nile, are officially unveiled.
Events
A symposium on "The role of Karl Marx in
the development of contemporary scientific
thought" is held to mark the 150th anniversary
of Marx's birth.
Left, moving the cliff temples of Abu Simbel was
one of the most spectacular achievements of the
International campaign to save the monuments of
Nubia, launched In 1960.
Below, a scientist working on a MAB project In
French Guiana studies the canopy of the rain
forest, an ecosystem rich In animal and plant
life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
1W
Education
The International Bureau of Education in
Geneva (IBE) becomes part of UNESCO. Estab¬
lished in 1925, the IBE became an intergovern¬
mental organization in 1929. It was for many
years headed by Jean Piaget (Switzerland).
The USSR establishes the Nadezhda K.
Krupskaya prize to help promote UNESCO's
campaign against illiteracy. Four other interna¬
tional prizes to encourage literacy work are
currently awarded: the International Reading
Association Literacy Award, the Noma Literacy
Prize, the Iraq Literacy Prize, and the King
Sejong Prize.
Exact and natural sciences
UNESCO organizes an international sympo¬
sium on the origins of modern man.
Communication
A meeting of experts held in Montreal out¬
lines a plan for long-term research on technical
progress in the communications media and the
impact of the mass media on contemporary
society.
Events
A symposium is held on "Truth and non¬
violence in Gandhi's humanism".
The UNESCO Prize for Architecture,
awarded for the first time, goes to the Japanese
architect Mitsuo Morozumi. The prize, awarded
every three years at the assembly of the Interna¬
tional Union of Architects (IUA), rewards the
authors of works of architecture inspired by the
moral aims of UNESCO.
m
General policy
A new building in rue Miollis is inaugurated
at UNESCO Headquarters in the presence of the
Head of State of the host country, M. Georges
Pompidou.
The Director-General decides to create a
Secretariat Round Table to study improvements
in programmes, management and human rela¬
tions within the Secretariat.
An experimental project to promote equal
access of girls and women to education is
launched in the Gandaki region of Nepal, with
financial assistance from NORAD (the Nor¬
wegian Agency for International Development).
Exact and natural sciences
At a Conference of Ministers responsible for
science policy in European Member States
(MINESPOL), held at UNESCO Headquarters,
170 Ministers and delegates from 30 countries
discuss the relative importance to be attached to
applied and fundamental research.
A Climatic Atlas ofEurope is published jointly
with the World Meteorological Organization
(WMO). This is the first of a series of climatic
atlases covering the different continents.
A Vegetation Map ofthe Mediterranean Region
is published.
Social sciences
The first part of a comprehensive study on
Main trends of research in the social and human
sciences is published. It covers sociology, polit¬
ical science, psychology, economics, demography
and linguistics. The second part (1978) covers
anthropology, history, aesthetics and art, law and
philosophy. Authors include: Jean Piaget, Stein
Rokkan, Paul Ricceur, Mikel Dufrenne, Maurice
Freedman, Geoffrey Barraclough.
Culture
The first volume of the General History of Africa
appeared In 1981. Since then 5 more volumes
have been published In English.
HISTORIA
GENERAL
DE
AFRICA
\I,.|,«W'«I'" l I
OF AFWÇA
àfrifanPldUSttffV.
An intergovernmental conference is held in
Venice to examine the institutional, administrative
and financial aspects of cultural policies. The con¬
ference, which marks the emergence in the late
1960s of the notions of "cultural development"
and the "cultural dimension of development",
leads to a series of regional intergovernmental
conferences: Eurocult (Helsinki, 1972); Asiacult
(Yogyakarta, 1973); Africacult (Accra, 1975);
Americacult (Bogota, 1978), Conference of Arab
Ministers of Culture-Alecso (Baghdad, 1981).
The Convention on the Means of Prohibiting
and Preventing the Illicit Import, Export and
Transfer of Ownership of Cultural Property is
adopted to combat a form of smuggling which
has been known to rob entire peoples of their
heritage.
A study programme on Slav cultures is
launched.
Focus on the environment
im
General policy
Portugal announces its withdrawal from
UNESCO (effective end 1972). Portugal resumes
membership in 1974.
The Executive Board adopts a resolution
recognizing the People's Republic of China as
the only legitimate representative of China at
UNESCO. A similar decision had been taken
previously by the United Nations.
Exact and natural sciences
The International Co-ordinating Council of
the Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme
holds its first meeting. MAB is an intergovern¬
mental interdisciplinary programme which seeks
to develop scientific knowledge about the rational
management and conservation of natural
resources. More than 10,000 researchers from
some 110 countries participate in this world-wide
effort to reconcile the demands of development
with respect for the environment and its
resources.
An Intergovernmental Conference for the
establishment of a world science information
system (UNISIST) is organized in conjunction
with ICSU.
Education
International Education Year. Paul Lengrand's
study, An Introduction to Lifelong Education, is
published.
Culture
The first session is held of the International
Scientific Committee for the drafting of a General
History of Africa (39 members, two-thirds of
whom are Africans).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Communication
A survey in 1 1 African countries on the prac¬
tical possibilities of developing a rural press leads
to the launching of a series of rural newspapers
in Africa. The following year, the first rural
newspaper in Bambara is published in Mali with
UNESCO aid.
Protecting the heritage
Wl
General policy
Education
Learning to Be, the report drawn up by the
International Commission on the Development
of Education, under the chairmanship of Edgar
Faure (France) makes a stimulating contribution
to world thinking on education.
The European Centre for Higher Education
is established at Bucharest.
Educational innovation networks for develop¬
ment are launched in Asia (1972); Africa (1976);
Southeast Europe (1977), the Caribbean (1979)
and the Arab States (1981).
Prospects, a quarterly review of education, is
launched. Currently published in 7 languages.
Culture
A ten-year plan for the study of the oral tra¬
dition and the promotion of African languages
is adopted.
The first festival of the arts of the Pacific is
held in Fiji. Others will be held later in 1976
(New Zealand), 1980 (Papua-New Guinea), 1985
(Tahiti), 1988 (Australia). The 6th is scheduled
to take place in 1992 in the Cook Islands, which
became a full Member State of UNESCO in
1989.
Two series of cultural studies on Latin Ame¬
rica are launched: (1) América Latina en su cul¬
tura (6 volumes published to date, on literature,
the plastic arts, architecture, etc.); (2) El mundo
en America Latina (3 vols, on the different ethno-
cultural components of the population of Latin
America).
im
Education
The General Conference adopts the Conven¬
tion concerning the Protection of the World Cul¬
tural and Natural Heritage. The Convention
comes into force in 1975, and becomes opera¬
tional in 1978 when the first 12 sites are put on
the World Heritage List and the first financial
aid is given from the World Heritage Fund.
The German Democratic Republic becomes
UNESCO's 130th Member State.
A reader scans Klbaru ("News"), a rural
newspaper published In the Bambara language In
Mall.
International Book Year is marked by the
launch of a long-term reading and book develop¬
ment programme.
Communication
UNESCO holds its first enquiry into the
international diffusion of television programmes.
Consultants are sent on mission to the Carib¬
bean to launch a multi-media enquiry into the
development of the communication media in the
region. Results include a training programme for
journalists and media technicians and the creation
of a Caribbean news agency (CANA).
A training programme for radio and TV spe¬
cialists in Asia is launched, paving the way for
the establishment of the Asian Institute for
Broadcasting Development. It is later expanded
to include the Pacific region.
A Regional Office for Education in the Arab
States is established in Beirut. Similar Offices
already exist in Dakar, Bangkok and Santiago
(Chile). In this year funding for UNESCO¬
UNDP teacher training projects stands at $22
million.
The International Council for Adult Educa¬
tion (ICAE) is established.
Exact and natural sciences
	.	L	
The first session is held of the Board of the
International Geological Correlation Programme
(IGCP). This programme, executed jointly with
the International Union of Geological Sciences,
seeks to increase our understanding of the Earth's
crust and the origin of natural resources.
An International Manual on Irrigation, Drai¬
nage and Salinity is published jointly with the
Food and Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations (FAO).
Culture
The Director-General appoints a specialist as
his personal representative to report on changes
in the Holy City of Jerusalem since 1968.
A seminar held in Belgrade lays the founda¬
tions of a programme of intercultural studies
which focuses largely on the interaction between
cultures and completes the traditional regional
cultural studies which have long been a feature
of UNESCO's work.
Ornate façades adorn the historic centre of St.
Petersburg, one of the sites on the World
Heritage List.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
im 4§ fcfl L
1 1
~-» A V fl
General policy
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow (Senegal) is elected
Director-General.
The General Conference grants observer status
to the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)
and to African liberation movements recognized
by the Organization of African Unity (OAU).
The General Conference condemns Israel on
the Jerusalem question.
The refusal of the General Conference to
include Israel in the European region of
UNESCO leads the United States to suspend
payment of its contribution. This situation comes
to an end in 1977 when the arrears are paid.
IGCP
Social sciences
lifts
The logo of the International
Geological Correlation
Programme.
The General Conference adopts the Recom¬
mendation concerning Education for Interna¬
tional Understanding, Co-operation and Peace
and Education relating to Human Rights and
Fundamental Freedoms, and also the Revised
Recommendation concerning Technical and
Vocational Education.
An interdisciplinary programme on "Man and
his environmentthe Human Habitat" is
launched. This programme includes components
from the social sciences, culture, the cultural
These terracotta dragons
come from Kasongan, Java.
Supporting arts and crafts Is
a priority of the International
Fund for the Promotion of Culture.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow (Senegal),
Director-General of UNESCO
from 1974 to 1987.
heritage, and architecture (the history and evo¬
lution of architectural forms in different cultural
regions, their influence on modern building, etc.)
Culture
An International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture is created, with the aim of promoting
cultural values, aiding artistic creation and
regional and international cultural co-operation.
So far almost 400 projects have been carried out
in 92 Member States for a global total
approaching $3.5 million, financed by voluntary
contributions.
The General Conference authorizes a study
programme on Arctic cultures.
Communication
The notion of the "right to communicate",
formulated in 1969 by Jean d'Arcy, is studied in
UNESCO's programmes. The importance of this
right is largely based on its capacity to condition
the exercise of many individual rights already
established (rights of meeting and association, the
right to belong to a trade union, etc.) and on
progress in communications technology.
Events
His Holiness Pope Paul VI awards the John
XXIII Peace Prize to UNESCO.
y
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
CARLOS FUENTES
talks to Fernando Ainsa
p
\
^
V
77ie Mexican writer Carlos Fuentes is one of the leading
figures in contemporary Latin American literature.
In his novels and short stories, pre-Hlspanlc myths mingle
with recent history to define the Mexican Identity.
One theme of his work, especially topical in a year which marks
the 500th anniversary of the meeting of the Old World and
the New, is the complex relationship between his country and Spain.
In a premonitory article published in 1982,
you speculated as to whether Europe and
Latin America could unite their efforts to
escape the double hegemony which then split
the world in two. It was a question of
inventing a "multipolar" world in which no
one would be anyone else's satellite and in
which each one of us could contribute to the
shaping of a polycultural, multiform,
civilizing ethos.
In the 1950s, while we were still students,
the people of my generation felt that we were
trapped, useless and sterile, between two blocs,
two superpowers, two mutually exclusive
ideologies. Each demanded total loyalty,
sacrificing the diversity and multiplicity of all
those countries and cultures that refused to
make an unqualified choice between com¬
munism and capitalism, between the Soviet
Union and the United States.
The cold war was no joke in Latin
America. In the name of the conflicting ideol¬
ogies and in face of the attitudes of the two
powers, many political and cultural opportu¬
nities were lost. The first visible manifestation
of the Cold War in Latin America was the
foreign intervention in Guatemala in 1954.
You will recall that Guatemala had just
had two successive democratically elected
governmentsthose of Arevalo and Arbenz.
That experiment was brusquely brought to an
end, to be followed by thirty years of geno¬
cide, repression and of democracy spurned.
Many other countries experienced similar
dramas, not to mention those that were sub¬
ject to various kinds of pressures or in which
dictatorial régimes were shored up.
The end of the cold war left not only
Latin America, but also Africa and Asia, in
an enormous political and even worse cultural
mess. The Third World had not been given
the chance to make its voice heard or to con¬
tribute to a world richer than that of the
"either or" choice between Moscow and
Washington.
This is why the emergence of
"multipolarity"which many Mexicans of
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
fe kve to àfeni od cultivate life au tk vim tkt wh it woéwhik-ârt id he,
soliàrity dû culture,
my generation had been seeking for nearly
forty yearswas a cause for rejoicing, even if
our joy was muted. We have just witnessed
the collapse of political theories and economic
systems that never had much to do with our
real problems, but we are well aware that the
transition from bipolar manichaeism to
pluralism will not be easy. After the euphoria
of the fall of the Berlin wall and of the rigid
communist dictatorships of eastern Europe,
we are beginning to appreciate the scale of the
perils that threaten us and of the obstacles
blocking the passage from bipolarity to mul-
tipolarity.
Are we not now seeing a resurgence of
ethnic nationalism and ofselfassertiveness by
minorities rather than the emergence ofa mul¬
tipolar world?
I never expected the birth of the multipolar
world to be anything other than difficult. It
was always going to be hard to impose cul¬
tural diversity as a value capable of bringing
new political realities into being. Basically, we
are all hunched over the blank pages of the
twenty-first century wondering fearfully
whether there has really been a twentieth cen¬
tury rather than an unnatural prolongation of
the nineteenth century, with its ideological
conflicts, its exaggerated nationalisms and its
illusions of progress.
The twentieth century believed in the
promise of human perfectibility through
progress and through absolute liberty,
including the liberty to do evil. It has been
a century of scientific enlightenment and of
political gloom, of the universal reign of tech¬
nology, but also of violence and ideological
crisis.
Was this a crisis of ideologies or rather of
a certain conception of the State?
To my mind the concept of the Nation-
State, which has dominated the world of
politics since 1917, is being seriously ques¬
tioned. In Latin America, we have the
enormous advantage that nation and culture
coincide, which is far from being the case in
the Soviet Union, in Canada, in Ireland or
even in France and Spain, where there is a cer¬
tain mismatch between the idea of the nation
and its cultural expression.
In America, we have learned how to create
a "polyculture" in each State, a multiracial
society which may have problems of its own
but which does not call into question the co¬
existence of several cultures within the same
nation. Our American nations are founded
upon racial mixing, and that rests on integra¬
tion, not exclusion. Whenever we have been
tempted to practice exclusion, we have failed;
and each time we have practiced integration,
we have been the richer for it. This is the fun¬
damental logic of our cultural experience,
which, ever since the sixteenth century, has
been one of openness to external influences.
Our capacity for integration comes to us
from our Iberian roots, from that peninsula
where Christian, Muslim and Jewish cultures
coexisted and which has experienced so many
invasions and conquests. It is a remarkable
coincidence that the very year, 1492, in which
Spain's historic image as a nation of welcome
was dimmed by the exclusion of the Jews and
the conquest of the kingdom of Granada, was
also that of the discovery of America. On 12
October 1492, the first contacts with pre-
Columbian civilizations opened up the
prospect of new intermixings of unexpected
richness.
Without wishing to minimize the crimes
committed against the indigenous populations,
I believe that what ultimately prevailed was
the tendency towards racial mixing and cul¬
tural interaction, so much so that nation and
culture are now one and the same and mutu¬
ally reinforce one another.
In Latin America, we have succeeded, after
a fashion, in conceiving and creating a world
in which values, far from being stifled by the
clash of opposites, are given new life through
lively communication and recognition of the
multicultural reality. Values cannot be dis¬
sociated from the social context which gave
rise to them. Respect for and knowledge and
acceptance of these values imply respect for
and knowledge and acceptance of what is
"different", of those who are different, even
if they appear to reject us. These "others",
those who reject us, enrich and mould us by
enabling us to be receptive to whatever is not
"us". The moulding of one by the other, the
transformation of our individual egos through
contact with all that is alien and different, is
part of the exciting challenge presented by the
multipolar, ethnically-mixed world towards
which we are inevitably heading.
But did not bipolarity also provide a form
ofprotection for many Third World countries,
a situation that enabled them to maintain a
presence on the world stage and to protect
themselves from one great power by seeking
support from the other? Today, especially in
Latin America, there seems to be a sense of
confusion at being thrown back on one's own
resources in this way, even though some see
the positive side ofthings and are pleased that
the Third World can finally take responsi¬
bility for its own problems and attempt to
solve them itself.
Yes indeed, but this applies not only to the
Third World; the same could be said about the
Soviet Union, for example, and even about the
United States, both of which find themselves
obliged to look more closely at their own
internal problems instead of working out
global strategies for others.
For our part, we Latin Americans must
put our own house in order, or as they say
back home, "scratch ourselves with our own
fingers". We are the only ones who can resolve
our problems. We must stop flagellating our¬
selves and casting ourselves as the eternal
victims of history. I personally have no feeling
of being a victim. I believe that we can, quite
independently, affirm our personality in the
political and economic fields just as we have
already done in cultural matters.
I am in no way underestimating the
problems connected with currencies, foreign
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
trade and debt, but it seems to me that there
is a whole series of basic problems relating to
agriculture, food provision and education that
we can solve by ourselves. A country that
cannot feed and educate itself from its own
resources is in no condition to make the great
leap forward we expect in the twenty-first cen¬
tury. The essential thing is to educate our
people and, above all, to feed them.
We have been victims of a gigantic mis¬
understanding. We thought that the industries
of the nineteenth century with their factories
and smoke-stacks were an earnest of
prosperity and the path to progress. All that
has been made obsolete by the rise of the auto¬
mated, high-tech, services economy, while we,
at- least in some countries, are still trying to
construct vast industrial complexes belching
out smoke and soot.
We must begin by tackling local
problemsbuilding that first school, first
hospital, first roadand proceed modestly,
patiently, step by step.
We cannot go on fooling ourselves, telling
ourselves that solutions will come from out¬
side. If we do, we shall fail, as happened at the
end of the nineteenth century, when we opted
for a liberal solution based exclusively on for¬
eign trade. The result was that a minority got
rich with no benefit for the majority. Here
and there, the democratic efforts of clear-
thinking politicians, such as José Batlle y
Ordonez, in Uruguay, and Lázaro Cárdenas,
in Mexico, helped to clean up the economy
and to bring about a partial redistribution of
wealth. Almost everywhere else, however, the
gap between the rich and the poor merely got
wider. We must not fall back into the vicious
circle of the errors of the past; and this is what
is likely to happen if we do not get to the root
of our own internal problems.
Do you think that the process of reducing
the contradictions and antagonisms in Latin
America is at last getting under way?
We are seeing a radical change in the struc¬
tures of our societies. We inherited centralized
structures that in some cases went back to the
pre-Columbian empires, survived the Con¬
quest and lasted on into the republics. Today,
however, I see developing a movement that
comes from the grass roots and the margins
of society and which is now overtaking the
vertical structures and institutions of the
pastthe Church, the State and the Army. In
other words, civil society is preparing to take
charge of our history and of civil society as
a whole. It is this society that creates and
transmits culture. Culture is the strongest,
most valid and most durable of our posses¬
sions, the one best able to withstand crises and
which has remained intact throughout the
present crisis.
In this sense, culture, as a response to life's
problems, is alive and well in Latin America,
from Mexico to Tierra del Fuego. By culture
I mean a way of living, thinking, dreaming,
struggling, loving, singing, dressing, furnishing
and decorating the home, remembering. All
this is very much alive and, in my view, has
a positive role to play in the context of the
multipolar world in which we shall henceforth
be living.
In welcoming the arrival of a multipolar
world, are you no longer afraid of the
"Balkanization" of Latin America?
The nations of our continent have their
own internal logic and cultural continuity
going for them. As I mentioned earlier, nation
and culture coincide in all of them, even those
countries with the ethnic diversity of Mexico,
for example. That is because their cultures
have managed to integrate the indigenous con¬
tribution or, in the case of Cuba, that of the
Black world. This cultural pluralism, which
exists in Mexico just as it does in Ecuador or
Venezuela, means that there is little danger of
the kind of separatist implosion to be seen in
the Soviet Union, in Czechoslovakia or
Yugoslavia. I do not think one can talk of
"Balkanization" in our situation. It is just not
a Latin American problem.
Our own form of "Balkanization" is of
a different kind. It comes into play when it
is a question of going beyond the concept of
the nation to create supra-national regional
groupings. This is an area in which we have
failed.
We have had neither the imagination nor
the political will to transform our common
cultural ties into political union. The contrast
between the cultural unity and the political
and economic disunity of Latin America is dis¬
turbing, because it represents a failure, a void.
We have been unable to achieve union because
we have too often sought or imposed develop¬
ment models that bear little relationship to our
cultural realities.
What is lacking is the will to bridge the
gap between our continent's cultural cohesive-
ness and some form of political union and eco¬
nomic co-operation, and thus to transform our
rich cultural affinities into an equally fertile
political and economic unity.
Remember what José Martí said: "The
country that only does business with one
other country is headed for slavery." We have
to open up contacts with everyonewith the
United States, the European Community, the
countries of the Pacific and amongst ourselves.
We must develop integrated free-trade zones,
as Argentina, Uruguay and Brazil have done
with Mercosur. There is also the reactivation
of the Andean Pact, the first steps towards a
common market linking the United States,
Canada and Mexico, and the Central
American countries' attempts at union. Great
opportunities for action exist both within and
outside the region and for providing openings
amongst ourselves and to the world.
To turn to your work as a writer, your sto¬
ries are strongly marked by the myths ofMex¬
ican history. While these myths have given
the country its identity, is it not possible that
their cultural weight may stand in the way
of desirable progress and jeopardize the
changes that society must inevitably make?
The myths are hardly obstacles to develop¬
ment, since once they have been transformed
into literature they become ideal instruments
for the essential task of reinventing the past.
This is the task of the novelist, whereas that
of the historian is to make a faithful recon¬
struction of it. The novelist takes it upon him¬
self to reinvent in depth a world that must
come alive again, for the future only exists if
the past does also.
True myths are living things that evolve,
contradict and jostle each other. Dynamic
rather than inert, myths influence each other,
and their contradictions reflect the contradic¬
tions of the real world.
My purpose has always been to bring the
pre-Columbian myths into confrontation with
the realities of contemporary Mexico. The past
is alive, it is all around us. It is not just by
chance that the remains of the Great Aztec
temple were found midway between those
two symbolic monuments of Mexico City, the
Cathedral and the Presidential Palace. A whole
culture, a whole way of life is present there
and in the traces of sacrificial blood as well.
One cannot understand Mexico without
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
knowing something of its past. This, no doubt,
holds true for other countries. In the absence
of myths, countries like Argentina, where
indigenous cultures have had little influence,
have found ways of inventing myths. In this
area, a dialectical, open approach is necessary.
It is clear that the void of the past must
be filled. We have to fill in the gaps, the
yawning hiatuses in a history that has not been
told, assimilated and handed down. In Latin
America people have often sought to fill these
gaps with dreams of utopia. In so doing, they
are resorting to imagination to create the past,
in order better to handle the present and the
future. As UNESCO's Director-General,
Federico Mayor, once put it: "We have to be
capable of imagining the past if we are to be
able to have a clear vision of the future."
This year, 1992, we shall be celebrating
thefive-hundredth anniversary ofthe meeting
of two worlds.
This will not be a matter for celebration,
but for reflection, and we should avoid falling
into the excesses of criticism or hyperbole to
which summary consideration of this anniver¬
sary could lead us. The past should not be seen
either as a succession of crimes or as a para¬
dise lost. It has to be recognized that we and
all that we have achieved over the past 500
years are the outcome of that brutal
encounter. There was a clash of cultures, but
the catastrophe of the Conquest gave birth to
us Amerindians. In a sense we have jointly
forged the culture that now unites us.
We are the product of intermixing and of
the Spanish language that most of us speak.
We come from a Catholic culture, but one
impregnated with religious syncretism, rich in
Indian and African influences, that cannot be
understood stripped of its indigenous, and
later Black, masks. As the Mexican poet
Ramón López Velarde put it: "We bear the
face of the Occident, tinged with the tint of
Moor and Aztec", and, I would add, of Jew
and African, Roman and Greek.
The indigenous culture of the Americas
has not disappeared, any more than it has tri¬
umphed. Let us say that it has survived to
become an integral part of what José Lezama
Lima calls the "Counter-Conquest"the
Indian and African response to the European
grip on America. The racial purity of the con¬
quistadors lasted no longer than the first night
of love between a Spaniard and an Indian
woman. It is this intimate contact between
men and women that distinguishes the Iberian
conquest from other colonial régimes that did
not experience ethnic mixing.
That is why there is no reason to lock our
gaze on the initial disaster of the discovery and
the Conquest, as some historians would have
us do. Instead we should be asking questions
about our identity, about who we are, and
trying to come up with the answers.
We cannot turn our backs on the culture
we have forged over 500 years without
renouncing all cultural activity for the coming
500 years. That is why I think that 1992
should be less a year of celebration than of
reflection on what we have been able to
achieve, so that we can go forward rather than
isten to the siren voices of extremism.
A final question, what will happen after
1992? -
The coming years will present great
problems, some of them on a planetary scale
(I am thinking of the environment), and others
stemming from the clash of unfamiliar cultures
and from the tide of migration (of manpower,
of peoples) from South to North and from
East to West. I am less concerned about con¬
frontations between nations than about cul¬
tural problems arising from fear of what seems
alien .
I believe that the next millennium will
fully justify the existence of UNESCO and of
the world's other cultural organizations. It is
within them that the great enigmas of
knowledge may be resolved. Will we one day
learn how to harmonize science, politics and
moral values and to achieve this without exag¬
gerated idealism or resort to criminal violence?
Will we be able to break out of the vicious
circle of illusion and disillusion, of progress
and violence, and replace it by a more com¬
prehensive view of humanity, one I am
tempted to call "the tragic vision"?
Happiness and history rarely coincide. We
must be wary, but not give up the fight
altogether. We have to defend and cultivate
life and the values that make it worthwhile-
art and love, solidarity and culture. Just
because we do not know if we shall succeed
is no reason for not trying.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF...
Mass Migration
in Europe
An international conference
on mass migration in Europe
will be held in Vienna
from 5 to 7 March 1992.
Organized by the Institute for
Advanced Studies, Vienna,
the International Institute for
Applied Systems Analysis
in Laxenburg (Austria), and
the Institute for Future
Studies, Stockholm, the
conference will examine the
economic, social, historical,
geographical and cultural
aspects of mass migration
in Europe and will include
a number of scientific
workshops. It will be attended
by researchers, politicians,
businessmen, writers and
journalists from Europe and
North America.
Ecotechnology
on display
The first international
exhibition of ecotechnology
and the environment is being
held at the Centre National
des Industries et des
Techniques, Paris, from
7 to 9 January 1992. Entitled
Ecosite, the exhibition is
divided into five sections:
environmental strategies;
clean technology;
ecoproducts; ecological
services and advice; and
information sources
relating to environmental,
health and humanitarian
activities.
Poor man's
pyramids
Nine mini-pyramids containing
human remains have been
discovered in the vicinity of
the Great Sphinx at Giza,
Egypt. Prior to this discovery
it was thought that pyramids
were only used as tombs for
pharaohs, high priests and
other notables, but these are
believed to have housed
individuals of lower degree.
Meanwhile, German
archaeologists have
announced the discovery of
the first pyramid ever found in
the Valley of the Kings, near
Luxor in Upper Egypt.
Inscriptions inside the
pyramid, which was built about
1400 B.C., indicate that it was
the tomb of Ba-Ran-Nefr, high
priest of the god Amon.
Paris 4,500 B.C.
Three dug-out canoes carved
from oak, one of them
virtually intact, are amongst
some remarkable relics
discovered on a Paris building
lot, which indicate that the
site of Paris was inhabited
6,500 years ago. Other items
unearthed include vases,
decorated bottles, flint axes
and a bow. The canoes, which
measure between 3.45 and
5.35 metres long, are the
oldest boats ever discovered
in Europe. At present, they are
being kept immersed in water
in specially installed tanks to
preserve them from rotting.
Chinese herb
to fight malaria
Heralded as a major new
weapon in the fight against
malaria, the drug arteether is
undergoing its first human
clinical trials in the
Netherlands as part of a
UNDP/World Bank/WHO
programme for research and
training in tropical diseases.
Arteether is a derivative
of artemisinin, or qinghaosu,
the active constituent
of the qinghao plant
(Artemisia annua), which has
been used for over 2,000
years in Chinese traditional
medicine to treat chills and
fevers associated with
malaria. The properties of the
qinghao plant were
rediscovered in the 1960s,
when the Chinese authorities
ordered a systematic
examination of indigenous
plants used in traditional
remedies. In 1972,
Chinese scientists were able
to isolate the plant's active
constituent.
...
Poet and Planet
The International Astronomical
Union has officially decreed
that planet number
4635 is to be named after
the French poet Arthur
Rimbaud (1854-1891).
Planet 4635 was discovered in
January 1988 by an
astronomer working at the
Haute Provence observatory in
France.
Pollution control
creates jobs
Efforts to protect the Earth's
deteriorating environment
have created millions
of new jobs and will create
even more in the coming
decade, according to a new
study by the WorldWatch
Institute, based in
Washington, D.C. "Less
damaging ways of producing,
consuming, and disposing
of goods are fully
consistent with the goal
of full employment because
they tend to be far more
labour-intensive", writes
Michael Renner, author of
Jobs in a Sustainable
Economy (WorldWatch Paper
104). The report points out
that pollution control has
become a major industry on
which the ten largest
market economies spent
more than $170 billion in
1989, creating some five
million jobs. Recycling has
also emerged as an important
means of job creation, and
may already be a larger
employer in the United States
than coal mining. Twice as
many people now work in
aluminium recycling as in
primary aluminium
production. High
unemployment stems from
the same economic choices
that cause industries to
destroy the environment, the
report says.
12
IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF... IN BRIEF..
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A,LmadOU Hampâté Bâ, the man who was
known as the "living memory of Africa", was
born into an aristocratic Peul family in Mali
at the dawn of the twentieth centuryhe liked
to say that he was "one of the eldest sons of
the century"and was a member of
UNESCO's Executive Board between 1962
and 1970. He died on 15 May 1991 at Abidjan
(Côte d'Ivoire).
Some people at UNESCO still cherish the
memory of this warm-hearted, smiling man,
who always wore a full-length embroidered
garment and was addressed by many as
"Papa". The saying with which he will always
be associated, that "In Africa, when an old
man dies, a library disappears"has become
so famous that it is sometimes quoted as an
African proverb.
Perhaps few still remember the occasion
on which it was uttered. It was in 1962, at a
meeting at which the rescue of the great
pharaonic monuments of Nubia, threatened
by the waters of the Aswan High Dam, was
being discussed. After expressing his pleasure
that UNESCO was endeavouring to save
artistic treasures of universal value, Amadou
Hampâté Bâ explained that other monuments
existed in Africa that were just as precious for
the cultural heritage of mankind, but were
unfortunately far more fragile and perishable.
These monuments were the great repositories
of ancestral African lore who were not being
replaced and whose knowledge would prob¬
ably die with them. "In sixty years," he said,
"the Nubian stone monuments, even if water¬
logged, will still be there, but our last great
'illiterate scholars' will have gone for ever, and
their knowledge with them."
Throughout his time as a member of the
Executive Board he pressed for the systematic
collection of these oral teachings and for the
rescue of African oral traditions, not only
because of their cultural value but also because
they enshrine a vast sum of historical, reli¬
gious, philosophical, scientific and literary
knowledge. He liked to quote this phrase by
his philosophical master, the Sufi mystic
Tierno Bokar: "Writing is one thing and
knowledge is another. Writing is the pho¬
tographing of knowledge, but it is not
knowledge itself. Knowledge is a light which
is within man. It is the heritage of all the
ancestors knew and have transmitted to us as
seed, just as the mature baobab is contained
in its seed." Amadou Hampâté Bâ was one of
those who made the greatest contribution,
notably at UNESCO, to winning world-wide
recognition for the cultures of Africa.
It is less well known that Amadou Ham¬
pâté Bâ often proved to be an outstanding con¬
ciliator on UNESCO's Executive Board. He
would defuse tense situations by telling an
apposite African story in which his audience
could recognize themselves. He was capable
of engineering a unanimous vote when a few
moments before the divergence between
different viewpoints had seemed insur¬
mountable.
Willingness to hear and respect the other
person's point of view, a desire to seek mutual
APPRECIATION
A <*
HAMPATE BA
THE GREAT CONCILIATOR
by Diélika Diallo
understanding through dialogue, hatred of
intolerancethese were the outstanding
characteristics of Amadou Hampâté Bâ. He
was a great African humanist, or rather,
simply a great humanist, since he transcended
frontiers: "When we are tuned in to the
universal," he said, "we shall have earned the
right to call ourselves human beings and be
worthy of our place in the concert of nations."
Nothing in his early life seemed to ear¬
mark him for a role in international affairs.
In childhood he received a traditional educa¬
tion, Islamic and African, Peul and Bambara.
His automatic entry into French education at
the age of twelve took him along a new path.
Who knows where it would have led if, at a
time when he was preparing to enter the Wil¬
liam Ponty college of education on the island
of Gorée (Senegal), his mother had not
ordered him to go no further with his studies
in French, "which had gone on quite long
enough". He bowed to her wishes and refused
to join the pupils who were leaving for Gorée,
with the result that the colonial authorities
sent him to distant Ouagadougou, where he
occupied a junior post as a "temporary writer
employed on a highly precarious basis."
Nevertheless, he achieved advancement. By
1933 he was senior secretary at the town hall
of Bamako and occasional interpreter to the
Governor of French West Africa.
His career took a new turn in 1942 when
he was appointed to a post at the French Insti¬
tute of Black Africa where he worked with
the founder of the Institute, Théodore Monod.
Ever since he was a child, he had collected oral
traditions wherever he had gone, but now he
could do so to his heart's content as part of
long-term ethnological, historical and lin¬
guistic research in the field. He published
many articles and a longer study, L'Empire
peul du Macina, a work entirely based on the
oral tradition.
In 1951, Théodore Monod obtained for
him a UNESCO scholarship which enabled
him to spend a year in France, where he estab¬
lished firm friendships with scholars such as
Marcel Griaule, Germaine Dieterlen and Louis
Massignon, who specialized in African and
Oriental studies. Subsequently, he returned to
France each year and gave a series of lectures
at the Sorbonne on Peul culture and civiliza¬
tion. With Germaine Dieterlen he published
Koumen (1961), a major anthology of Peul
initiatory stories.
In 1958, when Mali became independent,
he founded the Institut des Sciences Humaines
at Bamako. In 1960 he represented his country
at UNESCO's General Conference and in
1962 was elected to UNESCO's Executive
Board. In the same year he became Mali's
ambassador to Côte d'Ivoire and remained in
this post as long as his country, which had
broken with Senegal when the Federation of
Mali broke up, needed access to the sea via the
port of Abidjan. Four years' later he resigned
to devote himself entirely to his mission as "a
man of cultural and religious dialogue".
He began to publish a flow of works,
saving from oblivion some of the finest
examples of Peul oral literature including
Kaïdara, L'Eclat de la grande étoile, Petit Bodiel,
Njeddo Dewal, mère de la calamité, and La
Poignée de poussière (contes et récits du Mali).
In 1974 he was awarded the Grand Prix Lit¬
téraire d'Afrique Noire for his most famous
work, L'Etrange destin de Wangrin. He also
catalogued his vast collection of manuscripts,
the outcome of half a century's research into
African oral traditions. When they have been
reproduced on microfiche and a number of
works relating to them have been published,
they will be made available for consultation
by researchers at libraries in Paris and in
Africa.
The death of Amadou Hampâté Bâ is a
great loss for the world of African culture and
for all those who knew and loved the man.
However, his ideas live on in his works and,
remarkably, in his memoirs, the first volume
of which, recently published'under the title
Amkoullel l'enfant peul (Actes-Sud, Paris, 1991)
is a unique account of colonial Africa at the
beginning of this century as seen through the
eyes of a child.
D1ELIKA DIALLO
is a translator and a UNESCO staff member. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The demographic
dimension
Now 5.4 billion, world population will
probably double before it stabilizes
U
14
'NDER the guidance of its first Director-
General, Julian Huxley, the 1948 General Con¬
ference of UNESCO highlighted three major
groups of problems facing the postwar world-
nationalism, obstacles on the path of technolog¬
ical advance and population growth. The gravity
of "the problem of world population" led
Huxley to the view, expressed in "The Report
of the Director-General on the Activities of the
Organization in 1948", that "somehow or other,
population must be balanced against resources,
or civilization will perish".
In the same report, Huxley noted with alarm
that world population had already reached 2 bil¬
lion and that the 3 billion mark would certainly
be topped early in the twenty-first century. This
turned out to be a very optimistic forecast. The
world today has a population of 5.4 billion and
recent United Nations projections indicate that
by 2025 it will have reached 8.5 billion, almost
three times the figure forecast by Huxley, and
that demographic growth will not be halted until
the twenty-second century, when world popula¬
tion will stabilize at around 11.6 billion.
The very magnitude of these figures puts
population growth into the category of what the
National Research Council of the United States
recently described as "self-evident problems, such
as crime, sickness, illiteracy, hunger and poverty,
which must be resolved by means of appropriate
social policies". Since then, better knowledge of
the relationships that exist between demographic,
economic, social, political and cultural factors has
undermined some of our old certainties without
providing others to replace them.
Few today would venture to suggest that a
slowing of the rate of demographic growth would
of itself be enough to ensure a rapid improvement
in the standard of living of the world's most
impoverished classes. Nor would those who are
not unduly alarmed by present demographic
changes go so far as to deny that lower popula¬
tion growth rates and a more even distribution
of populations would make it easier to combat
underdevelopment and poverty and environ¬
mental problems arising from excessive popula¬
tion pressure. What, then, are the most effective
forms of action we can take to correct present
demographic trends?
Possible scenarios
The World Population Conference, held in
Bucharest in 1974, was the scene of a clash
between two contradictory theories as to how to
reduce population growth. The first of these,
which received the backing of a majority of the
developing countries, has been summed up in the
catchphrase "development is the best contracep¬
tive". According to its supporters, an improve¬
ment in the standard of living, coupled with
educational advances, would inevitably lead to a
better acceptance of, and demand for, means of
birth control.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The opposing viewpoint, described as "neo-
Malthusian" by its detractors, despite the fact that
it diverged considerably from the theories of
Malthus, was based on the principle that a reduc¬
tion in the rate of population growth, achieved
by means of a reduction in fertility, was a pre¬
requisite and not a consequence of development.
Supporters of this theory therefore advised the
organization of huge campaigns for the spread of
information and the distribution of con¬
traceptives.
The World Population Plan of Action,
approved at the Bucharest Conference, adopted
a less dogmatic tone and succeeded in taking some
of the initial virulence out of the debate.
Nevertheless, ten years later, at the International
Conference on Population, held in Mexico, in
August 1984, to assess the working and results
of the Plan, this debate re-emerged, but in a very
different political and ideological context. Dressed
up in neo-liberal guise, the "development first"
argument received the support of the United
States, whereas, this time, the developing coun¬
tries were calling for vigorous family-planning
programmes.
The defenders of the neo-liberal standpoint
maintained that a development model based on
free, individual initiative, with the market as the
principal regulator of the economy, was the only
Placards on the back of
Indian buses advertise the
benefits of the two-child
family. India was one of the
first developing countries to
sponsor birth-control
information campaigns.
mechanism capable of ensuring lasting develop¬
ment and of creating the necessary conditions
under which couples would, in their own interest,
come to modify their perception of the family
and themselves choose to have fewer children
better spaced out. This transformation of the scale
of values and of family preferences would
generate a demand for contraceptives which the
market could itself meet with only marginal
assistance from the State.
The principle of non-intervention by the
State applied also to the question of internal
migrationsany interference by the public
authorities would be likely not only to infringe
individual liberties, but also to distort the
workings of the market in goods and services and
this in the end would aggravate the very social
and community problems such interference was
designed to resolve.
Although to do so was in contradiction with
the principles they stood by, for political reasons,
the governments and many of the theoreticians
supporting this view treated international migra¬
tion as a separate case, as though in this field the
laws of supply and demand did not apply.
The argument of those who favoured family-
planning programmes seemed to find some justifi¬
cation in the rapidity of the demographic transi¬
tion (see box page 17) in Latin America and in
certain Asian countries, which appeared to con¬
tradict the notion that a reduction in birth rates
is conditional on structural change and to entail
acceptance of the view that the fall in the birth
rate is due, at least in part, to an evolution in the
understanding of and the aspirations, attitudes
and values relating to procreation.
On this basis, some have sought to draw the
conclusion that a vigorous family-planning
programme could act as a brake on fertility
without the need to introduce major social and
economic reforms. At this stage in the debate,
such a conclusion seems premature. Comparative
historical studies that have been made on the
demographic transition have shown that whilst
too much emphasis may perhaps have been
placed on structural factors as the prerequisite of
a reduction in the birth rate, their importance
cannot be entirely denied.
Learning
from experience
Social and demographic indicators concerning all
countries were recently published in "The State
of World Population, 1991", the annual report
of the United Nations Population Fund. They
reveal that:
the highest rates of population growth are to
be found in the poorest countries;
there are, however, some exceptions; in some
countries the population growth rate is lower
than might have been expected in view of the
level of the per capita Gross National Product;
the reverse is true in other countries where, 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
although the economic indicators, comparatively
speaking, are not so low, population growth rates
are high;
whether or not there is an official population
policy, the percentage of women making use of
family-planning services is, almost without excep¬
tion, higher in the more developed countries.
Given these facts, it might well be asked
whether there is any means by which population
growth rates can be significantly reduced. United
Nations projections according to which world
population will stabilize around the middle of the
twenty-second century, at about 11.6 billion, are
based on the supposition that there will be a dimi¬
nution in the overall fertility rate in the
developing countries, which will reduce from 3.8
to 3.3 births per woman by the year 2000. For
this to occur, the percentage regular use of con¬
traceptives in these countries would have to rise
from the present 51 per cent to 59 per cent. In
absolute figures, this would mean that, within a
period of nine years, 186 million women would
have to be persuaded to make regular use of
contraceptives.
Experience over recent years indicates that it
is extremely difficult to achieve a rise of these
proportions in the regular use of family-planning
methods. With the exception of Latin America
(excluding central America), the Caribbean, east
and southeast Asia, the other regions, which are
those that contribute most to world population
growth, would have to achieve a reduction of at
least 1.1 in the average number of births per
woman; in Africa south of the Sahara the average
would have to be reduced by more than half
(from 6.8 births per woman to 3.3).
Although they have been prime recipients of
international aid over recent years, the poorest
countries still have high fertility rates. Judging
Births per woman
1960-65
6.1 6,1
5,9
2.7
I
6,2
All developing
countries
Fertility trends in the
developing world, by region
(Source: United Nations,
1990).
NAMiBlANS
16
Poster advertising Namibia's
1991 census, carried out with
the aid of the United Nations
Population Fund. Lack of
reliable demographic data is
making it difficult to draw up
Namibia's first national
development plan, due to
come into effect in 1993.
MAKE SURE
YOU ARE
COUNTED
^Ä^A ^ THE GOVERNMENT
IN PLANNING THE FUTURE OF NAMIBIA
PARTICIPATE IN THE CENSf. )fi
by results, the efforts made to stem the rising
demographic tide through campaigns for the dis¬
tribution of contraceptives, coupled with infor¬
mation, education, communication and family-
planning programmes, have clearly not been very
effective. This relative failure casts considerable
doubt on the theory that dissociated demographic
evolution from economic progress and leads us
to ask what other options are open to us.
In theory, there are three such options. The
first is to establish an obligatory maximum limit
to the number of children per family. This,
however, would be contrary to paragraph 29 of
the World Population Plan of Action, which
recommended that all countries "respect and
ensure, regardless of their overall demographic
goals, the right of persons to determine, in a free,
.informed and responsible manner, the number
and spacing of their children".
The second option is to rely on "the magic
of the market economy" in the hope that it will
quickly rescue the poorest countries from the
abyss of underdevelopment, change family atti¬
tudes concerning numbers of children and
encourage the public and private sectors to
respond more effectively to the demand for con¬
traceptives. It is questionable whether such faith
in the market economy is justified, at least as far
as the poorest countries are concernedtheir
market mechanisms are weak and they are in
competition with the industrialized countries
which firmly protect their internal markets and
erect trade barriers against the importation of
products from the developing countries.
The third option, put forward primarily by
economists and social science experts of the
developing countries, is also supported by the
regional institutions of the United Nations as well
as by a number of eminent specialists of the deve¬
loped countries. It proposes that the newly-
developing international division of labour be so
oriented as to favour more equitable trading
between the developed and the developing coun¬
tries whilst enabling national economies to give
priority to the elimination of extreme poverty
and to raise the level of well-being of the general
public.
This third option, sometimes referred to as
"equitable development", involves raising
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
381
Numbers in millions
1960-65 1985-90
217
94
I
All developing East Asia Latin America South Asia
countries
Africa
Trends in the number of
contraceptive users, by region
(Source: United Nations,
1990).
RAUL URZUA
is co-ordinator of UNESCO's
population programmes and
director of its Division of
Population and Human
Settlements. A sociologist, he
is a former director of the
Roberto Bellarmino Centre for
Sociocultural Research at
Santiago and professor of
sociology at the Catholic
University of Chile. His many
published works include
Desarrollo Regional,
Migraciones y Concentración
Urbana en América Latina
("Regional development,
migrations and urban
concentration in Latin
America", 1985) and La opción
preferencial por los pobres: de
la teoría a la práctica ("The
preferential choice for the
poor: from theory to practice",
1987).
JACQUES VÉRON
is a French demographer
engaged on research at his
country's National Institute of
Demographic Studies (INED)
and its Centre for Population
and Development (CEPED). His
interests include the
epistemology of demography
and the relations between
population and development.
governments' social policieseducation, public
health, housing and employmentfrom their
present secondary role and placing them on at
least an equal footing with strictly economic poli¬
cies aimed first and foremost at growth. Among
these policies, demographic policies concerning
population growth rates and distribution should
be given priority if population pressures are not
to become an obstacle to the fight against
poverty.
Action along these lines seems to offer the
best chance of achieving the goal of preventing
the pressures of population growth and distribu¬
tion fuelling even more alarming trends than
those forecast by the United Nations. This will
only be possible if the developed countries, which
hold the reins of world economic power, are pre¬
pared to accept that demographic and environ¬
mental problems will not be resolved so long as
long-term objectives are sacrificed to the benefit
of short-term interests. Furthermore, the
experience of recent decades demonstrates that,
in the struggle for justice and against poverty and
social inequality, a necessary prerequisite is a
major effort to establish, consolidate and extend
democracy.
Whether we like it or not, the probability is
that the world population will double before it
becomes stabilized. Resolution of the problems
that this entails and preventing them from
growing to unforeseeable proportions is not a
question of means but of political will. The cur¬
rent upheaval of the world political scene pro¬
vides an opportunity, perhaps unique, to give a
new momentum to efforts by the international
community to increase the well-being of ordinary
people everywhere.
The demographic transition
by Jacques Véron
IN 1934, the French politician and polymath Adolphe
Landry formulated a new concept relating to population
change which he termed "the demographic revolution".
This concept was later taken up and given wider currency
by demographers at Princeton University, under the new
label of "the demographic transition".
The concept can be summed up as follows: Economic
advance (or development) upsets the initial equilibrium
between the mortality rate and the birth rate within a given
population, but this equilibrium will eventually be automat¬
ically restored by the interplay of internal mechanisms.
Before the rapid advances in medicine and public
health that have been made over the past century, today's
industrialized countries experienced high birth and mor¬
tality rates and, as a consequence, their demographic
growth rate was low. As medicine and public health
improved, this equilibrium was temporarily broken; the
mortality rate fell, but the birth rate remained unaffected.
As a result, these countries (with high birth rates and low
mortality rates) went through a period of rapid population
increase. Finally, the fall in mortality rates was "absorbed"
and birth rates fell until a new equilibrium (low mortality
and birth rates) was established. The birth rate seems in
some way to react to the fall in the mortality rate, but only
after a certain time-lag.
It is worth taking a closer look at the logic of this
model. Within a given society, vaccination campaigns and
advances in public health come as an impact from the
exterior. The mortality rate is affected immediately, since
some of these medical advances have a major effect on
one of its essential components, infant mortality. The
society, however, is accustomed to a high rate of infant
mortality for which it compensates by a high birth rate.
To counter the risk of losing children in infancy, parents
have more children; and the birth rate will not be modi¬
fied (intermediate period of disequilibrium) until parents
are fully conscious of the change that has occurred in the
mortality rate. Gradually, however, the change in the mor¬
tality rate is perceived and registered by parents, who will
then tend to have fewer children. At the same time, in a
society that was originally rural, but which is tending to
become urban, the status, role and utility (in terms of work)
of children is no longer the same.
The demographic transition model is based on obser¬
vation of demographic change throughout history in
today's developed countries in which the fall in mortality
rates was followed by a drop in birth rates, by urbaniza¬
tion, industrialization and improvement in education. Were
these changes really linked and, if so, how? Can there
really be said to be an automatic mechanism that restores
the demographic balance?
If the demographic equilibrium will automatically be
re-established, then there is no need for concern about
the rapid population growth occurring in many Third World
countries. The very high population growth rates in Kenya
and Bangladesh, for example, may simply mean that these
countries are passing through the intermediate stage of
disequilibrium. But can there be an automatic readjust¬
ment when the intermediate dislocation is very intense?
Excessively rapid population growth raises acute problems
concerning education and employment. There is a danger
that there will be no fall in the birth rate, since the socio¬
cultural changes required to bring the automatic adapta¬
tion mechanism into play will not occur.
If it is accepted that the demographic transition theory
may be faulty, then this implies that political action through
population policies may be necessary and that population
control programmes should be implemented. This view
takes the debate out of the scientific field and places it
in the realm of politics, and attention is then focused on
the persistence of high birth rates as an argument for inter¬
ventionist policies. " 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
y Nafis Sadik
One person in five lives in absolute poverty
A HE elimination of poverty is first and foremost
a moral imperative; but it is also essential for the
protection of the global environment and for the
health of the global economy. On all these
grounds, we can no longer tolerate a situation in
which one in five human beingsa total of 1 bil¬
lion peoplelives in absolute poverty.
Protection of the environment is a require¬
ment for ending povertya ruined and plundered
resource base could not support our current and
future numbersand slower, more balanced
population growth is both a precondition for, and
an outcome of, finding solutions to the twin
problems of the environment and poverty.
In the past, economic development was seen
as the solution to poverty, and demographic tran¬
sition (see box page 17) as the eventual solution
to population growth. Some damage to the
environment was accepted as a necessary, but
only marginally important, cost of development.
These assumptions are no longer justified.
In many cases development has not only
failed to eliminate poverty but has actually
increased it, with deadly effects on population
growth and environmental damage. For when
development efforts are ineffective, they disrupt
existing social and economic systems without
providing compensating benefits. Even when
development is effective it vastly increases human
sources of pollution and environmental destruc¬
tion. The industrial technology in use in most of
the world was developed without thought for its
environmental effects.
An unwanted side-effect of incomplete
development has been to encourage rapid popu¬
lation growth. Mortality has fallen and life expec¬
tancy has risen, but there has been much less
effect on birth rates. Increasing income and
improving child survival leads in the first place
to larger families. Only when development
programmes include a family-planning element
does family size fall significantly.
Another unintended side-effect of incomplete
development has been massive and sustained
urban growth. Classic development theory relies
on the city as the engine of economic growth and
therefore encourages urbanization. However, no
one foresaw rates of urban growth of between
4 and 7 per cent such as are being seen now in
many developing countries where urban growth
has spiralled beyond control.
The crisis is produced as much by numbers
and concentrations as by technologies and struc¬
tures. This is a peculiarly difficult dilemma. If
i
i
*'.-. j%
Several well-known musical
duos have helped spread the
family-planning message
through their songs: below
left, Nigeria's Onyeka Onwenu
and King Sunny Adé; centre,
Tatiana Palacios of Mexico
and Johnny Lozana Correa of
the Puerto Rican group
"Menudo"; right, Lea Salonga
from the Philippines and
Charlie Masso, a former
member of "Menudo".
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
development is simply the replication of world
experience to date, it condemns the environment,
and therefore itself.
The keys
to modern development
Education, health care and balanced population
growth, with special attention to the status of
women, are the keys to modern development.
They also form a basis for the elimination of
poverty and protection of the environment.
Developing countries' own resources of food
and raw materialsand above all their human
resourcesare sufficient for balanced develop¬
ment, if they are exploited in a thoughtful way
rather than for short-term gain. The aim- of all
who are committed to development must be to
work towards the marriage of public policy with
private interest and a full sense of community
combined with respect for human rights and
dignity.
There are many reasons why so many people
are and remain so poor. One is the sheer scale
of the problem; the poor are the fastest-growing
segment of the population in any country and
in the world as a whole. Another reason is that
the poor are trapped in a vicious cycle where
poverty, lack of education, lack of earning power,
poor nutrition and poor health feed on each
other. However the main reason for continuing,
large-scale poverty is quite simplethe lack of a
concerted will, nationally or internationally, to
do something about it. Many promises have been
made, but few have been kept. Many develop¬
ment theorists have pointed out that poverty can
kill us all, but they have not been heeded. Ending
poverty has simply not rated a high priority in
most countries, whether industrialized or
developing.
The poor themselves certainly have the will
and the motivation to defeat their poverty.
Anyone who has ever set foot in a slum, a poor
village or a shanty-town knows what ingenuity,
skill and effort go into the daily struggle to sur¬
vive. We in government and the development
business must learn not to get in the way. This
is not the same as abdicating responsibility; con¬
sider how many ready-made anti-poverty
programmes have come to grief because the poor
were not involved in their design and execution;
consider how many more have failed because
they ran foul of some contradictory policy.
Consider in particular how women have been
excluded and how their contribution to the
The father of eight children,
this Nepalese farmer
volunteered for sterilization.
He holds family-planning
meetings and literacy courses
for his family and neighbours
at his home.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Brazilian street children learn
a trade in a carpentry
workshop.
national and local economy and society has been
undermined by schemes with the word "develop¬
ment" in their titles. The pattern is so consistent
across continents and levels of development that
it is difficult not to conclude that the intention
was to exclude women from the new society and
to keep them safely at home with the children.
Community
involvement
Experience shows that the successful grass-roots
development programmes are those which
respond to national needs through local action
and involve both men and women, rich and poor.
For national policy to succeed, effective and
appropriate services must be delivered locally and
at the family level. Even more important, fami¬
lies and communities must be involved in the
policy-making and management process.
There is considerable scepticism today about
the ability of governments to deliver develop¬
ment services to the poor and even more about
governments' ability to involve communities in
decision-making, although in most countries this
has scarcely been given a fair trial. Where govern¬
ments are committedas, for example, in Sri
Lanka, or in Costa Ricathe experience has cer¬
tainly been that services such as education, health
care, family planning, agricultural extension and
even housing can be delivered with community
co-operation. Recent reports say that the State of
Kerala, in India, has achieved universal literacy
largely through a combination of official and
community action.
The other aspect of service delivery is, of
course, self-help. The poor are almost completely
self-reliant, because they have no one else to rely
on. Considering what they achieve with so few
resources, it should come as no surprise that they
can do a great deal when resources are more plen¬
tiful. With small amounts of outside help and
organization, shanty communities in Sri Lanka
have made themselves the model for a national
self-help housing programme. The Grameen
Bank in Bangladesh is a famous example of
success in extending credit to the poor.
Can successful community-based experience
be transferred to productive areas of the
economy, for example to industry or agricultural
policy? A growing number of economists and
other analysts of the development process now
think so. If, for example, the supply of water for
irrigation is controlled and paid for by user
groups, the result is that less water is used and
it is used more effectively.
The mix depends upon the country and the
community. Flexibility is the key to a successful
approach. Above all,' understanding that
improving services to the poor is an important
development goal must be inculcated at all levels.
The banking industry in Indonesia was very scep¬
tical about making loans to women's groups, but
it has been shown that with outside funding
women's groups will both repay on time and
make profitable investments. Commercial banks
are now much more enthusiastic about such
business.
If the global importance of small-scale
development is to be recognized, the big
organizationsinter-governmental groups, mul¬
tilateral agencies, international policy-making
institutions must give it their seal of approval.
It is very difficult for the very big to see the
very small, but it is important for them to learn.
There are too many, examples of massive,
internationally-funded development projects that
NAFIS SADIK
is Executive Director of the
United Nations Population Fund
(UNFPA), the world's largest
source of multilateral
assistance to population
programmes. On her
appointment, in 1987, she
became the first woman to
head a major voluntary-funded
UN programme. A physician of
Pakistani nationality, she is the
author of many articles in the
field of family planning and
health, and has edited a book
Population: The UNFPA
Experience (New York
University Press, 1984).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
have ended in expensive, environmentally dan¬
gerous and socially catastrophic failure.
A role for the United Nations
The United Nations system is being given more
work to do in the post-cold war era. The system
has already proved its value as a neutral forum
for discussion of different approaches to develop¬
ment. It has proved its value as a channel for
development assistance which is not tied to one
ideology or approach. Greater resources are now
needed so that the system can work towards a
new international consensus on the shape of
development.
Even more important, perhaps, than
resources for the future effectiveness of the
United Nations system will be a clearer sense of
direction. The United Nations is an inter¬
governmental system and, in the end, govern¬
ments decide how effective they want it to be.
It is quite clear that the various parts of the system
need better co-ordination. It is equally clear that
our agencies and their mandates, their political
direction and their management, are fragmented
and need to be reviewed and revised so as to meet
the needs of the next century. After three
development decades, the best we can sayand
it is a considerable boastis that we have sur¬
vived. We are supporting the largest number of
humans ever to have inhabited the planet at one
time. We have escaped nuclear war and we seem
to have reassessed the risks of nuclear melt-down.
The United Nations has not collapsed, blown
apart or withered away. Some of our institutions
are stronger than before and some of them have
learned how to work effectively. There is inter¬
national consensus on the need for action to pro¬
tect the environment, even if there is disagree¬
ment as to what that action should be. There is
a very strong and practical consensus on the need
for slower, more balanced population growth
worldwide.
There seems to be an even chance that the
female half of the population will get its share
of development investment in the future and be
allowed to make a full contribution to develop¬
ment work. The international community may
come to understand that enabling the poor to
escape poverty may be the key to survival for the
rest of us.
Health workers are taught
about birth control methods
as part of a family planning
programme in Lahore
(Pakistan).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
!íí*
1 . . « .M
i M
jJfÀ u
The environmental challenge
by Ronald Lee
How far can the world's ecosystem support continuing population growth?
22
RONALD LEE,
of the United States, is
professor of demography and
economics at the University of
California at Berkeley. A past
President of the Population
Association of America, he has
received the Mindel Shepps
Award for outstanding
research in mathematical
demography and demographic
methods. He has co-edited
several books on population
and economic development,
including Population and
Economic Development: Issues
and Evidence (Wisconsin,
1987) and Population, Food
and Rural Development
(Oxford, 1988).
A HE population of the world has multiplied by
a factor of seven since 1750, tripled since 1900
and doubled since 1950. Its rate of growth acceler¬
ated throughout this century, peaking in the
mid-1960s at 2.1 per cent per year and then
declining to the current rate of 1.7 per cent per
year. The rapid population growth since World
War II, unprecedented in recorded history, caused
grave concern and controversy about the ability
of the global economy and ecology to sustain the
increased numbers.
Classical economists like Thomas Malthus
(1766-1834) believed that, as growing population
made land increasingly scarce, rising food prices
would eventually choke off further economic and
demographic growth and that this would lead to
what they termed the "stationary state". For
them, natural resource constraints were at the
heart of the problem. Yet while the classical
economists stressed the central role of land in the
economy, the importance of land has dwindled
in the modern world. The share of the labour
force in agriculture is declining in most areas and
the possibilities for increasing the output from
a given amount of land, through increased inputs
of fertilizer, pesticides, new seed varieties, irriga¬
tion and better training, appear very great.
By the 1980s, policy-makers were in a state
of confusion. Was population growth good or
bad? Did it matter at all? Would expenditure on
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
family-planning programmes lead to more rapid
economic development?
This uncertainty led to systematic attempts
to assess our knowledge, including major projects
by the World Bank and the United States
National Academy of Sciences. In the mid-1980s,
these assessments revealed a surprising degree of
agreement among economists. While few of them
accepted the view that population growth was
good for development, the consensus was that it
mattered less than had previously been thought.
Earlier studies, it was believed, had failed to
appreciate the flexibility of the economic system.
Sounding the alarm
While economists were playing down the effects
of population growth, ecologists and environ¬
mentalists like Paul Ehrlich and Garrett Hardin
were sounding the population alarm. They
pointed out that the biosphere provided essen¬
tial inputs to economic activity and warned that
its limits and fragility placed bounds on sus¬
tainable levels of economic activity and that these
bounds had already been overstepped. The global
economy was consuming ecological capital with
careless extravagance rather than living off the
interest.
Ehrlich and Hardin had been expressing these
views since the 1960s at least and their views were
incorporated into a systems analysis model in the
Club of Rome report "The Limits to Growth".
This report, which attracted worldwide attention
in the early 1970s, came to the conclusion that
global collapse was imminent and inevitable
unless fundamental changes were made and that
catastrophe was inherent in the structure of socio¬
economic and ecological relationships.
Social scientists soon rejected the Club of
Rome approach in favour of careful analysis of
each relationship. In the 1980s, however, a flood
of environmental problems added new urgency
to the ecologists' position. Hot summers,
drought, acid rain, polluted waters, famine and
holes in the ozone layer seemed to confirm their
predictions, leading to heightened concern about
population growth.
Ecologists, however, had presented a broad
array of reasons to end or reverse population
growth; some of these were less solid than others.
Many of the older ideas about the economic con¬
sequences of population growth were again put
forward. These were unconvincing since they
were not supported by the more recent research.
Ecologists had also been issuing warnings about
the impending exhaustion of minerals, but
economists such as Julian Simon countered by
showing that the real prices of most minerals had
been falling historically, not rising, and that the
total costs of natural resources had not been rising
as a share of national output. Petroleum prices
had also tended to fall, if increases caused by
OPEC are excluded. In 1980, Simon wagered
Ehrlich that mineral prices would decline in real
terms during the following decade. In 1990 Simon
won this well-publicized bet and collected his
money. The historical record illustrates the sub¬
stitution of more abundant resources for scarce
ones in response to relative price changes. It
exemplifies flexible economies responding to
incentives communicated through market prices.
Some of the ecologists' other claims have also
appeared to be premature or exaggerated. For
example, real food prices have historically fallen
and per capita food production has increased. The
incidence of famines has diminished, not
increased, and modern famines often arise from
wars or mistaken policies rather than from defi¬
ciencies of agricultural production due to popu¬
lation growth.
"The tragedy
of the commons"
Yet many of the ecologists' most important
warnings appear correct, particularly those con¬
cerning renewable resourcesair, water, fisheries,
land, forest cover, the ozone layer and species
diversity. These resources can sustain a certain
level of use without diminution, but over-use
leads to their damage or destruction. Further¬
more, most of them lie outside the market
Opposite page, improved rice
strains growing at the
International Rice Research
Institute (Philippines). High-
yield, fast-growing hybrids
that are resistant to disease
have made a major
contribution to Asia's "green
revolution".
Below, destroying agricultural
surpluses in France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
economy and may be used cost free. This means
that economic agentsindividuals or firmscan
benefit from cheap disposal of pollutants without
bearing the costs of environmental degradation,
the costs being passed on to society as a whole.
As a result, economic incentives encourage over¬
use. The automatic signalling mechanism of
market prices is impotent and price changes serve
neither as an incentive nor as a signal of increasing
scarcity.
For some resources, such as forest cover,
there is little incentive even for national policies,
because the costs of policies are borne locally
while the benefits are shared globally. Hardin
called this type of problem "the tragedy of the
commons", and the name has stuck. Although
traditional communities with common property
resources have typically managed them effec¬
tively, these arrangements are vulnerable to the
forces of economic development. In any event,
modern environmental problems transcend local
communities, nations and even continents.
Damaging over-use of renewable resources is
intensified by population growth. Although, in
principle, over-use can be prevented by
appropriate policies and institutional arrange¬
ments, in practice this has been difficult to
achieve. The situation is complicated because
population is only one of several contributory
factors. Per capita income growth and changing
technologies, for example, also play important
roles, but in a given situation it is difficult to
assess how much is due to their influence and
how much is due to population growth.
Nevertheless, whether renewable resources are
well managed or not, population growth means
that less of their services will be available to each
individual.
Worries about population growth have thus
come full circlefrom the classical concern for
limited land, to emphasis on physical capital, to
more recent emphasis on human capital and the
ameliorative influence of competitive markets
and back once again to the natural constraints.
This time, however, the concern is for renewable
resources, most of which fall outside the market.
For some, the urgency of population control on
ecological grounds is obvious. Others remain
sceptical. Research on links between population
growth and the environment is under way, and
there is hope for a better understanding of these
links in coming years.
Because many of the ecological costs of popu¬
lation growth are global, the ecological incentives
to restrain population for national gain may be
weak. This is another tragedy of the commons,
which can only be removed by international
collaboration.
Sacks of seed are delivered to
a group of Tuareg, to help
combat desert advance in the
Sahel.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
" ;^TÇtrtrr<v_
The numbers crunch
Kby Harold Brookfield
Is it possible to measure the population 'carrying capacity' of our planet?
"Continents as crammed as
the Raft of the Medusa", a
drawing by the French artist
A. Robida (1883).
wHEN we speak of "overpopulation" or of
"underpopulation" the implication is that there
must be some level of population in any region
or country, or in the world as a whole, at which
neither of these conditions exists and at which
population is "optimal". When we say that the
condition of either land or people is worse than it
would be if there were fewer inhabitants, then
there must be some "maximum" population,
probably higher than the "optimal", beyond
which stress becomes palpable. Underlying all this
is the notion that our planet has a certain unde¬
fined, sustainable population "carrying capacity".
Most modern thinking relies on the different
formulations of the problem by Malthus
(1766-1834) and Ricardo (1772-1823). Malthus
propounded the "law", or hypothesis, that popu¬
lation tends to increase to the level which just per¬
mits subsistence for the great majority. Ricardo
modified the Malthusian theory by a more
thorough development of the empirical law of
diminishing returns as applied to successive units 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
of labour input, implying that limits are attained
through rising scarcities.
Historically, it is certainly possible to find in¬
stances of something like the Malthusian law. In
overwhelmingly rural early fourteenth-century
Europe, every poor harvest resulted in an increase
of deaths. In Ireland, in the 1840s, the ease of sub¬
sisting on potatoes led to rapid population growth
among a peasantry constantly pressing on the
limits of famine, across which they were thrust
by crop failure in 1845.
In the mid-1960s, a group of researchers, con¬
cerned by demographic upsurge and evidence of
stress in either society or resource management,
or both, began to seek ways to quantify the crit¬
ical population densities which mark the onset
of stress conditions. All dealt with mainly self-
sufficient agrarian societies using pre-industrial
technology and with land-rotation farming in
which the fallow period was a critical element.
The pioneer work was carried out in Africa
where a system first developed in 1949 in Zam¬
bia by W. Allan, with the object of determining
the need for land reallocation and rehabilitation,
was later extended to societies in other tropical
parts of the continent. Anthropologists and
geographers used and elaborated formulae, similar
to those Allan used to calculate critical popula¬
tion density, to quantify the productive capacity
of an environment, the number of people it could
support at given per capita requirements, and
hence the degree of pressure on resources.
Criticism of the
"carrying capacity" concept
Substantial criticism of the whole group of con¬
cepts embraced under the notions of "carrying
capacity", "critical population levels" and "popu¬
lation pressure on resources" was, however, al¬
ready building up. Increasingly it came to be un¬
derstood that a static population-resource equa¬
tion concealed more than it revealed.
Technical problems with early attempts to
make carrying capacity an effective, applicable in¬
dicator were summarized in 1986 by P.M. Fearn-
side. They addressed only one class of agriculture
and an essentially subsistence economy. Although
some authors introduced caveats, they neverthe¬
less calculated on the tacit assumption that pat¬
terns of consumption, income and employment,
crop and livestock mix and agrotechnology were
fixed. Few considered natural resource degrada¬
tion or took account of year to year variability
in the biophysical conditions of production. Most
studies were based on limited periods of field
research and there were deficiencies in the data
used on yields, the fallow period and the quali-
¿O ties of land and its resilience under human use.
Unfortunately, some of these deficiencies have
been carried forward into more recent work.
The UNESCO/MAB Eastern Fiji project of
1974-1976, which the writer headed, was assigned
the task of improving carrying capacity estima¬
tion. It was felt, not unreasonably, that islands
would provide the best laboratory. Within the
project, T.P. Bayliss-Smith took an important
step away from the old approaches, including his
own, by recognizing that the output obtained by
people from any resource-area is not a fixed quan¬
tity, but is relative to the intensity of input. The
Bayliss-Smith model is not specific to any partic¬
ular cultivation system and is applicable to open
as well as closed economies. It abandons the de¬
terministic approach of the 1960s and creates the
potential to take account of both natural and eco¬
nomic variability.
The price of progress towards realism was a
greater need for data, more complex calculations
and a result made up of choices rather than a sin¬
gle figure. The stage was set for a new computer-
based methodological step forward. This was
taken by P.M. Fearnside, who tackled the
problem of carrying capacity in a very different
environment from islandsthat of clearings made
by settlers in lowland rain forest along the trans-
Amazon highway in Brazil.
In this rather specific case Fearnside used as
his indicator the statistical probability of colonist
failure under specific population densities. He de¬
termined this probability through a complex
computer model which simulated the whole agro-
system of the settlers, employing data collected
over more than ten years to examine the causal
relationships between over sixty variables rather
than an independent condition of the environ¬
ment. This was a far remove from the work of
twenty years before.
Fearnside's method is very demanding of
data, research time and computer time, but it
approaches realism by turning the question away
from the simple numbers that can be supported
under a given and static set of conditions. Instead,
it focuses on issues such as levels of support ob¬
tainable from environmental sources under vary¬
ing conditions, or density limits on success among
poor settlers in a new environment. It shifts away
from determinism towards questions of sustaina-
bility, but in very specific contexts.
It would not, however, be reasonable to wait
on such intensive enquiries in all situations and
certainly not in the face of the large population,
development and environmental problems that
now confront much of the world. There is a
need for answers to questions posed by another
doubling of the global population and a desire
to know the sustainable carrying capacity of
HAROLD BROOKFIELD,
of Australia, is professor
emeritus in the Research
School of Pacific Studies, the
Australian National University
(Canberra), where he was until
recently professor of Human
Geography and convenor of
the Division of Society and
Environment. His principal
research has been in problems
of cultural ecology and rural
change in Melanesia and
Southeast Asia. He has served
as chief technical adviser of
projects in UNESCO's Man and
the Biosphere Programme and
is the sole or joint author of
11 books and some 150
papers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
environments and regions for use as a develop¬
ment planning tool.
How many people
can the world sustain?
A very fair first approximation to a global esti¬
mate of carrying capacity was made by E.G.
Ravenstein in 1891. He made reasonable estimates
of the world's cultivable area, its capabilities and
capacities and of yield improvements, to arrive
at a global capacity of close to six billion people
which he thought might be reached about the
year 2070, at the then current rates of growth,
A United Nations Population
Fund poster for World
Population Day, 11 July 1991.
without much loss or gain in living standards.
Since Ravenstein made his estimation, the
global situation has been transformed, not least
by the "green revolution". This and other fac¬
tors for change were taken into account in what
was probably the most ambitious attempt at
large-area measurement of carrying capacity ever
made. This major task, carried out in the early
1980s by the Food and Agriculture Organization
(FAO), in collaboration with the International
Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA),
covered the whole developing world apart from
east Asia and sought to determine the physical 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
potential population-supporting capacities of all
these countries and of soil and climate regions
within them. Soil associations derived from the
FAO/UNESCO soil map of the world were used
together with a climatic inventory created to
classify lands by mean length of growing period.
Potential yields for a range of crops were cal¬
culated on three bases: of "low inputs" assum¬
ing only manual labour, no fertilizer and no pes¬
ticides; of "intermediate inputs", with draught
animals, some chemical inputs and simple soil
conservation measures; and of "high inputs", as¬
suming complete mechanization, full use of op¬
timal genetic material and all necessary farm
chemicals and soil conservation measures. Con¬
sideration was also given to fallow periods and
to' the effects of both irrigation and land degra¬
dation on productivity. Two time periods were
used to determine the relation of actual popula¬
tion to carrying capacity1975, to represent "the
present", and 2000, using United Nations "medi¬
um" projected populations.
Results from each soil/climate zone, aggregat¬
ed by country, suggest that by 2000 most develop¬
ing countries could support their populations
from their own resources only if high levels of
input were employed, but also that a number of
countries would face inevitable shortage of food;
to reach these projections, trade within countries
was assumed. Evaluation of the method is best
based on the accompanying maps of major
regions, which show carrying capacity as persons
per hectare for each soil/climate zone, at each
level of input. The sheets for a "Southeast Asian"
region that extends west as far as Pakistan provide
a good basis for analysis; this area exhibits great
internal contrasts.
In the entire region, the map for low levels
of inputs shows virtually only the north coast of
Java as capable of supporting as many as five peo¬
ple per hectare. Almost the whole of Java, Bhu¬
tan and Bangladesh, most of Nepal, India and
lowland Viet Nam, large parts of the Philippines
and several upland areas throughout Southeast
Asia have calculated capacities less than their 1975
populations. On the basis of high levels of inputs,
only a few small, mainly upland areas are in the
latter category, though it is a different story with
projected 2000 populations.
More remarkably, however, on the high in¬
put assumption most of Sumatra, peninsular
Malaysia and the Philippines and the whole south
of Kalimantan (Borneo) are shown as having
higher capacity (ten or more persons per hectare)
than all but limited areas of eastern Java and the
north coast of that island. Similarly, most of
Kampuchea is shown as having greater capacity
to support population at high levels of input than
any part of Viet Nam. This information flies in
the face not only of present population distribu¬
tion, but also of a great deal of additional infor¬
mation on the quality of soils and water in cer¬
tain of these regions, particularly eastern Sumatra
and southern Kalimantan, where serious
problems have been encountered by transmigrant
schemes.
Despite the great body of data handled and
the vast resources employed, the methodology
differs little from that of the early carrying-
capacity calculations of the 1960s. On the basis
of incomplete environmental data and a uniform
set of assumptions about agricultural technolo¬
gy and basic consumption requirements, a deter¬
ministic result is produced. Only food supply is
taken into account and industrial and trading ca¬
pacities are virtually ignored. Moreover, the
necessary assumption of the high input levels case,
that the best agrotechnology can be applied every¬
where and by everyone, displays remarkable lack
of realism. As a statement about carrying capacity,
this onebased on a one-sector, closed-economy
modelmerely reveals the impossibility of deter¬
mining or even conceptualizing what it is in a
real, interdependent world.
An empirical notion
that should be discarded
Although there have been several further esti¬
mates, nothing like the FAO/IIASA project has
ever been attempted again. Discussion of carry¬
ing capacity, however, goes on and has taken on
a new lease of life in the modern context of sus-
tainability. In the new wave of environmental
concern it is often argued that population pres¬
sure contributes causally to degradation and
depletion. It has also been shown that degrada¬
tion can arise under both high and low popula¬
tion densities and under both poverty and af¬
fluence, while restorative management can also
occur in these circumstances.
Part of the damage now being done to more
and more of the environment is due not simply
to increased numbers, but to the greater mobili¬
ty of people and their activities and the enhanced
means they have of dealing damage through such
simple innovations as the chain-saw, as well as
the tools of modern industry. Growing numbers
are certainly a major element, but are not them¬
selves a sufficient explanation.
Setting aside speculation about future global
warming, there are already ways in which the en¬
vironment of the whole planet is changed by hu¬
man activity, with growing population pressure
as a major element. Even the advances of the
green revolution have reached something of a
plateau, though worldwide there is still vast scope
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
for improvement in both production and conser¬
vation.
To focus only on one element, however, is
to ignore questions of access to resources and cap¬
ital as causes of poverty and also to disregard the
scope for adaptation provided by the rapidly
growing division of labour, with its potential for
a more intelligent use of technology. Environ¬
mental variability is increasingly shown to have
major effects on human welfare and we must al¬
low for the possibility that it will increase with
global change. To rely for decision-making on
carrying capacity determined on the basis of
present conditions is a recipe for disaster.
Except for very specific purposes in very
small areas, no attempt to determine a popula¬
tion carrying capacity has attained credence.
Repeated predictions have been made concern¬
ing the population capacity limits of country af¬
ter country for at least half of this century. In
almost every significant case these limits have
been exceeded, while in most cases the present
people are now better off than their less numer¬
ous predecessors.
Carrying capacity is an empirical notion and
it has been empirically faulted so many times that
it should already have been discarded, at least as
a planning tool for local application. It is an im¬
pediment to rational planning for a more sus¬
tainable future. Carrying capacity for the whole
world may be another matter and on this the last
word still seems to be with Ravenstein and the
system he employed in 1891. His limits need ex¬
pansion in the light of what has transpired since,
but his very simple methods, using quantities that
can readily be changed and updated according to
circumstances, are all that so transparently sim¬
plistic and conditional a notion deserves. The real
problem is much larger; population pressure is
as much result as cause, and population numbers,
though important, are only one part of the
whole.
Crowd 2,
a watercolour by the
American artist Diana Ong.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Sixty million on the move by Alan B. Simmons
International migration
from South to North
is built into a global
system of social and
economic change
30
Xhe modern scientific community takes pride
in providing answers to world problems, yet,
paradoxically, it often makes a greater contribu¬
tion by the perspicacity with which it continues
to ask questions. The premature proposal of
simple solutions to difficult problems often does
no more than reveal ignorance.
The complex emerging patterns of interna¬
tional migration are a case in point. Efforts by
Europe, North America and other developed
regions to shut the door on the rising tide of
migrants from the Third World are not only
questionable on ethical grounds but may also turn
out to be impractical as well. Many migrants will
find ways round all but the most costly, vigorous
and harsh control systems. This is because the
very logic of social and economic change tends
to create new avenues and opportunities for
migrants. Just how this works is only now begin¬
ning to be understood.
Equally misguided is the argument that co¬
ordinated international development efforts and
economic growth in the countries of out-
migration will soon lead to a reduction in South-
to-North migration. There is a considerable body
of historical evidence to contradict this argument.
After a long period of economic growth in the
South, pressures promoting current migration
trends are indeed likely to ease or stop, but in
the short to medium termover twenty to thirty
years or even longerdevelopment efforts will
probably tend to increase South-North migra¬
tion. This is because the mechanization and
increased efficiency required to boost produc¬
tivity will mean that large numbers of workers
will lose their jobs. As unemployment rises, so
too will the numbers of people seeking refuge
elsewhere. The process may run over several
decades, since even in the best possible circum¬
stances development is gradual.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
"Some 16 million migrants
are political refugees. . . ."
Above, a refugee camp in
Ethiopia.
It is estimated that some 60 million people in
the world are currently "on the move". This
figure includes people displaced by war, civil strife,
political repression, environmental catastrophe,
the threat of starvation, economic hardship or the
desire to better their circumstances. Some 16 mil¬
lion of these people are political refugees within
the definition of the United Nations Charter, that
is, they are individuals seeking asylum from a
well-founded fear of persecution.
Potential migrants are heavily concentrated
in the poor regions of the Southin the previ¬
ously colonized nations of Africa, Asia, the Carib¬
bean and Latin America, and in the southern
regions of the Soviet Union. They not only move
to neighbouring countries within their own
regions, but, more and more, they are seeking to
move to industrially advanced regions such as
Europe, North America and Australia.
The Northern nations (and some migrant-
receiving nations in the South) are reacting with
alarm. In the North, this alarm has been fed by
graphic images in the press of Haitian, Albanian
and Sri Lankan "boat people" arriving in Florida,
Italy and Canada. Some leaders are calling for the
expulsion of unwelcome migrants, while others
are calling for increased efforts to solve the eco¬
nomic problems in the sending regions so that
migrant flows will be stopped at source. In some
countries pressure is mounting to stop virtually
all immigration.
The concerns underlying these attitudes are
complex, ranging from fear that migrants will
steal jobs or be a burden on social services, to
xenophobia and even racism.
The "globalization" of trade
There is a tendency to blame current South-to-
North migration on development failures in the
South and, indeed, the 1980s, the "Decade of
Development", were marked by economic stag¬
nation and declining levels of real per capita
income in Africa, the Caribbean and Latin
America. The decade will also be viewed histori¬
cally as a period of dramatic shift towards
"globalization" of markets and a related global
co-ordination of national economic policies.
Key trends, which are still under way,
include: globalization of production (final
assembly based on parts manufactured in various
parts of the world); globalization of consumer
markets (goods assembled in one nation are sold
in many others); the spread of "structural adjust¬
ment" programmes (to favour export-oriented
development); the rise of international trading
blocs (Europe, the North American Free Trade
Agreement, the Southern Cone trading bloc in
Latin America, etc.). Clearly globalization is not
an accident. It is the result of deliberate policies
promoted by the developed nations, by major
international institutions and by many less deve¬
loped countries that have taken their lead from
one of the major players.
One of the principal effects of globalization
has been to differentiate more sharply between
the "winners" and the "losers" in economic
development. Globalization and the policies sup¬
porting it have, for example, worked to benefit
the fast-growing economies of the Pacific Rim
(The Republic of Korea, Hong Kong, Taiwan,
Singapore, Malaysia and Thailand) because they
combined political stability, progressive policies
on education, low wages and other elements to
attract investors and promote exports. Mexico
may gain in the near future from globalization
due to the size of its labour force, industrial infra- '
structure and access to the United States.
Other regions have clearly been losers in the
new global trade and development game. Africa,
for example, has such poorly developed economic
infrastructures and such underdeveloped labour
force skills that even its very low wages and geo¬
graphic proximity to Europe did not attract many
new investors in the 1980s. Development aid has
Making electronic components Q A
in the Republic of Korea. O JL
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Loggers at work in the Central
African Republic.
been insufficient to fill this gap. Foreign direct
investment in Africa actually declined over the
1980s, as it did in most countries of Latin
America.
Third World countries that have experienced
economic growth in recent decades have also
generally experienced long periods of high unem¬
ployment and significant out-migration, although
there are some exceptions. Puerto Rico since the
1950s, Mexico in the 1960s and 1970s, and Korea
in the 1970s and 1980s, all experienced rather
spectacular economic growth, while at the same
time losing large numbers of workers and their
families through international migration. High
rates of natural population growth and the impact
of mechanization in agriculture and industry
created far more workers in these countries than
could be absorbed in the local economy. In the
late 1970s, on the other hand, Malaysia's eco¬
nomic growth was so fast that it actually suffered
from labour shortages. This, however, was an
exceptional case and cannot be taken as a general
model.
Over the 1980s, a much larger number of
countries lost ground economically, and rising
unemployment and falling real incomes in these
nations generated political crises and rising pres¬
sure for emigration. We have no crystal ball to
indicate which countries will be tomorrow's
winners and losers in the global development
game. What does seem clear is that development
in the new era of globalization will be inherently
uneven and will inevitably continue to generate
large pressures for international migration. The
places of origin of the migrants will shift as global
circumstances change.
The environmental impact
Poor nations with limited capital and technology
are obliged to seek economic growth through
export of those products they can produce
cheaply and, when wood and minerals are key
exports, control over the negative environmental
impacts of forestry and mining tends to become
lax. Similarly, the drive to be competitive lowers
the State's revenues for environmental
programmes, so that deforestation, brought about
as poor people seek fuel or new land to cultivate
or as entrepreneurs turn jungle into grazing land
for cattle, continues unabated.
Environmental degradation is but one ele¬
ment in the interconnected web of forces tending
to generate new patterns of South-to-North
movement. High unemployment, the rise of an
underground economy in illicit drugs, animal
skins or ivory, and international migration are
all linked in this web.
The developed nations are also involved. Not
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
only do the wealthy nations promote structural
adjustment and export-driven trade policies in
Third World countries (through their central role
in the International Monetary Fund and other
international financial institutions), but the logic
of internal development patterns in countries of
the North creates opportunities for migrants
from the South.
An international division of labour
Globalization of production has reinforced an
international division of labour in which scien¬
tific, technological, design, finance, management
and control jobs are concentrated in the North,
while labour-intensive and manual manufacturing
jobs are concentrated in the South. Economic
growth in the North leads to an expanding
demand for low-cost service and support activi¬
ties in the developed countries themselves. These
are jobs which workers in the developed countries
do not want, or will not take at the prevailing
wage levelin building, cleaning, gardening,
garbage collection, etc. This situation lends itself
to the sub-contracting of services to smaller com¬
panies which in turn may hire foreign-born
workers, including illegal immigrants.
The demand for drugs and other illicit inter¬
national commodities arises mainly in the North.
This has led to a globalization of underground
commerce, creating further employment oppor¬
tunities in both the exporting and importing
countries. Illicit commercial opportunities in the
importing countries favour migrants since they
are well placed to work across languages and to
link vendors in their home countries with buyers
in their new countries of residence.
A further effect of the globalization of trade
and international commerce has been to bring
about a dramatic fall in travel and communica¬
tions costs. Information flows across international
boundaries have increased enormously and have
given rise to an unprecedented level of informa¬
tion in the South about informal job niches and
economic opportunities in the North. This,
together with the globalization of consumer
products and advertising, has generated a rising
demand for income and purchasing power, all of
which fuels motivation of potential migrants in
poor countries.
An additional level of complexity arises in
some major migrant-receiving regions in the
North, where the presence of large ethnic com¬
munities changes the politics of immigration.
Families and ethnic groups originating in Third
World countries press the State to open the door
to ethnic kin. These pressures are most evident
in the multi-ethnic receiving countriesthe
United States, Canada and Australia.
A changing social and economic world
The conclusion that current trends in South-
North migration are part of a global system of
changing social and economic relationships,
favoured and promoted by the North, will not
please those who see the current migration crisis
as a process that can be stopped by stiff migra¬
tion controls or by short-term development
programmes.
Solutions to the current crisis must include
a longer-term perspective. It must be recognized
that, although international development efforts
will probably reduce migration in the longer
term, these same efforts will almost certainly
increase pressures for South-to-North migration
in the short to intermediate term.
The overall international system, and the way
in which the economies of the Northern coun¬
tries function within it, imply at least moderate
levels of international migration. Levels that are
too low will be opposed internally as well as
externally and will work against economic
development and co-operation in the interna¬
tional system.
It is difficult to imagine how economic growth
can take place in the South without extensive and
rising trade, technical exchange and co-operation
with the North. Similarly, it is difficult to imagine
how the North can achieve greater security
without fair and just co-operation with the South.
This mutuality of interest in the new global con¬
text will require legitimate procedures to permit
the short- and long-term movement of rather sub¬
stantial numbers of people from South to North
as new international institutions and arrange¬
ments are forged and strains arising from uneven
international development are compassionately
dealt with. To imagine otherwise is to go back
to a state of greater isolation of nations, conflict
between States and international chaos.
Water-carriers in the Sahel.
ALAN B. SIMMONS
is a Canadian sociologist based
at York University in Toronto,
where he is a Fellow of the
Centre of Research on Latin
America and the Caribbean
and a member of the Centre
for Refugee Studies. He has
published many articles on
globalization and international
migration, and is the author
(with A. Laquian and S. Diaz-
Briquets) of Social Change
and Internal Migration and
(with R. Cardona) of Destino La
Metrópoli. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The urban explosion
bv Mehdi Amani
By the end of the century, nearly half the world's
population will be living in cities
I
34
N 1950, there were 155 million more city-
dwellers in the developed than in the developing
countries; by 1970, there were only 30 million
more. Since then, the developing countries have
experienced an unprecedented wave of migration
from the rural areas and, as a consequence, urban
populations have multiplied by a factor of five
or even six.
By the end of this century, nearly half the
world population will be living in an urban
environment. The number of city-dwellers in the
developing world will total 1.9 billion, twice the
total for the developed countries. At the same
time, the rural population, which by then will
be getting on for 3 billion, will continue its inex¬
orable exodus towards the great conurbations.
In regions such as Europe, towns developed
at a moderate pace as a logical consequence of the
process of industrialization. This process increas¬
ingly enhanced the importance of socio-
professional groups employed in industry and the
service sector, the two main constituent groups
of urban populations in the developed countries.
In the developing countries, however, migra¬
tion flow to the cities began without this prior
stage of industrialization and at a frenetic rate;
as a result, urban growth in those countries is
today three times as fast as in the industrialized
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Computer graphic (1) shows
cities (represented by vertical
bars) projected to have over
4 million inhabitants in the
year 2000. Green portion of
the bars indicates population
in 1950; red indicates growth
between 1950 and 2000.
Developed regions of the
world are shown in white,
developing regions in brown.
Other illustrations show world
population figures for (2)
1950 and (3) 1985, and (4)
projected figures for the year
2025. Rural population is
shown in green, urban
population in brown.
Horizontal lines represent
increments of 200 million
population.
countries. One of the most serious consequences
of headlong urbanization has been to denude the
rural areas of a large proportion of their active
manpower and this has entailed a growing deficit
in the production of foodstuffs. As a result, many
countries of the South that were once self-
sufficient in food have now become major
importers of cereals even though they have at
their disposal large areas of agricultural land.
The ideal city
Economists and social scientists have long been
concerned with the question as to whether there
is an optimal size for cities. For some experts, the
optimal upper threshold, especially as far as
employment is concerned, is around 500,000
inhabitants. At between 1 and 2 million inhabi¬
tants the critical point is reached beyond which
maintenance of the general standard of living
becomes more difficult. These, however, are only
average estimates; it is clearly not possible to
establish an ideal size that could be applied to all
cities in all countries. It would be better to aim
at achieving reasonable rates of urbanization,
with moderate growth and with limited
megalopolitan development.
Nevertheless, urban growth, particularly in
the developing countries, continues at a giddy
pace. By the end of this century, the world will
have five giant megalopolitan areas with popula¬
tions of 15 million or more, three of which will
be in the developing world.
According to United Nations estimates, the
great cities in the industrialized world have almost
all reached the point of maximum growth at
which they are likely to remain for another thirty
or so years. Things are shaping very differently,
however, in the less developed regions, where
many cities that did not figure among the great
conurbations in the 1970s now take pride of
place among the great megalopolitan areas of the
world.
Mexico City, Sào Paulo, Calcutta and
Bombay, for example, which during the 1970s
stood sixth in the world ranking, topped the 10
million mark in 1985 to join the ranks of the
world leaders. In the year 2000, Mexico City will
have 26 million inhabitants, Sào Paulo 24 million
and Calcutta and Bombay a minimum of 16 mil¬
lion each. New urban agglomerations of 12 to 13
million inhabitants will also appear, including the
Cairo/al-Jizah/Imbabah conurbation, Djakarta,
Baghdad, Teheran, Karachi and Istanbul.
United Nations experts have carried their
population projections up to the year 2025, at
which time they estimate that there will be 93
cities with more than 5 million inhabitants, of
which 80 will be in the developing world. There
will be unimaginable growth, with the popula¬
tion of Abidjan being multiplied a hundredfold
in 20 years, the population of Mexico increasing
by 2,000 a day and the population of Cairo
swelling by 40,000 a month.
Tentacular
urbanization
In the developing countries, urban population
growth results primarily from migration and
from the geographical and spatial spread of cities
rather than from natural growth (excess of births
over deaths). Nevertheless, the fertility of
immigrant families and of inhabitants of areas
absorbed by the spread of the towns often
remains, for at least a generation, higher than that
of those who have been city-dwellers from birth.
When this period of adaptation is completed, the
fall in the fertility rate is often offset by a fall in
the infant mortality rate, which drops much
more quickly in the urban setting.
Under pressure from these various factors of
population growth, city limits creep irresistibly
outwards, swallowing up the surrounding agricul¬
tural land from which the cities draw their food
supplies.
In the industrialized countries, the expansion 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
of the large cities has no significant effect on
agricultural production, which is often in surplus.
In the developing countries, on the other hand,
this creeping expansion has a disastrous effect on
the environment, on resources, on the
geographical spread of the population and on
social and professional structures. A striking
example of this can be seen in the urbanization
of 500 hectares of fertile land every year in the
Nile delta owing to the expansion of the Cairo
conurbation.
This excessive expansion of the big cities
involves the construction of complex communi¬
cations networks which are a heavy burden on
shaky economies. Long and costly commuter
journeys weigh heavily on the limited budgets of
households forced out to the distant suburbs by
the high rentals and living costs of city centres.
Controlling urban growth
Reduction of natural population growth rates in
the developing countriesby action to influence
birth and fertility rates as well as mortality and
morbidity ratesfigures high on the list of
national and international priorities.
Without minimizing the importance of this
objective, the urgent need to curb urbanization
in the developing countries and to bring it into
line with policies for agriculture, employment
and population distribution also needs to be
emphasized. If urbanization and the mass exodus
from the rural areas continue unchecked, there_
is a danger that a slowdown in population growth
may of itself lead to a fall in agricultural produc¬
tion and an upsurge of unemployment in the
cities.
The urban crisis and the social, technological
and economic problems it brings in its train are
acting as a brake on the economic advance of the
countries of the Third World. It must be per¬
ceived as a worldwide process that requires con¬
certed action. The measures adopted should be
designed to promote the maximum development
of the economic potential of the country con¬
cerned, especially in the rural areas. The aim must
be to attempt to equate more closely the produc¬
tivity per head of the population in the various
regions by making the most of the natural and
human resources at their disposal.
An effort should be made to rectify the exces¬
sive concentration of infrastructures, economic
activities and services in the big towns and cities
and to create industries and intermediate areas of
activity to absorb rural manpower. Education
and training of rural populations, especially the
younger age groups, is essential if unemployment
and disparity of earnings, which are among the
main causes of the rural exodus and the over¬
population of the towns, are to be reduced. In
short, rural development should be integrated
into national development by closer collabora¬
tion between local communities and the public
authorities at the highest level.
MEHDI AMANI,
of Iran, is an adviser on
population and development. A
former professor of
demography and dean of the
social sciences faculty at the
University of Teheran, he has
also been a tutor at the French
National Institute of
Demographic Studies (INED) in
Paris and a project leader in
Africa for the United Nations
Population Fund (UNFPA). He is
the author of several books
and articles on the teaching of
demography and on problems
of population and development
in Third World countries.
JL HE history of African migration is as old as the
history of the continent. Population movement
for political, economic, religious and security rea¬
sons, as well as in response to demographic fac¬
tors, has been recorded from early times. More
recently, however, the patterns, directions and
motivations of migration have been deeply affect¬
ed by the colonial experience, which in turn in¬
fluenced economic, social, cultural, political and
demographic development.
The major streams of internal migration in¬
clude: migration from one rural area to another
(rural-rural migration), migration from a rural to
an urban area (rural-urban migration), migration
from one urban area to another (urban-urban
migration), and migration from an urban to a
rural area (urban-rural migration). In the African
context, however, the distinction between inter¬
nal migration and migration across national front¬
iers is blurred by the cultural affinities between
societies arbitrarily demarcated into separate
States. Thus the rural-rural stream is not confined
to internal migration, indeed, most inter-country
migration is of the rural-rural type.
Why people
migrate
The decision to migrate is triggered first and fore¬
most by economic considerations. People migrate
to improve their economic well-being and when
they are unable to satisfy their aspirations within
the existing opportunity structure in their local¬
ity. This does not, of course, apply to those dis¬
placed by natural disasters, such as drought or fa¬
mine, or those fleeing war or political oppression.
Internal migration takes place in large part
in response to existing imbalances and inequali¬
ties in development, employment opportunities,
income and living conditions between the regions
of a country, the dominant direction of such
movement being dictated by the location of
employment-generating projects. Thus, where
public and private investment is concentrated in
the major city, as is the case in most African coun¬
tries, the dominant migration stream will be
directed towards the capital. Where plantations,
mines and other enterprises are located in rural
areas and offer ready employment and other op¬
portunities, a substantial stream of rural-rural
migration is to be expected. This is the case, for
example, in Tanzania, Kenya and Cameroon.
The decision regarding where and when to
move is also affected by the experiences of, and
information received from, members of the fa¬
mily who have already migrated. Migrants in
Africa take advantage of the network of relatives
and friends in the towns to ease the migration
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Today more Africans than ever are on the move
and relocation process. The welfare system of the
extended family supports newly-arrived migrants
and shelters them from the strains and stresses
of the urban environment. Indeed, migration in
Africa is usually a household rather than an in¬
dependent, individual decision. Migrants also tend
to maintain links with their place of origin
through periodic visits as well as by the remit¬
tances they send back to relatives left behind.
In most of Africa, the structure of employ¬
ment is such that in plantation agriculture, indus¬
try, commerce and transportation, the demand
is mostly for men. Consequently, men tend to
migrate alone, leaving their wives and families be¬
hind, at least initially.
This has shaped the perception of the sex
roles, which tends to associate women almost ex¬
clusively with the task of housekeeper and
mother and with the economic structure of the
household. There is a lack of data about the in¬
volvement of women in the migratory process
owing to the numerical preponderance of males
in the migratory streams and the "invisibility" of
women who, as wives, merely accompany (family
migration) or join migrant males (marriage migra¬
tion). However, recent studies have shown that Tuareg on the move in Niger.
** » ~~~ *
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
autonomous female migration directed towards
attaining economic independence through self-
employment or wage earning has intensified.
The propensity to migrate is closely correlated
to educational attainment. Migrants are general¬
ly younger and better educated than the rest of
the population in their place of origin. This
reflects, in part, the youthful age structure and
the greater access to education by the younger
generation. Migration itself is linked to the pur¬
suit of formal and informal education in the cities,
where most post-primary institutions, apprentice¬
ship opportunities and informal sector activities
are concentrated. Since most wage employment
is centralized in cities, rural youths who invest
heavily in education must of necessity invest also
in migration if their education is to pay off.
Jn countries where cities have reached a rela¬
tively advanced stage of urbanization and eco¬
nomic development, women tend to predominate
in the cityward migration stream as their educa¬
tional status improves. The expansion of the serv¬
ice sector generates extra employment opportu¬
nities for women and this, coupled with their in¬
creased participation in wage employment, means
that the migratory sex ratio now favours women,
whereas in the early stages of city growth migra¬
tion was male dominated. Few African countries
have reached this stage. The exception is West
Africa where women have for some time been
dominant in the distributive trades. At this stage
urban-to-urban migration predominates, replacing
the rural-to-urban migration characteristic of the
initial stages of urbanization.
Many migrantscraftsmen, labourers, semi¬
skilled workers and service workersnow prefer
to migrate first to a neighbouring, medium-sized
town where they are likely to have relatives and
where cultural similarities make the adjustment
to urban life easier. For many migrants such
medium-sized towns will be their final destina¬
tion; for others, the so-called "step" migrants,
they are simply a stopping place on the route to
the capital city.
One other special category of internal
migrants has yet to be mentionedthe nomads.
These are pastoralists, most of whom are illiter¬
ate, who roam with their livestock over exten¬
sive areas with little concern for national bound¬
aries. Most nomads are to be found in Chad,
Ethiopia, Mali, Mauritania, Niger, Kenya and
Somalia.
The effect
on the cities
It is estimated that migration accounts for more
than half the high annual growth of the urban
population in Africa. Yet the economic bases of
cities are grossly inadequate to provide jobs, de¬
cent housing, clean water, smooth traffic circu¬
lation and a clean environment for their teem¬
ing populations.
The age selectivity in cityward migration in
predominantly non-contraceptive African socie¬
ties makes the urban age structure conducive to
high fertility. The combination of a high natural
increase and accelerating in-migration means that
Schoolboys receive
agricultural training in
Zambia.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Africa's urban population consists predominantly
of young adults at the stage of family formation.
As a result, Africa's major cities today appear
overwhelmed by the problems of rapid growth:
traffic jams, constant power cuts, water shortages,
slum housing and squatter settlements, uncleared
refuse and deteriorating sanitation. The age struc¬
ture of the urban population is such that this
situation is likely to continue for decades.
Migration policies aimed at alleviating these
problems are normally focused on the migrants
themselves, their place of origin and their desti¬
nation area. Two broad policy typesurban-
oriented and rural-oriented strategieshave been
applied in many African countries.
Five urban-oriented strategies have been pur¬
sued: direct controls or closed city programmes to
prevent in-migration (Republic of South Africa);
urban rustication or forced return to rural areas
(Mozambique); dispersed urbanization (Nigeria);
decentralization through the promotion of
medium-sized city growth and regional develop¬
ment (Zambia, Algeria); creation of new capitals
(Nigeria, Tanzania).
A few urban renewal programmes designed
to expand the economic and social base of the
towns to accommodate the influx of migrants
have been implemented, as have policies to make
jobs labour intensive and improve the social in¬
frastructure. In countries that have experienced
high urban unemployment among young school
leavers, selective programmes to absorb the
young unemployed migrants have been tried out,
such as the establishment of special youth camps
(Somalia, Zambia) and farm settlement schemes
(Ghana, Nigeria).
Several countries have experimented with
programmes aimed at enhancing the income of
farmers, improving employment opportunities in
rural areas and arresting out-migration at the
source. Efforts to retain or redirect migrants by
creating poles of regional growth, by shifting the
capital city or through small town development
have not achieved the desired results. Countries
that have implemented rural development
programmes through plantations in rural areas
(Tanzania, Ghana, Côte d'Ivoire), or have com¬
bined provision of social infrastructures with
rural employment opportunities, have succeed¬
ed in retaining a sizable proportion of potential
out-migrants in rural areas.
The question as to who decides who moves
and where they move to raises fundamental issues
of human rights. This is especially true in the case
of forced regrouping of people into compact
villages or forced migration to areas specified by
governments. In cases such as these the specific
needs of the people involved are not adequately
taken into consideration.
Devising
successful policies
The success of internal migration policies depends
to a large extent on a number of social, political
aékJL*
.ä M
4 «
^b*
Ft
Ml»'
1
jtL * ¿g ~^m
Kè?** w'It /
T^ A**^ ma , í~ ' 'Jy
X* *
v"-
K. 1 ~* k. E
and economic factors including: the political
system itself, the extent of government commit¬
ment, the influence of private sector investment
patterns and the effectiveness of government.
In Africa, as elsewhere in developing regions, such
policies tend to succeed when they enjoy high
national priority, a considerable allocation of
resources, effective co-ordination across various
levels of government and when policies are
centrally administered at the national level. The
poor performance of internal migration policies
in general can also be attributed to limited control
by governments over private investment in the
free market economies, the high costs of projects
and conflicting, unco-ordinated policies.
Planners in Africa have come to realize that
the fundamental causes of migration lie in social
and economic structures and that, although the
trend to cityward migration appears to be irrever¬
sible, it should not be allowed to proceed without
due policy guidance. Hence the promotion or the
development of medium-sized towns and rural
development should be seen as parallel strategies
to slow down the growth of the major cities.
At the rural end, sustained efforts should be
made to stimulate the growth and expansion of
rural informal sector activities and, where feasi¬
ble, the setting up of or active support for rural
industries and craft activities so as to diversify the
rural economy, generate additional employment
opportunities and enhance the income and living
conditions of rural populations.
Guineans In Gambia set out
on a trip to Conakry.
ADERANTI ADEPOJU
is a Nigerian economist and
demographer whose research
specialities are migration,
population policy and the
relationships between
population and development. A
former dean of the University
of Lagos, he is currently
training co-ordinator of the
UNFPA's programme on
"Population, Human Resources
and Development in Africa" at
the African Institute for
Economic Development, Dakar
(Senegal). 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The greying of the planet
Now that people are living longer more and more generations are coexisting,
often in the same family
^
k
A HE world has just experienced three decades
of rapid demographic change. In the past thirty
years, world population has grown from 2.7 bil¬
lion to a little over 5 billion. During this period
of unprecedented expansion, something occurred,
at first unremarked, that, nevertheless, was of
great importance for the futurefor the first time
since the eighteenth century, during the early
1970s, the growth rate of the world population
began to decline.
This new trend was an indication that, fol¬
lowing the industrialized countries, Third World
countries were in their turn entering the phase
of demographic transition (see box page 17). In
other words their fertility was dropping. The
speed with which this demographic transition is
completed is likely to be the factor which deter¬
mines not only the future size of the populations
concerned but also their age structure. The faster
the transition phase is completed the more
quickly their populations will age; for, as the
French demographer Alfred Sauvy used to say,
populations have no other choice than to grow
or to grow old.
When all is said and done, the aging of a
population, defined here as an increase in the
proportion of old people in relation to total
population, is striking evidence of the successes
achieved in gaining technological mastery over
certain aspects of life and death. The sometimes
excessive fears expressed about population aging
seem, therefore, somewhat paradoxical. Perhaps
this rather pessimistic attitude finds its roots in
the negative idea that the individual has of his or
her own agingan ineluctable process that ends
in death. No one can halt the passage of time and,
for the individual, rejuvenation is merely a
metaphor. Populations, however, do not stand
in the same relationship with time; through the
interplay of fertility and mortality rates, they can
indeed grow younger or older or maintain a stable
age structure. Of course, there are thresholds
above which the aging of a population becomes
virtually irreversible, but it is possible to achieve
a stable state in which the process of aging is, as
^rU it were, suspended in time.
The age pyramid
In demographic studies, intuition is not the most
trustworthy of guides, especially when the study
concerns the causes of population aging. For
example, of the three major demographic factors
(fertility, mortality and migration), the one that
has, until recently, contributed most to popula¬
tion aging is the drop in fertilityand not, as one
might have thought, a drop in mortality.
Reducing as it does the number of births, thus
reducing the size of the lower levels of the age
pyramid, a drop in fertility has been the most
influential factor affecting the age structures of
the developed countries. The same holds true
today for the developing countries.
The effect of lower mortality is less marked,
since it is applicable to all ages; indeed, it may
contribute to a certain rejuvenation of the popu¬
lation when it is centred primarily upon infant
mortality. It is only during the last twenty years
that the fall in mortality, which in the developed
countries has affected primarily the older age
groups, has contributed to the aging of these
populations by increasing the number of those
surviving within these age groups. Migration,
however, appears to have only a marginal effect
in the context of the population as a whole.
Mention should also be made of a fourth
factor that has recently been brought to the
forethe initial age structure. Populations that
have experienced important demographic change,
such as the postwar baby-boom, have stored up
a considerable potential for population aging. A
similar situation exists in certain Third World
countries such as China, where rapid population
growth has been followed by a sharp fall in
fertility.
Growing old together?
Comparative figures for population aging,
together with their recent and foreseeable evolu¬
tion, show that, in the industrialized countries,
the 60-and-over age group has grown from 1 1 per
cent to 17 per cent in 40 years and is expected
to increase by another 8 percentage points in the
next 35 years, attaining a proportion higher than
"\
fl
Q
-.--
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
1 i hí
j. \ i
\ *»>
/
i)
A.
J \\\
é¡7 \ m?
¿i
/., í 'K /
##
;í>
\
V
u
< I-
A J5¡.
fc
RMBMR
". . . The reduction in the ranks
of the younger generations, the
demographic burden of the older
generations and the lengthening
of the average life-span are
helping to reshape the family
pattern." Ink on watercolour
paper, by Faouzia Niazi-Lane
(Egypt).
that of the steadily diminishing under-15 age
group.
In 1950, in the developing countries, the
60-and-over age group represented 6 per cent of
total population, the equivalent to the propor¬
tion that obtained in France in 1775. Not until
the year 2025 will this proportion rise to the level
attained in the industrialized countries in 1950.
Nevertheless, the foreseeable pace of popu¬
lation aging for the developing countries seems
likely to be faster than that in the countries of
Europe. When the European countries entered
the phase of demographic transition, it took them
at least 100 years (in France), and often 150 years
(Germany and UK), to reach the threshold of 12
per cent in the 60-and-over age group, a point the
developing countries as a whole are expected to
reach in 75 years. In countries such as China,
where fertility has fallen dramatically, this per¬
centage will have been reached in a period of about
50 years, some time between 2005 and 2010.
Governments, however, whose task it is to
draw up policies and programmes, are less con¬
cerned with percentages than with absolute
numbers of elderly people. In 1950, there were
430 million people in the world aged 60 and over.
Of these, 250 million were in the developing
countries. In other words, the Third World coun¬
tries had 70 million more people in the 60 and-
over age group to look after than the industrial¬
ized countries, but with nothing like the same
resources with which to face up to the problems
of old age.
One last figure deserves examinationthat of
the very old. Medical advance has made and will
continue to make it possible to enhance the
chances of survival of the very old. Unfor¬
tunately, this has not been matched by any very
significant improvement in the physical and
mental condition of these survivors. In 1950, in
the industrialized countries, 40 per cent of those
in the 60-and-over age group were over 70 years
of age. In 1990, the proportion was of the order
of 50 per cent, and this is likely to be maintained
until the end of the century. In the Third World,
in 1950, the very old accounted for 30 per cent 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Four generations of women
under one roof (Marie-Galante
island, French Antilles).
42
of the 60-and-over age group; in 1990, the propor¬
tion was over 37 per cent and, in 2025, is likely
to reach 40 per cent.
In absolute numbers, there are today as many
very old people in the industrialized countries as
in the developing countriesjust over 90 million.
By 2025, however, the situation will have changed
completely, since there will be 160 million very
old people in the North as against 338 million
in the countries of the Southan increase of 400
per cent on present numbers. This "explosion"
of the number of very old people should be seen
in the context of an increase in total population
in the Third World over the same period of 70
per cent.
Clearly, changes on this scale in the age struc¬
tures will have important repercussions on the
demographic structure of families. In the indus¬
trialized countries, the reduction in the ranks of
the younger generations, the demographic burden
of the older generations and the lengthening of
the average life-span are helping to reshape the
family pattern. At the beginning of the industrial
revolution, half the individuals born lived beyond
the age of twenty; today nearly half live to
celebrate their seventy-fifth birthday. The family
of two or three generations will be replaced by
the four-generation family, which will include
two generations of retired persons and will be
predominantly female.
Does this evolution signal one of the final
manifestations of the nuclear family, which will
have gained vertically what it has lost horizon¬
tally? Or should we talk simply of the
phenomenon of family aging? In most Third
World countries, this situation is still a long way
off, but in a few, in which life expectation is
approaching seventy and in which fertility is
almost at replacement level, nearly all the condi¬
tions are in place for the appearance of this new-
type family. One essential point to note is that
this aging has become apparent in countries
whose level of development bears no comparison
with that of the industrialized countries at the
time when their populations began to age.
The weight of years
In the analysis of change in the age structure of
populations, demographers have the easiest role
to play. Their task is merely to lay down markers
to the more important trends that will be of use
in making projections for the future. It is quite
another story when it is a question of drawing
the economic and, above all, the social conse¬
quences of population aging. It would obviously
be impossible to deal here with all these conse¬
quences, but mention should be made of some
of them.
The first of these is the potential effect of
aging on the process of production, and especially
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
World population trends by age group between 1950 and 2025
(percent)
World population Industrialized countries Developing countries
0/14 15/59 60 and Total 0/14 15/59 60 and Total 0/14 15/59 60 and Total
over over over
1950 35 57 8 100 28 61 11 100 38 56 6 100
1990 32 59 9 100 21 62 17 100 36 57 7 100
2000 31 59 10 100 20 61 19 100 34 58 8 100
2025 24 61 15 100 18 57 25 100 26 62 12 100
Source : Economic and social implications of population ageing. United Nations. New York 1988.
on the working population. In the industrialized
countries, the irregularity of the generation flow
since the war will result in a series of peaks and
troughs in the work force. There will also be
longer or shorter spells of aging. Caught between
the conflicting evolutionary currents of the
younger and the older age groups, the working
age group will start to decline from the beginning
of the next century (see Table this page). The
increasing entry of women into the working
population has, it is true, helped to compensate
for earlier demographic deficiencies, but it is by
no means certain, in some countries at any rate,
that fuller incorporation of women into the work
force can be achieved without an unacceptable
fall in fertility. Increased immigration of foreign
workers could provide an alternative demo¬
graphic solution, but the problems this can raise
in the industrialized countries are already evident.
These difficulties have led to plans for greater
participation of older people in the work force.
In the industrialized countries, however, where
the burden of supporting retired persons is very
heavy, governments are torn between the desire
to reduce unemployment by allowing those close
to retiring age to take early retirement and the
need to have a sufficiently large work force to
finance their retirement systems. These con¬
flicting preoccupations also exist in the
developing countries, where employment policies
are impelling governments to allow retirement
at a relatively low age bearing in mind the levels
A 100-year-old man and his
95-year-old wife tend their
garden in Beverly, Mass.
(U.S.A.). As a result of
progress in medicine, the
number of very old people is
increasing.
already reached in expectation of life at birth. It
is clear, therefore, that the size of the retired
population is as much a result of political and
economic choices as it is of the vagaries of demo¬
graphic change.
No definite conclusions have yet been
reached on the much-debated question of the
negative effect of the aging of the work force on
productivity. Some experts maintain that popu¬
lation aging results in a reduction in the struc¬
tural flexibility of the productive machine and
acts as a brake on necessary change; others reject
this pessimistic view, recalling that, in the middle
of the nineteenth century, the French sociologist
Auguste Comte was predicting that an increase
in the life-span would act as a brake on social
advance since it would slow down the pace of
generation replacement. Closer to our day, Japan
and Germany provide examples of how popula¬
tions seriously affected by aging can demonstrate
extraordinary economic dynamism provided that
the aging process has been assimilated into their
long-term development strategies.
The role of the family
Population aging, however, does more than
modify the structures of the productive
mechanism; it also imposes on it considerable
constraints the financing of pension schemes and
of certain very expensive forms of consumption
specific to old age, such as medical attention.
The ratio between the numbers of economi¬
cally active and inactive adults gives us an initial
approximation, in demographic terms, of the size
of this burden. In the industrialized countries, this
ratio, which now stands at 3 to 1, will, by 2025,
fall to 1.5 active adults to 1 inactive adult. In the
developing countries the ratio is much more
favourable; at present it stands at 7.2 active adults
to 1 inactive adult, but, by 2025, it will have fallen
to 3.9 to 1. Time and space comparisons such as
these must be treated with circumspection, since
this ratio, which does not take into account
present and future differences in the productivity
of the working population, has only limited value
as an indicator.
The increase in public expenditure devoted
to pension schemes and medical and social
services for the elderly has revived discussion of
the respective roles of the family and the com¬
munity in assisting the older generation. But
before embarking on a discussion as to the rela¬
tive merits of this or that form of assistance, we
need to know how global demographic trends
will affect kinship structures and thus the con¬
straints that demographic change will have on the
family.
The English historian Peter Laslett has pointed 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
out that in England, in the time of Thomas
Malthus (1766-1834), the poor laws already bore
the stamp of demographic necessity. Despite high
fertility and a high marriage rate, 20 per cent of
female children were orphans by the age of 10,
and, at the age of 65, the same proportion of
women had no close relatives. The only possible
solution was for these people without family to
be cared for by the community.
Today, the number of orphans is very low
owing to a great reduction in the mortality of
parents. On the other hand, the marked fall in
fertility may create situations in which adults will
find themselves with no family support in their
old age. Since empirical data on kinship structures
are rare, even in the .developed countries,
demographers have had recourse to models which
enable them to reconstitute the initial shape of
kinship structures and to learn how these struc¬
tures evolve under certain demographic con¬
straints. For example, if mortality is held at a very
low level, and if the fertility rate is made to vary
from 1.8 children per woman to 1.4 over the same
50-year period, the proportion of elderly women
aged 65 or over without children of working age
will vary from 4 to 14 per cent.
Although the demographic situation is very
different in the developing countries, applying
such models to them is of greater use, since in
these countries the family still plays an essential
supportive role. Warning signs of difficulties to
come are already apparent in countries such as
China, where the policy of one child per family
has not only accelerated the onset of the demo¬
graphic transition, but has also upset the tradi¬
tional equilibrium within the family.
Competing generations
The rapid demographic changes that have
occurred in recent decades will lead to new rela¬
tionships between the generations. The extension
of the life-span implies an increase in the number
of co existing generations. As one writer pointed
out, today's societies are made up more and more
of people who are not contemporaries. To this
must be added the ups and downs in the numbers
of successive generations, whose economic, social
and demographic behaviour tends to be radically
different. To take just the question of the varia¬
tions in the generation flow, particularly within
the youngest and the oldest age groups, this is cer¬
tain to contribute to an intensification of social
tensions when a choice has to be made concerning
the allocation of resources to the various depen¬
dent groups. In the present climate of reluctance
to add to the tax burden, it seems unlikely that
there will be any increase in these resources. More
than this, the competition between the genera¬
tions is likely to be all the more acute in that
modern industrial societies seem to be prepared
to sacrifice the principles of solidarity on the altar
of immediate individual satisfaction.
"The marked fall in fertility
may create situations in which
adults will find themselves
with no family support in their
old age."
JEAN-CLAUDE CHASTELAND
is a French demographer who
was head of the United Nations
Population Division in New
York until 1990, and is now a
consultant with the French
National Institute of
Demographic Studies (INED) in
Paris. He has published many
articles on the demographic
problems of the Third World
and on questions of population
and development in general.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
UNES
Rewarding fair play
The UNESCO-supported
International Fair Play
Committee has awarded its
1990 trophies to the Italian
footballer Dino Zoff and the
British kayakers Ian Lawler and
Graham Burns. Zoff, for many
years the goalkeeper in the
Italian national side, was cited
for career-long exemplary
conduct towards team-mates,
opponents and the public. He
never contested referees'
decisions and once, before a
match in Rome, had a streamer
which was offensive to the
opposite team removed. Lawler
and Burns were nominated for a
sporting gesture during the
42-kilometre 1990 World
Championship event. The two,
representing their country,
stopped to help the Danish
team, whose rudder was
damaged, enabling the latter to
go on ahead of them and win
the Gold Medal. Diplomas of
merit were also awarded to a
number of sportsmen, teams
and clubs, and to the French
sports daily L'Equipe.
A boost for population
studies
UNESCO is launching an
international project to
introduce population education
at universities, particularly in
developing countries, which
continue to have the highest
population growth rates and are
increasingly recognizing the
importance of demographic
studies. The Organization, which
has already helped introduce
population education in primary
and secondary schools in about
100 countries, will assist with
the training of teachers and
researchers as part of efforts to
make the subject a permanent
feature of the academic
curriculum.
UNESCO's environment
activities on microfiche
The principal books, articles,
working papers and conference
documents produced by
UNESCO, or under its auspices,
from 1985 to June 1990 on the
theme of the environment have
been put on microfiche. The set
contains 8,400 pages on 100
microfiches packed in a plastic
card-index box, and comes
complete with a 137-page index
comprising subject index,
masterfile listing and title index.
The price is 2,600 French
francs per set. To give potential
buyers an idea of the scope of
the compilation, the index can
be obtained on microfiches free
of charge from UNESCO Press,
Sales Division, 7, Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France.
Just published, latest
volume of
Index translationum
Volume 38 of Index
translationum, UNESCO's guide
to world translations, is now
available. It lists 57374
translations published in 1985
in 59 UNESCO Member States,
including some works published
earlier that had not previously
been listed. The Index, the first
volume of which came out in
1948, is a reference work
targeted principally at
publishers, translators, writers,
teachers and students.
Tobacco alert
As a response to the dangers of
tobacco not only for the health
of smokers but also for non-
smokers exposed to the fumes
from other peoples' cigarettes,
the World Health Organization
(WHO) has named 31 May as
World No-Tobacco Day. The aim
of this annual event is to
encourage smokers to give up
the habit and to draw the
attention of the public and of
policy-makers to its harmful
effects. The day has a different
theme each year. In 1991 the
focus was on smoking in
public places and transport.
This year's message will be
"tobacco-free workplaces:
safer and healthier". Smoking
is discouraged at UNESCO,
and is forbidden in meeting-
rooms, workshops and rooms
where the air cannot circulate.
Time to celebrate
The UNESCO Courier has been
awarded the 1991 Türler
Media Prize for its April 1991
issue, "Perceptions of Time".
The prize, worth 10,000 Swiss
francs, was established in
1984 by the Swiss
watchmaking firm Türler, and
is awarded annually to a
publication devoted to the
theme of time. Türler has
had 9,000 copies of the
German-language edition of
the issue printed in a reduced
format for distribution to its
clients.
UNESCO issues Mozart
medal
To commemorate the 200th
anniversary of the death of
Mozart, UNESCO has issued a
medal struck by the Paris
Mint. Designed by the French
artist Raymond Joly, the medal
bears a stylized portrait of
Mozart on the obverse and the
UNESCO temple motif on the
reverse.
Celebrating Latin
America's women writers
UNESCO is paying tribute to
Latin American women by
hosting the 3rd International
Symposium on Latin American
women's writing from
23 to 25 January. The
Symposium will feature round
table discussions on themes
such as "the myth of
women and death" and
"literature and human rights",
as well as an exhibition
of the work of Latin American
artists and showings of films
presented at the Leipzig
Festival of Latin American
Women's Cinema, held in
November 1991. Many
figures from the worlds of
literature, the arts and
publishing will be attending
the Symposium, which will
close with a book-signing
session in a Paris bookshop
specializing in Latin American
literature.
WORLD POPULATION BIBLIOGRAPHY
United Nations:
World Population Prospects, 1990, New York, 1991.
World Population Monitoring, 1991, New York (in press).
State of World Population 1991, United Nations Population
Fund, New York, 1991.
Population and the Environment: the Challenges Ahead, United
Nations Population Fund, New York, 1991.
The State of the World's Children 1990, United Nations
Children's Fund (UNICEF), 1990.
Human Development Report 1990, United Nations Development
Programme (UNDP), New York, 1990.
World Bank:
World Population Projections, Short and Long-term Estimates,
1989-1990 Edition, World Bank, Johns Hopkins University Press,
Baltimore, 1990.
Others:
J.-C. Chesnais, La population du monde, de l'Antiquité à 2025,
Le monde à la carte series. Bordas, Paris, 1991.
Stanley P. Johnson, World population and the United Nations,
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, England, 1987.
J. Valiin, La population mondiale, La Découverte, Paris, 1986.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
t l Î R k
1 he ancient city of Petra lies in a semi-arid
region of south-west Jordan that dominates the
desert of the Arabah depression, dropping
down more than 1,000 metres to the west. The
massif forms a natural fortress, where once was
built a strange city, the capital of a kingdom
that dared to resist the might of Rome.
Today, Petra is one of the most beautiful
historic sites of the Middle East, a testimonial,
unique in size, to cave architecture, or what
one might almost call troglodytic urbanism.
Its 45 square kilometres house a succession of
over 500 great monuments, hewn from the
rock by astonishingly gifted Bedouin architect-
sculptors more than 2,000 years ago.
The road to Petra snakes through grey,
stony desert on a high, arid plateau. It is
difficult to believe that once, in ancient times,
an oak forest grew here. Then the road
descends into a small valley. Suddenly, at a
bend in the road, the magnificent site of Petra
comes into view below, a rocky chaos to
which the city owes its name, for "petros"
means rock in Greek.
Coming down from the plateau, the
traveller is plunged into a lunar landscape of
yellowy-white sandstone carved into thou¬
sands of sugar-loaf or whaleback-shaped
domes, an expanse of humps and protuber¬
ances whose contours are thrown into relief
by the harsh light of dawn. Already the first
cave monuments of the city can be made out,
among them the Obelisk Tomb. Gradually
the whiter rock gives way to steep slopes of
rose-red sandstone, which give the Petra massif
its dominant colouring.
The road into the massif passes through
the Sik, a narrow gorge about 3 kilometres
long, 100 metres deep and narrowing in places
to a width of a bare 3 metres. Straight stretches
are punctuated by sudden bends until the
gorge gradually opens out on a huge depres¬
sion ringed by flat-topped mountains whose
sheer slopes are dotted with magnificent
monuments.
The spectacle is overwhelming. In places,
patches of black, white and yellow alternate
with the dominant red of the multi-coloured
Left, approaching Petra through the Sik.
Opposite page, the white sandstone façade of
the Obelisk Tomb, near the entrance to the site.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
me-rei ciifiuUj'a for^M p
hy ]<A Emtnki
stone, which erosion has shaped into a natural
work of art, a ruined landscape of cliffs and
ravines pitted with grooves and cavities in
which sumptuous forms have been carved by
the hand of man.
The Valley of Moses
Everything in Petra speaks of history. Before
it even reaches the massif, the road runs
through the Wadi Musa ("the valley of
Moses"), at the entrance to which, under a
white dome, rises a spring reputed to be the
one the patriarch caused to flow from the rock
during his crossing of the desert.
Local tradition also claims that Moses'
brother Aaron is buried under the Djebel
Horoun ("Mount of Aaron"), where a small
white mosque supposedly shelters his tomb.
Charming in its rustic simplicity, it is a place
of annual pilgrimage.
Other legends have built up around the
Khazna Firaoun ("Pharaoh's Treasury"), an
astonishing cliff monument facing the mouth
of the Sik. It is topped by an urn that Bedouins
used to shoot at with their rifles in the hope
that from it would spill out the the gold of
the Pharaohs. The entire façade bears the scars
of their treasure-hunting.
Who were the sculptors and architects of
Petra? The Nabataeans, who probably origi¬
nated in southern Arabia, appeared in the
Middle East around the fourth century BC.
Strabo and Diodorus Siculus, two historians
of the Augustan era, tell us that the tribe con¬
sisted of some 10,000 nomadic Bedouins who
used to trade between Arabia and the Mediter¬
ranean. These caravaneers, "determined to
preserve their liberty . . . calling the desert
their homeland", who "have no vineyard or
field or seed, and have not built houses to
dwell in" (Jeremiah 35), nonetheless built an
empire with Petra as its capital. Diodorus Sic¬
ulus wrote of them: "They surpass other
Arabs in wealth, even though there are only
10,000 of them."
Petra benefited from a site that guaranteed
the security of its inhabitants and had its own
water source, the Aïn Musam element of
prime importance in the desert. Its location
at the crossroads of the trade routes linking
Syria to the Red Sea and India to the Gulf
and the Mediterranean gave them control of
the principal caravan routes with their traffic
in gold, precious stones, myrrh, incense,
spices, Phoenician purple, wood and exotic
animals.
King Obodas I, one of the great figures of
the Nabataean dynasty, ruled Petra during the
first century BC. Around the year 93, he
defeated Alexander Jannaeus, the king of the
Jews, in Golan, taking from him the lands of
Gilead and Moab. In 85, he killed the Syrian
king Antiochus XII in the Negev. These
events earned him divine status and he took
the title of Ilaha, meaning "God". The
Nabataean kingdom was now a power in the
Middle East and under Aretas III (84-62 BC)
it stretched from northern Arabia to the Sinai
peninsula and Damascus.
The Nabataean people underwent an
astonishing metamorphosis, the former
nomads becoming sedentary city-builders.
Many archaeological remains bear witness to
their urbanizing activities, of which Petra
remains the most spectacular example. The
city was to play a frequent part in the history
of the region in the days of Cleopatra, Herod
and John the Baptist.
In 64, Pompey created the Roman province
of Syria and, in 106, Trajan ordered its
governor to annex the Nabataean kingdom
and to turn it into the Roman province of
Arabia. The new territory was governed by
an envoy sent from Rome, and Petra itself was
given metropolitan status.
The region was gradually Romanized and,
little by little, its Nabataean character faded.
The desert fortress was unable to compete
with the economic might of the Roman giant
and, in the third century, bypassed by the new
trade routes, Petra went into a gradual decline.
Under Byzantine rule, a cave temple was trans¬
formed into a cathedral, a bishopric was
installed and Petra became a a Byzantine
administrative centre. In 636, after the battle
of the River Yarmuk, the Muslims took con¬
trol of the region, but since it was not on the
pilgrimage route to Mecca, Petra sank still fur¬
ther into decline and neglect.
At the time of the Crusades, the city, by
then in ruins, was occupied by the armies of
Baldwin I. In 1127, the crusaders built three
small forts there, the remains of which can still
be seen. The crusaders, however, did not stay
there long.
The last mention of Petra, in connection
with the Crusades, dates from 1276, during the
Syrian campaign of the Mamluk Sultan
Baybars against the crusaders. Subsequently,
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
Petra was lost in oblivion surviving, like Troy,
only as a legend.
A city reborn
In 1812, a Swiss traveller, Ludwig Burckhardt
(1784-1817), caught a glimpse of the rock-hewn
city while making a journey to Mecca dis¬
guised under the pseudonym of Sheik Ibrahim.
"I regret not being able to give a full report
on the antiquities of Sik", he wrote later, "but
... I was unprotected in the midst of the desert
where no traveller had previously gone. . . .
The inhabitants will grow used to the
enquiries of foreigners and then the antiqui¬
ties of Wadi Musa will be recognized as
worthy to figure among the most curious
remains of ancient art."
Burckhardt was soon followed by other
travellersin 1818, the British naval officers
Irby and Manglesi; in 1828, the Frenchmen
L. de Laborde and M.A. de Linant de Belle¬
fonds. In 1839, David Roberts made some fine
engravings of the site. From that time
Erosion has caused
extensive damage to
the Corinthian Tomb, right.
Preserving Petra
For several years, Jordan's Yarmuk University
has been involved in research into the weather¬
ing processes that are threatening façades and
monuments in Petra. Major studies have been
undertaken in collaboration with experts from
the Geological Institute at Aachen Technical
University in Germany, as well as with
specialists from the National Centre for Scien¬
tific Research, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
and the EDF (electricity supply service) in
France.
Work is going ahead in the following areas:
Geological study of sedimentary rocks in the
Petra area.
Research into the tectonics of the Petra mas¬
sif. Some monuments, including, the Treasu¬
ry, are now showing serious cracks.
Laboratory testing of various adhesives that
could help to consolidate the stone and act as
a water-repellent. This preliminary investiga¬
tion will be followed by field tests on natural
rocks in the area in preparation for the actual
preservation of the façades.
Over the past year micro-climatic data have
been collected from Inside the Palace Tomb,
since temperature and humidity play an impor¬
tant part in the weathering process. In addi¬
tion, wind speed and direction just outside the
edifice are being measured, since strong winds
also cause damage.
T.S. AKASHEH
Higher Council for Science
and Technology, Amman, Jordan
onwards, a stream of scientific expeditions
followed. Petra was slowly reborn to become
today one of the principal tourist attractions
of the Middle East.
The erosion that originally sculpted the
wonderful landscape of Petra has begun to
cause serious damage to some of the cliff
monuments. Because they are carved from the
rock, they are relatively fragile. Like the
mountain that shelters them, they are alive.
There are many eroding agentsthe capillary
action of water, saline outgrowths,
sandstormsand their effects are cumulative, a
factor that complicates every attempt to coun¬
teract them. Controlling the tourist influx also
poses problems, for people can in some ways
be a supplementary agent of erosion.
In Jordan, the Department of Tourism
and Antiquities, Yarmuk University, and the
Higher Council for Science and Technology
are co-operating to analyse the evolution of
the site and to determine the measures that
need to be taken to protect it and to prevent
further damage. These interdisciplinary
studies, involving specialists from such coun¬
tries as France, Germany, the United States
and Italy, are beginning to produce results.
There are plans to establish a Petra Natural
and Archaeological Park.
Since 1969, UNESCO has collaborated
with the Jordanian Government and with
French and Spanish missions to complete a
large-scale photogrammetric relief map of the
site. Since 6 December 1985, the date on which
Petra was added to the World Heritage List,
the Organization has been giving technical and
financial assistance for the study and restora¬
tion of important monuments such as the
Palace Tomb and the Qasr el-Bint ("Castle of
the Pharaoh's Daughter").
JACËK REWERSKI is a French geographer who
specializes in erosion and conservation problems and
also in troglodytic settlements. Among his publications
are Le monde souterrain de l'Anjou ("The underground
world of Anjou", 1986) and a number of works on
erosion at Petra.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDS
listening
CLASSICAL
Yehudi Menuhin.
5 CDs. EMI Classics
CDM 763985/6/7/8/9-2.
Last year the whole world, not
just music-lovers, celebrated the
seventy-fifth birthday of the violinist
Yehudi Menuhin. Even if his greatest
recordings as a performer (his work
as a conductor is another matter)
date from the 1930s, he
nonetheless produced some fine
interpretations in the 1950s and
1960s, and some of the best are
collected in this set. His violin sings
lyrically in Berg's Violin Concerto,
with Boulez conducting the BBC
Symphony Orchestra, and in pieces
by Sibelius and, more unusually,
Ernest Bloch and Carl Nielsen.
Chamber music is not overlooked.
Menuhin is partnered by Louis
Kentner on piano in Schubert's
Fantasy, in the Brahms Horn Trio
(Opus 40), Alan Civil plays the horn
and Yehudi's sister Hephzibah the
piano. Best of all is Menuhin's
Bartoksimply incomparable.
Anton Bruckner. Symphony No. 7.
Silesian Philharmonic Orchestra
conducted by Gérard Wilgowicz.
1 CD. GLT Editions 802 (distributed
by Harmonie).
This symphony, which dates from
1884 and was never reworkeda
rare event with Bruckner was
Intended as a posthumous tribute
to Richard Wagner, and at its worst
it has the ponderous quality of a
funeral monument, a slow
laboriousness that can seem dull.
The models for all future
interpretations of the work were
provided by the great German
conductor Eugen Jochum, one of
whose versions is still available in a
set of the nine Bruckner
symphonies made with the Berlin
Philharmonic (Deutsche
Grammophon 429079-2). But on
the strength of this recording, the
Silesian Philharmonic can stand up
to the comparison. Under the
direction of a conductor who
deserves to be more widely known,
its orchestral work is marked by
supple textures as well as by flights
of idiomatic lyricism, and never
lapses into pathos.
Emmerich Kaiman. Extracts from
Die Zirkusprinzessin (The Circus
Princess).
The Berliner Symphoniker
conducted by Robert Stolz, with the
choir of the Deutsche Oper Berlin
featuring Margit Schramm, Rudolf
Stock, Guggi Löwinger and Ferry
Gruber.
1 CD. Eurodlsc 258363.
The Hungarian composer
Emmerich Kaiman (1882-1953)
studied composition as a fellow
student of Bartok and Kodaly, then
abandoned "serious" music for the
world of the operetta and the
company of Franz Lehar and the
Strauss family. He was highly
successful, particularly with Die
Csárdásfürstin (The Gypsy Princess,
1915) and Gräfin Maritza (Countess
Maritza, 1924), before emigrating to
the United States in 1938. Die
Zirkusprinzessin was composed in
1926. These extracts, excellently
interpreted by Stolz, show
exceptional suavity and charm, and
in them the first murmurings of
musical comedy can be heard. A
minor master perhaps, but a
master all the same.
Sir Edward Elgar. Symphony No.L
Overture: In the South.
London Philharmonic Orchestra
conducted by Leonard Slatkin.
1 CD. RCA Victor RD 60380.
Enigma Variations.
London Philharmonic Orchestra
conducted by Bernard Haitink.
1 CD. Philips 432276-2.
Another minor master, as
charming and expert in his way as
Kaiman, Britain's Edward Elgar
(1867-1934) moved in more exalted
circles, with the great composers
among whose company he
sometimes claims a place. There is
a touch of Wagnerian prolixity in In
the South, a youthful work whose
inspiration is actually Italian; and
despite its beautiful adagio
movement, the First Symphony has
moments of heaviness. The Enigma
Variations are infinitely more subtle.
Claude dayman
Journalist and music critic
JAZZ
Roy Hargrove. Public Eye.
Hargrove (trumpet), Antonio Hart
(alto sax.), Stephen Scott (piano).
Christian McBride (bass), Billy
Higgins (drums).
1 CD. BMG Novus PD83113.
Jazz masters are getting younger.
At the grand old age of twenty-one,
Hargrove, whose second record this
is, stakes his claim to be the
natural successor to Clifford Brown.
His tone, which manages to be
smooth and sharp at the same
time, sometimes also brings to
mind Kenny Dorham or Lee
Morgan, both leading influences on
the new generation of trumpeters.
This disc, dedicated to Hargrove's
parents and to God, features a
dense, dancing music that is as
strong as any sound in
contemporary jazz. Not a single
note is superfluous. Among several
Hargrove compositions, all of them
interesting, the joyous, Latin-
influenced "Lada" stands out. Hart,
Scott and McBride, who belong to
the same generation as Hargrove,
all show a musical maturity that
belies their years, while the veteran
Billy Higgins, who has played in his
time with Sonny Rollins, Thelonious
Monk and Omette Coleman,
remains one of the most precise
and exhilarating of all jazz
drummers. Nectar for the ears!
Niels Lan Doky. Friendship.
Lan Doky (piano) with Bill Evans,
Randy Breaker, John Abercrombie,
Rick Margitza, Christian Minh Doky,
Adam Nussbaum and others.
1 CD. Milestone Carrere
9031-73592-2.
Born of a Danish mother and a
father from Viet Nam, Lan Doky has
recently made his mark both in
Europe and America. A product of
the Berklee School in Boston, he
went on to play with Woody Shaw,
Joe Henderson and other musicians
of similar calibre in New York. This
record includes some New York
tracks featuring a whole array of
brilliant sidemen, and others made
with a Danish backing group in
Copenhagen. Seductive and
ethereal though it undoubtedly is,
Lan Doky's playing suffers from a
certain coldness, reflecting the
contemporary tendency towards
technical perfectionism. But there
is much to enjoy in the long solos
that are his trademark.
Latin Jazz.
1 CD. CBS 467139 2.
The "Latin" in the title of this
enjoyable anthology does not refer
to jazz as played by Latin-American
musicians, but rather to Latin
standards played by North
Americans. It features Art Blakey's
"Cubano Chant", Bobby
Hutcherson's "Un Poco Loco", Duke
Ellington's "Peanut Vendor", Dave
Pike's "Besame Mucho", Miles Davis
playing "Corcovado", and others.
This is a happy kind of jazz with a
touch of the Dionyslac about it,
though still coloured by the pathos
of the blues. But these North
American musicians, talented as
they are, bring a foreign touch to
Latin rhythms. Ellington's playing
in "The Peanut Vendor", for
instance, is beautifully economical
in the placing of the notes,
but it is not Cuban for ¡t lacks the
phrasing that Havana musicians call
clave. Similarly, the Brazilian-
influenced tracks have a less
syncopated rhythm than
musicians would give them in Rio
or Bahia. For all that, this is a
record to buy.
FOLKLORE	
Federazione cori del Trentino.
Armoni di un popólo. Viaggio nella
storia e nette culture del canto
popolare trentino.
1 CD. Ginger GDRX 0123.
Several choirs from the Trentino,
a beautiful mountain region in the
north of Italy, come together on
this record to sing cradle songs
("Dormi, dormi"), ritornelli about
love ("La bela bruneta"), and
stories in verse ("Quande
me son sposà") in the local
patois. The words of the songs are
printed in the notes accompanying
the disc, making it easier to
savour the poetry of the language.
The polyphonies are varied,
' rich and sophisticated. Altogether,
the record displays a side of
the Italian folk tradition as
interesting as though less familiar
than the music of Sardinia or
Naples.
Festival de Mariachi.
1 CD. Th. Rodven 2789.
The word "mariachi", they say,
came originally from manage,
French for marriage. Whatever the
truth may be, this is a festive
music that owes some of its high
spirits to tequila. This compact
disc brings together such
performers as Beatriz Adriana,
Alberto Vásquez, Manolo Muñoz
and the Vargas de Tecalitlan
ensemble. Lola Beltrán,
the brightest star of Mexican
music, stands out with her
poignant interpretation of
"El Rey".
POPULAR MUSIC	
Retrospective 80/90.
1 CD. VeraBra 2040 2.
The German recording company
VeraBra specializes in compilation
albums, and this one offers
something for every taste. There
are the Lounge Lizards, Brazilian
music featuring Xiame and Hermeto
Pascoal himself a brilliant multi-
instrumentalist and musical jack-of-
all-trades some New York
flamenco with Gerardo Nuñez,
Israeli pop from Shlomo Bat-Aln,
Japanese pop courtesy of Toshiyuki
Honda, and Italian pop with Marco
Cerletti. In short, buy it for a rapid
scan of World Music of the last two
years.
Isabelle Leymarie AQ
Ethnomusicologist and journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS %
TO THE EDITOR ~
^eo>'
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
50
Cause for indignation
As a long-time subscriber (for 30
years) to the UNESCO Courier, I wish
to express my surprise and
indignation that there was no
allusion in your issue on Children in
danger (October 1991) to the
scourge of female genital mutilation.
The practice Is still as widespread as
ever (80 to 100 million women are
affected, some 20,000 in France
alone), and so are the pain and the
risk of complications and death
attendant on it. Imposed on
defenceless girls by persuasion or
violence, this practice is contrary to
Article 34 of the Convention on the
Rights of the Child, as is the practice
of "early marriage" which is also
widespread. Respect for cultures is
no reason to endorse such customs,
whatever certain ethnologists might
say. . .
The United Nations organized a
meeting on this subject in April
1991 at Ouagadougou, and UNESCO
promised to co-operate in the
necessary effort to provide
information and education in this
field. What a pity that you let such a
golden opportunity go by.
Dr. R. Boutet de Monvel
Issy-les-Moulineaux (France)
An unhappy childhood
Your issue on Children in danger was
one of the best you produced last
year. Onlyrarely do the media tackle
such important issues as this, and
few people really try to combat the
dangers which lie in wait for young
people. Children are still developing
when they reach eighteen, and need
guidance and support if they are to
have any chance of living a decent
life. Many children from unstable,
violent and disadvantaged homes do
not join gangs and do not express
their revolt openly. They repress
their feelings, escape into
themselves, and shut out the outside
world. Some also try to develop an
inner strength so that they can have
a chance at succeeding in the world
in their own way. For these children
there is nothing sadder than seeing
"perfect" families at the cinema, on
television or in newspapers, then
going home to be greeted by abuse.
As one of them myself, I would say
to others living in such an
environment that you must be your
own best friend; trust yourself and
ask for help if you need it. Fancy
clothes, money and fast ways out
are not the answers to finding a
path in life.
Angélique R. Mahal
New York
Save Dubrovnik
I should like to take the opportunity
of renewing my subscription to the
Courier to ask UNESCO to condemn
the attacks on the city of Dubrovnik,
which is inscribed on the World
Heritage List. This marvellous city
which I enjoyed visiting last year is
seriously threatened and UNESCO
has, to my knowledge, done nothing
to prevent it from being destroyed.
The honour and credibility of the
Organization are at stake. There is
no time to lose!
Jean-Louis Watiez
Bourgoin (France)
On 24 October 1991, the Director-
General of UNESCO, Mr. Federico
Mayor, and Mr. Javier Perez de
Cuellar, Secretary-General of the
United Nations, made a joint
declaration in Paris on the situation
in Yugoslavia, and launched a
solemn appeal to all parties
concerned to bring to an end the
tragic conflict and to negotiate a
peaceful settlement of their
differences.
In response to reports of damage
caused to the old city by shelling,
they also called on all parties to
respect the principles enshrined in
the Convention for the Protection of
Cultural Property in the Event of
Armed Conflict (the Hague
Convention, 1954) and in the
Convention concerning the
Protection of the World Cultural and
Natural Heritage (the World Heritage
Convention, 1972).
After recalling that "Dubrovnik is
inscribed on the World Heritage
List", they stated that they were
"sure that all parties concerned will
honour by every means at their
disposal the undertaking made by
Yugoslavia when it ratified these
instruments."
On 6 November, at UNESCO's
General Conference, Mr. Federico
Mayor referred to the situation in
Yugoslavia and revealed the results
of the mission of the personal
representative whom he had sent to
Dubrovnik. He pointed out that the
Federal Government and the Croatian
Government had confirmed their
agreement that UNESCO should
intervene within the framework of its
mandate, and that the staff of the
federal army had expressly renewed
its commitment not to attack the
heart of the city of Dubrovnik. Mr.
Mayor also announced his intention
of establishing a permanent UNESCO
observer in Dubrovnik to make an
inventory of damaged property and
prepare plans of action on behalf of
monuments and buildings that may
have been affected.
Beauty and ugliness in art
I was surprised to read in your
letters column for February 1991 an
attack on the work of the painter
Hans Härtung.
Objectivity in art involves respect
for other people's opinions, so I shall
not launch a polemic about the
critique, however trenchant it may
have seemed, nor put myself
forward as the defender of a specific
artist or work. But some statements
require an answer. . . .
One may well consider a work of
art unrepresentative of a style or
period, or think it has no place in the
development of a particular view of
art. But the terms used by your
correspondent recall the old
Manichean concepts of Beauty and
Ugliness from which modern art, in
its pluralism, freed itself long ago.
By what normative standards can
one set the "superb" profile of
Nefertiti against a "stupid" painting
by Härtung? What criterion of taste
dictates that the colours of a
"decomposing fish" are less
beautiful than others? Under what
ethical system can a painting be said
to "bring shame on humanity"?
The arbitrariness of these words is
surprising. Perhaps the canvas, like
many other contemporary works,
reflects the chaos and violence of
our time. No work of art escapes the
context of its age. Grunewald,
Brueghel, the Romanticsall
expressed the pain of their epochs.
What would the Expressionists be
without anguish, the Surrealists
without the absurd, medieval art
without its metaphysical anxieties?
The merit of our age is to have
made art a place of constant
questioning, a mirror in which
humankind can see itself and the
human condition so as to reflect on
the meaning of our destiny.
Modern art no longer accepts the
concept of beauty which, in the past,
forced all plastic creation to accept
a pre-established or imposed system
of values as its raison d'être.
Instead, its aesthetic is in constant
evolution.
Rejecting all categorical
assumptions has opened the way to
a more enriching interpretation of
works of art as well as to a wider
appreciation of the entire field of
artistic creationan approach that
no more excludes rigorous study
than it does the joy of creating,
viewing and discovering.
There is no disputing that our
century, which has called so much
into question, has yet to find its own
aesthetic equilibrium. Perhaps the
coming millennium will define itself
from our chaos.
But in the meantime, the
phenomenal development of the arts
in our time no longer allows us to
ignore the importance they have
assumed in our lives and the fresh
significance they have acquired: that
of a constantly renewed tool of self-
expression and culture that, without
denying the values of the past, is no
longer condemned to bear its
weight.
Henry Christiaen
Grenoble (France)
Reliefs
In your July 1991 Issue ("Mozart and
the Enlightenment, the Enigma of
Genius") the work that you describe
on page 15 as a bas-relief is actually
in high relief. In other words it is a
"sculpture ¡n which the figures are
almost detached from the
background", as the Pocket
Larousse dictionary defines the term.
Delphine Jambon
St-Bonnet-des-Bruyères (France)
Cover, page 3 (right):
© Gauzère/UNESCO Courier.
Back cover, pages 40-41: Faouzia
Niazi-Lane © UNESCO Courier.
Page 2: © Nicolas Arcilla-Borraz,
Paris.
Page 3 (left): Ulf Andersen
© Gamma, Paris.
Page 4 (above): © Günter R.
Reitz, Hanover.
Page 4 (below): ©J.-F. Turenne.
Page 5: UNESCO.
Page 6 (above): UNESCO/Alexis
N. Vorontzoff.
Page 6 (below), 7 (above right):
UNESCO/Dominique Roger.
Page 7 (above left): UNESCO.
Page 7 (below): UNESCO/
International Fund for the
Promotion of Culture.
Page 8: Martine Peccoux
© Gamma, Paris.
Page 11: Mireille Vautier ©ANA,
Paris.
Page 13: D.R.
Pages 14-15, 24, 33: © Claude
Sauvageot, Paris.
Page 16 (below): Camel Graphics/
UNFPA.
Page 18: from Population Reports
J-38, Population Information
Program, Johns Hopkins
University, Baltimore.
Page 19: D. Hinrichsen, London.
Page 20: D. Gras/Secours
Catholique © iph, Paris.
Page 21: Lily Solmssen/UNFPA.
Page 22: David Kinley/UNDP.
Page 23: Jean Guy Jules © ANA,
Paris.
Page 25: © Roger Viollet, Paris.
Page 27: UNFPA.
Page 29: © VLOO, Paris.
Page 30: Rémi Berli © Rapho,
Paris.
Page 31: M.Setboun © Rapho,
Paris.
Page 32: J.Reboul © iph, Paris.
Pages 34, 35: computer graphics
by Melvin L. Prucitt, from
Population Images © Robert
Fox/UNFPA.
Page 37: © Marc and Evelyne
Bernheim © Rapho, Paris.
Page 38: M.Renaudeau © Hoa-Qui,
Paris.
Page 39: Gcrster © Rapho, Paris.
Page 42: © Charles Carrie, Paris.
Page 43: Shelley Rotner/Unitcd
Nations.
Page 44: © Luc Pérénom, Paris.
Pages 46,47,48: ©J.Rewerski,
Angers, France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
le Courrier
UNESCOdel
Published monthly in 35 languages and in braille
by UNESCO. The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin, 75015 Pans, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévéque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Vligjel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Studies and research; Fernando Ainsa
Art Unit/Production: Georges Sen/at
Illustrations: Anane Bailey. [Tel.: 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Rmgelstcm (Tel.: 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solargc Belin (Tel.: 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel.: 45.68 47.15),
Moura Chatta
Administrative assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French,
Spanish and Korean: Marie-Dommique Bourgeais
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnkov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guiûotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanim (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra ligazer (Istanbu ;
Urdu: Wall Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catatan: Joan Carreras t Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dares-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Blazo Krsta;tc (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Paoageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J- Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen [Helsinki;
Swedish: Manni Kössier (Stockholm)
Basque: Gjrutz Larranaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghot Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Aodullah A. M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
Galician: Xabier Senh Fernández
(Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Assistant: Mane-Noere Branet (45.68.45.89),
Subscriptions: Mane Thérèse Hardy (45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité. Jacqueline Louise-
Julie, Manichan Ngorekeo, Michel Ravassard,
Michelle Robillard, Mohamed Salan El Dir.
Sylvie Van Rijsewijk. Ricardo Zamora-Pcrcz
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (45.68.45.64),
Accounts: ¡45.68. 45.65),
Mail: Martial Amegee (45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (4568 47.50}
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF.
Developing countries
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF
Payment can be made with any convertible currency
to the order of UNESCO
IrKJividual articles ana phoiograpns not copy enteel may be -eonrted
rovid ng the credit Ine reads "Reprinted iron the UNESCO Courier",
.¡is date of ssue. and three voucher copies are sert to the editor.
¡ articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
cover ng postage S gned articles express the opinions of tne authors
int ->ecess3':ly reoresent the pointons of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO Courier Photo captions ana headl nes
ten by the UNESCO Cower staff. Tne boundaries or. maps
i in the magazine do not mply officia: endorsement or
: ce by UNESCO or the unter: Nattons. The Courier
s prodjced in rrtcroft>nrn(rrilcrofl m and/or microficnejby: ;l; UNESCO.
7 Place Fontenoy. 7&70Ü Peris (2) University Microfilms ¡Xerox).
^rwArboi Michigan 48100. US. A : (3JN.CR. Microcard Edition, Inc. an
Head. Inc .111 West 40th Street. New York. U.SA; [4) Oeii and Howell
Co.. Ole Vnrsfield Road, Wooster, Orno 4¿691 U S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN CFA\CL
(Printed n France) DEPOT LEGAL CI JANVIER '.992.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 DIFFUSE PAR LES NMPP
Photocomposition The 'JNLSCO Courier
nnotogravure-inipress¡on: Maurj Ireprime
Z.l. route d'Etampcs. 15330 Malesherbes
ISSN 004 ¡-5278 . 1992 -£)P| 91 - 3 - bOC A
Them
of tk next im
(February W2);
Aho featuring,
an interview with African historian
Joseph Ki-2erbo
We are pleased to announce the
appearance of the 36th edition of the
UNESCO Courier, in the Galician
language.
SB*
nsand?
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
