<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="091412eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture or
any other subject which seems to
be an example of cross-
fertilization between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
Tricontinentale
1991, Montage by Monique Constant-Desportes
Elements from three parts of the world combine in this composite
work created by a woman doctor and artist of Martinique. Her
montage consists of an African mask which she brought back from
a visit to Cameroon, and a piece of basketwork, a typical art
form of the Carlb Indians, the first inhabitants of the Caribbean.
The mask is inlaid with European coins, symbolizing the
Westernization of black peoples. The artist, who describes herself
as an Afro-European living in the Americas, regards the
work as "representing the variegated reality of the Caribbean, a
somewhat incongruous yet at times successful mixture".
A
r
i J * i ...,i, ,..i i-i
A'*"1.»" ;« .»»»!
a»'
UMf/////fl/fi
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4
' Intervew
Oscar Niemeyer
talks to Edouard Bailby
tents
JUNE 1992
Con
44 Unesco in Action
newsbriefs
46 Unesco m Action
WORLD HERITAGE
The road to Sagarmatha,
rooftop of the world
by José Serra Vega
49 RECENT RECORDS
by Isabelle Leymarie
and Claude Glayman
50 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
8
In praise of tolerance
presented by Ehsan Naraghi
9 An awkward virtue
by Bernard Williams
14 Voltaire, crusader against tyranny
byJeanLessay
18 Gandhi and the struggle for non-violence
by Ramin Jahanbegloo
31 Black Africa's open societies
by Iba Der Thiam
34 Islam: a conflict of models
by Mohammed Arkoun
38 Against intolerance
by Edgard Pisani
40 The balancing act in the Vondelpark
by Niala Maharaj
45
Commentary by Federico Mayor
Cover:
Aspiration for Peace, collage
by the Indian artist V. Balu.
Back cover:
Rencontres (1991) emery
cloth mounted on wood,
by Martine Viala (France).
23
Greenwatch
ThellNESCO
- ^COURIER
45th year Published monthly
in 36 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure
the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail,
upon the intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between
their peoples and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each
other's lives	
Extract from the Preamble to the Constitution of Unesco, London, 16 November 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
OSCAR
NIEMEYER
talks to Edouard Bailby
I At eighty-four years of age, with more than
three hundred projects already built or at the
planning stage and with Brasilia as the pin¬
nacle ofyour achievement, you can justifiably
claim to be the most prolific architect of the
century. Do you still feel the urge to carry on
with your creative workf
I have little time left. I no longer travel, so
as to be free to devote myself to my family
and friends. However, I still go to my office
in Copacabana every day from nine in the
morning to seven in the evening, Saturdays
included. I am incapable of sitting in an arm¬
chair doing nothing or simply brooding over
the miseries of existence.
For me, architecture has always been a
hobby as well as a profession; it attracts and
absorbs me, but I don't attach overmuch
importance to it. The main thing for me is to
feel at ease with myself, to remain on the side
of the needy and to denounce social injustices.
That said, I have acquired a certain renown and
the commissions still flow in. I have, however,
reduced my team to four people so as to have a
quieter life. It is important tó remain active
right up to the end. You only live once.
So you are still working as an architect.
What projects are you currently working on?
I am going to complete the Monumental
Axis of Brasilia by constructing three build¬
ings which will possibly be the finest in the
capital the Museum, the National Library
and the Historical Archives. They will put the
final touch to my work as architect within the
framework of the master plan elaborated by
Lucio Costa, the great Brazilian town-planner
to whom I owe so much.
One of the most outstanding
exponents of modern archi¬
tecture, Oscar Niemeyer has
created buildings of dazzling
formal inventiveness in
his own country, Brazil, and
elsewhere in the world.
He is particularly noted for
his work on Brasilia,
the new capital of Brazil.
In telling the Courier about
his remarkable career he
recalls that architecture
Is not only utilitarian,
but art art form of major
significance, in which
he gives pride ofplace to
the imagination. Oscar
Niemeyer has published
many articles and
a number of books
Including Oscar Niemeyer
(Milan, 1977). French
journalist Edouard
Bailby is the author of
a book about Niemeyer
which will be published
later this year by
Balland, Paris.
I have a number of other projects in hand
that have already been approved, including
the Museum of Niteróia city pf 500,000
inhabitants near Rio de Janeiro and the
Brazil-Portugal Centre in the heart of Lisbon.
I have received orders for others, notably in
Sao Paulo. The site of my most recent com¬
mission is the Island of Gorée, offshore from
Dakar. I am particularly committed to this
one because it will enable me to denounce the
massive transportation of African slaves to
our continent in the days of the slave trade. In
Brazil, we received over four million of these
slaves. Much as they were humiliated and
exploited, they nevertheless took part in the
struggles for independence and made a deci¬
sive contribution to our culture. At a time
when we are celebrating the five hundredth
anniversary of the discovery of the Americas
by Christopher Columbus, it is essential to
recall their sacrifice.
You have always been alive to the problem
of human suffering to which you have given
expression in several monumental sculptures.
The most famous of these is the bloody hand
of the Latin American Memorial in Säo
Paulo, which symbolizes the struggle of
peoples against oppression. What are you
planning for Gorée?
Through the good offices of an eminent
personality for whom I have the greatest
esteem, the Government of Senegal invited me
to take part in an international competition.
As usual, I declined the invitation, but offered
instead to undertake the project without
charging a fee. My project was approved at the
beginning of this year and two missions came
to Rio de Janeiro to see me and settle the
details. Work should begin shortly.
The monument itself consists of an
eighty-metre-high panel in which I have cut
out the outline of a human figure. Rising
above the sea, it symbolizes the uprooted
African slave, vanished into space. The monu¬
ment is linked to the land by a simple foot¬
bridge which in no way detracts from its
appearance. I have designed a museum, a
reception room for important visitors and a
restaurant which will be open to the public. I
am pleased with this project, the form of
which I visualized whilst out walking,
because it emerged from deep within me.
Yet, in looking at your most remarkable
works, one has the impression that they have
involved many long hours of meticulous
research.
Like sculpture, architecture demands a cer¬
tain sensitivity and a capacity to escape from
one's surroundings. When I am asked to carry
out a project, I always think about it alone,
sitting in my office, lying on a couch, or while
out walking. Usually the broad outlines of the
project come to me fairly quickly; I don't get
bogged down in detail. Sometimes my creative
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
thoughts come to me as if in a dream. My
plans for the Mosque in Algiers which
unfortunately has not yet been started owing
to lack of funds actually came to me in my
sleep. I imagined it amid the sea, sparkling
with beauty. As soon as I awoke, I began to
draw it. I conceived the theatre in Brasilia
during the three days of Carnival. After I had
roughed out some sketches early on the fourth
day, Ash Wednesday, the project was ready.
I usually draw oh a very small scale
something which always seems to surprise my
fellow-architects and then I write an explan¬
atory text in the clearest and simplest possible
terms. I don't like looking up complicated
terminology in the dictionary. When we were
building Brasilia, each time President Jusce-
lino Kubitschek read my notes he was imme¬
diately able to grasp the thrust of my ideas.
Of course, I consult my engineer to see if my
project is suited to the terrain, the climate and
the budget, so as to be able to make any
modifications that might be needed. But that
is a purely technical matter, a question of
detail. As I am not an engineer or a specialist
in reinforced concrete, it is not my job to
resolve problems of stress or the resistance of
the materials employed. The main thing is for
the concept to be there.
What is your current conception of archi¬
tecture? Has it evolved since Brasilia?
The new technology now available would
perhaps have made it possible to have
constructed the buildings of the Square of
Three Powers in a different way. But I'm not
absolutely certain. Such modifications as I
might make today would not necessarily be
substantial ones.
Baudelaire once wrote that the unexpected
and the irregular, surprise and astonishment
are an essential aspect of beauty. I think he was
right. An architectural work must be beautiful,
light, different. I have always rebelled against
predetermined rules, didactic constraints and
right angles, which are a rigid, man-made
imposition. When that marvellous architect Le
Corbusier, the master par excellence of my
generation, walked up the ramp to the
National Congress building, he uttered these
words which I have never forgotten: "There is
a spirit of invention here."
Imagination is the starting-point in archi¬
tecture. From the time of the building of
Pampulha, on the outskirts of Belo Hori¬
zonte, in the early 1940s, I wanted to do
something different. I had the good fortune to
meet Juscelino Kubitschek, a remarkable man
full of drive and enthusiasm, who was Mayor
of Belo Horizonte at the time. Despite our
political differences, we soon became friends.
He gave me complete creative freedom and
this allowed me room to express myself. An
opportunity such as this is very rare in the life
of an architect. I have often been attacked
because I have questioned all the traditional
classicist and rationalist dogmas, but I have
remained indifferent to these criticisms.
When you speak of imagination, what
exactly do you mean? Do you consider your
style ofarchitecture to be withoutprecedent?
People may not like the monuments and
palatial buildings I constructed at Brasilia, but
no one can say that they have ever seen any¬
thing like them before. Some attempts have
been made to imitate the Presidential Palace,
the Alvorada, and I am flattered, but I don't
think imitation should play any part in archi¬
tecture, with the exception, perhaps, of hous¬
ing projects. We have to outdo ourselves, to
break free from the straitjackets in which we
are confined and give free rein to our in¬
ventiveness. Heidegger said that reason was
the enemy of thought, and therefore of imagi¬
nation. Beauty in architecture demands
freedom, and even more, perhaps, the element
of surprise.
Right angles separate and divide. Person¬
ally, I have always loved curves, which are an
essential feature of the natural world. It is not
easy to draw curves, to give them the sponta¬
neity they demand and then to organize them
in space in such a way as to achieve the visual
architectural effect that one is looking for.
Like Matisse, I maintain that my curves are
not gratuitous; they have a meaning. At one
point, even Le Corbusier, who had proclaimed
the virtues of right angles, began to despise
them. In the end he admitted that we were
right. One day he said to me: "What you do is
baroque, but you do it very well. You have the
mountains of Rio in your eyes."
You refer constantly to Le Corbusier. How
well didyou know him personally?
I was working as a member of Lucio
Costa's team when Costa was Director of the
School of Fine Arts in Rio de Janeiro. One
day, I think it was in 1936, he asked me to
accompany him to the airport to meet Le
Corbusier. You can imagine what a thrill this
was for a young architect. Everyone of my
generation in Brazil felt boundless admiration
for this man from the old continent, highly
cultivated and full of new ideas. Our architec¬
ture was strictly classical and lacked origi¬
nality. With his wisdom and experience Le
Corbusier turned everything upside down.
I was barely twenty-nine years old when
he produced his design for the Ministry of
Education and Public Health in Rio de
Janeiro. I already felt that I would be no
The Ministry of
Foreign Affairs, Brasilia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ordinary architect. I had had a gift for drawing
from the age of seven and my mother kept all
the drawings I had made at school. When Le
Corbusier's plans came into my hands, I made
a few alterations to them, for my own per¬
sonal pleasurefor instance I increased the
depth of the piles from four metres to ten.
This was a piece of teamwork under Le Cor¬
busier's direction, and the final plans took ev¬
erybody's suggestions into account. We sent
them to Le Corbusier for his approval and he
had them published in an architectural maga¬
zine with his own drawing of the building.
It is often said that you believe that an
architect should work alone, without calling
on outside collaborators. Yet your projects
seem to prove the contrary. At Pampulha, for
example, you called in the great Brazilian
painter Candido Portinari.
I have always said that it is for the architect
to choose the painters or sculptors who will
embellish his work. That is what I have done.
When I imagine an empty space, a room, or an
amphitheatre, I always know in advance
whether I shall furnish it with a granite wall,
tapestries or paintings. Architecture is a whole
which demands a symbiosis between the
structure and its decoration. When I built the
headquarters of the French Communist Party,
in Paris, which is one of my favourite works,
Jacques Duelos asked me: "Oscar, I have an
old desk of which I am very fond. It has his¬
toric associations. Can I put it in my office?" I
greatly appreciated his respect for my work as
an architect. Such respect is not always shown.
I thought that the seats that were put in the
nave of the Cathedral of Brasilia were really
dreadful. The last time I saw Jack Lang, the
French Minister of Culture, he asked me: "Are
those chairs still there?"
Why was your design for the cathedral of
Brasilia so totally different from conventional
church design? Why did you have a dark
entrance-way and a nave flooded with light?
The contrast is really striking.
I did not want it to be a place of penitence.
I am not myself a believer, but I tried to put
myself in the shoes of a Christian. Worship¬
pers enter the cathedral down a ramp, a dark,
underground passage, before emerging inside
the crown-shaped, translucent nave of
concrete and glass. To enhance the visual effect
and soften the impact of the Sun's rays, I
visualized stained-glass panels designed in
such a way as not to block out the view of the
sky. Marianne Peretti's work on these panels
was admirable. Lying flat on the ground in a
most uncomfortable position, she drew the
sixteen stained-glass panels, each the size of a
Left, inside the
cathedral of Brasilia.
Opposite page,
the cathedral seen
from outside with,
in foreground,
statues of the four
Evangelists by
Alfredo Ceschiatti.
basketball court. Unlike the Louvre Pyramid
in Paris, the nave of the cathedral opens out
into space. The first time he saw it, the papal
Nuncio said to the Bishop of Brasilia: "The
architect who created this masterpiece must be
a saint to have achieved so close a communion
between the Earth and God." As you can im¬
agine, I was very touched by these words and
I am still moved when I recall them.
I You cannot deny that you are more inter¬
ested in monumental architecture than you
are in designing low-cost housing. Doesn't
this indicate a degree ofconflict between your
political commitment and your work as an
architect?
I could have earned a lot of money if had
let myself be tempted into undertaking pater¬
nalistic operations or indulging in property
speculation. But that is not in my nature. I am
not motivated by profit. I worked on the
monumental buildings of Brasilia as a salaried
civil servant, receiving no commission or
under-the-table payments. In this way I felt
free and at ease with my work. However, I
did design some residential tower blocks in
the new Barra da Tijuca district of Rio de
Janeiro. I have also recently built some
schools, using a design which is beginning to
be generally adopted. Although these are pre¬
fabricated constructions, I tried to make the
most of a restricted budget.
Architecture, like any other profession, is
a way of earning a living. But when, as I did,
you have a patron of the stature of Juscelino
Kubitschek, you have to seize the opportu¬
nity to extend and fulfil yourself. I have
always refused to follow the mediocre, facile
path. Architecture must lead to beauty. The
problem is how to achieve that goal without
the risk of error. There have been occasions
when I have modified a project at the last
minute because it lacked perspective or as the
result of an acute observation by a friend. I
don't think I am an architect who is imper¬
vious to outside influence. I am prepared to
make any concession or to introduce any note
of fantasy that can enhance the plastic beauty
of an edifice.
Nevertheless, you are quite categorical
when you state that architecture can only be
beautiful if it is the fruit of invention or a
new departure.
I cannot work up any enthusiasm for
rationalist architecture, with its functional
limitations, its structural rigidity, its dogmas
and its theories. Reinforced concrete enables
architects with a sense of poetry to express
themselves. Architecture is the product of
dream and fantasy, curves and large areas of
open space. The architect must know how to
invent, while making use of all the technology
available. Why submit to rules and abstract
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
principles? When I was working on the
monuments of Brasilia, I deliberately did not
read a single, architectural magazine, for fear
of being influenced.
What I admire most in an architect is a
spirit of liberty. Gaudi, whose best-known
work is the Church of the Holy Family in
Barcelona, was an architect whose ideas were
confused. However, he had the courage to
break the established rules and this has given
him a special place in modern architecture,
even though the role played by Le Corbusier
was much more important.
When I designed the Ministry of Foreign
Affairs building in Brasilia, I did not, as some
writers have suggested, branch out into a new
form of architecture. I simply wanted to
prove that it was easy to create something,
using a form of architecture that was tech¬
nically irreproachable but also generous in
spirit, that would please everybody, whatever
their aesthetic background. It is not the build¬
ing that corresponds most closely to my own
temperament.
Ifyou had to devise a course for students of
architecture, on what principles would you
base it?
This year I have been asked to produce a
series of twelve lectures on video cassette for
the new university of Campos, a city of
400,000 inhabitants some 289 kilometres from
Rio de Janeiro. I am going to continue the
experiment that I began in Algeria in the
1960s, when I was building the university of
Constantine.
I think that the most important thing,
before students start out on an architectural
course, is to find out whether they have a gift
for the profession. The teachers must get to
know their students, sound them out, discover
their artistic leanings and their general back¬
ground knowledge, get talking to them so that
they can point out the hazards of the profes¬
sion. It is also essential that they know how to
draw, since this is basic to architecture. Stu¬
dents should spend six months in a school
learning to make technical and decorative
drawings; in this way they will develop a sense
of beauty. When this stage is completed, they
should be attached to a major architectural
office where they will learn to study a city
from both an architectural and an urban plan¬
ning point of view. They should be surrounded
by people with technical know-how experts
in concrete, air-conditioning, water, and so on.
Then, for a period of three years, they should
follow, on site, the construction of a town or
city, or an urban district, from start to finish.
Then all they would have to do would be to
learn how to write a clear, concise explanatory
report on a project. During my own profes¬
sional life I have often found that it has been
what I wrote rather than what I drew that won
approval for a project. Very few non-profes¬
sionals are capable of understanding an archi¬
tectural drawing.
Brasilia made you world famous, but you
have never lived there. Why not?
I did, in fact, live there for three years, the
time it took to execute my projects. At that
time, Brasilia was the end of the world. To
visit Rio de Janeiro or Sâo Paulo meant a
thousand-kilometre journey along muddy
roads. I lived in a small room with a bed, a
table, two chairs and a cupboard. I had a few
friends with me, not all of whom were archi¬
tects. There were two journalists, a football-
player and a poet. At night, for relaxation, we
used to strum away on our guitars and sing.
We never talked about work. This is my idea
of a convivial life. With the workmen with
whom we rubbed shoulders, the prostitutes
from their wooden huts and the dogs that
barked all day long, we all formed one huge
family. There was a real frontier atmosphere.
We had the feeling that the world was about
to change. For the thousands of workers who
came from every corner of Brazil, but mainly
from the north-east, Brasilia spelled hope.
The day in April 1960 when the new
capital was inaugurated, in the presence of the
President of the Republic and other authori¬
ties and personalities, everything changed.
The workers found themselves even poorer
than they had been before. That was the end
of our illusions. As soon as my work was fin¬
ished, I left. Never again have I experienced
the same fraternal atmosphere.
Today, some people criticize Brasilia as
cold, impersonal, inhuman, empty. But they
do not know Brasilia. Ask those who live
there with their families, ask their children.
They like it. They are far from the bustle of
the great urban agglomerations. There they
can enjoy open spaces and tree-lined avenues.
The light from the sky seems to bring with it
kindlier ways of living. Lucio Costa's genius
has made the new capital a model of urban
planning. As far as I am concerned, I am
nappy to have been the originator of the prin¬
cipal landmarks of the city. It is not our fault
if Brasilia has fallen victim to the injustices of
the capitalist society.
You might well repeat your question and
ask: "Why don't you five there, since the city
is built in your image." My reply would be a
simple one. I was born in Rio de Janeiro,
beside the sea, at the foot of mountains
covered in tropical vegetation. I have always
lived there. I know that this city is becoming
impossible to live in, with its six million in¬
habitants, its wretched shanty-towns, its vio¬
lence, its disorder, its polluted beaches and the
frenzied activity of daily life. But this is what
I am used to. How can you expect me to
adapt to anything else? I love Brasilia, but at
Rio de Janeiro I am at home. O
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
In praise
of tolerance
The period between the eighteenth-cen¬
tury Enlightenment and the Second World
War was by and large in Europe at
least one of optimism. There was a feel¬
ing that progress in science and education
would gradually make people aware of
their civic and moral responsibilities, both
in their national communities and in the
world at large. Those hopes were dashed
when the whole of humanity became
engulfed in the most devastating war in
history a war triggered by an ideology of
exclusion and intolerance that emerged in
one of Europe's most advanced and cul¬
tured nations. Optimism retreated and
gave way to a far more sceptical, circum¬
spect and vigilant attitude.
The creation in 1946, in the aftermath
of that war, of an organization such as
UNESCO, dedicated to the construction of
lasting peace through education, science
and culture, was in part a reflection of this
new concern. The tensions between
groups, nations and regions in the last
forty-six years have amply demonstrated
how farsighted UNESCO's founding fathers
were. Peace and understanding between
peoples are by no means the inevitable
outcome of progress in the various spheres
of human activity. No society can be safe
from the temptation to practise exclusion
and intolerance unless it shows constant
determination and vigilance.
Even societies which at certain points
in their history may have been open-
minded and receptive to others are not
immune to the risk of lapsing into rigid
intolerance. The past has shown only too
often that no society, whatever its system
of values, can claim to be intrinsically
endowed with the virtue of tolerance;
conversely, no society can be accused of
being permanently intolerant.
Doubtless human beings feel the need
of firm convictions. But when required, as
they are today, to live in ever closer
contact, they should beware lest their
convictions lead to bigotry. They must
realize that, while they are all equal in
dignity, they possess different talents and
convictions, and that this difference is a
source of enrichment for every one of
them, and for civilization. Provided, that
is, that everyone accepts a nucleus of uni¬
versal values.
The challenge facing us both now and
in the future is to accept that each of the
five and a half billion human beings living
on the planet today can have his or her
own ideas and preferences, and, without
denying those ideas and preferences, can
admit that those of others are just as
worthy of respect. It is by relentlessly
striving to practise what the British philo¬
sopher Bernard Williams calls this "awk¬
ward virtue" that we shall really begin to
work for peace.
Ehsan Naraghi
Consultant for this issue
EHSAN NARAGHI,
founder of the Teheran
Institute of Social Research
and currently an adviser
to Unesco, is an Iranian
sociologist and historian.
His published works
include L'Orient et la crise
de L'Occident (Paris, 1977)
and Des palais du chah
aux prisons de la révolution
(Paris, 1991).
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
An awkward virtue
by Bernard Williams
Peace-lover (1987), a
painted terracotta
sculpture by the Iraqi
artist Dhia Azzawi.
THE difficulty with tolerance is that it
seems to be at once necessary and
impossible. It is necessary where differ¬
ent groups have conflicting beliefs moral,
political or religious and realize that there is
no alternative to their living together; no
alternative, that is to say, except armed
conflict, which will not resolve their disagree¬
ments and will impose continuous suffering.
These are the circumstances in which tol¬
erance is necessary. Yet in those same circum¬
stances it may well seem impossible.
If violence and the breakdown of social
co-operation are threatened in these circum¬
stances, it is because people find others'
beliefs or ways of life deeply unacceptable. In
matters of religion, for instance (which, his¬
torically, was the first area in which the idea
of tolerance was used), the need for tolerance
arises because one of the groups, at least,
thinks that the other is blasphemously, disas¬
trously, obscenely wrong. The members of
one group may also think, very often, that the
leaders or elders of the other group are keep¬
ing the young, or perhaps the women, from
enlightenment and liberation. In this case,
they see it as not merely in their own group's
interest, but in the interest of some in the
other group, that the true religion (as they
believe it to be) should prevail. It is because
the disagreement goes this deep that the par¬
ties to it think that they cannot accept the
existence of each other. We need to tolerate
other people and their ways of life only in
situations that make it very difficult to do so.
Tolerance, we may say, is required only for
the intolerable. That is its basic problem.
We may think of tolerance as an attitude
that a more powerful group, or a majority,
may have (or may fail to have) towards a less
powerful group or a minority. In a country
where there are many Christians and few Mus¬
lims, there may be a question whether the
Christians tolerate the Muslims; the Muslims
do not get the choice, so to speak, whether to
tolerate the Christians or not. If the propor¬
tions of Christians and Muslims are reversed,
so will be the direction of tolerance. This is
how we usually think of tolerance, and it is
natural to do so, because discussions of tol¬
erance have often been discussions of what
laws should exist in particular, laws permit¬
ting or forbidding various kinds of religious
practice and the laws have been determined
by the attitudes of the more powerful group.
But more basically, tolerance is a matter of the
attitudes of any group to another, and does not
concern only the relations of the more
powerful to the less powerful. A group or a
creed can rightly be said to be "intolerant" if it
would like to suppress or drive out others,
even if, as a matter of fact, it has no power to
do so. The real problems of tolerance are to be
found at the level of human relations and of
the attitude of one way of life towards another;
it is not only a question of how the power of
the state is used.
If there is to be a question of tolerance, it is
necessary that there should be something to be
tolerated: there has to be some belief or prac¬
tice or way of life that one group may think
(however fanatically or unreasonably) to be
wrong, or mistaken, or undesirable. If one
group simply hates another, as with a clan ven¬
detta or cases of sheer racism, it is not really
tolerance that is needed: the people involved
need rather to lose their hatred, their prejudice,
or their implacable memories. If we are asking
people to be tolerant, we are asking for
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
something more complicated than this. They
will indeed have to lose something, their desire
to suppress or drive out the rival belief; but
they will also keep something, their commit¬
ment to their own beliefs, which is what gave
them that desire in the first place. There is a
tension here between one's own commitments,
and the acceptance that other people may have
other and perhaps quite distasteful commit¬
ments: the tension that is typical of tolerance,
and which makes it so difficult.
In practice, of course, there is often a very
thin or vague boundary between mere triba¬
lism or clan loyalty, and differences in outlook
or conviction. As Northern Ireland, for in¬
stance, constantly reminds us, an old enemy
may appear not merely as an enemy but as an
opponent in the struggle for truth and en¬
lightenment.
AN ACTIVE TENSION
Just because tolerance involves this tension
between commitment to one's own outlook
and acceptance of the other's, it is not, in its
true sense, the same as mere weariness or
indifference. After the European wars of reli¬
gion in the sixteenth and seventeenth centu¬
ries had raged for years, people began to
think that it must be better for the different
Christian churches to coexist. Various atti-
Brothers in faith
From the moment when worship illuminates the soul ofa
man, whatever his race, his soul takes on the lustre of the mystical
"diamond". Neither his colour nor his birth are ofany relevance.
Salif Tall Tierno-Bokar (1884-1948), Africa
Quotations relating
to the main theme of this
issue have been taken
from La tolérance, essai
d'anthologie, an anthology of
writings on tolerance
chosen and presented by
Zaghloul Morsy (Unesco,
latest edition 1988).
10
tudes went with this development. Some
people became sceptical about the distinctive
claims of any church, and began to think that
there was no truth, or at least no truth dis¬
coverable by human beings, about the validity
of one church's creed as opposed to another's.
Other people began to think that the
struggles had helped them to understand
God's purposes better: that He did not mind
how people worshipped, so long as they did
so in good faith within certain broad Chris¬
tian limits. (In more recent times, a similar
ecumenical spirit has extended beyond the
boundaries of Christianity.)
These two lines of thought in a certain
sense went in opposite directions. One of
them, the sceptical, claimed that there was less
to be known about God's designs than the
warring parties, each with its particular fanati¬
cism, had supposed. The other line of thought,
the broad church view, claimed to have a
better insight into God's designs than the war¬
ring parties had. But in their relation to the
battles of faith, the two lines of thought did
nevertheless end up in the same position, with
the idea that precise questions of Christian
belief did not matter as much as people had
supposed; that less was at stake. This leads to
tolerance as a matter of political practice, and
that is an extremely important result; but as an
attitude, it is less than tolerance. If you do not
care all that much what anyone believes, you
do not need the attitude of tolerance, any more
than you do with regard to other people's
tastes in food.
In many matters, attitudes that are more
tolerant in practice do arise for this reason, that
people cease to think that a certain kind of
behaviour is a matter for disapproval or nega¬
tive judgement at all. This is what is hap¬
pening, in many parts of the world, with
regard to kinds of sexual behaviour that were
previously discouraged and in some cases
legally punished. An extra-marital relationship
or a homosexual ménage may arouse no hostile
comment or reaction, as such things did in the
past. But once again, though this is tolerance as
a matter of practice, the attitude it relies on is
indifference rather than, strictly speaking, tole¬
rance. Indeed, if I and others in the neighbour¬
hood said that we were tolerating the homo¬
sexual relations of the couple next door, our
attitude would be thought to be less than
liberal.
There are no doubt many conflicts and
areas of intolerance for which the solution
should indeed be found in this direction in
the increase of indifference. Matters of sexual
and social behaviour which in smaller and
more traditional societies are of great public
concern will come to seem more a private
matter, raising in themselves no question of
right or wrong. The slide towards indifference
may also provide, as it did in Europe, the only
solution to some religious disputes. Not all
religions, of course, have any desire to convert,
let alone coerce, others. They no doubt have
some opinion or other (perhaps of the "broad
church" type) about the state of truth or error
of those who do not share their faith, but at
any rate they are content to leave those other
people alone. Other creeds, however, are less
willing to allow error, as they see it, to flour¬
ish, and it may be that with them there is no
solution except that which Europe discovered
(in religion, at least, if not in politics) a
decline in enthusiasm. It is important that a
decline of enthusiasm does not take the form
of a movement's merely running out of steam.
As the various sects of Christianity discovered,
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Eloge de la liberté
(c. 1926), oil on canvas,
by the German-born
painter Max Ernst.
a religion may have its own resources for
rethinking its relations to others. One rele¬
vant idea, which had considerable influence
in Europe, is that an expansive religion really
wants people to believe in it, but it must rec¬
ognize that this is not a result that can be
achieved by force. The most that force can
achieve is acquiescence and outer conformity.
As Hegel said of the slave's master, the
fanatic is always disappointed: what he
wanted was acknowledgement, but all he can
get is conformity.
THE IDEAL OF AUTONOMY
However, neither a decline in enthusiasm nor a
retreat into private taste can solve all problems.
If everything becomes a matter of private
judgement or taste, people lose a sense of social
identity and of belonging to a community
whose interests reach beyond their own. To
some degree, it is possible for people to belong
to communities bound together by shared
convictions religious convictions, for in¬
stance and tolerance be sustained by a dis¬
tinction between those communities and the
state. The state is not identified with any set of
such beliefs, and does not enforce any of them;
equally, it does not allow any of the groups to
impose its beliefs on the others, though each of
them may of course advocate what it believes.
In the United States, for instance, there is a vir¬
tually universal consensus that supports the
Constitution in allowing no law that enforces
or even encourages any particular religion.
There are many religious groups, and no doubt
many of them have deep convictions, but none 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
0 £#**.< W ¡fr>* ö ¿¿7
s * - X- 57/- o; *, JV rj * * il.m- ¿ ^
> © <£,Vi. "A
;Vf ; !ií4:^
12
4 <J"> i"
V^ -O-- i<£
ít , A ^ X »A > ,. I &
^¿9
A medley of signs
by the Tunisian painter
Gouider Triki
(gouache on paper).
BERNARD WILLIAMS,
Fellow of the British Academy,
has been White's Professor
of Moral Philosophy at
the University of Oxford since
1990. He was Provost of
King's College, Cambridge from
1979 to 1987, and Monroe
Deutsch Professor of Philoso¬
phy at the University of
California, Berkeley, from 1988
to 1990. His many published
works include Ethics and the
Limits of Philosophy (1985),
Utilitarianism and Beyond
(1982), Moral Luck, (1981,
ed with A.K. Sen) and
Descartes: The Project of
Pure Enquiry (1978).
of them wants the state to suppress others, or tions in groups or communities less than the
to allow any of them to suppress others. state, while the acceptance of diversity is
Many people have hoped that this can serve located in the structure of the state itself,
as a general model of the way in which a This is not to say that there is no need of
modern society can resolve the tensions of any shared beliefs. Clearly there must be a
tolerance. On the one hand, there are deeply shared belief in the system itself. The model of
held and differing convictions about moral or a society that is held together by a framework
religious matters, held by various groups of rights and an aspiration towards equal res-
within the society. On the other hand, there is
a supposedly impartial state, which affirms the
rights of every citizen to equal consideration,
including an equal right to form and express
his or her convictions. This is the model of
liberal pluralism. It can be seen as enacting
tolerance. It expresses tolerance's peculiar
combination of conviction and acceptance, by
finding a home for people's various convic-
pect, rather than by a shared body of more spe¬
cific substantive convictions, demands an ideal
of citizenship that will be adequate to bear such
a weight. The most impressive version of that
ideal is perhaps that offered by the tradition of
liberal philosophy flowing from Kant, which
identifies the dignity of the human being with
autonomy. A free person is one who makes his
or her own life and determines his or her own
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
convictions, and power must be used to make
this possible, not to frustrate it by imposing a
given set of convictions.
This is not a purely negative or sceptical
ideal. If it were, it could not even hope to have
the power to bind together into one society
people with strongly differing convictions. Nor
could it provide the motive power that all tol¬
erant societies need in order to fight, when
other means fail, the intolerant.
There must be, on any showing, limits to
the extent to which the liberal state can be
disengaged on matters of ethical disagreement.
There are some questions, such as that of abor¬
tion, on which the state will fail to be neutral
whatever it does. Its laws may draw distinc¬
tions between different circumstances of abor¬
tion, but in the end it cannot escape the fact
that some people will believe with the deepest
conviction that a certain class of acts should be
permitted, while other people will believe with
equal conviction that those acts should be for¬
bidden. No society can avoid collective and
substantive choices on matters of that kind, and
in that sense, on those issues, there are limits to
tolerance, even if people continue to respect
one another's opinions.
Some critics of liberalism claim that the
liberal pluralist state, as the supposed enact¬
ment of tolerance, does not really exist. What is
happening, they say, is that the state is subtly
enforcing one set of principles (roughly in
A dramatic scene
from the film version of
the famous American
musical IVesi Side Story
(1961), directed by
Robert Wise.
favour of so'cial co-operation and business effi¬
ciency) while the convictions that people pre¬
viously deeply held, on matters of religion or
sexual behaviour or the significance of cultural
experience, dwindle into private tastes. Other
critics will admit that the liberal pluralist state
does exist and to some extent succeeds in
expressing tolerance, but will insist that tol¬
erance is at best one political virtue, to be
weighed against other goods such as the satis¬
factions of a deeply experienced sense of com¬
munity, or of a society in which people's rights
(or the lack of them) are taken for granted,
rather than constantly staked out with fences of
litigation and explicit argument.
I suspect that only the future will show
whether liberal societies can preserve a variety
of strong convictions on important mat¬
ters. Perhaps it will show, too, how much it
matters to humanity if that variety, and so all
but a few convictions, fades away. Maybe tol¬
erance will prove to have been an interim
virtue, serving a period between a past when
no-one had heard of it, and a future in which
no-one will need it. For the present, however, it
is very obvious that there are still fanatical
convictions that are only too anxious to insu¬
late themselves against criticism; and there are
many people whose rights can be asserted only
by unwelcome speech. It does not look as
though the time has come yet in which we can
do without the awkward virtue of tolerance.
Jfc. '" ">
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CA it
Vo&Bre, crKsafer ^aîbjî fynww)/
by Jean Lessay
Above and following
pages: sketches by the
Swiss painter and engraver
Jean Huber (1721-1786)
show Voltaire in a variety
of moods.
Below, Voltaire pledging
his support to the Calas
family, an engraving
by Pierre-Nolasque Bergeret
(1782-1863).
IN social terms a value, and in those who
practice it a virtue, tolerance nevertheless
seems to have been a new idea in the eigh¬
teenth century. This may not seem to square
with the usual stereotype of that period,
which in Europe was supposedly marked by
great sophistication in all the arts, lively intel¬
lectual curiosity and brilliant social life. But it
becomes less surprising when we recall that
the wars of religion were then still fresh in
everyone's memory, and that fanaticism, albeit
in retreat, was not yet dead.
Conversation in the salons was unfettered,
but in France many books were forbidden,
seized and destroyed. Some unconventional
opinions and behaviour were connived at, but
that is not to say that they were tolerated:
tolerating means accepting the existence of
that which is different. Many men tolerant by
instinct and conviction were to be found even
among princes and potentates, but that did not
stop fanaticism from rearing its head under
cover of the institutions. Exclusion and perse¬
cution stemmed partly from the automatic
enforcement of laws, even those privately
regarded as outdated, and partly from the
demands of a section of public opinion which
used minorities as scapegoats for its own frus¬
trations and its taste for violence.
The word tolerance was still viewed with
caution, mistrust and sometimes hostility.
Though the Encyclopaedists had already had a
14
JEAN LESSAY,
a French writer specializing in
the American Revolution,
published studies on Lafayette
(Paris, 1983), Washington
(Paris, 1985) and the Count of
Rivarol, a royalist in the age
of the French Revolution
(Paris, 1989). He wrote the
present article shortly before
his recent death.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
profound influence in educated circles, there
were still theologians ready to defend intol¬
erance in the most spectacular form it took
in France, namely the prohibition of Protes¬
tantism by the revocation of the Edict of
Nantes in 1685. The negative effects of this
measure were still deeply felt several decades
afterwards, both in the intellectual sphere (in
the form of a brain drain) and in the economy
(in the form of an exodus of skilled craftsmen
to work abroad).
The advent of tolerance, or rather its rec¬
ognition as a factor for civil peace and a safe¬
guard against injustice, was largely the work
of philosophers, from Pierre Bayle (a refugee
in Holland) to Diderot, d'Alembert, d'Hol¬
bach, Jean-Jacques Rousseau and especially
Voltaire, who was its real champion.
THE CALAS AFFAIR
From his earliest days as a playwright, Vol¬
taire (1694-1778) indirectly attacked the
scourge of fanaticism that he was to fight
throughout his life. Thus in 1728, in his epic
poem La Henriade, he praised King Henri IV
for setting out to be the wise, enlightened
monarch of all Frenchmen, whatever their
beliefs. The concept of tolerance he tackled
directly in his Lettres philosophiques (1734),
his Dictionnaire philosophique (1766) and his
Questions sur l'Encyclopédie (1772). Three,
years before his death, under the title Le cri du
sang innocent ("The cry of innocent blood"),
he was to petition Louis XVI to review the
trial of a victim of fanaticism whose cause he
made famous, the Chevalier de la Barre.'
His main contribution to this war of ideas,
however, is still his Traité sur la tolérance
(1763). The exceptional importance of this
text, apart from the cogency of its arguments,
lies in the fact that Voltaire's treatise, unlike
John Locke's Letter on Toleration (1690), to
which he pays tribute, is not simply a philoso¬
phical dissertation. Thought here stemmed
from action, from what we would nowadays
describe as the writer's "commitment". For
over a year Voltaire had been waging an unre¬
mitting campaign to secure the rehabilitation
of a fabric merchant from Toulouse, Jean
Calas, a Protestant falsely accused of mur¬
dering his son. Calas was sentenced to death,
and in 1762 was broken on the wheel after
refusing to confess under torture. Actually a
majority of the judges were out to gratify an
ignorant fanatical crowd, which accused Jean
Calas, without a shred of evidence, simply
because on the basis of hearsay it ascribed to
Protestants a duty to kill their children if they
intended to convert to Catholicism. This was
supposedly the situation of the unfortunate
son, Marc-Antoine Calas: in actual fact he
committed suicide.
Voltaire dissected out all the intricacies of
this iniquitous business, and stirred up France
and Europe. Though the press then existed
/» ¿Slnui^S
y
The stranger
Everyone who turneth aside the judgement of the stranger is as
though he turned aside the judgement of God.
The Babylonian Talmud. Treatise of Chagigah, 5a
only in an embryonic state (France had fewer
than twelve newspapers), it is no exaggeration
to speak of a media triumph; the role of the
media was played by salons, clubs, cafés and
private correspondence. The Calas affair to a
large extent foreshadowed the Dreyfus case at
the end of the nineteenth century: a nation
aroused by the decision of an ordinary
tribunal which was regarded as an injustice.
Voltaire won over all liberal-minded people
in France, even those in circles close to the
Court, in favour of a formal review of the ver¬
dict and the payment of compensation to the
innocent victim's family, and thus gained public
acceptance of three points: that judges can make
mistakes; when they do, they must unequivo¬
cally admit as much and take the consequences;
if a minority is not respected, offenders are
likely to be sought first among its ranks.
Though no one religion had a monopoly of
fanaticism, the ultimate in intolerance (poli¬
tical ideologies did not yet exist), after Louis
XIV's decision to deprive Protestants of all
their rights, including that of possessing a civic
status, Voltaire came to regard France as fer¬
tile ground for all the abuses of fanaticism.
1. Beheaded at Abbeville in
1766 for an "impious crime",
though no evidence of it
was ever adduced. 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
A page of Sebastian
Münster's Cosmographia
universalis (1544) illustrated
with a portrait of Erasmus.
The Cosmographia, which put
forward original ideas
about the Earth's physical
features, was censored
by the Inquisition.
Liber III 407
mcnclatu/áfcirns omuto
quoi ipfc nofti.i
Im. Augufti, anno* CM
fío ffrimo« natfljM. LX
\M I I I N
16
He recalled that between 1745 and 1762
eight Protestant pastors had been hanged for
preaching according to their faith, and hun¬
dreds of their followers sent to the hulks.
This situation, according to him, could not
arise in England, Germany or Holland, for in
those countries religious pluralism existed
and members of different faiths could "live as
brothers and contribute equally to the good
of society". Doubtless Voltaire painted a
somewhat idealized picture of what went on
in those countries as regards freedom of
belief, but he did so in order to condemn the
laws in France, where "abuse of the most
holy religion has produced a great crime [the
Calas affair]". Hence it is "important for the
human race to consider whether religion
should be charitable or barbaric."
A UNIVERSAL VALUE
AND VIRTUE
In order to denounce fanaticism, which runs
counter to the spirit of the Gospels, the
writer presented a brief survey of religious
customs in Europe and Asia since Antiquity.
According to Voltaire, neither the Greeks
nor the Romans persecuted individuals on
the grounds that their beliefs offended the
local deities. The Athenians even took tol¬
erance to the point of building an altar dedi¬
cated to foreign gods they were unac¬
quainted with; and the Romans very wisely
held the view that it was for the gods them¬
selves to worry about offences committed
against them. If Christians were martyred in
the empire, it was not on account of their
beliefs, but because they disturbed public
order.
Voltaire saw evidence of this desire to let
people believe what they wished even in the
Old Testament. Not greatly enamoured of
the Hebrews of the Bible, nor yet of the
ancient Egyptians, he nevertheless saw "rays
of universal tolerance" shining out through
the story of Moses's followers. The Emper¬
ors of China and Japan also tolerated a
variety of beliefs when this did not endanger
the state. "Go to India", he wrote," "or Persia,
or Tartary, and you will see there the same
tolerance and the same serenity."
He did not attack any religion, for
"wherever there is an established society, a
religion is necessary; the laws guard against
known crimes and religion against secret
ones." But religion, essentially benign itself,
is corrupted by superstition and tolerance.
"Superstition is to religion what astrology is
to astronomy the very foolish daughter of a
very wise mother."
To combat superstition and intolerance is
the task of reason, the reason that "daily
spreads in France, into the merchants' shops
and the noblemen's houses;" it is for reason
to demonstrate the inanity of ridiculous,
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
monstrous practices such as the Inquisi¬
tion whose very name, the Abbé Grégoire
was later to say, is an offence against the
Gospel forced or bought conversions, and
autos-da-fé.
The author of the Traité sur la tolérance
regarded the review of the Calas trial as a
victory for philosophy, and this can hardly
be denied. He says that all beliefs should
have an opportunity to express themselves
"It would be foolish to claim to bring all
men to think in the same way about meta¬
physics. It would be far easier to subjugate
the entire universe by force of arms than to
subjugate the minds of every dweller in a
single town." In his conception of tolerance
he goes further than John Locke, who in his
famous 1690 letter excluded papists and
atheists from it; but he still does not present
a materialist or atheist view. For him
atheism, far from being synonymous with
tolerance, can on the contrary drift into
fanaticism like any religion. "A rational
atheist who was fiery and powerful," he
wrote, "would be just as disastrous as a
bloodthirsty superstitious man."
Tolerance, the antithesis of fanaticism, is
respect for others in their difference from
oneself. Paul Valéry was surely right to say
that it "can only be conceived, and make its
way into law and customs, in an advanced
age, when people have gradually enriched
and enfeebled themselves by the interchange
of their differences."
For Voltaire, this value/virtue also
contains an element of gentleness and bene¬
volence, and he often uses the word "indul¬
gent" to mean tolerant. "What is needed to
be happy in the next life is to be just. To be
happy in this one, insofar as the poverty of
our nature permits, what is needed ... is to
be indulgent."
According to him, the fight against intol¬
erance requires recourse to irony and
humour, in order to bring out its grotesque
inconsistencies. Thus we need to demonstrate
the absurdity of condemning those whose
opinions differ from ours to punishment in
the next world, whilst having to maintain
courteous relations with these same people
for purposes of living together. "Fanaticism
is not merely horrible, it is absurd."
In 1787, twenty-four years after the
publication of the Traité sur la tolérance,
Louis XVI signed the Edict of Toleration,
which gave Protestants a civic status which at
last allowed them to get married, make wills
and inherit, like the rest of his subjects. This
was only a modest step forward, but in the
right direction. Voltaire had cleared the way.
His aim, however, was not merely to enable
a category of French citizens to be given
back the rights they had been unjustly
deprived of: he claimed tolerance as a uni¬
versal value. No people on Earth, no indivi¬
dual, should suffer for lack of it. His words
are uncompromising: "I say to you that we
must regard all men as our brothers. What, a
Turk my brother? A Chinaman my brother?
A Jew? A Siamese? Yes, without doubt: are
we not all children of the same Father, and
creatures of the same God? But these peoples
despise us, and call us idolators! Well, I shall
say to them that they are quite wrong."
Eleven years after the writer's death,
freedom of thought and expression, for
whose recognition he had battled so hard,
were on 26 August 1789 proclaimed to the
world by the National Constituent
Assembly in the Declaration of the Rights of
Man and of the Citizen. In Articles 10 and 11
of this Declaration, which claimed to be uni¬
versal, tolerance in the widest sense of the
term at last found its philosophical and legal
basis although the word itself was not used.
All that remained was for people to show
tolerance to their fellows in daily life. But
will this struggle ever be won?
T 11 A I T É
it> it
TOLERANCE.
Title page of the first edition
of Voltaire's celebrated work,
published in 1763.
Below, one of the last
thoughts written down by
Voltaire, a few months
before his death in 1778:
"I die worshipping God,
loving my friends, hating not
my enemies and detesting
superstition."
/ST*
¡ÉÊÊ _J
Í 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Gandhi
and the struggle
for non-violence
by Ramin Jahanbegloo
18
IT is impossible to discuss the subject of
tolerance today without referring to the
thought and action of Mohandas Karam-
chand Gandhi (1869-1948), known to the
world as Mahatma ("great soul"). Yet the
word tolerance appears only rarely in his
works even though his whole life proved him
to be a man of exemplary tolerance. This
paradox is an indication of the difficulty of the
concept.
According to Gandhi, to affirm one's tol¬
erance is to establish a hierarchy between
one's own position and that of others. "I do
not like the word tolerance", he wrote in a
letter to his followers in 1930 while he was
imprisoned at Yeravda Mandir, "but could not
think of a better one. Tolerance may imply a
gratuitous assumption of the inferiority of
other faiths to one's own, whereas ahimsa
[non-violence] teaches us to entertain the same
respect for the religious faiths of others as we
accord to our own, thus admitting the imper¬
fection of the latter. This admission will read¬
ily be made by a seeker of Truth, who follows
the law of love.
"If we had attained the full vision of truth,
we would no longer be mere seekers, but
would have become one with God, for Truth is
God. But being only seekers, we prosecute our
quest, and are conscious of our imperfection."
Here we touch on one of the basic prin¬
ciples of Gandhi's philosophy. We are in an
area of spiritual theory in which the very
concept of tolerance is situated, not in relation
to a given political or religious context, but in
relation to a belief in the liberty of human
conscience. Gandhi demands more than just
respect for another human being; he seeks to
encourage the quest for truth, whilst being
convinced that this quest is inseparable from
obedience to the law of love. Thus, for
Gandhi, it is impossible to evoke the concept
of tolerance without affirming the notion of
truth. This is a crucial point, but it is even
more important to understand that truth can
only be respected through the path of non¬
violence.
The terms "non-violence" and "truth" are so
closely allied as to be virtually interchangeable.
"Ahimsa and truth", wrote Gandhi, "are so
intertwined that it is practically impossible to
disentangle and separate them. They are like the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The champion of
non-violence towards
the end of his life, in the
midst of a crowd of
respectful admirers.
two sides of a coin, or rather a smooth un¬
stamped metallic disc. Who can say which side
is the obverse and which the reverse?
"Nevertheless, ahimsa is the means; Truth
is the end. Means to be means must always be
within our reach, and so ahimsa is our
supreme duty. If we take care of the means,
we are bound to reach the end sooner or later.
When once we have grasped this point, final
victory is beyond question."
THE SEED AND THE TREE
Gandhi does not seek to establish a rational
explanation of the world on the basis of the
notion of truth, or to favour a traditional line
of thought. "Truth resides in every human
heart", he declares, "and one has to search for
it there. . . . But no one has a right to coerce
others to act according to his own view of
truth." It is, therefore, impossible to separate
religious life from political life, as is shown by
the way in which Gandhi organized his
struggle both against British repression and
against the injustice done to the untouchables
by the Indian caste system. Following the
Socratic example, Gandhi bravely confronted
the spirit of tyranny and intolerance of his
contemporaries with no other weapons than
fasting and prayer. "The only tyrant I accept
is the 'still small voice' within me, And even
though I have to face the prospect of a 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
minority of one, I humbly believe I have the
courage to be in such a hopeless minority."
By acting on the basis of these principles,
the Mahatma rid himself of all political reser¬
vations. On the contrary, the standpoint he
adopted aimed to ensure the victory of the
humanitarian approach over the political
approach, which seeks to put ideological
values before the values of the community.
His unwavering concern for truth and for the
equality of all citizens led him to revolt against
tricks and lies which he judged to be ignoble
means to noble ends. "Your belief that there is
no connection between the means and the
ends is a great mistake", he wrote. "Through
that mistake even men who have been con
sidered religious have committed grievous
crimes. Your reasoning is the same as saying
that we can get a rose through planting a
noxious weed. . . . The means may be likened
to a seed, the end to a tree; and there is just the
same inviolable connection between the means
and the end as there is between the seed and
the tree."
And he continued: "I am more concerned
with preventing the brutalization of human
nature than with the prevention of the suffer¬
ings of my own people. I know that people
who voluntarily undergo a course of suffering
raise themselves and the whole of humanity;
but I also know that people who become bru¬
talized in their desperate efforts to get victory
Gandhi and members of
his staff during the years
he spent as a lawyer In
South Africa (1893-1914).
20
RAMIN JAHANBEGLOO,
Iranian philosopher, is a spe¬
cialist on Mahatma Gandhi,
about whose political thinking
he is currently writing a book.
Among his published works
are Hegel and the French
Revolution and Conversations
with Isaiah Berlin (Peter
Halban, London 1991). As a
journalist, he is a frequent
contributor to the French
journals Esprit and Etudes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
over their opponents or to exploit weaker
nations or weaker men, not only drag down
themselves but mankind also."
In other words, the "political virtue" of
non-violence (which Gandhi sees as the ulti¬
mate virtue) stems from the fact that it unites
the members of the community by stressing
the role of the individual and by underlining
the decisive effect of that catharsis, or purifica¬
tion, that we must exercise upon our bodies
and our minds. Thus our capacity to play a
part in public affairs and to judge what is just
and what is unjust is entirely dependent upon
the individual and collective practice of non¬
violence. The finest lesson we can learn from
the philosophy of Gandhi is that, for the indi¬
vidual and the community, policies that make
power the criterion of truth can only lead to
disastrous consequences.
THE WORLDWIDE
INFLUENCE OF GANDHI
Fully aware of the dangers of political power
but also of the democratic duty he had to fulfil
in India, Gandhi declared: "If I seem to take
THE CONFESSION OF THE DECEASED
/ have not deprived the orphan ofhisproperty.
Ihave not done what the gods detest.
Ihave not calumniated a servant to his master.
Ihave not causedpain.
Ihave not made sufferingfor anyone. . . .
I have not made to weep.
I have not killed.
Ihave not commanded to kill.
The Book of the Dead, Ancient Egypt
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
1 . Literally, holding
on to truth. Name given by
Gandhi to the technique
of non-violent resistance as
practised by him and
under his guidance. Editor
Martin Luther King on his
return to the United States
after receiving the Nobel
Peace Prize (1964).
part in politics, it is only because politics
encircle us today like the coil of a snake from
which one cannot get out, no matter how
much one tries. I wish, therefore, to wrestle
with the snake. . . . My work will be finished,
if I succeed in carrying conviction to the
human family that every man or woman,
however weak in body, is the guardian of his
or her self-respect and liberty. This defence
avails, even though the whole world may be
against the individual résister."
The influence of Gandhi's teachings has
been felt throughout the world. Martin Luther
King's struggle for the rights of black Ameri¬
cans is a particularly notable example of it.
From the Montgomery bus boycott in 1955 to
the march on Washington in 1963, King
adopted Gandhi's non-violent techniques in
all his protest actions.
Martin Luther King described Gandhi's
influence in his book Strength to Love: "The
whole Gandhian concept of satyagraha1 was
profoundly significant for me. As I delved
deeper into the philosophy of Gandhi, my
scepticism concerning the power of love
gradually diminished,, and I came to see for
the first time that the Christian doctrine of
love, operating through the Gandhian
method of non-violence, is one of the most
potent weapons available to an oppressed
people in their struggle for freedom." He
added: "If humanity is to progress, Gandhi
is inescapable."
In 1968, the year of his death, these pro¬
phetic words of Martin Luther King were
borne out in the non-violent resistance of the
people of Czechoslovakia to the Soviet inva¬
sion. From then on, non-violence was insepa¬
rably linked to the various political and intel¬
lectual movements that for ten years bubbled
up in the Eastern countries. As Lech Walesa
declared in the 1980s, when he headed the
Polish Solidarity trade union whose strikes
brought about the downfall of the totalitarian
régime in his country: "The only way we can
oppose violence is to refuse to use it our¬
selves. . . . We have no other weapons than
truth and faith."
The people of the Philippines also adopted
the non-violent option in 1986 in their cam¬
paign of civil disobedience against dictatorial
rule. Since then, various forms of non-violent
action in Latin America, South Africa and the
Middle East have shown the topicality and the
relevance of the Gandhian heritage in the fight
for freedom and justice. O
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER JUNE 1992
EDITORIAL
Towards a new world ecological order?
Inthis month ofJune 1 992, the Earth is notquite as round as usual, for it has sprouted a summit
inRiodeJaneirowhichisbynowprobablyevenmorefamousthanthatdty'sotherpeak,theSugar-
loafMountain. From 3 to 14June, 166 headsofstate andgovernment and thousands of'delegates
willbe in Rio, gathered round tire bedsideofourailingplanet. We have treated theEarth verybadly.
Pollution has taken a heavy toll, what with the greenhouse effect and the ensuing risk ofrising
sea-levels, the hole in the ozone layer and nuclear hazards.
Prickingpeople's consciences is apainfulprocess. A heavyprice has to bepaidfor industrialgrowth
and theprovision ofmodern amenities. How are wegoingtofoot thebill? Will the main beneficia¬
ries oftheseforms ofprogress beprepared to make the necessarysacrifices ?And will those who have
hitherto been leftoutat last begin to reap the benefits or will they be penalizedforappearingon the
scene too late? Thepreparatory meetingfor theRio Summit, held inNew York, led to agreement on
the draftofan Earth Charterand on Agenda 21, definingsustainable developmentfor the coming
century, from theprotection offorests to the managementoftoxic wastes. Yet, even ifthere is a majo¬
rity infavourofthe broad principles, how will it be possible to reconcile all the points ofview?
WeneedonlytakeoneexampletMtissymptomaticofthesituation.ThepeoplelivingintheNorth
rightly denounce the damage caused by CFCs, chemical compounds widely used in refrigeration sys¬
tems, andaredemandingagain quite rightlyfrom a strictly environmentalstandpointthat they
should be banned. But what about the people in the South ? How will they react to the prospect of
beingdenied this modern amenityjust when they thought they would beabout to enjoy its benefits?
It has been estimated that it will cost$125 billion ayear to implement the resolutions setforth in
Agenda 21. Again, who is going tofoot the bill? Whether the Rio Summit turns out to be a displayof
psychological shadow-boxing, an unqualified success or simply a point ofdeparture, the fact
remains that it is thefirstofits kind. Itwillat least have had the virtue oftakingplace.
CAi
~T*sr
»
usual architecture of the
Unesco Courierhas
been modified, with the
introduction of a
new section entitled
Greenwatch which
appears in addition to the
main theme and the
regular features.
Greenwatch is a kind of
magazine within the
magazine. From its
position on the eight cen¬
tral pages it surveys,
as its title suggests, current
developments relating
to a world issue of
paramount importance
environment
and its survival. Its first
appearance coincides with
the Earth Summit being
held by the United Nations
in Rio de Janeiro, a
conference of crucial
importance for the planet.
Like the main body of
the magazine, Greenwatch
contains an interview
(in this case with a leading
specialist in ecology) and a
round-up of short news
items, as well as a longer
article on a major
environmental issue (the
depletion of the ozone
layer) and an extract from
a classic text evoking the
relationship between
humankind and nature
(the story of the flood from
the Gilgamesh Epic of
3,500 years ago)
.-X-,
r*?
'
*&r* ¿WZ*
'
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
World
PB
24
The United Nations Conference
on Environment and Develop¬
ment, which is being held this
month in Rio de Janeiro, will be
seeking to spell out, twenty years
after the Stockholm Conference,
the measures that need to be
taken to protect the Earth, the
only "living" planet of the solar
system. In addition to the plena¬
ry sessions to which Heads of
State have been invited, there will
be more than 250 meetings, semi¬
nars, workshops, lectures and
other events, which some 10,000
people are expected to attend.
One particularly important venue
will be the International Forum of
Non-governmental Organiza¬
tions, since the NGOs, with their
flexible working methods, are
eminently suited to be partners in
furthering the development pro¬
cess and ensuring the protection
of nature. Among the lecture
series that are being held, one will
set out to compare the methods
of sustainable natural resource
management used by indigenous
peoples.
BooJcshelf
ID1STÁII DESERTIFICATION
eserts occupyabout one fifth ofthe Earth's land surface, an area ofapproximately30 million square
kilometres. They are natural creations which have always existed, but today many ofthem are
spreading. This process of "desertification" results largely from human activities which cause
degradation ofthe land, reduce its fertility and make it unfit even for grazing. Desertification affects
certain regions in the developed countries ( USA, Canada, Australia ), but it is most acute in the
developing countries (in the Sahel, in South America and in the Mediterranean basin, as well as in
India, Pakistan and Mexico ). The problem has been aggravated in these areas by the pressures ofrapid
demographic growth.
Desertification, its causes, effects and possible ways ofcombating it are the subject ofa "Teaching
Module on Desertification", by C. Souchon and J.P. Deleage, published by Unesco and the United
Nations Environment Programme as No. 16 in their Environmental Education Series (available in
French and Spanish only). The example taken is the Sahel. The main themes covered include : The
interactions ofpeoples with their environment; water; soils and crops ; cattle-raising and grazing-land
management; energy, firewood and deforestation ; general problems ofplanning and management.
The booklet proposes a number ofpractical exercises to increase pupils' awareness ofthe state of
the environment in their region. In addition to educators and their pupils, the booklet also makes a
useful working tool for all those with an interest in the Sahel, such as technical assistance personnel
and members of non-governmental organizations. From it they can learn how to make a filter for
drinking water ora stove that makes more efficient use of fuel, how to combat soil erosion, and how
to cany out a reforestation project (which species oftree to select, etc). There is also a bibliography
and a list ofuseful addresses.
¡IE
DJi T
The luxuriant Dja Forest, in sou¬
thern Cameroon, figures on Unes¬
co's World Heritage List as a natural
site of outstanding beauty and is
also a part ofUnesco's Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) Programme net¬
work of Biosphere Reserves. A vir¬
tually intact example of a primary
tropical forest, Dja is extraordinari¬
ly rich in flora and fauna. A single
tree 30 to 40 metres high can be
home to as many as a thousand dif¬
ferent species of insect, and the
forest's streams and rivers support
some 120 species offish. Hippopo¬
tami, elephants and rare dwarf
chimpanzees are to be found in the
Dja Forest alongside gorillas, snakes
and a bird population so varied that
not all its species have yet been
identified and logged. The Dja
Forest is the site of a pilot project
whose objective is to help the
peoples who live there including
Pygmies to exploit the forest's
resources in a rational and sustain¬
able manner and to combat poach¬
ing, which is now reaching massive
proportions.
Two airlines, KLM and Garuda,
have decided that they will no long¬
er transport wild birds to the
United States. This follows bans
on this traffic imposed earlier by
Lufthansa and three US airlines.
In 1989, 87,300 wild birds were
loaded by these six airlines for
transportation to the United States.
On arrival, 2,430 of the birds were
found to be dead.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Ofthe 37 species ofwild felines, 22
are endangered to varying degrees,
according to the World Wide Fund
for Nature (formerly the World
Wildlife Fund). Agriculture, forest
exploitation and urbanization are
gradually depriving them ofthe spa¬
cious habitats they need. With this in
mind, the Indian Government and
the WWF have carried out a vast
joint campaign for the protection
of tigers as a result ofwhich India's
tiger population has more than dou¬
bled in fourteen years. Similar
results have been achieved with the
lynx which, despite protests from
sheep-raisers on whose flocks the
lynx preys, has been reintroduced in
several European countries.
The cost ofenvironmental protection
programmes in the United States is
expected to rise to over $ 185 billion by the
year 2000, according to projections made
by the US Environmental Protection
Agency (EPA). Over the past twentyyears
the cost of programmes for the protec¬
tion ofair, water and the tenestrial envi¬
ronment has almost quadrupled, rising
from $30 billion in 1972 to $1 15 billion in
1990 (equivalent to 2.1% ofGross Natio¬
nal Product). Ofthe overall cost the Fed¬
eral Government furnishes 11%, the
States 3.5%, the municipal authorities
22.5% and the private sector 63%.
A
Ul<
UAtr
TOT
LL
Since 1980 the city of Beijing has
been involved in a vast clean-up op¬
eration. At night, an impressive fleet
ofwater tankers invades the streets of
the city, crewed by municipal work¬
ers who wash the deserted avenues
and spray the trees that line them.
By day, other teams sweep the
streets, calmly indifferent to the tidal
wave of cyclists that swirls around
them. The clean-up campaign has
included drives to reduce the num¬
bers of domestic animals, birds and
flies, and the installation of a profu¬
sion of litter-bins and spittoons.
Today, with the help ofa $125-mil-
lion loan from the World Bank and
The thousand hills ofBurundi, once ravaged and laid bare by deforestation, are
green once more. Staff of the French Tropical Forest Technical Centre have suc¬
cessfully carried out a number ofconservation actions. They have taken measures
to protect the last remaining stretch ofprimary forest on the Nile /Zaire watershed,
which is the habitat of a flourishing chimpanzee population and a unique pool
ofgenetic diversity. The project beganwith a vast state reforestation programme,
the encouragement ofsmaller, community tree-planting schemes, and the plant¬
ing by private individuals ofsmall copses and anti-erosion hedges. It was not until
soil and forest degradation had reached an alarming level that the local popula¬
tion prepared to do battle against erosion and re-plant trees. A strong sense ofenvi¬
ronmental awareness was finally aroused and in the last ten years fiftymillion trees
( about one hundred trees per family) have been grown in Burundi.
the International Development Asso¬
ciation, the clean-up campaign has
taken on a new dimension. Work
now planned includes the construc¬
tion of a 32-kilometre pipeline to
feed an urban heating network in the
western sector of the city; the setting
up of a company to manage a new
sewerage system; and the construc¬
tion of a 72-hectare waste disposal
centre capable ofhandling 2,000 tons
ofwasteaday. m
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Dossier
iIT IOHR
m
26
The ozone layer, the tenuous
layer of gas that surrounds our
planet between twelve and
forty-five kilometres above our
heads, is being rapidly deplet¬
ed. Seasonally occurring holes
have appeared in it over the
Poles and, more recently, over
the temperate regions of the northern
hemisphere. The threat is a serious
one since the ozone layer acts as a fil¬
ter that traps almost all in-coming
ultraviolet radiation, which is harmful
to all living organisms humans, ani¬
mals and plants.
Even though the ozone layer is some
twenty-five kilometres thick, the
atmosphere in it is very tenuous and
the total amount ofozone, compared
with other atmospheric gases, is quite
small. If all of the ozone in a vertical
column reaching up through the
atmosphere were to be compressed
to sea-level pressure, it would form a
layer only a few millimetres thick.
Monitoring
and forecasting
Ozone (chemical formula O3), from
the Greek ozein, meaning "to smell",
consists of oxygen (O2) which under
the effect of solar radiation acquires a
free atom of oxygen. Ozone is highly
reactive to chlorine, hydrogen and
nitrogen. Of these chlorine is the most
The hole in the ozone layer was dis¬
covered in 1985 and became headline
news. How serious is the problem and
what is being done to solve it?
dangerous since it is very stable and
has a very long life. When they reach the
stratosphere, chlorine atoms attach
themselves to the ozone molecules and
destroy them, with consequent reper¬
cussions on the quality oflife on Earth.
Detailed study of the ozone layer
began comparatively recently, in 1930,
the earliest observations being made
by the English scientist Sydney Chap -
man. These initial observations were
taken up by the World Meteorologi¬
cal Organizatiop (WMO ) which estab¬
lished the Dobson Network consisting
of one hundred observation stations.
Since 1983, on the initiative ofWMO
and the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP), seven of these
stations have been entrusted with the
task of making long-term forecasts of
the likely evolution of our precious
shield.
In 1958, the researchers who per¬
manently monitor the ozone content
of the layer above the South Pole
began to observe certain seasonal
variations. From June there was a
slight reduction in ozone content
which reached a minimum in Octo¬
ber. In November there was a sudden
increase in the ozone content. These
fluctuations appeared to result from
the natural phenomena ofwind effects
and temperature change.
However, although the October
minimum remained constant until
1979, the total ozone content over the
Pole was steadily diminishing until, in
1 985, public opinion was finally roused
by reports ofa "hole" in the ozone layer
and observations were intensified.
The culprits responsible for the hole
had already been identified as being
supersonic aircraft, such as Concorde,
(although these have now been exo¬
nerated) and the notorious com¬
pounds known as chlorofluorocar-
bons, or CFCs. Synthesized in 1928 by
chemists working at General Motors in
the United States, CFCs are com¬
pounds ofatoms ofchlorine and fluo¬
rine. Having the advantage of being
non-flammable, non-toxic and non-
corrosive, they came into widespread
use in the 1950s. They are widely used
in refrigerators (15%), air-conditio¬
ners (20%) and to make the "bubbles"
in the foam plastic used, for example,
in car seats and as insulation in buil¬
dings (24%). They are also used as
propellants in aerosol sprays and as a
cleansing solvent in the computer
industry (24%).
In 1989 they represented a market
valued at over $1.5 billion and a labour
force of 1 .6 million. Of the twenty-five
countries producing CFCs, the United
States, France, the United Kingdom,
>
Japan and Germany account for three-
quarters of the total world production
of some 1.2 million tons.
The economic issues
These figures give some idea of the
importance of the economic interests
that are at stake in any decision to ban
the industrial use of CFCs. But, with
CFCs incriminated by scientists, the
question arose as to whether we were
prepared to take the risk of seeing an
increase in the number of cases of skin
cancer, eye ailments such as cataract,
or even a lowering of the human
immune defence system, all effects
that would follow further depletion of
the ozone layer. Not only humans
would be affected. So would repro¬
duction and growth ofplant-life; phy-
toplancton, the first link in the ocean
food chain and an element vital to the
survival of most marine species, would
not be able to survive in the first two
metres below the surface of the ocean.
UNEP decided that something had
to be done, and in March 1985 it orga¬
nized the Conference of Plenipoten¬
tiaries on the Global Convention for
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
the Protection of the Ozone Layer, the
Vienna Convention as it has come to be
called, which was adopted by twenty-
two countries. This was followed, in
1987, by the signing by twenty-four
industrialized countries of the Mon¬
treal Protocol on Substances that
their alarming statements ? In Novem¬
ber 1991 the United States and sixteen
European countries launched a vast
projectthe European Arctic Strato¬
spheric Ozone Experiment (EASOE).
Scientists from almost every European
country, as well as from Japan and the
million tons ofvolcanic gases into the
atmosphere.
Even if the entire world were to
agree today to halt all production and
use of CFCs, this would not provide
an immediate solution to the problem.
A single molecule of chlorine can des-
Map of the northern hemisphere
showing the distribution of
stratospheric ozone on 11 January
1992. Concentrations are
colour-coded from blue ( lowest ) to
red ( highest ). The map shows a
large loss of ozone over the tropics,
coinciding roughly with the
plume from the volcanic eruption of
Mt. Pinatubo (Philippines)
in June 1991.
Deplete the Ozone Layer, the first world
agreement aimed at halting the pro¬
duction of CFCs. As more evidence
emerged concerning the seriousness of
the threat, it became apparent that the
protocol was not stringent enough and,
year by year, its severity was increased
until in 1990 in London, seventy coun¬
tries agreed to stop all production of
CFCs by the year 2000. Clearly itwould
be extremely costly for the richer coun¬
tries to produce satisfactory substi¬
tutes that would meet the require¬
ments of efficiency, safety and
non-pollution; for the newly indus¬
trializing countries, however, the prob¬
lem would be even greater.
Two German chemists from the Max
Planck Institute, Frank Arnold and
Paul Cruzen, maintain that there has
always been a hole in the ozone layer
over the Antarctic. The French volca-
nologist Haroun Tazieff lays the blame
on the rays of the sun which, being
oblique at the Pole, bring an insuffi¬
cient amount ofultraviolet radiation to
reconstitute the missing ozone veil.
Have those who incriminate the
CFCs sufficient evidence to support
United States, participated. Funds for
the project were provided by various
. national research organizations and
the European Economic Community.
Observations previously made by
satellites of the US National Aeronau¬
tics Space Administration (NASA)
were completed by a series of land sta¬
tions, a ship, four aeroplanes, a num¬
ber of rockets and forty balloons each
carrying from 20 to 500 kilograms of
equipment. The objective was to mea¬
sure not only the ozone but also to
detect the presence ofCFCs, methane,
nitrogen dioxide and other substances.
The project ended in March 1992.
A new culprit
In December 1991, scientists work¬
ing on the project noted a depletion of
the ozone layer over the Arctic. In
February NASA announced that the
ozone layer was being depleted faster
than had generally been anticipated
and that it was also depleting over the
northern hemisphere. The finger was
pointed at another culprit, the Pina¬
tubo volcano in the Philippines, which
erupted in June 199 1 releasing twelve
troy from 10,000 to 100,000 molecules
of ozone. Furthermore, CFCs have a
lifespan of between 75 and 400 years
and they take ten years to reach the
ozone layer. In other words, what we
are experiencing now results from
CFCs emitted ten years ago.
Industrialists are now urgently
searching for substitute products.
Some, such as propane, are too dan¬
gerous because they are inflammable;
others, the HCFCs, might prove to be
toxic and to contribute to the green¬
house effect, i.e. to the process of glo¬
bal warming. Nevertheless, even if
there is no denying that the atmos¬
phere is at present in a state ofdistur¬
bance, nobody can say that the situa¬
tion will not right itself, whether in the
short or in the long term, especially if
we ourselves lend a hand.
FRANCEBEQUETTE, a Franco-Americanjournalistspecia¬
lizing in environmental questions, has been involved since
1985 in the WANAD-UNESCO trainingprogrammeforAfri¬
can news-agencyjournalists. She has played a leadingpart
in the preparation ofthis "Greenwatch" section.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Interview
28
Several theories have been advanced
to explain theformation of the Earth
and the appearance of life upon it.
Which of these theories do you sup¬
port?
- As far as environmental con¬
siderations are concerned, interest
focuses much more on questions
about the origins of life on our
planet. When did it first appear?
What processes were and are in¬
volved in biological evolution? To
what extent are we altering or dest¬
roying this tendency for species to
evolve ? For me these are the key
questions.
Life on Earth began about four
thousand million years ago ( give
or take a few hundred million
years), producing a rich heritage
of marine and terrestrial species.
Yet we are affecting the environ¬
ment to such a degree that we are
quite capable ofdestroying in a few
An environmentalist of international
reputation, Francesco di Castri
launched Unesco's Man and the Bio¬
sphere (MAB) Programme and is
currently co-ordinator ofall Unesco's
environment programmes. Published
here is thefirstpartofa longinterview.
hours the fruit of several million
years of evolution.
Such destruction is irreversible.
We can rebuild a city and even,
sometimes, an ancient monument,
but it is absolutely impossible for us
to replace an extinct species. How¬
ever, we should not succumb to
sentimental dreaming; the disap¬
pearance of a species is a perfectly
normal phenomenon in the evolu¬
tionary history of the biosphere.
Long before the spectacular extinc¬
tion of the dinosaurs, other species
had disappeared. Tomorrow, yet
others will disappear.
Environmental
education for
women in Burkina
Faso.
What is abnormal is not the
extinction of species but the rate
at which they are disappearing.
According to some experts, we may
be destroying as many as 50,000
species a year. Under normal cir¬
cumstances it would have taken
several thousand years for these
species to become extinct. Apart
from the abnormally high rate of
extinctions, the problem lies in the
fact that certain species that have a
key role to play are disappearing,
not for biological reasons, but
because ofhuman activities.
The objective is not, for some
abstract reason, to attempt to pre¬
serve all species, but to keep those
that have a vital role to play, in par¬
ticular those that are essential com¬
ponents in all biological areas
such as those species that
contribute to the functioning of
ecological systems and to the com¬
position of the atmosphere.
Which species doyou class as beingof
vital importance?
-To be able to answer your ques¬
tion with any precision, we would
need to know one of the great un¬
knowns the number of species
the biosphere holds. Estimates
range from around four million to
thirty or forty million (the most
likely figure ) and on up to as many
as one hundred million. At present
we know of the existence of only a
tiny proportion of species. As a
result, many species appear and
disappear without our even know¬
ing of their existence.
Today, the words ecology and eco¬
system are on everybody's lips. What
exactly do they mean ?
- Ecology is the study ofthe inter¬
actions of living organisms. This
includes the interaction of man
with the physical environment as
well as the interactions between
the different physical environments
themselves. It is not only the study
of the effects the environment has
on living organisms, but also of the
interactions of all the species. The
human species is one among many
others, but with this difference that
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
it has become capable of having a
determining influence on the evo¬
lution of other species. Not only
does it influence their numbers and
alter the conditions of their habi¬
tats, it can also, through biotech¬
nology, create new species. This
double power, biological and eco¬
logical, that one species can exer¬
cise on the evolution of the entire
biosphere is a factor unprecedent¬
ed in the history of the Earth.
The concept of an ecosystem is a
rather artificial and changing one.
The fact is that the definition of an
ecosystem varies according to the
approach adopted by the research¬
er who uses the term. For some
people, their gardens, or a culture of
microbes on a laboratory dish, are
ecosystems; for others ( more cor¬
rectly) a tropical forest is an eco¬
system. Others view the entire globe
as a single ecosystem. The one fea¬
ture common to all ecosystems,
however defined, is an internal flow
of energy, of genetic information
and, sometimes, of cultural in¬
fluences which pass from one of its
components to the others. Thus
ecosystems are complex systems
that exist at different levels of orga¬
nization, from small population
groups to the entire biosphere,
including the atmosphere.
Wliat were the great landmarks in
the awakeningofawareness abouteco¬
logical problems ?
- The basic concept of ecology
had already emerged in the nine¬
teenth century, but it was looked
upon primarily as an economic tool
for increasing the productivity of
ecosystems. "Agricultural ecology",
for example, aimed at increasing
crop yield by improvement of the
species cultivated. Thus the mean¬
ing given to the word ecology was
almost the opposite ofthat which it
has acquired today.
Silent Spring, a book by the
American author and biologist
Rachel Carson, was astonishingly
successful in arousing international
awareness of the dangers of envi¬
ronmental pollution. Among other
things, it revealed the drastic dimi¬
nution in the number of bird spe¬
cies caused by the use ofpesticides.
This awareness was accelerated
by increasing pollution of urban
air, which became almost un-
breathable in some cities, such as
Mexico City.
When did this "ecological awak¬
ening"occur?
-Rachel Carson's book was
published in 1962, but widespread
awareness can be dated from the
1970s. This decade marked a turn¬
ing-point, with the birth of the first
ecological movements and with
governments themselves beginning
to react, as witness the convening
by the United Nations of the first
major conference on the environ¬
ment, at Stockholm in 1972. This
trend has been accentuated by the
discovery ofholes in the ozone layer
and of the greenhouse effect. It
became apparent that humankind
was not only destroying species but
also the atmosphere that controls
the climate.
This enhanced awareness was
not restricted to the industrialized
Francesco di Castri is involved in a wide range of interna¬
tional activities related to the environment. President of the
Scientific Committee on Problems ofthe Environment ofthe
International Council ofScientific Unions ( ICSU ), President
ofthe International Union ofBiological Sciences ( IUBS ), and
a research director at the French National Centre of Scienti¬
fic Research (CNRS), he has written some 300 scientific articles
and is the author or co-author of a dozen or so books, the
most recent ofwhich, Landscape Boundaries. Consequences
forBioticDiversity and Ecological Flows, was published ear¬
lier this year. On 25 March 1992, the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme (UNEP) awarded him its Global 500
prize for actions and initiatives to promote the conservation
of the environment and sustainable development.
countries, but extended also to the
developing countries. The latter
became aware that their own natu¬
ral resources their forests and
regions bordering deserts were
being destroyed, not only by their
own demographic expansion but
also by anarchic forms of develop -
ment imposed from outside. The
necessity to sell commercial pro¬
ducts to the industrialized coun¬
tries in order to acquire foreign cur¬
rency has had serious effects on
their environment.
These two aspects of ecological
awareness that triggered in the
industrialized countries by pollu¬
tion and the imminent possibility of
climate change and that aroused
in the Third World by the disap¬
pearance of forests and the lower¬
ing of levels of public health are
today, I believe, merging to form a
new "planetary ecological aware¬
ness". It is now accepted that what
happens in the North also affects
what happens in the South, and
Vice versa. To be continued
Interview by Serafín García, journalist with Unesco's
Office ofPublic Information
School of
Rusty Fish, (1988).
Sculpture in
resin and oxidized
metal by Sandra
and Christian
Gamby. 8m x 1.5m.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Voices from the past
m
The myth of the Great Flood is almost universal. Its many versions relate how the world was engulfed and
humankind virtually annihilated by the deluge, which left only a few survivors belonging to the human
race and different animal and plant species. Human sinfulness is one of the main causes of the Flood,
but so too is the decrepitude of the world, for this is an ambivalent myth in which destruction paves the
way for regeneration.
On this page is the story of the Great Flood as it is related in the oldest extant epic in world history, the Gilgamesh
epic that was composed over 3,500 years ago in Mesopotamia.
Stunned shock overAdad's deeds overtook the heavens,
and turned to blackness all that had been light. . . .
All day long the South Wind blew. . . ,
blowingfast, submerging the mountain in water,
overwhelming the people like an attack.
No one could see hisfellow
they could not recognize each other in the torrent.
The gods werefrightened by the Flood,
and retreated, ascending to the heaven ofAmi.
The gods were cowering like dogs, crouchingby the outer wall.
Ishtar shrieked like a woman in childbirth,
Babylonian thesweet-voicedMistressofthe Gods wailed:
cylinder seal "The olden days have turned to clay,
depicting an because Isaid evil things in theAssembly ofthe Gods!
offering to a How couldlsay evil things in the Assembly ofthe Gods,
divinity. Syria, ordering a catastrophe to destroy my people?!
18th century Be. No sooner have Igiven birth to my dear people
than theyfill the sea like so manyfish !"
Thegods those oftheAnunnaki
the gods humblysat weeping, sobbing with grief,
their lips burning, parched with thirst.
Six days and seven nights
came the wind andflood, the stormflattening the land.
When the seventh day arrived, the storm was pounding
theflood was a war....
Thesea calmed, fell still, the whirlwind (and)flood stopped up.
I looked around all day longquiet had set in
and all the human beings had turned to clay!
The terrain was asflat as a roof.
¡opened a ventandfresh air (daylight ?)fell upon the side ofmy nose.
Ifell to my knees and sat weeping,
tears streaming down the side ofmy nose.
I looked aroundfor coastlines in the expanse ofthe sea,
and at twelve leagues there emerged a region (of land).
On Mt. Nimush the boat lodgedfirm,
Mt. Nimush held the boat, allowing no sway.
One day and a second Mt. Nimush held the boat, allowing no sway.
A third day, afourth, Mt. Nimush held the boat, allowing no sway.
Afifth day, a sixth, Mt. Nimush held the boat, allowing no sway.
When a seventh day arrived
Isentforth a dove and released it.
The dove went off, but came back to me.
no perch was visible so it circled back to me.
¡sentforth a swallow and released it.
The swallow went off, but came back to me;
no perch was visible so it circled back to me.
¡sentforth a raven and released it.
The raven went off, and saw the waters slither back.
It eats, it scratches, it bobs, but does not circle back to me.
Then Isent out everything in all directions and sacrificed (a sheep).
¡offered incense infront ofthe mountain-ziggurat.
Seven and seven cult vessels Iput in place,
and (into thefire) underneath (or: into theirbowls) ¡poured reeds,
cedarand myrtle.
The gods smelled the savour,
the gods smelled the sweet savour,
and collected likeflies over a (sheep) sacrifice.
Just then Beletili arrived.
She lifted up the largeflies (beads) which Ami had madefor his
enjoyment (1):
"You gods, as surelyasishall notforget this lapis lazuli around my neck
may ¡be mindful ofthese days, and neverforget them!
The gods may come to the incense offering,
butEnlil may not come to the incense offering,
because without considering he brought about theñood
and consigned my people to annihilation. "
The Epic ofGilgamesh, translated by Maureen Gallery Kovacs, Stanford
University Press© 1985, 1989.
CompanionsoftheSun
An extract from the Gilgamesh epic features in an anthologyof texts on the
relationship between humankind and the natural world which is to be
published ( in French ) by Unesco, Editions de la Découverte ( Paris ) and
the Fondation pour le progrès de l'Homme. Entitled Compagnons du
soleil ("Companions of the Sun"), the 500-page anthology has been pre¬
pared under the general editorship of the notedAfrican historian Joseph
Ki-Zerbo, ofBurkina Faso, in collaboration with Marie-Josèphe Beaud. The
idea for the anthology came from the Vézelay Group, an international panel
consisting of eight members, including Joseph Ki-Zerbo.
Joseph Ki-Zerbo describes the anthology as a collection of"the fundamental
or significant texts which, in the world's different cultures, testify to the rela¬
tions between man and nature" He adds that "the battle for the health of
nature will not only be won by recourse to political or legal procedures,
technical or fiscal remedies, or international agreements, however solemn,
but by an awakening ofsociety generated by innermotivations, which are
sustained by the powerful sources ofsymbolism, ethics and aesthetics. With
respect to nature, man must choose between symbiosis and suicide.'^
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Bkck Africa's open societies
by Iba Der Thiam
Painting on a wall
in Dakar depicting a
village meeting.
TOLERANCE has always held a pre¬
eminent position in the thought of many
African peoples. In West Africa, for
example, it is the fundamental principle on
which the entire social life of the Senegambian
region is built, governing the interaction be¬
tween individuals and ethnic groups as well as
international relations.
Nothing illustrates this better than the cen¬
tral place the concept of peace occupies in the
region's moral thinking. The Wolof saying,
"Ci Jaam la yeep xeej", which signifies that
peace bears innumerable promises, implies that
peace is the necessary precondition for social
stability, political equilibrium, economic pros¬
perity and moral and material progress.
Even before the experience of the slave
trade and colonial oppression, the aspiration
for peace was a deeply-felt need in a society
exposed for centuries of its long history to the
vicissitudes of wars fought in the name of
conquest or in defence of local aristocracies. It
has left its mark on the most anodyne details
of daily life. When two people meet, one says
as a greeting, "Are you at peace?" "Nothing
but peace," the other replies, as if the harmony
born of universal accord, whatever the philo¬
sophical, religious or moral starting-points or
choices of the people involved, could bring an
inner calm and sense of hope more valuable
than anything else life has to offer.
The same leitmotif of an aspiration for
peace and security reappears in the prayer
offered by each family to call down God's
blessings on its members and on all things. In
the words of one traditional Guiñean suppli¬
cation, "Let peace reign in the world! May the
pot and the calabash not fall out! Let the
beasts live in harmony! May every bad word
and unbecoming thought be rooted out and
packed off to the back of beyond, to the
depths of the virgin forest!"
As the principal element regulating rela¬
tions between people and between communi¬
ties, tolerance is the imperative that governs all
social life. In some African societies it means
refusing to mistrust other people and rejecting
both fear and preconceptions in dealing with
whatever is new, unknown, unusual or out of
the normal pattern.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
This ivory mask
with cowrie-shell eyes is
a product of the expressive
artistic tradition of the
Lega (or Balega) people of
the Congo.
32
IBA DER THIAM,
Senegalese historian, politi¬
cian and diplomat, is involved
in a wide range of activities
both in his own country
and internationally. A former
Minister of Education of
Senegal (1983-1988) and
member of Unesco's
Executive Board (1978-1983);
he is the author of a number
of books on history and
civics, including Histoire du
mouvement syndical africain
1790-1929 (Paris, 1991),
and of many articles. He is
also co-editor of the two
volumes of Unesco's History
of Mankind: Cultural
and Scientific Development,
covering the 19th and
20th centuries.
THE HUMAN DIMENSION
Professor' Cheikh Anta Diop suggested that
in the Cayor region of Senegal the election of
the king was a traditional perquisite of what
he called the "governing council". All the
social groups that made up the nation were
represented in this institution. The aim was
not merely to make the body representative
but also to encourage collégial participation
and friendly social relations in an atmosphere
of mutual tolerance and respect.
Although the diawerigne m'boul, the
officer presiding over the council, was always
chosen from among the geer or aristocracy,
the lamane diamatil, the bataloupe ndiob and
the badie gateigne, all of whom were gover¬
nors of important provinces as well as council
members, had to come from the gmegno, the
ranks of the people of caste, while the diawe¬
rigne boule represented the house-slaves.
For traditional societies of this sort,
humankind may be one in essence but it is
nonetheless diverse in its ways of living and
thinking and in the manner in which its
constituent groups come to terms with them¬
selves and other peoples. Consequently they
made the nitt or human being their principal
frame of reference. This human essence was
seen as a generic concept, independent of time
and place, the supreme embodiment of the
divine presence on Earth. Stripped of all
moral, philosophical or political connota¬
tions, it became a sublimated ideal to which
everyone owed consideration and deference.
It is in this light that the treatment of
strangers in some African societies must be
considered. Newcomers are welcomed with
kindliness and generosity, no matter what
language they speak or what their sex, age,
religion or social or political condition may
be, for they are human beings first and fore¬
most. As such, they have a right to food and
shelter. Their person, goods and health will
be protected, and they will be given a decent
burial if they die.
In some Wolof communities, it is quite
common for the head of a family to give up
his own house and bed, or that of his wives or
children, to strangers, without giving a
thought to his own state of health. Among
the Bassari, custom dictates that the tribal
chief may even graciously put a female com¬
panion at the newcomer's disposal, in the
hope that the possible seed sown by their
relationship may revivify and strengthen the
community.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Secret of Wisdom
T\oe Master said: "My doctrine amounts to one single thing
that encompasses everything". Tseng tseu replied: "Indeed". When
the Master had withdrawn, his disciples asked what he had
meant. Tseng tseu replied: "Ml our Master's wisdom lies inperfec¬
ting oneselfand in loving others like oneself".
Analects, Confucius (551?-479? BC), China
Following this logic, the differences be¬
tween peoples, far from being stressed as bar¬
riers separating humankind, are minimized to
such an extent that they finally lose much or
all of their meaning and their divisiveness,
and are blurred and blunted until they
become harmless. Integration of this sort
involves not a denial of the foreigner's iden¬
tity here I have in mind those insidious
processes of assimilation that are really more
like mutilation but a profound and freely
accepted awareness of the symbiotic comple¬
mentarity linking the individual to other
people. Unbreakable bonds are forged in this
fusing of essences.
RENEWING THE TRADITION
This was the state of mind in which Africa,
from the dawn of history, opened itself to
the outside world. From the time of Queen
Hatshepsut's expedition from her native
Egypt to the land of Punt in the years be¬
tween 1493 and 1490 BC until the nine¬
teenth-century explorers, there is no lack of
witnesses to the African spirit of tolerance
and unfailing hospitality.
It was as a result of the prevailing peace
that Habib ben Una'ida and al-Fazari, around
800 AD, were able to compile their chron¬
icles, the first to mention the existence of the
empire of Ghana; that Ibn Hawqal was free to
visit the lands south of the Sahara; that al-
Bakri, al-Idrisi, Yakut Ibn Said and al-Umari,
between the eleventh and the fourteenth cen¬
turies, could give us precious descriptions of
the kingdoms of the so-called Sudanic belt
from Senegal to the Nile; that Ibn Battuta
could visit Mali and Leo the African Tim¬
buktu. Free of dogmatism and sectarianism,
the spirit of tolerance encouraged dialogue
and the exchange of ideas.
The same phenomenon was at work on
the West African coast. Gomes Eanes
Zurara's chronicles of Guinea, and the travel
writings of Diogo Gomes, Duarte Pacheco
Pereira, Joâo de Barros and of the Venetian
La fermière en buste (1908),
oil on canvas by Picasso.
Ca'da Mosto all bear witness to the open-
mindedness of the peoples of Cayor, Baol and
Sine Saloum, whose humanity would also be
attested to by other Western visitors from the
seventeenth to the nineteenth centuries. Tol¬
erance extended to colour, language, religion
and ethnic and social origin as well as to sex
and philosophical or moral views. This
atmosphere enabled Christian missionaries to
carry out their work without risk wherever
traders had set up bases and colonizers had
raised their flags.
Despite long-held views to the contrary,
these were in effect open societies where
freedom and. justice reigned. Dare one say
that democracy and tolerance flourished there
until the slave trade and colonial conquest
and all that went with it native status, taxes,
military conscription, land seizure, forced
labour created an endemic state of violence
that corrupted social habits and ways of life
to the point at which they were no longer
recognizable.
So a precious heritage lies buried beneath
the still-smouldering ruins of colonial impe¬
rialism. Contemporary Africa must redis¬
cover it quickly, to create worlds of freedom,
peace and social harmony in which all its chil¬
dren can find fulfilment.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Islam: a conflict ofmodels
by Mohammed Arkoun
34
IN what sense can we speak of tolerance in
an Islamic context? The tolerance sought
after nowadays stems from the very situa¬
tion that down the centuries gave rise to the
intolerance of the traditional religious sys¬
tems, underpinned as they were by the appa¬
ratus of state power emperors, caliphs and
sultans, drawing their justification from reli¬
gious institutions.
In this respect Christianity and Islam are
very similar: their expansion as religions went
hand in hand with the establishment of
empires and kingdoms committed to a strict
definition of God's truth as the basis of
human laws. God intervenes in men's affairs
in different ways depending on their religion:
but power structures invariably derive their
justification from transcendent sacred
teachings whose orthodox versions are pur¬
veyed and sustained by what Max Weber
called "managers of the sacred".
Starting in the eighteenth century in
Europe, competition developed between two
historical models for the production and
reproduction of societies: one gave rise to
"Societies of the Book"; the other to secular
societies devoid of any theistic content and
relying for their legitimacy on universal suf¬
frage and democratic debate.
So the distinction is not, as commonly
stated, between religions such as Christianity,
Islam, Judaism and Buddhism, but between
functional religion-state solidarity and the
collapse of this solidarity in the model that
stemmed from the French Revolution and the
Enlightenment.
Now what becomes of the question of
tolerance if we look at it in the context of this
analysis?
Historically, first, the crucial break in the
eighteenth century constituted a watershed.
Before it, tolerance (in the sense of freedom
of religion and legal protection for basic
human and civic rights) was psychologically
and intellectually inconceivable in relation to
_Ji \- v t'
tvt* *
"<¿s
«£
¿fa. ¿JC/&> ¿¿hj¿>\^&p»~/^ :
\¿>$¿¡A
v .. y
'¿Jf¿ <rU*t>j h»*J¿/¿> IJSjj dy & '
Ï
hl
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
mutually exclusive theological systems
constructed by religious communities for
their own protection or perhaps their
expansion.
A PROTECTED AREA
A dogmatic theology claims for its commu¬
nity a monopoly of revealed truth, and hence
of the power that defends it. Islamic law was
less exclusivist than other systems: under it,
Christians and Jews enjoyed the famous
dhimmi (protected person) status. But this
was tolerance born of indifference, together
with humiliating measures designed to
emphasize the superiority of Islamic truth.
Judaeo-Islarhic and Christian-Islamic polemic
commonly uses the example of this dhimmi
status to stigmatize Islam's fundamental,
ever-active intolerance.
It is, however, anachronistic as well as
unfair to judge one of the Societies of the
Book in this way whilst sparing the others
any criticism, and to use the postulates of the
Enlightenment model to disqualify Islam
alone. On the Muslim side, one way of an¬
swering such accusations of intolerance
against Islam formulated on the basis of
Enlightenment logic would be to use verses
from the Qur'an chosen to bring out the idea
of tolerance. This would be equally anachro¬
nistic and manipulative, and I reject it: I know
very well that the traditional interpretation of
the verses most favourable to tolerance has
given way to the theological postulates of
God's truth placed under the vigilant protect¬
ion of theologian-jurists who confer on their
decisions a specially exalted ontological,
cognitive, legal and spiritual status.
Certainly the great texts of Islamic
thought helped, with others, to pave the way
to tolerance in its modern sense. I am think¬
ing of the writings of the mystics, the intellec¬
tual breakthroughs, the political protests, of
writers like Hasan al-Basri (d. 772), al-Jahiz
(d. 869), al-Kindi (d. 870), al-Tawhidi
Above, the constellation
of Aquarius. An illustration
from the Liber de stellis
fixarum (The Book of Fixed
Stars), a 13th-century
Latin translation of an Arabic
treatise. Opposite page,
detail of a 15th-century
Arabic commentary on the
Elements of Geometry by
Euclid, the mathematician
of Greek Antiquity.
(d. 1014) and al-Ma'arri (d. 1058). But all
these anticipations, intuitions and musings
form part of what anthologies since the days
of ancient Iran have called "the eternal
wisdom" (Javidan Khirad or al-hikma al-
khalida).
THE SYMBOLIC CAPITAL
What happened after the break?
Islam as a religion, Islamic thought and
Muslim society remained aloof from events.
While European societies underwent accele¬
rated change, planned and directed by a capi¬
talist mercantile bourgeoisie, the world of
Islam was subjected to the reverse process: it
grew feebler, its intellectual horizons and cul¬
tural activity contracted, and the tribal system
expanded as the central authority was 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
weakened. These developments helped the
establishment of the colonial empires, which
worsened the situation economically, politi¬
cally and culturally and led to the wars of
liberation following the Second World War.
This historical résumé, which deserves
to be amplified with detail, at least shows
that tolerance cannot be on the agenda in
societies which since the thirteenth century
have undergone a process whereby cultural
and ethnic groups became independent,
urban élites and popular masses became dif¬
ferentiated, and religion, language and cul¬
ture became homogenized in towns, villages
and regions. The Ottoman régime, and in
many respects the colonialists, fostered this
break-up of societies into particularist
groups; religion split into sects and fraterni¬
ties, power became hereditary, the economy
tended towards self-sufficiency, languages
became diversified into dialects, and culture
became confined to what the French socio¬
logist Pierre Bourdieu has called "the sym¬
bolic capital".1
These societies, fragmented into groups
isolated from each other, jealous of their
"identities" and often in revolt against the
government (especially if it was distant),
remained cut off from modernity until the
1950s. The colonial régimes certainly encour¬
aged the formation of socio-cultural enclaves,
in which the need to modernize institutions,
and ideas about society and intellectual life,
began to be felt. But it was not until the era of
political independence that nation-states
everywhere compelled separatist groups and
local independence movements to play a part
in "national reconstruction". This novel
socio-political driving force was very soon to
36
Tradition and Modernity,
a work by the Bahraini
painter Ahmed Baqer which
draws inspiration from
Arab life and festivities.
MOHAMMED ARKOUN,
Algerian-born scholar, is
Professor of the History of
Islamic Thought at the Univer¬
sity of Paris III (Sorbonne
Nouvelle) and Visiting Profes¬
sor at the University of
Amsterdam. He was formerly
Director of the Paris Institute
of Arab and Islamic Studies
and has lectured at many
of the world's academic and
cultural centres. Among his
published works are L'Islam,
religion et société (Paris,
1981), La pensée arabe
(Paris, 1985) and Ouvertures
sur l'Islam (Paris, 1989).
Many and one
O mankind! We created
you from a singlepair ofa male
and a female and made you into
nations and tribes that ye may
know each other.
The Qur'an, surah xlix,
The apartments (v. 13)
make tolerance as topical and as urgent as it
was in the Christian societies of eighteenth-
century Europe.
Thus we see that tolerance is not a cardinal
virtue dictated by the great religious and phi¬
losophical teachings, but represents rather a
response to social and political demand at
times of great ideological turmoil a ques¬
tioning of the "values" peculiar to the various
social groups that make up a nation.
The practice of tolerance everywhere calls
for an effort of individual will, plus political
will on the part of the state. We can say that
these two wills have so far by and large been
lacking in many Muslim countries, but this is
attributable to historical, sociological a'nd
anthropological factors rather than to the
silence of religious texts or the inadequacy of
Islamic thought.
The Encyclopaedists' audience consisted
of concerned citizens, ready to translate the
ideas of the Enlightenment into political and
economic terms. A similar audience existed
for brief periods in the history of Islamic
society: in the ninth and tenth centuries a
mercantile middle class in the big towns pro¬
vided scope for the development of an
Arabic-speaking humanism open to the
teachings of the "eternal wisdom", in which
Islam was but one of several components.2
A similar situation prevailed in several
societies between 1850 and 1940: this was the
so-called Renaissance (nahdha) period, espe¬
cially in the Arab world. An intelligentsia
open to the teachings of the Enlightenment
sought to promote liberal democracy, espe¬
cially after the abolition of the Ottoman sul¬
tanate; but the narrow social base of this
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
movement, coupled with the political vigi¬
lance of the colonial powers, prevented any
real development of modernity. Since the
1960s, population growth and the spread of
populist ideologies, together with large-scale
uprooting of settled populations and harsh
supervision in one-party states, have tipped
Muslim societies towards violent confronta¬
tions, growing protest movements and a
sense of collective frustration all of which
tend to foster the development of intransi¬
gent doctrines.
In this brief analysis I aim to suggest
and this will be my conclusion that in
contemporary societies the tolerance-intol¬
erance question takes on dimensions and
meanings which make it impossible to res¬
trict oneself to the isolated case of this or that
society, mode of thought or religion. What is
so inappropriately called "Islam" cannot be
removed from the context of the world forces
that govern the destiny of all peoples. When
journalists, political scientists and sociolo¬
gists use terms like fanaticism, xenophobia,
"0 mankind ! We created
you from a single pair of a
male and a female. . . ."
(The Qur'an, Surah XLIX, The
Apartments, v 13).
Calligraphy by Namane Zakri.
violence and intolerance in relation to pre¬
sent-day Islamic movements, these terms
need to be understood in the light of the
internal and external causes that give rise to
these manifestations.
This is not to minimize the climate of
intolerance that has grown up in some
Muslim societies in connection with what is
called the "awakening of Islam". If I stress
the magnitude of the political and economic
pressures still being exerted on these socie¬
ties, and argue that the changing importance
of religions needs to be appraised in the light
of the historical conditions and social set¬
tings in which they carry out their vocations,
it is in order to reinforce a tolerant approach
to the phenomenon of religion in general,
and hence to suggest a more understanding
attitude towards the expressions of contem¬
porary Islam.
1 . Pierre Bourdieu, Le sens pratique, Editions de Minuit,
Paris, 1980.
2. Mohammed Arkoun, L'humanisme arabe au IVe/Xe
siècle. Vrin publishers, Paris, 1982.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Against intolerance
by Edgard Pisani
38
EDGARD PISANI,
French politician, has been
his country's Minister of
Agriculture (1961-1966) and
Minister of Industrial
Development (1966-1967).
He was elected to the
European Parliament in 1979
and later carried out special
missions for the President of
the French Republic. Founder
and political director of
the periodical L'Evénement
européen, he has been
President of France's Institute
of the Arab World since
1988. He has published a
number of books, including
Pour l'Afrique (Paris, 1988),
Persiste et signe (Paris, 1992),
and Health and Social Welfare
(Pergamon Press, Oxford).
THE world vacillates between indifference
and intolerance. Fellow feeling seems to
be a thing of the past.
Indifference is a serious matter. In the big
cities, in Western societies, wherever small
human communities are withering away or
have already disappeared, the individual is iso¬
lated, and nobody communicates any more.
We no longer see or listen to each other. Do
other people exist for us or we for them? Our
encounters with them are random, self-centred
affairs and when we do speak we sense only the
painful vibrations of a voice without echo.
Little is said about this malady, although it
is magnified by the media, with their tendency
to turn everything into a happening. Yet it is a
destructive sickness that leaves us alone in the
crowd, alone in our homes, alone in the world,
alone in a void that our lost sense of the sacred
is no longer there to fill.
Intolerance is just as serious. It is not simply
the lack of a sense of solidarity with other
people: it is the rejection of others for what
they are, for what they do, for what they think
and, eventually, simply because they exist.
We are not talking here of the intolerance
of youth, that potent cocktail of intransigence
and revolt to which the French novelist Roger
Martin du Gard was referring when he wrote:
"I quite like the intolerance of youth. It is a
good thing for an adolescent to be systemati¬
cally in revolt against everything." We are
speaking rather of an urge that can soon
degenerate from irritation to murder.
Intolerance is probably no more wide¬
spread today than it was in earlier times. It has
always existed throughout history. It may be
akin to that instinct for possession and secu¬
rity that impels an animal to defend its terri¬
tory against intrusion. Going beyond the
spirit of conquest and the desire to acquire
possessions, it leads to domination and exter¬
mination. Intolerance is a refusal to admit the
existence of those who do not share the same
beliefs as oneself.
Once the others have been exterminated,
the intolerant man turns on his own brother,
accusing him of being lukewarm, divisive or
deviationist. From the Inquisition to the Stali¬
nist régime, the passion to convince gave way
to an urge to dominate, to twist the written
word and use it as a weapon.
Intolerance is an unquenchable desire for
absolute power, whether to preserve the iden¬
tity of the clan, the purity of the race, territo¬
rial dominion, the triumph of a political doc¬
trine or the glory of the Almighty.
At a certain stage in their evolution, both
religion and politics carry within them the
risk of intolerance. Social and economic life
too, although in different forms, as well as
ethnic and cultural matters. Even freedom
may cease to be a quest and become a doc¬
trine instead.
Intolerance is the rejection of difference, the
blood-drenched search for uniformity, the
exclusion of any form of autonomy or diver¬
sity. It repudiates exchange because exchange
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
defuses hatred; it excludes cohabitation because
cohabitation means accepting differences.
It is the death of Thought, pronounced in
the name of an idea. It spurns doubt, which
enriches our lives by inciting enquiry. It turns
its back on discovery, because discovery
upsets established certainties. It abhors inven¬
tion because invention rejects the old patterns.
It rejects democracy because democracy
implies freedom, debate and alternation in
office. It is the negation of diversity, however
discreet.
Intolerance and the struggle against intol¬
erance will last as long as there are human
beings on Earth. But is it possible to fight
intolerance without becoming intolerant one¬
self? Is there not a danger that what happened,
for example, in France, in the clash between
the clergy and the secularists, will happen
elsewhere and in other circumstances? At the
outset the secularists spoke out against the
domination of society by the Church, but this
soon developed into a struggle against the
Church simply because the values it stood for
were different.
Racism is but one form of intolerance. The
human species consists of men and women
who are different, but who are all evidently
human. Yet there many who deny the diver¬
sity that exists in nature and claim that there is
a superior race their own, of course.
How can we learn to accept the infinite
diversity of human beings within the evident
The alternative
/consider it my duty to make sure I understand others.
If they act in accordance with the will ofGod, it would be
reprehensible ofme to interfere in their actions; ifthey do not,
they are victims oftheir own ignorance and deservepity.
Akbar the Great (1542-1605),
mughul emperor of india
The Omnibus (1929), oil on
canvas, by the Mexican artist
Frida Kahlo (1907-1954).
Original and deeply rooted in
Mexican culture, her work
had a significant influence on
the Surrealist movement.
unity of the human species? How can we learn
that, like order and disorder, unity and diver¬
sity are but two facets of the same truth?
It is because of the inherent unity of the
human species that I accept and love its diver¬
sity. It is because of the diversity of cultures,
heritage, climate, ethnic groupings, beliefs,
customs, visions, that I seek the unity without
which diversity would be meaningless.
Although each taken singly is a relative
concept, unity and diversity together form an
absolute good.
Tolerance is the cultivation of diversity
within an awareness of and a quest for unity.!-.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The
balancing act \
40
LIFE can often be as sordid as a floor
cloth, clingy and ragged from constant
contact with the mundane. But it does
offer wonderful moments. Like yesterday.
Taking one step forwards then two steps
back, incipient summer was behaving with
the coy timidity of a bashful bride, ready to
burst into tears at any moment. In a fit of
exasperation I decided to risk it and, grab¬
bing Tonto, my faithful bike, I headed for
the Vondelpark.
The sky was an indeterminate blue, with
a touch of violet that threatened a storm. In
the park, a sparse scattering of young people
lay on the grass, stripped to the waist, expos¬
ing themselves to the risk of colds or worse
in the fitful sunshine. After all, when you've
tortured your flesh with thousands of
stretch-and-flex contortions all winter, you
can't let the weather stop you baking and
tanning the final product.
But even narcissism was at a low ebb yes¬
terday, confined mainly to willows batting
feathery eyelashes at their, reflections in the
canals and little lakes. Beside them, the ubi¬
quitous cyclists doodled along. The faces of
Amsterdammers, usually topped by tousled
mops of curly hair, are quite distinctive.
There is a rugged, weather-beaten quality to
them that contrasts sharply with the jovial
blue eyes. As they grow older, Amsterdam¬
mers seem to stiffen into openness, into
determined good humour as they cycle to
their graves with a Greenpeace badge on one
lapel and an Amnesty sticker on the other.
The floor of the park was the sharp
drenched green of the polders, a colour that,
like long afternoons in the swimming-pool,
leaves you acutely conscious that the human
body is 92 per cent water. In the sunshine,
the reflection of heavy foliage and big trees
gave the surface of the canals the magical
green shimmer of ducks' backs.
As I cycled along, the strains of a violin
reached my ears, a curious, jazzy melody
accompanied by a drum. I rounded the bend
approaching the Film Museum to find a knot
of stationary cyclists gathered round a small
amateur band. The quiet unassuming notes
of a perfect evening raga made a dappled
melody that blended with the light and
shadow of the park. Like the others, I stayed
awhile, perched lopsidedly on Tonto, one
foot on the path, the other on the pedal,
caught in the spell of the music.
In the background rose the imposing
bulk of the Film Museum, its sunny terrace
dotted with genteel coffee-drinkers whiling
away the time at little tables. There was a
vaguely gallic air about the made-up faces
and fashionable summer outfits. But the
Dutch can never quite carry it off. The
A group of musicians in the
Vondelpark (Amsterdam).
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
in the
young look too squeaky clean, their clothes
too practical and their innocent complexions
reflect their milk-based diets.
Round the next bend a surprise awaited
me. The grass was littered with bicycles,
their owners reclining beside them. I had
brought a biography of Van Gogh to read
and was heading for a sunny corner near the
lake, when the slow repetitive strains of an
Arab melody caught my ear. Beyond a vig¬
orous football game, at the foot of a monu¬
ment ringed with flowers, a group of
Moroccan youths in Western clothing were
playing ukelele-like instruments and small
drums, and singing. The distant, archaic lilt
evoked haunting memories of the ramayan
groups of Trinidad. Then the tempo speeded
up as flourishes, trills and a quickened
drum-beat broke the monotony of the song.
There is a sudden flurry of activity to my
right. In a spectacular whirligig of acroba¬
tics, two Turkish youths flicker across the
NIALA MAHARAJ,
of Trinidad and Tobago, is a
journalist with a special
interest in popular culture and
cross-cultural issues.
She has worked as a tele¬
vision producer in her own
country, as a publications co¬
ordinator in Rome, and as
an editor in Hong Kong. She
has contributed to many
leading newspapers and
magazines in Europe, the
Caribbean and Asia.
Vondelpark
BY NlALA MAHARAJ
grass, their arms and legs interlooping in
perfect syncopation as their bodies describe
graceful arabesques high in the air to a smat¬
tering of hand-claps from the lounging spec¬
tators. Then four more youths join in, their
shoulder-length curly hair whipping up and
down as they spring into human pyramids
vibrant with energy. They pause for
applause, get it, and flicker down to the grass
once more as though gravity does not exist.
Another good-humoured gathering at¬
tracts my attention. At the edge of the path,
a skinny, blond youth in a garish, orange-
patterned shirt is giving haircuts. A hand¬
made cardboard sign announces the price
ten guilders. He is at work on a long-haired
Latin American when the proceedings are
interrupted by his customer's daughter with
an imperious demand for a paternal kiss.
Memory stirs again . . . Sunday mor¬
ning . . . Barbers plying their trade under
mango-trees in Trinidad. I cannot resist. I
choose a vacant spot, lower my bike to the
ground and join in the free entertainment.
The sharp thwack of ball on racquet
punctuates the droning Moroccan music. To
one side of the football game, two muscular
young women in striped T-shirts hammer
out a ferocious game of paddle tennis. I have
never seen the game played with such speed
and aggression. Nearer the lake, a couple of
blond teenagers are clumsily engaged in a
desultory game of badminton.
The South American's haircut is finished.
The plastic cape is withdrawn from his
shoulders and a brush is flicked over his
neck. A Surinamese with a bushy Afro hair¬
style is beckoned forward and the blond,
lanky barber begins to sculpture a neat shape
out of the mass of hair. Near me, a couple of 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
ff/nrMS/^
Starry night (1890), oil on
canvas, by Vincent van Gogh.
42
Europeans embrace passionately on the
grass, devouring each other with kisses.
Then, slowly, they ease off and take to
stroking each other's face hypnotically.
I force my eyes back to my book, a cheap
biography of Van Gogh, one of the coun¬
try's most glorious figures, but a distant
flame suddenly catches from the famous
sunflowers on the open page. I look up. The
Moroccans have built a fire to warm up their
drums, just as our tassa musicians in Tri¬
nidad do. The music continues with increas¬
ed vitality, and a skinny girl of Asian appea¬
rance, her dress hitched high, begins a
sensuous barefoot dance beside the path.
The spectators smile encouragingly at her.
Her somewhat ravaged face is veiled by long
hair, so I return to Van Gogh. His brother
has just managed to bribe him away from the
clutches of a poor prostitute, providing him
with the money to enable him to begin the
long pilgrimage that was to lead him from
his early studies of peasant life to his trium¬
phant discovery of colour.
Another sound makes me look up again.
It comes from a ghetto-blaster carried by a
tall, mustachioed German with a bicycle,
which he sets down before beginning to
practise intricate, virile dance-steps, between
the acrobats and the barber, who is still
intent on his work. The audience is apprecia¬
tive, but the shadow of a nearby tree has
lengthened to cover me, so I move to the
sunny edge of the lake. I become aware of
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
the ever-present Vondelpark juggler. I am
surprised how much he has improved during
the year that I have been watching him prac¬
tise. Now the silver-coloured batons explode
from his hands like a burst of fireworks in
the evening sunlight.
A South American drinks vendor pedals
up with two blue coolers strapped to his
bicycle. The red-headed French family
nearby buys beer. He apologizes that he has
no mineral water for me. I turn once more to
Van Gogh and his unquenchable thirst for
recognition and his developing exile. The
low throb of a guitar, and I turn round. Two
Dutch guys and a Peruvian have settled on
the grass nearby. As I look on, the Peruvian
produces a small bamboo flute and conjures
up a delicate, perfectly-controlled jazz piece.
The Dutch guitarist throws back his head
and laughs joyously and long. No mere joke
could have ignited that laugh; the warmth of
pure well-being radiates so far out from their
circle that it seems to touch all those around.
They play Latin songs and sing. Their voices
are not very good and I can barely make out
the Spanish words. The guitarist laughs again
and again.
I try not to let my envy of their easy
companionship show by returning to Van
Gogh. He has cut off. his ear and has been
abandoned by Gauguin, who complains
that Vincent's brother looks at his paint¬
ings "with the cold eyes of the Dutchman".
The Latin American vendor cycles past
again, sells a few drinks and then parks his
bicycle near the group with the guitars.
They shift to make room for him in their
circle and he begins to sing in a weak tre¬
mulous voice. I strain my ears in anticipa¬
tion of the Spanish lyrics, but the words
are English and familiar.
". . . I am just a poor boy so my story's
seldom told. I have squandered my resis¬
tance for a pocket full of mumbles, such are
mumbles, such are promises. . . ." It is an old
Simon and Garfunkèl ballad that I remember
by heart from my teenage days in the 1960s.
". . . All lies and jests; still, the man hears
what he wants to hear and disregards the
rest. ..."
A confused stirring draws attention to the
other side of the path. The Turkish acrobats
and the German dancer have joined forces,
creating a mobile human pyramid with the
broad German shoulders over the bicycle
handlebars as its base. More and more of the
Turks pile on, their locks flowing in the wind
as the bicycle wobbles down the slope until,
at the last moment, they scatter to right and
to left. The spectators chuckle; it is starting
to become like a circus. The acrobats and the
clowns are as one in the fading light.
Love and justice
Therefore all things whatsoever ye would that men should
do to you, do you even so to them.
New Testament,
The Gospel according to St Matthew, VII, 12
"When I left home and my family, I was
no more than a boy," the drinks vendor
sings on, "in the company of strangers, in
the quiet of a railway station, running
scared . . . " the guitar ripples through the
interlude "Keeping low, seeking out the
poorer quarters where the ragged people go,
looking for the places only they would
know. ..."
The Dutchman raises his arm. "All to¬
gether now!" and the group joins in the
refrain, "Lai la lai . . . lai la lai, lai, lai la
lai. . . ." Those of us around begin to join in
hesitantly, but the wind is becoming chilly
and the crowd in the park is thinning out.
The drinks vendor's voice floats out
again. "Asking only workman's wages I
come looking for a job. But I get no
offers. . . ." The note goes too low and he
dissolves into a mumble. The laughing
Dutchman stops to adjust his guitar while
the flute plays on and I turn back to Van
Gogh. Now he is embracing utter loneliness
after the people of Aries have petitioned for
his eviction. His madness scares them. And
me. I know where it will lead.
I pause for respite and the guitar strums
again. "And I'm laying out my winter
clothes and wishing I was gone . . . going
home . . . where the New York city winters
aren't bleeding me, leading me-ee-ee . . .
going home. ..."
As I take up the next refrain with those
left in the park, the gooseflesh on my arm
tells me it is time to go. I put away my book
and pick up my bicycle. But the guitars rise
crescendo to the final stanza.
". . . In a clearing stands a boxer and a
fighter by his trade, and he carries the
reminder of every glove that laid him low
and cut him, till he cried out, in his anger
and his shame, T am leaving, I am leav¬
ing' . . . But the fighter still remains. ..." O 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
UNESCO ON VIDEO
In a changing world, a short video-
film produced by Unesco's audio¬
visual information service, shows by
means of specific examples how
Unescoin collaboration with its
member states, other United
Nations institutions, non¬
governmental organizations and
partners from many different
backgroundsis endeavouring to
respond to a number of major
challenges of our time: the
development of human resources;
the protection of the environment;
the preservation of the cultural
heritage; and the promotion of
intellectual exchanges to serve the
cause of peace. The programme's
running time is 25 minutes 45
seconds. It is available in English,
French and Spanish. Further
Information may be obtained from
the Audio-visual Production Service
of the Office of Public Information,
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris.
44
LAND OF THE FUTURE
Terre d'Avenir (Land of the Future) is
the title of the First International
Development Forum, held at Le
Bourget (France) from 5 to 7 June
1992. The Forum is being organized
on the initiative of the Catholic
Committee against Hunger and for
Development under the sponsorship
of the United Nations and Unesco.
By highlighting the increasingly
close links between environmental
and development issues, "Land of
the future" echoes the
preoccupations of the Earth Summit
being held in Rio de Janeiro at the
same time. The purpose of the
Forum is to bring together people
who are concerned in development
and to inform a wide public of the
issues involved. The Unesco Courier
and other Unesco publications are
being displayed at the Forum.
DRAWING COMPETITION
WILL ALERT CHILDREN
TO DRUG PROBLEMS
As part of its activities to mark the
International Day Against Drug
Abuse (26 June), Unesco, in co¬
operation with the Paris City
authorities, is organizing a drawing
competition for children in Europe.
The competition is open to primary-
school children in the 10-11-year
age group, who will be asked to
illustrate their ideas on how to
prevent drug abuse. Its purpose is
to alert families and the general
public to the gravity of the problem,
and to provide teachers with an
opportunity to raise the subject in
the classroom. Some thirty-three
European countries have been
contacted through their National
Commissions for Unesco, with a
view to their taking part in the
competition. The five prize-winners
and their teachers will be invited for
a one-week visit to Paris.
CANCER,
AIDS AND SOCIETY
Ways of integrating science,
medical practice and health policies
in a multidisciplinary approach to
cancer and AIDS were discussed at
a symposium held at Unesco
Headquarters from 23 to 25 March
and attended by 300 Internationally
known physicians, legal experts,
moral philosophers and politicians.
Unesco, which took part in the
meeting along with the World Health
Organization (WHO), the Council of
Europe and the European Academy
of Sciences, Arts and Humanities,
drew particular attention to the bio-
ethical dimension of research,
especially in cases where genetical
manipulation is involved.
Among other issues discussed
were the behavioural and socio-
cultural aspects of the prevention of
cancer and AIDS and policies for
tackling the two diseases in Europe
and the developing world.
Participants also raised the
question of human rights in clinical
tests and the impact of the media
on health policies.
A PRIZE
FOR CREATIVITY
A Unesco Prize for the Promotion of
the Arts, established through a
generous initiative by the Japanese
painter Kaii Higashiyama and with
the assistance of the National
Federation of Unesco Associations
of Japan, will be awarded for the
first time in May 1993. Its purpose
is to reward outstanding creative
achievements by young artists, or
groups of artists, in the visual arts
(painting, sculpture and graphics)
and in the performing arts, and to
encourage their further
development as artists. The Prize
will be awarded, once every two
years, to 5 laureates or groups of
laureates, by the Director-General of
Unesco, on the basis of proposals
from an international Jury of seven
eminent persons from different
parts of the world. Each prize will
consist of approximately
US$20,000. O
This text is the first ofa
series in which the Director-
General of Unesco will set
forth for readers of the Courier
his thinking on matters
of current concern.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
TIME OF PROMISE
WE are living in times of radical change, and the
international community through the United
Nations system must address the many challenges and
opportunities to which these changes give rise, not least
in the field of human rights.
With the fall of the Berlin Wall and the end of East-
West confrontation, ideological disputes on the basic
concept of human rights have been replaced by general
agreement on the crucial importance of their obser¬
vance, notably for the maintenance of international
peace and security. Human rights are assuming new
dimensions in international relations. A new practice is
emerging: the scope of domestic jurisdiction is narrow¬
ing and the principle of non-intervention is being inter¬
preted more flexibly. Respect for human rights is now a
factor influencing bilateral and multilateral relations and
is moreover regarded as an important criterion for the
recognition of newly independent states. This new and
broader perspective offers the United Nations opportu¬
nities for strengthening human rights mechanisms and
procedures, as well as for establishing new forms of pre¬
ventive and early-warning action.
The substantial progress of civil and political rights
in many regions of the world today in particular Cen¬
tral and Eastern Europe, Latin America and Africa is
obviously a source of great satisfaction. However, such
progress is hardly matched by improvements in eco¬
nomic, social and cultural conditions. There is a real
danger that advances in the political sphere will be
eroded by poverty and underdevelopment. Moreover,
totalitarian or authoritarian régimes in many countries
have left behind them a legacy of hatred, intolerance and
prejudice that can easily express itself as discrimination
based on differences in ethnic origin, language, religion
or belief. These risks are naturally increased by a wider
context of escalating population growth, environmental
threats and the pressures to which many national and
cultural communities are subjected.
TRAINING MINDS
The founding fathers of UNESCO were surely right to
affirm that the political and economic arrangements of
governments are not the sufficient conditions for build¬
ing a more prosperous and secure world. Such a goal
also requires the intellectual and moral solidarity of
mankind, universally recognized values, including res¬
pect for international law, human rights, fundamental
freedoms and human dignity. The surest location for the
defences of peace and human rights is in the minds of
men and women. It is therefore important that human
rights education should become part of the curriculum
from the earliest stages of schooling, since it is the best
way to forge attitudes, shape behaviour and prepare
individuals for assuming rights and responsibilities.
Our ultimate goal is the creation of a comprehensive
system of human rights teaching and education for all
citizens and populations, extending from primary
through university education to out-of-school education.
There are many areas in which UNESCO can make an
original contribution to the development of human rights.
One such area is that of academic freedoms. This issue has
hitherto been dealt with mainly in terms of the profes¬
sional status of teachers and scientific researchers. The
time would seem ripe to discuss and analyse the question
from a broader standpoint in terms of the rights and
freedoms of the members of the academic community,
freedom of scientific research, the right to teach, freedom
of intellectual co-operation, as well as the special respon¬
sibilities of scientists. Another area concerns the impact of
scientific and technological progress on human rights. Of
particular interest here is the study of bioethics. UNESCO
also envisages activities aimed at further elaboration of the
concept of cultural identity and cultural rights, which in
our view cannot be regarded as a sufficiently developed
category of human rights.
LIFE IN DEMOCRACY
But perhaps the most important area of reflection relat¬
ing to human rights at the present time is that of demo¬
cracy. No one can doubt the close links between human
rights and democracy. The struggle for human rights has
paved the way for the democratization process we are
currently witnessing in various parts of the world.
Equally, it is clear that only genuine democracy can
guarantee the full implementation of human rights.
However, democratic institutions can only function
effectively in a cultural context in which citizens,
playing their full participatory role as the agents and
beneficiaries of democratic processes, are able to exer¬
cise the free and informed choices on which democracy
ultimately depends.
Democracy rests on cultural foundations including
patterns of knowledge acquisition and exchange, atti¬
tudes and values which ultimately transcend political
structures. These cultural dimensions of democracy
merit the same kind of serious reflection that the cul¬
tural dimensions of development are at last receiving.
Only democracy can provide the framework within
which minority cultures can find full expression, inter-
cultural dialogue can effectively take place and tolerance
can flourish.
It is our deep conviction that research and education
on human rights need to be supplemented with research
and education on democratic practice. Our main objec¬
tive is to assist in the formation of citizens able and
willing to participate actively in the political, social, eco¬
nomic and cultural life of society and in the decision¬
making process. UNESCO is committed to play a part in
this endeavour, which we have called "the preparation
of societies for life in democracy". O
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
The road to Sagarmatha
by José Serra Vega
46
JOSE SERRA VEGA,
a Peruvian engineer and former staff
member of the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP), has worked in the '
Indian sub-continent on technologies geared to
environmental conservation, during which
time he spent two months in Tibet.
SAGARMATHA, Everest or
Qomolangma, as it is known in
Nepal, Europe and Tibet respec¬
tively, is the world's highest mountain,
with an elevation of 8,848 metres above
sea level. It is also one of the world's most
extraordinary places, for at least two rea¬
sons; On the one hand, it is the highest
point in the Himalaya (a Sanskrit word
meaning the "abode of the everlasting
snows"), the great mountain range sepa¬
rating the hot plains of India from the
high plateaux of Tibet, where two of the
sacred rivers of Hinduism, the Ganges and
the Brahmaputra, have their sources. On
the other, its spectacularly beautiful set¬
ting harbours a wide variety of plant and
animal life, as well as ethnic groups with
highly original cultures.
Some forty million years ago, as a
result of continental drift, the Indian sub¬
continental plate, which was moving at a
rate of ten centimetres a year, collided
with that of the Euroasiatic continent and
caused a powerful tectonic uplift. "Slices"
of the sub-continent were piled on top of
one other like a gigantic layer cake. In this
way the Himalayan chain began to take
shape, and from that day to this the
summit of Sagarmatha has risen at a
constant rate of two millimetres a year.
The Tibetan name Qomolangma,
which means "mother goddess of the
world", appears on a map drawn by the
Jesuits in the seventeenth century. More
recently, in 1852, it was recorded as "Peak
15", the highest mountain in the world, in
the great Trigonometrical Survey of India
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
carried out by the British on the initiative
of Sir George Everest. The survey in this
part of Nepal, which Europeans were for¬
bidden to enter, was made by Hindu
topographers, often disguised as pilgrims
and equipped with rosaries with a hun¬
dred beads instead of the usual 108 to help
them to count their paces and measure
distances. The surveyors also used ther¬
mometers hidden in their walking sticks
to measure the altitude by observing the
temperature at which water boiled.
At the foot of Sagarmatha is the high
valley of Solu-Khumbu, gouged out of the
rock by the Dudh Kosi, or "river of
milk", which rises in the mountain gla¬
ciers. There live the Sherpas in Tibetan
the "shar-ba" or "people living in the
east" who arrived in Tibet in the six¬
teenth century. The rhythm of their lives
was punctuated by the transhumance of
yaks and dzos (a hybrid between the yak
and the domestic cow) to the high pas¬
tures during the short summer, and the
movement of caravans which carried
cereals to Tibet through the Nangpa La
pass and returned with salt and wool. This
peaceful way of life was only interrupted
once in the eighteenth century by an inva¬
sion of Tibet by Gurkha warriors and a
counter-attack by Chinese forces in a bid
to help the Dalai Lama, which obliged the
Nepalese to withdraw and pay tribute to
the Celestial Empire.
Around 1950, the king of Nepal
decided to open his country's borders.
Mountaineers from all over the world
now had an opportunity to pit themselves
against the world's highest peaks, but this
brought a far-reaching change to the
Khumbu region and the life of the
Sherpas. In the 1980s international tour¬
ism became a mass phenomenon. In the
spring and autumn of 1990 alone some
12,000 tourists (approximately two tour¬
ists for each local inhabitant) visited this
fragile region.
Sagarmatha
National Park
In 1976 the Nepalese Government
decided to create the Sagarmatha
National Park, with an area of some
1,240 square kilometres, in order to
safeguard the region's exceptional plant
and animal life. Sir Edmund Hillary,
who with Sherpa Tenzing Norgay had
been the first to conquer Sagarmatha, in
1953, played an important role in this
initiative. Previously he had also made a
significant contribution, through his
Himalayan Trust foundation, to provid¬
ing the people of Solu-Khumbu with
schools, hospitals, bridges and drinking
water systems.
Reforestation is urgently needed and
several small-scale projects have been
started using the most common native trees
found in the Park, such as juniper, pine and
silver fir. A campaign, targeted especially at
young people, has been launched to make
the population aware of the problems
caused by massive deforestation over a
long period. Perhaps it would also be a
A snow leopard
good idea to plant copses around each vil¬
lage to provide the villagers with wood, as
is the practice in the arid zones of China.
In addition to Sagarmatha, the Park
includes some of the world's highest and
most beautiful peaks: Lhotse (8,501 m),
Cho Oyu (8,153 m), Nuptse (7,855 m),
the majestic Pumori (7,651 m), gigantic
glaciers and many lakes and ponds.
A number of rare and endangered
animal species are found in the Park. They
include the mysterious snow leopard,
which is rarely seen in its natural surround¬
ings but whose fur, supplied by poachers,
can be seen in the shops of Kathmandu; the
Himalayan thar, a goat capable of scaling
almost vertical slopes; the small musk deer,
which Tamang hunters from the foothills
hunt because of the commercial value of
the "musk pod", a gland which is consid¬
ered to have medicinal and aphrodisiac
properties by the Chinese and whose value
on the international market is higher than
' the average annual income of a Nepalese
villager; and the striking Impeyan pheasant
which has plumage of nine colours and a
green pennant-like crest.
It would be impossible not to men¬
tion the yeti, "the abominable snow¬
man". This legendary creature, a pro¬
duct of the Sherpa imagination, is
supposed to devour villagers, but no
other proof of its existence can be found
than a wall-painting and a fur-covered
skull (probably that of an antelope) dis¬
played in the Pangboche^.monastery.
Ancient Pathways
For tourists with enough time and phy¬
sical energy, the best way to reach the
Park is on foot. It takes around twenty-
five to thirty days to walk from Lamo-
sangu to Kala Pattar, directly opposite
the summit of Sagarmatha, along the
route from Kathmandu to the Tibetan
frontier, via Jiri, where the asphalt road
comes to an end.
After leaving Jiri, the traveller has to
cross the peaks of six mountain chains,
alternately plunging into tropical valleys
where there are multicoloured butter¬
flies, occasional snakes and, during the
monsoon, countless leeches, before
climbing again through woods and giant
rhododendrons which flower in March,
to cols some 3,200 metres high from
which the snowbound peaks can be
seen. The path wends its way through
villages where the houses have large bal¬
conies decorated with prayer-flags, past
small Buddhist monasteries with dark
sanctuaries redolent of yak butter,
beside many cultivated terraces, over
precarious bridges crossed by caravans
of nimble yaks, through pine forests,
and along the edges of sheer-sided
gorges. A swing hanging over a 600-
metre-deep precipice, at the bottom of
which a stream rushes, is a challenge to
the bravest.
Wayfarers can stay in the dwellings of
hospitable Newar and Gurung villagers
in the foothills, and share their tasty
dishes of rice and potatoes. After several
days' walk the first Sherpa houses come
into view. They are built of stone and
have multicoloured wooden windows,
flat roofs and Buddhist prayer-flags with
ribbons fluttering in the wind.
The World of Sherpas
The heart of the Sherpa home is the
kitchen with its burnished kettles,
copper saucepans and an ever-burning
fire. Visitors are invited to take part in
the life of the family, and are offered a
cup of chang, strong beer made from
malted rice. In many houses which are
also small restaurants, Western tourists
may be offered a menu more suited to
their taste, with sweetmeats, pancakes
with honey, cereals and dried apples. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
Sherpa society is exogamous and is
noted for its extremely liberal sexual
mores (there is a tradition of both poly¬
gamy and polyandry). It is divided hierar¬
chically, with the higher ranks being
occupied by descendants of the founders
of the villages; and blacksmiths, basket-
weavers and butchers belonging to the
lower orders. However, the opening-up
of Nepal to the outside world and the
closing of the Tibetan border by the
People's Republic of China in 1951 led to
far-reaching changes in the organization
of Sherpa society. Today it is common for
the more prosperous tradespeople to go
to Hong Kong and Bangkok to buy tex¬
tiles and electronic equipment. In the
shops of Namche Bazar, the region's
Sherpa centre, it is even possible to buy
Maradona T-shirts.
The Sherpas, who do not appear to
have been very religious in the early cen¬
turies of their settlement in Nepal, now
observe a stricter form of Buddhism, per¬
haps due to the influence of missionaries
from Tibet. Sherpa society today contrib¬
utes generously to the maintenance of the
famous monasteries of Thame and
Thyangboche.
In the courtyards of these monasteries
the annual festivals of Mani Rimdu are
magnificently celebrated in broad daylight
or at full Moon. Monks dressed in bro¬
cade and wearing masks depicting demons
or animals, mime the triumph of Bud¬
dhism over the forces of evil and dance to
the sound of flutes made from human
shinbones, drums and enormous copper
trumpets. These festivals provide the vil¬
lagers from all around with an opportu¬
nity to get together, see old friends and
arrange marriages.
A Himalayan black bear
The monastery of Thyangboche
stands in a spectacular setting amidst high
snowy mountains, on a summit covered
with woods that are fast disappearing.
Not long ago the monastery was badly
damaged by fire, but it is now being
rebuilt. On entering its kitchens full of
enormous bowls and churns for prepar¬
ing the roasted barley flour known as
tsampa, and salty tea whipped with
butter, a restorative drink for travellers
who have just come in from the cold, one
has the impression of travelling back in
time to the Middle Ages.
Beyond the monastery the path con¬
tinues to rise. Trees no longer grow. Tra¬
vellers would be well advised to make a
halt at Pheriche, around 4,300 metres
high, or at Lobuche, to let the effects of
altitude sickness wear off. After two days'
walk across wide stretches of glacial
morane, it is possible to begin the ascent
of the 5,545-metre-high Kala Pattar, from
which, in late afternoon, the golden peak
of Sagarmatha can be seen. Makalu, the
fifth highest mountain in the world, can
also be seen, along with the great swathe
of snow joining Lhotse and Nuptse,
which have still not been fully explored.
An Urgent Task
The next day's stage is across the specta¬
cular Khumbu glacier, which is covered
with masses of extraordinarily shaped
pieces of ice glistening like thousands of
diamonds in the Sun, as far as the base
camp of the expeditions which set out to
climb Sagarmatha. Sometimes four or five
groups of mountaineers will be waiting to
UNESCO IN ACTION
WORLD HERITAGE
begin the ascent, each by a different
route. Tents and containers are every¬
where, and also, unfortunately, piles of
rubbish which earlier expeditions have
not bothered to take away with them.
The federations and clubs to which the
belong ought to work out
some kind of scheme to provide funds for
keeping the site clean.
It is intended to increase the area of
the Park to some 3,900 square kilometres,
and the Chinese government proposes to
expand neighbouring reserves on the
Tibetan side to some 10,400 square kilo¬
metres, thus creating one of the world's
biggest conservation areas.
Safeguarding the site is now an urgent
task because of the increasingly serious
threats to the environment. Since 1950
tourism has had a devastating effect on
the forest resources. Owing to runaway
growth in the demand for firewood,
entire stretches of woodland have disap¬
peared. Many small hotels and houses
have been built along the paths, and
mountaineering expeditions have become
complex organizations employing hun¬
dreds of porters and sometimes camping
for several months waiting for the
weather to improve before they start on
the climb. The deterioration of the land¬
scape is extending to other regions such
as the high valley of the Arun, near Solu-
Khumbu, which was hitherto virtually
unaffected but is now being burned and
cleared to provide farmland and wood
supplies.
Some steps have already been taken to
encourage the use of fossil fuels and to
oblige expeditions to bring their own fuel
in the form of kerosene or gas. Two small
hydroelectric power stations have also
been built, one for Namche Bazar and the
other for the Thyangboche monastery.
By including this exceptional region
on the World Heritage List, UNESCO is
contributing to its conservation, but there
can be no doubt that more financial sup¬
port will be necessary from the developed
countries, which are the Park's main
users, to carry out large-scale reforesta¬
tion and meet the energy needs of the
population. Only energetic and concerted
action will make it possible for people,
plants and animals to continue to live on
these marvellous slopes for many genera¬
tions to come. O
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
MUSIC FROM AROUND THE WORLD
Argentina. Tritonic Musics of the
North-West
Musics and Musicians of the World
CD Unesco D 8208
To the world of music, Argentina is
the land of the tango, yet it has a rich
heritage of folk music that is little
known outside its borders. This
recording provides an opportunity to get
to know the music of the indigenous
peoples of the north-west region of the
country. With their strange sonorities
and striking rhythms, the tritonic
instrumental pieces for percussion and
wind bear little resemblance to any
other known musical forms, except
perhaps for some distant similarity to
Tibetan horn music. Equally fascinating
are the fondas and copias, vocal
pieces chanted in nasal tones in pre-
Columbian languages. Far less
westernized than the Indian music of
Peru or Bolivia, this ancient music
reveals clear evidence of Asian
influences preserved over the centuries
in Indian cultures.
Stellio et son orchestre antillais
L'Etoile de ¡a Musique créole
CD Music Memoria 30838
Known to the world as Stellio, the
clarinettist Fructueux Alexandre grew
up In French Guyana and in Martinique.
He it was who brought the beguine to
Paris, which he first performed at the
famous Bal Nègre in 1929. Here, he
and his bandtrombonist Archange St.
Hilaire, pianist and 'cellist Victor Collât,
violinist Ernest Léardée and drummer-
singer Orphélien (plus singers Léona
Gabriel and Jeanne Rosillette on some
tracks) offer a range of sparkling
pieces (mazouk, béguines, waltzes) all
strongly Influenced by the jazz of New
Orleans, a city close to the Antilles
both culturally and geographically.
China. China Wind and Percussive
Instrumental Ensembles
CD Unesco D 8209
These recordings, made in
Shanghai, illustrate various aspects of
Chinese "learned" and folk music. The
first five tracks, performed by a group
from the Quanzhou opera, are
reminiscent of Japanese gagaku music,
which is itself of Chinese origin. Two
pieces, "Approaching the dressing-
table" and "Four in one", played by
groups from south of the "River" (the
Yangzi Jiang), are strikingly original. The
later tracks, played by the Bainigan
village orchestra, cover a variety of
themes. The orchestra consists of wind
instruments (oboes, a flute, a clarinet),
strings (lute and viols) and percussion
(gongs, drums, etc.). The intricate
structures and sophisticated polyphony
bear witness to the quality of a musical
heritage that the West is only now
beginning to discover.
Mongolia. Traditional Music
CD Unesco D 8207
With Mongolia again coming to
occupy a prominent place on the world
scene and rediscovering its cultural
roots, It is fitting that its music should
be made available to a wider public.
Mongolian music is essentially vocal
(Mongolians like to sing to fill the
empty silence of the steppes) and
involves complicated techniques. The
famous diphonic Mongolian chant, the
Khoomii, has been the subject of many
studies by ethnomusicologists. "The
fair Altai", a love song, is sung in
homophony in a remarkable
performance by two men with quite
different voices who achieve perfect
synchronization through a series of
complicated glissando passages.
Equally astonishing is "The four
seasons", played on the flute using the
continuous breathing technique.
JAZZ
Abbey Lincoln.
You Gotta Pay the Band
Abbey Lincoln (vocals),
Stan Getz (tenor saxophone),
Hank Jones (piano), Charlie Haden
(bass), Mark Johnson (drums), '
Maxine Roach (viola).
CD Gitanes Jazz/Verve 511 110-2
After a few years of undeserved
eclipse, Abbey Lincoln (also known as
Aminata Moseka) has again come to
the forefront of the musical scene. With
her husky voice, which can slide from
velvety softness to metallic sharpness,
and her unique diction and phrasing,
Lincoln is a true musician and a
mistress of understatement. There is a
lot of love in her songssometimes
wounded love which finds release in
the wider love of life and of humanity.
Like Carmen McRae and other great
jazz singers, Abbey Lincoln knows how
to draw out the full value of the
wordsnever trite of her lyrics. Sad
at times, this recording, with solos by
Stan Getz, is nevertheless beautiful
and moving. It was recorded just before
Stan Getz died.
Archie Shepp Quartet.
/ Didn't Know About You
Archie Shepp (tenor and alto
saxophone), Horace Parian (piano),
Wayne Dockery (bass),
George Brown (drums)
CD Timeless Records SJP 370
At the end of the 1960s, Archie
Shepp was one of the chief advocates
of free jazz. Later he spent several
years as a university teacher. Today his
improvisations are made against a
more precise harmonic background,
but he has lost none of his militant
sharpness ("Go Down Moses") or his
power of expression. "Blllie's Bossa",
for example, is virile bossa nova, its
shape emphasized by the forceful
playing of the pianist. It is a far cry
from the delicate improvisations of a
Joào Gilberto or a Tom Jobim. Shepp's
name has now joined the roll of the
great saxophonists (Coleman Hawkins,
Dexter Gordon, John Coltrane and
Sonny Rollins) who have left their mark
on the history of jazz.
Tommy Flanagan.
Positive Intensity
Tommy Flanagan (piano), Ron Carter
(bass), Roy Haynes (drums).
CD Sony Music 467692 2
Another sparkling recording from
this sophisticated pianist from Detroit,
the cradle of several jazz pianists, who
was for many years accompanist to Ella
Fitzgerald. Flanagan's playing is calm,
economical, balanced and, to quote
the title of one of the tracks on this
compact, "Smooth as the Wind". The
refined music he distils, notably in
"52nd Street Theme" (a beboppers'
old faithful) classes him as the direct
heir of Bud Powell.
M Isabelle Leymarie
CLASSICAL
Karol Szymanowski.
Work for violin and piano
Annick Roussin (violin),
Pascal Le Corre (piano)
CD Accord 201122
Situated ¡n time between Chopin
and the post-1945 Polish School, the
composer Szymanowski is to Poland
what Janácek was to Czechoslovakia
and Bartok was to Hungary. More
innovative than Janácek but perhaps
less so than Bartok, his work is,
undeservedly, far too little known.
Recordings of his chamber music are
even more rare than those of his
symphonic or operatic works. His
"Sonata Opus 9" reveals the influence
of Brahms or of Richard Strauss, but
one cannot fail to be struck by the
extraordinary, magical beauty of his
"Myths Opus 30" (1916) in which he
pays tribute to the Greek myths that
have always exercised a certain
fascination over him. His genius comes
into full flower in his remarkable
"Berceuse Opus 52".
Ysang Yun.Garak 5 Studies
for flute, Octet, Concerto for flute
and orchestra
Pierre-Yves Artaud (flute), Jacqueline
Metano (piano), the 2E2M Ensemble.
CD ADDA 571166
Ysang Yun was born in Korea in
1917. After a stormy period of political
dissent, he has settled in Germany
where he teaches music and
composes. The most ambitious of his
works on this recording is his
"Concerto", written in 1977. It
contrasts the orchestra, representing
the metamorphoses of nature, with the
solo flute, beautifully played by Pierre-
Yves Artaud, which evokes a girl and
her almost sensuous attachment to a
statue of Buddha. This is an
entrancing, rather traditional work,
whose internal rhythms remind us of
the composer's origins.
Granados by Alicia de Larrocha
Allegro de concerto, Danza lenta,
Goyescas, El Pelele.
CD RCA Victor Red Seal RD 60408
The great Spanish pianist Alicia de
Larocha has recorded Granados'
"Goyescas" at least three timesin
1964 for Erato, a 1967 LP for Decca,
and in 1989 and 1990 for this
recording (there is also an old LP by
Everest Records, which brings together
recordings made by Granados himself).
A special tribute to the artist Goya, the
"Goyescas", dating from 1911, borrow
from the fantasies of Goya's paintings,
Spanish folklore and twentieth-century
experiments In keyboard technique.
Allcia de Larrocha brings out the
morbid undertones and the secret,
penetrating dance rhythms of the
"Goyescas" with consummate skill.
From the resonance of this original
music she draws out a new sense of
pathos and melancholy.
George and Ira Gershwin.
Girl Crazy
Under the direction of John Mauceri
CD 7559-792502
Produced on Broadway in 1930
during the Depression, this musical
comedy by George Gershwin had a
second great success in the 1940s
with the film version starring Judy
Garland and Mickey Rooney. The very
feeble libretto is based on the idea,
already in vogue at the time, of going
back to the land. Ira Gershwin's often
remarkable lyrics gave rise to a series
of hit numbers such as "Bidin' my
Time", "Embraceable You" and "I got
rhythm". One has a feeling that George
Gershwin is somewhat cramped by the
musical comedy straitjacket and is
already thinking in terms of the more
serious operatic form which he brought
to fruition with "Porgy and Bess". This
compact is a welcome addition to the
recorded history of his work.
Claude Glayman 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to the editor
50
CALLING ALL COURIER
READERS
For many years now, I have been
a regular reader of the Unesco
Courier, which provides a window
on the world and on others and
seeks to bring people together in
that noblest of pursuits, the
quest for knowledge. In order to
complete my collection of the
Courier, I am looking for the
following numbers of the French
edition: July-August 1956;
October 1960, January, April and
July-August 1962, April 1965,
May 1968 and January 1982.
In addition, for anybody who
may be interested, I have on
offer 113 copies of the French
edition, covering the period from
1964 to 1980, including
complete sets for 1976 and
1978.
Harold Labésse,
12, avenue Benolst Levy,
94160 Saint-Mandé (France)
EDUCATION IN MEXICO
In the first instalment of your
survey of Unesco's first 45 years,
published in your October 1991
number ("Children in Danger"),
you omitted to mention certain
important developments that
took place in 1947.
At the Unesco General
Conference held in that year,
Manual Gual Vidal, who was later
to become Mexico's Minister of
Education, was the first person
to put forward a proposal for a
basic education project. This
project was approved in plenary
session and was implemented in
part of the Mexican State of
Nayarit. At the same time, an
experiment along similar lines
was conducted in the Marbial
region of Haiti.
A step-by-step account of this
Mexican experiment is given in
the book Santiago Ixcuintla by
Mario Aguilera Dorantes and
Isidro Castillo, published in
Mexico City in 1970, which is an
extremely useful source of
information for teachers in
Mexico and elsewhere.
I realize that you cannot go
into details of all Unesco's
activities in the 45-year period
covered by your interesting
chronological survey, but in view
of the decisive role played by
your Organization in the field of
education, especially in rural
areas, I wanted to make this
additional point of clarification.
Maria Elena Guerra y Sanchez
Pàtzcuaro (Michoacán), Mexico
WHAT ABOUT MUSIC
EDUCATION?
In your review of the year 1953 in
"Unesco's First 45 Years"
(November 1991 issue on
"Environment and
Development"), you failed to
mention, among other important
events, the foundation in
Brussels of the International
Society for Music Education
(ISME).
Perhaps this was an oversight
on your part.
J. Lohmann
Rébénacq (France)
The International Society for
Music Education (ISME) was
established in 1953 at an
International Conference on
Music Education which was held
at Unesco's instigation and was
attended by teachers from forty
countries. The Society's aim is to
make music education an
integral part ofgeneral education
and community life and to
stimulate it as a profession. For
reasons of space, we have only
been able to give a brief overview
of the wide range of activities in
which Unesco has engaged or
with which it has been
associated. It is possible that a
fuller version of this 45-year
chronology may eventually appear
in book form.
CITIZEN OF THE WORLD
As a long-standing reader of the
Unesco Courier, I should like to
congratulate you on the high
standard of your publication,
which I read with great pleasure
each month.
Living as I do in the multi¬
ethnic microcosm formed by the
island of Réunion (who could
imagine a more aptly evocative
name?), I particularly appreciate
the variety and abundance of the
illustrations, information and
opinions you put together and
the way in which they relate to
one another.
I hope you will go on working
for greater mutual knowledge and
understanding between peoples.
Sylvie Buren
La Ravine-des-Cabris (Réunion)
PHARAOH'S TREASURE
IN PETRA
As a lecturer on cultural tours, I
know Petra well and was glad
that you published a feature on
that splendid site in your January
1992 number ("The Demographic
Dimension").
However, the monument you
reproduce in the photograph on
page 47 is incorrectly identified.
Contrary to what the caption
states, the monument shown is
not the Obelisk Tomb but the
Khazne Firaoun (or "Pharaoh's
Treasure"), which is the most
important and perhaps the most
beautiful monument on the site.
Monique Tillot
THE INVISIBLE WOMAN
I was amazed to read in Perdita
Huston's article "Women and
Nature: an alliance for survival"
(on page 15 of your March 1992
number "Women speak out on
the environment") that
"Women's labour has been
unpaid and thus considered
without 'value' since time
began".
What an outrageous idea!
Quite the contrary, the
completely unpaid work women
do, especially in the home, is of
incalculable value.
How can anybody make such a
preposterous statement?
G. Sirven
Saint-Céré (France)
If Perdita Huston had really said
what you claim she did, your
indignation would be quite
justified But she did not. Her
view coincides with your own. In
the passage in question, she
points an accusing finger at those
people who consider the unpaid
work done by women as being the
"bounty of nature" and who
refuse to take account of it, since
they regard it as without "value".
The Courier devoted Its entire
June 1980 number ("The Invisible
Woman") to an examination of
the factors which denigrate the
importance of the economic role
performed by women in society.
CORRECTION
We should like to apologize for two inad¬
vertent editing errors made in Annick Tre-
guer's article "The Chicanosmurallsts
with a message", which appeared on
page 22 of our April 1992 issue on "Art
in the street". The second line of the
piece of dialogue which opened the
article should have read "Because there
aren't any museums in East Los
Angeles" and not "Because there aren't
any museums in Los Angeles". The
lower photograph on page 24 shows a
scene in Chicano Park, San Diego, and
not in Estrada Courts, East Los Angeles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheUNESCO
r*r\i innCOURIER
45th YEAR
Published monthly in 36 languages and in Braille by Unesco, The
United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31. rue François Bonvn, 75015 Pans. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rlfaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: G lian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkn
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca. Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Anane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel. 45.68.46.85;
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Soiange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie B'achet (Tel. 45.68.47.15), Mouna Chatta
Administrative Assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French. Spanish and Korean:
Marie-Dominiq Bojrgeais (45 68 46 92)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Me'-tli (Berne)
Arabic; El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti ¡Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidor.i (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vima (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadougr Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (R o de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carre'as i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dares-Salaam)
Croatc-Serb, Macedonian. Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Blazo Krstajic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Vcolas Papageorgiou (Athens:
Sinhala: S.J. S^maraseke'a Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Vlarja'.ta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi;
Pashto: Ghotl Khaweri (Kaoul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafucdin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek (Prague)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Assistant: Marie-Noelle Branet [Tel. 45.68.45.89!
Subscriptions: Marie Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Alpha Diakité. Jacqueline Louise Julie.
Manichan Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassarc, Michelle Robillard,
Mohamed Salah El Din. Sy vie Van Rijsewijk,
Ricardo Zamora Perez
Customer service: G.nette Motreff (Te.. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Te . 45.68.45.65)
Mail: Martial Amegee (Tel. 45.68.45.70)
Shipping: Hector Gaxia Sandoval (Tel 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Birder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 yea's: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not cooyrighted may be reprinted
oroviding the credit lire reads "Reohnted from the Unesco Courier*,
plus date of issue, ard three voucher copies are sent to tne editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos w II be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
::e returned un ess accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed art des express the opinions of the authors
anc do not necessarily represent tne opinions of Unesco o' those of
the editors of tne Unesco Courier. Photo captions and heaclmes are
written Oy the Unesco Courier staff. The coundaries on maps
punhshea in the magazine Oo no: imply official endorsement or
accfotance by Unesco or the United Nut ens. The Unesco Courier is
prcluceo In microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco,
7 P ace ce Fontenoy, 74700 Paris; (2; University Microfilms 'Xerox).
Ann Arbo'. Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Micocard Edition.
Indian Head Inc.. Ill West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bel
and Howell Co.. Old Mansfield 3oad, Wooster, Ohio 44691.
U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - JUIN 1992
COMMISSION PARITAIRE H' 71842 - DIFFUSÉ =AR LES
N.V1.P.P.
Photocomposition: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Photogravure-impress on: Maury-lrormeur S.A..
Z.I.. route d'Etampes, 45330 Maiesherbes.
ISSN 0304-3118 N"- 6-1992-OPI-92-505 A
Cover, page 3: © V. Balu, Bangalore. Back cover: © Martine Viala, Marseilles. Page 2: © Monique
Constant-Dcsportes, Fort-de-France. Page 4: © Edouard Bailby, Paris. Page 5: René Burri
© Magnum, Paris. Page 6: R. Wollmann © Gamma, Paris. Page 7: Sebastiào Salgado © Magnum,
Paris. Pages 9, 12: © ÏMA-Philippe Maillard, Paris. Page 11: Roland © Artephot, Paris. Page 13:
© Cosmos, Paris. Pages 14, 15, 16, 17: (portraits of Voltaire) © Viollet Collection, Paris. Pages 14
(below), 17: © Viollet Collection, Paris. Page 16: © Archives Snark/Edimedia, Paris. Pages 18-19:
H. Cartier-Bresson © Magnum, Paris. Page 20: © Keystone, Paris. Page 21: © Margaret Bourke-
White/Z.¿/e /Cosmos. Pages 22, 40-41: Leonard Freed © Magnum, Paris. Page 23: Jean Mulatier
© Gamma, Paris. Page 24 (above): Eric Jumelais © Gamma, Paris. Page 24 (below): Philippart de
Foy © Explorer, Paris. Page 25 (above): Ferrero/Labat © Jacana, Paris. Page 25 (below):
F. Anderson/Liaison © Gamma, Paris. Pages 26-27: © NASA/S.P.L./Cosmos. Page 28: © C. Sauva-
geot, Paris. Page 29: © Sandra and Christian Gamby, Paris. Page 30: © Viollet Collection,
Paris/R. d'Uckermann Collection. Page 31: © Noak-Le bar Floréal, Paris. Page 32: Lavaud © Arte¬
phot, Paris. Page 33: Varga © Artephot, Paris-Hermitage, St. Petersburg. Page 34: © Roland
Michaud, Paris-Millet Library, Istanbul. Page 35: © Roland and Sabrina Michaud, Paris-Biblio¬
thèque de l'Arsenal, Paris. Page 36: © AlAP/Bibliothèque des Arts, reproduced from UNESCO,
40 artists, 40 countries. Page 37: Samuel Jouglet © Namane Zakri, Paris. Pages 38-39: © Fundación
Dolores Olmedo Patino A.C./Printemps-Haussmann, Paris. Page 42: © Rijksmuseum Kröller-
Müller Collection, Otterlo, Netherlands. Page 44: UxESCO/Dominique Roger. Page 41: Thomas
Laird © Explorer, Paris. Page 47: Varin/Visage ©Jacana, Paris. Page 48: Jean-Michel Labat © Jacana, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
w^
, /
^;;>v
I
o^o
.
»
*
*i
Zv < ft"
v?^-*^*^.
V- '
* .^
]]>
</page>
</document>
