<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="093019eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Ulli!
DECEMBER 1992
' - iW.U> *!K*t amtaHDK+»m 	
The
competitive
»,
' ft
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture or
any other subject which seems to
be an example of cross-
fertilization between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
é
, A
^A4S
/ >-"
\
<
¡
c
' f
r
r
THE ACROBAT
Engraving on steel (25 x 33 cm)
by Francis Hungler, 1991
^ys*:
Drawing inspiration from Hindu art, the French artist Francis Hungler engraved this acrobatic
figure on a circular-saw blade found in a loft. Against a background of primordial shapes-
circle, square and trianglehe sees an image of the destiny of humankind in which "the
point of perfect equilibrium and the breaking point are one and the same".
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 Interview
Susana Rinaldi
talks to Fernando Ainsa
The competitive
world of sport
8 Editorial by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
9 A bright but flickering flame
by Pierre Henquet
14 Who should foot the bill?
by Jean-François Nys
16 A red card for the round ball
by François Thébaud
Cover:
A composite image
specially created for this
issue of the Unesco Courier
by the Argentine artist
Ezechiel Saad.
Back cover:
Snow windsurfing in Iceland.
20 Brazil: fancy footwork for survival
by Roberto DaMatta
SJslands in majesty:
Nobel Prizewinner
Derek Walcott
by Edouard J. Maunick
22
31
Unesco and sport
Dopinga shadow over sport
by Miguel Angel Bermudez Escobar
34 Fallen stars
by Aleksei Srebnitsky
37 Fair play and the competitive spirit
by Michel Caillât
Special consultant:
Fawzi Mahjoub
41 Save Our Sports
by Roland Renson
23
Greenwatch
47
Commentary
by Federico Mayor
Unesco
«^COURIER
The
45th year Published monthly
in 33 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure
the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail,
upon the intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between
their peoples and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each
other's lives	>
Extract from the Preamble to the Constitution of Unesco, London, 16 November 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
SUSANA RINALDI
talks to
Fernando Ainsa
Susana Rinaldi is one of the world's
great tango singers. In this interview
she retraces the origins and
development of this original blend of
poetry and music that was forged in
the cultural melting-pot of the Río de
la Plata region and draws inspiration
from eternal themes such as
solitude, time, love, and death. As a
tribute to her efforts to promote the
ideals of Unesco, Susana Rinaldi was
earlier this year appointed Goodwill
Ambassador for Unesco.
You were already a well-known actress
when you started out as a tango singer. How
and when didyou discover this vocation?
I started to dance and sing the tango when
I was four. Later on, when I was a student, I
used to enjoy singing tangos for my friends,
although like all young Argentines of my
generation I was also mad about the bolero,
rock and the Beatles. Then I went to drama
school, and later pursued a career in the
theatre and television. In 1966, when I was
asked to make a record of poems by the Spa¬
nish poet Miguel Hernández, I refused
because I was afraid that I wouldn't do it as
well as Maria Casares, who had recorded
them earlier. I asked whether I could record
some tangos instead, and to my great sur¬
prise the record company agreed. So I made
my first tango record, which featured some
of the numbers that I have often sung since,
such as Melodía de arrabal ("Melody of the
Slums"), María and Sur ("South").
Since then I have tried to carry on the
tradition of the tango, with its recurrent
themes of injustice and the solitude of men
and women in big cities. I try to convey the
human qualities of the Argentine people and
their profound sense of solidarity with
others, something one does not often find
elsewhere.
During the dictatorship in Argentina,
between 1976 and 1982, I mainly sang
abroad. I tried to present an image of the
tango that was unfamiliar to Europeans. I
tried to show that it is not only a slinky and
spectacular dance, but a total experience,
whose poetry is a blend of music, words and
dance.
What is the tango, in your opinion?
First and foremost, it is a form of music so
distinctive that even a newcomer to it can
distinguish it from other Latin American
rhythms. But it is much more than that. The
lyrics are often pieces of literature that have a
poetic language of their own and express a
vision of the world. And of course the tango
is also a dance. Perhaps the best definition is
that given by the great tango composer
Enrique Santos Discépolo, who called it "a
sad thought that is danced".
To those who do not live on the banks of
the Río de la Plata, the tango seems very
complicated.
It is true that dancing the tango is an art
full of virtuoso touches; its cortes, quebradas,
sentadas, pataditas and lustradas ire all steps
that are rigorously codified and ritualized.
The tango dancer's body seems to be divided
into two parts. The top half is almost immo¬
bile, and the dancing is concentrated in the
bottom half. This is why the tango was
accused of being suggestive and sensuous
when it first appeared.
I wonder whether the tango is a not a
way of walking rather than a dance. When
the porteños the people of Buenos Aires
look out across the pampa to the horizon
and when they think of the aggressive
immensity of the city, they feel a kind of
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
melancholy that affects their way of walking
and gives the tango its hidden rhythm. It is a
dramatic, introspective dance. Ernesto
Sábato once said that Italians dance the
tarantella to enjoy themselves, but the por¬
teños dance the tango to brood on their fate
and chew over their bitterness.
All over the world, the tango is identified
with its legendary exponent, Carlos Gardel.
Yes. This is because the tango is above all a
performing art. The great tango singers like
Gardel have had a style of their own, their
own particular way of singing. The style
may be mannered to the point of caricature.
This is often because of the words, the way
in which lyricists have tried to outdo each
other in embroidering familiar themes. For
years, the tango was a prisoner of these cli¬
chés. The myth of "Carlitos", "the magician
of the tango", dictated the behaviour and
physical appearance the clothes, the hair¬
style, the smile of any tango singer who
wanted to succeed. At the same time, tango
singers had to act tough the tango was a
dance for hard men.
In his novel 62, modelo para armar, Julio
Cortázar caricatures the Argentine male as a
man of mature age, greying at the temples,
with his hairplastered down, and dressed in
apin-striped double-breasted suit.
People who are into tango do tend to have
a certain style, something that goes far
beyond the way they look. Don't forget that
this music from the poor districts of Buenos
Aires has become our trademark, at home
and abroad. Horacio Arturo Ferrer, a pro¬
lific writer of tango lyrics, says that the
tango is an emotional state specific to the
culture of the Río de la Plata. When young
rock fans say that the tango is old-fashioned,
they do not realize that it is an expression of
the cultural identity of a people. That way of
life still goes on in the streets of Buenos
Aires. The tango may be a passing fashion in
other countries, but for us it's the expression
of our deepest experience.
Whether people like it or not, the tango
is the supreme expression of the culture of
Buenos Aires of the rather sceptical atti¬
tude to life of people who don't believe in
anything and never have, and who have
"seen it all" even though they haven't been
anywhere.
Is this why the tango is so full ofsadness?
As a rule popular music prefers sadness
and despair to gaiety and optimism, except
in the case of political songs, and the opti¬
mism in them seems forced. But tangos do
tend to be on the gloomy side, I must admit.
A tango like Cambalache ("Bric-à-
brac") has done a lot of harm. It says that the
"world has been and always will be a rotten
mess" and that "the twentieth century is one
of evil triumphant", so that "it's all the same
whether you go straight or whether you are
a traitor, a fool, a wise man, a thief, a gen¬
erous man or a crook". It has done harm
because it lends justification to the ideas of
Argentines who want to shirk their responsi¬
bilities on the grounds that nothing is worth
doing since "one thing is as good as another,
an ass is just as good as a professor". This
philosophy of life justifies drifting and resig¬
nation. It's always somebody else's fault,
never one's own.
Do you think that this attitude can be
traced back to the origins of the tango: the
homesickness of immigrants, the resentment
of the indigenous population, the lack of
stable values in a changing world?
There has been a lot of argument about
the origins of the tango. Popular music in
Latin America is largely the outcome of the
transplanting of nineteenth-century Euro¬
pean dance-rhythms and their adaptation and
"cross-breeding" with indigenous and
African rhythms. Take the case of the Vien¬
nese waltz. It was transformed into the
Boston waltz, which was danced at a slower
tempo on the east coast of the United States,
the creóle waltz of the Río de la Plata, the
Brazilian "valsa" and the distinctive Peruvian
waltz. The mazurka was Americanized and
became the Uruguayan pericón oriental and
the mazorca or refalosas during the Rosas era
in Argentina.1 Paraguay adopted the polka.
The same thing happened with the tango,
but the process was far more complex. It
first appeared in the port cities of Monte¬
video and Buenos Aires. It is rather like the
alluvium from a river with many tributaries,
in which muddy water, organic and spiritual
matter, silt and sand are all blended together.
I defy anybody to retrace the origins of all
these influences and explain why the tango
became what it is on the banks of the Río de
la Plata!
Its origins clearly have something to do
with African rhythms like the candomblé, as
well as American music such as the habanera
and the danzón, and European dance-forms
like the Spanish, and especially the so-called
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Andalusian, tango, with its popular subjects
and tunes. All these formed the fertile sub¬
soil of a musical form that began in the so-
called "Negro" dance-halls of Montevideo
and in the brothels and piringundines
(dance-halls) of Buenos Aires, the shady bars
which a famous dictionary of lunfardopor¬
teño slang describes as "places of amuse¬
ment where people of dubious character
congregate". Even in colonial times, decrees
were drawn up to regulate the gatherings at
which "negro tangos" were danced.
It is virtually impossible to know how all
these different influences amalgamated to
form the tango as we know it. It is impossible
to say precisely when the tango was created,
but there is no doubt that it soon became a
popular dance in the poorer districts of
Buenos Aires, where gauchos, soldiers and
members of the underworld all met.
From 1870 onwards, there was a new
development, as wave after wave of immi¬
grants arrived on the banks of the Río de la
Plata. Many of them lived in tenement houses
known as conventillos. By 1887, 61 per cent of
the population of Buenos Aires was of foreign
origin and, in the thirty- to forty-four-year
age-group, there were seven foreigners to
every Argentine. Some 20 per cent of the
population lodged in conventillos, where
people of widely differing cultures lived
side-by-side. This is the world described in
El tango de la casera ("The landlady's
tango"), a late nineteenth-century tango and
one of the first with music and words by a
well-known composer.
The first tango from the poor districts to
be accepted by "respectable" society was La
morocha ("The brunette"), which was sung
in 1910 by the Uruguayan Flora Rodriguez
de Gobi, mother of the celebrated violinist
Alfredo Gobi. The appearance of the phono¬
graphic record in 1906 undoubtedly contrib¬
uted to its popularity. A few years later, the
brothel pianist Rosendo Cayetano Men-
dizábal composed El entrerriano ("The man
from between the rivers"), whose rhythm
has a very modern sound.
By the end of the last century, the tango
already had its "academies", its dance-halls,
and its milongas or creóle cabarets, in which
the passion for the tango reached fever pitch.
The dancing in these places was regarded as
being a contest between compadres1, who
drew arabesques on the beaten-earth dance-
floors with their high-heeled boots. They
were also meeting-places for immigrants and
native-born Argentines from very different
social backgrounds. They were frequented by
seamen from passing ships, the "black sheep"
of respectable families, jailifes (from the
English "high life") looking for thrills, and
calaveras, bachelors or married men on the
look-out for an easy pick-up, all drawn by
the tango and by the places where it was
danced. In these dives, some of whose names
are still nostalgically remembered, the
mythology of the tango was born, including
many of the stereotypes that still exist today.
These myths die hard. Is there any future
for the tango ifit cuts loosefrom the old style?
Television, radio and even advertising have
imposed this nostalgic image of the tango
and the idea that the old days were better
than the present. But as the Argentine writer
Maria Elena Walsh once said: "Try telling a
woman or a workman that the old times
were better than today".
Until the media decide to support a
modern repertoire of songs reflecting life as
it is in Argentina today, there will always be
a gap between the country as it is and the
way in which it finds expression in music.
It's not surprising that young people should
think that the tango is old hat, "old people's"
music in which they do not see the signs or
the myths of their time. A modern repertoire
does exist, but it is never broadcast, partly
for commercial reasons, but above all
because of a failure to appreciate the new.
There are tangos about topical issues,
depicting in few words the simple things of
life, the streets of Buenos Aires, and the hap¬
piness and despair of men and women in big
cities. There are tangos that celebrate imagina¬
tion and fantasy threatened by routine and
mediocrity. One of them is Horacio Arturo
Ferrer's Balada para un loco ("Ballad for a
madman"), which metaphorically celebrates
the new Don Quixotes of the twentieth
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
century, who wear a bowler hat instead of a
helmet and have exchanged Rocinante for a
taxi.
Many writers, including Roberto Arlt,
Julio Cortázar, Ernesto Sábato and Jorge
Luis Borges, havefelt attracted to the tango.
The great strength of the tango is that it has
fascinated writers as different as Borges
who wrote a poem entided "Tango", inciden¬
tally and a popular author like Homero
Manzi. The tango has enabled Ernesto Sábato
to come into contact with composers who
have put his words to music. It has stimulated
the thinking of essayists like Ezequiel
Martinez Estrada, who devotes a chapter to it
in his book Radiografía de la Pampa, and
Vicente Rossi, who has delved into its African
origins. The tango is the theme of poems by
Enrique González Tuñón. Writers like Baldo-
mero Fernández Moreno and Petit de Murat
have written lyrics for a number of tangos,
and so has Homero Expósito, a reader of
Homer, Baudelaire and Góngora. I sing
tangos with words by another "serious"
writer, Héctor Negro.
This ispan of"yourfight fornew standards.
You have to create a balanced repertoire
and resist the temptation to take things easy
and sing songs that are sure to be successful.
I could go on singing Sur, El motivo ("The
motive") and Tinta roja ("Red ink") for ever,
but I don't because I feel I owe something to
the authors and composers of my own time.
The great performers have always found
sustenance in the past, while at the same time
encouraging the new and making it their
own. Carlos Gardel made a rigorous selection
of the repertoire he inherited. He discarded
some famous numbers and revived others
that were little known. He sang old tunes in
an original way and introduced new ones.
But don't forget that recognition in Argen¬
tina only came to Gardel after his death. At a
time when he was playing to packed houses
in Europe and the United States, he could
scarcely fill two rows of the stalls in Argen¬
tina. As he said himself, "You have to learn to
love Buenos Aires from afar".
I have tried to do the same thing for my
own time. I have revived the songs of the
poet Cátulo Castillo, who was an excellent
lyric-writer of the 1940s and 1950s and the
author of successful plays like El Patio de la
Morocha ("The brunette's garden"), but who
was unjustly regarded as a superficial, light¬
weight writer. Yet he created a vocabulary
that is now part of the language of Buenos
Aires. If I had not made my LP Trova in the
1960s, Castillo would still be stuck with the
label that was foisted on him twenty years
earlier. I believe that every generation should
rediscover the past so as better to understand
the present.
I started out in the theatre and what I try
to do is to tell a story through each tango by
getting rid of all the platitudes which have
collected around it over the years and ob¬
scured its deeper meaning. There is no pre-
established formula for singing the classics.
Each one has a main theme that has to be
presented.
I Is it a handicap to be a woman in the
world of the tango?
There have always been women tango sing¬
ers, ever since the days of the pioneer Rosita
Quiroga, but they always sang about men,
stories told "by" and "for" men, in which
women stayed in the background. Singers
like Eladia Blásquez, Carmen Guzman, Mar¬
garita Duran and Mangui all tell human sto¬
ries with which anybody, men and women
alike, can identify. They refuse to think in
terms of male or female stereotypes.
I like to "put across" these stories written
and composed by women. I include them in
my repertoire because they go beyond the
usual clichés and give a new dimension to the
tango. Their lyrics express a philosophy of
living that is very different from that of the
"old guard". Musically too, the new tangos
represent a break with the traditional sub¬
jects and ideas. A composer like Astor Piaz-
zolla has brought to the tango a harmonic
conception so original that he influences all
the young composers, whether they realize it
or not. These days, nobody can compose in
rigid harmonies, in the style of the 1940s.
Do you think that the tango still has some¬
thing to say to the younger generations?
I want to try to get young people to
appreciate the tango as a modern form of
expression, as a type of music that reflects
current problems and preoccupations, and
not as music for oldies. I would like to teach
them to listen to this sort of music, which is
still so vibrant, and above all to discover the
splendid poetry of the lyrics. I feel sure that
if they knew more about our musical tradi¬
tion, it would help to solve in what one
might call a natural way many of the prob¬
lems of Argentine society. This is what I try
to express when I sing. It is my way of fight¬
ing for what I believe.
1. Juan Manuel Rosas, Governor of Buenos Aires,
dominated the Argentine political scene between
1828 and 1852.
2. Tough, quarrelsome and arrogant gang-leaders
who were typical figures of the Buenos Aires
working class districts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
EDITORIAL
8
Sport has become a universal language. At some time or other in their
lives many people respond to its appeal whether as a form of
recreation, a way of keeping fit, or a test of stamina. As a mass social
phenomenon, it provides an outlet for popular enthusiasm and an
opportunity for the individual to join in the life of the community. On
some occasions as during World Cup competitions and the Olympic
Games it cuts across political and ideological frontiers and creates a
ferment of excitement shared by a public scattered all over the
planet.
But the development of sport as a worldwide phenomenon has
only come about because of the increasing importance attached to
one specific aspect of sport top-flight competition to the
detriment of sport as a form of play and a means of education. It has
also resulted from excessive concentration on a limited number of
spectacular events, a process which has in turn exposed sport to ever-
greater attention from business and the media.
In recent decades these trends have sometimes led to excesses
and abuses: a worship of professionalization which can cause athletes
to specialize at a very early age, become slaves to overloaded
training and competition schedules, and fall prey to doping; wheeling
and dealing inseparable from the development of spectator sport on a
colossal scale; outbreaks of fanaticism and chauvinism that are
sparked off by the hot-house pressures of competition and are used,
in some cases irresponsibly, to give vent to social or national
frustrations.
Some people believe that these are reasons to condemn sport out
of hand. However, they tend to forget that in spite of everything sport
still has many things to offer: unique opportunities for personal
fulfilment; a magnificent training in community spirit; a civilized form
of confrontation between individuals and groups. All this forms a
subtle blend in which the desire to outperform others finds expression
in complete respect for rules that are the same for everyone, in which
competition brings adversaries together, and in which victory and
defeat are fused in love for an art practised communally.
For Unesco, one of whose tasks is to uphold the ethical standards
on which sport is based, sport will continue to be a way of bringing
together people from all over the planet as long as it remains the
"school of nobility" which Pierre de Coubertin, a century ago, saw as
its prime vocation.
Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
Spiros Louis,
the Greek shepherd who won
the marathon at the first
modern Olympic Games, held
in Athens in 1896.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
il bright but fíi
by Pierre Henquet
AFTER a period of remarkably rapid
growth throughout this century, sport
has, during the last thirty years, devel¬
oped into a phenomenon of worldwide impor¬
tance. Analysts and advocates of sport, political
leaders, researchers, journalists and administra¬
tors, have styled it an important aspect of
contemporary culture and civilization, a field of
social activity in its own right, a key factor in
political strategy and an economic force of the
first magnitude. In short, it is seen as a pheno¬
menon that has done much to shape our time.
More enthusiastic or lyrical sports fans go so
far as to view sport as the common denomi
nator of all humanity, a sublimated form of
capitalist competition, the most accessible form
of community experience or even, in the words
of Pierre de Coubertin, father of the modern
Olympic Games, "the brightest flame to blaze
in the hearts of humanity".
At once a technique, a leisure activity, an
institution and a myth, sport is a protean
concept. Although it appears to be a somewhat
irrational notion, it has attracted researchers
from a number of fields to a new discipline that
has come to be known as "sport science". Its
many definitions are often partial in both
senses of the word, and have led to debate
An archer prepares to light
the Olympic fire during the
opening ceremony of the
Summer Games at Barcelona
in 1992.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10
(which usually tends to be artificial or
semantic) over the distinction between sport
and games, body movement, physical activity,
physical education and physical culture. For its
part, UNESCO uses a single conceptual package
comprising "physical education and sport"
both in its programme and in the text of an
International Charter that was promulgated on
the subject in 1978.
Access to sport
In recent years, sport has become increasingly
institutionalized, with most countries estab¬
lishing systems of sporting activities jointly
administered by the government and voluntary
organizations. With its enormous pool of dedi¬
cated voluntary workers, this system is prob¬
ably the world's largest associative movement
in terms of numbers.
Between 15 and 70 per cent of the popula¬
tion of every country practises a sport (whether
Cameroonian soccer players
jump for joy after scoring a
goal in the World Cup,
Naples, 1990.
supervised or not) on a regular basis. It is esti¬
mated that the numbers involved amount to
over a billion persons worldwide. This
powerful force, grouped in a multitude of sport¬
ing clubs, leagues and federations at the local,
regional, national and international levels, is
considered by some to be a mainstay of demo¬
cracy in action and an opportunity for young
people, who are the most involved, to learn the
meaning of democratic pluralism.
However, access to sport and physical edu¬
cation is far from being a universal right, des¬
pite the brave words of the International
Charter of Physical Education and Sport. The
map of underdevelopment in sport is in all but
a few details identical to that of underdevelop¬
ment in general. In many countries of the
South, four out of five young people have no
opportunity to practise a sport.
Nevertheless, despite such discrepancies
and inequalities which are tending to get
worse instead of better sport has become
much more democratic. A marginal, elitist acti¬
vity at the turn of the century, it is now a mass
phenomenon which, if used for political ends,
can lead to risks of regimentation or the estab¬
lishment of a state of childlike dependence.
Traditional and modern sport
Whereas games involving imitation and illusion
prefigure the arts of entertainment, sport is the
offspring of physical games, especially competi¬
tive games, and should be regarded, in the words
of former UNESCO Director-General René
Maheu, as "a free and disinterested activity of
free people." Otherwise the game element disap¬
pears. Maheu considered sport to be the modern
incarnation of chivalric tradition, declaring that
"sport that resembles work is not sport".
The recent boom in top-flight competition,
to the detriment of amateur sport (a notion
that has disappeared from the Olympic
Charter), gives grounds for fearing that the
"play" dimension of sport will be increasingly
ignored and that competitive sport will
become professionalized.
For athletes subject to the constraints of
modern training methods, the fun has gone out
of sport, which is becoming hard labour. Some
regard sport as ambiguous, part work part play,
"playful work" or "industrious play". Others
consider sports as play insofar as they are
practised for their own sake. How far does
such disinterestedness exist today when it is
common knowledge that the leading lights of
sports that receive wide television coverage are
lavishly paid?
Traditional games and sports are another
matter altogether. Richly symbolic of the heri¬
tage of traditional societies, they are part of a
cultural totality of which they are a form of
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
expression and a means of regulation. The
values they enshrine and the skills and tech¬
niques they call for are very often different
from if not antithetical to those of modern
sport. Most often practised in an informal and
non-institutional context, traditional games and
sports are the reflection of both individual and
collective cultural identities as well as being
significant factors in cultural development.
In many countries, popular national and
regional games and sports (with few excep¬
tions) are losing ground, and this seems likely
to be an irreversible process. Some observers go
so far as to predict that the world's game cul¬
ture, however rich and diversified it may be, is
doomed to extinction even if certain "fossi¬
lized" forms may be preserved as folklore and
that it will be replaced by a sanitized, institutio¬
nalized, standardized, universal sports culture,
erected as a shining example of modernity.
However, physical activity as reflected in
sport is far from being the universal practice
handed down through the ages that many claim
it to be. To establish the preponderance of
sport over every other approach to physical
activity throughout the world is to proclaim
the hegemony of a specific concept of sport
that practised in the Western world today.
Traditional games and sports are neverthe¬
less part of the non-material cultural heritage of
humanity. As such, they deserve to be included
in a descriptive inventory, as recommended to
UNESCO by the International Congress on
Physical Activities, Sport and Development,
held in Nabeul (Tunisia), in February 1992. If
certain sports have to be preserved as folklore,
then at least let us have a catalogue of them.
Those countries most exposed to the seduc-
A phalanx of press
photographers during a
World Cup soccer game.
tion of modern sport (notably soccer and
tennis) risk seeing their cultural identity becom¬
ing gradually impoverished. Yet many leaders
in the developing countries fear that attempts
to promote the revival of national games and
sports, or a return to traditional physical activi¬
ties, would tend to marginalize their young
people even further, by denying them access to
internationally recognized modern sports,
which are an incomparable source of national
pride and prestige. Policies of this kind, they
argue, would run counter to the drive for inte¬
gration, as they would promote cultural prac¬
tices deeply rooted in the ethnic subsoil and
stifle the sense of national identity and of
belonging to the international community. The
world appears to be moving inexorably
towards the adoption of a universal sporting
culture, wherein sport, like society itself, may
well lose in spirit what it gains in strength.
After the brain drain the brawn
DRAIN
Sport is a flourishing and fast-expanding
market. The sports industry alone accounts for
between one and two per cent of the industria¬
lized countries' Gross National Product and is
growing more quickly than most other sectors
of the economy. Moreover, it managed to sur¬
vive the crisis of the 1980s with a healthy aver¬
age annual growth rate of five per cent.
Research on this new branch of the eco¬
nomy has revealed the considerable sums of
money involved in the production, trade and
distribution of sport-related goods and ser¬
vices. To take one example, in 1980 almost
7,000 companies with a total of over 300,000
employees belonged to the French Federation
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Youngsters at play in China.
of Sporting Industries. A survey carried out in
Germany estimated the number of salaried
posts in this sector at 45,000. Comparable
figures for the developing countries are not
available, but it can be assumed that the same
trends exist there, although to a lesser degree
and with a slight time lag.
At the same time, the sports industry is
becoming increasingly international, account¬
ing for between two and two-and-a-half per
cent of world trade. The world market for
sporting accessories, excluding infrastructures
and facilities, is far in excess of $50 billion.
Nevertheless, the terms of trade are unfavour¬
able to the countries of the South, which
depend on the industrialized world for
imported high-technology products, whereas
they themselves export goods with very low
added value.
Sports underdevelopment is a corollary of
economic underdevelopment, as indicated by
the unimpressive scores obtained by the devel¬
oping countries in international sporting
events (at the 1984 Olympics, only 62 medals
out of 687 9 per cent went to athletes from
these countries) and by the "brawn drain" that
goes hand-in-hand with the brain drain. We are
perhaps closer than we think to the time when
it will become virtually impossible for an ath¬
lete to step up to the Olympic podium if he or
she has not been trained in a country equipped
with modern facilities, or by a coach from one
of the industrialized countries.
Sport has thus come to play a prominent role
on the world economic scene. This relatively
recent development, as well as the internationa¬
lization of sport, is largely explained by the
close, complex, almost symbiotic relationship
that has been created and constantly reinforced
between sport, the media and advertising. Des¬
pite the important role played by the written
press in the early days of sport, it was televi¬
sion, more than any other medium, that seized
upon sport, turned it into a vehicle for advertis¬
ing and provided it with financial backing. In a
country like France, for example, in 1990,
soccer was financed by spectators to the tune of
35 per cent (as opposed to 80 per cent twenty
years before), by television (23 per cent), by
sponsors (22 per cent) and by official sources
(20 per cent).
Economic interests, inextricably linked to
media interests, are playing an increasing role in
shaping sports programmes, influencing their
rules, transforming sport into entertainment,
and having a large say in the way it is per¬
formed. With three sports (cycling, tennis and
soccer) taking up half the air-time devoted to
sport on European television, the standardiza¬
tion of physical activity is more than just an idle
threat. Economic interests, the media and sport¬
ing authorities have no choice but to get to¬
gether and make sport profitable. With the
twenty-first century just around the corner,
competitive sport needs television in order to
survive.
Top-level sport or sport for all?
What importance should be attached to top-
level sport in relation to the concept of sport
for all, and to the promotion of physical activ¬
ity and sport at school and in non-formal edu¬
cation programmes, particularly in the develop¬
ing countries? The cost of high-level
competitive sport already expensive is grow¬
ing more rapidly than the number of people
taking part. The priority facing developing
countries is to satisfy the basic needs of their
populations. Should top-level sport be regarded
as a basic need? Is it wise for such countries to
invest in sport at this level and host major
international sporting events?
Economists are divided on this question.
The necessary facilities are difficult to amortize
and maintain. They are ill adapted to the needs
of the local population and lead to technolo-
j*M
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
"Three sports (cycling,
tennis and soccer) take up
half the air-time devoted to
sport on TV".
Right, American tennis star
Pete Sampras keeps an eye
on the ball during the 1991
French Open in Paris.
PIERRE HENQUET,
of France, was a Unesco staff
member between 1946 and
1983. He is the author of
many articles on non-formal
education, functional literacy,
communications, youth and
sport. He is currently
assistant secretary-general of
the International Council of
Sport Science and Physical
Education.
IACOST
-
gical dependency on other countries because of
the complex ancillary equipment that is
required. Hosting the Olympic Games or
international championships often turns out to
be more expensive than expected, so that coun¬
tries have to resort to borrowing. However, the
sporting authorities in the Third World, moti¬
vated more by political than economic consider¬
ations, set great store by top-flight sport and
continue to campaign for greater geographical
diversity in the location of major events, and a
more balanced representation of countries in
international sporting bodies.
On the other hand, the promotion of phy¬
sical activity and sport for all should definitely
be considered an integral part and a vehicle
of development. The individual and collective
benefits to be derived from the regular, moder¬
ate practice of sport are incontestable. Physi
cally speaking, the practice of a sport, when
combined with sensible eating habits, is
unquestionably the most effective, pleasant and
inexpensive way to stay young and fit and to
reduce state expenditure on health. It would be
hard to imagine a more important asset to a
country than the health of its citizens.
At the psychosocial level, sport is character-
building and conducive to the full development
of the personality, improving emotional
balance, and helping the individual to put per¬
sonal success or failure into proper perspective.
Intellectually, it is a source of knowledge and a
guide in the learning process. Lastly, sport
encourages co-operation, solidarity and mutual
understanding, and can thus help people to
play a full part in the society in which they live,
and can contribute to the struggle against all
forms of exclusion. O 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Who should foot the M//?
by Jean-Francois Nys
"Every sport has a specific
image with which the
sponsor becomes
associated. . . ." Below,
French navigator Florence
Arthaud, winner of the Route
du Rhum transatlantic race
in 1990.
WHEN a major sporting event is due to
take place, especially if it is to be tele¬
vised, businesses scramble for every
possible inch of space on which to inscribe
their company logo the surrounds of the
arena itself, the bodywork of cars, the players'
shirts and even the flooring of indoor sports
halls. Only the Olympic Games are free from
this kind of advertising, but even there the offi¬
cial sponsors are authorized to use the
Olympic emblem (the five rings representing
five continents), an authorization which costs
them dear.
What is true for the Olympic Games holds
good for all sports. In order to cope with ever-
increasing outlays (salaries, administrative
costs), the clubs and organizers of competitions
are obliged to seek out sponsors or patrons.
Many companies respond eagerly to this invita¬
tion. Thus sponsorship of professional football
in France, which represented less than 1 per
cent of receipts in 1970, brought in nearly a
quarter of them in 1991.
14
By identifying itself with the image that a
sport creates and with the emotion, enthusiasm,
passion even, that it generates, a company
consolidates its position and role in society,
motivates its personnel, improves its reputation
and reinforces or modifies its image in the
public eye. Semiological studies in this field tell
us that every sport has a specific image with
which the sponsor becomes associated. Sailing,
for example, symbolizes space, the lure of the
open sea and controlled skills; fencing evokes
nobility, tradition, precision; while motor-
racing symbolizes virility, dynamism, authenti¬
city and pushing oneself beyond the limit.
In Europe, the money expended on sports
sponsorship amounts to more than 20 billion
francs. In the United States it is over $2.5 bil¬
lion. However, this source of financing is not
stable. It is not the primary function of busi¬
nesses to promote the development of sports,
except for those that exploit the market
directly, such as the makers of sports goods or
equipment and the sporting press. Most com¬
panies are prepared to invest in sponsorship
only insofar as it helps them to get their mes¬
sage across. Here sport finds itself in competi¬
tion with other interests such as cultural activi¬
ties, conservation of the environment, the great
humanitarian causes and scientific research.
Furthermore, a company's expenditure on this
form of communication will vary with chang¬
ing circumstances. It would be hazardous to
base a sports policy on such uncertain
resources.
The money for sport does not derive solely
from the private sector from players, specta¬
tors, the media and sponsors. State and other
public organizations contribute to a greater or
lesser degree to the financing of sport, in pro¬
portions which vary according to the country's
economic structure. In the former USSR, the
state assumed almost the entire charge, while in
the United States sport is a matter for the pri¬
vate sector. In France, public money expended
on sport amounted to 32 billion francs in
1990 as much as that contributed by private
companies and individuals.
This peculiarity of the French sports system
has evoked in the European Parliament the
question of the legitimacy of subsidies granted
to sports clubs by public organizations, with
some members of the Parliament regarding
such subsidies as an unwarranted interference
in the free play of competition.
Rather than seek an answer to this specific
question, one could, perhaps, broaden the
debate to consideration of the overall economic
basis of sport. If it is thought to be a private
matter, its management and financing should
be left to the private sector, and market forces
will prevail. Competition then becomes the
order of the day, with the various sporting
federations competing to dominate the market
for control of a particular sport and the clubs
competing to recruit players, to sell sporting
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Jumping with a motorized
parachute in Kenya.
events and to capture the imagination of the
public.
If, on the contrary, sport is seen as a collec¬
tive benefit requiring public sector control,
then it will be up to the state and the commu¬
nity to provide the necessary facilities, pay the
coaches and athletes, and make sport available
to all.
JEAN-FRANÇOIS NYS,
of France, is a lecturer at the
University of Limoges and a
researcher at the University's
centre of sports law and
economics. He is the author
of many works on sport,
including La santé:
consommation ou
investissement? (1980;
"Health: consumption or
investment?") and, with W.
Andreff, Économie du sport
(1986; "The Economics of
Sport") and Le sport et la
télévision (1987; "Sport and
Television").
If a strict market logic prevails, there is a
danger that inequalities will be created and that
access to sporting activities will be denied or
reduced for the less favoured members of
society. It is therefore appropriate for the public
authorities to intervene to mitigate the dysfunc-
tioning of the market, just as they should
control excesses such as doping and violence. O 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
1
4 rerf (flfrf for fhe round bull
by Francois Thébaud
16
FRANÇOIS THEBAUD
is a French journalist who has
covered all the major
international football
competitions since the end of
the Second World War. He
was the founder/editor-in-
chief of the football magazine
Le Miroir du football (1959-
1977) and is a former sports
writer on the Swiss daily
paper La Tribune de
Lausanne. His biography of
the Brazilian footballer Pelé
was published in the United
States by Harper and Row in
1976.
AY 1964, the National Stadium in
Lima 320 dead; June 1968, the River
Plate Stadium in Buenos Aires 80
dead; January 1971, Ibrox Park in Glasgow
66 dead; February 1974, Cairo 48 dead;
October 1982, the Luzhniki Stadium in
Moscow 99 dead; May 1985, the Heysel Sta¬
dium in Brussels39 dead; April 1989, Hills¬
borough, Sheffield 94 dead.
The settings for all these tragedies were
football stadiums, and their victims were men,
women and children who were there to watch a
big soccer match. Since no other sport has ever
been plunged into mourning by catastrophes
on such a scale, perhaps we should ask our¬
selves whether there is not some sort of special
relationship between soccer and violence.
Soccer supporters resent this accusation
against the most popular of all sports. They
argue that violence is endemic in modern
society, where it takes the most varied forms,
from mass slaughter on the battlefield to delin
quency and crime. Soccer stadiums are not
exempt, because the people who flock to them
are also products of society.
If that is true, why is it, then, that athletics
meetings and basketball or rugby matches are
not prone to the same baleful effects of their
social environment and do not give rise to the
kind of scene that so horrified those who wit¬
nessed the Heysel disaster on television?
TOO LITTLE TOO LATE
Soccer Association Football is clearly not at
the root of the violence. Yet it seems to offer
people more opportunities to get it out of their
system, primarily because in the 166 countries
affiliated to the Fédération Internationale de
Football Association (FIFA), it is the most
popular sport in terms of the number of people
who play it, the size of its public, and the pas¬
sions it arouses.
Packing people together like sardines on the
lower-priced terraces often leads to incidents
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
-*.. ^ -
In April 1989 wreaths and
flowers cover the pitch at
Anfield, the stadium of
Liverpool Football Club (UK),
in memory of the club's
supporters who had died a
week before during a
crush at Hillsborough,
Sheffield, before the
F.A. Cup semi-final.
that are not always reported in the press.
However, when the people on the terraces are
fans who have come to give "their" team
unconditional support and to exhibit equally
unconditional hostility towards the opposing
side and its supporters, the resulting crush
inevitably tends to degenerate into violence.
Attempts have been made to separate the
different groups of supporters and cordon
them off in enclosures situated well away from
one another, as well as keep close watch on
them when they enter or leave the ground, but
these measures have proved inadequate, as the
Heysel tragedy showed. Club managers and
sporting federations came to realize that far-
reaching changes were needed in the design of
stadiums, which often dated from pre-war
times, and even as far back as the early years of
the century in the case of the United Kingdom.
In theory, stadiums hosting international
matches are now supposed to have only seated
accommodation, not so much for the comfort
of the spectators as for safety reasons. Further¬
more, they are fitted out with electronic sur¬
veillance devices capable of detecting the slight¬
est sign of violence and enabling the police to
take rapid action.
The amateur spirit in rugby
The vast number of people attending soccer
matches is not sufficient in itself to account for
the game's unfortunate propensity for violence.
In both Europe and Oceania, rugby matches
attract crowds of 50,000, and no serious inci¬
dent has ever been recorded. Rugby is a sport
that is just as "manly" as soccer in certain res¬
pects, but it attracts a different public and does
not trigger off the same reactions.
Rugby football crowds have not changed
since the 1950s. They come from much the
same background, continue to believe in ama¬
teur sport and do not attach undue importance
to results. They are more interested in the spirit
of the game and the standard of play. They
keep their cool when the result or the refer-
eeing are controversial, and the stands remain
models of calm and good behaviour even when
the match is being fiercely contested on the
pitch.
By contrast, European soccer crowds have
changed almost beyond recognition. Manual
workers, who formed the bulk of the spectators
on the terraces before the Second World War,
have been replaced by white collar workers,
and middle class supporters sit in the stands.
Professional soccer is also increasingly domi¬
nated by the financial pickings at stake in big
matches. Winning is the main, if not the only,
obsession of players and spectators alike. The
way in which victory is achieved and the qua¬
lity of the game itself take second place. The
print media and television are partly to blame
for this by cutting back on the amount of space
and time they give to comment and analysis of
technical skills and the fine points of the game.
This being so, why should soccer support¬
ers be interested in soccer for its own sake, in
the quality of play, tactics and skills? Why
should they not contribute to the result by
taking part in the match? Intimidating the
referee and the players of the opposing side by
threats, insults and bottle or stone-throwing is
commonly the curtain-raiser to the outbreaks
of fighting between supporters and the ensuing
panic that are the direct cause of the tragedies
we have mentioned.
Nationalism and violence
Soccer fans did not always behave like this. Not
all that long ago, they often had an opportunity
to express their pleasure and enthusiasm during
matches which left spectators with the feeling
that they had shared an enjoyable experience.
What splendid memories we still have of the
Soccer is "the most popular
sport In terms of the number
of people who play it, the
size of its public, and the
passions it arouses".
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
France vs. Australia in the
Rugby Football World Cup,
Sydney (Australia), 1987.
matches played by the Hungarian and Brazilian
teams of the 1950s, or the performances of lead¬
ing clubs like Real Madrid or Rheims in the
1960s! And what about those never-to-be-for¬
gotten F.A. Cup Finals in England when,
before the kick-off, the 100,000 spectators in
Wembley Stadium became an immense choir
singing with one voice and creating an atmos¬
phere of fellowship in which the beauty of the
game was all that mattered. Great moments like
these are all too rare nowadays.
Instead of providing an occasion for peace¬
ful confrontation between styles of play
reflecting the different geographical, historical,
economic and cultural backgrounds of the
opposing sides, international competitions have
often become head-on clashes, with no holds
barred. During the World Cup and the Inter¬
continental Cup-winners' Cup there have been
many unpleasant examples of negative attitudes
to the game which spectators have not only
failed to condemn but in some cases have even
condoned.
National anthems played before matches by
brass bands and sung by the supporters clearly
do not encourage serenity on the terraces or
fair play on the field. But those who call for an
end to these practices of another age have not
been listened to in the world republic of foot¬
ball, where voluntary submission to a common
law the law of the game ought to exclude
any form of chauvinism that leads to violence.
IS SOCCER
REALLY BLAMELESS?
After the Heysel tragedy, the culprits were ini¬
tially sought among the "hooligans", who
work off their frustrations in the tightly packed
crowds at football grounds. However, as the
enquiry proceeded, it became clear that there
was no straightforward explanation for the vio¬
lence that had taken place. Violence is a pro¬
duct of society and of its contradictions and
shortcomings, and football stadiums are not
immune to it. However, the world of Associa¬
tion Football itself is not as blameless at it
would have us believe. Managers, trainers,
players and referees, journalists and spectators
must all realize that the battle against sectarian
nationalist attitudes and in favour of sports¬
manship is first and foremost theirs. This may
not bring violence in football stadiums to an
end, but at least it may help to limit its inci¬
dence and its consequences.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Sport and friendship
between peoples
I
Sport has, of course, developed on
an extraordinarily wide scale. It is
probably the aspect of modern life
which is most widely encountered through¬
out the world the only one, perhaps,
which is common to both industrial soci¬
eties and developing countries. It is also, to
a steadily increasing degree, one of the
most lively factors in international relations.
There are few international exchanges,
encounters or contacts which arouse so
much mass feeling as sports events.
But though it is becoming more and
more international in fact, is present-day
sport truly international in spirit, as Cou-
bertin thought and wished it to be? It is,
unfortunately, extremely doubtful. In point
of fact, nationalism, chauvinism and even
racism are more and more apt to win the
day and what a loss it is in international
sports events. The passions and emotions
that these events arouse and that are ampli¬
fied and broadcast to the four corners of the
Earth by the mass media are only very
rarely inspired, it must be acknowledged,
by the ancient moral law and social virtues
once presided over by Zeus Philios, god of
friendship. It is high time to act if we wish
to prevent the Altis of Olympia from degen¬
erating into the Roman Circus or the Hip¬
podrome of Byzantium.
Let me not be misunderstood. I am not
suggesting that the emotional appeal pos¬
sessed by sports events, which have
become the great popular drama of our
time, should be curbed. This would be
absurd and, for that matter, impossible.
One of the functions of such events
among the most salutary, moreover is the
same, at a much higher degree of intensity,
as that assigned by Aristotle to all drama:
catharsis, the purging of passions and in¬
stincts. Nor is there any question of trying
to deprive athletes of the admiration they
receive, especially from their fellow-citi¬
zens. Like any other form of excellence,
athletic feats are deserving of admiration,
and it is natural that those who have most
in common with the victorious athlete
should be the ones in whom this admittedly
noble sentiment wells up most strongly.
But just as no sports context can be
without desire for victory, so none can be
without rules and ethics. It is these rules by
which it is governed, these ethics by which
it is informed, that distinguish sport from
the savage struggle for life whose name is
war. It is compliance with these norms that
transforms a feat into a virtue, and since
these norms are by definition universal, it
follows that although the feat may be
ascribed to a given country, the virtue is
ascribable purely to humankind.
What can be more barbarous than this
identification of the public with the cham¬
pion, this appropriation by a nation of the
victory won by an individual or a team?
These flags, these anthems, these banner
headlines in the newspapers, screaming
"We won. . . ." or "National defeat", must
surely seem to us a monstrous exaggeration
of the spontaneous reactions of the crowd,
even a shameful exploitation of its most
generous impulses. In any case, this is the
opposite of catharsis: it represents a return
to a primitive disposition.
I think it is high time there was an
energetic reaction, including the abandon¬
ment of certain practices- which have
become part and parcel of the Olympic
Games, either with the consent of Cou-
bertin, such as the singing of national
anthems, or in spite of him, such as classifi¬
cation by nations which, as we know, is
not officially recognized. This is necessary
if we wish to restore sport I mean sport as
a whole, including athletes, organizers and
spectators to its international vocation of
promoting friendship between peoples.
From an address given by Mr. René Maheu,
Director-General of Unesco (1961-1974),
to mark the centenary of Pierre de Coubertin.
Paris, 28 October 1963.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Bruiil: fumy footwork for survival
by Roberto DaMatta
T
20
ROBERTO DAMATTA,
of Brazil, is The Reverend
Edmund P. Joyce Professor of
Anthropology and Senior
Fellow of the Kellogg
Institute, University of Notre
Dame (USA). Among his
works published in English
are Carnivals, Rogues and
Heroes (University of Notre
Dame Press) and A Divided
World: Apinayé Social
Structure (Harvard University
Press).
HERE are", so runs a popular Brazilian
saying, "only three really important
things in life cachaca, the lottery and
football." In other words, the national
consensus in Brazil revolves around an alco¬
holic drink, which helps one to celebrate the
joys or forget the sad moments of life, a game
of chance based on numbers, on which are
concentrated the dreams and aspirations of
social advancement, and a modern sport,
invented by the English and adopted by Brazi¬
lians with a passion equalled only by the skill
with which they practise it.
Of the three, football is the most foreign in
origin, since it was brought to Brazil by the sons
of rich families who had been bitten by the foot¬
ball bug while in England, where they had been
sent by their parents for their schooling. This
was how the venerable British game of Associa¬
tion Football, re-named futibol, came to be
adopted by the people of Brazil and to become
an abiding interest, evoking a passionate sense of
both individual and national identity.
After a brief initial period of resistance,
football, a pastime which combines the element
of competition with free and uninhibited
bodily expression, became the most popular of
sports. Perhaps this was because it is a team
game, incorporating the notion of a community
as close-knit a community exclusive as the
household or the family and to which one
is bound by unbreakable bonds of affinity,
sympathy and love.
Another reason for the Brazilians' irresis¬
tible fascination with football is that it is a game
played with the feet and not with the hands;
this adds the further element of chance,
requires of the players a high level of skill and
does much to ensure the "fine uncertainty of
the sport", even between unequal teams.
It is interesting to compare this with the
position in the United States, where a variant of
football has been adopted which involves hand¬
ling the ball and requires a high degree of tech¬
nical and tactical skill; this virtually eliminates
any element of chance in an encounter between
two unequally-matched teams. Thus the hand¬
ling code makes too great a disparity between
teams impracticable, which reflects, perhaps, an
inclination towards that scientific rationalism,
abstraction and specialization typical of soci¬
eties with a strong democratic tradition.
The Brazilian
touch
The use of the feet, as opposed to the hands,
nevertheless entails the use of the entire body,
and particularly the legs and the haunches, a
part of the anatomy which, in Brazil, is, sym¬
bolically, highly-charged. For example, we say
of someone who is adept at fending for himself
and getting out of awkward scrapes that he is
"swivel-hipped" and this expression is
equally applicable to a sly politician and to a
skilful footballer.
To the Brazilians, the type of football
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
"Football is a symbolic re¬
affirmation that the best and
most skilful can win . . . that
the rules of the game are the
same for everyone."
Agile legwork is a feature of
the capoeira, a form of
wrestling which originated in
Africa and has given its
name to a dance popular in
northeastern Brazil.
played in their country is characterized by
great skill in the use of both body and legs.
And perhaps, in football's exclusive reliance
upon the feet, there is a far-off, lingering
memory of capoeira, an indigenous form of
wrestling practised by the slaves brought over
from Africa, in which only the legs and feet
were used to "throw" an opponent.
Because it is a powerful force for social inte¬
gration, football has become, as it were, a dra¬
matization of many aspects of Brazilian society.
It has shown that Brazilians can act together in
a co-ordinated fashion to achieve victory. In
fact, this kind of open, positive identification is
comparatively rare in daily life in Brazil, where
most institutions seem to have lost their way
under economic pressures and a favours system
which the average citizen finds discouraging.
Football also promotes integration in that it
enables everyone to share in the experience of
victory and getting on in the world, in every¬
thing that is conjured up by the magic word
"success" something that few Brazilians are
likely to experience in a society with a strict
hierarchy and in which wealth is concentrated
in the hands of a few. The collective ecstasy of
the public at the football stadium the ecstasy
of a crowd, a prey to every form of mental and
physical anguish, that is body and soul behind
its team and its idols is no empty experience,
since it may lead on to victory.
Providing a complex spectacle, yet governed
by simple rules that everyone can understand,
football is a symbolic re-affirmation that the
best and the most skilful can win, that training,
technique and a dash of luck can bring victory
and, above all, that the rules of the game are the
same for everyone champions and minnows,
rich clubs and poor, blacks and whites, the edu¬
cated and the unlettered. In this respect football
is a school of democracy and egalitarianism. As
we watch our team performing in the grass
arena, we know that the rules of the game are
universal, that they are clear and must be res¬
pected by all, and that the referee is there to
ensure that they are respected even when pas¬
sions run high.
The spectator knows that, contrary to what
may happen in other circumstances, neither the
winners nor the losers can arbitrarily change
the rules since they transcend the desires and
impulses of the competing teams. Football
teaches us that the very immutability of these
rules is the guarantee of an alternation between
winners and losers. It is precisely because of
this association of the formal with the informal,
of rule with reality, that in Brazil and, indeed,
throughout the Third World football has
become an unparalleled focus of the emotions.
At all events, it is through football that Bra¬
zilians have, at last, come to identify with such
symbols of the nation-state as traditions, the
national anthem and the flag. It is through this
sport in which heart and head, strength and
ingenuity are allied and which gave us "fancy
footwork" (which we all need to survive) as a
national expression through football that
Brazil exists as a society and as a nation. Yes, it
was the wonderful, staggering experience of
winning three World Cups that gave us confi¬
dence in the creativity and generous spirit of
the Brazilian people.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND SPORT
i
A gymnastics class at Phnom Penh (Cambodia).
Unesco is the only organization in
the United Nations system whose
mandate covers the whole range of
problems relating to the international
development of physical education and
sport. Other institutions such as the World
Health Organization (WHO) and the Inter¬
national Labour Organisation (ILO) have
responsibilities in this field, but only in
specific areas relating to their constitu¬
tional competence sport and health and
sport in working life.
The broad thrust of Unesco's activities
in the field of sport is as follows:
Unesco supports intergovernmental
machinery concerned with the institutional
and normative aspects of sport. In 1978,
Unesco's General Conference adopted an
International Charter and created an Inter¬
governmental Committee for Physical Edu¬
cation and Sport. At the same time, an
International Fund for the Development of
Physical Education and Sport (FIDEPS) was
established. In view of the gradual disen¬
gagement of states which consider that
sport generates sufficient resources to be
self-financing, the statutes of the Fund now
enable representatives of the private sector
to sit on its Governing Board.
In 1988 an international conference of
ministers responsible for physical educa¬
tion and sport, held in Moscow, assessed
the world situation in this field and noted
the emergence of new forms of co-opera¬
tion and partnership between official and
voluntary organizations. The Conference
approved a series of eleven recommenda¬
tions, which provided a conceptual frame¬
work for action, as well as a text entitled
the Moscow Declaration, which contains
ten proposals of a general nature. A joint
declaration was adopted by Unesco and
the International Olympic Committee
(IOC) which defined common objectives
for the two organizations.
In order to reduce disparities between
countries in physical education and sport,
various activities have been and continue
to be carried out in co-operation with non¬
governmental organizations, and espe¬
cially with the International Council of
Sport Science and Physical Education. The
purpose of these activities is:
a) to encourage access to and participation
in physical education and sports of chil¬
dren and adolescents in the school system
and in the framework of non-formal edu¬
cation programmes;
b) to promote the practice of sport for all;
c) to train educators at the national,
regional and international levels;
d) to organize annual international phy¬
sical activity weeks which may form part
of a broader and more systematic pro¬
gramme entitled Fitness for Everybody;
e) to encourage the development of
research in sport science and the interna¬
tional exchange of information through the
creation of specialized facilities.
A third range of activities is designed to
safeguard and protect the ethical values of
sport: fair play, harmonious self-fulfilment,
the desire to surpass oneself, solidarity,
team spirit, self-sacrifice, loyalty, generosity,
respect for the rules and for one's adver¬
saries, mastery of aggression and violence.
These values are today threatened by forces
outside sport which are tending to reduce
sport to a money-making activity and are
leading to bitter and in some cases even
fatal confrontations. They cannot be main¬
tained by decree, even though decrees and
regulations can be useful and even indis¬
pensable. This is a task which society as a
whole must shoulder through the self-devel¬
opment that education provides. Physical
games take their meaning from the mental
climate in which they are played. L~J
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER DECEMBER 1992
EDITORIAL
Groundsforhope
by France Bequette
1f\(\Ç\will be remembered as the year of the Earth Summit at
MM/fiio. But all the talk ofgreat global threats and the major
V v rj Resolutions (which will often be hard to implement) that
were adopted should not eclipse the more modest projects, those
that work, but are rarely mentioned.
Some of these activities have been initiated by Unesco. This is
the case, for example, of projects for the establishment of news
agencies in West Africa (WANAD), Central Africa (CANAD) and
Southern and Eastern Africa (SENEAD) which, among other
things, have offered manyjournalists the opportunity ofacquiring
knowledge and understanding ofenvironmental issues. Other pro¬
jects are the result of individual initiatives. This, for instance, was
how the PIRATTES project took shape (see page 26). A young salt-
marsh workerfrom Brittany, France, on holiday in Benin, explained
how back where he lived, in Guérande, salt is extracted from sea-
water by the Sun and the wind. In Benin, ocean-salt production
depended on fire. The women there walked long distances to find
the mangrove wood they needed to boil brine down to salt.
Chopping down the mangroves, however, was destroying fish
spawning grounds and adversely affectingfishing. Later, salt-wor¬
kers from Brittany and Benin began working together, and today
fifty salt basins of the kind used in the Breton salt-marshes are in
operation. Next year, there will be twice as many, and the Breton
salt-workers, who have been taking turns to work in Benin, will
stop coming (they have already received similar requests from
Guinea and Niger).
On the other side of the Atlantic, a number of Puerto Ricans,
spurred on by a deep love of their country, set up a Conservation
Trust for the island. Their initiative came just in time. Pollution
due to waste, speculative building and the tourist industry had
begun to appear. By purchasing hundreds of hectares in the most
interesting areas, the Trust is now protecting hundreds ofanimal
and plant species, some ofthem unique.
These, and many other intelligent efforts conducted worldwide,
certainly give groundsfor hope.
^"«-ift
Dossier
by France Bequette
The salt of the
Earth: Sun, wind, and
fire
Rico saves
its treasures
30 Voices from the past
The brother and sister
who became thunder
and lightning
Alegendofthe
Caribou Eskimos
23
y.-:
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
World
The 1989 Basel Convention designed to control the
cross-border movement and disposal of hazardous
wastes came into force on 5 May 1992. The Convention
stipulates that the importing country must be provided
with detailed information on the nature of the wastes
and be in a position to treat them. Such is the case in
France, which at Saint-Vulbas, in the Ain department,
has a plant, the only one of its kind in the world, that can
destroy PCBs (polychlorinated biphenyls) without caus¬
ing any pollution, thanks to a 1,200°C incinerator. The
environmental organization Greenpeace brought pres¬
sure to bear on the French government to prevent PCBs
imported from Australia for destruction in this faci¬
lity. But if borders are closed and each state is obliged
to build such expensive, high-tech plants, is there not
a risk that more toxic wates will be illegally dumped in
natural sites?
24
Toxic waste sites are more often
found among poor communities
than in affluent districts. Most of
the 4,000 residents of Williams¬
burg, a working-class neighbour¬
hood in the northeastern part of
Brooklyn, are from the Caribbean
and Central America. A report by
the Community Environmental
Health Center at New York's
Hunter College revealed that at
least twenty-eight sites in the
Williamsburg area stored danger¬
ous, often "extremely danger¬
ous", toxic wastes. Four years
ago, a number of high school and
college students got together and
organized an action group which
they called "The Toxic Avengers".
They discovered an empty lot lit¬
tered with drums oozing toxic
liquids and called in environmen¬
tal agencies to clean it up. Since
then, the group has continued its
battle and undertaken commu¬
nity-awareness actions, teaching
that combating pollution should
be a priority just like fighting
drugs and crime.
For the past thirty years, the
World Food Programme (WFP)
has been one of the world's largest
sources of funding for activities in
developing countries aimed at
reversing environmental degrada¬
tion and increasing agricultural
productivity in sustainable ways.
In 1991 WFP, which was set up
in 1961 by the United Nations
and the Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United
Nations (FAO), undertook a review
of its environmental activities. The
11
review points out that environ¬
mentally sustainable development
must also be economically and
socially sustainable. In other
words it must be based on the
willingness of local people to parti¬
cipate in development activities in
a way that allows for them to be
sustained once external resources
are no longer provided.
Forfurther information,
please contact WFP, Via Cristoforo
Colombo 426, 00145 Rome, Italy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
During the night of 21 to 22
August 1986, Lake Nyos, located on
the volcanic rim in western
Cameroon, disgorged a vast cloud of
toxic gas which took the lives of
about 1,700 people and thousands
of cattle. Two years earlier, on 16
August 1984, a similar disaster had
taken place 100 kilometres away at
Lake Monoun, causing thirty-seven
deaths. In 1987, on Unesco's initia¬
tive, more than 200 research work¬
ers and experts met for a conference
in Yaounde, Cameroon, to try to
understand the causes of these inci¬
dents. Had there been a sudden
total or partial degasification of the
water? If so, was this due to a land¬
slide, a rockslip, a violent wind or to
an upwelling ofdeep water? Or had
a volcanic disturbance released the
gases from a subsurface reservoir?A
team from the University ofSavoy,
France, is working on a project to
bring the remaining water- trapped
gas to the surface through a system
of pipes. The quantities involved
are estimated to be 250 million
cubic metres for Lake Nyos, and 9.4
million for Lake Monoun. To avoid
another disaster, experts have set
up a buoy equipped with a satel¬
lite-transmission device, a seismic
monitoring system and meteoro¬
logical measurement platforms. In
addition, 4,000 people have been
relocated at a safe distance from
the two lakes.
If
The Brazilian state ofSäo Paulo has only been able to
conserve three per cent of its natural vegetation cover,
and erosion has caused the loss of 200 million tonnes
of soil. Such sorry figures have led to a programme for
the restoration of gallery forests in the lacare Pepira
basin, under the direction ofCarlos loly of the University
of Campinas. In recent decades, sugar-cane fields,
orange groves, grazing land, leisure areas and hydro¬
electric dam sites have made inroads into gallery forests
along the lacare Pepina river and its tributaries. So far,
250 hectares have been reforested with the help of
landowners and municipal authorities.
A remarkable book, Environ¬
mental Educationfor Our Common
Future, has just been published
jointly by the United Nations
Environment Programme, Unesco
and Norway. Designed as a hand¬
book for teachers throughout
Europe from kindergarten to secon¬
dary school, it reports, in Part I, on
the current ecological state of the
planet. Part II presents examples of
environmental education projects
in schools all over Europe, illus¬
trated with figures and photo¬
graphs. The handbook is a source of
useful and innovative educational
suggestions for all teachers, what¬
ever subject they teach. It is avail¬
able from Unesco, in English only.
\ro , ¡mental Education
for Our Common FuU
t^VI
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Dossier
m
SE SAIT OF
fl.il) B
Ulli.
by France Bequette
HOLLOWED out of tree-trunks, the
pirogues lie at rest on the
silvery-grey sand beneath
the whispering, shiny-leafed
coconut palms. Children play
around huts made of banco, a
mixture of clay and bamboo, and
roofed with leaves. This is Houakpé,
a village on the Atlantic coast of
Benin, some sixty kilometres west
of Cotonou, near Ouidah, and not
far from the Togolese border. In
lanuary 1988, Alain Courtel spent
his holiday in Benin, but it was not
mere chance that brought him to
Houakpé. Back home in Guérande,
a small French town in the depart-
Below, salt is produced from brine by solar
evaporation at the village of Kpablé (Benin).
Bottom, pans of brine are heated on wood stoves.
26
ment ofLoire-Atlantique, Alain had
spent fifteen years working in the
salt-marshes and he knew the
Atlantic ocean had two "salt peoples"
specializing in ocean-salt extrac¬
tion his fellow citizens ofGuérande
and the people in the Ouidah area.
He was also extremely interested in
the environment and development.
Alain Courtel brought with him
addresses, postcards of the Gué¬
rande marshes and a densimeter.
He toured the villages, collected
information and met Matthias Toffi,
a geographer who had left univer¬
sity to work in the field. He learned
that the region was very poor, that
fishing was in decline, that the
women ofthe village were worn out
by the exhausting labour of salt
extraction, and that supplies of the
fuelwood used in the salt-extraction
process were running out.
Courtel was surprised to learn that
salt extraction should need anywood
at all. Apparently, the methods used
locally were very different from those
he knew. In Guérande, sea-water
brought in by high tides is chan¬
nelled into shallow reservoirs
through a system ofsmall conduits.
The water then heats up and some of
it evaporates. The remaining solu¬
tion, which has a higher salt concen¬
tration, is fed bygravity into a second
basin and finally ends up in "crys¬
tallizing pans". The salt is gathered
daily from Tune to October. Each pan
yields an average of one tonne of
salt. In Guérande, about 200 salt-
marsh workers produce 10,000
tonnes of salt per year, sometimes
twice that amount in good years, like
1989. This is achieved using hardly
any tools and without harming the
environment in any way.
In Benin, the centuries-old salt-
production tradition seemed per¬
fectly satisfactory, but it turned out to
have a devastating impact on the
environment. In the dry season, the
Ouéoué lagoon recedes completely.
During that period, while the men go
fishing, the women scrape up the
salt-permeated soil, put it into large
baskets and then rinse the earth-
and-salt mixture several times with
water. An orange-coloured brine col¬
lects in bowls or calabashes placed
under the baskets. This is then
poured into a large pot built into an
"improved stove", that is, one that
needs much less fuel because it has
only one opening for the introduc¬
tion ofwood.
There may be as many as three
stoves under the roofofa single, dark
hut. Outside the heat is intense,
inside it is unbearable. Yet the
women and the children stand over
the boiling liquid, stirring it with
sticks, so that the water evaporates
more quickly. "It takes three hours of
boiling to get four kilos of salt,"
explained Toffi. To produce 135 kilo¬
grams of salt means burning one
cubic metre ofwood.
The best wood, the kind thatburns
slowly and generates practically no
ashes, comes from mangroves.
These strange-looking swamp-trees
with their exposed, stilt-like roots
reaching down into the muddy
swamp water form a forest fringe
along the shoreline and provide a
spawning ground for the fish that
dart in and out of the tangle of their
roots. By the time Courtel visited the
region, however, the mangroves
were so depleted that the women
had either to walk six to ten kilo¬
metres to fetch wood, or to buy
bundles of firewood for a small for¬
tune compared to the price that
could be obtained for the salt. About
2,000 people, mostly women, were
producing from one to one and a
half tonnes per family annually.
Courtel told Toffi about Gué¬
rande. "Where I live, in Brittany," he
explained, "they say salt is born of
the sun and the wind	 Here, it is
bom offire". Realizing all the advan¬
tages of eliminating the use of
wood the mangrove swamp would
be renewed and the fish would
return Toffi agreed to carry out an
experiment.
In the summer of 1988, the
PIRATTES project was launched.
PIRATTES stands for Projet intégré
de recherches sur l'amélioration des
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Air view of salt
concentration
ponds and
(top right)
crystallizing pans
at Guérande
(France).
techniques traditionnelles d'extrac¬
tion de sel, which is French for "inte¬
grated research project on the im¬
provement of traditional salt-
extraction techniques". The project
was financed by the French Co-ope¬
ration Mission, the French Ministry
of Co-operation, the French Anti-
Hunger Committee, the Fondation
de France and the region ofLa Baule,
in Brittany, France. In charge of the
project were the Guérande salt pro¬
ducers' group, the Benin scientific
and technical research centre and
the Association of Volunteers for
Progress a splendid example of
North-South co-operation founded
in friendship and seeking simple
solutions adapted both to the envi¬
ronment and to the conditions of
local daily life. Alain Courtel went
home to Brittany to tend to his crop
of salt, and came back to Benin in
October for a five-month stay, bring¬
ing a fellow salt-marsh worker with
him.
The first step was to meet the
Dagbo Hou-non, high priest of the
sea and chiefofthe voodoo medicine
men. Escorted by Toffi, Courtel
introduced himself as a "servant of
salt", and received a favourable wel¬
come. The next step was to get down
to work. He began by digging two
small basins in the village ofLanhou,
located at Boca del Rio, the mouth of
the river. This was no simple task.
The clay content of the soil, which
was different from the soil in
Guérande, was not homogeneous.
There were other problems: the air
humidity, the lightness of the wind,
the irregular flow ofthe tides, varia¬
tion in the salinity of the lagoon
water, and the tunnels made by little
sea-crabs known as toklins.
These difficulties were com¬
pounded by those inherent in any
yovo (White) project in Africa.
Geneviève Delbos, ethnologist at the
French National Scientific Research
Centre, who followed the experi¬
ment, explains: "The work pro¬
gressed in fits and starts due to the
fact that the salt-marsh workers had
to learn to adapt to both the phy¬
sical and the human environment
in which this collaborative effortwas
taking place. This was exacerbated
by the complexity of human rela¬
tionships in a culturewhere personal
joys and sorrows and social and
natural upheavals are always given a
traditional interpretation in terms
of the occult forces at play that are
manipulated by those who have the
fearsome and feared power of
'commanding' them."
Benin is the cradle of voodoo, a
magical country where, probably
more than anywhere else in Africa,
conciliation with the supernatural
is indispensable. One night, the
lagoon was suddenly breached, leav¬
ing a gap through which the ocean
rushed in, flooding the salt basins.
The first month's work was ruined.
There was only one solution left to
fill the salt basins with the brine the
women had collected from under
their large baskets full ofsalty earth.
The two technologies combined
beautifully.
Not everybody was totally
convinced, however. Marguerite, a
midwife who gathers salt when she is
not delivering babies, was sceptical.
We met her on a small island in the
lagoon, with two shallow basins near
the hut containing the furnace that
Marguerite's son fired with dried
palm leaves. One of the basins was
lined with a sheet of bright blue
plastic, the other with a thick layer of
clay. She picked up a fistful ofcrystals
that had formed in two months: "The
white man comes, he tells you what
to do, then he goes away. We don't
like this salt, it's too coarse. It has to
be ground." All the same, she had
agreed to try the system. But she was
too tired to attend the big party
PIRATTES threw in March to cele¬
brate the first bag ofsalt produced as
a result of the co-operative effort.
The following week, the Dagbo
Hou-non himself came to visit. He
was given an offering of djè, which is
"salt" in Fon, one of the most widely
spoken languages in Benin. He took
the opportunity to remind every¬
body that the lagoon forests were
holy and called on the voodoo spirits
to be kindly disposed to PIRATTES.
In 1992, the association was
honoured with the Technologiesans
frontières award, the highest prize
offered in the Enterprise and
Environment competition organized
by the Commission of the European
Communities.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Dossier
hito il save
mn m
1:
Children dip Into
the "touch tank"
in the
demonstration
room at the Las
Cabezas de San
Juan Nature
Reserve as part
of an educational
programme run
by the
Conservation
Trust of Puerto
Rico.
{f|"^HE Lord must have worked
overtime to create such a
beautiful island," say the
Puerto Ricans. Indeed, all its
3.5 million inhabitants seem
to be passionately attached
to this tiny (8,897 sq km) island,
formed by volcanic eruptions more
than 120 million years ago.
Puerto Rico is the smallest and
the most easterly of the islands
that comprise the Greater Antilles,
lying about 100 kilometres east of
the Dominican Republic. It was
discovered by Christopher
Columbus in 1493 and remained a
Spanish possession until 1898,
when, following the Treaty of Paris
which ended the brief Spanish
American War, it became a com¬
monwealth associated with the
United States. Puerto Ricans are
U.S. citizens with a special status.
They are exempt from federal
income taxes, and their official
language is Spanish.
Puerto Rico began to industrial¬
ize its historically agricultural eco¬
nomy just fifty years ago with a
programme called "Bootstrap",
Fomento in Spanish, which was
launched to enable the Puerto
Ricans to take their destiny into
their own hands. Pharmaceutical
products and the production of
electronic and scientific instru¬
ments are major components of
the economy. However, there is an
unemployment rate of 16 per cent.
More than half the families are on
U.S. food stamps, and 2.5 million
Puerto Ricans seek jobs and cash
on the U.S. mainland.
A passenger on a plane coming
in to land at San Juan airport sees
Puerto Rico as a green rectangle in
a turquoise-blue sea, a paradise of
white beaches lined with coconut
trees. However, Puerto Rico is a
paradise not only for tourists but
for archaeologists, botanists, and
ornithologists as well. The first
28
archaeological excavations reveal¬
ed traces of Indian groups from
northeastern South America
dating from the beginning of the
Christian era pottery, small clay
masks, and rock-carvings. The
natural environment also offers
fascinating research material,
including more than 3,000 plant
species, 232 kinds of birds, and
numerous reptiles and amphi¬
bians. Many of these plants and
animals are endemic to the island,
and some are found nowhere else
in the world.
On 24 December 1968, the
Governor of Puerto Rico, the U.S.
Secretary of the Interior, and the
Administrator of the Economic
Development Administration
decided to take action to preserve
the island's endangered treasures.
They created a Conservation
Trust, to be endowed through
contributions from petroleum
companies operating on the island
and through private, U.S. tax-
deductible charitable donations.
It was not a moment too soon.
The San Cristóbal Canyon, which
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Punta
Ballena
Biosphere
Reserve at
Guánlca (Puerto
Rico).
cuts through the heart of the
island's central mountain range
like the stroke of a sword, was
being used as a waste dump by
neighbouring towns piling up
debris and car wrecks. Dump fires
were a regular occurrence. In
1974, the Trust bought nearly 500
hectares along the northern rim
of the Canyon and gradually
cleaned it up, restoring it to the
red-tailed hawk and other wild¬
life. The Trust now plans to pur¬
chase adjacent tracts of land
along the southern rim and to
clear and mark out a system of
trails to enable visitors to discover
and learn about the site's envi¬
ronment and its wild inhabitants.
Punta Ballena, in the southwest
of the island, was threatened not
by waste but by development as a
tourist site. The setting, a forest of
mangroves and coves bordering
the Guánica State coastal dry
forest, represents such a unique
and beautiful ecosystem that, in
1985, Unesco decided to declare it
a Biosphere Reserve. After pur¬
chase from the Club Méditerranée
tourist organization of the eighty
hectares of forest, the Trust turned
this site into a protected habitat
for endangered species such as the
crested toad, the Puerto Rican
night-jar, the yellow-shouldered
blackbird, the manatee, and the
hawksbill turtle.
Further along the coast, to the
west, the threat to the Bahia
Fosforescente (Phosphorescent
Bay) of La Parguera came not only
from tourism, but also from hous¬
ing development. On dark nights,
bio-luminescent micro-orga¬
nisms, Pyrodinium bahamensis,
transform the bay into a sea of fire.
Because of the central hills and
mountains of the island, the popu¬
lation tends to press into a narrow
plain along the coastline. Had the
Trust not acquired it, the Las
Cabezas de San luán Nature
Reserve would also be a parking
area today.
Another 150-hectare site, in the
southwest of the island, was saved
by the Trust from the clutches of
speculative developers to become
the Inés María Mendoza de
Muñoz Marín Reserve. This land¬
scape of pastures and tree-lined
sandstone cliffs is home to the
grasshopper sparrow, the Puerto
Rican bullfinch, the black-whisker¬
ed vireo, and the American kestrel.
In the eastern part of the island
is another feature of great ecologi¬
cal importance, the Pterocarpus
Forest. Its trees, also called "coral
wood" because of their red sap,
have wide roots which reach down
into the marshy soil. In 1990, the
Trust purchased a 350-hectare
stretch of this forest, which is now
under its protection.
Although industrialized, densely
populated and urbanized, Puerto
Rico gives the impression of being
an oasis, with limited pollution.
The air is always clean thanks to
the trade winds, and environmen¬
tal conservation has become a
major concern. The Conservation
Trust is well-managed and effec¬
tive. The island could very well be
a model to other regions of the
world.
. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Voicesfrom thepast
mjmmm raid
«111 MIS
30
* From Intellectual
culture ofthe
Caribou Eskimos:
Iglulik and Caribou
Eskimo texts, by
Knud Rasmussen,
Copenhagen, 1930.
nn he Inuit (widely known as
Eskimos) live widely dispersed
in the Arctic regions ofAlaska,
. Greenland and Canada, but
are united by language and
culture. Their literature,
transmitted by the oral tradition,
and their remarkable plastic art,
bear witness to a profound
harmony between the people and
their environment.
The text on this page has been taken from
Compagnons du Soleil ("Companions of the Sun"),
an anthology of writing on the relationship
between humankind and nature co-published by
Umesco, Editions de la Découverte (Paris) and the
Fondation pour le progrès de l'Homme. The
anthology, which appeared in November 1992, was
prepared under the general editorship ofJoseph
Ki-Zerbo, in collaboration with Marie-Josèphe
Beaud-Gambier.
In the earliest times, there were no thieves
among mankind; but then one day it happened
during a songfestival, that a brother and sister
were left alone in a house, and here theyfound a
caribou skin with the hair off, and aftrestone.
These they stole, but hardly had they stolen them
when a greatfear oftheirfellows came upon
them.
"What shall we do to get awayfrom everyone?"
said one.
"Let us turn into caribou," said the other.
"Then people will kill us."
"Let us turn into foxes."
And so they went through all animals in turn,
and always they were afraid people would kill
them. But then one said:
"Let us turn into thunder and lightning, and
then people will not be able to catch us. "
And so they turned into thunder and lightning
and went up into the sky. When there is thunder
and lightning now, it is because one of them
rattles the dry caribou skin, while the other
strikes sparks from thefirestone.
(As told byAnarquil G.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
o shadow over sport
by Miguel Angel Bermúdez Escobar
Drawing by Blachon.
LEGEND has it that, once upon a time, a
young hunter from the north of what was
to be known much later as the continent
of America went to ask the medicine man for a
magic formula which would make him the fast¬
est and most cunning hunter in the tribe. The
medicine man told him: "Catch the first
monarch butterfly you see at the beginning of
the summer and rub the gold dust from its
wings on your chest, and you will become as
light as it is." The hunter did as he was told and
was soon darting along as swiftly as the
brilliant-hued butterfly.
We also know that the gladiators of Ancient
Rome ate the raw flesh of wild animals in order
to absorb the animals' strength and ferocity,
and that in Greece the dust and sweat from
wrestlers' bodies were used to make a tonic
prized by their admirers and would-be rivals,
who believed that it would pass on to them the
vitality and bravery of their idols.
We know from accounts left by the early
ßU_.y.>\
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
32
chroniclers of the New World that the pre-
Columbian civilizations were familiar with the
properties of plants used for curative or ritual
purposes. The Mexican Indians enlisted by
Hernán Cortés took peyotl during their
exhausting route marches, and the Indians of
the Andean regions of Bolivia, Peru, Ecuador
and Colombia chewed the leaves of the Ery-
throxylon coca shrub in order to stave off
hunger and fatigue. Coca leaves were so widely
used that they eventually became a form of cur¬
rency known as "cocada".
During the Second World War, special
rations were distributed to troops in order to
help them fight cold and fatigue and to prepare
for combat. Cannabis and other psychotropic
substances were widely used by American sol¬
diers in Viet Nam.
It is not known precisely when these prac¬
tices spread to sport although it is certain that
people in every age have sought to improve their
performance and sharpen their physical and
mental faculties. Certainly they have become
increasingly sophisticated with the progress of
science, and notably with the development of
amphetamines and anabolizing drugs.
A CONJURING TRICK
Even today, it is not easy to draw the line
between the physiological action of substances
which are capable of stimulating the body's
functions, and what is known as the placebo
effect the psychological impact and the ele¬
ment of auto-suggestion that accompany all
forms of medication.
The magical power of primitive rituals is not
altogether absent from modern sport. Trainers
and athletes alike admit that psychological
factors such as self-confidence, motivation, and
the will to win, all have a decisive influence on
results. "Neutral" foodstuffs, vitamins or injec¬
tions may have an extremely beneficial effect if
competitors are convinced that they are effec¬
tive. Substances of this kind are sometimes used
to upset other competitors, as when athletes in
the United States team at the Olympic Games
in Mexico City made a great show of inhaling
draughts of oxygen and when, in one particular
case, a runner put his opponents off their stride
before the start of a race just by lifting a per¬
fectly harmless pill to his mouth.
The result of a sporting competition depends
on a range of factors, including the athletes'
physical condition, their standard of training,
tactical skills, and psychological state. Nowa¬
days, when the results achieved in competition
are often only a hair's breadth apart, electronic
devices have to be used to measure them.
Hence, it is hard to know which of these factors
is responsible for a winning performance, and it
is even harder to tell whether the additive effect
of doping really has anything to do with it. And
supposing that doping does help to improve the
The American runner
Florence Griffith-Joyner
(far right) hoping for victory
before the start of the
women's 400-metre relay at
the Seoul Olympics, 1988.
MIGUEL ANGEL
BERMÚDEZ ESCOBAR,
of Colombia, is a specialist in
sports administration, on
which he lectures at the
University of the Rosary,
Bogota. Director-General of
his country's Institute of
Youth and Sport and vice-
president of the
Intergovernmental Committee
for Physical Education and
Sport (IGCPES), he has
played an important role in
the development of sport,
especially cycling, in
Colombia.
athlete's performance, how is it possible to
distinguish the placebo effect from that of the
chemical substance itself?
I am convinced that if it were possible to
isolate the effect of each of these factors,
doping would be found to be so counter-pro¬
ductive that no sane athlete or trainer would
follow a practice that runs counter to ethics and
is bad for the health.
Victory at any price
We all want to win because these days victory is
the key to happiness, to the earthly paradise.
Success at all costs is the motto of our modern
world.
It would have been surprising if sport had
managed to steer clear of this obsession. The fact
is that the determination to win at any price has
corrupted the sense of sportsmanship which
Baron Pierre de Coubertin wished to infuse into
the Olympic Games when he said in 1908 that
the main thing was not to win but to take part.
Why does this mentality exist? Is it because
of the sheer pleasure that people feel at win¬
ning, at coming first? We all know that this is
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
not so. The great principles that informed sport
only a few decades ago have given way to less
noble ones that are more in tune with the
consumer society in which we live.
Sporting success now offers material
rewards that bear no relation to the benefits of
sport as visualized by the Ancient Greeks or by
those who, with Pierre de Coubertin, laid the
foundations of modern sport. In addition, some
of those who profit from the exploits of ath¬
letes urge them to use, to the detriment of their
health, drugs that are capable of boosting their
short-term performance but invariably take a
heavy toll later on.
These pressures, coupled with personal
ambition and the demands of team-mates, sport¬
ing and commercial organizations, and society at
large, come to carry more weight than warnings
about the risks of doping and even the prohibi¬
tions spelt out in the rule-book.
An ethical problem
Sporting champions, then, are faced with the
awkward dilemma of whether to use drugs or
other stimulants to improve their performance
or whether to abstain and accept that their
opponents who do use them will have the edge
over them.
The advocates of doping use a battery of
arguments. They claim that the consequences
of drug-taking are less serious than the irrevers¬
ible and sometimes even mortal injuries caused
by the practice of sport itself, or that there is no
difference between taking drugs to cure illness
and using them to improve performance in
sport. None of these arguments is very convinc¬
ing. All of them conveniently gloss over the
ethical dimension of the problem.
Doping, like any other fraudulent practice
that purports to give an artificial boost to
people's physical potential, runs counter to the
very nature of sport, since it denies athletes a
chance to excel through their own unaided
endeavours. By giving an unfair advantage to
one competitor over the others, it violates the
elementary rules of competitive sport. It cor¬
rupts athletes morally and physically, under¬
mines their mental balance and the image
society has of them. It sullies the image of sport
and casts a shadow over sporting events. O 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
fallen stars by Aieksei Srebnitsky
34
ALEKSEI SREBNITSKY,
Russian journalist, is editor-
in-chief of the Moscow
newspaper Ismailovskii
Vestnik. He is a member of
the International Sporting
Press Association (ISPA) and
the author of many works on
athletes and sport.
THE other day a parcel arrived for me from
the United States at the address of what
was once the Novosti news agency,
where I worked for thirty years. Stephanie
Vogel of Seattle had discovered from my
articles in Soviet Life that I was an old friend of
Valéry Brumel, her favourite sportsman, and
asked me whether I could send her some
Brumel memorabilia postcards, catalogues,
badges, commemorative medals and suchlike.
Her parcel also contained a few ounces of
sliced dry sausage in a plastic packet, with the
following accompanying note: "I hope this will
be of some comfort to you, Brumel, in these
times of shortage."
Stephanie Vogel's gesture was not quite as
cranky as it may seem at first sight. In Soviet
Life I had chronicled the problems of the
former Olympic high-jump champion (1964)
after serious injury had prevented him from
pursuing his career in top-level competition.
Once a Soviet national hero, Brumel found
himself out of a job almost overnight. He was
no longer needed. Through a combination of
optimism and resourcefulness, he eventually
managed to survive by giving lectures and
publishing his autobiography. But by then he
had been through some very hard times indeed,
sometimes having to rely on the money he got
from returnable bottles at twelve kopeks a time
to pay for his next meal. It was only after Gor¬
bachev had introduced perestroika that Brumel
was able to draw a disablement benefit of 110
roubles a month. With that sort of income, the
ex-world-record-holder was certainly not
going to turn his nose up at the sausage sent by
his American fan.
There is nothing particularly unusual about
this story in the Soviet context. As long as
champions earn medals and foreign cur¬
rency for their country they are supported by
the state and feted by the media. But the
moment they fail to make the grade they are
left to their own devices. If they are accommo¬
dating and know how to please their superiors,
they can hope to land a job as a trainer or admin¬
istrator. But if they are independent-minded,
like Brumel, they can expect no support. That
is why, for many years, Soviet sportsmen who
were able to travel abroad often resorted to
smuggling on a grand scale so as to have some¬
thing to put away for a rainy day.
An athlete's career is a short one. The
physical effort required, unrelenting pressure
and psychological stress inevitably result in
serious traumas and premature ageing. There is
some truth in the joke about beer being better
for the health than sport. By the age of twenty-
three, young sports "veteran" Brumel had
already had a cartilage operation for a com¬
plaint that is common among high jumpers.
But not all athletes were lucky enough to get
patched up in this way. The only ones who got
help were those still capable of winning events
and breaking records. The legendary triple-
jump champion, Victor Saneyev, world record-
holder and Olympic champion in 1968 and
1976, was even sent to Finland for treatment.
When necessary, the Sports Ministry paid in
hard currency. It was just too bad for those
who were past their peak.
The sad story of
Vladimir Kissilev
We Russians are only just beginning to admit,
to our embarrassment, that the craze for drug-
taking, an activity once described as "the result
of bourgeois habits," also swept the Soviet
Union, the world's "leading worker and peas¬
ant state." At the 1980 Moscow Olympics
which were once hailed as "outstanding" and
are now regarded as "shameful" the Soviet
Union took advantage of its status as host
nation to drug its sportsmen as never before. In
athletics alone, it swept the board with fifteen
gold medals, a suspiciously high success rate
even in the absence of the Americans. Some of
the medal-winners had never been heard of
before the Games and were immediately for¬
gotten afterwards.
Vladimir Kissilev astonished everyone by
winning the shot-put event. He then completely
vanished from the public eye. Only recently did
his sad fate come to light. Drugs had taken their
toll: the ex-champion became an invalid and
several times came close to death. He eventually
managed to pull through, but the athletics offi¬
cials who had earned laurels and well-paid jobs
as a result of his exploits did not lift a finger to
help him.
As for the celebrated ice-hockey player
Victor Yakushev, he owed his salvation to a
sympathetic foreign sportsman. At the end of
his playing career he became a trainer and
enjoyed a relatively comfortable position. But a
few years later his former injuries manifested
themselves again. In. the course of an outstand¬
ing career, Yakushev had broken his femur
several times: no sooner had the bone set than
he would be sent back on to the ice rink. He
eventually contracted coxitis, which meant that
he would never be able to move again unless he
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Valéry Brumel,
Olympic high jump champion
in 1964 and world record
holder until 1973.
had a special hip operation of the kind hardly
ever performed in the Soviet Union.
Had Soviet society not slowly but surely
become more democratic, the famous Swedish
ice-hockey-player-turned businessman, Tumba-
Juhensson, would probably never have opened a
golf club in Moscow. During one of his frequent
trips to the capital he learned of the misfortune
that had struck down his former comrade and
opponent, and decided to try to raise money for
Yakushev to have an operation in Sweden. The
appeal he launched got plenty of publicity in the
media and brought in 150,000 kronor. When the
surgeons subsequently waived their fees, the
money was used to set up the Tumba Founda¬
tion, whose aim is to aid disabled sportsmen.
Yakushev was able to walk again.
Champions for sale
The wind of change which swept successively
through the Soviet Union, the Commonwealth
of Independent States (CIS) and Russia even¬
tually had repercussions in the world of sport.
Various charities were set up to help veteran
and disabled sportsmen, and a union of phy¬
sical-education, sports and tourism workers
saw the light of day.
All these organizations are driven by noble
ideals and make even nobler statements of faith,
but the country is in the throes of such eco¬
nomic chaos that it would be a mistake to expect
them to come up with a solution to everyone's
problems in the immediate future. Even so, I
have to admit to a feeling of uneasiness when 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Pole-vaulter Sergei Bubka
sets a new world record with
a Jump of 6 metres in Paris
in 1985.
36
perfectly fit young sportsmen brazenly beg for
what can only be called charity. Pair figure-skat¬
ing Olympic champion Aleksandr s Zaitsev,
husband and partner of Irina Rodnina, was
appalled to see certain sportsmen, during a press
conference at the 1 992Albertville Winter Olympic
Games, giving their bank-account numbers to the
assembled journalists and appealing, through
them, to the generosity of the public.
Since the collapse of the Iron Curtain,
dozens if not hundreds of young CIS athletes
have been offering their talents to the highest
bidders on the world market. With a few
exceptions, the terms they get offered are
modest, though better than what they could
expect at home. Sergei Bubka, who has just
settled in Germany, told me that his new athlet¬
ics club in Berlin had offered him $120,000, as
well as a very comfortable home, a car and a
number of other perks, such as free return trips
with his family to Donetsk, his home town,
whenever he wants. But Bubka is Bubka, an
unrivalled champion who deserves even better
than that. Colleagues of his in various other
disciplines accept less attractive offers, which
nevertheless guarantee them and their families a
decent living for several years.
As a result, football in the CIS has been
bled dry. Hundreds of top players have joined
professional clubs all over western Europe.
And the national ice-hockey team has been
forced to enter its B team, and sometimes even
its C team, in international championships
because its best players have been snapped up
by clubs on the other side of the Atlantic.
The altar of top-level sport
Young sportsmen do rather well, but the out¬
look for their elders is less rosy. Few manage to
hold their own like Yuri Sedykh. At thirty-
seven, he can do only one thing: throw the
hammer. But he can throw it a very long way
further than anyone else in the world. He is a
"veteran" sportsman who will make a great
contribution to athletics in France, where he has
settled with his family, and will earn a better
living than he could back home. But his is an
exceptional case. Most of those who give up
competition are doomed to a life of vegetation.
After having sacrificed their lives and their
health on the altar of top-level sport, all they
can do is sit back and hope that one of the new
mutual funds set up to help them will do its
job. But they should not expect too much.
Brumel told me, doing his best not to sound
sarcastic, that the former middleweight boxer
Boris Lagutin, who was Olympic champion in
1960 and 1964, came round one day to give him
an "exceptional allowance" of 500 roubles from
the social welfare fund.
I am told that the Yashin Fund of the
Dynamo Sports Club has set up a monthly
pension of 500 roubles for its veterans, with the
help of its football and ice-hockey teams. Some
payments have already been made. Athletes
also receive invaluable help from the Associa¬
tion XXI fund which, for example, enabled
Nikolai Balboshin, a superb wrestler who had
fallen ill and lost all hope of recovery, to get
better. There are thousands of other examples
of the way such welfare organizations have
brought back to life the expression is not too
strong former sporting stars who were in
danger of dying prematurely, such as the bas¬
ketball players Anatoly Polivda and Aleksandr
Siznenko, who at 2.42 metres is currently the
tallest man in the world.
Things are beginning to change, and sooner
or later there will be results. It is all rather
novel for us: we had got too used to leaving
everything to the state, which has other prob¬
lems on its plate at the moment.
Meanwhile, I have not yet had a chance to
give Brumel his sausage. At the moment he is in
Genoa (Italy), whose city council has given him
an award for his sporting achievements, and
where he is thinking of applying for Italian citi¬
zenship, since Russians are now entitled to dual
nationality. I am keeping the Seattle sausage for
him, as a reminder of Stephanie's thoughtful-
ness and the still recent period in his life when
things looked pretty bleak. O
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
fair play and the (ompetitive spirit
by Michel Caillât
Y
Carl Lewis of the United
States heads for a gold
medal in the long jump at
the Los Angeles Olympics in
1984.
ES, sport is an order of chivalry, an
honour, a code of ethics and aesthetics
which recruits from all classes and all
peoples, mixing them fraternally together
throughout the entire world. . . . Yes, sport is
education, the most concrete and the truest
form of education, that of character. . . . Yes,
sport is culture, because the ephemeral gestures
it describes in time and space for nothing
except the sheer pleasure of it, as Plato says
bring into broad daylight, by dramatizing
them, the most elementary values (which are
nevertheless the most profound and all-embrac¬
ing) of the peoples and of the very race itself;
culture, finally, because it creates beauty, and
creates it above all for those who have the least
opportunity to feast thereon."
With these words, in an address delivered in
1963, UNESCO's then Director-General, René
Maheu, evoked the great themes of sporting
mythology, which associate with the word
sport the values of loyalty, purity, beauty,
morality, and fraternity, and ascribe to it a
vocation that is both aesthetic and ethical.
Theory and practice
A recent arrival in the world of business, the
notion of ethics appears to be inherent in sport,
which could be said to be essentially ethical. It
rests on a series of powerful myths: the myth
that sport has always existed (that it is non-
historical); the myth that sport and human
nature originated in very early times (man as a
sporting animal); and the myth that sport has
somehow been led astray, perverted, hijacked.
The distinction made between sport practised
for its own sake and sport exclusively geared to
success makes for all kinds of hair-splitting
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
A free-fall monoski
parachutist in action.
about the extent to which an ideal which was
wishful thinking in any case has been cor¬
rupted.
What do we mean by sport? A common-
sense definition might include all forms of acti¬
vity requiring some degree of physical effort,
ranging from cycling with friends to the World
Cup final. But this definition is too broad to be
useful. A stricter definition would have us see
sport as an institutionalized competitive phy¬
sical activity that is structurally and historically
linked to industrial society. As a physical pur¬
suit that is most prevalent in societies where
competition is widespread, sport is simulta¬
neously a contest governed by rules and a
system in which human bodies are ranked
according to their performance. Competitive
sports involving physical activity whose prime
feature is a systematic striving for achievement
are thus a relatively recent social phenomenon.
Sport as we know it today has not always
existed. We therefore have to ask ourselves
what values present-day sport really embodies
and whether there is not an unbridgeable gap
between the values it purports to represent and
those which it actually brings into play.
Morality
and religion
Kant said that the postulate of morality is the
existence of God. Pierre de Coubertin, the man
who revived the Olympic Games, also took the
idea of religion as a basis for moral precepts. In
A la jeunesse sportive de toutes les nations
(1927), he states: "By renovating an institution
twenty-five centuries old, we wanted you again
to become devotees of the religion of sport as
envisioned by our great forebears. In the
modern world, so full of challenging prospects
yet so beset by the perils of decline, the
Olympic movement can become a school as
much of high and pure moral principles as of
endurance and physical energy." Coubertin
was convinced that sport, like religion, was
"closely bound to morality". Like religion,
sport offers reassurance and consolation.
Widespread practice of sport would be the
foundation of far-reaching social and ethical
reform capable of shaping a new civilization.
Sport was to rid society of ills such as alcoho¬
lism, moral depravity, wrong-doing, idleness,
and wanton eroticism, and bring about har¬
mony within nations, by settling the question
of the class struggle once and for all.
What Coubertin called his philosophico-
religious doctrine has inspired the vast majority
of thinkers, journalists and writers past and
present who believe implicitly in the thera¬
peutic virtues of sport and its purported ability
to "perfect the soul by perfecting the body". In
1942, in the middle of the war, Maurice Baquet,
the theoretician of the French Communist
Party, wrote that competitive physical activity
brings us closer to "the creation of the ancient
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
In 1990, 80 European
parachutists over Niort
(France) set a new women's
world record for the largest
free-fall parachute formation.
MICHEL CAILLAT,
of France, has published
several books on sport
including L'idéologie du sport
en France (1989; "The
Ideology of Sport in France")
and Sport en miettes (1981;
"Sport in Smithereens"). He
is also the co-author of
studies on the Olympic
movement and on the world
of football.
ideal of man as beautiful, good and brave both
on and off the sportsfield". Some twelve years
later, at the other end of the French political
spectrum, the Gaullist Essai de doctrine du
sport noted that "the moral essence of sporting
activity is not unselfishness but loyalty. . . . Fair
play is the basic tenet of sport. . . . Fairness gua¬
rantees the authenticity of the values estab¬
lished on the field. It brings a human quality to
the world of sport. ... As a factor of individual
self-fulfilment and as an indispensable element
of social organization, sport contributes to
human advancement".
When people talk about sport, they always
seem to be talking about what ought to be
rather than what is. Sport has always been in
jeopardy. The hour of its birth was the hour
when the first symptoms of its sickness
appeared and the first anguished calls for a cure
were made. As long ago as 1902, Pierre de
Coubertin denounced the immorality of row¬
dyism and pleaded that sport should be allowed
to flourish in an atmosphere of disinterestedness
and chivalry. Institutionalized sport is being
undermined by money, violence, cheating,
politicization, nationalism and doping. But
those who worship sport regularly demand that
"this scandalous state of affairs should be
brought to an end and the moral code of sport
should be defended". Perhaps this is a good
moment to ask point-blank whether there is a
morality of sport.
Infringements
of human rights
From an ethical standpoint, it is impossible to
justify an action solely on the grounds of its
effectiveness. This being so, does it make sense
to talk of ethics in competitive sport? Athletes,
whatever their level, are trained for the single-
minded pursuit of victory victory over an
opposing team, victory over themselves or the
weather, or victory for their country. This gives
rise to sport's great illusion the omnipotence
of the athlete's body. Yet competitive sport
above all entails dispossession of the body,
which is dragged into the maw of the system
too soon (the problem of intensive training at
an early age tends to be overlooked), roboti-
cized by attempts to achieve maximum 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Below, opening ceremony of
the eleventh Olympic Games,
Berlin 1936.
Below right, master and
pupil. The question of how
much training young
athletes should do is a
controversial one.
efficiency, bruised and scarred by self-inflicted
suffering, risk-taking and injury, dominated,
regimented, alienated, and turned into a com¬
modity. In this mad race for achievement, in-
strumentalized athletes will do anything to see
the colours of their country, region or village
hoisted atop the flagpole.
The moral code governing competitive
sport is one of effort, sacrifice and violence,
symbolic or otherwise. In the sporting system,
athletes are sorted and classified, singled out,
eliminated and selected. Athletes, whether they
are champions or run-of-the-mill performers,
have a kind of love-hate relationship with their
bodies. They have to go to the limits of their
capacities in order to experience intense joy in
the midst of agonizing pain. This is "asceticism
in joy" but also a form of moral indoctrination,
since it imposes values like elitism, abstinence,
submission, obedience and deprivation that are
the cement binding our society together.
To talk of an ethic of competitive sport is to
express a belief in the innate purity of sport, in
an ideal perverted by society and the use that is
made of it. It is also to refuse to see that sport
has all too often been an accomplice of human
rights abuses. In 1936, the sporting movement,
supported by political circles and the press, had
no scruples about holding the eleventh
Olympic Games in Berlin. In 1956, the Mel¬
bourne Games were inaugurated at the very
moment when Soviet tanks were "pacifying"
their fraternal state of Hungary. Twelve years
later, in Mexico City, the Olympic flame was
lit only a few days after Warsaw Pact troops
had invaded Czechoslovakia and only a few
hours after a demonstration by Mexican stu¬
dents and workers on the "Square of Three
Cultures" had been ruthlessly put down, with
forty deaths. In 1978, the World Soccer Cup
held in Argentina, where people were then
disappearing or being murdered in their thou¬
sands, took place only a few metres away from
a place where people had been tortured. Is it
acceptable for a major sporting competition to
be held in a country where there are massive
and systematic human rights violations? This
issue was raised again in 1980 by those who
wished to boycott the Moscow Olympics.
Once again, the sporting community of
players, journalists and administrators fell back
behind an inflexible and unacceptable line of
defence: sport and politics do not mix.
From the Berlin Olympics to the Moscow-
Olympics, a long list of events paint a sorry pic¬
ture of the Olympic ideal and sporting ethics.
Sport is the darling of governments, as long as it
causes no trouble. It is a world of phantasms, a
quest for the absolute, not for truth. Writing of
the moral value of the scientific outlook,
Stendhal proclaimed his enthusiasm for mathe¬
matics, in which "hypocrisy is impossible". By
subscribing to what Marcel Mauss called "an
obligatory belief of society", athletes and specta¬
tors agree to pull the wool over their own eyes
and participate in a form of hypocrisy. O
».* "1 - ' ~-v -
' ' 1 » * 1 'f
40 **'.. .
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Save Our Sports by Roland Renson
Women of the Canela people
(Brazil) take part in a log
C:
i
i OMPARED to what we usually describe as
"modern sports", that is to say the
highly standardized Olympic disciplines
that are practised in many parts of the world,
traditional sports and games tend to be
confined to a limited geographical area and are
often referred to as "national" or "local". They
are regarded as symbols of ethnic or regional
identity and are called "folk games" by analogy
with "folk music" or "folk dance". Such a
"folk-lorization" of traditional sports can have
both positive and negative consequences.
The positive effect is that the conscious "tra-
ditionalization" of certain sporting activities
provides them with a kind of cultural charter for
their protection. Such a charter should,
however, not be aimed at preserving them in a
reservation or in a folklore museum, where they
can be peered at by spectators or tourists. They
should be conserved actively by being incorpo¬
rated into our culture of play and movement.
It was a curious quirk of history that the
typical sports of Victorian Britain should have
been given international prominence as symbols
of progress by the French Baron Pierre de Cou
bertin (1863-1937). These "modern sports"
became part of a new dynamic life-style of the
social elite, the so-called "leisure class". In
contrast to the international breakthrough of the
modern sports movement around the turn of
the century, local traditional sports and games
gradually came to be regarded as the anachro¬
nistic remnants of a static and rustic pre-indus-
trial society. The same process is occurring
today, but it has now been "exported" to Third
World countries.
In much the same way as these countries
tend to regard the growing ecological aware¬
ness in the Western world as a luxury they
cannot afford, they have also set themselves
other technological and economic priorities
than the protection of their traditional sports
and games. Moreover, it is tempting for them
to invest in success in the international sporting
arena in order to gain worldwide recognition
and status. This combined process of moderni¬
zation and sportification, with its imitation of
the Western cultural model, has even been des¬
cribed as a symptom of colonization.
In this article we define traditional sports as 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Athletes of the Indonesian
island of Nias are renowned
for their prowess as high
jumpers.
42
"sports which already existed or had their roots
in physical activities before the spread of
modern internationally organized sport". A
limited sample of traditional sports has been
chosen to illustrate this heritage.
Ball games
There is a rich variety of traditional ball games.
They can either be played by hand or foot or
with a batting device. Traditional European
team-handball games include pärkspel on the
Swedish island of Gotland, kaatsen in the
Dutch province of Frisia, balle pelote in Bel¬
gium and France, pallone elástico in Italy and
pelota in Spanish Valencia or in the Basque
country. Most of the ancient and violent foot¬
ball forms have disappeared and have been
replaced by modern soccer, except for the tra¬
ditional calcio florentino in Florence (Italy).
In many southeast Asian countries, sepak, a
kind of "foot-volley-ball", is played with a
light rattan ball. In Meso- and South America,
various traditional rubber-ball games were
played using head, hand or elbow, hip or foot.
Most of them have vanished today but they are
sometimes re-enacted as tourist attractions.
Some ball games, such as Gaelic football in
Ireland and Australian or New Zealand rules
football, are played with both hands and feet.
All kinds of batting devices are used, from rac¬
quets, as in real tennis and in France's longue
paume game, to the sticks which are used to
play crosse, a variant of golf played in northern
France and Belgium. A traditional stick-ball
game played by the North American Indians
was also called crosse by the early French
explorers and is now known as lacrosse. Other
ball games make use of a tambourine (France
and Italy), a forearm cover or "bracchiale", as
in the Italian pallone, or a "chistera" in the
spectacular jai alai of the Basques.
Bowl and
pin games
Bowl games are played with a solid spherical
object that is either rolled or thrown at a target.
In pin games, targets are knocked down. Italian
bocee and the French jeu de boules are now
played far from their original home countries.
A special case is the game of closh, which at the
time of Erasmus (1469-1536) and Brueghel the
Elder (1525-1569) was popular all over Europe.
In this game a shovel-shaped bat is used to roll
a heavy round bowl through an iron ring fixed
in the ground. Apart from the well-known flat
green bowls, which spread from England to the
former British colonies, a wide variety of bowl¬
ing games are found in Britain and in the cen¬
tral and southern European countries.
The modern American game of tenpin bowl¬
ing has several historical variants, some of which
are highly standardized and mechanized, such as
kegeln in Germany and bordering countries.
Other pin games range from Karelian pins, in
which a stick is thrown instead of a bowl, to
pendelkegeln (Germany), in which the bowl
swung at the pins hangs on a wire.
Throwing
games
Throwing a stick or a stone as far as possible or
to hit a target is a basic human movement pat¬
tern. It appears in the modern athletic events of
javelin, discus and hammer throwing, and in
shot putting. In Sweden's traditional varpa
game the projectiles are heavy discs. Smaller
discs or coins, or sometimes stones, are used in
both children's and adult throwing games all
over the world. Javelin throwing is still practised
by several peoples, not only as a form of train¬
ing for combat or hunting, but also for recre¬
ational and competitive purposes. Such games
are reported in many parts of South America.
North American Indians have revived the game
of "snow snake", in which a short spear is
hurled as far as possible along a track in the
snow. Hammer throwing and tossing the caber
are typical events of the well-known Scottish
Highland Games. A log-throwing event vir¬
tually identical to caber-tossing is found in Por¬
tugal, where it is known asjogo dopanco, and in
Sweden, where it goes by the name of st'dng-
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Terra-cotta figurine probably
depicting a pelota player.
Dating from around 900-
1350, it was discovered at
Colima (Mexico).
In the Sudan, Nuba wrestlers
prepare for a match.
storming. Stone putting is practised in the tradi¬
tional festivals of Swiss farmers in the Alps.
The game known as road bowls in Ireland,
klootscbieten in the Netherlands and bosseln or
klootschiessen in East Frisia (Germany), is an
interesting example both of the expression of
regional ethnic identity and of the growing
international awareness of traditional games. In
1969, these three independent groups of bowl¬
ing enthusiasts joined together to form the
International Bowl Playing Association.
Shooting games
Shooting games have flourished in all cultures
and have evolved into modern high-tech sports.
Popinjay shooting, in which the target is a "jay"
or set of "jays" attached to a tall mast, is depicted
in many medieval and Renaissance paintings and
prints and is still a very popular traditional sport
in Flanders (Belgium). It even featured in the
1920 Antwerp Olympic Games. The target
shooting practised by Japanese samurai and Zen
priests is another example of the art of archery.
Some present-day crossbow guilds in Flanders
originated in the fourteenth and fifteenth centu¬
ries and can thus be considered as the first sports
clubs in Europe. The impressive crossbow shoot¬
ing festivals of the Italian balestrieri, such as are
held in the magnificent city of Gubbio in the
Umbrian hills and elsewhere, also have a long
historical pedigree. Witnessing the pageantry of
such competitions of crossbowmen competing
to win a flag ("palio") is like stepping back into
the living past.
When firearms were introduced, many
archery and crossbow societies replaced their
traditional weapons with culverins or carbines.
These associations of riflemen, especially in
Germany and Austria, but also in Denmark, are
highly organized and have preserved to a
notable extent their character as patriarchal
men's clubs, especially in rural areas.
Fighting games
Wrestling is probably the oldest and the most
universal traditional sport of humankind. So-
called Graeco-Roman wrestling, which has
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Yabusame, a form of archery
on horseback practised in
Japan since the 11th
century, is also a form of
meditation in Zen Buddhism.
Three targets are set up
beside a 218-metre-long
track for the archer,
traditionally a samurai, to
shoot at as he gallops along.
44
ROLAND RENSON,
of Belgium, is head of the
research unit in Sociocultural
Kin a nth ropo logy at the
Institute of Physical
Education at Leuven. In 1990
he was elected President of
the International Society for
the History of Sport and
Physical Education. He is the
author of a number of books
on traditional sports and
games, including, with
V. van Mele, Traditional
Games in South America
(1992), which has been
published under the auspices
of the International Council of
Sport Science and Physical
Education with financial
support from Unesco.
acquired official Olympic status, has no connec¬
tion with the wrestling styles of Greek and
Roman Antiquity, and the type of wrestling
practised during the ancient Olympic Games
has much more in common with present-day
pelivan (Turkish wrestling) or even with
modern judo. In Japan, sumo wrestling is
considered as the most typical national sport.
Wrestling is Africa's most widespread tradi¬
tional sport. The fierce wrestling of the Nuba
people in Sudan is particularly famous. Tradi¬
tional African wrestling is, however, rapidly
changing or disappearing and being replaced by
sports such as boxing and karate. Attempts are
currently being made to establish an interna¬
tional federation of traditional wrestling styles.
In Europe, international competitions have
already been staged, in which glima wrestlers
from Iceland were matched with adepts of the
lucha canaria wrestling style practised in the
Canary Islands. Moreover, an International
Federation of Celtic Wrestling was founded in
1985, bringing together Icelandic glima, Scottish
backhold and Breton gouren.
Tilting, the favourite sport of the knights of
medieval Europe, was officially abolished in
France in 1559 when King Henri II was mor¬
tally wounded in a confrontation with his cap¬
tain of the guard. However, some of its variants
have survived. They include ring tilting and
quintain, which can be practised either on land
or water, as in the case of joutes girondines in
France and the Fischerstechen in Germany.
The martial arts are practised all over the
world. Many of these sports have been highly
ritualized and stylized in an endeavour to make
them less lethal. Special protective gear is worn
by practitioners of such dangerous sports as
Kendo (Japan), and fencing, the latter of which
has had Olympic status since the first modern
Olympic Games were held in Athens in 1896.
Animal games
Several animal games have gained a reputation
as "blood sports" in the course of history and
have been officially abandoned in many coun¬
tries. Such cruel sports as bull-baiting and bear-
baiting were popular in medieval and sixteenth-
and seventeenth-century England, but these
baitings, in which specially trained bulldogs
were used, have not survived the so-called civi¬
lizing process. Cockfighting, however, is still
very popular in southeast Asia, especially in
Indonesia and the Philippines, and in the north
of France. In some countries where cockfights
are illegal, these games still have their clandes¬
tine but loyal supporters. Animals are also
matched in fair competitions, as in pigeon
racing and dog racing.
In most of these animal competitions,
people train and coach the animals. In other
cases, people engage in a direct and hazardous
confrontation with animals, as in North Amer¬
ican rodeos, bull-running in France and Spain,
and bull-fighting in France, Mexico, Portugal
and Spain.
Locomotion
games
Some traditional races with a cultic significance
still exist. The Tarahumara Indians of Mexico
take part in a kickball race during which run¬
ners may cover over 300 kilometres in forty-
eight hours as they run barefoot over rocky
mountain trails, kicking a small hardwood ball
in front of them. Another fantastic running feat
is the log race of the Timbira and Kraho
Indians of Brazil. In these annual relay races,
each of two rival teams has to carry a heavy log
over a considerable distance. All the partici¬
pants have to run the entire route but relays
take place every 100-150 metres. The race is
widely seen as an act of worship, and so the
concept of "achievement" seems more appro¬
priate to describe it than that of "competition".
The Watusi of Rwanda in Africa and the
inhabitants of the Indonesian island of Nias are
famed for their prowess as high jumpers. In
each place the jumpers use an inclined stone to
take off, but whereas Watusi athletes try to
clear a horizontal wooden bar, their Nias coun¬
terparts jump over a solid stone wall.
Among nomadic peoples who depend
almost entirely for their subsistence on their
reindeer, horses or camels, traditional sports
tend to highlight riding skills. Striking examples
include the reindeer-sledge races of the Sami
people of Norway, Sweden, and Finland,
Afghanistan's buzkashi game in which two
teams of horsemen vie with each other to cap¬
ture the carcass of a calf, or the annual King's
camel race in Saudi Arabia, in which almost
3,000 contestants take part. The famous Palio of
Siena, a traditional annual horse-race in the very
heart of this old Italian town, attracts so many
visitors that it is now held twice a year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
A bullfight at Pamplona
(Spain).
Acrobatics
Because of the limitations of the human
neuro-muscular system, which has hardly
changed since the emergence of homo sapiens,
acrobatic performances are strikingly similar
regardless of historical periods or cultures.
The acrobatics that we see in the modern
circus are, for example, very similar to those
performed in the arenas of ancient Rome. Nor
are the vaults and somersaults of modern
gymnastics very different from the tumbling
exercises described in 1599 by the Italian pro¬
fessional acrobat Tuccaro (1536-1604). The
"Cong-Fou" gymnastic exercises of the Chi¬
nese Taoist monks described by the French
Jesuit Amiot (1718-1793) had so much in
common with the Swedish gymnastics system
of Per Henrik Ling (1776-1839) that the
French physician Nicolas Dally (1859) was
tempted to believe that Ling had simply
copied them.
In all cultures, people try to keep in good
physical shape by performing coded sets of
physical exercises which arc clearly linked to
the ideological superstructure. These cover a
wide range, from Zen meditation, Tai Chi, and
yoga in the Eastern cultural hemisphere, to
aerobics, aquabics and callanatics in the Wes
tern world. A striking example of such tradi¬
tional acrobatics are the castellers or human
pyramids formed by amateur gymnasts in Bar¬
celona (Spain) as towering symbols of their
Catalan identity.
Traditional sports and games are too often
treated as the "Cinderellas" of modern sports.
It should not be forgotten, however, that these
traditional sports and games are at the origin of
almost all modern sports and that they may
offer a welcome alternative to a worldwide pro¬
cess of uniform "sportification", which tends
to reduce the great variety of past and present
forms of play to the narrow category repre¬
sented by modern competitive sports.
With the radical sociocultural and eco¬
nomic changes that are turning the world into
a single "global village", there is a risk that
many traditional sports may be lost for ever.
Traditional sports are important aspects of our
cultural heritage and deserve to be studied
more carefully. Analysis of this heritage could
help us to rethink and modify certain negative
aspects of modern sports. Traditional sports
should no longer play the role of barefoot
Cinderella. The time has come for them to
step into the boots of Tom Thumb and to
stand up and speak out. ö
>
.is*
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
NEWSBRIEFS
46
PIERRE DE COUBERTIN
INTERNATIONAL FAIR PLAY
AWARDS FOR 1991
Each year since 1964, the
UrMEsco-supported International
Fair Play Committeee has
awarded trophies to sportsmen
and women, personalities from
the world of sport and sports
institutions which have
distinguished themselves
through their exemplary
behaviour. Over a hundred
prizewinners have been
honoured so far.
On 15 October 1992, the
Director-General of Unesco
presented the trophies for 1991
to the following laureates:
» Robert Veghelyi (Hungary),
fencing
During the men's épée
competition of the World Cadet
Championships in Foggia (Italy),
Robert Veghelyi was fencing
against Seamus Robinson of
Australia for a last hit that would
give him a place in the final.
Veghelyi attacked and his green
light came on. The president of
the jury awarded him the hit and
the Hungarian team exploded
with joy. Veghelyi then informed
the jury that the hit had been on
the floor, and that this had
passed unnoticed. The point
was annulled, replayed, and won
by Robinson, who eventually
won the final. His title of world
champion owed much to Robert
Veghelyi's spirit of fair play.
*- Racing Club de France,
rugby
In the semi-final of the French
championship, the RCFteam
was playing against Toulouse. In
the 24th minute, a Toulouse
player tried to score a drop goal
but the ball went just under the
bar. The referee, dazzled by the
Sun, allowed the goal. The RCF
players saw that the goal was
invalid but nevertheless
accepted the referee's decision
without protest. Toulouse won
the match by one point, 13 to
12. After the match the RCF
players explained that they were
not in the habit of discussing a
referee's decision and that
anyway they could have won if
only they had played better.
*- Arthur Ashe (United States),
tennis
This outstanding champion has
been hailed by his peers for his
attitude of fair play throughout
his career as a professional
tennis player. He was the first
black athlete to win the Grand
Slam tournaments: the U.S.
Open in 1968, the Australian
Open in 1970, Wimbledon in
1971. Since his retirement, he
has continued to embody the
chivalrous spirit he showed on
the courts by using his prestige
as a former champion in social
and educational action to
promote human dignity.
UNESCO, NGOS AND THE
PRIVATE SECTOR-A
SUCCESSFUL PARTNERSHIP
Unesco's International Fund for
the Development of Physical
Education and Sport (FIDEPS) is
looking for ways of encouraging
the design and construction of
sports facilities in developing
countries, thereby helping to
reduce the disparities that exist
in this field between rich and
poor nations.
With the support of ASC (Art,
Sport, Culture) the
International Association for the
Promotion of Physical and
Cultural Activities a non¬
governmental organization
whose members include leading
figures in sport, the arts,
culture and economics, the Fund
organized an architecture
competition in 1988. Architects
were asked to design
inexpensive modular sports
facilities that could be built with
local materials and local skills.
In 1991 the BMW/France
Foundation agreed to take this
theme for its biennial
Architecture and Industrial
Design Competition. This was
not the first joint enterprise of
this kind, since in 1990 BMW
helped to organize the Paris-
Astrakhan motorcycle rally, part
of Unesco's Silk Roads project.
This successful partnership
will continue in 1993 with the
forthcoming Architecture and
Industrial Design Competition of
the BMW/France Foundation,
which will be concerned with
the environment, the city and
the car.
INTERNATIONAL
VOLUNTEER DAY
This year Unesco is again joining
with the United Nations
Development Programme
(UNDP) and the United Nations
Volunteers to celebrate
International Volunteer Day on 5
December. In 1991 the Day was
marked by many successful
events, including a week of
antipollution activities in Ghana,
tree planting projects in
Mauritania, Indonesia and
Ghana, the opening of a free
medical clinic in Jamaica, a
special day of hospital work in
Berne (Switzerland), and public
meetings and media campaigns
all over the world.
The United Nations
Volunteers Programme, under
the auspices of UNDP, offers
young professionals from all
over the world the opportunity to
take part in development
activities. Since it was created
in 1970, over 7,000 volunteers
have served in the field, living in
contact with the needy and
offering their competence and
experience in fields as different
as hydrology, teaching, civil
engineering and public health.
Unesco is associated with
this programme notably through
the Co-ordinating Committee for
International Voluntary Service,
a non-governmental organization
founded under Unesco auspices
in 1948. It has 130 member
organizations which will be
taking part, alongside many
other local and national
volunteer associations, in
special activities planned for
International Volunteer Day on 5
December. O
Commentary
by
Federico
Mayor
This article is one of
a señes in which the
Director-General of
Unesco sets out his
thinking on matters of
current concern
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The sporting ideal
THIS Olympic year has, once again, given us
all an opportunity to appreciate the impor¬
tance of the sporting spirit and universal
values whose flame burns as brightly as ever in
the world's athletes. In Barcelona I was able to
witness the universal appeal of the Games for
myself. Over 10,000 athletes, 65,000 spectators in
the Montjuic Stadium and close on three-and-a-
half billion television viewers were united during
the opening ceremony in an ardent desire to cele¬
brate the sporting ideal.
Observing that vast and motley crowd, I was
reminded of the words of Baron Pierre de Cou¬
bertin: "The ideal sports spectator is an athlete
who has taken a break from his or her own exer¬
tions to watch the performance of a more skilful
or better trained fellow athlete". Of course ath¬
letes watching as spectators are fully conversant
with the rules of the sport and the controlled
movement it involves; they are in a better posi¬
tion to judge the technical and tactical aspects of a
competitor's performance. But in a world where
the mass media make it possible for the peoples of
the five inhabited continents to follow Olympic
events as they take place, the spectator has
become considerably more sophisticated. Nowa¬
days, while often thrilled by the excitement of the
spectacle, the amateur has learnt to appreciate the
aesthetic quality of movement and excellence of
performance.
We all also know, alas, that spectators and ath¬
letes sometimes behave in a way that can mar the
educational function of sport. I shall not dwell on
the reasons for these lapses for which remedies
exist and which have been analysed and
condemned by all who strive tirelessly to defend
the sporting ethic. I shall simply lay stress for it
seems to me to be crucial on the need to encour¬
age fair play from the earliest possible age, at
school and through youth movements and asso¬
ciations, with the assistance of the media.
At its most recent session, UNESCO's General
Conference added an article to the International
Charter of Physical Education and Sport in which
it called on public authorities, specialized non¬
governmental organizations, the Olympic Move¬
ment, the world of sport, educators, health pro¬
fessionals, parents, and particularly the media, to
co-operate in averting the harmful influences that
threaten sport.
Happily, the harmful trends are counter¬
balanced by the exhilarating images that remain
etched in our memories. I am thinking of the
behaviour of the winners of the trophies awarded
annually by the International Fair Play Com¬
mittee as a tribute to the moral and sporting
qualities of athletes representing a multiplicity of
nationalities and sports.
I am also thinking of two athletes who ran in
the women's 10,000 metres at the last Olympic
Games. These two African women, whom poli¬
tics had put in opposing camps, found themselves
united by sport; running shoulder to shoulder,
they acknowledged each other's existence in their
shared effort. The image of the lap of honour they
ran together after the race, hand in hand, pro¬
jected the glow of fellowship in sport to the four
corners of the Earth. O
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Islands in majesty: Nobel
by Edouard J. Maunick
HBHRMHHHEmMPVV S599MSWI : i
48
ONE summer evening in 1962, in Castries, the capital of St.
Lucia, I went to see a play, The Malfinis. After the per¬
formance, I made a point of going up to the author,
Roderick Walcott, and telling him how much I had enjoyed his
work. Roderick thanked me for my compliments, but confided
to me with a smile that his talent stood no comparison to that of
his twin brother Derek.
My curiosity was aroused and I knew that I would not rest
until I had met Derek Walcott, who was then living not in St.
Lucia but in Trinidad. In the meantime I bought a copy of the only
book of his that I could get hold of. Entitled In a Green Night
(1962), it was a collection of poems of rare quality. To read it was
to enter the presence of a shaper of words fit for a teller of islands:
his own, as one of many other islands in the Caribbean, but more
than this, as partaking of the universal although none of its quid¬
dities was denied, neglected or ignored. Here was a profound
voice, in its utterances and in its silences. A voice which I was later
to encounter in other collections of Derek Walcott 's work: The
Castaway and Other Poems (1965), Sea Grapes (1976), The Fortu¬
nate Traveller (1982), The Arkansas Testament (1987) one of my
particular favourites but this is only a partial list.
When I eventually did meet Derek Walcott in Berlin in 1964
at a get-together of Black and Western writers and poets it was
as if we had always known each other. No ceremony, no pedantic
talk: just a warm, simple handshake, a dinner with beer, and a
long walk through the streets of Berlin during which we made no
attempt to pick at the wounds of a past heavy with night and fog.
All that mattered was our own inner Suns, which we want to
shine out to the world from our poetry. We spoke English, a bit
of French, and a lot of Creole. Strangely enough, the patois of St.
Lucia is very similar to that spoken in Mauritius. We were on
common ground.
Now that he has been awarded the Nobel Prize for Litera¬
ture, I am happy for him and for poetry, but also for the islands.
By honouring Derek Walcott, without in any way belittling the
genius of this immense poet, the jury salutes him for sailing to his
own compass, of braving winds and tides, and bringing his native
St. Lucia and with her the islands of all the seas in the world
safely to port.
It goes without saying that when a poet's work is hoisted to
such pinnacles of international recognition, it is bound to attract
widespread public interest. And a good thing too. But what a pity
that we have to wait for an event of this kind before a poet's voice
is heard and listened to. I don't know how widely or how well
Derek Walcott has been translated, but I do know that in France,
for example, no collection of his work was published until last
October, when Editions Circé of Strasbourg brought out a trans¬
lation by Claire Malroux of The Star-Apple Kingdom (1979).'
And yet much had been done over the years I am thinking of
translations published in the magazine Présence Africaine to
draw attention to the existence and range of a major body of
work, one which had, incidentally, won considerable recognition
in England, a stone's throw away from Paris.
It is constantly being drummed into us that nobody reads
poetry any more, a euphemism for the fact that not much poetry
gets into print. Publishers and readers although poets them¬
selves are not wholly blameless do not realize that to ostracize
poetry is to condemn the most consummate form of prayer,
whether it comes from the mouths of believers or pagans. I feel
that this has to be said. Best-sellers have abolished miracles;
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Prizewinner Derek Walcott
syrupy stories anaesthetize us with their blandness, and magnify
trivialities into high drama. Pseudo-poets, for all the world like
pirates on dry land, bore us with hard-luck stories of interminable
length that is when they aren't busy claiming to be the popes of
phantom churches, speaking for congregations of which they are
the only member. But enough of that! Let us render to the voice
its full measure, and to words the magic of saying. Poetry is not a
luxury, a sweet; it is a necessity, it is sustenance itself.
When Derek Walcott writes (I take a few lines at random
from his collection The Fortunate Traveller):
The moon shines like a lost button;
the black water stinks under the sodium lights on
the wharf. The night is turned on asfirmly
as a switch, dishes clatter behind bright windows,
I walk along the walls with occasional shadows
that say nothing. Sometimes, in narrow doors
there are old men playing the same quiet games
cards, draughts, dominoes. I give them names.
The night is companionable, the day is as fierce as
our human future anywhere. I can understand
Borges's blind love ofBuenos Aires,
how a man feels the veins ofa city swell in his hand \
he is not only telling his own story, he is telling ours, too. He
whispers to us the delicious temptation to look around so that we
can see, feel, experience the moment as a piece of eternity. He
summons us to our own assembly, wherever we may be from.
And he often awakens in each of us the possibility of our own
personal Odyssey. Again I quote:
At the end of this sentence, rain will begin.
At the rain's edge, a sail.
Slowly the sail will lose sight of islands;
into a mist will go the belief in harbors
ofan entire race.
The ten-years war is finished.
Helen's hair, a gray cloud.
Troy, a white ashpit
by the drizzling sea.
The drizzle tightens like the strings ofa harp.
A man with clouded eyes picks up the rain
and plucks the first line of the Odyssey. 3
1 Le royaume du fruit-étoile.
2 From "Port of Spain" in The Fortunate Traveller, Faber & Faber © 1982,
by Derek Walcott
3 "Archipelagoes", in the collection cited above.
EDOUARD J. MAUNICK, Mauritian poet and writer, is the author of a
number of books including Ensoleillé vif (Apollinaire Prize, 1976), Antholo-^ ACk
gies personnelles (1984) and Paroles pour solder la mer (1989). ^w
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
50
WOMEN AND THE
ENVIRONMENT
Your March 1992 issue ("Women
Speak Out on the Environment")
provided excellent coverage of
women's concerns for the future of the
Earth. The editorial staff, and
especially your consultant, Judithe
Bizot, deserve our congratulations and
appreciation for this coverage.
At the United Nations Conference
on Environment and Development, in
Rio, WorldWIDE Network (Women in
Development and Environment) held
a special workshop on "Women's
Voices on Community Action for
Environmental Management".
On behalf of the Board of
WorldWIDE Network, we look forward
to further coverage ofwomen and
environmental concerns.
Helen Freeman
Acting Chairperson
WorldWIDE Network
Washington, D.C.
SERMONS IN STONES
I was struck by the letter from reader
Madame Lacoustille, of Monpezat,
France, published in your July-August
1992 double issue. Unlike her, I find it
inconceivable that anyone could make
an assessment of people, in whom she
declares she is interested, without
taking into account the way in which
they express themselves in art and
architecture. The "save Angkor" appeal
to which her letter refers is a perfect
illustration of the importance of this
aspect of the human condition. Stones
bear witness to the mutual interaction
of peoples.
Christophe Veys
Brussels,
Belgium
THE WISDOM OF THE
WORLD
I would like to congratulate the
editorial staff of the Unesco Courier, of
which I am a lifelong reader, on the
quality and diversity of the articles
published, written by authors from all
over the world, and also on the beauty
of the illustrations (the June 1991
issue, "Maps and Map-makers", and
the November 1990 issue, "Sacred
Places", are two examples that spring
to mind). I was particularly impressed
by the February 1991 issue on "The
Quest for Utopia", the January 1992
issue entitled "The Demographic
Dimension" (to my mind the world's
major problem) and the July-August
1992 issue, "Universality: a European
s Vision?" (I believe it is, but you
certainly made us think again).
What I find remarkable, though
this is what we are all striving for, is
that these articles are being read in
dozens of languages by people who
are citizens of the world. Having
reached an age at which one draws up
a balance sheet, I am glad to belong to
the generation which gave these
movements their initial impetus, as it
is currently doing for European unity,
and thus contributed to the
emergence of a wiser world.
Yves Doriac
Former Unesco Club Leader
Anglet,
France
INSECTICIDE AND
HOMICIDE
In the spirit of the quest for
universality, as propounded in the
editorial of the July-August issue of the
Unesco Courier, should we not also be
asking this question: "Is there any
hope that humankind will evolve
towards universality so long as
humans continue to use and abuse
herbicides, fungicides, pesticides,
insecticides . . . and homicides?"
Jean Chaumet
Simiane-la-Rotonde,
France
THE SPLENDOURS OF
SAGARMATHA
The excellent article by José Serra Vega
on Sagarmatha National Park,
published in the June 1992 issue of the
Unesco Courier, describes very well the
splendour and rich ethnic background
as well as the threats accumulating
over that World Heritage site.
I spent five years in Nepal and
many of Mr. Serra Vega's conclusions
could be extended to the rest of the
I limalayas, such as the need for
outside support to stop deforestation,
supporting measures like planting and
tending village woods to supply
firewood, building small hydroelectric
power stations and convincing
climbing expeditions to carry their
own fuel.
I think that the Unisco Courier's
initiative of entrusting articles on the
World Heritage to writers from
developing countries is a very
interesting one as they may give a
fresh view of an area perhaps facing
similar problems to those found in
their own countries. I also enjoyed Mr.
Serra Vega's description of the
grandeur of the Amazon forest and of
the complex relations between fauna,
flora, ground and atmosphere in his
article about Manu National Park, in
your August-September 1991 issue.
Teresa Crichton-Stuart
25 Grafton Square
London
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, page 3: © Ezechiel Saad,
Paris. Back cover, page 15: ©
Alain Guillou, Le Croisic (France).
Page 2: © Francis Hungler,
Guebwiller (France). Pages 4, 5, 6,
7: All Rights Reserved. Pages 8, 9,
10,11,14,16,18,20,32-33,36,
37, 38, 39, 40 (left), 45:©
Vandystadt, Paris. Page 12:©
Marie Ange Donzé, Paris. Page 13:
© A. Muñoz de Pablos, Paris. Page
17: Cranham © Rapho, Paris. Page
21: M. Rio Branco © Magnum,
Paris. Pages 22, 40 (right): ©
Claude Sauvageot, Paris. Page 23:
Ricardo R. Medina © Conservation
Trust of Puerto Rico. Page 24
(above): © 1 990 Erica Berger, New
York, Newsday. Page 24 (below):
World Food Programme, Rome.
Page 25 (above): © J. Grangeon.
Page 25 (below): UNESCO-
Norwegian University Press. Pages
26, 27: © Bruno Jouan, Paris.
Pages 28, 29: Marvin Schwartz ©
Conservation Trust of Puerto Rico.
Page 30: P. Reimbold © Hoa
Qui, Paris. Page 31: © drawing
by Blacbon, from Sport (Vol. 2)
Robert Laffont publishers, Paris.
Page 35: © Y. Semov © APN,
Paris. Page 41: © J. Dieckert.
Pages 42, 43 (above): ©
Charles Lénars, Paris. Page 43
(below): George Rodger ©
Magnum, Paris. Page 44: E.
Weiland © Rapho, Paris. Page
46: UNESCO-Dominique Roger.
Theme of the next issue
(January 1993):
Rendezvous
with
space
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TheljNESCO
fB^COURIER
45th YEAR
Published monthly in 33 languages and in Braille by Unesco, The
United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
; ;. rue Francois Bonv r. 75015 Pans. France.
director: 3ahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Ade Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whi
English edition: Roy Ma kin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Meda E! Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Laba'ca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Rinje stein (Tel. ¿5.68.46.85;
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
.'ange Belin (Tel. 45.68.4-";
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47 15), Mouna Chatta
Administrative Assistant: Pritni Perera
Selection In Braille in English. French. Spanish and Korean:
Varie-Dominique Bourgeais (45 68 46 92:
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexande' Melnikov ivtoscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne]
Arabic: El-Saia Mahmoud El-Shen;li (Cairo]
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rcmc;
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (D
Tamil: M. Monammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Varini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux : Antwerp)
Portuguese: Boned cto Silva cR o do Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Za-'.i (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti ¡Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tcng-ok ;Seou';
Swahili: Leonard J. Shura (Dar esSa aam;
Slovene: Aleksand'a Kornnausor (Ljubljana)
Chinese: She- Guofen (Beijing;
Bulgarian: Dragomlr Petrov i S
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens:
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekerc Barda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta O-isane- (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egara (Donastia]
Vietnamese: Do Phjong (Hano :
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul;
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokotci
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. SI i lhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Steimakn It
Czech and Slovak: Milan Syrucek ¡Prague)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compcsteia';
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy ¡Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Desoouy, Alpha Diakité. Jacqueline Louise-Julie.
Manichan Ngonekec, Michel Ravassard, Michelle Robilard.
Mohamed Sa ah El Din, Sylvie Van Rijse
Ri Zamcra-Pcez
Customer service: Ginette Motrefl (Te 46.68.45.64;
Accounts: ¡Te . 45 68.45.65i
Mail: Martial Amegee (Tel. 45.68.45.70]
Shipping: Hector Garcia Sandoval (Tel. 45.58.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
.:,.:!: 211 French Francs. 2 years: 396 Fr.
for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 F-ench f'ancs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made witn any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Inclvidua: articles and photographs not copyrighted rnay be reprinted
oroviding the credit hne reads "Reprinted Ccurcr.
oljs date of issue, and three voucher copk-s are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name, \on-cooynght
chotos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned un ess accompanied by an international reoly coupon
covering postage. Signed a-ticles express the opinions of the autnors
and do not necessarily represent tne opinions of Unesco o' those of
the edtc-s of tne Unesco Courier. Photo can' ions and headlines are
written by the Ukfsco Courier st,ilf The ooundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imoiy e'ficial endorsement or
acceptance by Ji^snc or the Unted Nations. The Unesco :
produced In microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Uncsco, 7
i'lace de Fontenoy, 74700 Paris: (2) univers ty Microfilms (Xerox;.
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100 U.S.A.: |3) N.C R. Microcard Edit on,
lician Head Inc.. Ill West 40th Street. \ov. York, U.S.«. Bell
Howell Co.. Old Mansfield Roac. Wooster. Ohio 44691. U.S.A
' EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
3ÉP0T LÉGAL: Cl - DECEMBRE 1992
COMM SSION PARITAIRE N 71842 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.IV.P.P.
'"otocomposit'on: Le Courrier de l'U
i-notogravure-irrpressori: Maury-lnorimeur S.A.
Z.I., route d'Etanpes. 4533C Maiesherces.
ISSN 0304-311S N 12-1992-0PI-92-513 A
lis ssue comrjrises 52 pages arc a 4-pags nsert cetweer pages
10-11 and 42-43.
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1992
JANUARY
THE DEMOGRAPHIC DIMENSION (R. Urzúa). Interview with Carlos Fuentes. UNESCO's first 45 years: 1968-
1974 (M. Coni! Lacoste). Hampâté Bâ, the great conciliator (D. Diallo). The demographic transition (J. Véron).
Poverty, population, pollution (N. Sadik). The environmental challenge (R. Lee). The numbers crunch (H.
Brookfield). Sixty million on the move (A.B. Simmons). The urban explosion (M. Armani). Migrant Africa (A.
Adepoju). The greying of the planet (j.-C. Chastcland). Petra (J. Rewerski).
FEBRUARY
APARTHEID. Interview with Joseph Ki-Zerbo. UNESCO's first 45 years: 1975-1980 (M. Conil Lacoste). The making
of a tragedy (M. Ndiaye). A return to South Africa (R. Lazarus). Which model of democracy? (A. Sachs). State of
transition (G. Gordon, D. Davis). The future of women (F. Meer). Racial discrimination in cultural life (S. Scpamla).
People's literature (N. Gordimcr). The UN's long campaign against apartheid. UNESCO and the elimination of
apartheid (F. Fournier), A chronology of repression and resistance.
MARCH
WOMEN AND THE ENVIRONMENT (J. Bi/.ot). Interview with Vandana Shiva. UNESCO's first 45 years: 1981-
1986 (M. Conil Lacoste). Women and nature, an alliance for survival (P. Huston). Sounding the alarm (M.
Cherkasova). Kenya's green belt movement (W. Maathai). The task before us (J. Martin-Brown). Miuda's world (G.
Borrini). Japan's Seikatsu Club. 'Homes not slums' (M. Trcjos). Interview with Bella Abzug. Sahel women fight
desert advance (J. Oucdraogo). Who is really speaking in the environment debate? (P. Antrobus, N. Pcacocke).
S.O.S. Dubrovnik (J. d'Ormesson) /.'UNESCO: une entreprise erronée? (book review by L. Soliman). The music of
Myanmar (Khin Mya Kyu).
APRIL
ART IN THE STREET, interview with William Styron. UNESCO's first 45 years: 1987-1988 (M. Conil Lacoste). The
circus in search of its roots (A. van Buren). Brightening the city (J.C. Langlois). Sur le pont de Vierzon (C. Groud).
The Chicanos muralists with a message (A. Tregucr). Getting the show on the road (F. Grund). Sri Lanka's wayside
theatre (A.J. Gunawardana). Art goes underground (M. Ström). Music out of doors (F. Bensignor). Cartagena dc
Indias (E. Bailby). Launching the environmental revolution (L. Brown). A new look at international law (interview
with M. Bedjaoui).
MAY
REDISCOVERING 1492. (F. Mayor). UNESCO's first 45 years: 1989-1991 (M. Conil Lacoste). Portrait of a
continent (M. León-Portilla). Prophecies and presentiments (F. Ainsa). A new image of the world (W.E. Washburn).
Foreigners who served Spain (J. Gil). Discovery and self-discovery (J.A. Scabra). America before Columbus. The
Pacific shuttle (A. de la Serna). America and Russia: dialogue from a distance (V. Kuteischikova). The Guadalajara
Declaration. The birth of the modern age (E. Montiel). The invention of a culture (L. Zea). 500 years from now (F.
Fernández-Shaw).
JUNE
IN PRAISE OF TOLERANCE. (E. Naraghi). Interview with Oscar Niemeyer. An awkward virtue (B. Williams).
Voltaire, crusader against tyranny (J. Lcssay). Gandhi and the struggle for non-violence (R. Jahanbegloo). Black
Africa's open societies (Iba Der Thiam). Islam: a conflict of models (M. Arkoun). Against intolerance (E. Pisanî). The
balancing act in the Vondelpark (N. Maharaj). Greenwatch: Earth's ozone shield under threat (F. Bequette);
Interview with F. di Castri (1). Time of promise (F, Mayor). The road to Sagarmatha (J. Serra Vega).
JULY-AUGUST
UNIVERSALITY: A EUROPEAN VISION? Interview with Mikis Theodorakis. The two faces of Europe (E.
Barón Crespo). The moral imperative (K.O. Apcl). Louder than words (S. Na'ir). The common ground of humanity
(M. Hussein). Between two worlds (T. Ben Jelloun). Africa's long march (A. Kourouma). Eastern Europe: an uphill
road to freedom (A. Lichm). Latin America: a different way forward? (E. Sábato). A golden age of dialogue (V.
Vassilikos). Two great traditions (Wang Bin). The face of a stranger (E. Lévinas). Greenwatch: The road from Rio (A.
Da Costa); Antarctica, continent of science and peace? (F. Bequette); Interview with F. di Castri (2). After Rio: a
global partnership (F. Mayor). A dream city built on salt (R. Malkin). Stefan Zweig (G. Steiner). Ziryáb, master of
Andalusian music (M. Guettât). One sky, One world (T. Krol).
SEPTEMBER
THE KNOWLEDGE BEARERS. Interview/tribute: Atahualpa Yupanqui. Homer and the Greek ideal (B.
Geoffroy). The pilgrim's way (L. Eshgui). The guru and his disciple (D.S. Oueini). From Socrates to Spinoza (P.-F.
Moreau). Simón Rodríguez, champion of mass education (J. López Palma). Sartre (R. Sabbaghi). The swan song of a
master (K. Watanabe). Teachers at the crossroads (interview with J. Beillerot). A new partnership (J. Hallak).
UNESCO and the training of teachers (A. Lokisso lu'Epotu). Greenwatch: Who benefits from debt-for-nature
exchanges? (F. Bequette). Interview with F. di Castri (3). The pathfinders (F. Mayor). The Statue of Liberty (S.
Patterson).
OCTOBER
TELE . , . VISIONS. Interview with Hervé Bourges. A mysterious medium (J.-C. Guillebaud). News non-stop (M.
Berrah). Alternative television in America (N. Magnan). This is their life (J. Boissard). The cartoon boom (B.
Cormicr-Rodicr, B. Fleury-Vilatte). The United States: the early years (A. Garel). Egypt: a national obsession (S.
Gharib). India: TV at the crossroads (A. Vasudev, L.K.. Malhatra). Brazil: a magnet for talent (D. di Donato). Big
screen, small screen (F. Garçon). Greenwatch: How clean is nuclear energy? (F. Bequette). Water, a key resource at
risk (N. Mathews). Learning the lesson of tolerance (F. Mayor). Gorée, island of slaves (C. Haardt). Gorcc today (A.
Vcrdiani).
NOVEMBER
THE CHALLENGE OF DEMOCRACY. Interview with Abdel Rahman El Bacha. What is democracy? (A.
Touraine). A question of standards (A. Maalouf). Africa: promise and uncertainty (Fl. M'Bokolo). Latin America:
freedom for the have-nots (F. Henrique Cardoso). Poland: a difficult transition (W Adamski). The South: an elusive
ideal (R. Thapar). Iran: religion, secularism and democracy (E. Naraghi). The West: women's role in post-industrial
democracy (E.M. Barbieri). The artist as insect (A. Brink). Greenwatch: Living with waste (F. Bequette). For a
democratic culture (F. Mayor).
DECEMBER
THE COMPETITIVE WORLD OF SPORT. Interview with Susana Rinaldi. A bright but flickering flame (P.
Henquct). Who should foot the bill? (J.-F. Nys). A red card for the round ball (F. Thébaud). Brazil: fancy footwork
for survival (R. DaMatta). UNESCO and sport. Doping-a shadow over sport (M.A. Bcrmúdez Escobar). Fallen stars
(A. Srcbnitsky). Fair play and the competitive spirit (M. Caillât). Save Our Sports (R. Renson). Greenwatch: The salt
of the Earth (F. Bequette). Puerto Rico saves its treasures (F. Bequette). The sporting ideal (F. Mayor). Islands in
majesty: Nobel Prizewinner Derek Walcott (E. j. Maunick).
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
