<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="094277eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
OF
E
u «y,
M 1205 -9305 22,00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternative!/, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
SHADOW AND
BRIGHTNESS
1 992, watercolour
(76 x 56 cm),
by David Fujitsang
The work of David
Fujitsang, a Chinese-born
painter who divides his
time between France and
Asia, explores the
possibilities of aesthetic
and cultural cross-
fertilization between the
Orient and the Occident.
As an artist, he writes, "I
have chosen to be a
'bridge' rather than a
'fortress'. I prefer to work
for cultural exchange and
mixing, while remaining
deeply humble in face of
the world's creative
richness."
L»
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
Charles Halamoud
talks to Tony Levy	
10
9 UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
» RECENT RECORDS
by Isabelle Leymarie
Special consultant:
Hashim El-Tinay
WATER OF LIFE
Once upon a time in Sumer...
by Ane S. hsar I O
A hidden asset
by Jean Margot I 5
Running dry
by Sandra Postel 1 9
Climate of uncertainty
by Igor A. Shiklomanov 19
Shifting sands
by Harold Dregne 3 1
Crisis in the South
by Asit K. Biswas 3 5
The Aswan High Dam,
IS years on
by Mahmoud Abu-Zeid and M. B. A. Saad 3 7
The liquid of the gods
by Camille Talkeu Tounounga 38
The forgotten ones
by Tassoum L. Douai 40
The role of Unesco
by András Szöllösl-Nagy 44
Contents
NAY 1991
Cover:
Children ¡n the rain in Lesotho.
11
Greenwatch
41
Commentary by
Federico Mayor
TheUNESCO "The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it Is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
y^^vi ir)IT O ":'lat a Peace ')aset' exc'us've'y uPon trie political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
l y Jl J |\| r |\ unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if It is not to fail, upon the
^^^==. intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to Increase the means of communication between their peoples
46th year Published monthly and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
in 32 languages and In Braille EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, (6 NOVEMBER 1 945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
CHARLES MALAMOUD
talks to Tony Levy
The French scholar Charles
Malamoud, a specialist in the
history and religions of India,
describes in this interview the
characteristics of Vedism and
Hinduism, the great Indian
religions, as revealed in their
scriptures, rites and gods. A
linguist by training, Malamoud
started his career by studying the
Sanskrit language before turning
his attention to the Sanskrit
classics and in particular to the
patterns of thought underlying the
oldest of these, the Veda. His
published works include Le
Svâdhyâya, récitation personnelle
du Veda, Talttirîya-Aranyaka II
(Boccard, Paris, 1977), Lien de
vie, naud mortel, les
représentations de la dette en
Chine, au Japon et dans le monde
Indien (EHESS, Paris, 1988) and
Cuire le monde, Rite et pensée
dans l'Inde ancienne
(La Découverte, Paris, 1989).
Could you give an overview of the reli¬
gious history ofIndia?
If you leave aside the so-called Indus Valley
civilizations, which are only known to us
through rather scanty material remains that are
difficult to interpret and even to date I'm
thinking of the sites of Moenjodaro and
Harappa, from the third millennium B.C. the
religious history of India can be divided, in a
very schematic way, into a "Vedic" period,
from about 1500 to 500 B.C., and a "Hindu"
period, starting in about 500 B.C. and contin¬
uing to the present day. These dates are
intended as no more than a rough guide.
H Have other religions been involved?
Indeed. Two movements that took the form
of a critique of Vedism and Hinduism made
their appearance in India around 500 B.C. On
the one hand there was Buddhism, a univer¬
sally-minded religion (perhaps it would be
more accurate to describe it as a world view)
founded by the Buddha, a legendary figure
who probably also really existed. Then there
was Jainism, founded by another half-real,
half-mythical figure, Mahavira, the Jina. Bud¬
dhism was to play a major cultural and philo¬
sophical role in India, but it disappeared almost
entirely from the mainland by about 1000
A.D., while spreading to and taking root in the
Himalaya region, Sri Lanka, and central, east
and south-east Asia. Jainism was confined to
India, where it has survived to the present
day. Jainists now make up a small, prosperous
and well-organized minority of the Indian
population.
Another major event in Indian history
was the conquest of much of the sub-continent
by Muslims from Iran and Afghanistan, again
around the year 1000 A.D. Once they had
seized power, the conquerors made many con¬
verts so many that Islam became one of the
great religions of the subcontinent. After Inde
pendence and Partition in 1947, Pakistan, later
to be divided in its turn when its eastern part
became Bangladesh, was set up as an almost
entirely Muslim state. But in the Indian Union
itself, 1 0 per cent of the population are Muslim,
which means more than 100 million people
today. Another religion that came from outside
is Christianity in its various forms, which
began to be introduced into India by Euro¬
peans in the sixteenth century.
But the most ancient and characteristic
religion of India, the one that can be said to
be indigenous to the country, is the Vedic-
Hindu complex. It has by far the greatest
number of adherents, and it is the faith most
closely linked to traditional Indian ways of
thought and forms of social organization.
How are Vedism and Hinduism linked?
Well, Vedism and Hinduism are two suc¬
cessive phases or aspects of the same religion
rather than two separate religions. To put it
another way, there was never a clean break
between Vedism and Hinduism, for all their
very obvious differences and even contra¬
dictions. There wasn't even a deliberate or
consciously undertaken movement of rad¬
ical reform. Even now in very orthodox cir¬
cles, Vedism is still considered the source of
Hinduism and its ultimate authority, as valid
now as ever.
What's more, there is a third term in the
vocabulary of historians of religion that
underlines the continuity between Vedism
and Hinduism. This is the word "Brah-
manism". It has more than one meaning,
referring both to the form of religion codified
in the texts known as the Brahmana, which
date from the end of the Vedic period, and
also to the orthodox core of early Hinduism.
Does each phase have its own scriptures?
Vedism is known to us through the vast
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
corpus of texts called the Veda. These were
composed at various dates between 1500 and
500 B.C. There is no similar body of literature
for Hinduism proper certainly not one that
is as clearly defined or that carries the same
authority. Even so, as the word "epico-
Puranic" that is sometimes applied to Hin¬
duism suggests, the two great epics of the
Mahabharata and the Ramayana, along with
the vast mass of encyclopaedic writings
known as the Parana, are in a certain sense the
sacred books of Hinduism, containing ideas
that all Hindus accept. These epics were com
posed in the closing centuries of the 1 st mil¬
lennium B.C., the Purana about a thousand
years later. These dates are approximate.
Where does the Bhagavad Gitafit in?
It's a fragment of the Mahabharata.
Is there any link between the Purana and
the Vedic hymns?
They belong to two very different literary
forms, and their content is also different. The
Veda is often quoted in the Purana, and is
spoken ofwith reverence. But the Purana (the
An 18th-century Indian
miniature illustrates a scene
from the great national epic,
the Ramayana, in which the
exiled Rama crosses a river
in company with his wife Sita
and his brother Lakshmana.
term means "antiquities") are first and fore¬
most creation myths and genealogies of gods
and men, mixed with dissertations on cos¬
mology, ritual, social organization, summaries
of various sciences, descriptions of places of
pilgrimage and so on. Some of these elements
also exist in the Vedic corpus, but the format
and the diction, if I may use that word, are
quite different. The Purana are long-winded,
jumbled, loosely expressed. The Vedic hymns,
on the other hand, are dense, profound, often
hermetic: they are great poetry.
Could you describe the Veda more pre¬
cisely?
As I said, the Veda is a corpus of texts. It is
our only source of information about India
from 1500 to 500 B.C. There are no other
written sources, no external evidence, no
archaeological remains to speak of. The texts
themselves are composite, varying greatly in
age, content and form. Yet they are all linked,
the latest elements presupposing a knowl¬
edge of the earlier ones, since they quote
them. But orthodox Hindus today see the
Veda as homogeneous, in the sense that they
regard the whole work as a revealed text. The
revelation concerns gods as well as human
beings, and although it was not delivered in
one piece it does not assume a chronological
framework implying a before and after.
In using the word "revealed" you suggest
comparisons with other religionsfounded on
holy scripture.
There is a great difference between the Veda
and revelation in the religions based on the
Bible. The Veda is not generally viewed as the
word of a god addressed to humanity but as a
text outside of time that exists of itself and
reveals itself by itself. Strictly speaking, the
Veda has no author. But men of exceptionally
powerful vision "saw" that is the word that
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The 17th-century temple of
Minakshi, the consort of Shiva,
rises above the Indian city of
Madurai.
is used different fragments, different ver¬
sions of the text, put their vision into words
and passed it on to other men. These vision¬
aries are known as riski, a word usually trans¬
lated as "seer".
Yet even though the revelation has been
"seen", the Veda is primarily sound-oriented.
It is a collection or sequence of sounds formed
into meaningful words. The text of the Veda is
1 a manifestation of the word; words are oral,
made up of the sounds of language, and all
their power comes from vibrations of the
sound-waves. Furthermore rhythm, as deter¬
mined by the number of syllables and the
arrangement of long and short syllables, plays
an important part in the symbolism of the
work. A final point: the usual word to designate
the Veda as revelation is çruti, literally
hearing .
What is so extraordinary about the Vedic
revelation, then, is that the knowledge it con¬
tains (for veda means "to know") was "seen",
yet it consists of sounds. Nor can one resolve
the paradox by imagining that the "seers"
viewed a written text they subsequently trans¬
lated into spoken words, for the very notion
of writing is completely foreign to the Veda.
Even in later times when India had writing,
the very idea that the Veda could be learned
otherwise than by repeating the words of a
master was vigorously rejected.
Does this Word without an author have its
own specific intercessor?
Only the rishi, the seers who transmitted
the text to humankind through the medium
of sound. But they are not strictly speaking
intercessors, for they only put the Veda into
words, rather than interpreting it. What's
more, there is no question of them operating
in the other direction by transmitting the
thoughts or desires of human beings to the
Veda. They are simply the mouthpiece of
the Veda. The Veda is a text they discover and
that was there before them, not one they
have shaped themselves.
So it is an oral message that over the cen¬
turies has been committed to writing and
transmitted in written form. How much do
we know about the transmission process?
We don't know exactly when or how India
acquired writing. The oldest inscriptions date
from the third century B.C., and their technique
is so fine as to indicate a long previous history.
But there is no doubt that the corpus of Vedic
texts, or at least the oldest part of it, was con¬
stituted and transmitted from generation to
generation over many centuries without the
aid of writing. And I would repeat that even
when writing became common in India, even
when the Veda could be written down, the
text was still usually passed on orally from
master to pupil. To all intents and purposes
this process continued until our own day.
Studying the Veda means learning it by heart by
repeating it after the master. Highly elaborate
techniques are used to memorize such long
and difficult texts. But then even scholars for
whom reading and writing are everyday activ¬
ities habitually learn religious and even non-reli¬
gious texts they consider important by heart,
however long these texts may be.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
How wouldyou describe the Vedic corpus
itself?
Two principal layers can be discerned in the
text. The older consists of collections of
poems in the form of prayers, or more often
hymns, glorifying a god or a group of gods,
or the sacrificial act and its various elements,
or the people who carry it out. The most
important of these collections is the Rig-
Veda, the "Veda of Laudatory Stanzas",
which comprises about a thousand poems.
The other important group is the Atharva-
Veda, part of which consists of magical texts.
One of the main themes of the Vedic hymns
is a celebration of the power of the word,
which means ultimately a celebration of Vedic
poetry by the Veda itself. The hymns are
composed in an archaic form of Sanskrit. The
style is often obscure, marked by figures of
speech, particularly metaphors, of great
power and boldness.
The more recent layer consists of the
prose treatises known as the Brahmana,
which explain what the various sacrificial
rites of the Vedic religion are and how they
should be understood. They provide liturgical
instruction, but also information on the sym¬
bolism of the rites and on their links with
mythology. Furthermore, since the perfor¬
mance of the rites calls for the recitation, in
whole or in part, of Vedic poems, the Brah¬
mana explain why specific ritual gestures are
associated with specific texts. In this respect,
the Brahmana can be considered as a com¬
mentary on the Vedic poems.
The Brahmana themselves have appen¬
dices, the Upanishads. The Upanishads come
right at the end of Vedic literature, and
Indians like to say that they contain the
Veda's deepest meaning. The content of the
Upanishads consists of speculations whose
starting-point is a meditation on ritual. But
this meditation ends by going beyond ritu¬
alism: rituals are no longer considered in
themselves but as symbols of the cosmos and
of the organization of the spirit. This "meta-
ritualism" lays the foundations for a meta¬
physical world view.
To sum up, the hymns, the Brahmana
and the Upanishads jointly make up the Vedic
revelation.
To make learning and understanding the
Veda easier, India developed very early on,
towards the end of the Vedic period, auxiliary
sciences known as the Vedanga, literally
"members" added to the body of the Veda.
These are phonetics, grammar, etymology,
astrology, the study of metre, and the analysis
and use of ritual. Despite their Vedic origins,
some at least of these disciplines came to be
studied for their own sake and became non-
religious fields of study.
One should add that literal commentaries
exist for most of the Vedic texts. These are for
the most part quite late, but they are consid¬
ered authoritative.
The word brahman seems to crystallize
certain links, particularly the necessary one
between the divine word and human speech.
The word brahman is without any doubt
the most mysterious in the Sanskrit language.
In the speculative tradition that begins with
the Upanishads, brahman links up with
atman. The brahman, the Absolute of the
universe, corresponds to the atman, which is
the Self, the Absolute as revealed in the reflex-
ivity of the individual soul.
The term brahman lies at the root of a
whole complex of derivations that need some
explanation. First and foremost we have the
word brahman itself, which is neuter in
gender. Its principal meaning is "essential
content of the Veda". Because the Vedic
poems contain many statements in the form
of riddles, brahman also comes to have the
secondary meaning of "riddle" or "enigma".
The first derivation is brahman, gender
masculine, which designates men who arc
particularly well-versed in knowledge and
use of the neuter brahman in its first sense. In
An ascetic, as depicted in
the huge 7th-century
sculptured rock relief at
Mamallapuram
(Mahabalipuram) depicting
"The Descent of the
Ganges from the
Himalayas".
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Vedic ritual the brahman is the priest whose
job is to check that exactly the right formulas
are employed. As the "doctor of the sacrifice"
he says next to nothing but is, as it were, the
incarnation of the Vedic text on the sacrificial
ground. In post-Vedic Hinduism, Brahman in
its masculine form can also be a proper name,
for Brahman or Brahma is one of the great
gods who, with Vishnu and Shiva, makes up
the supreme triad, the triple figuration known
as Trimurti.
Then there's the word Brahmana, which
means "that which has reference to brahman"
and designates the sacrificial treatises I spoke
of earlier. Brahmana has another meaning in
Sanskrit, and that is what we think of when
we use the word "brahmin", which is to say
a man born into the highest of the four
"classes" of the Indian social hierarchy, the
priestly one. Brahmanism is the religion that
considers the brahmins to be the repositories
of Vedic knowledge, and that they alone are
entitled to officiate during sacrifices.
Can one say that the Veda created the
world?
Yes, certainly. The role of the Vedic texts in
the Creation is one of the themes of the Veda.
It is both a poetic motif and a principle of the
Vedic religion.
How does sacrificefit into what might be
called the geography of the sacred?
The sacrificial rite is one element among
others in the Vedic religion. Not all Vedic
ritual is sacrifice, just as not all the religion is
ritual. It is true, though, that sacrifice is the
main subject of the Vedic texts, and their
expositions of mythology and the creation of
the universe, their speculations on the corre¬
spondences between the macrocosm and the
microcosm and so on, are presented in the
context of sacrificial instructions. They also
tend to analyse such other rites as prayer,
funerals and marriages as though they too
were forms of sacrifice, organized in the same
way and with the same division of roles
between the participants.
Furthermore, as Louis Renou has pointed
out, one can see the idea developing that the
Vedic compilations are nothing more than
collections of mantras, forms of words to
recite during ceremonies. The gestures and
objects involved in rites become sacred and
effective insofar as they are "sacralized" by
the recitation of appropriate mantras.
It should be said that the clearest and
most vigorous creation stories present genesis
itself as a sacrifice, with the different ele¬
ments of the cosmos and of society coming
from the dismemberment of a primordial
victim, and also that the core of Vedic
mythology hinges on the efforts made by
the gods to take possession of the sacrificial
procedures and instruments or to put them to
their own exclusive use.
But another characteristic of Vedic civi¬
lization is that it produced thinkers, true
Characters from the Ramayana adorn the
Ranganatha temple at Srirangam, in Tamil
Nadu state, southeastern India. The temple
dates from the I Oth to the 1 6th century.
intellectuals in my view, who reflected on
the formal structure of the sacrifice, on the
way in which the various parts are linked
and on how all the acts of which it consists are
joined and separated. And since you men¬
tioned "geography", I would add that sacri¬
fices take place in the open, in a space
equipped with fire-altars and poles. Vedic
ritualists devised a whole system of geometry
to make sure that this equipment is set up in
conformity with the canons of shape and
size. Yet the sites themselves are considered
"abstract", in the sense that we know of none
that was marked out to serve exclusively as
the stage for any particular rite.
To whom are the sacrifices offered up?
To the gods or, using different procedures,
to ancestors. There is a whole mythology of
sacrifice, which can itself be seen as a divine
being, just as the word can. Various gods of
the Vedic pantheon have a double aspect, a
twofold reality. For instance fire Agni is
both a god to whom prayers are addressed
and the flame lit in the altars to receive offer¬
ings. Soma is a god, but also a plant whose
juice is considered the drink of immortality
and is therefore itself offered up to the
immortal ones.
Vedic speculation, particularly in the
Brahmana, tends to suggest that the gods
depend on the sacrifices made to them and in
a sense are even raised up by these sacrifices.
The right order of the world, prosperity in
our present existence and salvation in the
after-life can all be achieved by correct exe¬
cution of rites, much more than by any kind
of divine acquiescence or grace.
Ifsacrifice, in conjunction with the word,
helped to create the world and even the gods
themselves, is it possible to say that there are
established correspondences between the
macrocosm and the microcosm, the divine
and human worlds?
Yes, such correspondences exist, but it is up
to humans to discover them, to become aware
of them, to formulate them and in so doing,
to confirm them. Solving the Vedic riddles I
CONTINUED PACE 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
TO OUR READERS
OPERATION SOLIDARITY
THE FIRST RESULTS
^n7¡ÍÑ¡iWÍt°Kts me
?£ token of»(«
Paiial Booyer
I subscription to add
intellectual to material
sustenance .
Marie.UoUiseLePe»t.er
-It provides us with an
1 opportunity to come toge her
1 Se level of culture and
| ideas. . ' Philippe Guirlet
¿ont,'.*»*""0'
receiving than giving- G^ers
terris to me to be both
Stive and constructive
etherising generation,^,
Ricquebourg-Delwaulle
of hope. .
Bernadette Boicot
i flooding the world with
! understanding... ^espeyron
IThree months ago we launched
"Operation Solidarity",
inviting readers to offer a
subscription to the Courier as a
gift to a school, library or
university in a country of the
South. The response has been
so encouraging that after only a
few short weeks we can report
that the Operation is turning
out to be a great success. More
than a hundred subscriptions
have already gone out to
recipients in Asia, Africa and
eastern Europe, and this is
hopefully only a start, the first
step on a road leading to close
and lasting ties across
geographical and political
frontiers. The many letters we
have received testify that
solidarity is an ideal that seeks
an intellectual outlet as well as
other more tangible forms of
expression.
Thank you for your
generosity.
PLEASE KEEP IT MP!
rThTÁrííír^u^C^
S invited the Unesco
S^andCom-^-r
j ¡t is organizing on 15 «
1 May- . Dewaiiiy,
3 Place Louis Dew j
80037 Amiens. France
;ÏpP a kind of electron,
p§§£
could be swapped- ;
99 rue Louis «»=
sur Marne.
colleagues ¡n countries^
sou* byrSSSlí
1 information about equip
and resources.
Margaret Allen,
3006ATulane Place-
._ KS 67502, USA
Hutchinson, w
»HUTE W US
si«. «»»"""? W
soia»«»"-1"',,,,
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Once upon
a time
in Sumer. . .
10
by Arie S. Issar
EVER since very ancient times, human beings
have tried to explain the wonders of water,
for which they at first attributed responsi¬
bility to deities whose deeds were sung in hymns
and transmitted as myths and legends.
The earliest of these stories to come down to
us were written down in Sumer, Mesopotamia,
about 4,500 years ago. They tell of a universe
composed only of water, from which arose a
cosmic mountain that contained both heaven
and earth. The Sumerians believed that at the
creation of the world there was a fight between
the benevolent gods and Kur, the god of the
nether world, who controlled the primeval
waters. Kur was involved in a foul deed com¬
mitted against Ereshkigal, the sky goddess.
Ereshkigal was helped by Enki, the water god,
who set out in a boat to attack Kur. This evil
god fought back by sending the primeval waters
to sink the boat, but Enki, the god of good water,
triumphed.
The Babylonians, who adopted many
Sumerian traditions, chanted during their New
Year festivities the epic tale of the victory of the
benevolent god Marduk over Tiamat, the goddess
of the abyss. The tale began as follows: "When in
:or most of
mman history,
toter WQS the
stuff of myth,
hly in the
1 1th century
iid on
ipprooch based
)n observation
md experiment
lead to the birth
if modern
hydrology the height heaven was not named, And the Earth
beneath did not yet bear a name, And the
primeval Apsu who begat them, And chaos,
Tiamat, the mother of them both. Their waters
were mingled together." (Enuma Elish, The Seven
Tablets of Creation, Tablet One).
In the Old Testament, the existence of a
primeval ocean is taken for granted. The story of
creation begins when "darkness was upon the
face of the deep. And the spirit of god moved
upon the face of the waters" (Genesis 1 : 2). Inter¬
estingly, the Hebrew word for "the deep" is
Tehom, which brings to mind the Babylonian
Tiamat. After being defeated by Marduk, this
entity representing the abyss of primeval waters
and chaos was divided into two parts to form the'
bodies of atmospheric water and underground
water:
"Then the lord rested gazing upon her
[Tiamat's] dead body while he divided the flesh
of the body and devised a cunning plan. He split
her up like a flat fish into two halves. One half of
her he stablished as a covering for heaven. He
fixed a bolt; he stationed watchmen and bade
them not to let her waters come forth. . . . And
over against the Deep he set the dwelling of
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
'%. I
/
r\
A J
Nudinmud1 ". (Enuma Elish, Tablet IV, 135-142).
This story is reminiscent of the dividing of the
waters by the Creator as narrated in the Bible:
"And God made the firmament, and divided the
waters which were under the firmament from the
waters which were above the firmament: and it
was so. And God called the firmament Heaven."
(Genesis 1: 6-7).
Another reference to an ancient abyss appar¬
ently connected to the primeval waters is found
in the Canaanite myths deciphered from the clay
tablets found when the ancient city of Ugarit, on
the eastern shore of the Mediterranean, was exca¬
vated. In these myths El, the primeval deity, lives
at the sources of rivers in the midst of the outlet
of two deeps called Teomotaim.
Thus the Babylonian Tiamat, the Canaanite
Teomotaim and the Hebrew Tehom may all be
manifestations of the same idea of a state of
chaos, of an endless abyss of primeval water, a
state where life cannot exist and thrive. These
elements are also found in the Rig-Veda, an
ancient Hindu text in which the slaying of the
cruel dragon Vrtra by the valiant Indra involves
piercing the bellies of the mountains and letting
the water flow out.
In an impression taken
from a Babylonian cylinder
dating from the 2nd
millennium B.C., Enki, the
god of fresh water, is
shown amidst small
goddesses and streams of
water teeming with fish.
1. The father of Marduk and
the creator of humanity.
THE PRIMEVAL ABYSS
There is good reason to believe that these ideas
originated in prehistoric times, were brought to
Mesopotamia, transmitted to the Harappa pre-
Aryan civilization of northern India, and later
absorbed by the Aryan conquerors who settled
in this region during the second millennium B.C.
They may also have spread from Mesopotamia to
Egypt during proto-historical times, brought by
conquerors from abroad, probably from
Mesopotamia. The ancient Egyptians believed
in the emergence of a primeval mound from an
abyss of primeval water, at the site of the temple
of Atum-Ra at Heliopolis. The primeval waters
stretched endlessly in all directions. The rising of
the creator, the god Atum, from this water was
also the manifestation of the creation of order and
life. As long as he was immersed in the primeval
waters, all was chaos.
Ancient Egyptian texts found in the pyra¬
mids describe the Creator, who is the outflow of
the Primeval Flood, and who emerged from the
waters, as a serpent with many coils. In the cosmic
myth of Hinduism, the god Vishnu, the source of
the world and all things, is depicted as sleeping,
before the Creation, in the primeval ocean, on the II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
This diagram of a
hydraulic machine is an
illustration from
Athanasius Kircher's
Mundus Subterraneus, a
1 7th-century treatise on
geology.
thousand-headed serpent Sesa. In his sleep a lotus
grows from his navel, and in the lotus is born the
demiurge Brahma, who created the world.
The same basic ideas are found in the pre-Hcl-
lenic mythologies of ancient Greece. Although in
these myths creation is attributed to a woman's
touch, the motifs of a primeval ocean and a snake
recur: Euronome, the goddess of all things, rises
naked from chaos and divides the sea from the
sky, dancing lonely upon the waves. She catches
hold of the north wind, rubs it between her hands
and thus creates the great serpent Ophion. In
the Homeric myths, all gods and all living crea¬
tures originated in the stream of Oceanus which
girdles the world.
Sumer was located in the lowlands of
Mesopotamia, near where the waters of the Tigris
and the Euphrates flow into the sea. In a dry
year, when river levels are low, seawater
encroaches into the river inlets and the subsurface.
Today we know how to calculate the decrease in
the flow of a river as a function of the quantity of
precipitation in its catchment area, thereby
making it possible to forecast the rate of recession
of the fresh water and the penetration of the sea
water. The Sumerians, however, did not connect
the encroachment of the sea with the lowering of
the water level in their rivers. They had a con-
Fijw.i V
12
ceptual model which claimed just the opposite,
namely that the water of the river receded because
Kur, the great god of the primeval waters (sym¬
bolizing the saline water of the sea as well as
subsurface water) became furious with Niuntra,
the god of the south wind. According to the
Sumerian poem, as Kur rises the Tigris does not
rise, famine rages, the water in the small rivers
does not rise, the fields are not irrigated, and
nothing grows but weeds. Niuntra solves the
problem by building dikes to protect the rivers
against the encroaching sea water. This stops the
flow of the fresh water into the sea and raises its
level so that the fields can be irrigated.
Thus a natural disaster and a feat of clever
engineering are reported in the form of a con¬
ceptual model which seemed logical to the
ancients. The king or the irrigation engineer who
devised and ordered the construction of the dikes
understood that the recession of the Tigris and the
penetration of the sea were interconnected. He
might not have understood that the low level of
the Tigris was due to a dry spell caused by low
rainfall on the Zagros mountains and that the
encroachment of the sea could have been
enhanced by a global rise in the sea level due to a
climatic change which caused the glaciers at the
poles to melt. What he saw and understood was
the change in the balance between the water of the
Tigris and the water of the sea, and he found a way
of coping with it. This however was not sufficient;
he also had to put forward a theory to explain
what happened, and the theory that came to his
mind entailed a fight between gods.
THE DELUGEMYTH AND
REALITY
Another story found in many ancient mytholo¬
gies is that of the Deluge. The oldest known ver¬
sion is Sumerian. Adopted by the Babylonians
and Assyrians and repeated in the Bible, it is
explained in terms of an ethical world-view. In the
mythologies of the people of Mesopotamia, the
Deluge occurs because the gods fight among
themselves, while in the Jewish version it is God's
punishment for the wickedness of the people.
The conceptual model suggested by the present
author is that a flood did indeed affect the
Mesopotamian plain at the dawn of history, caused
by a global climatic change that caused the glaciers
to expand and rainstorms to sweep over the
Mediterranean as far as the Levant. This caused
flooding in the lowlands. One reason for this sug¬
gestion, in addition to the palaeoclimatic evidence,
is the fact that all the ancient stories, although
written in a land of rivers, give the reason for the
floods as rain and not river overflow. This indicates
that the deluge was a climatic anomaly.
As we have seen, the conceptual model of the
ancient Greeks also involved a primeval abyss of
water. This conception might have been formed in
prehistoric times, before the Greeks reached their
peninsula. Once settled there, they became con¬
cerned with the origin of springs. Greece is a
Mediterranean country where most rain falls in
winter. Summers are long, hot and mostly dry, and
during them the water supply depends on the
flow of the springs issuing in many cases from
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
limestone caverns. Greek mythology regarded
springs as the place of residence of Pan, a god
who enjoyed playing a flute made from reeds
growing at the waterside.
In Greece in the sixth and fifth centuries B.C.,
there was a school of scientists and philosophers
known as the pre-Socratics, who combined obser¬
vation and logic to explain natural phenomena. It
can be claimed that the pre-Socratics were the first
thinkers to use non-religious conceptual models
and theories in an attempt to understand nature.
One theory to explain the phenomena of springs
was suggested by the pre-Socratic philosopher
Anaxagoras of Clazomenae (500-428 B.C.). His
writings have not survived, but fortunately Aris¬
totle, who lived about a hundred years later, refutes
him after citing him in his book Meteorológica.
Anaxagoras put forward the theory, advanced
for its time, that all groundwater originates from
rain, which is raised by the Sun (evaporation),
then falls on the Earth and collects beneath it in
great reservoirs. Rivers, which are fed by springs,
are fuller in winter when the subterranean reser¬
voirs are full, and diminish in summer when these
reservoirs empty. Some rivers even dry up alto¬
gether when their sources of supply empty before
fresh rains come. Anaxagoras also maintained
that no water is generated during its flow through
the hydrological cycle. This is the first statement
of the principle of conservation of matter.
Aristotle did not agree with this theory. He
claimed that the volume of water is much greater
than the volume of the Earth, and suggested
another conceptual model in which he main¬
tained that water is formed continuously in the
Earth from air, which he considered to be a sort
of aqueous vapour. He also seems to have believed
that juvenile water is replenished from the depths
of the Earth. He suggested that high mountains
cool the vapours that rise from the lowlands and
condense them into water.
In this conceptual model Aristotle tried to
weld meteorological and hydrological observa¬
tions into a single rational theory. It seemed to
him that the volume of water flowing in springs
and rivers is much greater than the volume of the
Earth in which it had to be stored. Aristotle
explained this discrepancy by the idea of the con¬
tinuous generation of water. This was the basic
flaw of his theory.
RECONCILING ARISTOTLE WITH
CHRISTIAN TEACHING
The Romans, who adopted the Hellenistic philo¬
sophical and scientific paradigms, were practical
people. Their engineers preferred perennial springs
to rivers as a source of safe and continuous water
supplies for their cities. They liked these springs
to be on a higher altitude than their cities so that
there was enough pressure for the water to flow
along beautifully constructed aqueducts and
emerge as fountains in the midst of the cities.
When perennial springs were not available, in the
vicinity of cities in the more arid parts of their
empire, they dug wells to reach groundwater.
They probably learned this technique from local
people who knew from proto-historical times
how to locate and use groundwater.
Aristotle's erroneous assumption about the
volumes of water and Earth, and the theory of the
A massive sculpture at
Buddhanilkanta, near
Kathmandu (Nepal) shows
the god Vishnu reclining
on the coils of the serpent
of eternity.
ARIE SHIMSHON ISSAR,
of Israel, Is head of the Center
for Water Resources at the
Jacob Blaustein Institute for
Desert Research and
professor of geology at the
Ben-Gurion University of the
Negev. He has taken part in
hydrological projects In several
countries, and under the
auspices of the FAO served for
4 years as advisor to the
government of Iran In the field
of groundwater research and
development. He is the author
of many publications on
hydrogeology, hydrochemistry
and the Impact of climate
change on hydrology. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
perpetual generation of water which he devel¬
oped to answer it, dominated the scientific
thinking of civilization for more than 1,500 years.
Aristotelian views were adopted by the Chris¬
tian church and were taught in its schools to the
monks and priests who formed the literate class.
However, they were not accepted at their face
value. They had to conform with the Holy Scrip¬
tures, and much "scientific" research during the
Middle Ages and later was devoted to reconciling
Aristotelian views with the Bible and other con¬
victions of the church. The Scriptures were for the
monks a basic truth, like an observation of nature
that could not be doubted. Indeed, Aristotelian
writings and the Bible had greater authority than
any observation and thus provided the postulates
upon which the world-view had to be based.
THE DEVELOPMENT OF
SCIENTIFIC HYDROLOGY
In the seventeenth century, new ideas on the
need to study nature by observation became
widely current. Adherents of the classical para¬
digms of the church tried to find a middle way
between the Holy Scriptures and their own obser¬
vations. One solution was the theory advanced by
the GermanJesuit Athanasius Kircher, who in his
book Mundus Subterráneas (1665-1668) sug¬
gested that there are holes in the seabed which
communicate with caverns in the mountains and
that as a result of various processes the water is
made to flow upwards, thus fulfilling what is
stated in the Bible. Many other scholarly acro¬
batics were performed by pious people in order
to reconcile the Holy Scriptures, Aristotle, and
observable hydrological phenomena.
An unbiased understanding of what really
happens in nature came when people freed them¬
selves from the obligation to regard the ancient
writings as truths to be trusted more than obser
vations. Once this happened, new conceptual
models were created by such unconventional
thinkers as Leonardo da Vinci (1452-1519) and
Bernard Palissy (1510-1589), who hypothesized
that spring water consists of rainwater perco¬
lating through porous and fractured rocks.
The proof of these conceptual models came
when a quantitative approach was applied. This was
done first by Pierre Perrault, whose book De
l'Origine des Fontaines (1 674) presented a quanti¬
tative hydrological balance of the drainage basin of
the River Seine. This showed that all the water
that was drained by the river amounted only to
about one sixth of the total rainfall on its catchment
basin. This was followed a few years later by
another set of measurements and calculations by
the physicist Edme Mariotte, who modified the
figure to about one-eighth. Other quantitative
investigations which followed during the eigh¬
teenth century established the theory of the hydro-
logical cycle as it is found in modern textbooks.
Later, more precise calculations were made.
The engineer Henri Darcy calculated the flow of
water through a porous medium and thus for¬
mulated what is known as Darcy's Law, which
states that the volume of water flowing through a
certain section of porous rock is equal to the per¬
meability of the rock multiplied by the gradient of
the water table. This law was further developed for
application to various conditions by hydrologists
during the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.
With the coming of the computer era, some
hydrologists came to think that in the future only
very few field investigations would be needed to
supply basic data, and that all the rest of the work
would be done by computer. This approach is
reminiscent of the Greek belief at the dawn of
the classical era of philosophy, that logical rea¬
soning based on just a few observations would be
sufficient to reveal the mysteries of nature.
A scene from the lavishly
decorated tomb of
Sennefer, known as the
"tomb of the vines", at
Thebes, Egypt (I Sth
century B.C.).
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
H
.71«^* -IT*»
mmbf v,jF..; '..fl^KÄ1
Underground
water is an
important,
little-known
ond fragile
resource
Above, digging a well
in Burkina Faso.
A hidden
Qsset
by Jean Margat
UNDERGROUND water was for centuries the
great unknown of the water cycle. Despite
the intuitive insights of a small number of
geniuses, from the Greek Anaxagoras and the
Roman Vitruvius to Leonardo da Vinci, it long
remained the stuff of myth and imagination.
Until the time of Descartes, people thought it
came from the sea and somehow made its way up
to mountain springs, desalinating itself en route.
Its place in the circulation of the Earth's water was
not understood until the seventeenth century.
And we have only recently learned how to mea¬
sure its volume and flow.
REGULATING THE FLOW OF
STREAMS AND RIVERS
Virtually all terrestrial freshwater resources in
liquid form are underground. The 10 million bil¬
lion cubic metres of underground water represent
more than a hundred times the amount con¬
tained in all the world's lakes and rivers at any
given time. And even though it is less than the 28
million billion cubic metres contained in the
Earth's ice masses, subterranean water is more
evenly distributed on every continent. 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
Underground water is not stagnant. Although
it flows very slowly, its mass in motion makes an
appreciable contribution to the general circulation
of water. Almost a third of the flow of the Earth's
running water circulates underground for short or
long distances. The global volume is of the order
of 12 thousand billion cubic metres annually.
Subterranean water is linked to surface water
through countless springs and other forms of dis¬
charge. Without its unseen flow, which is wide¬
spread and regular even if rarely observed except
by speleologists, there would be neither springs
nor permanent rivers. The underground reserves
are the great regulators of surface streamflow.
Underground water is distributed in as orga¬
nized a fashion as surface water, in aquifers that
vary both in size and in the complexity of their
structures. Sometimes these serve as conduits,
sometimes essentially as reservoirs. Every conti¬
nent possesses major aquifers whose size rivals
that of the great river basins, containing billions
of cubic metres of fresh water, sometimes as
much as one or two thousand metres down.
In spite of progress in the knowledge and
skills of the hydrogeologists who study and con¬
trol it, underground water still means little to the
public at large, and even to many engineers and
administrators responsible for the management of
water resources. The air of mystery surrounding
it has encouraged the survival of water-divining,
the belief in which is still deeply implanted in
many cultures. Underground water is rarely
thought of as a communal resource, like rivers, and
its legal status is accordingly often different from
that of surface waters, whether standing or
flowing, which generally fall into the public
domain. Property rights to underground water
resources are generally linked to ownership of
the land above them, and laws pertaining to water
usually take little account of the continuity of
ground and surface water. The degree to which
human activities affect subterranean reserves is
either underestimated or ignored.
DRAWING
ON THE RESERVES
Yet underground water has been used and
exploited by humankind for thousands of years.
Through the ages, in every part of the world,
people have devised different ways of tapping
it, using energy sources as diverse as animal
labour, wind and solar power and the hydraulic
techniques employed in artesian wells.
Examples of the exploitation of underground
water resources include Iran's famous qanats,
galleries hollowed out over the course of the
centuries that, laid end to end, would stretch for
400,000 kilometres, the distance from the Earth
to the Moon; the 600,000 wells that irrigate the
Ho Pei plain in China; the 5,000 wells of Aus-
The Aven du Grelot, a
natural well in a limestone
region of southern France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
tralia's Great Artesian Basin, which produced 6
billion cubic metres of water in 1980; and the
150 billion cubic metres of water pumped each
year in India (a world record). Between 1940
and 1980 500 billion cubic metres were drawn
from the Ogallala aquifer to irrigate the High
Plains of the American Midwest, where 170,000
wells are currently in use. Thousands of modern
wells provide water for the villages of the African
Sahel. Two billion cubic metres will be extracted
annually from the fossil-water reserves of the
Libyan desert to feed the "Great Artificial River".
Underground water has many advantages as a
source of supply. It can be easily tapped over wide
areas using installations that require small-scale
investment rather than the heavy outlay needed, for
example, to build dams to control surface water. It
is a permanent resource that is relatively insensi¬
tive to climatic factors such as drought. In addition,
the quality of the water is generally better and
more consistent than that of surface water, making
it suitable for human consumption.
Around the world today, about 60 per cent of
drinking water, 15 per cent of household supplies
and 20 per cent of irrigation resources come from
beneath the ground. In most of the world's arid
lands, subterranean reserves constitute the prin¬
cipal water supply source. In addition, they con¬
stitute at least 20 per cent, and often more than 30
per cent, of all the water used in most industrial¬
ized countries. About 600-700 billion tonnes are
now tapped annually a greater tonnage than
for any other mined mineral.
THE RISKS OF
OVER-EXPLOITATION
There is a big gap between what people know
about underground water and the use they make
of it, and this accounts for much that is wrong
with the way it is exploited.
It is an often-undervalued resource that could
be more efficiently used during periods of
drought. On the other hand, it is sometimes used
to excess, and such overexploitation can be
harmful in many ways. It is important to realize
that underground and surface water resources
are not independent of one another, for ground¬
water helps regulate surface streamflow a role
that could be amplified by using it, for example,
to artificially refill storage basins that are in
danger of silting up. Considerable though they
are, however, freshwater reserves are not renew¬
able within a human lifespan, and so can only be
exploited for a limited time. Their use does not
allow for sustainable development.
The massive deposits of fossil water that exist
in several arid regions are vital resources, even if
only some of the water can be extracted, since by
the rules that govern any kind of mining opera¬
tion the intensity of production must control its 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
duration. In many countries these resources have
been exploited since the nineteenth century and
have already produced billions of cubic metres of
water 35 billion in Australia over 90 years,
about 15 billion in the Algerian and Tunisian
Sahara in 30 years, 200 billion in Arizona in 60
years, the same figure in 40 years in the American
Midwest provoking sizeable falls in the water
table, sometimes of 100 metres or more. Similar,
more recent but fast-growing developments now
provide the bulk of several Arab countries' needs,
providing 75 per cent of Saudi Arabia's water
supply and 85 per cent of that of the Libyan
Arab Jamahiriya.
But there is a time limit to the mining ofunder¬
ground water: it can only go on for a few decades,
a century at most. It therefore becomes necessary
either to look for alternative sources for when
the water runs out, or else to plan for the trans¬
formation of the activities that depend upon it.
Finally, most aquifers are exploited by many
different parties for different and sometimes
incompatible purposes. And like many river
basins, they frequently extend across several
regions or even countries. If conflicts are to be
forestalled, there must be co-operation between
the communities and nations concerned.
THE POLLUTION
TIME-BOMB
The pollution of underground water reserves is
even more pernicious than that of surface water,
in that it is less immediately apparent and is often
diffuse and cumulative. It also lasts much longer.
Even local sources of contamination can make
their effects felt over great distances and consid¬
erable periods of time sometimes several gen¬
erations because the affected water is stored in
the soil and is only renewed very gradually.
The principal threat to groundwater comes
from harmful substances introduced into the
natural environment. This may happen deliber¬
ately through excessive use of fertilizers and
pesticides in agriculture, or sometimes even
through the dumping of dirty or waste water in
cesspools or unintentionally, by rainwater
leaching materials from badly-sealed urban or
industrial landfills, for example, or as a result of
leaking sewers or reservoirs or following spillage
of dangerous products such as hydrocarbons
during transport. These forms of pollution, which
stem ultimately from negligence or ignorance,
have repercussions on the quality of springs and
river tributaries. They pose a threat to surface-
water resources and aquatic ecosystems.
From both an economic and an environ¬
mental point of view, prevention is by far the
best way to fight pollution and preserve the
quality of underground water. Attitudes will
have to change and efforts will have to be made
not only by water consumers but perhaps to an
even greater extent by all land-users, whether
public or private, who must be made more aware
of the consequences of their acts.
The Earth's water
18
JEAN MARGAT
is a French hydrogeologist
who headed the Office of
Geological and Mining
Research in Orleans (France).
His published works include a
dictionary of hydrogeology
(1977) and (as a co-author)
Introduction à l'économie
générale de l'eau (1981). He ¡s
currently preparing for FAO a
methodological guide to the
evaluation of water resources.
oceans and seas
(97.2%)
glaciers and ice-caps
(2.15%)
underground water (0.625%)
lakes and rivers (0.0091%)
atmosphere (0.001%)
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
» > < i > \¿
" »V -r :* / /
»calaííng
consumption is
threatening to
outpace water
supply
Running
dry
by Sandra Postel
FOR decades, water has been wasted, mis¬
managed and overused and the conse¬
quences are beginning to hit home.
Water scarcity typically conjures up visions of
drought, the temporary dry spells that nature
inflicts from time to time. But while droughts cap¬
ture headlines and grab our attention, the far
greater threat posed by our escalating water con¬
sumption goes largely unnoticed.
Signs of water stress abound. Water tables are
falling, lakes are shrinking and wetlands are dis¬
appearing. Despite the disastrous experience of the
years 1955 to 1985, engineers propose "solving"
water problems by building ever more mammoth
dams and river diversion schemes, with exorbitant
price tags and damaging environmental effects.
Around Beijing, New Delhi, Phoenix and other
water-short cities, competition is brewing between
city-dwellers and farmers who lay claim to the
same limited supply. In the Middle East, water
scarcity stirs up disputes and tensions that threaten
to spill over into armed conflict. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
SANDRA POSTEL,
of the United States, Is vice-
president for research at the
Worldwatch Institute in
Washington D.C., a non-profit
research organization created
to study and focus attention
on world problems. She Is the
author of several Worldwatch
papers, notably on global
water Issues.
In each major area of water use agriculture,
industry and cities demand has increased
rapidly, and because of improved living stan¬
dards world water demand has been growing
faster than population: at 800 cubic metres a year,
per capita use today is nearly 50 per cent higher
than it was in 1950. Global water use has more
than tripled in the same period, and now stands
at an estimated 4,340 cubic kilometres per year.
But we actually rely on a far larger share since
water bodies dilute pollution, generate electricity
and support fisheries and wildlife.
Worldwide per capita water supplies, which
drop as population grows, are a third lower now
than in 1970. In an increasing number of coun¬
tries, population has surpassed the level that can
be sustained comfortably with the water available.
Hydrologists designate water-stressed countries
as those with annual supplies of 1,000-2,000 cubic
metres per person. When the figure drops below
1,000 cubic metres, nations are considered water-
scarce that is, lack of water becomes a severe
constraint on food production, economic devel¬
opment and protection of natural systems.
Today, discounting water flowing in from
neighbouring countries, twenty-six countries,
collectively home to 232 million people, fall into
the water-scarce category. As many of them have
very high population growth rates, their water
problems are deepening fast. Africa has the largest
number of water-scarce countries, but the Middle
East is the most concentrated region of scarcity
in the world, and tensions over water rights there
could ignite during this decade.
Other parts of the world have not been spared.
Symptoms of water stress exist, not just in the
water-scarce countries, but in parts of water-
wealthy ones as well. When groundwater is used
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Left, Mono Lake in
California.
Below, crocodiles in a
reserve in Thailand.
Saudi Arabia, for example, now mines fossil
groundwater to meet 75 per cent of its water needs,
and that dependence is growing as a result of gov¬
ernment efforts to encourage large-scale wheat
production in the desert. Though the country
imports barley and other food crops, it became self-
sufficient in wheat in 1 984, and has since joined the
ranks of the world's top wheat exporters. In early
1992, King Fahd authorized payments totalling
$2.1 billion for 1991's record four-million-tonne
wheat crop, which was worth only one fourth as
much at the world market price.
Groundwater depletion in Saudi Arabia has
been averaging about 5.2 billion cubic metres a
year, and that rate is projected to increase by
nearly half during the 1990s. At this rate the
supply would be exhausted in fifty-two years. At
the faster extraction rates projected for 2000-
2010, it would dry up much sooner, and even
before that happens the groundwater will likely
become too salty to use without expensive treat¬
ment. Thus, little of Saudi Arabia's grain can be
considered a reliable portion of the long-term
food supply either for Saudis or for those coun¬
tries receiving its exports.
Other places dependent on fossil ground¬
water include Libya and the northwestern corner
of Texas, where the amount of water in that state's
portion of the Ogallala aquifer the largest in the
world has already been diminished by a fourth.
In Beijing, water tables have been dropping 1-2
metres a year, and a third of the wells have report¬
edly gone dry. Groundwater pumping in Mexico
City exceeds recharge by 50-80 per cent, which
has led to falling groundwater levels, aquifer
faster than nature replenishes it, water tables fall
and eventually the underground supply becomes
too expensive to keep tapping and too salty to use.
Overuse of groundwater is now endemic in parts
of China, India, Mexico, Thailand, the western
United States, North Africa and the Middle East.
FOSSIL
GROUNDWATER
DEPLETION
Some of the most troubling cases of unsustainable
groundwater use involve "fossil" aquifers, under¬
ground reservoirs that hold water hundreds or
thousands of years old and that receive little
replenishment from rainfall today. Like oil
reserves, these aquifers are essentially nonre¬
newable. Farms and cities that depend on this
water will eventually face the problem of what to
do when the wells run dry.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Irrigated land in Kenya.
compaction, and land subsidence that has caused
the famous Metropolitan Cathedral to slump.
As demands continue to rise and water supply
projects get more difficult to build, water budgets
are becoming badly imbalanced in many regions.
From southern California to Israel, from northern
China to parts of India, shortages are becoming
chronic and rationing a way of life. In China,
for instance, planners project that Beijing's total
water demand in 2000 could outstrip available
supplies by 70 per cent. Israel's annual water use
already exceeds its renewable supply by some
300 million cubic metres, or 15 per cent. With the
projected influx of new immigrants in the coming
decade, its yearly water deficit will worsen gready.
DAMAGE TO THE AQUATIC
ENVIRONMENT
Shrinking groundwater reserves, falling water
tables and projected demands that far exceed
available supplies are clear signals of water stress,
but perhaps the most worrying sign of trouble
comes from examining the health of aquatic envi¬
ronments. The damming, diverting and polluting
of watercourses have wreaked havoc on the
world's wetlands, deltas, lakes and riverine habi¬
tats. Of all imperilled biological species, aquatic
fauna is undoubtedly at greatest risk.
The shrinking Aral Sea is but the most dra¬
matic in a long list of natural areas destroyed,
degraded or at grave risk from human use and
abuse of water a list that includes California's
Mono Lake, south Florida's Everglades, Spain's
Donaña wetlands and Sudan's Sudd swamps,
places that are home to astounding numbers and
varieties of bird and wildlife species.
All these species are at risk from the degrada¬
tion of the environment. In North America alone,
the American Fisheries Society lists 364 species of
fish as endangered, threatened or of special con¬
cern. An estimated one-third of the continent's fish,
two-thirds of its crayfish and nearly three-quarters
of its mussels are now "rare or imperilled".
A distressing conflict has emerged over two of
water's roles: as a commodity, and as a key life-
support for all species. This duality calls out for
a fresh approach, one that pays greater respect to
the vital functions of this precious element.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
«ff
THE UNESCO COURIER MAY 19 93
.
Dossier
23 NATURE UNDER
THREAT
by France Bequette
26 World
Voices from the past
28 THE MIRACLES
OF LOVE
4r!
Dossier
Ml UM Ulii!¡E <
m
< ¡frIJU
by France Bequette
In June 1992, the authorities in
Kigali (Rwanda) seized a young
Eastern lowland gorilla (Gorilla
gorillagraueri) and a young chim¬
panzee (Pan troglodytes) from a
foreigner passing through the
country. He had purchased them for
$1,000 and $500 respectively. It
turned out that the same man had
been arrested two years before when
in possession of five baby chim¬
panzees.
Authorities in Buenos Aires
(Argentina) confiscated a number
of birds a dealer was holding ille¬
gally: three golden conures (Aratinga
guarouba), two blue-and-yellow
macaws (Ara ararauna), one yellow-
crested cockatoo (Cacatúa sul-
phurea), two black lories (Loriusgar-
rulus), one Alexandrine parakeet
(Psittacula eupatria), and two minas
(Gracula religiosa). The dealer spent
three days in prison.
In mid-May 1992, a European
arriving in Paris from Madagascar
was arrested after customs officers
found in his baggage 14 lemurs
(Hapalemur), 46 radiata turtles
(Geochelonia radiata), and 7 boa
constrictors (Acrantophis madagas-
cariensis). The animals were sent
back to the country they had come
from and the traveller is currently
facing charges.
Also in May 1992, 8 elephant tusks,
each measuring 22 to 30 centime¬
tres long and weighing about 12.5
kilos, were seized at Cochin airport in
the state of Kerala (India). They had
been taken from baby male ele¬
phants. The smuggler is now facing
trial. In the same month, a man was
arrested in Shanghai (China), while
attempting to sell the skin of a giant
panda (Ailuropoda melanoleuca) for
$30,000. He has been sentenced to 12
years in jail.
In July 1992, a European dug up 85
specimens of the native giant rat¬
tlesnake plantain orchid (Goodyera
oblongifolia) in Marquette, Michigan
(U.S.A.), with the aim ofselling them
in Europe. He was fined $3,525. I
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Dossier
NAM UNDER WM
24
Volumes of cases like these could
be quoted, all of them bearing wit¬
ness to the violence done to wildlife
on a scale that has brought some
species to the brink ofextinction. In
response to this threat, a Conven¬
tion on International Trade in
Endangered Species of Wild Fauna
and Flora (CITES) was signed in
Washington on 3 March 1973. The
Convention came into force on 1 July
' 1 975, and so far it has been ratified by
118 states. The CITES Secretariat,
based in Lausanne (Switzerland) is
attached to the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme and is financed
by the Parties to the Convention.
Endangered species are listed in
three Appendixes to the Convention,
in order of the degree of protection
they are afforded. Appendix I pro¬
hibits all international trade in ele¬
phants, giant pandas and coela-
canths, for instance. Appendix II
authorizes a controlled international
trade in members of the cat family,
crocodiles, corals, and orchids.
Appendix III restricts international
trade in some species from certain
countries, such as hippopotamuses
from Ghana, or black bears from
Canada.
Extreme cruelty
Wild fauna and flora face two
major threats: the destruction of
their habitat and unrestricted com¬
mercial exploitation. CITES provides
signatory states with the legal means
to repress a traffic that is motivated
by the lure of profit and often
involves acts of revolting cruelty. To
take one example, park rangers often
come across the bloody corpses of
elephants with their tusks ripped
out. Baby elephants are slaughtered
for their "milk teeth", which weigh
scarcely a kilo, compared with the
average 12.6-kiIo weight of an adult
tusk.
Specialists agree that elephants
are an endangered species, but views
differ as to the size of the surviving
population. There were a reported
two million elephants in Africa in
the 1970s. Today the figures vary
between 350,000 and one million,
depending on the sources, with
about 100,000 killed each year.
There are several reasons for the
iW
decline of the African elephant (Lox-
odonta africana). One is the use of
firearms, which are much deadlier
than traditional hunting methods.
Others include the change in vege¬
tation and the drying up of many
watering holes as a result of the
periods of drought that have struck
the southern Sahel over the past
twenty years. Deforestation and
desertification have destroyed many
habitats. Demographic pressure
and the extension of farmland have
altered the elephants' migration
patterns.
When people are forced to com¬
pete with wild animals in order to
survive, a real problem of priorities
arises. In Burkina Faso, for instance,
villagers complain that elephants
empty their water holes and trample
their crops. Similar conflicts exist in
southern Cameroon, where ele¬
phants eat the manioc and bananas
that the Pygmies grow in small plots
on the edge of the forest.
It is all too easy for people in
Western countries who are quite
happy to shoot the wild boar that
wreak havoc in their fields to insist on
protection for animals that cause
them no harm. Yet solutions to the
dilemma do exist. One is to pay
compensation to those who suffer
loss. This is what happens in Burkina
Faso, although the budget for the
purpose is quite inadequate. Another
solution could be to protect the ele¬
phants by confining them to
reserves, although the feasibility of
this is questionable.
Nazinga is a ranch in Burkina Faso
near the border with Ghana. It con¬
sists of 94,000 hectares of wooded,
swampy ground inhabited by
warthogs, large herbivores and ele-
A rhinoceros in phants. Between 1984 and 1989, the
the Amboseli elephantpopulationrosefrom216to
reserve (Kenya). nearly 500. According to Olivier Jean,
Hunted for their a veterinarian at the Rural Develop-
homs, ment Institute in Ouagadougou,
rhinoceroses are every year the animals destroy 20 per
now an cent of all trees under 40 centime-
endangered tres in diameter in their search for
species, with a food, an activity on which, according
estimated to the Worldwide Fund for Nature,
worldwide they spend 18 to 20 hours a day.
population of For the local people, who are
only 11,000. among the poorest in the world with
a per capita income of less than $140
a year, the ranch is a tempting
prospect. Hunters by tradition, they
regard the roan antelope as fair
game. An elephant tusk, which can
fetch as much as $175 per kilo, rep¬
resents a fortune. A distinction
should be made between killing ani¬
mals for food and poaching on an
industrial scale. Some poachers
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
_
operate in commandos, spotting ele¬
phant herds from helicopters and
slaughtering them with automatic
weapons. The rangers, outnumbered
and armed only with old rifles, are
powerless to stop them.
When the elephant was trans¬
ferred from Appendix II to Appendix
I of the Washington Convention in
1989, it was hoped that it would
become impossible for poachers to
sell their booty. Not so. Although the
trade in elephants, dead or alive, has
theoretically been banned, customs
officials regularly seize shipments of
ivory, as well as the horns ofrhinoc¬
eros another endangered species
hides, and live animals as well. The
World Conservation Union, an inter¬
governmental agency with its head¬
quarters in Switzerland, keeps
updated lists of endangered species
together with registers of protected
sites around the world. It also mon¬
itors States Parties' compliance with
the terms of CITES.
Poaching and smuggling
Traffic, which was founded in 1976
by the World Conservation Union
and is based in Cambridge (United
Kingdom), is another vigilant
watchdog. The cases reported in its
bulletin, also named "Traffic", show
that regulation of a formerly free
trade has led to the development of
bizarre forms of smuggling. Among
the examples cited are suitcases full
ofparrots with their beaks and wings
bound by tape; five baby pythons
hidden in a pair of socks; parakeets
and birds' eggs sewn into the lining
of articles of clothing. Freight ship¬
ments have also produced a crop of
surprises, such as the consignment
of Bibles which, on examination,
proved to have been hollowed out
and to contain young rattlesnakes.
Last year, a case of wild birds con¬
taining jabirus and crowned cranes
arrived in the Netherlands by air
from Tanzania via Moscow. The case
had been transported upside down
and six of the nineteen birds were
dead.
In Swaziland, the rhinoceros's fate
is hardly more enviable. Only 13
white rhinos and 6 black rhinos are
left, but they are still attracting
poachers. The reason is the belief,
widely held in the Orient, that pow¬
dered rhinoceros horn has aphro¬
disiac properties. Bears and giant
pandas are killed for their gall blad¬
ders, which feature in the Chinese
pharmacopeia. Juju markets in Africa
display gorilla skulls, the skins ofbig
cats, lion penises and dried birds, all
sold as ingredients for potions or as
good luck charms.
The problem is a complex one.
What steps can be taken when tra¬
dition clashes with the idea of pro¬
tecting living species? How can
people be made to respect the 2,500
animal and 35,000 plant species
included in the Washington Con¬
vention when, for example, a scarlet
macaw (Ara macao), which is on the
endangered list, can be bought for
$100 in South America and sold for
$6,000 on the U.S. market? Political
determination by states, an uncom¬
promising commitment on the part
ofairline companies, special training
for customs officials, and exemplary
punishments for smugglers could at
least reduce such attacks on the
planet's biological diversity.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists.
m
1 1,000 Rhinos
(1992), a
sculpture by the
American artist
Jude
Burkhauser, is a
cry of alarm
against the
threat of
extinction
hanging over
many animal
and plant
species. The
detail opposite
shows the horns,
which are
moulded out of
plaster and
painted in red
ochre.
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
World
SAYING
THE INDIAN TIGER
The operation launched in 1973 to
save the tigers of India is helping to
keep up the numbers of this endan¬
gered species. At the latest count
there were 4,334 animals in 1989,
up from 4,005 in 1984, living in 18
reserves covering an area of 28,017
square kilometres. This is one of the
biggest successes scored by the
World Wide Fund for Nature
(WWF), a nongovernmental orga¬
nization with 4 million members
and 28 national branches, which
has carried out 5,000 programmes
and invested some $250 million in
nature conservation.
A FRIEND IN NEED
In Burkina Faso, a priest and five
laymen travel through the bush,
giving farmers advice after carefully
listening to what the elders of the
community have to say. Marin Ter¬
rible, a member of the White Fathers
missionary society, is a former nat¬
ural science teacher who arrived in
Burkina Faso in 1973, at a time of
famine following a year of drought.
He carried out a botanical survey of
the country's ligneous vegetation,
and drew a map of it. He also com¬
pared Landsat satellite images with
aerial photographs taken in the
1950s. His findings were alarming
but the situation did not seem irre¬
versible. Now when Father Terrible
and his team are invited to a village,
they take with them strips of cloth
which are wound around two poles
and are painted with familiar scenes
that provide a basis for discussion.
The team also produces an illus¬
trated almanac full ofsensible advice
drawing on traditional knowledge.
Typical entries include how to make
a pulley system for a well, how to
build small earth embankments to
collect rainwater, and how to
frighten away locust swarms. Father
Terrible was invited to the Earth
Summit in Rio, but unfortunately he
fell seriously ill and was unable to
attend.
A 'SLEEVE-PUMP'
FOR A SAFE WATER SUPPLY
Although Colombia has plentiful supplies of ground¬
water safe for drinking, one-third of the rural popula¬
tion draws its water from unprotected rivers, streams
and wells. With the help of a $500,000 grant from the
United Nations Development Programme and active
government support, 40,000 people living in small com¬
munities across the country have now been provided
with safe water. A nongovernmental organization, the
Las Gaviotas Centre, has been working for over 20 years
on low-cost technologies such as the so-called "sleeve-
pump", which can draw water up from a depth of 1 to 40
metres and requires little physical effort to manipu¬
late. Pipes made of recycled plastic are used to run the
water to homes, a rare luxury in this extremely poor
region.
26
FERTILIZER
FROM WASTE
Marta de Oliveira Prado teaches in
a government school on the out¬
skirts ofPelotas, an industrial town
in the south of Brazil that is badly
affected by pollution. In a letter to
the Courier, she explains that thé
children in her class live in such
extreme poverty that they often
have to go out to work at the age of
four or five. Some families survive
on what they can scavenge from
waste dumps, and this gave Marta
de Oliveira the idea of teaching her
pupils how to make organic fertil¬
izer from garbage (see photo left).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A WORLD OF WASTE
Sustainable development links
quality of life for everyone with the
quality of the environment we
share. The waste generated by ram¬
pant consumption in the industri¬
alized countries is harmful to the
developing countries. One person in
the North consumes from 14 to 1 15
times more paper, from 6 to 52
times more meat, and from 10 to
35 times more energy than a person
in a developing country. So much
plastic flotsam now litters the
oceans that nearly 2 million
seabirds and 100,000 marine mam¬
mals perish each year by choking
or by becoming entangled in it.
&=¿2
PROS AND CONS
OF ECO-TOURISM
'MY PLANET IS MIY BUSINESS'
The Asian and Pacific region, under the
pressure of a rapidly growing population,
has turned to eco-tourism as a way of
boosting foreign earnings. Unfortunately, it
is paying a high price. Nepal, for instance,
whose high peaks attract growing numbers
ofmountaineers, has been inundated with
rubbish. Every year, thousands ofvisitors go
mountain climbing or trekking in Sagar¬
matha National Park at the foot of Mount
Everest, leaving behind metal cans, plastic
debris and other types of waste, and
burning large quantities of firewood, which
is desperately scarce in the region. There
appears to be no ready answer to this
problem.
"My planet is my business" is the
motto of the Ushua'ia Foundation,
which was established on 15
December 1990 by French televi¬
sion director and presenter Nicolas
Hulot, under the sponsorship of the
Fondation de France and with
backing from the French power
utility Electricité de France, the
chemical firm Rhône-Poulenc, and
the city of Paris. The Foundation
states that its purpose "is to change
our attitude to nature by making it
better informed, more sympathetic,
and more respectful." It organizes
"Discovery Missions" in France and
elsewhere in the world for groups of
young people and adults selected
on grounds of motivation. The aim
of the Missions is to study the major
ecosystems and the phenomena
that govern them, with the help of
scientific experts. Twice a year, the
Foundation provides financial sup¬
port for environmental projects that
wish to publicize their findings.
Applications should include a 15-
line summary description of the
project and relevant details about
those engaged in it. Applicants
should also specify whether they
are seeking a financial grant (in
which case a detailed budget should
be submitted), a sponsorship
arrangement or scientific coun¬
selling. Please write to:
Fondation Ushua'ia,
32 Avenue Charles de Gaulle,
F-92200 Neuilly-sur-Seine,
France (Phone 33 1 46 41 03 03;
Fax 33 14641 0042).
VETIVER GRASS,
A CHECK AGAINST EROSION
When planted in rows, vétiver grass forms a thick hedge
and weaves a dense web of roots that can bind the soil
as deep as three metres beneath the surface. It adapts
to a wide variety ofclimates and environments, and has
been known and used for centuries in China and India.
It can withstand fire and overgrazing, is resistant to
most diseases, repels snakes and rodents, and is vul¬
nerable only to cold. It slows down rainwater runoff
and hence stops the vegetation cover from being
washed away, thereby preserving soil fertility and pro¬
ductivity. There is also a financial advantage: while the
construction of anti-erosion barriers costs an average
of $500 per hectare, planting vétiver grass costs less
than $30 per hectare. The World Bank has already con¬
tributed $500,000 to vétiver grass projects.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
=. Voicesfrom thepast
m
The French Romantic historian Jules Michelet (1 798-1874) was the author ofa
monumental body ofwork in which he acclaimed the heroism ofpeoplesfighting
for theirfreedom. He was also a passionate lover ofnature. In L'Insecte (1857), the
man who spoke outfor the proletariat also made the casefor the humblest
members ofthe animal kingdom.
The extract on this
page appears in an
anthology entitled
Compagnons du
Soleil (''Companions
of the Sun") co-
published (in French)
by Uufsco, Editions
La Découverte (Paris)
and the Fondation
pour le progrès de
l'Homme. The
anthology was
prepared under the
general editorship of
the African historian
Joseph Ki-Zerbo, in
collaboration with
Marie-Josèphe Beaud.
I ove has wings. Mythology is absolutely right.
The fact can be demonstrated literally,
without metaphor. For a brief moment
nature displays a restless urge to fly to the
beloved. Each creature transcends itself, all
rise towards the light, all go hunting on the wings
of desire. Alluring colours further bespeak the
inner fire. All are on display, all aim to please.
The butterfly seems to look at you with the great
eyes ofvelvet that adorn its wings. BeeÜes of every
kind, like mobile stones, astonish you with their
fiery glitter, the energy that burns within them.
And then, from the deepest shadows, naked and
unveiled, the flame of love explodes in scintil¬
lating stars.
Strange transfigurations take place at that
moment. From behind the humblest masks, in
violent contrast, the most splendid characers
emerge.
An obscure marsh grub, inert, surviving on cun¬
ning, becomes a brilliant amazon, the elegant
winged warrior we call the dragonfly (Libellula).
The only creature of its kind to express the com¬
plete freedom to be found in flight, it is to the
insects what the swallow is to the birds. Who has
not watched its thousand varied movements, as it
turns and turns about over meadow or stream in
the endless circles it describes with its blue-green
wings? What seems at first sight a random flight is
in fact not random at all; it is a hunt, an elegant and
rapid extermination of thousands of insects. What
looks like a game is really the fierce absorption of
a brilliant warrior-being seeking nourishment for
its time of love.
Don't think these riches are just the gifts of
golden climes, that the brilliant ball-gowns these
creatures don to love and die are no more than
some passing reflection of the Sun, the all-pow¬
erful decorator whose rays coppered the enam¬
elling, the jewels we admire on their wings.
Another Sun entirely, one that shines for all the
Earth, even to the chilly pole, plays a bigger part,
and that is love. It exalts the inner life in them,
brings out all their power and, on the appointed
day, makes the final bloom burst forth. The
sparkling colours that delight us are the creatures'
energy made visible, articulate and eloquent. They
are the pride of an entire life which, having
reached its summit, stretches out in triumph,
wishing to spread and bestow itself. They are the
transmission of desire, the imperious prayer, the
urgent appeal to the beloved.
In pallid, temperate climes, you will still find
these brilliant liveries you might have imagined
tropical in their hue. Who has not seen the can-
tharis burst forth beneath our dull and indeci¬
sive skies? Even in the gloomiest wastes where
summer is only a moment long, love as if to
spite the Sun and the bare and barren land .
raises beings of sumptuous splendour, opulent
in their adornment and their dress. Abruptly,
wretched Siberia sees princes and great lords
parade among the insect race. The harsh Russian
climate does not prevent enormous carabids, piti¬
less hunters, prouder than Ivan the Terrible, from
decorating themselves in green morocco, black,
violet or dark blue pinpointed with jet. Some,
usurping the colours of the robes of emperors
and of tsars, even strut about in purple bordered
with Byzantine gold.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Climate
changes
Iesulting from
\uman activity
él have serious
implications for
te distribution
the worlds
water
Qimate of uncertainty
by Igor A. Shiklomanov
bove, the Perito
Moreno glacier
(Argentina).
SOME scientists already foresaw in the nine¬
teenth century that the progress of civi¬
lization and the growth of industry and
energy consumption that went with it might
soon affect the world's climate.
It was only in the 1980s, however, that an
unprecedented warming of the atmosphere was
observed. Average temperatures rose from year
to year to reach the highest point since records
began to be kept in 1850. It became increasingly
difficult to put this phenomenon down to mere
climatic variations. Even the most sceptical cli-
matologists began to concede that global warming
was a reality, and public opinion has generally
grown used to that idea.
Many countries have set up national research
programmes or joined in programmes co-ordi¬
nated by various international bodies including
UNESCO to look into climatic changes brought
about by human activities. A round-up of the
findings of this research, prepared by a group of
specialists drawn from various countries, was
approved by the second World Climate Con¬
ference, held in Geneva in November 1990.
This research shows that, if present rates of
population growth and industrial development
are maintained, the air temperature is likely to
increase by 2 or 3 °C in the next twenty to thirty
years. The warming effect would be greatest, as
much as 5 or 6 °C, in the cold and temperate
zones, and less marked in the tropical and sub¬
tropical zones.
The possible effect of these temperature
increases on the hydrosphere that part of the
Earth covered by water and ice is a matter for
serious concern, since the hydrosphere is partic¬
ularly sensitive to climatic changes, to which it
reacts immediately. Any alteration to the hydro-
logical cycle has a direct impact on economic
development and on the environment in many
parts of the world, causing an upheaval in the con¬
ditions in which the local populations live.
In the higher latitudes, the Arctic and
Antarctic in particular, there will be an increas¬
ingly rapid melting of the snow and ice, in which
enormous quantities over twenty-four million
cubic kilometres of fresh water have been stored
up over hundreds and thousands of years. This
will cause a gradual rise in the levels of the oceans,
which could amount to a metre within the next 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
century and much more thereafter, with obvi¬
ously disastrous consequences for low-lying
coastal regions such as the Netherlands or
. Bangladesh, as well as for such major conurba¬
tions as London or St. Petersburg.
As the air temperature goes up, evaporation
from both land surfaces and water surfaces will
increase too. The atmosphere will become more
humid, the processes of the hydrological cycle
will speed up and rainfall may increase. In short,
this change in the climate will profoundly disturb
all the workings of the system whereby the waters
of the Earth and of the seas are held in balance.
SHRINKING RIVERS
Rivers provide almost 90 per cent of the world's
supplies of fresh water. Hydraulic engineering
projects aimed at regulating their flow have con¬
siderably affected the volume of water they carry,
a large part of which (over 4,000 cubic kilometres
a year) is now drawn off for industry, urban
water supplies and, in especially large quanti¬
ties, irrigation. The creation of large artificial
lakes and reservoirs, often as big as natural lakes,
upsets normal streamflow and evaporation pat¬
terns over vast areas. Increased water consump¬
tion is also tightening the pressure on water
resources. In certain densely populated regions,
rivers have "lost" from 20 to 30 per cent of their
normal flow and some, like the Amu-Darya and
Syr-Darya in the former Soviet Union, as much
as 90 per cent.
The effects of rising temperatures on river
discharge are likely to be very serious, especially
in the arid zones. Annual discharges in such
regions will plummet, even if the air temperature
rises by only 1 or 2 °C and rainfall drops by no
more than 10 per cent.
Variations in precipitation have an even more
decisive impact than temperature increases as
such. If the latter were accompanied by even a
From its source in the
mountains of central Asia,
the Amu Darya flows
through the deserts of the
Turan Lowlands towards
its mouth on the southern
shore of the Aral Sea. Its
discharge has sharply
diminished in recent years.
Water pollution in the
Kowloon district of Hong
Kong.
SO
^^ . IjH '^ J
-- *ri
r . "" "^^^^^^
%-- . Jük*¿< ^"^*J
rvJ^g-- ^ r^*^^; - -^
> , ;
Iß
ferÊÊ2É
m
*^d- -*,-« ^tf
slight reduction in rainfall in the arid and semi-
arid regions which comprise 30 per cent of the
land-mass in Europe, 60 per cent in Asia and
vast areas of Africa and Australia, the world's
water problems would become much worse. The
change would affect not only annual flows but
also seasonal flows, especially in the temperate
zones, where the springtime peak discharge is
of great importance.
A temperature rise of 2 °C, leading to more
rapid melting of snow because of warm spells in
winter, would increase the discharge of the great
rivers of Russia and Ukraine the Volga, Dnieper
and Don by 50 to 100 per cent in winter, but
would decrease it by 25 to 30 per cent in the
spring. Similar conclusions have been reached
for Scandinavian countries (Finland, Norway
and Sweden), and for certain river basins in
Poland, Belgium and the mountain regions of
the United States. In all these areas, and over
much of the northern hemisphere as a whole,
seasonal and annual river discharge would be
particularly affected by air temperature changes.
These scenarios are of little relevance for the
warm and arid zones or for the tropics, where
forecasts sometimes contradict one another.
Palaeoclimatological data tend to suggest that
there would be only slight increases in air tern-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
peratures, accompanied by sizeable increases in
rainfall, but these optimistic conclusions are chal¬
lenged by other climate predictions, based on
global climate modelling, which on the contrary
envisage sharp rises in air temperatures and only
slight rises in rainfall.
DANGEROUS
FLUCTUATIONS
Research into the effects of global warming on the
hydrological cycle also shows another factor of
major importance possible modifications in the
maximum and minimum flow levels of streams
and rivers. On the basis of empirical data and the¬
oretical calculations foreseeing a twofold increase
in the proportion of carbon dioxide in the com¬
position of the atmosphere, it has been demon¬
strated that, in New Zealand for example, the
rainy seasons will become wetter and the dry sea¬
sons drier and longer, resulting in increased vari¬
ations in seasonal streamflow. According to the
same calculations, the maximum values for rain¬
fall and streamflow in Australia will rise and the
minimum values fall, summer and winter alike.
River levels are likely to rise significantly in the
north-west of the United States, north-eastern
Canada, the north and west of Great Britain and
the northern part of western Europe. The widest
fluctuations will probably occur in Japan and
California.
This alternation between extremes higher
river levels and more frequent droughts is
fraught with economic and ecological risks, espe¬
cially for urbanized areas and agricultural regions,
and could make it necessary to rethink the dis¬
tribution of irrigated farmland and to relocate
most of the water-consuming industries. The
warm and arid areas of the world could well run
into serious water-supply problems that in places
could degenerate into conflict.
To deal with all these problems, the authori¬
ties in some regions may have to revert to the
mammoth hydraulic engineering schemes that
were popular in the 1960s and 1970s: the building
of enormous reservoirs, river diversions, the
redistribution of water resources and increased
exploitation of fossil aquifers.
It is obviously no longer possible to close
our eyes to the potential consequences of man-
made climatic changes and variations in water
resources, consequences that call for extensive
research, especially if precise, detailed forecasts are
to be established for each part of the world an
extremely complicated task that requires close
collaboration by scientists the world over, in the
interests of all humanity.
IGOR A. SHIKLOMANOV
is a Russian geographer who is
a corresponding member of
his country's Academy of
Natural Sciences, vice-
chairman of its national
committee for the
International Hydrological
Programme (IHP) and director
of the state hydrological
institute in St. Petersburg. He
is the author of more than 140
scientific papers on the
problems of hydrology and
water resources. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Human
i
activities as well
as climatic
onditions are
responsible for
(esert advance.
he/ can also
help to curb it
Shifting sands
by Harold Dregne
D
ESERTIFICATION has been defined as land
I degradation in arid, semi-arid and dry sub-
humid areas resulting mainly from adverse
human impact.
It was long thought to be largely due to the
occurrence of droughts. Not until preparations
were being made for the United Nations Con¬
ference on Desertification, held in Nairobi,
Kenya, in 1977, and convened in an attempt to
prevent a recurrence of the human misery and loss
of livestock that occurred during the severe West
African drought of 1969-1973, did it become
clear that more than drought was involved in
the degradation of grazing land.
After all, droughts were an inevitable part of
the climatic regime in the drylands. Indigenous
plants had adapted to the sequences of wet and dry
years that affect all arid regions. They prospered
in the wet years, then called upon their adaptive
mechanisms to carry them through the dry years.
It was only when humans tipped the balance
against them by over-grazing and wood-cutting
that vegetation was no longer able to handle the
moisture stresses brought on by drought.
Grazing land is not alone in being subject to
desertification, and a lot of damage has occurred
32
M|
on both rain-fed and irrigated crop land. Most
descriptions of desertification are centred on
grazing lands simply because pastoralism is the
dominant land use in nearly 90 per cent of the
world's drylands.
Rain-fed crop lands become exposed to the
threat of accelerated (human-induced) water and
wind erosion as soon as the native vegetation is
destroyed when land is cleared for cultivation.
Controlling erosion requires good management
skills because crop production usually leaves
land bare and unprotected during some part of the
year. Salinization the accumulation of salts in the
irrigation water or in the original soil is an addi¬
tional threat to irrigated crop land and is usually
the consequence of inadequate soil drainage.
Vegetation degradation, water erosion, wind
erosion and salinization are the major desertifi¬
cation processes in the drylands. However, com¬
paction of cultivated land by machinery probably
does as much, if not more, damage in many coun¬
tries. A land degradation process that can be
locally important is the accumulation in the soil
of toxic substances such as heavy metals (lead,
chromium, etc.), pesticides and industrial wastes.
The adverse effect of such toxic substances is not
so much on the soil as on the humans and animals
that feed on plants growing in contaminated soil.
What is the extent of the problem? The results
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
s
Left, rice terraces in the
Philippines.
Above, a herd of cattle
near Lake Magadi (Kenya).
of a study made for the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme indicate that, over a total
area of some 5,160 million hectares, a quarter of
the irrigated land, half of the rain-fed crop land
and three-quarters of the rangeland are desertified.
CAN DESERTIFICATION
BE HALTED!
One interesting outcome of the desertification
study is the finding that there is an inverse relation
between the severity of desertification and the
intensity of land use. Rangelands represent a low-
intensity land use but have proportionately more
degraded land than the irrigated lands, where
land-use intensity is high. Rain-fed crop land,
where land-use intensity is medium, has an inter¬
mediate proportion of degraded land. This implies
that intensive land use produces a more sustainable
agriculture than does extensive use.
Methods of halting further land degradation
of all kinds and of reversing vegetation degrada¬
tion and salinization are known. Reversing water
and wind erosion is difficult, or impossible for all
practical purposes, since erosion causes removal
of soil, which requires decades, if not centuries,
to replace by natural means. Soil compaction by
machinery is readily controllable.
Improving salt-affected irrigated land is a rel¬
atively uncomplicated process and cost/benefit
analyses of salinity control are fairly easy to cal¬
culate, given the fact that the main cost is, usually,
to provide an effective drainage system. Recla¬
mation of the soil, once the reclamation system is
operating, is generally complete in three years or
less. Sometimes it takes only a few months.
In principle, grazing land improvement is
simple. All that is needed, in most cases, is to
reduce the grazing pressure on the vegetation. In
some situations seeding is necessary to ensure
that desirable perennial plants can be established
rapidly. Unfortunately, reducing grazing pres¬
sure is not easily implemented because fewer
livestock mean lower returns to the pastoralist.
Improving grazing lands in the dry sub-humid
climatic zone can be done much more rapidly
than in the arid climatic zone. Where it would
perhaps take five to ten years of good manage¬
ment to restore range productivity if weather
conditions were favourable in the dry sub-
humid zone, it might well require fifty years or
more in the arid zone.
Proven practices to control erosion by water
include terracing, strip cropping, contour culti¬
vation and minimum tillage. The two principal
objectives of such control practices are to protect
the soil from the impact of raindrops on bare
soil and to slow the down-slope movement of
runoff water. Bench terracing, which has been 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
practised for centuries on steep slopes in many
countries, particularly in Asia, is very effective but
is extremely labour-intensive.
Wind erosion control is usually accomplished
by building shelter-belts (wind-breaks), strip
cropping, using tillage practices that roughen the
surface, minimum tillage and spreading crop
residues over the soil. In each case the objective
is to slow the speed of wind movement at the soil
surface, thereby reducing the eroding ability of
the wind. One rarely used method of stopping
wind erosion is to spray the soil with asphalt.
Asphalt is selected as a last resort it is expen¬
sive in extremely arid regions where vegeta¬
tion cannot be established.
Solid walls, wooden fences and a latticework
of plastic strips are other devices that have been
tried for erosion control. Shelter-belts consisting
of a mixture of shrubs and trees are widely used.
The major disadvantage of shelter-belts is the
competition for water by tree roots extending into
the crop field.
Nearly all degradation control practices are
site specific that is to say that adjustments must
be made to fit local land, climate, economic and
cultural conditions. Bench terracing, for example,
is fine when soils are moderately deep and labour
is cheap, but it is completely impracticable when
soils are only moderately deep or labour is expen¬
sive. Similarly, minimum tillage is a highly effec¬
tive water and wind erosion control practice that
is only practicable if weeding can be done eco¬
nomically by hand labour or the timely applica¬
tion of herbicides.
THE SITUATION TODAY
My assessment of global desertification leads me
to draw a number of conclusions. First, that
grazing land deterioration in the drylands has
been going on for centuries in some areas and
more recently in all others. Rangeland produc¬
tivity has probably levelled off nearly every¬
where and will stay at a low level indefinitely. I see
little likelihood that the current situation will
change either for better or for worse. Grazing is
a low-value land use that cannot pay for expen¬
sive improvement measures. Only governments
can afford, for social or political reasons, to
improve rangelands. '
Second, there will be two opposite changes in
salinization of irrigated land as water shortages
become more acute. If the shortages lead to
increased water-use efficiency, salinization will
decrease. If the shortages are not met with prac¬
tices to increase water-use efficiency, salinity will
worsen. The sum of the two responses may well
be to increase global salinization of irrigated land.
There will almost certainly be an increase in dry¬
land salinity, which, globally speaking, is not
extensive as yet.
Third, water erosion is the major threat to
long-term soil productivity. For all practical pur¬
poses, water erosion removes soil permanently.
New soil material develops so slowly that it can
take centuries to change rock into soil. Whereas
gully erosion is readily observable, sheet erosion
gradually wears away the soil mantle. There is little
evidence of damage until, one day, a farmer notices
that the soil on his hills is orange-coloured instead
of the black it was originally. It is then that he real¬
izes that erosion has robbed him of topsoil and
that all he can do is to try to prevent further loss.
Fourth, wind erosion damage will be largely
unchanged in the future. Wind erosion is a fact of
life in the arid regions. Although there are many
knowledgeable people who believe this to be a
serious on-site problem, my view is that the
damage is modest on a global scale. Local
blowouts are one thing; they are very destructive,
but not extensive. Off-site damage to buildings,
highways, railways, machinery and human and
livestock health is another matter.
Whereas water erosion apparently causes as
much off-site damage (floods, reservoir sedi¬
mentation, water pollution, etc.) as on-site
damage, wind erosion stands out as having much
more severe off-site than on-site impact. The
only known study of on-site/off-site wind ero¬
sion damage costs was done for the State of New
Mexico, in the United States. That study con¬
cluded that off-site damage costs were about
forty-five times greater than on-site costs.
My overall conclusion is that no great change
in the extent and severity of desertification is
likely in the immediate future.
As part of a fight-the-
desert project in
Mauritania, fences are
built to keep the sand
from blowing away.
HAROLD DREGNE,
of the United States, is Horn
Distinguished Professor of Soil
Science at Texas Tech
University in Lubbock. He is
the author of 5 books and
many papers on arid lands,
irrigation water salinity, soils,
dryland agriculture and
desertification. In 1992 he was
a consultant with the United
Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP) project
on a World Atlas of
Desertification.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
i - ' H I
d
¿*ÊaW%-*
f\s a result of
poverty,
population
growth,
urbanization and
pollution, water
management is
set to become
the most crucial
natural resource
issue facing the
developing world
THE days when water could be considered a
cheap and plentiful resource are virtually
over, and many parts of the developing
world are already facing a water crisis which is
likely to intensify significantly during the coming
decades. This crisis in the South is the direct
result of four interrelated phenomena.
First, since nearly all the easily available
sources of water have now been developed or are
in the process of development, the unit costs of
future projects are bound to rise. Meanwhile,
many developing countries are saddled with very
high levels of debt, and the amount of new invest¬
ment available, both internally and externally, is
limited. In addition, competition for available
funds is intense.
Second, current estimates indicate that by the
year 2050 world population is likely to double to
10.64 billion, of which developing countries will
contribute nearly 87 per cent, or 9.29 billion.
While there is no one-to-one relationship between
population and water requirements, it is clear
that with a substantial increase in population,
water requirements in the South are bound to
increase as well. Furthermore, past experience
indicates that as standards of living rise so do
per capita water requirements, and so if current
Crisis in the
South
by Asit K. Biswas
poverty-alleviation programmes succeed, these
requirements will increase further.
Third, as the impact of human activities
increases, water is being contaminated by more
and more waste products such as untreated or
partially-treated sewage, agricultural chemicals
and industrial effluents. Already many sources of
water near urban centres of developing coun¬
tries have been seriously affected.
The fourth major factor relates to the
increasing delays in implementing new water
projects that are likely in the coming decades
owing to higher costs and lack of funds. Social and
environmental factors will also significantly delay
project initiation time, certainly more than in
recent decades.
In the South there will be increasing pres¬
sure to make water management more efficient
than ever before. However, the amount of time
available for these improvements is likely to be
short certainly no more than a decade, or at
most two. While technological problems may
be comparatively easy to solve, political, institu¬
tional and social constraints are likely to be a
very different matter. They may, in fact, pose the
most difficult challenge for water management in
the South in the twenty-first century. 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The Itaipú dam on the
Paraná River was built by
Paraguay and Brazil.
36
AS IT K. BISWAS,
Indian-born Canadian specialist
on water resources
development and
environmental management, is
the president of the
International Society for
Ecological Modelling, based in
Copenhagen (Denmark). A
former scientific advisor to
several United Nations
agencies and many
governments, he is the author
of a prolific body of work
which has been translated into
1 3 languages.
Here are some priority areas for action:
Raising theglobalprofile offreshwater issues.
Efficient water development and management
will require significantly more capital than the
countries of the South have access to at present.
Until water is placed squarely on the interna¬
tional and national agenda, the necessary funds
will not be forthcoming.
The conservation and efficient use of water
have only received lip-service so far. Since agri¬
culture is by far the largest user of water, efficient
irrigation management will undoubtedly be a
major conservation option in the future.
Although some progress has been made during
the past decade, the overall level of efficiency is
still far too low.
Considerable scope also exists for practising
water conservation in the domestic and industrial
sectors. In many towns and cities in developing
countries, more than half the treated water is lost
because of leakage. Design changes can signifi¬
cantly reduce water requirements in the industrial
sector.
Institutional strengthening and co-ordination.
Most water management institutions in the South
need considerable strengthening. In addition,
nearly all countries must substantially improve the
level of collaboration between institutions at
present water-related policies are developed in a
fragmented fashion. At the international level,
much better coordination is necessary between the
multilateral and bilateral assistance organizations.
Management of international water sources.
The only major sources of water that remain to
be developed are international in character, that
is they are shared by two or more countries.
Unless proper treaties are negotiated between
co-basin countries, international water bodies
are likely to be a fertile area of conflict in the
future.
Very few objective in-depth analyses of inter¬
national water bodies in developing countries
are currently available. To a great extent interna¬
tional organizations have deliberately steered
clear of the issue, mainly because it has been con¬
sidered to be politically sensitive.
Environmental considerations. The environ¬
mental aspects of water resource development
need more attention.
Research and training. Countries of the South
have to forge better links with one another on
research and training in water management. Cur¬
rently, there is very little South-South knowl¬
edge and technology transfer. For example, even
though countries like Egypt and India have many
common water problems, and the various insti¬
tutional, economic and technical constraints are
somewhat similar, Egyptian water professionals
have very little knowledge of Indian practices
and vice versa. Considerably more needs urgently
to be done in this area.
Equally, international organizations need to'
develop clear and cost-effective training strate¬
gies for water professionals of the South. Is it
preferable, for example, to bring them to France
or the United States for a two-week training pro¬
gramme, when the same amount of money could
provide more than a year's training at a good
Indian institution? Fundamental questions of this
type have yet to be asked, let alone answered
properly.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Aswan
High Dam,
25 years on
by Mahmoud Abu-Zeid
andM.ß.ASaad
The Nile at Isna, near
Luxor in Upper Egypt.
FROM time immemorial life in Egypt has revolved
round Nahr an-Nil, the River Nile, the longest
river in the world and the dominating feature of
Egypt's topography. The ancient Egyptians recog¬
nized the importance of the waters of the Nile to their
economy and kept records of the river level with the aid
of nilometers gauges formed by graduated scales cut
in natural rocks or stone walls.
It was therefore quite natural that, in the push for
development in the immediate post-war years, the
Egyptians should turn once again to the Nile for solu¬
tions. Thus was born the concept of the construction
of a new dam designed to control the Nile water for the
expansion of cultivation, to iron out the impact of
both drought and floods and to provide for the gener¬
ation of hydro-electric power.
Begun in 1 959 amid a furious controversy about the
possible ecological consequences, the Aswan High
Dam (one of the largest in the world) and its associated
power station have been fully operational since 1970.
Lake Nasser, the reservoir formed upstream as a result
of the construction of the dam, is over 500 kilometres
long, with an average width of 12 kilometres. It pene¬
trates some 200 kilometres into the Sudan and covers
an area of about 6,500 square kilometres.
The balance-sheet
The dam was conceived as an ambitious, multi¬
purpose project aimed at improving irrigation and
water resource control and development, increasing cul¬
tivation, providing protection against high floods and
severe drought, and facilitating navigation, fishery
expansion and electric power generation, while mini¬
mizing harmful effects on the environment and the
country's rich cultural heritage.
What is the situation after nearly a quarter of a
century of full-scale operation? In Upper Egypt some
380,000 hectares of cultivated land have been brought
under year-round irrigation, which means that two or
three harvests can be produced annually instead of
one. Water is available for a variety of crops, even in
low-flood years, and this has resulted, for example, in
the quadrupling of the area under rice cultivation.
Drainage has improved in all cultivated areas and pro¬
ductivity has increased by from 20 to 50 per cent. Some
420,000 hectares of new land have been brought into
cultivation since completion of the High Dam, and it
is estimated that a total of over a million hectares could
eventually be reclaimed.
From the point of view of flood and drought pro¬
tection, the Dam appears to have been an unqualified
success. Human lives and cultivated lands were suc¬
cessfully protected during the high-flood years of 1964,
1967 and 1975, and sufficient water was available in both
Egypt and the Sudan during the low-flood years of
1972, 1979, 1983 and 1984.
The vast size of Lake Nasser has led to a multipli¬
cation of the fish population, which has become an
important source of protein for Egyptian consumers.
The High Dam power station is now one of the main
pillars of industrial development in Egypt. It supplies
energy to many new factories in the Nile valley and to
many farms and villages in the rural areas.
Some negative side-effects
Since completion of the Aswan High Dam water
flowing downstream from it has become silt free and
this has had a number of deleterious side-effects:
Degradation and lowering of the river bed, affecting
the stability of existing hydraulic structures across the
Nile in particular the Isna, Nag Hammadi and Asyut
barrages (although recent studies suggest that the level
of degradation may be much less than was previously
thought).
Lower water levels and seepage of irrigation water
from nearby cultivated land, leading to the collapse of
parts of the river banks.
Raising of the water table due to excessive use by
farmers of irrigation water which is now available all the
year round.
Some deterioration in water quality and increased
salinity due to long-term storage in the lake upstream
of the High Dam.
A massive increase in aquatic weeds of various types
(82 per cent of water courses, canals and drains are
now heavily infested by weeds).
This sudden weed invasion, perhaps the most serious
side-effect of the construction of the High Dam, is
ascribed to the following factors: silt-free water allows
deeper sunlight penetration, thus encouraging weed
growth; the annual floods that used to occur before
construction of the High Dam used to flush the channels
and push weeds to the Mediterranean; with two to three
crops being cultivated annually, land fertilization has
increased, causing eutrophication of drains and canals.
Health impacts
Since the construction of the High Dam a number
of plans have been drawn up for the economic devel¬
opment of the region along the shores of the reservoir.
These include the establishment of human settlements,
industrial development and tourism and recreational
projects. There is a serious risk that such schemes will
affect the water quality and the aquatic ecosystem of the
reservoir. Furthermore, deterioration in the quality of
the water of the reservoir would affect downstream
river users.
MAHMOUD ABU-ZEID AND M. B. A. SAAD
are respectively president and secretary-general of the
Centre for Water Research (Cairo). 3J
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The liquid of the gods
by Camille Talkeu
Tounounga
Awealth of symbolic meanings source of
all life, purifying substance, regenerating
element is attached to water in Black
African traditions.
In the creation myths of the Dogon of Mali,
water is a divine green seed that impregnates the
Earth so that it brings forth twin green beings, half
man, half serpent. Also according to Dogon
mythology, impregnation presupposes that oil,
the male seed, combines in the womb with the
moisture of the vagina in a helix symbolizing the
creative vibration.
Like their Bambara neighbours, the Dogon go
further and assimilate water, the fertilizing seed,
Venerated for its
divine qualities since
the time of the
Pharaohs, water is
still invested with a
rich symbolism in
black Africa today
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The cross device on the
masks worn by these
Dogon villagers of Mali is a
symbolic representation of
Amma, the supreme god
of a cosmogony in which
water plays a vital part.
to light and to the gift of speech, the creating
Word. "Dry" water and "dry" words express
the idea of thought, the idea of potentiality, both
among humans and among the gods. Genesis
occurred when the supreme celestial god Amma
created in his likeness Nommo, the god of "wet"
water. In music, oil symbolizes the melody and
rhythm is represented by water, the word.
For these peoples, and in many countries of
sub-Saharan Africa, water, the life principle, is
closely involved in the rites accompanying child¬
birth. When the afterbirth is expelled, proving that
the child has indeed been born, one of the mid-
wives takes a mouthful of water and sprays it
gently over the baby. The cool touch of the water
makes it cry out it has "officially" received the
gift of speech.
Invested with divine properties throughout
Africa since the time of the Pharaohs, water plays
its part in the fertility of the fields and of all living
beings and all things, but in addition each kind of
water rain, spring, river, pond, lake, sea, dew,
water collected in a hollow tree has a particular
significance. According to the Bantu, creation
took place in a great whirlpool or in a bed of
reeds, somewhere to the East. The Fali of
Cameroon associate water, the uterine element,
with fish. Among the Bamileke of western
Cameroon, fathers bless their daughters on their
wedding day with water in which leaves oîfefe,
a kind of spinach symbolizing gentleness and
harmony, have been steeped.
CLEANSING
AND HEALING
Purification, indissociable from initiation rites,
cleanses the initiates of previous impurities, drives
away evil forces and protects them. Among the
Bambara, at the end of the initiation ceremony,
the chief of the kore, the initiates' society, sprays
a mouthful of water over the neophytes. They are
then washed, first in the meeting-place of the
kore by a former initiate, with water from the vil¬
lage's sacred pond, then a second time at the vil¬
lage's holy well.
The bellies of young Sara girls in Chad are also
cleansed with water taken from a gourd and
sprayed from their mothers' mouths, while Zulu
girls, after being kept in seclusion for some weeks,
take a ritual bath in the river and wash off the red
clay with which they have daubed themselves.
Water, the abode of the spirits, plays a part in
the voodoo ceremonies of Benin, Togo and
Nigeria. It is a pervasive presence in Haiti, where
voodoo, practised both publicly and in the family,
is a way of rediscovering an identity that was
profoundly disturbed when the ancestors of
today's islanders were uprooted from Africa.
Haitians believe that they can reconquer that
mythical Africa whence all the spirits come, by
way of subterranean waters that constitute a
world of their own and teem with human activ¬
ities of every kind. This is why magical proper¬
ties are attributed to springs, rivers and waterfalls,
and why water is poured out before the altar at the
beginning of ceremonies, in order to summon up
spirits from the underworld.
Water may also be at the root of the tem¬
poral and religious power exercised by groups of
initiates, usually secret societies, which by super¬
natural means assume the magical attributes of
water spirits. One such organization is to be
found among the Duala, a people inhabiting
the coastal region of Cameroon, who have a
water ancestor, thejengu, represented in bygone
days as a black man with long hair, bulging eyes
and splayed feet and more recently as a long¬
haired white woman. Thejengu confers wealth on
men and fertility on women. It may take human
form, manifesting its power by miracles and
prophecies and acting as a counterbalance to the
authority of the chiefs. Until the German colo¬
nization of this part of Africa, thejengu played an
important political role among the Duala;
revered as an ancestor, a jengu could marry into
the nobility. Even today the jengu retains thera¬
peutic powers, for although the old beliefs have
all but disappeared from public life, they still
survive in the context of illness and healing, in the
form of invocations, states of possession or trance,
and prayers.
PRAYERS
AND PETITIONS
Water is a precious substance and when it is in
short supply disasters may occur. The peasant's life
depends on the rains. If they come late or not at all,
or if they are too abundant, he performs again
and again the rituals and invocations of which
the fabric of rural civilization is woven. Many
myths explain the origin of these practices.
According to the Diola of west Africa, in the
beginning there were two divinities, Amontong,
the god of drought, and Montogari, the rain god.
They owned great flocks and lived together until
one day they quarreled and came to blows. While
they were fighting, Amontong's wives sent off
their children with dried skins tied to ropes. Drag¬
ging the skins behind them, the children raised lots
of dust, which became clouds, and the noise made
by the skins became thunder. The gods discharged
their shotguns at them, creating lightning. Then
the children of Montogari took what remained of
the dust and made rain. B
CAMILLE TALKEU TOUNOUNGA
is a sociologist and anthropologist from Cameroon whose
most recent publications are Islam et négritude, Le
nomadisme en Afrique, l'exemple des Peuls and Symbolique des
masques en Afrique noire (all 1 993). 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The forgotten ones
by Tassoum L Douai
;
Women are
frica's front-
line troops in
e struggle for
survival against
drought, famine
and war. They
also have to
ight for
(cognition of
eir crucial role
in economic
velopment
ft
SETTING drinking water is a simple matter
of turning on a tap in the countries of the
North, but it involves a veritable assault
course for most Africans African women, to be
more precise, since in addition to looking after the
home and the children, cooking the meals and
tending the crops, women are also burdened with
this arduous task, which often means having to
walk miles to fetch the precious liquid.
Africa is a continent of climatic contrasts,
arid in some parts, rainy on either side of the
Equator, and for twenty years or so it has suffered
from disturbances in the normal weather pat¬
terns that have had disastrous effects, particu¬
larly in such regions as the Sahel. The Sahel
receives very little rain, and the impact of inade¬
quate rainfall is direct. Wells and streams run
dry, crops and cattle die off, villagers abandon the
land for the towns, malnutrition follows, infant
mortality increases and outbreaks of water-borne
diseases reappear. No reference to water in the
African context would be complete without a
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
mention of river blindness, bilharzia, viral
hepatitis, cholera and malaria.
Although the Sahel is the region worst
affected, the Horn of Africa and southern Africa
have also been ravaged by drought since 1991.
Southern Africa is facing an unprecedented food-
supply emergency. South Africa, traditionally
an exporting country that kept its less fortunate
neighbours supplied with cereals, is set to import
grain in large quantities. Cereal production in
the ten countries of the Southern African Devel¬
opment Co-ordination Conference (SADCC),
which stood at twelve million tonnes on average,
slumped this year by half, and eighteen million
people face famine.
THE POOR RELATIONS OF
DEVELOPMENT
Women are the first casualties of drought, famine
and war. They have to struggle to keep life going
in this nightmare world of ruin and desolation.
Poverty drives the menfolk away to neighbouring
countries or to swell the ranks of the urban
unemployed, leaving women to cope alone with
immense responsibilities. Deprived of traditional
forms of support, they need new sources of
income to ensure the survival of their families and
communities, but illiteracy and lack of training
invariably oblige them to seek employment in the
informal sector.
Above, harvesting blue
algae in Chad.
Left, a woman carries
water in Mali.
Their already precarious health situation has
been further undermined, largely by frequent
childbearing and chronic malnutrition. Their
working hours (according to some estimates,
women work on average 2,490 hours a year, as
against 1,400 for men) have been made even
longer by current shortages, which oblige them
to go farther and farther afield in search of water
and firewood not forgetting the long treks they
have to make with sick children to the few clinics
that exist, where they have to wait for hours as
they do at the well.
The efforts made and the aid provided during
the 1 980s as part of the United Nations Interna¬
tional Drinking Water Supply and Sanitation
Decade, have, it is true, started to bear fruit. Sub¬
stantial resources have been mobilized for this
battle, and a number of hydraulic schemes aimed
at alleviating women's drudgery have been
launched. The results have been uneven, but the
lessons learned from the projects that have failed
will certainly enable beneficial readjustments to
be made in the future.
Despite this, and despite the fact that they
are the most productive members of African
society, women remain the poor relations of the
economy, the outcasts of development schemes.
They are acknowledged to have duties but seldom
recognized as having rights. Due recognition
should be accorded to the importance of their
social and economic role, and they should be
helped, by means of literacy teaching and training,
to find paid employment, so that Africa can at last
make progress towards "sustainable develop¬
ment with a human face", fl 41
/m
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
TASSOUM L. DOUAL
is a Chadian economist who is
currently preparing a doctoral
thesis on the socio-economic
changes and the situation of
women in Chad during the
civil war. Among her
publications in English is
"Chad: Civil War and
Development Prospects",
which appeared in Voices from
Africa, published by the United
Nations Non-Governmental
Liaison Service, Geneva, 1991.
Pumps of contention
CHAD is one country where women have to
contend with both water scarcity and inse¬
curity. The government, with the help of a few
financial backers, installed water pumps in two
northern regions, Guéra and Ouaddai, where
drought is endemic. Attitudes being what they
are, however, women were kept out of the man¬
agement side of things. During public meetings,
they maintained a disapproving silence or merely
acquiesced politely. In the village of Mangalmé,
they refused even to attend, saying they were
not involved in "your pump business". After
long discussions, they plucked up courage to
say even though the men were present that it
was up to those to whom the pump belonged to
answer questions. It emerged from further dis¬
cussion that the management committee, com¬
posed entirely of men, had been giving preference
to water-sellers and herdsmen, obliging the
women to go on drawing the water for household
needs from the traditional wells. The wells were,
however, from five to fifteen kilometres away
from the village, and the women had to make the
long journey weighed down with heavy water-
jars attached to each end of a pole.
As for hygiene, we found out that in all the vil¬
lages where there were pumps the runoff channel
had been blocked to make a drinking-trough.
The livestock drank stagnant water from it, or
even out of the recipients that were being filled.
When asked if their health had improved since
they had drinking water, many of the women
sarcastically replied that they were not doctors so
they couldn't tell.
In another village, the men told us how satis¬
fied they were. "Look," they said, "our women¬
folk have grown bigger and more beautiful since
the pump was installed. It's great to see them
getting some rest. Let's hope it continues that
way, because it seems the pumps often break
down in other places." As regards these break¬
downs, Mariam, a fifty-year-old woman, told
us: "We have a great deal to put up with. It's
really very hard to have to go ten to fifteen kilo¬
metres to fetch water. Night-time is for sleeping
but we have to go and fetch water. Our daughters
don't even have time to grow because we trail
them around with us to teach them to put up with
suffering. Thanks anyway for the pump, but if
you really want to help us, show us how to repair
it, then we'll be able to get it going again ourselves
instead of having to go and look for a repairman
forty-five kilometres away, often only to find
he's left for the town. All the repairmen we've had
left sooner or later. There's no work here, you
know, so all the men leave." No expert could
have put women's needs more clearly.
Water-supply schemes should help encourage
the rural population to become self-sufficient in
food production and slow down the drift to the
towns. The installation of pumps in the villages
has not, however, given a boost to fruit and
vegetable growing and has not created new
sources of income. The reason is that this aspect
of the matter was not taken into consideration
Queuing for water in
the Sudan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
by the people behind the schemes; raising aware¬
ness and getting the local population to partic¬
ipate especially women, who after all are the
main intended beneficiaries are not high
among their priorities. Yet as long as women
continue to be left out of economic and social
development, it will be difficult to achieve any
progress in the villages. _
Miracle algae
BARKADROUSSO is a little country town in the
Kanem region of west central Chad. Its pop¬
ulation is about 800, mostly women. The Kanem
region used to be good cattle country, but drought
has decimated the herds and made life very diffi¬
cult. All the able-bodied men have gone, leaving
behind the women, children and the elderly.
Achta is one of these women. Aged about forty,
she lives alone with her six children. Seven years
ago her husband left to work in Libya, like so
many other men. It is five years since he last
came back. "God be with him," she murmurs,
"we're still alive, thanks be to God and the dihé."
The dihé is the only form of wealth that the
women of Barkadrousso possess. It is a blue alga,
invisible to the naked eye, that grows in profusion
in the natron-rich ponds of certain wadis. Very
high in protein content 15 grams are the equiv¬
alent of 100 grams of meat in mineral salts and
vitamins, it is the staple food of the local popula¬
tion, cooked as a thick soup or made into a sauce.
On the day of the harvest, a hundred or so
women gather around the pond with their con¬
tainers. Many have their daughters with them.
When the signal is given, they collect as much dihé
as they can. Half of them have come more than fifty
kilometres to Barkadrousso for the purpose.
At one time, most of the streams in the Kanem
produced dihé, which the women sold, dried, at
the market in Mao, seventy kilometres away.
With the proceeds they bought tea, sugar and
clothes. Nowadays the market traders gather the
algae themselves. Achta says: "All the wadis
around here have dried up. Ours is the only one
left. God has been good to us. I don't hear from
my husband any more. A lot of women are in the
same situation. I'm old, but look at those two over
there. They only have two children each and
their husbands have been gone five years. It's a
good job we have dihé, otherwise what would
become of USÍ
For these women, the blue algae have taken
the place of husbands, parents and livestock.
They provide their only source of income; they
are mother's milk to their children. "Our children
are not thin, thanks to the dihé, but look at the
next village!" It is true that the children in
Barkadrousso show no signs of malnutrition,
unlike those in the neighbouring villages.
A plan drawn up by the Chadian authori¬
ties, and warmly welcomed by the womenfolk,
aimed to replenish the dried-up wadis and pro¬
duce algae to feed the local population. Three
nongovernmental organizations from the devel¬
oped countries were ready to provide funding for
the project, but owing to the almost permanent
insecurity that reigns in the region, it has yet to be
implemented. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
For 30 years
UNESCO has
played a
leading part
in the
development
)f international
lydrology
44
ANDRAS SZOLLOSI-NAGY
is the Secretary of the
International Hydrological
Programme and the Director
of the Division of Water
Sciences of Unesco.
The role of Unesco
by Andras Szollosi-Nagy
CIVILIZATIONS have always been strongly
dependent on water. By now it should be
clear to everyone that the converse is also
true: vital water resources depend upon civiliza¬
tion or more precisely the "civilized" use of a
finite and vulnerable resource. This two-way
feedback underlines the strong need for co-oper¬
ation. Well co-ordinated international collabo¬
ration is essential if we are to understand the
processes occurring in the water cycle, to assess
surface and groundwater resources, and to adopt
an attitude that maintains the quality and quan¬
tity of water resources for generations to come.
Recognition of these needs led to the launching
by UNESCO of the International Hydrological
Decade (IHD) in 1964, the first truly international
scientific and educational effort in hydrology
ever made.
One result of IHD was that hydrological
maps containing hitherto unavailable baseline
information were drawn up, particularly for
water-short developing countries in Africa, the
Arab States, Latin America and Asia. This work
was made possible through the establishment of
internationally accepted mapping techniques.
IHD also developed regional water balances
which later served as basic references for cali¬
brating global-scale models. Hundreds of hydrol¬
ogists from all over the world took part in this
painstaking work. Techniques for assessing the
environmental impacts of water projects were
also developed.
One of the most important results of IHD
was the setting up of training courses for post¬
graduates and technicians in hydrology and water
resources. Every year some 500 participants, the
overwhelming majority of whom come from
developing countries, complete courses designed
and taught under UNESCO's auspices.
But there was still much to be done, particu¬
larly in the application of scientific progress to the
solution of practical problems. It was recognized
that economic and social activities tend to aggra
vate difficulties arising from natural fluctuations
in the hydrological regime, and that human
impact on water resources increases with the
spread of urbanization and population growth. In
1974, UNESCO therefore decided to launch a
long-term International Hydrological Programme
(IHP) with the aim of finding solutions to the
problems of countries with different geographical
and climatic conditions and at different levels of
technological and economic development. The
Programme is founded upon a network of
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
National Committees (some 141 to date) and also
on a strong partnership with the non-govern¬
mental scientific organizations. Over the years
very close co-operation has been developed with
the World Meteorological Organization.
In the early years of the IHP (1975-1980),
studies were carried out on hydrological para¬
meters for water projects, hydrological aspects of
droughts, changes in the hydrological regime
due to human activities, hydrological problems
related to energy development, the dispersion
of pollutants in aquatic media, socio-economic
aspects of urban hydrology, aquifer contamina¬
tion and protection, and land subsidence due to
groundwater abstraction.
A later phase of the IHP, which ran from
1984 to 1989, improved scientific knowledge of
hydrological processes and parameters for water
projects and led to a better understanding of
human influence on the hydrological cycle,
including the environmental impact of water
projects. The development of education and
training, public information and scientific infor¬
mation systems gained new momentum.
Recognition of the dangers of a possible cli¬
mate change on the distribution of water
resources in space and time as well as the need for
sustainable development set the theme for the
current phase of the IHP (1990-1995).
One of the least understood aspects of global
change is the land phase of the hydrological
cycle. In order to understand this phase, studies
of the processes whereby water is transported
through the atmosphere-vegetation-soil system
must be carried out on different scales. Together
with the International Geosphere-Biosphere
Programme, the IHP is currently trying to solve
this problem.
We must come to appreciate more fully that
our rapidly changing and increasingly vulner¬
able environment will only be protected if it is the
focus of outstanding legal, organizational and
scientific efforts. Without doubt, the need for
hydrological science as a base for integrated water
management will increase in importance. The
International Hydrological Programme is seeking
to satisfy this need, with the over-riding goal of
helping nations to help themselves.
The strips in this screen
serve to trap moisture
from clouds and mist. The
technique, developed in
the Andes, is now also
used in India and the Gulf
region.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
UNESCO AND THE FIGHT
AGAINST AIDS
Ten years after the discovery of the HIV
virus by his research team at the
Pasteur Institute in Paris, Professor Luc
Montagnier has created a World
Foundation for Aids Research and
Prevention, under the auspices of
Unesco. The Foundation is seeking to
mobilize private initiatives against a
scourge which has taken on tragic
dimensions, especially in the developing
world. Its first objective is to help
establish pilot centres where people
who are HIV positive can be given
laboratory examinations and clinical
tests that could rapidly evaluate the
effectiveness of new drugs. The
Foundation, which has received support
from several non-governmental
organizations, scientists and religious
authorities of different faiths, is also
planning to carry out social work,
initially by providing education for
Ugandan orphans whose parents have
died of Aids.
SUPPORT FOR MAURITANIA»!
WOMEN'S PROJECT
The Arab Gulf Programme for United
Nations Development Organizations
(AGFUND) has offered to support a
Unesco project to create a Women's
Handicraft and Development Centre at
Oualata, a village in the Mauritanian
desert. Women in the village, which has
a population of a thousand, face a hard
struggle to make a living since most of
their menfolk are migrant workers in
the capital city of Nouakchott and have
left them to cope as best they can. The
women have already formed a co¬
operative, but would like to increase
production, improve the quality of their
traditional handicrafts, and raise farm
animals. The aim of the project is to
restore a village building to house the
Women's Centre, where literacy classes
can be held and women can receive
training in improved techniques for
working with matting, skins and carpets.
LITERATURE WRIT LARGE
"Humour is inseparable from
humankind and, like it, is universal and
changing, individual and social". So
reads the preface to Cuentos divertidos
("Amusing Tales"), a collection of ten
humorous stories recently published by
Unesco and the Madrid publishing house
Editorial Popular. The collection
inaugurates Unesco's Large Print series
(Letra Grande in Spanish) of extracts
from works by some of the greatest
names in Iberian and Latin American
literature. The large-print format aims to
meet the needs of the newly literate and
people who have difficulty in reading.
Seven other books, including a second
collection of stories, Cuentos andinos
("Andean Stories"), will be published in
the series before the end of the year.
The books are on sale at the Unesco
Bookstore, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris; or can be ordered from Unesco
Publishing: Tel. (33 I) 45 68 49 73;
fax. (33 1)42 73 30 07.
A NEW HYDROLOGICAL GLOSSARY
A second (revised) edition of the
International Glossary of Hydrology has
been published jointly by Unesco and
the World Meteorological
Organization. It provides definitions and
translations of 1,800 terms in English,
French, Spanish and Russian, with an
alphabetical index in the four languages
and the universal decimal classification
for hydrology. The new edition, on
which an international group of
hydrologists has been working since
1 984, is an attempt to standardize the
vocabulary used by hydrologists and
research institutions in order to
facilitate exchanges of information and
international co-operation. The
glossary is available from scientific
bookstores or by mail order from
Unesco Publishing, Sales Division, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75382 Paris 07 SP,
France. The price of 200 French francs
includes postage by surface mail.
THE HISTORY OF CLIMATE CHANGE
REVEALED BY ARCHIVES
To understand and predict climatic
changes it is useful to have an idea of
what the climate was like hundreds if
not thousands of years ago. With this in
mind, a pilot project was launched in
1 990 by Unesco, the World
Meteorological Organization (WMO),
the International Council of Scientific
Unions (ICSU) and the International
Council on Archives in order to collect
historical climate data from archives.
Archival data can help to provide a
broader picture of the past climate than
the spot measurements provided by
other methods such as study of tree-
rings or air bubbles trapped in glaciers.
Reports in the local press, municipal
and church records, private documents
and estate registers provide a mine of
information about meteorological
conditions, unusual occurrences and
crop yields. Research has already been
carried out in six European archives to
identify documents containing climatic
data for the period 1 725 to 1 775.
This article is one ofa
series in which the
Director-General of
Unesco sets out his
thinking on matters of
current concern
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Towards education
for all
NEXT November, the Heads of State or Government of
nine large countries will meet in New Delhi in India
to give a new impetus to their efforts to achieve edu¬
cation for all. There is an obvious and powerful logic in this
initiative. The nine countries Bangladesh, Brazil, China,
Egypt, India, Indonesia, Mexico, Nigeria and Pakistan
collectively account for nearly three-quarters of the world's
adult illiterates and a sizeable share of the world's out-of-
school children. Thus there can be no significant overall
progress in education unless there is progress in these coun¬
tries. They are, so to speak, the key to the solution of the prob¬
lems of illiteracy and lack of education. If Education for All
progresses in these countries, it progresses for the world as
a whole. If it lags in these nations, or even in certain of them,
world statistics will reflect this failure. These countries, there¬
fore, have a special responsibility to the world community
a responsibility, I should add, of which their governments and
peoples are keenly aware.
These nine nations are facing enormous challenges which
are linked among other things to their size, cultural diversity
and disparities in wealth. But they are, at the same time,
nations with vast potential, nations which excel in countless
areas, traditional and technological alike. Not only do they
have problems; they have, in differing degrees, the means to
cope with them. They are thus seen by their neighbours not
only as examples, but also as nations which are capable of
extending a helping hand, and in many cases they are already
doing so. They are fully capable of serving as regional and
world laboratories and resources in the quest to bring edu¬
cation to all the world's citizens. The dynamism and the
weight of the expertise they possess, not just their sheer size,
give high promise and potential to this initiative.
Several of these countries are the cradles of great civiliza¬
tions. They invented writing systems and used them to record
many of the most momentous and meaningful chapters in the
human adventure. Their progress is thus of the highest sym¬
bolic value. At a moment when our faith in the human voca¬
tion is being sorely tried, when our optimism is daily challenged
by the follies and tragedies that beset us, how splendid it
would be to see these nations where civilization was born
lead the world into a new era of hope and enlightenment.
A UNIVERSAL
MOVEMENT
UNESCO attaches the highest importance to the initiative of
these large countries and will lend it all possible support. But
the Education for All movement is not limited to any one
group of countries. It is a worldwide undertaking in which
all nations, the richest as well as the poorest, have a right and
duty to participate. At the World Conference on Education
for All, held at Jomtien (Thailand) in March 1990, the devel¬
oping countries pledged to concentrate and accelerate their
efforts to achieve this goal, while the industrialized countries
undertook to lend considerably increased support to such
efforts. Initially, it was the sponsoring agencies UNICEF,
the United Nations Development Programme, the World
Bank and UNESCO that mobilized themselves and made
education for all their priority. But there is now clear evidence
that bilateral agencies are joining actively in this initiative and
providing new resources. Thus it is with great pleasure and
satisfaction that I can report to you that the alliance forged in
Jomtien three years ago has become a worldwide movement
in which a growing number of countries and organizations
are actively engaged.
This progress must, of course, be taken as an incentive and
not as a reason for complacency. In an age of slogans, it is
important to remind ourselves constantly that "education for
all" is a message with a real and urgent meaning and a goal that
is within our reach, if we firmly resolve to achieve it. But let
there be no doubt that the outcome is still very much in
question. Nothing will be more decisive in determining it than
the progress made in these nine large countries. If they suc¬
ceed in transforming education for all from a slogan to a
reality, I am certain that rapid progress will follow elsewhere
and that the world will enter the twenty-first century prepared
for a new age of enlightenment. 4J
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
RECENT
RECORDS
48
TRADITIONAL
MUSIC
MEXICAN INDIAN
TRADITIONS
Celebrations: 500th
Anniverary of the Encounter
between Two Worlds
Unesco Collection, Audivis
CD D 8304
This live recording, made in
France at the 1992 Avignon
Festival, features the rarely-heard
music of the Totonac, Zapotee,
Seri, Mayo and Tepehuan
peoples of Mexico, whose
histories are recalled in several of
the songs. Accompanied by
rattles, handclaps and other
percussive effects, these are often
monodic and have a fixed,
almost unvaried rhythmic
pattern. Some pieces featuring
horns recall the sound of brass
bands, though with a touch of
fantasy for some notes are
untempered. The dance of the
Negritos from Veracruz, probably
inspired by Mexico's black
population who live principally
in the Veracruz and Guerrero
regions but have a relatively low
profile in Mexican folklore and
ethnology, is particularly
rhythmic; violin and guitar come
together to suggest American
country or Tex-Mex music. The
groups featuring cowbells, fifes
and hand-drums, on the other
hand, recall traditional Provençal
music.
SULLY CALLY. Dornyé
Traditional music of
Martinique. The Roots People,
vol. I
Paroles de Tambours CD
SC92
Sully Cally, a percussionist,
actor and musicologist from
Martinique, recently published a
book packed with information
about his country's traditional
music. On this compact disc,
essential listening to go with the
book, Cally plays a damyé drum
with ti-bwas [petits bois or "little
wood") which are struck on the
side of the drum to create an
additional rhythm. He is
accompanied by several singers
and the bel-air (bêlé in Creole)
drum-playing of José Couf. The
bel-air musical tradition of
Martinique and that of gwo-ka in
Guadeloupe resemble Haitian
music with its strong African
influence. Although it is today
enjoying a come-back in the
Caribbean, it is still less well-
known elsewhere than the more
Europeanized and sometimes
insipid beguine. Buy this record
to hear marvellous Creole songs
and powerful rhythms that have
lost none of their earthy
authenticity.
CLASSICAL
PAGANINI. 24 Caprices
Patrick Gallois (flute)
Deutsche Grammophon
CD 435 768-2
This recording of Paganini's
Caprices transcribed for the flute
by the young French flautist
Patrick Gallois is a tour deforce.
Gallois, with his birdlike tone,
has virtuosity, pitch, energy all
the qualities necessary to
interpret these difficult pieces,
with their abrupt chromatic
leaps. On some tracks he sings
into his flute as he plays, a
technique that is used by jazz
musicians like Yusef Lateef but is
much less common in classical
music. Gallois writes in the
sleeve-notes that "Performing
Paganini's Caprices taught me to
transcend the flute	 Flautists
should 'forget' the flute, they
should be forced to abandon the
beaten track." One can only
imagine the effort it cost him to
achieve so transparent a tone, as
though we were listening directly
to his breathing, with no
instrument interposed.
MOZART. The Last Three
Symphonies: 39, 40 and 41
("Jupiter") .
The Chamber Orchestra of
Europe, conducted by
Nikolaus Harnoncourt
CD Teldec 903 1-74858-2
Recorded live in Vienna on 5
December 1991, the 200th
anniversary of Mozart's death,
this is a magisterial performance
of Mozart's last three
symphonies, all written in a six-
week period of 1788 during the
composer's stay in the city.
Harnoncourt, a 'cellist turned
conductor, brings out all their
elegance and musicality. The
phrasing is perfect, and the
melodic flow is as ample as one
could wish. This is a classic
recording any collector would
treasure as a standard by which
to judge others.
BACH. Tocaten und Fugen BWV
538, 566, Praeludium und Fuge
BWV 535, Orge/büch/em BWV
618-632
Marie-Claire Alain (organ)
Erato CD 2292-4570 1 -2
Marie-Claire Alain here plays
Bach on an organ built by
Gottfried Silbermann in 1714 for
the Cathedral of Freiberg. The
notes are unevenly tempered, as
would have been the case in
Bach's day, and according to
Alain the sound of the organ
dictated the choice of material.
The music unfurls vibrantly and
takes majestic flight, imbued
with intense emotion. Few
composers have communicated
religious passion so well and with
such musical rigour.
JAZZ
MONK
Thelonious Monk (piano),
Charlie Rouse (tenor sax), L.
Gales or Butcha Warren
(bass), Frankie Dunlop (drums)
Columbia CD 468407-2
Another Monk masterpiece
reissued by Sony Music in its Jazz
Originals collection, this CD
features such standards as "April
in Paris" and "I Love You",
recreated from scratch by the
pianist as solo setpieces, as well
as some lesser-known original
compositions including "Teo"
and "Children's Song". Monk
devises extraordinary harmonic
progressions on "Liza", while his
original way of stressing notes is
in evidence on "Children's Song",
"Just You and Me" and "Teo". He
is well served by the backing
group and especially by Charlie
Rouse, whose sound here is
particularly velvety.
DONALD BYRD. A City Called
Heaven
Donald Byrd (trumpet,
flugelhorn), Joe Henderson
(tenor sax), Bobby Hutcherson
(vibes), Donald Brown (piano),
Rufus Reld (bass), Carl Allen
(drums), Lorice Stevens
(vocals)
Landmark LCD 1530-2
This fine CD by Doctor
Donaldson Toussaint
L'Ouverture Byrd (to give him his
full name) was recorded in July
1991 with a group of high-quality
backing musicians. "King
Arthur", in march time, recalls Art
Blakey's "Blues March". Byrd uses
a mute for the thoughtful "I'll
Always Remember". Lorice
Stevens sounds a little like Abbey
Lincoln in "A City Called
Heaven" a traditional air Byrd
handles modally while there is
a positively Elizabethan quality
to her singing on "Remember
Me", inspired by Purcell's Dido
and Aeneas. Bobby Hutcherson's
poignant "Del Valle", played as a
waltz, contrasts with the more
complex and abstract "Not
Necessarily the Blues".
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
* INTERVIEW * CHARLES MALAHOUD talks te Tony Lévy ..» FMN pme .,
referred to earlier, which are one of the aspects
of brahman, involves linking similar elements
from the different levels of existence. There
are not just two of these, but more often
three: the level of the gods, which is that of the
cosmos; the level of the individual human
being (body and soul); and, between the two
of them, the ritual level. A ritual object, a
particular moment in a ceremony, is thought
to have a replica or counterpart in some spe¬
cific spatial or temporal element of the uni¬
verse, and also in some aspect of human
activity or an organ of the human body.
This network of correspondences is not
static. The Vedic authors, particularly in the
Upanishads, give much thought to finding
new, more refined and complex equivalences.
Several Sanskrit words convey this idea,
words that mean "connection", "link", even
"kinship". In Vedic India the idea of corre¬
spondences is more important than the con¬
cept of causality whereas Buddhism insists
on the sequence of cause and effect. Louis
Renou admirably clarified the difference
between Vedism and Buddhism on this point
in one of the articles collected in his book
L'Inde fondamentale, which came out in.
1978.
What differentiates Hinduism from the
Vedic religion?
We've already noted the differences with
relation to the nature and status of the holy
writings. If we turn to religious beliefs and
practices, and first and foremost to the pan¬
theon of gods, we find that some Vedic gods
survive into Hinduism, though in a weaker
and more obscure form, while others disap¬
pear completely. On the other hand, gods
that play only a secondary role in the Veda
move to centre-stage. Vishnu and Shiva are
the principal Hindu gods, co-existent and
venerated by all believers. But Hindus divide
into "sects" devoted to different aspects of
Vishnu or Shiva, for another important char¬
acteristic of Hinduism is that there are an
infinite number of divinities, but each is a
special manifestation of one of the principal
gods.
This is where the doctrine of avatars
comes in. At different times, depending on the
cosmic problems he had undertaken to
resolve, the god Vishnu made himself mani¬
fest by "descending" to Earth in various
guises, while always remaining himself. Each
of the personalities he adopted, and there are
canonical lists of these, has a mythology built
around it and is the object of a specific cult.
Rama and Krishna, for example, who are
both gods and heroes, are among the avatars
of Vishnu. It is extraordinary that these
avatars, destined to intervene in cosmic eras
earlier than our own, are still the object of fer¬
vent devotion today. I would also point out
that the theory of cosmic cycles, and the divi¬
sion of each cycle into a similar number of
successive eras separated from one another by
catastrophes, is also a Hindu innovation.
Unlike the Vedic gods, who are primarily
receivers of offerings, the Hindu gods are
seen as beings with whom humans can have
an intense emotional relationship. One of
the most remarkable aspects of Hinduism is
the appearance, in about the sixth or seventh
century A.D., of the concept of bhakti, or
fusional devotion, according to which wor¬
shippers seek to be absorbed into and fused
with the divinity they adore. Unity with the
god is the expected outcome of the love they
bear and the grace they hope for.
The Hindu conception of divinity is both
the cause and the effect of forms of worship
that are unknown to the Veda. In Hinduism
gods are represented by images or, more
accurately, they are present, alive and active,
in the images that represent them. These
images are permanently housed in sanctu¬
aries or temples, clearly defined places where
they are the masters.
The gods are present in every image of
themselves, but this presence has different
degrees of completeness and intensity, so that
there is a kind of hierarchy among images.
Worship consists of treating the image as a
living person whom one can contemplate,
revere and care for, and whose goodwill one
hopes to win. In Hinduism devotion to the
image of a god in his sanctuary or temple
occupies the place that the sacrificial rite held
in Vedism. Not that Hinduism did away with
sacrifices entirely; it shifted them from the
centre of life and religious thought and gave
them a secondary role.
What is asked of the Hindu gods?
The things of this world, first and fore¬
most: health, prosperity, above all offspring.
Wisdom and all kinds of success. On a wider
scale, the gods are expected to provide good
harvests, the normal round of the seasons,
order in society and the world. But also per¬
sonal salvation in the after-life. And this raises
the question of what salvation is and what it
is that one needs to be saved from. The
answer is: from unpleasant forms of life after
death. People want to avoid hell and go to
heaven. Such a desire was already expressed
in Vedism. When Hinduism emerged, how¬
ever, a new concept was added, and that was
the famous doctrine of karma (or karman).
The idea is that people are caught up in an
endless stream of successive lives. Death is
simply the unending passage from one life to
the next. The type of existence a person enters
at the end of each life is determined by his or
her actions in previous lives. Which is to say
that we always have the life we deserve. If it
is pleasant, it is to allow us to enjoy the fruits
of meritorious acts accomplished in some
previous existence. If it is disagreeable, it is the
result of bad deeds committed in past lives.
One's karma or stock of acts is of course
constantly renewed, as long as one passes
through lives in which taking action of some
sort is unavoidable. But Indian Hindus see the
necessity of rebirth in a series of lives that are
always deserved, through the workings of
an autonomous mechanism, as a misfortune
or rather as a state of subjection from which
they seek release. Salvation in the context of
karma is not a matter of seeking to obtain a
happy life in a heavenly abode after death, for
such a destiny would itself inevitably be tem¬
porary. Real salvation lies in deliverance, the
possibility of reaching the end of this mech¬
anism and so concluding the process of
rebirth.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Tenth-century sculptures
at Chamba, Himachal
Pradesh state (India), show
the god Shiva and his
consort Parvati.
How can this be brought about?
It can only be achieved by individuals who
have exhausted their karma by various
methods that involve on the one hand a very
difficult process of mental awakening and
on the other various kinds of asceticism. As
to the condition of those who achieve deliv¬
erance and the attitude to be adopted towards
them, different schools have different views,
though none has very much to say on the
matter. In popular Hinduism, however, deliv¬
erance is thought to lead to eternal happi¬
ness, which is another blessing expected from
the gods, or more accurately from the god one
entrusts oneself to in bhakti.
In speaking of Hinduism I have concen¬
trated on what distinguishes it from Vedism,
and I have also stressed the great diversity of
beliefs, doctrines and forms of worship con¬
tained within it. But I should also point out
that from a different viewpoint what is
striking is the continuity of certain funda¬
mental principles that are always present.
These include the idea that there is an order
that englobes nature as well as society. The
division of society into "classes" is not a
human institution but a fact associated with
the structure of the cosmos. Since the indi¬
vidual soul subjected to the laws of karma
passes not only through human existences
but also those of animals and gods, one might
well ask if there is anything special about the
role humankind plays in the cosmos. In fact
it is distinguished from all the other life-forms
by the fact that only humans act in such a way
as to produce karma.
Buddhism is thought to have emerged
from Brahmanism around the fifth or sixth
century B. C. What are the links, and the dif¬
ferences, between Brahmanism and Bud¬
dhism?
It is by no means certain that Buddhism did
grow out of Brahmanism, nor that it should
be explained as a deviation or an innovation
in relation to a pre-cxisiting Brahmanic faith,
even though this is often said. It might be
more accurate to think that Buddhism is
rooted in the religious traditions of the eastern
part of the Ganges Valley, a region which
was perhaps not exclusively given over to
Brahmanism.
It is true nevertheless that the Buddhist
texts presuppose the existence of Brahmanic
society and religion and are in fact a critique
of certain Brahmanic concepts. But the fact
that the Brahmanic texts are in Sanskrit, while
the earliest Buddhist texts are in Pali, a Middle
Indo-Aryan language, is evidence of early
Buddhism's autonomy of Brahmanism.
The distinctive characteristic of early
Buddhism seems to be the belief that suf¬
fering is ever-present, and that it is linked to
the impermanent nature of things. One has to
become aware of suffering, recognize its
causes and discover the means of deliverance
from it. From that flows a sentiment of uni¬
versal compassion, and a critique of both the
Brahmanic rites and the pretentions of the
brahmans, the masters of ritual. Then again,
Buddhism is the creation of a human founder
who lived in a known time and place. The
story of his life, his ordeals, the way he was
"illuminated" by the truth, his efforts to build
up the community of his first disciples all
these events make up a story that is an essen¬
tial part of Buddhist doctrine.
Without forcing the comparison, what
wouldyou say about the similarities and dif¬
ferences between Vedism andHinduism and
the religions of the Book?
I wouldn't overemphasize the gap between
Indian polytheism and the monotheism of
the religions of the Book. There is a differ¬
ence, obviously, but stressing it tends to lead
to oversimplification. On the one hand one
could point to the divine plurality of Chris¬
tianity; on the other to the idea, so often
repeated by Hindus, that all their countless
gods are only aspects of a single God. What
seems more important to me is that for the
religions of the Book, human beings are rad¬
ically different from the rest of creation.
Humanity is destined to have a history, and
that history is oriented and punctuated by
successive moments of revelation. We've seen
that in Vedism and Hinduism humanity and
society cannot be said to have existed before
the event of revelation and that revelation
cannot even properly be described as an event.
In my view, the most significant difference
between the two groups of religions lies in
this relationship to time.
SO
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
ThelÏNESCO
flw^COURIER
46th YEAR
Published monthly In 32 languages and In Braille by Unesco, The
United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: Violette Ringelstein (Tel. 45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Prithi Perera
Selection In Braille in English, French, Spanish and Korean:
Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki ¡Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Ca'reras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: D'agomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Soph e Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donastia)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernandez (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
\gonekeo. Michel Ravassard. Mohamed Salah El Dm
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: ¡Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel : 45 .68 .45 .65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
o-der of Unesco
Indiviaual art ces and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Urjzsco Courier".
plus date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signée articles reprnted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors
and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Lnfsco or those of
the editors of the Unzsco Courier. Photo caotions and headlines are
written by the Unzsco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps
published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unzsco Courier is
p-oduced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: 11) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans: (2) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor. Mchigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition,
ludan head Inc., Ill West 40th Street. New York. U.S.A.; (4) Bell
and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - MAI 1993
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N1 71842 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P,
Photocomposition: Le Courrier de l'UNtsco.
Photogravure: ETIC GRAPHIC, Impression: IMAYE GRAPHIC,
2.1. des Touches, Bd Henri Becquerel, 53021 Laval Cedex (France)
ISSN 0304-3118 N- 5-19930PI-93-515Á
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between pages
1011 and 42-43.
Theme of the next issue
Qune 1993):
MINORITIES
Also featuring an interview with
the Italian writer and semiologist
Umberto Eco
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Cover, pages 3, 45: Steele-
Perkins © Magnum, Paris. Page
5: © Roland Michaud, Paris.
Pages 6, 7, 8, SO: © Monique
Pietri, Paris. Pages 10-11, 13,
14,32, 38: ©Charles Lenars,
Paris. Page 1 2: © Jean Loup
Charmet, Paris. Page 1 5: Mark
Edwards © Still Pictures, London.
Pages 1 6- 1 7: J. P. Barbier © Hoa
Qui, Paris. Page 1 8: All Rights
Reserved. Page 1 9: P. Le Floc'h
© Explorer, Paris. Pages 20-2 1 :
Hansen © Explorer, Paris. Page
21: UNESCO/Szöllösi-Nagy. Pages
22, 24 (above), 30 (below),
32-33: © Alain Guillou, Le
Croisic. Page 23: Zullo © Sipa,
Paris. Pages 24 (below), 25: Val
Josephs © Jude Burkhauser. Page
26 (above): Axel © Jacana, Paris.
Page 26 (below): © Marta O.
Prado. Page 27 (above):
Alexandra Boulât © Sipa, Paris.
Page 27 (below): Michel Viard
©Jacana, Paris. Page 29: Mark
Gamba © Sipa, Paris. Pages 30-
3 1 : Edward Igor © Sipa, Paris.
Pages 34-35: Jörgen Schytte ©
Still Pictures, London. Page 36:
Frederico Mendes © Sipa, Paris.
Page 37: A Stragesko © ANA,
Paris. Pages 40-41: © Mali, Paris.
Page 4 1 : © Tassoum L. Douai,
Paris. Pages 42-43: © Carlos
Fernández Járegui, Montevideo.
Pages 44-45: © Liba Taylor ©
ANA, Paris.
Organisation de séjours
linguistiques et culturels
en centres américains
44, avenue de la Libération
60530 DIEUDONNE
Tél. : (16)44.26.50.96
Fax : (16) 44.26.95.21
Pour les jeunes :
13-20 ans : IMMERSION en FAMILLE
avec jeune Américain du même âge.
( 1 0 villes aux USA) de 3 à 4 semaines en juillet :
8200 à 9800 F
10-15 ans : SUMMER CAMP au COLORADO
3 semaines : 12400 F
Nos prix comprennent : voyage, séjour, assurance.
Accompagnement des groupes par un professeur d'anglais.
Le nombre de participants par ville est limité à 20.
Professeurs : possibilité de former votre propre groupe.
Pour les adultes
1 8 ans et plus :
VANCOUVER [CANADA)
cours + accueil en famille
NASHVILLE (TENNESSEE)
cours + excursions + hôtel
ORCA est une Association loi 1901 agréée Tourisme et Jeunesse et Sports
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
EACH MONTH,
ESSENTIAL
READING FOR AN
UNDERSTANDING
OF THE
PROBLEMS OF
TODAY AND
TOMORROW
CH MONTH: PECIALISTSOFDIF
ART IN THE STREET . . . REDISCOVERING 1492 . . .
IN PRAISE OF TOLERANCE . . . UNIVERSALITY:
A EUROPEAN VISION? ... THE KNOWLEDGE
BEARERS . . . TELE-VISIONS ... THE CHALLENGE
OF DEMOCRACY ... THE COMPETITIVE WORLD OF
SPORT . . . EXPLORING THE COSMOS . . .
VIOLEN«... PSYCHOANALYSIS: THE HIDDEN I...
A TIME TO LOVE... WATER OF UFE
EW WITH Ar.
TURE, SCIENCE
FRANÇOIS MITTERRAND . . . JORGE AMADO . . .
RICHARD ATTEN60ROUGH . . . JEAN-CLAUDE
CARRIÈRE ... JEAN LACOUTURE . . . FEDERICO
MAYOR . . . NAGUIB MAHFOUZ . . . SEMBENE
OUSMANE . . . ANDREI VOZNESENSKY . . .
FRÉDÉRIC ROSSIF . . . HINNERK BRUHNS . . .
CAMILO JOSÉ «LA . . . VACLAV HAVEL . . . SERGEI
S. AVERINTSEV . . . ERNESTO SÁBATO . . .
GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND . . . CLAUDE
LÉVI-STRAUSS . . . LEOPOLDO ZEA . . . PAULO
FREIRÉ... DANIEL J. BOORSTIN... FRANCOIS
JACOB ... MANU WBANGO ... FAROUK HOSNY .. .
SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN . . . JORGE LAVELU . . .
LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG . . . TAHAR BEN JELLOUN
. . . GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ . . . JACQUES-YVES
COUSTEAU . . . MEUNA MERCOURI . . . CARLOS
FUENTES . . . JOSEPH KI-ZERBO . . . VANDANA
SHIVA . . . WILLIAM STYRON . . . OSCAR NIEMEYER
. . . NUKIS THEODORAKIS . . . ATAHUALPA
YUPANQUI . . . HERVÉ BOURGES . . . ABDEL
RAHMAN EL BACHA... SUSANA RINALDI .. .
HUBERT REEVES ... JOSÉ CARRERAS ... A LETTER
FROM FREUD TO EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY...
CHARLES MALAMOUD...
: REGULAR «fifi
r^cöuwm
]]>
</page>
</document>
