<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="095767eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ïiïînlïiiiïïï
DANIEL J. BOORSTI
THTTïïïïï
RÉGIS DEBRA
JOSEPH KI-ZER
FLORA L"
EDGAR HORI
JJ:VH:10: *Jl]
ALAIN TOURAI
J
TTTT
M
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Federico Mayor and the Abbé Pierre
call for a pact to combat poverty
To mark the "International Day for the Eradication
of Poverty", which was celebrated for the first time
at UNESCO's Paris Headquarters on 17 October 1993,
Mr. Federico Mayor, Director-General of Unesco,
and the Abbé Pierre, France's best-known defender
of the needy and homeless, launched a joint appeal.
The unabridged text of the appeal, which was read
out by the Abbé Pierre, is published below.
_ jprived people is spiralling upwards in all nations. How much poverty and
misery can freedom and democracy bear without seriously endangering world peace?
Destitution is a form ofviolence that knows no frontiers.
The International Day for the Eradication of Poverty proclaimed by the General Assembly
of the United Nations on behalf of the most deprived is above all an urgent appeal for sharing
and for intellectual, moral and material solidarity.
The anger that each of us feels when faced with victims of hunger, illness, ignorance and
violence is fully justified. It is a duty to refuse, with all our being, the unacceptable.
Poverty, in all its forms, imperils not only the poor, but also that which is human in those
who are better off.
That is why everyone, everywhere, should ruthlessly wage war on it.
Whether it be in the inner cities of the industrialized countries or in the rural areas of the
least or most advanced nations, whatever the priorities of states may be today, poverty
requires a general mobilization, not against others, but to save what is human in each of us.
The solemn appeal we are launching today comes from the heart as well as from the mind.
It is addressed to all of you here as well as to all the world's political, economic, social and
cultural decision-makers, and especially to the young, who have always felt an instinctive
revulsion against poverty.
We urge every organization at every level of society from families to sports clubs,
professional associations and community groups to make a firm, steadfast commitment.
A "civil pact" to fight against poverty and for human dignity must be concluded and put
into effect now.
No idea must be neglected, no amount of goodwill considered superfluous. Anger,
determination, imagination and audacity are needed to put an end to this tragedy.
If the "civil pact" is thus strengthened, it will triumph.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW WH
Michel Serres
40 UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
41 UNESCO IN ACTION
ARCHIVES
A defence of the
intellect
by Aldous Huxley
I International
Volunteer Day
by MJackson
46 UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
The painted caves of
Hogao
by ¡osé Serra-Vega
48 BOOKS OF THE WORLD
by Calum Wise
49 RECENT RECORDS
by Isabelle Leymarie
ents
BECEHBER 1993
IHE MEANING
OF PROGRESS
Editorial
PROGRESS TO WHAT?
A Western myth
by Régis Debray
\ Metaphors should be made at home
by Daniel J. Boorstin
1 5 Relative values
by Flora Lewis
NORTH-SOUTH:
BEYOND THE CREAT DIVIDE
1 8 The universal and the particular
by Joseph Ki-Zerbo
2 I One world
by Alain Touraine
1 1 The shadow of oppression
by Tariq Banuri
ISA shared crisis
by Edgar Morin
INTELLECTUALS: THE HISSING LINK?
Asking the right questions
by Dileep Padgaonkar
I Assuming responsibility
by André Brink
Cover:
Solaris universalis (1993), a collage by
the Quebec artist Alain Corrigou.
Greenwatch
41
COMHEHTARY
by Federico Nayor
TheljNK Trcf^(~\ "T^ Governments of the Sates parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
1 >J rVi^V_i-V_ * "t'lat s'nce wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
V"^T ITJir O "^at a Peace bistd exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
,V JV 1 1\ I r.l\ unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
Published monthly and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER 1945
46th year
in 32 languages and in Braille
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
MICHEL SERRES
talks to
François-Bernard Huyghe
Michel Serres of the Académie Française is an educator and
philosopher whose interests range from science and literature to
painting and environmental issues and whose self-proclaimed purpose
is to establish "the link between the sciences, law and religion". He
believes strongly that the philosopher should play a part in the life of
the community and is a member of Unesco's Ad hoc Forum of
Reflection, which is seeking to strengthen worldwide intellectual co¬
operation in identifying and responding to the new challenges facing
humanity. He is the author of some twenty books including Le Contrat
naturel (1990) and Le Tiers-Instruit (1991). His most recent works are
Eclaircissements (Editions François Bourin, Paris, 1992), a book of
conversations with Bruno Latour, and La Légende des Anges
(Flammarion, Paris, 1993).
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE
is a French writer and journalist.
One ofyour books is entitled Le con¬
trat naturel (The Natural Contract). Does
this mean man can make a contract with
Mother Nature?
Mother Nature does not appear in my
book. What I describe is a new shift, from
earth with a small "e", denoting earth as
one of the elements or the earth of farming,
to Earth with a capital "E", meaning the
planet, and hence a shift from a local per¬
ception to a global conception. We have
been witnessing the emergence of such a
global conception, from the technological,
human and scientific points of view, for
the past twenty years, which is why I
examine both meanings of the word
"earth" and hardly ever use the word
"Nature".
This idea of a new globality is perhaps
best symbolized by a photograph taken
from space, which arouses a feeling that just
about everyone who has seen it must have
shared. It shows the whole planet as seen
by a human eye. This new perception is an
event in the history of mankind. Owing to
this globalization of the way the Earth as
an object the planet is perceived, and by
a kind of recoil effect, the unity of
humanity is being gradually constructed.
Societies can only come into being if they
have an object in common; this object, the
globalized Earth, is new, and new bonds are
thus being established between humanity
and the planet.
The "natural contract" (which has
echoes of Rousseau's "social contract")
applies to this emerging bond. The idea of
standing in a legal relationship with the
entire planet was foreign to previous gen¬
erations, but just as human societies cannot
be conceived of without the social con¬
tract, the construction of the globality and
unity of the human race cannot be con¬
ceived of without the idea of a natural con¬
tract. The Enlightenment philosophers had
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
already worked out a concept of the human
Universal and natural law, but no-one
before our times could have imagined this
construction of the global. The natural
contract is thus not a metaphor to describe
our relationship with the Earth, but a full¬
blown philosophical concept.
Does it not relate back to to the dis¬
covery of laws the laws governing our
survival, for example?
No law, in the legal world itself or in the
philosophy of law, comes into being unless
it is preceded by a contract. Contracts are
a prerequisite for all laws. But the same
word is used to denote laws in the physical
sciences and the laws we humans enact,
and until now these two sets did not inter¬
sect. The natural contract establishes a rela¬
tionship between the exact and the human
sciences, between the two kinds of laws.
Do you know of a single philosopher
worthy of the name who has not at some
time been forced to think anew about sci¬
ence and the law, and about the relationship
between the two kinds of laws that govern
them? The whole problem of Western phi¬
losophy resides in this relationship or
linkage.
The philosopher's job is to describe
the conditions that have to be met in order
for laws to be made, not to describe the
content of those laws. It is to think about
the nature of the bonds on which duties are
grounded. In the case of the social con¬
tract, the bonds are between human beings
only, while physical laws relate exclusively
to links between objects. What is the rela¬
tionship between these two kinds of bond?
A link must be forged between
humanity, now in the process of becoming
one, and this new object, planet Earth.
This relationship, which entails new duties,
is what I call the natural contract. We can
discuss the duties when cases come to
court. We have already seen lawsuits
involving the users of a national park and
the park itselfwhich thus becomes a legal
entity possessing rights. As cases like these
are tried, and judicial precedents are set, the
duties involved will gradually be estab¬
lished. The law did not cover these areas. It
therefore has to be thought through, first
in philosophical terms, then in legal and,
lastly, political terms.
Should the Earth be viewed as a "sub¬
ject", an entitypossessing rights?
That is the main problem facing the
philosopher. How can an object become a
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
What steps can be taken against the development ofa universal culture
that only expresses a single force?
subject? All advances in law have consisted
of taking things that had been objects and
turning them into subjects. Slaves, who
were objects, became subjects before the
law, and the same is happening with chil¬
dren and embryos. Every time law makes
progress, it turns objects into subjects in
this way. The planet was an object and I am
suggesting it be made a subject. This inno¬
vation has met with a certain amount of
resistance, but in philosophy one must
learn to challenge generally accepted ideas
and be ready to accept that an issue has
taken on a new form.
Have atomic weapons helped the idea
ofglobality to emerge?
The shift from the local to the global
did indeed begin some time ago. The
atomic bomb has been what I have called
a "world object", in other words a tech¬
nological object one of whose dimensions
is world-wide in scale. It was one step on
the road from the local to the global. Today
we have the means to assess this relation¬
ship between the local and the global and
express it in equations. Climatological
models are another example.
Cross-fertilization is another ofyour
concepts.
Education today produces scientists
who, generally speaking, are ignorant out¬
side their own fields, and cultured people
who know nothing about science. Most
of today's problems stem from the separa
tion between these two groups. Both have
become decision-makers but they no
longer understand each other. The latter
enact human laws without bearing in mind
the existence of objects and of science,
while the former discover and apply nat¬
ural laws without taking human beings
into account. This is where I first used the
idea of cross-fertilization imagine, as
Plato did, a sociologist familiar with natural
science or a politician well versed in
physics. The idea of cross-fertilization
means first of all devising an education
system that does not separate the exact
sciences and the humanities in a foolish,
dangerous way.
It then occurred to me that cross-fertil¬
ization was the global concept underlying all
learning processes. If you start to learn
physics, your life and your world are going
to change. You become crossbred by the
very fact of learning. That's why I started my
book on education (Le Tiers-Instruit) with
a portrait, describing how I learned to write
with my right hand even though I was left-
handed. Left- or right-handed people will
always be physically and intellectually hémi¬
plégie half their body is paralysed. If you
know how to use both hands your body is
whole. The crossbreed I'm talking about is
this monster a human being who can
use his or her right and left hands at the
same time, reborn at the point where the
two sides meet.
We experience this a little when we
learn to speak another language. It is as if
a second person were entering us to beget
a third, by cross-fertilization. The hybrid
offspring is what I call the tiers-instruit, the
"educated third party".
Traditionally, culture is viewed as
something that makes an individual
"blossom ". Is there a relationship between
your own idea of culture and this long-
established metaphor?
I'm not really fond of the word "culture"
which, like "nature", is one of those words
that always cause aguments. But to con¬
tinue with the metaphor let's say that cross¬
breeding is similar to a graft. When some¬
thing is learned, a third person is produced
from the rootstock into which the scion is
inserted.
Are you advocating aform oflearning
that would go on making us forever
someone else, helping us each to become, in
our own way, the "educated thirdperson "
that we unknowingly carry around inside
us?
We must accept and acknowledge this
"someone else", who keeps company with
us and takes us to meet a second person.
The moment you acknowledge otherness,
learning has this modifying effect. It is not
a matter of developing a philosophy of the
Other. The Other is the second person.
We are talking about the educated third
person begotten by the encounter between
the self and the other.
There are thousands of books on
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
*
teaching that have never served any pur¬
pose other than to enable inspectors to
terrorize teachers. No amount of teacher
training can provide you with specific
details about the individual pupils in such-
and-such a class at such-and-such a time of
day, and so the more specific the textbook,
the more illusory it is.
As far as teaching is concerned, giving
practical instructions advising teachers
to get their pupils to read the newspapers,
for instance often amounts to giving
abstract instructions. The reality consists of
particular cases and particular types of
pupil. Generally speaking, educational
theory is middle-of-the-road, neither spe¬
cific nor abstract. It is much less useful
than it claims to be or is thought to be.
The issue I am interested in is, what are the
necessary conditions for learning?
You are a member ofa UNESCO Forum
which is concerned with getting to grips
with specifics and recommending solu¬
tions.
In Le contrat naturel I take note of
something that happened, perhaps, after
the founding of UNESCO: the construc¬
tion of a human unity that, for many rea¬
sons, objective reasons in particular, could
probably not have been foreseen in the
late 1940s. The specific advice I give the
Forum will take this rise of the global into
account.
We are currently witnessing an irre¬
sistibly growing trend towards the global.
Unfortunately this trend is increasingly
monopolized by the most powerful, whose
might is right. That which is universal is
warped when it is taken over by a single
power, and we are increasingly under the
sway of a single culture.
What specific steps can be taken against
the development of a universal culture that
only expresses a single force? That is the
question.
H The media have a tendency to look
uponphilosophers as oracles, asking them
for their ideas about how to save the world
and their views on all kinds of current
events. What do you feel about this?
It's true that the media ask philosophers
all sorts of questions on a host of topics. Per¬
sonally, I never answer such questions
because I don't think my ideas on all kinds
of topics are necessarily useful. I only
answer questions about topics dealt with in
my books or about things like the Forum
you mentioned. In all other cases I keep
out of the media because my mind is not all-
embracing. Furthermore, I never engage in
polemics. Polemics is the enemy of every
form of invention. Those who do not invent
have no right to be considered as intellec¬
tuals or philosophers. Polemics is an unmit¬
igated obstacle to the invention of concepts.
Philosophers are not "competent" in
the sense of being experts, but they have a
very specific task, which is to produce
ideas. I would rather produce in my field
and refuse to answer questions outside it.
I'd never write a book attacking another
book. On the contrary, if I see someone
come up with a new concept I'm as happy
about it as if I had thought it up myself. A
new concept is something very rare and
very fragile. It must be protected like a
newborn child. It will bear fruit later, per¬
haps in fifty years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
<
o
WITH the collapse of the Berlin Wall, the ideological polarization in which intel¬
lectual life had been mired during much of this century came to an end. Ideologies
are dead; they have been replaced by a globalism that brings with it new hopes
but also new dangers. More diffuse polarities are emerging and spreading along ethnic, reli¬
gious, racial and regional fault lines. Above all there is the great divide that tragically iso¬
lates the privileged inhabitants of the prosperous, powerful North from the rejected
masses of the South.
Intellectuals of every standpoint are well placed to join forces and reflect upon these
promises and dangers as long as they can find a minimum of common ground from which
to expose the delusions of nationalism on the one hand and the snares of totalitarianism
on the other. In short, as long as they speak a common language.
Earlier this year forty writers and artists from all over the world gathered at UNESCO
Headquarters in Paris to discuss these issues. The meeting was organized on the initiative
of the French journalist Jean Daniel, the French political theorist Régis Debray, UNESCO
Courier Director Bahgat Elnadi and Editor-in-Chief Adel Rifaat. It was sponsored by La
Repubhlica (Italy), O Estado de Säo Paulo (Brazil), The Los Angeles Times (United States),
Le Nouvel Observateur (France), El Pais (Spain) and the UNESCO Courier. The event was
envisaged as the first of a series of "Meetings of Intellectuals and Creators for a Single World"
which will take place annually to discuss a given topic free from all political and commercial
pressures. This year's theme was, "Can North and South share the same idea of progress?".
On the following pages we publish excerpts from some of the oral and written contri¬
butions to the meeting, which gave rise to a fruitful exchange of ideas not least on a fun¬
damental question of terminology, the meaning and implications of the ambivalent con¬
cept of progress.
Progress can be seen as a myth of industrial modernity, an emanation of the Judaeo-Chris¬
tian tradition which has since the Enlightenment been treated almost as though it were a
secular version of the concept of Providence. During the nineteenth century it spread in
the wake of Western expansion. In all cultures and in all parts of the world, progress could
be clearly measured in the fields of science and technology but had little or no meaning in
art, religion and politics. Those who believed it would bring about international peace, social
harmony, the end of religious superstitions and ethnic conflict, not to mention the stan¬
dardization of cultures, have continually seen their predictions come to nothing.
For forty years the myth of progress has survived in its modern version, development,
and has contributed to the establishment, under the rule of market forces, of a world eco¬
nomic system encompassing part of the peoples of the South, but excluding the vast
majority. It has also had destructive and possibly irreversible effects on the environment.
Perhaps the very perception of a North-South dichotomy is itself an offshoot of the myth
of modernity. The geographical and chronological divisions between North and South have
become blurred now that poverty and destitution have become part of the urban landscape
north of the equator, and in all countries, rich and poor, new classes are living like their coun¬
terparts in London, Paris and New York.
The French writer Julien Benda defined intellectuals as a group which should be con¬
cerned with universal issues. Their role in the face of today's chaotic, divisive realities should
be to free themselves from manichaean, reductionist thinking in order to identify the values
common to people everywhere.
Their task is not to promise a paradise on Earth, but to encourage respect for others and
for their beliefs. It is not to impose an ideal world, but to help exorcize what is worst in
the present one xenophobia, intolerance and exclusion.
NEDA EL KHAZEN
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Progress to what?
There is currently widespread disenchantment with the idea ofprogress,
especiaily perhaps in those societies in which it has been the motor of
economic growth and technological change.
Should it be scrapped as the dubious legacy of an outworn ideology,
or are there circumstances in which it is still valid?
Atóalo Soroboko avisoa en
pays Mahafaly
(1991-92), a painted
wooden funerary sculpture
(237 x 45 x 45 cm) by the
Madagascar! artist
Efiaimbelo.
A Western myth
by Régis Debray
ACCORDING to an old maxim, "Truth is one
and error manifold". Strictly from the point
of view of knowledge, it would be regret¬
table if North and South went their different
ways. Both of them would do better to try to
arrive at a correct and, therefore, shared under¬
standing of progress, the characteristic myth of
the early industrial age. Whether the idea of
"progress" is an elaborate figment of the imagi¬
nation or a conventional but illusory represen¬
tation of reality, it is eminently emblematic of
what used to be called "ideology".
The illusion comes from confusing two time-
schemes, the cumulative time of "scientific and
technological development", which is linear and
marked by constant innovation, and repetitive
time, which belongs to the world of politics and
symbols. In the former time-scheme, ever more
efficient solutions are found to quantifiable prob¬
lems. In the latter, each generation discovers, and
immediately forgets, that certain problems will
never be solved.
Human groups have often adopted a less flex¬
ible language or a cruder religion, or exchanged
democracy for dictatorship, but they have never
been known to go back from the plough to the
hoe, from wheels to sticks, or from aircraft to hot-
air balloons. Just as living things do not regress
(genetic combinations become progressively
more and more complex), so, in the medium and
long term, technology does not go into reverse.
Objects tend towards perfection, and tools and
skills are continually being improved under their
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Portrait of a woman at her
toilet
(oil on canvas,
c. 1512-1515) by the
Venetian master Titian.
own momentum. This trend can be found
throughout history and all over the world, inde¬
pendent of ethnic factors. The relationship
between people and things is governed by a pre¬
dictable, though open-ended and non-program¬
mable, logic of progress.
Relationships between human beings clearly
obey other laws. The difference between "savage"
and "civilized" peoples has some discernible
meaning in the history of technology, but is
meaningless in the history of art, religions, lan¬
guages or forms of authority. Our command of
energy sources has increased a thousandfold since
the beginning of our era, but Martin Luther King
is not a thousand times greater a moral authority
than Jesus Christ. The computer represents an
advance on the abacus, but Andy Warhol is not
superior to Titian, nor is Husserl's philosophy
more "profound" than Plato's. The notion of
progress is without meaning in the symbolic,
intellectual, emotional or psychological realms. It
would be easy to show that it is equally mean¬
ingless in the realm of politics the wars of the
twentieth century have been more brutal and
bloody than those of the nineteenth, which were
already much deadlier than those of the eigh¬
teenth, and so on. In relation to the technological
and scientific ways and means of dealing with
objects or of human beings as objects, in the
field of medicine there is an objective and ver-
10
ifiable "before" and "after". In the forms of man's
domination over man, the only "before and after"
is purely subjective, and reversible.
Standard technology,
specific cultures
The noble advocates of progress who for two
centuries have lumped together technological
and political time, have been systematically
wrong in their forecasts. They predicted not
only that the railways would bring about world
peace and that electricity would lead to social
harmony and public education to the end of
religious superstitions, but also that the stan¬
dardization of technical objects would result in
that of cultures and religions. The emergence of
a human mega-race or, more accurately, the
superseding of the ethnically-based structuring
of human communities, was supposed to go
hand-in-hand with the emergence of the pro¬
ductive mega-system, or globalized industrial
production system. However, far from dis¬
solving in a converging, globalized, fast-
changing technological environment, ethnic
environments, territorially based and slow to
change, are turning inward, becoming more
intransigent, and proliferating. The globalization
trend is towards balkanization, each stage in
the movement towards technological and eco¬
nomic unity reactivating ethnic and cultural
diversity at a new level. The increasingly easy
flow of goods and information is paralleled by
an obsessive territorial neurosis. In a village that
is increasingly global and chauvinistic, feverish
migratory movements have as their counter¬
part a crisis-level siege mentality.
It is thus easy to imagine a principle of con¬
stancy at work in society, similar to the prin¬
ciple of stability posited for the psyche by
Freudian metapsychology, a constant relationship
between the factors of so-called progress and so-
called regression. The history of humanity is
recorded in a double-entry ledger. Each imbalance
brought about by a technological advance causes
an "ethnic" rebalancing, so that the present see¬
sawing between the trend towards world-wide
uniformity and demands for the right to be dif¬
ferent, between the "rational" and the "national",
between the economic imperative and religious
needs this whole dynamic of disequilibrium
could be interpreted as a zero-sum game, or
rather as an equation with variable but corre¬
lated values. This is pure speculation, of course.
In any case, let us admire the infinite superi¬
ority of the wisdom of Greek mythology over
our present-day economic myths. In the myth of
Protagoras, Zeus grants technical skills, or techne,
to the human race through Prometheus but is glad
to have kept the "art of administering public
life", or wisdom, to himself, out of man's reach.
The Enlightenment philosophers forgot this little
reservation.
The verifiable fact of scientific and techno¬
logical progress became a myth by being improp¬
erly transposed to the symbolic and political
realms, a transposition stemming from the late
encounter between religious messianism and
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
-*^^
industrial machinism, between a Judaeo-Chris¬
tian cultural tradition (progress as a secularized
form of Providence) and the initial industrial and
economic take-off of European societies. Out
of the chemical reaction between them came a
precipitate that settled out in France and England
at the end of the Age of Enlightenment, philo¬
sophically linked with the names of Turgot, Con-
dorcet and Comte. The nineteenth century saw
the new religion spread throughout the world, in
step with Western expansion, which of course was
at the same time military, political, economic and
mythological.
The end of an ideology
The metaphysicians of progress believed the indi¬
visibility of humanity to be the only subject of his¬
tory. For Condorcct the human spirit and for
Comte the human race are one, and the oneness of
all history proceeds from this world-wide homo¬
geneity. In north and south, east and west,
humanity marches in the same direction, and mere
Four Marilyns, a 1 962 work
by the American pop artist
Andy Warhol.
variations in speed are not enough to change that
direction or the order of events. In this view of the
world, the continents may not be in the same
time zone, but they all have the same watch and the
same calendar. The East must necessarily make up
lost time and join the West on its march a pos¬
tulate common to both market economists and
Marxists. The ideologies of progress therefore
predate ethnography, anthropology, positivism
and, a fortiori, the eulogizing of differences.
The choice between tradition and progress,
the closed and the open, may be a retrograde
legacy of nineteenth-century Europe. It is perhaps
because they cultivate their originality and his¬
torically exceptional character that the Japanese
so successfully absorb outside influences. At the
Seville Expo 92, the most efficiently performing
country on Earth was represented not by video
gadgetry but by a wooden Shinto temple. The
super-modern East is forging ahead of the modern
West because, in its symbolic structures, it has
already reached the stage of pine, while we are still
at that of fibrocement.
Nothing could be more pointless than, for
example, the rhetorical antithesis between "nation¬
alism" and "cosmopolitanism". It has been the
global tribes, formidably rooted in their indigenous
^identities and at the same time networking all
over the planet the Arabs of the Middle Ages, the
Jews of the Renaissance and the Enlightenment
and the British of the Industrial Revolution
who have always moved civilization forward.
Globally positive
The myth of progress continues to operate, in a
latent or residual way in the North, in a driving
and propulsive manner in the South. An idea
that has been to a greater or lesser extent mythol-
ogized but is accepted by all becomes an objec¬
tive social reality, to be treated as such, especially
since, in the Third World in particular, it still
plays a "globally positive" role. Just as contempt
for money is a privilege of the rich, scepticism
with regard to progress is the prerogative of those
who have historically benefitted from it. Political
redemption through technological progress is a
false idea that the poor and oppressed truly need
to cling to in order to face up to modernity and
its gruesome spectacle of injustices without
sinking into despair or delinquency.
The problem is that the. affluent West no
longer really believes in its ideals and myths of
redemption. After the collapse of socialism, we in
the North no longer look forward to a future
where a clean break with the past can improve our
lot. What we see ahead are not radical changes to
be carried out but improvements to be made
within the framework of the rational, democ¬
ratic state. This is called "managing". The hope
principle is defunct at its home base. Can it,
should it be extinguished worldwide?
Its extinction would put a cheap price on
human suffering. Doubling average life
expectancy in the span of a century, wiping out
diseases, lowering illiteracy rates and boosting
potential per capita energy consumption are ele¬
vating, worthy tasks that, though they do not I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Way Ahead, a photo by
Eddie Sethna
hold the key to long-term human happiness or
usher in the classless society, at least have the
enormous merit of narrowing the gap between
the two hemispheres.
In the short run, it is clear that North and
South are instinctively nursing two opposing
attitudes towards History and hence towards
progress. Orphaned by the present, the "South",
unable to take refuge in a past that only evokes
worse conditions, turns its eyes towards the
future, which is identified with a better life.
Orphaned by the future, the North has refo-
cused on its present, which it no longer sees by the
light of Utopia but by that of the past, glorifying
memory above all other civic virtues. Europe is
passionately building up its archives, recording
everything, creating museums of all kinds and
exulting in commemorations and anniversaries.
Yesterday's forward-looking and messianic out¬
look has been replaced by a backward-looking or
antiquarian view of history, in which we are no
longer active participants but nostalgic, wistful
onlookers. Nature was once a "conservative"
value opposed to History. Ecology, the only new
or rising political movement, mythologizes nature
to rally support. Back to the land, to local com¬
munities, traditions and threatened ways of life is
the order of the day. Even the idea of the
Republic, as the author of these lines upholds it
in the French context, can be interpreted as a
form of "return to the past" in the face of the
communalist and mercantile tendencies of the
now dominant, devastating Anglo-Saxon model
of democracy. "Preserving" is once again a pos¬
itive, even chic if not avant-garde term. It seems
as if, faith in the future having taken refuge among
the poorest inhabitants of the planet, the rich are
getting used to seeing progress not as the pursuit
of a better world but, to quote Milan Kundera, as
"the forerunner of the worst", and they have
good reasons to do so.
The danger lies in the advantage thus gained
by nihilism and cynicism. If progress is dead,
then anything goes. The law that says "the winner
takes all" is the law of a self-sufficient present
where making money fast and in any way pos¬
sible becomes the individual's supreme ideal.
The solution doubtless lies not in creating
yet another utopia or a new secular messianism,
but perhaps in waging a series of specific, single-
minded, ethically-based struggles, if not to achieve
the ideal best, then at least to steer clear of the real
worst. And today the worst seems to us to be the
very dilemma that the course of events would like
to lock us into: either, in the name of modernity,
to transform the planet into a supermarket, sub¬
jecting all public and private human activity to the
law of supply and demand; or, in the name of
identity, to shut ourselves off in vindictive fan¬
tasies of a return to some lost purity, to the exclu¬
sion of those who are different from ourselves,
and to the integrity of an ideology, community or
religious belief. To exchange the technocratic
myth that technological progress is all it takes to
solve political and cultural problems, for the
ideocratic frenzy that claims a fine-sounding
moral norm can take the place of economic and
technological solutions, would simply be to
exchange a caricature from the North for a cari¬
cature from the South. Another kind of public life
could be reinvented in the middle ground
between the politics of the dollar and the various
politics of God, that would be worthy of the
Enlightenment philosophers but without their
illusions, and that would combine the pessimism
of intelligence with the optimism of the will. The
lie must, in short, be given to all those who believe
that every criticism of the myth of progress is nec¬
essarily reactionary.
12
REGIS DEBRAY
is a French philosopher,
essayist and novelist. Among
his works published in English
are Teachers, Writers,
Celebrities: The Intellectuals and
Modern France (1985) and
Critique of Political Reason
(1983).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Prometheus Bound ( 1 762), a
marble group by the
French sculptor Nicolas
Sébastien Adam.
Metaphors should be made at home
jy Daniel J. Boorstin
THE Western idea of progress, widespread
since the eighteenth century, had its roots
in two characteristically Western ideas and
experiences. First, the Judaeo-Christian belief in
a Creator God who had made the world new; and
second, the rise of experimental science and the
work of Galileo, Harvey, Newton and others,
who documented man's increasing ability to
know and control the world. These ideas and
experiences were at odds with the cyclical views
of history presumed by other world-religions,
and even in the classical Greek heritage. If God
could make the world ex nihilo, and man shared
the powers of that God, then making the new was
not only possible for man, it revealed his spark of
divinity.
The Western enthusiasm for the natural sci¬
ences was contagious, inspiring social sciences
which aimed to make new and better institu¬
tions. As scientific knowledge accumulated in
the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, it was
encouraged and shared by the European com¬
munity, with an increasing faith in its Utopian
possibilities. It was this faith which stirred the 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
beliefs of Jefferson and the American revolu¬
tionaries in the possibility of creating a new
nation in a New World, pursuing the idea of
human equality and rights to life, liberty, and
the pursuit of happiness. It also inspired the
beliefs of the French revolutionaries of 1789 in
their power to clean out the cobwebs of the Old
Regime, and make a new Republic dedicated to
Liberty, Equality, Fraternity and the rule of
Reason. The spectacular successes of European
industry in the nineteenth century the creation
of steam power and then electrical power, along
with the epochal insights of Adam Smith,
Auguste Comte, Charles Darwin, Karl Marx and
others, with improvement of transportation, the
growth of cities and the increase of wealth
reinforced the hope (in Tennyson's words) that it
would be possible to "Let the great world spin
forever down the ringing grooves of change."
Can such an idea, that grew from distinc¬
tively Western memory, experience, and imagi¬
nation, take root and flourish elsewhere? Can it
be credible in parts of the world that do not share
the Judaeo-Christian belief in a Creator God, a
God of Novelty, and in a Creator Man, Apostle
of Novelty? Can the idea of progress survive in
societies that lack the melodramatic Western tri¬
umphs of science and technology, that lack the
rising standards of living, and have not succeeded
in making viable societies by newly-drawn con¬
stitutions? Can peoples be expected to share the
intellectual product when they had not shared the
processes from which it came?
More basic, even, than the idea of progress in
Western thought is the notion of which Blaise
Pascal was the eloquent spokesman. "Man is but
a reed, the weakest in nature, but he is a thinking
reed." And, though the universe destroy man,
man is still nobler, for he is aware of the advan¬
tage the universe has over him. Man's greatness,
then, is in his consciousness, his awareness of
his place in the world, of what the world holds
and might hold for him, and what he might hold
for the world. That consciousness has led man in
the West to believe in progress. But where will
that consciousness properly lead men who have
lived in drastically different circumstances, with
contrasting histories ? While the idea of progress
may be a suitable and suggestive metaphor for
Western history, elsewhere, among peoples who
have no similar historical roots, it may express
nothing more than a bitter Utopian irony.
Finally, how does it benefit the world when
people freeze the metaphors of alien history into
ideology? For ideology itself is a contradiction
and denial of man's endless powers of novelty and
change which are suggested by the very idea of
progress. Would we not, perhaps, profit more
from the diversity of human experience if we
encouraged all peoples to make their own
metaphors?
DANIEL J. BOORSTIN
is a leading American historian
who was Librarian of Congress
from 1975 to 1987. His many
books include a trilogy, The
Americans, The Image and The
Discoverers. His latest work,
The Creators, a history of
human achievements in thé
arts, was published by Random
House in 1992.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Relative values
jy Flora Lewis
c
An illustration for The
Adventures of Baron
Miinchhausen (1786) shows
Baron de Crac reaching for
the Moon.
I AN North and South share the same
idea of progress?" This is a provoca-
' tive question which I must answer yes
and no. On one- level, everybody has the same
basic needs adequate food, shelter, health care
and a sense of dignity. The "South", in its
metaphorical meaning of the poorest societies,
is still a long way from reaching these stan¬
dards. Moving towards them would certainly be
seen as "progress" both by themselves and by
those already much better off. But even in flat
material and physical terms, the idea is not so
simple. The population explosion in global terms
is the result of a dramatic reduction in mor¬
tality rates and an increase in life expectancy.
Women aren't having more babies than a century
ago in poor societies, but a lot more babies are
reaching adulthood thanks to scientific and
technological advances, which move geomet¬
rically while economic development moves far
more slowly.
Poverty increases because there are a lot
more people, and in some cases it increases
absolutely because of the consequent strain on
resources desertification (in the Sahel, for
example), deforestation, soil erosion and so on.
The fact that more people stay alive may be
considered progress, but the fact that they live
so badly, sometimes worse than their ancestors,
cannot be. The prosperous tend to have far
fewer children, who live better. Is that progress?
Yes, they feel it is. So this idea of material
improvement is shared. IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Yet, still in strictly material terms, above the
level of absolute misery, poverty and progress
are felt as relative conditions and inequality
measured by immediate surroundings can seem
more important. The rioters in South Central
Los Angeles last year certainly consider them¬
selves poor. They live in a city which flaunts
wealth and luxury, they watch TV which not
only urges ever more consumption but takes
them inside the homes of the well-to-do for a
vicarious taste of ease and comfort. They them¬
selves are enormously better off than many
hundreds of millions in Africa, Latin America
and Asia, but they do not make such a compar¬
ison. Why should they? They live in a society
which preaches democracy, equity and justice,
and they feel it has failed to deliver to them. Is
this progress? Perhaps, in the sense that they do
not simply accept their lot in resignation but
look for one way or another to improve it,
making their demands heard. This idea of
progress is probably also shared.
A challenge to the will of God
But even in those societies which do believe in
progress, at least as possible, if no longer
< v
inevitable, in the Victorian tenet, there is no
longer such conviction about what it really is.
Some cultures reject the whole idea as hubris, an
unworthy challenge to the will of God. There is
considerable confusion between "moderniza¬
tion" and "progress". Are they synonymous,
opposites, or simply different? All can be argued,
though the urge to modernize making use of sci¬
ence and technology, economic development,
greater autonomy, is very widespread, even
among such groups as fundamentalists who
think of restoring a golden age rather than "pro¬
gressing" toward an unknown future.
Progress suggests a certain philosophical
and moral content, as well as material improve¬
ment, and that, like beauty and justice, can be in
the eye of the beholder. The image of the ideal
society which would be the ultimate goal of
progress is not shared, not only among cul¬
tures, but not even within them. I would main¬
tain that there are and always will be arguments
because there is a permanent tension between the
consciousness of man as an individual and man
as a member of a community. Both are essential.
According to varying circumstances and per¬
ceptions, which change with time and place as
Carnovo/(l986),
mixed media on card
(I70x 130 cm), by the
Cuban painter Julio Garcia
Fortes.
K»*?-^. ^
16
i«.i
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
well as with cultural traditions, one or the other
need is felt to be more urgent. Sooner or later,
efforts to meet the one will lead to a feeling of
intolerable constraint on the other, forcing a
change of perceptions. This is why I reject
Francis Fukuyama's idea of an "end of history"
even in his narrow Hegelian sense. The social
versus individual dilemma is inherent in the
human condition and will never be resolved.
Therefore, I do not see how the idea of progress
can mean much more than providing human
satisfaction, which is inevitably an elusive,
evanescent state.
A sense of void
Modern industrial society ordered by democ¬
ratic government, which I assume is what is
meant by "North", has indeed gone a long way
towards satisfying certain needs, compared to
previous periods. But it also contains deep frus¬
trations and a sense of growing void, flagrantly
displayed in the drug culture. I suppose this is
what Malraux meant in saying "the twenty-first
century will be spiritual or it will not be". The
North has been unable to explain that void, and
therefore has come to doubt the reality of
progress. The "South" sees the failings and looks
for a different, more encompassing idea of
progress with greater warmth, more human
consolation and less alienation, though it hasn't
been able to explain it either.
There arc differences of emphasis, and in
this sense, no, the idea of progress is not shared.
That need not and should not be divisive or
confrontational. There is still much to commu¬
nicate and share and enrich in all ways, pro¬
viding we do not fall into the trap of blaming
"the enemy" for all that goes wrong, as we used
to blame "God's will". Nor do I think it matters
very much whether we all have the same idea of
progress. Absolute conviction, certainty about
the ultimate in human affairs, social blueprints,
provide the one approach that is sure to be
wrong, and they have been the source of a great
deal of the harm people have done to each other.
It is as well that we try out different ways of
seeking to fulfill our hopes and aspirations,
mindful that we all do have them.
Mille couleurs (1 989), a
design for a fresco by
Daoud Krouri.
FLORA LEWIS
is a distinguished American
journalist who is Senior
Columnist with The New York
Times, for which she writes a
twice-weekly column on
foreign affairs. She is the
author of several books
including Europe: Road to Unity
(Touchstone/Simon & Schuster,
1992).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
North-South: beyond
the great divide
In a world divided between haves and have-nots, is domination
the hidden face ofprogress? Or should we see progress within the context
of a single world facing the same problems, albeit to different degrees?
How far is it possible to imagine a definition ofprogress that would be
universally applicable?
The universal and
the particular
by Joseph Ki-Zerbo
18
FOR some time, I have been arguing that the
idea of universality is put forward by
people in centres of power and places that
dominate the rest of the world. The spectacle of
the chaos reigning in the modern world impels
us to fall back on this idea as though on a
fortress. When danger threatens we use it like a
lifebuoy, clinging to it because we feel that it can
save the world.
Now terms such as the universal, progress
and development need to be approached with
great vigilance and in a critical spirit. I agree
that we should talk about the universal, but
without overlooking its counterpart, the par¬
ticular; and we should relate them to each other
dialectically rather than as a pair of opposites.
The universal feeds on particular cases, and par¬
ticular cases must make use of the universal.
This dialectical approach seems to me to
revalidate the idea of the universal, providing it
is agreed from the outset that there is a piece of
the universal in every individual. As regards
democracy, for instance, either we say that the
democracy the world needs is of the type
designed in the West which is liable to be met
with counter-arguments or even fierce objections
to any such intrusion or we seek to find in
every culture some starting point or predispo¬
sition towards democracy.
To take the case of Africa, that continent's
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Above, Jour de fête
(1984), acrylic on canvas
(100x300 cm), by the
Moroccan-born artist
Fatima Hassan.
Below left, Germination
(1992), by the Brazilian
painter Kinkas.
JOSEPH KI-ZERBO,
of Burkina Faso, is a noted
historian who was general
editor of the first volume of
Unesco's eight-volume General
History ofAfrica. He is the
author of a history of black
Africa (Histoire de l'Afrique
noire, 1978).
history obviously contains advance pointers to
the state as an institution based on the rule of law.
Africans have a saying, "The king docs not have
royalty, royalty has the king", meaning that even
a king is subject to a higher authority. This idea
suggests that of the rule of law. I have confirmed
this myself in the case of the emperor of the
Mossi, who remained seated while people around
him continually made suggestions as to what he
should do. He was literally the first slave of law
and custom.
This gives the lie to our modern African dic¬
tators, who claim that democracy has never
existed in Africa and is an idea alien to our culture.
Africans who think this ignore the reality of their
culture and history. This type of particularism is
to be avoided.
Or again, consider man's relationship with
nature, with health, with life and death. In this area
every culture has good and bad, positive and neg¬
ative aspects. The universal must operate on the
basis of positive particulars. None of us, I think,
defends a "tribalization" of principles. The uni¬
versality of human rights is a just idea for the
simple reason that we all have a human identity. It
is as human beings that we all claim the applica¬
tion of these rights.
On the subject of progress, I recently wrote,
"It's all very well to move fast as long as you
know where you're going". We cannot speak of
progress solely in relation to means: the direction
and purpose must be defined from the outset. In
short, we cannot speak of progress without raising
the question of ends: and this raises an ethical
problem, since wc have to choose a model or a
plan for society. This aspect of the matter is often
left out of the discussion. What kind of society do
we want to build? In this context development
has tended to mask and even to promote
domination. Some Western leaders I am
thinking of Ronald Reagan in particular have
said, "They should do as we do!" On that basis,
development becomes a way of imposing a pre¬
determined model.
It is important to realize that the human and
social sciences are lagging behind the other sci¬
ences. In my opinion no development is pos¬
sible without the development of the former. In
the last ten years the world has witnessed a mul¬
titude of events that no-one foresaw because far
too much priority has been given to the sciences
that contribute to material development. People
have devoted themselves to the accessories of
intelligence, to the detriment of the brainwork
that is the prime mover of human progress.
We have reached the point where people's
individuality has been dismembered, split into
fragments. They have lost touch with certain
transcendent values and they have lost their
sense of community. By way of illustration of 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
On/Off (1 99 1),
a mixed-media work
measuring 48 x 39 x 25 cm
by Romuald Hazoumé, an
artist from Benin.
this process another picture comes to my
mind that of the god-king Osiris, whose body
was chopped up into pieces by his brother
before being put back together again. I believe
that this Egyptian myth is relevant today to
human society as a whole: it is time to recon¬
struct man and put him together again.
Intellectuals can play a crucial part in this
respect, not only by weaving the dreams and
myths that human beings need to give them a
reason for living, but also by blazing the trail
towards solidarity and mutual recognition on
the basis of universal values. A Senegalese stu¬
dent recently said to me, "Professor, what we are
interested in today is not development, but hap¬
piness." I was impressed by his remark. At a time
when everyone is talking about progress and
development, this young man brings us back to
the essentials. No doubt people will say that
happiness is as hard to define as progress. All the
same, it is what we should be aiming for.
Universality as the West understands it is a
truncated concept. It is based only on one
sequence of history. I have often rebuked my
Western colleagues for their lack of receptiveness
to other histories, their hermetic approach, and
their tendency to think that things have only
been happening in the last four centuries. If
they do go further back, it is to make ancient
Greece the absolute starting point, forgetting
that Greece was itself influenced by other his-
20
tories, especially that of Egypt, which in turn
owes much to Africa.
But let us go back to Ronald Reagan's posi¬
tion. It does not hold water. Take the question
of energy consumption. If the world's per capita
energy consumption was as high as that of
North America, the consequences would be
devastating. It is not enough to say that this
model is undesirable; it is impossible. Wanting
everyone to adopt it is a tragic mistake. Western
thought, by persisting on this ecumenical path,
actually tends towards exclusiveness.
Could we not get intellectuals to turn their
attention seriously to this dialectic between the
universal and the particular? This would lead to
agreement on some intangible principles which
hold good for all human beings, such as respect
for life and man's relationship with nature and
knowledge. What's the point of advocating uni¬
versality when in my country 70 to 75 per cent
of the population can neither read nor write? In
Africa we are moving directly from an oral tra¬
dition to the post-industrial era of the audiovi¬
sual, skipping the crucial stage of writing.
It is Utopian to propose the application of
universal values to peoples in situations where
the conditions for this do not exist. The principle
of intercommunication, whereby individuals
get to know themselves and communities get to
know each other, is essential. I have already
suggested that the right to know oneself and to
be known should be added to the list of basic
human rights. Many people, especially in the
developed countries, think nowadays that there
is nothing interesting to be learned in the coun¬
tries of the South. People who go there as
tourists do not really enter into their histories,
their cultures or their civilizations. This makes
it impossible to achieve the "co-responsibility"
we sometimes hear about.
The foundations of universality need to be
strengthened and another organization of peo¬
ples established. People say that the United
Nations Organization represents the peoples
of the world, but today this is no longer true.
States have gained the upper hand. They have
been described as cold monsters, but I wonder
whether they are not deep-frozen monsters.
Transcending the paradigm of the national
state, a legacy of nineteenth-century Europe, seems
to me one possible route to the universal. Modern
man's technological achievements are creating
new patterns, a new image of the world which
makes this framework obsolete. We must tran¬
scend the nation-state and move towards the estab¬
lishment of livelier and more receptive communi¬
ties. Movement in that direction will bring us
closer to the universal, and to progress.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
One world
3y Alain Touraine
The Universe: a Thousand
Billion Galaxies
(1980-1990), a
photomontage
(100 x 100 cm) by the
Russian painter George
Kuzmin.
THE idea that the predominant trend is
towards progress and universalism, with
counter-currents running back towards
religion and the irrational, is one that often seems
to be taken for granted.
This view is far removed from reality. As con¬
cerns the West, there is another way of looking at
things that seems to me much closer to the mark.
The idea of progress was uppermost in the minds
of certain intellectuals and statesmen for a century,
but from 1870 onwards it was no longer dis¬
cussed. The history of the West has been some¬
thing quite different. Pushing paradox to its
limits, I would even go so far as to say that if ever
there was a time when people believed in progress,
it was in the Middle Ages.
Modernity dismisses the idea of a general
movement embracing nature, society and the M. I
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Eyeing Out (1 993),
a "collograph" or collage
print by the Finnish artist
Raija Patchett.
individual. These are becoming separate, distinct
areas, and I think that political and cultural life in
the West has been a matter of managing the rela¬
tionships between them. On the one hand, the
idea of progress has been shattered and sup¬
planted by that of economic growth, and, on the
other, an idea which is completely foreign to the
very concept of progress has emerged, the idea of
democracy, linked to that of individualism. None
of the great eighteenth-century exponents of
progress, including Rousseau as well as Voltaire,
came out officially and openly in favour of
democracy, quite the reverse. In fact, the concept
of the nation, which first appeared in Germany,
is the dominant concept of the twentieth century.
In other words, the history of the West docs
not chronicle the universal triumph of reason
but the process of learning how to manage the
relationship between economic growth what we
may call practical reason and the ideas of nation
and freedom.
This great current, previously moving in the
direction of integration, is now moving, world¬
wide, in that of disintegration. We have the
impression of living at a time when, to use exprès-
11
sions that are almost slogans, markets, tribes and
individual consciousnesses are living in separate
worlds. Society as such no longer exists. This is
important. Any solution that calls for the world
to be rebuilt around the individual, around the
economy or around cultures, is destined to fail
and can only end in disaster. In the world of
today, the objectivity of markets is completely dis¬
sociated from the plurality of individual con¬
sciousnesses and cultures.
The West, and many other parts of the world,
must now think how to live in accordance with
several principles at the same time. The distin¬
guishing feature of Western modernity is, I repeat,
not the universalism of progress, but the combi¬
nation of the universalism of reason, the partic¬
ularity of nations stronger, of course, in more
recently-built nations such as Italy and Ger¬
many and the universality of human rights, in
other words, the combination of individualism
and democracy.
I believe that this is the heart of the matter: not,
above all, to argue the case for the universal
against that of the particular, but to argue in
favour of the need for a society, a country, a
group of countries or the entire world to combine
several principles. The desire to make societies
one-dimensional ethnically pure, dedicated to
the rationale of the market or even entirely
devoted to individual interests is the funda¬
mental danger today. In every part of the world,
learning how to combine several principles is
essential.
In my view it is crucial that these problems
should be discussed in the context of one single
world. I believe it has become dangerous to talk
about "the third world", "the first world" and
"the second world". It is dangerous to think even
that a North-South divide exists. This is a mis¬
representation. Today the same issues arise in
both in differing proportions. Instead of saying
that reason resides in the North, with all its flaws,
while particularism reigns in the countries of the
South, we should, I think, be stating this problem
of combinations in the same terms for every part
of the world; otherwise, there will be a head-on
confrontation between those who argue that
reason should be given priority and those who
maintain that priority should be given to plu¬
rality and cultural diversity.
ALAIN TOURAINE,
French sociologist, is director of studies and director of the
Centre for Sociological Analysis and Intervention (CADIS)
at the School of Advanced Studies in Social Sciences, Paris.
Among his works published in English are Return of the Actor
(1985) and The Voice and the Eye: The Analysis of Social
Movements (1981).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The shadow of oppression
by Tariq Banuri
Camp Followers (1926),
oil on canvas
(81 x 95.5 cm), by the
Mexican painter
José Clemente Orozco.
IF the world were a single country, it would
be a "third world" country. Reduced to
scale, the aggregate economic, social and
environmental characteristics of the whole world
are the same as those of a typical third world
country. The inequality of wealth, consump¬
tion and power, the diversity of cultures, reli¬
gions and languages and the degree and nature
of conflicts over these differences, the diversity
of genes and species and the rates at which they
are being extinguished where can one find
these today but in the South?
But the parallel runs deeper than levels of
inequality, diversity or violence. There is what
may be called an absence of a collective com¬
munity. Just as there is no such thing as a global
community, in southern societies there is no
such thing as a national community. Think about
a reduction in global consumption levels to
accommodate the environmental crisis, and ask M. ¡S
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Motor ( 1 9 1 8), oil on
canvas (135 x 118 cm) by
Fernand Léger.
whether there can be a general agreement over
whose consumption ought to be sacrificed.
Should the poor die to enable the rich to live in
the style they have been accustomed to, or
should the rich give up centuries of progress
and revert to what they might view as a sub¬
human form of consumption in order to let the
poor survive? It is relatively easy to answer this
question within the national boundaries of
northern societies, but very difficult to do so at
the global level.
Thus the question "can the North and South
share the same idea of progress?" can be refor¬
mulated more simply as "can the population of
a southern country share the same idea of
progress or have any idea of progress at all?"
In other words, instead of looking for a con¬
sensus between the North and the South, let us
begin by looking at how the basis for consensus
in the South differs from that in the North.
A concept that continues to possess deep res¬
onance is colonialism. It is possible to portray the
conflict over progress as one between two con¬
trasting attitudes towards colonialism. This con¬
flict squares off the (unconscious) champions or
24
legitimizers of colonialism against its critics. Half
a century after the supposed demise of colonial
rule, these two strands have not moved towards
a synthesis. On the contrary, one can sense
already the distant rumblings of a revival of colo¬
nialism, first within the South itself, and later
across the globe. There is a grave danger that
from the standpoint of history the second half of
the twentieth century will appear as but a brief
interruption in the long march of colonial rule.
One can be somewhat polemical here. It
seems that while the discussion of progress solely
in terms of outcomes is legitimate in the North
(presumably because there is a consensus over
institutions and processes, the so-called end of his¬
tory), this is not possible in the South, where
there is a continuing history of powerlessness
and injustice. If this is so, then the overall objec¬
tive of progress (growth, conservation) may be
less important in the South than the mechanism
through which the objective is to be achieved. It
may make sense in the North to formulate theo¬
ries of salvation (which, in the words of Ashis
Nandy, "do not save, but only justify action in the
present"), but understanding in the South cannot
begin without a theory of oppression.
In other words, the legitimacy of the idea of
"progress " in large parts of the southern popu¬
lation would depend on our ability to formulate
it, to use Nandy's words again, in terms of "the
expansion of the awareness of oppression". In
general, neither the North nor the elites of the
South have defined progress in this manner.
This was most evident in the discussions of
the United Nations Conference on Environ¬
ment and Development (UNCED), which was
itself a major attempt to define a shared idea of
progress in the face of impending catastrophe.
The North viewed itself as Noah building an
Ark to defend us from the deluge; the South
saw itself as Jesus being sacrificed on the cross
for the sins of humanity. The North sought to
focus on technology and organization, the South
on politics and injustice. The story of UNCED
is meaningless to one who sees only the shaping
of a piece of wood but not whether it will bear
the weight of Noah or of Jesus. E3
"*" sssa
TARIQ BANURI
is a Pakistani writer and journalist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A shared crisis j¡ Edgar Morin
The Human
Condition
(1992),
oil on canvas
(80 x 60 cm)
by the
Vietnamese
painter
Duong Dinh
Sang.
WEmust realize, and make sure others fate of a specific planet and its specific inhabi-
realize, that we all share the same tants, facing the specific problems of life, death
destiny. Unity, in this global age, and progress,
means that wc have a common destiny, of life The idea of progress, doubtless the key con-
andof death. The universal is no longer abstrae- cept of the modern Western world, became
tion, but specific, because what is at stake is the current during the eighteenth and nineteenth
Mariytft T
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ye mwezongu matunda haya
matamu (Do these Fruits
Taste Good?), 1 992, acrylic
on plywood (6 1 .5 x 6 1 cm)
by the Tanzanian artist
George Lilanga di Nyama.
26
EDGAR MORIN,
French sociologist, is emeritus
director of research at the
National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS), Paris. His
most recent published work is
Terre-Patrie (Editions du Seuil,
Paris, 1993).
centuries and has since become universal. The
idea of progress seemed to be a veritable law
governing the way the world would evolve. It
was based on the scientific determinism that
then predominated a kind of historical law
that could be represented in various ways, that
of Auguste Comte as well as that of Karl Marx.
It seemed to have been reinforced by the idea
that biological evolution started out with single-
cell creatures and ended up with human beings,
and to be supported by developments, which
could only be beneficial, in science and in the fac¬
ulty of reason. In other words, the idea that
spread was that of progress as being necessary
and inevitable. World wars and other setbacks
seemed to be merely unfortunate accidents
caused by the death throes of reactionary and
anti-progressive forces.
Furthermore, the concept of development,
which itself became generally accepted after the
Second World War, gave rise to a kind of tech¬
nological and economic model of progress in
which economic growth emerged as, so to speak,
the only driving force needed for every form of
human progress, including opportunities for
personal fulfilment. This conception completely
obscured the havoc wreaked by growth and
technological and economic development on
cultures, in Europe to begin with, but on a much
greater scale in the rest of the world.
Progress, that is to say the future, is today in
crisis, a crisis of which there were already pre¬
monitory signs before the war but which is now
omnipresent. It affects the entire world, and
especially the developing countries, since it has
become clear that both the Western and Eastern
models of development have most often ended
in failure.
The crisis started brewing in the totalitarian
regimes of the East, whose promise of a radiant
future for mankind has crumbled in recent years,
but it has also affected the West, where no-one,
and rightly so, any longer believes in historical
or even physical determinism. The realization
has dawned that science can manipulate, enslave
and destroy as well as benefit humanity, and
certain half-baked forms of reasoning thinking
that, in the abstract, is logical but is bereft of any
empirical basis have been spread abroad, mas¬
querading as "reason".
I therefore believe that we are experiencing,
in various forms, a shared crisis of progress
whose globalization I also believe to be the
reason why people today are turning back to the
ethnic group or to religion. When the future is
lost and the present unhappy, miserable and
distressing, the past is all that is left. I feel that our
primary duty is to discard the idea of mechan¬
ical progress based exclusively on a technolog¬
ical and economic foundation.
We should realize that underlying the idea of
progress was the idea of "a better life", lived
decently and with a civilized respect for others.
The idea of progress must henceforward be
governed by this ethical imperative, thus
becoming something desirable and possible
rather than an inescapable mechanism.
In my opinion this means that we must
abandon the linear perspective according to
which there was an advanced world, a back¬
ward world and a primitive world, all of which
had to share the same conception. It must be
acknowledged that every civilization or culture
is a blend of the most diverse ingredients
superstitions, arbitrary beliefs, profound truths
and age-old wisdom and that this includes
Europe, which also has its truths, its myths and
its illusions, starting with the illusion of progress.
Rethinking the idea of progress is becoming
a priority.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER -DECEMBER 1993
INDIGENOUS
PEOPLES
TREATING NJfflU
I
I
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
F the inhabitants of the Nicobar
Islands in the Bay of Bengal
south of Myanmar had not
remained faithful to traditional
ways ofmanaging the resources
of their ecosystem, the environment
in which they live would not have
survived for long. Some ofthe archi¬
pelago's twenty-two unequally-sized
islands are sparsely-wooded, while
others are covered with dense
forests that are home to rare tree
species. A few of them, such as Car
Nicobar and Chowra, are overpop-
ulated, but no one goes hungry and
everyone can get hold of enough
wood to build a house and a fishing
boat. According to a study carried
out by G. Prakash Reddy, professor
of social anthropology at the uni¬
versity of Tirupati (India), the bal¬
ance between forests, grasslands
and farmland is respected. When¬
ever a villager needs grass to roof
his house or wood to repair it, he
asks the island Council. Anyone
who cuts down a tree must replant
one of the same species in the same
spot. The Council recommends
burning dried coconut shells and
waste vegetable matter for cooking,
except for great feasts, when dead
wood is used. During one of the tra¬
ditional ceremonies that punctuate
the year, pigs are sacrificed so that
there are not too many of them
when food for people and livestock
becomes scarce.
The example of the Nicobar
Islands shows that, contrary to
widespread belief, some of the
planet's inhabitants did not wait
until the 1970s before starting to
take care of their environment.
Two young men
emerge from
the Sacred
Forest at the
end of an
initiation
ceremony (Côte
d'Ivoire).
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
INDIGENOUS PEOPLES
MM MM
1TI IHI
iE
Social and religious traditions on
every continent have helped to
manage nature without destroying it.
Travellers in the west African
savanna, for example, can see dense
forests or copses that have been
respected because they are sacred.
These areas, including some in
Casamance (Senegal), are currently
being studied for Unesco. Eugène
Faty, who lives in Casamance,
observed the sacred Oussouye
forest south ofDakar, which no one
is allowed to enter, on Unesco's
behalf. The fruits that grow on its
trees are untouchable. They fall to
the ground, where their seeds give
rise to dense undergrowth. Trees
and animals are strictly protected,
and may be removed only during
initiation ceremonies which take
place every twenty or twenty-five
years. If a tree must be cut down or
an animal killed, its forgiveness
must be asked first. The same tra¬
dition used to be found among the
hunters of Parakou and Save, in
northern Benin. The hunters were
also healers who maintained a close
relationship with plants and ani¬
mals, from which they made med¬
icines. Not everyone had the right to
kill a lion or buffalo. Before and after
the hunt, the privileged hunters had
to offer sacrifices which cost them
very dear, thus naturally limiting
the quantity of quarry they could
take.
READING NATURE'S OPEN BOOK
Although European settlement has
profoundly altered the quality oflife
of Australia's Aborigines, nature is
still an open book to them. With nei¬
ther watches nor calendars, they tell
the times and seasons by the blos¬
soming ofplants and trees. When the
milky-white "oyster flowers" are in
bloom, real oysters are plump, white
and ready for gathering, and when
the pinkheather in Darwin, Northern
Territory, blossoms, it means honey
is plentiful. Food is closely related to
religion. People, the earth, animals
and plants all belong within a vast
system of laws created by the ances¬
tral spirits during the "dream-time".
The honey ants of Papunya, in the
centre ofthe country, are a beneficent
reincarnation of these spirits because
they provide the Aborigines with the
sweetmeats they relish. Some foods
become totems and may sometimes
be eaten during ceremonies, which
helps regulate both hunting and
gathering. Custom requires the Tiwis
of Bathurst Island, not far from
Darwin, always to rebury a piece ofa
yam to make sure the tuber grows
back right away.
Shark fishing offthe Tonga Islands
is a ritual activity, remote from any
concern for catch size or profit, and
does not deplete the sea's abundant
resources. "Throughout the Pacific,"
writes Marie -Claire Bataille-Ben-
guigui of the French National
Museum of Natural History, "the
shark is a revered or even sacred
creature. It is, depending on the
place, the incarnation ofeither gods
or ancestors". In the Tonga Islands,
the shark is considered to be a love-
token from the deity Hina, a female
figure observed on the moon, to the
world ofhuman beings. Harpooned
or caught with fish nets or slip-knots,
the sharks are shared out, but they
28
An initiation in
the forest of
Kalounaye
(Senegal).
cannot be sold and the pieces cannot
leave the village. Traditional fishing
methods are, however, being
replaced by more efficient, environ¬
mentally threatening techniques.
The small kingdom of Bhutan,
northeast of India, is another place
where religious beliefs help protect
the environment. A specialist who
lived there for ten years says the
people of Bhutan, steeped in Bud¬
dhist philosophy, have a profound
respect for rivers and for mountains,
some of which it is forbidden to
climb. Species that have become
extremely rare, such as the snow
leopard and the Himalayan black
bear, live in peace in Bhutan because
animals there are never killed for
sport. When black-necked cranes
migrate from Siberia or northern
Tibet to spend the winter, landing
in the fields in large flocks, the local
people, who respect the birds, con¬
sider it an excellent omen.
On the other hand, the forest has
not been spared. The cutting ofwood
for fuel and the clearing of forests
for agriculture have seriously jeop¬
ardized the ecological balance. The
government has launched an $8.9
million programme to set up exten¬
sive forest reserves and encourage
farmers to plant trees around their
property because wood supplies 98
per cent of their energy needs. A
World Bank report indicates that
overexploitation of the forest does
not seem to have alerted the local
population, which, moreover, is
increasing at a rapid rate.
It is hard to believe that the bare,
eroded, arid lands of Cochabamba
in central Bolivia supported a lush
tropical forest as recently as the
nineteenth century, who was
responsible for this act of destruc¬
tion? Trees played a major part in
Inca mythology. Michel Schlaifer, a
specialist in forestry who has been
working in Cochabamba for three
years, has written that the Incas
regarded the roots of trees as a link
with the ancestors in the world
"below", the trunk as representing
the "present" world, and the
branches as symbolizing the rela¬
tionship with the gods in the world
"above". In his History of the New
World, published in 1653, the
Spanish historian Bernabé Cobo
observed that a Spanish household
burned more wood in a day than
an Indian household burned in a
month. The Spanish cooked several
times a day whereas the Indians
prepared all their food for the day in
one go. The Indians built their
dwellings of rammed earth, while
the Spanish settlers used wood for
house frames, furniture and doors.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A Lacandón
fisherman at
Bonampak in
the Maya
Biosphere
Reserve
(Mexico).
In addition, wooden pit-props and
other structural supports were
needed for the many mines. Later,
when the railways came, wood was
indispensable as fuel. No-one made
any attempt to plant new trees.
THE ROLE OF THE SACRED
Colonization brought with it the
system of cash crops and quick
profits, but it was not the only factor
that upset the balance between man
and nature. Some specialists argue
that the New Zealand moa (or
dinorcis), a giant bird that was
unable to flyand was an easy prey for
Polynesian hunters, became extinct
because it was not protected by a
taboo. Research in this field is con¬
tinuing in New Caledonia, where
similar reasons may explain the dis¬
appearance of the macrofauna.
According to the Zairian sociolo¬
gist Simon Mukuna, many activities
by indigenous peoples are wrongly
attributed to a desire to protect the
environment. The Baoulé of Côte
d'Ivoire, for instance, respect the trees
on their sacred mountain because
the spirits of the dead live there and
harmonymust be preserved between
them and the spirits of the forest. Is it
possible that the sacralization of
nature is the bestway to protect it? In
the summer 1992 issue oí Diogenes,
the quarterly journal of the Interna¬
tional Council of Philosophy and
Humanistic Studies (no. 159, pp. 58-
60), the Mexican philosopher Luis
Villoro writes ofAztec civilization as
follows: "Time and space were deter
mined in terms of the sacred; the
sacred pervaded their institutions,
their daily lives, their artistic cre¬
ations, and formed the basis of all
their beliefs	 The gods are a tan¬
gible presence in all things: in trees,
rivers, mountains, time and space,
and in the daily activities ofmen	
The desacralization ofnature and of
society began with transcendental
monotheism. The alienation of the
sacred was accentuated in the
Renaissance. Nature began to be seen
not as the impression and sign of
divinity, but as a manipulable object,
destined to be dominated and
moulded by man".
In Ghana forests have been pre¬
served because they are regarded
as sacred. Unesco has launched a
three-year project entitled the "Co
operative Integrated Project on
Savanna Ecosystems in Ghana",
which will study carefully preserved
sacred forests with the help of
fetishists, village communities,
farmers, women and local authori¬
ties. The aim is to reconstitute in
the surrounding area the flora that
is best-adapted to the climate and
soil. This is a good example of how
the knowledge and practices of
indigenous peoples are being pos¬
itively reassessed during the Inter¬
national Year devoted to them.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD- Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agency journalists.
Prayer-flags in
Bhutan.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
WHEN PROSPERITY INCREASES POLLUTION
CLEANING UP
THE BLACK SEA
Each day, five major rivers (the
Danube, the Dniepr, the Dniestr,
the Don and the Koban) pour pol¬
lution generated by 165 million
inhabitants of 17 countries into the
Black Sea. Waste water from cities,
agricultural pesticides and fertil¬
izers, industrial discharges and oil
poured from ships have already
caused serious damage. Algae pro¬
liferating in the polluted water have
killed marine life and ruined the
once flourishing fishing industry.
Catches have plummeted from
900,000 tons in 1986 to 100,000 tons
in 1992. Swimming has been
banned on many beaches, reducing
revenue from tourism. The six Black
Sea countries Bulgaria, Georgia,
Romania, Russia, Turkey and
Ukraine have decided to launch
a three-year, $30-million project
with the help of the Global Envi¬
ronment Fund, to restore the sea's
ecological balance. The task will be
divided among the six countries,
with Romania, for example, working
on the fishing industry, Georgia on
biological diversity and Bulgaria on
the emergency measures to be
taken if disaster strikes.
30
OIL-SNIFFING
DOGS
A Canadian company, Imperial Oil
Resources Limited, is using dogs to
sniff out underground oil, natural
gas and chemical pipeline leaks.
Labrador retrievers, which are also
used to detect drugs and as guide-
dogs for the blind, can locate leaks
from pipes buried as deep as five
metres underground. When a
pipeline springs a leak, a foul-
smelling chemical is pumped into
the suspected section. This sub¬
stance, which was specially devel¬
oped for the Canadian company, is
what the dogs actually detect. Impe¬
rial Oil's Ron Quaife says that, in
136 leaks so far, the dogs have failed
only twice, and have saved pipeline
owners millions of dollars.
Summer and winter smog is posing
a serious health hazard in many
cities ofcentral and eastern Europe.
During winter smog episodes in
Krakow (Poland), for example,
patients afflicted with respiratory
diseases are taken for the night to
the Wieliczka salt mine to find tem¬
porary relief. Industrially generated
fogs, which have largely disappeared
from western Europe, are increasing
in eastern Europe, where the
number of cars is doubling every
seven years. Bratislava (Slovakia),
Budapest (Hungary) and Prague
(Czech Republic) are particularly
affected. Winter smog is caused by a
TREES ATTACKED BY
KILLER MIST
Trees along several of the world's
coastlines, including the French
Mediterranean littoral and the
Italian coast near the mouth of the
Arno in Tuscany, are turning yellow
and withering. In 1992 the French
Agronomic Research Institute
(INRA) launched a programme
which led to the conclusion that
detergents and hydrocarbons on
the surface of the water become
concentrated in sea mist. These pol¬
lutants are then carried by the wind
to the shore, where they attack
leaves and pine needles, damaging
the surfaces so that salt can pene¬
trate. The growth of urban settle¬
ments along the coastline and the
increase in shipping will make it
increasingly difficult to solve this
problem.
mixture ofprimary pollutants, such
as sulphur dioxide, suspended par¬
ticulate matter, nitrogen oxides and
carbon monoxide. Summer smog is
caused by ozone, a secondary pol¬
lutant produced by complex chem¬
ical reactions between primary pol-
lutants and sunlight. A major
contribution to it is made by exhaust
emissions, particularly from cars not
equipped with catalytic converters.
UNDERSTANDING RIO
A Geneva-based foundation, the Centre for Our Common
Future, has published a remarkable little book entitled
The Earth Summit's Agenda for Change. A plain-lan¬
guage version ofAgenda 21 and the otherRio agreements.
The book, written by Michael Keating, is divided into
four sections: the social and economic dimensions of
Agenda 21; resource conservation and management;
strengthening the role of major groups; and the means
of implementation of sustainable development. Each
part is broken down into a number of one- or two-page
sections illustratedwith tables and graphs ofgreat clarity.
In addition to the English version there are also versions
in French, German, Spanish, Italian and Russian. For
further details please write to the The Centre for Our
Common Future, 52 rue des Pâquis, 1201 Geneva,
Switzerland. Tel: (4 1 22) 732 7 1 1 7. Fax: 738 50 46.
*<>
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
THE WORLD'S COLDEST
CASSAVA
Cassava is a tuber that feeds approx¬
imately 800 million people, or one
person in every seven. The Inter¬
national Center for Tropical Agri¬
culture (CIAT) in Cali, Colombia,
has frozen cassava shoot tips by
plunging them into liquid nitrogen
at -196° C, stopping the plants' cell
functions and making it possible to
preserve them indefinitely. Rigob-
erto Hidalgo, a researcher at the
Center, says, "Genetic diversity
cannot be recreated after it disap¬
pears, so gene banks are the basis
for tomorrow's food supply." In 1991
CIAT froze plant parts in liquid
nitrogen, recovered them and made
them grow again into whole plants.
The Center is already planning to
extend the process, which so far has
been used only to preserve cassava,
to other tropical species such as
potatoes, sweet potatoes and
bananas.
PROTECTING THE BIJAGOS
ARCHIPELAGO
The Bijagos archipelago is part of
the westAfrican country ofGuinea-
Bissau, which is wedged between
Senegal and Guinea. Now part of
the Archipel Island and Coastal
Biosphere Reserves Network, which
is integrated into Unesco's Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) programme,
the island chain comprises some
80 islands and stretches over '900
square kilometres. Social and cul¬
tural anthropologists as well as
ornithologists are very interested
in the archipelago, whose environ¬
ment is still well preserved, although
new buildings for the tourist
industry are starting to appear along
the coasts. As a result, the govern¬
ment and a number ofnational and
international organizations have
decided to promote the establish¬
ment of a national park and a bio¬
sphere reserve. The project is
accompanied by an awareness-
raising and information campaign,
training programmes for local
people, and a coastal planning pro¬
ject that has already resulted in sev¬
eral land-use maps for Guinea-
Bissau and the Bijagos archipelago.
INITIATIVES
Six years ago Conservation International (CI), an
American non-governmental organization, began
breaking new ground in the field of environmental
protection. In 1987 the group organized the first
debt-for-nature swap bypurchasing part ofBolivia's
external debt on the international market. CI raised
funds that helped the South American country's gov¬
ernment create a "biosphere reserve" comprising 1.5
million hectares of the Beni humid tropical forest in the
middle of the country.
A project aimed at breaking down the pol itical borders
between ecosystems by defining transnational "biore-
gions" is even more far-reaching. Costa Rica and Panama,
for example, signed an agreement setting up the bina¬
tional La Amistad Biosphere Reserve, and in 1991 CI
brought together representatives of Guatemala, Mexico
and Belize to define the boundaries of a tropical rain
forest corresponding to those of the ancient Mayan
empire. In Guatemala 25,000 square kilometres have
become the Maya Biosphere Reserve, which is comple¬
mented by other reserves in the neighbouring countries.
Large-scale projects currently underway in seventeen
countries have made CI famous. They are accompanied
by a host of related activities. For example, teams of CI
experts are assessing the diversity of plant and animal
species in remote areas of the Amazon forest and Papua
New Guinea. CI has also developed a geographic infor¬
mation system to pinpoint environmental hotspots
where protection and management are top priorities. It
is encouraging young people in Costa Rica and Suri¬
name to study the medicinal properties of local plants
with village shamans, ensuring that their knowledge is
passed on to future generations. At the same time it is pro¬
moting sustainable use of the forests' myriad non-timber
products, such as the tagua palm nut, which looks and
feels like ivory, decorative plants, spices, waxes and
resins. In Guatemala, for example,
villagers harvest chicle, a natural
latex used in the manufacture of
chewing gum.
CI has adopted the "biosphere
reserve" concept defined by
Unesco, combining nature con¬
servation with local development
and scientific research. Michel
Bâtisse, formerAssistant Director-
General with Unesco's Science
I Sector, is a member of the orga-
| nization's Board of Directors.
Unesco and CI have produced
an educational film entitled
Biosphere Reserves in Tropical
America, which is available in
English, French, Spanish and
Portuguese.
Conservation International,
1015 Eighteenth St. N.W,
Suite 1000, Washington DC,
20036 United States.
Tel: (202) 429 56 60.
Fax: 887 51 88
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
intellectuals:
the missing link?
An Indian journalist and a South African novelist (page 36)
reflect on the responsibilities of intellectuals today and tomorrow and
issue a warning against the temptations of utopianism that deluded so
many of their predecessors.
!
~ii\
'Z
Asking the right
questions
by Dileep Padgaonkar
31
DILEEP PADGAONKAR
is the Editor of The Times of
India. He was formerly head of
UNESCO's Office of Public
H
Information.
AVE we become obsolete? We failed to
foresee the chaos, anarchy and violence
that have been wreaking havoc in many
parts of the world during the last few years. We
were not prepared, mentally and emotionally,
for the implosion of the Soviet Union, the upsurge
of ethnic, nationalist and religious hatreds in
Europe, Africa and Asia, the sight of people too
emaciated or terrorized to express a single
coherent thought or voice a single coherent
sentiment.
We do not know what questions to ask. The
grandiose interrogations that world views, holistic
approaches and ideologies prompted until only
the other day now invite ridicule, scorn and,
what is worse, apathy and indifference. Our
vocation is to connect individuals and events,
events and trends, trends and processes, signs
and fantasies. We are not able to do so. And it is
this inability which provokes us more and more
to speak about the uncontrollable forces now
taking hold of our minds in terms which are
either apocalyptic or embarrasingly autobio¬
graphical. No longer can we echo Malraux:
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
"There is more truth in the
ink of scholars than in the
blood of martyrs",
mixed media on canvas
(89x116 cm) by the
Moroccan painter Hamid.
Qu'importe ce qui n'importe qu'à moi? (What
does anything matter that matters to me alone?)
This sense of our own obsolescence must
lead us, inevitably, to question the assumptions we
made, the logic we followed and the goals we set
for ourselves during our intellectual itinerary.
These are admittedly large questions which can
at best yield tentative, vague and extremely gen
eralized answers. But we can no longer avoid
them. Whether we were conservatives, liberals or
Marxists, our notion of progress tended to be
linear and measurable. Progress meant "marching
ahead" on the strength of capital, technology,
management, marketing and, depending on where
we placed ourselves on the ideological spectrum,
on the distribution of incomes and assets and
the creation of cultural artefacts and services.
We assumed that material wellbeing, civic
order and cultural give-and-take were goals
shared by humanity everywhere and that the
obstacles in the way of reaching these goals were
class interest, mercantile aggrandisement or the
never-satiated appetite for influence and power of
certain nations or groups of nations. This is why
our moral categories were biased in favour of
individual freedoms and egalitarianism. This is
why we reposed our faith in reason and ratio¬
nality. This is why we assumed that economic
advancement, social justice, higher standards of
education, culture and health, equality before
the law and such other elements of a democratic
order would forever banish the demons of prej-
' udice, hate and bigotry.
Messianic creeds and millenarian
fantasies
We were wrong. In retrospect we made no
allowance for several factors which have now come
to play a pivotal role in shaping the destiny of
individuals, communities and nations. We did not
pay enough attention for instance to the fact that
in two crucial areas of our life the economy and
information the centres of decision-making
would no longer be local or national bureaucracies
but more and more transnational oligarchies of
bankers, speculators and myth-makers in the
media. In these two areas the sovereignty enjoyed
by national governments is being eroded day by
day in the name of the free market, the interde¬
pendence of economics, the free flow of ideas and
images.
Nor did we adequately appreciate the extent to
which rising expectations for a better life mea¬
sured almost entirely in terms of higher levels of
consumption would inevitably engender frus¬
tration, which in turn would lead to the atomiza-
tion of individuals, the destabilization of societies
and the progressive entropy of institutions whose
role is to protect life and property, dispense justice,
temper greed and avarice. When individuals, soci¬
eties and the various bodies of governance are
thus rendered rudderless, messianic creeds and
millenarian fantasies step in to promise a socially
stable, spiritually sound and materially prosperous
future. In the period after the end of the Second
World War these creeds and fantasies, which derive
their sustenance from references to a glorious 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
past, a past free of ethnic, racial, linguistic and
religious "impurities", were fringe phenomena.
Now in the North and South alike they threaten
to come centre-stage. They frown on reason, sus¬
pect objectivity, decry tolerance, despise the sec¬
ular outlook and debunk modernity.
Make no mistake about it. To people who
are afraid of chaos and deprivation, this appeal to
return to "fundamentals" of religious faith has a
powerful emotional and moral appeal which is all
the stronger because the rational and secular dis¬
course has proved again and again to be a case of
hopes unfulfilled, a case of double-speak and
double-think, of hypocrisy and arrogance. That
those who advocate a return to "fundamentals"
and to various "cleansing" operations have no
* morally viable alternatives to offer is another
story altogether. But few are willing to even con¬
sider listening to such a story right now.
Lost certainties
The India I come from is no longer the India of
Mahatma Gandhi and Jawaharlal Nehru. This
was the India in which I was born and where I
grew up. When these two men held India in thrall
every Indian had an enticing challenge to shoulder:
to gradually minimize the importance of, if not
altogether shed, the "givens" of his birth his
religion, his caste, his linguistic and provincial
affinities the better to assume his larger identity
as a citizen of a vast multi-religious and multi-cul¬
tural nation. This, in turn, would enable him to be
at peace with himself and with the world at large.
Our articles of faith were democracy, secu -
larism, democratic socialism, non-alignment. Wc
took pride in the fact that we were an old civi¬
lization but a young nation; that our people were
poor and largely illiterate but yet held in their
hands the power to make and unmake govern¬
ments; that our press was free; that though our
country was partitioned on religious lines in 1947
wc refused to tread the path of theocracy; that
Hinduism, which owed its genius to its eclectic
and pluralistic nature, would ensure that our
democracy would avoid the pitfalls of majori-
tarianism; that our system would steer clear of the
excesses of capitalism and communism alike, and
that we would build a modern India on the foun¬
dations of a civilization which has given mankind
some of its shrewdest philosophical insights and
some of its most sublime aesthetic experiences.
Today, money power and muscle power have
often replaced arguments about electoral pro¬
grammes. Corruption is all-pervasive. People have
little faith in the fairness and efficiency of the
administration and the courts. Our secularism
too has come under a cloud because religion is
being blatantly exploited for electoral gain. The
minorities are being told to reject all reform on the
Panic (1 987),
gouache on paper
(57 x 82 cm)
by the Tunisian painter
Gouider Triki.
ground that it would endanger their identity. The
majority is being persuaded that the "appease¬
ment" of the minorities has gone far enough. The
secularists are clearly on the defensive.
The collapse of the Soviet Union has if any¬
thing precipitated the fall of the two remaining pil¬
lars of Nehruvian India: socialism and non-align¬
ment. Interdependence in the economic sphere has
led purely and simply to obeying the dictates of
international financial institutions and the transna-
tionals regardless of the costs to social justice and
to sovereign decision-making. As for non-align¬
ment, there is no-one left to be non-aligned against.
The emerging world order is nothing if not "prag¬
matic", that is, one where the currency of power
is economic clout, military (preferably atomic)
might and political and social "order".
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Unwilling to participate in the media carni¬
vals, unable to succumb to the seductions of
the marketeers, profoundly sceptical of funda¬
mentalisms, reduced to the role of a helpless
spectator of nations losing their sovereignty
and of societies redefining their identities on
the aggressive agenda of separateness, the intel¬
lectual appears to have reached two debilitating
conclusions. First, that the North-South
dichotomy is not a geographical or even civi-
lizational expression, but that it is very much
present in the minds of individuals everywhere.
Second, that for the present at least this
dichotomy cannot be overcome because, in the
truest sense, it is rooted in the quest for power
at one end and in the quest for self-fulfilment at
the other. The discourse of the International
Monetary Fund and the Pentagon, and of their
surrogates elsewhere in the world, shapes the
former quest while the discourse of the cler¬
gyman shapes the latter. Nations may come
together or fall apart but in both cases people are
called upon to worship at the altar of Mammon
and to converse with the Almighty, either
directly, if possible, or through His intermedi¬
aries on earth if necessary.
Striking a balance
The cashier, the communicator, the clergyman
rule the roost: none of them has any use for elab¬
orate conceptual systems, logic or the reason of
the sort dear to the Enlightenment philosophers.
The cashier, communicator and clergyman enter¬
tain no doubt; their sole concern is how best to
market their certainties. The certainty of the
cashier is ever more cash; that of the communi¬
cator, ever more slick messages; that of the cler¬
gyman, ever greater simplification of the ago¬
nies that torment the soul. In plain words, the
intellectual, to be effective, cannot be content to
discredit cash, subvert the slick message and
expose the chilling banalities of fundamentalist
speech, but must propose solutions which do
not emanate either from a cockily self-confident
ideology or from its counterfeit, religiosity.
This is of course easier said than done.
Perhaps a beginning can be made if intellec¬
tuals learn to strike a balance between the imper¬
atives of economic progress brought about by sci¬
ence and technology and efficient management of
men and resources, concern for human rights, the
protection of the environment, and affirmation of
cultural identity without aggressivity or apologia.
Perhaps a constant preoccupation with the spir¬
itual and moral yearnings of individuals every¬
where is required. Emphasizing one of these
imperatives at the expense of the others may well
be the reason why the world appears to have
gone out of gear.
Participants at the first
Meeting of Intellectuals and
Creators for a Single World
Tariq Banuri (Pakistan),
Tahar Ben ¡elloun (Morocco),
Jacques Berque (France),
Daniel }. Boorstin (United States),
André Brink (South Africa),
Lester Brown (United States),
Fawiia Charfi (Tunisia),
Mustafa Chérif (Algeria),
Jean Daniel (Le Nouvel Observateur),
Régis Debray (France),
Amos Elon (Israel),
Luc Ferry (France),
Celso Furtado (Brazil),
Nathan Cardeis (Los Angeles Times Syndicate),
Susan George (United States),
Bernard Guetta (Fronce),
Mahmoud Hussein (Unesco Courier),
Joseph Ki-Zerbo (Burkina Faso),
Jean Lacouture (France),
Gilles Lapouge (0 Estado de Säo Paulo),
Flora Lewis (United States),
Antonin Liehm (Czech Republic),
Pavel Lounguine (Russia),
Adam Michnik (Poland),
Edgar Morin (France),
Sami Naïr (France),
Ehsan Naraghi (Iran),
Olesegun Obasango (Nigeria),
Erik Orsenna (France),
Dileep Padgaonkar (India),
Stanley Sheinbaum (United States),
Oliver Stone (United States),
Alain Touraine (France),
Immanuel Wallerstein (United States).
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Assuming responsibility
by André Brink
Running Man, a
"geometric" photographic
sequence produced
in 1886 by the French
scientist and photographer
Etienne Jules Marey.
FIRST of all we must be clear about what we
mean by the words "progress", "North"
and "South". ("North" of what? "South"
of what? The problem of positioning becomes
crucial here; and the suggestion of tidy objec¬
tivity north and south of an immovable neu¬
tral equator has fallen into disrepute since
Copernicus).
Progress is a combination of motion and
direction, from one point to another. Before
anything else, we should clear our vocabulary to
make sure North and South agree on starting
points and (temporary) goals. All too often in the
past the starting point has been implied to be
wherever the South finds itself at a given
moment; and the goal the position occupied by
the North. At the very least, it seems to me that
the guideline should be what Camus said about
freedom and justice: accepting that neither is
attainable in an absolute form, at least one knows
that in any situation it is possible to aspire to
more freedom and more justice.
What sort of progress?
But having clarified the principle, we still need
to define the context of the progress we have in
mind. Are we talking about technology, eco¬
nomics, social behaviour, judicial systems, or
politics? Again, the vantage point would deter¬
mine everything. It is easy to predict which
position will be assumed by those in the North
who interpret the collapse of Marxism as, ipso
facto, the vindication of capitalism. And the
very notion of "universalism" is suspect from the
moment the question of "whose universalism?"
is posed.
Are we talking about aesthetic progress? If
we are, then surely the great Northern (here
identical with Western) tradition of symmetries
and masterpieces, of the pursuit of excellence, of
the beautiful, of the whole, appears to serve, if
not as a consummation devoutly to be wished,
then at least as a time-honoured and thoroughly
proven point of departure. But the South African
experience places it under a question mark, if not
under threat of erasure. How "valid" is a tradi¬
tion that originated in ancient Greece among
those individuals who had the leisure to indulge
in aesthetics because they had enough slaves to
take care of their manual work?
This dangerous division between "higher"
and "menial" pursuits is itself open to ques¬
tion. (And yet it has "validity"! Who would be
so rash as to discard all its products, from Homer
and Sophocles via Chaucer and Ronsard and
Michelangelo and Shakespeare and Rembrandt
and Mozart and Tolstoy and countless others?)
The point is that the moment "validity" enters
into the discussion it invites, once again, the
question, "Validity for whom?", which sub¬
verts all aspirations towards the objective and the
universal. It is so easy for such matters to be
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Dawn,
a detail from the tomb of
Lorenzo de' Medici
sculpted by Michelangelo
in about 1521.
drawn into the games of power that preoccupy
our world. And of one thing I am sure I
hope! and that is that when we speak of
progress it is not progress in increasing the effi¬
ciencies of power we have in mind. (The oppo¬
site may be closer to our intentions: the curtail¬
ment of power; the minimizing of power in
order to maximize freedom and justice and the
pursuit of truth.)
As a writer, my concern would primarily
be with progress of a cultural kind, or within a
cultural context; and for the purposes of speci¬
fication I would focus on those impulses of cul¬
ture involved in the production ofmeaning and
the definition of morality, of ethical responsi¬
bility. Assuming once again, with Camus, the
absence of objective or absolute value systems,
certainly, in respect both of significance and of
morality, it would be possible to strive for an
increase, and an enhancement, in any given con¬
text, social or otherwise.
Surely, actions, projects or products can con¬
stantly be improved in terms of their "load" of
meaning or their moral "validity" to or for an
increasing number of individuals (and in their
impact on each individual). The problem of a
defining instance may appear to remain: who
"decides" on what will make a given cultural
achievement more morally acceptable, or more
significant? And once again the danger of an
imposition of criteria from outside or above is only
too real. (But perhaps "value" may precisely be 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
ANDRE BRINK,
South African writer, is
Professor of Modern Literature
at Rhodes University,
Grahamstown, South Africa.
His most recent books are
Adamastor ( 1 993), An Act of
Terror ( 1 99 1 ) and Stores of
Emergency (1988).
determined in terms of the dangers to be faced
in the process, the risks to be taken, the odds to
be surmounted, the boundaries to be tran¬
scended.) To me, the advantage of such a view
lies in the way it minimizes the opportunities for
such an imposition, as each individual would be
encouraged to evaluate her or his own experi¬
ence (cultural or otherwise). And surely this
would be an ideal ingredient of true democ¬
racy. It makes the individual experience the
starting point of cultural progress: yet that expe¬
rience remains at all times fully inserted within
social interchange and collective responsibility.
Obviously this goes far beyond, but need not
exclude, the conceptions of culture presently
encountered in much of the world: culture as the
"organization of leisure" in the North; culture
as combat and "conscientization" in the South.
That dangerous animal,
the intellectual
We know that, at least since Julien Benda's La
Trahison des clercs, the term "intellectual" is
itself at risk. We know Camus's warning that
"The intellectual is a dangerous animal that
easily commits treason." But who still conceives
of that species as the lonely, aloof, disinterested
creature who judges human events, in an ivory
tower of dispassionate sanity, in terms of a tran¬
scendental Good or Evil? We know that the
much-vaunted "free agent" of the Age of Reason
is a fiction: we are all subject to the tussle and
play of ideologies, even when we least suspect it;
and at least we have learned this much from
Marxism, that we accept our involvement
even our implication in our social context and
in history.
But this does not remove our responsibility.
This, to me, is the key to the intellectual's
role, both within the general processes of change
in which all individuals and societies are engaged,
and in the specific convulsions of transition our
world is experiencing in this particular /zw de
siècle: that of responsibility. Responsibility to the
individual conscience as much as to the social
collective; responsibility to history (that is, not
only to the present, but to past and future);
responsibility towards those values which guar¬
antee the compass of our humanity: freedom,
truth, justice. And it also means a responsibility
against whatever threatens to diminish that
humanity, which would include a responsibility
against ideology, against dogma. The intellectual,
today, is no longer only the one who says,
"J'accuse!", but the one who affirms, "J'assume
ma responsabilité".
At the very least this assumption of respon¬
sibility by the intellectual towards the processes
of progress would imply the elimination (in
oneself; in one's society) of mentalities and atti¬
tudes resulting from our adherence, for too
long, to the divisions of Empire and Barbar¬
ians, West and East, North and South: in the
North, the belief in superiority and in centrism;
in the South, the victim mentality, which makes
it too easy always to blame others for all predica¬
ments and problems. Once again, both these
attitudes are demonstrated quite spectacularly in
South Africa today; but once again the virtue of
this demonstration is its applicability to most of
the world's societies, in one form or another
ranging from ethnic jokes to genocide.
The lure of power
In the exercise of this responsibility the greatest
danger is, once again, the lure of power. In the
old South Africa, the white minority dictated its
master narratives and used its control of the
media and the means of cultural production to
help maintain its political control. There are
signs, in the transitional South Africa, of cultural
commissars trying to impose their ideological
position (curiously and anachronistically Stal¬
inist in many respects) on others in order to
turn the tables on the "opposition". Even if it is
not hard to understand the justification of such
a démarche, it goes without saying that this
simply perpetuates the principle of binarity
which was the undoing of the ancien regime.
The intellectual notably the intellectual in
her or his manifestation as writer should
clearly distinguish between two separate possible
roles to be played: first, as writer, in which the
act of creating itself predominates, with its
emphasis on individual experience and the indi¬
vidual conscience, the individual responsibility
towards excellence (this is the context within
which Marquez characterized the writer as rev¬
olutionary in terms of "writing as well as he
can"); second, as "vedette", which is the conse¬
quence of the first. (As a result of writing well
whatever that is perceived to be in a given situ¬
ation she or he acquires notoriety, which can
be used as a base for influencing the cultural/
social/political debate.) It is imperative to dis¬
tinguish between the two.
The first role holds only the danger of with¬
drawal; but that, it seems to me, is a danger
society has to accept as a given; it is the price to
be paid for the possibility (never the guarantee)
of cultural quality. For it is simply not possible
to "program" writing or any cultural activity
for that matter; the whole value of the indi¬
vidual in society is vested in this. And in South
Africa it is significant that, after decades of
"struggle literature" (much of it, I should point
out, remarkably good by any standards) the
African National Congress itself is turning more
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
1 1 , ( '
:r-~ "^ M
¡So - , '«ci -r^rs©'^
^«S
lïiliM
:_f
;
. .
-
-
i n
and more towards this aspect of individual
unpredictability and responsibility in cultural
activity.
The second function of the writer as "cul¬
tural worker" holds the real danger of involve¬
ment in power strategies. It cannot be shirked, and
it cannot be denied. The nature of our media-
informed world is such that tremendous poten¬
tial power is lodged within this function. For
that very reason, once again, one's basic appeal is
to responsibility in respect of each of the social
and moral forces I have outlined earlier.
Ultimately, then, the differences we impose
on our categorization of North and South are
both confirmed and transcended within the
processes of cultural progress. Through the cre¬
ative exploration of our different situations we
affirm our common humanity; through our
dedication to mutual excellence, we foster a
mutual respect; through our involvement in
humanity we create space for the individual;
through our assumption of responsibility we
allow each other to assume our full worth as
members of the human family. Progress is the
same for all, and never the same; it demands
awareness of difference and diversity as a starting
point, yet it never fails to affirm that as women
and men of South and North we are all as weak
as the weakest among us, as strong as the
strongest. I am, we are; we are, I am.
Untitled collage
(1992, 160 x 120 cm)
by the French artist
Pascal Lièvre.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS
40
NEW MEMBER STATES
The number of Unesco Member
States now stands at 1 8 1 (as of 28
October 1993). Recent signatories
of the Organization's Constitution
include Slovakia, the Czech
Republic, Tajikistan, Bosnia and
Herzegovina, the former Yugoslav
Republic of Macedonia,
Turkmenistan, Eritrea, the
Solomon Islands, Andorra,
Uzbekistan and the Pacific island
state of Niue.
SCHOOLS FOR ONE WORLD
UNESCO's Associated Schools
Project (ASP), which now
encompasses more than 2,900
establishments in 1 16 countries,
celebrated its 40th anniversary on
1 2 September 1 993. A major
international network, ASP seeks
through student exchange
programmes, teacher training,
publications, audiovisual materials
and other initiatives to create
citizens conscious of their
responsibilities as members of the
world community. In the past ten
years it has concentrated on four
main areas: world problems and
the role of the United Nations
system in solving them; human
rights; intercultural learning; and
concern for the environment.
THE INTERNATIONAL
PEACE BOOK
Over 200 political leaders and
distinguished religious, scientific
and cultural personalities from 72
countries have contributed
messages to an "International
Peace Book" that was presented at
a ceremony held on 12 October at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris.
Nobel Peace Prize laureates
Mother Teresa, Rigoberta Menchu
and Polish President Lech Walesa,
as well as Pope John Paul II and
former Senegalese President
Leopold Sedar Senghor are among
the Book's signatories, who are all
committed to the idea that "Peace
should no longer be defined by the
absence of war and violence. ... It
should become a goal that is
voluntarily fixed and continually
reformulated." Other contributors
to the Book, whose Honorary
President is Federico Mayor,
Director-General of Unesco,
include the Lebanese writer Amin
Maalouf, the American opera
singer Barbara Hendricks, United
Nations Secretary-General
Boutros Boutros-Ghali, the late
Willy Brandt, and Johan Jörgen
Holst, the Norwegian Minister of
Foreign Affairs, who played a vital
role in the recent Israeli-Palestinian
accord.
INTERNATIONAL YOUTH AND
STUDENT CARDS
More than 3 million students and
young people under 26 years of
age, 60 per cent of them
Europeans, carry cards sponsored
by the Federation of International
Youth Travel Organizations
(FIYTO) and the International
Student Travel Conference (ISTC)
that provide travel discounts and
facilitate access to museums and
other cultural leisure activities. On
8 October in Vienna, Unesco
signed a memorandum of
understanding with the two bodies
that is designed to promote a
wider use of the cards. The aim is,
by making the cards more widely
accessible, to strengthen
exchanges between young people
worldwide.
BIOETHICS COMMITTEE HOLDS
ITS FIRST MEETING
The first session of the
International Bioethics Committee
(IBC) was held at Unesco
Headquarters on 1 5 and 16
September. At the meeting, some
40 leading scientists discussed a
report on the human genome
prepared by an interdisciplinary
task force headed by Noëlle
Lenoir, President of the IBC and a
member of the French
Constitutional Council. The
Committee asked its Bureau to
study the form and content of a
possible international instrument
for the protection of the human
genome and to write a report on
the four topics which it will
examine at its second session in
1994: the current state of
knowledge in genetics; genetics of
populations, development and
demography; therapeutic
applications of genetic research;
and genetic screening and
individual genetic testing element
of freedom or source of
constraint?
COMMENTARY
by
Federico
Mayor
This article is one of a
series in which the
Director-General of
Unescorecently elected
for a second term by the
Organization's General
Conferencesets out his
thinking on matters of
current concern
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
LISTEN FOR THE STIRRINGS OF NEW LIFP
THE closing years of the twentieth century mark a turning
point in history. Fault-lines are appearing in the old world
order, and as it breaks up it is as if history were subject to
the laws of plate tectonics.
We cannot stand idly by as passive witnesses to the rapid
changes whereby our world is adapting to economic, social,
and cultural upheavals of unprecedented scale. We have a duty
to find new ways of freeing the human race from the threats and
fears of this fin de siècle.
Of course, all this is nothing new the world has long known
the scourges of poverty and underdevelopment, illiteracy and
unequal access to health care, war and genocide, hunger and
malnutrition, massive indebtedness, unemployment, lack of
equal opportunities for women, the scandal of great wealth
alongside dire poverty, the population explosion and strife
between communities. I, for one, shall not sing the praises of the
1 960s and 1 970s. For the vast majority those were dark years in
which the voice of human suffering was smothered under the
heavy blanket of dictatorship and totalitariansim.
But today we are seeing the hope born of democratic revo¬
lution, in the East and in the South, being transformed into anx¬
iety and despair, as reality falls short of expectations, as human
aspirations are overwhelmed by the immensity of the problems
that lie ahead, as development founders in so many parts of the
world; and above all as the quest for happiness meets with failure
in the most developed countries, where tried and trusted proce¬
dures and mechanisms have ceased to be effective.
We must "invent" the future; we must find imaginative ways
of redistributing both work and leisure. We must learn to give of
ourselves. We must be prepared to make sacrifices in the search
for new strategies. We must find a better way to share our one
remaining unspoiled treasure our future.
In so-called "traditional" societies economic activity was
regarded as merely one aspect of a wider existence. It was part of
a daily routine conditioned by the rhythms of nature, faith and
social relations. Over the centuries the means of production
developed or were transformed slowly, in harmony with the
seasons and the environment, in concert with myths and customs.
Individual initiative formed an integral part of the collective
enterprise. Each member of the community was guided in his or
her behaviour by an understanding of the common culture and
standards of the group.
The first signs of the rapid disruption of this balance appeared
in Europe. With advances in science and technology and the
advent of industrialized society, a social system and methods of
production were developed that led increasingly to the separa¬
tion of the individual from the community, of culture from
nature, of work from leisure. Human beings were themselves
fragmented, with the growing specialization of productive labour.
By its progressive reduction of human relations to quantifiable
factors, the industrial revolution began a standardizing process
in which the natural differences between individuals were replaced
by a heightened potential for social conflict; in which human
beings could be treated as abstractions added and subtracted,
counted and manipulated. In short, spiritual and cultural values
no longer played a part in the material world.
No doubt the power and influence wielded over material
things by industrialized society derive in part from the logic of
this process whereby complex entities are systematically reduced
to simpler and simpler elements. Meanwhile, we have lost a
world vision, a feeling of respect for our neighbour and a sense
of community.
The gulf is not only between nations, but within nations. In the
developing countries, in fact, the polarization of society, something
virtually unknown in the past, is widening the gap between the
incomes of certain privileged classes and those of the rest. And so
it is that disparities arise in opportunities for education and par¬
ticipation in the cultural and political life of a country.
THE POET'S MESSAGE
Can we allow ourselves to remain unmoved by the mute con¬
frontation between the worlds of rich and poor? The American
philosopher Hannah Arendt wrote of a "culture crisis". But a cul¬
ture crisis is a social crisis, a crisis of the values on which society
is founded. Work is becoming increasingly scarce due to increases
in productivity. Unless it is shared it is hard to see how a culture
based on industrial activity could fail to be in crisis. Sharing can give
new meaning to the idea of development in industrial societies, by
endowing it with an educating and civilizing function to replace
the rigid concept of the three stages of life: youth, a time to learn;
maturity, a time to produce; old age, a time to rest and await
death. Tomorrow's culture must enrich all life's activities, at every
stage of life's journey.
In affluent societies the sense of life's possibilities has been lost
and must be found again. But how are we to grapple with the
misery confronting the poor countries of the world, in which the
gulf between rich and poor is even wider, even more unbridgeable,
where extreme poverty can block all hope of access to stability in
working life and to fulfilment as a human being? In these countries
access to forms of culture that depend on investment in science,
technology and education is usually out of the question.
Yunus Emre, the great Turkish poet of Anatolia, whose 750th
anniversary we celebrated last year, once wrote: "Our only enemy
is hostility itself. We bear a grudge against no-one. For us
humankind is indivisible." Across the centuries, it was a man of sci¬
ence, the anthropologist Claude Lévi-Strauss, who was to respond
to the poet's message of universality through a lesson in diversity
which he gave in a famous study prepared for UNESCO, Race and
History: "It is diversity itself which must be saved," he wrote, "not
the outward and visible form in which each period has clothed that
diversity, and which can never be preserved beyond the period
which gave it birth. We must therefore listen for the stirrings of new
life, foster latent potentialities, and encourage every natural incli¬
nation for collaboration which the future history of the world may
hold. . . . Tolerance is a dynamic attitude, consisting in the anti¬
cipation, understanding and promotion of what is struggling into
being. We can see the diversity of human cultures behind us,
around us and before us."
It is by grasping the two handles universality and diver¬
sity that make up the uniqueness of culture that we may remain
faithful to the message of the poet and the logic of the scientist.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
A defence ofthe intellect
byAldous Huxley
The International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation, Unesco's
forerunner, held a meeting on "the
future ofthe European mind" in
Parisfrom 16-18 October 1933 at
which Aldous Huxley inveighed
against the degradation of
contemporary thought. Thefamous
British novelist, who had recently
publishedBrwe New World (1932),
passionatelyyet humorously
defended the intellectual values
threatened by the extension ofmass
culture. He spoke in French, the
language in which, as he said, "the
mind and rational goodwill ofthe
age ofVoltairefound expression and
travelledfrom one end ofEurope to
the other."
+ 1
We are here to discuss the cur¬
rent state of the European
mind and how to preserve
what has been achieved by it. A look at
contemporary intellectual life (I am
speaking of the life of the masses, not of the
elites) brings out two extremely impor¬
tant facts: firstly, that intelligence and its
instrument, logic, are generally denigrated;
and secondly, that what I may call the con¬
temporary lifestyle is remarkably vulgar
and crude. Improving the lifestyle is desir¬
able in itself. We appreciate intuitively that
beauty is superior to ugliness. The reaf¬
firmation of intellectual values is desir¬
able in itself, but also and especially
because it is only in the name of intellec¬
tual values such as truth and justice
that the countries of Europe can reach
agreement. People only make sacrifices
and as Mr. Benda so rightly said yesterday,
sacrifices must be made for things they
believe in and to which they attribute
supreme value.
Anti-intellectualism is already an old
movement, and it shows itself in various
forms Bergsonism, Freudianism and
Watson's behaviourism. There is no point in
summarizing these doctrines, since
everyone here is quite familiar with them.
What interests us is to find out why anti-
intellectualism has enjoyed and still enjoys
such great popularity, and secondly how it
can be combated. The reasons for its pop¬
ularity are, unfortunately, all too obvious. It
flatters men's passions, particularly lazi¬
ness: it is so difficult to reason, so easy to
trust to instinct and intuition. If it were a
matter of laziness the harm would not be
very serious. But anti-intellectualism also
flatters more dangerous passions. It is
admirably well adapted to justifying the
complex ofhatreds and vanities that is the
very essence of nationalism. National-
Socialist philosophy, for example, continu¬
ally speaks of "particular truths" as opposed
to the mundane objective truths of intel¬
lectuals. Then there are Nordic instincts,
the infallible intuitions of blond men.
How can we combat anti-intellectu¬
alism? How can we reinforce that faith in
Aldous Huxley (1894-1963).
reason without which the political unity of
Europe cannot be achieved? First ofall there
is logic. All anti-intellectual doctrines are
self-destructive. For example, you may say
with Freud that all intellectual construc¬
tions are merely rationalizations of con¬
scious or unconscious desires. Very well.
But your own anti-intellectualist doctrine is
one of these intellectual constructions. You
find yourself on the horns of a dilemma:
either your doctrine is true, in which case it
represents no more than the expression of
a repressed, probably sexual, desire, and
has no objective meaning, or it has an
objective meaning, in which case it is false.
Unfortunately logic has very little influ¬
ence with the masses. The masses need to
be spoken to in terms of absolute
authority, as Jehovah spoke to the
Israelites, or in parables, that is in terms of
art. Children and the feeble-minded and
unfortunately there are many of those
are the only people who can be spoken to
with authority, and that authority must
first be possessed. The various national
educational systems are not under our
control, and we are not demagogues or
rabble-rousers. So the only way we can
influence people's minds is by persua¬
sion that is, by art. Logic destroys anti-
intellectualism. But the masses only accept
this logic when it is embodied in a work of
art. Unfortunately works of art cannot be
produced to order, as Napoleon and the
Bolsheviks painfully discovered. All we
can do is hope. An intellectual artist may
appear and then again he may not. It is
not within our power to create him. We
can organize everything, except art.
BAD LITERATURE IN INDUSTRIAL
QUANTITIES
I now come to the second observation we
have made in examining the modern
world. Our times are anti-intellectualist;
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
V
they are also vulgar. The contemporary
lifestyle is frankly disgusting. We live on a
diet ofPonson du Terrail and Paul de Kock.
The quite specific vulgarity ofour era shows
itself in the quite specific vulgarity of our
popular art, which is also the cause of it. As
nearly always happens, the movement is
circular and vicious. What are the causes of
this vulgarity? They are partly economic
and demographic, partly intellectual and
aesthetic. Industrial development and the
development ofvirgin territory in the New
World have led to a sudden expansion of
Europe's population, which has more than
doubled in one century. Next comes pri¬
mary education for all. An enormous poten¬
tial readership has been created, forwhom
entrepreneurs have set up a new industry
the reading matter industry. Now this
reading matter could only be and will only
be ofvery poor quality. Why? It is a matter
of arithmetic. The number ofwriters with
artistic talent is always very limited. So it fol¬
lows that at any time the bulk of contem¬
porary literature has always been bad. Now
the amount ofliterature produced annually
has grown faster than the population. There
are twice as many ofus today as there were
at the beginning of the nineteenth century.
But the number of printed words we con¬
sume each year is at least fifty if not a
hundred times greater than the number
consumed by our great-grandparents.
Hence it follows that the percentage ofbad
literature in the total must be higher than
ever. Europeans have got into the habit of
reading all the time. It is a vice, like smoking
cigarettes or rather, perhaps, like smoking
opium or taking to cocaine; for this litera¬
ture, which is almost all bad, is a mental
substitute for narcotic and hallucinatory
drugs. Europe is being fed stuffed, one
might say with tenth-rate literature.
This is completely new. In the past,
people were only familiar directly or indi¬
rectly with a few books, but they were of
very high quality. English people, for
instance, until quite recently grew up with
the Bible and Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress,
both of unmatched purity and nobility of
style. Nowadays, they grow up with the
Daily Express, magazines and detective
stories. Universal education has had the
lamentable result that instead of occa¬
sionally reading masterpieces people con¬
tinually read rubbish.
There is another very alarming phe
nomenon: language itself is being cor¬
rupted by advertisers. The disease is not as
far advanced in France as in America and
England, where advertising has already
tainted a great many of the noblest words.
For example, the word "service" crops up
again and again in English-language
advertising. People talk about the manu¬
facture of pills and canned foods as they
once used to talk about the work of Saint
Francis ofAssisi. A man sells you a can of
beans with a 20 per cent net profit. Fine.
But it is unacceptable that he should talk
to you with clerical unction about the "ser¬
vice" in the Christian sense of the word
he has done you. The same thing has hap¬
pened to many other words. Beauty, Grace,
Adventure, Virile, Romantic a whole
vocabulary of splendid words has been
used in advertising and thus made sus¬
pect. It is reaching the point where people
cannot hear these words without imme¬
diately reacting with cynicism. It is very dif¬
ficult to separate words from the things
they signify; and when words are tainted as
they are every day, the values are tainted
also. Every language is a vehicle for the
best traditions of the race: ifyou ruin this
vehicle, as advertisers are doing, you
destroy these traditions.
THE CATERWAULING
OF POPULAR MUSIC
What has happened in the realm of litera¬
ture has happened also in that ofpopular
music. But here the invention of talking
machines rather than primary education
has created a big audience of listeners. (It
is, by the way, the invention of the rotary
press that has led to the current growth
of the literature industry.) Listening matter
is needed for this huge audience: it is man¬
ufactured, and inevitably it is ofvery poor
quality. But in the case of popular music
things are complicated by aesthetic mat¬
ters. For the last 130 years musicians have
greatly developed the technical means
used to express their feelings. Beethoven
created a whole repertoire of technical
means to express the passions means
unknown to even his most brilliant pre¬
decessors. The enrichment of musical
technique progressed throughout the
nineteenth century. Berlioz, Wagner, Verdi,
the Russians, Debussy all contributed
new means of expression to the common
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
stock. Naturally the feelings these com¬
posers aimed to express did not always
have the purity and nobility that charac¬
terize Beethoven's. Wagner, especially, gave
music the power to express and with
great power ofartistic persuasion things
that are fundamentally despicable. Popular
composers have learned their craft from
the great artists. Thanks to Beethoven,
Berlioz, Wagner, Rimski-Korsakov and
Debussy, they are now in a position to
express with gripping power the basest
emotionsthe most abject sentimentality,
the most animal sexuality and the most
frenetic collective joy. . . .
The disease is not completely curable,
but I believe it can be mitigated, firstly
through education. We pay too little atten¬
tion to the development of taste and a crit¬
ical faculty; or ifwe try to develop them, we
always choose remote, outdated exam¬
ples. If I had to teach young people the
art of telling beauty from ugliness, the real
from the imitation, I would try to choose
my examples from the contemporary
world. I would focus their critical facul¬
ties on politicians' speeches and on adver¬
tising. I would get them to hear the dif¬
ferences in quality between a piece ofjazz
and one of Beethoven's late quartets. I
would get them to read some detective
story, and then Crime and Punishmentor
The Possessed.
So much forwhat can be organized. But
there are also forces that cannot be orga¬
nized, and this brings us back again to art.
If fine art remains pure, all is not lost. There
will always be an elite to respond to the
appeal of this art, to let itself be shaped by
it, to experience its style. Artists have an
enormous responsibility. It is for them,
especially now that organized religions have
lost their power, to undertake the task of
restating, revivifying and preserving spiri¬
tual values. If they compromise with the
world, in the Christian sense of the word,
they lose not only their artistic souls but
also the souls of a whole potential elite. ^ ¡*
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
International
Volunteer Day
by BillJackson
44
Eachyear since it was established
on the initiative of the United
Nations Volunteers Programme
(UNV) in 1985, International Volunteer
Day has been celebrated in at least
ninety countries to honour the millions
ofvolunteers all over the world who give
their time to help their fellow human
beings.
At a point when the trend in many
countries is to cut back on social ser¬
vices they once provided, international,
national and local volunteer organiza¬
tions in both the North and the South are
playing a vital role.
In one developed country Aus¬
tralia the New South Wales Volunteer
Centre describes volunteers as "the
people who deliver meals, serve at
school canteens, raise funds to buy com¬
munity equipment, run clubs, watch
neighbourhoods, fight bush fires,
operate drop-in centres and carry out a
host of other services which the com¬
munity demands but could often not
afford without the free help they pro¬
vide."
In developing countries it is some¬
times asked whether there is any real
need for international volunteers and
whether volunteering may not be an
outdated import from colonial times.
Sadly, one has only to witness the degree
ofneed and suffering in countries such
as Angola, Somalia and Bosnia to realize
how much there is for such volunteers to
do.
Some 120 countries on the long haul
to development are happy to welcome
specialists from the UN Volunteers Pro¬
gramme and other international bodies
that work side by side with local orga¬
nizations. "It is a matter of pride," said
the governor of the Punjab (Pakistan)
on International Volunteer Day 1992,
"that nearly 3,500 voluntary social wel¬
fare agencies, comprising hundreds of
Top, a UN Volunteer (at left of photo)
supervises the unloading of sacks of grain in
Afghanistan. Above, two Volunteers, one
British and one Dutch, explain the electoral
process to Cambodian villagers through an
interpreter before the elections of May
1993. With the help of almost 50,000
specially trained Cambodians, 465
Volunteers from 45 countries carried out a
programme of civic education, registered
4.7 million voters and supervised the polling
stations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
thousands of dedicated and selfless
workers all over the Punjab, are engaged
in voluntary social service and as such
supplementing government's efforts in
every conceivable field."
The past two years have brought
major changes for international orga¬
nizations that, like UNV, send volun¬
teers all over the world. The sheer scale
and frequency of famines and refugee
crises have required programmes that
had been almost exclusively devoted to
long-term development to set up spe¬
cialist humanitarian relief units.
The current trend is towards having
volunteers who serve in developing
countries concentrate on helping local
communities to manage their resources
to the best effect. Thus we can expect to
see more and more emphasis on vol¬
unteers from outside working on a peer
basis with local people in such fields as
adult literacy, youth initiatives and pop-
Above, a Volunteer from Myanmar (centre)
with her opposite number during a
vaccination drive in the Comoro Islands.
Below, in Bhutan a Ugandan Volunteer
shows students how an anemometer works.
ulation and family life education as well
as the protection of human rights and
work on the cultural aspects of devel¬
opment such as the restoration of
archaeological sites of national impor¬
tance.
Unesco Director-General Federico
Mayor and United Nations Volunteers
Programme Executive Co-ordinator
Brenda Gael McSweeney have launched
a joint appeal calling for the develop¬
ment of international volunteering.
Noting that "Volunteers are urgently
needed change-agents and peace-
builders," they call on "governments,
United Nations agencies, non-govern¬
mental organizations and decision¬
makers everywhere to take advantage
of International Volunteer Day to intro¬
duce practical measures to promote and
facilitate voluntary service. There was
never greater need, nor opportunity, to
mobilize volunteers for international
programmes of all kinds. Volunteers are
an unparalleled source of energy, action
and hope. Their efforts must be encour¬
aged in everyway possible, so that they
make the world a better place and
inspire the next generation by their
example."
BILL JACKSON,
of Ireland, is chief of the external relations division
of the United Nations Volunteers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Thepainted caves of
MogOO byJosé Serra-Vega
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
With its paths shaded by slender
poplars and its cool, swift-
flowing streams, the oasis of
Dunhuang is an island of greenery in an
otherwise arid landscape on the edge of
the Gobi and Takla Makan deserts in
China's Gansu province. Some twenty- five
kilometres to the southeast are the famous
Mogao caves 492 temples and sanctu¬
aries hewn into a 1,600-metre-Iong stretch
of a sheer cliff overlooking the Dachuan
river. They are a unique record of a period
when Buddhist culture in China was at its
height, and the Tang dynasty, which
reigned from 618 to 907, was at the apogee
of its power. In 1987 they were placed on
Unesco's World Heritage List.
The area's history is closely associated
with the first Chinese raids against the
nomads of central Asia at a time when the
struggle to control trade routes and the
Hexi corridor sparked endless clashes
between the emperors of China and
nomadic tribes of Huns, Mongols and
Turks.
A long section of the Great Wall
defended the empire's northern border.
Around 117 B.C. this line of fortifications
housed two garrisons, one ofwhich, based
at Dunhuang, was for several centuries
the last bastion of Chinese civilization at
the empire's westernmost frontier. Beyond
stretched an immense salt desert so hot
that camels were provided with patches of
leather to protect their knees from being
scorched by the sand when they knelt
down.
A CULTURAL CROSSROADS
The two busiest roads plied by merchants
travelling from the West to China followed
the lines of oases that stretched to the
north and south of central Asia. One fol¬
lowed the course ofthe Tarim river on the
edge of the Takla Makan desert; the other
ran through the oases fed by melting ice
from the Kunlun mountain range. Both
converged on Dunhuang.
Dunhuang is strategically situated at
an intersection of the Silk Roads which
from the time of the Han dynasty (206
B.C-220 A.D.) brought China into contact
with the Indo-Iranian civilizations and
Mediterranean Europe. For more than a
thousand years it was a busy frontier post
and trading settlement where caravans
came and went. It was also an active Bud¬
dhist centre.
At Dunhuang travellers wearied by the
harsh climate and attacks by desert looters
Below left, the entry to the Mogao caves.
Below right, inside Cave 296 (Northern
Chou dynasty), whose decoration is inspired
by the ¡ataka, narrations of former
incarnations of the Buddha.
found a garrison to protect them, com¬
fortable taverns and hospitable young
women. They could deposit or borrow
money and hire camels for the 1,700-kilo¬
metre trip to the capital of the empire.
There were warehouses where they could
store their merchandise and many
craftsmen were ready to serve them. Pay¬
ment could be made in gold, currency,
textiles or grain. Debtors were penalized
with high interest rates and, in serious
cases, confiscation of their property.
A RELIGIOUS MICROCOSM
Cut off from the rest of the empire for long
periods of time, Dunhuang was a cos¬
mopolitan enclave thronged with way¬
farers of diverse origins and callings. The
intensity of its economic life was matched
by the religious activities of the monks
and missionaries who gathered there
Buddhists, Manichaeans, Nestorians and
Muslims.
Buddhism originated in India during
the fifth century B.C. and reached China
during the Han dynasty. But Buddhist cul¬
ture, thought and art only began to spread
extensively throughout central Asia when
it was encouraged by the rulers of the
Kushan empire during the first four cen¬
turies of the Christian era. The Mogao
caves are just one link albeit the most
famous in a long chain ofBuddhist cave-
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
temples stretching from Afghanistan to
the heart of China.
According to an inscription deciphered
at Dunhuang, the first cave may have been
hewn on the orders of a monk named
Luzun in 361 A.D. almost a century
before Buddhism was recognized as
China's official religion in 444 A.D. This
was the first step in the construction of
the huge cave-temple complex, a task that
took nearly a thousand years (from the
fifth to the fourteenth centuries).
Throughout this period, missionary
monks who journeyed along the Silk Roads
from India to convert China to Buddhism
would meet Chinese monks and pilgrims
travelling in the opposite direction, seeking
the roots of their religion in India. To avoid
the Himalayas the pilgrims had to make a
long and dangerous detour through a vast
expanse ofunsafe or hostile territory. They
trekked westward across the deserts and
high plateaux of Tian Shan, the Pamirs
and the Hindu Kush before reaching the
Ganges valley. After purifying themselves
in the river's sacred waters at Benares and
visiting the site of the Buddha's Enlight¬
enment at Bodh Gaya, the travellers would
study Sanskrit and learn about the mys¬
teries of Buddhist thought before setting
out on their return journey laden with
relics and holy books.
A TREASURE TROVE OF BUDDHIST ART
The Mogao caves bear witness to a number
of important episodes in the history of
central Asia. The Tang dynasty's powerful
grip on the Silk Roads during the seventh
century is reflected in colossal statues of
the Buddha and in frescoes illustrating
transcendental doctrines. Tantric themes
began to appear when the site was occu¬
pied by Tibetans between 790 and 851,
increasing in number after the conquest of
Gansu by the Tangut and the proliferation
of lamaistic sects under the Western Hsia
dynasty, which ruled from 1036 to 1227.
This ensemble ofstatues and paintings
deeply rooted in the events of Chinese
history is also a treasure trove of a thou¬
sand years of Buddhist art. Each temple is
entered through a chapel leading to a wide
corridor. The lofty roofs are conical. Mag¬
nificent frescoes depict the birth, life and
death of the Buddha and his successive
incarnations; impressive processions of
bodhisattvas and other Buddhist saints;
dancing angels and magicians; disciples
and believers; palaces and monasteries in
the midst of awe-inspiring landscapes;
dragons, elephants, wild beasts and bou¬
quets and garlands of flowers.
The caves are covered by some 45,000
square metres of splendid frescoes and
house over 2,400 painted statues of out¬
standing refinement and beauty.
A portrait of King Uygur,
the principal donor of Cave 409 (Western
Hsia dynasty), shows him holding a
perfume-burner as he steps forward to pay
tribute to Buddha.
The paintings and sculptures display
' an elegant blend of Hindu, Persian, Indo-
Hellenic and Greco-Roman influences
combined with characteristic features of
Chinese art, which are prevalent in the
treatment of architecture, landscape,
clothing, facial expressions and women's
hair styles.
The thousand or so caves must have
been a spectacular site at the height of their
splendour during the late seventh and early
eighth centuries. Some were perhaps the
work of private individuals, but most of
them must have been financed by pow¬
erful political clans whose exploits are com¬
memorated by carved stelae. Others were
made by Buddhist communities dedicated
to the worship of the household god and
other divinities, to providing aid after nat¬
ural disasters, and to the organization of
spring banquets, funerals and cultural activ¬
ities ofvarious kinds.
Invasions, the turbulent history of
medieval China and natural wear-and-
tear have taken their toll of the temples.
Looting and profanation were only halted
in recent times. The effigies of the Buddha
were coated with soot and smoke when
troops of the White Russian army
retreating from Siberia spent the winter
of 1920 in the caves. Considering the van¬
dalism they have suffered, it is a miracle
that nearly half of them have survived.
Since 1949, the Dunhuang Cultural Relics
Research Institute has been engaged in on-
site conservation, research and analysis,
and the only invaders have been tourists.
In the late nineteenth century the dis¬
asters and strife that engulfed China
brought a flood of refugees to Dunhuang.
In 1900 a Taoist monk named Wang Yuan
Lu (Wang Gulu) attempted to restore one
of the Mogao temples with his own slender
resources, discovering in the process a
walled-up hiding place where monks had
hidden some 30,000 manuscripts and
relics when the site was invaded by the
Xiasinl036.
The British explorer Sir Aurel Stein
(1862-1943) heard of the discovery while
on an expedition to the Takla Makan oases
and in 1907 he visited Dunhuang and
studied the documents with mounting
excitement. The earliest text was a treatise
on Buddhist canon law translated by Xuan
Zhang, the most famous of the Buddhist
pilgrims who visited India during the sev¬
enth century. With it were fifth-century
scrolls written in Brahmi script, Tibetan
religious texts, paintings on silk and reli¬
gious banners. To general indifference,
3,000 scrolls and 6,000 manuscripts,
objects and paintings made their way to
the British Museum in London.
Aurel Stein was the first of a long line of
visitors to the caves. The French sinologist
Paul Pelliot examined some 20,000 old
documents by candlelight at the incredible
rate of a thousand per day until over¬
whelmed by fatigue and by dust from the
ancient manuscripts. He discovered
Tibetan manuscripts preserved between
two boards knotted together, Buddhist
poems, folktales, accounting ledgers and
other texts in Chinese, Sogdian, Uighur,
Khotanese, Kushan, Sanskrit, Hebrew and
Syriac. Some 4,000 of these documents
were removed to the Guimet Museum in
Paris.
When they heard of the interest for¬
eigners were showing in the Chinese her¬
itage, the authorities in Beijing ordered
10,000 documents to be brought to the
capital, but they were transported in such
unsatisfactory conditions that many of
them were lost en route. Others reap¬
peared in Berlin, Saint Petersburg and
Kyoto. Shortly afterwards, the market was
flooded with copies produced in Tianjin.
This extraordinary collection, now dis¬
persed, is vital evidence of the history of
Asia and especially of the spread of Bud¬
dhism in China under the Tang dynasty.
The documents and the cave-temples
where they were found are also the most
spectacular illustration of the cultural and
artistic exchanges that took place along
the Silk Roads.
JOSE SERRA-VEGA,
a Peruvian engineer and former staff member of
the United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP), has worked in the Indian sub-continent
on technologies geared to environmental
conservation. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS OF THE WORLD
by Calum Wise
PAROLES DEVOILEES.
An anthology of contemporary Turkish
short stories by women writers.
Edited by Nedim Giirsel.
278 pp. Arcantère/UNESCO Publishing.
Unesco Collection of Representative
Works. (In French).
'Women's writing is a specific form of
writing," claims Nedim Giirsel in her fore¬
word to this anthology although no-one,
in Turkish or any other language, has ever
been able to define exactly what it is. One
is on much firmer ground if one asserts
that there is a specific Turkish women's
literature (that is, one written by women).
This book is a proofof it. The authors of the
stories in Paroles dévoilées ("Unveiled
Words") are outside the currents ofmilitant
feminism and a modern, theoretical
approach to literature. Rather, their work
provides an intimate, introspective
glimpse of family life. They remain rooted
in Turkish soil (like Yasar Kemal's Mehmed)
and in contemporary Turkish life, yet their
world has affinities with those ofKatherine
Mansfield and Virginia Woolf.
There have been Turkishwomenwriters
who were militant socialists and repub¬
lican activists, but the sixteen authors
selected here by Nedim Giirsel are not
among them. All but one were born
between 1925 and 1957, making them the
heirs and beneficiaries of Mustafa Kemal
Ataturk's Republic, which was founded in
1923. As if to give this first generation of
women writers a certain amount of sym¬
bolic significance, the collection opens with
a short story by Halide Edip Adivar, an early
twentieth-century "ideological" novelist.
The harsh yet sensitive tone of these short
stories, often narrated in the first person,
introduces the reader to an objective fic¬
tional world where the events of everyday
life upstage political and national ones.
MEMORIA DE AMERICA EN
LA POESÍA. ANTOLOGÍA
1492-1992.
Poems selected by Fernando Ainsa and
Edgar Montiel.
3 1 3 pp. Unesco Publishing.
Unesco Collection of Representative
Works. (In Spanish).
Last year, Unesco organized a series of
events to mark the "Fifth Centenary of the
Encounter between Two Worlds", com-
_ _ memorating the European discovery of
^O America. The Unesco Courier devoted its
*"+* i-i.nn
May issue, entitled "Rediscovering 1492",
to the subject. The articles described var¬
ious aspects of the encounter as well as
its intellectual, cultural and artistic reper¬
cussions, which have radically changed
our view of the world. One of the authors
concluded by suggesting that we should
"begin preparing now for the fifth cente¬
nary of... 1992."
Two other contributors to that issue
of the Courier, Fernando Ainsa and Edgar
Montiel, were probably thinking of both
present and future generations when they
put together this anthology of Spanish-
and Portuguese-language verse by ninety-
seven poets spanning nearly five centuries.
The volume contains works by interna¬
tionally-known figures who have been
translated into many languages, such as
Asturias, Borges, García Lorca, Lope de
Vega, Camôes, Neruda and Paz, as well as
poems by writers whose reputation is
mainly confined to their own countries. A
number ofanonymous Guaraní, Quechua
and Náhuatl works are also included.
Clearly there is a logic in this selection. It
seeks to engage readers' emotions as well
as their intellects by presenting a broad
spectrum of talents and sensibilities
focused on a central theme: America, the
source of one of the great myths of the
modern Western world that of the land of
plenty.*
AN ELUSIVE EAGLE SOARS
An anthology of modern Albanian
poetry.
Texts selected, translated and
presented by Robert Elsie.
213 pp. Forest Books/UNESCO. Unesco
Collection of Representative Works.
Albanian is currently spoken by some six
million people in the Balkans. The lan¬
guage is actually divided into two dialects,
with Gheg in use to the north and Tosk to
the south of the Shkumbin River, along
whose course ran the Roman Via Egnatia,
an extension of the Appian Way. The lit¬
erary language, which has become stan¬
dard throughout Albania as well as in
Kosovo and Macedonia, is a mixture of
both dialects, although approximately 80
per cent of it is based on Tosk. The earliest *
vernacular texts date back to the Counter-
Reformation, and the oldest known
Albanian poem was written in 1592.
Modern Albanian poetry came into exis¬
tence during the 1930s, when Lasgush
Poradeci and Migjeni broke with the tra¬
dition of romantic nationalism that had
dominated the genre until then. As Robert
Elsie points out in his introduction, "the
twentieth century arrived late in Albania."
The break with socialist realism was
another turning point. The new departure
sparked a lively literary debate pitting tra¬
ditionalist and innovative currents the
latter led by Ismail Kadare against each
other. This anthology recounts the difficult
birth and stormy history of modern
Albanian poetry with a representative selec¬
tion of verse written by poets within and
outside the country. It includes a helpful
introduction as well as an extensive bibli¬
ography of works published in five lan¬
guages. Mimoza Ahmeti (born 1963), is the
youngest poet whose work appears in the
collection. She wrote, "It would be awful/
Waking up the same every morning/But it
would be even worse/Seeing the end of the
day/With morning eyes".
* See The Discovery ofGuiana, by Sir Walter Raleigh,
who was a buccaneer in the service of Queen Eliz¬
abeth I of England, as well as an explorer. His
account was largely responsible for the spread and
success of this myth in Europe. This year, UNESCO
and Editions Retz (Paris) are publishing the first
unabridged French translation of Raleigh's work
under the title El Dorado.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
JAZZ
MICHEL CAMILO
Rendez-vous
Michel Camilo (piano),
Anthony Jackson (electric
double bass), Dave Weckl
(drums).
Columbia CD 473772 2
The Dominican pianist,
here accompanied by veteran
studio musicians Anthony
Jackson and Dave Weckl, is as
expressive, impulsive and
irrepressible as ever. This
wonderful recording features a
funky, highly inventive
interpretation of "Caravan", the
dreamy ballad "Remembrance",
and various numbers charged
with the prodigious energy that
is Camilo's hallmark.
GABRIELLE GOODMAN
Travel'm' Light
Gabrielle Goodman (vocals),
Don Alias (conga, percussion),
David Bunn and Barry Miles
(piano, synthesizer), Tony
Bunn, Anthony Cox and
Ruben Rodriguez (bass), Mike
Cain (piano), Kevin Eubanks
and Wolfgang Muthspiel
(guitar), Mark Feldman
(violin), Gary Thomas
(soprano and tenor sax),
Buddy Williams (drums).
JMT CD 514 006-2.
At a time when the great
jazz divas Billie Holiday,
Dinah Washington, Sarah
Vaughan, Ella Fitzgerald are
either dead or retired, it's
encouraging to see that a new
generation of singers is getting
ready to take over. Gabrielle
Goodman is one of them.
Travelin' Light is her first
recording. Goodman, who
started out singing gospel and
classical music, is astonishingly
smooth and natural. Her
ascents to the upper end of the
scale bring to mind the 1970s
pop singer Minnie Ripperton.
This is a splendid piece of work,
with inventive backing from
musicians Mike Cain and
Anthony Cox, who often
perform together, and Kevin
Eubanks and Gary Thomas,
who are well known for their
love of experimentation and
their refusal to make
concessions to commercialism.
RECENT RECORDS
by Isabelle Leymarie
MUSIC FROM
AROUND THE
WORLD
AZERBAIJAN
Azerbaijani Mugam
Bahram Mansuro (tor)
Anthology of Traditional
Musics
UNESCO/Auvidis CD D 8045.
Virtuoso Bahram Mansurov
performs this beautiful music,
which is based on a number of
contemplative mugams (a
mode similar to the maqam
and the raga), on a metallic-
sounding lute known as the tar.
Once a Persian satrapy and
ruled by the Mongols in the
thirteenth century, Azerbaijan
has produced many artists and
musicians, but the folk
traditions of this land in the
southeastern Caucasus are
little known. This fine
recording, which forms part of
the excellent series produced
by Unesco to preserve the
world's musical heritage, fills
some gaps in our knowledge.
BAHRAIN
Fidjeri: Songs of the Pearl Divers
Musics and Musicians of the
World collection
UNESCO/Auvidis CD D 8046.
The origins of these old
songs sung by the pearl divers
of Bahrain to accompany work
on board ship can be traced
back to mythology.
Accompanied by clapping,
drumming, small cymbals and
empty water jars, the songs
evoke the harshness of life at
sea and exalt the greatness of
Allah. They express the sense of
community of the pearl divers,
whose way of life and cultural
traditions are dying out as a
result of competition from
cultivated pearls and the
impact of technological
progress.
White Country Blues. 1926-1938
A Lighter Shade of Blue
Set of 2 CDs. Roots n' Blues
4728862.
This anthology presents a
number of white singers from
the southern United States who
flourished in the 1920s and
1930s. The performers are
unknown to the general public
even in their own country, yet
they laid the foundations for
the work of an entire
generation of folk and
hootenanny singers, including
Arlo Guthrie and Bob Dylan. It
is often hard to tell the
difference between them and
the black bluesmen by whom
they were strongly influenced.
With their nasal voices and
rustic instruments, they also
form part of the hillbilly
tradition. Some comic pieces,
such as "Adam and Eve",
performed by Mr. and Mrs.
Chris Bouchillon, came out of
vaudeville, which declined with
the growth of the record and
movie industries during the
1920s.
CLASSICAL MUSIC
MAURICE RAVEL
Daphnis et Chloé
London Symphony Orchestra
& Chorus conducted by Kent
Nagano.
Erato CD 4509-91712-2.
The Russian critic and
impresario Sergei Diaghilev
commissioned Ravel to
compose this splendid three-
part "choreographic
symphony", which is one of his
major works. The scenario is by
Michel Fokine, then the
choreographer of Diaghilev's
Ballets Russes. The lush
timbres and tonal colours
create a magical, dreamlike
atmosphere and an
extraordinary sensuality. "My
aim in writing it," said Ravel,
"was to compose a vast musical
fresco less concerned with
archaism than with fidelity to
the Greece of my dreams, a
Greece, moreover, that is fairly
close to that imagined and
painted by late eighteenth-
century French artists". This is
an outstanding version by the
London Symphony Orchestra
and Chorus, sensitively
conducted by Kent Nagano.
FRANZ SCHUBERT
Piano Sonatas D 664 & D 959
Elisabeth Leonskaja
Teldec CD 9031-74865-2.
Russian pianist Elisabeth
Leonskaja follows up her
recent, highly acclaimed
recordings of Brahms and Liszt
with this brilliant performance
of two Schubert sonatas that
were composed in 1819 and
1828 as the second part of a
trilogy that became famous.
These charming works, in
which Schubert has freed
himself from Beethoven's
influence and already
anticipates Bruckner, cast a
spell whose effects linger in the
memory.
J.F. REBEL
Les Elément.
Les Caractères de la Danse.
Le tombeau de M. de Lully
Les Musiciens du Louvre. Marc
Minkowski
Musifrance CD 2292-45974-2.
This recording is an
opportunity to enjoy the
little-known work of Jean-Féry
Rebel, a pupil of Lully. Rebel is
best remembered for his
courtly music and dances, but
his works are more profound
than their titles suggest. Les
Elémens opens with with a
bold, gripping, almost
Wagnerian "Cahos" which,
wrote the Mercure de France in
1738, "in the estimation
of the greatest Connoisseurs is
one of the most beautiful
symphonic works that exist in
this genre". Rebel himself said,
"I have dared to link the idea of
the confusion of the Elements
with that of confusion in
harmony". His undertaking
is totally successful. The
lightness of the delightful
"Rossignols" and the two
"Tambourins" from the same
suite is in marked contrast with
the introductory "Cahos". The
second part of the recording,
Les Caractères de la Danse,
consists of a series of dances
entitled "Bourrée", "Chaconne",
"Sarabande", and "Rigaudon".
They are less unusual than Les
Elémens, but just as
captivating.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1993
JANUARY. EXPLORING THE COSMOS. Interview with Hubert Reeves. The satellite era (N. Henbest).
Remote sensing the Indian experience (K. Karnik). Mars in fact and fiction (F. Leary). Face to face with
infinity (N. Rukavishnikov). A new view of the ocean (I. S. Robinson). Where are they now? (N.
Longdon). The extra-terrestrial junkyard (H. Brabyn). Greenwatch: People and paper (r. Bequette).
Culture and new-found freedoms (F. Mayor). Aurovilfe, the fulfilment of a dream (L. Solimán).
FEBRUARY. VIOLENCE. Interview with José Carreras. When cities run riot (L. J. D. Wacquant). The ruses
of racism (M. Wieviorka). A looming avalanche (A. Nuikin). Undertones of war (I. Colovic). A story too
far? (D. Hermant). Rock 'n' Revolt (I. Leymarie). The Seville Statement. The political solution (S. Na'ir).
Greenwatch: A budding romance between industry and the environment? (F. Bequette). Encouraging
diversity (F. Mayor). Heritage: Hadrian's Wall (A. Allan). The Indus Valley civilization cradle of
democracy? (S. A. Naqvi).
MARCH. PSYCHOANALYSIS: THE HIDDEN I. A letter from Freud to Einstein. Freud and Freudianism
(J. Hassoun). The inner adventure (O. Marc). How to say T (E. A. Lévy-Valensi). The Ajase complex (E.
Barrai). Africa: the healer's art (A.-M. Kaufmant). The talking cure (C. Azouri). Russia: the revenge of
subjectivity (A. Mikhalevich). Psychoanalysis in Quebec (M. Panaccio). Greenwatch: The right to clean air
(F. Bequette). War and peace in the minds of men (F. Mayor). Books: An atlas of world literature (E.
Reichmann).
APRIL. A TIME TO LOVE. . . Interview with Luc Ferry. In search of a new language (A. Brink). The love-
child (H. Lopes). The plight of the playboy in early spring (T. Ben Jelloun). Double portrait with a glass of
wine (L. Futoransky). From France, with love ((J. M. G. Le Clézio). The enchantecf garden (R. Depestre).
Why Ulysses? (M. Hussein). Miss Savitri and her shadow (N. Sibal). Behind the silver screen (J. Charyn).
Letter to a lovelorn girl (J. E. Adoum). Greenwatch: Can the world feed itself without chemicals? UNESCO
and the human genome (F. Mayor).
MAY. WATER OF LIFE. Interview with Charles Malamoud. Once upon a time in Sumer. . . (A. S. Issar). A
hidden asset (J. Margat). Running dry (S. Postel). Climate of uncertainty (I. A. Shiklomanov). Shifting
sands (H. Dregne). Crisis in the South (A. K. Biswas). The Aswan High Dam, 25 years on (M. Abu-Zeid
and M. B. A. Saam. The liquid of the gods (C. T. Tounounga). The forgotten ones (T. L. Douai). The role of
UNESCO (A. Szölli-Nagy). Greenwatch: Nature under threat (F. Bequette). Towards education for all (F.
Mayor).
JUNE. MINORITIES. Interview with Umberto Eco. What is a minority? (D. Meintel). Identity a card
with two faces (M. Peressini). Communities at the crossroads (E. Picard). The siren song of self-
determination (R. Lcmarchand). Guests, immigrants, minorities (R. Kastoryano). A sense of difference (Y.
Plasseraud). The Yugoslav quagmire (P. Garde). Passover in Sarajevo (L. Davico). Why? (B. Elnadi and A.
Rifaat). A protective framework (J. Symonides). Greenwatch: Environmental education in action (F.
Bequette). Heritage: Ait Ben Haddou, a desert-born model for urban design (L. Werner). Antwerp 93,
cultural capital of Europe.
JULY-AUGUST. WHAT IS MODERN? Interview with Oliver Stone. Modern times, new approaches. (A.
Wasscf). When less means more (A. Levy and P. Lionni). Micro-Mega (Y. Beauvais and A. Poulain). The
sky horizon (E. Petit). The devalued image (S. Younan). The apple of my eye (N. Merkado). The more
generation (R. F. Amonoo). The spare parts syndrome (B. Teo). Sound barriers (R. M. Schäfer). Architects
of disorder (F. and D. Montes). The third bank of the river (R. DaMatta). A world steeped in music (I.
Leymarie). Me and my shadow (S. Lane). Pieces of music, music of pieces (L. Milo). Rimbaud's quest (S.
Na'ir). Greenwatch: S.O.S. climate but don't worry (F. Bequette). They could have done so much, but
dared to do so little. . .' (F. Mayor). Heritage: Santísima Trinidad, memories of slavery and sugar (E.
Bailby). Traditions for Tomorrow (D. Gradis). Mahmoud Mokhtar (1891-1934) (M. Youssef). Books: A
voyage through European literature (E. Reichmann).
SEPTEMBER. RHYTHM, GESTURE AND THE SACRED. Interview with Andre Brink. The baby and the
saint (V. Marc). The heartbeat of day and night (Y. Tardan-Masquelier). Marcel Jousse, theorist of gesture.
Africa: the power of speech (A. Hampâté Bâ). Meaningful gestures (E. Gasarabwe-Laroche). Hands that
speak volumes (S. Na'ir). Testing times (A. Diouri). Greenwatch: Saving the Mediterranean (F. Bequette).
Human rights are universal (F. Mayor). Archives: A League of Minds (P. Valéry). Reaching the general
conscience (P. Valéry and H. Focillon).
OCTOBER. TIME TO DISARM. Interview with James D. Watson. Making disarmament work (D. David).
Wanted: a new philosophy (J. Klein). Europe after the Cold War (A. Zagorski). An appeal for non-violence
(F. Mayor). Investing in peace (J. Fontanel). The business of war (C. Carle). The bomb or peace (J. Singh).
Greenwatch: MAB at age 25 (M. Bâtisse). Culture first and last (F. Mayor). Archives: Goethe, a mind for
the universal. (T. Mann, G. Opresco, P. Valéry). Heritage: Portobelo, a bridge between two oceans (J. Scrra-
Vega). Books: C. Wise.
NOVEMBER. THE STORY OF NUMBERS. Interview with Amos Oz. The origin of numbers (T. Levy).
Sumerian sums (J. Ritter). The mathsticks of early China (Du Shi-ran). The star system (B. Riese). Making
something out of nothing (P.-S. Filliozat). Hindu-Arab roots of medieval Europe (A. Allard). Words,
gestures and symbols (P. Gcrdes and M. Cherinda). Greenwatch: UNESCO: Helping to save the Earth (F.
Bequette). Heritage: The valleys of the Niger (T. Dévisse). Archives: Miguel de Unamuno on the future of
culture. UNESCO's General Conference: United we stana. . . (F. Mayor). Solidarity and sharing: UNESCO's
programme for 1994-1995.
DECEMBER. THE MEANING OF PROGRESS: A NORTH-SOUTH DEBATE. A Western myth (R.
Debray). Metaphors should be made at home (D. J. Boorstin). Relative values (F. Lewis). The universal and
the particular (J. Ki-Zerbo). One world (A. Touraine). The shadow of oppression (T. Banuri). A shared
crisis (E. Morin). Asking the right questions (D. Padgaonkar). Assuming responsibility (A. Brink).
Greenwatch: Indigenous peoples: Treating nature with reverence (F. Bequette). 'Listen for the stirrings of
new life' (F. Mayor). Archives: A defence of the intellect (A. Huxley). Heritage: The painted caves of
Mogao Q. Serra-Vega). International Volunteer Day (B. Jackson). Books: (C. Wise).
5©
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: © Alain Corrigou, Quebec. Page 5: Ulf Anderson © Gamma, Paris. Page 7: J. Mimouni ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 9: André Magnin © Jean Pigozzi Collection. Page 1 0: © Giraudon, Louvre Museum,
Paris. Page 1 1 : © Giraudon/Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts, New York. Page 1 2: © Dr. H. R.
Sethna, UK. Page 13: © Lauros-Giraudon, Louvre Museum, Paris. Pages 14-15: © Edimedia/Snark Archives,
Paris. Page 16: ©Julio Garcia Fortes, Havana. Page 17: Olivier Pasquiers © Le Bar Floréal, Paris. Page 18:
© Kinkas, Paris. Pages 1 8- 1 9, 34: © Philippe Maillard, Institut du Monde Arabe, Paris. Pages 20, 26: Claude
Postel © Jean Pigozzi Collection. Page 2 1 : © George Kuzmin, Moscow. Page 22: David Patchett © Raija
Patchett, UK. Page 23: Roland © Artephot, Paris. Museum of Modern Art, Mexico City. Page 24: Babey ©
Artephot, Paris. Page 25: © Duong Dinh Sang, Hué. Pages 27, 28, 29: © François Guénet, Paris. Page 30
(above): © Alain Guillou, Le Croisic, France. Page 30 (below): Méro © Jacana, Paris. Page 3 1 (above): R.
König ©Jacana, Paris. Page 31 (below): Unesco. Pages 32-33: © Hamid, Martinique. Page 36: © Musée
Marey, Beaune, France. Page 37: © Lauros-Giraudon, Paris. Page 39: Jean-Claude Roche © Pascal
Lièvre/Musée de la Poste, Paris. Page 40: UNESCO-Michel Claude. Page 42: © New York Times. Page 44
(above): H. Oikawa © VNU. Page 44 (below): © VNU. Page 45 (above): Jensen © VNU. Page 45
(below): Pommaret © VNU. Pages 46, 47: © Rinnie Tang, Paris.
TheLfclESCO
^i^OURIER
46thYEAR
Published monthly ¡n 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
3 1 , rue Francos Bonvin, 7S0 i 5 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Gecrges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation:
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim {Tel. 45.6846.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Pritni Perera
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Alexander Melnikov (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic: Ei-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar- es -Sal aam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville ^iyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: juxto Egaña (Donascia)
Thai: Duargtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Ghoti Khaweri (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassar (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45 68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie. Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel: 45.68.45.65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs not copyr ghted -nay be reprinted
provid ng the credit line reads '"Reprinted from the Umsco Courier", plus
cate of ssue, and three voucher cosies are sent to the editor. Signed arti¬
cles reprinted must bear autnor's rame. Non-copyright photos will be sup¬
plied on request. Unsolicited manusenpts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international rep'y coupon covering postage. Signed arti¬
cles express t~e opin onsofthe authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of Usesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Cower. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The bound¬
aries on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance oy Unesco or the Unted Nations. The Unesco Cojrier is pro¬
duced n microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (I) UNESCO. 7
Dlace de Fon:enoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microhms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor. Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Ecition, Indian Head
Inc., 1 1 I West 40th Street New York. U.S.A.; (4) Bell ard Howell Co.. Old
Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 4469 1 . U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI - DÉCEMBRE 1993
COMMISSION PARITAIRE Nc 71842 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: IMAYE GRAPHIC.
Z.I. des Touches, Bd Henri-Becquerel, 53021 Laval Cedex (France)
ISSNO304-3I 8 N: I2-I993-OPI-93-52IA
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
sages 10-11 and 42-43.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
DU 7 AU 10 DECEMBRE , CNIT, PARIS-LA DÉFENSE
LES DEUX RENDEZ-VOUS
PROFESSIONNELS
INCONTOURNABLES
DE CETTE FIN D'ANNÉE !
EDUC
7 Ie Salon des Professionnels
de l'éducation et de la formation
Sous le haut patronage de:
François BAYROU, Ministre de l'Education Nationale.
François FILLON, Ministre de l'Enseignement Supérieur et de la
Recherche.
EDUCATEC, vitrine unique en France des outils
pédagogiques, des équipements et matériels
didactiques dédiés à l'éducation et à la formation
professionnelle, réunit l'offre la plus innovante de ses
250 exposants français et étrangers, et de
nombreuses institutions. EDUCATEC, qui a reçu l'an
passé plus de 32 000 visiteurs de 45 pays différents,
vous propose également cette année prés de 50
conférences et tables rondes où interviennent les
meilleurs experts sur les thèmes d'actualité qui vous
concernent.
2 Salon des Professionnels
de l'information
Sous le haut patronage de Jacques TOUBON,
Ministre de la Culture et de la Francophonie.
Le BIME 93, Salon des équipements et techniques
pour les bibliothèaues et médiathèques, réunit les
éditeurs de logiciels documentaires, de logiciels de
gestion, de support électroniaues, les fabricants de
rayonnages, de systèmes antivol, les sociétés de services
diverses, protection des ouvrages, GED, archivage, etc..
Chacune des journées du BIME 93 est dédiée à un
public précis, avec conférences et tables rondes:
Mardi 7 décembre: Les bibliothèques publiques.
Mercredi 8 décembre: Les CDI de l'enseignement.
Jeudi 9 décembre: Les bibliothèques universitaires.
Vendredi I0 décembre: Les centres de
documentation spécialisés.
l'accès eux conférences e' tebtes rondes e." ojatuil 001/ tous les visitews.
Information: EDIT EXPO INTERNATIONAL I2,rue Vauvenargues 750 18 Paris
Tél. (1)42 23 13 56 Fax (1)42 23 1307
L'HEBDOMADAIRE
DES 13
h iMUmiiti: l'Afrique du Sud
.Prix Nobel de la Paix
LES.ÇLES.
d6 19CI II 31 ITC
LE NOWEL EMPIRE
Dès la classe de 4°, s'informer, comprendre
les événements, se faire une opinion.
Des informations claires dans les domaines
les plus variés en France et à l'étranger :
économie, société, culture, sciences, sport...
Un dossier sur un sujet de fond.
Mise en page aérée. Nombreux lexiques,
encadrés, cartes et graphiques couleur, photos...
12 PAGES COULEUR, UN DOSSIER À CONSERVER
MILAN PRESSE
BON D'ABONNEMENT
à renvoyer à : Milan Presse - Service Abonnements - B.P. 82 - 31 150 Fenoulllet
Je m'abonne pour 52 numéros PUNE
aux Clés de l'Actualité au prix de 312 F
MLLE, M NOM
PRENOM DE L'ENEANT
COMPLÉMENT D'ADRESSE (RÉSIDENCE, ESC, BÂT)
NUMÉRO RUE/AV./BD./LIEU-DIT
CODE POSTAL COMMUNE
TÉLÉPHONE DATE DE NAISSANCE
Mode de paiement retenu
Ll Chèque bancaire ou postal à l'ordre de Milan Presse
_l Carte Bleue ou Visa
N°
Date de fin de validité Signature indispensable
1 9
S'ABONNER PLUS VITE :
, PAR UliPHONE :
(16)6176 64 11
fUt:
Ot)H7HStJ
3675 M/U*
Mot-Clé Abo
PAIEMENT PAR CM7I BLEUE 0« VBA UMQUEMCHT EN RAPPELANT LE CODE QHl
Offre valable jusqu'au 31/11/94 en France métropolitaine uniquement.
Pour l'étranger, nous consulter au 61 76 64 1 1 ou par Minitel 3615 Milan
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
TheljNESCO
^COURIER
EACH MONTH, ESSENTIAL
READING FOR AN
UNDERSTANDING OF THE
PROBLEMS OF TODAY AND
TOMORROW
THE CHALLENGE OF DEMOCRACY ...
THE COMPETITIVE WORLD OF SPORT ...
EXPLORING THE COSMOS ... VIOLENCE ...
PSYCHOANALYSIS: THE HIDDEN I ... A TIME
TO LOVE ... WATER OF UFE ... MINORITIES...
WHAT IS MODERN?... RHYTHM, «ESTURE AND
THE SACRED... TINE TO DISARM... THE STORY
OF NUMBERS... THE MEANING OF PROGRESS...
EACH MONTH: ANJ
FROM THE WORLD
CULTURE-
E, SCIENCE,
FRANCOIS MITTERRAND ... JORGE AMADO ...
RICHARD ATTENR0R0U6H ... JEAN-CLAUDE
CARRIÈRE... JEAN UCOVTURE ... FEDERICO
MAYOR... NA6UIB MAHFOVZ ... SENBENE
OUSMANE ... ANDREI VOZNESENSHY ...
FREDERIC ROSSIF ... HINNERK BRVHNS ...
CAMILO JOSÉ CELA ... VACLAV HAVEL ...
SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV ... ERNESTO
SÁBATO ... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND ...
CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS ... LEOPOLDO ZEA ...
PAULO FREIRÉ ... DANIEL J. BOORSTIN ...
FRANÇOIS JACOB ... MANU DIBANGO ...
FAROUK HOSNY ... SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN ...
JORGE LAVELLI ... LÉON SCHWARTZEHBERG ...
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN ... GABRIEL GARCIA
MÁRQUEZ ... JACQUES-YVES COUSTEAU ...
MELINA NERCOURI ... CARLOS FUENTES ...
JOSEPH KI-ZERBO ... VANDANA SHIVA ...
WILLIAM STYRON ... OSCAR NIEMEYER ...
MIKIS THEODORAKIS... ATAHUALPA
YUPANQUI... HERVÉ BOURGES ... ABDEL
RAHMAN EL BACHA ... SUSANA RINALDI ...
HUBERT REEVES ... JOSÉ CARRERAS ...
A LETTER FRON FREUD TO EINSTEIN ...
LUC FERRY ... CHARLES MALAMOUD ...
UMBERTO ECO ... OUVER STONE... ANDRÉ
BRINK... JAMES D. WATSON... ANOS OZ...
MICHEL SERRES...
LD HERITAG
ACTIVITIES WORL
THENE OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(JANUARY 1994):
DESERTS
ALSO FEATURING
AN INTERVIEW WITH THE FRENCH
WRITER AND NATURALIST
THÉODORE NONOD
]]>
</page>
</document>
