<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="096815eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
JUNE 1994
_ TECHNOLOGY
ESOURCEFUL GEM
M 1205-9406- 22,
INTERVIEW WITH
ANTONI TAPIES
ENVIRONMENT
DEFEATING DECIBELS
HERITAGE
BUTRINTI
REDISCOVERED
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
From Sarajevo
On the occasion of International Press Freedom Day
the Director-General of Unesco launches an appeal for peace
Mjet us make this week a historic turning point from a culture ofwar to a culture of peace!
In South Africa, under the clear-sighted leadership of Nelson Mandela and Frederik de
Klerk, elections have been held and apartheid is over. The Middle East, thanks to the farsighted¬
ness of Yasser Arafat, Shimon Peres and Itzhak Rabin, is ending the first stage of a new departure
towards peaceful coexistence and neighbourliness.
In this one week the spirit of understanding and mutual respect has come to two of the most
long-standing and most difficult problems of coexistence. The same thing has happened in El Sal¬
vador and Mozambique. I therefore solemnly appeal to all the parties in Bosnia and Herzegovina
(knowing full well how recent and deep the wounds are) to halt the fighting and sit down at the
table of dialogue and conciliation. You can make this week a historic occasion for peace. In par¬
ticular I appeal to the Serbian leaders to stop now and take part in peace talks.
From Sarajevo, on the occasion of International Press Freedom Day, I solemnly appeal to all
those engaged in conflict, especially fratricidal conflict, to cease hostilities and embark on a dia¬
logue for peace. Peace in justice, equity and freedom.
In Rwanda, Angola and Afghanistan, please realize that everything can be discussed, a solu¬
tion can be found to every problem, except death! Let there be no more dying for causes that
deserve so richly to be lived for!
Today is a great day for hope, and we thank all those who have been at the inception of the
processes that are coming to fruition, all those who have been able to overcome their hatred and
desire for vengeance and have agreed to turn a page towards the future.
Today from Sarajevo a new song of life and freedom goes forth to the whole world. May the
force of reason prevail over the reason of force!
We have not been able to share our past or live in harmony. But we still have intact a
common treasure, our future. And this week can be a crucial turning point from war to peace
everywhere. From Sarajevo I also appeal to people all over the world to contribute to the recon¬
struction of this country and to the restoration of its multicultural symbols: the library, the
Mostar bridge, the churches and places ofworship of every religion, schools of every kind.
We can no longer just sit back and gape in wide-eyed wonder. The time for active solidarity
has now begun. Your contribution, whatever the amount, will show that we, especially in Europe,
are no longer passive. And that the momentum of love between peoples is the strongest force.
Today is a day of hope. There are examples to follow. Great events to celebrate. On behalf of
the United Nations agency mandated to build peace in the minds of men, I ask you to make a gift
to all the world's children and young people: lay down your weapons and use your free hands to
build a new world based on love.
Federico Mayor
Sarajevo, 3 May 1994
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
I INTERVIEW WITH
Antoni Tapies
Contents
JUNE 1004 I
THE RESOURCEFUL GENE
UNESCO IH ACTION
40
NEWSBRIEFS
41
HERITAGE
Butrinti rediscovered
by Zip Xholi
45
ANNIVERSARY
Martin Luther King:
Death, where is thy sting ?
by Edouard]. Maunick
46
ARCHIVES
The downfall of idealism
by Thomas Mann
48
Recent recordings
by Isabelle Leymarie
49
Books of the world
by Edgar Reichmann
50
Letters to the Editor
Biotechnology for beginners
by Monkombu Sambasivan Swaminathan
Achievements, expectations and challenges
by Albert Sasson and Edgar j. DaSilva
f The state of the art
by Toshiomi Yosh'tda
The magic of mushrooms
by P. Atthasampunna and S. T. Chang
) Creative ferment
by Peter L Rogers
UNESCO's international network
of microbial resources centres
A rising tide
by Rita Colwell
! From the Green Revolution
to the Gene Revolution
by Indra K. Vasil and Luis Herrera-Estrella
r Art and the science of life
by John Hodgson
Cover:
genetic manipulation of mouse eggs.
Greenwatch
Defeating decibels
by France Bequette
COMMENTARY
by
Federico Mayer
Special consultants for this issue:
Albert Sasson
and Edgar J. DaSilva
The
MM
Unesco
courier
4 7th fear Published monthly
in 32 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER (945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
ANTONI
TAPIES
talks to
Serafín García Ibáñez
Born in Barcelona in 1923, Antoni Tapies is
one of the greatest Spanish artists of our
time. Largely self-taught, he was influenced
early in his career by the Dadaists and the
Surrealists and then in the 1950s he engaged
in the experimentation with informalism for
which he became famous. Major museums
began to hold exhibitions of his work and
in 1958 an entire room was devoted to it at
the Venice Biennale. Awards from Unesco
and the Carnegie Foundation testified to his
growing international reputation. He has a
highly personal way of using materials, con¬
structing his compositions from common¬
place and discarded objects packaging,
sand, marble dust, latex, cast iron, rags
mixed with thick impasto and incised with
expressive graffiti-like markings. His later
assemblages incorporate objects such as
buckets, mirrors and even larger items. He
has written widely about his art, and a
volume of Conversations with Antoni Tapies
was published in 1991 (Prestel Verlag, Ger¬
many).
SERAFÍN GARCIA IBANEZ
is a journalist with Unesco's
Office of Public Information.
You started out as a law student and
then abandonedyour law studies to devote
yourself to painting. Did you take that
decision on an impulse?
I had an artistic vocation. When I was
a child I loved drawing. I lacked the basic
skills, but as time went by I became con¬
sumed by a desire to do better than all
my classmates. My father, who was a
lawyer, hoped that I would follow in his
footsteps and join his practice. He was so
insistent that I actually studied law for
five years before dropping it. Then I had
the good fortune to win a scholarship
awarded by the French Institute in
Barcelona which enabled me to go to Paris.
Those scholarships were wonderful. They
carried no obligations, and although they
were not worth very much financially,
they provided enough to live on. For me
it was an extraordinary stroke of luck.
What sort ofperson are you?
I would say off the cuff that I am an
anxious person. I worry about everything.
I need to know everything. I tend to live in
a state of anxiety with the feeling that life
is some kind of great catastrophe. I feel the
desire, or rather the intense need, to do
something useful for society, and that is
what stimulates me. In every situation I
always look for what is positive and ben¬
eficial for my fellow citizens. I am inter¬
ested in study, reflection, philosophy
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
One should come to art with an open mind, without searching
for references. One should simply listen to one's feelings.
but always as a dilettante. I also consider
myself a dilettante as a painter.
It is hard to reduce art to aformula and
one might almost say that everyone has
their own definition. What is yours?
For me, art is a mechanism, a system
that makes it possible to change the spec¬
tator's way of looking and to bring him or
her closer to a state of contemplation of
reality at its deepest level. The artist is like
the mystic: each one acts in his own way
but their common purpose is to achieve
the inner illumination that enables them to
perceive the depths of reality. For me this
is what art is about.
What do you mean by "reality", a word
you often use?
When I talk of reality, I am always
thinking of essentials. Profundity is not
located in some remote, inaccessible
region. It is rooted in everyday life. That
is what great thinkers have taught me,
above all the philosophers of the Far East,
for whom true wisdom which I am far
from achieving is the conjunction of
samsara (the ordinary world) and nirvana
(profound reality). To achieve contact with
reality is not to transport oneself else¬
where, it is not transcendence but thor¬
ough immersion in one's surroundings. A
reality which is neither purely physical
nor metaphysical, but both at once.
Your work is known all over the world
but manyfind itperplexing. Do you think
this is because the public is used to figu¬
rative art?
It is true that the education we receive
inculcates certain mental habits. As far as
art is concerned, for example, it is gener¬
ally thought that painting is copying
nature, in other words reality in its most
superficial form. Today this is the role of
photography, the cinema and television.
What is called photorealism in painting
no longer has any point. Not because it is
questionable in itself but because there
are other ways of expressing and
explaining what it shows us.
You yourselfstarted out asa figurative
painter. . . .
Yes of course, just like everyone else.
Like the artists of my generation, at any
rate. We were attracted by what we have
just been talking about: the imitation of
nature. I did not attend an academy, I
made one for myself, painting the por¬
traits of my friends and forcing myself to
control what I wanted to express.
Does a work ofart have a message?
Is the medium the message? This is an
endless source of debate. The way in which
things are presented is one part of the mes¬
sage. Like the most conventional of figu¬
rative painters, I could paint a still-life
with apples, for example, but I would do
it in terms of something else that I wanted
to express. I would paint those apples in
my own way. Perhaps I would sketch a
whirlpool, or a world in movement, an
impression of living, organic matter.
Painting expresses the painter's way of
thinking, his perception of reality. The
kind of realism we are talking about is not
so far from the work of certain contem¬
porary painters. Today we have other tech¬
nical possibilities, but some of them are
very simple. People think that computers,
new machines, the power of technology
make it possible to reproduce reality with
a high degree of precision. My equipment
is extremely modest it amounts to a
brush whose bristles are rather worn.
That's all I need. The simplest tools can
express the deepest feelings.
You use very ordinary materials such as
cardboard or hessian for yourpaintings.
That too is a message. Materials are
expressive. Gold leaf will make a totally
different impression on you from that
made by a piece of torn cardboard. And
the piece of cardboard will have different
connotations, and will arouse different
feelings from those produced by a piece of
polished marble. These commonplace
materials, which had been ignored, were
exactly what I was looking for. They pro¬
voked the spectator and made him think.
Perhaps on the spur of the moment he
thinks they are rubbish, but when he gives
the matter a little thought he sees that
there is profound wisdom in the humblest
objects. The Japanese say that the whole
universe is contained in a grain of sand.
These objects, which seem to be nothing
but rubbish, can deliver an authentic
human message.
Is it necessary for the artist andhis work
to bepolitically, socially or morally com¬
mitted? Or is beauty sufficient justifica¬
tion for a work ofart?
I have always thought that the ideolog¬
ical component the political component
even was necessary. But it has to arise
from the artist's general vision and not,
as has happened in totalitarian fascist or
communist countries, from an overtly
political discourse. My political commit¬
ment results from my way of working.
The details naturally take their place on
this backcloth. The message, whatever it is,
is essential. The person who only paints to
amuse the gallery or play the fool must be
very unhappy. But, I repeat, the message
emerges from the work itself; it is the
work that reveals its social, political or
philosophical content.
A message only has meaning if it is
understood, and the language ofcontem¬
porary art isperhaps not within everyone's
reach. Is an initiation necessary?
I think so. An initiation in the educa¬
tional sense of the term. Unfortunately, it
is a training one must follow when young,
for sensibility is formed in childhood. I do
not think that educational systems in the
West, especially in Spain, are up to it. Art
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
must be taught at school in order to edu¬
cate the taste of children and young
people, to prevent them from falling into
banality. Most people approach art with
preconceived ideas: they want to see in it
what, as a result of conformism or because
they are ill informed, they expect to find in
it. One should come to art with an open
mind, without searching for references.
One should simply listen to one's feel¬
ings.
Which painter orpainters do you most
admire?
There are so many of them that it would
be boring to give you a list of all of them.
I am a collector in a small way and I like
to be surrounded by my favourite authors,
painters and sculptors. And I am
extremely eclectic. I am deeply moved by
the great art of Egypt, Chinese painting of
the Song and Yuan periods (which has
inspired some of our contemporaries) and
the works of the great Chinese and
Japanese calligraphers. African art and
pre-Cortesian and pre-Columbian art as
well.
And among Spanish painters?
Spanish painting and art cover an
immense range. I love the Romanesque
style Catalan Romanesque above all
but also certain features of Gothic art, the
mysterious works of Ribera, Zurbarán,
and of course Picasso and Miró.
You have left out another Catalan
painter, Dalí.
Dalí produced some very interesting
work in the 1930s. Then he began to do the
kind of thing I was attacking a few minutes
ago photo painting. And from an ideo¬
logical point of view, Dalí ceased to
interest me from the time of the Civil War.
I was disappointed by his behaviour as a
citizen and as a human being.
Do you have any pastimes or hobbies
outsidepainting?
I collect books, all kinds of books, old
and new. Books that talk of the mysteries
of life in every period. I also love listening
to music. I am particularly fond of
Romantic music: I find Wagner
enchanting. But I also appreciate later
composers such as Bruckner and Mahler,
and even more modern composers such as
the Italian Scelsi, whose admirable work is
still not widely known. At present his is
my favourite music. I also like the modern
French composers and some of the Ger¬
mans, such as Stockhausen.
Do you like flamenco?
I don't know it well. I ought not to say
that, because one cannot know flamenco,
one can only feel it. It hasn't often hap¬
pened to me, but whenever I have had an
opportunity to see and hear great cantes
being interpreted, I have been extremely
moved.
Literature uses words, music uses sounds.
Architecture, sculpture andpainting deal
in matter. Does this mean that there are
uncrossable frontiers between these dif¬
ferent forms ofexpression?
Speaking from experience I will say no.
These are academic classifications that are
used by force of habit. Sometimes I feel
that I am very close to the poets: it has even
been said that some of my paintings are
poetic metaphors. At other times I feel
affinities with music: I use fragile materials
which when they crack produce a musical
sound. I have also been told that my relief
effects in painting are close to sculpture,
and in fact I deliberately work in three
dimensions. Today the very precise fron¬
tiers that separated painting, sculpture and
other forms of art arc tending to fade away.
You designed the medal struck by
UNESCO to commemorate the centenary
of the birth of Pablo Picasso. And you
recently designed another to mark the cen¬
tenary of the birth ofJoan Miró.
When UNESCO entrusted me with
these commissions, I felt a tremendous
sense of satisfaction since it created a kind
of continuity, a link with the preceding
generation through Picasso and above all
Miró whom I knew very well and to
whose work I have devoted much study. I
even worked with him since I was a
member of the governing body of the
Miró Foundation in Barcelona. I feel very
close to him and I have always had great
admiration for him both as a man and as an
artist. He was extremely human and had a
vision of the world that was full of fantasy.
We both tend to escape into dreams,
dreams that are rooted in the depths of
our being and awaken in the unconscious
mechanisms that are far closer to tangible
reality and everyday life than one might
think. I see in Miró's painting the convul¬
sions of the break with academicism and
the return to innocent things charged with
meaning. As for Picasso, with the gen¬
erous positions he took, his fidelity to
humanism, and his espousal of certain crit¬
ical approaches to social and political
issues, he was for me a great master.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
TECHNOLOGY
ITHE RESOURCEFUL
GENE
»
' -
1 itSf
>
Hi"
By unlocking the treasury of the living
world, modern biotechnology can help
to solve some of the world's most
urgent problems hunger
and malnutrition, disease, energy
supplies and pollution....
s
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
BIOTECHNOLOGY FOR BEGINNERS
by Monkombu Sambasivan Swaminathan
rrevious page, lettuce
grown in liquid nutrients,
using the technique known
as hydroponics, in a
Japanese vegetable factory.
Kept at constant
temperature with 24-hour-
a-day lighting in a carbon-
dioxide-rich atmosphere,
the lettuce reach maturity
4 to 5 times faster than
normal.
AMONG the more than five billion
. women, men and children living
on our planet, no two individuals
are alike and the same is true of cross-polli¬
nated plants as well as animals and micro¬
organisms. This kaleidoscopic diversity, which
exists in all living beings, provides the basis for
biotechnology, which may be described as the
technological modification and improvement
of living organisms.
The rediscovery of Gregor Johann
Mendel's laws of heredity in the early part of
this century helped promote an understanding
of the origins and workings of genetic diver¬
sity. The principal phenomena involved are
segregation, mutation and recombination of
genes. Together, these three actions generate
opportunities for the immense genetic diver¬
sity in living organisms.
In the past, the existence of genetic vari¬
ability enabled humans to select plants and
animals for domestication. Over 10,000 years
ago, plants such as wheat, barley and rice were
selected for cultivation from the wild flora.
After their initial domestication, these crops
were continuously improved through selection
of naturally occurring variability. In plants
like fruit trees and the potato, occasional muta¬
tions gave rise to new varieties. Thus, today, we
not only have over 1.5 million species of plants
and animals, but also a large number of genetic
strains within species. For example, more than
100,000 varieties of rice are grown in different
parts of the world.
From the beginning of this century, tech¬
niques such as planned hybridization and later,
the induction of mutations, were used by agri¬
cultural and biological research institutions
to create new genetic combinations.
Hybridization also became a method of
increasing the growth of crops and animals, a
phenomenon known as hybrid vigour. Hybrid
maize developed in the United States in the
1930s helped to double maize yields. The iden¬
tification of genes for a semi-dwarf plant type
in wheat in Japan and in rice in China in the
1940s provided the raw material for the green
revolution witnessed in these crops in Asia in
the late 1960s. Identification and utilization of
genetic mechanisms for male sterility in plants
made the commercial exploitation of hybrid
vigour possible even in a self-pollinated crop
like rice. Today, hybrid rice occupies nearly 18
million hectares in China.
Biological diversity thus became the basis
of continuous improvements in productivity.
Selection, mutation and hybridization were
used to improve plants, animals and micro¬
organisms of interest to agriculture, industry
and medicine. Thus, new antibiotics and vac¬
cines could be developed. Fermentation tech¬
nology made rapid strides. Classical biotech¬
nology involving non-molecular techniques
is responsible for many of the improvements
witnessed in scientific endeavours involving
living organisms.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Genetic engineeringthe hard core
of modern biotechnology
Against this background, we may examine the
new vistas opened up by molecular biology.
This area of science was inaugurated by James
Dewey Watson and Francis Crick forty years
ago when they described the double helix
structure of the deoxyribonucleic acid mole¬
cule, commonly known as DNA. Since then,
emphasis has shifted to the study of the mol¬
ecular basis of genetic diversity and to the
standardization of methods that can help
achieve novel genetic combinations through
what are known as recombinant DNA tech¬
niques, whereby scientists use tiny circular
pieces of DNA known as plasmid vectors to
achieve gene splicing. These techniques have
opened up a new world of genetic engineering,
leading to the creation of transgenic organ¬
isms organisms containing genetic material
into which DNA from an unrelated organism
has been artificially placed. They are already
being used in the production of insulin, inter¬
feron, and human growth hormone. Although
the term "biotechnology" is used to denote a
wide range of procedures such as cell and
tissue culture, micro-propagation and fer¬
mentation, the hard core of modern biotech¬
nology is genetic engineering.
The birth of an industry
Present-day biotechnology, which combines
conventional and molecular techniques, has
every prospect of becoming a great industry. In
addition to already existing applications in
health and medicine, large-scale uses in agri¬
culture, industry, energy supplies, environ-
Diogas production
on a farm in the village
of Rangasamudra,
Karnataka province (India).
Cow dung is mixed
with water in a trough
from which it is piped
into a tank where it is
transformed by heat into
natural gas (photos I
and 2). As a result of this
easy-to-use system,
gas can replace wood
as domestic fuel (photo 3),
thus helping to halt
deforestation in this part
of southern India.
In the United States
tomatoes with a shelf-life
of several weeks
are grown by deactivating
the enzymes that cause
them to rot. In container
at left are ordinary
tomatoes 25 days
after being picked;
at right, genetically
altered tomatoes.
mental protection and the exploration of space
are becoming exciting possibilities. Biotech¬
nology will probably provide the key to pro¬
ducing more food and other agricultural com¬
modities from less land and water in the
twenty-first century without the adverse eco¬
logical implications associated with the high
doses of mineral fertilizers and chemical pes¬
ticides being used now to make high-yielding
varieties of rice, wheat, maize and other crops
express their full potential.
Many transgenic plants are currently under
field testing in several parts of the world. Early
applications of recombinant DNA method¬
ology gave rise to micro-organisms that can
clean up oil spills. This led to the birth of
biorcmediation technology, which has been
widely used to treat the problems of "oil lakes"
created by the 1991 Gulf War. In fact, biotech¬
nologies have opened up unlimited opportu¬
nities for the purposeful use of biological
diversity. For example, at our Research Centre
in Madras, we are assembling a gene pool for
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Drought-resistant crop
varieties and a new system
of drip irrigation enable
farmers to grow asparagus
in the desert of lea (Peru).
IO
MONKOMBU SAMBASIVAN
SWAMINATHAN is an Indian
scientist who played a leading
role in the "Green Revolution"
in Asia. He is Director-General
of the International Rice
Research Institute, Los Baños,
The Philippines, and has
worked extensively in the
fields of plant genetics and
agronomic research and
development.
breeding crops for tolerance to salt-water
intrusion. Mangrove trees that inhabit inter-
tidal regions along the shore have such genetic
traits. When we have enough scientific knowl¬
edge, it may be possible to transfer genes for
salt-water tolerance from mangrove trees to
other plants. Such research is important due to
the possible rise of the world's sea level in the
not-so-distant future.
Microbiological enrichment of cellulosic
wastes can be an important source of animal
feed, particularly where farm animals are
reared under stall-fed conditions. Biomass
refineries are now being established in several
countries.
Questions of safety and ethics
New research tools always generate hope and
fear, and questions about safety and ethics
have kindled public concern about biotech¬
nology. Critics fear that "playing God" with
living systems may create an environmental or
medical disaster, or lead us to interfere with
human nature itself. This is why countries
with a significant biotechnology programme
also have strict biosafety regulations. Com
mittees dealing with ethical issues also exist in
many scientific organizations.
Another issue of public concern, particu¬
larly in developing countries, is the use of
basic genetic material from plants from these
countries by private seed companies in indus¬
trialized nations solely for private profit. Since
most biotechnological research in industrial¬
ized nations is in the private sector, and the
private sector depends on developing countries
for genetic resources, questions relating to
systems for patenting and monetary compen¬
sation are the centre of widespread interna¬
tional attention. This was reflected in the
Global Biodiversity convention signed by
over 150 nations at Rio de Janeiro in June
1992.
Besides providing the foundation for global
food security and for sustainable livelihoods,
the wise use of biotechnology and a broader
understanding of both conventional and mol¬
ecular genetics could contribute to the elimi¬
nation of irrational beliefs and prejudices
about the dangers of diversity. These societal
benefits may ultimately be the most significant
contributions of modern biotechnology.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
ACHIEVEMENTS, EXPECTATIONS
AND CHALLENOES
by Albert Sasson and Edgar J, DaSilva
HE world of biotechnology is vast and
varied. Some idea of just how varied can
be gauged from a report published by
the Organization for Economic Co-operation
and Development (OECD), which defined
biotechnology as "the application of scientific
and engineering principles to the processing of
materials by biological agents to provide goods
and services". The "biological agents" referred to
are mainly micro-organisms, animal and plant
cells, and enzymes. The "goods and services"
include the products of the agriculture, fishery,
food processing and pharmaceutical industries.
The scientific basis of biotechnology is mul-
tidisciplinary, and the core disciplines include
molecular and cell biology, biochemistry, genetics,
microbiology, immunology, chemical and process
engineering, computing and data processing. So
many fields of activity are involved that it is per¬
haps more appropriate to talk of "biotechnolo
gies" in the plural rather than the singular. These
technologies may be simple or sophisticated,
cheap or expensive. They range from time-hon¬
oured processes such as fermentation, to genetic
engineering, the ability to take hereditary char¬
acters from one organism and transplant them
into another, thus creating "transgenic" plants and
animals with desired characteristics.
Genetic engineering is a powerful tool that
holds vast promise for medicine and agriculture,
where basic research has advanced so far since the
mid-1970s that there has been much talk of a
"biotcchnological revolution". However, it raises
many sensitive ethical and legal questions, as well
as questions relating to safety and public atti¬
tudes.
During the 1980s, biotechnologies in the
industrialized countries progressed on many
fronts. In North America, research led to the
discovery and manufacture of the first commer-
Advances in
biotechnology
are
transforming
social
and economic
structures
Monoculture
the cultivation of large
tracts of land to produce
a single variety of crop
which is harvested all
at once is a typical
feature of modern large-
scale agriculture. It has
a number of disadvantages
including low resistance
to pests, the use of large
amounts of chemical
fertilizers and pesticides,
and consequent risks
of groundwater pollution.
Below, a wheat field
in Canada.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
I hese scientists at the
Botanical Conservatory at
Porquerolles (France) have
propagated in vitro date
palm plantlets resistant to
"Bayoud", an incurable
disease which threatens
the palm groves of North
Africa and, eventually,
elsewhere.
12
ALBERT SASSON is
Director of Unesco's Bureau
of Studies, Programming and
Evaluation. He has written
numerous works on biology,
microbiology and
biotechnology, including
Biotechnologies: Challenges and
Promises (UNESCO, 1984),
Biotechnologies and Development
(UNESCO/CTA, 1988) and
Biotechnologies in Developing
Countries: Present and Future.
Volume I : Regional and National
Survey (UNESCO, 1993).
cial biotechnology-derived products such as
insulin, human growth hormone and tissue plas¬
minogen activator. The most recent such product
was the antihaemophiliac factor VIII, produced
by an American firm for the treatment of
haemophilia A. Also in pharmaceutics, new devel¬
opments in molecular biology made it possible to
produce vaccines using yeasts and animal cells.
Attempts were made to increase the rate of
growth of farm animals by injecting growth hor¬
mones produced via genetic engineering. So far
there are no transgenic animals on the market, but
transgenic animals such as mice are being used in
the laboratory as human disease models. Some of
these recent and possible future developments are
shown in the box on page 14 and others are
described elsewhere in this issue.
However, a "knowledge revolution" does
not necessarily lead immediately to a revolution
in practice. It has, for example, been estimated that
it may take twenty or thirty years before the
impact of recent biotechnological discoveries in
plant and animal breeding and in food production
is truly felt.
Consumer interests and biosafety
In the public mind biotechnologies are often
identified exclusively with genetic engineering
or with human reproduction technologies rather
than with industrial microbiology, biochemical
engineering or fermentation, or associated with
food safety or public health concerns.
Governments and industry are increasingly
aware that there is a need to inform the public
better about the new biotechnologies, that the
participation of both experts and non-special¬
ists is required to assess the objectivity of infor¬
mation, and that public confidence in regulation
effectiveness must be significantly improved.
France is one European country that has
established a mechanism, in the form of a Com¬
mittee on Biomolecular Engineering, to control
the risks associated with the production and
release of genetically-engineered crop species or
domestic animals. According to the Committee,
1993-1994 would be a crucial period when
numerous projects concerning transgenic plants
implemented over several years were close to the
homologation phase prior to marketing. Most of
the requests for trials examined by the Com¬
mittee concerned plants that had been engineered
for resistance to herbicides, insect pests or specific
diseases, or were designed to provide improved
nutritious quality. A similar situation existed in
other industrialized countries.
In the United States, the government was
asked by the Environmental Defence Fund and
several other groups to create new, or modify
existing, regulatory structures for biotechnologies
through legislation. However, the U.S. govern¬
ment's "Report on National Biotechnology
Policy" found that the risks posed by bio-engi¬
neered organisms should not be exaggerated and
stated that "products developed through biotech¬
nology do notper se pose risks to human health
and the environment." On 26 May 1992, the U.S.
administration announced that genetically mod¬
ified foodstuffs would not need special autho¬
rization or labels before being marketed, because
they do not pose specific biosafety problems.
This decision, which was criticized by several
consumer and environmentalist groups, ended a
ten-year period of uncertainty for the industri¬
alists concerning the regulations on the use of
biotechnologies in the agro-food sector.
Economic effects
Biotechnologies are expected to make a significant
impact on agricultural production. Market bal¬
ances published for the United States and Europe
suggest that they could increase productivity by
decreasing costs per unit of output (e.g. fewer
chemical inputs) or by increasing yields per unit
of output. Forecasts made in the early 1990s
mentioned possible milk production increases
of from 10 per cent to 16 per cent within a five-
to-ten-year period, if bovine growth hormone
were to be used. (Its utilization was approved by
the Food and Drug Administration in November
1993.)
Biotechologies are expected to contribute to
long-term trends towards the reduction of the
share of agriculture in total employment, but job
loss may be partly offset by job creation in related
sectors, particularly the food-related services.
Still, the dissemination of agricultural and food
technologies in the OECD countries is expected
to be a gradual process in the next decade, without
major, destabilizing impacts on the social struc¬
ture of employment.
During the 1980s biotechnologies were estab¬
lished in developing countries with varying
degrees of priority and sophistication, a process
illustrating not only the contrasting economic
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
and scientific development conditions of these
countries, but also the various possibilities for
applying biotechnologies at levels of investment
and complexity suitable for each specific situation.
Biotechnologies
and developing countries
Everyone agrees that developing countries need
to move up the gradient of biotechnologies, from
the low-cost ones to the more sophisticated and
expensive ones. The more richly endowed
national systems are already well on the way,
and even the smallest and poorest need to think
about developing and using modern biotech¬
nologies. For instance, a country where crop
species provide the staple food could profitably
invest in a tissue culture laboratory, at a capital
cost of about $20,000. This would enable it to
import, as tissue cultures, virus- or disease-free
clones developed in research stations abroad,
and to multiply them rapidly, if they proved
adaptable to local conditions and acceptable to
producers and consumers.
The significance of biotechnologies for the
Third World is illustrated by the example of
Asian agriculture. In the early 1990s, Asia has
more than 50 per cent of the global population,
over 70 per cent of the world's farming families,
but only 25 per cent of the world's arable land. At
the beginning of the twenty-first century, the
per capita land availability may be 0.1 hectare in
China and 0.14 hectare in India. Meanwhile, the
average Asian population growth rate is 1.86 per
cent. The only way for countries like China and
India to feed their growing populations is through
continuous improvement in yields. China has
gone into large-scale exploitation of rice hybrids
for this purpose.
There has been an almost three-fold expansion
in the world's irrigated land since 1950, much of
it in the developing countries. Scope for further
r\ biochemical engineer in
the United States carries
out a computer-controlled
process for the
development of a malaria
vaccine using genetic
engineering.
In this water purification
facility at Narragansett,
Rhode Island (U.S.A.),
waste water is purified
naturally though
processing in tanks by
minerals, bacteria, fungi
and algae (foreground),
and then by certain species
of molluscs, fish and large
aquatic plants
(background).
expansion is being gradually reduced and conse¬
quently improved water management and the
incorporation of genes for drought tolerance
into major crop species are now urgent necessi¬
ties.
As we have seen, however, more than excel¬
lent research is needed before biotechnologies
can achieve commercial success. The latter
depends on factors related to "social capability",
which includes facilities for the diffusion of
knowledge and conditions facilitating structural
change. Today scientists and political leaders in
developing countries are concerned about a
number of aspects of current global trends in
biotechnological research and development. Some
of the questions they are asking themselves are:
"S" Will the "biotechnology revolution" help
resource-poor farmers increase productivity?
^ Will genetic engineering research directed
at finding substitutes for national products not
have adverse impacts on the farming sector and
the export products of their countries ? Such fears
are based, for example, on the possible use of
natural or synthetic sweeteners as substitutes for
cane or beet sugar, as well as the development of
substitutes for vanilla flavouring, cocoa butter and
diosgenin.
Will products produced by genetic engi¬
neering be safe? Will developing countries be
used as testing grounds for genetically modified
organisms, as a way of avoiding the stringent
regulations prevailing in the industrialized coun¬
tries?
ts" What will be the impact of the extension of
intellectual property rights to individual genes and
genotypes on the availability of such improved
material to developing countries and resource-
poor farmers? Will intellectual property rights be
exclusively reserved for rewarding formal inno¬
vation, even though the informal innovation
system has played, and is playing, a key role in the
identification and conservation of plant and
animal and genetic resources?
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE STATE OF THE ART
The 1980s and early 1990s have seen rapid
advances in biotechnologies on many fronts.
Here is a sample of achievements and pros¬
pects:
PHARMACEUTICALS
Today . . . production by microbial or animal
cells of hormones, substances for breaking
down blood clots, blood coagulants, lympho-
kins, interferons (anti-cancer), vaccines
against viral, bacterial and parasitic
diseases (e.g. hepatitis B and C, schistoso¬
miasis, malaria)
and tomorrow. . . Breakthroughs may occur
in the fields of anti-Aids vaccines or drugs
and anti-cancer medicines.
DISEASE-RESISTANT PLANTS
Today. . . Progress has been rapid since
1982, when the first transgenic plant was
created. Several dozen plants have since
been modified to increase growth perfor¬
mance and resistance to viruses and other
pathogens. In 1994, several hundred trials
were being carried out on transgenic plants
in Europe, North America, Japan and Aus¬
tralia.
and tomorrow. . . Some of the transgenic
plants already tested (potato, cotton, rape-
seed, tomato, tobacco, soybean) are
expected to be marketed by the mid- or late
1990s. A transgenic tomato variety with a
prolonged shelf-life (U.S.A.) is already being
marketed; this will also be the case for a
virus-resistant tomato variety (Japan).
However, delays due to safety requirements,
public concern and the need for more
research may slow down large-scale market¬
ing of genetically modified crop species bet¬
ween now and the year 2000.
NEW FOODS
Today. . . Bioconversion of starch into sweet
products, food flavours and enhancers, fruit-
juice processing; derivation of amino-acids
and other nutrients, pigments and vitamins
from micro-algae; new foods from fermenta¬
tion; cheese-making enzymes, lactose-free
dairy products, yeast hybrids.
and tomorrow. . . Products that may be mar¬
keted by 1995 include genetically modified
baker's yeast, new food colourings and
ingredients, high added-value compounds
from plant cell and micro-algal cultures. By
the end of the century we may see geneti¬
cally modified food bacteria for flavour and
quality, modified food enzymes, novel bio-
catalysts for food processing, and increasing
numbers of rapid biotests and biosensors for
food contaminants or pathogens.
FASTER-GROWING ANIMALS
Today. . . Already in commercial exploitation
are: diagnostics, new vaccines and drugs, in-
vitro fertilization and embryo transfer in
domestic animals, growth hormone adminis¬
tration to increase growth and milk yield,
feeds and feed additives. So far no trans¬
genic domestic animals are on the market.
Transgenic animals such as a transgenic
mouse carrying a human cancer gene have
been used in the laboratory as human
disease models.
and tomorrow. . . Between now and the end
of the century, the development of fish, pigs
and cattle with rapid growth potential
through the insertion of growth hormone
genes, improved carcass quality and, for
cattle, increased milk yield, is expected to
be rapid. Gene transfer may also lead to the
multiplication of genetically superior animals
through the development of disease-resis¬
tant breeds.
MORE PRODUCTIVE
FISH AND ALGAE
Today. . . Growth hormone genes from
rainbow trout have been inserted into a
number of other commercial fish species. No
transgenic fish have yet been patented. A
wide range of products derived from micro-
algae are used in the manufacture of food¬
stuffs, cosmetics, dyes, paints, paper, tex¬
tiles, etc.
and tomorrow. . . Vaccines for disease and
stress control in aquaculture is a probable
growth area. In Scandinavia nearly all trout
and salmon produced by aquaculture are
vaccinated, compared to 5% ten years ago.
Promising new antibiotics, anti-cancer
agents and food additives will be developed.
T. Yoshida
TOSHIOMI YOSHIDA, of
Japan, is a Professor at the
International Centre of Co¬
operative Research in
Biotechnology, Faculty of
Engineering, Osaka University.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Will it be possible to balance the market-
driven features of biotechnology research by
concern for the long-term well-being of
humankind, poor as well as rich? Research on
staple food crop species in the developing coun¬
tries needs to be supported internationally, for
the sake of global, human sustainable devel¬
opment conducted in a spirit of solidarity. The
same international effort is required to find
cures for diseases prevailing in the Third World.
No panacea
The perfecting of conventional biotechnologies
and the expansion of more advanced biotech¬
nologies as a result of further discoveries in
cell and molecular biology are leading to far-
reaching economic and social change because of
their applications in agriculture and food pro¬
duction, the cure and prevention of disease,
the meeting of energy needs, and environ¬
mental protection. The spectacular progress
of biotechnologies is full of promise for
humankind.
However, these advances should not be
seen as a panacea. They are not intended to
substitute, but to complement, the wide range
of technologies used in the various areas of
social and economic development. For instance,
plant biotechnologies, including genetic trans¬
formation of crop species and varieties, are
complementary to conventional crop breeding
and selection of cultivars.
The value of biotechnologies is that they can
be applied at different levels of complexity,
investment and effort in the production of
food crops, livestock husbandry, chemical and
pharmaceutical industries, the conversion of
biomass into fuel, the transformation of agri¬
cultural and industrial by-products and pollu¬
tion abatement. Developing countries are now
taking advantage of these characteristics. This
trend will continue.
r\ cell culture laboratory
in Egypt.
EDGAR j. DASILVA, a
microbiologist and former
vice-president of the World
Federation of Culture
Collections (VVFCC), is
responsible for the life sciences
in UNESCO's Basic Sciences
Division. He has been largely
responsible for the preparation
and implementation of the
MIRCENs (Microbiological
Resources Centres)
programme.
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
fHE MAGIC OF MUSHROOMS
by R Atthasampunna and S.T Chang Fungus with
a future
THE mushroom has always been a
thing of mystery. In ancient times the
seemingly miraculous manner of its
growth without seed, its sudden appearance
after rain, its equally rapid disappearance and
ts curious umbrella-like shape gave rise to a
ealth of allusions and mythologies. Today, it
is continuing to perform feats of magic and
versatility, not only as a source of food, but by
helping to convert agricultural and industrial
wastes into useful matter.
16
I he mushroom as symbol
of longevity. Detail of a
Korean painting (late- 1 8th,
early- 1 9th century).
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Edible mushrooms provide high quality
protein that can be produced with greater
biological efficiency than animal protein. They
are rich in fibre, minerals and vitamins, and
have a low crude fat content. These properties
are major contributing factors to the tradi¬
tional recognition of mushrooms as "healthy"
food.
However, although a large number of
mushroom species are not only edible but
also possess tonic and medicinal qualities,
some are lethally poisonous. There is no
simple way of distinguishing between edible
and poisonous mushrooms, and one should
eat mushrooms only if one knows their names
and their properties with considerable preci¬
sion.
Mushroom cultivation, moreover, requires
relatively little in terms of large-scale equip¬
ment, capital, land and processing. In the rural
areas of less-developed countries, where large-
scale capital-intensive operations are inap¬
propriate, well-managed mushroom farms
can make important contributions to the
nutrition and economic welfare of the local
people. This is especially true in regions where
the indigenous population suffers from pro¬
tein deficiency.
Nature's garbage man
However, the mushroom would not be
worthy of its versatile reputation if it were
only a source of food. It can also help to solve
one of humankind's most urgent and growing
problems its propensity to create waste.
The agricultural, forestry and food pro¬
cessing industries generate huge quantities of
wastes, much of which is either burnt, dis¬
charged into watercourses or used for landfill.
And yet it constitutes a potentially valuable
resource. Most agricultural, industrial and
household solid wastes are rich in organic
matter, mainly cellulose, hemicellulose and
lignin, substances that are highly resistant to
biological degradation and have little or no
food value in their original form. Further¬
more, their disposal can be a major source of
environmental pollution. However, when
properly treated with bioconversion tech¬
nology the process whereby micro-organ¬
isms are used to transform organic residues
into utility products they can be modified
and upgraded into high-quality protein for
human and animal consumption, and used
for the production of microbial metabolites
and the generation of new feedstocks for the
polymer industry, which creates materials
such as plastics, resins and synthetic rubbers.
Edible mushroom production is a partic¬
ularly effective form of bioconversion tech¬
nology. Mushrooms differ from green plants
in that they cannot use sunlight to manufac¬
ture their food. What they do is produce
enzymes that degrade the complex substrates
on which they grow and then feed themselves
on the soluble substances thus produced. They
can be cultivated on a wide variety of woody
and cellulose wastes, and the spent residue
left after harvesting can be used as an animal
feedstock and/or a soil conditioner.
There is also rapidly growing interest in
/\bove, Shiii take (Lentinus
edodes), a fragrant
mushroom grown in Japan
from which a natural
product, active against
certain types of tumour, is
extracted.
Below left, the poisonous
mushroom fly agaric
(Amanita muscaria).
P. ATTHASAMPUNNA of
Thailand, is Director of the
Microbial Resources Centre
(MlRCEN) at the Thailand
Institute of Scientific and
Technological Research,
Bangkok. She is a specialist in
biofuel research and also heads
the Microbial Culture Service
Unit at her country's National
Centre for Genetic Engineering
and Biotechnology.
S.T. CHANG, of Australia, is a
specialist in fungal genetics. A
former Executive Secretary of
the Headquarters of
UNESCO's Southeast Asian
Network on Microbiology, he
is now Chairman of the
Biology Department at the
Chinese University of Hong
Kong and Director of the
Hong Kong MlRCEN on
Bioconversion Technology. He
is a member at large of the
Executive Board of the
International Union of
Microbiological Societies.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Mushroom spore used to
inoculate wood with fungus
for growing Shii take on a
mushroom "farm" in
Texas (U.S.A.).
Cultivated mushrooms
are grown in former
quarries near Paris on
sacks of manure covered
with crushed chalky soil.
The harvest lasts from
3 to 6 months.
mushrooms as a source of high-value metabo¬
lites, substances which can be used to treat
tumours, strengthen the immune system and
reduce blood pressure and cholesterol levels.
One such substance, PSK, also known as
Krestin, is made from the mushroom Coriolus
versicolor and has become the best-selling
anti-cancer drug in Japan, where it has 25 per
cent of market share and in 1987 had an annual
sale of $357 million. One Japanese company
has annual sales of lentinan, a polysaccharide
derived from another mushroom, Lentinus
edodes, amounting to $90 million. These nat¬
ural products are active against certain types
of tumours and have the advantage of not
being toxic to non-target cells.
Mushrooms also represent a relatively
untapped source of novel products for use in
the food and drink industries as illustrated
by the growing number of products reaching
the retail market. Important examples include
natural food additives such as colorants and
flavour compounds that can be used to replace
chemical additives that are often considered
less acceptable. Furthermore, the food
industry is already subject to consumer pres¬
sure to produce "healthy" foods and, as the
emphasis on prevention rather than cure of
diet-related diseases grows, this trend will
become even stronger.
It should be noted that world production
of cultivated edible mushrooms is, well, mush¬
rooming. Nearly 4,000 tons of mushrooms
were cultivated worldwide in 1989-1990, a
dramatic increase from just over 2,000 tons
cultivated in 1986. There has been a particu¬
larly sharp increase in growth over the last five
years. This trend is expected to continue in the
future.
While it is likely that more low-tech
processes such as mushroom bioconversion
technology will be of interest to developing
countries, it is certain that the application of
microbial biotechnology to solid organic
wastes will be an important tool for their food
industries and environmental management in
the years to come.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Known since Antiquity,
fermentation processes offer
great opportunities to today's
food industry
FERMENTED foods and beverages, in their
many and varied forms, have been a great
source of pleasure to humans over the cen¬
turies. The ancient art of cheese-making involves the
fermentation of milk or cream. Bread involves a
yeast fermentation, and loaves of bread have been
found in Egyptian pyramids built 6,000 years ago.
The discovery of fruit fermentation was made so
long ago that the ancient Greeks believed that wine
had been invented by one of their gods, Dionysus.
And from about 2500 B.C., Egyptian documents
describe the malting of barley and the fermentation
CREATIVE FERMENT
by Peter L. Rogers
of beer. Kui, a Chinese rice beer, has been traced
back to 2300 B.C. More than 3,000 years ago, the
Chinese used mouldy soybean curd to clear up
skin infections and Indians living in central America
used fungi to treat infected wounds. The Pénicillium
mould in cheese-making was often used for similar
purposes.
It is only since the time of Louis Pasteur, who in
1 857 established that alcoholic fermentations were
caused by living cells, that we have begun to under¬
stand the fundamental role of micro-organisms in
these fermentation processes. In fact, the successful
development of the food industry in Western coun¬
tries has involved the use of micro-organisms not
only to enhance the flavour, texture and nutritional
qualities of many foods and beverages, but also to
control spoilage through sterilization and proper
packaging. In other societies as well, control of
spoilage has been achieved by fermentation.
In recent times, there has been a growing interest
Above, rows of ewe's milk
cheeses in a cave at
Roquefort-sur-Soulzon in
the Aveyron department
of France. Bread-mould
(inset) is added to the
cheeses as they ripen.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
in studying traditional food fermentations with a
view to understanding the characteristics of the
micro-organisms and to designing better processes
for foods with enhanced flavours and better nutri¬
tional and preservative qualities.
A recipe for flavoursome fish sauce
Fermented foods can be classified broadly into
three types, depending on the way the fermentation
is carried out. Some fermentations occur under
liquid culture conditions, some take place almost
entirely on solid material, while others are a com¬
bination of both. Some of these processes are now
being practised on a very large industrial scale, but
it is important to remember that most, if not all, had
their origins in traditional small-scale activities.
In liquid culture fermentations, the raw mate¬
rials for the fermentation are allowed to solubilize
or are mixed together with large quantities of water.
Then either a specific inoculum is added to start a
new culture, or a natural culture develops. A good
example is the production of fish sauce, which has
been practised widely in Korea, Japan and other
Asian countries for centuries. Because fish are
highly proteinaceous, they spoil very rapidly in
tropical temperatures. To make fish sauce, the fish
is normally mixed with salt (20-35 per cent) and
allowed to solubilize in vats or tanks at tropical
ambient temperatures.
The maturation process, which involves the
transformation of the fish tissue into simpler com¬
pounds (by the action of enzymes) and the subse¬
quent growth of beneficial microbial flora (which
suppresses harmful micro-organisms) usually takes
three to twelve months or longer. During this period
special bacteria and yeasts, which are capable of
surviving the higher salt concentrations, develop and
give the final fish sauce its distinctive flavour and
aroma. Other examples of liquid culture fermenta¬
tions are fermented milk products such as yoghurt
and soy sauce. (Soy sauce production was described
in seventh-century Chinese and Japanese litera¬
ture and more than one million kilolitres of it are
produced annually in Japan today.)
Semi-solid fermentations are usually carried
out with solids such as grains or chopped vegetables
that are mixed with water and allowed to ferment.
The production of ogi, a traditional African fer¬
mented starch cake made from maize, sorghum or
millet grains, is a good example of a semi-solid
process. Fermentation is anaerobic and sponta¬
neous, and requires only one or two days. During
this time, the ogi develops a yoghurt-type flavour
which is a critical factor in its acceptability. Various
moulds and bacteria have been identified during the
fermentation process and it is evident that Lacto¬
bacillus bacteria are responsible for the produc¬
tion of lactic acid, which is the major component of
In Abomey (Benin), a girl
sells yovo-dofco, a fritter
made of marwè, a
fermented paste of sugar,
yeast, wheat and maize
flour.
PETER L. ROGERS, of
Australia, is a Professor of
Biotechnology at the
University of New South
Wales. A member of
UNESCO's Southeast Asian
Network on Microbiology
since 1975, he has
published extensively on
fermentation processes and
the application of recombinant
micro-organisms.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ogi flavour. The industrial production of ogi is
based on an upgraded village method and the final
product is a dry form of the starch cake that has a
longer shelf-life.
A soybean-enriched variant called soy-ogi has
about 15 per cent protein content and has been
used to treat children suffering from kwashiorkor,
a protein deficiency disease. Other well-known
semi-solid fermentations are the fermented veg¬
etable products of sauerkraut and the Korean
kimchi.
The third type of fermentation, solid substrate
fermentation, can be seen in the creation of soybean
tempeh, a fermented product consumed as a staple
food in Indonesia and other countries in Southeast
Asia.
Tempeh manufacture involves a two-step fer¬
mentation process. In the first stage, soybeans are
soaked in tap water for twelve to twenty-four hours
during which an acid fermentation develops. After
soaking, the soybeans are boiled in water, drained,
cooled and then arranged in trays for the second fer¬
mentation, which is conducted with the fungus
Rhizopus oligosporus. A mixed culture of bacteria
and fungi occur, with the bacteria being very impor¬
tant in improving the nutritional content, in par¬
ticular enhancing vitamin B12.
In Indonesia, tempeh is eaten by all sectors of the
population and is often used as a substitute for
meat among many low income groups as it is an
excellent high protein food that can be preserved
without the need for expensive refrigeration. It is
also becoming increasingly popular among vege¬
tarians in Western countries in the form of tempeh
burgers.
Besides tempeh, other examples of such
solid substrate fermentations include fermented
meat products, cheese making and the produc¬
tion of gari, a staple in parts of Africa such as
Nigeria.
UNESCO'S INTERNATIONAL NETWORK
OF MICROBIAL RESOURCES CENTRES
The microbe is helping to free Third World farmers from dependence
on costly chemical fertilizers
Progress in biotechnology depends to a large extent on the availability of
microbes. To meet this need UNESCO, in active collaboration with the United
Nations Environment Programme (UNEP), began in the 1970s to establish a
network of Microbiological Resources Centres (MIRCENs) directed to the
needs of developing countries. The first MIRCENs were six regional centres
in Nairobi (Kenya), Porto Alegro (Brazil), Bangkok (Thailand), Dakar (Senegal),
Cairo (Egypt) and Guatemala City. Although the MlRCEN concept applies mainly
to the developing countries, "technical" MIRCENs began to be established in
the 1980s in the technologically advanced countries, and today the UNESCO
network comprises twenty-seven centres in twenty countries.
The MIRCENs provide facilities for the management, distribution and
use of microbial gene pools world-wide, assist in the conservation of micro¬
organisms and encourage the development of new inexpensive technologies
for specific regions. They promote the applications of microbiology to
strengthen rural economies, and provide local centres for training, particularly
in the developing countries. Each one has a special research interest. Sev¬
eral MIRCENs in developing countries are particularly concerned with research
into biofertilizer technology so as to lessen their regions' dependence on expen¬
sive chemically derived fertilizer that may have adverse effects on the envi¬
ronment. The Nairobi MlRCEN has built up a venture whereby over 20,000
packets of quality-controlled biofertilizer or "black ash" are provided to
farmers in Kenya and surrounding areas of East Africa.
Training is a particularly important activity, and many researchers, exten¬
sion workers and industrial technical staff have benefitted from short courses
and intensive on-the-job training programmes organized at the different cen¬
tres. In 1991 UNESCO launched a scheme for short-term fellowships in
biotechnology whereby scientists, particularly from the least developed and
developing countries, can carry out research at a MlRCEN and learn to use
techniques that are not normally accessible to them. So far 112 Fellow¬
ships have been awarded. For further information please write to:
UNESCO MlRCEN Short-term Fellowships in Biotechnology,
Division of Basic Sciences (Attn. Dr. E. J. DaSilva),
UNESCO, 1 rue Miollis,
75015 Paris, France.
Tel. (33-1) 45 68 38 83 - 45 68 41 82
Fax: (33-1) 43 06 11 22 - 45 67 16 90
i
Nuoc, a fermented fish
sauce widely consumed
in Asia, is stored in these
containers at a small
Vietnamese factory.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Brewing p/'tto, a kind of
beer, in northern Ghana.
Gari is a gritty, pre-cooked, dry starch food pro¬
duced by fermentation of cassava roots. Although
it is a good source of calories, it is deficient in pro¬
teins, vitamins and minerals.
Remarkable advances
Although the major commercial emphasis of
biotechnology in recent years has been the pro¬
duction of recombinant proteins for pharmaceutical
purposes, there are also many opportunities in food
biotechnology that will make an impact on both
developing and developed countries.
The new opportunities in food biotechnology
can be grouped into four main areas: the improve¬
ment of microbial cultures, larger and improved fer¬
mentation processes, improved food properties
and better detection of contaminations.
Many indigenous fermented foods are pro¬
duced on a very small scale either in homes or in
small-scale cottage industries in villages. In these sit¬
uations, the microbial cultures are often traditional
and highly variable. For example, some types of
tempeh in Indonesia are produced by wrapping
the soaked soybeans in a hibiscus leaf, which pro¬
vides the natural flora for inoculation.
As our understanding of the microbial ecology
of such fermented foods has increased, there have
been efforts to produce a more standardized
inoculum which would create tempeh of higher
quality for the villagers. These programmes have
been initiated by government research laborato¬
ries in countries such as Indonesia and Malaysia.
A similar pattern has emerged in developed
countries involved in cheese-making: specific cul¬
tures of lactic acid producing bacteria are now
being supplied to manufacturers for better quality
cheeses. Techniques of genetic engineering are also
being used to isolate new strains that are resistant to
attack by various bacteriophages, small virus-like
particles that can infect the usual lactic acid bacteria
and cause the disintegration and dissolution of
cells.
Food biotechnology can also lead to improved
food properties. The main advantages provided by
fermentation include higher vitamin levels and
increased digestibility, better flavour and texture,
and longer storage properties. Inoculation with
selected micro-organisms can protect the foodstuff
against breakdown by contaminating micro-organ¬
isms. In many cases, metabolic products of the fer¬
mentation process such as acetic acid (vinegar),
lactic acid and alcohol provide natural inhibitory
compounds. In other cases, the fermenting micro¬
organisms can produce natural antibiotics, which
provide further protection against invaders. The
use of these antibiotics in food preservation is likely
to be an area of considerable importance in the
future.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER -JUNE 1994
DEFEATING
DECIBELS
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
Traffic and
low-flying
aircraft are
major causes
of noise
pollution in
cities. Right,
a Hong Kong
street.
1 hat is a drop of water? It's
the best way of demon¬
strating how noise is
transmitted. When a water
drop hits the surface of a
pond, it causes waves that spread
outward in concentric circles, just
as sound waves move through the
air. Moreover when the drop strikes
a resonant surface, it produces a
noise that may seem like torture
even if the impact is very mild. It is
not so much the intensity of noise
that makes it unbearable as its
repetitive nature, the attention we
give it and the impossibility of con¬
trolling it. Noise is becoming a
threat to human health, and as
such, ranks among the foremost
environmental problems in the
industrially developed countries
that are member States of the Orga¬
nization of Economic Co-opera¬
tion and Development (OECD).
"People consider noise to be the
main local environmental
problem, sometimes even more
important than air pollution or the
quality of drinking water," says an
OECD study, The State ofthe Envi¬
ronment, published in 1991.
Although they suffer just as much
from noise, the inhabitants of
developing countries don't talk
much about it, largely because it
is overshadowed by the demands of
the struggle for survival.
Noise is a blend of sounds. Its
frequency, i.e. the number of vibra¬
tions per second, is calibrated in
hertz. The human being perceives
sounds between 20 and 20,000 Hz,
while elephants are sensitive to
infra-sounds (less than 20 Hz) and
bats and dolphins, though virtu¬
ally blind, move about thanks to
ultra-sounds that they emit at
greater than 20,000 Hz. We experi¬
ence the sound level, expressed in
decibels (dB), as pressure on our
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
DEFEATING DECIBELS
ears. With the audible threshold
being zero dB, 85 is the risk level, 90
dB the danger level and 120 dB the
pain threshold. Beyond that the
ear-drum may rupture.
NOISES THAT HURT
It is therefore easy to understand
that too much noise can damage
our ears. What is more surprising is
that our health is affected in other
ways too. There are immediate
effects, i.e. cardio-vascular prob¬
lems with an accelerated heartbeat
and high blood pressure, gastric-
intestinal problems, a decrease in
alertness and ability to memorize,
nervousness, pupil dilation and a
decrease in the visual field. These
effects may be temporary; others
are longer lasting, e.g., insomnia,
nervousness, bulimia, chronically
high blood pressure, anxiety,
depression and even sexual mal¬
functions!
Discomfort may arise from even
very low noise levels. A couple, for
example, lives in a small town. Next
door there is a cock that crows at
dawn. The wife doesn't mind, but
her husband can't stand it. He
wakes up early and waits for the
cock to crow; when it does, he flies
into a rage. This happens every
morning until, rather than wring
the bird's neck, the couple moves
away. Another example. A sixty-
year-old widow lives alone. A
young couple moves into a semi¬
detached house next door that
they've just built. The noise of their
love-making enrages the widow,
and she lodges a complaint. An
expert measures the disturbance
caused and notes that there is no
possible effective sound insulation.
The judge orders the young lovers'
house to be pulled down; it is not in
conformity with the legal norms
of the building code.
Noise is a psychological fact. It
contains an emotional element. In
a manual entitled Noise and Its
Effects on Health the French Min¬
istry of Social Affairs emphasizes
that "active, ambitious people with
a sense of responsibility seem less
24
. r .. . >
' - - '.r£ jr. i ,
*. - -
The noise of
public-works
machinery is
highly
unpleasant for
operatives and
anyone else who
happens to be
near. Left
roadworks in
Panama City.
bothered by noise than introverted
people". It adds, "Certain groups
are more sensitive to noise or are
apt to be made more sensitive to it
by specific factors: those prone to
depression, hypochondria and
anxiety or who are going through a
difficult experience such as a
divorce, unemployment or rela¬
tional problems."
On the other hand deafness is
the most indisputable effect of
noise on people. An explosion of
140 dB can cause permanent deaf¬
ness, for it destroys certain cells in
the inner ear that do not regen¬
erate. Permanent deafness can also
occur gradually as a result of expo¬
sure to 85 dB sound-levels over sev¬
eral years. This level is not con¬
fined to factories where
occupational medicine, at least in
the rich countries, is trying to
reduce noise levels. A rock concert
emits as many decibels as a work¬
shop for testing jet-engines. The
noise-prevention brigade of Lau¬
sanne's city police department in
Switzerland received permission
to order the lowering ofnoise levels
at a concert given by the singer
Michael lackson, after posting the
following notice to spectators,
"Bring ear-plugs or cotton".
Moreover, the craze for the
Walkman has been held respon¬
sible for serious hearing problems
among the young. Germany has
calculated that noise-related health
costs and payments made for
hearing loss amount to nearly 4
billion dollars annually!
INCREASING SOUND POLLUTION
More than a third of the 400 million
inhabitants of the OECD countries
are exposed to a daily dose of 65
dB, an unacceptably high level; 200
million live in an uncomfortable
sound environment. The foremost
culprit is road traffic. Between 1970
and 1988 inlapan, for example, the
motorway network was extended
by 510 per cent, while the number
of motor vehicles increased by 200
per cent and total traffic grew by
126 per cent. Aircraft are guilty too.
They constitute a nuisance for 2
per cent of the population in the
United States, i.e. 5 million people,
four times more than in Europe or
lapan.
Trains disturb a smaller per¬
centage of people, usually depen-
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
ding on their frequency, the density
of the rail network and local topog¬
raphy. Factories, workshops and
building sites, though increasingly
well monitored, are no less a dis¬
turbance for a fair amount of the
population, not to mention for the
workers themselves. Among the
sources of neighbourhood noise
problems the cause of countless
complaints and court cases are
stereo systems and household
appliances, joint-housing equip¬
ment and barking dogs.
What can be done about rapidly
growing sound pollution? Australia
is the champion for noise reduc¬
tion. Some of its states require a
"noise" label for chainsaws, lawn-
mowers and pavement breakers.
When the police in the southern
city of Adelaide spot an unsafe or
noisy car on their roads, they pre¬
sent the owner with a "defect
notice". The car's registration is sus¬
pended until it has been repaired in
an authorized garage. In New
South Wales noisy vehicles can be
stopped and tested by the side of
the road. The excellent results thus
obtained are derived from close
co-operation between the police
and environmental officials.
However, Switzerland is the only
country with legislation designed
to ensure that the best possible
technology for reducing noise is
always used. It requires construc¬
tors, for example, to encapsulate
already low-noise-producing truck
engines. The costs are covered by
the users. Moreover, the Swiss
Society of Engineers and Architects
has defined the required norms for
sound-proofing building interiors:
stairwells, lifts and heating and
ventilation systems.
A NEW CHAPTER
IN ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION
In Switzerland, as in France, Aus¬
tralia and lapan, the authorities are
trying to promote the notion of
"quiet" communities with reduced
levels of industrial, traffic and
domestic noise. In Australia big
campaigns against noise, featuring
posters proclaiming, "Be neigh¬
bourly, it feels nice" or "A quiet day",
have a real impact on the popula¬
tion. In Switzerland the picture of a
black cat on wheels encourages
people to drive quietly. Unfortu¬
nately new problems are arising
more and more urgently in the
OECD countries, i.e. rapid increases
in motor traffic, especially planes
and trucks, increases in evening,
night-time and weekend noise
levels in rural areas, and a prolif¬
eration of motorized pleasure craft,
Walkmen and ghetto blasters.
The history of sound is linked
to the history of humanity. "The
acquisition of language," writes
sound engineer Denis Fortier, "then
of chanting and music, has taken
thousands of years of patient
learning, the time required for the
brain to learn oral and auditory
communication." The Greek
philosopher Pythagoras believed
that music enabled man to harmo¬
nize with the cosmos, which, long
before the theory of the Big Bang
was formulated, ancient India
believed was born from sound.
Sound is vital for communicating,
but when it becomes noise and a
nuisance, it can also kill communi¬
cation. From now on the fight
against noise must be a part of any
environmental policy.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists.
"A rock concert
emits as many
decibels as a
workshop for
testing jet
engines".
Above, Joe
Cocker at the
1976 Le
Castellet pop
festival in
France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
THE SUN, FRIEND OR FOE?
The World Health Organization
(WHO) believes that the public is
not sufficiendy aware of the dangers
posed by overexposure to ultra-violet
rays. As a result, an international
research programme on health,
ultra-violet sunlight and modi¬
fications to the environment
(INTERSUN) has been launched by
WHO, the International Cancer
Research Centre and the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP). It entails setting up a net¬
work ofcentres for monitoring solar
ultra-violet radiation at ground-level,
the exposure ofpopulations to it and
resulting health problems. Although
small doses are beneficial they help
stimulate our production ofvitamin
D prolonged or intensive exposure
could damage our immune system
and provoke skin and eye ailments.
THE FUTURE
OF MIGRATING WASTE
The United States administration is
seeking to ban exports ofhazardous
wastes except to Canada, Mexico,
lapan and western Europe, and has
asked Congress to approve a pro¬
posal to this effect. U.S. Greenpeace
has welcomed the move, which
would effectively ban the export of
toxic wastes to most developing
countries. In 1992 the U.S. Senate
approved the Basel Convention,
signed in 1989 by 116 countries, on
the control of transboundary move¬
ments ofhazardous wastes and their
disposal. However, the U.S. cannot
ratify the Convention until domestic
law is changed to conform to its pro¬
visions. Under the Convention,
importing countries must give their
consent and must possess adequate
disposal facilities. In practice, the
bulk of the 130,000 metric tons of
hazardous waste shipped by the
United States in 1992 went to Mexico
and Canada.
HOW TO WIN THE WAR
ON HUNGER
According to Mr. lacques Diouf,
Director-General of the United
Nations Food and Agriculture Orga¬
nization (FAO), by the year 2000 there
will be a billion more mouths to feed,
yet there will be 15 per cent less crop¬
land per head. Livestock is another
major area ofconcern. Ambylomma
variegatum, a parasite that attacks
cattle, sheep, goats, horses and dogs,
causes heavy financial losses. A pro¬
gramme exists for ridding the 14
already-infested Caribbean islands of
the parasite within five years and
preventing it from spreading to the
American continent. And there is
one success story to give us hope:
the fight against the new world
screwworm in north Africa was
crowned with success.
RUSSIA CREATES A HUGE
ARCTIC RESERYE
Ayear ago Russia decided to create a
stricdy protected zone ofmore than
40,000 square kilometres on the
Taimyr peninsula on the northern
Siberian coast, i.e. an area the size of
Switzerland. This zapovednik or
nature reserve, proposed by the
Russian Academy of Sciences and
the World Wide Fund for Nature
(WWF), is the most arctic landfall
for migratory birds. More than 150
species have been counted. There is
also a wide variety of marine life:
fish, seals and walruses, as well as
polar bears and the world's largest
herd ofwild reindeer. The decision to
"freeze" these lands, which are
already affected by pollution from'
nearby industry, is all the more
impressive since beneath them are
deposits ofprecious metals, coal, oil
and natural gas.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
PACHAMAMA,
MOTHER EARTH
Manuel Vegas-Velez, an expert in
marine biology, has written to tell
us ofhis activities in Peru, a country
rich in natural resources. Along its
coastline, which bathes in the tem¬
perate waters of the Humboldt cur¬
rent, live 700 species of fish, 800
species of molluscs and more than
300 species of shellfish. Tropical rain
forest still covers 61 per cent of the
country's area, and minerals such as
gold, iron and zinc are found there,
as well as oil and natural gas. A
non-governmental organization,
Pachamama, has launched a range
of projects to promote the wise
exploitation of these abundant
reserves. One project aims to restore
fertility to hills eroded by coca
growing. Another is concerned with
managing the two new marine
reserves ofMancora and the Illescas
and Lobos islands to the northwest
ofPeru. This team ofPeruvians, now
a member of The World Conserva¬
tion Union (IUCN), was self-
financed when it began operations
but is currently looking for assis¬
tance in order to carry out its pro¬
grammes.
Address: Camino Real 479, Lima 27
Peru. Tel: (51) 1442-8948, Fax (51)
411-990.
THE DANGERS OF CHEMICAL
ACCIDENTS
The Organization for Economic Co¬
operation and Development (OECD)
has published three guidance docu¬
ments about chemical accidents.
The first is designed to assist man¬
agers and other decision-makers in
developing appropriate policies and
plans of action. The second docu¬
ment is a more detailed and tech¬
nical practical guide to action in the
event of a chemical accident. The
third, ChecklistforAction, is aimed at
persons with overall managerial
responsibility for chemical accident
contingency planning (in French and
English). OECD, 2, rue André-Pascal,
75775 Paris Cedex 16, Fax (33-1)
4524-1675.
CANADA'S CONTEST
BETWEEN FIR
AND BIRCH TREES
After a forest-fire it seems to make
sense that the new trees growing in
should be the same as those burned
down. Not so, say Ross Wein and
Simon Landhausser, researchers at
Canada's University of Alberta.
Conifers, they have found, tend to
give way to birches and poplars, a
phenomenon they attribute to the
climate, which is warmer and drier
nowadays than at the beginning of
the century and better suited to
broad-leaved trees than to the cold-
preferring cone-bearers. The light
seeds of broad-leaved trees are car¬
ried by the wind and are gradually
colonizing the northern regions at
the expense of coniferous trees.
Could this really be a proofofglobal
warming?
77
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
INITIATIVES
THE LESSON OF EASTER ISLAND
Birth rates
and child death
rates both
decline when
countries
expand access
to health and
family planning
services
and education
for girls.
| Above, a school
in Viet Nam.
Population Action Interna¬
tional (PAI) is an American
non-governmental organiza¬
tion whose work is inspired by a his¬
torical event. When a group ofPoly¬
nesian voyagers arrived on Easter
Island in the fifth or sixth century
AD, they found a plentiful supply of
natural resources and created a
unique civilization, now famous for
its enormous and mysterious stone
statues. But studies of fossilized pol¬
lens have shown that as the popu¬
lation grew, the lush green forest
diminished, leading to a fatal ero¬
sion of the fertile soil and disap¬
pearance of the island's wildlife.
When a Dutch traveller set foot on
the island in 1722, he observed that
it was completely barren. Deprived
of natural resources, the 3,000
people living on the island spent
their time fighting fratricidal wars. In
other words, environment and pop¬
ulation are inextricably linked.
Human overpopulation exhausts
the earth, which, in turn, can no
longer feed that population.
In the past, as Population Action
International (PAI) points out,
"People altered local landscapes;
today we are changing the earth
itself. And the parables of the past
send a warning: Nature has the
upper hand. If human activities
cause climate to warm dramatically
or soil to wear out or water sources
to fail, the risk to humanity will be
incalculable". Yet as long as the
world's wealth is not shared more
equitably and children's health not
better guaranteed, couples in the
most disadvantaged nations will
continue to resort to large families as
away to insure against old age.
Family planning is not PAI's only
concern. It also conducts pro¬
grammes for promoting studies for
girls, especially in south Asia, the
Middle East and Africa where the
largest disparities in school enroll¬
ment exist between boys and girls. In
1992 it launched a population and
environment programme, one of
the results of which was an inter¬
esting pamphlet on water manage¬
ment for the planet. It is the first in
a series of case studies analysing the
effects ofdemographic pressure on
natural resources.
PAI was founded in 1965 as a
non-profit organization. It has an
annual budget of about 3 million
$US and receives no support from
the American government or from
multi-lateral agencies such as the
World Bank or the United States
Agency for International Develop¬
ment (U.S. AID), the policies of
which it does not hesitate to criticize
when it thinks fit.
Contact Robert Engelman, Director,
Population and Environment
Program, PAI, 1120 19th Street,
suite 550, Washington D.C. 20036,
Tel: (1-202) 659-1833, Fax: (1-202)
293-1795.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A RISING IIDE
by Rita Colwell
Marine
biotechnology is
transforming our
knowledge and
use of the sea's
resources
I he Kombu alga is grown
on Rishiri, an island
adjacent to Hokkaido
(Japan).
RITA COLWELL, of the
United States, is President of
the University of Maryland
Biotechnology Institute.
Adviser to several public
bodies, national and
international, she is a member
of the Executive Board of the
International Council of
Scientific Unions and of the
Scientific Advisory Committee
of the United Nations
University's Biotechnology in
Latin America and the
Caribbean programme. She is
the author or editor of 16
books, author or co-author of
several hundred papers and
articles and produced an
award-winning documentary,
Invisible Seas, on marine
microbiology.
IT is only a decade since marine biotech¬
nology was first recognized as an area
of great potential. In that short span of
time astonishing progress has been made.
Some of the most striking advances have
been in the aquaculture industry, where direct
genetic manipulation using recombinant DNA
techniques has made it possible to develop an
entirely new approach to fish farming. This is
important because of the significant expansion
of aquaculture in recent years. According to
some estimates aquaculture may be supplying
25 per cent of world seafood consumption by
the end of the century.
Fish are highly amenable to genetic manip¬
ulation because their eggs are large and can
therefore be injected with DNA constructs.
Major research efforts in genetic manipulation
have been directed towards enhancing the
growth and production of fish with superior
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Below, a mullet is given
an injection of hormones
at the Hawaii Oceanic
Institute.
Bottom photo, carp eggs
seen through a microscope
at Ahrensburg Scientific
Institute (Germany).
When they hatch, the
alevin are kept immobile in
heated water and fed with
granules of egg white.
They grow three times
more quickly than in
natural conditions.
resistance to cold temperatures. With the spread
of intensive fish farming and the concomitant
increased risk of disease, the development of
disease-resistant fish has also become an
increasingly important objective.
Goldfish with a human gene
The first successful growth hormone experi¬
ment using fish was the transfer into a goldfish
of the human growth hormone gene, yielding
offspring significantly larger than untreated
fish. Since then, several vertebrate genes have
been introduced into fish species, including
Atlantic salmon.
Of more practical significance has been the
achievement of growth enhancement using fish
growth hormone. In several experiments, fish
injected with growth hormone reached double
the weight increment of untreated fish over a
sixty-day period. However, as growth hor¬
mone is not easy to administer to fish, research
is now focusing on generating transgenic fish.
Up to 1990, thirteen transgenic fish species
30
had been reported, including transgenic variants
of commercial varieties such as the Atlantic
salmon, channel catfish, carp and tilapia.
Research is now underway to determine the
physiological, nutritional and environmental
factors that maximize the performance of trans¬
genic fish. Major problems of safety and envi¬
ronmental impact must also be solved before
large-scale, commercial production of trans¬
genic fish will be permitted.
Antifreeze for salmon
Genetic manipulation of Atlantic salmon has
been carried out to try and increase the resis¬
tance of this species to cold. Many marine fish
that live in cold water produce proteins which
act as an "antifreeze" and protect them by
inhibiting the formation of ice crystals in their
serum. Atlantic salmon lack genes for the pro¬
duction of these proteins and therefore cannot
survive in icy waters. However, genes coding
for antifreeze proteins have now been trans¬
ferred to Atlantic salmon, and the expression of
adequate concentrations of these proteins in
their blood could extend the range of envi¬
ronments where this fish can be grown.
Shellfish are also amenable to genetic
manipulation, especially for enhancing their
rate of growth and their size. It has been shown
that bovine growth hormone can enhance the
growth rates of California red abalone, and
similar results have been reported for the appli¬
cation of biosynthetic rainbow trout growth
hormone to young oysters.
Unlike fish and shellfish, anthropoids such
as lobsters shed their exoskeletons during
growth by means of a moulting process that is
under hormonal control. Thus, regulation of
moulting by the hormone-secreting endocrine
gland may improve growth efficiency in the
lobster. However, knowledge of the molecular
genetics of marine crustaceans such as shrimp,
lobster and prawns must be expanded before
commercial production of these species will
be efficient and reliable. Growth, development,
and disease resistance have yet to be controlled.
One factor on which the successful
exploitation of a fish or shellfish species in
aquaculture depends is the ability to obtain
consistent, controlled reproduction as eco¬
nomically as possible. It has been shown that
water temperature and the period of daily illu¬
mination the fish receive can be manipulated
sufficiently to improve spawning. Fortunately,
some important advances have been made
recently in the use of hormone treatment to
control reproduction of fish species that are
important in aquaculture.
The farming of marine macroalgae sea¬
weed has been practised for several cen¬
turies in Asian countries, particularly Japan,
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Above, dried dihé, a blue
alga rich in protein,
mineral salts and vitamins.
It is harvested by women,
top, in pools in parts of
Chad, where it constitutes
an essential part of the
diet.
and products derived from them have been
widely used as sources of medicine and food.
Macro- and microalgae yield a wide range
of products, including food additives and
supplements, culture media, pesticides, plant
growth regulators and antibacterial, anti¬
cancer and antiviral agents.
Seaweed for medicine and food
Microalgae have proved useful for large-scale
production of fatty acids which may help to
reduce the risk of coronary vascular disease.
The green microalga Dunaliella salina is
grown in large-scale, intensive culture in
California to produce beta-carotene, a sub¬
stance associated with the prevention of
cancer. It has also been suggested that oceanic
farming of marine algae could reduce global
carbon dioxide levels.
The application of biotechnology to the
cultivation of marine algae presents an
opportunity for countries near rivers and
the ocean, especially developing countries
with extensive coastal regions. This potential
is most likely to be realized by the formation
of partnerships with industrialized coun¬
tries. However, to achieve success, an under¬
standing of molecular genetics and an appli¬
cation of the techniques of modern molecular
biology will be required. Although molecular
techniques have not yet been widely applied
to achieve strain enhancement or the pro¬
duction of transgenic plants and algae of
commercial importance, this approach is now
being adopted in several laboratories in the
United States, Asia and Europe.
Marine organisms are sources of a very
wide range of natural products that have bio¬
medical, biotechnological, agricultural and
industrial applications. Chitin is one such
product that has made it to market in a
variety of forms as poultices to heal
wounds, extenders, and emulsifiers for pho¬
tography yet still remains a focus of exten¬
sive study. If and when the genes for chitin
synthesis are cloned, the production of this
compound will increase immeasurably since
a stable source can then be obtained.
In the past decade, more than 1,000 new
compounds, natural products, and other dis¬
coveries relating to the molecular genetics
of fish and shellfish growth, metabolism and
reproduction have been recorded. Promising
new antibiotics, anti-cancer therapeutic
agents, improved aquaculture stocks and
food additives have cither been discovered or
are in the development stage. Where once
only a few pioneers toiled in their laborato¬
ries, there are now major new centres of
biotechnology research and development in
Norway, Japan, the United States and else¬
where. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Only
biotechnology
can make it
possible to
produce enough
food to keep
pace with the
world's swelling
population
FROM THE GREEN REVOLUTION
TO THE GENE REVOLUTION
jf Indra K, Vasil and Luis Herrera-Estrella
T~| HE rapidly-growing world popula¬
tion and increasing demand for more
and better food are certain to pose
serious threats to social, political, economic
and environmental stability early in the twenty-
first century. Without a decline in the current
rates of growth, today's population of nearly
5.5 billion is projected to nearly double to 10.7
billion by the year 2030. Almost all of this
growth will occur in the already overpopu-
lated and impoverished countries of Africa,
Asia and Latin America, which will be home to
nine out of every ten human beings.
In this near future, additional land for
growing food as well as for meeting all the
other needs of the expanding population will
have to be derived from the destruction of the
already dwindling and endangered but pre¬
cious protected natural areas. Undoubtedly,
these changes will place unprecedented strain
not only on the global, social, political and
economic infrastructure, but will also cause
further deterioration of the fragile environ¬
ment of our already fully occupied planet. It is
doubtful that world food production, which is
barely adequate to meet today's needs, can
keep pace with current rates of population
growth. Indeed, in the past few years crop
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Ina U.S. Department of
Agriculture plant genetics
laboratory at Beltsville
(Maryland) fluorescent
bands of DNA are
photographed under
ultraviolet light.
Left, growing improved
wheat varieties in India.
yields have generally levelled off or have actu¬
ally declined in many of the developing coun¬
tries.
What can be done to reverse or at least fore¬
stall these dangerous and suicidal trends? First
and foremost it is necessary to bring down the
rate of population growth to a sustainable level.
In the interim, food production must be dra¬
matically increased. Scientists expect that plant
improvement through the use of biotechnology
will be an important part of this process.
Plants in the human diet
Ninety-eight per cent of global food produc¬
tion is land-based. Of the total human diet, 92
per cent is derived from plants, with no more
than thirty plant species accounting for most of
the calories and protein intake. Cereal grains
like wheat, rice and maize alone provide more
than 53 per cent of the world food supply.
Historically, major technological advances
in agriculture have been a driving force for
economic growth, political stability and social
and cultural development. In recent history,
the most dramatic results of agricultural
improvement were those of the Green Revo¬
lution, which was based on the introduction
and adoption of high yielding and otherwise
improved varieties of wheat and rice devel¬
oped at the international agricultural centres in
Mexico and the Philippines, in close co-oper
ation with national agricultural programmes.
The introduction of these varieties, partic¬
ularly in Mexico, India, Pakistan, Bangladesh
and China, in the mid-to-late 1960s helped not
only to save millions from starvation and death
but also to prevent widespread social and polit¬
ical unrest.
It was in recognition of this that the Nobel
Peace Prize was awarded to Norman Borlaug,
the American agronomist who developed vari¬
eties of "miracle" wheat in Mexico and played
a seminal role in the introduction of such vari¬
eties in the developing countries of Asia and
Latin America.
The benefits of the Green Revolution con¬
tinue to be felt in the developing world. During
the 1980s, agricultural production in China
rose at an annual rate of 8 per cent, making it
the largest producer of food in the world. In the
developing countries as a whole, wheat and
rice production increased by about 75 per cent
in the fifteen years between 1965 and 1980.
From 1950 to 1980, wheat production increased
four-fold in Mexico, while rice production
doubled in Indonesia. Similarly, wheat pro¬
duction in India increased three-fold in less
than twenty years, from 1965 to 1983. The
introduction of similar improved agricultural
practices combined with high quality seed on
a limited scale in parts of Africa, under the
leadership of Norman Borlaug, has increased
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
INDRA K.VASIL, of the
United States, is a Professor of
Plant Cell and Molecular
Biology at the University of
Florida, United States, where
his laboratory is noted for
research on the biotechnology
and molecular improvement of
cereal crops. Chairman of
UNESCO's Biotechnology
Action Council, he is author or
co-author of more than 325
research publications and
editor or co-editor of 18
books.
LUIS HERRERA-ESTRELLA,
of Mexico, is Head of the
Department of Plant Genetic
Engineering at the Centre for
Research and Advanced
'Studies, National Polytechnic,
Irapuato, Mexico. He received
UNESCO's JavedHusain
Award for Young Scientists for
his work on the genetic
transformation of Latin
American crops, particularly
for resistance to plant
pathogens.
Delow, cassava plants
produced by cloning at the
Institute of Tropical
Agriculture, Ibadan
(Nigeria).
Below right, a tiny peach
plant produced in the
laboratory by cloning.
the yields of maize, sorghum and millet by 300
to 400 per cent.
Plant improvement: a slow process
The process of plant improvement is painfully
slow, however, and is generally limited to the
discovery of useful genes in wild germ plasm
and their introduction into commercial varieties
during many years of breeding and selection.
The process is also restricted to recombina¬
tion of genes within the same or similar species
because of biological limits to hybridization
between unrelated species.
It is highly doubtful that conventional plant
breeding alone can help produce the vast quan¬
tities of food that will be needed to feed the bil¬
lions more people that are expected to inhabit
the earth during the next few decades. It is in
this context that biotechnology has attracted
great attention, for it provides an excellent
opportunity to supplement and complement
plant breeding by providing mechanisms for
the introduction of agronomically useful genes
into crop species by overcoming all barriers to
gene transfer between species.
In addition, it has already been demon¬
strated that crop species can be engineered to
make them resistant to certain insects and
viruses, as well as to compete successfully
against weeds. Introduction of such technolo¬
gies on a wide scale could immediately increase
the amount of available food by more than
one-third, by saving from destruction food
that is lost to pests, pathogens and weeds. This
would give us the needed time to integrate
biotechnology into the traditional methods of
plant breeding to improve the quantity and
quality of food produced by plants.
If carefully planned, co-ordinated and
implemented, plant biotechnologies could have
such a profound impact on world food pro¬
duction as to bring about a Gene Revolution in
the twenty-first century. It is vitally impor¬
tant, however, that the practice and benefits
of plant biotechnology should not be limited to
North America, Western Europe and Japan,
where much of the current activity is concen¬
trated, but be systematically introduced into the
poor and developing countries where the needs
are urgent and compelling.
Simple, inexpensive procedures
Plant biotechnology has two important com¬
ponents, one based on the use of tissue culture
methods, and the other involving a combina¬
tion of cellular and molecular biology. Each
offers powerful methods for plant production
and improvement. Many of the procedures
involved are simple and can be practised
without substantial investment in facilities and
infrastructure for the rapid mass production
and multiplication of plants.
One of these technologies is clonal propa¬
gation or meristem culture, the process that
occurs when shoot buds of plants are isolated
and placed in culture in the presence of plant
hormones so that many new shoot buds form.
Such buds can be separated from each other and
induced to form roots and complete plants.
Rapid, large scale and economical clonal mul¬
tiplication is of particular value for many forest
and fruit trees, plantation crops, endangered
species and medicinal plants.
As a rule, one shoot bud placed in a culture
can be made to produce more than a million
plants in one year. The rate of multiplication
can be further improved and the costs sub¬
stantially reduced by automation of much
of the process. It is significant that all the plants
produced from the initial shoot bud are iden¬
tical to each other as well as the source material.
This is of paramount importance where a
selected and valuable variety is being multi¬
plied and no genetic variation is desired.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
I he southern delta of
Viet Nam is home to many
varieties of valuable wild
rice. However, the wild
plants (at left in photo) are
often considered as weeds
by farmers and are being
replaced by new varieties.
Www
The well-established and reliable methods
of clonal propagation are simple and do not
require elaborate and expensive laboratory
facilities. They can be easily and profitably
practised as a small-scale industry at the village
level, not only to provide quality material for
plantings but also as a source of employment
and earnings. This technology is potentially
most useful for reforestation of vast areas in
Asia, Africa, Latin America and Eastern
Europe.
Global reforestation using this method can
greatly reduce the damaging effects of pollution
and acid rain, the dangers of the greenhouse
effect, soil erosion and flooding, while pre¬
serving precious natural sources of energy and
providing a natural habitat for endangered
flora and fauna.
Another important use of meristem cul¬
ture is the elimination of viruses, which cause
more than 50 per cent yield loss in many crops,
especially those which are propagated vegeta-
tively, such as potato, sugarcane, cassava and
banana. Cells at the extreme tip of a shoot are
generally devoid of virus particles. Plants
obtained from the culture of very small shoot
buds are, therefore, free of viruses, and provide
maximum yields of quality material. This tech¬
nology is well established and can be practised
on a large or small scale as necessary.
The most powerful and useful methods of
biotechnology are those that involve genetic
transformation, the transfer of genes, at the
level of DNA, from one species to another.
Two main strategies have been used for this
purpose. The first and most commonly used
method is based on a natural system offered by
the soil-borne micro-organism, Agrobacterium
tumefaciens (crown gall bacterium); the second
uses the direct physical delivery of DNA from
one organism to another.
The crown gall bacterium contains a circular
piece of DNA, called the Ti (tumour inducing)
plasmid. During normal infection of a plant
by the bacterium, a part of the plasmid called
T-DNA (transfer DNA) is transferred to the
host plant cell and becomes permanently inte¬
grated into its nuclear DNA. The T-DNA con¬
tains left and right border sequences which are
necessary for its transfer to the plant cell. In
between are genes that control the synthesis of
certain plant growth regulators that cause the
crown gall disease.
rxice seeds are sterilized
before being sent to the
International Rice
Research Institute at Los
Baños (Philippines).
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
For directed plant transformation, the Ti-
plasmid is disarmed by removing the genes
responsible for tumour induction and replacing
them with genes of interest. The useful genes
are then transferred by the bacterium to the
host plant cell during an infection process that
does not result in the crown gall disease.
Because of its simplicity and ease of use, this
method has been used extensively since the
production of the first transgenic plants (plants
in which foreign genes have been transferred by
genetic transformation) in 1983.
Unfortunately, for a variety of reasons that
are still not clearly understood, the cereal grains
such as wheat, rice and maize are not amenable
to transformation by Agrobacterium. Fortu¬
nately, several methods of direct DNA delivery
, have been developed to produce transgenic
cereals.
Currently, the molecular genetic improve¬
ment of plants is not limited so much by tech¬
niques for DNA transfer as by the relatively
low number of agronomically useful genes that
have been identified, characterized and cloned
at the molecular level. The best characterized
and therefore mos't widely used are the genes
that confer resistance to insect pests, to viruses
and to broad spectrum herbicides. Such genes
have been successfully transferred to crops like
wheat, rice, maize, soybean, cotton, oil seed
rape and tomato. The transgenic crops are
therefore protected from the enormous yield
losses they would otherwise suffer as a result of
pest and pathogen infestation, and competi¬
tion with weeds for life-giving nutrients and
water.
Major efforts initiated during the past few
years to map the genomes of some important
crop plants are expected to provide valuable
information about the location and identity
of other important genes those that confer
resistance to environmental stresses such as
temperature, drought and salinity and those
that control yield.
Saving plants from extinction
Thousands of wild plant varieties, which are
valuable sources of useful genes, have either
been lost forever or face imminent extinction as
a result of the increasing destruction of natural
forests for agricultural and urban use. Con¬
servation of these irreplaceable resources for
future generations and for the maintenance of
biodiversity has thus become a global concern.
In recognition of this, the Consultative Group
on International Agricultural Research, which
is responsible for the network of international
agricultural centres around the world, has taken
a step in the right direction by establishing the
International Plant Genetic Resources Institute,
with the mandate to conserve plant genetic
resources.
Intriguing
patterns of
cross-fertilization
have developped
between
microbiology and
modern art
ART ANO THE
SCIENCE OF LIFE
by John Hodgson
ART and science both endeavour to
explore the mysteries of existence.
_> Art does it by creating physical forms
that reveal intangible subject matter or illu¬
minate previously unconsidered aspects of the
physical world. Science progresses by dis¬
secting the physical world, assessing how each
of the parts works first in isolation and then as
a part of the whole. One significant difference
between art and science, however, is the extent
to which they concern themselves with telling
people about their discoveries.
The archetypal scientist caricatured as a
person devoid of normal human drives, human
emotions and human values is concerned
with the acquisition of knowledge. Moving
from one piece of knowledge to the next like
a hunter, he or she is generally unconcerned
about communicating that knowledge to a
wider public. Indeed, science often appears to
build its walls high with the bricks of experi¬
ment and cement them together with quick-
drying jargon and runic mathematics. In its
keep are the precious jewels of knowledge,
jewels that belong to everybody but are jeal¬
ously guarded. In media reporting of science
you will often find phrases such as "researchers
have revealed" or "scientists have unlocked
the secrets of", reflecting both the mystery
that has become attached to science and the
possessiveness about knowledge that has
become attributed to scientists.
In art criticism, on the other hand, the
stock phrases are "X shows us that" or "What
Y is trying to say to us is", phrases that demon¬
strate the intrinsic role of communication in
art. It is not enough for the artist merely to
have had insight; if he or she cannot convey
that insight to other people, then the art has
failed.
We all have an interest in biology, even if it
extends only to our personal health, longevity
and ultimate mortality. Because biological sci¬
ence now has its public to please, biologists,
perhaps more than any other scientific group,
need to communicate widely. But even within
the narrow confines of their profession, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Left, false-colour scanning
tunneling micrograph of
DNA.
Above, Pathway, a Carrara
marble and sheet plywood
sculpture (1 22 cm high, 30
cm diameter) by the
British artist John Maine.
imprecise nature of living organisms even
the simplest bacterium or virus decrees that
biologists cannot call upon precise formulae to
describe their discoveries. They need to invoke
artistic forms.
For instance, proteins, which are respon¬
sible for most metabolic processes, are often
depicted as winding ribbons, reminiscent of
Maurits Escher's graphic art. This style of rep¬
resentation was developed by Jane Richardson,
a highly-regarded researcher at Duke Univer¬
sity in North Carolina. Richardson's work is
the design of completely new protein mole
cules based on information she has gleaned
from existing natural proteins. Part of her con¬
tribution to her field, however, has been her
ability to capture certain qualities of proteins
by depicting them in certain ways.
No protein actually looks like Richardson's
ribbons. In fact, no protein could ever be seen
at all because the wavelength of visible light is
too long to resolve the detailed structures.
Proteins are "visualized" through a combina¬
tion of X-ray light and computer analysis, a
combination that produces the Escher-like
images. However, the ribbon provides a useful 3J
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
way for scientists to think about proteins
because it illustrates the way that the com¬
plex chemical chain that makes up the pro¬
tein winds round on itself.
By adjusting the computer analysis, pro¬
teins can equally well appear as pointillist
paintings, as similar to the works of Salvador
Dalí or as architectural drawings. There is no
"correct" way of depicting a protein. What
needs to be recognized, however, is that the
way scientists visualize the molecules does
influence how they think about them.
Conveying emotions
Just as an Impressionist painting is not a pho¬
tograph but an image that can convey a sense
of emotion or atmosphere, images of proteins
and other important biological molecules can,
if portrayed in a suitable fashion, indicate a
whole range of properties of the molecule.
For instance, some regions of proteins are
known to be very mobile; but how can you
show that in a two-dimensional image? One of
the solutions that protein chemists have come
up with is to use "glowing coal" images;
mobile parts of the molecule are represented by
yellow and orange colourations while static
regions are much darker. There is probably a
good case to be made for showing the regions
where the structure is uncertain as soft-focus
images.
An appreciation of aesthetics can be impor¬
tant for scientists who wish to understand the
mechanisms of biology. Perhaps the best
example of this is the work of James Watson
and Francis Crick in elucidating the structure
of the fundamental heredity material, deoxyri¬
bonucleic acid (DNA) in 1953. Watson and
Crick performed very little experimental work
Above, hand-tinted
electron-transmission
micrograph showing the
DNAs of two bacterial
viruses partially spliced
together. Where the two
DNAs are spliced together
they are coloured yellow.
Above right, Untitled
(1988), oil on canvas by
Noel Forster (United
Kingdom).
on DNA; instead they attempted to build
models of DNA based on the research findings
of other scientists. One expectation they had,
however, and adopted as a guiding principle,
was that the structure of DNA would have
an inherent beauty. This enabled them to elim¬
inate some of the possible structures as inele¬
gant or downright ugly. The symmetrical mol¬
ecular structure that they developed in 1953
has stood the test of time and has become an
icon of the revolution in biological under¬
standing.
dm '-mm
& m -A &
ft O '?. *!
Coexistence Human-Vein
Air-leaf Parasite-Tree Sun-
Breath Fragility. Sycamore
leaves on wood panel
(Il8x 191.8 cm),
by the British artist
Garry Fabian Miller.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
If biotechnology is undoubtedly being
enriched by the application of artistic consid¬
erations, the reverse is also true. The forms of
molecules and organisms that are first seen by
scientists, even if they have not inspired art, can
certainly find parallels in recent art. The helical
structure of DNA, for instance, is reflected in
John Maine's plywood and marble sculpture,
Pathway. Noel Forster's untitled oil painting
shows a weaving, bullet-shaped pattern which
is highly reminiscent of the false-colour pictures
of viruses produced by electron microscopists.
And the images that neuroscientists produce of
nerve cells in the brain are extraordinarily sim¬
ilar to paintings such as a red gouache work
produced by Anish Kapoor in 1989.
Similar parallels can be seen earlier in the
century. The American artist Alexander
Caldcr's Calderberry Bush of 1932 is one of the
artist's free-standing mobiles. In the way the
size of the red disks increases, the work
reminds one of the molecular machinery that
is present in all living cells for the synthesis of
proteins. The same theme is expanded in
Caldcr's Wh*) Four leaves and three petals, in
which protein synthesis appears to be taking
place on an undulating framework. That frame¬
work has its equivalent in what is called the
"endoplasmic reticulum", a sort of membra¬
nous network that spreads throughout the cell
and forms a kind of work-bench on which
protein synthesis takes place.
Whereas Calder used three dimensions, the
Catalan artist Joan Miró expressed similar
images in two dimensions. Much of Miró's
work appears to depict simple cell-like struc¬
tures that have various functional forms dotted
inside them. These forms closely resemble
mitochondria chloroplasts or other sub-units
of cells.
For me, one of the most provoking and
biotechnologically relevant pieces of modern
art is Garry Fabian Miller's arrangement of
sycamore leaves, which goes by the rather
extended name of Coexistence Human-Vein
Air-Leaf Parasite-Tree Sun-Breath Fragility.
Miller has taken square sections of sycamore
leaves in various states of health and decay
and arranged them on a panel. As one views the
work from left to right and top to bottom the
leaves become progressively more decayed
until the final squares show nothing more than
a leaf skeleton.
For me, the work illustrates both the peren¬
nial and natural process of autumnal rotting
and the role of interacting organisms in this
process. It is clear that many of the leaves are
being degraded by cellulose-eating fungi and
these fungi are an integral part of the recy¬
cling process. Looked at from a biotechno-
logical point of view, the work reminds us of
the importance not only of trees but also of
fungi. Biotcchnologists use fungi for antibiotic
production, for traditional and modern food-
making processes and for solving problems in
waste disposal or recycling. On a more global
scale, the Miller piece also brings home the
self-sustaining nature of biology and the
dependence of human life on the cycle of
growth and death in nature.
*0> *»'S- :,' Il «g am
s V * .-£ - !* "
JOHN HODGSON, a British
microbiologist, is senior editor
of the London magazine
BiolTechnology. He has written
widely for the press and has
been responsible for drafting
several governmental reports
and brochures. He is the
author of Biotechnology-changing
the way nature works, and is the
publisher and editor of The
Genetic Messenger.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
NEWSBRIEFS... NEWSBRIEFS...
40
PALOMA O'SHEA AWARDED
THE PICASSO MEDAL
On 2 February 1994, Paloma O'Shea
(Spain) was presented with UNESCO's
Picasso Medal by Federico Mayor in
recognition of her activities for the
promotion of Spanish culture.
President of the Isaac Albéniz
Foundation, she has for over twenty
years devoted herself to promoting
music and young musicians and, among
her other achievements, was
responsible for creating the
prestigious Santander international
piano competition. UNESCO's Picasso
Medal has rewarded artists and
personalities in the world of the arts
since 1981 for their contributions to
international cultural dialogue. Past
winners include Yehudi Menuhin,
Ingmar Bergman, Nadine Gordimer
and Pina Bausch.
PROTECTING MOENJODARO
FROM THE ELEMENTS
The protohistoric site of Moenjodaro,
which is included in the World
Heritage List, is exceptional for its
size, its town planning and the
artefacts collected on the site. The
vestiges of this brick-built city are,
however, at present under serious
threat from the floodwaters of the
nearby river Indus and the capillary
rise of groundwater; humidity and salt
are eroding the walls of the buildings.
International archaeologists and
scientists are working together to save
Moenjodaro from destruction. Experts
from UNESCO are currently at work
installing a monitoring station that will
determine the exact relationship
between the degree of humidity, which
may also be coming from the
atmosphere, and salt absorption.
Among the several protective
measures already implemented are the
laying of new salt-free mudbricks, the
coating of the outside faces of the
walls with mud mortar, and the
covering of some buildings with
geotextile material.
1995, THE YEAR
OF LOUIS PASTEUR
UNESCO will participate, in 1995, in
the commemorative activities marking
the centenary of Louis Pasteur's death.
Pasteur's brilliant research in the fields
of microbiology, immunology and
fermentation technology, his inspired
insights that led to the development of
vaccines, his scientific rigour and his
moral qualities make him one of the
great benefactors of humanity. An
inaugural ceremony at UNESCO
Headquarters in Paris on 1 7 January
1995 will be followed by high-level
symposia, on subjects dealt with by
Pasteur, to be held in different regions
of the world: From Spontaneous
Generation to Molecular Evolution
(February, Rio de Janeiro),
Epidemiology and Public Health
(March, Hanoi), Etiology and
Pathogenesis of Infectious Diseases
(April, Dakar), Microbes, Environment,
Biotechnology (May, Tahiti),
Stereospecificity and Molecular
Recognition (September, New York)
and Vaccines (September, Paris).
Other centenary activities include a
travelling exhibition and the striking of
a commemorative medal.
MARISA BEREHSOH,
UNESCO GOODWILL AMBASSADOR
"It is not always easy, when one
belongs, as I do, to the exclusive world
of cinema, to convince others of one's
good faith in wanting to serve an
ideal", said Marisa Berenson upon
being named UNESCO Goodwill
Ambassador on 23 March. A member
since 1 993 of the Administrative
Council of the International Fund for
the Promotion of Culture, the
celebrated American actress initiated
the Artists with a Difference project,
which is committed to combatting the
exclusion of disabled artists. As one of
her first tasks, Ms Berenson will set up
an international committee to help
and support UNESCO's important
projects. Marisa Berenson joins a
circle of men and women who have
distinguished themselves by their
talent and their commitment to
UNESCO. Placido Domingo, Ivry
Gitlis, Ikuo Hirayama, Miguel Angel
Estrella, Yehudi Menuhin, Marcel
Marceau and Jean-Michel Jarre are
among the artists already named
UNESCO Goodwill Ambassadors.
EDUCATING CHILDREN
WITH DISABILITIES
About 80 per cent of the estimated
200 million disabled children in the
world are living in developing
countries, and very few receive good
health care and education. Fewer than
2 per cent receive special services of
any kind. UNESCO has devoted a new
64-page booklet to them, setting out
the key principles governing the
education of young people with
disabilities and reviewing the
provisions (legislation, administrative,
educational, etc.) being made for
them. The booklet, entitled Educating
Children and Young People with
Disabilities, is available free of charge
from UNESCO, ED/BAS/PE, 7, Place
de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 (France),
Fax (33-1)4065-9405.«
THIS ARTICLE IS ONE
OF A SERIES IN WHICH
THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF
UNESCO SETS OUT HIS
THINKING ON MATTERS OF
CURRENT CONCERN
UNESCO IN ACTION
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
Sharing the future
m OOKING towards the future, I think UNESCO's
¡y role could be summed up as fighting for human
~3m& dignity and solidarity, both ofwhich are inseparable
from respect for freedom.
North and South alike are doomed not only to suffer
the same endemic ills that go together with underdevel¬
opment but also to consume the same products, whether
they be dreams or material goods, exported by the indus¬
trially developed nations. In both, we are witnessing the
growth of sprawling monster cities, with their mixture of
splendour and squalor, vast agglomerations where alien¬
ation and the worst kind of solitude, that experienced in the
midst of crowds, are rife; where extreme poverty radical¬
izes the emotions and the longing for justice degenerates
into hatred and violence; where the well-to-do, blinkered
by their own affluence, see no promise for the future other
than that held out to them by "market forces" alone.
Well-being, democracy, freedom and education are
not rewards to be conferred by one set of people and
gratefully accepted by another. They develop, find expres¬
sion, take shape and attain fulfilment in each one of us. Sci¬
entific and technological advances are indeed necessary in
order to facilitate this process, but they need to be applied
judiciously and in moderation, since if they go too far
they could have the opposite of the desired effect, lulling
and inhibiting us and making us the slaves of our handi¬
work instead of its masters.
A single read
This is why I would assert that the culture of peace calls,
at all levels of decision-making but especially at the highest
level, for a clearsighted and at the same time open-hearted
perception of the historic change now under way.
We must not cling to the past, merely taking stock
and laying stress on past achievements. Time has become
the most valuable of commodities, and we do not have
enough of it. Since we cannot draw up an inventory before
we set out, we shall have to do so as we go along. We have
to set off on the road to the future, without undue haste but
resolutely the same road for all, not just for a chosen few,
involving a process of change whereby civil society pro¬
gressively comes to occupy those areas of activity that the
state will have to hand over to it. The creation of ever-wider
interfaces, especially at the local level, is absolutely essen¬
tial if, in spite of wounds that are still fresh and painful, there
is to be a reconciliation. Regardless of our different out¬
looks, we must all unite so that our paths converge and
combine into a single road, pluralist and integrated, where
each is mindful of our common future.
We must advance united, or rather reunited, in pursuit
of a grand project to usher in, at the end of the present mil¬
lennium, peaceful coexistence, justice and freedom, world¬
wide interaction and a form of competition that preserves
identities and diversity. History is something to be written
and made, not described and viewed from outside. The sole
protagonists ofprogress and its only beneficiaries must be
human beings individual men and women and it is up
to each and every one of them, exercising their rights to the
full, to shape their own destinies.
It is unimaginable that such a process, whereby each
individual is given a chance to be listened to and to play a
part, could take place in an atmosphere of isolation and dis¬
trust. It calls for a thorough educational approach. As the
great Cuban patriotJosé Martí said with prophetic insight,
"Education means pulling individuals up to the level of their
time".
Ready for dialogue
In the first instance, the lifting of barriers and the removal
of obstacles will allow contacts to be revived and dialogue
to be established as we look to the future. The ideal dialogue
is sometimes said to be that between grandparents, who
have lost their memory, and grandchildren, who do not yet
have memories. We would do better to ensure that our chil¬
dren's memory is not like ours nor like that which our
grandparents have already lost.
Let us open doors instead of shutting them; let us
build bridges instead of destroying them. If we are to be
stubborn, let us be stubborn only in our resolve to engage
in dialogue and in our endeavours to discover new ways and
means. It is impossible to forget, but provided we acknowl¬
edge that those who come after us are the only people
who really matter, that mindfulness of the future should
guide our steps, then we can put the past behind us and
advance together, in step, towards that new age to which
all aspire.
Sharing, talking together, respecting other people and
our environment, all the avenues leading to a future com¬
mensurate with the human condition meet at the same
crossroads, that represented by democracy. Civil society
has to take charge of its own destiny, with the state, hith¬
erto all-powerful and omnipresent, contenting itself from
now on with the role of watchful guardian, ensuring com¬
pliance with the rules that society itself has chosen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
BUTRINTI
rediscovered
byZijaXholi
42
In Albania, archaeologists
have rescued a great city
of theAncient Worldfrom
the mud and vegetation
that concealed itfor
centuries
ALBANIA has witnessed the passing
of a wide variety of civilizations.
From Antiquity to the beginning of
the twentieth century, successive domina¬
tion by the Roman, Byzantine and Ottoman
empires has left its traces. The city ofBoth-
rota Butrinti in Albanian is one of the
fragments which form the fabric ofAlbania's
ancient cultural landscape, in the south¬
west of the Balkan peninsula.
Nestling in the highlands in the far south
of the country and surrounded by dense
vegetation, Butrintiwas doubly protected by
nature and by the fortifications which its
inhabitants built in ancient times. How¬
ever, this was not sufficient to isolate the city
from the rest of the world. Less than ten
kilometres from the island ofCorfu, Butrinti
was linked to the Mediterranean by the
Vivari canal, which ran from the Butrinti
Lake to the Ionian Sea.
The proximity of the sea and the lake, the
gentle climate and the beauty of the sur¬
rounding countryside provided a splendid
environment for the foundation ofa city. In
taking advantage of this site, the architects
of the past constructed whatwas to become
one of the major maritime and commercial
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Above, the ruins of the
amphitheatre (4th-3rd century
B.C.). In background, remains of
houses with colonnaded
courtyards.
Opposite page, the baptistry (4th-
6th century) with its double row of
granite columns and mosaic floor.
Right, a statue belonging to the
school of Praxiteles unearthed at
Butrinti.
ZIJA XHOLI, of Albania, lectures ¡n
history and philosophy at Tirana
University and is a member of the
Academy of Sciences of the Republic of
Albania. His publications include
Thinkers of the Albanian Renaissance
(1987).
centres of the Ancient World. Butrinti
reached the height of its glory in the fourth
century B.C., at which time the city num¬
bered 10,000 inhabitants.
The sight of the fortifications alone,
which date from the sixth century B.C.,
evokes the military and economic potential
of the city at that time. The hill on which the
acropolis stands is encircled by a wall built
of huge stone blocks. In places this wall is
two metres high and 3.5 metres wide.
The amphitheatre, dating from the third
century B.C., bears witness to the cultural
riches of the city. The stone banks ofseating,
ofwhich twenty- three rows have been pre¬
served, would have held an audience of
1,500. The theatre is situated at the foot of
the acropolis, close by two temples, one of
which is dedicated to Asclepios, the Greek
god of medicine, who was worshipped by
the city's inhabitants. Approximately thirty
inscriptions, almost all in ancient Greek,
carved in the western façade of this temple,
and another hundred or so found on a tower
which was rebuilt in the 1st century B.C., are
the only examples ofwriting discovered in
Butrinti. These inscriptions are mainly con¬
cerned with the liberation of slaves. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
44
Excavations have brought to light many
objects plates, vases, ceramic candle¬
sticks as well as sculptures, including a
remarkable "Goddess of Butrinti", which
seems to completely embody, in the per¬
fection of its features, the Greek ideal of
physical beauty.
The ramparts served to remind the
inhabitants of their peaceful life and the
uncertainty of their future. For centuries,
the walls faithfully defended Butrinti. But
no wall is invincible, and these huge blocks
of stone finally ceded to the assault of the
Roman legions which landed on the Adri¬
atic and Ionian shores in the second cen¬
tury B.C. Under the rule of the occupiers,
Butrinti was to fall slowly into decadence.
Unlike Dyrrachium and Apollonia, cities
comfortably situated on the roads joining
Head of Apollo (4th century B.C.)
known as the "Goddess
of Butrinti".
Rome to the East, which experienced a
wave ofprosperity, Butrinti far from the
major road links was at the mercy of the
whims of patricians and senators whose
sole concern was achieving rapid personal
gain.
In spite of this, three monumental foun¬
tains, three public baths, a gymnasium
decorated with mosaics, and especially the
aqueduct constructed during the reign of
Augustus, prove that the site was not com¬
pletely abandoned. Augustus also oversaw
the reconstruction of all the ancient city
walls and the erection ofnew fortifications.
He accorded Butrinti the status of a colony,
and it was at this time that the city minted
its first coins.
Christianity brought new life to Butrinti.
The palaeo-Christian period adorned the
city with two basilicas and a baptistry,
which is among the most beautiful in the
Mediterranean region. Sixteen granite
columns, forming two concentric circles,
support the roofof the main hall. The floor
is paved with a magnificent mosaic repre¬
senting the Tree ofLife and decorated with
medallions embellished with animal
motifs.
But this was to be a mere respite. Bar¬
barian incursions and Norman raids in the
eleventh century, a catastrophic earth¬
quake in 1 153, conquest by the Venetians
in 1386, the subterranean infiltration of
water and the subsequent epidemics com¬
pleted the ruin of the city and forced the
inhabitants to flee. Butrinti was buried in
silence and oblivion. Throughout the
occupation by the Ottoman Empire, from
the fifteenth to the twentieth centuries,
the city remained in deep slumber. The
waters covered Butrinti in mud, and an
abundant vegetation completely hid the
remains from view.
It was not until the beginning of the
twentieth century that systematic excava¬
tions were carried out at Butrinti by the
Italian archaeologist I. Ugolini, followed by
his compatriots R Marconi and D. Mustili.
Between 1928 and 1941, the ground was
cleared and the ancient city gradually began
to reveal its hidden treasures.
Following the liberation of Albania in
1944, Albanian archaeologists undertook
more ambitious excavations. In turn, the
ramparts, the acropolis, the agora, the
amphitheatre, the temples, public baths
and private residences re-emerged into
the light ofday. The entire city arose, almost
intact, under the fascinated gaze of the
archaeologists. The mud and vegetation
that covered Butrinti had protected it from
the natural and human ravages of time.
Today, this rediscovered city represents
a unique cultural treasure whose value far
surpasses national frontiers. The impor¬
tance of Butrinti can be gauged from its
inclusion in 1992 on UNESCO's World Her¬
itage List.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
MARTIN Luther King, Jr., who was born
on 15 January 1929, would have been
seventy- five years old this year. He died, aged
less than forty, assassinated in Memphis, Ten¬
nessee, on 4 April 1968.
Anniversaries have a definite role to play in
the mental calendar. With each passing year,
events which have stamped a particular mark
on the history ofhumanity resurface from the
shadowy pool ofmemory. However, there is no
doubt that some of the events and public fig¬
ures recalled by a particular date speak to us
independently of such anniversaries, moving
through our daily lives and conditioning, in
some way, our present circumstances. They
are not waiting to pop out from the next page
of our diaries. They are ever present, chal¬
lenging us. Thus it is with the life and death of
Martin Luther King.
As is the case with a number of other
exceptional public figures, circumstances in
the closing years of this century are such that
the fate of this son of black America is again
becoming topical as a landmark and an inspi¬
ration. It is tempting to echo the words of
Albert Dürer who, four centuries earlier-
believing Martin Luther to have been killed fol¬
lowing the Diet of Wormswrote in his
journal on 17 May 1521: "0 Lord, would that
you might give us such another man as this!"
"Such another man" as Martin Luther King
would be a warrior ofnon-violence, one who
sought his weapons in Gandhi's armoury, to
wage war without sword, bullet or bomb.
During a voyage to India in February and
March 1959, on the invitation ofPandit Nehru,
Martin Luther King and his wife Coretta visited
New Delhi to add a wreath to the carpet of
flowers permanently adorning the sanctuary
where Mahatma Gandhi was cremated. "I may
travel to other countries as a tourist," he told
journalists, "but I travel to India as a pilgrim."
These were flowers ofgratitude to a man who
stood up against the staunch defenders of the
caste system in a sub-continent steeped in
almost unbearable poverty, a man who dared
to raise the Untouchables to the rank ofHar-
ijans (Children of God). Was this not precisely
the same cause as that to which Martin Luther
King strove to devote himself: ensuring that
the blacks of the United States should not be
considered as inferiors or even pariahs?
In New York, shortly before this journey,
while he was signing copies ofhis book Stride
Toward Freedom in a department store, a men¬
tally-deranged forty-five-year-old black
woman had struck Martin Luther King in the
chest with an ornamental paper-knife, grazing
his aorta. Had the victim so much as sneezed,
the aorta would have punctured, leading to
certain death. This was only one of numerous
attacks which dogged the career of this
remarkable pastor, whoin December 1955,
at the age of twenty-six, on hearing that
another black woman, Rosa Parks, had been
arrested in Montgomery, Alabama, for refusing
to give up her seat on a bus to a whitehad
decided to devote himself to freeing his com¬
munity from the scorn, derision and shame
which had been heaped upon it. Freedom
became his watchword and rallying call.
Surrounded by friends, all of whom
believed as he did that "the time for silence is
past, the time has come to speak out", he leapt
into the fray, armed by the memory of the
Martin Luther who, seeking to lead his com¬
panions out of the Babylonian Captivity (the
title of one of Luther's treatises), wrote these
words which must have been familiar to
Martin Luther King: "Would it not be against
Nature if, a fire being declared, each citizen
were to remain still and let the fire wreak its
havoc, solely because he is not Mayor of the
city?"
The violence endured by Martin Luther
King in thirteen years of campaigning
included both physical and moral attacks: he
was to be arrested several times, beaten,
imprisoned, prosecuted for "incitation to riot"
and fraud, accused of treason against America
by those who opposed his stance on the Bay
of Pigs operation in Cuba and the Viet Nam
war, and "to spice things up" Martin Luther
King's opponents circulated tapes made with
the use ofhidden microphones, even sending
to his wife tape-recordings of high-spirited
Martin Luther King in 1 966, two years before
he was assassinated in Memphis (Tennessee).
evenings spent while on tour in the southern
States.
He was to be spared no form of attack. But
nothing was able to break his resolve to build
a new America, the land of the famous
"dream" which he described on 28 August
1963 to a crowd of200,000 peopleblack and
whiteassembled in Washington D.C., and to
millions ofAmericans at home, sitting in front
of their radio and television sets. Martin Luther
King's words on that day will remain forever
etched in the memory of people in all cor¬
ners of the world: North, South, East and West.
Indeed, nothing could halt the war
declared by Martin Luther King in the name of
his fellow black Americans. He fought the
good fight to the end, stubbornly rejecting
violence, trusting in the civil disobedience he
had learned from Henri David Thoreau, who
had himself been influenced by the same
Hindu mystics who had nourished the sub¬
lime non-violence of Mahatma Gandhi, the
inspiration for Martin Luther King's approach
to his task. Nothing could stop him, until a
bullet fired from a rifle struck him down on the
evening of 4 April 1968, sounding the death-
knell of the man: "with the golden voice, melo¬
dious as the flutes of angels/ A voice of blazing
brass which rings out over Sodom and
Admah."*
* L.S. Senghor: Elegy for Martin Luther
King.
EDOUARD J. MAUNICK, Mauritian poet and
writer, former Director of the UNESCO
Collection of Representative Works, is at present
associate editor of the magazine Jeune Afrique. He
is the author of some fifteen works, including
Ensoleillé vif, which won the Prix Apollinaire in
1 977, Anthologies personnelles (Actes Sud, Paris,
1 984) and Paroles pour solder la mer (Gallimard,
Paris, 1989). 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
R H
Thomas Mann
The downfall ofidealism
III this second excerptfrom the
address he gave in 1935 at a meeting
organized in Nice by the
International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation on the
theme ofthe education ofmodern
man (see previous issue), the German
writer Thomas Mann has harsh
wordsfor the moral waywardness of
the masses and their betrayal ofthe
intellect. This text, written almost
sixtyyears ago at the time ofthe rise
ofNazism, is in some ways still
strikingly topical. The third and
final instalment will appear in next
month's issue.
Text selected and presented
4#£ by Edgardo Canton
THE First World War was not the
prime cause of the impoverish¬
ment of European civilization. It
only accelerated and accentuated it. It
was not the war that threw up the gigantic
wave of eccentric barbarity and dema¬
gogical, primitive brutality that is over¬
whelming the world; it only enlarged and
intensified its blind rage. Modern man is
both the victim and the product of the
disorganized and confusing as well as
exciting and exhilarating impressions that
assail him. The fantastic development of
technological expertise with its triumphs
and disasters, the blare and thrills of
sporting records, the exaggerated impor¬
tance and remuneration given to crowd-
drawing "stars", the boxing matches fought
for fabulous prizes and held in vast arenas
before huge crowds these are some of
the characteristic features of our time,
along with the decadence and decline of
concepts that are edifying and salutary in
their severity, such as culture, the mind, art
and ideas. These are the conceptions of
the bourgeois age, the glad rags of nine¬
teenth-century idealism.
In fact the nineteenth century was
above all a period of idealism. With a cer¬
tain emotion we see todayjust how ideal¬
istic it was. It not only believed in the ben¬
efits of liberal democracy but in socialism,
a socialism that would elevate the masses,
instruct them and have them participate
in the advantages of science, culture and
art, in short, in civilization. Today we are
convinced that it is more important and
also easier to dominate the masses by
increasingly perfecting the crude art of
using their psychology, i.e. by replacing
their education with propaganda, not, it
would seem, without the intimate con¬
sent of the masses, who can easily be
swayed by dynamic propaganda that
seems more modern and more attractive
to them than any educational idea. The
masses are organizable, and it can be seen
that they always accept organization grate¬
fully, whatever the spirit behind it may
be, even if it is the spirit of violence. Vio¬
lence is a principle that greatly simplifies
things; it is no surprise that it should be
understood by the masses.
If these modern masses were merely
primitive, if they only consisted ofhappy,
naive barbarians, it would be possible to
get along with them and hope for some¬
thing, but they have two qualities that
make them quite simply appalling: they
are sentimental, and they are disastrously
philosophical. The mind of the masses,
imbued with noisy modernism as it is,
speaks in romantic jargon. It talks of race,
the earth and blood, a stack of old ideas
both traditional and pious	 The result
is a hypocritical blend of sentimentality
and popular stupidity bathed in mawk-
ishness, a triumphant combination that
characterizes and defines our times.
THE IDEALISTIC REBELLIOM
Things are even worse concerning the
masses' philosophical system. Of course,
they didn't invent it; it has trickled down to
them little by little from the intellectual
spheres above. The role played by the
mind for several decades now has been
extremely remarkable. It has turned
against itself, has begun to indulge in irony
at its own expense and has pathetically
abdicated in favour of life and the gener¬
ative forces of the unconscious, of the
dynamic, and of the subterranean deities,
those august and dark creative forces
whose maternal breast is the sacred source
of all life. We all know of this attack by the
mind against itself, against reason that it
has pilloried by accusing it of destroying
life: it is a bold and fascinating spectacle,
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
E
Thomas Mann in 1936.
but apt to engender confusion so that per¬
haps it would have been better not to let
the general public in.
It is clear that the struggle against ide¬
alism was started by idealism. The nine¬
teenth century was so bitterly in love with
truth that through Ibsen's voice it even
wanted to recognize the "lie of life" as
indispensable. But it is easy to see that
there is a big difference between the
person who accepts the lie because of
painful pessimism and bitter irony and
the person who accepts it because of a
lack of love for the truth. Today this dif¬
ference is no longer apparent to everyone:
Nietzsche's polemical virulence against
Platonism, Socraticism and Christianity
was the polemic of a man more like Pascal
than Cesare Borgia or Machiavelli. It was
the ascetic victory of a Christian-born
man over himself. Marx's fight against
German idealism's conception of truth
and morality was not without analogies to
Nietzsche's. Marx undertook the struggle
because of idealism, because of love for a
new truth and justice and not out of con¬
tempt for the mind.
This contempt was to be expressed in
the decades that romanticized the ideal¬
istic rebellion against idealism, thereby
opening up dangerous possibilities ofpop¬
ularity. Those who professed these theo¬
ries neither saw nor cared about the dan¬
gers to which humanity and civilization
are exposed by any intellectual attack on
the mind, about the seeds of latent reac¬
tion in a revolution of this sort, about the
dark possibilities ofabuse they can lead to
when, transposed into reality, they
become in the bat of an eyelid the charter
for all kinds of "spiritualism", for all kinds
of human indignity, for impudent con¬
tempt for truth, freedom, justice and
honour. We are forced to observe that the
mind has been lacking in a sense of
responsibility and has not understood
that morality and mind go together, that
their rise and fall happen simultaneously
and that contempt for reason leads to
moral licence. Thousands of proponents
of irrationalism have not bothered to find
out whether or not they are leading the
people into moral impoverishment and
training them to be apathetic towards all
kinds of atrocities.
THE HULLABALLOO OF THE FAIR
The new masses heard rumours about the
sensational downfall of the mind and
reason that had taken place in the higher
spheres; they learned that this was the
latest thing, and they did not seem very
surprised about it, for movements of this
kind had already long been rampant
among them. Many things that would
never have been accepted by the more
demanding humanity of the nineteenth
century had again become possible, had
once more insinuated themselves into our
habits, owing to our age's fairground hul-
laballoo: all kinds of occult sciences, half-
sciences and quackery, obscure sects and
stupid back-street religions, bare-faced
bluffing, blind and simple faith and the
airs and graces of an old charlatan, all
these aberrations had their day, drew in
the masses and set the tone of the times.
Many cultivated men saw these things
neither as a vulgar, modernistic hotch¬
potch nor as the degeneration of civiliza¬
tion. Instead they mystically proclaimed
that we were witnessing the resurrection
ofdeep-rooted vital forces and venerable
popular feelings. The ground was even
prepared for the most absurd and the most
shameful of mass superstitions. And this
was not the vague and thoughtless super¬
stition of the past, but a modern democ¬
ratic superstition based on the right
of every person to think, in short a super¬
stition that went with "philosophical
ideas".
(TO BE CONTINUED)
4J
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDINGS
by Isabelle Leymarie
JAZZ
Carmen McRae Sings Great
American Songwriters
CDMCAGRP 16312
This disc contains a selection
of songs by Gershwin, Cole
Porter, Jerome Kern, Rodgers &
Hart and other composers,
recorded in the 1950s. McRae is
sometimes accompanied by a
piano and guitar, sometimes by
big bands with string sections.
Some of her accompanists are
outstanding instrumentalists,
like Kenny Clarke and Tadd
Dameron, but for the most part
the backing is provided by
session artists. She interprets
some of the great jazz
standards, "My Romance", "My
Funny Valentine" and
"Summertime", with her
wonderful clarity. In the same
way that Billie Holiday is
famous for conveying emotion,
Sarah Vaughan for her vibrato
and Ella Fitzgerald for her
brilliant improvisations, McRae
is famous for her diction. Every
syllable is crystal-clear and
different from the last. A jazz
classic.
LEE KONITZ. Rhapsody
Konitz (alto sax), Helen
Merrill, Jay Clayton (vocals),
Peggy Stern, Paul Bley
(piano), Gary Peacock, Ben
Allison (bass), and others.
CDKICj 174
In terms of style, this is "white
jazz", with the emphasis not on
swing but on intimacy, with
each piece being performed as
if it was chamber music.
Inventiveness is omnipresent,
especially in Jay Clayton's
48
vocals and the harmonies of
Stern and Bley. Clark Terry, the
only black musician on these
tracks, contributes a stronger
beat in his duet with Konitz on
"Flyin'Mumbles and
Jumbles". His individual sound
spices up Konitz's more
flowing, "classic" (in the
academic sense of the word)
style.
MUSIC FROM
AROUND THE
WORLD
CUARTETO PATRIA.
A una Coqueta
CD Corasón COCDI06
Hailing from Santiago de Cuba,
in Oriente province, cradle of
the bolero and the son, the
Cuarteto Patria, led by Eliades
Ochoa, is made up of two
guitars, bongos and a double
bass. A traditional group that
has kept its country flavour, it
performs pieces by Cuba's
leading composers of popular
music: Luis Marquetti,
Francisco Repilado, Miguel
Matamoros, Manuel Corona
and Lorenzo Hierrezuelo. Easy
listening though the music
may be, it is not as simple as it
appears at first hearing, as may
be judged from the guitar and
bongo solos, frequently off¬
beat in relation to the basic
rhythm.
VIET NAM. Tradition
of the South
Anthology of Traditional
Music Collection
CD Corasón COCDI06
Although Viet Nam is now
open to tourism and has
figured in several recent films,
its ineffably beautiful music
remains a great mystery to
most listeners. This disc offers
a series of recordings of
"entertainment" music
belonging to the tradition of
the southern part of the
country, but affected by various
influences from elsewhere. The
music, improvised and here
played on a dan tranh, a
sixteen-string zither, a ty ha,
rather like an old Chinese pipa,
and a song lang, a hardwood
block, is governed by modes
and "modal nuances" that
express, as in India, various
emotions: joy, serenity,
solemnity, calm and sadness.
This is one of the most
flourishing of the musical
traditions in southeast Asia.
TURKEY. L'art vivant
de Talip Ozkan
CD Ocora C 580047
Less harsh than some classical
Arab music, tempered by
influences from the heartland
ofAsia, Turkish melodies
inevitably recall the opulence
of The Thousand and One
Nights, and Turks are in general
fervent lovers of dancing and
music. An expert in his
country's oral heritage, Talip
Özkan is a virtuoso of the long-
necked lutes, the divan saz and
the tambura. Here he offers us
music from various regions
Anatolia, Edirne, Aydin, the
northeast and the border
region between Turkey and
Iran seldom heard outside
Turkey, enabling us to enjoy all
the nuances of this fascinating
world of sound.
GERARD
ZUCHETTO/MICHEL
ROUSSET. L'Hérétique.
Poems by René Nelli
CD Gallo 765
France is at present witnessing
a renaissance of regional
languages and dialects, one of
which is Occitan, famous in
days gone by for its courtly
literature. Occitan remained a
living language for a long time:
my grandmother, born in
Carcassonne, often spoke it to
me and knew countless old
poems and songs in the
language. The Centre for
Popular Music in Caret has
undertaken to collect the
vanishing folklore of the
French southwest. Keenly
interested in the troubadours
and the Cathars, René Nelli is,
with his strong, dense
language, one of the great
Occitan poets. The singer
Zuchetto and the pianist
Michel Rousset, with a
contribution from Dominique
Regef on the cello, rebeck and
israj, do an admirable job of
setting these poems in Occitan
and French to music. The
booklet that comes with the
disc contains translations of
them into several languages.
CLASSICAL MUSIC
CAMILLE SAINT-SAENS.
La Muse et Je Poète.
Ensemble Orchestral de Paris
directed
by Jean-Jacques Kantorow
CD EMI Classics 0777 7 549 1 3 2 6.
The Ensemble Orchestral de
Paris and several soloists the
violinist Patrice Fontanarosa,
the cellist Gary Hoffman, the
flautist Clara Ñovakova and
the clarinettist Richard
Vieille play several of Saint-
Saëns' vibrant, refined and
romantic works: the Odelette
for flute and orchestra, the
Tarentelle for flute, clarinet
and orchestra and the Suite for
orchestra with its Prelude,
Sarabande, Gavotte, Romance
and Finale, as well as the
Romance for flute and
orchestra. The texture is
variable: the music is
sometimes compact and
intense as if moved by surging
passion, sometimes sparkling
with subtle chromatic effects,
as in the barcarolle, Une nuit à
Lisbonne, dedicated to Don
Luiz, King of Portugal. M
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS OF THE WORLD by Edgar Reichmann
On the trail
ofFernäo
Mendes Pinto
Wien Renaissance Europe
discovered the distantEast
pI eregrinations ofFernäo Mendes Pinto,
in which he relates the very numerous
and very strange things which he saw
and heard in the Kingdoms ofChina and also of
Tartaria, of Sornau, which is commonly known
as Siam, in those of Calaminhâ, of Pegu, of
Martaban and in many other Kingdoms and
Realms ofthe Orient, ofwhich little or nothing is
known in Occident. And also relates the many
and exceptional adventures which befell him
and many other persons	" Thus reads the
title page ofa monumental work, first published
in Lisbon in 1614, which was subsequently trans¬
lated from Portuguese into many other lan¬
guages and published in various editions
throughout the world. Today, there are signs of
a resurgence of interest in this remarkable best¬
seller of the seventeenth and eighteenth cen¬
turies, as evidenced by recent translations into
American English, French and Japanese.
Who exactly was Femäo Mendes Pinto? Most
reference books have little to say about him. A
contemporary ofanother poet of the warm seas,
Luis de Camoens, he explored the East Indies and
published an account ofhis travels, Peregrinaçâo
(1614): this is all we are told. The index of place
names in the most recent French edition of this
worktranslated by Robert Viale and containing
an illuminating commentary by the translator-
yields further information regarding the myste¬
riously named places visited by this writer-
adventurer. Thus Calaminhâ, initially thought to
be Tibet, has been identified as Laos; Pegu was
the capital of Burma, and Martaban was a very
ancient city in the same country.
Femäo Mendes Pinto's life was that ofa char¬
acter in a baroque novel. It has similarities with
that of the French explorer Henri de Monfreid in
this century. Probably from a modest back¬
ground, talented and cultured, at the age of
twenty-seven Pinto left his position in an aris¬
tocratic Portuguese household and set out into
the unknown to make his fortune. He did not
return to his homeland for more than two
decades, during which time he explored the
horn of Africa, the coast of Arabia, the fabled
land of India, and Southeast Asia, China and
Japan. After returning to Portugal, he obtained a
royal pension late in life and devoted his twi
light years to the writing of his book. This man
who was at various times a trafficker and a slave,
condemned to death and reprieved, an ambas¬
sador, a missionary and a friend of the Jesuit St.
Francis Xavier, is, because ofhis epic story-telling
genius, an exemplarywitness of the way in which
Renaissance Europe perceived other civiliza¬
tions.
A THIRST FOR CONQUEST
Pinto does not depict the Portuguese as supe¬
rior to the peoples he discovers. On the con¬
trary, with the exception of their religious prac¬
tices and military weakness, he admires the
munificence of these distant civilizations
particularly Chinato the extent of indicating,
by contrast, the weaknesses of the West, espe¬
cially in the areas of social organization, justice
and economics. As Robert Viale points out in
his introduction, this is the account of a lucid,
meticulous observer, who went so far as to
count each and every wick in the 1,439 lamps
in one temple he visited, but one who is also at
pains to provide the reader with a full picture
of whatever he is describing.
This thirst for detail and astonishing pre¬
cision are by no means innocent, however.
For Fernào Mendes Pinto, everything has a
price, and the defensive weakness of the pros¬
perous countries which he visits awaken in
him the desire for mastery. As early as the Aviz
dynasty (1385-1580), Portugalthis small
country at the furthest western extremity of
Europehad established its first trading mis¬
sions on the African coast. Portuguese navi¬
gators rounded the Cape of Good Hope in
1487, and founded a colonial empire in the
Indies, of which Vasco da Gama became
Viceroy. More than the metaphysical quest for
an improbable grail, probably more than the
thirst for knowledge, it was the attraction of
great wealththe fabrics, spices, precious
wood, gold and gemstones which abounded
on the Far Eastern shoreswhich made Euro¬
pean caravels hasten to these hitherto
unknown lands.
ENTHRALLING ADVENTURES
However, these travels also form a series of
amazing adventures. The narrator recalls his
youth prior to his departure, his discovery of
India, and the harrowing demise of the King of
Aaru (a now-extinct kingdom on the north¬
east coast of Sumatra). Among a host of other
portraits, Femäo Mendes Pinto paints a picture
of Beijing in the sixteenth century, "wherein the
king of China holds his residence". The author
also evokes "the cares which are dispensed to
all infirm and needful persons", stating that
"throughout the kingdom are to be found habi¬
tations destined for the poor", but also relates
the way in which "the town of Martaban was
sacked and destroyed and the manner whereby
the Queen and many other women were sub¬
jected to manifold tortures".
The author condemns the religious
hypocrisy of his compatriots, who cause harm
by invoking the name of the Lord; he is horri¬
fied by the cruelties of the Inquisition. His
"peregrinations" illustrate those of a humanity
which wishes to progress, reaching beyond its
limits and breaking away from the conditions
imposed by the environment, to finally
encounter the "Other". But at what cost? the
reader is tempted to enquire, after turning the
last of the 777 pages of this Odyssey of the
1600s. The disappearance of the civilizations
of the Andes and Central America, the depop¬
ulation of Africa by slave traders, the geno¬
cides which ran like a sore through the fol¬
lowing centuries suggest that he who sets out
in search of the "Other" without first taming his
appetite for conquest and his lust for wealth
runs the risk of losing himself on the way.
Fernào Mendes Pinto, Pérégrination, travel
writings translated into French from the Por¬
tuguese and presented by Robert Viale, Col¬
lection Outre-mers, La Différence publishers,
Paris, 1991. ISBN: 2-7291-0597-2.
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: M. Baret© Rapho, Paris. Pages 4,
6: Emmanuel Scorcelletti © Gamma, Paris. Page 7:
Satoru Ohmori © Gamma, Paris. Pages 8-9: Markel
© Gamma, Paris. Pages 9, 32: © Claude Sauvageot,
Paris. Pages 10, I I, 35 (above): Lynn Johnson©
Black Star/Rapho, Paris. Page 12: Patrick Land¬
mann © Gamma, Paris. Pages 1 3 (above), 33, 34
(right): Fred Ward © Rapho, Paris. Page 1 3
(below): Filipacchi/Liaison © Gamma, Paris. Pages
14-15: Jörgen Schytte © Still Pictures, London.
Page 1 6: Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris. Pages 1 7
(above), 1 8 (above): Howell/Liaison © Gamma,
Paris. Pages 1 7 (below), 24: Gérard Boutin ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 1 8 (below): Alain Le Toquin
© Explorer, Paris. Page 1 9 (above): Y. Cavaille ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 1 9 (inset): Francis Jalain ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 20: © Vincent Poulain, Paris.
Page 2 1 : M. Fournie © Explorer, Paris. Pages 22,
34 (left): Bruce Patton © Panos Pictures, London.
Page 23: J. P. Porcher © Explorer, Paris. Page 25:
Jacques Joffre © Explorer, Paris. Page 26: Missir ©
Explorer, Paris. Page 27 (above): © Société
Pachamama, Lima. Page 27 (below): Durand ©
Jacana, Paris. Page 28: Boiffin Vivier © Explorer,
Paris. Page 29: Nacivet © Explorer, Paris. Page 30:
Michael Friedel © Rapho, Paris. Page 3 1 : © M. Y.
Brandily, Paris. Page 35 (below): Paris. Aventurier
© Gamma, Paris. Page 37 (left): Laurence Berkeley
Laboratory/ SPL© Cosmos, Paris. Page 37 (right):
© John Maine, The South Bank Centre, London.
Page 38 (left): Pamela and David Parker/SPL ©
Cosmos, Paris. Page 38 (right): © Noel Forster,
The South Bank Centre, London. Page 38-39: ©
Fabian Miller, The South Bank Centre, London.
Page 40: © Fabian. Pages 42, 43 (above), 44:
Michel Setboun © Rapho, Paris. Page 43 (below):
All Rights Reserved. Page 45: © Archiv für Kunst
und Geschichte, Berlin. Page 47: Lotte Jacobi ©
Archiv für Kunst und Geschichte, Berlin. 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
r
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
so
WHEN THE SAHARA
WAS A TROPICAL FOREST
In the article entitled "The dry lands" which
appeared on page 1 1 ofyour January 1994
issue, I read that "arid and semi-arid
regions are concentrated in two zones
straddling the Tropics of Cancer and Capri¬
corn, on each side of the Equator. The main
cause of aridity is to be found in the circu¬
lation of the atmosphere above our
revolving globe. The almost permanent
ridges of high pressure that predominate
around the 30°-latitude mark stop rain
from forming."
I do not think that this has always been
the case. Several million years ago, what is
now the Sahara was apparently a tropical
forest, which means that the explanation
given for the present situation is invalid
for such very ancient times. Is there any
way of finding out about the climatic
changes that have taken place since then?
JOSEPH EMPAIN
BRUSSELS (BELGIUM)
The general circulation ofthe atmosphere is
an extremely complex phenomenon. It is
true that the Sahara has experienced far
less dry periods than today, as we know
from the remarkable neolithic frescoes of
Tassili N'Ajjer. These periods occurred not
millions ofyears ago, but in the course ofa
rainy period following the most recent
glaciations, less than 10,000 years ago. At
that time the general circulation necessarily
shifted. However, the explanation given,
which takes account of the situation since
the historic era, remains globally valid.
Michel Bâtisse
OUCH!
I was happy to see in your excellent
November 1993 issue ("The Story of Num¬
bers") a reference to my language, Breton.
On page 1 0 there is a table showing ways of
forming the number 18 in different lan¬
guages. In Breton 18 is actually written
triwec'h (and not "tri-ouch"\ as you have it).
Our Welsh brothers say deunaw (2 x 9), but
also un deg wyth (1 x 10 + 8). The Celts of
the Gaelic branch say a h-ocht-déag (8 +
10).
Thank you again for this allusion to
Breton, a language which, while no longer
openly attacked as it was for years, still has
no official status . . .
ALAN ER IIOULVENN
KERILIEU LANDAD (FRANCE)
A FAITHFUL READER
I have read the Quin'ersince it began publi¬
cation and have every issue except for the first
one or two. I wonder whether you have many
such faithful readers.
MARIE-HELENE ERNST
RUE DU CHATELARD
87370 SAINT-SULPICE-LAURIERE (FRANCE)
EMOTION IN ART
I agree with what Henry Christiaën said in his
letter which appeared in the February issue
of the UNESCO Courier. As an academically
trained artist, I think, like him, that with the
development of techniques for the mass pro¬
duction of images some emotions have
become subdued, latent.
Turning to abstract geometric forms
appears to be a result of fear a retreat from
reality leading to a sharp deviation from
life forms to a kind of cubistic art. And yet the
photographer searches for design and bal¬
ance in interpreting his emotions, as docs
the careful painter and brush artist.
I think a deliberate return to reality might
result in a form of creation that encourages
an understanding of the artistic message.
MILDRED BOIIN
HOUSTON, TEXAS (U.S.A.)
FOR A CULTURE OF PEACE
I greatly appreciated the editorial of your
October 1993 issue ("Time to Disarm") which
mentions Lord Noel-Baker whom I had the
good fortune to meet at a UNESCO sympo¬
sium with Sean MacBridc, and with whom I
had warm relations until his death.
But I appreciated above all the "Appeal for
non-violence" launched in that issue by the
Director-General of UNESCO, Mr. Federico
Mayor. I welcome the fact that he puts the
accent on generosity, a necessary and suffi¬
cient condition for the creation of the culture
of peace that he calls for in his interesting
Commentary. It is admirable that he should
find generosity "natural" for human beings,
thereby showing himself to be a profound
humanist.
I read with far less enthusiasm about the
meeting between Goethe and Napoleon so
brilliantly described by Paul Valéry (in the
"Archives" feature). It seemed to me out of
place in the Courier, since Napoleon belongs
precisely to that culture ofwar whose end Mr.
Mayor wishes to see.
MME M.C. CHARPY
ST.-TROPEZ (FRANCE)
TheUNESCO
¿ COURIER
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31. cue François Bonvm, 750 1 S Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz dc Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Anane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation:
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant:
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtin Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Voiodimir Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: XabierSenin Fernández (Santiago de
Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
I year: 21 I French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 1 32 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of UNESCO
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unhco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed anieles
repnnted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be sup¬
plied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily rep¬
resent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the UNtsco
Courier. Photo captions and headlines are written by the Uni sro Courier
staff The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
UNtiCO Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche)
by: (I) Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris: (2) University Micro¬
films (Xerox). Ann Arbor. Michigan 48 100 U S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head Inc.. I 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A.: (4)
Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mnnsfie'd Road. Wooster. Ohio 4469 1 , U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: C I -MA! 1994
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL 2. rue Christophe-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 0041-5278 N 6-I994-OPI-94-526A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
A major contribution to the understanding of
the economic and socio-cultural implications
of biotechnologies
Biotechnolo^n
developing court»
present and future
v Volume 1:
and national survey
by Albert Sasson
1993, 764 PP-
,SBN 92-3-102875-8
280 FF (¡nduclmg postage^
pnce 280 t-r i ordinary mail)
An evaluat.cn oHhe«eveiop.ng
biotechnology R & D '" nationa. surveys
Wor.d through regional ^ and Latin
»frira the Arab States.,
'" , the Caribbean
America a"d the , nt
« AC,nra1u s"« organize
government measur bio,ndustnal
biotechnology R * u
development of
. An authoritauve assess ^ as
through UNESCO
SS"":s"-Ä;:rues,payable
-nratrenÄo'viSA credit card to.
through a Fren rf Sales Division,
UNESC0 P-ng.P-ot.cn ana Sale
U7Nplace ae Fontenoy. ^
¡KB?*»"
Just published
Sei/e/7 outstanding new CDs
of traditional music:
AKA Pygmy Music
Japan: Ainu Songs
Tajik Music ofBadakhshan
Islamic Ritual from the Province ofKosovo
Turkmen Epic Singing: Köroglu
Viet Nam: Tradition of the South
Côte d'Ivoire: Baoulé Vocal Music
These recordings form part of the UNESCO
Collection of Traditional Music of the world
published by AUVIDIS in collaboration with
the International Music Council (IMC).
They may be obtained via your local record
dealer or from the UNESCO Bookshop,
7 place de Fontenoy,
75352 Paris 07 SP, France.
Lutece
Langua
College
8e y^
Propose depuis 1978
des stages d'anglais
pour scolaires,
universitaires et
adultes, à Jersey,
Guernesey et Londres
Stages renforcés pour la
préparation aux examens
Cours pendant toute l'année
préparant aux examens de
Cambridge et de la Chambre de
commerce de Londres
Q Stages intensifs suivis d'un
placement professionnel
Stages "sur mesures" individuels
ou séminaires pour professionnels
(cadres, juristes, gestionnaires, etc.)
Séjours linguistiques pour jeunes
et adultes de 2 à 6 semaines
pendant les vacances scolaires
(tous niveaux, classes de 8 élèves,
professeurs hautement qualifiés,
hébergement en famille, programme
sportif et excursions).
Pour obtenir de plus amples renseignements :
Lutèce Language College
P.O. BOX 623 9 New street
St. Hélier, JERSEY Channel Islands
Tél. : (19.44) 53459502
Fax : (19.44) 53469010
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
nAJtösm
BbV
The Unesco Courier is the onl/ international magazine
published in 32 languages and read by hundreds of thousands of
people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with UNESCO's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms.. .without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
MONTH. ESSENTIAL READING UNDERSTANDING PROBLEMS
AN INTER
FROM THE
SCIENCE, C
JLAR FEATURES 0
EWORLD HERITAG
; WORLDWIDE...
OF TODAY AND TOMORROW
MINORITIES... WHAT IS MODERN?... RHYTHM, GESTURE AHB THE SACREB... TINE TO BISARH... THE STORY OF
NUHBERS... A NORTH-SOUTH DEBATE: THE MEANING OF PROGRESS... DESERTS... WORLBS WITHIN WORBS...
HUNAN RIGHTS, THE UNFINISHED TASK... NODERN MANAGEMENT ANB LOCAL TRADITIONS... A NEW LOOK AT
THE HISTORY OF CONHBNISH... BIOTECHNOLOGY: THE RESOURCEFUL GENE...
FRANCOIS NITTERRANB... JORGE AMADO... RICHARB ATTENBOROUGH... JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE... JEAN
LACOBTBRE... FEBERICO NAYOR... NAGUIB NAHFOBZ... SENBENE OBSHANE... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY...
FREDERIC ROSSIF ... HINNERK BRBHNS... CAMILO JOSÉ CELA... VACLAV HAVEL.. SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV...
ERNESTO SÁBATO... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND... CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS... LEOPOLDO ZEA... PABLO FREIRÉ...
BANIEL J. BOORSTIN... FRANCOIS JACOB... MANU BIBANGO... FAROBK HOSNY... SABRBBBIN AGA KHAN...
JORGE LAYELLI... LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG ... TAHAR BEN JELLOUN... GABRIEL GARCÍA NARGUEZ... JACGUES-
YVES COUSTEAU... NELINA NERCOURI... CARLOS FUENTES.., JOSEPH KI-ZERBO... VANBANA SHIVA... WILLIAM
STYRON... OSCAR NIEMEYER... NIKIS THEOBORAKIS... ATAHUALPA YBPANGUI... HERVÉ BOURGES... ABBEL
RAHNAN EL BACHA... SUSANA RINALDI,.. HUBERT REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS... A LETTER FRON FREUB TO
EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY... CHARLES MALAMOUD... UMBERTO ECO... OUVER STONE... ANDRE BRINK... JANES B.
WATSON... ANOS OZ... NICHEL SERRES... THÉOBORE HONOB... YVES COPPENS... EDOUARD J. HAUNICK...
JEAN HALABRIE... TRINH XBAN THUAN... ANTONI TAPIES...
THENE OF OUR JULY-AUGUST 1994 DOUBLE ISSUE:
NOT-SO-STRANGE STRANGERS
ENCOUNTERS WITH OTHER CULTURES AND WAYS OF LIFE
ALSO FEATURING AN INTERVIEW WITH THE CHILEAN WRITER
JOSÉ DONOSO
tmPVSSSOÊ
ffÊSÊÊÊ HHH^bbbbbbHhbHb^I
]]>
</page>
</document>
