<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="096850eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
MAY 1904
H
'
â .
. -0
M 1205 -9405 -22,00 F
mmm
m
£*«5l
M^^>i*:WSï
"HÜ
Mf
afôSWS
EuBiâffi
DUBM
ffl?
BJH
EW LOOK
AT THE
STORY OF
i i i u : i h;
INTERVIEW WITH
TRINH XÜÄM THUAN
INVENTING
THE URBAN FUTURE
QUEBEC: A CITY
BEYOND COMPARE
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
Orient and
Occident
by Jean Tallaron
An admirer ofArabic
calligraphy and Oriental
painting and poetry, Jean
Tallaron (1933-1977) was
a teacher before devoting
himself entirely to a form
of experimentation in
painting that focused on
the beauty of gesture. Of
the work shown here, he
wrote: "The art of the
Scythians, Slav or Persian
iconography and Arabic
calligraphy are the
meeting point between
the Orient and the
Occident."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
4 INTERVIEW W/TH
Trinh Xuan Thuan
Contents
HAY 1994
A NEW LOOK
AT THE HISTORY
OF CONNBNISN
9 An end and a beginning Cover:
Students demonstrate against police
by François Hartog repression (Prague, 1990)
11 RUSSIA Wanted: a new language
by Nikolai Kopossov
UNESCO IN ACTION
15
42 16 ROMANIA Past imperfect
UNESCO AND THE PREVENTION
OF NATURAL DISASTERS
by Zoe Petre Greenwatch
The Yokohama
Conference
10 GEORGIA The historian's responsibility Inventing the urban
future
44
by Georges Charachidzé by France Bequette
ARCHIVES
The collectivist betrayal
11 POLAND Myths that die hard
by Henryk Samsonowiczby Thomas Mann
40
HERITAGE
11 THE CZECH REPUBLIC Lost illusions 41
Quebec« a city beyond
compare
by Eva Schmidt-Hartmann COMMENTARY
by André Charbonneau, Yvon
Desloges and Marc Lafrance 15 BULGARIA When memory plays tricks by
49
by Liliana Deyanova Federico Nayor
Letters to the Editor
18 Unesco's historical works
by Christophe Wondji
19 AFRICA i/ An authentic picture Special consultant for this issue:
by Jean Dévisse François Hartog
The
ÏÏÏÏÏÏ
u>
I U
NESCO
OURIER
47th year Published monthly
In 32 languages and In Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION Of UNESCO, LONDON, 1 6 NOVEMBER 1 945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
TRINH
XUAN
THUAN
talks to
Neda El Khazen
Trinh Xuan Thuan is an astrophysicist from
Hanoi (Viet Nam). At the University of Vir¬
ginia in the United States he teaches a
course on astronomy for poets. As a "sur¬
veyor of the universe," he tries to under¬
stand its structure using the most sophis¬
ticated instruments of observation available
today, such as the Hubble space tele¬
scope. He has written widely and with
great clarity on the formation and evolution
of galaxies. His The Birth of the Universe:
the Big Bang and After appeared in 1993
(Harry N. Abrams, New York and Thames &
Hudson, London) and Secret Melody will be
published later this year (Oxford University
Press).
Astronomy bas made amazing strides
since the time of Galileo's telescope. How
does an astronomer work today?
The telescope is still the astronomer's
favourite instrument because communi¬
cating with the universe is usually done via
light and this light has to be captured. Since
the telescope that first enabled Galileo to
discover the mountains on the moon and
the satellites orbiting Jupiter, telescopes
have continued to improve, growing bigger
and better. In the world today there are
about fifteen giant telescopes with mirrors
measuring more than three metres across.
On top of an extinct volcano in Hawaii, at
an altitude of 4,500 metres, a colossus of a
telescope with a diameter of ten metres has
just been completed.
By putting telescopes into orbit around
the earth, we have been able to completely
escape turbulence from the earth's atmos¬
phere. The Hubble space telescope, which
was launched in 1990, is one of the greatest
achievements of contemporary astronomy.
It weighs eleven tons and is eleven metres
long it is as big as a locomotive. Because of
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
It is the stars that made the elements necessary for life. ... The
story they have to tell is one of the utmost importance to us because
it leads to our own. We are only Stardust
an optical flaw, it suffered from myopia, but
thanks to repairs done by astronauts from the
American space shuttle, it has now regained
its sight. Already it is beginning to give us a
vision of the universe in all its splendid clarity,
pick up even weaker radiation, and perceive
objects at even greater distances. For the
astronomer, to see far is to see early, because
it takes time for light to reach us. Sunlight
takes eight minutes to reach us; light from the
nearest star takes four years, and from the
closest galaxy the light left two million years
ago, when man first appeared on our planet.
We hope that Hubble will allow us to go
back in time to two to three billion years
after the Big Bang so that we can actually
witness the birth of galaxies, which remains
one of the great mysteries of contemporary
astrophysics.
Has the conquest ofspace changed the
way weperceive the universe?
Undoubtedly. Because conquering space
has also meant conquering the electro¬
magnetic spectrum. Generally it is believed
that astronomy is limited to what the eye
can see. But there is a whole range of light
waves that escape human eyesight, such
as infrared waves, microwaves (as in ovens)
and radio waves. So we have developed
radio telescopes that do not pick up waves
transmitted by radio and television sta¬
tions, but those produced by sources in
the cosmos. There are also ultraviolet light,
X-rays and gamma rays which contain a lot
of energy and which are blocked by the
earth's atmosphere fortunately, because
they are harmful to us. And so we have put
in orbit satellite telescopes specializing in
these diverse types of radiation so that
they can restore for us the cosmic landscape
in all its richness and variety.
How doyou analyseall this information?
After the telescope has picked up light
signals they are recorded by an electronic
detector. They are then digitalized, trans¬
lated into digits like the notes of music on a
compact disc. These digits are stored on
magnetic tapes, and using powerful com¬
puters the astronomer can process these dig¬
italized images, which can be viewed on a
screen, converted to colour, contrasted and
varied at will, depending on what he is
looking for.
Astronomers today no longer spend
their nights guiding telescopes in dark¬
ness, looking through the eyepiece, fighting
cold and struggling to stay awake. In a
well-lit, warm and comfortable room,
astronomers now command telescopes by
computer. They simply indicate the posi¬
tion of the star or galaxy they want to
study and it appears on the screen. Soon
communication satellites will enable
astronomers to make their observations
without going to the observatory. They
will not waste their time waiting for the sky
to clear, and they will be able to work in the
quiet of their own offices.
The Hubble space telescope was named
after a great American astronomer whose
workprovided the basis for the Big Bang
theory. What exactly is the Big Bang?
This theory gives the universe a historical
dimension, that is, a past, present and future.
It is based on a fundamental discovery made
by Edwin Hubble, who realized in 1929
that galaxies were fleeing the Milky Way,
and the further away they were, the greater
was the speed with which they were fleeing.
The universe, therefore, is expanding. If we
reverse the course of events, we get back to
the point at which everything started, some
fifteen billion years ago, when energy was
extremely high and there was an enormous
explosion: the Big Bang. The universe is
not immutable, as Newton believed. It has
a beginning and it is not eternal. The Big
Bang created time and expanding space.
Since then, other observations such as the
discovery of the cosmic background radia¬
tion which is left-over heat from the pri¬
mordial explosion have come to support
this theory. It is also confirmed by what
we have learned about the chemical com¬
position of stars and galaxies.
Matter was formed from the incred¬
ible energy freed by the Big Bang.
Yes, a tiny fraction of a second after the
primordial explosion, at exactly 1043 second
afterwards. What had happened before?
No one knows. Here we are up against a
wall that we cannot penetrate with our pre¬
sent knowledge and physics is out of its
depth. So at 10'43 second after the Big Bang
the universe is no bigger than the head of a
pin. It is extremely dense, and hotter than all
the hells of Dante. There is a quantum
vacuum. It is not a vacuum of calmness and
tranquillity, devoid of substance and
activity as we might imagine it but a
vacuum bubbling with all the energy that
had been released by the Big Bang, filled
with phantom particles and antiparticles.
This energy makes the universe expand
with lightning speed: it is dilating at a stag¬
gering rate during an infinitesimal amount
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
of time. Simultaneously, it is cooling off
and becoming diluted, making the ascent
towards complexity possible. Energy gives
birth to matter. At 106 second, when the
volume of the universe is about the same as
that of the solar system, the most elemen¬
tary particles, quarks, combine to produce
protons and neutrons. At the third minute,
when hydrogen and helium nuclei appear,
98 per cent of the universe's mass has been
constituted. The universe continues to
expand, bathing in a soup of radiation and
matter. But it is a non-homogeneous soup
in which there are irregularities. Some areas
are denser than others and one or two bil¬
lion years later they will give rise to galaxies
and stars. This fabulous ascension towards
diversity will persist to our day.
Where does life begin ?
In the heart of the stars. It is the stars that
made the elements necessary for life
oxygen, carbon, nitrogen, even heavy ele¬
ments such as iron. The story they have to
tell is of the utmost importance to us
because it leads to our own. We are only
Stardust. We are made up of chemical ele¬
ments that were created in stellar crucibles
and expelled into space by supernovae.
One has to realize that stars are born,
live and die just like human beings but on a
considerably bigger time-scale. They are
born in gigantic stellar nurseries, of col¬
lapsing hydrogen and helium clouds com¬
pressed into gaseous balls by gravity. In
their core, which is heated to tens of millions
of degrees, thermonuclear reactions take
place producing intense radiation that dif¬
fuses towards the surface. An equilibrium is
established between the outward push of
radiation and the inward gravitational pull.
During millions, billions of years, the
star consumes its hydrogen. When there is
none left, it starts to use up its helium
reserve. The combustion of helium pro¬
duces an enormous blast of energy. The
star distends on a colossal scale, and turns
red. In this cosmic oven the alchemy that
creates the bricks of life goes on relent
lessly. After several million years, more
than twenty new elements have been cre¬
ated in the heart of the red giant.
After the combustion of helium, it is
the turn of carbon, then oxygen, to burn.
Afterwards, more complex elements such
as neon, magnesium, aluminium and sul¬
phur appear. The same sequence of events
repeats itself: each time a combustible ele¬
ment has been exhausted, a new one starts
to burn, creating heavier and heavier ele¬
ments. When iron appears, the star has
come to the end of its life.
Why does this alchemy stop with iron ?
Because burning iron takes energy and
the star, which is running out of fuel, can no
longer provide energy. It stops radiating
and fades. Gravity takes over and com
presses the star until it collapses and dies.
Low-mass stars transform themselves into
white dwarfs. They then become invisible
and join the countless stellar corpses that
litter the galaxies. That will be the fate of our
sun in nine billion years. A high-mass star
(ten to thirty times the mass of the sun), on
the other hand, dies a violent death. Com¬
pressed by gravity, such a star reaches an
extraordinary density and when its heart
contracts, a shockwave is produced that
leads to a lightning explosion, shining with
the intensity of a billion suns. That is called
a supernova.
A supernova utilizes its enormous
energy to produce elements heavier than
iron, such as gold and silver, which later on
are used to make jewellery for pretty
women! The explosion projects all these
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
elements into interstellar space at a speed of
thousands of kilometres per second. These
are the seeds for future planets that may
bear life. The atoms of which we are made
today were created in a high-mass star that
exploded more than four and a half bil¬
lion years ago, before the birth of our sun.
Do you believe that life can exist else¬
where, on otherplanets, in othergalaxies?
It's probable. After all, the universe which
we observe is made up of a hundred billion
galaxies like the Milky Way, and each one
has a hundred billion stars, of which billions
resemble our sun. Each one of those stars is
accompanied by a group of planets. Some-
Sunset and starry sky photographed
from a 2,400-metre-high
observatory in the Canary Islands.
where there has to be a planet that is neither
too hot nor too cold for life to develop.
Scientists believe that other intelligent forms
of life can exist in our galaxy, or elsewhere
in the universe, but how and where do we
find them? It's like looking for a needle in a
haystack. We do not know in which direc¬
tion we should point our telescopes nor on
which frequency they should be set to pick
up possible signals. For the 500th anniver¬
sary of Christopher Columbus' voyage,
NASA launched a programme to listen to a
thousand stars like our sun on two fre¬
quencies and also to randomly scan the sky
on millions of frequencies.
What is the "anthropicprinciple" that
appears in modern cosmology?
The term comes from the Greek word
anthropos meaning man and, in a larger
sense, intelligence, consciousness. According
to the anthropic principle, the universe is
fine-tuned to an extraordinary precision
for consciousness to appear. One must
realize that our universe is determined by
four basic forces and about fifteen num¬
bers which are called physical constants.
The basic forces are gravity, which keeps the
planets circling the sun and our feet on the
ground; electromagnetic force, which makes
it possible for molecules to combine and
form strands of DNA; the strong (nuclear)
force, which binds protons and neutrons
together to form atomic nuclei; and the
weak (nuclear) force, which is responsible
for radioactivity. As for the numbers, they
include the speed of light, the mass of a
proton, the charge of an electron or the
gravitational constant. The value of these
numbers has been determined with great
precision: light travels at 300,000 km per
second. Why 300,000 km/s and not 3 m/s?
We have no idea why. We were given these
numbers and we have to live with them.
Astrophysicists cannot reproduce the
conditions of the Big Bang in their labo¬
ratories because these conditions were so
extreme. They would need a particle accel¬
erator the size of several light years which
is impossible. However, with their com¬
puters and their equations, they can have
fun building models of the universe
which I call toy universes to which they
attribute different physical constants. What
is extraordinary is that all these toy uni¬
verses are infertile. If the physical con¬
stants were varied ever so slightly then we
would no longer be around to talk about it.
If, for example, the intensity of gravita¬
tional force were increased, then the uni¬
verse would become more compact and
the stars would be ten million times less
massive than our moon. They would con¬
sume their fuel too quickly and the com¬
plexity necessary for the creation of life
could not develop. On the other hand, if
you decreased only a little the force of
gravity, then interstellar clouds could no
longer collapse and create stars. Without
stars there are neither heavy elements nor
life. Take, for example, the electrical charges
of a proton and an electron. The proton is
approximately two thousand times more
massive than the electron, and yet their
electrical charges are rigorously equal, but
opposite. If they would differ only by a bil¬
lionth of a billionth, the stars, the sun and
the earth would explode.
You can vary any other physical con¬
stant, the result is always the same: toy uni¬
verses are empty and sterile. One can con¬
clude from this that these constants were
fine-tuned to an astonishing precision so
that life could emerge and consciousness
appear. If you want to picture this precision,
imagine the accuracy that would be required
for an archer to be able to hit a 1 square cen¬
timetre target 15 billion light years away.
Talk offine-tuning makes one think
ofa hand that regulates. Should we think
in terms ofsome kindofregulatory mech¬
anism or should we see life as the result of
a long succession ofrandom happenings?
If one opts for chance, then one is forced
to invoke the theory of parallel universes
which quantum mechanics does allow for.
CONTINVED ON PACE SO »
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The fall of the Berlin Wall in 1989 marked the end
of a conception of history that had prevailed in Europe
for two centuries« How should the link between past,
present and future be defined from now on?
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
AN END AND A BEGINNING
by François Harto;
Afew months before the fall of the Berlin
wall an American historian named
Francis Fukuyama published an essay
entitled "The End of History?", which attracted
widespread media attention.1 Communism was
collapsing, and only democracy now remained
as the "final form of all human government".
History, in the sense of "a simple, coherent evo¬
lutionary process", had come to an end.
In the long story of the world the end of his¬
tory has been proclaimed cheerfully, anxiously
or resignedly more than once. To my mind,
however, the keynote of 1989 was something
different unpredictability: the unpredictability
ofwhat happened in that year, the growing unpre¬
dictability of the future it heralded, the unpre¬
dictability, even, of the past that it brought to an
end. The recent past was primarily affected, but
the remoter past has also become opaque and in
a sense unpredictable. This is where the historian
comes in.
History clearly needs rewriting in the former
Eastern bloc countries (the very expression used
to designate these countries smacks of uncer¬
tainty, as though they can only be described in
terms of something they have ceased to be and it
is not yet possible to say what they are). It is
equally clear that this will be a difficult task and
will involve more than just making corrections,
replacing inaccuracy with accuracy. There is also
a risk that new distortions will take the place of
old ones (the new ones perhaps mere revivals of
older historical myths). The articles in this issue
of the UNESCO Courier, with their varied
approaches, give some idea of the extent of the
task and of what is at stake.
It would be quite wrong to regard this essen¬
tial rewriting as the business of the "East" and
no one else. The changes in the East are affecting
the West and will continue to do so. We are all
in the same boat. We always have been. Despite
the antagonism between the two camps, some of
their basic presuppositions were the same. Both
shared a similar relationship with time and a
/\ joyful crowd on the Berlin Wall,
1 1 November 1 989.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
"The triumphal car of the
Republic". This illustration
commemorating the
establishment of the
Republic in France
appeared in a daily
newspaper, Le Petit Journal,
in 1912.
IO
FRANÇOIS HARTOG
is a French historian who
teaches ancient and modern
historiography at the Ecole des
Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales in Paris. He is
currently working on a book
on the Ancients and the
Moderns and history. Among
his published works are Le XIX'
siècle et l'histoire: le cas Fustel de
Cou/anges (1988, PUF
publishers, Paris; "The I9th
century and History: the Case
of Fustel de Coulanges") and
Le Miroir d'Hérodote (new
edition 1991, Gallimard
publishers, Paris; "The Mirror
of Herodotus").
similar idea of history, based on the idea of con¬
tinuous progress. Scientific socialism, its face
turned towards the radiant future, for long even
looked like the cutting edge of modernity. In
spite of very real political differences, we were
both beneficiaries of what I would call the same
great regime of historicity. That regime, which
began to exist around 1789, finally broke down
before our eyes in 1989. This is why the
rewriting of history is, for a fundamental reason,
also the business of the West. Should we talk of
rewriting, or of writing? What history should we
write today? What past, for what present?
A complete change of perspective
"When the past no longer sheds light on the
future, the mind walks in darkness." This sen¬
tence written by the French historian Alexis de
Tocqueville conveniently describes what may be
called the ancien régime of historicity and the
moment of its overthrow. Before, when the rela¬
tion of the past to the future was governed by
reference to the past, the "mind" knew where it
was going. For the purpose of writing history,
that was the heyday of the idea of history as a
teacher and guide for living, first set forth by
Cicero and later handed down and referred to
until the present time. History offered a collec¬
tion of examples for the instruction of readers
and primarily of rulers. The general idea was that
history was made for those who were supposed
to make it. By extension it came to be thought
of as "the common school of the human race".
During the period of the French Revolu¬
tion things became blurred, the landmarks of the
past faded, time suddenly seemed to speed up,
and the future became totally uncertain: the
mind walked in darkness. It was also a time
when people referred intensively to the past.
All kinds of analogies were put forward, as
people clung to the comforting idea of historical
parallels in an effort to understand and express
the strangeness of what was happening. The
French revolutionaries, for example, went back
to classical Antiquity to try to describe their
unprecedented actions.
In fact, however, a new regime of historicity
came into effect between the end of the eigh¬
teenth century and the beginning of the nine¬
teenth. Henceforth the past was no longer
expected to shed light on the future; the future
was expected to shed light on the past. The
future would make sense of the past; it would be
the starting-point for the writing of history.
Tocqueville is a witness to this reversal. In order
to understand France's past he travelled towards
or even into the future, sailing to America to
portray the "new" i.e. democratic, society there.
As a result he was able to see the Revolution not
so much as a break but as a continuation, an
extension, in many ways a completion of the
work of the absolute monarchy. This gradual
shifting of the relationships with time went
hand in hand with the growth of a modern
notion of history.
History as articulated in Germany in the
second half of the eighteenth century was history
in the singular, history as an end in itself, a
process. It defined itself as "knowledge of itself".
The philosophy of history superseded and took
over from the theology of history. What had
once been studied in history lessons no longer
had any point. How could history be "exem¬
plary" when the past no longer shed light on the
future? Or else the only lesson of history is
History with a capital "H", with its judgments
and its dustbins. In the logic of progress the
exemplary gives way to the event, which is
always unique. What is past is past.
To quote the French writer Julien Gracq,
"history has become essentially an ultimatum
issued by the Future to the present". I would
merely add that the ultimatum also extended
to the past and fell on historians, who during the
nineteenth century organized and regarded their
discipline as the science of the past. The pre¬
dominant medium of this ultimatum was
national history the nation having of course
been the outstanding phenomenon of the nine¬
teenth and early twentieth centuries. Any his¬
tory worth the name was bound to reconsider
the past in terms of the nation, searching for its
origins, celebrating its past and future glories,
and all too often surrendering to its mystique.
This was also the time when scientific history
and patriotic history went hand in hand, and
when in France three entities three persons,
almost France, the Nation and the Republic,
came together in the writings of Ernest Lavisse
to form a secular Trinity, the foundation of a his¬
tory as memory of the nation.
This regime of historicity was challenged
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
both before and especially after the 1914-1918
war. The German thinker Walter Benjamin
started to look for a different relationship with
history, i.e. a different historical temporality.
The idea of "remembrance", meaning reliving
the past, was central to this relationship. His¬
torical time only really comes into existence
when there is "a dazzling conjunction between
the past and the present". At the same time his¬
tory freed itself from the "tyranny" of the
national, political history was criticized as super¬
ficial, and in the 1920s economic and social his¬
tory developed in response to this crisis of his¬
tory. There was a search for a different
time-scale, inspired by economists' models and
organized not in simple linear terms according
to a succession of events but incorporating ideas
of cycles and conjunctures, and sensitive to the
recurrences, the enduring features and the long-
term processes of history in a word, ending up
with different layers of temporality, with Fer¬
nand Braudel's concept of la longue durée
long-term structures and trends.
But these criticisms and challenges, impor¬
tant though they were, were not enough to
make us change our regime of historicity espe¬
cially when it was fortified by the revolutionary
vistas opened up by the October Revolution,
followed by postwar reconstruction, the prac¬
tical victories of socialism after 1945 and the
East-West competition that followed them.
Signs of crisis began to appear in the West in
the 1960s. As regards relationships with time,
there was first the widespread acceptance of the
idea that there was no future. Then the idea that
the present is all that matters, each day con¬
suming (and therefore producing) more and
more novelties and historical events to feed the
media system it has created. It is thirsty for pre¬
diction. But, more surprisingly, it has also turned
out to be obsessed with conservation (the suc¬
cess of the "heritage" theme). It would also like
to be able to watch itself happening, with,
already, the eye of history.
The most typical manifestation of this dream
of controlling or abolishing time is the concern
to save more and more time to the point of
almost making it disappear, forgetting about it
or escaping from it. But this present, which is
somewhat unreal because it wants to be the
whole of reality, is also a time when people are
seeking identity and roots. Memory and com¬
memoration became the catchwords of the
1980s, and were eventually, though not at first,
taken up by historians, as they began skating
over the surface of memory.
All in all, it gradually appeared that the future
no longer shed light on the present, and hence not
on the past. History has ceased to be the future's
ultimatum to the present. At the same time, the
future has regained its unpredictability (the oppo¬
site of an end of history) and the past its opacity.
It is the historian's task to revisit the past, to
find other ways through it, to ask it other ques¬
tions, to acquire new points of view, and to
express a different relationship with time in
short to try and define the features of the regime
of historicity that we have now entered.
It is not a matter of putting across a back¬
ward-looking view of the past, nor of setting up
the past as a judge of the present under the
impression that the days when history taught
lessons have returned; but rather of reading the
marks left by a forgotten, repressed, aborted
past against the background of the present
not so much commemoration as remembrance.
"We must reopen the past," wrote the philoso¬
pher Paul Ricceur in 1985, "and revive its unful¬
filled, inhibited, nay its murdered potentiali¬
ties." That is what Michelet, who saw historians
as a bridge between the living and the dead,
meant when he called on "the silences of his¬
tory" to speak.
1 "The End of History ?" was published in summer 1989
and later appeared in expanded form in a book, The End
ofHistory and the Last Man (New York, Free Press and
Toronto, Maxwell Macmillan Canada, 1992).
trotest posters in the
eastern part of Berlin
against a decision by the
authorities to remove the
statue of Lenin ( 1 99 1 ). The
large panel bears the
ironical message: "Here
the Berlin Senate
decontaminates German-
German history in the
framework of a cleansing
operation against those
who think differently.
Sponsor: Clean and
Remove All. Contractor:
Black-out and Co."
i»	-r.<
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
After ceasing
to toe the
Marxist line,
some Russian
historians are
still searching
for a fresh
approach to
their country's
past
Wanted: a new language
by Nikolai Kopossov
H
12
ISTORY is a language unto itself that
allows historians to speak simultane¬
ously about the past and about them¬
selves. It is not enough to say, like the great his¬
torians of old, that history is written on the
basis of sources: no less important is the fact that
it is written by historians.
The rewriting of history therefore does not,
in my view, mean "simply" the reappraisal,
however radical, of historical events. It means
changing the language of history, which in turn
calls for a historian of a different cultural and
anthropological type, and for a rethinking of the
relationship between history and society.
Thus defined, the rewriting of history has not
yet been undertaken in Russia. We go on
speaking the same historical language as before.
The only difference is that we now speak it
much less often and more reluctantly, the main
reason, in my opinion, being that historians
have not changed as much as society.
A blurred picture of the past
Perestroika brought about radical changes in
the Soviet public's awareness of history. The
major offensive against communist ideology
took place on the battlefield of history, but it was
not waged by historians. It is no wonder that
politicians took such an interest in history, since
history, more than anything else, was the source
from which the Soviet regime drew its legiti¬
macy. In the period that proved decisive for the
overthrow of communist ideology, the years
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Left, World youth is for
peace! A painting to the
greater glory of Stalin
(1951).
Above, Music Peace
Festival in Moscow ( 1 989).
between 1987 and 1989, discussion centred
mainly on an assessment of the role of Stalin. The
democratic press scored a decisive success when
it managed to link the name of Stalin, in the
popular mind, with the gulag, the Soviet regime
and socialism.
It did not, however, succeed in completely
overcoming the traditional idealization of Stalin's
rule. Apart from the fact that there were still a
number of convinced Stalinists, large segments
of the population had lost their moral bearings
as regards their attitude towards the country's
past. While some rejected the Soviet historical
experience out of hand, others did not know
what to think about it. For many Soviets, the
idealized image of Lenin continued to coun¬
terbalance the image of Stalin and to lend moral
credibility to the Soviet regime.
By 1990, however, everything "Soviet" had
been discredited to such an extent that Lenin's
image too was gradually tarnished. In June 1991,
a majority of Leningraders voted for a return to
the city's former name of St. Petersburg. How¬
ever, the image of Lenin had not yet become
such a powerfully negative symbol as that of
Stalin by the time that history, quite simply,
ceased to interest people.
The political events of 1991-1993 removed
history definitively from the forefront of public
concerns. The Soviet regime's loss of legitimacy
became complete, and the democratic ideology
that came out on top looked elsewhere for legit¬
imacy, primarily to an idealized image of
Western civilization, the market economy and
parliamentary democracy. But if that image had
a "historical dimension", it was that of a history
alien to Russia.
On the other hand, the communists and
nationalists who joined forces to form the oppo¬
sition could not agree on an assessment of the
Soviet period because of the deeply held anti-
communist views of some of the nationalists.
The opposition's own forays into history have
in the main been limited to the extolling of
Russia's military exploits.
The reawakening, in connection with the
nationalist movement, of interest in the Orthodox
church and its history and in the history of
Russian religious thought is of relatively minor
importance, owing in part, perhaps, to the fact
that the Russian church adopts an extremely
cautious stance and plays only a modest role in
social life. There are no grounds for believing that
a plan for the rebuilding of society attractive to II
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Tob. /leHMH OMMLUflET
3eM/IhO OT HeMHCTM.
"Comrade Lenin sweeps
away the scum of the
Earth". A Soviet poster of
1920.
14
NIKOLAI KOPOSSOV
is a Russian historian who is a
research fellow at the
Independent Humanities
Academy in St. Petersburg and
associate director of studies at
the Ecole des Hautes Etudes
en Science Sociales in Paris. He
is co-author, with Dina
Khapaeva, of a sociological
study on the "Mass Historical
Consciousness of the Soviet
People".
the majority of the population can be worked out
on the basis of an "Orthodox renaissance".
There is thus no political movement in Russia
today that has succeeded in creating an image of
the country's past that would inspire Russians
with confidence in the future. We are witnessing
a crisis of historical awareness in the population
at large. How are professional historians reacting
to this situation?
Historians defend their turf
From the very beginning oîperestroïka, the polit¬
ical passivity of most historians stood in marked
contrast to the exceptional intensity of the debates
about history. It was left to journalists, writers,
sociologists and economists to set the agenda in
the rethinking of the past. If historians expressed
themselves at all in public, it was usually to sound
a warning against jumping to conclusions. The
main thrust of their contributions to the debates
was to deliver a lesson in professionalism to jour¬
nalists who had dared to encroach on their terri¬
tory. The situation, however, became more and
more ambiguous: anything that people acknowl¬
edged as being "the truth about history" they
learned from sources other than those whose
vocation it was to act as guardians of that truth.
The insistent calls for historians to "tell the truth
at last" threw them into confusion. Most of them
were in no mood for any radical changes in their
field.
It is true that there was a movement for reform
among historians, calling for democratization of
their discipline, the abolition of ideological sur¬
veillance, the lifting of the political ban on research
into the "blank spaces" of history, wider access to
the archives, international contacts and so forth.
These demands were reasonable as far as they
went, but they related only to the most obvious
defects in the manner in which the writing of his¬
tory was organized under the Soviet regime, and
scarcely touched upon its internal problems.
Many of the reformers' demands were met:
learned societies were given greater indepen¬
dence and the most conservative of their senior
officials replaced, while the editorial boards of the
historical journals were revamped. The principal
journal, Voprosy istorii ("Questions of History"),
became one of the most widely read publica¬
tions of the democratic press. Curiously, it soon
began to give pride of place to publishing eye¬
witness accounts, especially the previously
banned memoirs of disgraced public figures not,
it will be agreed, a sign that much original research
was being done. The direction taken by the
country's leading historical journal faithfully
reflects the state of Russian historiography as a
whole, which, apart from a certain political reori
entation, continues to discuss the same prob¬
lems as before from the same viewpoints as
before, and observes the same professional stan¬
dards as before.
Although much of what had hitherto seemed
unshakeable has been challenged or even
rejected, historians are making no attempt to cast
such radical doubts upon the basic concepts
and standards of their own profession, and the
task of changing it from within is an issue that
has not been raised. Only a few expressions of
dissatisfaction with the prevailing intellectual
and professional standards are heard today.
Generally speaking, the old "history establish¬
ment" has not given ground. Worse still, while
the earlier rise in public interest in history did
not bring about any substantial change within
the profession, the decline in that interest has
helped to reactivate its conservative forces.
Hence, since about 1992 historians specializing
in the Soviet period, who had until shortly
before then been obliged to admit that their
discipline was in deep crisis, have been regaining
their self-confidence and denying that there is
any need to reconsider their approach, although
they have not yet influenced public perceptions.
History is thus, after being slightly smartened
up, refusing further, more far-reaching changes.
Why is this so?
Sticking to an ideological
compromise
The process of renewal in social science pre¬
supposes that new social experience and a new
individual self-awareness will be expressed in
terms of scientific theory. It is precisely this
"renewal mechanism" that has functioned badly
in Russian historiography.
As a result of the long domination exercised
over it by Marxism, history became incapable of
expressing anything other than a rather limited
range of social experience, the experience of
statehood, nationhood and social conflicts. The
social experience that became more and more
important for individual self-awareness in the
post-war world and especially during the
1960s the experience of the individual playing
an active role in culture was almost impos¬
sible to express in the language of Marxist his¬
tory. Even after ceasing to toe the Marxist line,
history, as normally written in Russia, remains
heavily dependent on the nation-state concept.
Of course, not all Russian historians are
affected by this dependence. In the 1960s and
1970s, for instance, the increase in research into
cultural history, which practically fell outside
the Marxist historian's field of vision, gave expres¬
sion to the experience of the individual as playing
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
an active role in culture. It was, to my mind, pre¬
cisely because of the tremendous psychological
energy they put into the study of medieval culture
that eminent historians such as A. Gurevich, Y.
Bessmertny and L. Batkin were able to produce
such excellent work. It is noteworthy that the his¬
torians of this group are today advocating change
from within the profession.
They are, however, exceptions. The majority
of Soviet historians hew too closely in their
thinking to the ideological compromise offered
to the intelligentsia by the Brezhnev regime. At
the price of an outward show of loyalty to
Marxism and on condition that their personalities
and their individual social experience should on
no account emerge from their research, histo¬
rians were allowed to write studies that were to
a large extent devoid of ideological content. Most
Soviet historians invested all their emotional
energy in this compromise, which was a rela¬
tively harmless but perfectly respectable form
of opposition to the regime.
Many people were, of course, aware of the fal¬
sity of this situation, and this made them all the
more indignant about the medieval history spe¬
cialists who allowed themselves to use the lan¬
guage typical of the times to "express a personal
opinion" and "speak on their own behalf". This
conflict, which had been simmering for a long
while, came out into the open in the perestroïka
period, when it became all too evident that "pro¬
fessional ideology" had made Russian histori¬
ography incapable of dynamic development at a
time when the circumstances were exception¬
ally propitious for the emergence of new
approaches to history. H
The cover of the Soviet
magazine Ogonyek (1949)
shows Stalin as a star
beaming down on Moscow.
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
When the
collective
memory has
been warped by
Stalinism and
national-
communism,
re-establishing
a critical
outlook is an
uphill job
Past imperfect oy Zoe Petre
16
IN the countries of eastern Europe, control of
the collective memory has been an essential
feature of dictatorship. From the time of
the Communist Manifesto of 1848, history was
the arena in which the very legitimacy of the dic¬
tatorship of the proletariat was decided. As
George Orwell wrote in his famous novel, 1984,
"Who controls the past controls the future."
To begin with, this take-over of history had a
dual purpose. First, it was designed to impose an
official interpretation of the past as a forecast of
the present and a supposedly glorious future.
Second, it was a deliberate attempt to blot out all
consciousness of national history and all positive
memories of the past. The Romanians, who had
shown a reprehensible loyalty to their nation by
claiming their historic provinces and their national
identity, had to be taught that this loyalty and this
identity were "bourgeois prejudices" generated
by a false view of history. Impoverished by Stal¬
inist dogma and subjected to an obsessive search
for the "class struggle" the historian's only
legitimate criterion this new version of history,
which denied the past any specificity, was
designed only to justify the present.
Hundreds of teachers, hastily trained during
the 1950s, continued to use the rudimentary
stereotypes of this Stalinism which they had par-
rotted in their youth. Later, however, another
branch was grafted onto this stock, namely the
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
"i
7W:
^^V1 A .
i - kj
Left, Nicolae Ceausescu
addresses the National
Assembly In 1 977 during a
ceremony to mark the
centenary of Romania's
independence.
Below, televised images of
the trial of Nicolae and
Elena Ceausescu In 1989.
national communism of Nicolae Ceausescu and
his entourage.
National history was muzzled for ten years.
Then, playing the card of restoring the past,
giving the impression that the "people" had man¬
aged to preserve the sense of national identity that
had been distorted by professional historians,
and exploiting the frustration of people trauma¬
tized by the crushing of their memories, this
second manipulation finally destroyed the critical
approach to history. First national history was
annihilated by the universalist claims of Stalinist
doctrine. Then universal history was annihilated
by being reduced to a mere backcloth for an
inflated vision of national glory. Increasingly
pompous language, together with a growing
refusal to think about method or exercise critical
judgment, eventually brought in a falsely pious
rhetoric of commemoration whose deleterious
consequences are far from forgotten today.
Admittedly this exercise was never entirely
successful. In the interstices of the system some
people continued with dignity and humility to
practise the profession of historian with dignity
and humility, and a brilliant array of teachers,
trained between the wars in Europe's great history
departments, went on teaching until the 1970s.
These historians handed down to their pupils an
ethic, a model and a historian's conscience that
helped them survive both intellectually and
morally. During the short and deceptive interlude
of 1965-1971 when the regime made apretence
of openness to the outside world in order to con¬
solidate its position this generation of pupils
managed to make contacts and set up a network
of intellectual communication that mitigated
their isolation and allowed them to maintain a cer¬
tain professional dignity.
Exploring continents, rethinking
concepts
These remnants of historical awareness became
essential after 1989, when a revival of the human
sciences began to get under way. The enormity of
the task still to be accomplished by historians is
obvious. It involves rethinking concepts and
bringing to light the forgotten continents of his¬
tory, with drastically reduced human and mate¬
rial potential. A brief list of the objectives of this
work shows that it will be an uphill job. In my
opinion, such a list consists of two main parts: one
of gaps to be filled, and one of ideas to be chal¬
lenged. And of course the two parts overlap.
The most important gaps are due to the pro¬
hibitions of the period just ended. Both docu¬
ments and interpretation were subject to cen¬
sorship. The state archives only kept part of the
documents prc-dating the Second World War.
Those regarded as "sensitive" (documents
relating to the Royal Family, the political parties
and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs) were placed
in reserved archives, mainly those of the com¬
munist party's Institute of History. These
archives have only become accessible since 1990.
For the documents of the past fifty years
ÎI
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Ihe Romanian royal family
photographed between the
(those of the communist party, the political
police, and the army), it is still necessary to
apply jointly to the army and the secret ser¬
vice. The recent opening of the state, communist
party, Komintern and KGB archives in Russia
has added a mass of documents essential for the
study of the history of the communist regime in
Romania. Moreover, one of the most urgent
tasks is to quickly establish a stock of "non-
traditional" documents oral history and audio
and visual archives of the last fifty years. This
is indispensable for sophisticated modern
research into the mentality of totalitarianism.
The history of the origins, establishment
and development of the communist regime,
with all its ramifications, is the area which most
urgently needs to be studied. In a critical exam¬
ination of the past fifty years, far more is at
stake than mere scholarly interest: it amounts to
a test of a society's capacity to make a clean
break with its past. Some major topics that must
now be studied include: the history of the anti-
communist resistance and the repression; the
history of the institutions of communism, and
of the divergent, indeed marginal and under¬
ground economies and societies, that the system
controlled or masked; and also the leading fig¬
ures of the system and the dynamics of its polit¬
ical, military, and intellectual elites.
This field, so far more closed to critical inves¬
tigation than any other, needs to be reopened. At
the same time, research should be carried out
into the great taboos of official communist his¬
toriography: the institutions of the modern
Romanian state (the monarchy, the army, the
parliamentary system and the political parties in
the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, including
18
the real history of the communist party, which
was subject to a particularly distorting cult);
the history of Transylvania, the key to the dis¬
putes between Romania and Hungary a front¬
line subject for historians; universal history,
systematically marginalized by the institutional
system and also by lack of information and con¬
tact with the international academic commu¬
nity; and lastly the basic techniques of historical
research epigraphy, palaeography, and literary
criticism, genealogy, diplomatic and heraldry.
These tools of rigorous investigation were
neglected as well as feared by the kind of rough-
and-ready history that prevailed for so long.
As regards concepts, the situation is even
more difficult. On the one hand, resistance to the
ideologization of history was often reflected in
a kind of conceptual paralysis, a rejection of
any historical discussion, and a positivism that
was never really questioned. Moreover, no his¬
torian managed to escape completely from the
division of the historical field laid down by the
regime, even by keeping the official line at arm's
length. Once at least half the resources of his¬
torical research were devoted to the study of
social or national movements, the accumulated
results of this work were bound to end up by
endorsing a viewpoint in which social conflicts
(or the nation) constitute the main driving force.
The sleep of reason
The two-pronged offensive against the critical
awareness of history Stalinist indoctrination
and then the official history of national commu¬
nism thus resulted in the establishment of a his¬
torical mythology. If even professional historians
sometimes find it hard to remember that this
mythology exists and to free themselves from it,
what can be expected of people at large? The
myth of a people's origins, of founding fathers or
saviours, of a people both chosen and crucified by
history, this edifying "nineteenth-century" per¬
spective focusing on a people's identity, is the
most difficult obstacle to surmount. This approach
is the basis for a false appreciation of the present,
which is all the more difficult to correct because
it has become sacrosanct. There is still widespread
confusion about whether history is an essentially
critical exercise or an act of commemoration, a
pious discourse about the past.
Keeping the invasion of stereotypes at bay is
not easy, particularly in a society which has
known not only the traumas of forty-five years
of totalitarian rule but also the violence of a
bloody and spectacular change of regime. This
violent break was seen as a threat to the identity
not only of the privileged groups of the old
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
regime, who were directly accused, but also of
the "little people", who had resigned themselves
to coming to terms with totalitarianism and
whose precarious inner comfort was now dis¬
turbed. These men and women, hitherto crushed
by fear, refuse to give up the amnesia that for so
long helped them to survive and in many cases
cling to the myths of national identity in order
to regain their shaky dignity. Not the least of
them are the professional historians who repress
their critical spirit.
If, in the field of history, "collective knowl¬
edge" today corresponds to neither of the two
official versions, the mongrel view that has
emerged from them has no more affinities with
a critical consciousness of history than they do.
A separate study would be needed to cover this
curious blend of incredulity and myth, of dis¬
trust and stereotypes, in which emotions (espe¬
cially hatred) overcome rational thought. It pro¬
duces a kind of rant, a tissue of empty and
inconsistent verbiage that robs of its meaning not
only the fabric of the myths of official history,
but also history as a rational judgment, sup¬
ported by evidence, of the past.
Such a climate cannot foster calm historical
discussion. But this discussion must take place.
If critical learning and a truthful collective
memory are not re-established, the sleep of
reason may continue. The real historians of the
East, Romanian historians among them, must
recover the memory of their own history. It is
they, with their experience, both individual and
collective, who are best equipped to recall the
real memory of communist totalitarianism as a
global phenomenon of twentieth-century his¬
tory. The destructive nature of the century now
drawing to a close, which stems not from some
chance feature but from the inhuman, deeply
perverse essence of both fascism and commu¬
nism, has only just begun to be considered. It is
our duty to think more deeply about it. The
lion's share of this task will no doubt fall on
the historians of eastern Europe. It is for them
to collect the documentary evidence, and to
carefully dismantle the institutional, social, and
ideological machinery in order tô put the tools
essential for the search for truth within reach of
their colleagues the world over.
The great illusions of the past about the
heuristic or educational capacities of writing
history have collapsed. Critical study of the
past remains the only defence, fragile though it
be, against a hideous return of human error.
Demonstrators give the V
for victory sign after the fall
of Ceausescu.
ZOE PETRE,
of Romania, is professor of
ancient history and dean of the
history faculty of the
University of Bucharest. She
was co-author with Liana
Lupas of a commentary (in
French) on Aeschylus's "Seven
against Thebes" ( 1 98 1 , Paris
and Bucharest) and recently
published (in Romanian) a
study on "Greek Civilization
and the Origins of Democracy"
(1992, Erasmus publishers,
Bucharest). 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The dangers of an idea of
history that fuels ethnic
conflicts
The
historian's
responsibility
by Georges
Charachidzé
10
GEORGES CHARACHIDZE,
is a Georgian-born French
historian who teaches the
languages and civilizations of
the Caucasus at the Institut
National des Langues et
Civilisations Orientiales and at
the Ecole Pratique des Hautes
Etudes (IV* section), both in
Paris. He is also director of a
research centre on the
Caucasus and the Indo-
European world associated
with France's National Centre
for Scientific Research (CNRS).
Among his published works are
Prométhée ou te Caucase (1986,
Flammarion publishers, Paris;
"Prometheus or the
Caucasus") and La Mémoire
indo-européenne du Caucase
(1987, Hachette, Paris; "The
Indo-European memory of the
Caucasus").
IT is a well-known fact that the Soviet Union's
intellectual bureaucrats, from the 1930s
onwards, imposed upon the country a theory
of history that they had put together from scratch.
Strangely enough and here we come to the
heart of the matter this theory was taken on
board and, as it were, absorbed by everybody,
from social scientists and intellectuals to school¬
children and the man in the street. It entered the
public domain, merging with people's own ideas
about their national past. The theory is easily
summarized, since it boils down to a few crude
assertions: the history of any human group, seen
as something smooth and uniform, describes a
flawless trajectory from its palaeolithic origins
through to the predictable, inevitable stages of
modern evolution. It progresses under its own
impetus along the clearly signposted path leading
to the ideal society of tomorrow, if not indeed
today. All this is familar, all too familiar.
An unexpected convergence
What is less well known are the ways in which
this theory was adjusted to fit in with the ways in
which the history of the various peoples of the
U.S.S.R. was written. In Georgia, and doubtless
elsewhere, there was no problem in making the
adjustment: officialdom's view of human evolu
tion fitted in nicely with the "national" concep¬
tions of history. Thus, an early view of the past,
that of the chroniclers and their royal masters of
the eleventh to eighteenth centuries, pictured
humanity, worldwide to begin with and then
Georgian, as marching straight towards its first
goal, the introduction of Christianity in the fourth
century. It then brought on stage the unbroken
line of Georgian sovereigns, whose epic story
likewise tended towards a single end: the defence
of the faith, the frontiers and the rights of the
kingdom, which would lead to the complete ful¬
filment of its Christian grandeur and legitimacy.
There was nothing in this that was contra¬
dictory to Soviet official dogma: these stages
indeed corresponded to those that any well
ordered community should pass through before
achieving its final goal and entering the promised
society. School textbooks and other official pub¬
lications were quite clear about this, vying with
one another to stress the positive nature of the
country's conversion to Christianity, and it is
obvious that neither perestroika nor indepen¬
dence has made any difference in this respect.
Let us take another example. Nineteenth-
century history, that of the philologists and the
romantics but also that of their followers in
more recent times, according to whom Georgia
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
was engaged in a constant struggle to preserve its
identity, also fits in easily with the official Soviet
version. The main thing was to see the course of
Georgian history as leading up to the country's
entry into the Russian, and later Soviet, empire.
On the way, the saga of the Georgian people
merges spontaneously into the march of uni¬
versal history as its destiny blends in with that
oftheU.S.S.R.
It was not that the Soviet authorities
"decreed" and imposed on the Georgians the
view the latter should take of their own his¬
tory. They simply encouraged the development
of this view, changing its emphasis slightly and
"adding to" it (especially the end of the story, the
country's incorporation into Russia and then
into the U.S.S.R.) in other words they
endorsed it.
They likewise endorsed the resumption and
continuation of the task begun by the kings and
queens of Georgia, that of compiling the complete
annals of the kingdom. It was, again, the Soviet
state that, through its specialized academic insti¬
tutions, authorized and supported the scientific
enterprise of publishing historic manuscripts and
documents, especially religious texts. Finally, the
three conceptions of Georgia's past that of the
former monarchs, that of traditional historians,
and that of doctrinaire Soviet historians worked
their way together into the collective conscious¬
ness, becoming part and parcel of Georgian lore
and combining to form the new, commonly
accepted version of history.
This, then, is how things stand after inde¬
pendence (1991). Georgians all know, and never
tire of repeating, that they must now cast off the
old ideological straitjackets and at last give his¬
tory, regained at the same time as national sov¬
ereignty, free rein. The question is, how to go
about it and, above all, what to do?
There are, first of all, two obvious tasks to
which many people have already committed
themselves: that of expunging or correcting the
falsifications practised for seventy years by Soviet
officialdom and its local representatives, and that
of filling in the "gaps" in history, its "forgotten"
or forbidden periods. For several years now,
newspapers, magazines and books have been
making a good job of bringing to light the history
of independent Georgia from 1918 to 1921 and of
the national uprising of 1924, reconsidering the
"Russo-Georgian rapprochement" of 1783 to
1801, and revealing the extent, the depth and the
true nature of terror and repression, with their
camps and massacres. All this is happening spon¬
taneously, so to speak; the competence of those
involved is almost as great as their enthusiasm, and
it will not take long to put paid to Soviet manip¬
ulations of the past.
But what about history as such, in particular
that blend of different views of history that
people carry around in their heads? These ideas
are so familiar that it is hard to reject them lock
stock and barrel. They do not lend themselves
easily to analysis or even to being sorted out. The
counterfeit versions of the past put about by
Soviet officialdom are difficult to separate from
the other conceptions of history since they
overlap with them, enfold them and are contin¬
uations of them.
Remembering 'forgotten' times
Since independence, two changes have occurred
but have not affected the basic doctrine. Firstly, all
references to Soviet-style "socialism" have been
removed. History is thus again seen as performing
a perfect trajectory, from its beginnings to the
goal towards which the Georgian people is
heading of its own free will: that of the nation, free
and entire, at last coming into its own. The sce¬
nario is thus the same as that of the nineteenth-cen¬
tury historians. Secondly, in this case marking a
break with those historians but harking back to the
ideas held dear by the kings and their chroni¬
clers, the Christian faith is regarded as the driving
wpposite page,
The new man ( 1 92 1 ), a
watercolour by Nikolai
Kogut (1 89 1- 1 959).
Below, a mid- 19th-century
lithograph depicting a
Georgian prince.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
I n May 1 989, a young
woman brandishes a
sacred ¡mage In Tbilisi
during a massive
demonstration to
celebrate the anniversary
of the Georgian Republic
of 1918.
force in history. In other words, the saga of the
Georgian people is still working itself out in
accordance with the very model that was until
lately favoured by the Soviet authorities, the
only difference being that it now culminates in
the fulfilment of the Christian faith.
This is why recent historical publications,
whatever their level, their scope or their reader¬
ship, add nothing new to the existing edifice.
They either carry on from where traditional his¬
tory left off, supposedly purging it of all
"Marxist" impurities, or they re-issue religious
texts that have already been studied and pub¬
lished for a long time, simply giving them a wider
circulation. All the major historical research pro¬
jects are oriented towards the past of the
Orthodox church or religious archaeology, or
towards republishing, on a grand scale, the writ¬
ings of the fathers of the Georgian church
which have in any case long been in print. There
is no escaping the obvious fact that Christian
teleology is purely and simply taking the place of
the teleology of "scientific socialism".
As to the idea of history as destiny, unfolding
uninterruptedly from ancient times, close to
the very beginnings, through to the ultimate,
quasi-eschatological goal, there is no question of
modifying or even touching it. That idea, how
ever implausible, remains firmly in place, for it
makes it possible to set up, as a defence against
the demands, legitimate or otherwise, of the
ethnic minorities, the Abkhazians and Osse-
tians in particular, the perfectly preserved mono¬
lith of Georgia's long history.
As long as the ethnic conflicts continue and
as long as they are being fought on the battlefield
of what is mistakenly supposed to be history, the
rewriting of history, necessary and salutary
though it be, will remain a dead letter. It is not
enough to rid the theory and practice of history
of the superficial traces left by Soviet ideology,
which are more a matter of vocabulary than of
substance. Such measures will continue to be
insufficient as long as the conception under¬
lying the whole historical edifice remains intact.
While the Georgians' almost pathological blind¬
ness to their own history persists, it will be
quite impossible to extirpate its real Soviet roots.
In fact, the persistence of this blindness in
regard to the past and the return to a retrograde
conception of history fuel and reinforce the cul¬
tural and political component of the present
ethnic conflicts. In Georgia, more than else¬
where, history and historians bear responsi¬
bility for the present and the future which in
Georgia's case is a great pity.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Historians
should eschew
the role of
prophecy and
myth-making
Myths that die hard
by Henryk Samsonowicz
Above, a ceremony held
in the church of St.
Stanislas In Warsaw in
1983 to mark the third
anniversary of the Gdansk
agreements which led to
the creation of the
"Solidarity" trade union.
IN eastern Europe, historical materialism had
a dual role: first to demonstrate that all
changes must inevitably lead to world com¬
munism, and secondly to justify the political
activities of the moment and, in particular, the
reasons for whatever policy was pursued by
Moscow at any given time.
In Poland, this doctrine was supposed to
"explain" both the territories annexed from
Germany after the Second World War and the
territories lost to the U.S.S.R. in the east. It also
led to certain manipulations (comical, to say
the least) of Poland's past. For example, Casimir
III the Great, who ruled in the fourteenth cen¬
tury, was downgraded in the official textbooks,
where he was designated by the figure "HI"
because he had annexed part of Ukraine to
Poland and abandoned Pomerania to the Teu¬
tonic Knights. After 1956, Casimir was par
tially rehabilitated but suspicion of him
remained strong. Depending on whether or not
they justified the gradual progress of mankind
towards communism, historical figures,
processes and actions were decreed to be either
"progressive", meaning good, or "retrograde",
meaning bad.
However, as the institutional crisis gathered
momentum, attempts to impose such crude
views of the more distant past were gradually
abandoned. The situation in regard to recent
history was quite different, however. For
example, it was forbidden to write about the
massacre of Polish prisoners of war by the Rus¬
sians at Katyn, the bloody repression of the
Stalin era, the civil war in Poland after 1945,
the war against the Ukrainians or the anti-Semi¬
tism that was rife during the events of 1968.
Similarly, it was extremely difficult to publish
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
In October 1956, during
the rising in Budapest
(Hungary), demonstrators
climb on a Soviet tank in
front of parliament.
24
HENRYK SAMSONOWICZ,
of Poland, teaches medieval
history in Warsaw.
anything at all about controversial popular fig¬
ures such as Marshal Józef Pilsudski in Poland,
Jozef Tiso in Slovakia or Imre Nagy in Hungary.
Black legend, white legend
This state of affairs confirmed the physical law
that action and reaction are equal and oppo¬
site. Fighting to preserve its identity, civil society
was to create a mythology of history: there
would be a "white legend" as well as a "black
legend". In Poland Marshal Pilsudski (1867-
1935) never enjoyed such popularity in his life¬
time as he did under the regime of martial law
proclaimed after 1981. There were three rea¬
sons for this. First, he had achieved victory in the
war against Russia in 1920. Secondly, he was
the symbolic figure of the political generation
that had succeeded in restoring the state after the
First World War. Thirdly, he was perceived as a
politician who stood for the sovereignty and
independence of Poland. The opinion that
society formed of him was of course based on
what was known at the time about the history of
the inter-war years, but it also reflected a genuine
collective need and the country's profound
desire to see its dignity asserted.
This reaction to the official version encour¬
aged a search for truth in the old textbooks that
had been used before the days of the communist
regime. The nineteenth-century historians were
particularly highly thought of by readers. The
Lithuanians, the Poles, the Czechs and the Slo¬
vaks did not acquire their own state until after
the First World War, while the Bulgarians, the
Romanians and the Hungarians only achieved
independence in the nineteenth century after a
long period of subjection. In every case in which
a national community did not have its own
state, history played an essential compensatory
role. Real or imagined, made up of facts but
also of myths, history reflected a search for
identity and was often positioned in relation to
a Utopian golden age. That is why historical lit¬
erature written at a time of subjection to "com¬
fort men's hearts" became popular again during
the period of Soviet domination.
Witnesses for the prosecution
However, this "idealizing" current also endeav¬
oured to absorb what were known as the "blank
spots", the parts of the past that had been deleted
from official history. The human hecatomb sac¬
rificed to the October Revolution, the war of
independence between Poland and Russia, the
mass deportations and massacres perpetrated
against the Poles in the days of Stalin, the total
indifference the Soviet authorities had shown
towards the desperate Warsaw insurrection
those were just some of the subjects raised by the
opposition and followed with interest by the
whole of society at a time when they were passed
over in silence or distorted by the authorities.
In any case, those who had taken part in the
events of the recent past were still alive. Their
role had been diminished or falsified, but their
testimony was too important to be completely
ignored. These people provided knowledge of
the "blank spots" through their activities and
through their writings, which were circulated by
the only independent institution in Poland, the
Catholic church. The number of these actors and
witnesses of the history of the immediate past
grew rapidly as the crises of the communist
system proliferated Berlin in 1953, Budapest
in 1956 and Prague in 1968. In Poland, social dis¬
content erupted on several occasions. There
was street fighting in 1956 between the army and
workers in Poznan, student uprisings against
censorship and police methods used by the
authorities in 1968; bloody repression of the
workers' demonstrations at Gdansk in 1970;
more workers' demonstrations at Radom and
Warsaw in 1976.
Each of these crises led to changes, some¬
times substantial, in the government (this was
both a warning to the rulers and a source of
hope to the ruled), and also swelled the ranks of
active opposition militants belonging to suc¬
cessive generations of Poles. The light these
militants threw on events was naturally quite dif¬
ferent from the official interpretation.
The great Solidarnosc (Solidarity) movement
in 1980 was the most striking illustration of this
CONTINUED ON PAGE 3 1 »
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER MAY 1994
mm . . , . . . #,,!,,,,. ,
b^iBBwjl" ** I " » .
'»fliiFir-
INVENTING
m
mE
u
M FUTMI
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
Early this century, the German
sociologist Georg Simmel (1858-
1918) stated that "In big cities
the individual has a form and
degree offreedom that does not
exist elsewhere". Will this still be true
in six years' time, when it is expected
that halfofhumanitywill be living in
cities? Will cities still be "hot-houses
of civilization" or are they going to
destroy their inhabitants with high
pollution and low quality of life? "In
1900, there were sixteen cities world¬
wide with a population of one mil¬
lion or more," writes François Lapoix,
a specialist in urban ecology. "In 1950
there were seventy-one and today
there are 220, thirty ofwhich have a
population of more than five mil¬
lion." The third millennium will be
the age of the gigantic, sprawling
megacity. lohn Celecia, a specialist in 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
mini im «m future
Unesco's Division of Ecological Sci¬
ences, feels that it is important to
distinguish between the cities of the
industrialized world, whose inhabi¬
tants are in a position to be con¬
cerned about quality of life, and
Third World cities where sheer sur¬
vival is at stake. Nevertheless, all
cities face the same kind of prob¬
lems and issues: population influx,
the use of space, transportation and
public utilities such as water, elec¬
tricity and waste disposal.
When these problems are not
solved the health of city dwellers is
threatened. "Gases and dust are the
two leading causes ofbad air quality
in cities, and their detrimental effects
combine and cumulate," says Claude
Allègre, professor of earth sciences
and department head at the Institut
de Physique du Globe in Paris. "Such
gases as nitric oxide (NO) and
nitrogen dioxide (NO2), sulphur
dioxide (SO2), carbon monoxide
(CO), ozone (03), tetraethyl lead,
methane and a variety of other
organic compounds of lesser impor-
26
tance have reached abnormallyhigh
levels in cities." These gases, which
are extremely toxic, can cause serious
illness and irreparable damage in
young children. Unlike gaseous pol¬
lutants, dust generated by burning
coal, industry and vehicles is not
usually the subject ofenvironmental
measures.
Why are New York, San Francisco
and Rome healthier places to live in
than Mexico City, Los Angeles or
Athens? A city's weather is deter¬
mined by its topography (e.g.
whether it is located in a basin or in
mountains), its average tempera¬
ture, and wind conditions. Mexico
City, like Grenoble in France, was
built in a basin. Rising hot air is
blocked by a layer ofcooler air above
that traps heat and pollution. In Los
Angeles, sizzling hot air from the
nearby desert lies motionless over
the city. Athens, which is partially
enclosed by mountains, has no ven¬
tilation that could disperse the
deadly nephos, or "smog". In New
York, San Francisco and Rome wind
disperses pollutants.
At the heart of the problem is the
automobile. In Mexico City, two mil¬
lion cars spew thousands of tons of
carbon monoxide into the air every
day. There are approximately 500
million cars in the world today, 80
per cent of which are privately
owned. In the last twenty years the
total number of vehicles has dou
bled, seriously damaging the air
quality in cities. "We're driving
dinosaurs	 Our cars are made for
the past, not the future. We have to
radically rethink a number of phe¬
nomena that our civilization has
produced, and car traffic tops the
list," says Frederic Vester, a German
biologist who has founded an insti¬
tute for the study ofbiology and the
environment in Munich. The twenty
car manufacturers who dominate
the world's automobile market now
have to take the environment into
account. Among the solutions to the
problem are the catalytic converter,
lead-free gasoline, "diester" fuel
(made with vegetable oil) for diesel
engines, compressed natural gas,
cars that run on solar energy and,
above all, electric cars. But though
the electric car offers an appealing
solution, it has drawbacks high
cost and low performance. About
100 kilos of lead batteries (the best
kind available) are needed to pro¬
duce as much energy as one litre of
gasoline, and after only 80 kilometres
the batteries have to be recharged.
THE PROBLEMS OF WATER AND
WASTE
Water is another big problem. In
Mexico City, drinking water is
increasingly difficult to obtain. Wells
1,500 metres deep have been dug,
and pipelines bring in water from
up to 100 kilometres away. The
poorest inhabitants ofPhnom Penh
in Cambodia and Abidjan in Côte
d'Ivoire have to buywater from street
vendors, who are in many cases
unauthorized. Unclean water can
carry cholera, typhoid, enteritis,
poliomyelitis, hepatitis and a host
ofparasites. Another consequence of
AN IMPORTANT DATE
FOR URBAN ECOLOGY
"Cities and Sustainable Development" is the overall theme of
"Global Forum '94" which is being held in Manchester (United
Kingdom) from 24 June to 3 July 1 994. Representatives from 50
of the world's cities, 65 per cent of which are located in devel¬
oping countries, have been invited. Delegations from all conti¬
nents and the major geographical regions will share experi¬
ences regarding the urban environment, health, transportation,
communication, employment, markets, and finance. The con¬
clusions will be passed on to the United Nations Commission for
Sustainable Development and the United Nations Conference
on Habitat II that will be held in Istanbul in 1 996. For further
information, please contact the Town Hall, Manchester. Tel.
(44-61) 236 08 68; Fax. 234 37 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
1. The Earth
Summit's Agenda
for Change. A plain
language version of
Agenda 2land the
other Rio
Agreements,
published by the
Centre for Our
Common Future,
52 rue des Pâquis,
1201, Geneva,
Switzerland.
lack of water is lack of sewers. In
Addis Ababa (Ethiopia), an inade
quate sewage system has led to
serious river pollution.
The big cities of the South are
often hit by violent tropical rain¬
storms which wash away uncol¬
lected waste, and their most vulner¬
able inhabitants are people living in
shantytowns built on low-lying
ground that is subject to flooding.
They use sheet metal, palm leaves
and cardboard to build ramshackle
shelters on patches of waste land
where wells are often near latrines.
Figures published by the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP) are eloquent. In 1992, 80 per
cent of the population of Addis
Ababa were living in shantytowns or
as squatters, 70 per cent in
Casablanca (Morocco) and almost
as many in Calcutta (India), 60 per
cent in Bogota (Colombia), 39 per
cent in Manila (Philippines) and 20
per cent in Bangkok (Thailand) .
The problem of waste, which is
closely linked to that of water, is
growing worse. "The metropolis is a
gigantic stomach," writes Michel
Giraud. "It consumes a lot and spews
out enormous amounts of waste."
Cairo produces 4,500 tons of refuse
every day, and only two-thirds of
Mexico City's garbage is actually
collected." Huge garbage dumps in
Dakar and Manila have become
polluted settlements for masses of
outcasts.
CREATIVE SOLUTIONS
According to the Centre for our
Common Future based in Geneva
(Switzerland), "Informal settlements
and urban slums should be
upgraded to erase the deficit in
urban shelter. All urban areas need
such services as clean water, sanita¬
tion and waste collection, and
higher-income neighbourhoods
should pay the full cost ofproviding
such services."1 Several organiza¬
tions of the United Nations system
are also addressing urban problems.
Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) programme, for example,
studies urban ecology and the
ecology of populations. Its primary
objective is to study how social con¬
ditions (the organization and struc¬
ture of a society, its industries, its
transportation, and its buildings)
affect the natural environment and
the quality of human life. Creative
thinking, sharp analyses, and a judi¬
cious comparison of solutions are
all necessary in the effort to rethink
the future of the city.
In 1879 Iules Verne wrote, "Why
don't we use our imagination to the
full and draw the plans for a model
city built on rigorous scientific data?
We would invite all the peoples of
the world to visit this city where life
is good." The question is still as valid
as ever.
SUGGESTED READING:
* Shaping Cities: the Environmental
and Human Dimensions, by Marcia D.
Lowe (Worldwatch Paper 105).
Worldwatch Institute, Washington,
D.C. (1991).
*" Tlie Urban Environment. A
Sourcebookfor the 1990s, compiled
and published by the Centre for Urban
Ecology, Birmingham (UK).
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD- Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE ENVIRONMENT IN Fiji
To learn about the environment in
Fiji, the place to go to is the South
Pacific Action Committee for
Human Ecology and the Environ¬
ment (SPACHEE), a non-govern¬
mental organization that was
founded in 1982. Its office and Envi¬
ronment Resource Centre are at the
University of the South Pacific in
Suva (Fiji) where students, teachers,
community groups and govern¬
ment staff can consult a compre¬
hensive collection ofenvironmental
resource materials. SPACHEE also
publishes a quarterly newsletter
that focuses on fragile island ecosys¬
tems and organizes campaigns to
raise public awareness on such mat¬
ters as coastal waste dumping, sea
turtles, and logging. For further
information, please write to: Uni¬
versity of the South Pacific, PO. Box,
Suva, Fiji. Tel. (679) 21 24 65; Fax.
(679) 30 25 48.
LISTENING TO INDIGENOUS
POPULATIONS
A remarkable new book entitled The
Law ofthe Mother enables readers
to share the lives of dozens of com¬
munities that are trying to preserve
their traditions, sometimes in spite
28
of restrictions imposed by well-
meaning defenders of nature.
Numerous questions are raised.
Should a group, for example, accept
a ban on hunting in its territory
because it has become a national
park? The book also presents exam¬
ples of how populations sponta¬
neously protect their environment.
When a child is born to the Karen
people, who live in the highlands
of Burma and Thailand, the father
goes deep into the forest and places
the placenta and umbilical cord in
the branch ofa tree, which symbol¬
izes life and longevity. How could
he ever allow the life tree of a
member of his family to be felled
and sold? This beautifully illustrated
book, a collaborative effort between
the World Wide Fund for Nature
(WWF) and The World Conserva¬
tion Union (IUCN), with support
from the Commission of the Euro¬
pean Communities, is published (in
English only) by the Sierra Club.
It can be ordered from IUCN, Pub¬
lications Service, rue Mauverney
28, CH-1196 Gland, Switzerland.
Tel:. (41 22) 999 00 01; Fax: (41 22)
999 00 02.
SEEDS FOR
SELF-SUFFICIENCY
From 1961 to 1970, during the Viet
Nam War, American planes in the
hope of flushing out the enemy
dropped some 72,000 tons of defo¬
liants on two million hectares of
forest in the south of the peninsula.
The trees have not grown back
because the Americans also sowed
seeds that have transformed the
former woodlands into grassy
savannah. Attempts to reconstitute
the forest cover using Australian
acacias have yielded promising
results, but because of lack of funds
it has been impossible to reintro¬
duce indigenous species such as
the dipterocarp, whose wood is
valuable. In the heart of Ho Chi
Minh City, France has created a 20-
hectare botanical garden where
Vietnamese foresters collect 20 to 30
tons of dipterocarp seeds annually.
The Franco-Vietnamese scientific
co-operation programme, which
was set up last year, will be able to
reconstitute the forest if it succeeds
in obtaining funds.
INDIAN POLLUTERS FACE THE
LAW
One ofour readers, Dr. Bharat Desai,
assistant professor in environmental
law at lawaharlal Nehru University in
New Delhi, wrote to us recently to
say that the law has become very
tough on polluters in India. He cites
two cases, a gas leakage from a New
Delhi fertilizer plant, and one of the
world's worst industrial catastrophes
(more than 3,000 dead and 100,000
wounded), which occurred when the
highly toxic gas methylisocyanate
escaped from the Union Carbide
pesticide plant at Bhopal in
December 1984. In both instances
the Supreme Court of India ordered
the companies to pay hefty sums as
compensation to the victims. In the
former case, the Court ruled that a
company dealing with hazardous
substances that cause injury has
"strict and absolute liability". For fur¬
ther information, please write to: Dr.
Bharat Desai, lawaharlal Nehru Uni¬
versity, School of International
Studies, New Delhi 110067, India.
IN GRANADA, SCHOOL AND
WATER MIX
In Granada, children who are
learning about water don't just sit in
school. They go and see where it
comes from, how it is collected and
treated, and how it is distributed to
users. When they get back to school,
they work from a handbook that
suggests a series ofpractical exper¬
iments, such as a solar distiller. The
handbook, which is illustrated with
photos and diagrams, is a model of
its kind and can easily be adapted to
other contexts (in Spanish only).
Address: Aula de Educación ambi¬
ental, Carmen de los Mártires,
Granada, Spain. Tel. 22 20 96.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A FOREST OF DWARFS AND
GIANTS
The forest of Dja, in the south of
Cameroon, is on Unesco's World
Heritage List and also forms part of
its network of biosphere reserves.
It is a tropical forest with huge trees
whose canopy is so dense that only
mushrooms and moss can grow
beneath them. As many as 1,000
different kinds of insect can live in a
single tree and the watercourses
contain 120 species offish. Strangely
enough, this world of giants is the
home ofsmall animal varieties such
as rare dwarf hippopotami, ele¬
phants and chimpanzees. The
variety of birds is so great that they
have not yet all been indexed. The
United Nations Development Pro¬
gram (UNDP) and Unesco, with the
help of Germany, have raised $2
million to study the forest of Dja
and improve its protection.
A LOVELY LITTLE FOREST
Even though it is no bigger than 80
hectares, the Fray lorge forest in
northern Chile is a wonderful
curiosity ofnature whose existence
is now threatened. One of our
readers, Daniel Yanez, has sent us
an affectionate description ofwhat
has been described as a "relict
hydrophilous [water-loving] forest"
located in an arid zone, which exists
because of the fog that forms almost
daily on the Pacific coast. The fog is
absorbed by the trees' leaves,
leading to rainfall amounting to
some 1,500 mm per year as opposed
to 90 mm in neighbouring areas.
The forest is the remnant of a much
larger forest that was overexploited
by logging for firewood and timber.
The Ministry ofAgriculture, which
manages the 10,000-hectare Fray
lorge National Park, has listed in it
more than 400 plant species
mainly subtropical flora and cacti
that are characteristic of southern
Chile. According to our reader, the
forest is losing about three hectares
per year and may soon disappear. If
nothing is done to capture the fog
artificially, which is technically fea¬
sible, then it will not be possible to
reforest the area. For further infor¬
mation, please write to: Daniel
Yanez, rue aux Vaches, Mestreville,
27950 Saint-Pierre-d'Autils, France.
INITIATIVES
A CLEAN
ISLAND
m
The
Lanmanalaugar
valley, 100
kilometres east
of Reykjavik.
Situated in the north
Atlantic on the edge of the
Arctic circle, some 800 km
west of Scotland, Iceland
is an island of ice and fire. Over
half of its population of 260,000
live in or near Reykjavik, the cap¬
ital. During the summer months,
however, the numbers of foreign
tourists are so high that they rep¬
resent almost 60 per cent of the
entire local population. With a
landscape that is unique in
Europe, Iceland has many fasci¬
nating features. Its rocky coast¬
line is broken by deep blue fjords
where countless birds find
refuge. There are beaches with
black sand, volcanoes, geysers,
and pools ofbubbling lava. Veg
etation is minimal, consisting
primarily of dwarf birches, wil¬
lows, moss and lichen. Beneath
the midnight sun it is possible
to eat delicious Icelandic
bananas (grown in greenhouses,
of course)!
Iceland, which lies across a
great crack in the Earth's crust
known as the mid-Atlantic ridge,
is constituted almost entirely of
volcanic rock, lava and sedi¬
ment. It is rich in hydroelectric
and geothermal power, both of
which are renewable and less
polluting than fossil fuels. How¬
ever, this does not mean that the
air in Iceland is entirely pure.
While it is true that Icelandic air
contains less than half the
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A mass of
blue lupins
beside a river
of hot water
near the village
of Stong.
average amount of sulphur
dioxide found in most Member
States of the Organization of
Economic Co-operation and
Development (OECD), it does
have a higher rate of nitrogen
oxides, emitted essentially by
the fishing fleet. At present, sul¬
phur dioxide emissions from
underground steam for energy
aire higher than those from
human activities that burn fossil
fuel. Underground water
sources are plentiful and ofgood
quality, but increased building
and the rapid development of
tourism and aquaculture, as well
as more exports ofbottled water,
will make it necessary to watch
over this resource carefully.
Domestic waste water is dis¬
charged, for the most part
untreated, into the ocean, where
powerful currents disperse it in
the open sea. Only Reykjavik has
a modern treating facility for
solid industrial and domestic
waste. Small quantities of toxic
waste are legally exported.
GLUTTONOVS
WHALES
The quality of the soil, however,
is at risk. When Irish monks first
visited Iceland in the eighth cen¬
tury they probably discovered
an island of forests. Today, only
two forests remain, covering a
mere one per cent of the terri¬
tory. In 1990, 8,000 volunteers
planted 3.4 million trees. Nev¬
ertheless, three-quarters of the
country is affected by erosion.
Because of the harsh climate,
vegetation regenerates only very
slowly, and it has been further
deteriorated by agriculture,
animal herds, tourists, cross¬
countryvehicles and snowbikes.
So far, the island's animals
are not threatened. The arctic
fox or isatis [Alopex lagopus) is
proliferating. The bird popula¬
tion is both large and varied. Ice¬
land still hunts whales, which it
considers a traditional source
of food and a threat to its shell¬
fish supply. The cetaceans are
accused of depleting this
resource more rapidly than the
country's fishermen. But there is
a growing awareness that the
whale population must be man¬
aged wisely, like the fish reserves
for which a quota for each
species is imposed.
If the government wants Ice¬
land to keep its image as a clean
island, then it must use imagi¬
nation in implementing its
ambitious environmental policy,
especially in the face of financial
difficulties caused by a slow¬
down in economic growth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PACE 14
In April 1943 German
troops discovered in the
Katyn forest (Russia) mass
graves of thousands of
Polish officers executed by
the Soviet security
authorities. Below,
identifying the dead.
phenomenon. Almost all the participants in pre¬
vious movements were involved in it and made
no secret of their commitment. Several million
people were now in active opposition. The
proclamation of a "state of war" by the gov¬
ernment led to a definitive break between "offi¬
cial history" and "true history", as the majority
of the population called it.
Démythification
When the communist system collapsed in 1989,
the vision of the past that it had imposed col¬
lapsed with it. The history created by living
people and the versions which had "comforted
men's hearts" in previous years now came to the
fore again. Genuine scientific historiography
also experienced a fresh dynamic.
There were several reasons for this. The first
is based on the national and international pres¬
tige enjoyed by Polish historical science. Since
the nineteenth century, Polish society has held
its historians in high esteem. Also, the
researchers into ancient and recent history
included men who were known for their oppo¬
sition activities, so that all the more trust was
placed in them. People were more willing to
accept from them theories which were still not
popular. In addition, the participation of Polish
historians in international research and their
co-operation with universities in many countries
increased their credibility when they wrote the
history of their nation.
Polish researchers have long drawn on the
cultural anthropology of scholars such as Claude
Lévi-Strauss and Georges Dumézil. They had
taken part in programmes to apply the principles
of Fernand Braudel's universal history and
exploited the theories of American, German
and English researchers.
The second reason is equally, if not more,
important. Institutional change had led to the
abolition of anti-democratic constraints. Once
freedom of expression was regained, censor¬
ship abolished and "ideologization" of the past
ended, the conditions for genuine scientific
work once again existed. Moreover, Polish
society had acquired its own state, laws and
institutions. There was no longer any need to
resort to an idealized image of the past to glorify
national identity.
Hence the rewriting of history in Poland, as
elsewhere in eastern Europe, is defined by three
main features. First, the rejection of a single point
of view in other words, of an official version of
history. Secondly, the possibility of writing about
the past without neglecting any of its aspects, a
feature that implies the authorization of public
debate in a spirit of complete critical freedom, not
so much about the existence of the facts as about
their interpretation. Thirdly, the abandonment of
the idea of history as a substitute for public insti¬
tutions and as a way of providing the nation with
a sense of identity. Historiography must abandon
the role of prophecy and myth-making and
devote its energies instead to the analysis of his¬
torical processes. Society and historical science
will both be all the richer.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
tsss
A hard look at
a troubled past
P m
JVhS*\>V.\KK\^
Svaty Vaclav a Radslav Zlicky r. 929.
Lost illusions
by Eva Schmidt-Hartmann
31
EVA
SCHMIDT-HARTMANN
is a Czech sociologist and
historian who teaches at the
Carolinum Collegium in
Munich (Germany). She is the
author of many studies on the
modern history of central
Europe, historiography and
political thought.
AS in every other former communist
country, public interest in the past in
post-communist Czechoslovakia began
with curiosity about everything that had been
previously forbidden. The history of churches
and religion, old noble houses and individual
politicians were the most popular topics in the
media and in books. Clubs that were heirs to a
rich tradition were founded and the historic
heritage of Prague and other cities became
tourist attractions that brought in ready cash.
The liberated state derived its new legitimacy
from its brief but glorious past.
As the many different faces of the past were
dusted off and rediscovered, long-forgotten and
repressed memories of unpleasant and con-
flictual situations and developments resurfaced.
For example, the controversies between the
Czechs and the Slovaks dating from the era of
the first democratic Czechoslovak Republic
between 1918 and 1938 took on a new lease of
life. The exploitation by the tourist industry of
everything to do with Franz Kafka raised ques¬
tions about the fate of the German and Jewish
peoples in the Bohemian regions who had made
up nearly one-third of the total population
before the Second World War. The passionate
debate that ensued prompted recollections of
many facets of past suffering and raised the
question of how different sections of the popu¬
lation had behaved in those days and what assis¬
tance they had given to the victims of harsh
persecution. The myth of specifically Czech
democratic traditions began to be undermined.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
St. Wenceslas (Vaclav I) is
shown on this postcard
reproduction of a painting
by Adolf Liebscher.
Regarded as the patron
saint and defender of the
Czech nation, he ruled
Bohemia from 921 to 929.
The debate focused particularly on one ques¬
tion not least because of its significance
throughout Europe today: whether, and if so
how, different nationalities can live together in
a democratic state. On this subject, the history
of Czechoslovakia offers a particularly rich fund
of experience.
Modern Czech historical consciousness was
formed during the nineteenth century in an age
when Czech society acquired nationhood as an
integral part of the Habsburg monarchy. As a
defence against the lordship of the German-
speaking Austrians which was experienced as a
repression of nationality, Czech historians
emphasized the cultural and historical origi¬
nality of their nation. At the same time, Czech
society did all it could to promote the democ¬
ratization of multinational Austria. The idea of
Czech nationhood, differing from others
because of its democratic character, was born at
that time and undoubtedly encouraged the adop¬
tion of parliamentary democracy by the
Czechoslovak state created in 1918.
But the Czechs were not alone in Czecho¬
slovakia. Even if they dominated the new state,
the latter also contained Slovaks, Germans,
Hungarians and other small ethnic groups. They
perceived the newly founded state as the fulfil¬
ment of their struggle for emancipation from a
Habsburg monarchy dominated by German
speakers, and regarded the new republic as
"their" state. They were deaf to similar endeav¬
ours by other nationalities to achieve self-deter¬
mination. By clever manipulation, democrati¬
cally elected majorities managed to ensure that
a parliamentary system functioned, but they
made no compromises with the members of
other nationalities and did not allow them any
share of power.
When the communist dictatorship fell in
1989 and democracy was restored, the Czech
and Slovak memories of their common past
proved very different. While the Czechs spoke
of democracy, many Slovaks stressed the way in
which their nationhood had been jeopardized.
Three years later, the two nations went their
separate ways and formed two independent
states. The public debate on the past that
emerged in post-communist Czechoslovakia
did much to ensure that national conflicts
became unbridgeable. Once again, it transpired
that democracy provided no miracle recipe for
conflicts between nationalities.
The age of suspicion
Czech society also gradually discovered that
its democratic traditions had not prevented it
from committing massive crimes against another
nationality. Today, people are asking to what
extent the expropriation of three million Ger¬
mans after the end of the Second World War,
their forced exodus from the country and the
confiscation of the property they left behind
them contributed to the establishment of the
dictatorship of the communist party in 1948. The
popular belief in the collective guilt of the Ger¬
mans at the end of the Second World War, the
neglect of individual liberties, blind belief in
progress and uncritical faith in individual polit¬
ical leaders are often the subject of public debate
by historians today.
Communist rule itself is starting to be viewed
by historians in the longer term context of Czech
history rather than as the rule of violence imposed
by outside forces the Soviet Union and its
henchmen without the co-responsibility of the
Czech people. Today, few if any proponents
remain of the idea of a Czech society shaped by its
own supposedly democratic tradition on the one
hand, and evil imported from outside on the other.
On the contrary, people are now asking how it was
that large segments of the Czech population could
be convinced by communist ideology, why there
were so few avowed opponents of the regime,
and how certain elements of national self-aware¬
ness were exploited by the communists in an
attempt to win over public opinion. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
lop, Tomas Garrigue
Masaryk, the first
President of the
Czechoslovak Republic
(1918-1935), arrives on
Prague's Wenceslas Square
in 1918.
Above, a demonstration in
Wenceslas Square in
Prague in November 1989
during the velvet
revolution that led to the
election of the dissident
writer Vaclav Havel as
President of the Republic.
34
Here, the lively debate over traditional
images of history is a source of valuable infor¬
mation. Today, a traditional dislike of elites, a
populist vision of politics and a taste for author¬
itarian rule are coming to be seen as typical fea¬
tures of the political culture of both bourgeois
and communist Czechoslovakia. It is gradually
becoming apparent that the communists rein¬
terpreted traditional myths of Czech history
but were able, first and foremost, to make ide¬
ological capital out of prejudices deeply rooted
in the popular mind.
However, it is hard to come to terms with
such a rapid change in the historical self-aware¬
ness of a society. New knowledge is often dis¬
cussed in simplified form, and where a cautious
and difficult critical assessment would be useful,
radical prejudices tend to crop up instead. Often
a glorified image is replaced by its opposite
denigration. Discussion turns into heated
polemic based on slogans in which complex
historical relationships are personalized and
viewed in crudely simplified terms. Only a few
years ago, historians were still often called upon
to make statements of decisive importance in
their capacity as guardians of truth; today many
complain of the public's loss of confidence in
statements based on historical studies.
The way in which history has been written
in the past four decades is therefore a matter of
controversy among a general public that takes an
interest in history. Were all the historians who
obtained permission to publish their works
under the communist regime minions of the
rulers or were they able to present the results of
serious research? Can any confidence be placed
in a historian who served the communist regime?
What is the relevance of the moral and political
integrity of a historian to the quality of his or her
works ? How does a presentation of history that
has been purged of communist jargon to incor¬
porate a new vocabulary and a few additions
differ from sound modern historiography?
The uncertainty principle
In the schools and universities, complaints are
being voiced about the lack of new teaching
materials; historical journals are facing financial
problems, and the Czech Republic, which now
has only ten million inhabitants, is not a big
enough market for books written primarily for
specialists to be profitable. These practical prob¬
lems contribute to an uncertain perception of the
past by a broad sector of the public.
In reality, however, this climate of uncer¬
tainty corresponds in many respects to the
changed consciousness of modern societies,
which is a widespread phenomenon. In the West,
the process of disintegration of the historical
images handed down from the nineteenth cen¬
tury, which remained popular everywhere until
the 1950s, has been slower but certainly not
dissimilar to current developments in Czech
society. Who in Europe today would claim that
the English have an ideal recipe for a satisfactory
political system, that the French are the only cre¬
ators of culture and that the Germans are inca¬
pable of democratization? The fact that the
post-communist reinterpretation of history
shows the Czech past to have been many-faceted
and the Czechs themselves as neither better nor
worse "democrats" than others should therefore
not come as a surprise.
The modern approach to history has revealed
that many historical concepts once regarded as
"scientifically proved" are myths, although such
realizations are only gradually finding their way
into the school textbooks. The disappearance, .
practically overnight, of traditional historical
myths comes as a hard blow to many. People
today must learn to live with the new uncer¬
tainty instead of using it to paint frightening
scenarios of crisis. For the democratic future
of Czech society, the démythification of its
democratic traditions has brought valuable new
insights into the complex relationships that
spelled the end of democracy in the inter-war
years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
gftftPVt*
A sociologist discovers how
history can be retouched by
those who took part in it
When
memory
plays tricks
jj Liliana Deyanova
o
UR past is becoming more and more
unpredictable." Bulgarians today are
increasingly familiar with this paradox.
Not for the first time, they are asking them¬
selves such questions as these: Did the commu¬
nists come to power on 9 September 1944 as the
result of a "popular uprising" against a monar¬
chist-fascist dictatorship, without direct inter¬
vention by the Red Army, or as the result of a
coup d'état by a gang of traitors and terrorists
supported by Russian guns? Was Bulgaria ever
fascist? Who saved the Jews from deportation to
Nazi concentration camps? The communist
party or King Boris III?
In one of its first directives, the new govern¬
ment set up in 1944 enjoined teachers "not to
expound the positive actions of monarchs in his¬
tory lessons, but to stress the tyrannical quality
of their rule and the struggle of the oppressed
people". The triumphant workers and peasants
were to be glorified. Thus was history rewritten.
It is no surprise to find Spartacus described as a
"proletarian"; the most grotesque illustrations
of communist iconography came close to
depicting him brandishing a hammer and sickle.
Today's history books, on the other hand,
avoid talking about "the positive aspects of the
proletariat", and filter or exclude previously sacro¬
sanct expressions such as "anti-fascist popular
uprising" and "the glorious October Revolution".
Perhaps this is what the French sociologist Jean
Baudrillard has described as "a rewriting of history
that is contrary to the totalitarian version"?
A sociological enquiry
In Bulgaria a far-reaching research programme
has been launched on "the rewriting of his¬
tory". It is sociological rather than historical, and
is less concerned with discovering the truth
about past events than with understanding how
they are interpreted in the various "rewritten"
versions. The content of history books and his¬
tory lessons, exhibits in historical museums,
and biographies are all being studied as part of
this programme.
A\ propaganda poster
showing Todor Zhivkov,
secretary general of the
Bulgarian communist
party from 1 9S4 to 1 989,
and a text vaunting the
country's economic
strength.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
In September 1944, the
Soviet army occupied
Bulgaria. A coalition
government declared war
on Germany. Below, in the
little town of Lovec, the
population salutes the Red
Army and shouts anti¬
fascist slogans.
By examining the ways in which individual
biographies are being rewritten it is possible to see
the two-way relationship between biography
and history. We can discover how people see
their own lives and try to "legitimize" them by
making sure that they conform to newly-accepted
standards, and also how new interpretations of
certain historic events are being inserted in these
"revised" biographies. Two different processes are
involved: giving meaning to one's own life, and
using one's life story to make sense of the past. It
is possible to identify various strata in the col¬
lective memory by seeing how certain events are
given emphasis, important facts are omitted,
minute details are magnified, and what Freud
called "screen-memory" comes into being.
In this context it may be hard to say exactly
"what happened on 9 September 1944". Perhaps
we ought instead to see what the various inter¬
pretations of 9 September are, or even find out
about the different 9 Septembers stored in the dif¬
ferent layers of the memory. What story do those
who once called themselves "active combatants
in the struggle against fascism and capitalism"
now tell? What story do their victims tell?
To carry out this analysis we are using a
variety of sociological techniques and a number
of sources. By collecting the life stories of people
as they are described in the eulogies pronounced
at their funerals and in later conversations with
those who knew them we have tried to find out
how biographies are orientated nowadays', by
people on both sides of the fence.
We shall not dwell on the way in which
people make crude manipulations (intentional or
otherwise) of their own past. What interests us
is the way in which episodes in a biography are
unconsciously reorganized at the time of death.
In every biography we have noted a transference
of guilt, a refusal to be associated with evil. Evil
is rejected: it is done by enemies, or at a pinch by
black sheep on one's own side. What is inter-
36
esting in the biographies we have assembled are
the compromises, the guilt-feelings, the justifi¬
cations and rationalizations. Matters of this kind
are not mentioned at funerals, but they can be
taken into account precisely because of the way
in which they are passed over in silence.
We examine and compare the various strata
of a biography to see how it is constructed,
what is concealed, retouched or given emphasis,
how sensitive matters are evaded (e.g. the case of
someone from a middle-class background who
joined the Communist Party), and what appar¬
ently serves as mitigating circumstances (e.g.
euphemisms whereby a crime is called a
"youthful mistake", or a compromise is
described as "the wisdom of experience"). In
other words, we try to find out how biogra¬
phies are "normalized".
Biographical revelations
We have distinguished four categories of biog¬
raphy. In each of them, the subject always
remains an outsider, a figure who is somehow
divorced from events.
First, what is striking about the biographies
of communist leaders is the extraordinary inno¬
cence they affect with regard to everything that
happened. Thus Anton Yugov, an ex-prime min¬
ister, is said to have fought "for a humanist
society that did not come about, but that was not
his fault	 He was not to see his dreams come
true. Others are guilty." Elsewhere, however,
Yugov is described as "a titan of the Revolution";
he was "one of the protagonists of history, and
will always belong to it".
The "titan" thus makes history but is not
responsible for what happens. This is a peculiar
logic, but one that is aware of its own illogicality
and seeks to justify Yugov's failings by adding:
"errors did not spare him, either". This is a typ¬
ical example of exteriorization. The errors are the
subject of the sentence; they come from an out¬
side source. There are wicked men like Todor
Zhivkov, who "seized power". Yugov, more¬
over, "had his own opinion about things, and
that did not please the sinister Zhivkov, General
Secretary of the Party". In this kind of biography
we see how the ideal of the revolutionary, "the
humanist society", is made into the norm.
The same method appears again in the
biographies of humbler figures: "He had no
feeling of guilt towards anyone," reads one typ¬
ical sentence. By shifting emphasis one can try
to make the subject of the biography appear
innocent. A militant's life is always portrayed as
a sacrifice "Total commitment of self to build
a new life, making a gift of oneself." And even
if "ne'er-do-wells, careerists and profiteers" or
"people placed by chance on the stage of his¬
tory" deceived them, "real revolutionaries
always resented the contradiction between the
ideal (the norm) and reality, which they regarded
with a critical eye". These revolutionaries were
always indignant about mistakes; they wrote
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
H
-. i
fftl
«
1 1
L~-v ^
i
"...
-mm
.*"'' c
i« r\$ %*dtK* jV^^^tMH iPÉTr M^J^ V^h v i T'a à
m%%ÏVp Fm rTa, i
à* *' /Wr i W ¿Si *
ms - m. ¿ f
p" /' Wm
letters to protest and complain: that is one of the
distinctive features of this category of biog¬
raphy. Another way of acquitting revolutionaries
is to emphasize their "disinterestedness" and
their "refusal of privileges" with phrases like
"he left no worldly goods" or "he donated his
inventions to his professional association".
What was the point of these sacrifices? How
did these disinterested, self-sacrificing people
manage to build such a society? Our findings
reveal a denial of responsibility. To work for
the construction of socialism, at whatever level,
was to be a cog in a piece of machinery. Deeper
levels of personality and identity (where prob¬
lems of morality and guilt are, in the last analysis,
decided) were unaffected.
The biographies of those who were perse¬
cuted after 9 September 1944 and have since
been rehabilitated belong to a third category. A
striking feature of their tragic stories is a feeling
of inevitability, of an all-pervading, irrational,
insuperable destiny. The thread running through
their stories and the value judgments on which
they are based, is the dichotomy between "com¬
munist barbarians" on one side and "us superior
beings" on the other. Life is divided into two
parts: "Before the Revolution he was happy",
after it "his life was trapped" or "life stopped".
"He was a talented man, but his life came to a
standstill: the communists shattered his creative
genius," says a woman intellectual from "a
family with the gene of culture".
Here too the break is always seen as coming
from outside. Had it not occurred, the "gene of
culture" would not have been stunted it is as
though life was lived in a pure ideal environment
that only the impure reality of socialism could
taint. Communism is seen as the main cause of
a ruined life. The person was a failure because he
or she did not live a "normal life" and a "normal
life" is impossible without "a normal society".
People whose life-stories fit into this category
see themselves as possessing a particular gene,
which is the other side of "the hereditary taint"
which the communists long accused them of
possessing an excuse which for long allowed
them to hound the "old guard", the "bour¬
geois". For the victims of repression, every¬
body except those on their own side was
mediocre, pretentious and ignoble.
The fourth category consists of people who
managed to "overcome the resistance of socialist
circles", people whose "gene of culture was able
to develop". Admittedly, they lived amidst "the
poisonous vapours of hatred and hostility", but
they "sowed the seeds of good". Though they
came up against "a scowling present", they
remained "part of our tradition", giving meaning
to the emptiness and absurdity of life.
In this category too we find the same tragic
dichotomy: a life torn between "a scowling pre¬
sent" and "tradition", between "yesterday" and
"now", between the "old guard" and the "new
people" two groups permanently divided.
f\ pro-reform
demonstration in Sofia
In 1989.
LILIANA DEYANOVA,
of Bulgaria, teaches sociology
at the university of Sofia and is
a member of her country's
Institute of Social Criticism.
Her published works include
"The Sociology of Symbolic
Forms" (Sofia, 1 993) and a
number of studies on the
sociology of personality.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S HISTORICAL
WORKS
H
ISTORIANS often change their methods and the problems they
study without in any way lessening their commitment to the
search for historical truth. As the French historian Marc Bloch
once wrote, "each age reconstructs the past in terms of its own preoc¬
cupations."
Since the fall of the Berlin Wall and the collapse of the Soviet bloc,
many countries have been attempting to rewrite their histories. Among
them are Russia and other countries of eastern Europe, as well as the
former Soviet republics in the Caucasus and central Asia, such as
Azerbaijan, Georgia and Tajikistan, where there is an evident desire to
look into the past to help rebuild a national cultural identity.
At a time when ideologies and theoretical models are being widely
questioned, new ways of looking at the past can also be observed in the
West. To take one example, the French Revolution of 1789 is no
longer seen exclusively in terms of the onward march of liberty and
progress. Analysis of the Revolution now finds room for an objective
view of certain episodes, such as the Terror and the revolt of the
chouans, during which liberties and cultural identities were stifled.
Long before these changes took place, Unesco had been engaged
on a number of major historical projects, including the history of the
scientific and cultural development of humanity, and general histories
of Africa, Central Asia, Latin America and the Caribbean. These pro¬
jects have made use of new scientific procedures in historical analysis,
different visions of history and appropriate methodologies (such as the
use of African oral traditions) to establish and interpret the facts via
a wide range of viewpoints.
Rewriting history means, first and foremost, taking into account
new discoveries and advances in knowledge; it also means accepting
other explanatory hypotheses, rehabilitating ignored or marginal¬
ized civilizations and cultures, and accepting a history that has many
dimensions and moves in many directions, while always remaining true
to human experience. This new approach, this change of emphasis and
focus, make the UNESCO histories as topical as ever.
However, UNESCO's mission is also to contribute to the recon¬
struction, for the future, of a history which is an instrument of mutual
understanding as well as a corpus of knowledge. On the basis of
books already written or yet to be written, new historical syntheses
(regional or inter-regional) will go further than the deciphering of civ¬
ilizations using traditional methods, and reveal complicities, conver¬
gences, and trends that are universally shared. Rewriting history will
thus involve far-reaching changes in approach and emphasis.
CHRISTOPHE W0NDJI
Head of Unesco's Section of General and Regional Histories
In the following article, Professor Jean Dévisse, one of the architects
of UNESCO's General History ofAfrica, sets an agenda for the rising
generation of historians of Africa.
The true history of Africa
is only now beginning to be
written
Above left, brass head of the Oni, a
religious chief, from lle-Ife (Nigeria). It
was produced by the lost wax method..
The tiny holes In the surface were used for
attaching ornaments.
Above centre, terra-cotta
anthropomorphic statuette from
Bankouni, near Bamako (Mali). Date
unknown.
Above right, bronze head of an Oni. It
belongs to the art of Ife (Nigeria) and was
produced by the lost wax method in the
mid- 1 3th century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
An authentic picture by Jean Dévisse
AT a very early stage, Western historians
surrendered to the stubborn refusal of
African history to fit into their conceptual
frameworks. They left it to sociologists to study,
in piecemeal fashion, the cultures of individual
"ethnic groups" or "tribes". The sum of their
efforts was to draw attention to a number of
curious features and to suggest that they existed
throughout the continent and its deliberately
obliterated past. The institutions of the priest
king and chieftainship, both obviously phe¬
nomena quite unlike anything that had existed
anywhere else in the world, were all that was
needed to define the continent's past.
African peoples too have felt tempted to assert
unique features that distinguish them from others.
Three striking examples have been analysed in
recent years, from among the hundreds already
recorded or presently being studied. The
Nubians,1 who once considered themselves "emi¬
nently Christian" were from the fifteenth century
onwards eager to claim Arab origins and genealo¬
gies. The Hausa,2 in common with many other
peoples from Africa and the Indian Ocean, also
lay claim to an Arab origin. The Tuareg3 claim a
relationship with the Ottoman Empire.
One must therefore constantly be on guard
against the oversimplification which says that the
true history of Africa, which was deformed or
denied by "negationist" European studies of
the nineteenth century, is that which the peoples
themselves and their story-tellers repeat orally
today. To rediscover and rewrite African history
means going backwards in time. The writing of
African history today runs as much risk of being
retarded by a prickly regard for African speci¬
ficity as it did in the past by colonialist negativity.
A symposium1 held in Nice in 1986 on the
initiative of Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, then
Director-General of UNESCO, demonstrated
that the writing of history in the late twentieth
century must be based on the use of two impor¬
tant disciplines.
The first of these is chronology. Without a
solid framework, history soon becomes nothing
more than a vague anthropological discourse.
History is more than a mere sequence of events,
but without precise reference to a fixed time-
scale, interpretations become hazardously
impressionistic.
The second discipline is the comparative
method, which should be more widely used. Too
many detailed studies are hidden away in mono¬
graphs. As anyone knows who has contributed to
the reconstruction of African history during the
millennia prior to 1700, comparisons can be
highly illuminating. They reveal convergences,
nuances and differences, always provided that
the results are related to a construction of world
history composed of more than the mere juxta¬
position of national or continental histories.
Comparative study presupposes the rapid
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Ambassadors to the king
of the Congo are shown In
this illustration from the
Dutch physician and
geographer Olfer Dapper's
"Description of Africa"
(1686).
Below right, cross-section
of a slave ship. The slaves
are packed below deck.
(Illustration from a mid-
1 9th-century French
treatise on naval
engineering).
publication which receives little encourage- taken place in this field in the United States and
ment from present economic systems of the Jamaica, for example, is now being echoed in the
burgeoning crop of excellent work produced countries of Central and South America and the
each year, particularly by African researchers. Caribbean, in lands which have long been reticent
about such matters. The repercussions of the
BrealfinS new SrOlind rewriting of African history on "racial integra-
- , . it- i tion" a watchword in many states of the Amer-
Spectacular progress is currently being made in L r i j i i j
r ~.r , ° . , J r i- icas may prove benehcial, provided they do
two areas, rirstly, growing numbers ol studies are i j 1 1_ j j- ui
, . -il n- r i i not lead to racial hatred and irreparable ruptures,
being carried out on the ellects ol the exploitation T , L -li l.
r,° -at- -11111 It has now become possible to examine other,
ol human resources in Africa, particularly black , , , f r ¿ i » r
. r . 1-11 i i i i r much older forms ol human migration irom
Alnca, which has occurred not only in the last lew Ar- A jr i ru-i
. , , . ' . . n Alnca to Asia and Europe, the existence ol which
centuries, but over several millennia. 1 he înllu- , u u u i ur i_ j ï s
[ , . ... ... c r has been shown by a recently published atlas.
ence ol this exploitation on the lives ol groups ol ,-n i_ i i i i il ï j
, i-i i 1 he stages by which the planet has been populated
human beings and on the economies, strate- r a r a -ja v
j- ° j -Jill from Alnca America and Australia were popu-
gies ol response and protection developed by , < , , u . j
°. r . , , , . r i i lated much more recently can now be traced as
African societies, the slow evolution ol which is r j -r j i r i. i r
, , . ..... . part ol a more detailed analysis of the evolution of
currently being perceived with increasing r, i_ j r
, . \ , ° r r r. ° the environment over thousands of years,
clarity has become a mai or focus of interest. Ti i u r j u
,. , ,. , 1 he same rigour must also be applied to the
Ihese studies are enabling us to make a i . r »t
, , ö . r , critical treatment of sources. IN o one now sen-
	 serious attempt to explore the question of the , * r i u u- .
ill » r 1-1 ously contests the use ol oral sources by histo-
arrested development ol a continent which, J , ¿
JEAN DEVISSE, i- if i i « i i nans. However, we still need to refine our
* ,r , according to all the evidence, was devel- i j r n j- j n
of France, is professor . ? . , , . . , .. , , methods ol collecting, editing and critically exam-
»m oping in the global sense, including the cul- _. °i ^ . ,,' i >m.
emeritus of African history at r &. . &,., . '. b, . , ining oral data, just as historians in the North did
the University of Pari? i and tural dimension which is now integrated into the _ ° _ ' . , _
tne university oí rans i ana b two centuries ago with regard to written sources,
rapporteur of the International concept of development-in the fourteenth cen- Work has onl ^ust b &¡n this fidd but extra_
Scientific Committee for the tury, at the very time when Europe was expen- ,. i i j l j
,...,,. , ,. , ' ., { . j c . . r r ordinary progress has already been made,
publication of Unesco s General encing a terrible period of crisis. /r & /
History ofAfrica. He is Secondly, work is commencing outside Africa
^r«hiwtonwÎe in an area which was long considered unfruitful Ai|,»ea's ea|,|y metalworkers
Ki-V 'l.S- u-'i. and even dangerous, namely the study of the Another endangered legacy consists of the irre-
Niger basin which was r. & ..' . J r -i i i 11 -j i i j ji
described in the November African communities that were forcibly inte- placeable evidence that can be produced by metic-
_ M^ 1993 ¡ssue of the Unesco grated into the life of Asia and the Americas. ulous archaeological research. In recent decades,
Trw Courier. The spectacular change of attitude which has many spectacular discoveries have been made in
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
this domain. The discovery of many aspects of the
past traces of animal and plant substances,
remains of meals, shrines, villages, towns, evi¬
dence of climatic change, ceramic objects has
considerably enriched our knowledge.
One revealing example is provided by studies
on copper and iron. Until recently, it was taken
for granted that south of the Tropic of Cancer
Africa had not produced copper nor refined
methods of making copper alloys. Today, the
map of Africa is dotted with sites where metal was
smelted during the past 3,000 years, and others
where objects made of fine alloys have been
found, many of them produced using the "lost
wax" technique. At one time there was a debate
among those who believed that iron could only
have entered Africa from the north-east: either
from the Caucasus or Egypt. Now, however,
archaeological evidence from seven or eight coun¬
tries of the intertropical zone, particularly around
the equator, proves that the forging of iron was
practised there as early as 1000 B.C. The era of
quasi-theological debate has fortunately given
way to meticulous work in the laboratory.
Lastly, there is a need for greater co-opera¬
tion between disciplines. History must be allied
more closely with other domains: the environ¬
mental sciences, geology, geography, human
and animal palaeontology, dietetics, linguistics,
medicine, and palaeobotany, to name but a few.
Nor should one forget the essential role of sci¬
entific laboratories, which are now deeply
involved in research on African history.
The "rewriting" of the history of Africa will
require a major international effort, sustained
over several generations. First and foremost it
calls for the mobilization of African govern¬
ments and researchers. For my part, I only regret
that sufficient time no longer remains for me to
witness this development.
1. See L. Kropacck, ch. 16 of General History ofAfrica,
vol. IV, UNESCO-Heinemann International-University of
California Press, 1984.
2. W.K.R. Hallam, "The Bayajida Legend in Hausa
folklore"', Journal of African History, 1966, pp. 47-60.
3. M. Hamani Djibo, Le sultanat touareg de l'Aya. Etudes
nigériennes no. 55, 1989.
4. See Etre historien aujourd'hui (edited by R. Rcmond).
UNESCO-Crès, 1988. 350 pages.
5. Grand Atlas de l'archéologie. Encyclopaedia Universalis
publishers, Paris. P. 309, map by Jean Chavaillon.
HISTORY IN GLOBAL PERSPECTIVE
A selection of history books
published by Unesco
ALREADY PUBLISHED:
General History ofAfrica
This monumental work, in which nearly 350 scholars participated, consists of eight vol¬
umes, all of which have been published in English. Publication of the unabridged ver¬
sion is scheduled in a number of other languages, including French (in which volumes
I, II, III, IV and VII have already appeared), Spanish, Arabic, Portuguese, Chinese,
Korean and Japanese. Each 800- to 1 ,000-page volume contains illustrations, maps,
graphs, an extensive bibliography.
The General History ofAfrica has been prepared under the direction of an Inter¬
national Scientific Committee consisting of 39 noted scholars, two-thirds of whom are
African. It provides, for the first time, a comprehensive approach to the history of ideas,
civilizations, societies and institutions that form the rich pattern of African history.
Volume I: Methodology and African Prehistory
Volume II: /Indent Civilizations ofAfrica
Volume III: Africa from the Seventh to the Eleventh Century
Volume IV: Africa from the Twelfth to the Sixteenth Century
Volume V: Africa from the Sixteenth to the Eighteenth Century
Volume VI: Africa in the Nineteenth Century until the 1880s
Volume VII: Africa under Colonial Domination 1880-1935
Volume VIII: Africa since 1935
Special introductory price (until 30 June 1 994): 1 ,740 French francs (all eight volumes)
300 FF per volume, except for Vol. VIII (2 1 0 FF)
The General History ofAfrica is co-published with Heinemann Educational Books
Ltd and the University of California Press. Exclusive sales rights in the United Kingdom
and British Commonwealth: Heinemann; in North, Central and South America: Uni¬
versity of California Press.
An abridged version is also in publication. At present volumes I, II, III and VII are
available at 60 FF (co-published with James Currey, U.K., and University of California
Press, U.S.A.).
"* History of Humanity
This History, which is being co-published with Routledge, London, will comprise 7 vol¬
umes in which a worldwide team of 450 contributors will explore humankind's cultural
and scientific development from the earliest times to the present day.
Volume I is being published this month. In it 40 internationally renowned experts
retrace the major steps from the origins of humankind to the first societies 5,000 years
ago, paying particular attention to archaeological discoveries. 750 pages, 1 40 pho¬
tographs, 171 figures and 74 maps.
Volume I : Prehistory and the Beginnings ofCivilization (850 French francs from
Unesco; £85.00 from Routledge)
History of Civilizations of Central Asia
This major multi-volume history presents for the first time a comprehensive histor¬
ical and cultural picture of the vast region stretching from the Caspian Sea to the bor¬
ders of China, written by specialists from all parts of the world.
The first volume studies the dawn of civilization, from Palaeolithic times to around
700 B.C., when foundations were laid for the constitution of the great Achaemenid
Empire. (See "Books of the World", Unesco Courier, September 1993).
Volume I: The dawn ofcivilization: earliest times to 700 B.C. ( 1 992, 535 pages,
200 FF)
Volume II: The development ofsedentary and nomadic civilizations: TOO B.C.
to A.D. 250 (1 994, 573 pages)
IH PREPARATION:
General History of Latin America (in 7 volumes)
General History of the Caribbean (in 6 volumes)
*- The Various Aspects of Islamic Culture (6 volumes)
These books and other Unesco publications on history may be ordered from Promotion and
Sales Division, Unesco Publishing, 7 place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07 SP, France. Fax (33-1)
42 73 30 07, at any bookshop or through Unesco Publishings sales agents in each country.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND THE PREVENTION
OF NATURAL DISASTERS
THE YOKOHAMA CONFERENCE
4*
IN the past two decades, natural
disasters such as earthquakes, hur¬
ricanes, tsunamis, floods, landslides,
volcanic eruptions, forest fires,
grasshopper and locust infestations,
drought and desertification have killed
an estimated three million people,
adversely affected at least 800 million
lives and resulted in enormous eco¬
nomic damage, which in 1990 alone
reached $47 billion. Developing coun¬
tries suffer the greatest social and eco¬
nomic damage because of their limited
resources for disaster warning and pre¬
vention. Today, the risk of natural dis¬
asters is increasing as a result of popu¬
lation growth, urbanization, alteration of
the natural environment, substandard
dwellings and public building and inade¬
quate infrastructure maintenance.
The International Decade for Nat¬
ural Disaster Reduction (IDNDR; 1990-
2000), was launched by the General
Assembly of the United Nations on 22
December 1 989 to reduce through con¬
certed international action, especially
in developing countries, the loss of life,
property damage and economic and
social disruption caused by natural
disasters.
A World Conference on the Reduc¬
tion of Natural Disasters is being held
this year from 23-27 May in Yokohama
(Japan). The conference has been con¬
vened to review the accomplishments of
the Decade to date, chart a programme
of action for the future, facilitate the
exchange of information on the imple¬
mentation of programmes and policies,
and increase awareness of the impor¬
tance of disaster reduction policies.
There are many more ways of dis¬
aster prevention and mitigation than is
commonly thought. They need to be
made better known to the communities
concerned, the authorities, educators
and development planners.
Unesco, which is a member of the
United Nations steering committee for
IDNDR, has for many years been
engaged in the assessment and mitiga¬
tion of risks arising from natural hazards.
It is committed to promoting policies of
prevention, with a strong accent on
enhancing preparedness and public
awareness.
At the Yokohama conference,
Unesco and the World Meteorological
Organization (WMO) are organizing a
technical committee on warning sys¬
tems. Unesco is also organizing a series
of Poster Sessions which will provide a
forum for scientific and technical pre¬
sentations in the form of display mate¬
rials on such themes as warning sys¬
tems, education, health, earth science,
engineering and architecture, legisla¬
tion, regulation and land use.
Unesco has published two booklets
for the general public: Standing Up to
Natural Disasters and Disaster Reduction
as well as a children's cartoon book,
Tsunami Warning. These can be ordered
from Unesco, Publications and Docu¬
mentation Unit of the Science Sector, I
rue Miollis, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15
(France). To order, ring (33-1) 45 68
41 20; Fax. (33-1)43 06 II 22.
For more information, please write
to: IDNDR Secretariat, Office of the
United Nations in Geneva, Palais des
Nations, CH- 1 2 1 1 , Geneva 10 (Switzer¬
land). Tel. (4 1 -22) 798 6894; Fax. (4 1 -22)
733-8695.
THIS ARTICLE IS ONE
OF A SERIES IN WHICH
THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF
UNESCO SETS OUT HIS
THINKING ON MATTERS OF
CURRENT CONCERN
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
An active pact
WE are living in an age of paradox, an age
which is baroque in its immoderation, and in
which the hopes born at the end of the Cold
War hopes for a more peaceful world enjoying
greater prosperity, justice, solidarity and freedom
encounter the despair of the poor, whose impover¬
ishment grows steadily worse, and the excluded,
whose rejection is ever more complete.
At this watershed it is vital that we rethink the
development of our societies from top to bottom.
Only in so doing can we lend substance to our hopes.
Having learned from experience, we will not forget
that the sole protagonist and beneficiary of develop¬
ment is humankind.
In this connection, agreement has been reached on
three essential issues: social integration, the fight
against poverty, and productive employment. Rather
than seeing social development as merely the devel¬
opment of "social services", UNESCO views it as a
global process whose ultimate aim links up with that
of human development. The interdependent nature of
the phenomena and trends involved in this process
and the increasing internationalization of the economy
demonstrate clearly that our present problems are
intertwined and that human societies therefore need
an active form of solidarity which could take the
form of an "international social pact".
An imperative and I prefer to speak of an ethical
imperative for this type of solidarity is sharing:
sharing of means, of knowledge, of work, of leisure.
This type of solidarity also involves shared choices and
I will mention here only those which in my view are
most important.
Social development in the broader sense to
which I refer involves first of all a global struggle
against all forms of exclusion starting with
poverty through the development of human
resources and productive employment. It means that
developed countries, having realized the nature of
their own difficulties and the links between those
difficulties and the constraints experienced by other
groups of countries, must proceed forthwith to make
the necessary changes in their ways of thinking and
their behaviour with regard to social integration,
growth, consumption and employment.
It also means that the strategies adopted by deci¬
sion-makers must take account of those whose inse¬
cure conditions contribute to international insta¬
bility I am thinking of emigrants, refugees, displaced
persons and members of minority groups.
It also involves a shared determination, a joint
effort of all parties, at both the national and the inter¬
national level. At the national level, it is essential to har¬
monize, with imagination and daring, policies for
employment, education, health, science, technology,
regional planning, population and social integration. It
is also essential that the private sector, the trade unions,
the non-governmental organizations, indeed all parts
of society co-operate with the authorities to ensure that
these policies are successful. The role of women (so
indispensable for social development), training and
the acquisition of new skills (for jobs connected with
the environment, for example) such questions need
to be treated in the context of society as a whole. Real
social development necessitates the active and demo¬
cratic participation of all members of society.
At the international level, changes in the eco¬
nomic situation and the extent of economic co-oper¬
ation will clearly play a considerable part in forming
the social pact, on condition that they are reflected in
a reorientation of commercial exchanges and financial
mechanisms. Within the United Nations system, the
required change of direction is already being made,
but it is essential to improve the coherence of the
activities being carried out to acknowledge the human
and social dimension of development. Allowances
for this dimenson must involve scrupulously planned
demilitarization, so that the new priorities gradually
open up areas of genuine decision making and
empowerment for civil society.
This will not be easy. But it would be illusory to
think that social development can be achieved through
the worn-out, myopic approach of economic devel¬
opment pursued up to now.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
R H
Thomas Mann giving a radio talk in 1 928.
The following year he was awarded the
Nobel Prize for literature.
Thomas Mann
The collectivist betrayal
44
In 1935 Thomas Mann (1875-1955)
tookpart in a meeting in Nice
(France) organized by the
International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation on the
theme of"the education ofmodern
man", and delivered a lecture thefirst
instalment ofwhich is published
below. (The second and third
instalments will appear in
forthcoming issues.) Mann, who had
leftHitler's Germany two years
before, here expresses his beliefin
"European civilization" and defends
the culture threatened by the rise of
Nazi ideology. Readers mayfind
some ofthe ideas he putsforward are
still surprisingly topical.
Deep down, Goethe never lost his
kind heart or his good nature;
and in his old age he confesses
to us that he loved youth dearly, and that
when young he liked himself much more
than he liked himself as an old man.
But these words occur among others
which do not hide his impatience with
and lack of faith in the younger generation.
"When you see," he wrote in 1812, "not
only how people, especially the young,
devote themselves to their pleasures and
passions, but also how the age's serious
forms of madness change and distort all
that is highest and best in them, so that
everything that should make them happy
becomes their loss, to say nothing of the
unspeakable pressure from outside, then
it is not surprising that people obstinately
persist in committing crimes against
themselves and others."
We know all about that: the distortion
of all that is highest and best in young
people, the unspeakable outside pressure,
and also the crimes. "The incredible pre- .
sumption," wrote Goethe on another occa¬
sion, "to which young people give rein will
manifest itself in a few years' time in the
greatest lunacy," words that might have
been uttered today, a really topical
prophecy. He also wrote: "Young people no
longer listen. It is true that listening
requires a special kind of culture." Cul¬
ture! A word that attracts the sneers of a
whole generation. These sneers are
directed against the favourite word of the
liberal middle class, as ifculture were really
only another word for middle-class liber¬
alism, as if it did not denote the opposite
ofbrutishness and human destitution: the
opposite also of idleness, of that miser¬
able sloppiness that is still sloppiness even
when it adopts a martial gait, in a word, as
if culture, as form, as desire for freedom
and truth, living by conscience and cease¬
less efforts, were not the discipline of
morality itself!
AN ESCAPIST GENERATION
So who bothers nowadays? The children of
the modern world claim that life is harder
for them than it ever was for us, because
they share its risks, its distress and its total
uncertainty, whereas we grew up in the
economic security of the bourgeois cen¬
tury. But they exaggerate the importance
of material things: and in any case, must
not we children of the past in our old age
now get used to a change in the circum¬
stances that have taken us from bourgeois
satiety to heroic penury? The important
thing is that young people have no idea
about "culture" in the lofty, profound
sense, or about inner struggles, individual
responsibility or personal effort; they take
their ease in collective life instead.
Collective life is comfortable compared
with individual life deliriously comfort-
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
able. What the collectivist generation
desires, and allows itself, is a perpetual
holiday to escape from itself. What it wants
and loves is ecstasy: and if we look at this
term, expressive of noble, holy ideas and
essential for the exaltation and religious
uplifting of life, we see at once that the
collectivism that is fashionable today is
but one example of the popular distor¬
tion that great and venerable European
concepts undergo when they are distrib¬
uted and handed over for consumption
by the masses.
"To make but one with all of life," cried
Hölderlin in Hyperion. "At these words
virtue doffs its warlike armour, the spirit of
man lays down the sceptre; death disap¬
pears from the midst of life, and everlast-
ingness and eternal youth inspire and
beautify the world." The Dionysiac event
that these words portend is cheapened in
the collectivist ecstasy, the purely selfish
hedonistic pleasure, informed by no real
meaning, that young people get from
marching in serried ranks to the rhythm of
songs that are a mixture of folk-songs that
have fallen into the gutter and newspaper
articles.
AN IMPOVERISHED CIVILIZATION
These young people like to melt into the
mass untrammelled by any personal
responsibility, and don't really mind which
way they are going. When asked what sat¬
isfaction they get out of it all, they are in no
hurry to draw definite conclusions or make
projections. The collective intoxication
that brings freedom from the self and its
burdens is its own reward. Related ideas
such as "the state", "socialism" and
"national grandeur" are more or less
excuses subsidiary and, frankly, super¬
fluous ideas. What matters is to achieve
ecstasy, to break free from the selfand the
need to think, i.e. essentially to free oneself
ofall morality and all reason and also, of
course, of fear, of the anxiety that leads
people to crowd together in dense masses,
keeping each other warm and singing
loudly. This aspect of the matter is far and
away the most likely to arouse our sym¬
pathy and commiseration.
This sense of wellbeing that people
feel when they escape from themselves
and shake off all personal responsibility
goes back to the war. When we speak of
modern man, today's man, we are of
course thinking of the post-war European,
the man who fought in the war or was
born into the world created by the war.
We tend to regard the present state of the
world, economically, intellectually and
morally, as the result of the war. But per¬
haps that is going too far. There is no
denying the enormous material and moral
havoc the war caused, but it did not create
our world. It merely brought to light,
accentuated and exaggerated what was
already there. The incredible impoverish¬
ment of civilization and the moral deca¬
dence we cannot avoid observing by com¬
parison with the nineteenth century are
not the result of the war, although the war
doubtless made a big contribution to
them. The movement had already started
beforehand. It is an old phenomenon,
caused primarily by the rise to power of
mass man, as José Ortega y Gasset has so
brilliantly shown in his book, La Rebelión
de las masas (1929; The Revolt of the
Masses, 1932).
It is a tragedy that all the confusion of
our times is due to the generosity and
boundless benevolence ofthe nineteenth
century, that immensely productive age
whose scientific and social blessings
enabled the population of Europe to
increase threefold; it is a tragedy that this
crisis, which bids fair to send us back into
barbarism, grew out of its shortsighted
magnanimity. Ortega splendidly describes
how the new masses irrupted into a civi¬
lization which they proceeded to use as
though it were a natural phenomenon,
ignorant and utterly disrespectful of the
complex mechanisms that were essential
to its existence.
As an example of the masses' attitude
to the conditions that gave them birth, it is
worth recalling that they trampled liberal
democracy underfoot or, more precisely,
that they used liberal democracy to destroy
liberal democracy. It is very possible that
they will bring about the decline of tech¬
nology too, despite all the childish love
their primitive souls have for it, because
they do not know that technology is merely
the practical application of free and dis¬
interested research pursued for love of
knowledge, and because they despise ide¬
alism and everything related to it and
hence freedom and truth.
INTELLECTUAL DECLINE
"Primitivism" is the right word to use. "The
average modern man," says Ortega, "has a
much healthier, more vigorous, but also
much simpler mind than his predecessor
of the last century." Thus if a play such as
Ibsen's Wild Duck is played to a modern
audience (assuming that the term, with
its overtones of elitism, is the right one to
apply to the modern masses), it will turn
out to have become completely incom¬
prehensible thirty-five years later. The
audience takes it as a farce, and laughs in
the wrong places. In the nineteenth cen¬
tury there was a society capable ofunder¬
standing the European irony, the double
meanings, the idealist bitterness and the
moral refinement of a work of this kind.
This faculty has been lost; and the proven
possibility of the "disappearance", the low¬
ering of the intellectual level almost
overnight to a primitive state in which
people are not merely insensitive to the
finer points but feel a fierce hatred for
them this whole phenomenon, which
would have been thought impossible in
the nineteenth century, because then
people believed in continuity, is all the
more frightening because it opens up
wider vistas. It shows that victories can in
the end be lost and fall into oblivion, and
that civilization itself is by no means cer¬
tain to escape this fate.
(TO BE CONTINUED)
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton ¿L «C
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
QUEBEC
a city beyond compare
byAndré Charbonneau,
Yvon Desloges and Marc Lafrance
The cradle ofFrench civilization in America and afortified city
ofoutstanding interest, historic Quebec is one ofUnesco's world
heritage sites
When he built his first lodging,
which served as a warehouse,
home and fort on the northern
bank of the St. Lawrence in 1608 on the
site ofwhat is today Place Royale; Samuel
de Champlain harboured great ambitions
for Quebec that it should become the
main port of the new colony, its political
and religious centre, its major stronghold.
The future proved him right. In the span of
one and a half centuries, Quebec became
the capital of an immense French empire
in America a giant with feet of clay
extending from the Gulfof St. Lawrence to
the Gulf of Mexico, and from the Atlantic
Ocean to the Rocky Mountains.
Located on a steep hill with two
plateaux one high, the other low
Quebec acquired its characteristic fea¬
tures very early on. In the upper town were
the fortress, the governor's palace, reli¬
gious and administrative buildings and
numerous dwellings. The lower town was
the commercial district whose port was
until the mid-nineteenth century the far¬
thest point up the St. Lawrence that ocean¬
going vessels could sail. From Quebec furs
were exported in the seventeenth and
eighteenth centuries, as was lumber in
the nineteenth, bywhich time the city had
become the third largest port in North
America and the principal point of entry
for immigrants to Canada.
Moreover, the city and its educational
institutions served as the administrative
and intellectual centre of the new colony
46
View of Quebec.
(19th-century
French engraving).
of New France, and was the apostolic seat
of a large diocese that extended over a vast
area ofNorth America, from the Atlantic to
Louisiana. From it explorers and mis¬
sionaries set sail in search of new lands
and new souls. It was the destination of
French settlers who found there reminders
of the land from which they had come.
The cathedral, built in the middle of the
eighteenth century, and the seventeenth-
century parts of the Ursulines Convent
and the Seminary, are all that remains of
the complex of religious buildings the
archbishopric and other institutions
that once stood in the upper town.
In spite of important political, eco¬
nomic and social changes, Quebec has
succeeded in preserving its cultural her¬
itage, which is based on its institutions
and architecture, but also on its geography.
While large architectural structures have
undergone major changes, the layout of
the city remains fundamentally the same,
spreading out like a spider's web, with a
chequerboard pattern added in the middle
of the eighteenth century by the engineer
Chaussegros de Léry. The typical Quebec
house had a distinctive architectural style
adapted from a French model. Most of
them were destroyed during the bom¬
bardment of 1759 and were rebuilt after
the English conquest by craftsmen using
traditional skills. Large chimneys, fire-
break walls and high roofs are character¬
istic features.
THE FORTIFIED CITY
The upper town offered many tactical
advantages to a city that was strategically
important as a centre of communication
with the mother country and as the port of
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Château Frontenac looks out over the
St. Lawrence. It is named for Louis de
Buade, count of Palluau and Frontenac,
who was governor of New France in the late
1 7th century.
entry for supplies from France. Indeed,
Quebec's defensive system reflected the
advances of European fortification tech¬
niques from the seventeenth to the nine¬
teenth centuries. Several elements of the
system have survived to evoke the rich
military past of a city that has experienced
no less than five sieges.
Champlain's first wooden house calls
to mind a medieval castle equipped with
platforms for cannon. By the end of the
seventeenth century, however, and during
the first halfof the eighteenth, the colony
was caught in the throes of rivalry between
European nations. Quebec became a prize
in the conflict between troops and military
techniques of the old continent. A suc¬
cession ofdefensive walls were built whose
geometry and contours reflect the influ¬
ence of the great French military engineer
Vauban. Several military structures from
this period have survived, notably the walls
around the old city, which were built by
Chaussegros de Léry after 1745. Quebec
was besieged twice during the Seven Years
War (1756 to 1763), which was caused by
rivalry between France and England in
North America.
After the Treaty of Paris (1763), as a
result of which New France became an
English colony, Quebec continued to be of
great strategic importance, although its
situation was transformed by the Amer¬
ican War of Independence against the
British. American troops attempted to
seize the city in 1775. British contribu¬
tions to the defence system can still be
seen. The construction of a citadel on the
top of a strategic site is a classic response
by an army ofoccupation in a newly-con¬
quered land, and the British were no
exception to the rule. After many projects
had been put forward and some building
work was done between 1778 and 1782,
the Citadel, which still dominates Cape
Diamond, was finally built between 1 820
and 1830 to plans by Colonel Elias
Durnford.
Old houses in the
lower town evoke
the atmosphere of
Normandy or
Brittany, where
their first occupants
originated.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
Rebuilt in neogothic style in the 19th
century, the St. Louis gate was one of the
fortified passages through the city wall.
The surviving elements of the defence
system are one of the dominant features of
Quebec's urban landscape. They are widely
regarded as a key cultural resource that
gives Quebec its distinctive character
among North American cities.
THE END OF AN ERA
Quebec's era as a military fortress ended
towards the middle of the nineteenth cen¬
tury. The departure of the British garrison
in 1871 provided an opportunity to
abandon the fort and destroy the old mil¬
itary gates. It marked the start of changes
whereby the fortress became a historical
monument and of struggles between the
forces of progress and the supporters of
conservation.
It was a bitter struggle, waged during a
time ofsteady decline in Quebec. The large
sea port, the shipbuilding industry and
the lumber trade collapsed and the city
lost ground when Ottawa became national
capital after the creation of the Canadian
Confederation. Yet in spite of these diffi
culties, major building projects such as
the Parliament buildings (1886), City Hall
(1895) and the Château Frontenac (1894)
enhanced the city's image and gave it a
new skyline.
The preservation movement launched
by the government of General Dufferin in
1874 to protect the old walled enclosures
determined the present shape of Quebec.
The construction of the famous Dufferin
terrace that overlooks the cliff, and the
opening of new entry points into the city
transformed Quebec from a fortress city
into a national historic site.
The preservation movement grew
stronger during the twentieth century. The
fortifications were classified as a monu¬
ment ofnational historical interest in 1957.
Around the same time, the government
of Quebec undertook the restoration of a
number ofhouses and buildings situated
on Place Royale in the lower town the
E za
ANDRE CHARBONNEAU, WON
DESLOGES AND MARC LAFRANCE
are Quebec historians working with Parks
Canada-Quebec Region. They have been active for
over twenty years in the protection and
presentation of Canadian historic sites. They are
co-authors of Quebec, the Fortified City: from the
17th to the 19th century (Quebec, 1982).
former commercial and residential heart
of Quebec. In December 1985, following a
recommendation by the International
Council on Monuments and Sites
(ICOMOS), the historic district ofQuebec
was added to Unesco's World Heritage List.
Rue Notre-Dame, in the lower town, is one
of the oldest thoroughfares In North
America.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
p LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
THE UNIVERSALITY
OF HUNAN NICHTS
Are human rights universal?
Would that they were. We per¬
ceive this universality as self-evi¬
dent, like other values we hold
dear. The important point, how¬
ever, is not whether those rights
are universal from the philo¬
sophical or metaphysical point
of view but whether everyone
feels them to be universal.
It is doubtful whether they
do. We take our stand on the
principles set forth in the Uni¬
versal Declaration of Human
Rights, adopted in 1948; but at
that time the United Nations had
less than sixty members, and the
forty-eight votes cast in favour
of adoption were all, or nearly
all, "Western" votes, whilst decol¬
onization had scarcely begun
and we had only just started to
speak about the Third World.
The United Nations now has
nearly 200 members. The coun¬
tries that have joined have thus
"subscribed" to the Declara¬
tion but how? By a solemn
undertaking, by a statement that
is binding on them, at least
morally? It seems not.
These countries are under
an obligation, but what sort of
an obligation? Moral only, since
the United Nations has no real
means of coercing those who
should fail to respect their
undertakings. As Jean-Jacques
Rousseau said long ago,
"Without the sword conventions
are mere words", and everything
depends on governments' good
faith.
How is it possible to talk
about the universality ofhuman
rights when the Islamic coun¬
tries, for example, some years
ago proclaimed, quite officially,
an "Islamic Declaration of
Human Rights"? Ifwe are to con¬
sider that declaration valid, then
why not a Catholic, Protestant,
Jewish or any other declaration?
Muslims are not alone in dis¬
puting the universality ofhuman
rights. Africans too have set
themselves apart by publishing
an "African Charter on Human
and Peoples' Rights" that,
although it does not define the
concept of "peoples" very clearly,
shows that they think "the
people" should take precedence
over the individual.
Furthermore, in the socialist
system, the concept of "natural
law" that we so cherish is totally
denied, the law being no more
than the expression of a rela¬
tionship between the state and
the citizen and any supranational
surveillance thus being totally
negated. Other countries, for that
matter, adopt the same negative
attitude in the name of their
sacrosanct national sovereignty.
Let us not, lastly, forget that
the countries of the Third World
are claiming a new right, the
right to development. The most
important thing for us, say the
leaders of those countries, is the
fight against hunger and poverty,
with "Western-style" human
rights tagging along behind. In
point of fact, respect for human
rights has never got in the way of
development, and those leaders
are sometimes mainly concerned
to perpetuate the regimes they
have set up. We must, in any case,
take account of this situation.
So let us not delude our¬
selves. Ourhuman rights reflect
our society, and they are by no
means accepted world-wide.
Whether we like it or not, we
have to face the fact.
It remains for us to draw the
conclusions and ask ourselves
what we ought to do to ensure
that they are indeed felt to be
universal throughout the world.
There is obviously no question of
trying to impose them that
would be to deny the very values
for which we standso we must
learn to use the power of per¬
suasion. Relations between peo¬
ples are much more highly devel¬
oped than they used to be; let us
learn to make use of them. Our
industrial civilization has man¬
aged to impose its technology
all over the world; it would be
hard to believe that it could not
just as successfully "export" its
noble ideas.
Meanwhile, we still need to
learn to "accept others", to try to
understand them and not turn
them away, in other words to
practise the seemingly forgotten
cardinal virtue of tolerance.
Bob Zeegers
Former United Nations
Development Programme
expert
Callian (France)
A LIVING LANGUAGE
OF SIBERIA
Vladimir Belikov, whose article
"Language death in Siberia"
appeared in your February 1994
issue, Worlds within Words, is
right to be pessimistic about the
survival of the languages of the
peoples ofSiberia. I would, how¬
ever, like to give your readers a
rather more encouraging piece
of information.
In August 1993, during a
short stay at Atchan, a village of
the Nanai people on the banks of
the Amur river in eastern Siberia,
I discovered that the Nanai lan¬
guage is extremely well protected
because of a well-adapted edu¬
cational system. At the village
school, which since 1983 has
been known as a "national
school", all the lessons are taught
in Nanai, including those on
applied art. Certain traditional
activities such as embroidery are
still practised.
For young Nanais, the diffi¬
culties come later. When they
have to go to the city to continue
their education at secondary and
higher level, they face difficul¬
ties in adapting and integrating
which are due both to their
material circumstances and cul¬
ture differences. These small
peoples (no value-judgment
intended) have to blend into the
Russian cultural and linguistic
mass if they are to have any
chance of integration. This
encourages them to lose their
own identity.
Vladimir Belikov is to be
thanked for his work.
Brigitte Julia-Ripoll
Perpignan (France)
THE MISSING DESERT
As a lover of the desert, I was
extremely interested to read your
January 1994 issue devoted to
this theme.
I was very surprised, how¬
ever, not to find a single men¬
tion of the world's purest (if not
biggest) desert the desert of
Arabia. It haunted the European
imagination and a substantial
article deserves to be written
about it.
Ma'rib, the capital of the
Sabaeans, was built in the
middle of this desert, its waters
confined by a great earth dam
which, as the Qur'an says,
enabled two gardens to blossom
"on the right hand and on the
left hand". The trade in incense
that plied through the desert
brought prosperity to the cities of
Petra and Palmyra. Here the
Roman legions sustained a
crushing defeat in 24 B.C. In the
desert of Oman are the famous
aflaj, underground drainage tun¬
nels that make farming possible.
The desert ofArabia has also
been intensively explored by
such illustrious figures as Lady
Anne Blunt, Louis Arnaud, H. St.
J. Philby, Wilfred Thesiger, Amin
Rihani and many others. It is also
the home of the culture and civ¬
ilization of the Bedouin. In
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: Peter Turnley/Black
Star © Rapho, Paris. Pages 2 and4:
All Rights Reserved. Pages 6-7:
David Parker© SPL/Cosmos, Paris.
Pages 8-9: Alfred © Sipa Press,
Paris. Pages 1 0, 1 2, 32-33: © Jean-
Loup Charmet, Paris. Page 1 1 : Her¬
bert Kraft © Archiv für Kunst und
Geschichte, Berlin. Page 1 3: Le Seg-
retain © Sipa Press, Paris. Page 1 4:
SNARK/Edimédia, Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Pages 1 5, 20: ©
Edimedia, Paris. Pages 16-17:
Arthur Grace © Sygma, Paris. Page
1 7: P. Durand © Sygma, Paris. Page
1 8: Paul of Romania Archives © Sipa
Press, Paris. Page 1 9: Chesnot ©
Sipa Press, Paris. Page 2 1 : © Jean-
Loup Charmet, Bibliothèque des
Arts décoratifs, Paris. Page 22:
Novosti © Sipa Press, Paris. Page
23: Wildenberg © Sygma, Paris.
Page 24: MIT © Sipa Press, Paris.
Page 25: Thomas Hartwell ©
Sygma, Paris. Pages 26, 27: Diego
Goldberg © Sygma, Paris. Page 28:
All Rights Reserved. Page 29: ©
Alain Guillou, Le Crolsic (France).
Page 30: © Valdin DIAF © MISS
International, Paris. Pages 31,44:©
Archiv für Kunst und Geschichte,
Berlin. Page 34 (above): Illustra¬
tion/ Sygma, Paris. Page 34
(below): Tom Haley © Sipa Press,
Paris. Page 35: Steve Benbow ©
Cosmos, Paris. Page 36: J. Chaldej
© Archiv für Kunst und Geschichte,
Berlin. Page 37: Heimo Aga ©
Cosmos, Paris. Pages 38, 39 (left):
D. Rouvre © Réunion des Musées
Nationaux, Paris. Page 39 (right):
© Charles Lenars, Paris. Pages 40,
46: © Dagli Orti, Paris. Page 41:©
Léonard de Selva, Paris. Page 42: ©
Fabian. Page 47 (above): © Sipa
Press, Paris. Page 47 (below): Ben
Simmons © Sipa Press, Paris. Page
48 (above): UNESCO-Jacques Collin.
Page 48 (below): Don Carl Steffen
© Rapho, Paris.
Mouny Berrah's article, even the
film Lawrence ofArabia is not
mentioned. What a pity!
Joseph Chelhod
Antony (France)
NOT ENOUGH WONEN
Your magazine is very interesting
but you do not have enough
women contributors. Take the
issue entitled A time to love. . .
(April 1993). On such a subject
there was every right to expect an
equitable division between the
sexes. And yet eight out of your
ten contributors were men!
Publishing an issue about
women from time to time is not
enough. There should be parity
between men and women in
every issue. Are not women one
of Unesco's priorities? More
effort please!
Florence Montreynaud
Paris (France) 49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
» CONTINUED FROH PAGE 7
In these parallel universes, all combina¬
tions of constants and physical laws would
be possible. Most would be infertile but, by
chance, our universe has found the winning
combination and we are the big prize. In
this hypothesis, we are the result of a lucky
throw of dice.
Also, with quantum mechanics, a first
cause is not necessary. In the microscopic
world of elementary particles, causal rela¬
tionships do not even exist. At any
moment, phantom particles can arise sud¬
denly and unexpectedly from an energy-
filled void. It is impossible to predict where
and when they will appear. Some physicists
think that what is true for one elementary
particle is also true for the entire universe
at its beginning. At 1043 second after the
Big Bang, the universe measuring 10~33
centimetre was 10 million billion billion
times smaller than an atom. It is quantum
uncertainty that made it possible for time,
space, and then the universe to arise spon¬
taneously from the void.
Science cannot decide between this
notion of chance on one hand and necessity
on the other which the anthropic principle
expresses. As for me in this instance I
speak more as a man of faith than of sci¬
ence I opt for the second hypothesis: to
assume that there is an infinite number of
parallel universes inaccessible to observa¬
tion and hence to experimental verifica¬
tion goes against the simplicity and
economy of natural laws. On the contrary,
what I find striking when I study the uni¬
verse is its unity, its intimate harmony;
this allows us, in our little corner of the
earth, to work out physical laws that can
explain phenomena occurring billions of
light years away and discover properties of
celestial bodies so far away that their light
had left before the atoms of our bodies
had even been made.
This same unity can be found in physics
itself, where one discovers links between
phenomena that, a priori, have nothing in
common. In the nineteenth century, James
Maxwell unified electricity and magnetism.
In the twentieth, Albert Einstein taught us
that time and space were one and the same
thing. At the moment, physicists are trying
to prove that the four basic forces of nature
are in fact only one single force.
From the harmony of the universe we
get a deep sense of beauty: not only because
it contains objects of incredible splendour,
but also because it is simple. Such varied
phenomena as the expansion of the uni¬
verse, the movement of the planets or the
form of a snowflake can all be explained by
the action of the four basic forces and by
that alone. Theories that describe the uni¬
verse have to be as simple, as beautiful as
that. I am convinced that beauty and truth
go together, and that an aesthetic sense can
nourish intuition and guide research. The
greatest physicists, such as Einstein or
Dirac, had an acute sense of the beauty of
their theories.
If the extremely precise workings of
the universe are not due to a series of
chance occurrences, then one has to assume
that there was a Creative Principle which
regulated it at the very beginning. As
Voltaire said: "The universe confounds
me, and I cannot believe that this clock
exists and has no clock-maker."
Will the research carried out by astro¬
physicists today using an extraordinary
wealth of resources ultimately lead to a
metaphysical quest?
It certainly responds to a very ancient
yearning that of the first human beings
who turned their gaze upwards to the sky.
My colleagues and I are the descendants of
those men, with greater resources and more
sophisticated instruments. But it is still the
same quest that leads us to ask questions
about our origins and the roots of life. By
making it possible for us to situate our¬
selves in the long history of cosmic evolu¬
tion, astronomy helps us to transcend the
weightiness of our bodies and the brevity
of our lives.
SO
NESCO
JH COURIER
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin. 75015 Paris. France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation:
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange ßelin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant:
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montreux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyad.gama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodimir Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de
Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo. Michel Ravassard. Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
I year: 2 1 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be repnnted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Uncsco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies arc sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be sup¬
plied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily rep¬
resent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco
Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff. The boundaries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche)
by: (I) Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris: (2) University Micro¬
films (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48 100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition. Indian Head Inc.. I ! I West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.; (4)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 4469 1 . U.SA
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI -MAI 1994
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N" 7 1 844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de ('UNESCO.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL, 2. rue Christophe-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 004 1 -S278 N"' 5- 1 994-OPI-94-526A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Edifions du comité
des travaux historiques et scientifiques
Editeur de documents universitaires et de recherches historiques
I . rue d'Ulm 75005 Paris Tel : 49 55 23 64
American ¡Business ichool
Programme de l'Université de
Hartford dispensé en anglais.
Bachelor in Business
Administration
1 e,e - 2eme - 3èrre années à l'A. B. S.
ou 1 e,e - 2eme années à l'A. BS. et
3en"eannée aux U.S.A. sur le
campus de I Université de Hartford
Spécialisations: Finance/Econo¬
mies. Marketing
Préparation intégrée
TOEFL & GMAT.
Master in Business
Administration
4eme année: Paris ou Hartford.
Admission
1 è,e année: BAC , High School
Diploma. .
2eme année: DEUG. BTS, DUT. .
3emeannée: Licence. .
AMERICAN
4 YEARS
FRANCE/U.S.A
Au!
American business ichool
Enseignement supérieur prive . en liaison avec
UNIVERSITY OF HARTFORD
PARIS 75116 - 15. AV. DE LAGRANDE ARMEE. Tél. : (1) 45.01.96.01
LYON 69009 -24, AVENUE J0ANNES-M ASSET Bât 5. Tél. : 78.64.1 5.31
MARSEILLE 13006 - 26-28. COURS PIERRE PUGET Tél. : 91.55.05.48
WE MAKE A HABIT OF SUCCEEDING
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine
published in 32 languages and read by hundreds of thousands of
people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal respect
for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms...without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
MONTH, ESSENTIAL READING
OF TODAY
, ATOPIC OF UNIV
N THROUGH THE
N --TS OF DIFFFP
iN UNDERSTANDS
TOMORROW
PROBLEMS
WATER OF LIFE ... MINORITIES... WHAT IS MODERN?... RHYTHM, GESTURE AND THE SACRED... TINE TO
DISARM... THE STORY OF NUMBERS... A NORTH-SOUTH DEBATE: THE MEANING OF PROGRESS... DESERTS-
WORLDS WITHIN WORDS... HUNAN RIGHTS, THE UNFINISHED TASK... MODERN HANAGENENT AND LOCAL
TRADITIONS... A NEW LOOK AT THE HISTORY OF COHNUNISH...
FRANCOIS NITTERRAND... JORGE ANADO... RICHARD ATTENBOROUGH... JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE... JEAN
LACOUTURE... FEDERICO NAYOR... NAGUIB NAHFOUZ... SENBENE OUSHANE... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY...
FRÉDÉRIC ROSSIF... HINNERK BRUHNS... CAMILO JOSÉ CELA... VACLAV HAVEL... SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV...
ERNESTO SÁBATO... 6RO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND... CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS... LEOPOLDO ZEA... PAULO FREIRÉ...
DANIEL J. BOORSTIN... FRANCOIS JACOB... MANU DIBANGO... FAROUK HOSNY... SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN...
JORGE LAVELLI... LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG... TAHAR BEN JELLOUN... GABRIEL GARCÍA MAROUEZ... JACQUES-
YVES COUSTEAU... MELINA MERCOURI... CARLOS FUENTES... JOSEPH KI-ZERBO... VANDANA SHIVA... WILLIAM
STYRON... OSCAR NIEMEYER... HIKIS THEODORAKIS... ATAHUALPA YUPANQUI... HERVÉ BOURGES... ABDEL
RAHMAN EL BACHA... SUSANA RINALDI... HUBERT REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS... A LETTER FROM FREUD TO
EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY... CHARLES MALAMOUD... UMBERTO ECO... OLIVER STONE... ANDRÉ BRINK... JAMES D.
WATSON... AMOS OZ... MICHEL SERRES... THÉODORE MONOD... YVES COPPENS... EDOUARD J.MAUNICK...
JEAN MALAURIE... TRINH XUAN THUAN...
]]>
</page>
</document>
