<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="096934eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
COURIER
APRIL 1994
ANAGEHENT
AND LOCAL
TRADITIONS
Interviewwith
lean Malaurie
The National
Park
dilemma
A paradise
garden in the
Seychelles
j
M 1205-9404- 22, OF
If
3P
¿I
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
Watercolour XXII ( 1 989)
(62 x 45 cm)
by Mona Yazbeck
"Sometimes light patches of mist, rising from the mountainsides in the morning breeze, broke
loose like white feathers that a bird might have released in the wind," wrote the French poet
Alphonse de Lamartine on 2 September 1832, during a visit to Lebanon. The Lebanese artist
Mona Yazbeck has chosen the transparent fluidity of watercolour to paint impressions of her
country inspired by the travel writings of visitors to the Orient, a fashionable literary genre in
nineteenth-century Europe. She has rediscovered intact the face of a war-torn land, just as it
might have appeared to those who looked on it with wonderment for the first time.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW WITH
Jean Malaurie
Contents
APRIL 1994
MODERN
MANAGEMENT
AND LOCAL
TRADITIONS ^rtU
UNESCO IN ACTION
40
NEWSBRIEFS...
HERITAGE
The Vallée de Hai: a
paradise garden in the
Seychelles
by Guy Lionnet
45
ARCHIVES
Art and the home
by Le Corbusier
46
TRIBUTE
Cziffra: a legacy of freedom
by Stany Kol
47
ANNIVERSARY
Ulugh Beg, the
astronomer-king
byjasmina Sopova
48
BOOKS OF THE WORLD
49
RECEHT RECORDINGS
by Isabelle Leymarie
50
Letters to the Editor
presentation by Philippe d'lribarne
1 1 Business cultures
by Geert Hofstede
1 7 Togo Going by the book
by Alain Henry and Yao Badjo
10 Tunisia They do it their way
by Riadh Zghal
1 1 Mexico «/ Local loyalties: a hidden asset
by jean Ruffier and Daniel Villavicencio
1 1 Eastern Europe Voices from the past
by Tatjana Globokar
15 Japan The new samurai
by John Harford
Cover design specially executed for
the Unesco Courier by the Belgian
graphic artist Dimitri Selesneff.
Greenwatch
The National Park
dilemma
by France Bequette
COMMENTARY
by
Federico Mayor
Special consultant for this Issue:
Philippe d'lribarne
TheljNESCO
^XOURIER
47th year Published monthly
in 31 languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples cf the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER I94S
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
T E R V I E W
JEAN MALAURIE talks to
Bahgat Elnadi and Âdel Rifaat
The Arctic, from
stones to man
In 1948, twenty-six-year-old Jean
Malaurie embarked on his first polar
expedition, to the west coast of
Greenland. Two years later he spent
a winter with the Inuit, learning their
language and hunting techniques
and sharing their everyday
experiences. On his return to
France, he initiated with the Paris
publishing house of Pion a series
entitled "Terre humaine" with the
publication of Les derniers rois de
Thulé (The Last Kings of Thule,
Jonathan Cape, 1983), his account of
his experiences among the Inuit,
which has since been translated
into twenty-two languages. He holds
the only chair in France in polar
geography (at EHESS, the Ecole des
Hautes études en sciences
sociales) and was the founder, with
the historian Fernand Braudel, of
EHESS's Centre of Arctic Studies.
As well as pursuing an academic
career, he has continued to carry
out research in the fieldover
thirty one-man expeditions have
taken him from Greenland to Alaska
and northeast Siberia. Specialists
from all over the world contributed
to a work published in his honour in
1990: Pour Jean Malaurie, 102
témoignages en hommage à
quarante ans d'études arctiques
(Pion publishers, Paris).
Not the least ofyour many claims to
fame is to have initiatedan important series
of ethnographic publications, "Terre
humaine".
"Terre humaine" is the embodiment of a
current of ideas, a growing awareness of
"transdisciplinarity", the overstepping of
the boundaries of academic disciplines. Like
the UNESCO Courier, it is devoted to the idea
of getting to know one another. Under the
influence of Marxism, interest has in our
times focused on systems, tending to leave
individuals out of the picture. Structures
and economic and social forces do, of
course, exist, but there is also an unpre¬
dictable player on the stage of history
the human being. That was why I thought
it essential to create a current of ideas that
would reintroduce the personal element
and put into perspective what we acade¬
mics call anthropology, sociology or eth¬
nology the observation of other people, in
short.
Its other concern is to let people speak
for themselves. In the West, who writes?
The writer. But tape recorders now enable
us to take down the remarks of people who
have never held a book in their hands. My
aim in this collection, which began in 1955
with my own book Les derniers rois de
Thulé {The Last Kings of Thule) and now
comprises over seventy volumes, was to
abolish the class struggle one far more
insidious than that denounced by Karl
Marx between intellectuals on the one
hand and the meek and lowly on the other.
I have on occasion recorded the words of
convicts, even of some awaiting execution
on death row in one of the toughest jails in
Texas. In another book, to be published
shortly, an Indian woman, a pariah from
southern Madras, tells her life story. What
these men and women have to say is irre¬
placeable.
"Terre humaine" also serves as a
reminder that the social sciences are not
alone in studying humanity, and that the
Bible, the Qur'an, the Vedas and the great
works of literature throw a necessary light
on our societies' problems. I have there¬
fore sought out unpublished material by
great authors. Who would have thought
anything remained unpublished of the
works of Zola, one of the world's most
translated authors? And yet 800 pages of
notes, tied together with string, had been
lying around for eighty-three years in
France's Bibliothèque nationale until I pub¬
lished them under the title Carnets
d'enquêtes en France, une ethnographie
inédite. This document is a real lesson in
modern journalism, written in the manner
of Truman Capote, a style that was new for
its time. I also published Les Immémoriaux
by Victor Segalen, which was gathering dust
in the Plön publishing house. Written by a
Breton Catholic, it is a remarkably out¬
spoken piece of work, describing the effects
of the introduction of Christianity in a tra¬
ditional society, that of Tahiti, which lost its
balance and its joie de vivre as a result, and
discussing the whole question of this inter¬
ference in other peoples' lives, with the
backing of the colonial power, from the
right to conquer their territory to the right
to subjugate their souls. The notebooks of
a great unknown writer, comparable in
stature to Gide, André Suarès, are to be
published soon. I am currently negotiating
with UNESCO for some of these books,
which have a universal appeal, to be made
more widely available, in languages other
than French or English, less widely used
languages.
Your understanding oftraditionalsoci¬
eties has hadconsiderable influence on your
criticisms of industrial society.
We are going through a terrible crisis,
with unemployment increasing daily not
only in western Europe but in Japan and
America too. The jobless are the outcasts of
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
industrial society, and the crisis can only
get worse as more and more jobs are auto¬
mated. We are condemned to live in a society
where human beings are at the centre of
the crisis. In "economism", the human being
is a nuisance. This is the height of absurdity!
We need only look at the case of the many
young people who go on living with their
parents beyond the age of thirty because
they are unemployed. With no work to go
to, glued to the television or absorbed in
video games, their lives become an extension
of adolescence, and they may well reach
early retirement age without ever having
held down a proper job, so their outlook
remains that of adolescents a situation
unprecedented in history.
In spite of that, we go on advocating
development. Every international confer¬
ence discusses development. Some of the
"developing countries" will never know
what it is. What is more, by showing them,
in the television series we export to them,
affluent families enjoying a comfortable
lifestyle they cannot aspire to, by dangling
before them a future they will never reach,
we are helping to upset their balance. We
shall have destroyed them completely before
they can straighten themselves up. These
are unwholesome practices that are under¬
mining an age-old balance for the sole pur¬
pose of finding outlets for the products we
manufacture.
The concept of loss ofbalance seems to
play an important role in your thinking.
Balance is essential in nature. For fifteen
years I studied balance in stones, stones
that have been there since the very beginning
of all things 700 million years in the case
of the Archaean platform in the Arctic.
Under the influence of my first intellectual
mentor, Emmanuel de Martonne, one of
the founding fathers of modern geography,
I came to be interested in weathering
processes. I began by studying scree, the
rock fragments that accumulate at the foot
of cliffs, and the geodynamics of its forma
tion in the great cold and hot deserts, with
their extremes of temperature. As my
research progressed, I turned my attention
to the stones themselves and the labyrinths,
grooves and cavities that form in them.
There is a special dialectic at work here that
gives each stone an identity of its own. Like
ourselves, stones have a "passport" to the
future. Theirs is the result of a compromise
between their mechanical resistance sand¬
stone, limestone and granite each have their
own and the destructive forces of frost,
humidity and geochemical agents. As in
human societies, there are various forms of
compromise: for a particular stone to last for
millions of years it protects itself by com¬
promising as to its shape triangular or
oblong or its size, creating what we call an
ecosystem. I took systematic measurements
to verify this balance, from top to bottom of
the scree-slopes, first in the Sahara, among
the Tuareg, then among my friends the Inuit
in northern Greenland, and found that if a
single factor, humidity or temperature,
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
varied, however slightly, the compromise
was disrupted and the process of finding
the right balance had to start again.
The Inuit realized rather early that their
understanding of the world began with
stones. My debt to them is incalculable:
they have an exceptional ability to read
nature's book. The fact that their five senses
are, through constant use, far more acute
than ours they can see in the dark means
that they can observe the world around
them very closely. Learning from these great
teachers, I gradually came to transfer my
attention from stones to human beings.
We have a lot to learn about teaching
from these peoples who for ten thousand
years have been bringing up their children
naturally, in a way very different from ours.
They have no books and believe in chil¬
dren and adolescents learning by doing and
by example, which is how they taught me.
Bringing up children is, after all, "raising"
them, awakening their self-awareness
through the encounter of one culture with
another, seeking out hidden wonders and
discovering the genius loci.
So you were gradually introduced by
the physical ecosystem to the social
ecosystem?
The Inuit were a people without a written
language, so they had no Homer, Mon¬
tesquieu or Rousseau, yet they have estab¬
lished a social contract that would have fas¬
cinated Lenin. At the level of small groups
of fifty to a hundred families, theirs is a
communist, a truly egalitarian society, where
everything is shared. There are no social
classes because they want to prevent any
accumulation ofwealth, and land and prop¬
erty belong to the group. They even try to
pool their thoughts: the first duty of Inuit
when they meet is, as in any nomadic society
for that matter, to converse and tell each
other what they have been doing. Even
families are affected: a ritual exchange of
men and women takes place at certain times
of the year, not only to cement relations
among members of the group but also to
prevent a particular man becoming the
master of his companion, or vice versa. One
child in three is handed over to a family
that is not consanguineous. Children are
the children of the group. But at the same
time this is an anarchist society that rejects
the state.
In addition to this social contract, which
is concerned with the organization of per¬
sons and property, this society has a broad
religious vision, shamanism, centred on the
balance between man and nature, a vision
that is not limited to the immediate envi¬
ronment but opens upwards to embrace
the cosmos earth, moon, sun and stars
in a profound understanding. The shaman
is convinced that the world is held in balance
and that due respect must be paid to certain
age-old taboos whose meaning is wrapped
in mystery but which obey their own
.underlying logic. As to reading nature's
great book, it was by first studying stones
that I discovered an invaluable key to deci¬
phering it.
H How does aperson become a shaman?
The shaman starts out by subjecting him¬
self to sexual and dietary asceticism. When
he thinks that his education has gone far
enough, he goes to a high point, a cliff facing
the sun that is riven with fractures that put
it in contact with earth-forces, like the
Pythia of Delphi in ancient Greece. He
stands there facing the sun and takes a rock
which he rubs against another, for hours,
days, weeks or months until the moment
comes when he reaches a state of spiritual
ecstasy. Sometimes nothing happens in the
first year. He may come back again and
again, until ecstasy takes place. He knows
this is happening when he becomes two
entities. He sees his body break up, his skin
comes off, his bones are laid out on the
ground before him! Reconstituted in the
form of a bear or a walrus, he sees himself as
a bear and hears himself talking like a bear.
But there is a great danger that he will be
unable to return, to recover his human state.
Inuit art is obsessed by this anguish which
is depicted in many sculptures of figures
that are half-human, half-animal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The idea of metamorphosis is undoubt¬
edly a very important component of human
thought, as in the return to the unity of the
sexes, in which male and female are one.
This great aspiration is often depicted by
small androgynous statuettes. In some cases
shamanistic initiation involves homosexu¬
ality, as it does in other traditional societies,
notably among Amerindians.
Which otherpeoples haveyou studiedat
close quarters?
I have been carrying out research for the
last forty years in northern Greenland but
I have also been many times on mission to
northeastern Canada Hudson's Bay and
Baffin Land, to the central Arctic regions of
Canada and the Alaskan societies of the
Bering Strait area (Saint Lawrence Island).
The island of Ittygran
in the Siberian Far North, an Inuit
sanctuary since the 1 3th century.
I have lately turned my attention to
northern Siberia. For forty years the Soviet
government prevented me and all West¬
erners from going there. Then in 1989 I
learned, through one of Mr Gorbachev's
advisers, that I was being offered, in com¬
pensation for all those years lost to research,
the chairmanship of the "Committee for
the Defence of the Arctic Peoples of Russia"
that had been set up under the Russian Cul¬
tural Fund, at present chaired by Nikita
Mikhailov. I was at last to have an oppor¬
tunity to visit the cradle of the Inuit people,
born on those shores at the time of its migra¬
tion from Asia towards Alaska.
An international expedition, the first
since the October Revolution, went out
there in 1990, with myself as scientific
director. I have carried out thirty-one mis¬
sions to the Arctic and this was one of the
most fruitful of my career. It enabled me to
visit a site of outstanding historical signifi¬
cance, the island of Ittygran, the Carnac of
the Arctic, which was hidden from the eyes
of the world by the Soviet authorities until
1976, when it was studied by the distin¬
guished archaeologist Sergei Arutiunov. I
was the first Westerner to set foot there. It
is a small island, lying offshore to the north
of a hunters' village, silent, deserted, with
eagles circling overhead. Great spears point
skywards and the skulls and jawbones of
whales are set in lines along the shore.
From the thirteenth century onwards,
groups of Inuit hunters came here to per¬
form sacrificial rites in a state of mystical
exaltation. The most interesting feature of
the site is undoubtedly the numerical rela¬
tionship that forms the basis for the align¬
ment of fifteen groups of enormous whale
jawbones, some weighing nearly 600 kilo¬
grams: the alignment follows a strict 2:4
alternation that refers back to the logical
structures of the most ancient Chinese book
of divination.
While investigating the stones on the
island and checking their orientations
against the map, I came upon a grave, a
recent grave containing the remains of a
Soviet Inuit hunter with a comb and a rifle
by his side. These peoples have remained, at
least in their innermost being, impervious to
seventy years of indoctrination in dialectical
materialism. The four batteries of psycho
logical tests that I carried out provided evi¬
dence, when they were analysed by Marie-
Rose Moro and Tobie Nathan, of their rich
imaginary world dominated by the Relet, or
spirits, despite the fact that the Soviet gov¬
ernment had banned the shamans, or at least
banned them from practising shamanism.
Was the Soviet system totally negative in
this respect?
No. It has to be admitted that, concerning
the Arctic regions, not everything about it
was bad. A market economy would have
been, and would still be, disastrous for tra¬
ditional societies. Protected until now by a
policy of guaranteed prices, the hunters and
herdsmen of- northern Siberia have man¬
aged to preserve their way of living and sub¬
sisting. By being kept out of the mainstream
they have been spared the frightful media-
borne contamination and other catastrophic
influences that our so-called "advanced"
civilization brings in its train. They have
escaped the ravages of drugs that could dec¬
imate the peoples of Alaska, as smallpox
and diphtheria decimated the Amerindian
populations in the eighteenth century. They
have also been preserved from Aids, a ter¬
rible threat to these traditional societies,
whose relatively open-minded attitude to
sex and to addiction to alcohol makes them
particularly vulnerable.
In addition to the obvious mistake
made by the Soviet authorities in trying to
impose atheism upon the societies of
northern Siberia, whose identity is based
on a cosmic, religious vision, they also
made the mistake of not forming a cadre of
trained specialists from among these peo¬
ples who, since they were granted
autonomy in 1926, were supposed to run
their own affairs. I accordingly impressed
upon the authorities that they should, as a
matter of urgency, make it their business to
form such a local elite.
You were recently appointedPresident of
the Saint Petersburg PolarAcademy. . . .
A staff college for the peoples of the north
was set up in Saint Petersburg under the
aegis of the Russian Ministry of Education,
the Ministry of National Minorities and
Regional Policy, and the government of the
Sakha Republic, and on my initiative. On 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
January 1994, it was transformed, in the
course of a solemn ceremony at the cele¬
brated Russian Geographical Society, into
the Polar Academy. The authorities asked
me to be its president, and I was honoured
to accept. The Academy has a staff of sixty
Russian teachers, the cream of Saint Peters¬
burg's academic community, plus ten French
experts whose places will in due course be
taken by other European or American
teachers. French is the first foreign language
and is compulsory. Our aim is to help the
twenty-six ethnic groups of northern Siberia
- to take charge of their own administration.
I have given the Russian authorities my
personal undertaking to train, in two-year
courses, candidates selected by their respec¬
tive autonomous regions. We have at present
thirty students, aged around thirty, on each
course. The celebrated Paris Ecole nationale
d'administration is sponsoring us, and other
leading French educational institutions are
participating in the teaching activities, with
the Ecole des Hautes études en sciences
sociales and the Centre of Arctic Studies
being responsible for overall co-ordination.
As we would like to launch a daily paper for
the far north, Le Monde diplomatique, the
international affairs supplement of Le
Monde newspaper, is also taking part in the
project, and I have every hope that UNESCO
will join in this undertaking, which is very
much in its line of action.
For the time being, the trainees have to
travel to Saint Petersburg, but it has been
decided that a nomadic school will be set up.
This means that every two years the
Academy will send out a team comprising
the year's top five students and their Russian
and French teachers, all of whom will be on
the same footing. The Sakha Republic will
select a specific area of its territory for global
study, covering environment, medicine,
ethnography, education and the economy.
The Sakha Republic was chosen as being the
most advanced of the northern republics.
Teachers and students alike will be billetted
with the local inhabitants and with the rein¬
deer herdsmen and will have to enjoy the
cold. As I know these societies well, I am
convinced that the teaching will have an
infinitely greater impact by being integrated
in this way into their lives. As happened to
the geographer Arsenev in Kurosawa's great
film Derzou Ouzala, shot in Siberia, the
learner on his home ground will become
the teacher.
How do you explain thefact that these
peoples, who are obviously fascinated by
our modem civilization since they want to
be incorporated into it, are not afraid of
losing their authenticity and their specific
values?
They want to go down the road of devel¬
opment because of the deal they are being
offered nice houses with television, city
lights and so on without being told they
will have to pay for these amenities and
without necessarily having the means to do
so. What is more, we descend on these soci¬
eties in the role of conquerors with our tech¬
nology, our cars and aircraft. We are well fed
and well equipped, we've made it! And
above all we come proclaiming aloud that we
are going to help them, whereas in fact we are
only looking out for new markets.
This is where it seemed to me there was
an urgent need to step in. The north Amer¬
ican Indians and the peoples of northern
Siberia must be made fully aware that the
deal they are being offered is a swindle
whereby they will lose out completely. After
losing their religion, their culture and their
language they will lose their very selves.
You surely wouldn 'tpropose a system of
complete self-sufficiency.
Traditional societies should move for¬
ward at their own pace, which is not our
pace; they should not go for abrupt change
but for a slow, considered evolution so that
they can take the best, not the worst, of
what our Western civilization has to offer.
Like the physical world, the history of
traditional societies has its own biological
clock. We should help, as honestly as we can,
to train the new elites so that they can
choose for themselves, so that they can
weigh the pros and cons of what is on offer.
We should help these societies to an aware¬
ness of this. In order to do so we should, as
a matter of priority, help them to train
people who are capable of taking or leaving,
in full knowledge of the issues, what we
offer them.
Intellectuals, men of goodwill with no
vested interests in the market, must help
these people to understand and thwart our
most subtle commercial machinations. By
doing this we also defend our own long-
term interests. If we continue to exploit
them by pretending to help them, then
sooner or later there will be a a terrifying
revolt, perhaps even involving atomic
weapons. We have an intellectual duty to act
in such a way that our industrial societies
cease to blindly export their pseudo-devel¬
opment, as they have done to Africa, with
catastrophic results. Too many ruling-class
Africans imitate us and despise their peas¬
antry, rural people migrate to the cities to
become functionaries think of places like
Dakar and Nouakchott the creatures of a
parasitic state dependent on the West. That
is what is called neo-colonialism. They are
not trustworthy representatives of their
societies, but joke figures who will one day
wreak horrible vengeance.
Cadres belonging to indigenous peo¬
ples must be trained as a matter of urgency,
throughout the world.
In the Siberian Arctic, the situation is
already alarming, what with leaking oil
pipelines and nuclear pollution by the armed
forces. This is an international problem, we
are all concerned. Siberia is so vast that it
influences the Arctic Ocean, at the top of the
world, where climatic development is
shaped. And who are the guardians of these
waters if not the indigenous people, who
have a vocation for ecology? Because of
our obsession with short-term profits we
cannot see the wood for the trees. Those
whom the gods wish to destroy they first
make mad!
If it proved impossible to avoid pollu¬
tion at the time of economic planning (Gos-
plan), what shall we do to prevent it when
American and European companies flock to
the Far North? Do we want to ruin the Far
North in the same way as Amazonia? That
is another reason for training the indige¬
nous people so that they can see all these
dangers, decide what to do, and take their
future in hand.
And let's be quite clear about this. We
shan't be teaching them to defend their
future out of generosity or charity. By pro¬
tecting them we protect ourselves; we
defend our own future on an earth that will
at long last be human.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
;
MODERN MANAGEMENT AMD
LOCAL TRADITIONS
by
Philippe d'lribarne
The actor Sakata Hangoro III
in the role of a warrior,
Japanese print by Katsukawa
Shunei (1762-1819).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
B
USINESS firms, especially big industrial
firms, are held up as a model of ratio¬
nality and organization. Many countries
where "traditional" cultures still prevail look to
them to play a catalytic role in bringing about
change and to challenge social practices that are
looked down upon as archaic; they are sup¬
posed to be a force for modernization, not only
of technology but of mentalities and forms of
organization.
Credibility is lent to this view by the exis¬
tence of international management methods,
developed in the industrialized countries, which
countries with less efficient economies are urged
to adopt if they want their business organiza¬
tions to become competitive. These methods
are publicized by books on management, "busi¬
ness schools", certain management consultants
and major institutions like the World Bank and
the transnationals.
It might be supposed, looking at things this
way, that there was a standoff between some
universally valid organizational principle, rep¬
resented by the "right" management methods,
on the one hand, and, on the other, a host of spe¬
cific traditions, each expressing specific preju¬
dices, that need to be overcome if the highest
levels of productivity are to be reached.
Reality is, however, obstinately at odds with
this view. Japan has scored great economic suc¬
cesses while managing its businesses in its own
particular way. American companies, long held
up as a model of efficient, rational management,
are now criticized for "short-termism" and
over-compartmentalization, and the difficulty
they have in making the necessary improve¬
ments seems to be linked to certain cultural
characteristics peculiar to the United States.
Yet methods everywhere have been inspired
by the American model. When consultants go
off to far-flung corners of the planet to suggest
remedies for ailing businesses, they come up
with the same answers: explicit job descrip¬
tions, clearly formulated objectives and a free
choice of the means for attaining them, quan¬
tifiable criteria for assessing performance, and
performance-related rewards and sanctions.
These management methods do produce
results relatively objective assessment criteria
are an incentive to work rather than to suck up
to one's superiors, and the exercise of setting
objectives provides a good opportunity to think
problems through and find solutions to them
but they also have limitations. As a result of
undue emphasis on the tangible, certain factors
may be overlooked which, though subtle, con¬
tribute to the successful functioning of a business
organization goodwill gestures that create a
good atmosphere and make for co-operation,
informal aspects of customer service, and so on.
The cult of specific objectives, clear-cut
responsibilities and quantifiable results is in fact
the outgrowth of a particular political culture. In
the American political tradition, any form of
arbitrary power is viewed as creating servitude,
and such arbitrary power is held strictly in check
by the labour contract. John Locke, in his
famous Two Treatises of Government (1690),
thus evokes the "freeman" who "makes himself
a servant to another by selling him for a certain
time the service he undertakes to do in return for
wages", but gives his employer only "a tempo¬
rary power over him, and no greater than what
is contained in the contract between them", as
opposed to "slaves", who are "subjected to the
absolute dominion and arbitrary power" of
their masters. In the United States today, the
contract binding superior to subordinate in the
IO
Metalworkers, France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
same way as a contract between buyer and seller
still acts as a safeguard to the relationship
between free individuals under the rule of law.
The French "feudal" model
This is by no means a universal model, and to
prove it one need look no further than a European
country like France. The French example is all the
more convincing in that France, like the United
States, proclaims its devotion to universal values
and considers itself, regardless of any cultural
specificity, to be the birthplace of human rights.
The rejection of servitude, in a relationship
of subordination to a business firm, is just as
forceful in France as in the United States, but it
takes different forms and gives rise to different
modes of organization. As long ago as the Middle
Ages, whereas in England the relationship between
free men was governed by contract, feudal alle¬
giance to an overlord was the rule in France. The
French thought certain forms of personal loyalty
and allegiance compatible with freeman status
while to the English they may have smacked of
servitude. This allegiance was, however, primarily
a way of showing respect for the privileges vested
by custom in a noble office, not servility, and this
attachment to the nobility of a certain estate
nowadays of a certain occupation and to both its
prerogatives and its obligations has impacted pro¬
foundly on the modern French business world.
The concatenation of contractual buyer-seller
relationships that is the order of the day in Amer¬
ican corporations is nowhere to be found in French
businesses, where the general rule is for informal
relations among occupational groups passion¬
ately attached to the rights and duties associated
with their work. The same individuals who are so
keen to "do a good job", professionally speaking,
are equally hesitant about carrying out any orders
from above that they see as damaging to their tra¬
ditions, and the external show of respect for supe¬
riors that often results in France being ranked
among the countries with a strongly hierarchical
structure goes hand-in-hand with a high degree of
independence in the performance of the func¬
tions that each considers to be his or her own.
Combining the rational and the
traditional
There is a common tendency to contrast what arc
supposed to be strictly rational organizational
methods with what are described as purely tra¬
ditional forms of behaviour, but in point of fact
any efficient organization, in whatever cultural
context, is both rational and traditional.
Business management presupposes the estab¬
lishment of a set of structures and procedures
for ensuring the division and co-ordination of
labour. This demands a deliberate effort at rational
organization directed towards the goal of effi¬
ciency. The desired results will not, however, be
forthcoming unless the behaviour expected of
the staff is in keeping with their sense of duty and
their idea of authority and of respect for their own
dignity matters that bear the strong imprint of
tradition.
The relationship thus created between ratio¬
nally designed structures and procedures on the
one hand and, on the other, local traditions is
one of synergy, not competition. Tradition alone
is powerless unless it is given expression in struc¬
tures and procedures, whilst it is only in the light
of tradition that the latter make sense in a way that
makes it possible for them to be imposed and
respected. The headway made in correlating these
two factors and adapting them to different cul¬
tural contexts has so far been uneven.
Every industrial country has its own man¬
agement tradition, often handed down in the
form of local practices or of skills transmitted by
word of mouth rather than in theoretical works.
This tradition reflects the adaptation of a long-
established cultural background to the needs of
a modern economy. Built up gradually as the
economy itself is built up, it is constantly being
enriched, propelled by its own dynamics, or rein¬
terpreting and then assimilating practices that
have proved effective elsewhere.
In countries where they have generally been
introduced from abroad, modern business orga¬
nizations have brought with them methods often
ill adapted to the local context, and the low level
of success obtained by these methods is usually
attributed to those countries' inability to run a
modern economy, for which radical cultural
changes are reputed to be necessary. Fortunately,
there is little basis for this view, and the few
efforts that have been made too seldom, alas
to reconcile rational organization with tradition
have produced many promising results as the
present issue of the UNESCO Courier sets out to
show.
r\ Swiss watchmaker, heir
to a tradition of
craftsmanship over 300
years old.
PHILIPPE D'IRIBARNE,
of France, is director of
research at France's National
Centre for Scientific Research
(CNRS). He has carried out
comparative studies of
business management systems
in different countries and the
relations between principles of
rational organization and local
traditions. He is the author of
Le chômage paradoxal (PUF
publishers, Paris, 1990) and La
logique de l'honneur (Point-Seuil,
Paris, 1993).
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Business cultures by Geert Hofstede
Every organization has its symbols, rituals and heroes
n
ANAGEMENT means getting things done
through (other) people. This is true the
world over. In order to achieve this,
one has to know what needs to be done and
one has to know the people involved. Under¬
standing people means understanding their
background, from which their present and future
behaviour can be predicted.
Their background has provided them with a
certain culture, the word culture being used in
the sense of "the collective programming of the
mind which distinguishes the members of one
category of people from another". The "category
of people" may be a nation, a region or an ethnic
group, women or men (gender culture), old or
young (age group and generation culture), a
Ljn am JTJk w~*
L3H MM UIU LJLÍ UT.ll bCil
UU 1^ 1>«4 bfM '£V
MM MM tftt \SM 113
12
An office building in
Tokyo.
U MM Hri rtu Ulm yJ-1
MM MM WW UBM WT\
mm ¡orara mm .jm
mmmmmmmm'
msüí tarf yir ¡nsr
MU
s=
social class, a profession or occupation (occu¬
pational culture), a type of business, a work
organization or part of it (organizational cul¬
ture), or even a family.
Culture is composed of many elements,
which may be classified in four categories: sym¬
bols, heroes, rituals and values.
Symbols are words, objects and gestures
which derive their meaning from convention. At
the level of national cultures, symbols include
the entire area of language. At the level of orga¬
nizational culture, symbols include abbrevia¬
tions, slang, modes of address, dress codes and
status symbols, all recognized by insiders only.
Heroes are real or imaginary people, dead or
alive, who serve as models for behaviour within
a culture. Selection processes are often based
on hero models of "the ideal employee" or "the
ideal manager". Founders of organizations
sometimes become mythical heroes later on,
and incredible deeds are ascribed to them.
Rituals are collective activities that are tech¬
nically superfluous but, within a particular cul¬
ture, socially essential. In organizations they
include not only celebrations but also many
formal activities defended on apparently rational
grounds: meetings, the writing of memos, and
planning systems, plus the informal ways in
which formal activities are performed: who can
afford to be late for what meeting, who speaks
to whom, and so on.
Values represent the deepest level of a culture.
They are broad feelings, often unconscious and
not open to discussion, about what is good and
what is bad, clean or dirty, beautiful or ugly,
rational or irrational, normal or abnormal, nat¬
ural or paradoxical, decent or indecent. These
feelings are present in the majority of the mem¬
bers of the culture, or at least in those persons
who occupy pivotal positions.
Nationality (and gender as well) is an invol¬
untary attribute; we are born within a family
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
"rounders of
organizations sometimes
become mythical heroes
later on and incredible
deeds are ascribed to
them." Above, head of
Zeus (plaster cast,
anonymous).
within a nation, and are subject to the mental pro¬
gramming of its culture from birth. Here we
acquire most of our basic values. Occupational
choice is partly voluntary (dependent on the
society and family); it leads to choice of schools,
and at school we are socialized to the values and
the practices of our chosen occupation.
When we enter a work environment, we are
usually young or not-so-young adults, with
most of our values firmly entrenched, but we
will become socialized to the practices of our
new work environment. National cultures,
therefore, differ mostly at the level of basic
values, while occupational and, even more, orga¬
nizational cultures differ more superficially (in
their symbols, heroes and rituals).
National culture differences
Results from a number of research projects have
led me to classify national cultures along five
dimensions. The first four were found by com¬
paring the values of employees and managers in
fifty-three different national subsidiaries of the
IBM Corporation. They have been labelled:
1) Power distance, or the degree of inequality
among people which the population of a country
considers as normal: from relatively equal to
extremely unequal.
2) Individualism, or the degree to which
people in a country have learned to act as indi¬
viduals rather than as members of cohesive
groups: from collectivist to individualist.
3) Masculinity, or the degree to which "mas¬
culine" values like assertiveness, performance,
success and competition prevail over "femi¬
nine" values like the quality of life, maintaining
warm personal relationships, service, caring,
and solidarity: from tender to tough.
4) Uncertainty avoidance, or the degree to
which people in a country prefer structured
over unstructured situations: from relatively
flexible to extremely rigid.
The table on page 14 lists for twenty-five
out of the fifty-three countries studied the scores
for these dimensions (the table also contains a
fifth dimension that will be explained later). All
scores are relative: the scales have been chosen
so that the distance between the lowest and
highest scoring country on each dimension is
about 100 points.
The table shows that European countries 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
vary widely on all four dimensions. Power dis¬
tances are large in France and Portugal; collec¬
tivism prevails over individualism in Portugal
and Greece; Austria and Italy are very masculine,
while Sweden and the Netherlands arc very
feminine; Belgium and France are uncertainty-
avoiding, while Denmark and the United
Kingdom easily accept uncertainty.
All these differences affect ways of manage¬
ment in these countries. Large power distances
favour centralization, while small power dis¬
tances favour decentralization. Collectivism
favours group rewards and family enterprises,
while individualism favours easy job-hopping
and individual rewards. Masculinity favours com¬
petition and survival of the fittest while femi¬
ninity favours solidarity and sympathy for the
weak. Uncertainty avoidance favours strict rules
and principles, while its opposite favours oppor¬
tunism and tolerance of deviant behaviour.
The fifth dimension
In subsequent research, a fifth dimension of
national culture differences has been found.
Professor Michael H. Bond of the Chinese Uni
versity of Hong Kong studied value differences
among students in twenty-three different coun¬
tries using a questionnaire originally designed in
the Chinese language by Chinese scholars.
Analysis of the data produced four dimensions,
three of them very similar to three of the IBM
dimensions (all except uncertainty avoidance),
the fourth entirely new and very meaningful.
This fifth dimension was called "long-term
orientation" (LTO) as against "short-term ori¬
entation". Values positively rated in LTO are
thrift and perseverance; values negatively related
are respect for tradition, and fulfilling social
expectations, "keeping up with the Joneses".
The last column in the table lists the LTO
scores by country, this time based on the data
collected by Bond. The highest scores on the
fifth dimension are all found in East Asian coun¬
tries: Hong Kong, Taiwan, Japan. As these are
also the countries with the world's fastest rates
of economic growth in the past twenty-five
years, we can say that long-term orientation is
strongly related to recent economic growth.
Not only values and practices, but even the¬
ories are products of culturally determined
socialization. This has far-reaching consequences
14
Country
Austria
Score for 25 countries on 5 dimensions of national values
Ranks: I = highest, 53 = lowest (for L.T. Orientation, 20 = lowest)
Power distance Individualism Masculinity
Uncertainty
avoidance
Long term
orientation
Index
(PDI)
II
Rank
53
Index
(IDV)
55
Rank
18
Index
(MAS)
79
Index
(UAI)
70 24-25
INDEX
(LTO)
Belgium 65 20 75 8 54 22 94 5-6
Brazil 69 14 38 26-27 49 27 76 21-22 65 5
Denmark 18 51 74 9 16 50 23 51
Finland 33 46 63 17 26 47 59 31-32
France 68 15-16 71 10-11 43 35-36 86 10-15
Germany 35 42-44 67 15 66 9-10 65 29 31 11-12
Greece 60 27-28 35 30 57 18-19 112 1
Hong Kong 68 15-16 25 37 57 18-19 29 49-50 96 1
India 77 10-11 48 21 56 20-21 40 45 61 6
Ireland 28 49 70 12 68 7-8 35 47-48
Israel 13 52 54 19 47 29 81 19
Italy 50 34 76 7 70 4-5 75 23
Japan 54 33 46 22-23 95 1 92 7 80 3
Mexico 81 5-6 30 32 69 6 82 18
Netherlands 38 40 80 4-5 14 51 53 35 44 9
Norway 31 47-48 69 13 8 52 50 38
Portugal 63 24-25 27 33-35 31 45 104 2
Spain 57 31 51 20 42 37-38 86 10-15
Sweden 31 47-48 71 10-11 5 52 29 49-50 33 10
Switzerland 34 45 68 14 70 4-5 58 33
Taiwan 58 29-30 17 44 45 32-33 69 26 87 2
Turkey 66 18-19 37 28 45 31-33 85 16-17
United Kingdom 35 42-44 89 3 66 9-10 35 47-48 25 15-16
U.S.A. 40 38 91 1 62 15 46 43 29 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
for management training in a multicultural orga¬
nization. Not only our techniques but even the
categories in which we think may be unfit for a
different environment.
Organizational cultures
Research data on differences in organizational
cultures within a given country were collected
in 1985 and 1986 in twenty work organizations
or parts of organizations in Denmark and the
Netherlands. The units studied varied from a toy
company to two municipal police forces.
Analysis of the data showed large differ¬
ences between units in symbols, heroes and rit¬
uals (we labelled the three together "practices"),
but only modest differences in values. Different
organizations within the same countries can
maintain very different practices on the basis of
fairly similar employee values.
Six independent dimensions made it pos¬
sible to describe the larger part of the variety in
organizational practices:
1) Process-oriented as opposed to results-
oriented units, the former being dominated by
technical and bureaucratic routines, the latter by
"Individualism favours
easy job-hopping and
individual rewards."
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
"Employee values have
been developed in the
family and the school. . . .
The workplace can only
change people's values to a
limited extent."
16
GEERT HOFSTEDE,
of the Netherlands, taught
organizational anthropology
and international management
at the University of Limburg,
Maastricht, before becoming
the first director of the
Institute for Research on
International Co-operation
(IRIC). His most recent book is
Cultures and Organizations:
Software of the Mind (McGraw
Hill, London, 1991).
a concern for outcomes. This dimension was
associated with the degree of homogeneity of the
unit's culture: in results-oriented units, every¬
body perceived their practices in about the same
way; in process-oriented units, there were vast
differences in perception within the unit. We
consider the homogeneity of a culture as a mea¬
sure of its "strength"; strong cultures are more
results-oriented than weak ones, and vice versa.
2)Job-oriented as opposed to employee-ori¬
ented units. Job-oriented cultures assume
responsibility for the employees' job perfor¬
mance only, and nothing more; employee-ori¬
ented cultures assume a broader responsibility
for their members' well-being. A unit's posi¬
tion on this dimension seems to be largely the
result of historical factors, such as the philos¬
ophy of its founder(s) and the presence or
absence in its recent history of economic crises
with collective layoffs.
3) Professional as opposed toparochial units.
In the former, the (usually highly educated)
members identify primarily with their profes¬
sion; in the latter, the members derive their iden¬
tity from the organization for which they work.
4) Open systems as opposed to closed systems.
This dimension refers to the style of internal
and external communication, and to the ease
with which outsiders and newcomers are
admitted.
5) Tight internal control as opposed to loose
internal control. This dimension deals with the
degree of formality and punctuality within the
organization. It is partly a function of the unit's
technology: banks and pharmaceutical compa¬
nies can be expected to show tight control,
research laboratories and advertising agencies
loose control; but even with the same tech¬
nology, units still differ on this dimension.
6) A pragmatic as opposed to a normative
way of dealing with the environment, in partic¬
ular with customers. Service units should be
found towards the pragmatic (flexible) side,
units involved in the application of legal rules
towards the normative (rigid) side, but reality
does not always correspond to this pattern.
According to this research, what a person
has to learn when (s)he joins a work organization
is mainly a matter of practices. Employee values
have been developed in the family and the school;
they play a role in the selection and self-selection
process for the job. The workplace can only
change people's values to a limited extent. In the
popular literature, organization cultures are often
presented as a matter of values. The confusion
arises because this literature does not distinguish
between the values of the founders and leaders
and those of the bulk of employees.
Founders and leaders, on the basis of their
values, create the symbols, the heroes and the rit¬
uals that constitute the daily practices of the
organization's members. However, members
only to a limited extent have to adapt their per¬
sonal values to the organization's needs. A work
organization, as a rule, is not a "total institution"
like a prison or mental hospital. Organizational
cultures according to our data reside at a more
superficial level of mental programming than the
things learned previously in the family and at
school. In spite of their more superficial nature,
organizational cultures are still hard to change
because they have developed into collective
habits. Changing them is a top management
task that should be based on a strategy and a
cost-benefit analysis. Here again there is no
single formula for success.
All statements in this article should be seen
as only "statistically" true: they are common
trends, but individuals may differ from them. '
Within each country there is a wide range of
individuals, and this fact too should be taken into
account in order to manage successfully. How¬
ever, an insight into cultural differences will
prevent us from attributing to an individual's
personality forms of behaviour which are
normal in his or her country, and from trying to
apply supposedly universal success formulas to
people who are not universal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
TOGO ^ Going by the book
A cose of efficiency based on scrupulous observance
of a rule-book that contains echoes of village
traditions
by Alain Henry and Yao Badjo
Above, a motorcycle
assembly line in Burkina
Faso.
IN his account of the 1948 strike on the
Dakar-Niger Railway, the Senegalese writer
and film director Sembene Ousmane recalls
how one of the European supervisors said: "If
ever we go, there'll be nothing left"1. The phrase
has come down to the present day as a kind of
curse. Many people still believe African busi¬
nesses are foredoomed to hopeless inefficiency,
while on the World Bank's reckoning there are
too many foreign experts in Africa.
Should we doubt, as some people do,
whether African cultures are compatible with
industrial modernization? It is by no means
certain that we should, as is shown by the fol¬
lowing example of an African business that is
getting excellent results.
Detailed instructions
The enterprise in question, which we shall call
STAR, is an industrial firm producing and selling
consumer goods manufactured to international
standards. When we visited it, the books were
balanced. The World Bank itself cites it as an
example to be followed, and there is only one
European white-collar worker among its 650
employees. While its success is certainly attrib¬
utable to management style, it is obvious that it
also has a motivated workforce 2.
Visitors curious to know the reasons for this
dynamism are told that there are written rules of
procedure. They are shown manuals that set I J
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
I
Late 1 9th-century photo
of a "medicine man" in
southern Africa.
ALAIN HENRI,
a French civil engineer who
was born in Cameroon, is a
research associate with
France's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS).
His research interests focus on
the modernization of
management in Africa. He is
the author of Tontines et
banques au Cameroun (Karthala
publishers, 1991).
YAO BADjO
¡s a Togolese engineer who was
formerly director general of
the Togolese national water
authority. He is currently with
the infrastructures division of
the West and Central African
Department of the World
Bank.
forth precisely what each employee is supposed
to be doing. Procedures for carrying out main¬
tenance work, making out invoices, stock¬
taking, mailing and even organizing the end-
of-year staff party are covered in surprising
detail. The manuals even specify the frequency
with which such routine tasks as the sending of
telexes should be done. Where necessary, alter¬
native solutions are suggested, and there are
repeated reminders of the need to ensure that
particular points have not been overlooked.
Former employees recall with a smile one of
the first items in these manuals, explaining how
to receive customers and advising that they be
treated "with an iron hand in a velvet glove".
Though less detailed for the upper echelons,
the instructions nevertheless cover every post, up
to that of managing director.
Equally surprising is the interest taken in the
manuals. Supervisors advise their staff to read
them "like novels", and everyone, from shop-
floor level to the boardroom, refers constantly to
them. STAR is thus more fully equipped in this
respect than European firms, most of which have
little if any of such documentation. This codifi¬
cation of working practices may, it is true, be
reminiscent of Taylorism-style "scientific man¬
agement", but with the significant difference that
it emanates from the workforce itself, not from
some outside authority.
It is worth pointing out the influence this
example has had in sub-Saharan Africa. A major
Cameroonian firm, for instance, recently issued
a manual in twelve volumes of about a thousand
pages each, and one of the first steps to be taken
when the Power Company in Côte d'Ivoire
was nationalized was the revision, in collabora¬
tion with the staff, of the rules and regulations.
Respect for the written word
When the manuals were first issued, the
employees of STAR are said to have been satisfied
to "find what part they were required to play".
According to some of the managerial staff, the
object was to "channel behaviour patterns", so
that employees were not "tempted to do the first
thing that came into their heads". Apart from
providing a useful way of learning skills and
passing them on, these manuals thus meet a
widely-felt need and fit in with prevalent ways of
thinking. Those for whom they are intended rely
on them to "safeguard themselves against over¬
sights". Whereas in the Western world an over¬
sight is usually regarded as misconduct, here it is
accepted as part of "human nature". It is only to
be expected that numerous checks and verifica¬
tions should be carried out in order to combat
shortcomings that are tolerated in the social envi¬
ronment but are not allowed in industry.
Staff in enterprises without manuals have a
hard time fending off inadmissible requests from
colleagues. Unless justified by reference to the
rules, a refusal is taken as being "unfriendly",
while, conversely, failure to abide by explicit
instructions is put down to thoroughly repre¬
hensible "shirking" or even "troublemaking".
For the rules to provide this kind of shelter,
however, it must be clear that it is' impossible to
get round them. Their application is therefore
closely monitored and they are observed to the
letter to avoid any charge of subjective inter¬
pretation. The respect thus shown for the
written word gives the lie to certain clichés
about the oral nature of African culture.
Traditional ethics in a modern form
The STAR manuals may be regarded as an adap¬
tation to the world of industry of the precepts by
which village life was traditionally ruled. They
proceed from a social obligation of goodwill,
and enable people to be judged fairly on their
intentions. The administrative officer herein plays
a role comparable with that of the sorccrcr-cum-
healer to whom villagers used to turn to unmask
those who wanted to harm the community: those
found to be "at fault" are given a severe dressing-
down.
Many African tales illustrate the necessity of
understanding a neighbour's ulterior motives,
while other stories set up the figure of the true and
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
borne present-day
management procedures
in Africa recall the rules
that governed traditional
village life (see article).
Below, a village in northern
Cameroon.
faithful friend as a social ideal. Similarly, a good
man is one who can show that his intentions are
good. It therefore seems justifiable to judge indi¬
viduals by what they have accepted to do rather
than by what they have succeeded in doing.
A strange misunderstanding
Considering how effective they are, one would
have expected STAR's methods to have gained
widespread acceptance, but this is not yet the
case. Foreign experts, French in particular, who
have been approached about introducing them are
fairly hesitant, finding it hard to believe that they
could act as an incentive. In their cultural back¬
ground, rules are mainly there to be interpreted,
and they would prefer not to be "straitjacketed"
by pettifogging procedures that seem to them
unlikely to encourage a sense of responsibility.
Africans themselves believe the opposite,
and foreign experts' reluctance is put down to
the fact that it is in their interest to keep their
skills to themselves an explanation reinforced
by recollections of the colonial-era overseers
who carried a notebook around in their pockets
to mark down the settings of all their machines.
It is true that the manuals fulfil something of the
same role as the foreign experts, who are often
called in to validate the "objectivity" of admin¬
istrative decisions, but who, in the belief that
they are showing greater respect for their
African partners, would rather suggest new
management methods than get to grips with
existing procedures. Perhaps unwittingly, they
are thus helping to prolong their own presence.
Efficient local management of businesses is
of the greatest importance for the development
of the African economies. Some experts,
thinking they have found the solution, have
suggested that workers be given individual
objectives against which to be assessed, but in the
African context any criticism bearing upon indi¬
vidual results is seen as a personal attack and
soon causes strongly hostile reactions.
Such imported methods stem from a different
conception of how people work as a group. They
are unsuited to the local mentality and this explains
why they fail, a failure wrongly ascribed to some
inherent shortcoming in the cultures concerned.
It may be easier than it seems to change outlooks:
all that is needed is to bear in mind the specific
characteristics of the host society and to encourage
foreign experts to adapt themselves thereto by
reminding them of the old African saying that "a
foreigner is a baby who needs to let himself be cos-
setted and trained".
1. Sembene Ousmane, Les bouts de bois de Dieu, Le
Livre contemporain, 1960, Presse Pocket, Paris.
2. For a detailed case study of this business, see "Vers
un modèle du management africain", by A. Henry, in
Cahiers d'études africaines, 124, XXXI-4, 1991 .
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
TUNISIA t/ They do ¡t their way
Sometimes the most efficient management style is to take things as they come
by Riadh Zgbal
N
f\ chemical factory in
Qafsa, a part of Tunisia
that is rich in phosphates.
Y father always told me: 'When you
work, always remain aziz'l" the
workman we were interviewing began.
Aziz means "dignified", but also has connotations
of pride, independence, self-respect. In other
words, a distinction must be made between
someone who sells his labour for wages and
someone who sells himself, between the labour of
a free man and that of a slave. Popular culture,
however, equates paid employment with servi¬
tude, as these proverbs attest: "The olive tree is
wealth; work in the service of men is degrada¬
tion", "Only destitution drives a free man to
work for a free man", and "A man who works
under the orders of another is a dying man".
20
Other sayings speak of the need to keep one's dig¬
nity at any price: "Better to die than suffer humil¬
iation" and "Suffer hunger rather than accept
kindness from someone who will later remind
you of your debt".
This rejection of working for others has
roots in the religion itself, which recognizes no
intermediary between Allah and man. The
Qur'an glorifies the brotherhood of believers
and extols justice, an implicit warning to the
strong to deal fairly with the weak. Belief in
the worth of the human person and equality
before God is moral compensation for the
downtrodden.
"Woolliness" in the workplace
This conception of man in the workplace reveals
a fundamental contradiction: on the one hand,
the cruel realities of a human society made up of
rich and poor, of nobles and commoners, of
scholars and the unschooled, where to work in
the service of others is for most people a neces¬
sity; on the other hand, a belief in the equality of
all and the need to safeguard one's dignity while
working for others. How can this dilemma be
resolved?
One possible response is resignation, under¬
pinned by a belief in fate, mektub that which
is written, the path God traces for each of us.
Another possibility is to draw a line between
working time and time spent outside work, thus
maintaining at least a semblance of indepen¬
dence.
A third response consists of looking to pater¬
nalism to provide a counterweight to the theo¬
retically humiliating state of being a subordinate.
In the framework of a paternalistic relationship,
the subordinate looks up to his superiors, wishing
to see his interests, even outside the workplace,
defended by the hierarchy. He places feelings
above the objective definition of individual rights
and duties. This primacy of emotional responses
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Festivities in Tatouine,
southern Tunisia.
gives rise to a charismatic style in the exercise of
authority and makes for situations that are not
cut-and-dried.
Organizations usually put down markers of
some kind so that their members know where
they stand and can predict the behaviour of
others. What we have observed in the Tunisian
workplace is a certain reluctance to formulate
precise rules for dealing with particular prob¬
lems. Where rules have to be established, they
are left deliberately ambiguous and lend them¬
selves to diverse interpretations. Individual
responsibilities are loosely or poorly defined,
and when a discussion is opened on a specific
question, it is often suspended without a clear
decision being taken.
This "woolliness" is not confined to the
workplace; it also manifests itself in ordinary life.
In a changing society where traditional values are
continuously being questioned, uncertainty pre¬
dominates when any new situation arises.
Landmarks in an uncertain world
This indeterminacy, associated with paternalism,
gives rise to a strong attachment to interper¬
sonal relationships and to social allegiances. The
active networks of solidarity that grow up
between individuals belonging to the same
family, region, school or even workplace provide
some landmarks in an uncertain world.
In short, to understand the behaviour of the
Tunisian worker, one must bear in mind a whole
range of cultural factors: attachment to the values
of equality and dignity, the role of paternalism as
a regulator in situations where inequality is
inevitable, the absence of regulations, indetermi¬
nacy and the importance of relationships based on
membership of social groups. Taken individu¬
ally, each of these factors is found in other cultures,
but this particular combination of cultural para¬
meters is what distinguishes the Tunisian case.
Going against this cultural profile can disrupt
the smooth operation of a business organiza¬
tion. In Tunisian businesses administered in a
bureaucratic fashion (i.e. with a formal hierarchy
and impersonal authority based on a set of rules
and competence), we found many cases of atti¬
tudes that are hardly conducive to efficiency.
The workers are disinclined to work because of
the influence real or imagined of personal
relationships on career prospects. The super¬
visor is judged, not on his competence, but on his
friendliness and courtesy. His authority may 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
I he town of Kairouan,
huddled around the
9th-century Great Mosque.
be undermined if he does not come from the
same social group as his subordinates, and the
absence of well-defined procedures, coupled
with the feeling that paid employment is undig¬
nified, invalidates that authority.
22
A minimum of regulations
On the other hand, a business which takes
account of this cultural reality has a better chance
of achieving a relatively satisfactory perfor¬
mance. A comparative study of productivity in
one industrial enterprise brought to our notice
a workshop where an absolute minimum of
regulations paradoxically went together with a
relatively high productivity.
The workers in this factory were unhappy
with their pay they considered their wages
were too low or unfairly distributed but they
were nonetheless concerned about the survival
of the business and were afraid of being dis¬
missed or of being forced to take early retire¬
ment. They were therefore prepared to maintain
a minimum level of productivity without
pushing themselves too hard. This being the
case, one of the supervisors had the idea of
reducing to a minimum the distance between
himself and his workers. He adopted a more
flexible style of management by rotating assign¬
ments: the operator of a certain machine might
be shifted to another or given a manual job to do,
his assistant taking charge of the machine if
need be. This flexibility softens the differences
in status between the workers and reduces
fatigue and boredom by allowing them to share
the unpleasant jobs. It also contributes to the
smooth running of the workshop in the absence
of key personnel. The supervisor himself told us
that the production rate does not slow down
when he is not there.
This system of organization creates a kind
of community in which social and professional
differences are blurred and where productivity
levels, more or less tacitly agreed, are the respon¬
sibility of everyone. Although this does not dispel
the feelings of frustration and injustice many
workers are convinced that they work harder
than their colleagues without getting anything in
return for their extra effort and competence
these aggressive sentiments arc diverted away
from the shop floor towards top management,
which is held responsible for the unfairness of the
wage system, and this helps to keep shop-floor
relations on a fairly even keel.
This shop was considerably more efficient
than the other two shops in the factory, which
were run on more authoritarian lines.
This form of organization of work might
appear to have been inspired by the most
advanced modern management methods, but
what had happened was, basically, that in a con¬
text of general undcr-productivity and in the
absence of an organizational policy, the super¬
visor had simply adapted his management style
to the mentality of his workers, without the
least reference to a theoretical framework.
RIADH ZGHAL,
of Tunisia, is dean of the faculty of economic sciences and
management at the University of Sfax. Among her published
works are an "Introduction to social psychology and
organizational behaviour" (in Arabic, Beirut-Damascus,
1 993) and La culture de la dignité et le flou de l'organisation
(CERP, Tunis, 1993).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
MEXICO Locol loyalties: a hidden asset
by¡eon Ruffier and Daniel Vûlovilnào
A modern factory can run smoothly without a highly skilled workforce
Apprentices being trained
at a car factory in Puebla,
Mexico.
ACCORDING to an idea so widespread that
it has almost become a truism, ultra¬
modern factories that work properly are
only to be found in countries with industrial
experience, high-quality infrastructures, plentiful
capital and a skilled workforce. If accepted, this
idea would mean that the less developed coun¬
tries are inevitably condemned to backward¬
ness, and would commit the world to an increas¬
ingly unfair division of labour and wealth. Yet
companies in various parts of the world are suc¬
cessfully using sophisticated technology without
having a skilled workforce or a strong industrial
background.
Such cases are of course rare. They have also
been very little studied. Many research workers
have investigated the most efficient factories in
Japan, Europe and North America, but their
conclusions are only valid for a limited number
of countries that enjoy similar conditions. In this
article we shall see how a small factory sixty
kilometres from Mexico City has managed to
become highly competitive at producing
yoghurt.
Teething troubles
Beyond an ungated level crossing lies a red-brick
estancia built around a chapel, a relic of past
grandeur. Here a French multinational company
has set up a yoghurt factory not just anywhere
but in the middle of a big cattle farm. This once
had its own milk-packing shop, but it eventually
closed down, and the herd was considerably
reduced. Only a tenth of the milk used to make
the yoghurt comes from the estancia.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
"Amate", a bark painting
by a Mexican folk artist.
24
JEAN RUFFIER,
of France, is a researcher with
the Groupe Lyonnais de
Sociologie Industrielle (GLYSI).
DANIEL V1LLAVICENCIO,
of Mexico, is a teacher and
researcher at the National
Autonomous University of
Mexico, in Mexico City. Like
Jean Ruffier he is a member of
the International Institute for
the Development of
Technologies, which analyses
successful industrial
undertakings in both the
industrialized and the
developing countries. The
present article is based on the
results of a survey carried out
between 1981 and 1984.
The estancia provided some of the factory's
first workers, and the French managers who
came to start it up and instal the automated pro¬
duction lines took great pains to train them.
The factory had, however, been planned and
built as though it were in Europe, and the most
advanced equipment had therefore been selected
for it an ill-considered choice, given that the
factory was one of the first in the group to open
in a country without much of an industrial tra¬
dition. Machines were brought in, and only
then were people recruited to operate them.
The company set about initiating the old dairy's
best workers into the operation of modern plant,
and managed it not very well, but at least the
factory was running.
Then an unforeseen conflict broke out
between the representatives of workers on the
old estancia and the local branch of the food
industry union, which they wanted to leave.
The management was powerless to prevent the
victory of the union, which managed to force it
to dismiss the dissident workers' representa¬
tives. In this way the company lost its most
highly-trained employees, who were in charge
of the most complex parts of its plant.
As a result of these events, which took place
five years after the factory started up, the French
management had to begin recruiting again. It
took on farm workers, recruited from far
enough away to ensure that the coalition that
gave rise to the conflict did not re-form. The fac¬
tory made a new start: it went on installing
machinery, and soon the new manager was its
only French employee. Two years later it ranked
among the most efficient in its group. How did
it become so successful?
A poorly qualified workforce
By and large, the operatives' only work experi¬
ence had been as farm labourers or domestic
servants. To start with, many workers could
neither read nor write. They knew nothing
about the dairy industry, and had never even
seen yoghurt until they arrived in the factory,
which was one of the first in Mexico to make it.
We looked in vain for home-made produce of a
similar kind on the local market. Hence, when
the workers joined the company it was their
first taste both of factory work and also of the
product they were going to make.
In the other factories in the group there are no
illiterate workers, and those who operate the
yoghurt-making equipment have at least some
technical knowledge of food processing and
they have been eating yoghurt since childhood.
In degree of specialization there is the same
contrast. The Mexican factory, though highly
automated, has neither skilled operators nor
electronics engineers. At all levels of its hierarchy
it is short of competent staff, which is hardly sur¬
prising given that the dairy industry is almost
non-existent in Mexico. Nevertheless it works
perfectly, and its yoghurt is renowned for its
quality. It is still highly competitive, even though
it now has to compete with other factories some
of which enjoy preferential treatment that
enables them to purchase milk at subsidized
prices. How does it manage to use state-of-the-
art technology without any of the advantages
that more developed countries have in this
respect?
On the production line, knowledge
is power
The main difficulty for ultramodern companies
stems from the great complexity of their equip¬
ment. Making yoghurt successfully on fully
automated production lines means not only
understanding dairy industry technology but
also having a clear idea about how the equipment
works and where it is located, and about con¬
tainer capacities and the transit time of the
product. It means knowing something about
electronic programming, and being able to trace
and repair mechanical and electronic faults to
say nothing of human error, technical break¬
downs and variations in the quality of the raw
materials, particularly milk.
Nobody is knowledgeable enough to master
all the machinery and production processes
single-handed. Exchange of information is there¬
fore crucial, and this is where things get com-
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A ceremonial meal
during the San Andrés
fiesta in Mexico's Chiapas
state.
plicated. The workmen are not willing to pass on
what they know. A technician who taught all¬
comers what he had learnt, and so enabled them
to operate his piece of machinery, would thereby
become less indispensable. He supposes that
the system could then do without him. Thus the
technicians all try to keep some of their knowl¬
edge to themselves, thereby forcing the others to
bargain for their co-operation.
The dilemma is that if those in charge of
production do not exchange enough informa¬
tion, it is difficult for them to deal with unfore¬
seen production problems. Conversely, if they
do not protect themselves they become inter¬
changeable, and their efforts at self-improve¬
ment in their jobs will never be noticed or
rewarded. Furthermore, interchangeability calls
to mind one of the great bugbears of Mexican
culture: the doppelgänger or double, a malignant
being that can cause confusion and take a
person's place.
There is an obvious contradiction here
between the general interest and that of indi¬
viduals. The workers have everything to gain
from an efficient factory both higher wages
and greater job security so it would be in their
interests to communicate to the fullest extent.
But no one wants to give up all the information
he possesses.
Building up local loyalties
From their first conflict the factory workers
learnt that they were vulnerable and could count
neither on the union (which could turn against
them) nor on the management (which was weak
and could be forced into sackings). Most of
them had given up farm work to go into
industry, thereby boosting their incomes but
losing their place in their traditional society. In
their new jobs they were again in danger of
losing everything, and their only safeguard was
a new form of solidarity, which they were to
build inside the factory, in secret, on the basis of
their own traditions.
There are many different kinds of links
between the workmen. One is the system of
compadres, under which they are committed to
a broadly reciprocal, even-handed interchange
of favours, such as acting as godparents for each
other or each other's children at christenings,
first communions and betrothals. When one of
the compadres helps another to build a house, or
someone else to cope with health problems or
financial difficulties, he does so in the certainty
that in case of need the compadres will not let
him down. Another, still stronger link is that
between cuates or drinking companions, who 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
I erra cotta figurines from
Ocotlán, Oaxaca state,
Mexico.
confide in each other without inhibition, and are
sworn to complete loyalty. The compadres
system is common knowledge, but the network
of cuates is kept a secret.
Sociability inside the factory may also take
other forms, such as family ties and more or
less discreet liaisons. The women a very
tightly-knit group are in general opposed to
these liaisons, which may threaten the cohe-
siveness of their group. These women workers
are of course in a rather special position because
of their financial independence. They enjoy a
degree of independence that they consider
threatened both within the factory, where some
of them are subjected to sexual pressures, and
also outside, where their families try to get them
to resume their traditional role in the home. To
protect their independence they organize a range
of out-of-hours sports and games, from which
men are excluded.
All these networks have contributed greatly
to the technical success of the factory, in par¬
ticular by allowing the workmen to find a place
of their own in the production system.
Group loyalty and human error
In order to explain to us how yoghurt is made
on an industrial scale, a French engineer used
equations; a Mexican workman showed us the
pipes that carry the milk. We cannot say which
was the better explanation: we felt we under¬
stood them both.
The difference between these two approaches
is especially interesting when it comes to
tracking down the cause of a breakdown. The
French engineer will rely on a complete dia¬
gram of the production system, whereas the
Mexican workman will visualize the progress of
the milk in his mind's eye and think what might
have happened at each point in the circuit. His
big handicap is that he is only familiar with part
of the circuit, and so he has to collate his knowl-
26
edge with that of his colleagues. Such exchanges,
which oblige the individual workman to lift a
corner of the veil of mystery on which his
authority in the company is based, are quite
safe when they take place between compadres or
cuates, whose solidarity is total. In other words,
membership of a solidarity network makes it
possible to play the production game with less
risk.
The example of human error is particularly
telling. Most breakdowns involve a human ele¬
ment a mistake, negligence, or wrong treat¬
ment of a mechanical failure. In order not to have
to admit to his mistake in front of someone
else, the culprit first tries to repair the damage
himself at the risk of compounding the error
and making things worse. To protect himself
from possible punishment, he is tempted to
report the breakdown without mentioning what
he did after it happened, and this makes it far
more difficult to find out what has gone wrong.
By revealing his mistake to comrades who will
not betray him, the workman does his best to
keep production going whilst at the same time
safeguarding his own interests.
Our investigation showed that the solidarity
networks extended over various parts of the fac¬
tory and several levels of its hierarchy. They are
a key factor in the efficiency of the workforce.
These networks also play an important part
in training. Training someone means taking the
risk of being replaced by him, but a learner who
belongs to the same network as his supervisor
will do nothing detrimental to him. The man¬
agement realized that its attempts to get a senior
to train a junior not chosen by himself were
doomed to failure, but it also noticed that the
most skilled workmen surrounded themselves
with assistants. The number of assistants ended
up by becoming a status symbol: with one assis¬
tant you become important, but with two you
have no more need to go on working. Hence, the
number of assistants had to be kept down, but
without doing away with them altogether, so as
not to lose the advantage of the new recruits'
being taught by the old hands.
This tension between imported industrial
methods and local traditions is no doubt the
explanation for the factory's fine performance.
The French management stands for high and
increasing productivity. Meanwhile, the Mexican
solidarity networks facilitate productivity,
although that is not the reason why they exist.
They are quite capable of paralysing production,
if they think that serves their interests. The
management has been able to win their support
by showing itself deeply committed to the suc¬
cess of the firm, whilst at the same time coming
to terms with methods of working that are not
fully under its control. M
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO COURIER -APRIL 1994
m
E NATIONAL MI DI
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
"1 Tational parks are universally
% recognized as places of excep-
1 tional beauty and of major
I importance as regards the flora
- - ' and fauna that countries are
trying to preserve and protect. We
should not, however, underestimate
the threats to which they are
exposed ifwe want to ward off those
threats. The world's first national
park, Yellowstone, was created in
the western United States in 1872, at
the height of the industrial revolu¬
tion. Today, there are more than
8,500 national parks in 120 coun¬
tries, totalling about 850 million
hectares almost three times the
size of India. In the beginning, these
parks, not to be confused with the
biosphere reserves Unesco began
designating in 1971, were above all
places for leisure and meditation,
Above,
Amboseli Park, Kenya.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
TT
E m
Biscuit Basin in
Yellowstone
National Park
(United States),
the world's first
protected site,
established in
1872.
but they are now tending to become
conservation areas. The two pur¬
poses are difficult to reconcile,
insofar as the ever-growing "smoke¬
less industry" of tourism has a
potentially considerable destruc¬
tive impact. It is also becoming
increasingly difficult to find unin¬
habited areas to protect, as the
human population continues to
grow and as agriculture, industry
and urban development take up
more and more space.
A national park, according to the
World Conservation Union (IUCN),
"contains one or more ecosystems
not materially altered by human
activity and it contains fauna, flora,
geomorphological sites, and habi¬
tats of scientific, educational and
recreational interest"; it may also
contain a natural landscape ofgreat
beauty. When creating a park, the
authorities must take steps "to pre¬
vent or eliminate . . . exploitation or
occupation" in the whole area. Visi¬
tors are allowed to enter for "educa¬
tional . . . and recreational purposes".
The purposes so defined are much
more difficult to implement than it
may seem. The first parks were
28
established by coercive means (the
"fences and fines" method), but it
soon became apparent that no bar¬
rier or law could prevent local pop¬
ulations from farming the land,
poaching, cutting down trees or even
practising slash-and-burn cultiva¬
tion methods in order to survive.
Worse still, how could they allow
themselves to be evicted from their
land in order to protect the natural
environment?
DAMAGE AND DESTRUCTION
Such operations sometimes work
well. Brazil's Iguaçu National Park
and the Guastopo park in Venezuela
were emptied of their inhabitants,
and the government compensated
and relocated hundreds of families.
However, the Brazilian government
took the opposite approach in 1961
when it set up the Xingu National
Park and moved in seventeen tribes
whose land had been confiscated.
Some of them took legal action
against the government to reclaim
their former territories because they
could not adapt to the unfamiliar
ecosystems. In 1985, after several
banana plantations in Costa Rica
had been abandoned, 800 unem¬
ployed labourers and their families
invaded the Corcovado National
Park on the Osa Peninsula, and
began prospecting for gold, pol¬
luting the rivers with sediment and
mercury. A court order gave the
police powers to evict them after
they had been indemnified, but no
sooner had they left than other
prospectors arrived, setting off
armed conflicts. At Khao Yai, Thai¬
land, the creation of a 2,200 km2
park led to a bloody battle between
wardens and villagers, with fatalities
on both sides. Despite strict pro¬
tection measures, poaching and tree
cutting continued, with the result
that 5 per cent of the forest has been
destroyed and 5 to 10 per cent has
suffered damage.
The situation in the parks in the
areas ofarmed conflict in west and
central Africa is no better. Gérard
Sournia, director of the French
branch of IUCN, who has spent
many years there, says: "By defini¬
tion sparsely populated in time of
peace, parks and the species that
inhabit them can offer, in time of
war, many advantages not only to
the belligerents but also to the local
people, as zones of incursion or safe
havens, out-of-the-way battlefields
or new sources of supplies and
commodities, such as ivory and
rhino horn, that can be sold to buy
arms, or as land to be used for sub¬
sistence farming there are many
claims on their territory". For thirty
years, international, civil or tribal
wars have been raging in this corner
of the world, and parks in Rwanda,
Zaire, Niger, Senegal, Mali, Mauri¬
tania, Togo and Chad are paying a
high price. Animals are scattered
during the fighting or gunned down
with automatic weapons, as in
Zaire's Virunga National Park and
the Queen Elizabeth National Park
in Uganda. Such disorders, Gérard
Sournia stresses, discourage inter¬
national co-operation and fund-
raising efforts. "In Niger," he writes,
"and more precisely in the Ai'r-
Ténéré region, the Tuareg rebellion,
the taking of hostages among staff
and employees of the reserve (of
whom at least two have lost their
lives), threats against expatriates
and the theft of equipment, espe¬
cially vehicles, have led IUCN,
which heads the project, acting in
accord with the funding sources
and local authorities, to withdraw its
personnel to the capital and sus¬
pend the project". To take another
example, during the 1960s, over 70
per cent of Uganda's tourist busi¬
ness came from its Murchison Falls
Park, and growth rates in tourist
spending reached nearly 25 per cent
per year, but following Idi Amin's
1971 military coup tourism came
to a halt and was even banned two
years later. Visitors are returning
with the new-found political sta¬
bility and are helping the economy
get back on its feet.
TOURISM'S PROS AND CONS
A remarkable document, Industry
andEnvironment, published by the
United Nations Environment Pro¬
gramme (UNEP) in 1992, reveals
that "tourism's share of GNP in, for
instance, Tunisia is 6 per cent, in
Barbados 32 per cent, and in the
Maldives 18 per cent". Tourism is a
major world industry with an
annual investment in capital pro¬
jects ofmore than $400 billion, and
more than 130 million employees
serving over 450 million people trav¬
elling internationally, and ten times
as many travelling domestically. For
some countries, such as Kenya,
tourism is the primary source of
hard currency. In Amboseli National
Park, animals are worth far more
alive than dead: American
researcher David Western estimates
the value of a single lion as a tourist
attraction to be $27,000 a year, while
an elephant herd may be worth as
much as $610,000 per year. On the
other hand, the growing number of
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Iguaçu vehicles tracking cheetahs, a tourist
Falls, Brazil. favourite, has become a threat to
their existence. Another difficulty
is that the land was originally the
territory of the pastoral Masai, who
are aggrieved that, while their tra¬
ditional hunting practices have
been forbidden, they do not share in
tourism's benefits. In Nepal, as the
UNEP study points out, "young men
have virtually ceased to enter the
monasteries ... to become priests,
choosing instead the more lucra¬
tive life working in support of
trekking and climbing expeditions
in the Himalayas". These sherpas
invest the money they make in
building bigger houses, a threat to
forests since they require more fire¬
wood to heat, or they buy more live¬
stock, thereby increasing grazing
impacts.
The situation is different in
developed countries. Some very
beautiful parks, victims oftheir own
success, are literally invaded in the
holiday season. Every summer,
more than 800,000 people visit La
Vanoise National Park in the French
Alps. Some days, its trails are
crowded with thousands of people
looking at the flowers and observing
the wildlife. Elsewhere, the craze
for off-road vehicles four-wheel
drives, all-terrain motorcycles and
mountain bikes is causing irre¬
versible damage to soils. It is not
enough to ban them; ways have to
be found of enforcing the ban. The
problem here is not only one ofedu¬
cating the public, but also of
recruiting, training and paying
enough wardens. In France, there
are between ten and seventy war¬
dens per park, as enthusiastic as
they are badly paid. Theywatch over
the park, help scientists with
research on the flora and fauna, and
provide visitors with information.
In some reserves, they are also in
charge of buildings that house a
system of cameras that allow visi¬
tors, for example, to engage in bird-
watching without disturbing the
birds. In such cases, the park has
only one purpose, to protect a nat¬
ural environment to which humans
are not allowed access. In the same
vein, some "conservationists" have
suggested that parks reduce to
between 2 and 3 per cent the area
open to the public, and set up a
scaled-down reproduction of the
parks' most spectacular landscapes
outside the parks themselves in
order to keep visitors away.
Couldn't we do better? Last
December, a meeting was held in
the United States, attended by 100
people, mainly U.S. biosphere
reserve managers and representa¬
tives from various federal and local
authorities, to work out a plan of
action for the American biosphere
reserves. This important initiative
will greatly contribute to the
strengthening of the World Network
ofBiosphere Reserves, the situation
and status ofwhich will be reviewed
in March 1995 at a UNESCO-orga-
nized conference in Seville. Even
though they do not always achieve
all they set out to do, these reserves
are superior in conception to
national parks, since they take the
conservation ofbiodiversity and of
ecosystems as their starting point,
participate in an international
research and management network
and, above all, combine environ¬
ment and development, so safe¬
guarding the quality of life of local
populations.
FRANCE BEQUETTE
is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental
questions. Since 1985 she has been
associated with the WANAD-Unesco
training programmeforAfrican
news-agencyjournalists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
L	D
TWO CHIMPS
SAY GOODBYE TO THE CIRCUS
A photographer travelling with a Greek circus who took
pictures of children posing with two young female
chimpanzees had his animals confiscated in November
1993. Greece joined the Convention on International
Trade in Endangered Species ofWild Fauna and Flora
(CITES) in lanuary 1993, but as it had not yet enacted
legislation to implement it, the customs authorities
invoked contraband legislation instead. The photog¬
rapher claimed to have bought the animals in Spain but
not to know their country oforigin. TRAFFIC, the WWF
wildlife trade monitoring programme, undertook to
remove the chimps and place them in a rescue centre.
As their origin is unknown, they cannot be returned to
the wild.
TEN GREEN BOTTLES
HANGING ... IN THE
WARDROBE
Patagonia, an American outdoor
clothing company, has pulled off the
feat ofproducing sweaters from bot¬
tles made ofPET, the only recyclable
plastic. The bottles are washed,
chopped into chips, melted down
and formed into fibre which is spun
into yarn. The garments, perfect for
climbers and skiers, are warm, soft
and machine-washable, and do not
absorb moisture. The material goes
by the name ofPCR Synchilla fleece
(PCR stands for post-consumer recy¬
cled). Patagonia is pressing ahead
with research into ways ofrecycling
PCR Synchilla itself!
SELF-PACKAGED PRODUCTS
UNEP has announced an innova¬
tion proposed by a Canadian firm,
Bonar, Inc., which has traditionally
used multiwall paper and plastic-
coated paper bags to ship indus¬
trial resins for plastics and rubber
manufacturing. Its bright idea has
been to make the packaging of the
resins from the same or similar
resins, which are perfectly suitable
for the purpose. This means not
only that there is nothing to be
thrown away but that the packaging
can be tossed, together with the
compound it contains, into the
manufacturing process.
30
OMAN:
DATES AND SARDINES
ON THE MENU
FOR GOATS
In most of the Gulf States, the Sul¬
tanate of Oman in particular, water
is in short supply, and the resulting
scarcity of forage is the chief
obstacle to the development of live¬
stock rearing. Solutions are, how¬
ever, to hand. According to Oman's
Ministry of Agriculture and Fish¬
eries, the country's annual pro¬
duction of sardines is around
25,000 tons, not all ofwhich is con¬
sumed by the local population,
whilst about 10,000 of the 85,000
tons of dates produced annually
are of inferior quality. Both dates
and sardines can be used as pro¬
tein supplements for growing
calves and goats. Hopefully, the
meat won't taste of sardines	
ON THE
WATERFRONT
The Organization for Economic
Co-operation and Development
(OECD) last year published a
remarkable document that will be of
great interest to all those who are
concerned with the land-sea inter¬
face. It includes ten case studies
covering relatively limited geo¬
graphical areas such as Izmir Bay,
Turkey, the Lagoon of Venice, and
Lake Geneva, and others that deal
with larger areas such as southeast
Tasmania and the south coast of
the United Kingdom, a whole
country (Norway) and an interna¬
tional space (the Baltic Sea). A
variety of competing or even con¬
flicting activities are concentrated in
coastal zones, including aquacul¬
ture, docks and harbours, tourism
and recreation, urban and indus¬
trial development, quarrying, agri¬
culture and effluent disposal. While
not claiming to solve all the prob¬
lems thus raised, the management
methods presented in these studies
maybe a source of ideas that could
be used elsewhere in the world.
OECD, 2, rue André Pascal, 75775
Paris Cedex 16. Tel. (33-1) 45 24 80
89; Fax 45 24 85 00.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
INITIATIV E S
TUNA CATCH CUTBACKS
The aim of the International Com¬
mission for the Conservation of
Atlantic Tunas is to conserve the
fish in the ocean rather than in tins.
Delegates at its 1993 meeting agreed
to reduce the Western Atlantic tuna
catch in 1994 to 1,995 tonnes and in
1995 to 1,200 tonnes, 55 per cent
less than the 1991 level. This mea¬
sure was motivated by the decline in
bluefin tuna numbers over the last
twentyyears, owing to over-fishing.
Some experts consider the response
too timid, motivated more by eco¬
nomic considerations the price of
the meat and jobs for fishermen
than by concern for the conserva¬
tion of an endangered species.
According to the World Wide Fund
for Nature (WWF), lapan consumes
40 per cent of the world bluefin
catch, purchased mainly from Aus¬
tralia, the United States, Taiwan,
Spain and Canada, and a single fish
can go for $60,000 at auction.
NEWS FROM THE OZONE
LAYER
The December 1993 issue of Ozon-
Action, the quarterly newsletter of
the Industry and Environment Pro¬
gramme Activity Centre of the
United Nations Environment Pro¬
gramme (UNEP), reveals that at the
beginning ofOctober last "Antarctic
ozone levels fell below 100 Dobson
units, the lowest daily minimum
concentration ever recorded. This
represents a 70 per cent reduction
as compared to the average con¬
centrations before the ozone hole
formed. Over Europe, from
December 1992 through March
1993, ozone concentrations have
been observed to drop from mean
values by an average of 13 per cent."
Although the annual growth rate for
atmospheric chlorofluorocarbon
concentrations has declined in both
hemispheres as a result of a 60 per
cent reduction in consumption,
these concentrations will continue
to rise until the turn of the century.
UNEP IE/PAC, 39-43, quai André
Citroën, 757739 Paris Cedex 15, Tel.
(33-1)44 3714 74.
Li FE m m
Eu
Lions Clubs International only
has a distant relationship with
the big cat, even though its
emblem bears the animal's
profile. Lions is the acronym
of "Liberty, intelligence, our nation's
safety". With the motto "We Serve",
Lions is the world's largest service
club organization, an association
of men and women who give their
time to humanitarian causes. More
than 40,000 clubs in 175 countries
unite 1,600,000 members around
an ideal of generosity, openness of
heart and mind, and an interest in
people, regardless of race or nation¬
ality, religion or philosophy. A 37-
year-old American insurance man,
Melvin Iones, founded the first club
in Chicago in 1917. In 1945, he rep¬
resented the movement at the
United Nations. Originally open
only to men, the Lions Clubs began
acccepting males and females aged
18 to 27 in 1968. In 1975, Lioness
Clubs were created exclusively for
women. In 1987, the clubs became
mixed.
The Lions have been involved
in environmental issues since 1970,
and in 1982 the Executive Director
of the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP) presented the
movement with its "Environment
Leadership" medal. Each year the
Lions Clubs in France organize sem
inars on themes such as water,
renewable energy sources, waste
processing and the detection and
monitoring of atmospheric pollu¬
tion. In 1991, the French branch of
Lions Clubs International launched
an operation called "2,000 fountains
for the year 2000 ". It aims to list and
then restore fountains that were
more or less abandoned when piped
water was brought to rural areas, in
an attempt to revive the tradition in
which they served as village meeting
places. Already 240 fountains have
been restored. In the same year, a
project named "A drop of water for
Africa" provided a number ofwater¬
less Malian villages with water-holes
equipped with simple but effective
hand-pumps. Also in Mali, in col¬
laboration with a Canadian non¬
governmental organization, Groupe
Action Nord-Sud (GANS), the Lions
are promoting out-of-season market
gardening on 20 hectares of irrigated
land and supplying farmers with
ploughs. A plough is ten to twenty
times more efficient than a hand¬
held hoe, but it brings with it the
problems of harnessing, feeding
draught animals and repair. This
change in cultural habits will suc¬
ceed because it has the full support
of the local population.
Lions Clubs were pioneers in
developing the use of the white stick
and the training of guide dogs for
the blind and visually impaired.
Currently Lions Clubs International
is running a campaign known as
SightFirst to combat the problem
of blindness worldwide by helping
to provide health care services
where these are desperately needed.
Lions Clubs International is a non¬
governmental organization which
has consultative status with Unesco
and as such attends major confer¬
ences as an observer and takes part
in certain commissions and
working groups.
World headquarters: Lions Clubs
International, 300 22nd Street/Oak
Brook, Illinois 60521-8842, U.S.A.
Tel. (708) 571 54 66; Fax 571 88 90.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
EASTERN EUROPE */ Voices from the past
Each nation has its own
language, history and
ways ofworking
32
SINCE the fall of the Berlin Wall, eastern
Europe has been overrun by Western busi¬
nessmen eager to initiate entrepreneurs in the
former communist countries into their methods so
as to establish dialogue, if not partnership, with
them. Well armed with advice and management
techniques, they are sometimes welcomed with
open arms and sometimes eyed with suspicion, but
their message, a simple one, is always the same: for
more than forty years you have been running
your businesses without having to face competi-
tition or reckon with market forces, and we're
here to let you into the secrets of competitivity.
Whether they are German, French, British or
by Tatjana Qobokar
Italian, they set up more and more joint ventures,
consultancies and business schools. There are a few
surprises in store for them along the way.
A/lore differences than meet the eye
There are surprises on both sides. Western busi¬
nessmen realize that, contrary to the stereotyped
image they have of the command economy
laggardly decision-making processes, inefficiency
in the workplace, buck-passing and the rest
there are marked differences from country to
country. It was convenient, between 1945 and
1990, to lump the whole of eastern Europe from
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
r\ foundry at Nowa Huta
in the suburbs of Krakow,
the site of Poland's largest
iron and steel industry
complex.
the Baltic to the Black Sea together as a monolithic
bloc, all ruled over in the same way by socialist
regimes. Nobody took much notice of the fact
that the peoples of the Iron Curtain countries
were quite different one from another, and had
their own cultural identities that inevitably influ¬
enced management styles.
Meanwhile, east European entrepreneurs
were surprised to find, in their dealings with
Westerners, that the efficiency, consistency and
speed of decision-making that were the proud
hallmarks of Western business were sometimes
conspicuous for their absence, and that those
dealings could be more or less easy, depending on
where their partners came from.
The rapprochement that has followed the
breakup of the eastern bloc has, if nothing else,
taught those on either side that each nation has its
own language, history and traditions but also its
own way of working. There is, however, a danger
that these differing characteristics will again be
smothered, in the countries of eastern Europe,
under management methods copied from the West.
They should be studied systematically so that they
can be integrated into the local business context.
Between 1985 and 1992, we were able to carry
out research in this field in Poland, Hungary,
Slovenia and Bosnia and Herzegovina. This
research brought to light some widely differing
behaviour patterns and value systems linked with
the history of each of these countries.
Idealism and pragmatism
"To work in peace, I have to know that the
manager likes me," an overseer in a Polish fac
tory told us. We were at first surprised at such
an emotionally loaded attitude to relationships
in the workplace, but found it fully under¬
standable once it was set against the general
background of the enterprise.
Our interviewee expressed a strong need for
trust and for constant reassurance as to his supe¬
rior's feelings towards him. From other clues we
came to the conclusion that the bonds of soli¬
darity between the workers in the factory were
similar to the bonds of comradeship so much in
evidence between the soldiers on the many bat¬
tlefields of Poland's stormy past.
Because of this solidarity, patriotic feelings
far removed from everyday realities are involved
in attitudes to work. Those we interviewed laid
little emphasis on the job in hand or the factory's
performance but placed great emphasis on the
importance they attached to Poland's prosperity
and glory. "Poles are stirred by anything to do
with the homeland," as A. Podgorecki confirms
in Une théorie de la sociétépolonaise (1991).
The motivations of Hungarian workers, on
the other hand, are simpler and more pragmatic.
In the factory we investigated, individual ambi¬
tions are subordinated to the cohesion of the
group. A good worker, in the eyes of the super¬
visor, is one who is unassuming, talks little and
does his workmates' jobs for them, an attitude
viewed as desirable and indeed necessary inas¬
much as it serves the higher interest of the group.
The group in question may be a production
unit, a department of the administration or a
maintenance service. Its cohesion is seamless,
and it tries to solve its problems without "out¬
side" interference. Although such loyalty is not
The siege of Czestochowa
by the Swedes in 1655 is
pictured in this late 17th-
century painting by a folk
artist. The siege ended in
victory for the Poles.
.:
r-
y^v"ÉÉih \ 3 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
**.<**'&,
feasants of Swabian
descent in the Banat,
Hungary, are shown in this
early 20th-century
postcard.
34
TATJANA GLOBOKAR,
a Slovenian-born economist, is
a research associate with
France's National Centre for
Scientific Research (CNRS).
She is the author of many
studies on the economies of
east and central European
countries.
necessarily reflected in a feeling of belonging vis-
à-vis the enterprise, it does on the other hand
give rise to keen competititon between the dif¬
ferent groups, each of which wants to outdo
the others.
The roots of this attitude go back into the
past of a society that is a patchwork of peoples
and religions, obliged by a hostile environment
to turn inwards upon itself, coalescing in feudal
times around the local gentry. In a context of
such ethnic and religious diversity, community
spirit was the glue that held society together.
Family and village communities
We observed similar, albeit more individual¬
istic, attitudes in a Slovene factory, The emphasis
here was on know-how, which seemed to be
the one and only criterion for accepting and
tolerating other people. "We get on well with
this foreman. He's always been in the iron¬
works. At least he knows his stuff", we were told
by a workman, while the foreman in question
told us he always listens to the workman because
"who knows the job better than him?"
We built up from this a picture of Slovene-
style management under which the workers can
develop their skills if they are placed in an atmos¬
phere of collective mutual aid. The strong con¬
cern for equality that permeates their relation¬
ships with each other gives them a feeling of
dignity and trust. In organizational terms, this
is reflected in a negative attitude towards exces¬
sively hierarchical structures and a positive one
towards internal communication, enabling
everyone to have his say and prove his point.
The reason why Slovenes set such store by
equality, mutual aid and competence is that the
basis of their society is the village community.
When Slovenia was occupied territory, the pos¬
sibilities for climbing the social ladder were
very limited outside of that community. The
community thus favoured equality and soli
darity among its members, whose only way of
making their mark was by means of their skills.
As our experience in Slovenia had confirmed
the part played by different cultures in former
Yugoslavia, we turned our attention to Bosnia
and Herzegovina.
In this country inhabited by Bosnian Mus¬
lims, Catholic Croats and Orthodox Serbs, the
influence of the "zadruga" model of social orga¬
nization is still strongly felt. The zadruga itself,
the traditional extended family of the Balkans
where the sons lived and worked together under
the authority of the father, has all but disap¬
peared but is still very much a part of the mental
landscape. The two focal points are the father
and the brothers. The father is the chief incar¬
nate, whose duty it is to protect the family com¬
munity and dedicate himself to its welfare. The
brothers represent the submission of individuals
to the group, which is bonded together by strong
feelings of solidarity.
This family hierarchy appeared to influence
the two-way relationships in the factory we
researched, the higher echelons exercising
paternal authority and the workers practising
fraternal solidarity. Superiors took on the role of
the all-powerful, protective but also well-
beloved father, a role their subordinates were
content to let them play. The "chief", of what¬
ever rank, is the one who knows everything,
anticipates everything and is also prepared to
listen to everyone. On the shop floor, on the
other hand, where an egalitarian spirit reigns,
relations among the workers are characterized
by familiarity and spontaneous co-operation.
The expressions "our factory", "our house"
and "our family" cropped up continuously in
interviews. Each member of this "family" had a
specified role and his ambitions in working life
were integrated into the collective endeavour.
What are the lessons for
management?
This brief overview of the distinctive features of
certain countries of eastern and central Europe
clearly shows that modern management requires
a thorough knowledge of the employee's cultural
and social background. As of now, the man¬
agers and management consultants who get the
best results are those who display the ability to
look, listen and act on intuition: it is useful to
know that unduly hierarchical structures should
not be imposed in countries where the com¬
munity spirit predominates and that individu¬
alism should not be accorded preferential treat¬
ment in those where the individual willingly
takes a back seat not only so as to avoid con¬
flicts but also to help give full scope to the abil¬
ities of each individual as part of the common
endeavour.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
'Most successful
Japanese businessmen
have the skills of the
samurai in the sense
that they are never
afraid to take difficult
decisions and do not
flinch from bad news'
JAPAN i/ The new samurai
byJohn Harford
Above, a computer-
generated image of Yin
and Yang
H
OW is it that a relatively small island
country with hardly any natural
resources has become such a powerful
force in world trade? One simple story tells
everything. In 1952 the small Japanese com¬
pany that was eventually to become Sony Cor¬
poration struck a deal with Bell Labs of the
United States for the production of transistors.
The American company's last words of advice
were, "Whatever you do, do not try to use tran¬
sistors in radio sets; they cannot accept the elec¬
trical frequencies required."
Later, having solved the frequency problem,
and thus helped to launch the transistor revo¬
lution, the Japanese company set itself the objec¬
tive of producing a miniature radio that would
fit into a shirt pocket. Unfortunately the
designers were unsuccessful in producing a
model that was quite small enough, and so all the
members of the sales force were issued with
shirts with extra wide pockets.
The sense of purpose illustrated by this story
is one of the outstanding features of Japanese
business practice. It is based on qualities that are
simple to describe in words but very difficult to
put into practice. The qualities are respect, trust,
loyalty, courage, practicality, solidity, substance,
simplicity, brevity, calmness, tolerance, patience,
perseverance, clarity and wisdom. To understand
their place in Japanese business one has to go
much deeper than studying such outward mani¬
festations of social behaviour as politeness, def¬
erence and courtesy. These are only external reflec¬
tions from a deep pool. One needs to look at the 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
tffigy of the Buddha on
Repulse Bay, Hong Kong.
36
whole context of Japanese culture, which has
grown and been influenced for centuries by a
number of concepts, philosophies and religions.
Some of the most significant of these influ¬
ences came from China via Taoism, Confu¬
cianism and Chan (Zen) Buddhism. The written
language of Japan also came originally from
China, as did Japanese medicine and military tac¬
tics, and many philosophical concepts. One
good example of this influence is the Japanese
adoption of the Chinese character system. There
are literally thousands of calligraphic symbols in
the average Japanese daily newspaper. (To read
a paper it is necessary to know about 2,000
characters). The ability to perform this incred¬
ible feat of recognition and mental storage is
developed by the repetitive practice of writing
characters from a very early age. By the time a
child is four, in some cases even younger, he or
she will have absorbed the skills of patience,
perseverance, endurance and the "work ethic"
four of the most potent attributes of successful
management.
The universe and the individual
The Japanese regard individuals as a micro¬
cosm of the universe and as irrevocably bound
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
to changes which continually occur. This puts
humankind firmly in its place in the order of
things. Most of them understand the concept of
harmonizing and not conflicting with natural
events. The idea of change is indicated by the
concept of Yin-Yang, the mutual interaction
of positive and negative forces which not only
oppose each other but also mutually support
each other. The Japanese believe a balance
between Yin and Yang forces must be continu¬
ally sought in all matters. The saying that "the
only thing that is constant is change" is an
everyday reminder that one should always be
taking corrective action to retain one's balance.
The concept of Yin and Yang can be seen in
the fluctuations between night and day, male
and female, hot and cold, dark and light.
Its importance in business forecasting and
planning rests on the belief that changes or
events can be predicted in advance to the extent
that a sudden increase in Yang will be immedi¬
ately followed by a rapid descent to extreme Yin
and vice versa. In other words, if corrective
action is not taken quickly, disaster will follow.
When changes occur too rapidly in nature,
thunderstorms, earthquakes and flooding result.
Parallel situations arise in business if things are
done in a precipitate manner. Accordingly busi¬
ness planning in Japan takes into account the
advisability of introducing change slowly and
harmoniously.
Planning and ritual
The exploratory process that is carried out
before embarking on a business project can be
likened to rituals that are associated with
preparing land for sowing and date back to
ancient times. The ground must be fertile, the
seeds (ideas) must be of good quality and must
be placed at the right spacing and depth so as not
to interfere with each other. The ground must be
well drained and irrigated if necessary, and weeds
must be discouraged.
Plans are based on an idea or ideas. In Japan
ideas are allowed to sprout naturally into matu¬
rity, and since they are taken seriously they are
subject to quality control, like any other
product! When the Japanese have an idea they
do not go around telling everyone about it,
they put it aside mentally and allow it to mature.
This process is called pondering, or searching
for perfect clarity, literally waiting for the mud
to settle down. The idea is then looked at by a
group, whose members take the concept away
as individuals and apply the pondering process
themselves. This process may be repeated many
times before the group agrees that the concept
is viable, for a plan is constructed like a pyramid
built in wafer-thin layers, the thinner the better.
No new layer is added until the previous one
has set hard. The bottom layers receive input
from all members of the group, and the final
Japanese managers take
part in a rigorous training
course at Fuji Nomiya,
1 00 km from Tokyo.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
38
JOHN HARFORD
is a British engineer and
management consultant who
has first-hand knowledge of
Japanese management and
business methods, on which he
has lectured widely. He is a
registered practitioner of
Chinese medicine.
layer represents the approval and go-ahead from
the chief executive or board of the company.
This process exercises the skill of patience: "With
a light top and heavy bottom, solidity and inspi¬
ration are present and success is guaranteed."
The group pondering method is used exten¬
sively for solving problems. It is very effective
for optimizing human resources and means that
doing things in a fit of enthusiasm is avoided.
Dealing with difficult problems
The key to dealing with difficult problems in
Japanese eyes is Ki, "internal strength". In
ancient Japan survival meant avoiding immi¬
nent death at the hands of a warlord by devel¬
oping martial and military skills and belonging
to a group. Professional soldiers or samurai
acted as protectors to the group, who paid the
samurai's salaries. The samurai had a strict code
of honour and conduct and were impervious
to suffering and hardship; they also had to be
masters of strategy and tactics. Only men of
iron resolution, outstanding courage and
strength could withstand the training. The one
skill that was paramount was calmness under
pressure. The development of principles
requiring these qualities and involving mental,
physical and spiritual toughness and the will to
succeed is at the heart of management training
in Japanese companies today. This "whole
person training" is carried out in addition to
learning the skills and techniques of business
management. Thus most successful Japanese
businessmen have the skills of the samurai in the
sense that they are never afraid to take difficult
decisions and do not flinch from bad news.
The belly
If you look at any representation of a Buddha or
a Japanese warrior, you will see that they both
have a well-developed belly. The belly inJapanese
is called the Hara, and traditionally training the
Hara has been an important activity for many
Japanese. It is of fundamental importance to
anyone wishing to accomplish great things. "A
man without a developed Hara will not aspire to
greatness" is a common Japanese saying.
The Hara represents the "seat of life and
vitality". InJapanese medicine the internal organs
and the energy associated with them form part of
the mental process as well: "To think only with
the head is considered insubstantial." The
Japanese word for a plan, Fukian, literally means
"belly project", thus implying that there must be
heart in the plan as well as purely intellectual
content. Traditionally, the strength of the Hara is
developed by sitting or standing, coupled with
deep abdominal breathing and strong mental
concentration. This causes the Ki or life force
energy to grow and hence increases the power to
get things done. Strong Ki is evident in Judo,
Karate, Kendo, archery, sword drawing, the tea
ceremony, flower arranging, meditation and
successful businessmen!
The concept of Ki is baffling to most occi¬
dentals. It cannot be seen, heard or smelled, and
therefore it is not amenable to normal methods
of reasoning or study. An appreciation of Ki
can be achieved by working with an accom¬
plished teacher, by doing and feeling things
under close supervision. The irony is that Ki, the
most important driving force in any kind of
activity, is an imponderable, but its reality is
readily accepted in the East. Perhaps the term
"inner strength" could make it understandable
to occidentals. No movement or activity can
occur without the consumption of Ki energy.
The quest for balance
Enlightened Japanese managers understand the
need to avoid excess and the need for balance and
restraint to avoid illness caused by psychological
disturbances or imbalances. Their approach is
based on the belief, central to Japanese traditional
medicine (which is itself based on traditional Chi¬
nese medicine) that the physical, mental and spir¬
itual aspects of any disease or illness cannot be sep¬
arated from one another in diagnosis or treatment.
The patient must be treated holistically.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Two of the most important features of
Japanese medicine and culture are the Yin-Yang
theory, described above, and the Laws of the
Five Elements. In simple terms, if your Yin and
Yang energies are not balanced you are sick and
it is the doctor's job to create a balance.
According to the Laws of the Five Elements, all
human beings are made up of a combination of
five elements (or tendencies): wood, fire, earth,
metal and water. The five elements are in turn
related to the internal organs, the emotions,
colours, smells, tastes and the seasons. In busi¬
ness terms they are concerned with helping in
staff selection, creating effective organizations,
creating a harmonious working environment
and reducing stress and tension generally.
Element Organs Emotion
Fire Heart Joy
Earth Spleen Sympathy
Metal Lungs Sadness
Water Kidneys Fear
Wood Liver Anger
Training and leadership
Business training methods in Japan are practical
and follow a traditional pattern. Trainers are
highly respected for their skills and trainees are
expected to pay full attention at all times. The
responsibilities are mutual: the teacher gives out
what the student needs, and the student absorbs.
Each party must be humble and respect the other.
The training of young managers is similar to
martial art or military training. The emphasis is
on doing real things rather than debating or
attending lectures or "business games".
It is not normal for graduates to go straight
into management. When they join a company
they are usually assigned to a very experienced
mentor with specialized skills. Usually three or
more graduates will work in a single office for up
to three years, during which time they are given
tasks to accomplish under guidance from the
mentor. The system of training is akin to a "drip
feed", which means that substantial skills are
acquired slowly and organically.
The Western world could learn much from
what makes the Japanese so successful in business.
It is not just a case of adopting Japanese tech¬
niques and technology but of recognizing and
developing the necessary human skills. Such a
process would take time, but the qualities and
attributes can be learned by exercising determi¬
nation and constantly keeping an open and flex¬
ible mind. The East has borrowed heavily from
the West in improving its business performance;
the West could also take note of the lessons of
Japanese history and culture and consider
applying them in its own organizations. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
4P
UNESCO IN ACTION
NEWSBRIEFS...
MOTHER TERESA HONOURED
The Director-General of Unesco
travelled to Calcutta to present
Mother Teresa with the 1 992 Unesco
Prize for Peace Education, awarded to
her by an international jury "in
recognition of the achievements of a
life entirely dedicated to serving the
poor, promoting peace and fighting
injustice". Accepting the award,
Mother Teresa said that works of love
are works of peace and that it is
important to pray, because the fruit
of prayer is "the deepening of faith
and of love". She announced that the
$50,000 prize money, donated by the
Japan Shipbuilding Industry
Foundation, would be used to build
an extension to the Nirmala Kennedy
Centre, a home for the handicapped
she runs in Calcutta. The award for
1993 was shared by Madeleine de Vits
(Belgium) and the Graduate Institute
of Peace Studies (Republic of Korea).
MODERNIZING THE HERMITAGE
MUSEUM
The Government of the Netherlands
is putting $1.2 million towards the
cost of a project for the development
of the Hermitage Museum, St.
Petersburg (Russia). The project, part
of UNESCO's Programme for Central
and Eastern European Development
(PROCEED), aims to improve the
museum's lighting, labelling,
computerization and marketing, and
also includes the training of
professionals.
FIRST JAPANESE SITES CHOSEN FOR
HERITAGE LIST
For the first time, a number of
Japanese sites Himeji-jo Castle and
the Buddhist monuments in the
Horyu-Ji area and the Yakushima and
Shirakami-Sanchi natural sites have
been placed on UNESCO's World
Heritage List. Together with 29 other
sites chosen by the World Heritage
Committee meeting in Cartagena
(Colombia) last December, this brings
to 41 1 the number of sites, in 94
countries, listed as being of
outstanding natural or cultural value.
OPERATION BOSNIA
The first Unesco school in Bosnia
and Herzegovina was inaugurated on
30 January under the Organization's
"Operation Bosnia" programme. It
stands on a hilltop overlooking the
town of Grude, opposite a site where
the French humanitarian organization
"Médecins sans frontières" is building
a village for refugees from the Mostar
region. It will enable several hundred
children to go back to school after a
two-year break in their studies. The
school has four large classrooms, a
library and a playground. Two more
schools will be built soon, in
Nevesinje and Kalesija.
WOMEN IN THE MEDIA
Unesco is setting up a network for
the development of women media
specialists in the Mediterranean Arab
countries, linking universities and
training institutes in three European
countries (Belgium, France and the
Netherlands) and four Mediterranean
countries (Egypt, Jordan, Morocco
and Tunisia). The project aims to
strengthen media initiatives Involving
Mediterranean Arab women,
promote international research and
define communication strategies that
would help to change attitudes
towards and perceptions of women in
general and Arab women in
particular. The European Union has
approved financial support for the
project under its MED-MEDIA
programme, recently created to
promote co-operation among media
professionals and reduce prejudice
and ignorance over such issues as the
Middle East conflict, immigration and
racism.
HELPING FORMER YUGOSLAVIA'S
FREE PRESS
An extra $20,000 has been granted
by Unesco's Director-General to the
Sarajevo daily Oslobodenje. This
supplements the $50,000 already
provided by the Organization under
its priority programme to help the
independent media in the former
Yugoslavia, an activity conducted in
collaboration with professional media
organizations, the Office of the UN
High Commissioner for Refugees and
the United Nations. If you would like
to offer your support, please ring
Unesco on (33-1) 45 68 42 13.
ÍTHIS ARTICLE 15 ONE
OF A SERIES IN WHICH
THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF
UNESCO SETS OUT HIS
THINKING ON MATTERS OF
CURRENT CONCERN
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
Preventing pollution
WATER, soil and air pollution is a world¬
wide problem. We cannot go on taking
a piecemeal view of the preservation of
our heritage. We must adopt worldwide rules of
conduct. A situation in which one country takes
appropriate action while its neighbour does the
opposite cannot be tolerated. Some countries
are much worse polluters than others, and it is
they who should foot most of the bill.
The industrialized countries are at present
responsible for between 70 and 85 per cent of all
pollution and its disastrous effects on the world's
cultural heritage. Although they have a much
larger population, the developing countries
account for far fewer of the sources of pollution
and contribute less to environmental degradation.
How can countries that cannot afford to do so be
asked to behave as the industrialized countries
themselves have failed to behave? Take defor¬
estation, for example. In the North memories
should not be so short that people forget how, for
centuries, they have been devastating their forests.
Instead of laying down the law to others they
should be helping them to adopt rules of conduct
better than theirs have been in the past.
Like natural disasters, man-made catastrophes
know no frontiers. There have been many episodes
in history as sombre as the eruption of Mount
Pinatubo in the Philippines. That volcano gave off
as many toxic substances in a day as the burning
oil wells in Kuwait gave off in a year. The differ¬
ence, however, is that there was nothing we could
do to prevent the Pinatubo eruption, but we were
perfectly capable of averting the Kuwaiti oil well
fires, and should have done so. These were exam¬
ples of, on the one hand, an unavoidable disaster
and, on the other, of a problem that was remedi¬
able because it was the work of human hands.
A moral duty
Prevention is a duty demanded of us by something
much more than cultural, economic or political
considerations. As in the case of preventive mea¬
sures in the field of health, it is our moral duty. If
we want to preserve the health of our planet and
of its cultural monuments in particular, we should
take all the preventive steps our resources allow.
The resources we now have at our disposal are
considerable those, for instance, provided by
satellite-based remote sensing, which covers the
whole world. To find out whether monuments in
Iraq had suffered war damage, there was no need
to send a fact-finding mission; we had only to
examine the photographs accumulated day by
day in two or three world centres.
We therefore have the technical means to ensure
that international standards are respected, and to
avoid pollution that is mainly attributable to the
activities of 18 to 22 per cent of humanity, by
which I mean that highly privileged fraction of the
world's population whose appetite for creature
comforts and gadgets, so characteristic of the con¬
sumer society, needs to be curbed and corrected.
Respect for future generations is now a moral
duty. It is the supreme concern of such people as
Captain Cousteau, who has for so many years
been opening our eyes to the wonders of nature
and who is now sounding the alarm, alerting us to
the fact that we are in the process of destroying the
seas, the very lungs of the planet. As we all know,
there is no life without light, but it is precisely at
the interface between the waters and the dry land
that we are destroying ecosystems by dumping
huge quantities of toxic products. The great threat
now hanging over the human race is the human
race itself.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
THE VALLEE DE MAI
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
«
Thegranitic islands of the Seychelles
archipelago, rising from a large
submarine plateau that may have
been the legendary land of Lemuria, are
like great hanging gardens. Forming, so
to speak, a "microcontinent" of their own,
they bear little resemblance to the other
islands, volcanic or coralline, of the Indian
Ocean. They are distinctive in other
respects too: one of them, Praslin, is home
to an astonishing native species of palm,
the famous coco-de-mer.
Two hundred years ago, these as yet
virgin islands were covered in vast, tropi¬
cally luxuriant rainforests that filled the
ravines and valleys and clambered up hills
and mountains.
In the lowlands, up to an altitude of
300 metres, grew giant trees more than 30
metres tall and with boles of 15 to 20
metres in diameter, and even they were
dwarfed by the superb Dipterocarpaceae,
as much as 65 metres tall.
Between the altitudes of 300 and 600
metres was intermediate forest that
formed a canopy only twenty or so metres
above the ground but was very rich in
endemic species. Huge bare boulders
emerging like islets from a sea ofgreenery
provided a habitat for interesting com¬
munities of ferns and oforchids, including
the paille-en-queuewüh its gorgeous spray
of mother-of-pearl flowers and delicious
gardenia-like scent.
On the mist-shrouded heights, the
trees grew to no more than 15 metres, but
it was here that the pitcher plant or
Nepenthes was to be found, usually
winding itself around a species of man¬
grove tree that also grew there.
These ancient forests, with their botan¬
ical links to Africa, Madagascar, India and
Malaysia, were largely replaced by plan¬
tations, leaving only a fewprecious vestiges
on the mountain tops of Mahé and Sil¬
houette Islands. A few of the smaller
islands such as Praslin provide the last
natural sanctuaries for the coco-de-mer.
A LIVING MUSEUM
The Vallée de Mai Nature Reserve is per¬
haps the most attractive and interesting of
these sanctuaries. It is easily accessible by
means of the well-surfaced road linking
the villages of la Grand'Anse and la Baie
Sainte-Anne. As it is only some 18 hectares
in area, it takes only an hour to walk the
length of the path that runs round it. The
low hill overlooking it affords a superb all-
round view. Its shady groves of palm and
pandanus give the visitor some idea of
how beautiful the woodlands of Praslin
must once have been.
The Vallée de Mai is an outstanding
reminder ofwhat the world's flora was like
at an earlier stage, a kind of living museum.
Much too small to survive on its own, it
owes its continued existence to human
intervention. It is thus both a fine example
of rational management of the environ¬
ment and a conservation area for rare and
interesting botanical species. These
include the bois rouge (red wood), a large-
leaved tree of the Dilleniaceae family so
called for its brightly coloured trunk; the
capucin, a sapotaceous plant whose large
seed resembles a hooded head; the
latanier latte, a palm with large, stiff, dark
green fronds; the palmiste, perhaps the
handsomest of Seychellean palms; and
two species ofpandanus, the vacoa parasol
with its perfectly symmetrical triple
branches, and the vacoa marron with its
astounding aerial prop roots, sometimes
over 30 metres in length.
As if to make up for the solemn immo¬
bility of its trees, the forest swarms with
animal life: emerald-green geckos, big
dark-brown snails of the primitive
Acavideae family, big, black but reputedly
harmless scorpions, lovely shimmering
snakes, little "tiger chameleons", tawny-
breasted bats, big-billed bulbuls, charming
souï-mangas, red, white or blue fruit-
eating pigeons, and the little vasa parrots
whose clear, strong whistling call shatters
the silence of the valley in the early
morning and late afternoon.
Indisputably, however, it is the 4,000
coco-de-mer palms, a unique population
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
A paradise garden in the Seychelles
byGuyLionnet
Air view of the Vallée de Mai.
of trees whose splendour rivals that of the
cedars of Lebanon or the giant redwoods
of California, that make the Vallée de Mai
one of the botanical wonders of the world.
THE LOVE-LIFE
OF THE COCO-DE-MER
Lodoicea sechellarum, the coco-de-mer,
is one of the six species of palm native to
the Seychelles. With its straight, bare trunk,
its fans of large, stiff fronds and its huge
fruits, it is a truly majestic tree.
Like all members of the Borasseae
family, it is dioecious, i.e. the male and
female reproductive organs, stamen and
pistil, grow on separate plants; the male
and female palms stand side by side like a
loving couple. Unable to live one without
the other, the two sexes are similarly pro¬
portioned. There are several surprising
things about them. The male is about five
metres taller than the female and appears
to be protecting her; its stamen resembles
a large penis. Under the smooth, shiny epi¬
dermis of the fruit, a huge, green, heart-
shaped object some 50 cm. long and
weighing 15 to 20 kg., the nut itselfthe
"sea coconut", the biggest and heaviest seed
in the vegetable kingdom consists of two
grey-black lobes, covered in a very tough
integument and with a narrow groove
between them, recalling a smoothly
rounded pair of female buttocks. According
to an old Seychelles legend, on wild stormy
nights the coco-de-mer palms consum¬
mate their union in a strange ceremony to
witness which spells death to humans.
When ripe, the fruit gives off a pun¬
gent odour. Generally speaking, only three
or four fruits ripen on each inflorescence,
though as many as ten have been known to
reach maturity, and in such cases the
bunch of fruits may weigh as much as 200
kg. The trees produce only one or two
bunches a year.
Another remarkable feature of these
trees is their extremely slow rate ofgrowth
and, linked with that, their longevity. They
take three years to germinate and, after
they fruit the first time, it takes twenty-
five years before they start to bear fruit
again and getting on for a thousand years
before they reach their full size the oldest
coco-de-mer in the Vallée de Mai are reck¬
oned to be over 800 years old.
Why do they occur only in the Sey¬
chelles? One theory is that when the orig¬
inal continent of which the Seychelles are
thought to represent the remains broke
up and disappeared in the course ofaeons
ofgeological time, many plant species also
disappeared because they could not adapt
to their new habitats, whilst others, like
the coco-de-mer, lived on in isolation on
certain small islands. In the case of the
Above, a Phelsuma, a small arboreal gecko
found in the islands of the Indian Ocean.
Top, a Vanigula seychellensls, a gastropod
native to the Vallée de Mai.
coco-de-mer, this isolation was to prove
final, since there were three factors standing
in the way of its natural dispersal. In the
first place, its nut is too heavy, when still
fresh and thus capable of germinating, for
sea-borne dispersal. Secondly, since the
species is dioecious the male and female
palms have to grow side by side for repro¬
duction to take place. Lastly, the species is
also gregarious, fruiting and reproducing
well only within a community.
THE REMAINS OF EDEN
It was in 1768, in the course of the Marion-
Dufresne expedition that had sailed from
the Ile de France (now Mauritius) to recon¬
noitre the Seychelles, that the coco-de- 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Below, a group of Seychelles fodies
(Foudiae seycheffenses), a bird
species endemic to the Seychelles.
Bottom photo, a cluster of coco de
mer nuts.
44 I
mer was discovered on Praslin Island. Its
existence had, however, been suspected
and it gave rise to all kinds of legends that
long haunted the imagination of those
who dwelt on the shores of the Indian
Ocean and of the early European naviga¬
tors; it is in fact to one of these legends,
according to which it grew underwater,
that it owes its name of "sea coconut". Its
nuts were much sought after for their
aphrodisiac properties, and its shell was
reputed to be an excellent antidote.
It was, however, the Englishman
Charles Gordon General Gordon ofKhar¬
toum who was the author of the wildest,
and hence the most amusing, theory. In a
still unpublished study, dated 1881, the
year of his visit of inspection to the Sey¬
chelles, and entitled Eden and its two
sacramental trees, Gordon claimed that
these islands were the remains of the
earthly paradise and that the coco-de-mer
was the tree of the knowledge ofgood and
evil. He seems to have been struck not
only by the extraordinarily suggestive
shape of the nut but also by the fact that it
was contained within a heart-shaped
fruit the heart ofman being, according to
the Scriptures, the seat of his carnal
desires. To explain how Eve could have
tasted of a fruit with such a hard shell and
so indigestible a nut, Gordon added that
the coco-de-mer might have been dif¬
ferent in times gone by and might have
lost its mystical properties by reverting to
what he called its natural state.
The Vallée (formerly Val) de Mai, so
called because its original owner acquired
it during the month of May, remained
intact until the 1930s, after which, for fif¬
teen years or so, plantations were laid out
there. In 1945, the Seychelles authorities
bought the land and cleared it ofdead wood
to prevent forest fires, causing soil erosion.
From the 1950s onwards, a sustained effort
was made to restore the site. In view of its
great ecological interest, it was declared a
nature reserve in 1966, became a National
Park in 1979, and in 1983 was selected as a
World Heritage Site.
As in the case of the Aldabra atoll,
another World Heritage Site in the archi¬
pelago, administration of the Vallée de Mai
Nature Reserve was entrusted in 1989 to
the Seychelles Islands Foundation, a non¬
governmental organization on which are
represented such major international sci¬
entific bodies as the Royal Society (London),
the Smithsonian Institution (Washington,
D.C.) and the Paris-based research organi¬
zation ORSTOM. By the support it gives to
the Foundation, Unesco makes a major
contribution to the maintenance and
preservation of the two sites.
GUY LIONNET,
of Mauritius, is technical advisor on environmental
issues and honorary president of the Seychelles
Islands Foundation. He is the author of Par les
chemins de la mer: périples aux Seychelles au temps
des voyages aux longs cours, which will be published
shortly by CR.I publishers, Réunion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Le Corbusier
Le Corbusier (Charles Edouard Jeanneret-
Gris; 1887-1965).
Aftergiving his views on the
architectural perfection of
Venice (see the Unesco Courier,
March, 1994), Le Corbusier
invited modern society to
devote its art and industry to
the service oftown planning,
starting with the home.
Art and the home
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
I believe that a town consists primarily
of dwellings; the temples and the
palaces come afterwards. Now that
we have set our subjects of concern in per¬
spective, you will at once realize why
modern society, in the mass, is not in the
least concerned about creating for itself an
art that assuages its highest desires. The
very basis on which society rests is
missing homes. Housing in the world's
cities is awful. It has been sacrificed on
the altar of profit, and the only thing that
has so far supplanted money has been the
violent crisis that we are now experiencing
and that may perhaps show us what a vain
thing money is and how pointless it is to go
too far in its pursuit. What is required is to
point human consciousness in the right
direction, so that our hearts and minds
may aim for true, real, tangible goals,
accessible by our own efforts rather than,
as at present, by savagery, cruelty and reck¬
less greed.
I have taken part in a series of ven¬
tures all of them, needless to say, unsuc¬
cessful in the field of urban develop¬
ment in major capitals such as Stockholm,
Antwerp, Moscow, Paris, Buenos Aires and
Algiers, and all I can say is that those cities
are at present in a state of unconscious¬
ness, of ignorance ofwhat I claim modern
civilization has to offer them. They need to
be shaken out of their torpor, their abdi¬
cation of responsibility. Since it is a good
idea in all matters to have a clear termi¬
nology, I came up with a maxim. I said
that "a city is a collective endeavour that
should provide each individual with the
essential joys." These "essential joys" are
easy to describe.
I "said my piece" long ago; I waded
into the muddled debate over styles, fash¬
ions and snobbery, with the sledge
hammer argument that "la maison est une
machine à habiter" houses are machines
for living in. I have been threatened a thou¬
sand times with a beating for saying that.
When I say "for living in" I do not mean just
that the occupants' material needs should
be satisfied. I top the expression out by
adding "and for meditating in after the
most pressing needs have been met". But
for a home to become a place of medita¬
tion it must take on an entirely new form.
To be at all attainable, this in turn requires
an overall composition for the town, the
redesigning of its paths of communica¬
tion, boldness in the creation of its visual
spaces, anewwayofbuildinghomes, and
sound design for even the least of house¬
hold objects. As to the design of these
smallest household objects and here I
refer back to Venice, and the gondola in
particular I would like our modern inge¬
nuity to snatch the task out of the hands of
"professionals" who are not up to it, and
turn these minor things into magnificent
machines that are as efficient as those
built by engineers but, being subject to
the discipline of meeting our spiritual
needs, embody proportion divine pro¬
portion to the same degree as certain
well-known examples of work hitherto
done more or less by hand. I cannot accept
debasement ofeither neither of the hand
nor of the machine; there is no reason why
the faultless exactitude of the machine
should be inimical to beauty.
It is not widely enough realized that
modern architecture, immensely impor¬
tant as it is in the construction of a
machine-age society, finds its way into
every occurrence of life, even into a speech
or a book. That same unity can prevail in
all objects, and will one day prevail, pro¬
vided that, at some point, the spiritual T9
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
R C H I V E S
46
currents are strong enough to indicate a
line of conduct and make the unanimity
apparent.
In conclusion, I would say that art itself
is at the very basis of the great metamor¬
phosis that is already under way. If we go
on, in defiance of any logic, applying the
old architectural formulae we no longer
need today thick walls and so on we
shall be unable to tackle the problem of
cities today. The problem is to create "inte¬
riors" that will bring back serenity and
quiet; to eliminate noise; to flood them
with sunlight (modern technology has
done away with stone façades with holes
punched through them and replaced them
by glass walls, making it perfectly feasible,
technically and economically, in modern
buildings to open apartments on to sky¬
scapes and green landscapes); to arrange
the accommodation and the objects the
interior spaces, fixtures and fittings in
such a way as to make the maintenance
simple, the functions efficient and the life
lived there a life filled with tenderness;
and lastly, whilst achieving this harmo¬
nious combination ofaims, to keep prices
down to a level that is compatible with
modern economic conditions, a level it
would be madness to think of exceeding.
The world has never been rich and
building must be, as it has always been,
economical only the nineteenth century
indulged in extravagant spending for the
benefit of a few, to build homes that were
merely appliances for bringing happiness.
When large-scale industry, which has sub¬
sided into turning out countless futile con¬
sumer goods, finds its rightful path again
and produces goods intended for fertile
consumption, for the home, and at last
turns its attention to building, doing in
the factory all the marvellous things that
can be done only then will the result be
achieved. Let me illustrate these asser¬
tions with a striking example, that of the
car, which arouses general admiration
because it is well made and relatively
cheap. For ages I have been wearing myself
out making the point that if only we could
bridge the gap between that miracle, the
car, and our housing its planning and
design, its fixtures and fittings we could
provide modern society with admirable
accommodation that would be, in artistic
terms, as beautiful, as clear-cut and as
capable ofarousing emotion as the car or
the aircraft.
What we need today are people with
enough faith and enough strength of char¬
acter to persevere in drawing up even
in the nothingness of this world killed
stone dead by money the plans required
in every domain. One day those plans will
be the common heritage ofall. Just look at
my own domain of construction: one per
cent of my workmen already take an
interest in the question, and that's not bad.
When those plans are sufficiently vast and
pure for it to be possible to see in them that
unity towards which we are heading, the
workman will understand that what goes
on in the factory relates to his own home.
When, for instance, the first group of three
or four thousand homes is erected some¬
where using the same machines as he uses
today to build cars for the rich, he will
realize that society has new aims in sight.
That common faculty will then come into
operation that long-forgotten seed
love, the love that goes into all human
endeavours. That is where art will manifest
itself, where art will burst forth. I see no
other way of motivating art than through
the way in which work, any work, is under¬
taken. Then we shall no longer be
searching about, at earnest meetings like
this one, for ways to attract ordinary
people to the higher expressions of music
and the fine arts cubism, futurism,
expressionism, constructivism and so on,
and all the "isms" yet to be. Firmly
grounded upon enthusiastic participation
in the common pursuit, the many and
varied tiers of artistic expression will rise
up serene and bright. For my own part, I
believe in the so-called "higher" arts,
which I believe are not for everyone; but it
is heartrending for me to look at today's
dismal spectacle of the whole mass of
people indifferent or even hostile to what
they are doing. I believe in an imminent
upturn, an age ofharmony close at hand.
Greece shows us an example of such
harmony, the Middle Ages too; and Venice
sets one before our very eyes.
CZIFFRA:
a legacy of freedom
GvoHGY Cziffra, who died on 15 January
1994, left his native Hungary in 1956
and made his home in France. A fabulous
pianist who immediately won extraordi¬
nary acclaim, a prodigious virtuoso who
summoned up a shimmering tone from
the instrument in joyous communion with
the music, he appeared to audiences
around the world as a magician of
unheard-of talent. His effect upon them
was reminiscent of that produced, more
than a century before, by the likes of
Paganini or Liszt. Cziffra was indeed so
steeped, throughout his life, in the music
of the latter as to become the very incar¬
nation of Liszt.
Critics, however, soon began to look
disparagingly upon him, in the name of
"good taste", as being too far outside the
stylistic mainstream of the times. I studied
the piano in the 1960s, and I well remember
the disdain in my teacher's voice when he
came out with one of his favourite criti¬
cisms: "Oh no! Not like Cziffra!" (Strangely
enough, the popular French singer-com¬
poser Georges Brassens and György Cziffra
were in his eyes guilty of the same sins, a
pairing that was not to the discredit of
either of them). It is true that the musical
establishment cold-shouldered him. How
did he take it, he who had done so much for
musicians?
This "good taste", not unalloyed with
intolerance, affected me for a while. I was
taught that the flashes of inspiration and
thrills of delight conjured up by those fin¬
gers ofhis were too spontaneous to merit
approval. He had been my god, but I had
to abjure that religion. Is it any excuse to
say I was young at the time?
It was only later that I learned about his
life, a life of hardships and ordeals,
willpower and passion that may tomorrow
have passed into legend. It is perhaps
because of the way his playing radiates
energy and tenderness that it now has the
power to move me again. Whatever the
Pharisees may think, romanticism needs
warm-heartedness in order to blossom;
academicism stifles it. Such music is a
freely offered gift: are we capable ofhearing
the song of one who transfigures it?
Freedom in Cziffra's case meant never
giving in to any dogma, be it political or
artistic. In leaving us he bequeaths that
freedom to us, for which we give thanks.
STANY KOL
Unesco staff member
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
ULUGH BEG, THE ASTRONOMER-KING
byJasminaSopova
Fromhis birth in Soltaniyeh in 1394 to
his death in Samarkand in 1449, the
life story ofMahmud Turgay was one
ofwisdom and ofenthusiasm. A sagacious
ruler who has gone down in history by the
name bestowed on him of Ulugh Beg, the
"great prince", he is also known as the cel¬
ebrated scholar Guragon. Governor ofparts
of Khorasan and Mazandaran from 1407
onwards, he ascended the throne of the
Timurids only towards the end ofhis life, in
1447.
Grandson of the famous Mongol con¬
queror Timur, the founder of the Timurid
dynasty whose empire stretched from the
Mediterranean to Mongolia, and son of
Shah Rokh, a ruler famed for his peaceable
nature and his interest in the arts, Ulugh Beg
also made his contribution to the intellec¬
tual life of Samarkand and became one of
the leading makers of the Timurid Renais¬
sance. He enhanced the splendour and
prosperity of Samarkand, building a mag¬
nificent madrasah or religious school,
entirely overlaid with ceramics, a convent,
a caravanserai, the Alike Kukeltash great
mosque, and a small mosque of such
exquisite workmanship that it was known
as the "carved mosque". The madrasah
played a decisive part in the progress of
astronomy, Ulugh Beg's preferred field of
study, providing the point ofdeparture for
another colossal undertaking that the "great
prince" had in mind since childhood.
Fascinated by the thirteenth-century
Maraghah observatory, he gave orders, soon
after the opening of the modrasa/z, in about
1424, for his architects to build an obser¬
vatory that would be without equal any¬
where in the world. This was how the
Samarkand observatory, which for 300 years
was likewise to inspire astronomers and
architects, came into being.
It was erected on a rocky hill some
twenty metres high, set in a handsome
park and with living quarters around it.
The main building consisted of a long
tunnel, three storeys high, leading from
the entrance and plunging below ground
before curving back skywards, thus
forming a giant sextant, the largest astro¬
nomical instrument of its kind in the
world, with a forty-metre radius. The pur¬
pose in constructing it on such an
imposing scale was to enable more accu¬
rate observations to be made of the transit
of the moon and the planets through the
solar meridian. Equipped with an astro
labe and an armillary sphere, its primary
function was to obtain precise measure¬
ments of the length of the year and ofsuch
important astronomical data as the angle
between the trajectory of the sun and the
celestial equator.
The main scientific findings to come
out of these observations are to be found
in the set of astronomical tables known
as the Zij-i Gurgani, written in Persian,
Arabic and Turkish. Although they were
probably completed by about 1437, Ulugh
Beg kept making modifications to them
right until his death. Ulugh Beg must share
some of the credit for their accuracy, often
compared to that of modern tables, with
his first astronomer royal, Ghiyath al-Din
al-Kashi, who was held in the highest
esteem by his master.
Among the documents left by Ghiyath
al-Din to posterity, one that deserves par¬
ticular attention is a letter addressed to
his father in which he describes the work
of the observatory in minute detail and
The gigantic sextant of Ulugh Beg's
observatory, Samarkand. Tunnelled right
through the rock and with a 40-metre
radius, it was the largest astronomical
instrument of its time.
also sketches a portrait in words of Ulugh
Beg. Carefully pointing out that what he
was writing was not a gesture of defer¬
ence the ruler could not stand flat¬
terers but the strict truth, he tells us that
the "King of Islam" was already an accom¬
plished scholar by the age of twenty- five,
always avidly in search of knowledge. A
man of immense erudition, he knew nearly
all of the Qur'an by heart and had a talent
for quoting aptly from it. He wrote Arabic
very well and expressed himselfwith great
eloquence, rhetoric being among his
favourite exercises. He regularly attended
the madrasah, often surprising his lis¬
teners by his apposite comments and his
speed in mental arithmetic. He also had an
exceptional memory, as the following
anecdote shows. As befits a ruler, he was an
enthusiastic huntsman, and as befits a
scholar he kept a detailed record in his
notebook of what birds had been shot,
when and where. . . . When one day the
librarian despondently announced that
the notebook had disappeared, Ulugh Beg
cheered him up by saying he knew it all by
heart, and proceeded to dictate it all from
memory to his assistant, who took it down
in a new notebook. When later the original
turned up, the two texts were compared
and were found to differ in only four or
five particulars.
Forever gazing at the stars, Ulugh Beg
also wished to tell his future from them,
but the stars that had looked down benev¬
olently upon the scholar reserved a cruel
fate for the man. It is said that a great rift
occurred between him and his son Abd
al-Latif over the interpretation of their
respective horoscopes, and things came to
such a pass that the son finally, so it is
said, killed his father.
Thus it was that Samarkand came to
lose one whose image has gone down in
history as that of a simple, modest man, a
respected ruler, an eminent scholar, a poet,
historian and patron of the arts to whose
court the greatest minds of the time
flocked. Despite his early death, the scale
of his achievement was such that it
became known far beyond the frontiers
of the Islamic world and its influence on
astronomy extended into Europe.
JASMINA SOPOVA
¡s a Macedonian essayist who has written widely
on the art and literature of black Africa, the Indian
Ocean and the West Indies. 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS OF THE WORLD
ONE GIRL'S WAR
48
Alata and Mimmy confide in each other nearly
every day. In the secrecy of their little bedroom
that looks out on the hills ofSarajevo, a room full of
books, records and all those little treasures they
never like to be parted fromincluding one or
two cuddly toys to remind them they are still chil¬
drentell each other about the ordinary hap¬
penings of their daily life. Or, to be precise, Zlata
talks while Mimmy "listens".
The story begins in September 1991 . Zlata Fil-
ipovic is eleven. The holidays are over and it's back
to the old routine ofschool, music lessons, friends'
birthday parties, outings to the cinema, pancakes
at granny's house, skiing trips, satellite television,
and the still unfulfilled dream of getting Michael
Jackson to send his autograph. Zlata has an old
desk diary where she notes down anything that
takes her fancy during the day. Sometimes she
sticks in an amusing picture or adds a drawing,
and her sentences are frequently punctuated by
exclamations sometimes in English of "Super!",
"YO, BABY, YO!", "Tralalalala!", "I AM HAPPY",
"Yoopee" and the like. Mimmy has not yet been
given a name: she is a silent confidante, just an
ordinary diary, occasionally rewarded with a "ciao"
or a "night-night".
One day Zlata finds daddy in uniform and
mummy in tears. She is shattered to learn that her
father, a lawyer, has been ordered to report to his
police reservist unit. It's something they have to
adjust to, it's only for a while anyway, but a nagging
doubtcombined with fearcreeps into their
family life. Zlata knows nothing and cares nothing
about politics, but she begins to wonder about
what is happening in Slovenia and then in Croatia:
will Bosnia-Herzegovina be next? She is worried for
her parents' friend who lives in Dubrovnik, and
she shares their anxiety when the telephone lines
are cut	
After a month's silence, from 4 February to 5
March 1992, Zlata's entries start again: "My God!
There's been trouble in Sarajevo. On Sunday (1
March), a small group ofarmed civilians (according
to the TV) killed one of the guests at a wedding
and wounded a priest. On Monday (2 March) , there
were barricades all over town. There must have
been a thousand of them! We ran out ofbread." At
this point the nightmare begins. There are no more
"Yoopees" but "I'm frightened of WAR!", "MUR¬
DERERS!", "I'm sad Mimmy", "It's HORRIFIC, "I
NEED PEACE!". Spring, summer and autumn go by
andanewyear, 1993, begins. "The war's still going
on, you know". But sometimes the electricity comes
back on and it is possible to heat the apartment, to
cook and watch television, and sometimes there is
water as well, so things are all right: "It doesn't take
much to make people in Sarajevo happy."
Tuesday, 2 June 1993: "First water and elec¬
tricity and now gas. We are on the verge ofsuicide.
It's a DISASTER. Mimmy, I can't stand it any more.
I'm fed up of everything. I'm tired to death of all
these b... . I apologize for swearing, but I can't stand
it any more. I've really had enough. I feel more and
more like killing myself if those cretins up there
or down here don't kill me first. I've had all I can
take. I WANT TO SCREAM, TO SMASH EVERY
THING, TO KILL SOMEONE. I'm only human, I
can only take so much. I'm suffering terribly! I
SHALL BE IN A BETTER MOOD NEXT TIME."
Despite the increasingly frequent bouts ofdespair,
the will to live finally gets the better of the distress.
"I am still alive and healthy, my parents are alive and
healthy. ... So here we go, ON WE GO. But who
knows for how much longer?" A presentiment of
dread seeps insidiously into Zlata's life: "I have a
feeling that there will be nothing left here, not a
living soul."
After more than a year of bombardments, of
cold, hunger and sickness, of friends who have left
and friends who have died, nothing is as it was
before. The kitchen is the only room still in use.
Zlata's bedroom is an ideal target for the gunners
hiding up in the hills, and the room where they
keep the piano is just as dangerous. At night they
spread mattresses on the floor to stay out ofthe way
ofbullets flying in through the windows. They sleep
in the kitchen because it's freezing everywhere
else. Water is a precious commodity when it has to
be fetched from the standpipe or collected when it
rains; they drink it a mouthful at a time and wash
in a few drops, all in the kitchen. Then there is the
cellar: how can they ever forget the long hours
spent crouching there in the dark and cold, with the
infernal din of the bombardments in their ears?
When they do emerge, it is into a scene of total
destruction. Day by day, as the city is gradually
wiped out, the children ofSarajevo see their child¬
hood disappearing. The old post office, the mater¬
nity home, the Olympic village ... the age ofinno¬
cence goes up in smoke.
Life goes on, but interspersed with deaths, and
funerals take the place of festivities. People go on
falling in love, marrying and remembering one
another's birthdays, but neither the celebrations nor
the presents are like they used to be: people give
"German" cabbagesGerman because they were
bought with marks on the black market or "great
big kisses" because they have nothing else to give.
Zlata is a big girl now. The war is ruthless. Pedi¬
gree dogs are abandoned to become strays, bird¬
cages are emptied of their occupants, trees are
burned to ashes, and children grow up before their
time. Zlata now has other wonies and otherwishes:
to go to school a little more often, to get a little
more than a hundred grams of bread a day, not to
suffer the same fate as Anne Frank. Her entries are
different: "Tuesday, 21 September 1993: Dear
Mimmy, the historic match WAR vs PEACE has
been postponed. That means PEACE has lost
again." Mimmy has grown up too.
Word gradually got about that Zlata was
keeping a diary, and it was passed around in Sara¬
jevo before leaving towna press photographer,
Alexandra, one day took a copy to Paris. It is being
published all over the world, so that people can
hear, in seventeen different languages, its fear¬
some message: "War has taken hold ofus and will
not let us go". J.S.
Zlata's Diary: a child's life in Sarajevo'^ being
published in English by Viking Penguin/Penguin
Books. The passages quoted here were translated
from the French edition, LeJournal de Zlata,
published by Robert Laffont-Fixot, Paris.
JAZZ
Mulgrew Miller. Hand in Hand
CD RCA 01241 63153 2
Miller (piano), Eddie
Henderson (trumpet,
flugelhorn), Kenny Garrett
(alto and soprano sax), Joe
Henderson (tenor sax), Steve
Nelson (vibraphone), Christian
McBride (bass), Lewis Nash
(drums)
Mulgrew Miller is not only a
talented pianist and a warm¬
hearted human being but also a
top-class composer, as may be
judged from the marvellous
pieces on this recording, which
will provide listeners with a
source of endless pleasure. He is
a consummate harmonist,
whose orchestral ideas are
drawn in part from the piano
tradition of Memphis,
Tennessee, where he lived for a
while (and where one of his
mentors, Phineas Newborn, also
hailed from), and in particular
from Oscar Peterson and McCoy
Tyner. His bass-hand playing is
intelligent and his phrasing
surprises. Steve Nelson, one of
New York's most talented vibes
players, weaves a subtle
counterpoint. Eddie Henderson,
a wily instrumentalist with a
keen ear, not as well known to
the general public as he should
be, provides the right tie-in
between Kenny Garrett,
eloquent and incisive, and Joe
Henderson, lyrical and warm.
Roy Hargrove. Of Kindred Souls
CD RCA 01241 63154 2
Hargrove (trumpet,
flugelhorn), Marc Cary (piano),
Gregory Hutchinson (drums),
Rodney Whitaker (bass), Ron
Blake (tenor and soprano sax).
Guest artists: Gary Bartz (alto
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
RECENT RECORDINGS
by Isabelle Leymarie
sax), André Hayward
(trombone)
Hargrove is a trumpeter
accomplished beyond his years,
with a deep tone and a fertile
imagination. Gary Bartz, a
leading figure on the jazz scene
in the 1970s, re-emerges in fine
form on this compact after a
while in the wings. Marc Cary, a
young, inspired pianist who has
a great future ahead of him,
provides an incisive chordal
backing. This is music straight
from the heart, played by
musicians striving for
authenticity, unlike so many
performers of the previous
decade whose only concern was
for commercial success.
Horace Silver. It's Got To Be
Funk
CD Columbia 473877 2
Silver (piano), Oscar Brashear
(trumpet and flugelhorn), Bob
Summers, Ron Stout (French
horn), Suzette Moriarty
(trombone), Bob McChesney
(bass trombone), Bob Maize
(bass), Carl Burnett (drums).
Guest soloists: Red Holloway
(alto and tenor sax), Eddie
Harris (tenor sax), Branford
Marsalis (tenor sax), Andy Bey
(vocals)
Funky this record most
assuredly is. With the passing
years, the genial pianist from
Cape Verde has lost none of his
sparkle and sense of economy,
but his orchestrations have
grown richer since the time of
the Jazz Messengers and their
mellowness here is due to the
presence of several bass-register
brasses. Silver swings
uninhibitedly, leading his fellow
players on, and has great fun
with his titles, from "Funky
Bunky" to a "Yo' Mama's
Mambo" that is a mambo in
name only. He gives us his
inevitable "Song For My Father",
with vocal by Andy Bey, and,
with "The Lunceford Legacy"
and "When You're In Love",
shows what a master he is at the
art, so often a thankless one in
jazz, of the piano solo.
TRADITIONAL
MUSIC
Kenya. Musiques du Nyanza
Double CD album, Ocora
Radio France 560022/23
Ocora is to be congratulated
for putting together this
collection of the music, seldom
recorded, of Kenya. These
recordings are of the songs of
the Lake Nyanza (ex-Lake
Victoria) region, whose
population includes the Luo, a
people of herdsmen originating
from the Sudan who speak a
Nilotic language and have now
taken up farming, and the Gusii
and Kuria peoples, who are of
Bantu origin and whose
relations not always
harmonious with the Luo are
based on barter. The Luo
accompany themselves with
lyre-like instruments, rattles
attached to their ankles and
metal rings that keep the
rhythm. Their music, steeped in
the Sudanese tradition, is very
different from that of the Gusii
and Kuria, with its richer
instrumentation of lyres, flutes,
musical bows, whistles and
percussion instruments.
Deep Forest
CD Sony Music COL 474 1 78 2.
This disco /hip hop
compact, orchestrated with
rhythm box and synthesizer, is
an entertaining collage of
fragments of Baka songs from
Cameroon, songs from Burundi
and Senegal, and Pygmy songs
originally collected by two
musicologists, Hugo Zemp and
Shima Aron. Purists may take
umbrage, but these tracks lay no
claim to be anything more than
music to dance to. At the same
time they are, indirectly, a
tribute to the creativity of the
singers of the African forests,
anonymous masters of rhythm
and forerunners of hip hop, who
have previously inspired several
Western musicians, notably
Herbie Hancock and Philip
Glass.
Alfredo Rodriguez. Para Yoya
CD Bleu Caraïbes 82875-2
This is the fourth record by
the Cuban pianist Alfredo
Rodriguez, a leading figure on
the New York salsa scene in the
1970s who now lives in Paris.
Accompanied by Cuban, French
and British musicians, he takes
us on a musical tour through
some varied countryside:
guaguancó rumba tailing into
salsa ("N'importe qui, n'importe
quoi"), plain, straightforward
piano-playing ("Maria y
Maria"), a Yoruba chant ("Cante
a Oggún"), a tribute, with
traditional drums and lyrics
partly in patois, to the queen
("Yoya") of one of the "Tumba
francesa" societies (formed by
people of Haitian origin living in
eastern Cuba), a message of
greetings to Africa against a
background of bata drums
("Africa 93"), merengue
("Mariana"), and a lyrical
instrumental piece by the late
"Peruchin", the Cuban pianist,
with the composer's son on
guitar ("Te espero en el mar").
Those who like Caribbean
music will find much to enjoy in
this colourful medley.
CLASSICAL MUSIC
Kathleen Battle. Italian Opera
Arias
London Philharmonic
Orchestra conducted by Bruno
Campanella.
CD Deutsche Grammophon
435 866-2
Accompanied by the
London Philharmonic
Orchestra, the pianist John
Constable and the Ambrosian
Opera Chorus, chorus master
John McCarthy, the soprano
Kathleen Battle sings arias by
Bellini, Rossini and Donizetti.
Her voice, at once full and
restrained, preserves its
richness in the high notes, rising
in supple chromatic
progression. Endowed with a
profound musicality, she
cultivates austerity, but an
austerity charged with emotion.
She has an admirable mastery
of the art of rallentando, picking
out the notes without ever
"attacking" them. Though
Rossini sometimes seems
conventional, Bellini and
Donizetti have an ethereal
charm that is perfectly served
by this superb diva's voice.
Barbara Hendricks. La Voix du
Ciel
Double CD album. EMI
Classics 7 54909 2
Backed by various
orchestras, Barbara Hendricks
here sings an eclectic range of
vocal music, from the spirituals
of which she is particularly fond
and in the tradition of which
she grew up, to the Schubert
and Gounod versions of the "Ave
Maria", byway ofVilla-Lobos,
Richard Strauss, Fauré,
Schubert, Duparc and Ravel, not
forgetting Lehar's "Merry
Widow" and Loewe's "My Fair
Lady". Her mellifluous voice,
with its impressive vibrato,
lends itself easily to these many
changes of register, but to my
mind it is the classical
repertoire that suits her best
and gives scope to her talent in
all its majesty.
Palmarès de l'Année. Edition
1 994. Scarlatti, Strauss,
Janacek, Beethoven, Berlioz,
Verdi, Britten, Mozart, Chopin
etal.
Boxed set of 5 CDs. Deutsche
Grammophon 439 988 2
A wide-ranging selection,
made by various magazines and
academies, of the year's best
recordings. It includes such all-
time favourites as "The Magic
Flute", "Prélude à l'après-midi
d'un faune" and "Pictures at an
exhibition" as well as lesser-
known works such as Biber's
Sonata for two violins,
trombone and violone,
Jeinichen's Concerto in F major,
and Britten's "Four Sea
Interludes". Bernstein, Boulez,
Domingo, Von Karajan,
Pavarotti, Pogorelic and Fischer-
Dieskau rub shoulders with
other great musicians in perfect
harmony. Classical buffs will
renew their acquaintance with
some familiar pieces while the
more adventurous can sample
works that are less frequently on
offer.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
INTELLECTUALS AND THE
SCRAMBLE FOR PROFITS
I have been a subscriber to the CourierLor ten
years, and I have learned a great deal about
the world from it. However, although last
December's issue ("The meaning ofprogress: A
North-South debate") gave several able intel¬
lectuals an opportunity to express their feelings,
it was, to my mind, as restrained as ever in its
attitude towards the basic cause of the vio¬
lence, the crime and above all the poverty that
afflict the countries of the South, namely the
insensate scrambling for profits by the people
in charge of those countries' economies.
No clear denunciation of this evil seems
to me to emerge. Perhaps too many intellectuals
fit comfortably into the system. Why not a real
effort in your magazine to find a forward-
looking economic and political viewpoint?
André Pilet
Amfreville-s/les-Monts (France)
THE WEST STILL BELIEVES
IN PROGRESS
I have strong feelings about the article in your
December 1993 issue by Régis Debray ("A
Western myth"), which is as peremptory in
tone as it is cleverly written. While I agree with
some of the ideas expressed, some of the others
made me think . . . and want to challenge them.
At all events and this may be taken as a com¬
pliment to the author it was a thought-pro¬
voking piece, but one that, in my opinion, errs
on the side of exaggeration and presumption.
I do not agree that the West has ceased to
believe in progress and is increasingly back¬
ward-looking. I think such pessimism and scep¬
ticism merely reflect the confusion and impo¬
tence of an intelligentsia that unfortunately
dominates the media and publishing.
In reality, I find that ordinary people still
believe, and believe very strongly, in science
and progress. Each of them hopes to receive
better medical care and social benefits, to be
better educated and informed, to be treated
with greater consideration, to enjoy more
freedom and to see his or her children obtain
better positions though education.
I disagree with Régis Debray when he con
trasts two time-schemes, the "cumulative time"
of scientific and technological development
and the "repetitive time" of the world ofpolitics
and symbols. This seems to me to state the
case in too cut-and-dried a way. Could anyone
deny that progress in science and technology,
i.e. rational thought, has brought about a
gradual evolution in moral, political and even
religious ideas, in mentalities and mores? Exam¬
ples I would quote are personal and political
rights, freedom of thought and expression,
women's rights, children's rights . . . even animal
rights; and there is nothing to show that this
movement is reversible quite the contrary,
as Michel Serres demonstrates in the interview
at the beginning of this issue with his idea of the
"natural contract".
Nor do I agree with the author when he
asserts that "the noble advocates of progress"
(why the sarcasm?) were wrong when "they
predicted . . . the end of religious supersti¬
tions" an assertion that is, to say the least,
premature. Religious superstitions (not to be
confused with genuine belief) have greatly
declined in our societies based on rational
progress: witchcraft and magic have given way
as scientific medicine has advanced, and over
the last century fewer and fewer of the "mira¬
cles" occurring at Lourdes have been accredited
by the Church.
I do not agree with him either when he
speaks of "each stage in the movement towards
technological and economic unity reactivating
ethnic and cultural diversity at a new level".
This does not seem to be borne out in western
Europe and North America, as the European
Union and North American Free Trade Area
show. On the contrary, where there is a deep¬
ening of ethnic, cultural and national differ¬
ences it often occurs as a reaction to the frus¬
tration felt at not being able to take sufficient
advantage ofmodern technical and economic
progress.
I disagree with those who trace back the
concept of progress to the "messianism" of
Judaeo-Christian tradition without explaining
why it took until the seventeenth century for
that concept to emerge in societies that had,
after all, been invoking that tradition for 1400
years! I believe it was, on the contrary, the weak¬
ening of religious messianism, under the
impact of rationalism, that allowed the idea of
gradual material and human progress to take
root. The ideology of human progress, on the
one hand, and religious tradition on the other,
seem to me fundamentally incompatible.
Bernard Goldstein
Tulle (France)
SO
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: © Dimitrl Selesneff, Paris. Page 2: © Mona Yazbeck, Lebanon. Pages 5, 6-7: ©Jean
Malaurie, Paris. Page 9: © Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris. Galerle Huguette Bères, Paris. Page 10:
Théodule Gilou ©Ask Images, Paris. Pages I I, 32, 36: ©Alain Guillou, Le Croisic, France. Page !2:
Haley © Sipa Press, Paris. Pages 13, 16, 20, 22, 35: Michelangelo Durazzo © ANA, Paris. Page 15:
Dailloux © Rapho, Paris. Pages 1 7, 23: Ron Giling © Panos Pictures, London. Page 1 8: © Jean-Loup
Charmet, Paris. Bibliothèque des Arts Décoratifs, Paris. Page 1 9: G. Sioen © Rapho, Paris. Page 2 1 :
Mattes © Explorer, Paris. Pages 24, 26: Mireille Vautier © ANA, Paris. Page 25: José Vicente
Resino/Black Star © Rapho, Paris. Page 27: Ghislaine Bras © Ask Images, Paris. Pages 28, 29, 30
(below): Joe Viesti/Viesti Associates © Ask Images, Paris. Page 30 (above): Jean Philippe Varin ©
Jacana, Paris. Page 31: © Lions Club, Illinois, U.S.A. Pages 33, 34: ©Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris. Page
37: Olivier Martel © Explorer, Paris. Pages 38, 39: Babout © Rapho, Paris. Page 40: © Fabian, Paris.
Pages 42, 43, 44 (below): © Lyndsay Chong Seng, Seychelles. Page 44 (above): Daniel Simon ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 44 (middle): Michel Pignères © Gamma, Paris. Page 45: Doisneau © Rapho,
Paris. Page 46: © Gamma, Paris. Page 47: © Charles Lénars, Paris.
TheUNESCO
¿Courier
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 32 languages and in Braille by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
3 1 , rue François Bonvin, 750 1 5 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation:
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin {Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant:
Selection ¡n Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanmi (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Serpil Gogen (Ankara)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egara (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Victor Stelmakh (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45 68.45 65
I year: 21 1 French francs, 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies arc sent to the editor. Signed arti¬
cles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be sup¬
plied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines arc written by the Unesco Courier staff. The bound¬
aries on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (I) Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann
Arbor, Michigan 48 1 00 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head
Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, USA; (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old
Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 4469 1 . U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI -AVRIL 1994
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrter de I'Unesco.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL, 2. rue Christophe-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 0041-5278 N^' 4-I994-OPI-94-525A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
TOP latina
C'EST ...
ESPACE
CHAMPERRET
PARIS
3, 4, 5 JUIN 1994
LE PREMIER
SALON
DE L'AMÉRIQUE LATINE
EN FRANCE
DE NOMBREUX EXPOSANTS
Compagnies aériennes
Tours operators
Agences de voyages
Transporteurs internationaux
Banques et assurances
Importateurs de boissons et de produits
alimentaires
Restaurateurs
Hôtellerie
Artisanat
Éditeurs (livres et musiques)
Medias (radio presse et TV)
Éducation
Art et culture
Associations culturelles
Ambassades
Chambres de commerce
Organisations internationales
UN CONCEPT INÉDIT
ESPACE ÉCHANGE PROFESSIONNEL
Opportunités d'investissements,
implantations, secteurs d'activités,
pôle de rencontre multilatéral et décisionnel
ESPACE CONFÉRENCE
Économie, géostrategie, culture, tourisme
ESPACE ÉVÉNEMENT
Concerts traditionnels et contemporains
Petits déjeuners professionnels
Cocktails littéraires
Grande soirée de gala
Prix d'entrée public 30 F Étudiants, Chômeurs, Groupes (1 0 minimum) 20 F Visa pour les 3 jours 50 F
CONTACT : JOSÉ ORTIZ CHRISTIAN MARTINEAU
Tel : (1) 43 48 60 40 Fax : (1) 43 48 48 1 1 - Minitel : 3615 SOL A SOL
lat na
MM M\
SARAJEVO
From 1 1 to 22 April 1 994 an exhi¬
bition of seventeen wood engrav¬
ings executed in 1 993 by Sarajevo
artists will be held at Unesco
Headquarters in Paris. Witnesses
to the suffering caused by the
destructive fury of men, the
engravings also exemplify the
power of art to resist barbarism.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
trve
«gS^5
¡FWftSWS»
-agía**:
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine
published in 32 languages and read by hundreds of thousands of
people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal respect
for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms... without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
MONTH, ESSENTIAL READING
TODAY
UNDERSTANDING
TOMORROW
PROBLEMS
A TINE TO LOVE ... WATER OF LIFE ... MINORITIES... WHAT IS MODERN?... RHYTHH, GESTURE AND TH
SACRED... TINE TO DISARN... THE STORY OF NUMBERS... A NORTH-SOUTH DEBATE: THE MEANING O
PROGRESS... DESERTS... WORLDS WITHIN WORDS... HUNAN RIGHTS, THE UNFINISHED TASK... NODER
MANAGEMENT AND LOCAL TRADITIONS...
FRANCOIS NITTERRAND... JORGE AHADO... RICHARD ATTENBOROUCH... JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE... JEAN
LACOUTURE... FEDERICO HAYOR... NAGUIB NAHFOUZ... SENBENE OUSNANE... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY...
FRÉDÉRIC ROSSIF... HINNERK BRUHNS... CAHILO JOSÉ CELA... VACLAV HAVEL... SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV...
ERNESTO SÁBATO... GRO HARLEN BRUNDTLAND... CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS... LEOPOLDO ZEA... PAULO FREIRÉ...
DANIEL J. BOORSTIN... FRANCOIS JACOB... HAND DIBANGO... FAROUK HOSNY... SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN...
JORGE LAVELLI... LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG... TAHAR BEN JELLOUN.,. GABRIEL GARCÍA MAROUEZ... JACQUES-
YVES COUSTEAU... NELINA HERCOURI... CARLOS FUENTES... JOSEPH KI-ZERBO... VANDANA SHIVA... WILLIAM
STYRON... OSCAR NIEHEYER... NIKIS THEODORAKIS... ATAHUALPA YUPANQUI... HERVÉ BOURGES... ABDEL
RAHNAN EL BACHA... SUSANA RINALDI... HUBERT REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS... A LETTER FRON FREUD TO
EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY... CHARLES NALANOUD... UMBERTO ECO... OLIVER STONE... ANDRÉ BRINK... JANES D.
WATSON... ANOS OZ... MICHEL SERRES... THÉODORE NONOD... YVES COPPENS... EDOUARD J.MAUNICK...
JEAN MALAURIE...
REWRITI COMMUNISM
FEATURING INTERVIEW ASTROPHYSICIST
TRINH XUAN THUAN
]]>
</page>
</document>
