<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="098006eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A CODE FOR
LIVING
THE ETHICS OF HUMAN ENGINEERING
icattcttaaaggtcaggctctacaaatonaaccca
agaccctaatttgggttcacctcagtc -aatc
tatgtgagtaactggaagatactgat^ ^caa
:agct-ttgttgcgcaggtcaacatgt<?« tgg
attccaccaatattattataattcctày ;tga
atcgagttcagap*
"gttaagtgo
INTERVIEW WITH
tctaccaaggtc
tgaatacttcct
tgtggactatta^
:ctagcatt"ta"taiJ
tgggtcatcagccaacs
aaacaggcgtgatlJratt *.
aaaactgttgctt-fètaggattt
"tggaaaccaatgcttactai
tggtacatgctttaacttt-
agaagaaaactagctaaag
^atc
ca
-t
^iac:
tc;
ja*
.aa(
<ggcc
iaai
NOËLLE LENOIR
HERITAGE
THE TOWER OF LONDON
:nvironment
OF MEN AND MOUNTAINS
M 1205 22.00 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
Pulsating
Valley
oil on wood ( 1 20 x 150 cm)
by Anne Yanoushka
de Lamater
"My semi-figurative
paintings are inspired by
musical rhythms,
mysticism (particularly
Zen Buddhism) and my
own internal life," writes
the Canadian artist Anne
Yanoushka de Lamater.
"They represent
overlapping realities,
fluctuating tides of
consciousness, expanding
and contracting." She
clearly drew on these
sources of inspiration to
produce the painting
shown here, which
"originated in a dream in
which I was flying over
mountain peaks and
valleys, In a light,
harmonious state."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
I Contents
SEPTEMBER 1994
Cover:
The 4 letters of the genetic
alphabet, A, G, C and T. Variations
in their sequence make each
person unique and Irreplaceable.
A CODE FOR LIVING
THE ETHICS OF HUMAN ENGINEERING
5 Interview with Noëlle Lenoir
HERITAGE Î
The Tower of London
by Francis Leary
Melina's last battle
GREENWATCH |
Of men and mountains
by France Bequette
UNESCO NEWSBRIEFS.. .2
PORTRAIT Í
Mercator, cartographer of genius
by Jean Portante
ANNIVERSARY <
Seoul at age 600
A city built to face in the right direction
by Choe Chong-Hyon and Yi Tong-Ok
GLOBAL VIEW '
Human development:
a question of security
ARCHIVES |
Haiku by Bashô
LISTENING <
The Maroons, musicians of freedom
by Isabelle Leymarie
REFLECTIONS <
Elvis the African
2/ The return of the chief: a royal welcome
by George Darley-Doran
Letters to the Editor !
I Scientific knowledge and human
dignity by Jean Dausset
The prospects for gene therapy
by Renato Dulbecco
Prenatal diagnosis: foretelling the
quality of life by Hans Galjaard
1 Genetics in the market-place
by Ezra N. Suleiman
I Unesco and bioethics
by Georges B. Kutukdjian
> Fact file
To find out more...
Consultant: Georges B. Kutukdjian
29
Commentary by Federico Mayor
TB& UNESCO
COURIER
47th year
Published monthly in 3 1
languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding anda truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER I94S
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE. UNESCO
(JPURIER
47th YEAR
Published monthly ¡n 32 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin. 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant:
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigarma (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Bangla: Abdullah A.M. Sharafuddin (Dhaka)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Te! : 45.68.45.65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO Couner", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompa¬
nied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced
in microform (microfilm and/o-- microfiche) by: (I) UNESCO, 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100 U.SA; (3) NCR. Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc.,
1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York. U.SA: (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster. Ohio 4469 1 . U.SA
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG {Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL CI - SEPTEMBRE 1994.
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71842 - DIFFUSE PAR L£S N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL 2. rue Christophe-Plantm
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 0041-5278 N; 9-I994-OPI-94-529A
nth by month
Changes are occurring so thick and fast in so many areas that the
world as we knew it only ten years ago has altered beyond recog¬
nition. All the familiar landmarks that we had regarded as permanent
fixtures of our lives since the end of the Second World War have been
relegated to a past which is itself already growing steadily dimmer
in our memories. Yet the shape of things to come is still not clear.
We are in a twilight zone, shrouded in the mists of a new dawn that
is slow in coming. It is a time of questioning, a time conducive to
daring thoughts and new ideasbut also a time fraught with all
manner of dangers and violence.
Unesco is at the heart of the efforts being made to pave the way
for a future in which the spirit of peace will vanquish the spirit of war,
in which freedom and the rule of law, justice and solidarity will
become key values for all of us.
The Couner is endeavouring to play its part in this ambitious enter¬
prise by continuing to broaden its coverage and to eschew blinkered
and dogmatic thinking.
You will probably have noticed that we have been gradually intro¬
ducing a number of changes in recent issues. These stem from
our concern to put readers in closer touch with the vast range of pre¬
sent-day developments and to remain fully attentive to their ideas
and criticisms.
To make for easier reading and consultation changes are being
made in the presentation of the monthly theme. The regular features
section is being expanded. International affairs will be consistently
followed up through a "global view" feature that will situate the activ¬
ities of Unescoespecially as described by the Director-General in
his regular "Commentary"in their world context. Reports on Bio¬
sphere Reserves, appearing between the Greenwatch section and the
Heritage feature, will also add to our coverage of Unesco's main fields
of activity.
As we endeavour to go on improving the Courier's editorial style
and the quality of its articles and illustrations, we look forward to
benefitting from your support and suggestions, and above all from
your discriminating readership.
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-11 and 42-43.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
NOËLLE
LENOIR
talks to
Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
The first woman member of France's Constitutional
Council, Noëlle Lenoir has been president of Unesco's Inter¬
national Bioethics Committee since it was established in
September 1993. She also chairs the group of advisors on
the ethics of biotechnologies of the Commission of the
European Communities. A specialist in public law, she is
the author of a major report on bioethics, Aux frontières
de la vie (2 vols., 1991, La documentation française, Paris).
In what respects are advances in the life
sciences, and especially in genetics, impor¬
tant landmarks?
There are stages in the history of sci¬
ence when knowledge takes such great
steps forward that our understanding of the
world is completely transformed. The dis¬
coveries involving the human genome
belong to one of these stages.
By choosing the plants they gathered
and by influencing the diversification of
animal species to cater for their own needs,
human beings have always been involved
in genetics without realizing it.
The era of the life sciences really began
in the eighteenth century, when the idea of
the evolution of species emerged in what
might be called an intuitive manner,
through the work of Buffon1 in particular.
These insights were later borne out by the
observations made by Gregor Mendel2 in
the second half of the nineteenth century,
even though he did not have a clear grasp
of the idea of "genes" and never made
explicit reference to them.
It was not until the twentieth century,
however, that genetics as an independent
scientific discipline really came into its own.
Progress in the field has since been marked
by increasingly striking discoveries, such
as the unravelling of the double helix struc¬
ture of DNA by Francis Crick and James
Watson in 1953, the elucidation of the work¬
ings of messenger RNA by François Gros,
François Jacob and Jacques Monod in the
1 960s, the emergence of genetic engineering
techniques in the 1970s, and by the most
recent developments in physical and genetic
mapping.
These discoveries are revolutionary not
only for the history of science but also for
the history of humanity. For the first time,
human beings now have access to knowl¬
edge about their own life mechanisms
through genetics, neurobiology and embry¬
ology. Also for the first time, as a result of
genetic engineering, they can take steps to
alter the human genome. They could also
acquire the capability to transform their
own species.
This is what manypeople regard as the
mind-boggling side ofgenetics.
I think there are three reasons for this.
First, as a result of the astounding devel¬
opments in genetics in the past forty years
or so, people are now faced with the hard
facts about their condition. The explana¬
tion of life, and of human life in partic¬
ular, is capable of bringing about a pre¬
cisely programmed transformation of
human beings.
Second, this capacity to alter living
things is not just something that is theo¬
retical or might happen one day. It results
from techniques that are already being
used at least as far as other species are
concerned. Transgenesis the process
whereby a "foreign" gene is inserted into
the reproductive cells of a living organism,
so that it is altered and becomes capable of
transmitting certain properties to its off¬
spring is already being used on animals
and plants. We are now creating laboratory
animals, into which we inject, say, cancer
genes, so that they can then be used as
models for human diseases. Eventually we
shall be able to "humanize" animals by
injecting them with human genes for trans¬
plantation purposes, so that their organs
will become compatible with the body of
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
the person receiving the transplant. Exper¬
iments on producing transgenic animals
are even being carried out in order to pro¬
duce improved stock, such as pigs with a
reduced amount of fat. But the terrible
question arises as to whether there is a
taboo on applying transgenesis to the
human species, even though there might be
a therapeutic justification for doing so.
The third reason why people are bewil¬
dered is because of the incredible short¬
ening of the time-lag between the making
of a discovery and the time of its applica¬
tion. As a result of this, the gap between
different cultures is growing wider, since
some adapt more quickly than others. At
the same time, we can see cases of countries
in the forefront of research where there is
a growing mismatch between the wealth of
new possibilities being offered by science
and people's mentalities and ways of life
and their view of the world. This "credi¬
bility gap" is becoming even wider because
of the speed at which the media pass on
information about scientific discoveries to
the public. In the past, before discoveries
became public knowledge, they had to go
through a process of verification, publi¬
cation and discussion within the scientific
community. Nowadays, it is accepted that
even though the results of research may
only be approximate or tentative, they can
be published.
The technological and scientific age in
which we live can accordingly be regarded
as both positive and negative. It is positive
because of the hopes aroused by science as
a result of the progress made in therapeutic
treatment, the relief of human suffering, the
improvement of individual and collective
welfare, and the creation of forms of cul¬
ture which the mass of the population can
enjoy or which offer increased scope for
individual freedom. It is negative because
of the increasing duality of the societies
in which we live. Inequalities exist not
only between rich countries and poor,
between those which have research centres
and industries and those which do not,
but also within each national or cultural
community. It is absolutely imperative for
the sake of democracy worldwide that
everybody should be informed about what
is going on in the life sciences, so that they
can have some idea of the changes taking
place. Over and above the struggle against
inequality, what is at stake is the protection
of rights and freedoms. Ignorance and false
knowledge are sources of prejudice. In
genetics, any misreading of the facts can
also give rise to behaviour that is liable to
undermine those freedoms.
What kindofsocio-cultural upheavals
are being caused by genetics?
Research on the human genome has
implications that are not exclusively sci¬
entific or medical. They lead on to appli¬
cations which affect all aspects ofpeople's
lives, whether it be private life (their choice
of life-styles and consumption patterns;
their perception of their genetic "identity");
family life (the plans people make as couples
or parents; their relations with other family
members); or life as members of society
(health protection and access to medical
care; the availability of jobs or state or pri-
Confronted
with the upheavals
due to the progress
of genetics,
one wonders towards
what Kind of society
and what new
planetary equilibrium
we head.
vate health insurance; provision for chil¬
dren's education, and so on).
Particular emphasis should be laid on
two areas of thinking. The first is bound up
with the concentration of research in the
industrial countries, which is giving rise
to economic and socio-cultural imbalances.
There is an urgent need to study the poten¬
tial spin-off from this research in the devel¬
oping countries, so that its applications
can be controlled. The second area is con¬
cerned with the eternal question about the
meaning of life and the human condition.
It would be dangerous to imagine that
there is some kind of scientific answer to
this question. Science does not relieve us of
our responsibility as individuals and mem¬
bers of the human family quite the oppo
site. The quickening pace of scientific
progress could even be said to make us
more aware of the fact that "our future is
not written . . . and the human condition is
incompatible with certainty".3
Is this where bioethics comes in?
Bioethics arose out of fundamental ques¬
tions that were asked about the influence of
the development of molecular biology on
the future of humanity. The term appears
to have been coined in the United States in
the 1970s, when genome manipulation
techniques, what we call "genetic engi¬
neering", were being developed.
With the passing of time, these ques¬
tions have become increasingly crucial. In
view of the upheavals caused by the devel¬
opment of genetics, people are wondering
about the kind of society we are moving
towards and the kind of planetary balance
that will be struck.
Bioethics is not confined to thinking
about the relationship between science and
society. It is concerned with the relations
between human beings and nature in all its
biological diversity, including the nature of
human beings themselves.
This may account for the constant
progress being made by the ethics move¬
ment all over the world. Nowadays, it is
impossible to keep pace with the number of
ethics committees (see page 27) and ethics
research centres being set up. Although
bioethics is essentially multidisciplinary, it
is now being taught as a subject in its own
right in universities, schools and vocational
training institutions.
The human genome mapping pro¬
grammes launched in the United States,
Europe and Japan are all being matched by
special funding for ethics research. Ethics
has become an important feature of
research and health policies and even of
industrial strategies. It now addresses itself
to decision-makers, in both the public and
the private sectors.
Bioethics is a way of thinking about
our future and our values, but at the same
time it is a form of language. It enables
specialists to enter into a dialogue with
decision-makers and the public, to work
together on the problems of humanity
raised by scientific knowledge and to
ensure harmonious relations between indi¬
viduals and society and, in the final
analysis, the survival of the human species.
It has to be acknowledged that
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
bioethics has grown up in a context in
which doubts are being voiced about the
general idea of progress as being intrinsi¬
cally a source of good. In this respect, it
reflects the anxieties of our age.
What part do scientists and doctors
play in all this?
A decisive one, obviously. However, the
problems that have to be resolved in order
to contend with the new situations cre¬
ated by science go far beyond the sphere of
responsibility of scientists and doctors.
Take the case of prenatal diagnosis. It may
reveal anomalies in the foetus or some
more or less serious handicap or disease
that is bound to affect the unborn child.
This diagnosis is made in response to a
pressing social demand from parents. How
will the parents react if the diagnosis reveals
an anomaly? Who will help them make
the decisive choice as to whether or not to
let the pregnancy go on to its term, try in
utero treatment that is still at the experi¬
mental stage, or else prepare to accept the
disabled child and provide it with the nec¬
essary postnatal care?
As knowledge and its applications
grow, an increasing number of decisions of
this kind have to be taken by doctors, fam¬
ilies and communities.
Some of the advances made by science
do provide solutions. Take the case of in
vitro fertilization. When it becomes pos¬
sible to cryopreserve oocytes, a process
which is currently at the experimental
stage, it will no longer be necessary to
freeze surplus embryos. Other advances
made in biology and genetics pose new
questions, however. This is the case with
"micro-injection", which can make it pos¬
sible to choose a child's sex by separating
out the X and Y spermatozoa, although
this is not the purpose for which it is
intended. This technique, which is designed
as a remedy for male infertility, consists of
the in vitro injection of a spermatozoon
into an oocyte, so that it becomes fertilized.
The resulting embryo is then transferred
into the womb by in vitro fertilization.
Should we allow this kind of selection
process for choosing the sex of an unborn
child?
There is also the question of diagnosis
before conception, if a man and woman
belong to families that are carriers of some
transmissible defect, they can have a genetic
examination. If they both carry the same
defect, they may decide not to have chil¬
dren. In Cyprus, the Orthodox Church, in
agreement with the government, has used
this type of premarital examination to
check the spread of thalassaemia, a very
common genetic disease on the island. By
appealing to people's sense of responsi¬
bility, it has proved possible to cut the
morbidity rate of the disease by half.
This is one example of how decisions
involving reproduction can be monitored
at the instance of the political authorities
and society, with a helping hand from the
church. Other examples can be cited. In
China, an interventionist approach seems
to be the practice in similar situations.
There may be a temptation to adopt an
authoritarian attitude, especially in societies
facing serious difficulties in allocating
health resources, largely due to demo¬
graphic factors.
How does bioethics differfrom scien¬
tific ethics generally?
Bioethics is not the ethics of the bio¬
logical sciences. It is not the same thing as
a code of professional conduct. It is not
concerned with professional practice but
with its impact on society. The key idea
behind bioethics is respect for human dig¬
nity. This idea runs through all currents of
ethical thinking, including religions. One
of the basic instruments in bioethics is the
Nuremberg Code drawn up by the World
Medical Association in 1947, following
the revelations made about the excesses
perpetrated in the name of science under
Nazism. This document lays down the
principle that anybody invited to take part
in medical experiments should give his or
her consent. The Nuremberg Code stipu¬
lates that man cannot be an object for sci¬
ence. The principles of human dignity,
individual freedom, equal rights and soli¬
darity appear to command an international
consensus as guidelines for bioethics.
Based on these foundations, bioethics
is a way of resolving conflicts of values. The
conflict between community pressures and
individual freedom, for example, is illus¬
trated by the case of genetic screening pro¬
grammes. Should such programmes be
made compulsory in the interests of public
health or should it be left to the discre¬
tion of individuals to decide whether or
not it is advisable to undergo tests,
knowing that the results may be fraught
with consequences for themselves and their
families?
The French National Ethics Com¬
mittee recently gave an opinion on the
subject. The issue was whether screening
for trisomy 21 (Down's syndrome) should
be compulsory or voluntary for certain
women. The Committee considered that
people had to face up to their responsibil¬
ities. It recommended that, in certain cases,
doctors should be required to suggest as a
matter of course that families "at risk" be
tested. Those families would then be free to
decide whether to accept the suggestion
or not.
From the standpoint of bioethics, are
there are a certain number of rules that
are valid for all countries and in all com¬
munities?
I feel that bioethics rules out a dogmatic
approach, any idea of one culture domi¬
nating another. For instance, some African
communities develop a stronger sense of
solidarity than that in Western communi¬
ties, which are often individualistic. Yet
the art of living together is not practised
only in the context of villages, regions and
countries. Nowadays, it has to be envisaged
in planetary terms. From this point of view,
bioethics tries to set up a bridge between
cultures, so that the new powers arising out
of genetics do not make discrimination
and exclusion any worse.
What about eugenics?
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Eugenics is a form of racism based on a
pseudo-rationalist scientific approach.
There can be no question of science
"improving" the human species, in the
sense of some people being of greater value
than others. We must make sure that the
folly of genetic purity does not take over
from the folly of racial purity.
The only way to oppose eugenics is to
ensure that human rights come first.
Human biodiversity is sometimes said to
be proof of the absurdity of racism. I per¬
sonally am embarrassed by this sort of
talk. Can we draw any social or philo¬
sophical conclusions from the fact that we
'are all different? Probably not, because
biodiversity is simply a fact of life. People
are what matter. The idea of "scientifi¬
cally" manufacturing a set of people exclu¬
sively composed of individuals with certain
characteristics must be outlawed because it
runs counter to the dignity of human
beings, who are unique, free and respon¬
sible for their actions. Even so, we must ask
why, for the sake of biodiversity, we should
seek to preserve some human communities
from any outside inputs. What is unique
about human beings is that they can adapt
to their environment and change them¬
selves, at the same time as they change the
natural world around them. In the words
of the American novelist Paul Auster4,
"Each man is the entire world, bearing
within his genes a memory of all mankind".
Does bioethics have anything to tell
us about North-South disparities?
Bioethics must help to obliterate the
disparities between North and South
arising from the quickening pace of sci¬
entific research and its applications. Sci¬
ence, economics and social development
are all interlinked. The economically
advanced countries are virtually the only
ones to invest in research' and they are also
the first to reap the benefits from it.
It is in a bid to break with this trend
that UNESCO, under the impetus of Fed¬
erico Mayor, has pledged not only to con¬
tribute to the human genome programme
but to foster intercultural dialogue on the
subject through the International Bioethics
Committee. I shall merely mention the
new generation of medicines that will be
developed through the progress made by
genetics. They will not be standardized
medicines but will be individually designed
to eradicate diseases at their source. It
would be quite wrong to use them exclu¬
sively to treat the diseases found in the
industrial countries. With the spread of
Aids, we can no longer say that the diseases
of our time are respecters of geographical
barriers. We have to take a worldwide
approach to human health.
Even so, considerable difficulties are
involved in framing a policy for sharing
between rich and poor. How are we going
to apply gene therapy in the countries of
the South say a therapeutic operation on
an individual's genome, so as to provide a
missing gene and counter the effects of a
pathological defect? How can we make
sure that the people in those countries can
enjoy the benefit of new medicines pro¬
duced using gene therapy techniques,
whose potential is enormous? How can
we ensure that the new generation of vac¬
cines produced by genetic engineering can
be manufactured and distributed all over
the world?
Areyou suggesting that there should be
a universalist approach to bioethics?
It's essential. Bioethics, I repeat, must be
based on human rights.
Even so, the time has come to lower the
temperature of a debate that sometimes
gets so heated that the public becomes
bewildered. We must take account of a
number of factors. In the first place, we
should remember that human history has
always gone hand-in-hand with scientific
advances that have revolutionized civi¬
lizations. The discoveries made on the
human genome form part of that history
and people have to be capable of coping
with the issues they raise. Secondly, it is not
surprising that seemingly desirable changes
brought about by the applications of
genetics should give rise to anxiety and
even to opposition. However and this is
the third important point bioethics has to
distance itself from an outlook that is dom¬
inated by the risk of taking the wrong
turning. In other words, it is urgent to
switch from a defensive attitude to a more
balanced approach that makes allowance
for benefits and risks alike. Scientific
progress should be neither worshipped
nor reviled. Nevertheless, it calls on the
universal conscience to provide a guar¬
antee that everyone-individuals and soci¬
eties alike-has access to it and that it will
not get out of control.
Bioethics accordingly requires us to
be "good, honest and virtuous", regardless
of the economic and power issues at stake
in scientific competition. This being so, it
is bound to be a universal ethic of respon¬
sibility and solidarity.
1 The French naturalist and writer Georges Louis
Leclerc, Comte de Buffon (1707-1788). Through
his study of the earth and its geological ages, he
became increasingly convinced that the universe
had come into being through a slow process of
transformation and that living species were not set
in a hard and fast mould. He paved the way for the
theories of evolution. Editor
2 The Austrian monk and botanist Gregor Mendel
(1822-1884). His work on the hybridization of
peas led to his discovery in 1 865 of the laws gov¬
erning the transmission of hereditary characters
which bear his name. He is regarded as the
founding father of genetics. Editor
3 Primo Levi, in Other People's Trades, New
York, Summit Books, 1989.
4 The Invention ofSolitude, New York, Sun Press,
1982.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Ifmisused, our
growing knowledge
ofhuman genetics
could have
disastrous
consequences.
Should there be any
restrictions on
research and above
all on the
application of its
results!
knowledge and
human dignity by Jean Dausset
Above, freeze-dried DNA
produced by the Human
Polymorphism Study Centre In
Paris, founded by Jean Dausset
In 1984. The Centre provides
the international scientific
community engaged in gene
mapping with DNA obtained
from 61 families (800
Individuals) regarded as having
been "healthy" for several
generations.
Molecular biology has invaded all or
very nearly all areas of medical research,
investing scientists engaged in research in
human genetics with heavy responsibilities.
Perhaps for the first time, these researchers
are now faced with two agonizing questions:
how far should they go in their research and
how should their findings be applied?
The answer to the first question is quite
unequivocal. There are no limits to knowledge,
which is the pride and honour of humanity.
We are the only creatures capable of under¬
standing and influencing our environment.
Under no circumstances should research be
halted or even slowed down. It must be pursued
on condition that studies made on human beings
respect human dignity.
In theory, the answer to the second question
is also unequivocal but it nevertheless raises
some serious problems. It is unequivocal because
new knowledge should be used for the good of
humanity and not be diverted to serve the inter¬
ests of individuals or communities which do
not respect human rights. In the case of human
genetics, unwise use of new techniques could
have disastrous consequences.
There can be no doubt that the powers now
vested in research scientists impose new oblig¬
ations on them and raise crucial ethical issues. We
are only too aware that all technical progress has
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
"Multi-blotters", powerful
instruments used for analysing
DNA at the Généthon laboratory
near Paris. Founded in 1990,
Généthon is the first laboratory
to be equipped with facilities on
an industrial scale, in order to
speed up the mapping of human
genes.
IO
JEAN DAUSSET,
French medical doctor, is
internationally known for his
work on tissue groups and the
HLA system, which has been
instrumental in the considerable
progress made in organ
transplants and grafts and
earned him a share (with George
Snell and Baruj Benacerraf) of
the 1980 Nobel Prize for
Physiology or Medicine. He is
Professor of Immuno-
Haematology at the
tarisboisière-Saint Louis Medical
Faculty in Paris and of
Experimental Medicine at the
Collège de France. In 1984, he
set up the Human Polymorphism
Study Centre (C.E.P.H.), and is
now president of the Foundation
Jean Dausset-C.E.P.H, which
plays an active part in the
human genome project. He is a
former member of France's
National Advisory Council on
Ethics and since 1982 has been
President of the Universal
Movement for Scientific
Responsibility.
its positive and negative sides. It is up to society
to reap the benefits from it, while as far as pos¬
sible averting potential risks and deviations, so
that the balance is tilted in favour of the advan¬
tages. There can be no denying that, in the long
run, the advantages accruing from genetics will
be considerable.
An end to hereditary diseases
Thanks in particular to the work being done
by the Human Polymorphism Study Centre,
in Paris, in conjunction with Professor Daniel
Cohen and the Généthon laboratory, the genetic
map and the physical map of the human genome
have been plotted more quickly than might have
been hoped, and it is now possible to locate on
the long DNA strand the genes responsible for
the most common genetic diseases. For instance,
it has proved possible not only to pinpoint the
genes responsible for cystic fibrosis and
Duchenne muscular dystrophy but actually to
isolate, describe and sequence them. The same is
true of many other genetic diseases, and hardly
a week goes by without the genes responsible for
one or another of them being identified.
These discoveries have given rise to a great
wave of hope. Now that we know which genes
are defective, we can start thinking about devel¬
oping specific therapies either to correct the
gene itself or the protein coding it.
This is how the idea of gene therapy came
about. A distinction must be made between two
types of such therapy. One is somatic therapy,
which deals only with the cells of the body (or
soma). This has absolutely no effect on heredity
and is therefore perfectly ethical, since it can
be likened to a simple graft. The other is germ-
line therapy, which is concerned with repro¬
ductive cells, male or female, or with the
embryos of certain cells. In this case, any change
is handed down from generation to generation
and, in some individuals, the human genetic
heritage will be altered accordingly. Thus, as
things stand at present, germ-line therapy must
be strictly banned.
In addition to these hereditary diseases caused
by a single flawed gene, we are now studying
such widespread pathological conditions as dia¬
betes, cardiovascular or neuropsychiatrie dis¬
eases and cancer. These diseases may have a
variety of causes, due to the action not only of cer¬
tain genes but of environmental factors.
They are now thought to be due to the simul¬
taneous existence in one and the same individual
of a relatively limited number of defective genes,
say five or six in the case of non-insulin depen¬
dent diabetes, for example. If, through bad luck,
these five or six genes exist together in the same
person, it is to some degree probable, though by
no means certain, that he or she may contract the
disease. We therefore now have a means of quan¬
tifying the risk.
Prevention is better than cure
This, in turn, is how the concept of predictive
medicine came about. Prevention is better than
cure. And preventing means predicting.
The concept of predictive medicine came to
me when it was found that many diseases are
connected with the antigens of the HLA system
(human leucocyte antigen system).1 For instance,
somebody with the HLA-B27 antigen is 600
times more liable to suffer from ankylosing
spondylitis than somebody without it. It is now
possible to identify in the genome the genes
predisposing people to certain illnesses.
This gives an idea of the prospects being
opened up by the application of genetics to
medicine. With predictive medicine, we shall
certainly be able to avoid much pain and suf¬
fering and perhaps even live in perfect health to
a ripe old age. In short, medicine will be tailored
to the individual and will prove less costly and
more effective.
But these discoveries also have negative
aspects. It seems pointless, indeed heartless, to
tell people that they are predisposed to a disease
when we still cannot offer any preventive treat¬
ment, not to mention the unnecessary anxiety
and the host of psychological side-effects this
may cause.
What is more, such information obviously
has to be kept strictly confidential. The results
of genetic testing should be divulged only with
the authorization of the patient, since there is a
risk that they may be used by insurance com¬
panies or employers to make unacceptable dis¬
criminations. If such abuses are to be avoided, it
will be necessary to lay down strict rules. There
must be a public debate on this issue. Universal
answers will have to be found. UNESCO is
actively engaged in this search.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
So act as to treat
humanity, whether in
thine own person or
in that of any other,
in every case as an
end withal, never as
means only.
Immanuel Kant
German philosopher
(1724-1804)
In conclusion, I should like to dispel the
myth that genetics creates in the public mind. It
is only natural that current developments in
this field should make people afraid. But are
their fears justified? Or, rather, to what extent are
they justified? People are often afraid of the
seemingly all-powerful scientist. It is not the
scientist they should be afraid of, but individuals
or groups of individuals driven by a lust
for pov/er that is often tainted by a totalitarian
ideology.
And so we must regard with serenity the
revolution that is taking place today. It is a rev¬
olution that must be harnessed in the service
of humanity and lead to the long life, happy
and free of ailments, which we all hope for.
This is the dream I invite you to share a
dream in which genes spell hope.
The only priority we have set ourselves is to
relieve suffering. As Paracelsus2 put it, "medicine
is love".
1 The antigens of the HLA system are present in virtually
all the nuclear cells of the body, which is why they are
called "cell antigens". They are genetic markers that are
particularly useful for studying the biological make-up of
individuals or population groups and evaluating their sus¬
ceptibility to certain diseases. Editor .
2 Swiss doctor and alchemist (1493-1541) Editor I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
he prospects for gene therapy
There are an
estimated 100,000
genes in the human
body. By replacing
defective genes
with healthy ones,
it will bepossible to
treat many
hereditary diseases
such as
haemophilia, cystic
fibrosis and,
eventually, some
forms ofmuscular
dystrophy and
cancer.
by Renato Dulbecco
11
Rapid progress has been made in recent
years in characterizing hereditary dis¬
eases and in understanding their causes. These
diseases are due to alterations of genes, which
encode the information for building the body
and making it work. Genes are the carriers of
hereditary traits and are contained in filaments
of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid) that are present
in the cells of all organisms. The precise number
of genes in the human body is unknown, but it
is estimated to be around 100,000.
Every cell has two copies of each gene, one
deriving from the father, the other from the
mother. The information in the genes is used for
making proteins, the agents for building the
body and making it work. A disease appears
when a gene is altered in such a way that either
it does not make its corresponding protein, or
else makes a protein that is incapable of func¬
tioning. Since the same protein is encoded in
both genes of each pair, if only one fails enough
protein continues to be made to satisfy the needs
of the organisms, and there is no disease. A dis¬
ease appears when both fail and no functional
protein is made. This generally happens when a
child is born from two healthy parents, each of
whom carries an altered gene of the same pair.
Such parents have a one-in-four chance of gen¬
erating a defective child.
Hereditary genetic diseases can vary greatly
in severity. At one extreme are diseases such as
phenylketonuria, which, after detection at birth,
can be completely prevented by adopting a suit¬
able diet. At the other are those like Lesch-Nyhan
syndrome, which affects only boys, causing a
terrible form of mental retardation in which they
tend to eat themselves and must be kept bound to
their beds to prevent them from eating their fin¬
gers. Even so, they may eat their lips or their
tongues. All hereditary diseases generate a degree
of handicap, and for the majority of them there
is not as yet any effective therapy.
Vectors and receptors
During the last ten years many of the genes
responsible for hereditary diseases have been
discovered, leading to the possibility of a new
form of therapy known as "gene therapy" that
is based on the introduction into the patient's
cells of a good copy of the defective gene so as
to perform the missing function. The concept is
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
straightforward, but the implementation pre¬
sents many problems, which so far have limited
its use to only a few cases.
To treat a hereditary disease with gene therapy
several conditions must be met. In the first place
the gene responsible for the disease must be
known and must be isolated in a form that con¬
tains all the information needed to make the pro¬
tein. Many copies of the gene must be available,
to maximize the number of cells into which it can
be introduced. The fresh genetic material is usu¬
ally inserted into the malfunctioning cells by
means of a "vector" or carrier. Such vectors are
often obtained from viruses; but many viruses
may either kill cells or change them to cancer
cells. To prevent these adverse effects the genes
responsible for causing them are removed from
the viruses.
The first vectors used in gene therapy were
made from viruses known as "retro-viruses".
However, retro-viral vectors have important
drawbacks: they only enter into some types of
cell, and then the gene they carry acts weakly. The
major disadvantage is that they cannot become
established in cells that do not multiply. More
recently viruses of another kind, known as
"adeno-viruses", have been used extensively
because they can become established in cells that
do not multiply. Today most gene therapy is
being carried out using as a vector either adeno¬
viruses or other viruses with similar properties.
Many attempts have been made to use other
ways of delivering genes into cells. One of them
takes advantage of the ability of certain "factors"
present in the blood or other body fluids to enter
cells by interacting with "receptors" present at the
surface of cells. For this method to work, the
cell into which the gene must be introduced needs
to have a suitable receptor at its surface, and this
limits the types of cells that can be used.
A method suitable for any cell has thus been
developed, which consists in embedding the
gene into a microscopic vesicle called a "lipo¬
some", made up of an artificial membrane sim¬
ilar to those that surround the cells. When the
vesicle touches the cell, its membrane fuses with
the cellular membrane, and the gene it contains
enters the cell. This method seems to have few
drawbacks but it has not yet been used widely
enough for its efficacy to be proved. Most
recently it has been shown that naked DNA
can enter cells, opening up the possibility of an
even simpler method for gene delivery.
Inserting the gene into a suitable vector is the
first step in gene therapy; the next step is to intro¬
duce the vector into the cells. The type of cell to
be targeted depends on the nature of the disease
produced by the genetic defect. In many of the
attempts using viral vectors the cells are taken
from the body, grown in vitro, and returned to the
body after introduction of the gene. To carry
out this procedure the cells must be accessible, like
those of muscle, skin and blood, but unlike those
of internal organs. With the newer approaches
using receptor binding, liposomes, or naked
DNA, the handicap is not so great, and genes have
been introduced into the liver, lungs and muscle.
The first attempt to use gene therapy on a
human being was carried out in 1990 on a girl
affected by adenosine deaminase (ADA)
Opposite page, a chemist
engaged in the production of
liposomes at the European
Molecular Biology Laboratory in
Heidelberg (Germany).
Liposomes are tiny vesicles
that can be used in gene
therapy to Introduce genes into
malfunctioning cells.
Right, a girl suffering from
thyroid deficiency who grew
taller after being injected with
human growth hormone.
Formerly extracted in
insufficient quantities from
human cadavers, the hormone
is now produced in large
fermenters using a bacterium,
Escherichia coli, under
controlled conditions.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The first attempt to
use gene therapy on
a human being was
carried out in 1990
on a girl suffering
from a serious
disease of the
immune system.
Unable to defend her
body against
infections, the child
had to live under a
plastic bell. She
could not play with
other children or go
to school.
14
RENATO DULBECCO
is an Italian-born American
virologist who was awarded the
1975 Nobel Prize for Physiology
or Medicine, together with David
Baltimore and Howard M. Temin,
for their studies of the workings
of cells, viral contamination and
the genesis of cancer. He is the
co-ordinator of the human
genome project for Italy and
Honorary President of the Salk
Institute for Biological Studies in
La Jolla, California (U.S.A.).
Among his published works is an
8-volume Encyclopaedia of
Human Biology (1991).
deficiency, that is, the cells of the immune system
lacked an essential enzyme and were unable to
defend her body against infections. The child
had to live under a plastic bell. She could not play
with other children and could not go to school.
The cells lacking the enzyme are accessible
because they are made in the bone marrow and
then enter the blood. The therapy was carried
out by taking the cells from the blood, intro¬
ducing the ADA gene into them, and then
returning them to the patient's blood. The result
has been good. The defence functions of the
girl's immune system were re-established and she
was able to leave her abode and go to school.
One drawback of this therapy is that the
modified cells do not last a long time, and so the
treatment must be repeated at frequent intervals.
This difficulty might be overcome by introducing
the gene into large cells of the bone marrow
known as stem cells, which have a much longer
life span. However they do not multiply readily
in vitro, and therefore the retro-viral vector would
not work for them, and, moreover, they are very
difficult to isolate. The therapy is therefore effec¬
tive but still needs much additional work.
Hope for haemophiliacs
Another promising case for gene therapy is
haemophilia, which causes a tendency to bleed
due to lack of a coagulation factor which is
made in the liver and then secreted into the
blood stream. There are two forms of the disease:
A and B, in each of which a different factor is
lacking. Attention has been concentrated on
haemophilia B because the gene responsible for
the factor (called factor IX) is of manageable
size; the other is too big for the available vectors.
Work has been carried out on dogs, which also
suffer from this form of haemophilia, using a
retro-viral vector. To replenish the blood with the
factor two strategies were followed. In one case,
cells were taken from the animal, either from
OUR GENES: WHAT 1
THE MAP SHOWS
Some locations of mutations discovered
by scientists
Neurofibromatosis, Type 2
Tumours of the auditory nerves
and tissues surrounding the brain 0
Down's Syndrome
Congenital mental deficiency
condition marked by three copies
of chromosome 21
Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis* *
(Lou Gehrig's Disease)
Fatal degenerative nerve ailment A
ADA Deficiency
Severe susceptibility to
infections. First hereditary .
condition treated by gene therapy Á
Familial Hypercholesterolemia
Extremely high cholestero
c
Myotonic Dystrophy i
Frequent form of adult muscular
dystrophy
1
Amyloidosis 1
Accumulation In the tissues of an
insoluble flbrilar protein
&
Breast Cancer*
5% to 10% of cases»
A
Polycystic Kidney Disease 1
Cysts resulting in enlarged kidneys
and renal failure
C1
FROM THE WHOLE TO THE(MICROSCOPIC) PARTS
The
human
body
contains
100
trillion
cells
*
There is a
nucleus
inside each
human cell
(except red
blood cells)
Each nucleus
contains 46
chromosomes,
arranged
in 23 pairs
One
chromosome
of every pair is
from each
parent
The
chromosomes
are filled with
tightly coiled
strands of
DNA
»3SCCC
«fgágM»
Genes are
segments of
DNA that
contain
instructions to
make proteins,
the building
blocks of life
<g£
Tay-Sachs
Disease
Fatal
hereditary
disorder
involving lipid
metabolism
often
occurring in
Ashkenazi
Jews and
French
Canadians
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Muscular dystrophy
(Duchenne and Becker
types)
Progressive
deterioration of the
muscles
Haemophilia
Blood defect
making it
difficult to
control
haemorrhaglng
ALD
(Adrenoleukodystrophy)
i Nerve disease potrayed
\ in the film Lorenzo's Oil
Gaucher's
Disease
A chronic enzyme
deficiency
occurring
frequently among
Ashkenazi Jews
WHEN CAN WE GET TESTED?
g DNA test currently available
I Gene mapped but not yet isolated
y Diagnosis available through family-
linkage study of DNA markers
DNA test under development
Rfl
Familial colon cancer*
)0ne in 200 people has this gene: of those 65% are
likely to develop the disease
Retinitis Pigmentosa*
Progressive degeneration
of the retina
Disease
Neurodegenerative disorder tending to
strike people in their 40s and 50s.
Familial Polyposis of the Colon
Abnormal tissue growths
frequently leading to cancer
Haemochromatosis
Abnormally high
absorption of iron from
kthe diet
Sprirocerebellar
Ataxia
Destroys nerves in
the brain and spinal
chord, resulting in
loss of muscle
control
Cystic fibrosis
Mucus fills up the
lungs, interfering
with breathing.
One of the most
widely prevalent
genetic diseases
Multiple Exostoses*
A disorder of cartilege and
bone
Malignant Melanoma
Tumours originating in the skin
Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia,
Type 2
Tumours in endocrine glands and
other tissues
Alzheimer's
Disease
Degenerative
nerve disease
marked by
premature
senility
Retinoblastoma
A relatively common tumour of the
eye, accounting for 2% of childhood
malignancies
PKU
(phenylketonuria)
An inborn error of metabolism
that frequently results in
mental retardation
Sickle cell anaemia
Chronic inherited anaemia, primarily affecting
blacks, in which red blood cells sickle, or
form crescents, plugging arterioles and
capillaries
* One form of the disease
Source: Time magazine, 17 January 1994 IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
subcutaneous tissue, muscle, or the epidermis,
grown in vitro, and after introduction of the
vector, were implanted into the animal, where
they continued to produce the missing factor for
many months, and perhaps indefinitely.
The other strategy was to introduce the same
vector into the liver. To overcome the difficulty
that the liver cells do not multiply, one third of
the liver was surgically removed in order to
cause a regeneration of the organ, and there¬
fore cell multiplication. The result was a steady,
although low, production of the factor, which
again lasted for a long time, with a satisfactory
correction of the disease. These results show
that there is much hope for a long-term control
of haemophilia through gene therapy.
A disease targeted for gene therapy since its
gene was isolated a few years ago is cystic
fibrosis, in which many types of secreting cells
are affected, but especially those of the lung
with accumulation of mucus and limitation of
oxygen uptake. Results suggest that human gene
therapy holds promise as a treatment for this dis¬
ease, especially if it can be done by delivering the
gene through nebulization, which is very simple.
Attempts to treat cancer
Attempts to use gene therapy have been made
for a number of years in the treatment of cancer,
which is a genetic disease, although not usually
transmitted hereditarily. These attempts have
taken two main directions. One, applied to brain
Below, model of a DNA
molecule. Bottom photo, James
Watson and Francis Crick
(right), winners of the Nobel
Prize for Physiology or Medicine
in 1962. Their discovery of the
double helix structure of
deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)
was a turning point in the study
of genetics.
16
tumours, is to introduce into the cancer cells a
vector carrying a gene that converts an anti-
herpes drug into a cell-killing substance. The
gene, in a retro-virus vector, is injected into the
cancer mass, where it is able to perform its
action because the cells are multiplying, whereas
it has no effect on normal brain cells, which do
not multiply. Experiments with cancer trans¬
planted into mice showed that the tumour was
destroyed after the mice were injected with the
anti-herpes drug. The problem in this experi¬
ment is that the vector only penetrates some of
the cells so that the remaining cells may start a
new growth (even though the toxic substance
produced under the action of the gene can pass
from one cell to another). Whether this approach
will be useful in human patients remains to be
seen; clinical trials are under way.
The other direction being taken by attempts
to use gene therapy to treat cancer is to enhance
the body's defences against the tumour. It is based
on the idea that, at least in some cases, the body
recognizes the cancer cells as foreign and should
react immunologically, causing their destruction.
This does not happen in the patient because the
immunological defences are paralyzed. The
approach is therefore to potentiate the immune
response, which is attempted in two ways. One
is to grow the immune cells in vitro in the pres¬
ence of potentiating factors, and then introduce
into them the gene for a cell-killing substance,
after which they are injected back into the patient.
Preliminary trials in patients with mela¬
noma a malignant skin tumour using the
potentiated cells without the introduction of the
gene have given encouraging results a reduction
of the skin tumours and of their metastases in the
lungs. The other approach to potentiating the
immune response consists in introducing into
the cancer cells a gene that will cause them to acti¬
vate the immune cells with which they come in
contact; once these cells are activated they can
attack cancer cells at other sites in the body. The
modified cancer cells thus constitute a kind of vac¬
cine against the cancer. Experiments in animals
have yielded promising results.
Many approaches to gene therapy can be
applied to hereditary human diseases, and some
promising results have already been obtained.
The future is bright for diseases such as adeno¬
sine deaminase (ADA) deficiency, haemophilia
and cystic fibrosis, and the prospects are good
for muscular dystrophy and for some cancers.
Development of this field is obviously still at a
very early stage, and improvements will cer¬
tainly be made in areas such as the mode of
delivery of the gene to the cells and the isolation
and growth of suitable cells. There is every
reason to expect that gene therapy will become
a powerful weapon in the treatment of diseases
caused by gene alterations. H
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
renatal diagnosis:
foretelling the quality of life
by Hans Galjaard
Mother and Child (1992)
mixed media on wood
(60 x 60 cm) by the Moroccan
painter Hamid.
DNA technology has revolutionized the
laboratory diagnosis of genetic disease. It
has also provided new perspectives for the detec¬
tion of very minute chromosomal aberrations
which are invisible under the microscope. In
the near future DNA probes for specific parts of
each human chromosome will facilitate large-
scale prenatal diagnosis in women at risk of
giving birth to offspring with a congenital mal¬
formation or genetic disease. They will also
contribute to the elucidation of the causes of
hitherto unexplained mental retardation and
physical handicap.
At present some 750 disease genes have been
Screening for most genetic
risks will eventually be possible
through analysis ofchromosomal
aberrations. But social or religious
factors may impede the applications
ofscientificprogress.
identified. This has widened the scope of the pre¬
natal diagnosis of genetic diseases and the detec¬
tion of gene-mutation carriers, who are usually
healthy themselves but may have an increased
risk of producing affected children. DNA tech¬
nology also offers new perspectives for the
development of animal models for human dis¬
eases, making it possible to study pathogenesis
and work out new therapeutic strategies. The
latter will be especially important in the var¬
ious types of cancer for which specific chro¬
mosomal aberrations and gene defects have been
identified both in germ cells and somatic cells.
These techniques of diagnosis and carrier
identification form the basis for genetic coun¬
selling to couples who on the basis of their
family history or exposure to possible harmful
environmental factors fear the birth of a hand¬
icapped child. The choices are often difficult
and involve refraining from pregnancy, accepting
the risk, adoption, fertilization with donor
gametes, or prenatal diagnosis with the option
of terminating the pregnancy if the foetus is
found to be affected. Follow-up studies in our
own centre revealed that 50 per cent of couples
at high genetic risk refrain from pregnancy when 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Current techniques of prenatal
diagnosis and detection of
genetic diseases make it
possible to counsel couples
who risk giving birth to a
handicapped child because of
their family ancestry. Above, a
married couple in Japan.
18
HANS GALJAARD,
of The Netherlands, is Professor
of human genetics at Erasmus
University and Chairman of the
Department of Clinical Genetics
at the University Hospital of
Rotterdam. A member of his
country's Royal Academy of
Sciences and its National Health
Council, he has published
hundreds of articles in scientific
journals, chapters in many
specialized works, and several
monographs on technological,
social and ethical aspects of cell
biology and genetics.
there is no prenatal test available. If, however,
there is such a test, 85 per cent of the couples
choose to have progeny because they know
they can avoid the birth of a handicapped child.
Hence, prenatal diagnosis should not only be
considered as a technology leading to abortion
but also as an approach that may provide re¬
assurance and stimulate couples, who might not
otherwise have dared to do so, to reproduce.
In the wealthy countries clinical genetics
services are universally accepted as part of
modern health care. The only controversial issue
is whether or not a pregnancy should be termi¬
nated because of an affected foetus. Abortion
remains ethically, religiously unacceptable to a
minority. Nearly all countries offering this
option have, however, legalized abortion up to
twenty-four weeks of pregnancy and a few
countries, like the United Kingdom, do not
even have a time limit in the case of an affected
foetus. The only remaining concern is social
pressure on those parents who give birth to an
affected child when this could have been
avoided. It is clear that freedom of choice should
also be guaranteed for people who for moral
reasons do not want to use a specific technique.
In the Scandinavian and northwestern Euro¬
pean countries today 50 to 60 per cent of preg¬
nant women of advanced child-bearing age
undergo prenatal diagnosis and the rest do not
want it, even if they know of its existence.
Social attitudes to screening carriers of
hereditary diseases
In a number of populations a particular genetic
mutation is so prevalent that population
screening for carriership is justified, provided
that a reliable, easy and cheap test is available,
and that the population involved has been well
informed. Such carrier screening programmes
have led to a marked reduction or an eradication
of ß-thalassaemia, a hereditary anaemia which is
found amongst Mediterranean populations, of
sickle-cell anaemia in Cuba, and of the severe
neurological Tay-Sachs disease among Jews in
North America and Israel.
The importance of economic, social and reli¬
gious factors is evident in the success or failure
of population screening for carriership. In some
Mediterranean countries where the prevalence
of ß-thalassaemia carriers is as high as one in
seven, the church and health authorities have co¬
operated, and the same is true for the Jewish
authorities in North America and Israel in the
case of the Tay-Sachs screening programme.
In the United States, however, attempts at
carrier screening for sickle-cell anaemia among the
black population, one in ten of which is a carrier,
have failed. There are several reasons for this.
Almost 60 per cent of black children are born out
of marriage and 80 per cent are born to very
young mothers, so that it is difficult or impossible
to test both partners and provide timely genetic
counselling. In addition, many blacks and His-
panics are not insured for health care and cannot
afford genetic testing. Furthermore, termination
of pregnancy in federally funded clinics has for a
long period been impossible. Finally, when car¬
rier screening was propagated, many members of
the black community felt it to be yet another
means of discrimination.
The fact that carrier screening for sickle-cell
anaemia has been successful among the black
population in Cuba demonstrates that political
and social background plays an important role
in the acceptance of genetics services. Cuba and
China are both examples of low income coun¬
tries which have given a high priority to health
care and education. Contrary to many other .
Asian countries contraceptive use in China is
high (71 to 86 per cent), people are well informed
about prenatal care and the one-child-family
policy motivates couples to make use of all
available technology to ensure the birth of a
healthy child. The main limitation is the rela¬
tively high cost of genetic testing.
In India, Bangladesh and Pakistan, which
account for 30 per cent of the world's child mor¬
tality and for 40 per cent of its non-immunized
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
"About 6,000 conditions in human beings are now known to be associated with a
microscopically invisible defect in a single gene, and more than 2,500 of these
concern genetic diseases which result in early death or chronic impairment. It is
possible to diagnose 400 of these diseases by biochemical analysis."
children, illiteracy, low contraceptive use (12 to
43 per cent), inadequate education, the status of
women and poverty are'major limitations on the
future application of gene technology. The deeply
rooted preference for male offspring, which has
a religious basis in Hinduism, has unfortunately
led to misuse of prenatal diagnosis, as it had pre¬
viously for economic reasons in China. In India
there are private clinics which perform prenatal
sex determinations for members of the higher
social classes who may terminate their pregnancy
if the foetus is female. So far only one state has
imposed a legal ban on this practice, and attempts
at national legislation have failed.
In countries where Islam is the major reli¬
gion (their total population is about one billion
people worldwide) different religious schools,
political structures and ethnic backgrounds are
associated with different interpretations of the
Qur'an in terms of reproductive technology. In
general, diagnostic methods and genetic coun¬
selling will be accepted, as well as certain con¬
traceptives, depending on the number and sex of
the children already present in the family, and the
goal. Sterilization and abortion are usually not
acceptable. In most Muslim societies abortion
during the first forty days of pregnancy is per¬
mitted ("halal"), and after 120 days is strictly
forbidden ("haram"). In between those times the
soul is believed to enter the foetus and abortion
might be considered under special circumstances,
but it is not liked ("marrouh"). This excludes
amniocentesis the removal of fluid surrounding
the foetus in the womb for therapeutic or diag¬
nostic purposes as an option for couples at risk
of having an affected child, but there would be
some scope for early procedures like chorionic
villus biopsy or foetal cell testing in maternal
blood. Family and tribal traditions play a major
role, which mean an additional obstacle to the
acceptance of certain genetic services.
Religion also plays a role in Latin America
where the Roman Catholic Church is widely
influential and where abortion laws have not
been liberalized. Unequal distribution of wealth,
illiteracy, low contraceptive use in rural areas and
a high rate of teenage pregnancy are other major
problems. Again, as in several other developing
countries, some private clinics offer genetics
services, but their use is restricted to the few who
can afford them.
An interesting illustration of the importance
of religion and tradition is provided by Japan, a
country with a high gross national product, very
advanced technology and the world's lowest
infant mortality rate. However, clinical genetics
is hardly developed in Japan, for two main rea¬
sons. The presence of a handicapped relative is
often hidden from the outside world because it is
associated with feelings of guilt and shame. This
makes it difficult to perform more extensive
family studies on the basis of an index patient.
Secondly, despite one of the highest abortion
rates in the world for social reasons, the Japanese
tradition does not approve of judgments of the
value of a human being and hence the finding of
an abnormal foetus is not accepted as a reason for
abortion. Wealth and technology alone are not
sufficient for the incorporation of new services
into the health care system.
In order to implement genetic services at a
global level much has to be done to improve
living conditions (clean water, sanitation,
housing, nutrition, work), reduce infant mor¬
tality, illiteracy and poverty, and extend educa¬
tion, especially of women, in order to make
people aware of the possible benefits of contra¬
ceptive use and timely prenatal care.
In countries such as India, the
status of women may be an
obstacle to some applications
of gene technology. Below,
Indian village women in
Karnataka hold a weekly
meeting to manage the craft
co-operative they have created.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
"How can science
be left free to
pursue its
discoveries and the
state be allowed to
exercise its
responsibility
towards society!"
enetics in the market-place
by Ezra N. SuleimanThe prospect of shopping for "spare part"
organs and tissue confronts modern
societies with acute ethical dilemmas
SO
There have always been but few certain¬
ties in the world, and the most funda¬
mental of them life and death are now being
questioned by the scientific engineering of the
last decade. As Andrew Kimbrell observed in his
recent book, The Human Body Shop, "the engi¬
neering and marketing of life . . . raises some of
the most profound questions our society has
ever had to answer: What is life? What does it
mean to be human? Should we allow our scien¬
tists to become the genetic co-authors of evo¬
lution? How do we define death? Who deter¬
mines what life is worth living? Do we want a
'free market' in human organs, tissues, genes
or children?"1
Genetic engineering not only raises funda¬
mental questions about the meaning of life and
death, it also challenges our notions of the life
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
process. It spawns whole industries that seek to
exploit every scientific advance made by this
process. It challenges our notion of human
rights.2 It raises ethical and moral questions
about using foetuses for "spare parts" for, as
Andrew Kimbrell has written, "many experts
feel that the current disapproval of 'growing
foetuses' for medical use will be short-lived."
While philosophers and ethicists must, and
will, continue to debate the morality of some
aspects of genetic engineering, the fact is that the
issues raised by biotechnology cry out for poli-
- cies that establish the contours within which
these scientific advances can legitimately occur.
We now know that the implications for the
scientific community and for society of the dis¬
covery of the genome are nothing less than rev¬
olutionary. That this discovery is the culmina¬
tion of many years of research does not lessen its
impact or alter its unprecedented character.
When scientific research advanced to the point
of giving us the atomic and hydrogen bombs, the
world marvelled, but only realized the full impli¬
cations of these scientific discoveries after their
dangers had become a fact of life. Should the
development of the weapons of mass destruc¬
tion remarkable scientific discoveries in their
own right not be seen as a warning signal for
us today where genetic engineering is con¬
cerned? Should we not react now, for the process
is already well advanced? To ask these ques¬
tions is to ask what role the state should take in
orienting research and in regulating the diffusion
of the discoveries of genetic engineering.
The role of the state
This is a matter of concern to the entire inter¬
national community. It can no longer be
regarded as a matter best left to scientists. Just as
war is too important to be left to the generals, so
life and death are too important to be left to
the hazards of scientific discoveries.
Underlying the issue of the role of the state
in scientific research are the questions of the
responsibility of the scientific community and
the "ownership" of scientific results. These are
fundamentally ethical issues, and as such must
be debated by society.
There are essentially two views regarding
the role that the state should play in encouraging
and regulating scientific research. The first holds
that the state should in no way interfere in sci¬
entific research because science can only advance
unfettered. Following from this premise, it is
believed that:
The state should remain a bystander where
scientific research in general is concerned.
The state should not seek to dictate the
diffusion of scientific results. Scientists are the
best judges of what results should be made avail¬
able to the public. They are the owners of these
results and discoveries.
The state should not determine the direc¬
tion of scientific research. By the same token, it
should not seek to control the outcome of sci¬
entific discoveries.
The interference of the state in scientific
research risks making science an instrument of
a state ideology rather than the objective pursuit
of knowledge.
The second and diametrically opposed view
is that the state, charged with responsibility for
society, has an obligation to involve itself in sci¬
entific research. This view is based on the belief
that:
In a democratic society, science must never
become a mere instrument of a state ideology. It
can proceed freely and still leave a role for the
state.
The state has a responsibility for preserving
the cohesion of society and for ensuring equality
before the law.
The state has an obligation to be active in any
area that poses a potential threat to individuals,
Peter loves Jane
Peter loves Jane. After an accident, Jane loses an arm. Someone else's arm is
grafted to replace the amputated arm. Peter is still in love with Jane. After a
time Jane falls ill with a serious kidney disease. A kidney transplant is success¬
fully carried out. Peter still loves Jane. Then she has another accident and suf¬
fers extensive burns. Substantial skin grafts are necessary. Then Jane is diag¬
nosed as having a serious heart condition. A heart transplant is considered.
Is Peter still in love with Jane? Is poor Jane, with an arm, kidney, skin and
heart that are not her own, still the Jane he loved? How many organs, how
much tissue can Jane exchange while still remaining the object of Peter's love?
How many kilograms and how many square metres can she have replaced and
still remain the same person?
The object of Peter's love and Jane's person cannot be measured by kilo¬
grams, square metres or even by the number of organs preserved or trans¬
planted.
Jean Bernard
French haematologist
(De la biologie à l'éthique © Buchet-Chastel, Paris 1990) 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A confrontation between
science and the authorities:
Galileo before the Holy Office,
1633, by the French painter
Joseph Nicolas Robert-Fleury
(1797-1890).
22
EZRA N. SULEIMAN,
of the United States, is IBM
Professor of International
Studies and Director of the
Committee for European Studies
at Princeton University. He is the
author of numerous books,
including Politics, Power and
Bureaucracy in France (1974)
Bites in French Society (1979)
and, in French, ¡.es Hauts
Fonctionnaires et le Politique
(1976) and Les Elites en France
(1979)
that affects the equilibrium of society and that
affects the social order in any way.
Both these views express general ideologies
regarding the proper role of the state in demo¬
cratic societies. How can they be reconciled?
How can they be applied to the specific context
of the discovery of the genome? How, in short,
can science be left free to pursue its discoveries
and the democratic state be allowed to exercise
its responsibility towards society?
First of all, there is no contradiction between
requiring the state to guarantee the freedom of
scientific research and expecting it to play a role
in regulating the consequences of this research.
This is particularly the case in biotechnology.
Secondly, as many of the potential conse¬
quences of biotechnological research are already
becoming known, the state has the obligation to
regulate some of the adverse or nefarious uses to
which this research may be put.
Thirdly, regulating biotechnological research
and the diffusion of its results is not a way of
opposing the scientific community. Scientists
themselves do not have control over the uses of
their discoveries. Hence, scientists can work with
the state to ensure the ethical uses of their
research.
Fourthly, research in biotechnology is expen
sive and, in an era of scarce resources, the state
needs to justify such expenditures. And justi¬
fying expenditures requires justifying the use of
these expenditures.
Because of the potentially profound effect on
society on inequality among individuals, on
the relation of the individual to society and,
finally, on the very concept of collectivity the
state has an obligation to be perhaps more
involved in this area of scientific research than
in others.
The state, however, cannot merely impose
guidelines. It must have its own guidelines to
follow. A democratic state is always subject to
controls, and the confines of its actions in the area
of biotechnology must be carefully demarcated.
The state needs to develop its levels of inter¬
vention in scientific research through wide-
ranging discussion in a democratic context. This .
ensures the legitimacy of actions, and ensures
controls over actions. In short, the state needs to
work with the scientific community to ensure
the freedom of research and the ethical uses of
the results of this research.
1 Andrew Kimbrell, The Human Body Shop: The Engi¬
neering and Marketing ofLife (New York, 1993).
2 See Eugene B. Brody, Biomedical Technology and
Human Rights (Dartmouth Publishing Co., Cambridge,
U.S.A. and UNESCO, 1993).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
NESCO
and bioethics
by Georges B. Kutukdjian
Through ethical
reflection,
humanity can now
keep pace with the
challenges of
science instead of
realizing too late
when things have
gone wrong
A biologist using state-of-the-
art microscope equipment to
insert DNA segments into
embryos.
I Scientific research on the human genome,
I and especially on gene therapy and the
diagnosis of genetic diseases, has far-reaching
implications for the lives of all of us children,
men and women alike. It is a field holding out
immense prospects for man's self-transformation
and it will, in the long run, require societies to
make certain choices. As a result, it is giving
rise to anxieties that may in some cases be jus¬
tified but are more often irrational.
These anxieties lie behind the effort many
countries are now making to look into the eth¬
ical framework of such research. Legislation is
starting to be adopted to define limits for med¬
ical practice and some types of research, in order
to ensure that human dignity will be respected.
Two points must be stressed, however. In the
first place, the type of legislation differs signif¬
icantly from one country to another and we do
not have any common yardstick to judge it by.
Secondly, it does not exist everywhere in the
world, but only in some of the industrial coun¬
tries. Elsewhere, there are are still a number of
grey areas surrounding research and experi¬
mentation.
It is for all these reasons that the Director-
General of UNESCO decided to set up an Inter
national Bioethics Committee and invited Ms.
Noëlle Lenoir, a member of the Constitutional
Council of the French Republic, to preside over
its deliberations.
The Committee met for the first time in Sep¬
tember 1 993 and commenced its work by identi¬
fying three priority themes. These are genetic
screening and testing, the therapeutic applications
of genetics research, and population genetics.
Genetic testing
Should genetic screening be made compulsory
for so-called "risk" populations or should it
simply be made available to them? Should it be
introduced into premarital examinations or be
included in prenatal diagnosis? Should it be car¬
ried out before gamete donation or the implan¬
tation of embryos fertilized in vitro?
At the outset, a distinction must be made
between two kinds of genetic tests. Tests in the
first category are used to identify a particular
gene which is virtually certain to bring on a
hereditary disease. Those in the second cate¬
gory show whether or not a person has a pre¬
disposition to certain diseases and thus reveal sit¬
uations involving varying degrees of probability.
Depending on the environment and sundry
other factors, about some of which little is
known, the outward symptoms of a disease may
appear in its early stages or may emerge only
later, and the disease itself may vary in severity.
A genetic mutation may become more dominant
and grow worse from generation to generation.
On the other hand, the tendency for genetic
damage to occur may be reversed. In short, the
same defect in a person's genotype (genetic con¬
stitution) may take different forms in his or her
phenotype (the physical constitution as it inter¬
acts with the environment).
This influence of the environment on the
form a genetic mutation may take brings into
play the concept of the responsibility of indi¬
viduals towards themselves and their families
and the responsiblity of citizens towards the
community. Preventive medicine could there¬
fore be said to go hand-in-hand with predictive
medicine.
Should people be told that there is a proba¬
bility that they will eventually develop Hunt¬
ington's chorea, for example, and transmit it to
their offspring? Should their close or distant 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
O-*
Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde: the temptation
I knew well that I risked death; for any drug that so
potently controlled and shook the very fortress of iden¬
tity might, by the least scruple of an overdose or at the
least inopportunity in the moment of exhibition, utterly
blot out that immaterial tabernacle which I looked to it
to change. But the temptation of a discovery so singular
and profound at last overcame the suggestions of alarm.
... I compounded the elements, watched them boil and
smoke together in the glass, and when the ebullition had
subsided, with a strong glow of courage, drank off the
potion.
The most racking pangs succeeded: a grinding in the
bones, deadly nausea, and a horror of the spirit that
cannot be exceeded at the hour of birth or death. Then
these agonies began swiftly to subside, and I came to
myself as if out of a great sickness. There was something
strange in my sensations, something indescribably new,
and, from its very novelty, incredibly sweet. I felt
younger, lighter, happier in body; within I was conscious
of a heady recklessness, a current of disordered sensual
images running like a mill race in my fancy, a solution of
the bonds of obligation, an unknown but not an inno¬
cent freedom of the soul. I knew myself, at the first
breath of this new life, to be more wicked, tenfold more
wicked, sold a slave to my original evil: and the thought,
in that moment, braced and delighted me like wine.
Robert Lewis Stevenson
Scottish writer
The Strange case ofDr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde (1886)
relatives be warned? What about employers
and insurance companies? Can a company's
medical service insist on being given the results
of genetic testing?
Since genetic testing may extend over several
generations and involve varying numbers of
individuals, questions about the storage and
confidentiality of the data are bound to arise
sooner or later. How long should genetic data be
kept and how can its confidentiality be guaran¬
teed ? Who should be empowered to divulge or
withhold information which often involves
whole families?
Similarly, if people can choose to know what
their genetic future will be, can they also choose
not to know? Should they or should they not be
compelled to take account of the results of
genetic testing?
In this regard, it is important that people
should be freely able to exercise their discretion.
Information that is liable to change their whole
lives and force added responsibilities on them
should not expose them to any form of dis¬
crimination. Genetic testing should not prompt
the authorities to adopt repressive policies
leading to a restriction of individual freedoms.
Another ethical issue connected with genetic
testing is bound up with the need to ensure that
all countries, including the least advanced ones,
reap benefit from them, so that they too can
join the fight against hereditary diseases.
Therapeutic applications
The first question that has to be raised relates to
the pre-implantation diagnosis performed on
artificially fertilized embryos which, in view of
its greater simplicity and lower cost, is likely to
replace gene therapy in cases of rare genetic dis¬
eases. This involves a choice that is already
framed in ethical terms.
The second question is whether the work
currently being done is not liable to become nar¬
rowly focused on looking for the genes that
account for people's behaviour their sexuality,
for example their talents and abilities, or even
their "déviances". This could lead to a kind of
genetic reductionism whereby people would be
defined exclusively in terms of their genome, or
to a situation in which some individuals or groups
of individuals might be stigmatized by society,
ostracized or even eliminated. This would be
tantamount to adopting eugenic policies.
There are other problems. We know, for
example, that through agriculture, gene therapy
could bring about radical changes in public
health. A diet of genetically modified plants
could become a regular form of treatment, a
sort of oral "vaccine" given in repeated doses.
However, the in vivo reproduction of these
plant species would be liable to give rise to new
recombined organisms that could become vec¬
tors for diseases. In such an eventuality, what
kind of preventive measures and legislation
should be instituted?
The same applies, mutatis mutandis, to the use
of human genes for the development of transgenic
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
animals. What limits should be set on the supply
of human genetic material? Should it be reserved
solely for therapeutic purposes, say for xeno¬
grafts, and its use for any other purpose, such as
for improving livestock, be ruled out?
We have to accept that the issue of transge-
nesis applied to the human species now has to be
faced. Reports of germ-line therapy experiments
on embryonic cells or spermatozoa have recently
been published in scientific journals.
As a result of the rapid strides being made by
genetic engineering, it is now possible to store
gametes and germ cells in "banks" for possible
future use, such as for autografts. This practice
is now regarded as acceptable, under certain
conditions, for young cancer patients who have
to undergo X-ray treatment or chemotherapy
and who wish to preserve their chances of later
conceiving children by in vitro fertilization
techniques. With the exception of these medical
cases, the storage of gametes and germ cells
poses the problem of the storage of human
products generally, as well as that of storage
methods and the criteria governing access to
such "banks".
Lastly, careful thought has to be given to
the best ways of protecting the intellectual prop¬
erty of researchers whose inventions have indus¬
trial or commercial applications. Should such
protection be regarded as akin to copyright?
How is it possible to regulate access to genetic
data banks and their possible industrial or com¬
mercial uses?
First, steps must be taken to secure the free
and informed consent of population groups
participating in major surveys on population
genetics. The scientific aims and objectives of the
surveys should be clearly explained to them.
The results of these surveys should not be
detrimental to those who participate, nor should
they lead to discrimination against them. Nor
should they be allowed to lead to the establish¬
ment of a genetic pseudo-classification of the
population groups involved.
These results should also be communicated to
the individuals and population groups concerned.
Access to genetic data banks where the infor¬
mation is stored, the processing of this informa¬
tion and its use should be rigorously defined.
The human genome project
Deciphering the totality of genetic information
on the human race is an ambitious project which
calls for international co-operation. The ensuing
progress will help to prevent and treat genetic
diseases which are incurable today. It will also
make a significant contribution to understanding
the structure and the functions of the genetic
system and individual development, as well as
the "natural history" of DNA.
Such fundamental knowledge of human beings
clearly raises ethical, social and legal problems, and
consequently it is not surprising that UNESCO
attaches very great importance to it. The human
genome project has a place among UNESCO's
activities because of UNESCO's ethical mission
and its competence in the fields of education, sci¬
ence and culture. UNESCO offers an ideal envi¬
ronment for multidisciplinary debates on the dif¬
ferent aspects of study of the human genome.
UNESCO is thus fully involved in this project.
By organizing or encouraging meetings, holding
workshops, helping to finance training pro¬
grammes and awarding short-term scholarships,
Unesco is seeking to do three things: to
encourage international co-operation and co¬
ordination, to stimulate debate on the many
repercussions of the human genome project,
and to promote the participation of countries of
the South and East. The sharing of knowledge
between North and South, East and West is,
after all, an ethical imperative in itself.
St. Cosmas and St. Damián
graft onto the deacon
Giustiniano the leg of a recently
deceased Ethiopian. 15th-
century fresco by Fra Angélico
in the San Marco Museum,
Florence.
(Illustration taken from the
catalogue of La vie en kit,
éthique et biologie © Fondation
de l'Arche de la Fraternité,
Paris).
GEORGES B. KUTUKDJIAN
is the head of Unesco's
Bioethics Unit. A philosopher
and anthropologist, he has
published a number of papers
on kinship systems and
proverbs, and literary essays on
Marguerite Duras, Kafka and
Proust. He was the co-editor,
with Antonio Papisca, of a
collective work on the rights of
peoples, published in 1991 by
CEDAM, Padua (Italy).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
r<p
Doctor Frankenstein
When I found so astonishing a power placed
within my hand, I hesitated a long time con¬
cerning the manner in which I should use it. . . .
I doubted at first whether I should attempt the
creation of a being like myself or one of simpler
organization; but my imagination was too much
exalted by my first success to permit me to doubt
of my ability to give life to an animal as complex
and wonderful as man. ... I prepared myself for
a multitude of reverses; my operations might be
incessantly baffled, and at last my work be imper¬
fect: yet, when I considered the improvement
which every day takes place in science and
mechanics, I was encouraged to hope my present
attempts would at least lay the foundations of
future success. . . .
No one can conceive the variety of feelings
which bore me onwards, like a hurricane, in the
first enthusiasm of success. Life and death
appeared to me ideal bounds, which I should first
break through, and pour a torrent of light into
our dark world. A new species would bless me as
its creator and source; many happy and excel¬
lent natures would owe their being to me. No
father could claim the gratitude of his child so
completely as I should deserve theirs. Pursuing
these reflections, I thought, that if I could bestow
animation upon lifeless matter, I might in process
of time (although I now found it impossible)
renew life where death had apparently devoted the
body to corruption.
Mary Wollstonecraft Shelley
Frankenstein or the Modern Prometheus
The 1818 Text
William Pickering, London, 1993
To find out more,
Books
1978: RIBES, Bruno, Biology and
Ethics. Unesco, Paris, 200 pp.
1979: DE VICENTE, Roman
(ed.), Replies from Biological
Research, Consejo Superior de
Investigaciones Científicas,
Madrid, Raycar S.S., 481 pp.
1986: VINCENT, Jean-Didier,
Biologie des passions. Editions
Odile Jacob, Paris, 401 pp.
1987: SHANNON, Thomas A.,
An Introduction to Bioethics,
Second Edition, Revised and
Updated. Paulist Press, New York,
157 pp.
1988: WALTERS, James W, (ed.),
Bioethics Today: A New Ethical
Vision. Loma Linda, California,
Loma Linda University Press,
116 pp.
1989: MIETH, Dietmar, and
POHIER, Jacques (eds.), Ethics in
the Natural Sciences. T. and T.
Clark, Edinburgh, 128 pp.
SMITH, George P., The New
Biology: Law, Ethics and
Biotechnology, New York, Plenum
Press, 303 pp.
1990: Bioethics. Special Issue,
Bulletin of the Pan-American
Health Organization, 652 pp.
BISHOP, J.E., and
WALDHOLZ, M., Genomethe
story of the most astonishing
scientific adventure ofour time
the attempt to map all the genes in
the human body. Simon and
Schuster, New York/London,
352 pp.
Council of Europe. Le médecin
face aux droits de l'homme. Padua,
Italy, CEDAM, 1485 pp.
DAVIS, Joel, Mapping the
Code: the Human Genome Project
and the Choices ofModern Science.
Wiley, New York, 294 pp.
WINGERSON, Lois, Mapping
Our Genes: the Genome Project
and the Future ofMedicine.
Dutton, New York, 338 pp.
1991: BANKOWSKI, Zbigniew
and CAPRON, Alexander Morgan
(eds.), Genetics, Ethics and Human
Values: Human Genome Mapping,
Genetic Screening and Gene
Therapy.Proceedings ofthe
XXIVth CIOMS Conference,
Tokyo and Inuyama City, Japan;
22-27July 1990. Council for
International Organizations of the
Medical Sciences, Geneva, 200 pp.
LENOIR, Noëlle, Aux
frontières de la vie. Vols. I and II.
La Documentation française, Paris,
237 pp. and 477 pp.
1992: Consorcio para la
Organización de Madrid, Capital
Europea de la Cultura 1992,
Biotecnología y futuro del hombre:
la respuesta bioética. EUDEMA
S.A., Madrid, 173 pp.
Council on Ethical and Judicial
Affairs of the American Medical
Association, Code ofMedical
Ethics. Current opinions. American
Medical Association, Chicago,
Illinois, 64 pp.
1993: BERTRAND, Jordan,
Voyage autour du génome. Le tour
du monde en 80 labos. Les
Editions INSERM, Paris, 182 pp.
BRODY, Eugene B.,
Biomedical Technology and
Human Rights. UNESCO, Paris
and Dartmouth Publishing Co.,
Aldcrshot (England) and
Brookfield, Vermont (U.S.A.),
312 pp.
GROS, François, Regard sur la
biologie contemporaine. Gallimard
and UNESCO, France, 318 pp.
Periodicals
BIOETHICS (quarterly)
Basil Blackwell Ltd.,
108 Cowley Road,
Oxford OX4 1JF,
United Kingdom.
Tel: 0865 79 11 00.
BULLETIN OF MEDICAL
ETHICS (10/year)
Editorial Office: 3 1 Corsica Street,
London N5 1JT, United Kingdom.
Tel: (44 71) 354 42 52.
HUMAN GENE THERAPY
(bi-monthly)
Mary Ann Liebert Inc., 1651 Third
Avenue, New York
NY 10128, U.S.A.
Tel: (212) 289 23 00.
JOURNAL OF CLINICAL
ETHICS (quarterly) University
Publishing Group, 107 E., Church
Street, Frederick,
MD 21701, U.S.A.
Tel: (301) 694 85 31.
JOURNAL OF MEDICAL
ETHICS (quarterly) B.M.J.
Publishing Group, B.M.A. House,
Tavistock Square, London
WC1 9JR, United Kingdom.
Tel: (44 71)387 44 99.
JOURNAL OF MEDICINE
AND PHILOSOPHY
(bi-monthly) Kluwer Academic
Publishers, Postbus 17, 3300 AA
Dordrecht, Netherlands.
Tel: (31)78 33 49 11.
THE LANCET (weekly)
Lancet Ltd., 42 Bedford Square,
London WC1B3SL,
United Kingdom.
Tel: (44 71) 436 49 81.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
National ethics committees worldwide
Over the past ten years or so, many-
countries have established national or
local committees responsible for setting
out an ethical position in relation to
developments in the life sciences and
medicine, such as organ transplants,
medically-assisted procreation and exper¬
iments on human beings.
Similar committees have been set up by
some hospitals to give an opinion on
medical practice or on the hospital as
institution, or by public bodies funding
scientific research with a view to giving
their approval to research projects.
In countries where no such national or
local committees exist, this advisory role
may be performed by bioethics institutes
forming part of research centres or uni¬
versities.
Many ethics committees have also set
themselves the task of educating, briefing
and alerting the public. Their work is
essential if the public is to grasp the
importance of the issues at stake and is to
be involved in establishing priorities and
making choices in life-sciences research
and its applications. These committees
often encourage discussion between spe¬
cialists and the general public.
In some countries, committee members
are appointed in their personal capacity
by national authorities; in others they
are named by professional bodies, such as
the Bar or Medical Associations.
As a rule, the statutes of these commit¬
tees designate the people or institutions
empowered to refer to them matters
within their competence. However, the
committees may also decide on their own
authority to examine specific issues or
matters of topical interest.
In most cases, the committees hand
down recommendations or opinions
which, although only of an advisory
nature, are largely taken into considera¬
tion by such decision-making bodies as
parliaments, governments and profes¬
sional associations.
UNESCO has conducted a wide-ranging
survey among its Member States in a bid
to identify the main national ethics com¬
mittees or other similar bodies, to asso¬
ciate them with the work of its Interna¬
tional Bioethics Committee, and to
encourage the establishment of an inter¬
national network of national and local
ethics committees.
The list below gives details of the main
national ethics committees in a number
of countries. Readers are invited to con¬
tact their own country's committee for
further information.
Georges B. Kutukdjian
NATIONAL BIOETHICS COMMITTEES
AUSTRALIA
Centre for Bioethics, 12 Clarence Street, Burwood, New
South Wales, Australia. Tel: (6102) 745 2364
Dr. T. Connolly (Director)
International Association of Bioethics, c/o Mrs Kay Boyle,
Executive Officer, Centre for Human Bioethics, Monash
University, Clayton, Victoria 3168, Australia.
Tel: (61 3) 565 4279, Fax: (61 3) 565 32 79
Prof. P. Singer (President), Prof. R. Chadwick (Secretary)
CANADA
National Council on Bioethics in Human Research,
774 Echo Drive, Ottawa, Ontario K1S 5N8, Canada.
Tel: (613) 730-6225, Fax: (613) 730-8251
Mr. A. Lynch (President)
FRANCE
Comité Consultatif National d'Ethique pour les Sciences de
la Vie et de la Santé, 101 rue Tolbiac, F-75654 Paris Cedex
113, France. Tel: (1) 44.23.60.16,
Fax (1)45 85 68 56
Prof. J. Bernard (Honorary Chairman), Prof. J.-P. Changeux
(Chairman)
INDIA
Indian Council of Medical Research, Central Ethical
Committee, Ansari Nagar, New Delhi 110 029, India.
IRELAND
The Health Research Board, 73 Lower Baggat Street,
Dublin 2, Ireland. Tel: (353-1) 76 11 76
MALTA
Ministry for Home Affairs and Social Development, Bioethics
Consultative Committee, Casa Leoni, St. Joseph High Road,
Santa Venera HMR 18, Malta. Tel: (356) 485 100,
Fax: (356) 443 595 Ms T. Mamo (Administrative Secretary)
NEW ZEALAND
Health Research Council of New Zealand, Ethics Committee,
P.P. Box 5541, Wellesley Street, Auckland, New Zealand.
Tel: (64-9) 379 82 27. Fax: (64-9) 377 99 88
Professor N. Kinross (Chairperson)
SRI LANKA
Faculty of Medicine, Ethical Review Committee, Kynsey
Road,
Colombo 8, Sri Lanka. Professors S. Goonewardena and K.
Mendis (Chairpersons)
UNITED KINGDOM
The Nuffield Foundation, Nuffield Council on Bioethics,
28 Bedford Square, London WC1B 3EG, United Kingdom.
Tel: (44-71) 631 05 66 Fax: (44-71) 323 48 77
Mr. D. Shapiro (Executive Secretary)
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
Congressional Bioethics Advisory Board, c/o Pacific Center
for Health Policy and Ethics, University of Southern California
Law Center, Los Angeles CA 90089-0071, U.S.A.
Tel: (1-213) 743 77 34 Fax: (1-213) 743 63 14
Professor A. Capron (Chairman)
Hastings Center, 255 Elm Road, Briarcliff Manor, New York
10510, U.S.A.
Tel: (1-914) 762 85 00 Fax (1-914) 762 21 24
Dr. D. Callahan (Director)
National Institute of Health, Bioethics Program, Building 10,
Room 1C116, 9000 Rockville Pike, Bethesda, MD 20892,
U.S.A.
Tel: (1-301) 496 24 29 Fax: (1-301) 402 02 44
Head: post vacant
UNESCO'S
BIOETHICS
DATABASE
To provide information on human
genome research and its applica¬
tions and on related bioethical
publications, UNESCO's Bioethics
Unit has set up a database which
currently comprises more than
2,000 references. Mainly conceived
as a working tool for UNESCO's
International Bioethics Com¬
mittee (IBC), the database could
also be useful to UNESCO National
Commissions, other United
Nations agencies and external
users (researchers, scientists, ethi-
cists, journalists, universities, etc.)
interested in updated sources of
information on bioethical issues
related to genetics. The database,
available on personal computer
under Windows, is an application
based on a DBMS (DataBase Man¬
agement System) software. At pre¬
sent it compiles publications avail¬
able at the Bioethics Unit and at
the central UNESCO database, and
data obtained by several on-line
databases and members of IBC.
A summarized printout citing all
publications in the database has
been produced for easy consulta¬
tion. The database is not at present
directly accessible to the public,
but the Bioethics Unit would be
happy to respond to requests.
Bioethics Unit, UNESCO,
1 rue Miollis, 75015 Paris, France
Tel: 33-1-45 68 45 09
Fax:33-1-43 06 07 72
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN
< ction
28
A UNESCO BIOETHICS
CHAIR
The first Unesco Chair in Bioethics,
which was recently created in the Faculty
of Law and Social Sciences of the
University of Buenos Aires, is expected to
foster the dissemination of knowledge
and information on genetics and
molecular biology and their social,
cultural, ethical and legal implications.
Other universities in Latin America will
be associated with its activities, with the
aim of developing a regional co-operation
network, in particular in connection with
research on the human genome. It will
form part of a world-wide network which
UNESCO ¡s planning to establish, with a
view to promoting international co¬
operation in this field.
TESTING GOD AND THE
DEVIL
On 1 5 September, the International
Marine Environment Award of the World
Underwater Federation (CMAS) will be
presented at a ceremony at Unesco
Headquarters in Paris to a team of divers
from the Polar Biology Group of the P.P.
Shirshov Institute of Oceanology of the
Russian Academy of Sciences in Moscow.
It rewards some twenty years of
courageous research under the ice in
unexplored polar regions where, in the
terms of the letter which the scientist Dr
Igor Melnikov addressed to CMAS, "for
hundreds of hours testing God and the
Devil" this team discovered and described
hitherto unknown biological communities
playing a key role in polar marine
ecosystems. The biennial award, which is
supported by Unesco and the
Intergovernmental Océanographie
Commission under the patronage of King
Juan Carlos of Spain, was presented for
the first time in 1992 to the British
association Coral Cay Conservation.
A RADIO STATION FOR
RWANDA
Dismayed at the tragic situation in
Rwanda, the Director-General of Unesco
has decided that the Organization will
give its support to a "Reporters sans
Frontières" project aimed at setting up a
PEACE-MAKERS
OF THE YEAR
On 6 July, at Unesco Headquarters,
Mr. Itzhak Rabin and Mr. Shimon
Peres, respectively Prime Minister
and Foreign Minister of Israel, and
Mr. Yasser Arafat, President of the
Palestine Liberation Organization
(PLO), jointly received the Félix
Houphouët-Boigny Peace Prize from
the hands of the Director-General
of Unesco, Mr. Federico Mayor.
Mr. Mayor welcomed the three
prizewinners who, he said, "by their
clearsightedness, their courage and
their determination, have succeeded
in making the path of peace prevail".
He then went on to present them
with gold medals and peace
diplomas and a cheque for 800,000
French francs. The presentation was
followed by a repeat of the historic
handshake on the White House
lawn after the signature, on 1 3
September 1 993, of the Declaration
of Principles on Interim Serf-
Government Arrangements.
In his acceptance speech, the
Prime Minister of Israel expressed
the hope that similar handshakes
would be exchanged "between the
residents of Gaza and Ashkelon,
Jericho and Ma'ale Adumim". The
Minister of Foreign Affairs spoke of
a "historic divorce" from war,
hatred, suspicion and terror. The
PLO leader called for a frank,
precise and rapid application of the
terms of the peace agreements.
Former United States Secretary
of State Henry Kissinger, Nobel
laureate and President of the
Houphouët-Boigny Peace Prize jury,
said: "We chose to express our faith
in the hopes of our honorées, in the
dreams they expressed, and not in
the second thoughts that they may
have. Too many have died. Too many
hopes have been blighted for us to
do less than pay tribute to the best
possible outcome. We pay the
honorées this expression of our
respect and our faith that they
conclude what they have started".
Created in 1 989 in honour of
the former President of Côte
d'Ivoire, the Houphouët-Boigny
Prize, one of the United Nations
system's most important awards,
was awarded in 1 992 to the Hague
Academy of International Law and in
1991 to Frederik de Klerk and
Nelson Mandela.
humanitarian radio station for the
country. The station will be located in
Tanzania or Zaire and will be operated by
a team of journalists belonging to
Rwanda's two ethnic groups with the
assistance of the Swiss French-language
Broadcasting System. It will put out
practical information for the country's
civilian population on matters relating to
basic needs crucial to their survival, such
as water, food, medical care and shelter.
THE VISA BARRIER
Before the collapse of the Berlin Wall,
Western news agencies sometimes had to
wait for years before they could open
offices in Moscow. Now, journalists from
Russia and other ex-Soviet States are
having to wait from three to five months,
and sometimes for as long as a year and a
half, before they are granted visas for
Western countries. The delays, which are
due to the tightening of those countries'
immigration laws, were among the
problems raised by Russian journalists
with representatives of eight Western
media professional organizations at a
meeting held at Unesco Headquarters in
May. These representatives undertook to
ask the Member States of the Conference
on Security and Co-operation in Europe
to relax the entry requirements for
journalists. They also called on Unesco to
organize and co-ordinate assistance to
Russia's independent media.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
What happened to development?
"We can help a tree to grow by tending its roots, not bypulling on its branches "
THE cause of the serious prob¬
lems confronting so many
of the countries of Eastern
Europe today is not freedom,
but rather the burden of
oppression which they had to
bear for so long. Similarly, eco¬
nomic circumstances or the
hand of fate are not responsible
for keeping those countries that
have long been described as
"developing" on the poverty
line. The fault lies in our atti¬
tudes, the attitudes of all of us on either side of the divide sep¬
arating the haves from the have-nots, and in our views on how
development aid should be dispensed and received.
At the receiving end, people may look upon aid as a kind of
miraculous gift that will turn pumpkins into glass coaches
and make deserts blossom. To wait for such miracles to happen
is to wait indefinitely, like waiting for Godot. The answer to the
many problems the developing countries are facing does not lie
beyond their borders or beyond their reach. It lies deep within
themselves and in their political determination to re-order
their national priorities from top to bottom, put down the
foundations of democracy in knowledge and citizenship, and
see to it that development becomes everybody's business, the
fruit of their creative talents and endeavours in both the sweat
of their toil and the cool of their moments of rest.
COLLECTIVE SCHIZOPHRENIA
When it comes to development aid, we have to speak out and
make it perfectly clear that the approach adopted hitherto, in
which economic growth was regarded as the be-all and end-all,
has turned out to be wrong-headed. It is true that growth is the
driving force behind progress, but it is by no means synony¬
mous with development. We have to completely change course
if the intolerable and all-pervasive imbalances existing in the
world, the chasm between rich and poor across the globe and
in individual countries alike, the collective schizophrenia from
which we are suffering, are not to spell the demise of the
human species.
I am weighing my words: the fact is that poverty and
famine, like war, are killers. Every day that comes, they stifle all
hope and dignity in thousands of human beings and claim
thousands of lives, especially of children. Combating poverty
is an economic, social, political and ethical imperative a "pol-
ethical" imperative.
Today, more than ever before, development is humanity's
common goal. The destiny we share comes from our economic
interdependence, the ever-tighter interweaving of the human
fabric as a result of the rapid strides being made by communi
cations, and the planet-wide nature of such afflictions as drug
addiction, Aids, pollution, terrorism and poverty, which are no
respecters of national borders. No country is immune from the
heavy toll they take and, as a result, a new perception is growing
of what human security could and should be. It is this that is
giving rise to a new approach to development.
It is true that it has taken us several decades to grasp the
complexity of this process, whose social, cultural and indeed
spiritual features we cannot go on blithely ignoring. Whenever
we cleared one hurdle and made some headway, we thought we
had found the password. The ideal form of development was
described in such terms as endogenous, self-directed or all-
inclusive, and, later, as sustainable. We have now grasped the
main point, which is that development must first of all make
it possible to spark off the full potential of the human beings
who are both the prime movers in the process and its ulti¬
mate beneficiaries. Sustainable human development is the only
acceptable definition of our common goal.
A LIVING ORGANISM
World Bank Vice-President Ismail Serageldin once described the
sort of development for which we are all striving as being like
"a tree we can help to grow by tending its roots, not by pulling
on its branches". This is an image that has the merit of giving
us an immediate insight into three ideas. The first of these is that
development is a complex process, with its upsteam and down¬
stream factors and the causal links between them, and with
knock-on effects that have yet to be gauged. The second idea
is bound up with the first, inasmuch as development is an all-
encompassing process, none of whose features can be left out
of the reckoning. As a result, the approach to it has to be both
interdisciplinary and intersectoral. The third idea is funda¬
mental, since development is a process that is by definition
dynamic, like a living organism towards which we have to
adopt the highest standards and show respect, especially since
we are dealing with people.
When it comes to environmental issues and to social justice
or population growth, the change in direction will mean that
there will have to be a far-reaching rethinking of attitudes
and of the systems used for redistributing wealth and modes of
production and consumption the world over.
Since this is bound to be a long-drawn-out task, there is all
the more reason to embark on it without a moment's delay.
Changes as radical as these will require everybody young
and old, men and women, rich and poor, people from North and
South alike to play their part. This is yet another reason
why such a worldwide transformation should start here and
now in the places where you and I live, in our homes, our
neighbourhoods, our villages and towns. It is at the municipal
and local levels that the answers calculated to save the world will
be worked out and put to the test.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The TowerofLondon ^ram'sUary
Äverygreat and most strong tower*
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
30
TheTower ofLondon is the most
popular historic site in the
British Isles, welcoming two
and a half million visitors a year. The
biggest drawing card is the lewel House,
where the Crown Jewels are displayed in
all their panoply. In March 1994, a com¬
pletely newJewel House, located on the
ground floor of Waterloo Block, was
opened by Queen Elizabeth II. The
Jewels are seen in brilliantly lit glass-
enclosed cases in a series of rooms,
while visitors are borne slowly past on a
moving floorway or "travellator". Above
the cases, giant screens project a
panorama of the Jewels' history, with
the Coronation illustrating their cere¬
monial purpose.
While the Coronation rites extend
back to St. Edward the Confessor in Saxon
times, the Jewels at Queen Elizabeth's
Coronation, that the visitors see, come
from the Restoration ofCharles II in 1660
or later. The Puritans ofOliver Cromwell's
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Mi
\ \
> '
William the Conqueror's
Tower, whose stark
silhouette has long been a
familiarfeature ofthe
London skyline, isa
microcosm ofnine
centuries ofEnglish history.
The symbol ofthe power of
the monarchy, it has never
surrendered to the
sightseers whoflock to it in
their millions and
make it one ofthe British
capital's mostpopular
tourist venues.
in the Regalia; the Coronation Robes;
the Crowns, Sceptres and Orbs, among
them the great gold St. Edward's Crown
made for Charles II and still used at the
investiture; the Imperial State Crown
made for Queen Victoria, thickly set with
precious stones and worn at state cere¬
monies such as the opening of Parlia¬
ment. The State Crown also displays in
its lower cross the large ruby of the Black
Prince, which adorned the helmet of
Henry V at Agincourt in 1415, and the
Stuart sapphire, and in the uppermost
cross gleams a sapphire said to be from
the ring of the Confessor himself. In a
royal sceptre sparkles the Star ofAfrica,
the largest cut diamond in the world.
White granite brought from Caen
Adjacent to the Jewel House is the mas¬
sive White Tower, the original tower built
by William the Conqueror at the end of
the eleventh century. The Norman king,
who overthrew the Saxon Harold at
Hastings, consolidated his triumph by
Above, aerial view of the Tower of London within its
double fortifications. Right, one of the forty-odd
Yeoman Warders who guard the Tower. Famed for
their colourful uniformround-brimmed hats and
tunics embroidered with the royal crown and
monogram they are more commonly known by
their nickname of "Beefeaters".
short-lived regime in the 1650s despised
the glittering trappings ofmonarchy and
sold off the medieval Crown Jewels. A
few pieces survived and eventually
returned to the royal collection.
One passes in succession the Royal
Maces, Trumpets, and the Great Sword
of State; the jewelled Sword of Offering
girt about the Sovereign by the Arch¬
bishop; the medieval gold Ampulla and
Spoon, by which the Sovereign is
anointed with holy oil, the oldest objects 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
"TheJewels are seen in
brilliantlylitglass-enclosed
cases in aseries ofrooms,
while visitors are borne
slowly past on a moving
floorway."
32
.. building strong castíes throughout Eng¬
land. For London, he chose the site of a
former Roman camp on the Thames and
in 1078 he confided to Gundulf, Bishop of
Rochester the construction of what
William Fitzstephen's 12th-century
Chroniclewould describe as "a very great
and most strong Palatine Tower". Unlike
wooden Saxon structures, the Tower of
London was built of Kentish limestone
with dressings of white granite stone
brought from Caen.
The White Tower, its Caen stone
white-washed, with spired turrets at the
four corners, still dominates the sur¬
roundings. Over the centuries, addi¬
tional structures were built until the
whole consisted of thirteen towers of
the Inner Ward and six towers and bas¬
tions of the outer ward.
Previously, the only entrance by land
was over a walled causeway, 30 metres
wide, leading to the barbican of the Lion
Tower. Here prowled the King's beasts,
and the Constable, the chiefofficer of the
tower, was paid 14 pence per day, with 6
pence more for chunks ofbloody meat,
to feed the lions, leopards, bears and
wolves.
Palace and prison
Today, the Lion Tower has gone and the
beasts were despatched in 1834 to the
new London zoo. The entrance is now
through the gate of the Middle Tower
and across another smaller causeway
over the dry moat, drained in 1843, up to
the Byward Tower, with guardsmen in
scarlet coats and tall black busbies.
The various towers before the visitor
evoke mingled memories: ofcenturies of
cruelty and anguish, of brilliant
pageantry, of all the great work of the
kingdom carried on within these walls.
No better description of the original
purposes of the Tower ofLondon may be
found than in John Stowe's Survey of
London, published in 1598.
"This Tower is a citadel to defend or
to command the city; a royal palace for
assemblies or treaties; a prison of state
for the most dangerous offenders; the
only place of coinage for all England at
this time; the armoury for warlike pro¬
vision; the treasury of the ornaments
and the jewels of the crown; and general
conserver of the most records of the
king's courts ofjustice at Westminster".
The Conqueror's massive White
Tower now beckons. After the disastrous
fire at Windsor Castle in 1993, the His-
Left, State crowns. At
right is the crown made
in 1937 for the
coronation of Queen
Elizabeth, the consort
of King George VI. It
contains the Koh-i-
Noor, the famous
diamond presented to
Queen Victoria by the
East India Company in
1850.
Left below: in
foreground, the orb
made for Charles II In
1661 and used since
then at the coronation
of his successors. In
background is Queen
Mary's orb. it was
made for Queen Mary,
who was crowned
jointly with her
husband William III in
1689.
toric Royal Palaces Agency, which man¬
ages the Tower, created a fire escape on
the second floor which will take visi¬
tors, who may number 1,000 at peak
periods, down to the first floor near a
well-marked exit. A fire detection and
alarm system is likewise installed. The
Jewel House has a fire control centre for
the entire site.
St. John's Chapel occupies part of the
second and third floors, while the White
Tower houses the finest collection of
armour in Europe. It was begun by
Henry VIII whose gigantic suits may be
seen in the Tudor armoury on the top
floor. Renaissance and medieval armour
are on the second floor, while tourna¬
ment armour is found on the first floor.
From the White Tower, on the left-
hand side, is the stretch of greensward
called Tower Green, where a plaque,
placed at Queen Victoria's command,
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
indicates the site of the scaffold. Here,
those of the highest rank, condemned
for defiling or reaching for the Crown,
were beheaded. Two of King Henry's
unfortunate wives met their doom on
Tower Green. Both were accused ofadul¬
tery, though probably Queen Anne,
mother ofElizabeth I, was innocent. Her
execution was delayed so that, atAnne's
request, a skilled headsman with a fine
sword might be brought from France.
The morning of her execution, 21
May 1536, she asked the Lieutenant of
the Tower ifhe had seen the sword and
if it was good. The Lieutenant assured
her that it was. "Then," quoth Anne, "it
were well for me, for I have a slender
little neck."
When the Tower guns boomed,
announcing the execution, bluff King
Hal was cross-gartered and wearing
yellow, signs of joy. The royal widower
was soon to wed Jane Seymour. Anne
was buried in the nearby Chapel of St.
Peter ad Vincula, where Queen
Catherine also lies.
The last to perish on this raven-
haunted Green was Queen Elizabeth's
gallant cavalier, the Earl of Essex, who
aspired to the Crown. Now plump glossy
ravens strut on Tower Green, once the
scene of so much blood and grief, while
the wind sighs in the stately sycamores.
A tradition holds that if the eight care¬
fully guarded ravens should go, the
Tower will fall.
Every night at 10 p.m., the ancient
Ceremony of the Keys is enacted by the
ChiefYeoman Warder, with an escort of
a sergeant and three guardsmen in
scarlet tunics and black busbies. First
he locks the outer gate, then the great
doors of the Middle Tower, finally those
of the Byward. Returning to the Inner
Ward, he is challenged by an officer with
bared sword. The guardsmen present
arms; the yeoman warder raises his
Tudor hat and cries: "God preserve
Queen Elizabeth!"
As chimes toll the hour, a bugler
sounds the lingering silvery notes of
"The Last Post", which echo across 900
years in the night and memories of
London's mighty Tower.
FRANCIS LEARY
is an American writer and journalist whose works
include The Golden Longing, a study of life in 15th-
century Europe, and several novels.
"Glossy ravens strut on
Tower Green, once the scene
ofso much blood andgrief.
A tradition holds that ifthe
ravens shouldgo, the Tower
willfall."
The execution of the Earl of
Strafford on Tower Hill beneath
the Tower of London, on 12 May
1641. An engraving by the
Prague-born artist Wenzel
Hollar, who died in London in
1677.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
MELINA'S LAST BATTLE
34
THE unforgettable Medea who bestrode
the stage in Salonika, the headstrong
Ilya who appeared, larger than life, on
cinema screens all over the world, the
determined resistance fighter who took
on her country's military junta, the ever-
active Minister of Culture, Greece's leading
lady, is no longer with us. But she has
bequeathed to us the legacy of the over¬
brimming vitality that made her so charis¬
matic a figure.
Her memory lives on in the Melina
Mercouri Foundation that has been created
by her husband, the film director Jules
Dassin, in order to further the causes for
which she fought and fulfil her dream of
completing the construction of the new
Acropolis museum and bringing back the
Parthenon sculptures to Greece.
Melina Mercouri fired the first shots in
"the battle of the Parthenon sculptures" in
the 1980s, but their turbulent history goes
back many years before that.
"Furiously, but withpleasure"
Between 448 and 432 B.C., the great
sculptor Phidias and the celebrated archi¬
tect Ictinus built a temple dedicated to
Athena, the goddess of wisdom, on the
hill of the Acropolis in Athens. The temple
had two parts, the "hundred-foot-long"
Hecatompedon housing a 12-metre-high
gold and ivory statue of Athena by Phidias,
and the Parthenon, the "room of the
maidens", which later gave its name to the
entire building.
The förty-six simple yet imposing
columns of the outside colonnade sup¬
ported a frieze whose ninety-three square
"metope" sections depicted scenes from
Greek mythology. At either end were two
pediments illustrating the birth of Athena
and her contest with Poseidon. The inner
walls of the "celia" or chamber housing the
statue of the goddess were decorated with
a 160-metre-long frieze.
The Parthenon's Doric splendour
remained untouched by the hand of time
for some 900 years. Then it suffered its
first indignity. It was taken over by new
gods and visited by foreigners prompted
more by greed than respect. It was used
successively as the place of worship of a
Christian cult, a Catholic church and a
small mosque. When the Venitians laid
siege to Athens in 1687, a cannon ball
caused extensive damage, and General
Francesco Morosini took advantage of the
situation to carry away everything he could
tear off the pediments.
A century later the British ambassador
On 6 March Melina Mercouri,
known to her fellow-Greeks as
"the light of Attica", passed
away after a long struggle
against cancer, the last of her
many battles
7
\
^j
to Athens, Thomas Bruce, seventh Earl of
Elgin, succeeded in obtaining authoriza¬
tion from the Ottomans, who had ruled
Athens since 1456, to remove "certain stone
fragments on which inscriptions and figures
have been carved". Between 1801 and 1803
he removed most of the remaining sculp¬
tures and shipped them to London. Some
ten years later, the British parliament bought
them from him and donated them to the
British Museum, where they remain to this
day and are more commonly known as the
Elgin Marbles.
This, then, was how the Parthenon,
one of the seven wonders of the ancient
world, came to be stripped of the essence
of its beauty, "It was as though it had had
an eye gouged out," Melina Mercouri said
not long ago. "It is cruel, and it is very
ugly. I shall carry on fighting this battle to
the very end." The battle to which she was
referring was aimed at returning the sculp¬
tures to their original location. As the
Greek poet Yannis Ritsos put it, the sculp¬
tures "cannot get used to seeing less sky".
Melina Mercouri threw herself into this
struggle with the same fervour that she put
into her political and theatrical life. As she
said in the December 1991 issue of the
UNESCO Courier, she campaigned in poli¬
tics iñ the same way that she rehearsed in the
theatre "furiously, but with pleasure". Pas¬
sion was the driving force behind everything
this exceptional woman did. The whole
Greek nation gradually came to identify
with her, and this in itself was a stunning act
of revenge on the colonels who had stripped
her of her Greek nationality. In her bid to
save her homeland from dictatorship during
her seven years' exile, she went on singing
The Children ofPiraeus on stages all over
the world. On the international political
and cultural scene, as Minister of Culture
from 1982 onwards she never let up in her
fight for the return of the "marbles" to their
homeland.
A certain idea of Greece
In 1984, the Greek authorities lodged an
official request with the British govern¬
ment for the marbles to be returned. In
1989, they launched the project for the con¬
struction of a new museum on the Acrop¬
olis, where "an enormous room will remain
completely empty until the Parthenon frieze
is returned", as Melina Mercouri stated late
in 1993, shortly after she had returned to the
Ministry of Culture.
But this was not her only concern. She
also set out to create a University of the
Mediterranean; to carry through the "Arch¬
ipelagos" programme aimed at reviving the
memory of the Greek islands; and to host
the 1996 Olympic Games in Athens. These
were all projects to which she gave herself
to the full in her determination to serve a
certain idea of Greece and to stave off the
threat of death that hung over her for the last
five years of her life.
She died without seeing the Elgin mar¬
bles back on the Acropolis. But she had
already laid her plans. "Ask me if I'll be
alive when they come back," she said. "The
answer is yes, I'll be alive! And if not, then
I'll be born again". E.J.M.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
OF MEN AND
MOUNTAINS
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
.ÄÄfrtP*; i/)
I
on
UJ
£T
D
O
u
O
u
en
The world's great mountain
ranges such as the Andes, the
Alps, the Himalayas and the
highlands of Madagascar and
Ethiopia are not as solid as they
look. Back in 1973, a report pro¬
duced by Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere Programme (MAB)
acknowledged just how fragile they
really are. "Mountain areas in dif¬
ferent parts of the world are at very
different levels of influence by man's
activities," the report points out.
"Generally speaking though, man's
impacts on mountain ecosystems
are producing critical situations at
a faster rate than in many other
types of ecosystems. The inclina¬
tion of the slopes accelerates and
aggravates all processes of site
destruction such as erosion and
landslides. Site restoration is much
more difficult than in lowlands.
Mountain ecosystems must there¬
fore be treated in an especially
careful way."
Some 10 per cent of the world's
population lives in mountain areas,
but at least halfofhumanity depends
more or less directly on the resources
they provide in the shape of water,
energy, minerals, forests or recre¬
ational areas. This is one of the rea¬
sons why the United Nations Con¬
ference on Environment and
Development (UNCED), held in Rio
de Janeiro in 1992, devoted chapter
13 of its Agenda 21 to developing
mountain ecosystems.
"Mountain" is used here in the
broad sense to cover all areas higher
than 900 metres above sea level, a
zone representing one-quarter of
the world's land surface. "We are
dealing with maximum global
diversity from sea level to almost
9,000 metres, from tropical rain¬
forest to permanent ice and snow,
and from climates with over 12
metres of annual precipitation to
extreme high-altitude deserts,"
writes Peter B. Stone in his preface
to a remarkable collective work enti¬
tled The State ofthe World's Moun¬
tains (1992) of which he is the
editor-in-chief.
H0TSP0T AREAS
It should come as no surprise that 40
per cent of the world's biosphere
reserves are to be found in moun¬
tain regions and that half of the
"hotspot areas" are located in the
tropics, in such regions as the
uplands ofMadagascar, the slopes of
the Andes in westernAmazonia, the
eastern Himalayas, the Philippines
highlands, the mountain forests of
the eastern rift in Tanzania, India's
Western Ghats and the montane
forests of Sri Lanka. Although in
absolute terms there are fewer plant
species in mountain regions than in
lowland areas, endemic species in
danger of disappearing tend to be
found in these regions. In Sabah, in
Malaysia, for example, Mount Kina-
balu is home to 4,000 to 4,500 plant
species, more than one-quarter the
number of all recorded species in
the United States. Nor should we
forget that potatoes, coffee, wheat,
maize and numerous varieties of
Snowy peaks of the Himalayas
glow in the sunlight.
fruit trees all originally came from
the mountain areas of the different
continents.
Mountains also supply us with
water. The rivers flowing down from
the Himalaya, Karakorum, Pamir
and Tibet ranges, fed by melting
snow which the forests regulate and
slow down, are the economic
lifeblood of the areas they cross. If
the forest cover were to be depleted,
the snow would melt more quickly
and would give rise to water short¬
ages in the dry season. In South
America, deforestation in the Andes
is liable to have an adverse impact
on the whole of the Amazon basin
and could cause severe flooding.
The same is true in Africa, where
the rivers rising on Mount Kenya
provide arteries for entire civiliza¬
tions. Mountains also have an influ¬
ence on climate and on both local
and continental air- current pat¬
terns. The temperature falls by
0.5°C to 1°C for every 100-metre
rise in altitude, because the air is
thinner and absorbs less of the sun's
heat. Precipitation increases with
altitude, and hence such regions
are blessed with rainfall. This is true
of the North American Rockies, the
Andes in South America and the
Himalayas in northern India. Were
it not for the mountain formations
of the Maghreb, the Sahara would
soon extend right up to the Mediter¬
ranean seaboard.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
DANS: FOR AND AGAINST
Advantage is often taken of these
abundant water resources to build
dams. A study carried out by the
International Commission on Large
Dams (ICOLD) shows that the go-
ahead is given each year for the con¬
struction of some 300 large dams
(measuring 15 metres and upwards
in height) and that work is actually
started on roughly the same
number. Nearly 3,000 dams are
expected to be built world-wide
between 1991 and 2001. The sur¬
face area of the catchments they
will create will cover 1.5 million
square kilometres, representing an
area the size of Spain, France and
Germany combined. Mountain
dwellers can have a very different
view of dams from people living in
low-lying downstream areas, who
look forward to having electricity,
being protected from the destruc¬
tion caused by flooding and
enjoying the benefits of irrigation
(even though they may be deprived
of the fertile silt that used to be
deposited by the river before the
dam was built). People living in
upstream areas often resent man-
made lakes because of the bitter
experience of being forced out of
their homes, the swallowing-up of
plant and wildlife and even out¬
breaks of water-borne diseases. In
any event, they are not asked for
their opinion and there is very little
prospect of their being given a
hearing. In any case, is there really
any justification for halting devel¬
opment for the sake of saving a
flower or a rodent from extinction?
People remote from the seat of
powerwith no means ofrepresenta¬
tion often belong to ethnic minori¬
ties. They are left out of the main¬
stream as far as progress and
affluence are concerned and do not
even have any say in decisions
affecting them. Although they are
the custodians of their cultural values
and traditions, they are exposed to all
sorts ofpressures. Their ownership of
the land may be disputed in cases
where it is occupied by migrant
squatters who have been forced out
of lowland areas and who do not
necessarily share the uplanders' cui¬
tare and can do onlyunskilled work.
Their state of health and their diet
may be poor. Teaching is frequenüy
of a low standard and there may be
no schools in the vicinity. The people
may find it difficult to market the
produce they grow apart from the
plants used in making narcotic
drugs, ofcourse. At times ofconflict,
mountain areas invariably become
places ofrefuge for rebels, and there
are instances on every continent
where they form the borders between
states that are not always on good
terms. By contrast, mountain regions
like the Alps have become one big
playground, crisscrossed by roads
and tunnels, with chair-lifts dis¬
gorging hordes of tourists, whether
sports-lovers or not, all year round.
WORKING WITH LOCAL
POPULATIONS
Experience has shown that it is
imperative for local populations to
be involved in all development pro¬
jects. Between 1979 and 1986 Thai¬
land learnt this to its cost, when the
government set out to develop
farming in the north of the country.
As Professor Kenneth N. Brooks, of
the University of Minnesota, in the
United States, put it in a documenthe
prepared for the United Nations Food
andAgriculture Organization in 1993:
36 I
Peruvian villagers
of the high Andes.
"The main goal of the project was to
sufficiently intensifyagricultural pro¬
duction to enable shifting cultivators
to settle on lands ofslopes less than 35
per cent, thereby enabling steeper,
more fragile lands to be reforested.
This was to be achieved by (1) the
development of irrigated and rainfed
terraces; (2) promotion of Arabica
coffee and legumes as cash crops.
(3) reforestation of lands with slopes
exceeding 35 per cent. The project
encountered several problems which
may be attributed to the failure to
involve the local Karen in the plan¬
ning process."
Conflict arose because the gov¬
ernment had not taken the trouble
to study the traditional land own¬
ership practices of the Karen ethnic
minority which had a different legal
status from that in the rest of the
country. Still more serious was the
fact that, in an earlier project, a large
number of farmers had been
encouraged to grow Arabica, but
this had turned out to be a failure.
Had they been consulted, some
other type of crop might have been
contemplated. On the other hand,
the community itself indicated the
most suitable sites for building ter¬
races, and this operation proved
more successful than expected. This
example illustrates the insecure
status of mountain dwellers, who
are treated like social outcasts in
most countries. How can we blame
them for the deforestation that is
the blight of mountain areas when
they do not know where to turn for
other resources? It would be like
blaming them for being poor.
Poor as they are, mountain
people often have an aura of mys¬
tery about them. Situated at the
meeting-point between heaven and
earth, mountains are the abode of
the gods. Every civilization and
every religion has its sacred moun¬
tain, like the mountain-temples of
Angkor, Mount Olympus in Greece
and the monumental stupa of
Borobudur. Is this not an added cul¬
tural reason for taking good care of
our mountains?
The "mountain-
temples" of
Angkor.
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions. Since
1985 she has
been associated
with the
WANAD-Unesco
training
programmefor
African news
agency
journalists.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
W O R
A HIGHLY CHARGED SUMMIT
CONFERENCE
In April 1992, the world's seven largest
electricity companies decided to form
the E-7 group, the energy equivalent of
the Group of Seven (G-7), the exclu¬
sive club of the world's industrialized
nations. Belying its name, the E-7
actually has eight member compa¬
nies. France, lapan (with two compa¬
nies), Italy, Canada (also with two),
Germany and the United States
together account for 1,427 billion kilo¬
watt-hours of energy sales, with a
turnover of $110 billion, 105 million
customers, 330,000 megawatts of
installed capacity, 381,000 employees
and a wide variety of energy-gener¬
ating facilities. One aspect of the E-7's
work is, in fact, concerned with the
choice ofproduction methods, since
hydroelectric power and other renew¬
able energy sources, nuclear power
plants and thermal plants running on
natural gas, diesel oil or coal all have
different effects on the environment.
The E-7's task should be to promote
clean energy, especially in the devel¬
oping countries, through technology
transfers.
MALARIA AND THE WEATHER
A group of Dutch scientists, led by H.
J. van der Kaay, has studied the con¬
nection between the climatic changes
caused by El Niño and the malaria
epidemics which broke out in
Ecuador, Peru, Bolivia and Pakistan
in 1983, when the phenomenon was
especially noticeable. El Niño (Baby
fesus) is a warm current in the Pacific
Ocean occurring from early
December onwards (which accounts
for its name). At irregular intervals,
its waters mixwith the cold waters of
the Humboldt current flowing along
the coastlines of Ecuador and Peru.
This gives rise to torrential downpours
in the region, but at the same time
causes severe drought inAustralia and
Indonesia. The rainfall is instrumental
in spreading Plasmodiumfalciparum,
the parasite responsible for the most
virulent form ofmalaria. Advances in
weather forecasting should make it
possible for scientists to gain a better
understanding of El Nino's different
phases and give advance warning to
those populations most exposed to
the threat of epidemics.
A QUECHUA INDIAN CHAMPION OF THE
ENVIRONMENT
Six champions of the cause of envi¬
ronmental protection were honoured
by an American foundation in April,
when they were each awarded the
$60,000 Goldman Environmental
Prize. Luis Macas, 43, a Quechua
Indian, is an ardent defender of
indigenous rights in Ecuador. After
leading a general strike in 1990, he
persuaded the government to hand
over title to almost 1.2 million hectares
ofland in the Amazon region to Indian
communities. These communities are
now having to contend with the
inroads being made by oil companies
drilling in the region. Luis Macas is
heading the negotiations aimed at
prevailing on these companies to
show respect for the rainforest's fragile
ecosystem.
TOURISM YERSUS DEVELOPMENT
ON RHODES
The successful development of the
island of Rhodes, whose population
has almost tripled in the last 30 years,
MANAGING FRAGILE ECOSYSTEMS
In March 1 994, a United Nations inter-agency meeting was held at the head¬
quarters of the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) in
Rome on the theme, "Managing fragile ecosystems: sustainable mountain devel¬
opment", as a follow-up to Chapter 1 3 of UNCED's Agenda 2 1 .
Unesco is contributing to the follow-up in a variety of ways, including a
project on "The impact of human activities on mountain and tundra ecosys¬
tems" under its Man and the Biosphere Programme, and through the work
of the International Hydrological Programme, the International Geological Cor¬
relation Programme, the Programme on Geology for Sustainable and Envi¬
ronmentally Sound Development and the Programme on Natural Disaster
Reduction.
FAO is calling for a major international conference on the subject to be
convened in the near future.
is in danger of being compromised by the yearly influx of
tourists. In 1990, Rhodes had 800,000 visitors ten times the
number of local residents. Water shortages, a chronic
problem for all the Greek islands, become critical in summer.
There is also a waste-disposal problem and the bathing
beaches close to Rhodes harbour are badly polluted. How
can this superbly beautiful island, which owes its prosperity
almost entirely to the tourist industry, make a success of
development?
MORE BRIGHT IDEAS FOR RECYCLING TYRES
In the previous issue of the Courier, we described anti-
noise screens made out ofold tyres. Here is another imag¬
inative idea for making use of this bulky waste product.
Pneusol, known as "Tyresoil" in English, is the invention of
Mr. Nguyen Thanh Long, of the Central Laboratory of the
Public Works Department in Paris*. This technique, in
which used tyres are combinedwith natural or artificial soil,
is being used in civil engineering applications and public
works projects. The tyres, partly or completely shredded,
are used to increase the watertightness ofearth dams, sta¬
bilize road embankment slopes and provide highly effec¬
tive anti-earthquake material. Tyresoil not only costs three
times less than concrete and other materials, it also pro¬
vides a useful means of disposing of used tyres, ofwhich
Europe discards some 2.5 million tons each year. H
*Laboratoire Central des Ponts et Chaussées, 58, bd. Lefebvre,
75732 Paris Cedex 15, Tel: (33-1) 4043-5000, Fax: (33-1)
4043-5498.
AUSTRALIA'S "WATERWATCH"
The Australian authorities have had the excellent idea of
entrusting local communities, schools and children's
groups with monitoring rivers and wetlands and helping
to implement the 1971 Ramsar Convention on Wetlands.
Their Waterwatch programme ensures nationwide coor¬
dination ofall community-based water qualitymonitoring
projects, including Streamwatch (river monitoring) in New
South Wales and Ribbons of Blue in Western Australia.
Some projects provide basic equipment for monitoring
water quality through the measurement of such parame¬
ters as dissolved oxygen content, bacteria levels, temper¬
ature and the percentage of phosphates or nitrates.
Further information about Waterwatch can be obtained
from Australian Nature Conservation Agency, GPO Box
636, CanberraACT2601, Australia, Tel: (06) 250 0337, Fax:
(06)2500286.
u
<
LU
CiL
*1
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
INITIATIVES
U
H
<
GREENPEACE, THE RAINBOW WARRIORS
CL
O
ROT***
Greenpeace
activists in
Austria block the
railway lines into
a coal-fired power
plant.
38
The five million-odd members of
the Greenpeace movement
have one thing in common they
make a nuisance of themselves. Just
mention in their presence words
like nuclear testing or toxic waste
or the slaughter ofwhales and they
are up in arms. Their reaction is
non-violent but vigorous, some¬
times fraught with danger and
always with one eye on the media.
In 1971, they were just a bunch
of madcaps intent on stopping the
Americans from conducting a
nuclear test on an island in Alaska.
On their way to the test site, they
stayed with the Cree Indians, who
recounted to them the legend of "a
tribe, composed of all peoples and
all religions, which would one day
take back the earth from the people
who had defiled it and restore it to
its former beauty". As a token of
friendship, the Crees baptized them
"the Rainbow Warriors".
This was the starting-point for
a series of operations focusing on
eight main themes: civilian uses of
nuclear energy; disarmament; chlo¬
rinated hydrocarbons found in pes¬
ticides and some types of plastic;
the ecology of the oceans; toxic
waste and pollution transfers; the
ozone layer; climate change; and
forests.
Like top-flight athletes, Green¬
peace's hardiest members scale the
smokestacks of nuclear power
plants, clamber up cranes or dam
walls, chaining themselves to the
installations or draping banners
from them. They travel all over the
world on their fleet of eight ships,
two helicopters, a hot-air balloon
and a bus fitted out as a mobile lab¬
oratory. In their small inflatable
dinghies, they deliberately position
themselves in the line of fire ofhar¬
poons or directly under the gang¬
planks used for dumping drums of
toxic waste into the sea.
The national or international
campaigns they mount are based
on the work done by a network of
scientific experts and on on-the-
spot investigations. In 1990 Green¬
peace-United States published a
new edition of its massive survey
of the international trade in waste
products. More recently, Green¬
peace-France has brought out an
interesting document on the ship¬
ment into France of large amounts
ofwaste from other countries. The
account it gives ofsome of the cases
with which we are personally
familiar is strictly accurate. This
virtue of accuracy is essential if
Greenpeace is to be seen to be cred¬
ible in the eyes of the international
organizations with which it has con¬
sultative or observer status.
Greenpeace justifies its activi¬
ties by pointing out that it has con¬
tributed to the halt to French
nuclear testing in the atmosphere in
the South Pacific, the outlawing of
seal-fur imports by the States of the
European Union, the adoption ofa
moratorium on whale fishing and
bans on ocean dumping ofnuclear
waste and the incineration of toxic
wastes.
The stands Greenpeace takes on
issues and the campaigns it con¬
ducts are often regarded as going
too far and as being ill-timed. The
advocates of nuclear energywould
be happy to do without their con¬
stant on-the-ground opposition.
The same goes for arms merchants,
ever since Greenpeace launched a
crusade against landmines, with the
backing of many humanitarian
organizations appalled at having to
pick up the shattered remains of
horribly mutilated corpses in
Afghanistan, Cambodia and
Mozambique.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
ercator
portrait
cartographer ofgenius
by Jean Portante
On 4 December 1994, Unesco will be associated with the commemoration of
the 400th anniversary of the death of the Flemish geographer Gerhard
Mercator, founder of modern mathematical geography and inventor of the
plane map projection of the earth that bears his name.
For me the name of the great cartographer
Mercator will always be associated with
cigars. I have a distant memory ofhis bearded
face, at once jovial and pensive, emblazoned on a
cigar band, and for some reason perhaps because
of the Atlantic tobacco trade it always evoked
for me the myth of the boundless ocean and of
endless voyaging from one continent to the other.
In fact it was only much later that I learned that the
face on the cigar band was that of Mercator, the
man who rescued the word 'AÜantic" from oblivion
by reviving it on the map of the world he drew in
1569, at the height of the Renaissance. The term
"AÜantic" had first been coined in Antiquity, but in
medieval times the vast expanse of sea to the west
ofEurope was usually designated as the "Northern
Ocean" or the "Occidental Ocean".
Mercator, whose real name was Gerhard Kremer
(the German word Kremermeans merchant, mer¬
cator in Latin, the international language of the
Renaissance), had settled in Duisburg in the
Rhineland in 1 552 and had been working for years
on the then unprecedented scheme of projecting
the planetary globe or at leastwhat was known of
it at the time onto a flat surface.
Maps predate writing
Cartography had been invented long before the
Renaissance. Indeed, the first rudimentary maps
probably predated the appearance of writing.
Tablets of Phoenician origin show that by about
3000 B.C. men were already charting the main
commercial shipping routes. Although the Egyp¬
tians, with their cadastral measurements, carried
on where the Phoenicians left off, it was the Greeks
who invented map-making as we know it. Once
Thaïes ofMiletus had established that the earth is
round, and his findings had been confirmed by the
Pythagorean school, Ptolemy, at the beginning of
the Christian era, determined mathematically the
concepts of latitude and longitude. Although
Ptolemy miscalculated the earth's circumference
a most fortunate error that was at the root of
Europe's encounter with America the cartog¬
raphy of Antiquity, which was preserved in the
Arab world until the Middle Ages, contained all the
data on which Mercator based his work.
After the use ofthe compass became widespread,
sometime in the thirteenth century, the first advances
in cartography were subsequendymade by naviga¬
tors like Christopher Columbus, Vasco da Gama,
Balboa, Magellan and Elcano. By the earlyyears ofthe
fourteenth century, how¬
ever, rapid strides were also
being made through the work I
of mathematicians and
astronomers, most of them
German or Flemish, like Mercator
himself.
An armchair traveller
What do we owe to Gerhard Kremer Mercator for
all these developments? Born in 1512, he was a
typical Renaissance man, combining his talents as
a philosopher and geographer to devise a system
for projecting the earth's spherical surface onto a
flat map. When he was only eighteen and still a stu¬
dent at Louvain University, his teacher, the
astronomer Frisius, introduced him to the art of
constructing terrestrial globes. He produced his
first rudimentary map of the world at the age of
twenty-six. Not many years later, in 1541, he was
commissioned by the Emperor Charles V Flan¬
ders was then under Spanish rule to create a ter¬
restrial globe and its celestial counterpart.
The planisphere bearing his name was first pub¬
lished in 1569 after more than fifteen years' work.
Consisting of a set of eighteen engraved sheets
based on portolano charts, it is the product of an
original method ofprojection. The earth's surface is
shown in the form ofa flattened-out cylinder, with
the meridians and parallels represented by per¬
pendicular straight lines intersecting at right angles,
and the spacing between the parallels progressively
increasing from the equator to the poles. This
arrangement gives rise to some distortion in the
representation of distances, but it enables naviga¬
tors to set their course and ensure that the route they
take tallies with the map. The Mercator projection
is still used in sea and air travel today.
One of the founders of modern cartography
was thus himself an armchair traveller. His pas¬
sionate interest in cartography and his skill in
accurately portraying the world, with its conti¬
nents and oceans, in the limited space ofonly a few
pages prompted him to complete two other works:
a critical study ofPtolemy, Tabulae Geographicae
G Ptolemaie ad mentem autoris restitutae etemen-
datae (1578), ana Atlas sive Cosmographicae med-
itationes de Fabrica Mundi etfabricatifigura (1585)
("An Atlas or Cosmographical Meditations on the
Making of the World"), the definitive version of
which was published by his two sons in 1595, a year
after his death. h
This portrait of Mercator is
inset Into the border of a 1631
edition of a revised version of
his Atlas first published in 1605
by the Dutch geographer
Jocodus Hondius and often
reprinted since.
JEAN PORTANTE
is a Luxembourg writer whose
work includes stories, poems
and plays, as well as travel
books and radio programmes.
His latest novel, Mrs. Haroy ou
la mémoire de la baleine,
chronique d'une immigration,
was published in 1993 by PHI,
Echternach.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Seoul at age 600
A city built to face in the right direction
by Choe Chong-Hyon and Yi Tong-Ok
40
Capital of the Republic
of Korea since 1 945,
Seoul stands on the
Han river 60 km from
its estuary with the
Yellow Sea. This city
whose story can be
traced back to
prehistoric times
became the prestigious
capital of the Yi
dynasty 600 years ago.
When General Yi Song-gye, founder
oftheYi dynasty (1392-1910), came
to the throne in 1392, his first wish was to
transfer his capital to Han-yang (present-
day Seoul), but he was prevented from
doing so because ofobjections by some of
his subjects. The following year, at the
prompting ofone ofhis court officials and
with the encouragement of a Buddhist
monk named Muhak, the sovereign
decided to set up his capital on Mount
Kyeryongsan. His plans were again frus¬
trated, however. The mountain lay too far
south on the Korean peninsula and was
not consonant with the p'ungsu theory
based on the principles of yin-yang and
the five elements, according to which good
fortune was closely bound up with the
environment of one's place of residence
and the direction in which it faced.
Some ten other sites were envisaged
including, yet again, Han-yang, which was
finally chosen in 1394. Its location was
deemed to be favourable on several
counts: the city was in the centre of the
country, was accessible to shipping, had
roads fanning out to the north, south, east
and west, and was surrounded by moun¬
tains and rivers.
What was the reasoning behind this
decision, which created such difficulties
and took so long to make? The answer is
that our Korean ancestors looked upon
the earth as a living substance. Whenever
they selected a site, for whatever purpose,
they not only took account of its geo¬
graphical location but abided closely by
the principles enshrined in the divinatory
tradition ofgeomancy ("earth divination"),
based on the ki, the life force informing the
universe. According to the p'ungsu theory,
the ki was considered to emanate from
Mount Paektusan, the highest mountain
on the peninsula, and to strike southwards
in the direction ofMount Pukhansan, one
of the four mountains surrounding Seoul.
The city would therefore be cocooned and
protected by this life-enhancing energy.
I KYONGBOK PALACE
General Yi Song-gye ordered the Govern¬
ment Bureau in charge of the capital's
foundation to build a royal sanctuary for
his ancestors, temples for the tutelary salt
Below, the National
Museum building in
Kyongbok palace.
CHOE CH0NG-HY0N,
of the Republic of Korea, is
Professor of Architecture at
Hanyang University in Seoul.
One of his main fields of
interest is traditional
Korean architecture.
YI T0NG-0K
is in charge of the Korean
edition of the Unesco
Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
í
and grain deities, and palaces and defen¬
sive walls, and to lay out the streets. Before
work started on the new capital, ritual sac¬
rifices were made to the earth and sky
gods, the spirits of mountains and rivers
and the spirits of the five directions pro¬
tecting Kyongbok palace.
The symbol of the Yi dynasty, the
palace was built at the very heart of this
highly propitious location. Inaugurated
in 1395, it was comparable in size to the
Palace ofVersailles. In front of the building,
the Kwanghwamum Gate marking the
centre of the capital was flanked by two
stone carvings of haet'ae, mythical crea¬
tures resembling lions and representing
water. According to the principles of geo-
mantic divination, these beasts protected
the palace from the spirit of fire emanating
from Mount Kwanaksan, south of Seoul.
Round the palace were the "four great
gates" Tongdaemun to the east,
Sodaemun to the west, Namdaemun to
the south and Pukch'ongmun to the north.
Between them were the "four small gates"
facing north-east, north-west, south-east
and south-west.
Owing to its location and design, the
palace functioned as a source of energy.
The literal meaning of the name
"Kyongbok" given to it by a certain Chong
To-jon (1337-1398), a Confucian sage from
the early days of the Yi dynasty, is "pray for
good fortune". According to the theory of
the five elements, the southern gate of the
royal residence faced "the earth and the
centre". It was from this point that the sov¬
ereign's authority extended in all direc¬
tions to the furthest corners of the country.
anniversary
The twelve animals of the
Chinese zodiac, left, keep
watch on the stone
balustrades of the staircase
leading to the Kyongbok
palace throne room.
Below, detail of the palace
roof. Bottom, Kyongchon
pagoda (134S), a ten-storey-
high edifice of carved marble.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
global view...
Human development:
a question of security
I "We need another profound
I transition in thinking from
nuclear security to human secu¬
rity". In these terms the Human
Development Report 1994, pub¬
lished by the United Nations Devel¬
opment Programme (UNDP), pro¬
poses a new approach to world
affairs in which security and terri¬
torial integrity are no longer
regarded as synonymous, and
people rather than national borders
have to be protected. It is true that
the nuclear threat continues to exist,
but the risk of a global catastrophe
is a thing of the past. By contrast,
unemployment, famine, disease,
the deterioration of the environ¬
ment and rising crime rates are
widespread problems against which
weapons are of no avail.
Security is based on
development, not weapons
Over the past twenty years, the
number ofjobs created in the indus¬
trial countries has increased at only
half the rate of growth in Gross
Domestic Product (GDP). In 1993,
more than 35 million people were
4*
The health of indigenous peoples
IDSMT, the Institute for the Development of Health
Amenities in the Tropics, has recently been created in
Marseilles (France). Its aim is to safeguard the health of
indigenous peoples living in isolated communities in
the world's tropical regions. The Institute's multidisci-
plinary staff has called upon Survival International, a non¬
governmental organization which has been defending the
rights of indigenous peoples all over the world for the past
25 years, to help it set up health training facilities that
will enable the communities themselves to cope with their
health problems. The first target group will be the
Yanomami who live in Neblina National Park (Brazil),
where recent incursions by gold prospectors have given
rise to outbreaks of infectious intestinal and respiratory
diseases. H
IDSMT, Hôpital Houphouët-Boigny, 416 chemin de la
Madrague-Ville, 13005 Marseilles (France).
seeking work, a high proportion of
them women. Young people con¬
tinue to be haunted by the spectre of
unemployment, which is often
bound up with their ethnic origins.
In the developing countries, more
than 10 per cent of the active pop¬
ulation are jobless. Insecurity of
employment goes hand-in-hand
with insecurity of incomes, which
are eroded by inflation rates as high
as 1,500 per cent. In short, one-fifth
of the world's population, the bulk
of them living in the industrial
countries, monopolize more than
four-fifths of the world's income
and virtually all promise of devel¬
opment.
What is more, although the
overall availability of food in the
world is no problem, some 800 mil¬
lion people suffer from malnutri¬
tion. This is compounded by enor¬
mous disparities in health standards
between rich and poor: the indus¬
trial countries have one doctor for
every 400 people, but the devel¬
oping countries, where infectious
and parasitic diseases kill 17 mil¬
lion people every year, have only
one doctor for every 7,000 people,
and this figure falls to as low as one
doctor for every 36,000 in sub¬
sanaran Africa.
Harvesting the peace
dividend
The military statistics are equally
alarming. With the sharp increase in
conflicts within individual coun¬
tries, some 90 per cent ofwar casu-
alities are now civilians, whereas at
the beginning of the century 90
per cent of them were military
personnel.
In spite of significant cutbacks,
military expenditure all over the
world is still equivalent to the com¬
bined earnings of almost half the
population. If the resulting savings
are to be put to good use, they must
not be allowed to become swal¬
lowed up in the overall mass of
expenditure and debt. The Human
Development Report underscores
the need to invest all of them in
human development. If all coun¬
tries were to agree to cut back their
military expenditure by 3 per cent
per year between 1995 and the year
2000, the peace dividend could be
$460 million.
What can be done?
"It is justice not charity that is
wanting in the world," wrote the
English novelist Mary Woll-
stonecraft as long ago as 1792. Two
centuries later, we are still faced
with the same anomaly, in that aid
Mothers international
Every Thursday since April 1977, a
group of Argentinian mothers, their
heads draped in white headscarves,
have paraded round the Plaza de
Mayo in Buenos Aires, demanding to
be told the truth about the fate of
their children who disappeared during
the military dictatorship between
1976 and 1983. Having become the
symbol of a non-violent struggle for
the sanctity of life, they were
awarded the Sakharov Prize recog¬
nizing the freedom of the human
spirit by the European Parliament in
1992. They have now decided to
give their movement a broader inter¬
national basis. On their initiative, 30
mothers from different countries,
including Brazil, the former
Yugoslavia, Ukraine and Italy met in
Paris in March to exchange experi¬
ences and join forces in denouncing
the oppression to which their children
fell victim and combating such evils
as drug abuse, nuclear pollution and
organized crime.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
globa \üew
All for one against
drug abuse
"Drug abuse is a worldwide threat
that must be tackled in a spirit of
solidarity on an international scale,"
said United Nations Secretary-Gen¬
eral Boutros Boutros-Ghali before
the Organization's General
Assembly in October 1993. Fol¬
lowing the adoption of the 1988
Vienna Convention against Illicit
Traffic and the 1990 Global Pro¬
gramme of Action, in 1991 the inter¬
national community created an
effective weapon in the form of the
United Nations International Drug
Control Programme (UNDCP). This
Programme has attacked the
problem on all fronts and, in partic¬
ular, has started to mobilize the
non-governmental organizations
(NGOs) active in this area. The
World Forum due to be held under its
auspices in Bangkok (Thailand) from
12 to 16 December this year will lay
stress on the NGOs' role in curbing
drug demand.
UNDCP, B.P. 500, A-1400 Vienna
(Austria).
is all too often tied to circumstances.
There can be no doubt that the aid
made available in cases of the
utmost urgency is essential, but it
cannot provide a lasting solution.
The industrial countries commit,
on average, 15 per cent of their Gross
National Product (GNP) to social
security as against 0.3 per cent to
foreign aid. The disproportion is
even more dispiriting when it is real¬
ized that the 15 per cent is spent on
about 100 million people, while the
0.3 per cent is supposed to help
almost 1,300 million people. Another
paradox lies in the fact that, until
1986, the bilateral donors of the
industrial countries gave, on average,
five times as much assistance per
capita to high military spenders as
they gave to lowmilitary spenders. In
addition, after 40 years' foreign aid,
90 per cent of the $1,200 million
spent on technical assistance each
year continues to be used to finance
the services of foreign experts,
whereas the beneficiary countries
Learning to be
tolerant
The United Nations Year for Toler¬
ance in 1995 will coincide with the
fiftieth anniversary of the United
Nations. With this in mind, the
Director-General of Unesco, Mr. Fed¬
erico Mayor, has launched a solemn
appeal to public figures, families
and the media to encourage chil¬
dren and adolescents to show tol¬
erance towards others and reject
violence as a means of resolving
conflicts. This appeal was echoed by
the World Conference on Human
Rights held in Vienna in June 1993,
which underscored the importance
of education for peace, tolerance
and international understanding.
This is the theme chosen for this
month's session of the International
Conference on Education in Geneva,
which will be attended by Ministers
of Education from all over the world.
Further information about the Con¬
ference may be obtained from
Unesco-IBE, case postale 199, 1211
Geneva 20 (Switzerland).
Danger:
landmines!
In 62 countries all over the world,
some 100 million landmines are
waiting to explode at any time. In
Cambodia alone, there are more
mines in the ground than there are
people in the country. Since 1975,
anti-personnel mines are thought
to have caused one million victims,
most of them civilians and above all
children, who often take them for
toys. Mines are cheap but lethally
effective weapons which have in
recent times come to be used on a
massive scale and may remain dan¬
gerous even after hostilities have
ended. Some continue to be active
for as long as 40 years! Existing
international instruments have so far
proved inadequate for combating
this hazard, and so the 1980 Inter¬
national Convention on Prohibitions
or Restrictions on the Use of Certain
Conventional Weapons is to be
revised at a Conference scheduled
to be held in Geneva in 1995. In
addition, a worldwide campaign
aimed at outlawing the production,
sale and use of anti-personnel mines
has been launched by Handicap
International, a French NGO, with
the backing of the International
Committee of the Red Cross and
UNICEF.
Handicap International, 14 avenue
Berthelot, 69361 Lyon Cedex 07,
France.
now have their own national experts
in many areas.
Without detracting from the
cases where foreign aid has proved
successful, such as in increasing food
production, building infrastructural
facilities, eradicating smallpox or
promoting family planning, it is still
necessary to completely recast the
structure of international co-o
tion, strike a proper balance W
furnishing emergency a.
technical assistance and se»Wp~socii
security systems all over the world. In
short, action has to be take
upstream rather than picking up th'
pieces downstream.
particularly promising. The prin¬
ciple behind it is quite straightfor¬
ward. At the present time, the devel¬
oping countries devote, on average,
13 per cent of their budgets to human
development priorities. Their goal
should be 20 per cent, representing
$88 billion a year, which is not
beyond their capabilities. Likewise,
now that the cold war is over, the
donor countries are in a position to
ncrease their aid for human devel-
Among the strategies put forward
in the UNDP Report, the worldwide
"20-20"-type compact appears to be
opment from 7 per cent to 20 per
cent, from $4 billion to $20 billion.
If such a compact were based
on shared responsibility and were
ie placed under international man¬
agement, it would be possible for
all countries to achieve their key
objectives between now and the
end of the century. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
R H
Haiku by Bashô
/Ç.fr^y^*"-'
"A League ofNations presupposes a league of
minds," saidPaul Valéry in 1932. In line
with this approach, the International
Institute ofIntellectual Co-operation
published between 1925 and 1946 several
series ofbooks on economics, social issues,
education, art, literature and other themes.
The Japanese series published in 1936
featured an anthology ofpoems by Matsuo
Bashô (1644-1694), the great haiku poet,
with illustrations by his compatriotFujita
Tsuguhara, a painter better known as
Léonard Foujita (1 886-1 968), who lived in
France. Below arefourofthe haiku, with the
commentaries and paintings that
accompanied them.
Octopus traps: how soon
they are to have an end these
dreams
beneath the summer moon.
Under the bright moon
I walked round and round
The lake-
All night long.
44
'Japanesefishermen caughtoctopus using traps
thrown into the sea. Thefate ofall creatures is
equally ephemeral and the dream of poor
humanitydoes not last much longer than thatof
the condemned beast. This is a traditional Bud¬
dhist idea that life is but the evanescentdream of
an instant. . . . For those who understand it, this
haiku not only evokes a picturesque image, it is
full ofintense and profound emotion.
" All night long Bashô admired the moon in
the sky or in the water's deep round mirror. He
could not make up his mind to sleep.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
English translations by Harold G. Henderson
(1 and 2, opposite page), an Introduction to
Haiku, An Anthology ofPoems and Poets from
Bashô to Shiki (Doubleday, New York, 1958)
and by Noby Yuasa (3 and 4, below), Bashô, The
NarrowRoad to the Deep North and other travel
sketches.
Wake up! Wake up! It's I,
who want you for companion,
sleeping butterfly.
With a hat on my head
And straw sandals on my feet,
I met on the road
The end of the year.
' A simple reflection by the poet-pilgrim on the last day oftheyear.
Texts selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
Right from the beginning of the slave trade,
black people in almost every part of the New
World rose up against slavery and, whenever they
could, escaped from the slave ships or froiTi mines and
plantations. They took refuge in the impenetrable trop¬
ical forests, where they set up more or less self-gov¬
erning communities, in some cases with a highly
organized ranking structure. The runaway slaves
were called "Maroons", probably from the Spanish
cimarrón meaning "wild". These communities were
given such African-sounding names as cumbes,
mocambos, quilombos and candombes. In some
countries, such as Puerto Rico, they were also known
as palenques, from another Spanish word meaning
"stockade", since they often built fortifications to
defend themselves from attack. Some of them were
short-lived, but others survived for several centuries.
One of the most famous quilombos was that of Pal¬
mares in Brazil, between Alagoas and Recife, which
featured in Carlos Diegues' film Quilombo. The pop¬
ulation of Palmares chiefly consisted of blacks of
Bantu origin. When they were attacked by the whites,
their king, Zumbi, threw himself over a precipice
rather than surrender.
In some cases, the members of these Maroon
communities all had the same ethnic origins and,
because of their isolation from other groups, were able
to preserve musical forms going back to their Ashanti,
Yoruba or Bantu roots. These forms, which generally
evolved more slowly than in Africa, now provide us
with an idea of the kind of music that used to be
played on the continent in earlier times. In cases
where peoples of different origins lived together in the
cumbes and palenques, they produced original forms
of music specific to their particular locality.
REBEL COMMUNITIES
Four main groups of Maroons, each remarkable for its
closely-knit social structure and the strength of its cul¬
ture, have survived up to the present day. These are
the Garinagu (singular: Garifuna), also known as
Bush Negroes, who settled on the seaboard of Belize,
Honduras and Guatemala; the Djukas and Saramakas
of Suriname; the palenque of San Basilio, near Car¬
tagena in Colombia; and the Maroons of Jamaica
living in the Saint Elizabeth parish of Accompong
Town and in Cockpit Country and the Blue Mountains.
The Garinagu took refuge with the Carib Indians
of the island of Saint Vincent, intermarried with
them, learned their language and shared their way of
life. In 1797, some years after France had ceded
Saint Vincent to Britain, the British deported these
Maroons to the virtually barren islands off the coast
of Honduras, from where they made their way to the
mainland.
The Djukas and Saramakas escaped in 1633
when their Portugese Jewish planter owners hid
them in the jungle in order to avoid paying taxes. Their
ranks were swollen by fugitive slaves from the Dutch
coastal plantations.
San Basilio was founded in 1608 by slaves who
had escaped from Cartagena under the leadership of
Domingo Bioho (known by the name of "King
Benkos"). Benkos was eventually captured and
hanged, but the palenque survived.
In Jamaica the Maroon phenomenon began during
Spanish colonial rule. When Oliver Cromwell seized the
country in 1655, other slaves took advantage of the
LISTENING
The
Maroons,
musicians
of
freedom
by Isabelle Leymarie
political disorders to escape in their turn. A number
of chiefs, named Juan Lubola, Cudjoe, Johnny, Accom¬
pong, Cuffee and Quaco, took command and grouped
their followers into "nations", each with its own poli¬
tical system, language and customs.
One distinctive feature of the Maroon commu¬
nities is the overwhelming importance they attach to
spiritual things. They worship their ancestors, along
with forest and water spirits, animal deities and the
gods of the Ewe, Fon and Congo "nations", a clear
pointer to the ethnic origins of their members. Some
cults are hybrid; the W/m7(a word meaning "wind")
of Suriname pray to the divinities of both Dahomey and
Congo. The Kromanti rites of the Djukas and Sara¬
makas are intended to appease the anger of their gods
and heal the sick. The Kromanti play of the Jamaican
Maroons is used to call up the spirits of the dead
thrcugh religious dances named after the Ibo, Man¬
dinga and Kokose Mongola (Bantu) "nations".
For the uprooted Africans of the quilombos and
palenques, sometimes speaking different languages
The Maroons, runaway slaves
whose descendants still live in
a few communities scattered
round the Caribbean, have
preserved a culture in which
music and dancing are the
prime modes of expression and
are a hymn to freedom.
and with no other way of communicating among
themselves, music came to play a fundamental role.
In the Caribbean during colonial times, the rebels gave
the signal to attack the whites by beating their
drums or by blowing into conch shells (known as
"lambis" in Martinique and Guadeloupe) or cow horns
(called "abengs" in Jamaica). As intermediaries bet¬
ween humans and their ancestors or gods, the drums
are endowed with divine properties, and the dan¬
cers pay their respects to them before they start dan¬
cing or performing before them. The drums are
blessed and plied with offerings. Each god or group
of gods has its own drums and rhythms, and the
ancestors or gods whose favours are being sought
stand over the worshippers and convey messages to
them.
A FORM OF RESISTANCE
According to African custom, death gives rise to
outward expressions of joy in order to gladden the
dead person's soul, and in some cases it cuts across
the dividing-line between the sacred and the pro¬
fane. In Garinagu funeral rites, for instance, the mour¬
ners perform the punta, an ancient fertility dance
which is notable for its gyrations of the pelvis and qui¬
vering buttock movements and is also performed on
other occasions out of sheer pleasure. The Awasa,
which is sung and danced at funeral wakes among the
Maroons of French Guiana, is sometimes performed
in play-acting situations in which members of the
opposite sex are openly taunted. In such cases, it
helps to relieve tensions that would otherwise be
liable to upset the fragile balance of the community.
In black societies generally singing, dancing,
instrumental music and the words accompanying
them are all connected and are a favoured mode of
expression. The words of songs in particular are
used as a way of mocking other people and exercising
social control. Although the Maroons show respect
for their religious traditionsbecause ritual streng¬
thens the solidarity of the community and its links
with the ancestral homelandin their secular music
they attach special importance to improvisation and
innovation, which help to preserve the vitality of
their societies.
In the 1930s, for example, local orchestras in the
palenque of San Basilio adopted the Cuban rhythm
known as son, while in the 1960s the Maroons of Suri¬
name added the kaseko, a kind of calypso from the
coast, to their repertoire. In Jamaica, young Maroons
have introduced a reggae beat into their traditional
drum playing and in Belize and Honduras Maroons are
returning from the cities with a modernized version
of the punta called punta rock.
The Maroons are also well known for their graphic
art and their oral tradition and are a striking symbol
of the forces of resistance and freedom. Their survival
is under threat from the encroachment of the modern
world. Will it be possible to safeguard their music,
their songs and their paintings before they disap¬
pear forever?
ISABELLE LEYMARIE,
a Franco-American musicologist, is the author of La
Salsa et le Latin Jazz (PUF, Paris, 1993). She is
currently working on a study of black music in Latin
America and the Caribbean.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
the African
by George Darley-Doran
For eleven months a year,
Elvis Johnson-ldan lives in
London with his wife
Elizabeth and their three
children. Each December,
however, he returns to the
village ofJukwaa, his
birthplace in Ghana, where
he reigns supreme. In the
previous issue George
Darley-Doran described how
he met the young Anglo-
African chief In London and
Accra. Here he
accompanies him on his
return to Jukwaa.
I It was late morning when we reached
Jukwaa. People emerged from all the tintop
mud and brick houses and gathered excitedly
around the car as we parked in a little open space
on the other side of the main road. A man of
about fifty-five, in a T-shirt and shorts, thrust his
hand through my window and exclaimed: "You
are a 100 per cent welcome!" He introduced
himself as Elvis's brother Rutherford. We got
out of the car, smiled back at the crowd and filed
into a simple little house. This apparently served
as a kind of royal sitting room with sleeping
quarters attached to it.
We had only been in the room for a couple of
minutes before we made for the Bethel Chapel
the big, grey Methodist structure that looms in a
solemn and imposing manner over a village oth¬
erwise characterized by an atmosphere of happy
chaos. We must have made an unusual sight:
Elvis, Matthew, Christopher and myself in jacket
and tie and Liz, Eunice and Theresa in dresses. We
walked into the church from a side entrance,
with the congregation beaming at us.
The preacher, a diminutive man of about sixty,
continued his sermon in a high falsetto. Every few
moments the sermon would be interrupted by a
member of the congregation, to whom he would
nod sagely in agreement. At the front of the con¬
gregation was the choir, who in their black cloaks
and mortarboards looked as if they were about to
receive their diplomas. After a few minutes, the
preacher broke off from his sermon, came down
from the pulpit and announced in English
everyone's happiness that God had brought us
safely to Ghana and his wish that God would
inspire us all towards greater love and unity.
Then the whole congregation shouted
"Akwaaba!" (welcome) and burst into a rousing
Fanti rendition of "While Shepherds Watched
Their Flocks by Night" to the accompaniment of
bongos, maraccas and jazzy vocal harmonies.
That was followed by some more preaching,
after which everybody left the church and we
headed back to the royal sitting room.
Nana Elvis and Liz took their places on the
ceremonial U-shaped wooden stools at the head
of the room, and the rest of us sat on armchairs
and sofas around the walls. Matthew and Christo¬
pher fidgeted in their formal clothes. People
immediately began filing in to pay their respects.
They introduced themselves to me as either a
brother, sister, cousin, nephew or niece of Elvis.
I later discovered that these terms are applied to
even the most distant of relations. The main thing
was that everybody was family, and overjoyed to
see their chief and his broni (white) family. Elvis
smiled benignly and murmured his thanks to all
and sundry. Matthew leaned over and asked me,
"Why is everybody being so nice to us?"
A walking encyclopaedia of. traditional
knowledge
Seated protectively in front of Elvis was Dou¬
glas, his okyeame, the direct translation of which
is "linguist". Every Fanti chief has a linguist, who
serves as a kind of first lieutenant, communicating
with the people on behalf of the chief and acting
both as a political envoy and a personal bodyguard.
The linguist is a walking encyclopaedia of all the
traditional knowledge and information connected
to the stool under which he serves. He is also the
bearer of the akyempona, or sceptre, of his chief.
These sceptres are made of wood, stand about
two metres high and are topped by a gilded sym¬
bolic emblem. Elvis's akyempona, for example, fea¬
tures a little seated man pointing his finger at three
smaller figures an indication of his special
responsibilities for youth.
Douglas occupies a position of some impor¬
tance, and certainly looked the part that day:
short, thick-set and bullish, he was swathed in
a heavy robe of thick blue cotton (as worn, in
various colours, by all Fanti men on ceremonial
occasions). He had a gold chain around his neck,
from which dangled a gold lion pendant. Dou¬
glas is in his early thirties and will serve under
Elvis until one or the other dies. There is little
doubt that Douglas would lay down his life to
protect his chief.
The next morning, Elvis had to attend a formal
welcoming ceremony, which the rest of us
(including even Liz) were excluded from. When he 4J
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
A village party in Jukwaa.
48
GEORGE DARLEY-DORAN
is a Turkish-born Englishman
who lives in London, where he
works as a television
correspondent.
came back towards midday, he was wearing a
stripy blue robe and cap. He did not give much
away about the ceremony. All he said was that liba¬
tions had been poured and that spirits had been
invoked, which had manifested themselves
through some of the people attendant. We went to
a restaurant for lunch. Over the meal, Elvis joked
that we didn't need to worry about dinner because
he had fined someone a goat that morning. I asked
what sort of crime had been committed and he just
replied, "Oh, somebody said something they
shouldn't have in my absence."
The main event of the day
The main event of the day was a "beach party" on
the banks of the Ayensu River, which flows past
Jukwaa towards the sea. The party was orga¬
nized as a fund-raising event for the public latrine.
This happens to be the major construction pro¬
ject ofJukwaa. The site is on the outskirts of the
village, and the project will cost another 1 .5 mil¬
lion cedis (about $3,500) to complete. The village
does what it can to raise the money, while Elvis
has been approaching various charitable foun¬
dations in Britain. Until such funds are raised, and
the latrine is completed, the people ofJukwaa will
simply have to make do as they always have
done with the village dump.
The beach party was a great success. Elvis (in
his robe) and Liz (in a more demure European
outfit) sat on their ceremonial stools in the shade
of a big green awning. Surrounding them were the
senior members of Jukwaa's six leading clans.
These were accompanied by their wives, who
all wore Dutch wax-printed cotton dresses. It
was every Westerner's idea of a traditional African
durbar. Facing away from them, it was a dif¬
ferent story. Hundreds of children and adoles¬
cents danced wildly to the HiNRG disco music
blasting out from the banks of speakers on either
side of the DJ. A big crowd assembled on the
banks of the river and cheered as the little nanas
Theresa, Matthew and Christopher were pulled
through the water on an inflatable plastic dinghy.
I left the party towards evening with Ruther¬
ford, who had offered to show me around the vil¬
lage. Our first stop was at a small, four-walled
structure located to one side of the royal sitting
room. This was thepusuban or spiritual heart of
Jukwaa. Growing out of the roofless monument
was a thicket of plants and trees. These, according
to legend, had been planted by the original Idan
settlers of the village. Painted on one of the walls
of the monument was the message (in English),
"KNOW YOUR ASAFO LEADERS", under
which was a long list of names. Rutherford
explained that the asafo leaders constituted a
kind of military hierarchy. In the old days, the
asafo class had been responsible for defending the
stool lands against marauding tribes. Nowadays,
titles such as tufohene, asafo supi and asafo akyere
are only ceremonial, but they do confer an ele¬
ment ofprestige. Another wall of thepusuban was
decorated by a marvellous picture of a double-
headed flying dragon. This, Rutherford told me,
was a mythical beast relating to the legend of the
people of Jukwaa. Many generations ago, the
ancestral forebears were routed from their orig¬
inal home by the Asante. They went into exodus,
in the course of which legend has it they were
led by this mythical dragon to the present loca¬
tion of Jukwaa. The name of the village, inci¬
dentally, means "place of peace", which is what
the first Idan settler is said to have exclaimed
upon arriving at the site.
A place of peace
The legend ofJukwaa and its people is an ongoing
one. The "keeper" of the legend is the Okyeame-
hene, or state linguist. From an early age, the
Okyeamehene will have memorized and learned
how to articulate the history of his people. On the
most significant occasions, he will recite the
legend in the form of extended poems and songs.
Part of the legend is related in drum language. The
entire recitation takes an hour a day for two
weeks. The Okyeamehene of Jukwaa died in
1990 and his son is still in the process of being
groomed to take his place.
From the pusuban, Rutherford and I went
down a path that led away from the main road,
out of the village and past the school (a long,
low building at the top of a gradually sloping
football pitch). After a few minutes, we came
upon the local akpeteshie distillery. Akpeteshie is
a spirit derived from sugar cane. The distillery was
operating at full capacity, and the chief distiller
kindly agreed to give us a guided tour.
Around the distillery compound were large
piles of sugar cane, which resembles thick
bamboo. In the middle of all these piles was a
shed in which was situated an antique petrol-
driven sugar cane crusher. This made a roaring
noise as long stalks of sugar cane were fed into .
it. Juice poured out from one side and crushed
pulp from the other. The pulp is taken away
and burnt, and the juice is fermented in big
metal vats. After two weeks, the fermenting
liquid is transferred into old petrol drums. The
drums are covered with lids and log fires are lit
underneath them. There are usually about six
drums on the go. Emerging from each lid is a
metal pipe, which spirals downwards through a
vat of cool water. The alcohol condenses in this
pipe and then seeps through a cotton-wool filter,
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
from which it spurts into a plastic bottle. The
resulting akpeteshie is a clear white spirit, the
Ghanaian equivalent of Italian grappa, Cretan
raki, and Yugoslavian slivowitz.
It was dark by the time Rutherford and I left
the distillery. We got back to the village and entered
the royal sitting room, where Elvis and Liz were
holding court. Somebody brought in the goat
referred to earlier. It was presented to Elvis, who
patted it affectionately. Then the animal was led
away to be slaughtered as a ritual offering to the
spirits.
Sports day
Liz and Elvis went to Accra the next day. I spent
the morning in the village, where life was carrying
on as usual. In front of each house women were
making fufu, the staple of the Ghanaian diet,
which is prepared from plantain and cassava.
The two ingredients are boiled until soft, usually
over a charcoal fire. Then they are transferred into
a big wooden mortar and pounded for about fif¬
teen minutes with a long, thick sugar-cane pestle.
The final result is a doughy lump of fufu. This is
covered in a spicy tomato broth and eaten with
fingers out of a communal bowl. Fufu is swal¬
lowed without being chewed, like oysters.
Ghanaians of every class love fufu so much that
they will happily eat it every day of their lives. The
"thump, thump, thump" of fufu being pounded
is perhaps the archetypal sound of Ghana.
Around the women making their fufu, chil¬
dren played, chickens pecked at the dust and
goats wandered about with their kids. Children
queued up with buckets at the village water tap.
It made a peaceful little scene. Tranquil as things
were, however, one could also feel the excite¬
ment mounting for a major event that was to be
held that afternoon: the annual sports day.
After lunch I walked up to the school with
Elvis's older brother, Payne, who is an architect.
There was already a big crowd by the time we got
there, virtually the entire population ofJukwaa.
The normally featureless schoolyard had been
turned into a spectators' gallery. Beneath the
green awning, the men of consequence sat with
their wives. All of them were in their best robes
and dresses. Payne and I sat down, he on a stool
and myself in an armchair that had been carried
up especially for me.
Launching the afternoon off was the under-
10s' football. One of the teams was called the
Christian Babies. They had black uniforms, with
a white skull and crossbones on the chest. The
other team was called the Idan Stars. There was
laughter and applause from the audience as the
little boys battled it out. The Christian Babies
came out on top.
Next was a game played by the teenage girls.
This is a little difficult to describe. There are sev¬
eral teams of about fifteen girls each. They all
form a big ring. Girls hop into the ring two at a
time, from opposite sides, making a kicking
motion as they hop. The first girl to make such a
motion "kicks" the other one out, although they
never actually touch. The girls compete with one
another until there is one clear victor and her
team wins the game. As the game progressed,
Village elders with teams
before a football game.
the girls displayed a competitive spirit that can
only be described as intense. Upon their victory,
the winning team let out an enormous cheer and
then trooped in formation around the chiefs'
enclosure, chanting all the while.
The high point of the afternoon was the
men's football. This pitted the born and bred
Jukwaa men against those who had come to
live in the village from other parts. Prior to the
game, the two teams lined up in the centre of the
field to be given a speech by Nana Kwesi Ansa,
a frail but dignified elder in a colourful che¬
quered robe. He called upon them to play fairly
and honourably. Then he sat down and the game
kicked off. Regrettably the result was a foregone
conclusion. The visiting residents were tougher,
almost to a man. Jukwaa's finest played hard
but were just not up to the competition. The
game was considerably livened by the occa¬
sional invasion of the pitch first by a flock of
chickens, then by a herd of goats and finally by
a long green snake. Douglas went to work on the
snake with his big stick and then picked it up and
waved it at the crowd, to the horrified shrieks of
all the females. Despite all the mishaps, it was a
fine match and the final score was only 1 -0 to the
visitors.
Once all the games were over, the prize-
giving took place. The Christian Babies were
presented with a bunch of plastic flowers, the
winning girls' team with a silver plaque and the
visiting men with a silver trophy. As he pre¬
sented the trophy, Nana Kwesi congratulated the
visitors warmly and called upon the home team
to bear no hard feelings and to play better next
year. Then everybody dispersed and gradually
trailed back to the village.
Payne and I returned to the royal sitting room
and rested for a while. We were going to need
plenty of energy for the funeral rite that was to be
held later that evening.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
SO
M SPEAKING OUT AGAINST NUCLEAR
FUNDAMENTALISM
Your October 1993 issue ("Time to Disarm")
is easy to read and contains some stimu¬
lating contributions. In particular Jasjit Singh
in his article raises questions which rarely
get asked, concerning what he rightly calls
"nuclear fundamentalism".
The glossary which comes as part of his
section, but which may not be his, is not
quite accurate about the Non Proliferation
Treaty. As Article VI of that Treaty makes
clear, it is also a nuclear disarmament treaty.
That is the obligation on the nuclear signa¬
tories, and it balances the obligations placed
on non-nuclear powers.
Why is it that in such a good issue you
neither use nor refer to the Non-Govern¬
mental Organizations and their campaigns
for disarmament? Those who have written for
you are either official or semi-official people.
Nothingwrongwith such status. But there are
many many others actively and intelligently
working for change who might have con¬
tributed.
Bruce Kent
Past President,
International Peace Bureau,
London, United Kingdom
AN EXCEPTIONAL DEBATE
Your December 1993 issue ("The Meaning
of Progress, A North-South Debate") made
excellent reading. I have been a subscriber to
the Unesco Courier for several years, and
although I appreciate all your articles for
their honesty, erudition and broadness of
scope, one or two issues a year are out¬
standing. However fascinating cultural dif¬
ferences and disparities may be, I prefer to
read about the ideals and values ofuniversal
humanism that draw people closer together
and prove the essential unity of human
beings.
Lucette Perrin
Decazeville, France
m GANDHI AND RESPECT FOR OTHERS
I was extremely moved by Richard Atten-
borough's film about Gandhi when I saw it
again on French television last April. What
wisdom, what intelligence, what rectitude
and what humility! It is wonderful to see that
such qualities exist, but what a challenge it is
to cultivate them in oneself!
Drawing inspiration from Gandhi's wise
words, I should like to remind the world of
the fraternal bonds constituted by our
common flesh and our common origin and
by the fate we all share on this little plot of
earth sailing through the cosmos.
Why then should there be there so many
wars and so much hatred and intolerance
towards all that is different, when these very
differences are the source of our originality
and our wealth? A love of differences, though
so often conspicuous for its absence, is the
necessary fertilizer in the compost ofhumanity
that can enable all races, all opinions, all cul¬
tures and all religions to express, develop and
make known their unique features.
Why do the world's political and religious
leaders, scientists, philosophers and thinkers
not follow Gandhi's example and take action,
creating national and international institu¬
tions and passing laws to ensure that all cit¬
izens of the world, in all places and in all cir¬
cumstances, can live in peace and harmony
in respect for the rights and freedoms of
others, as stipulated in the 1948 Universal
Declaration of Human Rights?
For how much longer shall we allow our¬
selves to be led by self-centredness and
money rather than by our minds and our
consciences?
Alfred Schanzenbacher
Metz, France
Q ANOTHER FORM OF ENERGY?
In the article entitled "Energy for a Sustain¬
able World" in your November 1991 issue
("Environment and Development, A Global
Commitment") you cite numerous ways of
using the energy sources that our planet pos¬
sesses in abundance, i.e. water, wind, solar,
geothermal, photovoltaic cells, etc. But what
about snow, ice and névé?
If you hike through high mountains, you
have to use special creams and oils to protect
your skin from being burned not only by the
sun but by its reflection off the snow. There
are many névé glaciers around the world.
Many ice-fields were formed in the ice ages
that are far from having melted. Would it not
be possible to exploit this energy source,
which is located in areas that, for obvious
reasons, are uninhabited?
Claudia Merazzi
Bienne, Switzerland
UNESCO ACTION IN BIOTECHNOLOGY
I should like to add the following precisions
to the box on "Unesco's International Net¬
work ofMicrobial Resources Centres" which
appeared on page 21 ofyour June issue ("The
Resourceful Gene").
In 1991 Unesco launched, with the
Biotechnology Action Council (BAC), chaired
by Prof. I.K. Vasil (U.SA.), a scheme for short-
term fellowships in plant, aquatic and allied
environmental biotechnologies which was
complemented by a Unesco professorship
scheme in all fields of biotechnology. So far
130 Unesco BAC fellowships have been
awarded (50 to women and 80 to men) to: 20
applicants from Africa, 43 from Asia, 9 from
the Arab states, 34 from eastern and southern
Europe and 24 from Latin America and the
Caribbean. Six eminent scientists from the
U.K., Sweden, Australia, Lebanon and
Switzerland have been sent as Unesco
biotechnology professors to Brazil, Malaysia,
Thailand, Viet Nam and Jordan. Unesco
chairs in plant biotechnology have been
established at the University of Beijing
(China) and Makerere University (Uganda).
Edgar DaSilva
Division of Basic Sciences,
Unesco
HUMAN RIGHTS AND THE SHARI'AH
In your March 1994 issue ("Human Rights,
The Unfinished Task") I read with close atten¬
tion the Vienna Declaration and Programme
of Action adopted on 25 June 1993 by the
World Conference on Human Rights, as well
as the Tunis, San José, Bangkok and Cairo
Declarations that preceded it.
All these documents expressly or implic¬
itly recognize that human rights are "uni¬
versal, indivisible, interdependent and inter¬
related". However, I find the Cairo Declaration
disturbing in that it specifies that human
rights are subject to the provisions of the
Shari'ah, the Holy Law of Islam. As soon as a
conflict arises between human rights and
the rules of the Shari'ah, the latter will take
precedence over the former, which will thus
be ignored.
André Hamy
Bois-Grenier, France
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, pages 3, 12: Michael Lange/Visum ©
Cosmos, Paris. Page 2: © Anne Yanoushka de
Lamater, Vancouver. Pages 5, 7: J. Benaroch ©
Sipa Press, Paris. Pages 8-9, 1 0: Steve Murez ©
Rapho, Paris. Pages 9, 1 1 (right), 1 3 (above),
IS, 17 (right), 19 (above), 21, 23 (above), 25
(above), 27: Clive Freeman/SPL © Cosmos,
Paris. Pages 1 1 (left), 18, 19 (below), 35, 36
(above): © Claude Sauvageot, Paris. Pages 1 4-
1 5: Time Graphic by Nigel Holmes. Research by
Leslie Dickstein. Source: Dr. Victor H. McKusick,
Johns Hopkins University © 1994 Time Inc. Dist.
by LA. Times Syndicate Intl. Page 1 6 (above):
MacCoy/BSNY © Rapho, Paris. Page 16
(below): Omikron/SPL © Cosmos, Paris. Page
17 (left): © Hamid, Martinique. Page 20: C.
Duys © VLOO, Superstock, Paris. Page 22:
Peter Willi © Explorer, Paris. Page 23 (below):
Geoff Tompkinson Aspect Picture Library ©
Cosmos, Paris. Page 25 (below): St. Mark's
Museum, Florence © L'Arche de la Fraternité, La
Vie en Kit, Paris-la Défense. Page 29: Unesco-
Ines Forbes. Page 30: Marcello Bertinetti ©
Rapho, Paris. Page 3 1 : Jacob Sutton © Gamma,
Paris. Page 32: D. Chalmers © Miss
International, Paris. Page 33: © Jean-Loup
Charmet, Bibliothèque des Arts Décoratifs, Paris.
Page 34: Maria Issaris © Gamma, Paris. Page 36
(below): Marco © Ask Images, Paris. Page 37:
Guy Thouvenin © Explorer, Paris. Page 38:
Geier © Greenpeace, London. Page 39: © Jean-
Loup Charmet, Archives of the Ministry of
Foreign Afffairs, Paris. Pages 40-41, 41 (right):
J.-R Nacivet © Explorer, Paris. Page 40 (below):
G. Boutin © Explorer, Paris. Page 41 (below): A
Reffet © Explorer, Paris. Pages 44, 45: All Rights
Reserved. Pages 47, 48, 49: © G. Darley
Doran, London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
THEME
OF
THE NEXT ISSUE
(OCTOBER 1004):
SLAVERY
ALSO FEATURING AN
INTERVIEW WITH
ISRAELI POET
PROJET 239
SOCIETE
CHERCHE FAMILLE
Un dossier complet sur les relations
entre famille et société
128 pages - 65 F - Etranger 70 F
Abonnement (4 n°s/an) : 230 F - Etranger : 260 F
Pour recevoir ces numéros ou vous abonner, envoyez vos nom,
adresse et règlement à : Assas Editions
14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS - Tél. : 11] 44 39 48 48
ETVDES
Questions d'éthique
(à paraître)
Réflexions sur la foi en Dieu
Antoine Fournel
Au centre de la morale, la conscience
Jean-Yves Calvez
Le numéro : 55 F - Etranger : 62 F
Abonnement (11 nos/an) : 460 F - Etranger : 560 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
The
encounters with other ways of life
t t
swrçjnswgstrangers
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine
published in 22 languages and read by hundreds of thousands of
people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms,,, without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
EACH MONTH, ESSENTIAL READING FOR AN UNDERSTANDING OF THE PROBLEMS
OF TODAY AND TOMORROW
RHYTHM, GESTURE AND THE SACRED.., TIME TO DISARM.., THE STORY OF NUMBERS... A NORTH-SOUTH
DEBATE: THE MEANING OF PROGRESS... DESERTS... WORLDS WITHIN WORDS... HUMAN RIGHTS, THE
UNFINISHED TASK... MODERN MANAGEMENT AND LOCAL TRADITIONS... A NEW LOOK AT THE HISTORY OF
COMMUNISM... BIOTECHNOLOGY: THE RESOURCEFUL GENE... SURPRISING STRANGERS... A CODE FOR LIVING
THE ETHICS OF HUMAN ENGINEERING...
CHANA, TRINIDAD,
CHINA, SENEGAL,
SIBERIA. MEXICO...
PAVEL LOUNGUINE,
ALEKSANDAR PETROVIC
FACES OF TIBET
INTERVIEW WITH
mi MNOse
ENVIRONMENT
CCRAL- TAKMC THE
PHSE OF THE PUUKT
HERITAGE
I ^LETTER FROH
«¡A
UNESCO AC
FRANCOIS MITTERRAND... JORGE AMADO... RICHARD ATTENBOROUGH... JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE... JEAN
LACOUTURE... FEDERICO MAYOR... NAGUIB HAHFOUZ... SENBENE OVSMANE... ANDREI VOZNESENSKY...
FREDERIC ROSSIF... HINNERK BRUHNS... CAMILO JOSÉ CELA... VACLAV HAVEL... SERGEI S. AVERINTSEV...
ERNESTO SÂBATO... GRO HARLEM BRUNDTLAND... CLAUDE LÉVI-STRAUSS... LEOPOLDO ZEA... PAULO FREIRÉ...
DANIEL J. BOORSTIN... FRANCOIS JACOB... MANU DIBANGO... FAROUK HOSNY... SADRUDDIN AGA KHAN...
JORGE LAVEUI... LÉON SCHWARTZENBERG... TAHAR BEN JELLOUN... GABRIEL GARCIA MAROUEZ... JACQUES-
YVES COUSTEAU... MELINA MERCOURI... CARLOS FUENTES... JOSEPH KI-ZERBO... VANDANA SHIVA... WILLIAM
STYRON... OSCAR NIEMEYER... NIKIS THEODORAKIS... ATAHUALPA YUPANQUI... HERVÉ BOURGES... ABDEL
RAHMAN EL BACHA... SUSANA RINALDI... HUBERT REEVES... JOSÉ CARRERAS... A LETTER FRON FREUD TO
EINSTEIN... LUC FERRY... CHARLES MALAMOUD... UMBERTO ECO... OUVER STONE... ANDRÉ BRINK... JANES D.
WATSON... ANOS OZ... MICHEL SERRES.,. THÉODORE HONOD... YVES COPPENS... EDOUARD J. HAUNICK...
JEAN MALAURIE ... TRINH XUAN THUAN... ANTONI TAPIES... JOSÉ DONOSO... NOËLLE LENOIR...
]]>
</page>
</document>
