<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="098936eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
THE SUN
ANCIENT MYTHS
NEW TECHNOLOGIES
-.$**>
-V
I ' *i
\<
*tte&
* T
%
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
'UNITED NATIONS YEAR FOR TOLERANCE'
Voltaire
Prayer to God
I now turn from men to address my words to Thee, God of all
beings, of all worlds and of all time: if it is permitted to feeble crea¬
tures lost in the vastness and imperceptible to the rest of the uni¬
verse, to dare to ask anything ofThee, who hast given all and whose
decrees are unchanging and eternal, condescend to look with pity
on the errors inseparable from our nature; let not these errors be
our undoing. Thou didst not give us hearts to hate and hands to cut
each other's throats; grant that we may help each other to bear the
burden of a painful and fleeting life; that the little difference
between the clothes which cover our poor bodies, between all our
different and inadequate forms of speech, between all our ridicu¬
lous customs and imperfect laws, between all our senseless opin¬
ions and our estates, so disproportionately different in our eyes
and so alike to Thee; grant that all these little nuances that distin¬
guish the atoms known as men from each other may not be signals
for hatred and persecution; that those who light candles at midday
to worship Thee may tolerate those who make do with the light of
Thy sun; grant that those who put a white cloth over their robes to
say that men should love Thee may not hate those who say the
same thing wearing a coat of black wool; that it may be the same to
worship Thee in the jargon of an ancient tongue or of a newer; that
those whose clothes are dyed red or violet, who reign over a small
plot heaped from the mud of this earth and own a few rounded
fragments of a particular metal may enjoy without pride what they
call grandeur and riches, and that others may see them without
envy; for Thou knowest that there is in these trifles nothing for envy
or for pride.
Let all men remember that they are brothers, let them hold in
abomination the tyranny exercised over souls, no less than the
brigandage which forcibly robs labour and peaceful industry of
their fruits! If the horrors of war are inevitable, at least let us not
hate each other, let us not torment each other in time of peace, and
let us use our moment of existence to bless, in a thousand different
tongues from Siam to California, Thy bounty which has accorded
that moment to us.
Treatise on Tolerance (1763)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
JANUARY 1995
Cover:
Montage of a photo of the sun
above a sand dune and, inset, an
8th-century Indian miniature, The
Heart ofSurya, depicting the sun
god Vishnu and his wife Lakshmi.
THE SUN
undent myths
new technologies
I Interview with Montserrat Caballé
36 HERITAGE
The Pantheon, Rome's other symbol
by Cécile Duvelle and Mauro Rosi
41 GREENWATCH
Solving the food/population equation
by Lester Brown
40 LISTENING
Mambo mania
by Isabelle Leymarie
45 GLOBAL VIEW
The Unesco Prize for the Promotion of the Arts
46 UNESCO IN ACTION
Newsbriefs...
47 ARCHIVES
Men of little faith
byJohan Bojer
48 ANNIVERSARY
Louis Pasteur
Scientist and humanist
by Louise L. Lambrichs
50 Letters to the Editor
Our middle-aged neighbouring star
by Pierre Lantos
11 Myths with the sun in them
by Philippe Borgeaud
A light that shines through time
and cultures
by Madanjeet Singh
Zoroastrianism and the cult of fire
by Mahin Tadjadod
Manolo plugs into the sun
by Christopher Flavin and Nicholas Lenssen
India's self-help solar villages
by Sanjit Bunker Roy
31 The World Solar Summit
interview with Boris Berkovsky
The new library of Alexandria
'Alexandrina nova': a star is born
33 Fact file
Consultant: Juliette Boussand
Commentary by Federico Mayor
TB& UNESCO
Courier
48th year
Published monthly in 30
languages and in braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, I i NOVEMBER I94S
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THÉ. UNESCO
Courier
48th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin. 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda EI Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca. Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (45.68.46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46,87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Te!. 45.68.47. 1 5),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Cameras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard j. Shuma (Dar-es-Saiaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Sen in Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard. Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tei. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45,68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel 45.68.45.65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: I year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Couner", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompa¬
nied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Couner. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by UNESCO or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced
in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (I) UNESCO, 7 Place de
Fontenoy. 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100 U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edison. Indian Head Inc.,
I I I West 40th Street. New York, USA; (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.SA
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI -JANVIER 1995
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de 1'Unesco.
Impression: ¡MPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL. 2, rue Chnstophe-Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 0041-5278 N: I-I995-OPI-94-533A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 2-3 and 50-5 i .
onth by month
This year, which the United Nations has proclaimed "Year for Tolerance",
promises to have a full programme of international events: the centenary
of motion pictures and radio; the fiftieth anniversary of the foundation of the
United Nations and the adoption of Unesco's Constitution (Unesco did not
actually become fully operational until the following year); two international
summit meetingsthe first, in March, on social development, the second,
in September, on the situation of women.
As everyone knows, there is a world of difference between the gilded
surroundings in which such events take place and the tragic situation in
which hundreds of millions of people are afflicted with hunger, endemic dis¬
eases and illiteracy, and tens of thousands are killed, uprooted or traumatized
by war, ethnic and religious conflicts, and outbursts of fanaticism. All
those who, directly or indirectly, in intergovernmental and non-govern¬
mental organizations, work on behalf of international co-operation for
peace, are constantly aware of the terrible gap between their dreams and
the reality, between their efforts and the limited effects of their action.
To the question they often hear: "What's the point?", they unhesi¬
tatingly reply, "Without these dreams and effortsdespite the mistakes,
failings and even sometimes the cowardice that tarnish themwhat would
happen? What would there be to resist the offensive of incomprehension
and violence?"
The unique and patiently woven network of shared experiences, of suc¬
cesses and failures, that we call the international community is still irre¬
placeable. This does not mean that it cannot and should not change. On the
contrary, at a time when it is celebrating its fiftieth birthday, in a world that
has been completely transformed, the United Nations must also change and
be given a new lease on life by the major powers that define the framework
of its action. It must be instilled with determination to act for the common
future of all rather than the immediate self-interest of each. And of course
it must possess the means to implement its decisions.
The coming year, with its watchword of tolerance, will thus be a
challenging one. The forthcoming international events will only make
sense if they go hand in hand with clear thinking and well targeted action.
The Unesco Courier will keep its readers informed of what is being done to
achieve these goals in the fields of culture, education, science and com¬
munication. We cordially invite you to express your opinions on these
issues via our "Letters to the Editor" page.
We hope you will agree with us that the sun is an appropriate choice
as the main theme of the first issue of the year. Central element in human
mythology, emblem of promise and new beginnings, bringer of light, warmth,
life and creation, the sun is now becoming, thanks to scientific and tech¬
nological progress, a colossal source of usable, affordable energy. It is up
to us to see that "the sun is for everyone" and that this energy is tapped
for the good of the greatest number.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
MONTSERRAT
CABALLÉ
talks to
Serafín García Ibáñez
One of the greatest singers of our time, the Spanish
soprano Montserrat Caballé has won accolades in
opera-houses all over the world. Her repertoire includes
no less than forty roles, notably in operas by Mozart,
Richard Strauss and Wagner, and in Italian romantic
opera, in which she has specialized. She has been a
Unesco Goodwill Ambassador since 1994. Here she talks
about her life and art.
Let's begin with your childhood.
It was very happy; I had wonderful par¬
ents. Despite the Civil War and the difficult
post-war period when you never knew
where the next crust of bread was coming
from, they were always happy and opti¬
mistic. It was a joy for us to make that
crust multiply, as it were, by dipping it in
water. A chunk of stale bread was turned
into a kind of copious bread soup for the
five of us.
My father and mother were always
ready to help and share with others. My
father always used to say that in this life we
all travel together down the same road.
This positive attitude on my parents' part
provided me with solid foundations, a
wonderful launching pad for life.
How did you start singing?
Thanks to my parents. They loved
music, especially classical music Spanish
music rather than opera, actually. We had
a few records and the radio. And then they
were always singing! I got a taste for music
very early on, and it grew with age.
I didn't have the money to study, but I
thought that if I could pursue an artistic
career, by singing and serving the cause of
music, then perhaps I would be able to
learn something and at the same time con¬
tribute to my family some of the physical
comforts we had lacked.
Later, when I was about eighteen or
nineteen, I forgot about the materialistic
aspects of my choice and fell deeply in
love with music. I committed myself to it
totally. It became a vocation, an absolute
passion. Not only has it brought me a great
deal of professional satisfaction, it was
through music that I met my husband,
who was also a singer.
In 1965 1 had the opportunity to make
my debut in New York as a stand-in for
Marilyn Home, who was expecting a baby.
That opened many doors for me. While
continuing to serve music, I have been able
to do what I always dreamed of doing
help the suffering, especially young
orphans.
My husband and I created a foundation
which takes in 500 or 600 children a year on
a farm at the foot of the Pyrenees. I also
give charity concerts and am delighted to
be able to contribute to UNESCO's work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A soprano's voice
is a little like a mother's
cry, which is why it attracts
all human beings.
Is it true that you nearly gave up
singing.
Yes. I had operations in 1974 and 1985
for tumours. But things couldn't have been
too bad, for here I am chatting away with
you! (Bursts into laughter)
What are the essential attributes of a
soprano voice?
Some sopranos have extraordinary range
and can cover up to three octaves, but I'm
not one of them.
A soprano's voice is a little like a
mother's cry, which is why it attracts all
human beings. The sound of a mother's
voice expresses a feeling of great intimacy,
which has a truly magical effect on the lis¬
tener. You have to sing very, very badly for
this not to happen. That's an enormous
advantage that we sopranos have to start
with. I am convinced that the sound of a
soprano's voice affects people so strongly
because it evokes maternal memories in
each of us.
In the course of your career you have
sung in all kinds of opera, from Bellini to
Verdi, from Puccini to Wagner. Wasn't that
a little risky?
Of course! But I can't imagine any
worthwhile work without an element of
risk. You've got to take all kinds of risks if
you want to grow and put the quality and
value of your work to the test. I don't
think that routine work is real work.
Which have been the most difficult
roles you've sung and which have you
enjoyed the most?
Perhaps the most difficult or at least the
most gruelling opera I've sung in is Bellini's
// Pirata.
Salomé is one of my favourite roles. I
love the character and I love what Richard
Strauss made of her. She is a product of that
rare phenomenon, a real osmosis or com¬
munion between the librettist and the com¬
poser.
The role of Isolde is also exhilarating,
but in Wagner the orchestra plays an
important part. In Tristan und Isolde the
real protagonist is the orchestra. Of course
the singers have to be good, but even if
they're not first rate, the opera still gives
pleasure because of the prominent role of
the orchestra.
I also love singing Norma, Semiramis,
La Traviata. In fact I have enjoyed singing
all the roles I have interpreted. Don't ask
me to choose! (Laughter)
When you mentioned Salomé, you
talked about an osmosis between the
libretto and the musical score. Doesn't
that always exist?
I've always let myself be carried along by
the composer's inspiration. If I feel shivers
run down my spine when I listen to the
music, even when I don't understand the
words or know the story, then I know that
the music is going to give depth to the
character even if she seems unexceptional
on a first reading. On the other hand, even
with a well constructed libretto, if the
music doesn't go with the character, then
the character won't come to life on stage.
It has been said that you have a sub¬
lime voice and are thoroughly professional
but that you are not very interested in the
acting side.
It's not that I'm not interested. It's just
that I shall never accept that dramatic con¬
siderations should spoil the performance of
the music. Opera is primarily music, which
has to be well sung and interpreted. The
dramatic aspect comes second, very impor¬
tant though it is. With a creative director
you can put on a magnificent show, but
today we're seeing too much superb visual
presentation at the expense of the music.
In an opera house with an average of
two or three thousand seats some are
even larger it is imperative for the voices
and the feelings they express to reach right
up to "the gods". In a theatre with a smaller
number of seats between 600 and 800
expressions and gestures and the emotional
charge they carry can be seen by everyone.
To reach the most distant members of the
audience and make them tingle, you must
have voice, expression and feeling.
The great singers learn their parts by
heart in languages that are often not their
own. Was that ever a problem for you?
Not for German. I began in Germany
and lived there for six years. I speak and
write the language fluently. Russian, on
the other hand, and English have given me
trouble. And as for French, I must admit
that I don't pronounce it very well. Let's
say that I've got a strong Perpignan accent.
(Laughter)
What happens if you forget your lines
on stage, right in the middle of a phrase?
Oh boy! That's happened to me several
times, and I'm sure I'm not the only one.
When it does happen, the only thing to
do is follow the music until you can pick up
the thread again. If you suddenly dry up,
SELECTIVE DISCOGRAPHY
Brahms: A German Requiem, Sherrill Milnes,
Montserrat Caballé, Boston Symphony
Orchestra conducted by Erich Leinsdorf
Bellini: Norma, Montserrat Caballé, Plácido
Domingo, Florenza Cossotto, Rugglero
Ralmondi, London Philharmonic Orchestra
conducted by Carlo-Felice Cillario
Donizetti: Lucrezia Borgia, Montserrat Caballé,
Shirley Verret, Alfredo Kraus, RCA Italiana
Orchestra conducted by Jonel Perlea
Puccini: La Bohème, Montserrat Caballé,
Placido Domingo, Rugglero Raimondi, Sherrill
Milnes, London Philharmonic Orchestra
conducted by Sir Georg Solti.
Richard Strauss: Salomé, Montserrat Caballé,
Sherrill Milnes, Richard Lewis, London
Symphony Orchestra conducted by Erich
Leinsdorf
Verdi: La Traviata, Montserrat Caballé, Carlo
Bergonzi, Sherrill Milnes, RCA Italiana
Orchestra conducted by Georges Prêtre
All these recordings are on the RCA label
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
^
jL
^m^^à
' lfp 1
Montserrat Caballé with the Director-
General of Unesco, Mr Federico Mayor,
at a ceremony to mark the singer's
appointment as a Unesco Goodwill
Ambassador (22 April 1994).
you hang on to the last word you've sung
and hope that you will be able to carry on
where you left off.
What about the type of Spanish
operetta known as zarzuela?
I think it is a superb musical form and
very much a part of our heritage. I have
always tried with the modest means at my
disposal to do what I can for zarzuela
which, I seem to remember, was not always
highly thought of at the beginning of my
career. It went badly downhill during the
Spanish Civil War in spite of the first-rate
companies that managed to keep the tra¬
dition alive, that run by Plácido Domingo's
parents, for example.
But things are better nowadays thanks
to Tamayo and his company and the great
conductor Ataúlfo Argenta, who is fairly
and squarely in the zarzuela tradition.
Singers like Plácido Domingo, Teresa
Berganza, Pilar Lorengar and many others
have done a lot to bring about this revival.
I personally am very proud of the Paris
Grand Prix I received for a recording of a
zarzuela recital.
Can bel canto be practised in the open
air?
It is a good thing that music is being
performed in the open air today. It attracts
a wider audience than the traditional opera-
going public. But I think the open air is
more suited to recitals of popular pieces,
including bel canto arias.
Our music must not be confined to the
elite of some 30,000 or 50,000 people who
can afford opera seats; the hundreds of
thousands of people who show up at big
open-air concerts also have the right to
hear it. But a recital is better because the
visual element that is an essential part of
opera does not work on a vast stage.
In the same context, what advice would
you give to a music-lover? To attend a live
but perhaps mediocre performance or listen
to a perfect recording?
It all depends on what you want. If it's
perfection you're after, you'd do better
with the recording, but to experience
musical intensity, you need to be there in
your seat. Recording techniques are now so
perfect that recordings constitute archives
that people can consult at home whenever
they want. For myself, I like recordings as
a reference, but for intensity of feeling I
prefer a live performance. One's response
is not at all the same. I say that as someone
who sings, records and is never happy with
the result. (A long peal of laughter).
People say there's a crisis in opera.
Not as far as the public is concerned.
The number of opera-goers and the sales of
recordings prove that there are more fans
today than there were twenty years ago.
There are far more music-lovers now.
I would be more inclined to think that
there is a social crisis. The theatre is going
through a crisis because neither private
benefactors nor governments have the
resources to subsidize culture as they did
thirty years ago. There are other, more
urgent needs. So opera seasons get shorter;
only two or three new productions are
staged instead of fifteen or twenty. Only
ten or a dozen operas are presented each
year, whereas twice as many were put on
twenty years ago.
Is there a lack of new talent?
Absolutely not! The present generation
of young singers is outstanding. But to
make a name for yourself you've got to
appear four or five times in the same place-
and come back year after year before
people start to talk about you.
One last question. What are your inter¬
ests outside music?
I'd like to see all human beings, in dif¬
ferent countries and within each country,
draw closer together and understand each
other better. I'd like to see the North and
the South stop regarding each other
uncomprehendingly and try to understand
that what seems a defect in some may be a
quality in others.
Tolerance, in other words?
"Tolerance" is the word. But unfortunately
it often sounds like an impossible dream.
SERAFÍN GARCIA IBÂREZ is a journalist with
Unesco's Office of Public Information.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Our middle-aged neighbouring star
by Pierre Lantos
8
An X-ray image of the sun
taken by satellite showing the
activity of the corona, the outer
layer of the solar atmosphere.
The corona is formed by gas at
very low density but an
extremely high temperature
(1 to 5 million degrees Kelvin).
The brightest areas are active
regions where sunspots would
be seen in visible light. The
darkest regions are coronal
holes from which a stream of
charged particles is ejected
into space.
PIERRE LANTOS,
of France, is a research director
at his country's National Centre
for Scientific Research (CNRS)
and an astronomer at the Paris-
Meudon observatory. He is the
author of Le So/e/7 (Paris, 1994).
Once upon a time there was a vast empty
space within our galaxy, nearer to the
edge than the centre. We should probably never
have known anything about it had it not become
the birthplace of a star our sun. For the space
was not entirely empty; it c'ontained an enor¬
mous cloud of hydrogen molecules and par¬
ticles of dust. This cloud became unstable, then
collapsed and broke up into smaller and smaller
clouds. Our sun and its planets were born of one
of these tiny clouds.
When such a cloud collapses under the effect
of its own weight, a lot of energy is released, and
the surrounding temperature at first only a
few dozen absolute degrees rises and eventu¬
ally reaches several thousand degrees. Contrac
tion comes to an end when the star's core tem¬
perature reaches a million degrees and nuclear
reactions begin. Tens of millions of years elapse
between the time when the hydrogen cloud
begins to destabilize and the birth of the adult
star. This is a very brief youth for a star like the
sun whose life will last for ten thousand million
years or more.
A nuclear furnace
When they tried to explain the origin of solar
energy, nineteenth-century astronomers
advanced three hypotheses: that it was due either
to chemical reactions, to the contraction of the
star or to meteorites falling into the sun. By the
end of the century the most lucid of them had
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The sun is actually a middle-agedstar, But even though halfits life
is ove)) there's no causefor alarm. The heavenly body that gives
us light still has a brightfuture ahead ofit.
Right, computerized false-
colour photo of a giant cluster
of sunspots. The picture was
taken a few months before
maximum in the 11-year cycle
of solar activity.
Above right, Aurora borealis,
the northern lights,
photographed over spruce trees
near Fairbanks, Alaska (United
States). These luminous
displays appear in the night sky
at high northern latitudes when
charged subatomic particles
from the sun interact with
atoms and molecules in the
earth's upper atmosphere.
realized that none of these processes could
supply the energy the star needs over a very
long period. The great experimental and theo¬
retical discoveries made in the first half of the
twentieth century revealed that solar energy is
actually produced by nuclear fusion reactions
that convert hydrogen into helium. These reac¬
tions take place in the core of the sun where
700 million tons of hydrogen are changed into
helium each second and four million tons of
matter are transformed, as Einstein showed,
into energy.
Today several experimental methods can be
used to investigate the opaque interior of the sun.
One of them consists of studying the elementary
particles known as neutrinos that are released by
the fusion of the gas nuclei and are capable of
passing effortlessly through the whole volume
of the sun. But although the neutrinos are very
speedy messengers, the energy released by
nuclear fusion in the central part of the star
takes some ten million years to reach the surface,
moving centimetre by centimetre in a random
fashion. It finally appears in the form of light, an
immense source of life for our planet.
Opots and flares
The main observable phenomena on the sun's
surface are sunspots, which are darker than the
rest of the disc. In Antiquity some observers saw
them with the naked eye. They are signs of the
sun's magnetic field, which, created deep inside
the star, structures its entire atmosphere. When,
during a total eclipse of the sun, the extended
part of this atmosphere the corona can be
observed, it is clear that the solar atmosphere is
not uniform.
Above the spots, in the solar corona, the
magnetic field can stock energy and suddenly
release it. Solar flares which occur frequently
in weak form can nonetheless have a strong î#
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
In the core of the sun 700 million
tons of hydrogen are changed into
helium each second and four
million tons of matter are
transformed into energy.
Artist Julian Baum's striking
portrayal of the sun as it will
appear near the end of Its life in
around 5,500 million years. It
will evolve into a red giant, 300
times brighter and 50 times
bigger than it is today.
disturbing influence on the interplanetary envi¬
ronment. Like the spots that produce them,
they follow an eleven-year cycle, which is due to
the oscillation of the mechanism creating the
magnetic fields inside the sun. When solar
activity is at its height, the earth's space envi¬
ronment is bombarded with a shower of highly
destructive protons emitted during flares, inter¬
planetary shock waves, and an increase in ultra¬
violet rays and X-rays that are thousands of
times more intense than when the sun is calm.
At such times satellites have a higher rate of
breakdowns and their orbits are greatly dis¬
turbed. Astronauts travelling to the moon or to
other planets would be in serious danger of
radiation during a big flare. On the earth's sur¬
face, we are well protected from the sun's
caprices by our planet's atmosphere and mag¬
netic field. It should be noted, however, that
on rare occasions particle emissions from the sun
may disturb the earth's magnetic field, as can be
seen by an increase in the northern lights, and
have severe effects in telephone and computer
cables and electricity distribution grids. During
flares, radio communication may also be diffi¬
cult, and even impossible, in certain regions.
As already noted, the sun will live to an age of
some ten thousand million years. At 4.5 thousand
million years old, it is now in middle age. It will
continue to burn its hydrogen for about the same
amount of time and remain stable. But then, in its
last thousand million years, the sun will dilate, and
its surface temperature, around 5,800°K at pre¬
sent, will be reduced by half. It will then become
what astronomers call a "red giant", i.e. it will be
at least fifty times bigger and 300 times brighter
than it is today. Life on earth will become infernal.
Then, lacking fuel, the sun will shrink and lose its
brightness, ending up as one of the ghost stars that
wander through the universe.
So, in five billion years, "Stop the world,
we have to get off".
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Myths with the sun in them
by Philippe Borgeaud
Pharaoh Akhenaton making an
offering to Aton, the solar disk
(about 1353 B.C.). The name
"Akhenaton" (literally "he who
pleases the solar disk") was
adopted by Amenophis IV at the
beginning of his reign as part of
his religious and political
reforms.
From ancient Egypt to the Aztecs, from the
Amazon to the Baltic, the sun has always played
a leading role in mythology and tradition
In the religious universe of Ancient Egypt
the sun was the core around which ev¬
erything revolved. The Egyptians attentively
watched the sun's daily round, which they repre¬
sented in the form of a scarab indicating the
future, and later as the resplendent solar disk, but
devoted even more attention to describing its
nightly course, during which the sun god, Re,
was joined by his earthly son, the pharaoh,
when the latter died. Travelling every night 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
through the underworld in his boat, Re had to
face trials and defeat hostile forces, especially
attacks from Apepi, a giant snake. For the sun,
dawn was equivalent to rebirth.
The eye of Re
One of many Egyptian traditions concerning the
sun was that of the revolt (or plot) of men.
When Re, as lord of the earth, grew old, he con¬
sulted the gods and made up his mind to
despatch against the plotters the lion-goddess
Sekhmet ("the powerful"), who was also his
eye (this personification of the solar eye reflected
the sun's omnipotence). The gods did not intend
to wipe out human beings, simply to reduce
their number. But Sekhmet, consumed with
rage and drunk with blood, lost all self-con¬
trol. To calm her down and prevent her from
massacring all humanity, Re thought of an anti¬
dote. He poured out a large quantity of beer that
he had dyed red. The lioness drank it and became
so drunk that she forgot her fury. Humanity was
saved, but the goddess remained angry. Eventu¬
ally Re became weary of humans and decided to
leave the earth. He climbed onto the back of Nut
(the celestial Cow) and rose into the sky.
Other stories in the same mythological cycle
tell how Re's eye, in the form of a lioness named
Tefnut, went into exile in deepest Nubia. The
Taperet with raised hands
worshipping the Egyptian sun
god Re-Horakhty. Painting on
wood, ancient Egypt, 9th
century B.C.
12
sun god was thus deprived of his eye, and as a
consequence the whole country was engulfed in
chaos. The gods had to send emissaries to mol¬
lify the terrible goddess and encourage her to
return, a task that was finally accomplished by
Thoth, a clever baboon. The goddess turned
herself into a cat (Bast), or became Hathor, god¬
dess of amorous desire. To everyone's delight she
returned to Egypt.
The five suns
In Aztec tradition, as recorded in such accounts
as the Leyenda de los Soles ("Legend of the
Suns", written in Náhuatl in 1558 after the
Spanish conquest), our sun was preceded by
four other suns, corresponding to four different
epochs.
The first sun or "Four-Jaguar" shone at the
time when the earth was inhabited by giants. It
was buried when the sky collapsed and, under
cover of dark, the jaguars devoured everyone in
the world. The second sun, "Four-Wind", was
destroyed by a great hurricane that turned
people into monkeys. The third, "Four-Rain",
was obliterated by a rain of fire that turned
people into turkeys. And the fourth, "Four-
Water", ended in a deluge that drowned the
mountains and transformed human beings into
fish. Only a single couple escaped, protected
by Tezcatlipoca, god of the night sky, but they
made the gods angry and "Tezcatlipoca cut off
their heads, stuck them onto their rear-ends and
turned them into dogs".
The fifth sun (our own), known as "Four-
Movement", is also under threat and condemned
to eventual destruction by earthquakes and
widespread famine. Humankind must put off
this evil day by keeping the sun supplied with
energy. Human sacrifice is necessary to fuel the
sun and keep the world alive. The myth of the
fifth sun's birth was therefore also a founding
myth of ritual sacrifice among the Aztecs.
The most famous version of this myth is
that told by the sixteenth-century chronicler-
monk Bernardino de Sahagún in his Historia
general de las cosas de Nueva España ("General
History of Things in New Spain").
Bernardino de Sahagún tells how the gods
gathered in Teotihuacán, an ancient Central
American city, and asked, "Who will be respon¬
sible for lighting the world?" One of them, Tec-
ciztécatl, immediately volunteered. Then the
gods asked, "Who else?" But no one else dared
to volunteer for this task. The inconpicuous
Nanahuatzin, who was afflicted with bubas
(pustules), sat silently apart from the rest. They
turned to him and said, "Let it be you, little
buboso". "I accept as a favour what you ask me
to do," he answered. "So be it."
The two gods began by doing four days of
penance. Then they lit a fire on a stone that is
known today as Teotexcalli ("the divine rock").
Everything offered by Tecuciztécatl was pre¬
cious: instead of palm fron^ds he offered rare
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Left, The Sun Stone (basalt,
3.35 metres in diameter, 24
tons, early 16th century). At
the centre of this huge circular
disk, sometimes called "the
Aztec Calendar", the fifth sun of
Aztec mythology is shown with
human features.
Below, the Sun Pyramid, the
largest of the ceremonial
buildings in Teotihuacán, some
40 kilometres from Mexico City.
A pre-Columbian metropolis,
Teotihuacán flourished between
250 and 650 A.D.
feathers; instead of bales of hay he offered balls
of gold; instead of maguey thorns, precious
stones; instead of bloody thorns, bunches of
red coral; and last but not least, high-quality
copal. Nanahuatzin, on the other hand, offered
instead of palms nine green reeds that he tied
together three by three, hay and maguey thorns
anointed with his own blood and, instead of
copal, the scabs of his own bubas.
At midnight the gods formed two lines, one
on each side of the place where the fire had
burned for four days. Tecuciztécatl and Nanahu¬
atzin took their places with their faces turned
toward the fire between the two rows of gods
who remained standing. The gods turned first to
Tecuciztécatl and said, "Come, Tecuciztécatl,
cast thyself into the fire!" But the fire was ter¬
ribly hot, and however hard he tried he became
frightened and drew back. And so the gods
turned to Nanahuatzin and urged him to try
instead. Without the slightest hesitation,
Nanahuatzin threw himself into the flames and
began to burn at once. When he saw that, Tecu¬
ciztécatl also threw himself into the fire.
When the two gods had been consumed by
the fire, the others sat down and waited for
them to reappear. After a long time, the sky
turned purple, and the earth was flooded with
light. It is said that the gods knelt down in order
to see where Nanahuatzin would arise now that
he had become the sun, and that only a few of
them predicted correctly. When a very red sun
rose languidly in the east, no one could look at
it because it was blinding in its magnificence, and
rays burst from it in all directions.
The love of Etsa and Nantu
A myth of the Jivaros Indians of the Amazon
tells how Etsa, the sun, is the son of the Creator,
who blew mud onto him while he was sleeping.
The mud became a woman, the moon (Nantu),
with whom the sun wished to couple. But Nantu
was frightened and did not respond to Etsa's
advances. Taking advantage of a moment when
Etsa was concentrating on painting his face to
make himself more attractive to her, she flew like
an arrow to the upper world, where she too
painted her face, but with black lines, before
clambering up into the heavenly vault like a
jaguar.
Etsa tied two parrots and two parakeets to
his wrists and knees and flew up to Nantu. A
violent dispute broke out between them. Con¬
sumed with anger, Etsa struck Nantu, creating
an eclipse of the moon. Then Nantu got the
upper hand, causing an eclipse of the sun. The
outcome of this quarrel, which was destined to
break out again, was the moon's submission to
the sun. Defeated, Nantu cried, and her face 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Two Greek relief depictions of
Helios, the sun god, wearing a
radiant crown and driving the
heavenly chariot.
Left: 3rd century B.C.
Above: 4th century B.C.
14
PHILIPPE BORGEAUD,
a Swiss historian of ancient
religions, Is head of the Centre
of Ancient Near Eastern Studies
(CEPOA) at the University of
Geneva. Among his many
published works are Recherches
sur le dieu Pan (Rome-Geneva,
1979) and La mémoire des
religions (Geneva, 1988).
became red, which is why a red moon always
announces rain.
Finally Etsa and Nantu married and cou¬
pled on the banks of the Kanusa river. Preg¬
nant by the sun, the moon swelled and gave
birth to a child, Uñushi (the "Sloth"), ancestor
of the Jivaros. Uñushi soon had a whole string
of brothers and sisters, including the freshwater
dolphin, the peccary and above all a young
woman named Manioc, the boon companion
of the Jivaros.
Lady Sun and Lord Moon
The traditional poetry of the Baltic countries also
contains a rich corpus of stories about the sun,
moon and stars.
' In one popular Lithuanian song, Moon (mas¬
culine) and Sun (feminine) are a divorced couple.
They separated because the moon betrayed the
sun with the morning star. Perkunas the thun¬
derer punished the guilty husband by slashing
him with a sword, thus giving rise to the phases
of the moon.
Such stories are probably the extensions of
very ancient cosmological traditions. A Chris¬
tian missionary whose story was recorded in
the fifteenth century tells how a tribe in this
region venerated a huge iron hammer. He was
told by a pagan priest that Lady Sun, formerly
locked away in a tower by a local tyrant, was
delivered by the signs of the Zodiac, which used
a huge hammer to demolish the keep.
In old Icelandic mythology (the Gylfagin-
ning or The Beguiling ofGylfi, the first part of
the Prose Edda, written by Snorri Sturluson in
the thirteenth century), Mani (masculine, Moon)
is the brother of Sol (feminine, Sun), and both are
the children of Mundilfari ("He who drives
time"). Moon and Sun rush across the sky, never
slowing down, she in front, he behind, each
with a monstrous wolf snapping at their heels.
At the end of time the wolves will catch
them up and eat them. The stars will disappear,
the mountains will crumble, the oceans will
invade the land, and gods and men will perish.
But there will be survivors, including a small
number of gods and a human couple fed by the
morning dew, in a green and lovely land that will
rise from the sea. Sun's daughter will continue
her mother's path over the fields, which will
produce harvests without having to be ploughed.
Helios and his heavenly chariot
In Greek mythology Uranus (Starry Sky) and
Gaea (Earth) formed the first union in a world
where nothing existed but Abyss and Desire,
and gave birth to the Titans, who were gifted
with enormous but ill-defined power. Two of the
Titans were Hyperion ("he who circulates in the
heights") and Thea (the "divine"). This first
generation of sexed offspring is similar to that of
Night, a daughter who sprang fatherless from
the Abyss (Chaos). Uranus prevented his off¬
spring from emerging "toward the light" and hid
them in the body of Gaea, with whom he con¬
tinued to couple "by bringing the Night". Gaea
appealed to her children for vengeance and gave
a weapon to her youngest child, Cronus, who
cut off Uranus' genitals, thereby separating
heaven and earth.
In the following generation Helios the sun-
god, brother of the Moon and Aurora, and a
contemporary of Zeus and the Olympian gods,
was said to have issued from the love between
Hyperion and Thea. He reproduced in luminous
fashion the divine quality and the heavenly
course of his titanic parents.
Helios was a wonderful charioteer. By day he
drove his chariot drawn by winged horses from
east to west across the sky as far as the banks of
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
the stream of Ocean whose regenerating waters
girdle the earth. There he embarked in a large
hollow cup or cauldron and sailed through the
night to the dawn over Ocean's stormy waves.
The daughters of Ocean were Helios's com¬
panions. From their union sprang strange and
fearsome children, including Circe the sorceress,
who lived on the western isle of Aeaea (located
near Italy, according to the Odyssey legend)
and Aeetes, the king of Colchis, a land located
at the foot of the Caucasus on the shores of the
Black Sea. Aeetes was the father of another
famous sorceress, Medea.
Helios was an ideal observer of men and
gods, a spy in the service of his cousins the
Olympians. Nothing escaped him, not even the
kidnapping of Demeter's daughter Persephone
by Hades, lord of the underworld. Yet he lived
sheltered from the problems of the Olympian
gods. If he was slighted, others would avenge
him. Thus Odysseus' companions in the
Odyssey insult Helios by killing and eating part
of his flocks. Helios asks Zeus for reparation,
and Zeus punishes the evil-doers by making
them die in a shipwreck at sea.
Nothing must disturb Helios's calm tran¬
scendant regularity. One day, his son, Phaethon
(the "radiant") asked his father to let him drive
the sun chariot to prove his own divinity. Not
possessing his father's skill, the young man
drove too close to earth and scorched it, where¬
upon Zeus smashed the impudent boy with a
thunderbolt and hurled him into a river. Helios
did not even have time to mourn, leaving that to
Phaethon's sisters, the Heliades, whose tears
became drops of amber, the physical expres¬
sion of a sun-caused sorrow.
It took an utterly wicked crime to make the
sun sufficiently upset to deviate from its course.
It was committed by Atreus, who killed the
children of his twin brother Thyestes and then
served up portions of their cooked bodies to
their father at a banquet. When Thyestes had
eaten, his brother showed him his children's
heads and told him what he had just eaten,
whereupon Helios turned back on his course in
horror.
Above, dancers wearing sun and moon masks at the feast of
St Peter and St Paul In Sibayo, southern Peru.
Above right, in a Japanese ritual dance the Shinto sun
goddess Amaterasu ("radiant heaven") emerges from the
cave in which she had taken refuge, thereby plunging the
world into darkness.
Right, a modern Druid ceremony at Stonehenge in Wiltshire
(England). The exact purpose of this group of megaliths, the
largest in the British isles, is not known, but according to
one theory It was a temple of the sun.
Thinking in images
The supernatural and the fantastic are characteristic features of myths, in which
animals sometimes have the power of speech, human beings may change into ani¬
mals or plants, and gods and heroes wield fantastic powers.
The liberties that myth takes with reality do not represent a breakdown of the
rules of reason. The world's components are seen as raw material from which a
story can be constructed; real things become toolsimageswhereby a story can
become a vehicle of meaning.
What the French anthropologist Claude Lévi-Strauss called "the savage mind"
is capable of thought as rigorous as that of philosophers or mathematicians. It is
a mind that functions with the aid of elements of the real world. It does not focus
primarily on that world but thinks with the help of it. It is therefore not surprising
that some of the images that crop up in myths recur in many different places and
historical periods. This does not mean, however, that they are always and every¬
where endowed with the same meaning.
Among these recurrent images are those linked with celestial light: the sun,
the moon, the planets and the constellations. The sun is an essential item on this
list, prompting, as it does, thoughts of the beginning and the end of things, and
of the daily victory of light over darkness and nocturnal anxieties. As it undergoes
the great changes in intensity that mark its course from one horizon to the other,
from dawn twilight to high noon and back to evening twilight, the sun indicates
spatial directions as well as dividing up stretches of time. Above all it makes things
visible. It brings light as well as heat. Very often it is regarded as an eye and an
observer, in line with the very ancient and widespread notion whereby an eye illu¬
minates the thing it sees. Such is the case of the eye of that fearsome arbiter the
Egyptian sun-god Re, and that of the Greek sun-god Helios, which nothing escaped.
P. B.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
A light that shines through time
and Cultures by Madanjeet Singh
16
MADANJEET SINGH
is an Indian art historian, writer,
painter and photographer. A
former ambassador, he is
currently a special advisor to the
Director-General of Unesco. He is
the author of many books, and
compiled and presented a
collective work entitled The Sun,
Eternal Flame of Creation,
published in 1993 in several
language versions (Unesco,
Paris; Harry N. Abrams, Inc.,
New York; Thames & Hudson,
London, for the English edition).
After their emergence as tool-
making hominids about one-and-
a-half million years ago during the
Old Stone Age, our prehistoric
ancestors instinctively related the
sun to all-embracing nature stones,
mountains, trees, plants, flowers,
birds, beasts, water and fire. Living
in caves or beneath overhanging
rocks, they used wooden sticks and
unpolished chipped stones for
hunting wild beasts, and depicted
hunting scenes and solar symbols
in rock carvings. Such petroglyphs
have been discovered in central Asia,
Africa, Europe and in other parts
of the world as far distant as
Indonesia and southwest America.
They show the sun in a variety of
forms, either as rays emanating from
a circle or anthropomorphically, as
a nimbus surrounding a head.
These rudimentary circular and
Left, Coronation of
the Virgin by the
Italian painter Fra
Angélico
(1400-c. 1455).
Below,
anthropomorphic
rock carving
of the sun god at
Saimaly Tash in
the Tien mountains
of Kirgizia.
Bronze age
(4000-2000 B.C.).
spiral patterns are thought to have
led to the earliest forms of hiero¬
glyphic writing, the invention of the
wheel, and the universally popular
spiral design, as well as to the image
of the halo as a sign of spiritual lumi¬
nosity. In time almost all elements of
nature became deities and totems of
sun cults and were represented in
human or animal forms, forming
the basis of organized religions that
invoked the sun as the divine light of
virtue. "Sûrya is the ultimate truth,"
states Aditya-Hrydya Sutra, and this
is beautifully depicted in an Indian
miniature painting, Heart ofSûrya,
in which Vishnu and his consort
Lakshmi are seated in the sun, much
like the beautiful figure of Mani
(216-274 A.D.), the founder of
Manichaeism, in the still-used
temple of Cao'an on the eastern
coast of China near Quanzhou in
Fujian province. In the Samyutta
Nikaya, the Buddha calls the sun
"the fiery heart, my kith and kin",
and this concept is also incorpo¬
rated in Christian art, as can be seen
in Fra Angelico's painting Corona¬
tion ofthe Virgin, now in the Uffizi
(Florence).
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
People have always venerated
the sun as an emblem oflife, truth,
justice i
Right, a sacred feast of Roman initiates in the cult of
Mithra (2nd century A.D.). Worship of this Indo-lranian
divinity with solar associations inspired a major religious
movement, Mithraism, in the Roman Empire between the
1st and 3rd centuries A.D.
Left, inside a
painted cave-
temple at
Dunhuang (China).
The prophet Mani
is shown with Fu-xi
and Nu-wa, the sun
and moon deities
(6th century A.D.).
Prophets
Prophets such as Zoroaster (late sev¬
enth and early sixth centuries B.C.)
and Mani invoked the sun's divine
light of virtue to conquer the dark¬
ness of evil. The sun god Mithra
became the charioteer of Ahura
Mazda, the Zoroastrian Creator
God of Light, who is opposed by
the evil darkness of Angra Mainyu
or Ahriman. Ahura Mazda is "like
the sun to behold for the sun is
the greatest of all visible, earthly
fires", stated Zoroaster (c. 628-551
B.C.). Even today in several eastern
Iranian languages the word for the
sun is simply "of Ahura Mazda".
Manichaeism was truly an ecu¬
menical faith embracing all people,
as Mani, its founder, tried to inte¬
grate diverse religions such as
Gnostic Christianity, Zoroastri-
anism and Buddhism, in a strongly
dualistic philosophy based on the
eternal struggle between good and
evil, light and darkness. It was once
professed by many peoples, from
Spain in the west to the eastern coast
of China.
Parsees, whose name is derived from
Parsa or Persian, are Indian followers of
Mazdaism (Zoroastrianism) who live in the
Bombay area. They have temples in which
the sacred fire is kept burning perpetually.
Left, the Parsee yasna ceremony in which
fire is propitiated as one of the seven
creations, along with water, plants,
animals, humans, the earth and the sky.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A symbol ofpower
Above, the sun
chariot in the
Apollo fountain in
the grounds of the
Château of
Versailles (17th
century). It has
been suggested
that the
charioteer's
features are those
of France's Sun
King, Louis XIV.
18
Great conquerors and rulers
employed the spirit of solar univer¬
sality in order to ensure the loyalty of
their subjects. Confronted with
antagonistic sects which engendered
social tension, ethnic hatred and reli¬
gious animosity, they tried to create
stable government based on norms of
unity symbolized by the sun.
Akhenaton (c. 1353 B.C.) sought
to unite his people under the all-
embracing light emanating from the
sun-disc, the Aton. Alexander the
Great (356-323 B.C.) aspired to rule
the world "like the sun", especially
after his conquest of Egypt, when
he chose to become the "son of the
Sun-God Amon". The Mauryan
emperors in India were inspired to
emulate the example set by
Alexander's brief incursion into India
in 326 B.C., which helped to revive
the ancient sun-related Vedic con¬
cepts. Chandragupta Maurya (c. 321-
297 B.C.) cast himself in the "sun-
guardian" image of Universal
Emperor, and Ashoka (d. 238 B.C.?),
the last major emperor of the Mau-
»II ;
, IS
'MA
Left, medallion depicting Cybele, the
mother-goddess of ancient Greece.
Combining Greco-Roman, Mesopotamian,
Persian and Indian art styles, it was
inspired by Alexander the Great (356-323
B.C.) who wished to rule "like the sun".
Below, a composite solar symbol inspired
by several cultures, this capital adorned
with lions is from a commemorative pillar
erected in Sarnath (India) during the reign
of the Emperor Asoka (3rd century B.C.).
ryan Dynasty, erected numerous pil¬
lars inscribed with sun motifs. The
Roman emperor Aurelian (215-275
A.D.) sought similarly to bring diver¬
gent sects and tribal minorities in his
empire under the aegis of the Uncon¬
querable Sun (Sol Invictus). The
"Divine Sun" was at the centre of
the syncretic Din-i-Ilahi cult, around
which the Mughal emperor Akbar
(1542-1605) tried to rally the diverse
peoples of his vast Indian empire.
Louis XIV (1638-1715), the "Sun
King" of France, glorified the myth
of Apollo, and often appeared
dressed as this sun deity at the lavish
feasts he organized in the vast gardens
of his great palace of Versailles. A
sculpture of Apollo stands in the
grotto of Thetis at Versailles, and
elsewhere in the gardens a figure of
the sun in a chariot is said to represent
the king.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Mountains
Below, the
pyramid temple of
Kukulcán, today
known as the
Castillo, at
Chichén Itzá,
Yucatán (Mexico).
(Post-classical
period, 950-1500
A.D.)
The mountain often became the
"heavenly ladder" needed to reach
heaven where the sun god and other
solar deities supposedly lived. In
Egypt the notion of "the ladder of
Horus" (the sky-god) reaching to
the sun-door, the crossing point
from mortality to immortality,
seems to have originated in very
early step pyramids. In Mexico the
Aztecs related the Teotihuacán pyra¬
mids to the sun and the moon.
Shamash, the sun god of the Semitic
pantheon, rose from the eastern
mountains and inaugurated the
practice of building elevated citadels
like the ziggurats to the Babylonian
moon-god Nanna. Pausanias, a
Greek traveller in the second cen¬
tury, relates how he saw sun altars of
worship on the highest acropolis at
Corinth. The mountain at Bojone-
goro in Java is venerated because
"the sun comes out of it", and in Sri
Lanka, Saman "the deity of the
morning sun" is worshipped on
Samanolakanda Mountain, also
called Adam's Peak. The Chinese
Emperor Wu-di of the Han Dynasty
(140-87 B.C.) frequented the Cheng
mountain at the eastern end of the
Shandong peninsula in order to
worship the sun rising from the sea.
The mountain deity of ancient
Japan, Yama-no-kami, is wor¬
shipped as "the sun of forests and
animals".
JH
Joined by a rope,
these two rocks off
the seashore at
Futamigaura
(Japan) symbolize
the primordial
divine couple. The
sun-door of life
stands on top of
the larger rock.
A religious
structure of
Babylonian origin,
the ziggurat was
probably both a
symbol of the
primeval mountain
and the meeting
point between
heaven and earth
through which the
gods passed. Left:
an illustration from
an early 20th-
century German
book showing the
ziggurat of
Babylon.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
This painted wood carving from Indonesia,
left, shows the Hindu god Vishnu riding
Garuda, the giant eagle and king of birds,
on which he flew to his Imprisoned
mother's aid.
Below, cover of a Russian émigré
magazine, published in Berlin in 1921-
1922. Its title, The Firebird, is that of a
famous Russian folk tale.
Y^JAK-í'TiZA.^
Birds
The mythical sun-bird depicted on the
gateway of a 17th-century monument in
Bukhara (Uzbekistan).
20
Birds flying in the sky naturally
became identified with the sun. In
central Asia this tradition goes back
to the Old Stone Age, and is notably
exemplified by the petroglyph of a
strange bird depicted, with other sun
symbols, in the Shakty cave in the
Pamir mountains. The mythical fire¬
bird of Russian folklore was
endowed with extraordinary powers:
"even one of its feathers could flood
the whole world with the sunlight
of happiness". In ancient Egypt, a
fabulous bird known as the bennu, a
kind of heron, was traditionally asso¬
ciated with sun worship as a symbol
of the rising sun and of life after
death. It was also known as the
phoenix, and its image appears on
the coinage of the late Roman Empire
as the symbol of the Eternal City.
The Chinese name for it is pheng or
ch'i-lin, and in Islamic mythology it
is called rukh oranqà (Persian
sîmorgh). Garuda is its counterpart in
India and southeast Asia.
The depiction of the sun in
animal form results largely from
ancient beliefs in which birds, ani¬
mals, reptiles and fish were assigned
special significance. Perhaps the ear¬
liest known representation of a bird
is the eagle/falcon image on the
palette of King Narmer from Hier-
akonpolis (c. 3,000 B.C.), symbol¬
izing the sun god Horus.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
A leitmotiv ofart
n African sun mask.
Art styles throughout history have
also been inspired by the sun, from
the Amarna sculptures in ancient
Egypt to the Impressionist art forms
of modern times. With his emphasis
upon maat, or truth, Akhenaton
created the first-ever "realistic"
artistic style, ordering artists and
craftsmen to depict faithfully what
they actually saw rather than follow
tradition-bound canons glorifying
the Pharaoh's personality.
During Akbar's time a distinctly
Indian style of painting was inspired
by his "solar vision". It is charac¬
terized by a vivid treatment of the
physical world which can be seen
in the celebrated manuscript which
Akbar ordered his artists to prepare
of Hamza-nama (c. 1567), the story
of the deeds of a legendary adven¬
turer who lived during the reign of
Harun ar-Rashid.
The shining spirit of the sun also
inspired Japanese painting. The
imperial edicts of the seventh and
eighth centuries which formed the
basis ofJapanese political, legal and
ethical values refer repeatedly to
"the sun's bright, pure, honest and
sincere heart," and these virtues
were also incorporated into the
realm of aesthetics, so that purity,
directness and brightness became
the essence of Japanese art and lit¬
erature. The pervasive influence of
the sun in Japanese culture is evi¬
dent in haiku poetry, calligraphy
and ink-drawn scrolls, as well as in
the tea ceremony, flower arrange¬
ment and garden design.
"The Triumphal Procession of the White
Horse", an episode from the legend of
Akbar, Mughal emperor of India (1556-
1605), is depicted in this 16th-century
Indian miniature.
f¡&fe ¿s
*L 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Architeäure
22
Inside a yurt or tent of the Kalmyks, a
traditionally nomadic people of Mongolian
origin who live in Siberia and central Asia.
Early 19th-century French lithograph.
Below, the Roman town of Bram in the
southwest of France was built in the 4th
century A.D. according to a "solar" plan.
In the field of architecture, it is
amazing how the simple sun motif
in the shape of a small circular
opening in the roof of a nomadic
yurt developed into as grand and
marvellous a structural source of
illumination as that seen in the dome
of the Pantheon in Rome and its
rotunda. Apparently the Roman
baths and similar structures built to
serve as tombs for pagan emperors
were also "glorified yurts". It was
not until the fourth century that a
Christian meaning was given to
light-oriented architecture in the
baptisteries and funerary chapels
attached to basilicas. The manner
of orienting pagan shrines towards
the sunrise was also adopted by
Christian churches, built with the
altar located at the east end or more
accurately in the direction where
the sun rose on the feast day of their
patron saint.
The sun inspired the circular
urban plan which encircles the cen¬
tral shrines in many medieval towns
in Europe, one notable example
being the Roman town of Bram in
France (founded in 333 A.D.). These
towns recall the ancient Zoroastrian
townships in Central Asia, which
were conceived either on a circular
design or in the shape of a crossed
circle.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Pageants andfestivals
Most pageants and festivals around
the world can be traced back either
directly to the sun or indirectly to it
through agricultural and fertility
rites. Processions involving animal
and reptile solar symbols in many
Asian, African and native American
societies also have equivalents in
Europe. The once-popular giants'
carnivals in Douai and Dunkirk in
France and Antwerp in Belgium,
actually originated in sacrificial rit¬
uals of ancient solar cults, in which
huge osier frames of greenery were
carried much like the Jack-in-the-
green-basket-clad figures in Eng¬
lish May Day parades (which are
essentially fertility celebrations).
Christians in Wales adopted another
pagan ritual of fertility and concep¬
tion in which the link between the
sun and water was invoked by
"walking-sun-wise" around a holy
well three times.
Zoroastrianism and
the cult of fire
by Mahin Tadjadod
'Fire must play the same role on earth
as the sun does in the sky'
A product of the Indo-European tradition, the cult of fire
was practised in ancient times by the Scythians and
was also known to the Greeks and Romans. An eternal
flame burned on the altar of Pan at Olympia, the Greeks
kept a gold lamp permanently in the sanctuary of
Pallas Athene, and the Persian king Xerxes I (486-465
B.C.) of the Achaemenid dynasty is said to have spared
the temple of Delos because its cult reminded him of
the fire of Iran. (In India and Iran fire was the dominant
feature of the ancient Aryan religion.)
The prophet Zoroaster transposed fire to the spir¬
itual realm as a symbol of divine splendour and power,
the source of human life and love for Ahura Mazda, the
"Wise Lord". Strictly speaking, fire was never a divinity
in itself, but rather the visible sign of God's presence.
Mazdaism (another name for Zoroastrianism) is based
on a strong affirmation of the oneness of Ahura Mazda,
whose essence is consubstantial with infinite light.
Ahura Mazda's eye is the sun, and his son is fire,
burning before him in his spiritual form.
A FLAME KEPT ALIGHT FOR 3,000 YEARS
The Bundahishn ("Book of the Original Creation")
speaks of the "three fires of Persia" that long wandered
where the wind blew them before descending from
heaven at the time of the mythical Kayanid kings.
According to one theory they are linked to the three
social classes instituted by Zoroaster's three sons:
priests, warriors and farmers.
Since then the flame has never gone out in the tem¬
ples. At night it is put to sleep with prayers and at dawn
it is awakened with praise.
Fire rewards and punishes. It is the symbol of sin¬
cerity and purity. It burns the sinner and protects the
virtuous. Trial by fire, the Ordeal, decides whether a
person accused of a crime is innocent or guilty. Falsely
accused of having raped his mother-in-law, Siyavosh, the
hero of the Iranian epic, the Shah-nama ("The Book of
Kings"), passes through fire and emerges unscathed.
Since he is stainless, he is spared by the fire.
Even today the Zoroastrian community obeys these
ancient precepts. Its faithful still make offerings to fire
and are careful not to defile it with their breath. This
is why Zoroastrian priests, the mobads, cover their
mouths with the panam (two pieces of white cotton
cloth knotted behind the head) when they face the fire
and recite the Avesta, the holy book.
Today the faithful still come to the Zoroastrian
temple at Yazd, the most venerable in all Iran. The
building and the garden around it are carefully tended,
and it is said that the fire burning inside has not gone
out for 3,000 years.
Above, a sun mask worn at
the Venice carnival.
MAHIN TADJADOD,
of Iran, is the author of several plays inspired by Persian
mythology and epics.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Music
Below, a scene
from a 1991 Paris
production of The
Magic Flute.
Sarastro, the high
priest of the sun,
stands before the
Solar Circle.
The flute and drum are among the
most ancient musical instruments.
The flute, as a phallic symbol, is uni¬
versally identified with the male,
while the drum represents the
female's womb. Together they sym¬
bolize the sun and hence fecundity,
happy life, and rebirth. The flute
and drum are in most cultures the
principal accompaniment to sun-
dances, which are generally per¬
formed with four dancers repre¬
senting the four quarters of the
universe. The flute's cosmic signifi¬
cance is also evident in Mozart's
opera The Magic Flute, in which
two "realms" are separated by light
and darkness, and there is a struggle
to possess the powerful Sevenfold
Solar Circle the sun.
A tom-tom player
(Sierra Leone).
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Manolo plugs into the sun
by Christopher Flavin and Nicholas Lenssen
A unique andpotentially revolutionary means
ofgeneratingpower, solarphotovoltaic cells are
meeting the energy needs of thousands of
villagers in the developing world. One of them
is Manolo Hidalgo. . .
Above, a solar energy power
plant at Carrisa Plain, California
(U.S.A.).
In Joba Arriba, a scattered farming set¬
tlement of about 5,000 people on the
Dominican Republic's northern coast, Manolo
Hidalgo decided to give his family a different
kind of Christmas present in 1991: electric
lighting. No longer content with dim and smelly
kerosene lamps to light the homework of his
three children, Hidalgo knew that his chances of
getting electricity in the conventional way by
hounding government officials in the hope they
would extend the nearest power line the neces¬
sary fifteen kilometres were faint at best.
Hidalgo came up with a faster, more reli¬
able option. Travelling to the nearby town of
Sosua, he visited a small store called Industria
Eléctrica Bella Vista, which offered a self-con¬
tained solar panel that converts the sun's rays
directly into electric current. With help from the
store's electrician, Hidalgo mounted the roughly
one-metre-square panel on his roof and wired it
to a lead-acid battery in order to store electricity
for use in the evening. The day after visiting 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
A solar-powered water pump in
a refugee camp in Hargeysa
(Somalia).
Below, solar panel and water
pump in a Moroccan village.
Sosua, his home had five working electric lights,
as well as a radio and television set, all pow¬
ered by his solar photovoltaic (PV) panel. With
the flip of a switch on that December day,
Hidalgo and his family joined tens of thousands
of rural people who in the past few years have
begun getting their power directly from the sun.
It is hard not to be struck by the irony that
the basic energy needs of some of the world's
poorest people are being met by what is arguably
the most elegant and sophisticated energy tech¬
nology yet developed. Indeed, solar photo¬
voltaic cells, which can be used in everything
from handheld calculators to suburban rooftops
and large desert power stations, are a unique
and potentially revolutionary means of gener
ating power. Solar cell technology is advancing
rapidly, and many experts expect the devices to
be ubiquitous in the early part of the next cen¬
tury. But the greatest short-term impact of solar
photovoltaics will be in the rural Third World,
providing power to many of the more than two
billion people like Manolo Hidalgo who do not
yet have it.
Solar photovoltaic cells are semiconductor
devices made of silicon similar to but far less
expensive than the chips used in computers
that convert the energy from sunlight into
moving electrons, avoiding the mechanical tur¬
bines and generators that provide virtually all the
world's electricity today. French scientist
Edmond Becquerel discovered in 1839 that light
falling on certain materials could cause a spark
of electricity known as the "photoelectric
effect" and that this charge could, under the
right conditions, be propagated, forming an
electric current. Within fifty years, scientists
began to manufacture primitive solar cells out of
a rare element known as selenium. The high
cost and low efficiency of these devices made
them useful in only one serious application
photographic light meters.
The precursors of the modern photovoltaic
cells used on Manolo Hidalgo's roof did not
emerge until 1954. Early that year, a small team
of scientists at the Bell Laboratories in New
Jersey began looking for a way to generate elec¬
tricity for telephone systems in remote areas. As
they tried to improve the selenium cells, a sep¬
arate Bell team discovered that a silicon device
26
CHRISTOPHER FLAVIN,
of the United States, is Vice-
President for Research at the
Worldwatch Institute in
Washington, D.C., a private non¬
profit environmental research
organization.
NICHOLAS LENSSEN,
of the United States, is a Senior
Researcher at the Worldwatch
Institute. His research and
writing deal with energy policy,
alternative energy sources,
nuclear power, radioactive
waste, and global climate
change.
This article has been
extracted from their book Power
Surge, Guide to the coming
energy revolution (W.W. Norton
& Company, New York and
London, 1994).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Cleaning domestic solar
heating panels in Australia.
they were testing produced electricity when
exposed to sunlight. When the work of the two
groups was merged, a breakthrough was
achieved: a silicon cell that converted 4 per cent
of all incoming sunlight into electricity five
times as much as the best selenium cell. Within
a few months, the Bell team had pushed the
cell's efficiency to 6 per cent. Excitement about
this development was compounded by the fact
that silicon is the second most abundant ele¬
ment, constituting 28 per cent of the earth's
crust. Soon, the Bell scientists began to speculate
that silicon solar cells might become a major
source of electricity, and their enthusiasm was
echoed by the popular media, which touted the
imminent arrival of a solar-powered future.
Dpin-off from the space race
Realizing that potential turned out to be a far
greater challenge than anticipated. The initial
silicon solar cells cost roughly $600 per watt
($3,000 in 1993 dollars), several thousand times
as much as electricity from conventional plants.
After building a few prototype solar panels,
Bell Labs decided that no commercial applica¬
tions were within reach and shelved the new
technology. The photovoltaic cell was saved
from obscurity by the U.S. -Soviet space race
in the 1960s. In the rush to find a practical way
to power satellites, U.S. space scientists dusted
off the solar cell.
During the next decade, a sizable infusion of
U.S. government funds served to jumpstart the
photovoltaic industry. Within ten years the price
of solar cells was cut by a factor of five to ten, the
cell efficiency rose and the durability of the
devices improved. Producing these early PV
cells required pure, expensive silicon and
More than 200,000 homes in
Mexico, Indonesia, South Africa, Sri
Lanka and other developing countries
have obtained electricity from
rooftop-mounted solar systems over
the past decade.
wasteful, energy-intensive manufacturing
processes. Individual wafers of silicon were
sliced from long crystals grown at temperatures
above 1,400 degrees Celsius. Although costs
were beginning to fall, PVs were still too expen¬
sive for any application other than the govern¬
ment-funded space programme.
The 1973 oil crisis created a new race to
bring photovoltaics back to earth. Government
energy agencies and scores of private companies
invested billions of dollars in advancing the state
of photovoltaic technology. By 1980, the effi¬
ciency of commercial PV modules had risen to
more than 10 per cent, and the price had fallen to
roughly $12 a watt ($21 in 1993 terms). Finally, sil¬
icon PV cells were cheap enough to fill the niche
Bell Labs originally tried to create for them.
During the 1980s, solar cells were widely deployed
at telephone relay stations, microwave transmit¬
ters, remote lighthouses and roadside callboxes
applications where small amounts of power are
needed and where conventional power sources are
either too expensive or not reliable enough.
The technology continued to advance during
the next decade, and by 1993 the average whole¬
sale price of photovoltaics had dropped to
between $3.50 and $4.75 a watt, or roughly 25-400
a kilowatt-hour, thanks both to higher efficien¬
cies and more automated manufacturing
processes. As costs fell, sales rose from 6.5
megawatts in 1980 to 29 megawatts in 1987, to 60
megawatts in 1993. The worldwide industry,
including ancillary activities such as retail sales and
installation, did roughly $1 billion worth of busi¬
ness in 1993.
Although still too expensive to compete
head-to-head with conventional generating
technologies, photovoltaic cells have found ever-
larger niches in the global energy market. The 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Some of the many uses of
solar energy. Above, a solar
reflector cooker (Kenya); above
right, a Paris street lamp
(France); right, a telephone
booth in Australia.
28
technology's versatility was best demonstrated
in the mid-1980s, when Japanese electronics
companies came up with a particularly inge¬
nious application, attaching tiny solar cells to
small consumer devices such as handheld pocket
calculators and wrist-watches. These require
only a trickle of electricity, well within the capa¬
bility of a small solar cell even when oper¬
ating in a dimly lit room. Since the late 1980s, the
Japanese have sold an average of about 100 mil¬
lion such devices each year, an application that
absorbs 4 megawatts of solar cells annually, 6 per
cent of the global market. The use of solar cells
in consumer electronics has levelled off in recent
years, as has that in telecommunications, sur¬
passed by more rapidly growing applications
ranging from rural water pumps to village homes
and rural electricity.
By the early 1990s, thousands of villagers in
Africa, Asia and Latin America were doing the
same thing as Manolo Hidalgo, using photovoltaic
cells to power lights, televisions and water pumps,
needs that are otherwise met with kerosene lamps,
rechargeable batteries and diesel engines. More
than 200,000 homes in Mexico, Indonesia, South
Africa, Sri Lanka and other developing countries
have obtained electricity from rooftop-mounted
solar systems in the past decade.
Prospects for using solar photovoltaics in
ever-wider applications hinge on how rapidly
the technology evolves. Prices will need to be cut
by a factor of three to five in order for large-scale
grid-connected applications to become eco¬
nomical. Most PV experts are confident that
such reductions can be achieved by continuing
the advances in cell efficiency and manufac¬
turing processes of the past two decades and
by capturing the cost-saving potential of mass
production.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Solar panels supply power for a
water pump (above right). This
pump in the village of Sarwal in
Bihar (India) has been powered
by solar energy since 1982.
India's self-help solar villages
by Sanjit Bunker Roy
India is full ofcontrasts and contradictions. On the one hand there is "Bharat"* or traditional
India with its 600,000 villages, where life moves slowly, where centuries-oldsocial structures
remain unchanged, and where 70per cent ofthe country 's 940 million people live and die. And
then there is "India", a young country struggling to overcome the usualproblems of
underdevelopment, "India", argues Bunker Roy, has often optedfor large dams or electrification
projects that sometimes fail to respond to the needs of the humbler inhabitants of "Bharat". Here
he talks about two successful community-basedprojects which, with the use ofsolar energy, have
transformed the lives ofpoorfanners in depressed regions ofBihar and Orissa and ofpeople
living in remote Himalyan villages.
rit takes twenty-nine-year-old Tsewang
Narbo two days to walk across the 6,000-
metre-high Khardungla pass, the highest in the
Ladakh area of India's northern state of Jammu
and Kashmir. A further 60 kilometres by bus
and army truck bring him to the district head¬
quarters in Leh. Here he picks up distilled water,
fuses and other equipment before beginning the
long trek back home to his wife and five children.
But Tsewang Narbo does not mind the hard¬
ship or the strain. Since 1993, this barely literate
man has become one of the most important per¬
sons in the remote Himalayan village of Diger
where he is responsible for the upkeep and main¬
tenance of 59 solar photovoltaic units (SPVs)
which provide lighting for his and surrounding
villages and which have transformed life during
the long-snow-bound winters when tempera¬
tures can reach -30°C.
Until 1989, the energy needs of these far-
flung villages had been most inadequately met by
Diesel Generating (DG) sets which are costly,
centralized and unreliable, as well as using fossil
fuel that pollutes the environment.
Since it takes twenty-five days to haul up as
many litres of fuel to these villages located at a
height of 5,000 metres, the inhabitants used it
extremely sparingly to make it last the six months
ofwinter. At night, entire families huddled around
a single light no stronger than a candle flame.
Solar lighting therefore seemed nothing short of
a miracle.
When the idea of training semi-literate, unem¬
ployed rural youth to install, maintain and repair
solar units was first put forward by an organiza¬
tion called the Social Work and Research Centre
inTilonia, Rajasthan, engineers and government
officials felt it would never work. They were
convinced the rural poor were too backward and
illiterate to be given so much responsibility. There
was also resistance from contractors and trans¬
porters who supplied DG sets, transmission
wires, poles and diesel, and who stood to lose
their business.
But the response from the villagers was so
enthusiastic that it ground out all opposition.
They were even willing to pay one dollar per
unit per month for solar lighting; paying for such 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
At night, entire families huddled
around a single light no stronger
than a candle flame. Solar lighting
therefore seemed nothing
short of a miracle.
In Tllonia, a village in India's
Rajasthan state, "barefoot
engineers" operate solar
installations and teach young
people about solar energy.
30
SANJIT (BUNKER) ROY
is director of the Social Work
and Research Centre at Tllonia,
Rajasthan state, in northern
India. He is also chairman of the
Environmental Liaison Centre
International (ELCI), a non¬
governmental organization
based in Nairobi.
services, however heavily subsidized, is unheard-
of in Ladakh. So far, nearly $3,000 have been
collected from the 28-village community.
Tsewang Narbo, who was selected for the job
by the village community in June 1993, is now
capable of fabricating invertors devices that con¬
vert direct current into alternating current and
other apparatus, repairing fuses, changing tube
lights, filling batteries with distilled water, and
installing solar units in villages which can only be
reached on foot. (When the SPVs were installed in
1993, the batteries and panels were brought up by
yaks and then airlifted by helicopters of the Indian
Air Force.) His job has so far brought him a total
of $260, a welcome addition to his meagre earnings
from goat farming.
Tilonia's efforts have also brought about a
change in the energy policy of the State Govern¬
ment of Jammu and Kashmir. There are now
about a dozen trained persons like Tsewang
Narbo who look after solar units installed in 500
individual houses in over twenty villages.
Solar pumps bring life to dying villages
The large-scale use of solar energy in India was
first promoted by Pierre Amado, often described
as "a Frenchman with an Indian heart". Amado,
who served as French Cultural Attaché in India
between 1953 and 1960, was so fascinated by
Indian culture that he specialized in the Ganges
Valley civilization and now teaches post-graduate
courses on the subject in Paris.
"As I became older," he explained, "I began to
ask myself: 'I have taken so much from India, but
what have I given back?' I thought the time had
come to pay my debts to India. Since I knew the
villages in the Ganges valley particularly well, I
decided to launch a project there. I talked to sev¬
eral researchers and came to the conclusion that
the use of solar energy for pumping irrigation
water would be most appropriate."
India has over 90 million farmers with small
land holdings. Most of them remain without
water during the summer months. There is water
but no power to pump it and so many farmers are
being forced to migrate to the cities. "I realized
that unless something was done to help these
very tiny hamlets inhabited by very poor people
they would be condemned to underdevelopment
for centuries to come. The villages I am talking
about are not connected to roads and have not
been electrified," says Amado.
In 1979, Pierre Amado launched an associa¬
tion called ASVIN (Application of Solar Voltaics
in Villages in India and Nepal), which in Indian
mythology signifies the twin sons of the sun,
symbolizing agriculture and animal husbandry.
Working with local voluntary organizations in the
villages of Sarwar (Bihar) and Gobalpur (Orissa),
ASVIN has been able to demonstrate that if the
community is taken into confidence during the
planning process, and if local skills are mobi¬
lized, barely literate villagers are capable of
installing, maintaining and repairing solar pumps
for irrigation on their own.
"I remember the ceremony to inaugurate the
solar pumps in the village of Sarwar in Bihar in
1982," says Amado. "The Development Com¬
missioner gave wheat and vegetable seeds to each
family. Since in this region wheat has not tradi¬
tionally been cultivated, I thought the villagers
would either sell the seed or grind it for flour. But
not one of them sold the seed. They told me 'We
want to eat the wheat grown with our solar
water.' I call it harvesting the sun."
* Bharat ¡s the traditional Sanskrit name for India. Editor
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The World Solar Summit
interview with Boris Berkovsky
A solar highway to sustainable development
July 1993 marked the start of Unesco's "World
Solar Summit Process". What is involved in this?
The "World Solar Summit Process" is a cam¬
paign launched as a result of a successful meeting
on the theme of "The sun in the service of
mankind" that was held at UNESCO Headquar¬
ters in July 1993. Experts from all over the world
attended the meeting in a personal capacity and
contributed to highly specialized discussions
on renewable energy sources, including solar
energy. Over sixty assessment reports were pre¬
pared, covering all aspects of research, devel¬
opment, production, marketing and public atti¬
tudes. As a result of these reports, we launched
a campaign with specific projects, targets and
evaluation systems.
What are the goals of the campaign?
They are clear and detailed. The major aims
are to enhance understanding of the role that
renewable energy sources can play in safe¬
guarding the environment; create a global infor¬
mation network using state-of-the-art commu¬
nications technology; promote and harmonize
co-operation in training and research; demon¬
strate that the use of solar energy is a cost-effec¬
tive and rapid way for many developing coun¬
tries to reduce energy costs in remote rural
areas; and to identify and define strategic projects
of exceptional quality and global importance.
In practical terms, what is the field of appli¬
cation of solar energy?
It could be far broader than it is today. Solar
energy is not a miracle solution, but it has not
been widely used until now because of lack of
investment. Solar energy should be given the
place it deserves in the mix of energy sources. It
is available, flexible and ecologically viable.
Considerable progress in exploiting solar energy
has been made, and today it is realistic, not
Utopian, to be optimistic about its prospects.
Where has the most progress been made in the
past few years?
Notable progress has been made in research
and technology. Solar energy has a leading part
to play in all fields where only small amounts of
power are required, especially in remote rural
areas not covered by the grid. In this context, Ol
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
solar energy is being widely used to generate
electricity for telephone systems, and in devel¬
oping countries it is also providing much of the
power for refrigerating vaccines. Solar cookers
have been developed, and after proving their
worth in India, they are now being used in
Nigeria and are being produced locally in other
parts of the world. Solar pumps are increas¬
ingly being used in Mali.
Has North-South co-operation encouraged the
development of new technologies?
The countries of northern and southern
Africa are making growing use of renewable
energy sources, and this means that there must
be a gradual transfer of technology to ensure that
the aid they receive is effective. In the field of
photovoltaic electricity, where the number of
uses is still growing, specialists must be trained
so that solar energy can be rationally used for
pumping water, providing community lighting
in remote villages, refrigeration in dispensaries,
for telecommunications and various other appli¬
cations.
A World Solar Charter is currently being pre¬
pared. What is going into it?
This document is intended to define uni¬
versal principles, rules and procedures of the
World Solar Programme. It will stress a number
of priorities such as the creation of national
infrastructures to act as focal points; the
matching of social and economic development
aspirations in rural areas; development of global
networking systems; and the adoption of new
education and training programmes at all levels.
What will be the next important meeting of the
World Solar Summit process?
The World Solar Programme, which will be
carried out between 1996 and 2005, should be
approved by a World Solar Summit scheduled to
be held in March, 1996 in Harare, on the invi¬
tation of Mr Robert Mugabe, the President of
Zimbabwe. The Summit will put us on a solar
highway towards sustainable development.
Interview by Juliette Boussand
32
BORIS BERK0VSKY
is head of Unesco's Engineering and Technology division, and
president of the organizing committee of the World Solar
Summit.
The new library of Alexandria
'ALEXANDRINA NOVA7:
A STAR IS BORN
In 1988 the Egyptian government, in co-operation with Unesco,
began work on the new library of Alexandria, which will open at the
beginning of the next century. It is designed to meet a threefold pur¬
pose: to foster a spirit of openness, to explore many fields of
knowledge and to render knowledge accessible through state-of-the-
art technology.
Alexandria was predestined to play this role. In Antiquity it was
the site of the first universal library in the history of humanity. As
a crossroads in today's world between the West and the Middle East,
Alexandria will use its new library to become a beacon once again
for the Mediterranean world.
An instrument of knowledge and education like its illustrious
ancestor, the new "Bibliotheca Alexandrina" will be fully comput¬
erized. Its catalogue will gradually become available for consulta¬
tion in the region's universities and information centres. Through
a regional server, researchers throughout the world will be able to
access a data bank containing the library's important collections.
In addition to specialized collections on Mediterranean civiliza¬
tions, the library will contain major collections on science and
technology, environmental issues and economic development. It will
also house an international school for the information sciences.
Strikingly beautiful in its architecture and entirely functional,
the library is being built on the shores of the Mediterranean in the
form of an up-ended cylinder, 160 metres in diameter. Its "roof"
slopes at an angle to counteract the harmful effects of sea spray
and allow the upper floors of the library to enjoy natural light.
The architects have not strictly speaking designed the library
as a solar symbol, but they agree that it is intended as an image of
radiance and openness. From above, its circular form resembles the
sun as generally depicted in ancient Egyptian hieroglyphs. This asso¬
ciation with the solar disk is accentuated by a desire to renew con¬
tact with the universal knowledge and wisdom of the ancient
library and to contribute, through this ultra-modern centre of cultural
and scientific exchange between East and West, to understanding
between peoples and to the construction of peace.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The sun is a star
The sun is a globe of gas that derives its
energy from thermonuclear reactions (the
conversion of hydrogen into helium).
The sun is a star like any other. It appears
brighter because it is nearer.
The elements of which the sun is composed
are the same as those found on earth and
throughout the universe.
THE SUN'S PHYSICAL
CHARACTERISTICS
Diameter: 1,400,000 km
109 times that of the earth
Mass: 2 x 1030 kg
333,000 times that of the earth
Age: 4.5 thousand million years
total life span: 10 thousand million years
Density (compared to water):
average: 1.4
at the core: 160
in the photosphere: 10~9
Energy output:
total: 4 x 1023 kW
received on earth:
if there were no atmosphere: 1,400 W/m2
after passing through the atmosphere:
240 W/m2
Temperature:
at core: 15 million0 K
visible surface
(photosphere): 5,800° K
corona: 1.5 million0 K
Magnetic field:
In the photosphere between 1 gauss (twice
the earth's magnetic field) and 3,000 gauss.
Distance from sun to earth:
149,600,000 kilometres
varying between 147 million km in winter
and 152 million km in summer (for the
northern hemisphere)
Main elements
except in the thermonuclear core:
(percentage in mass)
Hydrogen: 73.5%
Helium: 24.8%
Other elements: 1.7%
including
Oxygen: 46%
Carbon: 17%
Iron: 9%
Neon: 7%
Others: 21%
Source: Palais de la Découverte, Paris
THE SUN'S STRUCTURE
corona chromosphere photosphere North Pole core the radiative zone
prominence sunspots the convective
zone
Source: Le Sole/I, P. Untos. PUF publishers. Paris ('Que sais-je?" serte*)
FURTHER READING
The Sun: Eternal Flame of Creation, compiled and presented by Madanjeet Singh, with a preface
by Federico Mayor, Director-General of Unesco; UNESCO/Thames & Hudson, London, Harry N.
Abrams, Inc., New York, 1993.
The Atmosphere of the Sun, C.J. Durrant, Adam Hilger, Bristol, 1988
Solar Astrophysics *, P.V. Foukal, Wiley, New York, 1990, 496 pp.
An Introduction to Solar Radiation *, M. Iqbal, Academic Press, Toronto, 1983, 370 pp.
Secrets of the Sun, R.G. Giovanelli, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, Mass., 1984
Discovering the Secrets of the Sun, R. Kippenhahn, Wiley, Chichester, 1994
Daytime star, S. Mitten, Charles Scribner's Sons, New York, 1981
Guide to the Sun, K.J.H. Phillips, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, U.K., 1993
Physics of the Solar Corona *, I.S. Shklovskii, Pergamon Press, Oxford, 1965, 475 pp.
The Sun *, M. Stix, Springer Verlag, Berlin, 1989, 400 pp.
The Restless Sun, D.G. Wentzel, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., 1989.
IN FRENCH:
Sous l'étoile Soleil, J.C. Pecker, Fayard, Paris, 1984
L'avenir du Soleil, J.C. Pecker, Hachette, Paris, 1990
Le Soleil est une étoile, J.C Pecker, Presses Pocket, Paris, 1992
Le soleil, P. Lantos, "Que sais-je?" series, PUF, 1994
* indicates more technical works.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY
Building a culture
/see two global threats which are jeopardizing
the future of the world and call for the utmost
vigilance from UNESCO.
The first is the split between North and South,
which is growing wider and can only be gradually
reduced by establishing a genuine world partner¬
ship for development. If this development is to be
genuine, it must be human, in other words it must
be endogenous, sustainable, equitable and con¬
scious of its cultural dimension. Promoting this
kind of development on a worldwide scale will call
for a new sense of solidarity in the international
community and developing much greater synergy
between the organizations and mechanisms
involved internationally.
We should invest less in peace-keeping, for which
countries are traditionally well equipped, and more
in peace-building, which is a much more difficult
exercise, as so many recent events have shown.
The most crucial problem of our time is that of
population growth, which it will only be possible to
control through education and the development of
human resources. By investing in education, espe¬
cially in education for young women, it should be
possible within the space of fifteen years to scale
down the rate of population increase, which is cur¬
rently running at one million persons every four
days. Furthermore, the only way to stem the flow
of emigration, which may in a few years' time
result in violent social upheavals, is to encourage
endogenous development: helping countries to
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
B Y FEDERICO MAYOR
of peace
release their own potential and to encourage the
transfer of knowledge so as to alleviate the poverty
and distress that compel people to leave their own
countries.
The type of human development which Unesco
is advocating and is resolutely encouraging in all
the fields of its competence is not confined to the
economically least privileged countries. The con¬
cepts and principles involved apply as much to the
rich countries as to the poor: as long as the privi¬
leged 20 per cent of the world's population, who
enjoy 80 per cent of the resources it has to offer, are
not prepared to share them and reduce current
inequalities and imbalances, all strategies for the
future will remain empty rhetoric. Human devel¬
opment is not meant for some as opposed to others,
but for everyone. The "haves" must realize that
sharing means giving something up, and the ben¬
eficiaries of aid must realize that only develop¬
ment based on their own talent and natural wealth
will enable them to control their own destiny,
without relinquishing their culture, identity and
history.
The second threat is one that compromises the
peaceful coexistence of different cultures and ethnic
groups. Such coexistence is both a duty and a right.
Here UNESCO has set itself the priority of pro¬
moting a "culture of peace". Accordingly it must
step up its efforts to encourage the development of
a worldwide culture of non-violence, peace and
equity, especially through respect and mutual tol
erance and the consolidation of pluralistic and
open societies that can flourish in a climate of
democracy and respect for human rights.
We start from the central idea that the use of
force to keep the peace is symptomatic of conven¬
tional attitudes and procedures. Force is costly in
terms of economics and human suffering, but it is
a price we have become accustomed to paying. It
must be admitted that the good sense needed to
forestall conflict, to make coexistence and recon¬
ciliation possible, in short to build the defences of
peace, does not yet form part of our "defensive
capability". In the case of most nations, the vision
of the founding fathers of UNESCO, who had just
lived through the horrors of war and genocide,
has not been interpreted as it should have been, by
adopting appropriate domestic and international
instruments. As a result, the prevention of war
does not feature in our budgets or our political
programmes and some, with a short-sightedness
that it is difficult to understand, wonder what ben¬
efits can accrue to them by helping Unesco to
grow and prosper.
The future will depend on those who are capable
of attaching a value to intangible things, who
realize that not everything can be measured in
terms of foreign exchange or can be bought and
sold. As the Spanish poet Antonio Machado warned
us, "only fools confuse value and price". The only
way for us to change course is by attaching value
to good sense, not by paying the price of force.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The Pantheon, Rome's other
symbol by Cécile Duvelle and Mauro Rosi
The Pantheon is one ofRome's oldest, best-preserved and most
popular monuments. It is located in the heart ofthe old city, which
was included on Unesco's World Heritage List in 1 980.
People are sitting round the foun¬
tain. Some are reading, some are
chatting, and even though it is
midwinter some are eating a granita di
caffé con panna (iced coffee topped with
whipped cream), the speciality of a nearby
coffee shop. Here in the Piazza della
Rotonda, a square in the heart of Rome's
historic centre frequented twenty-four
hours a day by strolling tourists, Romans
and the ubiquitous pigeons, people often
sit and relax at the foot of this great
baroque fountain from which water
gushes endlessly and which is topped by
an authentic Egyptian obelisk from a far-
off temple to Isis.
Across the way, ignored as only a
familiar feature of the landscape can be,
stands a monumental circular domed
building the Pantheon which gives
onto the square via a marble and granite
portico more than thirty metres wide. The
passersby seem unaffected by its myste¬
rious presence and the ancient and sacred
aura it exudes despite its excellent state of
preservation. One might even think that all
this puts them at their ease.
The Pantheon has stood there since it
was built in 27 B.C., during the turbulent
period between the fall of the Roman
Republic and the rise of the Empire, when
Julius Caesar's adopted son, Octavius, was
pitted against Antony and Cleopatra,
among others. Some tourist guides refer to
it, after the Coliseum, as "the other symbol
of Rome". It was in the heart ofRome that
the Pantheon was built, was transformed
and survived many centuries of change.
Perhaps because it provides a thread of
continuity it seems such a natural part of
the great city today.
A familiar temple
At first, as its Greek name indicates, the
Pantheon was "the temple ofall the gods".
Its appearance changed over the centuries
to accompany the metamorphoses of
Rome itself as capital of the early and
then the later Empire, of the Western
Roman Empire, as Papal Rome, as the
baroque Rome of the Counter Reforma¬
tion, as the city of the Vatican and, since
1870, as the capital of Italy. Each of these
stages in Rome's history was marked by
momentous events.
36
Opposite page, aerial view of
part of the old city of Rome.
Near centre of photo is the
dome of the church of
Sant'Agnese in Agone on the
Piazza Navona. Higher up is the
dome of the Pantheon, pierced
with a round opening or oculus.
Left, the Pantheon's imposing
façade on the Piazza della
Rotonda. The portico bears the
Inscription: M. AGRIPPA L.F.
COS. TERTIUM. FECIT (Marcus
Agrippa, son of Lucius, consul
for the third time, built this).
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Originally the Pantheon resembled a
Greek temple with a central altar and a
pronaos (or portico). A rectangular
building, it was rebuilt in its present cir¬
cular form by the Emperor Hadrian. The
most radical functional change was intro¬
duced in 609 as a result of a decision by
Pope Boniface IV, who restored it, dedi¬
cated it to Christian worship and named it
Santa Maria dei Martiri (St Mary of the
Martyrs).
The history of the Pantheon has not
been uneventful. Pope UrbanVII ordered it
to be stripped of its bronze statues so that
they could be melted down and used in
the canopy of St Peter's basilica. Later, the
great Counter-Reformation architect
Bernini added what the Romans soon
began to call "donkey's ears", i.e. two small
pinnacles, one at each end of the pediment.
In 1980 the Pantheon and the historical
centre of Rome were added to Unesco's
World Heritage List. The listing was justi¬
fied in the following terms, "Ever since its
foundation, which legend sets in 753 B.C.,
Rome has always been associated with the
history of humanity. The capital of an
empire that dominated the Mediterranean
world for five centuries, it later became
the capital of the Christian world and still
today performs these essential religious
and political functions." The Pantheon,
which wears its 2,000 years so lightly, is a
living historical reality.
Naturally most people are primarily
interested in the Pantheon as a monu-
UNESCO INACTION
HERITAGE
ment and as a museum. It is the eternal
resting-place of the immortals and of a
number of artists and kings, including the
first king ofunited Italy, Victor Emmanuel
II, his son King Humbert I, and Humbert's
queen, Margherita of Savoy. A few years
ago, the prospect of transferring to the
Pantheon the mortal remains of Italy's last
king sparked off controversy in some sec¬
tions of Italian public opinion which has
still not died down. Also in the Pantheon is
the tomb of Raphael, who was long con¬
sidered as the greatest of all painters and
whose genius conferred so much beauty
on Rome. Other major artists interred there
are Giovanni da Udine, Perin del Vaga,
Annibali Carrachi, Taddeo Zuccari and
Baldassare Peruzzi.
A living monument
The Pantheon is also a favourite meeting
place for Romans and for visitors to Rome.
With its apocalyptic traffic jams Rome is a
city where punctuality is always threat¬
ened; the slightest incident can make you
half an hour late for an appointment.
People often arrange to meet in a familiar
place where they can sit and wait. The por¬
tico of the Pantheon with its sixteen tow¬
ering granite columns and its pediment of
white marble provides perfect shelter on a
torrid summer day or during the acquaz-
zoni, the diluvian summer and winter
rain that is so different from London drizzle
and the only slightiy heavier rain of Paris.
People meet there before going to the
cinema, window shopping or talking busi¬
ness. Impeccably groomed young people,
wearing sun glasses from March to October,
gather at the foot of the walls on each side
of the Pantheon. As they sit and wait, they
read the papers, chat and eat ice-cream. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The Pantheon is at the heart of a lively
neighbourhood that does not only live on
its past but is also a centre of commerce,
culture and politics. In this sense Rome's
historical centre is fortunately different
from that of many other cities which, in
Italy and elsewhere, have been destroyed
as living communities and sacrificed on
the altar of their own beauty. So many
places where people live become lifeless
museums dedicated to the past! One day
perhaps we shall decide to protect exam¬
ples of urban beauty from becoming
museum pieces and prevent the impov¬
erishment of life in traditional urban com¬
munities.
Luckily, Rome's historic centre is not a
tourist showcase. Economic life goes on
there independently of the museums and
the visitors. With its pizza stands, its
organic and macrobiotic food shops, its
Zen meditation centre and handicraft
shops, bookshops and jewellers, the Pan¬
theon district bustles with life. On the Via
della Maddalena, there are a number of
excellent and renowned ice-cream shops,
ranging from the innovator who some
wo years ago launched a sensational liquorice
ice-cream, to Giolitti, a temple of tradi¬
tionalism, with its small, round, French-
style tables, elegant and nimble waiters,
and flavours and utensils that have not
changed for a century. Nearby is the Par¬
liament building. The street, paved with
sampietrini, "small sacred stones" or
"small St Peters", is closed to cars but is
used by noisy and acrobatically ridden
mopeds, and horse-drawn carriages filled
with tourists.
In summer the light beige of the Pan¬
theon stonework, mingled with the red
and ochre of the surrounding buildings,
creates an "African" effect that is accentu¬
ated by the greenery that protrudes from
between the stones.
A sublime presence
The Pantheon is a monument, a meeting
place and a refuge, but it is also something
more. It does not stand in splendid isola¬
tion; its mystery gives light and meaning to
everything around it. Not only on the Piazza
della Rotonda, but far beyond in the nanow,
cobbled streets, everything from stray
cats to fashion shops is somehow illumi-
The Pantheon
in figures
DATES
27 B.C.: The Pantheon founded by
Agrippa as a temple to the glory of the
Olympian gods
80 A.D.: First extensive restoration, by
Domitian.
125: Restored by Hadrian. The
Pantheon acquires its extraordinary
coffered dome with an opening (oculus)
at the apex.
609: The Pantheon becomes a
Christian church dedicated to St Mary
of the Martyrs (because of the martyrs'
remains transferred to it from the
catacombs).
1563: Restoration of the great bronze
door.
DIMENSIONS
Portico: 33 metres wide and 15.45
metres deep.
Columns: 12.5 metres high.
Walls: 6.7 metres thick
Dome: 43.3 metres high with the same
diameter
Oculus: 9 metres in diameter.
MATERIALS
Gra lite, marble, brick and bronze.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
nated by its poetic grandeur. As Heidegger
writes in his Holzwege of a Greek temple,
such a building "attributes their essential
characteristics to things and the idea they
have of themselves to people". Around the
Pantheon the mundane and the sublime
intermingle.
But even if the Pantheon did not exist,
Rome's historic centre would still be one of
the world's most beautiful places. All
around are exceptional sites, buildings
and monuments, where imperial Rome,
Renaissance Rome, and the Rome of the
popes and the Risorgimento meet and
overlap. To move away from the Pantheon
is not to elude its mystery. Here beauty is
almost commonplace, an unobtrusive,
silent, discreet companion. In Rome the
past is not a memory. The fountains still
exist, as they did four centuries ago, to
provide drinking water for passersby, to
refresh and bring delight. As in the sev¬
enteenth century the churches are open to
the community and the public at large.
They are Christian temples where mass is
celebrated at least twice a day, centres for
social action and for receiving alms. Hands
in pockets, on bicycles or mopeds, people
go about their business through the
entrancing city, occasionally stopping to sit
down on marble benches that date from
the baroque period and wear their 400
years with panache.
Two minutes away from the Pantheon
is the Piazza Navona, unchanged since
the Counter Reformation. Even closer is
the beautiful church of San Luigi de
Francesi with its Caravaggio paintings. In
the opposite direction is the Piazza della
Minerva, where Stendhal once lived. An
Egyptian obelisk crowned by a small ele¬
phant, ironically called "the chick" by the
Romans, stands in front of the church of
Santa Maria sopra Minerva, a gothic
building housing the tomb of St Catherine
of Siena, and a miniature museum of
painting. Also no more than a few min¬
utes' walk from the Pantheon are the
Palazzo Madama, seat of the Italian Senate,
the Mausoleum of Augustus, the Piazza
di Spagna and the Piazza Sant'Ignazio.
Perhaps this explains why there are so
many well-stocked shoe shops in the
Eternal City.
CECILE DUVELLE AND MAURO ROSI
are staff members of the Unesco Publishing Office.
Opposite page, inside the Pantheon. Its dome Is
one of the world's largest. Light pours in through
the unglazed oculus onto the coffered Interior of
the dome and the walls beneath. Large recesses
adorned with columns once contained statues of
the gods.
Below, Via del Corso, one of Rome's busiest
streets. The 1.5-km-long street owes its name to
the horse races that were once held there.
People meet at the Pantheon
before going to the cinema,
window shoppingor talking
business. Impeccably groomed
youngpeoplegather beneath its
walls, readingnewspapers,
chatting, eating ice-cream.
m -
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
listening
MAMBO MANIA
by Isabelle Leymarie
40
Of African and European parentage, the mambo
is the result of a long cross-cultural journey, an
example of the kind of sensual alchemy which
is a speciality of the Caribbean. Mambo, conga
and bongo were originally Bantu names for
musical instruments that were used in rituals
and gradually became secular. Mambo means
"conversation with the gods" and in Cuba des¬
ignates a sacred song of the Congos, Cubans
of Bantu origin. The Congos have absorbed a
variety of foreign influences and the mambo is
a delicious cocktail of Bantu, Spanish and
Yoruba.
Despite its African resonance, the mambo
can be traced back to an unexpected source,
English country dance, which in the seven¬
teenth century became the contredanse at the
French court and later the contradanza in Spain.
In the eighteenth century the contradanza
reached Cuba where it was known as danza and
became the national dance. Its hold grew with
the arrival of the planters and their slaves who
fled from Haiti after it became independent.
The Haitian blacks added a particularly spicy
syncopation to it called the cinquillo, which is
also found in the tango, itself derived from the
contradanza. Gradually other black elements
found their way into the contradanza, some
titles of whichsuch as "Tu madre es conga"
("Your mother is Congo"), which was played in
1856 in Santiago de Cuba at an aristocratic ball
in honour of General Concha, and "La "negrita"
reflect this blending.
A NEW KIND OF MUSIC
At the end of the nineteenth century the con¬
tradanza threw off its European yoke, and freer,
more spontaneous dancing by couples replaced
the starchy formality of the contredanse. This
new kind of music was known as danzón. In
1877 it had a huge success largely due to
pieces such as "Las alturas de Simpson" by a
young musician from Matanzas, Miguel Failde.
The danzón had several sections, one of which
was a lively coda which musicians soon got in
the habit of improvising. It was played by brass
'MAMBO,
que rico el mambo!'
In the post-war years
the mambo was a euphoric and
voluptuous celebration of the
long-awaited return of freedom.
Many will remember the great
Italian actress Silvana Mangano
dancing the mambo
in the marvellous film of the
same name.
bands or típicas, which gave way in the 1920s
to lighter combos known as charangas, which
featured violins, sometimes a cello, a piano, a
güiro (a grooved calabash scraped with a comb),
a clarinet, a flute, a bass and double drums
adapted from European military drums.
Charangas, notably that of the flautist
Antonio Arcano, flourished in the late 1930s. In
1938 Arcaño's cellist, Orestes López, com¬
posed a danzón he called "Mambo", and in
the coda Arcano introduced elements from the
son, a lively musical genre from Cuba's Ori¬
ente province. As a signal to band members that
they could start their solos, Arcano would call
out, "Mil veces mambo!" (A thousand times
mambo!). Today, in the Latin American music
known as salsa, the mambo is a theme that is
played in unison by the rhythm section and
serves as a transition between two improvised
passages.
Arcano was a talented musician, but it was
his countryman Pérez Prado who was the first
to market his compositions under the name
"mambo", which he popularized as a specific
musical genre. He used jazzier instruments,
including brass and drums. Early in the 1950s
his mambos "Patricia" and "Mambo N° 5" took
Latin America and the United States by storm.
THE TEMPLE OF MAMBO
By the mid-1950s mambo mania had reached
fever pitch. In New York the mambo was played
in a high-strung, sophisticated way that had
the Palladium Ballroom, the famous Broadway
dance-hall, jumping. The Ballroom soon pro¬
claimed itself the "temple of mambo", for the
city's best dancersthe Mambo Aces, "Killer
Joe" Piro, Paulito and Lilón, Louie Máquina
and Cuban Petegave mambo demonstrations
there and made a reputation for their expressive
use of arms, legs, head and hands. There was
fierce rivalry between bands. The bands of
Machito, Tito Puente, Tito Rodriguez and José
Curbelo delighted habitués such as Duke
Ellington, Bob Hope, Marlon Brando, Lena Home
and Dizzy Gillespie, not to mention Afro-Ameri¬
cans, Puerto Ricans, Cubans, Upper East-Side
WASPs and Jews and Italians from Brooklyn.
Class and colour melted away in the incan¬
descent rhythm of the music. Even jazz musi¬
cians such as Erroll Garner, Charlie Parker,
Sonny Rollins and Sonny Stitt fell under the
mambo's charm, as can be heard on the many
latin recordings they made in the 1950s.
In 1954 the cha-cha-cha, a kind of mambo
created by the Cuban violinist Enrique Jorrin, a
member of the Orquesta América charanga,
swept through Havana and New York. Easier to
dance than the mambo, with a squarish beat
and a characteristic hiccup on the third beat, it
spread to Europe, before being dethroned in the
early 1960s by the pachanga and then the
boogaloo.
Since the mambo there has never been a
dance that has given rise to so much unbridled
fantasy and pyrotechnics or reached such
rhythmic rapture. Today it is making a comeback
and bringing a glimmer of paradise regained as
the world again moves to its magical beat, m
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
is a Franco-American musicologist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
SOLVING
THE FOOD/POPULATION
EQUATION
BY LESTER BROWN
Seldom has the world faced an
unfolding emergency whose
dimensions are as clear as the
growing imbalance between food
and people. For our generation, the
challenge is to reverse the deterio¬
rating food situation and achieve a
balance between people and food
that is both humane and sustain¬
able. And this, in turn, depends on
reversing the deteriorating rela¬
tionship between ourselves (cur¬
rently increasing by 90 million per
year) and the natural systems and
resources on which we depend.
It cannot be argued that
resources are not available. Despite
the end of the cold war, the world is
still spending close to $700 billion a
year for military purposes, much of
it designed to deal with threats that
have long since disappeared. Mean¬
while, the United Nations Popula¬
tion Fund (UNFPA), the lead agency
in the effort to stabilize world pop¬
ulation, has an annual budget of
$240 million.
To stop soil
erosion, tree
seedlings are
planted behind a
protective
windbreak of piled
stones
(Burkina Faso).
STABILIZING WORLD POPULATION
Elements ofa global food and pop¬
ulation strategy are, however, begin¬
ning to emerge. In April 1994,
UNFPA sketched the outlines of a
bold effort to stabilize world popu¬
lation at 7.8 billion by the year 2050.
This plan is a broad-based one that
includes family planning, raising
the level of female education and
pressing for equal rights for women
in all societies.
Implementing the proposed
UNFPA Programme of Action
requires an estimated $11.4 billion
for 1996, gradually rising to $14.4
billion by2005. Of this total, roughly
two-thirds is to be mobilized within
developing countries themselves.
The complementary resource flows
from donor countries would
increase to $4.4 billion (1993 dol
lars) in 2000, rising further to $4.8
billion in 2005.
Achieving the UNFPA's fertility
reduction goals requires substan¬
tial increases in female education.
Although the education ofgirls and
women contributes simultaneously
to economic progress and lower fer¬
tility, in many countries, fewer than
half the girls ofprimary-school age
are in class. Almost all governments
have adopted universal primary
education as a goal, but many have
seen their educational system over¬
whelmed by the sheer number of
children entering school. The gov¬
ernments ofhigh-fertility societies
cannot realistically hope to rein in
population growth without broad¬
ening access to education and thus
providing women with options
beyond childbearing.
Fulfilling this social condition
for a more rapid fertility decline will
require a heavy investment in both
school building and teacher
training. Providing elementary edu¬
cation for the estimated 130 mil¬
lion school-age children not now
in school (70 per cent ofwhom are
female) would cost roughly $6.5 bil¬
lion per year. Providing literacy
training for those men and women
who are illiterate and beyond school
age would require an additional
estimated $4 billion per year.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
WO RLD
42
THE SPACE SHUTTLE'S EYE
IN THE SKY
In April 1994 a space radar laboratory
developed by the United States, Germany
and Italy was sent up on the U.S. space
shuttle Endeavour to study the earth's envi¬
ronment. It sent back images of more than
69 million square km of the planet's sur¬
face, including such environmentally-deli¬
cate areas as rain forests in Bolivia and
Brazil, and the Sahara Desert. The radar
can penetrate beneath the tree-tops,
making it possible to map variations in
vegetation, wetlands and flooding under
the forest canopy. The system should also
make it possible to detect patches of crude
oil dumped at sea by ships and even to dis¬
cover new archaeological sites.
THE DESERTIFICATION
CONVENTION
An International Convention to Combat
Desertification was signed at Unesco
Headquarters in Paris on 14 and IS
October 1994. The United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme (UNEP) estimates
that the lives of 900,000 million people in
over 100 countries are threatened because
their land could be transformed into
desert. More than a quarter of the earth's
surface is concerned. According to UNEP.
69% of the world's 5.2 billion hectares of
cultivated dry land have deteriorated and
are in the process of becoming desert.
The figures are 73% for Africa and 70% for
Asia. In the arid zones, i.e. 35% of the
earth's surface, 500,000 hectares of irri¬
gated land become desert each year
because of mineral salts in the water which
leave deposits after evaporation. The poor
countries are anxious. In 1980 an action
programme promised them $2.4 billion,
but they only received $600 million. UNEP
currently estimates that between $ 1 0 bil¬
lion and $22.4 billion will be needed annu¬
ally for the next 20 years to restore fertility
to the drylands. The Convention will come
into force when it has been ratified by 50
states. For further information contact
EorthAction (a network of 1,000 citizen
organizations in 126 countries) 9 White
Lion Street, London NI 9PD, United
Kingdom. Tel.: (44 71) 865 90 09; Fax:
(44 71)278 03 45.
THE BEST COFFEE IS PREDIGESTED!
CERES, the journal of the United Nations
Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
has revealed a disturbing piece of news.
The best coffee grains are not picked from
the bush but picked up from the ground in
the droppings of the luwak (Viverra
musanga). a small cousin of the civet cat
that lives on the coffee plantations of
Indonesia, the world's third largest coffee-
producing nation. Luwaks choose the
ripest, most perfectly formed berries and
eat the sweet husk. But they cannot digest
the beans, which pass through their ali¬
mentary canals almost intact, undergoing
A young
Bangladeshi village
woman
(background) is
taught family
planning
techniques.
MASSIVE REFORESTATION
On the food side of the equation,
major efforts must be made to pro¬
tect the soil- and water-resource base
and increase investment in agricul¬
tural research. At the root of food
scarcity in many developing coun¬
tries is the loss of vegetation from
deforestation, overgrazing and over-
ploughing. As vegetation is
destroyed, rainfall runoff increases,
reducing aquifer recharge, increasing
soil erosion and, in turn, lowering
the inherent productivity of the
ecosystem.
Where firewood is scarce, crop
residues are burned for cooking
fuel, thus depriving the soil of
needed organic matter. Adding trees
to the global forest stock is a valu¬
able investment in our economic
future, whether the goal is to sat¬
isfy the growing firewood needs in
the Third World or to stabilize soil
and water regimes. Accordingly, we
propose as part of a global food
security budget a massive refor¬
estation plan totalling $5.6 billion
a year by the end of the decade.
More than a billion people live in
countries that are already experi¬
encing firewood shortages. Unless
corrective action is taken, that
number will nearly double by the
year 2000. An estimated 55 million
hectares of tree planting will have to
be done to meet the fuelwood
demand expected then. In addition,
anchoring soils and restoring hydro-
logical stability in thousands of
Third World watersheds will require
tree planting on some 100 million
hectares.
SOIL CONSERVATION
Planting trees to restore watersheds,
thereby conserving soil and water,
complements the expenditures on
soil conservation by farmers. To cal¬
culate the cost of a global effort to
stabilize soils, data are used from
the United States, where it is esti¬
mated that roughly $3 billion a year
would be necessary to stabilize soils
on U.S. cropland.
First, it is assumed that one tenth
of the world's cropland cannot sus¬
tain cultivation with any economi¬
cally feasible soil-conserving agri¬
cultural practices roughly the same
proportion as in the United States.
This would equal some 128 million
hectares wordwide. Applying the cost
ofconverting such land to grassland
or woodland in the United States, at
$125 per hectare as a first approxi¬
mation, the global costwould be $16
billion per year. If expenditures to
conserve topsoil on the remaining
erosion-prone cropland another
100 million hectares are compa¬
rable to these, a global programme of
conservation practices enacted by
2000 would cost an additional $8 bil¬
lion annually.
By 2000, when both the crop¬
land conversion programme and
the full range of soil- conserving
practices are in place, global expen¬
ditures to protect the cropland base
would total some $24 billion per
year. Although this is obviously a
large sum, it is less than the U.S.
government has paid farmers to
support crop prices in some years.
As a down-payment on future food
supplies for a world expecting at
least two billion more people, $24
billion is an investment humanity
can ill afford not to make.
At a time when the backlog of
yield-raising technologies is
shrinking, international expendi¬
tures on agricultural research are
diminishing. The urgency of
reversing this trend is obvious. A
remarkably successful international
network of seventeen agricultural
research institutes identifies gaps in
global agricultural research and sys¬
tematically fills them. Despite its
widely recognized success, funding
LESTER BROWN,
ofthe United States, is President ofthe
Worldwatch Institute, a private,
nonprofit environmental research
organization in Washington, D.C.
This article has been extractedfrom
his book Full House, Reassessing the
Earth's Population Carrying Capacity,
written with Hal Kane and published by
Norton & Company, New York and
London, 1994.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
.* .
'Í*¡tJ-»l ,/v~ .-^^*u
of this network has dropped. At a
time when every technological
advance, however small, is needed to
help buy time to slow population
growth, investment in these centres
should be rising, not falling.
FOOD SECURITY AND POLITICAL
STABILITY
In summary, the food security
budget we propose, including
needed expenditures on both sides
of the food/population equation,
would start at $24 billion in 1996,
increasing rapidly to just over $58
billion in the year 2000 and then
grow much more slowly, reaching
$61 billion by 2005. Athough the
budgetwe propose is described as a
food security budget, it is also a
political stability budget an
investment in an environmentally
sustainable, politically stable future.
Aside from the global food secu¬
rity budget, which involves public
expenditures, there are several
needs that are best satisfied by
reforming economic policies,
specifically those that deal with
water efficiency and global
warming. With water becoming
increasingly scarce, future gains in
irrigation depend heavily on the
more efficient use of irrigation
water. The key to this is to remove
the subsidies that provide farmers
with free water or water at a nom¬
inal cost. Only if farmers pay market
costs for water will they make the
needed investments in irrigation
efficiency.
In a related area, much progress
has been made in recent years in
reducing fertilizer subsidies, a prac¬
tice that often led to excessive fer¬
tilizer use and damaging levels of
nutrient runoff into rivers and lakes.
The other area needing major
reform is the tax system, which
should be restructured so that those
who burn fossil fuels pay the full
costs of their use. As it now stands, a
utility company that bums coal pays
only for the costs associated with
extracting and burning it, while
others are left to bear the indirect
costs of air pollution health-care
costs, crop losses and the damage
from acid rain to forests and fresh¬
water lakes. The motorist driving
down the road never pays for the
crop damage in the adjoining fields
caused by pollution from the auto¬
mobile.
Similarly, those who burn fossil
fuels are not paying the costs of
global warming and overall climate
instability. Accordingly we recom¬
mend a restructuring of the tax
system to partially replace income
taxes with taxes on fossil fuels. This
would help offset the inability of
the market to fully incorporate
costs, steering the evolution of the
global energy economy in an envi¬
ronmentally sustainable direction.
A plantation of
eucalyptus trees
near Sucre
(Bolivia).
A little girl at the blackboard in a rural
school in the United Republic of Tanzania.
WORLD
a slight processing that actually improves ^J
their taste. Thirty years ago, the produc¬
tion of the precious beans was from 1.000 |
to 2,000 kg per day. By 1 990, however, one
company that specializes in luwak coffee
was only able to buy about 20 tons a year, ^.
partly because plantation workers had
taken to hunting luwaks for food. Which ^>-
should come first, a good roast or a good ^>
cup of coffee?
LU
FROM SWORD TO PLOUGHSHARE
In a swords-into-ploughshares operation
following the end of the Cold War an
American military reconnaissance plane UJ
has been converted into an environmental
research aircraft. It will be used by the nf
National Center for Atmospheric
Research in Boulder, Colorado. The twin- . _
engine jet can fly at any altitude from sea V«^
level to 20 km in the lower stratosphere
and will study in particular the 1 2 to 18 km
zone, a region not adequately covered by
other research aircraft. The aircraft will
mainly be studying atmospheric chemistry
and climate questions.
AIR POLLUTION: THE PRICE OF
PROGRESS?
Steelworks in the Chinese city of Benxi
employ 140,000 people and turn out excel¬
lent products, but they also cause heavy air
pollution. The city is located in a windless
valley and releases 540 tons of pollutants
into the atmosphere each year. Whereas
the World Health Organization has set a
recommended limit of particles in the air
at 90 u.g/mJ, in Benxi the level reaches
740! Respiratory diseases and lung cancer
affecta third of the population, a far higher
figure than the national average. Air pol¬
lution, made even worse by growing auto¬
mobile traffic, is the most frequent cause
of death in China today. Is this the price of
development?
LINGUA FRANCA
French-speaking environmentalists often
complain that almost all reference works
are in English. Now, as a result of an ini¬
tiative by the French Minister of the Envi¬
ronment a remarkable new book has just
appeared. Entitled La planète Terre entre nos
mains ("Planet Earth in Our Hands"), it
presents the implementation of the Agenda
21 programme set by the Earth Summit
held in Rio de Janeiro in June 1992 and
contains a mass of rarely compiled infor¬
mation and useful addresses, including a list
of video cassettes and organizations that
distribute them.
Contact La Documentation française.
29-3 1 , Quai Voltaire, 75344 Paris Cedex
07. Tel.: (33 I ) 40 1 5 70 00; Fax: (33 I ) 40
15 72 30.
F. B.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
NITIATIVES
U
H
<
Z
LU
LU
CE
Opposite, the
terrifying figure of
"Mr. Aids", created
by Senegalese art-
school students for
ENDA.
44
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions.
ENDA TIERS MONDE, A FRUITFUL THIRD-
WORLD DIALOGUE BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
The international association ENDA Tiers Monde
(Environmental Development Action in the Third
World) is the hub of a network of reflexion,
exchanges and field projects that extends to many parts
of the Third World, from Senegal to Bolivia and from
India to the Caribbean. Set up in 1972, notably with
support from the United Nations Environment Pro¬
gramme (UNEP), it became in 1978 an international
non-profit organization with headquarters in Dakar
(Senegal). Through its efforts, researchers, engineers,
economists, sociologists, educators and communica¬
tions experts offer their services to volunteers, farmers,
city-dwellers and technicians in developing countries,
help them to win respect for their rights, identify their
needs and achieve their goals. ENDA works at grass¬
roots level and does all it can to involve local popula¬
tions in the conception, implementation, management
and control ofdevelopment activities. It promotes local
cultures and the use of local resources, and tries to
resist imported consumption patterns and lifestyles. Its
members are fieldworkers who are more familiar with
village huts than air-conditioned offices and hotels.
IN THE FIELD
In 1990 the people of Dakar and its outskirts were
inspired by the words of a current hit song to start
cleaning up parts of their city and to cover walls with
multicoloured frescoes. A movement known as Set setal,
"be clean and make clean", was launched. ENDAjoined
forces with it an ENDA team was already busy
improving conditions in one of Dakar's slums.
Far away on another continent, in Bogota (Bolivia)
ENDA has created the world's first recycling school,
where children and adults learn about the uses of dif¬
ferent kinds of wastes and are taught techniques for
recycling them. The courses, which began in September
1994, last from six to twelve months and are fee-paying,
although the size of the fee varies according to the
pupil's means. In Rufisque (Senegal), where the local
people were more than willing to pay a small sum to
improve the salubrity of their neighbourhood, ENDA
launched a garbage collection project using wheelbar¬
rows four years ago. The compost produced from the
garbage is sold to urban vegetable gardeners, enabling
them to fertilize their gardens without using chemical
products. Three similar projects are underway in Ho Chi
Minh City (Viet Nam), Santo Domingo (Dominican
Republic) and Bamako (Mali). Know-how and tech¬
nology are imported from Bombay (India), Bogota
(Colombia) and Porto Novo (Benin).
In the Caribbean ENDA is working with a Unesco-
Worldwide Fund for Nature programme on the study of
medicinal plants. Four languages (English, Creole,
French and Spanish) are used in the programme, which
covers fourteen countries. Two competitions involving
the identification and use of medicinal plants have
been held in secondary school leavers' classes in Mau¬
ritius and Dakar.
In Zimbabwe, South Africa and Bolivia, an ENDA
"youth action" team is training street educators to help city
children and teenagers left to their own devices. This
means getting on terms with the street children, helping
them to survive byproviding emergency aid but, above all,
trying to find longer-term solutions to their problems.
In 1987 an ENDA health team joined the fight against
Aids in Africa. It uses every available channel of com¬
munication books, newspapers, comic strips, video,
TV programmes, movies, plays, music and public
events. A telephone help-line has been opened in Dakar.
During major international conferences, ENDA pub¬
lishes a daily newspaper to voice the concerns of the
peoples of the South.
ENDA produces a wide range ofwritten and audio¬
visual documents on environmental and development
issues in English, French and Arabic. For further infor¬
mation contact ENDA Diffusion, 54, rue Carnot, BP 3370
Dakar, Senegal. Tel.: (221) 22 98 90; Fax: (221) 22 26 95.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
global view. . . glob* view.
The Unesco Prize
for the Promotion of the Arts
-*
I In 1993, on the initiative of the Japa-
nese painter Kaii Higashiyama,
Unesco created an international prize for
contemporary art. Awarded biennially,
and known as the Unesco Prize for the
Promotion of the Arts, it is intended to
encourage young artists all over the world
in such fields as painting, the graphic arts,
drama, dance and music.
In 1993 the prize went to a number of
artists working in new technologies
(including video and photography),
painting (including drawing and the
graphic arts) and sculpture (including
"installations", works that explore the rela¬
tionship between people and their envi¬
ronment, and "Land Art", in which the
artist works in and with nature).
Thirty-seven artists were pre-selected
from almost 300 candidates Five winners
were chosen, and four other candidates
received honorary mentions. Charlotte
Gyllenhammar (Sweden) and Osman
(Turkey) shared the prize for sculpture.
The prizewinners in the new technologies
section were Susan Gamble (United
Kingdom) and Michael Wenyon (United
A world encyclopaedia
of music
The International Music Council (IMC) is
preparing to publish the first world history of
music. Produced by an international team of
specialists and entitled The Universe of
Music: A History, the 12-volume work will
cover all musical genres from all periods. The
first volume, dealing with Latin America, is
scheduled for publication in the first half of
1995. The History will be published in Eng¬
lish by the Smithsonian Institution, Wash¬
ington, D.C. (United States), before being
translated into several other languages.
The IMC, a nongovernmental organization
founded in 1949 as a consultative body to
advise Unesco on music, regularly organizes
meetings known as "rostra" to encourage
traditional music, promote exchanges
between the world's musicians and help young
composers and musicians. Scheduled to be
held in 1995 are international rostra for com¬
posers, in Paris; a young musicians' rostrum
in Bratislava (Slovakia); and regional rostra in
Korea, Colombia, Ghana and Tunisia.
The International Music Council, 1, rue
Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France. Tel.:
(33-1)45 68 25 50; Fax: (33-1) 43 06 87 98.
States). Felim Egan (Ireland) won the
award for painting.
The works of the thirty-seven pre¬
selected candidates are featured in a cata¬
logue that has recently been published by
Unesco's Division of the Arts and Cultural
Life. While the selection does not pretend to
provide a panorama of contemporary art
worldwide, it does give what the president
of the jury, Pontus Hulten, calls "a good
general view of the situation and produc¬
tion ofyoung artists in the world today".
The overriding impression is one of a
quest that is both familiar and new.
Familiar, because it continues the path
marked out at the beginning of the century
towards freedom and non-conformity in
the act ofcreation. New, because it delves
even deeper into the realm of invention.
Zodiac, a work by the prizewinners in
the new technologies section, blends ele¬
ments of traditional art-forms (sculpture,
theatre and painting) in a new aesthetic,
while creating on a symbolical level a syn¬
thesis between tradition and innovation.
An easel, the time-honoured tool of the
painter's trade, stands in the middle of a
room that reminds us ofa floodlit stage. It
does not support a canvas but a shim¬
mering horizontal bar which, although it
seems tangible and "real", is actually pure
illusion. It is a hologram, a three-dimen¬
sional image produced by interference
between light from laser beams. This tech¬
nique of using light to create art has been
used for at least two decades without
losing any of its fascination.
Water, as well as light, features among the
works shown. Pose, by the French artist
Emmanuel Saulnier, is made from pyrex
glass, demineralized water and embossed
aluminium. Just as extraordinary is a huge
creation entitled Kabelseele (literally "cable
soul"), into which Swiss artist Walter
Siegfried has introduced the human voice.
Rigid Waves, an original work by German
artists Monika Fleischmann and Wolfgang
Strauss, uses mirrors to put the spectator
literally in the picture as he or she
approaches it.
These creations of light, water, sound,
voice and the human face are works that
live, move and change with their audience.
The challenge set by the new generation
ofartists is to capture the fleeting nature of
experience and to abandon the docility of
stone for less tractable media. Is the static
work of art now a thing of the past?
Zodiac (1989), 4.2 x 160 cm., a hologram on easel
by Susan Gamble (United Kingdom) and Michael
Wenyon (United States), prizewinners in the "new
technologies" category of the Unesco Prize for the
Promotion of the Arts (1993).
Candidates for the 1995 Unesco Prize for the
Promotion of the Arts should contact their
country's National Commission for Unesco.
The catalogue may be obtained from the
Division of the Arts and Cultural Life,
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75732 Paris 07.
Fax: (33-1) 4273-0401.
Hell Extinguisher (1992), 59 x 100 x 85 cm., wire,
sheet iron, assorted materials by Abu Bakkar
Mansaray (Sierra Leone). Honorary mention, Unesco
Prize for the Promotion of the Arts (1993).
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN
action
1 ±1
46
SVALBARD'S GIANT REPTILE
The world's northernmost museum is In Norway's
Svalbard archipelago, which lies only a thousand
kilometres from the North Pole and has a population
of some 3,700. An old barn, a lot of enthusiasm
and a little money were enough to provide a home
for artefacts of great historical interest. The museum
is devoted to both human history, especially that of
whaling, which attracted many Dutch, British, Russian
and Scandinavian fishermen to the islands in the
17th and 18th centuries, and natural history, espe¬
cially the polar bear and other arctic animal, bird and
plant species. The museum's pride and joy is its cast
of a 60-cm.-wide paw print of an iguanodon, a giant
reptile that lived in Svalbard 130 million years ago. A
giant reptile living practically at the North Pole is
enough to set anyone's imagination humming, but the
fact ¡s that the archipelago was once located near the
equator and has slowly drifted northwards.
This and many other stories can be found in the
June 1994 issue (N° 182) of UNESCO's quarterly
Museum International devoted to museums of the Far
North (from America to Greenland and Scandi¬
navia to Russia). Published in English, French, Russian,
Spanish and Arabic.
Q For further information contact Museum Inter¬
national, 7, Place Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07, France.
Tel.: (33-1) 45 68 43 39; Fax: (33-1) 42 73 04 01.
EXPOLANGUES, A VOYAGE OF
LINGUISTIC DISCOVERY
The Unesco Courier and Its 30 language editions will
be taking part in the thirteenth "EXPOLANGUES"
Salon in Paris, which aims to link the study and
practice of foreign languages with the discovery of
others and to encourage contacts between people
speaking different languages. The Salon, which will be
held in the Grande Halle de la Villette, Paris, from 27
January to I February 1995, provides the opportu¬
nity for an intercultural encounter based on the
idea that "the voyage that all students of language are
invited to make is primarily a voyage of emigration
from oneself".
a For further information contact OIP, 62, rue de
Miromesnil 75008 Paris. Tel.: (33-1) 49 53 27 60; Fax:
(33-1)49 53 27 88.
SCHOOLS FOR TOLERANCE
Wishing to give "a major priority in education to
young people, who are particularly vulnerable to
intolerance, racism and xenophobia", some 100
ministers of education and other officials who took
part in the International Conference on Education in
Geneva last October agreed to take steps to
encourage the practice of tolerance in schools.
Among the measures envisaged are including lessons
WOLE SOYINKA,
UNESCO GOODWILL AMBASSADOR
The Nigerian writer Wole Soyinka, Africa's
first winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature
(1986), was named a Unesco Goodwill
Ambassador on 21 October 1994. "His
work in defence of freedom and human
rights makes him particularly qualified
to help Unesco promote its programmes in
culture and communication," said Mr
Federico Mayor, Director-General of Unesco.
On 3 November, Wole Soyinka's United
Nations laissez-passer (allowing him free exit
from his country) was confiscated by the
Nigerian authorities, provoking an immediate
protest from the Director-General. On
arriving in Paris after clandestinely leaving
Nigeria, Wole Soyinka thanked Unesco for
aiding his efforts to leave his country, during
a press conference organized at Unesco
Headquarters on 2 1 November by the Inter¬
national Parliament of Writers.
on peace, human rights and racism in curricula at all
levels; eliminating negative stereotypes and distorted
views of others from textbooks; encouraging demo¬
cratic school management involving teachers, pupils,
parents and the local community; reforming teacher
training by encouraging the participation of experi¬
enced personnel in human rights and democracy; and
developing media education to prepare children for
a critical analysis of information. The next Interna¬
tional Conference on Education, in 1 996, will focus
on the role of teachers confronted by social and edu¬
cational change.
INDEX TRANSLATIONUM
ON CD-ROM
The first CD-ROM edition of Index Translationum,
Unesco's guide to world translations, has just been
issued and will now replace the paper edition. The
Index provides a cumulative list of works translated
and published since 1 979 in more than 1 00 countries
and covering every field (literature, social and human
sciences, basic and natural sciences, art, history,
etc.). It is a valuable instrument for rapid retrieval of
references to works by more than 1 50,000 authors.
Each entry includes name of author, title of the
translation, name of translator and publisher, year of
publication, original language, and number of pages.
Also included is a trilingual (English/French/Spanish)
user's guide. The disk may be used in a network.
H Index Translationum, CD-ROM, 1994, (Unesco
Reference Books), ISBN 92-3-0022962-9, 1,100
French francs (airmail postage included).
PRESERVING AMERINDIAN
LANGUAGES
Two books that preserve and celebrate the
Amerindian languages of Peru and Mexico have
recently been published with Unesco support. Both
are by 1 6th-century Spanish Catholic missionaries
who studied the languages of the indigenous popu¬
lation in order to understand and convert them.
The first, Arte de la lengua mexicana (1547, "The
Art of the Mexican Language") by Brother Andrés
de Olmos, is published with a critical interpretation
by Asención and Miguel León-Portilla, who are
leading specialists in the Náhuatl language. The
second, written by Brother Domingo de Santo
Tomás, is Gramática o Arte de la Lengua General de los
Indios de los Reynos del Perú ( 1 560, "Grammar or Art
of the General Language of the Indians of the King¬
doms of Peru"). It is accompanied by an explanatory
supplement by a linguist, Rodolfo Cerrón-Palomino.
Both books have been published under the spon¬
sorship of the Spanish Agency for International Co¬
operation, the Instituto de Cooperación Iberoameri¬
cana and Unesco.
120 ARTISTS MOBILIZE FOR
BOSNIA
A UNESCO-sponsored travelling exhibition entitled
"Images for peace: a painting, a symbol", presents 1 20
works by contemporary European painters, sculptors
and photographers. Each work in the exhibition,
which is the brainchild of a French association named
"Des images pour la paix", has been donated by its
creator to the Sarajevo museum. This cultural and
humanitarian gesture is intended to demonstrate the
artists' solidarity with the artists of Bosnia and to help
to maintain the tradition of freedom of expression
and receptivity to the outside world in this war-
torn country. Inaugurated in Paris at the end of
1994, the exhibition will be shown in several other
cities in France and elsewhere in Europe (including
Antwerp, Barcelona, Berlin, Geneva and Lisbon).
"Des ¡mages pour la paix", 27 rue de Charonne,
7501 1 Paris. Tel. and Fax.: (33 I) 48 07 07 79.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Johan Bojer Men oflittlefaith
The letter published below appeared in Correspondance, thejournal ofthe
International Institute ofIntellectual Co-operation, in 1934. In it the Norwegian
novelistJohan Bojer (1872-1959) spells out the dangers ofa divorce between public
and private morality. His letter is a reply to thatfrom the Chinese thinker Cai
Yuanpei which was published in our December 1994 issue ('Religion and politics
today', page 46).
To Mr. Cai Yuanpei
Dear Sir,
Oslo
You say that Chinese thinkers are
extremely astonished by the idea
that there should be one form of
morality for the private individual and
another for the state. And you call upon all
those who wish to work for better co-ordi¬
nation between the countries to organise
their own lives so that they can provide a
model of this.
If I understand you correctly, you mean
that the world political and economic crisis
can be reduced to a question of individual
morality.
That reminds me of something that a
Chinese philosopher wrote some thirty
years ago about Western civilization. He
stressed that the Christian countries have
constructed a vast system which com¬
prises a God in heaven, a devil in hell, and
a third God who saved men by dying for
them, whereas a thoughtful Chinese
believes that the highest thing a man can
aspire to is to behave well.
But it might well be asked: "What is
meant by the expression to behave weW.
On this point Chinese wisdom and the
Christian religion agree. To do unto others
wit
Text selected by Edgardo Canton
as you would have them do unto you. Con¬
fucius and Jesus Christ both believe that it
is only by starting from the individual that
the world can be improved. Start with
yourself.
They would certainly not be happy if
they were told: start with your own
country.
This is because the great ideals are
readily thought to be something unreal
something that can be discussed or pro¬
fessed and even written into an electoral
programme. But who will accept that they
commit him personally?
And so we have pacifists who wage war,
priests who believe in the religion of
charity but sow hatred of a neighbouring
people and incite to vengeance and vio¬
lence, and socialists who curse capitalism
in public speeches but are themselves mil¬
lionaires and live in great houses. One of
the first things young people learn from
their elders is: preach some great and
noble idea but you will only practise it if
you are a simpleton.
In 1914 there were two world powers
which could have stopped the war. One
was the Church, the other was socialism.
Both had the duty to curb hatred between
peoples and to assert that all men are
brothers, in spite of frontiers. Both failed to
do their duty. The two camps threw them¬
selves into the slaughter.
A state does not need
to behave well
A congress was held to lay the founda¬
tions for lasting peace, and at the same
time surreptitious preparations were made
for war. The delegates were suspicious of
each other, knowing that it is praiseworthy
to lie, deceive and commit perjury when
you do so in the name of your country.
The person who utters the finest words
about peace is perhaps the representative
of an arms factory and makes a fortune
Christ the King, a mural painting
(12th-13th centuries) in the Roman crypt of the
cathedral of St. Etienne, Auxerre (France).
through war. We have reached the point
where a man can feel delighted by another
man's success while a state is jealous of
others. A decision whose purpose is to be
useful to everyone makes a patriot furious.
How? Would his own country not profit
from it? If the world can be saved from a
new catastrophe by the disarmament of
his own country, whose military power
and prestige will perhaps be slightly
reduced, this patriot is indignant. What
treachery! Let the rest of the world go to the
devil as long as your own country is on
the winning side. A state does not need to
behave well.
Is it forces outside mankind that are
sending us the next war, that black cloud
on the horizon which fills our nights with
bloody ghosts? No! So can't men do any¬
thing about it? They don't dare. So do they
want war? No . . . and yet . . they do.
For our thinking is chaotic. We profess
humanism and venerate brute force. We
love our brothers, and hate them too. We
like to build, but we also like to destroy. The
Christian believes and does not believe
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
ARCHIVES anniversary Louis
48
in his doctrine. He talks movinglywhen he
accuses capitalism of causing wars
between peoples; but he preaches civil
war himself.
A scientist may be pious and go to
church on Sunday, but work for six days a
week on the development of a new gas
that will destroy a city in a few seconds. For
he believes in God, and he does not believe
in God.
Take a Christian pacifist who fought
againstweapons while he was in the oppo¬
sition. Make him prime minister and
everything changes. He has to choose
between his own convictions and the
machine. His country has become great
and powerful because ofwars. It must arm
indefinitely to preserve its gains. Can the
pacifist stop armament? No, he does not
even want to do so. He also has tradition in
his mind. He continues to manufacture
guns, bombs and tanks. Nothing has
changed.
We lack faith and we lack confidence.
We do not believe in political parties
whose programmes are as garish as neon-
lit advertisements. We do not believe in
the press, for we know that it sows hatred
and lies, with the sole aim of increasing
sales. We do not believe in parliamentar¬
ians with their stock-in-trade of convic¬
tions, nor even in priests who all too often
adapt their God to the needs of the gov¬
ernment.
However, the glimmerings ofa renais¬
sance are starting to appear. The Oxford
Movement, for example, is a peaceful rev¬
olution against torpid Christianity and
spineless idealism. It is Christian without
building churches, formulating dogma or
electing popes. It knows no frontiers and
does not divide men into races or classes.
Its religion is action. Its highest duty is to
carry out God's will, that is to behave well.
When this movement, which is
spreading more quickly than most people
think, reaches parliamentarians and gov¬
ernments, we shall see even politicians
feel confidence in each other, the disar¬
mament conference will not end in an
arms race and even states will start to
behave well.
Hoping, dear sir, that you will excuse a
peasant from such a small country as
Norway, who has taken upon himself to
impose on your time, I remain
Your respectful admirer,
JOIIAN BOJER
* The Oxford Group or Moral Rearmament
Movement was founded in the 1920s by
Frank Buchman (1878-1961), who launched a
worldwide evangelistic campaign for moral
and spiritual revival based on God's
guidance, moral absolutes and the "life-
changing" of individuals through personal
work.
Apioneer ofthe modem era in medical sci¬
ence, Louis Pasteur died a hundred years
ago, in 1895. Among his many great contri¬
butions to knowledge, he showed that micro¬
organisms cause fermentation and disease
and developed vaccines for rabies and
anthrax.
Iouis Pasteur was one of the
greatest scientists of the late
nineteenth century. By cre¬
ating the field of bacteriology, he
revolutionized medical science. His
discovery of the microbial cause of
disease led to the introduction of
asepsis in surgery (the sterilization
of surgical instruments) and made
possible the manufacture of vac¬
cines. By establishing the Pasteur
Institute at the end of his life, he
also began a tradition of research
and prevention that has had a far-
reaching influence on Western
medicine in the twentieth century.
He was born in 1822 at Dole in
eastern France, and spent his child¬
hood in the nearby wine-growing
town of Arbois where his father, a
tanner, set up in business in 1826.
His secondary education took place
in Besançon where he was no more
than an average student. In 1843,
however, he entered the prestigious
Ecole Normale Supérieure in Paris.
Around this time his work on polar¬
ized light led him to an important
discovery that made his name. He
noticed that the crystals of tartaric
acid, a salt found in wine deposits,
are assymmetric. He also discov¬
ered that living organisms, espe¬
cially in the fermentation process,
tend to produce molecules that are
optically active. Studying the mole¬
cular structure of crystals more
closely, he was led to differentiate
organic from mineral substances.
Starting out from chemistry, he had
already reached the frontiers and
mysteries of biology.
The researcher
Pasteur obtained his doctorate in
chemistry and physics in 1 847, and
in the following year was appointed
professor of chemistry at the Uni¬
versity of Strasbourg. In 1854 he
became dean ofthe science faculty
at the University of Lille, where he
began to study the fermentation of
milk and alcohol. By asking such
questions as how fermenting agents
work on matter and where the
microbes responsible for fermen¬
tation originate, Pasteur was exam¬
ining the still-unresolved question
of spontaneous generation, the
theory that living organisms arise
from nonliving matter. This theory,
championed by Félix-Archimède
Pouchet, director of the Museum of
Natural History in Rouen, and
others, was disproved by Pasteur.
In 1862 Pasteur became inter¬
ested in the formation of vinegar,
and in the following year studied
the different forms ofdeterioration
in wine. These studies led him to
discover a way of preserving food
by heating it below boiling point,
thus preventing fermentation. This
process, known as pasteurization,
caused a revolution in the food
industry.
From studying the microbes
responsible for fermentation to the
study of those that cause contagious
diseases was a short step, one that
Pasteur took in 1865 when he began
a mission that led to the isolation of
bacilli causing diseases that were
decimating silkworms in the south
ofFrance and to the development of
methods of preventing contagion.
In 1868, at the age of forty-six,
Pasteur was semi-paralyzed by a
stroke. In a lesser man this might
have spelled the end of a brilliant
career, but Pasteur was soon back at
work. In 1871 he applied pasteur¬
ization to the preservation of beer
and solved the storage problems
experienced by the brewing
industry. In 1873 he was elected a
member of France's National
Academy of Medicine
After 1877 Pasteur, working in
close collaboration with Charles
Chamberland and Emile Roux,
devoted most of his time to the
study of contagious diseases in the
higher mammals. Using findings by
C. J. Davaine, who had already iso¬
lated the infectious agent, he turned
his attention to anthrax, a deadly
disease in sheep and other animals,
and eventually developed a vaccine
against it. In 1879 he began to study
chicken cholera and established
procedures that served as a model
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
i A ü 1 Ë U K, scientist and humanist by Louise LLambrichs
A portrait of
Louis Pasteur
dating from 1845.
A LIFETIME OF RESEARCH AND DISCOVERY
1847-1849: Pasteur's work on crystals form the basis of
stereochemistry, the study of the spatial arrangement of
atoms in molecules.
1853-1857: studies fermentation, especially alcoholic and
lactic fermentation.
1863-1871: develops "pasteurization", a method of
enhancing the keeping qualities of liquid foods or beverages,
which he applies to wine and beer.
He demonstrates the infectious and hereditary nature of
pébrine, a disease affecting silkworms, and invents a system
of selective breeding, thus saving the French silk industry.
1871-1879: research into ways of treating infectious
diseases; he identifies the anthrax bacterium; the bacterium
responsible for gas gangrene; the staphylococcus and
streptococcus bacteria; the chicken cholera bacillus.
1880: He produces a successful inoculation material against
anthrax, a disease of animals and people.
1885: first successful inoculation against rabies.
1888: foundation of the Pasteur Institute in Paris.
for his method of vaccination. His
research into anthrax led him to dis¬
cover the bacillus that is respon¬
sible for gangrenous blood-poi¬
soning. Later he isolated the
microbe subsequently known as
staphylococcus, which leads to the
formation of pus, boils and
osteomyelitis, an inflammation of
the bones and bone-marrow. This
discovery revolutionized accepted
medical theory, for pus had often
been considered as part of the
healing process rather than a patho¬
logical symptom.
Turning his attention to puer¬
peral fever, which caused the death
of many women after childbirth,
Pasteur showed that its origins were
microbial and convinced doctors
and surgeons of the importance of
asepsis. The practice whereby doc¬
tors sterilize their instruments and
wash their hands before exami-
nating patients, a direct result of
Pasteur's researches, brought about
a dramatic reduction in hospital
mortality rates.
A benefactor of humanity
In 1881, at the height of his fame,
Pasteur was elected to the French
Academy. He now began to investi
gate rabies. After years of false starts
and dashed hopes in the study of
this terrible disease, his discovery of
a vaccine against it crowned his life's
work and has been widely regarded
by posterity as the symbol of his
achievements. About the same time
Pasteur began a subscription cam¬
paign for the foundation of the
research institute that would bear
his name. Eventually, branches of
the Pasteur Institute would be
established in many parts of the
world, where they became a training
ground for researchers involved in
the struggle against contagious dis¬
eases and the search for increas¬
ingly effective vaccines.
When, on 28 September 1895,
Louis Pasteur died in Villeneuve-
L'Etang, near Paris, he was mourned
by the entire nation. The press paid
lavish tribute to a "secular saint",
and he was buried with full national
honours.
What is so remarkable about Pas¬
teur is not only the breadth of his
approach but the fact that his work
had a decisive impact in so many
fields. He was not a dilettante or a
brilliant jack-of-all-trades but a rig¬
orous scientist with prodigious
powers ofsynthesis. Science for Pas
teur was one and indivisible. He
made light of the boundaries
between disciplines, and approached
all the problems he studied in the
same way, attempting to discover
their hidden mechanisms and to
reveal, through the laws that govern
them, the inner logic that links living
and nonliving phenomena.
Pasteur was the living symbol
of the scientific progress that at the
end of the nineteenth century
seemed capable not only of con¬
quering mortal diseases but of pro¬
moting the welfare of individuals
and society. One ofPasteur's greatest
strengths was his ability to defend
the interests of science in the corri¬
dors of power. Unlike his mentor,
Claude Bernard, who always main¬
tained a low profile, Pasteur was
convinced that the battle for sci¬
ence should be waged on the polit¬
ical front as well as in the labora¬
tory. In this respect he was
astonishingly modern.
LOUISE L. LAMBRICHS
is a French writer and philosopher whose
published works include La dyslexie en
question (1989) and (with Dr. Fabrice Dutot)
Les Fractures de l'âme (1988).
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
r ETTERS TO THE EDITOR
50
Genetic diseases and racism
When I read your September 1994 issue on
bioethics I was amazed to discover (on pages
14-15) that certain hereditary diseases occur
frequently among Jews. Could you give me
more information about this?
Marie-Reine Boureau
Bléneau (France)
I learn from your issue on bioethics that
Gaucher's disease and Tay-Sachs disease
occur particularly often among Ashkenazi
Jews and, in the latter case, among French
Canadians.
I fee] unhappy about these racial refer¬
ences in a bio-medical context and would
like to know more.
Jean Chollet
Thésée
(France)
Genetic diseases are inherited. All popula¬
tions may carry particular genetic diseases
as the resultofaccidental mutation or because
ofa mutation's advantage in certain envi¬
ronments.
If a mutation occurs in a relatively iso¬
lated and rapidly expanding population
group (AshkenaziJews orFrench Canadians),
then that group may suffer from a much
higher risk of the disorder. Such has been
found to be the case with Gaucher's and Tay-
Sachs diseases.
Research on genetic disorders has resulted
in successful preventive medicine. In Sar¬
dinia and Cyprus, for example, the popula¬
tions concerned have welcomed information
allowingavoidance ofthe genetic risk oftha-
lassaemia, a hereditaryform ofanaemia. As
a result, the incidence of thalassaemia has
been dramatically reduced.
It would be shameful to give up the cura¬
tive and preventive power ofmodern genetics
through fear of racism. Equally, we must
avoid eugenic misuse ofgenetics: that is one
ofthe most important tasks to which Unesco
is dedicated.
David Shapiro
Executive Secretary
The Nuffield Council on Bioethics
London (U.K.)
Member of Unesco's International Bioethics
Committee
The Casse-cou Steps
I should like to correct the caption to the
last photo illustrating the excellent article
on the city of Quebec which appeared in
your May 1994 issue {A new look at the history
ofcommunism). The photo actually shows
rue Petit-Champlain, not rue Notre-Dame as
indicated in the caption. Above this street,
the oldest in the country, are the famous
"Casse-cou Steps".
Yves Laberge
Sainte-Foy, Quebec
Official abolitions of slavery
Congratulations on your excellent issue on
slavery (October 1994), aptly described on
the cover as "a crime without punishment".
The dates which you give in your
chronology of the official abolition on page
30 clearly show how long it took before
awareness of this evil phenomenon spread
around the world.
I should like to make a correction with
regard to Argentina. Although it is true that
slavery was abolished there in the constitu¬
tion of 1853, the first official act of abolition
dates from 1813, when the Constituent
Assembly proclaimed what was called "lib¬
ertad de vientras" ("freedom ofthe womb") .
After that date all children (including those
of slaves) were born free, and anyone who
arrived in the country also automatically
became free.
M. Milchberg
Paris
(France)
Thankyoufor this interesting piece ofinfor¬
mation. As you point out, our chronology
was restricted to measures of abolition
adopted by countries on a constitutional
basis. Editor
Rethinking economic
development
On rereading the interview with Jean
Malaurie in your April 1994 issue {Modern
management and local traditions), I was
struck by what he said about the inevitable
nature ofworld economic activity.
He makes me think of the proverb
(Indian, I believe), which says, "Ifyou give a
man a kilo ofgrain you will feed him for a day.
If you give him a sack of grain you will feed
him for a month. If you teach him to grow
wheat, you will feed him all his life", but in
that case, I would add, "the wheat-farmers of
the Middle West would not be able to sell
their wheat to the Indians".
Isn't this the biggest paradox ofour time?
We want to help the developing countries
by bringing them Western technology, with
the attendant risk of cutting them off from
their roots and the certainty of closing their
markets to our products, which they will
manufacture themselves and try to export.
How can the leaders of Europe, and
above all those of the seven most industri¬
alized countries, be made to understand
that economic development should be envis¬
aged on a world scale?
I think that this is bound to be, in the
early twenty- first century, the major debate
on economics and culture.
Paul Marguin
Chaudes-Aigues
(France)
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: Ken Ross © Viesti Associ-
ates/ASK, Paris. Cover (inset), pages 3, 13
(below), 1 9 (above): © Madanjeet Singh,
Paris. Page 5: Tim O'Sullivan-FSP © Gamma,
Paris. Page 7: Frédéric Reglain © Gamma,
Paris. Page 8:©Jisas/Lockheed/S.P.L/Cosmos,
Paris. Page 9 (right): © Jack Finch/S.P.L./
Cosmos, Paris. Page 9 (below): © Nigel
Scott/S.RL/Cosmos, Paris. Page 1 0: © Julian
Baum/S.RL./Cosmos, Paris. Page I l:©Jürgen
Liepe, Egyptian Museum, Cairo. Page 1 2: ©
Louvre Museum, Paris. Pages 1 3 (above), 23,
24 (above): © Charles Lénars, Paris. Page 1 4
(above): © Staatliches Museum, Berlin. Page
1 4 (below): © Vladimir Terebenin, Hermitage
Museum, St Petersburg. Page 1 5 (above left):
Marco © Ask Images, Paris. Page 1 5 (right):
© Hidesaburo Hagiwara. Page I 5 (below), 1 7
(middle): All rights reserved. Page 16
(above): © Serge Domingie/Marco Rabatti,
Uffizi Museum, Florence. Page 1 6 (below): ©
Karidin Akmataliyev. Page 1 7 (above): © Dagli
Orti, Paris. Page 1 7 (below): © Khojeste Mis-
tree, Zoroastrian Studies, Bombay. Page 18
(above): © Robert Polidori. Page 18
(middle): © Roland and Sabrina Michaud/
Rapho, Paris. Page 1 8 (below): © Madanjeet
Singh, Sarnath Museum, Varanasi, India. Page 1 9
(middle): © Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris. Page
19 (below): © Mary Ellen Miller. Page 20
(above left): © Dagli Orti, National Museum
of Ethnography, Indonesia. Pages 20 (above
right), 21 (below), 22 (above): ©Jean-Loup
Charmet, Bibliothèque des Arts Décoratifs,
Paris. Page 20 (below): © Francesco Venturi,
DEA Publishing, London. Page 21 (above):
© Guy Notte, Paris. Page 22 (below): ©
Krzysztof Pawlowski. Page 24 (below): Orban
© Sygma, Paris. Page 25: Georg Gerster ©
Rapho, Paris. Page 26 (above): © Panos Pic¬
tures, London. Page 26 (below), 43 (above):
Sean Sprague © Panos Pictures, London. Page
27: Penny Tweedie © Panos Pictures, London.
Pages 28 (left), 42: Paul Harrison © Panos Pic¬
tures, London. Page 28 (above right): J. M.
Charles © Rapho, Paris. Page 28 (below
right): John Miles © Panos Pictures, London.
Page 29: © Pierre Amado, CNRS, Paris. Page
30: © S.N.R.C, Tilonia. Page 32: Unesco.
Page 33: David Hardy © S.P.L/Cosmos, Paris.
Page 34: UNESCO-lnes Forbes. Pages 34-35:
Joel Damase © Explorer, Paris. Page 36: John
Ross © Rapho, Paris. Pages 37, 39: Giansanti
© Sygma, Paris. Page 38: Bertinetti © Rapho,
Paris. Page 4 1 : Jeremy Hartley © Panos Pic¬
tures, London. Page 43 (below): J. R Degas and
Parra © Ask Images, Paris. Page 44: © Enda,
Paris. Page 45 (above): © Wenyon and
Gamble, London. Page 45 (below): Claude
Postel ©C.AA.C. 1 994, Jean Pigozzi Collection,
Paris. Page 47: F. Jalain © Explorer, Paris. Page
49: © Dagli Orti, Paris, Maison Natale de Louis
Pasteur.
Photo inset on cover and photos on pages
1 1, 12, 13 (below), 14, IS (right), 1 5 (below left),
1 6 (below), 1 7 (below), 18 (above), 1 8 (middle),
1 8 (below), 1 9 (above), 1 9 (below), 20 (below),
22 (below) are taken from The Sun: Eternal
Flame of Creation, compiled and presented by
Madanjeet Singh, UNESCO/Thames & Hudson,
London/Harry N Abrams, Inc., New York.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
13,hEXP0LANGUES
International Exhibition for Languages, Cultures of the world and Travel
Teaching
Publishing
Translation
Study abroad
Computer i
Equipment
Travels
27th January
to 1st February 95
Grande Halle
de la Villette
Paris
Germany
Honorary host
1995
Cultures of the world
Embassies,
Publishing cultural centres
French publishers Cultural organisations
Publishers from outside R.e?!.on,s . _ .
France Media (press, radio, TV)
Foreign language or . Travel
specialised bookshops Rail and sea companies |
Libraries Airlines
Teaching press Travel agencies
Tourist Information
Teaching centres,
Pre-school teaching
Schools, universities, THE VISITORS
polytechnics Pupils, students,
Study abroad 3eneral Public wi,h
Study visits In France, an interest in languages |
and in other countries Teachers interpreters,
French as a foreign translators
language Publishers, booksellers
Specialists in linguistics
Language Administrative officials
and business Officials of educational
Training systems
Language engineering Company management
Equipment Vocation training
Translation and officials
interpreting Work council officials
TRADE DAY FRIDAY JANUARY 27th - 2 to 8 pm
To receive a registration form, please return this attached
coupon to 0IP 62, rue de Mlromesnll 75008 Paris - France
Tel. : (33-1 ) 49 53 27 60 Fax : (33-1 ) 49 53 27 88
Name	First name	
Company name
Address
	Tel	
Company activity	
Courrier de runesco
la grande halle
Unesco Courier
subscribers: offer your
friends-and yourself-copies
of this new publication
"What happened to
development?"
From 40 internationally-known specialists, the latest thinking
on the problems of development in the world today.
In June 1994 Unesco organized an international symposium
on the theme "What happened to development?"
Participants: President François Mitterrand, Unesco's
Director-General Federico Mayor and some forty intellectuals,
researchers, economists and experts on development.
"What happened to development?" contains resumes
of the participants' contributions and a synthesis of the dis¬
cussions. A 90-page round-up of current ideas on the prob¬
lems associated with development today, in the North and in
the South.
Special price for Unesco Courier subscribers: 40 French francs
(postage included)
Regular price: 60 French francs (postage included)
Send your order with your remittance, made payable to The
Unesco Courier 31 rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris Cedex 15,
France
3617 GENEALOGY
CHAMPAGNE
ARDENNES
Dressez votre généalogie
grâce à des millions d'actes
de naissance, actes de décès
et actes de mariage
consultables
sur minitel.
Ces informations sont
mises à votre disposition
en accord avec les Cercles
généalogiques
des régions présentes.
AUVERGNE
LORRAINE
3617 GENEALOGY
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Ml
OURIER
AND
! Wife
! TAHAR BEN JELLOUN
I JEAN DANIEL
RÉGIS DEBRAY
MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
SUDHIR KAKAR
RASHEEDUDDIN KHAN
S EHSAN NARAGHI
ME
three good reasons
for offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and'
tomorrow
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity ofworld culture and
knowledge
ft associates its readers with UNESCO's mission of furthering "universal respect
for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms.. .without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
THEME
OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(FEBRUARY 1 90S):
COMMUNICATIONS
INTERVIEW
WITH THE FRENCH WRITER AND PHILOSOPHER
RÉGIS DEBRAY
ENVIRONMENT
ROAD TRAFFIC AND CLEAN AIR¬
AN INCOMPATIBLE COUPLE!
HERITAGE
THE INDIAN TEMPLE OF TANjAVUR
]]>
</page>
</document>
