<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="099251eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
OURIER
¿ Jv V
AND
)
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN
JEAN DANIEL
RÉGIS DEBRAY
MAHMOUD HUSSEIN
SUDHIR KAKAR
RASHEEDUDDIN KHAN
ADAM MICHNIK
V
-\
R KTJil ihvJ.V
m à
S&.
¿%.
[V T ^.
9412 22,00 F t.
	Hill
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some
striking connection or
resemblance. Please add a
short caption to all
photographs.
' ' .vr* i
Im
¿^
.v** »o;
*
Untitled
1 992, oil painting ( 1 0 x 15 cm.)
by Dominique Baroux
"With my subscription I am enclosing this gift I made
to thank you for all the wonderful picture ideas your magazine
gives me," writes French artist Dominique Baroux, who has
sent us this small pointillist painting. Fascinated by Persian art
because it reminds her of the embroidery she did in her
childhood, the artist has used needles and sharpened bamboo
to place fine dots of oil paint on paper. The effect "resembles
grains of sand or tiny pearls," says the artist. "My work is only
the end product of long inner questioning, rhythm, prayer and
meditation."
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
DECEMBER 1994
Cover:
Extremists destroy the mosque at
Ayodhya in India's Uttar Pradesh
state on 6 December 1992,
fomenting violent, confrontations
between Muslims and Hindus.
5 Interview with Wolf Lepenies
36 HERITAGE
The splendour of Spis
by Edouard Bailby
41 GREENWATCH
The sea's dwindling harvest
by France Bequette
34 UNESCO IN ACTION
40 PORTRAIT
Hryhoriy Skovoroda
An Enlightenment philosopher of the Ukraine
by Tatiana Zolozova
45 GLOBAL VIEW
S.O.S. Children
46 ARCHIVES
World peace begins at home
by Cai Yuanpei
48 ANNIVERSARY
José Carlos Mariátegui (1894-1930)
Witness to an age
by Alfredo Pita
49 BOOKSHELF
A fresh look at the past
by Christophe Wondji
i Unesco Courier Index 1994
RELIGION
AND POLITICS
TODAY
The comfort of certainty
by Flora Lewis
The embrace of the community
by Jean Daniel
18 Faith and reason
by Adam Michnik
The fundamentalists and science
by Faouzia Charfi
21 From barbarism to tolerance
by Kanan Makiya
Roads to revolution
by Ehsan Naraghi
The abdication of thought
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
Behind the veil of fundamentalism
by Mahmoud Hussein
Economism, the ally of obscurantism
by Régis Debray
India: the threat to union
by Rasheeduddin Khan
29 Black Sunday
A new Hindu identity
by Sudhir Kakar
Fact file on world religions
35
Commentary by Federico Mayor
TB& UNESCO
COURIER
47th year
Published monthly in 30
languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their peoples
and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. . . ."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TBE. UNESCO
Q)UR1ER
47th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and ¡n Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75015 Paris, France.
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque. Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud Ef-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimai (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Siiva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Wali Mohammad Zaki (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Tong-ok (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Surintatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senin Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy. Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel : 45.68.45.65
I year: 21 1 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
I year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to the
order of Unesco
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied
on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompa¬
nied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced
in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (I) Unesco, 7 Place de
Fontenoy. 75700 Paris: (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100 U.S.A.: (3) NCR. Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc..
1 1 1 West 40th Street. New York. U.SA; (4) Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster, Ohio 4469 1 . U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ AU LUXEMBOURG (Printed in Luxemburg)
DEPOT LÉGAL: CI - DÉCEMBRE 1994
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N" 71844 - DIFFUSE PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'UneSCO.
impression: IMPRIMERIE SAINT-PAUL, 2. rue Christophe- Plantin
L-2988 Luxembourg
ISSN 0041-5278 N: I2-I994-OPI-94-532A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 10-1! and 42-43.
onth by month
It was in Tirana twenty years agT Our guidea Party member, of
coursewas unwilling to linger in front of the ageless and clearly
abandoned mosque.
"Doesn't anyone come and pray here any more?"
The man's smile was slightly condescending. Surely we knew
that religion is an optical illusion, a smokescreen laid down by the
oppressors among the oppressed? Marx had summed up the matter
perfectly when he described religion as "the opium of the people."
There was no reason why religion should survive once its social and
political foundations had disappeared, as they had in Albania. Clear¬
sighted peoples can look truth in the face.
What do the clear-sighted see today? One thing is undeniable. It
is the foundations of socialism that have collapsed, in Albania and
in the rest of eastern Europe, and that at a time when religion
occupies an important place in peoples' lives. Or perhaps it is
simply reoccupying the rightful place of which its enemies had
vainly tried to deprive it.
But the collapse of European communism has generated shock
waves that go much further than this swing of the pendulum. The
bankruptcy of totalitarianism in the East, which has led to that of
authoritarian nationalism in the South, has created a political and
ideological vacuum that fundamentalism is trying to fill. Where reli¬
gion was until recently gagged by or in thrall to the state, it is now
being used as a lever with which to challenge the state; yesterday
excluded from the political reckoning, today it is summoned by the
fundamentalists to fill the entire political arena. In the process it is
denying individual values in the name of the community, repressing
freedom in the name of dogma, and extinguishing intelligence in the
name of faith.
The relationship between politics and religion has always been tur¬
bulent, but humanists all over the world are starting to feel alarmed
about its latest episodefundamentalism. In an attempt to under¬
stand the emergence of fundamentalism and its extremist deviations
towards intolerance, violence and crime, a meeting of "Intellec¬
tuals for a Single World" was held in New Delhi earlier this year. Enti¬
tled "Religion and Politics Today", the meeting was jointly organized
by the Unesco Courier, the Rajiv Gandhi Foundation and World Media
Network.
The present issue presents some of the highlights of the New Delhi
symposium, contributions to a debate that is far from over.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
WOLF
LEPENIES
talks to
François Hartog
German sociologist Wolf Lepenies is the head of Berlin's Wis-
senschaftskolleg, a European institute open to researchers from
all over the world. A member of many learned societies in the
United States, Japan, the United Kingdom, Sweden and France,
he held the European chair at the Collège de France (Paris) from
1991 to 1992. He believes that intellectuals have an important
political role to play in Europe today and calls on them to
abandon purely ideological debates for the sake of more
immediate, practical problems.
Less than two years ago you published
a book about the bankruptcy of European
intellectuals. Would you write the same
book today?
A distinction has to be made between the
rest of Europe and Germany. In Germany,
intellectuals are unable to handle the new
situation that has arisen from reunifica¬
tion. The greatest challenge facing the
country today is how to become a
"normal" nation-state within the Euro¬
pean Union. Certainly it is not an easy
task, but intellectuals are not making
enough commitment to it. And there isn't
enough of what I would call "intellectual
patriotism" (the eighteenth century has
given us a wonderful definition of patrio
tism as the position adopted by those who,
without any official power, commit them¬
selves to the public weal). For intellectuals
this is a great time, one that gives them all
kinds of opportunities to act, but they
prefer to take up a position that is half
candid, half contemptuous, or else they
think about grand, Utopian projects.
In Germany you head a unique institu¬
tion known as the Wissenschaftskolleg.
What does it do?
The Wissenschaftskolleg is an institute for
advanced studies in the human sciences.
Every year we invite forty or fifty
researchers from all over the world to work
on their own projects for ten months. The
main idea is to "shake up our guests pro¬
ductively", so that at the end of a year
spent in contact with other temperaments,
other disciplines and other theoretical tra¬
ditions, they can cast a fresh eye on their
own work and question what had previ¬
ously seemed obvious. We also set up what
we call priority groups. This year, for
example, we have two groups working on
theoretical biology.
The Wissenschaftskollegwas founded
in Berlin at a time when the city occupied
a very special position in Europe. Have
the collapse of the Berlin Wall and German
reunification changed its situation?
Yes, our role is changing. We thought
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
that more and more people would be inter¬
ested in internal German questions and
that we would have to concentrate far more
on Eastern Europe. But we are also starting
to broaden our scope and commitment to
questions concerning the developing coun¬
tries. We want to extend our work to com¬
parative cultural studies.
Since 1990 Germany has been a nation
but a nation that is still in the making	
Until 1990 we were hoping that the two
German states would eventually, in the very
long run, become one. History decided oth¬
erwise. Paradoxically, in a context in which
we should be thinking in terms of doing
away with nation states Germany has to
start by becoming a nation state like any
other by developing its own national prin¬
ciples. That is Germany's big problem. We
are torn between our desire to rapidly create
a united Europe and the need to begin by
creating a unified Germany.
German unification has been seen in
various ways. Heiner Müller, for example,
talks of a colonial process regarding the
former German Democratic Republic
(GDR), and Jens Reich describes the
impression of foreignness ( Verfremdung)
that someone from the East may feel when
arriving in the West.*
Both views make sense. But it must be
said that there is a certain reciprocity. This
sense of foreignness is found in both East
and West. Even now I feel a foreigner in
many parts of East Germany, but a for¬
eigner in a positive sense, spontaneously
discovering something new and unex¬
pected. The real difference is that in the
West this foreignness is experienced as a
change of scenery, an encounter with some¬
thing new, whereas in the East it is felt as an
alienation or a threat.
As far as colonization is concerned, it
is true only insofar as West Germans
assume that they are on the right track and
that it's up to the East Germans to catch up
with them. It is a colonialist attitude to be
convinced you are right and to want to
impose your ideas on others.
We have not asked ourselves enough
questions about whether there were things
worth saving in the former GDR. Much
could be said about this, from the role of
women to the health-care system and edu¬
cation the polytechnics, the role of the
teacher outside the classroom, and so forth.
But the colonization theory doesn't
hold up to closer scrutiny. It doesn't cor¬
respond to what has really happened. In
1989 it was possible to believe that a new
phase of ultra-modern industrialization
and massive investment for profit was
beginning. But nothing of the sort hap¬
pened. If a colonialist operation of that
kind had taken place, we wouldn't be in the
economic straits we are now. Today the
state has to do almost everything that we
expected of the market economy!
Moreover, it would be wrong to think
that the East Germans were taken
unawares and were forced to adopt
Western lifestyles. In the East there was a
sense of expectation along these lines, and
the West was quick to respond. There was
a conjunction of interests here.
We are finding out that it is impossible
to write the history of the GDR without
rewriting that of the Federal Republic
because of the extent to which the two
were intertwined.
That is true. But the paradox remains
that although the two histories are bound
together, the mentalities and lifestyles that
evolved over the same time-period are not.
The problem today is how to adjust these
two mentalities.
Were some of the illusions of 1989
and the mistakes that followed the results
of our failure to consider the dimension of
time?
Yes. We didn't think for a moment about
what time might signify as an overall expe¬
rience for the individual, for nations, for
peoples and states. We simply did not ask
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
what it might mean for the rest of Germany
that a large part of the German people had
lived under totalitarian systems since 1933
(the Third Reich, then the post-war com¬
munist regime). This was an oversight that
is costing us dearly in Europe today.
Is the expression "constitutional patri¬
otism" (referring to the 1949 constitution
of the Federal Republic) suggested by
Jürgen Habermas still a valid response to
what is happening today?
I don't believe it goes far enough. If one
tries to promote a widespread and reason¬
able allegiance to German democracy, it is
not enough to tell the Germans that it is
necessary and desirable to opt for consti¬
tutional patriotism. For me that is too cold
and calculating. But we can't do without a
certain kind of patriotism, i.e. a feeling of
belonging to a country and a society.
Outbreaks of xenophobia suddenly
increased in 1991-1992. How worrying
are these explosions of violence?
Of course there is plenty to worry about
since the symbols of national socialism are
still being brandished in Germany. All the
same I think there is a glimmer of hope.
How many of the people who wave these
symbols around and commit violent acts in
their name really should be considered
neo-fascists? We do not know how far this
hides a more general protest that seeks to
express itself in ways that cause the greatest
outrage and in Germany the best way
to do that is via national socialism.
These attacks also bring up the
problem of immigrant integration. The
former Federal Republic always claimed not
to be a country of immigration although it
has never ceased accepting foreigners.
How can reality be squared with the
country's principles and laws?
Germany is in fact a country of immi¬
gration and the problem is that we are not
ready to incorporate this into our political
thinking and practice. Immigration rates
A lot of consideration can
be given to cultural
differences, but a country
ajso has a right to expect a
certain 'cultural solidarity*.
Without that the question
of nationality will not be
resolved.
into Germany are twice those into the
United States, a traditional country of
immigration. Let us openly be a country of
immigration and then set quotas, for no
country can open its borders to everyone.
Maybe the fundamental problem is that
we do not make the distinction between
requests for asylum and immigration. The
right of asylum cannot, of course, be sub¬
ject to quotas. I think it would be a good
thing to introduce a certain sense of reality
into our legislation.
Do you think there will be a debate on
possible modifications to the right to citi¬
zenship?
We really must get away from the notion
that citizenship is determined by lineage
and birthplace. It should be linked to proof
of a person's readiness to adapt to a certain
culture and live within it. A lot of consid¬
eration can be given to cultural differences,
but a country also has a right to expect a cer¬
tain "cultural solidarity". Without that the
question of nationality will not be resolved.
Does the Wissenschaftskollegs sci¬
entific policy fit into a larger political frame¬
work?
I'll answer with a specific example. In
1989 I had the idea of founding a similar
institute in Budapest. Today this institute
exists, and its foundation might serve as an
example of how to avoid certain mistakes.
The first principle was that it should not be
a bilateral institution. I am against all forms
of bilateralism in matters of cultural rela¬
tions. The Collegium Budapest is sup¬
ported by six European countries: Ger¬
many, Austria, France, The Netherlands,
Sweden and Switzerland. That was an
important basic condition for its success.
The second principle was not to play at
charity. The division of Europe was a hand¬
icap for the West as much as the East. Both
sides suffered. Both sides must help each
other by by keeping this common experi¬
ence in mind.
Designed in and for a bi-polar world that
has ceased to exist, the European Commu¬
nity today seems to be at a standstill. There
seem to be difficulties in translating the
new situation into political terms. What can
intellectuals say or do about this?
One of the intellectual's main duties is to
attack the polarized image that exists every¬
where in the European Community,
according to which there are those who
give and those who receive. There is little
doubt as to who gives and who receives.
This Community attitude is derived from
the idea of financial adjustment. This is
how we are behaving today towards the
rest of Europe: we see the possible entry of
countries like the Czech Republic, Hun¬
gary, Slovakia and Poland from a single
angle, i.e. just how far can the "giver"
countries allow themselves "to go", that is,
how many more "receiving" countries can
the Community take in? We are not pre¬
pared to recognize that the entry of these
countries is an opportunity that would
make sacrifices worthwhile. I think that
working for the overthrow of this narrow-
minded economic point of view in Euro¬
pean thought is a very important intellec¬
tual task for the future.
s Heiner Müller, a playwright; Jens Reich, co-
founder of the Citizens' Forum and a
presidential candidate in the 1994 national
elections.
FRANÇOIS HARTOG is a French historian.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The comfort of certainty
by Flora Lewis
^ . à t*
In France the separation of
church and state was designed to
protect the Republic.
In the United States its purpose
was to preserve freedom of
religion.
wk+z*"
M
44^*11«***
V
8
Some years ago in Mozambique, a Por-
I tugúese settler who had decided to stay
on after independence was showing me around
Luanda. We came to a particularly handsome,
newly restored church, and he explained that as
part of the recently launched reform policy to
enhance people's confidence, the Marxist gov¬
ernment had decided to end its compaign against
the church. "The trouble", he said, "was that
both promised heaven, but we promised to
deliver it on earth. We haven't succeeded."
That is the straightforward fact which led to
the collapse of communism an attempt to pro¬
vide an all-encompassing secular faith to regu¬
late all aspects of man's relation to man, making
the idea of man's relation to God not only super¬
fluous but subversive. It has failed, and where it
was imposed there has been a robust revival of
the traditional religion, a testimony of the deeply
felt need of all kinds of people with differing cul¬
tures for something to believe in beyond the
evidence of everyday life. One way or another,
people do seek meaning, a sense of purpose,
that politics cannot adequately provide.
But seldom does religion, by itself, provide
the organizing mechanisms through which soci¬
eties can deal with the perennial issues of power
and the need to adapt to changing circumstances.
That is why there is always an element of poli-
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
&&&****&
A*Q
Friday prayers at the Istiqlal
(independence) mosque in
Jakarta, Indonesia.
tics, even in the most fundamentalist states, even
in the most totalitarian dictatorships, though it
may be hidden in religious rhetoric or a "cult"
(a word borrowed from the vocabulary of reli¬
gion) "of personality". People have conflicting
interests and they can be ordinary. The way
societies deal with this is politics, whatever it
may be called. Politics and religion are pre¬
sented as two different worlds, the one material,
often self-serving, the other spiritual. But they
are inevitably intertwined, and can no more be
isolated from each other in social life than body
and soul can be kept apart in a living person.
Take that as given. The question then is their
impact on each other, their differing priorities,
how they are to be reconciled. The separation of
church and state, which does not necessarily
mean their opposition, is a Western idea that
emerged from the Renaissance and the Refor¬
mation, buttressed by the tremendous advance
of science into the realms of mystery which
once could only be penetrated by religion, by
faith. Just now, quite apart from the familiar
challenges that knowledge of cosmology, of
physics, of biochemistry present to religious
dogma, there are troubling new questions posed
by innovative techniques in biology, lumped
under the new word "bioethics". These have
to do with genetic manipulation, extra-corporeal
conception, the possibility of women, fertile or
not, giving birth to somebody else's genetic
baby. The possibilities didn't exist before, so
neither did the questions. Are the answers to be
supplied by politics (legislation), religious
- - am -
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Politics and religion are presented as two different
worlds, the one material, often self-serving, the other
spiritual. But they are inevitably intertwined, and can
no more be isolated from each other in social life than
body and soul can be kept apart in a living person.
10
authority, or individual choice? A great debate
is beginning in Western countries. A bill is
already before the French Senate. Religious
views will certainly play an important role wher¬
ever these questions are being faced.
One nation, under God
In any case, separation of church and state has
never been so complete or so widespread as the
concept suggests. There are modern democracies
with formally established churches. Israel and
England are examples. The Catholic church has
special status in many countries, such as Italy,
THE CHURCH
AND THE TSAR
In which canons is it
written that the Tsar is to
govern the Church, change
the dogmas and incense the
altar? His only duty is to
watch over it and protect
it from the wolves which
would destroy it, not to
teach how to believe and
how to make the sign of the
cross.
ARCHPRIEST AVVAKUM,
Russian theologian (1620/21-1682)
Spain and Poland. Germany provides publicly
funded support for both Catholic and Protestant
church institutions. In the United States, the
tax system gives indirect support to churches of
all kinds, and it can be a matter of political or
judicial decision as to whether or not any group
claiming to be a religion actually qualifies for this
privilege.
The two countries which historically and
emphatically insist on separating church and
state came to that decision for opposite reasons.
In France, after the 1789 Revolution, it was to
protect the state from the power of the church,
deemed abusive under the Ancien Regime. In the
United States, it was to protect the churches
from the power of the state, to ensure the rights
of religious diversity and religious dissidents, a
major motive for the original colonization of
North America.
Nonetheless, the sessions of Congress open
with a prayer, the pledge of allegiance is "to
one Nation, under God" and the oath of public
office is taken with one hand placed on the
Bible.
The vehemence of the introduction of reli¬
gious issues in American politics waxes and
wanes abortion, prayer in public schools,
public funding for church-run schools are heated
current controversies. The Washington Post
writer E.J. Dionne, Jr., commenting on con¬
temporary arguments about the proper domains
of religion and politics in the United States,
concludes that a certain tension between the
two is desirable, both for government and reli¬
gion, since each would lose from immunity to
challenge excessive claims of authority. Despite
the Constitution, whose first amendment
adopted in 1791 reads "Congress shall make no
law respecting an establishment of religion, or
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
prohibiting the free exercise thereof." The issue
of religion and politics has never been defini¬
tively settled in the United States and probably
never will be. Desirable or not, some tension
persists. What is consistent is the requirement of
tolerance, room for difference.
Not just a religion
This is the core of the issue, the fundamental of
democracy. It isn't about the coexistence of reli¬
gion and politics, but about whether religion
claiming to encompass politics is compatible
with democracy (or, as in Mozambique, whether
politics claiming to liquidate religion is com¬
patible with democracy).
Islam is a special case in today's world
because some militant Muslims, identified as
fundamentalists or Islamicists, insist that their
The Spring ceremony in
Seoul's Chong Myo sanctuary,
where the tablets listing the
names and accomplishments of
Korea's Confucian kings are
kept.
faith gives the basis for all necessary social reg¬
ulation, all functions of government. Aliza
Izetbegovic, the president of Bosnia and Herze¬
govina, wrote in his Islamic Declaration of 1970
that Islam is "not just a religion", an idea that
helped provoke the conflict in his benighted
country. Though they used existing secular law
to run for election in hopes of gaining power
(thwarted by a coup) Algerian fundamentalists
in the Islamic Salvation Front (FIS) declared
that once they were in a position to rule, no
constitution or legislation would be appropriate
because the Qur'an contains, in God's words, all
the regulation that state and society require.
There is no room, in this view, for choice and
interpretation. Authority claims to know what
God intends, so disagreement, rebuttal and
opposition are not just to the mortals who rule IjL
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
but to the will of God himself. This is not com¬
patible with democracy because, though they
base their fiats on scripture, these are people
telling other people what they must believe.
Even if scripture is considered infallible, the
people who say what it means and how its
instructions and denunciations are to be applied
are not infallible. The attempt to impose their
single-mindedness takes especially ugly, repul¬
sive form in the campaign in parts of North
Africa to murder intellectuals for the sheer
reason that they are the ones most able and
likely to formulate and express other ideas. Nei¬
ther liberty nor democracy can tolerate this vio¬
lent breach of tolerance.
The phony Islamic threat
The American Arabist Edward W. Said attacks
those who raise alarm at what he calls "the
phony Islamic threat" by pointing out how
much diversity exists within Islam, how many
different interpretations have been offered and
widely accepted over the centuries. The cur¬
rent militant version has no better claim to
exclusive truth than the others, though it makes
its assertions more aggressively. It is spawned,
Said argues, by reaction to "corrupt and
mediocre governments", not by the intrinsic
precepts of religion itself. "Islam is a cultural
identity", he says, "not a synonym for bomb-
throwing. The real danger in the Arab world is
not the people, but the ruling elites."
In any case, the logic of proclaiming " God's
will" as the answer to the problems of society is
a closed circle. If what is must be because God
Below, François Mitterrand at his investiture as President of
France at the Elysée Palace, Paris, on 21 May, 1981.
Below right, Bill Clinton, 42nd President of the United
States, taking the oath of office on the steps of the Capitol
in Washington, DC, on 20 January 1993.
willed it so, then how is urgent change to be
brought about? How are people to help them¬
selves and others? How is hope to be found on
earth, the only place we surely know? This,
along with violence and persecution, is what so
offends democrats when they warn against
allowing religion the upper hand in politics.
The door is slammed shut against innovation,
initiative, the individual's responsibility to think,
without which there can be no freedom.
Of course, it is true that not everybody
values democracy, and those who do also cherish
other values which it is the duty of democracy
to protect. Democracy does not pretend to be a
faith, though so far as I know all religions do
preach God's equal concern for all human beings
and do not make a hierarchical order of those
who deserve His blessings. Democracy is simply
a way of enabling society to function. It recog¬
nizes human failings and propensity to error, and
makes it easier to correct mistakes peaceably
than systems which claim absolute righteousness
and can only be obeyed or overthrown. It guards
against the sin of hubris, always a threat.
The issue of religion and politics has come to
the fore again in this period because of a number
of circumstances, including the spread of democ¬
racy, the immediacy of communications which
make people much more aware of others outside
their own communities, and the sense of bewil¬
derment, uncertainty and insecurity which the
modern world has much magnified. But this is
not really new; there is a tendency to recur¬
rence. The French writer Emile Zola wrote a
century ago, "great disorders lead to great devo¬
tions". They are the times when people most
want the comfort of certainty. But the human
condition cannot assure it. People need spiritual
solace; they also need politics to cope with life
in an ever more complex society.
12
FLORA LEWIS,
a distinguished American
journalist specializing in
international affairs, is a
syndicated columnist whose
work is widely distributed. She is
the author of several books, the
latest of which is Europe: Road
to Unity (1992).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The idea of the sovereign individual
regarded independently of his religion and
his origins is a relatively recent
development. It was preceded by the idea
of a community towards which the
individual has contradictory feelings.
Let us get down to essentials. We are
here first and foremost to know whether
we should render unto Caesar that which is
Caesar's and whether the temporal can be sep¬
arated from the spiritual.
If we believe, for whatever reason, that such
a separation is impossible, we must conclude that
religious belief in a divine order should dominate
civic organization and we must consider a theo¬
cratic state as legitimate. This being the case,
one question that arises is whether theocratic
states can respect their minorities if they hold a
different religion from that of the state or if
they have no religion at all.
However, if we consider that a separation
between the spiritual and the temporal is desirable
and possible, we must ask ourselves about the role
of a secular state. Can political ethics exist without
a spiritual basis, or laws without a transcendental
basis? Or is the function of the secular state
merely to organize the coexistence of different
religious communities? If it is, then we must
examine the categorical imperatives of a federa¬
tive government and the natural or civic rights it
lays down. In other words, are the ethics of a god¬
less state legitimate and effective? 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A Hindu celebration in
Malaysia.
14
God as Head of State
The English Revolution of 1688, the American
Revolution of 1776 and the French Revolution of
1 789 were major initiating events of an anti-theo¬
cratic trend. From the Habeas Corpus Act of 1679
to the Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the
Citizen of 1791 we can see the emergence within
the civic community of a movement to pass sen¬
tence of death on God and deny Him a place as
Head of State. Secularism as it is practised in
modern states coincides with the definition of
religion found in Greek and Roman Antiquity.
Aristotle and Cicero regarded religion as sepa¬
rate from civic administration. The gods were
omnipresent, but they were not necessarily obeyed.
We should now ask ourselves what has hap¬
pened in our secular states to change the nature
of our expectations of religion and politics. I
hope that I shall not be accused of Gallo-cen-
tricity if I refer to the French example, or what
is left of it, since it is being threatened on all sides.
In France too religion is separate from the state.
Furthermore, with the beheading of Louis XVI,
the death of God-as-Hcad-of-State was more
than just symbolic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
LIVING IN
ONE'S TIME
Politics and religion are
obsolete; the time has
come for science and
spirituality.
JAWAHARLAL NEHRU
(1889-1964)
Speech to the Sri Lankan
Association for the Advancement
of Science,
Colombo, 15 October 1962
In a sense the individual, transformed into a
citizen, was born in France between 1789 and
1791, even if almost two centuries went by
before he reached maturity. This was a hugely
presumptuous creation. The free thinkers, the
radicals and the Voltaireans who had contributed
to the Encyclopédie had contested the power
of the Catholic church, whilst remaining mis¬
trustful of the people. The Revolutionaries and
the members of the Constituent Assembly cre¬
ated this promethean idea of the sovereign indi¬
vidual, someone considered apart from his reli¬
gion, his origins, his environment and his social
class. The republican state was not merely the
arbitrator between the various communities,
which had no legal or official existence. It was
the expression of popular sovereignty by free
and equal individuals. Now, communities are
starting to spring up again in France, forming
ranks and sometimes joining to lobby for some
reform or other. This is undoubtedly an alarming
trend, as we can see today in its ludicrous con¬
vulsive culmination in the United States, in
Lebanon and even worse in the former Soviet
Republics and the former Yugoslavia. We are
living in the era of communalism.
Why is this? I should like to suggest three
reasons.
Man is a religious being
First, we have forgotten that Man is a religious
being. He is more than Aristotle's political
animal or Hobbes's man who is wolf to man. He
is, and always has been, a social and religious
being. The individual is an invention, a con¬
struction, which appeared late in human his¬
tory. The community existed before the indi¬
vidual, who cannot exist without it. The
individual keeps wanting to get away from the
community, yet always wants to return to it. A
great French Hellenist, Jean-Pierre Vernant,
admitted that he had spent his life thinking like
Marx that nation and religions were doomed
by history. Later, he said, he realized that he
could understand nothing about his subject,
Greece, unless he resigned himself to accepting
the permanence of both concepts within Man.
The first conclusion is that everything in
modern life which too brutally assails the indi¬
vidual's integration into his religious community
will eventually cause the individual to react,
sometimes even to regress. The expression "reli¬
gious community" must not be taken to imply
a community of believers. What is most often
regretted in religious tradition is not faith or
even belief, but a certain balance in a patriarchal
society imbued with religious feeling.
Secondly, we have for some time been going
through a crisis of reason linked to the emer¬
gence of the individual. The cult of reason, the
progress of science and the organized cult of
history and the people have been celebrated
and experienced in a religious way. The cult of
reason has even led to totalitarian ideologies.
The crisis of reason does not only stem from
the ideologies that led it astray or even from
the scientific limits that scholars have recently
imposed on it. According to the French philoso¬
pher Emmanuel Lévinas, it results from the
tremendous outcome of two ideologies of
TriumphAnniversary of the
Universal Democratic and
Social Republic, a French
allegorical engraving, 1848.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The opening session of the
new German Bundestag, Bonn,
1992.
progress liberalism which ended up in nazism,
and communism which bore Stalinism along
with it. "World wars and local conflicts, national
socialism, bolshevism, the camps, the gas cham¬
bers, nuclear arsenals, terrorism and unem¬
ployment it's all too much for one genera¬
tion." I feel I must add to this the horrors of
colonization and decolonization. This crisis of
reason leads to either a temporary nihilism or a
permanent need for transcendence.
The powers taken from the Gods
I attach even more importance to the third
reason. Our century has not only dispossessed
the Gods of all powers in civic life, of the power
to destroy humanity, to recreate humankind
and to reproduce ad infinitum. It also enjoys the
ubiquity of images, eliminating space and time
by means of waves. What kind of New Man
will emerge from the mediasphere? We have no
idea, but we do know that there is only one
earth, one world, one planet. From a philo-
What is taken to be a return to religion is
often a return to what preceded religion.
While Man's natural religious side should
be taken into account, this drift back to
nature should be resisted. Certainly we
must fight for the separation of religion
16
sophical point of view, it is disconcerting to
think that nothing human can remain unknown
to us. But knowing that the world is one does
not mean that its unity has been achieved. Quite
the opposite. And it is to be feared that the
upheavals we must suffer before we achieve this
unity will be terrifying. Population movements,
soaring birth-rates, the mingling of peoples, the
mixing of cultures and the babelization of the
world's languages everywhere gives rise to anx¬
ieties, withdrawals and tensions.
Remember that Babel, far from being a
tribute to multilingual cosmopolitanism, was a
curse.
The Tower of Babel is a tower of punishment
and misery. Before accepting to be happy to
belong to planet earth, we wonder who we are
and prefer to be what we were or what we
thought we were. We chase after what is called
"authenticity", which often means reinventing
our roots and claiming to have rediscovered
our fathers' religion, a religion whose message
we sometimes use selectively in order to reject
others.
For some the need for the religious expresses
a lack; for others it expresses nostalgia. It may be
regret for a world of continuity and immanence
where an animal feels an integral part of its com¬
munity, like "water in water". To the French
writer Georges Bataille, it is a need for intimacy
with things and with others. It may also become
regret for a transcendental and original state,
such as the soul in Plato's universe or paradise
before the Fall. The historian of religions Mircea
Eliade identified and studied rites in ancient
Greece, India and Christianity which show or
imply a need and desire to return to an imagined
time of origins and an age of founding myths
which can, when necessary, be reconstructed.
If we contemplate the force of the three rea¬
sons I have just given, we can assess the fragility
of regimes which claim to counter or ignore it.
We can also understand how systems that
manage to satisfy humankind's basic religious
needs can have a future, however totalitarian
these systems may be. Finally, we can see the
essence of despotism and the precarious nature
of democracy.
The sacrifice of Abraham
We also start to fear a return to the religious
socio-psychological phenomena described by
the French scholar René Girard, who sees prox-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
imity as the key to aggression and its continu¬
ance. For Girard, the enemy is the person next
door, one's brother, what the Ten Command¬
ments call one's neighbour. If we are asked to
love our neighbour as ourself, it is precisely
because he is the person we are most likely to
treat as a rival and thus consider hostile. The
person who resembles me most strongly but
who is not me is my enemy. He is the part of
myself which I like in myself but of which I
am dispossessed because it is outside me, and so
I wish to destroy it. In other words, fratricide is
the only real war. We only fully hate what we
know best, and from which we are separated by
hardly anything any little difference will do.
In this situation there can be no spontaneity
in love; the initial drive is to appropriate what is
identical. Love can only exist in this social (and
Below, a statue of an angel
with hands uplifted in prayer. It
stands on a grave in the
cemetery of Florence (Italy).
JEAN DANIEL,
of France, is Editor-in-Chief of Le
Nouvel Observateur, a weekly
magazine which he founded in
1964. Among his recent works
are Cette grande lueur à l'Est
(1989) and La blessure (1992).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
thus religious) self at the price of immense self-
restraint, in fact a kind of rape. In the nature of
the sons of Abraham, therefore, there is an ini¬
tial inaptitude for love because they are reli¬
gious before being the sons of the Prophet. The
heritage of Abraham and eventually the Judaeo-
Christian heritage is not one of love at first sight
but of learning to love. If we adapt the reflexes
observed between religions, races and nations,
we arrive at the Balkan proverb quoted today by
a Croatian leader: "We have no friends. We just
have allies among the enemies of our enemies".
This is a very pessimistic interpretation, and
we are in no way obliged to share it. However,
it helps to remind us that religion exists before
religious belief and that initially belief often
corrected what was imperfect in natural reli¬
gion. For example, the sacrifice of Abraham
would lead, through the customs practised by
the Chaldeans, to human sacrifice. Now, what
is taken to be a return to religion is often a
return to what preceded religion and what faith
corrected, or would have corrected by evolving.
In other words, there are many reasons for
taking into account Man's natural religious side,
but there are even more for resisting the results
of this drift back to nature. Certainly we must
fight for the separation of religion and politics.
In conclusion, I would say that religion
colours, nourishes and impregnates politics, but
religion alone cannot inspire the political orga¬
nization of the community. It is one thing to take
into account the irreducible nature of the reli¬
gious act, but it is quite another to submit the
institutions of people who have achieved the
dignity of the individual to the manifestations of
religious belief.
We asked how to provide a basis for the
need to resist Man's irreducible religious nature.
I think that the answer lies in the universal
nature of everything that emerges into con¬
sciousness. The eighteenth-century philosopher
Montesquieu answered this question in a way
that has since become widely accepted. It is
worth recalling here: "If I knew some scheme
which was advantageous to myself but hurtful
to my kindred, I would banish it from my mind.
If I knew of some scheme which was advanta¬
geous to my kindred but hurtful to my country,
I would try to forget it," he wrote. "If I knew
what was of advantage to my country, but
hurtful to Europe and the human race, I should
regard it as a crime."
The coexistence of secular
rationalism and religion is a
safeguard of freedom and democracy
I understand a rationalist when he tells a
Catholic bishop: Non serviam I shall
not serve.
A secular rationalist is someone to whom I
feel close. When I argue with him, I argue with
a part of myself, with a fragment of my biog¬
raphy. I understand his aspiration for freedom
in the name of a heroic atheism which makes a
human being a master of the world, the sailor
and the ship. I understand his disagreement
with the situation in which someone tries to
restrict his freedom in the name of God.
I understand and yet I continue to argue
with him.
A good cause
A secular rationalist certainly represents a chal¬
lenge for a Christian. But this challenge may
not be a threat, but a noble competition for a
good cause. It may be a way of "cleansing"
one's own religious and philosophical convic¬
tions. A great deal depends on whether the
atmosphere in which the discussion takes place
is one of mutual respect or religious war.
Faith in a world without God, a world ruled
by enlightened intellect, designed in a laboratory
and cleansed of religion such a faith is Utopian
and dangerous. Utopian because there is no his¬
torical evidence to support this belief: secular¬
ization changes the role of religion but does
not eliminate the need for it.
For the rationalist, the main axis of the
Catholic vision of the world is that of a helpless
individual, enclosed by his feelings of guilt and
the authority controlling him. I think differ¬
ently: the main pivot of the Catholic view of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Faith and reason
by Adam Michnik
world is a human being invested by God with
such self-esteem that he bends his knees only
before God. Some repent in the confessional,
others do it elsewhere. But one has to respect the
choice of others: the confessional is a place in
which to give an account of one's conscience, and
this is essential for everyone.
In the story of the shepherd and the sheep,
the rationalist sees the conscious surrender of
freedom by the Catholic. I think differently. A
Catholic knows that human beings can accept
God and his commands only as free subjects.
That is why a Catholic must always choose
freedom against slavery.
But the question remains: how should this
freedom be exercised? Is Pope John Paul IPs
statement that "freedom is not moral relativism"
not worth serious consideration? Do we not
need an institution which will refuse to submit
to the latest fashions and situations and will
The annual pilgrimage to
Czestochowa in Poland, above,
has attracted crowds since the
17th century.
obstinately remind us what is good and what is
bad?
I am afraid of a world of rationality without
limits and of culture without the sacred, for it
would be a world without morality and without
culture. I am also afraid of the logic of a religious
cold war which extremists on both sides of the
barricade are eager to put forward.
The need for a confessional
One can understand the world without visiting
temples, and want to live without a shepherd yet
defend the right to have a shepherd and a teacher.
One can make the effort to see, behind the
words and institutions, people who deserve
respect, living with the conviction that Christ
blessed them with faith and called upon them to
lead a responsible and compassionate life, a life
of dignity and hope. 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The
fundamentalists
and science
by Faouzia Charfi
I In several Arab countries fundamen¬
talist students are in the majority in
scientific institutions in the universities,
especially in the engineering faculties. This
is because the exact sciences can be more
easily dissociated than the human sciences
from the humanist context in which they
developed.
How can rejection of Western values be
reconciled with the necessary acceptance of
the scientific revolutions experienced by
the West? The answer is, by accepting only
their technological contributions. Funda¬
mentalists prefer technology, which leaves
little room for doubt, to science that incites
to reflexion. And they make skilful use of
technology. During a pre-election meeting
in 1991, the Algerian fundamentalist leaders
did not hesitate to use laser technology to
write the sacred formula "Allah is great"
on a cloud.
Fundamentalists only accept what is not
likely to contest their interpretation of the
religious texts. At the end of the twentieth
century, it is difficult not to recognize the
progress made in physics and biology, for
example. But it is possible to accept only the
implications of biological research for med¬
ical development; the theory of the evolution
of species does not need to be taught. From
progress in physics they willingly accept
the remarkable development of the means of
communication but are ill at ease with the
finite value of the speed of light	
In the name of an unavoidable reference
to the sacred, scientific knowledge is muti¬
lated, curbing the cultural and scientific
development of Islamic countries where
today scientific thought is less free than it
was during certain periods of the Middle
Ages.
FAOUZIA CHARFI,
a Tunisian physicist, teaches in the faculty of sciences
of Tunis University.
Below, Allegory of Reason, a
French painting dating from the
revolutionary period (artist
unknown).
Opposite page, The Good
Shepherd. (Italian engraving,
about 1800).
On the brink of mass insanity
In this world which is dangerously approaching
the brink of mass insanity, I think that religion
and secular rationalism should coexist. The con¬
flict between the religious fundamentalist and
the irreligious nihilist can be transformed into a
kind of ecumenical peace. The intellect could be
a guarantor against political doctrines which,
in the name of ethnic, social and religious soli¬
darity, call for absolute obedience. This will be
a constant source of resistance to political char¬
latans, but not to the Gospel.
The totalitarian experience has revealed the
undisputed importance of the Church. The
stand taken by the Church then showed its
other face, its virtuous face, at a time when the
intellect tended to seek reconciliation with a
reality which seemed impossible to change.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Remembrance of the Cross called upon people
to fight against slavery. This remembrance was
a source of courage and the wisdom of the heart.
I would thus suggest to the Catholic and
the secular rationalist the following: demand
from yourself as much as you can; forgive others
as much as you can.
A perfectly devout world and a completely
secular, rationalized world are the two faces of
the same utopia. Every attempt to realize this
utopia has led to a multiplication of conflicts and
sins. Sin and the defence of the sacred are part of
human experience. So too are the absurd and the
defence of reason.
ADAM MICHNIK,
of Poland, is Editor-in-Chief of
Gazeta Wyborcza, Poland's
biggest-selling daily paper.
Among his many books are The
Church and the Left (1977) and
Polish Questions (1987).
From barbarism
to tolerance
by Kanan Makiya
The history of 17th-century
Europe can help us to
understand intolerance today
Parts of Europe were very wild and
I cruel places in those times. The con¬
tinent was engulfed in religious wars, some
small and some not so small. Germany lost
half its population. Whole tracts of land
were laid waste, their villages were sacked
and the people in them massacred. Very
little value was placed on human life. Some
historians think that the imprint of all this
destruction on German culture and politics
could still be felt in the twentieth century.
Although religion was the principal ide¬
ology in the seventeenth century, attempts
to suppress religious dissent always failed
in practice. In the name of Catholic or
Protestant ideals, ordinary men and women
died in droves.
Did all the fanaticism and destruction in
Europe usher in a new age "teaching
mankind by the rudest possible process", as
one writer put it, "the hard lesson of tol¬
eration"? Hardly, since national wars very
quickly replaced religious ones, and ideo¬
logical wars soon found their way back
into European affairs. But the forms of
intolerance tended to change in Europe.
And that is important. Cruelty and forms
of punishment, for instance, became an
issue. And if a kinder, less cruel age was not
ushered in, it is fair to say that a powerful
new idea was born.
KANAN MAKIYA,
an Iraqi-born writer on politics and art, is a Fellow at the
Centre for Middle Eastern Studies at Harvard University
(U.S.A.).
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Roads to revolution
by Ehsan Naraghi
In Iran the Shi'ite clergy rallied the
discontented to trigger off the
insurrection that brought down the Shah
22
I From the beginning of the sixteenth cen-
I tury the time of the foundation of the
Safavid dynasty during which Shi'ism became
the state religion of Iran the Shi'ite clergy shared
the governance of the country with the monarchy.
Even the democratic constitution of 1906-1907
recognized the clergy's right to name five Shi'ite
mullahs to verify the conformity of state law
with Islamic law, the Shar'iah. This clause in the
constitution was respected during the first legis¬
lature, but after 1912 it was not implemented. It
gave the clergy a pretext to claim its share of
government power and legitimized its criticism
of the monarchy. Furthermore, the clergy kept
control over two important fields: education and
justice. However, after 1921, the date when the
Pahlavi dynasty was founded, this control was
denied and the clergy were completely elimi¬
nated from responsibility in the field of justice. In
education, they were still allowed to train mullahs,
but that was all. Thus a Westernized policy
replaced the clergy in all fields. This explains the
immense frustration of the Shi'ite clergy towards
the imperial regime.
Modernization and social disorder
During the following decades, with the accel¬
eration of an anti-democratic modernization
process and the social disorder created by it,
the clergy found strong allies in the growing
numbers of young people uprooted from the
countryside and directed towards the towns,
and in university students who were firmly kept
down. Lastly, the clergy won the support of
the middle class bazaar traders, who felt left
out by the process of modernization.
Thus, by the mid-1960s, religion was again
making a wide impact on social and economic life.
An eloquent young Islamic intellectual, Ali
Shariati, painted the picture of a religious utopia
which held a strong attraction for the young,
The Prince and the Saint, a
17th-century Safavid miniature.
Below, Teheran, 1979: a
demonstration in support of
Ayatollah Khomeini.
EHSAN NARAGHI,
Iranian sociologist and historian,
is Special Advisor to the
Director-General of Unesco. His
most recent published work in
English is From Palace to Prison:
Inside the Iranian Revolution
(1994).
who had become disenchanted with the Soviet
Union. Ali Shariati spoke to them of the law of
the Qur'an and the words of the Prophet and of
the Prophet's son-in-law, Ali. As examples of
Islamic militants he pointed to Ali and his son,
Hussein, and especially to their martyrdom,
which became the symbol of the Shi'ite combat.
The Shi'ite leader Ayatollah Ruhollah
Khomeini, who lived in exile between 1964 and
1979, first in Iraq, then in France, made the most
of being outside government control and
preached a different message from that of the
apolitical Shi'ite tradition. Young theologians
used the errors of the regime (such as the spec¬
tacular celebration at Persepolis in 1971 to mark
the 2,500th anniversary of the founding of the
Achaemenid dynasty) to fan popular discontent.
Finally, during the reign of the Shah there
were far too many ties with foreign countries,
especially the United States. The presence of tens
of thousands of American experts provided a
pretext for the opponents of the regime to criti¬
cize Iran's subordination to foreign influence.
Nationalist language complemented the moral¬
istic discourse.
By the end of the 1970s, the charismatic figure
of Khomeini had become the incarnation of puri-
tanism, radicalism and nationalism opposed to a
discredited government.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The abdication of thought
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
Fundamentalism and totalitarianism both
reject dialogue. They also have two enemies:
laughter, which is a foil to dogma of
all kinds, and subjective experience, which
sustains artists, rebels and poets
I When critical thinking is abandoned,
giving free rein to all kinds of absurdities,
and when doubt either methodical or
strategic absents itself, the individual ceases
to be an individual, melts into the crowd, and
becomes trivial, stifled and unrecognized.
Dialogue becomes impossible.
Rejection of dialogue is inherent in ideo¬
logical extremism, whether religious, political,
or both. The Other only exists insofar as he
enters the citadel of certainties and does
not think of leaving it, still less of voicing a
rejection or denouncing an error. Society
is viewed as a monolithic block with all its
exits sealed, for it senses danger, a threat
from outside introduced by those who have
gone astray.
From within this barricade enemies are
defined in simplistic terms. They are individuals
free in thought and deed, and in all kinds of dif¬
ferent thought philosophies, religions, liter¬
ature, art, poetry. And laughter. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
litar food, signalling the end of
the Ramadan fast, is taken in
common in a mosque.
24
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN
is a Moroccan-born novelist and
poet who writes in French.
Several of his works have been
published in English translation,
including The Sacred Night
(1989) which won the Goncourt
Prize in 1987, Silent Day in
Tangier (1991) and The Sand
Child (1987).
Humour, a weapon against fanaticism
Laughter is the special attribute of human beings,
of free human beings. It marks the birth of
doubt it is an admission of the fact that there
are other ways of thinking and living. Humour
is a form of self-questioning, a less tense face of
despair. By its very essence it is anti-totalitarian.
It mocks the sacred and helps the prisoners of
authoritarianism to become aware of their con¬
dition. In his novel The Name of the Rose,
Umberto Eco has shown that the failure of reli¬
gious fanaticism is caused by the ability to laugh
uproariously; laughter has no respect for dogma
and is thus intolerable.
Another systematic enemy of fundamen¬
talism is subjectivity. Voicing one's individu¬
ality, demonstrating it in one's own manner,
expressing it according to one's own rules,
making it an asset, an identity all this is intol¬
erable for fundamentalism, whose aim has
always been to make society uniform, to rally it
under the same banner, and to exclude from it
the slightest expression of the individual will.
Among those condemned arc all creative artists
who draw elements of their creations from their
innermost selves, all rebels and all those who
aspire to have a private life.
From the moment when you are told how to
dress, what to wear, what should be the length
of a woman's dress or the colour of a man's
thought, from the moment when someone has
the right to interfere in your private life, when
you are told that you are under surveillance
and that someone can intervene at any moment
to call you to order, subjectivity becomes sub¬
version and even indecent assault!
At the base of all monotheistic religions
there is a totalitarian logic to which one finally
gives way, through fear or through faith,
accepting God as the only judge. But when men
substitute themselves for God, and take the ini¬
tiative of speaking and acting in His place, the
very foundations of religion itself are weakened
by this encroachment.
Islam has always been subject to various
currents. None has done it greater harm than the
so-called "fundamentalist" current. Muslim cul¬
tural values can help consolidate an identity
which has been ill-treated by history and which
finds it difficult to adjust to modern life. It all
depends on how these values are analysed and
interpreted. They v/ere long ignored or
neglected. That is why, today, some young
people are identifying with these values and
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Behind the veil of fundamentalism
by Mahmoud Hussein
For the moment the splits in Islamic societies are
encouraging a return to the reassuring
certainties of the fundamentalist message. How
long will it last?
clinging to them. Unfortunately, Islamicism is a
movement whose motivations are more political
than strictly religious.
Forcing dialogue
If the Islamicists are closed to dialogue, is it
possible for intellectuals to force open this
armour-plated door? Should one give up and
adopt an attitude of powerlessness, rejection
and lassitude? The supporters of totalitarianism
do not like moderates; they despise those who
attempt to create links and bring together diver¬
gent points of view. The killing of intellectuals
in Algeria shows this clearly.
Existing political systems bear a heavy
responsibility in the development of protest
movements of Islamicist origin. Are wc going to
remain silent, withdraw into our ivory towers
and look on without reacting? The intellectual's
role is to seek and find new ways of bringing
about the triumph of intelligence and the
advance of the ideas of progress and freedom.
We must use our imagination and go beyond the
situation in which we simply acknowledge that
violence has become a disturbing feature of
everyday life.
It is impossible to appreciate the real
danger of fundamentalism if it is reduced,
as it often is, to its excesses, to the manifestations
of a blind and criminal terrorism, which is only
its extreme outcome. This political nebula is
actually divided into many tendencies, some of
which, although they may be less barbaric, are
not necessarily reassuring. For this reason it is
important to grasp the inner logic of funda¬
mentalism, especially those aspects of it that
may seem attractive. For fundamentalism has a
message, part of which responds in the modern
world to unsatisfied expectations.
The fundamentalists, although themselves
divided into more and less radical wings, find the
climate particularly favourable to their develop¬
ment in countries where the powers-that-be
appear to most people to be iniquitous and to be
leading to the accelerated dissolution of links of
social and cultural cohesion as a result of an
uncontrolled opening up towards the world
market and a dualization of society. In this context,
some people adopt Western interests and ways of
life whilst others feel excluded from them.
Thus the very identity of these countries is at
stake. And it is questions like "What has become
of us?" and "Where are we going?" that enable
fundamentalists to articulate a global and radical
approach. Their discourse is a political one. It
would like to think of itself as submissive to
God but not to the order of things. It is anti-
Western and anti-modernistic, but it would like
to think of itself, paradoxically, as anti-archaic.
It rejects the fatalism of the traditional broth¬
erhoods just as it rejects the conformism of the
religious authorities associated with power. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The absence of a precise message consisting
of clear and evaluated objectives does not
weaken this discourse the religious content
fills the vacuum. The function of this content is
not to provide a programme but an incanta¬
tion; its purpose is not to resolve but to exorcise.
It is not primarily aimed at reason but at blind
faith. At a time when no one knows precisely
what form the future may take, the strength of
fundamentalism lies in its ability to promise
radical change without having to specify its out¬
lines since God is claimed as its guarantor.
The emergence of the modern individual
In this context, what are the current prospects
for those who preach secular and republican
ideals? Some have immersed themselves in the
study of the sacred texts in the search for quo¬
tations, metaphors and arguments to support the
democratic ideas they put forward. They are
fighting from a position of weakness on their
opponents' own ground, ideologically and psy¬
chologically trapped.
As for those who openly defend some¬
times even at the risk of their lives a vision
clearly based on values such as the separation of
the temporal and the spiritual, equality of status
for all religions away from the political sphere,
the freedom of the governed to choose those
who will govern them, they are, quite obvi¬
ously, in the minority. Not only because they are
out of place in a climate of general religiosity but
also because they are only making professions of
faith that do not yet lead to precise and credible
proposals for changes in society.
But what today is the weakness of the
upholders of a democratic future should in the
long run become their strength.
The dual upheaval undergone by Islamic
societies their forced entry into a market which
26
is becoming global in ways and at a pace which
are ruthlessly disrupting internal balances and
hierarchies, and the advent of the autonomous
individual into the political life of these societies
in place of the traditional notables and feudal
chiefs is tending to increase the fragility of
the national fabric, the psychic instability of
individuals and the unpredictability of events.
But fragility, instability and unpredictability are
signs of the maturing of a new situation, of the
transition of societies to a higher stage of com¬
plexity, "plasticity" and ultimately creativity. The
opening of these societies towards the world
market however unjust and cruel the condi¬
tions in which it occurs brings with it the ferment
of knowledge, information and innovation, which
will be assets in the changes to come. And the
continuing increase in the number of individuals
responsible for their conscience and their destiny,
however harrowing their daily lives may be, nev¬
ertheless raises questions, doubts, desire for change
and self-improvement which are all necessary
seeds for future rebirths.
The currents that bear these potentialities
for openness and change are the only ones that
can take up, in the long run, the dual challenge
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
of globalization and individualization. This
challenge presupposes an increasing adaptability
of individuals and groups to dislocation, dis¬
continuity and the irregular pace of computer
civilization.
The fundamentalist option and the democ¬
ratic option are two possibilities stemming from
one and the same reality: the advent of a modern
individual, accountable for his thoughts and
actions, and now subject to a dual temptation
accepting the gamble of freedom, with all its
solitude and risks, or seeking refuge in reas¬
suring certainties and solidarities, eclipsing both
his free will and his fear of the future.
Hopes for democracy in the South perhaps
hinge on this: the current globalization is taking
place under conditions that challenge some of
the fundamental facts of democracy in the North
itself. We are all increasingly dependent on each
other in facing our fundamentalisms and in cre¬
ating together a setting for our freedoms.
MAHMOUD HUSSEIN,
French political scientist and writer. Most recent published
work: Versant Sud de la liberté: essai sur l'émergence de
l'individu dans le tiers monde (1989; "The Southern Slope of
Liberty: an essay on the emergence of the individual in the
Third World").
Women demonstrate against
fundamentalism in Algiers on
22 March 1994 .
Opposite page, a
demonstration in support of the
Islamic Salvation Front (FIS) in
Algiers, 1991.
Economism,
the ally of
obscurantism
by Régis Debray
Our own Utopian and mil¬
lenarian thinking has failed, and
we are seeing an official return to vintage
brands that are firmer and less falsifi-
able. The retreat from politics by disil¬
lusioned people is today opening the
door to its take-over by the revealed
religions. The pendulum has swung. The
laissez-faire, mercantilist and minimal
state is playing into the hands of clerics
and mafias who will stop at nothing
until it unconditionally surrenders. "You
do not destroy what you replace," said
Auguste Comte (the most clear-sighted
sociologist of his day) prophetically.
Religion is not the opium of the people
but the vitamin of the weak. How is it
possible to keep the neediest people
from turning to it if democratic states
have nothing more attractive to offer
than material prosperity? Clerical fanati¬
cism prospers anew because there is no
freely accepted civic religion, no secular
and agnostic spirituality. Today the
greatest ally of obscurantism is
economism. If our cynics in high places
were less interested in the Dow Jones
index, perhaps there would be fewer
dévots in the mosques and basilicas.
REGIS DEBRAY
is a French philosopher, essayist and novelist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
India: the threat to union
by Rasheeduddin Khan
<
9* f*~
28
For 45 years India has been facing religious
movements which contest the foundations
of the secular pluralist state created at the
time of independence
I In India we use the word communalism to
designate the political exploitation of reli¬
gion, rather than the word fundamentalism,
which belongs to the strictly religious sphere.
Communalism appropriates religious tenets,
traditions and values and perverts them. It
exploits religious feelings and fear of others to
serve certain political interests. It is the enemy
of the concept of the federal nation-state based
on secularism and rationality.
Two formations emerged in India after the
achievement of independence: nationalism, with
secular overtones, and communalism Hindu,
Sikh and Muslim. In recent years the Indian
state has been besieged by a major opposition
grouping based on religious militantism. The
Hindu movement based on the idea of Hin-
dutva is perhaps the most dangerous.
The land of the Hindus
Hindutva is an ideology that gives supremacy to
the Hindu identity and denies any rights to reli¬
gious minorities, or to Hindus of inferior castes.
The idea of an exclusively Hindu India has been
articulated since 1925 and more particularly
since the entry on the Indian political scene of
Guru Golwalkar, who launched the idea that
India should be called Hindustan. In a pam-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A wall painting in Jaipur (India)
showing Christian, Hindu, Jain,
Muslim and Sikh at prayer
together.
Black Sunday
The destruction of the Ayodhya mosque on 6 December 1 992
sent shock waves through India
" 'Black Sunday' as it was called in the media will remain a disturbing experience in the minds and
hearts of those millions of our compatriots of all religions who recognize our common mother¬
land as a generous land of pluralism and accommodation," says Rasheeduddin Khan.
On that day, in the ancient city of Ayodhya in northern India, Hindu mutants celebrating a
religious ceremony sacked the mosque erected on the site which, they believe, marks the birth¬
place of the Vedic hero Rama.
In the hours that followed, there were clashes all over the country. Mosques and Hindu tem¬
ples were destroyed and "pogroms" were organized by small extremist groups, especially in
Bombay. A number of Muslims were shot by the police during demonstrations.
The confrontations continued for several weeks. Anti-Indian rioting occurred in several
Muslim countries, especially in Pakistan and Bangladesh. Almost 2,000 people died.
This crisis marked a revival of Hindu extremism and widened the gap between the Hindu and
Muslim communities.
Vinod Mehta, editor-in-chief of the daily The Pioneer, wrote of an India at war with herself,
and Salman Khursheed, a Muslim and secretary of state for foreign affairs publicly exclaimed his
concern about the rise in extremism and what he termed "a declaration of war against the secular
state!"
phlet entitled We or Our Nation Defined (1930),
he wrote, "Hindustan is the land of the Hindus
and the land for the Hindu nation alone to
flourish upon." He also claimed that "the foreign
races in Hindustan must adopt the Hindu cul¬
ture and language . . . must entertain no idea but
the glorification of the Hindu race and culture
. . . and must lose their separate existence to
merge in the Hindu race. ..."
The amazing conclusion was that non-
Hindus "may stay in the country, wholly sub¬
ordinated to the Hindu nation, claiming nothing,
deserving no privileges, far less any preferential
treatment not even citizen's rights." Golwalkar
denigrated the work of Gandhi and Nehru, who
had striven for inter-communal harmony and
friendship, and associated them with those who
"have committed the most heinous sin by killing
the life-spirit of a great and ancient people."
Golwalkar's ideology helped to break the
already fragile link between Hindus and Mus¬
lims. However, no act of war since the partition
of the country in 1947 was so traumatic as the
destruction on Sunday, 6 December 1992 of the
mosque at Ayodhya, built under the auspices of
the Mogul Emperor Babur (see box on this
page).
This "black Sunday" still disturbs those who
see India as the land of pluralism and coexistence
between communities. In direct contradiction
with centuries of intermingling of populations,
the attack was the tragic outcome of the Hindu
nationalist campaign begun eight years before.
After independence, India had the option
of becoming either a Hindu state, in response to
Pakistan declaring itself an Islamic state, or
remaining a secular state. Finally no definite
choice was made. India is not a Hindu state.
Neither is it an authentic secular state. Due to the
pressures of communal politics and confusion in
the ranks of the secularists, the Indian state is a
Hindu version of a pseudo-secular state. If it
wishes to be recognized as a dynamic modern
state, India must restore its image as a secular
state. Any secular state should show respectful
indifference to religions.
RASHEEDUDDIN KHAN,
an Indian political scientist, is
Director of the Indian Institute of
Federal Studies (Jamia
Hamdard). Among his published
works are Federal India: a
Design for Change (1992) and
(as editor) Composite Culture of
India and National Integration
(1987).
It is one of the greatest frauds on the people to
suggest that religious affinity can unite areas which
are geographically, economically, linguistically and
culturally different.
ABDUL KAMAL AZAD
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A new Hindu identity
by Sudhir Kakar
Psychoanalysis of a Hindu ideology
A demonstration in New Delhi
on 4 March 1991 calling for the
construction of a temple in
Ayodhya.
30
SUDHIR KAKAR
is an Indian psychoanalyst best
known for his book Intimate
Relations: Exploring Indian
Sexuality (1989). Among his
other published works are
Shamans, Mystics and Doctors
(1989) and The Inner World: A
Psychoanalytic Study of
Childhood and Society in India
(1979).
In many parts of India today, especially
the northern and central states, a new
Hindu identity, Hindutva, is being constructed.
It is the basis of an amorphous group of Hindu
parties and groups, the Sangh Parivar, and bears
only a faint family resemblance to its predeces¬
sors. Analysing the fantasies, images and arche¬
types contained in the campaign speeches of
the votaries of this new identity, we can dis¬
cern some of the stages in its construction.
The first notable feature of the speeches is the
way in which they redraw the boundary of the
Hindu community by hailing selected gods and
heroes who are presented as ideals to be shared
by members of the community in order to main¬
tain its cohesion.
They also evoke a shared social loss, sym¬
bolized by the Ram temple at Ayodhya. This
temple is a symbol of the mourning of Hindu
society: mourning for lost honour, lost self-
esteem, lost civilization.
This emerging Hindu identity is presented as
being constantly threatened by external and
internal forces. Constant vigilance is needed to
prevent that which has been recently united
from being divided. The speeches single out the
political forces representing this threat. A
process of idealization and a search for scape¬
goats come next.
Group narcissism
Hindu tolerance, compassion, depth of insight "
and breadth of social concern are idealized.
These are the qualities inherent in a Hindu
group self which makes the individual member
feel righteous and pure. This increase in self-
esteem can be maintained only by projecting
the bad, the dirty and the impure onto another
group, the Muslims.
The process of splitting activates the group's
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
persecution fantasy. The Muslim ceases to be a
stereotype and becomes an archetype the
archetype of tyranny. A note of helplessness
creeps into the speeches at this stage, engen¬
dered by fear of persecution. This feeling reveals
the fragility of the group's self. The positive
self-image of the Hindu is tarnished by his fear
of being impotent to change the material or
social conditions of his life. Are we tolerant or
are we merely weak? Or are we tolerant because
we are weak?
The crumbling self demands restoration
through forceful action. The campaign speeches
channel this need by calling for collective and
united action in the political arena. They hold
out the possibility of some kind of self-assertion
through the electoral process, where all the per¬
secutory anti-Hindu forces, from within and
without the Hindu fold, can be engaged and
defeated.
The Sangh Parivar cannot be faulted for fos¬
tering Hindu pride. This is a normal aim of any
group's narcissistic economy. The question is
when narcissism becomes deviant or abnormal.
This group pride and narcissism have made
it possible for the Hindutva forces to offer a
specific vision of India's future. The pivotal
issue for them is not the acceptance of global
techno-science and the economic institutions
and forms of modernity, but their possible
impact on Hindu culture and identity. Such
an approach will have great appeal to the
emerging middle classes and sections of the
intelligentsia which are committed neither to
THE COMMON LIGHT OF PAY
There will always be many who, by tradition and
temperament, find solace in belonging to a partic¬
ular sect. Also, there will be others who think that
such solace can only be allowed as legitimate within
the pale of their own. Between such, there must be
quarrels. . . . Has India, in her religious ideals, no
space for the common light of day and open air for all
humanity? The vigour with which the sectarian
fanatic will shake his head makes one doubt it; the
bloodshed which so frequently occurs for trivial causes
makes one doubt it; the cruel and insulting distinctions
between man and man which are kept alive under
the sanction of religion make one doubt it.
RABINDRANATH TAGORE
(1861-1941)
Towards Universal Man
universal modernism nor to post-modern tra¬
ditionalism.
In a society in the throes of modernization,
there is a pressing need for continuity with the
past in order to maintain a sense of individual
and collective identity. It is this need for a con¬
tinuity of collective memory, or more accu¬
rately for a collective representation of the past
in times of rapid change, even turbulence, which
the Sangh Parivar addresses with considerable
social and political success.
A poster in Calcutta.
^	
who is high, who is low ?
we are all
EQUAL
insis i on
your civil rights
tat U-jT T^^S« 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE
32
1125
Growth in numbers of believers (in nillions)
1000
875
750
625
500
375
250
125 [J
"
1900 1970 1986 2000
Islam
Catholicism
Hinduism
Protestantism
Buddhism
Orthodox Catholic Church
Chinese religions
Animism
World religions
Source: Atlas des religions, editorial
director Antoine Sfeir © Plon-Mame,
Paris, 1994.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
ON WORLD RELIGIONS
Catholicism
Protestantism
Orthodox Catholic Church
Judaism
Islam
Hinduism
Buddhism
Shintoism and Buddhism
Chinese religions
Animism
Coptic Church
Thinly populated regions
PRINCIPAL FOUNDERS OR REFORMERS OF RELIGIONS
(in chronological order)
ABRAHAM (monotheism) about 1850 B.C.
MOSES (Judaism) about 1250 B.C.
ZOROASTER (Zoroastrianism) 650-583 B.C.
LAO TZU (Taoism) 605-520 B.C.
BUDDHA (Buddhism) 563-483 B.C.
CONFUCIUS (Confucianism) 551-479 B.C.
MAHAVIRA (Jainism) 540-468 B.C.
JESUS CHRIST (Christianity) 4 B.C. -30 A.D.
MUHAMMAD (Islam) 570-632
NICHIREN (Japanese Buddhism) 1222-1282
NANAK (Sikhism) 1469-1539
LUTHER (Lutheranism) 1483-1546
HENRY VIII (Anglicanism) 1491-1547
CALVIN (Calvinism) 1509-1564
Source: Les religions de l'humanité by Michel Malherbe, Criterion publishers, Paris, 1992 © Criterion, Paris, 1990.
FURTHER READING
THE STATE AND RELIGION
Spiritual authority and temporal power in the Indian theory
of government
Ananda Coomaraswamy, Kraus, New York, 1942.
Religion and politics in the United States
Kenneth D. Wald, Congressional Quarterly, Washington,
D.C., 1991, 326 pp.
Religion and political culture in Kano
John Paden, University of California Press, Berkeley, 1973,
461 pp.
Religions of immigrants from India and Pakistan: new
threads in the American tapestry
Raymond Williams, Cambridge University Press, New York,
1988, 335 pp.
Law and revolution: the formation of the Western legal
tradition
Harold J. Berman, Harvard University Press, Cambridge,
Mass., 1983, 672 pp.
The crisis of Church and State, 1050-1300
Brian Tierney, University of Toronto Press, Toronto, 1988,
212 pp.
Churches and politics in Latin America
Daniel Lewis, Sage Publications, Beverly Hills/London,
1980, 288 pp.
Religion and nationalism in Soviet and East European
politics
Pedro Ramet (ed.), Duke University Press, Durham, North
Carolina, 1989, 516 pp.
Church and State through the centuries: a collection of
historic documents with commentaries
Sidney Z. Ehler and John B. Morrall (eds.), Biblo and Tanner,
Cheshire, Conn., 1988, 625 pp.
FUNDAMENTALISM
Islamic fundamentalism
Youssef Choueiri, Twayne, New York, 1990, 224 pp.
Fundamentalism
James Barr, Trinity Press, Valley Forge, Pennsylvania, 1981,
400 pp.
Fundamentalism and American culture: the shaping of
twentieth-century evangelicalism 1870-1925
George M. Marsden, New York, Oxford University Press,
New York, 1980, 320 pp.
RELIGION AND POLITICS
Global economics and religion
James Finn, Transaction Publications, New Jersey, 1983,
277 pp.
Iran: religion, politics and society
Nikki Keddie, Frank Cass, London, 1980, 256 pp.
The sociology of religion
Max Weber, Beacon Press, Boston, 1993, 384 pp.
History of political philosophy (3rd ed.)
Leo Strauss and Joseph Cropsey (eds.), University of
Chicago Press, Chicago, 1987, 992 pp.
Religion and politics in the modern world
Peter H. Merkl and Nlnian Smart (eds.), New York University
Press, New York, 1983, 296 pp.
The social teaching of the Christian churches
Ernst Troeltsch, University of Chicago Press, 1981
(2 vols.)
Kings or people: power and the mandate to rule
Reinhard Bendlx, University of California Press, Berkeley,
1978, 704 pp.
The political and social ideas of Saint Augustine
H.A. Deane, Columbia University Press, New York, 1966,
356 pp.
Religion and political conflict in Latin America
Daniel Levine, University of North Carolina Press, Chapel
Hill, 1986, 266 pp.
The Church and the Left
Adam Michnlk, (trans. David Ost), University of Chicago
Press, Chicago, 1993, 301 pp.
GENERAL
The encyclopedia of religion
Mircea Eliade (ed.), MacMillan, New York, 1987, 17 vols.
New Catholic encyclopedia
McGraw-Hill, New York, 1967, 15 vols.
The Oxford dictionary of the Christian Church
F. L. Cross and E. A. Livingstone, Oxford University Press,
Oxford, 1983, 1520 pp.
A dictionary of Hinduism
Margaret and James Stutley, Routledge, London, 1977,
372 pp.
A popular dictionary of Buddhism
Christmas Humphreys, Curzon Press, London, 1976, 224
pp.
The Encyclopaedia of Islam (New Edition)
E. J. Brill, Leiden, 1983-1994, 7 vols.
Encyclopaedia Judaica
Cecil Roth (ed.), MacMillan, Jerusalem, 1972, 16 vols.
African religions and philosophy
John Mbiti, Heinemann, London, 1990, 288 pp.
The world's religions
Stewart Sutherland, Leslie Houlden, Peter Clarke and
Friedhelm Hardy, Routledge, London, 1988, 995 pp.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN
tion
34
THE THIRD-MILLENNIUM
GENERATION, A NEW
PEACE-KEEPING FORCE
From its inception in a Paris suburb in
1981, the organization known as Le
'Chemin des enfants (The Children's Way)
has been committed to a struggle against
violence, overpopulation, poverty and
war. It is now launching a new project,
Génération Troisième Millénaire (Third
Millennium Generation), intended to offer
young people an opportunity to make a
practical contribution to peace. With help
from the World Federation of Unesco
Clubs, Centres and Associations
(WFUCA) it hopes to recruit from
Unesco clubs worldwide young people
between 1 8 and 30 who would meet with
the leaders of present or potential
conflicts round a table to express their
rejection of force and destruction. "We
firmly oppose the use of force," these
new peace-keepers will say. "It is our
absolute right, for when a conflict breaks
out somewhere in the world, we are
involved, we are the losers."
For further information, contact Marcel
Canetti Le Chemin de% enfants, B.P. 14,
92193 Meudon Cedex, France. Tel.: (33-1)
4626-0852
A TRIBUTE TO GANDHI
To mark the 1 25th anniversary of the
birth of Mahatma Gandhi, Unesco has
issued an official medal bearing his
portrait. Engraved by the French artist
Trémois, the medal is available in gold,
silver and bronze. Etched beneath the
profile of the Mahatma ("great soul") is
this message of hope: "In the midst of
darkness light prevails". The medal may
be ordered from UNESCO's Numismatic
Programme, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, France. Tel.: (33-1) 4568-1808.
UNESCO GIVES PRIORITY
TO WOMEN'S LITERACY
On 8 September, the Director-General of
Unesco presented Unesco's 3 literacy
prizes at a ceremony held to mark
International Literacy Day. The
International Reading Association Literacy
Award went to the Malawi National
Centre for Adult Literacy and Education,
which has taught 645,000 people, 85% of
__ 	 -	
UNICEF GREETING CARDS
Since its foundation 48 years ago,
UNICEF (the United Nations
Children's Fund) has helped to
improve the conditions of
millions of needy children in
many countries by providing
medical care, food, safe drinking
water and educational supplies. It
relies heavily on voluntary
donations from governments,
private donors and proceeds
from the sale of greeting cards,
games and gifts. This year artists
from many countries have again
contributed a wide range of
designs for UNICEF Greeting
Cards, which are now on sale at
UNICEF sales points throughout
the world. Designs include
snowy landscapes, festive streets,
traditional and contemporary
religious motifs, comic and
fantastic drawings, Christmas
trees, "animated" and
"silhouette" cards in kraft or
parchment paper hand-made in
Nepal and invidually printed with
wooden blocks.
them women, how to read. A Roman
Catholic school for girls, Loreto Day
School in Sealdah, Calcutta (India), was
awarded the Noma Prize, notably for its
"Barefoot Teachers" programme for
training high-school dropouts to teach
primary school in slums, and for its
"Rainbow" programme that invites
homeless street children into the school
at any time of the day. The National
Union of Tunisian Women received the
King Sejong Literacy Prize for its work in
improving the status of women and its
programmes to improve school
attendance rates. In the address he gave
during the award ceremony, the Director-
General called attention to "the essential
links between women, education,
demographics and development".
THE FIRST INTERNATIONAL
TEACHERS' DAY
International Teachers' Day was
celebrated for the first time on 5
October, marking the anniversary of the
adoption of the UNESCO/International
Labour Organisation Recommendation
Concerning the Status of Teachers in
1 966. Since 1 966 the number of teachers
worldwide has risen from 1 6 to 47
million, and that of pupils from 372 to 527
million. Classes are often overcrowded,
especially in the poorest countries, where
the average number of pupils per teacher
ranges from 29 in Yemen to 90 in the
Central African Republic. In addition to
deteriorating working conditions,
teachers are also facing a drop in salaries,
which have decreased by an average of
10% because of the economic crisis and
structural adjustment policies. In this
difficult context, International Teachers'
Day is intended to highlight a profession
whose important role in society is not
always fully recognized.
MOTHERHOOD TODAY
In the International Year of the Family, as
ever, it is timely to remember that the
fundamental unit of society, the family, is
based on motherhood. With this in mind,
two French associations concerned with
protecting children in danger and
supporting families in difficulty have
organized a symposium on "Motherhood
Today", to be held at Unesco
Headquarters in Paris on 5 December.
Although medical progress has reduced
the risks of having children, the
Association de Maternologie of Saint-Cyr-
L'Ecole and the Fondation pour L'Enfance
point out that many aspects of
motherhood still remain mysterious. At a
time when more and more women are
bringing up children on their own and may
need help and support, they hope that the
symposium will draw particular attention
to the psychological aspects of
motherhood.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
té l\tt "1
4
COMMENTARY BY FEDERICO MAYOR
Education, key to the future
ft IO two years ago, Cairo
^ yesterday, Copenhagen and
mW , Beijing next year this extremely
mM important series of United
K^^J Nations conferences"" reflects a
A growing awareness that the chal-
^L lenges facing our world arc
universal. These meetings are
^L stages on the long road to
the management of our global
W interdependence.
^mM B jj^ They can be seen as part of a
jpj^J trend that is leading to a signifi
cant shift in thinking about
development. Economism, one of the most persistent of this cen¬
tury's reductionisms, is in retreat. Development is increasingly rec¬
ognized as a process encompassing all aspects of human exis¬
tence and as a right due to all human beings in their diversity.
A NEW APPROACH
The regulation of population growth is undoubtedly one of the
most urgent challenges facing us. But it is only one factor in a com¬
plex equation that can spell the difference between greater pros¬
perity for all in a more equitable world, or increased poverty, envi¬
ronmental degradation and social and political tensions of all
kinds. Population policies must therefore form part of an inte¬
grated sustainable human development strategy that includes
protection of the environment, the promotion of economic well-
being and the furthering of social progress, notably through
enhancement of the status of women.
To be effective, such a strategy must be radical, in the sense of
going to the root of our problems. I believe that this means, first
and foremost, investing in education that is to say in knowledge
and knowledge creation, in individual awareness and respon¬
siveness. All the available evidence suggests that there are enormous
dividends to be reaped from investing in education. Experience in
many countries has shown that it is the key not only to eco¬
nomic growth but also to political development and social
progress.
Nationally and internationally, we continue to invest in a
shortsighted way. Our investments are still geared to past threats
or to dealing with the symptoms of problems. Wc are largely
unprepared or unwilling to address current challenges of a non-
military nature that constitute actual or potential threats to human
security. Every day we confirm our perverse preference to pay the
heavy human and financial costs of peace-keeping and relief oper¬
ations rather than make relatively modest investments in the
social sphere. We ignore, at our peril, the need to tackle our prob¬
lems at source.
Everywhere, in all social and cultural contexts, increased edu¬
cation for girls and women means lower fertility rates, as well as
reduced mortality and morbidity levels. This shows that women's
reproductive choices depend on a process of empowerment,
which can only come from improved educational provision,
training for economic self-reliance and the enhancement of
women's legal and social status.
Special efforts need to be made to reach the large section of the
female population that has so far proved unreachable the 29 per
cent of girls worldwide not enrolled at primary school, the 65 per
cent of the world's 900 million illiterates who arc women. This will
call for a whole range of innovative learning and teaching methods,
including interactive and distance education, and for learning
facilities to be made permanently available to people of all ages,
without formal academic requirements.
The family is the basic unit of society and the reflection of local
cultural and religious patterns. The search for endogenous solu¬
tions to development problems must respect the fundamental
role of the family in social life. In particular, the control of fertility
should not be based on coercion or technocratic prescription. Nor
should it involve the imposition of external models or dogmatic
interferences. The only sustainable basis for fertility control is the
informed choices of empowered men and women, fully con¬
scious of their human rights and dignity.
A LIBERATING FORCE
It was for this reason that UNESCO joined with the United
Nations Population Fund in organizing the first International
Congress on Population Education and Development, which
was held in Istanbul in April 1993. The Congress recognized that
population problems should not be viewed in isolation from
overall development issues and recommended that "to ade¬
quately prepare the younger generations to meet the challenges
of the twenty-first century, population education programmes
should be extended to the various levels of the education system
. . . and be developed as an integrated dimension of educational
curricula."
Education is more than the provision of education and instruc¬
tion. It is the awakening of human creative potential; it is the
building of endogenous capacities; it is forging attitudes of toler¬
ance and understanding; it is providing individuals with the ability
to master their own destiny. For too long the lives of too many
people have been dependent on powers exercised by others, on
others' visions, on ignorance, on oppression. Education is liber¬
ation. It is the main gateway to peace, equity and justice. Those
who hold the key to this gateway teachers, parents and partic¬
ularly mothers have a crucial responsibility: the world we leave
to our children will depend on the children we leave to our world.
* UN Conference on Environment and Development, Rio de Janeiro,
1992; International Conference on Population and Development, Cairo,
1994; World Conference for Social Development, Copenhagen, 1995;
World Conference on Women: Action for Equality, Development and
Peace, Beijing, 1995.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The splendourofSpis
by EdouardBailby
A unique ensemble
of medieval fortifications in Slovakia
Thesite is dramatic. Perched atop a
rocky outcrop 634 metres above
sea-level in the centre ofSlovakia,
Spis castle Spissky Hrad dominates a
green carpet of rolling hills and valleys.
Bathed in light, buffeted by the wind
blowing off the Tatra mountains, its ram¬
parts dominated by an imposing keep and
looming watch-towers bear witness to a
troubled history that stretches back into
the MiddleAges. No other castle in eastern
Europe has such extensive fortifications.
The visitor needs a fairly detailed map
ofSlovakia to find the way to Spis castle. It
lies about ten kilometres from the town
of Levoca (population 17,000), whose
church of St. James boasts a Gothic altar-
piece of gilded wood that is 18.6 metres
high, the tallest in the world. The entire
region abounds in such treasures, largely
unknown to tourists, who tend to favour
the sunny forests of the Tatras in summer
and their ski-slopes in winter.
The castle is built round a keep and an
inner courtyard, which are protected by
two romanesque inner walls with forti¬
fied access gates and an outer wall in
which the main gate is located. There are
also a chapel, garrison buildings and a
large barbican. The castle is reached by a
narrow, winding country road barelywide
enough for two cars to pass each other.
Sometimes coaches pull up at the foot of
the walls and disgorge streams of school-
36
Above, the imposing ramparts of Spis
castle. Left, the church of the Holy
Spirit (13th century) in the nearby
village of Zehra.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
children, who love to play in the ruins at
least those open to the public and
scramble along the ramparts that run
along the crest of the hill. There is a small
museum where they can learn about the
castle and its history.
An eventful past
Archaeological excavations have shown
that this area has been peopled since
neolithic times, i.e. the fifth millennium of
the pre-Christian era. In the first century
A.D. people ofSlavic origin began to build
an ingenious network of mud walls, ves¬
tiges ofwhich are still visible today. Early
in the tenth century Magyar tribes came
down from the Ural Mountains, setded in
the Carpathian Basin and extended their
dominion as far as the Tatras. For a thou¬
sand years, right to the end of the Habs-
burg Empire, Slovakia was ruled by Hun
garian monarchs, who left many traces of
their presence. One of them is Spis castle.
To crush Slovakian peasant uprisings
and check foreign invasions, a system of
fortifications was built at the beginning
of the twelfth century. It included a tower
(22.5 metres in diameter), which was sited
on a geological fault and eventually col¬
lapsed. It was not until the thirteenth cen¬
tury that a genuine castle began taking
shape on the rocky outcrop. Work stopped
in 124 1 when the area was invaded by Tar¬
tars, Mongolian horsemen who pillaged
the region. Eventually, however, the Hun¬
garian king Bela IV expelled the Tartars
from his kingdom, established a system
of feudal lordships to bring prosperity
back to his lands, and built a number of
defensive fortresses. Spis castle was
embellished in 1249 with a palatial
romanesque building and in 1270 with a
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
'Restoration work will take ten
years and costabout
$1.6 million, and we'regoingto
have a liard time raising this
sum without international
help,' says the director ofthe
Spis museum.
magnificent keep. But in less than a cen¬
tury another enemy invasion caused mas¬
sive damage.
Then in the fourteenth century, King
Lajos I of Hungary (1342-1382) decided
to rebuild the castle in the Gothic style.
Two vast courtyards were built within the
walls, and the expanding castle became
one of the pillars of the Hungarian defence
system. Each succeeding owner con¬
tributed to its growth. The Zapolsky family,
whose descendants still bear the heredi¬
tary title of "Governor of the County of
Spis" built the chapel of St. Elizabeth in
the late Gothic style and added fortifica-
38
tions on either side of the main entrance
gate. In 1531 the castle passed into the
hands of the Hurzó family, which owned
the country's biggest foundries and intro¬
duced Renaissance elements into the
castle's architecture. The most recent
changes were made by the Csaky family,
one of the wealthiest in the Austro-Hun-
garian empire.
When Stephan Csaky died in 1663, his
kinsfolk moved a few kilometres away into
the Hodkovce and Bijacovce palaces. Only
a small garrison remained in Spis castle,
leaving in 1780 after the castle was gutted
by fire. The local people plundered what
remained. They took timber for their
houses, fuelwood, iron sculptures and
stone for building.
The years passed, the tide ofwar ebbed
and flowed, and the castle was forgotten.
Only its ruins survived, neglected and aban¬
doned to the elements. In 1945, in the after¬
math ofthe Second World War, Spis castle,
which still belonged to the Csaky family,
was declared a national cultural monu¬
ment by the Czechoslovak Republic.
In the 1970s restoration and archaeo¬
logical excavations were conducted at the
castle, but theyproved to be very expensive,
were suspended on several occasions and
were finally abandoned a few years ago.
When Slovakia became an independent
republic in 1993, it asked for three historical
sites in the Spis region to be included on
Unesco's World Heritage List: the wooden
village of Vlkolinec, the mining village of
Banska Stiavnica and Spis castle. In
December 1993 the sites were added to the
List.
'We need tourists'
Eva Spalekova, the director of the Spis
museum, is responsible for administering
the castle. She received us in her office in
Levoca, across the road from St. James's
church. "We have calculated that restora¬
tion workwill take ten years and cost about
$1.6 million," she explained. "And we're
going to have a hard time raising this sum
without international help." Last year part
of the ramparts collapsed, and the rest
had to be shored up. But work was delayed
by an unusually hard winter and the
extremely strongwinds that blow at certain
times of the year. We noticed a huge crack
in another wall that supports the keep.
"We're counting heavily on tourists," Eva
Spalekova continued, "who pay a small
entrance fee. Their presence is a great
encouragement to us. We need them."
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Spis castle is part of a complex of
medieval military, political and religious
monuments Zehra, Spissky Podhradie
and Spisska Kapitula that has no equal in
central and eastern Europe. The sites form
part of the castle's estates and are associ¬
ated with it on the World Heritage List. In
the charming village ofZehra at the foot of
the chalky hill, a staircase leads to the late-
thirteenth-century church of the Holy
Spirit with its immaculate white walls.
Remarkable frescoes dating from the thir¬
teenth to the seventeenth centuries line
the interior, but they are under attack from
mildew and will not survive much longer
without restoration.
The little town of Spissky Podhradie at
the foot of the castle was razed by the Tar¬
tars in 1241 but rebuilt two centuries later.
A fine example of medieval town plan¬
ning, it also has a romanesque parish
church and seventeenth-century Renais¬
sance-style houses.
Standing above the town, of which it
now forms part, Spisska Kapitula was orig¬
inally a fortified religious complex and is
certainly the most astonishing site on the
old feudal estate. The castle provost lived
there in the monastery of St. Martin, which
has not survived. Despite the Tartar inva¬
sion in the thirteenth century and the fre¬
quent Bulgarian raids that forced the
inhabitants to build fortifications that are
still intact, many architectural vestiges of
the complex have survived. Within the
oval area enclosed by its ramparts a maze
of narrow streets climb to St. Martin's
cathedral. Founded in the thirteenth cen¬
tury and added to over the years, the cadie-
dral is a blend of romanesque, Gothic,
Renaissance and baroque elements. In
1819 the first teacher-training college in
the kingdom of Hungary was opened in
the adjoining episcopal palace, which is
mainly Gothic. The hamlet's twenty- three
listed buildings belong to the Catholic
Church and are much in need of repair,
especially the old houses along the main
street, most ofwhich are in ruins.
It is urgent that the international com¬
munity should become aware of the uni¬
versal quality of Spis castle and the three
sites associated with it. Without its aid, this
unique medieval ensemble and the mas¬
terpieces of Gothic and Renaissance art
that it contains may one day disappear.
A party of schoolchildren climb
the narrow path to the castle
(above) before making a
spectacular tour of the
ramparts (opposite page).
EDOUARD BAILBY
is a French journalist who has
been a correspondent with the
weekly L'Express and a press
officer in Unesco's Office of
Public Information. He is the
author of guides to Cuba (6th
edition, 1993) and Hungary
(1991), published by Arthaud,
Paris.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
portrait
Hryhoriy Skovoroda
An Enlightenment philosopher ofthe Ukraine
byTatianaZolozova
40
IT n an old district of Kiev, the Podol, a monu¬
mental statue looks out over Peter Mogila
-L Academy Square. It depicts a gently smiling
man who looks for all the world as if he has just
stopped for a chat with the bystanders. He is
wearing a simple Cossack's outfit, and slung over
his shoulder is his faithful knapsack in which one
can easily imagine a flute, a Hebrew Bible and a few
manuscripts. The monument is a memorial to
Hryhoriy Skovoroda, one of the Ukraine's most
brilliant thinkers. Engraved on the pedestal
beneath the statue is the epitaph he wrote for
himself: "The world wanted to take me over, but it
didn't succeed". The words sum up the beliefs, the
destiny and the thought ofa man who sacrificed a
clerical and university career and abandoned the
comforts of life as a court poet and musician,
choosing instead to live in freedom as an itinerant
philosopher.
Skovoroda was born in 1722 to a Cossack family.
After studying the Bible and learning Latin and
singing at the school in his native village, Cher-
nuhy, at sixteen he entered the Peter Mogila
Academy, the leading university in eastern Europe
and the most prestigious Western-style establish¬
ment in the Ukraine at that time. While there he
studied the works ofgreat European thinkers such
as Bacon, Descartes, Leibniz, Locke, Spinoza and
Bruno. In 1742 he went as a singer to the court of
the Tsarina Elizabeth in Saint Petersburg, but he
did not take to court life and returned to Kiev to
continue his philosophical and theological studies.
When the time came for him to leave the Academy,
it was suggested that he enter holy orders, but he
decided instead to accept a diplomatic mission
that would take him to many countries over the
next four years. Back in the Ukraine, he taught
poetry in a seminary at Pereiaslov, not far from
Kiev, then at the high school in Harkiv. But his
modern teaching methods created a scandal, and
he was forced to turn his back on official institu¬
tions. At this point the richest, most exciting and
most fruitful period ofhis life began.
For twenty-eight years, between 1766 and 1794,
Hryhoriy Skovoroda wandered alone, taught in
market places, and wrote. During this time he wrote
eighteen philosophical treatises, works with tides
such as Narcissus: A Conversation about Knowing
Thyself, TheABCofthe Universe, and OftheAncient
World. He also produced a book of poetry, a col¬
lection of fables, seven translations ofancient clas
sics, and a voluminous correspondence in Latin
and Ukrainian with his pupils and friends.
In the spirit of the Enlightenment, he called
for the return of authentic values, a free spiritual
life and a just society. His adherence to modern
European philosophy did not prevent him from
admiring the scholars and poets ofGreekAntiquity,
the Old Testament prophets, St. Paul and St. Augus¬
tine and the sages of non-Christian religions. He
owed much to Plato and the teachings of the Bible,
which he regarded as the supreme expression of
human wisdom.
Skovoroda's poetry, the most outstanding poetry
written during the baroque golden age in the
Ukraine, is inseparable from his philosophy. In
addition to his philosophical and satirical stories
and poems, his investigations into the natural
rhythm of language and into types of poetry, we
owe a debt to this inspired poet for introducing a
profound feeling for nature into traditional
Ukrainian lyricism. He was the Slavic harbinger of
Romanticism.
Hryhoriy (Grigori) Skovoroda,
1722-1794.
TATIANA Z0L0Z0VA,
cultural attachée at the
Ukrainian embassy in France, is
the author of a book on French
instrumental music since 1944
(Kiev, 1989) and of many
articles and essays on the arts
and philosophy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
THE SEA'S
DWINDLING HARVEST
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
Tuna fishing in the
Mediterranean.
W!
f e are risking another dis¬
aster," says Eduardo
Loayaza, fisheries advisor
with the World Bank's Agriculture
and Natural Resources Department.
"There are too many fishing boats
chasing too few fish. It's like defor¬
estation but it's invisible because it's
happening under water." Who is to
blame? The fishermen, who have
been described as "the last race of
hunter-gatherers, out to snatch what
they can, while they can"? Govern¬
ments? International organizations,
which seem unable to enforce regu¬
lations drawn up after tough negoti¬
ations? Or technological progress
that makes fishing boats and equip¬
ment increasingly efficient?
A UNITED RESOURCE
On one point everyone is agreed:
the seas are emptying. Once they
were very full. There are more than
20,000 species ofmarine mammals
grouped into 350 families. Some
fish, such as cod, mackerel, sardine
and tuna, are migrators. Others such
as salmon and eel divide their lives
between sea water and fresh water.
Others still, such as grey mullet, red
mullet, sole and skate, live near
coasts. Four-fifths of the earth's
animal life lives in the seas and
oceans, which provide the world's
population with an average of4% of
its food. In Asia alone more than a
billion people depend on fish and
seafood as their major source of
animal protein, while approxi¬
mately 60% of the people in devel¬
oping countries derive 40% or more
of their animal protein from fish.
How are fish stocks evaluated?
At the beginning of the 20th cen¬
tury the countries of northern
Europe created the International
Council for Exploration of the Sea
and launched the first programmes
to measure the impact of fishing on
fish resources. In the 1940s mathe¬
matical models were established
and were widely used by special¬
ists. For several decades, attention
focused on fish resources and their
management, and quotas were
fixed.
More recently the question of
resources management began to be
studied by fisheries biologists,
whose mission, as described by
Jacques Guegen of the French
Research Institute for Exploiting the
Sea (IFREMER), is "to quantify
marine animal (or plant) stocks in
order to define the catch that may
be taken without endangering a
species' continued existence." Fish¬
eries biologists have several
methods at their disposal. One is
experimentally fishing a given stock
(i.e. fish with similar biological char¬
acteristics living in the same region)
and then extrapolating the results to
the entire geographical area.
Another is to count the eggs mixed
in with the plankton in spawning
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
WORLD I
42
SWITZERLAND'S DYING FORESTS: A
FALSE ALARM?
In 1983 dire warnings went out in Switzer¬
land that the country's forests were dying
and that something had to be done quickly
to curb the air pollution that was killing
them. Measures were duly taken, not all of
them very popular. Speed limits were
reduced; unleaded fuel was promoted,
and catalytic convertor exhaust-pipes
imposed. Four years later the picture
already looked less black, and today sci¬
entists are saying that ten years' study is
too short to confirm that the deterioration
will continue. Switzerland's forests are still
there, although it is true that they are not
in the pink of health. The scientists refuse
to dramatize, however, and are calling for
more data. The same goes for global
warming. Perhaps we should wait a while
before planting palm-trees in Siberia.
CAN HUNTERS TURN
GAME-KEEPERS?
The Pan-African News Agency (PANA)
reports that wildlife resource manage¬
ment is still posing problems in West
Africa. The increasing rarity of game is
due mainly to the proliferation of firearms,
the spread of cash crops and pastoral
farming. In Senegal, for example, wildlife
specialists point out that entrusting wildlife
management to hunters is ineffective, and
that game is disappearing from the wide
open spaces that were once reserved for
traditional hunting. Data needs to be col¬
lected on the structure and reproductive
capacities of each animal population and
policies should be unified under a single
authority that would reconcile wildlife
protection and hunting. In Senegal, wildlife
protection is in the hands of the national
parks department, and the department of
water, forest and hunting issues hunting
permits, usually without knowing the state
of existing stocks.
MACEDONIA'S THREATENED LAKES
Environmentalists in the Republic of Mace¬
donia have launched an appeal to save
Lakes Ohrid, Dojran and Prespa. Lake
Dojran is shared with Greece, and Lake
Ohrid. which is included on UNESCO's
World Heritage List, with Albania. 80 per
cent of the animal species found in Lake
Ohrid are endemic and of ancient origin,
and the lake is known as a "museum of
living fossils". The level of Lake Dojran
has fallen to 2.5 metres below the min¬
imum set by an agreement between
Greece and Macedonia, and that of Lake
Prespa. which is shared by Macedonia,
Greece and Albania, has dropped 5 metres
in the past 14 years. Studies are currently
underway to determine whether this is
due to natural causes or human activity
FURTHER
READING
« Fisheries
Enforcement
Issues, OECD,
1994.
Reports ofthe
Committee on
Fisheries, FAO,
1993.
<*" It can't go on
forever,
The implications
of the global
grab for
declining fish
stocks,
Greenpeace
International,
1993.
grounds. Alternatively, schools of
fish can be detected by means of
sonar, a technique used in subma¬
rine warfare. Mathematical models
are used to establish a link between
fishing methods and the amount of
fish caught. They enable experts
working in the laboratory to draw
practical conclusions, e.g. calling
for larger mesh in fishing nets,
increasing or reducing the amount
of fish caught or modifying the
fishing season.
According to statistics published
by the Food and Agriculture Orga¬
nization of the United Nations
(FAO), marine catches grew from
20 million tons in 1950 to reach 86
million tons in 1989. In a document
published in 1993 FAO stated that
"the world fish catch has increased
more than four times in the past 40
years, but the over- intensive use of
modern technology and search for
short-term benefits, coupled with
continuous government support
for otherwise uneconomic produc¬
tion, has had a devastating impact
on many important fish stocks.
Commercial fleets have driven
some species to commercial extinc¬
tion and sometimes close to bio¬
logical extinction, by destroying
ecosystems such as coral reefs and
algae fields." In 1989 there were over
one million large-scale and twice
as many smaller scale fishing
boats on the world's oceans and
seas. A factory ship can freeze and
store up to 20 tons offish fillets per
day taken from 40 to 50 tons of fresh
fish. But to operate economically
The fish market in
Tokyo (Japan).
such vessels need to be supplied
with large catches. Boats are there¬
fore constantly being modified and
increased in size.
Modern fishing techniques
include the use of long-lines that
may be up to 100 km long; bottom
trawls that rake the sea bed; purse
seine nets (up to 1,000 metres long
and 100 metres high) that encircle
shoals offish; gill-nets (up to 60 km
long) that are made ofhard-to-detect
nylon filament and are maintained
vertical by a system of floats and
weights. The non-governmental
organization Greenpeace reports
that one of the world's biggest trawl
nets measures 110 metres by 170
metres at its mouth and has an
overall capacity of 30,000 m2, large
enough to encircle twelve Boeing
747's. An even bigger net, now under
construction in Iceland, will have a
30% larger opening. FAO has clas¬
sified almost every commercial fish
species in every ocean and sea as
"depleted", "fully-exploited" or
"over-exploited".
Fish are a limited resource. For¬
tunately they are highly fertile, but
they need time to reproduce. It takes
cod, for example, seven or eight
years to reach sexual maturity. As
Alain Maucorps, of the Department
of Fish Resources of IFREMER,
writes, "Extreme overexploitation
occurs when not enough young fish
reach reproductive age. There is a
fertile biomass (the cumulative
weight of the stock) threshold
beneath which the number of
exploitable fish and thus the very
survival of the stock can be seri¬
ously endangered. Simulation
models demonstrate that as soon
as this threshold is reached, the
stock can disappear very quickly."
WASTE
Catching fish when they are too
young is thus dangerous for the
species. And yet from 50% to 80% of
the hake caught in the Bay ofBiscay
(between France and Spain) are
smaller than the regulation min¬
imum because net mesh-size is too
small. Waste is another very serious
problem. In Guyana, for example,
for every 5,000 tons ofshrimp taken,
fishermen throw away 20,000 tons
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
British fishermen in
the North Sea.
of dead or dying fish they don't
want. The International Council for
Exploration of the Sea estimates
that 80 million cod were thrown
away off the north Norwegian coast
inl986andl987 because they were
too small to sell, a waste of nearly
100,000 tons. Other annual catches
of which Greenpeace is strongly
critical are the 100,000 blue sharks,
the 48,000 GulfofMexico sea turtles,
birds (an estimated 750,000,
including 44,000 albatross) and
marine mammals such as whales
and dolphins, especially in the trop¬
ical eastern Pacific where the purse
seine nets used by tuna fishers
imprison not only fish but also
cetaceans looking for the same
food.
SAVING FISH TO SAVE FISHING
In a document calling for the pro¬
hibition of driftnets, the French
environmental group Equipe
Cousteau considers that without a
total ban on this gear "fishing will
soon be nothing more than a
memory". The Cousteau team
recalls that "in 1991 the United
Nations General Assemblyvoted for
a ban on driftnets longer than 2.5
kms., to take effect in 1992. The
United States, then the European
Union, decided to adopt this rec¬
ommendation, but France, where
about forty vessels practise tuna
fishing with driftnets, was granted a
special exemption."
The United Nations Convention
on the Law of the Sea was adopted
in 1982, and although it has not yet
entered into force, its principles are
widely accepted as customary by
fishing and coastal countries. In the
Convention, the principle of free
access to fisheries resources is aban¬
doned and fish, previously consid¬
ered res nullius (belonging to no
one), have become res communes
(whose users can be defined at the
international level). Coastal states
have Exclusive Economic Zones
extending 200 miles from their
shores (except in the Mediter¬
ranean) in which they must monitor
fishing boats and the gear they use.
But no one really has the means to
do this.
Another problem lies with devel¬
oping countries which transfer their
fishing rights, then see their waters
plundered by industrial fishing
fleets which deprive them of an
indispensable source of protein.
This is particularly hard to accept
when the fish is converted into fer¬
tilizer and food for domestic ani¬
mals, chicken, cattle and even . . .
pen-reared fish!
The situation is critical. It remains
to be seen which will die out first,
the fish or the fishermen.
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions. Since
1985 she has
been associated
with the
WANAD- Unesco
training
programme/or
African news
agency
journalists.
Processing fish on
board a French
trawler.
WORLD
excessive use of pesticides by apple-
growers near Lake Prespa has resulted in
soil and water pollution. An appeal for aid
has been launched by the "Ecological
Movement of Macedonia" in Skopje, Tel.:
(389) 9 1 220 5 1 8; Fax: (389) 91331 434.
CHILDREN MEET THE FOUR
ELEMENTS
An Indian scientific journalist, Dilip M.
Salwi, has sent us four short children's
books written by him and charmingly illus¬
trated by Atanu Roy. Clear, easy-to-read
and informative, they introduce children to
the four elements: air, fire, earth and water.
Already published in Hindi and English,
they could well be translated into other
languages. The author can be contacted c/o
Ratna Sagar Publishers. Virat Bkavan,
Mukherjee Nagar Commercial complex,
Delhi 110009, India. Tel.: 7122505.
WOOD GETS
THE GREEN LIGHT
Swiss architects are rediscovering wood.
Engineers have calculated that it takes
from five to ten times more energy to
build with metal and concrete than with
wood. Solidity and quality being equal,
wood comes out on top. It takes 3.8 times
more energy to manufacture a 7.5-metre
beam using steel than it does using wood,
5 times more using concrete and 1 6 times
more using aluminium. The same process
causes 1 1 times more pollution using steel
than using wood, 20 times more using
cement and 50 times more using alu¬
minium. In view of the widespread belief
that wood is highly inflammable, it is inter¬
esting to learn that insurance companies
and firemen are encouraging its use as a
building material.
A YOUNG PEOPLE'S
ENVIRONMENTAL SUMMIT
A 10-day Global Youth Environmental
Summit is being organized in the United
States for June 1995 by the Thompson
Valley High School (Colorado) and the
Niles West High School, Skokie (Illinois) in
collaboration with the United Nations
University for Peace in Costa Rica. Two
students from each U.S. state and from
each country in the world will attend, as
well as political leaders from different parts
of the world. The summit's major objective
is to educate participants on environ¬
mental issues and to help them "acquire
the social action skills necessary to create
positive change in their community". For
further information, contact Nicole Reak,
Thompson Valley High School, 1 669 Eagle
Drive, Loveland, Colorado 80537, U.S.A.
Tel.: (303) 669-080 1 : Fax: (303) 667- 1 628.
u
<
Z
LU
LU
C¿
(J}
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
u
I-
<
al
In November 1993, El Tiempo, a daily newspaper
in the Peruvian city of Piura, decided to launch a
tree-planting campaign. To carry out this "Green Cru¬
sade", the paper called on concerned citizens and insti¬
tutions to make a joint effort to defend the environ¬
ment. A brigade of volunteer foresters was created,
consisting of some fifty agronomy students from the
national university of Piura and the Almirante Miguel
Grau Advanced Institute of Technology. Its task was to
mobilize the population, and draw up plans for green
spaces and planting points. The Provincial Council
chipped in with a donation of3,000 saplings, the Regional
Department of Agriculture gave 5,000 more, and con¬
tributions were also received from the National Food
Aid Programme, the College of Engineers and non¬
governmental organizations.
The aim of the Green Crusade was to create 33 parks
and green spaces in a year in some 50 educational cen¬
tres. "Everybodywho wanted" was invited to join in, the
only qualification being that volunteers had to be ready
to work hard. The participants attended a three-day
course at the university in order to learn how to plant
and reproduce the chosen species of forest, ornamental
and fruit trees. It might have been feared that the initial
enthusiasm would wane after the first flurry ofactivity,
but that was not how things turned out. El Tiempo
awarded prizes to the most productive groups. And
the young volunteers who worked to the end of the
project received a professional training programme
certificate from the university, as well as a straw hat
and a pair ofpruning shears.
February 1994 was declared "ForestAction Month",
and the people of Piura were invited to a planting ses¬
sion attended by political, military and religious leaders.
Two hundred trees were planted on the Plaza Civica in
the San Martin neighbourhood. In March, which was
proclaimed "Tree Month", a lecture was given on envi¬
ronmental policy. April was devoted to environmental
education, and May to an awareness campaign aimed
at mothers. Meanwhile, 500 saplings were planted at Fe
y Alegria High School in the El Indio district. Teachers
taught their students how to use a tree-nursery, fer¬
tilize and irrigate, design gardens, and prune and graft
trees.
Ten thousand trees have already been planted in
twenty green spaces. The most significant result so far
is that the people of Piura are now convinced that the
environment must be protected and that steps must be
taken to improve living conditions in general. Now all
that remains to be done is tend the trees a safe bet
given the enthusiasm with which El Tiempo intends
to continue its campaign for the greening of Piura.
LUZ MARIA HELGUERO,
Director, El Tiempo,
Jr. Ayacucho 751, apartado 1 14, Piura, Peru.
Telephone: (51) (74) 32 51 41.
Fax: (51) (74) 32 74 78.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
globa view... ajo
S.O.S. Children
To mark the close of the International Year of the Family,
here is a portrait of a family with a difference
I In the space of ten years, Virginie
I Kankoua has had thirteen children,
five ofwhom are now old enough to leave
home. One of her older daughters, who
suffered from depression as a child, has
started a small sewing business. Another
has opened a beauty parlour. Their mother
is proud to see them well integrated into
society. It is her greatest reward for the
long years of hard work, patience and
devotion she has given to these children.
Child care a new
yardstick of progress
The Progress ofNations 1994, the latest
issue of an annual report published by
UNICEF, the United Nations Children's
Fund, ranks the world's nations
"according to their achievements in child
health, nutrition, education, family plan¬
ning and progress for women". Based on
data collected from various United Nations
agencies (including Unesco), the report
shows that some developing countries
meet the needs of their people better
than some wealthier countries. We learn,
for example, that Sri Lanka and Zimbabwe
both have a per capita Gross National
Product (GNP) of less than $600 dollars
yet still manage to provide 90 per cent of
their children with at least four years of pri¬
mary education, i.e. twice that of Brazil
with an annual per capita GNP of nearly
$3,000. Nearly 30 per cent of the children
In Guatemala are suffering from malnu¬
trition, but less than 5 per cent in
Paraguay, which is not much wealthier.
Viet Nam has a per capita GNP of only
$240 but its child-survival rate is higher
than that of Algeria, whose GNP is about
seven times higher. Disparities like these
show that social development does not
automatically result from economic
progress but constitutes a goal in itself
that should be pursued and evaluated
directly.
Not one of them is a natural child of hers,
for "Mama Virginie" works in the S.O.S.
Children's Village ofKara, Togo, where she
takes in orphaned or abandoned children,
cares for them, sees that they go to school
and loves them.
The village ofKara, built between 1974
and 1979, today consists often houses, an
administrative building, a kindergarten,
a primary school, a nutrition centre, a
farm, a cafeteria and a youth club. Nine
"mums", helped out by five "aunts" live
there with about ten children each.
Brothers and sisters are never separated.
The director, the educators and the main¬
tenance men are all "dads". The village
also has sponsors. The children don't know
them since they tend to live far away from
the village, but thanks to their material
support, their presence is felt.
There are 315 other S.O.S. Children's
villages in 122 countries. The first one was
founded in 1949 in Imst (Austria), where a
young medical student named Hermann
Gmeiner had the idea ofbringing together
war orphans and widows or unmarried
women in a few houses that he had built
for them. Ten years later the idea had
caught on in France and elsewhere in
Europe. In the 1960s it spread to Asia,
South America and Africa.
In 1964 the International Federation
of S.O.S. Children's Villages was founded
and today it is the biggest non-govern¬
mental organization working on behalf of
children in distress. Based in Innsbruck
(Austria), it has consultative status with
the United Nations and Unesco.
From Imst in the Tyrol Mountains to
Antananarivo in Madagascar, from
Busigny, France, to Bamako, Mali, from
Choglamsar in northern India to Teguci-
galp, Honduras, from Pokhara, Nepal, to
Port-au-Prince in Haiti, S.O.S. Children's
villages are giving thousands ofchildren a
chance to enjoy a real childhood.
To subscribe to the S.O.S. Children's
magazine Villages dejoie (French only), to
make a donation or sponsor a village,
please contact Village d'enfants S.O.S.,
6, Cité Monthiers, 75009 Paris.
Tel.: (33-1) 4526-7179; Fax: (33-1) 4995-0285.
tib ew
The 1994 UN Population
Award
The 1994 United Nations Population
Award has been won by to President Hosni
Mubarak of Egypt and by the Turkish
Foundation for Health and Family Planning.
The award is made annually to persons or
institutions who have raised public aware¬
ness about population problems and pos¬
sible solutions. "We are not only hon¬
ouring the laureates. . . ," declared UN
Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali
at the award ceremony, "we are also sig¬
nalling our continuing concern for people's
needs and aspirations for a peaceful world
in balance with population, environment
and development."
More than 100 million
victims of sexual
mutilation
Female sexual mutilation is commonly
practised in 28 African countries, and
the World Health Organization (WHO) esti¬
mates the number of women and girl vic¬
tims of these practices at between 85 and
114 million. No religion prescribes these
mutilations which belong to traditions
intended to preserve virginity and repress
female sexuality. Apart from their
degrading and traumatic nature, they may
lead to death, haemorrhaging, tetanus,
septicemia and the spread of Aids. In the
long run they compromise sexual activi¬
ties and may cause infections and com¬
plications during childbirth. Combating
such practices is difficult, and according
to a recent WHO report the women them¬
selves must take the lead. Several orga¬
nizations, including the Inter-African Com¬
mittee for the Elimination of Harmful
Traditional Practices, are trying to con¬
vince women that they can renounce such
customs without betraying their cultural
values.
Further information may be found in
Mother and Child Health and Family
Planning: Current Needs and Future
Planning, a report by the Director-
General of WHO to the WHO Executive
Board, 12 January 1994. 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
World peace begins at home
Published below are extractsfrom a letter by the Chinese thinker Cai Yuanpei
(Ts'ai Yuan-pei; 1863-1940) whichfirstappeared in Correspondance, the
journal ofthe International Institute ofIntellectual Co-operation, in 1933. In
the letter Cai Yuanpei discusses what he regards as the regrettable propensity
to dissociate private moralityfrom public morality and to demand ofthe
individual the kind ofrational and altruistic behaviour that is not expected
ofthe state.
to his own state but hostile to the other
Chinese states; in the secondary stage of
world peace, everyone is loyal to the Chi¬
nese states, while hostile to those outside
China; in the final stage ofworld peace, all
the barbarian (non-Chinese) states, large
and small, far and near, have come up to
the same level of civilization, and every
citizen conducts himself as a perfect gen¬
tleman."
To the Chairman of the International
Committee of Intellectual Co-operation
Academia Sínica (Shanghai)
In the book Ta Hsueh ("The Great Learning")
we find a unifying conception ofworld order
which seeks to lay its foundations in the
psychology of the individual.
This book was written two thousand
years ago byTseng Ts'an, a disciple ofCon¬
fucius, later incorporated in the Li-Ki by
the Han scholars, and finally chosen, as
one of the Four Books to be studied by every
schoolboy, by the scholars of the Sung
Dynasty. . . . The passage I wish to refer to
reads as follows:
"In ancient times, those who wished to
make clear their virtue before the world
would first put their country in order; those
who wished to put their country in order
would first bring about right relationships
in their family; those who wished to bring
about right relationships in their family
would first cultivate their own self; those
who wished to cultivate their own self
Text selected and presented
by Edgardo Canton
46
would first rectify their own heart; those
who wished to rectify their own heart
would first make their will sincere; and
those who wished to make their will sin¬
cere would first try to attain knowledge;
and they would attain knowledge by
studying matter.
"When matter is studied, then knowl¬
edge may be attained; when knowledge
is attained, then the will becomes sincere;
when the will is sincere, then the heart is
rectified; when the heart is rectified, then
the self is cultivated; when the self is cul¬
tivated, then there exist right relationships
in the family; when right relationships
exist in the family, then the country is in
order; when the countries are in order,
then there is peace in the world."
The end to be aimed at is described as
"world peace", while the method of
attaining this peace begins with "making
clear one's virtue before the world". This
virtue is regarded as rational conduct, and
proceeds, neither from superstition, nor
from blind acceptance, but from the exer¬
cise of intelligence. The development of
intelligence is again described as the
attainment of knowledge through the
objective study of matter. It is therefore
characteristically free from theological
and metaphysical fancies.
The conception of world order was
further elucidated in the Kung-Yang Com¬
mentary on the Spring and Autumn
Annals. According to Kung-Yang, a Con-
fucianist, there are three stages in the
development ofworld order, as follows:
"In a world of chaos, everyone is loyal
WELL EDUCATED CITIZENS
Expressed in modern terminology, the first
stage is the stage of nationalism; the
second stage, when one is loyal to all the
Chinese states while hostile to the others,
may be regarded as rather similar to the
American Monroe doctrine and the con¬
ception ofa federation ofEurope; the final
stage is more or less foreshadowed by the
League of Nations.
"Peace" is thus regarded as a stage
when all the large and small, distant and
near states are treated alike. The final ref¬
erence to every citizen conducting himself
as a perfect gentleman points to the stage
when all should be so mentally disciplined
that they can successively form the ever-
widening units which culminate in a world
of universal peace.
European philosophers have evolved
theories wherein either individual liberty
or state sovereignty is pushed to the
extreme, both ofwhich are incomprehen¬
sible to the Chinese mind. The Chinese
scholars think that the successive units of
human society from the cell to the indi¬
vidual, the group and the higher groups
like the state and the world differ in size
and complexity, but not in their behav¬
iour.
What is regarded as good or evil in a
small unit is also regarded in the same
way in the larger units. Chinese scholars
are sincerely puzzled when one holds that
honesty is a virtue as between individuals
but could be ignored in international
diplomacy; that while mutual considera-
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
V
tion, as stated in the Confucian or Chris¬
tian Golden Rule, should be the rule for
intercourse between individuals, the
reverse attitude ofaggression and whole¬
sale slaughter should be countenanced;
that while selfishness is regarded as a
shame and self-sacrifice a virtue in indi¬
vidual conduct, self-aggrandizement
should be the norm for international poli¬
cies; that while in individual conduct
chivalry consists in helping the weak and
defenceless, the dictum that might is right
should be accepted as the rule in inter¬
national relationships.
A NEWWORLD ORDER
The League of Nations is, I believe, com¬
mitted to a new conception ofworld order
and dedicated as an instrument to abolish
dishonesty, unkindness, unrighteousness
and lack of mutual consideration from
international politics. The International
Committee of Intellectual Co-operation
has especially the duty of bringing about
the support of the scholars of the world for
this new conception. If it is accepted that
the successive units ofhuman society are
causally related as described above, then
we may deduce two principles which are
worthy of our own effort and may well
cover our multifarious activities:
1) All supporters of the idea of intel¬
lectual co-operation should try to live up
to the norm of individual conduct, which
will thus serve as the ideal for group con¬
duct also.
2) All should co-operate in the work
of objective study and investigation of
facts bearing on all international prob¬
lems, analyse the causes and effects and on
the strength of this objective study make
recommendations for the consideration of
the proper authorities.
I believe the above two proposals are
well in accord with the Confucian political
philosophyand with the aims and objects of
the Institute of Intellectual Co-operation.
CAI YUANPEI
K'ung-Fu-Tzu
(or Confucius), circa
551-479 B.C., a portrait
dating from the
18th century.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
anniversary
José Carlos MarIÁTEGUI (1894-1930)
José Carlos Mariátegui, a wood engraving by the
Mexican artist Alberto Beltran.
Peruvians called him and still do
the Amauta, the Quechua lan¬
guage word for "master". In his
lifetime, and after his untimely death at the
age of thirty-five, he was regarded as a
master not only in Peru but in many other
parts of Latin America, and today, more
than sixty years after his death, the influ¬
ence of his life and work can still be felt
thanks to the publication ofseveral dozen
of his books, his letters and much of his
journalism.
José Carlos Mariátegui was born in 1894
and died in 1930. His short life, in the last
few years of which he was confined to a
wheelchair and suffered the amputation of
a leg, was remarkable for its richness and
creativity. As one of his biographers has
observed, his considerable output ofwork
is "a triumph of intelligence over pain and
an unceasing battle of the will to domi¬
nate a precarious destiny".
He stood apart from the Peruvian and
Latin American intellectual landscape in
the early part of the century. This land¬
scape, which his tragic life and the pow¬
erful influence of his activities were to
. 0 transform, was then dominated by the
Ho modernist movement in literature and by
Witness to an age
the early working-class and student strug¬
gles. A frail young man from a poor provin¬
cial family, he became an apprentice
printer on the Lima daily, La Prensa, in
1909, and while still an adolescent con¬
tributed light pieces to the paper under
the pen name Juan Chronicler. He soon
founded and ran an opposition paper, La
Razón, an act that forced him to leave for
Europe where he spent three years and, as
he said later, "got married and espoused
the ideas I would later defend". Right to the
end ofhis life he was publisher and editor
of the cultural and literary journalAmauta,
which had a crucial influence on Peru's
intellectual development.
Mariátegui showed remarkable insight
as a witness and analyst of the spiritual
and material crisis of his time and as a
polemicist and popularizer ofcontempo¬
rary ideas, from surrealism and avant-
garde literature (including the work of
Joyce) to socialism (starting with Marx,
although he also grasped the importance
of Gramsci with astonishing intuition and
was a lucid interpreter of Sorel and Croce)
and psychoanalysis. One ofhis many note¬
worthy accomplishments was to discover
and explore the affinity between Freudi¬
anism and Marxism.
The development of a theory ofmyth as
a driving force in modern man's behav¬
iour and a clear-sighted analysis of the
spell cast on the European masses by their
demagogical and populist leaders were
important features of Mariátegui's work
in the 1920s, when he also organized a
trade union and the first Peruvian Marxist
party, which he called "socialist" rather
than "communist". He became swept up in
the turmoil of the times, was condemned
by the Communist International and then
virtually excommunicated from the move¬
ment. The perspicacity of his social
thinking was matched by the indepen¬
dence ofhis political activities and he suf¬
fered the consequences.
It was in the columns of Amauta that
the distinctive nature of Peru and of Latin
America in general was discussed for the
first time in a universal context. Mariátegui
byAlfredo Pita
took part in the debate on the indigenous
Americans a first attempt to understand
in depth and from the inside the cultural
schism that prevented Peru from being a
nation. But when the problems of educa¬
tion and agricultural production in Russia
became headline news, for example, he
turned his attention to them and also
wrote of Jean Jaurès and Rolland, of Bar¬
busse and Valéry, ofPirandello and Trotsky.
Although confined to a wheelchair, the
master continued to work indefatigably,
and welcomed a wide circle of people to
his home in Lima students, workers and
trade unionists, poets such as Martín Adán
and José Maria Eguren, and intellectuals
like the liberal American writer and
thinker, Waldo Franck.
In 1927 the Peruvian government
banned Amauta and Labor, another
journal Mariátegui had founded in support
of the working class, and he thought of
going into exile again. "I prefer exile," he
wrote, "to resigning myself to silence.
Without Amauta and Labor, without a
platform from which to express myself, I
shan't be able to resist my overwhelming
need to breathe the air of a free land."
Amauta reappeared, however, and its
editor stayed. He then published the
extremely influential Seven Interpretative
Essays on Peruvian Reality.
His death brought an end to an
inspiring and many-sided career and
sounded the death knell for Amauta, a
very great loss for Latin American letters.
From 1923 to 1930 Mariátegui had written
in Amauta of revolution and the crisis of
socialism, of the links between revolution
and intellectuals, of the processes of Fas¬
cism, the awakening ofthe Orient and the
rise ofanti-Semitism. What other themes
might he have tackled ifhe had lived ten or
twenty years longer?
ALFREDO PITA
¡s a Peruvian journalist who is presently working with
Agence France-Presse in Paris. He has published
several collections of poems and short stories, and
a novel, El cazador ausente (1994; "The Absent
Hunter").
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
A FRESH LOOK AT THE PAST
Presenting the first volume of the new
HISTORY OF
HUMANITY
IN 1946, UNESCO's first Director-Gen¬
eral, Julian Huxley, wrote that "The
chief task before the humanities today
would seem to be to help in constructing
a history of the development of the
human mind, notably in its highest cul¬
tural achievements". With these words,
Huxley set forth the idea which led to the
production under UNESCO's auspices of
a six-volume History ofthe Scientific and
Cultural Development of Mankind, an
enterprise which began in 1950 and took
almost twenty years to complete.
The ink of the first edition was barely
dry before Paolo E. de Berrêdo Carneiro,
President of the International Scientific
Committee in charge of the project, was
thinking about bringing it up to date.
"The day will come when what we have
written will, in its turn, have to be
replaced," he wrote. "I like to think that
our successors will attend to this, and
that a revised edition of the work we
have begun may be published at the
dawn of a new millennium."
Now UNESCO is embarking on the
publication of an entirely revised and
updated edition of this major work. Enti¬
tled History of Humanity and com¬
prising seven volumes, the new history is
far more than a simple revision. Both in
structure and content it is radically dif¬
ferent from its predecessor. "If the first
history could be thought of as a summing
up," says S.J. De Laet, editor-in-chief of
Volume I of the new History of
Humanity, "the second is more like a
new point of departure."
Published in June 1994, Volume I is
entitled Prehistory and the Beginnings
of Civilization. It consists of two parts.
The first covers the period from the ori¬
gins of humankind to the beginnings of
food production; the second continues
the story to the appearance of the first
societies, 5,000 years ago. Some forty
internationally known specialists have
contributed studies of the world's dif¬
ferent geo-cultural areas from Africa
to China, from Europe to the Andes,
from North America to Australia
giving a comprehensive picture of the
infancy of humankind.
With more than 700 pages of richly
documented text, as well as detailed bib¬
liographies, many figures, tables and
maps, this is an attractively produced
book as well as an important contribu¬
tion to scholarship.
Christophe Wondji
Head of UNESCO's Section of General
and Regional Histories
History ofHumanity, Volume I, Prehistory
and the Beginnings of Civilization,
edited by S.J. De Laet,
co-edited by A.H. Dani, J.L. Lorenzo,
R.B. Nunoo, published by UNESCO, Paris
& Routledge, London, 1994
(850 French francs from UNESCO;
£85.00 from Routledge).
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, pages 3, 30: Baldev © Sygma,
Paris. Pages 5, 6: Christian Irrgang ©
Wolf Lepenies, Berlin. Pages 8-9, 23,
24-25: Abbas © Magnum, Paris.
Pages 10-11,22 (above), 28, 3 1 : ©
Roland and Sabrina Michaud, Paris.
Page 1 2 (left): © Gamma, Paris.
Page 1 2 (right): Roger Sandler ©
Cosmos, Paris. Page 13: © Digital
Art/Westlight/Cosmos, Paris. Pages
14, 1 7: © Patrick Lagès, Paris. Page
15: ©Jean-Loup Charmet, Musée
Carnavalet, Paris. Page 1 6: Laurence
Chaperon © Gamma, Paris. Page 1 9:
© Alain Guillou, Le Croisic, France.
Page 20: © Tapabor, Paris. Page 2 1 :
©Jean-Loup Charmet, Bibliothèque
des Arts Décoratifs, Paris. Pages 22-
23: Alain Mingam © Gamma, Paris.
Pages 26, 27: Benito © Sygma, Paris.
Pages 32-33: Atlas des Religions ©
Plon/Quarante-quatrième Parallèle,
Paris. Page 35: UNESCO/lnes Forbes.
Pages 36, 37, 38, 39: © Edouard
Bailby, Paris. Page 40: © Tatiana
Zolozova. Page 4 1 : Jean Gaumy ©
Magnum, Paris. Page 42: Bruno
Barbey © Magnum, Paris. Page 43:
Harry Gruyaert © Magnum, Paris.
Page 44: Veiller © Jacana, Paris. Page
47: © Explorer Archives, Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Page 48: © Peruvian
Embassy, Paris.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1994
50
JANUARY. DESERTS. Interview with Théodore Monod. The dry
lands (M. Bâtisse). The call of the wilderness (J-C. Carrière). A place
of trials (M. Tajadod). A painter's paradise (M. Zaalouk). Screenplays
in the sand (M. Berrah). Hidden waters (D. Balland). A long look at
the world's arid lands (M. Bâtisse). Africa: learning to manage the
desert (M. Skouri). Greenwatch: Protecting wetlands (F. Bequette).
The price of peace (F. Mayor). Archives: A greater awareness of
truth (Rabindranath Tagore). Heritage: The Stone Age temples of
Malta (Ann Monsarrat). Books: (C. Wise). Music (I. Leymarie).
FEBRUARY. WORLDS WITHIN WORDS. Interview with Yves
Coppens. The gift of tongues (S. Wurm). Babel revisited (P.
Mühlhäusler). Nigeria's choice (A Bamgbose). Language death in
Siberia (V. Belikov). The chicken and the banana (compiled by S.
Wurm). Of gifts and gaffes (J. Tian). Greenwatch: Can Angkor be
saved? (F. Bequette). The spirit of Granada (F. Mayor). Archives: The
way to coexistence (A. Toynbee). Heritage: The royal palaces of
Abomey (J. Sopova). Music: (I. Leymarie).
MARCH. HUMAN RIGHTS. Interview with Edouard J. Maunick.
The birthright of humanity (F. Mayor). The U-word (I. Fall). NGOs:
the fight to be heard (S. Bessis). One and indivisible (A. Bernard). Free
speech democracy's watchdog (H. Darbishire). States of bondage
(M. Nowak). Secdplot for the future (S. Hessel). UNESCO: the rights
of all (F. Fournier). A new departure (A. Mock). Greenwatch: Small
islands: dreams and realities (F. Bequette). Dossier: The Vienna Con¬
ference. Heritage: Haiti: King Henry's fabulous works (F. Leary).
Archives: Venice: a picture of harmony (Le Corbusier).
APRIL. MODERN MANAGEMENT AND LOCAL TRADITIONS. (P.
d'lribarne). Interview with Jean Malaurie. Business cultures (G. Hof-
stcde). Togo: Going by the book (A. Henry and Y. Badjo). Tunisia:
They do it their way (R. Zghal). Mexico: Local loyalties: a hidden asset
(J. Ruffier and D. Villavicencio). Eastern Europe: Voices from the
past (T. Globokar). Japan: The new samurai Q. Harford). Green¬
watch: The national park dilemma (F. Bequette). Preventing pollution
(F. Mayor). Heritage: The Vallée de Mai (G. Lionnct). Archives: Art
and the home (Le Corbusier). Cziffra (S. Kol). Anniversary: Ulugh Beg,
the astronomer-king (J. Sopova). Books. Music: (I. Leymarie).
MAY. A NEW LOOK AT THE HISTORY OF COMMUNISM. Interview
with Trinh Xuan Thuan. An end and a beginning (F. Hartog). Russia:
Wanted: a new language (N. Kopossov). Romania: Past imperfect (Z
Petre). Georgia: The historian's responsibility (G. Charachidzé).
Poland: Myths that die hard (H. Samsonowicz). The Czech Republic:
Lost illusions (E. Schmidt-Hartmann). Bulgaria: When memory
plays tricks (L. Deyanova). UNESCO's historical works (C. Wondji).
Africa: An authentic picture (J. Dévisse). Greenwatch: Inventing
the urban future (F. Bequette). An active pact (F. Mayor). The Yoko¬
hama conference. Archives: The collectivist betrayal (T Mann). Her¬
itage: Quebec (A. Charbonneau, Y. Dcsloges and M. Lafrance).
JUNE. BIOTECHNOLOGY. Interview with Antoni Tapies. Biotech¬
nology for beginners (M. S. Swaminathan). Achievements, expecta¬
tions and challenges (A. Sasson and E. J. DaSilva). The state of the art
(T. Yoshida). The magic of mushrooms (P. Atthasampunna and S. T.
Chang). Creative ferment (P. L. Rogers). UNESCO's international
network of microbial resources centres. A rising tide (R. Colwcll).
From the green revolution to the gene revolution (I. K. Vasil and L.
Herrera-Estrella). Art and the science of life (J. Hodgson). Green¬
watch: Defeating decibels (F. Bequette). Sharing the future (F. Mayor).
Heritage: Butrinti rediscovered (Z. Xholi). Anniversary: Martin
Luther King, Jr. (E.J. Maunick). Archives: The downfall of idealism
(T. Mann). Music: (I. Leymarie). Books: (E. Reichmann).
JULY-AUGUST. SURPRISING STRANGERS. Interview with José
Donoso. Elvis the African (G. Darley-Doran). Borshch and sympathy
(N. Santy). Lost illusions (N. Bissoondath). 'Living like savages' (P.
Jacquin). Inuit blues (interview with Pavel Lounguine). The genius
of peoples (J. Malaurie). The Fulbe and the Samurai code (R. Ogawa).
The hornbilPs quest (K. Sulang) A photographer in Tibet (P. Nor-
mantas). Dreams of twenty young women (H. T. Simon). 'One
turning planet' (D. Harris). Mexico City: the shock of discovery. My
friends the Gypsies (interview with Aleksandar Petrovic). The son of
Polish Jewish immigrants looks at the Palestinians (M. Rajsfus). A
European artist discovers the salt of the earth (J. Leenhardt). We are
Siamese if you please (M. Sportes). Café society (R. R. el-Tahtâwî).
Getting to know Chief Iamory (L. G. Binger). When the Mom-
buttu women cried hosanna (G. Schweinfurth). Greenwatch: Coral:
taking the pulse of the planet (F. Bequette). Social development and
quality of life (F. Mayor). The rescue of the Bulgarian Jews in 1 943
(E. Vaillant). Anniversary: Olexander Dovzhenko (L. Hosejko).
Heritage: Letter from Borobudur (E. Hattori). Archives: The new
obscurantism (T. Mann). The Delhi Declaration. The U.N. goes to
school (S. S. Shelley). Books: (R. Silva-Cacércs). Music: (I. Ley¬
marie).
SEPTEMBER. BIOETHICS. Interview with Noëlle Lenoir. Scientific
knowledge and human dignity (J. Dausset). The prospects for gene
therapy (R. Dulbecco). Prenatal diagnosis: foretelling the quality of
life (H. Galjaard). Genetics in the market-place (E. N. Suleiman).
UNESCO and bioethics (G. B. Kutukdjian). Fact file. What happened
to development? (F. Mayor). Heritage: The Tower of London (F.
Leary). Melina's last battle. Greenwatch: Of men and mountains (F.
Bequette). Portrait: Mercator, cartographer of genius (J. Portante).
Anniversary: Seoul at age 600 (C. Chong-Hyon and Y. Tong-Ok).
Global View: Human development: a question of security. Archives:
Haiku by Bashô. Listening: The maroons (I. Leymarie). Elvis the
African, part 2 (G. Darley-Doran).
OCTOBER. SLAVERY. Interview with Yehudah Amichai. Under the
whiplash (O. D. Lara). Who was responsible? (E. M'Bokolo). A slave's
story (M. Grandy). A continent of fear (M. Gueye). The Black Code
(I. Futcha). The long road to abolition (N. Schmidt). 1794: The French
Convention abolishes slavery (L. Sala-Molins). Forced labour (G.
Thullen). The slave route (interview with Doudou Diène). Fact file. The
challenge of cultural pluralism (E Mayor). Heritage: The Danube
delta (M. Cazacu). Anniversary: Hermann von Helmholtz (R.
Schröder). Greenwatch: Saving the Aral (F. Bequette). Global View: The
plight of the world's street children. Books: (E. J. Maunick). Archives:
The future of culture (G. Marañón). Listening: The guitar (I. Leymarie).
Reflections: Elvis the African, part 3 (G. Darley-Doran).
NOVEMBER. NOMADISM. Interview with Myung-Whun Chung.
Nomads and the modern state (A. Bourgeot). The Tuareg (Photos by
F. Dal Chele). The myth of the Moken (J. Ivanoff). The return of the
Bedouin (R. Boceo and R. Jaubert). The Gypsies (P. Williams). Forest
rovers of the Amazon (H. Reid). The vanishing African herdsman (J.
Galaty). A halt to advancing deserts (F. Mayor). Heritage: The
monastery of Alcobaça (J. A. Seabra). Greenwatch: Red alert for
the earth's green belt (F. Bequette). Global view: Literacy: How to
reach the excluded. Anniversary: Rabelais: the ribald scholar (A.
Frontier). Archives: Marie Curie. Listening: (Interview with Catherine
Français).
DECEMBER. RELIGION AND POLITICS TODAY. Interview with
Wolf Lcpcnics. The comfort of certainty (F. Lewis). The embrace of
the community (J. Daniel). Faith and reason (A. Michnik). The fun¬
damentalists and science (F. Charfi). From barbarism to intolerance
(K. Makiya). Roads to revolution (E. Naraghi). The abdication of
thought (T. Ben Jelloun). Behind the veil of fundamentalism (M.
Hussein). Economism, the enemy of obscurantism (R. Debray).
India: the threat to union (R. Khan). A new Hindu identity (S.
Kakar). Heritage: The splendour of Spis (E. Bailby). Greenwatch: The
sea's dwindling harvest (F. Bequette). Portrait: Hryhoriy Skovoroda
(T Zolozova). Global view: .S.O.S. Children. Archives: World peace
begins at home. Anniversary: José Carlos Mariátegui (A. Pita). Book¬
shelf: A fresh look at the past (C. Wondji).
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
VENTE EN LIBRAIRIE
G. ARCHIBALD
LES ÉTATS-UNIS ET L'UNESCO
1944-1963
Les rêves peuvent-ils résister
à la réalité des relations internationales?
1994 - 380 p. - 170 F
PUBLICATIONS DE LA SORBONNE
RELIGION ET POLITIQUE
/ IL TOUATI
ENTRE DIEU ET LES HOMMES
Lettrés, saints et sorciers
au Maghreb (XVIIe s.)
1994 - 312 p. - 190 F
D. VIDAL, G. TARABOUT et E. MEYER (eds)
VIOLENCES
ET NON-VIOLENCES EN INDE
Purusharlha, 16
1994 - 288 p. - 195 F
ÉDITIONS DE L'ÉCOLE DES HAUTES
ÉTUDES EN SCIENCES SOCIALES
E. NARAGIII
ENSEIGNEMENTS
ET CHANGEMENTS SOCIAUX
EN IRAN DU Vile AU XXe S.
Islam et laïcité : leçons d'une expérience
séculaire
1992 - XI + 224 p. - 120 F
ÉDITIONS DE LA MAISON DES SCIENCES
DE L'HOMME, PARIS
M. CIIARLOT (ed)
RELIGION ET POLITIQUE
EN GRANDE-BRETAGNE
1994 - 190 p. - 120 F
PRESSES DE LA SORBONNE NOUVELLE
M. MESLIN (ed)
CAHIERS D'ANTHROPOLOGIE
RELIGIEUSE
Volume 3 :
L'expérience mystique
1994 - 112 p. - 80 F
y
' CGUIMBARD
OÙ VA L'ITALIE?
1994 - 472 p. - 130 F
PRESSES DE L'UNIVERSITÉ DE PARIS-SORBONNE
G. VINCENT et J.-P. WILLAIME (eds)
RELIGIONS
ET TRANSFORMATIONS
DE L'EUROPE
1993 - 428 p. - 180 F
PRESSES UNIVERSITAIRES DE STRASBOURG
CiD
o i p p u a i o h
Centre
Interinsti luiionncl
pour U Diffusion
de publications
en sciences humaines
131, boulevard Saint-Michel 75005 PARIS
Tél. (1) 43 54 47 15 Fax (1) 43 54 80 73
Daniele Hervieu-Léger
Effondrement de la pratique religieuse,
montée des fondamentalismes, nouveaux
mouvement religieux... Comment s'y reconnaître
dans un paysage religieux bouleversé?
Cet ouvrage permet d'élucider les transformations
qui affectent les "grandes religions", et ouvre
des perspectives instructives sur le fonctionnement
de notre civilisation sans repères.
Coll. "Sciences humaines et religions"
274 pages, 120 FF
44 18 12 0 2 erf
PROJET I
RELIGION ET POLITIQUE
SI LOIN, SI PROCHES
Au politique, l'espace public ; au religieux, la
sphère privée : cette distinction a pacifié, en
Europe du moins, des rapports hier conflictuels.
N'est-elle pas remise en question ?
Rapprochées par leur crise commune, à l'ère
des croyances relativisées et privatisées, mais aussi
de l'irruption d'autres traditions, religion et poli¬
tique doivent-elles redéfinir leurs rapports ?
Avec les contributions de : A. Bastenier,
J.-M. Donegani, D. Hervieu-Léger,
F. Khosrokhavar, E. Marienstras, P. Michel,
J. Roman, P. Valadier, J.-P. Willaime.
En vente dans les grandes librairies
Ce n° (128 p.) : 65 F Etranger : 70 F
PROJET 14, rue d'Assas - 75006 PARIS
® (1) 44 39 48 48 - Minitel : 36 15 SJ*PROJET
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER
SUBSCRIBERS: OFFER YOUR
FRIENDSAND YOURSELF
COPIES OF THIS NEW PUBLICATION
"WHAT HAPPENED TO DEVELOPMENT?"
From 40 internationally-known
specialists, the latest thinking on the
problems of development in the world
today.
In June 1994 Unesco organized an
international symposium on the theme
"What happened to development?"
Participants: President François
Mitterrand, Unesco's Director General
Federico Mayor and some forty
intellectuals, researchers, economists
and experts on development.
"What happened to development?"
contains résumés of the participants'
contributions and a synthesis of the
discussions. A 90-page round-up of
current ideas on the problems
associated with development
today, in the North and
in the South.
--^-s,r
deve/opmeiit?"
THEME OF
THE NEXT ISSUE
(JANUARY 1995)
THE SUN
ALSO FEATURING AN INTERVIEW
WITH THE SPANISH SINGER
MONTSERRAT CABALLÉ
ORDER FORM INSIDE
]]>
</page>
</document>
