<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="100263eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
I
a worldwide emergency
k**£'
M 1205 9506- 22,00 F .
Il
NTERVIEW WITH NICOLAE BREBAN
HERITAGE: SUSAH, PEARL OF THE TUNISIAN SAHEL
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to
all photographs.
The Aids
hippogriff
1989, sculpture
(35 x 30 x 25 cm)
by Sigismond de Vajay
"I try to express my
solidarity with the
world's suffering
through my sculptures,"
writes the young Swiss
artist Sigismond de
Vajay. When creating
his hippogriff a
legendary monster of
Greek mythology by
melting plastic cutlery
over a flame, he was
haunted by the bull in
Picasso's famous
painting, Guernica. "I
model my sculptures
while the plastic is still
hot," he says, "and have
often left the skin of my
fingers stuck to it." He
notes that "This
century's wars have
raged between East and
West, but today's
afflictions such as Aids
and drugs spread along
a North-South axis.
Shall we be able to
overcome them?"
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
JUNE 1995
Cover: Computer-generated image
of the human immunodeficiency
virus (HIV).
Right, a red ribbon, international
symbol of the fight against Aids.
A WORLDWIDE EMERGENCY
4 Editorial by Federico Mayor
Interview with Nicolae Breban
40 HERITAGE
Susah, pearl of the Tunisian Sahel
by Moncef Ghachem
43 GREENWATCH
Turkey, land of diversity
by France Bequette
47 LISTENING
Cultural counterpoint
by Isabelle Leymarie
© From HIV to Aids
by Robin Weiss
9 The state of research
by Luc Montagnier
3.0 What can be done?
by Michael Merson
3.4 The Maghreb: women in the front line
by Hakima Himmich and Latifa Imane
3.7 Zimbabwe: the social roots of Aids
by Mary Bassett
20 India: no time to lose
by Ishwar Satyanarayan Gilada
22 Europe: the political dilemma
by Rita Süssmuth
26 New therapeutic approaches
by Jean-Marie Andrieu
27 Health and human rights
by Jonathan Mann
32 The search for a vaccine
by Marc Girard
35 Aids in a different light
by Marie-Thérèse Bocabeille
38 Fact file
Consultants: Caroline Eysel and Ralf Altmeyer
THfe UNESCO
Courier
48th year
Published monthly in 30
languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their
peoples and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. ..."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON, 16 NOVEMBER 1945
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
HE. UNESCO
OURIERXs
48th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and In Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin. 75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.
Fax: (33-1) 45.66.92.70
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomo
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel. 45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French. Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45.68.47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Clauce Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Javaid Iqbal Syed (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Martí (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kang Woo-hyon (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. ¿huma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Katri Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Sudhasinee Vajrabul (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de
Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax: 45.68.45.89
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. 45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 French frarcs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French frarcs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
individual articles and photographs rot copyrighted may be repnnted pro¬
viding the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Ukesco Courier', plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles
reprinted must bear author's name. Noncopyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by
an international reply coupon covering Dostage. Signed articles express the opin¬
ions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco
or those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Ukesco Couner staff. The boundaries on maps published in the
magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The UHESCoCouaeris produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans: (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100 U.S.A.: (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edi¬
tion. Indian Head Inc, 111 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.: (4) Bell and
Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster. Oh o 44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - JUIN 1995
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DiFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unésco.
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR.
Z.l. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malserbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N" 6-1995 0PI-95-538A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 2-3 and 50-51.
Editorial
The human immunodeficiency virus strikes at chil¬
dren and adults, at rich and poor, at blacks and whites,
in both North and South. Like pollution, it knows no frontiers.
It is a danger for us all, and no country, however well endowed
in specialized scientific resources or in institutions, can tackle
it alone. Humanity must unite to defeat it.
Many have already fought against the disease, in the United
Nations system, in national teams working on a professional
or voluntary basis, in local associations and movements.
Thanks to them, considerable progress has been made on a
number of fronts research, care and prevention.
Progress has been made, but it is not enough. Because of its
far-reaching human implications and its impact on economic
and social life, Aids has acquired a multidimensional quality
which is not yet fully appreciated. It is increasing the already
vast differences between countries and hindering the devel¬
opment efforts of the poorest of them. It is highlighting the
effects of ignorance and extreme poverty and the flagrant
inequalities of our world in the areas of health, information and
education.
In view of the nature of the pandemic, the difficulty of the
problems associated with it and the need for better co-ordi¬
nated action at the international level, the United Nations
has decided to set up a joint HIV/Aids programme. Under this
programme, UNESCO will be working alongside the World
Health Organization, the United Nations Children's Fund, the
World Bank, the United Nations Development Programme
and the United Nations Population Fund.
exchanging information and changing behaviour
UNESCO will draw on the experience it has built up, notably
through its preventive education programme, not only in
order to pass on information but also to bring about changes
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
by Federico Mayor
Aids: a worldwide emergency
in people's behaviour with regard to Aids both as a disease and
as a social phenomenon.
Since action to provide information and establish com¬
munication is effective only if it is adapted to the socio-cultural
environment in which it is carried out, UNESCO will make avail¬
able to its partners the benefits of its research and experience
on that pervasive and elusive factor which is cultural specificity.
UNESCO will also continue to assist research through its var¬
ious networks concerned with molecular and cell biology
and microbiology, and through the World Foundation for
Aids Research and Prevention that Professor Luc Montagnier
and I set up at the beginning of 1993. Our first concern is to
develop exchanges of information and co-operation among
researchers in all the disciplines involved and to promote the
participation of specialists from the countries hardest hit,
especially African specialists.
International mobilization
UNESCO's task also involves perhaps most importantly pre¬
venting or checking, with the agreement of the communities
concerned, any measures including legislative ones that
would tend to exclude or discriminate against people who
are suffering from the disease or are HIV-positive, or to vio¬
late human rights and fundamental freedoms or the dignity of
the human person. This is vital for the preservation of the
"intellectual and moral soli¬
darity of mankind".
Aids is clearly not just a
medical problem. It under¬
lines the interdependence of
our world and the need for an
interdisciplinary strategy
implemented with the close
co-operation of all con¬
cerned. The international
mobilization needed for this cannot be confined to action by
the United Nations system.
It must be backed by states and their political leaders,
since the aim is the rational organization of efforts and funding.
Within each country, those in charge of health and also of the
economy, finance, and education have a crucial role to play in
fighting the scourge. They will have to encourage practical pre¬
ventive action and make all aspects of Aids an integral part of
their policies and development projects.
The resources available for combating this great collective
threat are limited, particularly when compared with the
resources of all kinds devoted to defence. In our budgets we
have funds to pay the price of war, but we have made no pro¬
vision for the cost of the fight against Aids, malaria, pollution
or ignorance, i.e. the cost of peace. The transition from a cul¬
ture of war to a culture of peace must be speeded up.
International action would stand little chance of success
unless it was supported by the mobilization of everyone in
civil society: non-governmental organizations, foundations,
associations and the private sector. Only solidarity in its most
elementary sense that which binds together the representatives
of a species in the face of a common foe will enable us, through
an alliance of science and wisdom, to overcome both the med¬
ical epidemic and the social, cultural, economic, political and eth¬
ical offensive that Aids has unleashed on humanity.
The great Italian tenor Luciano
Pavarotti (centre) offers his support
to the World Foundation for Aids
Research and Prevention, created in
1993 by Professor Luc Montagnier of
the Pasteur Institute, Paris (at left in
photo) and Mr. Federico Mayor,
Director-General of UNESCO (right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
From HIV to Aids
by Robin Weiss
Is the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) the result of
germ warfare, genetic manipulation or monkey cell
cultures? Is HIV really the cause of Aids?
The human immunodeficiency virus
(HIV) is a new virus to humankind.
Actually, there are two main types of the virus:
HIV-1 is responsible for the worldwide pan¬
demic of Aids; HIV-2, which can also cause
Aids, occurs mainly in West Africa but is now
spreading rapidly in some Asian countries such
as India. There is evidence from stored blood
samples that HIV first started to spread epide¬
mically in the late 1970s, but Aids was not reco¬
gnized as a distinct new disease until 1981.
Regrettably, although HIV and Aids are
new, they are here to stay. HIV belongs to the
family of retroviruses, in which the viral genes
become inserted into our own genetic material
in the chromosomes. Because HIV establishes
long-term, persistent infection in this way there
is no possibility of eradicating Aids, as the World
Health Organization succeeded in doing with
smallpox in 1977 and may achieve for
poliomyelitis by the turn of the century.
When we are faced with such an appalling
catastrophe as Aids, it is tempting to look for
someone or some organization to blame for the
situation. The world is not short of "conspiracy
theories" on the origin of HIV that it arose
from germ-warfare research, from new genetic
engineering technology or from growing the
polio vaccine in monkey kidney cells. None of
these fanciful, exciting ideas holds up to what we
know about HIV, and its origin in humans may
be much more mundane.
HIV-1 is related to a virus found in some
chimpanzees and HIV-2 is even closer to a virus
occurring naturally in sooty mangabey monkeys
in West Africa. Thus it seems likely that HIV
originally transferred from these animals to
humans (a process called zoonosis), although HIV
has now become a human-to-human infection.
Turning into Aids
HIV-1 is a usually fatal infection, whereas some
people infected with HIV-2 get Aids and others
remain well. HIV-1 actually kills a higher pro¬
portion of the people it infects than smallpox
ever did, but unlike smallpox, the incubation
period takes years, not days. During these years
of relatively good health, the HIV-infected
person may pass the virus on to others through
sexual intercourse, from mother-to-child or via
blood contamination. On average it takes about
nine years to develop Aids in western coun¬
tries though some infected people succumb to
Aids much more quickly, and others have sur¬
vived over fifteen years. In developing countries
progression to Aids may occur two to three
years earlier. During the long incubation period,
HIV is active, particularly in the lymph glands.
Yet it takes time to cause severe disease because
the body has considerable reserves of the
immune system to call upon which only slowly
become exhausted owing to HIV infection.
A few investigators have queried whether
HIV really is the cause of Aids, blaming life¬
style, especially drugs, instead. However the
evidence for HIV's causing Aids has now
become overwhelming. Quite simply, wherever
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Opposite page, schematic
illustration of the structure of a
retro-virus such as HIV-1. At
centre are strands (red) of
genetic material consisting of
ribonucleic acid (RNA) enclosed
in a core protein shell (green).
The outer envelope (yellow)
consists of a lipid bi-layer with
protein spikes (orange). In HIV
the spikes consist of
glycoprotein gpl20. They
recognize CD4 markers on
white blood T-cells, causing the
cells to become infected. The
virus kills T-cells after infection,
damaging the human immune
system.
Aids occurs, HIV has preceded it. HIV-negative
people do not develop Aids, although there are
some rare inherited or acquired immunodefi¬
ciencies that might occasionally be mistaken
for Aids.
The only factor common to Aids, for
example, in young adults in Africa, teenage girls
in the sex bars of southeast Asia, homosexual
men in North America, haemophiliacs in Europe
or Japan and injecting drug-users .in South
America is HIV. Moreover, those infants who
acquired HIV from their mothers die of Aids
while those who escape the virus, even if their
mothers have it, remain healthy.
Thus HIV is both necessary and sufficient to
cause Aids. Yet many "co-factors" influence
the speed at which Aids develops in the infected
person. These co-factors include individual
genetic make-up, age at the time of infection
(older people tend to develop Aids quicker),
nutrition, life-style including drug abuse and
exposure to other infections.
How does HIV cause Aids?
There are four main attributes to Aids, namely,
immune deficiency, tumours, wasting disease
and brain disease.
(a) Immune deficiency. HIV infects cells of the
immune system, especially a certain type of white »
blood cell, and also scavenger cells in the tissue
known as macrophages. It infects the cells by
docking onto the CD4 molecule on the surface of
these cells and gaining entry into the cells in this
way. CD4 cells are crucial for other lympho¬
cytes that make antibodies or kill cells infected by
other germs. If there are not sufficient CD4 cells
in the blood and body tissues, then the immune
system cannot work properly, and the body
becomes susceptible to all sorts of other infections
as a result of this immune deficiency. That is why
"I waver between
states of great
anxiety and calm.
Sometimes this has
helped me to tight.
1 talk myself into
believing that when
treatment finally
becomes effective
I'll actually slip
through the net."*
the fatal illnesses in Aids
are usually secondary
infections by microbes
other than HIV, because
HIV has led to the
depletion of CD4 cells,
and the other microbes
only then have the
opportunity to grow.
Hence they are called
opportunistic infections.
These opportunistic
infections include well-
known disease-causing
germs such as the tuber¬
culosis bacterium,
which cause much more
widely spread and
severe infections in
HIV-infected people. However, opportunistic
infections also include microbes such as Pneu¬
mocystis carinii, which is quite harmless in healthy
people but causes a fatal pneumonia in Aids.
(b) Tumours. Only a few kinds of cancer are
common in Aids, particularly lymphoma and
Kaposi's Sarcoma. The same kinds of tumour
sometimes appear in other immune deficient
conditions, such as patients with organ trans¬
plants who are deliberately immuno-suppressed
so that they do not reject their transplants. These
tumours are probably themselves caused by
viruses. They can be regarded as opportunistic
cancers in the sense that a healthy immune system
would prevent them from developing. Thus their
appearance is akin to opportunistic infections.
(c) Wasting disease. Many Aids patients lose
weight drastically and become emaciated. That
is why Aids was often called "slim" disease
when it first began to spread in Africa. The
wasting away of body fat and muscle is another
effect of HIV infection. It is partly due to poor
A false-colour scanning
electron micrograph of a T-
lymphocyte infected with HIV.
An infected T-cell typically has
a lumpy appearance with
irregular, rounded surface
protrusions. The tiny spherical
virus particles (coloured in
green) on the surface are in the
process of budding away from
the cell membrane. This
intensive reproduction of the
virus leads to the destruction of
the host cell. Depletion of the
population of T4 lymphocytes
through HIV infection is the
main reason for the destruction
of a person's immune system
in Aids.
* AH the personal
statements by patients
quoted in this issue have
been extracted from
Vivre le sida Le livre
blanc des états généraux,
published by éditions du
Cerf, Paris, 1992.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
"When I learned 1 was HIV-positive, I thought Id be dead in
three months, that death was inevitable. But I started doing
research, and the medical team following my case were always
forthcoming with information. I finally understood how the virus
works, and that helped me to accept it. It became clear that
despite the onus of the treatment it was possible to lead an
active, intense life."
appetite, but more important is a change in the
body's balance of tissue growth and wasting as
a result of macrophage cells becoming infected
by HIV. After HIV infection, cells release the
wrong chemical signals (called cytokines) which
leads to wasting as well as to immune deficiency.
(d) Brain disease. Patients with Aids develop
impaired brain functions leading in severe cases
to dementia, i.e. the loss of conscious thought and
normal behaviour. In patients with Aids dementia,
HIV has invaded the brain. A particular type of
cell in the brain, called microglia, resembles
macrophages and these cells are sensitive to HIV
infection. They in turn affect the maintenance of
healthy nerve cells in the brain, again via local
cytokine signals. Thus when the microglial cells
become infected with HIV, the surrounding nerve
cells begin to die, leading eventually to the
demented states.
Thus the different illnesses apparent in Aids
depend on which cells and tissues become infected
with HIV. The virus does not necessarily kill these
cells outright. It can induce immune destruction
through the presentation ofviral components and
reduced replenishment of cells through the aber¬
rant cytokine signals. What is surprising is how
long it takes HIV to cause Aids.
Because HIV infects the immune system it is
invading the very cells that exist to combat
infection. A balance of power ensues in which at
first the immune system makes all the right
responses to combat HIV, but in which HIV
eventually gains the upper hand and slowly
destroys the immune system. In fact, some sci¬
entists believe that HIV somehow persuades
the immune system to autodestruct.
Right, HIV particles emerging
from the surface of a
lymphocyte. Each tiny sphere
measures 100 nm in diamètre
(l/10,000thofamm).The
photo was taken using an
electron microscope.
8
ROBIN WEISS,
of the United Kingdom, ¡s
Director of Research and
Professor of Viral Oncology at
the Institute of Cancer
Research, London. A specialist
in retroviruses, he has
conducted research on HIV since
1984 and has played a
pioneering role in understanding
the structure and biological
behaviour of the virus.
H IV variation
One reason why HIV usually wins this battle
between invading infection and the body's
response is that the virus is very mutable, that is,
it changes its genes and outer coat so rapidly that
the immune system has difficulty keeping up.
This induces an overactivation of immune
responses that eventually leads to immune exhaus¬
tion and destruction. As HIV infection progresses
to Aids, more virulent forms of the virus often
arise. There is also some evidence that those indi¬
viduals who become infected by HIV from others
who have already developed Aids tend them¬
selves to progress to Aids more quickly.
The variation in HIV strains is even greater
between individuals than within an infected person
and in different geographic areas different sub¬
strains of the virus may prevail. This extensive
variation makes the development of a universal
vaccine all the more formidable. The propensity
for variation is also one of the major stumbling
blocks to anti-viral therapy in Aids. The virus
soon evolves resistance to the drugs like AZT
that would otherwise block its reproduction. So
each drug is only effective for a short time. Com¬
binations of anti-virais, however, have more hope
of preventing or at least delaying Aids, but they
will be far too expensive for global use.
Exceptional cases
Despite the gloomy view that HIV has been
winning thus far, I am optimistic that we shall
make genuine strides in controlling infection
and disease. HIV is as intensively studied as
any virus has ever been, and some of our new
knowledge has quickly been adapted to improve
human health. For instance, within one year of
confirming HIV as the cause of Aids ten years
ago, blood tests were refined from being exper¬
imental research tools to be applied as mass
screening tests to protect the world's blood sup¬
plies from HIV contamination. No other diag¬
nostic medical test has had such a rapid and
important impact in preventing disease.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
As we gain a better understanding of why
infected individuals progress to Aids, so may our
means of halting that process improve. Cur¬
rently medical researchers are focusing on a
minority of individuals who have been infected
with HIV for more than ten years without
showing any signs of progression to illness.
These people have a relatively low level of virus
in their bodies and are able to maintain normal
levels of CD4 cells. In one case, at least, the
person harbours a defective form of HIV, rather
like a form of simian virus that protects monkeys
from Aids. The more we can find out about
how such individuals suppress their HIV infec¬
tion, the more chance we have of discovering
treatments that may enable all infected people to
shift the balance of power in favour of keeping
the virus under control.
There is some new evidence that a few indi¬
viduals may be exposed to HIV infection
without the virus's actually colonizing their
bodies. A small number of women who sell sex
seem to be permanently resistant to HIV infec¬
tion even though they frequently entertain HIV-
positive partners. These women have specific
and effective immune responses to HIV. Finding
out why will help vaccine-development because
we can regard the women as being naturally
immunized against HIV.
In summary, the pace of scientific discovery
about Aids and HIV has been rapid indeed, far
faster than in many other diseases such as malaria,
tuberculosis and cancer. At the moment Aids is
winning the race, but there is the opportunity to
catch up provided the right effort is made.
LUC MONTAGNIER
The state ofresearch
Although patients and the public are not yet aware of it,
important advances in the understanding of Aids patho¬
genesis have been made in the last four years which could
lead to better therapeutic approaches in the near future.
It appears that indirect effects of HIV infection, via cir¬
culating HIV proteins or non-infectious virions, could
amplify the direct infection of target cells. Moreover, the
strong oxidative stress which follows HIV infection could
also increase damage to the immune system.
We now have powerful weapons with which to coun¬
teract the effects of HIV infection, as well as the appro¬
priate laboratory tools with which to make a rapid eval¬
uation of the effectiveness of the combat. But we do not yet
know how to combine these weapons optimally.
I therefore propose that a network of clinical research
units be created in which researchers and clinicians will
work closely together: for small cohorts of HIV-positive
asymptomatic individuals, "à la carte" treatment will be
defined, based on the return to normal of all surrogate
markers.
Such treatments will have to be complex to counteract
the multiple facets of the disease. One could, for instance,
envisage combinations of several antivirals (reverse tran¬
scriptase inhibitors and antiproteases), of antibiotics, of
antioxidants and cytokines involved in the restoration of
cellular immunity against the virus and the opportunist
agents (IL-2, IL-12).
The first step will be to stabilize to a low level the HIV
infection in such patients. A further step may be a complete
eradication of HIV infection.
LUC MONTAGNIER,
of France, Is Professor of Virology and head of the Viral Oncology Unit at the Pasteur
Institute in Paris. His team was the first to discover HIV-1 in 1983.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
What can be done?
by Michael Merson
Aids is gaining ground everywhere, but we now know much
about how to slow the spread of HIV
Below, a child victim of Aids at
a summer camp in Middleville,
New Jersey (U.S.A.).
Globally, the World Health Organiza¬
tion (WHO) estimates that around 4
million women, men and children developed
Aids between the start of the pandemic and
mid-1994. That figure included a rise of 1.5 mil¬
lion in just one year, and the total may approach
10 million by the year 2000.
The numbers of Aids cases are rising every¬
where. Proportionately the increase is greatest
in regions where the epidemic is newest, such as
Asia. Asia's share of global Aids cases rose eight¬
fold in the year to mid-1994. In absolute terms,
however, the heaviest impact is still being felt in
the parts of North America and Africa where
HIV struck first.
In New York City, for example, Aids is the
leading cause of mortality among men and
women aged twenty-five to thirty-four. In
the Masaka district of Uganda, Aids accounts for
close to half of all mortality in the total popu¬
lation.
In Africa Aids is having an economic and
social impact out of all proportion to the num¬
bers dying. Employers face higher medical costs
and the loss of staff with valuable training or
skills. Communities witness the break-up of
their basic units, i.e. families, as more and more
children are orphaned. WHO estimates that up
to eight million children could lose their mothers
to Aids by the year 2000.
As far as infections are concerned, WHO
estimates that 17 million had occurred by mid-
1994 three million more than a year before. A
little over 60 per cent of all infections to date
have been in sub-Saharan Africa, but the wave
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
of HIV is now crashing over Asia, home to
more than half of the world's population. WHO
estimates that the total number of HIV infec¬
tions in south and southeast Asia surged by one
million to 2.5 million in the year to mid- 1994.
China is very vulnerable, as shown by a sharp
rise in the reported incidence of sexually trans¬
mitted diseases (STDs), which make HIV trans¬
mission more likely. If HIV takes a strong hold
in the world's most populous country, the
impact on Asia could be huge.
In the countries of central Asia and eastern
Europe, WHO estimates there have been some¬
thing over 50,000 infections, although the figure
may have to be revised upwards when HIV data
on people practising high-risk behaviour
becomes available. In North Africa and the
Middle East another region where the Aids
threat once seemed remote there have been
an estimated 100,000 infections.
Latin America and the Caribbean have had
an estimated two million infections so far. More
and more parts of Brazil, which may hold the
key to the ultimate extent of the epidemic in this
region, are seeing rising HIV prevalence in their
STD clinics.
Prevention strategies
We now know a good deal about how to slow
the spread of HIV. There is no easy solution, no
single recipe. But there are effective strategies
and approaches in Aids prevention, based on
knowledge and experience acquired from many
countries.
Like syphilis and other sexually transmitted
diseases, HIV can be transmitted through trans¬
fusion of contaminated blood and the sharing of
needles. The world must do all it can to ensure
the safety of the blood supply. It is unacceptable
for a procedure designed to save lives to
A giant "Bleachman" roams
the streets of San Francisco
(U.S.A.) handing out packets of
bleach so that drug users can
sterilize their needles and avoid
infection.
Eastern Europe and Central Asia
Western Europe
50,000 +
Mi
North America 500,000 + East Asia
1 Million + ^fl
North Africa
& Pacific
50,000 +
& Middle East South & Southeast Asia
Latin America
100,000 + ^ ^L 3 Million
& the Caribbeau kfc A KrS
2 Million
Sub-Saharan
^^ «
Africa Australasia
11 Million 25,000 +
GLOBAL TOTAL: 18 MILLION
Left, estimated distribution of
total adult HIV infections from
late 1970s until late 1994.
(Source: WHO-Global
Programme on Aids, January
1995).
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
"To some extent the answer is inside each of us. I produce
psychological antibodies, and I create the best possible
environment for myself so as to make a little progress each day.
What hurts the most is the pity from the hospital people. When
the nurses sgueeze my hand, look at me full ofpity and wish me
luck, it hurts."
Sexual intercourse is
the main mode of
transmission of HIV,
and it is in this area
that we must focus
our efforts.
endanger them. For drug injectors, WHO rec¬
ommends harm reduction programmes which
give legal access to sterile injection equipment.
But sexual intercourse is by far the main mode
of transmission of HIV, and it is in this area
that we must focus our efforts.
To prevent sexual transmission, we must
change people's sexual behaviour or make sure
it is safe from the start. Safer sexual practices
include abstinence, mutual fidelity, non-pene¬
trative sex, and protected sexual intercourse the
use of condoms. All sexually active people must
know about these options and follow one of
them as a protection against infection. Media
campaigns and special activities targeted at the
most vulnerable groups can reduce the number
of HIV infections, especially in a non-discrim¬
inatory environment that respects the rights of
individuals.
Young people are particularly vulnerable.
Worldwide, half of HIV infections to date have
occurred in people aged fifteen to twenty-four.
Children must be educated about sex and the
risk of HIV infection before they become sex¬
ually active. Research has proved conclusively
that sex education in the classroom does not
lead them to early sexual experimentation or
promiscuity. It gives them the skills to avoid
risk situations and leads to more responsible
sexual behaviour. Out of school, peer educa¬
tion and face-to-face contacts should be used
with young people.
Apart from the promotion of safer sex,
including condom use, the second main way to
prevent sexual transmission of HIV is the early
diagnosis and treatment of conventional STDs
such as syphilis, gonorrhea and chancroid. For
the treatment of STDs, WHO is now recom¬
mending the use of simple flowcharts to help
decide how to treat STD patients appropriately
at their first visit. WHO believes STD services
should be part of primary health care facilities,
to make them more accessible. At the same time,
special STD services should be set up for those
most at risk.
A necessary part of any Aids/STD preven¬
tion programme is condom promotion. There
are now many examples of condoms proving
12 Young Tanzanians orphaned
by Aids.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A pig-rearing project for former
prostitutes in Thailand. Its
objective is to generate income
as an incentive to discourage
girls from returning to
prostitution.
MICHAEL MERSON,
of the United States, is a
specialist in infectious diseases.
From 1990 to 1995 he was
Director, then Executive Director,
of WHO's Global Programme on
Aids (GPA). He left the GPA
earlier this year to become Dean
of Public Health and Chairman of
the Department of Epidemiology
and Public Health at Yale
University Medical School, New
Haven, U.S.A.
effective in Aids/STD prevention. In Thailand,
for example, a recent 100-per-cent condom-use
campaign in brothels has reduced STD rates to
almost zero.
Safer sex campaigns and better STD treat¬
ment can achieve impressive results in a relatively
short time, but we must not neglect more long-
term action to address social factors which fuel
the spread of HIV. Prime among these is the
status of women.
The Aids pandemic has not only drawn
attention to the vulnerability of women to HIV
infection and STDs, it has also highlighted the
inequalities that affect most women, particu¬
larly in developing countries. These social
inequalities sometimes push women to the point
that they take up sex work, with its associated
risks of acquiring a fatal infection.
For women to be able to insist on safer sex,
to have the choices that too often are not theirs,
their social and economic status must be raised.
They must have equal access to education and
employment and supportive laws to protect
them from violence and abuse.
Vare for the infected
Prevention is only one side of the response to
Aids, of course. The other is care for the infected.
What is needed is a continuum of care, from
the home to the community to the hospital. For
developing countries facing many health prob¬
lems, this will be difficult to achieve. At a min¬
imum they must reorient national spending so
that health care gets its due. Donor countries,
too, should play their part by providing more
resources for care.
Both in prevention and care, the response of
any country must be truly national, embracing
health and non-health sectors, communities and
individuals. Non-governmental organizations
can play a key part in taking safer sex messages
to people government services find hard to
reach, and in providing care in the community
for the infected or ill. In many countries, people
living with HIV/Aids are invaluable partners.
The international response should also be
multisectoral. This is one reason why WHO
and five sister United Nations agencies the
United Nations Development Programme, the
United Nations Population Fund, UNESCO,
UNICEF and the World Bank are currently
setting up a joint and co-sponsored UN Pro¬
gramme on HIV/Aids. The new programme
aims to unite and co-ordinate UN support to
national Aids programmes and make the best use
of limited resources.
"I'm from Nantes in western France. I'm
HIV-positive. I got the news on 22
November 1989. That day my life was
totally changed. There's nothing left of
me. I try to live from day to day, but I feel
there's nothing left of me."
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The Maghreb: Women in the front line
by Hakima Himmich and Latifa Imane
Two members of Morocco's anti-Âids association
explain why women in the Maghreb are particularly
exposed to HIV infection
14
More than four million women are now
I infected with HIV. Over 3,000 more are
infected each day. Most of them are between
fifteen and thirty-five years old and live in the
Third World. The disease is taking the heaviest
toll of African women. According to WHO
one out of every forty African women is
affected.
The latest reports show that the epidemic is
spreading rapidly in the Maghreb. In Morocco
(the situation is pretty much the same in Algeria
and Tunisia) the percentage of women among
Aids sufferers rose from 8 per cent in 1988 to 25
per cent in 1994.
myriem, widowed at 25 and
HIV-positive
The figures indicate the vulnerability of women
like Myriem, who was widowed seventeen days
after her wedding. The virus was a legacy from
her forty-eight-year-old husband, who had mar¬
ried her after the death of his first wife. Contrary
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
r
A wedding ceremony in the
High Atlas Mountains,
Morocco. The shape of the
bride's headdress indicates
that she is a virgin.
A family planning session in a
village near Marrakesh.
to a widely held prejudice in the Maghreb Aids
is not only a disease of "loose women" who
have left the "straight and narrow". In over 55
per cent of female Aids cases in Morocco the
only known risk factor is marriage. Like half of
the women infected each day in the world,
Myriem had had only one sexual partner, her
husband.
Myriem found it hard to understand what
the doctor was saying when he explained that
she was the carrier of an invisible virus that is
spread mainly through sexual intercourse. She
was born in a rural area and never went to
school. Of course, she had heard of "Ades",
but she didn't know what it was. How could she,
a "clean" women, have become infected with a
"dirty" disease?
Myriem is the archetypal example of a
young, inexperienced, dependent and ignorant
woman who is defenceless against the infec¬
tion. There are many Myriems in the world,
especially in Africa and Asia. They are ideal
prey for a virus that chooses the weakest as its
targets.
To begin with, they are biologically vulner¬
able. We know today that in unprotected love-
making, men are three times more infective than
women. The more fragile female genital mucous
membrane encourages transmission of the virus
contained in sperm. Adolescent women whose
mucous membrane is not fully mature are at
even greater risk. This explains why young
women aged between fifteen and twenty-four in
developing countries have a much highter infec¬
tion rate than young men of the same age.
Another possible reason for this is that young
women often have sexual relations with sexually
experienced older men.
This fragility is often aggravated by the exis-
"When someone
tells me, 'You've
got to tight. It'll
help your
chances of
survival, ' I
always want to
ask what they
mean by 'fight'.
Fight what? And
how?"
tence of sexually trans¬
mitted diseases (STDs) that
generally reveal no symp¬
toms in women. Women
keep quiet and are rarely
treated. And even when
they have symptoms,
women in the Maghreb
prefer to keep their intimate
forms of suffering to them¬
selves rather than face
examination by a doctor. In
the absence of a public
health system adapted to
their needs, many women
turn to traditional medicine.
More than 70 per cent of
Moroccan women still give
birth to their children at
home, and consequently the
mortality rate is high.
Female sexuality: what goes unsaid
But the health system is not the only problem.
The most important issue is the way in which
female sexuality is perceived both by women and
by men. Although Islam only accepts sexual
activity within marriage, for men as well as for
women, the social balance of power enables
men to cheat. Sexual appetite in men is a sign of
virility and power. Female sexual appetite is
regarded with contempt. Men are expected to
have gained experience prior to marriage; but a
woman must be a virgin on her wedding night.
Myriem was a virgin when she got married.
Her husband, who knew he was ill, demanded
a certificate of virginity. Marrying a virgin is
supposed to have purifying virtues.
After marriage our societies continue to
show indulgence towards men's sexual
"excesses". Women must remain faithful, but
men are occasionally allowed to go and see
whether the grass is greener elsewhere. They
may even indulge in polygamy and take up to
four wives. They are men, after all, and as our
grandmothers said before us, "The eye (the
woman) cannot rise above the eyebrow (the
Today, as they face the threat of Aids, women
realize how little power they have. "I'm afraid,
really afraid. I know my husband is unfaithful to
me, but what can I do? How can I tell him my
fears without making him angry? People here
don't talk to their husbands about that sort of
thing." How many times have we heard that said
on our telephone help-line or in our information 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
sessions. More and more Moroccan women are
afraid of Aids and know they are at risk, but
they find it hard to talk about it. Only rarely do
they dare insist that a flighty husband use a
condom.
"I can't stand the pill, but my husband refuses
to use a condom. He says it's a piece of rubber that
reduces his pleasure. And I've had six children!
But there's nothing I can do. If I nag him about
it, he'll find another wife and I'll be out in the
street. Of course I'm afraid of Aids, but I'm even
more afraid of being kicked out. So. . . ."
Zahra, a thirty-three-year-old housewife, is
entirely dependent on her husband, and so she
has little chance of negotiating with him about
limiting the number of pregnancies or pre¬
venting STDs and
Aids. More than 69
per cent of the"The only friends I
could rely on are
dead."
women suffering
from Aids who are
being treated at
Casablanca Univer¬
sity Hospital are
jobless, like Zahra, and 57 per cent of them have
never been to school.
Their economic dependence and lack of
education seem to be additional risk factors.
Caught between the fear of Aids and anxiety
about being left on the shelf, women feel
trapped. In many cases the prospect of divorce
frightens them the most. "Of course I have
heard about Aids," said Zahra, "but I have
never seen anyone suffering from it. On the
other hand, I have seen plenty of divorced
women. So I know what I'm talking about.
When you don't know how to read or write,
your only security is marriage."
In the Maghreb there are millions of illiterate
Even when they
have symptoms,
women in the
Maghreb prefer to
keep their intimate
forms of suffering
to themselves
rather than face
examination by a
doctor.
A nurse with a patient in the
infectious diseases department
of Ibn Rochd Hospital in
Casablanca.
16
women like Zahra. Schooling is only compul¬
sory in theory. According to a study carried
out in 1990, one out of every two girls attends
primary school; one out of three attends sec¬
ondary school, and only six in a hundred reach
university. Access to school, especially in rural
areas, is still a privilege reserved for boys.
Lacking educational qualifications, these
women have no choice but to get married, or else
work for a pittance as housemaids or factory
hands. Some who have been abandoned or wid¬
owed turn to prostitution, which exposes them
to all kinds of abuse and danger but enables
them to support their families. This is what hap¬
pened to Zoubida, a thirty-five-year-old widow
with three daughters. "When my husband died,"
she explains, "he left me a small house, but my
in-laws sold it, and I found myself in the street
overnight. What else could I do? I started 'going
out' to feed my children. I had no choice."
Zoubida has been selling sex for ten years in a
small Casablanca street. No one knows about it
in her family, who live some fifty kilometres
away and think she works in a factory.
Zoubida only uses condoms when a cus¬
tomer asks her to. "A lot of men don't like con¬
doms," she says. "And there's so much compe¬
tition. All these high school students. If I refuse
to do it, there are a hundred girls ready to,
without condoms or anything." Zoubida has
such a low image of herself, her body and her
status that she feels she has nothing to lose. If she
contracts Aids or anything else, so what?
In any case, the infection process is often
incomprehensible. There are radio and television
programmes about it, and articles in the press,
but for Zahra and Zoubida, who have had no
schooling, media language is hard to follow.
What's more, talk about prevention is first and
foremost aimed at men.
Is Aids revealing the cracks in our social,
health and legal systems and in our traditional
ways? Perhaps the urgent need for specific
answers to the challenge of Aids will at last
force us to rethink our societies.
HAKIMA HIMMICH,
of Morocco, teaches at the Casablanca Medical School. A
specialist in infectious diseases, she is particularly interested
In HIV Infection and the vulnerability of women to HIV/Aids.
LATIFA IMANE,
a Moroccan journalist, is responsible for communication and
training with the Moroccan Association against Aids,
Casablanca.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Zimbabwe: The social
roots of Aids
Above, a family of gold-panners
in Zimbabwe. The father, 36,
has Aids. The mother, 34, is
HIV-positive. They have six
children.
by Mary Bassett
Epidemics depend not only on
infectious agents but on the social
conditions that sustain their spread
I In Zimbabwe, contemporary sexual cul-
I ture has been shaped largely by the twin
legacies of traditional patriarchal values and
colonial labour relations, which entrenched the
migrant labour system and made separation of
men from their wives a way of life. Migrant
labour dates to the expropriation of African
lands at the end of the nineteenth century.
Landless and forced to pay taxes in cash,
African men left their homes and families for
employment on big farms, in mines and in
towns. Women and children stayed behind in the
overcrowded Tribal Trust Lands, to which the
African population was now consigned. Here
they survived as subsistence farmers on poor
land, assisted by money sent home by their
men. This system remains intact and continues
to affect many families. Perhaps one-third to
one-half of rural households in Zimbabwe sur¬
vive with this "split family" strategy.
Some women also migrated to meet the need
for sexual services created by the artificial set¬
tlement of men without their families. Men
entered into new sexual relationships in town.
Hitherto, in traditional society, a man could
have more than one wife if his wealth permitted.
"Multi-partnering", which has become a fea¬
ture of life for all men, carries little long-term
commitment or financial responsibility.
In a 1987 study of Harare factory workers, we
found that married men whether living with a
wife or not were actually more likely to pay for
sex than single men. The same study showed that
four-fifths of married men had girlfriends in addi¬
tion to their wives. True, there are men who have
sex only with their wives and men who are single
and celibate; they are, however, the minority. Not
surprisingly this configuration of sexual relation¬
ships has led to rampant spread of sexually trans¬
mitted diseases (STDs). For many years sexually
transmitted diseases were the leading cause of the
out-patient attendance for both men and women
in urban areas. Aids is now the leading cause of
adult death in the capital city of Harare, accounting
for nearly one-quarter of deaths. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Wc'omen and HIV
Where heterosexual transmission is the most
common way of acquiring HIV, the status of
women has a clear bearing on risk. Much has
been written on women and Aids, often focusing
on prostitutes. Indeed, prostitutes have been
portrayed as the vector of the African Aids epi¬
demic. But very little has been written about
wives, and virtually nothing about the relation¬
ships between these often commingled groups.
The number of women who sell or barter sex
at one time or another is probably larger than is
generally thought. Some of the survey estimates
are so high (ranging up to 10 per cent) that Zim¬
babwean researchers find them unbelievable.
Very often the women involved are divorced
mothers who have children to support, and for
whom remarriage is an unlikely prospect. Added
to these women are growing numbers of young
rural women who flee deepening poverty and
recurrent drought in a bid to support their fam¬
ilies. Some sell single sex encounters. Probably
more common are relationships of varying
degrees of permanence which include domestic
and sexual services.
Despite the emphasis on women who sell
sex, however, it is critical to stress that these
women are a minority of women with HIV. In
fact the majority of women infected with HIV
are monogamous, married women. Of the 6,500
women who tested positive at the National
Public Health Laboratory in 1992, over 50 per
cent were married.
Married women, however, have been
neglected in both research and Aids-preven¬
tion programmes. Warnings to avoid multiple
partners have little relevance to these women.
Their husbands are the ones who are likely to
have multiple partners. It is very common to
hear women talk with a combination of exas¬
peration, amusement and irritation about how
impossible it is for their husbands to maintain an
exclusive relationship with a marriage partner.
Marriage is a vehicle for a woman's sense of
selfhood. To be a person, for both men and
women, involves entering the cosmology of ances¬
tors. In line with patrilineal inheritance, this
process must take place within the male lineage.
In Matabeleland, a
grandmother brings up her
grandchildren orphaned by Aids. Not having a husband has spiritual as well as
material significance. Furthermore, women
without men face a host of economic and social
disadvantages. Economic dependence is perpetu¬
ated by the fact that women are less likely than
men to be educated, have skills or stable employ¬
ment outside the peasant sector. In Zimbabwe,
despite a series of important laws passed in the
1980s which guarantee women's rights to property,
inheritance and maintenance, divorced and wid¬
owed women still face many hardships. These
paper rights have not yet been translated into
actual rights.
'Don't talk to us, go talk to the men'
How many researchers who have talked to
women about Aids prevention have been
admonished: "Don't talk to us. Go talk to the
men"? They are right. We also have to talk to
men. Because men are seen as the "winners" in
patriarchal societies and thus allegedly are not
amenable to change, they have been by-passed
by researchers eager to find ways to empower
women. But men remain the power-brokers in
both reproductive and other sexual decision¬
making. How are men instructed in their roles?
With whom do they talk about sex? How do
they view sexual pleasure and responsibility? In
order to find out what permits men to be sexu¬
ally irresponsible, we need to know what moti¬
vates them. For example, a follow-up study of
18
"Even today, I don't feel that I'm living with the virus. It's something
outside me, something remote. I never realized that death could reach
me. I feel hope and great confidence in life. I'm grateful to Aids. Joys
and sorrows, suffering and laughter, all the things I can share with the
people around me, are due to Aids."
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
the Harare factory men showed that some are
now foregoing girlfriends because of expense
and are opting for paid single sex encounters. In
trying to save money for their families, these
men are acting responsibly, but by turning to
paid sex, they and their wives may be at higher
risk of HIV infection.
Among adolescents from fifteen to nineteen
years old, the prevalence of HIV infection is low.
Data from the Zimbabwe National Blood Trans¬
fusion Service show that about 2 per cent of donors
in the school-going group test HIV-positive. But
among this group, girls are three times more likely
than boys to be seropositive. An excess of seropos¬
itive women in young age groups has been shown
throughout Africa. The basis of this vulnerability
is probably both social and biological. The social
pattern of partnerships, younger-woman/older-
man, means that men are more likely to be sexu¬
ally experienced and may be HIV-positive. Fur¬
thermore the genital tract is still maturing and
may be more susceptible to infection.
The epidemiology of HIV infection supports
the idea of targeting young people who are just
beginning to become sexually active and still have
low rates of infection. Targeting young people
raises many questions. How are young people
learning about sex? How can they be taught most
effectively? By whom? There were traditional
mechanisms for transmitting such information, but
studies suggest that throughout Africa urbaniza¬
tion and the disruption of traditional life have
eroded the strength of traditional institutions.
How important do young people consider
the Aids problem? In several studies done in
Zimbabwe, it was clear that young people are
more concerned about unemployment than
Aids. They greet with scepticism the concern
that they should practise safe sex when they
cannot find jobs.
N o easy answers
All epidemics depend not only on the "agent"
(in this case the human immunodeficiency virus)
but equally on sets of social conditions which
sustain its spread. It is not surprising that an
epidemic of the dimensions of the Aids epi¬
demic would have clear social roots.
The connection between economic hard¬
ships, the subordination of women and Aids is
apparent in everyday life, but if Aids-prevention
is to succeed, sexual relationships will have to
change before the problems of poverty and
inequality are resolved. At the level of individ¬
uals, we must do more to talk with married
people, both men and women. Difficult though
this may be, there is no alternative. Even with the
expansion of technical options, particularly
those under female control, it is hard to imagine
that we can escape the fact that the way men and
women construct their sexual relations will have
to change. To fail to recognize that culture can
and will change is to step away from a debate
which is central to Aids-prevention.
Finally, at the level of health services, there
is clearly room for improving more "biomed¬
ical" interventions. It is important to ensure
better identification and treatment of other
STDs, which enhance HIV transmission. Zim¬
babwe appears to have had considerable success
in reducing STDs.
Another promising area is female-controlled
methods, including the female condom, reduced
use of intravaginal drying agents and possible use
of microbicides. To tell women to tell men to use
condoms is clearly a limited strategy. The suc¬
cess of the family planning movement can be at
least in part attributed to the development of the
oral contraceptive. Women have the history and
experience of taking responsibility for the out¬
come of sexual activity. It makes sense to take
advantage of this and develop methods to reduce
HIV infection which women can control.
For all these interventions we must directly
face the issue of cost. The need for trained staff,
STD diagnostic equipment and adequate pro¬
vision of antibiotics will cost money, money
that the health services do not have.
Moreover, despite donor support, funds for
condoms are inadequate: although male condoms
cost only a few cents each, we are able to import
quantities only adequate for about 5 condoms
per adult per year. Worse, the female condom at $2
US costs about 100 times more than the male
condom. Obviously, without subsidized prices
this method will not be used widely.
Above, Warren Hills cemetery
in Harare, the capital of
Zimbabwe. "Aids is now the
leading cause of adult death In
Harare, accounting for nearly
one-quarter of deaths."
Attitudes can
and must
changethis is
centrai to Aids
prevention.
MARY BASSETT,
of the United States, is a
medical doctor and a Senior
Lecturer in the Department of
Community Medicine at the
University of Zimbabwe. She is
currently on leave as Director of
Harlem Center for Health
Promotion and Disease
Prevention in New York.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ndia: No time to lose
by LS. Gilada
A bold preventive education campaign brought
a marked reduction in HIV incidence among
Bombay prostitutes
20
1SHWAR SATYANARAYAN
GILADA,
of India, is a dermatologist and
venerologist and one of his
country's leading Aids
specialists. Founder and
Secretary-General of the Indian
Health Organization, he is also
chairman of Asian Solidarity
against Aids, a network of non¬
governmental organizations in
Asia.
The HIV infection made a late entry into
Asia, and the continent is still a low-pre¬
valence region for Aids. In the last few years,
however, there has been an HIV explosion.
Using the parameter of "doubling time" (the
time required for a twofold increase in cases) to
interpret the trend of reported Aids cases to
WHO during 1984-1993, the Aids scenario for
Asia looks grim.
At present Aids cases in Asia are underdiag
nosed, underreported and ill treated. Fear and
ignorance are compounding the difficulty of con¬
trolling the spread of the virus. In most places
there are no protocols to follow up HIV-infected
people: counselling, outpatient or inpatient care
services are far from developed, not to mention
prenatal HIV screening. Even today, most health
care professionals refuse to treat patients with
HIV/Aids and, unfortunately, even the interna¬
tional scientific community and major donors
delayed giving their attention to Asia.
Despite the growth of HIV/Aids in Asia,
there has been no major focus on the problem by
political leaders. In Zambia, when the then Pres¬
ident Kenneth Kaunda's son died of Aids, he
publicly pledged support to Aids control pro-
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
^-positive. I found out
grammes, justifying his action as the best pos¬
sible homage to his departed son. All too often,
Asian heads of state regard Aids as too insignif¬
icant an issue to be treated as a priority.
The sexual mode of HIV transmission pre¬
dominates in most Asian countries, and com¬
mercial sex workers (CSWs) and their clients play
an important role in the pandemic. In recent years
the increase in infection in CSWs in Thailand,
India, Cambodia and Nepal has been dramatic.
Project Saheli: Aids prevention through
peer education
During 1987, when a fairly high prevalence of
HIV was noticed in Nairobi CSWs, the Indian
Health Organization (IHO) warned that if the
Aids threat was not taken seriously, Bombay and
other Asian cities would face the Kenyan cap¬
ital's fate. The warning was widely ignored.
Since then the IHO has developed a peer
education programme for sex workers in
Bombay which has reduced HIV incidence and
widened the doubling time from eight months
in 1988 to four years in 1993. Known as "Pro¬
ject Saheli", the campaign reaches out to 10,000
CSWs through 350 peer leaders and distributes
1 million condoms every month in Bombay
and four other cities. It has no sustained funding.
After evaluating various approaches for
condom promotion such as social marketing
and door-to-door vending, we opted for the
"peer education" model for our work among
CSWs. The organization of prostitution is multi-
layered and the CSW is at the lowest end of the
scale ruled by brothel managers and brothel
three years ago. It was my
birthday present. . . . For the last
three years I have made no
plans. I had no prospects for the
future. Now 1 must try to think
thai maybe there is a future and
that I'm not just at death's door.
It's taken me three years to get
that far."
Opposite page, free
distribution of condoms to
Bombay prostitutes.
Below, a sketch performed in
the street by Jamshedpur
(India) students to alert
passers-by of the risks of HIV
infection.
owners. To intervene
effectively, we must influ¬
ence all levels of the hier¬
archy, with the ultimate
goal of empowering the
CSW to change her des¬
tiny. We have a three-tier
system of peer leaders:
one Saheli (friend) from
among the sex workers
for every twenty-five
girls; one Tai (sister) from
among the managerial
cadre for every ten
Sahelis; and one Bai
(mother) from among the brothel owners for
each major area.
While the Saheli and Tai are paid a fee for
their time, the Bai, usually an affluent lady from
their community, is not paid. The payment is
more than just an incentive, it gives their work
respectability, as the CSWs realized for the first
time that they could earn money through other
means than prostitution. They are given training
on the use and distribution of condoms, tech¬
niques for client negotiation and STD/Aids pre¬
vention through personal interviews, group dis¬
cussions, lectures, audiovisuals and role playing,
their task is to educate CSWs about Aids, STDs
and safer sex, to distribute condoms, escort sick
CSWs to mobile clinics or hospitals and to give
support to infected CSWs. They act in street
plays to educate the public and address public
meetings, workshops and conferences, and take
part in television programmes.
To help CSWs to express their aspirations
and voice their concerns, hopes and fears, a
bilingual quarterly, Sakhi-Saheli, is published.
The bulk of the information published is sent in
by CSWs themselves. They have started plan¬
ning for their children and are saving money for
a future they are looking forward to. Their
health has also improved dramatically. Doc¬
tors' fees have fallen. Apart from a marked
decrease in common STDs, the most valuable
fall-out has been a perceptible increase in the
doubling time of HIV infection.
In the absence of a vaccine and cost-effective,
widely acceptable therapies, the only means of
blocking HIV transmission is to educate and
encourage people to adopt protective behav¬
iour. In view of the success rate achieved in a
number of developed nations in containing
HIV/Aids, the situation is not hopeless if
prompt action is taken. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Europe: The political dilemma
by Rita Siissmuth
Can the epidemic be contained more effectively by coercion or by a liberal policy
based on education and individual responsibility?
22
RITA SUSSMUTH
was the Federal Republic of
Germany's Minister for Youth,
Family Affairs and Health from
1985 to 1988. She has been
President of the Bundestag, the
German parliament, since 1988.
Aids is a tough test for democracy. In all
the European countries especially in
the early days of the epidemic in the mid-
1980s demands were voiced for the sur¬
veillance of risk groups and systematic testing so
as to identify carriers of the infection and isolate
them in special institutions, such as "sidato-
riums" (the word is taken from the Aids pro¬
gramme of the French National Front party) or
banish them to uninhabited islands (advocated
by some isolated Scandinavian groups).
The proponents of these radical "solutions",
who were admittedly only supported by a
minority, hoped to protect themselves and
society at large against the risk of infection by
introducing these screening and isolation pro¬
cedures. However specific these problems may
have appeared to Aids, they were in the final
analysis far more general. The Aids debate was
and remains essentially no more than a new
version of a constantly recurring question: to
what extent does the end justify the means? Are
the means appropriate to the ends and are they
legitimate and effective?
Aids confronts our democracies with a rad¬
ical alternative: either we take up the challenge
of Aids courageously and develop new con¬
cepts to consolidate the links between indi-
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
"You mustn't say, 'I live better' that doesn't mean anything
vidual and collective responsibility and
freedom or we take action under statutory
provisions on epidemics, bringing the illusion of
safety associated with the misguided expectation
that detailed provision for screening can bring
effective protection. But if a test is administered
today, what happens tomorrow?
The role of the politicians
Aids disturbs politicians by confronting them
with new problems, with conflicting statements
by experts, contradictory demands and deci¬
sions whose consequences are serious in the
extreme. Be that as it may, action must be taken
despite all the uncertainty and the provisional
nature of our knowledge. The special responsi¬
bility of politicians consists precisely in taking
decisions in crisis situations and submitting
them to a constant critical reappraisal.
Comparisons in Europe point to effective
control of the epidemic especially through pre¬
vention in countries such as the United
Kingdom, Sweden and Germany, which adopted
an active Aids policy at an early stage and in
which the topic was the subject of detailed
debate in parliament. Countries in which deci¬
sions were taken late in the day (Italy, Spain) and
in which parliament was not effectively involved
show significantly higher Aids figures today.
The reason for this relationship resides in the
legitimacy which Aids prevention acquired
through a broadly based and frank discussion at
but simply, 'I am alive.' Wherever I've heard the word 'better', it
really means 'differently'. My life has been whittled down to its
essentials. But in absolute terms it is not better'. Just the
opposite. It's more burdensome, more painful because you're
closer to the reality of things. You live differently."
the highest level. The resulting political deci¬
sions, which must be taken at governmental
level, are binding on all the public bodies. They
also constitute guidelines for the action of the
professional groups, educational establishments,
associations and organizations set up under pri¬
vate law which are engaged in the fight against
Aids.
Aims and methods
As with any other infectious disease, the primary
aim of Aids prevention must be to reduce the
number of new cases of infection. The ques¬
tion which gave rise to serious controversy in
western Europe concerned the ways and means
of attaining this goal:
- Should authoritarian governmental action
be taken, e.g. compulsory testing where there is
a suspicion of Aids, with reporting of the names
of the victims and isolation of the virus carriers,
as with the epidemics and plagues of old?
- Or should the aim be to bring about a
change in individual behaviour among the virus
carriers and the population at large, following
the model of prevention of cardiac and can¬
cerous diseases which stem largely from indi¬
vidual lifestyles?
The controversy intensified once the HIV
antibody test became available because it was
now possible to introduce compulsory measures
with the help of the biological screening test.
The political debates on the use of HIV tests led
to a broad consensus in all west European coun¬
tries between the health politicians, public health
and Aids specialists and the representatives of
the affected groups. It was agreed that Aids could
not be halted without the active co-operation of
the risk groups and virus carriers and that their
willingness to co-operate depended on their con¬
fidence in the underlying social security system.
Quite rightly, authoritarian strategies were there¬
fore not adopted in Aids policy.
The clear political commitment in favour of
a voluntary fight against Aids based on educa¬
tion and self-responsibility encountered some
opposition.
Opposite page, a young Aids
patient in Paris receives care at
home (1993).
Left, a French Aids prevention
poster targeted at young
people.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
¡3
<* Tii' bi -i lo »oil with their hands.'*1
Above, a British poster
encouraging the use of
condoms. Below right, a
German poster urging young
people not to close their eyes
and pretend that Aids does not
exist.
24
First of all, the problem arose as to whether,
and if so how, the phenomenon of Aids could be
incorporated into existing statutory provisions
on epidemics. The classification of Aids dif¬
fered from one country to another, but as a gen¬
eral rule it was not included within the com¬
pulsory provisions on the control and reporting
of transmissible diseases. However, the penalties
for punishable offences, such as unprotected
sexual intercourse by a person infected with
Aids who is clearly aware of the inevitable risk
of infection, were applied or made even more
severe in most countries.
To implement a liberal prevention strategy,
it was also essential to make practical means
such as condoms, sterile syringes and sex edu¬
cation material widely available. Hitherto this
had not been a task for the state and the new
measures gave rise to protests on moral grounds.
Finally, it was essential to provide the pop¬
ulation with comprehensive information on the
risk of infection and means of protection against
it, with no moral prejudices and in readily under¬
standable language. Publicity for condoms based
on specific topics such as "healthy and happy
sexuality" (Sweden and Norway) or target-
group oriented advertising, e.g. an appeal for a
sense of responsibility in partnership (Italy, the
United Kingdom, Germany) brought better
results than publicity couched in general terms
To implement a liberal prevention strategy, it Is essential
to make practical means such as condoms, sterile
syringes and sex education material widely available.
Until now this has not been a task for the state.
and intended "for everyone".
All in all, it has been found that relevant
political decisions only gain social acceptance if
they are founded on a frank and constructive
dialogue with representatives of the interests
of risk groups.
Solidarity with Aids victims and persons
infected with HIV requires extensive medical
and psycho-social assistance, acompanied by
protection against social discrimination. It must
include the promotion of scientific research and
provide suitable compensation for the victims of
infected blood products. To put these require¬
ments into effect, substantial public funds have
been earmarked for the fight against Aids,
despite the fact that European health systems
have been constantly obliged to hold their costs
within strict limits since the early 1980s.
Efforts were made to protect the social rights
of Aids victims in order to preserve their oppor¬
tunities on the labour market, their access to
insurance and their normal involvement in social
life. Co-operation between state bodies and pri¬
vate self-help organizations, hospitals and home
care, was not only of medical and preventive
importance, but also pursued the aim of avoiding
as far as possible social discrimination against the
victims of Aids. The "streetworker programme"
in Germany and The Netherlands, the militant
pilot actions pursued by the French humani¬
tarian doctors' organization Médecins du Monde
and the provision of free health insurance in
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Table 1. Reported cases of Aids per million inhabitants
31 December 1987 31 March 1994 Rate of increase
Sweden 19.4 115 5.9
Spain 20.2 619 30.6
United Kingdom 21.6 155 7.2
Italy 24.6 376 15.3
Germany* 27.4 137 5.3
France 55.3 506 9.1
* The particularly good position of Germany in terms of the rate of increase is partly
explained by reunification in 1990: the former German Democratic Republic, which still has
a very small number of Aids cases (like all ex-communist countries) has brought about a sta¬
tistical reduction of the rate for Germany as a whole. Without reunification, the number of
Aids cases in Germany would have been similar to that in the United Kingdom.
It's time for schools to act."
A UNESCO poster for World Aids
Day, 1 December 1992.
France for beneficiaries of the RMI (minimum
income) programme, the free access to medical
care and health counselling under the British
National Health Service, and the development
of private therapy groups, often associated with
church organizations, for HIV-infected drug
addicts in Italy, are examples of European
responses to the special problem of Aids victims
who not infrequently become social outcasts.
I he political lesson of Aids
My own personal experience as the former
health minister of the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many between 1985 and 1988, i.e. in the years in
which the Aids debate was particularly vocif¬
erous, allows me to draw three conclusions:
Firstly, the politicians have had to learn to
listen to marginal social groups such as homo¬
sexuals, drug addicts and prostitutes, to under¬
stand their special problems and develop forms
of co-operation with them in order to achieve
effective prevention. They have been obliged
to learn how to deal in a pragmatic manner with
taboo-laden topics such as illness and death,
different forms of sexuality and drug addiction.
Secondly, the development of our modern
social state is inconceivable without special
health protection measures. All state measures
designed to fight Aids must be taken in a spirit
of respect for human freedom and individual
dignity, without discrimination on grounds of
their way of life, origin and position in society.
Thirdly, if Aids strategies are to have any
real prospect of success, they must focus on
education and the development of individual
responsibility. To check the further spread of
HIV we should therefore not count on author¬
itarian statutory measures but rather appeal for
a responsible individual approach to the hazards
of Aids.
Table 2. National profiles of the epidemic. Acute Aids cases by source of infection (adults) 31 March 1994
Total no. Homosexuals Injecting drug Homosexual Heterosexuals Blood Unknown
oteases % users (IDU) % IDU% % industry % %
Spain 24,202 15.6 70 2.2 7.6 2.8 5.8
Italy 21,770 14.6 66.1 2.3 10.3 2.2 4.5
France 30,003 48.8 23.8 1.5 15 5.8 5.1
Sweden 1,001 65.2 9.9 0.8 9.3 7.3 7.5
Germany 11,179 69.1 13.1 0.9 5.9 5.6 5.4
United Kingdom 9,025 74.9 5.4 1.6 11.6 5.4 1.1 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
New therapeutic approaches
by Jean-Marie Andrieu
By slowing down the activity of the immune system it may be possible
to slow down the development of the disease
The human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infects a specific cat¬
egory of white corpuscles, the CD4 lymphocytes. It causes a bio¬
logical disease typified by the gradual disappearance of these
CD4 lymphocytes from the lymphoid tissue. Clinically speaking,
this disappearance takes place silently between three and fifteen
years after infection. When the CD4 pool is severely depleted,
repeated opportunistic infections occur which eventually lead to
death, even if they are treated with antibiotics. In order to combat
replication of the virus, and the consequent destruction of the CD4
lymphocytes, researchers have turned their attention to the anti¬
retroviral molecules, the chief of which is zidovudine (AZT). For
a period generally lasting no more than a few months this med¬
ication slows down viral replication and thus the depletion of
CD4s.
The phenomenon of activation is a point of capital impor¬
tance in understanding the loss of CD4 lymphocytes. It is a process
encompassing a phase of cellular proliferation accompanied by the
emission of biological molecules and followed by the death of the
cells. Death is either spontaneous or caused by killer cells
according to a biological process called apoptosis. Activation
thus causes excessive cellular consumption. If it is accepted that
cell renewal in the immune system is a finite process, it is clear that
marked chronic cell consumption might exhaust the immune
system. It has long been known that the more biological symptoms
of activation there are, the more quickly infection develops. The
activation level of immune cells results from individual genetic
diversity and from environmental factors. Thus the high number
of pathogenic agents present endemically in Africa and in the
tropical regions are certainly constant factors in the activation of
the immune system, which would explain the faster development
of HIV infection in Africa.
It can thus be seen that forms of treatment that partially
inhibit excessive activation of the immune system may paradox¬
ically slow down CD4 activation and thereby preserve the CD4
pool. Cyclosporine and glucocorticoids are medication of this
kind. We have studied their effects on a small number of HIV-
infected patients . Among the HIV-infected patients treated over
a one-year-period with a small dose of glucocorticoids (0.5 mg/kg,
then 0.3 mg/kg), a decrease in the activation of the immune system
was observed as well as a stabilization of the concentration of the
virus and an increase in the rate of CD4 associated with a decrease
in their apoptosic rate. Nevertheless, a great deal of caution is
called for in exploring this kind of treatment. We hope that in the
near future Aids research groups will paya good deal of attention
to these new therapeutic approaches. Before considering its ther¬
apeutic use, the benefit/toxicity relationship of this kind of treat¬
ment must be evaluated with great precision.
* Journal of Infectious Diseases, March 1995;
AIDS, January 1995; Immunology Today, January 1995.
Health
Respect for human rights is
coming to he seen as a
fundamental part of public health
policies
JEAN-MARIE ANDRIEU,
OC a French haematologist, heads the tumour Immunology laboratory at Laennec Hospital in Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
and human rights
"T
I he general relationship
between socio-economic status
and health has been widely
documented." Left, a street
child in Sâo Paulo, Brazil.
by Jonathan Mann
The first major influence on health science
on the eve of the twenty-first century is the
phenomenon of globalization, the enormously
expanding and intensifying movements of people,
goods and ideas around the world. The Aids epi¬
demic has accelerated an appreciation of global vul¬
nerability to new disease pandemics.
Tourism is symbolic of the transnational
character of the modern world, for it consti¬
tutes one of the world's largest industries and is
inextricably linked with the history of infec¬
tious agents and epidemic disease. Mass tourism,
with its characteristic heavy influxes during
short periods, overloads sanitary infrastruc¬
tures, and outbreaks of disease are most likely
during these periods.
The Aids pandemic has been a shock, strongly
challenging the old view of the world as com¬
posed of isolated communities and illustrating
clearly the modern world's vulnerability to global
spread of infectious agents. The pandemic is
expanding relentlessly, and may well involve over
100 million people by the end of this decade.
This says much about our limited collective
capacity to deal with global health problems.
The emergence of new microbial threats to
world health is inevitable, yet our ability to
detect and respond to such threats with rea¬
sonable speed remains very limited, slow and
haphazard. Current international health regu¬
lations are clearly based on an old, nation-state
definition of "inter-national" rather than global 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
A human rights demonstration
in front of Lighthouse, a London
hostel for Aids sufferers.
28
health. A new global surveillance strategy must
draw on a broader, ecological view of health
and disease.
An ecological view of health
The definition of health itself is critical, for how
we define a problem will determine what we
do about it. The most widely used modern def¬
inition comes from the World Health Organi¬
zation (WHO) and states that: "health is a state
of complete physical, mental and social well-
being and not merely the absence of disease or
infirmity." Through this definition, WHO has
helped to move health thinking beyond a per¬
spective which focused on diseases, disabilities
and causes of death, to the more positive domain
of "well-being". The definition highlights the
importance of health promotion, described as
"the process of enabling people to increase con¬
trol over, and to improve, their health". Thus the
modern concept of health emphasizes the
broader, societal dimensions of health.
These changes in thinking about health have
been complemented by changes in the prac¬
tice of international health research. In
HIV/Aids prevention, for example, global
exchange of information has been unprece¬
dented and useful. Inherent in this approach is
the idea that when facing a problem like
HIV/Aids, every society and environment may
make useful contributions.
A second aspect of global learning involves
how research is carried out. Early in the pan¬
demic, international research was dominated by
so-called "safari" or "parachute" research, in
which scientists from industrialized countries
arrived, took specimens and left to publish their
results. These early projects were rarely collab¬
orative in any meaningful sense and were part of
a pattern inherited from colonial days. Increas¬
ingly, however, it became clear that both the
ethics of good research and the capacity to answer
the important questions depended on establishing
genuine international collaboration.
I he human rights revolution
As well as acquiring an increased capacity to think
in integrated, ecological ways about health issues,
the world in which health research is carried out
has been changing in another critically important
way. This involves the most hope-filled idea in the
world today that of human rights.
Among the fundamental characteristics of
modern human rights are the following: they are
rights of individuals; they inhere in individuals
simply because they are human; they princi¬
pally involve the relationship between the state
and the individual; and they apply to all people
around the world.1 Despite tremendous con¬
troversy, especially regarding the philosophical
and cultural context of human rights as cur¬
rently defined, a shared sense of concern, a
vocabulary and a set of human rights practices
are increasingly becoming part of community,
national and global discourse.
The human rights revolution strongly affects
both the goals and content of efforts to promote
and protect health, and in this way has a sig¬
nificant influence on the goals and practices of
health research. In the first instance, health
policies, programmes and practices have impor¬
tant impacts on human rights and dignity which
must be avoided or minimized as far as possible.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
"Veronica is seven years old. Her blood test shows that not one T4 cell remains; her immune
system is at zero. When she was five months old she had a pathological lung condition, two
cardiac arrests and an effusion in the right lung. But she recovered, which shov/s how
determined she is. She has an incredible will to live. Now she's m wonderful shape. She's had a
lot ofproblems, one thing after another: ear infections, lung infections and the like, until she
started being treated with AZT, which has an effect. We're lucky she can tolerate it. . . . She goes
to school regularly like other little girls, and works hard. She's even above the class average,
because children who spend a lot of time in hospital are more mature than the others. We tell
ourselves that there have always been epidemics and that some people have survived. Why
shouldn't we be among them?"
Aids spares nobody", says
this poster from the Philippines'
Department of Health.
For example, collecting information from
individuals, such as whether they are infected
with HIV, or have breast cancer, or have a
genetic predisposition to heart disease, can
clearly burden individual rights to security of
person and of privacy. Health status or health
behaviour information (such as sexual prefer¬
ence or history of drug use), if misused by the
state or made available to others, can also result
in grievous harm to individuals and violations
of many rights, leading to (as has occurred with
information about HIV infection) cruel,
inhuman or degrading treatment, arbitrary
detention or exile, attacks upon honour and
reputation, limitations of freedom of move-
6W-45D
NATIONAL AIDS PRtVENTlON AND CONTROL PROGRAM
DIPAHTMCNT Of HEALTH
^m
JONATHAN MANN,
of the United States, was the
founding director of the World
Health Organization's Global
Programme on Aids (1986-
1990), and is now the François-
Xavier Bagnoud Professor of
Public Health and Human Rights
at the Harvard School of Public
Health (U.S.A.). He Is also
Professor of Epidemiology and
International Health at Harvard,
and Director of the International
Aids Center of the Harvard Aids
Institute.
ment, violations of the right to marry and found
a family, and restrictions of the right to work
and to education.
Appreciation óf the impact human rights
violations can have on health has also changed.
These impacts are not limited to such obvious
cases as torture, imprisonment under inhumane
conditions, or summary execution and "disap¬
pearances". It is now evident that violations of
many, if not all, human rights may be associated
with negative effects on health. When cigarettes
are marketed without governmental assurance
that information regarding the harmful health
effects of tobacco smoking will also be available,
it can be argued that the right to information is
violated. The health cost of this violation in
terms of preventable illness, disability and pre¬
mature death, including excess cancers, cardio¬
vascular and respiratory disease, can be quanti¬
fied. A similar example involves governmental
withholding of valid scientific health informa¬
tion about contraception or regarding measures
to prevent infection with HIV.
Modern concepts of health recognize that
underlying "conditions" lay the foundations
for optimal achievement of physical, mental
and social well-being. Given the fundamental
importance of these conditions, it is remark¬
able how little priority has been given to their
identification, modes of action, relative roles
and possible interactions.
The most powerful analysis has focused on
socio-economic status. The general relation¬
ship between higher socio-economic status and
better health has been well and widely docu¬
mented. Yet this analysis has at least two impor¬
tant limitations. First, it cannot adequately
account for a growing number of discordant
observations. Second, while health workers
readily acknowledge poverty as a critical issue,
it poses an overwhelming challenge with which
they are neither trained nor equipped to deal: the
identification of socio-economic status as an 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The dialogue
between health and
human rights
evolved
dramatically.
Initially, health and
human rights
supporters clashed
as attempts were
made to control
Aids through
restrictive
measures such as
mandatory testing,
quarantine and
isolation.
30
A poster for a conference on
HIV/Aids and related problems
in Aboriginal communities of
Canada.
"essential condition" for good health paradox¬
ically may encourage passivity and hopeless¬
ness and therefore paralyse action.
A global Aids strategy
However, alternative approaches to identifying
"essential conditions" for health are emerging.
Experience with what can arguably be called the
world's first truly global strategy, created by
WHO to confront Aids, suggests an analytic
approach based on modern human rights.
The dialogue between health and human
rights evolved dramatically. Initially, health and
human rights supporters clashed, as health offi¬
cials and politicians sought to control Aids
through a series of restrictive and coercive mea¬
sures from the standard lexicon of public health,
such as mandatory testing, quarantine and iso¬
lation. This aggressive response was spurred by
a climate of fear, compounded by the marginal¬
ized nature of the groups most visibly affected
homosexual men and injecting drug users.
Human rights activists resisted these coercive
public health approaches. However, as experi¬
ence in HIV prevention began to accumulate,
health officials came to realize that discrimina¬
tion and coercion were interfering with the
effectiveness of the information/education and
service programmes, by driving those most
needing the services and support away.
The idea that respecting human rights would
be useful, or even essential, in order to achieve
Veoi*^ <S
Oj*em(nr 5-7, 1994
*J^ Toronto ^ C.IM.M* .
<k
%
mO F
Third C.in.Kli.ii! ! uni. i. -in on III V /AIDS
And Ki-i. ¡int I-. In \ in iniini.il CommuniUca
a public health goal was quite a novel idea, but
it came from practical experience rather than
theoretical considerations. Accordingly, a public
health rationale for protecting human rights
and dignity was developed.
However, while the WHO model works
extremely well at the pilot project or community
level, it has neither been able to become widely
disseminated nor has it influenced in any sub¬
stantial manner the natural history of the pan¬
demic. More than ten years after Aids was dis¬
covered, and despite the energy, courage and
creativity of the fight against Aids during the
past decade, it is clear that current efforts are nec¬
essary but will not be sufficient to bring this
global epidemic under control.
Docial discrimination
and the spread of HIV
Fortunately, through the experience of the past
decade, it was discovered that the spread of
HIV is strongly determined by an identifiable
risk factor. We are accustomed, in classical med¬
ical and epidemiological thinking, to consider
risk factors such as sexual behaviour, or drug-
taking or cigarette smoking, as individual. Yet we
gradually recognized a societal risk factor for
vulnerability to HIV infection in the scope,
intensity and nature of discrimination which
exists within each community or country. We are
not speaking principally about discrimination
against already HIV-infected people and people
with Aids, which is one tragic effect of the pan¬
demic; here we are considering those forms of
discrimination in society which antedated the
arrival of HIV. The damage which discrimina¬
tion does to HIV prevention was recognized
as occurring at two levels.
First, discrimination undermines and inter¬
feres with each component of the programme-
based approach to HIV prevention. People who
are discriminated against are much less likely to
receive information and education adapted to
their needs. Actually, their needs are likely to
remain unrecognized altogether. For example,
deaf people have received little or no informa¬
tion about Aids adapted for their use. Margin¬
alized groups are also much less likely to have
access to the health and social services needed for
HIV prevention. People who are discriminated
against often have difficulty organizing as a
community. They are less likely to participate
effectively in debates about Aids policies or
programmes, and more likely to be subject to
coercive and punitive measures. Put together, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Mi
A poster by Bronwyn Bancroft,
an Australian Aborigine artist,
illustrating the need for
information about needle-
exchange programmes and the
importance of "safe sex".
positive benefits of the programme-based
approach are least available to those who need
them most because of societal discrimination.
But there is a second and more fundamental
relationship between societal discrimination, vul¬
nerability to HIV and HIV prevention capacity.
The fundamental basis of HIV prevention is the
promotion of each person's capacity to learn
about and to apply this understanding fully and
freely in their life. Yet for each of us, social status
and role critically influence and constrain our
choices. Thus the debate about using a condom
is very different for a young person with hope for
a bright future through education and a young
person with little realistic expectation of a mean¬
ingful job. Put another way, when we assume
that people can simply choose and leave them to
choose, we are assuming that everyone has a
choice or a similar realistic range of choices.
I ale domination
a threat to public health
In many Third World countries, even when the
woman knows her husband to be HIV-infected,
she may be powerless to protect herself. For
divorce, entirely under the control of the man, will
mean civil and economic death for the woman.
In this context, therefore, it is entirely logical
and appropriate that women's organizations are
seeking to change the laws governing property
distribution after divorce, as well as laws on
marriage and inheritance to help prevent HIV
from spreading! These measures, by giving the
woman a choice and a voice in negotiating sexual
relations, are likely to be more effective in pre¬
venting HIV spread than producing more attrac¬
tive brochures or customizing brand names for
condoms. Again and again, we have seen that
discrimination creates an environment of
increased risk for women linked directly with
their unequal role, rights and status. (It is in
this context, as well as considering reproductive
health, sexual violence and many other issues,
that we can say that male domination of society
is a threat to public health).
In short, wc have learned that the HIV pan¬
demic flourishes where individual capacity to
learn and to respond is constrained. The major
way in which this capacity is constrained is by
belonging to a group that is discriminated
against, marginalized, or stigmatized. This sug¬
gests that to the extent that societies can reduce
discrimination and promote respect for the
rights and dignity of all their members, they
will become increasingly successful in preventing
HIV transmission. To this extent, they will be
uprooting the HIV/Aids pandemic rather than
simply addressing its surface features.
This leads to the larger hypothesis that the
"essential conditions" for health the societal
determinants of health status are better defined
by modern human rights than by the tradi¬
tional, biomedical, physical health-related mea¬
sures and analyses of health experts. Thus, a
strategic approach to the promotion and pro¬
tection of health is inextricably linked to efforts
to promote respect for human rights within
each society and globally.
1 The specific rights which form the corpus of human
rights are listed in several key documents. Foremost
among them are the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, the United Nations Charter, the International
Covenant on Civil and Political Rights and the
International Covenant on Economic, Social and
Cultural Rights, which constitute what is often called the
"International Bill of Human Rights". 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The search for a vaccine
by Marc Girard
The development of a vaccine against HIV raises highly complex scientific and
economic problems
Chromatography (below) is
one of many purification steps
used in the final stages of
production of an experimental
anti-HIV vaccine being
developed in the United
Kingdom.
The development of a vaccine to prevent
infection with the Acquired Immunode¬
ficiency Syndrome (Aids) presents biomedical
research with an urgent and serious challenge.
Simple prophylactic measures that could
prevent transmission of HIV, such as the
screening of blood donations, the proper steril¬
ization of surgical equipment and needles, or the
use of condoms, are often not a practical propo¬
sition in developing countries because of their
cost and/or because they meet with behavioural
or cultural barriers that are very difficult to
overcome. A vaccine against HIV is therefore
badly needed. (Vaccines are the most efficient
known way of dealing with virus diseases.)
However, in spite of almost ten years of
intensive research, HIV vaccines still elude us.
Nobody can be sure when a vaccine will be
available, nor even if there ever will be a vaccine
to cope with the seemingly endless variation of
HIV and its ability to hide and persist in the
body of infected individuals.
A persisting disease
Why can we not produce a vaccine against HIV
by using the classical methods that have been so
successful in developing vaccines against "clas-
32
sical" virus diseases? The answer to this question
lies in the very properties of HIV and in the
fact that Aids is a persisting disease. HIV is a
retrovirus and as such inserts its genome into the
chromosomes of the cell it infects, then transmits
it as a piece of chromosome from one cell gen¬
eration to the next.
The HIV virus actually does even "better"
than most retroviruses. Classical retroviruses
grow at low levels in infected cells, and cell
growth is usually compatible with virus pro¬
duction: the virus does not kill the cells. HIV,
however, has evolved a series of accessory genes
that allow it to grow very rapidly once it is acti¬
vated and to kill the cell after large numbers of
progeny virus particles have been produced. It
has been estimated that an asymptomatic HIV-
positive individual can produce more than 2
billion HIV particles per day.
Another reason why HIV persists in the
human body is that it can avoid the neutral¬
izing antibody response of the host. The virus
can persist in a latent state inside the infected cell,
remaining dormant and escaping surveillance
by the immune system. It can be transmitted
directly from an infected cell to uninfected cells
by a process known as cell fusion, in which the
virus particles do not come into contact with cir¬
culating antibodies. HIV can also be transported
by the infected cells to organs like the brain
where immune surveillance is minimal.
Finally, the reason why HIV persists so well
is that it attacks two of the major players of the
immune system, the CD4+ T-lymphocyte (also
known as the helper T-ccll) and the macrophage.
At the same time the virus perturbs the com¬
munication network between the different cells
of the immune system, leading to profound
dysregulation of the immune response.
The HIV virus has also developed a remark¬
able ability to change, both within infected indi¬
viduals and from individual to individual. Intrin¬
sically, it is no more variable than viruses such as
the influenza virus or the polio virus. But
whereas the influenza virus actively multiplies
in the infected host for only a few days, HIV
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
This Ugandan district nurse
(left of photo) visits Aids
sufferers and provides them
with medication and
counselling.
multiplies in its host for years, providing ample
time for variants to emerge and be stabilized.
Prototype HIV-1 vaccines
Most of the potential vaccines against HIV-1, the
cause of the Aids pandemic, that have been
tested in chimpanzees and human volunteers
so far have been of what is known as the "sub-
unit" type, consisting of purified viral proteins
mixed with an adjuvant. Such protoype vac¬
cines have demonstrated their protective efficacy
in animal models such as chimpanzees. More
recently it has been shown that immunization
with antigens substances that stimulate the
production of antibodies from one virus strain
(HIV-1 MN) could provide protection in chim¬
panzees from challenge with another virus strain
(HIV-1 SF2). This opens the possibility that
HIV-1 subunit vaccines may provide cross-pro¬
tection from infection with different virus strains
provided they belong to the same subtype.
Although extremely encouraging, these results
are still only preliminary. First of all there has been
no test for protection from infection by the sexual
route in the animal models. Challenge of immu¬
nized chimpanzees has been by intravenous injec¬
tion of the virus; whereas in nature HIV is essen¬
tially transmitted by sexual contact.
Secondly, it has been found that the HIV-1
strains used for challenging the animals are dif¬
ferent from the wild HIV-1 strains that are iso¬
lated from human patients. The challenge strains
have been selected to grow in the laboratory and
are easily neutralized by neutralizing antibodies,
whereas clinical isolates are not neutralized.
Thirdly, challenge of the animals is usually
MARC GIRARD,
a French biochemist, is Deputy
Director and Head of the
Molecular Virology Laboratory of
Paris's Pasteur Institute. He is a
member of the Steering
Committees of WHO'S Global
Programme on Aids (GPA) and of
its Global Programme for
Vaccines and Immunization.
"When I first knew I was HIV-positive, I thought I had Aids. I thought they
were the same thing. It took two weeks' reading before I understood. . . .
The doctor who had told me the news said that in these cases the family is
the best support. I phoned my family, and my father took it very badly. He
scolded me for spoiling the new-year festivities. 'You might have waited,'
he said."
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
All potential vaccines must
first be tested on animals, and
so far only chimpanzees seem
subject to infection by HIV-1,
although they do not develop
Aids. This is another of the
many difficulties in Aids
vaccine research.
done very shortly after a booster immuniza¬
tion, i.e. at or very near the peak of the immune
response. The fact that the antibody response
elicited by HIV-1 vaccines appears to be tran¬
sient in chimpanzees raises the question of
whether the vaccines would induce sufficient
immune memory to provide long-term protec¬
tion in a natural setting.
Finally, it has not been possible from studies
on animals to identify in a reproducible manner
correlates of protection that could be used to
predict vaccine efficacy. In other words, no
yardsticks are available by which to measure
potential vaccine efficacy.
Ohould prototype vaccines be tested
on humans?
Before undertaking large-scale (Phase III) effi¬
cacy trials in populations at risk, in which a
vaccine would be compared in a blind fashion
with a placebo, trials must be conducted to
assess the safety and immunogenicity (capacity
to stimulate immunity) of candidate vaccine(s)
in small numbers of human volunteers. Some
subunit vaccines have been tested on human
volunteers, and shown to be safe and immuno¬
genic. This does not mean, however, that these
vaccines would protect humans against infection.
To find this out, an efficacy trial is needed.
The National Institutes of Health of the United
States recendy decided not to proceed in expanding
efficacy trials of HIV-1 subunit vaccines, arguing
that more predictive scientific data were needed
that would make one reasonably confident that
protection could be achieved by the administration
of the vaccine. Furthermore, it was felt that vac¬
cines based on more than one viral antigen might
have a better chance of being effective. Finally, the
fear was expressed that individuals taking part in
an efficacy trial might perceive that they were
protected, which could make them change their
behaviour and be at higher risk of HIV infection.
34
Testing a vaccine in a developing
country which would not be able to
afford it later because of excessive
pricing is difficult to accept. It is also
clear that the concept of developing
a safe, sophisticated but expensive
medicine for the industrialized
countries and unsafe,
unsophisticated but cheap vaccine
for the developing countries is
ethically unacceptable.
At a recent WHO meeting, however, it was
decided that "Phase III efficacy trials . . . could be
conducted to obtain definite information on the
ability of candidate vaccines to induce protective
immunity in humans". This different attitude
reflects the fact that public health needs may differ
from country to country, resulting in different
recommendations in different parts of the world.
However, there should be no scientific or ethical
shortcut in planning an efficacy trial in any country.
Vaccine testing in developing countries
The prospect of launching efficacy trials in
developing countries is presently meeting many
difficulties, some technical and others ethical.
One technical problem is the fact that it has
not been possible so far, in spite of repeated
attempts, to develop a multivalent, "universal"
HIV-1 vaccine based on conserved antigenic
determinants. It is therefore necessary that spe¬
cific vaccines be developed to match the circu¬
lating HIV-1 isolates in the developing countries.
Another technical problem stems from the
need to strengthen local infrastructures in these
countries, i.e. hospitals and laboratories, and to
train local personnel. It is impossible to plan an effi¬
cacy trial that would involve from several hundreds
to a few thousand volunteers without appropriate
logistical and professional support in the field.
Among the many ethical problems that may
arise, that of the modification of sexual behaviour
that might possibly be induced by a large-scale
vaccine trial is of serious concern. Such a trial
would be dangerous if the attitude of the volun¬
teers towards prevention was significantly altered
as a consequence of their enrollment in it. Edu¬
cating the people is, therefore, one of the most
important prerequisites to a large-scale trial. It is
noteworthy that even some elites in developing
countries confuse the use of vaccines in prevention
and their use in immunotherapeutic interven¬
tions. Unreasonable expectancy of protection
from highly exposed and poorly educated people
is much to be feared. This could be overcome
only by repeated counselling and education.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 36
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Aids in a different light
by Marie-Thérèse Bocabeille
MARIE-THÉRÈSE BOCABEILLE
is a staff member of UNESCO's
Promotion and Sales Division.
THE POSSIBILITIES OF TRADITIONAL MEDICINE
Modern medicine so far has nothing effective to offer to Aids
patients, in spite of the massive technological, chemical, sur¬
gical and radiotherapeutic resources devoted to Aids research
in recent years. At the same time, the principles of traditional
forms of medicine have been ignored. And yet, while they
make no claim to halt the epidemic, they can make a big con¬
tribution to the strengthening of the immune defences and
to the prevention of opportunistic diseases.
According to Dr. Christian Tal Schaller1, who has twenty-
five years' experience as a practitioner of alternative medi¬
cine, there are two schools of thought. On the one hand there
are those who believe that the virus is the sole or major cause
of the immunodeficiency. On the other, there are practi¬
tioners who are in touch with natural medicine movements
all over the world and who subscribe to the dictum of the great
French physiologist Claude Bernard (1813-1878): "The virus
is nothing, the terrain is everything".
The "terrain" comprises all the different parts of an
individual that it would be too simple to limit to his or her phys¬
ical body. In addition to the physical organs, which are them¬
selves very complex, there are all kinds of complex forces and
states of mind that play an essential role in any process of
improvement.
Modern medicine, sophisticated though it may be, is
almost exclusively concerned with physical illnesses which
it regards as originating from outsidepeople are supposed
to "catch" a diseasewithout the individual's having any par¬
ticular responsibility for what happens to him or her.
It must be accepted, however, that this approach provides
no explanation as to why, for example, not everyone who is
HIV-positive develops Aids nor why some even return to
being HIV-negative.
As things stand at present, the possibilities offered by
traditional medicine cannot be ignored, much less snubbed
or made fun of.
'HOW I BECAME HIV-NEGATIVE AGAIN'
Niro Markoff Asistent, a Belgian therapist living in the United
States, was diagnosed HIV-positive in 1985. Some time
went by before she accepted her condition and recognized her
own responsibility for her rundown state. When her doctor
admitted there was nothing he could do for her, she decided
to take her life in her own hands. Using with the utmost care
the 500-day reprieve she had been given, she embarked on
a voyage of physical and mental self-discovery.
A year later, Niro Asistent became HIV-negative again.
Inspired by her experience, she created a foundation, the Self
Healing Aids-Related Experiment (S.H.A.R.E.), to which she
now devotes her life. "I believe," she writes, "that Aids is the
most powerful transformational tool that has ever been
available to us on a mass level. It has detonated a bomb under
the surface of society that is forcing us to reevaluate the entire
foundation of life as we know it. It is shaking the medical com
munity and its related industries, it is affecting the educational
and judicial systems. It is forcing us to question our values,
our morals and our identities.2
THE VIRUS, A NECESSARY BUT NOT A SUFFICIENT
CONDITION
HIV alone is not enough to cause Aids, because not all HIV-
positive people develop Aids. There are thus grounds for
thinking that other factors, or co-factors, are involved.
A California research centre3 has drawn up a list of co-
factors which may contribute to the acceleration or slowdown
of immunodeficiency. They include psychological factors
such as stress, depression, pain and the conviction that one
is dying. Others, such as nutrition, oxygenation, sleep or phys¬
ical exercise, are related to life-style. Therapeutic treatment,
relations with one's doctor, and the capacity to cure oneself
are also involved.
'HIV IS NO DEATH SENTENCE'
Mark Griffiths4, a British musician, was diagnosed HIV-posi¬
tive in 1986. He immediately began improving his quality of
life by learning to know himself and live at peace with himself.
He sought to disintoxicate himself physically and mentally by
natural methods, and gradually recreated the bond between
his inner self and his body. By following his own evolution,
without any miracle cure but with great confidence in his own
intuition, he became his own doctor.
In the summer of 1990, Mark Griffiths came across a text
entitled Is the Aids virus science fiction? by Peter Duesberg
of the University of California, Berkeley, which echoed many
of the doubts and questions that arose when he learned he
was HIV-positive, especially about the opportunistic dis¬
eases that he was told he would encounter. In September of
that year, he published a booklet entitled Healing into
freedom: Aids, the apprenticeship, in which he reported the
experiences of those he calls the long-term survivors.
Intent on encouraging the publication of alternative research
which would be both scientific and rigorous, he has become the
champion of a new way of looking at the question and a new
debate. He believes that to be HIV-positive should not be
regarded as a death sentence. He is fighting for patients to be
free to choose their treatment. He has created a network
which collects the testimony of people who have returned to
good health after a serious illness, of scientists who support
the theses of natural regeneration and therapists who teach
self-healing. The Aids acronym for him has been reshuffled to
read "Acquired Interior Development Source".
1 Dr. Christian Tal Schaller, 32 av. Petit Senn, 1225 Chêne-
Bourg, Geneva (Switzerland).
2. Niro Markoff Asistent, Why I survive Aids, Simon and
Schuster/Fireside, New York, 1991, pp. 243-244.
3. LIFE (Learning Immune Function Enhancement), Aids
Response programme, Center for Social Services, 3916 Normal
Street, San Diego CA 92163, U.S.A.
4. Mark Griffiths, 87, chemin du Vélard, F-01710, Tholry
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
36
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 34
Another problem is that of the subsequent
availability of the vaccine. Testing a vaccine in a
developing country which would not be able to
afford it later because of excessive pricing would
be difficult to accept. It should also be made
clear that the concept of developing a safe,
sophisticated, but expensive vaccine for the
industrialized countries and an unsafe, unso¬
phisticated but cheap vaccine for the developing
countries is ethically unacceptable.
Making HIV-1 vaccines available to
developing countries
It is obvious that the success of vaccination
against HIV will depend on the characteristics
of the future HIV-1 vaccines on their safety,
efficacy, duration of protection, stability, the
number of doses required for full immunization,
and last but not least, their cost. There has been
very strong political pressure to make HIV-1
vaccines available to developing countries at a
marginal cost. Even though we are still years
away from marketing such vaccines, it is appro¬
priate for the public health community to set the
stage for an effective global Aids-prevention
effort. One should realize, however, that the
cost of developing a new vaccine has reached
fantastic heights due to the enforcement of
stricter regulations, tighter quality controls,
higher safety standards, and to the very high
cost of clinical studies, not to mention the cost
of research itself. Aids-vaccine research for the
past ten years in the United States and Europe
has already cost several billion dollars.
The financial returns to be expected by the
vaccine manufacturers will obviously be low,
vaccines being quite different in this respect
from pharmaceutical drugs. How could a vac¬
cine be made available to developing countries?
One possibility would be to sell the vaccine to
these countries for a low price and for a compen¬
satory high price on the Western world market.
But how low is low? It has been estimated that an
HIV-1 vaccine would be administered yearly to
about 300,000 persons worldwide, which could
involve 1,200,000,000 doses, not counting subse¬
quent booster doses. Manufacturing, controlling
and distributing such an enormous number of
vaccine doses would cost several billions of dollars.
It is clear that we will have to invent a mech¬
anism, such as direct payment from an interna¬
tional agency to the manufacturing companies, to
provide the companies with sufficient reward
while at the same time supplying the Aids vaccine
to the developing world at a rock bottom price.
This is basically what UNICEF (the United
Nations Children's Fund) and the Pan-Amer¬
ican Health Organization (PAHO) are trying to
do for classical vaccines. But the chances of suc¬
cess of such an operation will depend strictly on
the goodwill of the industrialized nations.
Artists against
Puppets Against Aids,
a company from
Johannesburg, South
Africa.
Maw Lum Drama, a company
from Thailand that takes part in
a rural Aids-prevention project.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Aids: getting the message across
Photos and text from a report by Erika Lüdecke
Teatro Sociedad
Anónima, a street-
theatre company
from Chile.
On the fringe of the 9th International Aids Conference,
held in Berlin in 1993, Deutsche AIDS Hilfe, an umbrella
group for associations fighting Aids in Germany, organized
an "Aids CultureCultural Aids" Festival in co-operation
with the German National Commission for Unesco. For a
week artists from all over the world (painters, sculptors,
rockers, rappers, puppeteers and actors) used their
talents to inform the public and promote Aids prevention.
Photos show street actors and dancers who were among
the most talented and original performers at the Festival.
American
Dakotas Indian
Dance Group,
United States.
Mwanza Masauto Mobile
Theater (Triple MT),
itinerant
musicians and
actors from
Zambia.
The "Prevention Cabaret", a
Brazilian show created by
homosexuals.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
^V Ajoint UN programme against
^ Aids&
rTo strengthen efforts to fight the spread of Aids,
j six United Nations Agencies have agreed to co¬
operate in a joint United Nations programme on
HIV-Aids. The agencies are the World Health
Organization (WHO), the UN Development
Programme (UNDP), the World Bank, the UN
Population Fund (UNFPA), the UN Children's
Fund (UNICEF) and UNESCO. The programme,
which will combine existing efforts and will be
administered by WHO, will come into opera¬
tion in January 1996.
. '' The specialized agencies concerned have
already been involved in combatting the Aids
pandemic for almost a decade. Here is a brief
account of their activities:
World Health Organization: its Global Pro¬
gramme on Aids helps individual countries to
take short-term measures in response to the
crisis and to establish long-term national pre¬
vention programmes. Today national Aids pro¬
grammes have been established in virtually every
country of the world, most of them with WHO
advice and guided by WHO's Global Aids
Strategy. WHO also provides financial resources
and equipment, carries out epidemiological
monitoring, supports the development of vac¬
cines and research into new approaches to Aids
prevention and care.
WHO, 20 Avenue Appia, 1211 Geneva 27,
Switzerland.
Telex: 41 54 16; Telephone: (41 22) 791 46 52;
Fax: (41 22) 791 03 17.
United Nations Development Programme:
UNDP's particular responsibility is to provide
support in tackling the social and economic reper¬
cussions of the epidemic and minimizing its
impact on human development. Its mandate is to
increase awareness, expand the capacity of com¬
munities to respond, assist prevention, care, sup¬
port and treatment programmes for women and
help to develop multi-sectoral HIV strategies.
UNDP, One United Nations Plaza,
New York, NY. 10017, U.S.A.
Telex: 125 980, 236 286, 422 862;
Telephone: (1 212) 906 5000;
Tax: (1212) 8262057.
World Bank: the largest source of finance for
Aids prevention programmes. Since 1986 cumu¬
lative lending for Aids prevention and control in
some 40 countries amounts to over $500 million.
World Bank, 1818 H Street NW, Washington
DC 20433, U.S.A. Telex: RCA 248423, ITT
440098, WUI 64145; Telephone: (1 202) 477
1234; Fax: (1 202) 477 6391.
United Nations Population Fund: in 1992,
UNFPA supported Aids prevention and control
activities in 84 countries. It provides information
and counselling on Aids prevention, and dis¬
tributes condoms as part of maternal and child
health and family planning programmes.
UNFPA, 220 East 42nd Street, New York,
N.Y. 10017, U.S.A.
Telex: 7607883; Telephone: (1 212) 297 50 11;
Fax: (1 212) 370 0201.
United Nations Children's Fund: UNICEF
distributes information through school cur¬
ricula and health education programmes,
notably to women and children at risk. It also
provides orientation and training for those likely
to come into contact with Aids patients and
their relatives, and works to expand primary
health care services, with particular attention
to the sterilization of medical equipment. It is
also examining ways of caring for the growing
number of Aids orphans.
UNICEF, UNICEF House, 3, United
Nations Plaza, New York, N. Y 10017, U.S.A.
Telex: 7607848, 175989;
Telephone: (1 212) 326 7000;
Fax: (1 212) 888 7465.
United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization: Unesco supports an
interdisciplinary approach to Aids-related prob¬
lems, associating knowledge of their socio-cul¬
tural, ethnic and scientific aspects with a mastery
of communication techniques. UNESCO/WHO
pilot projects in school-based Aids education
adapted to different socio-cultural contexts have
been undertaken in different world regions. An
Aids School Education Resource Centre
(ASERC) for the gathering, exchange and dif¬
fusion of educative materials for young people
of school age has been set up at UNESCO Head¬
quarters. It contains over 2,500 publications
and 150 video films from all the world regions.
Bibliographies and extracts of didactic mate¬
rials are regularly published.
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07
SP, France.
Telex: 204461 Paris, 270602 Paris;
Telephone: (33 1) 45 68 09 29;
Fax: (33 1) 47 83 27 10.
The World
Foundation
for Aids
Research and
Prevention was
established in January 1993 by the
Director-General of UNESCO, Mr.
Federico Mayor, and Professor Luc
Montagnier, who discovered the
human immunodeficiency virus. The
goal of the Foundation, whose
president is Prof. Montagnier, is to
mobilize all kinds of private
initiatives, to create new partnerships
and find new forms of co-operation,
especially in research and prevention,
in order to support and add to action
taken by public authorities in the
fight against Aids.
Stimulus for research
One of the Foundations priorities is to
build an international network of pilot
research centres in order to stimulate
co-operation between researchers. The
first three centres arc being established
Documentation
The documents produced by Unesco are available free of
charge (except when stated otherwise) from the Section for
Preventive Education, Unesco (for address see box at left).
School Health Education to Prevent AIDS and STD: A
Resource Package for Curriculum Planners, Paris,
Unesco/WHO, 1994, 3 volumes.
Vol. I: Handbook for Curriculum Planners, 88 pp.
Vol. II: Students' Activities, 79 pp.
Vol. Ill: Teachers' Guide, 117 pp.
Selection of Extracts from Teachers' Guides, No. 1,
Paris, Unesco/WHO, 1992, 146 pp.
School Health Education to Prevent AIDS and Sexually
Transmitted Diseases (WHO AIDS Series 10), Geneva,
WHO/Unesco, 1992, 79 pp. Available at WHO Global Pro¬
gramme on AIDS, 1211 Geneva 27, Switzerland.
Education for AIDS Prevention. Bibliography. Paris,
Unesco, 1994, 180 pp. + Supplements.
Annotated list of videos gathered in the ASERC, Paris,
Unesco, 1994, 26 pp. (Multilingual).
List of posters gathered in the ASERC, Paris, Unesco,
1994, 25 pp.
Posters issued on the occasion of World AIDS Day.
AIDSFacts and Hopes (Ed. Prof. Luc Montagnier),
Paris, Pasteur Institute, 1988, 64 pp.
The Impact ofHIV/AIDS on EducationA Review of Lit¬
erature and Experience. Sheldon Shaeffer, Paris, Unesco,
1994, 45 pp.
Unesco Asian Planning Seminar on AIDS and Education
within the School System, New Delhi, 10-14 January 1994.
Final Report, 55 pp.
WHO/Unesco Pilot Projects on School-based AIDS Edu¬
cation: A Summary. Geneva, WHO, 1994, 55 pp.
Bibliography: Education for the Prevention ofAIDS (Bul¬
letin of the International Bureau of Education No.262).
Geneva, IBE, 1992, 48 pp.
VIDE0:A/DS, It's Time for Schools to Act! (Dir. Jean-Louis
Gros), Paris, Unesco, 20 mn on VHS/PAL and VHS/NTSC.
CD-ROM: A Bibliography on Education for AIDS Prevention
is available from the Documentation and Information Service,
Education Sector, Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris
07 SP, France. Tel: (331)45 68 10 29. Fax: (331)45 67 45 83.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
A World Foundation for Aids Research and Prevention
in Paris, Abidjan (Côte d'Ivoire)
and in California (U.S.A.). A
fourth is planned for Asia.
The purpose of the pilot pro¬
ject at the Saint-Joseph Hospital
in Paris is to create rapidly a
centre that combines clinical
examinations and laboratory
testing in order to ensure reg¬
ular follow-up of a cohort of
asymptomatic HIV-positive
patients receiving associated
treatment. The centre is due to
open at the end of 1995. Fol¬
lowing a media campaign called
Sidaction, carried out in France
in April 1994 under the auspices
of Luc Montagnier with the
major anti-Aids organizations,
the Foundation received 25 mil¬
lion French francs, which will
enable the centre to meet run¬
ning costs for two years.
The Abidjan Centre will be
concerned with applied research
and training and will also work
with Côte d'Ivoire 's National
Centre for Blood Transfusions
(CNTS) on the follow-up of
HIV-infected patients. The Ivo-
rian government has already ear¬
marked a site for the centre,
which will receive support from
WHO and the joint UN pro¬
gramme on HIV/Aids. The
centre will reach out to Africa as
a whole, opening branches in
interested countries with the help
of doctors and scientists from
industrialized countries who wish
to take part in this international
effort. The Foundation has
already sent a technician to the
CNTS and fitted out a labora¬
tory to launch a research project
in connection with the latter.
Negotiations have begun
with institutions in Los Angeles
and Pasadena (California,
U.S.A.) to set up a research
centre that will work with the
Paris and Abidjan centres.
A window of hope
The Foundation is encouraging
the creation of scientific com¬
mittees on Aids to complement
the work of these centres.
During a meeting of African sci¬
entists held in Paris under the
aegis of the Foundation and
UNESCO prior to the Paris
Summit on Aids of 1 December
1 994, it was decided to establish
an African scientific committee
and solidarity fund.
The Foundation will pro¬
mote the opening of new forms
of interdisciplinary co-operation
in order to identify any approach
that offers a ray of hope. A first
meeting with this in view was
held in Venice in October 1994
to establish a dialogue between
Aids experts and researchers in
other fields: physicists, mathe¬
maticians and chemists. Other
meetings will be held periodi
cally to promote similar forms of
co-operation.
Another of the Foundation's
priorities is to strengthen pre¬
vention by working with
UNESCO to find policies that are
most suited to each country's
socio-cultural context. Two pilot
projects are currently being car¬
ried out, one in Uganda and the
other in Ethiopia, in co-opera¬
tion with the universities of
Makerere in Kampala, Addis
Ababa in Ethiopia and Johns
Hopkins in the United States.
The projects are primarily aimed
at children and adolescents from
5 to 15, the age group least
affected by Aids and through
whom a "window of hope" may
open.
World Foundation for Aids Research
and Prevention, International
Secretariat, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris
Cedex 15. Tel: (33-1) 4568-3841;
Fax: (33-1) 4273-3745.
Glossary
Aetiology: study of the causes of diseases.
Aids: "Acquired Immune Deficiency Syn¬
drome", a serious disease caused by the
virus, HIV, which destroys the immune
defences of the body, which is then subject
to serious "opportunistic" infections and
certain cancers.
Antibodies: substance secreted by B lym¬
phocytes in response to aggression on
the body by substances known as anti¬
gens. Each antibody is specific for a par¬
ticular antigen. In the case of HIV, the
antibodies secreted are not all neutral¬
izing. In spite of their presence the virus
can thus continue its destructive effects.
Condom: a rubber sheath which fits over
the penis when a man is sexually excited
and the penis is hard. It can be used to
protect against pregnancy and sexually
transmitted diseases.
DNA: deoxyribonucleic acid, a large mol¬
ecule that carries genetic information and
forms the basis for heredity.
ELISA: abbreviation for Enzyme Linked
Immuno-Sorbent Assay. This is the sero¬
logical (blood) test most widely used to
detect whether the body has reacted to
the presence of HIV.
Epidemic: an occurrence of disease that
is temporarily of high prevalence. The rise
and decline of an epidemic are related to
such factors as the gravity of the disease,
the mode of transmission of the infective
agent, environmental conditions, length of
the incubation period and the existence of
asymptomatic carriers. Methods of com¬
batting an epidemic must be adapted to
these factors. Infection by HIV is trans¬
missible but not highly contagious. The
incubation period is long.
Epidemiology: study of the causes of
appearance, disappearance or dissemi¬
nation of diseases.
HIV: the human immunodeficiency virus,
which causes Aids. There are two main
types of the virus: HIV-1, which is respon¬
sible for the worldwide pandemic of Aids,
and HIV-2, which can also cause Aids and
occurs mainly in West Africa.
Immune system: all the mechanisms that
act to defend the body against external
agents (bacteria, viruses, parasites) or
toxic substances described as antigens. The
immune system can distinguish between
aggressors belonging to the body itself and
external aggressors. It can recognize those
which are aggressive, those against which
it already has defences (natural or acquired).
It knows how to organize an appropriate
attack against the antigens. To do this it
uses antibodies (or immunoglobulins) vehi-
cled by the circulatory flow (the "humoral"
response); specific cells called B and T
lymphocytes, which are capable of recog¬
nizing the antigens, organizing the response
and producing new antibodies (the cellular
response); macrophage cells which clean up
after the lymphocytes and antibodies. The
T4 lymphocytes, which co-ordinate immune
defences, are strategic cells that constitute
the target of HIV, which paralyses and
destroys them.
Immunosuppression: reduction in the
body's immune defence mechanisms.
Incubation: interval between entry of the
microorganism into the body and the date
of the onset of the first symptoms of the
disease. In the case of Aids, the incuba¬
tion period is very variable; it may range
from several weeks to several months or
even several years.
Opportunistic infection: infection induced
by a micro-organism that is usually well tol¬
erated by the body and only becomes
pathogenic when the body's defences are
depressed. The most serious manifesta¬
tions of Aids are caused by opportunistic
infections.
Prevention: individual or collective mea¬
sures aimed at limiting or avoiding risk of
accident or disease, reducing its conse¬
quences and treating its effects. In health
care, prevention includes social as well as
purely medical measures.
Retrovirus: virus in which the genetic
material is composed of RNA, but which is
converted in the cell to DNA by a special
enzyme, reverse transcriptase. HIV is a
retrovirus.
Seropositive or HIV-positive: a person with
a positive screening test for antibodies to
HIV. This person has been in contact with
HIV and should be considered to be poten¬
tially contagious by his/her blood and by
sexual relations. When the test does not
detect antibodies, the person is said to be
"seronegative" or "HIV-negative".
RNA: Ribonucleic acid. It transmits the
genetic information carried by DNA within
the cell. All the genetic material of the
human immunodeficiency virus consists
of RNA molecules.
STD: sexually transmitted diseases, i.e.
diseases that can be contracted by means
of sexual relations. Aids is essentially a
sexually transmitted disease.
Syndrome: a combination of symptoms
and signs that may constitute a common
denominator for certain diseases. The
immunodeficiency syndrome constitutes
the essential feature of Aids, but it can
also occur in other contexts, such as con¬
genital diseases or tumours (leukaemia)
or it may be drug-induced (immunosup¬
pressant treatment in transplant patients).
Virus: infectious agents responsible for
numerous diseases in all living beings.
They are extremely small particles (which
can only be seen under the electron micro¬
scope) and, unlike bacteria, can only survive
and multiply within a living cell at the
expense of this cell.
White blood cells: blood cells responsible
for the defence of the body against foreign
agents.
Sources: Adsfacts and Hopes, Pasteur Institute,
1993; Action for Youth. Aids training manual. League
of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies/World
Organization of the Scout Movement; te síefa,
réponses aux questions du personnel de santé sur
l'infection par le VIH, AP-HP & ARCAT-SIDA, 1993.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Susali. pearl of the Tunisian Sahel
by Moncef Ghachem
40
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
Jewel of the Sahel on Tunisia's east coast, witness to
3,000 years ofMediterranean history, the Medina
ofSitsah is a treasure-trove ofpast and present.
Famed for its craftsmanship, its
festivities and its hospitality,
Susafi is the capital of the Sahel,
the olive-growing region bordering the
Mediterranean in eastern Tunisia.
During the hot Tunisian summer its
streets are filled with singing and
dancing. Visitors flock from other parts
of Tunisia and from abroad to enjoy the
rhythms, colours and games of the
Aoussou (August) festival, when
colourful costumes and parades evoke
episodes in the long history of this cos¬
mopolitan city whose heritage includes
Christian catacombs, Roman mosaics,
the vestiges of a Byzantine citadel and the
ramparts of the Arab Medina (old town).
A thousand years before the Christian
era, Susah was already a trading centre
and a stopping-off place on the route
from Tyr to Spain. The Phoenicians,
who called it Hadrumet, established an
important trading station there two cen¬
turies before the foundation of Carthage.
During his campaign against Seipio at
the end of the Second Punic War, Han¬
nibal sailed to Hadrumet from Italy,
used its port and pitched his camp there.
Under the Roman Empire, rich colonists
who owed their wealth to the agricul¬
tural produce of the fertile back country
poured into Susah. In the seventh cen¬
tury battles between Arabs and Byzan¬
tines reduced the city to ashes. Then it
rose from its ruins and was given its pre¬
sent name. But two centuries went by
before it regained some importance
under the rule of the Aghlabids, who
improved its port and erected its main
monuments. In the twelfth century the
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Left, Susan's Great Mosque,
built in 851. Right, massive
pillars and arches in the prayer
hall.
Normans of Sicily used it as a base, and
in the sixteenth the Spanish attacked
and tried to occupy it. Two centuries
later it was bombarded by the French. In
the Second World War the Germans used
its port, which was badly damaged by the
Allies in the winter of 1942-1943. Fol¬
lowing the war, the modern city was built
and the Medina carefully restored.
THE GREAT MOSQUE
Its souks teeming with life, the Medina of
Susah is one of the most remarkable old
quarters in Tunisia. It gives onto the port,
where freighters laden with salt and oil
wait to weigh anchor. There are several
gates in the ramparts that girdle it, but the
main access is in the northeast, near
Farhat Hached Square, where Allied bom¬
bardments in 1943 opened a wide breach.
At the entry to the Medina on the right
flank of a broad esplanade paved with
rough stones is the Great Mosque, which
dates from the ninth century. Careful
restoration work has recreated its original
appearance. The main courtyard is sur¬
rounded by three vaulted galleries whose
squat pillars and tall arches are austere
and functional. The more decorative
southern gallery (modified in 1675 and
restored in 1965) leads to the prayer hall,
whose thirteen naves, each
with six bays, are similar in
style although they date from
different periods. The fourth
bay from the present mihrab
(the prayer niche in the wall
facing Mecca), is covered by
a dome resting on small shell-
shaped arches. Its lower sec¬
tions are adorned with highly
stylized floral patterns,
sculpted squares framing
rosettes and a fine inscrip¬
tion in Kufic script. The
ornate minbar (pulpit), like
a piece of wooden lacework,
contrasts sharply with the
sober architecture of the
Mosque.
A FORT MANNED BY
PIOUS WARRIORS
On leaving the Great
Mosque, the visitor can
wander through the narrow
streets of the Medina lined
with chalk-white houses,
climb stairways and and
plunge into mysterious pas¬
sageways before coming to
the austerely beautiful
Left, the minbar or pulpit of finely
carved wood.
Ribat, a fortified monastery dating from
the end of the eighth century. The Ribat
was one of the coastal forts that, from
Alexandria to Ceuta, formed a defen¬
sive line for Islam against the fleets of
Byzantium. Mooring rings attached to
the walls indicate that the latter were
once battered by the waves. The Ribat
takes its name from the murabitin, pious
warriors who were stationed there to
defend the city from enemy incursions.
The Ribat too has been recently
restored and now looks as it must have
done centuries ago. Ancient columns and
capitals flank the entrance, which was
protected by a portcullis. Openings in the
roof were used as points from which to
harass attackers. The low, dark guard¬
rooms used by the murabitin stand on
each side of the entrance hall, the roof of
which is supported by intersecting
arches. Around the central courtyard
are rooms that were used by the devout
soldiers for their ablutions, and galleries
concealing windowless cells. On the first
floor the cells only occupy three sides of
the quadrangle: the south wing contains
a prayer hall divided by heavy cruci¬
form pillars into two bays of unequal
size. The qibla, the inner wall facing
Mecca, is pierced with loopholes,
reflecting the building's combined reli¬
gious and military character. From the
top of the nador, which is both a watch-
tower and a minaret, there is a won¬
derful panoramic view over Susah and
the surrounding countryside.
MOSAIC MASTERPIECES
After leaving the Medina by the western _ -
Gate (Bab el-Gharbi), a stroll along the nfJL
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
m
CHRONOLOGY
42
Above, the Ribat, a late 8th century fortified
monastery. It is protected by a square perimeter wall,
each side of which is nearly 30 metres long. At each
corner and halfway along each wall are semi-
cylindrical towers.
A street In the Medina climbing to the Khalef el Fata
tower at the southeastern corner of Susah's ramparts.
The tower is thought to have been built in the 9th
century and modeled on the great Roman lighthouse
at Leptis Magna on the Tripolitanian coast of Libya.
ramparts takes us to the Kasbah, which
is dominated by the imposing Khalef
tower, built in 859. Fully integrated into
the urban fabric, the Kasbah houses the
city museum, which is noted for its col¬
lection of Roman mosaics, discovered
in Susah and in the surrounding area.
Masterpieces by the finest mosaic makers
line the walls of the patio. The opulent
lifestyle of the Romans who lived in the
Tunisian Sahel in the second and third
centuries seems to have provided the
craftsmen with their main themes. As
well as remarkable portraits of the sea
god, a triumphantly dancing Bacchus,
Apollo and the muses, Venus at her toilet
and Orpheus calming wild animals, there
are also many scenes from daily life, of
hunting, fishing and horse-racing, and
depictions of fish, fruit and birds
including fan-tailed peacocks.
The Kasbah museum also contains
Punic, Roman and Byzantine funerary
objects and remarkable stelae found in
the catacombs around Susah and assem¬
bled here after galleries collapsed as a
result of water infiltration. Used in the
second and fifth centuries and discovered
MONCEFGHACHEM
is a Tunisian poet and journalist. His latest work,
L'éperviernouvelles de Mahdia ("The Sparrow-
HawkStories from al-Mahdlyah", SPM, Paris,
1994) received a special mention from the jury of
the Albert Camus prize, 1994.
at the end of the last century, the cata¬
combs contain 15,000 pagan and Chris¬
tian tombs. They are over five kilometres
long and are lined with niches dug in the
walls and closed off by tiles or marble
slabs.
It would be wrong to leave Susah
without taking the magnificent corniche
that winds its way above the beach at
Boujaâfar. The sea stretches away into
the distance, its sounds seeming to offer
an eternal promise of happy and pros¬
perous voyages. Like many other
Tunisian coastal towns, Susah encour¬
ages tourism. The tourist area stretches
northwards, beyond the yacht harbour
at El-Kantawi, built beside a holiday vil¬
lage whose houses follow the curve of
the bay. These are elegant structures
that do not detract from Susah's cul¬
tural heritage. On the contrary they con¬
firm that Susah is still what it has always
been, a city of new beginnings.
'
9th century B.C.: Hadrumet is founded
by Phoenician sailors.
6th century B.C.: Hadrumet comes under
Carthaginian rule and becomes involve
in the Punic Wars.
310 B.C.: It is sacked by the Syracusan
Agathocles.
202 B.C.: Hannibal sets up his camp at
Hadrumet before being defeated by
Scipio.
146 B.C.: Wisely taking sides with the
Romans during the Third Punic War,
Hadrumet is granted the status of a free
city and named "Hadrumetum".
46 B.C.: Caesar annexes the Numidian
kingdom and rescinds Hadrumetum's
privileges.
A.D. 284-305: The city becomes the cap¬
ital of the new province of Byzacena.
429: Vandal invasion.
533: The city is reconquered by Justinian,
emperor of the eastern Roman empire,
and renamed Justinianopolis.
647: The city is conquered by the Arabs
and destroyed.
End of the 7th century: It rises from the
I ashes and is called Susah.
800: Beginning of the Aghlabid dynasty
(Sunnite Muslims).
827: Susah is used as the port of embarka¬
tion for the Muslim bines attacking Sicily.
844: Construction of the first Kasbah.
851: Construction of the Creat Mosque.
909: The Falimids (Shi'ites) come to
power.
1053: \fter the Zirids break with the
Fatimid Suzerain in Cairo and Ifriqiya
returns to Sunnite orthodoxy, Susah
rebels and its harbour is burned.
12th century: The city is occupied by the
Normans and then falls under the domi¬
nation of the Almohad Moroccan Berber
dynasty.
I.'5th century: The Hafsids come to power.
14th century: Decline of the Hal'sid state,
which collapses in the 16th century.
1574: The Turks dominate the whole of
Tunisia.
1 7th century: Susah becomes a port used
by big Ottoman pirate ships.
1705: The Husaynids come to power.
1770: Susah is bombarded by the French.
1784-86: Venitian bombardments cause
major destruction.
1864: The Sahel rises against Ottoman
rule.
1942-194.'): Susah is seriously daniagt
during allied operations in the Tunisia
campaign.
1988: The Medina of Susah is placed on
I MESCO's World Heritage List.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
Turkey, land of
diversity
by France Bequette
Right, a
"spontaneous"
settlement in
Ankara.
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
questions.
Apeninsula 1,565 long and 550 km
wide, Turkey has an extraordi¬
nary diversity of natural habi¬
tats and a correspondingly rich animal
and plant life. It shares borders with
Syria, the former Soviet Union, Iran,
Iraq, Bulgaria and Greece, and its 8,372
kilometres of coastline are washed by
the Mediterranean, the Aegean, the Sea
of Marmara and the Black Sea. All kinds
of terrain are found in Turkey: moun¬
tains, especially in central and eastern
Anatolia, with an average altitude of
1 ,250 metres, plateaux, fertile plains and
extensive beaches. The climate is equally
varied. The Mediterranean seaboard has
dry, warm summers and rainy winters,
while central Anatolia has a raw, dry
continental climate.
Turkey's population increased from
13.7 million in 1927 to 37.3 million in
1991 and may reach 70 million by the
year 2000. As part of a massive and con¬
tinuing east-west migratory trend, rural
populations are moving into the cities,
especially those on the coast. Today 59
per cent of Turks live in cities, particu¬
larly Ankara, Istanbul and Izmir, and
this is giving rise to serious environ¬
mental problems. Istanbul, straddling
the Bosphorus with one foot in Europe
and one in Asia, is not even sure of the
number of its inhabitants. Figures of
10, 13 or 15 million have been advanced.
New arrivals, mostly from Anatolia,
build dwellings wherever they can, with
little regard for hygiene or the dangers
of flooding. From time to time bulldozers
flatten these "spontaneous" settlements,
and their owners are relocated.
No such instant "solution" exists
for air pollution, which sometimes
reaches alarming proportions. Last Feb¬
ruary thick fog covered Istanbul, and
the sulphur dioxide level rose above the
alarm barrier of 400 micrograms per
cubic metre in seven of the city's dis¬
tricts. In some it even reached 680
micrograms.
In a recent interview, Ms Nesrin
Algan, head of the department of inter¬
national relations at the Ministry of the
Environment in Ankara, talked about
another problem facing Turkey. "Ero¬
sion is ten to twelve times worse than the
African average," she said, "and eigh¬
teen limes worse than the European. The
culprits are deforestation, fires and over
grazing in our mountainous areas." More
than a quarter of Turkey is covered by
woodland, mostly in the coastal areas.
Although nine million hectares are in sat¬
isfactory condition, eleven million have
been damaged by rampant urbanization,
by tourism, agriculture and pests.
MIGRATORY BIRDS AND MARINE
TURTLES
Nevertheless, Turkey continues to be a
veritable botanical treasure-trove. Some
12,000 different plant species have been
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
u
I-
<
S
LU
LU
K
O
This drawing by 9-
year-old Orner Erol
Is entitled "You are
right to cry, pretty
bird!" It won an
award in a drawing
competition
organized by the
Turkish Society for
the Protection of
Nature (DHKD) on
the theme of the
threats to
migratory birds.
recorded, a number almost as high as
that for the whole of Europe, and there
are about 80,000 animal species, more
than in Europe. Twice a year the
country is crossed by masses of migra¬
tory birds. The government has
launched a number of programmes to
protect the birds' stopover sites, espe¬
cially in wetlands. One site, the Manyas
Reserve, has been designated a Euro¬
pean diploma site by the Council of
Europe: three million birds belonging to
250 different species land there each
year. An association comprising gover¬
nors, mayors and local village dignitaries
is currently being set up to ensure the
Reserve is protected. Leaders of local
industry will be invited to join in order to
involve them in environmental protection
and the struggle against pollution.
Another important ornithological
site, the Menderes Delta, is seriously
threatened- by drainage, pesticides,
insecticides and poaching. The pres¬
sures from tourism are also consider¬
able. Plans are afoot to build roads and
vacation villages throughout the area. In
1992 a multidisciplinary study carried
out jointly by Turkey's Society for the
Protection of Nature (DHKD) and the
World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF)
made some preliminary suggestions
about conservation measures that need
to be taken, such as extending the
boundaries of the Dilek national park to
the Delta and to Lake Bafa, limiting
"wildcat" aquaculture and improving
the river basin. An information centre
open all the year round distributes doc¬
umentation to schoolchildren, organizes
seminars for teachers and advises
tourists about bird watching.
Turtles are less lucky than birds,
for they share with people a penchant
for beaches of fine sand that slope gently
to the sea. Turkey has seventeen main
nesting sites for two threatened species
of marine turtles, the loggerhead
(Caretta caretta) and the green (Che-
Ionia mydas), about 10,000 of which
are killed (accidentally or intentionally)
in the Mediterranean each year. Many of
these beaches have extensive dunes;
some are coastal wetlands that are also
important for fisheries and birdlife.
Patara, Belek and Akyatan are sites
where the dunes are still intact; the
dunes at Anamur were destroyed long
ago by illegal sand mining. Most of the
sites are affected by this practice and by
domestic and industrial pollution.
In 1988 WWF and a number of
Turkish universities began an ambitious
survey, co-ordinated by the DHKD, of
2,456 km of coastline. The survey orig¬
inated when a German-Turkish project
to build a huge tourist complex on
Dalyan beach, which has been a turtle
nesting site for millions of years, brought
protests from environmentalists in
Turkey and from a number of interna¬
tional institutions, including the World
Bank. The project was eventually can¬
celled and the area named a "specially
protected area" (SPA). Subsequently a
pressure group was formed (including
the Ministry of Tourism, several big
investors in the tourist industry and the
DHKD) to draw up a plan for managing
the Mediterranean beaches used by the
turtles. A project to build a road along
one of the main turtle nesting sites was
scuttled thanks to a court decision and
a vigorous press campaign.
The hue and cry in the media alerted
the public and also aroused the interest
of scientists, who began to study the
behaviour of the turdes, their choice of
nesting places , the number of their young
and the size of their population. On
Dalyan beach a thirty-five-metre-wide
zone was marked off by sign-posts in
order to protect the nesting area from
bathers. From May to October guards
are posted to keep out nocturnal
intruders whose lights would disturb the
turtles. Other places too, like Fethiye,
Patara and the Göksu delta, have been
named as SPAs although they have not
yet been given any specific protection.
MONK SEALS AND FLOWER
BULBS
Turtles are not Turkey's only endan¬
gered species. There are only about 400
monk seals (Monachus monachus) left in
the world, and half of them are found in
the Mediterranean region of Turkey and
Greece. The other half live in the
Atlantic. Turkey is a contracting party
to the Bern Convention on European
Wild Life and Their Habitats and to the
An anemone (right) and a snow¬
drop (left), two bulb plants
threatened by uncontrolled picking
for the export market.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Barcelona Convention for the Protec¬
tion of the Mediterranean Sea Against
Pollution, and its Ministry of the Envi¬
ronment decided to act when the United
Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP) noted that the number of monk
seals was at a critically low level. In
1991 Turkey's National Committee for
the Protection of the Monk Seal chose
the villages of Foça, on the Aegean Sea,
and Yalikavak as pilot areas for the con¬
servation of the species. Field surveys
were carried out, educational materials
were given to teachers, and brochures
were distributed to tourists to encourage
them to help to protect the seals' habi¬
tats. Artificial rocks were even placed in
the sea to prevent fishing boats from
coming too close.
Back on dry land, plants grown
from bulbs are at risk. Turkey is the
world's leading exporter of wildflower
bulbs (some 71 million annually in the
late 1980s). Uncontrolled bulb-gath¬
ering, paid for by big international com¬
panies, was endangering the survival of
certain species such as the snowdrop,
the anemone, the winter aconite, even
the Crocus olivieri istanbulinsis. The
DHKD, the Flora and Fauna Preser¬
vation Society (FFPS) and WWF
responded by encouraging villagers to
produce and market artificially propa¬
gated plants.
Turkey is also saddled with other
serious pollution problems, mostly due
to thermal power plants, the iron and
steel industries, petrochemicals and
automobile factories. Polluted seas,
rivers and soil are also causing concern.
In an attempt to find a solution, the
Ministry of the Environment is moni¬
toring the import and use of coal, lignite
N ITI ATI VES
8m95Miy«iy*k .Jfc I luw bm tot tor
bu*l»y«ti.l&«j? M 9S 000 000 )*ia And»«?
£ &
"I've been here for 95 million years. How
about you?" asks this sea turtle (Caretta
caretta) depicted on a poster produced by
the Turkish Society for the Protection of
Nature and the World Wide Fund for Nature.
The turtles are threatened by tourist
pressures at their nesting sites.
and other fossil fuels, and chemical
products. The collection, transporta¬
tion and recycling of domestic waste
have been improved. Lessons on the
environment are given in all primary
schools. Since 1993 any new tourist or
industrial project is legally obliged to
include an assessment of its environ¬
mental impact. I
BIRDLIFE INTERNATIONAL,
A WATCHDOG
FOR BIRDS
BirdLife International is a global partnership of
conservation organizations working for the diver¬
sity of all life through the conservation of birds and
their habitats. It was launched in 1993, although it built
directly on the structure and achievements of the Inter¬
national Council for Bird Preservation (ICBP), which was
founded in the United Kingdom in 1922. Its headquarters
are in Cambridge (UK), and it has regional offices in
Washington D.C. (U.S.A.), Quito (Ecuador) and Brussels
(Belgium) and a programme office in Bogor (Indonesia).
Among BirdLife's 52 partner organizations, whose com¬
bined membership is estimated at 1.5 million, are the
Bulgarian Society for the Protection of Birds (BSPB), the
Ghana Wildlife Society (GWS) and the Argentinian
Ornithological Association of Rio del Plata.
BirdLife's wide range of activities include helping its
partners establish priorities, implementing protection
measures in the field, taking part in major international
conferences and publishing books. It has identified world¬
wide 221 Endemic Bird Areas (EBAs), places where clus¬
ters of birds with restricted ranges are found, in the
world and will soon be publishing a directory of them.
Publications currently available include Important Bird
Areas in Europe (2,444 sites), Important BirdAreas in the
Middle East, Red Data Books giving details of threatened
birds including Threatened Birds of the Americas, and
Birds in Europe: their conservation status.
BirdLife's partners are involved in campaigns such as
those to protect the Menderes Delta in Turkey, the
Spanish steppes, the Da Lat Plateau in Viet Nam, Palas
Valley in northwestern Pakistan, coastal wetlands in
Ghana and Mount Kupé in Cameroon. In Indonesia,
where there are 381 unique bird species and 24 EBAs
(more than any other country), BirdLife is working with
the Indonesian Directorate for Forest Protection and
Nature Conservation to establish two large protected
areas (each of 100 km2) on the island of Halmahera,
which is still largely covered by virgin forest. BirdLife
works to ensure that the Washington Convention on
International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES) is
respected. Despite all efforts, however, many birds are
still being illegally removed from their natural habitats
and sold to collectors at exorbitant prices. H
BirdLife International, Wellbrook Court, Girton Road,
Cambridge CB3 ONA, United Kingdom. Tel.: (44-1223) 277-318;
Fax: (44-1223) 277-200. E-mail: birdlife@gn.apc.org
LU
111
cc
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
LU
0 R L
A TURTLE REFUGE IN
SWITZERLAND
Each year between 5,000 and 10,000 tiny Florida
marine turtles raised on turtle farms in Louisiana
(U.S.A.) are sold in Switzerland as pets. They grow
quickly, and when they are too big for the aquar¬
iums where they are kept, many of them are
released near to ponds or streams. Unfortu¬
nately the turtles, which can live for up to 50
years, wreak havoc on the ecosystem by
devouring all kinds of aquatic wildlife and even
birds' eggs. Now biologist Olivier Lasserre has
opened a refuge for abandoned turtles in the
canton of Vaud. He has already taken in 200;
eventually there will be room for up to 1,300
more. Perhaps it would be a good idea to explain
to children who buy the turtles what exactly they
are taking on.
RECYCLABLE CARS
In Europe today one of every four cars ends up in a junkyard, which not only
leads to considerable pollution but is wasteful, since automobiles are
almost entirely recyclable. Two French and German auto makers, Renault
and Mercedes, have signed a technical cooperation agreement in this field,
similar to one already reached between Peugeot (France) and Fiat (Italy). In
France, the problem is particularly urgent because in 2002 tips will be strictly
reserved for "ultimate" waste products, i.e. wastes that cannot in any way
be reutilized. The auto makers have committed themselves to produce cars
that will be 85 per cent recyclable by 2002, and 95 per cent by the year 2015.
GIANT ICEBERG ALERT
The British Antarctic Survey is monitoring a giant iceberg measuring nearly
2,000 km2 (about the size of Luxembourg) that has broken away from the
Larsen ice shelf. The iceberg, detected by satellite and confirmed by aerial
sighting, is about a thousand times larger than those usually found in this
part of the world and could eventually endanger shipping off the coast of
South America. It has been suggested that the formation of the iceberg may
be a consequence of the 2.5°C average rise in temperature that has
occurred in the region in the last half century.
GABON'S NATURAL
RICHES
The Pan-African News Agency (PANA) reports
that Gabon is one of Africa's richest countries in
terms of plant- and wild-life. Not counting sea¬
weed and lichen, there are more than 8,000
plant species, more than 600 species of birds
and 150 species of mammals, 19 of which are
primates, including 35,000 gorillas and 64,000
chimpanzees. With some 80,000 specimens, the
elephant population may be the largest and
probably the most stable in Africa. Forest, which
covers 40 per cent of the country, is still mostly
virgin with a deforestation rate estimated at
0.1 per cent per annum. The sea off the 800 kilo¬
metres of coastline abounds in fish and shellfish.
Ten new fish species, four of which are endemic,
have only recently been discovered.
RETURN OF THE CACTUS
After a two-year "stopover" in a French arboretum,
last February 300 cactus were handed over to the
Mexican ambassador to France so that he could .
return them to their country of origin. The plants,
members of a species that figures symbolically
on the Mexican flag, were discovered in tourists'
baggage by French Customs officials. There has
been a steady increase in infractions of the
Washington Convention on International Trade in
Endangered Species of animals and plants
(CITES). In 1994 alone French Customs seized
nearly 800 living animals (birds, turtles, snakes
and felines), 80 stuffed animals, 119 pieces of
African elephant ivory, 1,657 worked-ivory articles
and 2,417 articles derived from protected
species.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Cultural counterpoint
by Isabelle Leymarie
Mamady-Keita, one of
Guinea's greatest
percussionists, gives
lessons to children in the
village of Balandugu
where he was born.
Differences between
cultures find an echo
in music
ISABELLE LEYMARIE
is a Franco-American musicologist.
Although children in Europe are usu¬
ally initiated Into music by learning
how to read it, children in Africa start by
refining their ear, watching adult musicians,
copying from them and playing with them as
soon as they are able. Drummers often
teach their students rhythm by getting them
to feel it physically, by holding their wrists
to help them keep time, by singing to the
beat or beating out time with sounds or
rhythmic phrases. All of this helps their
pupils to absorb rhythm physically.
In African and Caribbean societies
instruments "speak", like the "talking"
drums that reproduce through their dif¬
ferent timbres the sounds of tonal lan
guages, and make certain rhythms seman-
tically intelligible by modelling them on
spoken language. "This is the way It says,"
jazz musicians may say when they describe
a virtuoso passage played on saxophone or
piano.
The language of rhythm
Rhythm Is the strongest distinguishing factor
between these different types of music.
The West, which highlights correctness of
timbre and the rigorous application of the
rules of harmony and counterpoint, tries
to tame and neutralize rhythm. It Is no acci¬
dent that some European languages, for
example, refer to offbeat rhythm (which Is, 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
48
incidentally, described in French by a word
with a pejorative connotation, contretemps)
as syncopation, as if rhythmic intrusion
can be so intolerable as to lead to a "syn¬
cope" or loss of consciousness. It is inter¬
esting to remember that when European
colonists made contact with Africans, the
instrument they often banned and destroyed
was the drum, the very symbol of rhythm.
Many kinds of black music use harmony
and counterpoint wonderfully, but they also
have the highest respect for syncopation.
This is not a matter, as in Asian or Arabic
music, of precise rhythmic cells, of a pre¬
determined and memorized rhythm
respected by the musician or the dancer, but
one of skill and personal inventiveness
(even within a group of instruments). It is the
spontaneous art of escaping from the beat,
of playing tricks, being unpredictable, every¬
thing associated with the Afro-American
slang word "hip" (smart, lively, unexpected)
as opposed to "corny" (square, conven¬
tional, boring). The downbeat, which is
favoured in Western music and corresponds
to the rhythm of military music, ¡s consid¬
ered "corny". The upbeat, which is used in
black music, produces the sensation of
swing and Is considered hip.
The West is disoriented by this con¬
ception of phrasing and this cult of rhythm,
and is more inclined to admire Indian, Chi¬
nese and Japanese ritual music, whose
rhythmic and ceremonial qualities seem
more directly intelligible to it than African
FURTHER READING
Dr. Guy Bérard, Audition égale comportement
("Hearing Equals Behaviour"), Maisonneuve, Metz,
1982.
Billy Bergman, Hot SaucesLatin and Caribbean
Pop, Quill, New York, 1985.
John Blacking, How Musical Is Man? University of
Washington Press, Seattle and London, 1973.
Dr.' Etienne Jalenques, La thérapie du bonheur
("The Therapy of Happiness"), Michel Laffont,
Paris, 1993.
music. Yet Yoruba liturgies, for example,
are works of awesome beauty and com¬
plexity. In them the iyá, the largest Instru¬
ment in the bata, the array of Yoruba holy
drums, talks to the gods In dazzling, almost
otherworldly rhythms that seem to emerge
from the void and are beaten out with
amazing precision. Black music also favours
"breaks" that modify the beat whenever It
slips Into a rut.
Abolishing duality
The Irish musicologist John Blacking spent
a lot of time among the Venda people of
South Africa before he really came to under¬
stand their music. He realized that his edu¬
cation had made him consider African art as
"different". At first he stayed in his tent
listening to Bach or Mozart, but in time he
began to change his conception of music.
"They [the Venda]," he wrote, "introduced
me to a new world of musical experience
and to a deeper understanding of my own
music." When he regarded music not as a
set of rules but as a series of human inter¬
actions and a bond between the body and
the mind, the distinction between "clas¬
sical" and "folk" music disappeared. And,
he added, "by discovering precisely how
music is created and appreciated in dif¬
ferent social and cultural contexts, and per¬
haps establishing that muslcality is a uni¬
versal, species-specific characteristic, we
can show that human beings are even more
remarkable than we presently believe them
to beand that the majority of us live far
below our potential."
An open, global, human approach to
musicall musiccombining the ear, the
eye and, above all, the heart, would do
away with this duality that locks us in our
solitude and prevents us from appreciating
cultures different from our own. Other peo¬
ples and cultures are an essential part of
our world, and if we cut ourselves off from
them we shall the poorer for It.
NICOLAE
BREBAN
talks to
Edgar Reichmann
Nicolae Breban (born 1934) is one of
Romania's finest novelists. During the
last years of the communist
dictatorship he lived in Paris, returning
to Bucharest after the December 1989
revolution. Today he is editor of a
leading cultural review, Contemporanu/.
His novels include In absenta stapinilor
("In the Landlords' Absence"; 1966),
Bunavestire ("The Annunciation";
1977) and Don Juan (1981).
What was the situation of fiction in
Eastern Europe over the last half century?
In Romania as in most of the countries
that suffocated for decades under totali¬
tarian regimes, fiction had in the first place
to struggle to survive and hold on to its
public. It lost its readers in the Stalinist
era, when many writers gave in to pressure
from the authorities, but by the 1960s
things began to change as a result of the
clandestine combat they waged against cen¬
sorship, against the bureaucracy and even
against certain fellow-writers who had
become the dictator's yes-men. Battle was
joined firstly by poets, then by critics,
essayists and novelists. Romanian litera¬
ture, like that of many other countries, is
now out of the rut and is gradually winning
back its readers.
Some people nevertheless consider
that culture in general and literature in
particular are still in crisis.
Romania as a whole is in crisis, an eco¬
nomic and social crisis, an institutional
crisis, a crisis of confidence and of course
a crisis in culture, in literature and in the
novel, but a crisis is not necessarily a bad
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
T E R V I E W
thing: it can be seen as a sign of vitality and
renewal, the first step towards profound
changes that need to be made. The trans¬
formations my country is going through at
present, spectacular though they are, are
vastly preferable to the socially lifeless,
brain-dead state in which it existed for
decades.
What could poets and novelists do in
those days?
Creative artists had to obey the peremp¬
tory directives issued by the authorities,
who made use of the publishing houses all
strictly state-controlled to oblige them
to conform to the fatuous criteria of so-
called "socialist realism". Bookshops were
flooded with Soviet-inspired works in
praise of the "positive hero", the "new
man", a mythical creature that existed
only in the minds of the communist leaders.
Many creative artists, and not minor ones
either, totally renounced their intellectual
freedom and independent judgment,
placing themselves at the disposal of the
authorities and glorifying "the collec¬
tivization of agriculture", "the class
struggle" and "the heroic traditions" of a
communist party that scarcely existed
before Romania was overrun by the Soviet
army.
There were a few great Romanian
authors, notably the philosopher and
poet Lucian Blaga, the novelist Hortensia
Papadat-Bengescu, and the poets
Gheorghiu Bacovia, Ion Barbu and Vasile
Voiculescu, who chose to remain silent,
the only form of resistance that was pos¬
sible under the Stalinist terror. They are
now dead, but each of them left behind a
body of work.
Some younger writers, who were drawn
into politics at the end of the 1940s, were
misled by the regime's slogans into believing
that Romania's brutal incorporation into
the Soviet bloc was the country's liberation
and marked the dawn of a better world, a
world of greater justice. Eventually they
realized their mistake and came into con¬
flict with the authorities.
Did Romanian writers' resistance take
specific forms?
Whereas in other countries a joint
struggle was organized on the basis ofpolit¬
ical demands, in Romania resistance took
individual forms. Each author had to
defend his or her own writings against the
censorship exercised simultaneously by
the party, the publisher and the fearsome
political police who in the 1950s used a
whole battery of measures such as the ban¬
ning of books, the blacklisting of authors
and the imprisonment of recalcitrant
writers.
In the 1960s, when the regime was
trying to make itself more popular as well
as to establish its legitimacy, it finally aban¬
doned these brutal practices in favour of
other forms of pressure. Authors were
forced to join the Writers' Union, which
was the only institution empowered to
remunerate authors and grant them var¬
ious perquisites, depending on how sub¬
servient they were. Some of them were
thus able to travel, with authorization from
the political police, to western Europe.
There was a positive side to these trips
abroad insofar as they helped to raise
writers' awareness and bring them face to
face with new situations.
In the mid-1960s, taking advantage of
a short-lived thaw, writers began to
demand independence of the regime and to
protest against its interference in their
work. The Writers' Union gradually
emerged from state supervision to become
a professional body of sorts , trying to pro¬
tect authors' rights and the integrity of
their works.
This slight change for the better did
not last, but novelists and poets made the
most of it to free themselves from the rules
imposed on them and win a certain degree
of freedom in matters of aesthetics and
form; but the ban on any political demands
or any challenge to the system remained in
place. Novelists were required to practise
self-censorship. This apparent renuncia¬
tion of any social mission and the ongoing
game of hide-and-seek with the apparatus
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW WITH NICOLAE BREBAN
of repression did much to stimulate writers'
ingenuity and imagination by fostering a
distancing process that was propitious to
novel-writing.
These innovative aesthetic endeavours
constitute albeit against a background
of tragic events what may be a unique
phenomenon in modern literary history.
Provided the dictatorship was not
attacked, it allowed writers a certain
amount of elbow room and lifted the
"socialist realism" edict. Any writer
infringing this compromise arrangement
was punished with a publishing ban or
with exile. While novelists as a result
became less pugnacious, their writings
gained in depth. This was the age of
metaphor and allegory, a real head-ache to
the publishers, censors and bureaucrats in
the ideological employ of the tyrant.
How was this new strategy for writing
novels reflected in your works?
How does someone become a tyrant?
This was perhaps the underlying meaning
of "The Annunciation", a 700-page novel
I published in 1977, when the short-lived
Romanian thaw was only a faded memory.
Although denounced at the time as "anti-
socialist" and "obscene" by the country's
top-level authorities, it won the fiction
prize awarded by the Writers' Union. A
kind of political Annunciation whence
the title emerged from the cruel depiction
of a lethargic provincial community, as if a
second novel, hidden from view, was tun¬
nelling its way through the first before bub¬
bling up to the surface. The novel's hero,
Grobei, a truly archetypal personification
of mediocrity, undergoes a strange meta¬
morphosis, to become a charismatic figure
who is prepared to exploit the masses in the
name of a ramshackle ideology. The duality
of the novel's structure reflects the dual
nature, the ambiguity, of this character.
For the purposes of this Romanian-
style "childhood of a leader", which had
the ambitious aim of exposing the origins of
a political myth, I deployed a wide range of
narrative techniques, not attempting to
hide my taste for the baroque and the
tongue-in-cheek use of clichés. Did my
compatriots have a special gift for toler¬
ating the abuses of absolute power? This
may be the question hidden in this story,
which combines the features of an alle¬
gory, a novel of manners and a satire on a
desensitized society, ready to accept any
sleazy compromise. The book's hidden
meaning did not escape the attention of
the regime, which explains the virulence of
the criticism to which it was subjected. Its
publication was held up for a long time by
the censor, and soon after it came out I
left Romania and went to live in Paris,
where I stayed until the collapse of the dic¬
tatorship in December 1989.
To what tradition of novel-writing do
you claim to belong, now that authors in
your country have regained a freedom of
expression unimaginable only a few years
ago?
I would be hard put to say to which lit¬
erary line of descent I belong. I no longer
believe in reductionist labels like "mod¬
ernism", "realism", "post-modernism",
"oneirism", "surrealism" and so on. I only
believe in the durability and vitality of the
novel, a major, universal genre and an
essential factor in communication, what¬
ever techniques novelists may wish to use.
I am naturally somewhat taken aback to see
Western literature awash with slim intimist
volumes, trivial confessions, novels and
opuscules that are not without charm, that
are sometimes intelligent and exquisitely
crafted but have little to contribute to the
debate on issues of the day that readers,
adrift in this rapidly changing world, so
urgendy need. I still feel nostalgic for novels
that raise problems and cause readers to
change their ways of thinking, as epito¬
mized, to my mind, by the works of
Thomas Mann, The Magic Mountain in
particular, and the whole of Dostoevsky's
work.
The theorists of the "nouveau roman",
as widely practised in France thirty years
or so ago, declared character and plot to be
dead; the cold eye of the novelist was all
that mattered. I, on the contrary, believe
that narrative and character, without
which there are no novels deserving of the
name, are alive and well. I would even go
so far as to assert that not only is the novel
the basis of universal culture but that the
character remains the novel's mainstay
the story, the plot, as well, of course, but
above all the character, with his or her
internal divisions. In "The Annunciation",
as in my other novels, I often tried to bring
about this kind of break with my heroes'
type-casting. The unity of the hero of a
novel, like that of real-life characters, is
always made up of contradictions. Nothing
is ever entirely black or white. No one has
understood as well as Dostevsky the mul¬
ticoloured nature of the human soul, at
times detestable and at other times sub¬
lime. I
EDGAR REICHMANN is a writer and literary critic.
Correction: On page 24 of our April 1995 issue ("The origins of writing"), the first sentence of the third paragraph of Shiro Noda's article "A four-in-hand script" should have
stated "It is generally agreed that Japanese writing dates back to the fifth century A.D.", and not "the fifth century B.C.", as printed. We apologize to readers for this error.
50
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover, page 3: M. Freeman © ANA, Paris. Page 2: © Sigismond de Vajay, Vevcy, Switzerland. Page 4: UNESCO-Dominique Roger. Page 5: Thierry Orban © Sygma,
Paris. Page 6: Leroy © Biocosmos/S.P.L./Cosmos, Paris. Page 7: © NIBSC/S.P.L./Cosmos, Paris. Pages 8-9: All Rights Reserved Page 9: C. Vioujard © Gamma,
Paris. Page 10: Lynn Johnson © Rapho, Paris. Page 1 1 (above): Roger Ressmcyer © Starlight/Cosmos, Paris. Page 1 1 (below): WHO, Geneva. Page 12: Alain Keler ©
Cosmos, Paris. Page 13: Peter Charlesworth © Rapho, Paris. Page 14: Martine Voyeux © Métis, Paris. Page 15: Jenny Matthews © Format, London. Pages 16, 37
(below right): Emmanuelle Barbaras © Rapho, Paris. Page 17: Gideon Mendel © Network/Rapho, Paris. Pages 18, 19: Tim Nunn © Panos Pictures, London. Page
20: Swapan Parekh © Black Star/Rapho, Paris. Page 21: Heldur Netocny © Panos Pictures, London. Page 22: Alexis Cordesse © Editing, Paris. Pages 23, 24, 25, 29,
30, 31: © Crips/UNESCO. Pages 26-27: Hans Jürgen Burkard/Bilderbcrg © Studio X, Paris. Page 28: John Cole © Cosmos, Paris. Page 32: Hank. Morgan ©
S.P.L./Cosmos, Paris. Page 33: Jacky Chapman © Format, London. Page 34: K. Kerbs © Dot/Cosmos, Paris. Pages 36, 37 (except photo below right): © Deutsche
AIDS Hilfe, Berlin. Page 40: Christian Sappa © Rapho, Paris. Pages 41, 42: © Rémi Tournus, Paris. Page 43: © France Bequecte, Paris. Pages 44 (above), 45 (below):
© The Society for the Protection of Nature, Istanbul. Page 44 (below): Claude Nardin © Jacana, Paris. Page 45 en bas: Jean-Pierre Champroux © Jacana, Paris. Page
46 (above left): Alain Rainon © Jacana, Paris. Page 46 (above right): J.P. Ferrcro © Explorer, Paris. Page 46 (below right): P. Pickford ©Jacana, Paris. Page 46 (below
left): Guy Thouvenin © Explorer, Paris. Page 47: L. Chevalier © Explorer, Paris. Page 49: © Editions Flammarion, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
A Unesco programme
Education for the Prevention of Aids
PILOT PROJECTS
UNESCO/WHO pilot projects in school-
based Aids education, adapted to the
socio-cultural context, have been under¬
taken and evaluated in different regions
of the world.
RESOURCE CENTRES
An Aids School Education Resource
Centre (ASERC) for the collection, ex¬
change and distribution of educational
materials for school-age children has
been set up at UNESCO Headquarters.
This Centre has over 2,500 publications
and close to 150 video films from all
over the world. A regional centre has
also been set up for Asia and the Pacific
(AIDSED Centre) at UNESCO's regional
office in Bangkok.
PUBLICATIONS
Bibliographies and selective extracts of
didactic materials are regularly pub¬
lished. Pedagogical guides and proto
types of educational material have also
been devised.
TRAINING SEMINARS
FOR DECISION-MAKERS
UNESCO organizes regional planning
seminars to strengthen awareness
among high-level officials from ministries
of education on the need for HIV/Aids ed¬
ucation and to inform them about effec¬
tive preventive education strategies. This
approach aims primarily at urging deci¬
sion-makers to promote school-based ed¬
ucation for the prevention of Aids.
UNESCO documents may be obtained
free of charge by contacting:
Education for the prevention of Aids
Unesco
7 Place de Fontenoy
75732 Paris 7 SP, France
Tel.: (33-1) 45 68 09 29
Fax: (33-1) 47 83 27 10
A resource package for educational
programmes on Aids
School health education to prevent Aids and STD: a re¬
source package for curriculum planners is a three-vol¬
ume guide to help education planners set a
curriculum and develop materi¬
als on Aids and sexually transmit¬
ted diseases (STDs) for pupils
aged 12-16 and their teachers. It
incorporates all the elements of
sex and Aids education pro¬
grammes that were found to be ef¬
fective in pilot projects conducted
by WHO and UNESCO in developing
countries in 1989-93.
School Health Education
to Prevent AIDS and STD
A RESOURCE PACXAGE FOR CURRICULUM PLANNERS
£*£S»»S
cuaocuu*' 4ssïftas. SS?
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
THEME OF OUR JULY-AUGUST 1994 DOUBLE ISSUE:
THE CINEMA CENTENARY
with contributions from:
JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE, MILOS FORMAN, GASTON KABORÉ,
MILCO MANCEVSKI, MARCELLO MASTROIANNI, NAGISA OSHIMA,
JEAN-PAUL RAPPENEAU, VOLKER SCHLÖNDORFF, KRZYSZTOF ZANUSSI.
and a previously unpublished study by
the great art historian ÉLIE FAURE:
THE CINEMA, LANGUAGE OF UNIVERSAL MAN
HERITAGE:
ZACATECAS, A BAROQUE CITY IN MEXICO
ENVIRONMENT:
DRY LANDS AND DESERTS
INTERVIEW WITH
THE ABBÉ PIERRE
ms way
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries
*
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms...without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
]]>
</page>
</document>
