<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="100576eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Ht!
A CENT
CINEMA
Mm
M 1205 9508 44,00 F
Aft«
ttësBm
Jean-Claude Carrière
Milos Forman
Tomás Gutiérrez Alea
Gaston Kaboré
Mani Kaul
Abbas Kiarostami
Milco Mancevski
Marcello Mastroianni
Nagisa Oshima
Jean-Paul Rappeneau
Volker Schlöndorff
Krzysztof Zanussi
and an essay
by Elie Faure
u&JMk
if a
*í
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered
for publication in this feature.
Your photo should show a
painting, a sculpture, piece of
architecture or any other
subject which seems to be an
example of cross-fertilization
between cultures.
Alternatively, you could send
us pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds
in which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to
all photographs.
Dreams
1991, ink and paper
(50 x 70 cm)
by Claudine Dufour
After spending many
years studying writing
systems from all over the
world, French artist
Claudine Dufour began
experimenting with signs
and symbols. "I follow
the watershed between
painting and writing, "
she says, "and,
stimulated and enriched
by my discoveries, I
mingle my signs with
those of other cultures. "
She adds, "I create
imaginary writing, a kind
of parody, happy to feel
like a musician, a
choreographer and a
calligrapher all in one. "
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
A CENTURY OF CINEMA
CONTENTS JULY-AUGUST1995
Appeal by the Director-General
of Unesco
Saving the cinematic heritage
by Federico Mayor
Interviews with...
18 fïiilos Forman
26 Jean-Paul Happeneao
34 Suresh Jinda!
36 (Viani Haul
38 Abbas Kiarostami
53 Tomás Gutiérrez Alea
60 Ptagisa Osiilma
65 Marcello Mastroianni
74 Pilleo üancevsici
77 Volker Schlöndorff
86 ANNIVERSARY
Abal Kunanbayev (1845-1904)
Interview with Chingiz Aitmatov
SO Letters to the Editor
Cover: (from top): Yaaba (Burkina Faso, 1989) by Idrissa
Ouedraogo; Persona (Sweden, 1965) by Ingmar Bergman; Raise the
Red Lantern (China, 1991) by Zhang Yimou; The Journey (Argentina,
1992) by Fernando Solanas; On the Waterfront (United States,
1954) by Ella Kazan; Onimaru (Japan, 1987) by Yoshishge Yoshida.
5 An art and an Industry
by Peter Schepelern
9 A birthday or a funeral?
by Krzysztof Zanussi
Xt^ Hollywood
by Tino Balio
Î6 Perchance to dream...
by Lionel Steketee
21 Methuselah or Peter Pan?
by Jean-Claude Carrière
2Q Windows of opportunity
by Jerry Palmer
^9 The first Indian studios
by Romain Maitra
41 A sllver*screen symphony
by Elie Faure
49 Egypt through the looking-glass
by Magda Wassef
56 Mexican melodrama: the remake
by José Carlos Avellar
68 Cineclttè
by Francesco Bono
70 The African cinema In crisis
by Gaston Kaboré
30 The Babelsberg Studios
32 Yesterday's Images for tomorrow's eyes
by Thereza Wagner
Special adviser: Jean-Claude Carrière
Consultants: Nahal Tadjadod and Niels Boel
Interviews with Miloä Forman, Jean-Paul Rappeneau, Suresh Jindal, Mani
Kaul, Abbas Kiarostami, Nagisa Oshima, Marcello Mastroianni and Volker
Schlöndorff by Nahal Tadjadod and Jean-Claude Carrière. Interview with
Tomás Gutiérrez Alea by Niels Boel. Interview with Milco Manfevski
by Jasmina Sopova
ThS UNESCO
¡COURIER
48th year
Published monthly in 30
languages and in Braille
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, It is In the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, If it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their
peoples and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives.
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO, LONDON. 16 NOVEMBER 1945
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THÉ UNESCO
(OURIER
48th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco. The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15. France.
Fax: (33-1) 45.66.92.70
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Aiain Lévêque, Neda El Khazen
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel. 45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
-Administrative Assistant: Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45.68.47.14)
Artwork Consultants: Eric Frogé, Laurence Reyne
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: VI. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Moacyr A. Fioravante (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Javaid Iqbal Syed (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kang Woo-hyon (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov ¡Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Katri Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Sudhasinee Vajrabul (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar ¡Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax: 45.68.45.89
Subscriptions: Marie-Tnérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65).
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. 45.68.49.19)
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 Frerch francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 yeór: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 Frerch francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted trom the Unesco Courier', plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed
articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on repuest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not neces¬
sarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Coun'erstaff. The boundaries on maps published In tne magazine do not
imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced In microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris: (2) Univer¬
sity Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100 U.S.A.: (3) N.CR.
Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc.. Ill West 40th Street. New York,
U.S.A.: (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio
44691, U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - JUILLET-AOÛT 1995
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de I'Unesco.
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.I. Route d'Étampes. 45331 Malsherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 7-1995-OPI-95 539 A
This issue comprises 92 pages and a 4-page insert between
pages 2 3 and 9091.
onth by month
For the Unesco Courier, whose editorial goal it is to explore all
activities and forms of expression with a universal dimension,
the centenary of motion pictures is a golden opportunity.
Cinema is, after all, an art that draws sustenance from all
others, a protean medium of communication with inexhaustible
resources, capable of accommodating the impulses of cre¬
ators of very different kinds, of reaching popular audiences
and of effortlessly crossing geographical and cultural frontiers.
For us this anniversary is an occasion to celebrate with an
international tribute to the extraordinary galaxy of talented
men and women who have shaped the first hundred years of
cinema and have made possible the miracle of filma unique,
worldwide artistic adventure involving a vast number of per¬
sonal aesthetic experiences and reflecting the culture of
almost every country in the world.
At the same time it would have been impossible to ignore
the tensions, the unresolved problems, the obstacles and
threats that are also part of the story. Is the cinema an art or
an industry? Can it be both at once? And if so, on what condi¬
tions? Where ruthless market forces prevail, is the American
film industry bound to come out on top? Are its weapons purely
economic? What chances does the cinema stand against
today's television and tomorrow's multimedia?
These questions often arise in the following pages, but they
do not overshadow the immense pleasure that the cinema has
brought to all those of us who have lived in the twentieth cen¬
tury. All the gifted artists who have been kind enough to con¬
tribute to this issue bear witness to this, as do the photos we
have selected from film libraries all over the world, a veritable
family album from the world of cinema.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
An art and an
industry
iiCT^Macra.H'.MM'JH
Torn from the start
between money-
spinning and
creativity, the
cinema took a long
time to win
acceptance as an art
in its own right
All through its first century,
cinema has enjoyed an
immense following, but it
, has also been feared and
scorned. Both the educated
bourgeoisie and the working-class public
were excited by the Lumière brothers' Ciné¬
matographe shows in Paris and Edison's
Kinetograph shows in New York at the end
of the last century. Soon, however, the cul¬
tural establishment became concerned about
Above, "Black Maria",
Thomas Edison's motion
picture studio in West
Orange, New Jersey
(United States).
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Toshiro Mifune (as
Tajomaru, the bandit)
and Machiko Ryo
(Masago) in Akira
Kurosawa's Rashomon
(Japan, 1950).
the enormous popularity of the new medium
and began to dismiss it as a vulgar and even
harmful symptom of modernity.
"Cinema materializes the worst popular
ideal," wrote the French writer Anatole
France (1844-1924). "It is not the end of the
world, but it is the end of civilization." His
opinion was echoed by his fellow Nobel
Prize-winner, the German novelist Thomas
Mann (1875-1955), who said: "It seems to
me that film has very little to do with art".
The French novelist Georges Duhamel
(1884-1966) and many other critics saw film
as a symptom of "Americanization", a vul¬
garization of the European spirit.
As recently as 1961, the American histo¬
rian Daniel J. Boorstin wrote that "Even at
its best, the movie remains a simplifying
medium," and in the present decade, the
outstanding film director Krzysztof Kies-
lowski has said, "The goal is to capture what
lies within. But there's no way of filming it.
Literature can do this, cinema can't. It can't
because it doesn't have the means. It's not
intelligent enough."
How far are these criticisms of cinema
justified?
Stories from the dream factory
At the Lumière brothers' first public
show in Paris on 28 December 1895, a short
film was shown about a boy who teases a
gardener. The naughty boy makes the gar¬
dener spray himself with water and eventu¬
ally gets his deserved retribution. This early
short, L'arroseur arrosé, marks what was to
become the main attraction of film, its
capacity to tell stories in a powerful and
popular way.
The medium started out mainly as a form
of expression based on imitation of theatre
and painting, but gradually it developed a
language and aesthetics of its own. A peak of
cinematic story-telling was reached in 1915,
with the great American director D.W. Grif¬
fith's The Birth of a Nation, a monumental
demonstration of the technical and stylistic
possibilities of the new art form (although,
with its racist depiction of the American
Civil War, it also showed the medium's con¬
troversial potential).
In the 1920s, film developed in relative
isolation from the other arts. While Marcel
Proust and TS. Eliot revolutionized litera-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
ture, Picasso, Kandinsky and Duchamp
showed new ways for painting, and
Stravinsky, Schoenberg and Bartok broke up
the tonal system of classical music, the
cinema was mainly trying to establish tech¬
niques of logical storytelling rooted in
Dickens' novels and nineteenth-century
popular fiction and melodrama.
Avant-garde cinema did exist in the 1920s
nonetheless. French experiments in Surre¬
alism and Dadaism, German Expressionism
and the Russian montage style were
attempts to explore new approaches to
cinema as an art. Films like Luis Buñuel's Un-
Chien Andalón, Robert Wienc's The Cab¬
inet of Dr. Caligari and Sergei Eisenstein's
The Battleship Potemkin are considered as
landmarks of cinema and are widely admired
for their originality. But they had little
influence on the mainstream of films.
Meanwhile Hollywood was building an
enormous entertainment industry and, despite
important European counter-currents such as
French Poetic Realism in the 1930s and
Italian neorealism in the 1940s, soon gained
worldwide dominance. The period from the
1930s to the 1950s was the era of classical
Hollywood storytelling, with the "star
system", the "genre system" and the "studio
system" as the main pillars of the dream
factory.
Challenging the system The cinema,
more than any other artistic medium,
depends on acceptance by and money from
the economic system, since the production
costs of a film are so much higher than those
of a book, a painting or a piece of music. As
a result, the "system" has always had more
influence over the cinema than over the other
arts. The history of the cinema records a con¬
tinuous tension between the inertia of the
system, geared to seeking easy money, and
film-makers seeking to fulfil their artistic
ambitions. There is film as art, created by
individualist geniuses who quixotically chal¬
lenged the system, and there is film at the
service of prevailing ideas and values.
The popularity and fascination of film
have been used for art and entertainment,
but abused for manipulation and falsifica¬
tion. Lenin called film "the most important
Peter Schepelern, of
Denmark, is a professor
in the Film and Media
Studies Department at
the University of
Copenhagen. He has
written several books
on film theory and film
history and contributed
film criticism to various
periodicals.
A still from the famous
Odessa Steps sequence
in Sergei Eisenstein's
The Battleship Potemkin
(U.S.S.R., 1925).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
7 J tâBI
Alain Resnais's ¿así Year at Marienbad
(France, 1961) with Delphine Seyrig.
WE m m a 1
iafl bT^V
"2fc> 3
Il l 1* ^ä
V
r V ffl »7^1
-* **\ijr
B^^^fc . H t^H ^ta
Michael Curtiz's Casablanca (United States,
1942). From left to right, Humphrey Bogart,
Claude Rains, Paul Henreid and Ingrid
Bergman.
of the arts" (1922), and during the 1930s film
became a political instrument of propaganda
in the hands of the totalitarian regimes
Stalinist Russia, Nazi Germany, Fascist Italy
and Spain. Leni Riefenstahl's Triumph of the
Will alone, in spite of its repugnant deifica¬
tion of Hitler, stands out as an original
work of art. Hollywood answered back with
films glorifying the democratic countries,
their values, their courage and resistance.
New waves and complexities The
first decisive breakthrough made by
cinema into the established culture came after
the Second World War, when a new generation
of film-makers gave form and feeling to the
post-war experience, perhaps more effectively
than their colleagues in the older arts. Vittorio
De Sica's The Bicycle Thief, Federico Fellinis
La Strada, Akira Kurosawa's Rashomon,
Ingmar Bergman's Wild Strawberries, Andrezj
Wajda's Ashes and Diamonds and Satyajit
Ray's Apu trilogy dealt movingly with the
search for humanism in an era of doubt and
shaken beliefs. This was cinema of great drama
and high artistic quality, but it was still largely
conventional and based on the premises of a
literary culture
In the 1960s film art broke new ground,
but remained within the popular mainstream.
The French New Wave films by the humanist
François Truffaut, the misanthropic Claude
Chabrol and the radical Jean-Luc Godard,
and films such as Michelangelo Antonioni's
L'Avventura, Federico Fellini's 8 1/2, Alain
Resnais' Last Year in Marienbad and Ingmar
Bergman's Persona were works that marked a
new modernism. Unlike earlier avant-garde
works, however, they were seen by a wide
general public. Film had finally gained accep¬
tance as an artistic medium.
Great films, contrary to other art forms,
often transcend the conventional distinction
between low and high culture. Virtuoso
Hollywood pieces such as Ernst Lubitsch's
erotic comedies, John Ford's westerns, Max
Ophuls' melodramas and Alfred Hitchcock's
thrillers contain no literary profundities,
but seen as visual art, as examples of pictorial
story-telling, they established a new concept
of film culture. Reluctantly the bastions of
high culture have come to realize that film as
a medium has its own value.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A birthday
or a funeral?
rzvsztof Zanuss
Is the cinema still asking
the eternal questions
that sustain creative art?
Krzysztof Zanussi
is a Polish director and
scriptwriter. Among his
best-known films are
The Structure of Crystals
(1969), Illumination
( 1 973) and Dotkniecie
(The Touch, 1992) with
Max von Sydow and
Sarah Miles.
Unlike cinema, none of the tra¬
ditional arts presided over by
the nine muses of Antiquity
owes its birth to an instru¬
ment or an invention. This
explains why a doubt has hovered over
cinema ever since its birth: is it really an art ?
The doubt stems not only from cinema's
suspect relationship with a piece of
machinery, but from its social and artistic
origins.
Right from the start, the cinema recorded
objective facts (as in the first films made by
the Lumière brothers, "Workers Leaving the
Lumière Factory" and "The Arrival of a
Train at La Ciotat Station") but it also told a
story (as in the "The Gardener and the
Cheeky Imp "[L'arroseur arrosé]). From the
aesthetic point of view, the second aspect of
cinema was already more advanced, or, as is
usually said, more creative.
Fiction, whose origins are rooted in liter¬
ature and whose visual expression is in the¬
atre, has played a dominant role in the his¬
tory of the cinema. But since the cinema
remained silent for the first thirty years of
its existence (a rather prolonged babyhood!),
it would be more accurate to compare it to
pantomime, which, like motion pictures,
was often accompanied by music. So in the
light of its genealogical tree, cinema might be
described as literature without words, or as a
form of theatre, but one far removed from
literature, supported by music and provided
with subtitles. With such origins it was dif¬
ficult to find a place on Mount Parnassus.
Humble Origins The cinema's social
origins were even less glorious. It is a
child of the fairground. Popular appeal is its
birthright: it took root among the people at
a time when the other muses were hobnob¬
bing in salons. It cannot even be compared
with other forms of popular art, with folk¬
lore, the memory of bygone days.
The cinema was born at the end of a cen¬
tury that saw an extraordinary artistic flow¬
ering and regarded art as its crowning glory.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
!rLJ
äsv
JT\
*jrr
A**'
La Sortie des ouvriers de
l'usine Lumière ("Workers
Leaving the Lumière Factory";
France, 1895), one of Louis
Lumière 's first films.
Artists have never been so highly regarded as
they were in the nineteenth century. Never
has such pride been felt in art which, in the
eyes of the European elites of that time, was
a testimony to human progress and evolu¬
tion in its highest form. But those elites
believed that the opera was the synthesis of
all contemporary art forms. Great opera-
houses were the temples of the late nine¬
teenth century. The cinema could only
appear to them as an insignificant novelty.
Running out of steam in point of
fact, the birth of cinema was a turning
point for the culture of our century. The age
of Gutenberg was drawing to a close. We left
behind the culture of the word for the cul¬
ture of image and sound, and entered a new
cultural era. By now we have put that
turning point behind us. The modern world
is inundated with audiovisual signs. Yet the
cinema, which is responsible for this
upheaval, seems to be in decline.
It is easy, but only half true, to say that
by moving out of movie-houses and onto
television and VCR screens films win
ground for the cinema. While we can see that
the output of the audiovisual sector is
growing, we are less apt to notice the decline
in its artistic potential, its aesthetic regres¬
sion, the spiritual poverty of what it offers,
and the increasing vapidity of the ideas
expressed. One need only compare the
cinema today with that of twenty years ago
when year after year film-makers like Jean-
Luc Godard, Andrei Tarkovski, Federico
Fellini and Ingmar Bergman were opening
up new aesthetic, moral and intellectual per¬
spectives and taking part in an extraordinary
blossoming of art that was comparable to
the explosion of Renaissance Florence or
Flemish oil painting.
The cinema is losing ground today in the
same area as that where other art forms are in
retreat. In the late twentieth century people
no longer expect art to do what it has done
for centuries. They no longer ask it to
describe the world in terms of a clearly
defined scale of values. They no longer expect
answers because they no longer ask the ques¬
tions that were once thought to be intrinsic
to humanity, about the meaning of life, suf¬
fering and death, about the nature of love
and happiness. Can art survive without these
questions? I am convinced it cannot. And
without them, can humanity itself survive?
As useless as Mozart An has always
been a diversion, a gratuitous, disinter¬
ested act. In the nineteenth century people
sometimes said that a beautiful object was
"useless, like Mozart." I have nothing against
art as a diversion because it is through diver¬
sion and through disinterested, unproduc¬
tive acts that thinking about life, happiness
and death is expressed. In the past this kind
of thinking was found in popular culture as
well as among the elite. The difference lay in
the language, not the message. The culture of
ordinary people also asks the basic questions.
A person who watches a mindless television
film or an episode of Dynasty today is no
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
>,
Le retour d'Ulysse ("The
Return of Ulysses";
France, 1908), a film
directed by Charles Le
Bargy and featuring
actors from the
Comédie-Française
theatre.
less educated than the film-goers of thirty
years ago who would queue to see the latest
Fellini or Bergman. So what has happened
since then?
I attribute the decline of the cinema to a
change in the role of culture. The language of
moving pictures still has some strings to its
bow, but the questions that could be dis¬
cussed in this language have gone. Thus the
centenary of the cinema is linked to its funeral.
But perhaps it is too early to bury the
body. Perhaps the heart is still beating. Per¬
haps we are in too much of a hurry to bury a
Europe that has so often experienced decline
only to rise again and become a dynamic force
in the evolution of humanity. Perhaps the
eternal questions will again be asked in the
world of new technologies and there will be a
place where I could make a new Illumination
(1978) or a new Imperative (1982). It does
not really matter whether it is for television, a
video cassette or a virtual-reality headset, just
as it doesn't really matter who does the
asking, myself or a film-maker several genera¬
tions younger than me.
To my mind the only thing that counts
is to know whether we will present these
eternal questions or only an imagination-
numbing "media mish-mash". A cinema attraction at a
fair in Sedan (France) in
1901.
M
Suwm KvrH». Mriw4 Mi- -Ow-
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Hollywood
»:^ro
M
A
How the major studios
"became a dream factory for
America and the world
Tino Balio,
of the United States, is a
professor in the
Department of
Communication Arts at
the University of
Wisconsin-Madison. His
most recent published
work is Grand Design:
Hollywood as a Modern
Business Enterprise,
1930-1939 (Charles
Scribner's Sons, New
York, 1993).
Hollywood did not become the
motion picture capital of the
United States until nearly
twenty years after the inven-
.! tion of the new medium. Pro¬
duction was centred in the greater New York
City area from 1894, when Thomas Edison
introduced his Kinetoscope peepshow, until
1908, when American producers began
migrating to southern California to take
advantage of the temperate climate and the
region's varied scenery to produce films year-
round and supply nickelodeon theatres with
westerns, comedies and other types of
simple story films. The queues at the box-
office were created mostly by immigrant
workers and their families in search of cheap
entertainment.
From these humble beginnings the
movies soon became a national art form.
Two innovations stimulated the transition:
feature films and the star system. The
growth of motion pictures from single
reelers lasting fifteen minutes to features
lasting ninety minutes and longer made it
possible to tell complex and compelling sto¬
ries that competed with the stage for the
patronage of the more affluent middle-class.
The creation of motion picture stars such as
Mary Pickford, Charles Chaplin and Douglas
Fairbanks created film fandom which enthu
siastically endorsed the high salaries paid to
these personalities by buying tickets that
escalated in price.
Hollywood was one of several players in
the world film market until the outbreak of
the First World War, when indigenous film
production in Europe came almost to a
standstill. Rushing to fill the void, Holly¬
wood underwent a period of rapid expan¬
sion, and film-making became a major
industry. Producers sought market security
by acquiring large chains of theatres; large
chains of theatres sought a steady supply of
films by acquiring studios. To finance these
mergers, companies turned to Wall Street.
The advent of the talkies in 1926 created even
closer bonds with banking interests. Only
the strongest film companies had the finan¬
cial resources or connections to make the
conversion to sound, with the result that by
1930 Hollywood emerged as a virtual oli¬
gopoly consisting of eight companies, most
of which continue to dominate the business
to this day.
The most powerful of the eight were the
"Big Five": Loew's (MGM), Paramount,
Warner Bros., Twentieth Century-Fox and
RKO. These five companies were fully-inte¬
grated, meaning they produced nearly all the
important motion pictures each year, oper¬
ated worldwide distribution systems and
owned the largest and best-situated theatres
where their films were guaranteed a showing.
Allied to the "Big Five" were the "Little
Three": Universal, Columbia and United
Artists. Universal and Columbia were pro¬
ducer-distributors that supplied the bigger
companies with low-budget pictures for
double features. United Artists was solely a
distributor for a few quality independent
producers. "Poverty Row" existed on the
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
periphery. Small studios such as Monogram,
Republic and Producers' Releasing Corpora¬
tion served small towns and rural areas. As a
group, they had a marginal impact on the
business.
The Studio System Hollywood
reached the height of its influence during
the 1930s and 1940s. After a brief decline
during the Great Depression movie theatre
attendance in the United States rose steadily
until it reached nearly 80 million a week by
1946, a figure that nearly equalled the entire
population of the country. To keep cinemas
well stocked with films, Hollywood had
perfected an efficient form of mass produc¬
tion called the studio system. Studios were
organized by departments such as screen-
writing, art direction, costumes, cinematog¬
raphy, editing and sound, all headed by a
production chief who oversaw operations.
The major studios turned out two types of
pictures: class A, with name stars, big bud¬
gets and high production values, and class B,
economy films to play the lower half of
double bills. To maintain audience interest,
studios produced an array of genres
including musicals, screwball comedies,
biographies, gangster films, westerns and
melodramas. And to satisfy the concerns of
motion picture censors, the industry
adopted the Motion Picture Production
Code in 1930, a form of self-regulation
whereby producers voluntarily agreed to
make their pictures simply with a generally-
accepted code of behaviour.
After the Second World War, Hollywood
experienced a series of upheavals that drasti¬
cally changed its operations. In 1948 the U.S.
Supreme Court charged the major companies
with having violated antitrust laws and
MGM cameramen film a
speeding train.
MGM films open with a
shot of a roaring lion.
Below, Leo recording his
first roar for the screen
(18 December 1928).
forced them to sell off their profitable
motion picture theatres and to abolish
restrictive trade practices. Soon after, the
same companies were also hard hit by the rise
of television, which caused box-office atten¬
dance to drop by 50 per cent during the
1950s. In Europe, the largest overseas market
for American films, Hollywood encountered
restrictive trade barriers as nations worked to
rebuild their devastated economies and
attempted to revive their flagging film indus¬
tries. Hollywood responded to these condi¬
tions by producing fewer pictures and laying
off redundant workers to reduce studio
overheads by making widescreen block¬
busters in colour to differentiate its product
from television, by producing pictures
abroad to take advantage of government
subsidies, and by collaborating with televi¬
sion to participate in the growth of the new
medium.
These measures revived Hollywood and
prepared it to meet the arrival of new televi¬
sion distribution technologies such as cable
television and home video in the 1970s and
1980s. The rising demand for entertainment
of all kinds created by these technologies
together with the commercialization of
state-controlled broadcasting systems in
Europe, the end of the Cold War and rising
standards of living in emerging economies,
made the film business truly international in
scope. The major Hollywood companies
have become huge entertainment conglomer¬
ates with interests in recorded music, televi¬
sion programming, book publishing and
cable communications in all the principal
world markets. Three studios Twentieth
Century-Fox, Columbia Pictures and MCA
have foreign owners. Hollywood will
remain the motion-picture capital of the
world but will maintain this position only
by strengthening alliances with foreign
interests.
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
/
> r
C «y
W
V
L*j7 I
\ >
The legendary couple Clark Gable
(Rhett Butler) and Vivien Leigh
(Scarlett O'Hara) in Victor Fleming's
Gone with the Wind (United States,
1939).
W
Gary Cooper as the frontier-town
marshal in Fred Zinneman's High
Noon (United States, 1952).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Singin' in the Rain
(United States, 1952), a
classic musical directed
by Stanley Donen and
Gene Kelly.
Perchance
to dream
Lionel Steketee
Economic muscle is not the only
explanation for the power of the
American cinema
Is cinema an art or a commodity? Is it
culture or commerce? The big American
studios made their choice long ago:
cinema is an industry, and every film is a
product. But things are not quite as
simple as that.
How is it that American cinema can make
people all over the world dream, laugh and
cry, and has done so for the last hundred
years?
As early as 1916, when Europe was
embroiled in war, D. W. Griffith's Intoler
ance laid the foundations of a new means of
communication that, in addition to its
artistic qualities, would vehicle not only a
message meant for a universal audience but
also the image of an entire country. Wit¬
tingly or unwittingly, the American film
industry has always been the instrument of a
certain kind of propaganda on behalf of
values specific to the United States. Without
it, people in America and elsewhere would
clearly be less aware of the American myth.
But this desire to propagate a way of life
is not enough to explain the impact of the
American cinema. Its openness has also,
played a role. It has always welcomed non-
American creators with open arms. Charlie
Chaplin, Frank Capra, Alfred Hitchcock,
Billy Wilder and Elia Kazan of the older gen¬
eration, and George Miller (Mad Max,
1979), Peter Weir (The Dead Poets' Society,
1989) and Ridley Scott (Thelma and Louise,
1990) today, all have one thing in common:
the universality of their language. It is pre-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Lionel Steketee,
who was born in
France of American
parents, is a
director, translator
and scriptwriter. He
has directed a
documentary on
contemporary music
in New York.
cisely because they were foreigners that they
had to, and did, use the camera to tell stories
that all kinds of audience, irrespective of
frontiers and languages, could understand.
One of the keys to this language, and
thus to the American cinema, is the explicit
use of emotion. "The most important thing
is to move the audience," said Alfred Hitch¬
cock, who is, nevertheless, one of the sev¬
enth art's "coldest" directors. In classics like
Michael Curtiz's Casablanca (1942) and a
recent production like Robert Zemeckis's
Forrest Gump (1993), American film-makers
make audiences laugh and cry by getting
them to identify with the characters,
whether they are larger than life or just ordi¬
nary people. What counts is getting people
to fantasize and have fun, and putting us
back in touch with the lost simplicity of
childhood. "Adulthood leads to the loss of
dream and adventure, the gradual numbness
of imagination and freedom," says Steven
Spielberg.
This very American idea of getting people
to dream by means of cinema has a long his¬
tory. As early as 1909 the American sociolo¬
gist Jane Adams dubbed the cinema a "house
of dreams" and wrote, "By going to the
movies, today's young people living in
industrial towns can satisfy their needs for a
richer existence than that the world offers
them at present." This desire to induce
people to dream and to give them models to
identify with led to the creation of thrillers,
Bambi (United States,
1941-1942), a Walt
Disney-produced
feature-length cartoon.
A pioneer in the field,
Disney was the world's
undisputed cartoon king
for many years.
Francis Ford Coppola's
Apocalypse Now (United
States, 1979), an epic
rendering of the Viet
Nam War.
westerns and musical comedies, all typically
American genres.
Yet the American cinema provides some¬
thing more than dreams and entertainment,
even if its watchword was summed up by
Frank Capra when he said, "There are no rules
when it comes to film creation, only sins.
And the most deadly is boredom." Holly¬
wood has produced many films attacking the
"American model", and has on occasion
indulged in ruthless self-criticism (Joseph L.
Mankiewicz's All about Eve, for example). In
the wealth and diversity of American cinema
everyone can find enjoyment as well as the
expression of their anxieties.
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Czech-born
American director
Milos Forman has
won American
Academy Awards
(Oscars) for Best
Film with One Flew
Over the Cuckoo's
Nest (1975) and
Amadeus (1984).
Left, directing Tom
Hulee (Mozart) in
Amadeus.
Milos Forman
interview
> Tell us about your first
contact with the cinema.
It was unforgettable. One Saturday
night, when I was four or five years
old, my parents took me to see a film
in Caslav, the city where I was born in
the country that was then called
Czechoslovakia. I found out later that
it was a documentary about Smetana's
opera The Bartered Bride. Oddly
enough, it was a silent film. On the
screen gigantic people opened enor¬
mous mouths from which no sound
emerged. But the audience knew the
opera by heart and began to sing
louder and louder. The women were
in tears. It was an extraordinary intro¬
duction to the cinema!
Some time later I saw Snow White
and the Seven Dwarfs, which I
thought was wonderful. I thought
that I had seen the most beautiful
thing in the world, and I fell in love
with Snow White. In a store I had
bought coloured cakes of soap
shaped like the seven dwarfs, and
each day I used a different one. When
I saw the film, I stopped using these
pieces of soap so that they would last
longer.
How did you get started in
theatre, in directing?
During the war my brother Pavel,
who was being hunted by the
Gestapo, joined a troupe that staged
operettas. He designed the stage sets.
It was thanks to him that I saw my first
play, which struck a deep emotional
chord. He also took me backstage.
That was extremely disconcerting: the
young women undressing before my
eyes, the jokes, the music, the smell of
starch and mothballs and sweat. It
was a revelation to me and I decided
there and then that the theatre, this
other world, would be my life.
Looking around me, I gradually
discovered that there is often a differ¬
ence between what people think and
Above, Jack Nicholson gets a lift
from Will Sampson in One Flew
Over the Cuckoo's Nest.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
what they do. I learned to decipher
their feelings when they often
couldn't do so themselves. It's the
same with fictional characters. There's
always a mask that needs to be
removed, and essentially this is what a
stage or film director does.
I When you went backstage,
did you already know that
you wanted to become a
stage director?
No, I had no idea at that time. I
vaguely thought that maybe I would
become an actor or even a playwright.
I was very young. I remember very
clearly, towards the end of the war,
when the German authorities decided
to close all the theatres and movie
houses in Bohemia. Everybody was in
tears, on stage and in the audience.
The conductor silenced the orchestra.
I thought that the world which 1 had
just entered was disappearing forever.
I Later on you went to film
school?
Yes, in Prague. I studied screen¬
play writing and film technique. Milan
Kundera was one of my teachers. He
was already known as a poet. He was
not much older than we were, and the
female students adored him. He made
me read Les Liaisons Dangereuses,
which I made into a film many years
later. I wrote hundreds of pages,
analysing films and screenplays. And,
of course, we saw films.
I Which ones?
We saw all the films we could.
Today, when I try to remember which
ones had the biggest effect on me
back then during those decisive, for¬
mative years when choices are
madeI would put Charlie Chaplin
first. I admired and loved his work
enormously. Next I would mention
A scene from Milos
Forman's 77ie Firemen's Ball
(Czechoslovakia, 1967), a
satire on life in a small
Czech town.
Italian neorealist films, the work of
Cesare Zavattini and Vittorio De Sica,
especially Miracle in Milan and The
Bicycle Thief. I liked their blend of fun
and feeling. In a word, I liked their
humanity.
ft After film school, you
went into television. By
then, the communist
regime was firmly
established in
Czechoslovakia. Were you
a victim of censorship?
During the whole of the first part of
my life, in the theatre, in films, or in
television where, by the way, I pre¬
sented films everything I did meant
waging, as resourcefully as possible,
an endless struggle against censor¬
ship, which was ubiquitous. The
need to struggle, to be cunning day
in day out, made me realize very early
on that film plays a social role, that it is
a certain way of looking at the world,
and that it can even help to change
the world, even if only to a slight
extent.
Every actor who appeared on tele¬
vision first had to fill in a form in which
he wrote out his lines, which were
then submitted to the censor "up
there", as we used to say. One day, I
wanted to present two jugglers on a
variety show. I was asked to report to
the censor what they were going to
say. Of course they weren't going to
say anything. I tried to explain this but
it was no good. So I advised the jug¬
glers to fill in their forms anyway,
which they did. They wrote down
something like: "Hey! Ho! Hop! Hop!
Yup! Ah!" The form came back with
the official stamp of approval. The dia¬
logue had been accepted "up there".
There is something else that I'll
never forget. Under communism, in
principle, all society's problems were
solved. Consequently, any conflict
between good and evil in a contem¬
porary context, at any rate became
impossible. How could drama even
exist in such a situation? You can't
imagine the endless discussions that
were held to solve this problem which
today seems ridiculous.
ft Was it ever solved?
Yes. The great minds of the Party
found a solution. Conflicts should be
between "the good and the best".
ft Even since your first film,
the documentary Talent
Competition, you have
stayed very close to
reality.
Yes. I have always been fascinated
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Hana Breechova (right) as
Angela, the factory worker, in
Milos Forman's A Blonde in
Love (Czechoslovakia, 1965).
by what is called "reality". I wanted
and still do my films to seem real.
But when a camera is filming, it always
distorts the reality it seeks to record
and people stop acting naturally. This
is something that cannot be helped.
Ironically, it was my interest in reality
that led me to fiction. There, at least, I
can create my way another kind of
truth.
ft But you also want to tell a
story.
I've always wanted to tell stories.
Telling a story, I think, is a way of
approaching even, perhaps, under¬
standing life. And storytelling, with
all its surprises, is also a source of
pleasure.
ft In 1968, when Warsaw
Pact troops invaded
Prague, you decided to go
and work in the United
States. Unusually, you
made a fresh start in
another country and in
another language. You
have won two Academy
Awards, one for One Flew
Over the Cuckoo's Nest
and another for Amadeus.
What is your secret?
There is no secret. Adapting to a
new life in the United States was a
matter of survival. I had no choice. I
took advantage of an opportunity that
the French film director Claude Berri
gave me, and made Taking Off In New
York in 1969. But that film was not
successful in the United States. Prob¬
ably it was too idiosyncratic. For a few
years I had a hard time and then sud¬
denly had a success with Cuckoo.
No, I don't have a secret. Other
film-makers who had come from
Europe, especially Central Europe,
people like Ernst Lubitsch, Billy Wilder
and Fritz Lang, also made a new life
for themselves in the United States. Of
course I had to change the way I
worked and even the kind of stories I
tell. Until I could walk into a bar and
understand everything people were
saying, I couldn't hope to make
movies in America that were close to
reality, movies like Black Peter and A
Blonde in Love. I wasn't really at
home, even If I was now carrying an
American passport.
ft Did you return to
Czechoslovakia?
I went back as soon as I could, in
1979, and my first official reception
was held at the American embassy.
After that, I made Amadeus there.
Now I often go back. My two sons live
and work in Prague. Vaclav Havel,
President of the Czech Republic, is an
old friend.
ft But you have no plans to
make a Czech film?
Some day, perhaps. Why not? But
I would have to change the way I work
again and get used to my country '
which has changed considerably all
over again.
ft Do you feel at home in the
United States now?
I have always felt at home in places
where I could work in peace. I felt at
home wherever I had a roof over my
head and could put down my suit¬
case. In recent years it has been easier
for me to make films In the United
States than in Central Europe, and I
had a good roof over my head in Con¬
necticut. How could I possibly not feel
at home?
But maybe one day the forces that
took me far from the land of my child¬
hood will bring me back again. Who
knows?
ft Do you think the cinema
has a future?
As far as I am concerned, yes. Five
years after Valmont, I am almost cer¬
tainly going to make a new film. We're
supposed to start shooting at the
beginning of next year.
ft And the cinema in
general?
Yes. Films will go on being made.
There's no doubt about that. What
sort of films? That's the big question.
The answer is in the hands of the
people who will be making them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Methuselah
or
Peter Pan?
n wanji
t is very hard for us not to realize we are
100 years old, for everyone keeps on
telling us so: the cinema is about to clock
up the first century of its existence.
Is the cinema young or old? Has it,
within a mere century, come full circle? Is it
not beginning to repeat itself, to show signs
of senility and approaching death? Could
this first century also be its last?
It is certainly true that the language of
film has evolved incredibly fast. The gulf
Is the cinema young or old? asks
a leading French scriptwriter in a
forceful article on the dilemmas
facing the seventh art, including
the tensions between America and
Europe over the liberalization of
trade in audiovisual products.
that separates a monologue in Racine from a
Surrealist poem, or a Giotto from a
Kandinsky, was bridged by the cinema in
less than fifty years. It is an art in a hurry
and ever on the move, a form of expression
that is constantly being manhandled and
mauled. This sometimes leads film-makers to
regard straightforward shifts of syntax, or
state-of-the-art equipment, or satellite
broadcasting, or so-called "new" images, as
profound or even revolutionary changes.
That great inventiveness, which has been a
characteristic of the cinema since its very
beginnings, tends to generate a state of exhil¬
aration in practitioners of film, which
encourages them to confuse, not for the first
time, technique with thought, technique
ES
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
with emotion, technique with knowledge.
Signs of change are mistakenly identified
with the deeper substance of film. The won¬
derful proliferation of images that dog us
wherever we go only aggravates this feeling
of intoxication. Struck dumb by each new
marvel of technology, we obstinately over¬
look the most fundamental thing of all: the
true and singular meaning of what we see.
Yet what we see is a repetition of the same
familiar patterns in different technological
disguises. We talk of eternal youth and
renewal, and we applaud. This explains our
sense of utter confusion, our feeling that
everything we thought we knew is con¬
stantly being called into question. It explains
our permanent state of feverish dissatisfac¬
tion, our almost unhealthy need to switch
from one form to another and to regard
that process as real change.
It also explains our weariness, which
arises from the repetition of an illusion. We
Pierre Brasseur,
Arletty and
Jean-Louis Barrault in
The Children of
Paradise
(France, 1943-1944),
directed by
Marcel Carné
and written by
Jacques Prévert.
know full well that at a time when we are
swamped by images it is increasingly diffi¬
cult to create an image a truly dense and
radiant image which our brain immediately
locks into and never abandons.
So is the cinema old? In its 100 years of
existence, it would seem to have gone
through every conceivable phase: primitive,
classical and baroque periods, followed by a
renaissance (also known as the "NewWave"),
a Surrealist, symbolic and even abstract
period, all jumbled together and overlapping
each other without any chronological rhyme
or reason. The result today is that film¬
makers seem to have lost their productive
ambition and are resigned to working in an
often conventional narrative form or pro¬
ducing remakes of the same old stories.
Amazing maturity There was a time,
thirty or forty years ago, when the
cinema vowed it would swallow up all other
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
forms of expression, from architecture and
painting to music, drama and, of course, lit¬
erature. It was hailed as the complete art, the
art we had been waiting for since the begin¬
ning of History, the art of the twentieth
century and the centuries after it.
Naturally, the dream fizzled out. Litera¬
ture is not dead, nor is painting; and the the¬
atre all over the world seems more thriving
than ever. Film has had to resign itself to
being nothing but film which is already
quite an achievement. And the technical
exploits which brought it such loudly pro¬
claimed glory are now a nuisance and even a
hindrance.
Sooner or later we may enter the universe
of virtual images and be able, in our drawing
rooms, to act out scenes with utterly sub¬
missive creatures that are the spitting image
of Marilyn Monroe or Napoleon. But that
day is still several decades away, and in the
meantime the cinema remains an image lim¬
ited by a frame and projected onto a flat
screen, either large or small. That projection
has to obey a certain pace and send out a pre¬
cise number of frames per second, otherwise
the film being shown becomes an incompre¬
hensible mishmash of images or else, on the
contrary, slows down and stops.
Paradoxically, then, what was once the
very strength of the cinema may today be its
weakness. Film is a technical exploit, but an
exploit limited by the technique itself. It is
far from certain that we shall succeed in
extricating ourselves from that contradic¬
tion.
The cinema has also aged in another, even
more alarming way: it has lost its inventive,
investigative streak, selling its soul to com¬
mercial forces and giving up the notion of
original expression. As a result, a great debate
continues regularly to pit American distrib¬
utors against European film-makers. Let us
examine that issue in a little more detail.
TWO traditions The American cinema,
or rather the American sound image as
conveyed by both cinema and television,
seems to be spreading into every corner of
the world, rapidly destroying all local pro¬
duction. This conquest is in fact a recon-
quest. At the beginning of the 1920s, Holly¬
wood enjoyed a virtual monopoly in the
manufacture of moving pictures about 80
per cent of world production. That per¬
centage fell during the decades that followed,
as a result of the rise of national film indus¬
tries and the advent of the Second World
War, which cut off many countries from the
American distribution network.
Ever since 1 945, a clearly defined and fully
avowed process of reconquest has been
underway. The bosses of this industry
regard film as a commodity that is in no way
cultural in nature. The American distribu¬
tors' firm and sincere message to us is: the
cinema is our patch why don't you go and
manufacture something else?
Rather than spend time on the superficial
slanging match in which the Americans are
regularly described as "imperialists" and the
French as "chauvinists", it is important to
remember, I think, that our two opposing
stances, which were brought into confronta¬
tion during the GATT1 negotiations, are the
product of two parallel traditions.
The older of those traditions is Anglo-
American and goes back to an eighteenth-
century statute on copyright passed in Eng¬
land during the reign of Queen Anne. This
statute enabled printers to buy a work from
an author and do what they wished with it.
In the last three centuries that tradition has
been kept alive although it has had a
bumpy ride in northern Europe and, at a
later date, in the United States.
Another tradition, which began with
Beaumarchais in France in the eighteenth cen¬
tury, holds on the contrary that the person
who writes a work is its actual author and
has financial and moral rights to it. That
view, which was vigorously promoted by
Victor Hugo, gained currency and resulted,
at the end of the nineteenth century, in the
Bern Convention, to which nearly 100 states
throughout the world now adhere
Jean-Claude Carrière,
French writer,
playwright and
scriptwriter, is
President of FEMIS, a
Paris cinema and
audiovisual school.
Erich von Stroheim
(centre) with (from his
left) Pierre Fresnay and
Jean Gabin in Jean
Renoir's The Great
Illusion (France, 1937),
the story of a group of
Frenchmen in a German
prisoner-of-war camp
during the First World
War.
|
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
This radical difference between two con¬
ceptions explains why the American cinema,
never regarded as an art, has been very much
the work of producers. In Europe, on the
other hand, and especially in France, the
notion has grown up that the cinema is a
means of expression and even an art in its
own right. For this reason, the author or
authors of a film, by virtue of the fact that
they enjoy rights to their works as a result
of the Bern Convention, regard themselves
as artists on a par with painters or writers.
The immediate upshot of all this has been
that if the cinema is an art it should be con¬
nected with the Culture Ministry and be
helped and even protected. This help has
taken various forms in France since 1947, but
consists mainly of a tax on cinema takings,
which finds its way back into the hands of
producers when they produce a new film.
Adangerous misunderstanding The
various debates that pitted the French
against the Americans during the GATT
talks have not affected our longstanding and
unshakable admiration for the great Amer¬
ican cinema. Film seems to have been etched
into the very substance of America. It is hard
In Luis Buñuel's The
Discreet Charm of the
Bourgeoisie (France,
1972), written by Jean-
Claude Carrière, the
colonel's guests
discover they are on
stage before a theatre
audience.
to imagine one without the other. The dis¬
agreement is in fact based on a misunder¬
standing. Once that is realized, it becomes
clear that our two traditions, which have
always existed alongside each other, and very
often harmoniously, cannot possibly merge
into a single tradition.
Neither of the two can be wiped out by
the other. They have to go on coexisting.
Any monopoly of images in the world of
Celia Johnson
and Trevor
Howard in Brief
Encounter
(United
Kingdom,
1945), directed
by David Lean.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
the near future would be unfair for some
and dangerous for everyone.
The argument one most often hears is
that of "free competition". The trouble is
that these two words do not mean the same
thing everywhere. It is obviously absurd to
claim, for instance, that Mali and California
are "free" to compete with each other. As
someone put it, it is a case of "a free fox in a
free henhouse".
A straightforward trade clause in a treaty
could well result in the demise of a means of
expression something which even the most
ferociously dictatorial measures have never
been able to achieve in the history of the
world. And that has already occurred in
many countries. Producers and authors have
not always spotted the danger. They have
preferred to throw in the sponge on the pre¬
text of "allowing a free play of market
forces". And the fox got in through the
main door, bringing with him basketfuls
not only of sounds and pictures, but of var¬
ious products represented and often extolled
by those sounds and pictures, such as
clothes, drinks, cars, cigarettes and even the
ordinary things of daily life. We now know
that no image is innocent. An image is much
more than an image.
AVital language Thus, at a deeper level,
the question we have to ask ourselves is:
is the filmed image necessary for a people? Is
this way of telling ourselves our own sto¬
ries, of holding a mirror up to our own faces
with today's techniques, a simple pleasure of
life or a vital necessity?
I would answer that it is a vital necessity.
American distributors would argue the con¬
trary: it does not matter, they would say,
that the Africans, the Brazilians or even the
Europeans can no longer make films. We'll
make them for them.
African television viewers already have no
choice: they are given a forced diet of for¬
eign-made police series and sentimental soaps
that never address their own concerns.
And the same lurking danger threatens
Europe. The French production system,
which is possibly the most sophisticated in
the world in that it allows public subsidies to
be used along with private money, is Europe's
last bastion of resistance against the American
invasion. If it were to be swept away, not only
would the death knell be sounded for the
French cinema, but we could kiss goodbye to
the last remnants of a European cinema Wim
Wenders, Andrzej Wajda, Pedro Almodovar,
Theodoros Angelopoulos and many others
and indeed to the last surviving examples of
ambitious, individual and experimental film¬
makers in the world, whose films are always
co-produced according to the French
system Akira Kurosawa, Nikita Mikhalkov,
Zhang Yimou and Souleymane Cissé.
By sticking up for ourselves we are
sticking up for others. It has nothing to do
with chauvinism. On the contrary, the aim
is to defend a "different cinema" wherever it
emerges in the world. Two radically different
conceptions have clashed. The two countries
which invented the cinema, the United States
and France, are confronting each other once
again. This is no doubt a great pity, particu¬
larly as this trade war is one-way. No one in
Europe wants to see the American cinema
disappear. It would be absurd and unreal.
The American cinema has long been very
widely shown on French screens, and I only
hope that this continues to be the case.
French films, on the other hand, are virtu¬
ally nowhere to be seen in the United States.
So, when it comes down to it, is the
cinema young or old? The answer can be
provided only by those who will work in
the cinema of the future. There is no way
that it can disappear as a product. But as a
means of expression, a form of artistic exper¬
imentation or a way of looking at the
world and not as "entertainment", which
makes us turn away from the world it is
indisputably under threat.
Even so, let's lay our bets on the younger
generation, on the indomitable forces that
are ours, on the obscure, startling and
breathless leap from one century to the next.
1 GATT: General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. A set of
international agreements (now superseded by the World Trade
Organization) concerning some 140 countries and aimed at the
liberalization of world trade. An agreement reached between the
United States and the European Union on 14 December 1993
maintains protection for the European audiovisual industry in the
name of what has been called the "cultural exception". (Ed.)
Theo Angelopoulos's
The Suspended Step of
the Stork (France,
Greece, Italy and
Switzerland, 1991)
features Marcello
Mastroianni and Jeanne
Moreau in the story of a
reporter who
recognizes a writer who
has supposedly
disappeared.
M
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
interview
«Jean-Paul Rappeneau
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
French director
and screen-writer.
His film Cyrano
de Bergerac won
ten Césars, the
French national
film award.
> When did you first become
a film-goer?
It was just before the Second
World War. I enjoyed Walt Disney's
Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs
and The Adventures of Robin Hood
directed by Michael Curtiz and William
Keighley. I saw them in Auxerre, the
town where I was born, in the Grand
Casino, which was also used for
stage plays. And the theatre was my
first great love.
At the end of the war American
films poured into Europe, and like
every other teenager I raced to see
them. We started a film club in Aux¬
erre, and I was one of the organizers.
That's where I really started to learn
about the cinema and love films.
I remember Eisenstein's The Gen¬
eral Line and The Battleship Potemkin
and Pudovkin's Mother. When I was
fifteen, in 1947, I was stunned by
Orson Welles's Citizen Kane. I saw
that you could use all kinds of the¬
atrical devices in the cinema but go so
much farther than the theatre. It was a
turning point in my life. The supreme
art for me ceased to be the theatre and
became the cinema.
I thought of nothing else but
making films. I talked my father into
buying me a camera if I passed my
baccalaureate. He kept his word, and
while I was studying law studies
which I never finished I also began
making films on my own in the coun¬
tryside.
A little while later, when I was about
twenty, I met a producer and worked
for the next three years as his assis¬
tant. Then I made a few industrial
Left, Jean-Paul
iRappeneau's
Cprano de Bergerac
(France, 1990).
Adapted from
Edmond Rostand's
play by Rappeneau
and Jean-Claude
I Carrière, it stars
Gérard Depardieu
I (at right) as Cyrano
and Anne Brochet
as Roxane.
Right, Jean-Paul
Rappeneau and
Gérard Depardieu
holding their 1991
Golden Globe
Awards, presented
by the Hollywood
Foreign Press
Association.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
shorts and a short commissioned film
called Chronique provinciale ("Provin¬
cial Chronicle").
ft What made you take the
plunge and become a
director?
With Alain Cavalier, I had produced
an outline for the film that was to
become A Matter of Resistance.
When I actually began to write the film,
I noticed that the dramatic situations
we had invented inevitably turned into
comedy. I called Alain to talk to him
about this and told him I was worried.
He answered, "Don't stop, whatever
you do! Let it come!" I shot the film In
1965. It received the Prix Delluc and
was a box-office hit. Since then I've
never stopped, although I go at my
own pace which is rather slow.
Today I am happiest directing big
pictures like Cyrano de Bergerac or Le
hussard sur le toit ("The Hussar on
the Roof"). I think that's what I was
made for.
ft What about the technical
stuff?
I picked it up gradually, especially
through making advertising films
where I really discovered and devel¬
oped the techniques of cinema, espe¬
cially as my approach to films was
rather literary. I started making adver¬
tising films after my third feature,
Lovers like Us.
ft What future do you see for
the cinema?
That's the big question. Business
and artistic problems are intertwined.
Here in Europe we have got to resist
the American offensive and at the
same time ask how to renew the film
medium. Hasn't it all been said before?
But all my doubts fade away when
I talk to my two sons. Their enthu
siasm for the cinema is intact. They
know all the interesting films that are
going to come out. They rush to see
them, then talk about them. I'm
expecting a comeback of film fandom,
with different masters and different
landmarks. No, basically, I have no
fears about the future of the cinema.
ft What are your feelings
about aufceurcinema?
I respect and like auteur films. I am
completely convinced that the cinema
needs auteurs. I hope I'm one of
them. Moreover when I write and
develop my films, I try to write with the
public in mind. It's extremely impor¬
tant. Without losing an iota of my
ambition, I've always got the public in
mind. I like to think that I'm "a film-goer
who makes films".
Catherine Deneuve and Yves
Montand starred in Jean-Paul
Rappeneau 's Lovers Like Us
(France, 1975).
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Windows of
opportunity
Jerry Palme
Countries where the
film industry is
trying to find a niche
between television
and the powerful
international
distribution networks
The animation
department at the
Uzbekfilm studios in
Tashkent (Uzbekistan).
Some years ago, when I was in
Budapest, Hungary, researching
an article about Hungarian
cinema, I found that each of
Hungary's four film studios had
an annual budget sufficient to produce
around ten films, roughly equal to the spe¬
cial effects budget for a single Hollywood
major film.
Recently I read in a report from India
that in the villages local businessmen rent a
satellite dish that is capable of receiving the
output of Star TV from the Asiasat satellite
and run cables to rented TV receivers. This
makes television reception extremely cheap.
How can locally produced films or even
television compete with this satellite
which transmits old American TV series
bought at a bargain price?
But neither of these stories has quite the
ending we might expect. The Hungarian film
industry has survived the transition to the
free market. And in India the availability of
cheap cable television has produced a rapidly
expanding market for local language TV
showing Bombay-made films and local pro¬
gramming.
These stories from Hungary and India
illustrate the threats and the opportuni¬
ties that are offered to world cinema by
television and the American film industry.
Both the threats and the opportunities are
complicated, and neither derive only from
the fact that America is the majority pro-
|
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Beqabu, an Indian
film by M. N.
Chandra, was shot in
studios located in
the Bombay
suburbs.
Jerry Palmer,
of the United Kingdom,
is Professor of
Communication at
London Guildhall
University. He is the
author of books about
popular fiction in the
novel, film and
television, and has
been a film reviewer
for British magazines
and BBC radio.
ducer of films and TV programmes in the
world.
Does Hollywood dominate world
cinema? It is no longer the world's biggest
producer of films. The Indian film industry
produces more feature films per year than the
United States. Japan and China are big pro¬
ducers, too. On the other hand, Indian, Chi¬
nese and Japanese films are only viewed by
local or expatriate populations, whereas
American films are seen more or less all over
the world. Certainly few Japanese viewers will
have seen Indian films, and vice-versa, but
substantial numbers of viewers in both these
countries will have seen many American films.
Thirty years ago most of the revenue
from U.S. films came from sales inside the
United States. In the last year for the first
time U.S. films made more from their sales
outside the United States than from the U.S.
market. U.S. control over foreign distribu¬
tion has increased in importance recently.
Although there is nothing in the logic of
distribution systems to prevent the U.S. stu¬
dios distributing foreign films as well as U.S.
ones, in fact the U.S. market is so huge in
comparison to most other national markets
and American audiences so much prefer
home-produced films, that the Hollywood
studios place most emphasis on selling
home-made products.
For as long as international distribution
networks are U.S. -dominated, Hollywood
will dominate world cinema. This is not
because home-based movie industries in
other countries are incapable of producing
material that their local audiences prefer we
know in the case of the Asian countries that
this is not so. And the case of European tele¬
vision is interesting here too. In Europe
during the last few years home-produced
programming has started to pull in bigger
audiences than imported U.S. programmes.
The message is clear: where home-produced
material that appeals to the local audience is
available, and a distribution system which is
not American-owned is in place, American
culture finds it more difficult to penetrate.
This introduces the second point: to
what extent is television a threat to world
cinema? To understand this, we must be
clear about what the differences between film
and television are. They are not primarily
distinguished by their systems of represen¬
tation despite differences in picture
quality but by their systems of transmis¬
sion. Although films are of course shown on
television, the television system is funda¬
mentally different from the cinema system
because it is (potentially if not actually)
multi-channel, because it reaches directly
into the home and because it is transmitting
more-or-less permanently a mix of pro¬
gramme types. If the current experiments
with high-definition TV turn into broadcast
or cable systems, the differences in picture
quality between film and television will vir¬
tually disappear.
Film and TV: an ambiguous rela¬
tionship Indeed, one of the ways in
which television has most fundamentally
influenced cinema is in the restriction of
cinema to narrative fiction "feature films",
as they are called in English. Before televi¬
sion, cinema was used to make documen¬
taries, newsreels and advertising. The cine¬
matic forms of the first two have been killed
off completely by television, the latter mar¬
ginalized. That is to say, the differences in
the transmission systems have created what
are apparently the differences in the systems
of representation. Film and television tell
different types of story because of these
restrictions in film story-telling.
For many years film-makers blamed televi¬
sion for the decline in cinema audiences. But
research in Britain suggested that it was not
television that stole the audiences, but home
entertainment in general, in combination
with the shift away from the large urban cen¬
tres whose inner city population was the
source of the enormous cinema audiences
between 1930 and 1960. Television also offered
new opportunities to film-makers, both in
the form of extra revenue through TV screen¬
ings of movies and through commissioning
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
feature films that probably would not have
been made without this support.
The relationship between film and televi¬
sion is very ambiguous. On the one hand, the
presence of television sets in every home pre¬
sents an alternative to cinema. At the moment
differences in picture quality, plus the social
value of going out to the cinema instead of
staying at home, reduce the competition
from television. But the differences in picture
quality will probably be removed by high-
definition TV. If the information super¬
highway becomes a transmission system for
entertainment, it is possible that we will be
able to select movies from a "movie bank" for
transmission into our own homes. But it is
likely that the movies in question will only
be the most popular ones, since a system
which would allow anyone to select any
movie they liked for transmission would
probably not be economically viable.
If only the most successful movies are to
be transmitted, they will probably be
American because those are the films which
attract the biggest audiences internationally.
This means that the cost of each viewing can
be reduced because of the likely number of
viewings. On the other hand, local distribu¬
tion networks using the superhighway (if
there are to be such things) might be able to
benefit from a high number of local view¬
ings of films made on a relatively low budget
for local audiences. Here another factor
comes into play: it is already technologically
possible to show a film on a video disc
which has several alternative sound-tracks in
different languages. This potentially enlarges
the audience for films in non-majority lan¬
guages without using sub-titles, which tend
to put audiences off.
It is likely to be control of distribution
systems rather than production systems
which determines whether world cinema can
survive the threats from new TV systems
and American predominance and turn them
into opportunities.
Steven Spielberg's E. T.
(United States, 1982)
unites a gentle creature
from outer space and
his young earthling
protector.
Filming at the National
Picture Studios in
Rangoon (Myanmar).
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The first Indian
Romain Maitra
Three studios where
the world's most prolific film
industry was born
HuZl'l .^"SKi
g
B^& ^^3 Ifir £^P Rjfl
SAT WtIiBÍ"
The logo of New
Theatres Limited.
The Indian film industry was born
and took root in and around Cal-
.cutta, Bombay and Madras,
major port cities where there was
a strong backdrop of intellectual
and theatre activities. From the 1920s on,
enterprising film-makers in these regions
made films in a variety of genres such as
mythology, history, folklore and fantasy,
whose popularity cut across social barriers.
These films were products of the studio
system. The major studios had distinct iden¬
tities of their own. Three of them in partic¬
ular left a mark on Indian cinema in the 1930s.
New Theatres Limited, with its famous
banner of a trumpeting elephant, was the
vision of Birendra Nath Sircar, a civil engi¬
neering graduate of London University,
who gathered a group of talented men
around him and raised Indian cinema from
the status of a novel form of entertainment
to that of an art. New Theatres was a nursery
for a number of directors and actors who
later became household names.
As one cinema historian has written,
"Sircar wanted, not a production company,
studio and cinema halls, but a system, a perva¬
sive, self-supporting, efficiently managed,
supremely equipped network of men and
women and machines which would sell the cel¬
luloid dream like it had never been sold before
in India, in markets determined by the caprice
of public preference." The artistes, who
worked as salaried staff and not on contract,
had to be at the studios whether or not they
were working on a film; when not acting, an
actor might be given riding or fencing lessons
or assigned temporary technical duties.
New Theatres' first big success, Chan-
didas, was based on the life of a Hindu saint.
With Devdas, adapted from a famous Ben¬
gali novel, it captured the huge all-India
market. Most Indian films had hitherto been
vehicles for song-and-dance sequences, but
Devdas was a serious treatment of a pow¬
erful dramatic situation. A fire in the studios
in 1940 and later a sharp financial decline
brought about the demise of New Theatres
in 1955. The impact of communalism in the
1940s and the advent of the star system also
helped to seal its fate.
The second important studio, Bombay
Talkies, was founded in 1934 by Himan Rai
and became the true precursor of the Indian
commercial cinema. Its films captivated audi¬
ences with a blend of political and social
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Studios
A Throw of Dice (India,
1929) by Franz Osten and
Himansu Rai, was
produced at the Bombay
Talkies studio.
comment, glamour, melodrama and melo¬
dious soundtracks. Achhut Kanya (1936) is
the tragic tale of an Untouchable girl in love
with a Brahmin youth, who ends by giving
up her life on the altar of caste barriers and
religious bigotry. Films such as Savitri
(1937), a mythological tale from the Mahab¬
harata, effectively captured Hindu values
and sentiments.
Foreign technicians, mainly German and
British, were employed at the Talkies, and a
lot of modern equipment was used. A staff
of more than 400 Indians ate together in the
company canteen, irrespective of the castes to
which they belonged. Well-known actors
would sweep the floors if need be. Famous
authors conducted seminars for the staff,
who were assigned a variety of duties to
broaden their knowledge of the film medium.
Prabhat Studio was launched by a group
of men who had learned their trade as junior
apprentices in a film company in Kolhapur.
One member of the team had done odd jobs
at the Bombay docks before becoming the
art director. Another had worked as a
mechanic, accountant, electrician and scene
painter before becoming the sound recordist.
The most important director of Prabhat's
early films, V Shantaran, started out as a
sign-painter and doorman in a makeshift
cinema. These barely educated men possessed
indomitable will, energy and organizing
ability. In 1933 they moved to a fine location
on the outskirts of Pune, 100 miles south of
Bombay, covering a wide expanse ranging
from hilly tracks to marshland The facilities
at this great film production complex, which
had no highbrow pretensions, ranged from a
huge studio and art factories to accommoda¬
tions for the staff and actors.
The veteran actress Durga Khote recalled
later, "At Prabhat we reported for work at
5:30 in the morning, and we knew that
shooting would be definitely over by 4:30 in
the afternoon. There was no departure from
this routine as shooting was done in sunlight,
and no artificial lights or arc lights were used.
We were called for work at 5:30 because it
took two full hours for make-up with the
hard grease of the old days. By 8 o'clock we
were ready for takes, and by tea-time we used
to pack up, as no more shooting was possible
with the fading sunlight."
Prabhat Studio made many good films,
including Amrit Manthan ("Churning of
Nectar"), produced by V. Shantaram after his
return from a study tour of German stu¬
dios. Amrit Manthan was a milestone in film
technique and evoked a wide-ranging human¬
itarian appeal on the issue of animal sacrifice.
Prabhat's peak period lasted barely ten years
since it could not cover a wider market
due to its early regional language films in
Marathi.
In addition to these three studio units,
an equally strong complex of studios arose
in the mid-1930s in Madras, South India.
Films in the South Indian languages enjoyed
autonomy from the all-embracing Hindi
film market. Modern Theatres near Madras,
founded by T. R. Sundaram in 1936, had a
staff of 250 and made an average of three
films per year.
Romain Maitra
is an Indian journalist
and critic specializing in
dance and the fine arts.
He also writes scripts for
documentary films.
The emblem of Prabhat
Studio.
The logo of Bombay
Talkies Ltd.
M
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Suresh Jindal
i n t e r v i e
ft When did the Indian
cinema begin?
It dates back to the days of the
Lumière brothers who were the first to
show films in India. That was in
Bombay at the turn of the century. In
1 901 , Charles Pathé brought his cam¬
eras here. The first Indian films were
made in 1912, including the famous
Raja Harishchandra by Dhundiraj
Phalke, who had been trained in
Europe. To edit his films, he held up
the frames between his fingers.
The Indians, who were under
British rule at that time, soon realized
what advantages they could draw
from the cinema. They turned to
mythology and history to find their
Suresh
Jindal (left)
is an Indian
producer
whose film
The Chess
Players
(1977),
directed by
Satyajit Ray,
won an
Indian
national
award for
the best
Hindi film in
1978.
roots and indirectly oppose the
British.
Taking their inspiration from Méliès
and the Lumière brothers, they
invented special effects which still
seem astonishing today. The marvel¬
lous Hindi cinema was born in the
wake of the nationalist movement.
Realism was a later development.
With the coming of talkies and
music, four main genres appeared: the
mythological film, the historical saga,
the musical comedy and the social
chronicle often heavily influenced
by Soviet cinema. Major directors
emerged, such as Santaram and
Chetan Anand.
The Indian cinema soon became
popular. Film techniques were easily
adapted to the Indian scene. India pro¬
duced an enormous output of, essen¬
tially, new versions of American
films something that would create
copyright problems today. Later, a cer¬
tain snobbery led us to prefer Amer¬
ican and English films to our own
Indian productions. This had the
blessing of the English government,
which was very keen on creating a
local elite of "brown sahibs".
ft The golden age of Indian
cinema came after the
Second World War. . .
in the 1950s and 1960s. After
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Left, Mrinal Sen's Genesis
(India, 1986), featuring
Shabana Azmi, Nasruddin
Shah and Om Puri.
independence, Indian films carved out
for themselves an enormous and con¬
stantly growing market. That was the
golden age. Famous actors like Ram
Rao were idolized on a scale
unknown in any other country. The
actor even came to be identified with
the gods he played. That is still the
case today. The masters included
Guru Dutt, Raj Kappur, Satyajit Ray,
Mrinal Sen and many others. But the
age of the great masters is over now.
ft Is that when your career
began?
At that time I was in the United
States, studying at the University of
California at Los Angeles. Reading
was my first passion. But in the
1960s I lived on a diet of American
films. At the same time, at the univer¬
sity, where we talked for hours on
end, I discovered Fellini, Kurosawa
and even Satyajit Ray. But I knew that
I would return to India and I did so in
1974 when my father died. I soon
decided to set up a distribution com¬
pany. My mother was opposed to the
idea. At that time the cinema was not
highly thought of. It was a job for a
marasi, a strolling player. "You are
going to become a marasi," she said.
To which I replied: "If I have bad luck
tomorrow, I'll blame you." I promised
to come back to her if films didn't
work out. But my company was suc¬
cessful and I am still going strong.
ft How is distribution
organized in India?
As a general rule, the cinema
owner asks the distributor to agree to
a flat rate price. He does not share in
the risk. That is the first obstacle,
especially for ambitious films. But the
National Film Development Corpora¬
tion, a production company in which
the government and television are
both involved, helps to produce high-
quality films. However, the funds
raised are often ridiculously small. And
the major distribution circuits do not
take these films. There is also the lan¬
guage problem (it is unusual, for
instance, for a Bengali film to be
shown elsewhere in India), and the
inadequate number of cinemas, to say
nothing of poor projection quality.
ft How does the Indian
cinema stand today?
Our national market is threatened.
For the first time, the Americans
dubbed one of their films, Jurassic
Park, in Hindi. It was a smash hit. That
success is bound to make them con¬
tinue. How can we resist? I really
wonder. First, we must give up the
idea that our domestic market is
untouchable. We must fight and
invent. And we can only do so if we
regain our lost passion, or better still a
new passion, for the cinema. M
Satyajit Ray's Ghare-baire
(India, 1984) based on a story
by Rabindranath Tagore.
g
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
inte r v
Mani Kaul
An Indian director whose film Siddeshwari won an Indian
National Award for the best documentary in 1989, Mani
Kaul adapted Dostoevski's The Idiot for the screen in 1991.
ft How did you first come
into contact with the
cinema?
I came to the cinema rather late in
life, because I had eyesight problems
as a child. I was already thirteen when
the doctors found a cure. It was then
that I discovered the world electricity
wires, for example, which I had never
seen before, and of course the
cinema. I think the first film which left
its mark on me was Helen of Troy
(1955), an American costume drama.
First, I wanted to be an actor. Of
course my father objected. Then I saw
a documentary and I realized that films
could be made without actors. It was
a revelation. I remember the film was
about Calcutta.
Fortunately, I had an uncle who
was a film director in Bombay. In fact he
was well known. His name was
Mahesh Kaul. I met him and he was
kind enough to tell my father not to
insist too much on his opposition to
my plans. He even advised him to send
me to the film school In Pune. I spent
three years there and still have excellent
memories of it. I remember one remark¬
able teacher in particular: Ritwik
Ghadak, who was himself a director.
I studied under his guidance and I
Indian director Mani
Kaul and his cameraman
during the filming of
Mati Manas ("Mind of
the Earth").
think I was his favourite pupil. But I
betrayed him. When I saw Robert
Bresson's Pickpocket (1 959), my out¬
look changed completely. From then
on I swore by Bresson, whom I met
later in Paris that was a red letter day
for me.
One Indian film left a deep impres¬
sion on me at the time, and that was
Abrar Alvi's The Master, the Mistress
and the Slave (1 962), with Guru Dutt.
I saw it about twenty times, because a
friend of mine had a cinema in Jaipur.
The film portrays the disintegration of
a land-owning family. It was a big hit
throughout India. I also saw many
American films and films by the great
Indian masters.
I began by making commissioned
documentaries. I made one on civics,
for example. In 1968, I started work
on my first full-length feature film.
Because of a strike which went on for
several months, It took two years to
complete. Then I went on as best I
could, often going back to documen¬
taries. In my films I tried to put across
my great interest in the theatre, music
and Indian song. Without sacrificing
my own tastes, I am always searching
for that elusive rapport with the public
which is indispensable to us film¬
makers.
ft What about television in
India?
It began in the early 1 960s, but the
big event was the broadcast of the
Asian Games in 1982. In the days of
Indira Gandhi, television was system¬
atically regarded as a means of educa¬
tion. Everything was in the hands of
the state, with no private involvement.
That situation lasted for a long time.
Only one cinema film was shown
each week. The other programmes
dealt mostly with agriculture and
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Industry (as in communist countries),
although there were some about
music, yoga and science. There was
no competition whatsoever with the
cinema.
All that changed in 1984. First
because of the appearance of pirate
videos. The lack of copyright protec¬
tion opened the door to Intensive
piracy. "Video rooms" opened all over
the country to show pirate copies of
films made very cheaply in very poor
conditions.
At the same time, television itself
changed. It began to make soap
operas and open up to private invest¬
ment. That was the second threat after
pirate videos. This time the cinema
was hard hit. Many films lost money,
something which had been very
unusual until then.
Today twenty-five channels can
be widely received and the number
is growing. We also receive foreign
channels, especially American chan¬
nels such as CNN and MTV. As a
result, Indian girls are abandoning
their traditional costume and wearing
jeans and other Western-style clothes.
The audience has also changed
both for the cinema and television.
Vulgarity and violence have appeared,
just like everywhere else. And one pri¬
vate channel is just like another. They
all broadcast more or less the same
programmes.
ft Are fewer films being
made than before?
No. Strangely enough, the number
of films being made has hardly
changed and the geographical distrib¬
ution of film production is much the
same as before. Four states (out of
twenty-five) account for half the
output. The list is headed by films
made in Tamil in Tamil Nadu State in
the south, followed by films made in
A potter and his grand¬
daughter in Mani Kaul's
Mati Manas, a
documentary on the
history of pottery.
Telugu, also in the south. Hindi films
only occupy third place. Andhra
Pradesh State is also a major pro¬
ducer. Whenever a film is made in one
of these four systems, it is immediately
translated Into the other three lan¬
guages.
The Indian cinema is threatened
today by a real danger, apart from hard¬
ening of the arteries, and that is the
invasion of dubbed American films.
The offensive has been launched. We
wonder how we can react from inside
what we thought was a fortress. But,
despite its strong personality, India
clearly risks being faced with a major
problem: the gradual disappearance of
genuinely Indian images, words and
cinema, possibly leading to a loss of
identity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Abbas
Kiarostam
i n t e r v
ft Why do you make films?
Because I can't do anything else!
Making films is something I have to
do. It's like dreaming: it comes natu¬
rally, it fulfils a need. The driver of an
Underground train who spends hours
travelling through the dark tunnels
dreams all the time. While they're in
prison, convicts dream of the world
outside. Blind people see by means of
dreams. Life is impossible without
dreams, and thanks to the cinema I
can give shape to some of mine and
let others share them. A link with other
people is made through my dreams.
It's a strange kind of pleasure, com¬
municating with people I don't know
and can't see but who can see my
dreams. . . .
All artists yearn to communicate. It
makes them ill if they can't share their
dreams. I must be one of these
people. This need links me to my audi¬
ences and, first and foremost, to my
actors. During filming, and because of
it, I empathize so strongly with the
actors that they become part of me.
The relationship becomes so intense
that when shooting is over I find it
impossible to part company with
them. That's why my film Where is the
Friend's Home? (1987) had two
sequels, And life goes on ... (1 992)
and Under the Olive Trees (1 994), and
will be continued in my future films. I
am so fond of the region where these
three films were made and the people
who live there that I am in no hurry to
move on.
What happens behind the camera
gives me just as much pleasure as
what happens in front of it. Behind it,
one catches life unawares; in front,
everything is planned and organized,
even the actors' feelings and move¬
ments. Everything Is subordinated to
technical requirements. The equip¬
ment, the constraints of photography,
the overpowering presence of the
crew and especially of the director, all
The Iranian
director Abbas
Kiarostami (left)
has made some
20 films, the
latest of which,
Under the Olive
Trees (1994),
was entered in
competition at
the 1994 Cannes
Film Festival.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
affect the actors' attitudes. The liveli¬
ness and excitement that are to be
found behind the camera often dry
up, fade away and die in front of it.
We should have to get rid of the film
crew and all their paraphernalia before
the actors' performance could be the
real thing, a true reflection of their
identity. Only then could their complex
inner life become visible.
People do not know themselves
until they get to know their own
repressed desires. They have to be
revealed to themselves. Before any
transformation can take place, we
have to know our own legitimate
needs, which originate in dreams. Our
dreams grow out of the bitter experi¬
ence of daily life, which they
endeavour to transcend by seeking a
life of their own.
The cinema can provide a window
looking out from the mediocrity of life
on to the world of dreams. Reality is
the launching pad for dreams. Every¬
thing must start from reality, just as
you launch a kite into the wind but
hold on to the strings. The kite-strings
lead us to reality. We enter the dream
world and come back to real life.
After dreaming, reality may seem
easier to bear, since the change of
scene has brought an influx of energy
and alleviated the sufferings of
everyday existence. On the other
hand, reality may seem intolerable,
uglier and more oppressive than
before a dead end. If this is the case,
then we must change reality. We
follow our dream until reality is trans¬
formed into dream and dream into
reality.
ft What difficulties are
Iranian film-makers
facing today?
First of all, the same difficulties as
those faced by film-makers the world
over. No director can be sure his or her
film will be a success. Generally
speaking, producers want to back a
good film, a quality film, but above all
a money-spinner and there's never
any guarantee of that. One of the
hardest things is to win a producer's
confidence.
The difficulties specific to Iran, an
Islamic country, are the limits imposed
by religion. We film-makers are great
liars; we create lies to suggest truths.
We bring in a man from one place and
a woman from another, and select a
particular house and a particular child
to present a true picture of a family. But
if the woman has to get out of bed
wearing a veil, I am the first to find the
scene implausible. I live in an Islamic
society and my family are Muslims, but
neither my sister nor my wife wear
headscarves in bed. So far I have man¬
aged to avoid this kind of scene which
gives a false picture of reality, but
because of these restrictions many
subjects are automatically ruled out.
ft Is that one of the reasons
why you work with
children?
Not at all. I like working with chil¬
dren. It started quite by chance and
then I came to like having them
around. They are at ease in front of
the camera. They are not thinking
about fame or money. They are
amenable.
ft No American films are
allowed to be distributed
in Iran. What do you think
of this ban?
It's both a good thing and a bad
thing: good for Iranian film-makers,
who are protected from competition
from American films and have been
able to make films and win the appre¬
ciation of cinema-goers; bad for
Iranian audiences, who can never see
American pictures at the cinema. The
situation clearly has both negative and
positive aspects, negative because
any ban is undesirable but positive as
regards the protection of the Iranian
film industry.
ft Doesn't the fact that
people regularly watch
foreign films on video
stop them going to the
cinema?
There is a certain class of people
who no longer go to the cinema, who
are video consumers. The cassettes
are of poor quality. They are recorded
abroad direct from television sets and
distributed in Iran.
The recent Introduction of satellite
television has created a flagrant con¬
tradiction between what people,
young people in particular, see at
home and what they see outside the
home. To take one example, children
are not allowed to go to school in
jeans but at home my son can see, on
satellite television, images of freedom
that constantly conflict with life in Iran.
This contradiction is psychologically
harmful and wounding for him. It is
sad for a film-maker like me to end up
saying that it would be better if we
didn't have satellite dishes in Iran.
When a balance cannot be struck
between the inside and outside, you
have to do as best you can, so my
Opposite page, above,
Where is the Friend's
Home? (Iran, 1987).
Right, Under the Olive
Trees (Iran, 1994). Two
feature-length films by
Abbas Kiarostami.
EQ
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
And Life Goes On (Iran, 1992),
was released the same year that
Abbas Kiarostami was awarded
the Roberto Rossellini Prize at
the Cannes Film Festival for his
life's work.
son and I agreed that we should shut
the television set away in a locked
cupboard. But I know that my heart is
locked in that cupboard too. While I
was out, he opened the cupboard
and plugged the set back in.
ft Who goes to the cinema in
Iran?
Ordinary people, the man in the
street, the people from the bazaars
what we call the "third class" but also
middle-class people. A film currently
showing in Tehran, The Red Hat and
the Cousin, is breaking all box-office
records. Its success proves that people
need to go to the cinema to be enter¬
tained. They don't go to keep up with
developments in the art of cinematog¬
raphy or to be preached at.
ft Let's go back to your work
with children. . .
Working with children has helped
me In my private life more than in my
professional life. Children know less
than adults but they have a healthier
attitude to life. I've made the best pos¬
sible deal with them: I've provided
them with knowledge and they've
brought me health. Children have
taught me to live. They are budding
mystics.
ft The Chinese philosopher
Lao-tze was nicknamed
"the old child» . . .
When I had a real problem I would
put it to my younger son, who always
had a magnificent answer. They have
an answer to everything: "So what?"
It's great. You present them with ter¬
rible disasters and they reply "So
what?" You tell a child "Wrap up well
or you'll catch cold" and he replies
"So what?", "You'll get wet""So
what?", "You'll have a temperature"
"So what?"
When times are hardest they
answer your questions without hesi¬
tation. They stop what they're doing
for a moment and come out with their
"So what?", then go back to their
game. Like the Sufi mystics, they take
advantage of the moment, they live in
the present, the here and now. I
believe the definition of mystics also
fits children. There are budding mys¬
tics all around us and we don't appre¬
ciate them.
ft Apart from children, you
like to work with non¬
professional actors,
mostly from rural
backgrounds. How much
difference does appearing
in a film make to their
lives?
Financially speaking, their situation
Is improved but you need to get very
close to them to know how much they
may have changed Inside. Maybe it
harms their ego, as some Iranian jour¬
nalists have claimed they become a
focus of attention for a short while and
then all of a sudden they are forgotten.
But I have no choice in the matter, I
can't re-engage the same children all
the time. When I feel guilty about this, I
try to imagine how I would feel in their
shoes. Would I refuse a pleasant
dream, knowing that when I awoke
life's difficulties would still be there?
No, I would be prepared to make the
trip. . . .
ft What is the first image
you remember seeing on
film?
The roaring Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer
lion, in 1950, when I was ten. But I
also played with bits of film when I
was small. I thought they were stamps
that had to be looked at against the
light. . . .
ft How did you get into film¬
making?
By chance. I studied at the Tehran
Faculty of Fine Arts, designed adver¬
tising posters and illustrated children's
books. In 1969 I was asked to do
some work for the Institute for the
Intellectual Development of Children
and Adolescents. I worked with ama¬
teurs on my first film, Bread and the
Street (1970). It's the story of a child
who buys some bread and wants to
go home but Is frightened by a dog in
the street. We didn't have a child actor
or a trained dog and I was a novice
myself. We three non-professionals
got together, and that became a kind
of model for my later work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT
silver-screen
symphony
by Elie Faure
Elie Faure (1873-1937) was one of the great j ^ NEW ART
art critics of the twentieth century. An ardent
humanist who believed in the unity of the
universe, of humanity and of art, he had an
all-encompassing vision of art, in which he
saw parallels between works of different
periods and cultures. The article published
here, written in 1937, is his response to a
survey on the intellectual role of the cinema
carried out by the International Institute of
Intellectual Co-operation (IIIC), the
forerunner of Unesco.
Whether a film be good or bad,
whether it be fiction, science or doc¬
umentary, the informed observer cannot
fail to detect in it the characteristic features
of an absolutely distinctive art form, a
form emerging, it should be noted, at a
time when the most varied or successive
cultures seemed nearly to have exhausted
those forms of expression whereby they
had been handed down to us. By a neces¬
sary coming together that might be called a
coincidence, were it not for the fact that
the machine civilization which engendered
the cinema had not at the same time
brought face to face various ideas and
values, motion pictures came into being at
the very moment when art forms quite
unfamiliar to us Cambodian, Javanese
and Mexican architecture and sculpture and
especially African and Polynesian carv¬
ings came along to overturn our most
firmly established aesthetic concepts and
hence to sow the seeds of doubt and
anguish in our hearts and minds. It was
also the moment when, for the same rea¬
sons, an immense task of destruction and
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT
reconstruction was under way in minds
shaped by economics, replacing, among
most of the so-called civilized peoples and
in all fields of thought and action, the con¬
cepts of individual aptitudes and aims with
the concept of forces and of needs awaiting
fulfilment.
There ensued a renewed, if not indeed
new, and pressing demand for forms of
expression to be devised in response to these
needs and forces. The cinema, the offspring
of scientific culture and technical develop¬
ment, offered itself as a natural means of
meeting that demand, just as music and
dance offered themselves to primitive peo¬
ples as a way of expressing the culture of
myths and as architecture offered itself to
the great religious syntheses Brahmanism,
Buddhism, Christianity, Islam to express
the social culture of which they are the sub¬
limated manifestation.
A symphonic mode of expression
The cinema does indeed display all the
social features that medieval Christian
architecture to take the closest and most
recent example of an endeavour to achieve
what I would call a symphonic mode of
expression offered for unanimous accep¬
tance by the multitudes. The cinema is
anonymous, like architecture, and like
architecture it addresses all possible specta¬
tors, regardless of age, gender or country,
by the universality of its language, the
countless places where the same film is or
can be shown. It too is obliged, in order to
construct its buildings, to marshal financial
and organizational resources that are
beyond, overwhelmingly beyond, the
capacity of the individual. It too can appeal
only to rather general, rather simple senti¬
ments in order to gain the immediate
acceptance of all. The means employed in
architecture are similar to those of the
cinema, by which I mean that nearly every
trade is or may be involved: on the one
hand the stonecutter and the stonemason,
the labourer and the glazier, the plumber
and the smith, the painter and the master
builder; on the other, the wardrobe mis¬
tress and the set designer, the electrician and
the cameraman, the extra and the effects
man, the director and the actor. An analogy
to the standardization of film stock can
easily be found in the flying buttress or the
rib vault, the principle of which remained
unchanged throughout Christendom for
two centuries. In the social context, the
replacement of the feudal system by the
towns and guilds is strikingly paralleled by
the growth of trades unions and the
gradual collectivization of the ownership
of the means of exchange and production.
Moreover, a good film may be com¬
pared, by virtue of the musical quality of
its rhythm and of the sense of communion
required of its audience, to the ceremony
of the mass, and it may likewise be com¬
pared, by virtue of the universality of the
sensations it evokes and the feelings it stirs,
to the "mystery" that filled the cathedral
with throngs of worshippers drawn from
every corner of the city and its environs.
The cinema is today the most "catholic" of
the means of expression that the evolution
of ideas and of technology has placed at
man's disposal.
3Iind and machine
Considering the technical nature of all the
processes the cinema employs in order to
reach its audience, are we entitled to confer
upon it the status of an art a status which
it should possess if it really seeks to express
the sentimental aspirations and lyrical out¬
pourings of the multitudes? We certainly
are. Just as very many empirical but never¬
theless very rigorous sciences went into the
building of the cathedrals and the Egyptian
or Greek temples, many exact sciences and
precision techniques underlie and are
employed in film-making.
I must admit I fail to understand for
what transcendent, or for that matter prac¬
tical, reasons this subordination of the
most complex feelings and psychological
nuances to the revelations and demands of
the machine for recording images should
present an insurmountable obstacle to the
emotions of the audience, when the T-
square, compasses and plumbline did not
prevent Athenians from admiring the
proportions and the play of light within
the perfect rectangle described by the
Parthenon, and led the eyes of Christians
to follow the stone ribbing that lent a
musical cadence to the high, shadowed
vaulting of the transept of the cathedral of
Notre Dame in Soissons. Is not the corre¬
spondence between the rhythms that rule
the vegetative functions of life and the
mathematical laws that govern the universe
of stars and molecules the most reliable
guarantee of the aesthetic and moral value
of that which brings us together in the
loftiest communion? Is there, apart from
the human voice and dance, any other
direct means of communication between
artists and those they seek to impress? Is
there not always something, some man-
made tool, that intervenes between the
object represented and its representation
the sculptor's chisel and calliper, the
painter's canvas, brush and paints, and the
writer's pen, ink and paper? Music, whose
harmonic texture corresponds to sensa¬
tions that may be transposed into the
Portrait of Elie Faure
(1873-1937)
by Picasso
(lead pencil, 1922).
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT-
mathematical ratios of the keyboard, never
reaches the listener except via some
"machine" that reproduces those ratios
very accurately, and sometimes via a very
large number of extremely varied instru¬
ments to which the same sets of symbols
inflexibly dictate the incredible complexity
of the orchestral composition.
The cine camera, too, is only an inter¬
mediary between the infinitely varied and
prodigiously complex spectacle unfolding
before it and the cameraman behind it. The
human mind, let us not forget, the mind
that built the camera and all the rest of the
equipment, the artificial light sources in
particular, is constantly called in to discard,
arrange, compose and subordinate one to
another all the elements that go to make up
the poem. As Pascal said of the tennis ball,
some place it better than others.
II. A LANGUAGE WITH
LIMITLESS POWERS
The cinema records images mechanically, it
goes without saying, but who, if not
human beings, selects and arranges those
images? Whilst the cinema, thanks to its
capacity for reproducing gradations of
light or form too subtle to be apprehended
directly by the naked eye, reveals to us a
whole world of harmonies hitherto unseen
and often unsuspected by that eye, which
sees only those harmonies, it may serve,
for the brain for which it is the interme¬
diary, as the point of departure for the dis¬
covery of unfamiliar relationships between
objects and hence an inexhaustible source
of new images and ideas for the keen imag¬
ination and lyrical sense.
The emergence of an unsuspected
universe
Cinema's great contribution has been to
demonstrate to us, by exclusively technical
means, the "scientific" or if you wish
strictly objective nature of the affinities of
colour and analogies of form caught by a
few artists (I am thinking of Velasquez,
Vcrmeer, Georges de la Tour, Goya, even
Manet) of whose vision we are reminded
by certain filmsThe Mark of Zorro}
Underworld2 and a few others a vision so
personal that the number of film-goers
capable of taking it in is scarcely greater
than the number of those who communi¬
cate it to us. Could it not be said that
Hindu and Khmer sculpture, and the
paintings of Tintoretto, Rubens and
Delacroix, for example, seem to prefigure
the art of recording volumes in movement
on film, by virtue of the new spaces they
reveal to us, their daring angles of view,
their dramatic handling of relief,
chiaroscuro and surfaces that twist and
turn, appear and disappear? Or that the
Egyptians, in the way they modulated
light to bring out the undulating, subtle
transitions from the background up to and
into the profiles, were the forerunners of
that continuity in the luminous and
microscopically close-up vision of the
world that cinema achieves, at least for
those that have eyes to see?
Basically, the great artists of the past
played the same role in the aesthetic sphere
as the Greek philosophers played in the
intellectual, and the Old Testament
prophets in the moral. They were vision¬
aries. They deciphered with ease, in a book
invisible to others, a reality that the cinema
unfolds before us with the simplicity of
childhood and the precision of arithmetic.
The miracle of cinema is that the revelations
it offers us advance in step with the auto¬
matic process of its own development. Its
discoveries are an education for us and dic¬
tate the way we work. "Slow motion", for
instance, has drawn a whole unsuspected
world out of the murk of invisibility.
Thanks to it alone we have learned of the
meticulous precautions a bullet takes in
order to pierce a steel plate or a thick tree.
Only thereby do we know that a running
dog is performing a patient crawl. Boxing,
skating or the flight of birds are forms of
swimming or dancing no less graceful than
swimming or dancing themselves, and this
too we know from slow motion, thanks
to which again the poetry of dynamic
equilibrium expressed in sport or combat
holds no more secrets for us. Each one of
the admirable machine's revelations repre¬
sents, for the dialectical progress of visual
and, consequently, metaphysical analysis, a
supremely and unprecedentedly sure step
along the way.
The eye captures the music of life
This miracle has, incidentally, already given
rise to a series of consequences that subject
our human conception of the universe to
constant pressure. The mechanical recording
and screening of images have not only
ensured for all time the mutual agreement
and cross-fertilization of the most rigorous
scientific procedures and the loftiest aes¬
thetic joys; they have to all intents merged
Music that
reaches us through
the eye
together, within the same form of expres¬
sion, apprehensible to the senses, the
simultaneity of the impressions inflicted
upon us by our way of looking at the
individual and the succession of feelings it
imprints upon our thinking. Is this not a
serious betrayal of pure Cartesianism? A
good few years ago, I wrote that "the
cinema manages, for the first time in his¬
tory, to arouse musical sensations that are
interdependent in space by means of visual
sensations that are interdependent in
time", and that "in fact, it is a form of
music that reaches us through the eye".
This incredible phenomenon seems to con¬
tain the secret of a power of expression
whose unity is the most decisive conquest
ever won in our spiritual life, and this may
well be the most unexpected philosophical
gift that Charlie Chaplin's fanciful and
profound genius has bequeathed to us.
We now possess the limitless capacity
to absorb the whole of life, even those
manifestations of it that are least accessible
to the human eye, to cast a dazzling light
on the infinitely complex drama of light
and shade, of shifts of shape and colour, of
the imperceptible undulatory motions that
ensure the continuity of gesture in the
world of animals and plants, of the infini¬
tesimal rhythms that closely link molec¬
ular vibrations to the great pulse of the
cosmos, thus precipitating that same
drama, in a living, active state, in our inner¬
most lives, where it will determine our
psychological attitudes and, soon, even our
reflexes.
The possibilities of the language of the
cinema thus seem to us to be virtually lim¬
itless. With film it is possible to create
poetry, novels, drama, history, science,
journalism and even grammar I mean
technology. The spoken or written word is
necessarily analytical in its means and sym¬
bolic in its expressions. A vast area remains
out of bounds to it, that of the object
given three-dimensional, material form and
the languages whereby it is expressed
dance, sculpture, painting, mime, sport,
the daily sights and sounds of the street at
which words can do little more than hint,
|
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT
whereas the cinema can automatically incor¬
porate them into the visual, moving reality
of its action, while its frame-by-frame
development makes it akin to musical com¬
position to which so many fine films,
even silent ones, contrive to suggest a kind
of equivalence. There is, furthermore, no
language other than, precisely, the spoken
word to which music itself can be more
closely associated, so much so that its own
cadences merge with the beat of the coun¬
terpoint. The universalism towards which
humankind is moving, unanimously, at an
ever-increasing pace now possesses its own
instrument of exchange and expansion.
I apologise for emphasizing in this
way, while bringing to the fore these infi¬
nitely complex means, the primarily visual
nature of cinema, thus laying myself open
to the charge of tautology; but the fact is
that the mass audience, and many film¬
makers, paradoxical as it may seem, have
never realized this. When forced to look at
the matter from this angle, they think it
sufficient to be able to tell a hawk from a
handsaw. But the whole question of the
eventual destiny of the cinema is wrapped
up with the solution to this very problem.
I would go further: it is the whole problem.
What I mean is that no progress can be
made therein without relating it at the
outset to that education of the visual facul¬
ties which the great painters or sculptors
dispensed to some and which the cinema
alone, by virtue of its function as universal
spectacle and its limitless power of insinu¬
ation, is capable of dispensing to all. When
and if the cinema loses sight of the fact that
it Is, first and foremost, an instrument for
producing moving visual harmonies, it
immediately goes off the rails, ending up
in the same cul-de-sac into which its
repeated successes have often side-tracked it
and sometimes boxed it in.
III. THE PRIMACY OF
THE IMAGE
In the post-war years, the cinema worked
very successfully at ridding itself of its
preoccupation with the theatre, gradu¬
ally and perhaps unbeknown to most
film-makers moving towards a visual,
rhythmic interpretation of the world, an
interpretation to which increasingly sup¬
portive contributions were made by the
use of slow-motion, improved lighting
u Wi | methods, technical advances such as double
exposure, and also the gradual evolution of
silent-film acting in the direction of
sobriety.
Cinema is not theatre
The "talkies", and dubbing in particular,
cast doubt on all that had gone before, and
the visual qualities of films have declined in
strict proportion with the improvement in
sound. I have just said that the cinema
seems to me powerful enough to be able to
absorb drama and, since there have been
some remarkable successes in that respect, I
stand open to the charge of contradicting
The cinema must
remain the language of
universal life and
universal man, getting
through to the human
mind by means of
unanimously
communicable
processes.
myself. The fact is, in my opinion, that
film cannot fully attain to the nature of
theatre without perfecting all the other
forms of expression lyric, plastic,
musical, scientific, documentary that it is
known to be capable of assuming, in order
to bring to their highest pitch the tech¬
nical, visual and rhythmic qualities
without which film drama would be
doomed to rapid decline even before
reaching the level of development one is
entitled to expect of it. Another point is
that it would be absurd on the pretext
that cinema can be more powerfully the¬
atrical than theatre itself to sacrifice all its
resources to this single aspect of its power.
If the theatre absorbs the cinema, the
cinema is lost, for the time being at least.
Film should absorb theatre as theatre itself
long ago absorbed music, set design, cos¬
tume, and the use of extras and mime,
while leaving them free to develop indepen¬
dently of it.
The talkies: listening versus looking
There can be no doubt that sound
recording is a crucial achievement for the
cinema and holds out prospects that are
almost as inexhaustible as those offered by
visual images. The voices of the universe
the sounds of the sea and rushing streams,
the wind rustling through branches and
cornfields, birdsong, the hum of insects,
the confused murmur of crowds, the creak
of wheels, the panting of machines and the
alternation of sound and silence the
voices of the universe envelop, espouse,
balance, identify and augment the impres¬
sions conveyed by the sight of breaking
waves, rain falling on steaming earth,
waving corn and foliage, nuptial flights and
honey gathering, surging demonstrations
and military parades, the rhythmic
motions and glints of steel whereby
machines mark the beat of modern
industry, myriads of undetectable micro¬
scopic lives, impressions that form part, as
it were, of the shape of a world of a thou¬
sand interrelated parts. To be convinced of
this one need only watch a silent documen¬
tary. Such is the force of habit that it seems
to us almost as lifeless as a photograph
projected on to a screen seemed to us after
the coming of the cinema. To adapt the
words of Carlyle (or maybe Whitman) to
our present purpose: "If the universe is
incomplete, man will be incomplete."
The immense complexity of the world
must reach people and enter into them
whole and complete. This is precisely why
the human voice, which is only one part of
it perhaps the most moving of all, if the
silence of the mind withdrawn into itself
were unable to challenge its supremacy
should not absorb the whole of the uni¬
verse, except at certain moments of analysis
or emotion that the inner unfolding of the
spiritual drama should suffice to deter¬
mine. This is the same mistake, but in
reverse, as that made by Wagnerian drama,
which seeks to reinforce music, which is
itself expressive enough, with a setting that
is external to it. Words are, indeed, suffi¬
cient unto themselves, but the universe of
which they constitute only a fragment is
equally self-sufficient, and if they act in
partnership it should not be to the detri¬
ment of one of the partners. What I mean is
that, except in the case of films that are
markedly theatrical in form, the story-line
should be organized not around the dia¬
logue but around the image.
IV. FALSE STEPS
The truth of this is evident from the fact
that it is already possible, after several
years' experience, to measure the retreat
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT
into which the "talkies" have forced the
beauty and purity of images. I hope and
believe that this retreat will be temporary,
but temporary only if the public and its
wretched educators reject a cinema that has
become subordinate to words and return
to a cinema that has words as its subordi¬
nate. Words make such demands on the ear,
even when they are pointless or stupid and
insult the intelligence, that attention is
transferred from the image to the words.
The audience listens and ceases to look. The
image retreats into the background. It
becomes merely an illustration of the dia¬
logue, and even the most cultivated
member of the audience very soon loses the
habit of savouring the beauty of the image,
not so much, it is true, in order to savour
the beauty of the words as not to miss any
twist of the plot.3 On the many occasions
when I have tried stopping my ears, I have
found that words and plot draw a double
veil between the image and the mind, as one
may easily realize by seeing a film first in its
original version and then dubbed.
Hallelujah!,* for example, in its orig¬
inal version in English, which I have diffi¬
culty in understanding and gave up trying
to follow, made a very powerful visual
impression on me. When it was dubbed
into French, that impression vanished
because I was listening instead of looking.
As you know, this is not the only draw¬
back of "dubbing", that monstrous nega¬
tion of aesthetic unity whereby the voice
fits neither the expression nor the move¬
ments nor the human form in action, nor
even universal form, and seems extraneous
to the events taking place on the screen. For
the universe is one and man is one. If you
cut man into two while the universe
remains one, the whole cosmic drama in
which man is only an actor immediately
loses, for minds with a modicum of clear¬
sightedness and hearts with a modicum of
nobility, all its emotive power. I might add
that "talkies", and especially dubbed films,
deprive the cinema of the human univer¬
sality that, from the beginning, endowed
it with psychological power and social
importance. The cinema must remain the
language of universal life and universal
man, getting through to the human mind
by means of unanimously communicable
processes. Furthermore, as it is even more
and more fully than before the language of
universal life since the spoken word has
been integrated into it, it would be mon¬
strous if words were to give it the coup de
grâce after providing it with the ultimate
means of action.
In silent films, the eye sees through
appearances
Not long ago I watched two old silent
films, which did not have captions.
Although they were unremarkable from
the photographic point of view, they
impressed me by the way in which images
reduced to being self-explanatory suddenly
stand out from the screen. Without
employing exaggerated gestures, the direc¬
tors and actors are compelled, in order to
make themselves understood, to display
constant ingenuity and impassioned intel¬
ligence, combinations of attitudes, hence
requiring the spectator to rise to the level
of attention they call for. Between the
visual quality of the film and its psycho¬
logical interpretation there is a continuous
exchange that captions, and even more the
spoken word, have done away with. It is
the memory of the gestures and expres¬
sions that stays with us, not that of the
plot, and it is the moral significance of the
drama that haunts us and not the story¬
line. A way of closing a door or placing a
soup tureen on a table is far more mean¬
ingful without words explaining the sig¬
nificance of the action. Though fore¬
warned, I was surprised to find I retained
from these films a very different impres¬
sion from that inflicted on us by talking
films or even captioned silent films. A new
world enters into us, the world that held
man's attention before speech and created
speech by a miracle of intuition and energy,
that compels the eye to see through appear¬
ances and seek behind them a meaning that
words, pandering to our laziness, dispense
to us in an arbitrary and indeed often
abstract manner, without demanding the
slightest effort from us.
This shows particularly clearly what
powers of expression the film-maker
deprives himself of when he uses words
either constantly or unwisely. Only the
free arrangement of silence and sound
enables the film-maker to pick and choose
among countless forms of expression. One
silent film, New Year's Evef takes place in
three settings, simultaneously or in turn:
the street, a drinking den and a small bed¬
room where a three-cornered domestic
drama is raging. The street and bar-room
scenes undoubtedly lose much because
their characteristic sounds are missing: in
the first case the muffled noise of crowds,
King Vidor's Hallelujah!
(United States, 1929). From
left to right, Daniel Haynes,
William Fountaine and Nina
Mae McKinney.
cars, cries and footfalls, in the second the
sounds of singing and the clink of glasses,
quarrelling, music, laughter and shouting.
If the film were to be remade, who in their
right minds would deprive themselves of
the dramatic contrasts between the carefree
or joyous character of these scenes and the
silent tragedy which, only a short distance
away and unknown to everyone there, is
wreaking havoc in three hearts ?
The first casualties
Note, incidentally, that the film-maker, the
actor and above all the "producer" are the
first casualties of mistaken interpretations
of the art of the cinema. Spiritual casualties
at any rate, since very few of them realize
that they are leading the cinema to perdi¬
tion and even fewer are worthy of suf¬
fering therefrom. The beauty of the images,
even when one stops one's ears in order to
see them better, seems to diminish from
film to film. Compelled to give almost
undivided attention to the synchroniza¬
tion of sound and image and to guide the
image through the labyrinth of the dia¬
logue, film-makers bother less and less
about its intrinsic quality, which they leave
to the apparatus alone, heedless of the fact
that its chance discoveries need to be helped
by the careful choice of motif and decor,
by raising or lowering the lighting, varying
camera angles to follow movement and ges¬
ture, slowing the pace or speeding it up,
and using double exposure, slow motion
or speeded-up film to stimulate the spec¬
tator's dramatic or lyric imagination. In
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
fact, double exposure and slow motion,
which played a crucial part in the develop¬
ment of our understanding of rhythm and
image, have almost disappeared from the
cinema except, as regards the latter of the
two, in the documentary, which in any case
uses it only for picturesque effect and
seems no longer to understand the aesthetic
value of images that show us objective
proof of the harmonic continuity of
shapes and movements.
The glories of the documentary
We should not, of course, be unduly con¬
cerned about this temporary and partial
setback for the educational virtues of this
admirable apparatus. Although sentimental
or romantic films have taken audiences
whose puerility puts up less and less resis¬
tance too far away from them, we can
still see scientific films, in which powerful
lighting and enormous magnification reveal
to us the hitherto secret life of insects,
crustaceans, molluscs, flowers, seeds, coats
of velvet or satin, the dense, deep glow of
shells, the glittering jewels of suction pads,
the vibration of pistils and of antennas
searching for their prey, the sinuous
waving of tentacles, the diamonds and
opals of scattering air bubbles, and the har¬
monious movements involved in the
dramas of love and hunger. Or else those
accounts of big game hunting in Africa or
Indonesia that show in graphic detail the
tragic truth of the scenes imagined by
artists such as Barye,6 while others show us
the visual subtlety of a Vermeer or a
Velasquez. The arabesque of the muscles of
the python, the furtive gleam of its scales
that allow us to visualize its energy, the
ripple of the coats of the leopard or the
tiger, the darting gleams of teeth and claws,
the splendid sight of skulls or jawbones
shaped by the blending, on the undulating
bone of their surfaces, of the internal forces
of instinct and the external caress of light
on their surface. We are also aware that, in
spiritual matters, each new conquest has
temporarily to be paid for by a retreat, of
greater or lesser duration, from former
conquests. We likewise know that the
cinema is all the more unlikely to be
exempt from this universal law insofar as it
is richer in its resources and more sur¬
prising in the incessant revelations revela¬
tions we are always tempted to exhaust
completely, while ignoring the previous
revelations, from which the wonderment
into which we are cast by each new miracle
detaches us before we have even followed
them through to their ultimate conse¬
quences.
Whenever the subject arises of the
"machine" whose extraordinary develop¬
ment has taken us by surprise, a general
outcry goes up about the new efforts it
demands of our lazy minds. It is neverthe¬
less a human artefact. Its present com¬
plexity should not stand in the way of
spiritual growth. It may even be regarded
as the most encouraging example of the
intervention of the mind in the task of
organizing the world, which has been, since
it began, humanity's specific task. The
charges levelled against the machine are
always the same, that "price to be paid for
progress" which we are unwilling to accept
because we persist in seeing "progress"
from its moral angle and not from its spir¬
itual angle, from where we would see it as a
complex of often antagonistic forces
advancing in fugal style, not as an uninter¬
rupted linear development.
V. INEXHAUSTIBLE
POSSIBILITIES
And so we are compelled to denounce, in
the evolution of this hitherto undreamt-of
achievement of our minds and at the very
time when it is daily producing felicitous
consequences, the false steps that it makes
and that are all the more surprising in that
each of them causes us to stumble at the
threshold of a further advance. An instru¬
ment such as the cinema cannot, however,
degenerate. Like mathematics, it derives its
dynamic concatenations from within itself.
It is one of those great starting-points that
teach man how proud is his dramatic des¬
tiny. Its very universality, which places at its
disposal, for the first time ever, the activities
and genius of all peoples and all human
groups tending in one and the same direc¬
tion, opens boundless possibilities for its
future development. Some of the advances it
has made in our own day more or less at the
same time as sound recording animation
The arabesque
of the muscles of
the python, the
furtive gleam of its
scales. . .
and colour present terrible dangers, but
those dangers will be overcome by their
own power. While it is true that the public's
total lack of visual education threatens, in
both of these cases, to inflict paltry images
upon us, we shall be delivered from their
thrall by the training of an elite of artists
and technicians. As in the great eras of
painting and architecture, it is they and they
alone who must gradually impose their own
vision, their own feeling for rhythm, move¬
ment and colour on wider and wider audi¬
ences, especially if social conditions are pro¬
pitious to the formation and influence of
such audiences.
Fantasy and imagination in cartoon
films
Animation, surely, holds out incomparable
promises. Some American productions have
already offered what may be the richest
prospects that man's poetic genius, always
eager for an atmosphere fresh enough to
clear its lungs and dense enough to keep it
aloft, has glimpsed since the outpouring of
lyricism that covered Italian crypts with
glowing frescoes, poured twilit magic and
floral symphonies into the naves of French
churches where the changing light flooded
in upon the congregation through stained-
glass windows, made English theatres the
setting for the impassioned speeches of
murderers, kings and maidens, the voices of
the tempest and the glitter of the stars, and
spread over the heads of the German
throngs the echoing vaults of cathedrals
whose pillars sprang up from among the
stalls of cobblers, watchmakers, brewers and
smiths forming a great, instinctively inno¬
cent choir of the common people. It is very
moving to observe, in this respect, that it is
America, so disdained by "intellectuals", so
"materialistic", so subservient to "eco¬
nomic" considerations, that, in the sublime
disorder of the modern world, in the course
of this immense act of parturition which
resembles the chemical formation of some
unknown substance in a bubbling crucible
more than some religious or moral drive
towards "idealism", should be offering this
fantastical imagination, this rhythmic verve,
this flame of poetry intoxicated with
freedom, joy, mischief and unflagging
invention.
Have you seen wild flowers, buttercups
and moss joining in with the work of the
tiny insects and the love-making of the
birds, flower-bells ringing for the nightin¬
gale's wedding, dolls marching mechani-
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT
cally to the quacking of ducks, ants and
caterpillars advancing in procession to the
crystalline song of the toads, new-born
maybugs showered with dew from the sta¬
mens of cherry blossom? Considering all
the poetry awakened from these prolifer¬
ating multitudes, hitherto unseen and inert
for most of us and in any case obliged, in
order to reach us, to borrow the language
of words, too symbolic and too inacces¬
sible for the many, what good is there in
pointing out the mistakes of form and the
sometimes shocking clashes of colour that,
with varying degrees of success, the unceas¬
ingly complex enlargement and enrichment
of this new language are bearing forward
towards unheard-of prospects? From these
humble beginnings, we may already look
forward to the emergence of geniuses of
the stamp of Michelangelo, Tintoretto,
Rubens, Goya and Delacroix, who will
thrust forward their internal drama to
meet up with the dramas of space in the
onrush of shapes and movements, by
means of symphonic forms of expression
capable of driving the combination of art,
music and the spoken word ahead into an
ever-receding future
The pitfalls of colour
In this respect too a decisive effort needs to
be made to re-incorporate into the territory
of visual harmony the ground lost through
the onslaught of colour films. It is not
enough to have integrated this great dis¬
covery into the total expression of life that
cinema promises to be, only to imagine that
nothing can be done about it. On the con¬
trary, this achievement demands fresh
efforts to maintain it. "Nature" is in itself
by no means harmonious, as the existence
of painting, an art of elimination and selec¬
tion, amply demonstrates. "Black and
white", with its spontaneous, profound
harmonies of silver and velvet, turning,
appearing and disappearing and with its vol¬
umes in movement, had spoilt us, because it
acts as the interpreter of "value", not colour;
but the mechanical recording of colours is
fraught with the risk of grave miscalcula¬
tions, especially as regards "location"
filming, which gifted and well-intentioned
film-makers are powerless to arrange in an
orderly fashion. The total visual symphony
requires them to organize premeditated har¬
monies of increased complexity by means of
the concerted movements of form, whereby
contrasts and reflections are constantly
brought into play in chiaroscuros, half-
Josef von Sternberg's
Underworld (United
States, 1927) is
considered to be one
of the first gangster
films.
tones and violent lighting and in ever-
changing relationships.
A broad, united effort needs to be
made, and it is to be expected, as indeed we
may foresee from cartoons or even the sim¬
plest films, that the film director of the
future will play a role more akin to that of
the orchestral conductor than to that of the
painter. The slightest works of Disney or
his imitators require the work of numerous
teams of artists, teams that will have to be
strengthened for the great orchestral works
of the future. Legions of set designers,
dancers, costumiers, extras and technicians
of every kind will certainly be recruited too.
These circumstances restore the cinema,
which is still a prey to various kinds of
financial and show-business skulduggery, to
its rightful place in the domain of regener¬
ated communities, and show up clearly its
necessary contradictions with the obstinate
individualism in which our age, in spite of
the directions in which it is irresistibly
headed, remains regrettably bogged down.
VI. THE MISSION
The cinema thus awaits a completely
renewed social terrain. True, it has not yet
fulfilled the promises that architecture, in
times past, kept in relation to the mass of
believers, but that is because its social bases
and the mystical impetus that can only
spring therefrom are still in the process of
formation, and it took architecture several
centuries to attune itself to the emerging
sentiments of which it was, ultimately, the
expression. I know of no worse aesthetic
prejudice than that of thinking that, once
the instrument has been discovered, the
masterpiece will follow of necessity and at
once. It is strange that so many disgruntled
people should criticize the cinema for not
having, by the age of forty, produced the
definitive masterwork, when it is carrying
out within itself the complex and difficult
task of developing its resources, while
those same critics find it quite normal that
Christians should have waited a thousand
years to fulfil the poetic mission promised
by Christianity. If the capital which the
cinema needs more than any other art,
given its gigantically complex organization,
were to remain in the hands of busi¬
nessmen or groups of businessmen having
no other aim, in securing control of it,
than the pursuit of their own interests,
unless capital were to become entirely
social, the cinema would soon join the
ranks of the most degenerate illustrated
periodicals, sentimental stories and so-
called "popular" fiction. It would vanish
altogether as an art form. The weakness of
the cinema is a function of its greatness.
Two dangers
The fact that cinema is and can only be a
collective art, that it lives and develops and
can only live and develop by appealing con¬
stantly to the unanimous voice of the
crowds, requires from all who play a part
in organizing it a continuous effort to
assimilate its advances, and constant
involvement in using to good effect the
revelations it brings. Though we are far
from having reached that situation, though
we even seem to be getting farther and far¬
ther away from it, we are well aware that
history is full of unforeseen but predeter¬
mined reversals. The origins of Chris¬
tianity, for example, have shown us how a
dual spiritual process seemed, at times
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
DOCUMENT
when society was in total anarchy, to lift
the wills and souls of some to precisely the
same extent as the wills and souls of others
declined. The history of early Christianity
bears many similarities to the events
leading up to the society of the present.
The unspeakable depths to which cer¬
tain film-making enterprises have sunk, the
philistinism and vulgarity of the "pro¬
ducers" and retailers of images, the des¬
perate efforts some firms have to make in
order to keep American cinema up to the
level of the inventiveness of its directors
and the prodigious resources in personnel,
equipment and technology they have at
their disposal, the development of Russian
cinema, conscientiously struggling to
remain collectivist and to ward off the
temptations of dialogue and the star
system, the undeniable progress made by
French cinema in recent years, should all
warn us against taking the sombre view
towards which a superficial examination of
the question would seem to incline us.
Although the cinema is at present adrift
between two shoals, those of private
interest and of its permanent partner, plu¬
tocratic demagogy, these two shoals will
sooner or later be submerged by the irre¬
sistible rise of societies towards collective
forms of production that subordinate pri¬
vate interest to the general interest and
gradually push plutocratic demagogy from
the plane of sentimental abstractions,
having "idealistic" education as its instru¬
ment, towards the plane of human realities,
the means to which is psycho-physiolog¬
ical education.
Freedom of expression under threat
An immense task is being carried out, of
which economics is the starting point and
trade unionism, whose goal is to remake
man by means of his functional aptitudes
and his real interests, will be the main organ.
This should ultimately dispel the dangers
that threaten the cinema by re-integrating its
freedom of expression, so firmly cast in the
mould of its mechanical resources, into a
society solidly built around the strict har¬
monic organization of its production.
Everything is interconnected, in disorder as
well as order. This freedom of expression,
constantly hindered and dissipated by
today's social chaos, is threatened not only
by the financial skulduggery and the public
bad taste which it creates and which serves its
ri%\M purpose in a continuing process of give and
take. The state, its police and its censorship
The cinema
is and can only be a
collective art.
act in the service both of this skulduggery
and of this bad taste, thus maintaining the
feeble-mindedness and exaggerated sentimen¬
tality that they need in order to function.
The cinema is tending to become, like
the press and radio, an instrument of domi¬
nation and mindlessness in the service of big
business and of the sham political bodies
that represent it in government. The state,
almost everywhere, is but a pale reflection of
the oligarchies that have gradually taken over
the organizations and individuals capable of
influencing public opinion and making use
of the outdated abstractions whereby it can
so easily be misled for purposes that are
totally unconnected with the public interest
and are indeed increasingly contrary to it, in
all fields. Helped on by mental laziness, the
world would very soon be on the way to
perdition unless an underground movement
of progressive organization, brought about
by the concentration of capital and labour
and by the power of machines more and
more rapidly imposing unity upon
exchanges among different peoples and on
those peoples' reflexes, acted automatically
to construct a new order among the general
anarchy. The cinema, the unwitting victim of
the legal disorder, is one of the most effective
instruments of the emerging real order.
The perfectly attuned orchestra
If this legal disorder were to persist, a pos¬
sibility that in my opinion the organic
growth of all the elements of the real order
should rule out, two schools might well
emerge within the movement that draws
the cinema and society itself towards their
destinies. One of these schools would
address itself to the elite and the other to
the amorphous mass of the majority of
spectators, and there is no doubt that, in
the present state of uncertainty, a split is
appearing that could have deplorable conse¬
quences for the society that is emerging as
well as for the cinema. But the cinema
cannot be untrue to its historic destiny.
No art is more involved with the multi
tude, its needs, its impulses, its joys, its
sufferings and its deeds. It feels its real
presence. Itself a language of movement, it
partakes of the movement of the crowds
that impart their movement to it. Great
political crises are a function of the inner
movement that prevents societies from
dying and manifests itself in commotions
and demonstrations. There is a profound
logic in the evolution of the arts. It was
natural that the reign of painting, now in
decline, should have coincided since the
Renaissance with the reign of the indi¬
vidual to whom it gives expression but
who is now gradually joining the increas¬
ingly vast and urgently required organiza¬
tions that collective needs are constructing.
What is a crowd in turmoil? It is the
hubbub of the assembled orchestra before
the symphony begins. The art of the great
ages is a totalitarian art. Mistakes, it is true,
may occur here and there, but the mosque,
the pagoda or the cathedral together express
the great emotional and lyrical depths that
only the enthusiasm of crowds is capable of
stirring. And the cinema must be mosque,
pagoda and cathedral all rolled into one, a
mosque, a pagoda, a cathedral expanded out
to the ill-defined limits of living, dead or yet
unborn humanity, out as far as the tele¬
scopic or microscopic infinities of form and
movement the perfectly attuned orchestra,
a thousand instruments strong, of sensi¬
bility and intelligence and of the multitudes
in action.
1 The Mark of Zorro (1920), an American film
directed by Fred Niblo, which signalled the birth of a
new kind of cinema hero, played by Douglas Fair¬
banks. (Ed.)
2 Underworld(\927), directed by Josef von Sternberg.
Two gangsters, old friends, become rivals for the love
of the same woman, a story-line that was to become
familiar. (Ed.)
3 I refer only for the record to those silent documen¬
taries (wildlife or travel films), some of them very
lovely, the commentaries of which are nearly always
pointless, often dim-witted, sometimes execrable and
meant only as a sacrifice to the fashion of the
"talkies", and whose only effect is to exasperate those
spectators who like to think that they go to the
cinema to see and appreciate beautiful images. (Ed.)
4 Hallelujah! (1929), an American film directed by
King Vidor, was the first film with an all-black cast. It
was rapturously received by the intelligentsia in
France, where it is regarded as the first historically
important talking picture. (Ed.)
5 New Year's Eve (1923), a German film directed by
Lupu-Pick with a screenplay by Carl Mayer. It is typ¬
ical of a school of cinema {kammerspiel) that entrusts
the whole meaning of the film to the power of the
images and the use of light. (Ed.)
6 Antoine Louis Barye (1796-1875), French artist.
One of the leading sculptors of the 19th century, he
established animal sculpture as a major genre. (Ed.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Egypt through
e looking-glass
Maâda Wasse
Omar Sharif and Faten
Hamama in Salah Abou
Seif's psychological
thriller No Sleep (Egypt,
1957).
The development of
Egyptian cinema has
followed, the vicissitudes
of a nation's life
Magda Wassef is an Egyptian film and
theatre specialist. She is the author of
several studies on cinema including
one, written for Unesco, on "The
cultural heritage in Arab cinema".
ETgyptians have been film fans ever
since 1896 when the first
Lumière shorts were shown in
Alexandria, only a year after
' their projection in Paris. By the
turn of the century there were several cin¬
emas in Cairo and Alexandria, mainly
showing American and European films.
The first entirely Egyptian film was The
Civil Servant (1922), a short feature
directed by Mohamed Baoumi. In spite of
the prevailing climate of misogyny, how¬
ever, the real pioneers of Egyptian cinema
were women such as Aziza Emir, Assia
Dagher and a few others. The tenacious
g
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
ISR STUDIOS
Misr Studios, known as "the Hollywood of the East", were
the first fully equipped modern cinema studios not only in
Egypt but in the Middle East and Africa. Opened in 1935 on
the Avenue of the Pyramids in Giza, less than fifteen kilo¬
metres from Cairo, they were the brainchild of Talaat Harb,
director of the Misri Bank, the first wholly Egyptian bank.
Since 1917 anumbei of studios had been built in Egypt, but
their resources were extremely limited. Talaat Harb sent
Ahmed Badrakhan and Maurice Kassab to France to study
directing and Hassan Mourad and Mohamed Abdelazim to
Germany to study photography. The first film made at Misr
Studios was Wedad, starring the great singer Umm Kulthum
(at centre of poster above). It was a smash hit and was
shown at the 1936 Venice Film Festival. Although Wedad was
co-directed by the German Fritz Kramp, the studios' tech¬
nical advisor, and Gamal Madkour, Misr's next feature, Al
hall el akhir ("The Last Hall", 1937), was made by an
Egyptian, Abdel Fattah Hassan. Most of the important films
made in Egypt between 1935 and 1955 came from Misr Stu¬
dios. Between 1936 and 1960, when the studios were nation¬
alized, 182 features were made there. H
Aziza Emir was both producer and leading
lady of Egypt's first full-length feature,
Leila (1927), which was a smash hit and
launched the Egyptian motion-picture
industry. Notable among the dozen or so
films made in the late 1920s was Mohamed
Karim's Zeinah (1929), an adaptation of
Mohamed Hussein Heikal's novel, the first
in Arab literature.
Early musicals Egyptian talkies of
the early 1930s were strongly influenced
by popular love songs. Mohamed Karim's
The White Rose (1933), starring the great
singer Mohamed Abdel Wahab, entranced a
vast public both in Egypt and abroad. It
made the name of the Egyptian cinema and
introduced it to a new genre, the musical.
Every film-maker had his own singing star.
Mohamed Karim, for example, directed all
Mohamed Abdel Wahab 's films, and Ahmed
Badrakhan directed five of the seven films
starring the famous woman singer Umm
Kulthum. Kamal Selim's Determination
(1939) signalled a move away from these
light-hearted productions. By showing the
life of Cairo slum dwellers, Selim brought a
new, more realistic atmosphere to Egyptian
cinema.
ESCapist films During the Second
World War packaged Hollywood-
inspired musical comedies were all the rage.
Films, studios and cinemas proliferated. The
actress-singer Leila Mourad became Egypt's
Mary Pickford in Egypt's Sweetheart, a role
recreated by Togo Mizrahi in Leila (1942),
the first in a series made over a ten-year
period. Singer Farid El Atrash and dancer
Samia Gamal were a famous double act.
Following in the footsteps of Kamal
Selim, Ahmed Kamel Morsi (The District
Attorney) and Kamel El Telmessani (The
Black Market) set out to deal with contem¬
porary problems. Both these films were
shot in 1943, but neither was shown until
1946 because of a tacit form of censorship.
In 1947 a censorship code along the lines
of the Hays Code in the United States was
officially introduced. Many subjects became
taboo, and as a result specific references to
real-life situations tended to disappear. Puri¬
tanism and conservatism were the pretext
for this.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The revolutionary ferment of the 1940s
was stifled by increasingly repressive mea¬
sures that affected all aspects of cultural life.
Only musicals, comedies and melodramas
were given free rein.
Years Of paradOX New archetypes
emerged after the Nasscrite revolution
in 1952. Patriotic films such as Rodda Kalbi's
Give Me Back My Heart celebrated the rev¬
olution and railed against the old social
values.
Yet a few talented film-makers continued
to explore a realist vein. Among them were
Salah Abu Saif, who took the side of the
most underprivileged, especially women, in
The Leech (1956) and / Am Free (1959);
Henri Barakat, director of the classic Song of
the Curlew (1959); Atef Salem, one of
whose best-known works is We Students
(1959); and Kamal El Sheikh, who made Life
or Death in 1954. Youssef Chahine showed
an instinctive concern for contemporary
problems in films like The Nile's Son (1951)
and Cairo Station (1958).
But important though they were, these
films were only a drop in the ocean of
Egyptian cinema. With an average output of
sixty movies a year, the industry continued
to satisfy the escapist desires of the mass
public and meet producers' and distributors'
demands for profitability. A change of
course only came at the beginning of the
1960s.
Acinema revolution After i96i the
state exercised almost complete control
over the cinema. The size of the private sector
was considerably reduced. For the first time
film-makers were free from the restrictions
imposed by the external market that had
previously held sway.
Ideology began to infiltrate into scripts
and lead them into unexplored territory.
One favourite theme was the world of the
peasantry, which featured in Tewfik Salah 's
pioneering The Heroes' Struggle (1962),
Salah Abu Saif's The Second Wife (1967) and
Youssef Chahine's The Earth (1969). Yet
most of these films only attracted a limited
public, compared with that of films which
gave comic treatment to serious subjects such
as the population explosion and the equality
of the sexes.
Youssef Chahine's
Central Station (Egypt,
1958). The director
plays a newspaper
vendor, and Hind
Rostom a fruit-juice
salesgirl.
Mohamed Karim's Vive 1'amour
(Egypt, 1938), a musical starring
singer Mohamed Abdel Wahab
and Laila Mourad.
Mohamed Khan's
The Wife of an
Important Man
(Egypt, 1988).
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Kamal Selim's
Determination (Egypt,
1939), the first major
Egyptian realist film.
Kamal El Sheikh (The Thief and the
Dogs, 1962) and Salah Abu Saif (Cairo 30,
1969) were among a number of film-makers
who were sympathetic to the social insights
of Naguib Mahfouz (Nobel Prize winner
for literature in 1988) and adapted several of
his works to the screen. But the ideals and
structures of Nasserism collapsed with
defeat in the Six-Day War of 1967.
Rejection and renewal The ten¬
sion was relaxed by success in the war of
1973. Nasserite protectionism was replaced
by the economic liberalism of Anwar El
Sadat. The State Broadcasting Authority,
hitherto responsible for production and dis¬
tribution, was dismantled, and there was a
return to the law of the market-place. Shadi
Abdel Salam, who had directed The
Mummy in 1968 in exceptional conditions,
tried for fifteen years to make Akhenaton,
but in vain.
Ali Badrakhan's El Karnak and Mam-
douh Shukri's The Dawn Visitors, both
made in 1975, harshly criticized the excesses
of the Nasser regime. A new generation of
film-makers, trained at the Cairo Film Insti¬
tute, came on the scene and showed with
uncompromising realism the explosion of
free-wheeling capitalism in a society where
social climbing has become an ideal.
Violence and mockery After the
sensational assassination of Sadat in
1981, violence became the keynote of the
first half of the 1980s. Some twenty films
that came out in 1983 alone ended with the
murder of a corrupt person. On screen pop¬
ular justice exacted revenge in Samir Saif's
The Monster and Saad Arafa's Marzouka.
Discontent also gave rise to mockery, a
favourite Egyptian form of expression
whose symbolic figure in cinema is the actor
Adel Imam. A typical film in this vein was
Raafat El Mini's The Lawyer. Some films
took on the subjects of sex and drugs.
Actress Nadia El Guindi became their muse
after appearing in Hossam El Din Mostafa 's
El Bateneya (198Q).
Several directors brought new life to the
cinema during these years. Among them
were Atef El Tayeb (The Innocent), Raafat
El Mini (The Last Love Story), Mohamed
Khan (The Wife of an Important Man),
Kha'iri Beshara (Bitter Day, Sweet Day),
Mounir Radin (Days of Anger) and Hani
Lashine (The Puppet Player).
In the 1990s the Egyptian film industry
is again in thrall to a paradox. On the one
hand, output is declining (barely twenty
films were made in 1994) and unemploy¬
ment is rising. On the other, film quality
and viewing facilities are improving (cinemas
are being renovated). Satellite has revolution¬
ized the audiovisual landscape (for worse
rather than better).
Fortunately a director of the quality of
Youssef Chahine is still making films. Others,
including Mohamed Khan and Atef El
Tayeb, who emerged in the 1980s, are contin¬
uing to show their originality. Bright new
talents such as Sherif Arafa, Yousry Nas-
rallah, Asma El Bakri and Khaked El Hagar
are showing great promise.
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
interview
Tomás Gutiérrez
Alea
Cuban director Tomás
Gutiérrez Alea, whose film
Strawberry and Chocolate
(1994) won the Silver Bear
award at the 1994 Berlin
Festival.
Tomás Gutiérrez Alea's
Strawberry and
Chocolate (Cuba,
1994), starring Jorge
Perugorria as the artist
(right) and Vladimir
Cruz as the student.
> Your latest film,
Strawberry and
Chocolate, tells about an
encounter between a
homosexual intellectual
and a member of the Cuban
communist youth
movement. Where did you
get the idea of looking at
the problem of
homosexuality in Cuba?
I read Senel Paz's* original story in
manuscript. What I wanted to show in
the film, and what I believe, is that the
problem is broader than just homo¬
sexuality. It's the idea of tolerance and
accepting other people. Basically the
film is the story of a youth, David, who
learns to become a man by tran¬
scending his limited vision of reality
when he comes into contact with a
social outcast.
> Were you surprised by the
film's success in Cuba?
I sincerely thought people would
like it because it's a moving human
story with a fair share of humour, and
because I was satisfied with my work.
But its success went beyond my
expectations.
But your film is pretty
hard on life in Cuba. At the
end your hero, Diego, even
decides to emigrate.
Weren't you afraid of
being labeled an "enemy of
the revolution"?
To my mind a society can go for¬
ward only if it is aware of its errors and
failings. Criticism is an ideal revolu¬
tionary weapon.
I How do you see your work
as a film-maker in a
nationalized system
compared to your
colleagues in Europe and
the United States?
Each system has its pros and cons.
|
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
But I would like to say that Cuban
cinema isn't a typical "state-run"
cinema. It is true that to make films you
have to go through the government-
controlled Cuban Film Institute. But the
Institute is run by open-minded cre¬
ators, not by civil servants. It Is not like
some other bureaucracies with which it
is more difficult to work. Here the state
monopoly on production may tend to
limit creative development, while under
a capitalist regime there is a risk that
producers who are only interested in
profits will go for sex-and-violence for¬
mula movies. On the other hand, it is
true that the absence of a monopoly
encourages the existence of indepen¬
dent directors and producers.
I Is there a crisis in the
Latin American cinema?
Latin American cinema is in a state
of permanent crisis because it is not in
control of distribution. Our films are
seen less in Latin America than in
Europe and even in the United States!
Cuba is an exception to the rule
with its Latin American Film Festival
and our San Antonio de los Baños
film school, which takes students
from all over Latin America. In addi¬
tion, the Cuban revolution has always
insisted on the importance of close
cultural ties with the rest of the conti-
Riccardo Larrain's La
frontera (Chile, 1991).
Luis Puenzo's The
Official Story (Argentina,
1984).
nent. In Cuba you can see films from
Argentina, Mexico, Venezuela and
other Latin American countries, but
we are virtually the only country in that
position because the major distribu¬
tion circuits are controlled by transna¬
tional companies linked to the inter¬
ests of Hollywood producers.
But doesn't a fascination
with Hollywood also enter
into it?
It's true that American producers
have substantial resources at their dis¬
posal, but they also know how to
make attractive films and sell them
admirably. Good films, important films,
are also made elsewhere, but no one
can see them. When someone tells
me that if a film hasn't been suc¬
cessful it's because it isn't commercial,
I say, "Start by showing it in normal
conditions."
This doesn't mean competing with
Hollywood in special effects. We've
got to offer something else, another
kind of cinema that doesn't depend
on violence, special effects and the
sensational. Let's take advantage of
streamlined technical equipment to
make inexpensive quality films. That
can be done anywhere.
I Which film tradition do
you belong to?
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Barravento (The
Turning Wind, Brazil,
1962), the first feature
film by Glauber Rocha
(1938-1981).
Our cinema is the heir of Italian
neorealism. After the.war we in Latin
America saw films shot with rudimen¬
tary equipment, sometimes even on
worn-out film stock, films like The
Bicycle Thief or Open City, which
broke away from the Hollywood pro¬
ductions we had got used to. It was a
Fernando
Solanas's El Sur
(Argentina,
1988).
revelation, and we took to it very
quickly. It enabled us to solve the
problem of our still faltering film
industry, i.e. how to make films with
the resources at our disposal that
expressed our personality yet still
strove for the universal. So neorealism
was the starting point for all of us.
This doesn't mean that we are making
neorealist pictures today. That was a
moment in the history of the cinema, a
productive episode which has led on
to other things.
As for me, I think I am making more
analytical films, but I don't deny my
debt of gratitude, or my admiration, for
my neorealist teachers. I have also
been influenced by other film-makers
such as Luis Buñuel, to whom I feel
close in so many ways, and Jean-Luc
Godard with whom I find it harder to
identify but who has given me several
keys to cinematic expression.
* El lobo, el bosque y el hombre nuevo ("The
Wolf, the Woods and the New Man"), winner of
the Juan Rulfo Latin American Short Story
Prize, 1991.
|
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
Mexican melodrama
Jose Carlos Avella
Nostalgia for traditional
melodrama is having surprising
effects on Mexican cinema today
MARIA ROJO JOSE ALONSO
1^,-^.L.í JAIME HUMBERTO HERMOSIILO
Right, María Rojo and José Alonso in Jaime
Humberto Hermosillo's La Tarea (Homework,
Mexico, 1990). Above, a poster for the film.
Jaime Humberto Hermosillo's film La
Tarea (1990, Homework) is a good
starting point for a look at modern
Mexican cinema. The viewer's first
reaction is whether the film really is
"cinema": it consists of a single shot from an
immobile camera that films two characters
who talk incessantly and sometimes disap¬
pear off-screen. It seems more like a piece of
theatre or television than a motion picture.
However, as a result of the skilful use of a
simple set and a dramatic construction that
fits into the solid tradition of studio filming,
the viewer soon realizes that the immobility
is deceptive and that the film has a dynamic of
its own.
The set consists of an apartment with cor¬
ridors, a front hall and a bathroom adjacent
to the room we see through the camera's eye.
Off screen but integrated into the action, the
viewer imagines the existence of a half-open
window through which shadows and noises
sometimes penetrate from the street outside.
In other words, the setting is not limited to
what can be seen on the screen. The outside
world has not disappeared.
The viewer is immediately presented with a
conundrum: why is the camera in this specific
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
the remake
spot? At the start of the film we see a woman
put a video camera under the table, facing the
entrance door. We don't know why she does
this, but it is a way of getting us interested in
what she is up to. We have been let into what is
clearly a secret to the man who now enters the
room and is invited by the woman to sit down
on the carpet. We smile at her efforts to keep
the man in the frame and at the man's awkward
movements as he tries to remain natural. Grad¬
ually we become accomplices in a game between
the two characters, each of whom seems to be
hiding something from the other.
Part of the secret is revealed about halfway
through the story. Virginia, a student of
cinema, is making a film with her former
boyfriend, Marcelo, who doesn't know what
is going on. She has hidden the camera under
the table to comply with her teacher's insis¬
tence that she should make a film using a
single camera angle, cinéma-vérité style. As the
subject of her film, she has decided to get
Marcelo to talk about the problems in his
love-life. When he notices the camera, he loses
his temper and storms off. But there is a
twist in the story. Marcelo comes back. He
has decided to play himself and to act as if he
does not know he is being filmed.
Dolores del Rio
and Pedro Armendariz
in a scene from
Emilio Fernandez's
María Candelaria
(Mexico, 1943), a
melodramatic treatment
of peasant life.
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
Jorge Fons 's El callejón
de los milagros (Mexico,
1994), based onJlíidag
Alley, a novel by the
Egyptian writer Naguib
Mahfuz.
Yet it is only at the end that the whole
truth comes out. Virginia's real name is not
Virginia, but Maria. Marcelo is actually José,
her husband, who is helping her make a film
for her cinema class.
Eloquent tears The question raised
by this film and what interests me here is
that cinema is not what is seen but the way
in which it is seen. The viewer discovers the
point of view of the person behind the
camera, i.e. either the director or an invented
character. The showing of a film is an occa¬
sion in space and time for an encounter
between the perspectives of the director and
the viewer.
La Tarea is entirely based on this rela¬
tionship. The camera is in fact caricaturing
the point of view of a specific viewer in the
history of the Latin American cinema, the
person who saw the melodramas made by
Mexican film-makers between the mid-1930s
and the late 1950s. These melodramas
brought to the screen a popular narrative
style that Mexicans have always loved and
that is reflected in political cartoons in the
newspapers, in radio serials, popular songs
and music, in national holidays such as 2
November (the day of the dead) and in the
grandiose tragic style of mural paintings. A
good story has to be a tear-jerker.
The major studios (where the Mexican
film industry was born) were ideal places for
making these film melodramas. There it was
possible to create the kind of private world,
tenuously connected with what is going on
outside, that is evoked by the small room in
La Tarea. In this magical setting demigods,
prisoners of a tragic destiny, suffer life's mis¬
fortunes on behalf of the viewer, who
watches what happens on screen like Her¬
mosillo's watching camera, without really
sharing in the characters' suffering. The
viewer is present at a ritual in which crying
becomes a pleasure.
The road to realism Then, in the
early 1960s, Mexican cinema changed.
Under the influence of television news, doc¬
umentary films and Italian neorealism, film¬
makers tried hard to cut loose from the nar¬
rative style of the studios. New ways of
storytelling appeared. Film-makers went out
into the streets with hand-held cameras, to
film what they saw, to look critically at
social problems and transmit images from
real life. All subjects, even non-realistic ones,
were treated in documentary style. Shooting
was done out of doors, in daylight.
But films made in this period are far
from escaping the "grammar" of studio
film-making, which abandons the strait-
jacket of visible reality for the realm of the
imagination. Films may have been shot in
natural settings, but the framing and the
photography in black and white (softening
lines with filters) tended to produce images
that were closer to dreams than reality.
Today we are witnessing a return to Mex¬
ican melodrama but in a revamped form
enriched by new cinema languages that have
appeared in Latin America since the 1960s.
Mexican film-makers are analysing melodrama
of the 1940s and 1950s with eyes that have
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Arturo Ripstein's
La reina de la noche
("The Queen of the
Night", Mexico, 1994).
seen militant films, Brazilian Cinema novo,
Argentine Tercer cine, Cuban Cine imper¬
fecto and Bolivian Cine junto alpueblo.
Old Wine in new bottles Melo¬
drama is blooming again. In Alfonso
Arau's Como Agua Para Chocolate (1991,
Like Waterfor Chocolate), young Tita cannot
marry Pedro because tradition says that she
must stay at home and look after her mother,
and so Pedro marries Tita's sister in order to
be near his beloved. In Dana Rotberg's film
Angel de Fuego (1992, Angel of Fire), set in
a circus, a father and his daughter hide their
incestuous love. The narrative style has
changed radically, however. Francisco Athié's
Lolo (1993), the story of young working-class
children on the fringes of society, is a blend of
classic Mexican melodrama and Italian neore¬
alism. Fernando Sariñana's Hasta Morir (1994,
To the Death) adopts an expressionist
approach to a similar theme.
This, then, is no return to past forms but a
sort of constructive, creative criticism of the
old melodramatic principle through films that
differ widely in style and inspiration. Such
films include documentaries like Arturo Rip¬
stein's Principio y fin (1993, "Beginning and
End"); science fiction like Guillermo del
Toro's Cronos (1993); political essays with
militant overtones like Jorge Fons's Rojo
amanecer (1989, Red Dawn) and El Callejón
de los Milagros (1994, "Miracle Lane"); and
cartoons like Carlos Carrera's El Héroe (1994,
"The Hero") in which a young woman who
wants to kill herself pretends that the man
who saves her has attacked her; when he is in
the hands of the police, she calmly prepares
again to take her life. Other examples are come¬
dies like Jaime Humberto Hermosillo's La
Tarea described above and Intimidades en un
Cuarto de Baño (1990, Intimacy in a Bath¬
room). The melodramatic structure, a distinc¬
tive way of looking at the world, varies from
one narrative style to another.
"We didn't do it on purpose," said
Arturo Ripstein about his latest film. "We
didn't say, 'Now we're going to make a
melodrama', as if we had to, but wc are all
children of our time and place, and we all
belong to a generation which was brought
up on and fed by the cinema and whose lives
are shaped by cinematographic images."
These films are indeed the fruit of almost
half a century of Latin American cinema.
This reworking of studio melodrama
reflects the feeling, very strongly held in
Latin America, that political, economic and
cultural life is melodramatic by nature. The
current state of the cinema is ample proof of
this. It seems clear that the market for films
is increasingly restricted to products from
the major audiovisual industries, to films
that resemble video games and vice versa. The
production and above all the distribution of
our films meet so many obstacles that we
fear we may, tragically, become foreigners in
our own land. In such circumstances a return
to melodrama also reflects a desire to make
closer contact with the public by using a
familiar, albeit reworked, language. It speaks
of a certain nostalgia for the days when the
Mexican cinema felt at home in Mexico and
elsewhere in Latin America.
José Carlos Avellar,
Brazilian cinema
historian and critic, is
secretary of the
International Federation
of the Cinematographic
Press for Latin America.
He is a board member of
Riofilme, a Brazilian film
distribution company.
Among his published
works are Le Cinéma
brésilien ("The Brazilian
Cinema", Centre
Georges Pompidou,
Paris, 1987).
M
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
i n t e r v i e
Nagisa Oshima
Japanese director Nagisa Oshima (right) won an
international reputation with In the Realm of the Senses
(1975). Many of his films, such as Merry Christmas,
Mr. Lawrence (198S) and Max mon amour (1986), have a
compulsive, disturbing quality.
> At this year's Cannes Film
Festival you presented a
work entitled 100 Years of
Japanese Cinema. Has the
cinemareally existed in
Japan for a hundred years?
Yes. At first French technicians
went there to shoot documentary
footage. Then the Japanese, with
their usual appetite for things from
abroad, ordered cameras and began
filming, Kabuki theatre to start with.
Production soon diversified, and the
history of the Japanese film industry
began in earnest.
> What is the leitmotiv of this
history?
I think Japanese directors have
been trying to get closer to freedom
in the last hundred years. In any case
that's how I see it.
> What do you mean by
"freedom"?
The greatest barrier to development
in Japan has always been our family
system. The very special power
bestowed upon the father is a throw¬
back to feudalism that was enshrined
in law even after Japan was opened
up in the Meiji period. The power of
the father has permeated the Japanese
social fabric, spreading into business
Wï"'
v
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
and even the army. Presidents of com¬
panies used to have, and sometimes
still have today, exhorbitant power that
turns their employees into children,
devoid of any responsibility, of any
adult feelings.
Any rebellion against this deeply
entrenched system was regarded as
extremely, Intolerably evil. The most
varied examples of this rebellion have
long been portrayed in Japanese
cinema. Even during the Second
World War our cinema dealt with
oppression by fathers both within
and outside the family.
I Did the law change after the
war?
The old system was abolished. All
the members of a family now enjoy
equal rights, as they do in the West.
But the system is so old that it has
Nagisa Oshima's The
Ceremony (Japan, 1971).
Akira Kurosawa's Ran (Japan, 1985), a
Japanese version of Shakespeare's
King Lear.
M
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
Akira Kurosawa's Rhapsody in August
(Japan, 1991).
survived nevertheless. For fifteen to
twenty years the Japanese cinema
continued to struggle against out¬
moded attitudes. It was only after
1960 that a new generation of film¬
makers, of which I am a member,
sought to make a different kind of
film, with the break-up of the family as
a backdrop. But at that time the film
industry was starting to decline.
> Because of television?
The rise of television in Japan had
a lot to do with it, as it has every¬
where else. In 100 Years of Japanese
Cinema, I included a scene from a film
of the period where you see an entire
family sitting round a big table
watching TV. They no longer have a
centre, a focal point; conviviality has
gone. The television set was more
than a match for the father figure.
> The feudal code was wiped
out?
Precisely. A generation of young
people emerged without any land¬
marks. They were utterly lost; they
didn't even know who to fight. They
were no longer confronted by a wall.
They even found it hard to communi¬
cate because opposition is a basic
form of communication. More and
more, and this is the case in Japan
today, you see young people turned
In on themselves, in a kind of autistic
condition. And naturally this attitude is
recorded in modern Japanese cinema.
> Did your film In the Realm
of the Senses (1976)
Yasujiro Ozu's / Was Born,
But... (Japan, 1932)
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
Akira Kurosawa's Kagemusha/The
Shadow Warrior (Japan, 1980)
Yuko Tanaka in Onimaru (Japan, 1987),
Yoshishge Yoshida's version of
Wu thering Heigh ts.
provoke sharp reactions in
Japan?
No. Nor did Merry Christmas, Mr.
Lawrence (1 982). We were expecting
violent reactions from Japanese ex-
servicemen. But films, works of art in
general, don't have a big effect on
Japanese society. I think Japanese
society is devoid of reaction. The only
hardnosed response came from the
police. The film was shot discreetly in
Japan, but it was edited and post-
produced in France. Its producer,
Anatole Dauman, was French.
To show the film in Japan there¬
fore, we had to import it. And then
the Japanese customs got in on the
act. They demanded and obtained
cuts, which also partially explains the
indifference of the public. This atti¬
tude on the part of the customs offi¬
cials was absurd, a real abuse of
power, because it had nothing to do
with them. But that's how it was.
Even the book, with photos from the
film, was banned. But I sued them; it
lasted seven years, and I won in the
end.
I Are the Japanese
puritanical?
They weren't at first. There was
great freedom of expression. But with
the arrival of Confucianism, Bud¬
dhism and Christianity things
changed, at least superficially. Deep
down, society is still not shocked by
sex. I think it is interesting that it was
women above all who defended In
the Realm of the Senses. Women
accounted for 60 per cent of the box-
office receipts.
I Is the censorship changing?
It is changing for the better, it is
becoming more liberal, if you don't
push it too hard. Things are
changing slowly but surely. On the
other hand, any overt rebellion imme¬
diately brings a reaction, an exagger¬
ated oppression.
I Should the cinema violate
taboos?
g
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
Shohei Imamura's Hogs and
Warships or 77¡e Flesh Is Hot
(Japan, 1961).
That's a question I am often
asked. I think that a film, like any work
of art, is not made for a specific
reason. A work of art is made without
any kind of certainty. It is produced in
fear, apprehension and doubt. It isn't
a purposeful, deliberate undertaking
that knows exactly where it is going.
It doesn't want to "express" any¬
thing. It is always possible that it may,
incidentally, offend certain taboos,
but that is not the aim.
After defeat in 1945, how
did Japan receive the
American cinema?
Very well. There was a kind of
hunger for it, even! We were hungry,
literally hungry. And American movies
were more than just movies. They
were like food. That lasted for a long
time. Even if we were opposed to the
United States and the Americaniza¬
tion of Japan, we were passionately
keen on American films. It is true that
they showed us things that for us
were incredible. Scenes of victory cel¬
ebrations, for example.
> Is the Japanese cinema
facing problems today?
It's going through a difficult
period, but I'm an inveterate optimist.
A critic once said something to me
that pleased me very much. He said,
"You are the only Japanese to talk
simultaneously of Japan, the whole
world and yourself." It's true that for a
long time our great film-makers talked
of nothing but Japan. Japanese films
seemed focused inwards on Japan.
It's also true that young film-makers
today talk only about themselves.
But that too will pass. The world is
immense. A synthesis of one kind or
another is always possible.
I Are you contributing to it?
I hope so. After Max, Mon Amour
I worked for more than four years on a
project that didn't come to anything. It
was about California in the 1 920s and
the relationship between the
Japanese actor Sessue Hayakawa
and Rudolph Valentino. It was a com¬
plicated story, involving their wives.
The film was called off one month
before we were due to start shooting.
At present I am still hosting my pro¬
gramme on Japanese television
almost every day. I talk with my guests
about culture, politics, society, even
the sects. I am living completely in the
present. And of course, I'm already
thinking of another film.
I How do you get on with
American film
technicians?
Excellently. I have often worked
with my old friend Mirek Hondricek,
a Czech cameraman, both because
of his great talent and because we
know one another well. But Amer¬
ican film crews are remarkable. I
would also mention Americans' love
of the cinema and their willingness
to lend a hand. To shoot the huge
demonstration scene in Washington
for Hair I appealed through the press
for unpaid extras. Thousands of
people turned up, all dressed in
period clothes and all full of enthu¬
siasm. Thanks to them the scenes
are really convincing. I wonder if
you'd find such enthusiasm in other
countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
The famous
Italian actor
Marcello
Mastroianni (at
left, with
Federico
Fellini) has
appeared in
over 80 films.
He has
received Best
Actor awards
at the Cannes
and Venice
Film Festivals.
interview
Marcello
Mastroianni
What is your first memory
of the cinema?
The first film I can remember seeing
was Ben Hur* My family and I were
living in Turin, where we had emi¬
grated from southern central Italy. It
was in about 1930 I must have
been six at the time. The images of
that spectacular film made a great
impression on me. I've never for¬
gotten it. I think it must have been
dubbed into Italian. Foreign films were
never released in their original version
in Italy. They were always dubbed.
I When did you decide to
make a career in the
cinema?
It wasn't something I consciously
decided to do. After living in Turin, we
moved to Rome. My grandfather had
six sons, all of whom lived in Rome.
When I was young, between ten and
fifteen, say, there wasn't much spare
cash to keep us amused. We were
short of money. We made our own
toys slings, for instance.
At that time the place where young
people got together wasn't the local
dance hall but the church. We weren't
particularly attracted by religion. We
went there because the local parish
had a football pitch and we had to
sing in the choir. There was a little the¬
atre in the basement of our church in
Rome. The priest wrote Christian
plays. That's where I first began to act.
I continued to do so at school, then at
university, where I studied architec¬
ture. 'We did amateur dramatics and
put on American and Italian plays. We
weren't all that bad.
Chance had a hand in what hap¬
pened next. We put on Angelica, a
play by an Italian anti-Fascist author,
Leo Ferrera. I got the part of Orlando,
and Angelica was played by Federico
Fellini's wife, Giulietta Masina. It was
particularly nice of her to take part in
our production as she was already a
star. Critics and theatre people took
the trouble to come and see the play.
One of them was the general manager
of the largest Italian theatre company
of the time, whose director was
Luchino Visconti. He came to see me
after the show and asked if I'd ever
thought of turning professional. He
was looking for a leading man.
It was shortly after the war. I was
twenty-six. My father had gone blind,
g
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
and I had to support my mother and
the rest of the family. "I have responsi¬
bilities," I told the man. "How much
were you thinking of paying me?" He
told me I first had to see Mr. Visconti. I
knew Visconti, but wasn't in the habit
of going to the theatre. We preferred
to go and see films with Gary Cooper
and John Wayne. I liked acting in
plays, but not going to see them. I dis¬
covered real theatre when I joined Vis¬
conti 's company. My career took off
quickly. The first play I acted in was
Tennessee Williams's A Streetcar
Named Desire, and the second,
Arthur Miller's Death of a Salesman.
At first I didn't dare tell my mother I
had given up my office job. It would
have sent her into a panic. I continued
to leave home every morning at 7.30,
as though I was going to the office.
But after a month I took the bull by the
horns and told her the truth. She was
very happy. That was when I really
started my career as an actor. I invited
my father to the show. We gave him a
special chair. He was very moved to
hear his son acting in a play. That's
how I started my career in the most
traditional way imaginable.
Marcello Mastroianni with Nastassia
Kinski in Alberto Lattuada's Stay as You
Are (Italy, 1978).
I How did you come to meet
Federico Fellini?
I had already played in a Visconti
film, White Nights, which was based
on a Dostoevski short story, with
Maria Schell, who was a European
star at the time. And during the ten
years I spent with Visconti's company
I'd had occasion to work with Fellini.
One day somebody came to tell me
that Fellini wanted to see me in Rome.
He had already made some wonderful
films. So I went along. He was on the
beach with his scriptwriter, the author
Ennio Flaiano. He told me he wanted
to make a film with Paul Newman. So
as not to steal the limelight from the
American actor, he needed some
pretty ordinary-looking guy to play
alongside him and had thought of
me. I replied that I was ready and
willing, but ventured to ask if I could
glance at the screenplay. He said that
was perfectly possible and called to
his scriptwriter, who was lying under
another parasol. He gave me a folder.
When I opened it, all there was inside
was a drawing Fellini was always
drawing things which depicted a
swimmer whose penis went right
down to the bottom of the sea. And
there were lots of women swimming
around it, like in an Esther Williams
aquatic movie. I went crimson with
embarrassment and said: "Yes, it looks
very interesting. Where do I sign?"
After that I never asked Fellini for a
screenplay. I made five films with him.
There was a great bond of friendship
and complicity between us. Fellini
was not just a great director, but a
true artist. If he hadn't been a film¬
maker, I think he would have been a
great writer.
Working with him was constant
fun and games. Everything was
turned into a lark or a joke. He liked to
work on actors in the same way he
would have worked dough. You had
to come before him like a naked child,
and then he would have fun with you.
He used to have enormous fun, even
with the bit actors he would go and
choose in the streets of Naples. The
Neapolitans are a way-out lot, even to
look at, and they have a very peculiar
mentality. If they couldn't say their
lines, Fellini didn't care. He'd say:
"Come on now, say one, two, three.
Laugh now! Laugh!" Then he post-
synched them. It was extraordinary:
with Fellini it was cinema non-stop.
Fellini was demanding, but he
never lost his phenomenal sense of
humour. It was a tremendous privilege
to work with him, even greater than
the privilege of appearing in films that
have gone down as masterpieces in
the history of the cinema. I have to
admit that I felt jealous when he made
films in which I didn't appear.
> Did you have an equally
friendly relationship with
any other Italian
director?
There was certainly friendship, but
never the same complicity that existed
between me and Fellini. We were like
schoolboys or army pals who
couldn't stop playing the fool. I've
had many director friends Ettore
Scola, Marco Ferreri and many others
I've worked with and greatly liked. But
there was something unique between
me and Fellini.
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
I Has your work with non-
Italian directors enlarged
your experience?
No. But I'd like to say something
that women directors may find a bit
silly. I find that women in that profes¬
sion, which has always been a man's
profession, feel somehow grateful to
male actors who agree to be directed
by them and have confidence in them.
So women directors tend to adopt a
maternal, protective attitude towards
them. That's my feeling anyway.
Every time I've worked with a
woman director, even if we weren't
friends, and even if it was just for one
film, she has looked after me like a
mother and cared about details that
would not have occurred to any male
director.
I People sometimes say that
the cinema isn't what it
used to be. What do you
think?
Yes, that's true. But I remember my
mother always saying that the world
wasn't what it used to be. It's true: the
world changes, people change, times
change, and one can't go on doing
things the way they were done in the
Marcello Mastroianni
and Anita Ekberg in
Federico Fellini 's La Dolce
Vita (Italy, 1960).
past. Nowadays, there might no
longer be a slot for a guy like Fellini.
People always say things were better
in the old days, but only when they
are forty or fifty years old.
t Even young people who
are interested in the
cinema say the same
thing. They think the
cinema has less freedom
than it used to have.
Look at Russia, where I've shot
two films. When film-makers there
could not express themselves freely,
they made good films. Ever since
they've been free, they have failed to
produce anything of note. Perhaps
it's because of the Americans. In the
old days, when I went to work in what
used to be the Soviet Union, I was
welcomed and I'm not being big-
headed like a star. Why? Because
the authorities didn't allow American
films in. It was above all the Italian
cinema that people were familiar with,
because of its social concerns. Now
all they go for are American films. The
competition is very stiff. It must also be
said that the conquest of a freedom
for which they were not prepared cre¬
ated a kind of vacuum. Before, they
were forced to make an effort to put
across certain ideas through the
medium of film. They had to work
hard to fool the censors.
But there's a crisis everywhere in
Italy and Germany too. I think we need
to be vigilant about the dangers of
television. Even stars no longer have
the same aura. They've lost their
stature, as Fellini used to say. In the
old days, you'd see a giant Marilyn
Monroe on a cinema screen; nowa¬
days she's a tiny figure on television.
Going to the cinema was a kind of
enthralling religious ceremony: the
lights would go down, the spectators
would enjoy the showing together,
then they would come out and have a
drink and talk about the film.
Television is a wonderful invention,
but it fosters loneliness, prevents
people from going to the cinema and
encourages them to stay at home.
Because of television, people read
much less than they used to.
t Do you believe in the
future of the European
cinema?
Of course I would like to. I'd like
there to be a European cinema. But
are governments going to do any¬
thing to help that wonderful idea of a
European cinema? There are home¬
grown films that fail to get released
because the cinemas are full of Amer¬
ican movies. It's unfair. But it's also, in
my opinion, unfair on the American
public. Just think how many fine
European films they have been pre¬
vented from seeing. I find this cultural
compartmentalization regrettable in a
world that has become so small.
" Ben Hur (1925), an American film directed by
Fred Niblo, which contains some spectacular
sequences and is one of the most famous films
of the silent era. {Ed.)
|
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
Mussolini's statement that
"cinema is the strongest
weapon" dominates the
inauguration of Cinecittà in
1937.
Cinecittà
The U.S director Mervyn
LeRoy's blockbuster
Quo Vadis? (1951)
being shot at Cinecittà.
rancesco Bono
The roller-coaster history of the
legendary Italian studios
tea
Francesco Bono,
an Italian film critic, is a
specialist in the cinema
of northern and central
Europe. Among his
published works are
Dansk Film (1993,
"Danish Film") and (as
co-editor) Nordic
Television History,
Politics andAesthetics
(1994).
During the night of 26 September
1935, a terrible fire destroyed the
Rome studios of Cines, then
Italy's biggest film company. It
was immediately decided to
build a new "cinema city" called Cinecittà.
The creation of Cinecittà was part of a
wide-ranging plan to promote the Italian
cinema implemented by the Fascist regime
from the beginning of the 1930s onwards.
To encourage production, it was decided in
1931 to institute a state subsidy system
whereby all Italian films would receive a 10
per cent bonus on their takings. In 1932 the
Venice International Film Festival was estab¬
lished; it remains one of the most important
such events in the world. In 1935 the film
school, Centro Sperimentale di Cine¬
matografía, went into operation. The cinema
was intended to promote the image of the
regime both at home and abroad. Mussolini
proclaimed the cinema to be "the strongest
weapon".
After building work lasting a mere 475
days on a site near Rome, Cinecittà was inau¬
gurated by II Duce on 28 April 1937. Italy's
replica of Hollywood was intended to mark
the beginning of a new era in the Italian
cinema. Between 1937 and 1939, some sixty
films were made at the studios by some of
Italy's finest directors and actors, from
Alessandro Blasetti and Roberto Rossellini
to Alida Valli and Vittorio DeSica. At the
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
beginning of the 1940s, over 100 films a year
were being made in Italy.
With the fall of Fascism in 1943, film
production came to a halt. German troops
smashed and looted the studios, which were
bombed by the Allies the following year. At
the end of the war, the only place where
films could be shot was in the streets: this
marked the beginning of the unique period
of neorealism.
HOllywOOd-On-Tiber But Cinecittà
rose from the ashes and became a veri¬
table legend, which from 1951 on spread
from Italy throughout the world. With the
help of a favourable exchange rate and cheap,
high-quality labour, the Americans took
over Cinecittà. The studios became an ideal
place to shoot the superproductions with
which Hollywood was trying to answer the
challenge of television. The first director to
come to Cinecittà from the United States
was Henry King, who shot Prince of Foxes
there with Tyrone Power and Orson Welles.
Two years later Mervyn LeRoy made Quo
Vadis? with Robert Taylor and Deborah
Kerr.
By the mid-1950s Cinecittà swarmed
with big international stars like Gregory
Peck, Rock Hudson, Ava Gardner, Elizabeth
Taylor, Kirk Douglas, John Wayne, Audrey
Hepburn and Jennifer Jones. Their high
jinks, brawls and love affairs were the talk of
the town. But American film-makers also
gave Cinecittà a strong sense of profession¬
alism and organization. It took Joseph L.
Mankiewicz two weeks to shoot the tri¬
umph scene in Cleopatra. The chariot race in
William Wyler's Ben Hur required three
months' work. The Egyptian port of
Alexandria was entirely reconstructed in
Torre Astura, a few kilometres from Rome.
In all, Hollywood companies produced
twenty-seven films at Cinecittà between 1950
and 1965, including such spectacular and
unforgettable movies as Charles Vidor's A
Farewell to Arms, William Wyler's Roman
Holiday, Anthony Mann's The Fall of the
Roman Empire and King Vidor's War and
Peace. It was the years of dolce vita enjoyed
by top people in Hollywood on the Tiber
that Federico Fellini immortalized in his
1960 film of the same name a partly critical,
partly affectionate portrait of a fleeting
period of wild living.
The television era In the mid-
1960s, Cinecittà suddenly woke up to
the fact that it was in the middle of a crisis.
The Americans had pulled out, and the reign
of the superproduction was over. Ever-
mounting competition from television cut
directors' ambitions down to size labour
costs were by then the same as in Holly¬
wood. An epoch was drawing to a close: sets
were dismantled, and dummy forums and
temples carted away. As Cinecittà's debts spi¬
ralled out of control, making renovation
impossible, it entered a dark period of its
history, even though a number of presti¬
gious films were still made there, including
Fellini's Satyricon (1969) and City of Women
(1980), and Luchino Visconti's The
Damned (1969) and Ludwig (1972). These
difficult years for Cinecittà partly coincided
with a world crisis in the film industry.
An upturn came at the beginning of the
Federico Fellini on set 1980s following the sale of a huge piece of
during the shooting of land owned by Cinecittà. In 1983 Sergio
La voce dellajuna Leone shot Once upon a Time in America,
and in 1987 Bernardo Bertolucci recreated the
Beijing of the interwar years for The Last
Emperor (which won nine Academy
Awards). Non-Italian film-makers started
coming back to Cinecittà. Johannes Schaaf's
Momo was made there, as was Jean-Jacques
Annaud's The Name of the Rose. Fellini,
who had always felt at home in Cinecittà,
paid a movingly melancholy tribute to the
studios with his 1987 film, Intervista.
Down the years Cinecittà has changed
considerably. Television companies now
occupy its biggest stages, from which live
shows and quiz games are beamed to millions
of households. And teenagers, whose knowl¬
edge of the cinema derives mainly from their
video recorders, queue up at its gates in the
hope of making a career in television.
(1990).
g
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
The African cinema
aston Kabore
Without firm economic and
cultural roots in the soil of its
own continent, African cinema
faces an uphill struggle for
survival
In the last twenty years the number of
festivals, retrospectives, film weeks and
special shows devoted to African
cinema has increased steadily in western
Europe as a whole, and nowhere more
remarkably than in France. That success
needs to be set against the sad fact that it is
extremely difficult to see African films in
Africa.
The number of film festivals organized
in Africa itself can be counted on the fingers
of one hand. The hundred-odd features
produced annually in African countries
(including Egypt) account for less than 0.1
per cent of films released for commercial exhi¬
bition. It is the congenital fragility of the
African cinema which, paradoxically, is
responsible for its extraordinary success out¬
side the continent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
in crisis
;. *
Aoua Sangaré in
Souleymane Cissé's
Yeelen ("The Light",
Mali, 1987).
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
A young face from
Gaston Kaboré's Wênd
Kuuni ("The Gift of
God", 1982).
ACultural fashion The African film
industry has no economic or cultural
foundations at home, and so is under the
control of people who organize events
devoted to African cinema in Europe and in
North America and who, although they
are convinced and sincere champions of
African film, tend to live in a dream world.
Only a few of them have any real idea of
what is really involved in promoting such
films through a festival. There is often a great
deal of confusion in people's minds when it
comes to concrete questions such as media
impact, the creation of a real public, back-up
and distribution.
African directors are of course under no
obligation to respond to the many invita¬
tions they receive from abroad. But they are
independent film-makers, whose isolation
and lack of funding encourage them to look
where they can outside Africa for the recog¬
nition they so much need. For many direc¬
tors from the Maghreb or sub-Saharan
Africa, an air ticket to or via Paris is often
the crucial factor in their decision to take
part in a festival. But the proliferation of fes¬
tivals is not in itself enough to give the
African cinema the commercial value it is
entitled to expect.
No one knows when African films will
go out of fashion. And if and when they do,
what will be left of the African cinema?
Little-known, and treated like a foreign
product on its own territory, the African
cinema seems to have lost its way. It is in
danger of yielding to the first siren voices that
come from the North. Moreoever, given its
financial dependence on Europe at produc¬
tion level, the worst scenario is to be feared
a total extroversion of a cinema with no roots
of its own. That makes it all the more urgent
to root the African cinema in its own soil.
Idrissa Ouedraogo's Yam
Daabo ("The Choice",
Burkina Faso, 1986).
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
airroring African society But how
I V lean that be done when Africa boasts less
than one cinema seat per 100,000 inhabitants,
when ticket prices produce such low returns,
and when the whole of the film industry is so
disastrously disorganized? Attempts have
been made to remedy this situation. A wel¬
come step was the setting up of the Consor¬
tium Inter-Africain de Distribution Ciné¬
matographique (CIDC), a common market
of film covering ten French-speaking countries
which was in operation from 1979 to 1985. It
went bankrupt when vital economic and pro¬
fessional considerations were ignored under
the pressure of political and administrative
constraints. The CIDC raised tremendous
hopes among professional film-makers in
Africa. Its failure left them in a state of shock,
and raised doubts as to whether African states
genuinely wanted regional integration.
Few countries continue to show any
interest in combining to create a single film
distribution market. Yet national markets
remain too small for companies to be able to
cover their production costs. The only answer
is to set up regional structures. The still infant
African cinema has already been seriously
jeopardized by the arrival of satellite dishes.
Sadly, many countries will doubtless see this
as a welcome excuse for doing nothing. On the
contrary, the present situation makes the need
to turn back the tide all the more urgent.
With a multitude of images now being
beamed into people's homes, it is more than
ever necessary to produce endogenous images
that will perform the vital function of mir¬
roring African peoples, their societies and
their concerns.
Gaston Kaboré,
of Burkina Faso, is the
director of Wend Kuuni
(The Gift of God), which
won a French César
award in 1985, Zan Boko
(1988) and Rabi (1992).
Since 1985 he has
headed the Pan-African
Federation of Film
Makers, a professional
organization that
promotes the
development of the art
of film and the film
industry in Africa.
Sembène Ousmane's
Guelwaar, An African
Legend ofAfrica in the
21st Century (Senegal,
1991).
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
interview
Macedonian director Milco
Mancevski (above). His film
Before the Rain won a
Golden Lion award at the
1994 Venice Film Festival
and was nominated for an
Oscar in 1995.
> When you were twenty,
you decided to leave your
country. At the age of
thirty-four you returned
and shot part of Before
the Rain there. Why did
you leave? And why did
you come back?
I think all twenty-year-olds need to
take off and reinvent themselves.
America the American dream is the
promised land of reinventing. It's no
coincidence that in the old days
people changed their names when
they landed there. It answered a con¬
scious or unconscious need to go
back to square one. I left because I
needed to leave. That was the first
reason. The second was the cinema.
And the third, which ties up with the
first, was the discovery of something
new a new culture, a new way of
life, a new vision. As for going back,
it's something I'm always doing. I'm
always schizophrenically in some
halfway house.
The myth of homecoming
is present in your film:
Aleksandar, a Macedonian
photographer living in
London, decides to go back
to his home village.
The film is actually based on three
mythical models: Ulysses or home¬
coming, Romeo and Juliet or impos¬
sible love, and Hamlet or self-ques¬
tioning. For me the cinema is not really
an art but a process of "myth-telling".
My work as a film-maker has involved
finding ways of telling myths in a new
language, no more than that, since
you can't invent new myths.
I Your three myths are
explored in the film's
three sections, which are
called "Words, "Pictures"
and "Faces". Where did
you get the idea for those
titles?
I have no preconceived ideas or pre¬
meditated message. When I was
writing the screenplay, it became clear
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
that these three elements were essen¬
tial. Don't forget they are the three
fundamental components of any film.
Take any film, analyse it, dissect it,
and that's what it'll boil down to.
> You have said in an
interview that the film
grew out of a feeling. . .
It was all very hazy at the begin¬
ning. After a long absence, I returned
to Skopje for personal reasons. War
was about to break out in Slovenia.
There was a kind of pressure in the air,
as when something important is
going to happen or when it's about
to rain. That was the feeling. The the
title followed. The story came after¬
wards.
I The story is constructed
around an imaginary
conflict between
Orthodox Macedonians
and Muslim Albanians. Is
that something you feel is
in the offing?
The story isn't specific to Mace¬
donia or the former Yugoslavia. It
could easily be set In Northern Ireland
or the former Soviet Union or some¬
where else in the world. From a prag¬
matic point of view the film spells out
a warning. But it's not a documentary
and must certainly not be regarded as
one. Anyway a documentary would
have had to involve politicians, given
the role they play in wars. Before the
Rain is far removed from politics. I'm
not capable of talking about politics,
which doesn't interest me anyway.
> It's a highly stylized film.
The cinematography often
has an unreal beauty.
I gave a lot of thought to that
problem. For a long time I couldn't
make up my mind whether to opt for a
more realistic, documentary angle or a
stylized approach. I ended up
choosing the latter, again without any
rational explanation. It just seemed the
natural choice though it could be
that the story itself and the characters
required it. If, in the first part of the
film, the images seem to come straight
out of a fairy tale, it's because the hero
of the story, the young Orthodox
monk, Kiril, treats the real world as
though it were a fairy tale. He and God
are as one. Everything is beautiful.
The full moon and shooting stars are
shown as he sees them. I've already
pointed out elsewhere that those
shots were commissioned not by the
Macedonian Tourist Office, but by the
character of Kiril.
> Do you see yourself as
belonging to any
particular tradition?
To many traditions, not one. I
don't think I belong to a particular cin¬
ematic movement. Everything you see
leaves a residue in you, especially if it's
good art. A great many film-makers,
artists and writers I admire are present
in what I do, though I don't know to
what degree. That's something for
other people to decide.
I Is there no connection at
all between what you
were doing previously
your commercials, music
videos, documentaries
and your feature film?
Does the writer in you
influence the film-maker?
When it comes down to it, I'm a
purist. I like pure art, like music,
painting and perhaps poetry. Narrative
film and the opera are to my mind
rather hybrid forms. That's why, in all
the work I've done so far, I've tried to
seek out the pure element. Of all the
forms you just mentioned, the one
where I feel the greatest freedom is
writing. When it comes to film-making,
I'm an apprentice. For me, film and
video are ways of broadening my
writing, which thereby gains a new
dimension and at the same time
reaches a wider public.
I also believe video and film have
virtually nothing in common. A music
video belongs to the world of design
and focuses on a star. A film tells a
story and focuses on people. What is
more, their means of expression are
completely different.
As regards documentaries, I've
made several, but I don't believe in the
genre. I don't believe in it because it
claims to reproduce objective reality,
whereas we all know how difficult it is
to say what objective reality is. The
very act of describing that reality
impinges on and alters it. However
hard they try and whatever their aims,
directors end up having to commit
themselves.
Aleksandar's funeral, the
opening and closing scene
of Mancevski 's Before the
Rain (1994).
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
> The question of
commitment is one of the
big issues underlying your
film. Many people in the
former Yugoslavia have
had to face this problem.
There are two options open to
Aleksandar: either he can rejoin his
cousins' "camp" by handing over to
them the young Albanian woman,
Zamira, who is suspected of murder,
or he can continue to protect Zamira
and clash with his own family. He
chooses Zamira and thus signs his
own death warrant.
Unlike Aleksandar, the young
monk, Kiril, is incapable of taking
sides. He shelters Zamira, not because
he chooses to do so, but by a quirk of
fate. Then he falls in love with her and
leaves the monastery to go abroad
with her. But he shies at the first
obstacle: when he is caught unawares
by Zamira's family, he yields unprotest-
ingly to the will of the grandfather and
turns his back on her. In a desperate
attempt to follow him, she dies at the
hands of her own brother.
Kiril does not get involved, does
not act, does not decide. He is one of
those people who submit. He is the
only one of the three main characters
who survives, but he is the most
tragic. Aleksandar, on the other hand,
dies, but dies with a smile on his face.
He is dead, but not really tragic.
Aleksandar decides to save
Zamira.
é Where do you stand
exactly?
It took me a whole film to explain
my position, and even then. . . . How
do you expect me to sum it up in a
few words? One thing is certain: no
stance really stands the test of time.
People like us, who grew up during
the period of the Cold War and com¬
munism, have seen how revolutions
can degenerate. You launch yourself
into an ideal with your head full of
dreams and, without your realizing it,
that ideal turns into a caricature of
itself. But there's nothing you can do
about it, as you've already committed
yourself. I've always wondered how
we can define ourselves in terms of an
ideology and stick to our guns when
the whole world around us is
changing.
I You take a stand against
violence. . .
Yes, of course. I condemn vio¬
lence, exclusion, tribalism, nationalism
and everything I regard as "collective
selfishness". But the problem is how
can you keep on being a pacifist
when someone throws stones at
you? If you react, you're compro¬
mising your ¡deals. If you don't react,
you end up getting bombs thrown at
you.
I One of the most violent
scenes in your film the
massacre in a London
restaurant is acted in
Serbian, without any
translation. Is it solely
aimed at spectators from
the former Yugoslavia?
On the contrary, it's aimed at
everyone except Yugoslavia. I origi¬
nally intended to shoot the scene in
another language. It didn't matter
which one, it could have been
Armenian, for example. Then some
technical constraints cropped up.
However that may be, the scene is
seen and experienced by Anne, an
Englishwoman. That's why it has not
been translated: Anne doesn't under¬
stand a word. She is present at one of
those massacres you glimpse on tele¬
vision before switching to another
channel. The difference in this case is
that war comes out of the television
set and into your own world. The
The young orthodox monk, Kiril
(foreground), and Zamira, the
young Albanian woman.
people directly Involved in a war aren't
the only ones involved. "Ask not for
whom the bell tolls, it tolls for thee."
> Did you have to make
sacrifices in order to
shoot your film?
All directors make certain calcula¬
tions. Those who make so-called art
films do too. Talking about politics,
putting in a dash of Surrealism,
shooting some very slow scenes,
projecting an image of the world as
seen through the eyes of a child
these are often "gimmicks" that help
you to sell yourself as a "director of
art films". American cloak-and-dagger
films and the kind of movies Arnold
Schwarzenegger appears in are gim¬
micks of a different kind designed to
attract another kind of audience. What
I mean is that form in itself is neither a
guarantee of quality nor a passport to
mediocrity. A film should have both a
highly emotive side and a very well-
structured side. One of those two
ingredients without the other results in
kitsch. Together they create a contrast
which gives an added dimension to
the finished film.
I didn't come under any outside
pressure when making Before the
Rain, apart from a problem of time, in
other words money. But that's all part
of the job.
]]>
</page>
<page number="77">
<![CDATA[
Volker
Schlöndorff
Above, the German director Volker Schlöndorff. His The Tin Drum won the Golden Palm award at
the 1979 Cannes Festival and a Hollywood Oscar for the Best Foreign-Language Film.
interview
I What was the first film you
ever saw?
A kind of German spaghetti western
called The Children of Mara Mara. I've
never come across it again, but it made
a very strong impression on me it
showed some children hung up on
meat hooks, like in a butcher's. That
was in 1953, when I was thirteen.
> Had you never been to the
cinema before that?
No, never. We mainly listened to
the radio. I remember that two or three
years later I saw Jean Cocteau's The
Blood of a Poet, and another high¬
light of that period was Alfred Hitch¬
cock's Rear Window.
I Was that when you first
wanted to make a film?
What I wanted, when I was about
fourteen, was to do something dif¬
ferent; I didn't want to be a doctor or a
lawyer, for example. Like a lot of
teenagers I wrote poetry and short sto¬
ries, but what I was looking for, even
more than a means of self-expression,
was a way of exploring the world. I
remember being fascinated by an
article in a magazine I found in the
cellar, with pictures of a film crew on
location somewhere in Africa men in
caps, camels, a camera on a tripod. I
said to myself, that's what I want to do.
I was also taking a lot of photographs
at that time, but most of all I read. I was
an avid reader, which explains the pas¬
sion I still have for adapting literary
works for the screen.
I What did you read?
A bit of everything, or perhaps I
should say a lot of everything. As
often happens in such cases I read
everything too soon. I was fond of
Faulkner, Hemingway and Balzac I
remember La Peau de chagrin and
Splendeurs et misères des cour¬
tisanes very vividly not forgetting
Dostoevski. I must have been twelve
when I read Schopenhauer: "It's not
at all the sort of thing for you," my
father said.
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="78">
<![CDATA[
> Why did you come to
France?
To learn French. When I was
about fifteen or sixteen I went to a
school in Vannes. A Jesuit there had
a great influence on me; we saw eye
to eye in matters of theology, philos¬
ophy and the cinema. It was at the
school film club that I developed my
knowledge of, and love for, the
cinema. I saw what we used to call
the "classics", from Buster Keaton to
Carl Dreyer, and discovered the great
pre-war German directors, Fritz Lang
in particular. A little later I got to know
the work of Friedrich Murnau, Ewald
André Dupont I'm thinking of his
film Varietyand Lupu-Pick.
> What about the films that
were coming out then?
I was impressed by many of them,
especially Elia Kazan's On the Water¬
front, with Marlon Brando, which
opened my eyes to the fact that the
cinema was capable of doing some¬
thing about injustice. There was also
Alain Resnais' Nuit et brouillard
{Night and Fog) with its powerful rev¬
elation of the death camps, and, in a
very different register, Henri Verneuil's
Please, Mr. Balzac, with Brigitte
Bardot and Darry Cowl, and Federico
Fellini's // Bidone (The Swindlers).
> In what way did they affe ct
you?
I gradually realized that making
films is a proper job that has to be
learned. After getting my school-
leaving certificate in France I enrolled
at IDHEC, the French school of cine¬
matography, but I didn't take the
course. ... In fact, owing to a series
of coincidences I was taken on as a
trainee by Louis Malle. He was
making Zazie dans le métro at the
time. That was my real introduction to
directing. I've been in films ever
since. . . .
> How did your career
develop?
It began in France, where I worked
Volker Schlöndorff's Young
Törless (Fed. Rep. of
Germany, 1966), based on a
story by Robert Musil, with
Matthieu Carrière (left) in
the title role.
Young David Bennent in
Volker Schlöndorff's The Tin
Drum (Fed. Rep. of
Germany, 1979), based on
Günter Grass's novel of the
same name.
1 ¿-
%]
under Jean-Pierre Melville and Louis
Malle, and then I decided I wanted to
be a German director and went back
to Germany. The first film I made, in
1965, was Der Junge Törless
("Young Törless"), based on the
novel by the Austrian writer Robert
Musil. It went down well. I then made
two more pictures with the actor and
film director Margarethe von Trotta. In
1978, my adaptation of the Günter
Grass novel Die Blechtrommel (The
Tin Drum) won awards at Cannes and
in Hollywood. I was deeply Involved In
the German film movement of the
1960s and 1970s alongside
Alexander Kluge, Rainer Werner
Fassbinder, Peter Fleischmann, Werner
Herzog and others. When that move¬
ment broke up, I left for the United
States, where I worked mainly for tele¬
vision. I also made Swann in Love,
based on Proust's novel.
i What are your recollections
of the United States?
The working conditions were
excellent, and I made films with such
Hollywood legends as Dustin
Hoffman and Richard Widmark. But I
find it hard to accept that films are
ordinary commercial products. I
believe that film-making, whether it is
an art as some people claim or just a
means of expression, deserves better.
The absolute power enjoyed by pro¬
ducers and distributors in the United
States gets in the way of such
expression at least as far as I'm con¬
cerned! Directors have to wage a
hard, endless struggle that in the long
run wears out even the most resilient.
]]>
</page>
<page number="79">
<![CDATA[
All the same, I would be happy to
go back to the United States to make
a film. I have some good friends there,
especially Billy Wilder, who made
Some Like it Hot, an amusing, astute
man. I go along with his idea that film
directors are showmen. . . .
> What does he mean by that,
exactly?
He says a director is like a music-
hall magician. He gets about the same
amount of applause every evening
but now and again, when he is in the
middle of his act, a beautiful naked
woman crosses the stage behind
him, unbeknown to him, and the
audience goes wild. He goes home
that night, well pleased with himself,
thinking: "That's it, I've found how to
do it, I've made it!" The next day he's
back on stage, raring to go. . . .
I But the naked lady, in other
words the sudden incursion
of life, fails to materialize?
Not that evening. It's impossible to
know when she will appear, but the
important thing is that she doesn't
walk out on us, that we still have a
chance. . . .
I After the United States you
returned to Germany. . . .
Yes, I moved around. I made
another film, my most recent, The
Voyager, based on the novel Homo
Faber by the German-speaking Swiss
writer Max Frisch. Then, in 1990, an
outstanding opportunity occurred,
the possibility of taking over the leg¬
endary Babelsberg studios of which I
am now director. These studios, at
Potsdam, near Berlin, in the former
German Democratic Republic, embody
the whole history of German cinema.
After reunification the question of
what to do with Babelsberg arose.
The technical facilities were in a dilap¬
idated state and everything needed
seeing to. I hesitated at first but then
took the plunge, helped by my old
friend Peter Fleischmann. Now the
studios are coming back to life and in
a little while we may well have
Europe's finest movie factory.
Is European cinema still a
feasible proposition?
Very much so. In the first place
there is the heartening example of
French cinema, which has managed
to stand up for itself better than the
others and Is doing well. We shall try
and take a lesson from the French
legislation. We are also encouraged
by the upturn In cinema attendance in
Germany and Britain, in addition to
which it seems obvious to me that, in
the cinema as in other spheres,
Europe still has plenty to say and
plenty to offer. Diversity is Europe's
strong point.
But surely the American
cinema dominates the
market in Europe, as it does
elsewhere.
In the movie theatres, yes, but tele¬
vision Is different. On television, most
of the big hits I'm talking about fea¬
ture films are domestic products.
There's no question of closing the
door to American film imports; that
would be ridiculous, and impossible
in any case! We simply have to
explain patiently and in simple terms,
as we aim to do in all our discussions
and negotiations with European insti¬
tutions, that there is room for another
form of cinema. This ambitious, high-
quality cinema is European cinema;
but it is also the rest of world cinema,
that of Nikita Mikhalkov, Zhang
Yimou, Abbas Kiarostami, Souley-
mane Cissé and a thousand other
young directors who will all go under
if we go under, without having had
the opportunity to make a film. Don't
forget that as well as producing films
Europe also coproduces them, in
Europe itself and outside of Europe.
> So there is no cause for
pessimism?
Nor for complacency. The struggle
ahead will be long, hard and compli¬
cated, since it Involves both eco¬
nomic and artistic considerations.
I What about the crisis in the
cinema?
That's nothing new. All my films
were made in a state of crisis, so. . . .
I So you think the crisis is
more apparent than real?
Of course not: Europe's film
output, for instance, has fallen off
considerably. We have not always
been aware of the danger ahead, but
there is no cinema crisis as such. In
point of fact, more films are being
seen today than ever before. The dif¬
ference is that now we often watch
them at home, on television or on
video. Does that mean the cinema is
weaker, is cinema-going no longer the
incomparable experience that set my
heart beating faster when I saw On
the Waterfront at the age of fifteen?
The answer depends on us.
Ornella Muti and
Jeremy Irons in
Volker
Schlöndorff's
Swann in Love
(France-Fed. Rep.
of Germany, 1984).
]]>
</page>
<page number="80">
<![CDATA[
The Babelsberg
Many of the stars of German
í cinema were born at the leg¬
endary Babelsberg Studios
outside Berlin. The first
studio was built there in
1912 its walls constructed entirely of
glass on a 40,000-square-metre site acquired
the year before by the Bioscop film com¬
pany. In the next eighty years some 2,500
films would be made at Babelsberg.
Among those who helped to make the
name of the new studios were the actress Asta
Nielsen, Paul Wegener, director of Der
Golem (1915), and Ernst Lubitsch, who pro¬
duced seven films there in 1918, including his
first international success, Carmen, with Pola
Negri. Two great directors whose careers were
closely associated with Babelsberg in the
1920s were Fritz Lang (Metropolis, 1927) and
Friedrich Wilhelm Murnau (Nosferatu, 1922).
Germany's first sound stages were built at
Babelsberg in 1929, and in 1930 The Blue.
Angel was made there with Marlene Dietrich
and Emil Jannings in the leading roles.
After the nationalization of the German
film industry in 1938-1939, Babels.berg fell
under the control of Nazi Propaganda Min¬
ister Josef Goebbels and his machine. By
then the industry was already suffering from
the exodus of talent which began in the early
1930s when directors such as Lang and Dou¬
glas Sirk fled the Nazi regime and went to
America.
After the Second World War, the state film
company DEFA Film AG was established at
Babelsberg and went on to produce over 700
features, including 150 films for children.
Architect's model of
the Babelsberg
Studios as they will
develop in the
1990s.
Right, Fritz Lang's
Metropolis (1927), a
classic of German cinema.
Opposite page, Josef von
Sternberg's The Blue
Angel (Germany, 1929-
1930), featuring Marlene
Dietrich (foreground) as
the singer, Lola-Lola.
]]>
</page>
<page number="81">
<![CDATA[
Studios
Between 1959 and 1990, the studio made over
600 TV films. Since 1992 the sound studios
have been renovated as part of a large-scale
investment programme and an international
centre of multiple media activities is being set
up. Today Babelsberg (which attracted over
500,000 visitors in 1994) is on the way to
becoming a veritable media city with com¬
mercial, service and educational facilities,
hotels, cinemas and restaurants. N. T.
The Babelsberg
studios in the late
1930s.
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="82">
<![CDATA[
Yesterday's
images for
tomorrow's eyes
by Thereza Wagner
At Unesco's Paris
Headquarters on 19
October 1994 Unesco
Director-General
Federico Mayor
appointed French
actress Catherine
Deneuve Unesco's
Goodwill Ambassador
for the safeguard of the
cinematic heritage.
T, he advent of the talkies in the
1930s coincided with the
\ founding of the first film
archives. The Swedish Film
Institute was created in 1933; the
Reichsfilmarchiv in Berlin was founded in
1935 (it ceased to exist after the Second World
War), as were the Museum of Modern Art
Film Library in New York and the National
Film Library in London. The French Ciné¬
mathèque was established in Paris in 1936.
Even then, it was estimated that 80 per
cent of the negatives of silent films had been
lost, either because of destruction on a mas¬
sive scale with the coming of the talkies, or
because they were gradually withdrawn
from the market, stored, and then disposed
of to make room for more recent works or
as a precaution against fire*.
The first task awaiting the film libraries
was thus to persuade the major producers to
lend or give a copy of each of their films for
safe-keeping. Although at first considered an
unusual request, this initiative eventually
came to be accepted by the film industry as a
way of helping to maintain the commercial
value of films in a volatile market.
Different approaches To begin
with the libraries had two distinct func¬
tions. One was that promoted by Ernest
Lindgren, the first director of the National
Film Library in London. Lindgren argued
that film libraries should collect films, pre¬
serve them, make inventories of them, store
them in decent conditions, establish national
filmographies and index collections. A dif¬
ferent point of view was put forward by
Henri Langlois, founder of the French Ciné¬
mathèque, who wanted to encourage research
into and study of the art of cinema, a field
which until then had been hardly explored.
This meant that films held in archives should
be shown to the public.
These two viewpoints soon became
antagonistic and divided archivists who after
1936 were affiliated to the International Fed¬
eration of Film Archives (FIAF). This con¬
flict only came to an end in the 1980s.
It was around the same time that the
"vinegar syndrome", a process whereby film
]]>
</page>
<page number="83">
<![CDATA[
Thereza Wagner is a
staff member of
Unesco's Section for
the Promotion of Arts
and Creativity.
UNESCO's Federico
Fellini medal, designed
by Italian artist Valerio
Adami and executed by
French sculptor Robert
Michel, is awarded in
recognition of efforts by
cinema professionals to
promote the seventh
art. It was presented for
the first time on 24 May
1995 to Mr. Pierre Viot,
president of the Cannes
Film Festival.
stock deteriorates, whitening the images,
appeared in films produced between 1950 and
1960 using cellulose-acetate film stock. This
kind of film, which was widely used in the
1950s because of its non-inflammable nature,
proved to be unreliable. About 60 per cent of
acetate film is presently endangered.
The figure is considerably higher for film
in developing countries where poor storage
conditions accelerate deterioration. Unfortu¬
nately very little is being done in these coun¬
tries, for people are not yet really aware of
the immense loss the disappearance of the
world's film heritage would represent. Fur¬
thermore, in this case restoration costs arc
proportionately far higher than the original
production costs of the films themselves. In
developing countries facilities for the
storage, preservation and safeguarding of
film are usually rudimentary.
Steps to save the film heritage
The size of the task is so great that sev¬
eral questions arise. What should be restored
and what restoration methods should be
used? Where should the restored heritage be
kept?
Film archivists in the developed countries
must preserve all "nitrate" films (those pro¬
duced before 1950) because of their rarity. It
is estimated that around three-quarters of
these films have already been lost. Decisions
must be taken concerning acetate-based films.
In the United States, Martin Scorsese,
Francis Ford Coppola, Woody Allen and a
few other highly respected film-makers grew
concerned that the colour of their films was
deteriorating and in the late 1980s decided to
create a company to protect them.
There are around a dozen film archives and
libraries in the United States. They are cur¬
rently restoring nitrate films with help from
private foundations, but their collections are
large and the work is far from finished.
Four years ago the Commission of the
European Communities launched the
"Lumière Project" to save the nitrate collec¬
tions in member countries of what is now the
European Union. With a similar end in view,
UNESCO has decided to initiate a far-reaching
international programme called "Let's Save the
Cinematic Heritage", aimed especially at the
developing countries. The programme is being
carried out in co-operation with FIAF, to
which more than 100 film libraries in some
sixty countries are today affiliated.
Films to encourage tolerance
The programme covers the promotion,
safeguard, protection and distribution of
films and the cinematic heritage.
In terms of promotion, UNESCO is exam¬
ining the possibility of drawing up a list of
films that should be considered as national
and international heritage. Work on this is
being done within the framework of
UNESCO's "Memory of the World" pro¬
gramme, in co-operation with states, film
libraries and archives. In the same perspective,
an international festival of restored and
rediscovered films on the theme of tolerance
was held in January 1995. It will be followed
up by a publication for primary and sec¬
ondary schools which will contain a list and
description of the sixty most important
films ever made on this subject.
As far as preservation and safeguard are
concerned, UNESCO has recently created a
fund with a special account for the restora¬
tion and protection of the cinematic heritage.
A major international appeal will be made
later this year for contributions to finance
the fund, whose president is the French
actress Catherine Deneuve, UNESCO Good¬
will Ambassador for the safeguard of the
cinematic heritage.
UNESCO will also encourage the imple¬
mentation of co-operation agreements
between film libraries and archives in the rich
and poor countries. With this in view, an
extensive public information campaign will
be held in order to promote the cinema and
the moving image. This is a long-term
undertaking and should be carried out in
each country through film festivals, publica¬
tions and other activities.
* Until 1950 film negatives were made of nitro-cellulose,
a highly inflammable substance prone to deterioration.
g
]]>
</page>
<page number="84">
<![CDATA[
APPEAL BY THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL
"The twentieth century will go down in history
as the century that added a new art to the his¬
tory of civilization: the seventh art. An art
which, if we really make an effort to safeguard
it, will preserve philosophy, history, daily life and
the problems, emotions and attitudes of an
entire age."
elina Mercouri
(Greek Minister of Culture and actress)
"What would we do if negatives of Amarcord
or of And the Ship Sails On were to disappear
forever? Surely the works of Sembène Ous-
mane, Fernando Solanas, Mrinal Sen and
Merzak Alouach also deserve to be protected?
I am not convinced that it is necessary to
appeal to intellectual snobbery, charity or clair¬
voyance to make people aware of the cata¬
strophe that is threatening the cinema. I should
prefer to think that it is through humanity, intel¬
ligence and above all through love for future
generations that we will save the cinema."
oussef Chahine
(Egyptian film-maker)
"Africa has a right to its ¡mage and its memory.
We must preserve, but we must also help to
distribute films in Africa. The African cinema
must develop because Africa has something to
contribute to the memory of the world. Africa
wants to have its own image, to produce and
preserve it."
(Burkinabé film-maker)
"I invite you to take action to defend the three
fundamental rights of cinema pluralism: the
'i m right of all nations to develop their own cinema
and to enable cinema and audiovisual works to
Saving the
cinematic heritage
Embracing as it does painting, the¬
atre, music, literature and pho¬
tography, the art of the cinema,
which was invented in 1895, is the
custodian of the memory of the
twentieth century and one of the
leading forms of expression of a
changing world.
A product of human creative
imagination and inventive genius, the
art of the cinema developed along
lines running counter to those of the
other arts, in that its discovery and
the progress it made were based on a
technical invention. It owes its suc¬
cess, which was immediate, to the
new dialogue it established with the
public, where every spectator is
under the illusion of actually being in
the midst of the action caught on
film. Film, the miracle of the moving
image, abolishes spatial and temporal
distance. It records, recounts, illus¬
trates and invents.
Today, more than three-quarters
of the perishable and highly inflam¬
mable nitrocellulose-based films
made prior to the 1950s are lost for
ever, while some 60 per cent of the
cellulose-acetate films made after
1950 are threatened by a process of
deterioration known as the "vinegar
syndrome", which bleaches the
image if the film is not properly con¬
served.
The wealth of images captured in
art films, features, documentaries,
full-length films, shorts, popular-sci¬
ence films, newsreels, instructional
and educational films, cartoons and
others, is in danger of disappearing
forever. The cinema has to be saved.
Under its Constitution, UNESCO
is responsible for "assuring the con¬
servation and protection of the
world's inheritance of . . . works of
art and monuments of history and
science", and devotes itself to fos¬
tering the action needed to safeguard
them. The conservation and restora¬
tion of the international cinematic
heritage entail special problems that
private support and spontaneous
gestures cannot by themselves
resolve. It is accordingly considered
necessary to look for answers to
them through partnership arrange¬
ments.
This is why, on behalf of the
United Nations Educational, Scien¬
tific and Cultural Organization and
of the Honorary Committee for the
Celebration of the Centenary of the
Cinema,
I solemnly appeal to the Member
States of Unesco to take appropriate
legal, administrative and financial
steps to set up or strengthen the
structures that are essential for safe¬
guarding the international cinematic
heritage, such as film archives, film
libraries, cinema museums and
restoration laboratories. If this action
is to be successful it will have to be
carried out in consultation with the
International Federation of Film
Archives (FIAF), the specialist inter¬
national organization whose mem¬
bership includes more than 100 such
archives in 63 UNESCO Member
States.
I invite cinema specialists and
]]>
</page>
<page number="85">
<![CDATA[
OF UNESCO
film-goers to join their efforts to
those whose task it is in every
country to ensure that their national
cinema is safeguarded, so as to make
it possible to compile exhaustive fil¬
mographies.
I invite film producers, actors,
directors, technicians and operators
to join forces, as they are already
doing in some countries, and set up
national foundations or associations
to alert the public to the urgent need
to preserve the national and interna¬
tional cinematic heritage; collect pri¬
vate or public funds to help finance
the restoration of national film col¬
lections; encourage projects for cre¬
ating copyright registration systems
in countries where archives for the
preservation of the cinematic her¬
itage do not yet exist; and ensure that
the national preservation practices
introduced are consistent with the
norms laid down by the Interna¬
tional Federation of Film Archives.
I invite the photography, cinema,
video and television industries, film
producers and distributors and all
industries concerned with cinema
generally to participate generously in
the national and internationl effort
being made by associations and orga¬
nizations to safeguard the cinematic
heritage, by contributing to the cre¬
ation of an international fund
designed to defray the cost of film
restoration and preservation work.
This fund will be created in the
International Federation of Film
Archives and Unesco::".
I invite cinema and television film
producers holding rights to films or
successors in title to join in the safe¬
guarding operation by participating
in it financially or setting up appro¬
priate restoration programmes; I
also ask them to do their utmost to
facilitate the distribution of restored
films in commercial and non-com¬
mercial circuits by concluding
agreements with film distributors
and distribution agencies.
I invite film festivals all over the
world to create a section in their
programmes on "films that have
been saved" and to organize public
showings with the co-operation of
the International Council for Film,
Television and Audiovisual Com¬
munication (IFTC).
I invite schools of film, television
and the audiovisual professions to
take appropriate steps, in conjunc¬
tion with the International Liaison
Centre for Film and Television
Schools, to alert future professionals
working in the film industry to the
problems of conserving and safe¬
guarding cinematic works.
I invite the industrialized coun¬
tries to co-operate with the devel¬
oping countries, so that the latter can
successfully engage in research on
their film production and ensure the
training of conservation specialists
through the requisite transfers of
knowledge and technology.
In conclusion, I invite members
of the international community,
such as film critics, specialists,
cinema-goers and others, to con¬
tribute in all appropriate ways to the
movement to safeguard the cinema
in conjunction with the national,
regional and international bodies of
the International Federation of Film
Archives.
Federico Mayor
UNESCO Headquarters,
2 November 1993
* The UNESCO Fund for the Safeguarding of
the Film Heritage was established in 1995. (Ed.)
be seen as the right of all authors and directors
to express their aesthetic and cultural identity
freely, and the right of all peoples to know and
benefit from the films made by all the different
nations of the world."
ernando Solanas
(Argentine film-maker)
"Throughout Black Africa, South America and
almost everywhere in Europe, cinemas, which
were meeting places just as important in their
own way as country churches, are closing
down one after the other because, at their very
doors, pirate video cassettes are sold for less
than the price of cinema tickets. We are not
asking you to set your face against progress,
but we invite all of you, in your respective
countries, to save these places of mass com¬
munion where, as Freddy Buache so neatly
puts it, 'members of the audience together
shared the same emotions.'"
(French film-maker)
"We know that without libraries, literature
would disappear, the memory of writing would
die with its authors, everything would be con¬
temporary, no worse than journalism but also
no better and the journalism not inspired by
the epic and romantic forms of the past. What
would our cinema look like if we had no
memory of its development? The question is
almost too banal, and yet we still treat that her¬
itage as if it had no value. Arrangements for
preservation and exhibition of past work fall far
below what is barely necessary."
(International Liaison Centre for Film and
Television Schools)
g
]]>
</page>
<page number="86">
<![CDATA[
ANNIVERSARY
Interview with Chingiz Aitmatov
ABAI
KUNANBAYEV
(1845-1904)
One of the few
photos of Abai,
here seen with his
two sons.
The ivork of the Kirghiz writer Chingiz
Aitmatov (b. 1928, the grandson of a
nomadic shepherd)powerfully illustrates the
conflict between modern society and ancient
civilizations in the former Soviet Union, as
well as confronting the problem of thefuture
state ofhumanity and the world. Among his
many short stories and novels translated into
English are Jamilia (1958), The White
Steamship (1970) and The Day Lasts More
than a Hundred Years (1 980). Here, to mark
the 150th anniversary of the birth of Abai
Kunanbayev, Aitmatov explains why the
Kazakhpoet's work is still relevant today.
What docs (his commemoration
mean to you?
Historical changes in a society are often tied
to a negative reappraisal of the values of the
past, particularly in the perception of the impor¬
tance of great figures from national and world
culture. One only need remember how artists
such as Gorky and Mayakovsky were treated
during our Soviet era, whose embers are still hot.
Abai is above history: he served no govern¬
ment or ideology. He embodies both an ethnic
and a personal inspiration, which has come to
be identified with the destiny of his people, their
struggles and their tragedies. Rooted in the
spirit of his nation, he lived during an excep¬
tionally complex period of Kazakh history. How
could such a brilliant mind have emerged
during this time in the remote steppes, so far
from world events? It's impossible to explain.
He is not a story-teller who respects tradi¬
tion and its rules, he is a civilizing genius,
capable of reconstructing everything through
his creative originality, of enriching the past
and developing a new personal view of the
world.
"I am without strength, I ain here
all alone. . . ,"' Abai lamented. "My
soul is in mourning . . . my efforts
arc sterile. . . ." What if he had not
been born "in a century of wolves,
among a pack of wolves"? If be
had lived in a more civilized age,
]]>
</page>
<page number="87">
<![CDATA[
might he have developed his great
talent even more?
No. Abai emerged at a time when he was most
needed. For the first time in its history,
Turkestan was discovering, through Russia, the
European ideas of the Enlightenment, which
would have enormous consequences for the
nomadic masses. Shortly after, these people
would be hurled into destructive upheavals
and live through two revolutions: that of 1917
and that of the 1990s, which rejects, annuls
and disavows totally and categorically the revo¬
lution of 1917.
What was the significance of
Abai's work during the period
between these two revolutions?
What role did it play during the
Soviet era?
In a context in which totalitarianism was
based primarily on the negation of the idea of
the nation in the name of proletarian interna¬
tionalism, Abai and the spiritual force that he
represented were a shield that protected us.
Abai was a kind of sanctuary, a bastion for
the Kazakh people. He enabled them to survive
spiritually, to resist the power of imperialistic
absorption. The heritage of his work preserved
and inspired the Kazakh intelligentsia at a time
when the dangers of nihilism were at their most
critical and troubling. The neighbouring peo¬
ples are also deeply indebted to the greatness of
Abai, in their struggle to preserve their distinc¬
tive languages and national spirit.
Like a tall,
shady cedar in the mountains. . . .
Born in the Chingiz author of an epic novel a positive role in Kazakh
mountains, into a nomadic about him (The Journey culture. The third
tribe, the Kazakh poet ofAbai), summed up in source is Russian, and
Abai Kunanbayev (1845- an article written in through it, the whole of
1904), usually known as 1954 Abai's unique world culture. In Abai's
Abai, transformed his contribution to Kazakh time, tapping this source,
people's language and culture: "Abai's literary particularly the great
the thematic range of work (his lyric poetry, Russian classics, which
their poetry through his maxims and translations) before Abai were
work and the far-reaching was fed and watered completely unknown to
influence of his from three major sources the Kazakhs, was a
personality. He which blend decisive force for
denounced feudal harmoniously."First, the progress.
customs, and called on ancient Kazakh culture "However, Abai and
his people to educate as established in the oral this is the sign of his
themselves and to unite. and written works of the great originality and
This year marks the past. . . . Second, the exceptional gifts
150th anniversary of his best examples of Eastern succeeded in remaining
birth. culture: classic poetry true to himself while
In describing the great written in Tadzik, Azeri drawing on these three
Kazakh poet as "standing and Uzbek. Discernible sources. Like all creators
out in the history of his since the beginning of of stature, he immersed
people like a tall, shady the century, this himself in a new culture
cedar in the mountains", tendency to turn towards without losing his strong
his compatriot Muktar neighbouring cultures individuality as an artist
Auezov (d. 1961), the has undoubtedly played and thinker."
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="88">
<![CDATA[
Reach deep into your soul,
remain true to yourself.
To you I am an enigma, I and
my journey.
Understand, you who come after
me, that I am opening the way
for you.
1 have had thousands of
adversaries, dont reproach me
for it!
Abai
"After a harsh, snowy winter,
doesn't spring follow, with its
flowers, high waters and
splendour?" Abai wrote. Arc his
ideas and his writings still
relevant today?
Today we are confronted with another pic¬
ture, another era, another aspect of Abai. I am
thinking of our everyday life today, at a time
when the democratic process has led to a radi¬
cally different situation. We are faced with
another extreme. Populist nationalism is playing
a reactionary, illogical role, that of a blind
driver on whom it would be dangerous to rely.
When it is out of control, the euphoria of the
national independence, sovereignty and freedom
that actually have been won during the democ-
An illustration
by K. K. Kongir
(1914-1986) fora
collection of Abai's
poems published in
the late 1940s.
' t
W. V' ""4- ¿r,U . £$& *r <*. 'u . - ;
]]>
</page>
<page number="89">
<![CDATA[
ratization process, through the joint action of
entire peoplesby the liberation of the centre
as well as the old peripheryis transformed into
ambition run riot. It has become a disintegrating
force, ruling out much-needed co-operation
between all national cultures.
Abai openly warned against all
forms of obtuse and blinkered
nationalism. . . .
Populist and chauvinist demagogy, which is
so fashionable and seemingly productive in the
short term, actually exacerbates the vanity of
national self-satisfaction. This leads to a provin¬
cial outlook and, ultimately, to isolation, an
inferiority complex and a weakening of the role
of elites who cease to take part in the develop¬
ment of common values. Without such values,
a people ceases to develop.
On the horizon of history, Abai appears as
an astonishingly contemporary figure, a man
endowed with a particularly penetrating vision,
a true prophet. Today is a good moment to think
of his ideas about the need for an ecumenical
approach to the world's diversity, and in partic¬
ular about reconciling the cultural values of
East and West that is, the values of our Asian
background and those of Russian culture,
whose historical mission is to act as a link.
Abai attached great importance to this char¬
acteristic of Russian culture. At the same he
remained profoundly Kazakh in his way of
thinking. He loved his people and was proud of
them, but he also called on them to be self-crit¬
ical. He presented his compatriots with the
unvarnished truth, refused to indulge a mis¬
placed national pride, and denounced the
defects and obscurantism of an ignorant nation.
All this has great relevance today, at a time
when nationalism is becoming a reactionary
political force, when the great democratic fig¬
ures of the past as well as the great Russian
philosophers are being reassessed in a national¬
istic perspective.
During the totalitarian era, Abai embodied
the national spirit and encouraged the survival
of the Kazakh nation. Today, in the post-totali¬
tarian era, his role is that of a spiritual unifier of
national cultures, based on a democratic vision.
His message lives on in a new age. H
Interview Iiv
Gulzatla Miirzalimetova
The School in the
Steppe (1911),
oil on canvas by
N. G. Khludov.
M
]]>
</page>
<page number="90">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS
TO THE EDITOR
DISCOVERIES
To my mind, by far the most
interesting issue of the Courier
published so far this year is the
April number on "the origins of
writing". For me it was an
opportunity to make two dis¬
coveries.
First of all the great Afro-
American writer Ernest J.
Gaines. Until then the only
Afro-American writers whose
work I knew were Toni Morrison,
Alice Walker and James
Baldwin. I am delighted that
Afro-American literature is at
last being recognized and appre¬
ciated throughout the world.
How about an article or an inter¬
view featuring Maya Angelou?
I owe my second discovery
to Isabelle Leymarie's article
about the sacred Indian dance-
form known as Odissi. Perhaps
like many other Courier
readers, I was hitherto
familiar only with the Bharata
Natyam form. Apart from any
thing else, dancer Devasmita
Patnayik is an exceptional per¬
sonality who is totally devoted
to her art, which, as she says,
is an offering, a devotional act
and a quest for perfection all
in one. This is an attitude that
believers in all religions should
apply to daily life, especially
in their relationships with
others.
It seems to me that the
ideas expressed by Devasmita
Patnayik and Mr. Federico
Mayor's appeal, elsewhere in
the issue, for a rehabilitation of
spiritual values and for a
responsible attitude towards
the environment, go a long way
to fulfil the wish expressed in
the "Letters" column of the
same issue by a reader from
Grand-Quevilly (France) to the
effect that the Courier should
offer its readers some examples
of enlightened approaches to
today's problems.
Keep up the good work!
THIERRY LAMBERT
Laon (France)
3B3ESï3SOSÎEjesaSE33ï:aiK3: ssäss»2äk^äi;
THE NINTH BORDEAUX BOOK
FAIR
The UNESCO Courier will be participating in the 9th Bor¬
deaux Book Fair (France) from 5 to 8 October 1995. This
year's Fair, the main theme of which is "Literature and
Cinema", will present a broad panorama of today's publishing
world and welcome more than 200 authors. Special attention
will be devoted to the French poet Jean de la Fontaine, the
300th anniversary of whose birth is being celebrated this
year, the Andalusian poet Rafael Alberti, and French nov¬
elist Jean Giono, who was born a hundred years ago. An exhi¬
bition, round table discussions and film screenings will high¬
light Giono's work, including his lesser known activities as a
scriptwriter and film-maker. For further information contact
the Salon du Livre de Bordeaux, 139, Cours Balguerie-
Stuttenberg, 33300 Bordeaux. Tel: (33) 56 43 04 35.
ZOROASTRIAN
DEBATE
I would like to clarify one of the
positions taken in your January
1995 issue ("The Sun, Ancient
Myths, New Technologies").
The dates of Zoroaster's
life have been much debated
by specialists, who place them
between 4000 B.C. and 600
B.C.; most recent scholars tend
to place him about 1500 B.C.
To give his dates unequivocally
(as you did on page 17) as "c.
628-551 B.C." is not entirely
factual and is misleading.
KOIIINTON M. RIVETNA
FEZANA (Federation of
Zoroastrian Associations of North
America)
Quebec (Canada)
THE TORAH AND
THE
PENTATEUCH
The word "Torah" is not, as
claimed on page 14 of your May
1995 issue ("The Pilgrim's
Way"), "a Hebrew translation
of the Greek word 'Penta¬
teuch'". Purely Hebraic in
origin, it means "law" or
"teaching", and designates the
first five books of the Bible.
The earliest translation of these
books from Hebrew into Greek,
forms part of the famous trans¬
lation known as the Septuagint,
and was undertaken in the 3rd
century B.C. by seventy Jewish
scholars in Alexandria. The
word "Pentateuch" was used
by the Greek translators to des¬
ignate these books.
MEIR LEKER
l'aris (France)
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover photos: Cahiers du cinéma,
Paris. Page 2: © Claudine Dufour,
Amiens, France. Page 5: © Boyer
Viollet, Paris. Pages 6, 10-11, 57,
81 (above): © Viollet Collection,
Paris. Pages 7, 12-13, 13 (below),
14 (below), 32-33, 40, 67, 68
(right), 78 (above): with
permission from the Kobal
Collection, London. Pages 8, 14
(above), 15 (above right), 15
(below right), 16, 17 (below), 18
(below), 23, 24, 28, 31 (above): ©
All rights reserved. PR0D/DB,
Paris. Page 9: Edoardo Fornaciari
© Gamma, Paris. Page 10 (left): ©
Association Frères
Lumière/Roger-Viollet, Paris. Page
11 (below):© Soazig
Collection/Explorer, Paris. Pages
15 (left), 18 (above), 19, 20, 36,
37, 38 (above), 39, 45, 47, 53
(below), 55 (above), 60, 61, 62,
63, 64, 73 (below), 78 (above): ©
Cahiers du Cinéma Collection,
Paris. Page 17 (above): © Walt
Disney/PR0D/DB, Paris. Pages
21, 69: Fabian © Sygma, Paris.
Pages 22, 80 (below), 81 (below):
© Sunset Boulevard/Sygma,
Paris. Page 25: Nikos
Panayotopoulos © Sygma, Paris.
Pages 26-27: B. Barbier © Sygma,
Paris. Page 27: V. Brynner ©
Gamma, Paris. Pages 29, 38
(below): © Régis d'Audeville,
Paris. Page 30: © Stéphane
Herbert, Paris. Page 31 (below): ©
Tadeusz Paksula, Paris. Pages 34
(above), 54: © Association des
Trois Mondes Collection, Paris.
Pages 34 (below), 86: All Rights
Reserved. Pages 35, 55 (below),
70-71: © Cinéstar, Paris. Page 42:
© Giraudon/SPADEM, Paris.
Pages 49, 50, 51, 52: © Institut du
Monde Arabe Collection, Paris.
Page 53 (above): © Niels Boel,
Copenhagen. Page 56: © José
Carlos Avellar, Rio de Janeiro.
Page 58: © Mexican Institute of
Cinematography, Mexico City.
Page 59: © Imcine/Mexican
Institute of Cinematography,
Mexico City. Page 65: Julio
Donoso © Sygma, Paris. Page 66:
© Sygma, Paris. Page 68 (left): ©
Piero Guerrinl/Gamma, Paris.
Pages 72, 73 (above): ©
ATM/Ferid Boughedir Collection,
Paris. Page 74: © Gamma, Paris.
Pages 75, 76 (above): Alex Bailey
© Sygma, Paris. Page 76 (below):
© CATS/KIPA, Paris. Page 77: © F.
Apesteguy © Gamma, Paris. Page
79: Georges Pierre © Sygma,
Paris. Page 80 (above): © Studio
X, Paris. Page 82: UNESCO-lnes
Forbes. Page 83: UNESCO. Page
88: © A. Ripinski. Page 89: © U.
Mukhamedzanov, V. Likhanov.
Photos © copyright ATM are stills
from films which may be obtained
from: Médiathèque des Trois
Mondes, 63 bis, Rue du Cardinal
Lemoine, 75005 Paris.
Tel: (33) 1 43 54 33 38;
Fax: (33) 1 46 34 70 19.
]]>
</page>
<page number="91">
<![CDATA[
International Poster Competition
To mark the United Nations
Year for Tolerance, Unesco's
NGO (Non-Governmental
Organization) Standing
Committee is organizing a
poster competition on the
theme of tolerance in daily
life.
The French composer
Jean-Michel Jarre, a Unesco Goodwill
Ambassador, is president of the jury,
whose members are drawn from all
parts of the world.
The poster that wins first
prize will be published
and distributed
worldwide. An exhibition
of the 50 best designs will
be held in all the cities
hosting Jean-Michel
Jarre's musical
spectaculars in 1996.
Prizes include: one Bangkok-Paris
return ticket, two Brussels-New York
return tickets, art books, sweat-shirts,
model cars.
Closing date for receipt of entries: 15 September 1995
For the rules of the competition, contact: NGO Standing Committee,
Unesco, 1, Rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15
Tel: (33-1 ) 45 68 32 68 Fax: (33-1 ) 45 66 03 37
II ES
i
i
"Restore a film with Unesco"
Unesco ¡s launching an international
fund-raising campaign to restore
films threatened with deterioration.
The aim is to alert world opinion to
the urgent need to safeguard the
world cinematographic heritage and
to provide an opportunity for as many
people as possible to be directly
associated with this effort.
Unesco is calling on private
individuals, foundations and other
institutions, businesses and
governments to join a broad
international movement to preserve
this part of the common heritage of
humankind.
Donors, whatever their means,
can make a personal contribution to
the restoration of a film of their
choice and thus be associated with
an important Unesco mission,
assuring "the conservation and
protection of the world's inheritance
of works of art and monuments of
history and science."
With widespread public backing,
Unesco will be in a strong position to
call on governments, the film
industry and specialized bodies to
step up their efforts to safeguard the
cinematographic heritage.
Unesco also wishes to work in
partnership with private companies
and foundations, with official
government bodies and with the
media to ensure that the "Restore a
film with Unesco" operation will have
a considerable impact and
attract wide support for efforts to
safeguard the world
cinematographic heritage.
For further information and/or to
send a subscription, please write to:
"Restore a film with Unesco"
Programme,
Unesco,
7 Place de Fontenoy,
75007 Paris, France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="92">
<![CDATA[
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(SEPTEMBER 1995):
WOMEN TODAY
INTERVIEW WITH THE BRAZILIAN PIANIST
NELSON FREIRÉ
HERITAGE
A BAROQUE CITY IN MEXICO
ENVIRONMENT:
DRY LANDS AND DESERTS
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamenta
freedoms.. .without distinction of race, sex, language or religion..."
]]>
</page>
</document>
