<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="101119eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
	.	
women
one half, of heaven
*
c
M 1205-9509- 22,00 F .
BEIJING:
THE FOURTH WORLD
CONFERENCE ON WOMEN
INTERVIEW WITH .
. NELSON FREIRÉ
HERITAGE: ,
BAROQUE ZACATECAS
ENVIRONMENT:
DRYLANDS AND DESERTS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
woman
Federico Mayor
Woman,
you brought with you
a new song.
But we did not let you
speak out
although yours
is the voice
ofhalf
the earth.
Woman,
your eyes
saw the world
another way.
But we did not want
to know the meaning
and the warmth
ofyour vision.
Woman,
you carried under your skin
ofall colours
the seed
of the future,
the light
which could illuminate
differentpaths,
rebellious
yetpeaceful ways,
woman-bridge
woman-bond
woman-root
andfruit of love
and tenderness.
Woman,
your hands outstretched
and your open arms
enfold the immensity
of refuge
and of comfort.
But we have not understood
the strength ofyour embrace
nor the cry ofyour silence,
amd we carry on
with neither compass
nor relief.
Woman,
with no other master
but yourself,
live
from now on
equal andfree,
now as companion
sharing
the same dream
for ever.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
SEPTEMBER 1995
Cover:
Stars in the night sky.
, Rigoberta Menchú,
i witness to an age
\ Commentary by Federico Mayor
Interview with Nelson Freiré
38 1995: UNITED NATIONS YEAR FOR TOLERANCE
A triptych by Sofia Gandarias
The art of Inference
by Sami Na'ir
40 HERITAGE
Baroque Zacatecas
by Francisco Segovia
43 GREENWATCH
Drylands and deserts
by France Bequette
50 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
one half of heaven
5 A time for partnership
by Riane Eisler
The North: a disturbing independence
An interview with Betty Friedan
The South: a joint struggle
An interview with Aminata Traoré
12 Pride without prejudice
by Anees Jung
15 A bank that only lends to the poor
An interview with Muhammad Yunus
Three women from Pakistan
by Attiya Inayatullah
Going it alone
by Christine Catarino and Laura Oso
21 Africa's invisible women
by Patricia Made
The Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo
by Alicia Dujovne Ortiz
26 Somalia: the great escape
by Hassan Keynan
Norwegian politics bridges the gender gap
by Hege Skjeie
Lithuania: the first statute for women
by Ugné Karvelis
Men supporting women
by Michael S. Kimmel
II Are men and women on the same wavelength?
by Catherine Vidal
The road to Beijing
An interview with Ingeborg Breines
34 Fact file
Women Nobel Laureates
Consultant: Ingeborg Breines
"The Governments of the States parties to this Constitution on behalf of their peoples declare,
"that since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed . . .
"that a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the
unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the
intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
"For these reasons, the States parties ... are agreed and determined to develop and to increase the means of communication between their
peoples and to employ these means for the purposes of mutual understanding and a truer and more perfect knowledge of each other's lives. ..."
EXTRACT FROM THE PREAMBLE TO THE CONSTITUTION OF UNESCO. LONDON. 16 NOVEMBER 1945
TBfe UNESCO
Courier
48th year
Published monthly in
30 languages and in Braille
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE. UNESCO
(TXIRIER
48th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational. Scientific and Cultural
Organization.
31. rue François Bonvin. 75732 Pais CEDEX 15, France.
Fax: (331) 45.66.92.70
Internet: unesco. courier@unesco.org
Director: Bahgat Elnadi
Editor-in-chief: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition: Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Miguel Labarca, Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey (Tel. 45.68.46.90)
Documentation: José Banaag (Tel. 45.68. 46.85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Belin (Tel. 45.68.46.87)
Secretariat: Annie Brächet (Tel. 45.68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant: Tneresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean: Mouna Chatta (Tel. 45.68.47.14)
Artwork Consultants: Eric Frogé
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: El-Said Mahmoud El-Sheniti (Cairo)
Italian: ¡Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Claude Montrieux (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Moacyr A. Fioravante (Rio de Janeiro}
Urdu: Javaid Iqbal Syed (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras - Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kang Woo-hyon (Seoul)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dares-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek: Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish: Katri Himma (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai: Sudhasinee Vajrabul (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Ukrainian: Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician: Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION. Fax: 45.68.45.89
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy (Tel. 45.68.45.65),
Jocelyne Despouy, Jacqueline Louise-Julie, Manichan
Ngonekeo, Michel Ravassard. Mohamed Salah El Din (Tel.
45.68.49.19:
Customer service: Ginette Motreff (Tel. 45.68.45.64)
Accounts: (Tel. 45.68.45.65)
Shipping: Daniel Meister (Tel. 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS. Tel.: 45.68.45.65
1 year: 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 Frenen francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries:
1 year: 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads 'Reprinted from the Unesco Couner", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed anieles
reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by
an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessanly represent the opinions of Unesco
or those of the editors of the Uhlsco Courier. Photo captions and headlines
are written by the Umsco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply officia: endorsement or acceptance Oy Unesco
or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2)
University Microfilms (Xeroxi. Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100 U.S.A.: (3) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head Inc., ill West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A.:
(4) Bell and Howeil Co.. Old Mansfield Road, Wooster. Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE ¡Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL: Cl - SEPTEMBRE 1995
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES N.M.P.P.
Photocomposition, photogravure: Le Courrier de ¡'Unesco.
Impression: MAURV IMPRIMEUR.
Z.l. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malsherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N" 9-1995-OPI-95-540 A
onth by month
The women's liberation movement has a long history, but it is only in the last
twenty-five years that it has become a world phenomenon. In the countries of the
South the conditions in which women as a group could set forth their demands
did not come about until the end of the colonial period, with the gradual opening
up of societies that had hitherto been cut off from the rest of the world, the under¬
mining of patriarchal systems, and the coming of a time when the members of the
new middle classes began to express their identity as individuals.
The shock waves that had radiated from the United States and Europe in the
nineteenth century and had reached upper-class Indian, Chinese and Egyptian
women in the years after the First World War now began to have a worldwide
impact.
As it passed beyond the pioneering stage and won an immense popular fol¬
lowing, the women's emancipation movement gained in effectiveness what it may
have lost in radical spirit. No longer to be regarded as one side in a war between
the sexes, it has become part of a political, social, legal and personal struggle
against power and behaviour patterns based on inequality. Women engaged in this
struggle find themselves confronting men and even sometimes other women; but
they also find that more and more men are joining their ranks.
The purpose of the struggle is that women should fulfil themselves in equal
dignity with men; find scope for their talents in all the areas and at all the levels
of responsibility that have until now been an exclusively male preserve; and have
the same social rights as men and above all the same chances of success. Per¬
haps it is even more important that they should make their contribution to
humankind's attempts to answer basic questionsabout life and death, the
family and society, economic development and the future of the world.
Self-expression by women on equal terms with men in every area of lifeper¬
sonal, social, physical, intellectual and spiritualis liberating tremendous cre¬
ative and productive forces, encouraging new forms of participation and at the
same time changing men's attitudes.
The oppression of women within the family has been at the heart of all social
domination systems for thousands of years. The ending of this oppression may lead
eventually to the collapse of other forms of domination. In this process our
common future is at stake.
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4 page insert between
pages 2-3 and 50-51.
BAHGAT ELNADI AND ADEL RIFAAT
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
A timeforpartnership
by Riane Eisler
Today's questioning of sex roles and
relations is part of a broader
movement towards greater
democracy and egalitarianism
rl Men are from Mars, proclaims a recent
book title, and women are from Venus.
This two-planet image vividly expresses the lin¬
gering belief that women and men are funda¬
mentally and unalterably different.
But if it were true that women and men are
inherently so different, how is it that their dif¬
ferences differ so much from one time and place
to another? For example, in Victorian England
the mark of real femininity was a "ladylike"
paleness and weakness, whereas in Kenya real
femininity was traditionally proved by a
woman's ability to do very hard work on behalf
of her family. In the Samurai Age ofJapan, real
masculinity was proving oneself a fierce warrior,
whereas among the Hopi Indians of North
America men were supposed to be peaceful,
agreeable, and non-aggressive.
Not only that, but over the last decades the
roles and relations of women and men have
been changing at a very rapid pace. For example,
large numbers of women have in many Western
nations begun to do things that were once con¬
sidered exclusively men's work, such as the
work of doctors, plumbers, engineers, lawyers,
welders and university professors all highly-
paid professions and trades from which women
were once barred. Similarly, men have begun to
redefine fathering to include some of the
"women's work" of feeding, diapering, and oth¬
erwise caring for and nurturing babies.
Moreover, even against enormous resistance,
women's and men's relations have gradually
become more egalitarian. At the same time,
although more slowly, once firmly entrenched
beliefs that men, and what men do, are more
important than women and what women do,
have also begun to change with such com¬
monplace remarks as "hope next time it's a boy"
increasingly considered offensive by both new
mothers and fathers.
For some people, both women and men,
these changes are a source of hope for a more
humane, less violent, less unjust future: one
where one kind of person (be it a person of a dif¬
ferent race, nationality, religion or sex) is no
longer viewed as of a lower order than another.
But for others, these changes are a source of
confusion and fear, yet another complexity to be
dealt with in a far too rapidly changing world.
Women, men and human relations
It is certainly true that our world has been
changing very fast over the last few hundred
years, so fast that, in the words of the futurolo-
gist Alvin Toffler, it has put some people in
"future shock". Rapid technological and eco¬
nomic changes have destabilized not only estab¬
lished habits of work, but long-standing habits
of thinking and acting. This has been the source
of much dislocation and stress. But as modern
history drastically demonstrates, technological
and economic change has also opened the door
Two surgeons, a woman
and a man, perform an
operation together (France).
Rosa Luxemburg (1870-1919),
revolutionary and political
theorist, Germany/Poland.
Florence Nightingale
(1820-1910), nurse,
United Kingdom
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
"As we can still see today
from their beautiful
nature-celebrating art, the
Minoans of Crete also seem to
have had a great respect not
only for women but for our
Mother Earth: what we today
would call an ecological
consciousness."
Above, a detail from a
fresco in the Palace of Knossos
(1600-1400 B.C.) in Crete.
RIANE EISLER,
of the United States, is co-
founder of the Center for
Partnership Studies in
California. She is the author of
many articles and books,
notably The Chalice and The
Blade: Our History, Our Future
(Harper and Row, San Francisco,
1990), which has been widely
translated. Her most recent
work, Sacred Pleasure: Sex,
Myth and the Politics of the
Body, has just been published.
for questioning much that was once taken for
granted be it the once supposedly divinely-
ordained right of kings and princes to absolute
authority, or the once also supposedly divinely-
ordained right of men to absolute authority in
the "castles" of their homes.
The questioning we see all over the world
today of sex roles and relations is thus part of a
much larger questioning. It is also part of a
much larger movement for change: the global
movement toward more democratic and egali¬
tarian relations in both the so-called private and
public spheres.
In fact, once we examine the constant interac¬
tion between the private and public spheres, it is
possible to see patterns or connexions that were
invisible in older studies, because these focused
almost exclusively on the public or men's world
from which women and children were excluded.
These patterns or connexions show something
that once articulated seems self-evident: that the
way a society organizes the roles and relations of
the two halves of humanity which is what men
and women are profoundly affects everything in
our lives.
For example, how these roles and relations are
organized is a critical factor in how a society
structures the family. Societies where women's and
men's roles are rigidly circumscribed, which are
generally also rigidly male-dominated societies,
are by and large also societies where we see a
generally authoritarian, top-down family struc¬
ture. Even more specifically, it tends to be a family
where men rule over women and parents rule
over children, with this rule ultimately backed up
by fear and force. On the other hand, societies
where women's and men's roles are more flexible
and there is more equality between women and
men tend to have more democratic families, with
less socially condoned use of fear and force.
Moreover, societies characterized by more
rigid male dominance (where sex roles are also
more rigid) are generally also more authoritarian.
For example, with the rise to power of Hitler in
Germany and the imposition of a brutally author¬
itarian and very violent regime, there was much
emphasis on returning women to their "tradi¬
tional" roles in a male-dominated family. Con¬
versely, in the Scandinavian nations, strong
emphasis on sexual equality has gone along with
both political and economic democracy, as well
as with social priority given to activities stereo-
typically associated with women such as child
care, health care and environmental housekeeping.
A new view of the paît
Further light is shed on these connexions by
archaeological studies such as those of the
Lithuanian-American archaeologist Marija
Gimbutas, the British archaeologist James Mel-
laart, and the Greek archaeologist Nicolas
Platon. These studies indicate that, contrary to
what we have been taught, the earliest cradles of
civilization were not authoritarian, male-dom¬
inant and chronically warlike. There are strong
indications that these prehistoric societies (for
example, Catal Huyuk in Turkey, which dates
back approximately 8,000 years) were more
peaceful and egalitarian societies in which, sig¬
nificantly, women were not dominated by men.
Thus, Platon notes that in the highly techno¬
logically developed Minoan civilization that flour¬
ished on the Mediterranean island of Crete
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
approximately 3,500 years ago the influence of
women is evident, and that this was a remarkably
peaceful and prosperous society in which "the
whole of life was pervaded by an ardent faith in the
goddess Nature." As we can still see today from
their beautiful nature-celebrating art, the Minoans
also seem to have had a great respect not only for
women but for our Mother Earth: what we today
would call an ecological consciousness.
So here again we see the variability of
women's and men's roles and relations, and how
these roles and relations are affected by, and in
turn affect, social structure. We see that stereo-
typically "feminine" values such as nurturance
and non-violence can be embraced by men, and
that women can take on stereotypically "mas¬
culine" roles of social and religious governance.
Most important, we see that neither war nor
the war of the sexes is inevitable.
But I want to emphasize an important matter.
There is no evidence that, because women in these
societies seem to have held high social and religious
positions, men were dominated by women. In
other words, these societies were neither matri¬
archies nor patriarchies. They conformed more to
what I would call a partnership rather than a
dominator model of social organization: a form of
organization that offers a viable alternative to the
complex tensions that are inherent in relations
based on domination and subordination.
(j'ender equity and quality of life
Indeed, if we re-examine modern history from
this larger perspective, we see that underneath its
many complex currents and cross-currents lies
a powerful movement towards a partnership
social organization, countered by strong resis¬
tance to it. We see that all the modern progres¬
sive movements have basically been movements
challenging different forms of domination
backed by force and fear. This is the common
thread in the eighteenth- and nineteenth-century
rights of man, anti-slavery, anti-monarchist,
socialist, pacifist and feminist movements. In
the same way, the twentieth-century anti-colo¬
nialist, anti-war, participatory democracy,
women's rights and economic justice move¬
ments are not isolated phenomena. They are all
part of a much larger movement: the movement
to create a world in which be it in our global
family of nations or in our individual families
principles of partnership rather than domination
and submission are primary.
Moreover, we see that the contemporary
movement toward gender equity is an integral
part of this larger partnership movement. This
should not surprise us, since the domination of
one half of humanity by the other is a basic
model for all forms of domination. Conversely,
the equal valuing of the two halves of humanity
teaches children from early on to value diversity,
rather than seeing it as a reason for ranking
"superior" people over "inferior" ones.
This is why those parts of our world where
the movement to raise the status of women has
been most successful are also more generally
democratic. Even beyond this, a recent statistical
survey of eighty-nine countries conducted by
the Center for Partnership Studies indicates that
if the movement towards sexual equality con¬
tinues, we can also predict a generally higher
quality of life for all.
This study, entitled "Gender Equity and the
Quality of Life", shows the Scandinavian nations
on the average with both the highest gender
equity and the highest quality of life. It also ver¬
ifies that there is a strong correlation between, on
the one hand, such gender inequity indicators
as substantially lower female than male literacy,
high maternal mortality, and low female partic¬
ipation in government and, on the other, indica¬
tors of a generally lower quality of life for all
such as high infant mortality, a high number of
refugees fleeing a country, and a high ratio of
Gross Domestic Product going to the wealthiest
as opposed to the poorest 20 per cent of the pop¬
ulation. Furthermore, the study indicates that
areas where the movement for women's rights has
made the least progress also tend to be those
where human rights ratings are generally lower.
In short, the way in which a society struc¬
tures the relations between women and men is of
profound personal, social and economic signifi¬
cance. It is encouraging that many governments
worldwide are beginning to pass laws to equalize
the position of women and men, following the
provisions of the United Nations Convention on
the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination
against Women. This will obviously vastly
improve women's quality of life. But it is also
essential if we are to move to a world of greater
partnership and peace, not only between men and
women but between the diverse nations, races,
religions and ethnic groups on our planet. H
. ^
J#BÊ/'
Anna Pavlova
(1881-1931), dancer,
Russia.
Petra Kelly (1947-1992),
politician (ecologist movement),
Germany.
A family in a Burkina Faso
village.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Betty Friedan THE NORTH
A DISTURBING INDEPENDENCE
8
The well-known American feminist writer and organizer Betty Friedan is the
author of TheFeminineMystique (1963), a classic of feminist literature. In 1966 she
founded the National Organization for Women (NOW), whose goals included the
legalization of abortion and recognition of the principle of equal pay for equal work.
Women's movements are now at least thirty
years old in the West. What progress has been
made in that time?
The modern women's movement began thirty
years ago, but the battle for women's rights began
a hundred years ago and seemed to end, in the
United States at any rate, in 1920 when women
won the right to vote. In 1963, when my book The
Feminine Mystique came out, the only image of
woman was that defined solely in terms of her
sexual relation to man as wife, as mother, as house¬
wife not as a person defining herself through her
own actions in society.
That image became especially pervasive in the
years after the Second World War when the men
came back from the war and took their jobs back,
and women, who had been working, had to return
home again. During the Depression and the war
there had been two generations of women who
had not had babies. Now they started to have babies
again, and industry needed them as housewives to
sell to. The old image of a woman's place being in
the home came back in the majority of women in
America used to work a little before marriage, but
basically they married and had children. Very few
women who didn't marry worked outside the
home. Anyway, the story of the battle for women's
rights seemed to be over.
History books date the beginning of the modern
feminist movement to my book because I broke
through the feminine mystique and stated that
women are persons and as such are entitled to their
human and American birthright: equality of oppor¬
tunity and the right to have their voices heard when
society takes decisions.
Over the last thirty years in the United States
and elsewhere women's movements have been
fighting for equal opportunities in education and
employment, for women to control their own
bodies, for the right to choose. Women have fought
to define ground-rules in fields and professions
such as the law and medicine which had hitherto
been defined only by men in terms of male experi¬
ence. In the United States we have succeeded to a
large extent in achieving those objectives. We have
laws on equal opportunity, employment and edu¬
cation. We have made sex discrimination illegal in
the way that race discrimination is supposed to be
illegal.
Women now occupy management and leader¬
ship positions in every field and profession. They
make 70 cents for every dollar men make. Their
enrolment rates in medical and law schools have
risen from 4 per cent to nearly 50 per cent. Women
who used to cook the church suppers are now
preaching the sermons. They are showing new
styles of leadership in management. They have
become empowered politically, and their votes can
be decisive in elections. Far more women have been
elected to national, state and city offices than ever
before, and more women are being named as judges.
What areas remain unconquered for women?
Has there been a backlash?
It's hard to overestimate how vast the changes
have been! In most Western countries and increas¬
ingly in the developing countries there is a growing
feminist consciousness. Women take for granted
that they are entitled to equal opportunity, that
they have the ability and the right to choose.
But yes, there has been a backlash in the United
States, and it is partly due to economic turmoil.
There has been increasing economic polarization
the top 1 per cent control 40 per cent of the wealth
of the nation. The ranks of the poor and homeless,
large numbers of whom are women, are growing,
and the middle class has its back to the wall. Middle-
class families in America survive because there are
two incomes, and the great majority of women
work outside the home and earn roughly half the
family income. But women's jobs are increasingly
contract-work, without health benefits and security.
Downsizing means that jobs are disappearing and
more and more workers are being laid off. The
main victims of this are men, the so-called "angry
white males." Their frustration is funneled and
manipulated into a backlash against women and
racial minorities. In the United States, they are
trying to cut out programmes for women, chil¬
dren, the elderly and the poor. They are pitting
white men against blacks, women and immigrants,
and they are trying to get rid of affirmative action
CONTINUED ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Aminata Traoré THE SOUTH
A JOINT STRUGGLE
Aminata Traoré (see "Five women in the spotlight", page 34) is a Malian social
psychologist whose extensive fieldwork has brought her wide first-hand
experience of African conditions. In Mali she has founded a cultural centre (the
Santoro) and the Hampâté Bâ cultural centre.
The women's liberation movement in the West
began about thirty years ago. What has it brought
to the women of the South?
I can't speak for all the women of the South. I
can only express my opinion as a black woman
from sub-Saharan Africa who thinks that her des¬
tiny is closely linked to that of her continent and
that she has no right to be fighting the wrong
battle. I think I can say that broadly speaking we
African women are determined to distinguish our¬
selves from Western feminism. Many women's
associations in Africa insist on being regarded as
"feminine" rather than "feminist".
I would add that I respect the struggle waged by
Western feminists. That struggle is motivated by
their own specific experience of life and pain, which
I have no right to interpret or judge. I would be
happy if this rule of mutual respect and reciprocity
could also be applied to their relationships with the
women of the South. That is not always the case.
They have appropriated to themselves the right
to interfere in our affairs, to dissect and pass judge¬
ment on them and to draw conclusions that have
sometimes become action programmes against
which we can do nothing.
This intrusion into our societies, where the
priorities are different, blocks our view of the
horizon, displaces our familiar landmarks and puts
us in a state of dependence that we should no
longer accept.
Can the principle of equal rights between men
and women be adapted to the societies of the
South?
Equal rights is a rallying cry that nowadays
has a meaning and an emotional charge so intense
that it is hard to shrug them off. But the lessons of
our own history suggest that we should give a
more qualified answer to this question.
Surprising though it may seem, I would say that
the right to difference and to life that is denied us
as dominated black people is more important to me
than the race to achieve a hypothetical equality
between the sexes. Furthermore, I am not ready to
make war on my African brothers with the
weapons of Western feminists. I'm more keen on
finding common ground with them so that together
we can extract our continent from the economic,
financial and political situation that is jeopardizing
our common future.
I suffer less from sexism than from racism,
against which I am far more helpless. But racism
doesn't attract as much interest or energy as fem¬
inism. Why is this so? Why do we need to be more
active and more determined in the struggle against
one form of oppression than another? Who decides
the priorities?
Structural adjustment programmes and dra-
conian measures such as the devaluation of 12 Jan¬
uary 1991 that overnight deprived millions of
women in French-speaking Africa of the bare
necessities (essential foodstuffs, health care,
drinking water and school supplies for children),
are only half-heartedly condemned. In situations
of serious deprivation like these, where men,
women and children are living on the edge of sur¬
vival, what matters is solidarity between the sexes
rather than equal rights.
Most Western feminists have gone over to the
neo-liberals in their international institutions for
funding development. Together they want to liberate
us from our cultural realities which they regard as
archaic, and from our governments which they con¬
sider to be corrupt. Privatization and decentraliza¬
tion seem to have become synonymous with
women's liberation in the poor countries!
Concentration on equality between men and
women is part and parcel of a social model based on
competition where man is a predator on man and
even more so on woman. Our situation is dif¬
ferent. If equality between men and women is to
replace older forms of solidarity in our societies, it
is for African women to take that decision and to
organize themselves accordingly.
What are the major demands of women in the
South? How can their status be improved by inte¬
grating them into the economy?
The struggle against humiliation and destruc¬
tion should be one of the main commitments of
women in the South, especially the women of
Africa south of the Sahara. I don't think that going
to Beijing with women from other regions of the
world should make us lose sight of the grave prob¬
lems facing our continent. In my opinion, the pri-
orities are as follows: SI
CONTINUED ON PAGE 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 8 the enforcement of the laws on sex discrimination
and race discrimination.
The backlash is also taking the form of attempts
by fundamentalist religious groups to undo the
right to abortion, the right of women to control
their own bodies, in short, to push women back
into the home again. I think in many countries
there is an uneasiness about women's growing
independence.
Is the quest for equality between women and
men continuing?
There must be equality of opportunities
between men and women. In many countries
women have no control over property or inheri¬
tance, and aren't allowed to earn. They are depen¬
dent on men, and in every single profession the
ground-rules are defined by men. When women can
move as equals in society because of what they
have achieved, their voices and experiences have a
special value because they have fought for equal
opportunity.
well as an ability to mobilize people for a common
goal and a common vision.
What are your hopes for the Beijing conference
and for the future?
It is clear that women will not be pushed back
and that going forward no longer means just the
fight for women's rights; it's no longer just a ques¬
tion of women being paid equally to men. There
must be a bridging between women and men. There
must be a new vision of community that inspires the
restructuring of work and home. New importance
must be attached to community networks and ser¬
vices. The priority must be to achieve a good life for
everyone women, men, children, the elderly and
the poor, young and old, black and white and to
bring to an end the polarizing differences that are
still tearing our nations and our world apart.
Interview by Judithe Bizot
10
In all societies, in both the North and the South,
the liberation of women has led to outbreaks of vio¬
lence against women. Why is this?
Violence is a symptom of the prevailing eco¬
nomic stress and the polarization between the
wealthy and the poor. In the United States men,
including college-educated whites, can no longer
take a career, a profession and life-long dominance for
granted. These are times of turmoil. Men are more
dependent than ever on women. Also women are
now reporting the violence battering and rape
more often than they did. Before, it was considered
a man's right to beat up his wife. But this violence
shouldn't be seen in terms of sexual politics. Women
are being treated as a scapegoat for the increasing eco¬
nomic pressures on men. It is not enough to have
shelters for battered women and to take punitive
measures against men. Women must come up with
a new vision of community with men.
What particular qualities do women bring to the
workplace and to management?
Women are showing new styles of leadership in
management that seem to be very well geared to
today's society and economy, which put a pre¬
mium on flexibility and the ability to adjust to
change. What seems to emerge from studies as I
know from my experience as a consultant to a
number of large companies and to the U.S. army
is that in a crisis and conditions of enormous change,
the hierarchical chain of command and the military
model of control break down. There has to be flex¬
ibility, there has to be non-hierarchical, autonomous
responsibility. Women bring this to the table as
A demonstration of
solidarity at the Third
United Nations World
Conference on Women,
held in Nairobi (Kenya)
in 1985.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 9 a) dismantling the mechanisms of poverty and
exclusion and freeing financial resources. This
approach goes far beyond the anti-poverty pro¬
grammes that are currently being considered. In
this regard African women must be able to dis¬
mantle the mechanisms of development funding,
and above all the way in which debts are contracted;
b) democratization, which will guarantee
African men and women the right to decide for
themselves and challenge their governments and
their foreign partners;
c) the strengthening, through information and
training, of women's decision-making powers and
their capacity to act.
In both North and South it is clear that women's
liberation has led to a rise in violence on the part
of men. Is it unrealistic to look for solutions to
this worldwide trend?
I shouldn't really answer this question since I
refuse to equate the liberation of women with
equal rights with men. In our countries every¬
body's rights economic, political and cultural
are flouted and not only because of the regimes cur¬
rently in power. Where violence perpetrated by
men is concerned, I should simply like to point out
that human beings men, women, children, young
and old all need their social, professional and
economic roles to be recognized. These roles can
change gradually without major upsets or disrup¬
tions. The frustrations this may cause must be
dealt with by mutual concessions on the part of
those involved.
Once men have lost their jobs they don't know
which way to turn. Is it really so surprising that
they grow violent towards women and children?
They are more to be pitied than blamed. When
will we understand the complexity of the under¬
lying factors that determine human behaviour and
personal relationships?
What are you hoping for in the foreseeable
future?
In Africa the greatest impediments to women's
advancement are economic and political. But inter¬
national thinking merely condemns our societies
and our cultures. The fact is that many parents
would like their daughters to attend school and
complete their studies. Farmers would like their
wives to work less and have access to health care
and drinkable water. Most men would like their
wives to have a paid job. What stands in the way of
all this? An unfair economic and financial system
that leaves vulnerable groups few opportunities
for survival. We lack resources, indigenous exper¬
tise and appropriate methodologies.
Interview by Judithe Bizot
and Daniele Granet
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Pride withoutprejudice
South Asian women question oppressive traditions
A scroll-assisted lecture on
breast-feeding in Calcutta
(India).
"I have a better life today than I did when
my husband was alive," said Zapathan. A
statement like this from a Muslim widow in
Bangladesh would have been unthinkable
twenty years ago, and I was taken by surprise
when Zapathan made it. Sitting on a wobbly
chair, her feet twisted in plastic sandals that did
not match, she uttered the words without a
trace of guilt or embarrassment. The thought
that she was dishonouring a very old tradition
did not seem to worry her. She had expressed a
truth that thousands of impoverished women in
Bangladesh are beginning to share, though few
have yet begun to voice.
Dangladesh: a merry widow
Zapathan lives in a tiny village in Mirzapur. I met
her on the premises of the Grameen Bank1,
where a group of needy women had gathered to
collect a modest loan that would help them start
a small business, repair a leaking roof or educate
a child. The Grameen Bank's revolutionary
12
lending system ensures that husbands, sons or
fathers are no longer necessary to help women
procure money. A thumb mark that once
labelled a woman as backward is today the sig¬
nature that gets her a loan. It is the first step that
leads her to write her own name.
"No one asked me my name before," said
Zapathan, saying her name with pride. "While
my husband lived, I was his wife, his follower.
His word was law." Her husband's law, like
that of a king, prevailed in a domain where he
had little to protect except a wife. It made her
helpless, faceless. Not even the neighbours were
aware of her existence. His death opened the
door, brought her out of her house and her vil¬
lage and led her to the Grameen Bank, which has
helped her more than any relative would have
done.
"Those unknown men to whom I could not
even talk trusted me and gave me a loan. When
I first held 500 takas, my hands trembled." She
raised her hand in a salute, a gesture that spoke
of power.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A traditional marriage
in a Rajasthan village (India).
India: access to credit
The Working Women's Forum in Madras, South
India, all of whose members are needy working
women, is driven by the same spirit as the
Grameen Bank. As well as providing loans, the
Forum organizes training and consciousness-
raising activities, night schools for children, and
family planning and health-care programmes. It
encourages inter-caste marriages and helps fight
exploitation, harassment and government
obstructionism.
In the last ten years, as the movement has
spread, the courage and commitment of its mem¬
bers have grown and they have begun to speak
out in public and become leaders. They have
learnt to stand up to policemen, government
officials, even cabinet ministers. "Why not hus¬
bands ?" I asked a group of them. They laughed
and slowly told me their fears. "He drinks and
beats me," said one. "Why don't you hit him
back?" I asked provocatively. "That's not our
Tamil tradition," she answered. "Why does he
beat you?" I asked. "Because he earns," she
replied. "But you earn too". "He earns more."
"If my husband did that to me, I would leave
him," said a dark young woman who was not
yet married. "You can't divorce and marry
again," said the older woman. "No, I won't
remarry. I will take a job and bring up my chil¬
dren," answered the young woman. "I thought
wisdom came with age," the old woman sighed.
"Now the young ones know better than the
old ones like me."
"The time is not far off when donkeys will
neigh and women will demand to sit on chairs,"
said a village elder in Gujarat, western India, as
he pulled at his hubble bubble.
I akistan: urbanization, the motor of change
"Change is coming, and it is coming faster than
people think," says Akhtar Hameed, the archi¬
tect of the Orangi Pilot Project in Karachi, Pak¬
istan. "Under the pressure of mass migration to
the cities and double-digit inflation the role of
women is changing dramatically. Urbanization
changes attitudes and breaks up traditions. Since
one income is no longer enough, women have
Dolores Ibarrurl, "La Pasionaria"
(1895-1989), political militant,
Spain.
Eleanor Roosevelt (1884-1962),
human rights militant,
United States.
'
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A journalist looks over the
latest issues of Dabindu ("Tears
of Sweat"), a newspaper
published by a women's
community development project
in Kataniyaka, on the outskirts
of Colombo (Sri Lanka). The
newspaper exposes the
oppression of women and
advises them how to stand up
for themselves.
14
ANEES JUNG,
an Indian writer and journalist, is
Special Adviser to the Director-
General of Unesco on issues
concerning women. She is the
author of a number of books,
including Unveiling IndiaA
Woman's Journey and Seven
SistersAmong the Women of
South Asia.
begun to work. The extended family is already
beginning to yield to the nuclear family. With
women having jobs and education becoming
imperative, the rate of population growth is
bound to slow down. This will happen in urban
areas first, then spread to the villages. It is only
a matter of time. What is happening in Orangi
is happening everywhere."
Orangi encourages women not to be depen¬
dent and urges them to turn their homes into
workshops. Family businesses sprout in every
lane, and women have begun to be entrepre¬
neurs. The Orangi Trust gives loans to units
where 40 per cent of the workers are women.
Almost 350 units are managed entirely by
women, including stitching centres, general
stores, schools, clinics, beauty parlours and
embroidery workshops. A recent survey of 585
of Orangi's schools showed that 45 per cent of
the 80,000 students were girls. Almost 90 per
cent of Orangi's schools are co-educational, and
68 per cent of the teachers are female. "These
women and girls," says Akhtar Hameed, "are
not in purdah as my mother was. And yet they
retain their modesty and their culture. Although
they are not wrapped in the chador or confined
within four walls, their conduct is not very dif¬
ferent from my mother's. Women who belong
both to the present and the past, they are the
finest achievement of Orangi."
Nepal: the burden of tradition
The image of Nepali rural women that remains in
my mind is that of a creature under a basket of hay
or manure, a metaphor that goes beyond her
working life. "Women have yet to learn to artic¬
ulate their feelings and anxieties," says Greta Ran,
who has launched a magazine about women and
called it "Donkey", to match her perception of the
peasant woman as a beast of burden. Greta Ran
feels that women are conditioned to be silent
beasts of burden and that if they begin to have indi¬
vidual feelings they suffer from a sense of guilt.
Indira Koirala, who works with village women
at the grassroots level and has just launched a self-
reliance project, does not agree. "Women are
acquiring the confidence to change their work
patterns but not their lives," she says. "They still
can't survive independently. They need more
time." Since her project began, she has seen a
change in them. When a group is formed and
given a name, the women feel they have found an
identity. They are no longer just wives or mothers;
they have the status of members of a group.
"Change is inevitable," said an old Nepali
woman named Aama, the Nepali word for
"mother". "Even the trails of my youth have
changed. I have seen streams and rivers change
their courses." Poor and uneducated, she has
watched the ebb and flow of life, not without
some regrets. The young, she complains, are
learning to read and write, but they have lost the
gift of knowing that comes from living close to
nature, close to tradition.
A shared vision
In Sri Lanka too, where the government and
several non-governmental agencies have set up
credit and savings societies that are managed
and controlled by women, more economic
power is coming into the hands of women via
small-scale loans. The Janashakti Bank, like the
Grameen Bank, distributes loans to groups of
five women, each of whom is responsible for
maintaining the group's credit. Janashakti too has
a payback rate of nearly 95 per cent.
In South Asia women who were afraid even
of each other are beginning to share their con¬
dition and seek a shared vision. They are forming
new groups. The old beliefs no longer corre¬
spond to life as it is, and as women seek to
renew them they are embarking on a journey
along a path to self-discovery.
1 See page 15 for an interview with the founder of the
Grameen Bank.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
An interview with MllhâmiliaCl YllMIS
A BANK THAT ONLY LENDS TO THE POOR
The Grameen Bank, which was founded in Bangladesh in 1983 by
Muhammad Yunus, a university professor, has won a unique reputation
because it lends only to the very poor. Most of its clients are women. It
has inspired similar ventures in other developing countries including
Malaysia, the Philippines and Burkina Faso, as well as in France, Canada
and the United States.
Muhammad Yunus.
What gave you the idea of founding a bank to
help the penniless?
When Bangladesh became independent in 1971,
everyone was euphoric. We were convinced our
lives would change for the better, but instead things
went downhill very fast. In 1974 Bangladesh was
hit by a famine. At that time I was teaching eco¬
nomics at ChittagongUniversity, and while I was
teaching beautiful economic theories, people were
dying. This was very hard to accept, and I started
thinking about what I could do to help the poor to
rise out of poverty.
Chittagong University is in a rural area, and as
soon as I left the campus I was in a village where I
saw people suffering for want of very small
amounts of money. I thought that if I could find
such small sums for them, they could overcome
their difficulties. At first I provided them with
money from my own pocket.
Then I thought of putting things on a more reg¬
ular footing and went to the banks, but they thought
my idea was crazy. "How can you lend such small
sums?" they asked, "and to the poorest people?"
They gave me long lectures on banking, but I wasn't
convinced. I said that the poor were the people who
most needed money, and that it was to them that
money should go. They wanted to give money to the
rich. I told them I thought that was a strange idea.
Eventually, I offered to act as a guarantor for
loans myself. I signed all the documents, took the
money and gave it to the borrowers. I was respon¬
sible for collecting the repayments, and was very
pleasantly surprised to find that everyone repaid
their debts on time. I went back to the banks and
asked them to increase the number of loans, but the
bankers said no. They were convinced that the
project would fail. All the same, I extended the
loans, first to two villages, then to five, ten, fifteen.
The result was always the same: everyone paid
back what they owed on time. But still the banks
refused to budge. I extended the project to the
whole district, then to five districts, but I still got
the same reaction from the banks. So I made up my
mind to found my own bank. I asked permission
from the government, but they too thought it was
a crazy idea. It was only after spending two years
knocking on doors that I was finally granted per¬
mission to set up the bank. That was in 1 983.
Today you have 12,000 employees and two
million borrowers, 94 per cent of whom are women.
Yes, most of our clients are women. It has been
a hard struggle to achieve this. Not only are the
men hostile"Why lend to her?" they ask. "She
Miriam Makeba (1932-),
singer,
South Africa/United States.
Eva Perón (1919-1952),
politician,
Argentina.
A loan from the Grameen Bank
enabled this woman to start a
confectionery business
(Bangladesh).
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
16
doesn't even know how to count" but at first the
women too were afraid to accept the money. They
asked us to give it to their husbands. Women in our
society have no self-confidence. From the moment
they are born, they are told by their families: "You
have brought misery on the family because you are
a girl." They are so often told they are worthless, that
they end up believing it.
How did you persuade them to borrow from the
bank?
It wasn't easy. But first one woman took the
plunge, then another and another. When one
woman succeeds, the others are encouraged. Seeing
that it works, the others try their luck.
What kind of projects do they want to finance?
Very simple projects such as raising a cow, selling
milk, processing rice, weaving baskets or sewing . . .
the things that women do anyway but never get
paid for. Now that we give the money directly to the
women, the husbands no longer take the receipts.
The women do the work and are paid for it.
Can a person borrow from your bank more than
once, or do you stop after a first investment?
No, we keep lending. Suppose you borrow
twenty-five dollars and pay it back within a year;
you feel more confident and know you can borrow
fifty dollars the next time. Once that's paid back,
your ambitions grow.
How many years does it take on average before
your clients achieve a financially viable situation?
Experience shows that ten loan cycles are
required before a person rises above the extreme
poverty line. More than a third of our borrowers
have already done this. It is very exciting to see
people emerge from poverty. Our aim is to make
sure that the two million families that are with us
all cross the poverty line within the next five years.
What kind of setbacks do you come up against?
Bangladesh is often hit by natural disasters. A
single cyclone like the one in 1991 that killed 150,000
people can wipe everything out. Or the cow you've
bought on credit falls ill and dies. The woman gets
very upset. She can't do anything, but this is money
that she has to pay back. She blames her luck and
starts to lose confidence. Our job is to reassure her.
Do you ever write off losses?
No, never. It's a principle with us. What we do
is transfer the loan into a long-term loan and then
grant a new, short-term loan.
But the debt grows?
Yes and no. Rich people are also heavily in
debt, but they make a lot of money. Being heavily
in debt is not a problem provided that debt is
earning money for you. There's only a problem
when you are heavily in debt and not getting any
A woman fishes in the Indus
while her children watch.
income out of it. In any case, when women sign on
with the Grameen Bank, there are a certain number
of promises they have to make, such as neither
giving nor receiving a dowry. They also promise to
send their children to school, not to drink pol¬
luted water, and to plant trees.
Do you ever refuse a loan if it's not for a good
investment?
We don't get involved. We don't have to. The
women asking for loans belong to groups and only
propose a project to us once it has been agreed on
by their group. We say, "The money is ours, but the
idea is yours." We refrain from giving advice so
people can become surer of themselves. It's also a
way of making them more responsible.
With a loan from the Grameen
Bank this Bangladeshi mother
bought a rickshaw to increase
her family's income.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Attiya Inayatullah
THREE WOMEN FROM PAKISTAN
Women leaders in villages of the developing world are starting to take practical
steps to dismantle the barriers that keep them in inferior status. Here are
portraits of three of them.
BIBI GUL
Bibi Gu! is thirty-five years old. She was born and grew up in the rough
tribal area of Baluchistan. When she was nine years old, her mother
died, her father remarried, and she was placed in the care of her
grandparents, who lived in penury. At thirteen, for a bride price that
was common in the area, they assured their financial future and
passed her on to a man more than twice her age.
For the next fifteen years her life was a cycle of repeated preg¬
nancies. She had six children who survived and three miscarriages.
Neither health nor education centres reached Bibi Gul's village,
because of opposition from the men of the community, who, however,
allowed an embroidery centre to be established to revive the dying
art of traditional stltchcraft.
Bibi Gul was encouraged by the embroidery trainer, who was
quick to appreciate her intelligence and learning ability, and rapidly
emerged as a competent teacher herself. She not only helped to pro¬
vide other girls and women with an Income-generating activity but also
established a forum for discussing women's issues.
In recognition of her emerging organizational abilities, Bibi Gul
was invited to a leadership workshop in 1989. It was the first time
that she had left her home town. She did not remove her burqa (the
local veil) throughout the eight-day workshop although only women
were present, and did not speak during the sessions. But when she
returned to her community, a great change came over her.
She began to visit other women in her village and talk to them
about health, Immunization, education, family planning and income-
generating opportunities, and encouraged them to participate in the
women's programme. She was gradually made responsible for three
of the villages in her area. This entailed travelling by public transport
to visit other house-bound women. She slowly shed not only her fears
and inhibitions but also her burqa when in female company. She devel¬
oped Into an active member of the community.
Bibi Gul had to face her husband's initial resentment of her new¬
found independence, and also became the object of adverse com¬
ment from the conservative community in which she lives. Never¬
theless, she has worked with quiet determination, teaching her
husband to care for their children when she is away on training
courses and gradually earning the respect of the female community
as a whole.
SHABANU
Shabanu Is thirty-eight years old. She comes from a large and
Impoverished family in an area where education for females is
regarded as unnecessary or even as a disadvantage. She dropped
out of school at eleven, first to look after her brothers and sisters,
then to marry a clansman. Then her husband deserted her and her
four children, and she was forced to borrow from her mother and
brothers to make ends meet. She resolved to overcome her depen¬
dence and ensure that neither she nor her children would ever be vul¬
nerable again.
She started attending women's group meetings, showing par¬
ticular interest in sessions devoted to education, income-generation
and the status of women. Recognizing that she faced problems
without formal educational qualifications, she privately prepared
for and passed her matriculation examination. She also took a
training course for birth attendants. She used modern, hygienic
techniques that benefited the mothers she delivered. Shabanu also
participated in a women's festival in which women from all over Pak¬
istan met to share their experience, demonstrate how they were over¬
coming their problems and participate in rarely available recre¬
ational activities.
When she was appointed as a supervisor in the local women's
programme, her income increased and she became able to educate
her children. As a supervisor, she motivates other women to take
action to improve their lives through education, health, hygiene, family
planning and income-generating activities.
KALSOOM
From as far back as she can remember, sixteen-year-old Kalsoom has
always wanted desperately to go to school. Her dream was to become
a teacher. Her family objected as they faced economic problems. A
maternal uncle, seeing her potential, helped her out. In 1993 Kalsoom
first came ¡n contact with the concept of human development when
she was selected from her school to attend a Girl-Child Workshop, an
Initiative aimed at encouraging young women to value themselves and
Increase both the opportunities available to them and their contri¬
butions to their community. The participants were encouraged to
improve their living conditions. Kalsoom's interest in helping others
resulted in her selection by other participants as a local leader, and
with her group she formulated a work plan for the community.
Kalsoom arranges regular meetings of local girls to explain to
them the importance of personal hygiene, cleanliness, basic health
care, education and the environment. She has organized a street
cleaning schedule in the village and encouraged the girls to plant fruit
trees and set up kitchen gardens to improve their diet and the envi¬
ronment. She has been trained as a home-school teacher, passing
on her own limited education to those unable to pursue formal edu¬
cation, and she oversees two other home-schools and an adult lit¬
eracy centre in her village. She is also active in seeking out and ini¬
tiating income-generating opportunities suitable for girls such as
tailoring and bag-making.
Helen Keller (1880-1968),
blind and deaf author and
educator, United States.
Hoda Chaaraoui (1882-1947),
militant feminist,
Egypt.
ATTIYA INAYATULLAH,
of Pakistan, is Chairperson of
Unesco's Executive Board. Her
fields of interest include
sociology, demography and
women's issues. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
'r À ;
Going it done
by Christine Catarino and Laura Oso
Why are there so many women-headed households in
countries of the South?
Above, a businesswoman and
family head in Douala
(Cameroon).
18
I According to the usual definition, the
head of a family is the person recognized
as such by him- or herself and by the other
members of the household. In some countries of
the South a patriarchal conception of the family
has discouraged women heads of household
from considering themselves as such, and as a
result their numbers have been underestimated.
Governments, development aid organiza¬
tions and non-governmental organizations
channel goods and services towards the family
head, who is supposed to be the family's main
source of support. This is why the social recog¬
nition of women as family heads is so important.
In addition to the accepted situations in
which a woman is the mainstay of the family
(widowhood, a partner's migration, single moth¬
erhood, an unstable marriage and polygamy
without cohabitation), there are cases where
the woman lives with a man who is not able or
willing to support the household.
matrilinear societies
In Africa women were heads of family in certain
traditional matrilinear polygamous societies
such as that of the Kwahu of Ghana, where
women inherit through the maternal line. Other
cultures in Ghana and elsewhere allow women
approaching forty to "withdraw from the insti¬
tution of marriage".
But the practice introduced in Africa by
colonialism causing men to migrate to work in
the mines and on the plantations of white
farmers, followed by post-independence devel¬
opments such as urbanization, increased migra¬
tory flows and changes in traditional family
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
structures combined to increase the number of
households run by women.
A number of demographic factors are also
involved, including women's longer life-
expectancy and the age difference between mar¬
riage partners, which means that more women
are widowed than men.
Kegional variations
United Nations statistics show that in the early
1980s women-headed households constituted
some 30 per cent of all households in Latin
America and the Caribbean, 20 per cent of those
in Africa and less than 15 per cent of those in
Asia. The lowest proportions of women house¬
hold heads are found in the countries of the
Sahel and North Africa (due to the influence of
religion, the strongly patriarchal nature of these
societies and traditional forms of cohabitation)
and in other Islamic countries such as Iran,
Kuwait, Pakistan and Indonesia.
In Latin America and the Caribbean, low
wages and unemployment due to economic
recession prevent men from performing their
traditional role in society. The resulting sense of
failure may lead them to abandon their families.
Macho attitudes, involving men in flashy expen¬
diture designed to reinforce their prestige as
males, may lead them to opt out of their respon¬
sibilities as fathers and leave the family home.
In Africa, the migration of a male spouse
may impose increased responsibilities on the
woman, who has to farm the family's land, while
a woman who leaves home may have to provide
economic support for the members of the family
left behind in the village. This feminization of
households is also encouraged by the form of
polygamy in which the man lives with only one
of his wives, while the others set up their own
households. Another form of non-cohabita-
tional polygamy exists when a male spouse
migrates to the city and takes a wife there, so that
he has both rural and urban households. Finally,
separations and divorces reflecting a decline in
customary family institutions take place because
the possibility of resolving marital conflict by the
community has ceased to exist.
L he age fiactor
The chances of women becoming family heads
generally increase as they grow older. The prob¬
ability is low for very young women, starts to
rise after the age of thirty-five and rises steeply
after age sixty-five. In Africa and in Asia and the
Pacific nearly half the women household heads
arc widows as opposed to 28 per cent in Latin
America and the Caribbean (36 per cent are
single). More women household heads are mar¬
ried or single than divorced, particularly in Asia
and the Pacific where the proportion of divorced
women is especially low.
The possibility that a woman will become the
head of a household thus fluctuates with age; she
may acquire and lose this status several times in
her life.
Low-paidjobs
Simone de Beauvoir
(1908-1986), writer,
France.
Women family heads are liable to sexual dis¬
crimination in employment and access to
Virginia Woolf (1882-1941),
novelist,
United Kingdom.
A Cameroonian notable and
some of his wives.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
poverty. Furthermore, a number of migrants'
wives, as de facto heads of families, receive eco¬
nomic support from their husbands.
A mother and her baby on a
collective farm in Tadjikistan.
20
CHRISTINE CATARINO
is a Franco-Portuguese
sociologist whose fields of
interest include women's
migrations and health-related
issues.
LAURA OSO
is a Spanish sociologist who
specializes in international
migrations and questions related
to women and development.
services simply because they are women. This
clearly limits their resources.
Often required to combine motherhood and
money-earning activity, they tend to find jobs in
the informal market sector (domestic work,
street vending, menial tasks that require little
training) because of its flexibility. In many cases
these are part-time jobs with proportionally
lower wages typical of this sector and limited
opportunities for improving social status. One
explanation given for women's lowly position on
the job market is their educational level.
In many countries women do not have the
right to own land, and as the traditional
authority-figures men may be given preferential
treatment in access to credit, technology and
social programmes.
Support networks, in many cases based on
female family links, do exist and help to relieve
Lihoice or constraint:
Do women choose to become family heads, or
are they forced into it by circumstances? In
Latin America and the Caribbean there are two
distinct approaches to this question. According
to one, underemployment and unemployment
prevent men from acting as the main family
breadwinner, and as a result women do more
paid work. According to the other, the growing
number of woman household heads is a conse¬
quence of women's greater autonomy due to
an increase in their income from paid employ¬
ment. In both cases the increase in women's
income boosts their role in the family. Their
new-found autonomy sometimes leads them to
terminate unsatisfactory marital relationships.
Other researchers believe that in Africa and
Latin America, women feel a strong desire to
withdraw from a social situation where macho
values prevail.
Do women become household heads vol¬
untarily or involuntarily? This raises the wider
question of whether their status is a form of
emancipation or the sign of a deteriorating sit¬
uation. A woman's deliberate choice to be head
of a household is often part of her search for an
identity outside that based on the family and the
conjugal unit; for a woman to accept such a role
involuntarily, on the other hand, is to accept
limitations on some of her aspirations.
A village meeting in Lesotho.
Most of the men work In South
Africa, and the women keep the
local economy going, although
tradition requires that they
recognize the authority of the
village chief (right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Patricia Made
AFRICA'S INVISIBLE WOMEN
The contribution of African women to the life of
their continent is largely overlooked by the media
In Africa, the exclusion of women from the media mirrors their
position in society at large. Between 80 and 98 per cent of them
work in subsistence farmingthey are the figures who can be
seen in the fields across the continent, using very simple Implements
to till the soil. Women who have paid jobs earn from 15 to 36 per
cent less than their male counterparts. Less than 9 per cent of
African parliamentarians are women, and women reaching ministerial
level are often shunted off into "soft" ministries such as health,
social welfare, education and women's affairs. Despite the education
drives of the 1960s and 1970s, 56 per cent of African women remain
illiterate. Women are excluded from power ¡n all sectors of society.
The media help to perpetuate this situation by gender stereo¬
typing and negative portrayal of women. The African media principally
serve an urban elite. Many of the items they publish are chosen for
their entertainment value, rather than for their value as Information
that could empower the majority of the people. Prominence and top¬
icality are the main criteria of newsworthlness. The people who
appear on the front pages are the people who occupy positions of
power. Most African women do not fall Into this category.
African women are often depicted ¡n the media as victims or sex
objects. They make the headlines when they are "battered" by
their husbands or commit bizarre or sensational acts. In one African
country it was noted that when the media did admit the existence
of gender gaps in education and employment, editorialists insisted
that women themselves are to blame because they do not take suf¬
ficient advantage of the available opportunities.
Nor do journalists (both men and women) view women as a
target audience for the information they write and produce for the
media. Since the majority of women are Illiterate and live ¡n rural
areas, they are generally disregarded as a media constituency.
The situation cannot be improved without an increase in the
numbers of African women actively Involved in the media, including
in management and training. As long as women remain without the
power to influence the flow of information and the type of coverage
given to events, ¡t will be extremely difficult to persuade the media
to present a less negative ¡mage of them.
A high drop-out rate
The dominant forces in the media, however, tend to resist any
move towards change. Women who are appointed to editorial
boards cr programming positions often lack professional experience
and are usually isolated in a male-dominated environment where it
A member of an Eritrean TV
camera crew filming in the
streets of Asmara, the
country's capital.
¡s difficult for them to be genuinely effective. Women who achieve
influential positions In the media are regularly subjected to harsh
critical scrutiny by male colleagues and other women. Some studies
show that there is a high drop-out rate among women who do
reach senior management positions. Women who are tied to a
home environment lack the flexibility and mobility essential to the
successful journalist; and women journalists have a reputation for
loose morals simply because they work long hours, often In close
collaboration with men. Because of such pressures, the numbers
of women entering the media are actually falling in some parts of
Africa.
In any case, the appointment of women to senior editorial posi¬
tions does not in Itself provide any guarantee against gender bias
in news reporting. The strictures of "producing good copy" are
such that even women editors will often regard women as news¬
worthy only when they do something sensational or bizarre.
Twenty years ago, at the Mexico City World Conference on
Women1, the media were seen as a catalyst for change. Since
then, however, little has changed, especially in Africa.
1. See the Unesco Courier, August-September 1975.
PATRICIA MADE,
a Zimbabwean journalist, is Managing Editor of the Southern
African Economist, a regional economic and business
magazine. She writes regularly on women's Issues for the
Women's Feature Service, an independent news and feature
agency based in India.
Alexandra Kollontai
(1872-1952), diplomat,
Russia.
Martha Argerich
(1941-), concert pianist,
Argentina.
This Malian woman, a judge, is
a campaigner against the
traditional practice of genital t\A
^4| mutilation of young girls.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Mothers of the
Plaza de Mayo
by Alicia Dujovne Ortiz
For almost twenty years the mothers
of those who disappeared during the
Argentine military dictatorship have
been fighting for justice
Above, the Mothers of the Plaza
de Mayo demonstrate in May
1995.
22
ALICIA DUJOVNE ORTIZ,
of Argentina, has written a
number of novels and children's
books. The French version of her
biography of Eva Peron has
recently been published by
Grasset, Paris.
Attached to the picket signs are photos of
young faces with a 1970s look. The girls
have long hair parted down the middle. The
boys' expressions and hair styles could belong
to no other decade. Each picket is carried by an
elderly woman wearing a headscarf. The women
are the mothers of desaparecidos, young Argen¬
tines who disappeared during the dictatorship in
the late 1970s. Every Thursday since April 1977
they have marched around the Plaza de Mayo,
the historic square in Buenos Aires on which
stands Government House, commonly called
the Casa Rosada. They will continue to do so
until the end of their days. They know that
there is no hope, but still they refuse to accept
that their children are dead. They are not seeking
compensation. They are making a protest that is
absolute and unending. It is almost as if their
grief is keeping them alive.
This indomitable movement began on the
day in 1977 when fourteen mothers of young
desaparecidos met in the Plaza de Mayo to hand
a petition to the then President of Argentina,
General Jorge Rafael Videla. They wanted to
know what had happened to their children, who
had been kidnapped by mysterious armed com¬
mandos. A year before, the army had over¬
thrown Isabel Perón. A government minister,
López Rega, had created the "Triple A", para¬
military forces that were schooled in torture. The
officers who established the dictatorship took
over this organization from López Rega and, so
to speak, improved it.
The torturers of the infamous Naval
Mechanics School had a weakness for young
pregnant women. Babies born in prison were
often given or sold to military families. The
perpetrators of these grim practices entered an
area of darkness from which there was no return.
By refusing to forgive them today, the Mothers
are quite aware of what they are doing. Human
errors can be pardoned; what is beyond the
frontiers of humanity cannot.
By confronting Videla and demonstrating
in front of the Casa Rosada, the women also
crossed a point of no-return, but in the other
direction. Their experience of horror gave them
superhuman courage. What did death-threats
matter to them? They knew very well and the
memory of their disemboweled daughters
reminded them of it at every moment that to
be a woman was no protection. In fact, some of
them would pay for their courage with their
lives. Azucena Villaflor de Vicenti, for example,
the instigator of the movement, was arrested
and never seen again. In the intervals between
beating them up and setting police dogs on
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
them, the soldiers ridiculed the women and said
they were "mad". How could they guess that
these "madwomen" would still be going round
the square eighteen years later?
"We do not go round in circles," says Hebe
Bonafini, the movement's guiding spirit. "We
march." It was the police who unwittingly gave
them the idea of walking round the pyramid
on the Plaza de Mayo. The Mothers had grown
used to meeting at the same place in the square
until one day the police ordered them to "move
on". The Mothers took the order literally and
have never stopped "moving" since. They also
showed their sense of humour whenever a
policeman demanded to see a woman's papers.
On these occasions, 300 women would step
forward, and the man would have to give up. If
it looked as if one woman was going to be
arrested, the others would demand to go with
her. Once in prison, they would start to pray, or
rather yell out prayers calling on God to vent his
wrath on their persecutors.
ies to life
Hebe Bonafini explains why the women march
in circles. "How else should the Mothers
march?" she asks "than round like their bellies
and the world through which their protest
echoes." Since the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo
were awarded the Sakharov Prize their example
has been followed by mothers in many other
countries: by Sicilian mothers fighting against
the Mafia, by Spanish mothers fighting against
drugs, by Ukrainian victims of Chernobyl, and
by Palestinian, Israeli and Yugoslav mothers
who reject war. All these women reconstitute the
symbolic circle of the cycle of life as opposed to
the straight lines of military parades.
The Mothers have resisted all kinds of bland¬
ishments and lies. These housewives, many from
poor families, might have been thought naive
whereas in fact they have a fierce intelligence.
When timid or conniving politicians made vague
i* p> * N v * / v ' V v
UN IftDR
i7[J5;3D.GpÛ>JL5fÎPRRtaDD5;
. MRDRE5 «: PLRZfl Df JiifX^ -
Left and below, a demonstration
in September 1983.
Ding Ling (1902-1986).
feminist writer,
China.
Philippine (Pina) Bausch
(1940-), dancer and
choreographer, Germany.
/ \ \
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
"Our children now live within
us. It is they who have brought
us into the world."
promises to look for their children, they saw the
reality of the concentration camps where those
children had been tortured. They were under no
illusions. During the dictatorship, in 1979, they
saw immediately that a visit by representatives of
the OAS (Organization of American States)
would not only be fruitless but would actually
make the situation worse. During the Falklands
War they were among the first to realize that the
military were playing on patriotic fervour to
dupe the people, just as they had by staging the
World Soccer Cup in Argentina in 1978.
After the fall of the junta, they understood
that they could expect nothing concrete from
President Raúl Alfonsín. Today, when a wave of
public confessions by the torturers, begun by
Captain Scilingo, is being continued by offi¬
cers who admit to the crimes committed under
the dictatorship, the Mothers know they should
not be satisfied with a list of the desaparecidos
nor conclude that they are all dead.
"We know that there were thirty thousand of
them," says one of the women, "and we know
all their names. Every mother knows who
arrested her child. What we want is a list of the
murderers and executioners and life imprison¬
ment for those who are still free. The govern¬
ment is hiding the truth from us. We don't really
want to know whether they died under torture
or were drowned with a stone tied to their feet.
Our children now live within us. It is they who
24
have brought us into the world; they have
become our fathers and mothers. If we want to
know what happened to our children, it is only
to punish their killers."
The refusal to forgive has become an accep¬
tance of life. These women, changed by suffering
into artists and poets, have invented an expression
that is absurdly and terribly beautiful, "Living
apparitions". They do not want piles of bones and
lists of bodies. They want justice. They know by
heart all the legal arguments and know, for
example, that while murder may be subject to pre¬
scription, illegal detention is a permanent viola¬
tion of human rights and is imprescriptible.
Accepting that their children are dead would be
tantamount to accepting el Punto Final (the Full
Stop), the name of the amnesty law voted under
the Alfonsín presidency. Calling off their protest
would mean that death had won.
The women live with an intensity and a
detachment that are impossible for others to
imagine because shared suffering has welded
them into a group. Initially they wore baby
clothes on their heads to help them to recognize
each other. These wounded lionesses have gone
far beyond individual suffering. Once each
mother marched with the photo of her own child.
Now they carry any picket sign, irrespective of
the photo on it. They are universal mothers.
When Scilingo revealed that priests were
taken along on the navy planes from which
naked and drugged prisoners were dropped into
the Rio de la Plata, the Mothers marched to the
cathedral and chanted an extraordinary but pro¬
foundly religious litany. While one of them
recited the list of the bishops and priests who had
collaborated with the dictatorship everyone
knows who they are they responded in chorus
after each name, "Lord, do not forgive them, for
they acted in Thy name! "
Other Mothers have taken a new path but
with the same goal of serving the forces of life.
In fact these Mothers are Grandmothers who
have sworn to trace their grandchildren who
were given to military families. Of 500 children
who disappeared in this way, they have already
found about fifty. Their leader, Estella Barnes de
Carlotto, explains that only 200 families have
formally asked for a search to be made. The
others are afraid. But the Grandmothers possess
an extremely powerful weapon in the National
Bank of Genetic Fingerprinting, where Ana
Maria Di Leonardo has recorded the genetic
identity of 170 family groups with a child or
newborn baby who disappeared. The genetic
chain is another woman's weapon, another end¬
less circle.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Rigoberta Menchú
'WE HAVE COME A LONG WAY...'
Rigoberta Menchú (centre)
takes part in a traditional
Indian celebration in
Guatemala, October 1992.
Rigoberta Menchú, a
Guatemalan Indian, was
awarded the Nobel Peace
Prize for 1992. A United
Nations goodwill ambassador
for the International Year of
the World's Indigenous
People, she has become the
spokeswoman for the
indigenous peoples of Latin
America and elsewhere.
am self-taught. When I was twenty I had the opportunity to
learn another language and discover a different world from that
of my own Maya culture. At the same time, unfortunately, I also
had to leave my home and my land, and see my parents, my
brothers and many of my friends die. Since then I've kept on
learning, sometimes painfully, far from my family and my commu¬
nity, in a foreign language and an unknown world
I
A collective memory
It is important to me that my personal experience should fit Into a
collective context that belongs to all peoples, but primarily to the
Guatemalan people. I lived through the most violent period in the
history of Guatemala, which had a profound influence on the cul¬
ture of the country's indigenous people and the society at large.
Everything I have been throughflight, exile, homesickness-
has been experienced by many Guatemalans.
One of the most important things I've learned is that one must
remain humble before knowledge. I'm still a student, a student of
time, of life, and I hope to keep on learning until my dying breath.
People should constantly renew themselves, their ideas and their
feelings. 1 have been awarded the Nobel Prize, and honorary doc¬
torates at several universities, but I am still intimidated when a jour¬
nalist asks me questions. Every question teaches me something.
I am very religious; I believe ¡n life. But I have my own own way
of believing, and if I were asked to explain what the heart of the sky
or mother earth mean to me, the short term and the long term and
even life itself, people would probably not understand anything about
my gods. I only know that if I didn't believe in something, I would
cease to exist.
My father died fifteen years ago, on 31 January 1980. My
mother died three months later. It was a tragic period for Guatemala,
a devastated land. Many of my compatriots were forced into exile.
I remember living for maybe a year and a half in very difficult cir¬
cumstances, terrified and traumatized by the war, with no experience
or prospects, knowing nothing of the world or what I should do.
Since those dark years we have come a long way in joy and enthu¬
siasm, fighting alongside the peasants for their rights. In fifteen years
we've made considerable progress. A growing number of my indige¬
nous brother Guatemalans are, for example, not only going into pol¬
itics, economics and local government but also into cultural and
artistic activities. Many are famous artists, and a lot of young
people are embarking on scientific careers without sacrificing their
identity. Pride in their identity is what makes a people great.
The all too familiar image of indigenous people as museum
pieces is the result of ignorance and the lack of information and
education that are typical of the late twentieth century. It ¡s unfair
to claim that indigenous people have made no contribution to
world culture. It always amuses me to read ecologists' mani¬
festoes ¡n defence of the environment, nature and respect for life
because they are simply rehashed versions of our own beliefs.
Indigenous peoples also have their own approaches to science and
medicine, and they have something to contribute to ways of
thinking and living.
Our Maya people have a rich, multifarious culture which they
have succeeded ¡n keeping alive. It is a profoundly collective cul¬
ture which tries to strike a balance between the rights of the indi¬
vidual and the interests of the community, and has succeeded in
surviving poverty, famine, suffering and war. For us, progress is
meaningless unless ¡t is shared by everyone. Every step forward
evolves from a collective rationale, and nothing is gained by the
action of an Isolated individual. In this respect our culture is
sometimes at odds with the rampant materialism and individualism
that you sometimes see in Western culture.
But we also have a lot of values In common at a time when rich
and poor peoples alike are united in the fight for survival, cultural
as well as physical. We have all joined forces to preserve the highest
human values. And as far as that is concerned I see no difference
between indigenous people and the rest, between men and women,
between Latin Americans and Europeans.
Grounds for optimism
We have also made a lot of progress internationally. Ten years ago
no one cared about indigenous people, but today we are wel¬
comed in Unesco and other International bodies. The world is
beginning to recognize and value indigenous people's way of
thinking. We have come a long way, and that is why I am profoundly
optimistic. Not only can we walk through the corridors of the
United Nations without being taken for a folk attraction, but people
now listen to what we have to say.
Our goals are ambitious, and it will be a long job. What we are
looking for is a solution to the conflict that is tearing my country
apart so that we can build a multilingual and multicultural nation
for all Guatemalans. But the international community still has a long
way to go If it wants to help us. Governments still misleadlngly talk
about indigenous "populations" rather than "peoples". It hardly
needs saying that at present the rights and personalities of these
peoples are not recognized as they should be, but here too, I think
that it is primarily a question of education and Information. 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
3#8K
Somalia: the great escape
With their society in turmoil, Somali women are breaking
free from the constraints of a patriarchal system
26
HASSAN KEYNAN,
a Somali poet, was formerly a
professor at the Somali National
University and secretary-general
of the Somali National
Commission for Unesco. He is
currently working as a
consultant with the Norwegian
National Commission for Unesco.
I In Somali society, male-female roles and
power relationships are regulated by tra¬
ditional beliefs and practices which do not admit
equality between the sexes. Somali "culture"
allows and equips men to dominate women,
who are systematically relegated to a subordi¬
nate, marginal existence.
The roots of these inequities lie in a patriar¬
chal tradition which confines women to house¬
keeping and procreation, excludes them from
positions of power and influence and denies
them access to resources and means of making
an independent living. This tradition imposes
severe restrictions on women's intellectual and
social development, and stifles their creative
skills and energy. It also discourages them from
openly expressing their thoughts and feelings.
Somali culture has established elaborate
myths, folk literature and traditional discourse
to rationalize and sanctify patriarchy. It is in
oral literature that men's campaign against
women begins. Enormously popular folktales
portray women as inherently incapable of being
rational rulers and decent wives. Proverbs
convey the message that womanhood/mother¬
hood is incompatible with intelligence and
wisdom. "A breast that contains milk cannot
contain wisdom," says a well-known proverb.
Poetry, a national institution of great power
and influence, portrays women as incapable of
rhyming one word with another and therefore
as unworthy of having a meaningful voice. The
ideal woman is the silent woman whose words
and ideas are limited to her immediate circle of
children and other women.
Kjivil war and famine
But disasters can sometimes generate unex¬
pected opportunities. The human tragedy that
has devastated Somalia has also started to usher
Somali society down the road to change. More
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
important, this nascent social metamorphosis is
most evident in male-female relations.
A number of factors have combined to
trigger the process of change. First, the pro¬
tracted civil war and famine have removed many
men from the family arena and placed addi¬
tional burdens on women. Female-headed
households have proliferated as a result.
Second, over one million persons, one-fifth
of the total population, have been forced to flee
their country in search of security and suste¬
nance. Most of them ended up in refugee camps
in neighbouring countries: Djibouti, Ethiopia,
Kenya and Yemen, but many sought asylum in
the Western world, mainly in Canada, the
United Kingdom, The Netherlands, Italy,
Sweden, Norway, Denmark and Germany. The
majority of these refugee/migrants are women
and children, and this has led to women's playing
a growing and more visible role.
Third, there are indications that Somali
women have shown greater resilience and
resourcefulness than men in coping with the
trauma of civil war and famine at home and the
anxieties and uncertainties of refugee life abroad.
Fourth, new possibilities seem to have opened
up for women refugees, especially where the
country of asylum provides adequate economic
support, protection from gender-based inequities
and understanding and tolerance toward
migrants.
Kole reversals
The seemingly eternal order of patriarchy has
been unceremoniously confronted with the
reality of change, and this has caused profound
reversals in gender roles and power relations.
The new status of women expresses itself in a
variety of ways. Perhaps the most prominent is
the exhilarating sense of freedom that women
feel and enjoy. The lifting of the oppressive and
dehumanizing burden of patriarchal dogma is
seen by many women as a wondrous intervention
designed to celebrate their humanity, dignity and
talent. Many Somali women glow with inspira¬
tion and exuberance and talk about their new¬
found freedom with poetic eloquence. "I feel I
have undergone a miraculous process of recre¬
ation and renewal," says one woman now living
in Norway. "I am a new person, blessed with a full
and fulfilling life. It's magic."
For many Somali women the arrival of
freedom was accompanied by another symbol of
empowerment. They have found a voice. Women
have begun to demand and defend their rights,
both privately and in public. They have become
more assertive in two traditionally male-domi¬
nated areas. Men can no longer run the affairs of
the family at will, nor can they contemplate
taking a second or a third wife on a whim and
with impunity. The patriarchal discourse is slowly
being demystified.
A significant number of these women have
become increasingly active in economic life, an
area previously inaccessible to them. Finding
employment can be enormously difficult for
refugees and migrants, but many Somali women
have managed to find work while their husbands
have remained largely unemployed. Most of these
women work in areas like child care, health,
food-processing, catering and cleaning. Many
have also established small family businesses that
deal mainly with women's and children's clothes,
jewelry, cosmetics and special types of incense
widely used by Somali women. The result is that
many households now have women, not men, as
breadwinners and heads of family.
The change has also drastically transformed
the allocation of tasks and responsibilities in the
domestic arena. The traditional norms and ethos
that excused men from household chores and
placed all the burden on women are no longer
acceptable to females. There is now a new order
that sees household chores and related duties as
evenly divided between males and females. Tasks
such as shopping, cooking, cleaning, washing,
ironing and child care now form part of men's
daily responsibilities, a development inconceiv¬
able in traditional Somali culture.
Men's apprehensions
Most men feel a profound sense of discomfort and
apprehension. Many believe that the changes
taking place in gender relations are too radical
and too destabilizing. They view the growing
empowerment of women as a serious threat to
their authority and dignity and, by extension, as
a threat to the moral and cultural norms and tra¬
ditions of Somali society. They complain about
humiliation and lack of respect, marginalization
and expulsion, orders being given by their wives,
loss of family coherence and values, and confusion
and disorientation in the way children are brought
up. Many men admit that they are no longer able
to cope with these pressures and humiliations. It
is reported that some are sinking into depression
and have started drinking heavily.
Opposite page: refugees in
Bardera camp (Somalia), wait
for a children's reception centre
to open.
Below: a young Somali
woman (foreground) working for
a mail-order company in London
(United Kingdom).
Marguerite Yourcenar
(1903-1987), novelist,
France.
Maria Callas (1923-1977),
singer,
Greece/United States.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Norwegianpolitics bridges the gender gap
Norwegian Prime Minister Gro
Harlem Brundtland (centre) at
the Earth Summit in Rio de
Janeiro (Brazil), June 1992. A country where women are integrated
into party politics at national level
I On 9 May 1986 a social democratic gov-
I ernment was formed in Norway. Its com¬
position set a world record: eight of the eighteen-
member cabinet appointed by the new Prime
Minister, Ms. Gro Harlem Brundtland, were
women. Since then, no Norwegian cabinet has
contained less than 40 per cent women, and the
representation of women in parliament has grad¬
ually reached approximately the same level. In
recent elections Norwegian voters were presented
with three different alternative governments; all
three candidates for Prime Minister were women.
To outsiders this development may seem
somewhat mysterious even insiders have
referred to it as "a political miracle", although it
is a miracle which is still largely confined to the
world of party politics. In large economic orga¬
nizations, the state bureaucracy and academic
institutions, the proportion of women in posi¬
tions of power remains low. And private sector
corporations are almost exclusively run by men.
Feminist influence
28
HEGESKJEIE,
of Norway, is a senior
researcher at the Institute for
Social Research in Oslo. She
has written several studies on
women's integration into
political elites in Norway.
Women's successful integration in Norwegian
politics is largely due to the influence the Nor¬
wegian feminist movement has come to wield in
the political parties. Unlike its counterparts in
many other countries, the Norwegian feminist
movement advocated integration into the
existing political structure as a viable strategy for
empowering women. Right from the start, the
movement co-operated with women inside the
party structure in making demands for political
representation. This co-operation was expressed
to a notable extent in local and national election
campaigns. In the 1971 local elections, it helped
to produce a majority of women on the city
council of the Norwegian capital, Oslo.
Women should represent women
From the 1970s on, two lines of argument were
advanced by women activists. Some women
maintained that the conflicting interests of men
and women required a balanced representation of
both parties. Others, in line with more conserv¬
ative political ideologies, argued that women's
experience could make a valuable contribution to
the decision-making process. Both sides agreed,
however, that representation of women by
women was necessary. Men could not negotiate
the values or the interests of women.
These arguments fitted in with a strong tra¬
dition of social representation in Norwegian
politics. While it is true that the Norwegian
parliament recruits its members disproportion¬
ately from social elites, it does so less than many
other national legislatures. The parties control
the nomination of candidates to almost all
important political appointments, and one issue
on which they compete for votes is that of their
own profile. Most party leaderships have tended
to believe that voters will take note of the rep¬
resentativeness of party lists with regard to
occupational background, region and age.
Arguments about the political relevance of
gender thus struck a familiar note.
Gender, however, was not merely regarded as
one more "relevant background criterion". Once
women managed to gain access to various party
leaderships, gender achieved a prominence that
forced most political parties to adopt a set of
formal regulations governing their composition.
The system of gender quotas, which is at present
practised by four of the six major Norwegian
parties, comes near to guaranteeing equal partic¬
ipation rights. The quota regulations state that
both sexes are to be represented by a minimum of
40 per cent and apply both to the composition of
party election lists and to appointments within the
national party organizations.
Apolitical rhetoric ofdiffterence
While men and women alike maintain that party
politics has now become a place for the ncgotia-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
tion of the different interests of men and women
politicians and that such differences are relevant
to political decision-making, some feminists con¬
tend that this "old" way of arguing for women's
political participation, even when proved suc¬
cessful, still smacks of continuing male political
domination. The obvious, self-evident right to
participate in politics, these feminists argue, is
still a male prerogative, and women have to jus-
tify their presence on the political scene. Even if
they are present in nearly equal numbers, they still
have to prove themselves.
This overlooks some simple political facts.
Firstly, providing justification or reasons for polit¬
ical participation is something that is demanded of
all political leaders. Justification is a general aspect
of representative politics. Secondly, new polit¬
ical movements commonly present themselves
as "an alternative". It is true that men have never
defended their positions with explicit reference to
gender. Only women's participation in politics has
been argued in these terms. But women political
leaders are relative newcomers to the political
community. By presenting themselves in terms of
the alternative, women are merely using a well-
known political stratagy.
The divisions between "masculine" and
"feminine" have long contributed to the legit¬
imization of practices which kept women out of
political life. In Norway today, they legitimize
instead practices which secure the presence of
women in political life.
Ugné Karvelis
LITHUANIA: THE FIRST STATUTE FOR WOMEN
The Statute of Lithuania, promulgated in 1529, was the first law in Europe to define the rights of women
as human beings and not simply as mothers or potential mothers.
The status of women in Lithuanian customary law was the result
of a synthesis between a strong matrilinear tradition and the
role played by women in a society where men were absent for
long periods fighting in the wars.
Whereas collective family responsibility was the rule every¬
where else in Europe, the Statute of Lithuania established the prin¬
ciple of individual legal responsibility and the equality of everyone in
the eyes of the lawirrespective of religion or social statusand guar¬
anteed the inviolability of the person and his or her property. It stip¬
ulated extremely severe penalties, as was the rule at that time, when
corporal punishment was traditionally accompanied by fines. The
Statute regarded a woman's life and physical Integrity as worth
double those of a man of the same rank, although ¡t is true that the
life of a woman "slave" (only prisoners-of-war were considered as
such) was worth a little less than two geese, I.e. the same price as
that of a male "slave".
A Second Statute, promulgated in 1566, went even further than
its predecessor, doubling the terms of imprisonment imposed for
offences against the wife, widow or daughter of a nobleman.
At a time when women ¡n other European countries were gen¬
erally kept under the guardianship of their fathers or husbands, the
Statute (a third and final version of which was promulgated in 1588)
even recognized that Lithuanian women had the right to choose their
partners freely. On the other hand, parents had the right to disinherit
a daughter who married without their consent.
The rights of young women to own property were spelled out in
meticulous detail, although they remained limited. If a father died
without having fixed the amount of his daughters' dowries, the
daughters automatically shared out one quarter of his property
among themselves. When a marriage took place, the bridegroom had
to "endow" his bride with full title to a part of his property.
Widows received even better treatment. They had the legal
right to administer their dead husband's lands, to freely dispose of
their personal property and to bring lawsuits. Ladles, like lords, were
obliged to finance the service of armed horsemen in the grand
duke's army, although they were not required to take part ¡n military
expeditions personally.
The question of rape was handled in the same spirit and in a way
that even today may seem remarkably favourable to women. By
simply lodging a complaint, the victim could haul the aggressor
before the courts and "prove the facts through the testimony of wit¬
nesses". These witnesses could be female, since the Statute stip¬
ulated that women had the same right as men to appear in court and
to take the oath. A rapist could be punished by the death penalty, Irre¬
spective of his social rank, and escape the executioner only If his
victim agreed to marry him.
Lithuanian women did not, however, enjoy equality with men in
every sphere. They had no access to political life. By the middle of
the sixteenth century, many voices were being raised in protest
against the granting of "men's" rights to women.
UGNE KARVELIS,
of Lithuania, is her country's permanent delegate to Unesco. An
author, translator and literary critic, she has for several years
produced a programme about world literature for French radio.
Young Lithuanians dance at a midsummer festival
early this century.
Vigdís Finnbogadóttir (1930-),
Europe's first woman head of
state elected by universal
suffrage. Iceland.
Corazón Aquino (1933-),
Asia's first woman head of state
elected by universal suffrage,
Philippines.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
well as human sisterhood, and both must rise
and fall together. Woman cannot be elevated
without elevating man, and man cannot be
depressed without depressing woman also". Or,
as one social reformer put it at the beginning of
this century, "Feminism will make it possible for
the first time for men to be free."
30
Men supporting
women
by Michael S. Rimmel
The feminist movement has always counted men among its
supporters
Most men have regarded the women's
movement with bemused indifference.
Some have actively opposed women's rights, as
if women's freedom would diminish men's
freedom. In a few countries there has been a
men's movement to encourage men to run off to
the woods to "bond" with other men, as if to
escape the effects of feminism.
But some men support feminism, in the
belief that equal opportunity is a right, not a
privilege. Pro-feminist men believe that the
changes feminism has brought to women's lives
are positive for men as well as for women. Some
of them support feminism because their moral
commitments or political ideologies are based on
the right of the individual to determine his or her
life, or because of a commitment to a principle
of equality that demands that all people enjoy
the same rights as citizens. Others support fem¬
inism because they are the sons of feminist
women, the brothers of feminist sisters, the
fathers of feminist daughters, the husbands of
feminist wives, or the friends of feminist women.
From the time of the earliest feminist move¬
ment in the nineteenth century until the present,
however, the most common reason why men
have supported feminism is because they believe
it is the right thing to do, because women are
equal individuals with rights that cannot be
abridged. As the great nineteenth-century Amer¬
ican abolitionist Frederick Douglass put it, male
support of feminism is a matter of "conscience
and common sense".
Some men have also supported feminism on
the grounds that women are socially and morally
superior to men. These men believe that women
can redeem men from the "muddle we have made
of politics", as one social reformer put it at the
turn of the century, and "will correct many of
these law-made wrongs that man has made".
Finally, some men have supported feminism
because they believed that it would benefit men
by demolishing conventional standards of
morality and allowing men to fully develop
themselves. As Frederick Douglass put it: "This
cause is not altogether and exclusively woman's
cause. It is the cause of human brotherhood as
A househusband hangs out the
washing.
A battle cry for freedom
Wherever feminist women have agitated for
reform, there have been men to support them.
Educational pioneers opened the doors of colleges
and universities to women in the nineteenth cen¬
tury, and supported women's entry into profes¬
sions historically closed to women. The founder
of Wellesley College in the United States wrote
that he supported women's education as a form
of "revolt": "We revolt against the slavery in
which women are held by the customs of
society the broken health, the aimless lives, the
subordinate position, the helpless dependence, the
dishonesties and shams of so-called education.
The Higher Education of Women is one of the
world's battle cries for freedom; for rights against
might. It is the cry of the oppressed slave."
On the economic front, pro-feminist men
supported women's rights to work, to own
property, to join unions, to enter the profes¬
sions, to receive equal wages for equal work, and
to be free of harassment on the job.
Politically, pro-feminist men were preoccu¬
pied with the struggle for suffrage. Since that was
granted to women in the first decades of this cen¬
tury, they have supported women candidates
for public office and have worked to eliminate
barriers to women's full political participation.
Socially, pro-feminist men have been active in
campaigns for birth control, the right to divorce,
and the right of a woman to keep her own name.
In addition, men have supported women's efforts
MICHAEL S. KIMMEL, -
of the United States, is
Professor of Sociology at the
State University of New York and
national spokesperson for the
U.S. National Organization for
Men against Sexism (NOMAS).
He is the author of a number of
books, including The Burdens of
Proof: A History of Men in
America, which will be published
later this year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
to end sexual harassment, domestic violence,
spouse abuse and the ritual torture and genital
mutilation of which women in certain societies are
victims. Around the world there are men who
oppose female circumcision, dowry death, and
customs which give men the power of life and
death over their wives and daughters.
Many pro-feminist men also feel a need to
support each other as they travel the painful,
often confusing path of challenging and
changing the assumptions about gender which
they have been taught. All over the world, there
are support groups for men who seek to be
more active and engaged fathers and in many
countries men are involved in efforts to end
violence against women.
In the United States, the National Organi
zation for Men Against Sexism (NOMAS) was
founded in 1982 to support "the continuing
struggle of women for full equality" and to pro¬
mote a vision of men and women working
together "as allies to change the injustices that
have so often made them see one another as
enemies."
NOMAS stands for four co-equal princi¬
ples: (1) to oppose sexism and support women's
full equality in the public and private sphere; (2)
to oppose heterosexism and homophobia, and to
support full equality for gay men and lesbians;
(3) to support the struggle of minorities for full
equality; and, (4) to oppose rigid definitions of
masculinity and promote changes among men
that will enable them to live richer and more
fully expressive emotional lives.
Catherine Vidal
ARE MEN AND WOMEN ON THE SAME WAVELENGTH?
A scientist answers an awkward question
Does a man's brain differ from a woman's? Yes, say the biol¬
ogists, in the sense that no one has exactly the same brain.
No, say the philosophers, sociologists, historians and
other representatives of the human sciences. The important thing
is to distinguish between the functioning of the brain as an organ,
which is studied by biologists, and the functioning of the human mind,
which ¡s the bedrock of civilization.
The question needs to be clarified both scientifically and ideo¬
logically. Scientific analysis of the brain can only be carried out in cer¬
tain limited conditions, which cannot do justice to the extreme com¬
plexity of cerebral activity. If, for example, exploration of the brain's
mechanisms for handling language ¡s especially important for clinical
medicine, it must be emphasized that even the most exhaustive
"physical" description of language Is not enough to explain language
as a vehicle of thought. Our knowledge of the human mind and its rela¬
tionships with individual and collective history is the result of investi¬
gations in a number of fields such as philosophy, psychoanalysis and
history. All these disciplines attest that men and women share equally
the faculties of intelligence, emotion and imagination.
This explains why scientific observation of a difference between
the sexes in the functioning of the brain should not be taken to reflect
a difference in thinking capacity, nor justify any kind of prejudice
regarding the respective competence of men and women or Inequal¬
ities between the sexes in the socio-cultural distribution of tasks.
The brain, like other physical organs, is influenced by genetic, hor¬
monal and environmental factors. The male (testosterone) and female
(oestradiol) sexual hormones are secreted very early on in the foetus,
permitting the development of the genitalia and of the secondary
sexual characteristics that permanently take form at puberty. Sexual hor¬
mones also influence the construction and functioning of the brain, where
differences between male and female sexual behaviour originate.
And so ¡t Is not surprising that anatomists should have observed
slight variations in size between certain areas of the brains of men
and women. Brain size has nothing to do with mental capacities, as
brain autopsies of great and lesser thinkers have shown. The inner
environment (hormones and diet) and the outer environment (family
and social interactions, relationships with one's surroundings) are
ultimately the factors that influence the precise set-up of the millions
of neuron networks that make up the human brain.
Throughout pre- and post-natal development the diversity of
people's experiences results in microscopic anatomical variations
between their brains. One might expect to find fewer differences
between the brains of men and women who have been raised in sim¬
ilar contexts than those between two Individuals of the same sex who
have had very different experiences.
Spectacular technical progress in the last few years has made It
possible for us to study the living brain. By means of new brain-scan¬
ning techniques such as positron emission tomography and nuclear mag¬
netic resonance, it is possible to scan the living brain rapidly and pain¬
lessly and to draw up detailed anatomical maps of cerebral activity.
Analysis of brain scans of men and women reveals individual vari¬
ations that are statistically insignificant. The only notable differ¬
ence between men and women observed so far concerns the iden¬
tification of word rhymes.
In the last analysis, while every man and woman uses his or her
own set of neuron networks, the Important thing ¡s that our brains enable
us to see the world around us and act upon It with the skills that are
unique to each individual and each sex. This is the basis of the Infinite
diversity of thinking that constitutes the wealth of human civilizations.
Frida Kahlo (1907-1954),
painter,
Mexico.
Valentina Tereshkova (1937-)
cosmonaut,
Russia.
False-colour scanner image
of a normal human brain in
cross-section.
CATHERINE VIDAL,
of France, is a neurobiologlst at ij«|
the Pasteur Institute in Paris. Oí
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The women builders of Cameroon
In many traditional rural societies of black Africa, building is a collective activity in which all members of
the community take partmen, women and children.
In some parts of Cameroon, building has traditionally been a woman's job. The women builders know
exactly what can and what can't be done with the locally available building materials and use skills that
have been handed down from generation to generation.
Today this tradition is dying out. The requirements of rapid urban development and the use of imported
materials are pushing women out of the building market.
However, international aid agencies and the people of Cameroon themselves are starting to realize that
skilled women builders can make a big contribution to their country's development.
It is time for practical steps to be taken to safeguard the know-how of these women, to integrate them
as partners in rural and urban development and to set up training centres where their technical knowledge
and skills can be adapted to contemporary building conditions and taught to younger generations.
HAMAN MOHAMAN
Cameroonian architect and town planner
32
Kotoko women
builders of northern
Cameroon renovate
a cob-walled
dwelling and teach
their skills to
young apprentices.
Studying the
Qur'an in a training
area beneath a fig
tree, symbol of life
and discussion.
Dwellings
constructed by
Doudou, a well-
known woman
builder, in
Ngaoundéré
(Cameroon).
Why is the Beijing Conference being
held?
It is the fourth in a series of major inter¬
national conferences on women, the first of
which took place just twenty years ago in
Mexico City during International Women's
Year. Thirty-six thousand women are
expected to participate in the Forum of
Non-Governmental Organizations that
will be held from 30 August to 8 September,
and from five to ten thousand people will
attend the official conference from 4 to 15
September.
The Conference is a sign that "women's
issues" are gradually ceasing to be seen in iso¬
lation and are coming to be regarded as of
concern to the whole of society, with their
dimensions of justice, human rights and
human resource development. They are
issues of concern to men as well as women.
If the questions that have been raised at
meetings of UNESCO's Consultative Com¬
mittee on Women are anything to go by the
delegates will have plenty to do. Those
questions have focused on issues relating to
tolerance, respect for individual rights,
freedom of opinion and expression, and
the fight against illiteracy and poverty.
These are all matters that call for radical
change, and we hope that the Conference
will be an opportunity to take a step in
that direction.
What progress has been made in the
last twenty years?
In many parts of the world there have
been reductions in infant and maternal mor¬
tality, improvements in nutrition and
hygiene, increasing life expectancy, increased
school enrolments and female rates of adult
literacy, but the fact is that these social gains
are unequally shared. The gap between the
rich and poor is widening, both between and
within countries. Wide gender-disparities
prevail, more and more of the world's poor
are female, and discrimination and violence
against women continue.
The situation of the majority of the
world's women therefore seems to be dete¬
riorating, especially in the least developed
countries. In sub-Saharan Africa, they bear
the brunt of cuts in social welfare policies
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
THE ROAD TO BEIJING
THE FOURTH WORLD CONFERENCE ON WOMEN
Ingeborg Breines, Special Adviser on Women, Gender and Development to the Director General of UNESCO, .
talks to the UNESCO Courier.
induced by structural adjustment pro¬
grammes. Around half a million women
still die each year from pregnancy-related
causes, most of them in the developing
countries.
But much also still remains to be done
in the most "democratic" countries, espe¬
cially in politics. The average proportion of
women in positions of political responsi¬
bility is less than 10 per cent. In working
life, statistics show that women work far
longer while often receiving much lower
wages than men, either because they work
part-time, because they do low-paid jobs in
the informal sector or simply because they
are paid less than men for equal work.
Women's work barely figures in official
economic statistics and is therefore seri¬
ously underestimated. This also hampers
women's access to credit.
H What can be done in concrete terms?
From UNESCO's point of view, access to
knowledge and quality education for girls
and women is the most important key to
women's empowerment and to their full
enjoyment of human rights. At present
nearly two-thirds of the world's illiterate
are girls and women. One out of three
adult women in the world today cannot
read or write. In most parts of the world,
girls are under-represented at every school
level. In general, their representation
lessens the higher one rises in the educa¬
tional system. The obstacles appear early
on: economic constraints, son preference,
distance from school, early marriage and
teenage pregnancy.
Unless the world community targets
female illiteracy and commits itself more
profoundly to removing the obstacles to
girls' and women's access to good quality
education and training, this gender gap will
continue to exist. This is one of the twelve
critical areas that form part of the Platform
for Action to be adopted at Beijing.
What are the other main issues that will
be raised?
They range from the increasing burden
of poverty on women, to inequalities in
health care, violence, inequalities between
men and women in power-sharing and
decision-making, the promotion of uni¬
versal human rights, women and the media,
women and the environment and the situ¬
ation of girl children.
Has everything been decided before¬
hand and will the Conference simply meet
and rubber-stamp an agreed programme?
Shortly before the Conference opens,
there is still no consensus on large and vital
parts of the Draft Platform. The most con¬
troversial issues relate to women's health, in
particular women's reproductive health,
and the human rights of women. The main
confrontation is not between North and
South, as was the case at the case ten years
ago in Nairobi, but between fundamen¬
talist groups of different religions and the
women's human rights movement.
9 What are you hoping will come out of
the Conference?
So much remains to be done. Take the
question of development, for instance,
which has been a main theme of all the
women's conferences since 1975. Whilst
development must always be rooted in its
given social and cultural context, it has
become legitimate to question traditions,
norms, practices, cosmologies and religious
customs that are based on the hypothesis of
male superiority and that obstruct equality,
especially at a time when traditional patri¬
archal ideas on women's place in society are
gaining force.
We hope that the Conference will refine
our understanding of the mechanisms of
discrimination, exclusion and violence
through the findings of research and through
the unique experience and struggle of
women. We hope that the participants will
commit themselves politically and finan¬
cially to the goals of the Conference, thereby
providing an important incentive to trans¬
form societies away from the culture of vio¬
lence and towards the building of a culture
of peace. Such a culture can only be achieved
within the context of equality between
women and men, acknowledging that nei¬
ther is in any way morally, spiritually or
intellectually superior to the other.
Katherine Mansfield
(1888-1923), writer,
New Zealand.
Barbara Hendricks (1948-1.
singer,
United States.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
THE RIGHT TO VOTE
Years in which women obtained the right to vote in their countries
on equal terms with men
34
1893 New Zealand The former Yugoslav 1959 Madagascar
1906 Finland Republic of Tunisia
1913 Norway Macedonia United Republic of
1915 Denmark Trinidad and Tobago Tanzania
Iceland Viet Nam 1960 Canada
1918 Austria 1947 Argentina Cyprus
Georgia Bangladesh Gambia
Germany Japan San Marino
Ireland Malta Tonga
Latvia Mexico 1961 Burundi
Poland Venezuela
El Salvador
Russian Federation 1948 Belgium Paraguay
1919 Belarus Israel
Rwanda
Luxembourg Lao People's
1962 Algeria
Bahamas
Netherlands Democratic Republic
Ukraine Niger
Monaco
1920 Czech Republic Republic of Korea
Uganda
Zambia
Estonia Seychelles
Slovakia Singapore
United States of 1949 Bosnia and
1963 Congo
America Herzegovina
Equatorial Guinea
1921 Armenia Chile
Islamic Republic of Iran
Azerbaijan China Kenya
Lithuania Costa Rica
Morocco
Sweden Croatia
1964 Malawi
1923-1924 Yugoslavia 1965 Afghanistan
Mongolia 1950 Haiti Botswana
1924 Kazakstán India 1967 Australia
1926 Lebanon Peru Zaire
1928 United Kingdom 1951 Antigua and Barbuda 1967-1970
1931 Spain Barbados Yemen
Sri Lanka Dominica 1968 Swaziland
1932 Maldives Grenada 1969 Libyan Arab Jamahiriya
Thailand Nepal 1971 Kiribati
Uruguay Saint Kitts and Nevis Switzerland
1934 Brazil Saint Lucia 1974 Jordan
Cuba Saint Vincent and the 1975 Andorra
Turkey Grenadines Angola
1937 Pakistan Sierra Leone Cape Verde
Philippines 1952 Bolivia Mozambique
1942 Dominican Republic Côte d'Ivoire Papua New Guinea
1944 Bulgaria Greece Sao Tome and Principe
France 1953 Bhutan 1976 Portugal
Jamaica Guyana 1977 Guinea-Bissau
1945 Albania Sudan
1978 Ecuador
Belize Suriname
Republic of Moldova
Guatemala Syrian Arab Republic 1980 Iraq
Hungary 1955 Nicaragua
Vanuatu
Indonesia 1956 Benin
1984 Liechtenstein
Italy Comoros
1986 Central African
Senegal Egypt
Republic
Slovenia Gabon
1989 Namibia
Solomon Islands Mali
1994 South Africa
1946 Cameroon Mauritius
Democratic People's Somalia
Republic of Korea Togo
Djibouti 1957 Colombia
Sources: United Nations
- Liberia Honduras
Statistical Division, New York;
Panama Malaysia Inter-Parliamentary Union,
Romania Zimbabwe Geneva.
FIVE WOMEN IN THE
SPOTLIGHT
Five dynamic women whose portraits appear in a
series of documentary films on women of the South
made by American sociologist Judithe Bizot with
Unesco support
O In Mali, Aminata Traoré works to provide health
education in poor urban districts and promotes com¬
munity management of water supply points. She has
founded a garbage collection co-operative in Bamako,
organized cultural and study centres, and created
outlets for local handicraft producers.
0 In Pakistan, Khawar Mumtaz has set up a non¬
governmental organization, Shirkat Gah, which
encourages women's education and the participa¬
tion of women in public life. It is also concerned
with problems such as arranged marriages and the
discredit associated with the birth of a daughter.
Shirkat Gah also campaigns against the violence of
which women are victims and defends their right to
education and work.
© In Costa Rica, where a group of women mobi¬
lized around the slogan "Homes, not slums!", Marta
Trejos, Co-ordinator of the Feminist Information and
Action Centre (Cefemina), instigated a programme
to build 6,000 homes for families from the shanty¬
towns of San José. Helped by architects with whom
they have designed purpose-built housing, San José
women volunteers are working on-site as well as
mobilizing support for the project.
O In India, Himalayan women who are determined
to safeguard the forest formed the Chipko movement.
A trained nuclear physicist, Vandana Shiva, has joined
them to fight against the ideology based on compe¬
tition that lies behind the excessive exploitation of the
earth's natural resources.
0 In Kenya, Wangari Maathai belongs to a group of
women who in 1977 created the Green Belt Move¬
ment, an organization which seeks to halt desertifi¬
cation by encouraging tree planting and soil and
water conservation.
Vandana Shiva and Wangari Maathai have each
won a "Right Livelihood Award", presented by the
"Right Livelihood Awards Foundation" in recogni¬
tion of their "alternative contributions to the well-
being ofhumankind. "
PATRICK DEVAL,
French journalist
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
ROSALYN S. YALOW
Physiology or medicine: 1977
MARIA GOEPPERT MAYER
Physics: 1963
M ^Ê
BERTHA VON SUTTNER
Peace: 1905
IRENE JOLIOT-CURIE
Chemistry: 1935
Women
Nobel
Laureates
MOTHER THERESA
Peace: 1979
ALVA MYRDAL
Peace: 1982
BETTY WILLIAMS
Peace: 1976
RIGOBERTA MENCHU
Peace: 1992 35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY
Listening to Africa
I The threat of unbridled
I selfishness looms over the
strange world which has been
gradually emerging since the
implosion of the communist
bloc. The age that is dawning is
not the age of the individual but
the age of individualism. It is
not the fair play of free compe¬
tition that is coming in but the
iron law of the strongest versus the weakest.
And so we are still witnessing the scandalous,
morally unacceptable situation in which the
poorest countries pay for the richest, in financial
terms and in terms of talent. A world in which
the poor countries become poorer every day
because of the debts they have contracted to the
rich is a sick world. It is iniquitous and absurd.
Worldwide financial and economic strategies
are formulated heedless of the socio-cultural sit¬
uation of the countries and partners involved. As
in Molière's play Le malade imaginaire, "the
patients are always wrong" and are to be pre¬
scribed the same medicine. Diversity is disre¬
garded, and the specific natural and human
resources, culture, history and outlook of each
country are ignored.
These strategies are targeted particularly on
Africa, which is seen as the region that is most
refractory to their demands. Some claim that
they are justified by defects or shortcomings that
seem specific to Africa. They point to such factors
as the instability of governments, the fragility of
democratic structures, the persistence of tribal
structures and the temptations of ethnic violence.
It is true that Africa today is at grips with immense
problems. But how can we fail to see, not only the
downside, but the enormous potential of Africa,
its reserves of enthusiasm, the formidable cre¬
ative dynamism that is waiting only for an oppor¬
tunity to express itself?
The forces of joy and freedom, of modernity
allied to team spirit, of the kind of efficiency that
respects human qualities all exist in Africa. What
should be done is not to make Africans' history
for them or to promote from outside a form of
development that Africa would not want. It is to
state clearly whether we want to use Africa's
current weaknesses as a pretext for leaving it by
the wayside of the road to development, or
whether we want to help it to draw on its
strengths and its potential, so that it can make its
own way to development and become a full
partner in the world community.
A moral imperative
But why help Africa in today's world, in which
many feel that it is already difficult enough to
help oneself?
In my view, the first reason is that the West
has contracted a historical debt towards Africa.
The current wealth, power and dynamism of the
West are in large measure the result of the con¬
tribution exacted from Africa. This contribu¬
tion in the form of people, hard labour, sacrifice
and natural resources was exacted first in the
form of slavery and later by colonization. In a
massive and historically unprecedented haem¬
orrhage, Africa was slowly drained of its life-
blood, its vital, creative and productive energy.
Today Africa is struggling to recover in a
world whose guidelines, laws and command
mechanisms have all been devised elsewhere.
Africa must learn to operate within these guide¬
lines, come to terms with these laws, and use
these mechanisms, while at the same time
reclaiming its own history, exploring its own
democratic pathways and development priorities,
and endeavouring to secure the material and
technical resources for its own renewal. This is
the first reason, a moral reason, for helping
Africa.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
B Y FEDERICO A Y O R
The second reason is political and economic.
The world, as we are constantly being told, is an
integrated unit in which financial, technolog¬
ical and media flows know no frontiers, in which
events are flashed instantaneously from one end
of the world to another. This space-time con¬
tinuum, however, is highly inegalitarian and
functions everywhere to the benefit of a few.
If the application of the same rules to all is
detrimental to a large part of humankind, then
the rules must be changed. Market forces alone
are incapable of providing social justice, equal
opportunities and more human relations
between individuals and between nations.
Since we are all on board the same ship at
the height of a storm, it is in our interest to learn
how to share tasks, to even out privileges and sac¬
rifices, and to strengthen our sense of sharing a
common destiny. The alternative is to face incom¬
prehension, revolt and chaos. In other words,
to face the threat of shipwreck.
A shared responsibility
But it is not enough to talk of the responsibilities
of the developed world. Clearly, the responsibil¬
ities of Africa are no less weighty. Nothing can be
achieved without determined and enthusiastic
efforts by Africans themselves to bring about
democratic and egalitarian development. More
than anyone else, Africans know that the sources
of the future are to be found within themselves,
that it is from among themselves that the people,
the ideas, the achievements, the innovations and
the great reform movements will come to lift
their continent to the level of partnership in
today's world.
The paths to be taken and the quality and
quantity of the efforts to be made form part of
Africans' responsibility to themselves and to the
rest of the world. No one can today claim to
possess a magic formula for successful develop¬
ment. However, a number of conditions must be
met if Africans are to assume their responsibili¬
ties fully. I would sum up these conditions, which
are the same all over the world, in three words:
democracy, justice and solidarity. There is a need
to narrow the gap between civil society and the
politicians, to reduce the disparities between the
privileged and the deprived, between the pow¬
erful and the weak, between those who partici¬
pate in the process of globalization and those
who are excluded from it. There is also a need to
overcome the unequal opportunities and levels of
development between African nations by stim¬
ulating the moral, intellectual, productive and
material energies of the entire continent.
As a Yaounde proverb puts it, "a single arm is
not enough to cut up an elephant". Some projects
are too ambitious and far-reaching to be suc¬
cessfully completed by a single person or a single
people. This has always been the case, and never
more so than today when we find ourselves in an
increasingly interdependent world. What can
the countries of Africa hope to achieve if each one
goes its own way? What, on the other hand, is
beyond their reach if they take advantage of the
tremendous new dynamism that will result from
the pooling of their energies and hopes?
In order to imagine the potential strength of
this dynamism we need only think of all the
ethnic conflicts that beset the continent and
could be de-escalated by its union. Today's fears
could become tomorrow's liberated energies and
reconciled hopes. I am not thinking of an artifi¬
cial, damaging form of unification that would
undermine subregional or local characteristics,
but of true union in accordance with major
guidelines collectively chosen, union made all
the more creative by its respect for the diversity
of the forces on which it is based.
All different. Yet all united. Let us define and
draw attention to Africa's collective and indi¬
vidual needs, and to the commitment of African
countries to meeting those needs. Let us point
out what African countries hope to receive from
others and what they can contribute themselves.
Above all, let us highlight what Africa has to
offer the world and what the world needs so
much. We all know that without wisdom knowl¬
edge cannot lead to happiness. And the breath of
wisdom comes from Africa, as I know from my
own experience.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
1995 UNITED NATIONS
A triptych by Sofia Gandarias
In 1992, the Spanish painter Sofia Gandarias produced
a triptych dedicated to Sarajevo, the beleaguered capital of
Bosnia and Herzegovina. The three works are an artist's appeal
for tolerance and solidarity.
"We are going to bury our child"
(1992),
oil on canvas, 162 x 130 cm.
Above, "Why?"
(1992),
oil on canvas,
130 x 97 cm.
Right,
"The last journey"
(1992),
oil on canvas,
130 x 97 cm.
38
SAMI NAIR,
a French
philosopher, is
Professor of
Political Sciences
at the University of
Lausanne
(Switzerland).
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
YEAR FOR TOLERANCE
The art ofinference by Sami Mr
We know that paintings can speak. Not in the sense that
they construct speeches, arguments or messages. If
they do this, they are posters, tracts, works of propa¬
ganda. A painting, as the French philosopher Maurice
Merleau-Ponty once said, speaks to the mind's eye by
making the image an ideal representation an idea in
action.
All Sofia Gandarias 's paintings speak. A consum¬
mate portraitist and a worthy rival of her predecessor
Velasquez, she holds that painting is not a descriptive
art but a form that has multiple meanings. For this
reason she is interested in what is unsaid rather than
what is said, in the virtual rather than the real, in the
potential rather than the actual, in what can be inferred
rather than what is clearly stated. Take, for example,
her portraits of writers such as Carlos Fuentes and
Juan Goytisolo, or performers such as Frida Kahlo,
Rudolph Nureyev and Yehudi Menuhin. Juan Goyti-
solo's face cannot be dissociated from what is hap¬
pening in Bosnia. The portrait of Fuentes is steeped in
the strife-ridden, violent history of Mexico. These
effects are achieved not through signposts or visual
references but through an exceptionally detailed treat¬
ment of the face portrayed. All the history ofMexico and
all that Fuentes has written can be seen in the hard,
oblique eyes of the great Mexican master. The shedding
of innocent blood, the conflict of a divided identity and
the endless impact of creative discontinuities can be read
in the majestic and irascible face of the great Spanish
writer Juan Goytisolo.
Sofia Gandarias has thus invented a new genre that
displaces the established borderlines between the arts,
the divisions between genres and the restrictive identi¬
fications of things. Look at her series of paintings
devoted to Nureyev: pervaded with undulation, move¬
ment, rhythm and plasticity, this is a blend of painting
and dance. Happy are they, who, like the messenger
god, Hermes, know how to occupy the ground between
things, signs, time and space! They are the mediators
who pave the way for evolving humanity. Sofia Gan¬
darias may be one of their number. This, at any rate,
seems clear to the eye that can register what is happening
in these powerful and ingenious works where the pos¬
sibilities of our civilization can be discerned, in both its
barbarity and its grandeur. 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Baroque Zacatecas
40
UNESCO IN ACTION
HERITAGE
Silver mines brought fabulous wealth
to the Mexican city ofZacatecas,
founded in the 16th century. In 1993
the remarkable monuments in its historic
centre earned it a place on [/JVESCO's
World Heritage List.
by Francisco Segovia
InDecember 1429, the Spanish con¬
quistador Ñuño de Guzman set out
J from Mexico City at the head of
an army of 500 Spaniards and 15,000
Mexican and Tlaxcaltec Indians. He was
travelling west towards the mythical
kingdom of the Amazons, but also to the
very real riches of the vast region which
corresponds to the present-day State of
Michoacán. He had taken its cacique,
Caltzontzin, prisoner and ordered him to
be burned alive.
On reaching Michoacán, he pursued
his conquest in the direction of the ter¬
ritories which were to become New
Galicia. He then divided his army into
three columns. He himself set out to
explore Nayarit and Sinaloa, while one
of his two lieutenants, Cristóbal de
Oñate, marched on west towards the
future city of Guadalajara. The other,
Pedro Almindes Chirinos (Peralmindes)
was to make for the unknown lands lying
further to the north. So it was that when
he reached the site of Zacatecas "of
which he took possession with little or no
opposition", as the chronicler Fray
Antonio Tello relates, alluding at one
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
and the same time to the ease of the ven¬
ture and the apparent lack of strategic
interest of this inhospitable and arid
land. The conquistador did not suspect
the fabulous mineral wealth which lay
below the soil of Zacatecas.
SILVER MINES
As soon as they had taken possession of
these regions, the Spanish soldiers began
to search for the legendary riches of the
northern provinces. In 1546, one of
them, Juan de Tolosa, brought back
from an expedition to the Cerro de la
Bufa, the long rocky eminence at the
foot of which the city of Zacatecas was to
be built, several bags of ore which
proved to be rich in lead and silver "of
very fine quality". The fate of Zacatecas
was sealed.
All through the sixteenth century, the
territories conquered by Peralmindes
were to remain the forward bastion of the
conquerors of New Spain. They were
also quite naturally to be used as the
point of departure for the evangelizing
missions and the first expeditions to
northern Mexico and what are now Cal¬
ifornia and Texas.
Despite the resistance of the Chichimec
Indians, the mining centre of Zacatecas
soon began to prosper as a result of the
influx of Spaniards, indigenous people
and black slaves captured in Africa and
brought over to work in the mines. So it
was that the camp set up by Tolosa at the
foot of the Cerro de la Bufa spread grad¬
ually southwards along the course of the
Arroyo de la Plata, whose former bed
lies beneath what is now Manuel Hidalgo
Avenue, the city's main artery. Because of
the steepness of the terrain Zacatecas
lies at an altitude of some 2,400 metres in
a mountainous valley the architects
Opposite page, view of Zacatecas
with the cathedral In right
foreground.
Left, framed by an archway, the
massive towers and dome of the
Jesuit church of Santo Domingo
are silhouetted on the horizon.
Above, the 18th-century cathedral
with its ornately decorated towers
and façade.
were obliged to erect tall buildings on
each side of the river.
»PmVEKEEL AM» INTROVERTED
ARCHITECTURE'
That is the reason for the very unusual
character of this city with its irregular
layout, in which the narrow, winding
streets seldom afford an overall view of
the buildings. For instance, it is virtu¬
ally impossible to contemplate the façade
of the cathedral, "the finest example of
baroque architecture to be seen anywhere
in the world", according to the historian
Guillermo Tovar de Teresa, from a dis¬
tance of more than two or three metres.
The first house in Zacatecas is
reported to have been built in 1547, just
before the fortress and the first metal
foundry. By 1550, the city had already
acquired a hospital (Santa Veracruz),
and a chaplain had been appointed to
watch over spiritual matters. In 1558,
the Franciscans founded their first hos¬
pice. Later the Dominicans, Jesuits and 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
other religious orders were to leave their
mark on the city by building a succession
of churches, convents and charitable
foundations. The diversity of their archi¬
tectural concepts, together with those
of the Spanish governors, shaped the
city's appearance throughout the six¬
teenth and seventeenth centuries, and
even much later, until the days of the
revolution (1910-1921).
Raúl Toledo Farias describes this as
"a powerful and introverted architec¬
ture, as befits a somewhat harsh cli¬
mate", reflecting the sober and mea¬
sured character of the inhabitants, which
is far removed from tropical exuber-
.. anee. However, there are also historical
reasons for this sobriety. Although
Zacatecas very soon became a city whose
population was strongly marked by
ethnic intermingling, the indigenous
influences on colonial art are far less
visible here than in southern Mexico.
In fact, Zacatecas as it is today is first
and foremost a creation of the eighteenth
century, a product of the development of
the mines but also of efforts to spread
Christianity. The convent of Our Lady of
Guadalupe was founded by the Francis¬
cans in the suburbs in order to spread
the faith. It was inaugurated on 12 Jan¬
uary 1707, but some parts of the build¬
ings (such as the south tower) were not
really completed until the nineteenth
century. Today it houses an important
museum of Mexican colonial art.
CATHEDRAL, CHERCHES
AND MUSEUMS
The construction of the cathedral itself
was fraught with vicissitudes. The pre¬
sent building replaced the Chapel of
Santo Cristo, which in 1718 became the
parish church to which a chapel was
soon attached. The architectural com¬
plex began to acquire harmonious fea¬
tures in 1721. Only one of the three orig¬
inal façades was preserved. Work went
on for a considerable time: the dome
was rebuilt in 1848 and the south tower
completed in 1904.
Almost opposite the cathedral, the
Jesuit church of Santo Domingo, built
between 1746 and 1749 by Cayetano de
Sigüenza, is a magnificent example of
Mexican baroque. Its eight altar-pieces
in carved and gilded wood in the chur-
Hfc rigueresque style, are the work of Felipe
An alleyway in the old town.
de Ureña and his son-in-law, Juan
García de Castañeda. Taken over by the
Dominicans again following the expulsion
of the Jesuits, this monumental church
was often used as a cathedral when the
latter was closed for structural work.
The former Jesuit College of San Luis
Gonzaga (1616) stands next to this
church. San Luis was famous throughout
Latin America for the quality of his
teaching (one pupil of this college was
Father Antonio Núñez de Miranda, the
spiritual father of Juana Inés de la Cruz,
the Mexican poetess). Following the
expulsion of the Jesuits and a brief inter¬
lude in the hands of the Dominicans, the
college was converted successively into a
barracks, a prison and a warehouse
before being restored in 1981. Today it
houses the Pedro Coronel Museum,
named for a painter and sculptor from
Zacatecas, whose rich and varied col¬
lections include ancient Greek and
Roman objects as well as paintings by
Antoni Tapies and Robert Motherwell.
The museum also contains an important
collection of medals and 25,000 volumes
which made up the libraries of the old
convents (including 15,000 from Our
Lady of Guadalupe alone).
The church of San Agustín has also
had a checquered history. Consecrated
in 1617, it was refurbished and conse¬
crated again in 1782. Tovar attributes it
to Andrés Manuel de la Riva, the archi
tect of the famous church of La Valen¬
ciana de Guanajuato and its baroque
convent. With the adoption of the
Reform Act (separating church and
state), San Agustín was sold to private
buyers who turned it into a billiard hall
and hotel! In 1882, the complex was sold
again to the missions of the American
Presbyterian church, which for religious
reasons decided to demolish the main
façade, which had been the architec¬
tural jewel of the city. The Catholic
church regained possession in 1942 and
it is now the bishop's palace.
AN ISLAND OF PINK STONE
AND STUCCO
The remains of the church of San Fran¬
cisco also deserve a mention. The church
was built in the sixteenth century but
today lies in ruins. On the other hand,
the restored convent has housed a
museum since 1990; the collections of
Rafael Coronel, brother of Pedro and
like him a painter and enlightened con¬
noisseur, are exhibited here. He brought
together several works by Diego Rivera
and a unique collection of 5,000 masks.
Last but not least, the Goitia Museum,
outside the city centre, is also well worth
a visit as it houses, in the former resi¬
dence of the Governor (1948), the works
of six artists who are thought to have
come from Zacatecas: Francisco Goitia,
Julio Ruelas, the two Coronel brothers,
José Kuri Breña and Manuel Felguérez.
The civilian architecture of Zacatecas
is in no way inferior to that of its religious
edifices. One prominent example is the
old house of "Gonzalez Ortega" which
stands next to the cathedral and is today
part of the Governor's palace. The two
buildings look out over the Arroyo de la
Plata, which is lined by a number of
remarkable edifices including Mala Noche
palace, Jesús González Ortega market
and the Calderón theatre. A stroll through
this labyrinth ofnarrow streets punctuated
with little squares and distincitve build¬
ings, is one of the charms of the colourful
island ofpink stone and stucco which is the
historic centre of Zacatecas . H
FRANCISCO SEGOVIA
is a Mexican poet, essayist, lexicographer and
translator who formerly taught literature at the
National Autonomous University of Mexico. Among
his published works are Figuraciones (1989), Nao
(1990) and Fin de fiesta (1994).
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
A Tuareg well
near Nouakchott
(Mauritania).
FRANCE
BEQUETTE
is a Franco-
American
journalist
specializing in
environmental
Drylands and deserts
by France Bequette
u
Ar
I
questions.
round 900 million people
living in drylands all over
the world are directly
affected by the phenomenon of
desertification which is also respon¬
sible annually for the loss of some
$42 billion in income: Asia
accounting for $21 billion approxi¬
mately, Africa $9 billion, North
America $5 billion, South America
and Australia $3 billion each, and
Europe $1 billion," reports the Sep¬
tember 1994 issue of UNESCO's envi¬
ronmental education newsletter
Connect. "Of about 100 countries
affected by what is now considered
to be one of the most serious global
environmental problems, 81 are
developing countries, including a
majority of the Least Developed
Countries."
The stakes are high, and the
solutions hard to find. Detailed
study, however, has enabled scien¬
tists to rebut certain false yet per¬
sistent ideas that tend to shed the
responsibility for desertification
onto people who are actually blame
less. These people are victims of the
disappearance of traditional prac¬
tices that were effective in managing
dryland ecosystems and getting the
most out of them. Jean-Jacques
Perennes, who has studied the
North African environment for forty
years, believes that small farmers
have been forgotten by the agro-
industry, by engineers and by the
technocrats in charge of major inter¬
national programmes.
DISTURBING THE BALANCE
V
In the past twenty years the defini¬
tion of the term desertification has
given rise to much debate. In 1994
the Intergovernmental Negotiating
Committee for the Elaboration of
an International Convention to
Combat Desertification defined
desertification as "land degradation
in arid, semi-arid and dry sub-
humid areas resulting from various
factors, including climatic varia¬
tions and human activities."
According to Monique Mainguet,
professor of geography at the Uni¬
versity of Reims (France), "One
third of the land-mass, from 35 to 37
per cent of our planet (45 million
km2) are dry areas inhabited by 15
to 20 per cent of the world's popu¬
lation. These lands are found in the
polar, temperate, sub-tropical, trop¬
ical and even equatorial zones."
Yet 69 per cent of these drylands
that are used for agriculture are
either degraded or seriously threat¬
ened by desertification. "Natural
factors," Connect points out,
"though capable of putting severe
strain on the ecosystem, by them¬
selves do not account for land degra¬
dation unless they are aggravated
by human activities such as ill-
planned cultivation practices, defor¬
estation, overgrazing and faulty irri¬
gation techniques."
Dr. Mainguet says that the imbal¬
ance has several causes. The first
dates from the beginning of the colo¬
nial period, when pastoral societies
lost their influence over arable
farmers, and hence their power to
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Masai shepherds
tend their flocks in
Kenya's Amboseli
National Park.
control access to land and water.
Arable farmers occupied the grazing
lands, and the herders were rele¬
gated for too long to unsuitable
areas. Today, because of advances in
veterinary medicine, the size of
herds is increasing. With the best
of intentions, outside funding
sources are increasing the number of
public wells without consulting local
populations, and traditional prac¬
tices have gradually been aban¬
doned. The situation is further com¬
plicated by demographic factors, a
reduction in the time when the
ground is left fallow, the felling of
trees for fodder and firewood, and
urban growth that increases the
demand for food, although farmers
feel excluded from development
because cereal prices are falling.
The British ecologist Edward
Goldsmith is indignant because, he
says, nomad pastoralists have been
accused of being unproductive and
of destroying the environment,
whereas well-boring programmes
that have led to overgrazing and
the prohibition on burning grass¬
land before grazing have increased
the proliferation of tse-tse flies and
reduced the nutritional value of
dry-season grass. Goldsmith
believes that in view of the disas¬
trous failures of modern animal
husbandry programmes, the tradi-
Millet granaries at
Dogondoutchi in
southwestern
Niger.
tional methods seem increasingly
soundly based.
Monique Mainguet provides
some interesting details about bush
fires. Whether accidental or delib¬
erate, these fires destroy the humus
which retains water, mineral salts
and microbial life in the topsoil.
They are harmful in the middle and
especially at the end of the dry
season, but not at the beginning of
the season when they free the soil
from the preceding season's residual
growth and provide the animals with
good-quality fodder.
GOOD AND BAD METHODS
Human beings have survived in
deserts only because they have been
able to increase the quantity ofwater
available to meet their needs. One
example of wise practice is found in
the semi-arid zone of Brazil's
Nordeste region, where organic
matter is used as fertilizer, and the
people avoid ploughing the land so
as not to cause compacting of the
soil. Run-off water is captured in
small ditches, and a layer of plant
debris spread over the ground main¬
tains moisture in the soil and turns
into humus. Grazing land and cer¬
tain crops are sheltered from the
sun by bushes and trees. Fodder is
stored in silos. In contrast to such
extremely useful operations, large-
scale irrigation threatens to cause
salinity of the soil, as well as being
costly and creating few jobs.
Constant irrigation is not a mir¬
acle solution, as some have thought.
The October 1994 issue of the UNESCO
Courier looked in some detail at the
example of the Aral region.
According to statistics compiled by
the United Nations Environment.
Programme (UNEP), 65 per cent of
the water used there goes to farming
(especially irrigation) and 23 per cent
Water cannon
being used in an
arid area of
western Colorado
(United States).
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
FURTHER READING:
* Arid Zone Research Series, a 30-
volume series published between 1953
and 1969 by Unesco, plus a map of the
world's arid regions
« Unesco Courier, January 1994,
"Deserts"
* L'homme et la sécheresse, Monique
Mainguet, Masson, Paris, 1995
< The Earth Report, Edward Goldsmith
and Nicholas Hildyard, Mitchell Beazley
London Ltd., 1988
« Sécheresse magazine, No. 1, vol. 5,
March 1994
to industry, while 8 per cent is used
for domestic purposes. At present,
according to Edward Goldsmith, 90
per cent of the land in Egypt, 68 per
cent in Pakistan, 50 per cent in Iraq,
38 per cent in Peru, from 25 to 30 per
cent in the United States and from 15
to 20 per cent in India, Russia and
Australia are suffering from salin¬
ization. Sodium chloride and sodium
sulphate, and sodium, magnesium
and calcium carbonates in the soil
or in irrigation water accumulate at
the root level of crops or, worse still,
turn into a sterile, rock-hard crust.
At an International conference
on "Arid Lands Today and
Tomorrow" held in Arizona in 1985,
UNESCO environmental specialist
Michel Bâtisse pointed out that
although industrialized countries
such as the United States and Aus
tralia have the resources to make the
best use of their arid regions, this is
not the case for countries like India ,
Kenya and Somalia. "Moreover," he
continued, "the spectacular but
somewhat artificial arid-land devel¬
opment schemes implemented here
and there, most notably in oil-rich
countries of the Middle East, should
create no illusion. Heavily subsidized
irrigation, careless mining of fossil
aquifers, energy-voracious desali¬
nation of seawater not to mention
the towing of icebergs are no
answer to sustained development."
UNESCO's Man and the Biosphere
Programme (MAB) has for many
years been trying to encourage a
harmonious balance between
research, its applications, engineers,
public authorities and people, who
often seem to be ignored by inter¬
national projects.
"Humanity's efforts to survive
in arid regions," notes Monique
Mainguet, "have helped to sharpen
the human mind. Was it not in these
areas that monotheism and the phi¬
losophy of continuing progress first
took hold? The 20th century, a time
of fewer certainties, has seen the
high water mark of one phase of
development, then the first signs of
decline. I wonder if great works,
because of their vast scale and their
sometimes disastrous consequences,
are not symptoms of a kind of loss of
control by human genius and the
prelude to a disturbing decline."
Will the 21st century be a time when
the idea that small is beautiful is
rediscovered?
INITIATIVES
THE COUNCIL OF EUROPE I
AND THE DRAGONFLY
The Council of Europe, whose headquarters are in
Strasbourg (France), was founded in 1949 and
today has 34 member states. As part of its com¬
mitment to finding solutions to the major problems of
society, it is involved in a wide range of environmental
activities, including the detailed study of endangered
species of fauna and flora one recent report notes that
of 164 taxa of dragonfly in Europe, 65 are endan¬
gered.
The Council has established a European network
of biogenetic reserves and awards a prestigious Euro¬
pean Diploma to well-protected sites that are important
because of their plant life, wildlife or landscape. Exam¬
ples of award-winning sites include the Camargue
National Reserve in southern France, the Abruzzi
National Park in Italy and the Germano-Luxembourg
Nature Park. The Diploma may be withdrawn if the sit¬
uation deteriorates: the Pyrenees National Park lost
its award when a large building was put up in a ski
resort there.
The Council has an Information and Documenta¬
tion Centre on Nature Conservation known as
Naturopa, which was set up in 1967 and operates
through a network of national agencies in member
states and through special correspondents in non-
member countries. The Centre publishes a ten-lan¬
guage monthly Newsletter-Nature and a quarterly
magazine, Naturopa. This year the Council has
launched a year-long campaign: European Nature
Conservation Year 1995. An impressive list of events
is scheduled to take place in member states (no fewer
than 500 in Germany, for example) incorporating
many good ideas worth pursuing when the Year is
over. Other forms of co-operation established by the
Council include the Convention on the Conservation of
European Wildlife and Natural Habitats (the Bern
Convention), and the Convention on civil liability for
damage to the environment. Far-reaching assistance
and co-operation programmes for eastern and cen¬
tral European countries are also being implemented.
A model act on the protection of the environment
has been prepared for central and eastern European
countries wishing to adopt or modify environmental leg¬
islation. In short, the Council of Europe is a mine of
information that the public is urged to consult.
Council of Europe, F-67075 Strasbourg Cedex, France.
Tel: (33) 88 41 20 00, Fax: 88 41 27 15
LU
LU
er
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
CHERNOBYL TO CLOSE BY THE
YEAR 2,000
Earlier this year the European Union sent the
then French Environment Minister, Michel
Barnier, on a mission to Kiev (Ukraine) to dis¬
cuss the Chernobyl problem. M. Barnier met
Ukrainian Prime Minister Evgeni Marchuk and
President Leonid Kuchma, who pledged to
keep Chernobyl's No. 2 reactor closed and also
to shut down the No. 1 and No. 3 reactors
before the end of the century. In return, Europe
and the world's most industrialized nations will
help the Ukraine maintain the steel and con¬
crete protective shell surrounding the core of
the No. 2 reactor, manage radioactive waste
and spent fuel, keep qualified staff on the
site, promote the region's economic read¬
justment and supply Ukraine with energy.
DIAL-AN-EXPERT ON
TORNADOES
The number of tornadoes is increasing. There
have been more than 1,000 of them since
1990, and since 1953 they have caused the
deaths of over 3,700 persons. Last year alone
tornadoes injured 1,139 persons and caused
damage amounting to $481 million. Now the
American Center for Atmospheric Research in
Boulder (Colorado, U.S.A.) has issued a list of
tornado experts and telephone numbers where
they can be contacted. The causes of tornadoes
are not precisely known, but their routes are. In
the United States they are concentrated in
what is known as "Tornado Alley", which runs
north from central Texas through Oklahoma
and Kansas into eastern Nebraska, Iowa and
South Dakota, and mainly occur in April, May
and June.
For further information contact Joan Van-
diver Frisch. Tel: (1-303) 497-8607; Fax: (1-
303)497-8610; E-mail: jfrisch@ucar.edu
ENDANGERED BLACK-REARED
GILLS
Viikki and Laajalahti are two sheltered, low sea
bays with extensive reed beds, meadows and
lush vegetation along the waterfront near
Helsinki in Finland. Both are protected areas
listed under the international Ramsar Con¬
vention (1974). However, the Viikki site has
been badly eutrophicated by effluents and
fertilizers, and the Black-headed Gull popula¬
tion, which used to number almost 10,000
nesting pairs, has been reduced to a few hun¬
dred individuals.
A BIRD WASHING MACHINE
Bird victims of oil spills are often killed not by
the oil but by the stress of being handled by vol¬
unteers who try to wash and save them. The
French oil company Elf and its affiliates, Sanofi
and Yves Rocher, have developed a machine
a kind of cylinder with bars to which the bird's
outstretched wings are attachedthat allows
the bird (whose head is covered with a pro¬
tective hood) to be washed with a special
shampoo that is sprayed into the cylinder and
then rinsed off.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO
PROTECT THE ENVIRONMENT
The Caribbean islands of Trinidad and Tobago
form a nation that grew rich on its oil reserves
in the 1970s and early 1980s. As a result of
oil-based industrialization and continuing urban¬
ization, the country is now facing problems
including industrial pollution, inadequate solid
waste management, deforestation, soil erosion
and flooding. The tourist industry, which rep¬
resents 3 per cent of Gross Domestic Product,
can only develop if the islands' rich wildlife and
natural resources and its fragile coral reefs are
protected. To help combat environmental
degradation, the United Nations Development
Programme and the World Bank are supporting
the country's newly formed Environmental
Management Authority with specialized advice
and training.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
INTERVIEW
NELSON
FREIRÉ
talks to Stany Kol
The Brazilian pianist Nelson Freiré revealed
his outstanding gifts and strong artistic
personality at an early age. His international
career, begun when he was very young, has
taken him to cities on every continent,
where he has given solo recitals and
concerts with some of the world's leading
orchestras and conductors. He often
performs duets with the famous Argentine
pianist Martha Argerich, with whom he has
made many recordings. Here he talks about
his life and art.
How does a person become a great
performing artist?
In my case it all started very early. I was
a child prodigy. I was born in 1944 in Boa
Esperança, a little town in Minas Gerais
state, the youngest of five children. There
were no musicians in the family, but my
mother was a music lover and bought a
piano with her first wages as a teacher. I
think there were only three pianos in the
whole town. She made my elder sister prac¬
tise. I began to play a little myself, by ear,
copying what I heard. I was rather sickly as
a child and had several illnesses, but I loved
the piano. When I was four, I told my par¬
ents that I wanted to take lessons.
So they found you a teacher.
Yes, but he lived a four-hour bus ride
away. I went to him once a week and had to
get up at four in the morning. In those days
there were no motorways. In fact the road
was a dirt track, often drenched with rain.
After twelve lessons, the teacher told my
father that there was nothing more he could
teach me and that I'd have to go to Rio de
Janeiro, which was then the capital of
Brazil, to get a decent musical education.
And so we moved to Rio. It was a big deci¬
sion for my parents, who had always made
their home in Boa Esperança, where all
their family lived. My father, who was a
pharmacist, had to give up his profession
and take a job in a bank.
I took tests at the Rio school of music.
The professional musicians were impressed
and said I was a child with "golden hands".
But I was still only playing by instinct. I had
a hard time finding a teacher. I was a rather
unruly child. For two years I went from
teacher to teacher. I even kicked one of
them because he kept touching my ears,
and I hated that. My parents were getting
fed up and were thinking of returning to
Boa Esperança, and then I was introduced
to Lucia Branco, one of the few piano
teachers in Rio I hadn't met. She was a
well-known teacher who had been trained
by a pupil of Franz Liszt. She advised my
parents to send me to one of her students
who, she thought, was mad enough to agree
to work with mc.
That's how I met Nise Obino, her assis¬
tant. It was love at first sight. With Nise I
went right back to square one, including
even the position of the fingers on the key¬
board. She managed to get me to make
remarkable progress. My relationship with
her was very strong, the strongest in my life.
One day when I was ill with a very high
fever, she came to see me and put her hand
on my forehead, and my temperature went
down immediately. We were very close until
her death last January, which was a terrible
blow for me.
Did you go to school while you were
being trained?
Yes, just like any other child. My par¬
ents didn't want me to be uneducated. I 47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
NTERVIEW WITH NELSON FREIR
only practised the piano a couple of hours
a day.
When did you first perform in public?
When I was four. Then, when I was
twelve, Brazil organized a big event, Rio's
first international piano competition. I was
invited to take part and was one of eighty
contestants. Several of the others were
already in their thirties and had a lot of
experience. Some had even won prizes in
other competitions. Lucia warned me that
it would be good experience for me but
that I shouldn't set my hopes too high.
Even so, I was among the finalists. The
final was an extraordinary event, a bit like
a big soccer match. The Brazilians are
mad about the piano. The hall was packed,
and the audience was very excited. The
president of Brazil, Juscelino Kubitschek,
who had followed the preliminaries, offered
me a two-year scholarship to go and study
wherever I wanted to.
And that's how you went to Vienna	
Actually, I only went there two years
after the competition, when I was fourteen.
I chose Vienna because I wanted to work
with Bruno Seidlhofer, an Austrian pianist
who was very well known in Latin America.
I'd played for him in Rio. I set off on my
own because my parents couldn't go with
me. I took the boat with Seidlhofer, who was
returning home.
In Vienna I was all alone for the first time
in my life. I was still quite young and didn't
know a word of German or anything about
the city. I found out what it meant to be
independent. Those two years were very
important for my personal development. It
was then that I met Martha Argerich1. I
didn't do much work, though, and didn't
enter any competitions. I did not five up to
expectations. Then the time came when my
scholarship ended and I had to return home.
Returning to Brazil wasn't easy. At sev¬
enteen I was in the middle of an adolescent
crisis, and I had to five with my family again
after acquiring a taste for independence and
living on my own. During the next year I
entered a few competitions but never turned
up on the day. Then in 1962 1 was offered the
opportunity of giving a concert in Sâo Paulo.
The concert was a big success and I recovered
my enthusiasm and desire to play.
You made a fresh start?
_ _ Not yet. Another failure was waiting
10 round the corner, in Belgium where I'd
gone at the age of nineteen to take part in the
Queen Elisabeth of the Belgians Interna¬
tional Musical Competition. When the
results were announced, my name wasn't
even mentioned. It was a bitter disappoint¬
ment. But Martha Argerich was there too.
Neither of us felt on top of the world, but we
were together, and that helped a lot.
Going back to Brazil after a flop like
that wasn't very enticing. Then I remem¬
bered that Anna-Stella Schic2 had suggested
that I should take part in a competition in
Lisbon where she was a member of the jury.
I called for information and was told the
competition was starting in two days' time.
I said I'd be there.
Without knowing the test pieces?
I knew everything except for a compul¬
sory piece that had to be played at the
beginning of the competition, Carlos Seixas'
Sonata in G-minor3. When I got there, I
asked for the score of this sonata, and they
gave it to me but thought I was mad. What's
more, when lots were drawn for the order
of performance, I had to play first. Anyway,
I got down to work and threw myself into
the competition. I walked off with first
prize! Things really changed for me after
that. For six very pleasant months I was
asked to give a number of concerts in Aus¬
tria, Portugese-speaking Africa and
Madeira.
But other countries were a closed book
for me until early in 1965 I received a
telegram from Brazil from Ernesto de Que-
sada, an old man who had been Arthur
Rubinstein's4 first agent and went on to
found the Conciertos Daniel. We had never
met, but he'd heard about me from a
member of the Lisbon jury. In his telegram
he proposed that I should give three con¬
certs in Mexico as a last-minute replace¬
ment for Alexander Brailowsky . That was
my first contract.
After that I returned to Brazil in style.
I did tours in Spain, Argentina, Costa Rica,
the Dominican Republic, Peru and other
countries. In short I started to earn a living.
One day when I was in Caracas Martha
Argcrich's agent contacted me and asked
whether I would fill in for Shura
Cherkassky6 and play Tchaikovsky's
Second Piano Concerto with the Bamberg
Symphony Orchestra.
Did you know the concerto?
When the Germans asked me that ques¬
tion, I said yes of course I knew it, whereas
in fact I'd never seen the score in my life.
And I had two weeks to learn it! I raced to
the music shops in Caracas, but no one had
it. I had to get it from New York. Then for
fourteen days I worked on it. When I
arrived in Schweinfurt I wasn't all that
sure I could do it by heart, so before going
on stage, I asked them to place a closed
score of it above the keyboard, just in case.
The next day the papers said "a new star is
born". That's how I got a foothold in Ger¬
many in 1966 and began receiving concert
offers.
I had a terrible experience in 1967. I
was going to play in Brazil, at Belo Hori¬
zonte in Minas Gerais state, and my parents
decided to go with me. Along the way, the
bus driver fell asleep at the wheel, and the
bus plunged into a ravine killing everyone
else on board, including my parents.
(silence)
When did you start playing duets with
Martha Argerich?
Publicly, in 1968 in London at a fes¬
tival run by Daniel Barenboim7. Martha
was invited to play in a piano duet, and
she accepted on condition that I should be
her partner. We'd often played four-handed
pieces at the house for the fun of it, but
this was the first time we did so in public.
We weren't very well prepared, and the
performance was not excellent. We didn't
play together again until 1980, twelve years
later, in Amsterdam. From then on we
really began playing together in concerts
and for recordings.
How do you explain the quality of your
partnership?
First of all we have known one another
very well for a long time. You know, the best
piano duettists are often brothers and sis¬
ters or couples. People have to be very
close in their personalities, tastes and sen¬
sibilities. What's more, Martha and I have
always been open to new discoveries. I
think we've kept clear of ruts and routines.
Is there a typical style of Brazilian piano-
playing?
After soccer the piano is the second
great love ofBrazilians. But while Brazilian
pianists have mostly worked in Europe and
have certainly been deeply influenced by
Europe, it is generally accepted that they
have a certain rhythm, a kind of vibration
that you don't find elsewhere. For the same
reason, some Brazilian pianists have inhi-
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
bitions and inferiority complexes. They try
to deny themselves by becoming more Euro¬
pean than the Europeans!
Doesn't that lead towards a certain
standardization?
There is a certain standardization of
styles today, especially, I feel, in the United
States. In my opinion it's due to changing
ways of training musicians, to the increase
in the number of international competi¬
tions and their growing importance in musi¬
cians' careers, to the money that is now
involved in music and to the somewhat hap¬
hazard development of compact-disc pro¬
duction. In other parts of the world,
including Europe, things haven't gone so
far, and musicians seem to be resisting this
move towards standardization. When I sit
on competition juries, for example, I am
struck by the quality and artistic tempera¬
ment of many young Russian pianists.
Do you think that Brazilian composers,
especially Heitor Villa-Lobos8, are performed
as often as they deserve?
No. Brazil has a lot of fine composers,
but Villa-Lobos is about the only one who is
widely known. And even he, who produced
a considerable body of work, isn't per¬
formed very often. I like his music and
think I ought to play it. I do so in my
recitals. I also play works by Santoro9 and
Mignone10, but I'm not sure that this great
tradition of Brazilian classical music has
remained as active today as it used to be.
B You perform all over the world. Is the
public always the same?
Clearly there are different publics in
different countries and continents. I love to
play in Germany. Music seems extraordi¬
narily natural with German music-lovers,
almost as if they become part of the music
during a concert. In Asia in Japan, for
example the public is always very enthu¬
siastic, but it has a particular way of lis¬
tening and communicating. Certain audi¬
ences, like the Germans, are open to all
performers, well known or otherwise. In
Paris on the other hand, people will only go
to a concert to listen to a star. I have a
fondness for Brazilian audiences that I feel
intensely when I play for them.
But I believe that music is and will
always be an international language. At
most the same works are not heard in the
same way in different places. There is
another kind of problem. I sometimes
wonder whether concerts and five perfor¬
mances aren't experiencing a kind of crisis
because of the extraordinary development
of compact discs. I think too much is made
of them, and I feel that people are gradually
losing the desire to go to concerts.
Talking about the United Nations, Villa-
Lobos once said that if world leaders lis¬
tened to more music, there would be fewer
wars	
He was right. Certainly it is hard for a
Brazilian to imagine life without music.
Such a life would be a dreadful propsect.
Talking of Villa-Lobos, the last piano work
he wrote, in 1949, was Hommage à Chopin
in commemoration of the hundredth
anniversary of the composer's death. Who
commissioned it? UNESCO!
1 . Martha Argerich, an Argentine pianist born
in 1941, has an extensive repertoire, including
classical, romantic and contemporary music.
2. Anna-Stella Schic, a Brazilian pianist born in
1925, was a close friend of the composer Heitor
Villa-Lobos, many of whose works she pre¬
miered.
3. Carlos Seixas (1704-1742), a Portugese com¬
poser whose work for the harpsichord is espe¬
cially well known.
4. Arthur Rubinstein (1887-1982), Polish-born
American musician, one of the 20th century's
most famous pianists.
5. Alexander Brailowsky (1896-1976), a
Russian-born American pianist particularly
noted for his brilliant performances of the works
of Chopin and Liszt.
6. Shura Cherkassky, (1911- ), a Russian-born
American pianist, who largely specializes in
romantic music.
7. Daniel Barenboim, noted Israeli pianist and
composer born in Buenos Aires in 1942.
8. Heitor Villa-Lobos (1887-1959), Brazilian
composer. Largely self-taught, he drew inspira¬
tion from Brazilian folk and popular music which
he investigated in his youth as an itinerant musi¬
cian. He later did much to develop musical edu¬
cation throughout Brazil. His music combines
indigenous Brazilian melodic elements with
Western classical music.
9. Claudio Santoro (1919-1989), Brazilian com¬
poser. A student of Olivier Messiaen and friend
of Heitor Villa-Lobos, he explored the possibil¬
ities of atonal music and then turned to musical
forms closer to Brazil.
10. Francisco Mignone (1897-1986), Brazilian
composer. He assimilated the style of the
Brazilian waltzes that the pianeiros played in
cafés at the turn of the century.
STANY KOL is Deputy Secretary of Unesco's General
Conference.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
(fc^ LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
NAME THE CULPRITS
50
While reading your March 1995 issue
("Development the haves and the have-
nots"), I was struck by the fact that you
simply described the deplorable condi¬
tions that exist in Chiapas, Moscow,
Bombay, Rio de Janeiro and Soweto and
'did not say who or what is really respon¬
sible for this state of affairs, namely the
existing power system. These countries
will never be able to heal their wounds
without far-reaching social, economic
and monetary reforms on an interna¬
tional scale.
You merely describe what is being
done by non-governmental organizations
and associations whose efforts will have
few long-term effects. That is not enough.
You should speak out and accuse the
culprits.
BERTRAND FERRO
Toul (France)
DEMOCRACY AND WORLD
CITIZENSHIP
I should like to hail Federico Mayor's
book, La mémoire de l'avenir ("The
memory of the future"), in which he
points out how necessary it is for
everyone to take part in democratic life
and to exercise their vigilance to pro¬
mote respect for human rights. I am con¬
vinced that we must act on every level to
make known the aspirations of interna¬
tionalism.
PATRICK MICHEL
Citizen of the world
ROUND IS NOT ROMAN
I should like to draw your attention to
the article "A light that shines through
time and cultures" published in your
January 1995 issue on the sun ("The
sun ancient myths, new technologies").
The town of Bram in France was founded
on the site of a Roman settlement (vicus
Eburomagus), but contrary to what the
author of the article seems to say, its
present circular form has nothing
Roman about it (Roman town-planning
tended to favour a rectangular layout);
it dates from the Middle Ages.
J. DELMAS
Villenave-d'Ornon (France)
S.O.S. CHILDREN
I would like to suggest that the article
entitled "S.O.S. Children" published in
your December 1994 issue ("Religion
and politics today") might have given
special credit to the outstanding role
played by UNESCO (principally on the
initiative of the Polish educator Dr.
Bernard Dreziewski) in the care and
rehabilitation of war-handicapped chil¬
dren and orphans during the post-war
years. Upon the suggestion of Professor
Jean Piaget, seminars were organized
in which I actively participated and
an international non-governmental orga¬
nization, the International Federation of
Children's Communities (FICE), was set
up under the auspices of UNESCO. Herr
Hermann Gmeiner's effort to found the
first S.O.S. Children's village was
inspired by the UNESCO initiative in the
1946-1948 period.
H. Z. HÖXTER
President, International Round Table for the
Advancement of Counselling (IRTAC)
London (United Kingdom)
FUTREMBEN!
When I compare the cast of the Egyptian
statuette of the scribe Nebmertuf sitting
at Thoth 's feet that stands on my desk
with the photo of it on page 23 of your
April 1995 issue ("The origins of
writing"), I can only conclude that the
photo was reversed. This does not
detract from the quality of the issue.
HUBERT PAVIE
Louveciennes (France)
Bravofor your sharp eyes (Ed).
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
Cover: Getreu/Schuster © Explorer, Paris. Page
5 (above): A. Wolf © Explorer, Paris. Page 5
(middle): © Jean Loup Charmet, Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris. Pages 5 (below), 7 (above),
17 (below), 19 (middle), 21 (above right): ©
Jean Loup Charmet, Paris. Page 6: © Dagli
Orti, Paris. Page 7 (middle): Owen Franken ©
Sygma, Paris. Pages 7 (below), 19 (below): ©
Claude Sauvageot, Paris. Pages 8, 10-11: W.
Campbell © Sygma, Paris. Pages 9, 15 (above
left), 46 (below right), 47, 49: All Rights
Reserved. Pages 12-13: Raghubir Singh ©
ANA, Paris. Page 12 (below): Nancy Durrell
McKenna © Panos Pictures, London. Page 13
(above right): © Lapi-Viollet, Paris. Page 13
(below): © Keystone/Sygma, Paris. Page 14:
Neil Cooper © Panos Pictures, London. Page 15
(above right): Daniel Simon © Gamma, Paris.
Pages 15 (middle), 23 (below right), 29
(below): © Viollet Collection, Paris. Pages 15
(below), 16 (below): Zed Nelson © Panos Pic¬
tures, London. Pages 16-17: C. Letourneur ©
Sygma, Paris. Pages 17 (above right), 33
(above): © Harlingue Viollet, Paris. Page 18:
Jean-Pierre Degas © ASK, Paris. Page 19
(above): Eric Préau © Sygma, Paris. Page 20
(above): © Armineh Johannes, Paris. Page 20
(below): © Béatrice Petit, Brussels. Page 21
(above left): © Patrick Lagès, Paris. Page 21
(middle): Ulf Andersen © Gamma, Paris. Page
21 (below): Betty Press © Panos Pictures,
London. Pages 22, 23 (below left): Carlos Car¬
rion © Sygma, Paris. Page 23 (above): J
Guichard © Sygma, Paris. Pages 23 (above
right), 31 (above), 31 (middle): © Keystone,
Paris. Page 24: Poveda © Agence Vu, Paris.
Page 25: Sergio Durantes © Sygma, Paris.
Pages 26, 29 (above): Gianni Giansanti ©
Sygma, Paris. Page, 27 (above): Pierre Vau-
they © Sygma, Paris. Page 27 (middle): ©
Sygma, Paris. Page 27 (below): Philip Wol-
muth © Panos Pictures, London. Page 28: Mark
Edwards © Still Pictures, London. Page 29
(middle): Matsumoto © Sygma, Paris. Page
30: Brenda Prince © Format, London. Page 31
(below): Dan McCoy © Black Star/Rapho, Paris.
Page 32: © Haman Mohaman, Paris. Page 33
(below): Fabian © Sygma, Paris. Page 35: © The
Nobel Foundation, Stockholm. Page 36: Unesco-
Ines Forbes. Pages 38, 39: Fabien de Cugnac/
Interpress Photo © Sofia Gandarias. Pages 40
(left), 41, 42: © Régis Bonnerot, Paris. Page 40
(right): ©Javier Hinojosa, Mexico City. Page 43:
M. Renaudeau © Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 44
(above): M. Denis-Huot© Hoa Qui, Paris. Page
44 (below): M. Huet © Hoa Qui, Paris. Page 45
(above): Jean-Paul Thomas © Jacana, Paris.
Page 45 (below): Gérard Boutin © Hoa Qui,
Paris. Page 46 (above left): Bernstein/F.S.P. ©
Gamma, Paris. Page 46 (above right): R. Moyer
© Rapho, Paris. Page 46 (below left): Varin/
Visage © Jacana, Paris.
CORRECTION. Owing to an error
in the production of our July-August number,
the final question and answer in the interview
with the Czech-born American film director Milos
Forman ("How do you get on with American film
technicians?") appeared (on page 64) as part
of the interview with Nagisa Oshima. We apol¬
ogize to readers for this mistake.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Writing and Cinema
10,000 square metres for 250 publishers and 200 authors.
Exhibitions > Jean Giono's writings > La Fontaine: morality yesterday and today > The wolf's joke > Contemporary art
> Massin, Doisneau: birth of a collection. Literary Prizes > Rafael Alberti, winner of the Ecureuil Foreign Literature Prize
1 995: an exhibition of his pictorial and literary works >- The Air Inter Prize for the first European novel. 25 debates and inter¬
views. Spotlight > Writing and cinema. A movie theatre >- authors/script-writers and authors/film-makers: 12 films.
from 5 to 8 October 1995 (hangar 5) Tel. 56 43 04 35
Unesco is now on-line via Internet
gopherunesco.org
or
url:http://unesco.org:70
Currently on-line are: UNESCO press releases, addresses, fax, telex and electronic mail numbers of UNESCO's regional
offices, National Commissions and UNESCO Clubs, the directory of UNESCO databases and information services, an index
of the contents of the last 22 issues of the UNESCO Courier, colour images of the Japanese Garden and other architectural
sites at UNESCO Headquarters, as well as works of art such as Henry Moore's reclining sculpture.
To contact the UNESCO Courier directly with suggestions and comments on the magazine, type:
unesco. courier® unesco.org
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
THEME OF THE NEXT ISSUE
(OCTOBER 1995):
THE UNITED NATIONS
AT FIFTY
INTERVIEW WITH THE COLOMBIAN WRITER
GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ
HERITAGE:
THE IGUAÇU FALLS
ENVIRONMENT:
WOMEN AND THE HEALTH OF THE PLANET
UNES
A CENTURY OF
CINEMA
s , M 1205 44.00 F
" II lililí! I I IHM III
Jean-Claude Carrière
Milos Forman
Tomás Gutiérrez Alea
Gaston Kaboré ~
Mani Kaul LmLtW .
Abbas Kiarostami i
Milco Mancevski ¡gg¡
Marcello Mastroianni
Nagisa Oshin .uA«t.
Jean-Paul Rappeneau :. -
Volker Schlöndorff
Krzysztof Zanussi
and an essay
by Elie Faure
Each month, essential
reading for an
understanding of the
problems of today and
tomorrow
three good
reasons for
offering your
friends a gift
subscription:
The Unesco Courier is the only international magazine published in 30
languages and read by hundreds of thousands of people in 120 countries
Each month it explores the astonishing diversity of world culture and
knowledge
It associates its readers with Unesco's mission of furthering "universal
respect for justice, for the rule of law and for human rights and fundamental
freedoms...without distinction of race, sex, language or religion...''
]]>
</page>
</document>
