<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="105969eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
: Jk\
landscape with figures
k^ THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN PEOPLE AND PLACES
HERITAGE
THE ISLAND OF
MOZAMBIQUE
GREENWATCH
GARDENS OF
THE FAR EAST
v'
M 1205 9705 22,00 F
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTERS?̂*
¿4 't .A*' » 'S*' ' We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture
or any other subject which seems
to be an example of cultural
cross-fertilization.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
TRIBUTE
TO GERÓNIMO
1990
Photo by Roger Gangloff
This cross-cut from a tree
uprooted by a storm
reminded French
photographer Roger
Gangloff so strongly of the
profile of the Apache leader
Gerónimo (1829-1908),
that he photographed it as
a tribute to the famous
hero of Indian resistance in
the American West.
© Roger Gangloff, Chätenay-Malabry
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
the unesco Courier
INTERVI E\
Aimé Césaire.
Martinique's great poet andplaywright talks
about bis belief in the constructive force of
poetry (p. 4).
The Island of Mozambique (Mozambique).
The remarkable architectural unity of
an old trading port on the sea route to the
Indies (p. 40).
contents
MAY 1997
LANDSCAPE WITH FIGURES
THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN PEOPLE AND PLACES
Month by month fryBahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	9
Reading the landscape	
by Yves Bergeret
Thresholds of divinity
by Masayuki Ninomiya
Sicilian flights	
by Jean-François Patricola
Colourful language
by Guillermo Piña-Contreras
Say it with flowers	
by Yannis E. loannou
What's in a name?
by Luis Mizón
Fact file: The world network of biosphere reserves .
Consultant: Yves Bergeret
Commentary Federico Mayor
HERITAGE
The Island of Mozambique by Patrick Lagès
GREENWATCH Gardens of the Far East by France Bequette.
LISTENING Ethiopia's azmariminstrels .
by Isabelle Leymarie
ANNIVERSARY Aleko Konstantinov (1863-1897) .
by Georgi DanaJlov
AUTHORS	
10
16
20
24
28
32
36
38
40
44
48
49
50
Cover: At the feast of Kasada, held during the full moon, the people of the Tengger Mountains In
Java (Indonesia) throw offerings into the crater of Bromo, an active volcano. ©joefen/Ask.Pans
THE UNESCO I OURIERB MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
interview Aimé Césai re
Aimé Césaire, who was bom in Martinique in 1913, is one of this century's major
writers. In his poetry, plays and political activities he has waged a lifelong strug¬
gled restore dignity to colonized peoples. Firstandforemosta poet, here he
talks to Annick Thebia Melsan about his faith in the power of words.
The usual way of trying to place you is by reference to
various things such as time and place, writing, poetry
and its different categories, political action and so on,
but how would you place yourself?
Aimé Césaire: That's a terribly difficult ques¬
tion to answer but, well, I'm a man, a man from
Martinique, a coloured man, a black, someone
from a particular country, from a particular geo¬
graphical background, someone willi a history
who has fought for a specific; canst;. It's not \cry
original but, broadly speaking, my answer would
be that history will say who I am.
You are from the north of Martinique. . . .
A.C.: I've always had the feeling that I was on a
quest to reconquer something, my name, my coun¬
try or myself.
That is why my approach has in essence always
been poetic.
Hecause it seems to me that in a way that's
what poetry is.
The reconqucst of the self by the self.
And what is your preferred instrument for that
purpose?
A. C: I think words are the essential instrument!
Fora painter it would be painting! Fora poet
it is words!
I think it was Heidegger who said that words
are the abode of being. There are many such quo¬
tations. I believe it w as lîené Char, in his surreal¬
ist days, who said that words know much more
about us than we know about them.
I too believe that words have a revealing as
well as a creative function.
Revealing, creative . . . exploratory, perhaps?
A.C.: Exploratory is \ery well put! It's the plum¬
met drojiped in the water, the homing dev ice that
brings ihe self back up to the surface.
You have often said that the black person's first
words, after the long years of silence, are bound to be
revolutionary words. Does that mean that poetry is
"revolutionary" as well?
A.C.: Yes, it is revolutionary because it is the
world turned upside down, ploughed up, trans¬
muted.
When the review Tropiques came out in Mar¬
tinique under the occupation in 1911, in the mid¬
dle of ihe world war, like a plunge into tin; con¬
tradictory wellsprings of tin; West Indian soul, a
stark glimpse into the depths of colonial alien¬
ation, it was truly a cultural revolution.
And when ihe Vichy censor banned Tropiques
in 1911 with the comment that it was revolution¬
ary, he showed himself to be a very good critic. It's
true! It was a cultural revolution.
We were carrying out a kind of Coperniean
revolution. There was good reason to be surpised!
And the Martiniquais were themselves surprised
as they slood revealed to themselves. It was a
strange encounter!
It modified quilo a number of values.
Which ones?
A.C.: We are by definition complicated beings.
That is the general rule for any society but one
that is particularly applicable, in the case of soci¬
eties where complex layers of sediment have
been laid down as a result of the inequalities of
colonial life. Not everything was negative, far
from it. The hybridization of which we are the
outcome has achievements and positive values
to its credit wherein the West and Europe, also
had their share. There was, as I say, a positive
side, the effects of which were only belatedly felt
by the non-Europeans but which are undeniable
and in which we are simultaneously agents and
partners and, I should add, sometimes the ben¬
eficiaries as well. The Abbé Grégoire1, Victor
Sclioelclier- and all those who spoke out and
> QuiTriEUNEsco Courier« may 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Identity means having roots, but it is also
a transition, a transition to the universal,
Mimé Césaire
in April 1994.
still speak out, who campaigned for human rights
without distinction of race and against discrim¬
ination, these were my guides in life. They stand
forever as representatives of the West's great
outpouring of magnanimity and solidarity, an
essential contribution to the advancement of the
ideas of practical universality and human val¬
ues, ideas without which the world of today
would not be able to see its way forward. 1 am for¬
ever a brother to them, at one with them in their
combat and in their hopes.
You made an important speech in Geneva in 1978, at
the event called "Geneva and the Black World", in
which you said: "The effective power of poetry, with its
two faces, one looking nostalgically backward, the
other looking prophetically forward, with the
redeeming feature of its ability to redeem the self, is
the power of intensifying life". Was your Cahier d'un
retour au pays natal, published in 1939, just such a
primary utterance?
A.C.: Yes, that is how I see it: a new starting-point,
a real start there are many false; starts in life.
I5ut I think that was, for me, the real start.
Disinterring memories, all that was buried,
bringing it back, presenting it so that it bursts
forth fully formed upon the world 1 think this
sends an important signal. To express, not sup¬
press, the force of one's reaction, to wield rein-
vigorated words as a miraculous weapon against
the silenced world, freeing it from gags that are
often imposed from within.
How does one set about "ungagging" the world?
A.C.: I simply believe in the redeeming power of
words.
Is that enough to deal with the human condition and
the way it repeatedly slides out of control?
A.C. : l'robably not, not without lov e and human¬
ism.
I really do believe in human beings. I find-
something of myself in all cultures, in that extra¬
ordinary effort that all people, everywhere, have
madeand for what purpose?
Quite simply to make life livable!
It is no easy matter to put up with life and
face up to death.
And this is what is so moving.
We are all taking part in the same great adven¬
ture.
That is what is meant by cultures, cultures
that come together at some meeting-point.
You invented the term "négritude", which has been
the mortar holding together a historic movement. Does
not the assertion of négritude carry with it the risk of
separating you from others, from "non-blacks"?
A.C.: We. have never regarded our specificity as the
opposite or antithesis of universality. It seemed to
us or at least to me to be very important to go
on searching for our identity but at the same time
to reject narrow nationalism, to reject racism, even
reverse; racism.
Our concern has always been a humanist con¬
cern and we wanted it to have roots.
We wanted to have roots and at the same time
to communicate.
I think it was in a passage in Hegel emphasiz¬
ing the master-slave dialectic that we found this
idea about specificity. He points out that the par¬
ticular and the universal are not to be seen as
opposites, that the universal is not the negation of
the particular but is reached by a deeper explo¬
ration of the particular.
The West told us that in order to be universal
we had to start by denying that we were black. I,
on the contrary, said to myself that the more we
were black, the more universal we would be.
It was a totally different approach. It was not
a choice between alternatives, but an effort at rec¬
onciliation.
Not a cold reconciliation, hut reconciliation in
the heat of the fin;, an alchemical reconciliation if
vou like.
1. Henri Grégoire (1750-1831), French ecclesiastic and
politician, a leader of the movement in the Convention for
the abolition of slavery. Ed.
2. French politician (1804-1893), campaigner for the abo¬
lition of slavery in the colonies, Deputy for Guadeloupe
and Martinique. Ed.
THE UNESCO COURIER! MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Aimé Césaire
The identity in question was an identity rec¬
onciled w ith the universal. Eor me there can never
be any imprisonment within an identity.
Identity means having roots, but it is also a
transition, a transition to the universal .
Fire, one of the main life forces?
A.C.: Yes, as vou say, fire.
There is an obvious fiery quality in my poetry,
but why? I belong to this island. . . . Why this
obsession in my poetry? It is not something that I
deliberately seek. I am aware everyone is
aware that the volcano is out there. It is earth
and it is fire.
Eire is not destructive. The volcano is not
destructive except in an indirect way. It is a cos¬
mic anger, in other words, a creative anger, yes,
creative!
We are far removed from that romantic idyll
beneath the calm sea. These are angry, exasper¬
ated lands, lands that spit and spew, that vomit
forth life.
That is what we must live up to. We must
draw upon the creativity of this plot of land! We
must keep it going and not sink into a slumber of
I bent the French language
to my purposes.
acceptance and resignation. It is a kind of sum¬
mons to us from history and from nature.
How, then, do you explain the fact that your
"primary utterance" was expressed in the language of
the colonial power, of colonialism?
A.C.: I have no problem with that.
It was not something I wanted, but it happens
that the language I used was the language I had
learned at school. That didn't bother me in the
slightest, it didn't in any way come between me
and my existential rebellion and the outpouring of
my innermost being. I bent the French language
to my purposes.
Nature and history have placed us at the cross¬
roads of two worlds, of two cultures if not more.
There is the African culture, which I see as being
below the surface; and precisely because it is
below the surface, overlooked, treated with con¬
tempt, it needed to be expressed, to be brought
out alive into the light.
But the other culture was the obvious one,
the one we were conscious of from books and from
school, and which was also ours, an integral part
of our individual and collective destiny.
And so I have tried to reconcile those two
worlds, because that was what had to be done. On
the other hand, I feel just as relaxed about claim¬
ing kinship with the African griot and the African
epic as about claiming kinship with Rimbaud and
Lautréamont and through them with Sophocles
and Aeschylus!
But what does the African griot think when he sees
the tragic events unfolding in Rwanda or Zaire and the
pall of hopelessness hanging over Africa, the Africa of
which you dreamed so often while you campaigned for
decolonization?
A.C.: I have never harboured any illusions about
the risks of history, be it in Africa, in Martinique,
in the Americas or anywhere else. History is always
dangerous, the world of history is a risky world; hut
it is up to us at any given moment to establish and
readjust the hierarchy of dangers.
I saw that very clearly as early as 1966, at a
time when great hopes had been aroused hy the
accession of many countries to independence.
Indeed, I spoke out about this at the opening sem¬
inar of the World Festival of Black and African
Arts in Dakar in April 1966, before an assembly of
African dignitaries who were new to their jobs and,
it must he admitted, unclear in their minds about
the world and the power relationships in it, about
themselves and about their irreversible responsi¬
bility.
I have the words of my speech of 6 April 1966
here in front of me. This is what I said:
"Africa is under threat, threatened hy the
impact of industrial civilization, threatened by
the internal dynamism of Europe and America.
You may ask why we should talk of threats when
there is no European presence in Africa , when colo¬
nialism has disappeared and Africa has become
independent.
"Unfortunately, Africa will not get off so
lightly. The disappearance of colonialism does not
mean that the danger of African culture disinte¬
grating has also disappeared. The danger exists
and everything contributes to it, whether the Euro¬
peans are there or not: economic development,
modernization, political development, higher
school attendance rates, education, urbanization,
the integration of Africa into the world network of
relationships, and so on and so forth. In short, just
at the moment when Africa is truly being born into
the world, it is in greater danger than ever of dying
unto itself. That does not mean it should not he
horn into the world. It does mean that in opening
itself up to the world it should keep its eyes wide
open to the dangers and that, in any event, the
shield of a merely political independence, politi¬
cal independence unaccompanied and unsupple-
mented by cultural independence, would in the
long run prove to he the most unreliable of shields
and the most untrustworthy of safeguards."
On top of that there has been political irre¬
sponsibility, and the whole gamut of cynicism has
been run through! Fortunately, however, there
have also been shining examples of the greatness of
Africa, such as Nelson Mandela. Africa is experi¬
encing the human adventure, and I am prepared to
wager that the vital force of eternal Africa will
once more inspire the song of the griot.
What about the Marxist Utopia to which you
subscribed in 1946 and which you condemned before the
Budapest crisis in your Letter to Maurice Thorez, in
THE UNESCO COURIER! MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
which you set out your reasons for breaking with the
Communist Party?
A.C.: It is true that, like so many of my contempo¬
raries, I believed in what turned out to he a false
Utopia. I am not at all ashamed about this. In the
postwar context it expressed a heartfelt enthusi¬
asm, a spiritual yearning.
But it was very soon followed hy disappointment,
a feeling of being manipulated, a conviction that one
was being lied to and, as I said at the time, an unbear¬
able awareness of "the collapse of an ideal and the
poignant illustration of the failure of a whole gen¬
eration". I felt an irresistible need not to keep silent
and, regardless of the prevailing conformism, to
break away at whatever risk to myself from the then
all-powerful framework of the Marxist apparatus. It
was part of my ontological choice as a human being
aware of the non-negotiable responsibility that goes
with a consciously accepted identity.
In Discours sur le colonialisme (1950), you said that
"nobody can colonize with impunity, there is no
innocent colonization. There will be a heavy price to pay
for reducing humanity to a monologue".
A.C.: Yes, I am deeply convinced that universal
civilization has a great deal to lose by reducing
whole civilizations to silence.
I think it would greatly impoverish human civ¬
ilization if the voices of African, Indian and other
Asian cultures were to fall silent. If the global¬
ization we are now being offered were to reduce
the dialogue of cultures to a monologue, it would
create a civilization doomed to languish and
decline. I believe in the importance of exchange,
and exchange can only take place on the basis of
mutual respect.
Is it still relevant, in 1997, to think in terms of
combat?
A.C.: We are always, all of us, warriors. The war
takes different forms at different times, but there arc
always things to rebel against. One. is always in rebel¬
lion against something, things that are unacceptable,
things I will never accept. That is the inevitable way
of the world, probably for everyone. There are things
with which I cannot come to terms. I cannot accept
that a people be stilled or that Africa be obliter¬
ated, I cannot resign myself to such things.
I desire passionately that peoples should
exist as peoples, that they should prosper and
make their contribution to universal civilization,
because the world of colonization and its modern
manifestations is a world that crushes, a world of
awful silence.
At the age of eighty-four, Aimé Césaire, well over half
a century after Retour au pays natal, are you still faithful
to your belief in the urgent relevance of poetry?
A.C.: Of course I am. I no longer have the same ele¬
mental energy, or the same strength, but I stand hy
it, I have not reneged on it.
Is poetry still effective today? Will it always be?
A.C.: At any rate, it is for me the fundamental mode
The voice ofpoetry is the only
one that can still be life-giving
and provide a basis on which
to build and reconstruct.
of expression, and the world's salvation depends on
its ability to heed that voice. It is obvious that the
voice of poetry has been less and less heeded during
the century we have lived through, but it will come
to be realized more and more that it is the only voice
that can still be life-giving and that can provide a
basis on which to build and reconstruct.
Wouldn't you say that underlying the poetic
dimension of your work there is always a purpose, an
ethical aim?
A.C.: Yes indeed, there is an ethical aim underly¬
ing everything. From the time of the Cahier d'un
retour au pays natal onwards, a concern for
humankind emerges, a searching for the self but
also a searching for fellowship and universality, a
searching for human dignity, which I believe to he
the bases of ethics.
And yet this century has not been one where ethics
has triumphed, has it?
A.C.: Certainly not, but one must speak out, whether
one is heeded or not; we hold certain things to be
fundamental, things that we cling to. Even if it means
swimming against the tide, they must he upheld.
What we seek is reconciliation, to be in league
w itb the cosmos, in league with history, to be in keep¬
ing with ourselves.
In other words, poetry is for me a searching after
truth and sincerity, sincerity outside of the world,
outside of alien times. We seek it deep within our-
selv es, often despite ourselves, despite what we seem
to be, within our innermost selves.
Poetry wells up from the depths, with explosive
force.
The volcano again.
No doubt I have reached the moment of crossing
the great divide but I face it iniperturbably in the
knowledge of having put forward what I see as essen¬
tial, in the knowledge, if you like, of having called out
ahead of me and proclaimed the future aloud.
That is what I believe I have done; somewhat
disoriented though I am to find the seasons going
backwards, as it were, that is how it is and that is
what I believe to be my vocation.
No resentments, none at all, no ill feelings but
the inescapable solitude of the human condition.
That is the most important thing. I
THE UNESCO (^>URI ER MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Tri& UNESCO
Courier
^^50th YEAR
Published monthly m 29 languages and in Braille by
Unesco. The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
31. rue François Bonvin. 75732 Pans CEDEX 15, France
Fax (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
e-mail: unesco couner@unesco org
Internet http //www unesco org
landscape with figures
CO
Director. Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition RoyMalkm
French edition Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Features Jasmma Sopova
Art Unit/Production* Georges Servat
Illustrations Ariane Bailey (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 90)
Documentation: José Banaag
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press
Solange Beim (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 87)
Film duplication. Daniel Meister
Secretariat Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45 68 47 15),
Administrative Assistant Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean. (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 47.14)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil* M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian AkbarZargar (Teheran)
Dutch Bart Chnstiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili Leonard J Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian. Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek" Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Rntta Saarmen (Helsinki)
Basque Juxto Egaña (Donoslia)
Thai: Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa Ahyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician* Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostcla)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax (33) (0)1.45.68 57 45
Subscriptions Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45.65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel (33) (0)1,45 68.49 19)
Customer service Michel Ravassard,
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 45 91)
Accounts. (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 65}
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel (33) (0)1 45.68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: (33) (0)1 45 68 45 65
1 year 211 French francs. 2 years: 396 FF.
Students lyear 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues: 72 FF
Developing countries.
1 year 132 French francs. 2 years: 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads 'Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date o( issue and three voucher copies are sent lo the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author's name Non copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nee
essanly represent the opinions of Ihtsco or those ot the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700
Paris. (2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100
U S A . (3) N C R Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc . Ill West 40th
Street, New York. USA (4) Bell and Howell Co . Old Mansfield Road
Wooster Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL Cl -MAI 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M PP.
Photocomposition, photogravure
Le Courrier de I Unesco
Impression MAURY IMPRIMEUR.
Z I. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 5-1997-0PI-97-559A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51.
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
An ancient stairway
hewn from the rocky
cliff leads to the Inca
city of Pisac (Peru).
-
1 «
1
THL UNESCO (_OURl ER MAY 190 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The "crossroads cities" described in the UNESCO Courier
earlier this year are places apart. They seem to stand
aloof from their immediate surroundings and to concen¬
trate their gaze on distant horizons. The world is
their oyster.
In the present issue we see a totally different attitude
to place, one in which towns and cities, buildings and
works of art are dovetailed closelyinto their physical set¬
ting and bear witness to the two-way relationship between
people and the places they live in. We see a tapestry in
which the strands of geological time, historical time and
eternity have been successfully woven.
The two themes are nevertheless bound by a common
thread: the fluctuating relationship between societies
and their environment, a relationship that at different
times and in different cultures has given rise to a vast
spectrum of sometimes contradictory attitudesfrom
the humility of the nomadic herder in the immensity of the
desert to the arrogance of the industrialist who regards
the whole planet as simply a productive resource.
Here, in a nutshell, is the whole range of human
experience.
) (ouiTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1 007 %
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Deciphering
an age-old
language
inscribed in the
world around us
T !
lerrace farming northwest of °
Sanaa (Yemen). © I
w the UNtsco Kurier may iC"J7
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
_r^»..;
ÄSSr
Treading the
BY YVES BERGERET
landscape
T:here is always an interaction between
people and the places where they live
and move and have their being. Wher¬
ever you arc, on familiar or unfamil¬
iar ground, other people have been there before
you or are there with you, silent or noisy
companions. Wherever you go, there are signs
of human presence. You are surrounded by
an all-pervasive language, speaking with one
or many voices, dead or alive. The physical
sediment of that language, deposited on
objects and scenery, constitutes what I mean
when I use the word landscape.
Seashells in the sand
Looking down from the aircraft window as
you cross the Atlantic coming from Europe,
you see tiny islands and great white filaments
of cloud stretched above the distant surface
of the ocean, an abstract spectacle dreamlike
in its ever-changing beauty. You land on a
Caribbean island. Immediately you arc
enveloped by the sultry heat. You drive to a
small town, not far from the sea. It is already
dark, and the chorus of insects and frogs is in
full swing. Eventually you drop off to sleep
in this completely alien world. When you
wake up early the next morning, the sun is
already beating down with all its force. You
walk around the town. The trees are quivering
in the sea wind. Leaving behind the fish mar¬
ket and a knot of huts buried in the vegetation,
you come to a cemetery at the sea's edge. You
walk along rows of graves covered in white
tiles. Suddenly the cemetery gives way to the
near-black sand of volcanic islands. In a plot a
few yards square there are a series of mounds,
each the length of a human body, around
which "lambis" large conch-like seashells
have been driven into the sand, the pointed
end downwards and the big, ochre-coloured
end upwards and open to the air. Under these
simple mounds some of the town's poorest
people, penniless old sailors, have unceremo¬
niously been laid to rest, naked, with only
the sea and some of its creatures, and the black
sand over them.
These unadorned graves speak volumes.
The seashells are the loudhailers of the dead
and the ear-trumpets with which they listen to
the voices of the living and hear the sea wind.
Until quite recently, the same kind of shells
were used by fishermen as loudspeakers as they
drew near to the shore at night. There is some¬
thing admirable about these graves: the dead are
respected and their spirits arc addressed via
one of the most beautiful and natural objects
the landscape has to offer. You arc on one of
those groups of islands between English-
speaking North America and Latin America,
between the Old World which has left its colo¬
nial imprint, and the faint memory of pre-
Columbian populations exterminated by set¬
tlers from the Old World, between a
remembered past in Africa whence, because of
the slave trade, most of the population is
descended, and a present of ethnic intermin¬
gling. You are on a volcanic island subject to
eruptions and cyclones. In this environment of
chronic instability and general rootlcssncss,
the landscape is a medium of human dialogue.
I Waymarks in the mountains
I would like to cite mountains, supposedly the
wildest of the world's wild places, as an
extreme example of the human quality of the
landscape. I have climbed many mountains,
trekked across many wastelands, from Iceland
to Chile, from Afghanistan to the Sahara,
from the Troodos mountains of Cyprus to
Mount Pelée in Martinique. Having had this
practical experience and having got to know
THE UNESCO CniRIIER MAY I9Q7 m
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
> mountains as they really are, I have observed
that a mountain is never virgin territory.
Everywhere there are visible signs of human
presence and human labour that were specifi¬
cally designed to be visible tracks, embank¬
ments, terraces, dwellings, markers of all kinds.
Even in barren desert uplands you will sec
where animals have grazed. You will come
across a tent whose occupants will greet you
and invite you to share their food or drink
and join in their conversation. In another place,
when you thought you were completely
alone, you suddenly come upon a few piles
of stones or a heap of round pebbles in a dry
river bed put there as landmarks or bound¬
ary stones to show the limits of the grazing
grounds. In desert regions and places where
there is little agriculture, these practices still
continue. In the mountainous regions of
Europe they have a different function. The
mounds of stones known as cairns now serve
to show hill-walkers the way in the absence of
a track. These "waymarks" arc living things.
If you remember, you add another stone to
the pile for the benefit of the strangers who
will come this way after you.
Sometimes landscape has religious rather
than secular associations. Mount Sinai is the
place where the God of the three great
monotheistic religions spoke with a human
M statue of the Virgin Mary
and votive offerings on a
Corsican peak.
voice to give humankind ten rules to live by.
In this case we have a monologue rather than
a dialogue: God issues commands. On some
mountain tops there are small shrines, stupas,
crosses or votive tablets. The summits of the
Italian Alps provide a particularly vivid illus¬
tration of this. On many of them there is a
small statue of the Virgin, affording protec¬
tion from lightning and misfortune. The
Christian traveller should thank her on reach¬
ing the summit.
I know some mountain peaks, not only
those in the Italian Alps, where a recess is hol¬
lowed out of the great cairn surmounted by a
religious statue. In the recess is a metal box
inside which is a school exercise book or sim¬
ply some scraps of paper, on which those who
have made the ascent have jotted down their
names, the date and a few comments. I always
make a point of reading them, for however
commonplace the ideas expressed, they have a
merit of their own by virtue of the authors'
long, exhausting climb, beneath a wild sky,
to look out on this vast horizon. I feel as if I
am shaking hands with the person who a week
before wrote these perhaps naive words at the
bottom of the final page, and I may even shake
the hand of someone whose name has become
almost illegible, who left the brief account of
his or her ascent thirty years ago, and who
HE UNESCO COURIER MAY 19*17
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
.... ti- ti M cairn built by travellers
may now be dead and gone. In this way 1 have m t. CMm ,
1 a j marks the summit of a pass in
recovered from deep within the landscape a northern India.
record of the weariness and the joy of
strangers.
After days of trekking through the moun¬
tain wilderness of the Jbel Sarho in Morocco,
I climbed one evening to the highest summit
in the range, where I found cairns of all shapes
and sizes scattered about. Three days later, a
nomad explained to me that this was a holy
place to which pilgrimage should be made once
a year. The proliferation of cairns, as I under¬
stood it, represented individual prayers, or
possibly quarrels between rival tribes. Above
all, however, it bore witness to the survival of
a pre-Islamic polytheism that has left many
traces in Berber country. Here there was no
question of an agreed religious significance;
on the contrary, the principle of dispersal, of
multiplication, was at work. A few months
later I saw another of these, so to speak, decen¬
tralized shrines, at the top of one of the tough¬
est mountains in the High Atlas, Jbel
Anghomar. The ascent is difficult, involving,
after days of walking, several hours of scram¬
bling up a slope of orange-coloured scree. At
the summit, buffeted by the wind and with a
sweeping view over the Sahara and the High
THE UNESCO (oURIEl
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Atlas range, was a mass of cairns, "kcrkours"
as the local Berbers call them, and fresh traces
of the blood of animal sacrifices.
Mountaineering is supposed to be a dis¬
interested activity and as far as commercial
gain is concerned so it is, certain media-ori¬
ented antics apart. But it too does not regard
landscape as a blank backcloth devoid of
human signs. The mountaineer, far from
climbing a featureless slope, is engaged in read¬
ing a history book written in various "regis¬
ters" of language. First comes the geological
register: the climber has to use one kind of
technique and equipment on limestone and
others on granite, snow or ice. Then comes
the register of sport: climbers "rehearse" a
route already "opened" by some predecessor or
other, work out a timetable and train to get
themselves in shape for specific moves and spe¬
cific feats of acrobatics. There is also an aes¬
thetic register to what I call the "composi¬
tion" of the ascent: climbers' senses and
thought processes are attuned to savour a par¬
ticular shape of mountain, a certain light at a
certain time of day; thorough gymnastic
preparation enables them to perform a kind of
effortless-seeming dance in the middle of a
rock face or even experience rapture up there in
the sky. The boldest climbers of all, those who
"open" new routes, arc able, before starting
out, to sight-read the signs of the rock face
and their aim is to make the route as elegant
and rigorous as possible. Thus, even an uncon-
qucrcd peak is first regarded and then scaled as
a form of technical and ethical language in
which the climber enters into a dialogue with
his or her fellow human beings.
One of the finest acts of communion with
landscape I ever saw took place in a small oasis
I he heads of 4 American
Presidents are carved from the
granite cliff face of Mount
Rushmore (U.S.A.). Left to
right: George Washington,
Thomas Jefferson, Theodore
Roosevelt and Abraham
Lincoln. They measure up to 18
metres tall.
in the Atacama desert of northern Chile. I had
been trudging over those waterless high
plateaux, some of the barest scenery I know. In
the distance volcanoes rose to over five thou¬
sand metres. One afternoon I came upon a few
houses huddled around a spring in a hollow of
the plateau. An annual pre-Columbian rite for
the purification of the irrigation channels was
in progress. Three days of ceremonies were
culminating in a meal which had to start with
a glass of fiery corn spirit. Custom required
that the first drops should be poured on the
ground to salute Mother Earth, to quench
her thirst and to make her fertile. After the
libation and invocation, the drinking could
begin, the ceremony could be brought to a
close, and people could return to their daily
work.
Thus, as we see, humans fulfil themselves
by transforming the place where they live into
landscape. They humanize it, first discovering
and then creating signs of human life there.
Landscape is a mirror in which people can see
themselves, interacting with others of their
kind through signs scattered about in town
and country.
I A sermon in stone
Drive through the wooded hills of Burgundy
along winding roads that pilgrims in the Mid¬
dle Ages travelled on foot, until you come to
the little town of Vezelay. Climb the narrow
main street along the backbone of the hill.
Enter the dark narthex of the basilica, and sud¬
denly there looms above you the great mas-
terwork of anonymous medieval sculptors.
They dragged limestone quarried from the
surrounding hills to the top of the slope, chis¬
elled patiently away at it until it took on the
form of a Christ rather too big for the man-
dorla within which he sits enthroned, his
knees pressed together and turned to one side
in a kind of dancing posture, and of the apos¬
tles who are receiving from Him the gift of
tongues. Pass through the door beneath the
tympanum and into the full light of the nave.
This Pentecostal scene carved into the grey
stone of Vézelay is a response by those who
lived here to their landscape, a hard, unsmiling
land where the dark woodlands, the succes¬
sion of hills and the difficult communications
make for a certain heaviness, a certain monot¬
ony. All this they accepted, but at the same
time yearned for something else, an escape, a
transformation.
THE UNESCO (ou RIERB MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
reed shelter in
an Algerian wadi.
At the beginning of this century, Victor
Segalen made a telling contribution to the
establishment of this concept of landscape,
especially in his essay with the tongue-in-
cheek title oí Equipée (Jaunting). He pretends
to be making preparations for a voyage to
China, which in fact he already knows well. He
describes the country, travels down its rivers,
visits its towns and presents a wonderful pic¬
ture of a vast, inorganic natural landscape,
when suddenly the description takes strange
poetic wings. Two eyes are watching the nar¬
rator, the two eyes of a young girl about
whom nothing else is known. The traveller
observing the landscape is in fact being
observed by the landscape. Further on in his
essay, Segalen defines what he calls the "Esthé¬
tique du Divers", which entails recognizing
the existence of a proliferation, a destabilizing
turbulence, in the real world; landscape is
indeed a proliferating human language.
As the ancient Greeks could hear the orac¬
ular pronouncements of Zeus in the rustle of
the great oak groves of Dodona, so we for our
part can read the meaning of the gnomon's
shadow on the face of a sundial.
r 15
THE UNESCO ^_OUR1ERB MAY I9<>7
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Symbolic
gateways in the
Japanese
landscape mark
the boundary
between the
realm of human
experience and
the world of the
gods
hresholds ofdivinity
BY MASAYUKI NINOMIYA
No visitor to Japan can fail to be
impressed by the many torii sim¬
ple yet highly remarkable gatc-
_ ways which adorn the landscape
in town and country, in field and forest, on
riverbanks and even in the sea. Although
unmistakably gateways, they consist simply
of two pillars set in the ground, surmounted
by two horizontal beams, one just above the
other. A number of variations on this basic
form may be encountered, but the principle
of construction remains the same. Virtually
devoid of decorative elements, the gateways
arc characterized by austerity and purity of
line. Constructed of wood, stone, porcelain,
metal or even reinforced concrete, they may be
left bare or be painted red and black. The
height and width of the gateway may vary
from one metre up to twenty or more.
Composed of a few elegant strokes, the
torii resembles an ideogram, a signature affixed
to nature by human hand. A gateway without
a gate, it cannot be closed nor docs it form an
16 > G>uTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
I his immense torii arch
stands between the little
Island of Itsukushima and the
coastline of Hiroshima Bay. At
high tide its feet are in the
water.
opening onto an otherwise closed space. How¬
ever, its very presence carries meaning. It is an
emblem of faith. The torii stands as a clear
pointer to the essential relationship between
humanity and nature which has existed since
ancient times. It forms a symbolic boundary
between two realms which are fundamentally
different in human experience: the sacred
province of the gods (kami) and the profane
sphere of everyday human activity.
The torrii constitutes an almost intangible
threshold across which nature and human¬
ity may communicate. A thirteenth-century
painting depicts a sacred mountain at the foot
of which one of these gateways may be seen.
The mountain is the sanctuary, and the torii
is the only visible sign of human presence.
I Sacredpillars
In addition to their aesthetic qualities, torii
also have an ethical significance which extends
far beyond the doctrinal framework of
Shinto, which is the foundation of religious
belief in Japan. In Shinto belief, the gods arc
neither omniscient nor omnipotent. These
far-from-perfect entities arc natural forces
which bear a striking resemblance to human
beings, although their behaviour sometimes
defies human understanding. It is only by
their works that the gods differ from mere
mortals. As if to stress this proximity, Shinto
conceives of the link between heaven and earth
in a very concrete manner, as the "August
Celestial Pillar" on the island of Onogoro.
In a more general sense, the pillar plays an
important role in Japanese mythology. The
architecture and rituals of Shinto consider
some pillars to be sacred. Anyone may pass
through a torii at will, it is always open to
wind, light and sound, and to animals and
humans alike.
The Suwa trail
To escape from the oppressive summer heat of
Tokyo, I spent a few days in a mountainous
region in the centre of Japan, staying in a
small house situated in a forest of pine trees,
silver birches and lacquer trees, the sap of
which is an irritant to the skin.
At the point where the path to the house
departs from the main road stands a torii built
of grey stone. The rectangular plaque hanging
from the centre of the horizontal beams is
inscribed with a name of great resonance: Suwa
Jinja. The Suwa sanctuary, situated near the
Suwa lake on Honshu island, is particularly
renowned for the four sacred pillars (tree
trunks stripped of their bark) set at its four
corners.
But this roadside torii does not lead
directly to the sanctuary. The three or four-
mctrc-high stone gateway, in perfect keeping
with its natural surroundings, simply marks
the entrance of the path leading to one of the
subsidiary areas of Suwa Jinja. The feet of the
pillars sprout from a clump of miniature
bamboo, while maple leaves brush the tips
of the beams. As I make my daily passage
through the torii, the structure makes no par¬
ticular impression on me; I perceive it as I
Mt the Ise Shinto shrine, in
the south of Honshu island,
young women perform a dance
symbolizing the creation
of Japan.
THE UNESCO ÇïURIERI
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
11! J |pi
I%tT1Irrr
perceive the surrounding vegetation. It is like
a guardian spirit, discreetly preparing the vis¬
itor for the realms beyond.
Leaving the house, I may choose to
descend towards this first portal, or to climb
a fairly steep path and move deeper into the
forest. On summer days, a continuous flow
of nightingale song accompanies my foot¬
steps like a meditative chant, occasionally
punctuated by the repeated tapping of a
woodpecker. Nature is bursting with life. A
few hundred metres on, this winding path
comes to a clearing where stands another torii,
this time set apart from the vegetation. There
is no central plaque, no decoration of any
kind. The bark has been roughly stripped
away to leave the bare pine, dappled with
irregular knots. In spite of its state, it per¬
fectly commands the surrounding space,
undoubtedly marking the entrance to a spe¬
cial domain. Built by human hand, it signifies
a space that may be described as "sacred". Its
massive pillars can be seen as evoking the
"August celestial pillar."
The surprisingly small scale of the central
shrine, hardly bigger than a postbox, makes
this "sanctuary" all the more intriguing. In
18
wnow-capped for// arches at
Takayama, on Honshu island.
comparison to the size of this building, the
space created by the torii appears immense. A
sizeable bottle of rice wine sits, half-empty,
along with a few small coins, before the
miniature temple. The divine spirit obviously
enjoys a drink and needs money. The modesty
of this sacred dwelling reminds one of the
humorous touches in some of the more
down-to-earth passages of the Kojiki1
(Chronicle of Ancient Times) and the
naivetyof the gods who created this world.
I The 'cloak' on thepillar
Japan boasts far more spectacular torii; at the
entrance to the Itsukushima sanctuary in the
bay of Hiroshima, for example. Here, the ris¬
ing tide laps at the feet of the red pillars, while
the main buildings also standing in the
water are fleetingly reflected in the undu¬
lating swell. This sanctuary is a perfect exam¬
ple of harmony between sky, sea and moun¬
tains, which form an ideal stage for the
appearance of the deities. It seems as if all these
elements were infused with a single breath of
life.
Also worthy of special note are a number
of white wood torii at the Ise sanctuary, in the
THE UNESCO lOURIER« MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
south of Honshu island. The pure, unclut¬
tered forms, the exceptional quality of the
wood and the sheer size of these torii are such
that they deserve an article all to themselves.
However, I have chosen to evoke my per¬
sonal torii which, in their own modest way,
represent a fundamental aspect of Shinto phi¬
losophy. Through them, I may understand
in the midst of a forest or on the side of a
mountain how humanity has entered into
a relationship with nature in order to escape
the bounds of a "natural" animal existence.
Out for a walk one morning, I discovered
on one of the pillars the discarded skin of a
cicada that had moulted. Perhaps the deity had
left behind its diaphanous cloak, and had
hopped off to return momentarily to its celes¬
tial home.
1. This collection compiled in 712 A.D. is considered
the first classic ofJapanese literature, and is a reference
work of the Shinto religion. Ed.
i Shinto shrine in Tokyo's
Ueno Park.
THE UNESCO QuRI 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
BY JEAN-FRANÇOIS PATRICOLÄ
In Sicily the eye is constantly drawn upwards by natural and
man-made stairways that etch the urban and rural landscape
Pantalica in Sicily's Iblci mountains,
its necropolis and troglodytic vil¬
lages with their thousands of niches
hewn from the rock long ago like
so many irregular steps.
Caltagirone (Qal'at al-Gîran in Ara¬
bic) and its flight of a hundred and forty-
two steps finely adorned with majolica
which leads up to the church and exem¬
plifies the tradition of ascent that has been
transmitted from generation to genera¬
tion in Sicily. For the festival of San Gia-
como in July it is illuminated by thou¬
sands of candles and lanterns, nocturnal
sentinels on the sculpted mountain,
which very small children light when
they hear a signal a whistle from the
capomastro.
Greek and Roman theatres at Syra¬
cuse and Taormina, their broad terraces
still thronged with spectators who come
to watch and listen to operas and
tragedies, with purple velvet cushions
which they hire at the entrance when
paying for their seats.
Richly ornate churches reflected in
their gleaming steps, inviting pilgrims and
tourists to climb painfully upwards
beneath the cruel sun.
Alleys whose every doorfront has one
step, sometimes two, where people sit
out on their chairs to enjoy the cool
evening air and chat with their neigh¬
bours. Alleys with tiny staircases which
might conceal an assassin or a couple of
timid lovers.
Left, the fountain on
Piazza Pretoria in
Palermo (Sicily). It
was built between
1555 and 1575.
flight, alley steps in
Taormina, on Sicily's
east coast.
U pposite page
above, a flight of steps
in Taormina, which for
25 centuries has
overlooked the Ionian
Sea from the foot of
Mount Etna.
on
e unesco Rubier« ma1
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The sculpted walls of the Alcantara
gorges, like monochromatic piano keys,
overlapping like so many steps that
Orpheus might have taken to reach his
beloved.
The Gorges of Tiberio, also known as
the Proserpine abyss, with their rocky
sides chiselled out like a titanic natural
staircase leading down into the bowels
of the earth.
In Sicily, everything climbs upwards.
The silence ofascent
The baroque cathedrals of Noto and
Ragusa, with polished steps so imposing
that they give a foretaste of the divine,
so wide that they overwhelm the reli¬
gious building to which they lead. The
Latomian quarries with steps eaten away
by the centuries; catacombs with seeping
moss-covered steps. All these steps cap¬
tivate walkers who, once they have set
foot on them, can no longer resist the
temptation to ascend or descend.
A mysterious power of attraction
emanates from these stone platforms,
which are, because of their size and
width, an extension of the marketplace
where people meet, stare or gaze long¬
ingly at one another. A real-life theatre
of mime, of smorfia the art of the gri¬
mace and facial sign-language and opera
THE UNESCO iOURILR MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
deipupi, the puppet theatre that retraces
the history of the Sicilian people, from
the lordly paladin who stood out against
the invader, to the labourer exploited by
rich land-owners.
People sit on the steps and stare at the
passers-by who walk theatrically to and
fro beneath them, in long noisy pro¬
cessions, iridescent with a thousand
colours. A never-changing ballet. Silence
descends. The suffering of pilgrims lit¬
erally sweats blood as they climb the
steps on their knees, one after the other,
leaving there a little of themselves that
the tired and thirsty stone sucks in greed¬
ily. Eyes cast down, the bearers of the
sácred relics of San Corrado Confalonieri
and of other patron saints of large com-
Oteps inlaid with majolica
leading up to the church of
Santa Maria del Monte in
Caltagirone (Sicily).
^r$%
.,*: <+ ^ v.
munities Sant' Agata, Santa Lucia, San
Sebastiano strain with the effort of
walking with eight hundred kilos of silver
on their shoulders.
Dry stone walls streak fields with
pumice and obsidian, vineyards, Etna's
black and fertile slopes, fields of Barbary
fig trees, columns of olive and almond
trees transfixed in eternal poses. Like life¬
lines across the palm of the hand they
bear witness to life gone by and mark its
stages. Sometimes, in their rectitude, they
caress the contours of a hill, holding back
roots and water, snatching from the
unproductive soil a few strips of farm¬
land and forming terraces, huge steps
across the hillside for invisible cyclops
to climb.
Church steps
Past and present are expressed through
these steps hewn in limestone, lava and
obsidian, and through all the cultures that
meet there.
Clergy and notables, vine and grape,
pagans and fervent believers, clusters of
scarlet and black, mingle on the steps of
churches. All let their feelings show
when the sacred relics pass by. On
church steps on feast-day evenings, the
camminanti, the travelling people, so spe¬
cial in Sicily, are loquaciously present,
begging or selling, with their unique form
of speech, immense candles for the pro¬
cession. On the waxy or mossy steps
people move like little children afraid of
falling. They sway like fishermen scourg¬
ing the wine-dark sea by order of the rais,
the chief, and harpooning the tuna
imprisoned in the almazraba the net
the scene of another tragedy in which
the fish come to die. On church steps
people take stock of the world, seek a
reply when fate hounds their families,
when neither clerical cloth nor talisman
can cure the wounds of heart and soul.
First and last steps
Platforms, terraces and stairways are the
veins of Sicily through which flow tiny
trickles of sand and water. Life and death.
They are the first furrows of the field
ploughed, the first verses written, the
first steps taken in life, as the family stand¬
ing on steps after the wedding sows
unspoken love, mingling with the grains
THE UNESCO ÇfJURIERI
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
.. ,_v 3 *
I he Roman theatre of
Segesta. It was hewn from the
rock on top of Mount Bárbaro
during the Hellenistic period
(3rd century B.C.).
of rice. But they are also life's last steps,
the steps leading to the tiered cemetery
whose hundreds of terraced crypts must
be scaled, step by step, for the last time.
Those who come to visit the dead in
the early morning, to avoid the heat of
the day, climb upwards as did the first
inhabitants the Sicani and the Siculi
and then the first invaders. Stage after
stage, step after step, penetrating inland,
settling there and recommencing the
eternal task without ever looking back¬
wards, until the stone steps are swal¬
lowed up, as they were at Netum the
once-splendid city of Noto, destroyed
by a terrible earthquake in 1693 by
brambles, Barbary fig trees, and heady
jasmin.
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
In the Dominican Republic, vivid
colour schemes enliven everyday life
with a host ofpolitical and sporting
allusions
Colourful
For the people of the Dominican Repub¬
lic creating colourful surroundings is
almost second nature
The dominant colours they use arc the
primary colours: blue, red and yellow, with
a few others thrown in green, sky blue,
purple and pink. Black is excluded from their
palette and white is used to separate other
colours or to create a neutral area. These
colours arc used to beautify dwellings and
their surroundings. If the doors arc blue,
for example, the main structure will be red,
green or yellow. The aim is to create a colour
scheme for a whole neighbourhood or vil¬
lage, not for each individual house. Variety
is the keynote. Doors and windows may be
the same colour, separated by white from
the dominant colour of the house. Few
houses arc painted in more than three
colours one at least of the four main tones
is always missing but no house sports only
one. The whole effect shows an intuitive
knowledge of the art of using colour.
I A symbolic attachment
The predominance of blue is a way of bring¬
ing the sea into everyday life. There is a para¬
dox here, for the Dominicans turn their
backs on the sea, which they regard as the
origin of all their misfortunes, of both nat¬
ural and human origin. They fear and shun
it. The only thing they like about it is its
colour. On other Caribbean islands gardens
are decorated with conches, sea-shells and
starfish, but not here. Dominicans believe
that conches bring bad luck. And blue is
always accompanied by white, like foam on
the crest of a wave. "In its desire to become
sky, the sea makes clouds of foam," Domini-
) Qu:THE UNESCO lOURIER B MAY 1197
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
anguage
BY GUILLERMO PIÑA-CONTRERAS
M palissade on the shore at
Samana, on the northern
coast.
can writer Ruben Suro has written of this
bond between the two colours.
The main structural element of the tra¬
ditional Dominican rural dwelling is the
trunk of a palm, the island's symbolic tree.
It is a more developed form of the Taino
Indian hut and the African cabin of the early
colonial days. The roof is usually made of
leaves from the royal palm and fibre from
another local variety, the cane palm.
The dialogue with the environment is
not limited to dwellings; it also extends to
artistic tastes and religious beliefs, the latter
of which blend aesthetics with superstition.
Many gardens contain an altar surmounted
by a picture of the Virgin Mary of Altagra-
cia (the country's patron saint) at the end
of a path of white stones. The niche housing
the image of the Virgin is usually painted
white, setting off the blue and red of her
robes. Houses where there is no altar arc pro¬
tected by crosses placed at the edges of court-
) (TlURITHE UNESCO IpURIER MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
yard or garden. These crosses are also painted
white, for white is the colour of faith. (In the
mountainous north, tresses of garlic are hung
on the door to keep the devil out.) Roads,
parks and other public places are decorated in
a similar manner. It is not uncommon to sec
roadside shrines at places where accidents
have occurred, and altars in public squares.
These practices are illegal, but they are toler¬
ated by the authorities and arc part and par¬
cel of the Dominican Republic's magical-
religious landscape.
People have also modified the appearance
of the urban landscape. Trees, especially palm
trees, and electricity poles are often painted
in a single colour to head height. For some¬
one who knows nothing about Dominican
political life, a row of palm trees or electric
power poles painted in alternating reds,
" few houses are painted in
more than three colours, but
no house sports only one."
" U ominicans want to create
a colour scheme for a whole
neighbourhood or village.
Variety Is the keynote."
blues, greens, whites, purples and yellows
is simply an eye-catching sight, a way of
enhancing the environment. In fact, each
colour represents an ideology. The colour
of the party that won the presidential elec¬
tion recurs at regular intervals, and so does
that of the party that won the local elec¬
tions. This way of marking out political turf
goes back to the early days of independence,
when colours were used to designate the
main parties in order to overcome the obsta¬
cle of illiteracy: red for the conservatives,
and blue like the sea for the liberals.
Politics and sport
Today the custom of painting pillars and
posts has become widespread, but it still has
political and sometimes sporting overtones.
Some people even paint the front door of
their house the colour of the party they sup¬
port. Colours can express sporting rivalry
as well as ideological conflict, since each of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
titte
life. The back wall behind the dance floor is
usually covered with an evocative painting
of a sugar cane plantation or a seascape. The
style is usually naive and the country's
dominant colours blue, red, green and
yellow are used. Even the colours of the
chairs are significant. Their variety is enough
to satisfy all tastes and tendencies, reflecting
the colours of the country's political and
sporting teams.
The visual landscape is backed up by a
landscape of sound. Music blares from every
corner. In bars, in houses, at every level of
society, the traditional beat of the merengue
explodes. On the breakwater, a long prom¬
enade on the edge of the Caribbean, the noise
soon becomes intolerable for anyone who
has failed to understand that deafening music
is a component of Dominican life. It's as if
the people were trying to struggle against
their environment, to drown out the hiss¬
ing of the waves, the moaning of the sea
winds and the shouts and din of the street.
Music is as aggressive as the colours that mark
the landscape. The climate and the habit of
living in the open air sharpens the senses,
especially sight and hearing. The elements
here arc part of human nature. The Domini¬
cans' dialogue with their surroundings is
also a dialogue with themselves.
big Dominican baseball teams has its own
colour: red, blue, green and yellow. Politics
and sport are ever-present in daily life.
Poverty also plays a role in this unending
dialogue with the environment. In the slums
poverty has given rise to a specific architec¬
tural style. Lacking the funds to buy con¬
struction materials, slum-dwellers use tin
cans, crates and all kinds of trash with great
imagination to cover the walls of their homes
in the shanty towns that sprawl around the
edges of the big cities, along river banks and
near the sea shore. To create an effect of uni-
formity, some people use cans of a single
brand as walls for their dwellings, or paint
them with distinctive naive murals. The vari¬
ety of colours used to decorate large aban¬
doned public buildings reveals the number
of families living there. Each family uses
colour to mark off its living area.
Bars where people gather to drink and
dance are one focal point of community
" Ihe traditional Dominican
dwelling reveals an intuitive
knowledge of the art of using
colour. For example, if
the doors are blue, the main
structure will be red,
green or yellow. "
THE UNESCO lOURIER B MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
AY IT WITH FLOWERS
BY YANNIS E. IOANNOU
The first-time visitor to Cyprus is
likely to be struck by the way in
which the natural world with all its
contrasts, wisdom and perfection is
recreated inside the islanders' houses. The
microcosm of the Cypriot house tradi¬
tional or modern, in the mountains, low¬
lands or towns is engaged in a constant dia¬
logue with the macrocosm of nature: with
what the Greek poet Odysseus Elytis has
called "the universe, the infinitely small, the
unfathomable".
The language of this dialogue is a miscel¬
laneous and multicoloured assortment of
pots of flowers, arranged in rows or placed at
random around the entrance door, along walls
and windows, on makeshift shelves or old
tables, suspended from trees or outer walls,
as if to welcome the thirsty traveller. The pots
of flowers strike a friendly note which might
otherwise be excluded from homes and gar¬
dens by utilitarian and often thoughtless
human intervention, to say nothing of the
intensely arid climate of a land where summer
lasts nearly six months.
I A tradition ofsymbolism
A geranium in a huge container stands har¬
moniously among daffodils, and all around
flowers growing in a conglomeration of pots
of all shapes and sizes create a vast coloured
landscape. To enter a house ungraccd by pots
of flowers is to experience a foretaste of death.
But let's take a closer look at these clusters
of pots. All kinds of receptacles, irrespective
of colour, size or material, are pressed into
service and used for planting cuttings. Buck¬
ets, metal or plastic drums, tin cans or mar¬
garine containers, milk and yoghurt pots all
form part of this astonishing miscellany.
They are not arranged according to any set
order but moved around depending on the
space available. There is no preordained aes¬
thetic pattern, as one might tend to think.
This is a world of its own, loaded over¬
loaded even with affection, love and respect.
It continually breaks the rules that govern
the decorative approach and stylization of
Western gardens. This is not mere decoration,
but a world in a state of flux, in the throes of
constant creation and recreation, ordained
by standards of raw beauty based on an orig¬
inal law which obeys no human model and in
my opinion achieves perfection. "Nature
" Ihe pots of flowers are there
as if to welcome the thirsty
traveller". Below, an outdoor
café in Athna, eastern Cyprus.
THE UNESCO lOURIER B MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
In Cyprus no
home is
complete
without a
'garden9 of
pottedplants
itself", Elytis tells us, "is neither good nor
bad, beautiful nor ugly. It simply is."[ It exists
in simplicity, humility and disorder, in a
beauty that is both elusive and familiar.
Symbolism, often dating back to Antiqu¬
ity, is associated with this strange world
whose "inhabitants" arc closely linked to tra¬
ditional life in Cyprus. The lily is associated
with purity. Certain cacti ward off the evil
eye. A vine inside the house would climb,
and sometimes still docs, up the walls of the
living room, twining round and clinging to
beautiful traditional plates hung as orna¬
ments but its two ends must never meet
because that would bring bad luck. This is
why in the past nobody was called Manolis
(the plant's common name).
The therapeutic uses and virtues of some
plants are also important. The mushy juice of
the aloe was once used as an ointment for
treating wounds and burns. Basil and gera¬
niums arc placed near doors or windows
eraniums are placed near
doors or windows where their
powerful smell wards off
mosquitoes."
where their powerful smell wards off mos¬
quitoes and of course basil leaves whet the
appetite of the Cypriots, who sprinkle them
over salads. Sprigs of mint arc systematically
put in the folds, made for this very purpose,
of the traditional halloumi cheese. Lavender
leaves in a cupboard keep the moths at bay.
The heady aroma of Spanish jasmine leaves
and marjoram is inseparable from crystal¬
lized fruit, especially in the island's rural areas.
Walnuts arc regarded as a gastronomic lux¬
ury. They used to be served when the object
of a visit was an engagement.
I A woman's perfume
Love is associated, perhaps even identified,
with certain plants which have a distinctive
odour and colour, such as jasmine flowers
hand-plaited with thread to make a necklace
which women used to wear for want of more
sophisticated perfumes or hide discreetly in
their blouses (especially on Sundays and
29
THE UNESCO Q^>URIIER* MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
holidays). In traditional society, before the
days of the sexual revolution, a woman who
was desired was inaccessible. Only her per¬
fume that wonderful blend of the flower's
smell with that of her body could be flcet-
ingly captured. Desire could be fulfilled only
in song, dance and amorous daydreams, as is
suggested by this couplet from a traditional
Cypriot song:
Jasmine at your door, oh my jasmine
I came to prune it
and your mother thought
I had come to carry you away.
The women tend the flower pots and are
perfectly familiar with the qualities and needs
of each plant. To keep jasmine perfectly fresh,
they plant it in metal or terracotta pots or,
better still, in wooden containers.
Water is a serious problem in Cyprus.
Planting flowers in pots rather than in a gar¬
den saves a great deal of water, especially in the
arid plains, since just the right amount of
water can be sprinkled over a flower pot.
There is no water shortage in the mountains,
but water is hard to transport, and access to
houses is almost always difficult. What is
more, plots of land suitable for cultivation
are so small that, to save space, pots are
30
M flower market in Llmassol
in southern Cyprus.
pressed close together there are houses
whose balconies overflow with flowers. The
sparse soil available is used to grow vegetables
for subsistence but also for the joy of gar¬
dening and swapping one's produce with that
of one's neighbour.
IDivineprotection
My wife was the first person I questioned
about the origins of the custom of growing
plants in pots. "Can't you see," she said, "that
these arc poor people's plants? To begin with,
they have no money to buy pots and they
never buy plants. Friends and neighbours
swap cuttings. . . . The pots don't count. It's
the plants that matter and the whole nexus of
affection that grows around them. . . ."
I was struck by her words. I had been liv¬
ing with these pots for as long as I could
remember without paying any attention to
this practice whose ceremonial, functional
and symbolic connotations can only be
explained by wisdom born of long tradition.
When women plant flowers (planting trees
is a man's job), arrange and rearrange flower
pots to make sure that each plant is in its
right place in the sun or shade, caress the
plants, feci the joy of watching them bios-
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
som, and tenderly water them, they are act¬
ing within a long tradition of hospitality
under divine protection. It would be a viola¬
tion of this tradition if strangers had to
knock at the door of a house without pot
plants they are an umbilical cord between
the domestic microcosm and the natural
macrocosm.
Pot plants perform the same function in
the monasteries that dot the hills and moun¬
tains of Cyprus, whose inner courtyards arc
oases of human warmth and fresh air. They
restore to passing guests the peace and seren¬
ity they lost on their journey. The visitor's
first contact with the spiritual and artistic
world of the Byzantine monastery is made
through this miniature universe that seems to
be in a state of rapture. Worship of God
blends with the worship of nature, while the
echo of the psalms intoned by the deep voices
of the monks or in the sensuous tones of
the nuns, accompanied by the song of the
cicadas outside, infuses the senses and the
spirit.
These pots brimming with scent and
colour are imbued with sanctity. They cele¬
brate the inexhaustible totality of man and
the world, the joys and beauty of the earth
and the monastic austerity which leads to
union with God. These intimate gardens
where everything is within reach provide the
mass of flowers which on Good Friday night
accompany Christ to His tomb in a volup¬
tuous blend of classical sensuality and Byzan¬
tine spirituality.
The geometrical order and perfection of
Western gardens are a far cry from this sim¬
ple beauty whose every feature prolongs the
stirrings of the soul. Here the law of analogies
between people and their landscape seems to
function to perfection. As Elytis says, "a line
a painter draws is not limited to itself alone,
but has an 'analogy' in the world of spiri¬
tual values. Seeing the mountains shaped this
way or that way must have an effect on the
human spirit, must have its analogy."2
1. Interview with Odysseus Elytis by Ivar Ivask in
Books Abroad, vol. 49, Norman, Oklahoma, autumn
1975.
2. Ibid " Ihe natural world is
recreated inside the islanders'
houses."
THE UNESCO lOURIER B MAY 1997
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
a name.''
ta
BYLUISMIZON
Early European explorers to Chile's south coast
symbolically annexed the places they discovered
by giving them European names
Mbove, a glacier flows down
to Beagle Channel on the
coast of Tierra del Fuego.
The Yahgan were a people living in Tierra
del Fuego ("land of fire")who used to
ply up and down the coast in their
small boats and build themselves
makeshift shelters on islands or on the banks
of inlets. The last of them, a woman who was
born in 1887 and died in 1983, wrote, "I am the
last survivor of the Wollaston islanders. There
used to be five Yahgan tribes, each from a dif¬
ferent place but all speaking the same language.
Before I could walk, I had been as far as Cape
Horn, strapped to my mother's back. Every¬
body called me Rosa, because that was how I
was christened by the English missionaries,
but my real name is Lakutia the kipa. Lakutia
is the name of a bird and kipa means woman.
32
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 190/
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
ÍH
V - ..*>. 	
All Yahgans arc named after the place where
they were born, and my mother gave birth to
me near Lakutia Bay. That's how it is done
among our people: we are given the name of
the place that welcomes us to the world."
It is several centuries, however, in Chile
and elsewhere in Latin America, since geo¬
graphical names told the simple tale of people
living in symbiosis with their environment.
Instead they speak of the clash of two peo¬
ples and two cultures fighting over the same
territory. Indigenous names and European
names of coastal features and mountains are
associated with different memories. Today
these names intermingle in a landscape into
which the indigenous population wanted to
melt while the Europeans simply wanted to
take possession of it.
I Leaving their mark
For the explorer who comes from afar, the
land is like a new-born baby, as yet nameless.
The names bestowed on places by the Euro¬
pean navigators and explorers who began
arriving on the southern coast of Chile in
the sixteenth century have political or reli¬
gious connotations, or else express a sense of
beauty or were even inspired by passionate
love. Only seldom did the newcomers keep
the indigenous name.
The annexation of the Araucan lands, fol¬
lowed by their exploration by naturalists and
their colonization, gave rise to a new series
of terms and appellations. The vast territory
inhabited by the Indians who provided
Alonso de Ercilla, in the sixteenth century,
with the inspiration for his epic of the con¬
quest, La Araucana, lay roughly between the
Pacific, the Andes and two rivers, the Bio-
Bio (or Malleco) to the north and the Token
(or Callc-Calle) to the south. These lands
were gradually integrated into the territory of
Chile in the nineteenth century, the process
being completed by 1883. There are still many
Araucans today, but the indigenous popu¬
lations of the clusters of islands that stretch
from the Isla de Chiloé to Cape Horn have
become almost entirely extinct.
Between Cape Horn and the main island
of Tierra del Fuego, the place-names arc some¬
times English (the Wollaston, Picton,
Lennox, Button, Gordon King and Scott
Islands), sometimes French (the Hermite and
Bertrand Islands and the Pasteur Peninsula),
or Spanish (Caleta Hernández, Santa Rosa or
Mejillones), with a few Yahgan Indian names
thrown in, such as Bahia Tckenika, Canasaca
or Wulaia. Thus, one name may be concealed
behind another. Onashaga was the Yahgan
name of the Beagle Channel and Yakashaka
was that of the Murray Channel, at the
mouth of the Strait of Magellan.
As for Valparaiso, the leading port on the
Pacific side of the continent before the con¬
struction of the Panama Canal, its Spanish
name means "Vale of Paradise". This was the
he village of Castro on
Chiloe Island (Chile).
> QjuiTHE UNESCO tpURIERB MAY 1997 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
* place where, in the great days of sail, mariners
who had passed the Strait of Magellan or
rounded the Horn making for the Pacific
coast of South America dreamed of drop¬
ping anchor.
I orres del Paine, in Chilean
Patagonia.
Acts ofpossession
History sometimes seems to have hesitated
over thé choice of a name, even to the point of
rejecting the one proposed by the discoverer.
Magellan, for instance, having entered the strait
that was to bear his name on the first day of
November, decided to call it All Saints' Strait,
but it subsequently became known by other
names Straits of Patagonia, Victoria and the
Moluccas, or again Dragon's Tail Strait but in
common parlance it remained the "Strait of
Magellan".
A similar process is associated with the
naming of Cape Horn. Although the first per¬
son to have mentioned it seems to have been Sir
Francis Drake, who entered the Strait of Mag¬
ellan on 20 August 1578, the first sailors to
round the Cape, on 29 January 1616, thus con¬
necting the two great oceans, were the Dutch¬
men Jacques Le Maire and Willem C. Schouten.
r" THE UNESCO IpURIERB MAY t>)9;
\s ape Horn, at the southern
extremity of Chile.
They named it Cape Hoorn after the village
where Schouten was born. Spanish captains
later wanted to rename it San Ildefonso, but
Spanish sailors were content to change
"Hoorn" to "Hornos" (Spanish for "ovens"),
perhaps in the hope of lending a little imagi¬
nary warmth to cliffs that are forbidding and
icy, despite forming part of the "Land of Fire".
The naming of a place is both an individ-
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
ual and a collective act. To name is to possess.
Every newcomer thus leaves the imprint of
his language and the signs of his passage.
Alonso de Ercilla, one of the discoverers of
Chiloé, an island with an Indian name,
expressed very well the keen powers of obser¬
vation and the underlying sense of pride of
the discoverer who leaves his mark upon a
place. In Part Three, Canto XXVI of La Arau¬
cana, he dwells at length on the exploration of
Chiloé and some of the neighbouring islands,
inhabited by Indians. The Indians, he tells us,
"were filled with amazement and wonder at
the sight of these strangers [white-skinned,
fair, hairy and bearded] with a different lan¬
guage and different clothing".
Before returning, Ercilla left behind a tan¬
gible memento of his visit. "I walked for half
a mile. Then, wishing to leave a visible, writ¬
ten sign of my having been there, in the bark
of the greatest tree that I saw I engraved with
the point of my knife these words, 'Don
Alonso de Ercilla came here, before any other.
He was the first to cross the channel, in a small
boat, with only ten men, this last day of Feb¬
ruary in the year 1558, at two o'clock of the
afternoon, as he was making his way back to
join his companions'."
I An echo ofpast voyages
Other names bear witness cither to the ordeals
undergone by their discoverers Cape Deso¬
lation, Land of Desolation, Deceitful Island,
Island of Anger, Hunger Harbour, Vain Bay,
Gulf of Torments or to their hopes: Eden
Harbour, Future Harbour, Cape Welcome,
Land of Springs.
An echo of the adventures they went
through, of the dangers they encountered and
their miraculous escapes, may sometimes be
heard, and then the names sound like votive
offerings. Hernando Alonso, pilot of the flag¬
ship of a famous Spanish expedition led by
Pedro Sarmiento de Gamboa, tells how, run¬
ning into a terrible storm in the Strait of Mag¬
ellan, ". . . as wc commended our souls to the
Holy Spirit, the Comforter, and to the Blessed
Mother of God, there came suddenly, by their
mercy, a little light and gentle wind which res¬
cued us from that peril, and soon thereafter we
rounded the headland of the island of Santa
Inés, which we named the Cape of the Holy
Spirit in recognition of the grace it had
accorded us."
In fact the Cape of the Holy Spirit already
Isla Robinson Crusoe (Nearer
Land Island) in the Juan
Fernández Islands, some
600 km west of Valparaiso
(Chile).
had a name, by which it is known to this day:
Cabo de Pilares (Cape of the Pillars), because
of its supposed similarity to the ruins of a
Greek or Roman theatre or to the megaliths of
Stonehcnge. The other names given to it never
caught on, as if what had most appealed to
the imagination of seamen was the strange
shape of the rocks eroded by the violence of
the elements.
Other places are even today still unnamed.
The southern coast of Chile, down to its very
tip, is formed of one enormous, shattered
mountain range of which all that remains to be
seen are thousands of mountain-tops, in other
words, thousands of islands. Between Cape
Horn and Chiloé, more than 3,000 islands,
channels, promontories and rocks are still
waiting to be named.
THE UNESCO IpURlERB MAY 1997
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE the world network
Biosphere Reserves are geographical areas considered typical of the balanced relationship between people and nature. As of April 1997, 337
Reserves, located in 85 different countries, have met the required criteria for this designation laid down within UNESCO's "Man and the
Biosphere" (MAB) Programme. They combine three functions:
species and genetic variation;
a development function fostering economic development that is ecologically and culturally sustainable;
a logistic function providing support for research, monitoring, training and education related to local, regional, national and global
conservation and sustainable development Issues.
The Reserves form a World Network within which exchanges of Information, experience and personnel are encouraged. They contribute to
meeting the objectives of the Convention on Biological Diversity and Agenda 21 that resulted from the 1992 United Nations Conference on the
Environment and Development held in Rio de Janeiro.
What are Biosphere
Reserves for?
How are Biosphere
Reserves selected?
How are Biosphere
Reserves organized?
Why a world
network?
Human pressures on natural
resources are drastically
reducing the diversity of the
earth's plant and animal
species, ecosystems and
landscapes. Biosphere
Reserves safeguard samples
of biodiversity, landscapes and
ecosystems and contribute to
the maintenance of the earth's
life-support systems which
serve to prevent soil erosion,
maintain soil fertility, regulate
river flow, replenish aquifers,
recycle nutrients and absorb air
and water pollutants.
Research may be
conducted on the dynamics of
the natural systems in the core
areas of Biosphere Reserves,
which have remained relatively
unaffected by human activity.
This research can be compared
with the functioning of human-
affected landscapes in the
buffer and transition areas.
Sharing knowledge of
practices that Improve human
well-being without degrading
the environment ¡s a central
purpose of Biosphere
Reserves. They are places
where issues can be debated
by all the stakeholders
concerned: scientists, local
farmers, fishermen, politicians,
private enterprises and nature
conservation associations.
To qualify for designation as a
Biosphere Reserve an area
should normally:
be representative of a major
biogeographic region, Including
a gradation of existing human
intervention;
contain landscapes,
ecosystems or animal and
plant species or varieties which
need protecting;
provide an opportunity to
explore and demonstrate
approaches to sustainable
development within the larger
region where the Reserves are
located;
have an appropriate zoning
system, with a legally
constituted core area or areas
devoted to long-term
protection, a clearly identified
buffer zone or zones, and an
outer transition area.
BIOSPHERE
RESERVE
ZONATION
The core area needs to be
legally established and give
long-term protection to the
landscape, ecosystem and
species it contains.
A buffer zone must be
clearly delineated. Human
activities in this area should
not hinder the conservation
objectives of the core area but
rather help to protect it. It may,
for example, be an area for
experimental research Into
ways of managing the
ecosystem.
The transition area, or area
of co-operation, extends
outwards from the Reserve. It
is here that local communities
and other stakeholders must
agree to work together to
manage and sustainably
develop the area's resources.
Biosphere Reserves have a
common interest In seeking
concrete solutions to reconcile
the conservation of
biodiversity with the
sustainable use of natural
resources for the benefit of
local people. The World Network
is supported by regional
networks or thematic networks
(e.g. for studying biodiversity).
Co-operation can take the form
of exchanges of Information
material, articles in the
Biosphere Reserves Bulletin,
co-operative projects, twinning
arrangements, exchanges of
personnel or organized visits.
The World Network is
governed by a Statutory
Framework formally adopted by
the General Conference of
UNESCO at Its 28th session.
This framework defines the
functioning of the Network and
foresees a periodic review of
Biosphere Reserves.
Core area
Buffer zone
Transition area
ft' Human settlements
R Research station or experimental
research site
M Monitoring
E Education and training
T Tourism and recreation
36
THE UNESCO lOURILR MAY 199/
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
ofbiosphere reserves
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION:
!f
From top down: Lanzarote,
Canary Islands (Spain),
Amboseli (Kenya), Huascarán
(Peru) and Mañanara
(Madagascar).
World Network of Biosphere Reserves,
Division of Ecological Sciences,
Unesco, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 41 51; Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 58 04; e-mail:
mab@unesco.org
A list of contacts for Biosphere Reserves and the guiding
documents for Biosphere Reserves are available
on the Internet URL:
http://www.unesco.org:80//mab/themabnet.html
BIBLIOGRAPHY:
Publications of the Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme include:
Biosphere Reserves Bulletin (also in French)
Nature and Resources (quarterly, also in French)
InfoMAB
Articles on Biosphere Reserves published in the UNESCO Courier
since 1990:
"Lake Fertó", by France Bequette, December 1996.
"Ta'i National Park", by Nimrod Bena Djangrang, December 1996.
"Palawan, the Philippines' last frontier", by France Bequette,
October 1996.
"Sonora, a living desert", by France Bequette, September 1996.
"Talamanca-La Amistad", by Frailan Escobar González, April 1996.
"Montseny, harmony in the hills", by France Bequette, March 1995.
"MAB at age 25", by Michel Bâtisse, October 1993.
"An ecological Eldorado: Peru's Manu National Park", by José Serra-Vega,
August-September 1991.
"The rock art of Tassili N'Ajjer", by Caroline Haardt, July 1991.
"S.O. S lemurs! A new biosphere reserve in Madagascar",
by Edouard Bailby, August 1990.
Two issues of the UNESCO Courier have been devoted to the Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) Progamme:
"Man and the biosphere: a partnership for sustainable development",
October 1987.
"Man and the biosphere", April 1981.
And an issue of UNESCO Sources:
"Biosphere Reserves: linking conservation and development"
(No. 69, May 1995).
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1007
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY Federico Mayor
The responsibility of
scientists
Knowledge is always good: it is its applications that can
be harmful or even evil. A hammer can he used improp¬
erly as an instrument of aggression; so at another level
can atomic energy. But we must he careful not to allow
only the negative aspects of science to he emphasized.
These are usually described in exaggeratedly dark
colours, while the good aspects are not news.
The scientific and technological community has a
duty to remind people of the enormous benefits sci¬
ence has brought. Some years ago, the Green Revolu¬
tion, which has transformed the future prospects of
millions of people in Asia, came under criticism from
environmentalists because it had tended to favour
richer farmers, who could afford the pesticides and
fertilizers on which the new varieties of wheat and rice
depended. The critics behaved as if this discredited
the entire enterprise, whereas their criticisms were far
outweighed by its highly positive aspects.
There are plenty of other examples. Does anybody
think about poliomyelitis any more? Or of the way we
have been able to reduce pain and even eliminate it with
the help of analgesics or modern anaesthetics? Or of the
transport and telecommunications systems that enable
us to be citizens and witnesses of the whole world,
THE UNESCO lOURIER« MAY 1^7
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
even though they compel us to assume the responsi¬
bilities this entails?
We cannot shirk our moral responsibilities. We must
admit that there have been a considerable number of
silent scientists in the twentieth century. The possession
of knowledge carries with it a moral obligation. What
would we think of a meteorologist who did not warn us
that a storm was coming? Or of clinical analysts who
failed to alert us to the urgent nature of their findings?
Scientists have to transcend the walls of their labora¬
tories, their departments, their faculties, and their
industries. To say that the scientific life is simply a mat¬
ter of "publishing or perishing" is both disparaging and
wrong. A scientist who chooses to remain silent, par¬
ticularly when irreversible consequences may follow,
is behaving both unprofessionally and immorally.
Genetics and ethics
In no field of science are the issues more complex than
in genetics, nor is there any other area of science in
which the discriminatory use of the information would
be more scandalous. The whole subject of bioethics, far
from being a luxury, should be the preserve of the
entire human community, since the advances made by
the few are a battle won for the whole human race.
Bioethics came into being, rightly, at the moment
when techniques of genetic manipulation first emerged
in the 1970s, and questions began to be asked about the
influence of molecular biology on the future of human¬
ity. Far from simply being concerned with an investi¬
gation of the relations between science and society, it is
concerned with the relation between man and nature
in its biological diversity. The development of bioethics
illustrates, I believe, a proper and appropriate response
by scientists and philosophers to the social questions
raised by science.
These are many. Genetic diagnosis and screening
make it possible to give reassurance to members of fam¬
ilies with a history of genetically transmitted illnesses.
However, should these tests be conducted only after the
disease appears? Should genetic testing be restricted to
hereditary, incurable, fatal or incapacitating diseases?
How can the confidentiality of information he guaran¬
teed overtime, especially when they could be of enor¬
mous interest to employers and insurance companies?
For the time being, the scientific community has
agreed that there should he no use of gene therapy on
the germ cells those that would transmit the changes
to the next generation and that the cloning of human
beings should be banned. But is this agreement based
on ethical principles, or does it merely reflect current
fears of the possible associated risks?
Moral dilemmas
Behind the first series of questions looms the spectre of
eugenic selection, with its attendant host of violations of
human rights and individual freedom.
The temptation for couples to use the results of
screening in selecting their potential offspring is under¬
standable, but it is difficult to draw the line between the
legitimate desire not to pass on serious genetic diseases
and the illusory quest for the "perfect child". At another
level, it is not impossible to envisage entire societies
being tempted to practise eugenic selection on entire
populations that it might consider genetically vulnera¬
ble or as presenting "risks".
Each society must work out for itself a route through
this moral maze, but there is also a role for the inter¬
national community. National rules may vary from coun¬
try to country, which could encourage a form of "genetic
tourism", in which people would be tempted to take
advantage of laxer regulations abroad. The first stirrings
of this have been seen in the use of techniques of in vitro
fertilization which allow women past menopause to
become pregnant. In Italy there are no rules or con¬
ventions prohibiting the use of this technique for women
in their late fifties or even sixties, so that women from
the United Kingdom have travelled there to take advan¬
tage of a treatment they would be denied at home
because of their age.
Without acting as judge and jury in such cases, it is
nevertheless clear that some international standards
are desirable. Similar arguments apply to the even
more vexed question of the patenting of the human
genome, where so far different countries have adopted
different approaches. For these very reasons, UNESCO
has created a World Committee on Bioethics*; perhaps
it would he wise to extend its scope to include every
impact of science on human life.
See the September 1991 issue of the UNESCO Courier, "A
code for living." Ed.
THE UNESCO (OURIIIERB MAY 1997
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
H E R I T A G E
THE ISLAND OF OZAM BIQUE
by Patrick Lagès
Arab, Indian and Portuguese architectural influences are blended in the port
of Mozambique. Once a trading post on the sea route from Europe to the East
Indies, this island harbour was placed on UNESCO's World Heritage List
in 1991.
The church of Our Lady of Mercy (17th century) is
the only one still used for worship on the island.
The little island of Mozam¬
bique, which lies four kilo¬
metres off the coast of Africa just
opposite Madagascar, was for hun¬
dreds of years a major centre of
intercontinental maritime trade. It
was occupied hy Aral) mendiants
from the tenth century until the
end of the fifteenth, and in the six¬
teenth century became a port of
call on the route from Europe to
the East Indies opened by the Por¬
tuguese navigator Vasco da Cama.
In 1507, the Portuguese built a
fortress on the island where the
Customs House stands today. A
later fortification that lias survived
is the fort of St. Sebastian, which
was built between lüöü and 1620
and is inspired by Italian Henais-
sanee military architecture.
Mozambique harbour grew
rapidly during the sixteenth and
seventeenth centuries. 1 ts business
houses stood on the sea front, along
a rocky licit where boats with a
shallow draught could land at high
tide. ()\cr the years a town of twist¬
ing streets lined with flat-roofed
houses took shape around a cen¬
tral square.
The town as it appears today has
a strongan hitcctural homogeneity
which is largelv due to the use over
w ) ^11THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
as-- ¿?
* *
.*>
- ,-;. », ...
-'
.-
the centuries of the same building
materials, mainly limestone from
quarries in the south of the island,
and wood for beams and framework.
The decorativ e style of the façades,
with their cornices, high rectangu¬
lar framed windows and rows of
pilasters, is equally homogeneous.
The fiat roofs, designed to collect
rainwater and compensate for the
island's lack of freshwater springs,
and a rectangular ground plan in
which space is divided into six
square rooms also uphold a general
impression of unity which encom¬
passes the smallest houses roofed
with palm leaves the macuti that
constitute around a quarter of the
city as well as the most luxurious
residences. The preponderant
architectural influence is that of
southern Portugal, although there
are undeniable Arab and Indian ele¬
ments.
THE COLONIAL TOWN
Alter crossing the three-kilomctre-
long bridge that links the island to
the mainland, the \ isitor comes to a
cemetery surrounded by white
walls. There is a white chapel, and
a child's white tomb in the form of
a sailing ship stands out among the
other funerary monuments, nolablv
Fishermen on
Mozambique Island.
the Muslim tombs, which are more
unobtrusive. Some distance away, a
nineteenth-century Hindu temple,
and crematorium illustrate the
island's cultural pluralism.
Arab and later Portuguese,
Mozambique island was visited by
such exceptional men as the trav¬
eller Fernao Mcndes Pinto, who
stopped off there in 1 5 ,'i 7 , and the
poet Luis de Camöes, who lived
there between 1567 and 1570
while completing his epic, The
Lusiads, a hymn to the great Por¬
tuguese explorers of his time. His
statue stands in a small square by
the sea. Hut Mozambique's colo¬
nial splendour, victim of the vicis¬
situdes of time and history, is today
no more than a memory. The aboli¬
tion of slavery, which gradually
brought a lucrative trade, to an end,
then the opening of the Suez Canal,
which moved the East India route,
northwards, inevitably condemned
the town to decline.
Apart from the ancient fortifi¬
cations, only half of the town is
stone-built. The visitor's eye is
immediately drawn to the hospital,
!Uï
In the old town.
UNESCO (plIRIER« MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
H The perfectly preserved St.
Paul's palace, with its walls of red
ochre with while edging, has claims
to be the island's most beautiful
monument. A Jesuit school founded
in 1610, it was destroyed by fire
sixty years later and rebuilt in
1674. From 1763 until 1935 it was
used as the residence of the island's
governors. It was converted into a
museum in 1969 and today houses
a fine collection of European and
Indian furniture of different peri¬
ods so that it looks for all the world
like a roy al dwelling. It is connected
to the sea front hy a small square
with Art Nouveau street-lamps
where two-coloured paving stones
evoke the undulations of the ocean
swell.
A MICROCOSM OF HUMANITY
On the sea front, the colonial town
slowly gives way to fishermen's
houses. On the shore the people
from the poorer neighbourhoods
go about their business. Women
and girls queue beside a fountain
for a little fresh water. Children
run around and always end their
games hy diving into the sea shout¬
ing with joy. Mozambique's popu¬
lation has increased by over 50 per
cent since 1968, largely because
of the war and the refugees dis¬
placed by it. The town market is
one of the island's liveliest spots.
A rigorously symmetrical quadri¬
lateral, with small towers rising at
each corner, it was built in 1887.
Its wares are mainly fruit and small
fish set out on trestle tables. Under
the shady porches of houses a cen¬
tury old, street vendors sell indi¬
vidual cigarettes, biscuits, sweets
and fizzy drinks to passers-by.
At the other end of the island,
between two beaches of white
sand, the fort of St. Sebastian now
only defies imaginary fleets. Its high
dark walls, built on the coral of the
island, plunge sheer into the sea.
The wind is the only guest in this
desolate spot, sweeping the white
terraces, groaning in the gigantic
reservoirs of rainwater dug in the
basement and whistling through
a majestic neo-classical building
constructed in 1877 and recently
repainted white, with a garden dec¬
orated with ponds and fountains.
For many years it was the biggest
hospital south of the Sahara.
VANISHED SPLENDOUR
Behind the half-open doors of pros¬
perous town houses can be seen
neglected but once well-tended gar¬
dens. In a Mediterranean-style café
with chequerboard iloor tiles,
superannuated fans churn the air in
a vast room where a handful of cus¬
tomers sit around tables with inlaid
chessboards. The menu, painted
on the wall by a local artist, never
varies: fish, mixed grill, salad.
Opposite, the church of Our Lady
of Mercy offers its immaculate
façade to the sun. Built in 1635 on
the ruins of an earlier church
destroyed by a Dutch bombard¬
ment in 1607, it is one of the oldest
buildings on the island. It houses
a small museum of sacred art, and
during the services the singing of
the faithful is punctuated by the
insistent beating of tom-toms.
St. Paul's palace,
built in the 17th
century. Once the
governor-general's
residence, it is now a
museum.
The island's main
mosque, built in the
19th century. A
Koranic school was
added to it in the
early 20th century.
42
THE UNLSCO lOURIfR MAY 1097 ..'.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
the old church. Birds nest in the
muzzles of cannon which still point
to the horizon. At the sheerest
point, on a bastion of the fortress,
is the chapel of Our Lady of the
Ramparts. Built in 1522, it is
thought to be the oldest European
building south of the equator. Be
that as it may, it is certainly the
oldest in Mozambique and is
thought to he the only building
outside Portugal built in the early
sixteenth-century Manueline style.
In the musty interior, the pre¬
vailing obscurity is barely dissi¬
pated hy dim rays of light that pen¬
etrate through cross-shaped
openings in the walls and east a grey
light on tombs that have been
sealed to the floor and contain the
remains of travellers and con¬
querors who died of fever and
wounds. The muffled sound of
waves beating on distant rocks can
be heard, as if the sea were trying
to efface all trace of human life.
In vain. These bodies mingled with
the land of Africa are forever part
of the history and life of the island
of Mozambique. I
The fortress of St.
Sebastian (1558-
1620). Its design was
inspired by Italian
Renaissance military
architecture.
A TIDE OF EVENTS
A child's grave in the
island's cemetery.
10th century: First mention of the island of
Mozambique in Aral) written sources.
10lh-15th centuries: Arab trading posts.
1498: Vasco da Gama lands on the island.
1502: Vasco da Gama's second voyage. Portu¬
gal's first trading station on Mozambique is
founded.
1307-1508: The fort of St. Gabriel is con¬
structed.
1522: The chapel of Our Lady of the Ramparts
is built.
1558-1620: The fort of St. Sebastian is built to
guard against possible Turkish attack.
1607: The island is unsuccessfully attacked by
the Dutch.
1750-1810: The slave trade period.
1762: The island ceases to he administered hy the
Viceroy of Coa and conies directly under the Por¬
tuguese crown.
1869: The opening of the Suez Canal makes it
possible to reach India from Europe without pass¬
ing the Cape of Good Hope and Mozambique.
1898: The capital of Mo/.ambiqiie is transferred
to Lourenço Marques (today Maputo). The island
becomes a simple provincial capital.
1917: The construction of the port of Narala, a
little further north, deals a deatli blow to the
island's economy.
1975: The independence of Mozambique is pro¬
claimed on 25 June.
1991: The island of Mozambique is placed on
UNESCO's World Heritage List.
THE UNt^CO lOURIER MAY 1997 4o
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
GREENWATCH
ardens of the Far East
In the early eighteenth cen¬
tury English landscape gar¬
deners began to rebel against the
«traitjacket of French classicism.
They were weary of gardens divided
into symmetrical blocks by rectilin¬
ear paths punctuated with statues
and fountains, gardens where no
plant had a right to grow outside its
appointed place. When the fashion
for informal landscaped gardens
appeared in England, the hand of
Chinese influence was widely felt.
"Everyone knows that English gar¬
dens are nothing more than imita¬
tions of Chinese gardens," wrote
Ceorges Le Rouge in 1774 of the
fashion for what were known as
"Anglo-Chinese" gardens, which
later spread to many parts of Europe.
In point of fart, Chinese influence
went no further than a pagoda or
pavilion placed at the edge of a
stream in the middle of a park.
The gardens of the Ear East are
small enclosed worlds that awaken
the senses and calm the mind. Every¬
thing in them seems designed to
I r
THE UNESCO l_OURIER B MAY 1007
The Park of the
Jade Spring in Li-
jiang, Yunnan
province (China).
Below, part of the
Chuo Cheng (Zhou
Zeng) Yuan garden
in Suzhu (China).
The garden is in 3
parts, divided by
walls. The central
and western
sections have been
composed around
a winding lake for
1,000 years. The
eastern part has
been laid out in a
modern, Western-
inspired style.
encourage meditation: murmuring
water, birdsong, the sound of frogs
and crickets, wind rustling in bam¬
boo leaves, the delicate smell given
off by lotus leaves after a summer
shower, and succulent fruit ripen¬
ing on the stem.
CHINA: ROOMS WITH A VIEW
"In Chinese," writes Antoine Gour-
nay, assistant curator of the Cer-
nusehi Museum in Paris, "the word
yuan (garden) means not so much an
area set apart from built architec¬
ture and mainly used for growing
plants, as a specific way of distrib¬
uting and arranging the space of a
dwelling." lie goes on to say that
"House and garden in China are
more often dovetailed together than
juxtaposed; what's more, the vege¬
tation that decorates this ensemble
is considered as secondary to rocks
and water." The regularity of archi-
by France Bequette
tecture contrasts with the irregu¬
larity of the garden with its twisted
rocks and ponds in a variety of
shapes.
Hocks symbolize mountains, the
place where sky and earth meet.
They are chosen carefully. The more
unusual their shape, the more they
are worth. Their size depends on
their creator's resources and ambi¬
tions. In the 11th century, the
Northern Sung dynasty emperor Ilui
Tsung spent twelve years creating
the Lake of Golden Clarity,
Longevity Mountain (;ï,000 m-) and
Gen Yu rockery ( 1 50 metres high) in
the imperial city of Bian Liang. In
his book Classic Chinese Gardens,
Qiao Yuri tells how the emperor "did
not hesitate to knock down bridges
or destroy roads and canals to trans¬
port these rocks." In China, where
mountains are worshipped (e.g. Knn-
lun shan, the residence of Tai ji, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
"immensely great one"), there are
no gardens without rocks.
Water is as essential as rocks, to
which it is a complement, since
water and rocks are yin and yang.
Sun-drenched, angular and hard,
rocks are yang. Cold and dark but
also free, ¡iure and regenerative,
water is yin. Liu Bang, Gaozu
(founding emperor) of the Han
dynasty in the third century B.C.,
created three artificial islands in Tai
Yi Lake, to symbolize paradise.
From that time on all imperial gar¬
dens used this symbol.
The first private gardens are
recorded in the year 900, the finest
examples being in the city of Suzhou
in Jiangsu province. Many men of let¬
ters went to live in the city in isola¬
tion from the world, and there they
practised gardening and painting on
silk. The format of traditional paint¬
ing on hand scrolls, which is read
cither vertically or horizontally, is
said to correspond perfectly with
the thought processes of the lover of
gardens.
Enclosed by walls, which provide
a neutral background, the Chinese
garden contains buildings for various
leisure activities. The landscape is
arranged according to the rooms from
which it is viewed. ¡No single point
a fiords an overall view. Natural com
positions are framed by open-work,
round, rectangular or fan-shaped win¬
dows, and doors shaped like full
moons or vases. Non-structural walls
are replaced by moveable partitions.
Covered walkways meander through
the garden so that it can be enjojed
in all weathers. The fusion between
the inside and outside areas is
complete.
Galleries, pathways and bridges
shun rectilinearity, for straight lines
are used by evil spirits. Garden design
is regulated by the science known as
fengshui, which literally means "wind
and water" and is expressed via geo-
mancy. For 2,000 y ears it was incon¬
ceivable to build a house without
first consulting a gcomancer. "If you
induce harmony of place," says the
Hook of Rites (Li ji), "then sky and
earth will assume their rightful
places and everything will prosper."
Antoine Gournay explains: "The site,
orientation and shape of buildings
are chosen so as to use to maximum
effect the breaths of the life force
(qiyun) that appear in ibis place, cap¬
ture their beneficial effects and take
precautions against their baneful
influences." The ideal site faces
south, turns its back to a mountain
and is near a stream flowing from
northwest to southeast. The garden
should be entered from the south.
The Ryoan-ji Zen
garden in Kyoto
(Japan) is
considered to be
the earliest
example of pure
kare-sansui or dry
stone-work
garden.
The Nanzen-ji sand
garden in Kyoto
(Japan).
JAPAN: PUTTING THE WORLD IN
ORDER
Japanese garden design is also gov¬
erned by fengshui, and as early as
the sixth century it was drawing
inspiration from Buddhism and Chi¬
nese practices. But Chinese and
Japanese thinking about gardens
went different ways. "By means of
the most ordinary things gardens
enable us to grasp the secret of
nature and its real essence," wrote
Soami, a sixteenth-century monk and
aesthete who wrote a book on gar¬
dens.
"The shadow of the bamboo
sweeps the steps
but not a speck of dust moves.
The moon plunges to the bottom
of the fountain
but the water is unruffled,"
leads an entry in the Zemin Kushu,
an anthology of quotations compiled
in the fifteenth century. The garden
is a place conducive to meditation.
Rigour, purity and asymmetry pre¬
side over its composition. Nothing is
left to chance. Its architecture is as
codified as calligraphy, the tea cer¬
emony or the art of flower arrange¬
ment. In fact gardening was done by
monks, painters or masters of the
tea ceremony until professional hor¬
ticulturists came on the scene. As a
way of putting the world in order, it
expresses a religion or a philosophy
with as much precision as a cathe¬
dral or a treatise. Its size is of no
importance. It can be miniaturized
and even be contained in a small
porcelain cup.
Japanese gardeners were poets
and philosophers. While resting
X
:,y^y -; -,(
> QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
from their labours, they composed
haiku, 17-sy liable poems celebrating
nature. "The dead leaves flutter
down one on the other. The rain falls
on the rain." Their studies lasted
for u j) to ten years. Their favourite
trees were pine, plum, cherry and
maple. Irises, peonies, azaleas and
chrysanthemums could be used to
add notes of colour. Everything was
arranged according to immutable
principles. A tree, for example,
should never be planted in the cen¬
tre of the garden, for it would resem¬
ble the kumaru ideogram which
means "to have problems". Stones
and jilants must be arranged accord¬
ing to the magical yang odd num¬
bers: three, five or seven.
The kare-sansui, a dry stone¬
work garden that would be incon-
Stone lantern and arched footbridge in
the Zen garden of Kenko-ji Temple at
Tsurumi, Yokohama (Japan).
initiatives
The water hyacinth: an aquatic pest
The water hyacinth is a thick-leaved freshwater plant with a pale blue flower. Imported into Asia and
Africa from South America because of its beauty, it proliferated unchecked in the silty, mineral-rich
water of lakes and rivers. When it is well established, it consumes the oxygen fish need to survive, hin¬
ders fishing and navigation and slows water flow to a trickle so that hydroelectric power plants become
useless. The economies of some Asian and African countries, especially the nations bordering Lake Vic¬
toria, Africa's biggest lake (some 70,000 km2), have been so hard hit by this persistent parasite that they
have declared war on it. The World Rank and the Global Environment Facility have committed several
million dollars to the struggle.
The opening moves in the battle, conducted using chemical herbicides, were not very successful, partly
because the range of usable products was severely limited by a concern to preserve aquatic life and main¬
tain water quality. Eventually the idea of introducing a natural predator was adopted and is now being
tried out experimentally by the Kenyan Institute of Agricultural Research, which imported nearly
35,000 weevil larvae from Australia and put them into the lake.
Since then, however, international experts meeting in Namibia for a symposium held under the
United Nations University's Zero Emission Research Initiative1 (ZERI) have expressed scepticism about
the weevil's effectiveness and are afraid that the introduction of this new insect into the lake's ecosys¬
tem may have unpredictable consequences. On the other hand, they showed interest in a proposal from
a working group of experts, endorsed hy Prof. S. T. Chang, a world famous Chinese expert on mushroom
growing, which suggests that if the hyacinths are harvested, dried and mixed with other waste, they could
make a useful substrate for the cultivation of mushrooms. Seven African a ml Asian nations have agreed
to take part in this experiment.
If the results are conclusive, the mushrooms could provide participating countries with a foodstuff
that would be nutritionally appreciable since it would contain iodine if seaweed residue were to he
added to the culture substrate. This is important since 30% of the population of southern Africa and
20% of the people living in the highlands of Southeast Asia suffer from chronic iodine deficiency. There
is also a possibility that the substrate could be recycled by earthworms, which would convert it into
chicken feed and a rich compost for enhancing soil fertility. The first findings will he examined at the
third international congress of the ZERI Programme to be held this June in Jakarta (Indonesia). M
1. See ihe Gieenwalcli fea tine, "Waste-free manu Tact u ring feasible goal or wild goose chase?" in I lie
March 1996 issue of the UXESCO Courier.ICd.
FURTHER READING:
/CHINOISERIES
by Dawn Jacobson, Phaidon Press,
London, 1993
/LES JARDINS CLASSIQUES
CHINOIS
byQiaoYun, Hayot publishers, Paris, 1988
/THE CHINESE GARDEN,
by Maggie Keswick, Academy Editions,
London, 1986
ceivable in China, appeared around
the middle of the fourteenth cen¬
tury under the influence of Zen phi¬
losophy. To achieve inner illumina¬
tion, satori, the sage creates an inner
void by silently contemplating a rec¬
tangle of raked white sand from
which deeply buried and carefully
placed stones protrude. Waterfalls,
rivers and waves are suggested by
furrows made by the rake. In the
most famous of these gardens, the
Ryoan-ji in Kyoto, which dates from
the Muromachi period (fourteenth
to sixteenth centuries), fifteen rocks
emerge from a lied of white gravel.
The crowds that visit the garden
every day see in it islands, constel¬
lations, clouds or even a tigress with
her cubs.
Later, when the tea ceremony
had been institutionalized, a garden
was designed to provide it with a set¬
ting. This "tea garden" is divided in
two: an inner garden and an outer
garden. The tea house must seem
isolated from the rest of the world.
The tall trees that surround it are
untouched by shears.
In places where hot springs shoot
out of volcanic soil, the garden
designer creates a pond for bathing
and relaxation. In this setting all
kinds of shapes and objects become
symbols. In the garden of the Silver
Pavilion (Ginkaku-ji, fifteenth cen¬
tury) in Kyoto, an ordinary pile of
sand meant for the garden's upkeep
caught the gardener's eye. Shaped
like a truncated cone, its flat top
reflected the moon so well that it
immediately became an altar to the
glory of the moon and a protected
monument. B
46
THE UNESCO lOURIER MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
w
î$Bf
BARK-LOVING BABOONS
Since 1992, when drought
forced them to change their
diet of small mammals, birds,
insects and plants, the 8,000
baboons of Manicaland, a
province in eastern Zimbabwe,
have taken a shine to the bark
of young pines. Now their
healthy appetite is causing $5
million damage a year in the
plantations. Timber merchants,
for whom this damage repre¬
sents considerable loss of
income, want to get rid of the
baboons, but traditional chiefs
and environmentalists are hos¬
tile to the idea.
THE WORLD'S
OLDESTTEATREE
A 2,700-year-old tea tree has
recently been discovered in
China's Yunnan province, not
far from a plant only 200 years
younger. The tree, which is 1.2
metres in diameter and 25.5
metres tall, is growing in virgin
forest at an altitude of 2,500
metres. The discovery is sur¬
prising because normally wild
tea shrubs do not grow more
than 10 metres tall. It tends to
support the theory that tea
may have originated in Yunnan
province.
MEDITERRANEAN BLUES
Some 130 million people live
around the Mediterranean and
each year, mostly in summer,
they are joined by 100 million
or more tourists. Each year
some 1.7 x 109 cubic metres
of municipal waste water are
discharged directly into the
sea, three-quarters of it
untreated, as well as 66 x 109
cubic metres of industrial
waste water, 120,000 tons of
mineral oils, 60,000 tons of
detergents, heavy metals,
phosphates and nitrates in
excess of admissible, or desir¬
able levels. These figures are
quoted in a recent report hy
the United Nations Environ¬
ment Programme (MAP Tech¬
nical Reports Series No. 100)
which notes that pollution in
the Mediterranean is serious
and that the overall picture is
discouraging. And yet the leg¬
islative framework needed to
apply vital safeguards exists.
What is required is political
determination to tackle the
problem vigorously. I
UNDERGROUND DAMS
While damming rivers pro¬
vokes lively debate (see
"Greenwatch", March 1997),
damming underground streams
where they come to the sur¬
face is much less controversial.
The Chinese have created
large underground reservoirs
in karst (limestone) by using
this "bottling up" technique.
During floods, river water col¬
lects in underground cavities,
where it is stored until needed
in the dry season. Not all types
of rock lend themselves to this
kind of scheme, however.
OASES UNDER THE SEA
"Undersea oases" are extraor¬
dinary ecosystems associated
with hydrothermal springs
that well up from the ocean
floor at temperatures higher
than 350°C. The springs are
usually rich in metal sul¬
phides, which are generally
toxic for marine life. Unable
to carry out photosynthesis for
lack of sunlight, creatures liv¬
ing in these ecosystems depend
on chemosynthesis for their
survival. A team of European
and American scientists have
explored the East Pacific Rise
between the Gulf of Califor¬
nia and the Galapagos Islands
where the oases were discov¬
ered in the 1970s. Among the
samples of animal life they
took from 2,600 metres in
depth were amazing 2-nietre-
longworms whose metabolism
has features in common with
both ¡liants and animals. To
study them under optimal con¬
ditions, pressurized aquariums
simulating their natural living
conditions have been devel¬
oped.
THE SUNFLOWER
WAY TO SOLAR POWER
Iiy observing the movement of
sunflowers, Swiss inventor
Emile Jansen has found a sim¬
ple way of maximizing the yield
of panels of photovoltaic cells,
which convert solar energy
directly into electricity. He set
out to design a system that
would turn the panels to follow
the sun without using either
electricity or harmful gases
(such as Ereon or the CFCs),
and at a cost that would be
absorbed by the increase in
energy production. He came tqi
with the "Jawisol" system,
which uses the principle of
dilating fluids. Powered by the
sun's heat, a jack filled with
fluid turns the photovoltaic
panels mechanically by a sys¬
tem of cables and pulleys. The
system has been proved effec
tive after two years of tests by
a Swiss engineering school.
Unfortunately solar energy is
not as popular as it might be. I
Jawisol, Case postale 74, CII-1%3
Savièse, Switzerland.
Tel: (41) 27 393 17 25;
Fax: (41) 27 3 »3 20 42
BOUNTIFUL
BAMBOO
bamboo throve all round the
equator, from Indonesia to Tan¬
zania and Costa Rica, until col¬
onizers arrived and cut it down
to make room for farmland. Its
qualities have long been under-
eslimated. It has a higher ten¬
sile strength than steel, grows
quickly (taking only 5 years to
reach maturity) and is an excel¬
lent building material. In the
province of Caldas (Colombia)
3-storey bamboo buildings
more than a century old are still
being used. Hamboo can also
be used as drainage piping and
as a basis for renewable fuels,
and bamboo shoots are delica¬
cies in Chinese and Japanese
cooking. With some 1,500 vari¬
eties in Africa alone, bamboo
is the renewable plant of the
future.
> QuiTHE UNCSCO tOURIERB MAY 1997 "1/
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
L I S T E N I ETHIOPIA'S
BY ISABELLE LEYMARIE B Z ÏX] B Y \ íTlÍ nStfelS
Are all three of you genuine azmaris!
Ejigayehu Shihahaw: No, the only uzmuri
is Weres Egeziaber. He only perforins tra¬
ditional music, whereas Fantahun She-
wakochew Mekonnen and I sing and play
other kinds as well. A real azinuri has to
play the masenqo, an instrument Weres
Egeziaber specializes in.
It is said that the meaning of the word
azmari has changed. Whereas it once meant
"praise-singers " it has supposedly come to
mean "those who criticize", or even "those
who denigrate".
E. S.: A few centuries ago the azmaris per¬
formed religious functions at the courts of
sovereigns. They celebrated liturgies and
officiated at certain ceremonies. Their
repertoire only gradually became more sec¬
ular. They began as praise-singers, then
they sang love poetry and eventually began
to invent humorous or satirical verse in
which they poked fun at their own pro¬
tectors.
In some regions, the griots, who are also
praise-singers and heirs to a long tradition,
are not allowed to criticize or abuse anyone
directly, although sometimes they allow
themselves to make a fewveiled allusions.
E. S.: In Ethiopia we are absolutely free to
do this. The azmaris in particular and tra¬
ditional singers in general excel in the art of
improvisation. They have a particular lik¬
ing for humour, alliteration, puns and
satire. No one really takes exception to
their mockery. Love songs are still hy far
the most popular part of their repertoire,
however.
Ethnological studies of Ethiopia say that
the azmaris are despised by the rest of society.
E. S.: That is true of musicians in general,
48 r
THE UNESCO f^URIERB MAY 1997
MjBBTpg-'
The azmaris are minstrels who belong to Ethiopia's Christian majority, the Amhara. Their
repertoire, whose origins are lost in the mists of time, consists largely of light poetry, much
of it extemporized. They use traditionalinstruments such as the krar, a lyre with similarities
to those used in ancient Egypt, the masenqo (a single-string spike fiddle) and double-
skinned drums. Women performers wear long white dresses with scarlet bands, and the men,
white shirts and trousers and a kind of cloak with a wide golden-brown sash. Three exponents
of this Amharic tradition, singer Ejigayehu Shibabaw (at centre of photo) and her
accompanists, (on her right in photo) Fantahun Shewakochew Mekonnen (krar, percussion
and vocals) and (on her left) Weres G. Egeziaber (masenqo and vocals), recently gave a series
of recitals in Paris. During their visit, they talked to Isabelle Leymarie.
not just the. azmaris. My father, for exam¬
ple, is a businessman, and is very hostile to
the fact that I am a singer. I had to run
away from home to follow my vocation.
Yet you give concerts outside Ethiopia and
you are just about to make yourfirst
recording. Isn't this success a point in your
favour?
E. S.: Not at all. He believes that it is
shameful to perform in public Even if 1
became a big star, be wouldn't change his
mind.
\\ eres Egeziaber: I must be an exception
because my family was overjoyed that I
became a musician. My parents are farmers,
and when I was eighteen I learned to play
the masenqo in my village from small
groups of itinerant musicians.
Ejigayehu Shibabaw, you are not from a
family of musicians, how did you learn the
traditional repertoire?
E. S.: By car. Hut that is very easy, because
in Ethiopia, even in Addis Ababa, every¬
one knows the old songs. Tradition is still
very much ali\ c. I didn't need recordings or
any special training. I speak two Ethiopian
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
languages: Amliaric, my mother tongue,
and Ago, which is a v cry rby thmic language.
And if I have to sing songs in other lan¬
guages, I learn them phonetically. Fan¬
tahun Sliewakochew Mekonnen studied
music for four years in a school where they
taught both classical Western music
and Ethiopian music. He often does
arrangements.
How did you form your trio?
E. S.: We met at a puppet show at the
Addis Ababa National Theatre, a big
employer of singers, dancers and musicians.
How do you improvise?
E. S.: We usually improvise words to a given
melody. Even during a concert I sometimes
invent new couplets when I feel inspired.
Do the musicians improvise too?
F. S. K.: Yes, but according to certain rules.
Ethiopian music Amliaric music in par¬
ticular is based on pentatonic scales.
There are a lot of them and each one
expresses a specific mood. We mainly use
four. Improvisation is traditionally done
inside this modal framework. Our instru¬
ments, especially the masenqo, are
adapted to this form of music. I also play
the trumpet and the piano. As well as the
traditional repertoire, I play pop music,
Ethiopian pop, using brass and keyboards
but with words sung in Amliaric. We also
listen to foreign music, but our inspiration
is mostly local, although we are not locked
in to the old modes. Sometimes we mix sev¬
eral modes or African modes and Western
scales.
Ejigayehu Shibabaw, do you sing more
modern music?
E. S.: Yes, I'm currently preparing to make
my first record, also using brass and key¬
board instruments. It will include a blend
of reggae and West African and Ethiopian
beats. I'm calling it Tsahay, "sun" in
Amliaric. Our country is rich in rhythms
often unknown outside Ethiopia so I
doubt I'll ever be short of inspiration. I
ANNIVERSARY
ALEKO KONSTANTINOV
(1863-1897)
Happy and glorious
BY GEORGI DANAÏL0V
Still going strong a century after his creator's death,
a hero of Bulgarian literature who stepped out of the pages
of fiction into real life.
It is a rare occurrence for a hero of literature to leap off the page, turn
his back on the writer who created him, and go off and live his own life.
I only know of one such case in Bulgarian literature. His progenitor
was Aleko Konstaiilinov, who was born in Svishtov in 1 863 and met his
end on the road between l'eshlera and Pazardhzik in 1897. Konstan-
tinovvvasa lawyer, publicist and journalist, who signed bis works with
the pen name "I hippy". Democrat, musician, nature-lover, mountaineer,
traveller and bohemian, he was an intellectual aristocrat and perhaps
Bulgaria's most brilliant writer.
After producing a travel hook about America, Do Chicago i nazad
('"To Chicago and Back", 1891) Konstantinov used a blend of love,
hate and satire to create a character of a type we come across every «lay
of our lives, a character we thoroughly detest and with whom at the,
same time we feel a secret complicity. Ostensibly we expel him from our¬
selves but at the same time we leave the back door wide open for him,
because when we are in a light spot we need his inventiveness and his
extraordinary adaptability. We loathe his impudence and braggadocio,
his crudencss and lack of sophistication, but we know that we have the
same intolerable quirks as he does.
Aleko Konstantinov created his character effortlessly, with aristo¬
cratic nonchalance. He gave him the name Ganyu, that of a merchant
> Con RIER B MAY 1997
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
ANNIVERSARY AUTHORS
of attar of roses he had met in Chicago, to which he added the name
Balkanski, meaning "Balkan" a bold yet justified generalization
and made him the central character of a series of short stories.
The Bulgarian public has taken Ganyu Balkanski so much to heart
that it has virtually forgotten his origin as a fictional character. This
earthy, authentic figure is so successful, active and alive that he is at
home in all kinds of settings and plots. He crops up in Prague and
Vienna, in Switzerland and Russia, where he has picked up the secrets
of journalism, the principles of unprincipled politics, election-winning
tactics.
Some critics have seen Ganyu Balkanski as the archetype of the Bul¬
garian petty bourgeoisie which was to he almost squeezed out of exis¬
tence hy half a century of socialism. To the amazement of the Marxists,
however, Aleko's hero did not go under with the bourgeoisie but con¬
tinued on his sprightly way, marching at the side of demonstrators
brandishing the red flag.
In the popular imagination, Ganyu has acquired a heroic dimension.
He has become a man worth two, a sexual titan, a lively mind who can
find original solutions to all kinds of problems. Like many undying
heroes of world literature, Bai Ganyu has a strong sense of humour and
the capacity to laugh at himself.
Someone once asked Aleko Konstantinov what was the happiest
day of his life. "The day when I had the idea of writing Bai Ga/iyit,"
was his answer. Ganyu Balkanski's creator was murdered hy hired
assassins on 21 May 1897. There is a theory that he was killed by mis¬
take and that the bullets were intended for his friend, the politician
Takev, with whom he was travelling in a coach. They had changed
places a few minutes before the coach reached the spot where it was
ambushed. Many years later, the Bulgarian artist Ilya Bechkov drew a
widely applauded cartoon of the scene. Aleko Konstantinov is shown
lying on the ground riddled with bullets and saying to Ganyu Balkan-
ski, who is leaning over him, "Did you do it, Bai Ganyu? You've shut my
trap, eh?"
In spite ofthat, I refuse to think of Ganyu Balkanski as a parricide.
In spite of all his faults and odious characteristics, I regard him as an
extremely resourceful man and do not see why he should always be pil¬
loried. He was a great survivor, and that's all. Perhaps the Bulgarians
would not have survived several centuries of domination without the
vitality, powers of endurance and flexibility ofAleko Konstantinov's hero.
And so Mr. Balkanski is still going strong. As for his creator, all that
survives of him in the house where he was born is his heart a hard piece
of yellowish muscle patched up hy pathologists and [»reserved in alco¬
hol exhibited in a glass case. As well as this relic visitors can see the
clothes Konstantinov was wearing when he was killed. His shirt bears
rust-coloured bloodstains. Imprints of his killers' footsteps are moulded
in plaster.
A superb bust of Konstantinov by Jcko Spiridonov can he seen in the
municipal gardens at Svishtov. Aleko is holding a cigarette and a hint
of a smile plays about his features as he gazes transfixed at some won¬
derful sight. "To Aleko!" says an affectionate inscription engraved
beneath the bust. What writer, politician or public man could boast of
being so close to the people?
In 1995, Chicago University also decided to erect a bust to Aleko
Konstantinov. A copy was made of Jeko Spiridonov's work but with¬
out the hands! It was said that moulding the hands would have made
the reproduction too expensive. And perhaps that cigarette would
have made a had impression. So only Aleko's smile made the journey to
America. B
ANNICK THEBIA MELSAN, a French university
teacher and diplomat, organized an exhibition on
Aimé Césaire held during the summit meeting of
Francophone states at Cotonou (Benin) in 1995.
She is the author of a 3-part film: Aimé Césaire,
une voix pour l'histoire (1993-1994).
YVES BERGERET, a French writer, is a curator at
the Georges Pompidou Art and Cultural Centre in
Pans and director of an international poetry
review, Poésie 97. His most recent publications
include Poèmes de Prague (1991) and Martinique
(1995).
MASAYUKI NINOMIYA, of Japan, teaches at the
arts faculty of the University of Geneva
(Switzerland). He recently published La pensée
de Kobayashi Hideo, Un intellectuel japonais au
tournant de l'histoire ("The Thought of
Kobayashi Hideo, A Japanese Intellectual at a
Turning Point in History", Librairie Droz, Geneva,
1995).
JEAN-FRANÇOIS PATRICOLA, of Italy, is a teacher
and researcher at the University of Nancy II
(France). He is editor-in-chief of L 'Estocade, a
French review of art and literature, and recently
published a collection of poems, Siciles (1997).
GUILLERMO PIÑA-CONTRERAS, a Dominican
writer and journalist, is Paris correspondent of
the Dominican magazine Rumbo.
YANNIS E. I0ANN0U, of Cyprus, teaches French
language and literature at the University of
Cyprus.
LUIS MIZON, a Chilean poet and essayist, is the
author of many works, including a novel, El
hombre del cerro plomo ("The man from Cerro
Plomo", Seix Barrai, 1991) and a collection of
poems, Jardin de ruinas ("Garden of Ruins",
1992).
PATRICK LAGES is a French photojournahst.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American
journalist specializing in environmental
questions.
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American
musicologist, is the author of Du Tango au
reggae, Musiques noires d'Amérique latine et des
Caraïbes ("From Tango to Reggae, Black Music of
Latin America and the Caribbean", Flammarion,
Pans, 1996) and Musiques Caraïbes ("Caribbean
Music", Actes Sud, Aries, 1996).
GEORGI DANAÏL0V is a Bulgarian writer and
playwright.
50
THE UNESCO ^>UR1I¡ERB MAY 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
V^)urier «Nikon
announce an
international
photo competition
on the theme of
THE THEME:
{The theme of the competition, inspired by
't the Preamble to Unesco's Constitution, is
peace in the down-to-earth context of
everyday life.
Peace in
everyday life
CONDITIONS
OF ENTRY:
The competition is open to professional
photographers in all parts of the world.
Contestants are requested to constitute a portfolio of up
to twenty black and white or colour prints of their work on
the theme "Peace in everyday life", and send it in with a
completed entry form. The portfolios must reach the
Unesco Courier offices by
15 July 1997.
THE JURY:
An international jury will meet
in Paris and choose the winning entry from
among 120 portfolios short-listed by a
preselection committee. Short-listing and
jury deliberations will take place at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris.
A "Unesco Courier- Nikon Prize
of
50,00 i
will be awarded to the winning entry.
Prize-winning photos will be published
in the Unesco Courier.
For further information, contact:
"Peace in everyday life" competition
Unesco Courier
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 PARIS CEDEX 15,France
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 69
Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
.
r2W&
A*.
W
THEME OF THE NEXT] JE
HOW IDEAS TRAVEL
T
INTERVIEW WITH:
VIVIANE FORRESTER
HERITAGE:
THE STATUES
OF PALMYRA
(Syrian Arab Republic)
ENVIRONMENT:
SAVE OUR SOIL!
í'íl
A
f
]]>
</page>
</document>
