<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="108625eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
«a«
M 1205 -9706-2
ill Í I'll í11;^^!' : 'I I
. *
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture
or any other subject which seems
to be an example of cultural
cross-fertilization.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
MUSIC
IN THE PLURAL
2995, mixed media (pencil,
Indian ink, oil paint and
adhesive tape on paper),
70x50 cm
by Martin Lersch
When music and painting
meet, says German artist
Martin Lersch, the results
can be very surprising. In
this sketch by him the left-
hand figure is based on a
black and white engraving
made by Giovanm'-Battista
Bracelli around 1630. The
figure on the right was
drawn by the artist in 1991
at a concert given by British
musician Courtney Pine
during the International
Jazz Festival at Viersen
(Germany).
© Musée du Mans, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO Q)U RI ER
Best-selling French author Viviane Forrester
speaks out against the drama of
unemployment in a time ofradical social
change (p. 47).
Palmyra (Syrian Arab Republic).
The spectacular ruins ofa metropolis of
Antiquity contain highly original sculpture
(p. 42).
CONTENTS
JUNE 1997
HOW IDEAS TRAVEL
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	5
On the road	6
by François-Bernard Huyghe
Manuscripts on the move	10
by Gerald Messadié
Best-sellers and gossip-mongers in 18th-century France	14
by Robert Darnton
' Wo rds have no legs, yet they walk'	18
by Youssouf Tata Cissé
The mixed signals of globalization 22
by Salah Guemriche
Cyberspace: a planetary network of people and ideas	25
by J. C. Nyiri
The test of time	30
by Louise Merzeau
Fact file 34
Consultant: François-Bernard Huyghe
Commentary Federico Mayor 36
GREENWATCH SaveOurSoils! by France Bequette	38
HERITAGE
Palmyra: faces that belong to eternity by Mahmoud Zibawi
Ancient and modern Egypt come face to face by Samlr Gharib	45
AUTHORS	50
Cover:
Lines of communication. Above, optic fibres; below, a Tuareg drum.
© Adam Hart Davis/S PL /Cosmos. Pans X Richer ©Hoa Qui Pans
THE UNESCO ^)URIER JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
th& unesco
Courier
^^50th YEAR
Published monthly in 29 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational. Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Pans CEDEX 15, France
Fax (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
e-mail: unesco.couner@unesco org
Internet. http.//www unesco org
Director. Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition RoyMalkin
French edition Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production Georges Servat
Illustrations1 Ariane Bailey (Te!. (33) (0) 1 45.68 46.90)
Documentation. José Banaag
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press:
Solange Beim (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 87)
Film duplication Daniel Meister
Secretariat: Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 47.15),
Administrative Assistant Theresa Pmck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian Irina Utkma (Moscow}
German Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic. Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian Gianluca Formichi(Rome)
Hindi Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil: M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian AkbarZargar (Teheran)
Dutch' Bart Chnstiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese. Feng Mmgxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian: DragomirPetrov (Sofia)
Greek Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala' Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish. Rntta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa Aliyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician. Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45.68 45 65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Customer service: Michel Ravassard,
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 91)
Accounts: (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 45 65)
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 47 50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 45 65
lyear 211 French francs 2 years: 396 FF.
Students: 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries:
lyear: 132 French francs 2 years 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
dale of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author s name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written hy the
Unesco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700
Pans, (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100
U S A , [3) N C R Microcard Edition Indian Head Inc.. Ill West 40th
Street. New York, U S A , (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfeld Road.
Wooster Ohio 44691. U S A.
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DÉPÔT LÉGAL Cl -JUIN 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M PP
Photocomposition, photogravure:
Le Courrier de ¡'Unesco.
Impression MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.l. Route d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 6-1997-OPI-9 7-600 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51.
4
THE UNESCO lOURIER I
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
HOW IDEAS TRAVEL
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
In a recent Unesco Courierinterview (February 1997) the French
historian and philosopher Alain de Libera talked about the
extraordinary way in which the idea of the individual travelled
across the centuries, continents and cultures.
This idea, which originated in ancient Greece, was enriched
much later in medieval Andalusia when it came into contact with
an Arab concept of intellectual activity as a blend of abstract
speculation and technical enquiry. This notion in its turn became
the foundation of a revolutionary institution, the university,
which spread throughout Europe and, between the Renaissance
and the Enlightenment, gave birth to the modern concept of the
human being. With the proclamation of the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights in 1948, an idea whose first glimmerings had
appeared 3,000 years before became a federating principle of the
human community.
The present issue sheds light on some of the highways and
byways along which ideas have travelled over the centuries. As
well as tracing their geographical twists and turns it notes the
increasing speed and range of the mediafrom caravans to
computers, from clay tablets to fibre opticswhereby ideas have
been communicated. It shows many-sided humanity gradually
becoming aware of its unity with the emergence and
transmission of ideas, principles and standards which deserve to
be shared by all since they give everyone an opportunity for
enrichment.
This path towards universality, with all its ups and downs, has
been above all else a road to freedom. H
THE UNESCO ÇjURIER |UNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Ideas have always followed in the wake of trade,
war and religion
UN THE ROAD
BY FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE
Isetail of an early
16th-century Venetian map of
the African coastline.
How do ideas travel? It may seem
incongruous to ask such a question
in a magazine that is published in sev¬
eral dozen languages and is read all
over the world. If we make no distinction
between the notions of representation, belief
and information, and regard "ideas" very
broadly as all those products of a human mind
that can be appropriated by another mind,
then we see that ideas do nothing but travel. It
is no more surprising to find that there are
practising Buddhists in California, that
Euclid's theorems are studied in China and
that Latin American politics are debated in
Australia than it is for a European to watch a
Japanese-made television or wear cloth woven
in Pakistan.
Globalization, a notion which attempts
to describe recent changes and which has itself
travelled, designates the circulation of mater¬
ial goods as well as the intangible circuits of
knowledge, patterns of thought and judge¬
ments. Current philosophical and political
trends in the West strongly approve of the
m
indach
: x>3 JZAJigv
: -
THE UNESCO ^UB.ER JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
creative potential of the free flow of ideas that
technology seems to promote. True, there is
debate about which views ought not be
allowed to spread, whether control of the
media does not sometimes lend itself to intel¬
lectual manipulation, and whether, metaphor¬
ically speaking, the bad money of stereotypes,
disinformation and triviality does not drive
out good. But the question of how ideas travel
arouses relatively little interest, so completely
docs it seem to have been solved.
This is to pass lightly over the fact that an
idea is an invisible entity made visible by traces
left by its passage and that it cannot change
the world unless it travels. Except in the nec¬
essarily limited case of direct verbal commu¬
nication, obstacles and intermediaries come
between the inception of an idea and the brain
of the person who picks it up, sometimes
much later or in a faraway place.
To conquer time and space an idea must
endure and it must move. It must be stored in
a memory and be transported. Of course, dur¬
ing the performance of these operations,
which may take a few fractions of a second
on the Internet or centuries in the case of cer¬
tain religious beliefs the idea changes. There
may be many reasons for this change, includ¬
ing the vagaries of translation, distortions
introduced by intermediaries or copyists, the
format required for transmission, and other
factors such as loss, censorship, interference
and interpretation. Movement has changed
the message.
* Intellectual highways
Ideas spread along routes which are changed by
technological innovation. Printing increased
the number of books and made the preserva¬
tion of ideas less dependent on the risks of
copying, destruction, censorship or a broken
journey. With the invention of the telegraph,
messages for the first time travelled faster than
people. On the airwaves words (and soon after,
images) no longer travelled from place to place
but covered whole territories, defying fron¬
tiers and walls. With telematics and the inter¬
connection of millions of computer memo¬
ries, recording, researching and transmitting
data has become almost a single operation.
During most of human history ideas were
conveyed in small numbers and with diffi¬
culty, peddled with a human escort moving
slowly in dangerous conditions. In short,
along roads. For centuries there was no dif¬
ference between the movement of people and
the movement of ideas and material goods.
Consigned to manuscripts and illustrated by
images or simply memorized by scholars or
the Adoration of the Magi
(detail), by the Italian painter
Andrea Mantegna (1431-
1506).
religious believers, ideas travelled on horse¬
back or by camel, in the holds of ships or at
walking pace. The range, the cadence of prop¬
agation and ultimately the success of the tech¬
nology, scientific conceptions and religious
ideas we have inherited can be explained by all
the factors that have stimulated or handi¬
capped travel by land or sea.
Unesco has rightly adopted the theme of
routes to bracket together projects connected
with cultural dialogue and cross-fertilization.
These very ancient routes owe their names to
a precious commodity that was transported
along them: silk, iron, and even slaves. Other
routes were determined less by trade than by
the centre towards which they converged, e.g.
Jerusalem, the holy city of the three monothe¬
istic religions, and al-Andalus, the province
where three cultures lived in peace.
The metaphor is unequivocal: by road comes
all that is new, all that is exchanged and that
changes us, all that transcends and transforms us;
THE UNESCO lOURIER [UNE 1097
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
I exico City's first printing
. press was set up in 1539. It Is
because of the road there is always a little of shown here ¡n a contemporary
someone else in us and any attempt to make engraving,
identity an isolate can never succeed. Such con¬
tacts are not, of course, necessarily pleasant or
peaceful: invaders, persecutors, prisoners and
deportees also arrive by road. But if movement
distorts or alters ideas, the opposite is also true:
conquerors assimilate the civilization of the
defeated and the victims of slavery fertilize the
cultures of the lands to which they are exiled.
And so, just as there arc memorable places
which symbolize the common past of com¬
munities, there are also memorable routes:
geographical itineraries where traces of phys¬
ical movement associated with mental change
have survived. As well as the chronological
mystery veiling the preservation from gener¬
ation to generation of beliefs, patterns of
thought, knowledge, references and other
forms of representation, there is the geo¬
graphical mystery associated with their move¬
ment, the movement of intangible things. The
question of time is connected with that of
geographical range. By following the tangible
traces of intellectual transmission or the routes
taken by groups of travellers we can learn more
about the spread of iron or paper technology,
of astronomy or the figure zero, of Buddhism
or Islam, a legend or a form of music. We can
also find out about what happened to them
during their journey.
All thinking about the origin of cultures,
their complexity, the dialogue between them,
and cultural intermingling raises very precise
questions. What kind of people travelled?
How long did it take to travel and at what
cost in terms of loss of human life? What lan¬
guages did they speak? What kind of archives
did they keep? What letters did they write?
What images did they carry ?
Tinker, tailor, soldier, sailor. . .
Some of the greatest travellers were soldiers.
War encourages technological invention and
stimulates mechanisms of transmission. As
the victors settle in new lands, some popula¬
tions arc put to flight and others arc deported.
War also causes the intermingling of peoples,
beliefs and knowledge. The conqueror is some¬
times the first to understand the value of new
information. Alexander the Great's troops
were accompanied by scientific expeditions.
The Umayyad armies brought paper-makers
back from Central Asia. Tamerlaine spared
from massacre the scholars, writers and artists
he wished to enroll in his service. If espionage
is considered as warfare waged by other means,
we are beholden to it for the spread of many
secrets in the field of technology (the most
famous being that of silk manufacture), car¬
tography and the sciences.
The routes taken by ideas also dovetail with
those taken by merchandise. The quest for
products yielding profits compensating for
the time and risks involved in travel to dis¬
tant parts has always been one of the main rea¬
sons for scattering to the ends of the earth
people who were interested in setting up net¬
works and organizing safe and frequent travel,
and were in many cases adept at writing and
curious about novelty.
Merchants do not seek to change the world
or to describe it, and what they say or sec is not
always recorded or broadcast, but they spread
ideas and information as a kind of by-product
of their travels. More specifically trade has indi¬
rectly been one of the great vectors of religion.
Getting together in foreign lands and practising
their faith, traders have often made converts.
Arab traders propagated the Qur'an farther
afield than any of the Arab conquests of the
first century of the Hegira. For reasons of secu¬
rity it was often wise for the preacher's itiner-
THE UNESCO lOURIER |UNEI907
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
ary to coincide with that taken by the merchant.
It is safer to travel with caravans or merchant
ships to cosmopolitan cities where the religious
message will get a better reception from an open-
minded public. This also explains why Bud¬
dhist monks also followed trade routes.
The universalist religions arc the third great
medium whereby ideas travel, in this case with
a deliberate purpose. Buddhism, Christianity
and Islam define the corpus of canonical texts,
the type of images and the kind of community
whereby the preachers of the faith should
spread salvation throughout the world. Such
questions foment doctrinal disputes and even
heresies. Should the Buddha's body be
depicted? Should the Prophet Muhammad be
painted? Should icons be allowed? Should the
Qur'an be translated or the Bible be propa¬
gated? Which Sutras belong to the accepted
canon? Who should interpret the word of the
Prophet? Should monks devote themselves
to their own personal nirvana or should they
be responsive to the concerns of laymen? To
what extent should Jesuits adapt the evangel¬
ical message to Chinese culture? The form
taken by a religious "idea" transposed thou¬
sands of kilometres results from the theoret¬
ical and practical answer to these questions.
Ideas are imported as well as exported. A
map of spiritual and intellectual poles of attrac¬
tion, starting with centres of pilgrimage, must
be overlaid on that of the propagation and
transformation of ideas. People from all over
the world meet and mix in Jerusalem, Mecca
and Santiago de Compostela. There, and on
much-used routes invested with a strong sym¬
bolic meaning, important cultural changes
come about. For centuries students converged
on the universities of Taxila, Bologna and the
Sorbonne. Sometimes the inclinations of a
prince or caliph attracted talented individu¬
als, gifted scientists or rare manuscripts. Those
who journeyed to the Library of Alexandria,
the "house of wisdom" in Baghdad, and the
court of Cordoba and the court of Roger II of
Sicily, were not seekers after salvation or the
fount of knowledge but bringers of ideas,
philosophers, physicians, astronomers and
translators who found material security and
intellectual stimulation.
What we see here is a complex set of phys¬
ical and mental barriers, topographical lines
of force and human strategics which decides
whether or not an idea crosses time and space,
whether a piece of writing produced in a par¬
ticular place and culture has an impact at the
other end of a continent. Was propagation
deliberate or accidental, due to expansion or
attraction? Did an idea travel from one place
to another slowly or as the result of a histor¬
ical cataclysm? Was its journey governed by
geographical constants or by the fortunes of
war, by the attraction of ancient crossroads
of civilization or by the discovery of a new
route? To understand where we have come
from, we still have far to go in retracing the
highways and byways of the past.
Ihe Mongol ruler Tahmaras,
the "fully armed", with an
Arab scribe. Detail of a
miniature from the Universal
History, a classic work by
Rashîd ad Dîn (1247-1318).
tt
THE UNESCO ^>URIER JUNE 1007 *
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
manuscripts on the move
BY GERALD MESSADIE
Manuscripts
travelled
adventurously
along the
information
highways of the
medieval world
The reproduction of the written word
began long before printing with mov¬
able type was invented in the middle
of the tenth century by the Chinese Pi
Sheng. By the end of the third millennium of
the pre-Christian era religious and political
documents were being copied on clay tablets
in the Near and Middle East. These copies were
made for the ruling castes, and it is unlikely
that they circulated beyond the borders of
the kingdoms where they were produced, for
they were of interest to few people. Later,
copies were also made of famous literary works
such as the ancient Mesopotamian epic of Gil-
gamesh, king of the city of Uruk. The story
of Gilgamcsh, who was deified and mythified
after his death in 2650 B.C., is both a found¬
ing myth and the celebration of a hero. The
cult of the hero was probably the reason why
poems such as the Iliad and the Mahabharata
were also copied several centuries later.
MProduction, collection
andpreservation
Fourteen sets of fragments of the Gilgamesh
Epic have been found between present-day
Turkey and Iraq. While language barriers do
not seem to have been real obstacles to the cir¬
culation of manuscripts, no proof has sur¬
vived to suggest that manuscripts crossed cul-
10 r
'* the unesco Courier iune 1997
I ravellers arriving in Beijing.
Miniature from a French
version (c. 1410) of The Travels
of Marco Polo.
tural frontiers. For instance, although Greek
was spoken throughout the Mediterranean
basin by the fourth century A.D., not a sin¬
gle fragment of the Iliad has been found either
in Palestine, Carthage or in major centres on
the Silk Route. The transport of a long piece
of writing recorded on clay tablets must have
been a laborious affair (the complete 3,000-
line version of the Gilgamesh epic would have
weighed several dozen kg). Even so, the spread
of papyrus and parchment, which consider¬
ably lightened this burden (a long poem could
have been recorded on a few volumina or
scrolls), only seems to have had a slight impact
on the communication of ideas and cultural
transfer.
Early in the first millennium of the Chris¬
tian era, literacy rates were still minimal in
most of the world. Written texts were
intended to be read in public, and this was
not to everyone's taste. In the second century,
for example, the Latin poet Juvenal com¬
plained that he had had to listen to readings of
many an indigestible tragedy.
Manuscripts were highly prized by certain
princes, who wished to accumulate as much
learning a magical commodity as possible
but were not very interested in transmitting it.
In the fourth century B.C. in Alexandria cus¬
toms officials seized all the books they found
on ships and had copies of them made for
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
restitution to their owners. The originals were
placed in the city's two great libraries, among
the most fabulous of the ancient world, whose
users were physicians looking for exotic reme¬
dies, navigators seeking maritime informa¬
tion, and minor poets on the lookout for
pieces of obscure knowledge or material to
plagiarize.
The first conclusion to be drawn is that
the spread of culture via manuscripts was neg¬
ligible until very late in Antiquity.
IApproval, condemnation
and destruction
Cultural barriers became slightly more per¬
meable with the coming of commercial pub¬
lishing in the strict sense, which was first prac¬
tised in Rome around the first century B.C.
Authors gave copyists the original version of
a piece of work so that several copies could be
made and offered to prospective buyers. These
copies on parchment were relatively costly,
and the copyist paid the author royalties based
on the number of copies sold or on his esti¬
mate of the value of the work. The pages of
parchment were covered with writing on both
sides and then sewn together to form what is
now called a codex, a book that was easy to
carry.
Copies of works by Aristotle began to be
found in Baghdad (where a Greek colony
prospered) and those of Tacitus in Britain.
But it would be an exaggeration to think that
this form of publishing had inaugurated the
free flow of ideas. The excesses of Imperial
Rome gave rise to many pamphlets that were
not to the liking of the emperors, and copy¬
ists who reproduced impertinent documents
did so at their own risk. The censor's hand
became particularly heavy after the reign of
Constantine the Great.
In the fifth century almost all the works of
the third-century philosopher Porphyry,
whose writings were likely "to rouse God's
anger", were destroyed. The works of the first-
century historians Seneca the Rhetorician,
Scrvilius Nonianus, Cluvius Rufus, Fabius
Rusticus, Aufidius Bassus and nearly all those
of Vclleius Paterculus, have also alarmingly
disappeared. There are excellent reasons to
believe that a large number of copies of the
work of Heraclitus, one of the greatest
thinkers of ancient Greece and perhaps of all
time, were in circulation until the second or
third centuries. All that has survived of them,
less than five pages of large print, has come
down to us indirectly in the form of quota¬
tions from authors in possession of complete
copies of a work that was probably also
destroyed.
Under the Christian Roman Empire,
Uetail of an Egyptian
papyrus manuscript from the
reign of Psamtlkl
(c. 663-609 B.C.).
monks soon became the only people licenced
to copy pieces of writing. They took advantage
of the situation and, following their superiors'
injunctions, obeyed their religious convic¬
tions. A monk named Xiphilin wrote, and of
course abridged, the only version that has
come down to us of Dio Cassius's history of
Rome, and Flavius Josephus's The Antiquities
of the Jews was "reworked" with the inter¬
polation of a passage on Jesus.
The second conclusion is that the more
ideas a work contained the smaller the likeli¬
hood that it would circulate untouched.
Manipulation, distortion
and invention
An additional peril to those of distortion and
censorship was that of manipulation by "well
intcntioned" copyists and the absurd mix-
ups due to the authors themselves. In the
reports despatched by Megasthenes, the Greek
ambassador to the court of Candragupta Mau-
rya in the fourth century B.C., it is impossi¬
ble to distinguish what is really Hindu from
what merely reflects the author's determination
to "Hellcnizc" his observations, as when he
purports to identify Dionysus and Hercules
among the Hindu gods.
»«e.
/ittiïftrtjr.'its1-1*3:1 fofa
ÏZb'K.iie^tA^áJuJlrfawh&*¿¿fC>j
THE UNESCO ^)URIIER JUNE 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Very few authors, even including the great¬
est writers of Antiquity, escaped the indig¬
nity of forgery. In those days people did not
know how to distinguish the authentic from
the false on the basis of style, writing or the
material used. Even today we do not know
for sure which texts were authentically and
entirely written by Plato, although some such
as the Second Alcibiades, the Theages and the
Axiochos are unanimously recognized to be
fakes. The First Alcibiades itself, with the sur¬
prising interruption by Zarathustra, is "dubi¬
ous". It is now accepted that Aristotle never
wrote the book on the Wise Men that was
long attributed to him.
The Italian historian Arnaldo Momigliano
believed that most Greek and Latin texts pur¬
porting to be translations of oriental originals
dealing with such figures as Zarathustra, Thoth
and Ilystaspe are pu re fabrications. Despite their
immense talents, the Greeks were not gifted
linguists. They garbled Persian and made a hash
of Hebrew, and all Egyptologists know that the
Greek texts purporting to be reproductions
of originals of the cult of Isis are embellish¬
ments that bear little relationship to the orig¬
inal. Plotinus asked Porphyry to unmask the
forger who had produced an Apocalypse of
Zarathustra, and as early as the third century
B.C., clever swindlers tried to sell "Aristotle's
real library" to Ptolemy III Eurcgetcs.
It was just as true in the past as it is today
that the most far-fetched stories the ones
that appealed to the simple stood the best
chance of survival. Herodotus (circa 480-425
B.C.) was taken in by the confabulations of
i doctor examines a urine
sample, following precepts
laid down by the great Persian
physician, alchemist and
philosopher Rhazès (9th-10th
century). Detail from a French
14th-century manuscript.
I he great library at
Alexandria (Egypt). The most
famous library of Antiquity, it
may have contained as many
as 700,000 volumes. Late
19th-century Hungarian
engraving.
Aristcas of Proconnesus (circa 550 B.C.) who
"described" the griffins, bird-men and giant
ants that were to be found in Asia. Giving cre¬
dence to the writings of the man Cicero had
dubbed "the father of history", Alexander the
Great believed that the Nile was a tributary
of the Indus. Seventeen centuries later Marco
Polo gave a description of China in his Book
of Travels that was invented from start to fin¬
ish and contained no mention of the existence
of paper, tea, the Great Wall, printing, bank¬
notes, ice-cream, none of which were known
in the West. Yet this far-fetched account
enjoyed a huge success. Of the versions pro¬
duced at the time 143 have survived, and there
must have been hundreds more!
The ideas and information that travelled
with manuscripts were clearly often at second
or even third hand. Accounts of the Far or Mid¬
dle East that reached the Greeks were often
confabulations, and so were many of the man¬
uscripts they wrote about them. More recently,
manuscripts about the New World especially
Spanish and Portuguese were also largely unre¬
liable, and the continent they described was
presented to Europeans as a land of fantasy.
The third conclusion to be drawn is that
false ideas circulate far more easily than true
ones.
Translation, utilization,
rediscovery
The Western tradition which holds that "the
Arabs" saved the Greek cultural heritage
should not be accepted without qualification,
true though it is that Arabs translated almost
all Aristotle and Plato, and Neo-Platonists
like Plotinus, Ptolemy and Euclid. It does
mean, however, that manuscripts of these texts
already existed. Furthermore, the term "Arab"
is very loosely used in this context since the
translators concerned included Turks, Per¬
sians, Mesopotamians from Baghdad, Jews
and converted Christians. Nor do the transla¬
tions seem always to have been masterpieces of
precision; some of the "free" interpretations
they contain are bewildering. The ideas they
conveyed to readers could often be quite dif¬
ferent from those in the original texts.
The greatest paradox is that manuscripts
circulated when the Islamic empires were at the
height of their power and in a totally different
way from that which is generally accepted. It
was through Latin and Hebrew translations of
Averroës's commentaries on Aristotle that
many Western Christian thinkers, including
Roger Bacon and Duns Scotus, first came to
know about Aristotle's ideas. Avcrroism nour¬
ished Christian philosophy and theology until
Thomas Aquinas launched his great diatribe
against the Parisian Avcrroists in 1274.
12
THE UNESCO IpUMtR JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The most famous manuscripts in the mod¬
ern world are the Dead Sea Scrolls. One of
their special features is that they never reached
their destination. Discovered by chance in the
twentieth century, some twenty-two centuries
after they were written, they raise a question
which is seldom mentioned but is nevertheless
central to the transmission of ideas via manu¬
scripts: who were they intended for? Were
these monks from Qumrân on the shore of
the Dead Sea, known as "Esscncs", who inde-
fatigably covered parchment rolls with copies
(often considerably modified) of whole books
of the Old Testament, working for them¬
selves, or were their copies meant for other
communities? And if so, which ones? What
originals did they use? It is very likely that
other manuscripts of the same type are await¬
ing discovery like the fragments discovered
in 1884 in Jerusalem which were rejected as
fakes through the obstinacy of a French
palaeographer and now seem to have been lost
forever.
Incidentally, one might also wonder what
happened to the hand-written scrolls that
Buddhist monks carried for centuries along
the Silk Route. There were hundreds of these
monks, and each one travelled with about fif¬
teen scrolls as his sole luggage. This adds up to
a large number of lost scrolls	
A fourth conclusion may be drawn,
namely that manuscripts circulated more eas¬
ily between cultures that were politically close
and were preserved with greater security in
those circumstances.
The men of letters of the young Islamic
empire were interested in the Greek and Latin
learning which had fostered the Byzantine
empire they were in the process of devouring,
and educated Christians were interested in the
learning of the Muslims who were threatening
them. And if we still have Latin rather than
Greek writings about the Celts, we should
probably be grateful to imperial administra¬
tors who were sufficiently interested in the
description of foreign peoples to have their
manuscripts copied in large numbers, thereby
increasing their chances of survival.
An appendix may be added to the fourth
conclusion: manuscripts have a far better
chance of surviving if they serve political and
ideological ends.
Quintactas
M Printing, diffusion
andprohibition
Printing seems to have decisively changed the
situation for manuscripts. By producing hun¬
dreds of copies of a text, the printing press
made it more likely that at least a few would
survive. In principle this was true except that
censorship of manuscripts intensified for an
4.TX ilni>iiio
couenet
tont) au
rúisq:
2&08qi
frnftnri
effe cfcfi
62
tú in co
i btblu
fuitCvti
pttrcgi
pcrttoe
nebant
ri Ubî(
rû nlcjfc I
n intent ¡
tú id c |
edftue!
diöfcö {
etíjmí I
fedcenJ
¿¡in hum mm.inimhitTn s
BlI urning books. Engraving
from Hartmann Schedel's
"Universal Chronicle", also
known as the Nuremberg
Chronicle (1493).
obvious reason, to stop them reaching the
printer. Having to destroy all the printed
copies and making possession of any surviv¬
ing copies a crime made the task of the thought
police much more complicated.
One of the most striking examples of this
kind of censorship is to be seen in the tribu¬
lations of a manuscript written in the seven¬
teenth century, which was copied by hand and
circulated throughout Europe until 1690
before being published anonymously in 1719,
probably in Holland. This printed edition
was seized and destroyed. Only three copies
have survived and are today conserved at the
universities of Leyden, Góttingen and Cornell
respectively. A replica was published in 1994 in
Italy by Einaudi, 275 years later. This work
by an unknown author, the Treatise of the
Three Impostors, or the Mind ofMr. Spinoza,
boldly claimed that the three monotheistic
religions were of human, not divine, inspira¬
tion. Many other manuscripts, old and new,
arc still sleeping in secret archives and inacces¬
sible libraries.
I will end this article with a fifth conclu¬
sion, namely that the most threatened manu¬
scripts are those that arc richest in ideas. I
THE UNESCO lOURIER |UNE 199/
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
^ mi M.ittuuin.'ii i
MP 'JV< Hi' /.It/ ¡
.¡ut.Cms)fi uni/..I r,fll,') ! mi ( '.i/',iiti,f./ut m Iil4,itte¡wilt ,1'm,-) un M.initnnJ mm ivtui en Con.mne(,Cnu- \
mrpnrmmmmA >». ) < «« Mk '.¡m <« mmwmw[mm\&mo.)i un rnU Mmm»mmm+.(m»)M w/^/mv ,/u, »¿/. 4/mu-m«**.
nuit.-.t.iiUfWi.; OanOM ,'fu/ml ,(W )a un /f.,/n*/flViu- mi ,.<v/ t'/mr.Crm- )i t un J'riH/ir .mm < Uii-i. > .l/
,: ,h,.)u mr,WmmÈim mm»fmiUmKflm)d m fnr/títnú \*iitv a	 .m,n.i, ,v.,, <:
.-. il ( Vme. C hi. ) M m»0Êm^jfmmHmm;ûmr) ip u» Eii>/«r,iM<¿t à ¡'Kinde Cr.tí),o un ' Till (fill ./> ù,.u.:;i ., ,, /,
V
fe
4/
Rumour, gossip and seditious songs fed the underground media
thatflourished in the reign ofLouis XV
Best-sellers and gossip-mongers
in 18th-century France
BY ROBERT DARNTON
Mbove, Parisian newshawks
at their usual meeting point, a
tree In the gardens of the
Palais-Royal, around 1750. By
gathering news and spreading
it orally, they were Important
links in the information chain
of 18th-century France.
T't would be a mistake to think that the
England of Samuel Johnson, the France
I of Diderot and the Germany of Goethe
"formed part of a media-free civilization.
Their world buzzed with a communication
network every bit as dense as ours. It was
merely different so different that most of
its media have been forgotten. Take the case
of eighteenth-century Paris. Who today can
even recognize the names of the genres and
modes of its communication system: mau
vais propos (saucy gossip), bruit public (pub¬
lic rumour), on-dit (rumour), pasquinade
(scurrilous pamphlet), canard (tall story),
feuille volante (scandal sheet), factum (squib),
libelle (lampoon) and chronique scandaleuse
(muck-raking history) ?
There were so many modes of communi¬
cation, and they intersected and overlapped
so intensively, that one can hardly picture their
operation. Let me give as an example an anec¬
dote which might be likened to a modern
14
THE UNESCO V^OURIER |UNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
"news flash". It was incorporated in a best-
selling biography of Mme. Du Barry, the mis¬
tress of Louis XV:
"There is a report, carefully spread about
by some courtiers, which proves that Mme
du Barry has not lost any favour or familiar¬
ity with the king, as some had suspected. His
Majesty likes to brew his own coffee and, by
means of this innocent amusement, to get
some relief from the heavy burdens of gov¬
ernment. A few days ago, the coffee pot began
to boil over while His Majesty was distracted
by something else. 'Hey, France!' called out
the beautiful favourite, 'Look out! Your cof¬
fee's going to pot!' We are told that 'France' is
the familiar expression utilized by this lady in
the intimacy of the petits appartements. The
details should never circulate outside of them,
but they escape, nonetheless, thanks to the
malignity of the courtiers."
The anecdote is trivial in itself, but it illus¬
trates the way a news item moved through
various media, reaching an ever-wider public.
In this case, it went through four phases: it
began as a mauvais propos, or insider gossip
at court. Then it took the form of a bruitpub¬
lic, or general rumour, in Paris. Next it was
consigned to writing in a manuscript news
sheet, or gazette à la main. And finally it fig¬
ured as an episode in a libelle, that is, a printed
book which belonged to a genre of scandalous
and highly illegal political literature.
M Forbidden best-sellers
In my own research, I have tried to identify the
forbidden books that were most in demand
during the twenty years before the French
Revolution. By studying orders of book¬
sellers and other sources, I have come up with
a retrospective best-seller list, the top fifteen of
the 720 works that composed the highly pop¬
ular corpus of literature which circulated
beyond the reach of the censors and the police.
The list contains some well-known works by
famous writers like Voltaire, the Abbé Raynal
and the Baron d'Holbach. But five of the top
fifteen best-sellers were libelles Wkc Anecdotes
sur Mme la comtesse Du Barry, quoted above,
or chroniques scandaleuses, a variety of muck¬
raking contemporary history. Although they
reached readers in every corner of the king¬
dom, all five have been completely forgotten,
like their authors, who have disappeared fro m
the history of literature.
How can we assess the impact of these
books on public opinion?
Thanks to advances in the new discipline
known as the history of the book, we have a
Exchanging information at
the Café de la Régence in
Paris, around 1750. Many
Intellectuals frequented this
café on the Place du Palais-
Royal. Contemporary drawing
by an unknown artist.
pretty good idea of how the printed word
became a force in European history; but we
know very little about oral modes of com¬
munication. They could have been more
important than the print media in societies
with a high rate of illiteracy, but their effec¬
tiveness is difficult to gauge because the spo¬
ken word generally vanished into the air.
In the case of eighteenth-century Paris, how¬
ever, oral communication about public affairs
was followed carefully by the police, who
posted spies in cafes, taverns, public gardens
and all the nerve centres for the spread of infor¬
mation. Spy reports cannot be taken literally, of
course, but they reveal a great deal about the
general tone and the modes of transmission in
oral communication. By way of illustration, I
will discuss two modes: gossip and songs.
IA hotbed ofgossip
Gossip provided the most important source
of news for Parisians under the Old Regime,
because newspapers did not exist. True, there
were many periodicals, and some of them con¬
tained articles about court ceremonies and for¬
eign affairs. But papers with news in them,
news as we know it information about
power struggles and personalities in the pub¬
lic sphere did not appear until the press was
freed of censorship in 1789.
If you wanted to know what was happen¬
ing in the corridors of power before 1 789, you
used your feet and your ears. You went to cer¬
tain cafés, certain benches in the Luxembourg
Gardens, a certain terrace in the Tuileries Gar¬
dens or the Tree of Cracow; and you listened to
the nouvellistes de bouche or newsmongers
who gathered at those centres of gossip. The
Tree of Cracow was an actual tree in the garden
I& -
-/
È
-4 ip?ii (fjsa
I;
iter
i3^:1 il
y^
3 G""THE UNESCO lOURIER |UNE 100/
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
of the Palais-Royal, which served as a meeting
place for those who wanted to know who was
winning in the War of the Polish Succession
from 1733 to 1735. During the next decades, it
became such an important institution that
ambassadors sent their servants to pick up news
items or to plant them, for gossip became
public opinion and public opinion became a
force to be reckoned with under Louis XV.
The regime acknowledged this new form of
power by placing spies wherever bruitspublics
(public rumour) or mauvais propos (bad talk)
were likely to break out. I have found spy
reports on conversations in forty cafés around
1730. Some are even written in dialogue:
"At the Café de Foy someone said that the
king had taken a mistress, that she was named
Gontaut, and that she was a beautiful woman,
the niece of the Duc dc Noailles and the
Comtesse de Toulouse. Others said, 'If so, then
there could be some big changes.' And another
replied, 'True, a rumour is spreading, but I find
it hard to believe, since the Cardinal dc Fleury
is in charge. I don't think the king has any incli¬
nation in that direction, because he has always
been kept away from women.' 'Nevertheless,'
someone else said, 'it wouldn't be the greatest
M late-18th-century
illustrated edition of
Malbrough s'en va-t-en-guerre,
a French song that was highly
popular at that time.
MORT ET COI\ VOI UE
L'INVINCIBLE MAÁBROí/K
L'a jaitir í
I*.*. trt-.Jium
î. ^l|)|im r , r »ÇV rr Wb...'» «T IfQ. lliMB^Q f^WT In Arm* ÍW* I V«*J .Hftl »T
. .- fax . »:-«-v, fc .- . ,-.-. >*vrr- .1 Í.-" »" . VI «*J p.l*M IJW *
nk*. il%»i«. i.. kMj>^.- ïêqtmm ' i . *fr*r7t m A tu^i , ir.1 ri r.' -Mi
M I Il - ^r ^~
evil if he had a mistress.' 'Well, messieurs,'
another added, 'it may not be a passing fancy,
and a first love could raise some danger on the
sexual side and could cause more harm than
good. It would be far more desirable if he liked
hunting better than that kind of thing.' "
As always, the royal sex life provided
plenty of material for gossip, but the reports
indicate that the talk tended to be friendly. In
1729, when the queen was about to give birth,
the cafés rang with jubilation:
"Truly, everyone is delighted, because they
all hope greatly to have a dauphin. . . . One of
them said, 'Parbleu, messieurs, if God graces
us with a dauphin, you will see Paris and the
whole river aflame [with fireworks in celebra¬
tion].' Everyone is praying for that." '
Twenty years later, the tone had changed
completely:
"In the shop of the wigmaker Gaujoux,
this individual [Jules Alexis Bernard] read
aloud ... an attack on the king in which it was
said that His Majesty let himself be governed by
ignorant and incompetent ministers and had
made a shameful, dishonourable peace [the
Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle, 1748], which gave
up all the fortresses that had been captured ... ;
that the king, by his affair with the three sisters,
scandalized his people and would bring down
all sorts of misfortune on himself if he did
not change his ways; that His Majesty scorned
the queen and was an adulterer; that he had
not confessed for Easter communion and
would bring down the curse of God upon
the kingdom and that France would be over¬
whelmed with disasters	 He promised Sieur
Duzemard that he would show him the book
entitled The Three Sisters."
I Seditious songs
During the twenty years that separate those
reports, a great deal had happened to damage
the Parisians' fondness for their king, and a great
deal more would happen between 1750 and 1789.
In his manuscript memoirs, the head of the Paris
police, Jcan-Charles-Pierre Lenoir, wrote that
he had to pay the crowd to shout "Vive la reine!"
when Marie-Antoinette, Louis XVI's queen,
rode through the streets in the 1780s, but his
efforts produced "only some scattered applause,
which everyone knew to be bought". It seems
clear that public opinion had shifted and that the
shift had involved an interpénétration of writ¬
ten and oral modes of communication.
Parisians did not merely talk; they also
sang. Songs were mnemonic devices and pow¬
erful vehicles for spreading messages, like com¬
mercial jingles today. People commonly com-
16 E UNESCO ^pUKILR JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
posed verse about current events and set it to
popular tunes, such as "The Bear Went Over
the Mountain" (" Malbrough s'en va-t-en
guerre" in French). The greatest songster of
the century, Charles Simon Favart, learned to
put words to tunes while rhythmically knead¬
ing dough in his father's bakery. Many oth¬
ers Collé, Gallet, Panard, Vadé, Taconnct,
Fromaget, Fagan also came from the artisan
classes. Their songs penetrated workshops and
taverns throughout the city, and street singers
accompanied by hurdy-gurdies relayed them
from corner to corner. Paris was suffused with
songs, many of them political. As the saying
went, government in France was "an absolute
monarchy tempered by songs".
When a hit song attacked the king and his
ministers, it was a serious affair. In 1749 the
police received an order to capture the author
of a song about the fall of the first Maurcpas
ministry. They had only one clue: it began
with the words, "People once so proud, now
so servile. . . ." But that was enough for them
to set their spies to work in taverns and cafés;
and before long one of their agents heard the
verse declaimed by a medical student named
François Bonis.
He was hustled off to the Bastille and asked
where he had got the verse. He had copied it,
he said, from a sheet of paper that was passed
to him by a priest in the hospital. The priest
was arrested and said he had got it from
another priest, who in turn was arrested and
attributed it to a law student, who said it was
dictated to him in class by a professor, who
claimed he had heard it from a wit in a café . . .
and so on, until the police had filled the Bastille
with fourteen suspects.
group of "incredibles"
meet in a Paris café. During
the early days of the Directory
(1795-1799) the incredibles
were fashionable young
royalists noted for their
mannered elegance. Engraving
made in 1797.
They never found the original author. In
fact there may have been no distinct author
at all, because it was a case of collective cre¬
ativity: people changed phrases and added
verses as songs made the rounds. And while the
police tried to follow the song to its origin,
they discovered that its path crossed those of
six other songs, each more seditious than the
last and each with its own chain of transmis¬
sion. Their words were memorized, declaimed,
read and sung. They circulated on scraps of
paper hidden in pockets and sleeves, and they
were printed in several chroniques scandaleuses,
which spread them to the farthest corners of
the kingdom.
Two lessons stand out from the cases I have
mentioned.
First, it makes no sense to separate elite
"print culture" from oral "popular culture",
because messages spread through different
modes of communication, which intersected
and overlapped among all segments of the
population. The media were mixed; they
reached a mixed audience, and so the history of
books should be studied as one ingredient in
the general history of communication.
Second, best-sellers, gossip and songs may
not provide an accurate version of events, but
they show how events appeared in the domi¬
nant media of the time. In the case of eigh¬
teenth-century France, I would go so far as
to claim they constituted a coherent account
of contemporary history, the only one, in
fact, that was available to eighteenth-century
Frenchmen, because publications about the
recent past and current events were not allowed
to circulate in the legal book trade. Illegally
circulated publications, in the form oí libelles
and chroniques scandaleuses, reduced the story
of public affairs during the reign of Louis XV
to a kind of folklore organized around two
master themes: despotism and decadence.
We know now that the folklore version of
the Old Regime was wrong. Mme Du Barry
had indeed spent some time as a prostitute
before her promotion to the royal bed, as the
libelles claimed, but Louis XV was no despot.
And when the Bastille was stormed on 14 July
1789, it contained only seven prisoners, most
of them incarcerated for immoral behaviour at
the request of their families. But the French
saw the Bastille as the embodiment of despo¬
tism. They experienced the events of the 1780s
as variations on the themes that permeated
their gossip, songs and books. They perceived
the collapse of the Old Regime from the per¬
spective of a political folklore that had been
spread far and wide by the dominant media of
their time.
THE UNESCO tOUKIER JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Words have no legs, £
yet they walk'
YOUSSOUF TATA CISSÉ
talks to Jasmina Sopova
Africa's continent-wide lines ofcommunication
based on respect for the spoken word
In traditional African societies
knowledge was transmitted orally. Did
this restrict the spread of ideas?
Youssouf Tata Cissé: Not at all. In Africa
ideas travelled with people. Human migra¬
tions, initiatory journeys, conquests and trade
routes made pathways along which ideas criss¬
crossed the continent.
Since ancient times Africans have moved
about and carried with them knowledge, tech¬
nology, beliefs, traditions and languages. What
other explanation can there be for the fact that
one finds the same ideograms tattood on the
bodies of Moroccan women and depicted in
the statuary of the Bambara and Malinke peo¬
ples of west Africa? How can you explain the
existence of the same place names, the same
divinities, the same rites and the same musical
instruments in the Nile Valley and in west
Africa? Comparative studies on the affinities
between pharaonic Egyptian and certain
African languages by the noted Senegalese
writer and Egyptologist Cheikh Anta Diop,
and his research on the migrations of peoples,
based on purely linguistic data, say a lot about
this flow of ideas in Africa.
The Nile Valley is often mentioned in the
oral traditions of the Soninke and Malinke,
who regard it as the original homeland of their
ancestors. Intrigued by this, I carried out
research into place names and ethnic names
and found nearly 400 names in Egypt, Sudan
and Ethiopia that also existed in west Africa.
Here are a few examples: EI Kantara in Egypt,
and Kantara, a Soninke clan name and fore¬
name; Segala, the name of an island in the Red
Sea and of several villages in Mali and Côte
d'Ivoire; Dakar in Ethiopia and Dakar, the
capital of Senegal. Moreover the oldest divini¬
ties of Pharaonic Egypt Bes, the oryx, the
vulture, the ibis, the falcon and the sphinx
are still celebrated in Mali where they have
their masks and statuettes.
The absence of writing was no obstacle to
the spread of knowledge. The cult of the spo¬
ken word in Africa meant that speech was an
important channel for the communication of
knowledge and ideas. That is why Mali's Bam¬
bara people say, "words have no legs, yet they
walk." Nothing can stop them.
18
the unesco Courier june i9*>7
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
What role have initiatory journeys
played in the spread of ideas?
Y. T. C: Initiation is much more than a hand¬
ful of "exotic" rites. It is a general education
that begins at six years of age and ends at
around thirty-three. Traditionally, it was car¬
ried out by six societies to which initiates
belonged one after the other, depending on
their age and the knowledge they had acquired.
They learned everything: history, the origins
of peoples, languages, mathematics, technol¬
ogy, morality and the secrets of nature and
the universe. During this process of learning
about life, young initiates were supposed to
travel, and they went to foreign lands with
their teachers, musicians, dancers and crafts¬
men. They lodged with local people and dis¬
covered new ways of life, new crafts and new
languages. In turn, they put on shows in which
griot in Casamance
(Senegal).
they demonstrated their own knowledge.
Enrichment was mutual. Only when they had
learned three languages did they return home.
This indicates the importance attached to
knowledge and respect for others. Nowadays
these initiatory journeys occur during the dry
season, but in the past they lasted seven years.
What influence was exercised by the
griots (story-tellers and masters of
ceremonies) and the donikeba
(teachers)?
Y. T. C: Doni in Bambara means "knowledge",
and the donikeba are "makers of knowledge".
We also have doma, or "knowers", and soma,
or "priests". These masters have an extraordi¬
nary memory, and are the guardians and prop¬
agators of tradition. In the past their social
status was so high that they enjoyed diplo¬
matic immunity in wartime.
Masters of the spoken word that they were,
griots acted as negotiators and ambassadors in
times of conflict, as did smiths, wood-cutters
and hunters, who were reputed for their man¬
ual dexterity and their knowledge. As musi¬
cians, poets, genealogists and historians, they
also played a considerable role in the spread of
ideas. Through a visualization technique
enabling them to put a face to every name, these
"troubadours" knew by heart the complete
genealogy of the family to which they were
attached, as well as the great deeds performed by
its ancestors. Some knew, and still know, the
history of a whole ethnic group or of an entire
kingdom. The history of Mali has been
recorded in verse and set to music. For a month
every year the griots of Kela, for example, recite
it all through the nights of Thursday to Friday,
Saturday to Sunday and Sunday to Monday,
100 hours in all.
Griots are also great travellers. They have to
visit various masters for periods of training
during which they increase their knowledge
while also spreading it.
To give you some idea of the distances they
can cover, let me cite a relatively recent exam¬
ple. In 1946, at the end of the Second World
War, griots left Bamako and went on foot via
Niamey to Agadez in Niger in other words
a distance of 4,000 kilometres to sing the
praises of the RDA (the Rassemblement
Démocratique Africain, a west African polit¬
ical movement), the triumph of General de
Gaulle, the abolition of forced labour, and
the forty-four-hour working week	 In this
3 (pUthe unesco Courier iune 1997
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
way political ideas spread through songs sung
by illiterate griots.
You also mentioned that ideas spread
as a result of conquest.
Y. T. C: Yes, because when warriors set out
to conquer new territory, they were accom¬
panied by religious leaders, masters of initia¬
tion, griots and smiths. All the corporations
of craftsmen the main repositories of tradi¬
tion were among their retinue. They took
with them their raiment, ornaments and jew¬
elry. They exchanged their knowledge with
that of the peoples whose land they occupied.
New civilizations were born as the result of
these encounters.
In peacetime ideas circulated as a result of
the formal relations between different cultural
and religious communities. Take the case of
Mansa Musa I, whç ruled the Mali empire
between 1307 and 1337. It is said that when he
made the pilgrimage to Mecca his escort con¬
sisted of 60,000 porters, 10,000 subjects and
500 servants. His wealth and generosity dur¬
ing his stay in Cairo were noted not only by the
Egyptians but also by Italians, Portuguese and
North Africans. In this way new doors were
opened for trade and cultural exchanges.
How did Islam reach Mali and what
contribution has it made?
Y. T. C: Mali is among the foremost Islamic
countries of west Africa. According to Soninke
oral tradition Islam was introduced around
666 by the envoys of Ocba Ben Nafi, a leading
figure in the expansion of Islam in Egypt and
North Africa. After laying the foundations
of the al-Qayrawan mosque in Tunisia, he is
said to have sent a delegation to the capital of
Wagadu (present-day Ghana) to ask Kaya
Maghan, the emperor, to convert to Islam.
The emperor rejected the proposal, but
allowed his subjects, especially those doing
business with Turkey (trade in diamonds,
eunuchs and slaves) to embrace the new reli¬
gion. The first converts were the Soninke.
The Qur'an was immediately translated,
with a commentary, first into Soninke then
into the country's other languages, so that
people could learn to recite the Qur'an by
heart and absorb Islamic dogma without
knowing Arabic. This is still done today. In
uring a ceremony in the
forest near Abidjan (Côte
d'Ivoire) a message is sent by
drum to announce the arrival
of masked dancers.
2C
THE UNESCO Courier i
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
other words, Islam has been integrated into
traditional societies without destroying tra¬
ditional cultures and languages.
Traditional art was also incorporated into
embryonic Islamic architecture. Architects
adapted old patterns of worship to the new
religion and built mosques in a unique style
known as "Sudanese", using banco compacted
earth reinforced with an exposed timber frame¬
work. One of the oldest mosques is in
Tombouctou. It was designed by an architect
named Ishaq el-Tuwedjin, whom Mansa Musa
had met in Cairo during his pilgrimage to Mecca.
The mosque at Djenné is by far the most beau¬
tiful. Built in 1907 and patterned on the early
religious buildings of the Ghana empire, it too
is typical of the Sudanese style widespread in
eastern Senegal, Ghana and Nigeria all the
countries visited by the Sudanese builders.
The egg-shaped dome added to the top of
minarets is another example of Sudanese syn¬
cretism. Bambara cosmogony holds that the
first thing the Supreme Being created was a
wondrous egg, Fan, consisting of nine com¬
partments into which He inserted the nine
basic states of existence. And so the egg-shaped
dome is a symbol of the traditional religion
grafted onto a Muslim place of worship.
The pattern marked on the ground in hop¬
scotch, a game played by children the world
over, is also divided into nine sections. I think
that the role of games in the transfer of ideas
should not be neglected, not only in Africa but
worldwide. And games mean music and song.
To get back to architecture, I would add that
during the colonial period a fusion took place
between the traditional style and the European
style, leading to what has been called "colonial
architecture". It is mainly found in administra¬
tive buildings, markets and post offices in Mali,
Mauritania, Burkina Faso and Niger.
Did colonization open new routes for
the movement of ideas in Africa?
Y. T. C: Colonization brought a break in con¬
tinuity. All aspects of traditional society were
disrupted. The setting up of French schools
and the use of French as the official language
disturbed the system of traditional teaching.
Only the Qur'anic schools continued to func¬
tion. All the traditional structures were shat¬
tered. Religious leaders became suspect. Reli¬
gious rites and objects were labelled as satanic.
The established channels for transmitting
knowledge and ideas were blocked. The use of
Toung Senufo adults return
to their village after their
Initiation Into the rules of life
in society (Côte d'Ivoire). Their
outfit is a sign of their new
status.
so-called "talking" or "messenger" drums was
strictly forbidden.
Why?
Y. T. C: Because the colonizers realized that
the beating of drums signalled that an upris¬
ing was afoot. The language of the drums
announced the arrival of the colonial army A
message could travel 500 kilometres in a single
night. In 1916, for example, during the Bobo
uprising in Mali, the drums carried the message
as far as Burkina. They said, "Warrior, take up
your quiver, don't forget your bow; even
struck down by the enemy, we must fight."
Who could understand these messages?
Y. T. C: Everyone. All initiates understand
the language of the drums. Youth societies,
initiatory societies, the griots they all have
their drums and other musical instruments.
Obviously there are secret codes that only the
initiates know. They arc the equivalent of mil¬
itary secrets in modern societies.
In 1 965, when I arrived in a Senufo village in
Mali, a rapid musical portrait was made of me,
so that the drums and balafons could announce
my arrival. Apparently they described my phys¬
ical and moral character. It was an impressive
performance.
3 (ouiTHE UNESCO t URIER ]UNE 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The mixed signals of globalization
BY SALAH GUEMRICHE Ahardlookatthe impact ofsatellite
communication on the South
Mbove, spreading
the news in the traditional way
(Fez, Morocco).
nee upon a time ideas circulated on
| foot, as part of people's baggage.
Later, the invention of writing and
the spread of literacy transformed
the very nature of human relationships, per¬
ceptions and knowledge of the world. Today
ideas spread largely via radio and television.
The increase in the number of data banks and
the global reach of the Internet are bound to
multiply and diversify modes of access to
information.
The abolition of frontiers and the advent
of the "global village" through the spread of
audiovisual communication, which was no
more than a Utopian dream in the 1960s, is
now on the way to becoming a reality. But is
not this vision, which underlay the theories of
the Canadian sociologist Marshall McLuhan,
the same as that which today provides the ide¬
ological basis of "globalization"?
In the 1 980s a broad consensus crystallized
around the bold ideas advanced in France by
Jean-Jacques Servan-Schreiber, who was con¬
vinced that technology was going to "take us
from the neolithic age to the post-industrial
age". In the post-independence ferment the
developing countries systematically opted for
massive technological investment in institu¬
tional communications, and decision-makers
in the West believed that the "working masses"
could be made technology-minded by decree,
like people treated in a vaccination campaign.
After having to compete with the wireless
and the transistor, then being sidelined by
THE UNESCO {^OURIER |UNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
television, traditional communication by
word of mouth was pilloried as a symptom of
underdevelopment and scornfully treated by
the written press. The fact is that this versatile,
time-honoured way of spreading informa¬
tion spells danger to any established order.
Immune to the cold rationalism of media sys¬
tems, the spoken word is a versatile and
uncheckablc way of transmitting subversive
ideas. It is also a means whereby society can
restructure itself.
In societies with an oral tradition, com¬
munication based on the primacy of words
over all other forms of representation is one of
the basic ingredients of popular culture. Radio
benefitted from this status and gradually
became accepted because the spoken word
broadcast by radio nurtures the oral tradi¬
tion when it does not compete with it
rather than denying or trivializing it. But the
basic effect of television is to trivialize. This
inclines us to believe that, unlike the televi¬
sion viewers of the industrialized societies
studied by McLuhan, viewers who are heirs to
an oral tradition will be unsatisfied rather than
fascinated by the TV image. They will miss
the way in which the spoken word alone was
once used to conjure up form, image and
colour. The televised image dispossesses the
spoken word of its descriptive powers.
Today every household in the world is
within reach of a satellite. Some developing
countries even have their own satellites, not as
instruments of emancipation but as adjuncts
of sovereignty, a means of monitoring ideas
that come from elsewhere.
M carpet designer in
Turkmenistan works on a
computerized pattern.
M cybercafé In Cape Town
(South Africa).
I Interference or competition?
The development of media networks, the pur¬
chase of parabolic dishes and the lure of
escapism combine to entice people who are
tired of unimaginative programmes produced
in their own countries to tunc in to more sen¬
sational programmes beamed from elsewhere.
Images created in the North often represent
values contrary to those of the people in the
South, and present characters, situations and
living conditions that are light years away fro m
their experience. Nonetheless a wide range of
audiences all over the world are swayed by the
adventures of the same heroes of the same tele¬
vision series. The only possible explanation for
this is the fact that these shows arc considered
as consumer goods and awaited and received
as such.
It is sometimes said that young people in
developing countries have more in common
with their Western counterparts than they do
with their own parents. Should we deduce fro m
this that we are heading towards a community
of references and ideas that transcend frontiers ?
To do so would be to forget the perverse effects
that are already beginning to appear. Is it not
more likely that the discrepancy between these
two modes of representation will sow dishar¬
mony and, eventually, schizophrenia and other
forms of mental conflict?
It would nonetheless be too simplistic to
see this phenomenon as the only expression of
the North's hold on the South. In the 1980s
Third World experts urged developing coun¬
tries to co-operate among themselves, convinced
that this would provide "the miraculous solu¬
tion that would put an end to unequal exchanges
and enshrine the advent of truly democratic
international relations, i A survey we carried
out in 1984 on the Afro-Arab programme for
audiovisual co-operation revealed a tendency
among certain partners under the guise of fine-
sounding principles of solidarity to continue
the former relationship of domination for
^ which the former colonial power was criticized.
(oURIER JUNE 1997THE UNESCO {^OURIE |
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
But there is a big danger that the eternal
reflex that leads some to denounce interfer¬
ence by others in their internal affairs may
soon lose its familiar landmarks. As the South¬
ern countries themselves become producers
of communication technologies, the expan¬
sionism they complained of for so long will
gradually become interpénétration.
The drums ofcyberspace
The issues raised by the traditional media
focused on the abolition of political fron¬
tiers in the interests of further "integration".
The issues raised by Internet involve the abo¬
lition of ideological frontiers and the stan¬
dardization of behaviour and ideas. Nelson
Thall, a disciple of Marshall McLuhan,
believes that the Internet's unavowed design
is to get "the whole world to think and write
like North Americans'".
This is not integration but assimilation.
It is certainly not what most users expect. For
them the Internet is rather a means of
"improving the dialogue between countries
and between individuals spread around the
globe".2 They are not looking to the Net to
escape reality but for a reality that is likely to
improve their quality of life at work and play.
As we said above, ideas once travelled in
people's baggage. Today they travel predomi¬
nantly via the airwaves and new communica¬
tion technologies. What is carried by the air¬
waves, of course, are the values of the society
that produces them. Democracy is one of those
values. The noble paradox inherent in transna¬
tional flows that are hegemonistic by nature is
that they subliminally transmit, albeit
through an ideological filter, the message of
freedom and human rights. And people can
feel that they are citizens of the world when
they know often in "real time" what is
happening on the other side of the globe.
Since its massive penetration of the
remotest regions, television has gradually
opened people's eyes to their own living con¬
ditions by showing them those of other peo¬
ples around the world. This awareness always
disturbs governments. Much criticism can be
levelled at these airwaves beamed from else¬
where, but at least they have helped to sow
the seeds of democratic aspirations that cannot
be stifled. It remains to be seen what deposits
they will leave in the collective memory of
tomorrow.
1 In A. and M. Mattclart, X. Dclcourt, La culture contre
la democratic? L'audiovisuel à l'heure transnationale.
La Découverte publishers, Paris, 1983. See our
contribution to this work, pp. 96, 104.
2 In Etats de la Francophonie dans le monde 1995/1996,
Paris, Documentation française, 1997.
Wo' ord and ¡mage.
Bedouin in the desert (Syria).
THE UNESCO ÍOURIER (UNE 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Cyberspace a planetary network
of people and ideas
BYJ.C.NYÍRI
Mbove, a computer-generated
¡mage illustrating the
information superhighway, the
communication network
capable of channelling an
ultra high-speed global flow of
text, sounds and images.
Ideas travelled in the same way, and with
the same speed, as people until the 1840s,
when magnetic telegraphy was introduced.
By 1860 there were 51,500 km of telegraph
lines in the United States alone. A permanent
transatlantic telegraph line was installed in
1866, and by 1872 most of the major cities of
the globe were linked.
With the advent of telegraphy, the trans¬
mission of information became practically
instantaneous, but it also acquired a peculiarly
fragmented character. If information is to
count as knowledge, it has to relate to a con
text. For face-to-face communication such a
context is provided by the situation in which
it is embedded. With a written text, especially
with a printed book, the context for each par¬
ticular passage is given by the wider textual
environment, indeed by the entire book, or
often even by the library in which the book is
found. The mere physical characteristics of a
book, and of stacks of books in a library, cre¬
ate a context of temporality convey a sense of
the past. Modern historical consciousness
emerged from the printed text.
Lacking a wider written context, and
THE UNESCO ^HJRIER |UNE 1907 v
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
employing characteristically short sentences,
telegraphic style comes close to the style of spo¬
ken language. However, telegraphic messages are
not embedded in concrete speech situations.
With the telephone, the experience of a living
conversation is partly restored. Facial expres¬
sions, gestures and the impressions of physical
surroundings are not transmitted; but tone,
mood and pace certainly are. Questions can be
asked, a dialogue maintained. Knowledge gained
from a telephone conversation might be about
events far away, yet it is up to date, and can be
rather complete; but of course it lacks the log¬
ical coherence of written communication.
^Electronic broadcasting
In the 1920s radio broadcasting rapidly became
the dominant mode of news dissemination
and propaganda. This was a decisive transition
towards a new era of non-written communi¬
cation, a transition not without effect upon
twentieth-century philosophy, in particular
upon Heidegger's and Wittgenstein's views on I oung women listen to the
radio in a sanatorium near
Moscow, around 1930.
the nature of linguistic meaning and the cog¬
nitive role of the community.
Radio broadcasting might enhance a sense
of global connectedness; but it also fosters
randomness and evanescence, lessening the lis¬
teners' ability to form an ordered picture fro m
out of what they have heard. Similarly with
television, where even the apparently all-
encompassing diversity of information pro¬
vided by satellite broadcasting, information
both verbal and visual, from local gossip to
international news, results in a motley of views
and messages entirely disconnected.
Television, of course, relies fundamentally
on images. Now it is possible to conceive of a
logic of images as complementing verbal logic,
and indeed it is to be expected that the former
is going to play an increasingly important role
in interactive multimedia communication, the
great promise of computer networking. How¬
ever, it is fair to say that in television broad¬
casting, as we know it today, the employment
of images often subverts rather than ampli¬
fies rational thinking.
I The networked computer
Just a few years ago it would have still been
possible to make an analysis of the cognitive and
social effects of the spread of the personal com¬
puter without specifically referring to the role
of computer networking. Today such an analy¬
sis would seem unnatural. Computers are, char¬
acteristically, enmeshed in networks. As such
they are not just number-crunchers and word
processors, but also, perhaps even primarily,
nodes of communication. The networked com¬
puter is a tremendously powerful instrument
for bringing together scattered information
data, texts, images, increasingly also sound
from all over the world, and indeed for build¬
ing up out of that information new edifices of
knowledge. The computer enables one to study
reference material in a breadth hitherto incon¬
ceivable, and in a depth not practicable in the
conventional printed medium.
However, both the isolated computer and
the networked one possess features which
appear to amplify, rather than alleviate, the dif¬
ficulties of finding one's way around labyrinths
of information. The knowledge stored in com¬
puters is physically never present, except for
the tiny segments momentarily on the screen.
When reading or browsing through a book,
when walking along the shelves of a library, or
even when flipping catalogue cards, one gains a
sense of orientation the electronic medium docs
not provide. For your knowledge to be coher¬
ent, you somehow have to know what you
know, have a survey, an overview, a memorized
^ THE UNESCO QïURIER JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
pattern of your knowledge. We have memory
images of certain important passages, recall the
pattern of text on a printed page, or the location
of a volume in a library. When texts are read or
scanned on the screen, such an overview will
hardly emerge.
MFrom e-mail to WWW
The basic form of networking is e-mail the
exchange of written messages via telephone
lines (and/or broad-width cables) and pow¬
erful intermediate computers (called servers),
between any two individual computer areas.
Travelling through a net of interconnected
networks, e-mail messages normally take just
a few seconds to reach their destinations, and
within minutes a reply might arrive. As a con¬
sequence e-mail messages are frequently quite
similar to exchanges in spoken languages: rich
in emotions, poor in grammar and typically
without the logical discipline of reflective writ¬
ing. E-mail messages might be sent to more
than one person, even to lists containing hun¬
dreds or thousands of addresses. In any case
they are easily forwarded to third parties.
E-mail messages are regularly seen by eyes
they were not intended for. They are, so to
i period engraving showing
a telegraph room in Paris in
1889.
"M Journey through Digital
Space", an exhibition held at
the abbey of Montmajour, near
Aries (France).
speak, overheard, just as written messages
often were in the age of reading aloud, the
kind of reading characteristic of manuscript
cultures. Another feature of manuscript cul¬
tures brought back by e-mail and by all
forms of working with electronic docu¬
ments is intcrtcxtuality: the free re-use and
mixing of passages, taken from any text, in
the process of producing a new one.
the Unesco Courier june 1997
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
E-mail gives rise to innumerable discus¬
sion lists, news groups and computer bulletin
boards, which have been described as the con¬
temporary equivalent of the ancient forum.
And while the overwhelming part of com¬
munication in the electronic market-place is
entirely fleeting and uninformed, the con¬
certed actions discussion groups frequently
initiate do have an immense democratic poten¬
tial, and the exchanges they pursue can indeed
provide information of high quality.
Such quality is of course more or less main¬
tained in the networked exchanges of the sci¬
entific community. There is today a growing
number of electronic scholarly journals; indeed
in some fields traditional periodicals have
already become obsolete. Even more signifi¬
cant are, as Stevan Harnad pointed out in Psy¬
chological Science in 1990, the changes per¬
taining to the so-called pre-publication
phase the phase of scientific inquiry "in
which ideas and findings are discussed infor¬
mally with colleagues, presented more for¬
mally in seminars, conferences and symposia,
and distributed still more widely in the form
of pre-prints. It has now become possible",
Harnad emphasized, "to do all this in a
remarkable new way that is not only incom¬
parably more thorough and systematic in its
distribution, potentially global in scale and
almost instantaneous in speed, but . . . unprece-
dentedly interactive." Scholarly skywriting is
the telling name Harnad gives to interactive
scientific inquiry in the medium of e-mail.
MTbe World Wide Web
The world of e-mail documents is unstable and
chaotic, difficult to navigate and impossible to
survey. By contrast, the World Wide Web
(WWW), today's ultimate computer network
achievement, is relatively stable and transparent.
The emergence of the Web amounts to a revo¬
lution in its own right. So-called Web pages
are self-published multimedia documents, each
having an address, and each connected throu gh
so-called hypertext links specifically conspic¬
uous words or symbols to a number of other
Web pages. Web pages form a m ore or less fixed
constellation of documents easy to scan and
study. We may know our way around in the
World Wide Web.
Multimedia documents may also convey
knowledge that mere texts cannot. The logic of í
images, as noted above, might come to fruit- I
fully complement the logic of texts. In the age î
of manual copying, and even in the age of the j
printing press, illustrations could only play a 1
subordinate role; and pictures as vehicles of I
thinking played almost no role at all. This is |
^ THE UNESCO |Q>URIER JUNE 1097
now changing with the possibility of manip¬
ulating images on the screen. Let us add that
knowledge is not just a matter of thinking; it
is also a matter of practices and skills. And
illustrations can show how things arc done. It
might be very difficult to give a verbal descrip¬
tion of, say, how a particular instrument is
handled, whereas a picture or a set of illustra¬
tions will easily explain it. Knowledge accessi¬
ble on the Web is not just global; it also tends
to be truly operational.
¡The virtual library
\s hildren in a computer class
(U.S.A.).
Quite a few of the great public and research
libraries of the world plan, or have already
begun, to digitize their materials first the
catalogues, and subsequently the holdings
themselves. Once digitized, these materials
(assuming that copyright problems and other
related issues have been solved) will be (and
many of them already are) accessible on the
net, thereby forming the joint stock of a huge
library that has no physical existence a virtual
library. This stock is, of course, continuously
enriched by scientific publications now issued
as electronic documents.
The advantages of the virtual library arc
obvious. Users of the net, whether living in
poor or rich regions of the world, may in prin¬
ciple have unlimited access to any library item.
Once they reach the documents they seek, they
can copy them electronically or make print¬
outs; and they can work with them in many
subtle ways, such as electronically searching
through them, and constructing concordances
and indexes. At the same time the original hard
copy items can be safely stored in buildings
that will gradually become book museums
rather than remain traditional libraries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
I he library of St. Catherine's
monastery, built in the 6th
century at the foot of Mt. Sinai
(Egypt), houses some 3,500
manuscripts, the world's
second largest collection after
that in the Vatican Library.
However, there are disadvantages too. Even
if multimedia technologies are fully employed,
bringing about a stronger illusion of physical
presence (e.g., pages of old books appearing
not just as a uniform text, but, if required,
as facsimile) electronic documents are poor at
creating a sense of place and time. That the ten¬
sions between the virtual and the physical are
not, in principle, impossible to resolve, is
shown by the programme of the new Biblio¬
thèque Nationale dc France. The BNF, which
is to be fully operational by 1998, is meant
to be both a giant physical library and a dig¬
ital on-line library. It is meant, as two of its
spiritual architects put it, to "consummate
the marriage of the universe of Gutenberg
with that of McLuhan. ... It will be open,
democratic, innovative, but all of those things
within a perspective ensuring the greatest
respect for the past." The BNF will no doubt
be a lighthouse in the torrents of the coming
global virtual library.
I Virtual universities
In an environment increasingly dominated by
multimedia computer networks, conventional
secondary and tertiary education is becoming
obsolete. Young people growing up with com¬
puters, introduced to the marvels of the net at
an early age, will experience traditional school
settings as simply unnatural. They become
used to finding their information not by ask¬
ing their elders or by going to a library, but by
surfing the Web.
On the tertiary level, lifelong learning is
expected, in the form of broad interdiscipli¬
nary education in the first place, and periods
of specialized training in new directions ever
after while being employed, or between jobs.
Tertiary education based on the net seems to
be the obvious solution. The virtual univer¬
sity is an institution of higher education with¬
out walls with no definite physical location,
no classrooms, no conventional library.
Although a minimum of face-to-face encoun¬
ters among registered students and their teach¬
ers and examiners seems to be inevitable, and
indeed called for, the learning process most of
the time takes the form of computer net¬
working.
The virtual university can be conceived of
as the twenty-first-century variety of distance
education. It needs to be stressed, however,
that the virtual university eliminates, rather
than bridges distance. The virtual university
preserves, or recreates, the personal community
of teacher and students, the audible and visi¬
ble character of lectures, the live interaction
of seminars. It is heir to the traditional uni¬
versity. But it is different both from the tra¬
ditional university and from distance educa¬
tion in the sense that, utilizing the possibilities
of interactive multimedia, it radically goes
beyond the inspirations of the printed book
of the fixed linear text. The creation of a virtual
university is a task of philosophical dimen¬
sions. It amounts to overcoming text-centred
modern European thought.
The working language of the Great Euro¬
pean universities of the Middle Ages was Latin.
From the sixteenth century on Latin was grad¬
ually complemented by the new literary
"national" languages emerging in close con¬
nection with the spread of printed books.
These new languages in turn became instru¬
mental in the creation of modern nation
states in building up centralized bureaucra¬
cies and national job markets. The university
henceforth served as the apex of a national edu¬
cation pyramid. It appears that in the case of
small nations the practical importance of
national universities is diminishing.
With the rise of a global economy and the
resulting need of a global education, the pres¬
sures to uphold a nation-wide cultural homo¬
geneity are weakening. A new interest is emerg¬
ing in local community life, local culture and
local dialect, an interest adequately reflected
by the popularity of local regional radio and
television broadcasts. Local activities are gain¬
ing a new significance by the fact that they can
be directly connected, through the net, to
activities on a global scale, without interven¬
tion or interference from national institu¬
tions. Computer networking is global, but it
is eminently suited also for the local and the
particular. Global knowledge and local cul¬
tures might happily coexist and exert mutually
creative influences.
THE UNESCO lOURIER JUNE 1007
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
From the clay
tablet to the
computer, a
wealth of tools
for memorizing
ideas and
transmitting
them through
time and space
The test of time
BY LOUISE MERZEAU
30
An idea must stand the test of time
before it can be transmitted through
space. In other words, it must be
proof against oblivion, falsity and fal¬
sification, and at the same time remain alive,
fertile and receptive to change. An idea can
only do this if it is fixed, first of all in the
memory, then in a material substance. This
paradox is more apparent than real: fixity is a
precondition and guarantee of the movement
of thought. But if memory is the prime vec¬
tor for the transmission of ideas, it is only
when ideas are externalized by inscription in a
medium or "carrier" that their lives are pro¬
longed beyond the limits of a single human
life. As a result of this process messages are
detached from the human body which they
outlive by being themselves "embodied" in a
device that memorizes and diffuses them.
I Traces and imprints
From the flintstone to the computer, the tools
that have been used to process these media are
THE UNESCO I^OURILR |UNE 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
kbove, a cluster of optical
fibres, hair-thin strands of
glass or plastic carrying
information as pulses of light,
play a key role in modern
telecommunications.
Left, hieroglyphics carved in
stone at Aswan (Egypt).
witnesses to this future-oriented process: each
technical aid is a step towards the victory of the
mind over the ephemerality of human life, a
first step towards someone else a person who
may be located in another place or another time.
The materials on which the inscription is
made are also repositories of this active mem¬
ory, places where the processing operations
leave their signature. Everything made by
human hand is a palimpsest. When the copy¬
ist monk of medieval Europe scratched out
what had been written on a sheet of parch¬
ment so that he could use it again, he left as
many traces as he erased. The original text either
became an illegible mess or disappeared entirely,
and then another text was written on the same
surface. Across the ages these scratchings-out
tell the story of a technique of writing (com¬
plete with calligraphy, desk, pen, pen-knife,
and ruler), a method of production and an
economic system (parchment was made from
animal skins which had to be limed, cleaned,
dried, chalked and then scraped, costing more
than the hours of work in the scriptory), and
of a method of dissemination which was itself
based on a certain form of knowledge (a sin¬
gle, inexhaustible and sacred message con¬
stantly referred to by writers and readers
belonging to a small circle of clerks).
Intangible though it may seem, a computer
file is not exempt from this trace-making
process without which it is impossible for an
idea to endure and travel. It is true that the
electronic text can be modified at will and that
by losing its definitive character it also loses the
variants and rough drafts that show the suc¬
cessive stages of its composition. But the com¬
puter memory contains far more information
than that which appears on the screen. With
each operation writing, copying, saving or
erasing the program records the instruction,
the code and the tag in a scries of figures com¬
prising 0 and 1 . While these digits may be inde¬
cipherable as such, they are nevertheless infal¬
lible witnesses to the intellectual operations
involved in producing a piece of writing or
an image or doing a calculation. By returning
to these instructions the program can recon¬
stitute, transmit and modify these data on
another machine at a later time.
{Travelling light
The evolution of techniques of inscription,
storage and recording shows how the quest
for greater precision has gone hand in hand
with a quest for greater mobility. The pur¬
pose of recording a message is not only to
make it unchangeable but also to make sure
I he Russian writer Fyodor
Dostoyevsky's desk and the
pen with which he wrote many
pages of The Brothers
Karamazov and The Diary of a
Writer.
E UNESCO ^lURIER JUNE 1097 V
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
that it can move freely in space and time, when
its medium can be easily handled, transported
or duplicated. From the clay or metal tablet of
the Sumerian era to the wax-smeared wooden
polyptych of ancient Rome, from the several-
metrc-long volumen to the bound leaves of
the codex (2nd-4th centuries), from the paper¬
back to the diskette and the electronic diary,
the written word has been packaged in increas¬
ingly handy as well as more reliable forms.
A thirteenth-century European student who
sought access to a piece ofwriting recommended
to him by his tutors was obliged to borrow an
exemplar or master copy from a stationer and
make a copy of it. His twentieth-century coun¬
terpart borrows a printed book from the library
and makes a photocopy, or downloads a digital
version of it from the network. In both cases, the
ideas circulate after being recorded in a medium,
but in the latter case the risk of the wording
being altered in the course of transmission is
much smaller than in the former. What applies
to texts applies even more strongly to the dif¬
fusion of images. One need only think of the
difficulties of copying a geographical map or an
assembly diagram, to realize how far inscrip¬
tion techniques engraving, printing or digiti¬
zation affect the propagation of knowledge.
Just as processes have become more reli¬
able, carriers have become more streamlined,
miniaturized and technically complex. Speed
and mobility go hand in hand with capacity to
record and store information. Today, thanks
to progress in electronics, information can
travel in real time and data circulate in billions
along optic fibres.
\ Package tours
Ideas travel best in groups. Sciences, arts and reli¬
gions are primarily collections, which assemble
the physical or mental universe into a corpus
where it can be reorganized so as to improve its
capacity for transmission. A message is more
certain to last if it belongs to a structured whole.
The origin of museums before they set
themselves the goal of safeguarding the her¬
itage lay in this need to concentrate scien¬
tific knowledge in a single centre of exchange
and research. The Mouscion of Alexandria,
300 years before the Christian era, was a,trca-
sure-house and laboratory, a community of
objects and thinkers from which knowledge
and beliefs flowed outwards to the entire Hel¬
lenistic world. In the treasuries of ancient tem¬
ples, medieval churches and princes, the same
foundational activity collection opened a
door to the future for works of the mind.
Something more than accumulation is
involved here: objects arc brought together
for processing, management and organization.
Inventories and indexes, follow-up and cata¬
loguing, as well as comparative study and rank¬
ing revitalize items in a collection by inte¬
grating them into generating systems.
During the French Revolution, it was the
concentration of biens nationaux, the "national
property" confiscated from the nobility and
the Church, that gave rise to the notion of
- 4M
/
I
ÊLwm^ 2ÈÊtw~'
M village meeting in southern
Bangalore, capital of the
Indian state of Karnataka.
32
THE UNESCO ^^OURIER JUNE 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
heritage. Faced with the need to protect images,
objects and buildings from sans-culotte van¬
dalism, the state began to compile invento¬
ries and descriptions of them and classify them
as historic monuments in a ranking that would
set an order of priority for their conservation
and restoration. Thus concentrated in an insti¬
tution i.e. a policy, places and agents ideas
expressed in stone, gouache or pottery gave
rise to a new idea: that of common property,
which belongs to all citizens and to no-one
in particular, and gives substance to awareness
of the national heritage.
In the sciences too, memory records and
produces knowledge by organizing proposi¬
tions. Grids, tables, projections, textbooks, dic¬
tionaries and encyclopaedias connect and sys¬
tematize data so that increasingly complex and
dynamic knowledge can be extracted from it. It
is through this kind of networking that each
person gains access to the memory of others.
n Illustration symbolizing
the power of a CD-ROM
(Compact Disc Read-Only
Memory) to store large
quantities of book text (up to
250,000 A4 pages).
As well as having a large
storage capacity, CD-ROM
enables text, ¡mage and sound
to be accessed from any part
of the disc.
MDon 't forget the guide
Once beliefs and knowledge have been con¬
centrated into territories, we still have to find
our way around them. This is where human or
technological guides come in. Access to a polit¬
ical, philosophical, scientific or religious her¬
itage docs not necessarily imply familiarity
with it.
The memory has always needed a helping
hand from signposts, which have ranged from
the use of "common places" (loci communes)
by Roman rhetoricians to the hypertext of
today. Taking in a set of images, using a tree-
diagram to find our way into a system of
thought, or hopping from one screen to the
next while surfing on the net always implies a
topology of information, complete with
road-signs, roundabouts, highways and
byways. The layout of annotations and foot¬
notes, the numbering of chapters and pages,
and the icons of CD-ROMs enable us to find
our way within the world of ideas and there¬
fore provide a basis for their transmission.
In addition to these signposts arc mediators
organized in institutions, groups, clubs,
schools and corporations. At once structured,
localized and receptive to their environment,
these mediators connect thought to the social
interactions that give it meaning. Their medi¬
ation fits the transmission of ideas into a strat¬
egy, a balance of power or a role-playing situ¬
ation. For shared space-time, a framework of
tensions and negotiations, is the basis of the
collective memory. Consensus designed to
buttress the social body's belief in its own
perpetuation never comes about automati¬
cally; its construction calls for constant stew¬
ardship of the collective experience.
These guides for the collective memory are
vested with the power to winnow out those
values that should be preserved from those
that should be forgotten. The controversy
often sparked off by the granting of amnesties
(the first of which dates from 403 B.C.) or by
the definition of imprescriptible crimes high¬
lights the ethical issues involved in the politics
of memory. From the viewpoint of history
and the formation of cultures, the choice of
what should be recorded and what should be
erased is never a matter of indifference.
The inclination of modern societies to
exploit to the nth degree everything they pro¬
duce poses a real question. While new tech¬
nologies bring within reach the Utopian dream
of a total grasp of events, phenomena and mes¬
sages, we must always keep in mind that remem
bering is indissociable from forgetting
THE UNESCO (1>URIIER JUNE 1907
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
FACT FILE
SAFEGUARDING THE DOCUMENTARY HERITAGE
Unesco's "Memory of the world" programme
In 1992 UNESCO launched a "Memory of the World" Programme
which seeks to protect and facilitate access to the world's doc¬
umentary heritage. The documents, images and sounds stored
in libraries and archives which comprise this heritage are a
major part of the collective memory, reflecting the diversity and orig¬
inality of peoples and cultures.
Much of the world's documentary heritage disappears through
"natural" causes, e.g. acidified paper that crumbles to dust, leather,
parchment, film and magnetic tape attacked by light, heat, humid¬
ity or pollution. Libraries and archives are also regularly afflicted
by external events which may be catastrophic unless anticipated by
preventive measures: flooding, fire, hurricanes, and earthquakes
as well as acts of war, criminal activity and accidental or deliber¬
ate displacement.
The UNESCO Programme has two complementary objectives
to safeguard endangered documentary heritage and to democra¬
tize access to it. With this in view, it seeks to develop products such
as text, sound and image banks which could be made available
on local and global networks, as well as compact discs, books,
postcards, microfilm and other forms of reproduction, and presence
on the Internet.
A "Memory of the World" register
The programme encourages governments to set up national com¬
mittees in order to increase awareness of the importance of safe¬
guarding their documentary heritage. The committees can inau¬
gurate preservation and information projects they would like to
see included on the "Memory of the World" Register. This Regis¬
ter, similar in some ways to UNESCO's World Heritage List, is an
inventory of the documentary heritage identified as having world
significance. An International Advisory Committee, whose mem¬
bers are appointed by UNESCO's Director General, grants the "Mem¬
ory of the World" label to projects proposed by the national com¬
mittees and recommends their inclusion on the Register.
The selection criteria are clearly defined. Documentary her¬
itage is considered to be of world significance if it has had a major
influence on world history; if it makes an outstanding contribution
to our understanding of the world at a particularly important time
or if it sheds light on aplace which played a crucial role in world
history; if it is associated with ¿person orpeople who have made
an outstanding contribution to world history or culture; if it doc¬
uments in a noteworthy manner a subject or major theme of world
importance; if it is an important example of an outstanding/orm or
style; if it has marked social, spiritual or cultural value which tran¬
scends a national culture.
National committees already exist in 26 countries. The first
international conference on the "Memory of the World" was held
in Oslo (Norway) from 3 to 5 June 1996 and was attended by
some 1 50 delegates from 65 countries. A resolution adopted by the
Conference invites all nations to establish national "Memory of the
World" committees and to play an active part in the programme.
Pilot projects
Several pilot projects currently under way are using leading-edge
technology to preserve precious and fragile documents and to facil¬
itate access to them. With support from UNESCO and the Library
of Congress in Washington D.C. (U.S.A.), the library of the Russ¬
ian Academy of Sciences in St. Petersburg is producing a CD-
ROM of the Radzivill Chronicle, a 15th-century illuminated man¬
uscript relating the history of Russia from the 5th to the 13th
centuries. The Asociación de Iberoamérica (ABINIA) has pro¬
posed a project to safeguard examples of the 19th-century press in
12 Latin American countries (via microfilm, digitization, exhibitions
and publications); a computerized inventory of some 6,000 news¬
paper titles has already been made. In Yemen a national commit¬
tee has been set up to select the most precious manuscripts found
in the ceiling of the Great Mosque of Sana'a, and a demonstra¬
tion CD-ROM has been produced in Cairo (Egypt). In a good
example of a regional project, thousands of old postcards (1890-1930)
relating to 16 countries of the Economic Community of Western
African States (ECOWAS) are being recorded on a CD-ROM.
Some 30 other projects are in the pipeline, including the restoration
and preservation of 7,000 hours of audio materials of Chinese folk
music, Tamil palm-leaf manuscripts in India, Vietnamese films
and Laotian manuscripts.
Lastly, so that UNESCO can play its role to the full as co-ordi-
nator and catalyst, three inventories in the form of regularly up¬
dated databases are being made in co-operation with a number of
professional bodies:
*" An inventory of library collections and archive holdings which
have suffered irreparable damage since 1990, to be published as
Lost Memory Libraries andArchives Destroyed in the Twentieth
Century;
*" A world list of endangered library collections and archive hold¬
ings;
*" An inventory of ongoing operations to protect documentary
heritage.
UNESCO has also published a brochure outlining the pro¬
gramme's technical, legal and financial framework and its work¬
ing structures. This document, entitled Memory of the World, Gen¬
eral Guidelines to Safeguard Documentary Heritage, is available
free of charge (in each of UNESCO's official languages).
For further information, contact Abdelaziz Abid,
head of the "Memory of the World" Programme, Division of
the General Information Programme,
UNESCO, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
Internet: http://www.unesco.org/cii/en/accueil.html
INDEX TRANSLATIONUM
The Index Translationum is an international bibliography of translated
works published all over the world. It first appeared in 1932, and has
been published annually since 1948. In 1993 the paper edition was
replaced by a cumulative CD-ROM edition that Is updated every year.
The Index Translationum is a unique working tool produced thanks to
ongoing international co-operation. The 1996 edition contains some
830,000 bibliographical entries for books translated and published in
over 100 countries ranging from Albania to Zimbabwe and covers a vast
range of subjects. Almost 200,000 authors are listed and over 400 lan¬
guages mentioned. (Periodicals, articles from periodicals, patents and
brochures are not included.)
The current Index Translationum may be ordered directly from:
Unesco Publishing, Promotion and Sales Division, 7, Place de Fontenoy,
75352 Paris 07 SP, France.
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57 41. Web site: http://www.unesco.org
Bibliography
Translators through History, ed. and dir. by Jean Delisle and Judith Woodsworth,
John Benjamins Publishing Company/UNESCO Publishing, 1995.
34 3 QuiTHE UNESCO ^^OURIER |UNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
ROUTES OF DIALOGUE
Cultural identities have been created over time by an
interplay of cultural influences and encounters and by
movements from one land or region to another. To find
out more about how these movements have influenced
our world, UNESCO launched a series of projects in 1988 to
study the routes that have connected the world's peoples from
time immemorial. Scientists and scholars from all over the
world have been mobilized in a far-reaching enterprise of
research, including four expeditions.
The first, The Silk Roads: Roads ofDialogue, highlighted
the pivotal role played by the movement of people, ideas and
values in the growth of cultures. It has given rise to numerous
initiatives and some 40 publications, including six produced
by Unesco. The Slave Route project, inaugurated in Benin in
1994, will study the causes, mechanisms and consequences
of the Black slave trade, which transformed the history of
Africa and the Americas. The Iron R oad project, launched in
1991, highlights the impact of African metallurgy on the evo¬
lution of African societies and cultures. The Roads of Faith
programme, which marks the international, intercultural and
interreligious importance ofJerusalem, also began in 1991. It
seeks to enhance understanding of the close ties that grew
over the centuries between the three monotheistic religions.
The Routes ofal-Andalus project between Europe, the Arab
world and sub-Saharan Africa, launched in 1 995, is designed
to highlight the lessons of the intcrcultural heritage of Mus¬
lim Spain where, between the 8th and the 15th centuries,
three cultures created a cosmopolitan civilization through
three religions.
THE UNESCO COLLECTION OF
REPRESENTATIVE WORKS
The Unesco Collection of Representative Works, which was created in
1948, encourages the translation, publication and distribution in major lan¬
guages (English, French, Spanish and Arabic) of works of literary and cul¬
tural importance that are not well known outside their original national
boundaries or linguistic communities.
The works that have been translated under this cultural co-operation
and exchange programme have been brought out as co-editions in part¬
nership with publishers from all over the world. To date, the catalogue of
these works contains some 1,000 titles from more than 80 countries,
translated from 100 or so different languages. The Collection endeav¬
ours to reflect the varied pattern of the world literary heritage in antholo¬
gies arranged by theme, type and country. It includes works expressive of
contemporary minority cultures and languages as well as traditional works.
By translating and distributing their works, the Collection has brought wider
international recognition to authors including Nobel laureates Yasunan
Kawabata and George Seferis.
As well as being nationally representative and possessing literary
qualities, works published in the Collection should be in keeping with the
ideals and principles of Unesco and may not, therefore, advocate war,
racism or violence in any form. On the contrary, they should encourage
tolerance, peace and mutual understanding among peoples and their
cultures.
For further information and to obtain catalogues, contact:
The Unesco Bookshop, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75352 Paris 07/SP, France.
Unesco Publishing, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
Bibliography
The January 1986 issue of the Unesco Courier {Treasures of World Literature)
was entirely devoted to the Unesco Collection of Representative Works.
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Unesco Publishing, 1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 43 00; Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57 41;
E-mail: http://www.unesco.org/publishlng.
CD-ROM:
Serindia: the Forgotten Oases of the Silk Roads, Mac/PC, 1995, 320 French
francs.
BOOKS:
The African Slave Trade from the Fifteenth to the Nineteenth Century,
1985.
The Silk and Spice Routes (Junior Books): Cultures and Civilizations,
Struan Reíd, 1994; Exploration by Land, Paul Strathern, 1993; Exploration
by Sea, Paul Strathern, 1993; Inventions and Trade, Struan Reid, 1994.
Les routes de la soie - patrimoine commun, identités plurielles, Jean
Leclant, 1994.
Les abolitions de l'esclavage, de Í..F. Sonthonax à V. Schoelcher, 1 793-
1794-1848,1995.
L'Afrique entre l'Europe et l'Amérique. Le rôle de l'Afrique dans la ren¬
contre de deux mondes, 1492-1992, Elikia M'Bokolo (editor), 1995.
La Société des amis des Noirs (1 788-1800) - Contribution à l'histoire du
mouvement ant-esclavagiste, Marcel Dorigny (forthcoming)
Los códigos negros de la América española (1 768-1843), Manuel Lucena
Salmoral (forthcoming).
ARTICLES IN THE UNESCO COURIER:
On the Roads of Faith:
"The thrice-holy city", Annie Laurent, May 1995 (The Pilgrim's Way)
On the Silk Roads:
"The return of the Fulk al-Salamah", François-Bernard Huyghe, August-
September 1991 (Sea Fever)
"The kingdom of Silla and the treasures of Nara", François-Bernard
Huyghe, July 1991 {Mozart and the Enlightenment)
"The fabulous land of Cathay", François-Bernard Huyghe, May 1991
(People at Play)
"Ambassadors, adventurers and empires", François-Bernard Huyghe,
April 1991 (Perceptions of Time)
"Threading through the past", François-Bernard Huyghe, March 1991
(A World of Music)
"In the wake of Marco Polo", François-Bernard Huyghe, January 1991
(Cities under Stress)
"A silken bond between East and West", Ahmad Hasan Dani, March
1989
"Rediscoverlngthe Silk Roads", November 1988 (A World Decade for
Cultural Development)
ENTIRE ISSUES OF THE UNESCO COURIER:
Slavery, a crime without punishment, October 1994
Al-Andalus: where three worlds met, December 1991
Averroes and Maimonides, two masterminds of the 12th century, Sep¬
tember 1986
Great trade routes, June 1984
ISSUES OF UNESCO SOURCES
When East meets West and North meets South, no. 70, June 1995
Silk Roads: a dialogue renewed, no. 18, September 1990
FOR FURTHER INFORMATION:
Division of Intercultural Projects
Unesco,1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 48 12
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 55 88
THE UNESCO L^OURIER JUNE 1957
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
COMMENTARY
I ro
to action
UNESCO-AN IDEAL IN ACTION
by Federico Mayor
in collaboration with Sema Tangjiane.
UNESCO Publishing
"CJtures of Peace" series, Paris, 1997. 124 pp
(French version, 1996, 131 pp).
In his latest book, Unescoan ideal in action, The continuing
relevance of a visionary text, Federico Mayor takes the Constitution
of the Organization he has headed for almost ten years as the
starting point of a wide-ranging inquiry into the meaning and
future of international intellectual co-operation. We publish below
the introduction to this work.
Docs it take a cataclysm on the scale of "the great and ter-
rihle war" that ended in 1945 to stir the conscience of the
world and hring those who hold the levers of political,
economic and spiritual power to summon up the same
dedication, drive and determination as inspired those
who, at that time, undertook to build a better world?
Is humanity fated to find the willpower and the
strength to take vigorous collective action only when it
is treading the very brink of the abyss? Is it only in times
of acute crisis that it is capable of relegating short-term
interests and concerns to second place and encouraging
the leaders of the nations, the most powerful nations in
particular, to be inspired by a historical and global vision?
The twentieth century is drawing to a close. It has
witnessed brilliant triumphs of human ingenuity and a
succession of unprecedented technological revolutions
that have made possible the production of goods and
services in a quantity and a variety that woidd have been
unimaginable at the end of the previous century. Sub¬
stantial progress has been made in education, health,
communication and many other fields. This century has
seen the liberation of scores of peoples, and political and
geopolitical upheavals whose scope and impact have
scarcely any parallels in the past. On the other hand, it
has been scarred by wars whose scale, ferocity and sheer
destructive power are also without historical precedent.
URIER JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Seen overall, the direction in which the world is moving the world and men and women of goodwill to work
on the eve of the twenty-first century is still disturbing, together for world peace and the common welfare and
despite the hopes aroused by such developments as the well-bring of all peoples. Not the least among those mech-
end of the cold war, the ending of apartheid and the anisms is UNESCO itself,
peace achieved in El Salvador and Mozambique. What is lacking is the determination to overcome
The spread of violence and of lethal conflicts, claim- national self-interest and short-term concerns and to set
ingmany victims every day, arouses terror, causes large- out upon the road of solidarity, the courage to proclaim
scale displacements of populations andlays waste whole and to convince others that, in an increasingly interde-
regions. The riseof fanaticism of allkindsandintolerance pendent world, peace and prosperity are unsure and
in its various manifestations have left people in a state of fragile unless shared by all.
shock and pose a threat to peace even when they do not This determination is something that has to be cre-
degenerate into civil war. Acts of genocide "announced" ated. The United Nations system bears a great responsi-
well in advance are committed while institutions that bility in that resjiect; and the organizations of which it is
should prevent or put a stop to them but are unpre- composed likewise need to show courage and perscver-
pared to do so look on in resignation. Although some anee in bringing this determination into being and exert-
succcsses have been achieved in efforts to protect and inga greater influence on the major decisions affecting the
regenerate the environment, the general tendency world world. By virtue of its ethical mission, UNESCO probably
wide has been towards a deterioration that ultimately has a pioneering role to play in this undertaking,
presents a serious threat to human survival. Growing Most of the organizations making up the United Nations
inequality creates tensions between groups of countries system are celebrating their fiftieth anniversaries, mak-
and cleavages within nations. Poverty, far from dimin- ing this an opportune moment to launch initiatives to
ishing, is worsening both in the industrialized and in the help restore to the system the strength of eon viction, the
developing countries. Entire peoples are faced with a vigour and commitment it had in its early days. An effort
situation where the general trend is towards impover- to rediscover the spirit, the will and the hope so remark-
ishment while a minority grows richer. ably expressed in UmíSCO's Constitution, and to educe
Despite some undeniable progress, democracy remains from it pointers for the action to be undertaken in this time
a tender plant, and it is far from having become a normal of transition, certainly counts as one such initiative,
feature of the daily life and political culture of citizens. The political, ethical and philosophical message of
Human rights and fundamental freedoms are still regularly the Constitution is contained in its Preamble and its Arti-
violatcd, and broad swaths of the population, young peo- ele I. The whole message, one might say the whole secret,
pie in particular, are marginalized and excluded from of a great text and UNESCO's Constitution, by the last-
debates about the future in many countries, including ing relevance of its humanist message, is one is not
some that set themselves up as champions of human rights. revealed at a first reading. What we read into such a
Failure to live up to ideals and values that formerly text is largely determined by the historical context, and
gave hope to millions of men and women, spurred them what holds our attention is usually only what appears in
on and helped them to look beyond short-term interests, the light of current events to be particularly important
and the misappropriation or erosion of those ideals and and what is of prime concern at that given time,
values have left people with a sense of emptiness, disil- To read the Constitution and the records of the Con-
lusionment, confusion and bitterness. Growing feelings ference that drafted and adopted itis,inthecircumstances
of frustration and humiliation are in danger of causing vio- of today, to have one's eyes opened to certain aspects of the
lent explosions, if nothing is done to calm them. message contained in the text that have not always received
It is clear that no nation is entirely exempt from a cri- the attention they deserve. Thus, in the present context the
sis of values, or perhaps one should say a moral crisis. principal ideas proclaimed and the key concepts contained
And yet	 Humanity possesses the knowledge and therein take on an even wider applicability and even greater
resources with which it could put an end to most of these forre than before. This is the case, in particular, with such
crises, and could eliminate, reduce or at least consider- concepts and ideas as peace, the democratic principles of
ably dilute the causes of these instances of appalling the dignity, equality and mutual respect of men, theintel-
inequality, injustice, discrimination, exclusion, frustration lectual and moral solidarity of mankind, the ideal of equal-
and humiliation. On emerging from "the great and terri- ¡ty of educational opportunity for all, the free exchange of
ble war", it provided itself with a set of mechanisms for ideas and knowledge, the eonimon welfare of mankind and
concerted action such as would enable the nations of increasing and diffusing knowledge.
THE UNESCO (^OURIER |UNE 1997 ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
OurSoils
I
by France Bequette
The conservation of water
and air quality and the pro¬
tection of plant and animal life are
causes that mobilize plenty of sup¬
port. Soil conservation is a Cin¬
derella in comparison. Little stud¬
ied, little known and neglected in
public policy-making, soil is per¬
haps too humdrum a subject to
attract attention. It is also a dis-
couragingly complex one.
When the earth was less popu¬
lated, its direct users farmers,
foresters and builders respected
this surface layer which is essential
for life. This is no longer the case.
All countries, developed and devel¬
oping alike, are experiencing vari¬
ous forms of land degradation. The
earth's surface is being eviscerated
by mining, pierced with oil wells,
churned up and concreted over. It
is treated with "unnatural" fertil¬
izers, herbicides and pesticides in
order to boost agricultural output.
Can we go on exploiting this nat¬
ural resource indefinitely?
Soil is the thin unconsolidated
veneer (from several centimetres
to several metres thick) of the
lithosphère, the top layer of the
Ferns and maple in
a Japanese
garden.
earth's skin that is subject to
weathering. It consists of frag¬
ments of parent rock weathered
hy the combined effects of water,
air, temperature and the plant, ani¬
mal and human life which it sup¬
ports. Pedology, a branch of
applied geology that studies the
chemical, physical and biological
characteristics of soil, as well as
Grass mites.
its evolution and distribution,
appeared in the late nineteenth
century. But it is only in the last
fifty-odd years that we have
become familiar with this orga¬
nized environment which, by sus¬
taining ¡liants and animals, nour¬
ishes human societies and is the
basis of agriculture.
A LITTLE-KNOWN STRUCTURE
Soil is divided into three strata or
layers that specialists call "hori¬
zons". They are differentiated by
the proportion of minerals or
organic matter in their composi¬
tion, variations in colour, texture
and porosity, and hy their water
and carbon dioxide content.
The mobile top layer of litter is
easy to observe with the naked
eye. It consists of plant debris
(branches and leaves, pine needles,
dead grass, mosses, seeds and
fruit) and animal debris (corpses
and droppings). Below it is the
humus-rich horizon of brown or
blackish earth containing the
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
A vertical section
of soil In a forest.
decomposed debris of the litter
and mineral particles brought up
from the deep layers by earth¬
worms. The quality of this hori¬
zon is crucial for plant growth.
While life is largely absent from
its compact parts, it is extremely
intense in channels formed by the
decomposition of dead roots and
holes dug by earthworms. The
third horizon is the interface
between the layer of humus and
the parent rocks. Lighter-coloured
than humus, it contains sand,
gravel, silts and clays.
Soil performs many functions,
but four of them are particularly
important, as French agronomist
and pedologist Alain Huellan points
out in his book Regards sur le sol.
Mlcroarthropods
from the forest
floor.
tains many plant and animal
species and many biological cycles
transit through it.
A nutrition function: it con¬
tains elements necessary for life
such as mineral salts, air and water,
which it accumulates and puts at
the disposal of plants and animals.
In short, it plays "the role of a
larder which \ a ries in size and abun¬
dance; it also retains water which it
returns to ¡liants as they need it.
Much of what plants eat, drink and
breathe comes from the soil."
A filtration function: it is a
porous environment which acts as
a purifier and provides the water
(wells, springs, rivers) which passes
through it with its chemical and
biological qualities.
A material function: it provides
raw material for construction and
other activities (buildings, pottery,
ores, etc).
A BIOLOGICAL CARPET
An incredible diversity of under¬
ground animal and plant life pro¬
liferates away from curious eyes.
Yves Coineau, a professor at
France's National Museum of Nat¬
ural History in Paris ¡s a specialist
in soil microfauna. "Lots of people
have heard about the fabulous
mass of marine plankton," he
writes, "but do not know that when¬
ever they put a foot down they *
A biological function: soil con-
0
*^* %¿p>
T*i *H:«.*\i *
EKE«!*'
*"**'M m^m 1
i^avIr S PI
THE UNESCO ^URIER JUNEI097 39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
stamp on myriads of tiny animals
forming dense, varied and active
populations which are in many ways
reminiscent of plankton. Walkers
think they are tramping over an
inert mineral soil whereas in fact
they are moving about on a con¬
stantly changing biological carpet."
Pedozoology, the study of ani¬
mal life in the soil, is a recent sci¬
ence and it is far from having drawn
up a complete inventory of its field.
To get some idea of the difficulties
it faces, we should bear in mind
that examination of the living mat¬
ter in the first 15 centimetres
below the surface of the average
meadow reveals (per gram) a flora
of 100,000 algae, 600,000,000
bacteria, 400,000 fungi, and a
microfauna (per cubic decimetre)
of 1,551,000,000 protozoans (uni¬
cellular creatures), 51,000 meta-
zoans (creatures consisting of sev¬
eral cells) including 50,000
nematodes (worms). In I'aris Yves
Coineau has created the world's
first microzoo where vistors peer
through microscopes to see surre¬
alistic creatures, including his
favourites, mites (Acariña) and
springtails (Collembola). He tracks
them down not only in the soil but
in our beds, where they find a lodg¬
ing after going through an extra¬
ordinary process of adaptation.
THE PRESSURE OF HUMAN
ACTIVITY
We live in close interdependence
with the soil. "The Hebrew word
adâmah means soil," Alain Huel¬
lan points out, "and is the origin
of the word 'Adam', the first man."
In Japan there are shinto temples
dedicated to soil and the Japan¬
ese sign for "soil" symbolizes the
rooted plant. This veneration for
the soil reflects awareness of its
mystery and importance. Soil is
the very root of humanity. If it dis¬
appears, humanity disappears.
"It's all a question of balance
between the functional capacities
and renewability of soils and the
excessive pressure of human activ¬
ities," Huellan maintains. "All over
the world there are too many exam¬
ples of seriously modified soils, of
soils seriously wounded by
exploitation erosion of course but
also déstructuration, compaction,
impoverishment and decliningbio-
logical activities, excessive desic¬
cation, accumulation of toxic salts,
leaching of fine and nutritious ele¬
ments, and pollution."
Above, a
springtail, a
primitive wingless
insect commonly
found In soil.
Left, a mite of the
Orlbatidae family.
Further reading:
Guidelines for soil survey and land evaluation in ecological research
by R.F. Breimer, AJ. van Kekem and H. van Reuler.
MAB Technical Notes 17, Unesco 1986.
Agricultures,
Cahiers d'études et de recherches francophones,
vol 1, n° 1, March-April 1992.
Regards sur le sol
by Alain Rueiian and Mireille Dosso,
Foucher, Paris, 1993.
Le sol
by Michel Robert, Masson, Paris, 1996.
The 16th World Congress of Soil Science, chaired by Alain Ruellan, will
be held from 20 to 26 August 1998 at Montpellier (France). The work¬
ing languages will be English, French, German and Spanish. Secre¬
tariat: Tel: (33) (0) 4 67 04 75 38; Fax: (33) (0) 4 67 04 75 49; e-mail:
isss@agropolis.fr
According to the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations (FAO), there are
an estimated 3,031 million
hectares of cropland worldwide,
877 million in (lev eloped countries
and 2,1 54 in the developing world.
Michel Hobert, of France's
National Institute for Agronomic
Research (INHA), has noted that
"the natural fertility of the great
tropical forests has always been an
illusion. In reality, they are a frag¬
ile ecosystem and as soon as they
are affected by deforestation
important and irreversible changes
take place; these concern more
than 1 1 million hectares each year
in tropical areas."
In the forest, there is consider¬
able soil stability and low erosion.
Hut mechanized clearance causes
the soil to become comparted and
impermeable. Water run-off and
erosion ensue. Krosion has many
causes, including overgrazing and
increased cropping to keep pace
with demographic growth, as well
as deforestation. Annual soil loss
is thought to affect between 5 and
7 million hectares a year, according
to FAO estimates; if erosion con¬
tinues on this scale, from 20 to 30
per cent of cropland will disappear
between now and the year 2000.
Soil should now be regarded as a
non-renewable resource, just like
peat, coal or oil. Nature needs from
100 to 400 years to create 10 mil¬
limetres of topsoil and from 3,000 to
12,000 years to form a soil laver
equivalent to the length of this page.
Humanit) cannot wait so long. Soil
protection is urgently needed. H
40
the Unesco Courier june 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
ZIMBABWE'S IVORY
DILEMMA
Zimbabwe has told the secre¬
tariat of the Convention on
International Trade in Endan¬
gered Species of Wild Fauna
and Flora (CITES) that it
would like to sell its 33-ton
reserve of elephant tusks to
generate some $4 million.
There are an estimated 64,000
elephants in Zimbabwe, where
they are a protected species,
and their numbers are rising in
contrast to the trend in other
African regions. Elephant herds
often cause extensive damage
to crops, and proceeds from the
ivory sale would be earmarked
for compensation to farmers.
But the sale of ivory from ele¬
phants, which are regarded as
an endangered species, has
been banned by CITES since
1990. The next meeting of
CITES will he held in Harare,
and its decision is anxiously
awaited. M
GREEN HOTELS
In many North American hotels
it is not unusual for guests to
find a small sign in several lan¬
guages posted in the bathroom:
"If you'd like us to change your
towels, throw them in the bath¬
tub; if not, hang them on the
towel-rail." This is an excellent
way to economize on water,
energy and polluting deter¬
gents. If we don't change towels
every day at home, why should
we do so in hotels?
AROMATIC RICE
Scientists at the Laboratory of
Genetic Resources and Tropi¬
cal Plant Impro\ ement, part of
the French ¡National Scientific
Research Institute for Devel¬
opment through Co-operation
(ORSTOM), have confirmed
that the aroma of scented rice
is determined hy a major gene
located on chromosome 8.
Thanks to this piece of gene-
mapping it will he possible to
speed up selection of plants
combining aromatic qualities
with high productivity and
resistance to disease. M
COUNTERFEITING CFCS
Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs),
enemies of the ozone la) er, are
used by police to make finger¬
prints appear clearly on porous
surfaces such as paper. Scien¬
tists in the United Kingdom,
who are trying to find a substi¬
tute, have successfully tested a
number of II FCs(hvd rofiuoro-
carbons, which contain no chlo¬
rine and are ozone-friendly) on
thousands of forged cheques.
Police forces all over the world
are interested in this new dis¬
covery.
INDONESIA LOOKS
TO THE SUN
The World Hank has approved a
loan of $44. 3 billion to Indone¬
sia to help encourage the use of
solar energy. At present over 115
million out of an estimated 195
million Indonesians have no
access to electricity. Thanks to
solar power, which is already
being used by ov er 20,000 rural
Indonesian households, children
can study in better lit environ¬
ments after sunset, and adults
can continue income-producing
activities at home. Customers
can buy a solar unit on credit by
ma king (low n payments of about
$75 to $100, then paying $10
per month for four years. The
Bank's Global Environmental
Facility grant will be used to
help households make down
payments. M
BOUNCY RUBBER
Rubber is a hydrocarbon pro¬
duced in its natural form by
numerous plants. It is found
blended in varying proportions
in latex, a milky liquid exuded
by various species, including
trees, vines, succulents and
herbaceous plants. The best
rubber-producing species is a
softwood tree from South Amer¬
ica (lleven brasiliensis), which
was introduced into Asia in the
19th century. This tall tree only
prospers in humid tropical or
equatorial climates. Wild spec¬
imens may live to be over 100
years old. A cultivated hevea
produces a daily average of 30
grams of rubber, obtained by
tapping. To make a car tyre 170
heveas need to lie tapped; 670
for a lorry tyre. Today through
the efforts of the French Centre
for International Co-operation in
Agronomic Research for Devel¬
opment (CIRAD), 120,000
hectares of particularly high-
yield hevea trees are growing in
west Africa.
THE UNESCO lOURIER JUNEI*)*)?
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
W^ÊKI^mW
ALMYRA faces that belong
to eternity
by Mahmoud Zibawi
Palmyra, "city of palms", was founded in an oasis between the Orantes and the Euphrates in the heart of
the Syrian desert towards the end of the third millennium B.C. It was the capital of Palmyrene, an ally of
Rome atthe beginning of the Roman empire (late 1st century B.C.). It enjoyed a golden age during the
reign of Zenobia in thethird century A.D., until it was sacked by the Roman emperor Aurelian in 273. In the
following centuries it recovered some of its importance, but never again played its former role. Its ruins
are among the most important of late Antiquity. One original feature of Palmyra is funerary sculpture
whose hieratic images and spiritual intensity transcend Greek, Roman and Persian influences and
foreshadow Byzantine art.
This marble head of
the Roman general
and politician Caius
Marlus (1st century
B.C.) ¡s a
masterpiece of
realistic Roman
statuary.
The finest specimens of
Palmyrene sculpture were
produced during the first three
centuries of the Christian era, at
a time when the pax romana
encouraged long-distance trade.
They belong to the art of the
Roman Middle East, where Hel¬
lenistic influence prevailed in an
area stretching from Egypt to the
borders of Mesopotamia. The
blending of civilizations and cul¬
tures in the melting pot of the
Roman Empire infused a new
.spirit into art. The classical mod¬
els of Rome, which still lived on,
were taken up and recreated
rather than imitated. The art of
Palmyra incorporates features
that came from the Persian
empire, while also displaying the
influence of local Syrian and
Mesopotamian traditions and of
Oriental traditions in general.
A salient feature of this sculp¬
ture is that each figure is pre¬
sented frontally and as an individ¬
ual. This concern for individuality
is particularly noticeable in the
funerary statues, in which
Palmyrene sculptors gave their own
twist to classical Roman portrai¬
ture, which in the second century
A.D. was moving away from real¬
ism towards idealization. The
extraordinary variety of types pro¬
duced by the realism of early
Roman statuary is replaced in the
imperial period by a gallery of ide¬
alized portraits. Strict individual
resemblance is abandoned. Artists
depict personages with imaginary
features. Figures from the past
and portraits of contemporaries
are reinvented. Rulers and sub¬
jects alike are shown with divine
attributes and are masked with
idealized faces.
This trend in Roman statuary
had a profound effect in the east¬
ern provinces of the Roman
empire. Emphatic stylization
deliberately transgressed the
canons of naturalistic beauty. An
attempt was made to purge the
human face of earthly affinities
and invest it with celestial quali¬
ties. In the painted portraits of
Fayoum in Egypt and the stone
carvings of cities in the Arab
desert alike, the face is shown as
transcending place and time. With
its thin lips, sharp nose, inordi¬
nately enlarged eyes and open
gaze, it belongs to eternity.
HOUSES OF ETERNITY
Palmyrene sculpture takes this
stylistic evolution to its highest
point. In the hypogea, under-
THE UNESCO lOURIER |UN£ 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Damascus
TURKEY
Syrian Arab
Republic
PALMYRA
/
IRAQ
« The central section of Palmyra's main thoroughfare. Some 1,200
°2 metres long, it crosses the administrative district of the ancient
| Roman city from east to west. Archaeologists have named it the
| Grand Colonnade because it was lined with porticoes. The Temple
| of Bel can be seen In the distance. The amphitheatre (centre) is one
| of the largest In the Middle East. At far right is the agora or foru m
2 (partly visible). In foreground is a tetrapylon, an edifice with four
I portals marking an intersection of two thoroughfares.
ground burial vaults known as
"houses of eternity" are a pleiad of
faces carved in rock. On each tomb
is a stele depicting the deceased
full-length or as a bust. In accor¬
dance with the convention of
frontality, the figures face out to
us, almost always in high or low
relief (sculpture in the round is
very rare in Palmyrene art). Their
idealized and youthful faces fit
into a conventional mould and all
possess similar features. Men,
women and children are depicted
as types. Veils and curls of hair
frame oval faces. The features are
simplified; movement is restrained;
expression is concentrated.
Contemplation is the sole form
of action. Two concentric circles
(the iris and the pupil) represent
the eye. The pupils are frozen
between the eyelids. "These enor¬
mous eyes, as unreal as the folds
of the robe, seem to want to pour
forth a torrent of life, and they
alone perform the magic task of
giving life to a bust which other¬
wise lacked all semblance of
being," wrote the archaeologist
Henri Seyrig. "For the Palmyrene
sculptor the most interesting
aspect of being is its deepest and
most permanent content."
The name of the deceased is
often preceded by the Aramaean
term nafshâ, meaning "breath",
"soul" or "person". Earthly like¬
nesses have been left behind by
these faces which concentrate on
A funerary stele
depicting a father
and son
(2nd century A.D.)
immortality. There are no explana¬
tory or descriptive inscriptions.
The contemplative gaze of the
deceased silently evokes life in
the next world. The faces of gods,
which also look out at the spec¬
tator, have the same spiritual
presence. The same face is por¬
trayed time and again. The human
becomes divine; the divine human.
THE UNESCO lOURIER JUNE 1997
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
H E R I T A 6 E
> î)' 1 .1 L^jfc
The body, which is the cen¬
trepiece of classical statuary, dis¬
appears stiffly behind the drap¬
ery of costumes. The rules of
anatomy are abolished. The fig¬
ures are squat and impassive, the
forms devoid of substance. In
these hieratic carvings the folds of
garments form regular patterns in
a blend of Greek and Oriental
styles. The composition is harmo¬
niously structured, but all sense
of movement is frozen. Lively
scenes are rare. This is static, not
dramatic, art. Domestic scenes are
shown on panels above sarcophagi.
Rut rather than lively Hellenistic
banquets these are group por¬
traits where figures rub shoulders
yet remain solitary. The standing
figures rise like ornamental
columns. Being is consummated in
the inwardness of contemplation.
The religious reliefs are similar
to the funerary statues. Immobile,
alone or aligned as if on parade,
numerous haloed divinities accom¬
panied hy their symbols are shown
standing, seated, in chariots, and
44
> :-i
Veiled women, detail
from a relief in the
shrine of Bel (1st
century A.D.).
sometimes riding horses or camels
in the sanctuaries of Palmyra.
Like the portraits of the dead,
these figures are depicted
frontally, their gaze fixed and
immutable. Often wearing Roman
military uniform, they herald the
future warrior saints of Christian
iconography. In some cases the
inscription giving their names
amounts to no more than an anony¬
mous adjective: one, unique, mer¬
ciful. In one corner a mortal is
depicted beside the god. lie is
the donor, who is piously offering
incense on a fiery altar, in a sym¬
bolic gesture caught hy the artist
who made these religious reliefs.
"And you, streets of Palmyra/
Forests of columns in the immen¬
sity of the desert/What has become
of you?" exclaimed Hölderlin. At
the crossroads of Syria and
Mesopotamia, on the boundary of
the nomadic and sedentary worlds,
the great ruined city has left
these eternal faces as its heritage.
Milestones in a long history
1980: The archaeological site of Palmyra is placed
on Unesco's World Heritage List.
LOCATION:
Horns province, Syrian Arab Republic
215 km northeast of Damascus.
The oasis city of Palmyra is bounded
on the west and north by hills, and opens
onto the desert to the south and east.
The ancient city stretches out to the
northwest; the modern city occupies an
arid plateau northeast of the oasis.
HISTORY:
The oldest tools found at Palmyra
date back some 75,000 years.
Beginning of the second
millennium B.C.: first known mention of
Tadmor, the original name of Palmyra,
still used in Arabic.
3rd century B.C.: Palmyra and its
territory constitute an Arab principality.
1st century B.C.: The city is under
Roman tutelage.
Around 129: The Emperor Hadrian
makes Palmyra a "free city".
2nd century: Palmyra's golden age.
The city's trading links stretch as far as
India and China in the east, and to Italy
in the west.
Mid-third century: The situation of
the Roman empire deteriorates; Palmyra
enjoys a certain independence; Odainat,
member of a family of Arab stock,
ennobled by Septimius Severus, becomes
"Imperator", and is therebyinvested
with authority in this part of the empire.
He proclaims himself King of Kings.
268: On the death of Odainat, his
son and heir, Wahballat, is too young to
govern. Wahballat's mother, Zenobia,
exercises power with the title of most
illustrious queen. She invades Egypt.
270: The army of Palmyra occupies
Antioch, capital of Syria.
272: Roman troops led by Aurelian
enter Syria. Zenobia defends the Syrian
capital. The queen breaks with Rome and
proclaims herself "Augusta". In August,
Palmyra capitulates. Aurelian
establishes a garrison there and leaves
the city.
Spring 273: Fresh outbreak of revolt
at Palmyra. The garrison is massacred.
Aurelian returns in haste and sacks the
city. Zenobia and her son are taken to
Rome as captives. Palmyra never recovers
from this defeat.
Late 3rd century: Diocletian makes
Palmyra part of the eastern limes, the
network of routes and military posts
protecting the empire against the
Persians.
Around 400, during the reign of
Arcadius, Palmyra recovers some of its
importance.
6th century: The Ghassanid Arab
dynasty, allied to the Byzantines,
dominates the Syrian desert. The
emperor Justinian takes a keen interest
in Palmyra, renovates it, surrounds it
with fortifications, provides it with
water, and instáis a garrison.
634:Khaledibnal-Walid,oneof
the generals of the first caliph, Abu
Bakr, takes Palmyra, which again
becomes Tadmor. During the first
centuries of Islam the city graduallyfalls
into oblivion.
12th century: A new period of
prosperity begins under governor Yusuf
ibn Fairiiz. Major renovation work.
1264: Horns and Palmyra fall
under the sway of the Mamluk sultan
Baybars.
1401: Tamerlane sends troops which
sack the city.
16th-19th centuries: Under Ottoman
domination, the city's decline
accelerates. Palmyra is reduced to a
village, at the mercy of nomad tribes.
17th century: European travellers
visit the ruins of Palmyra and make
enthusiastic descriptions of them.
18th century: The English
explorers James Dawkins and Robert
Wood, in 1751, and the French
philosopher Volney, in 1787, reveal
to the world the splendour of the
forgotten site.
the unesco Courier june 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Ancient and modern Egypt
come face to facebySamirGharib
Prestigious archaeological sites
threatened by urban encroachment
Above, the pyramids
and the nearby outskirts of
Cairo.
! In the last few years rampant population
growth and urban sprawl have combined
to pose an increasingly serious threat to Egypt's
archaeological monuments and sites. The ugly
side-effects of urban development water, air
and noise pollution, constant vibrations and dam¬
age to the environment are well known to all
the world's city-dwellers.
Cairo's older inhabitants remember that only
fifty years ago the main road to the pyramids,
beginning in Giza Square, ran through fields
before reaching the pyramids in the desert. At
that time the pyramids could be seen eight kilo¬
metres away. Now only a forest of buildings is
visible from Giza Square.
Traffic congestion choked the road so severely
that another road was built parallel to it,
encroaching on farmland which was replaced by
more bottlenecks and anarchic ribbon building.
There are no ear park facilities or garages in
these settlements and in some cases there is no
running water. In the absence of any kind of town
planning, using these two roads can be a hair-
raising experience.
To improve the links between Cairo and the
new towns around it, the idea was raised of build¬
ing a huge ring road, 95 kilometres long and 42
metres wide, at a cost of one billion Egyptian
pounds. The route of the highway would take it
very near the Giza pyramids an area which has
been on UlMîSC.o's World Heritage hist since 1979.
Nonetheless work on the ring road began in 1986,
without prior consultation with the World Her¬
itage Committee and in flagrant violation of
Egyptian heritage law, which protects land that
might contain historic monuments.
The alarm was sounded in 1 994 hy the British
daily The Independent, which drew attention to
the risks posed by the road to any monuments
that might be buried in an area where no archae¬
ological research had yet been done. As a result of
the debate triggered by the press and subsequent
3 Courier |une 1997 nthe unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
> TJlNUSCO intervention, work was suspended until An obelisk at Luxor,
the completion of a study by an expert committee.
This was not the first round in the fight to
preserve the plateau of the Pyramids. In the
late 1980s UlNIÏSCO sent an expert committee to
draw up a project to protect the area, including
restoration of the Sphinx and construction of a
wall between the archaeological site and the
nearby villages of Nazlet Essallab and Kafr Elga-
bal, which had been joined together by urban
growth. The project was abandoned, however,
in face of a storm of protest from local interest
groups.
THE THREAT TO LUXOR
The pyramids are not the only pharaonic remains
harmed hy urbanization. Luxor, one of the
world's most prestigious historic cities, is also
threatened. The site includes the temple of Kar-
nak, the temple of Luxor itself and the Road of
the Rams that joins them on the east bank of
the Nile, and on the west bank the Valley of the
Queens, with the temple of Ilatshepsut and the
tomb of Nefcrtiti, and the Valley of the Kings.
Until recently, pedestrians had to take a ferry
to cross the river and motor traffic had to make
a detour through the distant town of Esna where
a bridge spans the Nile. The idea of building a
bridge at Luxor was first raised in 1972 and was
adopted in 1982. The chosen site was located
north of the town, seven kilometres from the Val¬
ley of the Kings.
Supporters of the project poirtted to the many
services the bridge would perform for the com¬
munity and especially its role in encouraging
industrial development in the nearby town of
Armante, the centre of the region's sugar indus¬
try, hy making road haulage possible for the
enormous output of the sugar cane fields. The
bridge would also reduce the distance between
Aswan and Cairo by almost 100 kilometres.
The project was decreed to be in the public
interest in 1990, and work began. Five years and
25 million Egyptian pounds later, with the bridge
nearly complete, came a bombshell. It was
revealed in the press that the bridge's existence
might destroy all the archaeological remains on the
west bank. Egyptian artists and scientists joined
forces and called for the work to be halted.
The pharaohs and their builders chose the
site of their final resting place with very great
care. The tombs are on high, dry ground, out of
reach of the floodwaters of the Nile in an area
composed of two overlaid geological strata, a
limestone layer containing the tombs, and a layer
of clay which retains rainwater and atmospheric
humidity in its cracks. Inside the tombs, broad
pillars afford protection against earthquakes.
By saturating the lower clay layers with water,
construction of the bridge exposed them to the
danger of slippage, causing movement of the
upper limestone layers and the collapse of the
temples.
Other arguments drew attention to the risk
that this historic site, whose beauty and
grandiose solitude attract tourists, would be dis¬
figured by commerce and building which would
ultimately discourage tourism. But it is too late;
the bridge has been built.
Strict laws now forbid the encroachment of
urban settlements onto farmland and building on
the west bank of the Nile. The protected area
around monuments has even been extended. But
will these measures be enough to prevent urban
expansion so uncontrolled that it indiscriminately
destroys everything in its path, whether it is crop¬
land or archaeological heritage? M
46 3 QuiTHE UNESCO tpURIER JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
interview Viviane Forrester
e are witnessing a transformation
of society and civilization
French writer Viviane Forrester is a novelist,
literary critic and the author of an award-
winning biography of Van Gogh. Her most
recent book is L'Horreur Economique (1996),
an examination of the tyranny of economics in
the modern world which has become a best¬
seller in France. Forcefully written and well
documented, it paints the picture of a society
in which jobs are disappearing, depriving very
large numbers of people of the opportunity to
earn a living, and denounces the way in which
this situation is being exploited. The book is
currently being translated in some twenty
countries. Here Viviane Forrester talks to Edgar
Reichmann.
You are a novelist and you have a special
interest in English literature, notably the
Bloomsbury group. How did you come to write a
book about economics?
Viviane Forrester: I have never compartmental¬
ized creative activity. All thinking, to my mind,
is political, even when it does not claim to be. I
think that each of us, whatever our walk of life,
should feel concerned about the present state of
the world, which is entirely governed by eco¬
nomics. Isn't this situation inextricably tied up
with politics, in the highest sense of the term? If
Shakespeare were to come back to life today, I
think he would he fascinated by the tragic inter¬
play of powerful economic forces which are
stealthily transforming the lives and destinies of
the citizens or rather the populations of all
countries.
You pillory the optimistic belief that the
current crisiswith its corollary of long-term
unemploymentis temporary. Do you think that
this crisis reflects a major shift?
V.F.: I think it docs. To my mind we are witness¬
ing a profound change, a transformation of soci¬
ety and civilization, and we are finding it very
hard to accept. How can we say good-bye to a
society that was based on stable jobs that pro¬
vided a safety net and the basics of a decent exis¬
tence? Job security is on the way out. In my book
I concentrate on the ways in which this situa¬
tion is being exploited. For the first time in his¬
tory, the vast majority of human beings arc no
longer indispensable to the small number of those
who run the world economy. The economy is
increasingly wrapped up in pure speculation.
The working masses and their cost are becoming
superfluous. In other words, there is something
worst; than actually being exploited and that is
no longer to he even worth exploiting!
It is true that this state of affairs is not being
concealed, but there is a tendency to avoid talking
r i
THE UNESCO ^^pURIER |UNEI997 ~
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
What we are seeing today is economic
globalization and the globalization of
poverty.
about it clearly. In democratic societies, at any
rate, you don't tell people that they are regarded
as superfluous. Under totalitarianism there might
be an even worse danger than joblessness and
poverty. Once salaried work has disappeared, why
should a totalitarian regime not simply eliminate
those forces that have become useless?
What can be done to avoid this terrible
conclusion?
V.F.: In democratic countries there is an urgent
need for vigilance. It is often claimed that the
industrial age, when a regular wage provided the
means of subsistence, can somehow be patched
up. But those days are over. Wage-earning is dis¬
appearing and the panoply of temporary doles
and allowances designed to replace it is shrinking,
something that is nothing less than criminal. The
managers of the economic machine exploit this
situation. Full employment is a thing of the past,
but we still use criteria that were current in the
nineteenth century, or twenty or thirty years ago,
when it still existed. Among other things, this
encourages many unemployed people to feel
ashamed of themselves. This shame has always
been absurd but it is even more so today.
It goes hand in hand with the fear felt by the
privileged who still have a paid job and are afraid
of losing it. I maintain that this shame and this
fear ought to be ([noted on the stock exchange,
because they are major inputs in profit. Once
upon a time people pilloried the alienation
caused by work. Today falling labour costs con¬
tribute to the profits of big companies, whose
favourite management tool is sacking workers;
when they do this, their stock market value soars.
But isn't it possible that the accumulation of
banking and financial wealth, and the widespread
long-term unemployment you talk about may
lead to a so-called leisure society? This was
supposed to happen in the now-defunct Marxist
utopiaeveryone would be rewarded according to
their needs and not only for the work which
brought them a living.
V.F.: We lived for decades with the utopia you
allude to. What we are seeing today is economic
# THE UNESCO COURIER JUNE 1997
globalization and the globalization of poverty.
We are living with this globalization and with
sophisticated technologies that were unimagin¬
able not so lon<¡; aso. Their effects should be ben-
eficial for all of us. In point of fact they are
dreadful. It is essential to find a different way of
living, without necessarily trying to create an
ideal one. I do not think that the planet can
become a paradise, but I would like it at least to
he a home for decent societies in which everyone
is treated with dignity and people respect their
neighbours.
You talk in your book of "virtual markets".
What do you mean by that?
V.F.: I refer to a current form of business trans¬
action in which people deal in what does not
exist. These are transactions which do not involve
real assets, nor even symbols for such assets, hut
where people buy and sell, for example, the risks
involved in contracts which have not yet been
signed or are still being negotiated; where debts
are sold and are later bought and sold on again
and again; where deals are made, involving virtual
values which are already guaranteed: they in
turn give, rise to other contracts based on the
negotiation of the previous ones! In this market
in risks and debts people speculate on specula¬
tion. It is an unreal market, based on illusions.
While I was writing my chapter on this virtual
economy I read through what I had written and
said to myself that it simply couldn't be true,
that I was talking nonsense. The same evening,
former German Chancellor Helmut Schmidt
appeared on French television and confirmed
that a hundred times more deals were made on
these surrealistic markets than on the others.
This is very serious because it is leading us to
an autonomous economy, incapable of creating
real jobs. One person with a fax and a computer
can make this kind of deal, in which no invest¬
ment is required and people make bets, like in a
casino or at the races, on a virtual market which
has nothing to do with the labour market.
But your book also has a lot to say about
wealth creation and the forces behind it.
Virtual markets are leading us to an
economy incapable of creating real jobs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
V.F.: Today we hear a lot about "wealth creation".
In the past it was simply known as profit. Today
people talk about this wealth as if it will auto¬
matically go straight to the community and create
jobs, yet at the same time we see highly prof¬
itable businesses cutting down heavily on their
workforce. When people talk about society's
"movers and shakers", they aren't talking about
the hulk of their country's population but about
business leaders who relocate at the drop of a
hat. Politicians make jobs their priority, but the
Stock Exchange is delighted whenever a big indus¬
trial complex fires workers and gets worried when¬
ever there's the slightest improvement in the
unemployment figures. I wanted to draw people's
attention to this paradox. A company's stock mar¬
ket quotation depends largely on labour costs,
and profit is generated in the last analysis by
reducing the numbers of those who have a job.
What impact is this economic tyranny having
on culture, teaching, education and young
people?
V.F.: The present situation raises a vital question
for the future of the people of our planet, above
all for young people and their future. Today the
great thing is to he "profitable", not "useful".
This raises a very serious question. Should peo¬
ple be profitable in order to "deserve" the right
to live? The commonsense answer is that it is a
good thing to he useful to society. But we are
preventing people from being useful, we are
squandering the energies of young people by
regarding profitability as the be-all and end-all.
Most countries have lost their sense of priorities.
There is a greater and greater need for teachers
and medical staff, but governments are increas¬
ingly aggressive towards them. These are the
professions where posts are abolished and fund¬
ing is cut. Yet they are indispensable to the wel¬
fare and future of humanity. This confusion
between "usefulness" and "profitability" is dis¬
astrous for the future of the planet.
Young people live in a society which still
regards salaried employment as the only accept¬
able, honest and lawful way of life, but most of
them are deprived of the opportunity to achieve
this. In deprived inner city areas this is a major
problem. At the same time I often meet young
people with armfuls of degrees who are out of
work. What inexcusable waste! For generations
study was young people's initiation into social life.
I admire young people today because they go on
with their studies fully aware that they are run¬
ning the risk of rejection by society.
Twenty-odd years ago, during a writers' forum
in Austria, there was great amusement when one
of the speakers asked the audience (who came
from many countries) whether they had ever
heard of a French poet named Mallarmé. A later
speaker was indignant about our laughter. He
mentioned a number of brand names, none of
which we had ever heard of. They were makes of
rifles and machine guns. He was from a country
of the South, then plunged in civil war, where 90
per cent of the people knew the names of these
weapons but no one would ever have heard of
Mallarmé. I heard myself saying that if the users
of these machine guns, African peasant farmers,
the young people of Latin America and most of
the unqualified workers of Europe have never
heard of Mallarmé, it's not all their fault: they
don't have the opportunity. Some have machine
guns; others have the time to read Mallarmé!
That's another crime! The works of writers such
Should people be profitable in order to
"deserve" the right to live?
as Mallarmé, Senghor, Omar Khayam, Kafka,
Proust or Virginia Woolf should not he the priv¬
ilege of an elite. They break down the walls that
imprison us. Understanding the work of these
creative artists makes us freer, less blind and
less deaf. Their work helps to broaden our hori¬
zons, sharpen our thinking and open our minds,
the only way to a critical, clear-thinking outlook
and to effective action. Then someone at the
meeting stood up and shouted: "Mallarmé is a
machine gun!"
Your analysis deals primarily with the
situation in the industrialized countries. What
about the developing world?
V.F.: This is something about which the West
ought to feel heartily ashamed! It behaved rapa¬
ciously in the countries it colonized, and today it
closes its frontiers to their people who come
looking for menial jobs in order to survive, under
the pretext that they would make the unem¬
ployment figures worse. Even if there was an iota
of truth in this allegation in fact there is none
this kind of immigration can never be as preda¬
tory as the former colonial powers were, and
sometimes still are, in continents ravaged by
THE UNESCO ÇïURlER |UNE 1997 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Young people are being robbed of the chance
ofsalaried employment.
famine, pandemics and civil war. Those who try,
in some countries of the North, to convince pub¬
lic opinion that immigration causes unemploy¬
ment, divert attention from the truth. In the
North it is the relocation of certain industries and
the flight of capital that are increasingly causing
and perpetuating unemployment.
Only twenty or thirty years ago, there was
still reason to hope that the relative prosperity
of the North would spread all over the world.
Today we are seeing the globalization of poverty.
Businesses based in the North that set up in the
so-called "developing" countries, do not create
jobs for the people of those countries hut gen¬
erally make them work without any kind of social
security protection, in medieval conditions. The
reason is that the workforce underpaid women
and children, as well as prisoners costs less than
automation would cost in the country of origin.
This is colonization in another, equally heinous,
form.
In spite of your pessimism, do you see any
solutions on the horizon different from those that
led to totalitarianism?
V.F.: I am not pessimistic, far from it. The pes¬
simists are those who say there is no alternative
to the present situation, that we have no choice.
My book is an attempt to describe what is going
on. It's true that the situation is dramatic. All the
same I am, like many other people, the citizen of
a country whose democratic regime makes it pos¬
sible to reflect and freely resist the growing pres¬
sure that the economic factor is exerting on our
lives. By endlessly going on about the dictatorial
system that prevailed until recently in part of
Europe and elsewhere, some people want us to
think that the terrible failure of the U.S.S.R.
justifies the economic horrors facing us. This is
a kind of blackmail.
I would like there to be checks and balances,
alternative thinking, conflicts of ideas and inter¬
ests. Not violent conflict, of course, hut we
should wake up and stop being petrified, pris¬
oners of hackneyed thinking. Already in coun¬
tries where my book is being translated espe¬
cially in the United States, Brazil, Mexico,
Lithuania, Poland and in others such as the
Republic of Korea it is causing something of a
stir even before publication. Articles are appear¬
ing, people are asking me questions, friends of
mine who read French are asking for copies.
I am neither against the globalization of
exchanges, nor the emergence of new technolo¬
gies. Such an attitude would be absurd. But I am
against their being taken over by a tiny minority
of economic power centres, often in private
hands, whereas entire populations are excluded
from social progress. I am against the globaliza¬
tion of rejection and poverty and for the global¬
ization of well-being. I
AUTHORS
FRANÇOIS-BERNARD HUYGHE is a French writer who
teaches media sociology in Pans. His most recent
published work ¡s tes Experts (Plön, Paris, 1996).
GERAtD MESSADIÉ is a French historian, essayist
and novelist who has written extensively on the
history of religions. Among his works published in
English are A History of the Devil (1996), Great
Scientific Discoveries (1992) and Great Modern
Inventions (1992).
ROBERT DARNTON, an American historian, is Davis
Professor of European History at Princeton
University, New Jersey. He is the author of numerous
books on 18th-century European history and culture,
including, most recently, The Forbidden Best-Sellers of
Pre-Revolutionary France (HarperCollins, 1995).
Y0USS0UF TATA CISSE, a Malian ethnologist, is a
researcher at the French National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS). He is the author of Soundyata, la
gloire du Mall (Karthala, Paris, 1991).
SALAHGUEMRICHE, an Algerian journalist and writer,
is a specialist in communication questions in North
African societies. Among his recent published works is
a historical novel, Un amour de dyi/iad (Balland, Paris,
1995).
J.C. NYÍRI, of Hungary, is professor of philosophy at
the Eötvos Loránd University of Budapest and
director of the Institute of Philosophy of the
Hungarian Academy of Sciences. Notable among his
published works is Tradition and Individuality (1992).
tOUISE MERZEAU, of France, Is lecturer in
information and communication sciences at the
University of Paris X-Nanterre.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental questions.
MAHMOUD ZIBAWI is a Lebanese painter and writer.
He has published two monographs on the arts of
eastern Christianity, L'icône, sens et histoire (Pans,
1993) and Orients chrétiens, entre Byzance et l'Islam
(Paris, 1995).
SAMIR GHARIB, of Egypt, is a journalist and art critic.
EDGAR REICHMANN ¡s a novelist and literary critic.
His most recent novel, Nous n'irons plus a Slls Maria
was published in 1995 by Denoèl, Paris.
50
THE UNESCO (oURIIER JUNE 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Paulo Freiré
(1921-1997)
Paulo Freiré has left us, and with his passing something has gone from the
world's classrooms; on every continent teachers have felt, perhaps uncon¬
sciously, a moment's sadness before returning to their task with renewed
force and conviction.
He taught autonomy, hope to the oppressed. He knew, like Bolivar, that
education is the key to freedom. Paulo Freiré, teacher of liberation,
was imprisoned and exiled by those who fear men and women in control
of their destiny.
Paulo Freiré was driven by the urgency of change: he never forgot that,
as Salvador Ortiz-Carboneres has written, "the night is long for those who
wait for the light of day."
Technology, yes, but above all, tenderness. Above all, smUes and affec¬
tion to avoid the cold, demented world of machines. Shaping attitudes,
helping people achieve sovereignty over themselves. A critical sover¬
eignty, guided by lodestars that are neither bought nor sold.
A few months ago, I wrote the following lines in his biobibliography:
"Paulo Freiré 's long and brilliant trajectory in the art of teaching has made
him a legendary figure. The only pedagogy is that of love and anxiety.
That which leads all human beings, men and women, to assume their
responsibilities, to make decisions without outside interference, to walk
a tightrope between shade and light, between mist and radiance wher¬
ever freedom is the essence, the culmination and the reason of each Ufe."
One April day in 1995, in a little village in southern Sudan, I dedicated
a poem to my friend Paulo, the teacher of teachers: "Surrounded for¬
ever/by mangroves/baobabs and acacias/I shall think only of your
eyes/eyes of a wounded gazelle/girl of solitude/and distance. /I go away/cov¬
ered with mud and straw,/for your hut/now/occupies/all the spaces/of my
house./Our houses overflowing/and yours destitute./I must not forget/that
all the rest/ is unimportant./Ah, to remember/Your hut/full of love and
smiles!"
The giants of the intellect die but do not disappear. They simply become
invisible. Theirs is the most important of all lessons: they set us an
example.
Federico Mayor
Paris, 4 May 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
THEME OF OUR JULY-AUGUST DOUBLE ISSUE:
THE IMAGE OF WOMEN
IN CHILDREN'S LITERATURE
INTERVIEW
MSTISLAV ROSTROPOVICH
HERITAGE
TEOTIHUACAN, the city of the gods (Mexico)
ENVIRONMENT
FORESTS: THE EARTH'S GREEN LUNGS
AND
FOR HOLIDAY LIGHT READING...
JOIN EXTRATERRESTRIAL VISITORS
ON A MISSION TO UNLOCK...
UNESCO'S SECRET
]]>
</page>
</document>
