<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="109515eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
0)
w
UNESC©
OUR1E
DOUBLE ISSUE
UNESCO'S
SECRET
A TRUE
LIKENESS?
PORTRAITS OF WOMEN
IN YOUNG PEOPLE'S
LITERATURE
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTER SV
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture
or any other subject which seems
to be an example of cultural
cross-fertilization.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking '
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
THE WORLD
1997, terracotta
(height: 70 cm, depth: 45 cm,
width: 45 cm)
by Marie Mathias
This upbeat work by the
French sculptor Marie
Mathias inspired the
following comment from
critic Fernand Gamier: "All
born from the same clay and
held in the hands of an
invisible creator, these
children represent the
infinite wealth of faces that
live on earth and whose
harmonious intermingling
can be the source of love."
£> Mane Mathias, Grenoble (Frant
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (ou RIER
Mstislav Rostropovich, the great Russian
cellist and conductor, talks about hispassion
for music (p. 95).
Teotihuacán (Mexico), capital ofa
mysteriouspre-Columbian civilization, is
Mesoamerica's most colossal archaeological
site (p. 84).
contents
JULY-AUGUST 1997
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
A TRUE
PORTRAITS OF WOMEN IN YOUNG PEOPLE'S LITERATURE
japan Breaking the stereotype by Akiko Sueyoshi	
east áfrica Silent partners by Evangeline Ledi Barongo .
former USSR From ideology to love by Julia Prosalkova .
north America Mothers and daughters by Elke Liebs . . .
Dossier	
6
10
13
16
20
Consultant: Zelikha Abou Richa
UNESCO'S
SECRET
ANLBRZANDZKRR
ADVENTURE
byAlteau and Charles Doxuan 21
Declaration by Federico Mayor 73
Sarajevo's battered soul by Pascale d'Erm	76
Albania's threatened heritage by Ylljet Aliçka 78
GREENWATCH Forests: a breathing space for the planet by France Bequette .... 80
84
The divine faces of Teotihuacán by Cécile Romane
UNESCO IN ACTION Adult education for tomorrow by Christopher Mcintosh	88
REFLECTIONS Letters from Asia by Denis Sinor	91
AUTHORS	98
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR 98
Cover:
Above: drawing by Alteau © (/«emu com-
Below: drawing by Celia Johnson © sis. pans
THE UNESCO lOURIER |LILY-AUGUST 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TBfc. UNESCO
Courier
^*^ 50th YEAR
Published monthly in 29 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational. Scientific and
Cultural Organization
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Pans CEDEX 15, France
Fax (33) (0)1 45 68 57.45
e-mail unesco couner@unesco org
Internet. httpV/www unesco org
Director Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition. Roy Malkm
French edition Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbma
Features Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations Ariane Bailey (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 90}
Documentation; José Banaag
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press
Solange Beim (Tel (33) (0) 1.45.68 46 87)
Film duplication- Daniel Meister
Secretariat Annie Brächet
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68.47.15),
Administrative Assistant. Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian. Irina Utkma (Moscow)
German: Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian- Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian AkbarZargar (Teheran)
Dutch: Bart Christiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro}
Urdu: Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili: Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese Feng Mmgxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek- Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala* Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Rutta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque JuxtoEgaña(Donostia)
Thai: Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese. Do Phuong (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa Ahyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian Volodymyr Vasilmk (Kiev)
Gahcian Xabier Senín Fernandez (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
Subscriptions: Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 45 65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Din
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 49 19)
Customer service Michel Ravassard,
(Tel (33) (0)1,45.68 45.91)
Accounts (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 65)
Shipping Daniel Meister (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 47 50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel.: (33) (0)1 45 68 45 65
lyear 211 French francs 2 years* 396 FF.
Students lyear 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries.
lyear 132 French francs 2 years 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
dale of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author s name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
UNtsco Courier staff The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700
Paris (2) University Microfilms [Xerox) Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100
U S A . (3) N C R Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc , 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U S A , (4) Bell and Howell Co , Old Mansfield Road.
Wooster, Ohio 44691, USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL* Cl JULY/AUGUST 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M P.P
Photocomposition, photogravure:
Le Coumerde I'Unesco
Impression MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.I Roule d'Étampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 7/8-199 7-OPI-9 7-561 A
This issue comprises 100 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 98-99.
dQ>u RIlRB JULY AUGUST I9">7
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Month by month
by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat
In August 1947 Unesco began to publish a news bulletin about its activ¬
ities. Its title was the Unesco Monitor, and it was the forerunner of
the Unesco Courier, which began publication in February 1948.
That was half a century ago. Today, leafing through thefifty volumes
of the Cbí/ríerthat stand on our shelves, we can retrace, page by page,
a unique journey through the intellectual history of our time. This
body of reading probably has no equivalent in the international press.
How many magazines can claim to have opened their columns to so many
notable figures from so many of the world's cultures, gradually build¬
ing up over the years a kind of encylopaedia of the age's intellectual
life and its achievements in the sciences and the arts?
All those who have lent a hand are justly proud of their association
with this long and painstaking enterprise. One thing that none of
them can forget is that the Courier's Odyssey is first and foremost
Unesco's. If the Courier has been able to capture and harness the fair
winds of intelligence, it is because they have blowninto Unesco's sails.
What is Unesco's ultimate purpose? Torn between dreams of utopia
and the obligations of an intergovernmental organization, reconciling
the day-to-day demands of hundreds of field projects worldwide with
the principles laid down for it by its founders, does it exist to serve a
thousand different goals or a single one? In this issue we have asked
Alteau, a talented young cartoonist, and Doxuan, story-teller and
humorist, to answer this question in a form that we hope you will find
both visually and intellectually entertaining.
A year ago we gave twenty young cartoonists carte blanche to
draw the image of Unesco as they saw it. In the present issue we
invite readers on a journey of investigation that will take them to the
heart of Unesco and reveal the coherence of the ideals that are its
lifeblood.
THC UNESCO (oUKlERB JULY AUGUST 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
poñráts oj women
Japan
Breaking the stereotype
in young people's literature
1oW°
Ikiko Sueyoshi's Mama no
kiiroi kozô ("Mummy's little
yellow elephant", 1985) tells
the story of a divorce fro m
the children's point of view.
Above, the cover design. Left,
an illustration by Satoshi
Nakachi.
BYAKIKOSUEYOSHI
Japanese children's literature came into
being in the second decade of this cen¬
tury. The first literary review to be entirely
devoted to it, Akai tori ("The Bluebird"),
appeared in 191 8. The country was then enjoy¬
ing a period of prosperity, and the liberal cur¬
rent of opinion known as "Taishô democracy"
was in the ascendant. In education, efforts were
being made to develop children's characters and
creativity by introducing them to artistic activ¬
ities, and the emergence of books written specif¬
ically for children seems to have reflected soci¬
ety's sudden upsurge of interest in them. To
begin with, however, the authors were exclu¬
sively male, and women did not play any of
the leading roles in their stories.
Kenji Miyazawa, for instance, ignored
women almost completely. In "Matasaburô
the Wind" (1939), the predominance of male
characters is flagrant. The main character is a
little boy who has just started primary school
in his village. His father features in the story
but his mother never appears, and although the
teacher is not identified, it is evident from the
language he uses that he is a man, while nearly
all the schoolchildren who are named are boys.
There is a similar preponderance of male char¬
acters in "Night Train in the Milky Way",
which tells the story of a young boy's encoun¬
ters aboard a night train, and in "The Life
Story of GusukôBudori" (1941). This imbal¬
ance is understandable in view of the fact that,
at the time, Japanese women had neither real
social position nor employment.
Watarôsan to ushi ("Mr Watarô and the
Cow", 1942), the only one of Nankichi
THE UNESCO (7>URIER I |ULY AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
" I he emergence of books
written specifically for
children reflected Japanese
society's sudden upsurge of
interest in them."
Niimi's highly popular children's stories to
feature a female character, is particularly illu¬
minating about this situation. The main char¬
acter, who lives with his aged mother and an
equally aged cow, is a good sort, but his fond¬
ness for the bottle all too often leads him
astray. Fortunately, his cow knows its way
home and always brings him back when he is
in his cups, acting in this respect like a prop¬
erly dutiful wife. For that reason, Mr Watarô
has no need of a wife, but the reader learns in
the course of the story that when he was
young he had a beautiful, hard-working wife.
At one point, however, he had by force of cir¬
cumstances to choose between his wife and
his old mother, and he unhesitatingly chose to
separate from his wife, whom he sent back to
her family, and look after his mother.
One of Kusurô Makimoto's children's sto¬
ries, Haha no hi ("Mothers' Day", 1937), is
probably the first to have taken the mother's
role as its central theme. On Mothers' Day,
three children prepare the meal in place of their
mother. She is at first delighted but at the same
time confused, since it is traditionally the
woman's role to do all the household jobs,
and with nothing left to do she soon becomes
bored. The next day, things return to normal
and the mother goes about her work, unques-
tioningly and in silence. The idea that she could
have had a hobby or outside interest seems
never to have crossed the author's mind.
I Women take up thepen
It was not until after the war that things began
to change, when women turned to writing
themselves. The image of motherhood became
more substantial but still remained within the
bounds of the role assigned to mothers by
society.
In Momoko Ishii's Non-chan kumo ni
noru ("Non-chan goes up in the clouds",
1947), for example, a little girl who thinks
that her mother has betrayed her over some
trivial matter runs away from home in tears
and falls in a pond on the surface of which
the clouds are reflected. When she comes'
round, she finds herself on a cloud, where she
meets the old "guardian of the clouds". The
story gives the author a chance to describe a
typical Japanese middle-class family of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
time. Non-chan's father is a white-collar
worker and her mother, though a housewife,
is an educated woman and a talented singer. It
later transpires that she would have liked to go
to a school of music, no doubt in the hope of
turning professional, but she is quite happy in
her role of mistress of the house and mother,
and harbours no dreams of venturing outside
the home.
In the 1960s, there was an unprecedented
boom in children's literature. More and more
books were written by women and they con¬
tained more and more female characters the
portrayal of women by women who were
attempting to make young children aware of
what adult life could be like, involving such
unthinkable and absurd events as divorce and
death.
One example of this trend is Chiisai
Momo-chan ("Little Momo-chan", 1964),
which is also the first story to feature a work¬
ing woman. Momo-chan's mother has cho¬
sen to go out to work and has to put her
daughter in a crèche thus proving her to be
a determined woman, since at that time only
the children of single-parent or poor families
were sent to such institutions. Momo-chan's
adventures have remained popular with chil¬
dren and women ever since.
The main character in Toshiko Kanzawa's
Harapcko onabc ("The empty-bellied stew-
In Keiko Takada's Zawameki
yamanai ("Constant
murmurs", 1989), a mother is
tormented by doubts about the
purpose of her life. Left, the
cover illustration.
pot", 1969) is an old cooking pot who has
had enough of feeding other people and
decides to go off and eat lots of delicious
things, despite the efforts of the other kitchen
utensils to try and stop her. In a postscript, the
author, who is a woman, explains that her aim
in telling this story was to describe the "heart's
never-satisfied yearning" and the "sudden feel¬
ing of emptiness that may come over a house¬
wife who spends all her time working for her
husband and children". The fact that Hara¬
pcko onabe is not a work of realism no doubt
made it easier for Toshiko Kanzawa to express
a housewife's dreams and longings.
Career women and
bluestockings
In the 1970s, it was still difficult for women
to combine housekeeping and a career, and
people still looked askance upon single career
women. Yoshiko Okkotsu's Jttsansainonatsu
("The summer of my thirteenth year", 1974)
shows the stereotyped image of the unmarried
woman as a frigid bluestocking.
Little Rie's mother dies in childbirth, and
her father, a feckless drunkard, starts wom¬
anizing. Rie is taken in by her old aunt, an
unmarried teacher of English, who spends her
time reading weighty tomes in a foreign lan¬
guage and never has a kind word for her.
Finally, Rie can no longer bear the icy atmos¬
phere she lives in and runs away to live with her
father's current mistress, a fat, vulgar, unedu¬
cated hairdresser in a working-class suburb
who nevertheless welcomes her with open
arms.
From the 1980s onwards, it became normal
for women to go out to work and they no
longer had to make the choice between their
job and their home. The fathers who appear in
children's books of this period all fit the
stereotype of the career-obsessed man who
devotes all his time to his work and his busi¬
ness relationships and has no time for his-
home and family. More and more stories about
divorce paralleling what was happening in
society appeared at this time.
In Mama no kiiroikozô ("Mummy's little
yellow elephant", 1985), I told the story of a
divorce from the children's viewpoint. The
couple split up because of the husband's infi¬
delity. The mother then passes her driving test
and buys an old car to broaden her horizons.
j QuTHE UNISCO I OURItRl IIILY AUCUST CW7
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
She does her best to get along without her
husband, but it's not easy. She gets into several
scrapes and even causes a road accident. Her
adventures are presented as comedy, but she is
nevertheless shown as trying to win her inde¬
pendence.
Some authors still write about the woman
who is victimized by her husband and family
but whose life revolves around her home. In
7.awam eki yamanai ("Constant murmurs",
-t i>>
£' {, h
i CO f
T- ¿a A.
X
- 7°
A. 1
t-
1- A,
h
il
i-
>
il
i_ ^
i
L
tz
il
l±
<
h
>
A,
x-
<
CD
il
h
n
a
?
r
L
tz
en
il
X -r
L
u
<
<
r>
b
<
A.
V
-t
^
li
L
¿a
A
il
h
r>
tz
IZ
ti
V
T
L
1989), Kciko Takada gives a good description
of such a woman, tormented by doubts about
the validity of the life she is leading. She is a
conscientious mother who dutifully runs the
household and brings up the children. She has
followed her husband as he was posted from
one place to another, taking charge of the
removal each time and making great efforts to
adapt to each new environment. Her husband
gives her no help around the house. They had
two children, but the younger has died of an
illness brought on by pollution and she feels
guilty about the child's death.
Her only rebellious reaction is to drink
¿
t
<-
A.
X"
h
Vi
tz
-t
A,
x-
Above right, the cover of
Miyoko Matsutani's Chiisai
Momo-chan ("Little Momo-
chan", 1964), the first
Japanese children's book In
which the heroine, a working
mother, leaves her child at a
day-care centre.
Above left, Momo-chan and her
mother. An illustration by
Sadao Kikuchi.
heavily and engage in recriminations until
the day when she walks out, leaving a note
explaining to her husband that she wants to be
on her own for three months to try and sort
herself out. The husband, finding himself
alone and incapable of looking after the
domestic arrangements, calls in his mother-
in-law. Three months later, the wife returns
as promised. As a result of this escapade, the
husband finally realizes the importance of
family life, and the marriage gets off to a fresh
start.
In the 1970s and 1980s, nearly all the chil¬
dren's books that dealt with the problems fac¬
ing women in society were written by women,
but the situation has changed since the early
1990s, when some male authors started to take
an interest in women's issues. One of them is
Hiko Tanaka, whose Kalendâ ("Calendar",
1992) contrasts the women of his grandpar¬
ents' generation, whose lives were only the
lives of "daughters, wives and mothers", with
those of the younger generation, for whom "a
different life exists". M
THE UNESCO COURIER« [ULY AUGUST 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
East áfrica
Silent partners
BY EVANGELINE LEDI BARONGO
B«>elow(from left to right),
3 children's books from East
Africa: Okot p'Bitek's Song of
Lawino and Song of Ocol, a
study of the conflict between
traditional African cultures
and Western ways; Hare and
Hornbill, an anthology of
stories inspired by the oral
tradition; A Son of Kabira, a
best-seller by Ugandan novelist
Davis Sebukima.
For centuries, children in East African
countries gathered around the fire, usu¬
ally after their evening meal, to listen to sto¬
ries told by their grandparents. Boys learned
about the exploits of brave men and legendary
hunters, while girls learned the secrets of a
successful marriage.
Today this tradition is disappearing. "Mod¬
ernized" stories for children are told in class¬
rooms, libraries and clubs by teachers and
librarians. Many parents and grandparents no
longer have the time to sit around the fire
telling stories, and even if they did, the
extended family is contracting. Most children
no longer live in villages with their grandpar¬
ents but with their parents in cities and towns.
One consequence of these changes is that
traditional stories are being passed down to the
next generation through a growing body of
children's books and the children's sections of
daily newspapers such as the Kampala (Uganda)
New Vision. Most of the books are published
in English, but quite a number are being writ¬
ten in the major African languages, especially
Kiswahili. The stories arc mainly based on
myths, folklore and legends, although some
of them contain sharp social commentary.
The authors tend to use their writing to send
a message to teach, criticize, or try to correct a
social injustice. Most try to help children to
learn about themselves and their community,
explaining how they arc expected to behave now
and when they become adults. Their books are
based on strong moral precepts.
My daughter is my fortune
The image of women as a commodity is pcrva- '
sivc. A Son ofKabira, a popular book by Ugan¬
dan author Davis Sebukima, tells the story of a
preacher, Nanziri, who says of his daughter, "I
shall make a fortune out of her." His attitude is
in line with traditional practice, especially in
rural areas, where daughters may be sold in mar¬
riages that make their parents a fortune.
In the same book, the author describes an
argument between two co-wives about the
best way to celebrate the homecoming of their
husband's son. When the husband intervenes,
he says, "Don't start shouting now, you will
disturb my head. It is as if you were beating a
drum in it." The women immediately stop
arguing and go away because they know their
husband has no interest in what they have to
say. He alone will decide what is to be done.
Solomon E.K. Mpalanyi's Ndikumma
Okolya also shows women meekly accepting
their subordinate role. When one of the char¬
acters tells her friends that her husband mis¬
treats her and probably has a lover, they are
unsympathetic and laugh at her predicament.
They agree that her husband's behaviour is
Okotp'Bitek^anô**
song of
lawino
©W»
inewa'
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
wrong, but tell her that she must put up with
it as a normal part of married life. In the local
language in which the book was written, they
say, "Take care, friend, your husband can beat
you up with your own stick."
Another image offered to child readers is
that of woman as a family servant. In one story
by Davis Sebukima, a carpenter with two wives
receives a visit from the village chief, whereupon
he calls his first wife and asks her to bring some
beer. The first wife is preparing lunch and so
the carpenter orders his second wife to serve the
beer. She is busy with the housework, but she
stops what she is doing, docs as she is asked
and, as tradition demands, kneels down, fills
the glasses and serves the men. She remains seated
and refills the glasses when the men empty them
until her co-wife brings in the lunch.
The message is that the woman must serve
the man. When the chief arrived, the carpenter's
wives were busy. He was doing nothing and
could easily have fetched the beer himself. But
this is not a husband's job, and so he ordered
his subservient wives to do it for him.
In Fixions, first published in Nairobi in
1969, Taban lo Liyong writes about an old
man so rich that he had married sixty-five
wives who had cost him 8,000 head of cattle in
bride price. Here the author is telling young
readers that a man's wealth, status, prestige
IYI other and son at a book
fair in Nairobi (Kenya).
and social respectability are judged by the
number of wives he has. This reflects the tra¬
ditional linkage in this part of Africa between
a man's wealth and the number of his wives. In
a predominantly peasant economy, this is
hardly surprising. The more wives a man has,
the more hands he has at his disposal to labour
in the fields and create wealth for him.
A recent book of talcs for young and adult
readers, IjukaKabumba's The Wedding Ring
and Other Stories (Kampala, 1992) describes a
conflict about land ownership between two
co-wives, Buyanja and Buhcsi. Their husband,
Gyenda, arbitrarily decides that all the land
is his alone and that neither of the wives has
any claim to it. They are to use the land to
produce food and crops to sell, but nothing
must be sold without his permission and any
money they make must be handed over to
him. He is also in charge of their recreation.
"I shall use my discretion to decide which of
you will accompany me to parties," he says.
Another story tells how Buyanja decides to
leave Gyenda and go back to her parents. How¬
ever, her father immediately decides to pack
her off back to her husband, without listen¬
ing to her or consulting his wife.
Both of these episodes underline one of
the dominant male attitudes in Uganda and in
Africa in general: wives, daughters, sisters and
THE UNESCO (oURIER |ULY AUGUST 1007 J
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
women are not usually seen as decision mak¬
ers. This belief is formed at an early age, and
backed up by stories such as these.
African traditionalist or
Western copycat?
The main character in Okot p'Bitek's Song of
Lawino (Nairobi, 1972) is a young woman
named Lawino whose husband, Ocol, has had
a Western education. Their home is the scene of
a clash between traditional African culture rep¬
resented by Lawino and modern culture rep¬
resented by Ocol. Ocol recites a litany of com¬
plaints against his wife. She can't dance foreign
dances like the rumba and the samba; she has
an old-fashioned hair-do; she still cooks with
firewood instead of a Primus stove; she doesn't
know the names of the months; she doesn't
have a Christian name and is ignorant of the
word of God contained in the "Clean Book"
(the Bible).
Lawino begs her husband to understand
her and to respect their African culture. She
tries to get him to appreciate the beauty of
traditional dances and her Acholi hairstyle.
She tells him that the clay pots she uses for
cooking millet cannot be used on Primus
stoves, and adds that she knows the names of
the calendar months perfectly well, but only
in her people's Acholi language. Acholi names
like hers, she says, arc full of significance
because they convey messages, commemorate
events and bestow honour and recognition
for service to society. Christian names lack this
kind of significance.
The Song ofLawino is a powerful defence
of African culture, especially the culture and
respectability of the African woman, who is
depicted as a conservative traditionalist.
A very different image is presented In
Joseph Buruga's book, The Abandoned Hut
f\ Ugandan schoolteacher
marks her pupils' exercises.
L
^.lùLùL A . ^
(Nairobi, 1972), which portrays the African
woman as a copycat of European cultures, val¬
ues and life-styles.
Buruga tells the story of a man who asks a
woman named Basia why she has rejected him.
Without waiting for an answer he tells her
how he prefers his own culture and hates it
being adulterated by alien values like those
that have "spoilt" her. "Oh, Basia," he laments,
"you rejected me because I do not like your
ways. . . . You want us to go to the houses
[nightclubs] where people gather to drink
colourless liquids which at times look like
blood [red wine]." He explains that he is
against indoor drinking and dancing places
because the dancing keeps people up until the
early hours of the morning and because the
dancers are not involved in making music
(singing, drumming, etc.) but merely dance
to music produced by others. For him, this is
like being visited by spirits or attending the
funeral of a dead friend or relative.
"The Kakwa (African) people drink in the
open under the shade of trees or house veran¬
dahs," he says. "They drink when the sun is
still up in the sky. When night comes, the
drinking party closes until the following day.
The night is the time for night-dancers
(witches) to roam through the villages like
lost bulls."
Here the author is trying to tell his young
readers how important it is to take pride in tra¬
ditional African culture, while also describ¬
ing a widespread social phenomenon at a time
when many young African women frequented
nightclubs, bleached their skin to make it
lighter and wore wigs so that they seemed to
have long hair like European girls.
\ Social change
This image of women is to a large extent a true
reflection of reality. Society, not the authors,
are to blame for this. In recent times, how¬
ever, great strides have been made by women's
organizations and government policies to pro¬
vide greater opportunities for women. In
Uganda, for example, women arc involved in
national development at all levels. There is a
fully fledged Ministry of Women in Devel¬
opment and more than forty women parlia¬
mentarians in a House of some 280 members.
The principle of including women in public
decision-making is replicated in political orga¬
nizations right down to village level. In sum,
the role of women in society is improving
rapidly and spectacularly.
The authors of children's books cannot
fail to be aware of these developments, and it
is to be hoped that they will soon be offering
their readers far more positive images of
women than they have until now. H
l¿
THE UNESCO ^>URI ER IULY-AUGUST 1197
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
FORMER USSR
From ideology to love
BY JULIA PROSALKOVA
Mn illustration by I. Bilibin
from a 1900 edition of Lovely
Vasilisa, a Russian folk tale.
rThe picture of women in Russian chil¬
dren's literature before the October
Revolution of 1917 is similar to that found in
Western Europe. At the same time it has its
roots in Russian history, culture and Ortho¬
dox Christianity.
After the Revolution critics rejected this
image almost totally on the grounds of its
extreme sentimentality, and in the 1920s and
1930s made attempts to put children's litera¬
ture on a new footing, using stories inspired
by traditional folklore and classical Russian
literature
These critics, who were themselves out¬
standing writers, had very firm ideas about
the range of themes and styles and the aes¬
thetic and ethical criteria that should be used
in children's books. Writers such as Kornei
Chukovsky dismissed prc-Octobcr children's
literature as "commonplace and bourgeois",
objected to the image of women it projected,
and blackballed the themes of family, parents,
motherhood and love.
These guidelines were dictated by a strong
insistence on a culture dominated by political
and social considerations. The Soviet state
regarded children's books as a powerful instru¬
ment in the ideological education of the rising
generations. "The purpose of Soviet children's
literature is to shape a communist personality,"
wrote I. Motyashov. This was the drawback:
authors had to follow an ideological and edu¬
cational line and were obliged to write within
the official framework.
i Hard-working
mothers
Until the 1960s female characters were por¬
trayed in children's books with a complete
absence of psychological realism, as revealed
in a classic poem by the talented Soviet poet
Sergei Mihalkov, And what about you? A
group of children are sitting in the street on a
summer evening. They are at a loose end, and
to pass the time they start making all kinds of
boasts. One of them brags that his mother is
a pilot. This does not faze the other children,
who in their turn start boasting about their
own mothers' jobs. The mother of one child
is a doctor, another's is a policewoman, a
third's an engineer, a fourth's a teacher, and so
on. Finally the children agree that "We need
all kinds of mothers, they are all important".
But nothing is said in the conversation about
mothers as such, only about their work and
their jobs.
This is not surprising. The new ideology
had liberated women from some of their tra¬
ditional tasks by making the community
responsible for the upbringing of children,
in nurseries, kindergartens, youth clubs and
other institutions. The collectivist mind-set
imposed a pattern of behaviour exemplified
in heroines whose lives were dominated by
their sense of social duty.
Only a handful of books do not conform
3 (oil!THE UNESCO LjlURIER |ULY AUGUST 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
«
£.oya Kosmodemianskaya, a
victim of the Nazi invaders
during the war of 1941-1945,
was held up as a model for
Soviet youth. Above, two
illustrations from a
fictionalized biography (1951)
show her as a girl (in 1937)
and as a heroine honoured
with a statue.
Photos taken (rom The Story ofZoya and Shura
by L Kosmodemianskaya © State Youth Literature
Publishing House, Moscow 1951
to this model and succeed in bringing their
characters to life. Among the schoolteachers,
youth leaders, and two-dimensional mothers
and grandmothers the reader sometimes comes
across a girl or young woman of noble birth,
who experiences all kinds of trials and tribula¬
tions before finding a niche in the new society.
But the critics usually gave this type of heroine
a frosty reception.
From the 1920s to the 1950s women tended
to be portrayed as conventional, insignificant fig¬
ures. There were very few exceptions, the most
remarkable being Arkadi Gaidar's novel Timur
and his Squad. Even today children still love
Timur and his girl-friend Zhenka, a tomboy
who hides the depth of her feelings for Timur.
IHeroic figures
Faithful to the poet Mayakovsky's famous dic¬
tum, "Build life by example", the critics wanted
women revolutionaries and heroines who had
distinguished themselves during the Civil War
or the Second World War, or by "constructive
labour", to be displayed as models for the
younger generation. Authors wrote fictional
versions of the biographies of girls from rich
aristocratic families who had chosen to throw in
their lot with the people and the Revolution.
In the real world, these women led tragic
lives, but in children's books they were
depicted as cardboard figures. Their portraits
were drawn superficially and conformed to a
physical and psychological stereotype. In
appearance they are round-faced, short-haired
and clear-eyed, with resolute chins. In charac¬
ter they are bold, courageous and obstinate.
Little is said about the stirrings of love.
The most notable exception is Ruvim Fraer-
man's The Dingo: A Story of First Love, a
picture of everyday life in the Soviet Union
presented through the story of a teenage girl
and her mother, who is divorced from a hus¬
band whom she still loves. One day the hus¬
band arrives with his new family in the town
where the mother has settled with her daugh¬
ter, who falls in love with her father's step¬
son. The author convincingly shows how
envy, jealousy and the girl's initial hostility
towards the young man gradually turn into a
shy and touching first love.
Lyubov Voronkova, Valentina Osceva and
Maria Prilezhaeva are among the few women
writers who tried to create female characters
that would be credible to the younger genera¬
tion, only to be accused by the critics of senti¬
mentality, antisocial tendencies and philistinism.
The thaw
More realistic portraits of women began to
reappear in the 1 960s, the years of the "thaw".
Female characters started to ask themselves ques¬
tions, to have feelings and to act unpredictably.
From now on their image obeyed a creative
logic and was drawn with greater literary skill.
Authors became more responsive to their per¬
sonal inspiration rather than to the official line.
Women ceased to be merely iron-willed crea¬
tures faithfully performing their social duty
and began to be depicted as tender, homely and
absorbed in their children's affairs. Women
teachers became more feminine and Young Pio¬
neer leaders stopped speaking in slogans.
The change was largely due to the arrival on
the scene of a new generation of young writers
born after the Revolution. They kept official
ideology and the educative conception of chil¬
dren's literature at arm's length, and introduced
a new style and new subject-matter. Their por¬
traits of women were closer to everyday life,
more profound and more authentic.
In "The Thirteenth Year of Life", Sergei
Ivanov created two original female characters,
a good-hearted and pretty thirteen-year-old
girl and her mother, an intelligent woman.
The mother, who has married for the second
time, loves "the free life" more than anything
else, and thinks of herself as an attractive young
woman absolved from family obligations. The
selfishness of the mother is contrasted with her
daughter's attachment to the family home.
\Neglected children
In the 1970s and 1980s, the completeness of
women's involvement in working life gave rise
14
THE UNESCO lOURIER |ULY-AUCUST I «97
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
to psychological stories in which women and
children are presented as victims. Mothers'
lack of participation in the upbringing of their
families is seen as a cause of juvenile delin¬
quency and the cruelty of neglected children
left to their own devices. Problems such as
extreme poverty and family conflicts are
described for the first time.
Many female characters in books by N.
Dubov make the best they can of life with
ulia Korolleva, who fell in the
struggle against the Nazi
invasion, was another heroic
figure featured in postwar
Soviet literature for young
people. Left and above, 3
photos from a book about her
published in 1975: at the age
of three, as a budding actress
and as a sergeant in the Soviet
army.
Photos taken from Higher than the Example by
Elena llyina © Government publications for young
people's literature, Moscow 1975
^^ rtn illustration from a 1987
edition of Khavroshechka, a
»- -C"1 Russian folk tale.
their drunkard husbands, work as cooks and
do dirty jobs. Real-life experience in the Soviet
Union is here seen in a bitter light.
In the 1980s women's personal problems
and their relations with the world around
them come to centre stage. Girl heroines are
portrayed with greater physical realism and
psychological complexity.
The awakening of adolescent feelings is the
theme of R. Pogodin's The Oak Grove. In
this story whose gawky young heroine is not
yet a woman, but has ceased to be a child, the
author describes all the complexities and con¬
flicts of a teenager who is at once lighthearted
and frank, lyrical and lucid.
One of the best children's books published
in the late 1980s, Yuri Koval's Wormwood
Tales was inspired by the author's memories of
his mother and grandmothers. Written in sim¬
ple, poetic language, it vividly evokes the hap¬
piness of childhood, when mother and her
love arc always there.
Grandma's return
The symbolic popular figures of Russian folk¬
lore have also made a comeback, notably the
grandmotherly figures who are called "babas"
in our villages. In Russia, the "baba" has always
been associated in children's minds with the
idea of stability, and serenity, warmth and
patience, generosity and kindness.
One of the characters in Pogodin's novel
"Where the Goblin Lives", a lonely old
woman named Vera, would have been incon¬
ceivable in a book written between the 1930s
and the 1 960s. She spends her life looking after
other people's children, wherever they come
from, as if they were her own. Her last act,
when she is almost blind and is starting to
lose her mind, is to save the novel's young
heroes, who are on the verge of starvation, by
sacrificing for them her beloved rooster, the
only living creature in her dilapidated home.
With great generosity and love, an old peas¬
ant woman in Pogodin's story "Where do the
rainclouds come from?" rescues a city boy
from the solitude of orphanhood. She shares
with him her sense of the oneness of human¬
ity and nature. "I have killed a toad," the boy
tells her one day. "How can it live when it is so
ugly?" She docs not scold the child, but goes
out of the cottage, returns with a big stone
and puts it on the bench in front of him.
When he asks what it is for, she says: "You
might need it. I too am ugly."
3(0"THE UNESCO lOURIER« |ULY AUGUST 1097
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
North america
Mothers and daughters
BY ELKE LIEBS
I There is no such thing as the archetypal
I North American woman. She is as
many-sided as the continent itself, a vast
fusion of races and religions. All the same,
books for children and adolescents provide
an interesting overview of the expectations,
projected desires and anxieties of young peo¬
ple as they confront the older generation.
These books featuring parents and children
offer insights into what is considered socially
representative and generally acceptable or unac¬
ceptable.
However, the realism of this type of liter¬
ature is limited. It is a setting for encounters
I he cover of Lois Lowry's
Anastasia Krupnik (1979), a
story describing a strong
relationship between a little
girl and her family.
rö«"*00
between many-faceted realities, where con¬
flicts arise and solutions are sometimes found.
Above all these situations stimulate us to
think about our own identity and that of
others, about cultural differences and shared
values.
\A lust for life
^LjKI'1
These shared values might be generally defined
as "lust for happiness" or "lust for life". We
even find the theme of lust for survival in Vera
and Bill Cleaver's book, Where the Lilies
Bloom (1969). This is the story of a fourteen-
year-old girl who, after the death of her
mother and father, makes superhuman efforts
to bring up and hold together a large family,
thereby fulfilling a promise that she has made
to her dying father. The strength of character
that she deploys in the process would honour
an adult woman but it also consigns her to
great solitude.
The ideal in this book is that of the family,
whose life-giving and life-supporting func¬
tion is made abundantly clear. Led by the ener¬
getic Mary, the children collect rare medicinal
herbs which they sell to make a living. The
story ends when Mary's sister starts a family
of her own. The two girls have very different
characters and ideals. Mary is brave and has
disciplined herself to be so hard and unselfish
that childhood and youth pass her by. Her
very virtues deprive her of what she most
needs the love of others. Her sister is gen¬
tle, pretty, conciliatory and indecisive in all
matters except for her decision to marry.
The fact that the roles of the sisters are
reversed at the end of the novel raises the ques¬
tion as to whether these two images of woman
arc mutually exclusive in the author's mind.
They certainly provide a striking demonstra¬
tion of the psychologist Erich Fromm's the¬
ory that a person must first learn to love him-
or herself (and accept the love of others) before
becoming capable of loving others. The same
principle applies to the family. This story deals
with two kinds of survival physical and
THE UNESCO QoURIER JULY AUGUST I
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
AS SHE DASHED FROM THE LIBRARY A
OF EXCITEMENT SWEPT OVER HER..
WAVE
above all psychological for a girl, a young
woman, a human being and a family.
In / Would Rather Be a Turnip (1971)
another story by the same two well-known
authors of children's books, the family is seen
in a different light. After her mother's death,
twclvc-ycar-old Annie lives alone with her
father and an extremely wilful black house¬
keeper until the housekeeper's nephew, who
was born out of wedlock, moves in with them.
Annie's hatred of the intruder is expressed in
eloquent fantasies, as when she writes a "novel"
about an illegitimate child being thrown into
a dustbin. Unlike Mary, Annie is able to sub¬
limate her fantasies of violence and eventually
she saves the life of the once-hated new fam¬
ily member by shooting a bull that is threat¬
ening him. Through this symbolic act, she
liberates herself from the constricting world of
her prejudices and doubts. The little nephew,
Ln Australian poster to
promote literacy.
who is exceptionally gifted and far more
mature than she is, has long since won her
over and passed on to her his own love of
reading. She comes to understand that the
word "family" does not necessarily only
describe a blood-relationship.
Keep your cool is the rule
Awakening sexuality is another common
theme in literature for adolescents. At first it
is surprising to see how naturally twelve- to
fourteen-year-old girls use an erotic vocabulary
which still, absurdly, sometimes makes their
mothers blush. But this linguistic ease hides a
lack of real experience. In most cases, the greater
their skill with words, the greater their fear
of what lies behind them. But that fear must
on no account be admitted. Keep your cool is
the rule. So all these girls dream of the kind of
great love affair they have seen on television and
arc bitterly disappointed when they have their
own first emotional experience. What's more,
they can expect little help from their mothers.
We often come across the stereotype of parents
who arc desperately worried if their fourteen-
year-old daughter has not yet dated any boys
but are dismayed when she falls in love.
Patty Dann's book, Mermaids (1986), for
example, which has been turned into a highly
successful film, seems to me symptomatic of
this conflictual situation that many American
mothers impose on their daughters. Fourteen-
year-old Charlotte is familiar with her mother's
many relationships with men and makes ironic
comments about them. As a psychological
defence, she goes on a purity trip and decides she
wants to become a nun. Unfortunately, she is
also her mother's daughter and is constantly
falling in love. Despite her "experience", she
thinks she is pregnant after her first real kiss.
Erotic and religious fanaticism culminate in a
scene where she bares her breasts to the crucifix.
As George Bernard Shaw said about his Saint
Joan, she is "in love with religion".
Adolescents still occasionally go through
such phases today. But the situation in this
story becomes implausible when mother and
daughter both develop a crush on the same
man; when the mother's concern for her
daughter's welfare is confined to cynical com¬
ment; when she takes a malicious delight in
stealing her daughter's first love (making Char¬
lotte weep for the first time in her life); and
a QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER« |ULY- AUGUST 1007
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
when she does not even want to come into
the house with the father whom her children
long to see on his only visit, an incident which
verges on disaster.
The real message of this contradictory
book remains somewhat obscure. What we are
shown is a distorted picture of emancipation,
psychological neglect and sarcasm which pre¬
vents us from experiencing clear feelings. Just
three sentences are devoted to fourteen-year-
old Charlotte's first physical experience with
a much older man.
Fortunately, families aren't always so
neglectful in adolescent literature. In Lois
-, Lowry's short story, Anastasia Krupnik
(1979), Anastasia is treated with understand¬
ing by her educated and sensitive parents (her
father is a professor and her mother an artist)
when she rebels against the arrival of her baby
brother, whom she hates. Arguments between
the parents are worked out with humour and
mutual respect, even in the presence of their
ten-year-old daughter.
In one particularly moving scene, the daugh¬
ter questions her mother in great detail about her
first experience of love. This conversation is
coloured with a striking mixture of timidity
and frankness. Love, pain, disappointment,
death, weakness and strength are discussed in
simple language that even a little girl can under¬
stand. This story makes a pleasant contrast with
many others in which children and adolescents
are ignored when they ask questions and arc
told that they should know the answers to all
their problems by the time they are fourteen.
Down-and-out in Boston
Poverty is another subject which increasingly
appears in adolescent literature. In Lois
Lowry's Taking Care of Terrific (1983) the
heroine and her girlfriends decide to bring a lit¬
tle happiness into the lives of a group of poor
old women by taking them boating in one of
Boston's parks.
In other stories the protagonists are them¬
selves confronted with poverty. In Norma
Fox Mazer's novel Silver (1988), a fourteen-
year-old girl lives in a mobile home with her
mother, who works as a cleaner and has a
younger boyfriend. The general atmosphere
is one of mutual understanding and frank¬
ness. Then the daughter starts working secretly
as a house-cleaner to help her mother make
9 THE UNESCO COURIER« |ULY-AUCUST 1007
I he young heroine of Silver
(1988), a novel by Norma Fox
Mazer, discovers the value of
friendship and trust.
ends meet. She gets to know other girls and
finds out that life always holds problems,
sometimes big ones. One of the girls is forced
to endure sexual abuse in her rich uncle's house.
Her moral shame contrasts sharply with the
modest pride of the mobile home dwellers.
Here romanticism mingles with blunt social
criticism in a way that is neither Utopian nor
convincingly realistic. Yet the story docs cap¬
ture a slice of life that faithfully reflects what
is happening in America today.
Another theme is the experience of Jewish
immigrants in the United States, as it was
shaped partly by poverty and the ghetto and
partly by the events of the Second World War.
Judie Angell's book One Way to Ansonia
(1985), which opens in 1899, contains a nuraj
ber of fascinating portaits of women of dif¬
ferent ages. They have a hard time adapting to
their new culture and face problems that arc
due to the weight of their own culture's patri¬
archal traditions and customs. Once again, the
women demonstrate remarkable resourceful¬
ness. The main character displays boundless
energy in her battle to acquire education and
assert her identity. With her child in tow, she
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
leaves her family, returning later as an indepen¬
dent woman who is now capable of experienc¬
ing happiness.
Getting their man
After reading a number of books for young
people it is surprising to sec how many girls
and women believe that they must attract a
boy or a man, not from a position of inde¬
pendence and emancipation, but in order to
catch him and get him under their thumb.
The reader may well be surprised by the
extent to which these women depend on accep¬
tance by men. To keep the man they love, they
are apparently prepared to put up with arro¬
gance, rudeness and boredom, as well as being
lectured to and told how to behave. Hilda Col-
man's Notfor Love (1983) dishes up all the tired
stereotypes of American girlhood: a pseudo-
harmonious parental marriage based on indif¬
ference; interest in clothes, parties, sports and
boys, and anxiety at the emptiness of vacations.
It takes the political commitment of a man
friend extremely handsome of course to lead
the main character, Jill, in a different direction
and to remain true to her new ideals even when
her mentor seems to let her down.
Another book, Dear Lovey Hart, I am
Desperate (1 975), is more subtle. In her capac¬
ity as the university newspaper's "Miss Lonely
Hearts", a female student gradually comes to
understand the differences between superfi¬
cial and deeper feelings, conflicts and solu¬
tions. In the process she learns about herself
and her own contradictions.
The mothers portrayed in these two books
are another striking example of the clear-cut
contrasts that still typify the image of the aver-
rage woman. They are either helpless and resigned
or thoroughly self-assured, hard-working and
co-operative. They show respect and under¬
standing (or indifference) to their grown-up
daughters. When it comes to love affairs, the
daughters hardly ever turn to their mothers, as
if they fear incomprehension or rivalry.
But for the most part these women of all
ages are imaginative, energetic and determined
to make sense of their lives. In the final analy¬
sis, all the stories discussed here convey a sim¬
ple message: never give up the search.
" D ooks for children and
adolescents give a good idea
of what young people think
about their elders."
t UNESCO Ç)URIER I JULY AUGUST 1097
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
DOSSIER
Down with stereotypes
Equality
between
men and
women, a
priority for
Unesco
In accordance with its mandate, Unesco
is working to improve the status of
women worldwide. Its action, which
explores many different fields, calls for
standard-setting instruments, training,
supervising studies and research,
literacy campaigns (60 per cent of the
130 million children with no access to
schooling are girls), pilot projects,
conferences, seminars, symposia,
study grants, the compilation of
statistics, and publications.
20
THE UNESCO
Sexist schoolbooks
A teaching guide entitled Down with
Stereotypes! shows how sexist models
which belittle women are transmitted
from generation to generation. Most of
the messages conveyed to pupils,
students and children by school
textbooks and children's literature do
not take into full account the fact that
women's life patterns have changed
significantly in recent decades.
Women from different cultural,
social and traditional backgrounds have
proved that they can not only follow roles
and careers which have been traditionally
reserved for men, but that they can
contribute new outlooks and methods to
them. However, this change has not been
fully reflected as yet in school textbooks
and children's literature; nor has men's
increasing participation in roles and
careers which have been traditionally
regarded as reserved for women.
Some school textbooks and
children's books still convey messages
which are largely false and out-of-date.
They do not encourage or consolidate
the changes that are taking place and are
not adjusted to the new situations. The
goals of the United Nations Decade for
Women (1976-1985) were to promote
equality between men and women;
women's participation in development;
and women's contribution to the
strengthening of peace.
Courier july-august 1997
It has thus become urgent to eliminate sex stereotyping in school education and
to see that schools endeavour to promote positive and egalitarian attitudes
between the sexes. This idea has been reaffirmed on several occasions, notably
at the World Conference of the United Nations Decade for Women (Copenhagen,
July 1980), which urged governments "to take all necessary measures to
eliminate stereotypes on the basis of sex from educational material of all
levels". When strategies for the advancement of women were adopted at the
World Conference to review the Decade (Nairobi, July 1985), it was
recommended that "studies on women's contribution to all aspects of
development" be included in school curricula. The Report of the Fourth World
Conference on Women (Beijing, September 1995) identified as a critical area of
concern "stereotyping of women and inequality in women's access to and
participation in all communication systems, especially in the media".
Women
and the
media
The Report stresses that "the continued projection of
negative and degrading images of women in media
communicationselectronic, print, visual and audiomust
be changed. Print and electronic media in most countries do
not provide a balanced picture of women's diverse lives and
contributions to society in a changing world. In addition,
violent and degrading or pornographic media products are
also negatively affecting women and their participation in
society. Programming that reinforces women's traditional
roles can be equally limiting."
Changes can only occur when those responsible for the
conception, writing, illustrating, editing and interpretation of
school textbooks and children's literature are convinced that
the perpetuation of stereotyped sex roles and images does
have negative effects on society as a whole.
Further reading
Unesco Publications,
1, rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France.
Tel.: (33) (0)1 45 68 43 00; Fax: (33) (0)1 45 68 57 41;
Web home page: http://www.unesco.org/publishing
Breaking the Silence. Voices of women from around the
world, Anees Jung, 1997.
Gender differences in learning achievement, 1996.
Down with Stereotypes! Eliminating sexism from children's
literature and school textbooks, Andrée Michel, Unesco, Paris
1986.
An entire issue of the Unesco Courier. "Women, one half of
heaven" (September 1995).
Key
dates
1975: International Women's Year
1976-1985: United Nations Decade for Women
8 March: International Women's Day
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
£,
anlBRZahdZKRR
ADVENTURE
UNESCO'S
SECRET
-JtoxoAiV
M j
c
m
\¿&<-¡
%¡f*tyj&
-^**í>t
jí^-ir"
s^tíg-
Pfä os
i itt--'-^?: tC_, ^-=0 .s=n fft??i i^t-7 £--. s^r* ok-*7
3f| Ï2lj: «* B=-=' * WK» «* f 3V^ «r^.>
Av/
fê
^?t/ V*. r'/*
hm
ISS £g
p
/>
*-*£,c-*f-
v
r-
i
iSffr/
*
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ZKRR and LBRZ
are members of a team of extraterrestrial
Q space explorers. As our story
\begins, they have investigated r>
. \ all the planets except /
\ \ one-Planet Earth. /
The two little extraterrestrials are
equipped with a powerful device
(the facial encryption unit) that
enables them to move around the
human world incognito. Only our
readers can see them as they
really are.
ZKRRisthe
smarter of the
two. He takes his
mission very
seriously.
LBRZ is more of a
goofball. His head is
always in the stars.
This is Mr. ZWR, a wise old patriarch.
As he nears the end of his journey
through the universe he is still baffled
by the mystery of the small blue planet.
our friends aboard their flying saucer
succeed in unlocking the secret of this
unknown world? Read on to find out. . . .
Comic strip (pages 21 72) © Uvesco Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
* T&ù&LATtONi we MAfc ftJ ArLAST'
this Ttiwe we maqz it/
OK, OK , rAKe (T £AÇ,y,
I'm MOT V&AÇ i 60
Ahv fte[/\^
ÇtèZ
1/6 P.'
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
W T^6 ÇCOUT^Q
ftPi y W/6 Sarr ¿w
9A zr^cIH&Ç Ar rue
f36r5lWM
HÄP to ToRM £>A£K; fyeCAOSB oç- $OMB miZD £oiUG$~ONns
V/£5ßy 6T£A/N££ TUfNÔS L 8TÏU. ÇtxM'T UMOeRVlTYND.
Bb ^á^
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
exceu^MT/
Com Alvn6,WQ
IWA-AJT l you To f 9
<bte-
ïlziz^ new? r*iS (A/eeK at
ÜÑZSCO HeAP^UART^RS
iKi ?*$& 12zz6&ZZ22
Jl/VltZ S>CteUTi$T£, ARTISTS
An P 'Pourvu i ANS f£0M/4(¿
ovjep rne \a/orup Meeri/Jci
H£Re ha\J6 eeeN çpeAk\ùG>
AVoor um&sco'S Key ç&ie
IM«* 62222 22-Z2t?,22tll
uv ZZ22£ ^ ¿»PeAT KAWMê llizzz .u gemido
ovation AS Tne &ep£Seu~ \i\e\n&& that 106
TATivJe Of ÜNeSCO WAN9S CfÄTPVe^A^0^^^
u\t^ i m ti. ¿22¿¿>¿z o. zzzz^feoete ww-moe»*
ifA"»/.
.w...Seu>p/M \3U6,fne
ÜMIf^P NATIONS £PU£AT(ö/VAl-
SCl^MTlRC /iND Cüi/TüRAU-
OR6Am2-ATi<?M A6TSvu-32-¿
G>ZZZ2zzz22 CLACK!
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
6P^ß-'0MTH6 ,
et ink A6AIN- ufcLU
HAVP To 6er a
&?r £>ack/
ANP Wr TÄXe
TOO WN6 AÖOT ÍT
V¿f KNOlA/ IP WJp' ß£
mot im r//ng for. Tne
n£xt p-xiT wimpow we
COULD Pi MD ÖURS8/-V£S
STUoK (M THI5
t/M^SCÖ 1^6122, C)M6SCO. .,
IPOH'T KMouJ A/1UCH
/MORE THAN VOU -
it Sounds to Me
uké S¿Wip SoierOF
016 C5Rr¿AfNii2ATio/v)
P<?R SOAllUb ALU
rue pAferwuMôS'
-FR06L8AAÔ
HéR8/ T U/KAf /S
TS A VA/RUS M¿R^
ftmLoeföDusniy
SHRINK,/ AMP
wweN / (TS
PlS/v7PP64f2ßP
íc?/MPí^T^y
, /y^hfttTyRN
[(y*^7^ at
, 0N¿£
ir?
/^'
* SHftlWKi 0/vi£TeR.
2KRR / WMT
r?\v Tne
Oi,V <v\Añ
weAN,
"MO PljMKJy
Business
THlS Ti MP?"
so ppRHAPs uue
SUovuO 6>TA&X
ev 66TTikl£ IrA
TOUCH WITH THvS>/
PR, UMPSCc? ?
./H
0s
'Fßeciseuy,
VOWN THERE
And See what,
IT'S ALL A&OÜT.'
Vor &e CA^efUL.,
TWpft LlTTue CRVTT^Í^
Vöü (3R0U6HT ßß£K. 1
[Tne ¿Ne with au- thc
T£5TH THAT TRseP
to £o8ß>te us up/rf
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
S¿we TiiMe LMzR^rj^-
ONfHe
PACÍ AU
ewcpvPíioM
UNIT SO VAlÉ
cAr4 mix wirn
TWÉSg HUMAN.
WTHCUT aeiN6 Monttr}
Wow/ so /wy >
VeopLen i$\t
i\Ke this y
&VeßViA/H^ß8,/ «0
o
1^/ '. \iy^^"
G>
^pg XAJ II
oiiuonS F/ )) fí£-
0
fflf
UPMwéà&
in tIS
Yod \/ UT'S
QvMP suR8 THÉyY Poliovai
peAny Ape eAí^THA Th&m
UKI6 (^APéRS, ANt>¿£6
'ZKRR? / WHAT
HAppPKJS
U
\h'/
&
T(2y ANP LOOK
/M (9(28 HU/MAM Op
SoMZONe WIUU
M0T168 US /
SHOWS THe M8va)
HBßAß-Y ©F
.AiXXArVO^iA
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
, AS YOC kwovxj, Tne cup <pn£ was DeSTRoyeo NeARLy zooo year«
A6C IAJH6M rjouiOS ¿A£SAR WA£ #eSi£6£D IM AL-exAMPRiA-
' ' ' ! I l i i i i i i i i \ i i i i i i i ^ ~r-r
IT hap 0een fOÜNPßP i M 295 60 AMD Ç09~
cuNTOPieç, was THe imteluqctl/au cernee
OPTHE ANCi6Kf VNOP-uO . TJUST -fHIMK
it Hou&ep asmawas ioo ,ooo Papyrus &ou£
Af*. AßiAY <?P SCH0U9S ANO SCPvBES S?£^T
THeiR L-WeS TRANSLATIVE A/yp COPYIIM6
rVVAsiUS^RvPTS1 UGNi-r ToTHÊM £Y OTHER
Ue-RApveS- ITS fOUhiPER'S VPEA WAS To
6A-THER TOG.ETHEP AUUTH6 VaJORlP'S Çcd^S
Since 1986, UN GSCo has eeEKi
tW2k'iM& TO PiC^eATfe THE
U&PAPY, CA^P-YlNG OoT
PPEPAeATopy STUDIES, pbß
INSTANCE ... ^
OR OP6AN^iN.£> aw APCHi-
<&UT(JPAU CöMP&TTiorO fcfc
<HC peS\6rM op Tkte NtvAj
©OlUPlWxá- 	
eQOvfPeP vjjiTH AUL Tue latcSt
Técwwouo6v, iv\-Tue 2. \ St"
ctHTJP-y rue "ALe*AfJpe\NA
MOW, LiKtTHe OLD LtgRAoy
wu, ae a MAP-veLuoos
c,Tope House of fcüowuzvGe
ANP A 6P PtACE pCFL eAÇ,T
AND VAJ&&T TO e^6HAN6£ ipeAS
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The iwoex tpAnSuatio/vjum. iT
2%y2 Y0U WHETHER A P3o«?K'S ft«ri\
^AN 6PA GS AN D VAJ H I CH A G£ TH E WöRlD Ç
updated EVEp.y ye>kp.
ArVP-
O £0A4£O, (20/Meo/^6N6APA RAU ÇJON&O?
0AN6AN ARU» KETUEüa/AaíMO DAN ^AMa/M1
ATAÜ OlkATDAK i^élTO, ^)ADlUAH
KÉKASIHKU PAN AHrU $VKAN UA6t
oÇAciô CAP^Lerr.
VFm
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
«r
OOM'T &e
ALARMED ,you óuY S
I'M NOT CRAZy ,Wé'¿
UEAPMiyJ^, -r0 Speak
WOOMESiAW THRoU6H
T<^- AOTIki£
«tJ,
t ¿
Í-4.
<*=. **-
Aa/P that WAS A Bit
<oe $HAkespÊARE ^ith
Tne otoe ArvD ¿*vuy
MRS Mtfj?-
A*0
ÇOM'T ÍÓK&ET
; . To UEAfc-M
ty Your
UWES
VeS , t HAP THIS IPeA
WHEW \ va/ AC lOOK\v±G
TKROUÓM THÉ CAT/MO&ue
Of PEppESeWTATi
_WCRVCS
ÜM «
PepeeS&si
tatwe
60 HAT .^ vouDoM'T
KMO^J AficUT THAT
^	. eiTHeR ?
VAMECU 1
we've owlv
^5T STAJ2T6D
M
"AUSPICHT THtW, VT'S A OPLLEOTVOrO
OF -TeAwSLATtouS, OF MA9rts.v?ieceS
DF HTfeßATÜPC F^QVI AUL CA/CR. fHE
vooPl-o AmD FPe>M eve^Ry ASE
IFeof^A C-AO VUE6l\Kl in
ç^^wcw -to SHAKespfeApe iyj
iNDoneSiArA . ovep l/OOO So
Frt^ 1 Ni A HUAJOPeD "P^FtPöJT
CAM«S.iJA&fcS
So OMESco'S
K\wp Op A
p\)euç,niM£
woo se ?
REPeeevxe fesoucs uvke
-vne iMpex 1 tH\STop.y
PiooKS UIKE THE
CpEaJEPAU Hl^ToRy OF
APR» CA , CaUCTtoKSlKBTiig
w«p-u> HEpiTA^e series,
MA6A2iM£$ like T*e COURlEl
AWO MUSEUM-
UUELU
ITS Tpoe
ÜWESCO
Pue-USHPS UOT5-
OP
3uT of £?opSe
That '5 rjusr owe/
oe its ACTwiTtes.
WOT (T S AlAlt^
Purpose Aajp .*« 6ur
uooi< vMiHO'S here/
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
COfiAZ- AUONG, Povi'T UET'S
Tj)vSTUP.ß> him wjuiue we'S
(2E:HEAP.$|N\6 POR THte
B»G M16HT.
v¿=^
T
THE IPEA OP THVS ¿OL,
u&Ction^ ic, to Preserve
UoVAAT ÏOO MIGHT CAUU THE
N.OW- MATe^iAU H6R>TAÚ>e
A»JP MAKE (r MOP& UJIOELy
KwOuJfO: (VVJSvG , PArACe/
ORAL tPAOvtiowS , tuSTOMi
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
JréMíté u\ce MR uAScal-a eeHihiv, oor
eXTßATeßPeSTBAu FRiewDS ThKejórmSKiíS,
T^ST (V\e,^K£R . BY AAV
^eCKONtNô ijjPj SHOOUD 8f¿
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
HM/VtATMA/fje
TweyvE voNB
\nOMe VAlöRk ON
th£ Place
( Hey you ouys
\ ~PVeR HERE/ L
Could yöo takc «v picwe
l» fRÖWTOFTHATgUDpHA?
Tjusr fßeSS this
E>UTTOa) .
^thAwkS j fUMNV VA/Ay
TO KOUP A 6AMGRA BOT
Tne photo's pReTTy
6oop.
tS THIS Your FvR-St
M\S\T To
&ÖR-0£OQOR f
[MEANX THvS ISN'T
ABU S»M9 ¿
a^- MifMJfMJ vöü
HAP Me ÇOOL&P ft>R /4
m/ajote rnei2e ' yoo'p
HAVE T¿? ge/f/MARTiA/SNOt
ToknOvm E6VPT FRo/w
I'M POVM6 A RoundN.
THE-WO^LP TOUR OF
euAces that a Re ow
TH6 vworlo pteRvTAße
'A-vST. LOOK AT
^HES
£
¥
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Tnepe C AM IM FRONT
OF AF3U SiM&EiU.
THAT'S Aie NeXT TO ^f^^SV AT &&&bu<k
c'HARue/v»A6NG'S'TAcoAJE ^ l«A|\3
I hi AACPie^-
B"/v
i "/ 11 \
1 P'
f M
T3 c
1 *
,-vA-
<
6
c 1
L
-^, ^ li^^l^SM
. / V ~
L / r-
s I ,
* ^J ~ is
1 í
ANP THAT'S OAJPY FOR
STARTERS . THERE WERE
Çoé SvTES #N THe UATEST
U\ST 0uP3L\SHEP By 4ftc
UNESCO'S, WORlP MERITA^
C&ft~\lB '
Unesco i pip
you s*y'
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Vou caw't iMAéiwe Tne State
TPVvS TEMPLE WAS (W F3ACK lh\
THe SvXtvES
AFTeR A THOUSAMO WeARS op 6000 Times
ANP e>AP 1 THE PCACE WAS FALUW6 ApAßT.,,
%0 TXAT WAS
vjvjneR^ Unesco
CA(v\e in u
VKJ 1972 ^T UAUr\)CWeP
AN IWTeR/uATiONAp-
CAcMPA^M TO S»A\)e
^oRoe>oooR l%.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
^vAJe^ry. mm countrifs ANèweRep umfsco'S A??eAu fo&
MöMFY ANP T£CHi\)\CAU- SUPPORT TO He UP (kjOOajESv A
IT TOOK T6M V£ARS - O VjeR A M\LUO|và &LOC\<$ Qf StONF
UAAP TO ®e ÇMIFTEP /,
WAS fagofcü "
PUR THEONUy
Place unesco
HEUPEP To
SAVE 7
Ape YOU *oP0ihl6?
there 've &ee&
LOTS Of OTH^R.
CA/v\pav6nS '
£1 äs
^^z
I I
TflA/E»ATy-Pi\JE SO PAR, TO Fie PREC\Se
THe.R& WAS Or^fZ FOR VJEAJVCe , FOR
&XAMPU& i APTe^R THE Fuoo OS (hi
(966 it«
$ï>Uf rHF MOST FAMOtâ OF ALU WAS THF RiRS,T; ^TweeM I960 AajP I93o APooajD
2o rewipu$s (Ki mo&ia iajfrf Movjep 6ooiuy to savf Twe/vi fpo/uithc WAxeçis
OP TH E ASWAN »VU . WATA 000/
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
LT
)nn:nnn LOOK WW>ft
' V. fOUNO,
wi CAM TAKE IT BACK
IAMTH US ,TH6R£'S
TMI-S £AA1E f!2avi.
*iôht MCK mute
' fMHTOJ
CS ,
^kAy,¿?«Ay,THeRer¿
eN0U6H -TRAFFVCKVS16 »hi
Stoleaí vUORk:S Of ART
AS VT vS l
HOü A/1EAN üMFSCo'S A KiwO op
POUCHE PoRC£ AS VJJEUÇ ?
MO, MO. THAT'S NOT vTS 0ö&. IT H6ü?S
¿oiwrp-ves ro ^ee that THey have
-rne uawS aajpthe reSour-cfs TUey
Meep. THAT'S WHAT HAPPFNep (Ki C/WIßOP'.'
î>
O»
¿to
Da.
*o=
r>>
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
AH i HFRE'S MY CAR MOST Go
I'M TAKihiG A PUANF FOR
Tne ôAuapaoos in aim
HOUR'S TiME .
VXJHAT
ex»
.-^ = You 5oi
PO-THP^E!
VH*^
w*."* -^ _ «Jé" ^cTK;
'-«v
/^WHV , CONTmvJE ^x " _ -^v^
Í MY TOUR OF VA30RLP \ J^rÎT"
Course '
^^^^ o
,¿-
Sr^4
S
J}j*
~$ft'S A natorau Sire. A cömv/e^ton) acdftéo
Pj>Y UNESCO'S cSENeRAU COAJFERFNOE IN
[(blZ ALLOWS ÇOR NATURAU SlTFS AS UOfeUL
To Fie mcuupEp ok THe vwrup hfritaoe u»ST
The 6PAWD CANYON ANO rwe
6Al>APKG>oC, ARe 13VJÇ.T AS
MUCH PART OF THF ¿WW»)
HFRvTAGE AS THE TATi
MAHAU 09^ CHARTRES^.,
CATHEC^>r>
P>Uf I MOST &£ ON My
U/AY. \F 1 71/1 £OiN5 to Do
If AU IM gO CKYS THERE'S
NO Ti/ME TO EPARE im
\T
cf<
v^ THERE
THE/,
Pc^ ^^^^v,W
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
PON'T
MOVtí
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
WHAT
THE../
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
TR/\u.Aueë ITWiLALA !
VOOreS! HOOQAV'
l'\is eeeti \
Accepted/
can you eeue\ie
it ? ^A f)
fc\6HT, IT'S A ?ROCRA(MME ^
Of UNe^CO'S IWTE?NATVO-
NAU füHV FOR THE
T;RO(v\ot\on Of
t£> /*.lll/TitCi<= / -*^Ê
Vf S TO HELP VcUhG ARV»STS
HKE ME . THERE ARE
TRA)KnhJ6 ¿RAHTS /\WD
UViNG AUUOVAJAT/MOE.S,
MOT AT AUU IT'S AUS O
0OMCER.MED VJVJVTK THE
ARTS. VT WfLPS FILM¬
MAKERS im "SX\ieuoPiN<S
COOMTRVFS, OR6AMVZES
KÄJ^K**"""
oonretAVoww /viusvc
ANO THEM THERE'S
If S \J0ORK IM THE
COPYR\&HT RieuD.
THAT UTTue ©
SVMßOL you SeF I M
"<s Started uife
ifH UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
TChat fvjeswmE^ 2krr
ReTURMS TO THE SAUCER >M
RONFFFL A W/IKE OP:'
* "bP. ¿lù*^-
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
hmmm .' That -doesn-t
TAUUY VAMTH INFORMATVOM
WE^VE TJUST PvCKEOUT
C/lRRYON. AI Y OiV AMTEAJNA TêllS M 6 THAT we
shouud uooK further imto this ,». eur
REMEMBER ugE HAVErA'T MUCH T»fsA£ , WE'RE
AuREAoy CHAR6.N6 The SHRuFfE For
BLASTOFF (
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
ft'SA LESSotf
¡MOUT MAR» WE
/pepos »TS. uue
conoide (zeseAtcH
/iwp TRA1NIM6 OW
THESE ExReQiTiOfMÇ,.,
THAT'S VAJHY IT'S CALLgp
F^AflNé , ..
ÉR?.'1^
AWP IT'S*
'NESCO THAT
0R6AW17-ES
THESE
expepvTioi^Si
UWeSCO SROMÇORS THEM
THEY'RE A CO- OPERATVJE
V/ÉMTÜRE . MORE THAW ZO
UNVv/ERSVTiES ANO RESEARCH
CEWTRES ^AP TAKEN
FART v^ THEM AS Of
|39H AAJP THEY'RE StiUU.
¿Ol Wé» <3TRON6...
FX3T THVS wvuu
PRoGAQLH ®£ ONf
OF MY UAST
/ TÁUK AEOUT \
( ^AiUisi6 THE , )
^¡ACKltt \9Ç9, I IVAS ON AM (MTER- TChEM IM 1665 VWEMT -$,ND IW 1415 , | \NA<S
^NATXOA/AU E-XpEPiTioNlWTHE IWPlAK ^OM ANOTHER ONE TO VSiTHC. CARVFsFjEAM
oceAN withtmê iMTepéo«eR)jM6rJ. expuore the kuroshio w tm» wiwwwin.
TAU OC6AN06RAPH\C COMMISSION... CURCEWT IhJ THE <?h£\f\C
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
£ÜT fHAT'S O^UV ONe
EXAMPLE- THE VOEAVSTO
F»MP OUT ALU \A/£ CAM
A60UT THE OCEAfsi /WP
VTS RESOURCES'
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
HMMM , LET'S SeE .
MAM AMP ftHe
^s.m ElO,., FJiOmSPH"».
aaaaj And the
ER, VES, ßüT UUHftT'S
VT AlEANi , ¡'MACANO
THE F>OSpH£RE" ^
\ Tj?\ptw'T KWObO
yarp MOVED
l Ni VET/
OUHY, IT'S ONE OE UNESCO'S
EH6 SCiENTFiC
PR06RAMÍNABS.
Soo M eu ER HFAR^
OF EvOSPHE^e
RE^ER-NJES ?
V TS A NETWORK 0 F NATU -
RAU Ç»»TES »> EACH OMf
VS A SAAAPLE OF OOR
PLANET'S F3iOLOCm£AU
PWERSvTy ,.,
V
THE I PEA vS TO
PRESERVE ALU- THESE RvCHES
ANP lEARaJ tAOQsè Ardour
TneM so we can ev?uv/e eco.
logical p&?ï3>lems uiHre
PefoRÊÇTATitfN ANPTHE"AREEW
House eEEECT-" .
FOR IWSTANCe « NEXT
TO TH\S AAAPTHERF VS
A pvCTOR-E Of TH£
A/IAP» M v R£$£R\;F i M MFXiCQ
The iwTERfeSTlN6 Trim6 IS
That,
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
THAT'S (A/HERH \
we HID THE
SAUCER /I
oo1
F¿tf/U£ ON, 1&Ç2,!
lut caaù'X ueriíi&<\
f\nv xm SAuceR "
' s 1jT"t?«'-^: L'i.
etoof/ fiae >£
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
CONGRATULATIONS , U££2, you
Sure mape A Messoptupri
i TOLP you THe Saucer
NEEPEP MOEE CAMC0flA&& '
MGvJER MlMD. AAR21AJR
ToOD Me moSt times
THfeY ÇbM'T F3eU!EY
HUMAajS VWHO SAY
n HEYVF SeEM OOR
SAUCERS i
(M£MORv'2EO
T^eM(\P I M THAT SoOKCü
MAPiM i, w&Re m Com!
%
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
HA! HA! HA j yoü
Coouv ÇAY TriAT J
THE RESEARCH SYAT10M
VS STUPY/MC WAYS OF
fAZMlNC THIS PESEPTj
w
¥%.
Ano
UiÇr'pe $f£iu6
'(FTHIS OPÜNTiA
CACTUS COULD Ee
USEiP TO TESD
AnimalS.
(A/fcVE ALSO £eEM
TRY/N6 OUT ANOTHER
pLAMT , HVLARiA /MUTCA,
AS A PoSSv&LE
THAT'S G01M6 A <diT
FA&- 1 cut uneSco
HAS TAKÊM A COT
Of \ MTEREST \M
-CvAE T?Ro O^
ARvD LANDS.'
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
\H të5i, üA¡e$£0 LAVNCuev rue Fvrst-fv/fr internatonal programme o^
AR\P -ZONfS. ALTHOUGH. THEy CoYFR A TH»RO OF THE EARTH'S
Surface they' d mot £eEh¿ thoroughly STuPvep Till Then.
'"JChAT WAS THE FiRST ATTEMPT AT
CO- ORPINATEP STUpy. THE SPREAD
Of DESERTS \S STlUU A
El 6 PgoEtE/lA, , i	 ~cr
IT WAS, AN 0?eoRToN\TY To ¿SATRÊR
to 6ether. uotS of pata a^oot These
1R.E&VONS: HYPR0UO6V, NEUj ENefc&y
SOURCES/ eCOU06y, CL\N\ATOU06y^
AESOLUTEuy G\;eRyTRvvié /
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
yes, AS v »mas S'ayiñg?
The VHP took over
\ajhere the HYPR0LC61CA
T LEET OFF
IT AIMS TO HELP THE
Pf\]£LOpMttiT Of HYPRo
uocy And alSo to
iMpRov/e va/atsr
resources
MA-NACôEMENT.
HMMMíAh.
45*?
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
THFM THeRE'S UNeSCc'.S OTHER. £>VG
SC\6NCE PROGRAMMES , U\KE THE »6CP_
THE I MT&RMAT\ ONA V- &fOUOG\CAU~
CORR^UATOM PROCRAMWVE ,
STARTED IN (912 ...
THAT'S fo& Studying The
HVSTORY OF THE EARTH'S
CRUST AND ITS »RESOURCES
AMD CO-öRDLNAT\hl6
RESEARCH 0^ THESE
MATTET RS.
Eut unfsco was
AhFEADY (NTo &50L06Í.
ÇoR BxAcAPua , (THaPED
PuElvSH A [15,000,000
MA? Of AFRICA
9ACK im
Take rwe \&cp for ^
exAMpuf. unfSco seT
VT UPiw CoLUAV3oRATVO/^
with Another orga¬
nisation, thf IhiT^^.-
NATlONAV- UMVOhi OP
6Eouo6^al
ScvFNCFS-
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
A fc£ you CÇAZ9 CfS. WHAT ?
CAN'r You reui. A ccMPorek
FRon a PIANOS?/;?
IF You've LOST eYElO
Oust QH£_of MY Files
VW S3TRIH6 yoo up
FROM THE NEAREST
CACTUS IL
I've only Oust been)
hookep up to the
nftwortn and i've
Got A MESSAGE
AM26AP»/ / Thi«; IS G&EAT.i
excuse ^
M.FYJ IT'S ¿YYOTHER
rjoo RMA U ST- MvSS gum?
OF THE " COOK
ISXwtyvDS /VEUJS"
VA/AAJTS ( M FORAAAH OAj
A&oUt OUR STATION)
HEPE
COOK ISLANDS, EH ?,»,
NOLO WASN'T UNeSCO
OovNß EO/V|£TR)H<S \hA
THF COOK iSLAKiDS
60AS \T ?
MAH%£ yoo CO(/LP
6KOUU US «AJKEPE
THEY AF^E CNl A
* MAP?
«ST
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
miss oottfr?2_ MAPiMi ?
U/MAT A COINCIDENCE/
I'VE TJuST F^eM IM
Touch vàmth the
RESEARCH SrATloM.
yoS, I KNOW,
WE WERE THERE/
Must t8e noK\w& \t
was owuy A few
MlMÚT AGO AmDMEXK
Hor^KACTuy K1ÊX.T
REAUUy 7 pvp YOO KNOW UNESCO
HFuPEP US COMPUTERDOM
PAPER ? V CAM TeUU YOD AMYTHHAc;
YOU WANT TO KMOijU A&OUT ITS
VX/ORK IN THAT UM9
PERHAPS VJUF SHOUUDTAKF
Xwe%e _ TvN O OuT5 V PE /
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
TO STAKT WITH TíítSRE'S
Tne \PDC_jThe Intfr-
kíatvonal Programme
For the pEvjeuopMeNT
Of COMM0N\cAT\ OM
IT BEGAN in 1980 And
IT'S HELPED SET UP 9£V-
F«?AL REtGiowAL NtZvwS
A6eMdi ...
^VT'S Ai-So HFUPEP F3uv
It* FOovPfvieNT For
NEWSPAPERS And ra£\o
And ty Stations.
Jpy^WTHlMG FROM TRAiNvMfS SPeClA-
UST5 To P\6vTv2in6 \JALUA6UE
MANUSCRvPTS UKF THOSE IN THE
PRAGUE MATONAL- UERARW.
AND THERE'S ALSO THE \\? , THE
lNTE9^GoYeR,V\[AehlTAL- \hi FoRNAATvCS
PROGRAMME , STARTED lhA 1385 *
ANVP A\/v\mC To e»R\R<S ft^f OGVE-
lopi\*<G> count R\&«=> up To Scratch
vv^ \nFormat\oM Te(
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
sOTRAlhUVàG \h\ VNFORW\T\ON) TECHNO¬
LOGY Cot* F\Ri>T.v.
f &JT \\9 \S ALSO
(NVOLVED /Si PEvJEUOplhiC;
ÔOETU/ARE , SETTlMc; Up
COMPUTER SlETvAJORKE>,
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
You can
Say that
AGAIN.» AH,
Mfc ZVNR'S
OUR ¿ALU
HMA1M ! iT &<¿T$
MoRe and mo Re
COMPLY CAT&D i SVP '
we'i/e seem So many
Pvfeerent things, am
old Tempus , a ScH col¬
on EoARP A SHIP, a PARK*
A nevo SPARER, And
THAT'S NOT AUL- i«>^^
ScwEeoPy WHO TALKED
To US A&O0T UMFSCO
MAPE US EUEM MO RE
Confused, he wet*r
(ON AF300T COMEATTiNG
PvSCRvMliNATio/vi And
A9out SociAU Sciences
it* pact üu&%co
SEEMS TO EE INTO
ALU SORTS OR THINGS
EOT V STvuL CAN'T
«See v\ow -rneype Auu
£\CHT
HERE
ONF WOÇ.&
IS
VOC
oo o a
iOO o
W we've DecvpKe^-ED ç>o,v\e
[^<i\yù W^EORMATvONi . \'N\ SeND-
vM6 YOO THE fAA-p ztfeç&^tzs
Of A vj vuuAGE. &0 Tv-AERE7
strAvght away and report £ack
AS SOOK) AS, PbSS<
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
CAUGHT
G>L\AAPSE
JOf \T SOME-
;hfre oue»?.
/T^eRe v., CAN'T
ee ear
AWAy. \Lfl
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
RECEiYFP
?T\et»KueT AEOUT
SwEdenj /n THF
i»C0MF UiSiTOUR
^(COUNTRY" SERIES...$
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
DVnPTHEY SFtSAA YFR^
-" SuRPR\SED A^Tr\e WAy
SwEPVEH GHILPÍ2EN Uvie
MAVEE yoo know) that
CERNES- IT'S VA; HERE
CHiuoRe/* PCSCRV&E
THElR LwES To
CHiuD££N IN
OTK&PÎ. i
.COUWTRieS
IT'S poEUSHED
ey o'nesco under
IT'S ASSociATBD
GCriOOU^
^°^T^T(AT
UNesco's
U«NOUV£Ç?
, «AJITH
JCHoouS
\i weu^?,
OlvXAPYA MEAM , "AS
0UEUL,v?/ FIX) CATION
COMES f&fo<?^ E«VERy-
THnNG ELSe , IT iS t*he
Top, pRvoRTy PROCRAAI/Vlg-^
¿f^
WHAT FLSe PO YOU
THINK THE LETTER-
"E" ÇtanDS fo^ it*
THE NAMe UMESCO
(A/Euu, i thought it..
"Oost fcfc/-AeMee<R that'
THEpe wepe Stilu
N&ARLY A ElLLAON
V ULI TE RATE
So ALTH(0(j£H UMFSCo'S
EEEA3 Pv¿HTii*g; ILLITER¬
ACY S»nce the Start
You can Gee the
"¡ÍNJ THE I95o'S , FOQ EXAMPLE, IT UAÜA)CH ED
A F>\G> PR0 6>(SAMME TO EXTeND
J?R\MA«^y EDUCATION* VNiUATiï^
AMCR\CA."p !	"
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
Tjf HE NÜNABeRoF CHIUDRGN ATT
school in lativ\ AmêrvCa. -duMPev
PY ELEVEN MiUUCM PETWE&N 1957 AND 1965
it^NESCO M&HT TO WORK TO TRAlt*
^TMe TeACHeRS, School heads ,
mSpecTo^s Aajp So on who had to
PeAL with rnese wcvaj pupils.
\ 6zr ir i
UNESCO'S MA) si OoE
VS TO TRAlM PeoPLG
WHO THEM TEACH
OTr\efi Peoprjfl TO
YES p EUT THAT'S
NJOT ALL THERE \S
TO VT - TO TACKLE
A p Ropy-Em FRopeRcy,
VOO M£^t> To K/UOvJU
TbOUT
XtÜLWOH VS UJHY UNESCO
HAS PuP>L\SHEC> A
Svan^M2ç> ReeeRtNCe
WORK / THÉ VWORLO
epviCAT\ON Re9o<^T, eve^v
TuüOVCARS SlNCe 190,^ .
.«^VM,,""'"'/^'//>Vt*
'/'/// '//,'' '".lv
/" "\\NN *' '-"ii.i;.i«
T^NP WITH AULTHE C?HAMGES (h\ THE (aYORlD -
^^ONESCO'S ACREA Py THINKING AEOUT THE
ePUC-ATiON CHILDREN, VWIUU Ne&P I I* THF
NEXT CENTURY.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
RANGES FROM HTo Fj>uiLD
SCHOOL^ - BACK /N 19£>\ , FOR
INSTANCE, ITE>ETUPA TRAINING"
CENTRA I Si KHARTOUAA FOR SCHOOL
Building SPECiALvSTS.
TC 0 THE PROMOTION OF ScvENCE
T5ACHVh\c; »y	
JA Alp To PROTJECTS LIKE
UMITWIN , uohvCH AVIVAS Ta
\NCR-eASE CO-OPeRATiON)
AMONG ONuOERSvT\eS
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
f SO UUF've KipMAPPFD
A HUhAAN- <Seeaa9
U\f VJUAS ll* UR«.E
Çoft %oMf; BVG
esco pRvze
¿SoiNG> TO
hviva in ou9
AGMETRONÍ
e»,v3^v30T y e:AHi
LUE OAN-'T DO\ fvJÉVEF^
THAT ! IT'S MlM-O
against THeJL TJjose
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
S OKAY i
HE'S ReADY.
rAaA-
***- ®x®
ü.M.E.S.CO
Omvtep NatvonS
EOuCATvONAL SciEhlTV-
E\c And Cultural
ORGANV2AT10M» \85
MeMeeR States
«Jt^ I2>2»7 ««« ^N^
j^VV'VVV^.A... aa/V^
fROfoRA/WiWE ESTAEUNSHED
EVERY TWO Y6ARS Ey
THe Oe/vi^RAL CONHrR-
eNce vaj\th Rep«2.eseM-
TATNvjgS OF ALU THE
MGMEeR STAT
execuTwe £oaRd:
S8 MEMEeRS-
NVIVApe-R op MATvoNAL
co(v\iw\ssi on s:
n 9-
NUM&ER c*= NON -GOVERN -
MeNTAL ORGANA 2AT0NS..,
^Ty^\
OMéSco seems to
HAVE A PinCER 'sí
EveRY PiE-SAyvNC
TeMPueS, F3uiudiN£
^>C\KOOUS> , CEOU06Y,
HYDROUOGy, INFORMA¬
TION Tec HNOLOGy,
HVSTORy , MUSvC ,WHATgV6
^,^TS täeHlND ALL
THVS.WHAV-S ITMeAhl^i
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
THF OCORîLD WAS T)UST
EMERÔINC; PRoM LVARrt.
lULiMp IT WAS, IN OME Of THE
CiTeS HARDEST HIT is».
THAT VNAR, lONOONi .
That uNesco uuaS EoRsi
on lé NoyEMEep |9MS
THeRE m ONfSCo'S
u &vRTH CERTIFICATE " lÇ
TKe REASON fo(> [TS
E XI STANCE , /N THAT plVE-
LETTERWORDp^A^r
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
QW\WM6$* AvreAú rexx^ CU . VoxüAa) ^ Colour Vr\.veW\K£Z
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
d«i,,.t Federico Mayor
THE HUMAN RIGHT
TO PEACE
"The purpose of the Organization is to contribute to peace and security by promoting collaboration among
the nations through education, science and culture in orderto further universal respect for justice, forthe
rule of law and for the human rights and fundamental freedoms which are affirmed for the peoples of the
world, without distinction of race, sex, language or religion, by the Charter of the United Nations."
( C(» IN ST I T 1 T I O l\ O ! II INK SC O, A K T I C I. K I)
Lasting peace is a prerequisite for the exercise of all human
rights and duties. It is not the peace of silence, of men and
women who hy choice or constraint remain silent. It is the
peace of freedom and therefore of just laws of happiness,
equality, and solidarity, in which all citizens count, live together
and share.
Peace, development and democracy form an interactive tri¬
angle. They are mutually reinforcing. Without democracy,
there is no sustainahle development: disparities hecome unsus-
tainahle and lead to imposition and domination.
In 1995, the fiftieth anniversary of the United Nations and
UlSESCO and the United Nations Year for Tolerance, we stressed
that it was only through a daily effort to know others better and
respect them that we would he able to tackle at source the
problems of marginalization, indifference, resentment and
hatred. This is the only way to break the vicious circle that
leads from insults to confrontation and the use of force.
We must identify the roots of global problems and strive,
with imagination and determination, to cheek conflicts in their
early stages. Better still prevent them. Prevention is the victory
that gives the measure of our distinctively human faculties.
We must know in order to foresee. Foresee in order to prevent.
We must act in a timely, decisive and courageous manner, know¬
ing that prevention engages the attention only when it fails.
Peace, health and normality do not make the news. We shall
have to try to give greater prominence to these intangibles,
these unheralded triumphs.
A universal renunciation of violence requires the commit¬
ment of the whole of society. These are not matters of govern¬
ment but matters of State; not only matters for the authorities,
but for society in its entirety (including civilian, military, and
religious bodies). The mobilization which is urgently needed to
effect the transition within two or three years from a culture
of war to a culture of peace demands co-operation from every¬
one. In order to change, the world needs everyone. A new
approach to security is required at world, regional and national
levels. The armed forces must be the guarantors of democra¬
tic stability and the protection of the citizen, because we can¬
not move from systems of complete security and no freedom to
systems of complete freedom and no security. Ministries of war
and defence must gradually be turned into ministries of peace.
Dccision-makingprocedures and measures to deal with emer¬
gencies must be specially designed to ensure speed, co-ordina¬
tion and effectiveness. We arc prepared for improbable wars
involving thelarge-scale deployment ofinordinalely costly equip¬
ment, but we are not equipped to detect and mitigate the nat¬
ural or man-provoked disasters that occur repeatedly. We an; vul¬
nerable to the inclemency of the weather, to the vicissitudes of
nature. The protection of the citizen must be seen as one of the
major tasks of society as a whole if we really wish to consoli¬
date a framework for genuinely democratic living. Investing in
emergency help and relief measures and above allin preven¬
tion and the long term (for example, in continent-wide water dis¬
tribution and storage networks) is to be prepared for peace, to
be prepared to live in peace. Currently, we are prepared for
possible war, but find ourselves surprised and defenceless in our
daily lives in the face of mishaps of all kinds.
The United Nations system must likewise equip itself with
the necessary response capacity to prevent the recurrence of
atrocities and instances of genocide such as those which today
afflict our collective conscience Cambodia, Bosnia and Herze¬
govina, Liberia, Somalia and Rwanda...
There is today a general desire for peace, and we must applaud
the clear thinkingand strength of mind displayed by all the war-
ring parlies in the accords that have been reached in El Salvador,
Namibia, Mozambique, Angola, South Africa, Guatemala and the
Philippines. These agreements (ill us with hope hut also sad¬
ness, when we think of the lives sacrificed on the long road to
the cease-fire, and of the open wounds, so difficult to heal. Thus,
as we revive the concept of the "construction of peace in the
tQouTHE UNESCO lOURIER« |ULY-AUGUST 199:,
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
minds of men", we now call on all adversaries who still put their
trust in weapons to lay down their arms and seek reconciliation.
Condemnation will not suffice. It is time for action. It is
not enough to feel outrage when we learn of the number of
children exploited sexually or at work, of refugees or of those
suffering from hunger. We must react, each of us to the best
of our abilities. It is not just a matter of looking at what the gov¬
ernment is doing. We must part with something of "our own".
We must give, give of ourselves. We must stop imposing mod¬
els of development, models for living. The right to peace, to live
in peace, implies jettisoning the belief that some are virtuous
and correct while others are wrong, and that some are always
giving while others are always in need.
It is clear that we cannot simultaneously pay the price of war
and the price of peace. Guaranteeing lifelong education for
all would enable us to: control population growth, improve the
quality of life, increase civic participation, reduce migratory
flows, level out differences in income, assert cultural identity
and prevent the destruction of the environment through sub¬
stantial changes in energy use patterns and urban transport; pro¬
mote endogenous development and the transfer of knowledge;
foster the swift and effective operation of justice, with appro¬
priate machinery for international co-operation; provide the
United Nations system with appropriate facilities to tackle
transnational problems in time. None of this can be achieved in
a context of war. What is needed, then, is to reduce the invest¬
ment in arms and destruction in order to increase investment in
the construction of peace.
Education by example
The distillation of traditions, thoughts, languages, forms of
expression, memories, things forgotten, wishes, dreams, exper¬
iments, rejections, culture finds its supreme expression in our
everyday behaviour. Infinite cultural diversity is our great
resource, which is underpinned this is our strength by uni¬
versal cultural values that must be passed on from the cradle to
the grave. Family members especially mothers teachers, the
media, everyone must help to spread the ethical principles, the
universal guidelines that are so necessary today for haves and
have-nots alike: the latter because they have a right to the basic
minimum standards that human dignity demands; the more for¬
tunate because material goods fail to deliver the expected plea¬
sure. Where there is no longing, possession brings no enjoyment.
In education, tools are useful. But nothing can replace the
friendly words of a teacher, or the caresses and smiles of parents.
The only real education is education by example . . . and love.
Learning without frontiers whether geographical, or fron¬
tiers of age or language can help to change the world, by
eliminating or reducing the many barriers that today impede
universal access to knowledge and education. Education must
help to strengthen, reclaim and develop the culture and iden¬
tity of peoples.
Globalization carries with it a danger of uniformity and
increases the temptation to turn inwards and take refuge in all
kinds of convictions religious, ideological, cultural, or nation
alistic. Confronted with this threat, we must "emphasize the
forms of learning and critical thinking that enable individuals to
understand changing environments, create new knowledge and
shape their own destinies". Indigenous peoples must be placed
on an equal footing with other cultures, participating fully in the
drafting and application of laws. Peace means diversity, a blend¬
ing of "hybrid, wandering cultures" as Carlos Fuentes put it;
it means multi-ethnic and multilingual societies. Peace is not
an abstract idea but one rooted firmly in cultural, political,
social and economic contexts.
Eliminating violence
Above all, this profound transformation from oppression and con¬
finement to openness and generosity, this change based on the
daily use hy all of us of the verb "to share" which is the key to
a new future cannot be achieved without our young people,
and certainly not behind their backs. We must tell them they
who represent our hope, who are calling for our help and who seek
in us and in external authorities the answers to their uncertainties
and preoccupations that it is in themselves that they must dis¬
cover the answers, that the motivations and glimpses of light that
they are seeking can be found within themselves. Although at
times it may be difficult, given both their consternation and our
own, to present the situation to them in those terms, our position
as lifelong teachers and learners obliges us to say to young people,
as Cavafy put it in a poem: "Ithaca gave you the journey. . . . She
has nothing left to give you now". Each according to his own plan.
Each according to his own way of thinking. Free from self-serving
outside interference, especially when it robs the young of their own
"core", the intellect, talent and resourcefulness which are the most
precious individual and collective treasure of humankind. Sects
and the escape provided by drug addiction are the clearest symp¬
toms of this pathological state of mind that is our great problem
today. Indeed, education means activating this immense potential
and using it to its fullest so that each may become the master and
architect of his or her own destiny. We cannot give to youth what
we no longer possess in youthful vitality but instead we can offer
what we have learned through experience, the fruit of our failures
and successes, of the burdens, joys, pain, and perplexity and the
renewed inspiration of each new moment.
Let youth hold high the banner of peace and justice! So con¬
vinced am 1 of the relevance of this goal to the proper fulfilment
ofour mission that I have proposed to the General Conference that
it designate "UNESCO and youth" as a central topic for discussion
at its next session. That will be an appropriate moment since the
General Conference will be considering for adoption the "Decla¬
ration on the Safeguarding of Future Generations".
At all the United Nations conferences, regardless of the sub¬
ject under consideration (environment, popidation, social devel¬
opment, human rights and democracy, women, housing), there
has been a consensus that education is the key to the urgently
needed change in the direction pursued by today's world, which
is increasing disparities in the possession of material goods and
knowledge, instead of reducing them. To invest in education is not
only to respect a fundamental right but also to build peace and
74
THL UNESCO lOURiTRBIULY AUGUST 1<»7
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
progress for the world's peoples. Education for all, by all, through¬
out life: this is the great challenge. One which allows of no delay.
Each child is the most important heritage to be preserved. U\KSC()
may at times give the impression that it is only interested in pre¬
serving stone monuments or natural landscapes. That is not true.
Those efforts are the most visible. And the heritage thus safe¬
guarded the least vulnerable. But we must protect our entire
heritage: the spiritual, the intangible, the genetic heritage
and, especially, ethics. These are the basic, universal values that
our Constitution sets forth with inspired clarity. If we sincerely
believe that each child is our child, then we must radically change
the parameters of the "globalization" currently underway. And
the human being must become the beneficiary and main actor of
all our policies and strategies.
A system collapsed in 1989 because, concentrating on equal¬
ity, it forgot liberty. The present system focused on liberty, will
know the same fate if it forgets equality and solidarity. The
din made as the "Iron Curtain" collapsed drowned out the
tremor that ran through the foundations of the "winning" side
in the Cold War. We must, then, for the sake of both principle
and self-interest, redouble in every field the fight against exclu¬
sion and marginalization. We must all feel involved. We must all
work to ease the great transition from the logic of force to the
force of reason; from oppression to dialogue; from isolation to
interaction and peaceful coexistence. But first we must live, and
give meaning to life. Eliminating violence: that is our resohe.
Preventing violence and compulsion by going, as 1 said before,
to the very sources of resentment, extremism, dogmatism and
fatalism. Poverty, ignorance, discrimination and exclusion an;
forms of violence which can cause although they can never jus¬
tify aggression, the use of force and fratricidal conflict.
Swords into ploughshares
A peace consciousness in the interests of living together, of sci¬
ence and its applications does not appear overnight, nor can
it he imposed by decree. First comes disillusionment with
materialism and enslavement to the market, and then a return
to freedom of thought and action, sincerity, austerity, the
indomitable force of the mind, the key to peace and to war, as
affirmed by the founders of UlNKSCO.
Science is always positive, but the same cannot always be
said of its applications. Advances in technology and knowledge
can be used to enrich or to impoverish the lives of human
beings; they can help to develop their identity and enhance
their capacities or, on the contrary, they can be used to under¬
mine the personality and coarsen human talent. Only conscience,
which is responsibility and thus ethical and moral can make
good use of the artefacts of reason. Conscience must work in tan¬
dem with reason. To the ethics of responsibility we must add
an ethics of conviction and will. The former springs from knowl¬
edge, and the latter from passion, compassion and wisdom.
We are now approaching the end of a century of amazing sci¬
entific and technological progress: we can diagnose and treat
many diseases which cause suffering and death; we communi¬
cate with extraordinary clarity and speed; we have at our dis
posal instant, limitless information. However, antibiotics and
telecommunications do not compensate for the bloody con¬
flicts which have cut down millions of lives in their prime and
inflicted indescribable suffering on so many innocent people. All
the obscenities of war, brought home to us nowadays by audio¬
visual equipment, do not seem able to halt the advance of the
huge war machine set up and maintained over many centuries.
Present generations have the almost impossible, biblical task
of "beating their swords into ploughshares" and making the
transition from an instinct for war developed since time
immemorial to a feeling for peace. To achieve this would be
the best and most noble act that the "global village" could
accomplish, and the best legacy to our descendants. With what
satisfaction and relief should we be able to look into the eyes
of our children! It would be also the best way to celebrate the
fiftieth anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human
Bights, in 1998.
Other "rights" have been added since 1918. These should
all be taken into account, and to them should he added the right
which underlies them all: the right to peace the right to live
in peace! The right to our own "personal sovereignty", to respect
for life and dignity.
Constructing the defences
of peace
Human rights! At the dawn of the new millennium, our ideal
must be to put them into practice, to add to them, to live and
breathe them, to relive them, to revive them with every new day!
No one nation, institution or person should feel entitled to lay
sole claim to human rights, still less to determine others' cre¬
dentials in this regard. Human rights can neither be owned nor
given, but must be won and deserved afresh with every passing
day. Nor should they be regarded as an abstraction, but rather
as practical guidelines for action which should be part of the
lives of all men and women and enshrined in the laws of every
country. Let us translate the Declaration into all languages;
let it be studied in every classroom and every home, all over the
world! Today's ideal may thus become the happy reality of
tomorrow! Learning to know, to do, to be and to live together!
I appeal to all families, educators, religious figures, parlia¬
mentarians, politicians, artists, intellectuals, scientists, craft-
workers and journalists, to all humanitarian, sporting and cultural
organizations and to the media to spread a message of toler¬
ance, non-violence, peace and justice. Our aim must be to foster
understanding, generosity and solidarity, so that with our minds
more focused on the future than on the past, we may be able to
look ahead together and build, however difficult the conditions
or inhospitable the setting, a future of ¡peace, which is a fun¬
damental right and prerequisite. Thus, "We, the people" will
have fulfilled the promise we made in 1915, our eyes still seared
by the most abominable images of the terrible conflict that had
just ended "to save succeeding generations from the scourge of
war", "to construct the defences of peace in the minds" of all the
peoples of the Earth.
>cTHE UNESCO I^OURIERB |ULY AUGUST 1997
75
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
1
1
Sarajevo's battered
soul
~»5
^V
,« fe ij^,^
Sarajevo Library (in
background, behind
a minaret in the
Ottoman quarter).
I "The day the Sarajevo Library
burned down, in 1992, and
the ashes rained gently down over
the city," says Maja Barlich, a staff
member of Bosnia and Herzegov¬
ina's Institute for the Protection of
the Heritage, with sadness in her
voice, "everyone was crying, as if
they had lost someone dear to
them."
The magnificent Viennese-style
building which stood on the edge
of the Ottoman quarter, grandly
embodying the city's cultural iden¬
tity, spirit and history, was
destroyed by the fury and accurate
shelling of fighting men. The ruins
did not, however, remain silent for
long. Music soon took possession
of the shell of the building, hcrald-
by Pascale d'Erm
rushing waters of the Miljacka, now
flowing clear once more.
Leaving behind the seriously
shell-damaged high-rise blocks of
flats of the Tito period, the=trav-
eller arrives in the city centre, where
the strictly classical architecture and
the ochre and pink mansions, now
windowless or unsafe, serve as a
reminder that this was part of the
Austro-Hungarian Empire until
early in the century. Then comes the
fifteenth-century Ottoman quar¬
ter, Bascarsija with its maze of
medieval lanes and the oriental
charms of Slatilo cose, the "Sweet
corner", so called because of its
many pastry shops. This old neigh¬
bourhood was relatively little dam¬
aged and soon came back to life. Its
shops reopened quickly, and the
imposing Begova Disrinja mosque
is being rebuilt.
"Sarajevo was very badly dam¬
aged," emphasizes Colin Kaiser, head
of UNESCO's Sarajevo office. "They
wanted to smash the city's identity.
Irremediable losses of archival mate-
ing a kind of cultural resistance
movement. "We still went to the
ruined library during the war," Maja
Barlich recalls. "Several concerts were
given there I remember hearing
Mozart's Requiem." Ruined build¬
ings nearby were made the venue
for film festivals and other cultural
events. Despite the shelling and
bombing, Sarajevo's pulse went on
beating regularly.
Unlike its illustrious neigh¬
bours such as Dubrovnik or
Budapest, Sarajevo never enjoyed
the reputation of being an impor¬
tant cultural centre. Built in a nar¬
row valley, the city and its five cen¬
turies of history are strung out for
seven kilometres along the notori
ous "Sniper Alley" and beside the §
76
THE UNESCO lOURlfR JULY-AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="77">
<![CDATA[
Unesco is supporting the reconstruction of
Sarajevo's pluricultural heritage, damaged by the
savagery of ethnic cleansing
v» rn
The shell-damaged façade of a Sarajevo house dating from the time
of the Austro-Hungarian empire.
rial were caused by the destruction of
the library, the National Museum
and the Oriental Institute. A whole
segment of Bosnia and Herzegov¬
ina's memory has been wiped out."
The selection of targets and the accu¬
racy of fire produced terrible results:
universities, schools, research estab¬
lishments, museums and the finest
of the Austro-Hungarian mansions
were systematically targeted. The dif¬
ference in the amount of damage
done to religious buildings is no
coincidence: the Orthodox church
and cathedral seem to have survived
unscathed but some of the mosques
in the Ottoman quarter were heavily
bombarded. Some of the old resi¬
dential neighbourhoods also suf¬
fered badly; many houses that were
thought to have been spared were in
fact hit by shells.
Piecemeal
reconstruction
Sarajevo is no longer entirely a
wasteland. "The city has been chang-
The Library's
devastated interior.
ing very rapidly of late," explains
Francis Bueb, the founder of the
André Malraux Cultural Centre,
which was set up while the war was
still raging. "The streets have been
cleaned up, the rubble cleared, the
burned-out cars removed and the
broken windows replaced." The
reconstruction of Bosnia and
Herzegovina has begun, albeit on a
modest scale.
The rebuilding of the cultural
heritage may seem to be of sec¬
ondary importance to the major
institutions which are hard at work
finding funds for urgent small-scale
projects, but for the people who
live here, the return to normality
also involves the rebuilding of their
cultural identity. "Destroying our
heritage was a way of denying our
existence", says Maja Barlich. "The
cultural monuments and sites have
to be restored in order for us to
recover our national traditions and
identity."
Lack of co-ordination
Urgent action is needed. Winds can
be very violent in Sarajevo and can
hasten the collapse of weakened
buildings, while the lack of co-ordi¬
nation in international reconstruc¬
tion efforts is hampering opera¬
tions. Since the Dayton agreement
was signed, such efforts have
increased in number but there has
not been enough co-ordination,
some countries financing operations
without knowing whether or not
other countries have already drawn
up estimates for the same project.
This lack of co-ordination is pre¬
venting full realization of the objec¬
tives: Austria, for example, with the
help of European Union funding,
has undertaken the cleaning and
protection of the library, but no-
one knows who will be responsi¬
ble for the next stage of the opera¬
tion (the total cost of which has
been reckoned at around $14 mil¬
lion). Discussion has begun as to
whether the library will recover the
literary, cultural and historical func¬
tions it had before the war or be
assigned other functions of a more
administrative nature, such as it had
THE UNESCO Ç>URIERB |ULY AUGUST 1997 77
]]>
</page>
<page number="78">
<![CDATA[
in its early days. The debate is sure
to be lively, in view of the build¬
ing's symbolic importance.
The political make-up of Bosnia
and Herzegovina is scarcely con¬
ducive to making the country's cul¬
tural reconstruction any simpler:
each of the ten districts composing
the Muslim-Croat Federation, for
instance, has responsibilities in the
field of culture, but some districts
have no suitable structure to dis¬
charge these responsibilities.
On the road to
reconstruction
"At present there is no interna¬
tional-level order of priorities," says
Colin Kaiser. "The precise extent of
damage to cultural property in the
Muslim-Croat Federation is
unknown and, apart from exten¬
sive damage to religious buildings
mosques and Catholic churches
little is known about the situation
in the Serb Republic. This is why
we want to set up a forward-look¬
ing programme for the reconstruc¬
tion of the country's cultural her¬
itage." Unesco is due to send a
mission to Sarajevo in the near
future for that purpose.
For the time being, the main
project is for the rehabilitation of
the old town of Mostar, a pro¬
gramme financed by the Italian gov¬
ernment, and for the restoration of
a mosque, also in Mostar, funded
by Saudi Arabia.
In October 1996 UNESCO,
which has already been playing a
part in the refurbishment of the
National Museum, organized a sem¬
inar on the reconstruction of the
cultural heritage, enabling interna¬
tional experts to work alongside
Bosnian student architects and local
engineers. "There were 35 local par¬
ticipants and experts from all over
the world," explains Sibyl Renaud,
administrative officer in UNESCO's
Sarajevo office. "They worked on
two cases in Sarajevo the library
and the old Ottoman quarter and
three building sites in Mostar."
According to French architectJ.-
L. Taupin, a historic monuments spe¬
cialist who took part in the seminar,
"coexistence is working well. We can¬
not imagine the reconstruction of
Sarajevo without the city's history
being taken into consideration."
heritage has been
hard hit by recent
events in that
country.
Here Ylljet Aliçka,
Chief of the Foreign
Affairs Department
of the Albanian
Ministry of Culture,
Youth and Women's
Affairs, talks to
Jasmina Sopova.
The pictures coming out of
Albania since March 1997 show a
country in turmoil. The media
report army barracks being
sacked, automatic rifles being
freely toted around, curfews
being imposed, European soldiers
being landed for Operation Alba,
snap elections being called and so
on, but not a word about culture.
Ylljet Aliçka: In times of trouble,
unfortunately, culture is not
regarded as a priority inside the
country any more than it is out¬
side. The damage that is being
inflicted on Albania's culture is per¬
haps less serious than the economic
harm it is suffering, but it is
irreparable: in time the economy
will recover, but artefacts bearing
witness to centuries of culture will
have disappeared forever.
What is the bill for the damage?
Y. A.: It is hard to say with any cer¬
tainty at present, just as it is hard to
say what is the motivation behind
it: is it wanton destruction or delib¬
erate looting? The estimated cost of
damage to cultural property amounts
to around $800,000. Many municipal
buildings, cinemas and museums
have been wrecked. The Tirana Fac¬
ulty of Agriculture, which was par¬
ticularly well computerized, has been
plundered, and some 400,000 books
have gone up in flames.
Is there a parallel here with
what happened to the Sarajevo
library?
Y. A.: No, the books were not
burned for the same reasons. In Sara-
jevo the aim was to destroy a cen¬
turies-old heritage that was shared
by the different communities, to
wipe the slate of history clean. In
Albania, where the different ethnic
groups have historically lived
together in harmony, I would say
the burning of the books led on
from the street fighting. The books
78
THE UNESCO IpURILR JULY-AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="79">
<![CDATA[
threatened heritage
The medieval city of
Berat in central
Albania has a rich
architectural
heritage.
in the municipal libraries were
destroyed together with the library
buildings, and the Faculty of Agri¬
culture's huge collection disappeared
together with its computers. There
was no political motive behind the
destruction of the books.
What about the museums?
Y. A.: The Dürres Archaeological
Museum was seriously damaged and
eighty objects dating from the Illyr-
ian period were stolen, but the
inventory was preserved and will
perhaps make it possible to track
the objects down later, when the
country has dealt with its most
urgent problems. The case of
Butrinti, on the other hand, is far
more serious: this ancient site,
which was included on UNESCO's
World Heritage List1 in 1992, was
ransacked, its museum looted and
its records burned, so that no inves¬
tigation is possible. Being in the
south of the country, the site is for
the time being inaccessible to the
authorities.
So the looting will go on. . . .
Y. A.: Maybe, but the public is
starting to react, which is a very
encouraging sign. While some peo¬
ple are plundering and devastating
everything they come across, others
risk their lives to save whatever can
still be saved: a well-known film¬
maker, for example, personally
stood out against the attack on the
Tirana Cinematographic Centre,
and a librarian was killed when she
tried to protect the books in the
Berat municipal library. In both
Berat and Korcha men and women
took up arms to defend the
medieval icon museums, and many
of the icons arc now under protec¬
tion in private hands.
We do not, however, have the
resources to establish a strategy for
the protection of our cultural her¬
itage, which is why we have just
appealed for support to the Coun¬
cil of Europe in Strasbourg and
why we shall shortly be turning to
UNESCO and other international
institutions.
1 See "Butrinti rediscovered" by Zija
Xholiin the June 1994 issues of the
Unesco Courier (Biotechnology: The
resourceful gene)
-
THE UNESCO lOURIER JULY AUGUST 1997 I
]]>
</page>
<page number="80">
<![CDATA[
orests:
a breathing
space for
the planet
by France Bequette
Forests are the earth's most
complex and elaborate natural
ecosystems. They cover about 10
per cent of the planet's surface and
26 j>er cent of the continental sur¬
face area (excluding Greenland and
Antarctica). The globe's biggest pro¬
ducers of hiomass, they exercise
great influence on energy exchanges
between the atmosphere and the
ground, intercepting solar radiation,
acting as a windbreak, fixing carbon
dioxide and returning a great deal
of water vapour to the atmosphere
via évapotranspiration. They are
directly dependent on the climate
and also one of its main regulators.
THE PRIMEVAL FOREST
Some 300 million years ago forests
of tree ferns and giant horsetail cov¬
ered the earth. Traces of them can be
found in coal deposits. Then the
oceans submerged the continents.
When the water retreated about 260
million years ago, conifers appeared,
followed some 130 million years later
by broad-leaved trees.
In the Tertiary era, about 50 mil¬
lion years ago, the northern hemi¬
sphere had a mild climate that was
propitious for the development of
W THE UNESCO ÇjURIER I
plant life and was brought to an end
hy the onset of an Ice age. The fate
of vegetation was strongly influenced
hy the location of mountain chains.
Europe's east-west mountain mas¬
sifs prevented the migration of
plants, and tropical and sub-tropi¬
cal species died from the cold. In
the Americas on the other hand the
mountains run on a north-south axis
and presented no such obstacle. East
Asia had no Ice age and a large num¬
ber of species survived there and
later successfully reacclimatized to
places where they had once pros-
pered. This explains why the parks
and gardens of Europe contain maid¬
enhair, magnolia, maple and cherry
trees imported from Asia.
There are four major types of
forest (boreal-conifer, temperate-
broad leaf, scrubland and rain for¬
est). Conifers are dominant in the
boreal forest, from Alaska to
Boreal forest in
Alaska.
Labrador and from Scandinavia to
Siberia and Kamchatka, interming¬
ling with birch, willow and aspen.
The dark foliage of pines contrasts
with the white trunks of birches,
and the grass between the trees is
splashed with the colours of a thou¬
sand flowers. In the temperate zone
of the Northern hemisphere it is
too hot in the Southern hemi¬
sphere the appearance of the for¬
est changes with the seasons. The
slender trunks of oaks, elms and
maples form lofty groves of trees
crowned with intertwining branches.
Their leaves change colour from
light to dark green, then to the golds
and reds of autumn before falling to
the ground. On stony or sandy soils in
regions with Mediterranean or Cali-
fornian climates grow leathery-
leaved trees like the olive, succulent
plants such as cactus and the dense
scrub known as garrigue, maquis and
Olive trees in
Andalusia
(Spain).
IULY-AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="81">
<![CDATA[
chaparral. In tropical areas the lux¬
uriant forest demands an even heat
and plenty of rain throughout the
year. The trees reach for the sky in
search of sunlight, sometimes climb¬
ing to 50 or 60 metres amidst a tan¬
gle of lianas and epiphytes.
A CARBON RESERVOIR
We know more than we did about
the interactions between forest and
climate, but they still give rise to
debate among specialists. Gilbert
Aussenac of the French National
Institute of Agronomic Research
(INKA) believes that the forest is a
more effective sunlight trap than
any other plant formation. Heat
stocked in the morning is restored
to the atmosphere in the evening.
When it conies into contact with
humid air hovering above the for¬
est, it causes rainstorms.
In order to show that the rainfall
regime is strongly influenced by the
forest cover, scientists have made a
model of the total deforestation of
the 5-million-km Amazon basin. In
this hypothesis the temperature of
the air would rise by from Io to 3°C
because of the fall in évapotranspi¬
ration, which would also result in a 26
per cent decrease in rainfall!
Less well known, but vital for the
future of the earth's climate, is the
relationship between the forest and
the increase in atmosjiheric carbon
dioxide (CCL). The concentration of
CO¿ in the earth's atmosphere has
risen from 280 volumes per million
(vpm) at the beginning of the indus- Temperate
trial era to 360 volumes today. This deciduous forest
in Canada,
is a staggering increase when com¬
pared with the 80-vpm rise that
took place in the 200,000 preceding
years, as calculated from measure¬
ments made in niicrohubhles con¬
tained in polar ice. The ligure may
well double by the middle of the
next century.
Forests play a dual role in the
earth's carbon cycle by absorbing a
large amount of the C02 contained
in the atmosphere and also by emit¬
ting C02. The biosphere and the
atmosphere annually exchange enor¬
mous amounts of carbon. The annual
flow of atmospheric C02 fixed in
plants by photosynthesis amounts to
some 100 billion tons, but this is
almost entirely counterbalanced by a
reverse flow caused by the breathing
of plants and micro-organisms in the
soil such as bacteria and fungi, which
Tropical rain
forest in
Cameroon.
decompose ground litter and organic
matter. If, for the moment, forest
ecosystems are fairly good sponges
for absorbing the CO., which we pro¬
duce and which helps them to grow,
they will no longer be able to do so if
emissions continue to increase and
deforestation is not halted.
DEFORESTATION
According to the Food and Agricul¬
ture Organization of the United
Nations (FAO), which is carrying out
a Forest Resources Assessment Pro¬
gramme, forests covered some 3,454
million hectares world-wide in 1995,
somewhat more than half of which
were located in developing countries.
Retween 1990 and 1995 the world's
forests underwent an estimated net
loss of 56.3 million hectares, com¬
prising a loss of 65.1 million hectares
in developing countries partly offset
by an increase of 8.8 million hectares
in the industrialized countries. For¬
est loss was not, however, as great as
predicted and has decreased overall.
Some communities have no
choice but to contribute to defor¬
estation. In dryland and upland areas
exposed to erosion, for example,
needy communities chop down the
sparse trees to provide fuel, food
and a meagre source of income.
Other contributory factors are over¬
grazing, extensive farming and fire
the scourge of dry forests of the
£ Mediterranean variety.
I The development of subsistence
s farmingin Africa and tropical Asia and
J the implementation of far-reaching
}QxiRI ERB JULY AUGUST 1997
81
]]>
</page>
<page number="82">
<![CDATA[
economic development programmes
in Latin America and Asia are lead¬
ing to a considerable decrease of for¬
est cover in these regions. Again
according to the FAO, demographic
growth is expected to force certain
parts of the world such as sub-Saha-
ran Africa and Latin America to
transform forest into farmland.
There is no guarantee that such a
conversion will benefit the popula¬
tions in question. B
Further reading:
STATE OFTHE WORLD'S FORESTS
an FAO report, Rome 1997
LA GESTION DURABLE
DES FORÊTS
les dossiers de l'INRA, no. 12,
autumn 1996
BOIS ET FORÊTS DES TROPIQUES
QRAD-Forêt, no. 240, 1994
A WORLD CONGRESS ON FORESTS
The llth World Forestry Congress, jointly organized by Turkey and
the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO),
will be held in Antalya (Turkey) from 13 to 22 October 1997. Its
main theme is "Forestry for Sustainable Development: Towards the
21st Century".
The meeting will examine a number of sub-themes, including: a)
forest and tree resources, b) forests, biological diversity and mainte¬
nance of the natural heritage, c) protective and environmental func¬
tions of forests, d) productive functions of forests, e) the economic con¬
tribution of forestry to sustainable development, f) social dimensions
of forestry's contribution to sustainable development, g) policies,
institutions and means for sustainable forestry development.
For further information, contact:
The Organizing Committee of the llth World Forestry Congress,
Ministry of Forests, Atatiirk Rulvari, no. 153 Bakanliklar,
06100 Ankara, Turkey.
Tel: 90-312-417 7724; Fax: 90-312-417 9160.
E-mail: obdi-f@scrvis.net.tr
or
The Organizing Committee of the 1 lth World Forestry Congress,
Department of Forests, FAO, Via délie Terme di Caraealla,
00100 Rome, Italy.
Tel: 39-6-5225 5088; Fax: 39-6-5225 5137;
e-mail: luis.botero@fao.org;
web site: http://www.fao.org/waiceiit/faoinfo/forestry/wforcong
A fossilized tree
fern (New
Zealand).
world
PLASTIC PLANTS
Plastic exists naturally, albeit
in minute amounts, in the leaves
of many plants, including cotton
or mustard, but is far more
expensive to extract than pro¬
duce synthetically. However,
scientists now hope to increase
the plastic production capac¬
ity of certain plants through
genetic engineering, so that
some commercially grown
species such as sweet corn
could become veritable "plastic
factories". But there are still
many imponderables, and so far
cultivated biodegradable ¡plas¬
tic remains a pipedream. I
A BREATH
OF FRESH AIR
Air pollution is having increas¬
ingly damaging effects on health
in the world's big cities. In Bom¬
bay, for example, where the lev¬
els of lead in the air are esti¬
mated to have doubled between
1980 and 1987, it is thought to
be responsible for a steep rise
in respiratory ailments, heart
disease and skin allergies. The
World Bank and the United
Nations Development Pro¬
gramme have launched an urban
air quality management pro¬
gramme as part of their broader
programme to help five Asian
urban areas (Beijing, Bombay,
Colombo, Jakarta, Kathmandu
and greater Manila) solve their
worsening environmental prob-
82
THE UNESCO IpURlEB |ULY-AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="83">
<![CDATA[
lenis. Stricter emissions stan¬
dards and lower jirices for
unleaded gasoline are among the
main measures ¡proposed. I
LIGHTENING
THE PRESSURE
ON CORK
Cork, an impermeable protec¬
tive material that grows as the
inner bark of certain trees,
forms a particularly thick layer
in cork oak trees, which are
grown on a commercial basis.
But it takes a 25-) ear growth
period before the tree pro¬
duces its first yield, followed
by a 1 0-year wait between each
harvest. In order to meet grow¬
ing demand, cork is now being
harvested too frequently, weak¬
ening trees which have also
been threatened by a harmful
fungus since 1992. In 1996 a
Belgian organization called Le
Petit Liège (The Little Cork)
launched an operation to col¬
lect all discarded cork objects
for recycling. Cork is a good
heat and sound insulator, and
after being ground is used in the
building industry. Recycling of
this kind could help take the
{pressure off cork oaks in
France, Spain and Portugal.
ENVIRONMENT-FRIENDLY
CHEWING GUM
Fed up with finding pieces of
chewed gum stuck on chairs,
desks and even statues in pub¬
lic: places, an American inven¬
tor has patented a new kind of
chewing gum that turns brittle
when discarded and can be eas¬
ily removed from surfaces. The
gum will also dissolve in the
mouth after a period of chew¬
ing and can even be swallowed
without disagreeable after¬
effects.
HEAVY
EATERS
In the United States a number
of sites contaminated by heavy
metals are awaiting rlcanup
measures. But traditional soil-
washing technology is cosily and
impoverishes the soil, and as a
result there is growinginterest in
plant-based soil-cleansing tech¬
niques. Two scientists are exper¬
imenting with plants called
hyperaeeiimulators, which may
do the job less quickly but are
far more economical, environ¬
ment-friendly and effective.
Ilyperaccumulatora can absorb
metallic and other pollutants in
concentrations from 10 to 100
times the accumulation of a
metal tolerated by ordinary
crops. A small shrub called
Alpine pennycrcss (Thlaspi
caerulescens), for example,
digests zinc, cadmium and
nickel; and carrots absorb DDT
(see "Initiatives" in the U\HSC()
Courier, November 1996). The
scientists even wonder whether
some hyperaeeiimulators could
be used to farm metals as an
alternative to mininii! H
POLLUTION
HITS CASPIAN
FISHERIES
Serious pollution and heavy
overfishing are endangering the
marine resources of the Caspian
Sea. In Iran, for example, stur¬
geon catches are 75 per cent
down on 1984. After cutting its
quotas by half, Iran has drawn
up a sturgeon hatcheries devel¬
opment plan designed to boost
caviare production. It has also
concluded agreements with
neighbouring countries to
determine catch shares and
control poaching. Certain types
of net are being outlawed, and
the potential of some fish
species for human consumption
is beins reassessed. I
TROPICAL FOREST
CORNUCOPIA
An expanded and updated tw o-
volume edition of Tropical
Forests, People and Food has
been published in French by
U.MKSOO's Man and the Bios¬
phere Programme. The original
1 -volume English edition was
first published in 1993. The
study examines food resources,
food production and consump¬
tion and the cultural founda¬
tions for food choices and devel¬
opment strategies. The English
edition contains 74 scientific
articles about the daily lives of
people living in tropical areas,
their habits, their beliefs and
their understanding of the for¬
est's resources. This richly doc¬
umented volume is a must for
anyone interested in tropical
development. I
EARTHWORM FERTILIZER
The French Institute of Scien¬
tific Research for Development
in Co-operation (ORSTOM), the
University of Sambaljpur (India)
and an Indian fanning company
havepionecred the use of earth¬
worms to replace fertilizer on tea
plantations. The earthworm is a
useful ally because it enriches
the soil by its droppings which
are rich in minerals (nitrogen and
phosphates) and humus. By
making tunnels it improves soil
drainage and aeration. It also
stimulates the fungi that live in
symbiosis with tea-bush roots
and promotes water, nitrogen and
phosphorus absorption. The
selected worms, which belong to
a particularly active local vari¬
ety, are raised on the plantations.
The results speak for themselves:
tea production has risen by 35
to 240 per cent depending on the
site, and consumption of chemi¬
cal fertilizer has been halved.I
dÇiuTHE UNESCO (pURlERB |ULY AUGUST 1007
So
]]>
</page>
<page number="84">
<![CDATA[
HERITAGE
the divine faces of
EOHHUACÁN
by Cécile Romane
After a century of archaeological
investigation, the remains of the city-state of
Teotihuacán (Mexico) still guard many of their
secrets. This pre-hispanic site, the largest in
Mesoamerica, was included on Unesco's World
Heritage List in 1987.
In the absence of written
I records, the history of
Teotihuacán, the former capital
of the greatest pre-Columbian
urban civilization in the Valley of
Mexico (2nd to 7th centuries),
lying forty kilometres north of
Mexico City, is still shrouded in
mystery.
It was founded late in the first
century A.D., although the date
cannot be definitively confirmed
in the present state of archaeo¬
logical excavations. It extended
over 40 square kilometres and
boused a sizeable ¡population. The
number of inhabitants is esti¬
mated to have ranged from
100,000 to 160,000, depending
on the period.
After reaching its apogee
between the fourth and fifth cen¬
turies, it suddenly faded away,
according to recent datings (1996),
in the first half of the seventh cen-
Ceramic statuette of a woman with
moveable arms and legs (400 A.D.).
tury. We do not know the exact
reason why this culture died out,
but its decline is thought to have
been hastened by changes in the
ground water level and hence in
the availability of water supplies.
The original name of ihe city is
unknown. The Aztecs called it
Teotihuacán (the "city of the
gods") when they discovered its vast
nuns centuries later. It seemed to
them so imposing that only the gods
could have built it and that they
had created the Fifth Sun there
(see the ÜMW.O Courier, "The sun,
ancient myths, new technologies",
January 1995, p. 12).
THE CEREMONIAL CENTRE
A straight 40-metre-vvide high¬
way, known as the Avenue of the
Dead, runs for more than two kilo¬
metres in a clearly visible succes¬
sion of rectangular squares, all on
the same level with access stair¬
ways. It then continues for
another three kilometres, still
straight as a die, but with less for¬
mally structured adjoining archi¬
tecture. This grandiose prospect
was flanked on either side by over
8<
THE UNESCO lOURIER |ULT-AUGUSr I007
]]>
</page>
<page number="85">
<![CDATA[
HBMHM>mM>^l
Left, the Avenue of
the Dead and the
Pyramid of the Sun
(at left) seen from the
Pyramid of the Moon.
2,000 residential properties
divided into many "apartments",
forerunners of the modern housing
block.
Most of the monuments in
Teotihuacán's ceremonial centre
which, vast though it is, represents
only 10 ¡percent of the city's total
area, stood on this Avenue. The
most imposing of all, the Pyramid
of the Sun (225 x 222 metres at
the base), is the world's third
tallest pyramid. Located on the
east side of the Avenue, it now
rises to a height of around 63
metres (it was originally 75 metres
tall) and has a volume of one mil¬
lion cubic metres.
The less colossal but equally
massive Pyramid of the Moon (150
x 140 metres at the base and 42
metres high) stands at the northern
end of the Avenue of the Dead and
consists of four superimposed plat¬
forms, each set back from the oth¬
ers. The palace of Quetzal jiapalotl,
the mythical Bird-Butterlly, lies
on a square precinct in front of
this ¡pyramid. The bird-butterfly
is represented in bas-reliefs on the
¡patio pilla rs. This edifice, one of
A stone sculpture of
Huehueteotl, god of
fire (c. 200 A.D.).
the few which is not a temple,
may have been the living quarters
of the Moon ¡priests.
South of the Avenue of the
Dead rises the immense quadran¬
gular structure of the "Citadel"
with a side length of around 400
metres and a total surface area of
just under seven hectares. The
square which it forms is delimited
by four ¡platforms (mistakenly
believed by the Spaniards to be the
walls of a fortress). It could easily
accommodate 100,000 ¡persons.
Here stands the Pyramid of
Quetzalcóatl, or the Plumed Ser¬
pent. The monumental steps of
its Western facade have been ¡pre¬
served in excellent condition. The
typical feature of Teotihuacán
architecture is clearly visible
here. This is known as the "talud-
tablero" (slope-and-panel) system,
i.e. an alternation of inclined
embankments and vertical ¡panels,
generally adorned with bas-reliefs.
On its four sides, the ¡pyramid
bears 366 heads of Quetzalcóatl.
These take the shape of circular
¡projections with impressive gap-
ingjaws.
AN INFLUENTIAL CIVILIZATION
The city was designed to harmo¬
nize (dosely with the surrounding
('ountr)side. From the. centre of
the Avenue of the Dead, the sum¬
mit of the nearby mountain, the
Cerro Gordo, can be seen tower¬
ing up above the apex of the Pyra¬
mid of the Moon. The city has a
rigorously geometrical layout. The
ceremonial centre was built around
the North-South axis of the
Avenue of the Dead. The adminis¬
trative ('entre, the market and the
"citadel" lie on an East-West axis.
The layout of the religious and
¡priestly monuments, all lying in the
axis of the Pyramid of the Sun,
which coincides with the sun's rise
to its zenith, respects an astro¬
nomical logic. The cult of the sun
THE UNESCO COURIER I ¡ULY-AUCAIST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="86">
<![CDATA[
H £ R I T A G E
and the study of the ¡planets must
have been of very great importance
to Teotihuacán society.
This rigidly hierarchical soci¬
ety, which lived from trade, was
headed by a theocratic govern¬
ment. The city derived its wealth
from vast deposits of obsidian and
fertile soil. The social classes were
clearly separated according to
their ¡profession: potters, ¡painters,
gemstone ¡polishers, farmers, fish¬
ermen, etc. Teotihuacán was a cos¬
mopolitan centre, its population
consisting of different ethnic
groups living in different districts.
The most important economic,
religious and ¡political centre of
all Mesoamerica, it reveals a
sophisticated knowledge of geom¬
etry, architecture, astronomy and
art. The mythological scenes fig
uring in the ¡paintings which adorn
the ¡palace walls, the layout of the
buildings, reflecting astronomical
rather than military concerns, lead
us to supposes that this civiliza¬
tion, founded on the cult of ter¬
restrial and agrarian deities, was a
peaceful one.
Its influence was felt through¬
out Mesoamerica: two-thirds of
Mexico as we now know it.,
Guatemala, Honduras and Belize.
The art of ¡tottery and ceramic
ware, in ¡particular, left a lasting
mark on the cultures of the Mayas
and Oaxaca. This influence lasted
for a long time. For centuries,
other populations continued to
adore the gods of Teotihuacán:
Quetzalcóatl, the Plumed ser¬
pent, god of humidity and fertil¬
ity, and Tláloc, the rain god.
Some key dates
2ND TO 1ST CENTURY B.C.
The Valley of Teotihuacán is occupied by
a scattered population. There may
already have been a very active pilgrim¬
age centre (perhaps around a grotto).
1-200 A.D.
Concentration of the population and
gradual construction of a holy city. First
sanctuary: the Pyramid of the Sun. The
processional route, known as the Avenue
of the Dead, is laid out perpendicular
to the main axis. Construction of the
Pyramid of the Moon, the "citadel" and
the temple of Quetzalcóatl.
300-650 A.D.
The high point of the City State, cover¬
ing 36 square kilometres. With 125,000
inhabitants it is the largest metropolis
of the New World and the world's sixth
largest city. Its influence extends to
other civilizations: the Totonac culture
around the Gulf of Mexico, the Zapotee
culture in Oaxaca and the cultures of
Western Mexico and the Mayas to the
South.
AROUND 650 A.D.
Collapse of Teotihuacán and end of its
dominance.
Above, the Pyramid
of the Sun (63
metres), the world's
third tallest pyramid
Mh
38* -^
Above, one of the 366
carved heads of
Quetzalcóatl, the
Plumed Serpent, that
stud the pyramid
dedicated to this
divinity associated
with moisture and
fertility.
Left, high-relief heads
of the rain god Tlaloc
(left) and
Quetzalcóatl the
Plumed Serpent
(right) on the
Pyramid of
Quetzalcóatl.
86 iÇowTHE UNESCO lOURIER« JULY AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="87">
<![CDATA[
Excavation and restoration
The first excavations began in 1884. In 1905-1910, some monuments were restored, e.g. the Pyra¬
mid of the Sun to which the architect, Leopoldo Batres, arbitrarily added a fifth level. The
"citadel" was discovered and restored in 1917-1920.
Since 1962, archaeological research has been co-ordinated by Mexico's Instituto National de
Antropología e Historia (INAH). More systematic exploration of the site led to the discovery of
the Palace of the Quetzal Bird-Butterfly and other edifices. In the early 1970s, a natural cave orga-
nizedinto rooms joined by tunnels was discovered beneath the Pyramid of theSun.This was a cer¬
emonial setting, but the symbolic function of the edifice, which played a central role in the reli¬
gion ofTeotihuacán, is still unknown. Perhaps it symbolized the mythical centre of creation.
In 1980 Mexico began a far-reaching excavation and consolidation campaign, the Teotihuacán
Archaeological Project, in which 600 people worked for two years under the direction of Ruben
Cabrera of the Mexican National Institute of History and Anthropology. The project, concentrated
mainly on the south of the Avenue of the Dead, revealed vestiges of later strata than theTeoti-
huacán civilization.
Excavations confined to the Pyramid of the Plumed Serpent (1917, 1925, 1939 and 1982) led
to the discovery of tombs containing skeletons and offerings-obsidian objects, figurines in hard
stone and sculpted shells. In 1988-1989 the QuetzalcóatlTemple project, a joint ventureinvolv-
ing Mexican and American archaeologists, explored previously unstudied parts of the citadel. Then
in 1994-1995 strata subsequent to the Teotihuacán period were removed during a new Mexican
campaign. About 200 tombs were discovered in the pyramid itself, at its exact centre, in graves
under the floor and at the corners.
In 1973 René Millón of the University of Rochester (United States) began mapping the
entire site as part of the Teotihuacán Mapping Project. In his opinion the Pyramid of the Moon
may contain an inner structure, but the monument has not yet been decoded. C R.
Alternating slopes and vertical panels are typical features of
Teotihuacán's monuments. Above, the Pyramid of the Sun.
Below, a ceramic statuette with an open niche in its chest
containing a small idol in place of a heart (c. 500 A.D.).
d(7iuTHE UNESCO COURIER JULY AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="88">
<![CDATA[
Adult education for tomorrow
by Christopher Mcintosh
UNESCO IN ACTION
Laid-back language
learning in Hamburg
(Germany)
Samia Wadie Hannah
began her working life at
the age of five helping her father
collect garbage in the streets of
Cairo. She never went to school
and remained unable to read until
she enrolled in an adult literacy
class run by the priest of her local
Coptic church. Later she gained a
¡primary school diploma by corre¬
spondence. She now works as a
supervisor for an environmental
association in Cairo.
A few years ago an immigrant
from a Pacific rim nation came to
Houston, Texas with almost no
English and little understanding
of American culture. He enrolled
at San Jacinto College, a two-year
community college where he
learned the basics of English and
acquired an understanding of life
in the United States. He went on to
take a series of degrees, culminat¬
ing in a Ph 1) from the Massachu¬
setts Institute of Technology. He is
now a successful scientist.
Kerstin Ilerz-Ilabbert grew
up in Montabaur, Germany, where
her father was a heating
mechanic. After leaving school she
did an internship with a newspa¬
per hoping to become a journal¬
ist. Failing to find a journalistic
job, she trained as an office assis¬
tant in a ¡public relations firm,
where she was very unhappy. At
the age of twenty-three she
decided to go to university. Sup¬
ported by her ¡parents, various
grants and a ¡part-time job in the
Post Office, she completed six
years at the Universities of Hei¬
delberg and Hamburg and
emerged with an MA in German
literature, sociology and ¡peda¬
gogy. She now ¡plans to study for a
doctorate in literature.
These three people experi¬
enced a ¡profound change in their
lives because of the educational
opportunities offered to them as
adults. Millions of people all over
the world are at this moment
engaged in some form of educa¬
tion, but millions more are denied
that opportunity. Huge reserves
of human potential remain locked
away, unrealized. A new global
effort is needed if this potential is
to be released.
Against this backdrop, over
1,500 delegates from all over the
world are gathering for UlSESCO's
Fifth International Conference on
Adult Education (COFINTEA),
which is being held from 14 to 18
July in Hamburg, Germany (see
box). The conference will address
a wide range of adult education
issues, including the following.
WORK AND EMPLOYMENT
The world of work is changing
rapidly and dramatically. Tech¬
nology is developing at e\ er-inercas-
ing speed, industry is continually
seeking greater efficiency, global
competition is intensifying, and
secure jobs are becoming a rarity.
The British sociologist Charles
Handy believes that in a few years
time (inns in some industrialized
countries will be cutting their work
force by half, ¡paying staff twice
as much and obtaining three times
the ¡productivity. Wholesale clo-
88
THE UNESCO ^)URUERB |UL¥ AUGUST 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="89">
<![CDATA[
worldwide commitment to lifelong learning is needed to release huge
reserves of unrealized human potential
"There is a real
danger that the
Internet will be an
instrument for
transferring the
values, languages
and cultural norms
of the industrialized
North." Left, a
cybercafé in
Bangalore (India).
An adult literacy
class in Mauritania.
suits of departments and factories to develop their competence
will continue, and more and more throughout their lives,
work will be contracted out to It is in this context thai con-
small, specialized companies. All ' tinning education and training
of this will demand new solidarity ¡programmes are becoming so
as well as sound and flexible ¡poli- important at the work ¡dace. In
cics, so that adults can continue 1990 the Hover group in Britain
The Fifth International Conference
on Adult Education
"Adult learning: a key for the 21st century" is the motto of Unesco's Fifth
International Conference on Adult Education (COFINTEA), which is taking place
from 14 to 18 July in Hamburg (Germany). The Conference, organized by Unesco
with a number of international partners, is continuing the work of four earlier
Unesco adult education conferences: Elsinore (Denmark, 1949), Montreal (Canada,
1960), Tokyo (Japan, 1972) and Paris (France, 1985).
A major part of the discussions at Hamburg will focus on the theme of
democracy, i.e. making access to education more democratic and promoting
democracy through education. This theme links with that of promoting a culture
of peace and mutual understanding-something that is more necessary than ever
in a world where nationalities and linguistic and ethnic communities are
increasinglyinterpenetrating one another.
The most immediate outcome of the Conference will be two documents: a
Declaration on Adult Learning, in the form of a broad policy manifesto; and an
Agenda for the Future, containing a series of more detailed proposals.
Field technicians of
the Food and
Agriculture
Organization of the
United Nations (FAO)
hold an educational
workshop for farmers
in Cochabamba
(Bolivia).
launched a massive educational
¡programme costing £3!) million
¡pounds a year, offering employ¬
ees not only job-related training
but also grants to study whatever
subject they wished, from poetry
to guitar-playing. The outcome
was that annual revenue per
employee went up from £31,000
in 1989 to £122,000 in 1994
the result of a more motivated,
flexible and creative work force.
LITERACY
Approximately one billion adults
worldwide are unable to read and
write. A recent survey revealed
that even some of the world's rich¬
est nations have a high ¡percentage
of adidts whose literacy is below
the level of a ¡primary school leaver:
approximately 20 per cent in the
United Slates, 16 ¡per cent in
Canada, 15 per cent in Germany
and 10 per cent in the Nether¬
lands. This means that many adults
in these countries arc unable to fill
out correctly an application form
89
THE UNESCO (our ERB |ULY AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="90">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO IN ACTION
for a job, understand a simple bar
chart or read a bus timetable, let
alone compete in an increasingly
difficult labour market.
In the developing world the
problem is even more acute. One
developing country that has taken
this message to heart is India,
which is spending a massive 8 per
cent of its education budget on
adult literacy, reaching 50 mil¬
lion people every ) ear.
THE ENVIRONMENT,
MINORITIES AND GROUPS
WITH SPECIAL NEEDS
The ¡protection of the environment
demands the active ¡participation
of informed and empowered citi¬
zens world-wide. This in turn calls
for raising people's awareness and
knowledge whether about solar
energy, recycling or rain forest
protection. Yet in spite of a num¬
ber of inspiring exceptions, envi¬
ronmental education has remained
until now a regrettably marginal
field. In Germany, for example,
only 1.5 ¡>er cent of adult educa¬
tion courses deal with this theme.
Right, a poster
issued by the Federal
Ministry of
Education, Lagos
(Nigeria) as part of a
literacy campaign.
"Reading means
pleasure and
culture", reads the
slogan on a poster
issued by the
Egyptian Ministry of
Education (below).
;#L2fl
Many groups and communities
receive much less than their fair
share of educational opportuni¬
ties. This applies to women all over
the world. Another category con¬
sists of the estimated 70 million
migrants in the world today who
have been forced to leave their
homeland because of war, perse¬
cution or hardship. Migrant youth
are often excluded from regular
schools in their host countries and
grow up into under-educated and
therefore marginalized adults.
Another group with special
educational needs consists of the
millions of people in ¡prisons and
other correctional institutions all
over the world. Hetween 25 per
cent and 40 per cent of these have
I
A NATION
difficulty with reading, writing
and basic numeracy, and most
hav e no higher vocational or other
advanced education.
DEMOCRACY AND
A CULTURE OF PEACE
"in a community of many cultures
the interchange between them is
very important," says Justin Ellis,
Under Secretary for Adult Educa¬
tion, Libraries and Culture in
Namibia. "Often it is easier to do
this in non-verbal ways, such as
through music, dancing, theatre and
crafts. In our programmes we try to
combine education and culture."
At the same time it is neces¬
sary to question the nature and pur¬
pose of education itself. This
90
THE UNESCO ^)URIEH I |ULY AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="91">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
includes ha\ ing res¡iect for cultural
and linguistic rights instead ofusing
education to impose dominant cul¬
tures and languages on those who
come from a different background.
MEDIA AND TECHNOLOGIES
FOR EDUCATION
Radio and television have long
been used in distance learning.
Now videos, interactive compact
discs and the Internet are ¡proving
to be immensely valuable educa¬
tional tools. The Internet has also
opened up vast ¡possibilities for
education, and its potential has
only just begun to be exploited.
With an Internet link it should
eventually be possible for some¬
one to take anything from a liter¬
acy course to a study programme
in advanced engineering. Already
there are courses where students
link up via the Net to hold regular
"virtual reality seminars" and to
carry out joint study projects.
However, there are serious
drawbacks to the Internet. For
vast areas of the developing world
access to it is either non-existent
or limited, and where it exists it is
often too costly for most citizens.
On the other hand, if the Inter¬
net becomes more widely used,
there is a real danger that it will
be an instrument for transferring
the values, languages and cultural
norms of the industrialized North.
Even with a full connection, it is
difficult to use the Net system¬
atically for educational purposes.
Those who attempt to do so are
often overwhelmed by the sheer
chaotic multiplicity of informa¬
tion that surges back and forth
over the information highway.
In the twenty-first century the
¡public must learn to become
active, critical and discriminating
users of the media. In ibis way
they will resist ¡political and com¬
mercial manipulation and be able
to use the media intelligently for
educational purposes. M
Diplomats
and
merchants
used the
written word
to overcome
the language
barrier in
central Asia
long ago
Letters from Asia
l)v Denis Sinor
To communicate by means of
the written word, two con¬
ditions have to be fulfilled:
the sender and the recipient of the
communication must be familiar
with the same language and the same
script. In early and medieval Inner
Asia circumstances did not favour
the simultaneous existence of both
conditions.
In the past, there were far more
languages than there arc today. This is
a worldwide phenomenon, the rea¬
son for which lies in a steady increase
in populations which brings closer to
one another peoples once separated
by great distances. In the process, the
languages of the smaller peoples tend
to disappear; their speakers are
absorbed by a majority population
using another tongue. There is rea¬
son to believe that in Eurasia alone in
historical times hundreds of lan¬
guages disappeared, many of them
without leaving any written trace.
Others have survived in documents
now extremely difficult to decipher.
At the beginning of this century in
the relatively small area of what is
today the Chinese province of Xin¬
jiang, texts written in seventeen dif¬
ferent languages were discovered.
Most of these ceased to be used many
centuries ago.
Yet in the past, though less than
today, people of differing languages
had to communicate, and the only
way to do this was, for some of
them at least, to have command of
more than one language. While it
has always been possible for indi¬
viduals to acquire several languages
through learning, in earlier epochs
multilingualism was usually a by¬
product of a child's family circum¬
stances. In Inner Asia and elsewhere
such individuals often came to serve
as interpreters or translators.
The function of interpreters is
aural and oral: what they hear in one
language, they transpose into
another. The function of transla¬
tors is similar, but they use visual
and manual means. They read a text
in one language and write it down in
another. The need to communicate
by vision as opposed to audi¬
tion requires the simultaneous
command of more than one lan¬
guage and, in many cases, more than
one script. It was on competence in
such skills that cross-cultural com¬
munications depended.
WRITING FOR A MULTILINGUAL
READERSHIP
Few people were literate in the
period and in the lands with which
wc are concerned, hence correspon¬
dence between them must have been
sporadic and, as might be expected,
very few specimens of writing have
survived.
It often happened that several
scripts were used within one lin¬
guistic community. Old Turkic,
Uighur texts have survived in a num¬
ber of scripts and it is by no means
certain that even literate speakers
within that same group could read all
of them. Further complications arose
when people using different lan¬
guages and different scripts wished
to communicate with each other.
It may happen that one sender
wishes to communicate with a
number of recipients. Before the
invention of printing, texts destined
for a wider public were often
engraved in stelae or on mountain¬
sides, to be seen and read by all. In
Inner Asia such inscriptions were
very often multilingual. The inscrip¬
tion of Karabalgasun in present-day
Mongolia provides a good example.
Made in the middle of the eighth
century A.D. to glorify the deeds
of an Uighur ruler, it uses three
scripts and three languages. The
Uighur text (an Old-Turkic dialect)
was engraved in an original runiform
script; the Sogdian version used the
THE UNESCO y^OURIERB |ULY AUGUST 1907
91
]]>
</page>
<page number="92">
<![CDATA[
E FLECTI O
Letter from the Mongol Khan
Giiyiikto King Bêla IV of Hungary
"I, the Khan, envoy of the Heavenly King who gave me power over
the world to exalt those who submit themselves and to subdue
the adversaries, I wonder at you, king of Hungary, that, when I had
already sent three times ambassadors to you; why did you not
send back to me any of them. Nor did you send me your
ambassadors or letters. I know that you are a rich and powerful
king, that you have many soldiers under your command and that
you rule alone a big kingdom. Therefore it may be difficult to
submit yourself to me. However, it would be better for you to
submit yourself spontaneously to me. I understand moreover that
you keep under your protection the Cumans, my servants. I thus
enjoin you not to keep them with you, and for their sake have me
as an enemy; because it is easier for them to escape than for you.
For they, without homes and on continuous move may perhaps
evade, but you, who live in houses and have forts and cities, how
shall you escape from my hands?"
Sogdian script developed from Ara¬
maic; and Chinese characters were
used for the Chinese version. Texts
written in six languages (Sanskrit,
Tibetan, Mongol, Chinese, Uighur
and Tangut) and six scripts were used
in the Buddhist inscription of 1345
at the Chii-yung gate near Beijing.
There arc good reasons why
most of the still extant letters of
Inner Asian origin were written by
rulers to rulers. Though illiterate
themselves, they had at their dis¬
posal scribes who could write on
their behalf, and their writings had
a fair chance of being preserved in
the archives of the recipient.
The first problem that must have
beset the recipient of any diplomatic
letter must have been caused by the
script in which it had been written.
Thus the credentials presented to the
Emperor Justin II by the Turkish
ambassador Maniakh, who reached
Byzantium in 568, were said to have
been written in the "Scythian script"
(a general Greek term used to desig¬
nate peoples of the steppe). Unfor¬
tunately, we have no further infor¬
mation on this script.
On occasion there must have
been difficulties in finding a trans¬
lator. Such was the case in 1 267 when
Pope Clement IV could find no one
to translate the Mongol letter sent
to him by the il-khan Abagha, the
Mongol ruler of Iran. It appears
from the Pope's letter to Abagha
that previous correspondence had
been conducted in Latin, a reference
which would suggest that Euro¬
peans, perhaps missionaries, were
active in the il-khan's chancery.
THETORTUOUSWAYSOF
TRANSLATION
In the first half of the thirteenth
century the Mongol empire
expanded well into eastern Europe
and it became necessary for those
concerned to establish some rela¬
tions with each other, to exchange
some letters. The finest pieces of
medieval diplomatic correspondence
emanating from Inner Asia are the
letters scntby the Mongol rulers
to the Pope and to various western
princes.
The earliest known example of
such a correspondence is embedded in
a Latin report written by a Domini¬
can Friar called Julian in which he
described the information he had
gathered in eastern Europe about the
Mongols. The letter, addressed to
King Bêla IV of Hungary, had been
written by a Mongol ruler, proba¬
bly the Great Khan Güyük, some
time before Julian's return to Hun¬
gary in December 1237.
Only the Latin translation of
the letter has survived. According
to Julian: "The letter was written
in pagan characters but in the Tartar
[i.e. Mongol] tongue, so that the
king [of Hungary] found many
who could decipher it but none
who could understand it. But we, as
we crossed pagan Cumania, found
someone who interpreted it for us."
Of course the Hungarians them¬
selves used the Latin script, but they
had recently offered asylum to the
Cumans who spoke a Turkic lan-
The Gobi Desert
(Mongolia).
92
THE UNESCO IpURIEHB |ULY AUGUST 1097
]]>
</page>
<page number="93">
<![CDATA[
Six languages
(Sanskrit, Tibetan,
Mongolian, Chinese,
Uighur and Tangut)
were used in this
Buddhist inscription
carved in 1345 at the
Chii yunggate near
Beijing.
guagc, and it has been surmised that
among them were people who rec¬
ognized the script: probably that of
the Turkic-speaking Uighurs. But
being able to read a script is in itself
not enough to understand its con¬
tent; for this purpose an individual
who was literate as well as knowing
Mongolian had to be found. The let¬
ter (see box on opposite page) reads
something like an ultimatum.
The laborious process of mul¬
tiple translations is well illustrated
in observations by the Franciscan
Friar John of Piano Carpini, who
was sent as an emissary to the Mon¬
gols by Pope Innocent IV in 1245.
When the Great Khan Güyük was
about to send a letter to the Pope,
Piano Carpini was asked whether
there were any people in the Pope's
entourage who could read Russian,
Persian or Mongol. The Friar sug¬
gested that the best plan would be
for the Mongols to write in Mon
gol and to have the text translated,
there and then, word for word, into
Latin. The accuracy of this Latin
translation was then carefully
checked and the letter was taken to
Rome, where, in the course of time,
it was lost. Fortunately, a copy of
the text is incorporated in the
chronicle of Carpini's contempo¬
rary, the monk Salimbcnc. The
notaries and scribes working in the
Great Khan's court thought it wise,
for variety's sake, to prepare a Per¬
sian translation of the Mongol text.
It was discovered in 1920 in the
papal archives, and provides us with
a splendid example of the multilin¬
gual nature of the Mongol chancery.
The letter has a preamble, writ¬
ten in Uighur, clearly the adminis¬
trative language if not of the Mon¬
gol court, at least of the Uighur
scribes who manned it. This pre¬
amble was probably the standard
formula with which letters by the
Great Khans began. It reads: "By
the strength of Eternal Heaven,
powerful ruler of the great coun¬
try and of the sea: our command¬
ment." The preamble is followed
by a red seal written in Mongol (in
Uighur script) with a similarly
worded injunction.
Guy iik's letter was meant as an
answer to one written by Pope
Innocent IV and transmitted by
Carpini himself. It constitutes an
ultimatum to the Pope and other
princes of the West who arc
enjoined to appear in person in the
Mongol court, to pay homage to
the Great Khan and to listen to his
orders. Were they to disobey these
orders, the Great Khan would view
them as enemies. Güyük also cate¬
gorically rejects the Pope's repri¬
mands for Mongol atrocities com¬
mitted in Hungary and elsewhere.
Such acts, writes the Khan, were
committed in retaliation against
rTHE UNESCO lOURIER |ULV AUGUST 1007 *
]]>
</page>
<page number="94">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
A nomad
encampment.
Miniature by the
15th-century Tu rco-
Mongolian artist
Siyah Kalem.
these people for their arrogance and
because they had murdered Mon¬
gol ambassadors. He explains and
defends his past actions with the
following reasoning. "From where
the sun rises to where it goes down,
all the lands belong to us. Were it
not for the will of God, how could
that have happened?"
In stark contrast with the tone
and content of this letter is that writ¬
ten in Mongol and sent in 1305 by
the Mongol il-khan of Persia Olj eitü
to Philip IV the Fair, king of France.
By that time old feuds were forgot¬
ten, and the hope of an alliance
against the Egyptian Mameluks
seemed desirable to both parties. The
letter had two aims: to inform the
king of France that the fratricidal
struggle between the descendants of
Chinggis khan had been satisfacto¬
rily settled and that the il-khan was
ready to follow the friendly poli¬
cies towards France initiated by his
ancestors.
The likelihood of anyone's
being able to read a Mongol letter in
the French court was dim indeed,
and Oljeitü acted wisely by choos¬
ing as one of the bearers of his mes¬
sage a man who probably spoke
Mongol as well as French. This was
the Italian Thomas Ugi of Siena and
it may be assumed that it was he
who, on the back of the letter,
penned an Italian paraphrase of its
content. (See box this page.)
Letter from Oljeitii, Mongol il-Khan of Persia,
to Philip the Fair of France
"Our words. The ruler Oljeitii.
"To the ruler of France.
"How could it have escaped your attention that since ancient times the kings of France
had friendly relations with our good great-grandfather, our good grandfather, our good
father and our good elder brother? Although far away, you considered them near by and you
sent them messages whether or not favourable, and you exchanged ambassadors and gifts
of good will. At present when, by the grace of Heaven, I have occupied the great throne of
the il-khans, I would not act contrary to the precepts and rules established by my good
ancestors, norwould I depart from what had been agreed between you and them.
Considering it sacred, I would not abandon what had been agreed upon. More than ever, it
is myintention to be finked with you in friendship and to exchange ambassadors with you.
"As a result of calumnious utterances made by evil people we, elder and younger
brothers, allowed our mutual affection to wane. But now, all of us, descendants of
Chinggis khan, who for forty-five years had remonstrated against each other, have now '
reached an agreement. From the country of the Chinese where the sun rises, to the other
end of the world, our nations are linked by postal stations. We agreed that we would act
jointly against our enemies.
"We thought: how could we abandon the good relations that had existed between
our good forebears and you? So we sent to you ourtwo ambassadors, Mamalagh and
Thomas.
"It has come to our knowledge that you, kings of the West, also live in peace.
Verily, what is better than concord? As for those who would be hostile to either us or you,
with the help of Heaven, we would act jointly against them.
"We wrote this letter in the year 704 of the Snake (=1305 A.D.) in the first month
of the summer, at the city of Aliwan."
LONG-DISTANCE MAIL
Among the very few private letters
that have been preserved, pride of
place is taken by the so-called
"Ancient Letters" written in Sog-
dian, an east Iranian language no
longer in use. These writings were
discovered in 1907 by the explorer
Sir Aurel Stein in a ruined watch-
tower located between Lou-Ian and
Tun-huang on the trade route from
the West to China. These letters,
commercial writings penned by
Sogdian merchants to their princi¬
pals, were probably lost or aban¬
doned while being carried from cast
to west. Their exact date cannot be
established but it seems certain that
they were written not later than the
early fourth century A.D.
One of them is particularly inter¬
esting, and because of its historical
references and its moving, one might
say, tragic content, it stands alone in
the corpus of medieval Inner Asian
letters. Written by a certain Nanai-
vandak, a Sogdian merchant living at
the eastern end of the great trade
route, it was addressed to his princi¬
pal in Samarkand, some 3,200 kilo¬
metres away.
"Sir," writes Nanai-vandak, "if I
wrote you all the details of how
China fared, it would be a story of
debts and woe	 And, Sir, the last
emperor [of China] so they say
fled from Saragh [his capital city]
because of the famine. And his for¬
tified residence and fortified town
were set on fire. The residence burnt
down and the town was destroyed.
So Saragh is no more!"
]]>
</page>
<page number="95">
<![CDATA[
interview Mstislav Rostropovich
To celebrate his seventieth
birthday, in May 1997
Mstislav Rostropovich, the
great Russian cellist and
conductor, invited his
musician friends from all
overthe world to join him
atthe Rencontres
Musicales (Musical
Encounters) at Evian in
France. Among those who
attended were the St.
Petersburg Symphony
Orchestra, Isaac Stern,
Jean-Pierre Rampai, Itzhak
Perlman, the Orchestra of
the Nations and the Ballet
of Lithuania. Isabelle
Leymarie interviewed
Rostropovich during the
celebrations.
Are your exuberance, your enthusiasm and your
generosity innate or have you developed them over
the years?
Mstislav Rostropovich: Innate. I was born happy!
H How did your love for the cello originate?
M. R.: Little by little. At the age of four I began
to learn to play the piano, then three years later
my father said to me: "You are going to play the
cello." My father was a cellist himself so he prob¬
ably wanted me to perpetuate the tradition, lie
realized that 1 was very gifted musically. I was
already composing at the age of four.
Do you still compose?
M.R.:No.
Is it difficult to play both the cello and the
piano?
M. R.: I don't play the piano any more. My wife
won't let inc.
Why?
M. R.: I accompanied her on the piano for thirty-
five years. When she stopped singing, other
famous singers asked me to accompany them,
liut my wife put her foot down. "You're already
lucky that I allow you to conduct orchestras!"
Russian women are very forceful!
M. R.: Oh yes, very powerful. Very powerful. [Sal¬
vador] Dali's wife Gala, a Russian, had a very
forceful character just like my wife in fact.
They were friends and got along very well. I
remember one day my Calina said to Gala: "That
blessed moustache oí your husband's! Why don't
you cut it off while he's asleep':" Gala replied:
"Because he'd drop dead when he woke up and
saw it gone!"
Do you enjoy conducting an orchestra as much as
playing?
M. R.: Yes, the happiness and joy are just as
intense. Perhaps even more extraordinary
because the music 1 conduct is better than what
I play myself.
THt UNESCO lOURIER» JULY-AUGUST 1907
95
]]>
</page>
<page number="96">
<![CDATA[
7 regard my interpretation of a work as a
kind of improvisation. I put myself in the
composer's place.9
And yet you do not have the same physical,
sensual contact with an instrument.
M. R.: That's true, but when I conduct sym¬
phonies by Beethoven, Mahler or Shostakovich,
I'm in heaven.
Do an ear for music and musical tastes become
more refined over the years?
M. R.: Yes. Musical tastes develop, but gradually
and imperceptibly. I recently heard a recording
of the Dvorak concerto that I made as a young
man. Today I don't like it.
H How do you approach a new musical work?
M. R.: First (pf all by reading through the score
without an instrument. I bear all the music in
my head, the phrasing, the nuances, all the
details. Of course, when I pick up my cello,
changes may occur, but 1 always have a clear
idea in my head of what I'm going to do.
Improvisation has practically disappeared from
the classical repertory. Do you miss creating your
own music?
M. R.: Don't forget that interpretation to some
extent invol\ es improvisation.
And yet when Chopin or Liszt sat down at the
piano they created impromptu music at the drop of a
hat.
M. R.: Hut they were composers of genius! In their
day there were also pianists who were incapable
of improvising even on two notes. 1 regard my
interpretation of a work as a kind of improvisa¬
tion. It's as though I myself were composing it.
I put myself in the composer's place.
So we're talking about a re-creation.
M.R.: Exactly.
What qualities are needed to play well?
M. R.: First of all a tremendous love of music.
This is the only thing that can overcome the pre¬
concert emotional stress, the nerves, the stage
fright. If you don't love music, you feel naked on
the stage and just want to run away.
Despite your love of music, have you ever
suffered from stage fright?
M. R.: Yes, at a recital given by my wife in New
THE UNESCO t^UR'ERB JUL Y-AUGUST 1997
7 can only
V
by m\ love
York. I sat down at the piano without having
been able to practise beforehand. I was terribly
uncomfortable. Sitting there at the keyboard I
thought: "There are lots of critics out there in
the audience, waiting to pounce like a pack of
wolves. They'd just love to chew me up and spit
me out." I made mistakes right from the start
and played the first two love songs terribly badly.
Then I thought: "What the heck! I've already
made some terrible mistakes, they can tear me to
pieces if they want to, so now I might as well
play for my own pleasure." Then I started to
play really well.
In any case, you don't make musicforthe critics,
many of whom aren't musicians anyway! You play for
the love of it, because it responds to an inner need.
M. R.: That was the problem; I had been dis¬
tracted. If you think of something else instead of
concentrating fully on the music, you won't play
well. That's what I was driving at. I forgot the
[pleasure I should have been feeling while I was
playing and my performance; was affected. I can
only ] ) I a y well if I am totally possessed by my
love (pf the music.
At the concert yesterday evening, when you were
playing Brahms's Quartet for Piano and Strings opus
25 with Isaac Stern, Eugène Istomin and Yuri
Bashmet, I was struck by your concentration. While
your partners often exchanged glances or signalled
discreetly to each other, you were completely
absorbed by your cello and your score, although you
heard everything.
M. R.: Yes, my ears were particularly sharp yes¬
terday.
Ifelt thatyouwere putting all yoursoulinto the
beauty of the sound and that your relationship with
yourinstrument was one of love.
M. R.: Ah! Love, love, tra la la la! (Rostropovich
starts singing).
Afewyearsago,you played Bach's suites for
unaccompanied cello in the church of La Madeleine
at Vézelay in France. How did you come to do that?
M. R.: By chance. I had always thought that if I
were to record Bach, it would have to be in a
beautiful church. Not because it's religious
music: for me the important thing was to play
play well if I am totally possessed
of the music'
]]>
</page>
<page number="97">
<![CDATA[
'When the orchestra plays the last chord,
I slowly go down to Romeo and Juliet and
join their hands.9
Bach in an enijpty room and in a place that would
encourage concentration and spirituality. A lot
goes (Pii in an empty church. Subconsciously, 1
was looking for a church that would meet my
criteria, and until then I hadn't found one. Then
I visited the restaurant of a noted chef, Marc
Meneau, in Vézelay. My wife and I had a feast.
We wen; due to leave on the Monday morning,
but Marc said to me: "You mustn't leave the
area until you've seen this church I want to show
you." 1 told him that I was in a hurry, that I
didn't have a minute to spare. He insisted that 1
should see it that very day. When I entered the
church of La Madeleine; I crossed myself from the
sheer joy of discovering it. And I began prepar¬
ing to record there.
Romanesque churches are magical. They are
round, Like Bach's music.
M. R.: Yes, and what's more, the columns in this
church are rhythmical.
You are going to close these Musical Encounters
in Evian by playing Prokofiev's Romeo and Juliet
with the Ballet of Lithuania and the Orchestra of the
Nations, which you will also conduct. What made you
choose this work?
M. R.: When I was a student at the Moscow Con¬
servatory, I attended all the performances of
Romeo and Juliet at the Bolshoi. I knew how to
play all the music on the piano, from beginning
to end. It's wonderful music, an absolutely fan¬
tastic ballet. I have dreamt of conducting it for
years. But to do that I needed special choreog¬
raphy. 1 didn't want the dancers dictating the
tempo to me with their feet. 1 wanted there to be
a real give-and-take and I also wanted to set the
rhythm. So Vladimir Wassiliev, who started at
the Bolshoi, produced a new choreography spe¬
cially forme.
It's exciting because; the; sccnography is
highly inventive: the orchestra is eni stage, ne>t in
the pit, anel se> the; music itself is the; heart of all
the action. The; orchestra is placed se> that I can
conduct it while facing the audience. In front
of the orchestra is a stage; epn which all the street
activities go em. Above the orchestra is a kind epf
bridge em which Juliet's bedroom is placed, anel
e»n which all the inside scenes are; set. It's an
excellent idea.
In Wassiliev's latest ¡production it's impossi¬
ble to restrain one's tears. When Juliet is elying,
she bedels e>ut her hands tet Bepmeo, who is already
dead, without being able te) touch hi in. When the
orchestra j)lays the last chord, I slowly go elown
to them and join their hands. It's wonderful!
Wonderful! When I conduct the; scene with Friar
Laurence, when the twep young lovers ge) te) the
church, the music is in four-lour time. And se) I
make; the; arm movement lor 4/4 time, from left
to right anel from up te> down, identical to the; sign
e>f the cross. Romeo anel Juliet come to me as if
I were a priest, and I appear te> be; blessing them.
So you become Rostro-pope-vich!
M. R.: The; pre>eluctie>n is full of original ideas and
the score is admirable.
In spite of your cosmopolitan existence, do you
have a special affection for Russian music?
M. R.: Yes, of course. Above all for Shostakovich
because he was my great friend. I j)lay his music
with intense feeling.
Is the musical scene in Russia still as lively as
ever?
M. R.: Yes, very much se). Thine are many young
composers. There are; oidor e>ne;s too, who are;
still relatively unknown, which is a pity because
they are; great musicians.
Do you intend to record their works?
M. R.: Yes, I've been thinking about it for a long
time. For example, there; is a woman named Sofia
lîidiaïdulina, who is composing a j)ie;e;e fe>r me.
She lives in Germany at present and she; is mak¬
ing a name for herself in the; West. In Paris, Raelio
France elevoteel a major festival te> her. Galina
Utsvolskaya, another woman composer, lives in
Russia. She is immensely talented. She has a
considerable reputation, especially in the
Netherlands. The; Dutch are; wilel about her.
You are a citizen of the world and travel without
a passport. Howwonderfulit must be to do away
with frontiers like that! But where do you live most
of the time?
M. R.: In planes.
Apartfrom music and your family, what are your
other passions?
M. R.: J seek beauty everywhere and in every¬
thing. The beauty of nature, like Lake Geneva
elown there beneath us. Magnificent! The beauty
of women, magnificent! The; beauty of music,
magnificent! I
THE UNESCO QuR ERI JULY AUGUST 1997
97
]]>
</page>
<page number="98">
<![CDATA[
AUTHORS
AK1K0 SUEY0SHI is a Japanese author of
children's books. Notable among her many
publications are Mama No Kiiroi Kozo ("Mama's
Little Yellow Elephant", 1987), which won the Noma
Prize for Children's Literature, and The King of the
Earth and Tide [mi).
EVANGELINE LEDI BARONGO, of Uganda, is a
senior librarian at the Kampala Children's Library.
JULIA PROSALKOVA, a Russian specialist In
children's literature, is a researcher at her
country's State Library. She has written many
articles and is currently preparing a history of
children's literature during the Soviet era.
ELKE LIEBS, of Germany, is professor of German
and Comparative Literature at the University of
Potsdam (Germany). She has published many
articles and books on topics in her field, including
(with Helga Kraft) Mutter, Töchter, Frauen
("Mothers, Daughters, Women", Verlag Metzler,
Stuttgart, 1993).
ALTEAU is the pen name of the Paris-based
cartoonist Alain Smarnto. For several years he has
worked with punk rock groups, in journalism for
young people and in children's publishing.
CHARLES DOXUAN is a playwright, scriptwriter
and student of ancient history. He is currently
preparing a multimedia biography of the French
baroque painter Jean Jouvenet.
PASCALE D'ERM is a French journalist.
YLLJET ALIÇKA, of Albania, is head of the Foreign
Affairs department in his country's Ministry for
Culture, Youth and Women.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American journalist
specializing in environmental questions.
CÉCILE ROMANE is a Franco-British writer whose
published works include a novel, La Népalaise
(Orban/Plon, Pans, 1987) and a story, Les
Téméraires (Flammarlon, Paris, 1993).
CHRISTOPHER MCINTOSH, of the United
Kingdom, is head of publications and information
at the Unesco Institute for Education in Hamburg
(Germany) and Executive Editor of the International
Review of Education.
DENIS SINOR, of the United States, is Professor
Emeritus of Uralic and Altaic Studies at Indiana
University (United States) and Vice-chairman of the
Unesco Commission for the preparation of a
History of the Civilizations of Central Asia. His
published works include Studies in Medieval Inner
Asia (London, Variorum, 1997).
ISABELLE LEYMARIE, a Franco-American
musicologist, is the author of Du Tango au reggae,
Musiques noires d'Amérique latine et des Caraïbes
("From Tango to Reggae, Black Music of Latin
America and the Caribbean", Flammarion, Pans,
1996) and Musiques Caraïbes ("Caribbean Music" ,
Actes Sud, Arles, 1996).
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
DIVERSITY AND COMPLEXITY
I am seventeen years old and have been a Courier
subscriber for a year. I like the articles very
muchespecially since they often coincide with
my own ideas. In a world full of cruelty and
hypocrisy, your magazine shows us that all is not
lost.
I know that this century's most important
themes are diversity and complexity. I feel great
respect for all the world's cultures, and I enjoy
discovering their best features. In this respect I
think I am very lucky since I live between two cul¬
tures: my parents were born in the Republic of
Korea and I was born in Argentina. I have assim¬
ilated my parents' culture and that of my coun¬
try. Your October 1996 issue ("Exiles") helped
me understand that there are ether people who
live and feel as I do. On this subject, as on so many
others, the Courier is a companion that is help¬
ing me to grow up.
Analia Kim
Buenos Aires (Argentina)
NEW PRIORITIES FOR PEACE
Your magazine contains much thought-provoking
reading, and I was particularly interested by Fed¬
erico Mayor's article in the November 1995 issue
("Peace, a new beginning").
Peace, which once depended on two empires,
seems to have become everyody's business since
the fall of communism in the former Soviet Union.
In order to preserve it, we may need to define a
new order of priorities and show new vigilance. In
short, prevention and not cure should be the order
of the day; we should cultivate the idea of peace
within us.
The idea of peace is on the agenda and is
making its way in people's minds. So much the
better. But what can be done to combat the indi¬
vidualism and egocentricity of Western societies?
What can be done to encourage a new spirit of
sharing and fulfil this promise of peace?
Laurence Balague
Maisons-Alfort (France)
A CALL
FOR DISARMAMENT
We have read a mass of documents produced by
Unesco and other United Nations bodies. These
studies and reports are the outcome of enormous
effort and put forward some magnificent ideas.
After discussing them in depth, however, we
started to have some doubts. All these fine words,
spoken and written, have had no effect. The same
problems are still with us, and new ones have
even been added.
We have reached the following conclusion:
While diplomats work to maintain or restore
peace, the arms industries are flourishing and
delivering weapons to those who will one day
ignite conflicts and massacre populations. The
danger is now ubiquitous because international
gangsters can get their hands on highly sophisti¬
cated and destructive weapons.
THERE ARE TOO MANY UNSCRUPULOUS,
COWARDLY AND GREEDY COUNTRIES. TO SALVE
THEIR CONSCIENCE, THEY ENGAGE IN ACTIVITIES
WITH CULTURAL AND HUMANITARIAN GOALS AND
CREATE ORGANIZATIONS TO ACHIEVE THESE
GOALS.
Nevertheless we still believe in the ideals
defended by Unesco. In order to make a modest
contribution to specific action to promote disar¬
mament and a thorough overhaul of our way of
life, we have written a six-page document ¡n which
we set forth our ideas and proposals in the
plainest possible terms. We offer it to anyone who
may be interested.
On behalf of the members,
Unesco Club of Slovenia,
Henrik Jereb
Piran (Slovenia)
NO PLACE FOR COLONIAL LANGUAGE
The May 1997 issue of the Unesco Courier, ("Land¬
scape with figures, the dialogue between people
and places") is beautifully illustrated, and I espe¬
cially enjoyed France Bequette's article, "Gar¬
dens of the Far East". But "Far East" in the title?
This reminds me of the old saw, "Far from where,
and East of what?" Colonial language has no place
in the atlas of the year 2000. 1 think that "East
Asia" is the proper term.
Jacques Richardson
Paris (France)
READERS TO THE RESCUE
The cover of the November 1996 issue ("The mar¬
ket place, past and present") shows a painting
entitled Market Scene in Mexico (1987). You
invited readers to try to decipher the signature
on the painting. It seems to me that what is writ¬
ten in the lower right-hand corner is "Nicolás de
Jesús 87". The name has a strong autochthonous
flavour, like the subject of the painting, which I
think is magnificent ¡n its composition, its light
and its movement.
I have been a devoted reader of the Courier
since 1976, and always find in it subjects for
thought and discussion. For me and my friends
and students, it is a source of information about
ways of life all over the world.
Carmen Cadenas Mecías
Isla de la Juventud (Cuba)
I believe that the name of the painter of Market
Scene in Mexico is clearly "Nicolás de Jesús".
I should like to take this opportunity to con¬
gratulate you on the excellent quality of your mag¬
azine.
Armando R. Cavallo Llanos
Havana (Cuba)
98
THE UNESCO ^URIER JULY-AUGUST 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="99">
<![CDATA[
THkUNESCO msè,*-
QpURIER -IVIKOn
announce an
international
photo competition
on the theme of
THE THEME:
The theme of the competition, inspired by
I the Preamble to Unesco's Constitution, is
peace in the down-to-earth context of
everyday life.
Peace in
everyday life
CONDITIONS
OF ENTRY:
The competition is open to professional
photographers in all parts of the world.
Contestants are requested to constitute a portfolio of up
to twenty black and white or colour prints of their work on
the theme "Peace in everyday life", and send it in with a
completed entry form. The portfolios must reach the
Unesco Courier offices by
THE JURY:
An international jury will meet
in Paris and choose the winning entry from
among 120 portfolios short-listed by a
preselection committee. Short-listing and
jury deliberations will take place at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris.
A "Unesco Courier- Nikon Prize
of
will be awarded to the winning entry,
Prize-winning photos will be publishe
in the Unesco Courier.
For further information, contact:
"Peace in everyday life" competition
Unesco Courier
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 PARIS CEDEX 15,France
Tel.: (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 69
Fax: (33) (0) 1 45 68 57 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="100">
<![CDATA[
IN THE NEXT ISSUE:
WORLD HERITAGE
REPORT
T
INTERVIEW WITH
YOUSSEFCHAHINE
ENVIRONMENT
NO-WASTE FARMING IN FIJI
]]>
</page>
</document>
