<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="109538eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^?r~
ENVIRONMENT: SEAWEED AT YOUR SERVICE
HERITAGE: IRONBRIDGE GORGE (UNITED KINGDOM)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTER s V
We invite readers to send us
photographs to be considered for
publication in this feature. Your
photo should show a painting, a
sculpture, piece of architecture
or any other subject which seems
to be an example of cultural
cross-fertilization.
Alternatively, you could send us
pictures of two works from
different cultural backgrounds in
which you see some striking
connection or resemblance.
Please add a short caption to all
photographs.
THE CHAIR
1994, acrylic on newspaper
(80x56 cm)
by Michel Molins
This chair belongs to the
oldest member of a pygmy
group whose life
the artist shared during a
month spent in Africa. It
symbolizes the gradual
sedentarization "directly or
indirectly" imposed on the
world's nomadic peoples.
The painter sees this
widespread sedentarization
as a form of intolerance
and a refusal by dominant
societies to accept
ways of life different from
their own.
© Michel Molins, Toulouse
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
THE UNESCO (OURIER
48
Lebanese-born writer
Andrée Chedid
talks about her commitment to freedom.
44
Ironbridge Gorge (United Kingdom)
by Neil Cossons
A symbolic site of18th-century
England's Industrial Revolution.
contents
NOVEMBER 1997
Month by month by Bahgat Elnadi and Adel Rifaat	5
Theatre for tomorrow	O
by Richard Schechner
Rules made to be broken 12
by Jean-Pierre Guingané
An art in search of its roots	16
by Romain Maitra
Shingeki's restless century 19
by Ohzasa Yoshio
A common home	23
byAnatoly Smeliansky
The birth of modern Arab theatre	28
by Ghassan Maleh
The theatre of the oppressed 32
by Augusto Boal
Fact file	36
Consultant: Romain Maitra
Commentary Federico Mayor 38
Cover:
Time Rocker, directed by American Bob Wilson.
Libretto by Darryl Pickney; music by Lou Reed.
© Armelle Paranihoen/Enguerand, Pans
GREENWATCH Seaweed at your service by France Bequette
AUTHORS
40
50
THE UNESCO ^)URIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TUfc. UNESCO
Courier
^*^ 50th YEAR
Published monthly in 30 languages and in Braille by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization.
31, rue François Bonvin, 75732 Paris CEDEX 15, France.
Fax (33) (0)1 45 68 57 45
e-mail: unesco couner@unesco org
Internet http //www unesco org
Director: Adel Rifaat
EDITORIAL STAFF (Paris)
Managing Editor Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin
French edition Alain Lévêque
Spanish edition: Araceli Ortiz de Urbina
Features: Jasmina Sopova
Art Unit/Production: Georges Servat
Illustrations Ariane Bailey (Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 90)
Documentation. José Banaag
(Tel (33) (0)1 45 68 46 85)
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions and press
Solange Beim (Tel. (33) (0) 1 45 68 46 87)
Film duplication: Daniel Meister
Secretariat Annie Brächet
(Tel. (33) (0)1 45 68 47 15),
Administrative Assistant Theresa Pinck
Selection in Braille in English, French, Spanish and
Korean- (Tel (33) (0)1 45.68.45.69)
NON-HEADQUARTERS EDITIONS
Russian: Irina Utkina (Moscow)
German Dominique Anderes (Berne)
Arabic: Fawzi Abdel Zaher (Cairo)
Italian. Gianluca Formichi (Rome)
Hindi: Ganga Prasad Vimal (Delhi)
Tamil M Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Persian: Akbar Zargar (Teheran)
Dutch Bart Christiaens (Antwerp)
Portuguese Alzira Alves de Abreu (Rio de Janeiro)
Urdu Mirza Muhammad Mushir (Islamabad)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malay: Sidin Ahmad Ishak (Kuala Lumpur)
Swahili Leonard J. Shuma (Dar-es-Salaam)
Slovene: Aleksandra Kornhauser (Ljubljana)
Chinese1 Feng Mingxia (Beijing)
Bulgarian Dragomir Petrov (Sofia)
Greek Sophie Costopoulos (Athens)
Sinhala: Neville Piyadigama (Colombo)
Finnish Rutta Saannen (Helsinki)
Basque: Juxto Egaña (Donostia)
Thai Duangtip Sunntatip (Bangkok)
Vietnamese" Ho Tien Nghi (Hanoi)
Pashto Nazer Mohammad Angar (Kabul)
Hausa Aliyu Muhammad Bunza (Sokoto)
Ukrainian. Volodymyr Vasiliuk (Kiev)
Galician Xabier Senín Fernández (Santiago de Compostela)
SALES AND PROMOTION.
Fax: (33) (0) 1.45 68 57.45
Subscriptions Marie-Thérèse Hardy
(Tel (33) (0) 1 45 68 45 65), Jacqueline Louise-Julie,
Manichan Ngonekeo, Mohamed Salah El Dm
(Tel. (33) (0)1.45 68 49 19)
Customer service Michel Ravassard,
(Tel. (33) (0) 1.45 68 45 91)
Accounts: (Tel (33) (0) 1 45.68 45 65)
Shipping, Daniel Meister (Tel (33) (0) 1.45 68.47.50)
SUBSCRIPTIONS.
Tel "(33) (0)1 45 68 45.65
lyear 211 French francs 2 years: 396 FF.
Students 1 year: 132 French francs
Binder for one year's issues 72 FF
Developing countries
1 year: 132 French francs 2 years 211 FF.
Payment can be made with any convertible currency to
the order of Unesco or by Visa, Eurocard or Mastercard
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted
providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor Signed
articles reprinted must bear author's name Non-copyright photos will
be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not nec¬
essarily represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of
the Unesco Courier Photo captions and headlines are written by the
Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microliche) by (1) Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Pans. (2) University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100
U S A . (3) N C R Microcard Edition. Indian Head Inc 111 West 40th
Street, New York U S A ; (4) Bell and Howell Co . Old Mansfeld Road.
Wooster, Ohio 44691. USA
IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
DEPOT LÉGAL' Cl - NOVEMBER 1997
COMMISSION PARITAIRE N° 71844 - DIFFUSÉ PAR LES
N M P P.
Photocomposition, photogravure
Le Courrier de I'Unesco
Impression: MAURY IMPRIMEUR,
Z.I Route d'Etampes, 45331 Malesherbes
ISSN 0041-5278 N° 11-1997-0PI-97-564 A
This issue comprises 52 pages and a 4-page insert
between pages 2-3 and 50-51
©Gëly/Bemand.Pans
iNESCO Courier November 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
r
month by month
;'.:¿'-'.V|,i tó^y^^íjj^Tí^Bjrtjjt«
' .'. *
' ' Î ¿* > 3 d^rp^^M
,v'\ » -''^.iÚSal
jfC^rffií^^RjfflE
'>* -r :\iAfïlr5»S
wl$il
SÄ» ''*¿*<Ä'.
' t ^iv*i^^^
. '.:' ', ;*s =#.-*^o|Ss
-". *.
?M
by Bahgát Ètnadi ah
¡ms.
The award of the Nobel Prize for Literature to the Italian playwright Dario Fo, a fewweeks ago,
was a reminder both that the theatre is a major art and that it is in good shape. In spite of
strong competition from the cinema and to an even greater extent from television, theatre
still attracts vast audiences the world over.
What makes the theatre irreplaceable is the direct physical link it establishes between
what happens onstage and the audience. This explains why each performance in the theatre is
unique. However many times a film or a video is shown its content never varies; a theatrical per¬
formance is never the same twice running. The emotions it arouses are stimulated by a myste¬
rious process of alchemy, which begins when the actors encounter an audience that is always dif¬
ferent, and which dies out when the curtain falls. Theatre is designed to serve this mystery, to
enable it to happen again and again.
This plasticity which is the touchstone of theatre may be one of the reasons why theatre has
survived for so many centuries and found a place in so many cultures; why it has adapted to all
periods and has sometimes foreshadowed them and even announced their birth.
Since the invention of classical theatre by the Greeks, great dramatists such as Shake¬
speare, Beaumarchais, Goethe and Ibsen have given wide currency to this concept of theatre in
the West. But what of theatre elsewhere? This issue looks at what happened in Japan and India,
in Africa and the Arab world, and to some extent in Latin America and Russia, after theatre
rooted in traditional society was confronted with "the shock of the new"modern European
theatre which has tended to focus on what might be called intimate tragedy rather than the des¬
tiny of communities, highlighting theindividual personality rather than the archetype. Farfrom
collapsing, however, theatre in these countries has taken on a new lease of life in the twenti¬
eth century.
It is almost as if theatre-lovers everywhere had spontaneously agreed that the new should
not be allowed to sign the death warrant of the oldin this case theatre itselfbut should
instead seek channels whereby traditionalinspiration could irriga te modern forms of expression,
whereby the theatre, by transforming itself, would continue to celebrate life.
The ninth International Festivalof ExperimentalTheatre, held in Cairo from 1 to 11 September
1997, showed brilliantly how attempts are being made on all continents to present many of the
great questions of the conte mporary world through the prism of theatre.
In other words, where there's life there's theatre.
. 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
In an age of spreading computer technology and cultural Intermingling,
the world's many forms of theatre have reached a crucial stage
Theatre for tomorrow BY RICHARD SCHECHNER
The Dragons' Trilogy,
directed by the Canadian
Robert Lepage, a leading
exponent of the "forward-
looking avant-garde".
"Where is the theatre going?" The ques¬
tion is often asked, but perhaps it
would be more accurate to ask it in the plural
rather than the singular, for it is clear that there
are many different kinds of theatre and that
they are not moving in lock-step.
There is the theatre of artists, modeled on
Western-style plays made mostly of words,
written by playwrights and acted for the most
part in a naturalistic style.
There is the theatre of highly codified ges¬
tures, costumes and make-up, combining the
spoken word with sung dialogue and songs,
such as Japanese Kabuki.
There is theatre that could also be called
dance or opera because of its total integration
of movement, gesture, song and narrative
such as Chinese jingju or Indian Kathakali.
There is the theatre of ritual performances
addressing, honouring or entertaining the
gods as practised in many cultures around
the world.
There is the theatre of popular festivity
and ritual where people build and wear masks
and full-body costumes, such as Yoruban
gelede, Hopi kachina, or Trinidadian carnival.
There is the theatre of religious narrative which
takes many days to enact, such as Indian
Ramlila, Yaqui Waebma, or the Passion play
performed once every ten years at Oberam-
mergau in Germany.
There is so-called "mainstream" theatre
Broadway, the West End and Boulevard Theatre
There is also avant-garde or experimental
theatre.
The life and death
ofthe avant-garde
Once upon a time avant-garde or experimen¬
tal theatre was "in advance of" what was fol¬
lowing. But it has been at least twenty-five
years since that was so. Avant-garde theatre is
no longer in advance of anything, and most of
the persons working in it do not risk failure
in order to explore new boundaries of per¬
formance knowledge or practice. In fact, there
are strong arguments for saying that all today's
theatre is "official", paid for by governments,
foundations, or other mainstream funds or
desiring to be paid for by them. Of course,
many works are still labeled "avant-garde",
but the term does not refer to a single style or
tendency, but to several.
The current avant-garde consists of what¬
ever or whoever critics, audiences and artists
identify as belonging to the avant-garde. Calling
THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
A Chorus Line, directed and
choreographed by Michael
Bennett with music by Marvin
Hamlisch. It was first
produced on Broadway in
1975.
a theatre artist "avant-garde" is sometimes more
a way of praising the artist than describing the
work.
V* The historical avant-garde. This is the
line of development which began with natu¬
ralism in Europe in the 1880s and extended
through many successive waves of experi¬
mentation: symbolism, futurism, Dada, sur¬
realism, Happenings, environmental theatre,
performance art, and so on. Each of these
claimed hegemony over all its predecessors;
each was destined to be absorbed into the
mainstream in one way or another. Works that
were hissed off the stage by one generation
were honoured by the next.
This historical avant-garde ended in the
1970s. No more waves of newness came crash¬
ing onto the shore. With the emergence of
postmodernism, recycling came to the fore.
The end of the historical avant-garde probably
coincided with a certain perception of the final¬
ity of scientific knowledge, as new develop¬
ments in science came to be technical innova¬
tions and "improvements" rather than shifts
in fundamental paradigms. A definite mode
of stability reminiscent of the European Mid¬
dle Ages came to be felt. Perhaps if newness is
to become important again it will originate
outside the Euro-American cultural sphere.
But since the end of the Cold War and the
advent of "globalization", is anywhere really
outside the Euro-American cultural sphere?
^ The forward-looking avant-garde enacts
an amazing and sometimes apocalyptic future.
It celebrates the newest technology and is cur¬
rently dominated by interactive telecommu¬
nications and CD-ROMS, the Internet, virtual
realities, and multimedia.
f' The tradition-seeking avant-garde, on
the other hand, eschews high tech and looks
instead towards "ancient knowledge," "ritu¬
als," and "traditional performances" especially
in non-Western cultures. Here the ideas and
researches of the Polish director and teacher
of acting Jerzy Grotowski are dominant. Gro-
towski has said that his goal is "To re-evoke a
very ancient form of art where ritual and artis¬
tic creation were seamless. Where poetry was
song, song was incantation, movement was
dance. One might say but it is only a
metaphor that we are trying to go back and
discover what was before the Tower of Babel.
First to discover differences, and then to dis¬
cover what was before the differences	 We
can hope to discover a very old form of art, art
as a way of knowledge."
THE UNESCO lOURIER MOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
v' The intercultural avant-garde has two
aspects. One is positive, seeking and synthe¬
sizing "universals" and connections between
cultures. The other is ironic and probing, seek¬
ing out disjunctures and miscommunications
"at the borders." The work of the Danish direc¬
tor Eugenio Barba and his International School
of Theatre Anthropology (ISTA) is an example
of the first aspect (see the Unesco Courier,
January 1996); the practice and theories of the
performance artist Guillermo Gomez-Pena are
an example of the second.
At ISTA and in his writings, Barba
attempts to show how "pre-expressive" posi¬
tions, movements and gestures arc at the root
of all effective artistic performing. For Barba,
these are most clearly seen in Asian dance-the¬
atres such as Kathakali and Odissi in India,
buto in Japan, jingju, and kunchu in China.
Gomez-Pena emphasizes the contradictions
of living and working in more than one cul¬
ture simultaneously. While Barba wants to
find connections, Gomez-Pena and others like
him explore the ways in which cultures collide
and fail to communicate, with their attendant
fractures, difficulties, ideological contradic¬
tions and crumbling national myths. Barba
tends to work with traditional performers;
Gomez-Pena with both traditional and post¬
modern artists.
The principal goal of the historical avant-
garde was to expose, ridicule, and destabilize
official art and official culture. The principal
goals of the other four kinds of avant-garde arc
too various to summarize, but revolution and
rebellion are not today very important themes.
Nor is there an attempt to present "the shock
of the new". The newest work in today's
avant-garde is highly technological and these
technologies are immensely popular and wide¬
spread, global even. They arc innovative but
not shocking; they tend to integrate rather
than divide; and they cost a lot of money,
especially during the development stage, and so
there has to be a deep alliance with the social
forces that have money.
What next?
Once it was felt that theatre would disappear
in the face of various other forms of dramatic
entertainment and arts, especially movies and
video. But the emergence of computer tech¬
nology is more likely to lead to a collapse of |
the differences between the various media arts. ^
The use of the information chip instead of I
strips of celluloid or magnetic tape will mean s_
an increasingly easy-to-use flow back and forth S
of images and actions from computer to film 5
to video and also between the so-called live
and the so-called mediated.
I use the term "so-called" because interac¬
tivity will allow for the immediate interven¬
tion of "viewers" or "audiences" who will
become "users" or co-creators. And although
fixed-text media movies and television will
be ubiquitous, interactive exchanges on the
personal as well as the artistic level will increase
exponentially.
The emergence of chip technology and per¬
formance does not sound the death knell of
"live theatre". It means only that the various
avant-gardes will bifurcate even more. If today
there are five avant-gardes, in twenty-five years
there may be ten or more.
Collectively, there will be a lot of live per¬
formance, but each genre will have relatively
few scattered clients, brought together first by
means of the Internet and secondly by local
and regional "festivals" or other occasions that
gather into one spot for a limited time all those
interested in a certain kind of performance.
Rehearsing an Afro-Brazilian
dance in Salvador (Brazil).
S
THE UNESCO ^>URIE I NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Culture will no longer be defined as local¬
ized in place, but as localized in taste and prac¬
tice. People will be able to belong to a "drama
culture" or a "performance art culture" wher¬
ever they happen to live.
This new definition of "local" will have an
effect on traditional performance genres. At
present, such forms as Kathakali or No,
gelede, samba or wayang kulit have been tied
to a particular place, particular social practices,
and particular practitioners. But increasingly,
at least some of these forms are opening to
practitioners who might not be "born to
them," and arc frequently domiciled outside
their place of origin or primary practice.
Global tourism
and traditional arts
Global tourism exerts an extremely strong pres¬
sure. Governments and corporations often
indistinguishable from each other are replac
ing traditional patrons. Already many tradi¬
tional arts have been commercialized, global¬
ized and "smoothed out" to satisfy the tastes
of tourists and "art lovers". Only those societies
rich enough to establish categories comparable
to Japan's "living national treasures" will be
able to preserve their traditional arts as such.
And even when they are preserved in this way,
the traditional arts tend to exist in venues that
are, like museums or game parks, strictly fenced
off from the impact of ongoing life. Many tra¬
ditional arts will cease to exist. No effective
remedy has been found to stop this cultural
extinction, which is in any case not entirely
bad. Times and circumstances change; not every¬
thing that was can be preserved indefinitely.
Sometimes the urge to preserve is a mask hid¬
ing fear of change.
Nor ought we to underestimate people's
inventiveness and creativity, especially the
power of popular culture. As advanced
economics preserve some traditional arts in
their traditional forms, and other less pro¬
tected arts vanish, a new category of continu¬
ous creation of tradition through fusion and
hybridity is emerging. Throughout Latin
America, for example, performances fusing
African, European, and Native American reli¬
gions are thriving. Other parts of the world are
experiencing a similar surge of creativity.
Over the past several centuries immigra¬
tion and displacement have created the great¬
est movement among the world's peoples ever
experienced. From assailed or displaced frag¬
ments of cultural practices, new vigorous per¬
formances have arisen. And soon enough, for¬
merly "artificial" or "synthetic" practices are
transformed into new wholes. We live in a
period where older traditional arts exist side by
side with new traditional arts, the fruit of
both consciously "invented traditions" and
less thought-out but very robust hybrids.
'Ordinary theatre'the string
quartet of the next century
And what about "ordinary theatre" (in Euro-
American terms), the enactment of dramas
written by playwrights and performed by
actors? Of course, this kind of theatre is not
"universal" and "omnipresent". It is a specific
cultural occurrence and as such it could go
extinct. But I don't think it will. I believe that
this kind of theatre will become the string
quartet of the twenty-first century. By that I
mean that it will have a small devoted audi¬
ence, but it will not be important in the way
it was, say, at the end of the nineteenth century
> (ouiTHE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER I 997
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
when a new drama by Ibsen could shake up an
entire continent. The important debates about
public culture will be conducted outside the¬
atres on TV, over the Internet, in new ritu¬
als convened and enacted electronically, or via
mass movements assembled in the streets.
Liveperformance
But this is not the whole story. The Utopian
electronic global village may turn out to be as
non-existent as all previous utopias. The media
and the Internet are increasingly omnipresent
but they do not satisfy certain basic needs
that are met by live performance. In fact, live
theatre will flourish to some degree because
of the rapid development of media and instant
information transmission. Note that I say
"information" and perhaps ought to say
"data" and do not use the more complex
term "communication". The media provide
more information than communication, while
live performance often offers more commu¬
nication than information.
Live performance can be sub-divided into
non-theatre and theatre performances. The
former include performance in everyday life,
religious services, sports, and popular enter¬
tainments such as rock-music concerts and
theme parks. There are three kinds of live the¬
atre: Broadway, boulevard, and other large-
scale commercial enterprises; not-for-profit,
subsidized mainstream theatres such as the
Stadtheaters in Germany or the regional the¬
atres in the U.S.A.; experimental theatre and
performance art.
Commercial theatre is self-supporting
because it effectively exploits crossovers
between media and live performance. Shows
and stars exist both live and on tape, CDs,
and film. In this sense, the pop entertainment
industry is the most advanced performance
genre economically and technically.
The Stadtheater system is the way in which
the middle class tells itself that it is "cultured"
and "responsible". Its repertory is based on
"classics" but includes some new works and
the safer experimental artists who "graduate"
to official status.
Experimental theatre and performance art,
which I regard as the "contemporary avant-
garde", are harder to pin down. Some perfor¬
mance artists become fairly big stars and occa¬
sionally a movie star also continues to work in
The Polish director Jerzy
Grotowski has described his
goal as an attempt to
"discover a very old form of
art, artas a way of
knowledge". Below, a scene
from Grotowski's production
of Akropolis, based on a 1904
play by Stanislaw Wyspianski.
w the unesco Courier «November I
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
k^^5 -^
1 ÍF\ J
î
"WW i y. ->
* h* M0V/ 1, , , , , $ , ,
t1/ ' ^^ ^k v
experimental theatre. But basically, experi¬
mental theatre and performance art take place
in small venues for tiny audiences.
Yet they perform a very important func¬
tion. Live performance of this type contin¬
ues to be "dangerous". By dangerous I do not
mean that the performers wound themselves
onstage but that they work in front of audi¬
ences while making and recovering from mis¬
takes and unforeseen circumstances. Live per¬
formance is also able to explore risky or taboo
subjects, unlike large-scale media such as film
and video which involve so much money that
often the financial backers do not want to take
chances. Finally, live performances before/with
small audiences allow for the experience of
close contact physically, emotionally and con¬
ceptually between actors and spectators. This
experience of shared presence is irreplaceable.
Will there be money for this kind of the¬
atre? Surely not enough. At one time, exper¬
imental performance got no public or official
support at all. Maybe under those circum
stances the avant-garde was most alive, dan¬
gerous, and important, since it owed its exis¬
tence to no one except the artists and the
immediate audiences gave freedom to those
involved. Of course, censorship and worse has
always been and will continue to be a threat.
But the underground seems to find a way.
There is a real need for an unofficial or anti-
official theatre. Official theatre no matter
how beautiful is always just that, "official".
And in houses of worship live theatre's clos¬
est sibling laughter is scarce, especially laugh¬
ter of the sarcastic, ironic, parodie, and blas¬
phemous kinds. Nor do church, synagogue,
mosque or temple encourage bleak tragedy or
atheistic scepticism. Official or corporate the¬
atres, newspapers and media, as well as state
sponsored religions, all require continuous
challenge and critique. Corrective tones of
unbelief, mockery, parody, horror and delight
are found in experimental theatre and perfor¬
mance art. I hope the next century will see
plenty of this kind of theatre.
The god of evil in a 1980
Beijing Opera production of
The Monkey King Wreaks
Havoc in Heaven.
THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1997
ll
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Rules made to be broken
BY JEAN-PIERRE GUINGANÉ
Below, a show staged to alert
street children to the threat of
Aids. This example of social
action theatre was performed
in Kinshasa (Democratic
Republic of the Congo)
with support from Médecins
Sans Frontières, a
humanitarian aid agency.
F Theatre people only became an accepted
part of African society sometime in the
1980s. It was on European stages that most
of them, like the Congolese poet Sony Labou
Tansi and his Roccado Zulu Theatre, first won
recognition and fame. Then, largely as a result
of democratization and the spread of educa¬
tion, theatre took root in African soil and
endeavoured to become involved in African
society. This change can be seen in the flower¬
ing and spread of social action theatre, a form
of drama which has different names in differ¬
ent countries (it is known as "Useful The¬
atre" in Mali, and "Forum Theatre" and
"Debate Theatre" in Burkina Faso) and is
staged in local languages for grassroots audi¬
ences in villages and urban working class neigh¬
bourhoods. Social action drama attempts to
change attitudes about specific questions such
as hygiene, customs or relationships with
community property (a well, for example).
Signs of this change can also be seen in the
increasing number of facilities for production
and performance across the continent. The¬
atres, private cultural centres and festivals reveal
a strong determination by African artists to
produce theatre tailored for their public. What
impact has this had on the sources of inspira¬
tion used by creative artists ?
During the 1980s, political life was the pri¬
mary source for African playwrights, who
concentrated on describing what they saw as
the bankruptcy of African political regimes.
Plays like Sony Labou Tansi's Anthony Sold
Me His Destiny (1986) and The Street ofFlies
(1985), Zadi Zahourou Bernard's The Secret of
the Gods (1985), Senouvo Agbota Zinsou's
The Singing Turtle (1985) and my own The
Entranced Savannah (1990) and The Mad¬
man (1987) were highly popular.
With the advent of the 1990s politics were
replaced by three other main sources of inspi¬
ration: traditional dramatization, religious
ritual and folk art.
Traditional drama
Traditional African society is highly codified
and the individual is subject to such a wide
range of social, professional and religious rules
that he or she ends up thinking that only the
community counts.
Yet almost everywhere these rules provide
for moments of rcleasewhcrc the individual is
allowed to transgress the social code, often
through acting. In Mali, for example, the
avowed goal of the kotéba, a form of folk the¬
atre organized once a year by young people,
was to give the young a chance to criticize their
elders. This was the only occasion in the year
when they could do this without risk the
young people were in duty bound to have
their say about society, while their elders were
in duty bound not to hold it against them.
12
THE UNESCO iOURIC R NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Africa's social action theatre taps a heritage of traditional games
designed to help people let off steam
Scene from the Congolese
playwright Sony Labou Tansi's
Antoine m'a vendu son destin
("Antoine sold me his
destiny"), directed by Daniel
Mesguich (France).
Everything said in this form of theatre was
above the law.
In Burkina Faso certain Mossi societies held
a market at night-time once a year. During the
night, all established rules especially sexual
taboos were consigned to limbo, and a person
could go with the person he or she had dreamed
about all year long, even the wife or husband of
a close relative. When dawn came, however,
everything returned to normal.
These two examples are interesting because
they can be considered as forms of play, of
social dramatization or dedramatization. The
protagonists were aware that they were acting
because they knew that at a specific moment
the rules would change again. The current suc¬
cess of African social action theatre has roots
in social games of this kind.
Although this form of theatre was created
and tested in Latin America, especially Brazil,
by Augusto Boal, it has not simply been lifted
from Latin America and transplanted in Africa.
African society has changed so much that a
tool had to be found to enable ruling classes,
whether African or non-African, which are
often out of touch with everyday life, to com¬
municate with local communities in order to
involve them in development. African social
action theatre is far less political in its inten¬
tions than Boal's "theatre of the oppressed"
and is effective because it knows so much
about the mindset of those it wishes to reach.
It is intended for popular, often illiterate
audiences which can only be reached by deal¬
ing with things that are important to them
in their daily lives. Social action theatre draws
inspiration therefore from community life in
its raw state. The skill of the organizers lies in
getting the audience to identify with the char¬
acters before going on to achieve critical detach¬
ment from its own behaviour. They do this via
the process whereby traditional societies peri¬
odically call themselves into question by turn¬
ing social rules upside down as an encourage¬
ment to self-criticism.
From a formal point of view, social action
13
THE UNESCO lOURIER \OVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A performance of Guiñean
playwright Williams Sassine's
Légende d'une vérité ("Legend
of a Truth") directed by Fasou
Siba (Guinea).
theatre achieves very close contact with its
audience by adopting the acting techniques of
traditional artists such as the West African
griot. The goal of each performance is to cre¬
ate an atmosphere that will encourage com¬
munication between the different groups in
the audience. The audience and the audience
alone will make the decision whether or not to
change its behaviour.
Religious ritual
We have also seen a flowering of religious sects
and a strengthening of mysticism in tradi¬
tional religions Animism, Christianity and
Islam. As a mirror to life, the theatre could
not afford to ignore this movement.
Firstly we are seeing a return to traditional
ritual. In Côte d'Ivoire, for example, so-called
ritual theatre has been one of the main avenues
of experimentation in theatre, opened up by
studies carried out by Jacques Schcrer and
Werewcre Liking on the ritual and staging
techniques of the Basa people of Cameroon.
Since then, the presence of ritual in the theatre
has become commonplace. In 1985 Sony
Labou Tansi was already noting in the intro¬
duction to The Street ofFlies that "This play
is in the tradition of a theatre that is as old as
the Kongo world, the Kingizila or theatre of
healing." Zadi Zahourou Bernard has based
his entire theatre aesthetic on a ritual of the
Bete people of Côte d'Ivoire from which his
troupe, Didiga, takes its name.
W THEUNESCO ^JURIER NOVEMBER 1997
But these borrowings arc not limited to
traditional rituals; theatre has also drawn inspi¬
ration from imported religions. Concert Party,
for example, a form of popular theatre staged
in Togo and Ghana, owes its form to Chris¬
tian church rituals in those countries.
Nowadays most big African theatre shows
have their share of "rituality " either in the set¬
ting and the acting or in the words themselves.
Ritual seems to be necessary to win over the
Jean-Pierre Guingané's Le
baobab merveilleux ["The
Wonderful Baobab Tree")
staged by the Théâtre de la
fraternité of Ouagadougou
(Burkina Faso).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Members of Côte d'lvoire's
Ymako Teatri Company in a
performance of La légende de
Kaidara ("The Legend of
Kaidara") directed by Claude
Gnakouri and Luis Marques.
The play is based on a work by
the Malian writer Amadou
Hampaté Bâ.
audience. Perhaps that accounts for the success
of Mwambayi Kalengayi's (of the former Zaire)
production of La passion selon Pier Paolo
Pasolini ("The Passion According to Pier Paolo
Pasolini"), a play that depicts with fascinating
realism the lives of the many preachers who
haunt African cities without anyone knowing
whether they are politicians or men of religion.
In a different way, the costumes, make-up
and plot of Fasou Siba's Guinea National The¬
atre production of Williams Sassine's Legende
d'une vérité ("Legend of a Truth") bear a
strange resemblance to a ceremony of exor¬
cism in a village.
Traditional arts
At present, however, playwrights draw most
of their inspiration from folk tales.
Of a total of some twenty plays staged in
African theatres in 1996 and 1997, more than
half were based on folk tales. Some plays such
as Akonio Dolo's Zinimo . . . Zinimo Zi,
Souleymane Koly's La colère de la brousse
("The Anger of the Bush") and Habib Dem-
bclé's Fidélité cravachée ("Horsewhipped
Loyalty"), stay very close to classic tales
although they attach more importance to the
use of space and movement. They contain two
characteristic features of folk tales elements
of fantasy combined with an outlook on the
world that always makes a moral point. The
work of the African sage Amadou Hampaté Bâ
is also beginning to be adapted to the stage.
Through use of folk sources community
life, folk plays, religious ritual and folk tales
African theatre has confirmed its goal of
addressing itself above all to the audience it
wants to reach, an African audience. And that
is a good thing, for it is by translating the
deepest aspirations of this audience that
African theatre will earn credibility and some
day have a chance of attracting wider audiences.
Togo's Dana'i Puppet Theatre
(Togo), whose repertory is
largely taken from folk tales.
E UNESCO QoURIER« NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
An art in search of its roots
BY ROMAIN MAITRA
Rasilla, below, is a devotional and ritual theatre form which originated
in northern India.
I Indian folk theatre is a composite art
with a composite set of skills practised
by artists who stage a total performance
through the creation of verbal, spatial and
visual patterns. Folk theatre forms such as
fatra from Bengal, Tamasha from Maharash¬
tra, Nautanki from Uttar Pradesh, Rajasthan
and Punjab, Bhavai from Gujarat, Yaksha-
gana from Karnataka and Therukuttu from
Tamil Nadu feature a wide range of make-up,
song, dance, mime, improvised repartee, slap¬
stick or stylized acting, and even acrobatics.
These folk theatres give a glimpse of styles
of speech, music, dance, dress, behaviour,
humour, legend, proverb and wit in their
respective regions. The actors, who are often
very talented performers, speak directly to the
THE UNESCO Ç'URIERB NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Forms of folk drama rooted in the villages
could give new impetus to modern Indian theatre
Below and opposite page
above, an episode from the
Mahabharata, the great Indian
epic, directed by Raton
Thiyam.
audience audience participation is the hall¬
mark of Indian folk theatre and often
improvise. They are apt to mix up several
moods and disciplines, from time to time
bursting into song and dancing with gusto
when the chorus sings their dialogue. The
result is a form of drama which springs from
an exhilarating freedom of expression and pro¬
vides the villagers with a complete emotional
experience in an environment in which ideas
can be effortlessly communicated.
Folk forms have their own stage conven¬
tions and production styles. The scenography
is nonrealistic and the stage is usually a bare
space manipulated by the actors through the
use of stylized and symbolic make-up and by
codified gait, choreographic acting, and sym¬
bolic hand gestures. Change of location is
denoted by movement and by word of mouth
rather than by change of set and decor.
Folk theatre has inherited many of the clas
sical conventions of Sanskrit theatre. The clas¬
sical Sutradhar or narrator is used in several
vernacular theatres, and the classical Vidushak
or buffoon appears under different names in
different regions as Konangi, Komali, or
Joothan Mian. Other stock characters are
found in different regions.
While ageless in pattern these performances
are refreshingly novel in their appeal. Cosmic
or symbolic battles between the forces of good
and evil, mythological stories and legendary
romantic tales are sprinkled with commen¬
tary on current social or political conditions.
One reason for the survival of folk plays, in
fact, has been their capacity to gradually adapt
old themes to changing ways of life and sati¬
rize the latest local happenings. The exaggera¬
tion, malapropism and ready wit in the fol¬
lowing piece of dialogue from Naqal (from
Punjab), taken from Balwant Gargi's Folk
Theatre of India (1966), is typical.
E UNESCO COURIER! NOVEMBER 1997 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Inspector: How did you know that a thief
had burgled?
Wife: Pearly one, I heard the haystack bark¬
ing and saw it running toward the dog.
Inspector: What did you do then?
Wife: Great Sire, I jumped out of my bed.
Immediately I rolled my skirt and put on the
bed around my waist.
Inspector: Then what happened?
Wife: May God bless you with a dozen
children! Then I saw the courtyard rushing
past the thief.
Cobbler (peeping from behind): Sir, she is
trembling with fear. If you permit m-m-m . . .
if you per-
Inspector: Bark!
Cobbler. May the plume of your turban. . . .
Inspector: Be brief ! Tell me what have you
lost?
Cobbler: Sir, I have lost nine yards of my
cow, and the black-hoofed turban is. . . .
With the disintegration of the traditional
culture and the growing impact of industrial
society, however, folk theatre is gradually los¬
ing its artistic character and vitality. Powerfu 1
forces of globalization, accompanied by aggres¬
sive images and values of the West, are com
pounding the ill effects of 200 years of colo¬
nization which had already shaken traditional
Indian cultures loose from their moorings.
Urban influences have a weapon of matchless
power the TV and cinema whose shadow
is falling over village drama.
And yet at the same time, many Indian direc¬
tors realize that theatre forms borrowed from
the West are inadequate to project the social aspi¬
rations, ways of life, cultural patterns and pro b-
lems of the people of India as a whole. Since,
like theatre artists all over the world, they are
interested in establishing a closer relationship
between the theatre and the people, there is every
reason why they should make greater use of the
living tradition of indigenous theatre.
It is unfortunate that there has not been
more mutual exchange and collaboration
between the urban and rural traditions in
Indian theatre. Some leading theatre groups
in Calcutta, Bombay and Delhi are involved in
experiments of this kind, but they are rela¬
tively few. Ultimately, the outcome of their
work will depend on the resilience of the the¬
atre form itself to withstand and coexist with
the powerful invasion of commercial cinema
and television sitcoms and serials.
A scene from Therukuttu, folk
theatre from Tamil Nadu in
southern India.
18 ) Q^lURi:THE UNESCO lOU IER« \OVEMBEil 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The
chequered
fortunes
of Japan's
modern
drama
Shingeki's restless century
©J M Steinlein, Maison des cultures du monde, Pans
BYOHZASAYOSHIO*
Tue Watering Place, above,
was written and staged by the
Tenkei Gekijo company.
* People's names: following
Japanese custom, the
surname precedes the given
name. Ed.
There is a basic difference between classi¬
cal Japanese theatre and Shingeki or
"modern theatre", which emerged in the early
twentieth century under the influence of West¬
ern theatre. Classical theatre, which is performed
exclusively by men, is musical theatre with a
strong infusion of dance, unlike Shingeki,
which is purely verbal, a theatre of dialogue.
The traditional forms of Japanese classical
drama, Nô, Kabuki and Bunraku, are quite dis¬
tinct from each other and each one has its own
playhouses. There are Nô theatres (nôgakudo)
and Kabuki theatres, and Bunraku (a variant
of puppet theatre) is only performed on spe¬
cially designed stages. When Shingeki came
along, it created a need for Western-style play¬
houses in which the curtain divides the stage
from the audience. In response to the aesthet¬
ics of realism, women began appearing in plays
after centuries of banishment from the stage.
In theory neither traditional theatre nor
modern theatre, which politically speaking leans
to the left, receive state subsidies. National the¬
atres do exist Tokyo's National Kabuki The¬
atre (founded in 1969), the National Puppet
Theatre of Osaka, the Theatre of Traditional
Arts, Tokyo's Nô Theatre and the New
National Theatre created in 1 997 for ballet and
opera but with the exception of the Osaka
Puppet Theatre they do not have permanent
companies. There is no national theatre school.
In 1990 however, the state created the Soci¬
ety for the Encouragement of Arts and Let¬
ters which defrays part of the costs of theatre,
music and dance performances. This was the
first official state contribution to the theatre.
Support also comes from two long-established
theatre companies, Shôshiku, which finances
Kabuki performances, and Tôhô, which
together with other private companies have
funded the construction of numerous theatres.
Shôshiku and Tôhô producers stage sepa¬
rate Shingeki performances by recruiting actors
to work with the major stars of theatre, cinema
and television. This is what is known as com¬
mercial theatre. The avowed aim of these per¬
formances, which are held in theatres that can seat
from 1,000 to 2,000 people, is to make profit.
The traditional compartmentalization of
different types of theatre is not totally water¬
tight. Some Kabuki actors act in new produc¬
tions in films and on television, even including
r 3
THE UNESCO (^OURIER m NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Left, the two tramps in
Samuel Beckett's Waiting (or
Godot in a 1960 Tokyo
production by the Buragaku-za
(The Company of Letters).
American and British musical comedies. In the
last few years musical comedies mainly adap¬
tations of Western works have become increas¬
ingly popular. A show can attract tens of thou¬
sands of people and run for up to a year.
Takarazuka is a celebrated all-female review
and musical comedy company whose reper¬
tory includes works such as Oklahoma, Me
and my GzV/and Grand Hotel as well as Japan¬
ese works based on popular comic strips like
the well-known Berusayu no bara ("The Roses
of Versailles") which has entertained millions
of spectators. This company, which aims
largely at a female audience, still has an immense
following today.
Born again Shingeki
During Japan s militarist period before the Sec¬
ond World War, Shingeki was repressed, and
by the summer of 1945 only one company was
left the Bungaku-za ("The Company of Let¬
ters"), which had been founded in 1937. Dur¬
ing the democratization process initiated by
the American authorities, Shingeki came back to
life as popular theatre. Newly founded around
directors such as Aoyama Sugisaku::' and Senda
Koreeya, the Haiyû-za (Actors Theatre) Com¬
pany in 1946 staged Kensatsukan, a Japanese
version of Gogol's Revisor (The Inspector
General). After reforming his company,
Shînkyôgekidan, which he had been forced to
break up, Murayama Tomoyoshi returned to
the theatre in the same year with Kofuku no
îe, a production of Vladimir Fedorov's The
20
* THE
House of Happiness. Kubo Sakae, one of
Shingeki's great playwrights, inaugurated the
Tokyo Geijutsu Gekijô (the Tokyo Art The¬
atre) with actors including Takizawa Osamu,
and made a new departure in the same year with
Ibsen's A Doll's House. A number of leading
theatre people joined the communist party
(newly recognized as a political party) and, as
before the war, made it their duty to spread its
message through the theatre.
By 1948 the great figures of pre-war Shingeki
had already made their come-back. Some new
plays, such as Miyoshi Jurô's Sono hito o shirazu
("You don't know this man") and Tanaka
Shikao's Kumo no hatate ("At the end of the
clouds"), depicted post-war life. Others like
Kinoshita Junji's Yûzuru ("Twilight of a
Crane"), staged by the Budô no kai company,
and Onna no isshô ("The Life of a Woman"),
performed by the Bungaku-za company,
became classics of the modern repertory.
The year 1950 was a turning-point in post¬
war history. The Cold War between the United
States and the former Soviet Union had settled
in. When war broke out in nearby Korea, anti-
communist purges in Japan spared neither the
cinema nor the theatre. One Shingeki com¬
pany, the Haiyû-za, built a small theatre in
1954 (the Haiyû-za gekijô) where it staged
Onna no heiwa, a production of Aristo¬
phanes' Women in Parliament. It is still
unusual today for a Shingeki company to have
its own theatre; most of the time they hire
theatres for their plays.
i Qu RIER NOVEMBER 1197
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Haiyû-za became the leading Shingeki
theatre when in 1949 it founded its own train¬
ing centre, which came to provide it and other
companies with a plentiful supply of actors.
Shiki, a company founded by Asari Kcita and
Kusaka Takeshi, reappraised the approach
which had presided over the origins of
Shingeki, that of Stanislavsky-inspired real¬
ism. It specialized in the plays of Jean Girau¬
doux and Jean Anouilh, which had very rarely
been staged in Japan. In 1955, the Bungaku-za
(Literary Theatre) Company had a hit with
Hamlet in a version translated and directed
by Fukuda Tsuneari. Shakespeare is the most
widely performed playwright in Japan. In
terms of the number of performances per
author, he shares first place with the Kabuki
playwright Kawatake Miluami. The diversity
and depth of his work are a source of endless
fascination to theatre lovers.
One important feature of post-war Shingeki
was the introduction of Bertolt Brecht's plays
and theories of drama. Brecht's Fear and Mis¬
ery ofthe Third Reich was first staged in Japan
by Senda Koreeya with the Haiyû-za yôscisho
(School of Dramatic Art) in 1953. Debate about
Brecht's ideas on drama went hand in hand
with questioning about the renewal of the
modern world through theatre.
In 1957, for the first time in the history
of a Shingeki company, the Bungaku-za used
Kabuki actors in a Fukuda Tsuneari play
(Akechi Mitsubide). The first tour of Japan by
the Moscow Art Theatre the following year
had a tremendous impact. It marked the start
of a wave of tours by famous foreign com¬
panies that began to develop in the second half
of the 1970s.
Les Misérables, a musical
comedy adapted from Victor
Hugo's novel, being performed
at Tokyo's Imperial Theatre
(1997).
Notes from underground
Women's time has come,
a play for the commercial
theatre staged in Tokyo
by the all-female Takarazuka
company.
While big demonstrations against the renewal
of the security treaty with the United States
were taking place in 1960, Bungaku-za brought
the theatre of the absurd to Japan with their
production of Samuel Beckett's Waiting for
Godot. The play hinted that, like Godot, the
change long awaited by part of public opinion
would not appear. ... A series of plays by
Beckett and Eugene Ionesco were produced
around this time, which also saw the first per¬
formances of Shingeki outside Japan.
The events of spring 1960 also left their
mark on the world of Shingeki. The author¬
ity of the major companies such as Haiyû-za,
Bungaku-za and Mingei began to be ques¬
tioned and new companies critical of their pre¬
decessors emerged. This was a period of intense
experimentation and creative activity. Doubts
about the traditional left were accompanied
by criticism of Shingeki.
The aim behind this experimentation was
to create a different theatre from Shingeki,
and renewal took an extreme form in 1967
with a Karagumi (situationist theatre) per¬
formance. In the same year the Tenjôsajiki
r Í
THE UNESCO ^J>URIERB NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
company (The Gallery Company) broke new
ground as part of the drive for "the rehabili¬
tation of theatre". Faces wearing way-out
Kabuki make-up appeared on stage and pop
songs announced that Shingeki was a thing of
the past. A world of human folly was por¬
trayed in an atmosphere of utter confusion.
Put out of their stride by the emergence of
such a different kind of theatre, critics soon
dubbed it Angura ("underground").
Each underground company had its own
special features, but they all shared a belief in
the need to destroy the traditional perception
of theatre and staging, in the importance of the
actor's role, in a new approach to Nô and
Kabuki, in the abandonment of realism and in
exploration of the human unconscious.
The Tenjôsajiki company, directed by Tcr-
ayama Shûji, staged many bold experiments,
changing its use of space and stagecraft with
each performance. For Nokku, street theatre,
in 1975, Terayama transformed Tokyo's Sug-
A scene from Kabuki, one of
the classic forms of Japanese
theatre, directed by Oguri
Hangan(1997).
inami district into a vast stage, injecting dra¬
matic structure into daily life and obliterating
the boundaries between reality and fiction.
The action took place in thirty different places
at once, making it impossible for one specta¬
tor to see the entire show.
Strolling Dreamers
Starting in the 1970s young playwrights, direc¬
tors and actors influenced by Angura founded
a host of small companies which took their cue
from the main trends of contemporary theatre.
Among the most influential figures were
Tsuka, who cynically examined the foibles of
Japan and the Japanese, and Higashi, the author
of a musical comedy, Tokyo Kid Brothers.
Angura abolished the distinction between
author, director and company manager, a move
that came to be widely followed.
Japanese society in the 1980s became highly
prosperous and experienced the euphoria of
running the world's second biggest economy
after the United States. Concern about the
unemployment of young people disappeared,
and so did anxiety about the economic future
This was the context which gave rise to Noda
Hideki with his Company of Strolling
Dreamers (Yume no Yûminsha) and Kôkami
Shôji with his Third Stage (Dai san butai).
One distinctive feature of their style is the
absence of any "ordinary" people from the
stage. The heroes arc young people of inde¬
terminate social background. In its stagecraft
and its language this kind of theatre jumps
from one form to another. It turns away from
Angura's dark, brooding expressiveness and
stages shows full of light music and dancing,
in which sensitivity is the keynote. This form
of theatre, very different from Shingeki and
Angura, attracts crowds of young spectators
from all social classes. Many companies have
taken part in this kind of experimentation.
In the 1990s, however, most of the com¬
panies practising this type of theatre have had
chequered careers. The Company of Strolling
Dreamers no longer exists. The playwrights
of note are those who have gone back to every¬
day life and language. This marks a return to
early Shingeki. Independent playwrights are
making a come-back, and young authors are
producing their works with established
Shingeki companies. Whether these play¬
wrights work independently or not, I feel
that contemporary Japanese theatre is once
again at a turning point. M
22 HE UNESCO ^>UR!ERB NOVEMBER 1907
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Despite the sweeping changes that have occurred since the Soviet era,
Russian theatre is still a crucible of collective enthusiasm
A common home
BY ANATOLY SMELIANSKY
Ten Days That Shook the
World, directed by Yuri
Lyubimov at the Taganka
Theatre in Moscow (1965).
The play is based on John
Reed's eyewitness account of
the 1917 Revolution.
Just a hundred years ago, a famous
encounter took place in a well-known
Moscow restaurant, the Slav Bazaar, between
the actor and director Konstantin Stanislavsky
and the playwright and critic Vladimir
Nemirovich-Danchenko.
They talked non-stop for eighteen hours
and ended up agreeing to create a new company.
Little more than a year later, the Moscow Art
Theatre (MKhT) was born. It was to be a driving
force of twentieth-century Russian theatre.
The Art Theatre gave rise to numerous
other theatres and spawned many directors
and actors. It also nurtured some well-known
aesthetic critics and dissenters who developed
their own approaches to theatre. The names
of Vsevolod Meyerhold, Evgeny Vakhtan-
gov, Mikhail Chekhov, Alexander Tairov and,
in the European theatre, Bertolt Brecht, Peter
Brook and Jerzy Grotowski are associated
with the acceptance or aggressive rejection of
the ideas of the Theatre's founders at the begin¬
ning of the century.
In the 1930s, Stanislavsky's ideas were glo¬
rified by the Soviet state and many of his oppo¬
nents were liquidated. In reality, however, his
o fficial adoption was accompanied by the nega¬
tion of all that he stood for. In the early 1930s,
Stalin renamed the Art Theatre the "Theatre of
Academic Art" (MKhAT), which was the sig¬
nal for all the country's theatres to model them¬
selves on the Soviet-style MKhAT.
r 22
THE UNESCO {^URIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The leaders of the Revolution had realized
immediately that the theatre could be used as
a spiritual substitute for the Church they had
dismantled. It would not be good for the holy
places to remain empty. So for decades, until
the fall of the Soviet Union, this model of a
theatre-cum-church existed in one form or
another. If it was sacrilege, it was also remark¬
ably effective.
In Soviet Russia, the theatre replaced a par¬
liament which had become just a rubber stamp,
and a Church which had been half suffocated.
Several generations of directors, actors and
spectators had developed a kind of condi¬
tioned reflex. You didn't go to the theatre just
for entertainment but for communion.
The elite's notion of communion (sobor-
nost), which was very popular with the Russ¬
ian symbolists at the beginning of the century,
now found an unexpected place in society. The
theatre became perhaps the only focal point of
Russian sobornost, a spontaneous living con¬
tact between people. Directors and actors made
themselves servants of the cult of the theatre.
Audience expectations rose, to the point where
it was felt that life could be transformed by a
moralizing production.
When the Soviet Union began to fall apart,
the country had about 600 state-subsidized
theatres with between twenty-five and 160
* -
Students of the Theatre
Institute and young actors of
Maly Theatre, St. Petersburg,
in Claustrophobia, a play
written by them and directed
by Lev Dodin (1994).
Konstantin Stanislavsky
(right) and Vladimir
Nemirovich-Danchenko
in 1923. In 1898 they founded
the Moscow Art Theatre.
actors and actresses each. In the towns, the
theatre usually stood near the offices of the
regional party committee or the party-con¬
trolled House of Culture. The authorities
stressed, even geographically, the importance
of the theatre as a vital tool in leading the
"flock".
But while the vast majority of theatres
faithfully carried out their mission for the
party, some managed to express dissent. Oleg
Efremov, Georgi Tovstonogov, Yuri Lyubi-
mov and Anatoly Efros were not content just
to reflect the standard trends of Russian the¬
atre. They also worked through troupes which
were like families, designed not to break up
after a few weeks but to stay together for years
of joint creativity. This was the indelible fea¬
ture of what was, and still is, understood in
Russia as "theatre".
To be in the theatre in Russia is to share a
common home and to devote your whole life
to a joint endeavour. It's a long-term artistic
association which demands a special set of
structural, aesthetic and, especially, moral cir¬
cumstances.
The crisis
The coming of freedom put our biggest the¬
atre "temples" to the test. The deaths of Efros
and Tovstonogov plunged the Art Theatre
and the Taganka Theatre, the two biggest the¬
atres under communism, into crisis. After a
long internal conflict which spilled over into
the newspapers, the Kremlin decided in May
1987 to split up the Art Theatre. Efremov
remained as head of one half of the MKhAT
s while actress Tatiana Dronina took charge of
a the other. The split quickly turned ideologi-
| cal, with the first MKhAT naming itself the
> G>u RIERB NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Chekhov and the second continuing to be
called the Gorky.
While Efremov tried yet again to revive a
"troupe of friends" and to get back to the
founding tenets of the MKhT, the tempestu¬
ous amazon Dronina, who had no production
or management experience, gathered so-called
"patriotic forces" around her. At the Gorky
MKhAT, it was even decided to celebrate Stalin.
At the end of a production by Sergei Kurgin-
ian based on Mikhail Bulgakov's play Batum,
the white-uniformed generalissimo looks pen¬
sively into the distance and the crowd rises as
one on hearing the sound of the abolished
Soviet national anthem and its words: "Stalin
taught us to be true to the people. He has
inspired our work and achievements."
From temple
to entertainment hall
The two MKhATs, both of them in Tvcr-
skaya Street, arc a good illustration of the pre¬
sent state of Russian theatre. A similar thing
happened at the Taganka Theatre. When Lyu-
bimov returned there, he was greeted as a hero
and the audience chanted "stay! stay!" Some
people wept. The spring of 1988 was still a
heady time in Moscow. He stayed, dug up
plays which had been banned and put on oth-
Scene from the first act of
Konstantin Stanislavsky and
Vladimir Nemirovich-
Danchenko's 1902 Moscow Art
Theatre production of Maxim
Gorky's The Lower Depths.
ers, including Nikolai Erdman's The Suicide,
Pasternak's Dr Zhivago and Dostoyevsky's
The Adolescent.
But the collapse of the Berlin Wall didn't
bring success. Lyubimov no longer had anyone
to fight against. He had returned to a different
country, something he didn't immediately
grasp. When he did, it was too late. His main
opponent was a member of his troupe, one
of his pupils, Nikolai Gubenko. The dispute
at the Taganka took the form of a battle over
property, but as at the Art Theatre, it was
tinged with ideology. Gubenko was close to
the communists, led by Zyuganov, and as his
fellow actors said wryly, he had gone "from
the Taganka to the Zyuganka".
In this situation, the days of the Soviet
theatre came to be regarded with nostalgia.
Though squeezed dry by censorship and iso¬
lated by an "iron curtain" from theatre devel¬
opments in the outside world, the best pro¬
ductions of that era were an expression of the
society's spiritual life. One might say, recalling
Stanislavsky, that it was a theatre with "too
much to do".
In the new, relatively free atmosphere, the
Russian theatre lost its special importance.
The "super-theatre" became just theatre. Such
downgrading affected every aspect of intellec¬
tual life. The print run of "heavy-weight"
E UNESCO COURIER NOVEMBER I
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
newspapers and magazines fell tenfold, some¬
times a hundred-fold. Playwrights, directors
and authors who had thought of themselves
as good shepherds of the people were now
confused. Their books were no longer pub¬
lished and their plays became only one of
many leisure activities.
It was something quite new for Russian
theatre people to be just another part of the
modern entertainment industry. Artistic free¬
dom was no longer felt to be something spe¬
cial and healthy. People very quickly adjusted
to the new scene, just as they do to the air
they breathe.
The system of state subsidies for theatres no
longer covered half their budgets. In an effort
to survive, Moscow theatres opened casinos
and night-clubs on their premises. Many of
the old "theatre show enterprises," as the Soviet
authorities officially dubbed theatres, became
criminal show enterprises. With a high degree of
symbolism, signs saying "Money changed here"
were posted outside the capital's biggest the¬
atres. Just as the whole country was changing its
blood, so were the theatres. That said, it was
hard to see what was being exchanged for what
and, as it were, at what exchange rate. The loss
of social status and of the saintly feeling that
you were at the top of the tree, which were
embedded in the genes of Russian artists of
every kind, was one of the most important
results of the change.
Atth adse crossro
The new class invented its own structures and
took to what was called "tusovka", a slang word
of the new Russia which is difficult to translate.
The word evokes big extravaganzas, endless
Alexander Ostrovsky's Wolves
and Sheep, directed by Piotr
Fomenko(1997).
birthday celebrations, the razzmatazz of pub¬
licity, banquets, exchanges of honours, orgies of
words and other such pleasures which Russia
had forgotten while frozen under communism.
In the new Moscow, political, religious
and "artistic" tusovkas intermingled. The same
people went from event to event, variety artists
hobnobbed with the high clergy and satirists
with KGB bosses. The president sent his best
wishes to the biggest tusovkas, thus marking
the transition of the post-Soviet artistic elite
to a new lifestyle.
The Russian theatre embraced the new
trend, of which it was simultaneously recorder
and victim. "Perestroika" plays were built
around turning everything upside down. The
tired old heroes and institutions leaders of
the Revolution, party secretaries and collec¬
tive farm virtuosos were exposed and jeered
at. The popular actors who once played Lenin
now depicted the moving figure of the mur¬
dered Tsar Nicolas II.
Then came new characters: "international
girls," evil KGB agents, the heroes of the dis¬
sident movement. The puritan language of the
old era disappeared from stage and screen as
easily as the taboo of sexuality. A naked body
and a daring speech became a kind of symbol
of the freedom we had gained. "A stinking
mixture of blood and excrement," was how
elderly critics described the new art forms.
As Russia entered the market economy,
the theatre began to depict the emergence of a
new kind of human being, the transforma¬
tion of Soviet Man into the "nouveau riche"
or "new Russian." It was often hard to make
out any difference between the subject of the
artistic study and the resources used to carry
it out. Socialist realism and "capitalist realism"
turned out to be twins.
Renewal
There are no reliable statistics, but most the¬
atres in the capital are clearly full again, after a
crisis period in the early 1 990s. The country is
coming out of a critical phase and the healthy
theatre attendances of the past two years are
striking evidence of the change. The advent of
the free market has of course produced the
kind of openly commercial operations famil¬
iar in Europe and the United States.
More interesting are the persistence and
survival in Russia of what could be called, not
so much home-made theatre as cult theatre.
In a basement on Povarskaya Street, not far
from where Stanislavsky and Meyerhold set up
26
) ^>URI ER «NOVEMBER 1^97
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Lamentations of Jeremiah,
a work inspired by the Old
Testament book of the same
title, was set to music by
Vladimir Martinov and
directed by Anatoly Vassiliev
(1997).
a studio at the beginning of the century, is
Anatoly Vassiliev's School of Dramatic Art.
This is a modern experimental theatre labora¬
tory not especially noted for its annual "pro¬
ductivity" level, but its existence is crucial to
theatre in Moscow. Vassiliev's most recent
work, The Lamentations ofJeremiah, was
closer to a religious and liturgical event than to
traditional theatre.
Vassiliev is not alone. In St. Petersburg, Lev
Dodin is also trying to preserve a Stanislavsky-
style repertory theatre capable of withstand¬
ing the context of rampant capitalism. Among
the popular new theatres are the Piotr
Fomenko Workshop and Sergei Jenovach's
theatre. Also popular are the shows put on
by Kama Ginkas, usually at the small Young
Moscow Theatregoer's Stage (TIouZ). This is
serious new work, highly representative of
the creativity of the new Russian theatre.
In June 1997, an international conference
was held at the Art Theatre on the Slav Bazaar,
the meeting that laid the foundations of twen¬
tieth-century Russian theatre. It was attended
by all of Russia's leading stage directors and
many of their European and American col¬
leagues, who reflected on the theatre achieve¬
ments of the past century and the prospects
for the next.
I think it was Dodin who came up with the
best summary. For him, the Art Theatre of
Chekhov and Stanislavsky's time was a model
for "home-made" theatre, family theatre built
on two distinct foundations great idealism
(which made the theatre into a kind of cult),
and the kind of clearsighted economic calcu¬
lation that is inevitable in a market economy.
The twentieth century rubbished these
two foundations. Idealism degenerated into
Stalinism or fascism. Economic rationality
and honesty degenerated into cynical wheeling
and dealing. The laws of the marketplace have
infiltrated the remotest corners of the theatre
business and robbed our theatre of some of its
meaning.
We are back with the same problems which
were being argued about at the beginning of
the century. To start the new one, Russia needs
another Slav Bazaar. But is it only the Russian
theatre which needs something like that?
) ^>URITHE UNESCO lO IER NOVEMBER I 997
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Outward-looking pioneers in the 19th century set the scene
for contemporary theatre in the Arab world
The Lebanese playwright
Roger Assaf wrote, directed
and acted in Samar, above
(1997).
I In February 1848, a Beirut merchant
I named Marun Al Naqqash (1817-55),
put on in his own home a performance of 'Al
Bakhil, a play based on Molièrc's L'Avare.
When the curtain rose he stood before the
audience and delivered a prologue in true eigh¬
teenth and nineteenth century European style.
He promised to introduce his people to a new
artistic form, "a literary theatre . . . which shall
be Western gold in an Arab mould". This
form, he added, was of two kinds: drama and
opera. "It would have been much easier for
me," he said, "to start with the former but I
decided to take the harder course . . . because it
is more likely to meet with the approval of
the audience and delight them. I trust that I
have made the right choice . . . and that you will
benefit from this theatre, for it teaches . . .
proper manners, proffers good advice, pol¬
ishes and refines."
Al Naqqash went on to develop his adap¬
tative approach, still embryonic in Al Bakhil,
in plays which were based on The Arabian
Nights and performed in a playhouse which
he built for the purpose. After his death, his
brother Nicolas and his nephew Salim contin¬
ued his work, taking French theatre as their
major source of ideas and material. But faced by
what they considered insufficient appreciation
for their efforts they left for Egypt where they
contributed to a budding dramatic movement.
Meanwhile another merchant, Sheikh
Abou Khalil Qabbani (1836-1902), was doing
in Damascus what Marun Al Naqqash had
started in Beirut, although unlike Al Naqqash
he was not versed in foreign languages and had
not travelled abroad. He may have seen per¬
formances of Italian operettas by visiting
troupes and plays staged by Turkish actors,
but on the whole he was solidly rooted in the
local tradition. His major source was The Ara¬
bian Nights.
Al Qabbani set out to establish theatre in
Arab society as a form of entertainment that
was deeply rooted in tradition yet open to
new ideas and to the outside world. He failed
because conservative forces plotted against him
with the authorities in Istanbul and did not
28 > GuiRIERl NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
give up until orders were given for his theatre
to be closed.
Like Salim Al Naqqash and others from
Beirut, Al Qabbani packed up and left for
Egypt, where a young man named Ya'coub
Sannu' (or Abou Naddara as he preferred to
be called) had launched a new theatre move¬
ment. As a young man Ya'coub Sannu' had
been sent to Europe, where he learnt languages
and developed a passion for the theatre. On his
return to Egypt he worked with European
troupes whose repertoire consisted mainly of
operettas and farces and decided to emulate
them. Initially using these two Western forms,
he drew upon aspects of local tradition that
were conducive to the development of musical
drama. His characters were deeply rooted in the
social fabric and used the vibrant spoken Ara¬
bic of everyday life. With Sannu' the Western
gold and the Arab mould merged very well
although one sometimes wonders which is the
gold and which is the mould. The written text,
the form, and the Italian frame stage were West¬
ern-inspired innovations, but everything else
was deeply rooted in popular tradition.
Sannu' wrote scores of plays, most of
which were performed with him as principal
actor, director, producer and prompter. The
majority of his plays dealt with contemporary
issues, often in a comic vein. Many had polit¬
ical overtones which made him enemies and
alienated some of his former friends and spon¬
sors including the Khedive himself. His theatre
survived for only two years until it was closed
down by the authorities.
Traditional shadow theatre
Further west, traditional Arab forms were
holding their own in Tunisia, Algeria and
Morocco. All three countries had an active
shadow play theatre tradition. One form, fea¬
turing a satirical figure called Garaguz, was
banned by the French authorities in Algeria in
1848 on account of its anti-French political
bias. In addition to Garaguz, shadow theatre in
both Morocco and Tunisia featured a raivi or
narrator who told stories to a musical accom¬
paniment. In Morocco the Islamic Ashura fes¬
tival was celebrated with performances remi¬
niscent of medieval miracle plays. Western
forms, except for Sicilian marionettes, were late
reaching the Maghreb countries, and Western
influence only began to make itself felt when
travelling Egyptian companies visited Tunisia,
Algeria and Morocco at least half a century after
Al Naqqash, Al Qabbani and Sannu'.
Until the middle of the twentieth century,
successive generations of theatre practitioners
carried on where the pioneers had left off. The
end product almost invariably appealed to
local taste, speaking the language of the audi-
A Midsummer Night's Dream
by William Shakespeare,
directed by Khaled Galal
(Egypt).
ence, which was often drawn into the action
despite the increasing impact of the distance
imposed by the Italian frame indoor stage
earlier traditional performances usually took
place outdoors in courtyards.
Many translations were made of works by
European dramatists such as Racine, Corneille,
Shakespeare, Sheridan and Goldoni. Most of
them were adaptations in which translators
and directors "improved" texts or adjusted
them to suit contemporary taste. Romeo and
Juliet, for example, rendered as Martyrs of
Love, ended happily and was full of song and
music. During this productive period Arab
theatre professionals considered the world
drama tradition as their own and used it freely,
often shaping it to their needs. There were
perhaps more theatres per head of population
in the Arab world then than there are today
and intejise activity in the theatre generated
widespread interest and debate about the
objectives of drama and the forms of Arabic
that should be used in it.
George Abyad (1880-1962) was one major
figure in the history of the Arab theatre in
this period. He became widely known for the
formal style and eloquent literary language of
his adaptations of Western plays, mainly
> G>uTHE UNESCO I OURIERB NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
French classics, but soon turned to Arabic
plays. By virtue of his foreign training which
dictated the kind of plays he chose and his
exaggerated acting style he helped to move
Arab theatre away from its traditional popu¬
lar audience to a more cultivated and more
intellectual public.
For much of the first half of the twentieth
century there were two types of play in Arab
theatre. On the one hand therewere "serious"
literary translations of Western plays and orig¬
inal Arabic "literary" compositions; on the
other therewere the situation comedies, farces
and musicals which constituted the daily fare
of the commercial theatre. With a few excep¬
tions, notably Tewfik Al Hakim, there was
very little creative talent at work in Arab the¬
atre by the mid-1950s. Much had been
achieved, however, particularly in Egypt, where
a Higher Institute for Dramatic Art and a
national theatre company had been established.
The call ofmodernity
A new era in the history of modern Arab
drama began in the late 1950s with the devel¬
opment of a type of communal drama which
could contribute to the wider socio-political
A dramatization of Crime and
Punishment, based on Fyodor
Dostoyevsky's novel, directed
by Farid Al Zahiri (Yemen).
awakening. The entire Arab world was
responding to the call of modernity by devel¬
oping its academic and cultural institutions,
interacting with the outside world and react¬
ing to its challenges.
The fifth of June 1967, marking defeat in
the Six-Day War, brought home to many Arabs
the need for political stability and transparency,
democracy, dialogue and debate, objective analy¬
sis and freedom from rhetoric. It was thought
that drama could contribute to this process by
drawing on and contributing to national iden¬
tity, without however excluding foreign cul¬
tural influences. Direct imitation of Western
plays was to be shunned, but translation was
encouraged and assimilation promoted.
In countries such as Egypt, Syria, Lebanon
and Iraq, specialist drama magazines were
started, national or state-supported theatres
were promoted and national theatre compa¬
nies formed. Artistes were sent abroad for train¬
ing and foreign troupes were warmly welcomed.
In the universities student drama throve. The
coming of television brought performers an
additional source of income which further con¬
solidated their financial and social status. Cul¬
tural co-operation agreements with other coun¬
tries, socialist countries in particular, opened
important venues for the study of such arts as
puppetry, ballet, folk dance, music, acting,
directing and film-making. Altogether, the
1960s were a time of intense activity in the per¬
forming arts not only in Egypt but practically
everywhere else in the Arab world.
Representative figures of the effervescence
of the 1950s and 1960s included Nu'man
Ashur, Yusuf Idris, Alfred Farag, Mikhail
Roman and Mahmoud Dyab, all playwrights
working in Egypt; Roger Assaf and Nidal
Ashkar (back from France and England respec¬
tively), Yacoub Shadrawi (back fom Moscow)
and the Rahbani brothers (pioneers of the
operetta revival in Lebanon and the Arab
world) in Lebanon; Saadalla Wannous (back
from Cairo and Paris) and Rafiq Sabban (back
fom Paris) in Syria and Yusuf El Ani in Iraq.
Audienceparticipation
They all believed in the theatre as a moral and
political force and shared a determination to
produce good theatre based on tradition with¬
out being inward-looking. Yusuf Idris led the
call for "an Egyptian theatre", arguing that
most of the plays produced were Egyptian in
dress, dialogue, characters and situations but
Western in structure and style. He advocated a
return to AlSamer, that combination of one-
man chorus, narrator, entertainer and Shake¬
spearean fool, who worked alone or with one
assistant and perhaps a dancer, drawing on the
circle of onlookers around him.
THE UNESCO lOU RI ER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Al Samer, Idris argued, always achieved the¬
atricality, meaning the active participation in
the action of all the people present, actors and
audience alike. "If the action involves dancing, all
must dance; if it involves singing, all must sing.
Sender and receiver, actor and audience, must
become one; both sending and receiving". The
performance should be based on a text but
should allow for much improvisation on the
part of both cast and audience. Breaking through
the barrier between stage and audience is a feature
of ancient Egyptian and Mesopotamian rites,
classical Greek theatre, of the age of Shakespeare
and of course of contemporary European and
Eastern theatre. Idris knew this but did not
seek to use audience participation as a mere tech¬
nique or device; he wanted it to permeate the
whole performance, expressing the collective
folly, or wisdom, of the community.
A few years after Idris had put forward his
theory about Al Samer and put it into prac¬
tice in Al Farafir, Saadalla Wannous (1940-
1997) published his Manifestos for a New
Arab Theatre in which he, like Idris, but per¬
haps more forcefully, put the emphasis on the
public and the relationship between the pub¬
lic and the stage. The ultimate aim of a per¬
formance, he wrote, is to make us "come out
of our skin, unite in one group, and become
aware of our common destiny as a group, and
of the laws governing that destiny."
A chaque parfum, une fleur,
written and directed by
Rida Drira (Tunisia). Wannous translated his ideas into a play,
An Evening Entertainment for the Fifth of
June, that was a major landmark in his career. In
this play the line between actors and audience
gradually disappears until the director/actor
shouts in fear and consternation "what is all
this leading to? Has the theatre turned into a
public square or what?" This is exactly what
Wannous wanted: the theatre turns into a pub¬
lic square regardless of the consequences, which,
in the play, are the detention by the authorities
of the entire audience.
Wannous used the play-within-a-play
device in several of his later works, often in
conjunction with the device of the café story
teller. He explored history simultaneously
through the eyes of narrators and listeners,
who are the audience both within and out¬
side the play-within-thc play. He wanted to
generate this kind of dialogue in what he called
the theatre of politicization, which is in many
respects both total theatre and theatre as enter¬
tainment.
Much of what Wannous advocates may
echo Brecht, Piscator, Peter Brook or Peter
Weiss, but much of what he practised is also
reminiscent of the work of the three major
pioneers, Al Naqqash, Al Qabbani and Sannu'.
Wannous repeatedly calls on us to turn to
them since he feels they represent an outward-
looking approach to theatre.
THE UNESCO ÇoURIEI NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The theatre of the oppressed
BY AUGUSTO BOAL
Above, scene from a street
theatre show staged by the Luz
de la Luna company in Bogotá
(Colombia).
I Some people do theatre because it's their
I job, their craft or their calling. But all
men and women on Earth arc a theatre in
themselves. It's second nature to them.
In every one of us there's an actor some¬
one who acts and a spectator, who watches
the actor acting. We have the ability to watch
ourselves doing things. The other animals,
even in front of a mirror, don't recognize their
own reflection, so don't use it to improve
their own appearance. Cats don't look at them¬
selves in a mirror to smooth their whiskers
and lions don't comb their manes in front of
one. But we humans, even without mirrors,
can watch ourselves watching.
But we aren't content, any of us, to be just
actors and spectators of ourselves. We also
write our own scripts for every scene we are
involved in. We are in charge of the wardrobe
of costumes to be worn wherever we are (at
home, at work, during time off). We are also
the directors who stage our own actions.
So every human being is a miniature theatre.
The "theatre of the oppressed" is based on
this simple notion of elementary theatre,
where everyone is involved, whether trained
for it or not.
On stage, actors experience passions and
emotions just as wc do in real life. And we, in real
life, express ideas and feelings through dialogue,
movements and voice intonations, just like
actors. With one difference: the actor on stage is
aware of using theatrical language whereas wc
use language without this awareness (which is
why we aren't so good at using it).
Everybody, not just orators, is capable of
speaking. If we don't know how to swim in an
Olympic swimming pool, we can all splash
12 ) QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The conviction that there is an actor in each of us
is the driving force behind a form of drama that
seeks to awaken consciences and change lives
about in the bath. We have all kicked a football
around our backyards, even if we haven't
played at Wembley or Maracaná.
Some sports engulf entire nations like
football in Brazil, baseball in the United States
and table tennis in China but only some
athletes attain excellence. So it is with the the¬
atre. There are professionals, but everyone can,
and should, take part.
First steps
The theatre of the oppressed springs from
these basic ideas. It was born some years ago in
Brazil and elsewhere in Latin America when
military dictators first censored plays and
shows and then cracked down on theatre com¬
panies and actors.
At the time, I was running the Arena The¬
atre of Sào Paulo. They began by telling us
what plays wc should put on. The ones we
chose were all either banned or censored. Then
wc lost the theatre itself when they forced us
to make pointless alterations to it which wc
couldn't afford.
Each time, wc responded by devising new
kinds of activity. Wc ended up doing street
theatre and staging plays in trade union halls, A Salvadorian theatre group
in a play about domestic
violence (1996).
schools and churches. We had no money, so wc
had to do without scenery and costumes. We
acted in ordinary clothes.
In the end, we lost everything when the
police banned us from playing anywhere at
all. It was only then, when wc had neither the¬
atre, repertoire, scenery, costumes nor stars,
that we discovered the essential thing. Face-
to-face with our audiences, we realized how
like them we were, and also how different.
Wc had lost the rings on our fingers, but
not our fingers; our costumes but not our
bodies; our illusions but not our dreams. We
were like our audiences because we were human
beings like them. But we were also different
because we were specialists in a craft. We could
help the public make use of our craft.
This is how the first version of the Theatre
of the Oppressed was born. Wc called it
"Newspaper Theatre". We invented and devel¬
oped thirteen ways of turning newspaper arti¬
cles (or any other apparently non-dramatic
material) into plays. Then we went to our
audiences to tell them what we'd learned and
to help them write and produce their own
plays from texts they chose themselves.
For the first time, we were teaching our
public the "means of production" instead of
presenting them with a finished product. Wc
weren't telling them "what to do" but "how
to do it".
After we had set up dozens of popular
groups, wc had to stop because the dictator¬
ship was becoming harsher and harsher. After
many incidents, I had to leave the country
myself.
Fact orfiction?
The next version of Theatre of the Oppressed
surfaced in Argentina in 1971 and was called
"invisible theatre." The "El Machete" troupe
that I led put together a play about hunger
which was to take place, ironically, in a restau¬
rant. The script, a joint effort, was ready and
the production seemed OK. At first we wanted
to stage it in the street, but Brazilian friends
warned us. Argentina was going through a dif¬
ficult transition to democracy and as a Brazil¬
ian, I risked getting deported and handed over
to the Brazilian police.
In the end, my actors insisted that I should
take part in the show. One of them suggested
doing the play in a restaurant and having the
actors come in incognito as if they were genuine
> QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1 997 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
customers and without revealing that it was
part of a play. I would go in before the others
and sit at a table in a quiet corner to eat my
steak. The actors would then come in and the
various scenes would follow. There was one
problem though. The play involved two wait¬
ers and a maître d'hôtel who would have to be
played by actors. How would the real waiters
and maître d'hôtel react to that?
We began the play while the other cus¬
tomers were eating and chatting. To our sur¬
prise and delight, at the very moment the
actors were supposed to speak, a real waiter
and the maître d'hôtel himself stepped up to
say almost exactly the words in our script.
We were fascinated by this experience where
Coup de poing sur la pointe du
couteau, a play written and
staged by Augusto Boat in
Paris in 1980.
fiction mingled with reality and became just as
real, at the same time as reality became a kind
of fiction. But what worried me was that the
audience took part in the action without real¬
ising they were in a play which itself was inside
a piece of reality. So where exactly were they, in
fiction or reality? For them, how far was fic¬
tion real and reality fictional?
Spectators on stage
I continued doing this kind of theatre in sev¬
eral countries, always very successfully but
always with some anxiety and also regret that
it could not be done in an open manner.
We entered a new phase in Chaclacayo, Peru ,
where we devised "Forum Theatre" as part of
the Alfin integrated literacy programme which
was based on the ideas of Paulo Freiré. I was
promoting literacy through the theatre. Oth¬
ers did it through film, silk-screen printing,
local languages or Spanish.
It was here that we first came up with a
play in which the main character didn't know
what he was supposed to do or else made
wrong or unsuitable decisions. So I asked the
audience what they would have done instead.
There was a lot of response. So I suggested
doing the play again with the same script, with
the addition that if a member of the audience
wanted to change something, they could stop
the play there and then. The person would
then take over from the actor and instead of
Of THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Opposite page, Augusto Boal
(centre) directs a workshop.
Right, warming up the
audience before a performance
(1980s).
just speaking, could explain his or her idea in
dramatic form.
So the audience could use the same stage
language as the actors to convey what they
thought, what they wanted and dreamt about,
and what they proposed. Everyone, freely and
knowingly, would be "talking theatre".
"Forum Theatre" has become the most pop¬
ular version of the Theatre of the Oppressed. At
the eighth International Festival of the Theatre
of the Oppressed, recently organized by the
Mixed Co. in Toronto (Canada), as well as at an
earlier festival put on in Rio de Janeiro by the
Centre for the Theatre of the Oppressed there,
more than thirty countries were represented
by theatre groups or "professional" users of
the Theatre of the Oppressed, such as teachers,
psychotherapists and social workers.
Internalized oppression
Later on, in exile in Europe, I came across
forms of oppression more insidious than
those in Latin America. My European friends
told me of the oppression of feeling empty
inside, of being unable to communicate, of
being afraid of the future. At first I didn't
take these kinds of problems seriously. Then
I found that the suicide rate in the richest
countries was far higher than in Latin Amer¬
ica, and understood that if someone chose
death rather than loneliness, it was a kind of
oppression as real as any other.
At the Centre for the Theatre of the
Oppressed in Paris, over two years, Cecilia
Thumim and I developed elaborate ways of
expressing internalized oppressions, the ones
we carry around inside ourselves. As the fif¬
teenth-century Portuguese poet Sá de Miranda
put it, "my biggest enemy is the one inside
me, the one I carry in the core of my being."
When I got back to Brazil, I was elected a
Vereador (city councillor) in Rio de Janeiro.
I hired all the staff of my Theatre of the
Oppressed centre, and throughout my four-
year term wc worked with needy communities
(favelas), trade unions, schools, neighbour¬
hood associations and old people's groups,
landless peasants, black students, street chil¬
dren, Aids sufferers and others to create a sort
of "legislative theatre".
We helped our audiences-cum-playwrights
to write and produce their own plays, first in
their own communities and then as part of
"dialogues" between communities, so that
everyone could sec the oppression others suf¬
fered, and not just their own. Three times a
year, we put on an outdoor festival to let the
public know about us and give them a chance
to take part in our "forum" shows.
For each show, one of us wrote a proposal
which was sent to the "city council" where it
was studied by our lawyers. Sometimes, the
solution they recommended was an approach to
the mayor's office or else a street event. Or our
THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1 997
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
team would draft a law which I would present
to the real city council.
An opportunity for dialogue
In all, we presented about fifty proposed laws,
all of which came from the grassroots. They
were about protecting old people, children,
handicapped people and witnesses to crimes
(to put an end to impunity, one of the
scourges of Brazilian society), as well as mea¬
sures against racism and all other forms of dis¬
crimination.
Thirteen of them were taken up by the
council and became laws. So thirteen times we
managed to make wishes come true, in the
form of laws now in force all over Rio.
Why is the Theatre of the Oppressed so
amazingly successful? First, we don't try to
expound a message or a revealed truth. We try
to ask the right questions instead of giving
what wc think are the right answers. Next, we
offer a simple system of exercises, games and
methods which anyone can handle but which
can also be used for very complicated things
like psychotherapeutic introspection. Thirdly,
we create an opportunity for freedom which
produces dialogue. All of us want to talk with
people, to know their views and have the
chance to express our own.
We know our identity is the result of what
we are, but also of what others are and of what
we are not. I am a man because there arc women,
white because there arc black people, a father
because I have children. Pluralism, differences
and diversity are at the core of our existence.
Because of them, we know who wc arc
So the Theatre of the Oppressed is neither
a closed dialogue with itself nor a collection of
rules and obligations. It's a language. As such, it
involves all areas of human activity, not just
politics. It concerns teaching the young, psy¬
chotherapy, literacy and even the theatre itself.
In 1997, 1 shall be having a new experience in
Stratford-upon-Avon in England. With the
Royal Shakespeare Company and using the
play Hamlet, we arc going to see if we can apply
the psychotherapeutic methods described in
my book The Rainbow of Desire to helping
the actors get to grips with their roles.
This fascinating experiment has a great sym¬
bolic meaning for me. It means official recog¬
nition (for Shakespeare, I don't know how
much more official you can get than the Royal
Shakespeare Company) that the Theatre of
the Oppressed is truly theatre.
W THE UNESCO CpURIERB NOVEMBER 1997
FACT FILE
THE INTERNATIONAL
THEATRE INSTITUTE
Secretary General: André-Louis Perinetti
Unesco, lrue Miollis
75732 Paris Cedex 15, France
Tel: (33) (0)1 45 68 26 50
Fax: (33) (0)1 45 66 50 40
E-mail: secretariat@iti-worldwlde.org
Internet address: http://iti-worldwide.org
The International Theatre Institute, an interna¬
tional non-governmental organization (NGO), was
founded in 1948 by Unesco and the international
theatre community. It has maintained formal asso¬
ciate relations with Unesco since 1996.
Structure:
ITI today includes 95 national and associate Cen¬
tres worldwide. A Centre comprises professionals
active in the theatre life of the country and rep¬
resentative of all branches of the performing arts.
Its activities are conducted both on a national and
international level. The Institute has 7 Commit¬
tees each with its own board and programme
activities: Dance, Music Theatre, Playwrights, The¬
atre Education, Communication, Cultural Identity
& Development and Dramatic Theatre.
The Institute is run by an Executive Committee
composed of 14 elected members and 3 mem¬
bers co-opted following its biennial Congress, and
by an elected Secretary General. The General
Secretariat is based at Unesco headquarters in
Paris. Two regional bodies have been set up, in
Africa and Latin America, as well as a Documen¬
tation Centre and Archive Centre for Asia
(Bangladesh) and an Interregional Liaison Bureau
for the national Centres of the Mediterranean
region (Tunisia). The Albert Botbol University of the
Theatre of Nations has two permanent bases, one
in Tunisia and the other in Venezuela.
Objectives:
> To promote international exchange of knowl¬
edge and practice in the performing arts.
> To stimulate creation and increase co-operation
among theatre people.
> To increase public awareness of the need to
take artistic creation into consideration in the
domain of development.
> To deepen mutual understanding, thus con¬
tributing to the consolidation of peace and friend¬
ship between peoples.
> To join in the defence of the ideals and aims of
Unesco.
> To combat all forms of racism or social and polit¬
ical discrimination.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
27th ITI World
Congress
ITI contributes to fulfilling its own and Unesco's
goals through a range of activities, including sym¬
posia, conferences, workshops, training courses,
publications and the diffusion of international
information concerning theatre and through var¬
ious international events.
Hosted by the Korean ITI Centre, the 27th
World Congress of ITI took place in Seoul from 14
to 20 September 1997 and included the following
events:
> The International Festival of Higher Education
Theatre Institutes. Eleven international and six
Korean schools gave performances based on the
theme "Tradition and Experiment: What does the¬
atre seek to do in the 21st Century?"
> An International Production of King Lear.
Planned and organized by ITI/Unesco's New The¬
atre Project Group, this production of Shake¬
speare's play featured actors from Hungary, Ger¬
many, Japan, Korea and the United States and
was staged by the Korean director Jeong-Ok Kim.
The performances given in Seoul marked the start
of an international tour.
Regular
International
Activities
World Theatre Day, 27 March
World Theatre Day, which was created in 1961,
is celebrated annually by ITI Centres. Each year a
noted theatre personality or an outstanding fig¬
ure from another field is invited to share his or
her reflections on theatre and peace between peo¬
ples. This "International Message" is translated
into more than 20 languages, read to spectators
before performances in theatres throughout the
world, printed in newspapers and broadcast In
the audio-visual media. World Theatre Day also
features events ranging from small-scale demon¬
strations to big popular celebrations. In
Bangladesh, for example, the entire theatre com¬
munity joins in World Theatre Day celebrations,
as more than 1,000 actors and actresses parade
through the streets of Dhaka in theatre costumes.
Theatre exhibitions are organized, and in the
evening there is a lecture on theatre in
Bangladesh and performances by the country's
theatre companies.
The Albert Botbol University
of the Theatre of Nations
The University of the Theatre of Nations (UTN),
which has borne the name of its first director,
Albert Botbol, since 1993, was founded in Paris
in 1961 in connection with the "Theatre of
Nations". Since 1984 the UTN has been itinerant,
organizing each year with UNESCO's support a
session on a theme relating to the culture of the
host country. As a structure for exchanges
between young professionals all over the world, its
basic principles are inter-disciplinanty, interna¬
tional exchange, encounters between cultures,
the development of joint projects, the presentation
of work and mobility of activities.
The Theatre of Nations
Based in Paris until 1972, the Theatre of Nations
became an itinerant international festival in 1975.
The goals it pursues are those of quality, plurality
and diversity in contemporary theatre. Its orga¬
nizers work under the aegis of the ITI National Cen¬
tre of the country in which the event is taking place.
In September 1997, the "Theatre of Nations
Seoul-Kyonggi, 1997" included 5 separate but
interrelated events that took place in Seoul (Rep.
of Korea) and in the province of Kyonggi: the Inter¬
national Theatre Festival (some 15 international
productions); the BeSeTo (Beijing, Seoul, Tokyo)
Festival where plays from various Asian countries
were performed; an Open Air Theatre Festival
which presented some twenty productions (10
international and 10 Korean) on the theme of
"Nature, human beings, environment"; and the
Seoul Theatre Festival, which is celebrating its
twentieth anniversary in 1997.
For further information:
Theatre of Nations
2nd Floor, Juho Building
46-3 Myungryun-dong
Jongro-ku, Seoul 110-521
Republic of Korea
Tel: (82) (2) 744 8025 or 3673 2563-6
Fax: (82) (2) 745 7924
E-mail: TN@Theatre.or.kr
Internet address: http://www.theatre.or.kr
Bibliography
ITI Publications
Sews from the ITI Secretariat (quarterly, in Eng¬
lish and French)
The World of Theatre, 5th ed., 1997 (biennial, In
English and French), features articles from more
than 50 countries on theatre productions and
recent developments during the last two theatre
seasons, plus a calendar of main theatre events
from 1995 to 1997.
World Theatre Directory, 4th ed., 1997 (biennial,
bilingual English and French), a compilation by
country of national theatre profiles, ITI centres,
main theatres, festivals, publications, national
organizations and educational and research insti¬
tutions in the field of the performing arts.
Other publications
World Encyclopedia of Contemporary Theatre.
Europe (1994, vol. 1), The Americas (1996, vol.
2), Africa (1997, vol. 3). Forthcoming: The Arab
World[w\. 4), As/a/Ocean/a(vol. 5). A project of
ITI, FIRT, CIAT, SIBMAS with the support of Unesco
and the World Decade for Cultural Development.
Published by Routledge, 11 New Fetter Lane, Lon¬
don EC4P 4EE, United Kingdom. Tel: (44) (0)171-
583 9855. Fax: (44) (0)171-842 2307
Most ITI Centres and Committees also have
their own publications. For further information,
please contact ITI.
Main international
events in 1998
M 27 March
World Theatre Day
End of June
celebration of the 50th Anniversary of ITI,
Prague (Czech Republic)
27 June-20 July
Theatre of Nations, Zurich-Lausanne
(Switzerland)
End of June-beginning of July
International Festival of Higher Education
Theatre Schools (ISTRAPOLITANA 98),
Bratislava (Slovakia)
September
Symposium and Meeting of Higher Education
Theatre Schools on Ancient Greek Drama,
Nicosia (Cyprus)
24-31 October
Gth International Theatre and Puppet Festival
of Ouagadougou (Burkina Faso)
Last quarter
Regional Meeting of African Centres of ITI,
Ouagadougou (Burkina Faso)
Last quarter
BeSeTo Festival 1998 in Tokyo (Japan).
December
Regional Meeting of the Latin American and
Caribbean Centres of ITI, Havana (Cuba)
10-14 December
6th International Music Theatre Workshop,
Düsseldorf (Germany)
Some useful
websites
International Amateur Theatre Association
(IATA)
http://home2.inet.tele.dk/aitaiata
International Federation for Theatre Research
(IFTR)
http://www.arts.gla.ac.uk/tfts/iftr/home.html
International Society of Libraries and
Museums for the Performing Arts (SIBMAS)
http://www.let.uva.nl/vg/sibmas.html
International Organization of Scenographers,
Theatre Architects and Technicians (OISTAT)
http://www.oistat.nl
) Çç>wTHE UNESCO (OURIIR \OVEMBCR I9Q7 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
commentary
I
Federico Mayor
Science education and
sustainable development
The eve of a new millennium is an appropriate moment for
UNESCO and other international organizations to reflect on
their missions and the challenges that lie ahead.
Education for all remains the foundation for the achieve¬
ment of sustainable human development. Basic education will
continue to be an absolute priority, as it forms the essential first
step towards further learning and plays a critical role in the
shaping of values and the development of other necessary life
skills. For this reason we must ensure that we enter the next mil¬
lennium equipped and determined to "reach the unreached"
the world's 850 million adult illiterates and the over 200 million
children still deprived of the right to education.
Education means mastering one's own destiny; it means
personal sovereignty. It is the key to a genuine participatory
democracy, which is closely related to development and peace.
It is not just about knowledge; it is also about learning to do,
learning to be and above all learning to live together. Educa¬
tion and teachers have an ethical function that must never be for¬
gotten. In this connection, I should like to insist that while a
market economy may be acceptable, a market society most cer¬
tainly is not. What matters is not whether the market is free, but
whether/?eo/>/e are free.
A continuing process
Education can no longer be regarded as a one-chance affair. It
must be seen as a continuing process whereby people are offered
learning opportunities at a number of times throughout their
lives. This "lifelong" and "life-wide" education for all demands
the diversification and expansion of structures, and a better
linkage between general and vocational education. It also implies
the development of alternative educational opportunities and
delivery systems, both formal and informal.
The role and functions of higher education systems and
institutions need to be re-examined in the light of the pro¬
found transformations occurring in society today. Too often,
the model of higher education we sec in both the developing and
industrialized countries involves an acceptance of old, inap-
r1* THCUNESCO l^OURIERB NOVEMBER 199/
propriate models that have remained largely impermeable to
economic, cultural and social needs. We need also to reflect on
Article 26.1 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
which says that "higher education shall be equally accessible
to all on the basis of merit". Yes, merit and merit alone must
be the criterion; and once this criterion is satisfied, there should
be no limits of means, age or sex to access. Higher education
must be universally available throughout life to all those who
can benefit from it.
Secondary education must be treated as a level in its own
right, not simply a means to placing students at the door of the
university. Some of the most crucial needs in the educational sys¬
tem as a whole involve summoning individuals of all ages to such
modestly paid but highly important work as primary and sec¬
ondary school teaching. Secondary education must be recognized
as pivotal to any education system.
A new strategy for science education
Science education is a key component of all education systems.
The unprecedented growth in scientific knowledge and the dra¬
matically increased complexity of this knowledge, together
with an ever-increasing demand for high quality, constitute a
challenge for science educators at all levels. How to introduce sci¬
ence and its breathtaking advances into limited curricula frame¬
works, what should be the correct balance between education
in the basic sciences and the environment, and the intercon¬
nection of science education with education in technology
these are just some of the questions for which answers need to
be found. Science education can, of course, only be satisfac¬
tory if account is taken of the cultural background and ethical
implications of scientific progress.
The universities bear the great intellectual responsibility of
identifying new strategies to promote science education and
science teacher training, as well as setting and maintaining high
professional standards in education for scientific research. Intro¬
ducing new information technologies in science education,
updating basic and specialized university courses, as well as
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
modernizing university laboratories remain a pressing need
and a challenge for inter-university co-operation at the national,
regional and international levels.
Action needs to be taken to build university science educa¬
tion in the developing and least developed countries. I am con¬
fident that the world scientific community would gladly com¬
mit itself to such action. UNESCO will spare no efforts in
developing North-South co-operation via inter-university net¬
worksas in the UNITWIN and Unesco Chairs programme.
I believe that UNESCO and the Third World Academy of Sciences
are natural partners in such an endeavour.
Science today is at a turning point. All countries are having
to face important decisions in this field. The richer nations are
being required to rethink their science and technology priori¬
ties in the face of economic constraints and new political and eth¬
ical challenges, whilst developing countries are striving to build
up the critical capacity necessary for effective science teaching and
research leading to sustainable development.
If science alone is not capable of responding to people's aspi¬
rations for a better life, it has shown itself to be one of the major
driving forces behind development. And yet this fact and its
implications are still underestimated by decision-makers and
politicians seeking short-term success and benefits. Short-ter-
mism in policy-making naturally involves dangers for the basic
sciences. I believe that a healthy, productive scientific community
is dependent upon the pursuit of basic research. We must ensure
that the basic sciences are pursued by all nations, and that the com¬
mon stock of fundamental knowledge is shared by all.
Haves and have-nots
Another feature of the sciences today is the continuing asym¬
metry in the distribution of scientific research capacity world¬
wide. The developing countries are responsible for a mere 10 per
cent of research and development, whilst the member coun¬
tries of the Organization for Economic Co-operation and
Development (OECD) can claim 85 per cent. The world is still
divided between the haves and the have-nots.
Each country's capacity to move towards sustainable human
development depends on the existence of a critical mass of
skilled human resources in the many scientific, technical and pro¬
fessional fields needed for addressing complex environment,
resources and development issues. Training of the right kind and
number of scientists, experts, technicians and educational per¬
sonnel is urgently needed. Unesco has highlighted a number
of key problems within the context of the vicious circle of low
human and capital investment/low productive returns in which
so many developing countries are locked.
The first of these problems concerns the lack of "critical
mass" at national level. Despite considerable efforts, many
developing countries do not yet have sufficient trained per¬
sonnel for sustainable development of their natural resources
and suffer from a shortage of training facilities, especially for
preparing teams of specialists to conduct studies and research
useful for decision-making. The second problem is that estab¬
lished institutions and programmes may be of limited rele
vance to local conditions, with the result that many trainees in
the developing world receive an education that has little bear¬
ing on their countries' social and economic needs. A third prob¬
lem is lack of continuity. Students who return home with
skills inappropriate to their countries' needs often end up aban¬
doning their professional fields for other pursuits, such as
business or government.
Another challenge for developing and industrialized coun¬
tries alike is that nature does not respect the frontiers of scien¬
tific disciplines. Interdisciplinarity is required to study nat¬
ural phenomena in all their complexity. And yet most current
training programmes are sectoral or disciplinary and do not
address the complex interactions between people, resources,
environment and development.
All UNESCO's intergovernmental scientific programmes
dealing with freshwater, oceanography, coastal and marine sci¬
ences, the earth sciences, and particularly land resources include
a major component on training precisely oriented in this direc¬
tion. The goal of the recently launched UNESCO-Cousteau
ecotcchnology programme is to identify, promote, and mul¬
tiply transdisciplinary university efforts through financial
assistance and networking and through the establishment of
UNESCO-Cousteau Ecotcchnology Chairs. Here, one of the
basic tasks is to ensure that in villages and municipalities there
are people with the knowledge and motivation to prescribe
and perform all the "ccojobs" that are vital to the safeguarding
of our environment.
Water and food security
Access to water is considered a basic human right, but is there
and will there be enough water to go round in future? Can
water be considered a free commodity which is available in
unlimited quantities? The answer has to be no. Clearly, fresh
water is although renewable a very limited and vulnerable
resource. In my view water is going to be one of the major
issues of the twenty-first century. Wc need to practise greater
sharing of knowledge and resources in this field. My dream is
to see the channelling of water from places where it is plentiful
to others where it is scarce, together with the promotion
through education of new attitudes to water, awareness of how
precious a shared commodity it is.
The issue of food security will be ever-present in the first
decades of the new century. The application of sound scien¬
tific knowledge will be an important factor in attaining sus¬
tainable food production, based on enhanced agricultural pro¬
ductivity, the conservation and management of natural
resources, the protection of the environment, and the stabi¬
lization of world population. But once again the solution will
be ethical the greater sharing of knowledge and resources.
We must work together at the international and national lev¬
els to achieve a consensus among governments, the scientific
community and the public at large on the importance and the role
of science for the development of societies and the well-being of
humankind. Only in this way can a solid foundation be laid for
sustainable and equitable human development.
1 Ç)l!RI ERB NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Greenwatch Seaweed
| at your
service
BY FRANCE BEQUETTE
For many people seaweeds
are simply plants that grow
in water. This was the accepted
definition until the eighteenth cen¬
tury. They were regarded as "not
proper plants" because they liad
neither flowers nor seeds. Today,
this definition is out of dale. A sea¬
weed or alga may be cither veg¬
etable or animal, thrive in water or
on land and interest zoologists as
much as botanists.
Until the cud of the 1950s,
explains Bruno de Reviers, senior
lecturer at Franco's Natural His¬
tory Museum, scientists usually
classified living things as either ani¬
mal or vegetable. Seaweeds arc in
fact both. Says Reviers: "Sea¬
weeds aren't simple, they're a bun¬
dle of organisms drawn from very
différent groups, sometimes quite
philogenelically distant, that is,
without direct links."
The overall view of the world
of living things is changing very
quickly. The vegetable kingdom
was traditionally divided into thal¬
lophytes and cormophytes. The
former (from the Greek word for a
shoot, thallos) are "simple" (some¬
times called "inferior") vegetation,
without stems, leaves, roots or vein
systems. They included seaweed,
mushrooms, lichens, mosses and
even bacteria. Cormophytes (from
the Greek for stem, kormos) have
stems, roots and flowers.
So how were vegetables distin¬
guished from animals? By the abil¬
ity of animals to move, something
vegetables cannot do. But things get
complicated when some animals,
like sea anemones or coral, slay in
one spot, while some microscopic
seaweeds move about, like Spir¬
illum (a blue seaweed) or diatoms
(brown planktonic seaweed).
Another difference is that ve<r-
etables synthesize living matter by
using the energy of liglit through
photosynthesis, while animals trap
and cat prey. But like carnivorous
plants, some seaweeds can trap
prey too and feed off organic male-
rial as well. To cover this com¬
plexity, biologists now offer five or
moro categories, and fan-like
Nets for
commercial
seaweed farming,
Okinawa (Japan).
genetic lineages which take bet¬
ter account of the links between
species.
A LONG HISTORY
AND A COMPOSITE FAMILY
Seaweed is everywhere on land,
in the sea, in fresh or salty water,
on our plates, in the pharmacist's
cupboard, in water purification
plants and even sometimes in our
lungs. Ilowmany kinds are there?
Estimates range from 20,000 to
130,000 species, but the real fig¬
ure is probably around 45,000.
The very first marine plant
forms equipped with chlorophyll
which appeared on Earth were
really just bacteria. They were
blue, not green, because of the
extra pigments associated with the
chlorophyll. These pigments
enable energy to be drawn from
light, even when the rays received
by the chlorophyll and necessary
for photosynthesis pass through
water. The best-known blue sea¬
weed is Spirulina, found in lakes in
North Africa, Chad, Mexico,
Florida and the Bahamas. It is tra¬
ditionally eaten in biscuit form and
is cultivated these days in Viet
Nam and Israel.
To grasp this diversity, we have
to go back to the dawn of time.
Oxygen is produced by the photo¬
synthesis of blue seaweed. The
ozonelayerforms. About 700 mil-
THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
lion years ago, there is a great
burst of life and species multiply
and diverge. Think of a crown with
branches growing out from it. The
blue seaweeds are very far away
from the green ones, which in turn
have no connection with the brown
or red seaweeds. When the
branches multiply, a link develops
between green seaweed, ferns and
mosses, and between dinoph)te
seaweed and the plasmodium par¬
asite, which transmits malaria.
The common ancestors of some
green seaweeds gradually emerge
from the water and adapt to life
in air. Oddly, some later return to
living under water. Eel grass, for
example, which serves as a nurs¬
ery for young fish, actually flow¬
ers and reproduces through seeds.
Like seaweed it can take in nutri¬
tion directly through its leaves,
instead of its roots.
Brown seaweeds are microscopic
like diatoms or huge like giant
kelps, which grow to a length of 50
metres or more. They are found
anywhere from the surface to 150
metres down. Dinofiagellates are
simile-cell organisms which form
"red seas" and can secrete poisons.
Some of these poisons, which arc
100,000 times stronger than
cocaine for example, attack the
human nervous system and can
destroy it. This is what happens in
the ca.-e of ciguatera, a tropical dis-
Giant kelp
[Laminaria
macrocystis),
which may attain
a length of up to
60 metres.
case caught from fish which have
eaten poisonous seaweed (see "Nat¬
ural Disasters: Be Prepared!"
llMiSCO Courier, October 1997).
THE USES OF SEAWEED
Alvaro Israel, of the Israeli
National Institute in Haifa, has
identified 107 types and 493 vari¬
eties of seaweed used by human
beings. Most are grown and con¬
sumed in the Far East and the
Pacific in accordance with long tra¬
ditions. In Korea, for example,
brown seaweed was found in the
10,000-ycar-old remains of meals
in tombs at the Kiong-Lu burial
grounds. In fourth-century Japan,
the imperial court taxed the con¬
sumption of nori (Porphyru),
wakamc (Undurici) and konbu
(Laminaria). Since then, the
national dish of sushi (rice and raw
fish) has been served with nori.
In the West, famine in the fif¬
teenth century led people to eat
seaweed, which is why it was dis¬
dained for so long in this part of the
world. The Chinese eat the most
seaweed these days 20 kg a head
every year followed by the Kore¬
ans and the Japanese, with 13.4
kg. About 60 varieties of brown and
red seaweed are eaten in the forms
of vegetables, pâté, jam, soup,
bread or beverages. In the Pacific,
delicious little "grapes"' of eaulerpa
are served up as salads.
At the Seaweed Research and
De\ clopinent Centre (CEVA), part
of the French Research Institute
for the Use of the Sea (IFREMER),
Joel Fleurence is looking into the
nutritional value of seaweeds.
"Their make-up," Ik; says, "varies
according to the species, the sea¬
son, the surroundings, and geo¬
graphical and physiological factors."
Edible seaweeds are mostly
made iqi of carbohydrates com¬
plex sugars and dietary fibres.
Brown seaweeds contain the least
protein from 5 to 15% of their
dr) weight but red seaweeds like
Palmaria and Porphyra teñera
have about 47% and rival soya
(35%). They are very low in fats
and contain mineral salts and trace
elements such as magnesium,
arsenic, copper, lithium, sulphur
and zinc. They also have a full range
of vitamins, especially vitamin A,
A commercial
seaweed farm
laboratory in
Morbihan
(western France).
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
lack of which can lead to blindness.
Unfortunately they tend to disap¬
pear with drying or cooking, par¬
ticularly vitamin C.
From seaweed, industry gets
alginates and carrageens, valuable
additives which feature in much
of our food, for example, stabiliz¬
ing sauces and making dairy prod¬
ucts creamy. They hide behind the
European Union code names of
E400to407.
ENDLESS POSSIBILITIES
But not just any seaweed can be
harvested, any time or anywhere,
since seaweeds easily absorb pol¬
lutants like mercury. They are
increasingly being cultivated in
specially chosen and protected
places. In Asia, the 530,000
hectares of seaweeds farmed by
250,000 family businesses provide
950,000 jobs. According to the
Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion of the United Nations (FAO),
7,637,000 tonnes of fresh seaweed
were harvested in 1991, 90% of it
cultivated.
The uses of seaweed seem end¬
less. Do you want to make cherries
without cherry flesh? Make your
plants grow? Mop up urine in
babies' nappies? Have waterproof
umbrellas or mackintoshes? Make
plastic floors and wood shine with¬
out polishing them? Make dental
impressions without risk of burning
the patient? Have photographic
film where the gelatine doesn't
melt in the heat? Or put out forest
fires by dropping thick chemicals
from fire lighting planes? Biologists
think a lot more research should
be done into seaweed, especially
for food purposes, when the world
is going hungry and seaweed is
everywhere.
FURTHER READING:
ALGAE, AN INTRODUCTION TO PHYC0L0GY,
by C. van den Hoek, D. Mann and H.M. Jahns
(Cambridge University Press, 1995)
LES ALGUES QUI NOUS ENTOURENT,
by René Pérez (IFREMER, 1997)
HubÉMU/'^ **> -' - táx\* &Uí2w£
Found in seas throughout the world, Laminaria kelps grow in tidal areas.
initiatives
PROTECTING THE SOUTH PACIFIC
Fifteen countries and territories in the South
Pacific have joined forces to develop and
implement a 1997-2000 Action Plan to pro¬
tect their environment. They arc parties to
the Agreement Establishing the South
Pacific Regional Environment Programme
(SP1ÎEP), which was opened for signature
in 1993 and came into effect in 1995. SPREP,
which has existed as a distinct entity since
1982, now has the status of an autonomous
intergovernmental organization.
"Threats to the environment of the South
Pacific are an integral part of global concern
for environmental protection and sustainable
dev elopment," the Plan states. "International
agreements and action programmes, includ¬
ing Agenda 21, the Barbados Programme of
Action on the Sustainable Development of
Small Island Developing States, the Cairo
Programme of Action on Population and
Development, and conventions on climate
change, biodiversity, ocean management and
pollution, provide an important framework
for regional action."
besides facing the adverse effects of cli¬
mate change, these Pacific island countries
share problems of waste disposal and pollu¬
tion prevention. Population growth, espe¬
cially in urban centres, is putting increasing
pressure on them. Disposal of solid waste is
a particularly acute problem on very small
islands, where recycling is often not ceo-
42
nomical and landfill is the method generally
used. A range of liquid wastes risks polluting
freshwater systems and groundwater in the
region. Problems associated with the man¬
agement of toxic substances such as pesti¬
cides and heavy metals are also giving rise to
concern. The Waigani Convention aims toban
the import into all island member countries
of the South Pacific Forum (with the excep¬
tion of Australia and New Zealand) of haz¬
ardous and radioactive waste, and to control
the transboundary movement and manage¬
ment of hazardous waste within the South
Pacific Region.
In addition to a monitoring role, the
SPREP Secretariat is involved in public
awareness and training activities. It promotes
the inclusion of environmental issues into
school curricula and the publication of mate¬
rials in local languages. Supported by donors,
including several United Nations agencies, the
World bank, governments and non-govern¬
mental organizations, SPREP has an annual
budget of approximately $7 million. But
Pacific states complain they attract little out¬
side attention. Much needs to be done to guar¬
antee the future of these islands where 63
per rent of the population is under 23. I
SPREP Headquarters: P.O. Box 240, Apia, Western Samoa.
Tel: (685) 21929. Fax: (685) 20231. E-mail: sprep@talofa.net
> QuiTHE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER I 997
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
wo rid
AIRCRAFT
AND THE OZONE LAYER
In the 1960s, before chlorofluorocar-
bons (CFCs) were suspected of destroy¬
ing the ozone layer, there were fears that
it could be harmed by fleets of super¬
sonic jets. These fears have resurfaced
in the wake of a recent study by the US
National Oceanic and Atmospheric Admin¬
istration in Boulder (Colorado), which
has revealed that exhaust produced by
the Concorde supersonic aircraft con¬
tains a large quantity of sulphuric acid,
the particles of which serve as carriers
forthe chlorine pollutants that destroy
ozone.
GAS TO THE RESCUE
A filling station with a capacity to fill 14
million bottles a year with butane gas
(65,000 tonnes) was opened in March
1997 In Mbao, a suburb of Dakar (Sene¬
gal). Since a "butamzatlon" campaign
was launched in 1974, household use of
butane increased from 10% in 1982 to
27% in 1992, a rise which is partly due to
a 40% drop in the sale price of bottles.
Butane use enables Senegal to save
70,000 tonnes of wood and 90,000
tonnes of charcoal annually, thus help¬
ing to reduce the pressure on forests
as a firewood source.
INNOCENTSMUGGLERS?
"You wouldn't be the first ending up as
a wildlife smuggler without knowing it".
This is the slogan of an information cam¬
paign jointly launched by the Worldwide
Fund for Nature (WWF), the European
Commission and TRAFFIC Europe, the
wildlife trade monitoring programme of
WWF and IUCN (the World Conservation
Union) to inform citizens about a new
law on wildlife trade that came into force
in the European Union (EU) on 1 June
1997. WWF points out that "The EU is
the world's largest legal importer of live
cats and parrots, the second largest of
primates, boas and pythons, and the
third largest of tortoises and plants.
Global wildlife trade amounts to an esti¬
mated $20 billion annually and involves
350 million plant and animal species."
The new law requires an official permit
certifying that animals or plants imported
into the EU, or products made from
them, come from legal sources.
HUNGARY ACTS
ON CONSERVATION
A new Nature Conservation Act came
into effect in Hungary on 1 January
1997. It is designed to conserve the
whole of nature and not only the differ¬
ent categories of protected areas, an
original approach which might well be
taken up elsewhere. Wetlands have an
important place in the legislation, and
relevant articles include prohibition of
the introduction of non-native fish
species, of the release of harmful chem¬
icals within 1,000 metres of a wetland
shoreline, of water extraction where water
reserves are necessary for maintaining
the values of natural or near-natural wet¬
land habitats, and of building within 50
metres of the shoreline of natural or near-
natural watercourses.
GREENING
INDIA'S COAL FIELDS
The World Bank recently approved a pro¬
ject to safeguard the environment and
local communities in the coal-producing
areas of India. Three-quarters of the $84
million required for this project set up
by Coal India Ltd., one of the world's
biggest coal companies, will come from
the International Development Associa¬
tion (IDA). More than 600,000 employ¬
ees and people living in the vicinity of
510 of the company's mines are
involved. At the company's 10-hectare
central nursery in the state of Orissa,
more than 400 plant species are being
grown to help reduce soil erosion and
restore mined-out lands to productive
use. Other programmes are designed to
alleviate air, soil and water pollution and
reclaim unproductive lands.
RESPECT FORTHE SEA
The Aquarium of La Rochelle (France) and
the Nicolas Hulot Foundation for Nature
and Humanity (formerly known as the
Ushuaia Foundation) teamed up with the
European Blue Flag (for clean beaches) in
June 1997 to launch an operation called
"The sea Is not a dustbin" in two depart¬
ments on France's Atlantic coast. Twelve
thousand young people received an edu¬
cational pamphlet informing them about
the fragile ecological balance of the marine
environment. The operation was particu¬
larly urgent since in 1995 the Aquarium's
study centre for sea turtles recorded an
abnormally high number of leatherback
turtles washed up on beaches. Autop¬
sies revealed that most of them had died
from swallowing plastic bags, perhaps
mistaking them for jellyfish.
BAD BUZZ FOR BEES
Experts estimate that 90% of wild bee
colonies have been decimated in the last
few decades as a result of harsh win¬
ters, wet springs, the massive use of
pesticides, and two varieties of micro¬
scopic mites which suck the bees'
blood. One mite settles inside the bee's
respiratory tube, and the other, an exter¬
nal parasite which originated in Asia,
attacks chrysalises, larvae and adults,
causing major deformities that prevent
the insect from fulfilling its vital func¬
tions. Wild bees play an important role in
pollinating plants. What if they became
extinct?
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
H E R I T A G E
RONBRIDGE GORGE Symbolic birth¬
place of the industrial eraby NeilCossons
mwhsm
^Bcf~y^^
Wùk ^
* *
^ *
^f
^ v. 1
Wr
KC ISONBRIDGfc
K «¡ORGE
10*00* *J|
The world's first iron bridge, built in 1779
across England's River Severn, came to epitomize the genesis of
industrialization based on iron and coal
The Cast Iron Bridge over the River Severn near Coalbrookdale
(1823), a coloured aquatint engraving by M. Dubourg.
B . . . Ifan atheist who had never
heard of Coalbrookdale could be
transported there in a dream, and
left to awake at the mouth of one
of those furnaces, surrounded on
(disides by such a number of infer¬
nal objects, though he had been all
his life the most profligate unbe¬
liever that ever added blasphemy
to incredulity, he would infallibly
tremble at the last judgement that in
imagination would appear to him.
With these apocalyptic words,
written in 1801 , the dramatist and
traveller Charles Dunlin concluded
his observations on the Severn Gorge
in Shropshire, in the Midlands of
England. What drew Dihdin and
numerous other travellers there in
the late eighteenth and early nine¬
teenth centuries was the remark-
. .
t
r
-
ahle concentration of industrial
activity, concerned in the main with
ironmaking, spread along some five
kilometres of the valley of the River
Severn. Today this area, known as
the Ironhridge Gorge, is a World
Heritage Site in recognition of its
outstanding importance in the early
development of industrialization.
THE DARBYS OF COALBROOKDALE
The initial importance of the Sev¬
ern Gorge stems from the pioneering
work of the Quaker ironmaster Abra¬
ham Darby (1678-1717) who in
1709 developed a technique for
smelting iron using coked coal as a
fuel instead of the charcoal made
from wood which was convention¬
ally used at the time. lie had taken
over an existing charcoal-fired blast
furnace built about J 638 in Coal¬
brookdale, a small side valley of the
River Severn, and using local coal
converted into coke he was success¬
ful in smeltingironore to form a use-
aide iron.
Although the impart of this new
technology was limited at first, per¬
haps because there was little price
advantage in coke-smelted iron, by
the middle years of the eighteenth
century Coalbrookdale and the sur-
roundingarea, by then in the hands
of the second Abraham Darby
(1711-63), bad become an impor¬
tant source of good quality iron.
Ry using coked coal as fuel iron¬
masters were freed from the restric¬
tions imposed by limited supplies of
timber for charcoal. Already, by
1700, Rritain had less forest cover
44
THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The Iron Bridge
over the Severn as
it is today.
than any other European state, as a
result of clearance for agriculture,
cutting for charcoal and the
demands of the Navy for ship¬
building. Rut coal was available in
virtually unlimited quantities; and
with coke as a fuel, blast furnaces
could be built bigger, thus allow¬
ing larger castings to be made. Coke
smelting was to become almost uni¬
versal in the early years of the nine¬
teenth century.
THE WORLD'S FIRSTIRON BRIDGE
During the eighteenth century the
Coalbrookdale Company became
renowned not only for the making
of iron but for using iron in new and
innovative ways. Here the first iron
rails were made along which ran
trucks with iron wheels, pushed by
men or pulled by horses, carrying
iron goods down to wharves on the
river. Then in the 1770s came the
most dramatic and spectacular new
use for iron, in the building of the
world's first iron bridge.
The River Severn, England's
longest river, was one of the keys to
the success of the Coalbrookdale
area. It provided ready access to out¬
side markets for the products of the
iron foundries and forges, for coal
and clay from local pits, and foi-
bricks, tiles and pottery. Rut the
Severn also presented a barrier to
the movement of goods by road from
one side of the gorge to the other.
The need for a bridge resulted in
the novel proposal to build one ol
iron. Under the supervision of the
third Abraham Darby (1750-89),
then in charge of the Coalbrookdale
Company, the bridge was cast and
erected in the summer of 1779. It
was opened on New Year's Day
1781, the first large-scale use of iron
for structural purposes in the world
and a remarkable demonstration of
the utility and versatility of iron for
construction. With a span of 30
metres, the graceful semi-circular
arch reached across the gorge of the
Severn at its narrowest point, an ele¬
gant centrepiece for what the cotton
master Charles Ilulbert was to call
in 1837 "the most extraordinary dis¬
trict in the world".
As a river crossing and as a sin¬
gular example of new engineering
the Iron Rridge was an immediate
success but its symbolic significance
was much greater, not only in
Britain but throughout Europe and
in the United States. It epitomized
the birth of a new era in human his¬
tory in which industrial technolo
gies were to provide immeasurable
opportunities.
Even before the construction of
the Iron Rridge the valley of the
River Severn around Coalbrookdale
was already becoming a magnet for all
who wished to see the the birth of
industrialization based on iron and
coal. Many visitors from ov erseas came
to see the furnaces and forges of the
iron industry, coalpits and pumping
engines, the canal with its celebrated
inclined plane down which boats
could pass to the Severn, the famous
china works at Coalport and the Tar
Tunnel nearby from which oozed nat¬
ural bitumen used for waterproofing
and medicinal purposes.
The gorge exercised a peculiar
fascination on artists too. Here the
combination of topography the
River Severn llowing through its
precipitous gorge and the smoke
and flames of the furnaces and
forges conspired to produce a scene
at once picturesque, and sublime.
Rut one view above all others epit¬
omizes the artist's vision of the new
industrial Britain. It has become
the archetypal description of the
first industrial nation. Coalbrook¬
dale by ¡Sight, painted in 1801, is
the work of Philippe Jacques de
Loutherbourg (17-10-1812). In it,
45
THE UNESCO G>URI ERI NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
the buildings of an ironworks are
silhouetted against the glare of the
pig bed as the furnace is tapped.
In the foreground horses pull a
wagon on an iron tramway among
great castings. The painting has
become one of the most famous
images of the new industrial age.
DERELICTION AND DECAY
Throughout the nineteenth century
industry thrived in the Ironbridge
Gorge, as it was to become known,
but its unique contribution was
largely over. Other, better located,
industrial areas overtook it in scale
and influence. As canals and later
railways linked the growing indus¬
trial regions of Britain to ports like
London, Liverpool and Glasgow,
Coalbrookdale became bypassed.
By the beginning of the twenti¬
eth century the Ironbridge Gorge
was in decline. The Coalport China
Works closed in 1926, production
having moved to the Potteries of
Staffordshire, but the foundries in
Coalbrookdale remained, as they
do today. The last of the tile works
in the Gorge, where from the 1870s
decorative floor and wall tiles had
been made from local clay, closed in
1969. Dereliction and decay were
the features that characterized the
gorge. Cottages once occupied by
workers in the iron, pottery or tile
factories lay empty, shops closed
as people moved away to find work
elsewhere. To the north the area of
the old East Shropshire coalfield
was similarly in decline. The last
pit closed in 1979.
But the distinguished industrial
history of the Ironbridge Gorge was
never forgotten. Writing in 1955
Michael Rix (1913-81), an archi¬
tectural historian, referred exten¬
sively to the importance of the area
and its monuments and used for the
first time in print the term "indus¬
trial archaeology" to describe their
significance. In 1961, in the third
issue of the Journal of Industrial
Archaeology he made an impas¬
sioned jilea for the establishment
of "national parks" of industrial
archaeology stating that the "Iron-
bridge Gorge is a prime candidate
for such a designation".
THE BIRTH OF INDUSTRIAL
ARCHAEOLOGY
Ry then the Coalbrookdale Com¬
pany, now part of a larger industrial
Coalbrookdale by
Night (1801), an oil
painting by Philippe
Jacques de
Loutherbourg. This
view of the
Coalbrookdale
furnaces and coke
hearths has become
a classic image of the
Industrial
Revolution.
group, had excavated the Old Fur¬
nace and opened a small museum
in 1959 to commemorate the 250th
anniversary of Darby's smelting of
iron with coke. And a growing num¬
ber of those with an interest in
industrial archaeology made pil¬
grimages to see the extensive
remains, still surviving, of this pio¬
neer industrial site.
The years of industrial and
urban renewal after the Second
World War saw the sweeping away
of much of the evidence of Rritain
as an early industrial nation but this
destruction, inevitable as it was, led
to a growing recognition that the
archaeological evidence of the age
in which we still lived the indus¬
trial age was disappearing too.
Efforts began all over the country to
record or preserve the archaeology
of the Industrial Revolution.
Such was the extent of the
decline in and around the Iron-
bridge Gorge and the area immedi¬
ately to the north that it was des¬
ignated as a New Town, making it
eligible for special funding from
government. Under the terms of the
New Towns Act of 1946 new com¬
munities were established in many
46
THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1 997
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Upper Works at
Coalbrookdale,
an engraving made
in 1758.
parts of England, initially on green
field sites, in order to accommodate
the growing populations of great
conurbations like London, Birm¬
ingham and Manchester. Under the
same legislativ e provisions a second
generation of new towns was cre¬
ated with the same aims but
located in areas of industrial decay,
high unemployment and social
deprivation.
The old East Shropshire Coal¬
field became one of these new
towns. The objective was to renew
the worn-out infrastructure, build
new houses, and encourage new
industry to bring jobs to the area.
The boundaries of the new town of
Telford, named, appropriately,
after the great civil engineer
Thomas Telford who had estab¬
lished his early reputation in Shrop¬
shire in the 1780s, were specifically
defined so that the Ironbridge
Gorge was included in recognition of
its historical and archaeological
importance and amenity potential.
The new town could have
spelled the extinction of the indus
trial archaeology of the Ironbridge
Gorge. But from the outset enlight¬
ened planning and informed direc¬
tion and management of the new
town development corporation
ensured that proper recognition was
accorded to the most important
sites and monuments. It was Telford
Development Corporation that took
the lead in establishing the Iron-
bridge Gorge Museum Trust,
charged with the daunting task of
preserving and presenting to the
public the evidence of early indus¬
try in the Gorge.
The Trust was formed in 1968
and within three years was engaged
on a major programme of conserva¬
tion and interpretation. Most of the
physical requirements of the Gorge
have been met. The whole of the
valley has been designated as a Con¬
servation Area, and there are now
some 300 buildings listed as being
of architectural and historical
importance.
With the demise of Telford
Development Corporation, its work
of creating the new town substan
tially complete, one element of man¬
agement and control has gone. The
Corporation's support for the
Museum Trust has gone too, to he
replaced by a government endow¬
ment. Proper international recog¬
nition came with the designation of
the Gorge as a World Heritage Site
in 1986, the first area of industrial
significance to be so listed.
Places like the Ironbridge Gorge,
by virtue of their renown and the
recognition that comes with it suffer
peculiar forms of stress. Visitors in
particular are an iuescapable con¬
sequence of fame. They place stress
on communities and on the fabric of
historic environments. There is some¬
thing slightly obscene about places
that are monuments to work being
given over to pleasure. But visitors
have rights and demand access. If
the Ironbridge Gorge is to take its
rightful place as one of the great
monuments to human endeavour
then it needs all the attentive care
and thoughtful respect that we can
bestow. I
THE UNESCO lOURIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
interview
Lebanese-born poet, novelist
and playwright Andrée Chedid
has published overthirty books
including (in English
translation) Selected Poems
(1996), Multiple Child (1995)
and From Sleep Unbound
(1987). From her standpoint at
the crossroads of several
cultures she is an alert observer
of the tensions and divisions
of the modern world. In this
interview with Martine Leca, she
voices her commitment to
freedom in direct, simple
terms.
'An inner
freedom'
You often take the themes of your novels fro m
the Bible	
Andrée Chedid: When they coincide with topical
issues. If I only took my ideas from current events
their range might be limited and they would fail
to achieve a universal dimension. By bringing
together the present and the distant past, myths
are universal and open up avenues for exploring
all the facets of human nature. When you
immerse yourself in current affairs, you get car¬
ried away on the tide of events. Our inner life
suffers if our eyes are glued to what is going on
around us, whereas myth makes us steji back.
According to you, the world would be a more
tolerant place if it were ruled by women.
A. 0: A good question. Guided by their maternal
instinct, women would probably he less naturally
inclined to resort to physical violence. Rut every¬
one tends to be corrupted by power, and women are
no exception. Would women continue to he peace-
loving if they were in power? The common good can
only he based on equitable power-sharing between
the sexes, not by denying part of humanity.
You know a lot about Middle Eastern women.
How would you define their status?
A. C: Women in the Middle East are caught up in
a tide that ebbs and flows. They become the
beneficiaries of certain social changes, and then,
lo and behold, just when they are starting to
adjust to these changes, along comes a counter-
current that makes society move backwards.
Some kinds of freedom appeared in Middle Piast¬
ern countries, but they ebbed away as a result of
fundamentalist obscurantism. When I was young,
I thought the world was moving steadily forward
in a straight line. Rut there are slow-downs and
U-turns. I believe that human destiny is subject
to cyclical movements of this kind. This does not
mean that we should stop looking towards the
future, towards progress. My novel Les marches
de sable, for example, explores the innermost
fears, the hopes and the retreats as well as the
ideological and theological struggles that mark
these cycles. Whereas religion should ennoble
us, take us out of ourselves and make us more
humane, it can build walls between people.
You always try to steer clear of ideologies and
conventions.
A. C: Yes, as far as possible. I base my life on
the word freedom. I don't like being kept on a
lead. But this calls for eternal vigilance because
life is full of traps of which we are unawarecon¬
ventionality, unscrupulous ambition, age, tak¬
ing oneself too seriously. I try to elude all labels
and, of course, classification arisingfrommy ori¬
gins and culture. Age is a label one is old or
one is young. Other labels are blood, gender and
soil. I distrust anything that confines a person
to a specific station in life. There is something in
us that is so much larger, a sort of flame, an inner
freedom that defies definition. This indefinable
quality must constantly be reconsidered and
48 THE UNESCO I OURIER NOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
renamed. That is what I try to examine through
poetry, the form of expression I cherish the most.
One recurrent theme in your books is coming
and going between the city and the desert and vice
versa.
A. C: That is an unending process that ni) char¬
acters are pushed into by their instinct. Cities
for me mean freedom; they are places where peo¬
ple can escape from themselves and their back¬
ground. City life allows people to blend in with the
population, with others, without being chained to
them. If 1 lived in a village, I would feel that 1
belonged there; I wouldn't experience this self-
deliverance that the solitude of city life affords
me. City life makes it possible to expand, to be
with other people within minutes and to talk to
them in the midst of a crowd. You can walk in
the city without being disturbed. And poetry is all
around you. You just have to stop and observe.
What about the desert?
A. C: It's a place where you can make a fresh start
after you've been through some kind of ordeal.
It's a place for putting things together, for con¬
templation and simplicity. For dropping your
guard. It's a form of training in asceticism and
endurance, and a kind of filter. My characters go
into the desert to lick their moral wounds. Anas¬
tasia, for example, the heroine of Les marches de
sable, thinks only of emerging from this ordeal in
the desert, the crossing of which has purified and
strengthened her. Rut the teaching of the desert
is sterile if it is not taken back to the city. After the
desert, one has to return to the human world. It is
also important to listen to the desert in oneself. It
helps to take the sting out of death, to greet it
every day as an inevitable companion, so that we can
exorcise it and welcome it when the time comes. It's
impossible to see life clearly unless one has thought
about death at an early age. Death is a certainty
our only certainty and a scale of values. What
comes after, I don't know.
Is your work a quest for continuity?
A. C: My work is a step forward in this world, not
in the hereafter. It is this side of our existence
that concerns me. We keep on asking ourselves
the same questions where have we come from?
where are we going? and no philosopher, sci¬
entist or poet has ever answered them satisfac¬
torily. I am amazed every day that I exist as a
physical being through this combination of mol¬
ecules that I am made of. I'm not talking about
beauty, make-up or appearance. I wonder how
this factory of being with all its complicated
mechanisms has managed to take shape. This
Through writing
we bring together our body
and our mind
extraordinary mystery is enough for me. That is
why I don't try to pierce the mysteries of the
after-life, of the be)ond.
Is your whole life built around writing?
A. C: For me writing and life are inseparable.
Writing enriches life. But I'm not a metronome;
I can get by for a while without writing. The ges¬
tation of a book, for example, calls for a lot of
thought and imagination. Something builds up
inside me, and ink then traces on paper the
course of its development. But the desire to write
never leaves me. It is always there, coiled up
inside me, and if after a while no writing appears,
1 start to feel rather uncomfortable, because my
life is no longer harmonious. For me, writing is
like the act of love, which amplifies, sublimates
life and gives it a luminous tension. It puts mein
step with this inner vibration, this desire that 1
feel deep within me. Without it, purely mater¬
ial life is incomplete.
Isn't it self-centred, this act of love you describe
as part of writing?
A. C: Writing, when compared to the work of a
Mother Teresa or a great doctor, to the suffering
they alleviate and the difficulties they face, can
sometimes seem lightweight and facile, almost
like fun. But as the French philosopher Gaston
Rachelard wrote, we are "real and unreal", and
if we do not combine the real and the unreal, we
are traumatized because we are incomplete.
Through writing we bring together our body and
our mind. Poetry is an act of love, and love gives
you inspiration. This is not just love between a
man and a woman, but universal love. When I go
out into the street, when I mingle with the
crowds, I lov r others. I observ e them. I immerse
myself in them. The crowd is the clay from which
I mould my poems and novels. All these fleeting
moments with others nourish life, the force with¬
out which we would sink into the void that lies
in wait for us.
THE UNESCO COURIER I NOVEMBER 1997
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
You have restored a sense of poetry to the novel.
A. C: Poetry is asking questions at the deepest
level, an attempt to get to the bottom of things.
The act of writing is a moment of purification,
deployment and self-condensation during which
the writer is balanced on a thin wire strung
between alpha and omega. It is a moment to ask
questions about the purpose and the essence of
things. I feel very close to the Japanese poets
who write haiku, those formal seventeen-syllable
poems where the radiance of the essential flows
through the ink. I like to write briefly and suc¬
cinctly. A poem of a few lines often results from
a long chain of questioning and reflection that
may last several days.
What form does all this take in your daily work?
A. C: All my novels have a poetic texture. The raw
material is a block of rough, shapeless clay that I
work on until I've found the formula. The first
draft is always a sketch which is virtually illegible,
except to me. Then the characters emerge from
the rough matter, and their destiny takes shape.
I don't start methodically, with a prearranged
plan. At first I let things flow along and take their
course. Then I go back to what I've written and
look very closely at the words that will have to be
cut, tightened or straightened out. I look at the
text much more critically at this stage. I search for
the right word. Craftsmanship starts after visu¬
alization of the idea: I work on the rhythm, the
music. It's a process of question-and-answ er that
goes on day after day.
The Seine-Saint-Denis
Young People's
Book Fair (France)
As in previous years, the Unesco Courier
will have a stand at the annual Seine-Saint-
Denis Young People's Book Fair held in the
Paris suburb of Montreuil (France) where it
will be meeting some of its regular readers
and other young people wishing to find out
more about Unesco's goals and activities.
Literary works and a wide range of docu¬
mentary material, magazines, periodicals
and multimedia will be presented at the
Fair, one of the largest of its kind in France.
The special theme chosen for this year's
Fair Is "Memory: from the elephant to the
chip". The event will be introduced by an
International symposium on "Memory and
Oblivion" to which historians, researchers,
writers and artists will contribute.
The Fair will be held from
3 to 8 December 1997
Symposium: 1 and 2 December 1997
For further information:
Salon du livre de jeunesse
en Seine-Saint-Denis
3, rue Françols-Debergue
93100 Montreuil (France)
Tel: (33) (0)1 48 57 57 78
Fax: (33) (0)1 48 57 04 62
AUTHORS
RICHARD SCHECHNER is an American
theatre director, author and teacher. A
professor of dramatic art at New York
University, he has published a number of
books, including The Future of Ritual:
Writings on Culture and Performance (1993,
Routledge, NY).
JEAN-PIERRE GUINGANÉ, a playwright and
stage director from Burkina Faso, is
honorary dean of the Faculty of Literature at
the University of Ouagadougou where he
also teaches. He has recently published two
plays: La Musaraigne ("The Shrew", Editions
Gambidi, Ouagadougou, 1997) and Les
lignes de la mam ("Hand Lines", Editions
Gambidi, Ouagadougou, 1997).
ROMAN MAITRA is an Indian writer and
anthropologist specializing in the
performing arts.
OHZASA Y0SH10, of Japan, is a drama critic
specializing in contemporary Japanese
theatre. He is the author of a monumental 8-
volume History of Modern Japanese Theatre,
6 volumes of which have so far appeared.
ANATOLY SMELIANSKY, of Russia, is
literary director of the Moscow Art Theatre
and head of the Moscow Art Theatre
School. He has published a number of
works, including Is Comrade Bulgakov
Dead? (Routledge, NYC and Methuen,
London, 1993), and is editor-in-chief of the
Collected Works of Konstantin Stanislavsky
(founder of the Moscow Art Theatre).
GHASSAN MALEH, of Syria, is an advisor
with the International Theatre Institute (ITI)
and the Institute's main representative at
the United Nations Office in Geneva
(Switzerland).
AUGUSTO BOAL, of Brazil, is a playwright,
director and inventor of the school of theatre
known as the Theatre of the Oppressed. His
writings published in English include ïïie
Rainbow of Desire: The Boal Method of
Theatre and T/ierapy(Routledge, London and
New York, 1995). In 1994 he was awarded
Unesco's Pablo Picasso Medal for his
contribution to intercultural relations.
FRANCE BEQUETTE is a Franco-American
journalist specializing in environmental
questions.
SIR NEIL COSSONS, of the United
Kingdom, is director of the Science
Museum, London. From 1971 to 1983 he
was the first director of the Ironbridge Gorge
Museum Trust.
MARTINE LECA is a French writer and
journalist.
50
THE UNESCO QllRIERBNOVEMBER 1997
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
A splendid contemporary work to serve as a lasting
reminder of hope and pence.
N A I S S A N C t
hlL\i<
RENA S A N C E
The revival of a city, of a people, of hope
The first recording of
the Sarajevo Philharmonic Orchestra
since the war
m«==
Reí. CO -.7432152160-2
SPONSORED BY
Sales to benefit the Sarajevo Pliilhaimoiiic Oichestia
rORKS SPECIALLY composed e
JcfJarre, Eric Breton, Josip Slavenski,
Petar Konjovic, Asim Horozic, Riccardo Giovannini.
Performed by the Sarajevo Philharmonic Orchestra
under the direction of Ernst Schelle and Emir Nuhanovic.
CTiJKXn. Distribution by PJvkc
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
IN THE NEXT ISSUE:
ISLANDS:
A WORLD APART
INTERVIEW
RENÉ DEPESTRE
HERITAGE
potosí, a mining town
in bolivia
ENVIRONMENT
CLIMATE CHANGE:
THE GREAT DEBATE
]]>
</page>
</document>
